
   
      
         
            The means to keepe sinne from reigning in our mortall body A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, May 26. 1629. By William Foster, Master of Arts, and parson of Hedgeley in the county of Buckingham.
            Foster, William, 1591-1643.
         
         
            
               1629
            
         
         Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01092
            STC 11204
            ESTC S120710
            99855904
            99855904
            21412
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01092)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21412)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 887:12)
         
         
            
               
                  The means to keepe sinne from reigning in our mortall body A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, May 26. 1629. By William Foster, Master of Arts, and parson of Hedgeley in the county of Buckingham.
                  Foster, William, 1591-1643.
               
               [8], 30, [2] p.   
               
                  Printed by Iohn Haviland,
                  London :
                  1629.
               
               
                  Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A-E⁴.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-12
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-10
            John LattaSampled and proofread
         
            2008-10
            John LattaText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2009-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            The means to keepe Sinne from reigning
in our mortall Body.
            A
SERMON
PREACHED AT
PAƲLS CROSSE,
May 26. 1629.
            By William Foſter, Maſter of Arts, and
Parſon of Hedgeley in the County of
BVCKINGHAM.
            LONDON,
¶Printed by John Haviland.
1629.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHT
Honourable, Robert Lord Dormer,
Baron of Wing, Earle of Caernaruon, Lord
Lieutenant of the County of Buckingham,
my very good Lord:
As alſo
To the right honorable and vertuous
Lady, the Lady Anna-Sophia Counteſſe of
Caernaruon, his moſt gracious, deare,
and louing Wife.
            
               Right Honourable,
            
            
               I Formerly prouided this Sermon for you
in a Country Auditory. Your occaſions
then carried you elſewhere.
The approbation it receiued from
ſuch learned Diuines as hapned to
be preſent, made mee ſettle my thoughts and meditations
againe vpon it. Thoſe ſecond thoughts and
meditations gaue it a new being, and that growth,

that it came from the Country to the City. Meeting
there with the Preſſe, it preſumeth to preſſe
from the City to the Court, bearing your Honours
name in the forehead. For whither could it bee
ſent more fitly to cry downe the reigning of ſinne,
than to Court? where vertue and not ſinne ſhould
reigne among the Peeres and Nobles of ſo vertuous
and pious a King as wee haue:
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  . hiſtor. 
                     〈…〉
                   4. 3. who like the Emperors
Theodoſius the younger (beſides his priuate deuotions)
leauing his Princely ſports, is an aſsiduous
frequenter of publike prayer;Euſ
                     •
                  b. de vit. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . l. 4. 
                     •
                  . 33 and Conſtantine the
Great, (beſides his priuate reading) is a great and
conſtant hearer of Sermons, the meanes to receiue
ſacred inſtructions to keepe ſinne from reigning in his
mortall body. Let mee not be thought then preſumptuous
if I dedicate this ſmall worke of mine to your
Honours, to be a Remora to ſtay you from yeelding
to the inchanting allurements of ſuch perdition-working
Syrens, as are alwayes ſeducing the fraile nature
of man vnto ſinne. Neither doe I this, becauſe
I any wayes deeme your Honours prone to follow
ſuch, or becauſe you want either good precepts or
neere examples to follow.
                  D. Prid
                        ••
                     ux, his Maieſties Profeſſor or Diuinitie in the Vniuerſitie of 
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     
                  
                For, my good Lord, beſides
your owne gracious diſpoſition, you haue been brought
vp at the feet of Gamaliel in the Vniuerſitie, that
hath furniſhed you with the one: you haue thoſe noble

Lords,The Earle of Pembroke Lord Steward, and the Earle of Montgomery Lord Chamberlaine to his Maieſties houſhold. your Vncle and Father in Law, neere and
bright ſhining Lights to you in the other: you haue
the daily attendance of
                  D. Williams, with others. ſuch as are able and ready to
direct you in both. And you, right noble Lady, (as
inheritrix of your deceaſed Lady-mothers vertues)
are ready to ioyne in the practice of ſuch actions as
may bring eternall happineſſe to you both. But I dedicate
theſe my poore labours to your Honours to encourage
you to goe on in what you are. For your
Lordſhip well knowes that of the Poet;

                  Qui monet vt facias, quod jam facis, ipſe monendoOuid.
                  
                  Laudat, &amp; hortatu comprobat acta ſuo.
               
            
            I deuote them to you, as a ſure teſtimonie of my vnfained
reſpect to your Honours, and heartie deſire that
you may be ſaued in the day of the Lord. For ſeeing
this Sermon (ſuch as it then was) ſhould haue beene
yours before, ſeeing you haue beene graciouſly pleaſed
to receiue mee for yours ſince, to whom may it
more fitly be appropriated than to your Honours? So
that I may ſay to each of you with the Poet;

                  Hoc lege quod poſſis dicere jure meum eſt.
                  Marti
                        ••
                     
                  
               
            
            Cenſurers I ſhall haue, and doe expect, many;
but I feare or regard none. My aime is Gods
glory, to caſt my mite into the Treaſurie of the

Church, for the good of my Country in generall, and
to teſtifie my deſire of doing your Honours ſeruice in
particular. This is the marke I looke at, and I ſhall
euer endeuour by Gods grace to hit it. The criticall
Spectators I paſſe by, without any glance on them; I
ſhall neuer care to pleaſe them. That Archer which
lookes on the ſtanders by, and not on the marke, cannot
but miſſe his aime; and that Writer which endeuours
to pleaſe all, ſhall pleaſe none, neither God,
good men, nor himſelfe. But if (next to Gods glory
and the Churches good) your Honours, out of your
wonted candor, will be pleaſed to accept it, I ſhall
attaine my wiſhed ſcope, and ſhall be encouraged
further to ſhew my ſelfe,
            
               Your Honours deuoted Chaplaine and
humble ſeruant to be commanded,
WILLIAM FOSTER.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            A
SERMON PREACHED
AT PAVLS
Croſſe, May the 26.
1629.
            
               ROM. 6. 12.
               
                  Let not ſinne reigne therefore in your mortall bodie
that ye ſhould obey it in the luſts thereof.
               
            
            
               IN Adams being we had all our being:
and in his fall wee all receiued a fall.
His perſon (being the firſt) infected
our humane nature: our humane nature
(being from him) infects our
perſons. So that now no man liuing,
without the brand laid vpon him by
S. Iohn, of deceiuing himſelfe, and lying to others, can
ſay he is without ſinne:1 Ioh. 1. 8. 
               If we ſay that we haue no ſinne, we
deceiue our ſelues, and the truth it 
                     〈◊〉
                   in vs, 1 Ioh. 1. 8.
(Lawne, and that the 
                  ••
               eſt, hath his bracks, Roſes, and

thoſe the ſweeteſt, haue their pricks; Men, and thoſe the
beſt, haue their faults.) S. Iames outſtrips S. Iohn, and
ſaith, that we doe not onely offend all, but we offend all
many wayes;
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                
               In many things we offend all, Iam. 3. 2. The
Prophet Dauid (though this be alreadie too much, for
our ſtore) augments the ſtore, and makes the many ſins,
many many ſins, ſo many, that we know not how many;
Who can tell how oft he offendeth?
               Pſal 
                     •
                  9. 12. 
               Lord cleanſe me from my
ſecret faults: Pſal. 19. 12. So that then the righteouſneſſe
of man conſiſteth not in hauing no ſinne, for then
no man could bee iuſtified, no man could be righteous;
but it conſiſteth in mans ſtout reſiſting and ſuppreſſing of
ſinne, that it reigne not in him, and preſumptuouſly get
the dominion ouer him, and Gods free remiſſion of ſin,
that it bee not imputed vnto him, hee condemned for it.
Dauid therefore prayes againſt the dominion of ſinne,
that he may be innocent from the great offence:
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  . 
                     •
                  9. 13. and S. Paul
exhorts vs to reſiſt and ſuppreſſe ſinne and his luſts, that
it reigne not in vs, and wee incurre the irreuocable ſentence
of eternall death for our offence. Let not ſin reigne
therefore in your mortall bodie, that yee ſhould obey it in the
luſts thereof. As if the Apoſtle had ſayd; To exhort you
to an abſolute puritie, were to enjoyne you an abſolute
impoſſibilitie. For there was neuer yet any man altogether
pure, and without ſinne (Chriſt Ieſus excepted, who
was 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , both God and man) but yet a man need
not be all ſinne; he need not yeeld the powers and faculties
of his ſoule, and members of his bodie, as inſtruments
of vnrighteouſneſſe vnto ſinne, and ſo let ſinne
haue his full careere in him, and rule and reigne in his
mortall bodie, but hee may by the grace of God reſiſt
ſinne, and ſo haue but few, and thoſe but vnderling ſins;
and thoſe few vnderling ſinnes, by the great and ſuperabundant

mercie of God in Ieſus Chriſt forgiuen, and
not imputed vnto him. For, as when wee walke abroad
in the fields to take the aire, ye cannot hinder the Fowles
thereof from flying and houering ouer our heads, but
we may well hinder them from rooſting, building, and
making their neſts there:
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                  ▪
                Euen ſo, as long as wee liue in
this vale of miſerie, clad with theſe weeds of mortalitie,
this bodie of ours, wee cannot chuſe but haue ſinne houering
vp and downe in vs, but we may chuſe whether
we will let it rooſt there, wee may chuſe whether we will
let it build and make his neſt there, to rule and domineere
in our mortall bodie; therefore the Apoſtle here in my
Text ſaith, Let not ſinne therefore reigne in your mortall bodie,
that you ſhould obey it in the luſts thereof.
            
            In which Text I ſhall commend three things to your
obſeruation.
            
               1. Here is a King deſcribed by his reigning, namely
Sinne; 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Let not ſinne therefore
reigne.
               
               2. Here are his lawes declared, by obeying, viz. his
luſts; 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , That you
ſhould obey it in the luſts thereof.
               3. Here is his Kingdome ſpecified by the place where
he would reigne, viz. your mortall bodie, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ,
in your mortall bodie.
               
            
            For,Origen in Epiſ. 
               Peccatum velut ſedem quandam &amp; ſolium regni ſui
in noſtro corpore collocatum habet:
               ad Rom lib. 5. ſaith Origen. Sinne hath,
as it were,cap. 6. tom. 2. the fear and throne of his kingdome in our
mortall bodie.
            In all which there is ſuch an 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , and diſorder, that
this Common-wealth cannot ſtand long.
            1. The King he is inſulting, it is Sinne, which at firſt

got footing in Adam,
               
                  
                     〈…〉
                  . a little new inſpired ſlime of
the earth, and by that wound it ſelfe into all the
men of the earth.
            2. The kingdome that's decaying, it is your periſhing
mortall bodie: which as ſoone as it hath life and
being, tends to diſſolution and not being. Like
apples of Sodom,
               
                  
                     〈…〉
                   48. a touch turnes it into duſt and
aſhes.
            3. Laſtly, the lawes they are vnlawfull, they are luſts:
Quicquid libet licet. What it luſteth, that it willeth.
            Here is aliud ex alio malum, Diſorder vpon diſorder. A
wilfull king, a rufull kingdome, and hatefull lawes. S. Paul
therefore, the Embaſſadour of the King of Kings and
Lord of Lords, teacheth vs in my Text, how to order
this diſorder, and how to deale with each of theſe.
            1. Sinne muſt be ſuppreſſed, and kept from reigning:
Let not ſinne reigne therefore.
            
            2. Luſts, the lawes; they muſt not be obeyed, obey it
not in the luſts thereof.
            
            3. Your mortall bodie, the kingdome, that muſt bee
repaired, and of 
                  •
               uinate decaying mortall bodies, you
muſt make your ſelues ſtrong and liuely bodies. For ſo
it followeth in the verſe after my Text. Neither yeeld your
members as inſtruments of vnrighte
                     •
                  uſneſſe vnto ſinne, but
yeeld your ſelues vnto God, as thoſe that are aliue from the
dead, and your members as inſtruments of righteouſneſſe
vnto God. And of theſe three in their order. And firſt of
ſin, that he muſt be ſuppreſſed. Let not ſinne reigne, &amp;c.
            
               Let not ſinne reigne therefore.
               IT is the Parable of Iotham in the ninth of Iudges,
                  
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     . 9. 25. that of
all the trees the Bramble (that baſe hedge creeping

ſhrub) would needs take vpon it to be King. So of all that
mans nature is incident vnto, ſinne (that baſe deprauitie
of nature) muſt needs take vpon him to be king, and to
reigne in our mortall body. Nay that will not content him,
to reigne as a king, but he will make hauocke of all like a
tyrant. For Sin is the greateſt tyrant that euer the world
had.
               Other tyrants (though monſtrouſly raging) killed but
ſome perſons; Nero killed his mother that bare him, and
his Maſter Seneca that taught him; he burnt the Citie of
Rome that was vnder his ſoueraignty &amp; obeyed him; but
theſe are but petty ſlaughters in reſpect of thoſe which
ſinne makes. For, that ſpares none; it killed all thoſe that
liued before vs, it will kill all vs that are now liuing, and
all that euer ſhall be borne after vs. It is good therefore
to keepe our ſelues free-men, from being ſlaues to ſo
hauocke-making a Tyrant. Let not ſinne reigne therefore
in your mortall bodie, that you ſhould obey it in the luſts
thereof.
               
               No man would be willing to ſerue a Maſter, how great
a Prince ſoeuer he were, that when his ſeruant had ſpent
his youthfull yeares, cripled his ſturdie limbs, and waſted
his plentifull eſtate in his ſeruice, and comes for his reward,
will draw his ſword and kill him (ſurely none would
be willing to receiue their pay in ſuch crackt coine:) but
ſinne dealeth ſo with vs; when we haue yeelded all the
powers and faculties of our-ſoules, and the members of
our bodies, to be commanded by ſinne, whats the reward
he giues vs but death? ſo ſaith the Apoſtle in the
laſt verſe of this Chapter:Rom. 6. v. vlt. 
                  The wages of ſinne is death, but
the gift of God is eternall life through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.
Thoſe then which neglect the ſeruice of God, and giue
themſelues ouer to the tyrannous ſubiection of ſinne, are

like the perfidious Iewes, who reiected Chriſt the giuer
of life,
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      27. 21. and deſired Barabas a murderer to be giuen them,
Matth. 27. 21. Let vs therefore ſhake off the murthering
yoke of ſinne, and by true and heartie repentance ſend a
meſſenger of defiance vnto it, ſaying with thoſe citizens
in the Goſpell,Luke 19. 14. 
                  Nolumus hunc regnare ſuper nos; We will not
haue this man, we will not haue ſinne reigne ouer vs. And as
Origen exhorts,Origen. in Epiſt. 
                        〈◊〉
                      Rom. lib. 5. 
                  vnuſquiſ
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      peſsimum regem regnantem in ſuâ
carne depellat:
                  cap. 6. tom. 2. Let euery man expell this euill king reigning
in his fleſh. Let not ſinne reigne therefore in your mortall
bodie.
               
               Now Kings, as the Politickes teach vs, doe ordinarily

                     obtaine their rule two
wayes, either by

                           Succeſſion, and ſo are Kings,
as it were, naturally: or
                           Election, and ſo are Kings adoptiuely.
                        
                     
                  
but this king ſinne, becauſe he would be ſure to be king
ſome way, claimes the rule of our mortal body both theſe
wayes, both by ſucceſſion and election. But his title of
ſucceſſion hath beene found weake long agoe. That indeed
ſhewes his antiquitie, how Lucifer begot him when
he was caſt out of heauen. That indeed ſhewes that hee
hath free-hold of inheritance in our mortall body; but
truly no Lord to command it, or King to rule it. Elect
him not therefore for your King, ſo you ſhall preuent
him of his kingdome; ſo you ſhall keepe him from reigning
in your mortall body. Let not ſinne reigne therefore
in your mortall body.
               
               And that you may not elect him, you muſt know that
as there are three things concurring to the election of a
politicall King;

                     1 Nomination.
                     2 Conſultation.
                     3 Conſent or Approbation.
                  
               
               
                  
So this ſpirituall King ſinne comes to his kingdome by
three ſteps.Gregor. Mag. Paſ
                        •
                     or Curae par. 3. admon. 30. tom. 1. For as S. Gregery obſerues, there are three degrees
in ſin;

                     1 Suggeſtion, offered by the Deuill.
                     2 Delight, adminiſtred by the fleſh.
                     3 Conſent, yeelded by our reaſon.
                  
               
               The firſt, that is, Suggeſtion, is like to Nomination.
               The ſecond, that is, Delight, is like to Conſultation.
               The third, that is, Conſent, is all one with Appr
                     •
                  bation.
               Suggeſtion begins ſinne,
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                   Delight continues, Conſent
finiſheth ſinne. Now reſiſt ſinne in the beginning, ſo you
ſhall preuent him of his kingdome, and keepe him from
reigning in your mortall body. Let not ſinne therefore
reigne in your mortall bodie.
               
               When the Deuill profereth his intiſing ſuggeſtions,
bid him a
                        •
                     aunt Satan,
                  
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                   
                  thou ſhalt not tempt thoſe which belong
vnto the Lord thy God. Nay, Saint Chryſoſtome ſaith, that
euery man of God may ſay as God himſelfe,Matth 4. 7. 
                  Thou ſhalt not
tempt the Lord thy God,
                  Chryſ
                        •
                     ſt. hom. 5. in opere imper
                        •
                     . Matth. 4. 7. Quoniam qui hominem
Dei tentat, Deum tentat. For he which tempts a man of
God, tempts God alſo. Reſiſt him then wee muſt in his
temptations; and that we may doe to good purpoſe; for
in reſiſting him, we ſhall be ſure to foile and vanquiſh
him. For the the Deuill is an arrant coward, hee is like a
ſhadow.
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  Si fugio ſequitur, ſed me fugit illa ſequentem.
               
               If wee be afraid of the Deuill, and fly from him, hee will
purſue vs; but if we reſiſt the Deuill, and purſue him, hee
will fly from vs.Iames 4▪ 7. Therefore Saint Iames ſaith, Reſiſt the
Deuill,
                  lu
                        •
                     . Scalig. de Subtil 
                        〈◊〉
                     . 181. 
                        〈…〉
                     
                   
                  and he will 
                        •
                     ly from thee, Iames 4. 7. The Deuill may
well be compared to a tree (whereof Iulius Scaliger maketh
mention) growing in a Prouince called Pudiſeram, to

which if a man come, ramos conſtringit, it ſhrinkes vp the
boughes, as angry and diſpleaſed; but when he departs,
ramos pandit, it ſpreads and opens the boughes, as content
and pleaſed againe: So the Deuill, if we be afraid of
him, and fly from him, ramos pandit, he vſeth all ſubtilitie
he can, to catch vs, and ſpreads his nets of vanitie to enſnare
vs; but if wee take heart-a-grace, and affront him,
and meet him in the teeth, ramos conſtringit, he withdraweth
himſelfe, and vaniſheth; as he did when our Sauiour
Chriſt repelled him with Sic ſcriptum, It is written. Then
the Deuill left him,
                  Matth. 4. 11. 
                  and Angels came and miniſtred vnto him,
Matth. 4. 11. Chriſt could haue repelled him by the power
of his Deitie, but then we could not haue imitated him,
but he quelled him by the Word of God, to teach vs that
no weapon is like the Scripture to reſiſt the Deuill; no
ſword like the Sword of the Spirit,
                  Epheſ. 6. 16, 17. no ſhield like the Shield
of faith, whereby we may be able to quench all the fiery darts of
Satan, Epheſ. 6. 16, 17.
               But you will ſay that the ſuggeſtions of the Deuill doe
often get poſſeſſion of our hearts before we are aware!
True, he is malicious, ſparing none, not Adam in Paradiſe,
not Chriſt the Sonne of God in the wilderneſſe; he
is a cunning impoſtor, and can ſlily conuey his deluſions
into our hearts, making himſelfe of a deuill ſeeme a Saint,
of a foule fiend of darkneſſe,2 Cor. 11. 14. a bright Angell of light,
2 Cor. 11. 14. But if hee haue gotten thus much of thee,
giue no more place to him, ſtay here, and thou mayeſt
doe well enough yet: proceed not to the ſecond degree,
that is, let not thy fleſh be delighted with his ſuggeſtions
of ſinne, and ſo thou ſhalt preuent ſinne of his kingdome,
and keepe it from reigning in thy mortall body. The Deuill
may preſent his ſuggeſtions to vs, but vnleſſe our fleſh

with delight entertaine them, they cannot hurt vs: P
                        •
                     ecata
non nocent,
                  Greg. Mag. Moral. expo
                        •
                     it. in Iob, ſib. 16. 
                  ſi non placent; Sinne hurts not, if it pleaſe
not. Theeues may peepe in at our windowes, but if wee
keepe our doores and windowes cloſe ſhut, and faſt barred,
they cannot hurt vs. So the Deuill may peepe in at
the windowes and doores of our hearts, the eies and eares
of man; but if wee ſhut the windowes, and ſtop thoſe
doores of our fleſh with the deafe Adder, that they may
not harken to the voice of this Charmer, charme be neuer
ſo cunningly, he cannot hurt vs. Let vs tell then our fleſh
ready to be tickled with delight, that our ſenſes are deluded,
and that ſhe hatcheth but a viper, which in the end
will gnaw aſunder the very bowels where ſhe was conceiced.
For the bread the Deuill preſents thee, is truely no
bread to feed thee, but a ſtone to ſmite thee; the fiſh hee
ſhewes, is truly no fiſh to nouriſh thee, but a ſerpent to
bite thee; and the egge he would make thee put thy hope
in, will not hatch to proue a bird to delight thee, but a
Scorpion to ſting thee. Keepe then thy fleſh from delighting,
and thou ſhalt keepe theſe from hutting, and ſinne
from reigning. Let not ſinne reigne therefore in your mortall
bodie.
               
               But you will ſay that our fleſh is impure, and ſo may
quickly infect vs, and carry vs head-long with delight, as
the Deuill carried the ſwine into the ſea. Let it be ſo; if
thou canſt but ſtay here, thou mayeſt doe reaſonable well.
Conſent not to ſinne; let not thy will and reaſon, thy ſuperiour,
and rationall appetite, yeeld to thy fleſh and her
delight, thy inferiour and ſenſitiue app
                     •
                  tite. Though the
Deuill haue ſuggeſted thee, the fleſh delighted in it, yet
let not thy will conſent and yeeld vnto it. For it is conſent
that finiſheth ſinne, and cauſeth it to reigne in our

mortall body. Iueſt peccat
                        •
                     m cum delecteris, regnat autem
cum conſenſeris,
                  
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      in 
                        〈◊〉
                     . ſaith Saint Anſelme. Sin is then in a man,
when he is delighted in it, but it neuer reignes till he hath
giuen his full and expreſſe conſent thereto. And Saint
Bernard,
                  
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      Par. 
                        〈◊〉
                     . 
                  Vitioſ
                        •
                     s dico, qui ex voluntate conſenti
                        •••
                     , nec reſiſtunt,
quantum poſſunt. I call thoſe vitious men which
willingly conſent to ſinne, and reſiſt not what they are
able.
               But you will ſay our reaſon is depraued, and ſo may
eaſily be deceiued with apparent good, and the ſenſitiue
appetite tainting the rationall, may make the will to finiſh
what Satan ſuggeſted, and the fleſh luſted after.
               O wretched ſinner, now thou preſſeſt me too farre!
now thou commeſt too neare the pit! I ſcarce know what
to ſay vnto thee! But yet that thou mayeſt not be ſwallowed
vp in the gulfe of deſpaire, there is one vltimum
re
                        •
                     ugium, one laſt refuge yet left, that is, that thou accuſtome
not thy ſelfe to ſinne. Though the Deuill like the
Serpent, haue glided in his ſuggeſtions; though thy fleſh,
like Eua
                        •
                     ,
                  
                     
                        ••
                     en. 3. haue thought them faire to the eye, and pleaſant
to the taſte, and delighted in them; though thy will
and reaſon, like Adam, haue beene drawne to conſent vnto
them; yet let not Cuſtome, like the riuer Iordan, carry vs
as the fiſh that follow that ſtreame in mare mor
                        ••
                     am,
                  
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      contra 
                        〈◊〉
                     . into
the dead ſea, and inu
                     •
                  e vs to ſinne all our life time. There
is an axiom in warre,
                     
                        ••••
                     tarch. in A
                     
                        •••
                     heg regum 
                        〈◊〉
                     . that, Non licet 
                        •
                     is pe
                        •
                     care; No man
muſt offend twice. Oh that we could abſerue it in our
Chriſtian warfare in the Church militant, ſo ſhould we
ſtop the courſe and habite of ſinning; ſo ſhould we preuent
ſinne of his kingdome, and keepe it from reigning
in our mortall bodie.
               Saint Auguſtine therefore addeth a fourth degree of

ſinne,Auguſt. in Ioan. cap. 11. tract. 
                        •
                     9. 
                        〈◊〉
                     . 9. and that is, the vſe and cuſtome of ſinning. The
three firſt degrees of ſinne, may eaſily be reſiſted, but if it
once come to the fourth, and grow to a cuſtome, it will
hardly,Aug. in Pſal. 36. if euer, be remoued. Conſ
                        ••
                     t
                        •
                     dinem vincere dura
pugna; It is hard to ouerthrow a cuſtome, ſaith the ſame
Father. For cuſtome makes the face impudent, we bluſh
not to ſinne, the heart ſenſeleſſe; we feele not our ſinne,
our ſinne tyrannous, our mortall body is ruled by ſinne.
For, though ſinne it ſelfe he a tyrant, yet cuſtome will ſet
a ſharper edge vpon it. Cuſtome is a monſtrous tyrant, it
rules both Church and Common-wealth; ſta
                        •
                      pre ratione
volum as; if it be cuſtomes pleaſure that it muſt be ſo, it
ſhall be ſo, Law will not controule it, ſufferance hath
made it aboue all law Saint Auguſtine in his fourth booke,
and 24▪
                  Auguſt. de doct. Chriſt. l. 4 c. 24, tom. 3. Chapter, De doctrinâ Chriſtianâ, tells 
                     〈◊〉
                   that the
people of Caſ
                        ••
                     ea had an ancient cuſtome, once a yeare
for certain dayes together to meet, and diuide themſelues
into parts, and throw ſtones one at another, the father
not ſparing the ſonne, nor the ſonne the father. Which
cuſtome, though it were a moſt barbarous cuſtome, and
yearely the occaſion of the ſlaughter of many men; yet
Saint Auguſtine (whom we count the moſt learned and
eloquent of all the Fathers) found it an exceeding hard
matter to diſſwade them from their cuſtome;Idem. Ibidem. 
                  
                     
                        •
                     gi quidum
granditèr quant
                        •••
                      valui; I dealt with them (ſaith 
                     •
                  e) with
all the might and maine I could.
               But let vs come home to our ſelues. It was taken vp
for a cuſtome, for Carriers and Drouers, to labour themſelues
and their cattell vpon the Lords day. Which cuſtome
though it were expreſly againſt the Commandement
of God, and for aboue ſixty yeares together daily
cried out againſt, by zealous Preachers in their P
                     •
                  lpits,

yet it continued, and looked the Law in the face, till the
Parliament made a penall Statute to reforme it.
               And if we ſhould come yet nearer, and take a ſuruey
of perſonall ſinnes, we ſhall finde them by cuſtome and
habite made as hard to be caſt off, as locall and nationall
ſinnes. For Conſuetudo peccandi tollit ſenſum peccati. &amp; in
alteram naturam vertitur; The cuſtome of ſinning quite
bereaues vs of all ſenſe and feeling of our ſinnes, and is
changed into another nature. The common ſwearer
makes it a matter of nothing to thunder out a multitude
of 
                     •
                  oulevgly oathes together; nay the more mouth they
giue their oathes, the more gentleman-like grace they
thinke their oathes giue them.
                     
                        •••
                     kg. Confeſ. l. 2. cap. 3. tom. 1. Like Saint Auguſtines companions
of his youth, Tanto gloriantes magis, quant
                        •
                      ſunt
turpes magis; Glorying in that moſt, whereof, if they had
any grace, they ſhould be aſhamed moſt. Nay, I haue
knowne ſome, whom the cuſtome of ſwearing hath carried
ſo head-long to ſweare, that they know not when
they ſweare; ſo that being reproued for their ſwearing,
they would preſently ſweare they did not ſweare. The
common drunkard whileſt he ſwallowes his liquor, is ſo
ſwallowed himſelfe, that no remorſe for his ſinne appeareth
in him;Ier
                        ••
                     . 3. 3. he puts on a wh
                        •
                     res face, 
                        ••
                     d refuſeth to be aſhamed,
Ierem. 3. 3. He riſeth early to p
                        ••
                     ire in ſtrong drinke, as
Eſay ſpeaketh. Hee thinkes there is no kindneſſe, where
there is no drunkenneſſe, and makes one drunkenneſſe a
medicine to cure the diſtemper of another, and profeſſeth
that nothing but a haire of the ſame dogge, can allay the
diſtemper of his dog-like appetite. Oh to what an height
of impietie doth euill cuſtome bring men. It makes a
man,
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                   
                  Peccare quaſi pecucare; So to ſinne, that he degenerates
and becomes a beaſt in his ſinne, as Iunius obſerues.

I could ſhew you the like of gluttony and luxurie; ſo that
Pope Iulius the third being by his Phyſitians, for his
health ſake,Vergerius in Hiſtoriá Spierae. Sladanus. Surius. Criſpinus. Bal
                        •
                     us, &amp; alii. forbidden porke; miſſing it one day at his
table, gluttony made him reproue his ſer
                     •••
                  , and command
him to fetch him porke; for (ſaith hee) I care not
what the Phyſitian ſaith, I will eat porke in diſpight of
God himſelfe. And Ioannes à Piſa, Archbiſhop of Beneuentum,
and the Popes N
                        ••
                     cio for Ve
                        •
                     ice, wrote a booke,
and printed it, in commendation of that ſin, that I tremble
to name, that ſin, for the reigning of which in Sodome,
the Lord rained vpon them brimſtone and fire from heauen
and conſumed them. But let theſe examples teach
you how hard a thing it is to remoue and alter an euill cuſtome.
Can the Aethi
                        •
                     pian change his skin,
                  Ier. 13▪ 23. 
                  or the Leopard his
ſpots? Euen ſo may they doe good, that are accuſtomed to doe
euill, ſaith the Prophet Ier. 13. 23. O then, beloued, if
you will preuent ſinne of his kingdome, preuent the cuſtome
of ſinning, ſo you ſhall keepe ſinne from reigning in
your mor
                        •
                     all body. Let not ſinne reigne therefore &amp;c.
               But you muſt remember, that I told you that this was
but vltimum refugium, a laſt refuge; and a laſt refuge is to
be embraced only, when our caſe growes deſperate. The
beſt and ſafeſt way then to ſuppreſſe ſinne, is to deale with
him in the firſt or ſecond degree thereof: Nay in the very
firſt 
                     •
                  uſtfull motions, we muſt cruſh this cockatrice in the
ſhell,Pſal. 58. 7. and make out luſts and ſuggeſtions like the vntimely
fruit of a wom
                        •
                     n▪ which periſh
                        •
                     th ere it ſee the Sunne, Pſal.
                  
                     •
                  8. 7. For luſts are the lawes of ſinne, and if you would
not haue ſinne reigne ouer you, you muſt not obey the lawes
thereof. Therefore, ſaith Saint Paul, Let not ſinne reigne in
your mortall body, that you ſhould obey it in the luſts thereof.
               
               So that, as ſinne is to be ſuppreſſed, ſo his lawes which

are his luſts muſt not be obeyed. Obey not the luſts thereof.
And this leads me by the hand to the ſecond part of my
Text: that the lawes of ſinne muſt not be obeyed. Obey
not the luſts thereof.
               
            
            
               2. Obey not the luſts thereof.
               
                  DRaco, the Athenian Law-giuer, made ſuch cruell
Lawes,
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     . Gell. Noct. that Solon abrogated them, and Demades
the Orator ſaid,
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     . lib. 32. c. 18. that Sanguine non atramento ſcribebantur:
They were written in bloud, not in inke. But wee haue
more need to abrogate the lawes of ſinne, and it may be
more truly ſaid of Luſts theſe lawes, that they are written
in bloud, not in inke. For luſts the lawes of ſinne, are not
barren luſts, but they are teeming and conceiuing luſts.
Luſts, if they be obeyed, bring forth ſinne, and ſinne finiſheth
his worke with nothing but death: ſo ſaith S.

                     
                        •
                     ames;
                  
                     
                        •
                     am. 1. 15. 
                  When luſt hath conceiued, it bringeth forth ſinne, and
ſinne when it is finiſhed bringeth forth death, Iam. 1. 15. And
S. Paul ſaith,Rom. 6. 2
                        •
                     . that The wages of ſinne is death, Rom. 6. 23.
Luſts, the beginning are deceitfull; ſinne, the progreſſe,
hatefull; death, the con
                     •
                  luſion, dreadfull. For, ſix malis
praemiſsis nunquam colligi poteſt bona concluſio: Out of ſo ill
premiſes can neuer be gathered a good concluſion. Ieſus
therefore the ſonne of Syrach ſaith, that we muſt flie from
ſinne,Ecclu
                        •
                     . 21. 2. 
                  tanquam à facie colubri; as from the face of a Serpent;
for if thou commeſt too neere 
                        〈◊〉
                     , it will bite thee, the teeth
thereof are as the teeth of a Lyon, 
                        ••
                     aying the ſoules of men:
Ecclus. 21. 2.
               We muſt flie from ſinne, as from the face of a ſerpent;
For, as in the face of a ſerpent lieth all the danger, becauſe
there is the poyſon, and the teeth; ſo in obeying

of luſts, which are the faces, and firſt appearings of ſin,
we ſhall ſwell with the poyſon of ſin, and be bitten with
the teeth of death. Or wee muſt flie from ſinne, 
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      from
the face of a ſerpent, that is, from the heads and firſt luſtfull
motions of ſinne. A ſerpent hath a head, a taile, and a
bodie.Procop. in Exod. 
                  Capite immiſſo totus ſtatim illabitur, And if ſhe get
her head into a place, the whole bodie is ſo glib and 
                     •
                  ubricke,
that it will quickly enter in after: So in yeelding
to luſts, which are the heads of ſinne, the whole bodie of
ſinne will quickly follow after. For luſts, the heads of
ſinne, though they ſeeme ſmall, yet they will make no
ſmall worke where they enter. They are like young
rogues, who getting their heads in at the windowes,
creepe in and open the doores for the great theeues to
ſpoile the houſe. For luſts, the heads of ſinne, are not
idle heads, but like Ieſuites heads, working miſcheeuous
heads, contriuing treaſon againſt the ſtate both of ſoule
and bodie. Luſts will hatch ſinne, ſinne will produce
death, and death will bring a thouſand endleſſe woes and
miſeries.
               Now our luſts are many, our acts of ſinne many, and
the deaths produced by ſinne and the luſts thereof as
many.
               
                  Mi
                        ••
                     e 
                        ••
                     dis homines miſer
                        •
                     s mors 
                        •
                     na f
                        •
                     rig
                        ••
                     .
               
               Death aſſayes men a thouſand wayes. But death in
generall produced by ſinne and his luſts, is threefold,
               
                  Viz. Mors

                        1. Corporis. The death of the bodie.
                        2. Anima. The death of the ſoule.
                        3. Corporis &amp; anima. The death of both.
                     
                  
               
               1.Iohn 11. The death of the bodie. So dead was La
                        •
                     arus,
Iohn 11.
               2. The death of the ſoule. So dead are ſuch widdowes,

whereof S. Paul ſpeaketh, 1 Tim. 5. 6. So dead
was hee to whom out Sauiour Chriſt ſaid,1 Tim. 5. 6. 
                  Let the dead
burie their dead,
                  Matth. 8. 22. 
                  follow thou mee, Matth. 8. 22. A ſtrange
ſpeech, Let the dead burie their dead. As if the dead had
not as much need to be buried themſelues, as to burie other
dead; and as vnable to burie other dead, as themſelues.
But our Sauiour Chriſt meant it of thoſe which
followed ſinne, and not him (being via, vita, &amp; veritas;
The way, the life, and the truth,) that they were dead alreadie
in their ſoules;Theophylact. in 
                        〈◊〉
                      cap. 7. that in them (as Theophylact ſpeaketh)

                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   was 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , their liuing bodies were nothing elſe but
coffins of their dead carrion ſtincking ſoules,
               3.Luk. 16. 24. The death both of bodie and ſoule. So was Diues,
Luk. 16. He prayed, therefore he had a ſoule. Hee had a
tongue to be cooled, therefore a bodie: He was dead;
therefore dead both in bodie and ſoule. Thus die all they
that ſuffer ſinne to reigne in their mortall bodie. Nay,
they are not onely dead, but buried while they liue.
Their ſinnes become their graues:
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      Luc. 
                  Tumulusiſte mali mores;
ſaith S. Ambroſe.
                  
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     . tom. 1. Their throat is an open ſepulcher;
ſaith the Prophet Dauid,
                  Pſal. 14. 5. 
                  Pſal. 14. 5. Nay, they are not
onely dead and buried, but they are dead and buried, and
in hell whilſt they liue.Ambroſ. de Bon. 
                        〈◊〉
                     . c. vit. tom. 5. 
                  Nobiſcum videntur vinere, ſed
ſunt in infern
                        •
                     , ſaith S. Ambroſe, They ſeeme to liue with
vs, but in verie deed they are in hell. For where are preſumptuous
ſinners, but where the Deuill is, that firſt preſumed
to ſinne? And where is hell, but where the Deuill
is, that was without redemption caſt out of Heauen? O
then my beloued, take heed of going on in wickedneſſe,
nip ſinne in the bud, yeeld not obedience to the luſts
of ſin; Luſts are the iawes of ſinne, and the king reignes
where his lawes are obeyed. Luſts will goe on to acts;

acts will goe on to cuſtome; cuſtome will goe on to the
death and deſtruction both of bodie and ſoule. For God
will wound the hairie ſcalpe of ſuch as goe on ſtill in their wickedneſſe,
                  Pſal. 68. 21.
                  Pſal. 68. 21. The ſinner goes on in his ſinnes,
and God goes on to puniſh their ſinnes, ſinne followes
ſinne, and one death followes another. The ſecond
death followes the firſt: the death of the bodie begins,
and the death of both bodie and ſoule followes after.
The death of the bodie is, cum anima deſerit corpus, when
the ſoule forſakes the bodie, and is by order naturall, ſtatutum
eſt omnibus,
                  Heb. 9. 27. &amp;c. It is decreed for all men once to die,
Heb. 9. 27. The death of the ſoule is, cum animam deſcrit
Deus, when God forſakes the ſoule, and is by diuine Iuſtice
iudiciall;Ezek. 18. 4. 
                  the ſoule that ſinneth ſhall die, Ezech. 18. 4.
The death of both bodie and ſoule is,Auguſt. de Ci
                        •
                     it. 
                  cum anima à Deo
deſerta,
                  Dei. lib. 13. cap. 2. 
                  deſerit corpus; when God forſakes the ſoule, and
the ſoule forſaken of God, forſakes the bodie; and is by
equalitie proportionall. For both bodie and ſoule haue
ſinned,Cyprian. Epiſt. lib. 1. epiſt. 4. therefore they both die, both are puniſhed. Qui
i
                        ••
                     guntur in culpâ, non ſeparantur in poenâ; ſaith S. Cyprian;
Thoſe that are partners in the fault, muſt alſo bee partners
in the puniſhment for the fault. But yet a man may
ſo die the firſt, that he may eſcape the other death: Hee
may ſo die, that he may repaire the ruines of his mortall
bodie, and not die for euer.
               For as a ruinous houſe (though the wals bee fallen
downe, and the roofe periſhed) may by reparation be ſuſtained,
and be made more beautifull than at firſt, ſo long
as the maine and principall poſts thereof are kept ſound:
So this mortall bodie of ours, though it be ruinous, and
the fleſhy walls falling downe, and the thatch of the
roofe thereof decaying with hoatie haires, yet ſo long as
the principall pillars thereof bee not pulled downe (as

                  Samſon did the houſe vpon the Philiſtins) that is,
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      16. 29. ſo long
as the members of our bodie (the pillers thereof) are not
yeelded, as inſtruments of vnrighteouſneſſe vnto ſinne,
to let ſinne reigne; but yeelded, as thoſe that are aliue
from the dead, as inſtruments of righteouſneſſe vnto
God, and ſinne ſuppreſſed, wee may repaire this mortall
bodie, and make it more beautifull than before; Corruption
putting on incorruption,
                  
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                   
                  and mortalitie putting on immortalitie;
death being ſwallowed vp in victorie. O death where
is thy ſting? O hell where is thy victorie? 1 Cor. 15. 44, 45.
And this leads me by the hand to the laſt part of my text,
to ſpeake of the kingdome, our mortall bodie, and the repairing
thereof. Let not ſinne reigne therefore in your mortall
bodie.
               
            
            
               3. In your mortall bodie.
               ANd here by our mortall bodie, we muſt not vnderſtand
onely our lumpe of fleſh, part of man, but totum
compoſuum, the whole man, conſiſting of both bodie
and ſoule. For by a Synecdoche, the part is put for the
whole. The whole man, both bodie and ſoule, haue ſinne
in them, working their ruine and deſtruction, therefore
the whole man, both bodie and ſoule, are to be repaired,
and we are to labour for their reſtauration.
               I know there is a great diſpute betwixt the bodie and
ſoule, each endeuouring to put off the enormitie of ſinning
to the other. The bodie pleads for it ſelfe; that that
is but inanimis truncus. a dead and ſenſleſſe trunke, voyd
of all action and motion, and ſo could not ſinne, nor exerciſe
any operation, if the ſoule did not actuate and enforce
it. The ſoule, that pleads for it ſelfe, that that is purus
&amp; ſimplex ſpiritus, a pure and ſimple ſpirit, voyd of all

organs, without eyes to behold vanitie, without hands
to commit folly, without feet to follow enormitie, and if
the bodie did not detaine it as priſoner, it would mount
aloft, to take vp its reſidence in the place of ſpirits, and
therefore the fault of ſinning muſt needs reſt on the bodie.
But the verie truth is, that neither the bodie ſinnes
without the ſoule, nor the ſoule without the bodie, but
like Simeon and Leui,
                  Geneſ. 49. 5. they are brothers and partners in
miſchiefe, and ſo tend both to eternall deſtruction, vnleſſe
we wiſely endeuour their timely reparation.
               
                  Peter Martyr in his Commentarie on the fourth booke
of the Kings,
                  Pet. Mart. in 4 Reg c. 4. pag. 215 illuſtrates this by a prettie Simile. There
was (ſaith he) a maſter of a family, that committed the
cuſtodie of his Orchard to two ſeruants, one of them
lame of his feet, and the other blinde. The lame ſeruant
being taken with the beautie of the apples, told his blinde
fellow-ſeruant, that if he enioyed the vſe of his limbes,
and could goe as well as he, it ſhould not be long but he
would be poſſeſſed of ſome of thoſe apples. The blinde
ſeruant ſaid, he was as deſirous of them as himſelfe, and
if he could but ſee as well as he, they ſhould not reſt long
vpon the tree. In the end they agreed to ioyne together:
the whole-limb'd blinde man tooke the well-ſighted lame
man on his ſhoulders, and ſo hee reached the apples.
Their maſter comming, and miſſing his fruit, expoſtulated
the matter with them. Each framed his excuſe. The
blinde man ſaid, he could not haue them, for hee could
not ſee ſo much as the tree they grew on. The lame man
ſaid, he need not be ſuſpected; for it was well knowne
he could not climbe, or ſtand to reach them. But their
maſter perceiuing their craft, how they had both ioyned
together, put them as they were, one vpon the ſhoulders
of the other, and puniſhed them both together. So in

verie deed, neither the bodie ſinnes without the ſoule, nor
the ſoule without the bodie,Ambroſ. de fide 
                        〈◊〉
                     . c. 5. but corporis animique communis
eſt actus, ſaith S. Ambroſe, It is the common act of
both: therefore both bodie and ſoule tend to death, and
if they be not repaired, will fall to vtter ruine and deſtruction.
Wherefore as ſinne the tyrant muſt not reigne,
nor luſts, the lawes, be obeyed: So our mortall bodie,
his kingdome, muſt not runne to vtter ruine, but be repaired;
corruption muſt put on incorruption, and mortalitie
put on immortalitie.
               
               And the meanes to repaire our mortall bodie is three-fold:
               
                  Viz.

                        1. Diligent watching.
                        2. Often faſting.
                        3. Zealous praying.
                     
                  
               
               Faſting, that's good to repaire the bodie, that though
it be caſt downe it may be raiſed againe,
                     
                        •
                      Cor. 
                        •
                     . 27. and not become
a caſt-away, 1 Cor. 9. 27.
               Praying, that's good to repaire the ſoule, it conſecrates
it to God, makes the ſoule the temple and habitation of
the euerliuing God.
               
                  Templum mentis amat non marmoris, aurea in illo
                        
                           〈◊〉
                         vtra 
                           〈◊〉
                        .
                  
                  Fundamenta manent fidei.—
               
               Watching, that's good for both bodie and ſoule. By
watching, we may ſee and know when the luſts of ſinne
doe tempt vs, and ſo keepe them off and auoyd them.
By faſting, wee may ſo tame our bodies, that concupiſcence
ſhall not delight vs: and by praying, we ſhall ſo
rectifie our depraued will and reaſon, that it ſhall not
conſent vnto ſinne, to obey it in the luſts thereof.
               
               Firſt, we muſt watch, that ſinne enter not into vs. And
here we muſt doe, as is done in beſieged cities, keepe the
ſtricteſt watch, where the places are weakeſt, and the

enemie the moſt likely to enter. The places where ſinne
would enter, are three, the heart, the mouth, and the
hands. Therefore S. Bernard ſaith, that euery man muſt
keepe a three-fold watch.
               There muſt be

                     Vigilia

                           1. Cordis
                           2. Oris
                           3. Manus

                                 ſuper

                                       Cogitationes &amp; affectiones.Bernard in Seut.
                                       
                                       Verba.
                                       Opera.
                                    
                                 
                              
                           
                        
                        
                           A Watch
of the

                                 Heart
                                 Mouth
                                 Hands

                                       ouer our

                                             Thoughts and affections.
                                             Words and ſpeeches.
                                             Workes and actions.
                                          
                                       
                                    
                                 
                              
                           
                        
                     
                  
               
               
                  Firſt, we muſt watch ouer our hearts, that they be not
ſtained and polluted with euill thoughts. For, ſaith our
Sa
                        •
                     iour,
                  Matth. 15. 19. Out of the heart proceed euill thoughts, murders, Adulteries,
fernications, thefts, falſe witneſſes, blaſphemies, Mat.
15.Pſal. 14. 1. 19. And, the foole ſaid in his heart, there is no God, Pſal.
14.Ierem. 17. 9. 1. The heart (ſaith the Prophet Ieremie) is deceitfull aboue
all things, and deſperatly wicked, who can know it? Ier.
17. 9. It is good therefore to follow the counſell of wiſe
Salomon, Keepe thy heart with diligence, for out of it iſſueth
life,Prou. 4. 23. Prou. 4. 23.
               Secondly, we muſt watch ouer our mouthes, that wee
ſpeake no euill words: For, ſaith our Sa
                     •
                  iour Chriſt, By
thy words thou ſhalt be iuſtified,
                  Matth 12 37. 
                  and by thy words thou ſhalt be
condemned, Matth. 12. 37. And the wicked ſeruant was
condemned out of his owne mouth,
                  Luke 19. 12. 
                  Luk. 19. 12. For the
tongue in vdo eſt,
                  Auguſt. 
                        •
                     n Pſal. 38. 
                        •
                     om. 8. 
                  ideo facile labitur (ſaith Saint Auguſtine)
is placed in moiſture, and therefore is apt to runne ouer
to our owne deſtruction.Ber. de 3. cuſted. 
                  Facilè volat, ideo facilè violat, ſaith
Saint Bernard, It runnes glibly, and offends quickly. Our
euill words,Bernard. ſaith the ſame Father, are like arrowes, Leuitèr
volant, ſed grauitèr vnl
                        •
                     erant, The fly lightly, but they

wound deeply. Saint Gregory in the fifth of his Moralls,

                     ſaith there
are three
ſorts of
men, viz.

                           1 Some, that let looſe both heart and tongue
to impietie; they trauell with miſchiefe in
their heart, that they may vtter and bring
it forth with their tongue: Such was Eliphaz
the Temanite to Iob: Though he knew
he ſhould grieue him, yet he muſt ſpeake;
Who can with-hold himſelfe from ſpeaking?
                              Iob 4. 2▪
                              
                              Iob 4. 2. Such are the proud vngodly men,
which haue ſaid,
                              Pſal. 12▪ 4. 
                              with our tongue we will preuaile,
we are they that ought to ſpeake, who is
Lord ouer vs? Pſal. 12. 4.
                           2 Some,Gregor. expoſ. Moral. lib. 5. cap. 12. tom. 1. that though their hearts conceiue
euill, yet they refraine their lips, they bridle
their tongue from ſpeaking euill.
                           3 Others, that keep a watch ouer both heart
and tongue; that ſo neare as they can, they
neither thinke nor ſpeake euill.
                                 
                                    〈◊〉
                                 . 39. 
                                    •
                                 . Thus the
Prophet Dauid, I ſaid I will looke to my waies
that I offend not in my tongue, Pſal. 39. 1. I ſaid
I will looke to my wayes, that is, my heart, from
whence are the wayes to a mans tongue.Matth. 12. 32.
                              Out of the abundance of the heart the mouth
ſpeaketh, Matth. 12. 32.
                        
                     
                  
               
               
                  And of theſe three, the laſt is the pious and godly man,
and the ſureſt to keepe ſinne from reigning in his mortall
bodie.
                  
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      3. 2. 
                  Therefore Saint Iames ſaith, If any man offend not
in word, the ſame is a perfect man, and able to bridle the whole
bodie,
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      1 26. Iam. 3. 2. And, if any man ſeeme to be religious, and
bridle not his tongue, that mans religion is in vaine, Iam. 1. 26.
               But there are many that eſteeme lightly of words;
words are (thinke they) but wind, and who doe they hurt?
Though in their words they repine and murmure like Corah,
                  
againſt Moſes; raile like Goliah againſt Dauid; flatter
the State like Ierobeams young Councellers; curſe like
Shemei; lye like Gehezi; blaſpheme like Senacharib, and
are as vain-glorious as Herod; yet, ſo they abſtaine from
open violence, and pay euery man his owne, they thinke
their liues good enough: but theſe deceiue themſelues;
Euill words corrupt good manners,
                  1 Cor. 15. 33. 1 Cor. 15. 33. Where
euill words reigne in the mouth, there ſinne muſt needs
reigne in the mortall bodie.Ambroſ. in Eph. cap. 4. 10. n 3. 
                  Non credibile eſt cum bene viuere
qui male loquitur, ſaith Saint Ambroſe; It cannot be
thought that that mans life is good, whoſe ſpeech is bad.
It may more truly be ſaid to him, than it was ſaid to Peter,
Thy very ſpeech bewrayes thee,
                  Matth 26. 37. 
                  Matth. 26. 73. It ſtands euery
Chriſtian then vpon, to bridle his tongue, to refraine his
lips,Prou. 13. 3. to watch ouer his mouth; He that keepeth his mouth,
keepeth his life, but he that openeth wide his lips, ſhall haue deſtruction,
Prou. 13. 3.
               And in this watch of our mouths ouer our words, we muſt
obſerue three things.
               
                  There
muſt bee

                        1 Veritas in verbis, truth in our words. For
lying lips are an abomination to the Lord,Prou. 12. 22.
Prou. 12. 22.
                        2 Vtilitas in verbis, ſome profit muſt redound
by our ſpeech. Let no corrupt communication
proceed out of your mouth,
                           Epheſ. 4. 29. 
                           but that which
is good to the vſe of edifying, that it may miniſter
grace vnto the hearers, ſaith Saint Paul,
Epheſ. 4. 29. For one day we ſhall giue an
account for our corrupt communication,
we ſhall anſwer for euery idle word that
proceedeth out of our mouths. And if you
would more diſtinctly know what an idle
word is; Verbum 
                                 •
                              tioſum eſt quod ſine vtilitate,

vel loquentis,
                           
                              
                                 〈…〉
                              
                            
                           vel audientis profertur;
That is an idle word, by ſpeaking of which
neither ſpeaker nor hearer is bettered.
                        3 Parcitas in verbis; A meane and ſparing in
our ſpeech.
                           
                              
                                 〈…〉
                              
                            
                           For, ſaith Salomon, In the multitude
of words wanteth not ſinne, but he that
refraineth his lips is wiſe, Prou. 10. 19. And,
A fooles voice is knowne by a multitude of
words,
                              
                                 〈…〉
                              
                            Eccleſ. 5. 3.
                     
                  
               
               3. There remaines yet the third and laſt watch, that
is, the watch of our hands ouer our workes; wee muſt
watch ouer our workes, that we neither omit that which
we ſhould doe; nor commit that which we ought not to
doe. And here we muſt be ſure to keepe the moſt ſeuere
and ſtricteſt watch. For there redounds greater diſhonour
to God, and more ill examples to men, by the euill
acts of our hands, than by the thoughts of our hearts, or
the words of our mouths. If it pleaſe you therefore to
caſt the eye of your vnderſtanding vpon the Decalogue,
vpon the ten Commandements, you ſhall finde more
Commandements forbidding ſinne in action, than in
the ſpeech, or cogitation. Looke into the firſt Table;
there is one commandement forbidding ſinne in the
heart, namely, the firſt, Thou ſhalt haue no other gods but me.
There's another forbidding ſin in the tongue, namely the
third, Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in
vaine. But the other two forbid ſinne in action. Looke
into the ſecond Table, there's one Commandement forbidding
ſinne in the heart, namely the tenth, Thou ſhalt
not couet, &amp;c. There's another forbidding ſinne in the
tongue, namely the ninth, Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe
againſt thy neighbour. But the other foure forbid ſin
in action. And hereby we are taught, that if we will keepe

ſinne from reigning in our mortall bothe, we muſt watch
ouer our hands, to keepe them from acting and committing
ſinne.Eſay 56. 2. For, ſaith the Prophet Eſay, Bleſſed us the man
that keepeth his hand from doing any euill, Eſay 56. 2. So that
to conclude this point, the firſt way to ſuppreſſe ſinne, and
keepe it from reigning, is diligent watching. A watching
ouer our hearts for our thoughts,
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                   a watching ouer our
mouths for our words, but chiefly, and moſt diligently, a
watching ouer our hands 
                     •
                  or our actions.
               The ſecond meanes to ſuppreſſe ſinne, is often faſting.
Watching is like our beſieging of our enemy,
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                   but faſting
is like the pulling him downe, the ſpoiling and diſarming
him. For what are the armes and weapons of ſin, wherewith
he fights againſt vs, but the members of our mortall
body?
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                   And how are theſe armes made to be laid downe?
How are they pulled out of this tyrants hand, but by faſting?
Thus Saint Paul diſarmed ſinne, ſuppreſſed and
kept it vnder;1 Cor. 9. 27. 
                  I keepe my body vnder (ſaith he) I keepe it in
ſubiection, left, by any means, when I haue preached vnto 
                        〈◊〉
                     ,
I my ſelfe ſhould be a caſt-away, 1 Cor. 9, 27. And in very deed
our ſins are like thoſe deuils which could not be caſt out,Matth. 17. 21.
but by prayer and faſting, Matth. 17. 21.
               This exerciſe of faſting produceth three excellent

                     effects:

                           1 Vitia compri
                                    •
                                 i
                                    •
                                 . It allayes the heat of ſinne, it
tames and pulls downe the luſts of the bodie.
Therefore S. Baſil calls it,Baſil. the 
                                    〈…〉
                                 . 1. 
                                    〈◊〉
                                 . 1. 
                              
                                 〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                              ,
A medicine to take away the m
                                 •
                              lady of
ſinne.
                           2 Diabolum fugat. It puts the Deuill to flight.
Saint Ambroſe ſaith, that if a Serpent taſtes
but of faſting ſpettle,Ambroſ. Exam. lib. 6. c. 4. tom. 1. it killeth it: Vides quan
                                    ••
                                 
vis ieiu
                                    •••
                                 , vt &amp; ſput
                                    •
                                  ſue home terre
                                    ••
                                 m Serpente
                                    •
                                 
interficiat &amp; merit
                                    •
                                  ſpirit 
                                    ••
                                 em; Yee ſee the

force of faſting, faſting ſpettle will kill a bodily
Serpent, much more the ſpirituall.
                           3. Mentem eleuat. It eleuates a mans minde, and
makes him apt to be rapt into contemplation,
and his life here in earth to approach neere
in likeneſſe to the life of the Angels in heauen.
Therefore ſaith Saint Ambroſe,
                              
                                 
                                    〈◊〉
                                  
                                 
                                    •
                                 lia &amp; ieiun. c. 3. tom. 1. 
                              Quid eſt enim
ieiunium, niſi vitae coeleſtis image? For what is
faſting, but a repreſentation of our heauenly
life? Hoc gradu Elias aſcendit antequam curru;
Elias aſcended into heauen by this ladder of
faſting,Idem, Ibidem. before hee aſcended in his chariot of
fire, ſaith the ſame Saint Ambroſe.
                           
                        
                     
                  
               
               
                  Bonauenture therefore compares faſting to three

                     things.

                           1 To a little wood vnder a pot.
                                 
                                    〈◊〉
                                 . Diat. Salut. tit. 2. c. 6. Opuſc. tom. 2.
                           
                           2 To the nimbleneſſe of a little bird.
                           3 To the hollowneſſe and concauitie of a muſicall
inſtrument.
                        
                     
                  
               
               1. It is like a little wood vnder a pot. For as by withdrawing
the wood from vnder the pot, it incontinently
ceaſeth boyling: So by withdrawing the vſuall ſtore of
food from the body, the pride and ſuſtineſſe of the fleſh
is abated.
               2. It is like the agility &amp; nimbleneſſe of a little bird. For
as a little bird can eaſily by flying aloft eſchew the ſnares
of the Fowler: Fruſtra enim iacitur rete ante oculos pennatorum;
In vaine is the ſnare of the Fowler laid before the bird
that can take her wing, Prou. 1. 17. But groſſe and fat fowles
which cannot fly are taken: So the minde of a temperate
and abſtinent man may eaſily, by mounting aloft to heauen
vpon the wings of his contemplation, eſchew the
ſnares of the deceitfull fowler, the Deuill, whileſt thoſe
which with ſwine giue themſelues ouer to feeding, are
carried into a ſea of miſery.
               
                  
3. It is like the hollowneſſe or concauity of a muſicall
inſtrument, For as a Lute or Viall yeeldeth no delightfull
and muſicall ſound, vnleſſe the belly thereof be hollow
and emptie: So a man, vnleſſe his belly be ſo hollow and
emptie that his bones deſire not reſt, yeeldeth no muſicall
and delightfull harmony of prayers and thankſgiuing
in the eares of the Lord.
               For faſting is not commended of it ſelfe, ex opere operato,
of the thing done,Chem
                        •
                     it. Exam. Concil. Trident. part. 4. (as Chemnitius ſaith ſome Papiſts
teach; though Bellarmine diſauowes the opinion) but it is
commended ex opere operantis,
                  Bellar. de Bon. operib. in partic. lib. 2. cap. 11. Contro
                        •
                     . tom. 4. out of the faith and deuotion
attending the action. Deuout prayers, diuine eiaculations,
and heauenly meditations muſt accompany our
faſting. It was a caueat therefore which Saint Hierom gaue
to Calantia;
                  Hieron. ad Calant. epiſt. 14. tom. 1. 
                  Ca
                        •
                     e, ne ſi iei
                        •
                     nare aut abſtinere caeperis te p
                        •
                     tes
eſſe ſanctam. Hac enim virtus adi
                        •
                     ment
                        •
                     m eſt, non perfectio
ſanctitatis; Beware leſt if you begin to faſt or abſtaine, you
preſently thinke your ſelfe holy. For this vertue of abſtinence
is but the helpe, not the perfection of ſanctitie. We
muſt therefore, to ſuppreſſe ſinne, and to keepe it from
reigning in our mortall body, not only abſtain from meat
and drinke, but from all vice and impiety; and exerciſe
our ſelues in acts of deuotion, ſpend our time in prayer
and meditation, releeue the needy, and performe workes
of charity.Ambroſ. in D
                        •
                     m. 4. Quadrag. tom. 5. 
                  Qui ieiun
                        ••
                     t à cib
                        •
                      &amp; non abſtinent à malo, 
                        •••
                     
                     les
ſunt Diabolo, qui non manducat &amp; tamen à malo non ceſſat,
ſaith Saint Ambroſe. They which faſt from meat, but abſtaine
not from impietie, are like the Deuill, who eats neuer,
but is wicked euer. Therefore ſaith Saint Origen, Ieiuna
à mali
                        •
                      actibus,
                  Origen. in Leuit. cap. 16. 
                        •
                     om. 10. tom. 1. 
                  abſtine à malis ſermonibus, conti
                        •
                     e te à peſ
                     
                        ••••
                     is
cogitatio
                        ••
                     bus; Faſt from euill actions, abſtaine from
vaine ſpeech, refraine thy ſelfe from naughtie cogitations.
To our watching then we muſt ioyne faſting, and to

our faſting we muſt ioyne deuout prayer and holy meditation,
and this is the third and the laſt helpe to repaire
our mortall body, and to keepe ſinne from reigning in it.
               Let not ſinne therefore reigne in your mortall body, that you
ſhould obey it in the luſt thereof.
               The firſt helpe, that is, watching, is the beſieging of
ſinne; the ſecond, faſting, is the diſarming of ſinne; but
this laſt helpe, praying, is the vtter vanquiſhing and ſuppreſſing
of ſinne.Exod. 17. 9. For as Moſes lifting vp his hands, Iſrael
preuailed againſt their enemies, Exod. 17. 9. So let vs lift
vp our hearts and hands to God, in humble and heartie
prayer, and wee ſhall preuaile againſt ſinne, and keepe it
from reigning in our mortall bodie. The deadly ſerpent
the B. ſiliske (as Iſiodorus, Hiſpalenſis reporteth) is killed by
the breath of a Weaſell:
                     
                        •
                     ſ
                        •
                     od. Hiſpal. Ae
                     
                        •
                     imolog. lib. 12. cap. 3. So the breath of a faithfull
praying man is able to kill ſinne, and driue away the old
Serpent the Deuill, who ſuggeſteth vs to ſinne, and deſires
that it ſhould reigne in our mortall bodie.
               I will reduce all for you into three words, and ſo conclude.
               Explora.
               Deplora.
               Implora.
               
                  Explora. Let each Chriſtian, to keepe ſinne from reigning,
finde out his ſinne by watching▪ 
                  Deplore. Let him
driue it out when he hath found it, by weeping and faſting.
Implora. Let him deſire the gracious aſſiſtance of
God, that he may continue this combat, by praying. So
ſhall Sinne, Hell, and Satan be confounded, your mortall
bodie here be repaired, and after death moſt gloriouſly
be crowned.Reuel 2. 10. So ſaith God, Be thou faithfull, vnto
death, and I will giue thee a crowne of life, Re
                        •
                     . 2. 10. Thus
doing, though wee cannot altogether acquit and cleare

our ſelues of ſinne, yet we ſhall haue but few ſinnes, and
thoſe few ſinnes ſhall be remiſſible and pardonable ſinnes
vnto vs. Not for that they doe merit remiſſion, or are ſo
ſmall that they are vnworthy Gods puniſhment; but becauſe
remiſſion doth follow ſuch ſinnes, neither ſhall
they be imputed to vs to our condemnation. Herein we
ſhall be happie, that our ſinnes ſhall not be imputed vnto
vs. For they are not bleſſed, which haue no ſinne; for
then no man could be bleſſed (we are all miſerable wretched
ſinners:Pſal. 32. 1, 2) but ſaith the Prophet Dauid, Bleſſed is he
whoſe vnrighteouſneſſe i
                        •
                      forgiuen, and whoſe ſinne is couered.
Bleſſed is the man to whom the Lord imputeth no ſinne,
Pſal. 32. 1, 2.
               So that all men being ſinner
                     •
                  , here is the difference
betwixt the ſinnes of the wicked and the ſinnes of the
godly. The ſinnes of the wicked are committed with an
high hand, they meditate on them in their beds, they
commit them with all greedineſſe, they draw ſinne with
cart-ropes, they ſinne without repentance; therefore
their ſinnes are peccata regnantia, ſinnes reigning in their
mortall bodie, and neuer forgiuen them, but death and
hell reignes ouer them; they die the ſecond death, the
eternall death, the death both of bodie and ſoule. But
the ſinnes of the godly are committed without meditation,
through infirmitie, they are committed with a reluctancie,
there's a combat betwixt the fleſh and the Spirit,
they are reſiſted by watching, they are ſuppreſſed and
kept vnder by faſting, they are caſt out by praying, they
are repented of with repent mee neuer to be repented of;
therefore their ſinnes are 
                     〈…〉
                   ſinnes no
                     •
                  
reigning in their mortall bodie, but by the great mercie
of God, in Chriſt Ieſus, forgiuen and not imputed vnto
them, ſo that death hath not full power of them, they

die the death of the bodie onely, the firſt, not the ſecond
death,Reuel. 14. 13. and ſo die in the Lord, and die bleſſedly. For bleſſed
are they which die in the Lord, euen ſo ſaith the Spirit,
they rest from their labours, and their good works follow them,
Reu. 14. 13.
               In one word then to conclude all, with a true and
liuely faith in Chriſt Ieſus, reſiſt ſinne, let it not reigne in
your mortall bodie; and then you haue done all which is
required to your ſaluation: then you ſhall liue happily,
die bleſſedly, be rewarded plentifully, and poſſeſſe Heauen
euerlaſtingly. Which God of his infinite mercie
grant vnto euerie one of vs. To which God the Father,
the Creator of all, and hater of ſinne; God the Sonne,
the Sauiour of all, and Redeemer from the puniſhment
of ſinne; God the Holy Ghoſt, the Sanctifier of all, and
Purifier from the prauitie of ſinne, three Perſons, one
only wiſe God, bee aſcribed of vs all, all honour,
glorie, power, dominion, might, and
maieſtie, now and for euermore.
AMEN.
               FINIS.
            
         
      
      
         
            Errata.
            PAg. 2▪ lin. 15. read and he pag. 16. lin. 31. for iawes, read lawes. pag. 20. in 
                  •
               argine,
read c
                  •
               ntra.
            
         
      
   

