
   
      
         
            Musicke of sundrie kindes set forth in two bookes. The first whereof are, aries [sic] for 4. voices to the lute, orphorion, or basse. viol, with a dialogue for two voices, and two basse viols in parts, tunde the lute way. The second are pauens, galiards, almaines, toies, igges, thumpes and such like, for two basse-viols, the lierway, so made as the greatest number may serue to play alone, very easie to be performde. Composed by Thomas Ford.
            Ford, Thomas, d. 1648.
         
         
            
               1607
            
         
         Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2004-08 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01058
            STC 11166
            ESTC S121028
            99856219
            99856219
            21748
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01058)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21748)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 989:09)
         
         
            
               
                  Musicke of sundrie kindes set forth in two bookes. The first whereof are, aries [sic] for 4. voices to the lute, orphorion, or basse. viol, with a dialogue for two voices, and two basse viols in parts, tunde the lute way. The second are pauens, galiards, almaines, toies, igges, thumpes and such like, for two basse-viols, the lierway, so made as the greatest number may serue to play alone, very easie to be performde. Composed by Thomas Ford.
                  Ford, Thomas, d. 1648.
               
               [44] p. : music  
               
                  By Iohn Windet at [sic] the assignes of William Barley and are to be sold by Iohn Brovvne in Saint Dunstons churchyard in Fleetstreet,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  1607.
               
               
                  Signatures: A-L² .
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Lute music --  Early works to 1800.
               Viole da gamba music (viole da gamba (2)) --  Early works to 1800.
               Songs with lute --  Early works to 1800.
               Madrigals --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2003-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2004-01
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2004-04
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2004-04
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2004-07
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            MVSICKE OF SVNDRIE KINDES, Set forth in two Bookes.
            
               THE FIRST WHEREOF ARE, Aries for 4. Voices to the Lute, Orphorion, or Basse-Viol, with a Dialogue for two Voices, and two Basse Viols in parts, tunde the Lute way.
            
               THE SECOND ARE Pauens, Galiards, Almaines, Toies, Iigges, Thumpes and such like, for two Basse-Viols, the Liers way, so made as the greatest number may serue to play alone, very easie to be performde.
            Composed by THOMAS FORD.
            
            Imprinted at London by IOHN WINDET at the Assignes of WILLAM BARLET and are to be sold by IOHN BROVVNE in Saint Dunstons church yard in Fleet street 1607.
         
      
      
         
            
               
                  
                  A Table of the Songs contained in this booke.
                  
                     1 Notfull twelue yeares
                     2 VVhat then is loue
                     3 Vnto the temple.
                     4 Now I see thy lookes were fained.
                     5 Goe passions.
                     6 Come phillis.
                     7 Faire, sweet, cruell.
                     8 Since first I saw your face.
                     9 There is a Ladie.
                     10 How shall I then.
                     11 A Dialogue.
                  
                  When you sing alone to the Basse, such no 
                        〈◊〉
                      as are broken or deuided by reason o
                        •…
                      the wo
                        •…
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      the 
                        〈◊〉
                      or plaide in one stroke accord
                        •…
                      
                     
                        〈◊◊〉
                      Direction
               
               
                  
                  TO THE WORTHIE and vertuuos Knight, SIR RICHARD WESTON.
                  
                     SIR albeit musicke may instly chalenge an interest in the best parte of my education, I could be content for manie reasons to conceale my defects from the censure of sharper iudgementes, but the perswasion of some priuate friendes, together with the general good of such as take delight therein, hath encouragde me to vndergoe this hazard, which stands vpon the tickle point of liking, being in nothing more variable then in musicke: I shall not neede to make an Apologie in defence of these musickes, since none are so much in request nor more gene
                     
                        •…
                      receiued then of these kindes, which with all hartie affection I offer to your 
                        •…
                     rable iudgement not as a worke whose merit or worth deserues so iudicious a patron, but a manifestation of my worthlesse affection bound vnto you by many particular fauours: nor dare I vpon mine owne iudgement make expectation great with fair promises, yet thus much I dare presume, you shal find variety, and sith some of them hath beene gracd with your speciall fauour and liking, I doubt not they may also giue contentment to those that seekes delight, more then fautes, to whose kind acceptance vnder your worthie protection, I com mend these first fruites of my studies.
                  
                     Your Worships humbly deuoted
THOMAS FORDE.
                  
               
            
            
               
                  
                     
                     CANTVS
                     I. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        NOtfull twelue yeeres twice tolde A wearie breath I haue exchangde for 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         A wished death, my course was short the longer is my rest, God takes them soonest whom he loueth 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         best for he thats borne to day and, dies to morrow loseth some dayes 
                           •…
                        imirth 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈◊〉
                         but month
                           •…
                         of sorrow. Why feare we 
                           〈◊〉
                         deth that 
                           〈◊〉
                         cures o
                           •…
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         our sick-n esse Author of rest and ende of all distresses. ten come to grieue vs deth strikes but o nce and that stroke doth relieue vs. 
                           〈♫〉
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     ALTVS.
                     I 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        NOt full twelue yeares twise tolde, A wearie breath I haue exchangde, for a wished death, my 
                           〈♫〉
                         course was short, the longer is my rest, God takes them soonest whome he loueth best, for he thats 
                           〈♫〉
                         borne to day, and dies to morrow, loseth some dayes of mirth, but months of sorrow of sorrow, why 
                           〈♫〉
                         feare wee death that cures our sicknes-ses, that cures our sicknes-ses au-thor of rest &amp; end of all there mis-for-tunes oft-comes to grieue vs oft- ten comes to greue vs, deth strikes but once &amp; that stroke doth 
                           〈♫〉
                         distresses. relieue vs.
                  
                  
                     BASSVS.
                     I. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        NOtfull twelue ye
                           •…
                        res twise told, a wearie breath 
                           〈♫〉
                         I haue exchangde for a wished death, my course was short 
                           〈♫〉
                         the longer is my rest, God takes them soonest whome 
                           〈♫〉
                         he loueth hest for he thats borne to day and dies to 
                           〈♫〉
                         morrow 
                           〈◊〉
                         somedayes of mirth looseth some daies of 
                           〈♫〉
                         mirth, but moneths of sorrow, why feare we death that O there misfor-tunes 
                           〈♫〉
                         cures our sicknesses, author of rest, and end of all oft comes to grieue vs doth strikes but one &amp; that strok doth 
                           〈♫〉
                         distresses. relieue vs.
                  
                  
                     TENOR.
                     I. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        NOtfull twelue yeares twise tolde, a wearie breath I haue exchangde for a wished death, my 
                           〈♫〉
                         course was short the longer is my rest, God takes them soonest whome he loueth best, for hee th
                           •…
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         borne to day and dies to morrow, looseth some dayes of mirth, dayes of mirth, but months of sorrow: 
                           〈♫〉
                         Why feare we deth that cures our sicknesses our sicknesses au- thor of rest, and end of all O there mis-for- tunes of- ten comes to grieu vs to grieue vs, deth strikes but once &amp; that stroke doth 
                           〈♫〉
                         distresses, distresses, relieue vs, relieue vs.
                  
               
               
                  
                     
                     CANTVS.
                     II. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        WHat then is loue sings Cori- don since Phillida is growne so coy A flattring glasse to gaze vp- pon a busieiest A seri-ous t
                           •…
                        y. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         A flowre stil budding ne- uer blown A scanti
                           •…
                         d
                           •…
                        arth in fullest store yeelding least fruite where 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         most is sowne my dalie note shal be therefore heigh ho heigh ho chill 
                           〈◊〉
                        
                        ▪ 
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         no more heigh ho, heigh ho, chil loue no more. 
                           〈♫〉
                        
                     
                     
                        Tis like a morning dewi
                              •…
                            rose
                        Spread fairely to the suns arise,
                        But when his be
                              •…
                           es he doth disclose,
                        That which then flourisht quickly dies.
                        It is a selfe fed dying 
                              •…
                           pe
                        A pro
                              •…
                           e blisse▪ a 
                              •…
                           esse sore,
                        An aimelesse mark
                              •…
                           , 
                              •…
                           n erring scope,
                        My d
                              •…
                           ilie note shall b
                              •…
                            therefore,
                        Heigh 
                              •…
                           o, &amp;c,
                     
                     
                        Tis like a Lampe shining to all,
                        Whilst in it selfe it doth decay,
                        It seemes to free 
                              〈◊〉
                            it doth thrall,
                        And leades our 
                              〈◊〉
                            thoughts 
                              〈◊〉
                           ,
                        It is the spring of wintred har
                              •…
                           ,
                        Parcht by the s
                              •…
                           ers heate before,
                        F
                              •…
                           t hop
                              •…
                            kindly war
                              •…
                           h con
                              •…
                           erts,
                        My daily not
                              •…
                            shall be therefore
                        Heigh ho.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     ALTVS.
                     II. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        WHat then is loue sings Coridon, since Phillida is growne so coy, A flattring glasse to gaze vp-pon a busie iest a seri-ous toy, a flowre stil budding, neuer 
                           〈♫〉
                         blowne, A scantie dearth in fullest store, yeelding lest fruit, where most is sowne, my daily note shal be 
                           〈♫〉
                         therefore, heigh ho, chil loue no more, heigh ho chill loue no more.
                  
                  
                     BASSVS.
                     II. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        WHat then is lo
                           •…
                         
                        
                           •…
                        ings Corido
                           •…
                        e philida A flattring glasse to gaze vpon a busie 
                           •…
                        t, 
                           〈♫〉
                         is grown
                           •…
                        so coy a seri-ous toy. A flowre still budding neuer blowne 
                           〈♫〉
                         A scantie d
                           •…
                        th in fullest store, yeelding le
                           •…
                        t fruit where 
                           〈♫〉
                         most 
                           〈◊〉
                        , my d
                           •…
                        ily note shall be therefore, heigh ho 
                           〈♫〉
                         heigh h
                           •…
                        , 
                           〈◊〉
                         no 
                           •…
                        ore, heigh ho, ii chill loue no more
                  
                  
                     TENOR
                     II 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        WHat then is loue sings Coridon, since phillida is growneso 
                           •…
                        oy A flattring glasse to gaze vpon, a busie iest, a seri-ous toy, A flower still budding 
                           〈♫〉
                         neuer blowne, A scanti
                           •…
                         dearth in fullest store, yeelding 
                           •…
                        east 
                           〈◊〉
                         where most is sown
                           •…
                        , my daily note shall 
                           〈♫〉
                         be therefore▪ heigh ho, heigh ho, chil loue no more, heigh ho chill loue no more, no more.
                  
               
               
                  
                     
                     CANTVS.
                     III. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        VNto the temple of thy beauty &amp; to the tombe where pittie lie
                           •…
                         
                        
                           •…
                        pilgrime clad with zeale &amp; deuty do offer vppe my hart min
                           •…
                         eyes, 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         my ha
                           •…
                         loe in the quenc
                           •…
                        - lesse fire on loue
                           •…
                         burning alter lies conducted thither 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         by desire to be 
                           〈◊〉
                         sacrifice. 
                           〈♫〉
                        
                     
                     
                        But pitty on thy sabl
                              •…
                            herse, mine eyes the teares of sorrow shed
                        What though teares cannot 
                              •…
                           ate reuers
                              •…
                           , Yet are they 
                              〈◊〉
                            to the de
                              •…
                           d,
                        O 
                              •…
                           stresse in thy sanctuarie, why wouldst thou suffer cold disdaine,
                        To vse his frozen crueltie, and gentle pitty to be slaine.
                     
                     
                        Pittie that to thy beautie fled, and with thy beau
                              •…
                           ie should 
                              •…
                           ue liu'de,
                        Ah i
                              •…
                            thy hart lies b
                              •…
                           ried, and neuer more may be reuiu'de,
                        Y
                              •…
                            th
                              •…
                            l
                              •…
                           st 
                              〈◊◊〉
                            exte
                              •…
                           d, to accept these vowes, these teares I shed
                        Duties which I thy pilgrime send, to b
                              •…
                           y liuing pi
                              •…
                           y dead.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     ALTVS.
                     III. 
                           〈♫〉
                         _
                           •…
                        Nto th
                           •…
                         
                        
                           •…
                        ple of thy beauty, and to the 
                           •…
                        e where p
                           •…
                        ie li
                           •…
                        , I pilg
                           •…
                        ad with zeale &amp; deuty do offer vp
                           •…
                         my hart, mine eyes my hart lo
                           •…
                         in the 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈◊◊〉
                         
                        
                           •…
                        ues burning alt
                           •…
                        lies. Conducted thi
                           •…
                        er by desire, to bee beauties sacri
                           •…
                        ce. 
                           〈♫〉
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     BASSVS.
                     III. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        VNto the temple of thy beau-tie, and I pilgrim 
                           〈◊◊〉
                         zeale &amp; 
                           •…
                        uty do 
                           〈♫〉
                         to the 
                           〈◊〉
                         where pitty lies offer vpp
                           •…
                         my 
                           〈◊〉
                         
                        
                           •…
                        ies▪ my hart lo
                           •…
                         in the 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈◊◊〉
                         on loues bu
                           •…
                        ing a
                           •…
                        ar lie
                           •…
                        , co
                           •…
                        
                        ▪ du cted 
                           〈♫〉
                         thi-ther by 
                           〈◊◊〉
                         be beauties sa-cri▪ fice.
                  
                  
                     TENOR
                     III 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        VNto the temple of thy beautie, and to the tom
                           •…
                        e where pitty lies I pilgrime clad with zeale &amp; duty do offer vppe my hart my eyes. 
                           〈♫〉
                         my hart lo
                           •…
                         in the quenchle
                           •…
                        e fire on loues burning altar lies, Cond
                           •…
                        cted th
                           •…
                        er by desire to bee 
                           〈♫〉
                         beauties sacrifice.
                  
               
               
                  
                     
                     CANTVS.
                     IIII. 
                           〈♫〉
                         _
                           •…
                        Ow I se
                           •…
                         th
                           •…
                         loo
                           •…
                         w
                           •…
                         
                        
                           •…
                        ed qui
                           •…
                        ly lost and quickly g
                           •…
                        ed 
                           〈…〉
                         of wether
                           •…
                         hart vn-constant light as feathers, 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         tongue vntrusty subtle 
                           •…
                        ghted wan
                           •…
                         will with c
                           •…
                        nge delighted Syren pleasant 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           •…
                        oe to reason, C
                           •…
                        pid 
                           •…
                        gue thee for thy 
                           〈◊〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                        
                     
                     
                        Of thine eye I made my mirror,
                        From thy beauty came my error,
                        All thy wor
                              •…
                            
                           
                              〈◊〉
                            counted witty,
                        All thy 
                              〈◊〉
                            
                           
                              •…
                           med p
                              •…
                           tty,
                        Thy 
                              •…
                           se 
                              〈◊〉
                            
                           
                              •…
                           at 
                              〈◊〉
                            ag
                              •…
                           ued,
                        First of all my trust deceaued,
                        Syren.
                     
                     
                        
                           
                              〈◊〉
                            ac
                              •…
                           ptance when I 
                              •…
                           ed,
                        Louely words 
                              〈◊〉
                            c
                              •…
                           ning 
                              •…
                           sked,
                        Holy 
                              〈◊〉
                            
                           
                              •…
                           es but hart vnholy,
                        
                           
                              〈◊〉
                            
                           
                              •…
                           an my trust wa
                              •…
                            
                           
                              •…
                           olly,
                        Lilly white, and prety winking,
                        Soll
                              •…
                            vowes, but so
                              •…
                           ie thinking▪
                        
                        Syren.
                     
                     
                        Now I see O seemely cruell,
                        Others warme them at my fuell,
                        Wit shall guide me in this durance
                        Since in loue is no assurance,
                        Change thy pasture, take thy pleasure,
                        Beauty is a fading treasure.
                        Syren.
                     
                     
                        Pri
                              •…
                           e youth lasts not age will follow,
                        And 
                              〈◊◊〉
                            those tre
                              •…
                            yell
                              •…
                           ,
                        Wrinckled face for looke
                              •…
                            de
                              •…
                           ghtfull,
                        Shall acquai
                              •…
                            the dame despitefull,
                        And when time shall date thy glorie
                        Then to late thou wilt be sorry,
                        Syren.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     ALTVS.
                     IIII 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        NOw I see thy lookes were 
                           〈◊〉
                        , quickly lost and quickly gained Soft thy skin like wool of wethers hart vnconstant light as 
                           〈◊〉
                         Tong
                           •…
                         vntru
                           •…
                        e, subtle 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           •…
                        ighted, wanton will with 
                           〈◊〉
                         delighted, syren 
                           〈◊〉
                         to re
                           •…
                         
                        
                           〈◊〉
                         plag
                           •…
                         th
                           •…
                         
                        
                           〈◊◊〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         tr
                           •…
                        son.
                  
                  
                     BASSVS
                     IIII 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        NO
                           •…
                         I 
                           〈◊◊〉
                         lookes w
                           •…
                         
                        
                           •…
                        ined, quickly lost &amp; quickly gained, Sof
                           •…
                         thy skin like wool 
                           〈◊〉
                        , hart vnconstāt 
                           〈♫〉
                         light as fethe
                           •…
                        , Tong vntru
                           •…
                        , sub
                           •…
                        e sighted, wa
                           •…
                        - 
                           〈♫〉
                         ton will with change delighted, syren pleasant 
                           〈◊〉
                         t
                           •…
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         reason, Cupi
                           •…
                         
                        
                           •…
                        lague thee for thy treason,
                  
                  
                     TENOR.
                     IIII. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        NOw I see thy lookes were 
                           •…
                        ained, quickly lost and quickly gained Soft thy skin like wooll of wethers hart vnconstant light as fethers. Tongue vn- 
                           〈♫〉
                         trustie, subtle sigh
                           •…
                        ed, wan
                           •…
                        on will with change delighted, Syren pleasant 
                           •…
                        oe to reason 
                           〈♫〉
                         Cupid plague thee for thy treason.
                  
               
               
                  
                     
                     CANTVS.
                     V. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        GOe passions to the cr
                           •…
                         
                        
                           〈◊◊〉
                         sorrow
                           •…
                         
                        
                           •…
                        r 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         ceasing, Tell her those smiles, those smiles are emptie ayre growing hopes but 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         not en creasing hasting wasting with swift pace 
                           〈◊〉
                         of ioy in dull disgrace. 
                           〈♫〉
                        
                     
                     
                        Vrge her (but gently I request)
                        With breach of faith and wracke of vowes,
                        Say that my griefe, and minds vnrest,
                        Liues in the shadow of her browes,
                        Plying, 
                              •…
                           ying, 
                              〈◊〉
                            to die,
                        In 
                              〈◊〉
                            and 
                              •…
                           iserie.
                     
                     
                        Importune pittie at the last
                        (pittie in th
                              •…
                           se eyes should h
                              •…
                           er,)
                        Recount my sigh
                              •…
                            and to 
                              •…
                           nts past,
                        As Annals of a constan
                              •…
                            
                           
                              •…
                           ouer
                        Spending, ending many dayes,
                        Ofblasted hopes and slacke delayes.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     ALTVS.
                     V. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        GOe passions to the cruell faire, pleade my sorrowes neuer cea. sing, Tell her those 
                           〈♫〉
                         smiles are emptie, ayre growing hopes but not encreasing, hasting, wasting with swift pace, date of 
                           〈♫〉
                         ioy in dull disgrace.
                  
                  
                     BASSVS:
                     V. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        GOe passions to the cru- ell faire, pleade 
                           〈♫〉
                         my sorrowes neuer ceasing, neuer ceasing, tell her those 
                           〈♫〉
                         smiles are emp- tie, air
                           •…
                         growing hopes but not en- 
                           〈♫〉
                         creasing, hasting, wasting with swift pace, date of ioy in 
                           〈♫〉
                         dull disgrace.
                  
                  
                     TENOR
                     V 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        GOe passions to the cru
                           •…
                        l faire, the cruell faire and pleade my sorrowes neuer cea. sing, 
                           〈♫〉
                         tell her those smiles are emptie ayre, growing hopes but not encreasing, hasting, wasting with swift 
                           〈♫〉
                         pace, date of ioy in dull disgrace.
                  
               
               
                  
                     
                     CANTVS.
                     VI. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        COme Phillis come into these bowe
                           •…
                        , here shelter is from sharpest 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         showers, Coole gales of wind breaths in these shades daunger none this place enuades 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         here sit and note the chirping birdes, pleading my loue, pleading my loue in 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         silent wordes. 
                           〈♫〉
                        
                     
                     
                        Come Phillis, come bright heauens eye,
                        Cannot vpon thy be
                              •…
                           tie prie,
                        Glad Eccho in distinguisht voyce,
                        Naming thee will here reioyce.
                        Then come and heare her mercy layes
                        Crowning thy n
                              •…
                           e with lasting prayse.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     ALTVS.
                     VI 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        COme Phillis come into these bowres, here shelter is from sharpest showres, Coole 
                           〈♫〉
                         gales of wind breathes in these shades, danger none this place enuades, here sit and note the chirping birds 
                           〈♫〉
                         pleading my loue, ii. in si- lent words.
                  
                  
                     BASSVS
                     VI. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        COme Phillis come into these bowres, here 
                           〈♫〉
                         shelter is from sharpest showers, coole gales of wind 
                           〈♫〉
                         breathes in these shades danger none this place en 
                           〈♫〉
                         uades, here sit and note the chirping birds, pleading 
                           〈♫〉
                         my loue, pleading my loue in silent words.
                  
                  
                     TENOR.
                     VI. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        COme Phillis come into these bowres, he
                           •…
                        e shelter is from shar-pest, sho
                           •…
                        , coole 
                           〈♫〉
                         gales of winde, breathes in these shades danger none this place enuades, here sit and note the chir- 
                           〈♫〉
                         ping birdes, pleading my loue, ii. in si- lent words.
                  
               
               
                  
                     
                     CANTVS.
                     VII. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        EAire, sweet cruell, why doest thou fliemee, why dost thou flie me 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           •…
                        onot goe not, oh goe not from thy deerest, though thou doest hasten I am 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         niethee when thou see 
                           •…
                        st f
                           •…
                        re then 
                           〈◊〉
                         I neerest, Tarrie then 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         Tarrie then Oh tarrie, Oh tarrie then and take me with you. 
                           〈♫〉
                        
                     
                     
                        Fie, 
                              〈◊〉
                           , sweetest here is no danger, ii,
                        Flie not, flie not, oh flie not loue pursues thee,
                        I am no foe, nor forraine stranger,
                        Thy scornes with fresher hope renewes me,
                        Tarrie then, &amp;c.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     ALTVS.
                     VII. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        FAire, sweete, cruell, why dost thou flie me, why dost thou flie me, oh goē not from thy deerest' 
                           〈♫〉
                         though thou doest hasten, I am nie thee, when thou seemest far, then am I neerest, Tarrie then 
                           〈♫〉
                         ii- ii. and take me with you, oh tarrie then and take me with you.
                  
                  
                     BASSVS.
                     VII. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        FAire sweete, cruell, why dost thou flie me, 
                           〈♫〉
                         why dost thou flie me, goe not, oh goe not, from thy 
                           〈♫〉
                         derest, though thou dost hasten, I am nie thee, when 
                           〈♫〉
                         thou seem e farre, then am I neerest, Tarrie then 
                           〈♫〉
                         Oh tarrie, oh tarrie then and take me with you.
                  
                  
                     TENOR
                     VII 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        FAire, sweet, cruell. why dost thou flie me, why dost thou flie me, go not from thy 
                           〈♫〉
                         deerest, though thou dost hasten, I am nigh thee, when thou seemest far then am I neerest, Tarrie then 
                           〈♫〉
                         ii- Oh tarrie, tarrie then, oh tarrie, oh tarrie then and take me with you.
                  
               
               
                  
                     
                     CANTVS.
                     VIII. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        SInce first I saw your face I resolude to honour &amp; r
                           •…
                         nowne yee, If now I be dis▪ dayned I wishe my hart had neuer knowne yee, 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         What I that lou'de and you that likte shal wee beginne to wrangle No, No, 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         no, my hart is fast and cannot disentan- gle. 
                           〈♫〉
                        
                     
                     
                        If I admire o
                              •…
                            prayse you too much, that fault you may forgiue mee,
                        Or if my hands had stray'd but a touch, then iustly might you leaue 
                              〈◊〉
                           ,
                        I askt you leaue, you bad m
                              •…
                            loue▪ ist now a time to c
                              •…
                           ideme?
                        No, no, no, ile loue you still, what 
                              〈◊◊〉
                            b
                              •…
                           ide me.
                     
                     
                        The Sunne whose be
                              •…
                           es most glorious are, 
                              〈◊〉
                            no heholder,
                        And your sweet 
                              〈◊◊〉
                           , made my poore eye
                              •…
                            the boulder,
                        Where beautie mou
                              •…
                           s, and wit delights, and signes of kindnes bind me
                        There, O 
                              〈◊〉
                            where 
                              〈◊〉
                            I go, ile leaue my hart behinde 
                              •…
                           e.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     ALTVS.
                     VIII 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        SInce first I saw your face, I resolude to honour and renowne ye, What I that lou'de, and If now I bee dis-day
                           •…
                        ned I wishe my hart had ne-uer known ye 
                           〈♫〉
                         you that likte, shall wee beginne to wrangle, no, no, no, my hart is fast and cannot disentangle. 
                           〈♫〉
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     BASSVS
                     VIII. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        SInce first I saw your face, I resolude to If now I bee dis dai-ned I wish my 
                           〈♫〉
                         honour and renowne yee, What I that lou'de, and hart had ne-uer known ye, 
                           〈♫〉
                         you that lik
                           •…
                         shall wee begin to wrangle, no, no, no, my 
                           〈♫〉
                         hart is fast and cannot dis- entangle.
                  
                  
                     TENOR.
                     VII. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        SInce first I saw your face, I resolude to honour and renowne ye, What I that lou'de If now I bee dis-day-ned I wishe my hart had neuer known ye. 
                           〈♫〉
                         and you that likte shall wee beginne to wrangle, no, no, no, my hart is fast, and cannot dis- entangle. 
                           〈♫〉
                        
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     
                     CANTVS.
                     IX. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        THere is a Ladie sweet &amp; kind was neuer face so pleasde my 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         mind I did but see her passing by and yet I loue her till I die. 
                           〈♫〉
                        
                     
                     
                        H
                              •…
                            iest
                              •…
                           re, 
                              •…
                           tion and 
                              •…
                           er 
                              〈◊〉
                           ,
                        Her wit, her voyce▪ my hart beguil
                              •…
                           s,
                        
                           
                              •…
                           eguiles my hart. I know not why,
                        And yet I loue her till I die.
                     
                     
                        Her free beh
                              •…
                           our winning lookes,
                        Will make a Lawyer burne 
                              〈◊〉
                            bookes
                        I toucht her not, alas not I,
                        And yet I loue her till I die.
                     
                     
                        Had I her fast betwixt mine a
                              •…
                           es,
                        Iudge you that thinke such sports were harmes,
                        Wert any ha
                              •…
                           ? no, no, fi
                              •…
                           , fi
                              •…
                           ,
                        For I will loue her till I die.
                     
                     
                        Should I remaine co
                              •…
                           ined there,
                        So long as Phebus in his spher,
                        I to request shee to deni
                              •…
                           
                           ▪
                        
                        Yet would I loue her till I die.
                     
                     
                        Cupid is wi
                              •…
                           ged and doth ra
                              •…
                           ge,
                        Her countrie
                              •…
                            my l
                              •…
                           e doth change,
                        But change she 
                              •…
                           arth, or change she 
                              •…
                           kie,
                        Yet will I loue her till I die.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     ALTVS.
                     IX 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        THere is a Lady sweet and kind, was neuer face so pleasde my minde, I did but see her 
                           〈♫〉
                         passing by, 
                           〈◊◊〉
                         I 
                           〈◊〉
                         her till I die. 
                           〈♫〉
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     BASSVS
                     IX. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        THere is a Lady sweet and kinde, was 
                           〈♫〉
                         neuer face so pleasde my mind, I did butse
                           •…
                         her 
                           〈♫〉
                         passing by, and yet I loue her till I die.
                  
                  
                     TENOR.
                     IX. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        THere is a Lady sweet and kind, was neuer face so pleasde my mind, I did but see her 
                           〈♫〉
                         passing by, and yet I loue her till I die. 
                           〈♫〉
                        
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     
                     CANTVS.
                     X. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        HOw shall I then dis- cribe my loue, when all mens skilfull arte is 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         Far inferior to her worth, to prayse thu'n worthiest parte, shee's chaste in looks mild in her 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         speech in actions all dis▪ creet of nature louing pleasing most in vertue all complea
                           •…
                        e. 
                           〈♫〉
                        
                     
                     
                        And for her voyce a Philo 
                              •…
                           e, her lip may all lips skorne,
                        No sunne more cleare then is her eye, in brightest Summer 
                              〈◊〉
                           
                        
                        A mind wherein all vert
                              •…
                           es rest, and takes delight to be
                        And where all vertues graft themselues in that most fruitfull tree.
                     
                     
                        A tree that India doth not yeeld, nor euer yet was seene,
                        Where buds of vertue alwaies springes, and all the yeere growes greene,
                        That countries b
                              •…
                           st wherein she growes, and happie is that rocke,
                        From whence she springes▪ but happiest he that grafts in such a stocke.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     ALTVS.
                     X. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        HOw shall I then discribe my loue, when all mens skilfull art is farre inferior to her worth, to 
                           〈♫〉
                         prayse the vnworthiest part, shees chast in lookes, mild in her speech, in actions all discreet, of nature louing 
                           〈♫〉
                         pleasing most, in vertue all compleate.
                  
                  
                     BASSVS.
                     X. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        HOw shall I then discribe my loue, when all 
                           〈♫〉
                         mens skilfull arte is farre inferior to her worth to 
                           〈♫〉
                         praise thunw orthiest part, shees chaste in looke, milde 
                           〈♫〉
                         in her speech, in actions all discreet, of nature, louing 
                           〈♫〉
                         plea- sing most in ver- tue all com-pleate,
                  
                  
                     TENOR
                     X 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        HOw shall I then discribe my loue, when all mens skilfull art is farre inferior to her worth, to 
                           〈♫〉
                         praise thu'n worthiest, parte, shees chast in lookes, milde in her speech, in actions all discreet, of 
                           〈♫〉
                         nature louing, pleasing most, in vertue all compleate.
                  
               
               
                  
                     
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        S Hut not, shut not sweet brest 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         to see me all of fire, 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         Thy snow in- flames these flames of my de. sire, Thy snow ni'll hurt me 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         This cold wil coole me Take ths chast fire to that pure virgin snow. 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         Thou giust more blisse th
                           •…
                         mortall harts may know, 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         Let one griefe harme vs, and one ioy fill vs, let one loue warme vs, &amp; 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         one deth kill vs, and one death kill vs. 
                           〈♫〉
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     A Dialogue
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         F 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         Flie not, Flie not, flie not deer hart to find me all of snow, 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         and I de-sire de- sire sweet flames to know. Nor thy fire wil harm me 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         and this heate will warm me, be- 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         ing now thus warmd ile neuer seeke other fire. more blisse I 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         take then Angels can desire. Let one griefe harme vs and one ioy fill vs, let one loue 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         warm vs &amp; one death kill vs. &amp; one death kill vs. 
                           〈♫〉
                        
                     
                  
               
            
         
         
            
               
                  
                  A Table of the Lessons contained in this booke.
                  
                     1 A Pauen.
                     2 The Galliard.
                     3 An Almaine.
                     4 A Pauen.
                     5 The Galliard.
                     6 Forget me not.
                     7 A Pauen.
                     8 An Almaine.
                     9 The wild goose chase.
                     10 What you will.
                     11 And if you do touch me Ile crie.
                     12 The Bag-pipes.
                     13 Why not here.
                     14 Chang of Aire
                     15 VVhip it and Trip it.
                     16 Cate of Bardie
                     17 A snatch and away.
                     18 A pill to purge Malancholie.
                  
               
               
                  
                  TO THE VVORTHY and vertuous knight Sir RICHARD TICHBORNE
                  
                  
                     SIr hauing so contriued these Musickes as their seuerall natures requires a diuision I could not amongst manie friendes thinke vpon two more worthy to bee ioynde in this Dedication then your selues, aswell for your neere alliance in blood, loue and fauour to Musicke, which neuer goes vnaccompanied with other vertues, as also the many particular fauours I haue receiued frō you both, hauing no gratification or token of my loue and thankefulnes, but these issues of my braine, which I intreate you to accept &amp; take in good part, my cheifest labor in setting thē forh hath bin to expresse my inuention with as much facility and ease as possibly I could to the end (since it is a Musicke so generally pleasing) they who bestaffect it, may with little labour be actors of their owne delightes. If you find in them any matter of worth I haue my rewarde, if any matter of content I haue my end, which is nothing else then by some agreeable testimony, to leaue in you both, an impression of my thankefull rememrance of your loue and fauors.
                  
                     Your Worships humbly deuoted
THO. FORDE.
                  
               
            
            
               
                  
                  PRIMA PARS.
                  1. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     A Pauen. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      M. Southcotes Pauen.
               
               
                  
                  SECVNDA PARS
                  1. 
                        〈♫〉
                      _
                        〈◊〉
                      Pauin. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      M. Southcotes Pauin.
               
               
                  
                  PRIMA PARS.
                  II. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     THe Galiard. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
                  III 
                        〈♫〉
                      _
                        〈◊〉
                      Almaine, 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      M. Westouers farewell. This part to be plaide alone.
               
               
                  
                  SECVNDA PARS
                  II 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     THe Galiard. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
                  III. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     AN Almayne. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      M. Westouers fare well,
               
               
                  
                  PRIMA PARS.
                  IIII. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     A Pauin. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      M. Maines Choice.
               
               
                  
                  SECVNDA PARS
                  IIII 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     A Pauen. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      M. Maines Choice.
               
               
                  
                  PRIMA PARS.
                  V. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     THe Galiard. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
                  VI. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     FOrgetme not, 
                        〈♫〉
                      To play alone.
               
               
                  
                  SECVNDA PARS
                  V 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     THe Galiard. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
                  VI. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     FOrget me not. 
                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  PRIMA PARS.
                  VII. APauen. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      Sir Richard Westons delight
               
               
                  
                  SECVNDA PARS
                  VII APauin. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      Sir Richard W
                        •…
                     ons delight
               
               
                  
                  PRIMA PARS.
                  VIII. AN Almaine. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      Mounsieur Lullere his choice.
                  IX. THe wild goose chase. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      Sir Iohn Philpots delight.
               
               
                  
                  SECVNDA PARS
                  VIII AN Almaine. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      Mounsieur Lullere his choice.
                  IX. THe wilde goose chase. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      Sir Iohn Philpots delight.
               
               
                  
                  PRIMA PARS.
                  X. WHat you will. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
                  XI. ANd if you do touch ile cri
                        •…
                     . 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      Sir Richard Tic
                        •…
                     nce 
                        〈◊〉
                     .
                  This to be plaide alon
                        •…
                     , 
                        •…
                     od so from hence in this part to the 
                        •…
                     d.
                  Note by the way where you find letters thus markte.
                  Thumpe them with the first and second finger of the le
                        •…
                     t hand according to the direction of the pricks.
               
               
                  
                  SECVNDA PARS
                  X. WHat you will. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
                  XI. ANd if you do touch me ile crie. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      Sir Richard Tichbornes toy.
                  where you find letters thus markte.
                  Thumpe them with the first and second finger of the le
                        •…
                     t hand according to the direction of the pricks.
               
               
                  
                  PRIMA PARS.
                  XII. THe Baggepipes. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      Sir Charles Howards delight
                  XIII. WHy not here 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      M. Crosse his choice.
               
               
                  
                  SECVNDA PARS
                  XII. THe Baggepipes. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      Sir Charles Howards delight
                  XIII. WHy not here. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      M. Crosse his choice.
               
               
                  
                  PRIMA PARS.
                  XIIII. CHange of Ayre▪ 
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
                  XV. WHipit and Tripit. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      M. Southcotes Iig.
               
               
                  
                  SECVNDA PARS
                  XIIII. CHange of Ayre▪ 
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                     
                  
                  XV. WHipit and Tripit. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      M. So
                        •…
                     cotes Iig
                        •…
                     .
               
               
                  
                  PRIMA PARS.
                  XVI. CAte of Bardie. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      The Queenes Iig.
               
               
                  
                  SECVNDA PARS
                  XVI. CAte of Bardie. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      The Queenes Iig.
               
               
                  
                  PRIMA PARS.
                  XVII. ASnatch and away. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      Sir Iohn Paulets toy.
                  XVIII. APill to purge Melancholie. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      M. Richard Martins Thumpe.
               
               
                  SECVNDA PARS.
                  XVII. ASn
                        •…
                      and away. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      Sir Iohn Paulets toy.
                  XVIII. APill to purge Melancholie. 
                        〈♫〉
                      
                     
                        〈♫〉
                      M. Richard Martins Thumpe.
                  
               
            
         
      
   

