
   
      
         
            A declaration made by the Reformed Churches of France and the Principalitie of Bearn Concerning their vniust persecution by the enemies of the estate and of their religion. Together with their lawfull and necessarie defence. Acording to the French copie printed in Rochell.
            Declaration des eglises reformées de France &amp; souveraineté de Béarn. English.
            Eglises réformées de France.
         
         
            
               1621
            
         
         Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01186
            STC 11300
            ESTC S114327
            99849553
            99849553
            14707
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01186)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14707)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1350:07)
         
         
            
               
                  A declaration made by the Reformed Churches of France and the Principalitie of Bearn Concerning their vniust persecution by the enemies of the estate and of their religion. Together with their lawfull and necessarie defence. Acording to the French copie printed in Rochell.
                  Declaration des eglises reformées de France &amp; souveraineté de Béarn. English.
                  Eglises réformées de France.
                  Combort, fl. 1621.
                  Bern (Switzerland : Canton) aut
               
               40 p.   
               
                  S.n.],
                  [London :
                  M.DC.XXI. [1621]
               
               
                  Signed at end: Combort, President. Banage, Assistant. Rodil, Secretarie. Riffaut, Secretarie.
                  A translation of: Declaration des eglises reformées de France &amp; souveraineté de Béarn: De l'injuste persćution .. et de leur legitime defense, published at La Rochelle par Pierre Pié de Dieu.
                  Ordered "not to be printed".
                  Place of publication from STC.
                  Imperfect; some print faded and show-through.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Huguenots --  France --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-08
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-07
            Taryn HakalaSampled and proofread
         
            2007-07
            Taryn HakalaText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
               
A DECLARATION MADE BY THE REFORMED CHVRCHES OF FRANCE AND THE PRINCIPALITIE OF BEARN.
            Concerning their vniuſt perſecution by the Enemies of the Eſtate and of their Religion. Together with their lawfull and neceſſarie defence.
            
            Acording to the French Copie printed in Rochell.
            M. DC. XXI.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            A DECLARATION made by the Reformed Churches of France and the Principalitie of Bearn.
            Concerning their vniuſt perſecution by the enemies of the Eſtate and of their Religion. Together with their lawfull and neceſſary defence.
            WE the Deputies in the Generall Aſſembly of the Reformed Churches of France and the Principalitie of Bearn, perſecuted by the enemies of the Eſtate and of their Religion, who abuſe the Kings mind and conſcience, ſeeing that to our great griefe we are conſtrained by the violence of oppreſſion to haue recourſe vnto naturall and lawfull meanes (by a neceſſarie defence) to preſerue the libertie of our conſciences and the ſafetie of our liues againſt theſe our implacable enemies: We proteſt in the name of the ſaid Churches before God and men, inuiolably to remaine vnder the ſubiection of our King, acknowledging that he is giuen vs of God to be our ſoueraigne Lord. And that all the world may take notice that as this obedience, next vnto the worſhip of God, is the onely aime of our intention, ſufficiently manifeſted by our former fidelitie ingrauen in the pillars of our Eſtate, and in the crownes of our late Kings, raiſed vp againe by our predeceſſors and our ſelues, notwithſtanding the endeuors of our enemies factions: alſo the hatred and perſecution which we now endure, is raiſed vp for no other cauſe by our enemies, but for this holy and iuſt action; whereunto they know we are inſeparably bound, by the rules of our

Religion, by the example of our progenitors, and the right of our owne conſeruation.
            Firſt of all then we beſeech the King and all true French men, as alſo all Kings, Princes and Potentates, friends and confederates of the Crowne, and generally all men who are touched with the zeale of Gods glorie, with commiſeration of innocencie troden vnder foote, and with griefe for the miſeries which at this day threaten France: to informe themſelues here of our iuſt complaints, that in them they may ſee the perfidiouſneſſe of our enemies and their crueltie, and which (whether we will or no) they pull out of our boſome, and binde vs to publiſh for the iuſtification of our innocencie, and to let all ſuch as loue iuſtice and truth ſee, that the refuge of our defence whereunto we are brought, is both neceſſary and iuſt; our enemies being thruſt forward by no other motiue to kindle the fire in this kingdome, then to put out the light of our Religion, and to ouerthrow the moſt ſure reſiſtance which in the Eſtate may be oppoſed to forrein enterpriſes. But becauſe by their wonted ſubtilties they haue here followed the common courſe which tends to violence and crueltie, making to themſelues a way by falſe accuſations to the oppreſſion of a iuſt cauſe. And for a pretence to inuade vs, they haue proclaimed vs rebels and ſeditious; and to ſpread euery where this accuſation, they employ the Edicts and declarations of the King and of the Parliaments, yea and the mouth of Ambaſſadours in forrein parts. To the end that the ſimplicitie of thoſe who are leaſt informed either of the hatred, or of the power, or of the craft of our enemies, might not receiue ſome ſiniſter impreſſion of vs; touching the dutie of obedience and fidelitie towards our King and country: we will ſhew here that all the pretences and iniurious crimes wherewith they charge vs, are meerly artificiall diſguiſings borrowed as a veile to couer the outrages done to innocencie. For as to inflame the hatred of Kings and the furie of the people againſt the Goſpell, they haue heretofore accuſed the firſt Chriſtians, &amp; our fathers in theſe laſt times

of like crimes, namely that they tranſgreſſed againſt the decrees Act. 17. 7. of Ceſar, moued ſedition among the people, and did ouerthrow the royaltie of Princes. Vnder theſe ſuppoſed accuſations they haue cauſed them to ſuffer euery where the violence of the ſword, the burning of fire, the crueltie of maſſacres, the futie of warres, and the horror of all ſorts of exquiſite torments. It is true, that as our fathers were more weake and naked, or expoſed to a more eaſie ſlaughter, Religion then was directly charged with theſe crimes, and then they haue perſecuted and made open war vpon them for their profeſſions ſake. But now by a ſubtiltie fitted to their intentions, our enemies haue altered the method. They enterpriſe warre vpon the perſons, to breake in vpon Relgion. And becauſe that after ſo many perfidious and cruell practiſes, the arme of God hauing raiſed vs vp, as out of our fathers aſhes, and by the miraculous proſperitie of the late King (conducted by our ſidelitie vpon the throne of this monarchie) the breaches of the Eſtate being repaired, that there might be eſtabliſhed a firme peace, an Edict was granted vs for the libertie of our conſciences, and places of ſafetie to preſerue our goods and liues againſt the violence which the former euils made vs feare for the time to come: truly it were now too an apparent violating of peace, and they ſhould too manifeſtly declare themſelues enemies of the quiet of France, if openly this Edict made in fauour of vs, ſhould be reuoked, and it they ſhould make war vpon vs for Religion. It were alſo to ingage too many perſons in one ſelfe ſame cauſe. For theſe cauſes to couer their proiected purpoſe of the ruine of this Eſtate through ours, to arme the King againſt vs, and to deſtroy vs with greater eaſe then other wiſe they could poſſibly do. They haue proclaimed vs rebels and offenders, they haue endeuoured to make this cauſe more particular; they call the warre they make vpon vs a chaſtiſement of ſeditious perſons. But when we ſhall haue here made plaine to the eyes of all the world the purpoſe of thoſe who are authors of theſe troubles and confuſions; the long oppreſſion we haue hitherto endured

with all patience; the euidences of our right in the courſe we haue held in our complaints, and moſt humble ſuites made to our King, now laid againſt vs as a crime: Laſtly ye open perſecutiō which at this inſtant they inflict vpō vs by the armies already raiſed againſt vs in all the parts of this kingdome where they thinke we are able any way to reſiſt, We hope that we ſhall cleare our innocencie from theſe ſlanders, ſhall approue our iuſt and neceſſary defence, which we vndertake, waiting for the help and bleſſing of the Almightie. And finally we ſhall obtaine fauour and aſſiſtance from all ſuch as loue his glorie and the truth: and the ſuccour and helpe of whoſoeuer they be that deſire the conſeruation of this poore kingdome.
            Since the moſt ſure ſtay o
                  •
                the Edict for our ſafetie, eſtabliſhed The intent of our enemies, and the meanes to attain therto by the mightie hand of the late King, fell by the ſtroke of his death; the enemies of our Religion and of the publike peace, lifting vp themſelues with more hope of going forward and of bringing their purpoſes to paſſe, turned all their endeuours to ouerthrow this foundation of the tranquillitie of the State, knowing that the ſureſt way to bring againe the confuſion of troubles and of the forepaſſed warres, was to deſtroy the Edict which had deſtroyed them. But not being able to promiſe to themſelues that the good inclinations of the King, and the wiſedome of his Mother then Regent, and all well affected Frenchmen intereſſ
                  •
               d in the peace of the kingdome, would conſent, or could ſuffer an open breach of the Edict, they ſought to gaine by peece-meale that which they could not obtaine in the whole ſumme: and by fleights and more ſecret practiſes to cauſe things to fall into the gulfe, whereinto now they haue throwne them.
            The firſt groundworke of their plot did bewray it ſelfe with aſtoniſhment and iuſt apprehenſion of all of vs, when in the coronation of the King they made him take this oath: I will truly endeuour to my power to exclude from my iuriſdiction and lands vnder my ſubiection, all heretickes ſo denounced by the Church. As if he took his Crowne vnder this

condition and vnder this law, that he ſhould roote vs out when he could do it. The blood of that great Henrie crieth yet for vengeance for the furious and abominable murtherer, who proteſted and affirmed that the onely reaſon why he murthered him, was becauſe he was a fauourer of hereticks, that he ſuffered them in his kingdome, that he put them not to the ſword: and here they haue cauſed his ſon and ſucceſſor, to promiſe that he ſhall employ all his power to roote vs out. By this powerfull and effectuall reaſon they did ingraue in the Kings heart from his moſt tender yeares the neceſſitie of hating and deſtroying vs; and beſides the horror of the example of his Father cruelly ſlaine for maintaining peace with thoſe who are called hereticks, they take of him a ſolemne promiſe to raigne and ſit vpon his throne vnder this condition to perſecute thoſe whom his father conſerued and kept. For who is ignorant that vnder the name of heretickes, they meane vs? That we are proclaimed and ſtiled ſuch by the Roman Church? And therefore if the King be bound to the obſeruation of this oath according to their intention, what may we not then feare? Wherefore vpon former experience ought we not to feare againe the vnhappie bloodſheds which ſuch impreſſions and impoſed neceſſities vpon the conſciences of Kings, haue cauſed vs to feele?
            The like proiect of our enemies hath yet openly manifeſted it ſelfe, when endeuouring to make a fundamentall law to paſſe, and an vniuerſall principle of conſcience, that we ought not to be ſuffered in France; they obtained in the laſt Eſtates held at Paris, that the houſes of the Clergie and Nobilitie ſhould expreſly demaund by their roles the execution of this oath of the King, as alſo the reception and publication thereof by the Councell of Trent. A Councell which hath bin heretofore reiected publikely by thoſe Eſtates which were held when the moſt bloodie and violent troubles haue bin ſtirred vp againſt vs in this kingdome. A Councell which will not endure that Kings ſhould raigne, if they permit life and libertie in their dominions to thoſe

who are called heretickes.
            But the moſt apparent and moſt ſenſible proceeding of the proiect of our malignant enemies, is principally furthered by the ſeditious ſermons of the preaching Ieſuites and other Monkes, who, ſome yeares ſince, by an vnbridled licence and a manifeſt conſpiracie, contrary to the Edicts and their authoritie, did take vpon them to calumniate vs in their pulpits, and to make vs odious, preaching furie and ſedition, nouriſhing the people in hatred of vs, inſtructing them to haue vs in ex
                  •
               cration, and inſpiring in their mindes warres and murthers, do diſpoſe and prepare them vpon all occaſions to annoy vs. Hence it is that we continually feele ſo many violatings of the Edicts of peace, ſo many br
                  •
               aches which are made in vpon our ſafetie, ſo many outrages againſt our libertie. Notwithſtanding we may yet boldly affirme, that our patience might haue ouercome and as it were ſmothered the greateſt part of theſe euils, or at leaſt we might haue conceiued ſome good hope that in the end ſome remedies would haue bin prouided for vs by the bountie of the King and the wiſedom of his moſt faithfull Counſellers, if the Ieſuites were not exalted to the height of power whereunto they are come. For it doth euidently appeare, that by all ſorts of violent meanes they haue hitherto procured the rooting out of our Religion, and the ouerthrow of this Monarchie. Principally ſince their power hath growne to the proportion of their euill will, and that they ſee all obſtacles which heretofore were oppoſed againſt their hardy enterpriſe to be now broken downe or to yeeld vnderneath their power: what other expectation is reſerued for vs, but to feele the danger wherinto ſo long a time they haue proiected to plunge vs? The miſerable face of Chriſtendom at this day almoſt rent in peeces with warres and horrible confuſions, doth manifeſt ſufficiently to all the world what power their wicked and artificiall inductions haue to ſtirre vp a warre of Religion, almoſt vniuerſall. And who can preſume that France alone (which they haue made ſo often to feele ſo mournfull wounds by

their trecherous hands) being at this day in their power, and as it were vnder their abſolute gouernment, ſhould eſcape the common accident which they haue cauſed to fall vpon thoſe Eſtates where their credit and the diuerſitie of Religion haue giuen them pretence and matter to cauſe trouble. There is no man ſo vnacquainted with their deſſeines, who hath not heretofore foreſeene or foretold, that the miſerie and ruine of France drew neare when the counſels of Ieſuites ſhould preuaile. And now when on the one ſide we ſee them in ſuch high eſteeme, and on the other ſide France brought to the miſerie of ciuill warres: is any one ſo blinde that he confeſſeth it not, to be the worke of their hand? who would ſeek any other cauſe or beginning thereof? The feare of falling into theſe euils, hath cauſed vs to heare many aduertiſements from the wiſeſt and beſt affected French men, which ſo long time haue withſtood it with all their power. The force of the Parliament of Paris hath oft oppoſed its authoritie againſt their enterpriſes. And the remarkable documents which the iudgement thereof hath ſpread throughout France ſoone after the death of the late King, touching the danger and pernicious conſequences to the Eſtate, if they attained to greater credit, did guide the wiſedome of the Kings Mother to reſtraine their ouerboldnes in the Court and in the managing of affaires. And they could neuer obtaine their deſires during her regencie, and the authoritie which ſhe had in the gouernment of the Eſtate.
            But as all things fit their 
                  •
               urnes who ſeeke occaſion of What power the Ieſuits haue now in France. proceeding, hauing found in the gouernment following a more fauourable ſupport, as they are ready to vent the vſe of their miniſtery, helped by the opportunitie, and propt with that hand, they haue ſcaled that pinnacle of power, whereon we ſee them now mounted. Then we ſaw the boldeſt Ieſuite of the whole Societie brought into the Louure, and with a raſhneſſe beyond example plac
                  •
                himſelfe within the houſe of the Kings ſacred Maieſtie, that ſo at all houres and moments he might haue the gouerning

of him in his owne power. And euer ſince it hath appeared in the gouernment of the State, what power the Ieſuites haue gotten ouer the Kings affections. By two notable proofes ſoon after this Ieſuites introduction, it might eaſily be perceiued, that thenceforth nothing ſhould be impoſſible to thoſe of his Societie, whatſoeuer they would vndertake for themſelues or againſt vs. The neceſſitie of this diſcourſe requireth that we repreſent them.
            All France may well remember, that three dayes after this Ieſuite had got the Kings eare, they cauſed his Councell to cancell the Act of Parliament, by the which the opening of their Colledge in Paris was interdicted them, vntill ſuch time as they had publikly renounced their principles of the ruine of States and killing of Kings. And to ſhew that all oppoſition to their violence ſhould thenceforth be vaine, by an Order from the Councell (by them ſet vp in euery quarter of Paris in ſigne of triumph) they cauſed the Decrees of the Vniuerſitie (which had ſomewhat reſiſted them) to be annulled. With like facilitie, and at the ſame time, they obtained an Act in fauour of the Biſhops of Bearn the 25 of Iune 1617. for the reſtoring of all Eccleſiaſticall goods of that Country, which by a ſolemne eſtabliſhment decreed by the Soueraigne and Parliament, were ordained for the maintenance of our Paſtors, Colledge, Garriſons, Officers, and other charges of the country. 15 yeares together the Biſhops had followed this ſuite with all poſſible inſtance. The late King ſundry times ſollicited from Rome in their behalf, knowing wel the conſequences of ſuch a change, bound alſo by his oath to innouate nothing (beſide the libertie of Exerciſe giuen to the Roman Catholicks, with reſtitution of ſo much Eccleſiaſticall goods as was needfull for them, granted by Edict, and executed in the yeare 1599) had alwayes refuſed it them. The Queene mother of the King, for like conſiderations, and becauſe of the ſame oath taken by her Maieſtie now raigning, for the maintenance of the ancient eſtabliſhment (confirmed ouer and aboue by twelue ſeueral Patents

and Declarations obtained againſt the inſtance that the Biſhops made on the contrary) would not meddle with it. The proiect of our enemies could not be better aduanced then by a blow of this nature. For they knew that the execution of this Reſtitution would draw after it (as, alas, it is come to paſſe) the ſubuerſion of the countrey, and the vtter ruine of our Religion in the ſame, with hope that with the ſparkles they ſhould kindle there, they might ſet all France on fire. Wherefore they drew the King by his conſcience, and by vrging his oath, touching the rooting out of all Religion contrary to his, to make that Decree by prerogatiue: which for this cauſe (though giuen raſhly, without the aduice of the principall Officers of the Crowne and State in a buſineſſe of ſuch conſequence, and againſt the courſe of Law vpon the onely purſuite of the Biſhops, without hearing the Deputies of the country) would neuer be called in, notwithſtanding all the remonſtrances and ſupplications that could ſince be preſented, which haue not bene otherwiſe anſwered, then that the authoritie and conſcience of the King ſtood engaged in it. Thence we gathered a wofull experience of the Kings inclination in thoſe affaires that moſt concerne his State and our ſafetie. Seeing that this Ieſuite held all his affections bound with reſpects of Religion, and that deuotion vnto which his Maieſtie out of an inbred goodneſſe is naturally giuen, was as a ſpring vnto his conſcience, by the which he inclineth his whole will to what pleaſeth him beſt. Hee hath made himſelfe the Counſel of the Kings conſcience (to vſe his owne phraſe): and in this Counſell can he propound other Maximes then thoſe of Rome? that may be all reduced to this head of the ſubuerſion of this State and our ruine. He giues him for a law the determination of the Councell of Conſtance; That faith is not to be kept with hereticks. That whatſoeuer Edicts he hath made or ſworne, bind him not. That therefore he may, nay that he ought to br
                  •
               ake them. And the better to induce him, he reades him no other Lecture then the oath of his Coronation. Propounds

him no greater merit to be rewarded with Paradiſe, then the rooting out of Heretickes. Incites him to ſeeke that way a more glorious renowne, then euer S. Lewis got by warring with the Infidels. Theſe and ſuch like are the counſels of conſcience of this Ieſuite. By the which his Maieſtie ſetting aſide all other conſiderations of his gouernment, hath let himſelfe be caried away, and hath often ſaid, It is better to loſe his Eſtate then his ſoule. Taught (it ſeemes) to hold it for a Maxime, that there are occaſions of ſauing his ſoule with the loſſe of his kingdome. Now from the poſſeſſion of the Kings will, encloſed thus within the hand of the Ieſuites, they haue drawne to themſelues by a neceſſary conſequence, the whole gouernment of the State. Which they haue compaſſed the eaſier, by reaſon that all the ſage and old Counſellors and Officers that ſerued the late King, and France, in the eſtabliſhment and maintenance of the proſperitie and greatneſſe which it was raiſed to vnder his reigne, being now (as we ſee) put from all managing of affaires; they to whom the Kings abundant ſauour giues all authoritie in the gouernment, do willingly conſent, that the directing of the Counſell be committed to the Popes Sollicitors, Cardinals and Biſhops. And ſuch as yet remaine, or as are newly brought in, ſome nurtured with the leuen of old Spaniſh factions and affections, others won with the aduantageous liberalities of the new, or with Romiſh honours (whereof the Ieſuites are the chiefe brokers) concurre all together in one and the ſame conſent, touching the ſubuerſion of whatſoeuer the late King had eſtabliſhed, but chiefly for ſo much as concernes vs. And theſe allurements haue bene of ſuch efficacie, that he from whom the beſt expected an vnvariable affection to peace and good gouernment, in hope of a Church-dignitie, hath deuoted himſelfe to be an inſtrument of the firſt breach, through which, perſecution hath ruſhed in vpon vs. On the other ſide, the high and inferious Courts, and all Magiſtrates of the kingdome are filled with ſuch perſons as are wholy ſubiected to them, either by ſuperſtition, or by intereſt of

fortune. The people haue no other affections then ſuch as they ſuggeſt vnto them by their ſermons or by their priuate confeſſions.
            The power then of our enemies being ſuch, we haue How hardly we are dealt withal alſo, to our dammage, felt the effects of it by a contrary vſage to that that we found vnder the late King. For ſince they haue got this authoritie (we might very well ſay, ſince their reigne) there is no more fauour nor acceſſe at Court for thoſe of our Religion. Many to whom their fathers ſeruices and their owne had thitherto preſerued them the honour of ſome places neare the King, haue bene put by them. The greater part are conſtrained to rid themſelues of them, vnder this command, Change your Religion, or leaue your Office. It is told them that the King cannot with a good eye ſee the Huguenots about his perſon. In the Priuie Councel our greateſt oppoſites are our Iudges; and they whom we petition, are our ſworne enemies. We are ſhut out of Offices in all Courts higher or lower, againſt the freedome of the Statutes. If any one that is now in place turnes of our Religion, preſently the Attourneys Generall or their ſubſtitutes oppoſe his ſitting. The Courts conteſt with him, and repulſe him. And how many are there in the Court of Parliament at Paris and elſewhere, who are detained from comming to vs by the oppreſſion of this libertie? But when ſhould we haue reckoned vp all the kindes of iniuries done vnto vs? The ſeditious inſolencies dayly committed to hinder the free exerciſe of our Religion in thoſe places where we are tollerated. The attempts and enterpriſes againſt ſuch places as haue bin giuen vs in cuſtody for our ſecuritie. The ſecret practiſes to debauch the Gouernours of them, as it is newly confirmed in the Gouernours of Clermont, Ledeue and Argenton. The refuſall of prouiding for the reſtitution of thoſe places. The riots and outrages that thoſe of our Religion ſuffer in citie and country by the fury of the people, prouoked by their Preachers. The rauages and firing of our Churches and Church-yards. The inhumanities exerciſed in digging vp our dead, and hindring

their buriall. The violence offered ſick-folkes conſciences, euen in the agony of death, thereby to force them to renounce their Religion. The crueltie exerciſed on our poore and ſicke, who are caſt out of Hoſpitals. The vniuſt force practiſed in robbing vs of our children to bring them vp in the Roman Religion, againſt their fathers intent and laſt will. To be ſhort, all maner of wrongs and violences are done vs, againſt the Kings authoritie, and publik peace and tranquillitie.
            In all theſe miſchiefes we haue no other recourſe then to our complaints, which we continually direct to the Magiſtrates, either of the Prouinces or of the high Courts. But there, alas, in ſtead of remedies we finde poiſon. For not onely they ſend vs backe, and doe vs no right; but the iniuſtice wherewith they aggrauate the former iniury, augments their boldneſſe that did vs the wrong, encouraged by their impunitie, and by the law that they gather from the Iudges themſelues.
            Our laſt refuge is to the Kings iuſtice and Officers of State, whither (forced by the hard vſage we finde euery Our proceeding by complaint, which now is imputed vnto vs as a crime. where) we flie as to our ſanctuary: and there our enemies oppoſe our acceſſe with their vtmoſt violence. They perceiue that the Kings protection would defend vs againſt all their iniuries. They know that our courſe by complaints, which nature opens vnto euery one, would ſhroud vs vnder the couert of his iuſtice, where both our reſt and the publike tranquillitie ſhould be preſerued. And therefore we finde their conſpiracie to be the more malicious. For not onely they ſtop his Maieſties eare, and barre vs from all paſſage thereunto; but when we offer to approach it by our moſt humble petitions and requeſts, they lay for vs by a more then diuelliſh ſubriltie, the ſnare of their calumnie, to make vs fall into the blame of a pretended diſobedience. They turne our complaints into crimes: they terme vs ſeditious and rebels. This is the accuſation for the which they purſue vs criminally. This is the accuſation, for the which they now perſecute vs. We here call heauen and earth to

witneſſe betweene our enemies and vs, deſiring that the procedure of our complaints to his Maieſtie, which we wil here truly and fully lay open, being knowne to all, men may iudge of our innocencie, and of the calumnie of their accuſation; and finally of the vniuſt warre and perſecution which our aduerſaries vnder this pretext haue raiſed againſt vs.
            For the maintaining of the Edict of peace and reparation of the breaches thereof, the late King did eſtabliſh according to his equitie an order among vs, by the which we might from time to time with his permiſſion and grant aſſemble our ſelues by Deputies out of all the Prouinces, to tender him our complaints of all ſuch grieuances as might be done vs, and receiue from his bountie reaſonable anſwers, and ſuch as ſhould be neceſſary for the keeping of his Edicts. According to this order, feeling a more vrgent neceſſitie then euer, we addreſſed our ſelues vnto his Maieſtie by our Deputies generall in the yeare 1619, and it pleaſed his Maieſtie to grant vs, according to our moſt humble requeſt, a Briefe, by the which we were permitted to aſſemble ourſelues in the Citie of Loudun the 25 of September. The Aſſembly of Loudun, Where being met together out of all the Prouinces of the kingdome and Soueraigntie of Bearn, our bils of complaints being drawne, we preſented them in all humilitie to his Maieſtie, beſeeching him that by a fauourable anſwer to the principall articles and moſt important grieuances they might carry backe into all the Prouinces, by the teſtimonials of his good will towards our protection, ſome aſſurance to his ſubiects of the Religion, againſt ſo many threats and feares as doe apparently inuiron them. There would neuer be an end, if we ſhould here diſplay the ſeuerall heads of all thoſe complaints. We will onely touch ſome of them, to ſhew their importance, and the neceſſitie of obtaining ſpeedie iuſtice vpon them.
            We complaine that Leytoure a place of ſuretie hath bin wreſted out of our hands. That two of our Religion prouided of offices of Counſellours in the Court of Parliament

of Paris, could not obtaine their admiſſion in three whole yeares purſuite. That the exerciſe of our Religion being ba
               
                  〈…〉
               ſhed Clermont of Lodeue a place of ſuretie, vpon the reeſtabliſhing of the ſame ſued by vs, the execution of an order from the Kings Counſell was oppoſed vi &amp; armis. That our Churches haue bene burned or demoliſhed at Bourg in Breſſe, at Moulins in Bourbonnois, and at Lauall neare Guiſe. That at Beaux in Prouince Monſieur de Vere Captaine of the Caſtle, after many threats and outrages, to prohibite and hinder thoſe of the Religion from their exerciſe, did at laſt driue them out violently by force of armes the eight of Februarie 1620. That iuſtice could not be obtained for the exceſſiue outrages done to ſome of the Religion at Baugenci, and for ringing the Allarum bell againſt them; and that the Offenders that threw two men out of a garret, and ran one of them through with a ſword, haue bin heard as witneſſes to the informations made by the Lieutenant Generall in the iuriſdiction of Orleans; and that though the cauſe was referred to the Parliament of Paris, yet notwithſtanding the Attourney Generall in the ſame hath let the ſuite fall. That our Paſtors haue bin violently expelled the Cities of Bourges and la Chaſteigneraye. That diuers perſons profeſſing our Religion at Chaalons vpon Saonne, haue bin chaſed and baniſhed thence, as alſo out of the Dutchie of Barrois. That the places granted vs for the exerciſe of our Religion neare the Cities of Lyons, Dijon and Langres, were barred vs. That in thoſe places where the inhabitants haue actually enioyed the ſaid exerciſe euer ſince the yeares 1596. 1597. and therefore haue full liberty by the Edict, are there moleſted, as at la Chaſteigneraye, at la Chaſtre, at S. Cyprian, la Herle, Velus, Mauſſac, Langon, Bourg de Conde in Normandie, at Agiene in Viuarets, at S. Marcelin in Foreſt, at la Chaulme in Xaintogne by formall oppoſition of the Officers, at Florence Picuſque, at Montfort and Puget by the Conſuls, neare the Towne of Perigueux, at Montignac Charente by order from the Seneſchal of Angoumois vpon forfeiture of a thouſand franks.

That the education of children hath bin taken away from their fathers of our Religion, to inſtruct them in a contrary, as from the Maſter of Accompts at Paris, and by order of the Court of Parliament at Roane in the cauſe of one Couurechef. That many children of the Religion, haue bin ſtolen away by Monks. As at Ambrun the ſon of a citizen, at Millaud the ſonne of Monſieur Valette, at Leytoure a boy of ten yeares old, named Francis Aram, by the Ieſuite Regour the fourth of Ianuary 1620. That our graues haue bin inhumanely violated, or the burials hindred in diuers places, as at Aix in Prouince, at Gordes, at Mirabeau, at Ongle, at Xaintes, at S. Georgés of Oleron, and in many places of Guienne and other parts with crueltie &amp; barbariſme. That our poore ſicke haue bin caſt out of Hoſpitals, or their conſciences forced, as during the laſt contagion at Paris, in the Hoſpitall of Saint Lewes, where many were violented, and all acceſſe denied our Miniſters and Elders to comfort them. That the Parliaments, to the preiudice of the Courts eſtabliſhed, haue attributed to themſelues the knowledge of our cauſes, as the Parliament of Bourdeaux diuers times, and particularly in the buſineſſe of the inhabitants of Mas d'Agenois, who thereby haue ſuffered exceeding great vexations, whereof many of them are dead in priſon. But chiefly in criminall cauſes, as the Parliament of Thoulouſe, which hauing condemned Iohn de Naſſes Regiſter of Montauban to make honorable amends, would not giue way vnto an Order from the Councell for the referring of it to the Court of Caſtres. And againe, the Parliament of Bourdeaux in the cauſe of the inhabitants of Tartas, who in the ſurprize of the Caſtle hauing bin cruelly vſed, outraged and expelled, haue bin purſued and ill handled in the ſaid Parliament, which vpon the recrimination of the mutinous and ſeditious retained the knowledge of the cauſe to the preiudice of the Court of Nerac. In the Parliament of Aix, many of ours haue bin detained priſoners many yeares, though their cauſes were referred to the Court of Grenoble, and there retained according

to the Edict. We deſired moreouer that the alteration made in the Cities of Montault, Vareilles, Taraſſon, Montgaillard in the Countie of Foix, (where nothing ſhould be innouated, according to the Briefe of 1598.) might be repaired. That it would pleaſe the King to grant vs the Briefe for the cuſtodie of places of ſuretie, with the deliuery of the gouernment of the places in Dauphine. To call in the Decree for the reſtoring of the Eccleſiaſticall goods of Bearn. That the Towne of Priuas might be put againe into the hands of the inhabitants, and iuſtice done them of the riots, violences, and outrages committed againſt them. Beſides an infinite number of other grieuances publike and priuate, too long to rehearſe. In all the which we found our enemies ſtrength ſo great, that all iuſtice hath bin denied vs therein, and all the anſwer we could get was an abſolute command to breake vp our Aſſembly.
            But when as the importunitie of the miſchiefe and the neceſſitie of remedie forced vs to haue often recourſe vnto his Maieſtie. Then our Aduerſaries began to ſtile our ſuite and humble petition reiterated, by the name of rebellion, that ſo they might not onely take from vs all hope of iuſtice, but alſo make vs odious. And to open a doore for warre and perſecution, they obtained a commination of crime to be proclaimed againſt vs (as if it were a crime to complaine) threatning aloud our perſeuerance with the Kings ſword, and cauſing burſall Edicts to be extraordinarily confirmed in Courts of Parliament for preparatiues for warre againſt vs. The King neuertheleſſe out of his naturall goodnes and great inclination to iuſtice, Promiſes made at Loudun, with permiſsion to meet againe within ſix moneths in caſe of 
                     ••
                  performance. putting by the violence of our enemies, promiſed vs by the Prince his Highneſſe and Monſieur de Luynes now Conſtable, who gaue their word to the Lords Leſdiguieres and Chaſtillon for our better aſſurance, that within ſix moneths after the day of our ſeparation, the citie of Leytoure ſhould be reſtored vnto vs, and the Counſellers receiued into the Parliament of Paris. The Briefe for the cuſtodie of places of ſuretic, and the gouernment of thoſe of Dauphine

ſhould be deliuered vp vnto vs. And the ouerplus of our complaints fauourably anſwered, and the anſwers truly executed; and that within ſeuen moneths after the day of our ſeparation, the Deputies of Bearn ſhould haue audience vpon that that they had to ſhew vnto his Maieſtie. And in caſe theſe promiſes were not performed within the time, it ſhould be lawfull for vs to meete againe, to re-demand iuſtice of his Maieſtie vpon our grieuances. Now becauſe that vpon the condition of theſe promiſes, vpon the aſſurance with the which they were ſet forth vnto vs, and vpon the true intent promiſed in the performance of the ſame, dependeth the maine iuſtification of our procedure following, for the which we are vniuſtly declared faultie, and dealt withall by the rigor of armes; let all the world ſee here vpon what ground we build our ſinceritie and plaine meaning, and what right we had to reaſſemble our ſelues. For confirmation of the promiſe made vs to this purpoſe, we were ſhewed that it was the very firſt thing the King on his word promiſed to his ſubiects of the Religion, ſince he came to the Crowne. The Lord Conſtable, added that his comming in betweene, would be worth Briefes vnto vs, and happily more. The King himſelfe out of his owne mouth confirmed it ſince at Fontainebleau to the Deputies that certified the King of our ſeparation, in preſence of the Lord Duke de Leſdiguieres, who had aſſured vs as much before. Had it now bin lawfull for vs to deſire or imagine any better licence then the Kings ſacred word, the firſt that euer he gaue vs? Paper and inke can adde no weight nor authoritie to a Kings word. And certainly we ſhould haue held our ſelues vnworthy of our Kings fauour, and iniurious to his authoritie, if we had required greater aſſurance for this permiſſion then his owne word. Thus our Aſſembly broke vp the 13 of April, 1620. after an Act drawne among vs of our obedience, containing all conditions and promiſes aforeſaid, with order giuen to thoſe of Rochell for the calling of another Congregation, if need ſhould be, in ſuch a place as they ſhould thinke moſt conuenient. The

Deputies, after they had withdrawne themſelues, and giuen account in the Prouinces, were continued, or others ioyned to them, to meete together againe, in caſe of vnperformance of things granted according to the condition of the promiſes. This was done in all the Prouinces openly, to his Maieſties knowledge and the Lords of his Councell. It was not miſliked. The King made no declaration to the contrary. And yet this is moſt certain, that if there were any enterpriſe or attempt againſt the Kings authoritie, it was the nomination of the Deputies. But as that was acknowledged lawfull by permitting it, becauſe of the condition: ſo alſo our Deputies Generall ſuing the performance of things promiſed, did nor ſticke to adde alwayes this remonſtrance to the Lords of the Councell; Do vs iuſtice, and ſaue vs the labour of another meeting. The Prince his Highneſſe being diuers times preſent in Parliament to confirme the Kings command for the admiſſion of the Councellors, ſhewed vnto them the permiſſion we had to reaſſemble our ſelues, which they themſelues occaſioned by their refuſall.
            Now the prefixt time of ſixe moneths for the performance of promiſes expiring, the 13. of October, without The execution of the order of reſtitution in Bearn anticipated, and an alteration made in the country of the ſuretie and libertie in Religion. any effect, the King being gone into Guyenne in September, was ſollicited by our enemies to enioyne thoſe of Bearn to execute the order of Reſtitution, and to confirme it in the Parliament of Pau. The terme agreed vpon for their remonſtrances, which his Maieſtie promiſed to heare from the mouth of their Deputies, extended to the 13. of Nouember: which cauſed the Parliament of Pau. vpon the Kings command, to order that the Deputies ſhould make their remonſtrances to his Maieſtie, within the time agreed vpon (confirmed again by a letter dated the 21 of September from his Maieſtie to the ſaid Parliament) otherwiſe the time being expired, the order of Reſtitution ſhould be confirmed. His Maieſtie not contented with this Decree, before the remonſtrances of thoſe of the country were heard, was put on by our enemies to go himſelfe

thither. And although the Parliament by a ſecond Decree of confirmation, had preuented his Maieſties coming; yet through the induction of our enemies, he entred into the country with his armie.
            We would here willingly conceale the diſloyaltie of our enemies, and the cruelties there practiſed by their inducements, if their calumnious accuſations and the bitter anguiſh of our miſeries did not now conſtraine vs to open our mouthes for our owne iuſtification, and to call on vengeance before God and men. We will not ſpeake of the alteration made in the country, by the vniting of it to the Crowne of France, though it be euident it was not ſo much for any aduantage to France, as to make way for the alteration of our Religion. We will onely touch in few words ſo much as hath bin done directly for the ruine of the Goſpel. The King then being at Nauarenx, and purpoſing to keepe his promiſe with Monſieur de Sales, made firſt at Bourdeaux, and ſince confirmed in the country, that he would ſtill maintaine him in the gouernment of the Citie, in conſideration of his long ſeruices, and the ready obedience he ſhewed by all manner of ſubmiſſion vnto his Maieſtie: yet for all this, vrged by our enemies to take the gouernment from him and giue it to a Papiſt, but withheld by the religion of his promiſes, the Ieſuite that is ſtill at his elbow interpoſing his counſell of conſcience (or rather without conſcience) perſwaded his Maieſtie that it was lawfull for him to breake his promiſe, by an equiuocation, truly deſeruing the indignation of God and men. Your promiſe (ſaith he) Sir, is either of State or conſcience. Of conſcience (ſaith he) it cannot be, for it is contrary to the good of the Church. Seeing then it is of State, your Maieſtie ought to beleeue your Counſellours, who ſhew you, that for the good of your ſeruice, it is neceſſary that this place be no longer in the power of an Huguenot. Thus the King led by the Maiſter of his conſcience, who will be a ſuretie for him to God for all he ſhall do by his counſell, commanded Monſieur de Sales forthwith to reſigne his gouernment to Monſieur de Poyane
               
ſworne enemie to thoſe of our Religion. And then the Towne-gariſon being firſt remoued, and the inhabitant diſarmed, there were brought in foure hundred ſouldiers Papiſts vnder Monſieur de Poyanes command. This done, to take away all that might yet any wayes ſecure thoſe of the Religion, the ſix Captaines of the Parſans were caſſiered, and the Townes of Sauueterre, Orthes, Oleron and Nai filled with Papiſt-gariſons. The King being come the ſecond time to Pau, gaue the Biſhops the preſidencie in the Aſſembly of Eſtates there called, that ſo they might ouerſway the whole country. And God grant he trie not the ſame experiment of their perfidie that chaſed his father thence in his infancie; and that the neighbour-enemies practiſes finde not in them a ready way into France through that doore where our fidelitie hath alwayes beene a bulwarke. Now that no part of the ſecuritie and libertie of our Religion might remain vnviolated, the Papiſts were made maſters of all our Churches, notwithſtanding the condition of the reſtitution it ſelfe, bearing this reſeruation, that the Churches ſhould remaine ours till ſuch time as others were prouided vs. Theſe alterations made out of hate to our Religion, and to baniſh it the country, ſo augmented their boldneſſe who are continually taught and incited to miſchiefe vs, that whereas reſpect of the Kings preſence ſhould haue reſtrained them, yet their licentiouſneſſe ſo ouerflowed, that whereſoeuer they came, our Churches could not be ſaued from infinite rauages and ſcandals, ſo far, that euen within the Citie of Pau (the King himſelfe being there) after they had broken downe the pulpit and ſeates of the Church, they burned publikly the Bible and New Teſtament. The Miniſters were in diuers places outraged, and diuers perſons conſtrained againſt, their conſciences to kneele to Proceſſions. The ouerplus of the inſolences, violences and riots that this poore Country endured, was innumerable, and ſuch as the moſt ſauage enemies could exerciſe in the midſt of a conqueſt. Hereupon for triumph Arnoux makes a booke, titled, The King in Bearn;
               
where, not able to containe himſelfe for ioy to ſee his deſſeignes ſo forward, he plainly ſhewes how far he purpoſeth they ſhall entend, and what we muſt expect will be the ſequele of them. The King (by his reckoning) is not to ſurceaſe till he hath quite extinguiſhed the Religion that hee ſo much abhorreth: and highly extolling him for this commencement and purſuit of the deſſigne, aboue the late King his father; leaues to be vnderſtood that the death of that good King hauing bin haſtned for refuſing to do as much; his Maieſtie is to looke for more fauourable vſage at their hands ſo long as he will continue.
            Bearn brought to this pitifull eſtate, the King vpon his returne left part of his army in Guyenne, and ſcattered the reſt in Poictou, filling all our Churches with terror: And thenceforth no talk but of the ruine of all Huguenots. All the diſcourſe at Court is of the ſiege of Rochell. They ſay, it is not a three moneths matter; they ſtay but for weather. In the meane while all the promiſes made at Loudun being neglected, the time paſt, and nothing performed, (ſaue the deliuery of the Briefe for the keeping of places) notwithſtanding the earneſt purſuit of our Deputies Generall all this while; the congregation of Deputies nominated by the Prouinces (and bound to meet to preſent their requeſts to his Maieſtie vpon the vnperformance of promiſes) as called at Rochell againſt the 25 of Nouember. We will not omit that after the alterations made in Bearn, the Towne of Leytoure was reſtored to a Gentleman of the Religion; but let all in different perſons iudge, whether a Papiſt gariſon being left-there, and, againſt the order of the former gouernment of the Towne, a Lieutenant eſtabliſhed, that neuer had the approbation of the Synod of the Prouince, according to the intent of his Maieſties Briefe for the keeping of places of ſafetie, this be the ſquare dealing that was promiſed vs. Againe, we leaue it to be iudged, whether after that the ſafetie of a whole country hath bin wreſt
                  •
               d from vs, this maine promiſe executed after ſuch a faſhion, and all the reſt neglected and remaining vnperformed;

our right of complaining of ſo manifeſt an abuſe, and of theſe new and ſo intollerable grieuances, doth ceaſe, whether the neceſſitie of it be diminiſhed, &amp; whether the libertie of acceſſe ſhould be interdicted vs. Such then being the weight of the reaſons why we ſhould re-aſſemble our ſelues, and withall flie to the Kings iuſtice, hauing leaue ſo to doe; yet neuertheleſſe we were ſcarce all met in this place, when as a declaration came forth, that made vs malefactors, denouncing wrath and iudgement of cond
                  •
               mnation againſt the aſſemblers and aſſembled. But notwithſtanding foraſmuch as we finde that our grieuances are ſo vrgent; that our conſciences ſummon vs to fulfil the charge impoſed vpon vs by our Churches; and that they witneſſe vnto vs in ſinceritie that we proceed according vnto iuſtice. We endeuor to preſent vnto the King our moſt humble remonſtraces, to purge vs of the falſe accuſations and crimes laid vpon vs by our aduerſaries, who abuſe the authoritie of his name to breake his word with vs. To ſhew vnto his Maieſtie the vrgent neceſſitie of our iuſt complaints: To beſeech him in all humilitie that it would pleaſe him to deliuer our Churches from ſo many alarums and frights as do now enuiron them on all ſides. In a word, that he would ſhew himſelfe our Protector againſt ſo violent an oppoſition as is generally practiſed againſt vs ouer all his kingdome, to the preiudice of the authoritie of his Edicts, and againſt the open threats of our ruine, which by the example of the calamities of Bearn are made more fearfull. But we finde that our enemies had ſtopt his Maieſties eares againſt all our requeſts, which are reiected; neither will any thing be receiued or heard on our ſide. And at the ſame time we are criminally arraigned in Parliaments and other Courts of iuſtice. This Towne and all of vs are threatened with warre, as rebels and ſeditious perſons. Whereupon iudging by experience of what is paſt, and by our enemies method, which to our coſt we haue but too well learned and experimented, that this accuſation and theſe, threats were to authorize a refuſall and demall of iuſtice,

and to make vs loſe all hope of euer obtaining any thing hereafter in our moſt iuſt and neceſſary complaints; we inſiſt at ſeueral times on the iuſtification of our innocencie, and continue to beſeech his Maieſtie, and to lay downe our moſt humble petitions at his feete. But as all acceſſe is interdicted vs, and that to bring our proceedings into hatred euen with thoſe of our owne ſide, and to ſaue diuiſion in our Churches, our enemies cauſed it to be told our Deputies Generall and diuers others among vs, that the King, though reſolued to heare nothing from vs, would notwithſtanding deale fauourably with his ſubiects of the Religion, and do them iuſtice. That he was willing to heare our complaints by the Deputies Generall, and in the name of the Churches. To trie what would be the effect of theſe words, we ceaſſe all purſuite in our owne name, are ſilent, and put it ouer wholy to our Deputies Generall, to follow it in their owne name and in the name of the Churches. And certainly we may boldly adde, that if the eſtate of our calamities increaſing daily, and threatning worſe, had not augmented our apprehenſion and iuſt miſtruſt, ouercome with ſo many vexations, repulſes, threats, and with deſpaire of any ſucceſſe, we could deſire nothing more then to retire our ſelues; and it may be our Churches would haue pardoned vs. But at the ſame time the fraud of our enemies did further diſcouer it ſelfe, and the perſecution proiected againſt vs, breaking out in diuers places, hath manifeſted their deſſignes by ſo many perfidies and outrages, that being forced for iuſtification of our innocencie and lawfull defence againſt the warre they make vpon vs, here to lay open their proceedings before the eyes of all the world, we would be ſcrupulous for the honour of France to publiſh deeds ſo odious, if withall it were not knowne that the authors of them are France's greateſt enemies, and haue conſpired her ruine and ours.
            Firſt of all, vnder colour of theſe faire promiſes, that the the King would keepe his Edicts made in fauour of his ſubiects of the Religion, and would ſatisfie their complaints

of vnperformance of promiſes, my Lord Duke de Leſdiguieres is drawne to the Court, by perſwading him that his mediation would be a great furtherance vnto the buſineſſe, and all the Lords and perſons of greateſt note among vs are entertained with the ſame hopes. In the meane while Monſieur de Montmorenci is vp in armes againſt vs in Languedoc, and after many acts of hoſtilitie, ſets vpon Villeneufue de Berg a Towne of ours in Viuarez. And becauſe it was eaſie to be foreſeene that this violence would me
                  •
               te with oppoſition, Monſieur de Reaux Lieutenant of the Kings Guard is ſent from Court with apparent command to difarme all ſuch as he ſhould finde armed. Monſieur de Chaſtillon (whoſe prudence and affection to the Kings ſeruice and countries peace had hitherto withheld the peoples impatience, deſirous to repulſe the violence offered them) being informed of the ſaid Sieur de Reaux his charge by a yeoman of the Guard whom he had ſent vnto him, continued to ſtay our peoples commotion: and as he expects more particular newes from the ſaid Sieur de Reaux, and of Monſieur de Montmorencies obedience to the command he brought. Villeneufne de Berg hauing withſtood two ſcaladoes and diuers aſſaults at the gate, yeelding preſently at the Kings name to the ſaid Sieur de Reaux, and ſubmitting it ſelfe vnto his protection and keeping, Monſieur de Montmorenci comming in, eſtabliſheth there a gariſon, which at the ſame inſtant committeth all kind of riots and outrages. Hereupon our men being induced to aime themſelue for feare of the like frauds, and for the neceſſity of their owne defence. Monſieur de Reaux comming to Monſieur de Chaſtillon, and aſſuring him that Villeneufue de Berg ſhould be reſtored, and vnder hope that according to the articles agreed vpon betweene them, all things ſhould be reeſtabliſhed in peace, hauing obtained that he ſhould vnarme; whiles he was truly doing ſo, Monſieur de Montmorenci in ſtead of performing couenants, lodgeth fiue or ſixe companies in Villeneufue de Berg, and proclaimes with a drum Monſieur de Perant Gouernor thereof;

and more ouer hauing diſpatched diuers new commiſſions, dated the morow after Sieur de Reaux his ariuall there, he aſſiegeth Vals another place of ours in Viuarets, where euen the ſaid Sieur de Reaux himſelfe, whiles Monſieur de Chaſtillon reſted vpon his word, that Monſieur de Montmorenci ſhould performe couenants, aſſiſted in perſon, and was ſpectator of the battery. This little and weake place, without any defence but the inhabitants, hauing endured a hundred cannon ſhot, yeelding vpon honorable compoſition, directly contrary to the capitulation all manner of cruelties, violences and barbariſmes haue bin there practiſed vpon an infinite company of poore innocent perſons cruelly murthered or rauiſhed. And againe, contrary to the ſaid articles the like hath bin done at Valons a place neare vnto the other. Theſe frauds and breaches of counterfeit contracts, do manifeſt vnto the world that the Kings word and apparent command, haue bin vſed but as a ſnare for our plaine meaning, and vnder a ſecret approbation of all that Monſieur de Montmorenci ſhould doe to the contrary, to make vs loſe thoſe places.
            Moreouer at the ſame time Monſieur de Poyane hauing fortified himſelf in Bearn to beate out Monſieur de la Force, Monſieur de la Saladie is ſent from the King to Monſieur de la Force to command him to diſmiſſe thoſe troupes that he kept by him for his owne ſafetie and to maintain the Kings authoritie in his charge of Gouernour of the country againſt the violent enterpriſes of the ſaid Sieur de Poyane. But the ſaid Sieur de la Saladie in ſtead of carying backe Monſieur de la Forces anſwer to the King, as he ſeemed, went into Guyenne to Meſſieurs d'Eſpernon, de Vignoles, and diuers others to arme, ſo that in an inſtant all Guyenne was filled with troupes, beſides thoſe that were left there before.
            On the other ſide, at the ſame inſtant the troupes left in Poictou drew neare vnto this Citie and S. Iohn d'Angely. And by order from the Councell all Courts of Audit for Receits were remoued from all our places of ſafetie, where

they were eſtabliſhed; a palpable argument that though the citie of Rochell onely was threatned, yet all the reſt were aimed at, by a generall deſſigne of warre againſt vs ready to be put in execution; this remouall being to no other end, then to take from vs the meanes of helping our ſelues with thoſe profits in our owne defence when the perſecution ſhould come, which by conſequent they intended againſt vs.
            Now as by theſe new alterations of our peace by theſe menaces, by the open oppreſſion &amp; perſecution in ſo many places, we did foreſee well enough the ſtorme yt hung ouer our heads and ready to fall, knowing beſides yt our enemies puft vp with their ſucceſſe in the rauage &amp; deſolation of Bearn, did ſtay for nothing but a fit ſeaſon to continue our ruine by an open warre; which was too eaſie to be learnd by their open talke, vpon the returne from Bearn, of the ſiege of Rochell, of the meanes and facilitie of taking it. By the diſcourſe which the King was hourely entertained with of the ruine of Huguenots: by the calumnies laid vpon vs for a pretext; by the threats that followed; and by the preparations viſibly made for that purpoſe. Neuertheleſſe becauſe there was ſome ſpeech of the Kings good will towards his ſubiects of the Religion, and the authoritie of his Edicts, our Deputies Generall (to whoſe charge the whole purſuite was referred) preſented vnto his Maieſtie a bill of complaints, requeſting ſatisfaction for ſome of the moſt important grieuances, with a ſpeedier execution for the peace and ſafetie of our Churches.
            But after many inſtances and delayes, after diuers ſollicitations and ſupplications of all the chiefeſt among vs, euen of the Lord Duke de Leſdiguieres himſelf preſent at Court, our Deputies generall could neuer obtaine any anſwer. Onely Monſieur de Fabas one of them, and a Gentleman that came vnto vs from the Lord Duke de Leſdiguieres, hauing giuen vs to vnderſtand according to a writing of the ſaid Lord de Leſdiguieres vnder his owne hand. That for all amends after ſo many complaints, my Lord Duke de Leſdiguieres
               
did perſwade himſelfe (for the King, howſoeuer our Churches were giuen to hope that he would maintaine his Edicts, did not here ſo much as paſſe his word, neither by mouth, nor by any Officer of State) that if we would firſt ſeparate our ſelues, we ſhould obtaine the retraite of troupes from all places where we did miſtruſt them. That the gouernment of the places in Dauphine ſhould be ſearched and deliuered vs in ſix moneths if it could be found. That order ſhould be taken for the paiment of ſuch ſums of mony as haue bin promiſed them of Bearn in lieu of their Eccleſiaſticall reuenues. That Monſieur de la Force and his ſonnes ſhould ſtill hold their places. And moreouer, that he was promiſed aſſuredly that nothing ſhould be attempted during the time that ſhould be requiſite for the returne of our reſolutions. But as we were about them, we were informed by Monſieur de Chalas the other of our Deputies generall, that the next day after, contrary to the ſaid promiſes, our enemies had wrought the King to an abſolute and open reſolution of making warre againſt vs. That order was giuen for the leuying of an armie of one and forty thouſand foote and ſix thouſand horſe. And that the gouernment of Bearn was taken from Monſieur de la Force, and giuen to Monſieur the Marſhall de Themines, and the office of Captaine of the Guard, which his ſonne Monſieur be Marquis de la Force had, was giuen to the Marquis de Mauny, and that Monſieur de Manpauillan another of his ſonnes was commanded to leaue the Court.
            At the ſame time, as our enemies haſtened our perſecution by all kind of meanes, as, ſeditious ſermons, inſtructing of confeſſions d
                  •
               famatory libels, calumnies and impoſtures againſt our fidelitie, impreſſion of the Kingsha
                  •
               e to our Religion, and their declarations of warre publiſhed againſt vs, which haue wrought theſe effects. It happened in the citie of Tours the 19 of April laſt, that one Martin le Noir, (not long afore conuerted to our Religion, for the which he ſuffered many iniuries and reproches, ſo farre, that the people hauing made an effigie of ſtraw, and ſometimes calling

it by his name, ſometimes by the name of Martin Luther, did burne it publikly, and no iuſtice could euer be obtained for ſo outragious an inſolence) died: and as he was caried to his graue, the people made a head, and after they had abuſed his corpſe and thoſe that accompanied it, after they had committed all ſorts of indignities and in humanities in the digging vp of his graue, ſeeking to do worſe, ſtirred a more violent ſedition. So that hauing broken down and razed a houſe neare the Church-yard, they run to the Church, being halfe a mile thence, they fire it, they enter the Sextons houſe, and they pill and ranſacke it; and being increaſed to the number of a fearfull multitude, they continue three whole dayes together in firing and pulling downe our Church, without the Magiſtrates interpoſition, and comming too late he was not able to repreſſe ſo raging a violence. From thence the example of this ſedition paſſeth preſently vnto the Towne of Poictiers, where the people tranſported with like furie, haue razed to the very ground the walls of the Church-yard where they of the Religion bury their dead, broke and battered all the ſepulchers, and had committed the like violence vpon the Church, if the more carefull Magiſtrate had not ſtopped their courſe.
            Now the order of our enemies counſels and actions hitherto, and chiefly theſe tragicall and horrid vprores, the great preparatiues for warre, the vniuſt and rigorous dealing with Monſieur de la Force and his ſonnes, contrary to the late aſſurance, with the croupes ready vnder Monſieur d'Eſpernons command for the inuaſion of Bearn, witneſſed and ſhewed ſufficiently, that he houre of a generall perſecution was come, and that the deſſigne of our ruine ſo long a hatching now appeared. Wherefore our enemies, that their perfidies might play their part and performe their vtmoſt, promiſe that the King will ſee iuſtice done vpon the ſedition of Tours; and to take away all ſuſpition elſewhere, or to lull aſleepe the more confident ſort, they cauſe a declaration to be confirmed in all Courts of Parliament

the 27 of April, ſhewing that though the King would chaſtiſe ſome of his ſubiects of the Religion (ſuch as are termed rebels and ſeditious) yet he meant and promiſed to keepe his Edicts with the reſt as long as they ſhould remain in their obedience, and that he would maintaine and preſerue their libertie and ſafetie according to the contents of the Edicts. And finally they aſſure Monſieur de la Force, that if he would leaue Bearn, he ſhould no ſooner ſend Monſieur d'Eſpernon word of it, but he ſhould preſently withdraw himſelfe. Now we will ſhew what was the effect of theſe promiſes. We will begin with the laſt, which was firſt violated. After Monſieur de la Force had with drawne himſelfe, and had certified Monſieur d'Eſpernon of his diſarming and retrait by the Baron d'Arros, preſently Monſieur d'Eſpernon entred the country with his armie, and ſeiſed all townes and places where they of our Religion were moſt in number, filled them with ſtrong gariſons, razed the Caſtle of Montanay, and brought the people to ſuch a lamentable eſtate, that moſt of them, yea the chiefeſt haue bin forced to flie to quit their goods and country; diuers vnarmed and naked perſons were murthered, and the reſt remaine at this preſent reſtrained vnder a miſerable ſeruitude, ſuffering all ſorts of iniuries and cruelties. On the other ſide, the King ſetting forward for the execution of the menaces publiſhed againſt this Citie, after he had ſpred abroad his aſſurances, that he went not againſt his ſubiects of the Religion in generall, and made particular promiſes to the Gouernours of ſome of our places of ſafetie, that comming to them he would innouate nothing, paſſing by Tours, where the ſedition being renewed and growne ſtronger, and the Commiſſarie ſent to execute iuſtice, driuen out of the Towne, the priſoners fetcht out of priſon by violence, the houſes of thoſe of our Religion (who frighted with the firſt tumult had withdrawne themſelues) pild and ranſackt, onely the Kings reuerence violated, hath with much ado bin expiated by the execution of fiue poore beggerly rogues; (and that yet to entertaine their credulitie

whom our enemies would feed with hope that the keeping of Edicts ſhould be continued.) His Maieſtie came to Saumur, where Monſieur du Pleſſis relying vpon the expreſſe promiſes made him, that nothing ſhould be altered in the gouernment, and vpon the truth of the Declaration publiſhed three weekes before, hauing opened the gates of the Citie and Caſtle to the King, experimented to our great dammage the frauds and perfidies of our enemies, who induced the King to take away the gouernment from him, and to put a gariſon of foure hundred ſouldiers of his Gard in the Caſtle, and another in the Fauxbourg' of the greene Croſſe, and by this meanes to make vs loſe this place of ſafetie. With what horror and indignation can all France ſee the enemies of her peace and the Kings ſeruice abuſe thus perfidiouſly his name and word to commit theſe ſo deteſtable diſloyalties? It is but ten moneths ago that by his Maieſties expreſſe grant, the keeping of places of ſafetie was continued vnto vs for foure yeares. Of all others, the citie of Saumur was one of the moſt important for our ſafetie. It had bin in our cuſtody euer ſince the late King being King of Nauarre, requeſted by Henrie the third, came accompanied with thoſe of our Religion to deliuer him from the captiuitie and tyrannie of the leagne. That Towne was giuen him for his paſſage; and it remained thenceforth in our keeping, as a token of our good ſeruices and fidelitie to this Crowne. This place ſeated on the Loire was to ſerue vs, in the perſecutions and confuſions which the enemies of this Eſtate haue now ſtirred vp, for a retrait or commodious paſſage for ſo many poore diſtreſſed flocks, to ſaue themſelues from the future furie of fire and ſword. This Towne during the peace of theſe later yeares, was a nurſery of the Church, and was the ſeate of a flouriſhing Vniuerſitie. For theſe cauſes our enemies crueltie hath cauſed the King to begin this warre, in the which they carry him headlong againſt vs, by this terrible blow, ſo great, that to giue it vs with greater facilitie, all the precedent calumnies, all the pretexts of diſobedience and rebellion, all the particular

declarations againſt our Aſſembly and this Citie, all fraudulent declarations and promiſes made in fauour of ſuch as ſhould remaine in their obedience to the King haue bin ſet on foote. For can it be ſaid, that Monſieur du Pleſſis, whoſe long and faithfull ſeruices done to the late King and his Maieſtie now reigning, are knowne to all men, ſhould haue committed any act of diſobedience or rebellion? Nay rather did he not paſſe all meaſure of confidence in the diſloyaltie of our enemies, out of his reſpect to the Kings bare name? And hoping to auoide the ſtorme that hung apparently ouer our heads, did he not himſelfe publiſh the benefit of that deceitfull declaration; and to make the firſt triall of it, opened with ſuch confidence the gates of the Towne and Caſtle to the King? Wherefore the deſigne being thus vnmasked, our enemies were now pleaſed to manifeſt that it was intended againſt all in generall. For as ſoone as the King was at Saumur, newes came how that all the Proteſtants throughout all the principall cities of Normandie were diſarmed. Were they alſo traitors? Or haue they ſince the Declaration committed any act of rebellion or diſobedience? Beſides all this, whiles the King was yet at Saumur, Monſieur Arnaut comes to S. Iohn d'Angely on Saturday the 15 of this moneth, to command the Lord Duke de Rohan and Monſieur de Soubize to come to the King, who deſired their aduice for the taking vp of the preſent affaires. This was done to two ends: firſt, that vnder hope of iuſtice, the great ones and common people of our Religion might be withheld as they haue bin hitherto, whiles the preparatiues for warre againſt vs were euery where a haſtening. Secondly and chiefly, that there might be the leſſe ſuſpition of the Kings troupes led by Monſieur d' Auriac, who the very next day entring the ſuburbes of S. Iohn with three thouſand and fiue hundred men, aſſaulted the towne and gates, and would haue gone further, and taken it, if he had not found reſiſtance. Was this Towne alſo guiltie of treaſon? Could the Towne be guiltie, and not the Lords of it? And yet the King writes to Monſieur the

Duke de Rohan, as to his faithfull and affectionate ſeruant and his Lieutenant Gouernour in the Prouince of Poictou, which ſurely he would not do to a rebell and traitor. What other crime then hath this Towne committed, to be thus aſſailed and threatned with a ſiege, and forced to expect before her wals the Kings cannon and armie, which maketh towards it with all diligence and ſpeed? What crime alſo may the Towne of Iargeau (another place of ſafetie) haue committed, which was at the ſame time beſieged, other then our enemies oath to haue no mercie? then the hate of our Religion, whoſe ruine they haue conſpired?
            This is that which we lay downe before the eyes of all our Countrymen, and not of them alone, but of all Chriſtians, whom we here appeale vnto to iudge of our innocencie, and of the violent perſecution that we vniuſtly ſuffer. And though this true narration of our enemies proceedings againſt vs, and of ours towards our King, witneſſeth ſufficiently the calumnie of their accuſation, by the which they proclaime vs rebels; yet that we may not leaue any ſhadow that might alienate from vs the fauour of good mens equitable iudgements, their compaſſion of our miſeries, and their helpe in our iuſt and neceſſary defence: we can eaſily ſhew that as in vs there is neither appearance nor ſuſpition of the crime of rebellion which they lay vnto our charge. God forbid that any one ſhould thinke that the complaints which violence and oppreſſion doth extort from vs, do any way concerne our King, in whom we acknowledge &amp; reuerence with our hearts the image of God here on earth. But if laying vpon ſuch as abuſe his affections and conſcience, the iniuſtice of the which we complaine, we would name who, and tell what they are that accuſe vs, all France that groanes oppreſſed with the intollerable burthen of their tyrannie, would witneſſe for vs that we ſhould not ſpeake it by way of recrimination nor calumnie. But it ſhall ſuffice our innocencie, that we onely purge our ſelues of the accuſation. They accuſe vs of rebellion and diſobedience, and ſay that we kicke againſt the Kings authoritie.

Thankes be to God, the Religion that we profeſſe, and which we haue from time to time declared by a ſolemne confeſſion preſented to our Kings in witneſſe of the puritie of our ſeruice to God, and the ſinceritie of our obedience to them, hath long ſince acquitted vs of that imputation. We acknowledge no power on earth aboue our Kings. We ſweare not to any other. We deteſt all doctrine that teacheth, that either directly or indirectly we may be freed from the allegiance we haue ſworne vnto him. The holy profeſſion of theſe principles, hath euer been the ſquare and rule of all our fathers and our actions. When was it found that any of vs did bathe an execrable knife in the blood of our Kings? or ioyne ſwords with the great enemie to ſpill our countries intrailes? Or rather after ſo many wounds as France hath heretofore receiued from him, did not God vſe our fathers armes to raiſe her euen from the graue? And now that the ſame conſpiracie is newly reuiued, that they who haue ſworne mortall hatred to our Religion, and with the like furie haue vowed the ruine and deſtruction of all the Eſtates of Chriſtendome, and particularly of this Monarchie, gouerning at their pleaſure the Kings heart and wil by their ſuggeſtions to his conſcience, do induce him to hazard his State to vndo vs: we dare ſay, that time and experience will yet make him acknowledge that he hath not in all his kingdome a ſurer prop for his Crowne then our fidelitie. And certainly there can be nothing more plaine to all ſuch as looke vpon vs, then that the intereſt of our conſeruation is vnſeparably nailed to the peace and tranquillitie of this kingdome, and ſtrength of our Prince's authoritie. It is vndoubtedly true, that according to the humane meanes that God vſeth for the aduancement of his worke, the conſeruation and growth of our Religion in this country, do wholy depend on the libertie and ſafetie of the Edicts vnder which we liue; the maintaining of theſe Edicts, on the Kings abſolute authoritie. Witnes the happie reigne of Henrie the Great, whom as God had raiſed in abſolute power and authoritie higher then any other of the Kings

of Chriſtendome, ſo alſo vnder that proſperitie and greatneſſe of this Monarchie, our Churches were ſeene to flouriſh and replant themſelues, and the Goſpell to fructifie with ſo great ſucceſſe, that our enemies burſting for ſpight, neuer left till they had perfidiouſly depriued France of this ſo abſolute King. And though now for a pretext to inuade vs and ſtirre vp warre againſt our Religion, they haue accuſed vs of diſobedience; haue we done any thing elſe then complaine of the infringing of the Kings authoritie and Edicts, and demand redreſſe? And is there in this any ſhadow of rebellion againſt our Prince? We aſſembled our ſelues to demand iuſtice of him. Had we not need and right to do ſo? We haue already iuſtified it by the eſtate of our calamities, and the condition of the promiſes made vs. Haue we paſſed the limits of complaint? If being denied, we often returned, and diuers times endeuoured to lay downe our moſt humble petitions at our Kings feete; alas! who can diſtaſte it, or blame vs, when we behaue our ſelues towards our King. Gods image vpon earth, euen as God him ſelfe hath commanded vs? And becauſe many Deputies out of all the Prouinces, deſirous to carry backe from the Kings bountie and grace the effect of his good will towards vs, continued together; is it not a malignant and iniurious pettifoggerie, that to authorize a deniall of iuſtice, we ſhould be accuſed of ſhadowing the Kings authoritie? And for a ſpeciall preſident for the ſaid deniall, our enemies alledge that the Parliament after the preſentation of their bils, breakes vp, and ſtayeth not for an anſwer. But what proportion is there betweene vs and a Parliament? All our demands are particular. We demand not that ſuch rules be preſcribed vnto the State, or ſuch new lawes and orders, wherein certainly the Monarchicall authoritie would be diſparaged and quartered if the Parliament ſhould do more then aduice. But all that we demand, is, that our burnt Churches may be repaired; that the exerciſe of our Religion let and hindered vs, be re-eſtabliſhed; That Townes giuen vs by the King, and taken from vs by violence, be reſtored

vs; That officers may be admitted; That children taken by force out of their fathers armes be giuen them againe; and the like. Wherein ſhould the Kings authoritie be diſparaged, if he ſhould command out of hand that in euery one of theſe points iuſtice ſhould be done vs? If a priuate man to whom an iniury is done, may iuſtly complaine of it, and expect iuſtice from the King; why, if the if the iniury be done out of hate to a generalitie, may not a generalitie do the ſame? Can there be then any greater iniuſtice then to accuſe vs of rebellion and diſobedience, becauſe we complained and demanded iuſtice in this ſort? any greater crueltie, then to perſecute vs for this cauſe, and make warre vpon vs? But this is ſufficient to ſhew that the far fetcht pretexts of our enemies are but coloured ſubtilties, to execute the old deſigne of making warre vpon our Religion, and to plunge France in confuſion and trouble.
            Wherefore conſidering the iuſtice &amp; vrging need we had to haue recourſe by our complaints vnto the Kings protection: The right and permiſſion granted vs to reaſſemble our ſelues to that end in ſuch expreſſe and ſolemne termes: the failing and breach of promiſes, cauſed by the fraud of our enemies. Their violence in hindring our acceſſe vnto our King, and in cauſing all our ſuites to be reiected. The iniuſtice of their accuſation, and the ſlanderous crime of rebellion that they impoſe vpon vs. The diſloyaltie of their proceedings cōſidered, whiles they temporize vpon the refuſall of doing vs iuſtice, that they might take from vs three Townes at once in Viuarez, by the fraud of a treatie and breaking their publike faith. The inuaſion of the whole country of Bearn, contrary to ſuch an expreſſe ſtipulation, and ſo fully performed on our ſide: And after that to commit ſuch bloodie and inhumane acts of hoſtilitie. And laſtly, this infamous perfidie conſidered, that vnder the ſhadow of a Declaration authorized with the Kings ſacred name, &amp; confirmed in all the Courts of Parliament of France, promiſing libertie and ſafetie by maintaining the Edicts vnto all ſuch as ſhould remaine in their obedience; the Towne

of Saumur was ſeized on, where the gates were opened with ſo much obedience and reſpect vnder expreſſe and particular promiſes (beſides the publicke faith of the Declaration) that nothing ſhould be innouated. That by a like fraud and trecherie the Towne of Iargeau was at the ſame time inuaded, S. Iohn d'Angely aſſaulted, and now is in expectation of a ſiege. All Proteſtants diſarmed throughout all the chiefe Townes of Normandie, to prepare them, alas! for a more eaſie ſlaughter. If all theſe things, we ſay, be rightly conſidered together, we doubt not but it will eaſily appeare that we ſuffer this perſecution for iuſtice ſake, and by the hatred of our Religion, which a generall conſpiracie throughout all Europe now threatneth to deſtroy.
            Wherefore being forced for the libertie of our conſciences, and out of loue to our Country, to ſeeke in our ſelues, and towards the friends of our Religion and this State, a iuſt and neceſſary defence: we here yet againe preſent our ſelues with teares before our King, beſeeching him in all humilitie to conſider and beleeue, that the vowes and ardent deſires that we continually powre forth vnto God in our prayers, are for the proſperitie of his perſon and State. And that it would pleaſe him to remember that our fathers taught by their Religion the true obedience due vnto their King, haue neglected the ſefetie of their owne liues, to further and aduance the labours of Henrie the Great, in the recouery of his kingdome, perfidiouſly ſold and expoſed to the enemie, by the very ſame pretexts of hatred and perſecution againſt our Religion and vs. And that he would vnderſtand, that we following our fathers ſteps, as heires of their affections, haue neuer forſaken the dutie we were borne to, nor refuſed the true obedience and ready ſeruice that our Religion teacheth vs to yeeld him. And would to God, Sir, that your Maieſtie moued with the true intereſt of your greatneſſe, and out of your, naturall generoſitie, would for the ſetling of your Crowne and diginitie of your kingdome, turne your armes vpon the enemies of your State, and vſe our fidelitie in the defence of ſuch a cauſe.

We will boldly ſay for our ſelues, that in ſo glorious an emulation betweene your beſt ſubiects, we would cary away the priſe from them all. But we ſay now with teares of blood, and in the bitterneſſe of grones that teare our intrals, that the enemies of your Crowne and perſon, Sir, hauing induced you to draw your ſword againſt vs, and to bathe it in the blood of your loyalleſt ſubiects, will vndo both your Crowne and perſon altogether. They are your vndoubted enemies, that kindle your hatred againſt vs, to fire your Eſtate, and burie you in the ruines. Who hauing cruelly murthered the greateſt King of the world, your glorious father, becauſe he would not hate vs, and that his goodneſſe and iuſtice did protect vs as his truſtie ſubiects; do now induce your Maieſtie to hate and deſtroy vs, to ouerwhelme yourſelfe with the fall of this Monarchie. And if in this tempeſt which they haue already ſtirred vp, and which we feele comming downe vpon vs, we are conſtrained for our owne defence and preſeruation to betake our ſelues vnto naturall remedies, we here proteſt, Sir, before God, before you, and before all men, that our purpoſe is euermore to preſerue your authoritie and the reſpect of your obedience among vs; and that we will do our beſt endeuours to ſaue your ſacred perſon and kingdome from periſhing. God, who is the God of mercie and reuenge, and who according to the decrees of his counſell, ſometimes hath powred out his wrath with diuers examples of horror on the heads of Kings and nations riſen againſt him. Sometimes hath preſerued and reconciled to himſelfe the greateſt perſecutors of his Church, grant, according to our vowes, that your Maieſtie ſecure from all dangers, may acknowledge the Religion and fidelitie of thoſe perſons whom you now hate and know not.
            In the meane while we call here by our moſt humble ſupplications all Kings, Princes and Eſtates intereſſed in the innocencie of good and faithfull ſubiects oppreſſed, but eſpecially bound in conſcience before God to defend the cauſe of his truth. And requeſt them to prop with their

helpe and ſuccour the weake defence that of neceſſitie we oppoſe to the many and puiſſant forces of our enemies, who hauing choſen this time of purpoſe, now that they haue ſet on fire the greateſt part of the Eſtates from whence they imagine we might haue expected ſuccour, hope to oppreſſe vs with greater facilitie. But our chiefeſt truſt is in the arme of the Almightie, who ouerthroweth the deſſignes of nations, and blaſts the enterpriſes of people conſpiring againſt Iſrael. And ſince that for the glorie of his Name we are hated, and that to ouerthrow his truth our ruine is ſought after, we aſſure our ſelues that he will make vs feele the ſame deliuerance that our fathers haue proued by his ſuccour, which we call vpon from the bottome of our ſoules. Keepe not thou ſilence, O God; hold not thy peace, and be not ſtill, O God. For lo thine enemies make a tumult: and they that hate thee, haue lift vp the head.
            
            
               This is the Declaration of the Reformed Churches of France and Soueraigntie of Bearn by their Deputies aſſembled at Rochell. And in the name of all,
            
            
               
                  
                     Combort, Preſident.
                     
                     Banage, Aſſiſtant.
                     
                     Rodil, Secretarie.
                     
                     Riffaut, Secretarie.
                     
                  
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
               COurteous Reader, I pray thee amend theſe few faults of moment, pag. 3. lin. 17. we, reade do. lin. 28. action, r. affection. pag. 4. lin. 35. for, r. euen. pag. 7. li. 3. for, r. on. l. 32. thereof by, r. of the.
            
         
      
   

