
   
      
         
            The ioyful and royal entertainment of the ryght high and mightie Prince, Frauncis the Frenche Kings only brother by the grace of God Duke of Brabande, Aniow, Aláunson, &amp;c. Into his noble citie of Antwerpe. 1582. Translated out of Frenche by Arthur Golding, according to the copie printed by Plantine at Antwerpe, his highnesse printer.
            Joyeuse &amp; magnifique entrée de Monseigneur Francoys fils de France. English.
         
         
            
               1582
            
         
         Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01196
            STC 11310
            ESTC S112675
            99847921
            99847921
            12989
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01196)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12989)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 241:13)
         
         
            
               
                  The ioyful and royal entertainment of the ryght high and mightie Prince, Frauncis the Frenche Kings only brother by the grace of God Duke of Brabande, Aniow, Aláunson, &amp;c. Into his noble citie of Antwerpe. 1582. Translated out of Frenche by Arthur Golding, according to the copie printed by Plantine at Antwerpe, his highnesse printer.
                  Joyeuse &amp; magnifique entrée de Monseigneur Francoys fils de France. English.
                  Golding, Arthur, 1536-1606.
               
               [104] p.   
               
                  [By Thomas Dawson] for William Ponsonby, and are to be solde at his shoppe in Paules Churchyarde, at the signe of the Bishoppes head,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  [1582]
               
               
                  A translation of: La joyeuse &amp; magnifique entrée de Monseigneur Francoys fils de France.
                  Printer's name and publication date from colophon.
                  Includes an abstract of Plantin's privilege as Francis's printer--STC.
                  Running title reads: Mounsiers entertainment into Antwerpe.
                  Signatures: A-F G⁴.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Anjou, François, --  duc d', 1554-1584.
            
         
      
      
         
            2002-10
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2002-11
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2002-12
            Jennifer KietzmanSampled and proofread
         
            2002-12
            Jennifer KietzmanText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE Ioyful and royal entertainment of the ryght high and mightie Prince, Frauncis the Frenche Kings only brother, by the grace of God Duke of Brabande, Aniow, Aláunson, &amp;c. Into his noble Citie of Antwerpe.
            Translated out of Frenche by Arthur Golding, according to the Copie printed by Plantine at Antwerpe, his highnesse printer.
            
               ❧ Imprinted at London for William Ponsonby, and are to be solde at his shoppe in Paules Churchyarde, at the signe of the Bishoppes head.
         
         
            
            
            The Preface.
            
               STrange and wonderfull changes, haue by Gods iust iudgement happened heretofore vnto men, for their horrible and outragious crimes, euen in the greatest Empires, Monarchies, and common weales. And like as God, who knoweth how to pull downe the pryde euen of the greatest which abuse their authoritie, hath executed those iudgementes too manifest his iustice: so hath he also set them foorth for example to such as shoulde come after, into whose handes hee woulde put the scepters to rule folke withall: to the intent they might vnderstande, that as they report them selues to reigne by his grace, so in very deede they be his Lieuetenantes, &amp; Ministers of his iustice vpon earth, and therfore ought not to abuse that soueraigne and welneere diuine authoritie, wherewith he hath inhonored them.
            Also, (which thing hath not come to passe without Gods prouidence) there haue euer bin learned men of rare wittes, whiche haue

conueyed the remembrance of suche changes ouer to posteritie, to serue them for example: leauing in writing the causes of such chaunces, with their effectes and diuersities of falling out, to the ende that whensoeuer the like turnings come againe, men may bee in a readines to take the counsel which may be most for their welfare, or at leastwise wt may bee least hurtfull to their Countreys &amp; to their owne personnes. Thucydides the prince of Historiographers among the Athenians, affirmeth that his taking vpō him to write the ciuill wars among the Greekes, called the warres of Peloponnesus, whiche were full of diuers chaunges: was for the example of them that were to come after him, when they lighted into warres of the like kinde. And of a trueth, wise men whiche haue aduisedly examined the causes of the ciuill warres, as well which haue been in certaine ages past, as which haue bin in our age: haue founde many thinges resembling the saide warres of Peloponnesus, whither it be in the causes and the effectes, in difficulties of resolution, in differences of dispositions, in lettes of execution, in treasons, trecheries, surmizes, misreportes, or slaunders agaynste good men, and in such other like incidentes. The like also is to bee seene in other Historiographers:

For the more precisely &amp; faithfully they haue written, the more haue they done vs to vnderstande, that this saying of the Orator is true, That an Historie is the Scholemistresse of mans life. And soothly if euer any change in the world were notable &amp; worthie to bee imparted to posteritie▪ it is that which hath hapned in these Low coū
               treys. For whither ye haue an eye to the farre differing qualities of the two princes that entered 
                  〈◊〉
                into these warres: or to the inequalitie of their forces: to the diuersitie of the causes which mooued them to enter into armes on either part: to the diuersity of their successe, on the one part with secret enterprises sagely demeaned, and on the other part with wiles, deceites &amp; mischeeues practised: or to y• treaties of peace &amp; vnitie made, double made, and vnmade againe: to the diuersitie of partes whiche some selfe same persons haue followed almost at one time, or finally to the chāge of the prince that had bin followed with long, aduised, &amp; sage deliberation and to the incoūterings that haue bin made to the contrary, &amp; the things that are to ensue therof hereafter: these things (I say) being diligētly examined, will shew how there haue been feawe chaunges heretofore,

whiche haue better deserued to come to light, thāthat which we haue presētly before our eyes. Which thing maketh vs to hope, that God will not suffer so goodly and rare an example to bee buried, but that hee will stirre vp some wise, learned, and eloquent man, meet to set it forth in writing, to commende it to posteritie. Howebeit forasmuch as it is our duetie to helpe him that shall enterprise so great, so high, and so difficulte a woorke: and one (as it were) of most principall and speciall poyntes, fallen out in the inuesting of the Duchie of Brabande in the person of the Lorde Frauncis, onelye brother of the Frenche King, Duke of Aniow: and in his entering into the right renowmed citie of Antwerpe: I thought it my duetie to write downe the same truely now while the remembraunce thereof is yet freshe: as well to giue knowledge thereof to strāge nations, as to s
                  •
               rue his turne wt notes of remembrance, wt shall impart to posteritie the whole and vniuersall change happened in this countrey. By the way, I woulde haue all men to vnderstande, that although we haue no cause to repentevs of the receiuing of the saide Prince, chiefely for that it

hath pleased him to like well of it: yet notwithstanding, the said citie of Antwerpe had not any more then sixe dayes respit, to prepare for the entertaynement of so great a prince: to the intent that all men may perceyue, after what sort the people were affectioned, which in so short time vndertook so great a matter: and howe great the sumptuousnesse of his entertainement was like to haue bin, if the time might haue bin answerable to the good will and earnest desire of all the inhabitantes of the noble and riche citie of Antwerpe.
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶ The departing of the Mounsire the Duke of Aniow out of England, and the receiuing of him into Zeland.
            
               WHē the Queene of Englād and Mounsire the Duke of Aniowe vnderstoode by report made to her Maiestie and his highnes by Mounsire de Pruneaux, (who had bin sent ouer a litle before from the Duke to the Prince of Orenge, and had prosecuted the treatie the former yeres as his ordiniarie Ambassador,) what good will &amp; great longing he had found in the prince of Orenge, who was come into the Ile of Walckeren with a great number of Gentlemen, and with the deputies of the States &amp; of the chiefest and best Cities of the Lowe Countrey, to receiue his highnes and to do him most humble seruice: And when they had also heard the Ambassage of y• Lords of Ohain and Iunius, sent from the Lordes of the State to the Duke, to shewe vnto him the exceeding great desire whiche all the people had to see his highnes, for the present ratifiyng of the former couenants y• had passed betwixt thē: for the accōplishing wherof it was needfull that he shoulde passe ouer with all speede:

wherby the same thing was cōfirmed whiche had bin declared oft afore by ye Lord of Mount Saint Aldegond, ordinarie Ambassador to her Maiestie and his highnes: Upon the intelligence of these things, it was resolued by her Maiestie and his highnes, that the Mounsire shoulde depart. Wherevpon the Queene calling the Lord Haward, commāded him (for the Erle of Lincolne the high Admirall of England was thē sicke,) to take vpon him ye charge of the Admiralship, and to goe to Rochester, &amp; there to chooze vessels meete for the transporting of the Mounsire and his traine, and to furnish them with men of warre, Marriners, and all maner of necessaries as well of warre as of vittels. Which thing was done with such diligence and speede, that the ships being readie with all thinges in lesse then eyght dayes, passed out of the riuer of Rochester and the Thames, and were conueyed to the Downes nere to the town of Sandwich, where y• Moū
               sire was to take shipping. And forasmuchas ye Mounsire came into Englande accompanied but with a fewe princes and Lordes, and they also had left their traine in France, &amp; some of the same Lords were sent backe againe afterward by his commandement &amp; for his seruice.

The Qneene determined to giue him a companie &amp; traine meet for his greatnes, taking his iourney about so great and noble exployt. And therefore shee commaunded the Erle of Leycester master of the Horses, the Lorde of Hunsdon gouernour of Barwicke, her Maiesties neare kinnesman, &amp; the L. Hawarde the Uiceadmirall, (of whom the first two were of her priuie Counsell, &amp; al three were Knightes of the order of the Garter,) to attende vpon him, and to assemble as great a number of Englishe Lordes and Gentlemen, as coulde bee gotten in so litle time, to honour him withall: Whereunto the saide Lordes obeyed verie willingly: and there went with them to accompany them, the Lord Willowghbie, the Lorde Windsore, the Lorde Sheffeelde, the Lorde Hawarde, and the Lord Awdley, second sonne to the late Duke of Norffolke: master Sydney, Nephewe to the forenamed Erle of Leycester, sir George Caree, and master Iohn and Robert Caree all three sonnes of the saide Lord of Hunsdon: master William Hawarde brother of the said Lorde Haward: sir Thomas Shorley, sir Iohn Parrat, sir William Russell, sir William Drurie, and sir George Bowser Knightes, and a great number of other

Gentlemen, so as the whole traine that attended vpon the said Erle, was to the number of a hundred Gentlemen, and of mo than three hundred Seruingmen. The Lord of Hunsdon had of Gentlemen and others together to the number of a hundred and fiftie: and the Lorde Hawarde had as many.
            The Queene determined to accompanie the Mounsire to the seas side: and yet neuerthelesse commaunded the said Lords to keepe their course, and to attende vpon his highnes to the said place, with all maner of solemnities, interteynments and feastings. Hee on the other side desired and besought her Maiestie, not to depart out of London, as well for that the iourney would be painefull vnto her, as for that he sawe the wether fayre and winde fauourable, and therefore was loth to loose any occasion of perfourming his voyage withal speede. But hee coulde not preuaile. Wherevpon her Maiestie tooke her iourney with her whole Court, the first day of Februarie, and lodged that night at Rochester. The next day, abiding stil at Rochester, her Maiestie shewed him all her great ships wt were in that place, into most whereof his highnesse and the Prince and Lordes of his trayne entered, not without

great admiration of the Frenche Lordes and Gentlemen, who confessed that of good right the Queene of Englande was reported to bee Ladie of the Seas. Also he behilde howe all those shippes were ready furnished and well appointed. And her Maiestie tolde him, that al those vessels and the furniture of them, shoulde doe him seruice whensoeuer he would imploy them: For the which he humbly thanked her Maiestie: and so after all the great ordinance had bin shot of, they returned for yt day againe to Rochester.
            The third day they went to Sittingboorne, where dining both together, the Queene was serued after the Englishe maner, by the greatest Ladies of her Court: and the Mounsire after the Frenche maner, by the Gentlemen of his traine, which Ladies and Gentlemē dined afterward togithers. Then his highnesse be sought her Maiestie againe, to goe no further, declaring vnto her that the fayre wether pas-, sed away. But notwithstanding his intreatance, the Queene wēt on still to Cauntorburie. At which place, after one dayes tarriance, when shee had openly feasted all the Frenche Nobilitie, eyther parte tooke their leaue of other, not without great greefe and shewe 
                  •
               f verie great amitie, specially betweene her

Maiestie and the Mounsire. Whiche thing was perceiued also in the Lordes and Gentlemen of both the nations, and likewise in the Ladies, to all whom it was like greefe to depart after they had been conuersant and had liued friendly and brotherlie together, by the space of three monethes, without any change or alteration of their good willes. But the honour which inforced his highnesse, asswaged his griefe, and made him to proceede on his iorney with the said Prince and Lords of both the nations.
            The sixt day of the same moneth, whereas hee was determined to haue taken shippe, hee was counseled to lodge that night at Sandwiche, because the winde was somewhat changed. Howebeit, some of the Englishe Gentlemen, namely master Killegrey, master Dier and others, to eschewe thronging at their imbarking, went to Douer, &amp; there taking shipp the same night lay a while at anker, and somewhat after midnight sailed away with certain other vessels.
            The seuenth day, in the morning about ix. of the cloke, his highnesse tooke the sea in three great ships of war. In y• greatest of thē named The Discouerer, sailed the Moūsire himselfe

with the Erle of Leycester, and the Lorde Hawarde the Uiceadmirall: In the seconde called the Sentinell, went the Prince Daulphin: and in the thirde went the countie of Lauall, and the Lord of Hunsdon. Nowe as his highnes was yet at anker, there came a poste from a Lord of Englande, who brought him worde that the States of the lowe Countreys were reuolted, and namely the citie of Antwerpe, and therefore he prayed him not to depart, vntill he had more certayne newes. Notwithstanding this, his highnes determined to depart, and so sayled away with fifteene shippes: and hee had so fayre a weather, (whiche continued euen vntill after his entering into Antwerpe, and his feasting &amp; solemne entertainement there): that the heauen, the windes, the sea, and the earth seemed all to fauour his voyage, &amp; to further y• gladnesse which the people shewed in receyuing him with so great goodwill.
            In the meane time, the Prince of Orange, seeing the time fit, departed from Middleborowgh where hee had taryed the Mounsires comming sixe weekes and more, and came to Flushing, to take order for althings that were requisite for the honourable and commodious

interteyning of so great a Prince. At y• which place, vnderstanding by the letters of the saide Lords Ambassadors &amp; others, that the Mounsire was departed from London and comd to Cauntorburie: and therefore thinking that it woulde not be long ere he arriued there: hee dispatched Mounsire Treslon his viceadmirall of Zelande with a little Pynnesse called the Chasse, to goe before to meete the Mounsire: commaunding him that as soone as hee had discouered his fleete, hee shoulde giue him a watch worde thereof by the shot of two Cannous. Mounsire Treslon hauing about noone tyde discouered the shippes that were parted from Douer, and thinking that they had been the great fleete: gaue his watchworde, whiche was the cause that a certaine vessel went forth to the sea to meete his highnesse. But anone after, perceiuing his errour, he returned to Flushing, where by and by the fleete of Douer arriued. Then Mounsieur Treslon going foorth, founde the Mounsire and the great fleete betweene Newporte and Dunkirke: where after salutation giuen and taken on eyther side, the Mounsire standing vpon the Hatches of his shippe, espied his owne Secre
               
                  •
               arie named Nephewe standing likewise

vpon the Hatches of the Chasse, to whom hee sent his shipbote, commaunding him to come a boord to him, which thing hee did, and there aduertised the Mounsire, that as concer
                  •
               ing the reuolting of the states, there was no suche matter, but that all thinges went very well, and that his Highnesse was wayted for with great longing. That day by reason the winde 
                  〈◊〉
                turned Northeast, they could goe no further, but were faine to cast anker ouer against a place called Eastende, where they passed that night, wayting for the tide the next morning. His shippes were perceiued by them of Flushing, where anone after midnight arriued the Lorde of S. Aldegond, who assured the prince Orenge, that the next morning the Mounsire would arriue there with the tide. Wherevpon the prince of Orenge and the prince of Es pynoy with a great number of Gentlemen tooke sea the next morning, but because the tyde was against them: and on the other part the Mounsire hauing a side winde with him was constrained to haste to the Lande: by meanes thereof the Prince being not able to come aboorde to him with his ship, was fayne to turne sayle back againe to Flushing, where the Prince Daulphin had taken lande alredy,

and sought euery where for the prince his brother. When they had embraced and saluted one another lyke brethren, the prince of Orendge perceiuing the Mounsire to approche very neere, tooke the water againe. But when he perceiued him to come downe into his boate to take land, he turned backe againe, and hyed him so fast that he tooke land before him, and there tarried his comming. As s
                  •
               ne as he was arryued, while hee was yet in his boate ready to come a land, the prince receiued him with great reuerence, and embracing his highnesse knee, because he sawe the weather was cold, sayd vnto him in fewe woordes, that he was very glad to see that happy day, which had been so long expected, wherein he had the honour to behold his highnesse, and to offer vnto him his most humble seruice, with goods and life and all that he had besides: hoping that by meanes of his highnes, that countrye hauing indured so great aduersitie, shoulde now be fully set at libertie. Whereunto the Mounsire answered very wisely and breefly, And when he had imbraced him with such honour as was dew in respect of his age and doings: he came a land, and was brought by the prince to the palace of the citie, howbeit not

without great difficultie, by reason of y• great preace of men of warre and other people pestring one another, the folke of that countrey pressing to see his highnes, and the Englishmen which as then were come downe thither in greate number, pressing to know the prince of Orēdge: In ye mean whyle y• trūpets &amp; 
                  〈◊〉
                sounded with such noyse, yt the ayre rang of it, and 
                  •
               ll the Ordinanceshot off, (as well of the Queenes ships as of the other ships whereof y• number was great which lay thē in ye rode,) with so greate roring and thundering, that they conu
                  •
               yed the newes of his highnesse happy 
                  •
               yuall in the Lowe countrie, to Caleis and to other places of Fraunce. They of Flushing shot twoo peales, with so great noyse by reason of the great number of y• peeces y• are in the towne, that al ye ground rang of it. The Mounsire found in that place all sortes of his Officers: for his housholde and his garde of Swisses and Frenchmen, departing from Caleis and Bolloin foure dayes afore, were come to Middlebrowgh. The Magistrate of the citie waited for him at the gates of ye citie, who told him by ye mouth of their Recorder y• they were very glad of his cōming &amp; thought thēselues happy to see him, in hope that by his guiding and gouernment, they should see their

country restored to trāquillitie, &amp; set vp again in hir former renowme.
            The states of Brabād speaking by ye mouth of Mounsire Uan Stralen Amptmā of Antwerp, after their welcōming of him declared with what mind y• noble &amp; good cities of Braband had expected him, beseeching him most humbly to honour the country of Braband wt his presence out of hand. Next them the deputies of the citie of Brusselles (besides the declaratiō which they made of their own goodwil, &amp; generally of all the peoples of that country) declared also particularly, with what greate good will &amp; affection his highnes had bin waited for in that city, the cheef seate of the lords of yt country: &amp; that after so many mischeefes which they had suffered for withstanding the tyrannie of the Spaniards, next vnto god they had not any hope but in the comming of his highnesse their prince and Lord.
            Afterward they of Antwerp were heard: who declared y• affectiō of ye people towardes his highnes, their lōg lōging for him, and the great desire wt they had to see their prince &amp; souerain. The colonels &amp; captains of y• towne spake afterwarde, and declared vnto him how carefully and diligently they had kept y•
               
citie, in hope to put it shortly into his handes, and reioycing likewise at his comming.
            Unto all these Orations his highnesse answered very sagely and breefly as vnto all the residew, to the well liking and coutentment of all that stood by.
            The prince of Orendge taryed a while with the Mounsire in the towne house of the citie: and then taking his leaue went to visit the princes and Lords of both the nations that came with him, to see how they fared, and to take order that they shoulde want nothing, so farre foorth as the abilitie of the towne of Flushing (whiche is none of the greatest) coulde extende, where suche prouision was made, that all were well lodged and serued, notwithstanding that aboue 
                  •
               iue hundred men of the only english Lordes were come a land that day. All that afternoone was spent in feasting, in making of Bonsires, in firewoorkes, in sounding of trumpets, and in all manner of tokens of toy, which all men vttered vniuersally for the comming of so greate a prince.
            Also the foure members of Flaunders, which came by the councell of the prince of Orendge, wayted to present themselues vnto

him at middlebrowgh.
            The Prince of Orendge perceyuing that the Monsyre was mynded to go next daye too middlebrowgh, told him that there were three wayes The one about by the castle of Ramekins to euter in at the great chanell of Middlebrowgh, by the bowght of the foreland. An other by the little chanell through the countrye: and that he had kept shippes in a readines too goe the outer way, and a greate sorte of boates to goe the inner waye, because his highnesse could not iourney eyther by coche or on horsebacke by reason of the winter: and there was but onely one causey whereby folk traueled ordinarily on foote. The Mounsire beholding the fitnesse of the time, (for in deede it was very fayre wether, and vnderstanding that ye way was not past a good french league in length, vndertooke to go it on foote: and so did all the rest of the princes lordes and gentlemen as well of the same countrie, as of Fraunce and England. A greate sorte of the Mounsires house whiche were lodged already at Middlebrough, came to meete him, specially his gard of Frenchmen and Swissers. A good way out of the towne, the magi
               
                  •
               rate of Middlebrough came too meete him,

as it were about a third part of the way: and there making an oration to him, tolde him of the great and long desire which all the people had of his comming, and that the people of Middlebrowgh for their owne parte thought themselues greatly honoured, in that hee had voutsafed to come to their 
                  •
               itie, offering all duetifulnes vnto him. His gard also met him in the same place, and then began y• Swis sers to march on in their order, stryking vppe their drums after their maner. Moreouer sixe companies of the citizens well armed and wel arayed, stood imbatteled without the towne: who kept their place til y• M
                  •
               ūsire was past, and then they followed after leizurely behind.
            The deputies of the states of the Erledome of Zeland, wayted his comming at the towne gate. Who hauing declared ye gladnes which they conce
                  •
               ed, reioyced at the happy successe which his highnes had had in making ye peace in Fraunce, and in rescowing the city of Cā
               braye by his armye and in his owne person, and in his passinge into England, which they knewe he had taken vpon him for none other cause, then for the furtherance of the affaires of those countries, &amp; finally for y• hauing put his person in danger of y• passage, he was now

happilie arriued in zeland: most humbly thanking his highnes, &amp; declaring what hope they had conceiued of his presence and therewithall offering right humbly what soeuer their duetie required.
            At the entery of the gate one brought him a courser of Naples: but he determined with himselfe, (seeing that the princes and Lordes had not their horses there) to go through with his iourney on foote, and so entered into the citie of Middlebrowgh in this order.
            First went the Magistrates of the citie wt their vnder officers and ministers of Justice. Next them the deputies of the states of Zelād. After them followed diuers Gentlemen of all the three nations, with the deputies of the cities of Braband, and of the foure members of Flaunders. Then marched the Swissers after their accustomed fashion: in whose traine were a great sort of noblemen and Gentlemē, of whom the most part were Englishmen of the retinew of the three Lords sent thither by the Queene. Behind them insewed as it were in one troope togither, the Prince Daulphin, the Earle of Leycester, ye prince of Espinoy, y• countie de Laual the lord of Hunsdon, y• lorde

Haward, and the rest of the Lordes. Then came the Mounsire himselfe, hauing on his left hand some what more than halfe a pace beneath him, the prince of Orendge, of whom he alwayes asked some question. After him followed his gard of Frenchmen, and after them the garde of the Prince of Orendge, and last of all the six ensignes yt stood in battel ray without the citie, and tenne others whiche had marshalled the streetes vnto the market place, where all the rest of the citizens were imbattelled. Throughout all the streetes from the gate to the Mounsires lodging, there were rayles: and at euery tenth pace on eyther side were burning cressets. And so his hignesse and all the nobilitie which accompanied him, passed on, maruelling to see so goodly a citie in so little an yle, and so neere to three other good townes, not distant one from another aboue one league. But most of all they woondered at the beautie of the marketsted, and of the common hall of the citie. His highnesse lodging was verie well and richly hanged &amp; furnished, considering the small respit that the inhabitants had: so as hee was very well and 
                  〈◊〉
                lodged, both he and al the princes, noblemen, and gentlemen of all nations

that attended vpon him. That euening was passed in feasting, in making of bonfires in the streetes, in artificiall fire woorkes vppon the towres and steeples, and in sounding of trumpets.
            The next morning, the twelue deputies of the foure members of Flaunders, speaking to his hignes by the mouth of Mounsire Tayard the Recorder of Gaunt, declared at large the great good wil of al the people of Flaunders cowards him, and that lyke as they had been of the first that had sent vnto him, so they hoped to be of the first that should yeeld al hum ble seruice and subiectiō vnto him. Wherunto his highnes answered very discreetly, as his custome was. He passed the rest of the time in playing at tennis, with the Prince of Orendge and afterwarde with the other Lordes.
            The thirteenth day he had a solemne feast made him in the Townehall, where his highnes commaunded the tables too bee prepared of purpose, that he might haue the company of the Prince Daulphin, the prince of Orendge, the Earle of Leycester, the Prince of Espinoy, the Countie de Lauall, the Lord of Hunsdon, and the Lord Haward. For the Lordes

of England were highly regarded and honored euery where, both in respect of her Maiestie which sent them, and also for the woorthines of their persons. The feast was excellently well furnished of all things, and specially of tapistrie worke and other deuices of sugar: insomuch that both the Frenchmen and Englimen confessed, that they had not beene woont to see suche maner of seruices in their countreys.
            The fourteenth day, the prince of Orendge would needes goe see the putting of the ships in a readines, which should cary the Mounsire and his traine, which were in number foure and fiftie: and therefore he would haue gone to the foreland of Middlebrowgh. Whereof the Mounsire hearing, woulde needes goe with him.
            On thursday the fisteenth of that moneth, his highnes went to see the town of Ermwyden which is about halfe a league from Middlebrowgh. And vnderstanding that the english lords were gone to see the Towne of Uere, (called by straungers Camfer by reason of the passage that was sometime in the towne of Camp which is now drowned) he also tooke boate and went thither, where all the cōpany

was very well receiued by the inhabitantes, notwithstanding that they were taken vnprouided.
            The sixteenth day, his highnes was determined to haue taken ship: but there arose so great a storme, that the marriners counselled him to forbeare the sea for that day: by reason whereof his imbarking was deferred till the next morrow, at which time his highnes wi
                  •
               h al his traine sailed away. He himself was caried in a ship peynted all ouer with his owne colours, beset with a number of flagges and pensills of the armes of Aniow. The residue had theyr accustomed flagges so greatly feared of the Spaniardes, belaied with the coloures of the prince of Orendge. This fleete came y• daye against Beerlande in the yle of South Beueland, where they cast ancre &amp; spent that night there.
            The next day being arriued luckely at Li
               
                  •
               oo, after manye shot of ordinance from the Fort and from the shippes of warre which accompanied his hyghnesse, they did cast ancre againe. He himselfe went a land, and lay that night in the captains lodging, longing for the morning. This Forte of Lis
                  •
               oo is builded a three leagues beneath Antwer
                  •
                vpō the

poynt of a dike or causey in the parish of Lisloo. The place is so commodious, that with a Musket a man may easily shoot from the one banke of the riuer Skeld to the other: and by reason that the streame of the riuer and the tide of the Sea which passeth that way twice a day, doe make it crooked, that place beeing occupied by the enimie, might greatly hinder and anoy the sayling thereof. And therefore the citizens of Antwerp following the aduice and platforme layd foorth by the prince of Orendge, bestowed great cost in fortifying that place, which hath a great Tower with greate bulwarkes, rampires and ditches, and is so well strenthened and flanked to the purpose, and hath the water so at commaundement, that as nowe it is not too bee woone by anye force.
            The next day being munday the nienteenth day of February, his highnes departed thēce, to make his entrie into the renow
                  •
               ed citie of Antwerp.
         
         
            
            
               ❧ The royall entertainement of the right high and mightye Prince, Frauncis the French Kings only brother, by the grace of God Duke of Braband, Aniow, Alaunson, Berry &amp;c. into the citie of Antwerp.
            
            
               IN all greate and stately showes and assemblies, they that are the authours and setters foorth of them, indeuour too beautifie &amp; commend as much as they can, the things which they offer to the sight of those whom they intende to honour, &amp; of those which resort thither from strange places, to delight themselues with the beholding of them. The auncient Histortographers describe vnto vs manye greate tryumphes, and stately entertainementes of Emperours, Kings, and great Captaines, and they forget not to put into their writings, the great costlines and charges, and whatsoeuer else was set foorth to the showe, to content the

eyes of the beholders. And albeit that nother gold, siluer, precious stones, tapistrie, cloth of silke, fine linnen, diuersities of vessels, nor varietie of paintings were spared, but al such things haue inriched those showes: yet notwithstāding, there is not any thing y• hath yelded greater grace, beautie, and contētmēt to such assemblies than the multitude and brighnesse of armorie and of things perteyuing too martiall affayres, as engines, art
                  •
               lery, and showes of cities and castles beaten downe or taken by force from the enimies, And therfore in the Romane Empyre, (which excelled all the other not onely in conquests, martiall discipline, and politike order of gouernment, but also in sumptuousnes and royaltie) although infinite numbers of publike games and exercises were exhibited by them being the greatest Lordes of the world, who not only spared not any thing that was in their owne power, but also made the cities and countries which were any way bound vnto them, to sende vnto thē whatsoeuer rare &amp; exquisite thinges they could come by, to serue their turnes in the showes which they exhibited to the people: yet notwithstanding their Tryumphes haue so borne the bell aboue all the rest, that the woord

Tryumphing which commeth thereof, hath been applied to all high, great, and stately doings Not that in their other showes any thing was spared which might content the eyes 
                  〈◊〉
                of c
                  •
               etous folke, or satisfie the bludthirstie heartes of such as tock
                  •
                no pleasure but too behold the sheading of blood, yea and oftentimes of mans blood before their eyes. But in their triumphings nothing was so glorious as the armorie and personages of y• great Captaines that had been conquerers, whiche thing contented the b
                  •
               holders far more with out all comparison. And therefore when men intend to betoken the exceeding huge greatnesse of Rome, they terme it the Tryumphant Rome, which importeth as much as the riche, welthie, and victorious Rome, repl
                  •
               nished wt great numbers of noble Captaines, and valiant souldiers. And this terme is come of the great numbers of Truimphes, whiche were seene there in y• times of y• Scipios, Paules, Claudies, Metells, Pōpeis, Cesars &amp; others. True it is y• the other showes also were very glorious &amp; beautifull to behold, &amp; did (I wote not how) tickle the heartes of such as were fed with the beholding of their rich
                  •
               s and of ye infi nite nūbers of Liōs, Tigres, Pāthers, beares, and swordplaiers incountring one another to

to the death: but yet the beholding of a goodly companie of men armed in goodly armour, marching in good order (besides the contenting of the sight, which is farre better then too see riches) doth also wonderfully rauish mens mindes, and driue the beholder into an astonishment, setting him after a sort besides himselfe, and yet neuerthelesse filling him with a ioy and contentation surmounting all others. For as in the pleasures of the bodye, tho
                  •
               e seeme greates
                  •
                which doe moste alter the sences with their plea
                  •
               nes: so 
                  •
               ares it also with the delightes of the minde: which beecome so much the greater, when admiration beeing matched with them, doth also moreouer rauish the vnderstanding, and set a man as it were out of his wittes. And therefore when great personages (who can better iudge of matters thā plain simple folk can) do make discourse of things that are beautifull and desirable to behold: they speake of gold, siluer, precious stones, pictures, vessels, tablets, and diuers other exquisit Iewels: but yet they passe ouer those things and stand not vppon them, but when they come to talke of fayre armour, good horses and suche other thinges as belong to knighthoode and chiualry: then

they make such taryance vpon them, as they hold it for a thing fully agreed vppon and graunted that in beautie and glory nothing is comparable to a goodly armie. Onely this matter remaineth still in question vndecided: namely whether is the pleasanter sight, to see three or foure great battels of footemen well appointed in bright armour, wel flanked with small shot, and with their greate ordinance before them: or to see as many Squadrons of horsemen, or else twoo or three hundred ships furnished with their flagges and banners, and raunged in order as if they were ready to giue battel. But as for the rest of al goodly things, all men are fully agreed that they come nething neere to any of those three, and muche lesse doe them al three togither, if a man might behold them all at once, as it is reported that at one instant a man might haue seene the great armie of Xerxes both footmen and horse men raunged in battell ray: and also the two fleetes of the Persians and of the Greekes fighting vppon the Sea by Salamine, where by the wisdome and valiantnes of Themi
                  •
               ocles, the Greekes got that famous victorie of the Persians. In mine opinion that is the rause why the glad receyuing and ioyfull entering

of Frauncis Duke of Brabant into the Citie of Antwarpt, seemed so goodly and royall to all suche as sawe it: insomuche that there hath not been anye of them whiche hath not confessed that hee neuer saw the like. And yet were there very many present at it, as well of the same countrey as of straungers, whiche haue seene many stately and royall meetings, both in the same citie and in other cities of the Lowe countreys, and also in other great cities of other Countreys, as Paris, London, Roan, and Lions: and yet neuerthelesse the common voyce is, that this last hath passed all the rest. And truly the Citie had no more but sixe daies respit to prepare for it, as I sayde before: insomuch that they coulde not put to making any worke of silke, nor of golde aud siluer beaten or wouen, nor any embroderie: no nor in so shorttime make any meane apparell newe, nor any rare costlinesse of imagertes, pillers, tryumphall arches or other pageantes: but were constrayned to make a shifte with suche thinges as they had in a readinesse aforehande of their own store. In other entertemements, there haue in deede been seene great plentie of riches and royalties in attires of Kinges and Queenes, Princes and Princesses, Lords and

Ladies, Citizens and their wiues: but in th
                  •
                entertainement no such were seene: howebeit there was not any grossenesse, nor ought that might not well beseeme the neatnes and finenesse of that people, although it came nothing neere the sumptuousnesse of other intertainements. As touching triumphall arches, Chariots, Portratures and such other Showes: although there were many wittie inuentions &amp; agreeable to the time: yet haue men seene of thē in other places, which might match these. And as touching the number of their people, although it was great: yet it is well knowen that Paris exceedeth them in that behalfe. But the only reason of this contentment, commeth chiefly of the great nūber of people in armour, being not fewer then twentie thousande, in so good and so fayre armour: and of their order &amp; obedience, and of the small noyse which al that huge multitude made: insomuch that if it had not bin for the thundering of the Canons, and y• sounding of Trumpets, Clarions, Halboies, and other instrumentes, there was no more noyse than is among a Counsel of graue men. That thē was in mine opinion the onely very cause, wt was greatly furthered by their beholding of y• Mounsire of Braband, who represē
               the

statelines of old tyme, was clothed in a large Mantle, with ye Bonnet of his Dukedome vpon his head: so that among that great number of people, which were so well armed that three of the best cities in Christendome coulde not shewe so many fayre armours of their owne:) his highnesse resembled a precious stone or Iewel set in fine gold. And bycause that they which were the beholders therof, (for they could not be euery where, nor see euery thing) will be very glad to vnderstand of the things that so escaped them, and delight their mindes now with the remembrance of the things which they sawe before, as they delighted their eyes and mindes with the beholding of them that day: And strange nations too whom the fame of that so renowmed daies woorke is come, will take pleasure to vnderstande the same, whereof they could not be beholders: Therefore is this booke set foorth, for the satisfiyng of all men, and also to make it knowen to a number of men, (who partely for enmitie, partly for enuy, and partely for other surmizes and mistrustes will not beleeue it,) with what mind and affection the Prince of Orendge, and the other Lordes and noblemen of Braband, the good cities, and the small

Townes, and namely the most renowmed citie of Antwerp, haue receiued their new prince and soueraine Lord.
            The nienteenth day of the foresaid moneth in the forenoone, Mounsire y• Duke of Aniow departed from Lisloo and sayled towardes Antwery, hauing in his companie but twentie shippes: for the rest had gotten to Antwery afore, as well to put themselues in a readines as for other affaires. And he came about eight of the clocke, nigh to the new towne, and passing along by the townes side, left the forelād of Flaunders on his right hand and the towne on his left, and passed beyond all the towne &amp; the place where the Castle was. By the waye he heard all the Canons shot of from that part of the towne which faceth the riuer, &amp; from a great number of shippes which rode at ancre there: and he saw all the wharfes furnished with men of warre of the citie, well armed, who welcōmed him with their shot, and were answered againe by the shippes of warre that accompanied him, conducted by Mou
                  •
               sire de Tres
                  •
               on and the Uiceadmiralles and diuerse Captaines of Flushing. And so the firste foote that hee did set on lande in Brabande, was at a Uillage called Riell, whiche is at

the Canon wharfe of Antwerpt. The states of Braband, the Magistrats of the Citie, and diuers other States, comming in like order on horsebacke to the same place with their trumpets, Serieants and Heraults apparelled in cotes of ye armes of Lothyer, Braband, &amp; Limbourge: alighted there, and wayted on foote at the wharfe to receiue his highnesse, and to shewe him the good will and affection of the States and people. But the preace of people was so great, which resorted thither to see the prince, whom they looked for to be their duke: and againe there were so many impediments in his landing: that it was founde better for them by the aduice of the prince of Orenge, to returne backe and to tary for his highnesse vpon a Theatre which was prepared for him.
            This Theatre was set vp towards a corner of the Castle, and opened towardes the citie, so as his highnes being there, might at one time view both the Citie and the Castle, and behold the Counterskarfes: the deepe Ditches full of fayre water cleere to the verye bottome of the chanell, inclozed on eyther syde with heawen stone: the great and fayre buildinges, the goodly walles, beawtifull to looke on and very

thicke: and the broade Rampyres garnished with trees planted by hande, that it resembled a litle forest. The Mounsire was brought vp to this Theatre accompanied with y• prince Daulphin the only sonne of ye duke of Mountpanuser: the Erle of Leycester, and other English Lords representing the Queene of Englande: the Princes of Orendge and Espinoy, the countie de Lauall, the other english Lords, the Countie de Chateauroux, and a great sort of other barons, lords &amp; gentlemen, besids the chiefe Magistrates and Maisters of the companies of the Citie of Antwerpe.
            The Lordes of the State of Brabande waiting vpon the Theatre, came duetifully downe to go meete his highnesse: which thing hee perceiuing, did stand still. Then the prince of Orendge stepped foorth to take his place among the States, as one of the chiefe Lordes and Barons of the Duchie of Brabande. As soone as they had saluted his highnesse, and with great humblenesse kissed his hande, they mounted vp the steppes againe with him, after whom followed the Princes and Lordes of Fraunce and Englande, and when they were come vp aboue, they raunged

themselues on eyther side. There was set for the Mounsire a chayre couered with cloth of gold, wherin he sat him down. And vpō y• theatre there was likewise a trauers of cloth of Golde, &amp; al the Theatre was couered wt Tapistrie. On the front of the Theatre on the highest part thereof were the armes of the Marquesship of the holy Empyre: and a little beneath them on the ryghte hande, stoode the armes of Brabande with a wreath of fruites: and on the left hand stoode the armes of the Citie of Antwery. Also there were set vp twoo banners of 
                  •
               ilke azured with the armes of Aniow, and in one partition were written these verses.
            
               O Noble prince, whose footsteps faith and gentlensse preserue:
               Receiue thou heere the honour which thy vertue dooth deserue.
               That these Lowe Countries may at length take breath by meaues of thee,
               And thou a father to vs all in name and doings be.
            
            A
                  •
               er that euery man had taken his place and silence was made, the States of Braband began their Orarion by the mouth of Moun
               
                  •
               
               
de 
                  •
               esseiles doctour of both the lawes, Secretarie to the said estates: and one of their Counsell: the summe whereof was that the Barons noblemen and deputies of the chiefe cities, and of the other good Townes, representing the states of the Duchie and country of Braband, hauing now the good hap too see among them and to beholde face to face, the prince in whom next vnto God they had wholly set the hope of their deliuerance, and of the stablishing of their auncient rest and liberty: Did highly thanke the almightie Lord, which had shewed them that fauour: taking it for an assured warrant, that hee of his infinite goodnes and prouidence, had not forgottē nor forsakē their iust quarel: but had chosē his high nes too bee the defender of his people and the administrer of his iustice, too the ende that too Gods glorie, and to his owne honour, and renowme, the stormes of al troubles, and of al other thinges that anoyed their estate, might by the beames of his princely maiestie wisedome and prowesse bee chaced away, and the 
                  •
               ightues of their former prosperitie heretofore knowne to all nations, be made to spring vp and shine foorth againe: In respect wherof they gaue his highnes most humble thanks

for the singuler loue and good wil, which he of his owne onely motion and princely disposition, had voutsafed to continue towardes them vnto that instant, notwithstanding all ye crosse dealinges and practises that cunning heades coulde skill to put foorth to the hinderaunce of their affaires, forasmuch as they were not ignoraunt that for their calamities and miseries sakes, nothing coulde haue fallen in, whiche coulde haue made more to the fauour and furtherance of their case. Which thing they had esteemed &amp; would esteeme for euer, as a peerelesse president of his incomparable stayednesse and rare constancie: for the which, and for the great number of his other benefites and gracious dealings towardes them, they were and euer shoulde be bounde to acknowledge themselues indetted to his highnesse with all faithfull obedience, and were ready that day (by Gods grace) to submit themselues to him, as his humble vassalles and subectes. And although they doubted not but that his highnes did well vnderstande, and was fully satisfied, not onely of the generall causes which had vniuersally moued the states of the Prouinces of the Lowe Countreys together, to sewe to

him for succour, and to put thē selues into his hands: but also of the particular causes, which the states of that Duchie and countrie of Brabande had, to renownce their obedience to the King of Spaine: Yet notwithstanding to the intent to put his highnesse in remembraunce thereof, and to confirme that sacred resolution and high interprise of his, builded therevpon: and moreouer to yeeld some reason of all their doings to the Princes and Noblemen, and to the rest of that whole company, who for the honour of his highnesse were come thither of courtes
                  •
               e, to further the solemnity of his interteinment: to the intent yt at this his repaire thither, (which alwayes was called ioyfull,) they might vtter the more good will and gladnesse of heart: they would say no more but this, that as long as the Dukes of Brabande, (specially since the falling of that duchy into the hands of the Dukes of Burgoyne, and other the famous Auncetours of his highnes) gaue themselues to the gouerning of their subiects by them selues, thereby making it to appeare that they loued them and were not carelesse of them: they reaped so great commodities and notable seruices at their handes, that their names &amp; puissances became oftentimes

renowmed, yea, and sometimes dreadfull to
                  •
                the greatest Monarkes kings and commonweales of Christendome, whereof their wars and conquestes made proofe, howbeit that of those thinges as of matters familiarly known by the histories, it was not requisite to make discourse in that place and time, whiche were appointed to greater matters. But after that their Dukes and princes eyther by other alluremēts, or being wtheld in their other coūtry and Sentories, begā to leaue them for a time, and afterward at length to forget them, abandoning them to the pleasure and willes, and sometimes also to the lust and couetousnes of their vnder officers, wherof the king of Spain had lastly finished and perfected vp the work, leauing them disdainefully as husbandlesse &amp; fatherlesse vtterly destitute of his presence by the space of twentie yeres: It came to passe, that hauing altered &amp; chaunged almost all the whole state of the countrye, &amp; committed the offices to such as by the lawes and priuiledges of the country were not capable of them, or rather to such as would giue most for them, &amp; yet the vnsatiable couetousnes, malice, and exceeding tyrannical lordlines of the Spaniards being not contented therewith: in the ende,

when they had abused the whole commonweale after theyr owne lust, they grewe intoo so great pride, that they fell to 
                  •
               natching of y• priuate goods and substance of the inhabitāts, to liuing vpon the labour and sweate of the poore. yea and to rauishing y• chastitie of mens wyues and daughters: and (to fill vp the measure of al obhomination and crueltie) they fell to taking away the liues, and to sucking the blood of those which sought by all meanes to please them. Wherevppon in the end y• greate &amp; rightuous God (who hath a care of his seruants,) being offended thereat, made that people (who had aforetimes been of great valor) to cal to mind their former state &amp; liberte: &amp; gaue them both will and courage to maintaine y• same, in such sort as they had receiued from their forefathers. Which thing they sa
                  •
                could not be better done, than by the election which the sayd States of Braband, vnited wt the other prouinces, had made of his highnes person to be their prince and Lord, of purpose to bring all things backe to their former order hauing first sought (howbe it in vayne) for all remedies of their mischeefes &amp; of y• disorders of y• estate, frō the causes &amp; welsprings there of. Declaring y• the dukes in old time had bin

of great valour prowesse and powre, and had made many renowmed voyages and exployts of warre, &amp; that among others, they had chosē a duke of Aniow hertofore: who had bin equall with the rest in chiua
                  •
               rie and feates of armes, as their conquests and dominions witnessed. That they had had their princes gentle, milde, gracious, familiar, &amp; fauourable to their subiects: &amp; that his highnes had in y• beha
                  •
               fe alreadie giuen such proofes of his gētlenes, truth, &amp; 
                  〈◊〉
               , y• to their seeming, some ancient duke of Burgoyne was raysed vp againe vnto thē. Insomuch that in his onely h
                  •
               hnesse, they firmely beleued themselues to haue recouered whatsoeuer good renowne the dukes of Brabande, 
                  〈◊〉
                and Burgoine coulde haue left vnto them. Wherefore inasmuch as there remained no more, but to proceede to the accomplishmēt of y• chief work, which it had pleased the soueraingod to put into y• hāds of his highues, &amp; of the sayde states to performe y• day: they on their part were redy and resolute to do him the homage, fealtie, dewtie, and obedince, which loyall subiectes, &amp; good vassalls ought to doe to their rightfull princes: of which sort they trusted in God without doubting, that his 
                  •
               hnes was, and that he woulde promise by solemne othe vnto God so to continue.
            Herevnto his highnes answered in effect,

That intending not to holde the States with long talke, but onely to bee mindefull of the honour and good will which they had vowtsafed to yeeld vnto him, in that among so many other great Princes, they had chozen him cut to do deliuer them from the oppression and tyrānie of the Spantard, &amp; to rule thē according to their customes lawes &amp; priuiledges: he thā
               ked them hartily for it, assuring them that the iustnesse and equitie of their case, their honorable dealings in his behalfe, and the loue which they had▪ shewed him, had made him to resolue wt himself to take vpon him their protection, &amp; the restablishing of their auncient libertie, and to hazard therein whatsoeuer abilitie God had put into his handes, &amp; whatsoeuer els it should please the king his Lorde and brother, and the Queene of England of their fauour to bestow vpon him, yea euen to the sheading of his own blood and the spending of his life.
            This done, the foresaid Mounsieur 
                  〈◊〉
                told his highnes, howe it was y• custome there, to proclame openly before the people in yt duch tongue, y• points &amp; articles of the ioyfull interance, which y• dukes of Braband are bound to promise &amp; sweare at their admission. Hereupon, when as one hild the said articles translated into Frenche, ready to rehearse them poynte by poynte after the proclayming of them in

Duch: for asmuch as the day was farre spent, and communicatiō had bin had therof alredy, the Mounsire to win time thought it expediēt, by y• aduice of y• prince of Orēdg, y• they should be read but only in duch. Which thing was done by the sayd Mounsire Hassells, with a newe preface added too the articles, conteyning breefly the reasons and causes of y• dealing.
            After the reading of the sayde articles, it was demaunded of his highnesse whither hee lyked of them, and whither he were conte
                  •
               ted to be sworne to them, or whether it were his pleasure to be further satisfied of them. Wher vppon he sayde to the prince of Orendge, that forasmuch as he had seene the articles &amp; conferred of thē wi
                  •
               h him as they came by shippe out of Zeland, he held him selfe well satis
                  •
               ed with them, and was well contented to sweare vnto thē. Which speech of his was for
                  •
               hwith proclaymed, &amp; with further declaration, that for their better contentation his highnes was desirous to haue them al knowne, y• although the sayd articles were read but ouely in duch, yet woulde hee of his owne good minde, with aduized deliveration and certaine knowledge be sworne vnto them.
            
               Then did the said Monsieur Hesselles recite vnto the people in the duch tongue, the first othe which the Dukes of Brabande were of olde time accustomed and bound to take, for the obseruing of the saide Articles. Which doone, deliuering the booke wherein it was conteyned, to Messire Thierrey de Leiesfield Chauncellor of Braband, he read the same oth ageine openly in French, and the Mounsire spake it after him woord for woord.
            Then Mounsieur Hesselles taking the book ageine, told the people that y• Dukes of Braband made another second othe to the Barōs, Noblemen, Cities, Boroughes, and all y• Inhabitantes and subiectes of the countrey, too bee to them a good and iust Prince, and not to deale with them after his owne will, nor by way of rigor, but by law and iustice, and according too their priuiledges. Which othe was lyke wise rehearsed in the duch tong, &amp; the booke deliuered ageine to the saide Chaū
               cellor, and the Mounsire repeated the othe after him as he had doone the first.
            Then were the mantle and Bonnet of the Duchie b
                  •
               ought vnto him, whiche were of Crimzen veluet: the mantle was tra
                  •
               ed on the grounde, and both of them were furred

with powdred ermine turned vp very broade. The Prince of Orendge tolde his highnesse, that it behooued him too bee apparelled in those Robes. And when hee aske
                  •
                whither he must weare them intoo the citie, it was answeared yea: and that it was the solemne attyre of the Princes and Dukes of Braband of olde time. Wherevntoo when his highnesse had agreed: the Prince did first put vpon him the sayde mantle, and fastening the button thereof, sayd theis wordes: My Lord, you must keepe this button fast clozed, that no man may pull your mantle from you. And then he set the bonnet vppon his head, and sayde vnto him: Sir, I pray God you may well keepe this attyre, for nowe you may well assure your selfe that you be Duke of Braband.
            Then the saide Hesselles tolde him howe the custome required, that the States shoulde presentlie bee sworne too him ageine, to yeelde him fealtie. Wherevppon he vttered to the people the forme of the othe: and then the saide Chauncelor required it of the Barons, noblemen and deputies: and they pronounced it after him according too

the manner of the former othes, reuerently doing againe their homage, &amp; promising their fealtie and obedience.
            After the taking of the othes on both sides, as well by the Mounsire as by the States of Brabande, whyle his highnesse was yet still in his robes of estate, the Magistrates of Antwerpe commaunded their Recorder and Counseller Master Uanderwerck too come vp vpon the stage, to make him an offer of the Marqueshipp of the sacred Empyre, in the name of the citie of Antwerp. Which thing he did as followeth:
            Most gracious Lord and Prince, the Markgraue, Amptman, Boroughmaisters &amp; Skepons, the Treasurers, and Receiuers, y• cheefe Burgesses and Quartermaisters, the Wardens and auncientes of the Handycraftes; togither with the Colonelles, Wardens of 
                  •
               wyldes, and captaines of the Citie, were very glad when they vnderstood of your highnesses happy arriuall in the yle of Walckeren, as they haue caused too bee very largely and with all humilitie and reuerence shewed vnto you, by their deputies sent vntoo your highnesse for the same purpose.

But now, forasmuch as they see your highnesse not onely arriued in the countrie of Braband, but also receiued for Duke, and for their prince &amp; lord: their forecōceiued ioy is greatly increased and made fully perfect: trusting y• by this your comming, there will once ensue an end of the desolations, calamities and miseries, whereinto the Country hath bin brought by the vniust gouernment past, &amp; by the more vniust and wrongfull warre which the enemies hold yet still, to bring the whole country too destruction, with all manner of calamities and oppressions, which they are able to deuise. And therefore they giue your highnes most humble thankes, for the peynes and trauell which you haue voutsafed too take too come intoo this countrie: yeelding infinitely like thankes vntoo God, for that he hath giuen and sent them such a Prince, as not onelie is of abilitie and power, but also is willing, and well disposed to defend them from all enimies, and to rule and gouerne them with all good pollicie and iustice, according to the priuiledges lawes and customes of the coū
               trie. For although they be ioyned in league with the rest of the 
                  •
               tates of Braband, and generally with all the states of the low coūtries,

a
                  •
               d that they haue all entered intoo armes ioyntly togither: yet their so dooing hath not bin to exempt and withdraw themselues from the iust go
                  •
               ernment of their Lorde &amp; Prince: but onelie too mainteyne their auncient liberties, lawes, and priuiledges: that being gouerned according to the same, they might liue wt all duetifull obediēce, in good rest, peace, &amp; tranquillitie: The full accomplishment of which their desires, they thinke themselues too haue most happily obteined, 
                  •
               ith it hath pleased God of his infinite grace and mercie, to put into your highnesses heart, to take vpō you the souereintie of these lowe countries, the Dukedome of Braband, the citie of Antwerp, and the Marqueship of the sacred Empyre. For seeyng that God hath stirred them vp so great a Prince, the brother of a mighty king: they haue no doubt at all, but that your highnesse will (by Gods grace) soone finde meanes to deliuer these Countries, from the wretched wars wherin they haue bin so long plunged. The Markegraue, Amptman, Boroughmasters, Skepons, and other members of this citie, thinke it not expedient too repeate the causes of the warre, and the equi
               
                  •
               ie of the cace whereon they stande, forasmuchas

it hath diuers times heeretofore beene discussed largely ynough by the generall estates, and moreouer beene notably knowen too the worlde, and manie wayes allowed by your highnesse: Yet againe therefore, with all humble submission and reuerence, they thanke your highnesse that it hath pleased you too agree vnto them, and to promise the maintenaunce of their priuiledges, Lawes and customes, yea and of the articles comprised in the principall composition and in the ioyfull enteraunce intoo the Duchie of Brabande. Assuring your highnesse, that the people of the citie of Antwerp and of the Marqueship of the holye Empyre, shalbee and continew right humble subiectes too you, euen too the spending of their bodies and goods, &amp; whatsoeuer else they bee able to make, for the increasing of your honour and glorie.
            Heerevntoo his highnesse answered verye graciously, that hee thanked those noblemen for their good wil and affect
                  •
               n towards him, and that he ment to shew them by his doings, how desirous hee was too gouerne and rule the countrie with good policie &amp; iustice. And all this hee did at large and with very great grace.
            
               This doone, the sayde Uanderwercke turning himself to the people, cryed with a lowd voyce: that his highnesse as Duke of Brabande, Alaunson, Aniow, Berrey &amp;c. woulde bee sworne to the citie of Antwerp and the Marqueshippe of the sacred Empyre: desiring them to praye vntoo God, that by that so good and solemne deede, Gods name might bee sanctified, the safetie and prosperitie of the countrie procured, and the honor and glorie of the sayde Duke increased.
            Then was the othe which his high
               
                  •
               esse shoulde take, read openly too the people in the flemishe toong by the same Uanderwerck. Which beeing doone, Mounsieur the Amptman read the same othe too his highnesse in French, and his highnesse made and perfourmed the same in his handes, whiche the Borowghmayster of the Towne of Antwerpe hild vp, because the receiuing of the othe at his hande belonged vntoo him. Also the sayde Borowghmaister whose name was Syr Philip of Schoonhouen, kneeling downe before the Dukes highnesse, at the same tyme, gaue him a 
                  •
               ilte key, in token of subiection, and that

he might dispose of the citie as of his owne: which Key was deliuered againe by his highnesse too the Borowghmaister, too whom he saide very graciously, that he assured himself, that the saide Borowghmaister, and all the Burgesses and Inhabitāts of the citie, would keepe the citie faithfully for him, as they had doone vnto that instant.
            After the finishing and accomplishment of all the saide Solemnities, the Herawltes of Braband and Lotrick, (or in the vulgar Braband Wallon, Lothyer, that is too say Lotharing, or the true Lorraine,) cryed with a Iowd voyce, God saue the Duke of Braband. And then sownding the trumpets, they made a Largesse, casting a greate sorte of peeces of goold &amp; siluer among the standers by. Theis peeces were of two sortes: the one sort had on the one side the image of the Mounsire then Duke of Braband: the other sort had on the one side the armes of Aniow and Brabande, and about the verges was written Frauncis of Fraunce Duke of Braband. On the other side of thē all was a deuice of yc Sonne, with the Mounsires owne inscription, Cheriseth and Chaseth, which is the Mounsires ordinary poesie. Without the Towne were three

Regimentes of the Citizens, too the number of a three thousand men in order of battell, who made a goodlie shewe with their faire armours and their antesignes displayed. And they neuer went out of their place, vntill all the Ceremonies were dispatched, and that his highnesse was gone intoo the citie. Besides theis, there was an infinite number of people in the citie, whereof many were Straungers: who marueiled greatly at theis sightes, and especially the Frenchmen, who woondered to see their maister in that apparell, and spake diuersly of it, as is woont too bee doone in matters that are new and erst vnseene. But when they vnderstood howe it was the Dukely apparell, and that he wore it as a representation of antiquitie, the like whereof is worne yet still by the Electors of the sacred Empire in their greate ceremonies: they were astonished, and thought him to bee a Prince of more stately countenance and maiestie then afore: insomuch that it was sayd alowd amōg them, that seeing it was ye mantle of the Duchie, it should cost the liues of fiftie thousande Frenchmen, before it should bee plucked frō him againe.
            As soone as the Ceremonies were ended,

his highnes came downe from the Theatre, and mounted vpō a whyte courser of Naples, couered with a coperison of veluet richly imbroydered with gold. And so hee be gan too take his way towardes the right re nowmed and rich citie of Antwerp, and was conueyed along by the counterscarfe, vntoo the sumptuous and stately gate called Keizars gate or Sainct Georgis gate, whereat he entred into the good citie of Antwerpe,
            
               The order of his entering in was such as this.
               FIrst marched the 2. Serieant Maiors or Marshalles of the citie, accompanyed of two Pursiuāts with the armes of the citie, after whom followed the Trumpets with the armes of Braband.
               The first companie was of Almayne Merchantes commonly called Easterlinges, well mounted and well apparelled after the maner of Almayne.
               Next them followed the English merchāts in excellent good order: all appareled in Cassockes of blacke veluet, all of one fashion.
               Then came the Colonelles, &amp; captaines of

the citie: after whom followed a great number of Gentlemen, as well of the same countrie as of other nacions.
               Behind them went the bodie of the citie, that is to wit, the Wickmaysters, the Wardens, the auncient Magistrate, the masters of the Wardes, the Burrowghmasters, deputies, y• Wardens of the halles, the Usshers, the Secretaries, the Registers, the Receiuers and Treasurers, the Skepons, the Amptman, and the twoo Borowghmasters, all appareled in Clokes of black veluet, and all of one fashion.
               After them came y• Trūpets of ye States of Brabād, Lembourg, and Lothyer: &amp; after thē the states themselues in this order.
               First went the deputies of the vnder cities.
               The Deputies of the citie of Antwerp.
               The Deputies of Brusselles.
               Then succeeded the noblemen of Braband, as
               The Chauncellour of Brabande, and aboue him Lamorall Egmonde Brother too the Countie of Egmond, Baron of 
                     •
                  asebecke.
               A great number of Lords of the same countrie, of Fraunce, and of Englande well horsed and richly appar
                     •
                  ed.
               
                  The Swissers with their drommes and fiffes.
               The Mounsires owne housholde, among whom were intermingled certaine Lordes of England.
               Next this came the countie de Lauall, hauing on either hand an English Lord:
               The Prince of Espinoy, hauing on his right hand the Lord of Hunsoon, and on his left the Lord Haward:
               The Prince Doulphin, hauing on his right hand the Earle of Leycester, and on his lefte the Prince of Orendge:
               The Markgraue of Antwerp bare headed, bearing the mace of Iustice:
               The Lord Peterson Baron of Merode, taking vppon him that day as Marshall of Braband, and bearing the naked sword before the Dukes highnesse:
               Then came the Duke himselfe, mounted &amp; apparelled as yee haue heard afore.
               Next behinde the Duke, followed Coūtie Morice of Nassau sonne too the Prince of Orange, hauing on his right hand Coūtie Philip of Nassau, nephew too the said Prince, and sonne to countie Iohn of Nassaw: and on his left hand the Lord Shefeeld.
               
                  His Highnes was garded by the cōpanies of the Guyldes, that is to say, by the auncient brotherhoods of the Archers, Crossebowes, &amp; Harg webuzers in so goodly armour, as fayrer could not be found: The is went afore him and about him on a cluster without order, like flowredeluces vpon a royall robe.
               After them followed the gard of Frenchmē on a like heape, and after them the Prince of Orendges gard on foote.
               Then lastly in very good order came the twentie Antesignes of citizēs, which had stood in order of battell without the Towne.
               Ouer the gate where his highnes entered, there was a compartement of Doricke work, wherein was written as followeth.
            
         
         
            
            Too Frauncis the Sonne of Henrie the second, and onelie brother of Henrie the thirde King of Fraunce, called by Gods singuler prouidence to the souereigne Principalitie of the low Countries, and to the Dukedom of Braband, &amp; the Marqueship of the sacred Empyre, which God graunt to bee most happie and luckie vnto him, as to their inuested Prince whom they haue most earnestly wished for, &amp; who as now is happily come intoo this his most 
                  •
               er uisable citie, His moste harty Fauourers.
            The Senate and People of Antwerpe.
            
               THe Chariot of the Mayden of Antwerp could not goe out of the citie for wāt of roome too turne in: and therefore it tarried for his highnesse at the gate within the citie. This Chariot

was called the Chariot of Alyance: wherein sate a damosell apparelled in Satin red and white, which are y• colours of Antwerp: who had in her left hand a branch of Baytree, and on her heade a garlande of Laurell, in token of victorie against the tyrannies of the king of Spayne, &amp; in token of the deliuerance whiche the people hoped for by meanes of their new prince, through his gracious goodnes, faithfulnesse, victoriousnes, and defence: too whom with her other hand shee presented the keyes of the Towne, according to the verses written ouer her head, which shall bee set downe hereafter. Before her were the armes of the Marquiship of the holy Empyre. On her ryght hand was Religion apparelled like one of the Sibylles, holding in her one hande an open booke, named The Law and the Gospell: and in her other hande a swoorde: named Gods word: &amp; on her left hand was 
                  
                     •
                  ustice holding a balāce &amp; a sword in her hād, &amp; ouer the Balaunce was written, Yea and Nay. Before the Damosel sate Concord, clothed in white, yellow, and Orengetawny, bearing a target vppon her arme, wherein was paynted a crowned Scepter, with two little snakes,

and vnder them two dooues, all closed in with a garlande of Olif, betokening commendable gouernement with prouidence. Upon her head shee had a helmet, betokening Wisdome. In her hande shee caried a Launce, with a penon vpon it, on the one side whereof were the armes of Aniowe crowned with Olif, and on the other side a Lambe with a Woolfe, and a Lyon with an Oxe, to betoken the great peacefulnesse that is looked for vnder this Prince, as wel in Religion as in matters of State. At Concordes right hande satte Wisdome, and at her lefte hande Force. In the middes of the Chariot was a Pyller richly made of Corinthian worke, vpon the toppe whereof was a Harte hilde betweene two armed hands, which hart had two wings, betokening Vnion, Fayth and Force: and a Sworde wt two serpents writhing aboute it, &amp; holding their tayles to their eares; signifiyng discreete gouernement, and eares stopped against flatterers. At the foote of the pyller, was a compartement with the armes of Aniow and Brabande. On the brest of the Lyon of Brabande, were the armes of the Marquiship of the sacred Empyre, and of the Citie of Antwerpe, Upon the Armes was written

               Attonement. Upon the corners of the Chariot, were two armed Images, with morions on their heades, attyred in Orendge, white and blewe. The one of them was named Faithfulnesse, and the other Watchfulnes. In their hands they had eche of them a shield, wherein were paynted two swoordes a crosse, and two Dooues with a sheafe of arrowes, betokening Vnion. Uppon one of the Shieldes was written, Defence: and vpon the other, Offence. Ech of the images had a penon of azure silke: in one of the whiche there was a Pellicane killing herselfe for her yong birdes: and in the other a Hen a brooding her Chickens. Ouer the Maidens head were these verses.
            
               My rulers outrage wickednes, and furious tyrannie,
               Haue cast mee backe these keyes whiche I had giuen obediently,
               Upon conditions neuer kept O Prince of noble fame,
               With better boade of lucke and lotte receiue thou nowe the same.
               Thy godlinesse and proweffe haue of right deser
                     •
                   ued it.
               O treble happie Pri
                     •
                  ce to whō these Co
                     •
                  reys

do submit
               Their state! O happie Belgik, O most happie like to bee,
               Which vnderneath so great a prince mayst now liue safe and free.
            
            Sixe Gentlemen of the citie wayted at the gate with a Canapie of cloth of golde fryzed, which they afterwarde vnfoulded and carried it ouer the Dukes head, who went vnder it into the towne in the forementioned order.
            All the streets from the gate to his lodging, were set on eyther side with armed men vnder their ensignes with their 
                  •
               iffes and dro
                  •
               es. The officers caried gilt targets and swordes in their hands: and all the rest were armed after the best &amp; goodliest maner y• could be seen. His highnes proceeded forth on to the corner of the street called Gasthouse street, yt is to say, the Spittlehouse street, nere vnto S. Georges Churche, where was a showe made in the liknes of a table, very great &amp; high: which was made by one of the companies of their tragical &amp; comicall poets, commonly called among thē Rhetoricians. The company was called Care, or as some others terme it, the Follow sun, after y• name of a floure wt followeth y• sonne, &amp; the spee
                  •
               h of y• deuice was, Growing vp in vertue. The Showe or table had three compartimēts

or pertitions. The first was the first booke of Samuel y• fifteenth chap. where Samuel chargeth Saul wt his disobedience, &amp; hath a peece of his garmēt rent of by him, in token that the kingdome should be plucked frō Sauls house &amp; giuen to a better. Whereby was ment, y• the souerainetie of those low Coūtreys, was takē from the king of Spaine for his abhominable periuries, tyrannies, &amp; extorttons. In y• second compartiment was set forth, how Samuel cō
               manded I say ye father of Dauid to bring forth his sonnes: of whō God woulde make one the prince of his people, yt is to wit the yongest, wt was Dauid. In y• third was shewed how Dauid being anointed fought with Golias &amp; ouercame him. The title or superscription was a Pl
                  •
               igian worke, wherein were written these verses:
            
               As God bereaning Saul of Crown and Mace,
               Did dispossesse him of his kingdome quight,
               And after set vp Dauid in his place:
               so now likewise dispatching from our sight,
               The tyrants which oppressed vs by might,
               Hee giueth thee (O noble Duke) the Reyne
               Of these our Countreys, ouer vs to reigne.
            
            The frunt and krest being garnished with banners, skutchions of armes, Cressettes and

torches, carried the Dukes deuice Cherisheth and chaceth. And at the foote of the Table lay Discorde closed vp in a prison of Lattisworke, where shee was tormented with Helhoundes and Serpentes: and there were these verses.
            
               Alaunson whom God cherish ay,
               Doth chase all yre and wrath away.
            
            His highnesse passing forth still beyond the place called the Threewayleete, came to the streete named Hwyuetterstreete, that is to say, the Chaunlers streete, where was another stately Pageant with armes, torches, and cressets, made by another company of the Rhetoricians, called Peynters or Uiolers, who had for their deuice, Knit together by singlenesse. In this Pageant was paynted the neere aliaunce of Dauid and Ionathas: to betoken the firmenesse of the othe mutually made by his highnes and the States of Braband, and the Magistrates, Members, Colonelles, and Captaynes of the Citie of Antwerpe. In this table was written in a compartiment of Phrygien woorke.
            
               Like as the faithfull Ionathas did promise to defende
               
                  Good Dauid from the harmes whiche Saule against him did intend:
               So keep thou vs (O gracious Prince) which loue to liue in rest.
               Against the Tyrantes by whose force we haue bin sore opprest.
            
            Then went hee further to the ende of the streete where the Upholsters shops are, which part was full of burning torches &amp; barrels of burning pitch, and so came to the Merebridge. At the entering therof stood an Oliphant bearing a castle of stone with souldiers and artillerie. Before 
                  •
               e Olyphant were paynted the armes of 
                  〈◊〉
                Marquesdome and of the Citie: and 
                  〈◊〉
               , a speare with a banner of Taffata, with the armes of Aniow in a wreathe of Lawrel, and foure other bannerets of Crimosen taffata, pulled out, wherein were paynted the Handes of Antwerpe, with this posie: Cherisheth and Chaceth. And vpon his side of his belly were these verses.
            
               Whom light of Phebee heeretofore did leade,
               Inowe am drawen away,
               Her brothers beames to followe in her stead,
               A farre more certaine stay.
               I thinke my change right gainefull, sith I see,
               These Lower Countreys vnder him to bee.
            
            
               From the Merebridge hee went along the Mere streete, till he came to the warde, where were foure companies raūged in order of battell. Frō thence he passed to ye corner of Clare streete, where was a stage made by a company of Rhetoricians called ye 
               Olifbranche, who had for their posie, Behold grace. Upon this stage sate a Damsell named Antwerp, bearing in her bozom a pretie daughter called The knowledge of God: who hild a cofer wherein were priuiledges, lawes, fraunchizes &amp; truth: which were kept by the grace of God, &amp; by prouidēce, wisdome, faithfulnes, diligence, loyaltie, perseueraunce, vnitie, good heede, and order. And aloft was a compartiment of Phrygian woorke, wherein were these verses.
            
               O prince, our father, hope of helpe and stay:
               Dame grace, Gods impe, whō here thou seest to stande,
               From top to toe fayre clad in white aray,
               With branch of Olif in her heauenly hande:
               Hath willed thee to harber here within
               The stately walles of Ladie Antwerpe, and
               The loue of her with endlesse fame to win,
               By curing of her greefes with lawe and right,
               And 
                     •
                  cke by putting of her foes to flight.
            
            Somewhat lower towardes the middes,

was Neptune with his threetymed mace, riding ouer the waues vpon a Dolphin: and on his left hand were these verses:
            
               Gods heauenly grace, and soothfull skill, reuiuing Antwerpe newe,
               Through chare defence of faithfull leage haue kept her safe, as dewe
               To thee her Duke innobled both by father &amp; by brother,
               Both kinges of Fraunce, tone gone to Godlong since, still reigning toother.
               And therfore bend thou now thy wits, by rightfull force to wreake
               Her cruell foes, which did so ofte their leagues through falshod breake.
            
            He passed from Clarestreete through long newe streete vnto S. Catherins bridge, right ouer against Cros streete, where was a triumphall arche cunningly paynted and builded of white stone: whiche was garnished with his highnesses armes, and with torches and cresfettes, and with Musicke of Holboyes and Clarions, And on the top of it was written:
            
               To the happy cōming hitherof Fraūcis, only brother to Henrie the third, sonne to Henry the seconde,
               
               graundchilde to Frauncis the first, nowe inuested Duke of Brabande, the prince that hath most deepely deserued of this their Countrey, as a Father of the same.
            
            
               The Senate and people of Antwerp.
            
            Underneath this in another compartiment of Phrygian woorke, was written this:
            
               At length yet hinder not this Impe to bring thee wrooping world, againe to some redresse.
            
            In passing through the shorte Newstreete, and by the Marketsteed hee turned towardes the Coopers streete, in the street called Cheeslane to the great Market place, which was full of Torches of waxe, and of Barrelles of pitche vpon long poles vp to the highest windowes, which commonly are fiue stories high. In this Market place were inbattelled sixe en
                  •
               ignes with the ensigne of the youth whiche was vnder a green standarde, all in the best armor that was to bee seene in any place of the worlde. In the middes of the citizens was the great Giante the founder of the Citie of Antwerpe, whose Curace was azure, and his apparell tawnie white and gray: He boore banners of Azure with the armes of Aniow, and had these verses written before him:
            
               Feèrce Furi
                     •
                  , moody rage, vnbridled yre,
               Stoute Force, whot violence, cruell Tyra
                     •
                  y,
               
                  Nought booted me, ne furthered my desire:
               In keeping of my wished Soueraintie.
               The surest way for kings to gouerne by,
               Is meeldnes matched with a prudent minde,
               to vice seuere, to vertue meeke and kinde.
            
            
               For oft the calme and quiet gouernance, brings things to passe which violence coulde not win:
               Feercenes that cace will nought at all aduance:
               By mildnes shalt thou better holde folke in:
               Outrageous storming is not woorth a pin.
               By mine example therefore haue a care,
               All cruell dealings vtterly to spare.
            
            Behinde the Giant were written these verses:
            
               See you this Orped Giant here,
               so huge oslim and bone?
               Fame sayes that Antwerp was
               somtime a thrall to such a one.
            
            This Gyant was made by cunning to turne his face towardes the Duke as he passed by, &amp; to let fall the armes of Spaine which he hilde in his hand, and to put vp the armes of Aniow.
            Also there was a stage in the same Marketplace before the Towne house, ful of nimphes and vertues. But forasmuch as it serued chiefly

for the day of his taking of his othe in the citie of Antwerpe, which was the xxii. day of y• moneth: it shall bee spoken of more at large hereafter.
            His highnes departing out of ye market place, tooke his way towards the street called y• high street, &amp; when he came to the street called y• old cornmarket: there was a Whale carying neptune naked wt his threeforket mace in his hand, which betokened ye great cōmodities which y• citie of Antwerp receiued by the sea &amp; by ye riuer Schelt. Before this monster was another naked man, &amp; by him two other portratures, y• one of nauigation, &amp; the other of marchandize, wt a baoke of accounts, &amp; a purse, such as y• factors do cary with thē when they go to receiue money. Before the Neptune in a compartiment were written these verses.
            
               The lordship of y• seas to thee y• destenies beh
                     •
                  ght,
               In signe where of I Neptune yeelde this mace as thine of right.
               That Antwerp hauing rid allets by thee on sea and lande,
               May once inioy her wished fruite, &amp; safe from perill stande.
            
            His highnes kept on his way through y• high streete, to a place where sometime was y• gate called S. Iohns gate, which was beatē down the yeere before: in steed
                  •
                where of there was a

tryumphall arch of Ionian worke. This arch was wholly applied to his highnes own posie Cherisheth and Chaceth. On high ouer it was strained a couering after the maner of a round vault, wherein was painted the Sonne: &amp; vnder the Sonne was painted the sea with ships, and the earth clad with her verdure. Also there appeared a cloude on both sides, so as the light of the Sonne did shine forth and yeelde out his force to the earth. On the outside of the bowing of the Arch, were painted three goddesses: namely Flora, who hilde her flowers in her hand: Ceres, who had her corne: and Pomona, who hilde a horne stored with abundance of all things. Likwise the earth was clad wt greene trees, fruites, and feeldes replenished with all fruitfulnes, which thing came to passe by the heate and operation of the Sonne, which was betokened by this word Cherisheth. On the other side being the left hande, were drerie and barrē fields, the aire euery where lowri
                  •
               g and clowdie, and the trees and plantes withered, which thing was done by the three Helhounds Discord, Uiolence &amp; Tyranie, who fled away at y• sight of his highnes, according to y• signification of his other word, Chaceth. On another side stood the same po
                  •
               e againe, Cherisheth &amp; Chaceth, by another meane.
            
               At the right hande ouer the worde Cherisheth, was a great feelde well tilled, with a husbādmās house vpon it. The husbādmā himself being apparelled after ye frēch fashiō, was sowing of corne: &amp; another by him was spreading of Mucke. At the left hande was written the word Chaceth, on which side also was painted a French Captaine in armor, following his allyes, confiderates and souldiers: to doe men to vnderstande, that by the treaties, leages and agreementes, made with the dukes highnes, all tyrannie, violence, and discorde shoulde bee chased a way: &amp; that by ye beames of that sonne, the countrey should receiue al peace, prosperitie and abundance. Upon the forefrunt were these verses:
            
               Like as the rising of the Sonne doth chace the night away,
               And with his kindly heate the grounde well cherish ay:
               Euen so thy comming (noble Prince) doth Chace all tempests quight,
               And folke with cheerefull hope of freedome much delight.
            
            This Arch was impossed aloft with scutchions of the armes of Aniowe, compassed about with braunches of Olif, all vpon Azure. Also

there were diuers other s
                  •
               utchions, whose field was gewles bordered with argent, and a great nomber of burning torches. And the said Arche was furnished with diuers instruments of Musicke, &amp; the musicions themselues were clad in the colours of the citie.
            His highnesse passing vnder this triumphal arche, came to a place called the Owure, that is to say y• banke, where were two companies unbattelled, armed like all the residue. And so passing by the Ward there, he went to y• place that is right oueragainst the Mint: before the which there was a huge and monstruous seahorse, of twentie foote high, vpon whom sate a Nimph called Concord, bearing a shield wherin was painted a booke &amp; a rod, which was named The rule of truth. In her hand shee bare a flag, wherin was writtē 
               faithfull aliance. This monster of the sea was named Tyranny, and he had a brydle in his mouth with double Reynes of yron cheyned, called law &amp; reasō. Whereby the dukes highnes was done to vnderstād, that he as a true Perseus, was to deliuer yt countrey from all tyrannie, and afterward to gouerne it by iustice &amp; reason. Ouer against ye mintgate, where ye streete is narrowest, were two Obelisks or round Spires, &amp; between thē a triumpha
                  •
               
               
arch with his pillers of Corinthiā work, gilded &amp; inriched wt his relief vnder him. Upon y• forefront were his highnesses armes, and likewise on ye sides were other armes, wt banners, torches, and cressets. Under the armes of his highnes, were these verses following:
            
               Fulmighty is that cōmōweale, &amp; in a happy cace
               And blest with all commodities through Gods most heauenly grace,
               Where prince behaues himself as head, &amp; commons him obey
               As members, eyther carefully regarding others stay.
            
            From this tryumphall arch vnto the palace, yt is to wit, all along S. Mighels street, which is a mile in length, stoode on either side threescore &amp; ten pillers, with a space of 22. foote betweene piller &amp; piller. Euery piller was 12. foote high, &amp; vpon the pillers was a continual Tarras, &amp; on euery ech other piller was a cresset: &amp; on ye pillers between, were the armes of Braband, Aniow, &amp; Antwerpe, deuided according to ye spaces between the said pillers. And ye pillers were crested about wt garlāds of iuy.
            On the side of the street towards the palace, was a pageant with banners, torches and pyramids. Upon the vppermost part of one of y• sides wherof was a Crane, and vpon the other

side a Cocke. Giuing knowledge as well to y• heads as to ye members, yt watchfulnes is needful. A litle spaniel betokening faithfulnes, and a litle lambe betokening peace, were painted accompanied with ye Sibils, which represented wisedome, loue, faithfulnes, obedience, vertue, &amp; honor: without the which, no true peace can continue. And al these were guided by the light of the holy Ghost, which was resembled by a certaine brightnes that discouered ye chief instruments of discorde, namely Enuie &amp; Slaū
                  der, who peered out be hind, Enuy gnawing her own hart, &amp; Slaūder hauing double heart, double tongue, &amp; double face, howbeit with small effect. Foron y• two sides of this pageant, were two counterfets: on the one side, Hercules, &amp; on the other Dauid as it were in Copper, haning gotten the vpper hand of Golias, betokening strēgth &amp; stowtnes: and vnderneath was Concord, who hild discord in a cheine with collers about his necke: which discord offering wt his one hād an apple of gold, and wt his other hand threatning mē wt his force &amp; tyrānie, was yet neuer theles driuē into the dungeon of sorrow, where he is kept prisoner by cōcord, who kepeth the dore fast shut: betokening the same thing which ye coūtrey looketh for at his highnes hand, according to his posie, Cherisheth &amp; Chaseth.
            
            
               Upon the forefrunt of the compartiment made of Phrygian worke, were these verses:
            
               O let the earth the kissings sweete of peace and iustice see,
               And let her powre her riches foorth in all mens bozoms free:
               Let godlines and faithfulnes goe matched arme in arme,
               And let the bond of endlesse loue keepe all things knit from harme.
            
            Before the duke came at S. Mighels, where the palace was prepared for his highnes, y• day was so far spent, y• they were faine to light vp their cressets &amp; torches, which cast so great and cleare a light through the whole towne: that ye dukes highnes, &amp; the princes &amp; lords which accompanied him, &amp; likewise the souldiers with their glistering armors, were seen more clerely then at any time of the day. And as the multitude of people was verie great in the citie, so the neerer yt his highnes drewe to his palace, ye greater still did the number grow. So at lēgth the Duke of Braband and Aniow entred into his palace in the order aforementioned, hauing moreouer a two or three hundred as well of offenders as of banished folke, wt followed him 
                  •
               are headed and fettered, crauing mercie.
            
               The Herawlts did cast peeces of goolde and siluer abroade, as they had doone at the meetinges of all the Streetes as they passed through them.
            At the entrie of the palace was an Arche of twentie foote high, resting vpon three pillers of Phrigian worke. Upō the top wherof was a cōpartiment, wherein were the three Graces, that is to wit, Vertue, Glorie, and Honor, who offered vntoo his highnes an Olifbranch in token of peace, a Lawrelbowgh in token of victorie, &amp; a Crowne which was sent him frō heauen. And vnder the compartiment were written theis verses.
            
               O Prince whose merites passe his prayse, whose vertewz haue no peerz,
               Whose mynd surmounts his fortune far, whose thewz exceede his yeerz:
               Take gently heere this Olifbraunch, this Lawrelbowgh and crowne,
               Three presents giuen thee by three Nymphe, and sent from heauen downe.
            
            
               
                  The othe made by Frauncis Duke of Brabād to the members of the right renowmed citie of Antwerpe: and the othe made

by them againe vnto his highnes.
               
               THe Duke of Braband being come into his palace, caused a peale of a twentie or thirty thousand Hargwebuzers to be shot of, and then all the cōpanies, (sauing those which were to watch y• night,) began too withdrawe themselues apace. Which thing was doone in such order and with such silence, that in lesse than halfe an howre, al the citie was disarmed, after whiche manner they bad also armed themselues in lesse than an houre without any noyse in the morning. The Princes also &amp; y• Lordes withdrew thēselues to their lodgings, &amp; then was all the great ordinaunce of the towne shot of twice, as it had bin at the Dukes first comming to the citie, that all the towne seemed too bee on fire. Cressets were lighted and fires made for ioy through all the streetes and meetings, wayes, &amp; vppon y• steeples, in so great number and so continually, y• all the nyght resembled the day: insomuch y• when they that were without the Towne looked vp into the skye, they thought the element was all on fire. Theis bonfires cōtinued euery night vntil the next Thursday, on 
                     •
                  hich day his highnesse tooke his peculier

othe too the towne of Antwerp, in the dooing whereof, these solemnities insewing were obserued.
               The Amptman, Borowghmaisters, &amp; Skepons of Antwerp, came too the sayde Palace of S. Michael the next Thurseday being the 22. day of the same moneth. At which place they made humble su
                     •
                  e to his highnes, that as he had vowtsafed too giue his othe too the States of Braband and the Marquesdome of the sacred Empyre, and likewise too receiue theirs: so it might please him too giue his othe that day peculiarly to the citie of Antwerpe, and likewyse too take theirs, at the place of olde time accustomed. Where vnto when the Duke had assented, they tooke their way in the same order that had bin obserued at his entering into the towne, sauing that the Lorde Edwarde de clastro Ambassadour for Don Antonio King of Portingale, was that daye in the latter companie of the Princes and Lordes. And so they marched along the saide streete of Saint Michaell too the great marketsteede, where the sumptuous common house of the citie is. And bicause that on the day of his enteraunce in, it was not possible for him too

take a perfect view of all the showes, by reason that the night ouertooke them: they were presented vntoo his highnesse ageine, as well in the place before the mint, as in other places. Also there were two pageantes mo prepared, which were deuised both in one day. The one was Mount Parnasus whereon sate Apollo apparelled like the Sonne, and accō
                  panied with the nine Muses, playing vpon 
                     •
                  
                  uers kindes of Instrumentes, and with sweet voyce singing a certaine ditie together, writtē in commendation of his highnes. This Pageant was in the street called the high street, ouer against the street named Reyner streete. Right ouer against this Pageant, was another on the side of the streete called the flaxe market: Which was a mossie Rocke ouer growē with drie and withered trees, wherein appeared a caue verie hideous darke and drerye too behold, and in the same lay lurking the three Helhowndes, Discord, Violence, and Tiranny: who feeling Apollos beames, and hearing the sweetenesse and harmonie of the voyces and instrumentes, shroonke away and hidde themselues in the deepest of the Dungeon, &amp; afterward peered out ageine, to hearken whither that melodie and harmonie continued stil

or no: mynding to haue come foorth againe, &amp; to haue troubled the common weale, if ye same had ceassed.
               His highnesse passed on and with verie much adoo came to the great Market place, by reason of the infinite multitude of people, which could not be put asunder without great payne. As soone as hee was alighted from his horse, he went vp a scaffold which had bin set vp for the same purpose, in the middes of the Market place hard by the Towne howse, before whom went the Magistrate of the citie, and a greate number of Princes Lordes and Gentlemen. This Scaffold being great and large, of the heigth of fortie foote, was hanged with scarlet. Upon it was a cloth of estate, the backe whereof was cloth of gold frized, vnder the which was a chayre of the same. The day of his first comming thither, there had bin presented vnto him on the right side, Wisdome offering him a golden Scepter: on his lefte side, Iustice offering him the sworde of Iustice from aboue the Chayre: and behinde him Clemencie offering him the Cap of the Dukedome. Before the chayre as it were at the feete of it, were Obedience, Faithfulnes, Loue of God, and Reuerence. And by the chayres sides

there were with them, Concord, Sagenesse, vaeleantnesse, Good will, Truth, Pitifulnes, Perseuerance and Reason, of whom two on eyther side held eche of them a torch of virgin waxe, and they were all appareled like Nymphes. But on this day when his highnesse went vp too this stage, the Nymphes were away. And in steed of them, the chaire was garnished on both sides with pyllers. On the right side betweene the pillers was a Lyon holding a naked swoorde, to betoken the authoritie of the magistrate. Aboue the Lyon was an Eagle feeding her young, and turning her selfe towardes the shyning of the Sunne, as taking her force of the Prince. On the left side was an Oxe with a yoke on his necke, and aboue him a Hen brooding her chickens, and by her a cocke. The Oxe with his yoke signified obedience: and the cocke and the hen betokened the watchfulnes, care, &amp; 
                     〈◊〉
                   of the superior. The saide scaffold was garnished with bāners of azure beaten with the armes of Aniow, and with banners of gewles beaten with the armes of Antw
                     •
                  rpe, and with cressets and torches. And aboue among the armes were written these verses.
               
                  
                  At length thou art come, and ioyfull wee bee,
                  Thy presence long lookt for here present to see.
               
               And a little vnder, at the ryght hand vnder the armes of Braband, were these verses.
               
                  Of tryumphes though stately, kings boast but in vayne,
                  Vnlesse they by iustice doe vprightly reigne.
               
               And on the left hande vnder the armes of Antwerpe was written thus.
               
                  Nowght booteth law, Authoritie, or sage forecast of wit,
                  Unlesse to lawfull gouernment folke doe their force submit.
               
               And yet somewhat lower was written.
               
                  God, God is he the heartes of kinges which holdeth in his hande,
                  He, He it is that highest things doth make too fall or stande.
                  When he with gracious looke beholde
                        •
                      a people: they inioy
                  
                     A goodlie Ruler, vnder whom no troubles them anoy.
                  But if misliking make him frowne, then makes he them a pray
                  Too Tyrantes, vnder whom they tast of sorrow euery day.
               
               FRom this Scaffold, he might beholde before him an infinite number of people, readie too bee sworne vntoo him: and also three companies of banished and condemned men in fetters, and bareheaded, crauing mercie at his hande, which was graunted vnto them. Moreouer all the houses about the Market sted had Cressets burning on high before them. Nowe then, after that roome and silence was made, their Counseller and Recorder Uanderwerck propounded the matter as followeth.
               Right gracious Lord and Prince, y• Markgraue, the Amptman, the Boroughmaisters, the Skepons, the Treasurers, the Receiuers, the olde Deputies, the chiefe Burgesses, the Duartermaysters, the Wardens, the Auncientes of the Handicraftes, the Colo
                  
                     •
                  lles, the Wardens of the 
                     •
                  wyldes, &amp; the capteynes of the citie, your Highnesses most

humble and obedient subiectes, are exceeding glad to see that you whome they haue alreadie receyued for Duke of Brabande, and for their souereigne Lorde and Prince, are ready to make your othe vnto this Citie, and to receyue it at the hande of the Magistrates, Burgesses and Citizens thereof, in respect of the Citie it selfe, and of the Marquesdome of the sacred Empyre. Assuring them selues that your heighnesse wilbe vnto them a good, righteous, and lawfull Prince, to gouerne them according to their fraunchises, Lawes and Customes: And promising mutually on their behalfe to your heighnesse, to bee good, loyal and faythful subiects vnto you, to spend all their goodes yea and their liues in your seruice, and in the maintenaunce of your dignitie, rightes and preheminences. And like as God hath put into your highnes minde, to take vpon you, first the protection and defence, and secondly the whole Souereigntie of the Low Countries and Prouinces, which haue entred into league with you, vpon hope that the same God, will of his gratious goodnesse and mercie, so blesse and prosper your dealings and enterprises: as that they shall out of hand see the effecte of that communication

in the hyest degree, to the accomplishment of your royall and Heroycall desires, both in the generall, and also in the particular delyueraunce of the Countrey from the calamities and miseries of war: wherby they shall haue the better cause to acknoweledge the great goodturnes and benefites receiued at your heighnesse hand, and to honour, loue and serue you, as the very Protector of the land and father of their Countrey.
               When Uanderwerk had made an end, and the Dukes heighnes had aunswered him conformably to that which hee had spoken without the Towne: the said Uanderwerk told the people alowd, yt the Duke was ready to take &amp; receiue his oth, at yt hand of the Magistrate &amp; of al the people &amp; Inhabiters of the Citie of Antwerp. And that god had vouchsafed to sēd thē a Prince of so rare and heroycall vertues, of so great puissaunce, and the onely brother of so great a king: that they might well hope, that the same God would inable him to ridde these Countries within a while, from the great number of calamities and myseries wherewith they were oppressed. And forasmuch as his heighnesse had beene receyued with solempne delyberation of the states

confederate, yea and with solemne resolution of all the members of that Citie, and GOD had commaunded men to loue, honour and obey their Princes: he exhorted the people to yeelde him all humble obedience according to Gods commaundement. To which intent, the oth as well which his highnesse should make to the people, as which the people shoulde make to his highnes, should be read vnto thē. Praying God to giue such grace vnto his heighnes, as he folowing the same, might wel rule &amp; gouerne: and vnto the Burgesses and Citizens of Antwerp, as they might perform their obedience like good, loyall and faythfull subiects: that Gods name might be sanctified, to the benefit, prosperitie and safegarde of the Citie, and to the great increase of the Dukes puyssaunce, honour and glory.
               Then the same Underwerk red the othe which was to be made by the Duke, with the style of the Duke of Brabande, and all his other tytles. Which oth was red to his heighnes in French, and receyued by Syr Philip Schonehouen Lorde of Wan
                     •
                  roe Borowhmayster without the Citie.
               Which being don, y• said Uanderwerk red y• oth which the Magistrate &amp; people were to

make which was repeated word for worde by the Magistrates and a great number of people which were within the hearing of it. And this oth was exacted of the Magistrate and people of Antwerpe, by the Amptman in the name and by the commaundemente of the Duke.
               Uppon the finishing of these solemnities, the Duke himselfe did cast twoor three handfulles of golde and siluer amonge them, and then the Herauldes cryed Alargesse, and the trumpettes and drummes were sounded euerye where, and many instruments of musicke were played vpon, as had beene doone afore at his first arryuall.
               When he was come downe from the scaffolde, hee wente into the Townehouse with all the Princes, Lordes and Gentlemen, which were verye manye: where he was receyued by the Worshipfull of the Citie, and dyned openly at a very sumptuous and royall feast prepared for him: and so that daye passed in great ioye, contentation and admiration, as wel of his heighnesse and his company, as of all the reste of the people. Towards night were shot off two peales of great ordinance againe, and the fires of ioye were continue
                     •
                  
                  
much greater, and mo in number tha
                     •
                   afore.
               Thus ended the ioyefull and royall enterteinement of the right noble Prince Frauncis, Sonne &amp; brother to the kings of France, by the grace of God Duke of Braband. The rest of the weeke and the daies following, the Lordes of the priuy Counsell, the Offycers of the Aydes, of the Exchecquers, of the c
                     •
                  ambers of the accountes, and of the other Corporations, Colleges and Cōmunalties came to visit his heighnesse, and to offer him their humble seruice, promising al faythfulnes and obedience. All whome hee receyued verye gratiously, to their contentation: aunswering them so aduisedly, with so good grace and fitnesse, without omitting anye poynte of that which hee had purposed: that all men not onely wondered at him, but also were inforced to honour and loue him, and to set forth his prayses among the people. Fynally the Deputies of the reformed Churches, of both the languages, being presented vnto him by the Prince of Orendge, were gently heard: and they spake vnto him as followeth.
               Syr, wee be sent vnto your Heighnesse by the reformed Churches of this Citie, as well

of the language of Lowe Duchland, as of the French, to shew vnto you with all humilitie, reuerence and subiection, that wee haue thanked and still doe thanke God with all our heart, for voutsafing too bring your heighnes so happily hyther. And this our ioy is matched with the toy of all other folkes, as wee hope your heighnes hath vnderstoode by the glad and ioyfull receiuing and entertayning of you. Also Syr we hope, that as the great honour and felicitie which these Countries haue attayned vnto (wherein few Countries are able to match them) haue beene purchased vnder the souereignetie and gouernmente of the right reno
                     •
                  ed Princes, the Dukes of Burgoyn, which issued out of the most noble house of Fraunce: so vnder your guiding and gouernement being of the same house, the auncient renoume of the same dignitie, shalbe recouered by your prowesse, and mayntained by your wisdome. It is little more than three hundred yeares agoe, that these Countries being gouerned by sundry Dukes, Earles and Lordes, had not atteyned the renoume which other nations haue since that tyme so much wondred at. The first that began to giue increase to it, was Philip Duke of Burgoyne

surnamed the hardy, who was brothe
                     •
                   to king Charles the fifth, the sonne of king Iohn, and graundsonne of king Philip of Ualoys: of which kinges your heighnesse is lineally descended from the father to the son. For the first Duke of Orleance, of whome your heighnes is lineally desended from the father to the sonne, was the sonne of King Charles y• fift, &amp; as now there be no moe heirs males of the sayde Duke of Orleance: but onely your heighnesse and the kinge your brother. Whereby it falleth out, that the Dukes of Burgoyne are great vncles to your highnesse by the fathers side. And therfore wee doubte not but you will followe the footesteppes of their vertues, in restoring the state of the Countrie to her auncient renoume and dignitie: and also mainteine and increase the honour wherevnto it hath beene aduaunced, by those noble princes your Uncles. The second duke vnder whom this state hath beene greatly aduaunced, was Iohn the second. Neuerthelesse it came not to full perfection, til y• time of Philip the second. In which perfection it was maintained by Charles y• last duke of Burgoyne, so long as 
                     •
                  e liued. The said Philip y• second, to whom y•
                  
honour of stablishing that state most peculiarlye belongeth, was one of the most knightlye and val
                     •
                  aunt Princes of his tyme. Hee wan the victorie in nine foughten fieldes, in most of the which hee was put to the tryall and hazarde of his person, by fighting with his own handes. He was a very sage Prince, and such a one as had to deale with the greatest Princes in Christendome: of whom some were his aduersaries, and yet hee behaued himselfe so wisely, that he atchieued all thinges to his honour, whatsoeuer hee tooke in hande. Also hee was very rich: insomuch that for all his wars, which lasted aboue thirtie yeares, hee lefte behinde him more substance and readye monie then any other Prince of his time, as the Writers of the hystories of that age doe witnesse vnto vs. And yet notwithstanding, for al these great vertues and qualities of his, he was not named Philip the sage, nor Philip the valiaunt, nor Philip the rich: but Phillip the good. So well doe al folke by generall consent vnderstande, which is the vertue that best beseemeth and becōmeth a great Prince, and is best lyked of his people: namely that a Prince bee good and louing to his subiectes. Surely Syr, all men hope that your Heighnesse

will followe the example of that good Prince, the first bringer of the state of this Countrie to perfection, a right noble and renoumed prince of the house of France. And we praise God, for that as manye as haue had the honour to come into your heighnesse presence, yeelde record that you haue very great likelyhods of these vertues, which we prays God so to accōplish and make perfect in you, as al his people may to your great honour receiue the perfect and rype fruits of them. And this doe al the rest of the people desire as wel as we. Howbeit, we haue a most humble suite to make perticularly to your heighnes, which we most humbly beseech you to graunt. The thing that induceth vs to doe it, is that you beare the name of Frauncis. For as oft as we heare that name named: the remembraunce of that great king Frauncis, your heighnesse graundfather commeth to our minde. He was a right valiant, couragious, noble and godlye Prince: and yet notwithstanding, all the nations of the earth, did by one common consent surname him the Father of learning. For of a truth, since that Emperour and great king of Fraunce, called Charles the great, there was neuer any king of Fraunce that so heighly

fauoured learning, as this great king Frauncis. And as the sayd king Charles was the founder of the famous vniuersitie of Paris: so was king Frauncis the restorer thereof againe: and both of them to their great costes &amp; charges, called men of excellent knowledge thither out of straung countries, to teach the languages &amp; al kindes of artes and sciences. The house of this great king Frauncis was as an vniuersitie, and his table was a place of conference concerning al maner of learning. And like as other great Princes of his time following his example, inriched their dominions and kingdomes with learned men and learning: so wee most humbly beseech your heighnes, to follow the example of this great king your grandfather, in doing the like, and to make singular account of learning, and to take the professours thereof vnder your protection. True it is Syr, that through the malice of men, war is commōly the ouerthrower of fearning. But if a great Prince set himself against the mischiefe, he may easily stoppe it. Our desire is not that your heighnes shoulde neglect the exercise of chiualrie, for to giue your selfe to studie: but to follow so the one, 
                     •
                  s the other be not left of and forgotten. For

as we haue seene many cōmonweales florish so long as they professed chiualrie and learning together: &amp; yet haue falne into the hands of their enemies, euen in the chiefe flowre of their skil in sciences, by reason of their discontinuing of their former trade of armes, after which maner it befel to the Atheniās, to come into subiection to the kinges of Macedonie: so y• people which haue professed armes alone without learning, haue alwayes become barbarous, cruell and vtterly destitute of all humanitie, as we see at this day by the Tartars and Moscouits. And therfore to our seeming, a man may well say, that chiualrie is the foundation and sinewes of a commonweale: and that learning garnisheth and beauti
                     •
                  eth the body thereof with liuelye and freshe colours, seruing it for inrichments and ornaments. In respect whereof, as wee meant not to desire your heighnesse to forget those which make profession of chiualrie, whome you ought to imbrace as your strength: so we most humbly beseech you to vouchsafe to succour learning, and to maintaine learned men with your gratious fauour. Sir, very needeful causes moue vs to make this humble petition to your highnes: first for that we being professors of learning,

ought to haue learning in singular estimation, and to procure, if it be possible for vs, that the fruite of the thinges which we haue inioyed for a time, may be conueied to our posteritie: and secondly for the othes sake which we haue taken at the time of our proceeding in our degrees, which is, to maintain and further the schooles and learning of the vniuersitie, in what degree soeuer wee come vnto. And therefore wee hope that your heighnesse will doe vs the honour, to take this most humble request of ours in good parte. As touching our own persons, we promise your heighnesse all obedience, faithfulnesse and subtection: and that according to our small abilitie, wee will doe our indeuour towardes such as we may haue accesse vnto, that they also may yeelde obedience to your heighnes, and to the Magistrates whome it shall please you to set ouer the people. And here to make an ende, wee hartely pray God to preserue your highnes long time, in happy estate amōg this people, and to giue you the grace to rule and gouerne them iustlye and vprightly: to rydde them out of the handes of their enemyes: to maynetayne them longe in happy peace, and to restore this state agayne to the ancient

dignitie, greatnes, renowme, &amp; felicitie: that after your deceasse you may leaue a most blessed and famous rememembrance among al nacions. And for the bringing hereof too passe, wee yet agayne beseech the king of kings &amp; great prince of princes, too make you as valiant as Dauid, as wyse as Salomon, &amp; as zelous of his glorie as Ezechias.
               Herevntoo the Duke answered, y• he was very glad too see such a consent of all the people in the receiuing of him: &amp; that he hoped so too rule &amp; gouerne them, as they shoulde not bee disappoynted of the hope which they had conceiued of his gouernment, which he would fashiō out after y• patterne of his predecessors &amp; great vncles, who had gouerned these countries so happily. And he thāked them for their good will and loue, praying thē to continue y• same, &amp; promising too take them into his protection
                     •
                   togither with the rest of the people in generall: &amp; that as he had heretofore a singular regard of learned men, so would he bee willing to continue the same heereafter.
               After this maner began this great prince 
                     •
                  o gouerne that people with great authoritye and modestie: and the people too yeeld vntoo him very wissing and honourable obedience:

And all men hope both generally and particularly, y• God wil giue him the grace so to hold on in that so holy and commendable gouernement, as that by his example, he shall shew too all princes and too all others that come after him, how greatly the iust and lawfull gouernment auayleth. And that the people on their syde, shal shew what maner of obedience, loue, &amp; constancie is dew to good Princes, in which vertewes there was neuer yet any people that could skill to surmount them, nother shall any hereafter, by the helpe of the great God and euerlasting father of our sauiour Jesus Christ, too whom in the vnitie of the holy spirit, be all glorie for euer and euer,
               Amen.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶ A Summe of the Priuiledge graunted to the Printer by the foremencioned Mounsire Duke of Braband, Aniow &amp;c, for the printing of the foretranslated booke.
            FRauncis of Fraūce the kings only brother, by the grace of God Duke of Lothyer, Braband, Limbourge, Gelders, Aniow, Alaunson, Touram, berry, Eureus, &amp; y• castle Thierrie, Earle of Flaūders, Holland, Zeland, Zutphen, Mayne le Perch, Manutes of Melaun, &amp; Beaufort: Marques of the sacred Empyre, Lorde of Fryselande and Malines: hauing reteyned &amp; confirmed Christopher Plantine for his Printer, hath giuen him power to print all Proclamacions, commissions, Letters Patentes, Statutes, Ordinaunces, Placardes, and other thinges concerning the common weale in generall, or any citie in particular: and specially the discourse of his interteinement and receiuing intoo the citie of Antwerpe and the rest of the countrie thereabouts. And he forbiddeth all other persons, of what state, condicion, or qualitie

so euer they bee, too printe or cause to be printed, to sell or distribute abroade, the same or anie the like, vppon payne of forfeyture of the same bookes, and to bee fyned at his highnes pleasure, and to pa
                  •
               e all the sayde Plantines costes and domages, as is more largelye declared in the letters Patentes giuen at Antwerp the xvii. day of the Moneth of Aprill. 1582.
            
               Vndersigned
I. Van Assehers.
            
         
         
            ¶ Imprinted at London at the three Cranes in the Vintree by Thomas Dawson for william Ponsonby, 1582.
            
         
      
   

