
   
      
         
            The conuersion of a most noble lady of Fraunce In Iune last past, 1608. Madame Gratiana, wife to the high and mightie lord; Claudius, Lord of Tremoille; Duke of Thouars; peere of Fraunce, and Prince of Talmonde. A most Christian epistle, written by her, to the ladyes of Fraunce, to resolue them in the cause of her conuersion from popery, to the the profession of Gods Gospell: and aduising them to imitate her religious example. Truely translated out of French.
            Tremoille, Charlotte Brabantina, Duchess of, 1580-1631.
         
         
            
               1608
            
         
         Approx. 90 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2006-06 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01148
            STC 11262
            ESTC S102563
            99838335
            99838335
            2710
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01148)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2710)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1202:13)
         
         
            
               
                  The conuersion of a most noble lady of Fraunce In Iune last past, 1608. Madame Gratiana, wife to the high and mightie lord; Claudius, Lord of Tremoille; Duke of Thouars; peere of Fraunce, and Prince of Talmonde. A most Christian epistle, written by her, to the ladyes of Fraunce, to resolue them in the cause of her conuersion from popery, to the the profession of Gods Gospell: and aduising them to imitate her religious example. Truely translated out of French.
                  Tremoille, Charlotte Brabantina, Duchess of, 1580-1631.
                  Munday, Anthony, 1553-1633.
               
               [56] p.   
               
                  Printed by Thomas Purfoot, for Nathaniell Butter, and are to be sold at his shoppe at S. Austens Gate, at the signe of the Pyde Bull,
                  At London :
                  1608.
               
               
                  Translated by Anthony Munday.
                  Original French title not traced.
                  Signatures: A²  B-G⁴ H² .
                  The last leaf is blank.
                  Running title reads: A Christian epistle to the ladies of Fraunce.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.
               Mass --  Controversial literature.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-12
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-03
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2006-03
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-04
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
               
THE Conuerſion of a moſt Noble Lady of Fraunce. In Iune laſt paſt, 1608.
Madame Gratiana, wife to the high and mightie Lord; Claudius, Lord of Tremoille; Duke of Thouars; Peere of Fraunce, and Prince of Talmonde.
            A moſt Chriſtian Epiſtle, written by her, to the Ladyes of Fraunce, to reſolue them in the cauſe of her Conuerſion from Popery, to the profeſſion of Gods Goſpell: And aduiſing them to imitate her Religious example. Truely tranſlated out of French.
            Magna eſt veritas, &amp; praeualet. 
                  Eſdras. 3.
            
            
               AT LONDON, Printed by Thomas Purfoot, for Nathaniell Butter, and are to be ſold at his ſhoppe at S.
Auſtens Gate, at the ſigne of the Pyde Bull. 1608. (⸪)
         
         
            
            
               
To the right Worſhipfull, Sir Iohn Swynnerton Knight, Alderman of London, and true louer of learning. Alſo to the moſt vertuous Ladie his wife: All happineſſe hartily wiſheth.
            
               SIr, I am ſo bolde, as to preſent you and your worthy Lady, with a moſt memorable and iudicious labour of a Ladie▪ lately conuerted from the dimme and groſſe errours of ſuperſtitious Poperie, to the profeſſion of Gods true Religion and holie Goſpell. The reaſon of her Conuerſion, and many palpable abuſes, (beſides blaſphemies and ſacriledges) committed in Poperie: Shee hath ſet downe in an excellent Epiſt le, and ſent the ſame to her wonted friends and familiars, the Ladies of Fraunce, to encourage them in the imitation of this her godly example. My vnfained loue to your Worſhip, your louing Ladie, and all yours, I truſt ſhall pleade my pardon for this preſumption: In hope whereof, moſt humblie I commit you all to the heauenlie protection.
         
         
            
            To thoſe mis-led Ladies and Gentlewomen of England, whome ſeducing Seminaries and Popiſh Prieſts haue too much preuailed withall, to the great danger of their ſoules, if they continue ſtill in blindnes.
            
               LAdies and Gentlewomen, this Eipſtle of a moſt honourable French Ladie and Ducheſſe, by mee preſents it ſelfe to your gentle pervſing. I would my prayers, or ought elſe in me, could ſo farre preuaile with you, as but to reade ouer this her learned labour, in steede of thoſe other abuſing Bookes, which your falſly named ghostly Fathers, in ſecret beſtowe on you▪ Then ſhould I haue no doubt, but Gods good ſpirit ſpeaking by this Lady to you, would open both your eyes and vnderstanding, to let you ſee the great danger of your enemies ſeducing, and call you home in time to the ſheepefolde of faith, euen by her vertuous and religious example, that hath ſoworthily led the way before you. The Booke it ſelfe speakes much better things vnto yee, then any way I am able to doe: therefore to it, and Gods aſſisting grace in and by it, most humbly I leaue you.
         
      
      
         
            
            AN EXCELLENT Epiſtle, or exhortatorie Letter, written by Madame Gratiana, wife to the high and mightie Lord, Claudius, Lord of Tremoille, Duke of Thouars▪
                Peere of Fraunce, and Prince of Talmond: To all the honorable Ladies of Fraunce.
            To reſolue them in the cauſe of her conuerſion from Poperie, and aduiſing them to imitate her religious example.
            
               
                  GRacious and Honorable Ladies, 
            
            I am ſure it hath amazed ſome of you not a little, that I haue forſaken the ſocietie, wherein I was woont to meete you, and haue drawen vpon my ſelfe that diſgracefull name of an Huguenot (for ſo I heare you pleaſe to tearme me) and other ſcandalous imputations wherewith you vpbraide me; all which are to me no meane aduantage. To reſolue you therefore (at full) of my departing from your companie, and requiring withall, to forbeare your daily ſollicitations to realter me, peruſe but this ſhort diſcourſe which I ſend vnto you, and then I doubt not but in ſome meaſure you will reſt ſatiſfied.
            After God had determined in his good time, to

 withdrawe me out of the ſinck of ſinne and idolatrie,After her conuerſion, ſhe wrote this Epistle. to incorporate me in the communion of his Sonne, within the boſome of his ſanctified Church, the refuge for all them that deſire ſaluation, (and where I wiſh, and deſire in ſoule, that I could embrace you all:) After (I ſay) God had thus diſpoſed of my abſolute conuerſion, notwithſtanding my many reuoltes and back▪ſlidings, by your Letters, wherewith I was continually laboured, and other meanes of no ſmall moment; I fell vpon my knees, and as the bleſſed Virgin Marie ſaid in her Song, at that heauenly ſalutation brought her by the Angell Gabriell, euen ſo I ſpake to my God in my ſoule:
                  Luke 2. 38. 
               Be it Lord vnto me, according to thy word.
            
            And calling to remembraunce, that in the laſt conference we had together, you ſtoode vpon certaine points of Religion, wherewith you preſſed me very narrowly, and I could not then ſo readily anſwere you: I entreate yee to receiue therein ſatisfaction from me now, and to perſwade your ſelues withall, that it is Gods cauſe I take vpon me A vertuous acknowledgment of a godly Lady. (a weake woman) to defend, and he will thorowly ſtrengthen me againſt all reſiſtaunces. And ſince it hath pleaſed him to vſe my poore ſeruice if not (in this cleare light of his Goſpell) to aduaunce the ſame as I could wiſh, yet at leaſt (like a willing labourer) to bring ſtones and rubble to ſupply the building: you ſhall perceiue what knowledge his grace hath confirmed in me, which I wiſh were as liberallie engraſted into you, that our harts being

enflamed with the deſire of his glorie, we might all be of one minde in our Lord ſeſus, expecting his comming to enlarge and releaſe vs.
            Pardon me then (moſt Honorable and worthy Ladies) if I make plaine and lay open to you, I will not ſay the ſimple abuſes: but the wicked, ſuperſtitious and blaſphemous I dolatries, which are daily practiſed and vſed in your Romaine Church, only thereby to ouerthrowe, the true ſeruice and worſhip of the euerliuing God. And alb eit the number of theſe iniuries are infinite, ſufficient to fill a verie large and great volume, and whereof ſome of you haue (in priuate) tolde me your miſlike: yet at this time, according to my promiſe in our laſt conſultation: I will deale with the very cheefeſt abuſe of all, euen that which is intruded by Sathans inſtigation, into the moſt excellent and principall ſeruice of God, by you (and by my ſelfe heeretofore) tearmed the Maſſe. Perſwading my ſelfe, that when I haue (as it were with my finger) pointed at the blaſphemies, idolatrie and manifeſt ſacriledges therein committed:She takes on her, to note the abuſes in the Maſſe. you will ſuffer your eyes to be no longer blinded, with the pompe and exteriour deuotion of ſuch deceiuers; but rather that you will awaken your better iudgements, and looke into the impietie and prophanation, which lies masked vnder ſo hideous a Monſter. And I will ſhape mycourſe and methode,Her courſe intended in this Epiſtle.  by euerie abuſe in his ſuccinct place and ranck, and according as the nature of ſo weake an Epiſtle will beſt beare it.
            
               
They teach you, that in the Maſſe, Prieſts doe daily ſacrifice, and offer vp the bodie of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, to God the Father: to deface and expiate, not only the ſinnes of the Prieſt that makes the offring, but likewiſe of the people, who are his asſiſtants at the celebration of the Maſſe. Now we ſay, that this is a very great outrage and wronge, done to our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and to his true ſacrifice. Firſt of all, in transferring to mortall men, or communicating to them, the dignitie of his ſupreme Prieſthood;Chriſt his office of Priesthood, transferred to men. we woonder by what authoritie or allowance this ſhould be done? For the whole bodie of the Scripture declareth plainly to vs: That he is the eternall ſacrificer, according to the order of Melchizedeck,
                  Hebr. 7 9. 23. 24. 25. 26. yea, and that in ſuch ſort, As he is the only Prieſt of that order, and permitteth not the receipt of ſucceſſors or Vicars. For, as concerning the ſacrificers of the Law, there were made many to ſucceede one after another: Becauſe they were not ſuffered to endure, by the reaſon of death. But this man (ſaith the Apoſtle to the Hebrewes) becauſe he endureth for euer, hath an euerlaſting Priesthood.
                     Hebr. 9. 24. 25. 26. Which needed not daily (as thoſe high Prieſts under the Law, to enter the holy places yearely with other bloud) firſt for his owne ſinnes, and then for the peoples: Otherwiſe, it had bin needfull for him to haue ſuffered many times, ſince the foundation of the world. But now in the conſummation of the world, hath he appeared once, to put away ſinne, by the ſacrifice of himſelfe. Being both the

offering ſacrificer, &amp; the ſacrifice offered for ſinne, according to the nature of this holy ſacrifice of the new Teſtament, that the Sacrifice and Sacrificer ſhould be both one.
            
               Ieſus Chriſt is the only Sacrificer, without any ſucceſſor or Vicar. To Ieſus Chriſt then only appertaineth the honor, to be the Sacrificer of the new couenant: and they doe him intollerable outrage, to appoint him any Succeſſors or Suffragans, in regard the Apoſtle ſaith: There is one euerlaſting Sacrificer, which neuer ceaſeth, and paſſeth not from one to another.
               
                  Hebr. 9. 26. Nor can this honor be attributed to any other, but only he that is called of God, as Aaron was. So likewiſe Chriſt tooke not to himſelfe this honor, to be made the high Prieſt: but he glorified him, that ſaide vnto him: Thou art my Sonne, this day begate I thee. 
               
                  Heb. 5 4. 5. And as in the former place: Thou art an euerlaſting ſacrificer, after the order of Melchiſedeck.
            It is not I (Ladies) that haue ſpoken all this, but Gods infallibe word the ſacred Scripture.The popiſh Prieſts muſt ſhewe their warrant out of Scripture. And now if the Prieſts of the Papacie, would haue vs to acknowledge them for ſacrificers: let them ſhew vs, how the charge to ſacrifice Ieſus Chriſt, is giuen them by God in the holy Scriptures, and then we will lend a better eare to them. But this is not the propoſition only, that Chriſt Ieſus is the ſole ſacrificer of the new couenant: but there remaines a far greater matter. For his ſacrifice neither can or ought to be iterated or performed againe, nor can it be by any other: becauſe he offered himſelfe once for all and it appertaineth to no man whatſoeuer,No man can offer as Chriſt hath offered.
               
to make the like offering as he hath done. Neither could he, as of himſelfe, offer himſelfe againe, for then he muſt haue ſuffered and died againe, as I haue prooued before by the Apoſtle. And the offering which he made of himſelfe, was once only, and that ſacrifice is of perpetuall efficacie, for the clearing and wiping away of our ſinnes. Whereupon the ſame Apoſtle ſaith, We are ſanctified, euen by the offering of the bodie of Ieſus Chriſt once made. And by one ſole oblation, which he once only offered, hath he conſecrated for euer them that are to be ſanctified.
               
                  Hebr. 10. 13. 14. 18. And ſince he hath purchaſed for vs the remisſion of our ſinnes: there remaineth no more oblations to be made for ſinne, but his blood only is ſufficient: whereby he is entred into the holy places, hauing obtained euerlaſting redemption for vs And we haue daily libertie likewiſe, by the blood of Ieſus, to enter into the holy places: in regard that he is the eternall ſacrificer, to ſaue all ſuch as he ſhall preſent to God, liuing there as their continuall interceſſor. In all which alleadged places, the Apoſtle makes no mention at all, of any new oblation, or continual offering the bodie of Chriſt, by the hands of men.No mention is made in Scripture, of any new or continued offering.
            
            Who will not ſay then, that this is blaſphemie, not only in transferring to mortall men the dignitie of the eternall Prieſthood of Ieſus Chriſt, who neuer reſigned his office to any other; but likewiſe to reiterate and renew his ſacrifice daily, as if the efficacie of the ſacrifice, which himſelfe once offered

vpon the Croſſe, were not ſufficient to endure, and for our reconciliation to God? What ſhall we alſo thinke of this ſaying of the Apoſtle: If
               Rom. 5. 1
                     •
                  . 
               when we were enemies, we were reconcilea to God by the death of his Sonne: much more being reconciled, we ſhall be ſaued by his life. That is to ſay, becauſe he is daily aliue, to intercede in our behalfe, and procure vs grace and fauour, as hath bin before declared. Or, as he elſewhere ſaith: In regard he appeareth
                  Hebr 9. 14. now for vs before the face of God, to wit, in the powerfull vertue of his ſacrifice, to communicate the ſame to all beleeuers: There is therefore no neede, of any new ſacrifice or reiteration thereof.
            Vnderſtand, good Ladies, that I doe not tie my ſelfe, to note euery particular which is condemned,She dealeth not with euerie particularerror in the Maſſe. thorow the whole paſſage of the Maſle, which is very thicke ſowen with blaſphemies, from the beginning to the end: therein I ſhould tier both my ſelfe and you. As for example, ſhould I ſpeake of the Prieſts entraunce to the Altar, wherein (you knowe) I vtter no lye. Firſt, the Prieſt confeſſethThe Priests confeſſion. himſelfe, not only to God, but likewiſe both to he Saints and ſhe Saints, not ſo much as naming Ieſus Chriſt. Then afterward, in the beginning of their Canon, and before he goes to any conſecration, heSacrifice offered before conſecration, for the redemption of ſoules liuing. ſaith, That he offers that Sacrifice to God (to wit, the bread and wine, which are vpon the Altar, and as yet not conſecrated) firſt of all, for the Catholique Church, next, for the redemption of all their

ſouls, that are asſiſtant at the Maſſe. O deare Ladies, what a blaſphemie is this? O, that it ſhould euer be receiued among Chriſtians; Or that a ſinfull man ſhould preſume to ſay: That he offers an oblation of bread &amp; wine to God, and for there demption of ſoules. Nay, admit that it were the bodie &amp; blood of Ieſus Chriſt: yet (deare ſoules) you ſee it manifeſtly prooued vnto you alreadie, that it is not now at this day to be offred againe, neither can it, by the Apoſtles teſtimonie alreadie rehearſed.
            I paſſe ouer alſo manyp rayers ful of iniquitie, as well before, as after the conſecration. As in the Memento,
               The Prieſt in his Memento. when the Prieſt requireth the fauour of God, by the merits and intercesſion of Saints: As if the ſacriſice of Ieſus Chriſt, which they ſay they preferre in the formoſt place, were not ſufficient to impetrate ſuch grace of God.
            Then after conſecration, they commit a ſinne, whereof by no meanes (I thinke) they can excuſeThe Prieſts prayer after the conſecration. themſelues. For the Prieſt prayeth to God, that the oblation which he offereth (to wit, the bodie and the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt, according to the verie words vſed by the Prieſt) may be caried by the hands of his holy Angell, into the high Altar before Ieſus Chriſt. As if Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe had forſaken Heauen, &amp; ſtood in neede to be caried thither againe, and by the hands of an Angell. O, honorable Ladies, what a blaſphemie is this, againſt him that hath all power ſubiected vnder his feete, and ſitteth for euer at the right hand of God his

Father?
            
               The Prieſts Memento for the dead. Alſo in the Prieſts Memento for the dead, he prayeth for them, (that alreadie are ſleeping in the very height of peace) that God would giue them a place of peace &amp; refreſhing. But to what purpoſe is this? when the parties are poſſeſſed of ſuch a peacefull place alreadie, why ſhould they mooue any ſuch place afterward in vaine?
            There are many other things (louing Madames) the collection whereof would be very tedious vnto you, and which you may ſee very learnedly confuted, ech point by point, in the Booke which I ſhewed you at our laſt meeting, called the Anatomie
               The Anatomie of the Maſſe, printed in French. 
               of the Maſse, printed for your more eaſie vnderſtanding▪ in our owne language, more then thirtie yeares ſince, and neuer (all this while) anſwered by the contrarie ſide.
            But come we now to the eſpeciall point, concerning the confidente and peruerſe opinion, (wherein I my ſelfe haue ſinned too often, and which you hold as no meane Article of faith,) That the Maſſe is a worke meritorious, to cancell allThe Maſſe ameritorious worke, to deface all ſinnes. our ſinnes; Ex epere operato, as themſelues vſe to ſay. Which is as much to ſay▪ as that by the vertue of that worke, the labour is performed, without making mention of his faith and repentaunce, for whom the Maſſe is ſayd, and is therein asſiſted. Heereby you may perceiue (good Ladies) that the efficacie of the death of Ieſus Chriſt (whereof by true faith we are all made pertakers) is now attributed

to a work done by man: yea, &amp; may as wel beConcerning the dead. applied to the dead, as the liuing. By which means, the Sacraments ſhall but profit them only, which communicated in true ſaith and repentaunce. But then this cannot be ſpoken thus of them that are deceaſed, and departed out of this world: because they haue no more communion with the liuing, whereby to participate of their Sacraments.
            As for the Sacrifice of Ieſus Chriſt, that is (ſaith
                  Rom. 3. 25 the Apoſtle) through faith in his bloud, which makes vs partakers of the propitiation thereby obtained. Now the dead can haue neither faith nor repentaunce, but are gone as they placed before the end1. Pet. 1. 9 Iohn. 3. 18. of their faith, either for the ſaluation of their ſoules, or to be puniſhed in hell, for their incredulitie.
            Iouerſlip a great many blaſphemies, which deſerue ech one to be ſeuerally ſpoken of: For you haue tolde me, that ſome things you giue credit to, and others you doe not, eſpecially any thing which you conceite to be damnable. But you being heerein gouerned only by your Prieſts opinions, you hang your ſelues on their ſleeues, and are neuer the neerer, when you ſhall come to make your account. And your excuſe, concerningOf the prayers ſaid or ſung in the Maſſe. thoſe prayers which they ſing or ſay in their Maſſe, that they are in Latine, and you vnderſtand them not, but beleeue them to be good and holy▪ Truſt me (worthy Ladies) it is idle and friuolous, for you ought to vnderſtand them, and may if you will, thereby to examine and trie the ſpirits, whether

they be of God or no. You haue them publiſhed in printed bookes, and ſo haue had for many yeares together: And the Scriptures themſelues remaine for your further inſtruction, which though they forbid you the reading of them, yet be you rulde
                  Iohn. 5. 19. by him, that ſaith, Search the Scriptures, it is they that doe beare true witnes of me.
            
            But leauing all other, there is one moſt ſignall and apparant, and ſuch a blaſphemie, whereof I knowe you are almoſt daily partakers, being preſent at Maſſe. For both common opinion and intention,The Prieſt and peoples opinion preſent at Maſſe. as well of the Prieſt himſelfe, as the perſons there in place, doe run in this current: That it is an abſolute ſacrifice which is there performed by him, wherein all remisſion of ſins is to be ſought for, and all proſperitie, as well of the bodie as of the ſoule. For they auouch it, to be the ſelfe ſame ſacrifice of Ieſus Chriſt, which they but renew againe, to receiue a further fruite thereby, and ſo they reiterate the ſame as often, as they doe either ſing or ſay Maſſe, euen according as it was done vnder the Lawe. But what ſaith the bleſſed Apoſtle to this? The law hauing the ſhadow of good things to come, &amp; not
               
                  Hebr. 10. 1. 2. 3. 
               the very image of the things; can neuer with thoſe ſacrifices, which they offer yeere by yeere continually, ſanctifie the commers thereunto. And it is imposiſible, that the bloud of Bulles and Goates ſhould take away ſinnes. For would they not then haue ceaſed to haue bin offered, becauſe that the offerers once purged, ſhould haue had no more conſcience of ſins? This is then the reaſon, wherfore
               
               euery Prieſt appeareth daily ſacrificing, &amp; oft times offereth one manner of thing, which can neuer take away ſinnes. But this man, after he had offered one ſacrifice for ſinne, ſitteth for euer at the right hand of God. And wherefore one ſacrifice only? Becauſe (ſaith he in the verſe following) that by that alone ſacrifice, he hath conſecrated for euer them that be ſanctified.
            
            There is nothing (deare Ladies) more cleare andThe meaning of the holie Apoſtle. euident, then theſe words of the holy Apoſtle, to manifeſt openly: That the ſacrifice of Ieſus Chriſt, whereby we were once for all redeemed and ſanctified, cannot, neither ought to be reiterated or renewed. Therefore in Poperie, when they doe enterpriſe, to reiterate, or renew, or continue the ſame (for they make vſe of all theſe ſeueral tearmes) is it any thing elſe, but a meere renouncing of that only ſacrifice, remaining freſh, in full ſtrength and vigour, which Chriſt once offred vpon his Croſſe, to ſanctifie all beleeuers? And the fruite heereof is daily preſented to vs, in the preaching of the Goſpell, and we reeeiue the ſame by a true &amp; ſanctified faith, in him only. For to this end was the ſacred miniſterie of Gods word inſtituted by God himſelfe in his Church: and not for any nouell order of ſacrifices, as your (ſoules heauie enemies) doe make you to beleeue.
            
               Some perticular Ladies, not altogether popiſh. I knowe (honorable Ladies) and haue had ſuch particular intereſt in ſome of you, during the time of our often conuerſing in this manner together: that (in hart) you are far off from theſe groſſe prophanations,

and haue aſſured me (in ſoule) you doe much greeue thereat. Let me then perſwade you, not to come in ſuch places, where the Sonne of God is ſo highly iniuried, be not led by their outward appearaunce of deuotion, which ſerues but to beguile and abuſe the ſimple. Euen as is vſed in our ceremonie of meeting, and manner of courtſhip in the ſtreetes or elſe where: a good looke is giuen, or an affable conge allowed, when falſhood and trechery lurketh oftentimes in the hart. Make not then your faire ſelues guiltie, of ſuch foule and polluted behauiour, nor be you preſent where Chriſts name is miſpriſed, erecting another Altar, againſt the Altar of his Croſſe, and renewing his ſacrifice, by ſubſtitution of a newe one: as if his were but a yeare old, or like to the ſacrifices of brut beaſtes, lame or imperfect; Or as if the means which he hath ordained, for the application thereof (as the preaching of the Goſpell, and adminiſtration of his inſtituted Sacraments) were inſufficientThe fruite of the Sacrifice in the Maſſe. to conuay their vertue vnto vs. For this is the faireſt fruite of their pretended ſacrifice, that the reiteration and daily renewing thereof, is branded with the marke of inſufficiencie and imperfection, as you heare the Apoſtle to auouch the ſame: when he ſpeakes of the ſacrifices of the old Lawe, which
                  Hebr. 10. 9▪
                were performed often.
            True it is, that they would faine ground their ſacrifice vpon Gods word: but (good Ladies) marke in what manner I beſeech you, and be Iudges

your ſelues, for the caſe is very cleare. Behold (ſay they) Ieſus Chriſt making his Supper with hisSome of them ſay: Make this in my remembrance, and ſo they would haue it. Luke 22. 19
                Apoſtles, ſaid: Doe this in remembraunce of me. Doe, that is as much to ſay, according to their gloſſe; as make or performe this ſacrifice▪ becauſe that Chriſt had ſaid before; This is my bodie which is giuen for you. But if it pleaſed them to read all, they ſhould better perceiue the words and meaning of our Sauiour, which indeed are nothing leſſe, then agreeing with their glosſing.
            The Euangeliſts doe record vnto vs, that our Lord Ieſus hauing taken bread, and giuen thankes; The Euāgeliſts record of our Sauiours words. Lu. 22. 19.
               brake it, and ſaid to his Diſciples: Take, cate, this is my bodie which is giuen for you, doe this in the remembraunce of me. And how doe this? why no otherwiſe, but euen to doe it in the ſame manner, that is to ſay: To take the bread, and diſtribute it among them to be eaten, for no other mention is made there, either of offering, or of ſacrificing. For you ſee (ſweete Ladies) that Chriſt himſelfe vſed no other words, but Take, and eate. And the holy Apoſtle Saint Paule doth ſufficiently ſhewe vs, that of theſe words, doe this, there is no other vnderſtanding to be made but that which hath bin declared alreadie. For in ſpeaking of the wine at the ſame1. Co. 11. 25. Supper, he reciteth likewiſe the ſame words ſpokenThe meaning of Christs words in the Sacrament. by our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: Doe this alwayes and as oftentimes as you ſhall drinke, in remembraunce of me. Which importeth as much, as if he had ſaid: Alwayes, or as oft entimes as you ſhall drinke of this

wine in this Sacrament: Drinke it, in remembrance of me, that this may be in remembraunce of my Death, or continue as a memoriall thereof. Which manner or phraſe of ſpeaking, the Apoſtle himſelfe adioyneth in the following verſe. For alwayes, or as
               1. Co▪
                   11. 26. 
               oftentimes, as you ſhall eate of this bread, and drinke of this Cuppe: you ſhall ſhewe the Lords death vntill he come.
            
            
               Her admonition to the Ladies, concerning the expoſition of S. Paule. Conſider now, good Ladies I beſeech you, that theſe are none of our gloſſes, but the very expreſſe text it ſelfe, where you ſee manifeſtly by Saint Paules owne expoſition: what thing it is the Lord would haue vs to doe concerning as well the people, as the Paſtour. For the commandement, Doe this, directeth it ſelfe to all the faithfull, to wit: That we ſhould eate this bread of the Sacrament, and drinke the wine, in remembraunce of his death and pasſion. According as the words doe ſignifie themſelues, when he ſpake of his bodie, which is broken and giuen for you, and likewiſe of his bloud, which is ſhed or diſperſed for you. All which he ſpake, hauing regard to that which ſoone after ſhould enſue: His bodie was to be deliuered ouer to death, and his bloud to be ſhed vpon the Croſſe, for vs poore, wreched and miſerable ſinners.
            And the reaſon why he ſpake ſo of the time preſent, which is giuen, which is ſhed: is the common Latine versſion or tranſlation, allowed by the Counſell of Trente; expresſing thereby the time to come, which ſhall be giuen, which ſhall be ſ
                     •…
                  ed, then

which, nothing can be more manifeſt, honored Ladies, if it pleaſed you but to open your owneeies. For then you ſhould perceiue, that there Chriſt made on mention of offering. And if they would preſſe theſe words, which is giuen, to conclude thereby, that euen then when Ieſus madeAn excellent note, &amp; well worth the obſervation. his Supper, he offered vp his bodie in ſacrifice: Of necesſitie, and by the ſelfe ſame reaſon, they muſt alſo conclude theſe words, my bloud which is ſhed; that euen then he did ſhed his bloud, which cannot be, neither could be, for his bloud was not ſhed but vpon the Croſſe.
            Good Madames, entreat the very learnedſt of your Romaine Sacrificers, to ſhew vs but one place in the Scripture, where it is commaunded vs, to ſacrifice Ieſus Chriſt againe. For the place rehearſed,Concerning the Greeke word Poiein, and the Siriaque, Habad.
                maketh not any iote for them, and they know likewiſe well enough, that the Greeke word Poiein, vſed by the Euangeliſts, reciting the words of our Lord and Sauiour, and Saint Paule after them: Alſo the word in the Siriack tongue Habad, which our Lord himſelfe vſed, could neuer be vnderſtood to Sacrifice, or Offer.
            Goe we on then, to ſome other proprieties of the Maſſe. I come now to the Idolatrie, which weIdolatrie in holding vp the bread to be adored as God. find in the ſecond part of the Maſſe, to wit, at the Sacrament, and that is in this. They propoſe or hold vp a piece of bread to the people, to be adored and worſhipped by them for God ſaying: That there is the bleſſed bodie of our Sauiour, hidden

vnder the accidents of bread, although it doe not appeare to be ſo, and the faithfull can diſcerne but bread only. To prooue their idolatrie in this point, I will goe no whither elſe, but to the direct inſtitution of the Supper, according as our Lord himſelfe did inſtitute it, which they altogether depraue, only to confirme and eſtabliſh their Idoll: wherein, gentle Ladies, I craue not only your patience, but alſo your dilligent regard.
            
               How Christ promiſed vs to be partakers of his body and bloud. Luke 22.19
                Behold how Ieſus Chriſt promiſeth vs, that we ſhall be partakers of his bodie, and of his bloud, At all times, or as oftentimes, as we ſhall celebrate this miſterie, according as he did celebrate the ſame with his Apoſtles. In diſtributing the bread, he ſaid, Take, eate, this is my bodie which is given for you; doe this in remembrance of me. Likewiſe in deliuering the wine, he ſaid: Drinke you all of this, for this is my bloud. &amp;c. where we may diſcerne, that he putteth the commaundement in the firſt place,Chriſts commandement is in the firſt place. in ſaying to vs, that we ſhall take, eate, and drinke. Then he annexeth the promiſe, wherein he teſtifieth vnto vs, that that which we eate, is his bodie, and that which we drinke is his bloud. To enjoy then the effect and benefit of this promiſe, it behooueth, that the faithfull doe take and eate the bread, &amp; drinke the wine which is giuen to them. In briefe, there is the communion of many faithfull, in doing that, which Ieſus Chriſt repreſenting to the whole Church, did performe in this firſt Supper: For that which Ieſus Chriſt ſaid to his Apoſtles;

               Christs words to his Diſciples, is to all be faithfull to the worlds end. 
               Take, eate, drink ye all of this: he ſpake the very ſame to all the faithfull, euen to the ending of the world: As that which he adioyneth, ſufficiently declareth; My body which is giuen for you; My bloude which is ſhed for you, ſo is his bodie giuen, and his bloud ſhed for the faithfull.
            Hence then enſueth, that to all the faithfull, appertaineth the commaundement of taking, eatingThe promiſe is made to all and not to the Apoſtles onely. and drinking: becauſe he made the promiſe generally to all▪ and not only to the Apoſtles &amp; Miniſters of the Church▪ And we may ſee this teſtified by the Apoſtle Saint Paule, ſpeaking at large vpon this miſterie, theſe are his words. For we that are many,
               1▪ 
                  Cor. 10. 17. 
               are one bread and one bodie: becauſe we all are partakers of one bread. Wherefore (Ladies) it appeareth plainly that the bodie of Ieſus Chriſt, and the communion of his bloud likewiſe, are not to be giuen to vs in this Sacrament: but when many faithfull ſhall communicate together, according as ChriſtTake away the communion, and the promiſe is ended. deliuered vs an example, with his Apoſtles. Take away then the communion, which Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe hath ordained, he being the heauenly Lord, Maiſter and Author of this holy Sacrament: And then the promiſe there unto annexed, touching his body &amp; bloud, which he hath giuen for all faithfull communicants; hath no place at all, but is vtterlyThe right vſe of the Sacrament, wherein it conſiſteth. voide, For it remaineth no longer a Sacrament, nor as he ordained it, becauſe the right vſe of the Sacrament conſiſteth heerein: that the faithfull ſhould communicate together, according as he

hath commanded, ſaying, Take, eate, drinke yee. &amp;c. this muſt be done vpon necesſitie, if you would haue it to be a Sacrament, or the ſame which Ieſus Chriſt hath inſtituted; namely, the communion of many faithfull asſiſtants, to eate and drinke all together in this bleſſed banquet, for this is the eſſence of the Sacrament, as you may diſcerne very apparantly.
            
               What is don in the Maſſe Let vs now come to ſee, what is done in the Maſſe. Surely (good Ladies) it is ſo farre off from being any communion: as it may be rather tearmed, a kind of excommunication. For both you and I know, and ſo do all elſe, that know what the Maſſe is, that the Prieſt ſeparates himſelfe from all thereſt of the aſſemblie, to eate and drinke (by him ſelfe alone) the bread and wine which he hath conſecrated a part: and how doth he conſecrate them? Inſted of conſecration, which ought to beHow conſecratiō ought to be done. done, by preaching and publiſhing openly and aloude, the promiſes of our Lord and Sauiour, directed, not to the bread and to the wine, which are propoſed but as ſignes vnto vs: But to the faithfull perſons, asſiſting the communion, &amp; preſent there to communicate▪ Ieſus Chriſt being he that (euen then) conſecrates the bread &amp; wine▪ to make them Sacraments of his bodie and bloud (by his heauenly Prieſthood which yet ceaſeth not) and when this miſterie is celebrated according to his inſtitution.
            But the Prieſt deales quite contrarie, for he as

               How the Prieſt makes his conſecration in the Maſſe. if he were affraid to be heard of the people, makes his conſecration, by blowing or breathing vpon the bread, and wine, and mutters or mumbles very ſoftly and low, all the words of his inſtitution. As if it could pleaſe the Lord of truth and life, to haue his word murmured out of a dead mouth (as it were) in celebrating his ſanctified miſteries, of whoſe truth (by this behauiour) there iuſtly mayDoubt and queſtion may ariſe vpon ſuch priuie whiſpering. ariſe ſome doubt or queſtion. Or as if it were offence to him, that ſtands in feare of no power whatſoeuer: to haue them pronounced with the loudeſt voyce, to be heard and vnderſtood of all.
            In the Goſpel, the vertue, nature, and vſe of Baptiſme, are expreſſed clearely and openly. Ieſus Chriſt, making his Supper, did not mutter in any lowe voyce, either vpon the bread or wine, to deuineMark this, good Ladyes or coniure therinto his bodie and bloud. But he pronounced aloude, and euidently to his Apoſtles: That he gaue them there his body and his bloud, exhorting them to perſeuere in the ſelfe ſame kinde of action, at all times, or as often as they ſhould meete to reiterate the ſame, The remembrance of his death and paſsion. Euen as if he had beene then certainely aſſured, that no vtilitie or benefit could be had by Sacraments: except whatſoeuer was repreſented to the eye, might bee declared and warranted by the word of God. For otherwiſe, it were to abuſe the people in a fond kind of deuotion; to make a ſhew of ceremonies

before them, and neuer to deliuer or declare whatH
                     •
                  w people may be eaſily abuſed. they ſignifie, and what coherence or agreement they haue with truth.
            Therefore, when publike declaration is made of ſuch myſteries, with a chearefull predication to edifie the hearers, entring into their vnderſtanding, and winning impreſsion in their hearts, by aſſured perſwaſion of the promiſes accompliſhment; Briefely, when the grace of Ieſus Chriſt is pronounced vnto vs, and his promiſes expoſed: Euen then, and in that inſtant, doth his glorious power deſcend, to performe the worke, and then is the true conſecration acted indeed. Hereupon Saint Auguſtine ſaith very well; That the word of conſecration,
               S. Auguſtines words concerning conſecratiō. 
               is the word of faith preached: And that word conioyned with the terrene outward ſigne, maketh the ſame a ſacrament; Adding preſently after, I meane the word of faith, which we preach.
            
            What conſecration then is there in the Maſſe, when inſteed of all this, namely, expoſing to the people the recited promiſes, and declaring aloud the words of our Sauiours inſtitution: it is done in a manner of ſecret coniuration, and ſo are theThe Prieſt coniures in ſted of conſecrating. words whiſpered, which behauiour is more proper to charmers, then to be vſed in ſuch a holy and diuine Sacrament. What ſhall wee then thinke of them, when they dare forſake the rule of their Lord and Maiſter, to follow their owne fantaſies?
            
               No lawfull conſecration in the Maſſe Seing then it is ſo, and that in the Maſſe there is neither any lawfull conſecration, nor (as themſelues

cannot deny) any ſuch Communion as Ieſus Chriſt hath ordained (for one alone doth both eate and drinke, and that is the prieſt, and one man alone cannot make a Communion): It followeth then (deere Ladyes) and very neceſſarily that the body of Ieſus Chriſt is not in the Maſſe, where the Prieſt communicateth by himſelfe. And therefore the bread, which he makes to bee adored then, euen as if it were the body indeed of our Lord: is no ſuch matter, but remaineth ſtill very bread, euen as it was before his conſecration, being neyther more or leſſe, then as if it were in any other place, out of the Churches aſſembly, and the Prieſts, and whoſoeuer (for his owne pleaſure) ſhould ſpeake the very ſame words of their inſtitution, vpon any other piece of bread.
            And although they perſwade themſelues, that they haue and do hold in their hands, the very bodyThe Prieſt hath not any part of Chriſts body in his bread, which he makes an Idoll of. of Ieſus Chriſt vnder the bread, or in the bread, and therefore make the people to worſhip it; yet it is moſt certaine, that there is nothing elſe but an Idoll, and which (without any reaſon they make a meere imagination of. For the promiſe, wherein Ieſus Chriſt offered vnto vs his body and bloud, vnder the ſignes of bread and wine: appertaineth to none elſe (as hath beene already prooued) but onely vnto the faithfull, that receiue the ſame by faith, in the lawfull communion of the Euchariſte, celebrating the myſterie, according to the manner, as our heauenly Maiſter did ordaine it. Wherfore,

they which imagine, to haue any other thing then common bread, without the lawful vſe of our Lords Supper: are but abuſed, and beleeue meereThe people are deceiued in the Maſſe. dreames, as it can be no otherwiſe, becauſe they faile of the promiſe. For ſeeing that Ieſus Chriſt promiſed vs, to giue vs his body in the Sacrament, when the faithfull ſhould communicate together after his inſtitution: we may not be ſo vain or idle-headed, as to ſeeke it elſewhere, or according to our fantaſies.
            Let ſuch men therfore be admoniſhed, that they cannot excuſe themſelues of idolatry, both before God and men: when they are made to worſhippeThey worſhip a round cake in ſtead of God. (as if God himſelfe were ſubſtantially preſent) a round cake of bread, which is lifted vp to be ſeen, aboue the ſhoulders of the Prieſt, and (with exceeding great deuotion) to be reuerenced and adored of all there preſent.
            But Ladies, I haue held ye ſomewhat long in this point, becauſe it is of ſuch maine importance, yet perſwading my ſelfe to haue ſaid ſufficient, albeit not halfe ſo much as I could: I will proceed to diſcouer another wicked Idolatry, which theyShe proceedeth to another idolatry commutted by the ignorant people. procure the poore people to commit▪ euen without ſo much as thinking theron▪ And that is, wheras in their Maſſe▪ they ſhould obſerue the communion in that kinde as our Lord Ieſus Chriſt did firſt inſtitute it by inniting the people to communicate with the Preiſt, they fly from his example, and indeed, (once a yeare) they are contented to doe ſo,

and that is at Eaſter, for then the people ſhall beeThe people doe communicate but in one kinde. permitted to communicate, and yet it is but of one moitie onely of the Sacrament, wherein likewiſe they intermingle many fond inuentions, yea, and all the accuſtomed ſuperſtitions of their ordinarie Maſſes, without expounding, or declaring any part of the miſtery to the people.
            According to the inſtitution of our Lord in the Sacrament, they ſhould inuite the people, and breaking the body of Chriſt, after his example, it ſhould be truely giuen to the faithfull Communicants, according to the promiſe of our Sauiour. Notwithſtanding all this, they will obſerue their owne deuiſed manner, wherein they can no wayThe Prieſts are Idolators and make the people to cō
                  mit idolatry. exempt themſelues from being Idolaters, and making the people to commit Idolatry, in their giuing worſhip to the bare ſigne. The reaſon is, becauſe Ieſus Chriſt in the Sacrament, gaue his bodie to be lookte vpon with our ſoules eyes, and not to be ſuperſtitiouſly adored in the bread, which is no more but the outward ſigne, and (by faith) to bee eaten to euerlaſting life. For (worthy Ladyes)Chriſt did command no worſhip to the bread. Chriſt did not ſay, looke vpon this bread, then take, eate, and worſhip it: but he ſimply ſaid, Take, eate, this is my body.
            Therefore whereas the Sacrament ſhould bee a helpe, to liſt vp the vnderſtanding, of the faithfull vnto heauen, where Chriſt Ieſus is, and no where elſe, as concerning his true body, &amp; (from thence) giues himſelfe in powerfull vertue, to enioy and

poſſeſſe the ſoules of the faithfull, vnder thoſe formes by himſelfe asſigned: your Romaniſts doe abuſe the Supper very vildlie, and take it in a quiteThe Romanists doe abuſe the lords ſupper. contrary nature, for they are onely pleas'de, with looking vpon the bare ſigne and worſhiping it, taking the thing it ſelfe, for that which is meerely ſignified thereby, anſwerable to their doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, meerely forged, againſt the true nature of all Sacraments.
            They ſeeke not to eleuate mens vnderſtandings, to the place where Chriſt ſitteth at the right hande of his Father, but to lift vp their eies to their Godlike Idoll. Whereas Chriſt (without all doubt) in inſtituting this Sacrament, neuer addreſſed his promiſeChriſt directed not his promiſe to the bread &amp; wine only. to the bread and wine ſimply, thereby to make them become his body and bloud, as hath beene before declared: But to the faithfull communicants, and ſo thereby to aſſure them, that he would giue them the true participation and communion of his body, anſwerable to that which the bleſſed Apoſtle S. Paule ſaith, he being a moſt faithfull expoſitor of this miſterie. The Cup of bleſſing which we bleſſe, is it not the Communion of the blood of Chriſt? The bread which we breake, is it not the Communion of the bodie of Christ?
               1. Cor. 10. 16.
            
            Me thinkes (honorable Ladies) theſe words ſhould reſolue you, that Chriſt hath compriſed nothing elſe vnder theſe ſignes and elements of bread and wine, but what was behoouefull for the faithfull communicants, to whom the plaine ſignification

directeth it ſelfe, and whereof true faith dooth make them partakers, to vnice themſelues ſpiritually (with a meruailous efficacy) into the glorious body of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, to participate (in the end) of all his benefits, and deriue from him life and immortality.
            
               The ſumme of our Chriſtian doctrin and beliefe In theſe fewe words, vertuous Ladies, you may behold both what we teach and beleeue, that our feeding on Chriſt, is by faith onely, that is: in beleeuing the words of our Sauiour, in the vſe of the Sacrament; wherby we are drawne much neerer to him, and more ſtricktly vnited and incorporated (euen by the incomprehenſible vertue of his ſpirit,) to communicate and partake of all the benefits of his death, and to be renewed by him, and nouriſhed vnto euerlaſting life: vntill ſuch time, as he ſhall put vs into full poſſesſion, that is, at the departure of our ſoules from this world, and when our bodyes ſhall ariſe againe, at the day of our generall reſurrection.
            
               The expected benefit of the Sacrament. This is the fruit which we make account of, and are perſwaded to gather out of this Sacrament, and wherevnto faith ſerues vs as the onely inſtrument: Euen as with hand, eyes, and mouth, to beholde, take, and eate Ieſus Chriſt, without any need of his forſaking the heauens, or of his reall appearance vnder the formes of bread and wine, and ſo to communicate himſelfe vnto vs. Wherefore, to go and adore the ſigne, as if the ſigne onely were Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe: Or that hee ſhould deſcend

downe from heauen, and be newely formed; for one of theſe twoo muſt needs enſue by their tranſubſtantiation, which we mayntaine to be flat Idolatry.
            
               How we doe adore Chriſt in the Sacrament. Neuertheleſſe, we are taught in Scripture, that Ieſus Chriſt ought to be adored in the Sacrament, and we doe dayly and religiouſly worſhippe him: as being moſt eſpecially preſent in the holy action, euen in our ſpirits and faith, to vnite vs vnto him, and to impart his blesſings to vs; when the Supper is celebrated according to his inſtitution, and wee endeuour to haue it ſo ſtil continued and miniſtred among vs. But the manner of our worſhippe and adoration, is, in hauing our ſoules eleuated vp to heauen, and thither true faith is our onely conduct, there to behold him as our ſoueraigne aſſurance. We looke not for him in the naked elemētsWe honour god in bread and wine, as being his bleſſings beſtowed vpon vs. of bread and wine: for there we haue no commandement to honour him, but wee rather chooſe to worſhip him according as we ought, and that is in ſpirit and truth.
            Iudge now good Madames, where reaſon abydeth moſt, on your ſide, or ours, and whether your Prieſts commit not manifeſt Idolatry in their actions: when they receiue and admit the people to the communion of a Sacrament, which neuer was ordained by Ieſus Chriſt. May not wee then well and truely ſay, that they haue no communion at all, but what is of their owne inuentions? And that which they carry about the ſtreets, going in a ſolemne

               The Prieſt carries their Sacrament about the ſtreet. Proceſsion, is but a round Cake, being cloſed vp in a Boxe, or Pixe▪ which they cauſe to be adored with great veneration.
            It remaineth now, that wee come to the third propertie, which I haue obſerued in the Maſſe,The third propertie of the Maſſe to wit, Sacriledge: which already hath beene ſufficiently diſcourſed in our former proceeding, and yet we will note a fewe obſeruations more. This holy and diuine Sacrament, was inſtituted to make a Communion of the faithfull, in the body and bloud of our bleſſed Lord, and by celebrating it commonly, in remembrance of his death and paſsion. But Noble Ladyes, your Prieſts doe conuertThe Priests rob and deceiue the people. all to a contrary end, not onely in that which they doe in the ſacrifice; but in meere robbery and ſtealth beſide. For they take from the people, the Communion in chiefe, yea, that which is the principall fruite of this Sacrament, reſtraining it to the Prieſts onely: And the people there preſent, are made no more but ſilly ſpectatours, of that which the Prieſt doth alone by himſelfe, without knowing, or vnderſtanding what hee ſaith or doth.
            
               The Priests anſwere for themſelues. I know you will anſwere me, as (God forgiue me for it) I my ſelfe haue often done, that the prieſt, beeing the publike Miniſter, doth communicate in the names and behalfes, of all that are preſent at his Maſſe. Why then let me (faire Ladyes) mooue this queſtion: Where is any ſuch commandement throughout the whole booke of God, that wee

ſhould ſee the Prieſt to haue one Supper for himſelfe firſt, &amp; then at his leaſure, to communicate another to vs? 
                  •
               urely, as we cannot liue by that whichA witty cō
                  pariſon of receiuing the Communion. another eateth, but of and by that which wee our ſelues doe eate: Euen ſo, as needfull is it for vs, that wee ſhould communicate in this holy and diuine Sacrament, to liue in the true life of Ieſus Chriſt, who hath giuen himſelfe therein to vs; Not that any other there ſhould receiue it for vs, but that wee ought and ſhould receiue it our ſelues, thereby to haue Chriſt make his dwelling in vs.
            
               We cannot be wiſer the our maiſter Christ. Alas, good Ladyes, let vs not ſeeke to bee wiſer then our Lord and Maiſter, for if wee doe, it is but in vaine. And well you know, that hee neuer ſaide; Behold the Priest or Miniſter of the Church, bee eateth and drinketh for you, and I haue ſo appointed it: But hee ſpake plainely, without any ſophiſtication, and ſaid: Take, eate, drinke you all of this. And after him, his faithfull Seruant Saint Paul, writing to the children (by adoption) among the Corinthians, ſaid: Wee are many partakers of one and the ſame bread. And1. Cor. 10. 17. againe, Let euery man eate of this bread, and drinke of this cup. The counterſaite pretence then, which1. Cor. 11. 28. they doe alleadge, can no way couer or maske their ſacriledge: becauſe the commaundement is preciſely to all faithfull people, to take, eate, and drincke in this holy Supper.
            
               Chryſoſt. Hom. 18. ſuper cap. 8 2. Cor. 
               And Saint Chryſoſtome hath ſpoken very well to this purpoſe. Wee are no longer (ſaith hee) vnder the olde Law, where the Priest did eate his portion, and the

people had the reſt. But here, one body is giuen to all, and likewiſe one cup: And what ſoeuer is in the Eucharist Sacrament, is common as well to the people as the Prieſt.
            And, gratious Ladyes, deſire them but to ſatisfie you in this one particular poynt, namely, that if they beleeue, or giue any credit to the Canons of their owne Popes, they cannot then but confeſſeThe Popes Canons doe cōfeſſe their ſacriledge. and acknowledge their ſacriledge, for theſe bee their owne words: All they that are preſent at the Maſſe, and communicate not, confeſse themſelues to bee excommunicated. For their Canons further ſay, That
               Can. peracta de conſecra
                     •
                  diſt. 2 
               the conſecration being ended, all are to communicate, or elſe they are depriued of entring into the Church. For ſo did the Apoſtles ſet downe the ordinance, and wee hold the ſame in the holy Romaine Church.
            
            Moreouer, in the Canons that beare the title, By
               Can. omnes fideles de conſecrat. Diſt. 1. 
               the Apoſtles, it is thus ordained. That all they, which continue in the Church to the end of Moſse, and doe not receiue the Sacrament: ought to be corrected as perturbers and diſquieters of the Church. According to that which was ordained in the Counſell of Antioche; That all they which entred into the Church, ſhould behaue themſelues well, and heare the Sermon; and if they abſtained from the Sacrament: they ought to bee excommunicated, vntill they had bin ſufficiently chaſtiſed
               Chryſoſt. in Hom 3. 
               for that vice. And therefore Saint Chriſostome, in his Homilies vpon the Epiſtle of Saint Paul to the Epheſians, doth reproue them very ſharpely, that in his time would be preſent in the aſſembly at the Communion,

and yet not communicate. What ſay youNone ſuffered to communicate, but the prieſt onely. to this, ſweete Ladyes, when you ſee how many are preſent with your ſelues, at their daily Maſſes, and yet none of you are ſuffered to communicate, but the Prieſt himſelfe onely?
            Beſides all this, the prayers which they yet vſe to ſay in their Maſſe, do likewiſe very ſufficiently conuince them: for when the Church retained her wonted puritie, the people were then receiued to the Communion, and behold what their prayers then contained, and yet doe.
            
               Prayers in their maſſe, making againſt themſèlues. Lord thou haſt filled and ſatisfied thy familie, with thy holy giftes, to wit, the Sacrament. And another ſpeaks thus. We being filled and ſatisfied with the ſacrifice of thy pretious body &amp; moſt holy bloud, &amp;c. And another. We pray thee lord, that theſe things may be carryed by the hands of thy holy▪ Angell, vnto thy high Altar, (ſpeaking of the oblations of the faithfull, in receiuing the bread and wine vſed in the Sacrament) To the end, that all others as well as wee, that ſhall receiue the participation of the Altar, in the bleſſed body, and holy bloud of thy Sonne, may be filled with all happy benedictions.
            Theſe are the very true words (dere Ladies) vſed in their prayers, wherein if you will not credit me, I deſire you to reade them your ſelues, for your further ſatisfaction. And doubtleſſe, they would neuer haue ſpoken in this manner, if the Prieſt onely had then communicated, as now a dayes you ſee he doth. Otherwiſe, it had beene to ſay one

               They ſay one thing, &amp; do another, meerely begutling the people▪
                thing, and performe the contrary, as you may perceiue hath happened ſince: for now they haue vtterly depriued the people of the Communion. Tell me then, I intreate yee, is it not a mockery of God and of the people, to tell them, that they are pertakers in thoſe giftes of the Altar, and yet (all the while) to giue them iuſtnothing at all?
            In like manner they haue prouided, that the people ſhall vnderſtand nothing that they ſay, forThey ſpeake to the people in a ſtrange language. they ſpeake to them in a ſtrange language: but this is moſt certaine, and I deſire you Siſter Ladyes, to obſerue it, that the prayers before mentioned, doe remaine yet in the Canon of their Maſſe, to condemne them of impudence, both before God and men. So that if a more learned iudgement, then my weake womans capacitie, ſhould ſearch into the originall of this euill: it would be found out (as indeed it is very likely) that their enioyning and conſtraining the people, to confeſſe and declare their ſinnes to the Prieſt, was purpoſely intended, before their admiſsion to receiue the Sacrament.
            
               God will haue vs confeſſe our ſins to him onely. And this doe they alſo, without any ordenance of God, who commaundeth vs, to confeſſe and declare our ſinnes to him, and require pardon▪ as hee promiſeth to giue the ſame to all that are truely repentant, aſſuring and certifying vs thereof, yea, ſealing it in our ſoules and conſciences, by his owne word in his Goſpell, when hee is preached vnto vs, and when we beleeue effectually; wherevpon, and in regard whereof, the myniſterie of the

Goſpell is thus tearmed by the Apoſtle: He hath giuen
               2. Cor. 5 18 
               vs the miniſtery of reconciliation.
            
            The people then finding the burden of ſinne to be very heauy, as indeed it is, were vainely perſwaded to make a particular numeration of their ſins,The peoples growing to number their ſinnes. to the Prieſt or miniſter of the Church: which growing to a liberty and licence by little and little, by ignorance and malice in their Paſtours, the courſe thereof was not cut off, as it ought to haue been. But yet the people then were thereby granted this benefite, that they might communicate in the Sacrament once a yeare, or twiſe, or thriſe for them of greateſt deuotion, but all the reſidue of the people, muſt leaue the Prieſt alone at the Altare, there to communicate by himſelfe.
            
               Where God is neglected, one ſinne begetteth another. And thus one errour grewe to beget another, when once they began to decline from the direct pathes of perfection, and ſince then, they haue made a cuſtome of aſſembling the people together (but not inuiting them to the Communion) onely to heare their Maſſes ſayd or ſung in diuers angles of their Temples, for which they are not aſhamed (and Ladyes I am ſure you know it perfectly) to demand a price or valuation for ech ſeuer all Maſſe, a thing moſt horrible, and the like neuer heard of. Thus the Communion of the Sacrament, is not onely violently taken from the people, but theThe Sacrament is now made no account of. Sacrament it ſelfe (by this meanes) is made no account of. For wheras both Prieſt and people ought to meete together in one place, there to heare together)

the declaration of his bitter death and paſſion, and to participate (in common) in the Sacrament of this vnion▪ O deere Ladyes, I cannot ſpeake it without teares, or you heare it without much hearts griefe, if you were as you ſhould bee; That that diuine place, I ſay, ſhould now bee become a meere faire or maket▪ to traffique and merchandiſe thoſe ſacred bleſsings, which God out of his owne bountie made a liberail gift of, and freely beſtowed vpon all his faithfull ſeruaunts, to their ſingular comforte and endleſſe conſolation.
            
               Another ſacriledge cō
                  mitted in the Maſſe. But not to wander too farre from mine intended purpoſe, I come now to another moſt manifeſt ſacriledge, committed likewiſe in the Maſſe, to wit, that in thoſe Maſſes, where they doe admit the people to the Communion, eyther at the feaſt of Eaſter, or when they command a generall communicating: They then defraud the people of one part of the Sacrament, namely, the Cup. Oh what an audacious inſolence is this? Ieſus Chriſt diſtributed the wine, as well as the bread, when hee made his Supper with his Apoſtles, and ſpake hee not to make publike notice thereof, when giuing them the Cup, hee ſaid: Drinke you all of this? And after him, the Apoſtle left the very ſame inſtruction,1. Cor. 11. 28. to the Church of Corinth. Let eoh man (ſaith hee) prooue and examine himſelfe; and ſo let him eate of this Bread, and drinke of this Cup.
            
            But your Romaine diſciples, vnder the ſhaddow

of ſome ſuppoſed inconueniences, (imagined onely by themſelues, as if they would ſeeme to bee wiſer than the Maiſter) haue ordayned, that the people ſhall communicate but vnder one kind, and that is of the bread only. Is not this an enormous ſacriledge,They ſunder what God hath ioyned together. to ſeparate them a ſunder which God hath ioyned together, yea, and by his own expreſſe inſtitution? But let them be well aſſured, that the Authoures and fauourers of a crime ſo haynous, ſhall one daye yeeld a moſt ſtrickt account therefore.
            
               Concomitā
                  cy, their co
                     •
                  
                  ned excuſe▪
                True it is, that they alleadge their Concomitancy, in excuſe of this matter, (a woord expreſly forged, whereby to maintaine their ſacriledge) and herein they ſeeme to auouch, that the bloud keeps company with the body, and therefore is alwayes with the body. But when wee anſwere them, that Ieſus Chriſt knewe this Concomitancy as well as they: and yet notwithſtanding, he did not forbeare, to diſtribute both the ſignes of Wine and Bread; what reply they then? Why then they further inferre in anſwere (which indeed can carry it ſelfe for no anſwere at all)The bloud ſeparated from the bodie. It was Ieſus Chriſts will, that in his Supper wee ſhould conſider his bloud ſeparate, or apart from his bodye, and that wee ſhould repreſent before our eyes his death, euen as his blood was ſpilt and ſhed: And therefore in giuing the Cuppe, he ſayth: Drinke you all of this; For this is my bloude of the newe Teſtament, which is ſhed for many, for the remisſion of ſinnes.
               
                  Matth. 26. 27. 28.
            
            
               
Now, ſuch Concomitance of the body, and ofThe contrariety of concomitancy. the bloud, cannot agree or conſent with the death of Ieſus Chriſt (becauſe, to bee both in the body, &amp; to bee ſhed out of the body, are contrary things) wherfore, it neceſſarily enſueth, that that can haue no place in the Sacrament, which bringeth vs directly to the confideration of the death of Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; guides vs not to the effuſion of his bloud. It behooueth then, that wee haue the effuſion or ſtreaming forth of his precious bloud, euen as if it were preſent before our eyes, if wee would celebrate the Sacrament according as Ieſus Chriſt did ordaine it, becauſe (aboue all) it doth moſt aſſure vs in the Sacrament, that our ſinnes are forgiuen vs in his bloud, which is our cleanſing and1. Iohn. 1. 7 waſhing. But if theſe reaſons may gaine no place with you, faire Ladyes, nor them that are bothTraditions are their only foundatiō. your aduerſaries and ours, who (for the moſt part) build onely vpon traditions: At leaſt yet, will them to allow the Canons of their Popes, which doe manifeſtly condemne them in this poynt▪ and for a preſident, behold what is ſaid in one of the CanonsCan. Competimus de conſecrat. Diſt▪ 2. of the Pope Gelaſius: Wee haue vnderſtood, that there are ſome, who taking only a portion of the bleſſed body, do abſtaine from the Cup of his precious bloud. And becauſe it is not knowne, vpon what ſuperſtition they doe this: we will that they ſhall receiue the Sacraments together, or that they abſtaine and bee barde wholy from them both. For diuiſion or ſeparation in ſo ſanctified a miſterie, cannot be committed without very great Sacriledge.
            
            
               
Another Canon ſpeaketh thus. You are with vs
               Can. Quia. &amp; Can. In Coena de conſecrat▪ Diſt. 1. Can. Sacerdotes. 1. qu. 1. 
               in the Challice, Wee take this altogether, wee doe drink together, for we live together. And another. The prieſls which ſerue at the Euchariſt, ſhall distribute the bloud of our Lord to the people there, (for ſo he calleth the Sacrament of the bloud.) Whether can they now betake themſelues, to ſeeke for purgation of ſacriledge, being thus therein condemned by their owne Popes?
            Now honourable and renowned Ladyes, by theſe groſſe and moſt abſurde abuſes, which I haue beene ſo bold as to lay open to you, in this Popiſh kinde of ſeruice, called the Maſſe, filled full with notorious blaſphemies, Idolatries, and ſacriledges, as I haue in ſome weake meaſure ſhewen vnto you, and in the order as they are rancked: you may gueſſe what a many more there are beſide, which would aske a larger repetition, then this poore Epiſtle of mine at this time can permit mee. Let me put the caſe to your owne iudgement,She referreth this matter of the Maſſe, to the cenſure of the Ladyes thē
                  ſelues. whether the Maſſe may be thought to be any lawfull Communion in your Church, or no? Surely, were it but in regard of theſe alleaged abuſes, (wher of there wants not ſtore beſides) me thinkes you ſhould abſtaine from partaking with ſuch abhominations: Conſidering, that in ſhaking hands with ſuch foule deformed ſinnes, you pollute your ſoules with all impieties, and by your publike profeſsion of them, you conſent and adhere to all their blaſphemies, albeit you are vtterly ignorant of

them. For heere they meete in a full crowde together,They partake with ſin, that ſeek not to auoid it. and to all of them, you cry your ſelues guilty, when you ſeeke no way to eſcape out of ſinfull Sodome, though the flames flye daily and flaſhe into your faces.
            And I am well aſſured, that ſome of you are of my minde, in many of theſe recited abuſes concerning the Maſſe, though (as I haue done) you will not yet openly expreſſe it, yea, and haue in priuate confeſſed to mee, that your Prieſts of Romaine pollution, doe groſely ſinne in infinite ſuperſtitions, which they colour vnder cloudes of deuotion andThe Apiſh geſture and behauiour of the Prieſts. ſanctitie, vſing ſuch Apiſh carriage and geſticulations, both in the celebration of the Maſſe, and their friuolous preachings, as are no way conuenable with their profeſsion, that are to entreate on the miſteries of God. And yet in whatſoeuer they doe or ſay, both you, and the people doe ſolemnely aſsiſt them as ſpectatours onely, but no vnderſtanders, and ſuch are the greater part of the aſſemblie at Maſſe. And becauſe they ſhall not ſee into their iugling colluſions, they can find both their eares, eyes, and other ſences buſied, with muſicke, ſinging, and enſenſing, with diuers other geſtures, which deliuer ſome appearance of religious deuotion, onely thereby to beguile and retaine ſimpleHow highly God is diſhonored in their churches▪
                people. And where is all this done? but euen in the Church, where God is to bee worſhipped in ſpirit and truth, and where hee hath ordained the holie aſſemblie of his Seruants, to edifie &amp; nouriſh

all faithfull ſoules, in common and publike praying together, according as euerie one may well vnderſtand, by faithfull expounding and interpreting the word of god, concerning thoſe miſteries which he hath eſtabliſhed in his Church: To the end, that euerie faithfull man and woman, maye there receiue effectuall fruit, both for the guyding of their liues in chriſtian conuerſation, and conſolation of their ſoules here and in heauen.
            
               Of Gods vndefiled Church. Into which Church of God, ſwept cleane and purged from all corrupt pollutions, and reformed by the rules of his heauenly preſcriptions: Honorarable Ladyes, I haue at length found the happy entrance, where euery dilligent Paſtour &amp; Preacher, doe there paynefull and laborious endeuours, to expound &amp; deliuer Gods word purely to the people. And that they may eaſily vnderſtand what is ſayde vnto them, both for the edification of their faith, and further inſtruction in all piety, and wherof I myſelfe (to my no little comfort) haue foundHer deſire of their happy vnion in faith. a moſt plentifull encreaſe among Gods ſeruaunts, into whoſe fellowſhippe, I hartilie wiſh that you were all combined.
            Moreouer, among vs, there is not ſo much as one ſillable profered, either in publike praier, or explaining gods word, but it is heard, vnderſtood,The order obſerued in the reformed Churches. and moſt affectuouſly embraced. For nothing is here vttered, which hath not his firme fundation, on the expreſſe text of ſacred Scripture, or what is thence truelie and vnpartiallie deriued neceſſarilie

cohering and agreeing therewith: without any repugnancie to the Articles of the Apoſtles Creede, or the direct meaning of the Scriptures. For if any of our Paſtours ſhall preſume to doe otherwiſe, hee is grieuouſly cenſured, and reprooued according to good orders eſtabliſhed, for preſeruation of ſound doctrine, and preuention of intruding mens vaine imaginations.
            
               Of the Sacraments of Baptiſme, &amp; the Lords Supper reiecting the other fiue. As concerning the Sacraments, of Baptiſme and the Lords Supper (for Gods inſtitution allowing no more, wee leaue your other fiue, viz. Confirmation, Penance, Extreame vnction, Orders, and Matrimonie, to your Romaine Sinagogue, where they were firſt deuiſed.) And theſe other before named, I ſay, are adminiſtred in the ſame kinde and nature, as they were wholie receiued from our Lord and Maiſter: without addition of any thing to their wordes, or cutting off any part of their ordinance. And intelligence is publikely deliuered to the people, of the end, efficacie, and vtilitie of them, farre from thoſe vngodly courſes practiſed among you. Nor is there any other conſecration here vſed, but holy and deuout pravers, in the preſence of God and hisNo priuate whiſpering, as is vſed in the Maſſe. heanenly aſſembly: The Paſtor declaring openly, (and not in any muttering or coniuring manner) what is then done, and how it ſtands with the wordes and ordinaunce of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt; propoſing and deliuering the ſame ſo audibly, that

it may bee heard of the whole Congregation, and ſo conueniently in all poyntes applyed, that much godly benefite commeth thereby to the aſſembled ſoules at the Sacraments. Where Ieſus Chriſt doubtleſſe doth ſanctifie the Table, and the Bread and Wine there decently preſent, to make them the Sacraments of his body and bloud, when the forme is thus obſerued after his owne inſtitution.
            
               How the people are admitted to the communion: &amp; who are excluded. To this Communion of the Lords holie Supper, all the people preſent (after exhortation, to prepare their comming thither, in true repentance and firme faith in Gods promiſes) are freely and verie louingly admitted. And none are excluded from this heauenly Banquet, but ſuch as are notoriouſly knowne for prophane people, of wicked and vild life, or rebellious to all good orders and Diſcipline eſtabliſhed by authoritie, and the Reuerend Fathers of the Church, whoſe care and diligence for the good thereof, at all times and ſeaſons is very great and painefull. And (Noble Ladyes) the Bread and Wine, in all reuerend manner, as our Lord appoynted it, is round about diſtributed to euery aſsiſtant, without impayring the leaſt iote of the inſtitution. There is no requeſt made, that thoſe things mayFarre from that which is vſed in Poperie, bee carryed thence by an Angell, and preſented vpon the high Altar: Our ſoules doe aſſure vs, by a liuely faith, that Ieſus Chriſt is in heauen, ſitting at the glorious right hand of his Father,

and all the Communicants in our Chriſtian aſſembly, are ſo inſtructed and reſolued, and to heauen doe they eleuate both their eyes and minds, contemplating their Lord and Sauiour there, and hoping to partake of eternall life there with him, whereof the preſent action is a ſure pledge and earneſt pennie. Thus doe wee pronounce Chriſtes death and paſsion, thus doe wee acknowledge the effuſion and ſhedding of his bloude, whereof the Bread broken, and Wine deliuered in the Cuppe or Challice (for wee are not Ceremonious of eyther word, becauſe (in Gods feare) eyther of them is to vs indifferent) remaineth to vs as a perfect remembraunce, and the fruites thereof (wee hope) doe continue among vs, and ſo (with thankfulneſſe) we all receiue his benefits.
            And worthie Ladyes, becauſe (it may bee) you would gladly know, what other obſeruatiōs there are in Gods Church, which induced my conuerſion,Her further offer to the Ladies. and in time may draw others: As a verie young Scholler, ſcarcely yet well intred, I will ſet yee downe a briefe ſummarie, of ſo many, as my weake memorie, and the breuitie of time will permit me.
            
               No inuocation vpon ſaints, but on the euerliuing God, in trinitie of perſons. Here is no inuocation vpon any Saints, no, not vpon the bleſſed Virgin Marie: yet both of her, and all other Gods choſen Saintes, wee hold that reuerend eſtimation, which wee are commaunded to doe. The adoration and worſhip

here vſed, is to the onely euerliuing and eternall God, and according as hee hath manifeſted himſelfe in his word, to wit: the Father, the Sonne and the ſanctified Spirit, or holy Ghoſt. One onely and true God, in theſe three perſons or Hypostaſis, in whoſe name likewiſe all heere are baptiſed.
            
               No allowance of images, but that onely which God hath appointed. Here are no other Images admitted into our Temples, but that onely which our great God hath conſecrated to himſelſe, for his owne pecuculiar vſe, and to remaine for euer. And that is the Preaching of the Goſpell, with the true vſe of the Sacraments inſtituted by him: whereby wee diſcerne the nature of God, and his good will towards vs, more liuely and better figured in the whole Myſteryes of our Redemption, then they can bee deſcribed in a million of wodden or carued Images, or in any other matter whatſoeuer.
            
               No interceſſion, but to Chriſt only. Neyther is there recourſe made to any other interceſsion, for obtaining Gods fauour vnto vs, but to Ieſus Chriſtes interceſsion onely, hee being our alone Mediatour and Aduocate. And hee1. Iohn. 2. 2. is likewiſe the onely reconciliation for our ſinnes, and wee preſent none other but him to God, in all our prayers eyther priuate or publike. Nor is heere acknowledged any other purgation or Purgatorie, but onely the bloud of the ſelfe ſame Ieſus Chriſt: Thus are wee cleanſed, by vndoubted faith in him, accompanyed with true and vnfained

repentance, and that is to bee done in this life onely, which is the time both for beleeuing, and of well doing.
            
               No ſacrifice but Chriſt Ieſus onely. In like manner, heere is no confeſsion made of any other oblation, ſacrifice or ſatisfaction, wherby to aboliſh, deface and wipe out our ſinnes: but that alone, which Ieſus Chriſt made once for all, vpon the tree of his Croſſe to GOD his Father. Nor doe wee heere hold it expedient or needefull, that there ſhould bee any ſuperſtitious countenaunce, renewing or dayly reiteration thereof: In regarde, that hee neuer gaue any ſuch charge to any mortall man. For wee are aſſured, that his owne ſacrifice is daily freſh, and in full efficacy, to obtaine grace for vs, remiſsion of our ſinnes, and life euerlaſting. For though
                  Rom. 2. 3. hee dyed once for vs poore wretched ſinners, he liueth yet againe at this day, and for euer, and ſitteth at the right hand of God his father, to make continuall interceſsion for vs.
            
               What kinde of confeſſion is vſed in this Church As for the order of Confeſsion, which is here obſerued, and none other elſe acknowledged in this Church, it is in this manner. When wee aſſemble and meete together, wee make a publike and ſolemne confeſsion of our ſinnes to God: who giueth vs alſo true abſolution of them, by his h
                  •
               
               ly Goſpell, when wee (being heartily repentant) receiue by faith his vndoubted promiſes, according as they are davlie (for that purpoſe) preached and deliuered vnto vs, by the Paſtors and miniſters

of Gods Church, being congregated in our Eccleſiaſticall aſſemblyes.
            
               Of the meanes of our ſaluatiō. In breefe (honourable Ladyes) heere is neyther taught, or beleeued, any other meanes for our ſaluation; then that which God himſelfe hath reuealed in his holie woord. And that is, to embrace and receiue in a ſanctified fayth, Working by loue; the graces and mercies of God
                  Galat. 5. 6. offered and preſented to vs in Ieſus Chriſt, by the Goſpell: The preaching wereof wee receiue, and giue attention vnto with all reuerence, as beeing that onely doctryne, which is able to ſaue our ſoules. And wee are perſwaded, that to turne aſide (how little ſoeuer it bee) from Ieſus Chriſtes omniſufficient ſacrifice, to our owne workes, ſatisfactions, deſeruings, or the merites of Saints and their ſufferings, or any other meanes whatſoeuer, to confide, or put any hope at all therein of our ſaluation: were flatly to forſake the cheefe corner ſtone, and to build vpon another foundation, then God himſelfe hath layde. For there is not any other name under Heauen, whereby wee can or ſhall bee ſaued, but the alone name of Ieſus Chriſt. For bee was deliuered to death for our ſinnes, and is riſen agayne for our iustification;1. Cor. 3. 11 Act. 4. 12.
                there cannot bee (then) ſaluation in another. If this doctrine bee hereticall, as your Romaine Ieſuites, and Prieſts ſticke not to proclayme it: An eſpeciall note to be obſerued.they muſt then pronounce the holy Apoſtle Saint Paule to bee an hereticke;

Saint Peter and all the reſt of the Apoſtles, to bee Heretikes, who preached the very ſame, and haue left it ſo to vs in their owne writings, whereof God himſelfe will one day be the Iudge.
            
               Of the truth and ſincerity of this doctrine. Cenſure now, diſcreete and well-iudging Ladyes, if the ſingleneſſe, and pure ſimplicitie of this approoued doctrine, maintained poynt by poynt, and warranted by the word of God, (whereunto it hath alwayes ſubmitted it ſelfe, and dare auouch her true title in the face of any Counſell:) doe deſerue thoſe ſlaunders and calumniations, which the Diuell by his blaſphemous brood, doth daylie belch foorth againſt it. And in the other Scale of your vnpartiall opinion, (holding an euen hand to poyze the weight, and an vpright ſoule, to conceiue the worth of both rightly) conſider the now Romiſh Religion, the practiſes, blaſphemies, and abuſes therein committed, and then let God direct and order your verdict.
            
               The pompe and ceremonie of Poperie. For I will not ſo wrong the hope I haue of you, raſhly to forethink, that you will be ouerawed with pompe of Ceremonies, thunder cracks of curſes, the caſe and hollow cloſure for monſtrous impieties: Neyther that you will bee ſcrupulous of ſpirit, as to let the ſpacious ſpreading title of their Church, without any truth or equitie to warrant it, altogether ſway you in your opinion.The nature of the church of Chriſt. For the Church of Chriſt ſets not forth her ſelfe to ſale by the luſter and pompe of exteriour

ornament, or by antiquitie or ſuch like allegations; No, nor by continued ſucceſsion of Popes and Prelates, whereof you heare what daily boaſt they make. But her glory and triumph is, in the puritie of doctrine, which is as the onely ſoule of the Church, and in the ſincere adminiſtration of the Sacraments, all conſonant and agreeing, with the voyce of her great ſheepheard and Biſhop of our ſoules, our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. And hee faith;
                  Ioh. 10. 4. 5 
               That his ſheepe do know his voyce, and they will not liſten or follow a ſtranger. This (Ladyes) is the true touchſtone of iudgement, whereby to diſcerne Golde from corrupted mettall, to know the true Church from the falſe: And not by Croſſes by Miters, Cardinals, bonnets, or height of Steeples.
            That Reuerend and worthy Biſhop of Thouars, who hauing forſaken the Sinagogue of Sathans, and (by his great learning and induſtrious paines) diſcouered ſuch a hideous heape of abhominations, vſed and maintained in the church of Rome: hee, next vnto Gods good ſpirit (which was the principall and onely motiue) was the ſecondary meanes of my conuerſion, as (God haue the glory for it) hee hath preuailed with diuers otherA booke of much learning &amp; main importance, which likewiſe will bee very ſhortly publiſhed in Engliſh. Lords and Ladyes beſide, and in time may prooue to ſhake the proude Empyre of the Pope. His learned labours ſo lately printed, wherein hee opens all the pack of paradoxicall Poperie, againſt Bellarmine, and all the Romaine faction of Ieſuites, conuincing them by their owne arguments and writing:

I am bold (worthy Ladies) to ſend you with this Epiſtle. And where I comfarre too ſhort of ſuch ſufficiencie as in ſuch a cauſe as this is required: peruſe his paines for your further ſatisfaction, being printed in your owne natiue tongue for your better apprehenſion, and ſo plainely ſet downe, as it cannot but bee eaſily vnderſtood of you.
            Thus haue I, noble Ladyes, both briefely, and as the nature of an Epiſtle would permit me, declared the groſſe abſurdities and abuſes in the Maſſe, the blaſphemies, Idolatries, and ſacriledges therein committed, that God in his good time may open your eyes, and let you ſee the way out of that brutiſh Babylon. I haue alſo (in a meane meaſure) ſhewed you the order and gouernement of our reformed Church, as well for the Miniſterie and doctrine thereof, as alſo for the neere affinitie and true forme, which therein is continually vſed and obſerued, with the example of the chiefe Schoole-maiſter Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe, and confirmed by his bleſſed Apoſtles: As if it would pleaſe God to rancke you with vs, the truth ſhould make more manifeſt to you.
            
               Truth needs no ſecret corners. For heere is nothing done palliated, or in ſecret conſpiring, to betray poore peoples opinions, and deceiue their ſoules: All our actions are openly expoſed euen to the apparant view of God and men, yea, euen in all things, that concerne the order and policie of Gods▪Church. Heere, women

and the weakeſt capacities, may vnderſtand whatſoeuer is done or ſaid: for here is no ſtrange Language vſed among vs. And S. Paul ſaith: Strange
               1. Cor. 14. 22. 
               tongues are for a ſigne, not to them that beleeue, but vnto Infidels that beleeuenot.
            
            
               Her concluſion to the Ladyes. I confeſſe, honorable Ladyes▪ that my diſcourſe hath extended it ſelfe beyond the purpoſed limitation: but indeed, the merit of the ſubiect handled; may pleade my pardon one way, and the endeared affection I beare to you, with deſire of your conuerſion (for your ſoules ſauing health) I truſt will ſafely ſupport me the other way. If God haue choſen me as his meaneſt inſtrument, to worke but the very leaſt meaſure of your better inſtruction: his name haue the glory, and his powerfull word the deſerued praiſe, which carries much more weight and efficacy, then mens ſmootheſt eloquence, or the very ſubtilleſt arguments produced to the contrary: whether it bee of antiquitie, or vniuerſalitie, of Counſels, of Traditions, or whatſoeuer elſe. If now (this day) you will liſten to his voyce, and not harden your hearts; If you be not careleſſe of his gift, by me his vnworthy ſeruant offred vnto you; If you cloſe not vp your eyes, againſt the cleare light that ſhineth euery where; If you quench not the ſpirit, which God himſelfe hath kindled in you: All will redound to your endleſſe conſolation, and you bee renowmed to future poſterities. Feare therefore (deare Ladyes) this heauie threat of the diuine wiſdome.

                  
                  
                     Prou. 1. 24. 25. 26. 27. 
                  Becauſe I haue called, and you haue refuſed; I haue ſtretched out mine hand, and you would not regard; But haue deſpiſed all my counſell, and would none of my correction: I will laugh at your deſtruction, and mocke when your feare commeth. Then ſhall you call vpon mee, but I will not anſwere, they ſhall ſeeke me earely, but they ſhall not finde mee. &amp;c.
               
            
            
               From Thouars 
                  this 1. of Iune. 1608.
               
            
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

