
   
      
         
            A iournall, wherein is truely sette downe from day to day, what was doone, and worthy of noting in both the armies, from the last comming of the D. of Parma into Fraunce, vntill the eighteenth of May 1592, according to the French computation Wherevnto is added other newes from Genes, the which are confirmed by sondry letters of credite. Translated out of French by E. A.
         
         
            
               1592
            
         
         Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01162
            STC 11277.5
            ESTC S119978
            99855182
            99855182
            20657
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01162)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20657)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 711:18)
         
         
            
               
                  A iournall, wherein is truely sette downe from day to day, what was doone, and worthy of noting in both the armies, from the last comming of the D. of Parma into Fraunce, vntill the eighteenth of May 1592, according to the French computation Wherevnto is added other newes from Genes, the which are confirmed by sondry letters of credite. Translated out of French by E. A.
                  Aggas, Edward.
               
               [2], 21, [1] p.   
               
                  Printed by Iohn Wolfe, and are to bee solde at his shop, right ouer against the great South doore of Poules,
                  London :
                  1592.
               
               
                  E.A. = Edward Aggas.
                  Variant: has ".. from the comming.. Gens." in the title.
                  Formerly STC 14818.
                  Identified as STC 14818 on UMI microfilm.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               France --  History --  henry IV, 1589-1610 --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-02
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-02
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-02
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2007-02
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A Iournall, wherein is truely ſette
downe from day to day, what was doone, and
worthy of noting in both the Armies, from the
laſt comming of the D. of Parma into Fraunce,
vntill the eighteenth of May 1592. according to
the French computation.
            Wherevnto is added other newes from Genes,
the which are confirmed by ſondry
letters of credite.
            Tranſlated out of French by E. A.
            
               LONDON
Printed by Iohn Wolfe, and are to bee ſolde at
his ſhop, right ouer agai
                  •••
                the great
South doore of Poules,
1592
         
      
      
         
            
            
            A Iournall, wherein is ſet downe from day to day,
what was done in both the Armies, from the comming
of the Duke of Parma into France, vntill the
eighteenth of May 1592. according to the French
computation.
            
               THe Duke of Parma perceiuinge
himſelfe, notwithſtanding his
great and well prepared forces
aſſembled, namely the king his
maiſters power, conſiſting of
Spanyardes, Launceknights
Wallons, Italians, and Neapolitanes,
footemen: alſo his horſemen Wallons,
Flemminges, Italians, and Rutters: together
with the late Popes forces, conſiſting of Suitzers
and good nombers of Italians, on horſebacke and
on foote: likewiſe the aide of the Duke of Mayenne,
which was no ſmall nomber: vnable to force the
king to raiſe his ſieg from before Roan, determining
to practiſe the Spaniſh manner of Stratagemes,
vſed in the dayes of the late kinges Lewes the twelfe
and Fraunces the firſt, thereby to ſhonne the fury of
the French: retired out of the way into a place of
ſafety, there waitinge vntill their heat were ouer,
and all the French army in proceſſe of time, of it ſelf

                  •
               roken vp and ſcattered.
            To this end he ſ
                  •
               t a face, as if hee purpoſed to

beſiege S. Eſprit de Rue, a place lying beyond the Riuer
of Some, &amp; the rather at the requeſt of the Duke
of Aumale, and the inhabitantes of Abbeuille, and others
who found them ſelues greatly annoied therby:
ſtill lookinge for the departure of the kinges
French troupes, wherein he was no whit deceiued:
For the French, who for the moſt part ſerued vpon
their owne charges, did retire, as being perſwaded
that the Duke of Parma, conſidering hee was paſt
the Riuer of Some, meant onely to take his way into
the Low countries. There hee lay a whole moneth,
prouiding to plant his artillery before Rue, but vnderſtanding
that the king had no more remayning
with him but onely of French fiue hundred footemen,
and as many horſe, alſo that the reſt of his army,
conſiſting of ſtraungers, was ſcattered into ſeuerall
places, becauſe of the ſcituation of the towne
of Roan, which was enuironed with great Barricanes
&amp; valleis, whereby they could not paſſe from
one lodging to an other in leſſe then two houres: alſo
that ſome troupes of his forces were in the ſubvrbes
of S. Seuere, beyond the riuer of Seyne. The enemies
army, vpon the aduantages that their leaders
found themſelues to haue ouer the king, marched
toward Roan, and in foure dayes approched
within foure leagues thereof.
            Herevpon his Maieſty retired a league and a
halfe from Roan, drawing towardes Pont-del-Arch,
to a village named Gouy, there to aſſemble his forces,
and to receiue ſuch as he had ſommoned out of
the Ile of France, out of Picardy, and out of the gouernements
of Orleance, Chartres, and Normandy, attending
the ennemy notwithſtandinge in the ſame

place, with ſuch power as he had about him.
            The Duke of Parma and Mayenne, ſeing Roan ſet
at liberty, hauing tarried there about two dayes,
where the Spaniſh faction boaſted greatly that
they had remoued the king, whome they thought
certainely would paſſe the Riuer of Seyne, marched
thence towarde Caudebeck, a village lying downewarde
vppon the ſame Riuer, with full purpoſe to
take it.
            The fiue and twentieth day of Aprill, the king
vpon the arriuall of ſome French troupes, both of
horſemen and footemen, marched toward the enemy,
and lodged at Fountaine le Bourg, but by the way
he tooke three Caſtels, which the ennemy had before
ſeized vpon.
            The next day being the ſix and twentieth, the
Rendez-uous was at Freſnoy, and the army paſſed
on to Outeuille and there abouts, where the Dukes
of Montpenſier and Longueuille, with the Countie S.
Paul came in, with diuers other Lordes, ſome together
with them, others leading troupes a part.
            The ſeauen and twentieth day, the king vndertooke
to paſſe on to Iuetot, where the Dukes of Mayenne
and Guize were lodged, who were ſomewhat
brauely diſplaced, and more luſtely had beene, but
for certaine ditches that enuironed the groundes euery
way, whereby the Duke of Bouillon could not
paſſe as he would to backe the Baron of Byron, yet
were there ſome ſlaine and ſome taken, among the
reſt Blanque-Fort who is one of the ſaide Barons
traine, tooke young Chaſtre. Iuetot is not paſt one
league from Lauetot, where the Duke of Parma was
lodged, who was ſomewhat abaſhed, when he perceiued

the king ſo neere him with his army, &amp; hunting
after him, whereby finding himſelfe encloſed
betweene his Maieſtie and the Riuer of Seyne, hauing
beſides receyued a harquebuze ſhotte in hys
arm, at the ſiege of Caudebeck, which was not worth
the paines, and being in great neceſſitie of victuals,
he fortefied his lodging with trenches. After the
king had remained two dayes at Iuctot, on the laſt
of Aprill he drew neerer to the ennemy to a village
named Varicaruille and there abouts.
            The enemies purpoſed two hours before night
to ſet vppon the Engliſh, wherevpon the king returned
and ſent the Baron of Biron to conduct the
Engliſh, who were gone too farre out of their lodginges.
The ennemy came with ſome fourteene or
fiueteene hundred footemen: alſo in the fore-fronte
there were a nomber of horſe, beſides ſondry other
troupes that followed. The skirmiſh was hoate,
but in the end, coming to handy blowes, the Duke
of Parmaes horſemen gaue a charge, of whome there
were ſlaine ſixteene or ſeauenteene parſons of accompt,
euery one in veluet hoſen, beſides diuers others,
and fiue and twenty or thirty wounded.
            The Baron Biron, in the view of them al, ſtew
one of the principals, and Sir Roger Williams Coronell
of the Engliſh ſlew an other. At which tyme
they alſo tooke one Cornet, very well furniſhed
with all manner of weapons, and ſome that carried
money. This was a great diſgrace to their whole
power: as being done in the ſight of the reſt of their
army, which was allmoſt all in battaile aray, and
the Prince of Parma the Dukes ſonne had the repulſe.
            
               
The firſt of May the enemies army was betimes
in battaile aray in their fort and thereabout:
yet not without ſuſpect of ſome mening to diſlodge:
For there were paſſed ſome troupes both of horſe
and foote towardes the wayes, whereby they receiued
their victuals, namely toward Liſlebonne, Tankeruille,
Arfleur, Newhauen, Eeſcam, and Honflew, which
ſtandeth beyonde the Riuer, ſo that the ſame day
there were taken three or foure thouſand loaues, about
400. carriage horſes that were gone on a forraging,
and twenty faire horſes belonginge to the
artillery. There returned alſo many carriages
that came from the ſayde places loaden with victuall:
There were alſo taken ſome horſemen that
went foorth for to ſafeconduct them: ſo that the
loafe of bread that was worth but one ſouſe before,
was now ſould amonge them for twelue and fiueteene
ſouſes: and the pot of wine, the worſt for three
franckes, and that that was ſomewhat good was
ſould for foure.
            This firſt of May was the Feaſt of Iames and
Philip and it fell vpon a Friday, all which concurred
for the Spanyardes to lay the platformes of all
their enterpriſes and purpoſes: howbeit the king
tooke ſo good order in euery quarter, that we incurred
no inconuenience: but contrarywiſe the enemy
finding our troupes to bee (as they terme it)
frollicke, ſtood in greater doubt of being aſſaulted,
then in deſire to aſſaile.
            The ſecond day moſt of the enemies army ſtood
ſtill in battaile ray, parte of them paſſinge into a
wood, which lyeth betweene their Forte and the
kinges army, which was but fiue hundred paces

from one of their trenches, &amp; was enuironed with
a very deepe ditch, the trees ſtanding on both ſides
in manner of a hedge, ſo enterlaced that it was almoſt
vnacceſſible albeit there were none to defende
the ſame.
            The third day the king with his chiefeſt Captaines,
went to take a view of the head of the enemies
army, to the end there to endeuour to woorke
ſome effect. He found that the enemy had made fiue
rauelinges about the ſaid wood, which flancked
the champion whereby he was to goe to the head:
alſo that he had lodged two thouſande footemen in
certaine houſes that ſtood as in a villadge vnder
the ſide thereof, compaſſed with the ſame ditches
yet in ſome place ther were three ditches one with
in an other that deuided the fieldes from the ſayd
head, which was with in the reach of a ſmal coluering
on the one ſide of the Switzers lodgings, ſo that
planting the Canon he might haue ſtrooke into ſome
of our lodginges, namely into the Engliſhmens. Neuer
the leſſe the king, hauing taken counſaile in the
field, reſolued to ſeaze vpon the ſaid wood together
with the vilage therein comprehended, which was
one of their chiefeſt lodginges, and to that effect appointed
all his troopes to be in place before day in
battaile array, ſo to giue the aſſault at the breake of
daye: but the darkneſſe of the night was in parte
the cauſe that ſome that were lodged farre of were
not ſo dilligent but that it was almoſt eight of the
clocke before they arryued in eſtate to perfourme
the purpoſed effect. Neither could this aſſembly be
ſo ſecrete, but that the enemie did ſome what perceiue
it, which cauſed him to beleue that it was neuer

gathered with out intent to enterprize ſome
matter whatſoeuer: they for their parts put them
ſelues in battail, vſing all diligence to fortify &amp; raiſe
the ſaid rauelings, ſhoting of two canons to aduertize
all their troupes, where vpon ſome were of
opinion to referre the enterpriſe to an other time.
But the king finding al his troupes full of courage
and heat, reſolued to aſſault them in ſundry places.
On the one ſide the Engliſh and Wallons and the
reſt to ſupport thē: on an other ſide the French &amp; the
lance knights to ſupport them. The firſt, who were
as aduenturers, ſtrok in ſo valeantly that they entred
the trenches with hard ſight, rather with the
pike and ſworde, then with the harquebuze, and
forced the enemy out of the ſaid wood and village,
albeit they were two thouſād men, &amp; ſome Spaniſh
Captaines that were come at the bruite of the aſſembly
of our forces.
            There were left dead vpon the place aboue three
hundred men, whereof ſome were Spaniards and
ſome Wallons: Amongſt them were ſix or ſeauen
Captaines, and the Liefetenant Coronell of la Verlette
and he himſelfe wounded, without any loſſe of
ours, except two or three ſlaine, and ſeauen or eight
hurt.
            The Lord Baron Biron aduaunced himſelfe according
to his Office of Marſhall Generall of the
field, whereby hee beheld the countenance and retraict
of the enemies, and aduertiſed the king therof,
who ſent him fifty horſe, led by the Lord of Maligni,
Vidam of Chartres. Vpon their comming he purſued
them that fledde, euen vntill they came within
fifty paces of their firſt entrenchment, where their

army ſtood in battaile ray. Here were alſo ſlaine betweene
ſix and ſeauen ſcore, with the loſſe of onely
one of ours, who paſſed ſo farre that he was ſlayne
at the foote of the trench. So likewiſe were there
ſome horſes ſlaine and ſome hurt: yea there were
ſome ſuch enemies ſlaine as offered tenne, ſix, and
foure thouſand crownes.
            The king ſtood about eight houres offering the
battaile, hauing to that end aduaunced his Switzers,
horſemen and artillery. The enemies trenches
were raiſed very high in reſpect as they were
at the beginning in the field, and they ſomewhat
annoyed vs with their artillery: but the king placed
his forces els where, in place where the Canon
could not hurt.
            His Maieſty perceiuing after ſo long expectation,
and the night comming on, that the enemies
made no countenaunce to come foorth of their Fort,
returned euery man to his lodginge, vntill further
occaſion to do more, hauing by this effect with their
great hurt, giuen the enemies to know that our
footmen are as good or better then theirs, at the
coſt of the Spaniſh brauery and preſumption, who
can now graunt that the footemen the which the
king now hath are very good: for of his horſemen
they make no doubt, conſidering the many proufes
that they haue had.
            The next day being the fifth of May, about
eleuen of the clock, ther came other aduice, that the
ennemie diſlodged from their Forte, whereof grew
ſondry opinions, the greateſt importing that they
meant ſecreately to ſteale away to Roan, and from
thence to the Forreſt of Andely, which is but three

leagues thence leauing in Roan their munition and
moſt heauieſt baggage, and truly had they ben able
ſo to haue done and to gotten ſixe or ſeauen houres
before hand whereby to haue 
                  〈◊〉
                into the 
                  〈◊〉
               ,
with that aduantadge they might eaſily haue ſent
their horſmen and baggage before, and lefte their
footmen vpon the tayl, whome our horſemen could
not haue broken or fought withal in the forreſt neither
could our footmen haue marched in time to
ouertake theirs, but that afterward through this
forreſt they might haue retired euen to New caſtel or
toward Beauuais.
            
            The king here vpon ſent out ſome to vew the enemie,
who returned anſweare that they diſlodged,
then in the morning he ſent more &amp; ſtronger troops,
who gaue him to wit that the enemies were departed
ouer night &amp; that they were broken: here vpon
his Maieſtie reſolued to bring his maine battayle
toward Clayre, ſo to winne the fore part of the ſaid
forreſt, whiles himſelfe with his horſmen folowed
the enemie in the taile to the end truly to learne the
order of their march, what way they toke, &amp; what
iourneys they might be able to make: leauing the
Lord Marſhall Biron to conduct the armie &amp; to cauſe
it to march in order. His maieſtie had not marched
farre but he perceiued that he had not had certaine
aduice, for within halfe a league of the fort where
the enemy was lodged, he found them in battail array,
&amp; for a token that they went not ſcatering they
diſcharged ſome canons. But had he bene truly aduertized,
he would ſurely haue brought his army,
&amp; ſo vndoubtedly we had had battaile, &amp; that with
aduantage, or at the leaſt in equal ballance, which

is the thinge that the king chiefly deſireth.
The king ſeyng how the caſe ſtood, ſent word to
marſhall Biron to ſtay the army where it was, alſo
to conſider how to lodge, like wiſe ſoon after heſent
the Lord Baron of Biron ſonne to the ſaide Marſhall
to appoint the ſeate, which hee dyd at Iuetot,
twoo leagues from the ennemies campe, who began
allready to fortefie, notwithſtanding the ſtrong
ſcituation thereof, which was vpon a hill betwene
two valleis, neither was there any acceſſe vnto it,
but at one onely heade, and that very difficulte, as
being flancked with wood and vallies, beſides that
attending vntill the trenches were made, they had
placed at the ſaide heade three rowes of carriages,
whereof they had great plenty.
            The king ſeeing his army too farre off, namely
that his Rutters, were lodged three leagues off,
and diuers of his troupes ſo farre away, that they
could not come together vntill it were very late, determined
to retire vntill the nexte morninge, and
then to ſee whether hee coulde woorke any good
effect.
            The ſeauenth day of the ſaide moneth of May,
the king departed with ſome of his forces, to lodge
at a place called Saint Katerines, from whence hee
might plainely diſcouer the ennemies Campe, but
perceyuing that hee was firſt to paſſe twoo greate
vallies hee returned to the former lodging.
            The eight day, ſome went to diſcouer the ennemies
army, who found them within a great trench
which they had augmented.
            The ninth day, the king tooke counſaile to aſſaile
the ennemies horſemen, who were lodged along

a valley, for the commodity of water, and
in three villages beneath their army: Herevppon
hee gaue charge to Baron Biron to take
hys Regimente, wherein were ſixe hundred
French footemen, one hundred Engliſh pikes,
and one hundred Muſquettiers, and as many
Wallons, likewiſe the Launce knights, to
ſeiſe vppon this lodging. Hee alſo appoynted
that the Lorde Marſhall de Aumont, ſhoulde
marche after wyth hys Regimente, alſo that
when they were neere the execution, he ſhould
take on to the lefte hande, ſo to keepe that ſide
from hinderinge the ſame, as alſo to ſette a fa
                  ••
               ,
as if hee would fighte with ſuch as ſhould gather
together, namely wyth the laſte villages,
or elſe wyth the whole army.
            The Duke of Bouillon was likewiſe expreſly
appointed wyth hys Regimente to take
on to the righte hande, towarde the ennemies
Campe, where hee gotte vp aboue on to the top
of the valley, and marched towarde the ennemies
trenches within the volley of a ſmall culuering,
whereby hee ſtopped the ennemies from
comming foorth of their Campe to ſuccour thoſe
lodginges. The Lord Marſhall Biron marched
after with eight hundred French, two hundred
footemen Engliſh and Wallons, moſt of
them pikes, and then his owne Regiment.
            Being come to the firſt village hee ſlayed
and ſent foure hundred hargabuziers into the
wood on to the right hand, to ſupport the Duke
of Bouillon, if neede ſhould require, alſo two hundred

to his ſonne the Lord Bar
                  ••
                of Biron. The
kinge remained on the toppe of the Hill, to the
ende to make heade againſt the army, in caſe it
ſhould paſſe out at the ende or beginninge of the
valley with his Cornet, his Regiment, and the
Regiments of the Dukes of Montpenſier and Longueuille,
the counties of Saint Paul and Do. for it
was to bee feared that the ennemy would paſſe
that waye to hinder and diſturbe the execution
aforeſaid.
            The fight was ſore, for ye are to note, that
where commonly men ſet vppon lodginges by
night, the king would haue this done by day, to
the ende that if the ennemy ſhoulde offer any attempt,
he might bee ſeene comminge, and to bee
fought withall.
            Beſides of the kinges troupes ſome tarried
ouer long: others ſhewed themſelues in the
view of the ennemies campe, ſo that when the
ſayd Lord Baron drew neare the lodgings, he
found doble ward of Rutters and launces, and
almoſt all the troopes taking horſe, being in
nomber betwene thirtie &amp; fortie cornets, ſeuen
companies of men of armes of the ordinances,
and the Rutters.
            The ſaid Lord Baron had but few men,
in reſpect that the paſſage was narrow: albert
in deede the Lord great Maiſter of the horſe
came vnto him with ſome fiueteene or twenty of
the kinges Cornet, and the County of Chaſteau-Roux
Marſhall de Auments eldeſt ſonne, accompanied
with ſome gentlemen was alſo with the

ſaid Lord Baron.
            The ſayd Lord Ba
                  ••
               n ſeeing ſome threeſcore
and tenne or foureſcore Rutters comming
to charge vpon him, turned to them, albeit but
meanely accompanied, in reſpecte that parte of
his company had taken an other way, by reaſon
of a hedge, where were fiue and thirty men. For
he conſidered that if he ſhould retire from before
this troupe, it mighte bree
                  •
               e ſome daunger of
feare, to the reſt of thoſe that came behinde, and
therefore he reſolued to ſet vpon them. There
followed ſome ſtore of Piſtoll ſhotte and handye
blowes, wherein the ſayd Rutters were ouerthrowne,
and ſo he entred the village, where he
found certaine Spanyardes that ſtoode at defence,
and therevpon the ſayd Lord Baron ſtaid
for hys Harguebuziers, to diſtodge them from
the hedges and ditches, where the County Chaſteau-Roux
was hurte on the legge, which was
great pittie, in reſpect hee was both valiant and
forward.
            Thoſe that parted from the ſaid Lord Baron,
did report that they met with a troope of
lancers whom they withſtod, to the end ſo to fauour
the excecution, which was great both in
ſlaine, wounded, and priſoners: as alſo was the
ſpoyle and loſſe. For the ennemyes doe giue out
that they loſt foure hundred horſe of ſeruice and
ſixtene hundred other, a great deale of baggage
and moueables, and much ſiluer in veſſel and
coyne.
            There were ſundrye conflicts, and the Lord

Baron of Biron fought three or foure times againſt
both horſmen and footemen, who, gathered
together both in the lodginges and among the
hedges and ditches, yet in the end they were all
broken, &amp; the rather for that the Lord Marſhall
de Aumont put ſome of the ſpaniſh troops in feare,
as alſo thoſe that gathered again together.
The duke of Bouillon was forſed to put ſelfe vnder
couuert from the ennemyes artilery.
            The king alſo ſent a great troope of horſe
toward the enimies campe or trenches, to hold
them ſtill in feare that the ſaid troup wold enter
theyr Campe, whileſt the reſt of the army aſſaulted
the trenches.
            This execution perfourmed, the Lord Baron
began to cauſe thoſe whome he brought, to
retire, but in great diſorder by reaſon of their
booty, and thoſe two hundred freſh harguebuziers,
whome the Lord Marſhall had ſent him,
ſtoode them in good ſtead: When moſt of hys
troupes were on their way, himſelfe began alſo
to retire toward the right hande, at which tyme
the Duke of Bouillon beganne to diſcend into the
valley, being ſeconded by the ſmall ſhotte that
was ſent into the wood and hedges.
            All theſe troupes aforeſaid thus paſſed, the
Lord Marſhall Biron, ſounded the retreat, with
his booty, and the ennemies ſette a face as they
would haue followed in the taile, but they were
ſo well wellcommed, that ſondry of them were
ſlayne and hurte: And heere came his ſonne the
Lord Baron vnto him, wyth ſondry men of acaccompt

that were with him. This was perfourmed
thus honourably for the execution of
the kinges purpoſe to the ennemies great loſſe
as is aforeſayde: and hys Maieſty was alſo
come downe to ſee how thinges wente, from
whence hee commaunded whatſoeuer was requiſite.
            The eleuenth day of May, the king was
aduertiſed, that the enemy had brought a great
many of boates, which he cauſed to bee faſtened
by two and two, making thereof ſmall bridges
to paſſe ouer: and that they tranſported vppon
each bridge, ſome ſixty horſe with many footemen
and ſome baggage in the bottome, ſo to get
ouer the Riuer of Seyne. A matter ſcarſe to bee
imagined. Alſo that as for forrage, there came
great plenty a long the way towarde Liſlebonne,
and along the riuer, likewiſe that they had ſome
ſtore comming a longe from towarde Newhauen,
Harfleur, Feſcam, &amp;c.
            Herevpon the king determined to follow
their army, to the ende to cutte of their victuals
and forrage, alſo to aſſault Caudebeck, or compell
the ennemies to battaile. The which day hee
departed from Iuetot, and came to lodge in a village
called Lauetot.
            
            The twelfth day hee wente to take the view
of Caudebeck, where he found that they had made
a Fort at halfe the mountaine, wherein were a
good nomber of people, &amp; likewiſe in the towne,
But his Maieſty had brought but few troupes,
and therfore he referred al to the next day, being

the thirteenth. Likewiſe hee might beholde the
boates loaden with menne horſe, and baggage,
paſſing ouer the Riuer with all diligence.
            The ſame day hee marched with part of his
army and ſome artilery, and at the coming of
our footmen the enimies began to retire to a
place of execution where they made as it were a
litle fort, but paſſing forward they habandoned
their fort, which was at the mid mountain, neither
could we any lenger perceaue the number
of boats at the kay: But the moſt of them marched
toward Roan, and as for their forces they
wer al alredy paſſed ouer the riuer ſauing thoſe
that marched as it is aforſaid toward Roan and
foure hundred of the towne gariſon.
            Hard by the other ſide of the riuer the enimies
had before made a fort for the ſafetie of the
paſſage, where they had 7. peeces of ordinance,
which being taken forth of their boates they
left behinde them. In the forte had they lefte
ſome men, alſo in a ſmale vilage thereby ſome
both horſmen and footmen, who ſet themſelues
in battail aray without the daunger of the canon,
which the kinge cauſed to be often times
diſcharged againſt thoſe that were in the forte
and about the peces. Herevpon the enimies ſent
three teemes of horſe to draw away the ſaid
pieces againſt the which we ſhot ſundrie times
and ſlew ſome of theit horſes, which notwithſtanding,
they drew them away one after another.
            The king lefte certaine French in the aforenamed

fort aboue the towne, with ſome
Wallons and Engliſh, alſo ſome artillery vpon
the toppe of the mountayne and ther he lodged
the Suitzers. Likewiſe ſome of the ſhippes approched
and ſhot off, howbeit but few.
            The fourteenth day of May, the king cauſed
his company to ſhoote into the towne: they
that were within, made a brag, wherevpon the
king ſent them word, that he would hang them
all: But towarde eueninge they craued parley,
and ſo the king ſent the Lord Baron of Byron, to
make the compoſition.
            There came foorth of the towne of Caudebeck
foure hundred men, whereof two hundred were
Spanyardes, whoſe compoſition was the eaſier,
to the ende they mighte haue no cauſe of delaies
or longer ſtay. Becauſe it is hard to plant
a ſiege, alſo that the water ſtood in many partes
of the ditch, and could not be voyded.
            There were alſo threeſcore and tenne artillery
horſes, that coulde not paſſe away, and
ſome mulets, namely the Prince of Parmaes
owne. Beſides the king determined to departe
and to follow the ennemy, and therefore tooke
his way to Pont-del-Arch there to paſſe ouer the
Riuer of Seyne, to keepe the ennemy from temporiſing
on the other ſide of the Riuer, and to force
him to ſome action.
            The king being on the way to Pont-del-Arch
had aduice that the enimies horſmen that could
not paſſe at Caudebeck but tooke to Roan, had
paſſed the Riuer at Roan, and ſo marched wholy

toward Paris, wherevpon he reſolued with diligence
to make way to learne the trueth, where
the ennemy would become. He left his French
horſemen, with the Duke of Montpenſier to proceede
forward, alſo his footemen with the Lord
Marſhall Biron to the ende vpon aduertiſement
from himſelfe, to paſſe ouer Seyne, or to march toward
Paris, either to paſſe ouer the Riuer of Oyſe
at Creil, or at Ile-Adam, ſo to cut off the ennemies
retraict into the Low countries.
            
            The ſixteenth day, the king receyued letters
from the Lord of Archant gouernour of Eureux,
importing the ouerthrow of a great nomber of
the ennemies, whome hee ſurpriſed, lodged in
the ſuburbes of the ſaide towne, of whome fifty
were left deade in the place, and many were taken
priſoners.
            He writeth moreouer that vppon Friday
the fiueteenth day of thys moneth of May, the
Prince of Parma, ſonne to the Duke, had paſſed
a long not farre from Eureux, accompanied with
ſeauentene enſignes of footemen and two maine
troupes of horſe, who marched the one before,
and the other behind, ſo diſorderly and fearfully,
that it had bene an eaſie matter with a thouſande
horſe, to haue defeated them all: and that
he marched directly towarde Paris where he hoped
vpon the Sonday after, being the ſeauenteenth
of the ſame moneth, to arriue.
            The king purpoſeth ſhortly to returne to
the aſſault of Roan, who hath found her death in
place where ſhe hoped for health. For the ſame

towne hath had no ſupply of the thinges that it
ſtandeth in moſte neede of, neyther neede wee to
feare, ſo long as the king is maiſter of the fielde
and keepeth the Riuer of Seine ſhut vp, that the
ennemies ſhall deliuer themſelues from their
miſery and want of victuals.
            By letters of the eighteenth day from the
Campe neere to Caudebeck, wee heare that the
Duke of Parma remayneth at Roan ſicke of his
hurt: alſo that the Duke of Mayenne is likewiſe
ſicke in the towne, of a ſore and in a manner incurable
diſeaſe: likewiſe that the moſt parte of
the ſaide Dukes army is alſo there encloſed:
and moſt certaine it is that the Switzers are
there ſhut vp.
            There is newes come ſence that the Duke
of Parma hauinge paſſed the Riuer of Seyne, and
vnderſtanding that the king lay for him toward
Paris, hath paſſed the Riuer of Marne at Charenton
bridge toward Meaux, alſo that the ſaid Duke is
very ſicke.
            The Lord of Fay is at Guillebocuſ which he fortefieth,
as being a place that may greatly hinder
all trafficke betweene Roan and Newhauen.
            
            The Lorde Marſhall Biron, on the nine and
twentieth day of May, entered vpon Newcaſtle,
and it is thoughte that the buſineſſe will not bee
long.
            
               Roan is brought into great extremity, as being
victualed but from day to day. The king
purpoſeth very ſhortly to kepe it ſhorter.
            
               
               Other newes there is written from Genes the
fifth of Aprill 1592. the which are confirmed
by diuers letters.
               The Duke of Sauoy is retourned out of Prouence
vnto Nice, thence to departe to Thurine to
take order for the affaires of Piedmont where
they greatly feare the comming of the Lorde of
Diguieres. That both before and ſince hys departure
from the ſame place hee hath ſtill loſt,
namely the good willes of the people: alſo that
particularlye Aix was reuolted againſt him:
and had expelled all the ſtraungers hys adherents:
had chaunged magiſtrates and ſlayne the
conſull &amp; three counſelers. That the gouernor
of Antibe hauing receiued monie of the duke for
deliuery of the ſame to him, had mocked him,
and with the canon chaſed away foure hundred
ſouldiers ſent to take the poſſeſſion. The Marquſe
Seralin is come out of Spaine into Piedemont
to ſerue the Duke in his warres of Prouence, as
alſo to the ſame effect there are leauyed new
forces in Lombardy.
               
               The ſtates of Arragon, Catalogne and Valence
by comon accord &amp; conſent ſent vnto king Philip
to complaine of his executing of the cheife
Iuſtice of the ſtate of Arragon, whereto he aunſwered
that he executed him not as in qualitie
of chiefe Iuſtice but as a perticuler rebell, wher
of they craued declaration in writing togither
with the confirmation of theyr priuiledges:

Furthermore in as much as it ſeemed that the
king ment to ſend ſome men toward the Pirinean
mountaynes, they withall beſought him not to
ſende aboue fiue hundred at once according to
their ſaide priuiledges, whereto the king hath
as yet returned no aunſwere.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

