
   
      
         
            The maidens blush: or, Ioseph mirror of modesty, map of pietie, maze of destinie, or rather diuine prouidence. From the Latin of Fracastorius, translated; &amp; dedicated to the high-hopefull Charles, Prince of Wales. By Iosuah Syluester.
            Joseph. English
            Fracastoro, Girolamo, 1478-1553.
         
         
            
               1620
            
         
         Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01141
            STC 11253
            ESTC S105625
            99841352
            99841352
            5929
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01141)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5929)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 957:2)
         
         
            
               
                  The maidens blush: or, Ioseph mirror of modesty, map of pietie, maze of destinie, or rather diuine prouidence. From the Latin of Fracastorius, translated; &amp; dedicated to the high-hopefull Charles, Prince of Wales. By Iosuah Syluester.
                  Joseph. English
                  Fracastoro, Girolamo, 1478-1553.
                  Sylvester, Josuah, 1563-1618.
               
               [84] p.   
               
                  Printed by H[umphrey] L[ownes],
                  London :
                  1620.
               
               
                  A translation by Sylvester of: Joseph.
                  In verse.
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Signatures: A-E F² .
                  The first leaf is blank.
                  At least two known copies are bound with "Tobacco battered" by Josuah Sylvester, the pagination of which continues from this item.
                  Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
                  Lacking title page; title page and duplicate A3 from Huntington copy 22318 v.3 pt.1 filmed at beginning.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2006-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-12
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-01
            Pip WillcoxSampled and proofread
         
            2007-01
            Pip WillcoxText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2007-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            The Maidens Bluſh:
OR,
JOSEPH,
Mirror of Modeſty,
Map of Pietie,
Maze of Deſtinie,
Or rather
Diuine Prouidence.
From the Latin of Fracaſtorius,
Tranſlated;
&amp;
Dedicated
To the High-Hopefull
CHARLES,
Prince of Wales.
By IOSVAH SYLVESTER.
            
               LONDON
Printed by H. L. 
1620.
         
         
            
            
            
               TO
The High,
Hopefull-Happy Prince,
CHARLES
Prince of Wales,
Duke of Cornewall, and Earle of Cheſter.
            
               AMong the Preace that to Your Preſence flowes,
               With Ioy-full Honours, as this time requires;
               Inſtead of coſtly Suites, of curious ſhowes,
               Of precious Gifts, of ſolemne Panegyres:
            
            
               Accept a Heart which to Your Highneſſe owes
               Whole Hecatombes of Happy-moſt Deſires;
               Praying, All proſperous to your blowing Roſe,
               
               In All, to equall, or excell Your Sire's:
               
            
            
            
            
               〈1 page duplicate〉
            
            
               
                  
That in All Vertues of a Prince complete,
               All Princely Glories may attend you ſtill:
               All ehat may make a KING as Good as Great.
            
            
               All IOSEPHS Bleſſings (from th' Eternall Hill)
               Whoſe Happy Legend comes to gratulate
               Your High Creation, and Your Birth-dayes Date.
            
            
               The better Day,
               The better Deed.
            
            
               Look the next leaf,
               And ſo proceed.
            
         
         
            
            Prince
ARTHVRS CASTLE,
Chiefeſt ARTS CHAST LVRE;
Now,
Now, or Neuer,
Daign My HARTS LAST CVRE.
            
               LIke ſad Arion on his Dolphins Backe,
               Amid the Ocean of my Carefull Feares,
               Nigh ſtript of all, Now ſlept in hoary haires;
               Sit I (poore Relique of Your Brothers wracke.)
            
            
               My Harpſtrings quauer, while my Heart-ſtrings cracke:
               My Hand growes weary, and my Health it weares;
               To ſtirre Compaſsion in ſome Powerfull eares,
               At laſt, to land me, and ſupply my lacke.
            
            
               
You, You alone (Great PRINCE) with Pities grace
            Haue held my Chinne aboue the Waters brinke:
            Hold still, alas! hold ſtronger, or I ſinke.
            Or hale me vp into ſome ſafer place,
            Some Priuie-Groom, ſome Room within your Doores:
            That, as my Heart, my Harpe may all be Yours.
            
               In Effect, as in Affection,
To Your Hignes ſeruice,
Euer humbly deuoted,
IOSVAH SYLVESTER.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            The Maidens Bluſh:
OR,
JOSEPH.
            
               CHaſte Muſe of Muſes, that in ſacred Layes,
               With ſtraines vnwonted, doſt delight to raiſe
               From blacke Obliuion's ſad and ſilent Tents,
               Th'Heroick Geſts and Noble Monuments
               Of antike WORTHIES, and their fames reuiue,
               Through euery Age to All that ſhall ſuruiue;
               Now, Now reuolue th'Authenticall Records
               
               Of th'Holy Nation, whom the Lord of Lords
               Choſe for his Owne, (Whoſe Line directly came
               From Princely Loines of faithful ABRAHAM):
               
               And ſweedy tun'd to th'ſacred voyce of Truth,
               Sing That Religious, That rare-Modeſt Youth
               
               (Good Iſaac's Grand-child, and great Iacob's Son)
               Whom God indu'd, (by Dreames) of things yet done
               
                  
To tell the iſſue: Tell, ô! tell Thou All
               That He indur'd through ſwelling Enuies Gall;
               Till at the laſt, tryumphing of his Foes,
               Through Pharao's grace to Princely Place he roſe
               (As Egypt's Viceroy) by diuine Decree
               Fore-ſent, a Friend and Founder there to be
               Of th' happy People, and the holy Seed,
               From Whence, ſhould Hope of future Life proceed;
               And Whence Saluation ſhould be freely giuen,
               Through th'heauenly Key that ſhuld re-opē 
                  Heauen.
               
            
            
               
                  And, O! Thou Glory of Great STVARTS ſtemme,
               
               
                  Great Iacob's Heire, Great-Britaines Ioy and Gemme,
               
               
                  CHARLES, King of Hopes, &amp; Hope-ful Prince of Men,
               
               
                  My great Mecoenas, to encheer my Pen,
               
               
                  Aſsiſt Thou alſo: and with gentle Gales
               
               
                  Of Help-full Fauour, fill my Hopefull Sailes:
               
               
                  That maugre Enuie's Rocke and Fortunes Storme,
               
               
                  My ſacred Voyage I may ſafe performe,
               
               
                  To th' onely glory of my Ghoſtly Guide,
               
               
                  His Churches Profit, and Your Praiſe, beſide;
               
                  While, vnder IOSEPH's Wondrous Temperance,
               
               
                  His Piety, His Prudent Gouernance,
               
               
                  I prophecie Your Princely Vertues Crop,
               
               
                  (Your Parents Prayer, and Your Peoples Hope)
               
               
                  
                  God ſay Amen. But, Tide for none doth ſtay,
               I muſt aboord, I muſt mine Anchor waigh.
               Away to Sea: the Winde is wondrous good,
               Spread all our Canuas: O how ſwift we ſcud!
               Through all the Weſtern, and the Mid-land Seas,
               Arriu'd already to deſcry (with caſe)
               The Coaſt of Ioppa and Samarian Hills,
               With wealthy Sichems goodly Groues and Fields.
               Already (running twixt his winding banks)
               
                  Iordan begins to waſh our wel-come Planks,
               Where Hebron's valley our glad Welcome ſings,
               And euen Mount Tabor with the Eccho rings.
            
            
               
                  Th' Old Serpent knew (for Much to know is giuen
               Vnto that Hell-god, by the GOD of Heauen)
               It was decreed by euerlaſting Date,
               And promiſed, that there ſhould propagate,
               From Abraham's happy Stocke, a holy Stem
               Which ſhould confound th' Infernall Diadem.
               In doubt whereof, perplext and vexed ſore,
               His Ielouſie of Iacob grew the more.
               The more he enuies Sichem's Shepheard-Prince,
               As well becauſe, with duer Reuerence
               Did None obſerue and ſerue th'Eternall Lord,
               Nor iuſter liu'd, nor righter him ador'd.
               
                  
As for the goodly Bleſſings of his Bed,
               (Twelue luſty Sonnes) likely alone to ſpread
               Into a People holy and deuout.
            
            
               Therefore he labours, and he layes-about,
               With all the Engines of his helliſh Hate,
               That, That deere Iſſue to exterminate.
               Eſpecially, that louely Lad (whoſe Birth
               Had happy Stars, preſaging holy Worth;)
               IOSEPH, the darling of his Fathers age,
               Borne of his (firſt-lou'd) ſecond marriage:
               Whom, Nature-grac's, the Graces nurtur'd fine
               In liberall Arts, and loue of Law diuine;
               Inſpir'd his Soule with skill of future things;
               His minde aſpiring with celeſtiall wings:
               To Elders Modeſt, to his equalls milde,
               With Piety and Prudence paſt a Childe.
            
            
               Now, as frō flowres whēce Bees their hony make,
               The loathſome Spider doth his poyſon take;
               Hence did the Fiend in th' other Brethren hatch
               Cloſe deadly Hate, him harm-leſſe to diſpatch:
               Nor would He let the firſt occaſion ſlip
               That might aduance his wyly workemanſhip:
               For, for the moſt, to each mans Inclination,
               He knowes, in time, to offer his Temptation.
            
            
               
                  
It hapned then, vpon a Summers day,
               When as the Sunne had with his parching Ray
               Driuen all the Brethren all their flocks to driue
               To the coole Couert that the Woods would giue;
               Them-ſelues ſet round vnder a ſhadie Oake,
               Yong IOSEPH thus gently the reſt beſpoke.
            
            
               Brothers, I'le tel you my ſtrange Dream to night,
               Heare it, I pray (what euer meane it might,
               It was an odde one.) Early, when the Stars
               Were all call'd in (excepting Lucifer's,
               
               Dayes daily Vſher) ſlumbring ſweet this Morne,
               Me thought We all were in a field of Corne,
               All binding Sheaues; and when we each had One,
               My Sheafe, me thought, ſtood bolt vpright alone,
               And all your Sheaues did inſtantly incline,
               And lowly bow their bended tops to mine.
            
            
               Then Iudah, nettled with no little hate
               Againſt the Lad, began him thus to rate:
               Why, ſaucy Boy, What phant'ſies doſt thou fable?
               Is this your Dreame, you deeme ſo admirable?
               Hath not perhaps ſome Spirit inſpir'd you ſo?
               No doubt there hath: the ſpirit of Wine, I trowe.
               But, pray, What Augure doth your wonder bring?
               That you (belike) ſhall of vs all be King.
               
                  
Good King of Crickets, line thy Crown with Baies,
               Leſt drunken Vapors ſome Rebellion raiſe.
            
            
               The reſt concurr'd to gird the harmleſſe Boy
               With flouts and ſhouts of O God giue you ioy:
               
               
                  God ſaue your Grace. Your Maieſty to come,
               
               And tell, in Scorne, their Father all the ſumme.
            
            
               Hee, good old man, (not without God within)
               He ponders all that he had heard and ſeene;
               As if diſcerning ſomewhat in the Lad
               Of higher ſtraine, than euery ſtripling had:
               Yet, to conceale it from the reſt he ſeemes,
               And bids the Boy beware of guilefull Dreames.
               
            
            
               But, He, to whom GOD greater Honors meant,
               Soone after dream'd of grauer Argument.
               Him ſeem'd, that, ſet in ſtately Eminence,
               Before his Feet, with humble Reuerence,
               The Sunne and Moone and Eleuen Stars he ſaw,
               Stooping vnto him in obſequious Awe.
               Which well recording (for by heauenly grace
               That Gift he had) within a little ſpace
               He tells his Brethren of his ſecond Tranſe:
               Who, re-incenſt with ragefull Arrogance,
               Soone ſhew their Father, with his fatall Dreame,
               
               Their rancor, ſpleene, and cank'red ſpite extreame.
            
            
               
                  
                  Iacob, at firſt amazed, calls his Sonne;
               And, as interp'ring, thus to chide begun:
               What! Sirra; ſhall I, and your Mother too,
               And all your Brothers bow our Necks to you?
               Shall you be mounted on your Chaire of State,
               And Wee come All baſe Beggars to your Gate?
               If ſuch a folly haue befum'd your braine,
               And fill'd your phant'ſie with preſumptuous vaine,
               With idle Hopes: away with thoſe Conceits;
               Truſt not to Dreames, liſt not to ſuch Deceits
               So reaſon-leſſe, ridiculous, and light;
               Monſters, Chimaera's, ſhadowes of the Night:
               Which (if not good) it is not God doth ſend,
               But ſome Illuſion of the ſubtle Fiend,
               To traine our Weakenes to ſome ſinfull Trap;
               Or, to betray vs to ſome dire miſ-hap:
               As from his Cels falſe Oracles hee wreſts,
               From flight of Birds, and Tripes of mangled Beaſts.
            
            
               Haſt thou not heard of Belus, Anubis,
               
               
                  Ops, Hecate, and other Deities,
               
               Whom the blinde Heathen in their Temples haue,
               Frequent their Altars, and their Rites obſerue;
               Waiting their Anſweres with the humbleſt Awe,
               All which is hatefull to our Holy Law?
               
               
                  
Therefore be Wiſe: and looke henceforth we heare
               No more ſuch Dreames of ſuch phantaſtike geare.
            
            
               He thus diſmiſt, the reſt he milde beſpake
               To calme their ſtorme, and kindly bade them take
               The Flocks to Field, and driue them ſoft and faire
               To Sichem Woods, to feede in cooler aire.
            
            
               Their Fathers bidding they eft-ſoones obay'd,
               (Yong IOSEPH yet at home with him he ſtaid)
               Paſſing the fruitfull Vales and flow'ry Greenes
               Of plentious Hebron, to thoſe ſhadie Screenes.
            
            
               But, nor the Verdure of thoſe Hills nor Dales,
               Nor ſong of Birds, nor ſhade of Woods, nor Gales
               Of whiſpering Winds, could kill or cancell quite
               Thoſe odious Dreames they dream-on day &amp; night.
               Rather, they gather daily more Diſdaine,
               Sharpen their Enuy, giue their Rage the raine,
               With Threats &amp; Vows; while the euil ſpirit too nigh
               Still ſtirres and ſpurs their hatefull Ielouſie.
            
            
               Now, twice the Sunne had run his Iourny ſwift,
               When the next morning they prepare to ſhift
               To Dothan's pleaſant Downs for freſher Feed,
               And to be further off from home (indeed);
               And ſo the longer ere they could reuert,
               Which they euen loath'd, and hated at the heart.
            
            
               
                  
Wherefore (night after night, day after day)
               When, paſt their wont, their Father ſaw them ſtay;
               In muſefull care his IOSEPH cals he quicke,
               And bids him Thus: I pree-thee Boy goe ſeeke
               Thy Brethren out (on Sichem Downes they feed,
               Or neere about) and bring me word with ſpeed,
               What vncouth Reaſon of their ſtay there is:
               My minde miſ-giues me ſomewhat is amiſſe
               With them, or with their Cattle: hye thee, Lad.
            
            
               Away ſcuds IOSEPH (no leſſe ſwift then glad)
               As farre as Sichem: but there looking round,
               Neither his Brethren, nor the Flocks he found.
               Perplexed then, he calls them one by one;
               Hoaw, Brothers! Ruben! Leui! Simeon!
               
               Then, whoops and hallooes with his Treble throat,
               So loud and ſhrill, that, to his warbling Note
               With doubled Ecchoes, Woods and Caues reply:
               But, not a Brother anſwers Eare or Eye.
            
            
               By chance, a Wood-man that an Oke did ſhrowd,
               Hearing the Lad, and knowing, call'd him lowd,
               And told him thus; I heard your Brethren ſay
               They would to Dothan: Thither, that's the way,
               There ſhall you finde them with their Cattle ſafe,
               In better Paſture then is heere by halfe.
               
                  
Thanks thinks the Lad: and Sichem out of ſight,
               As ſwift as Roe he runs to Dothan right.
            
            
               When, from a Hill, his Hatefull Brethren ſpi'd
               Him yet farre-off: O! yonder comes (they cry'd)
               Our King to-come, whom both the Sun &amp; Moone,
               And all the Stars muſt ſerue and worſhip ſoone.
               We, We baſe Hindes, borne but for Heards &amp; Neat,
               Drudging all Day in the Suns ſcorching heat,
               Lodging all Night in holes or hollow Trees,
               Clad but in Lether, or in courſeſt Freeze,
               And meanly fed with Bread and Water, moſt;
               While He is ſet-vp with his Sod and Roaſt,
               His Meſſe of Goats-Milke, and his fill of Wine,
               In change of Coates, pranked &amp; painted fine;
               Snoring all night vpon his eaſe-full bed,
               Where, from the Forge of his phantaſtike head,
               He feignes theſe Dreames in meer diſdain of vs:
               But, Brethren, ſhall we, ſhall we ſuffer thus
               Him and his Scornings? Shall we be ſo blinde
               T'indure him ſtill, till growne a Man, his minde
               Growne big withall, and bearing proud vpon
               His Fathers fondneſſe, He ſupplant anon
               Our Haps and Hopes, vſurping All our due,
               And ſo (in fine) fulfill his Dreames too-true?
               
                  
O! We are Buzzards, Blockheads, Cowards all.
               Why rather heere, where none deſcry vs ſhall,
               Where all things ſort, where he is come ſo pat,
               Shall we not kill him, and make ſure for that?
               For, in this Pit we may him deepe interre,
               And ſay (at home) ſome hungry Wolfe or Beare
               (Whereof the Deſarts, not far off, haue ſtore)
               Him quicke deuoured, and to peeces tore.
            
            
               While theſe dire Counſels they together caſt,
               
                  Ruben (who all, in yeeres and pitty, paſt)
               Cry'd, GOD defend, ô Brethren, GOD defend,
               Againſt our Brother we ſhould ſo offend:
               O! in his bloud doe not your hands imbrue,
               Leſt Heau'ns drad Vengeance that dire fact purſue
               On Vs and Ours. Though no man witneſſe be,
               GOD, GOD himſelfe is witneſſe, and doth ſee
               And heare vs all: from him is nothing hid,
               Hee's all an Eye that neuer cloſeth Lid.
               But, if you needs will of the Lad be quit,
               
                  Sanz bloud or ſlaughter, put him in this pit,
               There leaue him to his Fate. This he aduiſ'd;
               That, resku'd thus from preſent death deuis'd,
               He, late at night returning to the Caue,
               Might hale him vp, and th' harmleſs ſtripling ſaue,
               
                  
To bring him ſafe vnto his aged Sire,
               And calme at length his Brethrens enuious Ire.
            
            
               Their Elders Words them All a little mou'd,
               And his aduice they all at once approu'd:
               Him downe vnſlaine, into the pit to ſlide,
               His worſe or better Fortune to abide.
               Then Ruben ſaid; be Witneſſe GOD for Me,
               How cleere I am from this your Cruelty:
               And as he ſpake, him from them far withdrew
               Into the Woods, to wait what would enſue.
            
            
               By this, was IOSEPH (full of liuely cheere
               For hauing found them) euen arriued neere;
               When, fell and furious, they incloſe him round,
               Lay hands on him, his tender hands they bound,
               With brauing Threats; Now ſhall you ſee (ſay they)
               Your Dreames fulfill'd: Muſt not we all obey
               
                  Your Mightineſſe? Our Sheaues muſt ſtoop to you:
               
                  Yea, to your State, Sunne, Moone, and Stars muſt bow.
            
            
               Wondring, and frighted with their vncouth guiſe,
               In vaine (alas!) in vaine he calls and cries
               To them for pitty of his Innocence;
               While inly Rage, with more Impatience
               Still egg'd them on, with fell Erynuis brands:
               And helliſh Pluto (who too-ready ſtands,
               
                  
Weening to croſſe the Deſtinies Diuine)
               
               Doth all their Edge 'gainſt him alone incline.
            
            
               Whē he perceiu'd (poor Boy!) no vows, no teares
               Could mollifie thoſe ſtony hearts of Theirs
               To hold their hands, already heauing him
               With violence vnto the Dungeons brim;
               His Eyes lift vp towards th' Empyreall Pole,
               
               Thus, loud he groned from a greeued ſoule.
            
            
               Great GOD of Abraham, Iſaac, Iacob, too,
               Who kenneſt all things, and canſt all things doe;
               If I ſincerely haue ador'd thee ſtill:
               If I haue gladly done my Parents Will:
               If I haue liued pious and vpright;
               Lord looke vpon me in this wofull plight.
               Or, if it pleaſe Thee, that I heere expire;
               Yet ſpare, ô Lord, ô ſpare mine aged Sire.
               And, ô! my Brethren (whom, with due reſpect
               Of Elderſhip, I euer did affect)
               How-euer Me you pitty not, I pray
               Pitty our Father (leſt vntimely gray
               His hoary head come to the graue for greefe)
               Let not him heare it: rather ſay ſome Theefe,
               Or knot of Theeues, Mee (by the way) bereft;
               That ſome falſe hope may of my life be left,
               
                  
To lengthen his: though heere (alas!) I lye
               Dead in theſe ſands, and hid from any eye:
               And as he ſpake, his Teares ſo faſt did fall,
               They ſtopt his ſpeech, and almoſt ſtaid withall
               His Brethrens rage; till Ruth-leſſe Iſachar
               
               Re-fand the fire. Nay, hauing gone thus farre,
               We may not now, We cannot ſafe deſiſt;
               For why? whereon I need not now inſiſt;
               Your ſelues (ſaid he) can quickly gheſſe, I trow,
               Miſchiefes enow, if now we let him goe.
               Let vs therefore goe on as wee decreed,
               Let's let him downe: Heereto they all agreed,
               With heart and hand, and did it inſtantly;
               And then Remorſeleſſe, on the Graſſe hard by
               Made no more bones, but ſate them down to dinner.
               O! the dull Conſcience of a hardned ſinner!
            
            
               But, frō th' Empyreall, through th' Aethereal Pole,
               GOD looking downe vpon the harmleſſe Soule,
               In tender Pity, and eternall Loue
               Towards his Owne; among the Troops (aboue)
               Of winged Heralds, that are euer preſt,
               Expecting gladly his Diuine Beheſt,
               To one he beckens, and he bids him Thus;
               Right Truſty, hy thee, hy thee down from vs,
               
                  
Toward Samaria, well thou knoweſt where,
               And whom thou know'ſt one day o
                     •
                  dain'd to beare
               A glorious Part, in honorable Place,
               Good Iſaac's Grand-Child, now in pitious caſe,
               Crying for ſuccour from a darke deepe Cell,
               Againſt his Brethrens enuious Furie fell:
               Goe comfort him, poore heart; but in what kinde,
               I need not ſay. Thou ſeeſt: thou know'ſt my minde.
            
            
               So, with his gratious All-directing Nod,
               Th'Angel, diſ-miſt, in th'inſtant ſpreads abroad
               Aethereall wings on his Aēreall ſides,
               And through the woundleſs Welkin ſwifter glides
               Then Zephyrus; or, then (when mounted high
               With many Turns, and towring in the Skye)
               The ſtout Ger-Faulcon ſtoopeth at the Herne,
               
               With ſodaine Souſe, that many ſcarce diſcerne:
               Such was the ſpeed of this Celeſtiall Bird
               (To proſecute, and execute the Word
               Of his great Maſter) towards Dothan Downe,
               Alighting firſt vpon Mount Tabor's Crowne,
               Amaz'd to ſee his Groues ſo ſodaine greene,
               And Lawnes ſo freſh, with flowery tufts betweene.
               The Hill-born Nymphs with quauering warbles ſing
               His happy-Well-come: Caues &amp; Rocks do ring
               
                  
Redoubled Ecchoes; Woods and Winds withall,
               Whiſper about a ioyfull Madrigall.
            
            
               But th' Heauenly Herald, frō the Mountain eying
               The Vale about, ſees there the Brethren lying
               Along the Graſſe, and buſie at their Vittle,
               And, from a Hill (thence diſtant but a little)
               Th' Arabian Merchants with their Camels, hard
               (As God would haue it) driuing thither-ward;
               Thence inſtantly he caſts his gentle Eye,
               On wofull IOSEPH, and immediately
               Deſcending ſwift, ſtands on the dungeons brim,
               Now ſhining bright with ſodain light from him.
               Wherewith the Lad at once diſmaid and ioy'd,
               The ſacred Torch-man (to that end employd)
               In louely Shape, with ſweet and liuely grace,
               Thus cheeres the Lad (himſelfe a Lad in Face).
            
            
               Feare not, deere IOSEPH, deere to God aboue.
               Thy Fathers GOD, who All doth guide &amp; moue,
               Hath ſent me hither from his heauenly Throne,
               To comfort and confirme thee, in thy Mone.
               Firſt, Hence thou ſhalt be fre'ed: yet, behold,
               Twiſe, as a Slaue, thou ſhalt be bought and ſold,
               Transferd to Memphis, and for many a yeere
               Shalt liue a Seruant and a Priſoner there.
               
                  
But if thou ſtill haue in abhomination
               Strange Womens Loue, &amp; ſtrange gods adoration:
               If ſtill with all thy ſtrength, with all thy heart
               Thou ſerue the Lord, and from him neuer ſtart:
               If in his Waies thou walke, and doe his Will,
               He will be with thee, for thee, in thee ſtill:
               So that where-ere thou goe, what-ere thou doe,
               Fauour and Fortune ſhall attend thee too.
               And that thou maiſt with greater confidence
               Contemne thy wrongs, and truſt his Prouidence,
               Know for a certaine, he hath deſtin'd thee
               A high Eſtate, and glorious Emperie;
               And time will come, when Thou with me ſhalt view
               Thy former Dreames in euery part proue true;
               When as thy Brethren with ſelfe-guilty brow,
               And thy good Father ſhall before thee bow:
               When thy Compaſſion, paying good for ill,
               Shall ſaue their liues that meant thee firſt to kill:
               Shall feed their mouthes that thought thee once to ſterue
               And buy thē ſeats that ſold thee forth to ſerue
               And not alone receiue themſelues to grace,
               But them and theirs within thy Kingdome place;
               That grown at length in number like the ſand,
               Thence the Almighty with a mighty hand,
               
                  
(In ſpight of Enuie and Ambitious ſway)
               May bring thē dry-ſhod through the Crimſon Sea.
               Directed ſafe in all their vncouth Way,
               By Fire by Night, and by a Clowd by Day;
               Through the drye Deſart, plentifully fed
               With Quailes frō Heauen, &amp; Manna (Angels bread)
               Into a Land where Milke and Hunny flowe;
               The happy ſigne of happier ſubſtance though:
               Where, in due Time (ô haſte ye Times away)
               A Golden Age ſhall ſee a glorious Day;
               
               A Day full oft to be fore-typ't, fore-told,
               Fore-promiſed by Prophets manifold;
               When from the Boſome of th'Eternall SIRE,
               Th' Eternall SONNE (What may we So admire!)
               
                  (The SPIRIT o'reſhadowing of a Virgin-Mother)
               Shall take Man's Nature, &amp; become your Brother;
               Old ADAM's Guilt, and Yours to expiate,
               And wide re-open Heauens long-locked Gate.
               Concluding heere, to Heau'n the Angell hy'd.
            
            
               IOSEPH, though firſt diſtract &amp; ſtupefi'd,
               With ſuch a Glory (and confuſ'd a-ſpace)
               Him re-collects, and re-erects his Face;
               Inlie reioycing, deepely rumining,
               All in his minde maturely pondering.
               
                  
And future Hopes confirme him paſſing ſtrong,
               Gainſt preſent feares, and all his Woes &amp; Wrong;
               That cheerely thus, with heart and hands erect,
               His holy Vowes he doth to Heauen direct:
            
            
               Great King of Kings, that ruleſt All-abroad;
               My Fathers, Grandſires, &amp; Great-grandſires God,
               Almighty Guide and Guard, ſtill gratious be
               To Vs and Ours, whoſe truſt is all in Thee.
               Eſpecially, thy fauour, Lord I craue
               Towards my Father, ready for the Graue:
               And as for Mee; how-euer pleaſe thee, deale
               Me ſowre or ſweet; or ſend me Woe or Weale,
               It ſhall be welcome, and I well content.
               Onely deere Father, if that Death preuent
               Mine eyes (vnworthy) of that wiſhed Day,
               That long long-hoped, happy Holy-Day:
               
               When frō thy Throne (whoſe Glory hath no End)
               Thine onely Sonne ſhall into Fleſh deſcend,
               At leaſt vouchſafe me, though in ſhadow dim,
               As in a Glaſſe to ſee and knowledge Him;
               And (thorough Faith) to feele the ſauing Sauour
               
               Of this thrice-ſacred, gratious, pretious Lauer.
               
               So, with an inward and deep ſigh, he ceaſt.
            
            
               The while, Arabians (Merchants of the Eaſt)
               
                  
With Camels loaden with their Country Ware,
               
                  Myrrhe, Storax, Incenſe, the moſt choyce and rare,
               Comming from Madian, towards Aegypt bound,
               Were paſſing by, where on the graſſie ground,
               The Shepheard Brethren ſate to eat and talke;
               And buſie yet, their Teeth and Tongues did walke,
               Till on the ſodaine they deſcry'd the Men.
               Whence Iudah thus begins: O Bretheren,
               Behold how GOD doth better farre prouide,
               Then we could plot (more ſafe for eyther ſide).
               For, to theſe Merchants if we ſell the Lad,
               Firſt, a good peece of Money will be had;
               Next, of our Brothers bloud we ſhall be cleere;
               And laſt of all, be ſure no more to heare
               Or newes, or noiſe, or name of IOSEPH here,
               Whether to Memph's or Marmorid's they wend.
               Therefore, forthwith one to them let vs ſend,
               The Mart to offer, and the Price to make,
               As of a Slaue; and bring their anſwer backe.
            
            
               They all agree, and one is ſent away
               To driue the Bargaine; while the reſt aſſay
               About a Tree-trunke faſtning fit a rope,
               And letting 't downe, to hale their Brother vp.
               And vp he comes as freſh as Maying Roſe,
               
                  
Or Daffadill that in a Garden growes;
               As liuely Forme as yerſt, as louely Face,
               Shining with ſignes of GODS aſſiſting Grace.
            
            
               By this, the Marchants with their Broker came,
               To ſee the Ware, and did ſo like the ſame,
               They ſtood not hucking, of the price to bate
               (So good, and ſo good cheap, who would not ha't!)
               But, who would ween (good God!) that euer He,
               That was prae-deſtin'd to ſuch dignitie,
               To whom ſuch Wealth and Honor ſhould befall,
               Should thus be ſold, and for a price ſo ſmall?
               (Saue that my Sauiour, Heire of Heauen &amp; Earth,
               That God-begotten, holy Virgins Birth,
               Whom Angels ſerue, whom Cherubins adore,
               To Iewes his Iudas ſold for little more;
               (Woe to His Soule, Woe to my Sinnes therefore!)
               As, Twenty Pence. O baſe and curſed Thrall!
            
            
               But, both ſides pleaſ'd, Ioſeph muſt ſuffer all.
               Now muſt he mount on his new Maſters packe,
               Vpon his Camels double bunched backe;
               To trot to Nile-ward (neuer heard of Nile)
               
               As proud and glad of ſuch a Load, the while
               His gentle Beaſt, now eaſieſt of the Troop,
               Apteſt to ſtop, humbleſt at need to ſtoop
               
                  
To this new Rider, with a cheerefull Neigh,
               Lifts light his feet, and ſtill he leads the way.
            
            
               Well: Now the Brethren haue their Brother rid,
               How ſhall his Fate, how ſhall their Hate be hid?
               Who, to their Father the ſad newes ſhall bring?
               This is the doubt: This they are hammering.
               In fine, they iump; firſt to ſend home his Coat
               (For they had ſtript him) and in bloud of Goat
               Deepe dipping it, Dan is inſtructed fit
               In this ſad manner to deliuer it
               To aged IACOB, doubting nothing leſſe,
               Than His miſ-hap, or their ſo Hatefulneſſe.
               Father (ſaid Dan) ranging within a Wood,
               Our Cur did find this Coat, thus ſtain'd with bloud.
               Not knowing therefore, whence, nor whoſe it is,
               Nor how it came, we thought it not amiſs
               To ſhew 't you firſt; and after harken further,
               As you thinke fit, in caſe of Maime, or Murder.
               But, Father IACOB had no ſooner ſpy'd
               The ſpotted Coat, with bloud and durt bedy'd,
               But, drown'd in Teares, he teares his hoary haire,
               With Aſhes ſprent, and rent his garments there,
               And cries, Alas! decre IOSEPH, ſtaffe &amp; ſtay
               Of all mine Age, ſo ſodaine tane away!
               
                  
O! O! My Sonne, Who? How? What did befall,
               To murder Thee, to murder Me withall?
               Doubtles, no Man: ſome ſauage Beaſt it was,
               Some hungry Boare, ſome hairie Beare, alas!
               Where are your Brethren? Quickly all of you,
               Through all the Woods, go take a thorow view:
               You may perhaps at laſt yet light on him,
               Or finde at leaſt ſome Part, ſome mangled Lim,
               Some wofull Relique, which I pray bring home,
               That I may giue it his laſt Rites, a Tombe:
               Or rather, let me goe my ſelfe to ſeeke,
               And finde my dead Sonne, or a Death, his Like:
               And ſaying ſo, downe in a ſwoune he ſlid,
               With much a-doo to be recouered.
            
            
               On th' other ſide, ſad Ruben towards night,
               When th'Euening Star began to twinkle bright,
               When Sheep &amp; Shepherds to their Cotes were gone
               All but himſelfe, himſelfe comes all alone
               Vnto the Caue, and calling twice or thrice,
               Why! Ioſeph, Ioſeph; when as none replyes,
               Diſmaid, and doubting, leſt in their diſdaine,
               His Brethren there the ſilly Lad had ſlaine;
               He makes a ſhift to cut a Holmen Pole,
               And by that help, gets downe into the Hole,
               
                  
Lookes round about; but finding nothing there,
               Gets vp againe, as full of greefe and feare.
               Then, hopeles, leaues that ſearch to ſeek the others;
               And by the Sheeps tracke, tracking of his Brothers,
               Soone findes them out; and out of them will know
               Both how, and where, they IOSEPH did beſtow.
               They tell him truly how it did befall.
            
            
               A little cas'd (though little pleas'd withall)
               To heare the Lad was yet aliue and ſafe,
               (Though for his thraldome he did inly chafe)
               He thus aduiſes: Brethren, let vs hye
               Home to our Father, and our beſt apply
               To comfort him; Let vs informe him this,
               That the Arabians (as their manner is)
               Spying the Lad alone vpon the Way,
               Purſu'd him, tooke him, ſtole him quite away;
               And while he ſtrugled from them to haue got,
               With a light hurt he bloudied all his Coate.
               Which let ſome Shepheards boy or other bring
               (As hauing found it) to auer the thing:
               For there be many can affirme (no doubt)
               They lately ſaw Arabians heere-about.
            
            
               This fitted thus, together home they goe,
               And doe their beſt to cheere their Fathers woe.
               
                  
But though perhaps with ſome ſmal hope relieu'd,
               Perpetually (alas!) he mourn'd and grieu'd,
               Nor could the Torrent of his Teares retaine,
               Nor outward Solace inly entertaine;
               But day and night a bitter life he led,
               Moſtly alone, although aliue, as dead.
            
            
               Meane-while, the Marchant well content &amp; glad,
               Holds on his Iourney, beares away the Lad;
               Wondring to ſee all things ſo ſute his will,
               Weather ſo temp'rate, and the Windes ſo ſtill,
               The Waies ſo duſt-leſſe, and ſo durt-leſſe faire,
               The Sunne ſo friendly, and ſo freſh the Aire;
               Aboue their Wont: for, hauing Heauen to friend,
               With IOSEPH, Graces, Hope, and Hap do wend.
            
            
               Now, hauing paſt Iudea's confines quite,
               From a ſteepe Hill, they haue anon the ſight
               Of ſtately Memphis lofty Towres and Walls,
               With glittering roofes of high &amp; ſumptuous Halls
               Amid a rich and pleaſant Plaine, repleat
               With goodly Heards of Cattell, Sheep, and Neat,
               With goodly Corne-fields, heere &amp; there between:
               And, neere the Citie, on a ſpacious Greene,
               They might behold, as in ſome Martiall Muſter,
               Thouſands of Youth in ſeuerall Troops to cluſter;
               
                  
Attending all, Some, manly Exerciſe;
               Some, light and ſpeedy, running for a prize:
               Some, ſtrongly actiue, wraſtling for a fall,
               Some, hurling Sledges, till they ſweat withall:
               Some, on ſwift Horſe-backe to out-ſwim the winde;
               Some, to ſhoot backward at their foes behind:
               Some with their Launces ready coucht in Reſt,
               Wheeling about, to charge in Flanke or Breſt:
               Some, at the Tilt, in ſtrong and ſteddy courſe,
               To breake their Staues, or beare down man &amp; horſe
               Whereon th' Arabians, with th' Iſaacian Lad,
               (Now very neer) ſtood gazing, as right glad,
               And all moſt greedy of ſo various ſorts
               Of Manly Poems, of ſo warlike ſports.
            
            
               An Eunuch of the Kings, one much eſteem'd,
               And Maſter of thoſe Martiall Games (it ſeem'd)
               Seeing thoſe Strangers, with ſo much delight
               Stand ſtill ſo long in viewing all the Sight,
               Sends to inuite them kindely to come neere;
               And then perceiuing that they Marchants were,
               Began to aske, What Ware, what rare deuice,
               They had to ſell? Nothing, ſaid they, but Spice,
               And this yong Lad; Whom if Your Lordſhip like,
               Accept as Yours, and freely, we beſeek:
               
                  
Or, if you nill accept him gratis, prize
               As pleaſe your ſelfe; your fauour ſhall ſuffize.
            
            
               Yes, ſaid the Eunuch, I accept your Loue,
               And of Your Preſent I ſo well approue,
               And prize it ſo, You could not bring me better:
               The more my hope, the more am I your debter,
               Such grace his Face preſageth to my minde;
               So ſhall you neuer me vngratefull finde,
               Said Potiphaer: and then he takes the Lad,
               And cauſing him to be right ſeemely clad,
               In Silken ſuit, giues him a Liuory
               Of Purple, garded with Embroderie.
               Then on a goodly Horſe he ſets him vp,
               The ſtilleſt, yet the ſtatelieſt in the troope.
            
            
               IOSEPH right ioyfull, from a baſhfull Brow,
               Returnes dumbe Homage, with a gracefull Bow
               Vnto his Lord: then, re-erect, appeares
               Taller and trimmer then were all his Peeres.
               Him, home before (thus furniſht) with a Guide,
               Sends Potiphar vnto his louely Bride.
            
            
               Now Heſperus the Euening on did bring;
               When, leauing Fields, the youthfull troops do ring
               About their Captaine, &amp; attend, in State
               To guard him home triumphant to his Gate.
               
                  
And louely IOSEPH, hauing had by this
               A view of his faire Lady-Miſtereſſe;
               
               And of his Office, tutured at large,
               What him belongd in his Lords Chamber-charge,
               Him humbly ranked (of his owne accord)
               Among his fellowes to goe meete his Lord.
            
            
               As burniſht Gold amid a heape of Sand,
               Or Orient Pearle among the Pebble Strand,
               Such ſeemed He, among tenne thouſand Squires,
               Whom Men and Matrones, yong and old admires:
               His paſe ſo graue, his Face ſo gracious,
               His eyes and Feet ſtill ſo officious
               About his Lord, as fixed ſtill on Him,
               With ſteddie Looks, and with as ready Limbe:
               No leſſe within dores then he was without,
               Actiue and apt in all he went about;
               On all occaſions, in what-euer kinde,
               Of Bodie's Labor, or of Birth of Minde.
               But aboue all, his faithfull diligence,
               And mature Wiſdome in all Managements,
               So well accepted and admired are,
               That not alone vnto his Truſtie Care
               His Lord committed what before he had;
               But, ouer All, him onely Steward made.
               
                  
For, Potiphar percein'd that vnder Him,
               What-ere he had did thriue and proſper trim:
               His Fields and Flocks more fruitfull then before;
               His Fauours greater, and his Honours more:
               All which, inſpired by ſome ſecret Teſt,
               To his yong IOSEPH he aſcrib'd, as Bleſt.
               And th' Oracles of Egypt, then a-foot,
               Seem'd euen to point at, and perſwade vnto 't.
            
            
               There was a Peach-Tree growing then amid
               
                  God Camoſh Temple, to him conſacred,
               Which, brought from Perſia long agoe, they ſay,
               When Iſis yerſt did all the World ſuruay,
               By her owne hand was planted, for Poſterity,
               To be a famous Monument of Verity.
               Heereon, arriuing from farre wanderings,
               Bright-ſhining Apis, with change-colour'd wings,
               Faire Apis ſetled; after whom did muſter
               A mighty Swarme, which hung all in a Cluſter
               Vpon one Bough. This wonder blowne abroad
               Among the Bards, they vouch that it did boad,
               Some Stranger ſhould from forrein parts arriue;
               And after him, a mighty people hyue,
               Through whom the houſe of Potiphar ſhould riſe
               To wondrous Wealth and goodly dignities.
               
                  
Weening therefore theſe Augures all fulfild
               In IOSEPH now, him euery one well-will'd,
               Him euery one accordingly reſpected,
               Him euery one for this the more affected.
            
            
               But faire Tempſar (wife of Potiphar)
               Aboue the reſt, his Parts did high prefer:
               Him more then All ſhee inlie did admire,
               And ſtill beholds him with a young deſire.
               Yet, ignorant what furie would enſue
               The pleaſing Paſſion ſhe did ſo purſue:
               What wily Godling to beguile her, ſought
               To ſnare her freedome in a ſeruile thought;
               As yet ſhe vented neyther Sigh nor Teare:
               All yet was ſweet, no bitter Fit, no Feare.
            
            
               Which th' enuious Prince of Styx and Acheron,
               
               Malignant Father of confuſion,
               Mans deadly Foe, obſeruing; and beſide,
               That Iſaac's ſeed ſtill happy multiplied:
               In fell deſpight, and full of deſp'rate rage,
               He calls a bird of his infernall Cage,
               A cruell Harpy, full of wicked Wile,
               A thouſand waies, the wiſeſt to beguile.
               Go, hye, ſaith He, my darling, hye thee quicke
               To faire Iempſar; ſhe is Phantſie-ſicke
               
               
                  
Already. Therefore ſo inſinuate,
               That more and more thou her intoxicate:
               Breath in her boſome, blowe-in new infection,
               Kindle the Tinder of her light affection
               To ſuch a flame, that neither Gods nor men
               May be of Power to put it out agen:
               And, doe thy beſt (for that I moſt deſire)
               If poſſible, ſet IOSEPH (too) a fire:
               But, if on him, thou nothing canſt preuaile,
               Returne to her, her Phantſie re-aſſaile,
               Fill her with Phrenzie, and with Furie double
               Still burne her fell, till all her Friends ſhe trouble:
               Till with diſgrace, diſdain'd, and deſperate,
               She turne her deere Loue to as deadly Hate:
               Till then, deſiſt not; but perſiſt and ply
               To play thy Part with Art and Subtilty.
            
            
               He, glad and ready for the worſt of Ills,
               With Stygian puddle halfe a Viall fills,
               Blending ſome bitter, ſharp-ſweet wine withall:
               Then ſnatching quicke one of the ſnakes that craule
               About Alecto's grim and ghaſtly Browes,
               Away he hies to Potiphar his Houſe,
               Within his boſome hiding what he had,
               And formally iuſt in the Form him clad
               
                  
Of Iphicle, the Lady Iempſars Nurſe;
               With better credit, to beguile the worſe.
               Then, to her Lady hauing made a ducke,
               Sweet Madame (ſaid ſhe, fie on all ill lucke)
               What ſad diſaſter, what misfortune rife,
               Hath made poore IOSEPH weary of his Life?
               My ſelfe, of late, haue ſeene him oft, forlorne
               Sit ſole and ſighing, and haue heard him mourne,
               Wiſhing for Death. And when I ſought to know
               The ſecret cauſe of his exceeding woe:
               O! Mother (ſaid he) whether I conceale it,
               Needs dye I muſt, or whether I reueale it.
               Inquire not therefore; for, tis better end,
               With my ſad life, my ſorrowe's cauſe vnkend.
            
            
               Not ſo, my Sonne (ſaid I) for oft a Wound
               Diſcouer'd, is recouer'd, and made ſound;
               Which, hid a while, would gangrene to the bone:
               Tell boldly (Lad) art thou in loue with none?
               If that be cauſe of thy diſtreſſe; Why Boy
               Be of good cheere, Thou ſhalt thy Deare enioy.
               
                  Hope well, and haue well: So ſhalt thou; or elſe
               I'le charme Loues Paſsion with ſome ſtronger ſpels.
            
            
               With baſhfull Bluſh, then ſaid he, yes, I loue:
               Be witneſſe, Gods, how earneſt I haue ſtroue
               
                  
To ſtrangle it! How I haue labour'd long!
               How loth (alas!) my Lord in thought to wrong!
               More wiſhing Death: Death now make good my triall,
               Happy were I, to liue and dye ſo loyall.
               And, ſaying ſo, on his faire Cheekes hee powres
               A Sea of Teares, in Pearle and Cryſtall ſhowres:
               So that, I ſee, without quicke Remedie,
               For loue of you (Madame) the Youth will dye.
            
            
               Alas! then ſaid the Lady, Woe is me,
               For his Misfortune and his Miſerie;
               To me right tragicke is the tale you tell:
               For, truth to ſay, I loue him but too well,
               And would enioy him, if I could or durſt;
               But ô! I cannot, ô, I may not: firſt,
               For ſacred Lawes, for Hymen's ſecret yoake,
               (Which neuer any yet, vnpuniſht, broke)
               For feare of danger, and diſhonors brand,
               And dreadfull vengeance of my Husbands hand.
            
            
               Why, my deere Daughter, damned Nurſe replies,
               The Gods doe laugh at Louers iniuries:
               And with thy Wedlocke thou maiſt well diſpenſe,
               On ſo good ground of ſo great conſequence,
               As is the ſauing of a Life ſo yong,
               So innocent, that neuer yet did wrong;
               
                  
Vnleſſe it be a wrong to loue too much,
               Or die for Loue (Who would not die for ſuch!)
               Louers muſt dare, and wiſe-men muſt not dread
               The worſt of Dangers that is threatened:
               For, euen the Gods haue Louers in their gard,
               And Loue and Pitty they will ſtill reward.
               I haue a Water of a ſoueraine vſe
               (Th' extracted Spirit of many a Chymick Iuyce)
               
               Which inlie ta'n, in a perplexed Caſe,
               Expells the Doubt, and ſhews Truth's naked Face;
               That, far from ambage, th' vndiſtract affection
               May of the better freely make election.
               If therefore, Madam, yet you ſtand diuided,
               What Part to take; to haue your doubts decided,
               I'le giue it you: and as ſhe ſpake, ſhe gaue
               The helliſh philtre made of Stygian waue.
            
            
               Thanks, deereſt Mother, ſaid her Ladiſhip,
               And taking all, not with a fearefull ſip,
               But full Carouſe, lifting her hand on high,
               Quaft off the poyſon, drew the goblet drye.
            
            
               This done, the Daemon with a Beldams face,
               Towards Ioſephs chamber hies with hobling paſe;
               Where he was praying, and deuoutly prayſing
               The God of Gods, for his ſo gracious raiſing:
               
                  
But when the falſe Fiend in his Portall ſpi'd
               A heauenly Warder (both his Guard and Guide)
               With threatfull brandiſh of a ſhining Blade,
               More ſpeed thē good, headlong he downward made
               In dreadfull Maze; and, as the fowleſt Fowle,
               Transformes him quicke into a Scrieching-Owle,
               
               Night's horrid Monſter, houering long aloofe,
               At laſt pearcht on Iempſars Chamber roofe.
            
            
               The wretched Iempſar, hauing quaffed vp
               The brim and bottome of the Stygian Cup,
               Now all alone, ſhe feeles her all a-fire,
               Bloud, Bones, and Marrow, burning in deſire;
               Sad, ſilent, ſighing, in a wondrous Fit;
               And all for Ioſeph, nigh beſide her wit,
               Now on her bed ſhe falls, and by and by
               Flings vp againe; and to and fro doth fly
               From place to place; ſoone weary of the beſt,
               Runs euery where, and no where findeth reſt;
               Like one whoſe breſt a burning Feuer fryes,
               Or whom ſome Serpents ſting doth agonize.
               At laſt ſhe breakes out; and Alas! quoth Shee,
               What, what is this that thus tormenteth me?
               O! is it Loue? or was it not the Drinke
               I tooke right now? No: it is Loue I thinke,
               
                  
'Tis ſurely Loue, Loue in extreamity,
               And but faire IOSEPH gently helpe, I dye.
               Then help, Sweet-heart, come, be thou boldly mine:
               Come be my Loue, and I will ſtill be thine.
               Both liuing louing, wee 'll die guiltleſſe both
               Of eythers blood: be witneſſe Gods how loth
               I would incur ſo fell, ſo foule a ſtaine,
               To kill ſuch Louer with vnkinde diſdaine.
               Duly and truly, while I ought and could,
               I ſerued Hymen, till (alas!) contrould
               By higher Godheads more Imperiall Right:
               He fauour me, as now I feele his might
               Farre, farre exceed weake Womans oppoſition.
               He will no doubt; and daine vs both Tuition.
               Sith wont, himſelfe, to loue, he as a Louer
               Will pity Paſſions, and our pleaſures couer.
            
            
               Thus hauing ſaid, impatient of delay,
               
                  Efren ſhe calls (Efren a Maid, that aye
               Vſ'd, as moſt truſty, diligent and charie,
               Her Miſtreſſe Errands to and fro to carry)
               Goe quickly Efren, ſeeke me IOSEPH out,
               And if the buſineſſe he is now about
               Be not too earneſt, and too inſtant too,
               But what he may as well heereafter doe,
               
                  
Bid him forth-with to come and ſpeake with Mee.
            
            
               Wingd with her words, about it ſtraight runs ſhe:
               And, after ſummons, IOSEPH comes anon
               Vp to his Lady; who then all alone,
               Firſt with a Bluſh, and baſhfull glanſe among,
               From quiuering boſome, with a ſhiuering tongue,
               Thus breakes the Ice (ſtil bidding him come neerer)
               Deare, my deare Ioſeph, then mine own Eyes dearer.
               Shall I intreat thee, what I might command,
               To anſwer truly what I ſhall demand?
            
            
               Madame, ſaid he, Should I be falſe to you?
               What ere it be, I ſweare to tell you true.
            
            
               I heare (quoth ſhe) that thou art deepe in Loue:
               If it be true (thou muſt thy Truth approue)
               Thou maiſt not hide it; though my ſelfe were ſhe,
               For whom thou ſuffereſt, thou muſt tell it me:
               Confeſſe it freely: and I muſt confeſſe
               As much to Thee; for, Thee I loue no leſſe:
               So, louing Both, we ſhall haue matuall Fewell,
               Nor Thou to Mee, nor I to Thee be cruell:
               Ioyne hands, ioyne hearts, how happy manifold!
               How great! how grac't! how will I heap thee gold!
               Thus ſhe proteſts, and with a ſodaine kiſſe
               Vpon his Lips ſhe ſeales her Promiſes.
            
            
               
                  
He, red for ſhame, ſelfe-ſadly ruminates
               His Heauenly Angels ſacred Caueats
               
               Againſt Temptations and Attempts vniuſt,
               Of Idoles ſeruice, and vnlawfull Luſt:
               Internall praying for ſupernall Strength,
               In modeſt manner Thus replies at length:
            
            
               Madame, what euer of my Loue you heare,
               How-euer feruent, or how deepely-deere;
               If you haue heard it, as (perhaps) impure,
               Vnchaſte, vnhoneſt Loue; I you aſſure
               None loue I ſo; nor wiſh I (I proteſt)
               So to be lov'd: and of my Lady, leaſt.
               My Lord, you know, hath nothing from me kept,
               I all command, onely your ſelfe except:
               And ſhall I then, diſloyall, Traitor proue
               Vnto my Lord; and to My God aboue?
               No, God forbid: No, rather let me dye;
               And in the ſands vnburied euer lye,
               A prey to Birds and Beaſts: and as he ſpake,
               She and her Chamber did he quick forſake.
            
            
               Shee, ſeeing then her Hopes ſo ſodaine daſht,
               Her ſelfe deluded; as with Lightning flaſht,
               Stands firſt a while moueleſſe, amaz'd and mute;
               Then grindes a Groan, and many ſighes purſue't:
               
                  
Then wrings her hands, falls backward on her bed,
               Diſtract in minde, her colour pale and dead.
            
            
               All which obſerued by that Diuell-Owle,
               
               Vpon the Roofe, he putteth off the Fowle,
               And re-puts-on Nurſe Iphicle a ſpace,
               To viſit Iempſar in ſo pitious Caſe.
               Alas! quoth ſhe, What ailes my Lady deere?
               My tender Nurſling, What hath hapned heere?
               Why are you daunted and deiected ſo?
               Be of good Cheere; be of good Comfort: Lo,
               I, I am heere; looke on me, looke, my Lamb,
               Your helpe at need, your louing Nurſe I am.
            
            
               At name of Nurſe, her ſomewhat ſhe erects,
               And with theſe Taunts a frowning glance reflects:
               Nurſe, once a Nurſe, or Mother more then Nurſe,
               But now a Step-dam, or ſome Furie worſe.
               Thou, thou haſt kill'd mee, thou haſt quite vndone me,
               Thou toldſt me Ioſeph was enamoured on me,
               Deep, to the Death; &amp; when I come to proue him,
               Alas! he loues not, nor will let me loue him:
               Nay, Prayers, Proffers, Preſents cannot moue him
               Thou, thou haſt made me make my ſelfe a mocke;
               To ſhame my Name, to ſtaine my Houſe &amp; Stocke,
               To wrong my Lord, to breake my Faith, to fall;
               
                  
Thou wert the Author, thou the cauſe of all.
               What wanteth more, but with a murderous blade,
               This guilty Soule to ſend to endleſſe ſhade?
            
            
               Falſe Iphicle doth her as ſharpe reproue;
               Ah, fooliſh woman, vnexpert in Loue:
               What wonder was it, if a baſhfull boy,
               Vntraind, vntoucht (as Virgin) firſt were coy
               To heare of Loue, a Nouice, yet a Stranger,
               Doubtfull of you, perhaps; fearefull of danger.
               'Twas not the courſe: you haue miſcarried it.
               Then be not hartleſſe, neither hopeleſſe yet,
               For I will once more vndertake the matter,
               Ile chide his rudeneſſe, and inſtruct him better
               How to behaue him: Haue you Patience
               But for three daies, and on the fourth from hence
               Will reigne a gracious Starre, whoſe milde Aſpect
               On Loue and Louers gently doth reflect;
               Vnder whoſe Radiance, in Coniunction ſweet,
               
                  Hymen and Cupid in one inſtant meet.
            
            
               With theſe her Words Iempſar, part re-cheard,
               Her ſinking heart againe a little rear'd:
               Then Goe, ſaid ſhe, the Gods grant better ſpeed:
               And that we may the better now ſucceed,
               We will the while the ſacred powers implore,
               
                  
Frequent their Altars, and their Shrines adore.
            
            
               Next morning therefore, by what time the Sun
               With glittering Rayes had gilt the Horizon,
               
               
                  Iempſar decks her, goodly to behold,
               In Scarlet, ſet with Iewels and with Gold
               (But much more goodly for her louely grace,
               And natiue Beauties of her Forme and Face)
               And to the Temple with a Traine ſhe tends,
               Of Matrons, Maidens, Seruāts, Neighbors, Friends.
            
            
               Among the reſt, the Steward alſo went,
               Faire-featur'd IOSEPH, with his Eyes downe bent,
               As inlie pitying with a griefe vnſhowne,
               His Ladies Paſſions as he did his owne:
               For, he ſuppoſ'd her gaite to Church had bin
               To ſeeke for Mercy, and forſake her ſinne:
               But, nothing leſſe; Shee all the gods requires,
               To friend her loue, and further her deſires:
               And ſo the next day, and the next enſuing,
               And euery day ſtill greater Gifts renuing,
               The reaking Entrailes of her Offrings viewing.
               But, when the fourth, long-wiſhed, wel-come day
               
                  Titan 'gan burniſh with his burning Ray,
               Haile happy day (ſaid ſhee) haile holy Lights,
               That fauours Louers, and that loue delights:
               
                  
And by your power and gracious Influence,
               Preſerue the Worlds perpetuall Increments.
               And then ſhe ſends for the beloued Lad:
               Who, ſelfely good, ſuſpecting nothing bad,
               Suppoſing now his Miſtreſſe minde reclaim'd,
               At leaſt from daring what before ſhe aim'd,
               Comes inſtantly: Shee, by the Nurſe ſeduc't,
               Preſuming All to her content conduc't;
               Nor ſooner ſpies him, but ſhe ſprings for haſte,
               About his necke her Iuory Armes ſhe caſt:
               Shee holds him, hugs him; ſaying, Welcome Mine,
               Mine, Mine thou art, and I am onely Thine:
               Then, Why delay we? Why defer wee thus
               Our ioynt delights, ſith none can hinder vs?
               Why burn we Day-light? Hence with Fear &amp; Sloth.
               Let's mix our Loues. This Bed will ſerue vs Both:
               She leapes vpon't, and like a Nay-leſſe Wooer,
               Holding his Cloake, ſhe puls him hard vnto her.
            
            
               The goodly Youth, as beautifull as blameleſſe,
               Amaz'd, aſham'd, to ſee his Lady ſhameleſſe,
               Roplyes, Alas! (Thus ſharpe reprouing her)
               Late Noble Wife of Noble Potipher,
               
               What mood? what madnes hath obdur'd your mind,
               To dare theſe Pranks, vncomely and vnkinde?
               
                  
To ſhame your Selfe, your Sex, your Houſe, your State,
               To wrong my Lord, and me vnfortunate?
               Theſe are the fruits of Eaſe-full Idleneſſe,
               Of wanton Pride, of waſtfull Pampredneſſe;
               From whence the Fiends (our foes) aduantage cull,
               To kill our Soules, and fill our Sins-ſacke full:
               For, 'tis not Iphicle, your Nurſe, your Friend,
               As you ſuppoſe: no, 'tis a helliſh Fiend,
               A Hag, a Furie ſent from Sulphury Styx,
               
               That thus deludes you with deceits and tricks:
               Shee dar'd, and did attempt to tampt me too;
               But, God forbad: ſhe me no hurt could doe.
               I ſaw her ſhrinking out, as I came in:
               I know the fained forme ſhe masketh in:
               I feele the Sulphury fume, the filthy Sent
               She left behinde her, when away ſhe went.
            
            
               He hauing ſpoken; from behinde the dore,
               The ſubtle Fury (lurking there before)
               With ſodaine ruſh did cruſh the poſts in ſunder;
               And comming in, fills all with feare and wonder;
               When ghaſtly ſquinting, griezly, Thus ſhe ſpake
               With helliſh voyce: Indeed you doe miſſ-take,
               Falſe, Iphicle I am not: I am one
               Oh th' Odious Siſters, ſent from Acheron,
               
               
                  
I'll make you proue it now: then forth ſhe drew
               A poyſonous Snake, and it at IOSEPH threw:
               But, th' Heauenly Warder ſtill repeld it back,
               And all th' endeuours fruſtrate ſtill did make:
               Vnable therefore Him to hurt at all,
               Towards Iempſar doth it ſoftly crawle,
               With ſlippery windings, wrigling to and fro:
               Into her skirts at length it twineth ſo,
               That vp it creepes, and quicke into her gets,
               Gnawes all her bowells, and deſpitefull ſpets
               His helliſh poyſon in her inmoſt heart.
            
            
               The Lad, thus frighted, quick away did ſtart,
               To his owne Chamber; and perplext in minde,
               Forgetfull he had left his cloake behinde.
            
            
               Seeing him fled, and feeling in her wombe
               The fretting Venome; wholly ouercome,
               In ragefull fury, ſodainely ſhe falls,
               And, Help, Help, Help, with a loud Cry ſhe calls,
               So loud and ſhrill, that all the Court it heard,
               And all the houſe, and neighbours neere it ſcar'd;
               As if within had 
                     •••
                  ne ſome ſodaine fire
               Which inſtantly would to the roofe aſpire.
               Help, Women, Help, quicke, quickly. O! the Slaue,
               The Iew, the Raſcall, the yong Hebrew knaue,
               
                  
Euen now (ô Gods!) finding me heere alone,
               (O the bold Villaine! Hath the like been known?)
               Dar'd t'haue defil'd great Potiphar his Bed;
               And, but my Nurſe me timely reſcued,
               Had rauiſht me (O, horrid thing to thinke!)
               But hearing Helpe, away the Slaue did ſlinke,
               And left, for haſte, his Cloak behind him heere.
               With Hue and Crye, purſue him far and neere,
               Lay hold on him, and lay him faſt in Hold;
               And let my Lord of his Abuſe be told.
            
            
               Thus fell Iempſar her complaint prefers.
               All which, and more, falſe Iphicle auers,
               And aggrauares, adiudging him exempt
               From pitie, fit to hang for ſuch attempt
               So inſolent, ſo impudent; and whets
               The hearers hearts. Then cloſe away ſhe gets,
               Vnſeene, and Owle-like in a Clowd inuolv'd,
               Her borrow'd Body into Aire diſſolv'd;
               Deſcending ſwift from whence ſhe came, to tell
               Her good-ill ſeruice, and ſucceſſe, in Hell.
            
            
               Poore IOSEPH then his fellowes felly ſeaze;
               And, haſty, hurry him towards Little-Eaſe:
               Faine would he ſpeake, but none would hear a word;
               None, none at all, and leaſt of all his Lord,
               
                  
Whom the Report already had incenſt;
               Yet not with Death to haue him recompenc't:
               But, in a Dungeon (worſe then Death) to dwell,
               For worſt Offenders the moſt loathſome Cell;
               There, kept Cloſe-Priſoner, to be barely fed
               With puddle-water, and with Barly-bread.
            
            
               But, better kept by his ſupernall Keeper
               (Yet, more his dear, the more their woes be deeper)
               A winged Watch-man ſhining heauenly bright,
               Is ſent to IOSEPH (when the firſt ſad Night
               With ſable Courtin had beclowded all)
               Who entring (through the Wicket and the Wall)
               Into the Priſon, with a new-come Ray
               Lightning the dungeon, driuing Night away,
               With ſpirituall Comforts, and with ſpeeches kinde,
               Cancels his feares, and well confirmes his minde.
            
            
               This, from a Tower th' Aegyptian Keeper ſpy'd:
               Some God, ſome God is in the Light, he cry'd.
               I know, ſuch Splendor, and the ſpeech I heard,
               If it be God, it muſt be needs inferd
               This Lad is guiltleſſe of the crime pretended.
               For, Innocents iuſt IOVE hath aye defended.
               Thenceforth, to IOSEPH bare he great reſpect,
               A kinde of Reuerence, with a kinde Affect;
               
                  
Tooke off the Irons from his hands and feete;
               Fed, lodg'd him better, made his priſon ſweet;
               Viſits him oft, intreats him friendly faire,
               With louing Comforts; lets him take the Aire.
            
            
               Now, twice foure Roundels Phoebe had compleat,
               When, on ſuſpicion of ſome treacherous feat
               Of poys'ning Pharao's Bread (as went the Fame)
               Two were committed from the Court (by name,
               The Kings chiefe Baker, and chiefe Butler, too)
               To the ſame Gaile where IOSEPH hath to doe.
               For, now his Keeper truſted him ſo deepe,
               He made him Keeper, and of nought took keepe.
            
            
               In ſhort time after, Eyther, in one night
               Dreamed a Dream; whence the next morrow light,
               Pain'd and perplexed, what they might portend,
               Too ſadly ſerious ſeem'd they to perpend.
               Which IOSEPH noting: Gentlemen, I pray,
               How hap (quoth he) you are ſo ſad to day.
            
            
               To-night (ſayd they) we dreamed each a Dreame,
               But none we finde that can interpret them:
               And that's our trouble. Can you tell them me?
               Come, let me heare them, if you can, quoth he;
               It may pleaſe God we may haue ſight therein.
               Right gladly, ſaid the Butler, I'll begin.
               
                  
Me thought I ſaw a greene and goodly Vine,
               With three faire Branches, budding, blowing fine,
               Then flowring freſh, then ſwelling Cluſters bluſh,
               Whoſe ſpumy Iuyce in Pharao's cup I cruſh,
               Which with my hand into his hand I raught,
               Whereof the King tooke-in his wonted Draught.
            
            
               Then, thus the Lad: I'll tel your Dreams Portent.
               Firſt, by that goodly Vine your Life is Meant;
               The Buds, Flowers, Fruits, be fruits your ſelfe haue bore,
               Your Seruices, your Vertues here-tofore,
               Which ſhall be guerdon'd, you reſtor'd to grace;
               The three faire Branches are but three dayes ſpace,
               When in your wonted manner you ſhall bring
               The wonted Cup vnto your Lord the King.
               Then, when with Pharaoh you ſhall gracious be
               (If I be worthy) but remember me,
               And that vnworthy I am heere detain'd.
            
            
               The Baker, hearing This thus right explain'd,
               Said, let me alſo, if you pleaſe, I pray,
               Report my Viſion; and your Verdict ſay.
               Me thought I had three Baskets on my head,
               Two full of Flower, the third of fineſt Bread,
               Made with moſt Art and Cunning that I might;
               But, all anon the Birds deuoured quite.
               
                  
Then ſaid the good Interpre'r: Things to come
               Are knowne to GOD; Men often faile in ſome:
               Yet, what I gheſſe and gather of this matter,
               I'll tell you true: I cannot, may not, flatter.
            
            
               That which you ſaw the Baskets filled with,
               Of diuers kindes, your Life betokeneth:
               The Flower your former, ſimple and ſincere;
               The Bread, your later, compound (as it were)
               Of all deceipts, Theft, Plotting, Poyſoning,
               Treaſon, and all diſcouer'd to the King;
               Who, for reward of theſe fowle Crimes, by Law
               Will hang you vp: and then the Birds you ſaw,
               Rav'ns, Vultures, Eagles, Kites &amp; carren Crowes,
               Shall eat your Carcaſe, peck your Eyes and Noſe.
               Within three daies, your Baskets number notes:
               Yet I may erre, and you may change your Lots.
               For, GOD doth change, when Men do change frō ill,
               His mediate Worke, not his immediate Will.
            
            
               This paſt, their Parts both diuers pondering,
               On the third day came Warrant from the King,
               To cleare and to declare the Butler Quit,
               And hang the Baker, at firſt ſight of it.
            
            
               Accordingly, from Priſon both are brought;
               But, to a diuers End, with diuers thought:
               
                  
Th' one with reproach, th' other with good report;
               Th' one to the Cart, the other to the Court;
               Th' one to the Gallowes, th' other to be grac't
               Of Prince and Peeres, and in his roome re-plac't;
               With Caps and Claps, with cheerful ſhouts &amp; ſongs
               Wellcom'd, rewarded, honor'd for his wrongs.
            
            
               Thrice through the Zodiak had Hyperian pranc't,
               And fourthly now his fiery Teeme aduanc't,
               When quiet ſtretcht vpon his Iuory bed,
               In ſweeteſt ſleepe, well toward Morning-ſted,
               To mighty Pharao the Almighty ſent
               A double Dreame, of ſo deepe Conſequent,
               That wondring much, the King awoke withall,
               Conceiuing it ſome high Prognoſticall.
               
            
            
               Wherefore, forth-with he ſummons farre &amp; wide,
               Through Aegypt and Chaldea, from each ſide,
               All that had knowledge in Aſtrologie,
               
               Cunning in Spels, or Skill in Prophecie,
               Or could fore-tell by Magick from below;
               Or from aboue, by Oracles fore-ſhow;
               Or by in-ſight of Sacrificed Heards;
               By Fire, by Water, or by Flight of Birds,
               Or by their Songs; by Sand, by Geomancy;
               
               Or by what-euer Heathen Feat or Phantſie.
            
            
               
                  
Then ſwarm'd the Court with Sages of all ſorts,
               Of diuers habits, and of diuers ports.
               Some on their Heads wore Hornes, hairy &amp; horrid,
               Som with thick Turbands did ſurroūd their forehed,
               Some with high Miters, ſome with trayling whoods,
               Some with rich Garlands, ſet with precious Studs;
               But, broad long-bearded all, adown their Chinne,
               With ſad aſpect, and of a ſallow skinne.
            
            
               Whom when before him Pharaoh had admitted,
               He tells his Dreames, firſt; then (as him befitted)
               Propoundeth Honors and rich Recompence
               To whom-ſoeuer ſhall expound the ſenſe,
               And ſets them dayes, &amp; nights, &amp; times, &amp; houres,
               To bring their Anſwere: But (beyond their powers)
               Daies, Nights, Times, Hours, they break, none doth appeare
               T'explane the Dreame, or the Kings doubt to cleare:
               Neyther their Spheres, Spels, Circles, Sorceries,
               Birds, Beards, nor Miters, could decypher This.
               Angry therefore, and thenceforth grieuing deepe,
               The King would hear none, but did priuate keepe.
            
            
               The Butler then remembring (at the laſt)
               During his Durance what before had paſt,
               (Which hitherto, as Courtiers, yet, for moſt,
               Good Turnes receiv'd, he had forgot, or croſt.)
               
                  
How truly IOSEPH by their Dreames did tell,
               What to the Baker and himſelfe befell;
               Fell on his knees, and cryes vnto the King,
               Pardon, My Liege, my ſtolid lingering,
               To tell your Highneſſe, in this manner mou'd,
               What (late) in priſon I both ſaw and prou'd.
            
            
               Your Maieſty (no doubt) remembers yet,
               Your Baker and my ſelfe you did commit
               To your High Marſhalls Tower; where then wee found
               An Hebrew Youth, a Priſoner (on falſe ground,
               As may be gheſt) late Page to Potiphar.
               
            
            
               Both growne in time with him familiar,
               Both of vs dreamed in one very night;
               Both of our Dreames to Him we did recite;
               Both he expounded; and both did ſucceed
               To both of vs, as he of both did reed.
            
            
               To me, ſaid he, Thou ſhalt in three daies ſpace,
               Returne to Court, recouer Place and Grace:
               But, to the Baker; Thou (ſaid he) that day
               Shalt be hangd vp, for rauening Birds a Prey,
               Vnleſſe thy faults thou canſt ſo quicke repent,
               That change of life thy threatned death preuent:
               (For, GOD doth chāge, when men do change frō Ill,
               His mediate Worke, not his immediate Will.)
               
                  
All which, for True, before your Eyes is cleere;
               The Baker hangd: and I your Butler, heere.
               Vpon my Life, my Lord, your hidden Dreame
               That Lad will read: he hath ſome Spirit ſupreame.
            
            
               Herewith the King re-cheerd, and inly glad,
               Commands him ſtraight, Go, quickly fetch the Lad,
               And in Our Name him inſtantly inlarge.
            
            
               Forthwith he hies him to performe his charge;
               Gets forth the Priſoner, ſhifts him, ſuits him preſt,
               Of his owne coſt, and hath him barb'd and dreſt;
               And then conducts him, baſhfull, to the King;
               Who well beholds the Lad, likes euery thing;
               Then queſtions thus: They tell me, Youth, that you
               Interpret Dreames; now, tell me, Tell they true?
            
            
               My gracions Lord, ſaid IOSEPH, God alone
               Immediately knows Dreames; and other none,
               Saue onely ſuch to whom that ſacred Gift
               Th' Almighty daignes: I may my Prayer lift
               Vnto my GOD for you, my Lord, and ſhall:
               It may be, He will grant this grace withall.
               For, ay with ſpeciall care he guides the things,
               That long to Kings; as onely King of Kings.
               A while then inly did he meditate:
               Then, prayes the King his Viſions to relate.
            
            
               
                  
Me thought, ſaid Pharaoh, by Niles banke I ſtood,
               And ſodainely from out the ſiluer Flood,
               Came ſeauen faire Kine, which ranging far &amp; wide,
               Fed in the Meades along the Riuers ſide,
               On Oxe-lips, Cowes-lips, Trifole and the reſt,
               Which for the Altar fat our Beaſts the beſt.
            
            
               Scarſe had I turn'd mine eye, when on the ſhore,
               Me-thought in th' inſtant came vp 7. Kine more,
               With ſtaring haire, too-weake to ſtand alone,
               Ill-fauoured, lanke, and leane, bare skin &amp; bone;
               As poorely fed, With Holly, Broome, and Heath,
               Anatomies, or liuing Formes of Death.
            
            
               Amaz'd with this, yet was I more anon,
               When theſe (me thought) for hunger, ſet vpon
               The former ſeuen, and ſo to worke did fall,
               That ſodainely they had deuour'd them all.
            
            
               Heerewith I waked: and anon agen
               Sweet ſlumber caught me, and I dreamed then
               I ſaw ſeuen goodly full faire Eares of Corne,
               Riſe from one ſtraw, ſcarce able to be borne:
               And by and by, ſeuen other Eares there ſprung
               Light, chaffie, blaſted, thin and cloſely clung,
               Which in like manner greedily did eat
               And quicke conſume the 7. full Eares of Wheat.
            
            
               
                  
Theſe were my Dreames, which I haue oft propoū
                  ded
               To many, yet by none can be expounded.
               Now, if for Thee this Honor be reſeru'd,
               If Thee alone my deeper Dreames deſerv'd;
               Then, happy Youth, reioyce with all thy heart,
               Eternall Fame ſhall trumpet thy deſart:
               And, with Reward we ſhall ſo richly ſtore thee,
               That in all Aegypt none ſhall be before thee.
            
            
               Great King, ſaid Ioſeph, both your Dreams be one,
               Sent downe from God, to be reueal'd by none
               (How-euer wiſe, how euer full of Parts,
               How-euer complete in all depth of Arts)
               
               Saue by ſome Veſſell of his owne Election,
               To whom he daignes the grace of his direction:
               And therefore could your Sages nothing ſhow,
               Not knowing God, though All-thing els they know.
               Know this, ô King: God by This Viſion ſends,
               To let you know what ſhortly he intends.
            
            
               Your ſeuen fat Bullocks are ſeuen fruitfull yeeres,
               Which through all Aegypt ſhal oreflow your ſhieres,
               While Nile, far fatter than to-fore he wont,
               Shall farder ſpread his ſlimy Sweat vpon't;
               When happy Memphis ſhall ſuch Plenty ſee,
               That your old Barnes ſhall, all, too little be:
               
                  
Your Riekes, your Garners, and your Bartons, All,
               Too narrow for your Crops, too ſhort, too ſmall!
               And, to confirme it, that it ſhall be ſo,
               Your ſeuen full Eares but the ſame thing fore-ſhow.
               Now be you pleas'd, my great and gracious Prince,
               To heare the reſt with heed and Patience:
               For, 7. poore yeeres theſe 7. rich years ſhall follow,
               Whoſe Penury their Plenty ſoone ſhall ſwallow;
               When Nile ſhall ſhrinke into his Chanell, nye
               Leauing the Ridges and the Furrows dry,
               Fields ſcorched, parched, burned euen to duſt,
               Both Solſtices like deawleſſe and aduſt:
               No Torrents guſhing from the Mountain tops,
               Nor (vnder Cancer) on the Aethyops
               
               Any returne of Winter's Moiſt againe,
               Nor any help of ſweet and timely Raine:
               So that the Husband cannot plough his Land;
               Or if he could, he ſhould but plough the ſand,
               And caſt his Seed amid the ſame to burne,
               Without all hope of any Crops returne,
               Or of increaſe: but rather preſt, for need,
               To quit his Plough, and on his Oxen feed.
               Your ſeuen leane Bullocks, &amp; ſeuen ſlender Eares,
               Deuouring, ſhew theſe ſeuen deuouring yeeres.
               
                  
This is your Dreame, ô King; and doubled Thus,
               That, more aſſured, more ſolicitous,
               More ſpeedily you may prouide before
               (Thus warn'd by GOD) a Salue vnto this Sore.
            
            
               Which, how to doe, (of me if you demand)
               I would aduiſe you firſt through all the Land,
               To build new Garners, long and large enough,
               From time to time to ſtore vp all the ſtuffe,
               That may be ſpared thoroughout your State,
               During thoſe Yeares of Plenty fortunate;
               Allowing onely for each Houſeholds need,
               And for their Land, a Competence of Seed.
            
            
               You muſt haue alſo Treaſure ready ſtill
               To buy this Store, if well proceed you will.
               And to this end, let there a man be ſought
               Diſcreet and wiſe, to wield it as it ought.
               Let him haue power, as in your Royall Name,
               Through all your Kingdome to diſpoſe the ſame;
               And vnderneath him to ſubordinate
               Sub-Officers, to ſerue him and the State.
            
            
               Thus IOSEPH counſeld: &amp; the while the King,
               With ſilence all maturely pondering,
               At laſt breakes out in ioyfull admiration,
               There is (no doubt) a Diuine Inſpiration
               
                  
In this yong man. Without a ſpirit Diuine,
               Of future things, none could ſo deepe define:
               There is none like him, none to match him neere,
               In all Chaldaea, nor in Egypt heere.
            
            
               Then, on his necke, ſhedding a ſhowre of Ioy,
               The King imbrac't, and kindely grac't the Boy;
               Then, thus beſpake him: Seeing God hath giuen
               Thee this to know, and to foreſhew, from Heauen;
               I know not one ſo wiſe and ſo diſcreet,
               Nor for this Office than thy ſelfe more meet.
               Thee, next to me, ſhall all my people ſerue,
               And call thee Sauiour: Thou doſt them preſerue.
            
            
               Then, on his backe a Purple robe he dons,
               Emboſſed round with rich and Orient Stones;
               About his necke a maſſie Chaine of Gold,
               And on his finger (as they wont of old)
               A royall Signet, a moſt precious Ring
               (Not to be worn by any, but the King,
               Or his Vice-gerent, whom he doth eſteeme
               And will haue deemed Second vnto Him)
               
               Which Pharaoh there then plucked from his owne,
               To put on IOSEPH's, that he might be knowne
               To be the Second to Himſelfe, in all.
               Then, on a Steed, the ſecond in his Stall,
               
                  
(Or ſecond Chariot) in this ſolemne Pompe
               He makes him ryde; and with the ſound of Trumpe
               Proclaimes, before him that they bow the knee
               To his Vice-gerent, to This Second Hee,
               
               To this Preſeruer of their State; or rather
               To this (adopted Sonne) their Countries Father;
               This Prince of Worth, this more then Man, this Miracle,
               This happy, holy, Heauen-inſpired Oracle;
               Who, the Kings Dreames in time interpreting,
               Had ſav'd themſelues, their Country &amp; their King.
            
            
               With all theſe Honors, and with Wealth conferd,
               With all applauſe good IOSEPH is preferd,
               To rule all Aegypt: which with great Dexteritie,
               Wiſedome and Worth, Care, Courage, &amp; Sincerity,
               He executes: And firſt, his Circuit rides
               O're all the Land; Barnes euery where prouides,
               Which in thoſe Plentious Yeeres he fils with Store,
               Of euery kinde. And, ſith it is no more
               Vertue to purchaſe than preſerue what's got,
               He ſlips no time, but prudently doth plot
               To kill all Vermine, cut off all Exceſſe
               Of Gluttony and beaſtly Drunkenneſſe;
               Abates their need-les Beaſts, Dogs, Mules, &amp; Horſe,
               Rids idle Roagues and Vag'rants, that be worſe;
               
                  
And rather buyes-in, from the Coaſts about,
               Than by a Licence Iets a Corne goe out.
               Thus he proceeds: and GOD ſo bleſt his hand,
               That all things proſper'd ouer all the Land.
            
            
               There was a City call'd Heliopolis,
               
               (Whoſe Surname from the Sunne deriued is)
               Whoſe Prince (a Prieſt too, to Apollo's Grace)
               Had one faire Daughter, (faire indeed of Face
               And outward Feature; but, much more diuin'd
               For inward Beauties, Graces of the minde)
               Whom Phoebus oft conſulted with, had ſhow'n,
               
                  Not to be matcht to any of their Owne:
               
               
                  But, by a higher Fate, reſerv'd to be
               
               
                  A Strangers Bride, with greater Dignity
               
               
                  To raiſe her Name, and honor her Poſterity.
               
            
            
               This Oracle at IOSEPH points in Verity,
               Thinks Phoebus Prieſt and great King Pharaoh, too:
               And to this end, th' Iſaacian Prince they wooe.
               When Aegypt now ſeuen happy yeeres had had,
               All plentifull, all proſperous and glad;
               It pleas'd the King, with Royall Pomp and State,
               Theſe Nuptiall Bands to knit and conſummate
               With ſumptuous feaſts; and (to prolong their ioyes)
               With Tilts and Tourneys, Dances, Maskes, &amp; toyes,
               
                  
So long, that now the ſeuen rich Years, at laſt,
               Were ended all, and all their Plenty paſt.
            
            
               And now, Sol's Palfreys, hauing paſt the Twins,
               Were poſting hotly towards Cancer's Innes,
               When the Aegyptians could no more perceiue
               
                  Nile's ouer-flood, nor any mud to leaue;
               But, pure, vnpudled on the ſand to ſlide,
               And in his Bottom him well-neere to hide:
               Their whilome fertile ſoyle now ſerely riues,
               Yawnes wide for thirſt, no hope of Harueſt giues:
               If any ſeed be ſowne, it neuer ſprings,
               Or neuer buds, or neuer beares; or brings
               Vnhappy Darnell, or dry Poppy ſeed,
               Or is deuour'd by Vermines hungry breed.
               So that they liue of former Yeeres remaines,
               Which hardly yet the firſt hard Yeere ſuſtaines;
               But men are faine to Graſſe and Rats to fall,
               To harmeleſſe Creatures, vncleane Beaſts and all.
            
            
               Then, to the King, City and Country fly
               To ſue for Comfort, and to ſeeke ſupply:
               He to his Vice-roy IOSEPH them refers;
               He, inſtantly to vnder-Officers,
               Who (by His Order) furniſh all their Wants,
               At equall Price; yet doe ſo high aduance
               
                  
The Kings aduantage, that from farre and nye
               The Wealth of all runnes to his Treaſury:
               His Checquer's full: yet had they paſt (alas!)
               Scarce foure hard yeeres, and had 3. more to paſſe.
               What ſhall they do, poor ſoules? How will they ſhift?
               Now nothing haue they, but their bare Lands left:
               Thoſe they would ſell; but, Who (Alas!) ſhuld buy?
               None hath the Purſe, except the King. They try
               The Prudent Vice-roy: who approues the thing,
               Bargains and buyes a Fift part for the King.
            
            
               This Famine raging fiercely euery where,
               Fame bruits abroad (which came to Iacobs eare)
               That yet in Aegypt they were ſtor'd ſo well,
               That they had Corne enough, and ſome to ſell:
               Old Izrael therefore calling vp his Sonnes,
               You ſee, ſaith he, our ſhort Prouiſions:
               You ſee how like we are to ſtarue and pine,
               And periſh all, without the hand Diuine:
               I heare there's Corne in Aegypt to be bought;
               Methink, ere now, you ſhuld your ſelues haue thoght
               It time to goe: Goe, get you quickly thither,
               Take Coine and Sacks: goe, hye you all togither,
               Saue Beniamin. The other Tenne agree,
               And, furniſht fit, ſet forth immediately.
            
            
               
                  
Arriv'd in Aegypt, they eft-ſoones enquire
               The Great Corne-Master; lowting lowe, deſire
               Corn for their money; IOSEPH knows them brim
               To be his Brethren: but they know not Him.
               He well remembers their vnkindneſſe paſt,
               (And, wrong receiv'd, draws ſtrōg reuenge too faſt.)
               Yet, for Gods ſake, his Fathers, and his Brothers
               (Yong Beniamin's) he ſpareth all theſe others;
               And ſpeakes to Them, but ſtrangely and auſtere:
               Whence? what are you? you (Sirs) that cluſter there?
            
            
               My Lord, Your Seruants are one Iacobs Sonnes;
               We come from Canaan (where our Father wonnes)
               Compeld by Famine, (which there rageth ſore)
               To ſeeke your Fauour; of your happy Store,
               To daign vs for our Money what you may.
               Our Father hath great Houſhold to defray,
               Himſelfe, Eleuen of Vs, our Little Fry,
               Shepheards and Bondmen a great company:
               And therefore hither are we come, my Lord,
               To craue the Helpe your Fauour may afford,
               To ſaue ſo many liues, that may be able,
               And ſhall be willing (ſome way ſeruiceable)
               To thanke your Lordſhip: for, our Father raignes
               As King in Sichem, and he ſtocks the Plaines
               
                  
With goodly Flocks of many Thouſand Sheepe,
               And ſtore of Cattle of all kindes doth keepe:
               Vouchſafe vs therefore of your Corne, we pray,
               That we may liue, what euer price we pay:
               For, we come hither, not to beg, but buy.
            
            
               * To buy? ſaid IOSEPH; nay, I doubt to ſpye:
               Spyes are ye all; ſo many ſturdy Clownes
               To troope at once through all our Forts &amp; Towns,
               To view and to ſuruay our Strength and ſtore,
               And ſo the weakeneſſe of the Land explore.
               Yet tell me of your Father and your Brother:
               But, I beleeue neyther the one, nor other:
               Where's your Commiſſion? Where's your Fathers Teſt?
               Why came not that one Brother with the reſt?
               Or why came you ſo many? It is cleere
               * You come to ſpy: and you ſhall buy it deere.
               Thus, though his heart did melt, his bowels yerne,
               He faines him fierce, and beares him roughly ſtern.
            
            
               They, proſtrate all, beſeech him not ſuſpect
               Them any ſuch. Our comming was direct,
               We ſweare (ſay they): The witnes we implore
               Of th' onely GOD our Father doth adore,
               Our Father ſent vs; Famine droue vs hither;
               For Corne we come: and that we come together,
               
                  
Our need, our number, and our diſtance, craue
               At once as much as we at once can haue:
               Our other Brother is but yet a Lad
               (And all the comfort that our Father had)
               Too yong to trauell ſuch a iourney yet;
               Which, vpon vs our Father layd, more fit.
               We thought on no Commiſſion: for, indeed
               In ſuch a caſe we thought there none ſhould need.
               Be good vnto vs, good my Lord, we pray,
               Pity our Father, (and if pity may
               Pearce you at all) pity our Brothers caſe,
               Pity our Babes, the hope of all our Race.
            
            
               Twixt ouer-ioyd, his eyes will needs run ouer,
               Which, yet a while, he turnes aſide to couer:
               Then, thus returnes; Your cunning anſwer ſhowes
               That you are falſe. Truth needs not ſuch a Gloſe:
               I am reſolv'd, and can belieue no other.
               By th' Life of Pharaoh, till you fetch your Brother,
               You ſhall not hence, one Hoſtage ſhall remaine,
               The reſt ſhall goe well loden home with graine:
               This fauour will I doe, expect no other,
               Nor moue me more, vntill you bring your brother,
               To teſtifie your Stories are not lyes:
               Elſe, by the life of Pharaoh you are Spies.
               
                  
(Here, Sirra, Marſhall, take them to your charge,
               Looke none of them be let to goe at large)
               I'll giue you three daies Reſpit, to revolue;
               Then let me heare what herein you reſolue.
            
            
               They (inly prickt in their owne conſcience
               For cruelties committed, now long ſince,
               'Gainſt this their vnknowne Brother, now a Prince)
               Among themſelues debating what was beſt
               (Seeing the Vice-roy did ſo deepe proteſt)
               Thought moſt expedient, and reſolue in briefe,
               To ſend home Nine, loden with ſuch reliefe,
               To fetch their Brother; leauing one behinde:
               Which Part, by Lot, to Simeon was aſſign'd;
               Whom they for Hoſtage to the Prince preſent,
               (Vpon the third day) with their full intent.
               Then he commands their Sacks with Corn be fill'd:
               They pay for it; but, ſecretly he will'd,
               That each mans money ſhould againe be put
               Into his Sacke, and then the Sacke re-ſhut.
            
            
               So, now their Hoſtage in ſafe cuſtody,
               They lade their Aſſes, and full heauily
               Leaue Aegypt and their Brother; hying home,
               Vnto Samaria: where no ſooner come,
               
                  
But their olde Father, forthwith miſſing one,
               Cryes, Where's your Brother? Where's my Simeon?
               
               What, is he ſicke, or dead (I doubt me rather)?
               Neyther, ſaid Iuda, dead, nor ſicke, good Father:
               Hee's well in Health, but doth for pledge remaine
               In Aegypt, till we all goe backe againe,
               And bring with vs our Brother Beniamin:
               
               For, ſuch conditions muſt we enter in,
               Or elſe we could haue brought you nothing thence.
            
            
               The Man we dealt with, a Great Man, a Prince,
               Next to the King, at our arriuall there,
               Askt many queſtions, whence, and what we were:
               Whether we had a Father, or a Brother,
               In what eſtate, how old; and many other.
               We, doubting nothing, told him truly all:
               Then, more auſtere, and more maieſticall,
               Now I perceiue (ſaith he) that you are Spies,
               And all your Anſweres are ſo many Lyes:
               You come but to ſuruay our Strength, and Store,
               To finde our Weakenes, and our Wants explore:
               You tell me of your Father and your Brother,
               But I belieue neyther the one, nor other.
               Where's your Commiſſion? Where's your Fathers Teſt?
               Why came not that one Brother with the reſt?
               
                  
Or, Why came you ſo many? It is cleare,
               You come to ſpye, and you ſhall buy it deare.
            
            
               We anſwerd for our ſelues the beſt we could:
               All would not ſerue: Th' iſſue was this; we ſhould
               Leaue one for Hoſtage, and the other Nine
               Should bring home Corne, and bring him Beniamin,
               
               Or neuer to returne vnto that place,
               Or neuer dare to looke him in the face:
               For, by the Life of Pharaoh, we were ſpies,
               (That is his Oath) and all our Words were Lyes.
               Good Father Iacob hauing heard all this,
               With many a ſigh (as ſorrowes manner is)
               Is there, ſaith he, vnder the Heau'ns bright Eye,
               Another Father ſo diſtreſt as I?
               One Sonne is loſt; another, Priſoner left
               In a ſtrange Land; another, now bereft
               (By your deuice, or your aduice at leaſt)
               And all of you (I doubt me) all the reſt
               To be extinct, while I ſuruiue in feares
               Of ſo bad newes to come to my ſad eares.
               Firſt would to God (ſo God were not diſpleas'd)
               My dayes were ended, and my ſorrowes eas'd.
               Thus ſpeaking wept he, and thus weeping ſpake.
               His Sonnes with Comforts ſeeke his Care to ſlake,
               
                  
Saying, The Godly ſhould not feare ſo deepe,
               Sith God his ſeruants will more ſafely keepe.
            
            
               Then to their Sacks: Each hauing his vnknit,
               Each findes his money in the mouth of it.
               Amazed all: ſad Iacob, there-upon,
               Sons, Sons, (ſaid he) there lackt but this alone:
               This is enough to kill all Hope (as vaine).
               For, if to Egypt you returne againe,
               The mighty Man that fain'd you Spies before,
               Will find you Theeues now; &amp; what need he more,
               Hauing ſo ſiſted, and ſo ſought your Coat,
               To finde a hole, that he might cut your throat?
               No, no (I ſweare) my Beniamin, my Boy,
               Mine onely comfort left, mine onely Ioy,
               I will not hazard on ſo tickle ground:
               You, you ſhall goe that are ſo promiſe-bound,
               If you thinke good, and God will haue it ſo:
               And when you are determined to goe,
               I'll giue you all the golden good I haue,
               Iewells and Coyne, your Brother to vn ſlaue
               And ſaue your ſelues; and to beſtow in Corne,
               If God be pleaſed that you ſhall returne.
               On th' other ſide, againſt his Fathers Feares,
               Sad Iuda thus intreats him, euen with Teares.
            
            
               
                  
Deare Father, heare vs firſt; and then I pray
               Haue Care of vs, and of your ſelfe this day.
               For, how ſhall we vnto that Man returne,
               Who ſolemnly hath by his Pharaoh ſworne,
               Except we bring our brother Beniamin,
               
               Nor we, nor he that is there cooped in,
               Shall be diſmiſt: nor ſhall we haue the grace
               To heare his voyce, or euer ſee his face;
               Where, GOD he knowes, what ſhall of vs become:
               And how much better ſhall you be at home?
               How will you liue? Where will you haue to feed
               This multitude, if there we doe not ſpeed?
               Father, for Gods ſake follow my aduice:
               Vpon my perill, ſtand not off ſo nice.
               This Lad will ſaue both vs and you, and all;
               And, on my life, no hurt ſhall him befall:
               Two tender pledges leaue I heere of mine;
               If he miſcarry, let Them pay the Fine.
            
            
               Then doubt not, Father, lay your feare aſide,
               And prudently for you and yours prouide.
               That thus our money was return'd; no doubt,
               By his direction it was brought about:
               But, for a pitte-fall, or for Pity, rather,
               It is vncertaine: this is certaine, Father,
               
                  
He is reported, ouer all that Coaſt,
               To be a good man, and a godly-moſt;
               And, if the Whole be partly gheſt by Part,
               We ſaw ſome tokens of a tender heart:
               For, while to him we there did ſad relate
               The ſad diſtreſſes of our preſent ſtate,
               Of you and of our Brother, and our Brats;
               Our miſery he ſo compaſſionates,
               That hee euen wept: which though hee thought to hide,
               And turn'd away, yet many of vs ſpy'd.
               Wherefore, good Father, let vs loſe no time;
               Prolong no longer, neyther doubt the Clime,
               Nor feare the man, nor faint for any thing:
               We ſhall be ſafe vnder th' Almighties wing.
            
            
               This, vrg'd with teares; the Old man, ouercome,
               Cryes, Go on Gods name, God re-guide you home:
               Goe when you will, and with you take the Lad,
               And ſome beſt Preſents that may here be had
               In this hard time; Myrrhe, Storax, Almonds, Hony,
               
               
                  Gumme, Cinnamon, and therewith, double Money,
               Both for the former which you brought againe,
               And for the New, if Now you ſhall obtaine.
               And We the while will pray and pay our vowes,
               To th' euerlaſting Patron of our houſe.
               
                  
The Lord of Hoſts, our Fathers God and ours,
               To proſper and protect you with his pow'rs.
            
            
               Bluſhing Aurora ſweetly peeping out,
               When Sol againe had brought his Teeme about,
               The Father and the Sonnes, together all,
               All vp and ready, on their knees doe fall
               In due Deuotion, as they daily wont:
               Then to their Breakfaſt (not to dwell vpon't)
               Furniſht of what their Iourney did require,
               Gifts, Money, Beniamin. Their tender Sire,
               Weeping, Him kiſſing, and imbracing, Thus
               Bids ſad Adieu: Deare Sonne, Ay proſperous
               Thy iourney be. If Fates thee ſafe reſtore,
               Then wiſh I life; for Teares he could no more.
               Then to the reſt; imbracing, bleſſing all,
               While all for Bleſſing on their knees do call.
            
            
               They to their long-hard iourney ſettling them,
               Leauing Samaria and Ieruſalem;
               
               Paſt Idumaeas Palmy Groues, and paſt
               
                  Syrbonian Moores, Arabian Deſarts vaſt;
               At length arriue on Egypts wealthy Coaſt,
               And reach at laſt their Memphis wiſhed moſt.
               Whom gladly IOSEPH entertaineth there,
               And inſtantly lets out his Priſoner.
            
            
               
                  
Admitted then to gratious Audience,
               Thus Ruben ſpake: When we, Right Noble Prince,
               Returned home, had to our Father done
               Your high Commands touching his yonger Sonne,
               Whom you required to be hither brought;
               Opening our Sacks to ſhoot the Corne we bought,
               In euery Sacke we found our ſeuerall Sūm
               (Which God he knowes, wee know not, how ſhould come.)
               Our Father hearing what was come to paſſe,
               And, ſeeing it, deep-ſighing, cry'd, Alas!
               Alas! My ſonnes, I ſee ſome ſad Miſ-hap
               Hangs ouer vs: and all our old good hap
               Is croſt and canceld. Sees Heav'ns glorious eye
               Another Father ſo diſtreſt as I?
               Twelue ſonnes I had, and one (alas!) is loſt;
               Another, Priſoner in a forren coaſt;
               Another, now (mine only comfort left)
               Surrepted Thus, and You withall bereft:
               And all of you to goe I wot not whither
               (Made Theeues) perhaps to periſh all togither.
            
            
               We comfort, We thus preſſe with all our powers,
               O Father, truſt our Fathers God and ours
               And for the Man that now in Aegypt ſwayes,
               He is moſt iuſt, moſt gentle. Him they praiſe
               
                  
For their Preſeruer, and their Father there
               Pious and pure: then, What is thence to feare?
            
            
               Wonne with our words, at laſt with much adoe,
               He granted vs to bring his Darling too.
               Goe then, ſaid he, God to and fro direct you;
               And with his wings of Fauour ſtill protect you.
               Take with you Beniamin; and take withall
               (Such as our Country yeelds) theſe Preſents ſmall,
               Gumme, liquid Storax, bitter Almonds, Honey,
               
                  Myrrhe, Cinnamon: take alſo double money,
               To pay both for the Corne you had before,
               And for as much as now you ſhall bring more:
               And to that iuſt Man (as you ſay) commend
               Me and my Sonne: pray him to ſtand a Friend,
               To pity Him, and You, and Me, and All.
               So all good Hap to Him and You befall.
            
            
               While this he ſpake; The Prince, with much adoe
               Refraining Teares, cryes, Welcome all of you,
               Your Selues, your Preſents, and your Brother here,
               Who quits you from ſuſpect: Be of good Cheere,
               Goe waſh your weary Limbes from ſoile &amp; ſweat,
               And ſoone I pray come ſit with me at meat.
            
            
               Thus ſaid the Prince The ſeruants, ſome prepare
               Bath for their Foet; ſome Veſſels; ſome their Fare;
               
                  
Buttry and Pantry, ſome; ſome ſpread the Table;
               And other-ſome, as buſie in the Stable.
               Him-Selfe the while diſpatcht affaires of State,
               Heard Suites for Food, appointed each their Rate;
               And then returnes vnto his Gueſts againe;
               Showes them his ſtately Houſe, his Stuff, his Train,
               His gold and ſiluer Plate, ingrau'n, imboſt,
               Couches and Carpets of a wonderous Coſt;
               And round about, moſt ſumptuous to behold,
               Deepe Arras Hangings, all of ſilke and gold,
               Of ſundry Stories there ſo liuely wrought,
               That, almoſt, liuing were the Figures thought;
               Such ſprightly Poſtures, and ſo ſpeaking Geſtures,
               So natiue Viſages, ſo naturall Veſtures.
            
            
               Faith-famous Abra'm, after Heav'ns beheſt,
               Leads heere his Iſaac to be kill'd, as Beaſt.
               The Lad here loads the Aſſe with Holmen ſprayes:
               The Father makes the Pile: Hereon he layes
               His bond-led, blind-led Sonne: his hand, heau'd vp,
               An Angell holds, and there is held a Tup.
            
            
               There, Iacob, flying his rough Brothers wrath,
               Hyes him amaine towards his natiue Path,
               His Fathers ancient Seat, and happy Realme,
               Betwixt ſwift Tigris, and th' Euphratean Streame.
               
                  
There, at a Well his Vncle's Daughter aides,
               Drawing vp Water for the tender Maides:
               There, on the Downes he tends their Fathers ſheep,
               Seruing for Rachel double Prentiſhip.
            
            
               While Iſr'els glad Sonnes (at this wealth amaz'd,
               Now full of Hope, on theſe things greedy gaz'd,
               Great IOSEPH calls (for, Supper was gone vp.)
               Come, giue vs Water: It is time to ſup:
               Then, tall, he ſets him in his Iuory Chaire,
               And bids them ſit, and treats them wondrous faire.
            
            
               Heere, Death preuenting Fracaſtorius,
               
               This, late begun, He left vn-ended Thus.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

