
   
      
         
            The association of the princes of France with the protestations and declarations of their allegeance to the King. Also a discourse vpon the surrendry of the seales into the Kings hands by M. du Vaiz [sic].
         
         
            
               1617
            
         
         Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01144
            STC 11258
            ESTC S102558
            99838330
            99838330
            2705
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01144)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2705)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1574:02)
         
         
            
               
                  The association of the princes of France with the protestations and declarations of their allegeance to the King. Also a discourse vpon the surrendry of the seales into the Kings hands by M. du Vaiz [sic].
                  Du Vair, Guillaume, 1556-1621.
                  Concini, Concino, maréchal d'Ancre, ca. 1575-1617.
                  Mayenne, Henri de Lorraine, duc de, 1578-1621.
                  Bouillon, Henri de la Tour-d'Auvergne, Duc de, 1555-1623.
                  Vendôme, César de Bourbon, duc de, 1594-1665.
               
               [40] p.   
               
                  Printed [by William Stansby] for William Barret,
                  London :
                  1617.
               
               
                  M. du Vaiz = Guillaume Du Vair.
                  "A remonstrance of the princes, to the French King", D1r-E3r, is signed: Cæsar de Vendosme. Henry de Lorraine, Duke of Mayenne. Henry de la Tour, Duke of Bouillon.
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A-E⁴.
                  Quire D is signed C and paginated 13-20.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               France --  History --  Louis XIII, 1610-1643 --  Sources.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-06
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-06
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-06
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2007-06
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               
                  〈◊〉
               
ASSOCIATION
OF THE PRINCES
OF FRANCE,
With the Proteſtations and Declarations
of their Allegeance to the
KING.
            Alſo
A DISCOVRSE VPON THE
SVRRENDRY OF THE
SEALES INTO THE KINGS
hands by M. du VAIZ.
            LONDON
Printed for William Barret.
1617.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            THE
ASSOCIATION
OF THE PRINCES
OF FRANCE.
            
               WEE vnder-written,
weighing the miſerable
eſtate whereto
this Kingdome is
now reduced, with
the confuſion which
threatneth an ineuitable ſeparation,
and iuſtly dreading that the Enemies
of the ſame, aſwell Domeſtique, as
Strangers, will make their vſe by preuayling
through the ruine thereof, if
good and ſpeedy order be not taken,
haue thought, that during the Kings
minority, and the keeping priſoner of

the firſt Prince of the Bloud, there was
no remedy more proper, to preuent,
and ſtop ſo great an euill, then to vnite
our ſelues moſt ſtrictly together, vnder
theſe Articles which follow.
            FIRST, We proteſt to continue
conſtant, and neuer to depart from
that loyall Obedience, and moſt humble
Submiſſion which we owe as true
and naturall Subiects of this Crowne,
to the King our Prince &amp; Soueraigne
Lord.
            And becauſe it is well knowne, that
Strangers and ſuch as fauour them,
haue ſeized on the ſacred Perſon of the
King, and on the whole Adminiſtration
and abſolute Gouernement of
the Kingdome, which they doe moſt
vniuſtly vſurpe, and exerciſe, with
great Tyrannie and Oppreſſion, and
doe violently detayne the Prince of
Conde priſoner, for no offence or lawfull
cauſe, againſt the publique faith of
the Treatie of Loudun, it is moſt apparant
that they haue no other end, then

to deſtroy the houſe of Bourbon, which
now only remayneth of all the Royall
Houſes, and doe ayme at the death of
our Princes, and in it, the change and
ſubuerſion of the State: For theſe
cauſes wee doe faithfully promiſe to
employ with one mind all our power,
goods, and liues for the conſeruation
thereof, and to hinder the miſerable
effects of ſo pernicious deſſignes;
and to take the publique Authority
from them who vſurpe the ſame, to reſtore
the King vnto the dignity of his
Crowne, to keepe and maintayne it in
all ſincerity, and integrity; to withdraw
his Maieſty from their wicked
purpoſes, and to keep him out of their
hands; to ſet the Prince of Conde at liberty,
to repaire the wrong done him,
by puniſhing the Authors of this violence,
to reuoke all thoſe Offices and
Dignities which haue been beſtowed
ſince the with-holding of them from
thoſe to whom of right they belong:
And to reduce the State into a due

forme, to eſtabliſh vnder the Soueraigne
Authority of the King, the lawfull
Counſell of the Princes of his
bloud, of other Princes, and Officers
of his Crowne, and of thoſe ancient
Counſellers of State, who haue gone
through many great and important
charges, and ſuch likewiſe as are deſcended
from Noble houſes, and Families
of great antiquity, who by naturall
affection and particular intereſt
do affect the preſeruation of the State,
to whom during the minority of our
Kings, or by reaſon of their indiſpoſition,
the Adminiſtration, Gouernement,
and Direction of publique affaires
ought to be referred, by the ancient
and fundamentall Lawes of the
Kingdome, by which, both Women
and Strangers are debarred from it.
And if it ſhould ſo happen (from
which GOD in his mercy keepe vs)
that the King ſhould depart this life,
we doe by theſe declare, that wee acknowledge
after his deceaſe for our

King and Soueraigne Lord, my Lord
the Duke of Aniou, which is the true
and lawful Heire and Succeſſor of this
Crowne, and during his minority, my
Lord the Prince of Conde to be lawfull
Regent and Gardian of the Kingdom,
to whom as firſt Prince of the bloud
this preeminence doth belong, with
the Councell before mentioned for
the common direction and adminiſtration
of the affaires of the Kingdome,
and not to ſuffer any other to
be admitted vnto the Regency, no not
the Kings Mother, to the preiudice of
the Lawes of this State. And if it
ſhould ſo happen that theſe Vſurpers,
who are moſt expert in limitting the
terme of life, and in plotting the death
of thoſe who ſerue for obſtacles to
their deſſignes, and enterprizes, who
ordinarily in ſuch caſes do vſe Kniues,
and Poyſon, to haſten their Deuilliſh
ends, ſhould attempt (by theſe moſt
deteſtable meanes) to take away the
Kings life, or the Prince of Conde's, we

proteſt before the Almighty, both to
ſeeke, and proſequute the iuſt vengeance
thereof, by all lawfull meanes
to the vttermoſt of our powers, not
only vpon themſelues who are the
chiefe Actors, but vpon their Adherents
alſo, domeſtique Seruants, and
Strangers, that in their perſons we
may leaue a memorable example vnto
ſucceeding ages, as well of the fidelity
and affection of true Subiects,
as of the iuſt puniſhment of ſo abominable
diſloyaltie and impietie.
            And to this purpoſe we will employ
both our Reuenues, and Liues, euen
as long as one drop of bloud remayneth
in our bodies, and will aduiſe our
poſterity to doe the like after vs. And
that we may prouide for ſuch an accident,
and for the ſafety of the Kingdome
againſt the plots of Strangers,
and for the Gouernement, and Adminiſtration
of the ſame; in caſe we want
a Prince of the bloud, we will call a
Parliament to be aſſembled in a free

place, whither we may haue ſure acceſſe,
to the end we may proceede
with that order which is conuenient
and neceſſary.
            We doe faithfully promiſe to execute
exactly, and obſerue inuiolably
the Lawes of this Kingdome; and in
particular the Treatie of Loudun, for
the common good of all the orders of
the State, and for the ſecurity of all the
good and faithfull Subiects of the
King.
            We will maintayne, and continue
the ancient Alliances, Treaties, and
Confederations, renewed by the deceaſed
King, with forraine Princes, Potentates,
&amp; Cōmon-wealths, Friends,
Allies, and Confederates, who are in
the protection of the Crowne, that we
may reeſtabliſh in the conduct of the
affaires of State the ancient maximes
of the late King, which he ſo happily
vſed during his raigne, for the ſecurity
of his State, and the publique peace

of Christendom, the which many men
haue left since his death.
            We doe further promise, that we
will oppose vnder the Kings authority,
by all meanes possible, and namely
by our iuſt Armes, and with the ſuccours
of all the Allies, and Confederates
of this Crowne, all thoſe who
would hinder the effect of this our Vnion,
wherin we haue no further end,
then to preſerue the Kings Royall authority,
and the dignity of his Crown,
to eſtabliſh his Scepter in his hand,
and in the hands of his lawfull Succeſſors;
And to maintayne vnder the
common liberty of French-men, our
Liues, Goods, Honors, and Dignities,
againſt the diſloyaltie, and perfidiouſneſſe
of thoſe who haue conſpired not
only our ruine, but the ruine of the
Kings houſe, and of the whole Kingdome.
            And that we may with the more
ſecurity proſequute ſo laudable and

neceſſary a deſſigne, for the common
defence of the State, the obſeruation
of the publique, and priuate Lawes
thereof.
            And for the deſtruction of thoſe
who are Enemies both to the King
and Kingdome, and by a firme connexion
entertayne a true and perpetual
concord, and liue together as true
members of one, and the ſame body,
vnder the head which ſhall be elected
by vs; and following the rules which
by vs hereafter ſhall be made, we doe
all of vs promiſe, and each of vs giue
his hand one to other, whereof God is
a witneſſe betweene vs, to keepe this
Vnion faithfully, and to performe all
thoſe things which ſhall thereon depend,
by common counſell, and agreement,
and by a mutuall correſpondency,
and cōmunication, to maintayne,
ſupport, and ſuccour each other, againſt
all men.
            And to this purpoſe, we doe renounce

all particular intereſts, reſpects,
dangers, and conſiderations,
which may be propounded to vs to
the contrary, that we may ioyntly haſten
to aſſiſt him or them who ſhall be
aſſaulted, or encountred in hatred of
the ſaid Vnion, or in conſequence
thereof directly, or indirectly, by
what way, or by whomſoeuer, to doe
our parts, and faithfully to contribute
our defence in common, and of euery
of vs in particular al the power wherewith
God ſhall enable vs, without excuſe,
delayes, or other ſhifts, and not
to leaue the preſent Vnion and Aſſociation,
nor lay aſide our Armes, vntill
the things before mentioned be prouided
for, nor hearken vnto any accord,
or treaty of peace, vnleſſe it be
by common conſent.
            This Vnion and Aſſociation ſhall
be both for vs &amp; our children, whom
we meane to be compriſed herein,
and vnto whom, if any of vs ſhould

chance to depart this life, or that for
any neceſſary cauſe he were allieged,
to goe out of this Kingdome: We promiſe
in this caſe to giue the ſame ſuccours
and aſſiſtance, as it already
ſaid.
            And to auoide all diuiſions, and
diſcontents which may happen amongſt
vs for any occaſion whatſoeuer,
we doe ſubmit our ſelues to the
iudgement of our Aſſociates, or to the
greater part of them in an equall
number: to whoſe determination we
will be lyable to conforme our ſelues,
and not take pretext to waxe cold in
that which concernes this Aſſociation.
This preſent writing ſhall be kept ſecret
amongſt vs, and not manifeſted,
vnleſſe at ſuch time as by cōmon aduice
it ſhall be iudged profitable.
            And for concluſion, proteſting before
GOD to keepe inuiolably the Articles
already ſet downe, we beſeech
the ſame GOD to indue vs with his

grace, and to be pleaſed to bleſſe vs in
al our good intentions, to guide them
and cauſe them to ſucceed, to the
eſtabliſhment of the Crowne,
and the good, and conſeruation
of our
Countrey.
         
         
            
            A
DISCOVRSE VPON
THE SVRRENDRY
OF THE SEALES INTO
THE KINGS HANDS
by M. du Vaiz.
            
               SIR, I willingly render
into your hands,
the charge which it
pleaſed your Maieſtie
to honour mee
withall; and with
the ſame countenance that I receiued
it without demanding, I redeliuer
without any griefe at all. The lawes
had ſufficiently inſtructed mee, what
obedience I owe to your Maieſtie; ſo
that you needed not ſend the Captaines

of your Guard with twenty Archers
to fetch me. Violence ought to
be vſed but againſt ſuch as reſiſt, and
not againſt mee that know how to obey
my Prince, and haue euer thought
this honour rather to bee an heauy
burthen, then a Dignity, which neuertheleſſe
I did accept for the good of
your ſeruice, becauſe euery vertuous
man doth owe his care and time to
the publique good, and it had beene
a ſhame to haue refuſed to die with
the Sterne in my hand, being able either
to hinder, or at the leaſt to keepe
off awhile the ſtorme that threatens
vs. God grant, Sir, that I be the Man
that ſuffereth moſt by this disfauour,
and that your Maieſtie and the State
be leaſt intereſſed. I am not taken at
vnawares in this accident, hauing euer
foreſeene, that as my beſt endeuours
were ſtil emploied, to follow ſo neere
as poſsible I could, the integritie and
vertue of Monſieur de Ʋilleroy, and the
preſident Monſieur Iaunin, ſo ought I

alſo to expect a fortune like to theirs.
Your Maieſties commandement agreeth
in that with the choice my
ſelfe ſhould haue made, if I had beene
at mine owne diſpoſing; deſiring,
rather to be a companion of their diſgrace,
if I may ſo terme freedome
from troubleſome Employments,
then to be vſed in the gouernment of
the State, with thoſe who now remaine,
being ſubiect in time, by conuerſing
with them, to haue to touch
of their bad tincture, whoſe proſperity
I enuy not, nor the augmentation of
their authoritie, which is giuen vnto
them at my coſt. For I haue neuer
beene accuſtomed, to giue an account
euery morning by ſtealth, neither
will I ſuffer any man to preſcribe
me what I ought to doe, if the good of
the State and reaſon doe not aduiſe
me vnto it. It is more honorable for
me, then the ſealing of a bill of eight
hundred thouſand pounds, in this
great penuriouſneſſe of th' Exchecquer,

to furniſh his turne that bluſheth
not at it: Nay, who beſides this, is not
aſhamed to demand the Duchie of
Alançon for a pawne, which is the portion
of a ſonne of France, and to pretend
the office of Conſtable, which
the deceaſed King would expreſſely
haue ſuppreſſed, after the Death of the
late Monſieur de Montmorency. Beleeue
not, Sir, that becauſe I would not conſent
to theſe things, I would oppoſe
your Maieſties authoritie. I know, it
hath no other limit then your owne
will. Yet you are obliged to gouerne
your ſelfe according to reaſon, and
follow the counſell of thoſe, that are
entred into the managing of the
State, by the choice of the deceaſed
King, as being more capable to giue
it vnto you then new-commers, drawn
from the dregs of buſineſſe and of the
people. This exchange which is made
from vs to them, is as Woolues vſe
ſheepe, when the Dogges are abſent.
Doth not your Maieſtie perceiue it?

dare you not remedy it for feare of
diſobedience? Sir, by nature you owe
it to them that preach it vnto you, but
they owe the ſame to you, both by diuine
and humane Lawes. When you
ſhew them the leaſt obedience, they
haue giuen you but too much example.
Remember if you pleaſe, that
you are paſt fifteene yeres of age, and
Kings are Maiors at fourteene, Iſaac
did follow his father Abraham willingly
to be ſacrificed, becauſe he was not
of yeres to feare any thing. I beleeue,
that had he beene a perfect Man, and
had foreſeene the danger, hee would
not haue carried the wood on his
ſhoulders. Theſe are but deceitfull
ſacrifices, I pray God keep your Maieſtie
in theſe occaſions from the effect.
For when I ſee that the authority
of the Court is made to moue when
they will, that they create and diſpoſe
of the Officers of the Crowne, and
none ſeeke to hinder them; The
Princes of the bloud, ſome being impriſoned,

and others retired for the ſecuritie
of their perſons; when I ſee
that amongſt the Lords thoſe that are
ſhewed but the ſhaddow of ſome better
fortune, lend their hands to their
owne ſeruitude. Thoſe that haue attained
to any eſtabliſhment in this
ſtrangeneſſe, doe maintaine it for
feare to returne to the miſery of their
firſt condition; ſo that it ſeemeth, the
people and Prouinces doe ſuffer together
in this exchange, by the example
of the great Ones, ſeeing that the
helpe of Lawes are vnprofitable, all
being in diſorder, through bribes,
through violences, and through corruption.
The Louure it ſelfe hath taken
a new face, as the Officers haue done.
There is nought of the old Court remaining
but the wals, the vſe whereof
is alſo changed, for they were wont to
ſerue for the aſſurance of Princes, but
now they ſerue for their priſon, and (it
may be) for yours, if I may freely ſay
ſo. It is not without ſome plot, that

they giue you when you goe forth, a
company of light-horſe-men choſen
by a ſuſpect hand. Theſe are your
Gards, after the manner of the Baſtille:
this diſtruſt counſelleth you ſufficiently
what you ought to doe, and there
needs no other aduice. They hiſſe at
me, they mock me and my diſcourſe:
ſo was Caſsandra ſerued in Homer, when
ſhe fore-told the deſtruction of Troy.
Sir, I haue nothing remaining to ſerue
your Maieſty but my tongue. If I were
ſo happy as to draw your Maieſtie out
of the errour wherein you are nouriſhed,
I would a thouſand times
bleſſe my diſgrace, which had giuen
me the boldneſſe to ſpeake freely, yea
in a time when words themſelues are
puniſhed. The falſhood of the Alcoran
is no otherwiſe authoriſed, then
becauſe it is forbidden to be ſpoken of
on paine of death. Their vſurpation
vpon your Maieſties authoritie hath
no other footing, then the danger of
telling you freely of it. Conſider if

you pleaſe, Sir, that thoſe who vſurpe
this power ouer your Maieſtie, are of
that Countrey, where euery one will
Raigne, neither is there any towne on
that ſide the Alpes that hath not his
Republique or petty king: And if
your Maieſtie had ſomewhat yeerely
looked into your Hiſtorie, you would
haue learned, that the bloudieſt Tragedies
that euer haue been in France,
came from thoſe parts, the laſt furies
are the ſubiect of a little booke that I
publiſhed, of conſtancie and the conſolation
of publique calamities. I
feare, that contrary to my intent, it wil
be a worke for your Reigne, if God in
his goodnes haue not mercy vpon vs.
Thinke not, Sir, that ſorrow to ſee my
ſelfe depriued of emploiments, induced
me to ſpeake ſo boldly. If I had
beene grieued for it, it is like married
people, that weepe when they muſt
go from their parents power, to enter
into the equalitie of Marriage: neuertheleſſe
it is true, that owing my ſeruice

vnto your Maieſty, I ſhould haue
receiued greater content to haue employed
it in your Councell of State
then in your Parliament, where matters
are of leſſe importance. For I ſuppoſe,
that if the Carpenter who made
the caruing worke for the Admirall,
where Don Iohn of Auſtria commanded
at the Battell of Lepanto, had
knowne that it ſhould haue ſerued for
ſo important an occaſion, whereon
depended the ſafety of the reſt of Europe,
he would haue taken more delight
in making of it, then if it had been
a Veſſell ordained for commers.
Notwithſtanding ſeeing your Maieſty
commandeth me to retire, in a good
houre be it. The leſſer Starres are part
of the perfection of the world, although
they do contribute leſſe then
doth the Sunne and Moone. In what
condition ſoeuer I liue, I will alwaies
to the vttermoſt of my power, maintaine
the good of your Maieſties ſeruice.
But if there be any of thoſe who

are neere you, that lament my remoue,
for my ſake: I will tell them
freely, Weepe for your Children of Ieruſalem,
that for want of courage ſuffered
your Maſter to be betrayed, and
not for me, that haue not offended,
vnleſſe, in being an honeſt Man.
Wherefore I take my leaue of you,
Sir, praying God that he will haue
pittie of your State, and
care of your education.
         
         
            
            A
REMONSTRANCE
OF THE PRINCES,
TO THE FRENCH
KING.
Dated the Fourth of
FEBRVARY.
            
               SIR,
            
            
               YOur moſt Humble
and moſt Faithfull
Subiects and Seruants,
the Dukes,
Peeres, ancient Officers
of your Crown,
and principal Lords
of your Kingdome; ſeeing the dangers
which inviron you, and the euills
which threaten your State with an inevitable

ſubuerſion, if ſpeedy order
be not taken, and that they are denied
all acceſſe vnto your Perſon, wherewith
they might freely, and ſecurely,
diſcouer the cauſes, and propound the
remedies thereof; doe in all humilitie
beſeech your Maieſtie to take in good
part, this their moſt humble Remonſtrance,
which cannot but well befit
their mouthes, ſithence it doth teſtifie
nothing but fidelitie and affection vnto
your ſeruice, to the conſeruation of
your Sacred Perſon, and the good of
your States. And it is by ſo much the
more conuenient, becauſe they are
thereunto obliged, both by Diuine
and Humane Lawes, by the Oath
which they haue taken, and the dutie
which they owe vnto your Crowne.
We are not ignorant, that the euill is
diſguiſed by thoſe who doe it, and
who labour by all poſſible meanes to
couer it, as well as commit it, ſtill indeuouring
to make thoſe diſtaſtfull

vnto your Maieſtie, who complaine
thereof. And the vnhappineſſe of
France is ſuch, that they hauing all the
power of your Eſtate in their hands,
they cauſe you to hold your faithfulleſt
ſeruants for Enemies. But the violence
of their Tyrannicall carriage is
growne to that exceſſe, that it cannot
longer be indured; The complaints of
it are generall; euery one ſeeth it, and
feeles the miſerable effects; And their
Artifices can no longer hinder the
cryes, and publique griefe from ſtriking
your Maieſties eares, and from
mouing your compaſſion to releeue
your People; and your iuſtice againſt
the Authours of ſo great miſeries;
which euery one knoweth, and openly
deteſteth; And by a common vow
of your faithfull Subiects are deſtined
to iuſt puniſhment, according to their
demerits.
            The inſatiable ambition, and auarice,
of the Marqueſſe of Anchre, and

his Wife is the only cauſe of the euils
we are ſenſible of; of the diſorders we
ſee, and of that wee feare moſt.
            This is the vlcer which hath feſtered,
yea, ſpoyled the whole body of
your State. It is of him only that men
doe complaine, and of the Miniſters
and Executors of his violent and raging
paſſions, and no other.
            This is the complaint of the greateſt
part of your Subiects, who as yet
haue true French hearts: who ſeeing
themſelues compaſſed about with
feare and apprehenſions, and expoſed
to all manner of dangers, by the inteſtine
conſpiracies which ayme at the
ruine of your State, doe implore your
Iuſtice, to protect them from the oppreſſion
and ſeruitude, vnto which
thoſe perſons would make them ſubiect;
and for to free your Crowne
from the many diſaſters, which now
increaſe to the ouerthrow of the ſame.
            The remedy (SIR) is in your own

hands, and in your power, which if
you doe not make vſe of, the diſeaſe
will ſhortly grow incurable: And
therefore to ſhunne it, the cauſe muſt
be taken away, which being knowne
vnto you, there needeth now no other
thing then your word only; to giue
order that the Marqueſſe of Anchre,
with his Wife and Adherents, be chaſed
from your Sacred Perſon, and
from the Queene your Mother: And
to giue way vnto Iuſtice, that it may
duly puniſh them for thoſe crymes
whereof they are culpable touching
your State.
            Euery man well knoweth what
deceit hee hath vſed, ſince the death
of the laſt king of moſt happy memory,
to draw vnto himſelfe th'entire
and abſolute Adminiſtration of your
Kingdome; to make himſelfe Maſter
of your Councels, of your Treaſure,
of your Armes, and of your Fortreſſes,
to diſpoſe of your publique Offices,

and Charges, your Fauours, and
Pardons; becauſe hee would bee the
ſole Iudge of Honours, and Dignities,
and diſpoſe of the life and death of
your Subiects. The courſes hee hath
taken to baniſh the Princes of the
Bloud from the Court, and to breed
diſcord betweene them, are not vnknowne;
and likewiſe of the reſt of
the Princes, Officers of your Crowne,
and principall Lords of the Kingdome:
The practizes and corruptions
which he hath vſed to weaken and
depreſſe the authoritie of your Parliaments,
and violently to choke the
lawfull freedome of their Remouſtrances,
impriſon your chiefe Officers, and
make a diuiſion through all the orders
of your Kingdome; that hee might
haue the whole diſpoſing of them,
and raigne alone within the State, as
he doth now with an inſupportable
preſumption and inſolency, ſuppoſing
that nothing can reſiſt his ambitious

Deſſignes, ſeeing that, through extreme
wrong and iniuſtice, hee hath
impriſoned the firſt Prince of your
Bloud; and by this audacious Action
violated the publike faith of the Treatie
of Loudun; vpon the obſeruation
of which did depend the repoſe and
tranquillity of your State, which he
had rather plunge into the calamities
of a Warre, then to haue the maske
of your Royall Authority taken from
him; whereof hee makes his benefit,
and vſeth it as an Inſtrument, for the
deſtruction of your moſt faithful Subiects.
            Theſe things are ſo manifeſt, &amp; his
proiects &amp; guile ſo plainly diſcouer'd,
that no doubt can bee made hereof.
And the ſtrange proceedings, and violence,
which he vſeth euery day vnder
your Maieſties name, againſt the
Duke of Neuers, vpon ſo notorious
pretexts, and forged imputations, that
euen the voice of the people ſerueth

for proofe enough to refute them; do
witnes ſufficiently, that the conſpiracy
is generall, againſt all the Princes and
Nobles of your Kingdome; who will
not ſtoupe to his tyranny, and can reſiſt
his plots, which he continually
puts in execution, thereby to ſubuert
the State.
            For what offence is the ſame Dukes,
ſauing only, that he is a Prince of the
moſt renowned Houſes of your Kingdomes,
one that loues his Countrey,
ſeekes the peace of it, and who hath alwaies
teſtified his zeale vnto your ſeruice,
and acknowledgeth no other
Authority lawfull then your Maieſty?
            Hee complaineth of ſome iniurie
done him by one of his Tenants; and
that in contempt of the dignity of his
Office, he cannot freely exerciſe his
charge in his Gouernment.
            He hath proſecuted an execution
of ſome feodal rights within his owne
poſſeſſions, by the ordinary means of

Iuſtice, as vnwilling to loſe that which
his Predeceſſors left him: Perceiuing
ſome ſecret enterpriſes, ready to bee
executed vpon his Houſes, he prouided,
as indeed he ought, for the ſecuring,
defence and keeping of them vnder
your Authority, and for your ſeruice.
            Theſe lawfull and neceſſary cauſes
are wreſted to his rebuke; nay, are imputed
to him as a haynous crime and
Rebellion.
            We haue ſeen the Declaration that
hath bin publiſhed againſt him, vnder
your Maieſties name, and the reaſonable
conditions vnto which hee doth
ſubmit himſelfe for his triall, and make
his innocencie appeare, which being
knowne vnto vs, we moſt humbly beſeech
your Maieſty to be pleaſed to
protect the ſame, and not to ſuffer it to
be oppreſſed &amp; violēced by the Marqueſſe
of Anchre, whoſe outrages and
offences we can no longer diſſemble,

becauſe our long patience hath not
hitherto ſerued for ought elſe, then for
to render it more audacious, and inſolent;
that we be no more vpbraided,
that our affection is ſo ſmall vnto your
Maieſty, that we are ſo ingratefull to
our Country, ſo diſloyal and vnprofitable
vnto our ſelues and to our Poſterity,
as to be ſilent, when we behold
the prodigious fauour of this Stranger,
trampling thus inſolently on the
throate of your State, holding priſoner
in his hands the firſt Prince of
your Bloud, treading vnder foot both
Lawes and Magiſtrates, emptying
your Coffers by his profuſions, conſuming,
your people with exceſſiue
charges, and cauſing your Subiects to
be trecherouſly murthered, without any
puniſhment at all. And for recompence
of ſuch trechery and diſloyalty,
conferring vpon them the Gouernments
of your places; depoſing and
diſcharging the chief Officers of your

Councels and Parlements, bereauing
them of thoſe Titles &amp; Honors, which
their Age, their Vertue, and their Deſerts
haue purchaſed them; for to eſtabliſh
in their places his creatures, who
are perſons altogether vnworthy, and
vnexperienced for the manageing of
your State, being men borne in bondage,
and therefore enemies to all honeſt
men, and moſt proper to execute
his paſſions, what detriment ſoeuer
may enſue thereby to your ſeruice,
holding nothing vnlawful which may
aduance his paſſionate deſſignes.
            This is that which hath induced vs,
thus humbly to beſeech your Maieſty
to conſider the miſerable eſtate wherinto
your Kingdome is now brought,
and to apply, by your Wiſdome and
Authority, the neceſſary remedy,
which dependeth vpon your own wil,
and not to ſuffer either your name, or
your Armes to be employed to the
effuſion of your Subiects bloud, and

oppreſſion of your Domeſticall ſeruants,
for the maintaining of Strangers
to their preiudice, but to baniſh them
for euer from you: and by the chaſtiſement
and due puniſhment of
the guiltie, reeſtabliſh confidence
and ſecurity in your Kingdom, repaire
the publike Faith, which hath
bin broken, and ſet the Prince of Condé
at liberty. And to the end that order
may be taken by conuenient meanes,
againſt the diſorders of your State; to
cauſe the Treaty of Loudun to be obſerued;
call againe vnto you, and into
your Councels, the Princes of your
Bloud, with the reſt of the Princes,
Dukes, Peeres, and the ancient Officers
of your Crowne, and Counſellers
of State, whom the deceaſed King
vſed during his Raigne, who alſo by
naturall affection, and as being particularly
intereſſed, as ſtrictly oblieged
to the conſeruation of your State. And
then we ſhall haue the happineſſe to

render you in all ſecuritie, euery 
                  〈◊〉
               
according to his Ranke, Dignitie, and
Place, that moſt humble ſeruice, and
faithfull obedience which wee owe
you, and which whileſt we liue we will
yeeld you, as being
            
               Your moſt humble, moſt loyall, and
moſt obedient Subiects
and Seruants,
Signed,
                  
                     
                        Caeſar de Vendoſme.
                     
                        Henry de Lorraine,
                     Duke of Mayenne.
                     
                        Henry de la Tour,
                     Duke of Bouillon.
                  
               
            
         
      
   

