
   
      
         
            Tvvo spare keyes to the Iesuites cabinet· dropped accidentally by some Father of that societie and fallen into the hands of a Protestant. The first wherof, discovers their domestick doctrines for education of their novices. The second, openeth their atheisticall practises touching the present warres of Germany. Projected by them in the yeare 1608. and now so farre as their power could stretch, effected, till the comming of the most victorious King of Sweden into Germany. Both serving as a most necessary warning for these present times.
            Colloquium Jesuiticum. English
            Francke, Christian, b. 1549.
         
         
            
               1632
            
         
         Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01233
            STC 11346.3
            ESTC S102623
            99838395
            99838395
            2771
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01233)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2771)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1549:7)
         
         
            
               
                  Tvvo spare keyes to the Iesuites cabinet· dropped accidentally by some Father of that societie and fallen into the hands of a Protestant. The first wherof, discovers their domestick doctrines for education of their novices. The second, openeth their atheisticall practises touching the present warres of Germany. Projected by them in the yeare 1608. and now so farre as their power could stretch, effected, till the comming of the most victorious King of Sweden into Germany. Both serving as a most necessary warning for these present times.
                  Colloquium Jesuiticum. English
                  Francke, Christian, b. 1549.
                  Freake, William.
                  Camilton, John. De studiis Jesuitarum abstrusioribus. English.
               
               [2], 36, 39-62 p.   
               
                  Printed by B[ernard] A[lsop] and T[homas] F[awcet] for George Giebes, and are to be sold at his shop at the Flower de Luce, by the little south-doore of St. Pauls Church,
                  London :
                  1632.
               
               
                  The first part and possibly part of the second are translations from "Colloquium Jesuiticum" by Christian Francke. The second part, however, is a translation of "De studiis Jesuitarum abstrusioribus", attributed to Joannes Cambilhon.
                  Translated by William Freake.
                  A reissue of "The doctrines and practises of the societie of Jesuites", with the preliminaries of both books cancelled, and cancel general title page.
                  Printers' names from STC.
                  Identified as STC 14538 on UMI microfilm.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Jesuits --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-12
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-01
            Jason ColmanSampled and proofread
         
            2007-01
            Jason ColmanText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2007-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            TVVO SPARE KEYES TO THE IESVITES CABINET. DROPPED Accidentally by ſome Father of that Societie and fallen into the hands of a Proteſtant.
            THE Firſt wherof, Diſcovers their Domeſtick Doctrines for Education of their Novices.
            The Second, openeth their Atheiſticall Practiſes touching the preſent Warres of Germany.
            
            Projected by them in the yeare 1608. and now ſo farre as their power could ſtretch, effected, till the comming of the moſt Victorious King of SWEDEN into GERMANY.
            
               Both ſerving as a moſt neceſſary warning for theſe preſent Times.
            
            LONDON, Printed by B. A. and T. F. for GEORGE GIBBES, and are to be ſold at his Shop at the Flower de Luce, by the little South-doore of St. Pauls Church. 1632.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            THE DOCTRINE AND PRACTICE OF THE IESVITES.
            
               WHen the time was now at hand and almoſt accompliſhed, wherein that rare and heauenly man Paulus Florenius abandoned that perverſe Fraternitie of the Ieſuites, and returned from them to the publike Societie of men, and we two were at that inſtant time walking together then thus ſpake Paul vnto me.
            
               PAVL. FLOREN.
               Me thinkes Chriſtianus (ſaith hee) when I conſider all Circumſtances impartially, comparing them one with another, this our profeſſion of Ieſuitiſme wherein wee liue is wholly compacted of Superſtition, Hypocriſie, and a great deale of diſſembled and pretended Sanctitie, being euen deviſed of the Deuill himſelfe in this elder and doating age of the world, purpoſely thereby

to make ſale vnto Mankind of all the Errors, toyes and Superſtitions of Poperie, and (to vſe a homely phraſe againſt my will, but that it is moſt proper and ſignificant in this caſe) to take the ſtinking excrements of Papiſtrie ſo odious in their owne nature, and ſauouring much more loathſomely at this time, eſpecially wherein they are ſo often ſtirred in, by many curious and great Schollers, and by compounding and tempering the ſame with pretences of Holineſſe, and wrapping them vp in a great number of obſcurities and ſubtilties to vent them once more to the whole Chriſtian world for ſweet Drugs and Spices of price, and that after ſuch a manner, that they will compell men to bee theyr Chapmen for them to buy whether they will or not. Yea, and the matter is now carried in ſuch ſort, that nothing can be diſcouered in the religion of Poperie, how baſe, falſe, and abhominable ſoever, which this Societie preſumeth not by ſome new deuiſe or other, eyther through blinding the eye of Vnderſtanding, or by craftie Conueyances, couering the abſurditie and falſhood thereof, to make appeare both faire and true. Wherefore I ſuppoſe, that it ſtandeth vs much vpon to conſider ſeriouſly in what a profeſſion wee liue, leaſt if wee ſhall neglect to take notice of the falſhood thereof now, our bleſſed Lord and Sauiour himſelfe neglect to acknowledge vs for his owne in the day of our generall accompt, and afterwards, wee may doe at that moſt excellent Prophet IEREMIE commandeth, Flie out of the Middeſt
                  Iere
                        ••
                     . 51. 6. 
                  of Babel and deliuer euery man his owne Soule.
               
            
            
               
               CHRISTIAN. FRANC
                     •
                  EN.
               Whereunto I replyed thus: And is it true Paul? Can you admit a thought, that the moſt Holy and Learned profeſſion in the world at this time, ſhould bee falſe and hypocriticall? I aſſure you, I hold this Religion to bee the true Religion, and ſo conſequently that our ſelues are bound to continue in the ſame, as in our lawfull Vocation, according to the Doctrine of the holy Apoſtle, and not to depart a jot therefrom, or elſe all Religions in the world to be falſe, and by all meanes to be auoyded.
            
            
               PAVL.
               I was of your mind Chriſtianus, ſaid Paul, before I entred into this Profeſſion, and therfore I burſt violently out of the armes of this flattering world (though ſhee was vnwilling to let me eſcape out of her clutches) and came running as it were in haſt to this Societie of Ieſuites, as to the moſt holy of all profeſſions of Religion, and the moſt pleaſing to GOD (as I ſuppoſed) and the moſt comfortable to mine owne ſoule.
               But now, whereas I expected to find true and vnfeigned Holines therein, Woe is mee, I meet with nothing but meere Hypocriſie and Diſſimulation.
               And now euen thine owne ſelfe (O Chriſtian) ſhalt ſee apparently that what I haue ſpoken is not deuiſed of hatred, or euill will, but that I ſpeake it as a man conuinced in Conſcience by the Truth it ſelfe, and euen enforced thereunto againſt my will, if forthwith thou doeſt but ſearch into the depth as I haue done, and into the very foundations of the Societie, and relinquiſhing all voluntary or (as our Societie termeth it) Holy ſimplicity and blindnes

of heart, thou be guided by the pure light of reaſon, and beholding the ſame with a ſincere vnderſtanding, no way for ſtalled with Ieſuiticall Deluſions, thou canſt take a view of the Cozenage and knauerie thereof: which if thou doeſt, (as it is my hope that thou wilt;) I doubt not but that thou ſhalt quickly diſcerne, by thoſe ſpirituall foundations which are layd in euery houſe of Probationers amongſt vs for the Education of Nouices, and inſtructing them according to the rule of that Societie, that none at all is fitting to bee admitted into this profeſſion, but ſuch onely as haue a propenſe inclination, eyther by nature, or acquired by ſeruile Education, and ſuddenly reſolued vpon in ſome ſit of aſtoniſhment, of heart to hypocriſie and ſuperſtition; That is to ſay, ſome ſuch man as is well skilled, by an app
                     ••••
                  nt Sanctitie of looke or demureneſs of Count
                     〈…〉
                  nce, to make ſhew in publike of his Deuotion (as they tearme it,) which our bleſſed Sauiour hath commanded to reſerue for our priuate Cloſets, and ſuch a one as praying in publike like a Phariſie at a Faſt, can cunningly change the coppie of his Countenance at pleaſure, which manner of behauiour, howbeit indeed and in truth it bee nothing but Hypocriſie, yet it is ſtiled by our Societie, Edification forſooth, and Deuotion.
               
               Verily Chriſtian, I doe euery day more and more plainely perceiue, and doe exceedingly bewaile to ſee, that this is the very foundation wherevpon our Societie is built, nor will my Conſcience

euer ſuffer me to bee at quiet, till I haue purged my ſelfe from theſe pollutions.
               But if ſo be, that your ſelfe hauing your vnderſtanding foreſtalled with daily Cuſtome, which is a ſecond Nature, doe not yet perhaps perceiue thus much. I will vndoubtedly proue vnto you by infallible Demonſtrations, how you may be able to collect thus much by very touch and feeling, which though it bee the moſt ſtupid of all Sences, yet it is the moſt infallible and hardeſt to bee deceiued.
            
            
               CHRISTIAN.
               Indeed, ſayd I, Paul, I doe confeſſe that I doe not yet fully vnderſtand thus much. Wherefore if you ſuppoſe me to be inveloped in a Myſt of Ieſuitiſme, be a meanes I beſeech you that I may Diſcerne, at the leaſt by touching the meaning of theſe things, whereof you haue now begun to ſpeake.
            
            
               PAVL.
               Well then, ſaid hee, come hither vnto me yet a litle neerer, and by calling thy memory to an accompt, lay thy hand (as it were) vpon all that Sanctity whereof thou haſt had experience hitherto, partly in thy ſelfe, and partly in other Ieſuites, and weighing the ſame deliberately together, with the ſeuerall diſpoſitions of the people, as they are Italians, Spaniards, French, or Dutch, ingenuous or blockiſh, free-borne, or baſe, conſider them apart ſeriouſly, ſo ſhalt thou at laſt bee reſolued. I aſſure my ſelfe, that thou haſt euer obſerued, and tooke notice of more frequent and outward expreſſions of Ieſuiticall Deuotion in Spaniards, and Italians, then in Germans, French, or other Nations, and

moſt vſually in ſeruile and blockiſh companions, much more then in free-borne and ingenuous Gentlemen.
               Now as touching the Spaniard himſelfe, you ſhall find that this Diſpoſition in him, proceedeth meerely from his ſeruile Education in the Chriſtian Religion: For there is in Spaine (as your ſelfe know as well as I doe) ſo ſtrict a courſe taken for inquiry into euery particuler man, touching his profeſſion, at the leaſt of the Romane Religion, and the ſame is ſo narrowly watched for flying away, that except the very Sonnes and Children themſelues ſhall bring a Faggot to the burning of their Fathers, (if once they be adjudged Heretickes) and ſo become little leſſe then the Executioners of their Parents, they are generally reputed Heretickes, and worthy to fry with them in the ſame flame.
               Whereby it is apparant enough, that the Spaniards of neceſſitie muſt be Superſtitious, and very frequent in all outward acts of Devotion, and both in life and death Romane Catholiques. Yea, they had need to take heed, that they doe not ſo much as ſmell like an Hereticke, when they are rotten in their Graues, leaſt if they haue fallen ſhort in outward teſtimonies of Religion, they happen to bee ſuſpected touching the Faith, and come to be moſt ſeuerely perſecuted to the third and fourth generation.
               How then can it bee poſſiblely, that the Spaniſh Nation, being borne and bred, educated and inſtructed in ſuch infinite ſlauerie of minde, being alſo by Nature hot and chollericke, ſhould chuſe but

be moſt violent, or (if you pleaſe to tearme it ſo) moſt Devout in his Religion?
               Yea, how could the Deuill himſelfe if hee were lyable to the Spaniſh Inquiſition, how could hee avoyd it, but hee muſt be compelled at all times to transforme himſelfe into an Angell of light, and to acquire ſome habite, at the leaſt to put on an outſide of Romiſh ſuperſtition and ſeeming Sanctitie? From this Fountaine ſprung that Ignatius de Loiola, who being a Souldier, and by the valour of the French at the ſeidge of the Caſtle at Pampeloun, in the Kingdome of Navarre, ſpoyled for following that profeſſion any longer, and outſtripping all others in Superſtition, became the Founder of the Ieſuiticall Order, by whom hee might in time to come, not onely bee reuenged of the French, but alſo make a Conqueſt of all the Chriſtian world beſides.
               You ſhall alſo obſerue in Italians, that they are exceedingly frequent in thoſe outward acts of religious Deuotion, and that through a naturall inclination which they haue to hypocriſie and diſſimulation, as a Nation which euer hath bin (as appeareth by all their antient Monuments and Records) very ſuperſtitious, and are to this day inclinable to worſhip a multitude of Deities, and marueilous prone to Idolatrie; inſomuch, that it may eaſily be demonſtrated, how out of this Cup of Fornication, that people hath powred out many things into Chriſtian Religion, and infected it throughout with deadly poyſon. Wherewith the whole Chriſtian world being for the moſt part inticed

and deceiued, by the ſweetneſſe, delitiouſneſſe, Antiquity, and faire outſide thereof; is, in a manner quite inebriated, whiles day by day in the matter of ſaluation, they reſort to a Rabble of Romiſh Deities, and to a Numberleſſe number of Saints forſooth, ſubſtituted by the Popes of Rome, in roome of the Heathen Gods, and propounded to be invocated and prayed vnto, and them multiplyed continually, though not in deed, yet in their names, as alſo to many Goddeſſes feminine Saints, amongſt whom queſtionles the Virgin Mary was brought in as in the place of Ceres, whom the Roman Matrons in the time of Heatheniſme, did moſt religiouſly adore with burning tapers, at ſuch time of the yeare as the Feaſt of Candlemas or Purification of the bleſſed Virgin was enacted.
               Which thing, I am the rather induced to beleeue ſeeing that for the increaſe of their Idolatry, this very ſolemnity was purpoſely contriued to fall into the moneth of February, that being the ſelfe ſameVa
                        •
                     ro. lib. 1. de Pop. Rom. vita. Macrob. lib. 1. Saturnal. 
                        •
                     . 13 Ovid. Faſt. 2. 4. time of the yeere the antient heathen Romanes kept their Feaſt called Februa, offering vp ſacrifices for all ſoules, and for the purging or expiating of the ſinnes of the whole City.
               For indeed, all the people of Rome, at that time of the yeare (as their owne Writers teſtifie) was wholly taken vp with making Oblations and Sacrifices, with lighted Torches and waxen Candles about the Sepulchers of the Dead, for obtaining of reſt to the Soules of their friends departed. And finding the Scriptures of God, vnwilling of themſelues to conſent to this Idolatry, they haue forced

and drawn them thereunto, (as it were) by the head and ſhoulders, and hauing by chance ſtumbled vpon one booke or other that ſeemeth to approue that opinion in ſome ſort, they haue made that booke Canonicall, that ſo their opinion might bee made altogether an Article of our Faith, in defence whereof, as well as of other points, all the Doctors, (or rather Doddipoles) of the Romane Church doe labour till they ſweate againe, but all in vaine, till at the laſt perceiuing, that they nothing aduantage their cauſe, by all the new Arguments they can deuiſe, and rake vp day by day, they retire in the end of all to the traditions of the Church as to their ſhort Anchor and onely ſafe harbour in that caſe: When as neuertheleſſe, that very tradition it ſelfe is for the moſt part (I may ſafely ſay altogether) vnderpropped by that great and principall Idoll of Rome, which with its greatneſſe doth (in a manner) reach vp to heauen. Yea maketh it ſelfe equall to that euer to bee adored and bleſſed Trinity, by that triple Crowne it weareth, and that threefold gemiculation which is expected from all ſuch as dare to approach neere vnto him.
               Neither indeed, can I ſuppoſe that the Germaines and Bohemians, being naturally and of themſelues inclinable to true piety, did ſo eaſily fall off from the Church of Rome, for any other cauſe ſo much as for this; to wit, becauſe in regard of that honeſtie and grauitie of manners which is in them by Nature, they haue euer abhorred &amp; cannot away with to this day a multitude of Idols and Ceremonies,

with all that leuity of Minnick repreſentations and ſuperſtitions, howbeit indeed they haue defiled themſelues for many yeeres together with this Idolatry and inconſtancie, being ouerborne by the authority of that Romane Idoll, and that infallibility of Spirit, which they ſo bragge that they hold in Feeſimple, or at the leaſt haue an euerlaſting leaſe thereof to themſelues and their poſterities for euer. And though it be ſo, that ſome men being caught by our Ieſuites, with the glorious names of Hierome, Ambroſe, Auguſtine, Bernard, Thomas Aquinas, &amp; other Saints, do returne to their former abominations, ſurely they are none but illiterate, and vnexperienced youthes or none of the wiſeſt and knowing men, but rather ſuch as being diſtracted with an importunate and confuſed rumour, of Learning and Holineſſe, are not able to vnderſtand the miſtery of this buſineſſe, or to diſcerne aright of matters in queſtion, nor doe perceiue, that foraſmuch, as theſe Fathers of our Societie haue made the Biſhop of Rome an earthly Deity, by appropriating vnto him a ſoueraigne Power, ouer all perſons, and an infallibility of truth in doctrine, ſo in lieu of this their Curteſie to him, this Roman-God-Almighty hath likewiſe conferred vpon them, and by a free donation entayled vpon them and their poſterity the name of holy Fathers, for euer and euer.
               And all this only for this purpoſe that ſo godly a peece of Doctrine deuiſed by them, and tending ſo much to the vpholding of his Fatherhood (I had

almoſt ſaid falſhood,) might not ſeeme any humaine deuice, but rather as it were a Divine conſtitution and an Oracle from Heauen: and that himſelfe euermore relying thereupon, might by vertue of his Diuine prerogatiue, haue power to create and ordaine for the whole Chriſtian world, what Articles of Faith hee pleaſed.
               Laſt of all, who doth not ſee, that ſeruile and blockiſh Companions (for thoſe onely remaine in our Diuiſion) doe for this very cauſe both more willingly fall into, and more obſtinately maintaine this blockiſh and ſlauiſh Religion, as more naturally agreeing to themſelues and their inclinations.
               But this point I am ſure, your ſelfe vnderſtand perfectly, who haue but a few dayes agoe (as you cannot chuſe but remember) expreſſed vnto mee your owne particular griefe, for the rude and blockiſh qualities of our Collegiates, when you related vnto me not without indignation, that after you returned from Italie into Germany, you were exceedingly moleſted in mind with Conſideration thereof, and did many a time wiſh your ſelfe out of this world, rather then to liue to be conſtrained to doe any thing againſt your Calling, with this thought, and the experience you had of the truth thereof, did wonderfully weaken and infringe: to wit, that in theſe parts, there were none obſerued to enter into or at the leaſt to continue in that Society of Ieſuites, but the very Dregs of Mankind, ſuch as were hardly capable of reaſon, much leſſe of true Piety and Religion: vnto whom neuertheleſſe, becauſe they exceed in number, you muſt

conforme your ſelfe in all things, if you deſire to liue in peace abroad, and enioy any quiet or content at home.
               And thus I haue made knowne vnto you, the foundation of our Society, let vs now proceed vnto the body thereof, the eſtate whereof is eaſily diſcouered from the originall, as it were, and cauſes therof. For inaſmuch as our Societie wch moſt impudently arrogateth to it ſelfe the name of IESV, is compoſed of ſuch a ſincke of Hypocrites and ſuperſtitious perſons, it deſerueth rather to bee tearmed a Phariſaicall Religion: howbeit (as I haue ſaid) it bee clothed with the moſt glorious name of IESV, to the end that wretched mortals might henceforth haue the Enemies and Traitors of their owne ſalvation, not onely lurking vnder ſheepes clothing, but alſo vnder the very ornament of Divinity, that by this meanes the very Elect (if it could bee poſſibly) ſuſpecting no falſhood to bee vnder ſo glorious a name of truth, might bee drawne into errour.
               Now the whole body of our ſociety, beſides their Father Generall, who is the Head and Coriphaeus of this Order, comprehendeth only theſe ſixe ſorts of perſons.
               The firſt, thoſe who haue profeſſed 4. vowes.
               The ſecond, ſuchas haue made profeſsion of 3. vowes
               The third, are ſpirituall Coadiutors.
               The fourth, are temporall Coadiutors.
               The fifth Schollers.
               The ſixth, Novices.
               
                  The profeſſors of 4. Vowes are ſo called, becauſe that ouer and aboue the 3. common vowes of Poverty, Chaſtity, &amp; Obedience, they make a peculiar vow of Obedience to the Pope of Rome, and promiſe him, that they will diſperſe and publiſh the errors and ſuperſtitions of the Romane Religion throughout all the world, whenſoeuer he ſhall command, Non petito viatico, at their owne coſt and charges.
               And againe, vnto the Father Generall they vow, Ab negationem honorum, to renounce all honours, forſooth, becauſe they will not be made Cardinals out of the Societie, and yet therein they are made very Cardinals in the Societie, as out of whom onely their Father Generall, who is in effect nothing elſe but the Pope of that Societie, muſt bee elected, and vpon whom as vpon hinges, the whole Societie may depend and be turned euery way for aduantage. Which men alſo may retaine a publique repute of being Learned and Holy men: and ſo this lying and fooliſh Societie, whiles it ſuppoſeth that it auoydeth Ambition, or would bee thought ſo to doe, falleth headlong into it, not much vnlike thoſe fooliſh Phyloſophers, whom Cicero mentioneth, who by ſetting their owne Names vpon thoſe Bookes, which they had written touching the Contempt of Glory, haue therein fooliſhly fiſhed for vaine Glory to themſelues.
               Now thoſe who haue profeſſed three vowes, are as very Byſhops in the ſocietie, and whereas in other Orders this degree is not diſtinguiſhed from ſimple Prieſthood, but as many as are ordained

Prieſts may alſo be Profeſſors. In this our ſocietie there is a diſtinction betwixt thoſe two, to the end (forſooth) that this degree may ſeeme the higher, and more eminent, if many yeares after a man hath beene made Prieſt he may be admitted to profeſſion, as vnto a Byſhopricke. By which diſtinctions they make it appeare vnto vs euidently enough, that they haue conuerted the baſe ſhew of Ambition, into a moſt beautifull and glorious picture, or outſide of vaine glory, which might moue all all men liuing with its beautie, and might allure and retaine vnto it ſelfe, a great number of perſons of all eſtates, and degrees, and of both ſexes.
               Whereas, if men looking ſeriouſly into this outwardMarke this. forme, and formall outſide; and with the piercing eye of true vnderſtanding ſhould behold the inſide thereof; queſtionleſſe, they might there diſcouer cloſely concealed vnder our ſocietie, that ſecond beaſt which maketh all the world to worſhip the firſt. Apoc 13. 12.
               For by the firſt beaſt, I vnderſtand the Byſhop of Rome, who in regard of that ſecular power which he vſurpes, is indeed and in truth that Antichriſt whom our ſociety now cauſeth to bee worſhipped almoſt all the world ouer, and that it muſt continue to doe ſo euer laſtingly, hath bound it ſelfe by that their fourth and more peculiar vow.
               Now that which our bleſſed Lord and SaviourMath. 
                        •
                     4. 22. Apocal. 13. 5. 12. 14. Dan. 12. 7. and his beloued Diſciple Saint IOHN, and the Prophet DANIELI doe ſpeake, touching the ſhort time of Antichriſts raigne, is to bee vnderſtood of the laſt perſecution, which ſhall be, at ſuch time as☞
                  
that firſt beaſt the Pope, ſhall by that ſecond beaſt our Societie, in ſome part haue recouered Germany, Bohemia, and other Kingdomes, lately taken out of their hands, and ſhall ſee many other Realmes and Principalities reduced to their obedience by the ſame. For then ſhall this ſociety being growne rich, magnifie its owne heart, and riſe vp againſt the King of Kings, and be cruſhed to peeces withoutDan. 8. 25. hands.
               Spirituall Coadjutors (vnder which name are comprehended all Prieſts and profeſſors of Diuinity or Phyloſophy, and all and ſingular teachers of the inferiour Arts not yet hauing made profeſſion) hauing firſt vowed Poverty, Chaſtity, and Obedience, doe aſſiſt this beaſt in peruerting and ſeducing of Soules vnto the firſt Beaſt. Wherein as any one ſhall approue himſelfe more apt and ingenious then his fellowes, ſo is he the more quickly admitted by profeſſion to bee a Member of this Monſter.
               Now thoſe who are called Temporall Coadjutors, haue charge to prouide for the backe and belly of this Beaſt, purneying and prouiding for the ſame and intermedling with all Domeſticke buſineſſe,
               Laſtly, Schollers and Novices are maintained at home, to this end onely, leaſt at any time there might prooue a defect in the Body of this Monſter. But that as old eaten limbes ſhall happen to decay, and fall off, ſo freſh and new ſupplies may be ſtill made out of this Storehouſe or Seminarie of young Ieſuites.
               
               
                  Moreouer, to the end this Idolatry and ſuperſtitionIn the Epiſtle of Ignatius de Loyola, who is read euery moneth at the Table. may be for euer concealed free from feare of diſcouerie, and that as it is preſerued, ſo it may bee increaſed continually, this Beaſt is accuſtomed to foreſtall the vnderſtanding of her whelpes, if they haue any, and to bind vp their very ſences, admoniſhing or rather Commanding in good earneſt, that all things which the Superior ſhall Command, be performed with blind obedience, and that whatſoeuer our ſuperior ſhall doe, bee paſſed ouer with blind judgement, without ſo much as Conſidering whether it be good and profitable, or hurtfull and damnable, which is enioyned or done, foraſmuch as euery ſuch thought taketh away the merit and valour of obedience. In which particuler, our Societie followeth the ſteps of the Canoniſts thoſe moſt pernicious flatterers of the Popes, and ſeducers of the whole Chriſtian world. For theſe were the onely men, who in times paſt perſwaded all Chriſtian Churches, that the Byſhop of Rome was of ſuch Soueraigne power, and authoritie; that albeit, hee ſhould lead the whole world into Damnation,Diſtinct 40. Cap. 51. Papa. no man had power to controle him, no man might be ſo bold as to demand of him a reaſon for ſo Deuiliſh an act.
               And euen thus altogether, or rather a great deale worſe, doth this Societie of ours inſtruct her Nouices, teaching that whatſoeuer our Superiours inioyneth to bee done or doth himſelfe, is not onely not to be queſtioned (much leſſe to be found fault withall) out euer to bee preſuppoſed as holy andIn the ſame Epiſtle. good, to vſe the very words of our Father Ignatius.
               
               
                  And all this onely to this end (forſooth) that all their Foolery, Idolatry, and Superſtition, may at length obtaine the name of Holineſſe, and bee adored as Ordinances of the Societie.
               And now (mee thinkes (I haue brought thee about neere enough to the Knowledge and ſenſible feeling (as it were) of the ſumme of our Religion.
               Neither doe I doubt, but that now at laſt, thou vnderſtandeſt how extreamely wee haue deceiued our ſelues, and bin gulled in making choyce of this kinde of life, and how veniall a ſinne wee ſhall commit, in withdrawing our ſelues from the ſame.
            
            Wherevnto I replyed.
            
               CHRISTIAN:
               Theſe are monſtrous and horrible things indeed PAVL, and truly in my minde I haue often ſeene ſuch kind of Monſters in Italy, but I blinding my vnderſtanding, as our own conſtitutions doe enioyne vs, did ſuppoſe theſe things to be nothing, but deuiſes of Sathan, whereby to divert me out of my courſe, and hauing but once ſhouldered mee out of my calling, by the loſſe thereof, to caſt mee headlong into euerlaſting miſerie.
               Now you, for your part (ſo farre as I diſcerne) putting confidence in moſt abhominable prodigies, rather then the ſtrongeſt arguments, endeauour to diſgrace both our owne firſt Calling, and the whole Religion of Rome: which thing, if I ſhall yeeld vnto you as lawfully done, ſeeing you are but

one man in this kind, I ſee no reaſon why, the ſame libertie may not be granted to the particuler Sects of all others that cauill at Religion. Foraſmuch, as there is no opinion which may not ſeeme to bee proued out of holy Scripture, being vnderſtood and interpreted by euery man as ſhall beſt ſtand with his particular liking.
               But yet conſidering, that all thy relations touching theſe Monſters are wonderfull probable, and the other things alſo moſt euident, and ſuch as doe convince the ſence and vnderſtanding, I cannot herein diſſent from you, nor indeed may I with ſafety, ſeeing I know you to bee as learned and ingenious as our Societie affoordeth any. I will rather endeauour to rouze vp my ſelfe, and call to exact accompt my beſt vnderſtanding in this caſe, which as you ſay, is ouerclouded with Ieſuitioall deluſions, and vnfold the moſt implicite notions of my heart-touching the Societie of Ieſuites, that afterwards you may expreſſe more at large, what is the very Species, forme, and Character of a Ieſuite, whom all the Chriſtian world ſo much honoureth and adoreth.
               And now to the end, that I may after your example fall out of hand vpon the fundamentall points of the Societie, hearken and I will relate vnto you what ſtrange things I haue ſeene and obſerued in theſe ſtranger times.
               I did in my younger dayes (I aſſure you) ſuppoſe, that the foundation of this Societie was altogether Diuine, and me thought I was no longer conuerſant on earth, ſo soone as I was admitted into

this ſocietie, as I thinke it is a vſuall thing with all our Nouices, or the greateſt part of them to be ſo affected. For ſo great is the power of our continued meditations touching diuine ſubiects, that a man ſeemeth euer to bee borne a new, not of naturall parents, but after a peculiar-manner borne a Ieſuite in the Societie of IESVS, euen as CHRIST our Redeemer was incarnate by the holy Ghoſt.
               And thus the whole nature of man being in a māner Deified doth witnes, as which doth from that time forward, wherein it hath giuen it ſelfe to meditations of this nature altogether forbeare to pamper and feed the body, abandoneth all ſocietie of the fleſh, by whipping and other voluntary afflictions of the body, reſtraineth and ſuppreſſeth pleaſure as a blot of infamy and diſhonour, acknowledgeth in euery Spirituall brother the Image of the Lord our God, as our eighteenth Rule commandeth, and withall abjureth and diſpiſeth riches, honours and all ſuch things, as by the vulgar are accounted moſt excellent and precious.
               And this was indeed (without any diſſimulation) my firme and conſtant perſwaſion as touching the ſocietie of Ieſuites, in the firſt yeere of my admiſſion thereunto.
               But this other yeere, when by chance I met with our Iapan-Letters, and there amongſt other things had read, not without aſtoniſhment, that among them of Iapan being our Antipodes, there are certaine religious men, whom they call Iamam buxa, or Souldiers of the Vallies, who purpoſely to at

taine an opinion of Sanctimony, doe puniſh themſelues grieuouſly, doe watch very much, doe Faſt exceeding long, and doe giue themſelues wholly to certaine Meditations compoſed of their owne heads, and that they preuaile ſo farre by theſe things, that they are beleeued many times, (as inſpired with an holy inſtinct) to ſpeake Oracles, and are accounted by all to bee perfect and Holy men; then eſpecially, when as they make no bones of it to kill themſelues voluntarily for their Idoll.
               When I had (as I ſaid) vnderſtood theſe and many other like paſſages out of Letters, written not onely by men of our Order, but alſo publiſhed in Print, I aſſure you I was amazed, and did ſo ſhake as if I had newly fallen from Heauen to Earth.
               For vpon a ſudden it came into my minde, to thinke that nothing could bee deuiſed more like to our Religion; and that therefore, it was vehemently to be ſuſpected, leaſt all this our Spirituall courſe of life ſhould not proue Divine, but Humaine onely and Phariſaicall. Foraſmuch, as very Idolators and Heathens wanting the light of the Goſpel, doe attaine thereunto; and indeed ſuch Heathens, as are ſaid to be wondrous like both in Nature, Manners and Diſpoſition, to our moſt ingenious Europians; I meane our Italians, and Spaniards; ſo that now it is apparant, that the like Religions haue bin deviſed and eſtabliſhed by men of like natures and inclinations.
               And what a ſtrange thing is it, that among thoſe Ethnicks of Iapan, not onely our profeſſion of Ieſuitiſme, but in a ſort the very entire Gouernment

of the Romane Hierarchy may be ſeene apparantly, founded and eſtabliſhed by an Heathen Spirit.
               For in the ſame Letters, it is related, that one chiefe man throughout the whole Empire of Iapan, doth hold the chiefe place of a ſupreame Iudge in matters Eccleſiaſticall, who is little leſſe then worſhipped as a God, and generally reputed ſo Holy a man, that hee may not be ſuffered to tread on the ground, and Cōmandeth farre &amp; wide many times vpon occaſion, euen conteſting with thoſe heathen Princes: Moreouer, this man hath the ordering and making of all the Tundi among them, who are in effect the Byſhops of that Nation; albeit, the nomination of them (as it is reported) be in ſome places in the Gouernours power; which Tundi are thereupon, in great and ſingular eſteeme both with high and low, and doe conferre Prieſthoods, doe appoint Faſting dayes, and grant Licences for eating of Fleſh, to ſuch as vpon Holy dayes goe on Pilgrimage to the Chappels of theyr Saints and Idols.
               Yea and further, the ſects of the Bontij which ariſe among them, and are nothing else but the Monkes of Iapan, haue no authority or eſtimation among the people; vnleſſe this great man haue approued him by his letters Patents and teſtimonials: Furthermore, theſe Bontij are ſaid to inhabite very large and ſpacious Colledges, after the manner of our Monkes, to liue a ſingle life, to erect an Altar in the middeſt of their Chappell, wherevpon they place a woodden repreſentation of Amida ſitting vpon a golden Roſe, very gallant to behold. Alſo

that they haue very great Libraries, with places wherein they eate and drinke together after the manner of our Refectories, and certaine Copper workes which ſerue them inſteed of bels to cal them vp to their houres of prayer.
               Againe, euery euening their preſident or cheife man among them, propoundeth to euery one his particular ſubiect for his meditations that night: and preſently after midnight they doe before the Altar in their Chappell dancing by turnes ſay ouer their deuotions out of the laſt booke of Xaca.
               
               Alſo, that euery morning each of them ſpendeth an houre in Meditations; that they build faire Cloyſters in their chappels for their Fotoquij, who are a certaine ſect of religious perſons amongſt them, that are ſhauen vpon their heades and chinnes, and doe obſerue a great number of holy dayes in the yeere. And yet for all this they write that theſe Bontij are moſt baſe fellowes, in their liues and conuerſations and as coueteous as any men liuing vpon Gods earth, and as well acquainted with all deuiſes how to rake vp money. That theſe Bontij doe make ſale vnto the people of many writings vnder their hands, by helpe whereof, the common people are perſwaded that they are protected from the Deuill.
               Alſo, that theſe Bontij haue a cuſtome to borrow money in this world, which they promiſe to reſtore with large intereſt in the world to come, for which they giue the Creditor bils of their hands as ſecurity, which he at the time of his death carrieth with him into the other world.
               
                  And laſtly, that theſe Bontij are for the moſt part the ſonnes of Noblemen, in regard that the Nobility of Iapan, being full of Children, do vſually take a Courſe to procure theſe ſonnes of theirs entered into the Order of the Bontij, for whom they are not able to prouide otherwiſe.
               You might ſtile theſe men Chriſtian Monkes, or (if you pleaſe) hauing reſpect vnto their qualities Clergy men and Prelates of the Church of Rome, if euer the light of the Goſpell had in any meaſure ſhined vpon them before the comming of our men amongſt them: or if euer any Chriſtian at all had gone ſo farre as vnto them, whereby they▪ might haue heard of theſe things and haue imitated them.
               Neither is prayer for their dead wanting among theſe Iapanezes, howbeit in that they are a little more ſuperſtitious then wee. For in the moneth of Auguſt, they are obſerued to ſet aſide 2. whole daies for Adoration of the Spirits of the Dead. And that a little before Night, they ſet vp a great number of Lampes and other Lights about the doores of their houſes, with much varieties of Paintings and trimmings. That afterwards they walke round about the Citie all night long, partly for Deuotion ſake, and partly to looke about them.
               Alſo, that towards the Euening, a great ſort of people doe walke out of the Citie to meet the Spirits of their Dead friends, now comming towards them▪ as they (forſooth) imagine. When they are at a certaine ſet place, where they ſuppoſe that the Ghoſts of their deceaſed Friends doe meet them;

firſt, they ſalute them kindly, euen as if they ſaw them; ſaying you are heartily welcome, wee haue wanted your good Companie long, I pray you ſit downe a while and refreſh your ſelues with ſome victuals, for wee know you cannot chuſe but be wearie.
               Then they ſet vpon Tables (as a banquet for the Ghoſts to feed vpon) Rice, Fruits, and other Viands, and when they haue demurred about an houres ſpace, as if they thought it high time to make an end, they invite and intreat them to come home to theyr houſes; ſaying, wee will goe before and prouide ſome good cheere for you. Alſo▪ it is obſerued, that aſſoone as theſe two dayes are ouer, they walke out of the Citie againe both men and women with lighted Torches, to conduct them (forſooth) who are now vpon departing, leaſt they ſhould ſtumble in the darke or hurt themſelues againſt any thing.
               Yet further it is obſerued likewiſe, that when they returne into the Citie againe, they make a diligent ſearch about all their high roomes, and tylings of their houſes, by caſting vp ſtones thereon, leaſt any of the Spirits (of whom they are in bodily feare) ſhould remaine behind in ſecret.
               Moreouer, it is written from thence, that when thoſe Iaponezes were demanded by our men, why they did ſet to thoſe Spirits a banquet; they made anſwere, that they are vpon their way towards their Paradice, which ſay they, was ten thouſand Millions of miles, and was a journey that could not bee ended in leſſe then three yeares time; and therefore

they tooke vp their reſting place there for a while to refreſh themſelues, and to enable them the better to hold out to their journeys end.
               But in all theſe things it is obſerued, that the Bontij, the Prieſts and Biſhops of Iapan doe all in all, and that there is no family, though neuer ſo meane, but it muſt offer one guift or other to the Bontij, for the peace of the ſoules of their deceaſed Friends
               I Omit for brevity ſake, their Holy water, their pots of ſweet odours ſet ouer hot coales to make perfume, their many and large Indulgences which theſe Bontij doe tender vnto the people, who are frequent at their preachments, and enrich their Cloyſters. Their beades to pray vpon, which a great number of the Iapanezes doe daily runne ouer, not onely within their priuate houſes, but publiquely alſo, carrying them about in their hands all ouer the Citty praying to their Amida, and to their Xaca for riches, honours, proſperous health, and euerlaſting Comforts. All which things verily are ſo true, that they are both obſerued and written by men of our owne Order, and I haue in relating thereof made vſe almoſt Verbatim of that tranſlation, which our Father Petrus Maffaeus hath made out of the Italian into Latine.
               
               And this indeed was an opinion of mine, or rather (as my Confeſſor told me) a temptation of the Devill caſt into my mind, touching the Societie of Ieſuites and the whole Church of Rome, which, for all that I was hardly able in many dayes to thruſt out of my thoughts, by oppoſing through ejaculations

of heart (as they terme them) and through faſtings with other afflictions of the body, a whole troupe of Arguments of this nature, violently burſting in vpon my vnderſtanding day and night.
               And now before this temptation was well diſgeſted and ouercome, behold vpon a ſudden there fell vpon me another of the ſame nature which ſo handled me, as ſcarcely it left any life in me; For ſhortly after it ſo fell out, that we had the 18. Chapter of the third booke of Kings read vnto vs at dinner time, for our Spirituall repaſt, wherein is contayned the ſtory of the Prieſts of Baal, and how for the pleaſing or appeaſing of their Idoll, they had a Cuſtome to cut themſelues with kniues and launces till they bled amaine. Which words when I heard our Chaplaine read, for (I confeſſe) I was not then a Diuine, neither had I euer as then read ouer the holy Scriptures, verily I did tremble and ſhake all ouer, as if I had beene taken with a ſudden fit of an Ague, nor had I any further ſtomacke to my dinner at that time, as remembring (to be true to you) our owne whippings whereby as well as with kniues &amp; launces we our ſelues are cruel to our own fleſh, many times ſpilling not a little of our owne blood, and I cannot ſay, but as theſe Iapaneze Ieſuites whom I told you of, that they haue named Iamambuxae, ſome of vs at ſometimes become guilty of our owne deaths, I am ſure wee ſpoyle our healths by it. But I feare leaſt theſe and fiue hundred more ſpirituall doubts, mentioned by me touching the Societie, may bee triviall to bee propounded vnto ſo judicious and graue a Divine, as

your ſelfe, not being worth your taking notice of. Wherefore letting other paſſages ſlip by vs▪ I will be bold to deſcribe vnto you onely two; Holy, and Catholique, that is to ſay, Italian Monſters and Idols, the maintenance whereof our Society hath peculiarly taken vpon themſelues, and concerning which, I am troubled and haue bin theſe ten yeares together, how I might make them Holy in my eſtimation, as they are made Catholique long ſince. Out of which diſcourſe of mine, you ſhall perceiue your opinion touching the Society of Ieſuites and the Romane Church, wonderfully confirmed and eſtabliſhed.
               The one of theſe Idols▪ I my ſelfe haue ſeene at Rome in the Chappell of St. PETER, which Idoll, men vſually call the Vicar of CHRIST.
               And I aſſure you, when firſt I ſaw it, I was of an opinion, that it was either CHRIST himſelfe, or ſurely ſomething more eſteemed of then CHRIST; foraſmuch, as all the people which flocked thither for deuotion ſake, ſo ſoone as euer they beheld it, ſet on high on a Throne and ſupported by the hands of red men like Seraphin-Angels, (leaſt perhaps it might daſh its foot againſt a ſtone) fell downe inſtantly vpon their knees beating their breſts, and performing ſuch outward acts of Devotion in that kind, as appertaineth to none but God onely.
               Oh holy CHRIST, (did my ſoule then inſtantly cry out in priuate) how long will it pleaſe thee to ſuffer this, that as low as thy ſelfe being true GOD, haſt humbled thy ſelfe on earth, ſo high thy

                  Vicar being but a wretched and a ſinfull man, ſhall extoll and aduance himſelfe aboue all heauens? That whereas thou hadſt no kingdome heere; yea, haſt ſaid, that thy Kingdome was not of this world,
                  John. 18. neither woudlſt take vpon thee any Kingly Maieſty. Thy Vicar neuertheleſſe, ſhould haue right and intereſt in all Kingdomes, and ſhould out ſtrip all Kings and Potentates; yea, euen thee, O King of Kings, in wordly Pompe and heauenly Maieſty of State.
               That whereas thy Diſciple St. PETER, who is ſaid to haue bin Created the firſt Pope, would not permit Cornelius the Centurion ſo much as to fall downe at his feet, much leſſe to kiſſe them; but inſtantlyAct. 10▪
                   tooke him vp, ſaying; Ariſe, for I alſo am a man: his Succeſſor for all that, forgetting himſelfe to bee a man ſhould ſit on high, as a very God Almighty, whoſe feet all men muſt fall downe at and kiſſe?
               But yet I recalled my ſelfe by and by, and ſomewhat pacified my minde with this Meditation: Surely, (ſaid I) it is altogether neceſſary, that the Pope ſhould retaine this his outward Pompe and Maieſty, the better by that meanes to draw vnto him the proud Emperours, Kings and Princes of this world, and to retaine them in true Obedience; as alſo to dazell the eyes of the vulgar people, to the end that what cannot be done amongſt ſuch men by Humilitie, may at leaſt bee brought about by Subtiltie and Policie, that whereas hee is not able to preſerue his reputation by teſtimonies of his owne Holineſſe

and vertue, as CHRIST and his Apoſtles and other Holy men haue done, hee may vphold it at leaſt by the outward glory of another, leaſt that whereas the auncient Romanes were in times paſt Lords of the whole World, if the power of the Biſhop of Rome, ſhould not extend it ſelfe fully both to Heaven and Hell, yea and Purgatorie alſo, a place deuiſed for this purpoſe; the Pope might hap to ſeeme inferiour to them, or at the leaſt not greater.
               That as Iupiter Optimus Maximus, the prime GOD of all among the Romans, is ſuppoſed to ſtrike ſome perſons to hell with his Thunderbolt, ſo the Romane Biſhop ſhould haue in like manner, his terrible Thunderbolt of Excommunication, whereby he might make the hearts of all Chriſtians to ſhake, and might thruſt down as many as ſhould but dare to lift vp their tongues againſt this Soueraigne power of his, lower then hell it ſelfe if it could be poſſibly.
               Laſt of all, that whereas the ancient Romanes being Lords of all the world, had a moſt honourable and ſtately Magiſtracie, cloathed in purple, whereof ſome were Gouernours of the Citie, others ruled as Vice-Royes in forraigne Nations: Euen ſo the Pope of Rome, ſhould haue not onely his Biſhops as Princes; but alſo his Cardinals as Senators clad in purple, who ſhould bee companions for the greateſt Kings, and out of whom alone the Vicar of CHRIST ſhould bee choſen by the very inſtinct of the Holy Ghoſt. As if the Holy Ghoſt ſhould

not aſwell be tyed to the Cardinals, thoſe baſe and beaſtly ſinckes of Luſt and Ambition, as the Chaire of PETER to the Citie of Rome.
               
               For indeed it is true, that the Holy Ghoſt hath ſayd; That by his goodwill, hee cannot indure to dwell in any but quiet, modeſt and humble perſons, and yet (forſooth) of late, he is euen conſtrained by compulſion, and (as it were) halfe againſt his will to reſide, whereſoeuer the Church of Rome ſhall be pleaſed to confine him.
               Howbeit, I muſt confeſſe, in this caſe my Conſcience did often tell mee, that they of the Church of Rome haue not beene able to tye the Holy Ghoſt ſo cloſe to themſelues and their Sea, but that twenty and ſeauen ſundry times fayling of the preſence thereof, they haue raiſed thoſe XXVII. Schiſmes which ſtand vpon Record in the Chronicles of their Popes: A thing which ſurely giueth infallible euidence, againſt their holy Spirit, and cauſeth all the priuiledges and power thereof, to incurre a juſt Cenſure; For alas! what ſhall wee ſay? Is it poſſible, that the Divine Godhead can bee an author of Errour and Diſſention?
               But when they are held cloſe to this Argument, then they anſwer; That the Holy Ghoſt departed not from the Church of Rome, at ſuch or ſuch a time, but onely through the miſtake of ſome, and ambition of others, the Church had gotten a Monſtrous head, hauing ſometimes a double, ſometimes a treble head, but that onely one of the reſt was the true and lawfull head of the Church.
               
               Oh, what monſtrous ſpirits haue you, (the Romaniſts)

what a monſtrous Church? Which can be compelled through Errour and Ambition, to ſubſiſt ſo often and with ſo many counterfeit Heads? To weare them ſo many yeares, and to inforce ſo many poore Chriſtian ſoules to accept and to beleeue them vpon paine of Damnation for true Heads of the Church, to their owne miſtake, the abhomination of all good men, and your owne and their moſt deſperate ruine.
               Well, now I perceiue plaingly enough, that this Monſter which hath ſo often had two Heads, and ſometimes three at once, may alſo through your monſtrous Luſt and Ambition, as eaſily acquire Seauen heads at once. But this may be ſufficient touching the firſt Monſter or Idoll.
               The other Idoll I haue ſeene at Loretto, which the Italians call their Lady of Loretto: And this is a Picture carued (as they would haue men beleeue) by St. LVKE the Evangeliſt. And for that cauſe, it is reported to be a worker of wonderfull Miracles. I am not able in words to expreſſe, in what infinite eſtimation this Idoll is held, what a report there is all Italy ouer, of the Myracles that it worketh. This is the onely Saint that all Italians haue in their mouth preſently, whether they bee amazed with any ſudden feare of Death, or taken Sicke with any grieuous diſeaſe whatſoeuer.
               Vnto this Lady of Loretto, doe all ſorts of people in ſuch caſes make Vowes, promiſe guifts, vndertake to goe on Pilgrimage vnto her Temple. And if it ſo fall out, that any man bee deliuered from any imminent danger, or diſeaſe, they preſently

then cry out a Miracle, a Miracle, and reſolue to performe their promiſe, and ſtraight wayes they vndertake a Pilgrimage to Loretto.
               
               Vpon theſe occaſions, there is great reſort to Loretto day by day out of all the parts of Italy; daily are innumerable Offerings preſented at her Shrine, and painted tables hanged vp in her Chappell expreſſing the whole manner of the Miracles. And truely at the firſt ſight thereof, the infinite multitude of Tables did ſomewhat moue me, and I was of the mind that ſome Divine eſſence ruled in that place. But when I came a little to my ſelfe, vpon ſerious conſideration of all the paſſages together, I eaſily diſcerned, that it was nothing elſe but meerely the dotage of the blockiſh people, who being onely guided by outward ſence, labour to haue a ſenſible God, I meane a Deitie, which they might ſee and feele: For vpon the one hand I obſerued, a man pictured vpon the Racke, and valiantly induring all thoſe torments by prayer made to the Lady of Loretto: hard by him was portrayed, a man falling from his Horſe, and eſcaping death by a ſudden prayer made to the ſame Lady: On the other hand, you might ſee a multitude of Sicke people miraculouſly reſtored to health by calling vpon her Name: Not farre from them, diuers Tables of people of all ſorts in a ſtorme at Sea eſcaping the violence thereof, by a Vow made to the ſame Lady; with many others of like nature not to be numbred.
               Which follies, euen CICERO himſelfe, being a diligent obſeruer of the Roman Superſtitions▪ did

in his time ſeeme to deride in his booke De Natura Deorum, touching the nature of the Gods of the Romanes, wherein making mention of the Philoſopher DIAGORAS deriding the Roman Deities; hee thus writeth: That when DIAGORAS vpon a time was come to Samothrace, and that a friend of his had tooke ocaſion to ſay vnto him; You Sir, who are of Opinion, that our Gods doe not heare the prayers of their Suppliants, and order humaine Affaires, doe not you obſerue by this multitude of painted Tables, how many men by prayer to the Gods, haue eſcaped the violence of tempeſts and ſtormes at Sea and come ſafe to Land?
               It is true indeed, ſaid the Philoſopher, heere is a multitude of Tables of them which haue eſcaped; For they are no where painted that haue ſuffered Shipwracke, notwithſtanding, their prayers to theſe Gods in this kinde, and haue periſhed at Sea.
               Which anſwere of his, was wittie and beſeeming a Philoſopher; for thereby hee did euidently enough declare, that ſuch people had not bin preſerued by the helpe or fauour of IVPITER, or IVNO, or NEPTVNE, or any other of their ſuppoſed Deities, to whom they had directed their Supplications in this caſe. Foraſmuch, as many others beſide, and ſuch as perhaps were honeſter, and better men then thoſe who eſcaped, though they had made the ſame prayers had periſhed in the waues.
               But foraſmuch, as all men generally were accuſtomed in any time of diſtreſſe to flye by prayer to

one or other of thoſe ſuppoſed Deities, and that it often fell out, that naturall cauſes being violently prouoked, and threatning Death, being eyther ſtopped in the middeſt of their courſe, or mittigated of themſelues, doe vpon a ſudden yeeld hopes of deliuerance. Thence is it, that the effect thereof is without any good reaſon, aſcribed to their fained and imaginary Deities.
               
               And euen thus and no otherwiſe, ſtandeth the caſe with our people of Italy, in adoring and beleeuing on that Idoll of Loretto, and offering vnto it Tables of Deuotion; becauſe, inaſmuch as all Italy almoſt maketh prayers vnto her, and that of neceſſitie it muſt fall out, that by one meanes or other in ſo great a Multitude of people, ſome few at the leaſt ſhall obtaine what they haue prayed for, either through the eſpeciall hand of God, or by the ſtrength of nature; And that nature at ſomtimes euen ſeemeth to worke a Miracle; all thoſe things, are by theſe ſtupi'd and blockiſh people attributed to their Lady of Loretto; except perhaps men would deny, that in the ſame manner, and for the ſame end, the Image of Ceres at a Citie called Enna in Sicilia, as the ſame Cicero witneſſeth, hath made open declaration of her power and Godhead (to vſe Tullies owne phraſe) by many Miracles and wonders many a time, and full often euen in the deſperateſt caſes afforded vnto her ſuppliants preſent helpe and remedy.
               But theſe things (as I haue formerly ſaid vnto you) almoſt none but the vulgar, and ſuch as are like vnto them doe runne after and beleeue.
               
                  For euen the more learned of their owne, Phiſicians, Philoſophers, and Diuines alſo, as many as haue not their mouthes ſtopped with ſome Eccleſiaſticall preferment, do in their better judgements contemne and deride, not onely theſe Miracles of Loretto, but euen the very Romane religion it ſelfe as falſe and fained, as I eaſily and apparantly diſcerned at my being at Naples, where they had at that time obtained ſome reſtraint of the violence of the Romane Inquiſition.
               Yea and moreouer, theſe Atheiſts euen to my face derided my name, becauſe it was Chriſtianus, for in the Italian Dialect by the word Chriſtian they are wont to intimate a Blockhead, or ſilly fooliſh fellow; which thing (as I conceiue) they doe for this reaſon, becauſe in their judgement they hold no man fit or inclinable to beleeue the Popiſh Chimaraes, but ſilly fooles and blockheads.
               And theſe are chiefly thoſe things which came into my mind to ſpeake and relate touching the Societie of Ieſuites, &amp; the Idols which it more particularly beleeueth in and adoreth, beeing rowzed vp thereunto by your diſcourſe, and beyond all expectation illuminated therewith.
            
            
               PAVL.
               At this word, Paulus looking ſtedfaſtly in my face, ſpoke thus vnto mee; I will not (ſaith hee) henceforth any more enquire after the Cauſes of ſo great blindneſſe in the Ieſuites. I will admit no more excuſes. If in thee so great a light of the truth could be depraued by Ieſuiticall Education and almoſt quite extinct in thee, as

I verily ſuppoſe it had beene in all likelihood, if God had not ſent me hither; What may I imagine they are not able to worke in the darke and infatuated vnderſtanding of others?
               When he had thus ſaid, immediately the watchword was giuen, that it was time to retire from our walke and recreation and both of vs in priuate retired to our priuate Chambers.
            
            Here endeth the firſt Booke.
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            A DISCOVERIE OF THE SECRET DESIGNES AND BLOODIE Proiects of the Societie of IESVITES of later yeares.
            
            
               WHat MARCVS CATO ſometimes ſpoke concerning the Romane Southſayers; that hee wondred how they could forbeare to ſmile vpon each other, ſo often as they met, may not vnfitly be applyed to the Ieſuites: It is a wonder that one Ieſuite when hee looketh vpon another doth not ſtraight way burſt foorth into a laughing outright, they being amongſt themſelues priuie to ſuch impoſtures practiſed vpon the people. I ſpeake not touching your ſimpler ſort of Ieſuites, from whom theſe more reſerued and cloſer practiſes of the Societie are altogether concealed, either in reſpect they are not held wiſe enough (forſooth) to bee acquainted with them, or that they are thought too deuout to entertaine them, or elſe in regard of their ſhort continuance in that Society: for all ſuch are ſo kept ſhort through ſeuerity of Diſcipline, that not one of them, except

hee bee wondrous quicke of ſent, can euer ſmell out in the leaſt meaſure what knauery is therein practiſed vnder a ſhew of Holineſſe. My diſcourſe onely toucheth the prime and principall fellowes of that Societie, their Regents, Fathers, Provincials, and Generals; all which, are ſo vniuerſally and joyntly tainted with all manner of wickedneſſe, but eſpecially with Whoredome, Couerouſnes, and Magicke, that indeed any reaſonable man may thinke it little leſſe then a Miracle, if a Ieſuite of this ranke meeting ſuch another vpon a ſudden, and beholding, as it were, another picture or liuely repreſentation of himſelfe, ſhould haue power to abſtaine from laughing outright.
            I therefore thought it not amiſſe, conſidering the premiſſe
                  •
               , to lay open vnto the world ſome particuler paſſages, and practiſes of that Society, of the greateſt part whereof my ſelfe haue beene an eyewitneſſe, and ſome part whereof hath been related vnto me by Ieſuites whom I am able to name, and will vndoubtedly nominate, if they ſhall but dare in the leaſt manner to lift vp their tongues againſt mee, or to contradict what I haue written. And howſoeuer at this time I paſſe ouer things briefly, and doe onely (as it were) giue you a firſt draught thereof, I doe purpoſe in due time (God aſſiſting me) to do it more largely and compleatly, with expreſſion of all and ſingular circumſtances thereunto appertaining.
            Firſt of all then, at my entrance into my Colledge of Ieſuites; eſpecially, if it be ſcituated in or

neere vnto any large, and populous, and rich place. But alas, why doe I ſay, if it be built there? (Seeing they haue no Colledges in any poore, meane, or obſcure place.) At your firſt entry I ſay into ſuch a place or Colledge, take principall notice of the Porter of their Gate, and him you ſhall find to looke like vnto the very picture of a very Charon, or rather a Cerberus; For the moſt part you ſhall obſerue him to bee a man of very great yeares, or if he bee younger, hee is a fellow of moſt approued truſt and ſecrecie. And this is the man, if any ſuch there bee, who is well skilled in all the myſteries of the Ieſuites Caball, or reſerued Diuinity.
            
            In this fellowes keeping is great ſtore of apparell both for Men and Women of euery degree and calling. And with this apparell doe the Ieſuites habite themſelues according to the quallity that euery one findeth himſelfe ableſt to perſonate, and ſo practiſe wonderfull Impoſtures in the world. For at ſometimes beeing habited like Souldiers very gallant, then walke in the ſtreets and highwayes Whoring and Swaggering in the publike Stewes. At other times in the ciuill habites of Citizens, profeſſing themſelues to bee of the reformed Religion, they pry vp and downe and liſten in Innes, in Play-houſes, in Tauernes, vpon the Exchange, and in all places of publike meetings, whereſoeuer there is any frequent reſort, what the people ſpeake vp and downe concerning them, what conſultations are abroad, what matter of Action is ſet a foot in any part. Another while,

like Doctors of Phyſicke, or of the Ciuill Law, with great gold Rings on their fingers, avowing and purpoſely profeſſing themſelues to be Papiſts; whereſoeuer they know any of the Common ſort that is wealthy and hath ſonnes, they deuiſe ſome cauſe of buſineſſe with them, and inſinuate themſelues into their acquaintance by ſtrange fetches, and in Concluſion doe adviſe them to bring vp their ſonnes in ſome Schoole or Colledge of Ieſuites, affirming that themſelues haue beene Educated by them, and that they haue ſo profited vnder them, that (God bee thanked) they neuer had cauſe to repent thereof: And ſometimes againe apparelled like Noblemen, and compleatly attended, they cauſe Coaches to bee prouided abroad, and frequent the Courts of Princes, as giuing attendance vpon Ambaſſadors of forraigne States, and ſerue as Intelligencers to vnlocke the cabinets of great Potentates.
            Nay further, I haue knowne them to make ſhew of being baniſhed perſons, and to craue collections amongſt Proteſtant Divines, purpoſely to learne vnderhand what ſuch men writ againſt them: yea ſuch were thoſe men for the moſt part, who ſo miſerably deluded ſo many Reverend men in many places by ſiniſter wayes vnder that habit, furthering the deſignes of their Societie, and breeding diſturbances in the reformed Congregations: of whom, to the end that all honeſt-hearted Miniſters may be more warie hereafter, I ſhall tell you hereafter, what proiects at this day the Ieſuites haue a foote to this purpoſe.
            
               But in the meane while perhaps you will ſay vnto me, whereto, I pray you, ſerueth ſo much womens apparell, or what is their end in depoſiting ſo much in the keeping of the Porter of their gate. Attend, and I will tell you: No Pander, that euer TIRENCE or PLAVTVS mentioned in their Comedies, was ſo nimble at the trade of winning pretty wenches, at are the Ieſuites at this day, but eſpecially that Porter of their gate whom I mentioned but now.
            For, that which the Confeſſors themſelues are not able to wring out of them by Auricular Confeſſion in their Churches and Chappels, this fellow knoweth how to winne from them by flattering ſpeeches, with wonderfull pleaſing and delightfull toyes, eſpecially if he meete with a poore widdow, or any ſuch ſilly woman which ſendeth her child to the Colledge now and then for an Almes; or with ſome Laundreſſe, or Spinſter; for bee ſhee Lotrix, or Petrix, hee will make her a Meretrix. Whom ſo ſoone as this baſe Pander hath once but allured to come to his net, although her apparell bee neuer ſo old and tattered, yet hee hath gay Gownes enough in ſtore, with accoutrements ſuitable, wherewith hee can make her both tricke and trimme, which when hee hath ſo done, hee knoweth how to convey her through many ſecret paſſages and by-wayes to his Venerable Maiſters, the Fathers of the Societie. And yet he neuer doth this in the day time, but neere vpon the ſhutting in of the Euening, and then they make away the whole night in Ryot and Luxurie, with reuelling

and Dancing, the younger ſort and Nouices of the Societie being kept farre enough from Diſcouery thereof.
            For they haue for the purpoſe certaine Vaults framed like Chambers, and roomes vnder ground as had thoſe ancient Romanes, who firſt deuiſed there Stewes in Vaults, whoſe inclination to all carnall laſciuiouſnes was ſo great, and ſo bruitiſh, that the Senate of Rome, fearing the iuſt anger of their Gods for the ſame, vtterly ſuppreſſed thoſe Lupanaria or publike Stewes.
            And thus much for the Ieſuites Porter of their Gate: onely I muſt not forget to tell you this one thing, that if any party who by chance ſhall come to the ſight of ſuch and ſo great a Wardrobe, doe demand with admiration, what is the end or vſe of it, anſwere is made vnto them, that it is the wardrobe, reſerued purpoſely for acting of Playes: but that is the leaſt part of their intention to my knowledge.
            Moreouer, when thou entreſt into any of their Churches, make account that thou walkeſt vnder an heauen of Iron: Bloody Mars is ouer thine head, not that Prince of peace; below thee is the very pit of Hell, and a ſhop of Tormenters.
            I now doe relate in good earneſt, what mine owne eyes haue ſeene; At Prague in Bohemia vpon the roofe of their Churches, are thouſands of Iron Bullets, Whips, and fire bals, ſuch as the Bohemians vſe: vpon the ſides are placed pieces of Ordnance, with a great number of Muſquets and

Harquebuſhes, with Pikes and Halberts. In the middeſt, where the Arches meete, are great heapes of huge Bullets of ſtone▪ And the like preparation haue they alſo made at Craconia. Nor doe I make queſtion, but that vpon due ſearch their Colledges in other places, would appeare as well provided.
            But ſome man may perhaps make queſtion, to what end Religious men ſhould make ſuch preparation, or what need there can be ſo to doe. I confeſſe, the matter at the firſt ſight aſtoniſhed me, and to my beſt vnderſtanding was exceeding ſtrange: but thus ſtandeth the caſe.
            The Ieſuites know well enough, that the courſes which they haue taken formerly, and now euery day doe take, are ſo indirect and turbulent, as maketh them odious, to all ſuch as they liue amongſt; yea, to very Papiſts themſelues, at leaſt to the wiſer ſort of them, in reſpect of many things which they haue done both tumultuouſly, and wickedly, whereſoever they haue got footing in the leaſt manner. For they haue no regard of any, they ſpare not to roote vp the very Catholickes themſelues, ſo that they may pleaſure the Popes Holineſſe therein, though it were with the betraying of their Countries, and ſetting the whole Chriſtian world in a Combuſtion. And therefore becauſe they are in daily feare to bee maſſacred by thoſe among whom they liue, they make this provident and timely prevention by Warre-like preparation.
            
               For indeed, they are afraid (as I my ſelfe haue heard them confeſſe) leaſt it might befall vnto them as vnto the Knights Templers, who notwithſtanding they were forward enough to ſerue the Pope at all times, and as good Catholickes as could bee wiſhed in the matter of Religion; yet, for theyr too much Ambition and Couetouſneſſe, whereby they became inſupportable, they were by the conſent of all Chriſtian Princes, and not without approbation from the Pope himſelfe put to the Sword all at an inſtant, and vtterly rooted out almoſt in a moment; as ſometimes were the Pythagorians, thoſe very Ieſuites in effect, among the Heathen, ſerued throughout Italy, and the Provinces adioyning.
            Now the reaſon, wherefore they doe make choiſe to lay vp their Armes and munition in their Churches▪ is onely this: For if when any Inſurrection or rebellious tumult ariſeth in a Province, the Papiſts come thither to helpe and aſſiſt them, by this meanes they haue Armes for them in a readineſſe vpon a ſuddaine: but if any who are of contrary Religion come thither to doe them wrong▪ or to ſteale any thing from them, they haue munition and ſtones aboue head, to deſtroy them withall before they be aware. And is not this (I pray you) he ready way to make the Houſe of Prayer, a Den of Theeues.
            
            And yet by your patience, if you will but attend, I ſhall relate things more ſtrange and horrible then theſe, in reſpect whereof, the things I haue related hitherto▪ may well ſee me tollerable, I may almoſt ſay Innocencie,
            
               Vnder the Pauement of their Church at Gratz, and elſewhere▪ to my knowledge, are Vaults and buildings vnder ground; whereunto, there is no way but by ſtaires, and ſteps; Here haue they hoorded vp (like to that Cacus whom Virgil ſpeaketh of) all theyr prey and treaſure, and doe obſcurely conceale a world of wealth: ſo profeſſing pouertie, not onely with publike conſent, but alſo with incredible pleaſure, ſuffering the ſame with admirable patience, and Curſing to the pit of Hell, all ſuch as are poore againſt their wils, as vnworthy of ſo bleſſed a Croſſe.
            But as for this their treaſure, for the moſt part it is ſo contriued, that it is buried directly and perpendicularly vnder their greateſt and chiefeſt or moſt eminent and higheſt Altar, and ſo they ſhall be ſure that when they Chant Maſſe, they ſhall Sacrifice to MARS aboue head, and to MAMMON below.
            Now furthermore, in their Vaults vnder ground they maintaine a very ſtrange Library, of Cords, Halters, Rackes, Swords, Axes, Iron-pincers, Stockes, Torches, Pillories, and ſouerall Inſtruments of Torture, wherewith and whereunto poore wretches being tyed faſt, are joynt by joynt torne a ſunder as many as fall into the hands of theſe Tyrants, who are farre more cruell in this kind, then MEZENTIVS or PHALARIS ever were.
            Nor are they without a Divels coate, and a long ſteeple crown'd hat with blacke feathers, a jagged doublet cut and ſlaſhed, breeches puffed out and

bagged like bellowes, downe to their anckles, ſuch as would euen make a man affrighted to looke vpon them.
            But perhaps, he that readeth this Relation, will wonder to what end Religious perſons, who profeſſe themſelues the Diſciples and followers (as they would haue all men to beleeue) of our moſt meeke Saviour IESVS, ſhould make ſuch proviſion. I will reſolue you this queſtion alſo, if you pleaſe to attend.
            With ſuch inſtruments as theſe, doth the Societie captivate the vnderſtanding of their Diſciples, vnto Ieſuiticall obedience. For if in the leaſt matter, they get any hinte of ſuſpition, againſt any of theyr Novices, that he will not be conſtant, or that he deſireth to eſcape from them, and that he is likely to betray the ſecrets of their Societie, they clap vp ſuch a fellow, in a faire paire of ſtockes, and having macerated him a long time with hunger, and cold, and want of all bodily comforts; at the laſt, they make an end of him, with ſome exquiſite tortures, and killing torments. I doe not belye them. I write nothing but a truth. There was at Gratz, about three yeares agoe, a young man named IACOBVS CLVSSEVS, a youth of an excellent and pregnant wit; this man did they lay hands vpon, and miſerably tormented him, by whipping and ſcourging, for a matter of no moment, and becauſe hee told them plainely, that hee would renounce their Societie, and complaine publikely (if ever hee got libertie) for this and other ſuch wicked

dealings towards him, they clapped him vp into ſuch a Priſon, vnder ground, as aforeſayd, from whence hee was neuer ſeene to come out againe aliue.
            Nor did any of vs that were Novices, make queſtion, but that hee was made an end of, with moſt exquiſite torments.
            Which vnparalell'd piece of tyranny, I purpoſe in due time to divulge to the whole world, with relation of all circumſtances, beeing the thing which the poore wretched Cluſſaeus, had a purpoſe to haue done himſelfe, if hee had not beene hindered and preuented by death.
            I ſhall withall make publike vnto the world, another ſuch piece of Villanie, committed by the Ieſuites of Fulda in Germanie, vpon the body of one MARTINVS, whom they ſtole away moſt baſely from his Parents, who are yet liuing at Miltenberg or Milberg.
            
            And how many women thinke you, haue beene deuoured and eaten vp in the ſame Gulfe? How many young Children ſlaine? How many young men, that haue beene ſole Heyres of very large and ample Patrimonies, haue beene made away by them? I doe not ſay, I thinke, but I beleeue, and am firmely perſwaded, ſo often as ſhrikes, and cryes, ſighings, and moſt woefull lamentations, were heard in the night ſeaſon, the hearing whereof; would put a man into a cold ſweat all over, and make his hayre ſtand on end, though our ſimpler Novices, beleeued them to bee

the Soules of ſome lately departed, it was nothing but the ſhrikes and mone of children lately murthered, or then a murthering.
            Moreover, that the extreame and Diueliſh malice of Ieſuites, may be in nothing defectiue, they are accuſtomed diuers times in thoſe their Vaults vnder ground to make the Diuell very fine ſport: putting on terrible diſguiſes, they cauſe ſome of theyr Novices to be called downe to behold theyr Tragedie, vpon whom they will ruſh ſuddainely with an horrible yelling noyſe, to make tryall, (forſooth) of theyr courage and conſtancie.
            For if they find any to bee timorous and fearefull, they admit not ſuch a man to the ſecrets of Magicke, as accounting them cowardly and degenerate, but appoint them to ſome of the inferiour Arts: but ſuch as appeare to bee of bold and vndaunted Spirits, they take eſpeciall notice of them, and reſerue them for ſerious imployments.
            And yet they are not alwayes ſucceſſefull for all this, as appeared by that which happened at Prague in the yeare 1602. For whereas there were fiue principall Ieſuites, who being habited as Devils made ſport with their youth, It ſo fell out, that there was found to bee a ſixth in their company, before they were aware, and hee queſtionleſſe was a Divell indeed, who catching vp one of the perſonated Diuels in his Armes, gaue him ſuch a kindly vnkind embrace, that within three dayes after, hee dyed of it▪ The fact was common talke

at Bake-houſes, and Barberſhops, and at euery table diſcourſed vpon, all over Prague.
            
            And yet for all that, the reſt of them, as nothing amazed with this Tragicall event, dare ſtill in an height of obſtinacio, proceed in that moſt vngodly and Diueliſh ſtudy of Magicke.
            Now amongſt that whole Societie, the prime man for a Magician, a French Ieſuite, whom the King of France himſelfe, had in ſo high eſtimation, that hee admitted him not onely to his Princely table, but alſo to familiar conferences in priuate; concerning whom, the Ieſuites themſelues did make their boaſt, that he had a glaſſe made by Art Magicke, wherein hee could plainely repreſent vnto the King, whatſoeuer his Maieſtie deſired to ſee: inſomuch, that there was nothing ſo ſecretly done or conſulted vpon in the moſt private Roome of of any Cloyſter or Nunnerie of other Orders, which hee could not eaſily and inſtantly diſcouer, and diſcloſe, by helpe of this his Inchanted, or rather Diueliſh glaſſe.
            And indeed it was by the Art and meanes of this Magician Ieſuite, that their Societie was confident, that they ſhould bee able to draw on theyr ſide, one of the moſt potent Princes of the Empire, albeit a Proteſtant: foraſmuch, as hee was obſerved to bee ſomewhat delighted in the Study of Magicke.
            Now, as for thoſe whom they take in as Nouices to be inſtructed in this way, they expound vnto thē thoſe nine hundred Propoſitions, which PICVS,

Earle of Mirandula publiſhed at Rome: as alſo the Booke of Iohannes Tritemius, together with a Tract or Treatiſe touching abſtruſe or hidden Philoſophy, written by Cornelius Agrippa: Likewiſe Theophraſius, concerning the Conſtellations and Seales of the Planets, with the Steganographia of I know not what Abbot, and the Art of PAVL to procure Revelations: meaning Saint PAVL, whom they affirme to haue beene inſtructed in the Art Magicke, and thereby to haue vnderſtood ſuch high Revelations and profound Myſteries.
            Yea, they bluſh not to affirme, that Saint IOHN was an excellent Magician: Nor doe they ſticke to ſay, that euen our bleſſed Sauiour CHRIST IESVS himſelfe, was a moſt abſolute and perfect Magician, as mine owne eares haue heard it oftener then once or twice related by ſome of that Societie, and ſuch as I am able to nominate.
            And thus much for the Ieſuites Church: Onely, take this direction along with you; thoſe Vaults and Roomes vnder ground, which I mentioned euen now, thoſe ſecret conueyances and Circean Dennes, are for the moſt part contriued to be vnder the Quire or Cloiſter, not where the people doe walke or ſtand.
            And now when thou ſhalt paſſe from their Temple into theyr Studie (for I will ſay nothing touching theyr Parlour, or Chambers, Refectories, or places of Recreation, inſtruction of Novices

who are newly admitted, and the trayning vp of other Schollers committed to the Ieſuites tuition; nor yet touching the Methode and Order of their Studies, but will reſerue that for another Diſcourſe; ſeeing thoſe paſſages are for the moſt part knowne abroad already, being diſcovered by another.) When, I ſay, thou ſhalt enter into their publike Library, thou ſhalt finde a moſt exquiſite choiſe of Authors of all ſorts, all of them moſt curiouſly bound vppe in Leather or Parchment with fillets of Siluer or Gold: and as for ſuch whereof there is daily vſe, they are layd in order vpon Deskes, faſtened with chaines vpon a long table.
            But as for the inner Librarie, that is onely reſerued for the Fathers of the Societie: it is free for none but them to goe in thither, and to borrow thence what bookes they thinke good. Thoſe ordinary bookes, are onely free for the Iuniors of the Societie, nor may they take a ſentence out of the reſt without ſpeciall leaue obtained from the Regent.
            Moreouer, in this firſt Librarie, are no Hereticall bookes (as they call them) but onely the Writings of moſt approued Authors and Catholickes all▪ For they hold any other vnworthy to bee placed amongſt them, as fearing perhaps they ſhould infect the reſt.
            Looke therefore vpon thy left hand, and there thou ſhalt ſee the wretched bookes of Heretickes, (as they tearme them) ſtanding all in

Mourning for the faults of their Authors, bound vp in blacke Leather, or Parchment blacked over, with the very leaues thereof dyed in blacke.
            Of theſe, not one of the Fathers themſelues may make choyſe or vſe, without leaue obtained from the Regent before hand: but your inferiour Ieſuites and younger Novices, may not bee ſo bold, as to deſire the ſight of any one of them, except he will before hand, with all virulencie and bitterneſſe, raile vpon, and diſgrace the Author, whom hee deſireth to ſee, by ſome infamous Lybell, and ſcurrilous Satyricall verſe, or writing.
            In the middeſt of theſe ſeuerall Libraries, is placed a Study, beeing divided into many Seates diſtinct, and ſeparate one from another, with a blew covering: on the right ſide whereof, ſit the Fathers; on the left, the vnder-Graduates; who haue already taken ſome Degrees vpon them. The other Novices, or (Freſh-men as wee call them) ſit mixt with the fellow-Commoners, that they may take notice of them, and euery man in his turne, beating into them by continuall diſcourſes▪ the ſweetneſſe and excellencie of the Order of Ieſuites; eſpecially, into ſuch as are of the richer ſort, or wealthy heyres.
            I will ſay no more at this time▪ as touching theyr Studies, but I will deſcribe briefly, the manner of the Viſitation, which euery Provinciall maketh; becauſe it is a point, which as I thinke, and for any thing that I euer read or heard, hath beene neuer hitherto divulged by any.
            
               Now euery Provinciall taketh his Denomination from the Prouince, or Kingdome rather, which is committed to his charge, and overſight. His place is to viſit the ſeverall Colledges, to take an account of theyr Revenewes, and ouer-ſee their expences, exactly and punctually: to take notice, what Noble perſonages doe commit their Sons to the tuition of the Societie, and how many they are in number? Whether there bee not yearely an increaſe of Schollers, as alſo of their meanes and Revenewes? Whether there bee any converted from Lutheraniſme, and how many ſuch?
            If there be no ſuch thing, or if the Popiſh Religion haue loſt ground, or if there be any decreaſe of theyr wealth, he ſharpely reproveth their ſloath and neglect, and chargeth ſtrictly, that they make an amends for the wrong they haue done, and loſſe they haue receiued in this caſe. But if they haue beſtirred themſelues brauely, and conuerted (as they call it) or rather perverted many Soules to Popery, if they haue beene frugall, and ſcraped wealth together, he praiſeth them very highly, and extolleth them to the skyes. Moreover, he demandeth, what is the opinion of the Neighbouring Hereticks concerning them? What bee the projects of the Nobles? What meetings they haue? How many? And where? What they conſult vpon? What they reſolue to doe? Whether the Hereticall Princes (as they tearme them) delight to liue at home or abroad? To whom they reſort moſt frequently? What is the ſeuerall diſpoſition of euery one of them? In what things hee is obſerued to take moſt

delight? Whether hee take any care of his people or not? Whether hee bee a Religious Prince or not? Or rather, whether hee bee not a man, who delights to take his pleaſure in drinking, Wenching, or Hunting? Whether hee haue any Catholickes about him▪ or that are neere vnto him? What the people report abroad, concerning theyr owne Princes? Whether the Churches of the Adverſaries, bee full of reſort, or not? Whether the Paſtors of thoſe Churches, bee learned and diligent men in theyr place and calling, or otherwiſe lazie Lubbers, and vnlettered? Whether the Profeſſion of Divinitie thriue, in the Neighbouring Vniverſitie of Heretickes? Whether theyr Divines maintaine frequent Diſputations, and againſt whom principally? What bookes they haue publiſhed of late, and vpon what Subiect?
            To theſe, and ſundry ſuch queſtions, if the Regent, and the reſt of the Fathers doe anſwer punctually, hee doth wonderfully commend theyr induſtry and vigilancie.
            If hee finde them defectiue in anſwering to theſe or any ſuch demaunds, hee reprooveth them ſharpely, ſaying: what meane you my Maiſters, doe you purpoſe, like lazie companions, to vndoe the Church of Rome? How doe you ſuppoſe your ſlothfulneſſe in theſe waightie affaires, can bee excuſed before his Holineſſe? How is it, that you preſume to take theſe places vpon you, and to manage them no better? What or whom are you affrayd of? Why doe not you buckle

vp your ſelues better to your buſineſſe, and performe your places like men? Theſe things (if you had beene ſuch men as you ought to bee) had not beene to doe now. Theſe things ſhould haue beene done long before this time. Doe you obſerue the incredible watchfulneſſe of the Heretickes, and can you bee lazie? And with theſe or the like ſpeeches, hee whetteth them on to their dutie.
            At the laſt, he enquireth as touching the ſchollers, fellow-Commoners, Novices, and the reſt, how many they are in number? How much euery one hath profited? To what ſtudy or delight each one is inclinable? Whether there bee any one amongſt them that is ſcrupulous, or vntractable, or not a fit ſubiect to bewrought vpon. For he adiudgeth euery ſuch an one fitting to bee remoued from the ſtudy of Divinity; except, he haue bin very well exerciſed in the diſputations in Schooles, and haue a very great and good conceit of theyr Religion beaten into him. Moreouer, hee enquireth if they haue any one in the Colledge, who can be contented, for the advantage of the Catholicke cauſe, to vndertake any laudable attempt, and to ſpend his blood in the cauſe, if at any time neceſſity ſhall ſeeme to require it.
            And at laſt, he ſendeth away all theſe informations being ſealed vp, vnto the Father Generall at Rome, by whom, they are immediately made knowne to the Pope himſelfe, and his Conclaue of Cardinals: And ſo by this meanes, an order is taken, that there is no matter of Action ſet on

foote, nothing almoſt conſulted vpon, throughout the whole Chriſtian world, which is not forthwith diſcouered vnto the Pope, by theſe traytors, that lurke in euery ſtate and kingdome. Alſo, it is not to be omitted, that the Ieſuites are tranſlated by theyr Provinciall, from one Colledge to another, and that for the moſt part once in three yeares, that ſo the Provinciall out of theyr ſeverall diſcoveries, may attaine to vnlocke all the ſecreteſt Cabinets of the Prince and State, where he doth reſide.
            In the laſt place, I will adde in ſtead of a Corallary, ſome ſtrange and wonderfull▪devices of the Ieſuites, which beeing but of late newly hammered in the forge, they haue earneſtly endeauoured; yea, and at this day doe labour, tooth and nayle to put in practice by publike conſent, for an Innovation to be made both in the Church and State throughout the whole Romane Empire. To this end, theyr chiefe and onely ayme is, how to ſet the Princes of the Empire together by the cares, and by taking off ſome of the principall Doctors of the Church, to bring the tyranny of the Spaniard, and the Primacie of the Pope, into Germanie. Concerning which very project, I haue heard the Provinciall DEL-RIO himſelfe, diſcourſing ſometimes, whoſe plots and Machinations, were ſuch as follow. In the firſt place, (ſaith hee) care and paines muſt bee vſed, to eſtrange the effections of the Princes of the Empire, one from another.
            Now the meanes (ſayd he) to effect▪ that is, to worke vpon theyr contrariety of opinions, in matters

of Religion: And for this end let the Emperor be incited to make a Declaration, that hee will not grant liberty of Conſcience in matters of Religion, except there ſhall firſt be a reſtitution made of ſuch goods, as were taken from the Clergie vpon the treaty at Paſſaw: for this is a point whereat they will ſticke aſſuredly, and deny it.
            Let the Emperor thereupon ſend his Princes, and demand the ſame of the Cities of the Empire? They will either obey or deny: If they conſent and obey, all is well: If they refuſe, let him proclaime them Rebels, and expoſe them to be ſeized vpon by the next neighbouring Princes: but ſtill let the matter be ſo caried, that he be ſure to oppoſe a Lutheran and a Calviniſt, the one againſt the other.
            Moreouer, ſome deuiſe muſt bee found out, that the Duke of Bavaria may fall foule either vpon the Elector Palatine, or vpon the Duke of Wittemberg, for then may the Emperor be eaſily wonne to proclaime him Traytor whom the Duke of Bavaria ſhall diſtaſt, and all meanes taken away of making pacification either with Papiſt or Calviniſt for thē; beſides, thereby will be raiſed vnreconcileable diuiſions in the Empire, neuer to be quenched before an highway bee made for the accompliſhment of our deſires. For the further ripening of which Deſigne, the Ieſuites vnbethought themſelues further of this Stratagem. It will follow (ſay they) neceſſarily, when any Citie of the Empire ſhall be proclaimed rebellious, that euery ſeuerall Prince will be more ready and willing to ſerue his owne turne vpon the ſpoyle thereof, then to admit any other

that ſhall be emulous of the ſame bootie to preuent him. This for the Generality. More particularly yet, meanes muſt be found out, to ſet the Princes of Saxony at difference, that their ſtrength and power may be broken, or at leaſt weakened.
            Now that may bee moſt conueniently effected thus: firſt, if the Adminiſtration of the Primacie of Magdeburg, which now is vacant, bee giuen to the Bavarian Elector of Colen, neither the Marqueſſe of Brandenburg, nor the Duke of Saxonie, will eaſily grant theyr conſents thereto.
            Secondly, if that ſucceed not according to our deſires, there muſt be ſome cauſe pretended, why the Duke of Saxony either doth ſeeme worthy, or ought to ſeeme worthy to be remoued from the Electorall dignity. For, if in times paſt, the Princes of the Empire caſt downe Wenceſlaus, from the Imperiall Throne, becauſe they had adjudged him a negligent Prince: ſurely the Emperour may take as juſt an occaſion, to remoue from the Electorall Dignity, the Duke of Saxony, who is drunke euery day. And in this reſpect, let his Imperiall Majeſtie reſtore and conferre that Dignity, vpon the houſe and family of the Dukes of Weymar, And becauſe theſe Princes are yet vnder age, let the Adminiſtration of that Electorſhip, be committed to Henry of Brunſwicke, a learned and vigilant Prince. This project being once ſet a foote, cannot chuſe but beget infinite diſtractions, throughout all Saxony, ſo ſhall it come to paſſe, that they ſhall waſt and weary themſelues one againſt another, and by that meanes, become vtterly vnable to withſtand a common foe when he ſhall come vpon them.
            
               And as for the Marqueſſe of Brandenburge and them of Pomerania, let meanes be vſed to moue the King of Poland who is the Emperors kinſman to covenant with his vncle the King of Swetheland, that they two ſhall invade and divide Pruſsia, and Canton the ſame: which thing the Marqueſſe of Brandenburge will oppoſe with all his powers. Now as concerning the Landgraue of Heſſen he muſt be vrged and ſollicited daily to divide the inheritance equally with his vncle Lodowicke and to reſigne the gouernment of Hertsfeild to the Biſhop of Wirtzburg: if he refuſe to doe ſo, let him bee proclaymed rebell, and let his inheritance bee aſſigned vnto his vncle Lodowicke.
            
            Moreouer, as for the Duke of Wittemberge, and the Elector Palatine, they two may with eaſe be ſet together by the cares, if the Duke bee commanded to make reſtitution of ſome Religious houſes, or otherwiſe vpon his refuſall be proclaimed Rebell, and ſome neighbouring Monaſteries bee aſſigned to the Elector Palatine, and amongſt them one eſpecially, which hee hath bin obſerued to haue aymed at long agoe.
            And theſe be thoſe killing proiects of the Ieſuites, which I haue heard from their owne mouthes, not without admiration euen to aſtoniſhment, and they haue many more of like ſort, all which I doe not at this preſent remember.
            Moreouer, there hath beene a Conſultation among the Ieſuites to ſend abroad ſome bold Aſſaſsinates, who by Poyſon or by the Piſtoll, may cut off the principall Doctors of the Reformed Churches,

fellowes who are ſo abſolute Maſters in that trade of Poyſoning, that they are able ſo to infect Platters, Saltſellers, Baſons, Kettles, Pots, and Caldrons, and ſuch like veſſels of ordinary vſe; that albeit, they ſhall be ten times ouer waſhed and wiped, yet ſhall they retaine the power and infection of moſt deadly and ſpeeding poyſon. Wherefore, I humbly aduiſe all godly and religious Gouernours and Miniſters of the Church, that hereafter they bee warie, and cautelous how they truſt any, but ſuch as of whoſe fidelity they haue had ſufficient triall.
            And theſe things could neuer haue fallen within compaſſe of mine vnderſtanding, nor euer did, before ſuch time as I heard them from the Principals and Heads of the Societie of Ieſuites, together with many other particulars, which I held my ſelfe bound in Conſcience to reveale to the world, for the good of my Countrey, and of the Church of CHRIST: which although I haue for the preſent onely giuen you as in a rude and firſt draught; yet I purpoſe, (God willing) in due time, to expreſſe the ſame at large, painting them out in their Colours, with circumſtances of time, place and perſons.
            ⸪
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

