
   
      
         
            Antiprognosticon that is to saye, an inuectiue agaynst the vayne and vnprofitable predictions of the astrologians as Nostrodame, [et]c. Translated out of Latine into Englishe. Whervnto is added by the author a shorte treatise in Englyshe, as well for the vtter subuersion of that fained arte, as also for the better vnderstandynge of the common people, vnto whom the fyrst labour seemeth not sufficient
            Antiprognosticon contra inutiles astrologorum prædictiones Nostradami, Cuninghami, Lovi, Hilli, Vaghami, &amp; reliquorum omnium. English
            Fulke, William, 1538-1589.
         
         
            
               1560
            
         
         Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01297
            STC 11420
            ESTC S116544
            99851760
            99851760
            17051
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01297)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17051)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1098:01)
         
         
            
               
                  Antiprognosticon that is to saye, an inuectiue agaynst the vayne and vnprofitable predictions of the astrologians as Nostrodame, [et]c. Translated out of Latine into Englishe. Whervnto is added by the author a shorte treatise in Englyshe, as well for the vtter subuersion of that fained arte, as also for the better vnderstandynge of the common people, vnto whom the fyrst labour seemeth not sufficient
                  Antiprognosticon contra inutiles astrologorum prædictiones Nostradami, Cuninghami, Lovi, Hilli, Vaghami, &amp; reliquorum omnium. English
                  Fulke, William, 1538-1589.
                  Painter, William, 1540?-1594.
               
               [72] p.   
               
                  By Henry Sutton dwellyng in Pater noster row at the signe of the blacke boy,
                  [Imprinted at London :
                  the. 23. day of December. And are there to be solde. Perused and allovved according to the Quenes maiesties iniunctions.] 1560.
               
               
                  A translation, by William Painter, of: Fulke, William. Antiprognosticon contra inutiles astrologorum prædictiones Nostradami, Cuninghami, Lovi, Hilli, Vaghami, &amp; reliquorum omnium.
                  Place of publication and printer's and publisher's names from colophon.
                  Against alamanack writers Nostradamus, Cuningham, Low, Hill and Vaughan.--STC.
                  Running title reads: An inuectiue agaynst astrologie.
                  Signatures: A-D E⁴.
                  Some print show-through.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.
               Astrology --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2003-04
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-05
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-06
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2003-06
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-08
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               ANTIPROGNOSTICON that is to saye, an Inuectiue agaynst the vayne and vnprofitable predictions of the Astrologians as Nostrodame. &amp;c. Translated out of Latine into Englishe.
            Whervnto is added by the author a shorte Treatise in Englyshe, as well for the vtter subuersion of that fained arte, as also for the better vnderstandynge of the common people, vnto whom the fyrst labour seemeth not sufficient.
            Habet &amp; musca splenem &amp; formicae suabilis inest.
            1560.
         
         
            
            Henry Bennet Calesian. Sonnet.
            
               THe Poets write, that Atlas did sustein
               On shulders huge ye massy heuēs frame
               So feigne they not, that Saturns heauenly reygne,
               And state he knew, or could expresse ye same
               Thastrologers, that neuer crept so hye,
               Do
                     •…
                   vaunt they knowe, what God doothe woorke in throne.
               Affyrmyng that to knowe this mystery,
               None can atteyne, but onely they alone,
               Whose fansies Fulce with booke of perfecte skyll,
               Confutes with suche as vaynly do professe
               Thēselues to know, of god the secrete will,
               But yf I myght to these rewarde addresse,
               I rede the rout, that eies vnlerned bleares,
               Shuld for their cunnynge weare kinge Midas eares.
            
         
         
            
            Willyam Painter.
            
               A Foule fall dontles Fulce doth geue thastrologers eche one:
               Bycause no firme foundation they buylde their arte vpon.
               Who doo surmyse and fondly fayne, mens fortunes to foreshewe.
               And make the symple forte beleue, that they their fates can knowe.
               But al thos
                     •…
                   bragges this boke doth breake and make them seeme full colde,
               With argumentes atchieued by arte with reasons manyfolde.
               Though Cunyngham the same doo carpe or Uaghan vayne it iudge,
               Or other suche, with scornefull scoffe thereat doo beare some grudge:
               Sith Grindall graue the grist hath ground and Molens molendine,
               The meale hath made, whence bulted was and brought this flower fyne,
               The lesse we nede theyr force to feare, we haue suche stuffe in store,
               Comparisons are odyous, therefore I adde no more.
            
            Comparatio omnis odiosa.
         
         
            
            ¶ To his louyng frende W. F.
            
               
                  OVR familiaritie is suche, that neyther we haue neede of preoccupation, nor yet of many wordes in vtteryng our requeste. These circumstances therfore being cutte of, I shall euen at one woorde, desyre you, that this translation of your Antiprogno
                  
                     •…
                  
                may be publisshed and made cōmon for all men, that either haue nede therof to vnderstande their errour, orels shall haue pleasure therin to see the vanitie wherwith they haue ben blynded. The rather thus trā slated, bicause a great numbre of the busiest and most curious Astrologians in Englād vnderstand no latin at all, orels so symply, that they can not perceiue the mynde of a Latin writ
                  •…
               r, and also that the cōmon sorte of wel disposed men, may hereby take, some profite. But if you thynk good to adde som what in this edition for the vnderstandyng of the common people you shall doo well in my opinion. Thus fare you well.
            
               From Seuenoke xxii. of Octobre.
               
               Your familiar frende
Willyam Paynter.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
               
                  SVCHF is the nature of mankynde, carnestely desprous to haue knowledge of thynges to come, that in seekyng out &amp; inuētyng of such artes as n
                  •…
               ight seme to pertain to the certayn therof, she hath taken greate and laborous paines. For trauailyng to get out a science of Diuination, or foreseeyng, out of euery element, she hath broughte foorth vnto vs Pyromancy, whiche is to for shewe thyngs by the Fyre: Hydromanci
                  •…
               , to declare of thynges to come by the water: Geomancie by the Earth: and diuers other artes of this kynde, promisyng the knowledge of hy
                  •…
               de and secrete matters. And lest the practisers of these artes shoulde at any tyme beynge destitute of their bokes and instrumentes, not bee able to tel of thynges to happen: she hath found out that handlom art of foreshewyng by the hand (which is an instrument, that euery man car
                  •…
               eth about with hym) so that by this sciēce of Palmestry, at no tyme nor place, they shall be to seke of diuina
                  •…
               ion or (as they terme it) Fortune tellyng▪ Fynally, there is nothyng so vaine or of so lyt
                  •…
               l importance, in w
                  •…
               ich she hath not boulted o
                  •…
               som cunnyng of forshewyng, seyng she hath alredy set forth. Capnomancy a
                  •…
               
               
Sciomancie, whereof the one teacheth to haue vnderstandynge of thynges to come by smoke, the other by shadow. These thinges peraduenture myght seeme somwhat tollerable, so long as mans witte is occupied in matters that are neare to hym (I meane the elementes and such like) if that those false diuinours would not drawe heuen it selfe and the starres, to their superfluous rules of Diuination, of whome a greate numbre doo not this modestly, and as it were dius
                  •…
               yng or gessynge; but arrogātly do pronoūce their oracles as though they had ben giuen of Apollo Pithyus, the god of foreshewing. It were a smal matter if they told only of rayne, and wethers, but also they must 
                  •…
               yl the whole world at their pleasure with warre, sycknesse, and rebellion. What shall we say that they ar not content to set out their oracles generally and vniuersally, but they must also thretten the lyfe of euery particular man, (as it were the goddesses of destenie) manifest
                  •…
               ly against the order of all learnyng and philosophie. Neyther is it ynoughe for theim to haue lordshy
                  •…
                and dominion ouer menne
                  •…
                bodies, excepte they dyd also charge they
                  •…
                myndes and soules wyth vertues or 
                  •…
               es, according to their owne preceptes &amp; rules.

grosse errour to desect, vanite to open, &amp; au thoritie to eleuate &amp; extenuate, I thought it worth the labour, bicause they so shameful ly now adais, do set forth their wares to sell among al mē, partly because they so proudly with al their force inuey ageinst such mē as contemne &amp; despise these and suche lyke their predictiōs. Yea som are not ashamed to cōmend a necessary vse of their diuinati ons. But that onely is necessary (if we beleue Cicero) without the which we can not lyue. Then how many thousandes of men be there, which not only lyue, but also lyue wel, and yet neuer haue regarde or care so muche as ones to see prognostications. Other some there be, whiche call all men that be desirous of goodly arts and sciences, to their Almanach, as to a storehouse, replenyshed with all precious iewelles. Finally what signe of arrogance or boastyng can be named, whiche in the booke of these pro phecies may not easyly be perceiued? Ther fore who soeuer dare be so bolde as ones to open his mouthe agaynste these oracles, streight way shall bee called an ignoraunt person, a detractour, and a sycophant. And this is the cause that so fewe haue taken vpon thē to detect &amp; opē their trifling in pro gnostications, leste he shoulde incurre the

reproches and contumelies of the prowde and arrogant rable of Prognosticatoures. For in our tyme (as farre as I haue knowledge) among al men, the most famous and excellent Doctour, Peter Dacquet onely hath both learnedly and playnely declared, that the vse of this fayned art is altogither vnprofitable for the woorkes and practises of phisike. But I beynge (as I thinke) sufficiently armed agaynste all the assaultes of all prognosticatours, hauynge also gotten conuenient leysure (except my tonge or pen do faile me) wil endeuour my self vtterly to ouerthrow this tower of Astrology, when's they behold the signification of the planets &amp; starres, that no pece nor parcel therof that remayn. Neyther am I so ignorant of that knowledge (yf any suche knowledge be) as they would goe about to perswade the common people, that all suche are, whiche despise their for shewyng and premōstratio
                  •…
               s: neyther beyng moued with the desyre of euyl speakyng or enuy, do I addresse my self to writyng: (for I am assured, that I do pro uoke waspes) but seeyng many whiche are desirous to learne the sciences, to haue also muche sette by this celestiall diuination, I thought good to admonishe them by this litle treatise, that they laboure not in vayue,

hopyng for that, which the place it selfe wil not suffre them to haue. that whē they haue throughely seene and considered the whole matter, they may leaue to haue in admiration these inuencions of the prognosticatours: and if they wyll nedes haue knowledge of secretes and thynges pertainynge to the future tyme, they may learne to seeke it out of suche thyngs as are more nere and better knowen vnto them. For as it is said and not withoute a cause: Those thynges that are aboue vs, perteyne nothyng vnto vs: and those thynges which are aboue our reache, ar not to be sought for, with muche curiositie. Neither let any man slaunder me, as though I went about to impugne or assaulte the moste beautyfull and certayne science of Astronomye, as the Prognosticatours themselues, (suche is their malice) crie out, yf any man speake boldly against the vanitie of Astrologie: But that science as of all humayn sciences it is the most diuine, so wolde I wishe that it shulde be embraced, learned, &amp; perceyued of most men, especially of all suche as beare and professe the name of Philosophy. And let not them bee troubled wyth theyr prowde bragge, whiche say, that their calculation is thend
                  •…
                and scope, where vnto the noble science of

Astronomie dothe tende, seyng there is no communitie or felowshyp betwene certen
               
                  •…
               y and vncertayntie, neyther can truth and fayned falshod, at any tyme be coupled and ioyned together. And as for the studious, they shall not be compelled in vayne to con sider the course of the stars (although this diuination be cleane banished awaye) seing the knowledge it self (yf we trust Aristotle) is an end and scope of it selfe. Moreouer be syde the most pleasant cōtemplacion of the whole workemashyp of the world, doth not ye sciens it selfe bryng wt it infinite profites and vtilities? What neade I to speake of so many kind of Dialles, so many differences of tymes and yeares? fynally so manye varietes and degrees of glystering lyghtes.
            One starre (whiche is the sonne) as it were the ymage of one god, communicateth hys lyght to all the rest, whome so longe as the residews of the starres beholde, resplendishynge with most bright beames, they 
                  •…
               hine ouer the whole worloe: But yf any of them by the enuious shadowe of the earthe, be dep
                  •…
               ued of his syght, strayght way as it were mor
                  •…
               yng, and without lyght, it is voyde of all beautye and glorye: Doth it nothyng auaile to know the cause of so diuers formes

and shapes of the moone? Suche varieties of dayes in length and shortnesse? So manye differences of heate and colde by reson of the Sonnes commynge neare or departynge farre from vs? They therfore whyche styffely affirme, that Astronomye cannot co
                  •…
               siste wythoute Astrologie, and that the knowledge of the one is vnprofitable without the vse of the other, are here reproued of a manifest error, or rather conuicted of a shamefull lye. Lest therfore vnder the bewtifull and glorious cloke of this sciens of Astronomye, they should any longer proceade to commende their false and hyppocriticall art, I would wishe that thys little booke were but ones perused and red ouer of all suche as seme to fauour this deceyte: and except either their wilful and per uerse affection, or elles to grosse ignorance dyd lette them, I am assured they would vtterlye forsake and reiecte thys kynde of forshewynge by the starres. For longe tyme vnder the pretexte and colour of Astronomye, thys auguration or diuinotion hathe bene cloked, in so muche that the professoures thereof haue not doubted openlye for Astrologians, to call theym selues Astronomars.

Other some confoundynge the names of Astrologie and Astronomy, bothe in teachyng and also in wrytyng, haue so mixed the one with thother, as though they were not distincie sciences, but the one of them dyd hange of an other, after the maner of relatiues. And herein they are 
                  •…
               ot vnlyke to men of vngracious lyuynge, whiche to the intent they may with lesse daunger and suspition committe he ynous offences, will gladly vse and frequent the company of suche as be taken to be good and honest men: but the difference of those artes, I thynke is manifestly knowen to all men, so that I am certainely perswaded, it were but loste labour to stande longe in puttynge a diuer 
                  •…
               e betwene them. Wherfore it shall suffise to admonisshe the symple sorte, leste when we speake agaynst the art of foreshewyng by the starres, they shoulde vnaduisedly thynke that wee dispute agaynste the course of the starres, their lawe, order, or learnyng. But wherof shall I take my beginnyng, or of what parte shall I chiefely goe about to publyshe and desorte so greate vanitie, whether of the vncertainte, therof▪ 
               
                  〈◊〉
                of the vnprofitable, yea hurtfull obseruation thereof that so muche troubleth the common wealthe, or rather of the impossibilitie,

shal I shewe that there is no suche science of diuination? If that whiche is vncertayn deserue not to bee obserued, for what cause, I praye you, doo you cleaue to the do
                  •…
               yng of Astrologie? If that whiche deserueth not so muche as to be consydered is worthily called vayne, or of none effect, wherefore shall menne more truste the diuination of the starres, then they wyll credite the vnconstant waues of the sea? It shall not be nedefull in this place to alledge Aristotles opinion of the future contingēt, nether to vouche thauctoritie of other philosophers, concernyng the vncertayne and vnknowē procedyng of matters. For who doth not see clerer then the sonne at noone days, that not the fourth part of those presages or fortellyngs come to passe, as they before haue pronounced them? Yea who is so forgetfull, or of lyttel memory, that can not recorde and remembre, that the moste parte of their predictions haue chaunced cleane contrary to their calculations. It is not therefore without a cause, yf we m
                  •…
                uayle with what face they dare he so bol
                  •…
                to propounde suche vayn and folyshe varicinatious, to be considered of wyse and discrete persons. Certainly euery science, of what sort soeuer it be, consisteth on thyngs

that be true certayne and immouable: but Astrologie which standeth on thynges that most commonlye are false, but alwayes vn certayne and vnconstant: Tell me all you prognosticatours, by what reason it may
                  •…
                be called a sciēce? but if this your methode &amp; rule of prophesieng be not to bee noumbred among those sciences, which consist of thin ges certayne and immutable, what other thyng is this your knowledge but folishnes so greate, that foly her selfe coulde not light lye inuent a thyng more fond and foolyshe. But peraduenture your predictiōs, be they neuer so vncertayne, yet they maye bee profitable to the publike welth, so yt which your arte lacketh of certayntie, it recompenceth wyth vtilitie: Nay rather with how greate euyls do you burden the cytie (I speake not of the horrible wonders that you threaten to fall on them) but what a dearth of vitayles youcause in the commē welth, while the farmers of the countrye (as I haue good vnderstandynge) beleuyng your oracles of the imtēperaunce of wethers do so craftily dyspose their wares, yt in abundaunce of al thynges, the common people suffer a greate and greuous scarcity. What? is it to be kept in sylence, howe slowlye and coldly the people in the last yeare, seduced by the foolyshe

prophesye of Nostrodamus addressed them selfe to sette vppe the true worshippynge of GOD and hys religion, good Lord what tremblynge was there? What feare?
            What expectation? What horror? Leste all thynges sodenlye shoulde bee turned vp sydowne, so that none almost of them that gaue any credite to prognostications, durst be bolde to open their faythe and religion, whyche they bore in theyr hartes. Yea thys Nostrodamus reigned here so lyke a tyrant wyth hys south saiynges, that wythout the good lucke of hys prophesies it was thought that nothyng could be broughte to effecte. What shal I speake of the common peoples voyce? Thys daye the Bishoppe of Rome must be driuen out of the parliamēt. To morow the Queene shal take vpon her the name of supreame head. After xx. dayes all thing shall ware worse. Such a day shall be the day of the last iudgement, that except the true prechers of Goddes holye woords hadde sharpelye rebuked the people for creditynge suche vayne prophesies, there shoulde haue bene none ende of feare and expectation. But oure craftye Nostrodamus, that coulde wrappe hys prophesyes in suche darke wryncles of obscur
                  •…
               ye,

that no man could pyke out of them, either sence or vnderstandyng certayn. Without double he hath herde of the oracles of Appollo, whiche the denyll at Delphos, gaue out of an ydoll to them that asked counsel, whiche were obscure, double, and suche as myght chance bothe waies, As that whiche was aunswered to kyng Pyrtus, demaundyng of hym:

                  I say that Aeacides the Romaynes maye ouercome.
               
            
            Neyther is that vnlyke, whiche the ryche Cresus entendyng to make warre agaynst Cyrus, had gyuen hym, that is:

                  Croesus percyng through the citie Halis shall ouerthrovve great ryches.
               
            
            So that you may wrest them to what sence you lyst. For Pyrrus while he did promise hymselfe victory ouer the Romains, might haue also vnderstode (as it came to passe in deede) that he hymselfe shulde be ouercome of the Romans. Lykewyse Cresus, while he turstyng thoracle, perswaded hymselfe, that he shuld ouercome Cyrus ryches, that were so great and abundant, brought his owne kyngdome, ryches, and what soeuer he possessed into vtter ruin and destructon The same trade of fortelling Sibylla Cumana

dyd also depe, of whom Uergile reporteth, that the recorded fearefull circum stances and doubtes, resowndynge in her caue. Finally, all they whiche inflamed with the diuelles sprighte, tolde of thynges to come, gaue either darke or doubteful answers to them that required their oracles. The same maner of foreshewyng in darke and double riddles our prognost
                  •…
                catours, as it were receiued of the heathenyshe prophets do obserue and keepe vnto this day fornot only Nost rodamus telleth thyngs darkly and doubtfully, but diuers others: yea many of our countreymen, an Cunyngham, a man otherwise bothe lerned and honest, Hyll, Lou, Uaghan, and not longe ago Askham, with sixe hundred more of that sort, among whiche, the afore named, maye chalenge the chiefe place, not that they prophecie truer then other, but that they haue more exactely (as they say them selues) formed their calculatiōs to the course of the starres. And leste any man shuld thynke that I sclander them, I entende to reherse certayne things out of their bookes, in whyche we wyll playnly note a double doubtfull forshewynge. By reson of Saturn in Cauro (say they) and the eclipse in Aprill, there shall folow mur

muryng amonge the common people: but Mercurius, with his eloquence dooth pacifie theim. Likewise Mars this yeare shall saue Englād harmlesse from many euils, except the Eclipse of the Moone do somewhat abate his courage. After the some maner doo they pronounce of wheate, bar ley, and otes, that they shall prosper well, except the heate, moysture, or other vnsea sonable weather doo endamage them. Finally this almoste is generall, yf they foreshewe a thyng to come without exception, it is false: if they pronounce it with exception, howe soeuer the game go, their error is without daunger of reprouyng. Moreouer they them selues confesse, that there bediuers impedimēts which cause yt many things to come not to passe, not only about in the heuens, but also here beneth. O good ly science, O diuine knowledge, whiche so many causes doo frustrate, and brynge to none effecte. To what purpose then serue so many prohibitions against the surgeōs, that they take nothyng in hande, but in a a prescripte tyme? Shall they tary seuen dayes before they lette a man bloudde that is sycke of the Pleuresie: Why doo you not by the same reason forbydde them that be poysoned to take any medicine, before

the signe apt to comfort the vertue expulsiue. But these matters by doctor Da
                  •…
               quet are so playnly sette before mens eies, that onelesse these Prognosticatours euen yet dydde geue suche cautions, it were but 
                  〈◊〉
                vayne for me asmuchas ones to make men cion of that super
                  •…
               tious abuse.
            Hytherto as (as I suppose) we haue sufficiently spoken of the inconstancy and vn certaintie of these pred
                  •…
               ons, yea and ynough also of the vn
                  •…
               rositable obseruation and credityng of the same.
            Nowe therfore let vs prepare our selues to that argumēt, which is al the prognostitators, what soeuer thei be, &amp; where soeuer thei be, ar able without al couin or deceipt to remoue: they shal not only defend their are, which otherwise must nedes fal down and vtterly decay, but also they shall hau
                  •…
                the writer hereof, with shame ynoughe, to retract and recant al that he hath hytherto against Astrologie sayd or written.
            And that we may by lytle and litle procede to the effect of our matter, we dare bebolde to affirme, That this is cōmon to all sciences, that they may bee demonstrated. For although the principles and grounds in euery arte, be of suche nature, that they canne not bee shewed and confyrmed

by things more general, and therfore it is said, that they can not be proued, yet by demonstration or induction they maye be so playnly sette before our eies, that no man neede to doubte, but that they are moste true and certain. For eyther they are shewed by a manifest figure that they muste nedes be true, and that it were impossible to thinke otherwise of them then so, or els by recitall of all the particulers, one vniuersall is euermore concluded. Therfore of suche foundations euery art is grounded, which beyng surely layd, meruallous workes are builded vpon them. But if the soūdatiōs which ought to be most stronge and sure, in any poynt doo fayle, streighte way yt whole buildyng with great weight falleth downe and is destroied. For dately experience teacheth vs, that no structure can be firme and of continuance, excepte the foundatiōs therof be first surely laide. And reason teacheth the same lesson, whiche with open mouthe crieth, and biddeth alway to beware of the beginnings. Whiche thynge although we see dayly in buyldyng of houses, yet may we see it also, yf we wyll vse a little diligence in euery arte and science. As in Geometry, it to a principle, that from one poynt to an other, you

may alwaies drawe a streighte lyne, this nowe by exaumple maye be demonstrated very easily. Likewise it is an other groūde that all the three angles or corners of a triangle, howe soeuer they be taken, are equal vnto. ii. rectangles. If this be shewed in euery particular kinde of triangle, as Orthogonius Oxygoniꝰ, Aequilaterus Scàlenus, and suche lyke, we shall plainly vnderstand that whiche is required. And that we haue here sayde briefely in a fewe, the same to be true in al other propositions, he that hath but meanly trauayled in the sciences can beare witnesse. But perchance some prognosticatour will start vp &amp; say, that although this is easy to be shewed in suche thynges as almost we may perceiue by our sences yet the same in thynges farther of; can scarsly be declared, As yt greatnes of the starres, or their distance from theearth, or from themselues one from an other: Doo not learned men teache, that the Sunne is an hundreth sixty and six tymes greatter then the earth? and that the Moone is thirty and nine tymes lesser thā the earthe? We graunt that these matters be difficult, and suche as hardly can be per swaded to the cōmon sort: yet as difficulte as they be, and harde to knowe, there is a

meane wherby men maye come to the science and vnderstādyng of them. We haue the shadowe of the earthe as it were a ladder, whereby we ascende into heauen, and beholde many thynges, wherevnto grosse wittes can not frame. But by no waie is it possible, that the principles of this arte of Astrologie, may be either demonstra
                  •…
               d or proued. Ther is no mean wherby mās witte may atteyne to so greate knowlege, ther is no methode, no inductiō, yt cā main tayn truth of th
                  •…
               se propositions, whyche they take for their principles.
            Nowe therefore (as I haue saide) the foundation of this tower, beeyng shaken, the whole weyghte of Astrologye, muste needes haue a greate and saubdeyne falle. And as Capitaynes experte 
                  〈◊〉
                feactes of warre, whenne they determyne vtterlye to subuerte and ouerthrowe a tower, castell, or other fortresse of their ennemies, with vnderminyng they loose the foundations of it, orels setting vnder it a quantitie of gunpowder, blowe away the whole substance: So we autendyng not onely to proue, that youre arte is vnproufytable, but also to condempne it to perpetuall prison of Oblinion and forgetfulnesse, goe

aboute to shewe, that there neyther is nor can bee any suche arte of diuynation or forshewynge. For by what reason are ye able to demonstrate or shewe, that Saturne is so hurtefull, malicious, and pestilent? By Induction? What if he haue do mynyon as you tearme it) in the Natiuitie of a Prynce, a warryoure, or a Sanguyne? Naye, there is nothyng dothe oftener fayle, then Predictions of natiuities: Howe thenne are you able to proue, that this Planette dooeth so muche, and so greate euylle amongest menne. I for my parte, coulde rather proue by probable reason thei contrarye. For it is nothynge lyke, that Saturne whiche is farthest frome the earthe, shoulde haue the mooste earthely nature. Besyde this, he that is farre hygher thenne Uenus, and nearer to the immense and large. Fyrmamente, whyche the Hebrewes doo call, A stretchynge abroade, by no meanes can bee counted woorse. Wherefore is the Planette Iupyter, more wholsome than Saturne? In whose tyme (whyle that he reygned or ruled on the earthe, the same antiquytie wytnessethe, that the golden worlde was, the whyche flatterynge

their king Iupiter, oscribeth to him better effectes then to his father. But how vnjust a thynge is it, and agaynst all reason, that the Sonne it selfe, without whom thother planettes haue no more beautie then the earthe, can searcely of them bee compted among the good 
                  •…
               holsome starres: where as he, whiche with his heate geueth lyfe, with his 
                  •…
               hynynge lyght, and with his beholdyng, gladnes to all liuyng creatures. (If an arre of astrologie were to be inuen sed accordyng to reason) shoulde haue the thiese rule among all starres, as well planettes as fixed. Lykewise the Moone whi the gouerneth humours, shuld be seconde to the Sonne, specially in dominion of lynyng creatures, for as muche as by these two, that is, Heate and Moisture, wherof the Sonne ruleth heate, &amp; the Moon moist nes, all lyfe is proserued and nourished. By what argument are you persuaded to preferre a trine aspecte before a quartile, where as the numbre of foure among the Pytha
                  •…
               rsens, which had the exact know Iudge of numbres, and to theym referred all thynges, was more reuerentely obserued then the rest: in so much that by foure they were wonte to sweare. But you wyll say
                  •…
               , that for the holye 
                  •…
               rinities sake the

numbre of. iii. is preferred. Thā grantyng the numbre of thre is good, booth it folow that the numbre of foure, in whiche God concluded the elementes, their qualities and all perfecte essences to be eu
                  •…
               l? What persuadeth you to thynk, that the. xii. signs of the Zodsake haue so dyuers qualities, and accordyng to resons iudgement, contrary to nature. For you will haue Aries to be fyery, which is the beginnyng of the spryng: more ouer you teach, that Taurus which is a sygne of the spryng, shuld be of earthly nature. Which thyng how muche it striueth agaynst reason euery man may perceyue, that knoweth aptly howe to referre the spryng tyme to the element ayre. Cancer also the beginnynge of Sommer is safed to bee a watrie signe. Howe fonde therfore 
                  〈◊〉
                vaine are your principles, whiche you are not able by any reason to demonstrate or proue, euvn fooles may easily vnderstande, seyng you so foolyshly referre fyer to water, and ayre to earth. Besydes this, it is no smalle matter in youre cunnyng, to attribute to euery plnner his propre sygnes. But here also howe much you diffre from your owne doctrine euen Chor
                  •…
               bus hymselfe if he were present, woulde perceyue, When you 
                  •…
               iuide

the. xii. lignes of the Zodiake into sowed orders or bandes. To some you ascribe a nature erthy, to some watry, to some ayry, and to somme fyery. Lykewyse when you giue to euerye housholder (as you call the planettes) theyr seruynge signes: you grant sem to Saturn som to Iupiter, and so forth to euery one their propre signes. But this I can not passe ouer with silence that almost euery housholder wyll mayntayne and kepe in his seruyce any seruan 
                  •…
               es that are so reyugnant from his owne nature and disposition. That ys they vse them as ministers in bringyng their workes to effect, I meruayle how they do not rather execute their owne wille, than the wyl of their maisters. As for example, Saturne whiche is sayd to be earthy, hath Aquarius to wayte vpon hym, which all togither consisteth of asry qualities. Iupiter reported to be ayry, hath two seruantes, Sagittarius and Pisces, of whome sagitarius is fyry, and pisces warry. Likewise Ma
                  •…
                that is whose and drye, is contente with the seruice of Scorpio, that is colde and moyste. Uenus boyng full of cold and moysture, hath Taurus an earthy sygne, and Libra an ayry sygne, dooyng her service.

I leaue here to speake offeigned the distinctions and difference of howses, angles, dignities, and other like of this kind: of all whiche yf they canne proue but one principle by good and sownds reason, the way shoulde be more easy for theim to depende the rest. But nowe seyng they haue nothynge that can testifie of the truthe of their principles, it remaynethe, that the arte it selfe beeyng grounded of falle propositions, and of them heaped to a huge and greate buildynge, this so selender and weake a foundation beeyng taken away, muste needes falle downe, and lye prostrate.
            These thynges I doo the oftener repete, that all men may knowe what vayn bragges they make, whyles they take that whi che is no cause, in steade of a sure and certayne cause. For by what reason Saturnus shoulde sygnifie this or that, neyther they them selues, nor any man elles canne shewe, and that wee haue spoken of Saturne, the same also maye bee sayde of all the reste of portendynge sygnes. Excepte peraduenture they wyll boaste of somme reuelations to bee geuen vnto the snuen
               
                  •…
               rs of theyr arte, whyche yf they bee not

ashamed to confesse (as is their mad boldnesse they shall turne the foly, which now a litle, repentance wold correct, into mer
                  •…
                madnes. Let vs grant them their priuate reuelations, visions, and fantasies, for so we shall encreace their follisshenes, with pride and vaineglorie, yet we are sure they are not to bee trusted. And to declare that more p
                  •…
               ninely, bicause all reuelations are not of one sorte, let vs deuyde theim into two kyndes: for some are geuen of good angels, and some of euyll: They that are geuen of good angels are suche, as the nature of good spirites is wont to be, that is to say true, profitable, and to be thorte, generally good. The oracles of 
                  •…
               uyl spirites agree in qualitie with the geuers of them: that is, they be false, hurtful, &amp; euyll. Now of whether sort this reuelation is, by whiche the principles of Astrologie at the first were reueled: let vs in few wordes consider. Now vncertayn these principles are, and to speake playnly, howe false, we may bothe see by daily experience, and also we haue sufficiently aboue declared. Seynge then it appeareth, that your science is not deriued from a good angel or spirite, whe ther you wyll haue it to come of an euyll spirite, or of neyther, the choyce at this

               
                  •…
               yme (O Astrologians) shalbe yours. In the meane season either ceasse to boaste of your rotten and cancred art, orels by som
                  •…
                waie perswade your principles to be true, to suche as without proofe can beleue nothyng. whether you entend to doo, we that shortly perceiue: for if you bold your peace wee haue ouercome, and wyll celebrate a triumph for ouerthrowyng your myghty gyant Atlas. But if any of you be so 
                  •…
               ham les, that he dare enter into battail again
                  •…
                truth, and vs, that maynteyn her quarell, yf he be found it 
                  •…
               onger in armes then we are, we wyl geue place, and yelde, but if he be not able to abyde our strokes, we wyll take the castell of Astrologie, and destroy all thynges that maketh resistence, with weapon, fire, and famine. Nowe we haue cast our dartes bothe in numbre and fo
                  •…
                sufficient among the thickest of our 
                  •…
               
               mies, it remaineth that we beate backe the weapons throwen of them, or at the least take them clean away, that they beyng destitute of them, may run about as it were fightyng and beatyng the aire with vayne strokes. And to begin of that part, in w
                  •…
               
               che they put no smalle confidence: I haue herd many which boasted, that they were able to proue their diuination out of holye

scripture: which mē whē by reson of cōten tion they wer cōpelled to bring forth what they could for their defēce, wold sain haue cōcluded their vaticination out of the first chap. of Genesis. For whē God the most excellēt wise workman, of nature had crea ted heauē &amp; orth, with his almighty word, had put also a difference betwene the light which he had made, &amp; darknes: more ouer had placed the firmamēt in the midst of the waters: Furthermore gathered ye waters, yt before couered ye whole face of ye erth for preseruatiō of liuing cretures that he entē ded to create into one place, &amp; fynally had garnished the earth with a moste pleasant ve
                  •…
               ure of trees &amp; grene herbes, the fourth day determinyng to create lights, to make distinction betwene day &amp; night, apointed then their propre vse, saying: The
                  •…
                shal be vnto signes vnto appointed seasons (for so the Hebru word soūdeth) vnto dais &amp; vnto yeres, &amp; the lightes shalbe in heuen to geue light vpō ye erth, whose eternal wil theffect streight way folowed. For god made two great lights, a greater light to rule ye day, &amp; a lesser light to rule yt night, &amp; also ye stars. Here the prognosticators take no smal cou rage, ye god ordened the lights, ye thei shuld be vnto signes. But how litle these signes make for yt purpose of their predictiōs, he ye
               
               
                  •…
               rarketh yc order &amp; discours of yt words shal easily 
                  •…
               cesue. For yt which foloweth of appointed sesons, likewise yt which foloweth of dais &amp; yeres, these seme to me to expon̄d what maner of signes thei shalbe, ye is, thei shalbe tokēs of sprig, sōmer, au
                  •…
               ūne, &amp; win ter, of dais natural &amp; artificial, lōg or short of yeres, according to ye sons course, or to ye moones course, &amp; so of yt rest. And wheras here is chiefly mētion made of ye sonne &amp; ye moon, if we wil nedes by signs, vnderstad for shewing, thei shalbe vnto signes of he
                  •…
                whē yt son oraweth nere to vs, of cold wh
                  •…
               
               ̄ 
               
                  •…
               h departeth, of abūdāce of humors whē yt moon encreaseth, &amp; ye cōtrary whē she is in the wane or decreasing. But vf of necessitie you wold haue vs to vnderstand fatall 
                  •…
               dictions, notwe standing the argument is in force, seing you know not what ye stars do signify, you can not by their aspects tell of thyngs to come. But there be som, whi che as they thinke wil defend their science we much more strength, requiring that we shuld grant them yt al things in erth ar ruled &amp; gouerned by the power of ye heuēly signes. Truly I am not so hard to be entre
                  •…
                ted, ye. I wold deny the Astrologiās being oppressed we such calamite so litle a matter but rather I wil geue thē more thē they de mād, &amp; such thigs as I wold beni thē if thei

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
were obstinate and stubburn, now flying to their shoote an
                  •…
               re and last helpe, I wyll gentilly graunt them. All higher thynges saith Aristotle, woorketh in the lower bebies. Let al the power in these lower thinges be confessed to come from aboue. Nei ther wyll we greatly at this tyme striue against that deriuation of causes (deuysed by M
                     •…
                  rcutius Trismegistus) from God to the angels, from them to the heuens, that it perteyneth to Fortune or fate, which he calleth 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , neither doo I see how it shoulde hurt oure cause that we haue in hande, if we graunted theim that whiche they moste desire, and moste earnestly require, that is, that the starres haue dominion &amp; exercise their power on mens matters contingently, that is, as it were a certaine inclination or some secrete motion, (for yf destenye consisted of the starres it coulde not be chaunged) but as for the signification of the starres bothe we learne by experience, neither doo the Prognosticators denye, but that they may, by diuers meanes be auerted or tourned to some other effect. Therfore seyng we haue granted this, that coulde not bee compelled, I long to see what helpe you can from thens transferre to youre selues. And nowe me

thynketh I heare an Astrologian triumphyng on this maner: If the course of the starres, their reuolutions and aspectes do so strongly woorke in these lower bodies, that they shuld be causes of many effectes in the earth: what felowe is this, that will denye a proposition bearynge witnes to so many learned mens writynges beyng allowed by so many authorities of all ages, That the cause beeyng graunted, the effect must needes folowe, by what reason dare he affirme the cause, and denye the effect
                  •…
               ? But these so thretnyng wordes, what are they at the length but very words in dede? For geuynge to euery cause her propre effecte, yet wyll I not graunt effecte to that whiche is no cause: or if it be a cause, I wil not graunt that to be the offect which they wyll haue. For they knowe not what the starres doo cause or sygnifie, but embracyng an art delyuered of their ancestors, without any sure grounde or foundation, haue it in estimatiō as a diuine knowlege whiche conteineth in it no more diuinitie and truthe then the rest of the Chaldeans superstitions that yet remayne: of whome this science was receyued: whiche learned &amp; wise philosophers in all ages contemned and vtterly despised. And not only heathē
               
men as Porphyrius, whiche to Iamblicus saythe, That it is impossible that a manu
                  •…
                shuld knowe the signification of the celestiall reuolutions. Iamblicus hymself whi che denyeth, that any vertue or power descendeth frome the starres, &amp; dyuers other contemned the vayne ostentation of this art: But the prophete Hieremye himselfe with lowde voyce forbyddeth the Israelites to feare the influence of the starres, as the heathen doo. But therfore (say you) do they signifie nothyng? Wherfore I pray
                  •…
                you, are they not to be feared? eyther bycause they signify nothyng, or bycause the signification of them to men is vncertain and vnknowen? What, doothe not Paule thapostle of the Gentiles exhort his scolar Titus, that he regard not foolyshe and su perfluous questions of Genealogies and natiuities? F
                  •…
               r what cause then dothe Ieremie forbydde to feare, and Paule to regarde Predi
                  •…
               ions of Astrologye, yf in theym were any thynge eyther to be feared or regarded? Go youre wayes nowe, and make the people afrayd with horrible threatnynges, proclayme great calamitie to follow
                  •…
               : Of pestilence, bat tayle, and famyne: or yf any thynge bee more greuous then these? Warne them of a sodayn

destruction that shall falle vppon theym. As two yeares ago Cunyngham threatned to Egypte, Babylon, Constantinople, and the Cities of Italye a mooste lamentable and vtter subuersion. Had not the Italyans, Egyptians, Grecian
                  •…
               , and Chaldeans greate cause to feare, consyderyng that by the iudgemente of astrologians so great ruine hanged ouer their heades? Who wolde not in this case haue be
                  •…
                afrayde, except it were such as (I can not tell howe preposterously) woulde preferre Hieremies pro
                  •…
               hecie before Cunynghā
               
                  •…
                prognostication? Lykewyse he that had rather gyue credyte to the Prognosticatours thenne to sainct Paule, shoulde he not hauynge his natiuitie caste, forsee by it, what good thynges, and what euyll
                  •…
                thynges he shoulde in all his lyfe attayne? so shall he deuyse to auoyde the euylle, and brynge the good thynges to effecte. O blockeheade, that must haue thy Natiuitie caste, howe dooest thou determyne to leade thy lyfe, lyke a bruite beaste, that thou wylle suffer all thynges to woorke vpon thee. Wherefore serueth thy reason which thou dost not vse? nay rather which thou dooste abuse in suche vanities. 
                  •…
               
               wynge thy fortune (ye saist) by thy natiuity

thou wilte endeuour thy selfe to seeke for good thynges, and auoyde euyll thynges. Why wouldest thou not haue doon so, although thou haddest neuer asked counsell of the 
                  〈◊〉
               ? Alas, when wyl the world leaue to haue in admiration suche curious vanities. But now an other obiection. Berosus the Chaldean, a most auncient histo riographer reporteth, that the holy Patriarke Noah dyd forsee the vniuersall floud by the aspect of the starres: and to the intent that he myght auoyd the danger therof, he made the arke to preserue the life of hymselfe, his sonnes, and their wiues, and beasts of euery kynde. Then is not so auncient a science muche profitable 
                  •…
               omans▪ lyfe, whiche the holye patriarke dyd practise, and by helpe of which mākynd, beasts and what soeuer in al the worlde was plesant or profitable in tyme past was preserued from vtter destruction? This no lyght or contemptible author hath reported, but euen Be
                  •…
               osus the Chaldeā. But Moses the Hebrue, beyng also a most iust lawe geuer and historye writer, as moste auncient, so moste faithe worthy, witnesseth, That the Lorde God spake vnto Noah, and foreshewed the vniuersall 
                  •…
               loude, commandynge hym to make the Arke. And lest the Astrologians

shulde dreame of a reuelation by the starres, prescribed vnto hym a determinate forme and measure of the ship that he willed to be made. Then where is your boastyng of the antiquitie and necessarys vse of Astrologie? where be your bragges of the patriarke Noah, whom you would haue to be a patron of your foly? Shal we beleeue Moses, whiche write that, whiche was reueled by God? orels Berosus whic
                  •…
                studieng to aduance an art inuented of the superstitious Chaldeans, imagyned and fained, that the floude was foreseen by the practise of that arte.
            Nowe therfore which way wil ye turne the saile of youre safetie? The Patriarke Noah dooth renounce you, Hieremie and Paule doth hate you: Porphy
                     •…
                  ius &amp; Iambli cus, dothe contemne you. Who shall then be your standard bearer? or who the trompettour to blowe out your praise? Ptholomeus ascribeth as much certaintie to you as to the wynde: For he affirmeth, That your prediction
                  •…
                doo not bynde any man, but onely drawe them that be wyllyng. Then by this reason their will shoulde be cause of those thynges that chaunce, and not the starres. For against them that wil not, the starres can do nothyng: and them

that hee wyllynge they canne not lette to 
                  •…
               oo what they wyll. If this bee true, as it is moste true what power is left to the influence of the starres: We grant, say they that of those accions whiche a man doth, his wylle is the nexte cause: But of those actions whyche be not in a mans power, that is suche, as he can not bryng to passe as he woulde, the starres be gouernours. But then to what purpose or end dryueth that notable sayeng, whych beyng sprong from anercellent learned manne, all men by their consente do
                  •…
               e allowe, that is, (A wise man shal rule the starres) Is not this ment, that the signification of the starres althoughe they were knowen, haue not so greatte power in mennes mattiers, but that a wyse mannes prouydence is of muche greatter force, so that not without a cause, A wyse manne is sayde to re
                  •…
               ls the startes, that is to saye, the Iufluence and signification of the starres.
            Yet sommetyme it commeth to passe, that in castynge a mannes natiuitie, you doo hyt
                  •…
               e ryghte of his lyse or maners. And we wyll not greately str
                  •…
               ue agaynst you, but seeyng you doo so often and so dyuers thynges foretell to euery mann
                  •…
               e by his natiuitie, yt were impossible, but that som

what muste nedes chaunce accordyng to youre predictions: yet this is by chaunce and not by arte: for he that wysely and 
                  •…
               
               ly gently reuolueth in his mynde, that hen uenly reuolution, can not be certainly per suaded, that so momentaneous and shorte face of the heuens shuld worke any thyng strongly so long tyme after: for in the moment of an howre it is continually chau
                  •…
                ged frome one to an other: and this is the cause, that Iamblicus thynkethe, that the differences of tyme, whyche the Astrologiaus obserue, auayleth lyttell or nothyng to the effecte of stronge and meruaylous woorkes. Besydes this a certayne Astrologian or Palmester, Iohannes Indagine affirmeth, that this shorte and momentaneous reuolution of the heuēs is of lesse effecte and power then that, whyche he 
                  •…
               l leth naturall astrologie, reducyng all fortes of menne what saeuer they be
                  •…
               , vnto xii. horoscopes, accordynge to the numbre of the twelue signes. Therfore as well he as the other dooe ascribe so manye and so dyuers qualities to euerye manne by hys natiuitie, that of necessitie some of theim muste bee in euerye manne, As he whythe saythe, That a manne shall bee apte to anger, Pryde, Loue, Pytye, and

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
suche lyke: where as there is no man but he shall fynd these &amp; suche like qualities in himself, yf he enter into his owne mynde.
            But to procede, howe euery starre hath a name, whiche oftentymes seemeth to be geuen by the signification therof. Wherefore it shall not be out of the way, somme thyng to tary in resonyng of their names, left perchaunce the Astrologians of them (as of a gnatte) woulde seeme to make an Elephant. Fyrst therfore that the names whereby the starres are called, are not of their owne nature, but geuen to theim by men. Iohannes de sacro Bosco, sufficiently heareth wytnes, with whom Uer
                  •…
               ll agreeth in his first booke of Georgikes, saying

                  The shipman fyrste then gaue to starres their nomber, and their name:
                  The Pleiades, Hyades, and Lycaons, heare of worthy fame.
               
            
            Neuertheles all the starres had not their names geuen theym of the same occasiōs yet they were al deuised for difference that they myght be one knowen from another, as Bernardus Syluestris sayth very pretily.

                  Leste that without
                        •…
                      distinction the cōmmon worde shulde go,
                  The names wherby the starres be cald, by men were termed so.
               
               
But of the names some were attributed vnto them for the forme whiche they seme to beare in heauen to theym that beholde them: Of that sort ar the wain, the crown, the shippe, the serpent, the harpe, and such lyke. Some beare their name of their propre place, in whiche they bee sette: As Aries the ramme fyrste of the stocke, and firste of the signes. Cancer the crabbe, 
                  〈◊〉
                beast that goeth backewarde, gaue name to that signe, in whiche the sonne retourneth to the lower hemispher. Libra, the ba lance, that maketh euē weight, so being the name of a signe, it maketh nightes &amp; daies of equal lēgth. Aquarius, the water he arer and Pisees the fishes, for the abūdance of water, that is, when the sonne keepeth his course in those places, gaue name to those signes. Caper the goate, whiche in fedyng lifteth vp himselfe, and semeth to hang on the rocks, was thought a mete name to be geuen that signe, in whiche when the Son is, he daily riseth vp toward vs frome the Antipodes, or men that go with their feete right against our feete. A greate number also of the names whereby the starres are called, were geuen of the Eth
                  •…
               kes, partly flattetyng their princes, and partly beleuyng that theyr sowles beyng translated

after their death into heuen, had the do
                  •…
               
               mon of certayne starres, and therof from ancient tyme came the names of Saturne, Jupiter, Mars, Mercurie, O
                     •…
                  ion, &amp; such like. The men of later tyme perchance thynke that they eyther haue changed or reteyned certayn names, by reason of the qualities which they ascribe to the starres them selues. But this is specially worthe the markyng, that they are accustomed not of the qualities to geue the names, but of the names to derine theyr qualyties: as to the Crabbe, which is a fyshe by the water side (although he be a signe of the sommer, yet beyng in heauen, they ascribe a wa
                  •…
               ry nature. Likwise to the Bull, whiche is a melancolike beast euen amōg the signes, they attribute an earthy dispolition: The rāme in deuē also they wil haue to beare domini on of the pe in erth, like as the bull of oxen. So also to Saturne whiche of the poetes was feigned to be a lur kynge god, they ascribe melancolike qualities, but Iupiter which in the Fables is found a gentil &amp; fauorable God, is also iudged to bee a well willyng planet. Venus which was gentyl and amiable, euen amonge the starres is said to keye ye same nature still. Mereurius which is reported of the poets to be a these and a crafty felow, being translated to the

numbre of gods, is also vnstable &amp; inconstant, applying himself to euery company, for with the good, he is also good, and with the euill, agreable in qualitie with theim. And now by this means we haue veriued the significations of moste part of the planets, from the very fountain out of which they are drawen, wherby euery man may se vpon what reason their principles both consist, out of which they feine themselues as it were gods, to haue knowledge of thin ges past, thinges present, &amp; things to com. But abide for, bid not the. iij. wise men by aspect of a starre in the east, vnderstande, that Christ was borne, and by leadyng of the same, come to the place of his birth, to worship him, how then do you cry that the predictions of the starres are to be cōtemned? If you entend to wrest this to the con firmatiō of your art, by ye same reason you shall cōclude ye inumerable wōders which at yt time chā
               
                  •…
               ed in al places were done by ye order of nature. But at ye time al thyngs ministred vnto god: &amp; ye his power might appere, Nature her self went our of her ac customed place. For at that time great &amp; wondrous meruaile hapned, in so much ye the diuinors, soothsaiers, magitians, and all they that were wonte to tell the significations of such matters, beyng demanded

what these wonders ment, answerd, That Nature was in trauail with the LORDE of all thynges created. There testeth no more nowe, but to dissolue Cunynghams confutatione (set forth by hym iwa certain Epistle, whiche he calleth his Inuectiue) by lyke force as we haue doon the test. Master Cunynghā thinketh yt he hath reduced al aduersaries calūniations vnto ij. poyntes: The fyrst is, that yt knowlege of Astrologie, is enemy to the most laudable sciēce of phisike: The other, That the Astrologiā can not foreshewe thynges to come by his starres. Concernynge the former parte he sendeth us ouer to Hipocrates the prince of phisike, in his boke De aëre, aqua, &amp; locis. Seyng therfore it was nedefull for me to reade ouer that booke (although not agreable with my study and profession) yet hauyng one lent me, according to the smal leisure that I had, and the litle capacitie of my poore wytte, I redde hym ouer bothe in Greke and latin. And truely as farre as I remembre the notes of the margent in the latin translation proclaimed open war betwene Hipocrates and me: but when I looked nerer to hym selfe, I found no man so frendly to me, whiche prescribed so profytable necessary vse of astronomy (not

ones dreaming of fatal signs, as they wold seme to haue hym. But seing peraduēture I shal seme to dispute on these matters beyonde my cunnyng, I wolde sayne learne of doctour Cunyngham what argumentt to confirme Astrologie he can gather out of that booke. In the meane tyme suche thynges as I redde and vnderstode, I wil briefely recite. Hipocrates speaketh muche of the risyng of certayne signes and stars, as of the Pleiades, Arcturus, Canis, and suche other, all the which sayenges are most plainly to be referred to the state of Tyme that is, when those signes rise or go down. And not here onely, but also in his Aphorismes, Hipocrates dryuethe to the same ende. Wherefore he concludeth, That the knowledge of Astronomye, not of Astrologie, is profitable to the science of phisike Bicause that by the course of the starres the phisition may forsee many thynges ne cessary to his science. Not that the starres 
                  •…
               oo foretell hym of any thynge, but that their risynge or fallyng is coincident with suche state of tyme. Secondly, master Cu nyngbam concludeth, that things to come may be forsene by aspect of the starres, by this argument. If the Maryner by his signes can forshe we the tempest to folowe,

the Phisition by his tokens, can forsee the increace or declination of the liknes. The husband man by his argument can fortell the state of the yeare to folowe, why may not the learned Astrologian by his starres haue knowledge of thynges to come? As for example, Mars is whotte and drye, nowe yt he see many fyery thynges mete with hym, may he not boldely pronounce that the yeare folowyng shalbe muche enclined to heate. But of howe smalle force this argument is, we shal vnderstande by the easy solution thereof. For grauntynge that the maryner, phisition, and husbande man can forsee thinges by his certayn sygnes and tokens: Yet what fatall necessitie (in gods name) compelleth vs to think likewise of thastrologians. For the example that is brought to confirm the matter, is more doubtfull then the matter it selfe: for we can not tell of what nature Mats is, nor thastrologians them selues, so that is they wyl proue any thyng by this argument, they must fyrst shew by what reson they call Mars whote, or Saturne colde.
            For except they bee sure of this, that they make their priciples tru, thei may at their pleasure conclude what thei list. But their propositions shall haue no more credite

then truth &amp; certayntie. Wherfore not because the phisitiā or the mariner can know any thing, therfore the astrologians shall do the lyke, except they fetch theyr premō strations of as sure groundes as the other do. But lest we should to insolently inuey agaynste these false tellers (foretellets I wold say, master Cunyngham hath geuen vs ensaumple of two yeares that chaunced accordyng to the predictions of moysture, 1524, and drynesse. 1540. But here I appeale to Cuninghams wisedom, why he bryngeth exaumple of two yeares onely, and them so longe agoe past? and why he dyd not she we exaumple of thre yeares laste paste? yf he wyll boaste that his arte is certayne and trewe, why doothe he not declare, that the euent of euery yeare was suche, as thastrologiās for shewed it shulde bee, whether because all menne with one voyce wold say nay
                  •…
               or els because of tyme longe paste he may feigne, and no manne reproue him. but there shal nede no such cō tention we wil grant. xx. yeres sens astrol. first began, whiche hapned accordyng as the prognosticators fortold them: wylyon then boast that your diuinatiō is true, be cause of. 2000. yeares onely, twenty serus for youre pourpose. But these thynges

beyng so clere I omytte.
            And that we may make haste to the had uen that is not nowe farre of, seynge this ap
                  •…
               she arte is vnprofitable to the woorkes of phisike, to the profite of the studentes, to the state of the common wealth: and seyng that without principles nothyng can be knowen: but astrology consisteth either of no principles, or of false, in is softe labony that is spent in thobseruation therof: in vayne it is to credite their predictions, vnsust it is, that she is of the vnlerned people reuerenced, more worthy to bee buried vnder the chanell of Lethe, the ryuer of ob liuion, than that she shoulde enioyeng the cleare lyght of men, be had in any estimation. But if there be any Prognosticatour that will take vppon hym to defende Astrologie thus battered in pieces, let hym make haste to dooe it, before she vtterlye false to ruyne.
            FINIS.
            ¶ Herafter foloweth a short Treatise, as well for the vtter subuersion of this fained art, as also for the better vnderstandyng of the cōmon people.
         
         
            
            The preface to the Reader.
            
               COnsyderyng with my selfe, (gentyl reader) that so manynotable workmen at thys tyme, hathe by theyr cunning, &amp; also by their diligēt laboure, haue layde the foundation of a moste woorthy buildynge: &amp; also brought the same a good waye aboue the grounde, intendynge by gods helpe not onely to finishe the playne worke thereof, but also to garnishe it with suche ornamentes as myghte beseeme so princely a palayce: I thoughte it not my parte for the good affection that I heart to the woorke, to stande altogyther ydell, yf by any meanes I myghte be profytable in the same. And walkynge about to see the compasse and fasshion of it, I perceyued that the great stones whiche pertayned to the structure were suche as neither by my strengthe I was able to lyste theym, nor

yet by my cunnyng in that kynd of mas
                  •…
                ry to place and ioyne theim: but as for hewyng or fashionyng them, I sawe it was so farre aboue my knowledge and vnderstandyng, that I dyd not ones applye my selfe to haue any medlynge with them. At the last when I had 
                  •…
               ewed all other thynges sufficiently, I espied a lyttle heape of rubbyshe whyche not only hyndered them that wente to and fro o
                  •…
               er it, in specdynge their worke, but also semed to be no small deformitie to the leuelled playnesse of the statte forme, whereon the buyldyng should stande, I myghte see also that some of the master masons them selues had taken paines in remouynge the same vnprofytable Chaos: which caused me to thynke, that I coulde not be better occupied then to conney the same quight out of the way, that it shoulde neyther be a lette nor an yll sight, in the procedyng of so necessary busynes. Wherefore I prepared and made for my selfe as it were a lyttell wicker baskette, whiche I myght easily beare, so cary away this hyndryng heape, where it shalbe confused and utterly dispersed abroade. And although the substance of my bas kette be symple and weake, yet it is good enoughe to cary tubb
                  •…
                
               
                  •…
               he and suche lyght stuffe as

I put therin. But as soone as I beganne to tourne vp the vpper parte therof, I vnderstode, that because it had lyenge longe compacte togyther, thers was bredde in it a great numbre of toades and snakes that beganne to hysse and spewe out theyr poyson agaynst me, bycause I diseased theim of their nesle and barrborowe. But God be thanked I come not naked among them, I haue an armoure called Veritas, that is able to withstande the malice euen of dragons, and crocodiles. Som men perchāce wolde meruayle why I woulde not strike 
                  •…
               eim, that so furiousely haue gone about to stynge me. In deede I haue prepared al redy moderate defence, but I staye vppon certayne dóubtes that are these:
            Fyrst, whether it be the poynte of al
                  •…
               
               ned manne to rayle or no
                  •…
               
            
            Secondely, whether the conclusion in Syllogismo litigiolo bee good or no?
            And thirdly whether there be a kynde of argument called Syllogismus conuciatorius, or no? these doubtes resolued I wold
                  •…
                procede. As for Uaughan I haue nothing to dooe with hym, but to wysshe hym his tyghte wyttes and a good tongue.
            I haue taken vpō me to dissolue this masse at astrologie, and that by goddes helpe I

wyll doo to the vttermoste of my power, so that my contention is agaynst no mā. But my labour is to remoue this obstacle out of good menues waies, and if any yll men hereafter exercise their malyce vpon me, I must nedes say as Socrates sayde: Though an asse spurne agaynst me, I wil not go to lawe with hym. Therefore they that haue delyte in railyng, let them rayle and spare not: They that haue pleasure in scoffyng, lette theim scoffe and flowte tyll they haue proued theym selues cōmen parasites and sycophantes in so dooynge, I wyll not ones be moued with suche vnhoneste meanes. But yf any man shall propounde any probable argument to mayntayne this cause, I wyll doo the best I can to answer it, and if I be not able (as I haue always offered) I wyll yelde vnto hym. Wherefore gentyll reader, if thou cansts fynde thy selfe eased with any of these two small trauayles, I haue my request.
         
         
            
            
               TO begyn playnly as we entende to procede, we must fyrst calle to remembraunce, what matter we haue in hāde and then with like plainnesse declare, what playne order we ent
                  •…
               nde to take in discussyng of the same. Therfore omyttynge all colours of rhetor
                  •…
               ke, and all impediments of paynted speache, our pur pose is (to speake it at one breathe) vtterly to ouerthrowe the science of astrologie. Astrologie (leste any man shoulde doubte, bycause it is no Englishe worde) is sayd to be a knowledge, wherby the practisers of it saye, that they can tell of all thyng that are not come to passe, before they come to passe, by the course &amp; mouyng of the starres, or els to describe it more plainely, is yt knowledge by whiche the prognosticatiōs be made, that tell of rayne and fayre weather, sickenes and health, warre &amp; peace, plentie and dearthe, with suche lyke: By whiche also they cast your natiuities, tell you 
                  •…
               oure fortunes, pretende to gyue you knowledge of thinges that be lost: and last of all appoynt you dayes and tymes good or euyll, for all thynges that you haue to doo. As, for workes of phisike, to let bloud to take purgations, and al other medicins

for other cōmon matters, to sow, to plant, to iourney by lande, to iourney by water, to bye and sell, to marye, to begynne anye woorke, and fynally to attempt any thyng that men vse cōmonly in their lyfe to doo. Our intent is therfore in this shorte Trea tise to persuade all such as he therto beyng deceiued by a false opinion of learnynge, haue gyuen credite vnto them: that herafter (yf they see that all is not onely vayne, but also vngodlye) they cleane forsake them and theyr prophesie
                  •…
                as thyngs that lette them to prosper well in theyr busines and also hynder theim to put theyr truste in God and his promyses. For what confidence hathe be in god or his worde, that dare not take in hande any honest and ver
               
                  •…
               ous affaires (in which God hath promised to ayde and set forwarde all theim that loue hym) except 
                  •…
               e must fyrste aske counsayle of a blynde southsayer and Astrologiā? And let them not be offended though I call theim blynde, for accordynge to the prouerbe, Who is so blynde as, he that wil not see? But perchaunce so
                  •…
               me will say
                  •…
               , that bycause I am blynde and ignoraunt in so goodlye a science, therefore I 
                  〈◊〉
                dysprayse it. As towchynge that

matter, they haue no cause to say so, for be it spoken withoute diswoorshyp of any of theym, and with smalle pryde in my self, I knowe what the arte is as well as they, and so muche the rather doo I condemne it, leste seynge the vanitie and vncertaintie thereof, I shoulde bee counted as they are, wylfully blynde, and not seyng when theyr eyes bee open.
            Thus much for oure entente, our order shall be suche, as best maye be perceyued. For wee wylle fyrste speak
                  •…
                agaynste the wholle knowledge generally, and thenne particularly agaynste euery membre and parcell thereof. And because wee wylle spende no paper in superfluous sentences, we must remembre what was sayd in the former booke, that it was impossible for any man to haue any knowledge of thynge
                  •…
                to comme 
                  •…
               y the course of the starres. Wherevnto wee wyll adde for playnner 
                  •…
               nderstandynge this that foloweth. As towchyng t
                  •…
                mouynge and course of th
                  •…
                hea
                  •…
               ens, bycause menne may see th
                  •…
               ym, they myghte also (as they haue doo
                  •…
               ) by longe and dilygent obseruation fynd out a learnyng, that shuld 
                  •…
               each the truth of thē, but seing the starres be all of one forme or facion, yt is sphericall or rounde like a ball,

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
(although some be greatter then some also some hygher then some) it can not be, that a man beholdyng or lookyng vpon them, shoulde vnderstande of what qualities or significations they are. As for the coloure of them (although to speake exquisitely by the rules of natural philosophie they haue no colour) is 
                  •…
               o lyke in moste (exceptynge the sonne and the moone) that in so smalle varietie of colours, a man can not discern so dyuers and manye qualities. And not withstandynge that they ymagine the planette Saturne to bee blacke or blewe, and Mars to be redde or fyery, they can if they were disposed (I meane the learned sorte) gyue an other reason of theyr colour, nothynge seruynge for the auauncement of theyr pretende
                  •…
                knowledge. By this it is manyfest, that by seeyng, lookynge, or beholdyng the starres, no man can knowe what they signifye, forasmuche as by the syght nothyng can properly be perceyued but colour and fashion. Then what waye is it possible, that a man shuld vnderstand what those hygh bodies all of one colour
                  •…
                and fashion shoulde betoken? Some wyll say peraduenture, that as the course of the starres was founde out by diligent obseruation, so lykewyse theyr sygnifications

were learned by earneste markyng wha
                  •…
                chaunced alwayes vnder euery sygne or planet. Howe vntrue this is, we shal part ly nowe declare, and partly leaue tyll we come to the particulars.
            Fyrst therfore that their significations coulde not so be learned, it is manyfest by this reason: That those thynges whyche chaunce or come to passe bee infinite, that is innumerable to men, howe then coulde a certayn numbre of men know or learne whether all those thynges came to effecte as they had marked in a few? for although they had taken their obseruation in as ma ny as they coulde, yet were there manye mo, yea tenne thousande tymes as manye whiche they knew not of, that myght happen clean
                  •…
                contrary to theyr deuise. Dothe it not then playnly appeare, that by obseruation no man coulde discerne what those sygnes and heauenly bodies dyd forshew? Then if neither by beholdyng thē, nor yet by marking or obseruatiō of thē, it might be that mans witte coulde fynde out their signification: there remayneth no waye howe to knowe them, but that fonde fantasy of reuelation by some spirite or aungelle. Whiche I haue not without a cause before touched (although some wold think

that I ymagin that obiection of my selfe) because that of some it is so obiected, not onely in woordes, but also in writynge.
            Concernynge reuelation we haue some 
                  •…
               ynge sayde all readye, wherevnto we wyll ioyne this, that God vse
                  •…
                not by his mynysters to reueale any knowledge vnto menne, but suche as is to his glory and theyr profyte. Nowe what auayleth it to Goddes glorye, that mortall men shoulde haue vnderstandynge of all thynges that he purposeth to doo, as who shoulde saye, he woulde haue men as cunnynge as hym selfe, or as thowghe he shoulde rule the world by theyr prognostications. And no profyte canne it bee to menne, to haue suche knowledge, whyche yf it were true, (as it is moste 
                  •…
               alse) they were not able to preuente. If, God therefore dooeth not reueals any thynge whiche is not to his glorye, and the proufyte of his creatures, me thynke that vayne obiection is cleane put out of the waye. Lette this suffise for our purpose of inueyenge generally. Therefore proceede we to the particulars, whiche althoughe there bee as many as there bee dyuers actions, yet we wyll intreate onely of two
                  •…
                sortes: the one of foreshewynge the states of thynges and tymes,

that other of chusyng dayes and oportunyties. And to begyn with that whyche semeth chieffest amonge theym, to prognosticate of warre and peace, I meruayle that menne are so madde, as to looke for warre oute of theyr predictions, knowing that the cause therof proceedeth not of the starres, but of the deuyll, whyche alwaye labourethe to breake the bondes of vnitie and concorde, that shoulde be among christian men. And where doothe he plant the cause therof, but in the kyng, whose heart the scripture witnesseth, that as the diuisions of waters, so is it in the lordes hande, and whether he will, he moueth it. Seyng therfore that the kyng is not subiect to the influence of the starres, neyther is anye thing that procedeth from hym, gouerned by theim, and thenne consequentlye and necessarilye it folowethe, that all matters concernynge the commune wealthe, as warre and peace, discorde and rebellyon, lawes, and suche lyke, can neyther bee forshewen nor foreseene by Astrologie: dearthe and plentye bee caused by reasone of seasonable weather, or vnseasonable: Then yf the starres haue nothyng to doo with wether, they haue lesse to dooe with plentie or scarcity, which ar caused therby

As for clowdes wherof rayne commeth, they are drawen vp in thynne vapours, by the heate of the sonne, into the myddle region of the ayre, and there, by colde, are made grosse, then by some wyndes they ar dissipated and dryuen abroade, or elles by some resolued and drop downe. And thys is the cause for the moste part, of rayne &amp; fayre wether, so ye except the vncertayntie of the wynd may be knowen by the stars, rayne and fayre wether can neuer be foreshewed. But wherof commeth the wynd▪ I am sure they wyll not denye the Philosophers definition gathered oute of the seconde booke of his Meteors, which is, that the wynde is an exhalation whot and dry, drawen vp by the heate of the Sonne, and for the weight of it selfe fallyng downe, is laterally or sydelonges caried aboute the earthe. By this definition all power of signifying starres is cleane excluded. And as towchynge the place frome whens the wynd bloweth, the same philosopher doth also declare, that as it hapneth the matter thereof to be caried, so frome that place it moueth. And here by the way where as I vse the wordes of Happen and Chaunce, you muste not take me, that I meane the thynge shoulde come by blynde fortune or

case: For I am of opinion, that nothyng commeth to passe without a cause, but my meanyng is, that by the causes and occasions therof, so it came to effect. But to returne into the way agayn, seyng the cause of the wynde is not forsene by the starres, no more can the wether that is partly caused by it, nor yet the dearthe or plentie whiche chaunceth by occasion of the weather, bee by Astrologie foreshewed. Then wi
                  •…
                al those 
                  •…
               ut of your Prognostications, for what shoulde they doo there, of whiche it is impossible that you shoulde prognosticate. Sycknesse and healthe depende vpon dyuers causes, but nothyng at al vpon the course of the starres. for what way soeuer the starres runne their race, yf there be in the body abundance or defect, or from outward by corruption of the ayre infection it must nedes be sycke: and it none of these bee, though all the starres in heauen with all their oppositions and euil tokens shuld meete in the howse of sicknesse, yet the body shoulde bee whole, and in good healthe. But you wyl say, that those causes of sicknesse are wroughte by the constellation of the starres. Wel ones we haue a good con fort of Hieremy the prophet, that those are not to be feared. And to aunswere this obiection

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
I woulde haue taken paynes, 
                  〈◊〉
                that the moste parte of Astrologians ar by profession phisitions, whiche yf they be in dede as they professe, and haue learnyng accordyng to their degree (which I doubt not but they haue) they knowe assuredly, that the causes of sycknes and helth hang nothynge vppon mouyng of the celestiall bodies. The more shame is it for theym, yf they stiffely and stoutely maynteyn and defende that which they know to be moste vayne and false. But leaue sycknesse and healthe to theym that haue chiefely to doo with theym, and comme to Natiuytyes or Fortune tellynges.
            If I hadde not beene my selfe seduced by suche a vayne credyte that I gaue to the wrytyngs of Astrologians, I would neuer beleeue, that any manne endewed with common sence and reasone, shoulde haue respecte to castynge of Natiuityes, or Fortune tellynges. For what madnesse ys yt to thynke, that beeynge but twelue sygnes and seuen planettes, euery syngular manne hath of theym his singular constellation. I confesse that euery syngular manne by the prouidence of God is guyded and preserued, but that euery man that is borne hath his syngular influence,

it is to muche incredyble. For I dare be bolde to saye (and if I were dryuen to it by good reasone proue it) that at one instant or Nunc, there is somtyme borne a kynge and a sclaue, a warryour and a cowarde, a wyse man and a foole, a learned manne, an vnlearned persone, a true man and a thefe, a ryche man and a poore, a Christian and a Pagan, a manne and a beaste. Howe thenne shall the Astrologian telle all these theyr Fortune, by one constellation? Furthermore what a straunge matter is it, that one constellation should woorke to so sundrye effectes? as yf an Astrologian hadde erected a fygure for one mannes natiuytie, a nother commeth to knowe of a thynge loste, at the same instant, the thyrde commeth to heare yf a sycke man shall dye or recouer, All these muste haue theyr aunsweres shapen theym oute of one fygure. But they wylle say perchaunce, that all these canne not happen at ones, then lette theym answere me to this question: Is there but one kynde of thyng done in the whole worlde, or vnder one meridian at one instāt or moment? And be allother ydle for that tyme▪ As for exāple, when one stealeth, is there nothyng done at that tyme but 
                  •…
               alynge:

When a kyng is borne, is none borne el
                  •…
                but kynges? Or when a sclaue is brought forth, is thir none els that season brought foorth but sclaues? Therefore yf they can not auoyde the mischefe of this answere, let them bee ashamed to practise any more suche vayne predictions, yea let them be astayde to vse tellyng of fortunes, lest they be counted in that poynte as yll as wicked Ma
                  •…
               asses, of whome the scripture reporteth, that amonge other his synnes he had also regarde to soothsayenge and fortune tellynge. As for Consurynge, I wyll not charge them, bycause theyr predictions ar not so sure as they are wonte to make.
            But perchaunce they wyll say that al that I haue yet sayde, eyther agaynst their arte generally, or against these particulars, y
                  •…
                of no more strength then stubble or straw. Wherfore to shut vp the gappe, I entende to laye a greate blocke in their waye. And I shall desyre, theym when they make answere, (if they make any at all) that accor 
                  •…
               ynge to the prouerbe, They wylle not stoumble at a strawe, and leape ouer a blocke. And the blocke that I wyll laye is of the heauy burthen that the Lord by the prophere Esays 47. Chapter threatneth vnto Babylon the inuentresse of this art,

where h
                  •…
                sayth: Nowe let the heauen g
                  •…
               
               sers and beholders of starres, the moone prophetes come and delyuer thee, yea and lette theym shewe thee, whan these thynges shall come vpon thee: Beholde, (sayth he) they shall be as strawe, whyche yf it be kyndled with syre, no manne maye rydde it from the 
                  •…
               hamence of the flame.
            Doo you not heare, O you Astrologians, that the prophets saythe, that you canne haue no knowledge of thynges to came, as of warre, syckenesse, dearthe, vnseasonable weather, destruction, and suche other, whiche he threatneth vnto Babylon. For it is manyfests, that this phrase or maner of speakynge, which the Prophete vseth, Lette them shewe when these thynges shall come to passe, is a stronger 
                  •…
               gation or denyall, thenne yf in playne woordes he hadde sayde: They can not shew
                  •…
                the
                  •…
               , when these thynges shall comme to passe. Marke also what rewarde is promised to the vsers of this foreshewynge, that they shal be
                  •…
                in Goddes wrathe as straw
                  •…
                kyndeled with syre.
            But I leaue this to theyr wysedom and discretion to consyder, and wyll proce
                  •…
               ede to the second kynde of particulars, that is Elections or chusynges of dayes.

And here haue I nothyng to do with Galeues (
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ) for it is meruayle yf that it be not obiected against me, but I begynne with good dayes to let bloude. And what is the cause of bloudde lettynge? surely I thynke eyther to dyminishe humors in the body, or els to abate heate, or at least some suche cause in the body. whiche if it be vrgent, wyl not sticke to kyll the body, without consideration of signe or planet, orels if it be not so vehement wyl hurt the body, without respect of good days or yll. Therfore seyng this abundance of bloude wyll not tarie for good dais or yll, but wyll procede to annoy the body: wherfore shuld the body tarye for good sygnes to bee rydde of it? And lykewise of purgations, what sort soeuer they be: If any thynge bee nedefull to be pourged, yt wyll not ceasse from annoyeng vpon good dayes, and woorke his malice onely vpon tuyll dayes: but who so euer is troubled with any suche thynge, shall feele that his disease lyttle regardeth the course of the starres, and he, yf he bee wyse, wyll as little regard them in sekyng for remedy. Who so shuld narowly marke this geare, should fynde out among them greuous absurdities, but wee entende to

make but shorte woorke. Nowe therefore must we leape from phisike to husbandry.
            Good days to sowe and plante, I thinke be whan the earth is moderatly moystned, and gentilly warmed with the heat of the sonne, whyche must bryng vp these seedes or plantes nourished with humours, and pleasauntly resolued with the southweste wynde, or other of lyke nature, As for the sygne or constellation yf the aforesayde lacke shall neuer prosper or encrease, the seedes sowen or plantes planted, nor endamage them, yf these causes d
                  •…
               o not sayle, and although bothe mete togyther, it is as muche healpe vnto the sedes as it was ease for the Camell whenns the Flye leapt of from his backe.
            To iourney by lande is good when so euer a manne hath honest and necessary affayres, the better yf the weather be faire, &amp; the way cleane, specially yf he be a foote manne. But he, that hauynge vrgent busynes wyll tary vntyll he haue a good day, is worthy to come to late, or as they say, A daye after the fayre. For he that wyll not take hold of occasions heare that is before him, when she hath ones tourned her back may clawe on her bare skulle, and fynde

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
neuer an heare to take holde of.
            Good dayes to iourneye by water, are partly as they are to iourney by lande, and also it is required, that they haue a good 
                  〈◊〉
                and prosperous wynde. With which i
                  •…
                they begynne theyr course, it is a greate 
                  〈◊〉
                that they shall haue good successe. If any manne hauyng wynde and weather, ty
                  •…
                and tyde conuenient, wyll tarye for 
                  •…
               erre or planette, sygne, or constellation, 
                  〈◊〉
                leese those former oportunities, thoughe he hadde all the fauourable starres in heauen an his syde, shall haue a troublesome voyage.
            Good dayes to bye and selle, bee market dayes, and all other whensoeuer a manne canne gette a good bargayne with honestie. I thynke but sewe marchantes wyll leese their mart in waightyng for heauenly healpe frome the starres.
            Euyll dayes to bye and sell be holydais, and suche tymes as menne shoulde be occupied in prayer, and hearyng gods word. Ill places to bye and selle, bee Churches, and other places appoynted for praier and preachynge. Other days and places be indifferent, if the bargayns he good.
            Good daies to mary are all the dayes in the yeare of theyr nature, in as muche as

to doo a good thyng it is good at al tymes: The mariage it selfe taketh not effecte (as these superstitious diuinours saye) of the daye or tyme but of the cause and circumstaunce in whiche it is contracted. For yf those bee nought, not Uenus nor Iupiter nor all the louynge sygnes can make that mariage good: And yf thou marry in the feare of God, though Mars and Saturne satte ouer thee, and thoughe it were on the moste dismall daye that euer Egyptian or Chaldean obserued, thou shalte be sure of the Lordes blessynge, whyche he promiseth to all them that in his feare and loue entreth into that honourable estate. So muche the more is theyr vnholsome harmonie to be hissed oute, that appoynts certayne days, in whyche yf a man shuld marry, the parties shoulde neuer agree or loue one the other.
            But I leaue the rest vntyl such tyme as I shall bee dryuen to answer them, where yf they keepe not modestie, as I thynke I haue doone, I wyl yet vtter more to the confusion of theym, and theyr arte.
            But to close thys parte of Elections as we dyd the other with a sure barre, wherwith God woulde barre the Israelites, in

the, xviii. chapter of Deuteronomie, sayeng by Moyses, Chere shall not be amonge you any choser of dayes or soothsayer. For those nations whithe the Lord casteth out before you among other abhominatiōs haue regarde to choosers of dayes, and sorcerers. Therfore yf this seeme not inough to keepe oute the Astrologians, but they wyll needes enter with theyr predictions and Elections, at the leaste lette all theym that nowe euen with theyr handes feele and handle the truthe, hereafter suffer them, as they are false prophetes, so to prophecie to them, whiche in the myddest of lyght and truth, wil peruersely embrace falsehod errour and darkenesse.
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶ Imprinted at London by Henry Sutton dwellyng in Pater noster row at the signe of the blacke Boy. The. 23. day of December. And are there to be solde.
            Perused and allovved according to the Quenes maiesties iniunctions.
            
         
      
   

