
   
      
         
            An historicall collection of the continuall factions, tumults, and massacres of the Romans and Italians during the space of one hundred and twentie yeares next before the peaceable empire of Augustus Cæsar Selected and deriued out of the best writers and reporters of these accidents, and reduced into the forme of one entire historie, handled in three bookes. Beginning where the historie of T. Liuius doth end, and ending where Cornelius Tacitus doth begin.
            Fulbecke, William, 1560-1603?.
         
         
            
               1601
            
         
         Approx. 283 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 115 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01289
            STC 11412
            ESTC S102772
            99838536
            99838536
            2918
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01289)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2918)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 293:05)
         
         
            
               
                  An historicall collection of the continuall factions, tumults, and massacres of the Romans and Italians during the space of one hundred and twentie yeares next before the peaceable empire of Augustus Cæsar Selected and deriued out of the best writers and reporters of these accidents, and reduced into the forme of one entire historie, handled in three bookes. Beginning where the historie of T. Liuius doth end, and ending where Cornelius Tacitus doth begin.
                  Fulbecke, William, 1560-1603?.
               
               [16], 20 [i.e. 209], [7] p.   
               
                  Printed [by R. Field] for VVilliam Ponsonby,
                  London :
                  1601.
               
               
                  Dedication and preface signed: William Fulbecke.
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Includes index.
                  The first leaf is blank.
                  P. 209 misnumbered 20.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Rome --  History --  Republic, 265-30 B.C. --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-01
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-01
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-03
            Jason ColmanSampled and proofread
         
            2007-03
            Jason ColmanText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            AN HISTORICALL COLLECTION OF THE CONTINVALL FACTIONS, TVMVLTS, and Maſſacres of the Romans and Italians during the ſpace of one hundred and twentie yeares next before the peaceable Empire of Auguſtus Caeſar.
            Selected and deriued out of the beſt writers and reporters of theſe accidents, and reduced into the forme of one entire hiſtorie, handled in three bookes.
            
               Beginning where the hiſtorie of T. LIVIVS doth end, and ending where CORNELIVS TACITVS doth begin.
            
            
            
               LONDON, Printed for VVilliam Ponſonby.
            1601.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE SIR THOMAS Sackeuill Knight, of the moſt noble order of the Garter, Baron of Buckhurſt, Lord high Treaſurer of England, one of her Maieſties moſt honorable Priuie Counſell, Chauncellour of the Vniuerſitie of Oxford. The Epiſtle Dedicatorie.
            
               RIGHT Honorable, I hope your Lordship will pardon my feare transformed into boldneſſe, who hauing vowed by good right vnto your Honor excellently deſeruing of the more polite learning, and milder ſciences, this ſmall hiſtory, and ſo much fearing or rather reuerencing your cenſure, that I did hold it better to ſmother it with ſilence, then to endow it with light, ſith your Honour hath trauerſed ſuch an infinite ſea of hiſtories, when as I do but offer certaine ſhallow riuelettes and ſlender parcels of an hiſtorie: yet now notwithſtanding, as if all were well accomplished, I preſume to deliuer it into your Lordships hands. Therefore, that it may appeare clearely and euidently to your Lordship, what cauſe did eſpeciallie mooue me to entertaine this determination,

I will by your Honours fauour, in few words, as becommeth me, explane and vnfold the ſecret ſenſe of my minde. The fortunes of noblemen, a man adorned with nobilitie: the ſtate and forme of politike affaires, ſome eye of a common weale: the aſpiring Icarian Romanes, he, whoſe authoritie is effectuall for the depreſſing of the Popiſh Phaetons, is onely fit to cenſure and with iudiciall ſtile to note. And what did perſwade me to this labour, being deſtinated to another profeſſion, and euen then champing vpon the vnpleaſant barke of the ſtudie of the Law, which might eaſilie procure a diſtaſt of more delightfull learning, I do not purpoſe to conceale. Plutarch in that part or region of his worke, which is entitled Lucullus (for his whole volume doth reſemble the hugeneſſe of the world) hath reported, and imparted to poſteritie, that Lucullus, Hortenſius, and Siſenna being famous for skill in Law, did by couenant determine to write according to lot the hiſtorie of that time. To Lucullus was allotted the deſcription of the Marſian warre, who content with this taske, did with great commendation finish it: and he being a worthie Conquerour, did in the Greeke language diſplay the notable conqueſtes of the Romanes: which thing hauing recorded and digeſted in my minde, I found by infallible exexperience, that one ſtudious of Law might afford ſome leaſurable time to the diuulging of an hiſtorie. For I do not deſpaire to follow theſe Romanes, though I do not aſpire to their exquiſite and induſtrious perfection: for that were to climbe aboue the climates: but to imitate any man, is euery mans talent. But this ſlender gift, of paper and ſmall accompt (I would it were worthie of your

Honour, your birth, your place) yet flowing from that minde, of which it was conceiued, that is to true nobilitie moſt addicted, take (moſt Honorable Lord) in good worth and aboue my deſert or expectation, and not onely with looking, but with liking vouchſafe it. The Lord God ſupport your Honour with vnchaungeable ſafetie.
            
               Your Honors moſt humble to commaund. WILLIAM FVLBECKE.
            
         
         
            
            
            The Praeface to the Reader.
            
               FOurteene yeares are now runne out ſithence I fully ended and diſpatched this hiſtoricall labour: for departing from the Vniuerſitie of Oxford in the yeare 1584, and addreſſing my ſelfe to the ſtudie of the Law, I thought it more conuenient and reaſonable at once to finiſh and perfect this worke, which I had already begun, then breaking my courſe with delaies to be ſtill ſtriking on the anuill, knowing that things begun, are more eaſily concluded then thinges interrupted can be conioyned; wherefore in that very yeare and ſome few daies following, I did begin, continue and conſummate the three bookes of this hiſtorie, ſince which time it hath lyen in the couert of my ſtudie, of my ſelfe ſeldome looked on, of others ſome times read, who by vrgent perſwaſion would haue mooued me to offer it to the publike view of my countreymen, to which I would in no wiſe condiſcend, alleaging for reaſon that it would be thought a blemiſh of impudencie in me to aſſay the diſcription of ſuch things, which by Appian, Plutarch, Paterculus, &amp; others haue bene excellently deliuered; which I tooke to be a ſufficient fortreſſe and ſupport of my excuſe and refuſall, but againe I heard that all the Romane writers which haue reported the accidents of this hiſtorie, are either in

their narrations too long and prolixe, or elſe too harſh and vnpleaſant, or elſe ſo exceeding briefe that the coherence and mutuall dependance of things could hardly be diſcerned or coniectured in the narrow compaſſe of ſo ſtrict deſciphering. This I heard with patience, and anſwered with ſilence, for I durſt not oppoſe my blunt arguments to their daintie appetite: the truth ſtanding ſo in the middle way betwixt bs both, that I could not with ſafe conſcience in all theſe allegations diſſent from them, nor with ſound opinion in all conſent vnto them, wherefore weighing more preciſely in minde, and ballancing with vnaffectioned thoughts the ſtate of the difference betwixt vs, and beholding the naked pourtrature of the thing it ſelfe without ſhadow of circumſtances, I perceiued that the great prolixitie and the too exceeding breuitie of the Romane hiſtoriographers could not well be couered with the veile of any reaſonable excuſe: and further the obiection of others could not well be confuted, who do condemne in their writings great diſagreament and contrariety of narration, wherefore remembring my firſt intent in the collecting of theſe hiſtoricall reports, which was to ſingle and ſequeſter the vndeniable truth of the hiſtorie from the droſſe and falſhood which was in many places intermixed and enfolded in it: and to do this in ſuch ſort, that my ſpeciall care in auoyding the extremities of length and breuity, two lothſome faults, from which notwithſtanding few writers be free, might fully and manifeſtly appeare: and conſidering likewiſe that hiſtories are now in ſpeciall

requeſt and accompt, whereat I greatly reioyce, acknowledging them to be the teachers of vertuous life, good conuerſation, diſcreete behauiour, politike gouernement, conuenient enterpriſes, aduiſed proceedings, warie defences, grounded experience, and refined wiſedome. And being again ſolicited by perſwaſible meanes, to commit the cenſure of this my hiſtoricall collection to the curteſie of others, I haue at laſt yeelded to this motion, repoſing my ſelfe rather vpon kinde conſtruction, then rigorous deſert. The vſe of this hiſtorie is threefold, firſt the reuealing of the miſchiefes of diſcord and ciuill diſcention, in which the innocent are proſcribed for their wealth, noblemen diſhonored, cities become waſte by baniſhment and bloodſhed: nay (which is more) virgins are deflowred, infants are taken out of their parents armes, and put to the ſword, matrons do ſuffer villanie, temples and houſes are ſpoyled, and euery place is full of armed men, of carcaſſes, of bloud, of teares. Secondly the opening of the cauſe hereof, which is nothing elſe but ambition, for out of this ſeed groweth a whole harueſt of euils. Thirdly the declaring of the remedie, which is by humble eſtimation of our ſelues, by liuing well, not by lurking well: by conuerſing in the light of the common weale with equals, not by complotting in darke conuenticles againſt ſuperiors: by contenting our ſelues with our lot, and not contending to our loſſe: by hoping without aſpiring, and by ſuffering without conſpiring. Let Rome in this hiſtory be a witneſſe, that a ſlipperie aſcending was alwaies accompanied

with a headlong diſcent, and that peace is a great deale better then triumph, which will be an occaſion I truſt to my countreymen of England to be thankfull to God for this ſweete quiet and ſerenitie of this flouriſhing eſtate, in which England now ſtandeth, wherein the day ſtriueth with the night whether ſhall be calmer: and let it mooue thee whoſoeuer thou art, courteous Reader, to pray with the earneſt endeuor of thy hart, that the Iris which is the pledge of our peace may ſtill ſhine amongſt vs, that the happie Virgin which is the ſtarre of ſafety in the Zodiacke of this common weale may continue immoueable, that our Halcyon may ſtill ſit in this Albion, on this white rocke to make the ſeas calme, and the waues ſilent, and to preſerue the league of heauen and earth, I meane true Religion amongſt vs. From my Chamber in Graies Inne 13. Octob. Anno Dom. 1600.
            
               Thine in all ſincere affection, WILLIAM FVLBECKE.
            
         
         
            
            A Table of the Romaine forenames written with one letter.
            
               A. Aulus.
               C. Caius.
               D. Decimus: for Decius it cannot be, becauſe that was the name of a familie, and in the monuments of the Greeke writers, it is written 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                      and not 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     
                  
               
               L. Lucius.
               M. M.' Marcus Manius.
               N. Numerius.
               P. Publius.
               Q. Quintus.
               T. Titus.
            
            
               Written with two letters.
               Ap. Appius.
               Cn. Cneus.
               Op. Opiter.
               Sp. Spurius.
               Ti. Tiberius.
            
            
               Written with three letters.
               Mam. Mamercus.
               Sex. Sextus.
               Ser. Seruius.
               Tul. Tullus.
            
         
         
            
            
               The names of the bookes and Authors out of which this hiſtorie was deriued.
            
               Appianus.
               Auguſtinus.
               Caſſiodorus.
               Caeſar.
               Cicero.
               Dio Nicoeus &amp; Dio Caſſius.
               Eutropius.
               Florus.
               Gellius.
               Gentilis Albericus.
               Hirtius.
               Iornandes.
               Ioſephus.
               Liber de viris illuſtribus.
               Liber antiquitatum Romanarum.
               Libri gentium &amp; familiarum Romanarum.
               Liuius.
               Lucanus.
               Manutius Paulus.
               Obſequeus.
               Oroſius.
               Plinius.
               Pedianus.
               Plutarchus.
               Saluſtius.
               Seneca.
               Sigonius.
               Strabo.
               Velleius
               Valerius Maximus.
               Zonaras.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            
            CLOTHO, Or the firſt booke.
            
            
               WHen vainglorious TarquineTarquin baniſhed. the laſt of the Romaine kings for the ſhamefull rape of Lucrece committed by one of his ſonnes, was baniſhed from Rome &amp; Conſuls ſucceeded, which as the name declares, had charge of prouiding for the cōmon ſafetie &amp; ſecuritie, the Romaines changed gold for braſſe, and loathing one king ſuffered manie tyrants, ſcourging their follie with their fall, and curing a feſtred ſore with a poiſoned plaiſter: for what could be more vniuſt, or more contrarie to the free eſtate of a citie, then to ſubiect the whole common weale to the rule of manie potentates, and to exclude the people from all right and intereſt in publique affaires? VVhat could be more abſurd then the

Senators onely to beſtow the Conſulſhip, the ſoueraigntie in warres, the ſupremacie in ſuperſtitious offices, according to their fancie and affection, to call Senates at their pleaſure, to conuocate aſſemblies when it ſeemed beſt for their owne profite, and to haue power of life and death vpon the bodies of their fellow citizens, &amp; the people to liue like their ſlaues, being barred and reſtrained from marrying with the daughter of anie Senatour, as if that pray had bene too high for ſo low a wing, and being held in ſuch diſdaine and diſreputation that common fellowſhip and mutuall ſocietie was denied them, which was indeede not to liue like free men in a citie, but like villaines and bondmen in a wainſcot priſon, and like ſillie birds in a golden cage: but when after long experience they had found, that winter ſucceeded ſommer, &amp; that the withered welfare of their citie could not be reuiued without ſome fortunate ſpring: to the intent that moderation might be induced, and that the meaner ſort might beare ſome ſtroke with the mightier, that the people might enioy the ſweete of the citie as well as the fathers, they

procured a new office entituled the Tribuneſhip, whereby they might protect themſelues as with a ſhield againſt the arrogant endeuors and outragious decrees of the Senatours, and thē the fellowſhip of mariage was brought in with the Senate, which before was prohibited the people, as if they had bene ſtained with ſome cōtagious iandiſe, or infected with ſome dangerous leproſie, and their ſuffrage was thē made neceſſarie to the election of officers, which before was as rare in that cōmon-weale as a white skin in Aethiopia. The people hauing thus erected their power, did by degrees more and more enhaunce it, till by many alterations it was turned from an Ariſtocracie, from the rule of them that were manie and mightie, to a plaine and viſible Democracie or eſtate popular, adminiſtred by the voyces of the multitude and magiſtrates, and by the vnited conſent of the whole corporatiō. Now when the people had by continuall incrochments aſſumed and ſeaſed into their handes the giuing and beſtowing of the greater offices, as the Conſulſhip, that ſtrong tower of the Senatous authoritie, and beſides that the

Dictatorſhip, the Cenſorſhip, the warlike Empire, the prieſtly dignitie, and many other moſt excellent honors, which before did ſolely belong to the Peeres of Rome, and now there wanted nothing to make their power equall, but onely that Plebiſcites, that is, decrees made by the people, ſhould binde the greater powers, as well as the people themſelues, frō which at that time the whole companie of the Nobles were exempted. Therefore to make them generall, and of like force againſt all, they wreſted from the fathers after much buſineſſe, the law Hortenſia, by which it was enacted that in euery important matter the people ſhould be equally intereſted with the Senate, and that the lawes ſo made and ratified by them, ſhould ſtretch as well to the Senators, as to the people themſelues. After that the common-weale was brought to this good and temperate conſtitution, many profitable lawes were eſtabliſhed, many victories followed, many cities bowed vnto them, manie monarchies ſued for their fauour, manie tyrants feared their puiſſance, &amp; manie countreys dreaded their inuaſion. Then there flouriſhed

in Rome moſt admirable examples of abſtinencie, modeſtie, iuſtice, fortitude, and which was the ſeale of their ſecuritie, an vniuerſall vnitie and agreement. Then the ſame of their Curij, their Coruncani, their Fabritij, their Metelli, their Fabij, their Marcelli, their Scipioes, their Pauli, their Lepidi, did ring in the world, whoſe great magnanimitie &amp; wiſedome in the tumult of warres, together with their ſingular temperance, and loyaltie in the calme of peace, is to be wondred at of all, and of all to be reuerenced. But when either the Senate or people did paſſe the liſts and limits of aequall regiment, the ancient and vertuous orders of the citie were immediatly troden vnder foote, and their good and laudable cuſtomes were encountred and put to flight by diſſolute and vnbridled enormities: then the Aſiaticall triumphs did incorporate into the citie a womaniſh wantonneſſe, then proude ambition mounted her plume of diſdaine vppon the top of the Capitolle, then their exceſſiue pride and iouiſſance for their victories had againſt Pyrrhus, for their cōqueſt of Carthage, for the ouerthrow of Philip, Perſeus,

Antiochus, mightie kings, for the winning of Spaine, Sicilie, Sardinia, Illyria, Macedonia and Greece, being as yet freſh in their memories, were as bellowes to puffe vp their ſwelling humours. Thē there ſucceeded a diſmall diſcord, which beginning when the eſtate was at the higheſt, did not end or expire, till it fell to the loweſt ebbe, ſticking faſt in the ſands of a grieuous deſolation. If a man will retroſpectiuely meaſure the ſpace of former times, &amp; the whole compaſſe of yeares, wherein the fortunes of the Romanes were by God his hand turned about, he ſhall finde that all the weight of their affaires, before the incohation of the Empire of Auguſtus, may be diſperſed into ſixe ages; wherof the firſt containing the number of fiftie yeares, was ſpent in the making of a towne; for that gorgeous ſeate which nowe we call Rome, was then but a plot ofRome built. ground, to which houſes were wanting, but afterward a great multitude of Latine &amp; Tuſcane ſhepheards, together with Phrygians &amp; Arcadians, flowing to that place, as to a temple reuerenced by pilgrims and trauellers, the common-weale was compacted of theſe ſeuerall

people, as a bodie of diuerſe elements. Romulus the founder of their citie &amp; empire, did delight wholly in mountaines, riuers, woods, mariſhes and waſtes, playing perhaps the eſpiall, to diſcouer and find out in what place it were beſt to erect a citie, and how to conuey things neceſſarie vnto it, and how to adorne it with continual increment and addition of demeiſnes; to ſuch imaginations the fields and places deſolate were moſt accordant, and to his ſauage ſocietie this practiſe of life was moſt acceptable.
            The ſecond age which chalengeth other fiftie yeares, did ingender in them working ſpirits and loftie cogitations, which eneagred and inflamed their mindes, againſt the confiners &amp; borderers: then it firſt began to beare the countenance and ſhape of a kingdome, which was after enlarged to the ſhore of the Midland and Adriaticke ſeas, which they rather vſed as bridges to other nations, then as bounders to their owne.
            The third age whoſe ſteps were an hundred and fiftie yeares, was the crowne and conſummation of their kingdome, in which whatſoeuer

was done was done by thē for the pompe, glorie and magnificence of that eſtate: as yet the Romane pride was in her blade, and in the tenderneſſe of her minoritie, this threefold age was ſpent vnder ſeuen kings, differing by fatall prouidence in the diſpoſition of their nature, as the frame and condition of that common-weale did eſpecially require: for who was euer more fierce and ardent then Romulus? Such a one they needed to inuadeRomulus eagreſt in ſight. the kingdomes of others. VVho more religious then Numa? Such the time did aske,Numa religious. that the furie of the people might be mitigated by the feare of God: VVherefore was Tullus that artificiall champion giuen vntoTullus an artificiall Captaine. them? That he might ſharpen their valour by his wit. VVherefore Aucus the great builder?Aucus a great builder That he might extend their citie with colonies, ioyne it together with bridges, enuiron it with walles. The ornaments; enſignes andTarquinius his ornamēts braueries of Tarquinius, did with rayes of dignitie illuſtrate and decore that eſtate. SeruiusSeruius taxeth the Romanes by polles. taxing them by polles, brought to paſſe that the Romane commō weale might know her riches. And the importune domination of

proud Tarquine did verie much profite, forProud Tarquine occaſioner of libertie. the people afflicted by iniuries, did force a paſſage to their libertie.
            The fourth age was as it were the youth of the Romane monarchie, when the flower of their proweſſe being greene, and the bloud of their mindes bloſſoming in their faces and armes, the ſhepheardly ſauageneſſe did as yet breathe foorth the reliques of an vndaunted ſtomacke. Then flouriſhed theſe Romane hazards, and miracles Cocles, Sceuola, Cloaetia, which chronicles do therefore witneſſe, that poſteritie may wonder. Then were the Tuſcanes repulſed and the Latines and Volſciās daily and deadly enemies, vanquiſhed by the triumphant husbandman L. Quintius Cincinnatus,The ſpeedie war of Cincinnatus. which war he ended within fifteene dayes, as if he had made haſt to returne to his tillage. Then were ouercome the Vientines, the Faliſcians, and the Fidenates: then the Galles a couragious nation, vſing their bodies for armour, in all reſpects ſo terrible, that they might ſeeme to be borne for the death of men, and deſtruction of cities, were vtterly vanquiſhed: then were ouercome the

Sabines and Samnites waſting and diſpoilingThe praiſe of Cāpania. the fields of Campania, being the goodlieſt plot, the Diamond-ſparke and the hony-ſpot of all Italie: there is no land more temperate for aire, for it hath a double ſpring-tide: no ſoile more fertile, and therfore it is called the combat of Bacchus &amp; Ceres, no region more hoſpitable in regard of the ſea, here be the noble hauens Caieta, Miſenus, &amp; the healthfull bathes Lucrine and Auerne, the reſting places of the ſea. Here the mountaines clad with vines Gaurus, Falernus, Maſſitus, and the firie hill Veſurius: here the famous citie Capua third ſiſter to Rome and Carthage doth imperiouſly ſtand. They begirt Samniū with warre and bloud on all ſides, till they had ruinated her verie ruines, and reuilled in her bowels, and twelue ſeuerall nations of Tuſcana waging hote and furious battell againſt them, in ſuch ſort and terrible maner, as if darts had bene throwne at the Romans from the coulds, were likewiſe ſuppreſſed. In this age happened the Tarentine warre, in whichPyrrhus fighting againſt the Romans. the armie of Pyrrhus continually ſlaying was continually ſlaine, and reuenge did liue in the

death of the Romanes: ſo that Pyrrhus did thinke him ſelfe to be borne vnder Hercules his ſtarre, who hauing cut off the ſeuen heads of Hydra, ſeuen other did ſpring vp. But from this Captaine the Romanes plucked ſuch ſpoiles, that neuer fairer were caried in triumph. For before this day nothing paſſed in triumph, but the heards of the Volſcian cattell, and the flocks of the Sabine ſheepe, the broken wagons of the Gaules, &amp; the cruſhed harneſſe of the Samnites: but in this triumph, if you reſpect the priſoners, they were Moloſſians, Theſſalians, Macedonians, Brutians, Apulians, Lucans: if you regard the pompe, it was gold, purple, curious pictures, tablets, and the delights of Tarentum. Next to this was the victorie of the Piſani and Salentini: this age ſhewed her force the ſpace of two hundred and fiftie yeares.
            Then followed the fifth age, in which the bodie of the common-weale grew to great ſtrength, the ioints and ſinewes being by mature ſoliditie ſetled in firme eſtate. Therefore the conquering nation hauing now attained to the verie manhood of manlineſſe, and diſplayed

her ſtanderd round about the ſides of Italie, to the skirts of the ſea, pawſed a litle, as a great ſcalefire, which conſuming all the woods and groues in the way that it goeth, is abrupted and put out of courſe by a floud cō
               ming betweene. But ſoone after ſeeing a rich pray on the other ſide of the ſea, ſuppoſing it to be a peece of gold pulled from her maſſe, they did ſo vehemently deſire the ſame, that becauſe it could not be ioyned vnto their dominion by bridges for the interruption of the ſea, therefore they reſolued to ioyne it by ſword and battell: and ſo was Sicilia ſubdued by the Romanes, which was the cauſe and originall of the firſt Carthaginian warre, which the warres of the Ligurians, Inſubrians and Illyrians did follow: and after the ſecond CarthaginianThe beginning of the ſecond Carthaginiā war. warre, ſo dangerous and bloudie to the Romanes, that if a man compare the loſſe of both nations, they which did conquer, were more like to perſons conquered. For it grieued that noble brood, and valiant people of Carthage to be abridged of the ſea, depriued of the Ilands, to pay tribute, and to vndergo not onely the bridle, but the yoke: to this age

muſt be aſcribed the circuit of one hundred yeares, which may be termed the golden age of the Romanes, &amp; the firſt age in which they ſhewing their ſtreamers on each ſide of the Ocean, did tranſport their warres into all nations of the world, in whoſe yeares the Romanes were honeſt, religious, iuſt, ſincere, vertuous, and dutifull.
            The ſixt age containing 120. yeares was troubleſome and vgly, bloudie &amp; deteſtable, vices growing with their Empire. For with the wars valiantly fought againſt Iugurtha, &amp; Mithridates, againſt the Carthaginians, Cimbrians, Parthians, Galles &amp; Germanes, by which the Romane glorie aſcended and pierced the skie, the ciuill ſlaughters of the Gracchi, and of Druſus, of Marius, Sylla and others were mingled and enterlarded: how mournefull a ſpectacle was it, that they fought the ſame time with fellowes in league, with fellowes in the citie, with bondmen, with fencers, all the Senate afterward contending and being in hurliburly with it ſelfe? Theſe times receiued of the other ages an exquiſite commō weale, as it were a curious picture, which after mildring

and decaying by age, they did not only neglect to renew, with the ſame colours, but they alſo forgot to preſerue the outwarde forme and lineaments thereof, for what remained of the auncient maners, which were both vnuſed and vnknowne: for by their recent vices they loſt the common-weale in fact, and in name retained it. How lamentable was the face of things at that inſtant? when euerie man confuſedly being found in the field, in the ſtreetes, in townes, in houſes, in highwaies, in markets, in temples, in beds, ſitting at the table or in the porch, was ſuddenly and ſauagely murdered? what howlings were there of them that died? what teares of them that liued, and beheld this? The cauſe of theſe miſeries was too great proſperitie. VVhat made the people ſo earneſt to extort the lawes of fields and corne, but verie famine procured by riot on the one part, and couetouſneſſe on the other? for ſuch was the lauiſh miſ-ſpending, &amp; exceſſiue vianding of ſome, that it can hardly be defined, whether more did periſh by the blade or by the banquet, and ſuch againe was the couetouſneſſe, &amp; greedie

exacting of others, that none can iudicially decide, whether the Romanes were more endamaged by the enemie in time of warre, or by the vſurer in peaceable ſeaſons. Hence grew the two ciuil broiles of the Gracchi, and that of Saturninus being the third, and that of Druſus being the fourth, who maintained the Senate againſt the Knights: and for the further abetting and auow of this quarell, he promiſed the freedome of the Citie to diuerſe Italians animated to this attempt, ſo that in one Citie there was as much diſcord as in two ſeuerallThe Italian warre. campes. This bred the Italian warre, becauſe promiſe was not perfourmed. AndMithridates an enemy to the Romans. next enſued the warre of Mithridates, ſeeing the Romans on each ſide intangled with garboiles, which preſently bred the enmitie betwixt Marius and Sylla, when Marius would haue deueſted Sylla of his Generalſhip giuenThe contention betwixt Marius and Sylla. him by the Senat for the oppugnation of Mithridates. Theſe two gaue Mithridates encoragement, by leauing the ribbes of the comweale naked and open vnto him, Marius led an armie, ambition led Marius: ambition I ſay ingendred by riches, did raiſe contention

betwixt them: from this the warre of Sertorius and Pompey had his originall, whereof the one was proſcribed by Sylla, the other protected. For Pompey was accompted Syllaes minion or fauorite, whom he therefore called Magnus, that himſelfe might ſeeme greater, being the Saint whom Pompey ſerued. Sylla was cruell in reuenging crueltie, and his medicine was worſe then the maladie itſelfe. This ſtirred the diſſention of LepidusThe diſſention of Lepidus and Catulus. and Catulus, whereof the one would haue ratified, the other reuerſed, all the acts of Sylla. Then Catiline whom his luſt occaſioned byCatilines rebellion. Syllaes indulgence brought to beggerie, oppoſed himſelfe to the Conſuls. Then PompeyPompeyes great dignity in Rome. entred the liſts, as a follower of Sylla, who obtained excellent dignitie in theſe times, but ciuill, and ſuch as the regular courſe of that common-weale did affoord, whoſe power &amp; authoritie Caeſar could not tollerate, becauſeCaeſar cānot brooke it. he could not match it: which notwithſtanding he being ouercome and ſlaine, Caeſar paſſed and tranſcended. But when this vſurper had bleached the floore of the Senate houſe with his owne bloud, who before had ouerflowed

and deluged the whole world, with the crimſon goare of moſt admirable men, the common-weale did ſeeme to haue rolled herſelfe into the ſtate of her priſtinate libertie, and it had returned vnto the ſame, if either Pompey had not left ſonnes, or Caeſar had not made an heire, or, which was worſe, if Antonius the thunder-dart of furie had not ſuruiued, being once colleague with Caeſar in the Conſulſhip, now ſucceſſor of his vſurpation. But while Pompeys ſonne ſtriueth for the honor of the name, the ſea ratleth with armour: whileſt Octauius reuēgeth the death of his adoptiue father, Theſſalie is againe made the baſis of tents and pauillions, and all Europe and Affricke groneth vnder the weight of iron, whileſt Antonius in the habit of his mind diuerſe and diſcoloured, doth either diſdaine Octauius or doate vpon Cleopatra, whoſe beautie if he could haue exceeded by his chaſtitie, his ſhame ſhould not haue blazed like a beacon at this day in the eyes of poſteritie, but he had won the garlād of cōqueſt, not meriting more then triumph. The armie of Octauius hauing ſlaine Pompeis ſonne, did in him ſlay enmity,

and Caſſius being ouercome by fight, Brutus by deſpaire, they did extirpate faction. Yet Antonius not chalenging part with anie, but principalitie ouer all, imagining that he wanted no kingly thing ſaue onely a kingdome, remained as a rocke or gulfe in the mouth of the hauē, whom he with ſome labor ſubdued. And, as in the yearely conuerſion of the heauens, it commeth to paſſe, that the ſtarres iogged together do murmure and threaten tempeſt, ſo with the alteration of the Romane ſtate, before Octauius founded his Monarchie, the whole globe of the earth with ciuill and forraine warre, with fight on ſea and land was terribly ſhaken. But the accidents and occurrences of theſe laſt hundred and twentie yeares, in the ſequele of this hiſtorie ſhall be, if God fauour theſe lines, more particularly &amp; diſtinctly reported. The firſt that made theThe valor of the former Scipio. Romanes mightie was the former Scipio that ſcourged Affrica with continuall warres and vexations, and in the end ſubdued it: the firſt that made them wanton and effeminate, was the later Scipio, by whom Carthage was ſubuerted,The proweſſe of the later Scipio. yet not by his fault, but by the caſualty

of the time. For when the riuall and enuious ielouſie of the Carthaginian glory, was by hisThe Romans made 
                     〈◊〉
                   by proſperity matchleſſe victorie finally determined, the Romanes did ſodainly degenerate, and with an hungrie gorge fed on the poiſonfull baites of bitter ſweete ambition, following wantons like wilde horſes, and addicted to pleaſure as their onely paragon, the auncient gouernement of the Citie was vtterly forſaken, the watchings of the campe were ended vpon beds of downe, their heauie armour was turned to light and faſhionable attire, and the wonted buſineſſe of the Citie was chaunged into idleneſſe. Then did Scipio Naſica build porches in the Capitolle, then did Metellus threaten the heauēs with haughtie buildings, thē did Cn. Octauius erect a moſt ſumptuous forefront, &amp; then did the riot of the Cōmons imitate the magnificence of the nobles. In the middeſt of this delicate iolitie, when the Romanes were now in the ruffe of their pride, a grieuous and deſpitefull warre was raiſed in Spaine by Viriathus of Luſitania, a notableViriathus an enemy to the Romanes. theefe &amp; ringleader to a multitude of rogues, which hong a long time in ſuſpence: but in the

end when Viriathus was ſlaine, rather by the couine then courage of Seruilius Caepio, a greater danger enſued, namely the warre of the Numantines. The citie of Numantia didThe Numantine warre. neuer affoord armour to any more, then ten thouſand citizens at one battell; but either through the fierceneſſe of their nature, or the default of the Romane captaines, or the indulgence of fortune, they brought PompeyPompey enforced to ſtrange leagues by the Numantines. the firſt of the Pompeys that was Conſull, a mā of note &amp; fame to moſt ſhameful leagues, &amp; Mancinus Hoſtilius, to a deteſtable truce, which vpon a remorce of minde, and change of opinion, againſt the law of Armes, and to the great diſcredit of the Romanes, he afterward broke: but Pompey eſcaped vnpuniſhed by fauour, Mancinus was puniſhed by ſhame.The puniſhment of Mā
                  cinus for breaking truce. For he was caried and tranſported by the Romane Heraulds vnto the Numantines, his hands being manacled, and ſo was deliuered vp into the enemies power, whom they refuſed to receiue, ſaying that a publique breach of promiſe was not to be puniſhed by the bloud of one man. This yeelding vp of Mancinus into the enemies hands, did cauſe in the

citie a perillous and pernitious diſſenſion.The parents of Ti. Gracchus. For Ti. Gracchus the ſonne of the right noble man Ti. Gracchus, whoſe mother was the daughter of Scipio Affricanus, by whoſe meanes and authority that reprochful league was made, taking it grieuouſly that any thing which he did ſhould be diſcountenanced, and fearing himſelfe the danger either of the like puniſhment or of the like iudgement, being at that time Tribune of the people, in life innocent,The praiſe of Ti. Gracchus in wit pregnant, and in purpoſe guiltleſſe: and furthermore adorned with ſo great vertues, as either nature could affoord, or induſtrie could perfect, or mans frailtie could containe. P. Mutius Scaeuola, and L. CalphurniusGracchus ſwarueth frō vertue. being Conſuls fell from vertue to vice, and extreme villanie: and hauing promiſed vpon a diſſolute fancie, that he would enfranchiſe and receiue into the Citie anie Italian whoſoeuer, turned all things into a contrarie ſtate, mingled vertues with vice, lawes with luſt, and brought the common-weale into an headlong and hideous danger. Octauius his fellow in office, who ſtood againſt him for theA Treuirate firſt made in Rome. cōmon good, he put from his place, &amp; created

a new ſtate in Rome entitled a Treuirate or Triarchie, that is the rule of three men, who were called Treuiri, himſelf for one, his father in law Appius who had bin Cōſul for anotherThe familie of Scipio Naſica. and C. Gracchus his brother for the third. At that time flouriſhed P. Scipio Naſica, nephew to him, who was iudged of the Senate in his life time to be the beſt of the Romanes, ſonne to that Scipio who purchaſed great praiſe for his good demeanor in the Cenſorſhip, nephew two degrees remoued to Cn. Scipio a man highly commended, vncle to Scipio Aemilianus whoſe commendation lieth in his name: this Scipio Naſica thogh he were nearly linked in kindred to Tiberius Gracchus, yet preferring his countrey before his kindred, thinking nothing priuately cōmodiousScipio Naſica oppoſeth himſelfe to Gracchus. which was not publikly conuenient, ſtanding in the higher part of the Capitolle, exhorted all the Romanes, which deſired the ſafetie of the common-weale, to follow him, vpō which words the Nobles, the Senate, and the greater and better part of the Romane knights did runne ſuddenly vpon Gracchus, ſtanding in the floore of the Capitolle with his adherēts,

and euen then conſpiring with a frequent aſſemblie of new-come Italians, he thereupon flying and running downe the hil whereupon the Capitolle was founded, his head being cruſhed as he was running downe, with a fragment of one of the boordes which was in theTi. Gracchus ſlaine. Senate houſe, did ſodainly end his life, which he might haue enioyed with great honor and quietneſſe.
            This broile and hapleſſe diſſention was the firſt conſpiracy in which ciuil bloud was ſhed, and the firſt diſpenſation of drawing ſwordes within the walles: after that time right was oppreſſed by violence, and the mightier man was accompted the better, the quarels of citizens that were wont to be cured by compromiſe and agreement, were now decided by ſword and bloudſhed, and warres were not followed according to the goodneſſe of the cauſe, but according to the greatneſſe of the pray. But it was no maruell, though this ſmall beginning had ſo great effect, and this odious faction ſo vnfortunate conſequence, for examples do not pawſe there where they begin, but being once receiued into a narrow ſtrait,

they make way to themſelues, raunging and ſpreading themſelues ouer the bodie of the world, and when men go once aſtray, they mind not how farre they go, thinking that nothing can procure diſhoneſtie to them, which hath brought profite to others.
            VVhileſt theſe things were done in Italie, Scipio Affricanus of the houſe of Aemilius, who deſtroyed Carthage, after many ſlaughters of his enemies in the Numantine warre, being nowe againe made Conſull, was ſent backe into Spaine, where his courage andScipio is ſent into Spaine. ſucceſſe did match and aequall his valure and fortune in Affricke, and within a yeare and three moneths after his comming thither, heScipio taketh Numantia. tooke Numantia, and cauſed euerie ſtone to be throwne to the ground, as a notable monument of a Romane victorie. There was neuer anie man of anie name or nation, that by the ſacking of cities did more aeterniſe his houſe or enlarge his glorie: for hauing rooted vp Carthage, he deliuered the Romanes from feare, and hauing razed Numantia, he deliuered them from reproch. Being returned into the Citie within a ſhort time, after

two Conſulſhips, two victories, and two notable triumphs, he was found dead in his bed,Scipio found dead in his bed. his iaw bone being diſſolued and diſlocated. There was no inquiſition made afterward of the death of this inuincible Captaine: the bodie of Scipio was brought out into the ſtreeteScipios body is brought out into the ſtreetes. his head couered, by whoſe great labours and warlike exploits, Rome lifted vp her head ouer all the world, to the terrour and diſmay of other cities and countreys. His death was, as the moſt ſay fatall, as ſome ſay conſpired: his life doubtleſſe was of that ſingularitie, that it was ouercome of no mans glorie, but onely his grandfathers.
            After the death of Ti. Gracchus, the ſameC. Gracchus a rebell to the ſtate. fury and rage of mind that poſſeſt him, entred as it were by a kind of tranſmutation into his brother C. Gracchus, a man as like to Tiberius in his vertues as in his errour, who when with great facilitie and eaſe of mind he might haue bene the Prince of the Citie and the ruler of the Senate, tooke the Tribuneſhip vpon him to raiſe tumults, to licence ſwords, and to reuiue diſcord, to no other intent or purpoſe but either to reuenge his brothers death, or

purchaſe to himſelfe a ſoueraigntie, and for the more haſtie purſuing of his drift, he beſtowed the freedome of the Citie vpon euery inhabitant of Italy: he interdicted and forbad by Tribunitial law, that no citizen ſhould poſſeſſe more then fiue hundred akers of land, he erected new hauens, he filled the prouincesThe ſeditious acts of C. Gracchus. with new colonies, he transferred the authoritie of iudgement frō the Senate to the Nobles, he determined to diſtribute and deuide corne amongſt the people: to be briefe, he left almoſt nothing vnaltered or vndiſturbed. This man was ſlaine by the ſharpe and haſtie purſuite of L. Opimius Conſull who was in armes againſt him, and Fuluius Flaccus wasFul. Flaccus a rebellious Senatour ſlaine. likewiſe ſlaine, one that had enioyed both the Conſulſhip and the honor of Triumph, a man of a deteſtable meaning, whom C. Gracchus had denominated and deſigned to be one of the Treuiri in the place of Tiberius his brother, being his aſſociate in all his enterpriſes, and defiled with the like diſhoneſt intendment. Opimius cauſed proclamation to beOpimius his proclamatiō
                made, that whoſoeuer could bring vnto him the head of Gracchus, ſhould haue the weight

of the head in gold. Flaccus inciting his ſoldiers on the hill Auentine, was there ſlaine, together with his eldeſt ſonne. C. Gracchus cō
               mitting himſelfe to flight leſt he might fall into the hands of them whō Opimius had ſent to take him, putting his bare necke vnder theC Gracchus beheaded. naked ſword of his ſeruant Euporus, was of him beheaded: and the ſame Euporus was ſuddenly a ſlaughter-man to himſelfe. Thus the two Gracchi finiſhed the courſe of their life, men that had a fortunate beginning, ſiniſter proceedings, &amp; a curſed ending, to whom if they had embraced quietneſſe, the commō
               weale wold haue offered theſe honors, which by tumult and diſquietneſſe they ſought, their mother Cornelia as yet liuing, a vertuous andCornelia lamenteth her children. learned Ladie; who hauing nurtured and trained them vp in the ſtudie of learning and vertuous demeanour, did greatly bewaile, that her good endeuors had ſo bad ſucceſſe, and that her two ſonnes, whom nature praetended to be the ſolace of her age, were ſo ſodainely and ſhamefully diſgraced, that ſhe could not ſee their bodies couered with earth, they being in moſt deſpitefull maner throwne into

Tiber, whoſe mindes ſhe had furniſhed and beautified with ſuch excellēt learning, ſo was her ioy ouercome and ſurpriſed with griefe, that ſhe muſt either loath her children, or elſe lament for them, but howſoeuer, for euer lacke them.
            In that tract of time C. Marius waging battaile in Numidia againſt Iugurtha, who were both fellow ſouldiers and managed armes together vnder Scipio Affricanus, ſent L. Sylla his Quaeſtor to Boc
                  •
               hus the King of theC. Marius taketh Iugurtha by Sylla his meanes. Mores, to treate and capitulate with him about the taking of Iugurth, whom by that meane he enioyed, and being made the ſecond time Conſull, in the beginning of his Conſulſhip and in the Calends of Ianuary, he brought Iugurth in triumph to Rome. The Cimbrians &amp; Teutons at that time did cauſe great ſlaughter and manie maſſacres of the Romanes in France, and hauing put to flight and diſcomfited Caepio, Manlius, Carbo, and Silanus, they killed in fight Scaurus Aurelius one of the Conſuls, and other excellent men of memorable qualities. The people of Rome did not thinke anie Generall ſo fit to encounter

theſe foes as C. Marius: &amp; whileſt he was in theſe warres, he was continually Conſull, his third Conſulſhip he ſpent in warlike preparation,C. Marius his third Conſulſhip. thinking it not ſufficient to haue ſouldiers, but to haue practiſed and skilfull ſouldiers, training them by pettie skirmiſhes, and encouraging thē by the conqueſt of baſe townes, to more haughtie and valorous attempts: his fourth Conſulſhip was ſpent aboutHis fourth Conſulſhip. the warres of Sextus, where he fought with the Teutons: and before that warre finiſhed, he razed out of the world the whole progenie of the Teutons. In his fifth ConſulſhipHis fifth Cō
                  ſulſhip. he planted his fight betwixt the Alpes and Rome, and in that battell Marius him ſelf being Conſull, and Q. Catulus Proconſul, a fortunate victorie enſued, farre beyond the expectationMarius his great victorie which he had againſt the Cimbrians. of the Romanes, and the admiration of ſtrangers, an hundred thouſand men being brought into the power of the Romans wherof ſome were ſlaine &amp; ſome were ſlaues. By this victorie Marius deſerued, that Rome ſhould not repent her ſelfe of his birth, nor requite his acts with reproch. His ſixth ConſulſhipC. Marius his ſixth Conſulſhip. was giuē him as the crowne of his merits,

yet he is not to be defrauded of the glorie, which during this Conſulſhip did of right belong vnto him, euen by the confeſſion of the enuious. Marius being the ſixt time Conſul,Saturninus a broacher of ſedition. Saturninus one of the Tribunes of the people, did promulgate a lawe, that what lands or demeſnes Marius had gained in France by his expulſion of the Cimbrians from thence, ſhould be equally parted &amp; deuided amongſt the people of Rome, and that euery Senator ſhould ſweare to this, thinking to bind them by their oath from diſpoſſeſſing and diſſeiſing the people of theſe alotmēts and purparties. Q. Metellus a Senator, againſt whom SaturninusQ. Metellus oppoſeth himſelfe againſt Saturninus. had a burning ſtomacke, denied to ratifie that lawe by oath, wherupon he had day giuen him to appeare before the Senate. ForMarius fauoureth the lawe of Saturninus. Marius being wholly addicted to pleaſe the people in all things, which did not oppugne his owne profite, did greatly fauour the law. Metellus though he were ſupported in this action by many good and vertuous citizens,Metellus cō
                  mitteth himſelfe to voluntarie baniſhment. yet fearing ſome bloudſhed in the citie by maintaining that cauſe, committed himſelfe to voluntarie exile, and ſhortly after water &amp;

fire was forbidden him, which was the title &amp; ſtile of the baniſhment vſed in Rome. This Saturninus was afterward made the third time Tribune, and becauſe he feared that C. Memmius, who at that time ſued for the Cō
               ſulſhip, would with maine force oppoſe himſelfe to his actions and enterpriſes, he gatheredSaturninus cauſeth C. Memmius to be ſlaine. a garriſon of ſouldiers, and cauſed him to be ſlaine. Marius preſently rowzing himſelfe for the puniſhmēt and reuenge of this proud Tribune, and by Senate-councell authoriſed, charged his bodie with harneſſe, and with a troupe of warlike citizens beſieged the Capitoll,C. Marius beſiegeth the Capitol. which Saturninus and the Praetor Glancias, together with Saufeius the Quaeſtor his adherents did hold as the caſtle of their defence. But Marius cutting in peeces the conduit pipes, enforced them to yeeld, and toC. Marius putteth the conſpirators to death. ſubmit themſelues promiſing thē life, liuing, and libertie; but when he had them in his power, he made hauocke of them all leauing notSaturninus his houſe deſtroyed by Marius. one aliue; the houſe of Saturninus he razed from the loweſt foundation. VVhen the conſpiracie of Saturninus was appeaſed, there began of freſh a new quarell betwixt the Senators

an
                  •
                M. Liuius Druſus a noble Gentleman, eloquent and modeſt, nature being as bountifull vnto him, as fortune was iniurious; he had alwayes a great deſire to reſtore the former honor to the Senate, and to transferre the iudiciall power from the Nobles: for they being poſſeſt of that authoritie by the law of C. Gracchus, which is aboue mentioned, did practiſe extreme and brutiſh crueltie vppon manie excellent Senators and guiltleſſe Citizens, and amongſt the reſt was ſlaine P. Rutilius, a man in that age incomparable: yet the fortune of Druſus was ſuch, that he was croſſedThe hard fortune of Druſus. and confronted by the Senate, in thoſe matters which he moued for the good &amp; behoofe of the Senate, they either not perceiuing, or not willing to perceiue, that though the petitions which Druſus made as Tribune, and as of dutie he ought, ſounded and indeed tended to the profite of the people, yet his drift to be this, that the people hauing leſſer things graunted them, might permit greater to the Senate, that ſo giuing them a litle the reyne, they might enioy the fruite of libertie, but yet might eaſily be plucked in if there

were anie feare of diſorder: which was the onely meane to preſerue the dignitie of the Senate, and to reſtraine the humours of the people, but the eyes of the Senators were ſo dazeled with enuie toward Druſus, with enmitie toward the people, and ſelfe-loue toward their owne perſons, that they did more allow the pernitious practiſes of the other Tribunes, then the dutifull meaning of Druſus: deſpiſing the reuerence wherwith Druſus did alwayes honour them, and yet digeſting the iniuries wherwith his fellow Tribunes did moleſt them: which vniuſt and abſurd dealing did euidently proceed from the gall of their enuie. Then this good Tribune hauing his mind ſurcharged with malcontentment, ſeeing that his honeſt purpoſe was maliciouſly peruerted, lacking patiēce to beare his griefe, and conſtancie to perſeuere in his commendable intents, reſolued ſodainly in a deſperat paſſion to maintaine the faction of the Gracchi, to entertaine into his heart rebellion, to ſwarue from vertue, to proſtrate himſelfe to the violence of fortune, and being garded with a great multitude of vnknowne ſoldiers,

who were ſeditious Italians, whom Druſus laboured to make free-men of the Eſtate, he thought to terrifie the citie, but within a ſhort time he was ſlaine in his owne porch, his ſideDruſus is ſlaine. being pierced with a knife, which ſheathed in his entrailes, and was left there ſticking and filling the mouth of the wound, but when he yeelded vp to the heauens his vitall ſpirit, caſting his eyes vpon the companie that ſtoode about him, &amp; lamenting that diſmall chance, he breathed out theſe words at the laſt inſtant and with the ſurrender of his ſoule: Tell me my friends and kinsfolke, may the common-weale at any time enioy a more faithfull citizen, then I haue heretofore bene? This ende of life had that noble Gentleman, who if he had bene armed with patience, might haue triumphed ouer enuy. Caius Marius was nowC. Marius in high reputation. become the refuge and defender both of Senate and people: he was of bodie hardfauored, in maners rigorous, famous for warre, &amp; odious in peace, vnſatiable in ambitious deſires, impatient in his wrath, and alwayes attempting ſome ſtrange noueltie: he did not long after valiantly endeuor to ſuppreſſe the

flames and perillous ſcalefire of the Italian warre, which becauſe it was moſt dangerouſly begun and continued, &amp; with great difficultie quenched and ended, I thinke it not amiſſe to make full deſcription thereof, laying for my foundation the cauſe which moued the Italians or Latines to reuolt from the Romans, and to breake their faith before conſtantly kept. But the cauſes of things are ſo ſecret &amp; miſticall, being the moſt remote obiects, to which our vnderſtanding may aſpire, that we may eaſily be deceiued by diſguiſed and pretenced reaſons, whileſt we ſeeke for the true and eſſential cauſes. For to report things that be done it is eaſie, becauſe the eye and the tongue may diſpatch it, but to diſcouer and vnfold the cauſes of things, requireth braine, ſoule, and the beſt proweſſe of mans nature, wherefore to find out the cauſes of this warre, diligence muſt be vſed. This warre is of diuerſe men diuerſly named, ſome terme it the Italian, ſome the Marſian, ſome the Sociall war: all which haue ſufficient reaſon to make good their ſeuerall appellations. The Italian warre it was tearmed, becauſe it was raiſed by

ſuch Italians, as were in league with the Romanes, which was the occaſion of the entercourſe of manie good turnes and benefits betwixt them and the Romanes: for though they did not inioy the liberties of the city of Rome in ſuch large and ample maner, as the citizens or free men of that Citie, yet they poſſeſſed them in farre greater meaſure, then others which were meere ſtraungers to that Eſtate, and that by the law of ſocietie, which to the Romanes was alwayes ſacred and inuiolate: this warre therfore vpon their reuolt was termed Sociale, as maintained by them who had contracted &amp; eſtabliſhed a league of ſocietie. The Marſian war it was called, becauſe the firſtThe Italian warre firſt attempted by the Marſians commotion was attempted by the Marſians, a free people of Italie. The cauſe &amp; the beginning of this war do in time greatly differ, for the cauſe hath a retroſpect to the firſt times of the Romane monarchie, when the people of Italie being greatly infeſted and endamaged by the continuall inuaſions of the Romanes, did watch oportunitie, and with ſerious expectation attended, if by anie poſſible meanes they might requite the Romanes with the

like, and recouer their auncient rights and iuriſdictions, and at one inſtant breake both the league and ſhake off the feare which they then had of the Romanes, and which was the laſt marke of their enterpriſe, rather cōmaund then condition with the Romanes. But as there is no euill without excuſe, and no praetence without ſome colour of reaſon, and no wiles can be wanting to malicious &amp; wrangling wits, therefore an occaſion was ſought for, whereby peace might be diſſolued, and diſcord warranted. Here now appeareth the error wherein Druſus was intangled. For they made him an inſtrument or lure to draw vnto them the free vſe of the Romane liberties, which in truth they did neither greatly deſire, not ſtrongly hope for, but they looked for a repulſe, and thought that would be a good occaſion to ground their tumults vpon, and as it were a vaile for their leud endeuours: whereby it is euident that as the cauſe of this warre is ancient, ſo the beginning thereof isThe repulſe of Druſus the beginning of the Italian warre. to be referred to the repulſe of Druſus, which happened ſixe hundred ſixtie and two yeares after the building of Rome. Theſe commotioners

of Italie had this purpoſe and intent, at their feſtiual meetings to ioyne their heads and hands together, and ſo to proceed to the Citie, there to worke the death of the two Conſuls Sex. Iulius Caeſar, and Martius Philippus: but this matter being diſcouered, they did preſently put to death Seruilius Proconſull,Seruilius Proconſull ſlaine by the cōmotioners of Italie. who was ſent vnto them at the firſt beginning of their ſtirres, by peaceable &amp; reaſonable meanes to appeaſe and determine them, and all the other Romanes which were at Aſculum, were ſlaine. This bloudie deed being reported at Rome, did greatly plunge the minds of the Romanes in doubt and ſorrow. For this ſlaughter was as it were an Adamant to draw the other Italians, who did not conſpire in this murther to their part, and as a firy beacon to the Romanes, to giue them warning not to preſcribe too much in their proſperitie, but to be circumſpect, &amp; by all warie preuention to anticipate theſe euils, which if it ſhould haue bene neglected of them, would preſently haue turned to ſuch a cloud of inconueniences, that the fire which did before ſerue to giue light, would after haue bent his

force to burne and conſume: for the next neighbour to admonition is correction, and it is eaſier to auoide then to eſcape a danger. But the Romanes with prouident care foreſeeing that the defection and reuolt of them who were linked in ſocietie with them, might be a great maime to their Eſtate, &amp; as it were a ladder for forreine and profeſſed enemies to ſcale the walles of their Citie, did therefore in this war make ſpeciall choiſe, both of Captaines and ſouldiers: for meane men were not to be employed in a warre of ſo great importance, and they that were vnskilfull, were not in the midſt of theſe eminent dangers, to be trained and taught. And becauſe they ſaw that the commodious ending and compoſing of this war, was the hinge whereupon the whole eſtate of the Common-weale did depende; therefore it was decreed by Senate, that both the Conſuls (a rare thing in that Commonweale, and neuer done but when exceeding daunger was feared) ſhould go in perſon to the managing of this warre. Neither were the Italiās vnprouided or vnaduiſed: for they knew, that if they were cōquered, they ſhould

fall from the eſtate of fellowes to be ſlaues, &amp; their league ſhould neuer more be truſted, which them ſelues had broken: and if they ſhould enioy the victorie, that they ſhould then haue all the wealth of the world at commaund. This golden bootie being enameld with a ſweete deſire of reuenging old iniuries (for they had written them in marble with a pen of yron) did greatly incenſe their minds, and rauiſh their ſpirits with a burning affectiō to fight. The Marſians who brought the firſt ſtubble to kindle this flame, were gouerned by Silo Popedius, a man as it ſeemed by deſtinySilo Popedius a naturall enemy to the Romans. oppoſed againſt the Romanes, to whoſe eares nothing was ſo delightfull as the report of a Romanes death, hating that hower in which he did not impeach their good eſtate. He in this reſpect was diuerſe from manie of his countrimen, in that he deteſted a Romane becauſe he was a Romane. VVherefore hauing ſingled out ſome of his factiō, who were partly by the inſtinct of their nature, partly by his inſtigation, obdurate and eager in hatred againſt the Romanes, hauing propoſed and ſhewed vnto them the ſcope and drifte

whereunto his purpoſe did aime, and hauing diſcloſed the meanes, whereby he hoped to compaſſe and effect his deſignements, and laſtly hauing declared vnto them the rewards which they might gaine by their valor, he did labour by this ſpeech to inflame their furie, I am moued and enforced to this new enterpriſe,Silo Popedius his oration to the Marſians. not by anie ambitious deſire of enhauncing my eſtate, but becauſe I ſee a poiſonful baite of deceit hidden vnder the pretence of Societie, becauſe I ſee too great charges &amp; burdens to be impoſed vpon vs, becauſe I ſee leud forreiners to be our commaunders, and originarie Italians, though men of good deſert, kept vnder the ſnaffle, and placed in the ſinke-hole. I ſee the credite of our nation defaced, the libertie deſtroyed, and the ſtate ouerthrowne, and for our great labours vndertaken, and dangers ſuſtained for the Romans, we haue this reward, that we are deſpiſed by them, and they haue not thought it ſufficient to be aided by vs, vnleſſe in the pride of their ſpirits they may inſult vpon our neckes, men of inſolent mindes, by nature iniurious to all other men and by fortune ſuperiour. If a man

ſhould examine from the beginning, and as they ſay from the roote, the degrees of their eſtate, what iuſtice ſhall he find? nay what iniuſtice ſhall he not find? The two twinnes whoRomulus &amp; Remus baſtards. were the founders of their city, were baſtards, begotten by the rape of a holy virgin, and by deſtinie were caſt foorth as of no regard, vntill a ſhe-wolfe feeling perhaps ſome ſauourNouriſhed by a wolfe. of her owne nature in them, did with her dugs nouriſh them. After, when from milke they were growne to meate, they were fedde by a chough, and when they had attained to mans eſtate, nothing would pleaſe then but a kingdome, &amp; a regall citie, the foundation wherof was ſolemnized by an augurie deriued from the flight of Eagles. Thus a moſt rauenous bird did ominate vnto them a monarchy, thus a moſt greedie beaſt whoſe hungry teeth, and vnſatiable appetite no pray could content, did giue them milke, thus a moſt theeuiſh and buſie brained birde was their foſter-father. Theſe were the portents and ſignes of their Citie, that it ſhould be a daughter verie like to the parents: theſe did prognoſticate vnto vs the ſpoiles, rapines, inuaſions and violent

incrochments that ſhould afterward be made by the Romanes. And for that cauſe Romulus wold not make or appoint limits and bounds for his kingdome, that he might by force enter into euery ſoile as his own. But what wold not Romulus do, which had the heart to ſhedRemus is ſlaine by Romulus. the bloud of his owne and onely brother? And thus was their citie cōſecrated by bloud: but ſome of the Romanes do with impudencie denie this fact, ſome with modeſtie do doubt of it, ſome with griefe do conceale it, and they which by cleare proofe are enforced to confeſſe it, do with this imagination mollifie the fault, that it was done by the conſent but not by the hand of Romulus. But whether he commaunded it, or committed it, he was a murtherer. After this hainous crime enſued the rape of the Sabine virgins, the rauiſhmentThe rape of the Sabine virgins. of whom they excuſe, becauſe they would not yeeld their franke conſent to mariage: ſurely they cannot iuſtly be reproued, if they, being a noble people, did denie mariage to ſuch a baſe aſſemblie of ſhepheards, heardſmen and hoggards, newly crept out of the ſtraw: for in that great aſſemblie of newe vpſtartes there

were but an hundred men, who were lawfully begotten, and theſe forſooth were at the firſt made Senators. But nothing doth more bewray the vniuſt dealing and lacke of conſcience in the Romanes, then the lamentable eſtate of the Saguntines, who had bin alwayes verie conſtant in fellowſhip and friendſhip toward them, and whileſt they did keep their faith to them, they loſt their Citie. Saguntus was fiercely beſieged by Hanniball, which when the Romanes heard, they ſent preſentlyThe Romane embaſſadors are deſpiſed of Hā
                     nibal. Embaſſadours to Hannibal to dehort him frō the ſiege, but being deſpiſed they went to Carthage, and there framed a complaint againſt Hannibal, pretending that he had broken the league, but failing of their purpoſe, they returned to Rome. Amids theſe delaies, that poore citie within eight or nine moneths after the laying of ſiege was deſtroied of the Carthaginians, when the inhabitāts were beforeThe miſerable famin of the Sagūtines. conſumed with famine, and one of them did eate anothers carkaſſe, and being wearie of the world, becauſe they ſhould not come as captiues into the enemies power, they made a common fire, into which, when one of

them had ſlaine another with the ſword, they were throwne. How manifeſt and manifold is the abuſe which they offred to the Carthaginians? They did incite Maſiniſſa the neighbour of the Carthaginians to quarrell withMaſiniſſa quarelleth with the Carthaginians. them, who praetended that the Carthaginiās ought to haue no more land then Dido the Tyrian queene did enioy, which was as much as could be meaſured by the hide of an Oxe being cut into thongs. But could their preſcription &amp; poſſeſſion during the ſpace of ſeauen hundred yeares be ſo eaſily diſſipated? by the ſame reaſon the Romanes ſhould content thē
                  ſelues with the cottages and cabbins, which firſt they inhabited. But the Carthaginians being greatly vexed by Maſiniſſa and the Romanes aſſiſting him, did fall proſtrate at the feete of the Romanes, and did grieuouſly cō
                  plaine of the intollerable couetouſneſſe and pride of Maſiniſſa, and requeſted with teares, that of three things they might obtaine one: namely, that either they might equally debate the whole cauſe and conrrouerſie before the regents of ſome common-weale leagued in ſocietie with them both, and indifferently

affected toward them, or that they would ſuffer them to defend thēſelues by iuſt warre againſt the vniuſt armes of Maſiniſſa, or laſtly, if fauour did more preuaile with them then truth, that they would once determine and certainly ſet downe, what and how much they ſhould yeeld to Maſiniſſa. But the Romanes did not one whit helpe theſe afflicted perſons, and that good Affricanus, whom they ſoScipio ſent as vmpier betwixt Maſiniſſa &amp; the Carthaginiās. much commended, being ſent as an indifferent vmpire betwixt them and their enemie, did make their diſcord a great deale more: and the deſolate Carthaginians, when they were enforced to prouide for thēſelues, were accuſed at Rome for the breach of league, and hereupon they were declared to be enemies. They had ſtraite commandemēt from the Romans to reſtore the Romane hoſtages, to deliuer their money and treaſure into the hands of the Romanes, and by that meane to purchaſe the ſafetie of their Citie: all this was done. VVell this was not enough: the Romanes muſt haue their ſhips, their munition and weapons: they deliuered theſe likewiſe: yet this ſuffiſed not: the Romanes

muſt haue their Citie, and the Carthaginians muſt build ſome other Citie farre from this: this was graunted vnto them, and CarthageThe Citie of Carthage burnt. the faireſt Citie of all Affricke was by them preſently burnt, and turned euen with the ground. Here when the Romanes were preſſed and vrged with their promiſe, their anſwer was, that in ſpeaking of the ſafetie of the Citie, they did meane the ſafetie of the citizens and inhabitants, not of the Citie which did conſiſt of ſtone and timber: O ſnares! ô impoſtures! ô ſophiſtrie! can the Romans without bluſhing obiect perfidiouſneſſe and trecherie to the Carthaginians? Surely as they dealt with them being leagued in ancient ſocietie with them, ſo I am afraid they wil deale with vs. And I do the rather ſuſpect it, becauſe I ſee they will ſtil haue a difference betweene them ſelues and vs. Herein lieth a myſterie, I will not ſay of the Punicke fraude, but of the Romane arte. And when it pleaſeth them to drawe the curtaine, we ſhall be made their ſlaues, and our goods their dearling. VVherfore I requeſt you all with all the vehemencie and force of my minde, that you would with

one heart contend for the recouerie &amp; defence of liberty, and that you would at length aime at ſuch a common-weale, wherein right and law, not the priuate will of powerful men may beare ſway. To the which purpoſe I know all the other people of Italie ioyned in league and fellowſhip with vs, will affoord the diligent aſſiſtance of their perſons, and the beſt wealth of their treaſuries. As for me, ſuch hath my birth, ſuch hath my education bene, that I preferre the dignitie of my countrey, and the libertie of this common-weale before all things in the world. VVhich if you do ſo deſirouſly embrace, I am fully reſolued to lay my life open to all dangers, without anie regard of eſtate or priuate reſpect: if not, I will lay downe weapons, and leaue the eſtate of the common-wealth as it now ſtandeth, to your owne diſcretion.
            
            The Marſians hearing the name of liberty, did greedily receiue it, and therefore applauding to Popedius, as informing them of that which was moſt for their vſe, becauſe there appeared in his ſpeech no ſignes of couetouſneſſe or ambition, but an earneſt and vehement

deſire of publique good, did reſolue to follow him as their generall.
            They had no ſooner ſet vp flagge of defiance againſt the Romanes, but there reſorted vnto them a huge multitude of all the prouinces of Italie: ſo readie are diſloyall perſons to caſt off the yoke of obedience, or common ſocietie, when they haue gotten a head. The metamorphoſis truly was verie great, to ſee the Citie of Rome enuironed on all ſides by foes, which before was garded by friends, &amp; there was none almoſt left to defend the City but the citizens, and nothing to defend the citizens but the Citie. The people that reuolted were the Marſians, the Samnites, the Vmbrians, the Veſtini, the Irpini, the Lucani, the Marruſini, the Aſculani, the Peligni, the Piſani: and they were led by great Captaines, men of valour and ſeruice, hauing as great deſire to fight with the Romanes, as the Romanes had to rule ouer them. The moſt of them were of ſo choiſe courage and conduction, that the Romanes had before in many warres relyed vpon their ſeruice. But yet the name of a Romane was ſuch a ſcepter to their ſpirits, that

they were ſtill kept in awe and order without anie thought of reuolting. Theſe men were now quite altered, as if they had lately bene at ſome mart of ſoules, and had exchaunged their mindes with ſome men by nature enraged againſt the Romanes: and it is greatly to be wondred how the mightie power of the diuine Maieſtie, doth ſway the moments of things, and ſorteth them in peremptorie maner to ſtraunge and vnlooked for effects, making reaſon blind, pollicie aſtoniſhed, ſtrēgth feeble, and valour daſtardly, turning loue into hatred, feare into furie, boldneſſe into trembling, and in the circuite of one minute making the conquered perſon a conqueror. The Romanes did not in anie warre ſhewe more wiſedome and courage, which two things are in common vnderſtanding repugnant, becauſe wiſedome for the moſt part procureth feare in dangerous accidents, which is oppoſite to courage, and courage cauſeth raſhneſſe which is contrarie to wiſedome. But ſo were their fortunes croſſed, &amp; the lot of warre was ſo variable, that this warre was reſolutely vndertaken of them, vnhappily continued, and

victoriouſly concluded. The Romane armie had two Generals: namely P. Rutilius one of the Conſuls, whoſe Lieutenants were Cn. Pō
               peius Strabo, Q. Caepio, C. Perperna, C. Marius, Valerius Meſſalla: and L. Caeſar the other Conſul, who had theſe Lieutenants, P. Lentulus, T. Didius, P. Licinius Craſſus, L. Cornelius Sylla, M. Marcellus, all famous Captains, men of excellent deſert and heroicall qualities, and the moſt of them fit not onely to manage a warre, but a kingdom, yea an Empire: yet of all theſe none did obtaine the victorie during the firſt yeare of their fight, C. Marius and L. Caeſar onely excepted, yet Caeſar was not long before with his whole armie diſcomfited, and Marius did with great difficultie atchieue one victorie, which was the beginning of a greater warre. The Conſuls did thus diſpoſe the encounters of themſelues and their Lieutenants, L. Caeſar was oppoſed to Vettius Cato, who led a wing of the Marſian armie, but Caeſar being ouer mated by a man of greater wiſedome and magnanimitie, was enforced to flie, and after the ſlaughter of two thouſand of his men, being hotely purſued &amp;

enchaſed of the enemie, was conſtrained (for neceſſitie will affoord no choiſe) to take Aeſernia for his refuge. C. Perperna did encounterC. Perperna diſcharged of his Lieutenancie. P. Praeſenteius, who put him likewiſe to flight, &amp; deueſted him of his armie, for which cauſe he was diſcharged of his Lieutenancie, and now was C. Marius ſought vnto by the Conſuls, to whom he yeelded ſuch aſſiſtance, that he rather ſeemed to be their protectour then their champion. P. Rutilius to reuenge the death of Q. Caepio, who was ſlaine by theQ Caepio ſlaine. ambuſh of Popedius, and the quarrell of his fellow Conſul, vpon the Marſians, did aſſay them by battell, but loſt a great number ofP. Rutilius ſlaine. men, &amp; in the end loſt himſelfe, being ſlaughtered in the midſt of his enemies. C. Marius with a freſh courage renewed the fight, &amp; putC. Marius putteth Vettius Cato to flight. to flight with extreme labor Vettius Cato the fatall enemie to both the Conſuls. But the meſſenger who brought the newes of this victorie of Marius to the Romane campe, did meete there another meſſenger, who reported vnto them, that Egualius one of the enemies campe had ſurpriſed Venafrum a towne of great ſtrength: that M. Lamponius another

of their enemies had ſlaine eight hundred of the armie of P. Licinnius Craſſus, and had put the reſidue to flight, that C. Papius Mutilus their enemie, had brought Nola a flouriſhing Colonie of the Romanes into his power, together with Q. Poſthumius their Praetor, that he had alſo taken Stauia, Minturna and Salernum, and did nowe beſiege Acerra a chiefe towne. Theſe newes ſucceeding the other did make the Romanes to heare with ioy, and to remember with ſorow. But no better fortune did enſue: for M. Marcellus being aſſigned for the defence of Aeſernia was taken priſoner by the Samnites, who ſurpriſed that Colonie. Cn. Pompeius was by three Captaines of the aduerſe part, Iudacilius, Aefranius, and Ventidius fiercely encountring, driuen to the village of Firmo, and there beſieged. L. Caeſar had a proſperous victorie againſt the Samnites, but C. Marius fighting againſt the MarſiansC. Marius fought equally againſt the Marſians. with doubtfull euent, did recompence the death of euerie enemie with the loſſe of his owne ſouldiers: ſo conſtant is the fortune of warre in inconſtancie. Now was come the ſecond yeare of this daungerous warre, which

continued old broiles, and made new Conſuls Cn. Pompeius Strabo, L. Portius Cato, both which were by the decree of the Senate enioyned to take vpon them the charge of this warre. They brought ſome new Lieutenants in the place of ſome that were dead, and ſome that were diſcharged. The ſucceeding Lieutenants were A. Albinius, Coſconius, Luceius, A. Gabinius, Sulpitius, L. Muraena, Caecilius Pius, Mamercus Aemilius. It ſeemeth that Rome in theſe dayes was a verie ſchoole of warfare, which did yeeld the ſupply of ſuch excellent Captaines, after the departure of Captaines not much more excellent. C. MariusC. Marius diſliked by the Conſul Portius. vpon a diſliking conceiued by the Conſul Portius (priuate humor is alwayes an enemie to publike good) was diſcharged of his place. But ſo it happened, that the Romanes changed their fortune with their Conſuls, but the Italians were more daunted and diſanimated by the continuance of the warre, then encouraged by the increaſe of their victories. For a baſe ſpirit cannot ioy in any honorable matter, &amp; nothing more deuoureth the heart of a rebellious or trecherous perſon, then the

inward fire of a glowing conſcience. L. SyllaSyllaes victore againſt the Sānites. had a notable victorie againſt the Samnites, and did ranſacke their tents. Cn. PompeiusCn. Pomp. Strabo his victories. did conſtraine the Veſtini, the Peliani, and the Aeſculani, and the Piſani to yeeld vnto him. Sylla did kil Cluentius a Captaine of the contrarieSylla killeth Cluentius. part at Nola, and he brought vnder his power the Irpini. A. Gabinius did fight proſperouſlyA. Gabinius after a proſperous fight is ſlaine. againſt the Lucani, and tooke many of their great townes, but when he wold haue ſpoiled their tents, he was ſlaine. Sulpitius hauing ſlaine all the ſouldiers of the Marrucini,Sulpitius bringeth the Marrucini to obedience. did reduce that whole region into the ſubiection of the Romanes. L. Muraena and Caecilius Pius had manie encounters againſt the Marſians, and in the ende enforced them to yeeld, but Popedius their Captaine the authorPopedius is ſlaine. of this warre was ſlaine in fight, in which war Portius Cato was alſo ſlaine, not throughPortius Cato ſlaine. his owne default, nor by the valor of his enemies, but through the malicious ſtomacke of the ſonne of C. Marius, who in reuenge of his fathers quarell, did throw his dart at him, and with a deadly wound did make him fall proſtrate to the ground: but becauſe he could

not be diſcerned in ſuch confuſion of fight, &amp; in the heate of the battell, he was not impeached for this trecherous murder. The Romans hauing enioyed and accompliſhed all things according to their deſire, returned with the great ioy and gratulation of their fellow citizens.Ca. Pōpeius Strabo triumpheth. Cn. Pompeius, for his ample victories &amp; great deſert was rewarded with a triumph. Thus was the Italian warre being left to the Romanes as the legacie of Druſus ended and appeaſed, which wrought two notable effects: for it brought the Italians from ſocietie to ſeruitude, and refuſing the bridle they receiued the yoke, and were euer after kept vnder the chaine of perpetuall commaund, but the Romanes it made glorious and inuincible: for their iuſt warres had alwayes good ſucceſſe, and their vniuſt warres or inuaſions, could not (as may partly appeare by this Italiā vprore) by forraine warre be reuenged. But for the cauſe hereof let no man make ſearch or inquirie, ſith it is no where to be foūd ſaue only in God his decretall booke, the contents whereof as I cannot know, ſo the comments of man in this matter I may not beleeue. This

thing therefore as vailed with vtmoſt darkeneſſe, I do with all humbleneſſe leaue to him who hath reſerued it to himſelfe: &amp; this onely I obſerue, which euerie man may note in the ſequele of this hiſtorie, that the Romans were puniſhed by the Romanes for their wrongs &amp; iniuries (if I may vſe coniecture in ſo thicke a miſt) done to their neighbours and others. Not long after the death of Druſus the Conſulſhip inueſted vpon Q. Pompeius &amp; L. CorneliusSylla is made Conſul. Sylla, who before his victory could not be too highly commended, and after neuer ſufficiently diſpraiſed: ſo contrarie and oppoſite he was to himſelfe, being more mercifull in the combat, then after the conqueſt, and Sylla fighting in the field was not ſo cruell asSylla his cō
                  trary nature Sylla triumphing in the towne. He was noblyHis diſcent. deſcended, being the ſixth man from Cornelius Rufinus, who was one of the chiefe Captaines in the warre againſt Pyrrhus. For the glorie and credite of that familie had bene long intermitted, and was almoſt periſhed, till it was raiſed and rampired vp by Sylla to the ancient grace, and reſtored with an ouerplus to the former dignitie. Sylla did a long

time behaue him ſelfe ſo modeſtly and contentedly, that he ſeemed to be without all intent for ſuing for the Conſulſhip, but after his Praetorſhip being much renowned by the Italian warre, &amp; for his great exploits in France, hauing ſlaine the ſtouteſt Captains of the aduerſe part, he tooke ſtomacke by reaſon of his good ſucceſſe, and making ſute for the Conſulſhip, was made Conſull, not one citizen almoſt withdrawing his conſent, and that honour he purchaſed when he was eight and fortie yeares olde. At that time MithridatesMithridates an enemy to the Romans. king of Pontus, a ſharpe and victorious ſouldier, being ſometime great in proſperitie, and at all times great in courage, in counſell wiſe, in ſtrength mightie, in hatred againſt the Romanes another Hannibal, had taken and poſſeſt Aſia, where he put to death all the Romanes that did there inhabite: the region of Aſia did by lot happē to Sylla as his prouince, he addreſſing him ſelfe thitherward with as great ſpeed as he could poſſibly make, came at length to Nola, which he beſieged, for thatSylla beſiegeth Nola. Citie did moſt ſtubburnly reſiſt the Romans, reuolting from that faithfulneſſe which the

Nolanes did religiouſly obſerue and exhibite to the Romanes in the Carthaginian warres: but not long after the laying of this ſiege, he was abridged of his Generalſhip by SulpitiusSulpitius a ſeditious Tribune altereth the ſtate a Tribune, who being in wealth, fauor, friendſhip, wit, and courage great amongſt the Romanes, hauing before ſought dignitie by deſert, did now by his leud decrees and diſloyall practiſes deſerue to looſe his dignitie. He aſſigned to C. Marius an imperiall praeheminence, &amp; the regimēt of all the prouinces that belonged to the citie of Rome, which honors as Marius did ambitiouſly deſire, ſo SulpitiusThe ambitiō of Marius. did iniuriouſly diſpoſe: and therewithall he enacted that Sylla ſhould be called from Aſia, and Marius ſhould be Generall in his place; manie other pernitious lawes he eſtabliſhed, both intollerable and deteſtable: for concluſion, he ended in murther, procuring by hisMurder committed by Sulpitius. bloud-thirſty ſeruants the death of one of the Pompeys, ſonne to Q. Pompeius, and Syllaes ſonne in lawe. Sylla hearing of this ſodaine change, and being ſolicited by the letters of his deareſt friends, made ſpeedie returne to the Citie, which hauing taken by force of

armes he droue out of it the twelue authoursSyllaes reuenge vpon the ſeditious of this newe and damnable faction, amongſt whom was C. Marius and his ſonne, together with P. Sulpitius the firſt beginner of diſcord, Sulpitius being taken by Syllaes horſemen in the Laurentine fennes was there beheaded, &amp; for the guerdon of his cruelty, his head being afterward conueyed to Rome, was erected vpon a pinnacle ouer the barre of the Senate houſe. C. Marius (a cleare mirrour of this worlds vnconſtancie) to whom if you will place him amongſt the fortunate, you muſt aſſigne the higheſt ſeate, if amongſt the vnfortunate, the loweſt, hauing before enioyed all pleaſures which proſperitie could yeeld, and now ſuffering all troubles which aduerſitie could bring) after his ſixth conſulſhip, and the ſixtieth yeare of his age, for the auoyding of Syllaes horſemen, ſtripped himſelfe naked, &amp;The extreme miſerie of C. Marius. flying to a marriſh of reedes did there hide himſelfe, plunging ſo deepely into the mud, that nothing could be ſeene of him but his eyes and noſtrels, who being afterward deſcried, was drawne by a thong of leather tied to his neck, into the priſon of Minturna. There

was ſent to kil him a captiue ſlaue, whom MariusA captiue ſlaue ſent to kill Marius. had taken priſoner in the battel which he fought againſt the Cimbrians: this bloudie Cimbrian aſſaying to ſtrike Marius, was ſodainly amazed, and terrified by the maieſtie of his countenance, though Marius was then full of yeares, full of miſerie, and void of weapons: but the ſlaue ſeeing ſo bright a ſtarre in ſo darke a dungeon, reuerencing the man whom he had before feared, and perſwading himſelfe that it was impoſſible for one man to worke his death, who not long before had almoſt deſtroyed the whole nation of the Cimbrians, left him aliue, and in trembling maner departed from his preſence. The Minturnians becauſe they held the worthineſſe of Marius in high reputation, deliuered him out of priſon, and attiring him with conuenient apparell,The Minturniās friends to Marius. beſtowing vpon him a pilgrims viande, which might for a ſeaſon relieue his hunger, diſmiſſed him out of their Citie. He hauing ouertaken his ſonne at Aemaria, directed his voyage vnto Affricke, where he led a poore and wretched life in the ruines and deſolate rēnants of the Citie of Carthage. Sylla leuied

an armie &amp; renewed his iourney toward Aſia, (the yeare wherein Sylla was Conſull, was the firſt yeare in which the Romane ſouldiers did ſlay their Conſull; for then Q. Pompeius beingQ Pompeius ſlaine. fellow Conſull with Sylla, was ſlaine by the ſeditious armie of Cn. Pompeius Proconſull.) After the broiles of Marius and Sulpitius the tumults of Cinna ſucceeded, who was not one iote more temperate then thoſe diſorderlyCinna beginneth a new broyle. and enormous quarellers, or rather furious and traiterous conſpirers. He was Cō
               ſull with Cn. Octauius, who becauſe one of them namely Cinna, fauoured Marius, and the other Sylla, fell to a ſodaine iarre, &amp; maintaining ſeuerall armies in the Citie, cauſed much terror, and ſome bloudſhed. Cinna wasCinna is expulſed the City. expulſed the Citie by the power of Octauius and the Senators, his Conſulſhip was abrogated, and in his place L. Cornelius Merula, Iupiters prieſt was elected. Cinna hauing corrupted the Centurions, Tribunes &amp; ſouldiersCinna is made Captaine of a ſeditious army. with hope of liberalitie, was admitted of that armie (which was as yet about Nola) for their Captaine, and hauing ſworne all his ſouldiers to obeiſance and loyaltie, he marched in his

Conſul robes toward Rome, his armie conſiſting of three hūdred bands of good ſouldiers amounting in the view of ſpials to the number of thirtie legions: but though he had manie ſouldiers and much courage, he lacked notwithſtanding factioners and fauourites to vphold him, and was deſtitute of popular credit, which might bolſter and ſupport his doings. For ſupplying of which want, he called from baniſhment C. Marius and his ſonne, with allCinna calleth C. Marius and his ſonne from baniſhment. the other Romanes which were before by Syllaes horſemen chaſed out of the Citie. VVhileſt Cinna was thus preparing warre againſt his mother towne, Cn. Pompeius father to that great ſtate, of whom we ſhall hereafter ſpeake, whoſe worthie actes in the Marſian warre, together with his victorie at Aſculum, was verie beneficiall and commodious to the common-weale, being fruſtrate of hope to continue the Proconſulſhip, ſhewed himſelfeCn. Pompeius father to Pompey the great his diſſembling and vnconſtancy. verie indifferent and equall to the factions, doing all things for his proper and priuate good, and lying in waite for oportunitie to ſerue his owne turne and aduancement, enclining his armie this way and that way, now as a

fauourer to Cinna, &amp; now as a friend to Sylla, following fortune by coniectures, and determining to ioyne with him, who by all likelihood ſhould be moſt puiſſant: at length heA great fight betwixt Cinna and Cn. Pōpeius encountred with Cinna before the citie wals, where after a maine ſea of bloudſhed, the Romanes that were vpon the walles, beholding the ſlaughter of their brethren, friends and kinſfolke vnder the wals, the battell was fully finiſhed, but the victorie was doubtfull. Not long after Cn. Pōpeius died, by whoſe death the ſouldiers of Cinna conceiued ſo great ioy and gladſomneſſe, that they forgat the finall ouerthrow of their fellow ſouldiers, and the Romans did beſtow their reuenge vpō Pompey being dead, which they did owe to him being aliue. Cinna and Marius did not without great hauocke of men and matrons inuadeCinna entreth the city the citie: but Cinna entred firſt, and publiſhed a lawe touching the receiuing of Marius, then C. Marius entred the wals with aC. Marius recalled frō baniſhment, entreth the citie. moſt fatall and daungerous returne to the citie of Rome. Nothing had bene more bloudie then his entrance, if his death had not ſhortly enſued: for hauing poſſeſſed the citie,

he was more vnſatiate in his crueltie then any rauenous tiger, and more mercileſſe in his tragicall puniſhments, then any furie, breathing nothing but bloud, and delighting in nothing but murder, neither did the licentious rage of his wrath content it ſelfe with the bloud of meaner men, but it ſeiſed vpon the ſtates and ſtarres of the citie. Then did Octauius one ofOctauius put to death by the crueltie of Marius the Conſuls, a man of a mild &amp; douelike humor, render vp his life into the pawes of theſe wolues: and Merula, who a little before the returne of Cinna had through feare renounced the Conſulſhip, cut in peeces his owneMerula cutteth in peeces his owne veines. veines, and ſprinkling his lukewarme bloud vpon the altar, vpon which he had often ſacrificed the bloud of beaſts, and intreating the gods for the execratiō of Cinna, to whom he had often prayed for the preſeruation of the citie, gaue vp his fainting ghoſt in a greatM Antonius the Oratour put to death by Marius &amp; Cinna. agonie of mind. M. Antonius the chiefe of the citie, and the Phaenix of eloquence, was ſlain at the commaundement of Marius and Cinna, by the ſwords of their ſouldiers, whome by the ſweetneſſe of his eloquence he did a longtime reſtraine and delay from the killing

of him. Q. Catulus a man famous for his vertuesQ. Catulus cauſe of his owne death. and valour in the Cimbrian warre, the glorie of which he did participate with Marius, as we haue aboue reported, when he was hunted to death by theſe greedie bloudhounds, ſhut himſelf into a narrow cloſet that was newly pargited with lime, and hauing there a fire of burning coales, which might raiſe vp a ſudden dampe, ſtopping his breath with a vaporous and darkiſh ſmoke, departed this world, rather according to his owne wiſh then his enemies will: then were the ſtreetes, channels, theaters, market places, and temples ſtrewed and ouerſpread with carcaſſes, ſo that it could hardly be iudged, whether theſe two tyrants did ſlay more that they might obtaine the victorie, or more were put to the ſword that they might ſafely enioy the victorie. For euerie one to whome Marius would not reach out his hand by way of ſalutation, was immediatly ſlaine. The common weale was now in a tottering and ruinous eſtate: couetouſneſſe was the cauſe of crueltie, and the more wealthie a man was, the more faultie he was iudged: the accuſer of a rich man had his

pay and reward out of the coffers of him that was accuſed: and then was profite and honeſtie confounded and made one. Afterward Cinna and Marius were Conſuls, Cinna was now the ſecond time Conſul, Marius the ſeuenthC. Marius dieth. time, who in that conſulſhip died, a Romane in war terrible to his enemies, in peace to his friends, and at all times impatient of quietneſſe: in his place was choſen Valerius Flaccus. Cinna being now the ſole regent of Italie, the greateſt part of the Nobilitie fled to Sylla into Achaia, who in the meane time did ſo fight with Mithridates his Lieutenants and Coronels about Athens, Macedonia, and Beotia, that he tooke Athens, and made great hauocke of his enemies. But if any impute the rebellion of theſe times vnto the citie ofThe Athenians faithfull to the Romanes. Athens, he is altogether ignorant of the truth. For the faith of the Athenians was alwaies ſo firme and inuiolate towards the Romanes, that euery action which was performed without blemiſh or ſtaine of promiſe, was ſaid to be done by an Athenian faith: but they being heauily oppreſſed by the vnſufferable vſage of Mithridates his hoſt, were beſieged of their

friends, when they were held captiue of their enemies, and obaying neceſſitie ſtayed their bodies within the wals, though their minds were without, and entirely with the Romans. Sylla did then conduct his armie into Aſia, where he found Mithridates very tractable &amp;Silla his hard conditions of peace cō
                  cluded with Mithridates. ſuppliant vnto him whome he puniſhed with the paiment of a great ſumme of mony, and with the loſſe of part of his nauie, enioyning him to depart out of Aſia, and out of all the prouinces which he had vniuſtly inuaded, and conſtraining him to content himſelfe with the inheritance diſcended from his father, which was the kingdome of Pontus: he tooke from Mithridates the Romane priſoners without ranſome, and vſed great ſeueritie againſt the traiterous reuolts, and runagates. Sylla hauing thus appeaſed and qualified forraine affaires, went by ſea toward Rome, and in the way met him certaine ambaſſadours from theThe king of Parthia ſendeth Ambaſſadours to Sylla. Parthian king, which were ſent to gratulate his victorie, he being the firſt of the Romanes to whome the king of Parthia ſent ambaſſadours. There was nothing more worthie among Syllaes labours, then that whole three

yeares ſpace, whilſt the factioners of Cinna &amp; Marius did beſiege the townes of Italie, he neither pretended any fauour toward them, neither did he omit that which he had in hād, namely the ſubduing and vanquiſhing of forraine enemies: for he knew when external tumults were ended, he might with more eaſe extinguiſh domeſticall enemies. Before the comming of Sylla, Cinna in a mutinie of his owne ſouldiers was ſlaine, a captaine moreCinna is ſlaine. worthie to be adiudged to death by the diſcretion of the conquerour, then to looſe his life through the furie of his ſouldiers, of whom it may truly be ſaid, that he aduentured thoſe things which no vertuous man wold attempt, &amp; that he brought thoſe things to paſſe, which none but a valiant ſouldier could accompliſh. His fellow Cōſul Carbo hauing no colleague did now praedominate and beare ſway. SyllaSylla paſſeth quietly thorough Italie. hauing entred Italie, it was thought he came not as a reuenger of warre, but as an authour of peace, with ſuch quietneſſe and mildneſſe he lead his armie through Calabria and Apulia, with a great &amp; ſpeciall regard of the growing corne, of meddowes, of men, of caſtles,

and cities, and indeed he aſſayed by lawfull articles, and equall conditions, to appeaſe the diſcord, but peace could not pleaſe them which were immoderatly couetous. Sillaes army did daily increaſe, euery good and diſcrete Italian making recourſe vnto him, and he had a moſt happy victory about Capua againſt Scipio and Norbanus Conſuls, Norbanus being ouercome by fight, Scipio being forſaken of his army, yet Sylla gaue him leaue to depart, without hurt or hinderance, ſo vnlike was he to himſelfe in his warres, and after his victory, for whilſt the victorie was freſh, he was more mild then equitie required, but when peace had taken roote, he was more cruell then any barbarous Scythian, for Q. Sertorious the fury and firebrandSylla diſmiſſeth Sertorious without hurt. of that rebellious warre, which not long after enſued, being diſarmed by Sylla, was ſent away in ſafety, and many others he did with the ſame clemency intreate: of purpoſe, as I thinke, that he might giue an example of a double and diuerſe mind in one man, and by that meane ſhroud and couer the contents of his heart. At that time to fill vp the meaſure

of publike miſhap, in the city of Rome, where before men did emulate one another in vertuous actions, now they did combate and contend in malicious practiſes, &amp; he thought himſelfe the beſt man, that was moſt wicked and iniurious. Sylla had three mighty aduerſaries, Carbo, and C. Marius, the ſonne of Marius that was the ſeauenth time Conſull, which both were Conſuls whilſt Sylla rong an allarme at the gates of Preneſte, and Pontius Teleſinus, who leuying an army of the Samnites, did ſtoutly confront Sylla before the walles of Preneſte, he was an Italian borne, but was not free of the city of Rome, a valiant ſouldier and a great enemy to a Romane name, who ſtood in defence of Preneſte, but not with the Conſuls. This Teleſinus conductingSilla fighteth with Teleſinus a Samnite. forty thouſand fighting men ioyned battell with Sylla at Collina, and brought both him and the commō-weale to extreame danger: for Rome was not in greater feare, when the tents of Hanniball were but three miles diſtant from her walles. Teleſinus did greatly encourage his ſouldiers, ſaying that the day of their battell was the laſt period of

the Romane glorie, and he cried that Rome, Rome muſt be throwne downe, and razed frō the foundations, adding therewithall that there wold▪ neuer be wanting inuadors of the Italian liberties, as long as the wood ſtoode where ſuch wolues were harboured. At the firſt houre of the night the Romane armie reuiued their courage, Teleſinus the next day after was found halfe dead, bearing the countenance rather of a conqueror then of a man ſubdued, whoſe head being cut off Sylla cō
               maunded to be caried along the ſtreetes ofC. Marius the younger is ſlaine by Syllaes ſoul diers. Preneſte. C. Marius, his life being in a deſperate caſe, was faine to creepe through certaine holes of the earth to eſcape his enemies, but he was ſlaine of Syllaes ſouldiers that were appointed for that purpoſe, of which towardly gentleman, what opinion Sylla caried, a man may eaſily coniecture: for when he was ſlaine he intitled himſelfe Sylla the fortunate, which had indeed bene true if he had endedSylla vſurpeth the Dictatorſhip. his life with his victories. For hauing entred the citie and vſurped the Dictatorſhip, which had bene an hundred and twentie yeares intermitted, (for the laſt Dictator before Sylla

was made the firſt yeare after Hannibals departure out of Italie, ſo that it was apparant, that the Romanes did not ſo much deſire the vſe of a Dictator, as they did feare his tyrannie) he began preſently to broach the bloud of citizens, hauing alreadie drawne to the bottome the bloud of ſtraungers: foure legions of ſouldiers, who had bene of the contrarie faction, and had now vpon couenant of life ſubmitted themſelues to his mercie, calling in vaine vpon the faith of a Romaine ſoldier, he cauſed to be ſlaine: fiue thouſand of that armie which fought againſt him at Preneſte,Silla cauſeth the ſouldiers of Preneſte to be ſlaine. being promiſed life by P. Cethegus his Lieutenant, he put to a ſudden and vnlooked for death, and cauſed their ioynts to be plucked in peeces, and commaunded that they ſhould be diſperſed and caſt abrode in the waſtes and mores. After theſe great and extreme cruelties, he put in practiſe the heauie penaltie of proſcription, which if it had diedProſcription put in practiſe by Sylla with Sylla, would haue beene a great part of the Romane happineſſe: by that meanes he brought to paſſe, that whoſe names ſoeuer he writ in the table of proſcription, ſhould be

vpon their attachemēt preſently put to death, their goods alſo were ſubiect to ſale, euery one taking the benefit to whome Sylla would graunt it: neither was he content to rage againſt them onely which had before oppoſed themſelues to him, but the moſt quiet and innocent citizens for the greatneſſe of their wealth he depriued alſo of life, and againſt ſilly women did he bend his wrath, as not ſatisfied with the death of men: and, which was a ſigne of a Thracian crueltie, as ſoone as the heads of the ſlaine citizens were parted from their trembling corſes, breathing as yet, their faces being not wholly depriued of a vitall bloud, he did gaze vpon them, and toſſe thē in his hands that he mightfeed on them with his eyes, though he could not cruſh them with his teeth. VVith what ſauageneſſe did he behaueM. Marius ſlain by Silla. himſelfe in the killing of M. Marius, whoſe eyes were pluckt out before his death, and euery part of his bodie was ſundred and diſioynted: and at that inſtant he enforced hisSylla his rage againſt M. Pletorius. ſword through the bowels of M. Pletorius, becauſe he ſeemed to be grieued with the torture of M. Marius. O extreme puniſher of pittie

and compaſſion, to whome it ſeemed a crime not to conſent to crueltie. Neither didThe aſhes of C. Marius thrown into a riuer by Sylla. he ſpare the dead, for the aſhes of C. Marius the elder he cauſed to be raked out of the graue and throwne into a riuer. Sylla whileſt he ſought the victorie, was to the Romanes a Scipio, whilſt he vſed it a very Mithridates. Many other bloudſheds he did commit, and more would he haue committed, had not the terrour of a guiltie conſcience followed him, with the blazing brand of his vexed ſoule, which torment ſome cal an ecſtaſie, ſome melancholie, ſome madneſſe, but I denying it to be any one of theſe, allow it to be all theſe, doubtleſſe it is a thing ſooner felt thē known, not to be auoided by medicine but by true felicitie. In this perplexitie he died, and yetSylla dyeth. ceaſſed not the ciuill or rather vnciuil and vnbrotherly diſcord: thus was Rome the famous citie of Europe, the mother and nurce of worthie Senators, the miracle of nations, the epitomie of the world, the kingdome of Mars, and the ſeauenheaded ſoueraigne of many prouinces exceedingly ſhaken with theſe quarrels, ſtained with theſe bloudſheds, and

grieuouſly diſcomforted with the death of her children, her babes were brought foorth for the ſword to glut vpon, the bodies of her ancients were made as pauements to walk vpō, her matrons became a pray and prize to euery rauiſher, her prieſts and deuoute ſacrificers were ſlaine before the gates of the temples. Syllaes bodie was conueied in ſumptuous manner to Campus Martius, in which place before the buriall the two Conſuls, namely M. Aemilius Lepidus, and Q. Luctatius CatulusDebate betwixt Lepidus and Catulus Conſuls touching the decrees of Sylla. did earneſtly debate about the repealing and cancelling of the acts and decrees of Sylla. Lepidus vrged that they who were proſcribed by Sylla, ought incontinent to be reduced to the citie, and there to haue reſtitution of their goods. Catulus together with the Senate defended the contrarie, ſaying that though his motion were good and honeſt, yet it might be the beginning of ſome tumult, which would be moſt daungerous if it were ſuddenly done, becauſe the common-weale was but newly recomforted, and had as yet enioyed but a ſhort pauſe of tranquilitie. By this diſſention they fell to weapons, Cn. Pō
               peius

and Q. Catulus hauing gathered an armieCn. Pompeius Magnus and Q. Catulus fight with Lepidus and ouercame him. did proffer battell to Lepidus, and in a light skirmiſh ouercame him. Not long before the death of Sylla, Q. Sertorius riſing in armes maintained warre in Spaine: for when he ſaw that the faction of Marius which he ſpecially fauoured, was vtterly defeated and diſſipated by L. Sylla, he fled preſently into Spaine, where before he had bene Pretor, &amp; there hauing gathered a great hoſt and contriuedSertorius leuieth armies in Spaine. an huge nauie, fearing leſt Sylla, who had put Carbo to flight and ſlaine Marius, ſhould ſend an armie againſt him, he cauſedLiuius Salinator the Lieutenant of Sertorius ſlaine. Liuius Salinator his Lieutenant to encampe in the mountaines of Pyraeneum, but he was afterward ſlaine by C. Anius the Romane Proconſul, who was ſent thither to abate the courage of Sertorius, and after him Q. Metellus was alſo ſent, but their proceedings were not proſperous. VVherefore Cn. Pompeius being as yet a priuate man, had charge giuen him of the Senate to go into Spaine. There came at that time for the aide and aſſiſtance of Sertorius, M. Perperna with a great multitude of ſouldiers. Cn. Pompeius made

way for himſelfe through the Alpes, betwixt the famous ſprings of Padus and Rhodanus. He immediatly after his coming into Spain, did enter into conflict with two of Sertorius his captaines, Herennius and Perperna, and not farre from the citie of Talentia ouercame them: Herennius was there ſlaine, Perperna eſcaped by flight. Pompey did paſſe the winter in the Pyrenae an mountaines, Sertorius in Luſitania, and at the beginning of the ſpring, Metellus and Pompeius did encounter with ſeuerall armies Sertorius and Perperna, in which battell Sertorius conſtrained Pompey to fly, and Metellus draue Perperna to the like extremitie, Pōpey was at that time wounded in the thigh, afterward they met againe at Seguntia, where Sertorius did the ſecond time ouerthrow Pompey, and Metellus Perperna: the third time when Sertorius was coming againſt Metellus, Pompey meeting him in the way, cauſed him to retire: Sertorius did againe oppoſe himſelfe to Pompey. Hauing taking Segida a noble citie of Celtiberia, where Sertorius loſt a thouſand ſouldiers &amp; Pompey as many: then they turned thēſelues

to the beſieging of townes, Pompey did beſiege Palantia, but Sertorius did raiſe the ſiege, and of them which beſieged Caliguriū he did ſlay three thouſand. Metellus and Pō
               peius with great ſtoutneſſe &amp; ſtomacke took many cities that were leagued with Sertorius and at Ilerda and Ilioſca the townes of the Ilergitanes they put Sertorius to a deſperate plunge, but Caligurium the citie of the Vaſcons he did with much proweſſe &amp; puiſſance defend. Sertorius was like to Iugurth in his fight, and in his fortune not vnlike to him, the exploits and ſtratagemes of them both were ſingular and admirable, but their end and laſt euent was miſerable and mournefull. IugurthaSertorius is ſlaine. was taken by treacherie: Sertorius by the treaſon of M. Antonius and M. Perperna his captaines was ſlaine, as he was ſitting at a bā
               quet, in the eight yeare of his rebellion, his empire was preſently transferred to M. Perperna, whome Pompey ouercame, tooke priſoner, and put to death, and in the tenth yeare after the beginning of this warre, he tooke Spaine. The Romanes were in theſe times buſied &amp; moleſted in Italie by certaine

fencers or ſword players, trayned vp in a ſhadowed fight vnder the gouernment of Lentulus, but defying their maiſter, and ſtirred with an helliſh humor to ſeate themſelues in the higheſt thrones of honor (for as fire is to gunpowder, ſo is ambition to the heart of man, which if it be but touched with ſelfe-loue mounteth aloft and neuer bēdeth downward till it be turned to aſhes) they raunged themſelues, and drew to their enſignes a great multitude offorlorn men. For in proceſſe of time their armie did encreaſe to foureſcore thouſand and moe. The leaders were Spartacus, Enomans, and Crixus, who making great ſpoile and ſaccage in Italie, at length imbattelled themſelues vpon the mountaine Veſurius. Againſt them were ſent Clodius Glaber, and Publius Varinius, but their armies were ſuddenly by theſe enemies diſcomfited: therefore the yeare next enſuing C. Lentulus and L. Gellius Conſuls, and Q. Arrius the Praetor prepared againſt them. Crixus one of theſe rebellious captaines, was together with his whole armie vtterly ouerthrowne: but Spartacus, in whome was more vigor of ſinewes,

courage, and counſell, conducting his ſouldiers from the Apennine mountaine to the Alpes, and from the Alpes into France, was at the firſt enforced to retire by one of the Conſuls, by the other to flye. But afterward hauing animated, ſurueyed, and marſhalled his men, he did ſuddenly turne backeSpartacus a fence-plaier, doth encounter the army of the Conſuls. vpon the Conſuls, gaue them battell, in ſeuerall places ouercame them: &amp; was marching toward Rome there to poſſeſſe himſelf of the Capitole, and to erect a monarchie, but that the Conſuls reuniting their diſſipated forces, did hardly with much labour &amp; great ſlaughter of men reſtraine and hinder him. But he hauing loſt his purpoſe, yet not looſing hisSpartacus taketh the citie of the Thurians. time ſurpriſed the goodly citie of the Thuririans, where breathing for a while &amp; refreſhing his armie, and ſoone after reencountring the Romanes, he obtained a glorious victorie, and a plentifull ſpoile. This ſucceſſe did notably enhance the pride of Spartacus, who preſuming now that he was better then the Conſuls, thought himſelfe therefore fit to be a king. And as Athenio not long before, a ſhepheard and drudge in the fields, hauing

ſlaine his maiſter in Sicilie, and muſtred vnder enſigne a great number of vagrant perſons, by whoſe meanes he did ſpoile, and lay waſt many hamlets, caſtles, and villages, and applauding to himſelfe in this ſucceſfull pillage and roguerie, was adorned with a purple garment, ſtrowted and walked along with a ſtaffe of ſiluer, and enuironed his head with a crowne of gold: ſo did this rebell of Italie aſſume to himſelfe a regall pompe and title, &amp; making fortune his reſt, which of all things is moſt vnlike to it ſelfe, thought he might as eaſily continue as beginne a conqueſt. But the Romanes who neuer could ſuffer victorie to warme her ſelfe long with the robes of a ſtraunger, committed the whole ſcope andM. Craſſus appointed for the warre againſt Spartacus. charge of the warre to M. Craſſus their Praetor, a man ambitious and venturous: he hauing ioyned battell with Granicus one of the rebell chieftaines, did ſlay both the captaine and thirtie fiue thouſand of his ſouldiers, and after fighting with Spartacus did ſlay him, &amp; with him fortie thouſand, fiue thouſand onely eſcaped, whom Cn. Pompeius returning from the Spaniſh warre, did ſuddenly meete

and preſently put to the ſword. After theſe times M. Cicero being Conſul, whoſe nouity and ſtrangeneſſe in Rome, the nobilitie and rareneſſe of his good gifts might iuſtly excuſe who for all his excellent qualities was more beholding to nature then education, as for his vertue famous, ſo for his eloquence moſt famous, by whom it was that the Romanes were not inferiour to them in wit, whom they vanquiſhed in warre, the conſpiracie of Catiline was detected and determined, and Cicero for his conſtancie, courage, &amp; watchfulneſſe, in ſuppreſſing the ſcalefire of that warre to the vtmoſt cinder, was intitled byCicero called Pater patriae. the name of Pater patriae, the father of his countrey. But before I enter into the diſcourſe of his rebellion, I muſt make knowne the perſon of the traytor, and the cauſe of the treaſon. L. Sergius Catilina was in face andCatiline his qualities. feature comely and abſolute, in wit prompt and pregnant, in eloquence ſweet and delightfull, in pompe and maieſtie princely and regall, in courtly behauiour quaint and delicate: and to ſet vpon this gold a Diamond, of a moſt noble parentage. There were certaine

families amongſt the Romanes, which ſurmounted &amp; ouerheaded the reſt, being moſt auncient and of a worthie originall, and they are parted into two diſcents, ſome of them hauing the Aborigines to their aunceſtours, and ſome the Troianes. The firſt and principall of the race of the Aborigines, was the familie of the Vitellij, being diſcended frō Faunus the king of the Aborigines, which did inhabite Italie before the comming of Aeneas, and Queene Vitellia, which in many places was worſhipped as a goddeſſe: the ſecōd was the familie of the Fabij, whoſe ofſpring is rightly deriued from Fabius the ſon of Hercules: the third was the lineage of the Antonij, iſſuing from Anton an other of Hercules his ſonnes: the fourth was the race of the Potitij, ſo named of Potitius, who did with great curteſie entertaine Hercules, when he was entred Italie: the fift was the houſe of the Mamilij, borne of Mamilia the daughter of Telegonus one of Vlyſſes his ſonnes begotten of Circe that notorious enchauntreſſe. The other families which referred their beginning to the Troiane roote, were ten in number:

firſt the houſe of the Iulij, who deſcended frō Iulus the ſonne of Aeneas: the ſecond the Aemilij, who tooke their name of Aemilius the ſonne of Aſcanius a Troiane, &amp; of that houſe was the matchleſſe Scipio, ſonne to Paulus Aemilius, who being the Romane Generall deſtroyed Carthage. The third the Nautij of Nautes one of Aeneas his companions: for when Diomedes hauing ſtolen the image of Pallas, did perceiue that it was of no vſe to him, after the deſtruction of Troy he offered it as a preſent to Aeneas paſſing by his kingdome, but as Aeneas doing then ſacrifice was turning himſelfe, Nautes did lay hold of the image, &amp; by that meanes did appropriate the vſe of it to himſelfe, ſo that the Nautij and not the Iulij did enioy the myſteries of Minerua: the fourth the Cloaelij of Cloaelius an other of Aeneas his companions: the fift the Iunij of IuniusThe linage of Catiline. an other of his aſſociates: the ſixt the Sergij of Sergeſtus one of the Troiane captaines, of which familie was L. Sergius Catilina, and before him none of that name was euer tainted with any ſauour of rebellion. The ſeuenth the Memij of Mueſteus, an other of the Troiane

trauellers, the eight the Cloantij of Cloanthus a bird of the ſame fether, the ninth the Giganij or the Gianij of the Troiane Gias, the tenth the Caecilij of Saeculus a Troiane alſo who built Preneſte. Catiline being adorned with the nobilitie aboue deſcribed, made himſelfe through his vices and miſdemeanor ignoble and odious: his life was the picture of licentiouſneſſe: to women he was ſo lewdly affectionate, that euery curtizane of Rome layed claime vnto him. And to marie Aurelia Oreſtilla into a vacant houſe, he committed the ſhamefull murder of his owne and onelyCatiline killeth his own ſonne. child: for two things he promiſed her, and performed for her, which were tokens of a mercileſſe heart, the balefull death of his ſon, and the chaunge of the ſtate, in ſuch ſort that Aurelia Oreſtilla ſhould be the Dictatreſſe of Rome. And for the performance he bound himſelfe by a curſed circumſtance, drinking mans bloud to fill his bloudthirſtie humour. In al his actions he was a perfect Protean, framing and compoſing himſelfe to all ſides and ſects: with the grauer ſort of men he would be ſad and ſeuere: with the riotous, prodigall &amp;

exceſſiue: with chaſt matrons modeſt and buxome: with light huſwiues wanton and vaine: with young gentlemen pleaſant and actiue: with auncient fathers demure and deliberatiue: to the baſer ſort curteous and pitifull: to the nobler perſons ſociable and gratefull: ſo variable &amp; diſcoulored he was in his doings, that M. Cicero did greatly maruell at his manifold dexteritie. The firſt ſparks of Catilines conſpiracie began to blaze and appeare, L. Tullus, M. Lepidus being Conſuls, ſixe hundred eightie &amp; ſeuen yeres after the buildingCatiline greatly indebted. of Rome. At that time was Catuline greatly indebted, &amp; becauſe he could not diſcharge the ſumme within the time appointed and limited by lawe, nor bring in an eſtimate or valuation of his goods, whereby it might appeare that he was able to defray the debt, heCatiline forbidden to make ſure for the Conſulſhip. was forbidden to make ſute for the Conſulſhip, whereupon being ſtirred by a reuengefull wrath, he ſought by all meanes poſſible to execute his iniurious intent. There was at that time in Rome Cn. Piſo, a man of deſperate boldneſſe, poore and yet preſumptuous, Catiline did open and impart his meaning to

him and Pub. Antronius, and they three determined to kill the Conſuls, which were made the next yeare after Catilines repulſe. The inquiſition of this matter was deferred till it came to greater ripeneſſe. Afterward they intended the death of the moſt part of the Senators: the time was appointed when their complices and confederates, abbetters, and aſſiſtants ſhould meet in armour: but becauſe Catiline perceiued that the number of theſe rebellious ſouldiers was not yet ſufficient to giue onſet to the citie, he withdrew his hand for a time, and diſmiſſed the armie. But a yeare after M. Cicero, and C. Antonius hauing entred the Conſulſhip, Catiline being now alſo diſgraced with another repulſe, recollected into his ſeditious braine his auncient plots and former villanies: then he conſpired with P. Lentulus &amp; C. Cethegus Praetors to worke the death of the Conſuls, to ſlay the Senate, to burne the citie, and to alter the ſtate: and for this purpoſe they did by letters inuite to this horrible maſſacre many Romanes that were employed in forraine ſeruice. This being apparantly euident, &amp; dangers

being now at the doore, and in a readineſſe to pierce into the citie, vnleſſe ſome mature aduiſe were preſently taken, a Senate was appointed in the temple of Iupiter Stator, vnto which place ſhameleſſe Catiline, imagining that he might bleare their eyes by a pretended purgation reſorted alſo, and with an vnchaunged countenance ſhrowded vnder the habite of a Senator, the heart of a ſerpent. And becauſe the method of this hiſtorie may ſeeme in this place to require ſome deſcription of the Senatorie ſtate, I will briefly ſet downe the conſtant and perpetuall order of the Romanes in going to their ſenate houſe, though I cannot counteruaile with aequall termes, nor with a perfect diſcourſe the great maieſtie and pompe, that in this reuerend ſolemnitie was obſerued. The firſt place in the proceeding to their Senate had the Dictator,The ſolemnitie which the Romans vſed in their proceeding to the Senate (when that office was in eſſe) the next the Conſuls, the third the Praetors: the Dictator was therefore preferred becauſe his power was ſupreme, and was not ſubiect to the controll of any other, the Conſuls were in the ſecond place, becauſe they were in praeheminence

next to the Dictator, and all the decrees of the Senate were ratified by thē, bearing date according to the dignitie of their perſons: their triumphs alſo were ſigned with the ſame marke: ſuch a triumph was ſaid to be done, ſuch an one being the ſecond time Conſull, and ſuch an one being the third time Cōſul, according as their aduancement was. In the third rancke of theſe greater Magiſtrates were the Praetors, becauſe they had authoritie to call a Senate as the Dictator &amp; the Conſuls had, which was not permitted to the inferiour magiſtrates: they had alſo iuriſdiction to examine any matter that was done within the hundred ſtone, after the vulgar ſupputation, within an hundred miles of the citie of Rome on euery ſide. Before the Dictator went twelue Lictors or Sergeants, who at the bidding of the Dictator and Conſuls did arreſt offenders, and commaunded ſtrangers that met them in ſigne of reuerence to light from their horſes, they caried in their hands an enſigne of terror, a double poleaxe enuironed with a bundle of rods. The Dictator was caried in a chaire of eſtate, being clad

with a purple gowne, edged with a crimſon border, and inueſted with a robe triumphall, which were the ornaments of the auncient kings of Rome: the ſame attire had the Conſuls and Praetors, but the Praetors did weare a ſiluer coloured garment, and did alwaies ride vpon milke white horſes: after theſe the next place had the Cēſors, if there were any at that time, for they were in the number of principall magiſtrates, their office being not of perpetuitie, no more then the Dictatorſhip. After theſe being the more worthie potentates, the inferiour ſort of the authorized perſons did immediatly follow. The firſt of that order were the Aediles of the chaire, becauſe they were conueyed to the ſenatehouſe in a chaire of yuorie, which monument of honour, as it ſeemeth was permitted vnto them, becauſe in ancient times they were truſted and adorned with the entire regimēt of the citie: theſe were created of the bodie of the Senate: next to them ſucceeded the Aediles of the people, which were raiſed to that dignitie from the roote of the people: after the Aediles followed they which had borne office, though they

were not charged with any office that preſent yeare. All of them ſeuerally marſhalled according to the worthineſſe of their calling, the Conſulians, the Praetorians, the Aedilitians, the laſt place had the Senators, which had not yet borne office. The number of them all in ſuch an aſſemblie did ſome time amount to the number of ſixe hundred all of them, theſe onely excepted who were borne in chaires of eſtate, riding on faire pampered horſes, and long traind gownes, the skirts of which were circumſcribed with theſe words, Senatus, populuſ
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                Romanus. VVhen the Senators were placed, and euery one began to expect what ſhould be ſpoken againſt the rebellious confederates, M. Cicero aiming at Catiline with his eyes, did thus pierce him with his tongue, &amp; with this inuectiue reprooued his maners.
            VVas there euer ſeene ſo great and notoriousCicero his Oration againſt Catiline. impudencie, graue fathers and worthie Senators, that a diſſolute and diſorderly rebell, a profeſſor of prodigalitie and vnthriftineſſe, a maintainer of theeues, barrettors and ſeditious ſlaughterers, a proclaimed enemie to temperance, iuſtice, chaſtitie, &amp; the whole

ſynode of the ſeuerer vertues, a man or rather a monſter of men, compacted of vices &amp; vanities, ſhould dare ſo much as to ſtaine this ſacred preſence with his prophane perſon, &amp; though he conſpire againſt vs, yet amongſt vs to conſult. To conſult (ſaid I) nay to conceale his trecherie. VVhat ſhould the iay do amongſt ſwans, or the owle amongſt nightingales, or the vultur amongſt amongſt doues, or Catiline amōgſt Catoes: do we not dread the thunderbolt when we ſee the lightening? and can we loue the traytor when we loath his treaſon? Canſt thou ſo diſſemble Catiline that we may not diſcerne thy doings? Nay there is no deed of thine, no drift nor deuiſe, which I haue not heard, nay almoſt ſeene, nay almoſt felt. Here, here they be in this our aſſemblie (worthie Senators) in this moſt graue and ſolemne councell of the world, which muſe continually of our death, of the downefall of Rome, and the deſolation of Italie. But thou yet liueſt Catiline, and yet thou liueſt not to abate, but to abet thy pride. VVhat vanitie hath bene at any time abſent from thine eyes? what villanie from thine hands? what

preſident of vice frō thy perſon? what young gentlemā hath there bene along time in this citie, whome, if he were once corrupted by the deceitfull baits of thy falſe entiſements, thou didſt not animate and incite either to deſperate attempts, by carying the ſword before him, or to effeminate examples by bearing the torch before him, and yet thou imagineſt that thy doings are not miſliked. Of thee Catiline when the Romanes keepe ſilence they pronounce ſentence, when they ſuffer thy miſdeedes they condemne them, when they are at reſt with themſelues, they are at deadly warre with thee. But why am I ſo earneſt againſt thee? Is it poſſible that any thing ſhold amend thee? may it be hoped for that thou wilt reforme thy ſelfe, that thou wilt ſhake off theſe faults? that thou wilt baniſh theſe enormities? Thou art not of ſo good &amp; vertuous inclination, that honeſtie may reclaime thee from whoredome, feare from vniuſtice, and reaſon from outrage: to this madneſſe nature hath framed thee, frowardneſſe hath exerciſed thee, and deſtinie hath reſerued thee, and for theſe deformities of thy nature

thou haſt bene more feared then truſted, and indeede more wily then we haue heretofore bene watchfull. But at length noble Senators, L. Catilina enraged with boldneſſe, breathing out bloudſhed, preparing in moſt hainous manner a ſcourge for his countrie, threatning to this citie fire and ſword, is ſufficiently knowne and abundantly hated. No plague can now be inuented of that monſter and horror of men within this citie againſt this citie, but in that he hath not drawne his bloudie ſword out of our naked bodies, in that he hath left vs aliue, in that we haue wreſted the weapon from his butcherous hands, in that the citizens be ſafe, &amp; the citie ſecure, can ye coniecture with what a bitter agonie and anguiſh of mind he is vexed: and if he beginne hereafter to renew his furie, take courage my Lords, and leade out againſt his broken and outcaſt band, the flower and the power of all Italie, and conſider with what foes we deale, which ſurfetting in banquets, embracing harlots, ſtuffed with meat, faint with wine, adorned with garlands, ſoupled with ointments, weakned by wantons, caſt from

their contagious mouths the ſlaunder of the vertuous, ouer whome I do hope there hangeth ſome heauie deſtinie: and that the puniſhment that hath bene long time due to their wicked luſt and licentiouſneſſe, is either now imminent or now approching: whom if my Conſulſhip do chaunce to quelle becauſe it cannot cure, it ſhall not procure a ſhort ſunſhine of peace to the common-weale, but whole ages and worlds of tranquilitie: that which may be healed by any meanes I will heale by ſome meanes, that which muſt needs be cut off I muſt needes cut off, therefore let them either leaue the citie, or leaue their tumult, or if they will ſtay both in this citie and in this mind, let them looke for their deſert, and aſſure themſelues of the full meaſure of reuenge, but if in ſtewes and tauernes they ſought onely beluing and baudrie, they were more to be ſpared, but yet wholly to be diſpaired of: but who can tollerate that cowards ſhould determine trecherie againſt the couragious, wild braines againſt them that be wiſe, ſottiſh drunkards againſt ſober Senators and ſluggiſh drones againſt carefull magiſtrates?

Theſe men building like gods vpon the earth, as if their houſes ſhould be heauens, whilſt they take their pleaſure in ſumptuous coaches, great families, coſtly banquets, rich attire, and in the lewd companie of laſciuious curtizanes, are fallen into ſuch a gulfe of debt, that if they would be free from it, Sylla is to be raiſed from the dead. But they ſhall ſoone perceiue, if they ſtill perſiſt in their naughtineſſe, that there are in this citie vigilant Conſuls, politicke gouernours, a puiſſant Senate, that we haue weapons, that we haue a priſon, which our aunceſtors haue made a reuenger of hainous and manifeſt faults. And now ſith you are deliuered through my care and induſtrie from a ſwelling cloud of terrors, without battell, without bloudſhed, without armie, without fighting. For this ſo great benefite noble Senators, I require of you no reward of vertue, no enſigne of honour, no monument of praiſe, but an eternall record of this very time: I deſire that all my deſerts, all the ornaments of my perſon, the fruits of my glorie, and the good aeſtimation of my diligence, ſhould be regiſtred and enrolled in

in your memories. No muteneſſe, no ſilence, no ſecret whiſpering can delight me, by your remembrance worthie Senators mine actes &amp; exploits ſhall be nouriſhed, by your words they ſhall grow, by your writings they ſhall not onely receiue life but aeternitie.
            
            Catiline hauing all this while itching eares,Catiline his impudent anſwer to Cicero. but a more itching toung, made in diſorderly manner this diſdainfull reply: I haue a long time maruelled and now with aſtoniſhment do wonder (ye noble Lords and ancient progenie of kings) for as to the reſt I will not bēd my ſelfe to them but againſt them, that with ſo patient eare, and minds impaſſionate, ye can digeſt the cholericke railings of this rhetoricall parot, whome ſince we firſt promoted from the pearch to the pinacle, from the bar to the bench, from the ground whereon we go, to the tribunall whereon we ſit, the Senate ſurfetting long ago on his rude and vnmanerly ſpeeches, is now conſtrained to make a diet of a diſeaſe: vpon me as ye haue plainely perceiued, he hath ſpent the whole cheſt of his gall, who am as free from the crimes intended, as he is farre from the vertues which he

aſcribeth to you. He thought perhaps (what wickedneſſe I pray you hath he not thought) to blow me out of the gates of the citie, by the venimous aire of his impoiſened lungs, but maugre his malicious throat. I ſtand before his lowring face, to the abaſhment of his frozen forehead, and the confuſion of his ill ſpeaking eloquence, as one irreproucable, being like a cage of chryſtall, vpon which the more poyſon is caſt, the more cleare it doth ſeeme. I am not made (Conſul Marcus) of ſo fleeting and brittle mould, that the gnaſhing of thy teeth ſhould either fray me or fret me: but if I were guiltie of the faults alleadged, why was I not impeached of them before thy Conſulſhip, but vnder the triumph of thy tearmes muſt ſuffer this intollerable iniurie? Catiline is an Epicure forſooth, becauſe Cicero is a Stoicke, Catiline is wanton, becauſe Cicero is iealous, Catiline is lawleſſe, becauſe Ciceroes will muſt be a lawe to him: Catiline is prodigall, becauſe he hath not beſtowed any bribes vpon Cicero: Catiline is rebellious, becauſe Cicero is fearefull and timerous: Catiline is an enemie to the common-weale,

becauſe he is not friend to Ciceroes priuate pollicie: mightie accuſations and vnanſwerable! Hath he not drawne bloud (trow you) of Catilines credit? It grieueth me worthie Senators, and truſt me, it grieueth mine heart, that the hope of the Romane youth, and the ſweet ſocietie of gallant gentlemen your ſelues attēding, bearing, &amp; forbearing, ſhould by the ſpawne of a ragge be ſo hainouſly diſgraced: as for his diſtempered declamation it is no noueltie with vs my Lords, for it is the vſuall methode of his mercenare toung, vpō poore and pitifull preſumptions, to hazard the life and ſoule of his clients cauſe. But what madneſſe is it for one that is lately crept into the citie to talke of antiquities, taking matters in hand which are elder then his memorie, which were forgotten and dead before he was begotten and borne? Thou art not auncient enough Cicero to ſpeake of our aunceſtors, nor worthie enough to talk of our worthies, thou art as a pilgrime in this citie, thou art ignorant of the orders and cuſtomes therof, thou ſeemeſt to wander in another countrie, and not to beare office in the Metrapolis

of Italie: thou threatneſt vs with extremities, and layeſt on load with impriſonments, as if our bodies ſhould be anuils to thine hatred: but ſuffer not my ſweet, mild and curteous magiſtrates of Rome, that vpon Ciceroes ſuggeſtion we ſhould endure ſuch reproch: the ignominie of arraignment is miſerable, the arreſting of guiltleſſe men is lamentable, baniſhment is diſcomfortable, but the racking, rowling, tearing and tormenting of men far be it not only frō the bodie of a Romane, but euen from his thoughts, from his eyes, from his eares. For mine own part I confeſſe, and profeſſe, and pretend, that Catiline liueth not to pleaſe, but to diſpleaſe and diſplace M. Cicero, of whome when I ſpeake, I ſpeake of tyrannie, of villanie, of baſeneſſe, and aſſure thy ſelfe Cicero, that either the law of Rome, or the lawe of reaſon ſhall be my warrant in this caſe, and to them that be diſcontented in this citie, thy fall will be a generall s;atisfaction.
            
            Catiline departed out of the ſenate houſe continuing his furie, and becauſe danger was feared, it was thought good that the Senate

ſhould be diſmiſſed in the night time. Catiline went with a ſlender gard to the tents of Manlius. Lentulus, Cethegus, and diuerſe others that were priuie to the conſpiracie, and did as yet remaine in the citie, were arreſted and impriſoned, and being conuicted by manifeſt euidence, were preſently put to death. The day wherein the puniſhment of theſe traitors was decreed, did greatly illuſtrate &amp; beautifie the worthineſſe of M. Cato. He diſcended from M. Cato the Prince of the Portiā familie, after whome this Cato in degree ofThe linage of M. Cato. diſcent was accompted and numbred in the third place. This M. Cato was of all the RomanesThe praiſe of M. Cato. moſt ſincere, and moſt like to vertue itſelfe, and ſeemed in his iuſtice and integritie to be nearer to God then to man, who did not liue honeſtly &amp; orderly becauſe he would ſeeme to be vertuous, but becauſe it was againſt the courſe of his diſpoſition to be diſhoneſt and diſorderly, thinking that onely to be reaſonable, which was iuſt and lawfull: he was free from fancies, and had alwaies fortune in his owne power: he was then Tribune of the people, young in reſpect of his yeares,

but in wiſedome and aduiſe a father, &amp; a right Senator, who (when others perſwaded that the conſpirators ſhould be kept aliue in ſeuerall wards) being the laſt of them that ſentenced the rebellious, did inueigh with ſuch force of mind and wit againſt the conſpirators, that by the vehemencie of his ſpeech he cancelled their opinions, which perſwaded lenitie, and made their ſoftneſſe to be ſuſpected: and the greater part of the Senate in fauour of Catoes gracious ſeueritie, did accō
               panieC. Caeſar inclined to ſedition. him to his houſe. C. Caeſar did at that time giue ſome token of a rebellious humor, whereof Rome taſted afterward too much, &amp; himſelfe in the end was poiſoned with the dregs. Catiline hearing what was done at Rome, gathered an armie, and making a laborious iourney through the ſteepe and craggie hils, intended a voyage into that part of Fraunce, which is beyond the Alpes: which Q. Metellus perceiuing, who was leader of three bands of ſoldiers in the Picē prouince, he remooued his tents and pitched them at the bottome of the Piſtorian heath, frō which place the armie of C. Antonius was not farre.

Catiline when he ſaw that he was on euery ſide embayed with mountaines &amp; armed mē, choſe rather to fight with Antonius, who cō
               mitted the vantgard to the conduct of M. Petreius. Catiline in that battell gaue a ſharpe onſet, and continued the fight with an vndaunted ſtomacke, but in the end was ſlaine, and dying with great indignation, was there trampled to death by the hoofes of horſes. Thus he that did defend himſelf in the Senate houſe, was confounded in the field, and that by the iuſtice of deſtinie, who with a ſcourge of ſteele followeth proud aſpirers: this inſolent Romane perceiued at the time of his death the deceitfull gloſe of his fawning fancie, &amp; the vaine ſophiſtrie of bewitching ambition.
            ⸪
         
         
            
            
               LACHESIS, Or the ſecond Booke.
            
               CN. Pompeius for his great valor &amp; magnanimitie iuſtly intitled Magnus, did in courſe of time grow to an exceeding greatneſſe of authoritie, and had purchaſed through his worthie exploits, the loue, applauſe and admiration of the whole world, his father was Cn. Pompeius an approued ſouldier, and a Conſularian, his mother was Lucilia a Senators daughter: he was of a comely perſonage, not ſo commendable for beautie, as for a pleaſing and conſtant complection, which continued euen to his laſt houre, his wiſedome was of a wonderfull excellencie, his life in all parts abſolute, his eloquence but indifferent, he was deſirous to haue honour offred, but was not ambitious to vſurpe it, a faſt friend &amp; a religious obſeruer of his word,

in reconciling mē that were at variance moſt faithfull, in receiuing ſatisfaction for offences moſt eaſie, neuer vſing his power to impotē
               cie, nor his wit to vanitie, from his cradle a ſouldier, in his youth a conqueror triumphant, and in all his warres couragious and dreadfull. For though Sertorius did more cō
               mendSertorius feareth Pō
                  pey. Metellus, yet he was more afraid of Pompey. And of the Spaniards he triumphed when he was but a Romane knight, not hauing as yet borne any office of eſtate. To be a knight of Rome was ſo much better then to be a common gentleman, by how much a patritian Senator was more honorable then a nouitian, whoſe aunceſtours were neuer of the Senate. And Pompey by degrees did endeuour to aduance his credit, and in the end by the conqueſt of many &amp; mightie nations, became peereles. Mithridates his power was enfeebled by Sylla, diſiointed by Lucullus, &amp; broken in peeces by Pompey, after which victorieMithridates ouerthrown by Pompey. Pompey entred the tē
                  ple of Ieruſalem. he ſubdued the Iewes, tooke their citie, and poſſeſt the temple of Ieruſalem, a rare and miraculous monument, which though he filled with his ſouldiers, yet he reſtrained thē
               
from the ſpoile. In that warre he partly recouered, and partly ſubdued to the Romane power, Armenia, Colchis, Cappadocia, Cilicia, Syria, and all the region of Paleſtine to the riuer of Euphrates. He ouercame beſide Paphlagonia, Galatia, Phrigia, Myſia, Lydia, Caria, Ionia, and all that part of Aſia which lyeth about Pergamus. He committed the regiment of Armenia maior to Tigranes, the Iſland of Boſphorus to Pharnaces, Cappadocia to Arioberzanes, Seleucia to Antiochus Commagenus: to Deiotarus and other Tetrarkes Galatia with Armenia minor, to Attalus and Pylaemenes Paphlagonia, to Ariſtarchus Colchis, to Hircane Paleſtine. And for a triple reward of theſe his victories, hePompey honored with a triple triumph. had the blazon of three triumphs: the firſt was of Affricke, the ſecond of Europa, and the third of Aſia. After theſe triumphs enſued the Conſulſhip of Marcus Bibulus and C.Caeſar his originall. Caeſar, iſſuing from the famous familie of the Iulij, and conueying his diſcent from Anchiſes the Troiane father to Aeneas: he was of excellent beautie, and in vigor of mind moſt ſharpe and vehement, in his rewards bountifull,

in courage farre aboue mans nature, or mans beliefe, in the haughtineſſe of his thoughts, in the celeritie of his fight, in the ſuffering of bitter euents and caſualties ſingular, in all his actions moſt like to Alexander the great, to Alexander I meane being ſober, and neither ſurcharged with wine, nor ouercome with wrath, vſing ſleepe and meate not for the pampering of his luſt, but for the continuing of his life. He was neare in bloud to C. Marius, and was Cinnaes ſonne in lawe, neither during Syllaes Dictatorſhip could he by any means be moued to diuorce Cinnaes daughter, though M. Piſo a Conſularian, did for feare of Sylla ſunder himſelfe from Annia Cinnaes widow, by which conſtancie Caeſar did greatly endaunger himſelfe; for his deathCaeſars death ſought for by Sillaes officers. was ſought for by Syllaes officers, Sylla himſelfe being ignorant of their purpoſe. Caeſar being made Conſul, a league of ſoueraigne ſocietie was concluded betwixt him and Cn. Pompeius, &amp; M. Craſſus. Pompey did therefore enter into that league, becauſe he would haue his acts and deedes, which he had made in the prouinces before mentioned, that were

conquered by him, fully confirmed and ratified by the Senate. Caeſar by taking that courſe had a double intent, to increaſe his owne honour by yeelding to Pompeis glory, and to eſtabliſh his owne authoritie by charging him with the hatred of this treuirall power. Craſſus had this drift to maintaine &amp; preſerue the aeſtimation which he had alreadie obtained by the power of Caeſar, and the authoritie of Pompey. There was alſo an affinitie contracted by marriage betwixt CaeſarPompey marrieth with Iulia Caeſars daughter. and Pompey: for Pompey tooke to wife Iulia Caeſars daughter. Caeſar had the regiment of Fraunce committed to him by the Senate, after whoſe Conſulſhip ended, and before his departure into Fraunce, P. Clodius TribuneClodius Tribune of the people becommeth ſeditious. of the people began to giue new edge vnto quarrels, and did with maine force bend himſelfe againſt Cicero. For what agreement could there be betwixt them, when their maners did ſo farre diſagree? The head of diſſention was cut off when Catiline was ſlaine, the bodie alſo was mangled when his confederates were put to death, but the ſerpents taile did as yet mooue: for Clodius did ſeeke by all

meanes poſſible, to take reuenge on CiceroClodius ſeeketh to reuenge himſelfe vpon Cicero. for the ſharp ſeueritie vſed againſt his friends which were of Catilines ſeed-plot, and of that ſeditious league. But it was to be wondred at, that a man conuicted of ſo notorious and hainous crimes, durſt proceede to ſuch impudencie as to attempt the diſgrace of M. Cicero, or any way to diſturbe his quietneſſe. At that time Clodius was infamous for his adulterieClodius infamous for adulterie with Pompeia Caeſars wife. with Pompeya Caeſars wife, which amiddeſt the moſt religious &amp; ſolemne rites of Bona Dea, this vnchaſt Tribune committed: and theſe ceremonies, which it was not lawfull for any man to behold, Clodius in womans attire did pollute. But he was the author of greater lewdneſſe then this, when with his owne ſiſters he became inceſtuous, two ofClodius infamous for inceſt with his ſiſters. them being his ſiſters german, and married to two worthie Romanes, the one of them to Q. Metellus, and the other to L. Lucullus, the third was his ſiſter by the halfe bloud, the wife of Q. Martius. For theſe and other his faults, he was condemned by the ſeuerall cenſuresClodius cō
                  demned by Senate. of two hundred Senators at one Seſſion, and this notwithſtanding was abſolued: ſo that I

do greatly doubt, whether the Conſuls that did abſolue him, or Clodius that was abſolued, did more deſerue puniſhment: for by that meane ſuch a window of impunitie was then opened, as could not be ſhut in the ſpace of many yeares enſuing. But Clodius becauſe he was Tribune, and becauſe he was Clodius, did thinke all time loſt wherein Cicero was ſafe. He was then in great fauour both with the people and Conſuls: for when any commoditie was ſought for by the Conſuls, which could not be preiudiciall to the people, he would labour earneſtly for the Conſuls, and when the people would haue had any benefite which did not concerne the Conſuls, he was wholly for the people: ſo that by diſpleaſing neither, he pleaſed them both. Vpon this ground he aduentured to make lawes, amōgſt which one was enacted againſt thē who had put a Romane citizen to death without the iudgement of the people of Rome, which lawe though it ranne in generall termes, yet in ſence and meaning it was directly leuelled againſt Cicero, who in his Conſulſhip had by Senate condemned the confederates of Catiline.

Cicero perceiuing this did clad himſelfeCicero mourneth. with mourning roabes, the Senators alſo were attired with blacke, as the aſſociates of his ſorrow, the Romane knights did weare his colour, the inconſolate citie did droope and deplore his ſtate, and the forreiners that heard thereof did enlarge the griefe. For the redreſſing of this maladie meanes were made to Craſſus, Caeſar, and Pompey. But Caeſar denyed to ſtand againſt Clodius, becauſe he feared that the lawes and decrees made by him the yeare next before when he was Conſul ſhould be diſanulled and abrogated by Clodius if he maintained hatred againſt him. M. Craſſus was monies weathercocke, and an hungrie cormorant of coyne, and therefore refuſed to meddle in this matter, becauſe they that craued the aſſiſtance of his authoritie, came not to him with golden faces: only Pō
               pey did helpe, countenance, &amp; comfort him, and proteſted openly that himſelfe would rather be ſlaine by Clodius, then Cicero ſhold be abuſed: but the Conſuls commanding the Senators and others to lay aſide their mournfull ſable, did ſo firmely lincke themſelues to

Clodius, both againſt Cicero and Pompey, that neither could Pompey profite him, neither would Cicero ſtay in the citie. For how could he expect any better ſucceſſe, L. Piſo &amp; A. Gabinius being Conſuls, men of notorious naughtineſſe, and raked out of the ſcum of Senators? VVherefore Cicero left the city,Cicero committeth himſelfe to voluntarie exile. and in the very day of his departure, his houſe that ſtoode on mount Palatine was burnt by Clodius, and the ſoile was conſecrated to Libertie: his goods were confiſcated, his lordſhips and farmes beſtowed vpon others: there was a lawe alſo made touching his baniſhment, wherby it was prohibited that he ſholdA ſharpe law made concerning Cicero his baniſhment. not haue the vſe of water and fire within the citie, that none within fiue hundred miles of Italie ſhould receiue him into his houſe, that none ſhould make any motion for him to the Senate, that none ſhould deliuer his opinion of Cicero, that none ſhould diſpute of that which was done, that none ſhould ſpeake of it, that none ſhould go vnto him, that none ſhould write vnto him. But in the end Cn. Pompeius hauing vndertaken emnitie with Clodius, being vrged by the earneſt petition

of Titus Annius Milo, and moued by the abundant kindneſſe of his heroicall nature, did in his mind make ſpeciall election of this care to reduce Cicero from baniſhment. VVherefore the yeare next enſuing, P. Lentulus and Q. Metellus being Conſuls, Cicero by a Senatorie decree was recalled from baniſhmētCicero recalled from baniſhment. with the great deſire of the Senate, and the great reioycing of Italie. The ground whereon his houſe ſtoode, was exempted from religious conſecration, and his houſe was not ſo ſhamefully throwne downe by Clodius, as it was ſumptuouſly reedified by the Senate, his poſſeſſions were reſtored vnto him, and all the acts which Clodius made in his TribuneſhipClodius perſiſteth to be an enemie to Cicero. were adiudged to be void. Clodius did greatly indignate at the returne of Cicero, &amp; hauing aggregated vnto him a raſcall route of thriftleſſe and vnconſcionable ruffians, he partly draue away, and did partly maime and murder the carpenters and workmen, that were buſied about the renewing of Ciceroes houſe, he burnt beſide the houſe of Q. Cicero,Clodius burneth, the houſe of Q. Cicero. he fought with Milo many times in the ſtreets: he purſued Cicero with ſtones, clubs,

and ſwords, &amp; arming all his men with brāds of fire in the one hand, and ſwords in the other led them to the burning of Miloes houſe: but this tempeſt and trouble of the citie, who did beſtow kingdomes and take them away, and deuided the world at his pleaſure, which burnt the temple of the Nimphes, that he might ſcorch the rowle in which his ſhame was enregiſtred, which with maſons, architectes, and meaſurers of ground did ſuruey almoſt euery cloſe and plot that lay neare vnto him, hoping in the end to make it his own purchaſe, and to dilate and extend his demeaſnes from the gate of Ianus to the top ofClodius threatneth death to Sanctia. the Alpes: which threatned death to Sanctia a matron, as holy in her manners as in her name, and to Apronius a young gentleman, vnleſſe they would ſell vnto him their inheritance: who told Furſonius in plaine termes, that if he would not lend him ſo much mony as he required, he would carie him dead into his houſe. This enemie I ſay to all good men, to his neighbors, to forreyners, to his friends,Clodius is ſlaine by Milo. to his kinſmen, was ſhortly after ſlaine by Milo, for whoſe death he did lye in awaite, and

his bodie being conueyed to Rome was loathed of the beholders, for it was the harbour of a foule oſtridge.
            Caeſar was now in hot warres againſt the French, of whoſe exploits as they did happē in nine yeares ſpace, whilſt he was Preſident there by the commiſſion of the Senate, I will make a brief rehearſall as the times did yeeld them.
            In the firſt yeare the Heluetians, whenThe Heluetians flye before Caeſar. Caeſar had ſcarcely ſet foote in France, burnt their houſes, and leauing their countrie diſperſed themſelues in the fields of the Sequani, and ſo came to the coaſt of the Toloſſians. Caeſar perceiuing that their abode in that place would be dangerous to the citie of Toloſſa, and being earneſtly intreated by the petition of the Ambarrians and the Allobroges, who did complaine themſelues to be greatly vexed and diſturbed by the Heluetians, remoouing his tents and hauing ouertaken them at the riuer of Arraris deſtroyed in purſuite all the villages of the Tigurines. Caeſars horſemen which were ſent before to obſerue what waies and pathes the Heluetians

did take, were by them diſcomfited. AfterwardThe Heluetians ouercome by Caeſar. they gaue battell to Caeſar, and in that battell they were ouercome, and yeelding themſelues to Caeſars mercie, they were enioyned to reſort to their owne countrie, and there to repaire their houſes. Then Caeſar being mooued by the complaint of certaine Frenchmē addreſt againſt Ariouiſta the kingCaeſar purſueth battell againſt Ariouiſta. of the Germaines, whome he did purſue in battell to the riuer of Rhenus.
            In the ſecond yeare he waged battell againſtCaeſar fighteth againſt the Belgians &amp; Neruians. the Belgians, the moſt of which were ſlaine. The like ſucceſſe had he againſt the Neruians.
            In the third yeare fighting on the ſea againſt the Venetians, he cauſed thē to yeeld: and P. Craſſus his Lieutenant did ſubdue almoſt all the countrie of Aquitania.
            In the fourth yeare the Germaines paſſing with a great multitude ouer the riuer of Rhine arriued in Fraunce, whom Caeſar aſſaulting on the ſudden did vtterly deſtroy: then he made a bridge ouer Rhenus, and determinedCaeſar ouerthroweth the Germaines. to vexe and exagitate the Germaines in their owne countrie, becauſe France was ſo much

diſquieted and moleſted by them, &amp; hauingCaeſar burneth the villages of the Sicambrians burnt there many cities and villages of the Sicambrians, being alſo certified that the Britanes did miniſter ſuccour, and gaue encouragement to the conſpiracies of the French, he ſayled into Britaine, and conſtrained theCaeſar ouer commeth the Brittains Britanes by ſharpe onſet to yeeld vnto him. Caeſars nauie that tranſported his horſe, was ſhrewdly ſhaken with a tempeſt, wherewith the Britaines being reuiued betooke themſelues againe to weapons, and fighting with Caeſar were put to flight: at length they ſued to Caeſar for peace, which he taking hoſtageCaeſar recō
                  ciled to the Britaines. of them did eaſily graunt, and returned into Fraunce, and the ſame yeare the Morines &amp; Menapiās rebelling he reduced to obediēce.
            In the fifth yeare Caeſar returning from Illyrium, to which place he went for the ſtopping and beating backe of an incurſion made by the Piruſtae, came to his armie in Fraunce, and addreſſed warre afreſh againſt the Britaines hauing broken truce, and enioyingCaeſar renueth his war againſt the Britaines. there a proſperous fight, a great multitude of the inhabitants being ſlaine, and a great part of the Iſland brought into the power of the

Romanes, taking hoſtages, and impoſing tribute he ſet ſaile for Fraunce.
            In the ſixt yeare the Eburons did rebell againſt Caeſar, Ambiorix being their king andThe Eburons ouercome by Caeſar. Captaine, whō in many places Caeſar fiercely and feruently purſuing, put to the ſword and diſperſed the remnāt of that rebellious companie.
            In the ſeuenth yeare Caeſar went into Italy, vpon occaſion of a mutinie which there did befall. The French thinking that he would be detained by domeſticall warre, and that it would be hard for him to returne to his armie during that diſſention, began now to take aduiſe of renewing warre againſt the Romanes. The Carnutians profeſſing that they would be leaders to that attempt bound others vnto them by oath, and hauing appointed a day they repaired to Genabis, where many of the Romanes did negociate, &amp; were earneſtly occupied and buſied about theirTreacherie againſt the Romanes in Fraunce. trafique &amp; merchandiſe, all which were ſlaine by the French, which maſſacre being certainly reported at Aruernum and other parts of Fraunce, the Pietons, the Pariſians, the Cadurcians,

the Tureus, the Aulerci, the Lemonickes, the Audians did ioyne in armour and did confederate with the Carnutians. Caeſar hearing of this new enterpriſe made ſpeedieCaeſar his reuenge vpon the rebels. returne into Fraunce, and hauing placed ſeuerall garriſons in the cities of the Volſcians, of the Artonikes, of the Toloſſians, &amp; in Narbo, which were neareſt vnto the enemies, he tooke Vellannodunum the citie of the Senones, &amp; Genabis the chiefe towne of the Carnutians, which he ſpoiled and burnt, and many other townes did he take, and ſeiſed vpon many of the rebels, receiuing ſome of them into his mercie, &amp; puniſhing very ſharply the moſt notorious offenders.
            In the eight yeare he purſued the Carnutians to their vttermoſt ouerthrow: the Bellofaci conducted by two valiant captaines Corbius and Comius, were enforced to ſubmit themſelues, and Corbius was then ſlaine by Caeſars horſemen.
            In the ninth yeare Caeſar did not enterpriſe any warlike affaires, but laboured ſpecially to cut off all occaſions of reuolting: therfore honorably emparling with the magiſtrates

of the cities: beſtowing vpon the gouernors great rewards, and burdening them with no new taxes, he brought Fraunce being wearied by many warres, to a perfect and perpetuall peace, and departed thence to Italie, but was ſtill garded with an armie of ſouldiers.
            In the ſeuenth yeare of Caeſars warfare in Fraunce, Iulia Caeſars daughter departed this world, and Pompeis litle ſonne which he had by her, within a ſhort ſpace after died alſo, which was a great cracke to the concord before continued. Pompey had alreadie proroged his Praeſidētſhip in the prouince of SpainPompey his Preſidentſhip in Spain proroged. for fiue yeares: but the people of Rome did exceedingly grudge, that either Caeſar or Pō
               pey ſhould in any forraine prouince haue an armie of ſouldiers at their commaund, ſith all warres both forreine and domeſticall were ceaſſed &amp; determined, becauſe they thought by that meane ſome daunger might grow to the Citie: for Pompey being now in Rome, did rule Spaine by Affranius and Petreius his Lieutenants, hauing in ſeuerall cities ſeuerall garriſons, and C. Caeſar had in the boſome of Italie an huge hoaſt, &amp; had then a garriſon

at Rauenna, where he was perſonally reſidēt: this did ſeeme alſo inconuenient to many of the nobles, and Pompey ſhewed himſelfe very partiall: for he did fawne vpon them which would haue had Caeſars armie diſmiſſed, but was very aduerſe to others who would haue meaſured him by the ſame compaſſe, who if he had died in Campania two yeares before the ciuill wars, where he was greatly aſſayed by ſickneſſe, at which time all Italie did make ſpeciall vowes for his health, his glorie which was gained by ſea and land he had caried vntouched to the graue. Vpon theſe conſiderations L. Lentulus and C. Marcellus being Conſuls, a decree was made by the Senate,A decree made by the Senate, that Caeſar ſhold diſmiſſe his armie. that within a time limited Caeſar ſhould diſcharge his armie, and if he would not, that he ſhould be accompted an enemie, for Caeſar wold haue bene made Conſul in his abſence: but M. Cato did well anſwere, that no citizen ought to praeſcribe lawes to the commonweale: wherefore it was ordained that Caeſar contenting himſelfe with one legion, ſhould beare only the title of the Preſidēt of France, and that he ſhould come into the citie as a

priuate man, &amp; in his ſuite for the Conſulſhip, ſhould wholly relye vpon the voices of the people. C. Curio an impudent oratour, a mā wickedly witted, and eloquent for a publike miſchiefe, whoſe mind no riches could ſatiſfie, nor any pleaſures ſufficiently pleaſe, who firſt ſtood for Pōpey (as it was then accompted for the common weale, which I do not ſpeake to reprooue, but that I might not be reprooued) and now was in ſhew and apparance both againſt Pompey and Caeſar, but in deed and mind wholly for Caeſar: this Curio Tribune of the people, poſted in haſt to Rauenna where Caeſar was, and ſignified vnto him the order of the Senate, applying his eloquence as a brand to the inflaming of CaeſarsCaeſar is incenſed by Curio againſt the Senate. furie. Curio came to Caeſar at the entrance of twilight, when the cloud of vapours and exhalations, is by nature diſpoſed to turn men into melancholie, which tooke ſo deepe hold on Caeſar, that making no anſwer to Curio, but caſting himſelfe on his bed he did in this ſort expoſtulate with the Romanes.The paſſionate ſpeech of Caeſar againſt the Senate.
            
            Thus is Caeſar meaſured with a ſcantling, dieted with a paring, and rewarded with nothing.

               Vaniſh from me thou ſad and vgly cō
                  cubine of Erebus, thou grimme and duskie night, which with thy blacke circumference doeſt hood winke our ſences, driuing the day from vs before we can fleſh our ſwords, contracting our ſinewes when they are but newly ſtretched, cauſing vs to lurke in our cabbons when we ſhould cleaue to the throats of our enemies; vaniſh I ſay from me, and delay not with thy lingering minutes my expeditiō againſt Rome. Againſt Rome? ô the eccho of my heart! nay for Rome, againſt the Romanes, amongſt whom is Cn. Pompeius Magnus, but not yet Maximus, for he lacketh a degree of that, and before he can attaine to it, there will be effuſion of bloud by ſucceſſiō. But what careth he for that, was he not one of Syllaes whelpes, whoſe ſword reaking with Italian bloud he ſo greedily licked, that the taſt thereof doth as yet relice in his rauenous and polluted lawes? But learne of Sylla, learn of thy Sylla Pompey, that a tyrant bathing himſelfe in goare, ſhall at length ſinke by the weight of his cruelties. VVhat Caeſar hath done, I referre to the Oracle of Bellona, what

he will do I leaue to the concealed decree of ſacred vengeance: what he may do, let the foredoming Parcae praedeſtinate: what he ought to do let warlike iuſtice pronounce. VVas not Pompey made Conſul without ſuing, without ſeeking, without ſpeaking? and ſhall I requeſting, yea and humbly requeſting ſuffer a repulſe? Fortune thou mightie and miraculous Goddeſſe, which in a moment doeſt procure a world of varieties, whetting with thine anger the points of our launces, ſhaking crownes and kingdomes with the ſpurne of thy foote, triumphing ouer our victories with the ſpeckled wheeles of thy voluble chariot, controlling our hope with thy frowning countenance: thou knoweſt great goddeſſe, that if Rome hath at any time flouriſhed: if it hath at any times taſted the pure and vnmingled extract of ſincere happineſſe, if it were euer caried on the brode wings of fame, if it did euer ſwim in a floud of plentie, it was through Caeſar and his fortune, &amp; yet we are now diſpiſed, and yet we will not be deſpiſed, fortune is able to reuenge the iniurie done to Caeſar, and Caeſar will alwaies fight for the praeheminence of his

fortune. Therefore for the honour of Aeneas againſt the defacers of his race, for the credit of mount Palatine, againſt the vniuſt magiſtrates of Rome, for the glorie of Romulus who ſhineth in the heauens like a giant-ſtarre againſt the ſeditious repugnants, I will ſhoot the ſting of my wrath, and they ſhall well perceiue that Caeſar aeſteemes no better of his enemies, then if a ſort of hares ſhould be harneſſed, which would truſt rather to their feete then to their force: auaunt frō me pitie thou feminine paſſion, for I will deriue my name of a martiall act, and wil be called à caedendo Caeſar, poſſeſſe therfore my heart thou dreadfull Nemeſis, ranſacke my vaines, rage within me wrath, aſſiſt me fiends, furies, and ye deformed ghoſts, ſubiect to the ſeuere edict of the baſer deſtinie, make your ſeats and circles in the waſt of Italie, and neuer forſake that place, till the fierie brightneſſe of Caeſars ſupremacie do deterre you from thence.
            
            Caeſar in this rage of mind, carried away with the whirlewind of his turbulent ſpirit, left Rauenna and paſſed ouer Rubicon: the Senate hearing of his rebellion, decreed that

Pompey ſhould be Generall, &amp; that he ſholdPompey is appointed by the Senat Generall againſt Caeſar haue monie out of the common treaſurie. There was preſent choiſe made of ſouldiers throughout all Italie, warres were proclaimed, and taxes were impoſed vpon the confines, ſuburbes and confederate cities. Caeſar hauing paſſed Rubicon ſeized vpon diuerſe townes of Italie, Piſaurum, Fanum, Ancona, Tignium and Auximon, and he ran ouer all the Picene prouince, with his armie which was forſaken of Lentulus Spinther the gouernour there, and from thence he went to Corfinium, which was held of L. Domitius Ahenobarbus, which he enioyed hauing Domitius alſo in his power, a moſt conſtant friend to Pompey, whoſe ſtandard was at no time aduaunced, but it was worſhipped and followed by Domitius: whome Caeſar did in thisCaeſar pardoneth Domitius. maner greet: Domitius I do franckly pardon thee &amp; all thoſe which belōg to thy charge, &amp; with theſe words I make a perfect diſclaime of anger and emnitie, I giue thee alſo free choiſe and election, whether thou wilt be a captaine in Caeſars campe, or ſtill adhere to Pompey. Domitius not demurring vpon

Caeſars offer, did incontinent fly to Pompey,Domitius flyeth to Pompey. who was then at Brunduſium, and there were many at that time which did obſerue the like faithfulneſſe to Pompey, to whom Caeſar did more plentifully offer the benefite of life, thē they did thankfully receiue it. Caeſar haſted to Brunduſium to aſſault the Conſuls in that place, but failing of his purpoſe he addreſſed toward Rome: there was then in the citie great feare and amazedneſſe, the people calling to memorie the crueltie of Marius, the matrons with their rented haire did diſplay their fearefulneſſe, the young damſels with ſalt teares did blemiſh their faces, their skriking voices &amp; deepe drawne ſighs, did moue the heauens to a ſympathie. The ſilly babes flying as it were from the face of Caeſar, did cleaue to the breaſts of their parents, the ſturdieſt necks did then begin to ſtoope, and the ſtrongeſt hearts to melt, and nothing could be ſeene in Rome but ſignes of ſorrow: for as the earth when ſhe is diſrobed of her budding and fructifying trees, and of her amiable verdure, which is her onely grace and garment roiall, is like a naked table wherein nothing

is painted, ſo was Rome at that inſtant being bereaued of her young and luſtie gentlemen, euen as if the ſpringtide ſhould be taken from the yeare: and a great deformitie did then alſo ariſe by the abſence of the graue and auncient fathers, who with their ſpreading ſhadow did ſhield and protect the bodie of the citie, and did nouriſh the riſing plants of the generous braſill, gathering ſtrength and ſoliditie vnder the curtaine of their boughs. Caeſar hauing entred Rome, vſed all ſorts of men with great kindneſſe and curteſie, and hauing conuocated an aſſemblie declaring and aggrauating vnto them the iniuries of his enemies, he transferred all the blame vpon Pompey, and made a notable pretence, that he was deſirous of vnitie, and that peace was the virgin of his heart. But Caeſars Diamond was nothing elſe but glaſſe, and his words nothing but wind, which at that preſent was clearely and euidently perceiued, for he went in great haſt to the temple of Saturne, where the treaſurie of Rome was before his ranſack inuiolably kept, and at the gates of the temple L. Metellus Tribune of the people did

boldly reſiſt him, and with theſe words entertained him.
            Caeſar the lawes of Rome haue made thisMetellus his ſpeech to Caeſar. place ſacred, thou ſhalt not enter into this temple but through the ſides of Metellus, &amp; no coine ſhalt thou carrie from hence without bloudſhed: vnſheath therefore thy blade, and feare not leſt thy wrongs be eſpied: for alas we are now in a deſolate citie, there be ſo few to condemne thy doings, that there be almoſt none to ſee them: thy priuate and rebellious ſouldiers ſhall not haue their pay out of the treaſurie of Rome, and if thou woldeſt be rich by violence, there be ſtrange wals for thee to batter. Caeſar in this ſort replied vnto him.
            
               Shameleſſe churle as thou art, this righthand ſhall not vouchſafe thee ſo much honor as that thy bloud may ſhine vpon a ſouldiers ſteele. Metellus, thou art not worthie of my wrath, and where thou hoiſſeſt vp the ſaile of lawes and cuſtomes, aſſure thy ſelfe Tribune that the lawes of Rome had rather be cancelled by Caeſar, then confirmed by Metellus. In the end by the earneſt intreatie of his friends,

who were addicted to Caeſar rather for feare then contrarietie of opinion, Metellus gaue place to Caeſar, and he ruſhing ſuddenly intoCaeſar ſeizeth the treaſurie. the temple, cauſed the treaſurie which in many yeares ſpace was leuied by polles, which was gained in the Carthaginian war, and in the victories had againſt Philip Perſeus, and Pirrhus, together with the tribute of Aſia, of Creet, and the wealth which Cato brought from Cypris, and which Pompey purchaſed by his warres, being caried before him when he triumphed, to be laid on aſſes backes, and to be caried as the ſinew and ſupporter of his warres. This was thought the fowleſt act that euer was committed by Caeſar, and it was neuer feared that Rome ſhold be poore by Caeſar. This captaine being as glad for this new bootie as ſome of his friends were ſorie, led his ſouldiers toward Spaine, where AfraniusCaeſar marcheth toward Spaine. and Petreius did rule the affaires vnder Pompey, but he did ſo maſſerate them with famine that he poſſeſt the greateſt part of Spaine, without ſhedding many drops of bloud: then he went into that part of Spaine, which is now called Andeluzia, where M. Varro captaine

to a great number of Veteranes, did hold a forcelet, but he being daunted with the preſence of Caeſar, reſigned all the prouince into his hands: thē he marched toward Dirrachio, taking by the way Orichum and Apollonia an Vniuerſitie towne, where his Nephew Octauius was taught at that time in the liberall artes and ſciences, who is ſaid to haue accō
               panied his vncle in the warres following, but becauſe it is a tradition of more antiquitie then credit, I do rather note it then affirme it. The fortune that Caeſar had, and the credite which Pompey enioyed in forraine nations, were two enticing lures, that drew to their ſeueral campes a great multitude of forrainers. To the aſſiſtance of Pompey from the coaſt ofThe forreiners which were readie in armes for the aſſiſtāce of Pompey. Greece which lyeth about the rockes of Cyrrha, and the clouen hill of Parnaſſus, came a great armie of the Phocenſeans, from Thebes and the regions thereabout came the Baeotians, the Piſaeans, and the Sicanians: from the townes that lye vnder Maenalus and OEte came the Dryopes, the Threſpoti, and the Sellians: from Creet and Gortyna a number of good archers did preſent themſelues to

Pompey: from Dardania, from Colchis, and the ſhore of the Adriaticke ſea, the Athamāts, Enchelians and diuerſe others: beſides theſe flocked vnto him thouſands from Babylon, Damaſcus, and Phrygia, together with the Idumaeans, Tyrians, Sidonians and Phaenicians: there came alſo from Tarſus, from Cilicia, from India, Perſia, Armenia, Arabia, and Aethiopia. For the aide of Caeſar there cameThe ſtraungers which were aſſiſtāt to Caeſar. many Scythians, Hircanians, and from diuerſe regions beyond the hill Taurus: likewiſe the Lacedaemonians, the Sarmatians, the Lydians, the Eſſedones, the Arimaſpians, the Maſſagites, the Mores, the Gelonians, the Marmarians, the Memnonians and they that dwell beyond the pillers of Hercules were readie in armour and ſhewed themſelues ſeruiceable to Caeſars commaund. Cn. Pompeius partly to welcome the ſtraungers that came to Dirrachio, and partly to encourage the Romanes which did follow him, and to make the cauſe of the vndertaken warre manifeſt to them all, the Nobles and Senators ſitting round about him in harneſſe, vſed this ſpeech vnto them.
            
               Let it not any whit diſmay you friendlyPompey his oration to his ſouldiers forreiners, and faithfull harted Romanes, that you are now farre from the wals of the taken citie, and if the Italian ingenuitie, and the heate of the Romane bloud be as yet warme within the Romanes, let them not marke vpon what earth they ſtand, ſo they ſtand vpon the ground of a good and lawfull quarrell. It is I truſt euident to you all that we are the Senate: for if we were in the vtmoſt climate of the world, aud directly vnder the freezing waine of the Northerne Beare, yet in our hands ſhould be the adminiſtration and regiment of the affaires of Italie. VVhen Camillus was at Veios Rome was there alſo, and the Romanes forſaking their houſes, did neuer chaunge their lawes. Now is Rome Caeſars captiue, and a ſort of ſorrowfull hearts hath he there in hold, emptie houſes, ſilent lawes, and cloſe courts: we are here as the puniſhers of Caeſars faults▪ and the armor which we now beare, is but onely the wrath of reuengefull Rome. Caeſars warfare is as iuſt as Catilines, and when he ſhould be like to the Scipioes, and the Marcelli, he falleth into the

rebellious faction of C. Marius, Lepidus, Carbo, Sertorius: and yet in truth I honour him too much to conſort him with theſe. He maketh accompt of me as of one withered, halfe dead and foredone with yeares: but it is better for you to haue an ancient captaine, then for Caeſar to leade an armie of ſpent and outworne Veteranes. And though the age which hope doth follow be farre more plauſible and acceptable, then that which death doth purſue, yet wiſedome and experience proceede from elder times, &amp; the head whoſe haires reſemble the feathers of the ſwan is a Senate houſe to a good armie. And if I may not be a ſouldier, yet I will be the example of a ſouldier vnto you. The aeſtimation that I haue alwaies had amongſt you Romanes, by whoſe meanes I haue bene extolled to that honour, aboue which neuer any Romane citizen did aſcend, may warrant my warfare. VVith vs alſo are both the Cōſuls, with vs the armies of many forraine kings &amp; potentates. Is Caeſar trow you ſo venturous, becauſe he warred ſo lōg againſt the vnruly French? why it was but a ſporting practiſe, more fit to

traine his ſouldiers, then to merite triumph: or hath his fortune againſt the Germaines raiſed his courage, he went not ſo ſpeedily to the Germaines as he departed from them, and rather fearing them then feared of them, he called the Germaine ſea the whirlepit of hell? or doth his bloud begin to boile within him, becauſe the fame of his furie did ſuddēly driue the Senators out of their houſes and harbours? VVhen I diſplayed my blazing enſigne vpon the Ponticke ſea, the Ocean was no more traced with the pirate ſhips, but they did all crowd into a narrow corner of the earth. Mithridates that vntamed prince, who long expected when victorie ſhould flie from Rome, I enforced to take his pauillion, in which he died like a fugitiue coward, &amp; therin I was more fortunate then the moſt fortunate Sylla. There is no part of the world without my trophees, and what land ſoeuer lyeth vnder the ſunne, hath either bene vanquiſhed or terrified by Pompey: and I haue left no warre for Caeſar, but this which now he maintaineth, in which though he ouercome, yet he ſhall neuer triumph. VVherefore the nearer

Caeſar doth approch vnto you, the more let your courage riſe, or if words cannot preuaile, imagine that you are now vpon the banckes of Tiber, and that the Romane matrons ſtanding vpon the wals of the citie, with ſtreaming teares, and diſperſed hairelockes, do exhort you and intreate you to fight: Imagine that out of the gates of the citie the old and grayheaded fathers, that are notable to weild weapons do proſtrate vnto your feete their hoarie heades, requiring ſuccour and defence of you: and thinke that Rome herſelf fearing a tyrant boweth vnto you: thinke that the infants which are alreadie borne, &amp; which hereafter ſhall be borne, haue mingled their common teares, and that they which as yet neuer ſaw the light, deſire to be borne free, and they which do now liue deſire to dy free: and if all this will not ſerue, then Pompey (if he may ſo debaſe the maieſtie of a Generall) with his wife and children will fal before your feet. But this is my laſt beheſt that I require of you, let not Pompey who in his youth hath alwaies honored you, be diſhonored through your default in his dying yeares, for your

ſelues, for your kindred, your freedome and good eſtate. I proteſt thus much, that I will neuer returne to Rome but I will carrie peace in my hand, and the Oliue braunch ſhall be my enſigne. The Romanes were greatly emboldened hearing theſe words, ſeeing their Generall ſo youthfully minded, &amp; as it were refined in the mould of Mars. VVherefore they expected Caeſar with prepared minds. And Caeſar hauing now praefected gouernors ouer Orichum and Apollonia, made great haſt to Dirrachio, in which place at his firſt comming Pompey gaue him the onſet, andPompey putteth Caeſar to flight. made him to flie hauing loſt a great part of his armie: and though M. Antonius came notM. Antonius helpeth Caeſar. long after to Caeſar with a freſh ſupply, ready to face and breſt the enemie, yet Pompey did ſo plague thē with continuall warring againſt them, when he ſaw cōuenient time; that Caeſars victuals being almoſt waſted, he was faine through penurie of corne to flye into Theſſali, and Pompey ſpeedily purſuing him in the champion plaine of Pharſalia, pitched his tents directly againſt Caeſars. In Pompeis campe all things were glorious, magnificent,

and glittering in ſhew: in Caeſars all things powerfull, actiue, and ſtrong. The Romanes being thus deuided both parties were greatly enflamed with deſire of fight: Pompeis ſouldiers were readie to depriue him of the enſignes, and to enter the field without a Generall: ſo deliberatiue was that noble Captaine of their welfare, and ſo deſperate were they and careleſſe what befell vpon them. In Pompey there was this deſire and thought to ouercome with as little bloudſhed as might be. But what fiends and damned ſpirits diddeſt thou inuocate Caius Caeſar? what Stygian furies, what infernall hagges, and what nightly terrors dideſt thou intreat? to what Eumenides diddeſt thou ſacrifice, intending ſuch a generall ſlaughter? Pompey being earneſtly vrged by his ſouldiers thought good to marſhall his men, and to ſet the armie as might be moſt conuenient for the ſoile whereon they were to combate. The left wing of the armiePompey marſhalleth his armie. was committed to L. Lentulus, the leading of the right wing had L. Domitius, the ſtrength and middeſt of the battell did wholly relie vpon P. Scipio: vpon the bankes and

ſides of the riuers did march the Cappadocians &amp; Ponticke horſemen: in the brode field were Tetrarches, Kings, and Princes, and all the purpled Lords that were tributarie to Rome: Pompeis ſquadrons were furniſhed with many Romanes, Italians, and Spaniards. Caeſar ſeeing his enemies to haue diſcended into the plaine, was heartily glad that ſo good occaſion was offred him, and that the day was come which with a million of wiſhes he called for: wherefore departing out of his tents and marſhalling his ſouldiers he made toward Pompey. In this battell, the fathers face was directly againſt the ſonnes, the brother was preparing himſelfe againſt his brother, the vncle was the firſt that leuelled at the nephew, and he that did ſlay moſt of his kindred was accompted moſt couragious. VVhen the trū
               pets denounced the warres, and gaue a ſigne of fight, the Caeſarians did fiercely giue aſſaultThe Caeſarians giue the firſt aſſault. to the Pompeians. The force and vigor of the warre did conſiſt in the launces, ſpeares, and ſwords, which Pompey had well prouided againſt, by ioyning the targets one with another, ſo that Caeſar had much ado to breake

the array: but fearing leſt his foremen ſhould faint, he cauſed the tranſuers legions to follow his enſigne, who as it were with a ſidewind aduenturing vpon Pōpeis armie, ſtroke them downe on each ſide ſo faſt as they went. The barded horſe being incenſed with the heate of the warre, his heart being boared with the point of the ſpeare, exempted himſelfe from the reine. The Barbarians being not able to reſtraine them gaue way to Caeſar, and the foming ſteede being now the regent of the field, the fight was confuſed and diſordered: for vpon whom the dart did vncertainly light, leauing their horſes perforce they lay groning and groueling on the earth, till the hoofes of the arrearing courſers did cruſh the veile of their braines. Caeſar was now come to the heart and center of Pompeis armie, but the night drew on which made both ſides pauſe: Caeſar did thanke his ſouldiers, and gliding through euery troope and band of them, he did put nouriſhing oile into their burning wrath. He tooke view of their ſwords, curiouſly obſeruing whoſe weapon was ouerflowed with bloud, and whoſe

was dipped at the point, whoſe hand did trē
               ble and whoſe was ſtedfaſt, who changed the countenance through feare, &amp; who through furie, and caſting his eyes on the proſtrate carcaſſes, frowning vpon them with curled forehead, as not yet ſatisfied he fed his irefull lookes with the deſolate aſpect of his ſlaine countriemen, but if he perceiued a gaſpe in the fleſh of his owne ſouldiers, he would endeuour to cloſe it vp with his hand, &amp; giuing them words of comfort and encouragement did ſooner heale them then indeede they were healed. At the dawning of the day next enſuing, and at the firſt entrance of that mornings bloudie houres, when the welkin had put aſide the vizard of the night, the ſtarres being couered and the earth diſcouered by the Sunne, Caeſar giuing his ſouldiers new ſwords, new darts, ſpeares and launces, and awaking their courage, giuing them alſo to vnderſtand with the point of his launce, in what part of the aduerſe armie the forreine kings, the Conſuls, the Senators, and the nobilitie were placed, directed them as it were by aime, to gage the bodies of many excellēt

men, who entangling their weapons in the intrals of theſe noble enemies, did throw to the ground &amp; to extreme ruine many princely potentates: many reuerent perſons were buried in go are: many of the Lepidi, of the Metelli, of the Coruini and Torquati: but amongſt the reſt the fortune of Domitius was dolorous and deſpitefull, he as before hath bene ſaid, was once pardoned and diſmiſſed of Caeſar, but now was ſingled out by Caeſar and grieuouſly wounded, but yet ſo great was his mind that he would not ſtoope to begge a ſecond pardon, whome Caeſar looking vpon like a tyrant, and ſeeing him rowle his fainting members in the moiſtned duſt, did with this bitterneſſe inſult, giuing him theCaeſar his ſpeech to Domitius. ſcornefull gaze: L. Domitius now I hope at length you wil forſake your maiſter Pompey, hereafter I truſt you will practiſe no enmitie againſt Caeſar. But as good fortune would, he had as yet breath enough to replie in theſe few words. Caeſar I dy a free man, and I go to the region of Proſerpina, not ſeeing thee as a conquerour, but as yet inferiour to Pompey, and euen at my death am I refreſhed with this

hope, that thou liueſt to be ſubdued by the rigor of deſtinie, which wil take reuenge both for vs, and for thy ſonne in law. Hauing ſpoken theſe words his life fled from him, and his ſight was taken away with a dreadful darkneſſe, by whoſe wounds ſo much bloud was not loſt, as there was glorie gained. For he gaue a cleare token of an honorable mind, accompting it a great deale better to haue dignitie without life, then life without dignitie. But Caeſar thinking nothing to be done if any thing were vndone, ragingly and earneſtly did ſeeke for the perſon of Pompey, &amp; ruſhing into the thicke of his ſouldiers, neuer ſtretched out his arme without deaths warrant, and neuer looked backe but when he ſaw none to fight withall. Pompey ſtanding a farre off on the top of an hill, ſeeing the fields to ſwimme with bloud, and the Romane Senate to be nothing now but an heape of carcaſſes, and that his owne decay was ſought for by the bloud of a multitude, reſeruing himſelfe to ſome better fortune, forſooke the field and fled to Lariſſa. Caeſar perceiuing it,Pompey flieth to Lariſſa. thought it better to giue ſome reſt to his armie,

then with a ſudden purſuite to make after him: wherefore he retired his ſouldiers, &amp; came to Pompeys tents. VVhen the wandering night was chaſed frō the inferiour Iſlands by the recourſing day, and the Sunne had imparted his brightneſſe to our vnder-neighbors, and the dreames were readie to poſſeſſe the Theater of the fancie, the weariſome creatures of the world declining to their reſt: the Caeſarians hauing ranſacked Pompeis tents, and refreſhed their fainting bodies with the viand there left, betooke themſelues to their eaſe, and repoſed their wearied limmes in theſe plots which the Pompeians did before lodge in. But how ſhall I deſcribe the deformitie of that night, in which hell did breath out the ghoſts of them that were ſlaine, the aire was infected with contagious vapours, and the ſtarres trembled at the beholding of the vncouth Stygians? Sleepe did bring no quietneſſe vnto them, but flames, murmurs, horrors, and the hideous ſounds of the skrikingThe dreams and viſions of the Caeſarians. Harpies. The ghoſt of the ſlaughtered Romane did appeare vnto them, and euery mans fancie was a fiend vnto him: ſome did

thinke that they beheld the image of a young man, ſome of an old man, others did dreame that their brethren were come to take reuēge on them, but in Caeſars mind were all theſe terrors: the ſlaine Senate did ſeeme to encō
               paſſe him on all ſides, brandiſhing their fierie ſwords, ſweating, frying and dropping with roſen and ſulpher, and the greateſt torment of all was a guiltie conſcience. He was now moleſted with the powers of hell, when his enemies that ſuruiued ſlept quietly in Lariſſa. Pompey after his miſhap in Pharſalie made ſpeedie voiage toward Egipt where PtolomePompey trauelleth to Egypt. did raigne: for Pompey hauing procured the reſtitutiō of his father to the throne of Egipt, and with many other ſinguler benefites hauing deſerued his fauour, thought that the young Prince in a kind regard wold haue entertained him according to his honour and deſert: but who doth buſie his memorie in recounting benefites? and who will thinke himſelfe beholden to one that is diſtreſſed? and when doth not fortune chaunge friendſhip? Ptolome, vnthankfull Ptolome, diſleagued with the ſenſleſſe litargie of foule ingratitude,

when by certaine report he heard that Pompey had approched to the ſhore, ſent out his dire and dreadfull meſſengers to depriue the aged bodie of the vnuanquiſhed mind. And when Achilles that bold butcherer did with his glaiue portend the laſt end of his daies, Pompey whoſe excellent qualities might encline a maſſagite to mercie, craued with conſtant countenance but a word or two of them, and as for life he was content to leaue it: the ſauage helhound would ſcarcely condeſcend to this requeſt, but at length his tygers heart yeelded, and Pompey in few words wiſhing to the Romanes libertie, to his wife comfort, to his ſonnes ſafetie, was beheaded by theſePompey is beheaded by the Egyptiās mercileſſe Egyptians, and his head was born as a preſent to Ptolome, which was farre too good a preſent for ſo lewde a prince. But how falſe was this world to Pompey, who had not now earth enough for his ſepulture, to whom before the earth was too little for his cōqueſt: but rare is that bird whoſe feathers do not moult, and happie is that man whoſe glorie doth not eclipſe. Caeſar made haſt after Pompey with an hote and earneſt purſuite, not

knowing that he was praeuented of the prize which he aimed at, and as the beaſts which nature hath placed in the wilderneſſe, when poore pilgrimes walke by their ſolitarie and vncouth dens, runne all together with one rage, hunting their footſteps, euery one thinking to purchaſe the pray, the Lion, the Leopard, the Beare, the Beuer, the Tiger, the Luzerne and the VVolfe, making the woods to ring with hollow outcries. So the Caeſarians did enquire and make after Pompey, amazing the ſeas with ſounding trumpets, drums, fifes, and ſhawmes, and neuer ceaſſed their purſuite till they were arriued in Egipt, where they were roially entertained of CleopatraCaeſar entertained of Cleopatra. the Egyptian princeſſe, who with complaint and mournfull melodie, did allure Caeſar, admiring her ſingular beautie, to tame and ſuppreſſe the pride of Ptolome, who had then deforced her from her ſoueraigne eſtate. Caeſar did not deny this faire Oratreſſe, hauing alreadie perſwaded him, if her toung had bin ſilent. Mars ſpent a long time with Venus, and before his departure from thence Cleopatra was another Calphurnia vnto him. But why

do I name Calphurnia? For what proportion can there be betwixt a chaſt matron and a ſhameleſſe curtizan. Caeſar labouring to reſtore Cleopatra to her former dignitie was ſuddenly aſſaulted by the king of Egypt withCaeſar is aſſaulted by the king of Egypt. an huge armie, and in that warre he was driuen to many extremities, the conduit pipes were cut a ſunder, and he was beſieged on euery ſide being as yet in Cleopatraes pallace, but in the end wraſtling out of theſe misfortunes, he gaue battell to the Egyptians at Pharoes, and conueying himſelfe into a gallie for the defence and ſafegard of his fleete which was grieuouſly toſt, he was ſo vexed and ſhaken by his enemies, that he was faine to leaue his gally, and ſwimming a great way in the riuer of Nilus, returned with great difficultieCaeſar ſwimmeth in the riuer of Nilus to his armie, but at the laſt encountring the Egyptians at Alexandria, he put the king and his whole armie to the ſword: and in theſe warres was burnt the notable librarie of Ptolomeus Philadelphus, but much againſt Caeſars mind, who as he was ſpecially learned ſo he made ſpeciall accompt of that monument of learning. Caeſar hauing raiſed Cleopatra

to her priſtinate roialtie, departed from Egypt and haſtened toward Vtica, but in the way being enformed that Pharnaces the ſon of Mithridates, whome Pompey when he had finiſhed the warre againſt Mithridates, had made king of Boſphorus, had ſubtracted from the Romanes, and atchieued to himſelf Cappadocia, Colchis, Armenia, and part of Pontus: Caeſar ſent againſt him Domitius Caluinus,Caeſar addreſſeth againſt Pharnaces. whoſe armie was diſcomfited by Pharnaces. Caeſar did then in perſon make expedition againſt him, and aſſaulting him at Zelia, cauſed him at the firſt ioyning of battell to flye, and hauing entred Boſphorus, he wasCaeſar putteth Pharnaces to flight. ſlaine of Aſander the author of his inuaſions. VVhileſt Caeſar was marching toward Vtica, M. Cato diſdaining to receiue life at the hāds of Caeſar, and greatly perplexed in mind that a man ſo rebelliouſly bent ſhould haue ſo proſperous fortune, did with violent handsM. Cato killeth himſelfe determine his daies. Caeſar hauing taken Vtica as he was returning to Rome, did encounter P. Scipio on the ſeas, who ſeeking byCaeſar encountreth P. Scipio. all warlike meanes to preſerue the ſlender ſparckle of his dying life, was at length ſlaine.

and Caeſar ſayling from thence enſhoared in Sardinia, and making no long tarriance in that place, came the fiue and twentieth day of that moneth, which beares his name at this day to the citie of Rome, where he was welcomed with ſuch applauſe, ſuch gratulation, with ſuch melodie, with ſo rare banquets, and with ſo gorgious ſhewes, that Pompeis death was not bewailed with halfe ſo many teares, as he was entertained with ioyes, and for the ſealing of their good affection towards him, they did grant to him by a fourefold triumph to enlarge his fame. A triumph was a moſt excellentWhat thing a triumph was amongſt the Romans &amp; how performed. honour, which the captaine who by battell had ouercome his enemies, returning with his armie into the citie did at the firſt enioy by the decree of the Senate, and afterward by the conſent of the people. It was called a triumph becauſe the ſouldiers did crye along the ſtreete as they went to the Capitolle, Io triumph. Surely the Romanes did greatly aduantage themſelues by the vſing of theſe triumphes, for by them men were animated to warlike exploits. But many thinke a common-weale then onely to flouriſh, whē
               
it hath peace and plentie, but being moued with the preſent face of things, and not forecaſting the ſequele, they ſlip into errour, and foſter in their minds fond opinions, for plentie breedeth ſecuritie, ſecuritie warre, warre deſolation. The ſtate of a countrey is then to be tearmed proſperous, when it is throughly furniſhed with men able and ſufficient to repulſe forreine forces, with the prouentions of the earth, and other treaſures of husbandrie. But how canſt thou aſſure thy ſelfe of free and peaceable inioying of the riches of thy countrey, the ſpace of one moneth without militarie diſcipline? For all regions except thoſe which are ſituate vnder the extremitie of the climates, are enuironed with the circumference of other nations, from which warre may ariſe as eaſily, as the winde bloweth from the foure quarters of the world, in which dangerous accident the firſt and laſt refuge of humane helpes is the ſoldiers arme. Doubtleſſe the Romanes were exquiſite in all heroicall deſert, but in their bountie and beneficence to ſouldiers incomparably excellent: for they knew, that the prouinces and Ilands adiacent

could not be wonne by home ſitting, or by a treatie of words: but they muſt gird their armour, confront their enemies, and exchange bloud for bloud, and when theſe countreyes were conquered, &amp; they had taſted the ſweet of the vintage, which the ſouldiers had gathered, they did not reward them with ſower grapes, neither powred they vineger into their wounds, but aſſigned vnto them penſionarie lands, for their maintenance, and making thē franke allowance of ample rewards, encouraged them with crownes of glorie, triumphs, honors and dignities, ſo that victorie flouriſhed there where armes were fauoured. Surely Princes &amp; potentates ought with tender indulgence to reſpect the infatigable paines of the ſouldier, leſt he murmur and ſay when he goeth to the fight, I ſhall either be ouercome, or ſlaine: and ſo be wholly ſubiect to the will and diſpoſall of mine enemie, or elſe be partaker of the victorie, and returne into my country, as into a pitched field, where I ſhall fight with penurie, contempt and vnthankfulneſſe, the laſt of which being either in the enemies chaines, or in the number of

his dead men, I ſhould neuer haue felt. But if the ſouldiers induſtrie be not quickened and ſtirred vp by bountie and reward, he hath no more will to performe any part of martial ſeruice, then a dead coarſe hath power to ariſe out of the graue. For what can be more precious to a man then his bloud, being the foū
               taine and nurſe of his vitall ſpirits, and the ground of his bodily ſubſtance, which no free and ingenuous nature will looſe or hazard for nothing. And in truth there is great ods in the euent, for the ſouldier may either be ſlaine and ſo die without receiuing of his ſalarie, or elſe be wounded and die vnder the cure, and ſo receiue his ſtipend to the halfe part. This account being thus caſt, it falleth out that the ſouldier looſeth all or ſome part, &amp; the Prince who is his pay-maiſter, ſaueth either all or ſome part. And whoſoeuer ſhall argument or diſcourſe vpon found reaſon, and infallible experience, may eaſily proue and conuince, that theſe commō-weales haue moſt proſpered, which haue liberally maintained and had in ſingular regard militarie artes. The mentioning of Caeſars triumph hath occaſioned

me to vſe this digreſſion. This word Triumphus is deriued of the Greeke name of Bacchus 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , who hauing ſubdued India, was the firſt inuenter of this honor. Of triumphs there were two ſorts obſerued of the Romans, one the graund triumph, which by praeheminence was called Triumphus, the other was the pettie triumph, and was commonly called Ouatio, of theſe triumphs ſome were done on land, ſome on ſea, ſome in the citie, ſome on mount Albane. It was therefore called Ouatio, becauſe the victoriate ſouldiers returning from the fight did ſhowte, and double the letter O. An Ouation did much differ frō a triumph, becauſe he which came into the citie by way of Ouation, was neither caried in chariot, nor cladde with robe triumphall, nor with any ornament of eſtate, neither did his armie march before him when he was entred the citie, neither was he crowned with laurel, nor brought in with ſound of trumpets, but walked through the citie on foot, his head being adorned with a mirtle crowne, his ſouldiers following him, and the ſhawmes onely ſounding. How the great triumph was celebrated,

may be perceiued by this of Caeſars which was thus performed.
            Caius Caeſar ſitting in a rich and ſumptuousCaeſar his triumphs deſcribed. chariot, bordred round about with the crownes of Princes, his vpper garment being of purpled tiſſue, and beſpanged with lines of gold, his victorious armie marching before him garniſhed with the ſpoiles of Europa and Affrick, his captiues being boūd with chaines, which were tied to his chariots taile, did repreſent a wonderfull maieſtie to the gazing people: the trumpets and the clarions did ſound on each ſide. His firſt triumph diſplaiedCaeſars firſt triumph. with a moſt radiant ſtanderd, the ſpoiles and conqueſts which he had in Fraunce: the images of Rhodanus and Rhene were wrought in ſiluer, the ſtreames were curiouſly deciphered, and the waues did ſeeme to riſe with a naturall and reall flowing. In the ſecond triumphCaeſars ſecond triūph. ſtood the citie of Alexandria, and after it the armes of vanquiſhed Ptolome were blazed, the riuer of Nilus was painted with a faire caeleſtiall blew: the azured waues being compacted of coſtly glaſſe. In the third triumphCaeſars third triumph. was a maske of Ponticke mourners, &amp;

the coarſe of Pharnaces was then caried in triumph: vpō the top of the coffin ſtood a triple plume, on the one part of which was written VENI, on the other VIDI, on the third VICI. In the fourth triumph Affrike went as captiue,Caeſars fourth triumph. and the perſon of Iuba king of Mauritania, his armes pictured as hauing mannacles of them was then alſo reſembled. For his victorie at Pharſalia there was no triumph, becauſe Pō
               pey was a Romane. VVhen Rome with ſmiling countenance had beheld theſe ſhewes, Caeſar accompanied with the Romane nobilitie entred the Capitolle, and there with ſpiced fires and fragrant odours did ſacrifice to Iupiter. After his thankes, vowes, and prayers perfourmed, he returned with the great applauſe and admiration of men, and amiddeſt other ſolemnities, Criſpus Saluſtius did greet him with this Oration.
            I know that it is a difficult and hard matterSaluſtes oration to Caeſar. to giue counſell to a king, or Emperour, or to any man that is highly aduaunced, becauſe they haue ſtore of counſellers, &amp; there is none ſo wiſe and warie, who can giue certaine aduiſe of that which is to come. Againe, bad

counſelles are manie times better liked then good, becauſe fortune dallieth in things, and fancy in men according to their pleaſure. But I had a great minde in my youth, to handle matters of ſtate, and in knowing of them I beſtowed great labour and trauell, not to this end onely, that I might obtaine ſome place of dignitie in the common-weale, which manie by euill artes and vnlawfull meanes haue cō
                  paſſed, but that I might alſo fully know the eſtate of the common-weale, as well in peace as in warre, and how much by munition, by men, and by monie it could do. Therefore toſſing many things in my mind this was my reſolution, to praeferre thy dignitie Caeſar before mine owne fame, and modeſtie, and to put anything in practiſe ſo I might procure glorie to thee. And this I did not raſhly or to flatter thee, but becauſe in thee amongſt the reſt, I find one skill very maruellous, that thy mind hath bene greater in aduerſitie, then in proſperitie. But with others it is a matter of more accompt and reckening, that men be ſooner wearie with praiſing thy valor, then thy ſelfart wearied with doing things worthie

of praiſe. Surely I hold it for a rule, that nothing can be fet from the depth of inuention, which is not readie to thy thought. And if this purpoſe ſhould onely raigne in thy breſt to deliuer thy ſelfe from the furie of enimies, and how thou maieſt retaine the fauour and good liking of the people, thou ſhould do a thing vnworthie of thy vertue. But if that mind be as yet reſident in thee, which from the beginning diſturbed the faction of ſeditious men, which brought the Romanes from the heauie yoake of ſeruitude vnto libertie, which without weapons did confound the armies of thine enemies, whereof haue enſued ſo many and ſo glorious actes both at home and abrode, that thy foes cannot complaine of any thing but of thine excellencie, then receiue from me ſuch things, as of the ſumme or ſtate of the common-weale I ſhall deliuer: which doubtleſſe thou ſhalt either find to be true, or elſe certainly not farre from the truth. There is no man brought vp in a free eſtate, who doth willingly yeeld ſuperioritie to another, and though the mightier man be by nature of a good and mild diſpoſition, yet because

when he will he may be wicked and iniurious, he is therefore feared: which hapneth becauſe many great men are peruerſly minded, and thinke themſelues ſo much the ſafer, by how much more they do permit other mē ouer whom they rule, to be wicked &amp; vniuſt. But ſurely a contrarie courſe ſhould be taken, when the Prince is good himſelfe, to labour and indeuour likewiſe to make the people good. For euery bad fellow doth moſt vnwillingly beare a gouernour, but this to thee Caeſar is of greater difficultie, then to others who haue ruled before thee: thy warre hath bene more mild then the peace of other mē: beſides they which did ouercome, do demaund the ſpoile, they which are ouercome are their fellow citizens. Through theſe difficulties muſt thou paſſe. And ſtrengthen the common-weale for ſucceeding poſteritie, not by weapons, nor as againſt enemies, but which is farre greater and more difficult, by peaceable meanes. Therefore to this point the ſtate of things doth call euery man either of great or of meane wiſedome, to vtter as much good as he can concerning this matter.

For mine owne part this I thinke, that as by thee the victorie ſhall be qualified and ordered, ſo ſhall all things follow. Thou diddeſt wage battell noble Caeſar with an excellent man, of great power, and deſirous of glorie, a man of greater fortune then wiſedome, followed by ſome few, enemies both to thee &amp; to themſelues, ſuch as either affinitie did draw vnto him, or ſome other bond of dutie: for none of them was partaker of his dominatiō,Pompey could not brooke an equall. which he could not tollerate. For if he could haue brooked an equall, the world had not bene ſet on fire with warre: but becauſe thou art deſirous to eſtabliſh peace, and vpon this anuill thou and thy friends do continually beate, conſider I pray thee of what nature the thing is whereof you conſult. Certainly I haue this conceit, that becauſe all things which haue beginning muſt haue end, when the fate and determined lot of deſtruction ſhall fall vpon this citie, that our citizens will contend and make warre againſt their fellow citizens, and ſo being wearied and conſumed will become a pray to ſome forraigne king or nation: otherwiſe, not the whole world, nor all

the people vnder the arch of the heauens being muſtred or aſſembled together, ſhall be able to ſhake or cruſh this flouriſhing common-weale. Therefore the good effects of concord are to be maintained, and the euils of diſcord to be baniſhed and driuen away: that may eaſily come to paſſe, if thou abridge the licence of riotous ſpending, and iniurious extorting, becauſe young gentlemen in theſe times are inured to ſuch a faſhion, that they thinke it a glorious matter vainly to miſpend their owne goods and the goods of other mē, denying nothing to their owne luſt, nor to the ſhameleſſe requeſt of their leud companions: and their reſtleſſe mind hauing entred into a crooked way, and diſſolute courſe, whē their maintenance faileth them, and wonted ſupplies are wanting, do conceiue a burning indignation againſt their fellow citizens, and turne all things out of courſe. In that commō
                  weale all things are well ordered, where offices and dignities are not ſold, and where ambition enioyeth not the rewards of vertue: this and all other euils ſhall ceaſe when mony ſhall ceaſe to be honoured, where riches are

precious, there all good things are vile: faith, honeſtie, modeſtie, chaſtitie, becauſe there is but one way to vertue, and that is hard and rough, but to mony there be many ſmooth waies: it is gained as well by euill as by good meanes. Couetouſneſſe is a ſauage and deuouring beaſt, immane, &amp; intollerable: which way ſo euer it wendeth, it waſteth, &amp; deſtroyeth townes, fields, temples and houſes: it mingleth holy and humane things together: neither armes nor wals can ſtop the courſe of it. It ſpoileth and bereaueth men of fame, children, countrie and parents: but if thou debaſe the high accompt of monie, the force of couetouſneſſe by good manners will be abated. I haue by reading found, that all kingdomes, cities, and nations haue ſo long enioyed a proſperous eſtate, whilſt true aduiſe did preuaile in them: but whenſoeuer fauour, feare, or pleaſure was the ſterne or motiue of their counſels, then their wealth was firſt diminiſhed, next their dominion abridged, and laſtly, their libertie impeached. VVherefore I beſeech and exhort thee renowned Caeſar, that thou wouldeſt not ſuffer ſuch a goodly dominion

as this to be tainted with ruſt, or by diſcord rented in peeces. If that thing happen, neither night nor day will appeaſe the ſtorms of thy mind, but by dreames being rowzed from thy bed, thou ſhalt be chaſed and purſued with continuall cares. I haue diſpatched in few ſuch things as I accompted honorable for thee Caeſar, and neceſſarie for this common-weale. The moſt part of men to iudge of others, haue ſufficient conceit, at leaſt in their owne conceit, and to reprooue an other mans deeds or words, euery mans mind doth burne with deſire. They thinke their throat is not wide enough, nor their toung glib enough to poure out of their breaſts their malicious exceptions, to whoſe cenſure that I am ſubiect, doth ſo little ſhame me, that it would haue grieued me to haue bene ſilent: for, whether it ſhall pleaſe thee to follow this courſe or ſome better, I ſhall not be mooued: ſith I haue ſpoken as much as my barrenneſſe could bring foorth. It remaineth for me and for vs all to wiſh, that ſuch things as thou ſhalt in wiſedome effect, the gods would proſper. Caeſar afterward to match his foure triumphs,

was made the fourth time Conſul: his ſtatueThe great honors beſtowed vpon Caeſar. alſo was placed amongſt the ſtatues of the auncient kings: in the Senat-houſe there was a throne of iuorie made for him: in the theater his roome was ſuch, as it contained pleaſure, pompe, and coſt: his image was exquiſitly painted in the Orcheſter, a place wherein the Romaine gentlemen did vſe to daunce and vaut: the moneth of Iuly was then alſo cōſecrated to Iulius, as the moneth of March is to Mars. Caeſar did not reſt in theſe honors, but thought ſtill to propagate his fame by warlike exploits. VVherefore hearing that Pōpeis ſons did raiſe great tumults &amp; vprores in Spaine, he made great haſt thitherward, &amp; at the towne of Siuill oppoſed himſelfe to Cn.Caeſar fighteth with Cn. Pōpeius the younger at the citie of Siuill. Pompeius one of the ſonnes of Pompey the Great, who was conſtrained to flye, but Labienus met him at vnawares, and hauing ſlaine him, brought his head to Caeſar. Sex. Pompeius his brother eſcaped by flight.
            ⸪
         
         
            
            
               ATROPOS, Or the third Booke.
            
               THe warre in Spaine being quickly diſpatched, Caeſar returned to Rome: and the Romanes did redouble hisThe Romans beſtow many honors vpon Caeſar. honours, for he was preſently made Dictator perpetuall, Cenſor perpetuall, Conſull for ten yeares, and Emperour of Rome: he was called alſo the father of his countrie. But Caeſars fortunes did ſoone after begin to decline, and theſe diuerſe coloured titles were but as reinebowes, which do glitter gallantly for a time, but are ſuddenly extinct: his fatall houre was now approching, and enuie ſtayed in the cloudes expecting his end. But as a mightie and huge oake, being clad with the exuuials and trophes of enemies, fenced with an armie of boughs, garniſhed with a coate of barke as hard as ſteele, deſpiſeth the force and power of the windes,

as being onely able to dallie with the leaues, and not to weaken the roote; but the Northerne wind that ſtrong champion of the airie region, ſecretly lurking in the vault of ſome hollow cloud, doth firſt murmur at this aſpiring oake, and then doth ſtrike his creſt with ſome greater ſtrength, and laſtly with the deepeſt breath of his lungs doth blow vp the roote. So vndoubtedly was it with Caeſar, who diſdained feare, and thought it a great deale better to die then to thinke on misfortune: but deſtinie is no mans drudge, and death is euery mans conqueror, matching the ſcepter with the ſpade, and the crowned king with the praiſleſſe peaſant. As none was more noble then Caeſar, ſo nothing was more notable, then the death of Caeſar: for his deareſt friēds became his greateſt enemies, and their hands plucked him downe, whoſe ſhoulders did lift him vp. Many cauſes were pretended of theThe cauſes of the conſpiracie bent againſt Caeſar. conſpiracie bent againſt him, the honours which were beſtowed vpon him, being both manie and great, did cauſe him to be enuied of the Nobles: and likewiſe it was a matter of cauill, becauſe ſitting before temple of Venus

genitrix the Senate comming to him to conſult with him of great affaires, he did ſit and welcome them, and did not riſe vnto them: another occaſion of quarell was, becauſe M. Antonius would haue ſet a Diademe vpon his head: the fourth cauſe was, becauſe he depriued Epidius, Metellus, and Ceſetius Flauius of the Tribuneſhip: fiftly it was greatly murmured, becauſe it was conſtantly reported, that L. Cotta Quindecemuir that is a cōtemplatiue reader of Sybillaes prophecies, would pronounce ſentence, that becauſe it was contained in the prophecies of Sybilla, that the Parthians could not be ouercome but by a king, therefore Caeſar ſhould be highted the king of Rome. For theſe cauſes a conſpiracie being raiſed againſt him, in which the chiefe agents of the Pompeians, were M. Brutus and C. Caſſius, and of the Caeſarians D. Brutus and C. Trebonius, in the Ides of March, and in theCaeſar is ſlaine in the Senat-houſe Senate-houſe, which was called Pompeyes court, he was pierced with three and twentie wounds, which becauſe they were many, and moſt of them were in the belly, and about the midrife, Caeſar as aſhamed of ſuch wounds,

did let downe his robe from his ſhoulders to couer them, and fell as a ſacrifice vnder the ſtatue of Cn. Pompeius Magnus. M. AntoniusM▪ Antonius is ſpared at the time whē Caeſar is ſlaine. and other friends of Caeſar, were ſpared by the aduiſe of M. Brutus, leſt they might ſeeme rather to be authors of a faction, then of Caeſars death. After this bloudie exploit, they by whō he was ſlaine, held the Capitolle. I cannot giue Brutus praiſe for this, but I rather thinke that he deſerueth diſpraiſe: for had the cauſe of quailing him bene iuſt, yet the courſe &amp; maner of killing him, doth apparantly ſeeme vnlawfull: for by that act the law Portia was broken,The law Portia broken by the killing of Caeſar. by which it was prouided, that it ſhould not be lawfull for anie to put to death anie citizen of Rome indicta cauſa. The law CorneliaThe law Cornelia broken by the killing of Caeſar. de maieſtate was alſo violated, by which it was made high treaſon, for any man to take anie aduiſe, or make anie conſpiracie, whereby a Romane Magiſtrate, or he which had a ſoueraigne power, without iudiciall proces might ſuffer death. And that ancient law was alſo deſpiſed, by which it was forbidden, that no Senator ſhould enter into the Senate-houſe armed with any warlike weapō, or hauing about

him anie edged toole. Surely they that will end tumult with tumult, can neuer be ſeized of good ſucceſſe or fortunate euēt: for diſcord may breed, continue &amp; augment contention, but it can neuer end it: and to expect that all differences ſhould be calmely compounded by generall accord, is a thing not much to be hoped for, becauſe it ſeldome happeneth. M. Brutus, the chiefe actor in Caeſars tragedie, was in counſel deepe, in wit profound, in plot politicke, and one that hated the principality whereof he deueſted Caeſar. But did Brutus looke for peace by bloudſhed? did he thinke to auoyd tyrannie by tumult? was there no way to wound Caeſar, but by ſtabbing his own conſcience? &amp; no way to make Caeſar odious, but by incurring the ſame obloquie? VVill anie man ſpeake vnto me of the wiſedome of Brutus, when he thinketh vpō the field of Philippi, wherein Brutus was like to the Comet, who feeding vpon vapours &amp; vaine opinions, at length conſumed and confounded himſelf: and thus were the two Bruti, I meane the firſt and the laſt, famous men of that honourable name, both fatall to the eſtate of the Romane

Common-weale: for the former of them did expell the laſt king of the Romanes, and the later did murder their firſt Emperour. But if Caeſars death had bene attended, till naturall diſſolution, or iuſt proceeding had cauſed it, his nephews entrie into the monarchie might well haue bene barred and intercepted: becauſe theſe honors were annexed and appropriated to Caeſars perſon. And if patience might haue managed their wiſdomes, though there had bene a Caeſar, yet ſhould there neuer haue bene an Auguſtus. But by bloudſhed to ſeeke for peace, is by oyle to quench fire. VVhen any innouation or alteration is to be hatched, the ſtate of things muſt be quiet and ſecure, that the wheele may be eaſily turned about, without hearing any noiſe. For to commit the murder of a ſoueraigne Magiſtrate, &amp; to defend thy ſelfe by armes, is as if a man ſhould couer himſelfe by water from a ſhowre of raine, or ſhould deſcend into ſome hollow of the earth for auoiding of infectious aire: &amp; if the moſt barbarous and immaine tyrant, ſhould trecherouſly, that is without warrant of iuſtice be ſlaughtered, though at his death he

were vtterly deſtitute of friends, yet his enemies ſhould be ſure to finde enemies: for no cōmon-weale can be without men of aſpiring humours, and when ſuch a murder is wrought they find preſent occaſiō to tumultuate, knowing that Anarchie breedeth confuſion, &amp; that it is beſt fiſhing in a troubled ſtreame: making a glorious praetence to reuenge the death of a Prince, though in heart &amp; in truth, they beare greater affectiō to the monarchie remaining, then to the Monarke who is taken away: neither in regard of ſupreme power and praeheminence, will I put diuerſitie betweene the perſon of a king and a tyrant; for he which attaineth to an imperiall or regall ſoueraigntie, by warlike induſtrie and victorious exploit, is no leſſe a Monarke, then he which cometh to it by election, ſucceſſion or deſcent: &amp; he that is made ſubiect by ſword, is as much ſubiect as he that by birth is a deniſon. But was Iulius Caeſar a tyrant? Surely there was more tyrannie in the ſlaughter then in the man ſlaine: Caeſar I graunt was a traitour to the State before the victorie, but after he exchanged that baſe name, with the beſt title of dignitie, and of a

traitour became an Emperour: yet did he not aggrauate to himſelfe that type of honor, the people offred it vnto him, he accepted it with thankes: manie had offended him, he pardoned them, yea rewarded them with great boū
               tie. He was content to haue a fellow Conſull, he ſuſpected none of them which were the workmen of his death, he did neither depreſſe the Noble man by ſlaūder, nor aduance them of obſcure condition by flatterie and bribes: &amp; which is incōpatible to tyrannie, he ſhewed ſelf-will in nothing, when he was inueſted with ſupremacie; but queſtionleſſe the Romanes ſhould not haue nouriſhed this lyon in their Citie, or being nouriſhed, they ſhould not haue diſgraced him. The goared body of CaeſarCaeſar his bodie is tranſported to Cāpus Martius. was honourably tranſported to Campus Martius. Afterward M. Cicero becauſe he was deſirous to reſtore peace, and to reconcile the ſtates, procured a decree to be made after the example of the Athenians, which they called their Amneſtia, that the killing of Caeſar ſhold be forgotten &amp; forgiuen, and this was ratified by Senate. But the conſpirors would not in anie wiſe lay aſide their armour, vnleſſe they

might haue certaine aſſurance and ſecuritie that their perſons, lands, and goods ſhould be ſafe and vntouched. VVherefore for pledges they had the ſonnes of M. Antonius, &amp; M. Lepidus, and then they deſcended out of the Capitolle. C. Octauius hearing of the great change that had happened in Rome, came as ſome ſay from Epirus, as others from Apollonia, to whom I rather agree: but he was welcome to all ſides and ſectes. And by the teſtament of his vncle, who had adopted him to be his heire, he tooke the name of Iulius Caeſar. M. Lepidus was at that time made Pontifexmaximus in Caeſars place. The Senate did aſſigne the prouince of Syria to Dolabella, and Macedonia to Antonius: but afterward when M. Antonius did ſhew himſelf too imperious, and would haue reſigned his charge in Macedonia, and haue bene Praeſident of France, he ſuffered a repulſe of the Senate, wherupon heThe Senate incenſed againſt M. Antonius. appealed to the people, which did greatly incenſe the Senate againſt him, and Octauius was alſo grieuouſly diſpleaſed with him, becauſeOctauius becommeth an enemie to Antonius. crauing his aſſiſtāce againſt the enemies of his vncle, he was in groſſe &amp; odious termes

abuſed of Antonius: Octauius therefore by the aſſent of the Senate, being accompanied with his vncles veteranes, prepared warre againſt him. D. Brutus to whom the prouince of France was committed by Caeſar, and after his death confirmed to him by the Senate, that he might reſiſt Antonius, who was then making toward Fraunce, came with an armie to Mutina, and there ſuffered himſelfe to be beſieged.D. Brutus ſuffereth himſelf to be beſieged by Antonius. The Senat did afterward ſend meſſengers to Antonius, to treate with him of peace, which were L. Piſo, L. Philippus, and Seruius Sulpitius. But when they returned without cō
               cluding any thing, warre was proclaimed, and Hirtius being Conſul went againſt him, Octauius as Propraetor, Panſa the other Conſul folowed them within a few dayes after. Caeſar and Hirtius hauing brought Bononia into their power, did pitch their tents neare to Antonius, who leauing a ſufficient armie to beate them from the wals of the towne wherein his forces were, did priuily and cloſely go from thence to meete with Panſa, as he was coming to Bononia, with whom he entred battell, andM. Antonius ſighteth with Panſa. had a proſperous victorie, but as he was retur|

                  〈2 pages missing〉
               
               
will not do it. The Pompeians were in truth wedded to too much partialitie, for why had Brutus the glorie of triumph, vnleſſe it were becauſe his life was ſaued by other mens valour? And why were the bodies of Panſa and Hirtius ſolemnely and honorably enterred, and Caeſar who was liuing, &amp; partaker of the victorie nothing regarded? Nay they did apparantly deſpiſe him. For, ſending meſſengers they enioined them to parle with his ſoldiers and leaue Octauius vnſpoken to: but they did with great choler anſwer, that they would not heare anie thing vnleſſe their Generall were preſent. This peruerſe and prepoſterous dealing made Octauius to enter the City in warlike maner, and as an enemy vnto them, and there he made himſelfe Conſul, &amp; Q. Pedius his colleague. M. Cicero did thenM. Cicero doth greatly commend Octauius. in publike aſſemblies greatly commend and extoll Octauius, but he ſpake one thing and meant another: for if dangers had bene once paſt, Ciceroes tongue would haue turned another way. VViſe and circumſpect he was to preuent a miſchiefe, but timerous &amp; fearefull to withſtand it when it was befallen. Afterward

affinitie was contracted betwixt Antonius and Caeſar, for Caeſar tooke to wife ClodiaCaeſar taketh Clodia to wife. the ſtep-daughter of Antonius. He was Conſul before he was of the age of twentie yeares, and in that Conſulſhip held nothing in ſo curious charge, as to take reuenge vpon the enemies of his adoptiue father: wherfore he requeſted Q. Pedius his colleague to enquire of them by whoſe conſpiracie he was ſlaine, and thereupon M. Brutus, C. Caſſius &amp; D. Brutus being abſent were condemned. D. Brutus to whom the Senate had committed the dealing with Antonius, being forſaken ofD Brutus is ſlaine. his armie fled to Aquileia &amp; was there ſlaine. But the eſtate of the Common-weale at that time ſhall appeare by an Epiſtle of M. Brutus written to C. Caſſius, which I haue here ſet downe: whereby a man may learne how to moderate and demeane him ſelf in common calamities, whē iuſtice is turned out of courſe and the lawes are ſilent. It was to this effect. M. Brutus to C. Caſſius ſendeth commendations; according to couenant &amp; promiſe my Caſſius, I write vnto thee ſuch news as I haue receiued from Rome. Octauius as I heare,

hath maried himſelfe to the daughter of Fuluia the wife of Antonius, for which mariage, I am neither verie glad, nor greatly ſorie: manie vſe ſuch mariages as pledges of reconciliation, and thinke them of ſufficient force to change hatred into loue, but are greatly deceiued. For it is one thing to make alliance, and another to make amity, ſith they proceed from ſeuerall cauſes, and hauing a different courſe, muſt needes produce diuerſe effects, for alliāce groweth, by bringing one kindred to the marches of another; but friendſhip either by long conuerſing together, or by a grounded opinion of good deſert, or by likeneſſe of qualities where there is no inequality of eſtate: and he that ſeeketh friendſhip out of theſe praecincts, will neuer find it. Therfore by ſuch mariage emnitie will not fully ceaſe, nor friendſhip firmely be ſetteled: for it is rather a meane betwixt theſe two extremes, then either a mother to the one, or a ſtepdame to the other. I receiued letters latelyAntonius writeth cō tumelious letters to Brutus &amp; Caſſius. from M. Antonius, directed to vs (whereof I haue ſent you here incloſed a copie) verie contumelious, minatorie, and not worthie to

be ſent from him, to vs: but his threatnings I do not much regard. For amongſt free men the authoritie of him that threatneth, is no more, then the law wil permit: for mine owne part I could wiſh that he were great in the Common-weale, ſo he were honeſt. I will not prouoke him to emnitie, but will alway praeferre the libertie of my countrey, before his friendſhip: he obiecteth to vs often the death of Caeſar, but he ſhould conſider how ſmall a time Caeſar raigned, not how litle while he liued. And Octauius forſooth digeſting at length, the hollow conditions of his father in law, ſeemeth greatly to ſtomake that we boſt ſo much of the Ides of March, when notwithſtanding only one man was ſlaine: yet not ſo much as he vanteth of the Nones of December, at which time he ſlaughtered more then one. Cicero once thought that the Commō
                  weale as a naked orphane ſhould be protected by armes, but now he praeferreth an vniuſt peace before a iuſt warre: wherein he ſheweth how vniuſt he is: he is fortunes page, and fauoureth them moſt who haue moſt fauourors. A wiſe man, though by oportunitie

he do alter his pace, yet ſtill keepeth his way, ſerueth time for aduantage not for feare, and as the ſunne ſetteth to riſe againe, ſo he changeth his courſe to continue his purpoſe: but to an vnconſtant man euerie accident is a cō
                  ſtellation, by which he is diuerſified and driuen from the center of his thoughts. Though Octauius call Cicero father, vſe him kindly, praiſe him, thanke him, yet it wil appeare that his words are contrarie to his meaning: for what is more auerſe from common ſenſe, thē to call him father whom he will not fuffer to be free? By theſe lineamēts I haue ſhadowed vnto thee my Caſſius the fickleneſſe and lubricitie of Ciceroes variable mind, which as it is not certaine to himſelfe, ſo it is not ſafe to vs: let him liue as he doth adulatoriouſly and abiectly: to me which am oppoſed to the thing it ſelfe, that is, to a kingly regiment, extraordinarie rule, domination and ſuperioritie which would extol it ſelf aboue the lawes, no ſubiection can be ſuch as that I may brook it. There can be no valiāt nor free mind without conſtancie, neither can any thing be glorious without the iudgement of reaſon. In the

buſineſſe of the common-weale I would haue nothing done, without the conſtitution and decree of the Senate and people, neither will I arrogantly praeiudicate, or boldly retractate that which they ſhall hereafter do, or heretofore haue done, but I accompt it more conſonant to the good eſtate of the cōmon-weale, rather with pitie to mollifie the miſerable eſtate of diſtreſſed perſons, then by graunting euerie thing to the deſire of the mightie, to inflame their luſt and inſolencie. Surely the Senatours are many times deceiued in their hope, and if a man haue done one thing wel, they preſently yeeld and permit all things vnto him, as though a minde corrupted by their largeſſe, and liberall offers, might not be traduced and caried away to euill purpoſes and attempts: but they may not beſtow any thing which to men euill diſpoſed may be either a praeſident or a protection, and I am afraid that Octauius by his late Conſulſhip, do thinke him ſelfe to haue aſcended higher, then that he will deſcend: for if Antonius by the death of Iulius Caeſar tooke praeſent occaſion of tyranniſing, how much more

will Octauius vſurpe, when both Senate and people do applaud to his affection. Neither will I commend the facilitie and prouidence of the Senate in this behalfe, before I haueful experience, that Octauius will content himſelfe, with the ordinarie honors that he hath receiued: but if it otherwiſe happen, I muſt needes pronounce the Senate guiltie of the fault, which they might well haue praeuented. Yet if this yong man do lay aſide ſiniſter and affectious humours, and imbarke himſelfe into the cōmon cauſe with impartiall thoughts, I ſhall then thinke that the Common-weale will be able to ſupport it ſelfe, by her owne ſtrength and ſinewes, that is iuſtice and integritie; and that thenceforth, no offence, ſhall either be cruelly reuenged, or diſſolutely remitted. Of our future affaires this is my determinate reſolution, ſo it may obtaine thy approbation; if things happen to be in better plight we will returne to Rome, if the eſtate be as now it is, we will liue as now we do, in voluntarie exile: if it decline frō bad to worſe, we muſt flie to armes as our laſt and worſt refuge, wherefore Caſſius do not faint, nor

diſpaire, let the hope of good things encourage thee, vertue onely is confident. From Smyrna 17. Kalend. April.
            
            Caeſar when by no meane he could be reuenged of Brutus, who was Praeſident of Macedonia, and Caſſius who had the regiment of Syria; he ſent for M. Antonius and M. Lepidus who were then in France, and they three meeting at Bononia, had conference of ordering and diſpoſing the common affaires, and there they agreed to be Treuiri, for the conſtitution of the common-weale for fiue years ſpace. To the charge of Lepidus Spaine and Gallia Narbonenſis were alotted, to M. Antonius the other parts of Fraunce, to Caeſar Libia, Sicilia, and Sardinia. After theſe conſultations they came to Rome, and aſſigned offices to whom it pleaſed them, asking no leaue either of people or Senate. At that time many excellent Lords and Gentlemen were proſcribed, together with an hundred and thirtie Senators, among whom was L. Paulus the brother of M. Lepidus, L. Caeſar the vncle of Antonius, and he who did ſo much praiſeCicero is put to death. Octauius M. Cicero. But that was done by

the venimous rancor of Antonius, by whoſe meanes he was beheaded, and the head wasFuluiaes deſpiteful dealing with Ciceroes tong. ſerued in meaſe vnto him, which when Fuluia the impudent wife of Antonius had eſpied, plucking and renting from the chaps his golden tongue, ſhe diſtained it with the ſpittle &amp; fome of her mouth, ſhe pricked it with needles, launced it with her nailes, brayed it with her fiſt, racked it with her armes, and ſtamped it with her feete. Fooliſh and ſenſleſſe anger, to inflict reuenge vpon a thing that was ſenſleſſe, and for the miſliking of the man, to hate the dead part of his body. But thou didſt nothing Antonius (for the indignation of poſteritie will riſe againſt thee) thou didſt nothing by taking away the publike voice of the City and that all-pleaſing tongue. Thou haſt diſpoiled Cicero of a poore remnant of dayes, thou haſt pared away his old age, thou haſt cauſed him to be ſlaine, when he wiſhed for death, but his fame and the glorie of his vertues and excellent learning, thou art ſo farre from abridging, that thou haſt augmented it: he liueth and ſhall liue by the memorie of all ages, and whilſt the frame of this world ſhall

ſtand, and this bodie of nature ſhal continue, which that onely Romane did in minde contemplate, by wit vnderſtand, &amp; by eloquence deſcribe, the commendation of Cicero ſhall alway accompanie it, the ſucceding wits ſhall wonder at his writings, &amp; euery mans doome ſhall condemne thy cruelty. But the miſerie of theſe times none can ſufficiently deplore, ſo vnpoſſible it is to expreſſe it by words. But this is to be noted, that the care of wiues toward their husbands, that were proſcribed, was maruellous, &amp; in the higheſt degree: the fidelitie of their free-men but indifferent, the loyaltie of their bond-men very ſlender, the loue of their children none at all, ſo griſly and loathſome is aduerſity to a mans owne bowels. Caſſius hearing of the great tumults of Rome, went from Syria to Smyrna in Aſia, where M. Brutus was, to take aduiſe of the ordering of the battel againſt M. Antonius, &amp; C. Octauius, who they heard did make expedition againſt them. VVherefore Caſſius hauing ouercome the Rhodians, and Ariobarzanes, and Brutus hauing ſubdued the Patareans, the Lycians, and other nations of Aſia,

which did before moleſt them, they haſted to Macedonia that they might there wage battell. And thither not long after came Caeſar, and M. Antonius with a huge hoſt, and before the citie of Philippi they faced their enemies with the tents. That fight was verie fierce and very doubtful, for Brutus put Caeſar to flight, and Antonius Caſſius, and each of their tents was ranſacked of the victor. C. Caſſius when Brutus, who he feared was ſlaine, returned a farre off, with his horſemen, thinking that they were the enemies that purſued him, did worke his owne death by the hand of one of his retinue. VVithin a few dayes after M. Brutus being ouercome in another battell, and ouerborne with deſpaire, enforced Strabo that fled with him to ſlay him with his ſword: which act, many noble Romanes to the number of fortie did imitate. There were neuer anie to whom fortune did ſooner approch, thē to Brutus and Caſſius: and neuer anie from whom ſhe did more ſuddenly flie: Caſſius was the better Captaine, Brutus the better Counſeller, Brutus was more to be loued, Caſſius to be feared, becauſe the one excelled

in vertue, the other in valor. VVho if they had conquered in this fight, it would haue bene more expedient for the Romanes to haue bene ruled by Brutus then Caſſius, by how much it was more ſafe to them in the end to be gouerned by Octauius then Antonius. The yeare following there grew diſcord betweene Caeſar and L. Antonius Conſul, and Fuluia wife to M. Antonius. They were offended with Caeſar, becauſe he ſhared that part of Macedonia to his ſouldiers which M. Antonius ſhould haue had. Fuluia was the more earneſt againſt Octauius, becauſe he had cō
               ceiued a deep diſpleaſure againſt her daughter, and had thereupon diuorced her. Caeſar was likewiſe incenſed againſt Antonius, becauſe he would not ſend to him that ſupply of ſouldiers, which he ought to haue. Antonius therefore in his brothers quarell, maintained warre, Fuluia leagued vnto him held Praeneſte, and there ſhe behaued her ſelfe as the other Conſul, cōtemning P. Seruilius who was indeed Conſul, being like to a woman in nothing but onely in ſexe: L. Antonius with an hoſtile inuaſion entred the citie of Rome, the

armie of M. Lepidus, who was left there as warden of the Citie being diſcomfited, and afterward departing thence toward Fraunce, was intercepted by Caeſar, who beſieged him a long time at Peruſia, in the countrey of Hetruria,Caeſar beſiegeth Peruſia and oftentimes making an eruption &amp; ſuffering a repulſe, he was conſtrained to ſubmit him ſelfe, whom Caeſar pardoned, but many of the Senators and Romane Knights were ſacrificed vpon the altar of Iulius Caeſar. He deſtroyed Peruſia, and hauing brought into his power all the armie of the contrarie ſide ended that warre, Cn. Domitius Caluinus, and C. Aſinius Pollio being Conſuls, PollioThe praiſe of Aſinius Pollio. was a man of notable gifts, who howſoeuer matters befell, was loued of all ſortes of men. Iulius Caeſar did make great reckening and accompt of him, after his death the enemies of Caeſar did greatly fauour him, M. Antonius had him in ſingular aeſtimation, Octauius held him neare vnto his heart, an excellent ſcholer, and a worthie ſouldier the onely obiect of the learned, whom both in proſe &amp; poemes, they haue condignely commended, ſo that I need not to proceede in his praiſes,

this is my only doubt, whether he were more to be extolled for his laudable qualities, then admired for his rare and wonderfull fortune; he was not long before with Antonius in Aegypt, but ſeeing him ſo vainely beſotted with the loue of Cleopatra, ſeeing him knight of the Cannapee, who was earſt Lord of the field, being aſhamed of him as he was a Romane, aſhamed of him as a General, aſhamed of him as now an vnworthie companion for Pollio, he left him in Aegypt with his concubine, and came to Rome. Afterward Caeſar and Lepidus fell at variance, ſo that Lepidus was compelled to ſurrender all his authority, and to ſtand to Caeſars mercie for his life. CaeſarOctauius Caeſar fighteth with Sex. Pōpeius did then fight with Sex. Pompeius on the ſea. Pompey being there ouercome fled to Sicilie, and afterward into Aſia, and as he was preparing warre againſt Antoni, he was takē of M. Titius, Antonius his Lieutenant, by whō he was ſlaine. The laſt ciuill warre which was betwixt the Romaines was that which was fought by Caeſar againſt Antoni at Actium. The occaſion of emnitie betwixt them was thus, Antonius did reproue Caeſar becauſe

he had taken to himſelf the armie of Lepidus &amp; that which followed Sex. Pompeius, which ought to haue bene common to them three. Caeſar did obiect to Antonius, that he did keepe Aegypt without lawfull commiſſion, that he cauſed Sex. Pompeius to be ſlaine without his conſent, that he caſt Artauaſdes a Prince, leagued with the Romans, and taken by trecherie, into priſon, &amp; diſhonored him, with gyues and fetters, to the great infamie of the Romanes, that he was more familiar with Cleopatra then became an honeſt man, that he had beſtowed too great giftes vpon her, that he had called Caeſars ſurmiſed baſtard begotten of Cleopatra, Caeſarion, to the great diſgrace of that houſe. Theſe things priuately by letters and publikely by meſſengers, were mentioned by mutuall obiection.Octauius readeth the teſtament of M. Antonius. Caeſar afterward did reade Antonius his teſtament in the open Senate, which came to his hands by this meane. Certaine ſouldiers which did flie frō Antonius to him, told him that the authentike will or teſtament of M. Antonius, did remaine in the cuſtodie of the Virgins veſtall, of whom Caeſar did obtaine

it, the tenor and forme whereof was thus.
            I M. Antonius one of the three ſtates ofThe teſtamēt of M. Antonius. Rome, and the ſonne of M. Antonius, do by this my laſt will and teſtament make and ordaine Philadelphus &amp; Alexander my ſonnes by Cleopatra, the heires of all my wealth and ſubſtance, which I had by deſcent from M. Antonius my father; but with this clauſe, and vpon this condition, that if I die in Rome or elſewhere, they ſhall ſolemnely conuey my bodie to Alexandria in Aegypt, and beſtow it there in a marble ſepulcher, which by this my will ſhall be made for my ſelfe and Cleopatra the Queene of Aegypt. But if they faile of this or do otherwiſe, without lawfull or vrgent cauſe, then I will that all theſe things which I leaue vnto my aforeſaid ſons, be conuerted to the vſe &amp; behoofe of the Nuns of Veſta, &amp; my ghoſt ſhal implore the aſſiſtāce of the Pō
               tifex-Maximus, &amp; the prieſts of Iupiter which are in the Capitol, to ſolicit the ſpirits of vengeance to puniſh the vnthankfulneſſe of my ſons, &amp; then I ordaine &amp; wil, that the Pontifex Maximus ſhall cauſe my bodie to be repoſed in a conuenient ſepulcher, within the walles

of this citie, and I will alſo that as many bondſlaues as be now in my power, ſhall preſently after my death be manumitted &amp; made free by the Praetor; and to euerie of my other ſeruants I bequeath a Seſtertian, &amp; a mourning garment. Laſtly, I do pronounce by this my laſt will and teſtament, that Caeſarion the ſon of Cleopatra, is the true, certaine, and vndoubted ſonne of C. Iulius Caeſar. And to the aforeſaid Cleopatra, I giue all my wealth and treaſure, that I haue gained, purchaſed and atchieued either in warre or in peace. Done by me M. Antonius vj. kal. Iul. Ap. Claudius, C. Norbanus Coſſ.
            VVhen the people of Rome had heard the purport of this teſtament, they thought that Antonius his drift, was to giue Rome to Cleopatra, for a ſpeciall fauour, for which cauſe they were maruellouſly moued againſt Antonius. Caeſar did behaue him ſelfe in this matter very wiſely and warily, for in wordes he praetended warre againſt Cleopatra only, and cauſed it to be proclaimed by the heralt, that the Aegyptian Queene did intend the ſuppreſſing of the Romanes. That was done

by Caeſar, to the end that he might auoyd the hatred of manie noble men, who did rather affect Antonius then him. But whē Antonius for the loue of Cleopatra wold neither come into the citie to render account of his doings, nor depoſe his Triumuiracie, but was wholly buſied in praeparing warre againſt Italie, Caeſar did furniſh himſelfe as well for ſea as for land: he therefore gathered manie ſouldiers out of Spaine, Fraunce, Lybia, Sardinia and Sicilia. Antonius likewiſe did make an armie of Aſians, Thracians, Macedonians, Graeciās, Aegyptians and Cyrenians. And in the yeare following C. Caeſar and M. Meſſalla being Conſuls, Antonius and Cleopatra at Actium a promontorie of Epirus, encountred Caeſar, who hauing proſperous ſucceſſe in many battels againſt them, as well on ſea as on land, they being at length ouercome fled to Alexandria in Aegypt. Caeſar did ſacrifice all theOctauius Caeſar ſacrifiſeth all the Pinnaſes to Apollo. pinaſſes which he had taken in warre, to Apollo, who was worſhipped at Actium, as a monument of thankfulneſſe for his victorie, and did alſo inſtitute a fiue yeres ſolemnitie, which was called the ſolemnitie of Actium,

beſides this he built a faire temple to Apollo, and in the place where his tents were pitchedOctauius buildeth Nicopolis. he founded a great city called Nicopolis, the citie of victorie. Aſinius Pollio did ſtill praeſerue the auncient amitie that was betwixt him and M. Antonius, for when Caeſar at his departing from Rome, requeſted him that he would ioyne with him, in his warres againſt Antonius, he made this anſwer: The benefites of Antonius towards me, will not permit me to be an enemie vnto him, and my merites at the hands of Antonius be farre otherwiſe, thē that Antonius ſhould be an enemie vnto me, wherefore leauing both and leaning to neither, I wil ſtay here in Italie, and be the ſpoile of the conqueror. Caeſar did afterward beſiege Antonius &amp; Cleopatra at Alexandria, where Antonius being in a moſt deſperate plight, being in no poſſibilitie to recouer Caeſars fauour, and hearing by a falſe rumor, that Cleopatra was ſlaine, did ſuddenly ſtab himſelfe. Caeſar tooke Alexandria, and with it Cleopatra, but becauſe ſhe would not grace Octauius ſo much as to be led in triumph byCleopatra killed by Aſpwormes. him, ſhe put Aſpes to her breaſts, and was by

them done to death, though her keeper had praeciſe charge to looke carefully vnto her. Aegypt was then brought by Caeſar into the forme of a prouince, and hauing made Cornelius Gallus Praeſident there, he came to Rome, where he had a triple triumph, the one of Dalmatia, which he brought to conformitie after his warre finiſhed againſt Sex. Pompeius, the other of Actium, the third of Alexandria. VVhen Caeſar with the great applauſe and gratulation of the Romanes had pacified the whole praecinct of the world, and for that cauſe had ſhut the temple of Ianus the third time, and an augurie of ſafetie was celebrated, which two things were neuer done but when the whole Empire was in quietneſſe, he purpoſed to depoſe the Empirie, &amp; to bring the common-weale to a good &amp; perfect conſtitution. To depoſe the Empirie, M. Agrippa did perſwade him, but Maecaenas did diſſwade him, whoſe opinion he yeelded vnto. VVherfore endeuoring by law to confirme the Empirie, and to win the fauour and good aeſtimation, as well of the Nobles and Senators, as of the people, he burnt all the letters which

the citizens that were then in Rome or out of Rome had writtē to Antonius, leſt any Senator who did follow Antonius his faction, ſhould thinke himſelfe to be hated of Caeſar for that cauſe, &amp; ſo ſhould attempt ſome miſchiefe againſt him: he releeued the common ſtocke, which was greatly waſted by ciuill warres, with his owne priuate wealth, &amp; them that were indebted to the common treaſurie, the billes of debt being burnt with his owne handes, he did free from the daunger of the rolle. And whereas many things were done, in the tumults and ſeditions of the citizens, againſt law and cuſtome by Lepidus and Antonius, he did repeale them by an Edict, and made his ſixth Conſulſhip, which he then enioyed to be the death-day of theſe lawes; by which meanes when he had worthily drawne vnto him the hearts of the people, yet in one thing he pleaſed them aboue the reſt, which was done rather of pollicie thē of plaine meaning: for hauing ſingled out a great number of Senators, whoſe loue toward him was ſpecially approued, in a very frequent Senate, he did offer to ſurrender the Empire into the

hands of the Senators and people. But ſome of the Senators, becauſe they ſuſpected that his wordes differed from his meaning, ſome becauſe they did feare greater daunger by a popular eſtate, others becauſe they feared his diſpleaſure, if they ſhould agree vnto it, they did with one voice refuſe the offer, and ioyned in earneſt ſute and humble petition vnto him, that he would be the ſole gouernour and abſolute Emperour of Rome, and for that cauſe they did decree that the ſtipēd of thoſe who did guard his perſon ſhould be doubled, that he might be in more ſafetie by that meane, both to his friends and to the cōmonweale. VVhen by the franke aſſent of the Senate and people, he had thus, not confirmed the auncient Empirie, but in deed created a new Monarchie, that he might ſeeme popular, he was content to charge him ſelfe with the weightie affaires of the Empire: but the authoritie and dignitie thereof he did cōmunicate with the people: and therefore vnto the Senate and people he did allot Numidia, Aſia, Graecia, Epirus, Dalmatia, Macedonia, Sicilia, Creta, Cyrene, Bythinia, Pontus, Sardinia

and Hiſpania Betica: which were the more peaceable and quiet countries. To himſelfe he tooke the other parts of Spaine, and all Fraunce, Narbonenſis, Lugdunenſis, Aquitanica Celtica, likewiſe Germania, Coeloſyria, Phoenicia, Cyprus and Aegypt. And that he might void out of their minds all ſuſpition of Monarchie, the ſupreme authoritie that was aſſigned to him he did only reſtraine to ten yeres continuance. The Romanes did beſtow diuerſe honors vpon Caeſar, planting before the doore of his Court a Bay tree, onThe Romans plant a bay tree before Octauius his doore▪
                the top whereof they ſet a wreath of oaken boughs, ſignifying that he was the man that had both ouercome their enemies, and ſet their citie in ſafetie. They decreed alſo that his Court ſhould be called a Pallace, ſo that in what region ſoeuer the Romane Emperor did ſoiourne, his Court was called a Pallace, and that he ſhould be called Auguſtus. For when many would haue adorned him with ſome title of excellencie, Caeſar had a great deſire to be called Romulus ſecundus, but becauſe that did reſemble too much the title of a king, he was content to be called Auguſtus,

that is, maieſticall or diuine. Thus had Caeſar the power of a king the ſtile only forepriſed. In him all the dignities and magiſtracies did meete, he was ſole Conſul, in determining iudicially of publike affaires, ſole Pō
               tifex, for he had that ſpeciall title, ſole Cenſor in taxing the Romanes by poales, and fining them for faults, ſole Tribune, in abrogating theſe lawes &amp; voiding theſe acts which were made and done by other magiſtrates: which though in ſhew they were manie, yet in deed there was now but one Magiſtrate in Rome, one Emperour, one Auguſtus; but theſe honors did not warrant Caeſars quietneſſe, for he was endangered by many trecheries, and being thereby too ſeuere in puniſhing both the worthie and vnworthie, vpon ſuſpition &amp; ſurmiſe without anie formall proceeding againſt them, he did indeed miniſter oile vnto the flame of their malice. Amongſt the reſt Cn. Cornelius, whoſe grandfather was Cn. Pompeius Magnus, did with his complices imagine and conſpire the death of Auguſtus, whom Caeſar would not put to death, becauſe he thought by that meane, he ſhould gaine

no great ſecuritie, neither would he deliuer them from impriſonment, leſt others might take courage &amp; counſell to attempt the like. VVith this doubt &amp; perplexitie he was grieuouſly troubled, and cares did torment his mind both in the night and in the day time; wherefore walking alone in his garden, and muſing what to do, Liuia the Empreſſe came vnto him, and prayed him of all loues to reueale vnto her, what griefe had encroched vpon his heart, and what was the cauſe of his vnuſuall dumpes, to whom Caeſar made this anſwer. Can any man, Liuia, be of a calme and contented mind; againſt whom on euery ſide are layd the ſnares of treaſon? Seeſt thou not how manie doe beſiege my quietneſſe, whom the puniſhment of condemned perſons doth not only not deterre, but, as if there were ſome hope of reward, others ruſh deſperatly forward to vnlawfull attempts. Liuia when ſhe heard this, did thus reply. It is no maruel, my Lord, if you be beſet with dāgers, partly becauſe you are a man, and therefore borne to caſualtie, partly an Emperour, by whoſe authoritie, becauſe manie are put to

death, many that liue do conceiue hatred againſt you; for a Prince cānot only not pleaſe all, but though he gouerne in moſt orderly and peaceable maner, it cannot be otherwiſe, but he ſhould haue many foes. For there be not ſo many iuſt as iniurious, whoſe humours can neuer be ſatisfied, &amp; they which be of the better ſort do aime at great matters, which becauſe they can not obtaine, and becauſe they are inferiour to others, are full of malecontentment, and for that cauſe they are offended with their Prince. But the danger vnto which you are ſubiect by them which do not cōſpire againſt your perſon, but againſt your eſtate, cannot anie way be auoided. For if you were a priuate man, none would offer you iniurie, vnleſſe he receiued wrong before at your hands, but an Empire, and the reuenues thereof, they which haue power do rather affect, then they which are poore do loath. This though it be a point of vnconſcionable men, yet as other faults, ſo this is the ſeed of nature, which out of ſome men neither by rewards nor by threats you ſhall be able to extirpate: for neither feare nor lawe

can do more then nature. VVhich being thoroughly cōſidered, it will ſeeme a great deale more conuenient to ſtrengthen and ſtabliſh your Empire with faithfulneſſe and loyaltie, then with ſharpneſſe and rigor. Auguſtus did thus reioyne: I know, Liuia, that the higheſt things be moſt ſubiect to hatred, &amp; the greateſt Emperours haue the greateſt enemies: for if our cares, griefes and perils were not greater then the griefes and perturbations of priuate mē, we ſhould be aequal to the Gods; but this doth chiefly moleſt me, that I cannot deuiſe anie remedie, which may cure &amp; conquer this miſchiefe. All men haue enemies, &amp; many haue bene ſlaine by enemies, but the eſtate of Princes lieth ſo open to caſualtie, that we are cōſtrained to feare our familiar frinds and our daily acquaintance, with whom becauſe we muſt continually conuerſe, we do continually feare, and this maladie is more hardly redreſſed then emnitie: for againſt our enemies we may oppoſe our friends, but if our friends do faile vs, where is thē our helpe? therfore both ſolitude and multitude is grieuous vnto vs, &amp; it is dangerous to be without

a gard, but to haue an vnfaithful gard is much more dangerous. Apparant enemies may be auoided, but falſe hearted friends we cannot anie way ſhunne: for we muſt call thē friends, of whoſe conſtant faithfulneſſe we can not poſſibly be aſſured; for my ſelfe I do plainely proteſt, that my heart abhorreth from the extremitie of puniſhment, and the neceſſitie of torture goeth greatly againſt my mind. Then ſaid Liuia, You haue ſpoken well my Lord, but if you will be aduiſed by me, &amp; you ought not to refuſe my counſell becauſe it proceedeth from a woman; I will aduiſe you of that which none of your friends will impart vnto you, not becauſe they are ignorant of it, but for that they dread your diſpleaſure. VVhich Auguſtus taking hold of, Tell it me Liuia ſaid he whatſoeuer it is. I will, ſaid Liuia, and that as willingly as you would heare it, for I am made partaker of your deſtinie. Caeſar being ſafe I am Empreſſe, and he being diſhonored, which misfortune the Gods auert, I am alſo diſgraced, and bereaued of glorie. That I may not vſe an ambuſh of words, nor a labyrinth of circumſtances: my theame ſhal

be one word, and that is, Clemencie. Change thy courſe Auguſtus, and forgiue ſome of thy foes, manie things may be healed by lenitie, which crueltie can neuer cut off. Neither do I ſpeake this, as if diſloyall and irregular perſons ſhould generally and without difference receiue mercie, nay they that be notoriouſly ſtained, and branded with conſpiracie, they that trouble the quietneſſe of the Commonweale, they that are ouerflowed with vices, whoſe life is nothing elſe but leudnes, ſo that they are paſt hope or helpe, cut them off my Auguſtus, as the putrified parts of a diſtempered bodie: but they which either through the infirmitie of youth, or the imprudency of mind, or through ignorance or miſchaunce haue offended, or which againſt their willes haue bene drawne into daunger, admoniſh them, but with minatorie ſpeeches: and let them finde grace but with condition. Some thou mayeſt puniſh with exile, ſome with infamie, and ſome with money: and that none may be vniuſtly condemned, nor by a fained accuſation ſuffer death, let the truth be tried by ſuch proofes, as may worthilie be approued.

For it behooueth thee Auguſtus, not onely to be free from doing wrong, but euen from ſhew and ſemblance of iniurie. Priuate men haue done enough if they haue not offended, but a Prince muſt endeuor not to be ſuſpected of faults. Thou ruleſt ouer men, not ouer beaſts, ouer Romanes, and not ouer Barbarians, and the onely meane to lincke their hearts vnto thee, is to benefite all and to oppreſſe none. For though a man may be conſtrained to feare, yet he cannot be enforced to loue; for when the ſubiect clearely diſcerneth that his Prince is bountifull, he is ſoone perſwaded: but when he is once reſolued vpon manifeſt praeſumption, that ſome be vniuſtly put to death, leſt the ſame thing happen vnto him, he may iuſtly feare: and whō he ſo feareth, he hateth with the ſtrength of his heart. But a Prince is the priuiledge of his ſubiects ſecurity, that they take no harme, neither of forreiners, nor of their fellow ſubiects, much leſſe of their Prince &amp; protector. And it is a great deale more magnificent and glorious to ſaue then to kill: wherfore lawes, benefites, admonitions muſt be vſed, that

men may become circumſpect, &amp; warie, and further they muſt be ſo diligently watched and obſerued, that though they would be, yet they may not be traiterous; and they which are greene in conceit, and as it were flexible waxe to the ſtronger powers, muſt haue perpetuall conſeruatiues leſt they be corrupted: and to tollerate the offences of ſome, is both great wiſedome and great manhood: for if euerie mans fault ſhould be his fall, the earth would ſoone lacke inhabitants. Thinke my good Auguſtus, that the ſword cannot do all things for thee: it cannot make men wiſe, it cannot make them faithful: it may conſtraine them, but it cannot perſwade them: it doth pierce the heart of him that is ſlaine, but it doth alienate the mind of him that doth liue. VVherefore alter thy opinion noble Emperour, and by vſing clemencie they will thinke that all that thou haſt heretofore done was done by neceſſitie and againſt thy will, but if thou perſeuereſt ſtill in the ſame minde and purpoſe, they will impute all that hath bene done to the auſteritie and ſoureneſſe of thy nature. VVith theſe ſpeeches of Liuia Auguſtus

being moued, pardoned many, and vſed as much lenitie as his owne ſafetie would beare: whereby he purchaſed the entire loue of the Romanes, and all his life time after there was neuer anie treaſon attempted againſt him. Thus after ciuill emnities extinguiſhed, forreine warres fully ended, iuſtice recalled, deſtiny ſatisfied, ſtrength was reſtored to lawes, authoritie to Magiſtrates, dignitie to the Nobles, maieſtie to the Senate, ſafetie to the people: the fieldes were without hinderance trimmed and tilled, the ſacrifices celebrated and ſolemnized, quietneſſe returned to men, and euerie poſſeſſion to his lawfull owner: good lawes were made, imperfect lawes were amended, bad lawes cancelled: the Senators were ſeuere without curriſhneſſe, the people honeſt without conſtraint: and with this harmonie peace pleaſed the Romanes.
         
      
      
         
            
            A Table of the principall matters contained in this hiſtorie according to the number of the Pages.
            
            
               A

                     Ancus a great builder.8 
                     M. Antonius the orator put to death by Marius &amp; Cinna.65 
                     M. Antonius: he helpeth Caeſar 138. He is ſpared at the time whē Caeſar is ſlain. 169 He fighteth with Panſa. 175 He fighteth with Hirtius. 176. He fighteth with both the Conſuls. ibid. Octauius becommeth an enemie vnto him. ibid. He writeth contumelious letters to Brutus and Caſſius. 180. The teſtamēt of M. Antonius.193 
                  
               
               B

                     D. Brutus ſuffereth him ſelfe to be beſieged by Antonius. 175. He is ſlaine.179 
                  
               
               C

                     Campania: the praiſe of it.10 
                     Carthage: the beginning of the ſecond Corthagiā warre. 12 Maſiniſſa quarrelleth with the Carthagimans. 45. Scipio is ſent as Vmpier betwixt them and Maſiniſſa. 46. the Citie of Carthage is burnt.47 
                     Q. Caepio is ſlaine.
                     C. Iulius Caeſar: he is inclined to ſedition. 103. his originall 107. his death is ſought for by Sillaes officers. 108. the Heluetians ſled before Caeſar. 116. they are ouercome by him. 117. he purſueth battel againſt Ariouiſta. ibid. he fighteth againſt the Belgians and Nerrians. ibid. he ouerthroweth the Germanes ibd. he burneth the villages of the Sicambrians. 118. he ouercommeth the Britaines ibid. he is reconciled to the Britaines. ibid. he renueth againſt them. ibid. the Eburons are ouercome by him. 119. his reuenge vpon the French rebels. 120. a decree made by the Senate that he ſhould diſmiſſe his armie. 122 he is incenſed by Curio againſt the Senate. 123. his paſſionate ſpeech againſt the Senate. ibid. he pardoneth Domitius. 127. he ſeiſeth the treaſurie. 131. he marcheth toward Spaine. ibid. the ſtrangers which were

aſſiſtant to Caeſar. 133. the Caeſarians giue the firſt aſſault to Pompey. 140. his ſpeech to Domitius. 143. the dreames and viſions of the Caeſarians. 145. he is entertained of Cleopatra. 148. he is aſſaulted by the King of Aegypt. 149. he ſwimmeth in the riuer of Nilus. ibid. he addreſſeth againſt Pharnaces. 150. he putteth Phanaces to flight. ibid. he encoū
                        treth P. Scipio. ibid. his triumphes are deſcribed. 156 Saluſt maketh an oration to him. 157. the great honours beſtowed vpon him. 165. he fighteth with Cn. Pompeius the younger at the Citie of Siuille. ibid. the cauſes of the conſpiracie bent againſt him. 167. he is ſlaine in the Senate houſe. 168. the Law Portia broken by the killing of him. 169. the Law Cornelia alſo broken.ibid. 
                     Q. Catulus: the diſſention of Lepidus and Catulus. 16. 76
                     Q. Catulus cauſe of his owne death.66 
                     Portius Cato is ſlaine.55 
                     M. Portius Cato Itichuſis his lignage. 102. his praiſe. ibid. he killeth himſelfe.150 
                     Catiline: his qualities. 83. his lignage. 85. he killeth his own ſonne. 86. he is greatly indebted. 87. he is forbidden to make ſute for the Conſulſhip. ibid. his impudent anſwere to Ciceroes oration.98 
                     Cincinnatus his ſpeedy warre.9 
                     L. Cinna: he beginneth a new broyle. 62. he is expulſed the Citie. ibid. he is made Captaine of a ſeditious armie. ibid. he calleth C. Marius from baniſhment. 63. a great fight betwixt him and Cn. Pompeius Strabo. 64. he entreth the Citie. ibid. he is ſlaine.69 
                     Cicero: he is called Paerpatriae. 83. his oration againſt Catiline. 92. he mourneth. 112. he committeth himſelfe to voluntarie exile. 113. a ſharpe law is made concerning his baniſhment. ibid. he is recalled from baniſhment. 114. he is put to death. 185. Fuluiaes deſpitefull dealing with his toung.186 
                     Cleopatra killed by Aſpworms.196 
                     Clodius: he being tribune of the people becommeth ſeditious. 109. he ſeeketh reuenge vpon Cicero. 110. he is infamous for adulterie with

Pompeia Caeſars wife. ibid. for inceſt with his ſiſters. ibid. he is condemned by the Senate. ibid. he perſiſteth to be an enemie to Cicero. 114 he burneth the houſe of Q. Cicero. ibid. he threatneth death to Sanctia. 115. he is ſlaine by Milo.ibid. 
                     Cornelia: ſhe lamenteth her children.27 
                  
               
               D

                     Druſus: his hard fortune. 32 he is ſlaine. 34. his repulſe is the beginning of the Italian warre.38 
                  
               
               F

                     Ful. Flaccus a rebellious Senator ſlaine.26 
                  
               
               G

                     A. Gabinius: after a proſperous fight he is ſlaine.23 
                     C. Gracchus: he is a rebell to the ſtate. 25. his ſeditious actes. 26. he is beheaded.27 
                  
               
               I

                     Italie: the Italian warre.15 
                  
               
               L

                     M. Lepidus: the diſſention of Lepidus and Catulus.16 
                  
               
               M

                     C. Marius: the contention betwixt him and Silla. 15. he beſiegeth the Capitall. 31 he putteth the conſpiratours to death. ibid. he deſtroyeth Saturninus his houſe. ibid. he taketh Iugurtha by Sillaes meanes. 28. his 3. 4. 5. 6. Conſulſhips. 29. his great victorie againſt the Cimbrians. ibid. he is in high reputation. 34. he putteth Vettius Cato. to flight. 52. he fighteth equally with the Marſians. 53. he is diſliked by the Conſul Portius. 54. his ambition. 59. his extreame miſerie, 60. a captiue ſlaue is ſent to kill him. 61. the Minturnians are friends to him. ibid. being recalled from baniſhment he entreth the Citie. 64. Octauius is put to death by his crueltie. 65. he dieth.67 
                     Mancinus: his puniſhment for breaking truce.20 
                     Metellus: he oppoſeth himſelfe againſt Saturninus. 30 he committeth himſelfe to voluntarie baniſhment.ibid. 
                     Metellus his ſpeech to Caſar.130 
                     Merula: he cutteth in peeces his owne veine.65 
                     Mithridates an enemie to the Romanes.
                     15. 58 Numa
                  
               
               
               N

                     Numa religious.8 
                     Numantia: the Numantine warre.20 
                  
               
               O

                     Octauius his requeſt to the Senate. 177. he reconcileth himſelfe to M. Antonius &amp; M. Lepidus. ibid. M. Cicero doth greatly commeend him. 178. he taketh Clodia to wife. 179. he beſiegeth Peruſia. 190. he fighteth with Sex. Pompeius. 191. he readeth the teſtament of M. Antonius. 192. he ſacrificeth all the Pinaſſes which he hath taken to Apollo. 195. he buildeth Nicopolis. 196. the Romanes plant a bay tree before his doore.200 
                     Opimius his proclamation.26 
                  
               
               P

                     C. Perperna diſcharged C. of his lieuetnancie.52 
                     Aſinius Pollio: the praiſe of him.190 
                     Cn. Pampeius Strabo: his victories. 55. he triumpheth. 56. his diſſembling and vnconſtancie. 63. a great fight betwixt him and Cinna.64 
                     Cn. Pompeius Magnus: his great dignitie in Rome. 16 Caeſar cannot brooke it. ibid. he &amp; Q. Catulus fight with Lepidus and ouercome him. 77. Mithridates is ouerthrowne by Pompey. 106. he entreth the Temple of Ieruſalem. ibid. he is honoured with a triple triumph. 107. he matcheth with Iulia Caeſars daughter. 109. his Preſidentſhip in Spaine proroguid. 121. he is appointed by the Senate generall againſt Caeſar. 127. Domitius flyeth to Pompey. 128 the forreiners which were readie in armes for the aſſitance of him. 132. his oration to his ſouldiers. 134. he putteth Caeſar to flight. 138 he marſhalleth his armie. 139. he flyeth to Lariſſa. 144 he trauelleth to AEgypt. 146. he is ſlaine by the AEgyptians.147 
                     Popedius. Silo Popedius a naturall enemie to the Romans. 40. his oration to the Marſians. 41. he is ſlaine.55 
                     Pyrrhus fighting againſt the Romanes.10 
                  
               
               R

                     Rome built.6 
                     
                     Romanes: the Romanes made wanton by proſperitie 19. the Romane Embaſſadors are deſpiſed of Hanniball. 44 the Athenians faithfull to the Romans. 67. the ſolemnitie which the Romanes vſed in their proceeding to the Senate. 89. treacherie againſt the Romanes in Fraunce. 119. what thing a triumph was amongſt the Romans, and how performed. 151. they beſtow many honors vpon Caeſar.166 
                     Romulus eagreſt in fight. 8 Romulus &amp; Remus baſtards. 42. nouriſhed by a wolfe. ibid. Remus is ſlaine by Romulus.43 
                     P. Rutilius is ſlaine.52 
                  
               
               S

                     Saturninus: he cauſeth C. Memmius to be ſlain. 31. his houſe is deſtroyed by Marias. ibid. he is a brocher of ſedition. 30. Q. Metellus oppoſeth himſelfe against him. ibid. Marius fauoreth Saturninus.ibid. 
                     Saguntines: the miſerable famine of the Saguntines.44 
                     Sabines: the rape of the Sabine virgins.43 
                     P. Scipio Affricanus the elder his valor.18 
                     P. Scipio Affricanus the younger: his proweſſe. 18. he is ſent backe into Spaine. 24. he ſurpriſeth Numantia. ibid. he is found dead in his bed. 25 his body is brought out into the ſtreete.ibid. 
                     Scipio Naſica: his familie. 22 he oppoſeth himſelf to Gracchus.ibid. 
                     Seruius taxeth the Romanes by poles.8 
                     Seruitins: he is Proconſull and is ſlaine by the commotioners of Italy.38 
                     Sertorius: he leuieth armes in Spaine. 77. he feareth Pompey. 106. Liuius Salinator the Lieutenant of Sertorius is ſlaine. 77. Sertorius is ſlaine.79 
                     Spartacus: he being a fenceplayer doth encounter the army of the Conſuls. 81. he taketh the citie of the Thurians. ibid. M. Craſſus appointed for the vvarre againſt him.82 
                     Sulpitius: he bringeth the Marrucines to obedience.55 
                     Sulpitius: a ſeditious Tribune altereth the ſtate. 59. murder is committed by him.ibid. 
                     L. Sylla: his victorie Samnites.

55. he killeth Cluentius. ibid. he is made Conſull. 57 his contrarie nature. ibid. his deſcent. ibid. he beſiegeth Nola. 58. his reuenge vpon the ſeditious. 60. his hard conditions of peace concluded with Mithridates. 68 the King of Parthia ſendeth Embaſſadors to him. ibid. he paſſeth quietly through Italy. 69. he diſmiſſeth Sertorius without hurt. 70. he fighteth with Teleſinus a Samnite. 71. C. Marius the yoonger is ſlaine by his ſouldiers. 72. he vſurpeth the Dictatorſhip. ibid. he cauſeth the ſouldiers of Praeneſte to be ſlaine. 73. he putteth in practiſe proſcription. 73. M. Marius is ſlaine by him. 74. his rage againſt Pletorius. ibid. the aſhes of C. Marcus throwne into a riuer by Sylla. 75. he dieth.ibid. 
                  
               
               T

                     Tarquin baniſhed. 1. his ornaments. 8. proud Tarquin occaſioner of libertie.9 
                     Treuirate: a Treuirate firſt made in Rome.21 
                     Tullus an artificiall Captaine.8 
                  
               
               V

                     Viriathus an enemie to the Romanes.19 
                  
               
            
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            
               
                  
                     
                        Faults.
                     
                     
                        Pag.
                     
                     
                        Correction.
                     
                  
                  
                     Monarchies.
                     Pag. 4.
                     Monarches.
                  
                  
                     Cloaetia.
                     pag. 9.
                     Cloaelia.
                  
                  
                     Maſſitus.
                     pag. 10.
                     Maſſicus.
                  
                  
                     couldes.
                     pag. 10.
                     clouds.
                  
                  
                     Glancias.
                     pag. 31.
                     Glaucias.
                  
                  
                     Eguatius.
                     pag. 52.
                     Eguatius.
                  
                  
                     Staria.
                     pag. 53.
                     Stabia.
                  
                  
                     Petiani.
                     pag. 55.
                     Peligni.
                  
                  
                     Talentia.
                     pag. 78.
                     Valentia.
                  
                  
                     Enomaus.
                     pag 80.
                     Enomaus.
                  
                  
                     Conſulians.
                     pag. 92.
                     Conſularians.
                  
                  
                     it greeueth my hart.
                     pag. 100.
                     it grateth my hart.
                  
                  
                     the Pictons.
                     pag. 119.
                     the Pictons.
                  
                  
                     the Tureus.
                     pag. 120.
                     the Turens.
                  
                  
                     the Audians.
                     pag. 120.
                     the Andians.
                  
                  
                     Achilles.
                     pag. 147.
                     Achillas.
                  
                  
                     aggrauate.
                     pag. 173.
                     arrogate.
                  
                  
                     Atia was.
                     pag. 176.
                     Atia, who was.
                  
               
            
            
         
      
   

