
   
      
         
            A lerned epistle of M. Iohn Fraser: Bachler of Diuinitie to the ministers of Great Britanie Wherin he sheweth that no man ought to subscribe to their confession of faith. And that their presumed authorite to excommunicate anie man, especially Catholiques, is vaine and foolish.
            Fraser, John, d. 1605.
         
         
            
               1605
            
         
         Approx. 132 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 54 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01221
            STC 11335
            ESTC S118714
            99853921
            99853921
            19324
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01221)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19324)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1097:16)
         
         
            
               
                  A lerned epistle of M. Iohn Fraser: Bachler of Diuinitie to the ministers of Great Britanie Wherin he sheweth that no man ought to subscribe to their confession of faith. And that their presumed authorite to excommunicate anie man, especially Catholiques, is vaine and foolish.
                  Fraser, John, d. 1605.
               
               98, [2] p.   
               
                  Printed by L. Kellam] Permissu superiorum,
                  [Douai :
                  1605.
               
               
                  Publication place and printer's name from STC.
                  Running title reads: An epistle to the ministers of great Britanie.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Church of England --  Controversial literature.
               Church --  Early works to 1800.
               Excommunication --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-01
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-04
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2007-04
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
            
            A LERNED EPISTLE OF M. IOHN FRASER: BACHLER OF DIVINITIE TO THE MINISTERS OF GREAT BRITANIE. Wherin he sheweth that no man ought to ſubſcribe to their confeſſion of faith. And that their preſumed authorite to excommunicate anie man, eſpecially Catholiques, is vaine and foolish.
            Permiſſu Superiorum.
            1605.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            
               TO THE 
                     •
                  VRITAINE MINISTERS OF GREAT BRITANIE HIS COVNTREYMEN Iohn Fraſer vvisheth vpright mynd tovvarde bothe God and Prince.
            
               HEARING of your extraordinarie dealing, according to the nature of your extraordinarie calling, in outward shew onely gainſt Catholique men, In very deed againſt o the God &amp; Prince. I thought it my duetie or the publike good, to write ſome thing ouching that ſubiect where by ye might nderſtand how ye deceaue your ſelues, and buſe others in that mater; which is this: 
                  •
               e labour by al meanes to conſtraine men, 
                  •
               ho at Catholique (for as to others men ye 
                  •
                not very careful) to approue ſweare and 
                  •
               bſcribe your confeſſion of faith; and in

caſe they refuſe, ye take vpon you to excō
               municat them. Wherefore with Godds grace we shal latt you ſee, that no honeſt man, true ſubiect or good Chriſtian with ſafe conſcience, can approue ſweare or ſubſcribe your forſaid confeſſion: &amp; that ye haue no power at al to excōmunicat any man: and although ye had, yet could ye not excommunicat Catholique men.
            2. As a plaine dealer without further preface I wil enter in the matter. Thē to the firſt head, it is certaine that whoſoeuer wil ſweare and ſubſcribe your new confeſſion, contrarie to the duetie of an honeſt man, putteth him ſelf in hazard to be menſworne, and that in the very entrie of his othe: for thir be your words, if I rightly remember: vve al and euerie one of vs vnder vvritten proteſt, that after long and devv examination of our ovvne conſciences in maters of true and falſe religion, ar novv throughly reſolued in the trueth by the vvord and ſpirit of God. Many faltes in fewe wordes, if men would long tyme, and duely examine them in their conſciences before they approue, ſubſcribe or ſweare them to be true: for firſt euery man here anſwereth for his companion &amp; fellow ſaying: vve al &amp; euerie one of vs &amp;c. where if any of the nōber hath ſpoken againſt the veritie or his conſcience, al the reſt ar lyers. Nixt,

what examination can be long in ſo weghtie a matter? certainely not fourtie dayes, yea not fourtie yeares. When theſe thinges cometh in controuerſie we may wel ſay without reprehenſion Deliberandum est diu, quod statuendum eſt ſemel. Thirdly, how can any man duely examine his conſcience in matters of true and falſe religion, ſeing that his conſcience or iudgement can not be a iuſt ſquare of religion, becauſe it ſurmounteth al humaine reaſon, &amp; is comprehended onely by faith, not of our owne forgeing, but of Goddes free gift? or how can he duely iudge vpon true and falſe religion who neuer hath ſeene, heard, or reade the reaſons of al parties? For as a tēporal iudge, not without great reaſon, may be thought to iudge very rashly, if he pronunce his ſentence &amp; decreit before he heare bothe the parties, not withſtāding the matter be of ſmal importance and value, and that he haue iudged according to the right, becauſe he hath iudged before he knew the ground of the matter, and ſo if he hath done wel, it was more by happe then good reaſon. So the ſpiritual iudge may be eſteemed rash and foolish, if in matters of religion and faith he decreit any thing, except▪ al reaſons be wel diſcuſſed. Wherefor he who would duely examine his conſcience in maters of tr
                  •
               w and falſ
                  •
               
               
religiō (ſeing he take
                  •
               h vpō him the charge &amp; place of a iudge) should with great diſcretiō, quyet ſpirit &amp; humble mynd, without any paſſiō trye both the true &amp; falſe, read al books touching that ſubiect, weighing the reaſon diligently: becauſe the profit is great to them that goeth right, and the danger likewiſe to them who goeth wronge. Now how the greater part of your ſweares and ſubſcribers can do or execute this charge truely I ſee not, yea can not geſſe, ſeing that a good nomber of your ſelues, who ar miniſters, and ſhould be beſt armed at deſtitute bothe of bookes and good learning. Certainly ye can not iuſtly aske of gentilmen, or others of meaner degree making profeſſion of armes or housbandry, that which, ye your ſelues who do make profeſſion of letters can not do: ye may eaſely iudge that gentilmen and commone people for lacke bothe of learning and bookes can not duely, and for lacke of tyme can not long and vvorthly examine their conſcience in ſic things their affaires ay hol
                  •
               ing them occupied otherwiſe; meikilles to ſweare that they haue done that, which neither haue they done, nor could they do at any tyme. Albeit there were no othere reaſon but this, yetafter my iudgement, it were moſt iuſt &amp; ſufficient for any man to refuſe your ſubcription and

ſwearing, and should moue you not to vrge men there to, except perhapes ye ſeeke only their vtter ruine and damnation, for doubtles they ar menſworne who ſweareth that to be true▪ which in their cōſcience they knowe to be falſe, or ar not aſſured if it be true, of which nature ar theis thinges which ar conteined in your confeſſion, ſeing they proceede of men who ar ſubiect to errour and falſe opinion, and ſo can gif no good aſſurance, where vpon men may eſtablish their faith. Which cannot be certaine and firme except it haue an infallible ground and fondament free frome all ſuſpiciō of errour. I may with many weightie reaſons proue that honeſtie could not ſtand with ſic maners▪ and ſhall bring them if it be needfull.
            3▪ For the feconde head it is 
                  •
               ar againſt the duetie of a true ſubiect towardes his Prince and liege lord, to whom he is obliged from the firſt moment of his birth to his laſt breath, wherefor can not gif his band of mā
               red, no
                  •
                othe of fidelitie to any other but with exceptiō of his ſoueraigne, which notwithſtanding ye deſire of your ſubſcribers: for ſpeaking of the worde of God (for ſo ye call your interpretations) and doctrine of your reformed kirk, ye ſay thus, to the vvhich vve ioyne ourſelues vvillingly in doctrine, faith, religion,
               
               diſcipline and vſe of th holie ſacraments as liuely mē
                  bers of the ſame in Chriſt our head, promiſing and ſvvearing, by the Great name of the Lord, that vve shall continue in the obedience of the doctrine and diſcipline of this kirk, and shall defend the ſame according to our vocation and povver all the dayes of our liues, vnder the paines conteined in the lavve, and danger bothe of body and ſoule, in the day of Goddes fearfull iudgement. There be here an abſolute othe and without any exception, made to you and your reformed kirk, not onely in matters of religion and doctrine, but alſo in gouerment and diſcipline. It is not my intent at this preſent to examine the manyfold abſurdities of this new forme of othe, in paſſing I ſay onely, that it shalbe very hard to any of your ſwearers to behaue him ſel
                  •
               e well with other proteſtant ki
                  •
               kes, who are bothe in doctrine and diſcipline far different from you: shall he enter incontinent in deſence of your reformation? shall he trouble all ſtates where he doeth come? Truely all men ha
                  •
               e that opinion of your religion, that it bringeth euerie where ſeditions with it, as the moſt turbulent ſect that euer yet was inuented in our contrey. Ne longe exempla petantur Betonio primi maduerunt ſanguine muri. Or shall he following the maxime of your faith call all in doubt not withſtanding of his othe,

               
                  •
               ecauſe ye are but men and may erre, except 
                  •
               e may gif ſome good and ſure reaſon, why 
                  •
               e onely ſay true, and all the reſt of the world falſe, and that nothing can procede out of your mouth, but veritie: for your othe importeth no leſſe with it. And certainely without that pretogatiue of aſſured veritie bound to your heads and tounges, to aſtrict men to your doctrine and diſcipline formed or reformed by you, neglecting the authoritie of your reformed kirk in generall, may ſeeme ſomewhat againſt reaſon, and very preiudiciable to the Prince and common wealthe. For by this othe all muſt depend vpon you as vpon the ſoueraigne magiſtrat, the ſolemne othe &amp; abſolute promiſe beinge made in fauour of your doctrine &amp; diſcipline, which ye haue in your hands and miniſtration. This may be eaſely ſeene by the othe made to the Kinges Maieſtie, or rather againſt him, which ye ſett downe in this forme. And becauſe we perceaue that the quyetnes and ſtabilitie of our religion and kirk doeth depend vpon the ſafetie, and good behauiour of the Kinges Maieſte as vpon a confortable inſtrument of Goddes mercie graunted to this countrey ſor the mainteining of his kirk and miniſtration of iuſtice among vs. VVe proteſt and promiſe with our heartes vnder the ſame othe, handwrit, and paines, that we shall defend his perſone and
               
               Authoritie, vvith our geir, bodies, and liues, in the defence of Chriſtes Euangell, libertie of our countrey miniſtration of iuſtice, and punishment of iniquitie, againſt all enemies vvithin this realme or vvithout, as vve deſire our God to be a strong and mercifull defender to vs in the day of our death, and comming of our lord Ieſus Christ to vvhome vvith the father and the holie ſpirit be all honour &amp; glorie eternally Ai
                     ••
                  
                Lat vs conſider the partes of this new othe. Becauſe (ſay ye) vve perceaue that the quyetnes and ſtabilitie of our religiō and kirk doeth depēd vpon the ſafetie and good behauiour of the Kinges Matie? &amp;c. Well begoune truely; that ye miſtak not your ſelues, ye lay downe the cauſe why ye will do or at leſt appeare to do ſome ſeruice to his Maieſtie, as long as ye perceaue thinges that pleaſe you, that is as long, as al thinges at donne according to your fantaſie, ye wil be good and obedient ſubiects, or rather maiſters, ſeing ye preſcribe conditions to him who truely is your Maiſter: and reaſons why ye will beſtow any thing vpon him. What if any reformed imaginations take you, or ſome extraordinarie zeall of your heauenly diſcipline trouble your braine, and make you perceaue according to your paſſion (as drounken men doeth ſee two candels where there is but one) any other thing in his Maieſtie? What if ye find not that good behauiour ye

looketh for? Muſt he dreſſe all his actions to your fantaſies and good pleaſure? will ye be cenſours and comptrollers of his doings if he vſe not your counſell and aduyſ
                  •
               ? If your perceauing of thinges to you agreable be the ground &amp; cauſe of your promiſe &amp; proteſtation, how ſoone ye preceaue in your fantaſie the contrarie, ye ought him nothing (I meane according to your opinion) ſublata cauſa 
                     •
                  ollitur effectus if I ſerue you becauſe ye nurish me, if ye ceaſe to nurish me, I am no further obliged to ſerue you. what shall become here of your hearty promiſes and proteſtations when your ſight shalbe changed? to what ſtate shal the cōmen wealth be brought when your foolish affections shewe a rule to the Kinges Maieſtie and honorable con
                  •
               ell to gouerne his realme? many thinges appeares to vs otherwiſe then they ar: and reaſons being knowen, they ar found good, that ſeemed ill before: we ſay cōmonly there should Artis ig
                     •
                  arus.no hyndman half work ſee. ye do many things in your houſe perhapes well &amp; honeſtly, which were neither expediet nor decent to be deuulgated to euery man: as alſo ye haue ſome ſecret counſell touching your affaires, which ye should looſſe, if your intention were publikly knowen. Think alſo that King
                  •
               s &amp; Princes according to their great rankes haue

ſecrets, which should not nor can not be published without preiudice of bothe Prince &amp; ſtate, the which can not be cōſerued ſometymes without the euident domage and hurt of ſome particulare men (as by the loſſe of one member ſome tyme we preſerue the reſt of the body) by which we ſhould not eſteeme &amp; meſure the princes actions but by the publik vtilitie, which they procure better then we can ſee or vnderſtand: becauſe their authoritie and experience gifeth them the wiſdome &amp; knowledge which we can not haue Caeſaribus virtus contigit ante diem. There be certaine arcana imperij whereto we can not penetrate, &amp; therefor lyke fooles oft tymes we do iudge rashly, &amp; condemne thinges which we vnderſtand not. Wherefor we should do well not to enter in iudgement of ſo high matters. Quam quiſque nouit artem in ea ſe exerceat. but your extraordinarie calling maketh you maiſters in all craftes, and your new diſcipline will not ſuffer you to haue ſo long patience. Ye who enter in Goddes cabinet when ye liſt, muſt know all things at the firſt inſtāt: nothing should be hid to you. ye haue receaued the ſpirite of diſcretion, nothing should be donne without your approbation. Ye ar in the chaire of veritie, ye may ſpeak what ye will; iudge whom ye pleaſe, comptroll

whome ye liſt: approue or improue as ye think good or ill: ye haue taken the power: ye haue receaued the othe: all men ar your ſubiects, ſo the Prince is ſubiect to your perceauing, the principall rule of your new populaire tribuna
                  •
               . But ye will ſay that my cōcluſion followed not vpō your antecedēt. I wold be glad it were ſo &amp; that I were deceaued in my opiniō, ſo willing I am to heare that there were no traittour in our countrey. But if we will conſider the ſolemne othe paſſed before in fauour of your new reformatiō, to defend and obſerue the doctrine and diſcipline thereof vnder ſo horrible a promiſe, or rather imprecations &amp; execrations as we haue noted before, it followed very neceſſarily: for ye may extend (as ye do when it pleaſed you) the borders of your diſcipline, as far as it ſeemed good to you, and interpret your doctrine as ye thinke moſt expedient, and ſo perceaue what ye pleaſe, where ye shall acknowledge or not, his Maieſtie as ye shall think it moſt fit for your preſent place, or proper for the aduancement of your reformed kirk, to whome ye will haue all men obliged with ſo terrible othes without any exception or reſtriction. A very hard obligation and lawe, principallie being at the execution and will of tippertin witted young

fellowes (who commonly at rash and foolhard
                  •
               e in all their doings) or in the hands of ambitious and ſeditious men, who willingly do trouble all to come to their de
                  •
               yre, to which by good meanes they can not eaſely atteine. your holie poets Buchanans pamphelet, hath many notable maximes to thi
                  •
                purpos, where vpō men may builde a world o
                  •
                ſeditions and diſcords: But if your poetes authoritie (whoſe aduiſe not the leſſe ye haue ſo skilfully followed that ye may ſeeme 
                  •
               ather maiſters then diſciples or prentiſes) can be no preiudice to your pretended innocencie Kno
                     •
                  .and good mynd, at leſt your prophe
                  •
               s words may ſerue for witnes of your vpright intentions. Ye shall haue the argument of the ſecond blaſt of the trompette written and ſett out by him ſelfe 1558. at your holie citie of Geneua foſter mother of all ſeditious ſpitites and vnquyet heads. Heare then your good Apoſtle: 
                  
                     •
                  ecauſe many are offended at the firſt blast of the trompette (behold how this holie ſainct is become penitente of his former offence) in whiche I affirme that to promote a Woman to beare rule or empire aboue any realme nation or citie is re
                     •
                  ugnant to nature, cont
                     •
                  mel
                     •
                  e to God, and a thing moſt contrariouſe to his reuealed and approued ordinance: and becauſe alſo, that ſome hath promiſed (as I vnderſtand) a conſutation of the ſame
               
               
                  
                     •
                   haue delayed the ſecond blast, till ſuche tyme as their reaſons appere, by the whiche I either may be reformed in opinion, or els shall haue further occaſion more ſimplie and plainly to vtter my iudgement. yet in the meane tyme for diſcharge of my conſcience (behold the holineſſe of this ex
               
                  •
               raordinarie patriarche, who thinketh him ſelue greatly burdened in his conſcience if he trouble not the whole ſtate of the commō wealth) and for auoyding ſuſpition, whiche might be ingendred by reaſon of my ſilence, I could not ceaſe (ô the good nature of this man, who can not ceaſe from ill doing, ſed quis Deus in fraudem?) to notifie theſe ſubſequent propoſitions whiche by Gods grace I purpoſe to entreate in the ſecond blast promiſed.
            
            
               1. It is noth birth only nor propinquitie of blood that maketh a king lawfully to reigne aboue a people profeſsing Chriſte Ieſus and his eternall veritie; but in his election muſt the ordinance, which God hath eſtabliſhed in the election of inferiour iudges be obſerued. autos epha. all princes ſhalbe ſubiect to the peoples iudgement, and the people to the miniſters.
            
            
               2. No manifest Idolater, nor notoriouſe 
                  •
               ranſgreſsor of Gods holie precepts ought to be promoted to any publike regiment, honour, or dignitie in any realme, prouince or citie, that hath ſubiected it ſelf to Chriſte Ieſus and to his bleſsed Euangil.
            
               
3. Neither can othe nor promiſſe bynd any ſ
                     •
                   people (call you theſe your hearty proteſt
                  •
               
               tions othes and promiſes) to obey and main
                     ••••
                   tyrannes (ſo ye call all Kinges that will not follow your fantaſie) againſt God and againſt 
                     〈◊〉
                   trueth knovven. that is your new forged faith.
            4. But if either ra
                     •
                  hly they haue promoted 
                     〈◊〉
                   manifeſt vvicked perſone, or yet ignorantly haue ch
                     •
                  
                  ſen ſuche a one, as after declareth him ſelf vnvvorth
                     •
                   of regiment aboue the people of God (and ſuche be a
                     •
                   Idolaters and cruel perſecutors) moste iuſtly may th
                     •
                   ſame men depoſe and punishe him that vnaduyſedl
                     •
                   before they did nominat appoint and electe. Is no
                  •
                this a moſte notable argument to be handle
                  •
                by a true ſubiect, and a man affectionat to the quyetnes of his natiue countrey? yet goo
                  •
                ſire Iohn Knoxe being in his owne opinion a prophete could not haue wanted many texts of the ſcripture to proue the mater. According to this exemplere and paterne of 
                  •
                choſen or rather imaginarie King, ye haue formed your othe: for neglecting birth and blood, ye will that the Prince be made by election, at leſt ſubiect to obſerue the ordenance that God hath eſtablished to be obſerued in inferiour iudges and magiſtrats, who may be depoſed and punished if he paſſe the rules preſcribed by you. For ye will the people be free from all obedience, promiſe and

othe to haue no place if the Prince go frome your religion, or as ye call it, refo
                  •
               med kirk, the declaration where of depended vpon your diſcretion &amp; wisdome ſeing ye ar made iudges aboue all men. 
                  •
               owbeit good reaſon wold gif libertie to the Prince as well to leaue you, as ye haue left the Catholik kirk if ye hade not alreddie occupied the place to commād ouer all without appeall. I will not further inſiſt in the examination of this blaſt of winde, ſeing it ſauoureth ſo ill that no true &amp; modeſt ſubiect can abyd it. I ſay only that your othe is as lyk this proiecte as euer dauther was lyk the mother, and lacketh but thinges which may very eaſely be vnderſtood as we shall shew after.
            4. But ye will ſay that I am 
                  
                     •
                  alignus alien
                     •
                   voluntatis interpres a maliciouſe interpreter of other mens myndes. What was your meaning, I pray you, when ye took your Prince, empriſonated and at laſt chaſed hir out of hir owen realme and purſued to the death? What was your meaning when during his Maieſties minoritie ye cauſed ſtrick money, marked with a ſword and this inſcription pr
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  e, in me ſ
                     •
                   mereor? What was your intent now of late yeares when ye beſeeged the toulbrigh of Edenburgh? was it the blad
                  •
                of rebelliō or ſword of Gedeor that was drawen out that

day? Why did ye cry at that tyme God and the kirk, if it was not to withdraw the peopl
                  •
               
               ▪ hartes and obedience from the Kinges M
                  •
               
               ieſtie to for ti
                  •
               ie your plottes? a courſe mo
                  ••
               
               ▪ dangerouſe where the Prince &amp; whole common wealthe were put in hazard vpon your 
                  •
               olie reformed worde. If I be not deceaued, ye would haue ſignified by God and the kirk your doctrine and diſcipline, to which ye will haue all men ſubiect, with no further obedience to others then ye think expedient, and ſo no place for the Kinges Maieſtie and his officers till it pleaſe you to employ them to execute your plottes, which onely charge ye would leaue to them, and that becauſe ye ar not able of your ſelues to execute ſundry thinges that ye haue inuēted▪ But ye will ſay, reaſon wold that all thinges ſhould be ſubiect to God: It is moſte true: But ye ar no Gods, yea not haue no charge nor command of God, as we shall shew here after and although ye hade, why ſhould ye, vnder pretenſe of your new forged or reformed diſcipline, 
                  •
               rouble the whole ſtate to the vtter ruine of the common wealth. Think ye that God and a King can not be in one realme to gether? or that God is accouſtumed to deſtroy Kinges, where he cometh? if your reformation proceded of God, we might very iuſtly ſo think▪
               
ſeing it troubles all Princes where it hath any credit. It was well ſayd by an ancient Scottish prieſt twelue hondred yeares ſince: Non 
                     •
                  ripit mortalia, qui regna dat caeleſtia. but he was a prieſt of the Romaine kirk, and not a brother of your reformation mother of your deteſtable paritie, grandmother of your preſent confuſion, where vpon is builded your ſinagoge: permitt me to ſay ſo ſeing ye force men to enter therein, becauſe your calling hath no power nor ſtrenght to inuite them. This can not ſtand with Princes lawfull authoritie. Heare Ieſus Chriſte him ſelf ſaying: date Caeſari, quae ſunt Caeſaris, &amp; quae Dei, Deo. Certainely all mē of quyet ſpirite should eſteeme them enemies bothe to God and good reaſon, who thinketh the one contrarie to the other. There were never yet any people that hade a religion without ciuil gouuerment: we haue ſeene in all common wealths theſe two ioyned together, but moſt perfectly where Kinges haue 
                  •
               ade the ſ
                  •
               ueraigne power, becauſe the vnitie is greater. Ye wold perhapes gladly ſay here (if ye hade the Chriſtian liber tie, that ye ſo earneſtly deſyre, that is licence to do as ye will) that ye at all prieſts and Kinges, and as ye haue caſt out the prieſts of the kirk for their misbehauiour, ſo wold ye caſt Kinges out of their

throanes &amp; realmes for lyk cauſe. aſſay againe the play. aſſure your ſelfs that knauery will not ay haue good ſucceſſe▪ If I be not deceaued ye shall now find Kinges more vigilāt, admonished by others mens exēples, then ye found the prieſts whom ye violently caſt out, not by your vertue &amp; ſtrenght, but by their fault &amp; negligence. God will caſt the ſchourge in the fyre, when he shall think it good.
            5. But to retourne againe to your words, As vpon a confortable instrument of Goddes mercie, graunted to this countrey for the mainteining of his kirk and miniſtration of Iuſtice among vs. With what reuerence obedience and modeſtie ye haue receaued that inſtrument, I leaue it to his Maieſties memorie and your conſciences: and if a few of you miniſters gaue him not more paine and trouble then all the reſt of the realme. If I ſee you ouer forgetfull I may well call ſome thinges to your memorie, although your daylie behauiour might very well releaſe me of that labour. Truely I think there be no ſubiects in Europe more obliged to their Prince then ye ar to his Maieſtie conſidering your de
                  •••
               tes: nor no Prince who haue hade more rebelliouſe ſubiects then he hath hade of ſome of you, ſo far as it did ly in your power. ye will do well in tymes comming to mend this, for feare ye

be conſtrained to render compt of all together, giftes abuſed may iuſtly be called beak: Your dayly railling againſt the preſent forme of policie in England sheweth well that your ſicknes do increaſſe. VVe protest and promiſe with our heartes (good and friendly words truely) vnder the ſame othe, handwritt, and paines (quid dignum tanto foret hic promiſsor hiatu?) that we shall deſend his perſone and Authoritie with our geir, bodies, and liues. Parturiunt montes naſcetur ridiculus mus. good Sires will not your new Euangell ſuffer you to do more for the Kinges Maieſtie? onely to deſend his perſonne &amp; authoritie? I praiſe your wiſdome to aduertiſe what 
                  •
               e may looke for at your hāds: yet ſure I am, that ye your ſelues wold not be content to haue a ſeruant in your houſe with ſo ſmall ſeruice, as ye offer here to your ſoueraigne whome ye wold ſeeme to haue greatly obliged. But at the leſt may his Maieſtie aſſure him ſelf of your aſſiſtence in defence of his perſone &amp; authoritie? No truely but in certaine caſes, which ye lny downe to him by writt that he may craue no further, to Witt, in defence of Chriſtes Euangell (I think as it is now reformedly preached and interpreted by you the diſcipline hauing it ſull courſe) libertie of our countrey (euery miniſte
                  •
                being maiſter) miniſtration of iustice (in chaſing

away ſic as will not acknowledge you in all affaires) and punishment of iniquitie: principally if any man gaineſay you. Nothing at all for the Prince? Nothing ſurely, if there cometh none of thes thinges in queſtion the Prince may ſtand alone for you, ſo far as I can ſee. Onely when ye haue a do, he shal be aſſiſted to do you ſeruice, otherwiſe he may do for him ſelf, if he thinketh it good. But if he touch your Euangell, yea with the vttermoſte of his finger, ye will put bothe perſone and Authoritie in hazard, ye ar ſo mightely gouerned by the reformed ſpirite. I will not geſſe further your myndes. Which beareth witnes, who ſo well does. But ye will ſuffer me to ſay that the ſubiect not onely is obliged of duetie ciuil, but alſo in conſcience before God to defend his Princes perſone without any exception becauſe he is vnctus Domini and one of the chief magiſtrates eſtablished by God him ſelf. Therefore we never did reade that the Chriſtians were blamed for defending of the Emprours perſonnes, not withſtanding that ſundry of them were moſt cruell perſecutors of the Chriſtian and Catholik faith, and did ſeeke by all meanes to deſtroy the veritie. The Chriſtians refuſeth onely to be executers of theſe deteſtable deſignes of the Emprours: yea I think it shall

never be found that the Ancient Godly fathers did lay to any Chriſtians charge as a cryme, that he hath garded and keapt the perſonne of Iulian the Apoſtata▪ for that neuer was againſt God, nor reaſon; ſeing they were obliged there to, as to a thing bothe honeſt and Godly, which they could not neglect without a great blame. Theſe onely were accuſed as curſed &amp; miſch
                  •
               euouſe men, who were inſtruments of his abominations. Certainely the Princes perſonne ſhould be holie and inuiolable; and we more carefull there of, then of our owne lines. Lykwiſe we may ſay of his Authoritie which cometh of God, and hath ay God for reuenger, if any man be ſo bold as to touch it irreuerently. Ye meſure the Princes perſone and Authoritie according to your fantaſie, making them great or ſmall, to be obſerued or diſpyſed, as ye think proper to your purpoſe and paſſion. But ye will ſay that it is well donne to defend the Princes perſonne &amp; authoritie. that is very true. who ſo euer is owing a hondred crownes, doeth well to pay one crowne, but not inough except he pay the whole ſomme, ſo your duetie is not complete in theſe few heads. Theſe fashions of othes a
                  •
                inuented onely to exempt by litill and litill the people frome the due obedience oght to the Prince▪
               
for the people thinking that the othe is the onely ſure rule of their due obligation toward, their ſoueraigne: and that they ar not further bound then the othe sheweth: if in their opinion any thing paſſe that boundes, they may think them ſel es free and diſcharged from further obedience as not conteined in their othe. For when I haue donne that, where to I am obliged, it is in my hād if I will do any further: If I do more, I merite thankes; if not, I merite no reprehenſion, nor blame, much leſſe punition. Ye will not be offended, if I ſay ſome what yet of your othe, which hath beene formed either with a great malice or extreme ſimplicitie (which of theſe two be moſt proper for your ſect I leaue the iudgement to others) which will be more cleerely ſeene if we shew the true forme of othe which should be geuen to the ſoueraigne Prince. The ſubiects of Emprour or King being as va
                  •••
               les (which we call cō
               monly lieges) should make to their Prince the othe ſimplie and without any condition, yea ſo farre that ſwearing fidelitie againſt al men they should not except them ſelues. And therefore the othe of fidelitie which the lawyers call ſacramentum fidelitatis should be made without any condition or reſtriction: for if any ſic thing be put in the forme of

othe deceitfully, or craftelie couuert with words, where by the ſubiects may with draw them ſelfs from the fidelitie towards their Prince or attempt what ſo euer thing againſt him, vnder what ſo euer pretext, they should be accompted as rebelles, lacking reithe
                  •
                occaſion, then an euill mynd. And for that ſame cauſe it is not law fall to put the reaſon in the othe, that he, who ſweareth, may haue no cloake nor excuſe to break his othe: E
                     •
                  t enim forme fidelitatis actus legitimus conditionem non recipiens. when the othe of fidelitie is made to him who is onely lands lord and not ſoueraigne, the vaſſall puteth no condition although he put an exception of the Emprour or King, as may be ſeene in this forme. Ego Titius iuro ſuper haec ſancta E
                     •
                  angelia, quod ab hac hora in antea vſque ad vltimum diem vitae meae, ero fidelis tibi Ca
                     •
                  o Domino contra omnem hominem, excepto Imperatore vel Rege. But the forme of fidelitie and othe made to 
                  •
               he Emprour or King, or any other ſoue
               
                  •
               aigne Prince, should be ſett downe in moſt 
                  •
               imple plaine and cleere words, without any 
                  •
               eceit fraud or guyll. For as the Kinges Em
               
                  •
               ire is free and abſolute, ſubiect to no other, 
                  •
                the othe of the ſubiects should be 
                  •
               ltoge
               
                  •
               er ſimple and without any reſtriction. I 
                  •
               ay all good and true ſubiects, not onely for

their duetie, but alſo for their conſcienc
                  •
                cauſe, compare this with our new reformed or reither deformed forme of othe, and conſider if it raſted not of rebellion and conſpiracie againſt the law
                  •
               ull Prince, and if this be not a beginning and foundament to bring in the Swiſers common wealth where the ſoueraigne magiſtrate at the yeares end is anſwearable to the people, by whome he is choſen. Doubtles theſe crafteſmen haue had before their eies Bruti vindicias, Buchanans precepts, Knoxes blaſts of the trompette of ſedition, Goodmans diſcours how ſuperior powers ought to be obeyed of their ſubiects▪ Knoxe hiſtories of treaſons &amp;c. or els the King of Poles othe, Si ſacramentum violauer
                     •
                   nullam nobis regni incolae obedientiam praestar
                     •
                   debebunt. the Poloniens may deſyre of their future Prince, what othe they pleaſe ſeing he is at their election and choiſe. But to preſcribe to your ſelues, how and what ye will ſweare to your Prince, to whome ye, your fathers and poſteritie ar allreddie obliged whether ye will or not, I know not how ye can be excuſed except ye miniſters eſteeme your ſelues in the ſame rank with the ancien
                  •
                arrogant Aragoniens, who in reception o
                  •
                their king were wount to ſay in this maner Nos, qui valemos tanto comme vos, y podem
                     •
                  
               
               
               m
                     •
                  s que vos, vos elegimos Re, con eſtas &amp; eſtas conditiones intra vos y nos, vn que manda mas, que vos. We, who ar as good as ye, and may more then ye, chooſe you our king, with ſic and ſic conditiones betwixt you and vs that one may commande more then ye▪ wold ye not think your ſelues braue men, if ye might truely vſe 
                  •
               ic ſpeech to his Maieſtie. But ye do meikill 
                  •
               orſe, ſeing in eff
                  •
               ct ye gif him no thing but aſſiſtence to do you ſeruice, without any further honour or profit. A great ſeruant truely, if ye were wo
                  ••
               hie m
                  •
               iſters. Certainly if the King were at your choiſe (as God forbid he were) ye could gif him no leſſe then ye do here by your othe: yea what leſſe can ye gif to your moderator of one day, then defend his perſone and authoritie, as long as he is in charge, for ye do nothing therein, but mainteine your ſelues. The Mu
                  •
               iners in the warres offer no leſſe to their new choiſen head, not for his cauſe, but for their owne. I am aſſured that there is no people in the worlde ſo ſeditiouſe or rebelle, but wold beſtow more vpon their Prince o
                  •
                head whatſo euer, then ye b
                  •
               ſtow here vpon his Maieſtie: In promptu ratio est, his Maieſties forces can not agree with your folies. But ye will ſay perhapes that the Kinges Maieſtie doeth acknowledge him ſelf

               In his ſpeech to parlament. to be made for the people and not the people for him. he ſpeeketh lyk a noble wiſe and moſte worthie Prince acknowledging what he oweth to God, in whoſe place he is eſtablished, whoſe perſone he doeth preſent, and in whoſe authoritie he doeth command. On the other part, why will▪ ye not lyk true and good ſubiects acknowledge▪ your duetie, towards him, to whome ye ar obliged, as to Goddes lieutenant aboue you? or ar all men obliged to you, and ye to no man? it is lawfull to you to be more familiar with his Maieſtie, then he is with him ſelf. More ouer ye ar not the wholl people being but onely the tribunes at your owen making, and albeit ye were, yet should ye not preſume ſo farre of your ſelues, as all should be donne by you, and at your appetite. It is certaine that the head is made for the body (as alſo the body for the head) yet should not the body be maiſter and command aboue the head nor yet preſcribe lawes or conditions to it, but should obey it in all thing without contradiction as being ſubiect and not ſuperior. The phyſiciens do teach, and (as I think) not without good reaſon that the wholl ſtrenght of the body, and all the functions thereof cometh of the head, where the ſenſes at chiefly, &amp; wittes ar onely. If we would credit you &amp;

your reformation, we should shortly ſee a deformed gouerment through all the world. I am aſſured that it wold be better dwelling among the antient Cyclops, if there were any, then among you: and if ye be curiouſe to know why, I shall mak you a deſcription In the ſeſsions presbiteries ſynodes &amp; generall coū
                  ſels.of your ſelues, where ye may ſee a part of your beauties with out a mirrour: Ye haue bene ſo impudent and shameleſſe, as to aske for your 
                  •
               eformed kirk an abſolute othe of all the Kinges Maieſties ſubiects, yea of him ſelfe (whome in his tender age ye did ci
                  •
               cumuent) that he should defend your doctrine and diſcipline, that is, embrace your inuentions and execute your plottes, ſo that his Maieſtie and all his ſubiects of what ſo euer qualitie or condition. should onely be veſtrae voluntatis imo tyrannidis miniſtri, to trouble and perſecute all theis that will not obey you, albeit it were bothe againſt his Maieſties honour and ſtate. Which I think his Maieſtie will ſuffer no longer to be donne, becauſe of the danger that may euſue there vpon. For what can be more perniciouſe within a realme, where obedience and modeſtie ar moſte neceſſarie, then to ſuffer the ſubiects to be corrupted either by monopoles or periuries or damnable opinions tending to a new forme of gouerment

and ſtate? or to permitt a 
                  •
               orme of common wealth within an other, as a cotadaill or fortreſſe within a towne, to hold the Prince and all his ſubiects bound ſ
                  •
               aues to yow. A thing, I know not whether more dishonorable to the Prince, or more dangerouſe. I ſay onely that the mo
                  •
               e his Maieſtie beareth with you the more ye at preſumptiouſe and the reddier to attempt ſome new interpriſe. Ye contented your ſelues before to raill againſt the ſtate and gouerment of Scotland; now, as if your iuriſdiction were amplified with his Maieſties empire, ye ar entred in England, all Britaine is fallen to your lot: ye will comptroll all mens actions there, ye will aſſiſt your brethren of that nation, defend them, their doctrine and diſcipline according to your reformed miniſteriall othe, for why should any man be ſo bolde as to touch in any wiſe your inheritance? or medle with your affaires? or command within your iuriſdiction? A ſurplice, a ſquare cappe, or a Bishoppe may ſerue you for a moſt iuſt reaſon to trouble all, ſo liuely is your faith finding Idolatrie in any thing that miſlyketh your humour. O tribus Anticris caput inſ
                     •
                  nabile. It were beſt his Maieſtie ſent you to the vnfound lands, where there is no man yet, that ye might forme a common wealth at your

owne fantaſie without other mens griefe or trouble. Certainely if ye were ſent ouer ſea fiue, or ſixe yeares to ſeek your meate as others haue donne, ye wold perchance be more modeſt, and vnderſtand how bontifull and patient his Maieſtie is ſuffering you ſo long to reigne and raill without ryme or reaſon: Coge
                     •
                  is aliquando per veſtrum ſcelus iracunda louem ſumere ſulmina. But ye the Saincts of God, his elected people, aſſured inheritance, indued with only faith voide of all good workes, deſtitute of free will, and yet willfull in all your opinions, predeſtinated to the heauens how ſo euer emptie of honeſtie, and covered with vice, ye zealouſe brethren, I ſay, ar aboue all Kinges and Princes, they at but your officers, executers of your good pleaſiurs and will: otherwiſe to no purpo
                  •
                in this world. To conclude this matter I will tell you the Catholik opinion herein, which is this. As we ar wholly and without any exception obliged to God in matters of faith and conſcience, ſo at we abſolutly and without any exception or reſtriction obliged &amp; bound to our Prince with all fidelitie and obedience in temporall affaires, that is in matters nether repugnant to God nor good reaſon, how ſoeuer they be to our dommage and hurt in worldly thinges, or to out

paines and againſt our repoſe. There is no reaſon, why the foote should refuſe to trauaill▪ when the head haue a doe, how hote that euer it be: wearineſſe can ſerue for no excuſe: at the nodde of the head, the reſt of the membres should be reddie: at ſic tymes excuſes ar but diſguiſed rebellions: the want of commodities maketh the way more difficill but not impoſſible. To the foote thes thinges may ſeeme very hard and iniuſt, becauſe of the great paines and many incommodities it muſt ſuffer, oftentymes not knowing the reaſon why, except that it is a member ſubiect to the head, and therefor obliged to obey according to the office and due function of a member, as it shall pleaſe the head to command. Wold ye that men should goe as Iugling tumblers doe, their feete vp, and their head downe? ye haue ſome reaſon ſo 
                  •
               o deſyre in maters of ſtate (although there be no reaſon, why it should be graunted to you) ſeing by that meanes ſundry of you myght hope for the higheſt place, as being in all degrees the very dregges of the people, yet being promoted without order or extraordinairely (for all is one in your perſonnes) ye at found worthie of the charge ye haue, ye become ſo perfect raillers: but how proper ye be to gouuerne Kinges and realme

(which ye will to 
                  ••
               pend vpon you in maters of greateſt conſequence) I leaue the iudgement to others; and principallie when it is queſtion of your zealouſe brethren, who ordinairely ar caried away rather by paſſion and opinion, th
                  •
               n guided by diſc
                  •
               eti
                  •
               n and wiſdome: where vpon ar founded an infnite nomber of rash iudgements that they haue made vpon other mens actio
                  •
               s. I think it not needfull that I ſpecifie any▪ the ex
                  •
               mples being ſo frequent
                  •
                and common. A n
                  •
               w ſorte of tyrannie me
                  •
               kill to be lamented▪ if we 
                  •
               ere not oppreſſed with a mor
                  •
                grieuouſe, 
                  •
               her by it is fre
                  •
                to no mā to vſe his naturall aire and inioye▪ the ſight of his friends and kinneſmen, except 
                  •
               e ſweare him▪ſelf your ſlaue, foreſwearing bothe God and Prince for a reformed folie: Ouer high a price truely▪ and ouer great ſubiection, for the ſmall reward that any mā can look for at your-hand. What ſo euer banishment were more to be deſyred, then that dwelling at home: for accepting that condit
                  •
               on, men incu
                  •
               reth the danger of double treaſon, diuine and humaine, which being donne, they were vnworthie not onely to be eſteemed his Maieſti
                  •
               s ſubiects, but to 
                  •
               e ſuffered to liue vpon the earth, if that come of their proper conſent and deſyre. And what fidelitie, I pray you, can

his Maieſtie look for of you, who requires of other men ſic othes as cutt away all aſſurance of fidelitie towards the Prince? ye pre
                  •
               erting your vaine opinions (that I ſay nothing more diſpleaſant) to the whol antiquitie, yea to all ages paſſed and preſent, in maters of religion, and your iudgement to all magiſtrates of what ſo euer authoritie or experience in maters of ſtate, and your interpriſes to peace and quyetneſſe, ar good Chriſtians and true ſubiects, well at your caſe in honour and Authori
                  •
               ie, although the greateſt part of you be the firſt honeſt men of your race, or rather the worſt that euer was of your race, shewing the common ſay to be very true. Aſperius nihib est humili cum ſurgit in altum, 
               
                  •
               et a beggar on horſeback and he will ride 
                  •
                gallop. But peiceable men, who haue not that turbulent preſomptious ſpirite, becauſe they prefer the authoritie of the vniuerſall ki
                  •
               k, and iudgement of the ancient paſtours and Ca
                  •
               holik conſent to their priuat and particula
                  •
               e opinion, reſpecting the magiſtrates as Gods officers and law
                  •
               ull inſtruments, they at Idolaters, papiſts, traitours to his Maieſtie enemies to the cōmon wealth, excōmunicat incōtinēt▪ put to the horne▪ their goods confiſcated, them ſelues banished out of the countrey: what rank or qualitie that euer

they be of, they ar not worthie to be faluted by the worſt raſcal fellow of your ſeſsions although they be compoſed ordinairely of the very ſinke of the people. But honeſt men muſt take patience, ſeing ye gif ſo litill reuerence to them, to w
                  •
               ome ye ar more obliged
            6. where I will no
                  •
               e a thing very remarcable, that neither riches, good traict
                  •
               ment, dignities, nor honours can mak you quyet and peaceable men; neither iniuries, indignities, banishment, loſſe of goods nor freinds can moue the Catholiks to leaue their duetie towards the Prince: which I doubt not but his Maieſtie ſome day will conſider when it shall pleaſe God to haue pitie of our miſe
                  •
               ies. Abyding which tyme, I pray you all good and Godly Catholiks (ſ
                  •
               ſfer me good ſites to turne my ſpeeche a litill to them) to behaue your ſelues towards his Maieſtie with due obedience and modeſtie, ſe
                  •
               king no pre
                  ••
               xt no
                  •
                excuſe to withdraw your ſelues: ſuffering paciently perſecutions if any be. Mixe no worldly reſpectes with heauenly bl
                  •
               ſlinges, God is highly offended when we mak
                  •
                to our particulare paſſions a cloake of his name, his honour and our affaires ar not of lyk rank, they should not be mingled together▪ If any harme cometh to you in his ſeruice, your reward wilbe th
                  •
                greater, ſoing ye haue 
                  •
               r
                  •
               
               uailled

for his glorie, and haue ſtand ſtoutly to his ryght, vnder whoſe banner to die, is to triomphe for euer: feare no damnage▪ not loſſe, ye haue a moſt ſure promiſe of a honderdfold profit &amp; the lyfe eternall. we should beſtow our goodes w
                  •
               llingly in his ſeruice who rccompenſeth ſo liberally. The leſſe of our priuat affections we midle here in, the better is outs, the more ample shal be our lords goodnes towards vs: becauſe his glorie the more cleerly doeth shine, when it is allone. But when his veritie is blamed for our misbehauiour, what can we look for at his hands, but for a iuſt punition for abuſing his authoritie and name? It were very hard to ſuffer ſundry thinges that occurre in thes ſpirituall wat
                  •
               es, if our captaine were not inuincible, and we aſſured how long we ſtand with him. We lack no good examples bothe of head and membres. We can not be firſt in this batai
                  •
               l where ſo many thowſands loſſing the earth haue conquiſed the heauens▪ there ar paſſed before vs infinite nomber of champions off all dignities ages and qualities, Kinges, Quyenes, nobles &amp; meane men, learned and ignorant, men, wemen, ould men and babes, poore and riche, who haue borne armour vnder this ſtandart, &amp; after the loſſe of all worldly goods haue shead their

bloode with ioy to their eternall bleſſe, becauſe they had only Goddes glorie before their eyes, which principally in this tyme ſo dangerous we should do, that our vice be not obiected to the Catholik religion, as if our faul
                  •
               es came of that which we profeſſe, and not of ou
                  •
                ſelues; to which ſorte of calumnies and craftie accuſations, our aduerſaries haue oſt recourſe, taking argumēts from ou
                  •
                liues and behauiour, which they can not haue frome our religion. We should not mixe the religion with matters of ſtate, they apperteine to diuerſe magiſtrates; God will haue vs here obedient to bothe, becauſe they a
                  •
                his lieutenants, eſtablished in his name and authoritie we should not ſerue our ſelues with the command of the one, to diſobey the other in his charge. Who ſo euer hender any of the two, can not ſerue him ſ
                  •
               lfe with excuſe of the other: we muſt follow bothe their commands according to their place &amp; rank: they at ordained by God to keepe one another, and not to diſtroy each other. If ſtanding to the true ſaith, to the defence of our ſoueraigne, we be perſecuted either in lyf body or goods, after the bataill, we shalbe reſtored to ou
                  •
                owne, or to meikill better. he who receaueth a prophete in name of a prophete, shall receaue the reward of a prophete 
                  Mat. 10
               
yea he who giueth a cuppe of cold water in the name of a Diſciple shall not looſe his reward, what shall he receaue I pray you, who willinglie, w
                  •
               en occaſion ſe
                  •
               ueth, gifeth his lyf to God in Gods name to declaire his veritie or mainteine his iuſtice in defence of religion or his Prince, ſo highly recommended to vs by God him ſelfe? lat vs not infect this gift &amp; oblation with our priuat plottes and paſſions, he who heard Sainct Paul in his weaknes, will graunt vs ſtrenght to ſuſteine all aduerſities: he will ſay to vs alſo ſufficiat vobis gratia mea: the more we looſſe here, the more we shall winne in heauen. Seing this patience ſure I am that the Kinges Maieſtie will not be ſo farre offend
                  •
               d, when he shall vnderſtand that thereis onely conſcience that do ſtoppe you to condeſcend to many thinges, and no rebellion nor contempt of his lawes, or ordainances: for in that caſe ye prefer onely God to him, and that becauſe your fi
                  •
               ſt obligation moueth you thereto. Byding in this reſolution, the victorie shalbe yours, and ye shall obteine, if not mans, at leſt Goddes fauour, otherwiſe ye may look to looſſe bothe: ſurther we may hope that his Maieſtie being better informed of the matter, wilbe more gra
                  •
               ious to his true and humble ſubi
                  •
               cts then to punish

them by death, banishment or priuation of their goods in fauour of the miniſters who byding at the ground
                  •
               s of their doctrine can neither be good Chriſtians nor true ſubiects as we haue sha
                  ••
                alreddie, and shall sh
                  •
               w more euiden
                  •
               ly here after if this be not thought ſufficient. Yet if our ſinn
                  •
               s be ſo great that God will haue vs punis
                  •
               ed with all tigour and extremitie in this preſent lyf, lat vs receaue the ſame not onely with patience becauſe we haue deſerued meikill more, but alſo with gladneſſe and thankes giuing as comming o
                  •
                his hand, who will gif vs the ſtrenght to beare it, ſeing that his quartell is mixed with our paines, lat vs crye for his helpe▪ and ſucco
                  •
               re who hath the heartes of Princes in his hand, that he may diſpenſe their actions to his glorie, to their and our ſaluation and publik peace and quietneſſe. how that shalbe donne, we muſt leaue it to his infinitie wiſdome and prouidence hauing alwaies in our heartes and mouthes, thy will be donne in earth as it is in heauen.
            Now to retourne to you againe (good ſites) it is not onely very dangerouſe, but alſo farre againſt the duetie of a good Chriſtian man to ſweare according to your deſyre, os reither command and force, to

witt that they abhorre and deteſt all contrario
                     ••
                   religion and doctrine (to your reformation) but cheiflie all kynd of papiſtrie in generall and particulere heades▪
                Becauſe the moſt chief heads of the Catholik Apoſtolik and Romane doctrine (w
                  •
               ich ye of your great humanitie and courteſie doe call papiſtrie at all occaſions and propos) a
                  •
                conteined in the ſymbol of faith m
                  •
               de by the Apoſtles, if ye haue any thing to ſay there to ye may. But as to vs, as we beleef in the ſymbol that there is one God omnipotente Fat
                  •
               er, Sonne, &amp; holie Ghoſt, w
                  •
               o hath created, redeemed, &amp; ſanctified vs by his infinite goodnes &amp; mercy; ſo do we beleef that there is one holie Catholik kirk, by whoſe mouth we ar inſtructed in all theis thinges, that we should beleef, or do; becauſe shee is the ſpouſe and myſticall body of Ieſus Chriſt, of whome as of hir head shee hath grace and power, and we command to obey. Theis at the generall heades of that which ye call papiſtrie (ſeing it pleaſed you ſo to terme it) where vpon ar biulded all particuler heades profeſſed by the ſame kirk, and all hi
                  •
                children remaning in due obedience within hi
                  •
                boſome. To deteſt and abhorre theis thinges, ye may eaſely iudge your ſelues (if paſſiō commād not aboue your 
                  •
               ittes) how hard a thing it wil
                  •
                be to 
                  •
               any

Chriſtian man, w
                  •
               o hath Chriſts ſpouſe in good eſtimation and as it becometh him to haue hi
                  •
                who is guided with ſo nobell a head: But ye will ſay that ye condemne not that which is good, but our errours: I anſweare to you in one word, ſo farre as I can ſee ye haue as litell iudgement to diſcerne vpon an errour, as ye haue power to condemne it. But this doth require a more ample diſcours. Moreouer to haue the Catholik religion in greater horrour and deteſtation then te Iewdaiſme, Turciſme, hereſie, or at heiſme I can not think that it cometh of a good and holie Frere Iohn Crag fleeing out of Italie frō the Catholik
                     •
                  : being (as he ſaid) in need he receaued a pourſe frome 
                     •
                   black dogge, iudge y
                     •
                   of that viaticum.ſpirite; but rather of him, who vnder the figure &amp; shape of a black dogge gaue a purſe with ſiluer to the forger of your confeſſion. But I vnderſtand well how the matter ſtanded: he who hath fled a way for knauerie, had rather ſerue any man then retorne back to his owne maiſter. It is not my intent at this preſent to refu
                  •
               e your negations of the faith: ye will gif occaſions, as ye haue giuen matter to anſwear by the groundes of your owne doctrine and maximes of your chief miniſters, which I graunt ye may deny, as ye haue donne many better thinges, by reaſon of your Chriſtian libertie, where by ye may 
                  •
               udge and condemne whome and what ye pleaſe if it agree not with the ſcriptures interpreted

by you, that is, with your opinion▪ where to ar ſubiect all thinges, by vertue of the ſpirite which guideth you as ſupreme iudges without appealle, for otherwiſe thinges can not ſtand with your credit: ye hold as the chief foundament of your deteſtations and refuſals, that the Pape is the Antichriſt: which point no man of iudgement can paſſe with, meikilles to ſubſcribe or ſweare it to be true. Sundry cunning and learned men hath moſt ſufficiently confuted this blaſphemous reuerie, ſo I may be excuſed if I enter no further in the matter, yet for other mens contentement, who haue not ſeene, or could not vnderſtand theſe bookes, I will bring here ſome reaſons why that can not be. And  firſt the Pape acknowledgeth not onely God to be aboue him, to whome all honour and glorie iuſtly doeth apperteine becauſe he is maker and authour of all thinges; but alſo he acknowledgeth the Angels and Sainctes (although in different degree &amp; maner, God for his owen cauſes and them for Goddes cauſe) who ar in heauen; and for that cauſe prayet
                  •
                to them as being Gods in time and moſt deare friends to interced for him; where as the Antichriſt if ye will gif credit to Sainct Paul, shall prefer him ſelf to all thing that is called God, where no exception is made.

Secondly we reade of no Pape who hath ſlaine  either Elias or Eno
                  •
               h, or any other excellent men indued with ſupernaturall giftes, principallie at Ieruſalem ſeing there hath beene there no Pape thes many hondred yeares. Further the Papes ſucceſſiuely haue raigned  th
                  •
               s ſ
                  •
               xteine hondred yeares not witſtanding of the great varietie and trouble of the 
                  •
               yme. The An
                  •
               ichriſt should reigne onely three yeares and an half. Moreouer there  was never yet any Pape receaued by 
                  •
               he Iewes for their true M
                  •
               ſſias, becauſe the Pape doeth teach that the true Meſſias is alreddie come: the Antichriſt should be receaued, Si alius venertt in nomine ſuo 
                     •
                  um recipietis. of contrarie there is no man they hate ſo meikill as they hate the Pape, becauſe he is the greateſt obſtacle thes 1600. yeares. ye being yet in lumbis in
                     •
                  iſibilis Eccleſiae. The Euāgell should  be receaued through all before the Antichriſt come: The Euangell is not yet receaued through all: and if the Pape be not yet come why preach ye againſt him? The Pape with  all diligence and 
                  •
               a
                  •
               e hath keaped and yet do keape Iuge ſaecrific
                     •
                  um the perpetuall ſacrifice which onely is accep
                  •
               able and pleaſant to God: &amp; therefore the Antichriſt will labour to tak it away: where in ye trauell as ye can. The pape mainteineth the religion of his 
               
forfathers, for he cond
                  •
               mneth all thing as errour that is contrarie to the doctrine of the primitiue kirk and venerable an
                  •
               iquitie; becauſe Ieſus Chriſt being the veri
                  •
               ie it ſelf, the religion founded vpon him, and published by his deare ſpouſe at his command, can neither be variable nor falſe. the Antichriſt shall miſpryce the religiō of his fathers wherein  ye imitat him perfectly well. The pape ſitteth at Rome and hath ſo donne thes many ages. The Antichriſt should ſit at Ieruſalem.  The Pape adoreth with all humilitie and reuerence the Trinitie, teacheth and commandeth all true Chriſtians to doo the ſame. The Antichriſt openeth his mouth with all ſorte of blaſphemie againſt the holie Triniti
                  •
               .  The Pape 
                  •
               alleth him ſelf Seruu
                     •
                   ſeruorum Dei, acknowledging that the honour he receaueth of men, is becauſe of his office that he hath of God, and that he is inſtitute Paſtour here in earth to ſerue the wholl flock of Ieſus Chriſt out lord whoſe ſeruant he is and chief miniſter: And therefor before all mortall men in dignitie ſeing he repreſenteth Chriſt our ſoueraigne Lord, yet ſubiect to ſerue all men, helpe and aſſiſt them becauſe of his office and charge, certainely the leſt of the realme is to be prefered to the greateſt, how lōg he repreſented the Kinges Maieſties

perſonne. The Antic
                  •
               riſt shall call him ſelf God. There hath beene two hundred and  thirtie Papes and more: there should be but one Antichriſt contrarie to Chriſt in all thinges: for we ſpeak here of the great Antichriſt. The religion profeſſed by the Pape hath dured  (with your owm prophetes confeſſions) more thē twalf hundred year
                  •
               s: the religiō or rather impietie of the Antichriſt should dure short ſpace, as he him ſelfe. The Antichriſt  should be an Apoſtate &amp; go out of the kirk of God, where by that his wickednes may be the greater being ioyned with rebelliō
               ▪ The Pape remaineth yet ſtill in the houſe of God.  There hath beene great number of hereſies &amp; heretikes during theis 1600. yeares that we haue hade ſo many Papes. But the Antichriſt should be the laſt of the heretiks, becauſe all wickedneſſe should be compleit in him, all heretiks ſeruing to him as foreriders, where of Simon Magus was the firſt a deteſtable magicien and a traiterous apoſtate, who not withſtanding hath found ouer many cō
               panions to follow him. Ieſus Chriſt should  ſlay the Antichriſt with the ſpirite of his mouth, that is, as ye interprete it, with the preaching of the Euangell, that hath he never donne to any Pape, albeit ye haue imaginated to your ſelfs, that ye haue ſlaine the Pape

by your preachinges, o
                  •
                rather taillinges, the Pape never hath had one houres ſicknes for all your crying; aſſure your ſelues that his infirmities cometh of other cauſes. Luther in ſpirite of prophicie as he thought made this moſt notable verſe Peſtis eram viuus, moriens tu
                     •
                   mors ero Papa: he knew very well the firſt part to be true, and therefore myght ſay it confidently, the laſt part was lyk the authour, falſe and vntrue, he being deade and his doctrine bothe, it being changed partly by him ſelf during his lyf, partly by his diſciples and followers after his deathe, where as the Papes Authoritie, becauſe it is founded vpon God, doth remaine, &amp; shall remaine till the  worlds end. The Antichriſt should oppoſe him ſelf to our lord in all thinges and abolish his name and honour ſo farre as he can: for ſo the name of Antichriſt doth ſignifie. The  Pape doeth the plaine contrarie. The Antichriſt ſhould come after Gog &amp; Magog: howbeit that the Papes hath beene ſo many ages, yet know we not, what Gog and Magog ar, nor what place of the world they dwell in.  The Pape honoreth the Sainctes as Gods vndoubted friends and deſyreth them to pray for him. Where vpon maliciouſly ye preach to the people that we gif Chriſts honour to the Saincts &amp; yet we acknowledge them as ſeruants

onely, who hath credit to pray and not to command. The Antichriſt should haue  in his name the number of 666. to find this number your brethren, further different frome you in doctrine and diſcipline then in place or habites, haue taken great paines tourning the Papes names, but all in vaine, it could not be found the holie ſpirite hauing ſo prouided againſt your calumnies. Many  thouſands ar ſaued in the Catholik kirk, which ye call the papiſt kirk, for otherwiſe all your forfathers ar condemned, yea all the ancient fathers, martyres, and doctours of the kirk, ſeing that they haue acknowledged the pape for their ſuperior, and chief vicare to Ieſus Chriſt, and a great part of you were baptiſed by the membres of the Antichriſt, in whoſe kirk no man can be ſaued. The Pape  armeth him ſelf &amp; al men ſo far as he can for Ieſus Chriſt, with reaſons, ſcriptures, generall counceilles, authorities of fathers, exē
               ples of martyres, conſentement of the wholl Catholik kirk of all ages. The Antichriſt shall arme him ſelfe and his followers with force and violence againſt Ieſus Chriſt. The Pape conſerueth, and haue conſerued at all  tymes the ſcriptures: The Antichriſt if he do according to his name and profeſſion, should deſtroy the ſcriptures. The Pape hateth and 
               
condemneth all ſort of rebellions and nouelties in religion: The Antichriſt should embrace them as moſt proper &amp; conuenient inſtruments for his auancement of perdition.  The Pape came ſo quietly, and peaceablye (yea according to your owen 
                  •
               ellowes ſaying) that ye can not yet goodly-tell, when, or how he firſt entred in the kirk, ye ar ſo troubled to tell well your new forged fable. The Antichriſt should come with ſic trouble and miſchief as neuer was ſince the beginning of the world, where in he shalbe more lyk to you, then to the Pape, ſeing we can well tell when ye came, and may yet shew ouer euident  markes of your vnquiet intré. And to be short the Antichriſt should be filius perditioni
                     •
                  
                the ſonne of perdition, chief inſtrument of ſatan, that is, ſo poſſeſſed and aſsiſted with the deuill, that he shall do all thinges in the deuils power and for his cauſe, and shalbe ſo perfect and accomplished (if I should ſo ſay) in all vice and iniquitie, that no man can equall him, meikilles to ſurpaſſe him, and principallie in pryde, as our maiſter and lord Ieſus Chriſt did excell in all vertue, &amp; chiefly in humilitie diſcite à me, quia mitis ſum &amp; hu
                     ••
                  
                  lis corde. Wherefor not without reaſon ſundry learned men haue repported the ſeuen montains to the ſeuen deedly ſinnes which

shalbe in the Antechriſt in moſt high degree that he may iuſtly anſweare to his name, The Pape can no wayes be thought ſo wicked: I call to witnes all ſort of Proteſtantes of what ſo euer nation, ſaction, or opinion who haue beene at Rome before or ſince the Iubile, and haue ſeene the Pape who now ſitteth Clement the eight a man worthie of that name, if any of them may ſay in his conſcience, that he is ſo wicked and deſperate a mā, as the Antichriſt is deſcribed to be in the ſcriptures. Sure I am that there is none of them ſo far drounkē in the miniſteriall humour, that will ſay ſo, if he ſpeak according to that he hath ſeene. It is ſo far from that the Pape can be the Antichriſt that his moſt excellente Maieſtie a Prince of rare iudgement and learning, doth acknowledge the Pape to be a temporall Prince, to whom he is obliged and to whome in all good offices he wilbe correſpondent. 
                  •
               hat wordes may be ſaid to your opinion who maketh our Kinge to haue obligation from, and commerce with the Antichriſt? I may ſay with your pardon and licence ſeſſionall, that he is a better &amp; more honeſt man, then any miniſters that either is or euer was in Scotland without exception of your chief pontifs firſt or laſt, Iohn or Robert. I am aſſured

that he who knoweth the Pape an
                  •
                your miniſters will ſay the ſame, principally if it were queſtion of humilitie and humanitie: and if I be put to my proues, I hope eaſely to diſcharge my ſelfe litill to you
                  •
                honours. If this be true as it is moſt certaine why should any man ſweare the Pape to be the Antichriſt, that is the moſt wicked and deteſtable man that euer was, is, or shal be, ſeing that there is none of your companie how godly brethren that euer ye be, but i
                  •
                meikill worſe, then he? or if they ſweare a thing ſo farre out of all reaſon and verit
                  •
               e as thinking it true, why should they follow or acknowledge you for true and lawfull paſtours ſent by God to reforme the world, if ye be worſe then the Antichriſt, who muſt be the moſt deteſtable and abominable inſtrument that euer Satan hath employed? If ye ſay that it is but ſimulation and hypocriſie in the P
                  •
               pe to deceaue men, I anſweare you, that if we graunt your foolish affirmation, ye muſt alſo graunt to vs that the deuill hath donne more good with the Pape, &amp; his hypocriſie, pretēded, or fained holineſſe, then euer the holie ſpi
                  •
               ite, which is in you, I ſay, could do by 
                  •
               ou and your pietie and reformed Godlineſſe: your actions may beare witnes if I lie. O Sanctas gentes quibus ha
                     •
                  
               
               
               
                  
                     ••
                  ſ
                     •
                  untur in 
                     •
                  ortis minima. Whoſe beſt workes a
                  •
                ſo litill worthe. Certainely ye ar very greatly obliged to theis, who will not ſweare a thing ſo preiudiciable to your honour and reputation, which neceſſarilie followed vpō your doctrine, if it were once admitted. Truely I haue not ſo hard opinion of you: for notwitſtanding I eſteeme you in all degrees farre inferior to the Pape: yet think I not that ye ar ſo low &amp; abiect, or ſo wicked and abominable as the Antichriſt, meikilles to think you worſe. Acknowledge the obligation ye haue to them, who doing according to their conſciences toward the Pape, hath donne ſo meikill for your honour. But ye will ſay that ye ar not ſo wicked as the Pape. I doubt not but ye will winne your cauſe, if it be referred to your ſaying or othe. If the boundes of this epiſtle wold ſuffer, or if it were my principall butte to traict that matter, I should mak a compariſon betwix the Pape and you, where I should mak you ashamed (if ye haue any shame in your forhead) of your ſelues, the merueillous differē
               ce being ſeene. I maruell how a miniſter can look to his companions vnlaughen when he ſeeth the people beleef a thing ſo ridiculous. And in cōſciēce beleef ye that the Antichriſt shal be a litill hypocrite or ſimple heretik?

               
                  •
               e shalbe more furiouſe then any that euer came to trouble the kirk. Becauſe ye cannot shew that the Pape is come with force and violence, as our Lord hath aduertiſed vs he shall come, ye wold mak the world beleeue that the Antichriſt should come to continue lyk a lamb. Ieſus Chriſt ſayeth the contrarie of him. It wilbe an ill reformed faith to gif our lord the lie: how can ye think, that he who shalbe inſtructed and fullie inſpired wi
                  •
               h the ſpirite of Satan, will in any wiſe, ether follow or conter
                  •
               ect our maiſter and lord Ieſus Chriſt? ye deceaue your ſelues and all others, who credits you if ye beleef ſo. The heretiks, who ar onely his foreruners hath entred in the kirk of God lyk Woulfes and Tigres, and ye your ſelues came with ſo great modeſtie and quietnes, that the earth did tremble and shake vnder your feete (I know nōt if it was for gladeneſſe of your cō
               ming) ſo mightelye that the whole policie &amp; publik buildings thr
                  •
               ugh out all Scotlād did fall downe as if it had beene a generall earth quake. verelie according to his nature and dignitie, he muſt be more violent and cruell then all the reſt. Is it poſſible that ye think the Antichriſt will vſe onely perſuations, faire words, &amp; li
                  •
               ill hen wyles, ſeing that ye vſe all ſ
                  •
               rt of violences and compulſions?

he wilbe more cruell then ye in all reſpectes, more craftie and more mightie: he will bring with him all miſchiefs that can be inuented, &amp; for that cauſe God will shorten his tyme. Think ye that that deuill (if I 
                  •
               hould ſo ſay) wil be lyk Clemē
               
                  •
                the 8. Are ye ſo ignorant or ſo foolish? Truely Pape Clement is ſo wicked, that it were better haue ten thowſand lyk him, then one lyk 
                  •
               ny of you, and his death more to be ſorrowed thē the death of a hundred thouſand of you, howbeit ye haue a better opinion of your ſelfs. Think not alſo that the modeſtie that is in the Pape, cometh of any feare he hath of you or yours. Ye ſlay him euery yeare with your tounges, but ſo ſoftlie, that he perceaueth it no more, then ye did the firſt Papes entring. How can ye beleeue that the Pape or Papes, ar, or can be the Antichriſt, ſeing they haue condemned all the hereſies that hitherto hath riſin againſt ether the diuinitie or humanitie of Ieſus Chriſt (as may be proued by your owen fellowes) yea they haue condemned the errours riſin now of late yeares amonge your ſelues, as the new hereſies of Gentilis, Stancharus, Blandrata, and other good diſciples of Caluin, againſt the holie Trinitie, whoſe errour ye approue not although bred among you. How can it

be that they shal be the Antichriſt, who ſo ſtoutly, ſo conſtantlie, with ſo great expenſes and danger doeth defend the dignitie of Ieſus Chriſt? for they onely whome ye in your reformed language call the Antichriſt, hath holdin, approued, &amp; yet doth defend &amp; approue, all &amp; wholl the generall councelles where Chriſts honour, authoritie, and diuine Maieſtie haue beene lawfully defended and keeped: yet can ye not shew any ſic thing donne by you, who calles your ſelues true Chriſtians and lawfull paſtours. What shall we think of theſe Antichriſtes, &amp; of you zealous Chriſtians? They keept the bible from corruption of hereſies, when ye could not be found, yea when none of your reformed brethren could be ſeene, at what tyme your inuiſibilitie excuſed you from ſic charitable offices. It apperteneth to him onely whome ye call the Antichriſt to defend Chriſts name, keepe the bible, diſtroy hereſies, confute errours, conuert infideles, ſend to all partes to cō
               
                  •
               ort the faithfull, to aſſure them, who ar in brangle, to reduce them, who ar gone aſtray, and that in Europe, Aſie, and Afrik. Which is donne yet in the new found Ils, where there is more Chriſtians now, then heretikes in all Europe, yea a great deal more: O good &amp; diligēt Antichriſt

who onely hath watched &amp; laboured in the viniard of our Lord as it becometh a true &amp; faithfull ſeruāt. And o ye wicked negligēt, ſluggish &amp; diſloyall paſtours who haue ſleeped like as many Endymious thes 1500. years paſt in ſome obſcure caue, till the moune of falſe &amp; foolish imaginations haue wakned you, to embrace againe the cloudes of errour in place of that heauenly Iuno of veritie Haue we not iuſt occaſion to wish of God to haue in your place ſo good and godly an Antichriſt? which if we hade in euery toune, we should not now haue beene in paine to refell your follies. We may bouldly ſay that this Antichriſt is meikill better reformed, then your kirk, and leſſe to be feared, then your reformation. I doubt not but ye wold here willingly anſweare, that ye contribu
                  •
               e with no leſſe good will for the diliuerance of Geneua, which ye make the people beleeue is beſieged by the Duk of Sauoye (where I will remark a great folie in you to beleeue a thing ſo mani
                  •
               eſtly falſe, &amp; a malice in them, who haue abuſed ſo farre your ſimplicitie and rash crudelitie) for their reformed faith. I wold alſo willingly know of you, why your reformed charitie extendeth it ſelf onely to ſic as haue rebelled againſt their lawfull Prince reither then to

them, who round about you ar in great need and diſtreſſe? If ye did helpe your holie citie becauſe of their neceſſi
                  •
               ie, I wold think it well done, if ye could do well with out preiudice to your onely faith. But to mainteine their rebellion againſt their iuſt and lawfull Prince, is but an open and euident argument of that which is ſecretly hid in your breaſtes as we haue ſaid here before. I was almoſt here deliberat to shew that a great nomber of the qualities which should be in the Antichriſt may be eaſely found in you, as in his ſorriders: but I will keep that to your anſwere, if perchance ye perſiſt in your Antichriſtian opinion. For then we shall ſee God willing, whither ye can better apply the markes to the Pape, or we to you.
            8. Now to your excommunication, a thing truely meikill to be wished of many, and to be embraced of all men: for who should not deſyre to be out of their followship, who ar ioyned together by periuries, treaſon, &amp; errours? Honeſt true and faithfull men should ſeek by all meanes to deliuer them ſelues of ſic companie if either willingly, rashlie, or by force they haue entred there in. Yet lat vs ſee what power ye haue to excommunicate

any man. Onely true and lawfull paſtours (which ye can not be, lacking as ye do, the law
                  •
               ull vocation) haue power and authoritie to excommunicate: where vpon it followeth that ye haue no power nor authoritie at all. we haue brought manv reaſons in our offer printed, why your calling can not be good, w
                  •
               ich for the preſent we will not repeate, becauſe your owen reformation will furnish vs good ſtore of reaſons to proue the ſame, which we will employ here becauſe they ar your owen and that moſt foundamentall. Ye will graunt me if I be not deceaued that the office and dignitie of a paſtour is ſo great and excellent, that it properly conuiueth only to Ieſus Chriſt, and is cōmunicated, to ſic as it pleaſed him to call there to, either by ordinarie meanes, or extraordinatiely that is immediatly by him ſelf. And for that cauſe no man should be ſo hardie or reither temerarie as to medle there with of him ſelf, if he wold not incurre the cryme of leſmaieſtie diuine, in taking the office of Ieſus Chriſt out of his hand. For this cauſe Luther, ſeing he could not well ſerue him ſelf with the ordinarie vocation of the Catholik kirk, where he was nurished and brought vp, took him to the extraordinarie, alledging he was ſent immediatly by God to

reforme the world Frome this extraordinarie power g
                  •
               fin to Luther, ye haue receaued your ordinarie calling, which I muſt shew to be falſe with moſt euident reaſons, to proue that ye haue no authoritie to excommunicate any man. Luther was ſent (if we will credit him and you) by God him ſelf to teach the trueth, the which might ſerue vs for a ſufficient warrand of his aſſured true vocation, that the true doctrine he broght with him, might force vs to acknowledge his power. I will for the preſent (albeit againſt the veritie) ſuppoſe all as true and good, becauſe out of theis principels and groundes we shall eaſely prooue, that ye haue no lawfull vocation, and conſequently at no true Paſtours, where vpon followeth the millitie of your pretended excommunication. Luthers doctrine (ſay ye) was true, ergo his vocation was good, and he a lawfull Paſtour. I ſay on the other ſyde (by the maxime of your owen doctrine) if his doctrine w
                  •
               s falſe his vocation was not good, nor yours receaued frome him, and conſequently neither 
                  •
               e, nor ye lawfull paſtours: or if your doctrine be falſe, your vocation (if ye hade any of him) is loſte and ye no paſtours, becauſ
                  •
                the true doctrine onely (as ye alledge) is the ſure proofe of true vocation. If Luthers

doctrine was true and of the holie Spirit, doub
                  •
               les yours is 
                  •
               alſe, ſeing ye teach doctrine not onely farre different frome his doctrine, but alſo in many heads plaine contrarie as may be eaſely shewen by bothe your writtinges Heare, I pray you what one The
                     •
                  log C. lu
                     •
                  
                  niſt. l
                     •
                  b 2. ſol. 135.
               o
                  •
                your Lutherian breth
                  •
               en ſayeth H
                     •
                  nc
                     •
                  gitur inter omnes piè eruditos conſtat Luth
                     •
                  rum non Vertumni aut Eceboli inſtar in veritate ſemel agnita &amp; profeſsa varillaſſe, ſed in 
                     •
                  a per Dei grat
                     •
                  am vſque ad extremum vitae halitam permanſiſse: Caluinistas verò, in hoc &amp; alijs articulis ſibi nunquam conſtare ex Zuinglij, Martyris, Bu
                     •
                  eri, Philippi, Victorin
                     •
                  , Hemmingy, profugorum VVitebergentium &amp; aliorum libris &amp; actionibus docers &amp; d
                     •
                  m
                     •
                  nstrari potest. And in the inſcription of the ſame book he ſpeaketh very plainely howye agree together and with the veritie. Theologiae Caluinistarum libri tres, in quibus ceu in tabella quadam, quaſi ad oculum pluſquam ex 223▪ 
               ſacramenta
                     •
                  iorum publicis ſcriptis, pagellis, verbis proprijs, &amp; auth
                     •
                  orum 
                     •
                  onibus indicatis, demonſtratur, eos de null
                     •
                   ferè doctrinae Chriſtianae articulo rectè ſentire: addita ſimul verae ſententiae aſs
                     •
                  rtione, &amp; contrariae opinionis refutatione: collecti opera &amp; ſtudio M. Conrad
                     •
                   Schluſſ
                     •
                  lburgij, dioeceſeos Rareburgenſis, ſuperintendentis &amp; coniunctarum Megapolenſium Eccleſiarum generalis inſpectoris. In his cataloge of heretikes he cō
               pteth the Caluiniſts, againſt whome he

writteth the third book that he concludeth thus. Epilog. de ſecta Caluiniſtarū. Cum igitur ex enumeratis noſtrae doctrinae rationibus, &amp; falſis ſacramentariorum fundamentis conſcientiam anxiā ſemper in dubio relinquentibus, luce meridiana clarius apparea
                     •
                   imp
                     •
                  os &amp; blaſphemos eſſe Caluiniſtarum errores; Nos ſecundum Dei verbum (ye ſee how this mā alledgeth againſt you the word of God for his warrand) Auguſtanam confeſſionem veterem, ſcripta viri Dei Lutheri, librum concordi
                     •
                   atque apologiam eiuſdem, à ſacramentarijs (he ſpeaketh of your ſect) tanquam blaſphemis hareticis nobis caueamus, &amp; ipſorum opinionem impiam tanquam praſentiſsimum &amp; noxium animae venenum toto pectore execremur. Further ye may ſee what Hunnius hath writtin not only againſt all the Caluiniſts in generall, but alſo in particular againſt Caluin in a book intituled Caluinus Iudai Zans. In the other part it will not be difficill to you to know what Zuinglius, Caluin, Beza, Lauatherus and the reſt of that band haue writtē againſt Luther and Lutherians, and with what diſpyte and iniuries they treate one another, Scires 
                     •
                   ſanguine natos, which may euidently proue the diuerſitie of their doctrine. If the one haue the trueth, neceſſarily the other can not haue it, ſeing they agree not: ſo if the one haue the true vocation the other can not

haue it, they being of repugnant doctrine.
            9. But ye will ſay that Luther did onely beginne the holie reformation which then was ſo neceſſarie in the kirk, that God was moued to ſend him extraordinarily for that cauſe: yet hade he not the ſtrength to performe it, as it was needfull; which worke Caluin with his followers, but principally ye, haue done by your reformatiō: changing all thinges, that no thing can be better, tourning af
                  •
               irmations in to negations, faire buildings in to kellyards or corne land, good order in to confuſion, charitie in to particular profit, obed
                  •
               ēce in to rebelliō, ſuperioritie in to a foli ſhe paritie, aſſu
                  •
               āce in to miſtruſt &amp;c. becauſe he &amp; ye haue bene moſt fullie inſtructed with the holie ſpirite. If we receaue this for a good anſweare, we muſt ſay that this hath bene dōne by a n
                  •
               w cōmiſſion that God ha
                  •
               h gifin to Caluin and you, farre different from the commiſſion gifin to Luther and his 
                  •
               ollowers: for the Lutherians according to this ſaying, hade only charge to beginne the matter, and ye to end it; but beginning and ending ſhould agree to gether, and not like aegri ſomnia or worſe. They should agree I ſay, if they be of one ſpirite, except they come of that ſpirite, who neuer yet could agree with him ſelfe. The holie ſpirite

who is the ſp
                  ••
               ite of vnion and concorde could not haue condemned by your mouth, which he hath approued by Luthers or Lutherians mouthes▪ I doubt not but ye truſt al that ye haue the holie ſpirite, yet the diuerſitie of your opinions aſſure me the contrarie, ſeing that the ſpirit, who approueth and authoriſeth the one and his doctrine, condemneth and diſchargeth the others and their doctrin. If ye ſay that the errours hade takin ſo deepe roote that it was not poſſible to take them out of mens hartes in short ſpace, and therefore we should not maruell if there be many 
                  •
               hingis in Luthers doctrine not agreable with the veritie. But, I pray you, hade it not beene more ſeemely and as eaſie to Luther (if he was ſent by God, whoſe aſiſtence he could not want in that caſe) to haue told the veritie at the beginning as to haue preached new errours ſo deteſtable, as ye ſay, and ſo contrarie to Godds worde and our ſaluation? what ſpirite moued him ſo to doe? If he 
                  •
               ad winked at ſome or many of theſe poinctes that ye call errours, which he found in the kirk before him becauſe of the inueterate opinion cōfi
                  •
               med by long vſe, there might be ſome apparent excuſe in your anſwere, but to bring in errour for errour, or to put out one to take in two (the people

being ſo docill to 
                  •
               eceaue what ſo euer impreſſion at that tyme Luther wold or cold haue giuen them) or to confirme obſtinatly an ancient errour is no worke of the holie ſpirite, who should haue guided your extraordinat
                  •
               e prophete and new ſent paſtour. Or was the holie ſpi
                  •
               ite ſo weake in Luthers mouth, that he could not teach him the veritie? or Luther ſo hard harted, 
                  •
               hat he could not receaue, nor conceaue the veritie mekilles teach it to others? or hade the holie ſpirite ſince that tyme found Caluin a more proper inſtrument to inſtruct the world truely and plainely in all thinges? Then why was he a lying ſpirite in Luthers mouth, ſeing it was o
                  •
                him, ye haue your extraordinarie calling, which now is ſo ordinairie and eſtablished that no man may preach without it?
            
               B
                     •
                   Za in epiſtol. th
                     •
                  olog. &amp; de notis Ecc
                     ••
                  ſiae. 10. I ſee not what can be anſwered here. or shal we tourne ba
                  •
               ke againe to the firſt foundament of Luthers extraordinarie vocation? where of the marke was the true doctrine, which ye ar conſtrained to denye and diſauow, if ye wold proue your owen good: for he condemneth you and your doctrine, and ye condemne him and his doctrine; which if ye denye obruam vos aduerſarum &amp; veſ
                     •
                  rarum partium voluminibus ſcriptiſque contrarijs.
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
what shal become here of your vocatiō? for lack of true doctrine it wilbe null, either in him, or you, or (if ye ſay bothe true in your mutuall accuſation) in you both? what shal become of your miniſterie if this falſe thunder be shaken out of your hands? ye will haue hard eſcapping out of this ſnare, wherein ye haue feltred your ſelues, fleing frome the Catholik kirk. For if ye ſay that it is ynough that ye agree in the groundes and foundaments of faith and religion which ar neceſſarie altogether for mans ſaluation, and in theſe ye agree with Luther and Lutherians, &amp; they with you. I wolde gladly vnderſtand what ar theſe groundes and foundaments of faith and religion neceſſarie for Iuſt. lib. 4. 
                  
                     •
                  ap. 1. 
                  
                     •
                  . 9.mans ſaluation. Is it to beleeue that there is but one God? Ieſus Chriſt to be God &amp; Gods Sonne? That our ſaluation cōſiſted in Godes mercy &amp; other ſic thinges as ſayeth Caluin? Or in the Creed, Lordes prayer, &amp; ten commands De notis Eccl
                     •
                  ſiae.as thinketh Beza? Or ſhal they be in the inuocatiō of our lord Ieſus Chriſt as teacheth du Pleſſis? Or ſhal theſe foundaments be the negation and deteſtation of the Catholik doctrine, or (as ye call it) papiſtrie according to your mēſwearing of the true fai
                  •
               h? If ye wil hold you at your owen groūd, I ſay onely that a negatiue faith, is no faith

properly, and ſo your negations wil neuer open the heauens to you, except that ye think that the Iewes gentils Turkes and heretikes o
                  •
                all ſects and at hei
                  •
               ts may haue place as well there as ye, ſeing they can deny heads of religion profeſſed by the Catholiks Ye ar th
                     •
                   firſt that eu
                     •
                  r did propoſ
                     •
                   negatiō
                  
                     •
                   for a faith.with noth leſſe aſſurance then ye, &amp; a great part of the ſame with you. If ye will ſay any of the
                  •
               s thinges which the others hade ſaid I ask you wherefore came Luther, ſeing theis thinges (as ye can not denie
                  •
               ) were beleeued in the Catholik kirk before that euer Luther blew the trompette of ſedition or as ye wold call it, reformation, if that honour had not beene reſerued to you? if the puritie of theis pointes was requeſit, why came Luther, ſeing he teacheth not that puritie? For that was reſerued to you onely as we haue ſaid often tymes. It were out of purpos to ſay that God hade ſent him to bring in new errours and confirme ould vnder p
                  •
               etext of ſome few that he hath taken away, where by an other might be ſent. Was it needfull that your Caluin should as an other Sainct Iohn the Baptiſt Parare viam Domini? In the meane tyme I will conclude (if there was ſo many errou
                  •
               s in Luthers doctrine▪ that it was needfull to ſend another in his place to teach the trueth) that his extraordinarie vocation

was not good, or els yours, who at come vpon a falſe token to gif him the lie. But Domini moderatores why shall we beleeue Luther in ſome heads of religion as hauing commiſſion of God and not in others, becauſe ye ſay it? According to your Eu
                  •
               ngell ye at all equall, not one greater thē an other: why shall we gif you more credit, then him? or if we refuſe to credit Luther, why shall we not re
                  •
               uſe to credit you alſo, that ye may remaine euer Pares? or why shall we beleeue your, when ye improue ſome thinges and approue others? is it not needfull here to haue a new extraordinarie calling to iudge with diſcretion and to our ſaluation? and if in any thing ye be gone wrong, ſhould there not be another extraordinarie prophete to correct you as ye haue corrected others? And ſeing that the true kirk (according to your reformed opinion) may erre, when sh
                  •
               ll we haue lawfull paſtours? ye put the true doctrine the certaine mark of lawfull calling, yet it can not be hade, becauſe euery man bringeth errour with him, and the kirk is vncertaine and ſubiect to errour and ſo we can not truſt hir. And certainely as to Luther, I credit you, when ye accuſe him of falſe doctrine and his followers, becauſe he him ſelfe doth acknowledge his nature to

be ſo corrupted and defiled, that he can do no good at all. But that ye be not draw in frome your paritie, I gif alſo credit to Luther and his followers when they accuſe you of ſo many errours, and your patriarche Caluin of ſo great wickednes, becauſe he acknowledges him ſelf of as good nature and inclination as Luther, and therefor can not tell the veritie ſincerely, as not being proper inſtruments for ſo precious a worke which wold be ſpilt, if they touch it. Monſieur du Pleſſis hath no better opinion of mans nature in generall, as may be ſeene in the third book of the Euchariſtie cap. 17. not far from the end, where he ſeemeth to ſay that the grace of God can not mak good, that cometh of vs, becauſe that we mix in with Goddes work ſome of our owen particular honour, glorie, profit, and ſo that there is no good which we can do well, nor no ill but we can do ouer well: for ſo he ſpeaketh. Notwithſtāding we read not that any, who hath beene ſent extraordinariely by God to preach the veritie, haue teached or propoſed in Godds name to be beleeued any falſe doctrine And it is to be ſuppoſed that God hauing ſent Luther, hath alſo ſufficiently inſtructed him in all thinges he ſhould ſay or do in that charge and office: for otherwiſe

ſeing the thinges that we should beleeue at aboue all naturall reaſon and humaine iudgement, how shall we know, if he, who is ſent by God, keep the direction which he hath receaued? if he be conuict in one falſhood, he loſſeth credit in all the reſt, and there by diſappointeth his maiſters intent, who employeth him, Further it is certaine that God of his in finite wiſdome &amp; power, either choſhed or maked the inſtrumēt proper, that he will employ, and ſuffers not in theis great matters to go otherwiſe then he will &amp; our ſaluation requireth. For it is impoſſible that man can be deceaued by God who is the veritie it ſelf. But ye will ſay that his doctrine who is ſent, should be examined with the word of God conteined in the ſcriptures: yea but he is come to interprete the ſcriptures to you and not to 
                  •
               ece
                  •
               ue any interpretation of you. His vocation gifeth him good aſſurance to ſpeak. If ye wold trie his vocation by the ſcriptures, ye should haue good reaſon, but to trie his doctrine hauing admitted his calling I ſee no reaſon.
            11. Moreouer if it be lawfull to call in doubt any mans doctrine who is extraordinariely ſent now in our dayes, why shall it not be lawfull to call in doubt the doctrine of all the
                  •
               s, that euer were ſent extraordinariely

by God, principallie ſeing ye acknowledge not the Authoritie of the kirk? For being doubt ſome and incertane in the one, ye can not be aſſured in the others ſeing that it is that ſame God that ſent them all, and for that ſame end▪ ſo shall we haue the whole bible, I ſay not ſubiect to triall, but ſubiect to be reiected by euery preſumptuous braine, as hath beene donne by ſund
                  •
               y in our dayes &amp; beſore. Further ſeing we should receaue nothing of any extraordinarie Paſtour but that which we haue tryed with the ſcriptures, I wold be glade to know, what triall can be made by wemen and children or ignorantes? For if triall should paſſe before, why should any man or woman (how ignorant that euer they were) reither then learned mē receaue any doctrine without triall? or why force ye m
                  •
               n to approue ſweare and ſubſcribe your negations before they haue well tried them to be true, or reither ſeing they find them falſe. But we will keep the reſt of this diſpute to the triall of your ſeſſions presbiteries and aſſembles prouincials and generals, where in ger erall and particuler we shall, God willing, diſcuſſe this matter the beſt we can. Now to your calling, which I ſay can not be good, whe
                  •
               her Luthers be good or ill. For if it be good who ſo

euer ingyre him ſelf to preach and teach in the kirk of God as being a lawfull Paſtour, not hauing power of Luther, should be eſteemed a priuat man and not a publik officer of Gods houſe, a traitour and not a true man, a woolf and not a hited, ye and yours being without his miſſion and calling, as we haue alreddie shewin, I ſee not what ye can pretend for you, to haue donne as ye haue. Which I proue once againe in this ſort: He who is ſent a Paſtour and Doctour in the kirk of God, principally is ſent to preach the Doctrine, as he receaued it of the Doctour who ſent him: if he doeth otherwiſe, his commiſſion or procuration conteining no ſic thing as he hade donne, can not ſerue him: for who ſo euer cometh in the kirk with charge, cometh as procurer, and not as proprieter, wherefor he should do according to his procuration, (becauſe he hath onely the handling of other mens goods and good) and not according to his fantaſie, as if all were his owen. Now if Luther the firſt of this new extraordinarie calling ſent you, it vvas to preach that ſame doctrine, which he preached &amp; hath deliuered to the world before he ſent you. If ye keep not that doctrine, his miſſion ſerueth you to no purp
                  •
               s, becauſe ye haue not donne the thing,

wherefor ye were ſent, it not your commiſſion iuſtly called back and ye declared euill officers? As when ye gif power or commiſſion to any new young ſcholler to gouuerne a kirk, it is not without iniunctions that he shall teach that ſame doctrine, that ye teach and that he hath heard of you, and not a nother forged at his owen fantaſie or inuented by an other. If he do contrarie to your command, wold ye not depoſe him as not doing according to the power receaued of you? and therefore iuſtly to be diſawowed, but ſo that he could not ſerue him ſelf againſt you with your procuration hauing paſſed the boundes preſcribed to him. Now if ye haue receaued any power of Luther or nor, I refer the matter to you, I ſay onely that ye haue preached and yet do preach another doctrine then he &amp; his followers do preach. ergo ye ar priuat men and not publik officers or lawfull paſtours in this new reformed kirk▪ except perhapes by verrue of your reformation it be lawfull to rulle without reaſon, ye may call your ſelues paſtours and ſainctes of God; ye will neuer perſuade to men of iudgement that ye ar his ſainctes as long as ye take vpon you, the charge of Paſtours without power or charge. Think not but thi
                  •
                merites a 
                  •
               u
                  •
               t excommunication▪
               
and not a conterfaited folie lyk yours, medling our ſelues with things for aboue your ſtate, being but priuat men, yea ſo meikill worſe then priuat men, that your vſurpation maketh you giltie of cryme of leſmaieſtie diuine. I
                  •
                ye will not credit me, go to Luther your firſt patriarche, and he will declare, w
                  •
               at he thinke
                  •
               h, ſeing he hath long ſince excommunicated you out of his new kirk becauſe in place of his heauenly doctrine (as he ſayeth) ye haue teached your doctrine which ye haue brought out of hell (tak you to him if the words be ſome what sharpe) to priſon the wordle; and for that cauſe in the very beginning he did excommunicat Caluin &amp; Zuinglius whom he called ſacramentaries and that moſt iuſtly according to their owen opinion: for they acknowledging him for that new beginning of their vocation and new reformed kirk, it behoued him to haue that power aboue them. So what doubt is but Luther hauing power to ſend them, hath power alſo to call them back if they paſt the boundes of his commiſſion? I he hath called them back and broken the commiſſion he gaue them before (as in deed he hath donne what he could that is in imagination as he gaue them that power) they at priuate men againe in

the middes of their reformation, and ye alſo, deſtitute of all power and authoritie to excommunicat any man. By this although Luther hath neuer called backe his power gifin to Caluin, yet could it ſerue him for no Warrand, ſeing that Luther denyeth planely that euer he him ſelf receaueth any charge to ſpeake or write ſundry thinges, which Caluin and Zuinglius haue ſpoken and written ſince that tyme: and therefor he calles them heretiks and ſacramentaries as I haue ſaid before. Or if he receaued charge to preach thes thinges, why condemneth he other men, who preached them? There were ſome excuſe, if he did not all, but there is no excuſe nor reaſon, why he should hinder other men hauing lawfull power of him ſelf, to do that which he could not do, or to condemne them, who teacheth the veritie that being the chief and principall end of his 
                  •
               xtraordinarie vocation. There is none of all 
                  •
               he Prophetee, Euangeliſts, or other holie writters, who haue written althinges, which 
                  •
               t hath pleaſed God to sh
                  •
               w to the world. 
                  •
               or ſo he hath though it good to diſtribute 
                  •
               is giftes at ſundry tyms, to ſundry perſon
               
                  •
               es, for ſundry reaſons, as he thought it moſt 
                  •
               xpedient for his glorie and our ſaluation. 
                  •
               ut there is none of them all who either

gaine ſayeth or condemneth the others▪ meikilles ſtoppeth them to ſay or write any thing that they haue in charge to declare and publish to the world▪ here tourne you to what ſyde ye will either Luther shal be a falſe prophete or Caluin an Apoſtate, &amp; his vocation null and yours alſo.
            12. I mak no doubt but ye will reither forſak Luther, howbeit firſt, then Caluin your laſt patron. I may obiect here to you the honourable titels (quo iure non diſp
                     •
                  to) that Caluin gifeth to Luther as to a true ſeruant of God, and not as to a falſe prophete, which were ſufficient to cloſe your mouthes if they could be cloſed. But I will paſſe this as if it were not, and ſpeak of Caluin and you, becauſe ye may ſay that Caluin him ſelf was ſent extraordinariely to performe that excellent worke, in vaine and falſely attempted by Luther, I will well by ſuppoſition, prouiding that ye reformed brethren will ſtand there to, and ſuffer me to examine the matter a litill: for we shall ſee, if ye can fight better vnder this new captaine. Caluin or any oth
                  •
               r ye will, was ſent (I ſuppoſe this now, in caſe ye will not ſtand by Luther &amp; tak your ordinarie calling of him) extraordinariely by God him ſelf to teach the veritie, and miniſtrate the ſacraments according

to the reformation 
                  •
               e was to make: if he did not his duetie in this moſt excellent and neceſſarie charge, ye should eſteeme him▪ as he is, a falſe prophete, who being commanded by God and aſſiſted by the holie Spirite (for ſure I am in your opinion he lacketh not that ioyned to his charge) yet wold not declare the veritie truely &amp; plainely without admixting ſome lyes of his owne by the deuils ſuggeſtion, where by the world migh
                  •
                be of new poyſoned with falſe doctrine vnder colour of Goddes ſoueraigne name. If this be true he merites more thē to be ſlaine 
                  3. book the kinges cap. 13.
               in the way by a Lyon for trāſgreſſing of the lords command, not in ſimple eating and drinking, being forbidden to eat or drink, as did the ancient prophete, but for teaching of falſe doctrine far by his cōmiſſion, which was to shew the veritie. If he did his duetie 
                  •
               n all thinges, where from cometh it, that 
                  •
               undry of your brethren in France &amp; other 
                  •
               laces, yea your excellent Apoſtle-Verelian 
                  •
               reat Pontif of Geneua M. Theodore Beze 
                  •
               is owen good diſciple, diſſentes from him 
                  •
                many heads, and as I think, ye alſo diſa
               
                  •
               ow him not in few pointes. Certainely I 
                  •
               aue not to this day found one who appro
               
                  •
               eth him in all thinges. For when any of 
                  •
               ours ar vrged with Caluins authoritie, y
                  •
               
               
anſwere that ye acknowledge not Caluin, but ſo farre as he agreeth with the ſcriptures, where ye find that he agreeth with the ſcriptures, ye will receaue him: what leſſe can ye gif to Plato, Ariſtotle, Cicero and Seneca, or any other profane writter? will ye reiect them although ye find them agree with the word of God? I think not. Truely Caluin is meikill obliged to you, if ye graūt him that, which ye can not refuſe to an ould wyf. Is this the reuerence ye beare to him for his extraordinarie calling? ar thes the thankes ye gif him for the vocation and pow
                  •
               r that ye haue receaued of him? shall not the ſpirite that ſpak in him haue more credit, then any of you? was he ſent with that condition that he should haue no credit, till ye found in the bible that it was true he ſayed. Truely if I be not far deceaued, it wil be very eaſie to mak you beleeue any thing ye pleaſe and otherwiſe impoſſible, if the iudgement be re
                  •
               erred to you poore Caluin (ſo far as I vnderſtand by your anſwers) receaued not the ſpirite in the beſt ſort. He receaued onely the ſpirite to tell you many thinges in forme of propoſition to your holie aſſemblies, and ye receaued of diſcretion and wiſdome, to iudge what was good an
                  •
                what was ill. ye haue gotten a more mighti
                  •
               
               
inſpiration then your chief prophet
                  •
               . I am glade for your cauſe. we can not faille to go well hauing gottin you for ſupreme iudge to trie all thinges, but, as I think, euery one in Semp
                     ••
                   diſcente
                     •
                   &amp; nunquam ad ſciē
                  tiam veritatis perueniente
                     •
                   
                  2. ad Timoth. 
                     •
                  . 7.
               his owin parish; for euer the further we go frome vnitie, the nomber is the greater, and Papes ar multiplied in your perſones. I loue your wittes to follow Ceſar, reither firſt in a village, then ſecond in Rome, yet good ſires, ſeing ye ar ſett vpon that high throne lyk to as many Salomons, that euery one of you &amp; iuris nodos &amp; legum aenigmata ſoluit, be not offended, if I ask ſome thinges at you, ſeing there reſted me yet ſome litill doubtes▪ I ask whe
                  •
               her Caluin was ſent extraordinariely to teach you the veritie, or be to teached &amp; examined by you? If he was ſent to teach you, ye should admitt him without any further triall &amp; tak the conference with the ſcriptures to confirme and ſtrengthen his ſayinges, &amp; not to confute thē: for ſo did the firſt Chriſtiās read the places of the prophetes cited by the Apoſtles. If he was ſent to be teached &amp; examined by you, why came he extraordinariely? to what purpos was ſo great honour, &amp; afterward to be ſubiect to you? But this for an other tyme; lat vs cōſider once againe the firſt. If Caluin was ſent extraordinariely vz. to teach you, he may ſay with

Sainct Paul: Ego enim accepi à Domino, quod &amp; tradidi vobis: there is no other witnes here but God and he. If ye of your reformed modeſtie will giue them bothe, or any one of them the lie, I can not mend it, ſeing, it is ye, who hath gotten the charge to reforme the world, and ſo this may be accompted as a reformed lie, with the which no man should be formalized: yet with licence I may vrge Caluins pretended right. If he ſpak &amp; writte according to the direction that he receaued of God how ſo euer thes thinges ſeemes ſtrange to you, yet should ye admitte them &amp; think, that they ar according to the ſcriptures: becauſe God is never contrarie to him ſelf, he being but one in diuerſe mouthes, &amp; not diuerſe in one mouth. how can it be poſſible that ye can better know, what charge Caluin receaued of God, then he him ſelf, who was (as he and ye pretend) employed? We receaue without any contradiction or gaineſaying the writtes of the Prophetes and Euangeliſts with all the reſt of the holie bible, becauſe thes writters were ſent &amp; aſſiſted by God. If there ſeemeth any diuerſitie, we accuſe our weacknes, &amp; not the ſcriptures of contradiction or falshood: for no ſic thing can be in Goddes work. So if Caluin, or any other, was ſent immediatly by God,

ye muſt receaue all his doctrine, except ye shew either that he hath beene ill inſtructed &amp; that it was Spiritus mendax in ore eius: or that he hath dōne beſides his cōmiſſion, of which neither can be true if God was the authour. It will ſerue you for nothing to ſay, that he was but a man &amp; might erre. Becauſe all the prophetes and Apoſtles were but men and might erre. yet the aſſiſtance of the holie Spirite ſuffered them not to erre in there commiſſion, &amp; therefor we receaue their ſayinge
                  •
                as Goddes owen fayinges, becauſe he was the 
                  •
               uthour, &amp; they onely the inſtrument. Why receaue ye not Caluin in this maner? or ſhew vs that God hade ſent any man to deceaue vs falſis vera im
                     •
                  iſce
                     •
                  s. I think ye will find no ſic Sinōs ſent extraordinariely by God, or if there be any, lett vs heare their names. If Caluin was ſent, as ye pretēd, ye should thinke that God hath inſtructed him well, &amp; hath giuen him good and ſufficient directions (for elſe the fault shal be Goddes &amp; not his) and ſuffered him not to go therefro: otherwiſe it hath beene a great vanitie to haue ſent him. Ye will perhapes replie that God in all ages had raiſed vp Godly fathers &amp; learned men to oppoſe them ſolues to errours and abuſes beginning to enter in the kirk, as S. Athanaſe, S. Baſile, S. Auguſtin, S. B
                  •
               rnard &amp; othe
                  •
               s

in great nomber, whoſe writinges notwithſtāding ar not altogether ſo cleene but ſomething may be tried &amp; corrected. I anſwere there be great differēce betwixt them &amp; Caluin or any other to whome the reformation 
                  •
               ath beene extraordinariely committed. For although theſe Godly and learned fathers were ſent by God, yet were they not ſent extraordinariely▪ but by the ordinarie way: for they receaued their vocation and power of the Catholik kirk in whoſe boſome they were brought vp and 
                  •
               eached: The doctrine which they had receaued of the kirk, they deliuered to the members of the kirk, where in they remained ſtill as obedient children, ſubmitting all their works and writtinges to hir iudgement, condemning as ſchiſmatiks or heretiks, all thoſe who left hir, employing their wholl trauell and writtinges to defend and mainteine hir againſt all Satans inſultes, never making any ſect a part, never alledging any particuler commiſſion to reforme others, nor yet to bring any new thing. Caluin to the contraire left the kirk where he was conceaued and teached an other doctrine, then he hath learned of his mother Chriſts ſpouſe, whome he shamefully foreſook, refuſing in any wiſe to acknowledge hir or hir iudgement▪
               
               
                  〈◊〉
                him ſelf to them, whome he condem
                  ••
               th in mynd and writting, oppugning and 
                  •
               u
                  •
               ſpryſing hir, who concea
                  •
               ed him, making a band a part, becauſe of the pretended commiſſion he had receaued to reforme all theſe thinges merited a good warrand to be beleeued, ſeing they conteine ſo many ſtrange maximes aboue or contrarie to all good reaſon, which can not be found in the foreſade godly and learned fathers who were ſent before. And therefore their example maketh nothing for Caluin and his doinges or errours. Ye will ſay for your and his defence, that they at but litle thinges where in ye diſſent frome him. I know that neither he, nor ye can do a great fault, ye ar all Goddes owen mignons▪ how ſoone that the lord heareth, tha
                  •
                it is y
                  •
               e, who hath committed any thing, it is incontinent excuſed, becauſe of your ſtrōge faith, which changes 
                  •
               nauery in good ſeruice. But I pray you how shall I know, if his faultes be great or ſmall▪ ſeing that ye will receaue no thing at all of his doctrine, till ye haue had it vpon th
                  •
                touchſtone of your iudgement? and ſo for their litill thinges, as ye call them, ye call all in doubt, at leſt with other men▪ who perchance may think meikill, that ye think litill. And here vpon (good ſires pardon me, if I be ſo

bold) I gi
                  •
                you no more credit then ye gif Caluin? for by your owen rule, I muſt 
                  •
               rye bothe his ſaying and your iudgement, before that I receaue any thing, yea I will re
                  ••
               aue, nether becauſe he ſayeth it, nor becauſe ye approue it (for that were to do w
                  •
               ong to the ſpirite and Chriſtian libertie) but 
                  ••
               ca
                  •
               
               ſe I think that I haue 
                  •
               ound it ſo in 
                  •
               h
                  •
                
               
                  •
               ible. For if I find it not there I will condemne and deteſt it as a plaine hereſie, 
                  〈◊〉
                that where i
                  •
                ye agree no
                  •
                with Caluin, but all the reſt, and this (as I haue ſaid) according to your owen rule and pretended C
                  ••
               iſtian libertie, where by 
                  •
               uery man is i
                  ••
               g
                  •
                in all thinges within the reformed kirk. Further it may ſeeme by the forſaid anſwer that ye think a man can not receaue a de
                  •
               dly wound; except he be (as they ſay) 
                  〈◊〉
                to the teeth. Certainely the largeneſſe of the wound oft
                  •
               ntymes m
                  •
               keth no
                  •
                the danger, but the place and part that is wounded. A man may be ſtrooken through the body, and y
                  •
               t liue; a pri
                  •
               k with a pi
                  •
               n
                  •
                in the hea
                  •
               t or harnes myght bring certain
                  •
                death, which should not be meſured by the greatnes of the wound, but by the lo
                  ••
               e of the man: ye ar not ignorant how litill difference was betwix the Cat
                  ••
               ol
                  •
               kes and the A
                  •
               
               rians if we will look to the lett
                  •
               rs. But to

reto
                  ••
               ne to your Apoſtle he was ſent to shew vs the true way, yet hath he ledde vs by the way and deceaued vs▪ how litill as euer the mater be▪ his part is not good▪ Certainely I can not eſteeme your Patriarche (be it Luther, Caluin, Z
                  •
               ingli
                  •
               s▪ Knoxe, Willox, Me
                  ••
               en, He
                  •
               io
                  •
               e, Craig or what ſo euer other ye will for all is one in thes mater) a true prophete, ſeing ye your ſelfes eſteeme him a liar. For a litill leaſing▪ principallie in matters of religion, maketh no leſſe a lier then a great leaſing, onely the greater it be, he is the mo
                  •
               e deteſtable who maketh it▪ Ye will perchance here reply to me▪ and ſay that God ſuffered him to fall in ſome thing 
                  ••
                where by bothe he and we might knew that he was but a man. I anſwer firſt that it was not 
                  •
               eed
                  •
               u
                  •
               l becauſe no 
                  〈◊〉
                could haue taken him for a God, although he 
                  •
               ade ſaid all true▪ for we beleeue not that the Apoſtles &amp; Prophetes ar Gods▪ albeit we be ſurely perſuaded that all is true that they haue ſaid, 
                  〈◊〉
                leſt that they haue left vs by writt. Next there was no ſic ſuperna
               
                  •
               urall thing in him as might bring 
                  •
               s in that errour, laſt of all it hath beene more prope
                  •
                
               
                  •
               or vs that he had ſaid althinges 
                  〈◊〉
                wit
                  ••••
                any ſuſpicion of falshood▪ where by we might aſſuredly haue knowen that God

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
had ſent him and ſpoken in him: and that for his cauſe, who ſent him, we should receaue him as an extraor
                  •
               inarie paſtour come to reforme the world. It was not needfull to hazard our ſaluatiō to proue him a man, but we needed many good arguments to proue, that God had ſent him, and principallie an argument taken frome the veritie▪ As to him ſelf I find him extreme proude in all his writtinges, yet think I no
                  •
                that he eſteemed him ſelfe a God, and ſure I am he died not with that opinion, I ſay no further. Ye will perchance aske of me here, if I wold conclude that ye ar alſo falſe prophetes and liers, if ye teach any falſe doctrine, as doubtles ye do? No truely, although in ſome ſenſe, I might moſt iuſtly ſo conclude: for 
                  •
               here is great difference now betwix you, as ye profeſſe your ſelues to be but ordinatie paſtours (if perchance ye content your ſelfes with ſo humble and ſimple a ſtile) and Caluin o
                  •
                any other, whome ye acknowledge to b
                  •
                ſent ext
                  ••
               ordinariely by God him ſelf: fo
                  •
                howbeit your power (if ye haue any▪ I vnderſtand) be diuine, as comming of God, ye
                  •
                your iudgement is but humaine▪ ſo that it i
                  •
                no meruaill if ye go ſometymes wronge i
                  •
                high maters which should be called re
                  •
               he an e
                  ••
               ou
                  •
               , then a lie, becauſe ye w
                  •
               r
                  •
                dec
                  ••
               
               ue
                  •
               
               
in your opinion as men. For this cauſe the ordinarie Paſtour is obliged▪ to follow the footſtopes of his forfathers▪ &amp; make no new way to him ſelf, nor any thing that ſeemed to incline to noueltie: becauſe humano iudgement should not be bold in diuine matters: for i
                  •
                ye open the doore that euery man may iudge as he liſt, there can be no aſſurance in religion, but dayly change, as ſpirites of men be diuerſe bothe frome them ſelf
                  •
               s and others. But Caluin (or any other ye will) being ſent by God him ſelf, came not here to tell vs his opinion as a man, 
                  •
               ut to declare Gods mynd and will as an inſtrument choſen extraordina
                  •
               iely for that effect. So that if he haue failled, it can not b
                  •
                called human a mentis error, but a per
                  •
               iciouſe lie againſt the holie ſpirite, who hathe geuen him expreſſe charge to ſpeak otherwiſe then he ſpak. For he lieth, who in his maiſters name ſayeth thinges which his maiſter never had ſaid; Omnis enim debet ſine 
                     •
                  a
                     •
                  o nucius 
                     •
                  ſſe. The Poetes haue fained the meſſengers of their fabulous Goddes, more diſcreit, then ye acknowledge the meſſengers of th
                  •
                true God; for ye shall not lightly find any one worde changed in M
                     •
                  rcuri
                     •
                  s Commiſsions, he is ſo religious in doing his charge. The ſame may be ſaid of Princes Embaſſadors in

theis dayes. I think it should meikill leſſe be permitred to any man to goe from the commiſſion gifin to him by God, either in eiking or pairing, what shall I ſay to ſpeek to contrarie? Now nothwithſtanding all this ſeing ye find errours in your Apoſtle, where by ye think not your ſelfes obliged to follow him, but with this caueat, if he agree with the written worde, ye gif the world
                  •
                plainely to vnderſtand that ye approue not his extraordinarie vocation▪ but receaues him as another man of the common ſo
                  •
               t, who may 
                  •
               eceaue many good and true inſtructions of your ſpit
                  •
               te▪ which is the true ſquare and rule of all other ſpirites, where vpon 
                  •
                conclude that ye haue no calling of his lying ſpir
                  •
               te (pardon me if I ſay ſo ſeing I ſay it after you) who could haue no ſi
                  •
                power▪ and for that ſame reaſon your vocation is fallen in non entery, becauſe ye haue bene ſo many yeares in violent poſſeſſion, and can not as yet shew either yours or any of your forefathers re
                  •
               oures: vpon theis 
                  •
               ands ye haue builded your houſe, yea erected your Kingdome of confuſi on, and eſtablished your lawes of pa
                  •
               rtie to haue all men ſubiect to your miniſteriall imaginations tending to the ruine of all ſuperior powers. The more high your interpri
                  •
               es b
                  •
               , th
                  •
                
               
                  〈◊◊〉
                you
                  •
               
               
tre
                  •
               ſon, the 
                  •
               uſt cauſe men 
                  •
               at
                  •
               
               ▪ not onely to diſobey you▪ but meikill more to gaineſtand you as 
                  •
               ſur
                  •
               ers of Chriſts Ieſus charge and office wit
                  •
               out his commiſſion or command, and troublers of the common wealth and ſeditiouſe ſubiects, qui eſt is nat
                     •
                   in pernicie
                     •
                   Principum 
                     〈◊〉
                   bonorum omnium▪
                Bragge of your excōmunication as ye pleaſe it is but an vaine imagination, a bugle to fra
                  •
                babes▪ or a ſcare crow▪ 
               
                  •
                found and a shew▪ without 
                  •
               ither danger or profite, and in a word i
                  •
                is but a falſe 
                  •
               honder where by no man can be made 
                  
                     •
                  elp
                     •
                  lo nigrio
                     •
                   
                  
                     ••
                  o.
            
            13. I look here for your laſt refuge ye will pay 
                  〈◊〉
                with your ordinarie fashion of ſcoffing▪ for ſome of you being asked where ye found the ki
                  •
               k do
                  •
                anſwer, in the 
                  〈◊〉
                midding of Papiſ
                  •
               rie▪ Truely a moſt meete and proper natiue ſo
                  •
               le for ſo wor
                  ••
               ie and noble a Lady as your ki
                  •
               k is▪ I geſſe your vocation was 
                  •
               ound in the ſame royall palace. This an
                  •
               wer as it is more neer to the purpos, ſo it contented 
                  〈◊〉
                meikill better▪ for the Apoſt
                  •••
                prieſts▪ monkes▪ and friers with other diſſol
                  •
               te 
                  •••
               d debouched men of our ki
                  •
               k were the firſt groundſton
                  ••
                of your re
               
                  •
               ormed f
                  ••
               ie congregation: ſo if we hade neuer had apoſta
                  •••
               , ye should neuer haue 
                  •
               ad Apoſtles▪ Luth
                  •
               r was 
                  •
                mo
                  •
               k, C
                  •
               l
                  •
               i
                  •
                a 
                  〈◊〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
none, Beza a Priour, Knoxe a Prieſt. If ye deſyre to be any further informed of this matter, our country may furnish you many true hiſtories of the great and charitable pietie of your primitiue kirk whē it begane 40. yeares ſince.
            14. Now to the laſt head of our diſpute, where as the matter is more cleare ſo shall we be more shorte. Giſing and not granting that ye hade good Calling and were lawfull true Paſtours hauing power to bind and looſe. I ask what iuriſdiction ye can haue vpon them, who neuer were ſubiect to you; neuer acknowledged nor could acknowledge you for lawfull paſtours hauing at altymes made profeſſion of the Catholik religion which is ſo far different, yea contrarie to that which ye profeſſe, and deſyres them to embrace, how can ye vrge theis men to acknowledge you, or how can ye excommunicat and ſeparate them frome you as rotten and ſpilt members frome the reſt of your reformed body, they neuer being of your body. Feare ye not that men laught at you and your folie, to diſpoſe ſo rashely vpon thinges neuer yours except perchance by a reformed imagination, or dreame? Kinges and Princes vſes not to banish out of their dominions other princes ſubiects who neuer

were within their boundes. True it is, that they may forbid any ſtranger to enter within their empires, and that for good and iuſt reaſons, yea for their only pleaſure if they will ſo, becauſe the lands ar theirs, and ſo may receaue, or hold out any man as they liſt, or punish ſic as wold without their licence enter there in. But to banish men that never were within their realmes, were a thing very ridiculouſe, that I ſay not, fooliſh. And to conſtraine free men, or other Princes ſubiects to gif them the othe of fidelitie and du
                  •
                ſeruice were altogether againſt reaſon, principally neuer being with in their iuriſdiction. Lykwiſe I ſay to you, that ye can not iuſtly force thes men now to acknowledge you who neuer were yours; ye may in deed forbid them to enter in to your kirk, or to aſſiſ
                  •
                to your ſeruice, if ye haue any, or to your prayers, or to take any charge amongſt you, ſeing that they 
                  •
               r not of you
                  •
                ſto
                  ••
               : but how ye can paſſe any further againſt them truely I ſee not, except ye wold ſay, that your power hath no other marches, then your will and fantaſie. An ample empyre truely if it be ſo. Ye will haue the ex
               
                  •
               reſſe word of God for all thing
                  •
               s that other 
                  •
               en ſay. I pray you bring vs here ſome good 
                  •
               nd euid
                  •
               n
                  ••
               e
                  ••
                of the ſcripture which may

ſerue you for bound &amp; charter of your bordors
                  •
                cite vs ſome ſure place, by whoſe authoritie ye may proue that it is lawfull to banish men out of your kirk, who neuer were in it. Think ye not but this meriteth two or three paſſages of the holie writt, befor ye paſſe to the execution there of. The Iew
                  •
               s did eſteeme the Gētils in rank of excommunicated men; bnt neuer did excommunicat them: that is did hold them as profane men deſtitute of the grace and aſſiſtance of God, and out of his kirk ſeing that they profeſſed not that ſame religion, which onely at that t
                  •
               me was the true religion. But neuer did they curt them of their body as rotten members thereof, becauſe they were not of their body, but reither a body a part diſtinguiſhed frome them bothe in religio
                  •
                and ceremonies, which onely the I
                  •
               wes did declare, and could do no further, C
                  •
               ptaines vſes not, to diſcharge or b
                  •
               ack out of their 
                  •
               ands, ſouldiours who neuer were vnder their banners. Chriſt Ieſus neuer gaue 
                  •
               o any ſic exē
               ple or command nor yet, the Apoſtles, y
                  ••
                none of their ſucceſſours after them▪ Where
                  •
                find ye the Iewe
                  •
                or gentils excommunicated by the Apoſtles or primi
                  •
               iue 
                  •
               irk? I find 
                  •
               ruell porſ
                  ••
               utiōs exerciſed ag
                  ••
               nſt the Chriſtians and their great patience with 
                  〈◊〉
               
               
and 
                  •
               eruent prayer made for their perſecutors, I find not their execrations and curſe
                  •
                againſt them. 
                  •
               e ſ
                  •
               e the Iewes yet among
                  •
                the Chriſtians and vnconſtrained to embrace the veritie▪ o
                  •
                ye
                  •
                excommunicated, except by that generall excōmunication where by they ar all declared ſtrangers in Goddes houſe and profane perſonnes▪ with whome notwithſtanding we may h
                  ••
                n
                  •
                
               
                  •
               peek; trafik, and communicat 
                  •
               iuille although that our kirk doores and prayer places be cloſed vp to them. They may haue action in law againſt any man who hath either offended them, or is owing them any thing▪ Iuſtice is not refuſed to them, becauſe they, ar me
                  •
                remaining with in the ſame commō wealth. Now ſeing the
                  •
               s branches were neuer your
                  •
                How can ye 
                  〈◊〉
                them of your tree. K
                     •
                  mi ſu
                     •
                   alteri
                     ••
                   arbor
                     •
                  s. If ye could do that, ye might hardely va
                  ••
               t your ſelues to haue donne a miracle, which hath beene ſo often craued at your hands for your extraordinaire vocation.
            15. But ye will ſay tha
                  •
                they ar in your Pari
                  •
               hes▪ and therefore ye haue power vpon them as vpon the reſt who ar within the ſame iuriſdiction.  I vnderſtand  well▪ ye ar 
                  •
               ands lo
                  •
               de
                  •
               , all is yours that g
                  •
               owe
                  •
                vpon 
                  •
               he gro
                  ••
               d. But good 
                  •••
               es▪ ye should firſt

shew that the ground is yours, and then diſpoſe there vpon at your pleaſour▪ we shall neuer op
                  •
               n our mouthes to gaineſay you. The iuriſdiction that ye pretend is ſpirituall, hitherto they haue neuer entred wi
                  •
               h in your dominious▪ Why will ye now force them to land, becauſe they ar driuen by ſtorme of wind vpon your coſtes? They ar 
                  •
               orie that your limites ar ſo neer to them. The onely ſight of your realme hath diſguſted them exceedingly: ſuffer them to ſtay where they ar and they will enter no further. They content them with your good will. The Turkes conſtraine no man to embrace their opinion, except he enter with in their temple: any man may be within the countrey without any compulſion. ye require more then the moſt cruell tyrannes▪ If ye will credit them it shall not be needfull to banish them out of your territorie. They deſyre not to enter. They haue choſen another free citie, where they like better to be burgeſſis, which they will loſe, if they enter with you. Vlyſſes was neuer more deſyrous to be deliuered out of Polyphemu
                  •
                cauerne, or danger of Si
                  •
               enes, or Charibdis then they to be exempt of your communion. It is but in vaine ye excommunicat them who neuer haue, nor yet deſyre to

communicat with you. Ye do as they tell the 
                  •
               able of the foxe and plummes, which he could not come by, nigra ſun
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  olo they ar black (ſayeth he) I will haue none of them. ye ar very liberall, ye gif to others, which neither is yours nor can ye haue▪ what extraordinarie reformed charitie is this in you to deliuer ouer to Satan Goddes creatures not being in your charge nor keeping, meikill leſſe at your gift? But good ſires why ta
                  •
                ye not the paines to shew that ye haue the true kirk, out of which there is no ſalu
                  •
               
               tion; and that ye ar lawfull paſtours, to whome all true Chriſtiās ar obliged to obey as to Chriſts vic
                  •
               i
                  •
               es and lieutenants▪ This were the ordinarie and eaſie way, if ye wold follow it; for this being once ſufficiently 
                  •
               hewen; I doubt not but they wold shew them ſelues very docil and very eaſie to receaue all your inſtructions, becauſe of your vndoubted authoritie and charge. Ye might then very well exhorte them to enter witbin your ſpirituall iuriſdiction, ſeing ye hade the lawfull power to receaue them, and to enroll them among the Children of God, and heauenly citizens. If they wold not yet heare you, ye might according to Chriſts command, shake the duſt of your feete▪ and leaue their blood vpō their owen heades except

perchance ye wold patiently abyde their conuerſion to God, ſeing that ſome ar called and do 
                  〈◊〉
                in the 
                  •
               ords vinia
                  •
               d▪ in the morning, ſome at midday, ſome in the 
                  •
               uening, and at laſt all ar new 
                  •
               tded for their l
                  •
               
               bours, 
                  •
               o the which none ar conſtrained▪ Ye know that faith is a gift of God, it c
                  •
               n not be found e
                  ••
               ry where. Spiritu
                     •
                   vb
                     •
                   vul
                     •
                   ſpir
                     •
                  t it de pended 
                  〈◊〉
                vpon our will, nor 
                  •
               eurs to make men bel
                  ••
               ue the veri
                  •
               ie▪ that appe
                  ••
               in
                  •
               d to God onely. vol
                     •
                  ntas 
                     •
                  ogino
                     •
                   p
                     ••
                  est
                     ••
                  
                
               
                  〈◊〉
                is God onely▪ who may change the hardnes of mens hea
                  ••
               es. Why will ye force men, ſeing we deny free will: If ye ſay as ye think why v
                  •
               ge ye men as if they had it▪ excuſe me, if I propoſe ſic thinges, ſeing I do it following your h
                  •
               mour and ſtrange opinions. I 
                  〈◊〉
                ſome exemple either of▪ ou
                  •
                maiſter 
                  •
               eſus Chriſt o
                  •
                of his Apoſ
                  •
               los▪ where either 
                  〈◊〉
                or Gentill euer was conſtrained to acknowledge the goſpell, o
                  •
                excommunicated 
                  •
               f 
                  •
               he wold non I will graunt to 
                  〈◊〉
                very freely▪ that all men who will not acknowledge the true kirk
                  •
                and lawfull paſtour
                  •
                a
                  •
                with out the communion and pa
                  •
               k
                  •
                of Ieſu
                  •
                Chriſt▪ but not 
                  •
               u
                  •
                out of th
                  •
                communion of 
                  〈◊〉
                park of Ieſus Chriſt: becauſe as I haue ſaid now often, they were ne
                  •
               er within i
                  •
               
               ▪ And therefore the Apoſtles and 
                  •
               h
                  •
               ir 
                  〈◊〉
               
               
did euer ciuilie cōuerſe with the 
                  •
               othe preaching and teaching the ve
                  •
               iti
                  •
                (where by our for fathers were con
                  •
               erted to God) but neuer admitted them to be preſent at Goddes ſ
                  •
               r
                  •
               ice till they hade left their errour &amp; were inſtr
                  •
               cted in the trueth, and ſo rece
                  •
               
               ned in the boſome of the kirk a
                  •
                true Chriſtians should be. If the Apoſtles had de
                  •
               a
                  •
               
               red from
                  •
                their companie all men, who wo
                  •
               d not incontinent embrace their doct
                  •
               ine, I think they 
                  •
               hold not haue 
                  〈◊〉
                ſo m
                  •
               
               ny as they haue donne. In their pa
                  •
               ien
                  •
               e they ouercame the world, wonn
                  •
                the fa
                  •
               ou
                  •
                of their enemies, aſſured the faithfull, b
                  •
               a
                  ••
               
               gled the infidel
                  •
               es ſeeing them die ſo co
                  ••
               dgeouſly for the ve
                  •
               i
                  •
               ie that they preached, &amp; at laſt left ou
                  •
                for fathers peaceable in the kirk of God? which certainely was a heauenly work donne by naturall inſt
                  •
               un
                  •
               en
                  •
               es indued with ſupernaturall graces and vertues, infuſed by the holie Spirite in the hear
                  ••
               s of 
                  ••
               ue and law
                  •
               ull paſto
                  ••
               s to confound all worldly wi
                  •
               dome and bring vs wi
                  •
               h ſimplicitie and obedience to eternall bliſſe . In pl
                  •
               
               ce of which godly modeſtie and meeknes ye employ your reformed force and violence shewing that ye had 
                  •
               e
                  ••
               her make, them 
                  •
               e made martyres, where in by many degrees ye ſ
                  ••
               paſſ
                  •
                the cruell barb
                  ••••
                of the Turkes,

impati
                  •
               t au
                  •
                importune in all your actiōs, yet according to your diſcipline (which is againſt all good diſcipline) impellens quidquid ſibi ſumma petenti obſis
                     •
                  it, g
                     •
                  udenſque v
                     •
                  am 
                     •
                  eciſſe ruina.—Magnámque cade
                     ••
                   magnámque reuertens dat
                     •
                  stragem latè, ſparſoſque recoll
                     •
                  gi
                     •
                   ignes.
            
            16. Thus faire for them who all wai
                  •
               e haue remamed Catholikes, as to others who haue at any tyme yeelded to you being 
                  •
               ither forced or deceiued by you, good reaſon requireth that they be ſett at libertie as before. Doubtles the law will declare all ſic men as free frome all obligation to you, as they who neuer were yours, becauſe of the violence and deceit ye haue vſed, principallie ſeing it is ſo fa
                  •
               re againſt the honour of God, the Kinges Maieſties ſervi
                  •
               e, and publik honeſtie, and yoú to be punished as publik tranſgreſſours of diuine and humaine lawes. If ye will haue men obliged to your doctrine and diſcipline, ſett vp new play, procee
                  •
                with honeſt lawfull and godly meanes without bothe fraud &amp; force errour or treaſon take an ordinarie ſure calling or proue wel your extraordinarie, and then, who hat
                  •
                once acknowledged you, punish him 
                  •
                your diſcretion and according to your lawes, if he reuolt frome you, But now as maters goeth, although I were a zealous brother

yet as faithfull Chriſtian and true ſubiect, I wold be gladd to be excommunicated out of your companie, where treaſon and hereſies ar confirmed with ſubſcriptiōs and ſolemne oathes.
            18. Now to end with you, I will yet make you an offer, as I think very reaſonable, which is this. Seing ye wil haue no thing that cometh of the Catholik Apoſtolik and Romaine Kirk, as being infected with ſuperſtition and Idolatrie▪ nor acknowledge the Pape, becauſe ye eſteeme him the Antichriſt, and therefor will haue no counceill gathered by him: do like good &amp; vigilant paſtours, aſſemble your ſelues by whoſe authoritie ye pleaſe, hold an vniuerſall ſynode among your reformed brethren of all ſortes through out the whole reformed world, without beginning and ending, that there appeere no ſuperiorite▪ make a round table, ſpeek al at once; diſpute vpon the controuerted heads: agree among your ſelues and we shall agree with you. what can ye ask more of vs? if no accorde can be hade among you, how can we agree with you? Conſenting with any one companie, we shall haue all the reſt for enemies, and shall not be aſſured if the partie, that we haue followed, will ſtand long at his

owen opinion. Or if ye think this offer of greater expenſes then eſperance, we will make you another, to agree with you &amp; ſubſcribe your con
                  •
               eſſion of faith, if ye can shew that euer there was any empire, Kingdome, canton, citie, toune, village or cothouſe, yea any ſingle man Catholik or heretik, young or old, lerned or ignorant, profeſſing your doctrine and gouuerned by your diſcipline before this laſt hondred yeares. If ye refuſe this offers, iudge your ſelues, what the reformed flock may think of you. Abyding your anſwere I will mak here an end and pray God to gif vs his eternall bleſſe, and to you (where by ye may atteine to the ſame) a faith that may ſtand with your duetie to God and Prince, and with Chriſtian charitie.
            Fare well.
            
         
      
   

