
   
      
         
            Ezras pulpit. Or, A sermon lately preached in Southwarke, before a worshipfull assembly Very necessary for these times. By William Freake, minister.
            Freake, William.
         
         
            
               1639
            
         
         Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01234
            STC 11346.7
            ESTC S120858
            99856051
            99856051
            21567
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01234)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21567)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 644:09)
         
         
            
               
                  Ezras pulpit. Or, A sermon lately preached in Southwarke, before a worshipfull assembly Very necessary for these times. By William Freake, minister.
                  Freake, William.
               
               [4], 22, [6] p.   
               
                  Printed by Tho. Harper for Richard Harper, and are to be sold at his shop at the Bible and Harp in Smithfield,
                  London :
                  1639.
               
               
                  The last two leaves are blank.
                  Identified as STC 11346a on UMI microfilm reel 644.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-01
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-06
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-06
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            Ezras Pulpit.
OR, A Sermon lately Preached in Southwarke, before a Worſhipfull Aſſembly.
Very neceſſary for theſe times.
            BY WILLIAM FREAKE, Miniſter.
            
               Luke 7. 4, 5. verſes.
               And when they came to Ieſus, they beſought him inſtantly, ſaying, that he was worthy for whom he ſhould doe this:
               For, he loveth our nation, and hath built us a Synagogue.
            
            LONDON, Printed by Tho. Harper for Richard Harper, and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the Bible and Harp in Smithfield, 1639.
         
         
            
            
               
To the right Worſhipfull, Sir Nicholas Rainton, Knight, Preſident, the Worſhipfull Martin Bond, Eſquire, Treaſurer, with the Governours of the Hoſpitall of little S Bartholomewes, W. F. wiſheth that Grace and Peace may be multiplied.
            
               WHat I ſtudied for your private Chappell, and there delivered before ſome of you, on Tueſday the 19. of Iune, laſt paſt, I have been importuned to make publick, as for a common good. If it be good, then quò communius, eò melius, the more publicke it becommeth, the more good it may doe. I wiſht well in the ſtudy and delivery of it to as many as deſire the proſperity of our royall foundation. In the publiſhing of it, I would gladly have it conceived that my zeale is the ſame for the publicke welfare▪ If that memorable act of your piety▪
               
which occaſioned this Sermon, ſhall provoke ſome well minded ones to imitate your example elſewhere, or incite the able handed to promote ſuch charitable undertakings for the comfort of ſo many ſick and diſtreſſed ſoules daily by your care refreſhed: it may redound much to Gods glory, your owne comforts, and the happineſſe of thoſe whom God ſhall move hereby to tread in your ſteps. If no ſuch thing ſucceed, yet it ſhall be your honour to have lighted up the candle of ſo good an example for the times to come: as it is, and ſhall be, for you all, that God may long continue to our Hoſpitall, your pious care for the happy and orderly government thereof, the daily prayer of
            
               Your Hoſpitaler, William Freake.
               From my Study in your Hoſpitall the 12 day of Feb. 1639.
                  
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            Ezras Pulpit.
            
               Neh. 8. 4, 5, 6, 7, 8. verſes.
               
                  And Ezra the Scribe ſtood upon a Pulpit of wood, which they had made for the purpoſe, &amp;c. to the end of the 8. verſe.
               
            
            
               BEloved: I finde it to be the obſervation of a Father, that the two Cherubins, which by Gods appointment were to be placed at the two ends of the Mercy-ſeat, Exod. 25. 18. as they ſhould be of beaten gold, ſo they ſhould bee ſo placed, that they might face each other: as an inſtruction for all Miniſters and Preachers of the Word and Goſpell, ſaith the learned Zanche, to take this care and courſe, that as their Doctrine ſhould be purely the word of God, and not their owne, ſo they ſhould be ever ſtudious to make their Texts to ſuit with the occaſions of their Sermons,

facing each other, as the Cherubins over the Mercy-ſeat, that ſo being a word in due ſeaſon, they may be like Apples of gold in pictures of ſilver, Proverbs 25. 11. And this I confeſſe▪ as it is my duty, ſo it hath beene my ſtudy in the preparation of my meditations for this place and occaſion, to reconcile the text of Scripture, which (by Gods bleſſing) I have made choice of, to the occaſion of this day and our preſent meeting. A worke, which if you pleaſe to vouchſafe your favourable attention, will aske us no great labour.
            1 Becauſe here is Ezra the Scribe, requeſted and appointed to bring forth the booke of the Law of Moſes, which God commanded Iſrael, as ye have it in the firſt verſe of this chapter.
            2 Becauſe here is a Congregation lawfully aſſembled: for, all the people had gathered themſelves together as one man, in the ſtreet that was before the Water-gate, in the firſt part of the firſt verſe of this chapter. And there was a congregation both of men and women, even as many as could heare with unde rſtanding, in the ſecond verſe.
            3 Becauſe here is Ezra the Scribe reading in the booke of the Law, before the

congregation, from the morning, even till mid-day, in the third verſe.
            4 Becauſe here is the manner of this religious duty▪ with ſilence and attention: for, the eares of all the people were attentive to the booke of the Law, as you may reade in the laſt words of the third verſe.
            5 Becauſe, here is the place and poſture of the Miniſter. He ſtands upon a Pulpit of wood, which they had made for the purpoſe (as our laſt tranſlation reades it) or, which they had prepared for the preaching, (as the former tranſla
                  •
               ion hath it:) And Ezra the Scribe ſtood upon a Pulpit of wood, &amp;c. So that all things (you ſee) are fitted for the occaſion of our preſent meeting, except in this one thing there prove a defect, that now there be a want of a learned Scribe to reade unto you. And in this caſe, I beſeech you, give me leave to make my prayer, and I deſire your charitable aſſiſtance therein. O Lord God, &amp;c. and ſo in a confident aſſurance of Gods gratious aſſiſtance, I prepare to the words of my Text. And Ezra the Scribe, &amp;c. And thus have I led your underſtandings to the words of our Text, which before I enter upon, give mee leave I beſeech you, to ſtoop and gather for you a flower or two that grow in the way to our

Text, by conſidering the context, and the coherence of theſe words with the former verſes of this chapter.
            Wherein I obſerve thus much.
            1 This people was newly returned out of captivity, into which they had been delivered for the great and grievous ſinnes of that nation in generall, as you may reade in the laſt chapter of the ſecond Booke of the Chronicles, from the 14 verſe to the end of the 16. And being now by the mercifull hand of their good God brought backe to their owne land and ruined City, they are ſetting a new governement among themſelves by way of reformation, both in their Eccleſiaſticall and civill State, being aſſiſted in the one by Ezra rhe Scribe, and in the other by Nehemiah, their religious and prudent Governor. Wherin that they may procure directions from heaven, and conceive the fairer hopes of happy ſucceſſe: they are aſſembled as one man, into a great and famous ſtreet of the City, there by faſting and prayer to call upon God in humiliation of ſoule; and there Ezra the Scribe ſtandeth upon a Pulpit of wood which they had made for the purpoſe, and reades the Law unto them▪ Doubtleſſe, if there had beene this true devotion in them, while their

Temple was ſtanding, and Ieruſalem in her proſperity, they might have eſceped the fiery furnace of the Babiloniſh captivity. But they have beene caſt into it, for the ſpace of ſeventy yeeres, and are now but newly delivered out of it. And now, ye ſee, they are become penitent, and wee finde them at their devotion in prayer &amp; faſting, being aſſembled for that purpoſe in a publicke ſtreet.
            1 Point, That we may obſerve, the ſweet benefit and comfort of affliction, where it is ſanctified to the Patient, and a right uſe made of it. This people had beene accuſtomed to finde mercy at the hands of their God, how grievouſly ſoever offended with them, ſo often as they did returne unto him by repentance and humiliation. Their fathers had truſted in him, and were delivered, as the Pſalmiſt truely ſingeth, Pſal. 22. 4. and now their children take the ſame courſe and proſper.
            
               Vſe To ſhew us, that affliction unto a childe of God, is but a refining of him from his dreſſe, and a trying of him for his future good. According to that remarkable ſpeech of the Lord, by the miniſtery of his Prophet, Zachary the 13. chap. the 8 and 9. verſes, where, threatning the Iewiſh nation

with utter deſtruction by the ſword of Titus Veſpatian the Roman Emperour, he ſaith, That in that day it ſhould come to paſſe, that throughout all the land, two third parts thereof ſhould be cut off and dye, but a third ſhall remaine therein: and I will bring that third part through the fire (ſaith God) &amp; I will refine them as ſilver is refined, and try them as gold is tryed: and then ſhall they all call upon my Name, and I will heare them: then J will ſay, this is my people, and they ſhall ſay it is the Lord my God. And thus was it with this people at this time; they had been in the ſurnace of affliction, they were humbled before God, and he heard them: hee acknowledged them once more to be his people, and they were in devotion before him, as before the Lord their God. To teach us all what courſe we ſhould take in this caſe, when by our finnes wee have brought our ſelves under the rod of God in what nature ſoever. Even to ſeeke God in his holy Ordinances in humility of ſoule for ſinne, who before we call, is ready to anſwer, and while we pray is ready to heare, Iſaiah 65. 24. But I inſiſt no longer upon this point, I paſſe to another.
            2 Ob. In the ſecond place therefore be pleaſed to obſerve with mee, thus much.

This people in their great diſtreſſe are compaſſionated by King Cyrus, in the firſt yeere of his raigne, who, according as Jeremy had prophecied, at the full period of ſeventy yeares, did by publicke Proclamation, looſe the bond of their captivity, as you may reade in the two laſt verſes of the laſt chapter of the ſecond booke of the Chronicles: and who according as the Lord had foretold of him by Name, no leſſe then one hundred and ſeventy yeares before hee was borne) performed all Gods pleaſure, ſaying to Ieruſalem, thou ſhalt be built, and to the Temple, thy foundation ſhall be laid, Iſa. 44. verſe the laſt.
            
            To which end, leaue is given by the King to Ezra the Scribe, and to Nehemiah their Governour, to direct and aſſiſt them in the repaire of their ſtate, and reformation of religion, a great comfort and encouragement to theſe diſtreſſed Iewes.
            2 Point, Doubtleſſe to teach us, by the example of theſe Iewes, that ſuch as unfainedly turne to God by true repentance, as did theſe penitent people, ſhall never want a ſeaſonable and comfortable deliverance, how grievous ſoever their ſinnes have been. yea, rather then fayle in ſuch a caſe, God will raiſe up helpe for them, where they

looke not for it. David in the dayes of Saul found it thus full many a time: Elias found it thus in the wilderneſſe, being fed by Ravens, in the firſt booke of the Kings, the 17. chap. at the 6 verſe. Manaſſes in the priſon found it ſo, when upon his unfained humiliation for ſinne, God wrought little leſſe then a miracle for him, bringing him backe to Ieruſalem, reſtoring him to his kingdome, and changing his iron fetters and chaines into a chain of gold and royall ſcepter, 2 Chro. 33. 13.
            The people of God have found this true by frequent experience in all ages: and that I may not looke too farre from home, the poore of this houſe and foundation finde it true: for whoſe emergent diſtreſſes, proviſion hath beene made, and ſtill is continued by thoſe who never ſaw their faces, untill that houre wherein their neceſſities enforce them to ſeeke unto us: meat and medicine for their hunger and ſickneſſes, cloaths for their nakedneſſe, with other neceſſary comforts. And that they may be inſtructed to make an happy uſe of Gods mercies extended unto them in this caſe, care is had for the ſpirituall food of their ſoules, by reading and expounding unto them the bleſſed word of God; ſo that, I referre it to your

conſideration, whether they have not as juſt cauſe miniſtred unto them to bleſſe God for his gratious providence over them, for ſoules and bodies, as had theſe Iewes to give glory to the God of Jſrael, in their particular: who foreſeeing that in time they would caſt themſelves by their ſinnes into the fiery furnace of Babylons captivity, had foretold them of a deliverer by the miniſtery of the Prophet Jſaiah, an hundred and ſeventy yeares before hand: and now in his owne time did performe his word punctually by this Monarch of Perſia, and his favour to his two ſervants, Ezra the Scribe, and Nehemiah the Governour. And now as upon theſe grounds we finde them renewed, and have learned ſomewhat from thence,
            3 Obſer. So we may obſerve in the third place, that upon their returne, they make proviſion for the publike exerciſe of true religion, as without which, their State could have no firme or aſſured foundation. Therefore it is ſaid in the firſt verſe of this chapter, that all the people aſſembled themſelves together, and ſpoke to Ezra the Scribe, that hee would bring the Booke of the law of Moſes, which he had commanded Iſrael. And Ezra the Scribe brought

forth the booke of the law before the congregation both of men and women. ver. 2. And if any would be ſati
                  •
               fied who this Ezra was, let him read Ezra 7. 6. and he ſhall find that this Ezra came up from Babel, and was a Scribe prompt in the law of Moſes, which the Lord God of Iſrael had given: a man to whom the king had granted all his requeſt, and to whoſe ſole direction this people had referred themſelves for the eſtabliſhment of religion &amp; the worſhip of God among them. From whence we mayobſerve thus much.
            3. Point. That the publicke exerciſe of religion, and the eſtabliſhment thereof is the firmeſt ground wherupon the peace and happy government of any State can poſſibly be built. The very heathens themſelves knew this: And therfore ſo ſoone as Romulus the firſt builder of Rome, had by force and armes layd a foundation of that city, next after him ſucceeded Numa Pompilius, who by an heatheniſh kind of religion brought that rude and barbarous people into ſome order, vt quod vi et injuriâ occupaverat imperium, religione ac iuſtitiâ gubernaret. ſayth their owne hiſtorian: that the commād which they had obtained by force and armes to the wrong of others, they

might eſtabliſh and adminiſter by a ſeeming practiſe of religion as in their owne right. The devill who was the founder of that Mōarchy could teach them thus much: haveing obſerved ſome what doubtleſſe from the practiſe of God himſelfe, whoſe Ape he hath ever affected to be in imitation: becauſe when the Lord had choſen to himſelfe a people of his owne, and had brought them out of Egypt, he eſtabliſhed their governement under Moſes and Aaron: not onely under Moſes, as their civill Magiſtrate to rule them by his love, but alſo under Aaron, as their high Prieſt by God eſtabliſhed to keepe them in awe by religion. Feare God and honour the King, ſayth Saint Peter, 1. Pet. 2. 17. As if the honour due to the king could never be given him in that State or kingdome where the feare of God is not taught by a publicke exerciſe of religion. Wee finde that theſe Iewes here are ſenſible of it, in that upon their returne from captivity, in their entrance to the reeſtabliſhment of their former gouernement, they have recourſe to Ezra the ſcribe, as the only man in thoſe times able to inſtruct them in that forme of religion, without which their civill eſtate could never be able to ſubſiſt. To which

onely end Ezra purpoſing to inſtruct the people as from Gods mouth, is here found in my text ſtanding upon a pulpit of wood prepared for the preaching.
            4 Obſ: But principally we may obſerve it in this their ſolemnity for the eſtabliſhment of religion, and in this particular: that as there ſtood at Ezras right hand Mattithia, and Shemai, Anania, and 
                  Ʋrijah, Hilkiha, and Maaſejah. Qui quidem er ant ſeniores è levitico genere omnes, ſayth Tremelius upon this place, elders, all of them of the trbe of Levi; ſo there ſtood at his left hand, as ready to aſſiſt him, Pedaiah, and Miſhael, Malchia, and Haſhum, Haſhbadona, Zecharia, and Meſhullan, moſt probably the cheife of their Nobillity and Gentry: that their religion and civill eſtate might ioyne hand in hand to eſtabliſh peace by a religious governement, and true religion by peace. And ſurely concerning that ſtate whatſoever, wherein there is this ſweet union betweene the civill &amp; eccleſiaſtical governement founded vpon the ſacred and revealed will of God, I may ſay truly as doth the Pſalmiſt, Pſal. 144. the laſt verſe. Happy are the people that be in ſuch a caſe: yea, bleſſed are the people that have the Lord for their God. Diſunion, and diſcord in

opinions or practiſe, ſeldome produceth any good in any ſoeiety of men whatſoever: but to a ſetled Church it is ever troubleſome and dangerous: in which regard it hath ever beene the care and ſtudy of all good men, who unfainedly deſire the publicke good and proſperity of Sion, to advance and improve all good meanes and motions conducing to the eſtabliſhment of this harmoniousunion, and accord on both ſides betwixt the civill and eccleſiaſticall governement: yea, in all publicke ſocieties and companies, the more prudent and diſcreet part thereof is ever ſtudious of publicke peace; as are theſe Iewes here in the beginning of their reformation, who to that purpoſe joyne the Church and State hand in hand, the Clergy and the Laity: not ſeparating them by factious and partiality, as ſome in theſe dayes, or alienating their affections from each other, upon petty differences, but by a mutuall conjunction of the Clergy with the Nobility, endevouring as with one conſent, the welfare of the publicke. In whoſe proceedings in this caſe, this is furthermore worthy your obſervation.
            5 Ob. That in their eſtabliſhment of Gods

publick worſhip in the exerciſes of religion, they are joyntly carefull to draw all the people to a publicke conformity. Which to effect, though it was a work of much difficulty, becauſe of their ſtrange matches, yet they conceived it to be a point of abſolute neceſſity, as without which their State would ſuddenly come to ruine. This ye may obſerve in the words of our Text, where it is ſaid in the 5 verſe: That when Ezra opened the Booke in the ſight of all the people, then all the people ſtood up. They were not allowed (it ſeemes) ſome to ſit while the others ſtood, according as every mans fancy led him, but all the people ſtood up, ſaith the Text. As alſo ye may obſerve it further in that which followeth in the 6▪ verſe, where it is ſaid, that when Ezra praiſed the Lord, the great God, then all the people anſwered Amen, Amen: as with an unanimous conſent, and with lifting up their hands: and they bowed themſelves, and worſhipped the Lord with their faces towards the ground. Here is a ſtanding up all together at one time, a lifting up their hands all together at another time, and a worſhipping of the Lord with their faces to the ground. in concluſion:
            
               
5 Point Let all things be done decently and in order, was S. Pauls rule, 1 Cor. 14. the laſt verſe, as intimating that there is no decency without order, in any publicke actions, in any publicke ſociety. The want whereof is the bane of the moſt hopefull undertakings, whether in peace or war, which, as oftentimes it is the decay of a State, ſo it is the ruine of an Army. To him that ordereth his wayes aright, will I ſhew my ſalvation, ſaith God, Pſal. 50. the laſt verſe, as intimating that all ſuch ſhall fall ſhort of the ſight thereof, as delight to walke in the diſorderly way. I wiſh that our factious ſingulariſts, whoſe queazy ſtomacks riſe againſt all conformity, would take this into conſideration. For my part, I freely profeſſe my ſelfe a diſciple to conformity, ſo long as I finde nothing againſt it in the ſacred Scripture. And I ſhall ever deſire to joyne in the practiſe of it, had I none other ground for it, but this in my Text: where I reade, that this people in the re-eſtabliſhment of their State and religion, were ſtudious of a publicke conformity in the worſhip of God, ſtanding up all together, ſaying Amen with one voyce, lifting up their hands, bowing, worſhipping, as

the publicke action and reading of Ezra gave occaſion.
            6 Ob. Yea, and (which is yet more remarkable in their proceedings in this kind) in making proviſion for the reading of the Law in publicke aſſemblies, they are carefull to have all decent accommodations for the ſame. Ezra the Scribe hath a Pulpit of wood, prepared for the preaching; and in or upon this Pulpit, hee ſtood, ſaith my Text, and read the Law unto the people, verſe 4. Which Pulpit was ſo ordered, that ſtanding therein, he was above all the people, ſaith the Text, verſe 5. to the intent, that his voyce might be the better heard, as our Engliſh gloſſe upon that place expounds it.
            6 Point A moſt pious and commendable care without queſtion, that in the publicke aſſemblies, all things might be done, not only decently and in order, but profitably alſo▪ to the edification of the Auditory. Which laſt thing moſt plainly appeareth in the two laſt verſes of my Text, where care is taken, that certaine ſelected Levites, whoſe names are expreſt in the ſeventh verſe, ſhould cauſe the people to underſtand the Law. To which end an order was eſtabliſhed,

that the Levites ſhould reade in the Law of the Lord diſtinctly, without hudling up things together, as many doe now adayes: and not to content themſelves with bare reading, but they ſhould alſo give the Sence thereof, and cauſe the people to underſtand the reading, as you have it in the laſt words of my Text. And now, I pray you, what patterne can bee more plaine, what warrant more ſtrong can the Scripture afford us for our order in our congregations, for decent carriage in publicke aſſemblies, for our reading Pewes, our Pulpits, our Sermons, our expoſitions of Scripture, after reading thereof, then this of this people in the words of our Text? wherein Ezra the Scribe ſtandeth upon a Pulpit of wood prepared for the preaching, with the Nobility and Clergy on his right hand, and on his left, opening the Booke in the ſight of the people, and reading the law unto them: at whoſe opening of the Booke, the people ſtand up, ſay Amen, bowing their heads, and worſhipping. The Levites by expoſition cauſe the people to underſtand the Law; reading it diſtinctly, and giving the ſence: which when I thinke upon, I cannot but breake into that patheticall wiſh of

a reverend Divine of our owne upon an occaſion not much unlike: O ſi Deus hoc faceret nobis tam commodum, quam Eccleſia propoſuit accommodum: O that the Lord were pleaſed but ſo to perſwade the hearts of men and women to an unity of affections in their publicke devotions, as the holy Ghoſt hath beene carefull to ſet us a patterne in Scripture and the reformed Churches pious in propounding us an uniformity, And ſo I have done with the explication of the words of our Text; I now onely crave your patience for a word or two of application, and I will draw ſuddenly to a concluſion.
            1 Our Text, you ſee, hath acquainted us with a people, that by a right uſe of affliction, are growne penitent and pious. A leſſon for the Patients of this houſe and foundation, to cha
                  •
               ke them out a way to the happy uſe of Gods corrections. That they may know that there is none other way ſo ready to remiſſion of ſinnes, as humiliation and contrition of heart for the ſame, wiſely inured to piety in devotion.
            2 It hath acquainted us with their practiſe of joyning the Church and State together in an unanimous conſent for the honour

of God in his publicke ſervice. To leſſon us in the neceſſity of a mutuall accord this way, if we deſire the proſperity of our Jeruſalem.
            
            3 It hath acquainted us with their ſtudy and practiſe of conformity in Gods ſervices that wee might know that our God is a God of order, and that the Church of God is truely repreſented by an Army well ordered, as being never▪ſo victorious over its enemies, as when it is terrible unto them as an Army with banners, Canticles the 6. ch. the 4 verſe.
            
            4 It hath acquainted us with their holy practiſe in accommodating all things in their publicke aſſembly, as to Gods glory, ſo to the peoples edification. Not onely to inſtruct us that ſuch ſhould bee the care of all good men, but to ſhew us what wee owe to God for the happy indeavours of ſuch religious ſpirits as are raiſed up by God to performe ſuch godly and chriſtian workes with a ſtudy for the publicke good. The names of thoſe noble Patriots, who were ſticklers in this reformation here in my Text, both Clergy and Nobility are recorded to their everlaſting honour, by the penne of the holy Ghoſt. Wee may therefore

by good warrant write up even in letters of gold, the names of ſuch pious Patrons as God bleſſeth us withall in this depraved and degenerate age of ours. And with this holy confidence upon juſt grouuds, that theis names are written in the booke of eternall life, of whom GOD maketh choiſe to be moved by his holy Spirit, to workes of this nature in this mutuall life. Miſtake mee not I beſeech you: this is no place for flattery: we ſtand in the preſence of the Searcher of all our hearts. I doe undoubtedly aſſure my ſelfe, that even they whoſe hands have beene deepeſt in the erection of this place, will be content to ſay as David, when hee had prepared all materials for the building of Gods Temple, 1 Chron. 29. 14. Lord, who am I? and what is my people, that wee ſhould be able to offer ſo willingly after this ſort? For, all things come of thee, and of thine owne have wee given thee. God hath given the meanes, God hath filled the hand, God hath inlarged the heart to doe this pious act in this place, and to God onely be all the glory for it.
            And now what remaineth, but an earneſt exhortation to a continnance in well-doing,

and that a courſe may be taken for an happy progreſſe in Gods favour to the royall foundation of our Hoſpitall? And to this end as I propound this people in our Text your patterne, and thereupon ſhall be bold to make a requeſt unto you; ſo I will conclude with an exhortation, and a prayer upon it. The requeſt I ground upon the practiſe of this people, in whom wee finde unanimity for preſervation of the publicke welfare, and the ſame in peace. And this requeſt I deliver in the words of Saint Paul, Phil. 2. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, verſes. If there be any if conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of love, if any fellowſhip of the ſpirit, any bowels of mercy, verſe 1. fulfill my joy, (and not mine alone, but the joy of God, and of his holy Angels) by being like-minded, having the ſame love, being of one accord, and of one minde, verſe 2. And let nothing be done through ſtrife or vaine-glory: but in humbleneſſe of minde, let each eſteeme other better then himſelfe, verſe 3. And let us not looke every man to his owne things onely, but every man alſo to the things of another, verſe 4. Let the ſame minde be in you that was in Chriſt Jeſus, verſe 5. This is the ſumme of my requeſt. And now my prayer ſhall bee

for every member of this royall foundation▪ as wel Officers as Governours, none excepted, that we may be not onely like minded one towards another, according to Chriſt Ieſus, as Saint Paul prayeth for his Romans, Rom. 15. 5. but that wee may live and dye in unity, peace, and concord: and herein, we beſeech thee to heare us, good Lord. That ſo performing our duties to God, and to the poore committed to our charge in all ſincerity and uprightneſſe of hearts, when our generall account ſhall be called for, wee may be received with an Eugee bone &amp; fidelis ſerve, well done good and faithfull ſervant, Math. 25. 21. Thou haſt beene faithfull over a few things, I will make thee Ruler over many things, enter into the joy of thy Lord.
            
            Vnto which joy, may hee be pleaſed to bring us, who hath moſt dearly bought us, even Ieſus Chriſt the righteous, to whom, &amp;c.
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            
               Feb. 16. 1638.
            Imprimatur.
            
               Guil. Bray.
            
            
            
         
      
   

