
   
      
         
            Iames Franklin, a Kentish man of Maidstone his ovvne arraignment , confession, condemnation, and iudgement of himselfe, whilst hee lay prisoner in the Kings Bench for the poisoning of Sir Thomas Overbury.
         
         
            
               1615
            
         
         Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01217
            STC 11332.5
            ESTC S3213
            33143174
            ocm 33143174
            28272
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01217)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28272)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1885:1)
         
         
            
               
                  Iames Franklin, a Kentish man of Maidstone his ovvne arraignment , confession, condemnation, and iudgement of himselfe, whilst hee lay prisoner in the Kings Bench for the poisoning of Sir Thomas Overbury.
                  Franklin, James, d. 1615.
               
               1 sheet ([1] p.). : ill.  
               
                  For J.T.,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  [1615]
               
               
                  In verse.
                  Atributed to Franklin by STC (2nd ed.).
                  Text enclosed in black border, with woodcut of hanged man on gallows at head of title.
                  "Hee was executed the 9. of December. 1615."
                  Reproduction of original in: Society of Antiquaries.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Overbury, Thomas, 1581-1613.
               Franklin, James, d. 1615.
               Great Britain --  History --  James I, 1603-1625.
               Broadsides --  London (England) --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-12
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-01
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2007-01
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2007-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            A Kentiſhman of Maidſtone, his ovvne Arraignment, Confeſſion, Condemnation, and Iudgement of Himſelfe, whilſt hee lay Priſoner in the Kings Bench for the Poiſoning of Sir Thomas Ouerbury.
            
            
               
                  IAMES FRANKLIN
               
            
            
               
                  I Am Arraign'd at the black dreadfull Barre,
                  Where Sinnes (ſo red as Scarlet) Iudges are;
                  All my Inditements are my horrid Crimes,
                  Whoſe Story will affright ſucceeding Times,
                  As (now) they driue the preſent into wonder,
                  Making Men tremble, as trees ſtruck with Thunder.
                  If any askes what Euidence comes in,
                  O'tis my Conſcience, which hath euer bin
                  A thouſand witneſſes: and now it tells
                  A Tale, to caſt me to ten thouſand Hells.
                  The Iury are my Thoughts (vpright in this,)
                  They ſentence me to death for doing amiſſe:
                  Examinations more there need not then,
                  Than what's confeſt heere both to God and Men.
                  The Crier of the Court is my black Shame,
                  Which when it cals my Iury, doth proclaime
                  Vnles (as they are ſummon'd) they appeare,
                  To giue true Verdict of the Priſoner,
                  They ſhall haue heauy Fines vppon them ſet,
                  Such, as may make them dye deep in Heauens debt.
                  
                     
                        •
                      About mee round ſit Innocence and Truth,
                  As Clerkes to this high Court; and little Ruth
                  From Peoples eies is caſt vpon my face,
                  Becauſe my facts are barbarous, damn'd, and baſe.
                  The Serieants that about mee (thick) are plac't,
                  To guard me to my death, (when I am caſt)
                  Are the black ſtings my ſpeckled ſoule now feeles,
                  Which like to Furies dog me cloſe at heeles.
                  The Hangman, that attends me is Deſpaire,
                  And gnawing wormes my fellow-Priſoners are.
               
            
            
               His firſt Inditement for Murder.
               
                  THe firſt who (at this Seſſions) loud doth call me,
                  Is Murder, whoſe grim viſage doth appall me,
                  His eyes are fires, his voyce rough windes out rores,
                  And on my head the Diuine Vengeance ſcores;
                  So faſt and fearfully I ſinke to grownd,
                  And wiſh I were in twenty Oceans drownd.
                  He ſayes I haue a bloudy villaine bin,
                  And (to proue this) ripe Euidence ſteps in,
                  Brow'd like my ſelfe: Iuſtice ſo brings about,
                  That black ſinnes ſtill hunt one another out:
                  'Tis like a rotten frame ready to fall,
                  For one maine Poſt being ſhaken, puls downe all.
                  To this Indictment, (holding vp my hand,)
                  Fettered with Terrors more then Irons I ſtand,
                  And being ask'd what to the bill I ſay,
                  Guilty I cry. O dreadfull Seſſions-day!
               
            
            
               His ſecond Indictment for poyſoning.
               
                  ANother, forthwith bids me come to'th Barre,
                  (Poyſon) that Hel-borne cunning Sorcerer,
                  That windes himſelfe into a thouſand formes,
                  And when the day is brighteſt flings downe ſtormes,
                  This hath an Angels face, a Mermaids tongue,
                  And notes of much deſtruction it hath ſung.
                  This, is the Coward Sinne, which (like a Pill,)
                  When 'tis moſt gulded, is moſt ſure to kill.
                  Whether this Hel-hownd ſtrike at Morne or Night,
                  So trecherous, cloſe, and ſpeedy is his fight,
                  That Armors all-of-proofe, nor Towers of Stone,
                  Can barre his bloody Execution.
                  This Snake with the ſmooth skin hiſſ'd out my name
                  Mongſt others more, and venom'd me with ſhame
                  That rancles to the ſoule. It ſayes that I
                  (For a poore golden handfull) did defie
                  Heauen and Saluation, when I gaue conſent
                  To teare the bowels of an Innocent
                  With lingring poyſons of themſelues too ſtrong,
                  But that their working God put off ſo long;
                  That darker deeds (by this) the light may try,
                  Which now perhaps in worſer boſomes lye.
                  To this Inditement holding vp my hand,
                  (Fettered with Terrors more then Irons I ſtand▪)
                  And being askd what to the Bill I ſay,
                  Guilty I cry. O dreadfull Seſſions-Day!
               
            
            
               His third for raiſing of Spirits &amp;c.
               
                  IN ruſhes then a heape of Accuſations,
                  For all thoſe Godleſſe damn'd Abhominations:
                  Raiſ'd by the black Art, and a Coniurers ſpelles:
                  As to call Spirits euen from the deepeſt Hells,
                  To fetch back theeues that with ſtoln goods are gone,
                  And calculate natiuities: ſuch a one
                  Credulity of fooles and women made me,
                  And to that glorious infamy betraide me.
                  A Cunning man, a Wiſe man were my ſtile,
                  When I both plaid the Foole and Knaue the while.
                  Art knew I none, nor did I euer reach
                  A bough of learnings tree; what I did teach
                  To others, or did practiſe, it was all
                  Cheating, falſe, apiſh, diabollicall.
                  To this being likewiſe ask'd, what I can ſay,
                  I guilty cry. O dreadfull Seſſions day!
                  This Diuells coate to my body made I fit,
                  Braue was the out ſide, thrid-bare was the wit.
               
            
            
               His Iudgment.
               
                  FOr theſe thick Stygian ſtreams in which th'aſt ſwō
                  
                  Thy guilt hath on the laid this bitter doome;
                  Thy loath'd life on a tree of ſhame muſt take
                  A leaue compeld by Law, er'e old age make
                  Her ſigned paſſ-port ready. Thy offence,
                  No longer can for daies on earth diſpenſe
                  Time blot thy name out of this bloody roule,
                  And ſo the Lord haue mercy on thy ſoule.
               
            
            Hee was executed the 9. of December. 1615.
            
         
      
      
         
            
               Imprinted at London for J. T.
            
         
      
   

