
   
      
         
            Offer maid to a gentilman of qualitie by Iohn Fraser, to subscribe and embrace the ministers of Scotlands religion, if they can sufficientlie proue, that they haue the true kirk and lawful calling. VVhereto ar[e] adioyned certaine reasons and considerations concerning theis tvva heades and foundaments, vvithout the light of vvhi [...] others can not be cleared, nor assured ground in religion in thir dayis established
            Fraser, John, d. 1605.
         
         
            
               1604
            
         
         Approx. 183 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 97 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01222
            STC 11336
            ESTC S118717
            99853924
            99853924
            19327
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01222)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19327)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1097:17)
         
         
            
               
                  Offer maid to a gentilman of qualitie by Iohn Fraser, to subscribe and embrace the ministers of Scotlands religion, if they can sufficientlie proue, that they haue the true kirk and lawful calling. VVhereto ar[e] adioyned certaine reasons and considerations concerning theis tvva heades and foundaments, vvithout the light of vvhi [...] others can not be cleared, nor assured ground in religion in thir dayis established
                  Fraser, John, d. 1605.
               
               [8], 184 p.   
               
                  Printed by Stephane Prevosteau, in the rue of S. Io. de Lateran, besyd the college of Cambray,
                  At Paris :
                  MDCIIII. [1604]
               
               
                  The roman numeral date in the imprint is made with turned c's.
                  Dedication  place and printer's name from STC.
                  In Scots.
                  Running title reads: The offer of Io. Fraser.
                  Imperfect; title page faded with loss of print.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            sco
         
         
            
               Church of Scotland --  Controversial literature.
               Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-12
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-06
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-06
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
               
               
OFFER MAID TO A GENTILMAN OF QVALItie by Iohn Fraſer, to ſubſcribe and embrace the Miniſters of Scotlands religion, if they can ſufficientlie proue, that they haue the true kirk and lauful calling.
VVHERETO AR ADIOYNED certaine reaſons and conſiderations concerning theis tvva heades and foundaments, vvithout the light of vvhilks others can not be cleared, nor aſſured ground in religion in thir dayis eſtablished.
            
            Ad ipſam ſalutem ac vitam aeternam nemo peruenit, niſi qui habet caput Chriſtum. Habere antem caput Chriſtum nemo poterit, niſi qui in eius corpore fuerit, quod eſt Eccleſia.  D. Auguſtinus.
            
            AT PARIS, Printed by Stephane Preuoſteau, in the ruë of S. Io. de Lateran, beſyd the college of Cambray
            M DCIIII.
         
         
            
               
Munus beatae vitae non niſi intra Eccleſiam reperitur, quae ſuper petram etiam fundata eſt, quae ligandi &amp; ſoluendi claues accepit. Haec eſt vna quae tenet &amp; poſſidet omnem ſui ſponſi &amp; Domini poteſtatem, per quam coniugalem poteſtatem etiam de ancillulis filios parere poteſt: qui ſi non ſuperbiant, in ſortem haereditatis vocabuntur: ſi autē ſuperbiant, extrà remanebunt.
            D. Auguſtinus.
            Quiſquis ille eſt, &amp; qualiſcunque ille eſt, Chriſtianus non eſt, qui in Chriſti Eccleſia non eſt.
            Idem.
         
         
            
            TO THE MINISTERS OF SCOTLAND, HIS deare contry-men, IOHN FRASER visheth the knavvledge of the verity &amp; eternal lyf in IESVS CHRIST our Lord.
            
               AS my offer is reaſonable, ſo hope I that ye vvill accept the ſame, and cleare your ſelfis vith reaſon, baith for your avvin cauſe, and for the contentement of ſic as ar in doubt, if ye haue the true kirk and lauful calling, or elſe beleueth aſſuredlie that ye haue nather of them. J am in died but à particulaire and ſingle man, quha maketh the offer, yet aſſure your ſelfs that there is no Catholik on lyf being of diſcretion and knavvledge, but vvil ſay &amp; promiſe, yea man accōplish the ſame, as being oblished to acknavvledge the true

kirk vnder no leſſe paine then eternal condemnation. Quherefore J pray yov to anſvver vvith à cōmune accord, or, if anie particulair amonges yov ather taketh the burding of him ſelf, or getteth that charge of yov, to approue his labours by your publique conſent. Mairouer becauſe ſindry in place of good and ſolide reaſons, giues iniurious vvords, reaſon vvald ye abſteine therefra, examining my argumentes &amp; anſvvering thereto ſolidelie, &amp; to vvy vveal my proofes and mynd, rather then to pik at vvords. For ſo I think to do, if anie anſvver be is maid to me, vvilling nather to giue nor receaue fals or light money, for good paimēt, meikle leſſe the droſſe and ſcumme of iniurious talk for good gold of ſufficient proofes. It is queſtion of à maiſt precious iovvell, lat vvs touch it vvith an innocent &amp; cleane hand, mouth, and hart. He shalbe victorious, quha hes or findeth the trueth, quhilk can not be haid except in the true kirk amonges the

lauful paſtors, to quhome vve ought duetiful obedience, quhilk moueth me at this tyme to ſubmit all that I haue vvrittin here, or shal vvrit eftervvard in matters of religion, to the iudgement of the Catholik Apoſtolik and Romaine kirk and paſtours of the ſame: (as in matters of eſtait, to his M. his honorable counſel, &amp; other vvhatſoeuer his magiſtrats or officers, if I haue ſpoken in any thing vnreuerētly: for my intention is vpright to both) becauſe at this preſent I am aſſuredlie perſuaded that shee is only the true kirk guyded by lauful paſtors. Quhen ye proue me that this honour appertineth onlie to your companie, and ſic others as agreeth vvith yov in vnitie of doctrine, J shal behaue my ſelf vith lyk ſubmiſſion and reuerence tovvards yov in al reſpectes. J haue tald yov my opinion and ioyned reaſons therto, quhereby ye may ſee me reddie to receaue yours &amp; to knavv therby quhat aſſurēce ye haue of your kirk &amp; calling, vvithout

the quhilk aſſurence nather can vve enter in vith yov, nor they quha ar alreddie vith yov, remaine vith ſaif cōſcience: for quha can be in quyetnes of mynd, not being aſſured if he be in Gods houſe, out of the quhilk there is no ſaluation? J proteſt before him, to quhom no thing is hidde that my offer procedeth of à ſincere mynd tovvardes his honour vvith earneſt deſyr of your vveal, and all Chriſtians and principallie of my contray men; &amp; nather of cōtempt of yov, nor preſumption of my avvin ſtrenth. As to anie of your perſonnes, the euil arriue to me, that I vvald vvish to yov. I am affectionat to the religion that J profeſſe, true it is (quhilk as J beleeue, can not iuſtlie offend yov, ſeing that if ye mak me youris, ye may haue me alſe forvvard for yovv) yet I haue vſed alſe litil offenſiue language as I culd. But if any thing hes eſchapped out of my penne, that may be interpreted othervvayes then I vvald vvish, J pray yov pardon me;

and think that oftentymes the bitternes commeth rather of the matter it ſelf, then of my natural. If anie be ſo hard and difficil that he vvil not accept my excuſe, nor pardon that quhilk in his opinion is offence; the beſt vvay to reuenge him ſelf on me, is to be maire modeſt then he thinketh me to haue beine; for he vvil beare avvay by that moyen the honour of Chriſtian modeſtie, quhilk J vvald glaidlie haue. The armes of flyting ar vnpropre in this field, quherein theis of ſolide reaſon may onlie obteine the victorie. If ye proue your kirk to be good and your calling lauful, J vvil eſteime vvorſe of all other companies diuided frome yov in doctrine, then ye can ſay, vvrit, or think. God of his infinit mercie by vertue of his trueth ioyne vvs all together here in his kirk militant, that vve may be partakers of eternal bliſſe in his kirk triumphant, to the quhilk bring vvs the father, ſonne &amp; holie ſpirit.
            AMEN.
         
         
            
            1. To Timothee 3.
            
               Theis things Jvvrit to thee, hoping that I shal come to thee shortlie. But if I tary long, that thovv mayeſt knavv hovv thovv aughteſt to conuerſe in the houſe of God, vvhilk is the Kirk of the liuing God, the piller and ground of trueth.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            OFFER MAID TO AN GENTILMAN OF QVALItie by M. Iohn Fraſer Priour of S. Nicolas, to ſubſcribe and embrace the Miniſters of Scotlands religion, if they can ſufficientlie prooue, that they haue the true kirk, and lauful calling: VVHERETO AR ADIOYNED CERTAIN REASONS and conſiderations concerning thes tua heades and foundaments, vvithout the light of vvhilks, others can not be cleared, nor aſſured ground in religion in thir day is eſtablished.
            
            
               
                  BEING now in the fieldes (wher ſolitude giueth me laiſer) and weal myndful of the offer and promiſe I maid you at viſiting, I thoght it not out of propos to affirme now by wreit, whilk I ſpak then by word vnto you.
            
            
               
               If the Miniſters may ſchavv by good and ſolide reaſons, that they haue the true kirk, and ar lauful paſtours therof, I shal vvithout any farther inquiſition, examination, or tryel of their doctrine ſubſcrybe their cofeſsion of faith, obey to their commande and vvil, yea accept that charge.
            
            Whilk promiſe and offer I mak for no vaine oſtentation of my ſelf nor to prouok any man by ſic braging, but that an neceſſarie duetie Act. 4. 12. oblisheth me to follow this courſe, whereof my groúds ar thir. No man can be ſaif except by IESVS CHRIST: no man can be ſaif by him, except he be a membre of his myſtical bodie, whilk is his kirk, wherevnto can be Ioa. 10. 1. no entrie but by the doore (if we wald not be eſtimed as theafs &amp; robbers)

that doore can not be opened but by them wha hes the keyes, that is, by the lauful paſtours: Our Lord hes gotten al power in heaven and in Matth. 28. 18. earth; he hes ſent his Apoſtles with lyk power and charge; and that they ſuld exerciſe this power truelie, and in al holynes, perpetual aſſiſtence of the haly ſpirit in al veritie was promiſt &amp; giuen to them: and in them Matth. 28. 20. and by them to their ſucceſſours in the kirk vnto the conſummation of the warld. So I am forced to haue recourſe to the Kirk our Sauiours ſpouſe: whilk I wil find in vaine and to no effect, if I be not receaued by the true officers in that holy tabernacle and houſe of God. Now in this great nōbre of pretended kirks (for there be more then an hondreth of diuerſe companies wha hes vſurped that honorable and ſoueraigne nam wher as there can be bot one true,

excepte we wald gif many bodyes to one head, whilk ſort of monſter lies hidderto ſurpaſſed al poëtical fiction) we ſuld vſe al caire &amp; diligence to find out the true kirk gouuerned by lawful paſtours: for whoſoeuer goeth wrang in this mater entring in the ſynagog of Satan in place of Gods kirk, he ſtrayeth frome eternal ſaluation, how ſoeuer he perſuade him ſelf to be in the true way.
            I think the reward or danger might mak anie man careful in ſeiking; &amp; circumſpect in election &amp; choiſing, not giuing rashlie credite to euery man, wha shal promis or vndertak to lead him to Gods houſe. we araduertiſt by our bleſſed Sauiour to be war, and not to beleif them, wha shal Matth. 24. 23. Mar. 13. 21. Luc. 21. 8. ſay lo heer is Chriſt, lo there. We at fallen in a dangerouſe tyme, wher the diuerſitie and multitude of opinions and ſectes putteth many-men

in doubt whome to flee, whome to follow. Only this is confeſſed &amp; grā
               ted by al men, that there is a kirk &amp; but ane only (I meane Catholique and vniuerſal) eſpouſe and myſtical body of IESVS CHRIST, houſe of God, piller of veritie, mother of al faithful, out of the whilk there is na ſaluation, nor lyf. For na man can haue our Lord for head, wha is not à member of his body. And ſeing no man gaineſayeth this, of neceſſitie it muſt be true, as a thing prented in al mens harts by God him ſelf, wha wil no man to haue excuſe wher he willeth no man to refuſe.
            And for that cauſe in the ſymbole of faith immediatly efter the articles pertining to the holy Trinitie and myſterie of our redeption, is adioyned. I beleef the holy Catholik kirk, or as it is in the ſymbole of Nice. I beleef one, holy, Catholik, and A poſtolique

Kirk. we muſt acknawlege hir for our mother; for by hir moyen the lawful ſonne man knaw his genealogie, birth, &amp; kinred in this ſpirituall familie. By hir the child man knaw God his father: I ESVS CHRIST apperteined to hir only: no man can cleam right bot by hir only, in whais fauour the contract of mariage was maid: he man be auowed by hir wha wald iuſtly protēd any part in Chriſts eternal inheritāce. S. Cyprian ſayeth De vnitate Eccle. cap. 5. very weal. Illius (Eccleſiae) foetu naſcimur. Illius lacte nutrimur, ſpiritu eius animamur: adulterari non poteſt ſponſa Chriſti, incorrupta eſt &amp; pudica; vnam domum nouit, vnius oubiculi ſanctitatem caſto pudore cuſtodit: haec nos Deo ſeruat: haec filios regno, quos generauit, aſſignat▪ Quiſquis ab Eccleſia ſegregatus adulterae iungitur: à promiſſis Eccleſiae ſeparatur. Nec perueniet ad Chriſti praemia, qui relinquit Eccleſiam Chriſti, alionus eſt,
               
               profanus eſt, hoſtis eſt: habere iam non poteſt Deum patrem, qui Eccleſiam non habet matrem. Si potuit euadere quiſquam, qui extra Arcam Noe fuit, &amp; qui extra Eccleſiam foris fuerit, euadit. &amp;c. Vve ar borne of hir birth and generation; vve ar nourished vvith hir milk; vve ar quickned &amp; taketh lyf by hir ſpirit. The ſpouſe of Chriſt can not be defiled vvith adulterie; shee is vncorrupt and chaſt. shee knavveth bot one houſe: shee keippeth vith a chaſt shamfaſtnes the holyneſſe of one bedchamber: shee doeth keip vvs to God. Shee doeth appoint to the kingdome the ſonnes vvhilks shee hes begottin. Vvhoſoeuer being ſeparated frome the kirk ioyneth him ſelf to the adultereſſe, he is ſeparated frome the promeiſſes of the Kirk; nether shal he com to the revvards of Chriſt, vvho leaueth Chriſts kirk: he is a mere stranger, a profane man, ane enimie: he can not novv haue God to his father quha heth not the kirk to his mother: If any
               
               man could eſcape vvha vvas vvithout the Ark of Noë, he alſo shal eſcape vvha shalbe vvithout the Kirk Sic lyk S. Auguſtin ſayeth: Si quis abſq. Eccleſia inuentus fuerit, alienus erit à numero filiorū. 
               lib. 4. C. 10 de ſymbolo To. 9 
               If any man shalbe fond vvithout the kirk▪ he shalbe as an ſtranger and not coumpted in the nomber of the lauful ſonnes. Out of Adams ſyd ſleipping in Paradiſe was formed Eua, of whois mariage come al mankynd; out of chriſts ſyd ſleipping on the croſſe was formed the kirk, the only lawful mother of al the faithful.
            Knawing once this kirk I wil mak no difficultie to entre therein, to follow &amp; obey hir voice; becauſe I am ſure shee can not erre, fail, nor be deceaued, nor deceaue anie man: And this I beleeve without any doubt: I ſay beleif, for many good &amp; w
                  ••
               ghty reaſons, yea and it muſt be ſo: for otherway is how shal shee preſerue and

keip me frome errour &amp; hereſie, not being hir ſelf exempt and free there fra, vnles perchance ye wald haue me more skeilful nor my guyd, in whilk caſe it war more ſeamly that I ſuld guyd hir, nor shee me: for certainely a doubtful leader can not mak an aſſured companie. If the wiſdome and authoritie of the Kirk be not ſufficient to help our infirmitie &amp; ignorance in maters of faith, wher shal we haue any ſure guyd knaw in to the wardle, to whome men of euery eſtait and condition may haue recourſe in their doubtes and controuerſies? qui dubitatin fide, infidelis eſt. vvha doubtes in faith is an infidelle; at leiſt if he remaineſtil in doubt.
            I doubt not bot ſome wil ſend me to the ſcriptures with certaine rules; the whilks may reſolue all queſtions and open wp al ſort of conttouerſies arryſing in matters of religion. I wil

accept their conſel, &amp; ſerue me with their inuention provyding I can ſee good reaſon. I wil ſay only at this time, that they wha vanteth them ſelfis to haue inuented and keiped (according to their iudgment) thes rules, can not agree amonges them ſelfis (as I shalbe habil to prouue, God willing, if anie man cal my ſaying in doubt) ſo that I can not hoppe to accord with anie of them, except, without anie farther rule, I ſay as he ſayes, wherein I moſt diſagree with many, ſeing he agrees with ſo few. But to the matter. I knaw there is no errour teached, nor can be teached in the ſcriptures: they war dytted by the holy ſpirit to holy men, wha, as good and true inſtruments of the veritie, did wreit as it was dytted to them by God. So I worshipe the ſcriptures for their authors cauſe, I embrace them for the veritie conteined in thom: yet

by reaſon of high myſteries hid therin, I dar nor be ſo bold as to decyd al 2. Pet 1. 20 queſtions thereby, knawing aſſuredly that no prophecie of the ſcripture is of priuat interpretation, but man be interpreted by the holie ſpirit as it was wreittin, that is by holie men, remaning within the boſome of the kirk, and authoriſed by hir, as they war, wha receaued it frome God: that is the true interpretation man be takin of the kirk, to whome God hes committed al veritie for our inſtruction. for if we shal with ſome men mak doubt of the kirks authoritie &amp; firmitie in al veritie, as not being euery wher certaine, thinking &amp; planly affirming, or rather as a ground of religion, ſurelie beleifing, that shee may erre and fail, to whome shal we haue refuge? what remeid shal we haue for the woundes of à doubtful conſcience? wha shal without iuſte

reproche apply thes rules to the ſcriptures and giue ws the true ſenſe? Wha shal pronunce the ſentence, and decreit, wher to al parties man ſtand? there man be one, ne circumferamur omni vento doctrinae: That vve be not 
               Eph. 4. 14. 
               carried about vvith euery; vvinde of doctrine. There wilbe an euill ordered houſe if euerie man be left to his awin fantaſie. We ar not put here nather to pley nor play, but with the honour of God ſeik our awin ſaluation in humilitie, veritie, &amp; charitie. I man haue an better and maire ſure guyd nor my ſelf, before I leaue the kirk: he man be better nor shee alſo, or elſe I shal change in vaine. If ther be anie ſiclik, I wald glaidly heare his nam, his qualitie, wher he dwelleth, how I might knaw him. I wald willinglie tak the paine, and beſtow the expenſes to ſeik him out. The love and deſyre of veritie with hoppe of

a maiſt ample reward wil mak the labour light.
            But ye wil ſay, it is the ſcriptures. but it is not the ſcriptures I ſeik, for I haue found them. I ſeik that whilk I culd not find, wher I fand the ſcriptures, to wit the true ſenſe of the ſcriptures; for otherwayis anie libraire might haue ſatisfied my iuſt curioſitie: for what curioſitie can be more iuſt, nor to ſeik eternal lyf? The heretiks and ſchiſmatiks, yea ſome Iewes and Turks hes the bible, and alleageth theirſelfs to haue the true ſenſe of the ſame: but how far they be therfra, their maiſte perniciouſe incredulitie doeth declaire. But it may be ſaid, that they tak not the ſcriptures, as they ſuld be taikin. I doubt not but they fail, becauſe they go wrang not hauing the aſſiſtance and help of the halie ſpirit. that is as meikel as wha wald ſay, alſe lang as ye

gang right ye gang not wrang. that is true: but how shal I go right? that is my queſtion: I deſire a guyd (for he who is vnlearned &amp; ignorant of the tounges can not ſerue him ſelf with thes rules, whilks learned men can ſcaircelie weal practeis) wha not onlie knaweth the true way and conteineth the ſame, but alſo wil ſchaw me it, and in caſe I vnderſtand him not weal at the firſt or ſecund time, wil tel me it ouer againe in mair plaine langage, and if I yet miſtak him, wil ſchaw me my fault and teach me the true meaning. And ſiclik if my nightbour &amp; I, be in contrarie opinion, wil ſchaw ws in plain termes whois meanīg is good, &amp; whois meaning is not good: or if there be any other ſenſe better nor them baith, will produce it for our good inſtruction.
            The ſcriptures telles me the trueth▪ I doubt not, but they ſuffer me to tak
                  •
               
               
a wrang ſenſe and aduertiſes me not that I am deceaued: as we may ſee to our great regrait now by experience of ſo manie diuerſe ſectes bred of ſiniſtrouſe interpretation takin out of the ſcriptures. Think not that al thes men do willinglie deceaue them ſelfs decipimur ſpecie recti. Vve ar deceaued by the outvvard ſchevv of the right. If they wald haue hard and obeyed the voice of the kirk (wha cried heigh and lowd that they vnderſtude not the true meaning of the ſcriptures) they haid not gone wrang, as they haue donne now, following their awin iudgment. Ye wil ſay perchance they laiketh the holie ſpirit, for whoſoeuer haith his aſſiſtance muſt go weal. I grant yow that (&amp; concludis thereon, that the kirk moſt go weal) but ſeing that euerie man hes not the holie ſpirit; how shal I knaw who hath him, who not? Amonges this

infinit nombre of them, wha pretendeth to haue that priuiledge (notwithſtanding of their contrarietie, manifeſt mark of their vntreuth, and that Satan oftentymes doeth transfigurat and 2. Corynt. 11. 14. chenge him ſelf in an angel of light) it shal be verie hard to anie man to knaw whidder his ſpirit be albus an ater, Blak or vvhyte, as ſayeh Zuinglius of de ſubſidio Euchariſt. To. 2. his ſpirit. Moreouer this can be but à ſpirit particulaire, and à ſpirit of diſcorde, except he agree with the general: for in matters of religion priuata veritas opinio eſt, non veritas. A priuat veritie is but an opinion and not a veritie. It can not be proper to ane only whilk was giuen for al. I ſeik a commound guyd of al Chriſtians. I wil not credit my awin priuat ſpirit, an other ſuld not luk for anie farther at my hand. The veritie is but one, the guyd and iudge muſt be of that ſaime nature. If I find out the true

guyd and rule, al men, wha wald be ſafe muſt follow that guyd and rule. So if myn, or anie other particulaire mans ſpirit be that ſure &amp; true guyd, whaſouer goeth therefra, muſt go wrang: yea all other rule without him ſerueth for noght. wher as the holie ſpirit can do weal althought he haue no rule preſcrybed to him: he wha maid the aſſe of Balaam to ſpeik, may cauſe any man he pleaces, tel the veritie he neiddeth no help of rules; his onlie aſſiſtance was ſufficient for the Apoſtles to ſpeik, &amp; vnderſtand all tounges and knaw all veritie for mans ſaluation. If anie particulaire perſonne hes gotten the ſpirit in this ſort, lat him ſpeik baldlie, we muſt be all his diſciples. There ar ſindrie who wald willingly tak on them that name as their ſtaitly ſtyl in wreitting may euidentlie declaire, yet for feare of mockerie they dar not ſay it: But

lat ws retourne to the ſcriptures examinated &amp; interpreted by thir rules.
            The ſcriptures (ſay they) be as the toucheſtone, wherwith the gold and ſiluer of Chriſtian religion be tryed and knawne frome the fals and contrefaict gold and baſſe money of erroniouſe and hereticall doctrine. At all ſic tryal ther ſuld be three thingis, the touchſtone, the gold or metall to be tried, and the goldſmith: we haue the touchſtone, to wit the ſcriptures, the gold to be tried, at the heads of religion called in doubt, to knaw if they be of good and fyne metal of veritie or noth. The debat is for the goldſmith, who ſuld trye the gold. It apperteined not to euerie man, ſeing that euerie man hes not learned the craft. Vntil we find a better, I think it beſt we receaue the kirk, or rather ſuffer the kirk ſtand with that charge ſeing no other preſenting him ſelf,

is worthee of that place, as in deid it apperteineth to no other but to the kirk. Yet ſeing that many doeth other wayes at this time we may iuſtlie ſay with Sanct Hierom ſola ſcripturarum 
               Epiſtola a Paulinum. 
               ars eſt, quam ſibi paſſim omnes Vendicant; hanc garrula an us, hanc delirus ſenex, hanc ſophiſta verboſus, hanc vniuerſi praeſumunt, lacerant, docent antequam diſcunt. There is only the craft of the ſcriptures, that all men challenge and vendicats to them ſelfs euerievvher euerie old babbling vvyf, euerie raving old fellovve, euery ſophiſt full of vvords. yea euerie an in general doe tak this ſcripture diſmember and teach it, befoir that thay haue learned it. We ar not now in queſtion of the ſcriptures, but of the interpretation of them, whilk ſuld not be thrawin to our iudgment, but our iudgment drawin to it, Bringing in 
               2. Cor▪ 
                  
                     •
                  1 5. 
               captiuitie all vnderſtanding vnto the obedience of Chriſt and hauing in reddines to
               
               reuenge all diſobedience, vvhen our obedience shalbe fulfilled. IESVS CHRISTS houſe is the ſchoolle of faith, &amp; not of ſcience; he knaweth ſufficientlie, wha beleefeth as he ſuld do. God hes at all time ſerued him ſelf with the kirk to teach men, to declaire and ſchaw his will publishing his veritie to the warld. he wilbe credited on his onlie word quoniam ipſe dixit &amp; facta ſunt, ipſe mandauit &amp; creata ſunt. his ſaying is more ſure, then anie mathematical demonſtration, he may mak an inſtrument of anie thing, wha maid all thing is without anie inſtrument. So our maiſter and Lord maid clay with his ſpattle to hail the blind man: in the hand of anie other that Ion. 9. 6 haid bein ſufficient to mak à ſeing man blind. May he not with the clay of mortall men heall our blindnes in the trueth. The riuer of Iordan haid only commune water without

anie extraordinaire vertue, yet Naaman being ſent ther, by the prophet, 4. Reg. it receaueth the power to heal him of his leproſie: the prophete of all prophetes or rather the mak air of al prophets heth ſent ws to the kirk: why shall shee not haue the vertue to hail ws of our leproſie of ignorance by him, wha ſent ws to hir? S. Peter ſaid in his name to the crippel man ſurge &amp; ambula, Ryſe aud gang. the naturall act. 3. 6 ſeiknes frome the birth culd not reſiſt his command. his ſchaddow healled infirmities: his worde act. 5. 15. ſlayed, his prayers raiſed wp the dead. ib. 8. 8. 9. 4. Shall Chriſts awin worde haue no ſtrenth? there is vertue in all aboundance, wher euer he will: ourweacknes can not ſtoppe him. I man ſay with Oroſius: Hocſi quiſquam hominum 
               Aduer. Pelagium de arbit. liber. 
               ita dicendum putet, vt ſub infirmitate hominis Deum non poſſe affirmet, &amp; omnipotentiae Deialiquid impoſſibile ſuſpicetur
               
               in omni creatura Coeleſtium, terreſtrium, &amp; infernorū: hunc non tantùm ſententia mea dixerim blaſphemum, anathema deteſtandum, ſed etiam vel in exemplum Nadah &amp; Abiu Diuino igne 
               Leu. 10. 2. 
               damnandum, vel iuxta perditionem Dathan &amp; Abiron hiatu terrae receptum viuum 
               Deut. 11. 6 
               ad inferna mergendum. If anie man thinketh that it may ſo be ſaid, that by reaſon of mans infirmitie and vveaknes he vvill ſay God can not, and thinketh any thing impoſſible to the omnipotencie and almightie povver of God in all creature of heaven, of earth and of hell. J vvald eſteim according to my iudgment this man not only blaſphemouſe, &amp; deteſtable cvvrs, bot alſo ather to the exemple of Nadab &amp; Abiu vvorthie to be condemned by the fire comming frome God, or according to the perdition &amp; deſtruction of Dathan &amp; Abiron being receaued be the opening of the earth vvorthie to be quicke thruſt doun to hell. Shal our Maiſter and Lord

haue no ſtrenth except that whilk he receaues frome the inſtrumēts he imployeth? shal the weacknes of the inſtrument hald bak his will? Quàm potens in faciendo de nthilo, tam facilis in 
               Idem. ibid. 
               perficiendo de facto. He is als facile and eaſie in perfecting anie thing maid, as he is mightie in making any thing of noght. there can be no weack inſtrument in ſo mightie an hand. Poteſt ergo omnia (ſayis the ſame Oroſius) in homine qui vtique poteſt omnia. He may then do all thing in man, vvha may do all things. I wil therefor follow the kirk with ful confidēce: I shal haue an good guyd, ſeing God hes commanded me ſo to doo. It wil be hard to perſuade me that the contrarie ſuld be donne, except they may ſchaw that ather they ar maire wiſe then God, in taking an other guyd; or that he heth giuen ws that commād to deceaue ws; wherof nather can be true. He is à God of

wiſdome and trueth. he hes promiſt to gowerne his kirk in all trueth, If shee erre the shame redoūdeth to hir head &amp; ſpouſe IESVS CHRIST, wha is hir guyd, redeemer, groundſton, &amp; Maiſſon, wha promiſt to buld hir vpon an rock, and that the gettes of hel ſuld not preuail againes hir. what reproche suld it be to his wiſdome or power, if he culd not, or wald not keip hir frome errour, according to his promiſe? But he knew not perchance, when he maid this promiſe, what power he haid: thir new Lords haid not as yet limitat the merches of his might: their breif of perambulation was not put, as yet, in execution. or shal we ſay Immenſa eſt ſinémque potentia coeli non habet, quicquid ſuperi voluêre peractū eſt? Promiſit quiae voluit, ſeruauit quia potuit. He promeſt becauſe he vvald, he keiped it, becauſe he might. and in trueth if this plight ancre

of the kirk war loſt, how shal we be aſſured of the veritie? wher shall we ſeik it? at their hands perchance, wha aſſures ws that the heal Catholique kirk may erre, becauſe they ar but men. If they be Gods, or may ſchaw ws any ſpecial priuiledge, wher by they ar exemtpted frome the general ruell of errour, to the whilk al men without exception (according to their iudgment, notwithſtanding Gods promiſe) ar ſubiect, it is reaſon we ſuld hear them, obey, and follow them, becauſe of their ſpecial prerogatiue aboue all others. But whaſoeuer ſayeth that al men ar ſubiect to errour and fals opinions, tyneth his credit in all other things hauing obteined credit in that. yea being a man as others, why may he not be deceaued in that, als weal as in the reſt? And doubtles he is deceaued, if he think his maxime of errour to

haue place in the kirk of God, wher he is rueller and gowernour him ſelf. Wha can keip anie thing weal, if it be ſo vnſure whilk he hes takin in his awin keipping? Farther the certaine and infallible conſtancie of the kirk in matters of faith may beſt be ſein in the grounds and moyens shee vſeth in teaching and guyding ws. It is maiſt certaine that the wark dependeth on the workar, the effect on the cauſe, and the end on the cheife beginnig. Wher the Authour, workar, cauſe, fondament, and original beginning ar neceſſaire all togidder and vnchangable, the wark, effect, and end moſt be of the ſame nature &amp; condition: Now ſeing the kirk hes for internal author, mouer, cauſe, and beginning, the father, the ſonne, and holie ghaiſt ſpirit of veritie and trueth, wha hes aſſiſted aſſiſts, and will aſſiſt hir to the end of the

warld, why shal not hir doctrine, &amp; shee hir ſelf be without errour or falt becauſe of hir good guyd? for faith whilk ſurpaſſeth al naturall and humain reaſon can haue no ſure ground but by the reuelation of God in his kirk. This aſſurance may be eaſelie ſein in the ſcriptures; becauſe wher it is ſpokin of the miſſion and power whilk our Lord geueth to the officers &amp; magiſtrats of his houſe; there alſo is maid mention of the promiſes of his perpetual aſſiſtance and preſence to his kirk. All povver is giuen to me in heauen and in earth: going therefor, 
               Matt. 28. 18 
               teach ye all nations, baptizing them in the nam of the father and of the ſonne and of the holie ghaiſt, teaching them to obſerue all thingis vvhatſoeuer I haue commanded yovv: and behold I am vvith yovv al dayis euen to the conſummation of the vvarld: As my father hes ſent me, 
               10. 20. 21. 
               alſo I ſend yovv &amp;c. And I vvill ask 
               Ion. 14. 16.
               
               the father and he vvil gif yovv ane other paraclete, that he may abyd vvith yovv for euer. Item. but the paraclete the holie ſpirit, vvhom the father vvil ſend in my name, he vil teach yovv all things, vvhatſoeuer I ſay vnto yovv. And in an other place he prayeth for his kirk. For them do I pray &amp;c. Sanctifie 
               Ion. 16 13. 14. 26. 
               them in trueth &amp;c. as thovv did ſend me in the vvarld, I haue alſo ſent them in the vvarld. The hail place is to be red for it maketh to the propoſe. Now if nather his promeiſes doeth oblish him, nor his prayer haue anie place for the ſtabilitie of the veritie in his kirk, how can it be true that S. Paul ſayeth. And he gaue ſome Apoſtles &amp; ſome prophetes, and other ſome Euangeliſts 
               Eph. 4. 11. 
               and other ſome paſtours, and doctours to the conſommation of the ſanctes vnto the vvark of the miniſterie, vnto the edification of the bodie of Chriſt vntill vve meit all into the vnitie of faith. Wher it is

plainlie ſaid that our Lord hes eſtablished Eccleſiaſtical perſonnes for the perfection of his elect in conſeruing thē frome the maliciouſe craft of Satan, that they be not deceaued by errour, nor caried away with euerie wind of doctrine; whilk can not be eſchewed, vnleſſe the doctrine of the kirk be without errour. We ſee the people of euerie contray doeth embrace the religion of their true or fals paſtours: ſo except the paſtours haue ſome certaine ruel &amp; guyd mair then humaine, without doubt their incōſtant doctrine shal mak à flock inconſtant. Ye ar the ſalt of the earth, 
               Matt. 5. 13. 
               ye ar the light of the vvarld &amp;c. Ye haue not choiſen me, but I haue choiſen yovv, 
               Io. 15. 16. 
               and appointed yovv that ye go and bring forth fruct and that your fruct, remaine: Whilk things war ſaid to the Apoſtles as repreſenting the kirk, becauſe they war the firſt fondaments therof,

laide by IESVS CHRIST him ſelf being yet on earth.
            The words of God hes yet their Gen. 1. 28. force: creſcite &amp; multiplicamini, bring forth fruict and multiplie: the words apperteineth to the poſteritie, &amp; yet doeth keip their ſtrenth, whilk they receaued in the begining. If ſo be in the temporall and corporal propagation, what shal it be in the ſpiritual? or shal his liberalitie be leſſe towards his kirk? shal shee be vnius aeui, of on aage, as ſayeth Liuius of Rome new lib. 1. dec. 1 begoune? Shal we think that ſo great priuiledge &amp; ſo deir coft appertineth onlie to the Apoſtles? there is na appeirence of reaſon: ſeing the promiſes conteineth à perpetual &amp; cōtinual aſſiſtence: I haue appointed yovv, that ye go, and bring forth fruict, &amp; thàt 
               Ion. 15. 16. 
               your fruict remaine. that vvhatſoeuer ye ask of my father in my name he maygifit yovv. Wha can doubt but they

haue deſyred that, according to his awin ſaying, the fruict broght out by them ſuld remaine in the kirk: that is that the veritie ſuld remaine for euer in the kirk? Suld not the ſpirit of conſolation and veritie eternallie abyd in the kirk, wher as neine of the Apoſtles did leif an hondreth years? when they paſt wp to heauen by their gloriouſe martyrdome as our eldeſt brethren to enter in their land of eternal lyf, whilk our Lord hed coft to them with his pretiouſe blood: They drew not wp the ledder efter them. The aſſiſtence in al veritie was giuen to them as being neceſſaire for mans ſaluation: the neceſſitie remaineth, why shal not the gift remaine? it was not giuen to the kirk for the Apoſtles cauſe, as apperteining to them onlie, but to the Apoſtles for the kirks cauſe they being hir principal membres: ſo the principall motiue

remaining, why shal not the priuiledge ſo neceſſaire remaine? they receaued it but as membres neareſt to the head, to be continued and conuoyed by them to the reſt of the body, Sicut vnguentum in capite, quod deſcendit 
               Pſal. 133. 2. 
               in barbam, barbam Aaron, quod deſcendit in oram veſtimenti eius. this ſueit oyll of veritie whilk is in the head IESVS CHRIST why shal it not deſcend vnto the beard of Aaron and to the border of his garmēt, that is to the Apoſtles &amp; their ſucceſſours to the extreme border of Chriſts kirk ſignified by his garment? And reaſon wald or rather Gods infinit mercie, that the ſucceſſours of the Apoſtles ſuld haue that ſame aſſiſtence of the holy ſpirit, becauſe they haue the ſame place and charge for the perfittīg of Chriſts body, whilk is his kirk. And therefor they ar called his officers &amp; ſeruants. and doutbles it war

agans all good reaſon to think, that the holie ſpirit haid gotten onlie charge to guyde the Apoſtles, as thoght our Sauiour haid ſufferred death for them onlie, &amp; not for the kirk in all aages. About the yeare of our Lord 1525. (ſindry ſectes being riſin wp vnder the colour, that the true kirk haid failled, all the paſtoures hauing erred, &amp; at laſt hauing decayed, and therefor alledging that they war ſent by God to teach the verity ſo many yeares vnknaw in to the warld) Dauid Georgius an cheif of the Anabaptiſts taking occaſion of that alledged &amp; imaginaire fal of the Catholik kirk, geue him ſelf out for the true Meſſias: Amonges the reaſons whilks he vſed againes the Lutheriens and other ſectes, the principal was takin frome their newnes, &amp; from the defection of the kirk, whilk they preached for that ſame occaſion

of their nouueltie; for otherwayes they culd not haue teached, nor yet bein miniſters, doctours or paſtours. If the doctrine of Chriſt (ſayis this peſtilent Dauid Georgius) and of his Apoſtles vvas true and perfect, certainlie the kirk that they planted and formed by their doctrine ſuld haue remaned, and dured neceſſairly, and neuer haue decayed, ſeing that Ieſus ſaid, that the gettes of hell ſuld neuer preuaill aganes hir: but novv it is manifeſt &amp; knavvin to the hail vvarld (according to your avvin cōmune ſaying) that the Antichriſt hes altogither ouerthravvin the doctrine of Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles, &amp; the kirk fonded and bulded by them, as may be ſeine in the papiſtrie: vvherfor the doctrine of Chriſt, &amp; of his Apoſtles vvas fals and inperfect. An blaſphemouſe cōcluſion, yet altogether neceſſaire, if the aſſumption war true, whilk ſindrie now adayis not onlie admittes to be true, bot alſo taketh it for ane

ground maiſt certaine, whervpon they haue bulded their new kirk. Abyſſus abyſſum inuocat.
            
            But to refut this perniciouſe opiniō lat ws ſee and conſidder what honorable titles the kirk hes in the holie ſcriptures, and how faire promiſes ar maid by God of hir ſtabilitie and infallibilitie: Sho is called the bodie, the fulnes, the ſpouſe of Jeſus Cſtriſt, the houſe of the Lord, the pillar and firmamēt or ground of trueth, boght vvith his blood, his vvealbeloued, his dovv, his vvinzard, his inheritance, his kingdome. &amp;c. ouer faire and ſpeciouſe names to euanish ſo ſone contraire to his bontiful promeiſes. I vvill marie the vnto 
               Hoſe 2. 19 
               me for euer, yea I vvil marie the vnto me in richtiouſnes and iudgement &amp; mercie. &amp;c. May I not ſay heir with S. Aug. Tom. 6. cōcione ad Cath. cap. 22. 
               Haec eſt mater vera, pia mater &amp; caſta intrinſecus viri ſui dignitate ornata, non forinſecus mendacio fallente turpiter colo.
               
               rata. This is the true mother, godlie and chaſt mother decked invvardlie vvith the dignitie and maieſtie of hir husband, not shamefullie coloured outvvardly vvith à deceauing lie. and in deid as the ſame S. Aug. ſayis, In ventre Eccleſiae veritas 
               Tom. 8. in pſal. 57. 
               manet: quiſquis ab hoc ventre Eccleſiae ſeparatus fuerit, neceſſe eſt vt falſa loquatur, neceſſe eſt, inquā, vt falſa loquatur qui aut concipi noluit, aut quem conceptū mater excuſſit. VVithin the belly or boſome of the kirk the veritie remaineth. vvhoſoeuer shalbe ſeparatted frome this boſome of the kitk, of neceſſitie he man ſpeik lies, of neceſſitie, J ſay, he man ſpeik lies, vvha ather vvald not be conceaued and ingendred, or els being conceaued, the mother hath caſt him out. But if shee heth become an harlotte and adultrèſſe, shee hes maid diuorſe, shee hes violat the law of mariage, whilk God haith promiſt ſuldbe keiped in faithfulnes. I doubt greatlie if they be

lauful childring to God, wha calleth their mother à whore, matris adulterio patrem quaerunt: can any man ſay mair freelie that he is an heretik, nor to ſay that the kirk he followis may, &amp; hes erred: shee wha abandoneth hir ſelf ſo eaſelie to euerie ſutter, can not be à true ſpouſe, shee muſt be an harlotte. Excuſe me if I ſay, that ſic men may be baſtards, but the kirk of God wil remaine à virgin for euer, by the aſſiſtence &amp; diligence of hir head &amp; ſpouſe he was born of à virgin, he wil haue his mēbres &amp; ofspring to haue that ſame honour, their true and ſpiritual mother being à virgin, becauſe shee is his ſpouſe. God man haue ſomthing out of the deuils power; he hes 
               Eph. 5. 27. 
               maid to him ſelf a gloriouſe kirk not hauing ſpot or vvrincle, or anie ſic thing: but that shee shuld be holy &amp; vvihout blame. to wit in doctrine. If God be ouerthravvin in his avvin houſe, he man be Matt. 12. 29
               
weackar then the deuill, whilk can not be granted, yea not thoght, without an execrable blaſphemie. Wherfor I man ſay with S. Aug. (whom I cite the maire willinglie that ſindry of the proteſtants alledgeth that he is theirs, notwithſtanding he be their greateſt enimie, at leſt to their doctrine) Credimus Eccleſiam Catholicam 
               Tom. 9. de ſymb. lib. 1 cap. 5. 
               ipſaeſt Eccleſia Sancta, Eccleſia vna, Eccleſia vera, Eccleſia Catholica, contra haereſes omnes pugnans: pugnare poteſt expugnari non poteſt: haereſes omnes de illa exierunt tanquā ſarmenta inutilia de vite praeciſa: ipſa autem manet in radice ſua, portae inferorū non vincent eam. VVe beleif the Catholik kirk, shee is the holy kirk, the onlie kirk, the true kirk, the Catholik kirk fighting aganiſt all hereſies, shee may fight, but shee can not be ouercum, al hereſies ar gone out of hir, lyk vuprofitable brā
                  ches cut of the vynetree. Shee (the kirk) doeth remaine in hir avvin root: the gettes
               
               of hell shal not ouercome hir.
            
            Lat ws ſee the other promiſes maid to hir, by hir head and maiſter, whilk ar ſo cleir &amp; in ſo great nomber, that no man can doubt, except he that wil receaue no thing, but that onlie whilk heth paſſed by the tryal of his iudgmēt, to whois iudgmēt to ſtand war tobe without any iudgmēt. God promiſt, as I haue ſaid now oftymes, Matth. 16. 18. that the gettes of hell, that is the power of Satan by errour and hereſie ſuld not preuail againes hir. hes not Satan preuailled, if he hes cauſed hir erre in teaching &amp; authorizing fals doctrine? S. Aug. ſayeth paſſing weal. Non inſultent haeretici per partes conciſi, 
               Tom. 8. in Pſal. 47. 
               nonſe extollāt, qui dicunt Ecce hic eſt Chriſtus, ecce illic: Qui dicit ecce hic eſt, ecce illic 
               Matth. 24. 23. 
               ad partes inducit, vnitatē promiſit Deus. Reges in vnum collecti ſunt, non per ſchiſmata diſſipati ſunt. Sed forte iſta ciuitas, quae mundū tenuit, aliquando euertetur? 
               pſal. 47.
               
               abſit: Deus fundauit eam in aeternum: Si ergo Deus fundauit eam in aeternum, quid times? ne cadat firmamentum? Lat not the heretikes inſult &amp; triumphe being diuided in ſectes, lat not thes magnifie &amp; praiſe them ſelfs, vvha ſayeth lo heir is Chriſt, lo there. VVho ſayeth lo heir is Chriſt, lo there, he induceth to factions. God did promiſe vnitie and concorde. The Kings vvar gathered to gether in one; not ſcattered by diuiſion. But perchance this citie, vvhilk haith comprehended &amp; occupied the vvarld, at lenth shalbe ouerthravven? God forbed: God haith founded and eſtablished hir for euer. if then he heth founded hir for euer, quhat feare ye? leaſt the firmament shuld fall? He promiſt alſo he ſuld be with hir all day is euen to the conſummation of the Natt. 28 20 warld: if he left hir not one day, when shuld errour haue occupied hir? So Ioan. 14. 16 shuld the holie ſpirit tary with hir for euer, &amp; teach hir al veritie: al veritie

&amp; errour cannot conſiſt togither. The father promiſt to his eternal ſonne, the ſame perpetual veritie for his ſeed. J vvil mak this my cōuenent 
               Iſa. 59. 21. 
               vvith them ſayeth the Lord: My ſpirit yat is vpon the, &amp; my vvords, quhilk I haue put in thy mouth, shal not depart out of thy mouth, nor out of the mouth of thy ſeed, nor out of the mouth of the ſeed of thy ſeed, ſayeth the Lord from hence forth euen for euer. For his kingdome shal Luc. 1. 33. haue no end. So ſayeth Daniel of his dominatiō, whilk shalbe throch al, &amp; cap. 7. 14 &amp; 27. for euer. And Micha ſayeth als far. cap. 4. 7. Now behold the amplitude greatnes &amp; authoritie. I shal gif thee the heathen for thyn inheritance, and the endis of the 
               pſal. 2. 8. 
               earth for thy poſſeſſion. In an other place al nations, vvhome thovv hes maid, shall come and vvorshipe befoir the ô Lord &amp;pſal. 85. 9. shal glorifie thy name. Iſaias ſayeth: In the laſt day is shalbe prepared the montaine 
               2. 2. 
               of the houſe of the Lord in the toppe
               
               of the montaines, and shalbe exalted aboue the hilles, and all nations shal flovv to it. Not onlie Iſaias, but alſo the other prophets ſay is the ſame. Mairouer the ſinnes of the childrine shall not takaway his inheritance of veritie amonges the Chriſtians: King Dauid aſſureth ws: his ſeed vvil I mak 
               pſal. 88. 29. 
               indure for euer, and his throne as the dayis of the heauen. But if his cheldren leif my lavv, and vvalk not in my iudgments, if they brak my ſtatutes &amp; keipe not my cō
                  mandement; then vvil I viſit their iniquities vvith a rodde &amp; their ſinnes vvith ſtrockes; yet my mercy vvill I not tak from him; nor offend in my trueth: my conuenant vvill I not brack. &amp;c. Ye ſee that God wil keip his ſonnes heritage notwithſtanding of mans iniquitie.
            But they wha approuueth not this ſtabilitie and conſtancie of the kirk, anſwers that shee failleth not, als lāg as shee heareth the voice &amp; obeyeth

the commandement of hir ſpouſe IESVS CHRIST, &amp; is guyded by the holie ſpirit, following the word of God, whilk is perpetuallie ioyned with the holie ſpirit; But if shee leif the word &amp; obey not hir ſpouſe, shee may fail and erre. What is this other to ſay, then that the kirk can not fail nor erre at all. For we haue ſchawin alreddie that there can be no ſic ſeparation, nor diſobedience: wherwpon we haue concludid the certaine and perpetual veritie of the kirk, in reſpect of the perpetual and aſſured aſiſtance of IESVS CHRIST and of his holy ſpirit in al veritie: for if shee war without hir head and gouernour shee culd no maire be à kirk. In whilk caſe they might rather ſay shee war decayed and dead nor erred and failled. but nather of thir can be true as we haue ſchawin by euident places of the ſcriptures. We man think that

our Lord hes bulded hir vpon a rock, as it becommeth his wiſdome, and Matt. 7. 24 not vpon the ſandis, as fooles doo who is houſes can not ſtand becauſe the ground is not ſure.
            As to the promiſes, whilk ſom men pretendes to be conditionallie maid to the kirk, becauſe ſome promiſes ar of that nature: they man vnderſtand that ſic promiſes toucheth onlie the particulaire, if they remaine in the kirk, if they follow the Lords cōmandement. God ſayeth to Moſes Ecce eſtlocus apud me, &amp; ſtabis ſupra petram. 
               Exod. 33. 21 
               Be hold there is a place by me, and thovv shall ſtand vpon the rock: On this rock the kirk is bulded, shee mā be ſtabill: Shee is the Lords inheritance gifin to him by God his father without anie condition: whilk may be ſchawin by great nomber of places of the ſcriptures. It depēdeth not vpon mens vertue or wice, ſtrenth or

weacknes, folie or wiſdome: he hes tak in the keipping of his awin right in his a win hand: he wil not be ſpoiled Matt. 12. 29 by à mightier, becauſe ther is Mar. 3. 27. neine mightier: if it haid depended vpō our worthines, I doubt if Chriſt Ieſus ſuld haue haid anie kirk at all: we man cleime to his infinit mercie, goodnes, and extreime loue, by the whilk he hes promiſt not to abandōne his kirk: not to ſuffer hir to go wrang: his grace is à ſufficient beild againes al ſtormes, and an ſure ancre in al danger. he will cair for nothing in this warld, if he be cairles of his wealbeloued ſpouſe, who is his dow Can. 2. 7. 6. 8. his perfite and vndefiled.
            The ark of Noë was not ſurmonted by the flood; it was ay hier then the water of the flood, whilk notwithſtanding was hier then all the reſt of the things vpon earth. Men, townes, hilles, montaines war lawer

then the water, whilk yet acknawledgeth the Ark to be aboue it: for it drouneth the reſt, but lifteth wp the Ark. quia dominus ſuppoſuit manū: Becauſe 
               pſa. 37. 23 
               the Lord did put his hand vnder it: and what culd ſurmont it, whilk was ſuſteined by the mightie hand of the Lord? This was without anie condition: but who war to be ſauued, it behoued them to be therin: to thē the promiſe was conditionall. The Ark, if it haid not haid the ſpecial aſſiſtence of God, haid beine ouerthrawin as the reſt, wha wanted that ſafegarde and protection.
            The veritie of that figure is giuen to Chriſt our ſauiour without anie limitation or condition: but to the particulaires, if they be there the water whilk out of the ark was mortall and deadlie, within ſcrueth for lyf. So may we ſay of the kirk, ſola eſt, quae 
               Aug. to. 10 de temp. ſerui. 181. 
               intra ſe poſitos validae caritatis compage
               
               cuſtodit; vnde &amp; aqua diluuij arcam quidem ad ſublimiora ſuſtulit, omnes autem quos extra arcam inuenit, extinxit. It is shee onlie vvho keipeth vvith a mightie band thos quha ar vithin hir: quhereby the vatter of the deluge carried vvp the ark on hight, but quhoſoeuer it fand vvith out the ark, it deſtroyed. Why shal not arca Eccleſiae ſuperior eſſe omnibus vndis &amp; fluctibus erroris? No thing can be in danger that cōſtantlie remaineth in the Lords keipping, how weack ſoeuer it be of it ſelf, hauing ſtrenth of it keipper.
            But they wil ſay perchance that all thir promiſes and prerogatiues ar ather to the kirk inuiſible, or for the reuelation of the holie ſpirit maid to euerie man in particulaire, whereby they ar gowerned and called his. Lat ws ſee, or rather lat ws cōſider (ſeing it can not be ſein) this inuiſible kirk. I pray yow reid the places cited before,

&amp; ye wil ſee that the promiſes ar maid to à viſible companie. The ſalt of the earth, the light of the warld. Sic lyk à citie ſet vpon à montaine. à candle ſette vpon a candleſtick: wha heareth the kirk, heareth God. wha contemneth hir, contemneth God: wha wil not heir, nor obey the kirk ſuld be to ws as an excōmunicat perſonne. Shee is ſignifiet by the Ark of Noë, by the children of Iſraël in the deſert, by the wynzard, by S. Peters bark, by à montaine, by the nettes caſſin in the ſea, by à piller. &amp;c. what is here inuiſible, or rather what can be viſible to him wha ſeeth not thes things? he hes miſter of à medicin, and not of reaſons, wha can not ſee à bark &amp; nettes, an Ark of three hondreth cubites lang, à vynzard, à citie, à candle vpon an candilſtik, à montaine, à pillar, fyf or ſex hondreth thouſand perſonnes to gidder. what

remeid for ſo deſperata blindnes? in ſo wolful à ſeiknes? Iubeas miſerum eſſe libenter. He man perish in his awin blindnes, wha wil not oppen his eyes. How can we acknawledge or obey this inuiſible iudge? Wher shal we find hir? nuſquāeſt ſi nuſquam videtur, cùm non ſit incorporea: how can we be ioyned with hir? &amp; out of hir boſom ther is no ſaluation. The kirk haid charg to teach al natiōs &amp; baptiz thē. I think it shalbe als difficil to hear as to ſee inuiſible doctours, except we wil receaue the auld brounies for paſtours. Shal we beleif that the kirk of God hes neuer beine ſeine, becauſe the doctrine teached now in ſindrie places was neuer hard before, the doctours therof not being as yet borne? If the kirk was euer viſible, it was that shee might be knaw in &amp; ſo followed. Whil thir men come shee was hid, now shee is knaw in. why hes she

changed nature? is it to deceaue ws? God forbid: shall we giue the cauſe won to the Anabaptiſts with their foolish and new inuented ſynagoge? Whilk doubtles man be receaued according to this opinion, or if it be receaued in others, why shall it not be receaued in them? If they haid yet remained inuiſible, they haid beine more worthie of credet. But what? anie thing is good enouch to theis fantaſticall ſpirits. Notus in Judea Deus, knaw in but in his kirk, and by pſal. 75 1. his kirk, ſeing shee is the pillar of veritie and trompet of his holie name. It is shee wha hes diſcouuered, aſſaulted and condemned, yea and at laſt deſtroyed all heriſies in euerie aage, not by inuiſibilitie, but by viſible preſence, in general concels, by dayly preaching and teaching of hir doctours and paſtours, and ſouueraine decreits of hir miniſteriall head. If

there be neine of thir things true, the kirk man be onlie an vaine phantaſticall imagination forged to abuſe men, lyk to the philoſophical ſtonne, where foolish men imployeth their lyf, mynd and moyens to find right noght at laſt. Quid amplius (ſayeth S. To. 9. in Epi. Ion. tract. 2. Auguſtin) dicturus ſum quàm caecos qui tam magnum montem non vident? qui contra lucernam in candelabro poſitam oculos 
               Ibid. tract. 1. 
               claudunt, VVhat shal I ſay farther but that they ar blind vvha ſeeth not ſo great à montaine? vvha cloſſeth their eyes ouer againiſt the candle put on the candleſtik. And in an other place. Ecce mons implens vniuerſam faciem terrae. Ecce ciuitas de qua dictum eſt: non poteſt 
               Daniel 2. 35 
               ciuitas abſcondi ſuper montem conſtituta. 
               Matth. 5. 14. 
               Illi autem offendunt in montem, &amp; cùm eis dicitur, aſcendite, non eſt mons, dicunt: facilius illuc faciem impingunt, quàm illic habitaculū quaerunt. Behold the montaine filling the face of the vvhol earth. behold
               
               the citie of vvhilk it is ſaid: à citie ſette one an hil can not be hid. They (to wit the heretik is) do ſtrik them ſelfs againeſt the hil. &amp; vvhē it is ſaid to them, go vvp, they ſay, it is not the hill. They do more vvillinglie dash their face againſt that hill, nor ſeik an dvvelling there. I muſt ſay with To. 8. pſal. 56. the ſame S. Auguſtin. O haeretica inſania, quod non vides, credis mecū: quod vides negas credis mecum Chriſtum exaltatum ſuper coelos, quod non vidimus; &amp; negas gloriam eius ſuper omnem terram, quod videmus. O heretical frovvardnes, and obſtinate maddeneſſe, thovv beleifis vith me that thov ſeeth not; thov denyes that quhilk thov ſeeth, Thov beleifis vith me that Chriſt is exalted aboue the heauens, quhilk vve haue not ſeine: &amp; thov denyes his glorie to be vpon all the earth, vvhilk vve ſee. And if I be not abuſed the perſecutions (whilk cōtinued almoſt frome Chriſts dayes to Conſtantin the greats aage, althoght not

in al place &amp; with lyk crueltie, wher many thowſand martyrs did beſtow their lyfis) war agains the viſible kirk of that aage: for if this new inuiſible kirk haid beine in tho is dayes, shee haid conſerued al hir membres from dāger by moyen of hir inuiſibilitie: And in deed al ſic men eſchapped the tyrānie of the maiſt cruel Emprioures by that ring Gyges. or rather becauſe Plato 10 de repub. neine of thes inuiſible men as yet war forged. Shall the kirk of God haue no other refuge in perſecutions (whidder they come of tyrānes, or of heretiks oppugning the veritie) but to flee to the darknes of inuiſibilitie (maire fitte for the mēbres of Satan prince of darknes, then for the membres of IESVS CHRIST author of light) as ſepia to hir blak blood or ink? God forbed. If they anſwer that they vnderſtand by the inuiſible kirk, the elect, wha becauſe they ar knawin onlie

to God ar called inuiſible. I anſwer that the ſame argument maketh the cōfeſſiō of faith ar. 17. inſered in the act of parliament halden the 1567. prented 1568. &amp; 1597. the condemned perſonnes als weil to be inuiſible, ſeing they ar knawin to God onlie in that qualitie, ſo all the warld ſalbe inuiſible. Secundly ſeing that I am oblished to ioyne my ſelf with the true kirk onlie: how shal I knaw hir not being God? I ſay onlie that we fand als lāg as they did regne, a viſibel, at leeſt ſenſible, and maiſt cruel perſecution agains ſic as culd not com out of the contray: for they war conſtrained to ſubſcribe &amp; ſweir that the preſent religion was good, albeit in their cōſcience they knew &amp; war perſuaded to the cōtraire: whilk perſecutiō was ſo cruel that the death it ſelf haid bein mair tolerable: yea I perſuad my ſelf that if the Miniſters wald haue proceded by way of death agains the Catholiks, that they ſuld not haue won ſo meikil agains thē as

they did then, by an extreme neceſſitie to whilk they pat them. But to retourne to their inuiſibilitie: we ar ſeiking à kirk to guyd ws, shee was inuiſible before our dayes (and now we haue ſo manie kirks viſible that we knaw not whilk to choiſe) why ſo lang inuiſible, and why now ſein? inuiſible when shee might haue bein knawin, becauſe ther was but few; &amp; now viſible when the great nomber maketh hir vncertaine to ws. Thir dark queſtiōs requiteth a new Oedipus to ſolue them. I ſay that abſolutlie shee man be kuawin to ws, &amp; not to God only: God of his infinit mercie, &amp; goodnes, hes and wil cōmunicat to ws his knawledge ſo far as it is neceſſaire for our ſaluation: but it is altogither neceſſaire (if anie thing be altogither neceſſaire for ws) to knaw the true kirk, ſeing shee is the only houſe wher God is ſurelie to be

found, truelie ſerued, deulie obeyed and eternal lyf mercifullie obteined, as is ſufficientlie prouen before. If I ſuld promiſe à thouſand pound to any man, and efter ſend him to an inuiſible theſaurer to be payed, ſuld he not haue iuſt occaſion to think me an abuſer? God hes promiſt truelie to his ſonne by the mouth of Dauid that his ſeed shal remaine for euer, &amp; 
               pſal. 88. 36. 
               his throne shalbe as the ſunne before him, &amp; lyk to the moune perfect for euer: if the ſunne and the moune, when they ar in ther great clearnes, be inuiſible I vnderſtand no thing. The kirk neuer hes beine obſcured ſo far by perſecutions, but shee might be kanwin beſydes the miſerable blindnes of the Iewes and Gentils, &amp; maliciouſe obſtinacie of heretiks, or factiouſe ſeparation of ſchiſmatiks. What? wil they mak the enimies of God to be eaſelie ſeine and found, wher his ſeruants

&amp; freinds dar not ſchaw them ſelfis? then God man hyd and keip cloſe his freinds for feare that Satan ſpoille him. he shall haue onlie ſic as he may ſteale without the deuils knawledge by moyen of the inuiſibilitie, changed now in à viſibilitie by vertue of an act of parliamēt halden at Edenbrugh without à vow, in the Queenes M. abſence the year of God 1560. ratified by an parliament of lyk force in his Maieſties minoritie 1567. But I paſſe this nec veterum memini, laetórue malorum. The deuil ſuld feght agains the members of the kirk, but shuld not preuail, becauſe the victorie ſuld be theirs, and they for their victorie ſuld be crouned, whilk can not be without battel. Nam qui certat in agone, non coronatur niſi legitimè certauerit. And if anie 
               2. Tim. 2. s 
               man ſtryue for à maiſterie, he is not crouned except he ſtryu
                     ••…
                   as he aught to doo. And

Sanct Paul ſayeth of him ſelf, Bonum 
               2. Tim. 4. 7. 
               certamen certaui, curſum conſummaui, fidē ſeruaui: in reliquo repoſita eſt mihi corona inſtitiae, quam reddet mihi Dominus in die illa iuſtus index &amp;c. I haue fought à good fight, I haue conſumate my courſe, I haue keipt the faith. Concerning the reſt, there is laid vp for me à crovvne of iuſtice, vvhilk the Lord vvill render to me in the laſt day à iuſt iudge.
            
            If any think hir inuiſible becauſe shee can not be ſeine all at one tyme, but only in hir partes: by that ſame reaſon they may think hilles &amp; mō
               taines inuiſible, yea the haill warld inuiſible, or rather no thing in the world tobe viſible, nather man nor beiſt, nor other thing, great nor ſmal; becauſe no thing can be ſeine al at one inſtant, one part cutting away the ſight of an other, as may be ſein by daylie experience.
            As to them wha thinketh that all

Gods promiſes appertieneth to the particulaires, whome he aſſiſts by a ſecret and particulaire inſpiration &amp; fortifieth by an interne and inward cōſolation; wherfor the holy ſpirit is called the ſpirit of conſolation: we haue refuted them before, and if this opinion war true, as it is not, it wald confirme &amp; ſtrengthen our ſentēce: For if the ſpirit of veritie be geuen to euerie man in particulaire, meikil maire to all togither. So the kirk hauing the ſpirit in ſo great abondance culd not erre. And doubtles naturall reaſon wil cōſtraine ws to think that if the particulaire can not erre (whilk man be if euerie man be aſſiſted with the holy ſpirit according to Gods ſolemne promiſes) the paſtours of the kirk ſuld les be ſubiect to errour, becauſe of their office, ſeing that the charge is geuen to them to teach and and guyd the faithfull that they be Eph. 4. 14.
               
not haid away with euerie wind of doctrine, except they wil ſay that paſtours be altogither vnneidful, ſeing that the halie ſpirit hes takin the office vpon him to guyd euerie an in particulaire, or that the particulaire men heth the holie ſpirit in all abondāce whilk is denyed to the paſtours, who for that cauſe may erre, wheras the particulaire is aſſured; an opiniō ridiculouſe and perniſiouſe, althoght it be embraced by manie now adayis. But this opinion of priuat inſpiratiō is fals, becauſe our Lord (to whom all appertineth by the gift of his father) maid theis promiſes to the Apoſtles when he ſent them as maiſters gowernours and paſtours of his kirk, to preach and teach throughout the hail warld. and therfor it was for the publik charge duetie and vtilitie of the kirk vniuerſall. In omnem terram exiuit ſonus eorum, &amp; infines orbis terrae 
               pſal. 18. 5. Ro. 10. 18.
               
               verba eorum. Mairouer this opinion, is abſurd, for if euery man hes the haly ſpirit, in ſic abondance, no man culderre, but wald ſay the treuth in althing is (I mein in mattres of faith) yea no man culd haue need of à maſter or paſtour, (as ſaid is) euerie one being maiſt ſufficientlie inſtrucked by the holie ſpirit, wha can not erre. vpon theis vaine imaginations the Anabaptiſts hes bulded their foolies. Neuertheles it man not be thoght that we deny that the holie ſpirit doeth aſſiſt the particulaires: For he aſſiſteth them in deed with his grace, wherby they ar moved to obey conſent and beleue the doctrine of the kirk, and to keep the vnitie required therin, but not to cōmand guyd and gowerne, whilk appertineth onlie to the paſtours, as ſaid is.
            Reſteth yet two obiections againes the ſtabilitie of the kirk in al veritie.

The firſt is, that the particulaire kirk may erre, whilk may be ſchawen by manie exemples: &amp; therfor the kirk catholik and vniuerſal may erre. The ſecond is, that the kirk Catholik is repreſented by a general concel: but the general concel may erre, and hes erred: Then the catholik and vniuerſal kirk may erre. To confirme the firſt obiection they collect againes the Iewes kirk the faultis committed frome the beginning of the warld to our Lords tyme: to the whilk albeet it be eaſie to anſwer, yet becauſe it is not our queſtion, wha ar ſpeeking of the Chriſtian kirk, I wil paſſe it for the preſēt, as making no thing agans ws. I ſay only that they ſal not be habil to ſchaw anie errour in the Iewes kirk approuued by publik conſent. For the ſentēce of death pronunced by Caiphas aganes our Lord was nawayeserroniouſe of it ſelf, (if we wald

lay aſyd the wicked mynd wherfra it proceded) ſeing it was according to our Maiſters will (qui paſſus eſt, quiae voluit) and Gods awen decreit of his infinit mercy and loue towards mankynd. And S. Iohne approueth it as coming of the holy ſpirit, wha prophecied by the mouth of an wicked man. The words of the Euangeleſt ar thir: But one of them named Caiphas, 
               Io. 11. 49. 
               being the high preeſt of that year, ſaid to them, yovv knavv nothing, nather doo yovv conſider that it is expedient for vvs that one man die for the poeple, and the vvholl nation perish not. And this he ſaid not of him ſelf, but being high prieſt of that year, he prophecied that Jeſus shuld die for the nation, and not only for the nation, but gather into one the children of God, that vvar deſperſed. wherby we may vnderſtand the qualitie of the decreit, notwithſtanding the wickednes of the inſtrument.

God bliſſeth his people by Balaams mouth: but this is maire ſolemne, Nom. 23. ſeing that IESVS CHRIST is put in poſſeſſion of his inheritance by the ſentence and decreit of the ſynagoge pronunced by Caiphas at that time high prieſt, Chriſt being declaired to be hee, wha was to redeame the warld with his death, by the whilk the ſacrifice of Aaron was to tak end, the ſynagoge hauing reſigned oueral right to the true heire, &amp; that by a general conſent, to the Iewes greatter and inexcuſable condemnation.
            As to the reſt of the argument it followeth not. The particulaire may erre, ergo the general may erre: For the partes (whilk ar as it war particulaires) of the elements do perish euerie day, the elemēts notwithſtanding doeth remaine, yea and recouuer at one ſyd, what they loſſe at the other: for it is impoſſible that the hail elements

can perish all at one tyme, I meine naturallie.
            So we ſee men die euerie day and that in great nomber at ſome times, yet becauſe there commeth others in their place, man can not perish altogether, becauſe God hes bliſſed him, and all leuing things by theis words Creſcite &amp; multiplicamini. Ariſt. wald haue anſwered homo non moritur, ſed hic homo. And whilk is maire, as man in particulaire remaining man, that is, retening the nature &amp; proprieties of man, can not die (for if he die he ceſſeth to be man) ſo the particulaire kirk remaining kirk, that is remaining in the doctrine, vnion, &amp; cō
               munion of the Catholik kirk, can not erre: for if she fal in errour of doctrine generally receaued and approued, outdrawing hir ſelf frome the holie Catholik kirk, shee is no maire kirk, but as à dead body poſſeſſed by

ſchiſme and hereſie. But if shee remaine in obedience and vnion with the Catholique kirk, albeet shee be aſſaulted with anie ſeiknes, or troubled with any wound of errour, yet by the lyf, ſtrenth, and health of the hail body of the Catholik kirk, shee may recouuer hir health. Euen as we ſee the finger being cut of the body, the interne and inward forme being loſt, it loſſeth the nature of à finger, althoght the material part remaineth as before: But remaining ioyned and vnite with the body, notwithſtāding any infirmitie or wound, it may be cured &amp; hailled, by reaſon of the lyf &amp; health of the reſt of the body with the whilk it is conioyned. A greene tree by violēce of ſtormie wind, froſt or ſeaſon of year may tyne the leefis, or branches ſome tyme, whilk the ſpring or ſpace of tym will bring againe: but if the ſtok be rotten or

drawen out of the ground, ther is no hoppe of leefis, meakelles of branches. he moſt plant an other tree, wha wald ſee leeſis or branches there againe: whilk experience can not be ſoght in the kirk: For IESVS CHRIST wil plant no other; and I knaw not wha culd tak the charge in his place. for it hehoued him to do better then our Lord hes dōne before him, wher by the promiſes maid to the perpetual kirk might ons be accōplished, ſeing that Chriſts kirk hes failled by interruption, as they ſay: whilk cannot be, notwithſtanding the faill of ſome partes, prouyding the parties noble keip their integritie: but they being loſt, there is no moyen to ſett wp againe that kirk; they may perchance ſett wp an other, if they haue receaued that power. And this far for the firſt obiection.
            As to the ſecond we receaue the

propoſition as good and true, if they vnderſtand à general concel laufully called, halden, concluded, and confirmed: for doubtlesſic à concel repreſenteth the Catholik and vniuerſal kirk, whilk we beleef can not erre: but that ſic concels heserred or culd erre, we deny plainlie. Yet to proue their ſaying, they alledge that the cō
               cels ar cō
               traire one to an other, whilk cannot be but errour of one, or baith the parties. And farther, concels hes corrected concels, as ſayeth S. Aug. but correctiō (ſay they) preſupponeth errour: for the proofe of the firſt they bring exemples at her of particulaire and prouincial ſynods agains general concels; or conuenticuls of heretiks agains à general, or els concels ſuſpect and diſawoued agains à lauful and general: Wherfor that proueth nothing againes ws, no maire, then maketh againiſt the authoritie

of à lauful parliament (ſi parua licet componere magnis) the cōuentions halden in diuers ſchyres being one aganiſt an other, or anie of them agains an iuſt and lauful parliament; or yet à ſeditiouſe aſſemblie of rebelliouſe perſonnes ryſing agains their laufull prince; or agains à parliament of the haill eſtaites called, halden, concluded, and confirmed by the free authoritie of à iuſt and lauful prince in his maioritie. There can not be anie cōtradiction in à kings or cōmoune Weatlh edicts, or actes, for correcting, or agreing together the opiniōs of particulaire towns or ſchyrs, or for condemning of rebelles, and their famouſe libelles: or by improuing of actes neuer approued by his forfathers; yea nor for changing of anything of policie in à better form being admoniſt by good experience, althoght it haid bein otherwayes ordonat

by à parliament before; provyding the mattres of them ſelf war indifferent. Where it is to be notted firſt, that we ſpeck here of general cō
               cels, and not of particulaires, whilk as they may erre, ſo aught they to be corrected by the generals (as meineth S. Auguſtin aganiſt the Donatiſts) if there be anie thing wrang. Secondlie it is to be notted, that this diſput ſuld be takin of thinges appertining and cōcerning the ſubſtance of the faith, wher there can be no changing or varietie, meakelles contrarietie: for it that is ons veritie remaineth ay veritie, becauſe the veritie is but one, whilk may be maid maire clear and plaine, not changed in the contraire. But things appertining to maners, ciuil diſcipline, commoune policie, and ceremonies, becauſe they touch oftētimes but ſingulaire mens actions, or certaine contrayes &amp; perſonnes,

or els ar maid by reaſon of the tym; not onlie may they be changed, the circumſtances being takin away, but ſome tym of neceſſitie man be changed, except men wilfullie wuld tyn all: of whilk things S. Aug. may be underſtād: for it is certaine he culd not vnderſtand of mattres of faith, ſeing in his dayes there was but tw a general concels halden (except ye wil compt the cōcel halden by the Apoſtles at Ieruſalem for one) the firſt of Nice, and the firſt of Conſtātinople, whilk with one cōſent ar eſtimed to be without errour, &amp; ſo culd not receaue correction the an, frome the other. Thridlie it is to be notted that we vnderſtand the only concluſions, whilk ar takin in the general cōcels, &amp; not al things whilk ar dōne or ſaid during the tyme the concels haldeth, as in diſputes and conference; whilk things procedeth of men, and may

therfore be conioyned with errour: and ſo can ſerue for na argument agains our ſentence. Althoght the matter requireth an maire ample diſcourſe (if our intention haid bein to expone this ſubiect at lenth) yet this may ſerue for the preſent.
            But or I paſſe farther I wald pray yow not to miſtak me in my former diſcourſe (for I ſee many miſtaken in the ſame matter) as if I wald thruſt doune, and tread vnder foot, or diminish the authoritie of the holie ſcriptures, by hauing recourſe to the kirk in ſeiking the true ſence of thē: we acknawlege them baith in equall dignitie, veritie &amp; certaintie, becauſe they ar baith of the holie ſpirit, hauing their vertue and force of him, as the Ambaſſadour and Ambaſſede or cōmiſſion of the King or prince wha ſendeth them. The an derogateth no thing to the other: for if there be

anie thing obſcure in the cōmiſſion, why may we not ask the Ambaſſadours iudgment without anie preiudice of his commiſſion? or rather as appertining to him, why shal we not ask his iudgment? for the lettres often times ar verie ſchorte cōtining ſommerlie the matter, who is maire ample declaration is referred to the Ambaſſadour, wha for that cauſe is ſent with lettres of credit, he otherwayes not being neceſſaire, becauſe the lettres might do all, except they might not authoriz them ſelfs.
            The kirk is Gods Ambaſſadour ſent to declaire his will, hauing the ſcriptures for lettres of commiſſion and credet, &amp; that in maiſt ample for me; as we haue ſchawen before: why shal not hir voice be hard before al others in declairing the true meaning of hir commiſſion? shal I ask at anie other why shee was ſent? The kirk &amp; the

ſcriptures ar twa lauful ſiſters of one father, none of thē ſuld be caſſin out, Alterius ſic poſcit opēres &amp; cōiurat amicè. Therefor Sanct Auguſtin ſayeth, To. 7. con. Creſc. lib. 1 cap. 33. that we keip the veritie of the ſcriptures, when we do that whilk is approued by the hail kirk, whome we ſee ſo weal recōmended to ws by the authoritie of the ſame ſcriptures, as that whilk can not deceaue ws, becauſe it is the holie writ. So without anie preference we proue the ſcriptures by the kirk, and by hir alſo the true ſence of them, as the cōmiſſion and the intelligence therof, is authorized by the Ambaſſadour.
            IESVS CHRIST proued him ſelf to be the true Meſſias promiſſed to the Iewes, and that by the prophetes and law: becauſe all things war compleet in him, that war foreſpokin by them to be in the true Meſſias. The ſame was donne by the Apoſtles and

is donne now euerie day agains the Iewes: yet it is not to be concluded that the prophetes and law ar preferred to our Lord. It is inough that the witnes be of ſufficient credet and authoritie with the parties. If any man refuſe this dignitie to the kirk, I wil pray him pardon me, if I ſay he doeth that whilk Satan deſyreth maiſt: for he laboreth to tak away the three thing is whilk onlie doeth aſſure ws of our Maiſter &amp; Lord IESVS CHRIST, to wit, the kirk, ſcriptures and miracles: whilk may be eaſelie ſeine: for the kirk being eſtimed à liar, &amp; worthie of na credet, what can be thoght of the ſcriptures &amp; miracles, whilk we knaw by the kirk only: but if the kirk be (as shee ſuld) of ſufficient authoritie with al true chiſtiās, thois thinges can not be called in doubt. And why ſuld not hir depoſition be hard, or rather hir iudgement

receaued, in whatſomeuer mater of religion, as à thing appertining iuſtlie to hir, and whilk shee may better knaw then any other, by reaſon of the ſtrait alliance betwixt hir head and ſpouſe IESVS CHIRST and hir? Shal euerie man knaw the will of the Lord, and ſenſe of his cō
               mandements, &amp; his deare ſpouſe onlie shalbe ignorant? Then in vaine heth he kiſſed hir with the kiſſe of Can. 1. 1. his mouth: in vaine heth he putte his left hand vnder hir head, and with his right hād in vaine heth he embraced hir. in vain heth he broght hir in 2. 6. his chalmers, if any man hes greatter priuiledge then shee; whilk muſt be, if euerie man ſuld tak that, whilk he think is good and true, and not that whilk the kirk thinketh &amp; declareth good &amp; true. And in very deed, neane of thes new factiouſe ſectes can haue credet till they haue perſnaded their

auditours that the ſpouſe of our Lord is an vnworthy lear. O blaſphemouſe toungis, and foolish hearars, wha ſo rashlie geueth credet, to an thing of it ſelf ſo incredible, &amp; ſo perniſiouſe when it is receaued. Chriſt cōmandeth ws to hear the kirk, Knox and Caluin forbeddeth ws, &amp; wil, we follow only the ſcriptures, that is, theirs or out awin iudgement. Suld it be doubted to whom we ſuld here obey? I man on force receaue the iudge ordonat by the prince, and not to conſtitute my ſelf, or anie other in that place, for that war à cryme of laeſmaieſtie, and worthie of à maiſt ſeuere punition to ſerue for exemple to other preſumptiouſe perſonnes.
            Now if we ſuld preferre the kirk to the ſctiptures (whilk we do not, althoght we preferre hir to priuat mens interpretation forged now of new, whilk when we contemne and

reiect, they deceptfully alledge ws to miſpriſe the ſcriptures) wha culd iuſtlie be offended with ws, ſeing shee is the ſpouſe of our Lord &amp; Maiſter, and the ſcriptures the cōtract of mariage betwixt them? wha doubteth but the ſpouſe is to be preferred to the contract of mariage? Mairouer the ſcriptures at maid for the kirk, and not the kirk for the ſcriptures: The ſabboth vvas maid for man, and not man for 
               Marc. 2. 27 
               the ſabboth, ſayeth the Lord. And alſo the kirk was before the ſcriptures, and shalbe efter them. for the kirk triomphāt shal haue no neid of theis memories and directions, hauing the plenitude of al knawledge &amp; veritie in the contēplation of him, in whom can be no ignorance, in cuius lumine videbimus lumen: ſatiabimur enim cùm apparuerit eius gloria. And laſt of al, our Maiſter &amp; Lord died for the kirk, &amp; not for the ſcriptures: the pryce ſuld

mak the matter maire preciouſe. Wherfor shee man haue ſome prerogatiue, ſeing shee laiketh nothing that the ſcriptures hes, and heth manie things whilk nowayes can be attribute to the ſcriptures? here I may ſay with S. Auguſtin Me piget eam 
               To. de vnitate Eccleſ. cap. 10. (Eccleſiam) commendare Verbis meis, &amp; haereticos non pudet eam oppugnare verbis ſuis. I am in paine to praiſe hir (to wit the kirk) by my Vvords: and heretiks ar not ashamed to aſſault hir vvith their vvords. But it may be asked ſeing it is ſo, to what end ſerueth the ſcriptures? ſuffer me to vſe à familiare exemple to declaire, &amp; expone à difficill and obſcure matter: we ſee by daylie experiēce the blind (notwithſtanding he haue à guyd, on whom he dependeth and in whome he truſteth) ſeek for à ſtaff by moyen of his guyd, wherby he may be maire habill to follow him ouer high montaines

and rockes, riuers and myres, ſaue him ſelf frome ſtokes &amp; ſtonnes in the way, &amp; precepices or heughes beſydes the way, &amp; defend him ſelf from bytting of dogges wher he shal paſſe. The kirk (wha not ans in the ſcriptures is cōpared to the moune, and to à body) of hir ſelf blind, hauing the light and ſight of hir ſunne and head IESVS CHRIST, hes for hir guyd the holy ſpirit, by whois moyen shee hes the ſtaff of the ſcriptures, wherby shee in following hit guyd &amp; leader ſurmonteth maire eaſelie the high montaines of ſpiritual &amp; ſupernatural difficulties, &amp; rockes of naturall ſubtilities, paſſeth ouer the deape riuers of tribulation and perſecution, and myres of vyce, ſaueth hir ſelf frome ſtomling ſtockes and ſtonnes of this preſent lyf, and precipices of ſchiſme and hereſie, not ſtanding to go the ſtraght way for

the ſclandrous townges of the one or the other. This is donne to hald ws in exercice of al vertuouſe humilitie and good actions: God doeth nothing without good and iuſt reaſon: Sed qui ſcrutator eſt maieſtatis opprimetur à gloria. This ſtaffe whilk our mother hes receaued of hir guyd ſuld nather be violentlie nor craftelie taken frome hir, to abuſe or beat hir▪ it is good in hir hand, to whois vſe it was prepared; It is violence and ſpoliation, if it be found any other wher: It appertineth onlie to hir and hirs: as geuen for hir ſeruice. Other men hes no part by iuſt tytle.
            And to conclud this diſput of perpetual veritie in the kirk (for that is my principal motiue to ſeak to the kirk) it can not be thought with good reaſon that God hes ſuffered his kirk &amp; wealbeloued ſpouſe, to whom he hes maid ſo many great &amp; notable promiſes,

geuen ſo high titils, and honored with the mariage &amp; death of his onlie ſonne, hes ſuffered (I ſay) his kirk to perish in hir chyldhead and firſt age, for laik to haue cōtinued in hir the lyf of vetitie, whilk hes beine loſſed ay ſince the Apoſtles days, if we wil beleue ſome men. Shal we not rather think that God is merciful without repentence, and conſtant in his liberal promiſes; and that ſic peſtilent opinions ar inuented onlie by preſumptiouſe braines, who is vaine imaginations culd haue no place if the kirk keippeth hir authoritie, whilk they wald glaidlie ouerthraw to eſtablesh and authoriz their nowelties, by the whilk, they wald haue ws beleue that God is à lear: For what is it other to cal &amp; think God à lear, then to ſay that nather is it, nor can it be true, whilk he hes ſaid and promiſt. S. Auguſtin diſputane aganiſt

the Donatiſts of the greatnes &amp; amplitude of the kirk, maketh almaiſt the lyk concluſion. Quaſi aliud ſit prophetiam crimine falſitatis arguere, quàm 
               de vnitate Eccleſiae c 9. Tom. 7. 
               dicere quae pręnunciauit non poſſe cōpleri: hoc eſt enim dicere, non eſſe prophetiam, ſed pſeudoprophetiam. As if it vvar an other thing to accuſe the prophecie of falshed then to ſay that, that vvhilk it haid foreſpoken culd not becompleit: for that vvar als metkel as to ſay that it vvar not à prophecie, but à fals prophecie, or lee.
            
            Becauſe I haue maid mention now ſindry tymes of S. Auguſtin, &amp; ſome other ancient writars, and wald be ouer prolixt, if I ſuld citte al the places whilk may be propre here, I will pray the learned reader tak the paines to ſee and read diligentlie S. Auguſtin de vtilitate credendi ad Honoratum, &amp; de vnitate Eccleſiae contra Petiliani Donatiſtae epiſtolam. &amp; Tertulian de praeſcriptionibus aduerſus haereticos.
               
to thir may be adioyned S. Cyprian de vnitate Eccleſiae, and Vincentius Lirinenſis aduerſus prophanas nouitates.
            
            I knaw ſindry wald be glaid to read theis buikes wha can not haue them; to who is iuſt deſyr I wald willinglie ſatisfie, if I haid the moyen. In the mein tyme, if I shal gather out ſome proprieties, whilk the ancients hes notted in the true kirk, &amp; paſtours, and alſo fals kirk &amp; fals paſtours, no man iuſtlie can be offended.
            
               
                  
                     1 Antiquitas.
                     1 Nouitas.
                  
                  
                     2 Vnitas
                     2 Schiſmata.
                  
                  
                     3 Conſenſus &amp; concordia.
                     3 Diſſenſio ac diſcordia.
                  
                  
                     4 Multitudo idē ſentientiū
                     
                     4 Paucitas idem ſentientiū
                     
                  
                  
                     5 Amplitudo per orbē ter tatum.
                     5 Anguſtia in angulis.
                  
                  
                     6 Maiorum reuerentia
                     6 Maiorum, etiam ſuorum contemptus.
                  
                  
                     7 Majeſtas etiā regibus ipſis venetanda &amp; culta.
                     7 obſcuritas, vicinis vix cognita, ſuis neglecta.
                  
                  
                     8 Paſtorum ſucceſ
                           •
                        io.
                     8 Sibiſuccedere &amp; in ſe deſinere
                  
                  
                     9 Perpetuitas.
                     9 Nupera origo.
                  
                  
                     10 Viſibilitas
                     10 Inuiſibilitas.
                  
                  
                     11 Veriras.
                     11 Error.
                  
                  
                     12 Conſtantia in eadem patr
                           •
                        mque doctrina.
                     12 Inconſtantia in ſua patr
                           •
                        mque doctrina.
                  
                  
                     13 Firmitas contra omnes omni
                           •…
                         hoſtium incurſus
                     13 Infirmitas, aeui breuitate cognita.
                  
                  
                     
                        
14 In lia quae ad nominis Chriſtiani propagatione pertinent, diligentia.
                     14 In ijſdem vel propagandis inertia, l vel euertendis peruerſ
                           •••…
                         quis deijcit, non erigit.
                  
                  
                     15 Doctrinae vniuerſalitas.
                     15 Priliata opmio.
                  
                  
                     16 victoriae cōtra hoſtes heteticos &amp; ſchiſmaticos.
                     16 Infoelices, etiam contra fubs pugnae.
                  
                  
                     17 Authoritas ſecure audienda quia, ſine errore.
                     17 Nullum ad firmandos animos pondus, quia ag
                        
                           •
                        oſci
                           •
                        ſe errori obnoxiō.
                  
                  
                     18 Humanitas &amp; modeſtia
                     18 Superbia &amp; iactantia pluſqam Thraſonica.
                  
                  
                     19 Otdo &amp; diſciplina.
                     19 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                         &amp; f
                           ••
                        ilis conuer ſatio.
                  
                  
                     20 Certa fides &amp; minime dubia.
                     20 Perpetua inquiſitio cut verius fluctuatio.
                  
                  
                     21 Fidei regula Chriſtianis Eccleſia, quia Dei tabernaculum in ſole poſitum &amp; vitis frugifera Domini manu plantata.
                     21 Apud haeretidos ſibi quiſque regula eſt, quia in ſen ſu ſuo latebtas quae
                           ••••…
                        , vi ſarmēta inutilia à vite reſectafacile agnoſcas.
                  
               
            
            I haue put theis twa ranks the one oppoſite to the other, to know what the Miniſters will approue, or improue in anie of them: as to ws, we firmly beleue that the qualities mentionat in the firſt appertineth to the true kirk onlie; and ar found in the Catholik, Apoſtolik Romaine kirk onlie; whilk we conſtantlie beleue to be the true &amp; onlie kirk, becauſe we find neine but hir, to whome ſie

notable promiſes hes beine maid; or in whome they haue beine accomplished, but in hir onlie. Wherfor if the Miniſters wil haue ws to quyt the place where we ar, as being vnfytte for our ſaluation, becauſe the qualities whilk we alledge ar not to be fond in hir, they man ſchaw ws an other wher we shal find them, ſeing they ar altogather neceſſaire to be found in the ſpouſe of IESVS CHRIST: for otherwayes ather will they trauell in vaine, or we chenge lyk fooles, changing for an worſe, and leuing à kirk, whilk (as we ar ſurelie perſuaded) is ſure &amp; can not erre, to follow à cōpanie that they them ſelfs, wha inuiteth ws, aſſureth ws to be vnſure, affirming that it is ſubiect to errour in ſo far, that God him ſelf can not keip it therfra, at leeſt hes not keiped it, not withſtāding of his many fold promiſes. Doubtles whaſoeuer perſuadeth

ws that the houſe, where he wald haue ws enter, is not ſure: conſequentlie perſuadeth ws (by preſenting ws the danger whilk may arryue) not to enter therein, except he be à fooll or think ws fooles. It shal not be needful here that the Miniſters accuſe or ſpeek euill of any other man: but rather ſpeek good of them ſelfs, prouyding they proue it weall, ſchawing that they haue the kirk Dominam &amp; matrem gentium indued with the notable and excellent qualities required in the true kirk, and can not be found but amonge them, and theirs. It will not content ws (if we be cairefull, as we ſuld be, of our ſaluation) to ſay that our kirk is euil, they man proue that their awin is good. I ſay this becauſe in place to proue themſelfs to haue the kirk▪ they raill aganis the vyce of the Catholiks, as if our ſinnes maid them à good right, or

they them ſelfs war without ſinne. Many hes left the Catholik kirk, &amp; yet hes not followed them, but hes taken an other partie. Many alſo hes fled frome viciouſe Catholiks, &amp; hes entered amōges maire viciouſe Proteſtants: for I hear of nein, as yet, wha ar become better men, for the leuing of ws, or being out of our kirk. I call their cōſcience &amp; our whol contray to be witnes. I am ſure that Luther &amp; Caluin firſt inuenters or renewers of this religion, acknawledgeth that the warld is becom worſe ſince the comming of their new Euangell. I doubt not but they knaw what is Caluins opinion here anent ſeing the eſtimation they haue of him. Luther ſpeeketh plainlie. Mumdus indies ex hac doctrina fit peior: homines vno antea, nunc ſeptem diabolis obſidentu
                     •
                  , diabolus nunc plena cohorte homines inuadit, vt ſub clara Euangelij luce multò ſint quàm
               
               antea ſub Papatu auariores, aſtutiores, fraudulentiores, crudeliores, libidinoſiores, procaciores ac peiores. The vvordle becommeth daylie more vvicked by this doctrine: before men vvar beſieged by one deuill, novv they ar beſeiged by ſeuen. The deuill novv doeth aſſaile men vvith an hail band of deuils, ſo that vnder the clear light of the Euangell men ar become meakel maire couuetous, maire craftie, maire deceptfull, maire cruell, maire lecherous, maire shamleſſe and maire vvicked, then before vnder the Papiſtrie. An other of theis good brethrine ſayeth almaiſt the ſame, Vt totus mundus agnoſcat eos 
               Smidelinus 
               non eſſe Papiſtas, ne
                     •
                    bonis operibus quicquam fidere, illorum operum nullum exercent penitus; itiunij lo
                     ••
                   comeſſationibus &amp; perpota
                     •
                  ionibus nocte dieque vacant▪ vbi pauperibus benigne facere oportebat, eos deglutiunt &amp; excoriant▪ precationes vertunt in iuramenta, blaſphemias &amp; diuini nominis execrationes, ádque tam perditè,
               
               vt Chriſtus ne ab ipſis quidē Turcis hodie tantopere blaſphemetur. Demū pro humilitate regnat paſſim ſuperbia, faſtus, elatio; atque hoc vniuerſum vitae genus, ab illis Euangelicum dicitur inſtitutum. That all the vvarld may knavv them not to be Papiſts, nor truſt in good vvorks, they exerciſe none at al of theis vvorks, in place of faſting they imploy their tym night &amp; day in extraordinaire eating and drinking. vvhere they ſuld haue behaued thē ſelfes liberallie and bountefullie tovvards the poore, they deuoore them, &amp; as it vvar pluckes of the skinne of them: they change their prayers in oothes, blaſphemies, and execrations of Gods name, and that ſo deſperatlie, that Chriſt is not this day ſo greatlie blaſphemed amonges the Toorkes them ſelfs. finallie in place of humilitie doeth regne throgh all, pryd, diſdaine, preſumption. and they cal al this ſort and maner of lyf à trade euangelik. If thes men ſayeth true, the matter is euill mended,

and we haue lytill occaſion to chāge. I may truely ſay that they haue maid our men worſe, &amp; hes not mended their awin. That we may ſay with Tertulian that ſtantibus ruinam non ia 
               de proſcriptionibus ad uerſus haer. 
               centibus eleuationem operantur. If true paſtours shuld be knawen by their warks, I leue yow to iudge what shal be thoght of theis new Eccleſiaſtical order &amp; new kirk where ſo few good fructes ar to be found by their awin confeſſion. It is an euil breuing that is not good in the newing: I think the Miniſters of Scotlād wald ſay als meikel of their flock, if they wald lay to their cōſcience the hand, that they haue laid to ſo meikell kirk geare ſo wrangouſlie. At this tyme I will ſay no mair, but (abyding their anſwer) pray God grant to ws al, for his infinite mercies cauſe, his trueth &amp; grace that we may knaw his veritie &amp; follow his command. And this meikell

touching the firſt head, and reaſons whilk moueth me to ſeek &amp; cleame to the kirk and offer to acknawledge the Miniſters, if they haue hir. now to the nixt article.
            
               SI IN VIRIDO QUID IN ARIDO
            
         
         
            
               
THE houſe of God, that is, the kirk being found, I muſt adreſſe my ſelf to them, wha hes the power &amp; charge to lette me in; wha hes the keyes; wha may not onlie ſchaw me the infinite treaſures of Gods goodnes towardes ws with his manyfold mercies and grace, but alſo will, and may by vertue of their charge mak me partaker thereof being impted in the tree of lyf by participation of the holie ſacraments and knawledge of the true faith, &amp; receauing of the ſame, that is, I muſt go to the true &amp; lauful paſtours and prelats, whome I man knaw, not by the execution of that charge (albeet that be alſo required) but by the power they haue receaued to execute ſic à charge. For it is not à certaine and ſolide proofe, that anie man is à lauful magiſtrat, if

it may beſchawē that he heth geuen out ſindry ſentences and decreates; or that he heth cauſed execute ſindly men to death (for thos thinges ar donne oftentymes by wrangouſe &amp; tyranicall vſurpairs) but the power he hes to pronunce and execute decreats, is required: otherwayes the fact ſuld mak the magiſtrat, and not the authoritie, whilk is contraire to al good reaſon; ſo I ask not now, wha taketh vpon them the offices &amp; functions of paſtours, but whahes that power, that is, wha hes the lauful power &amp; miſſion, whilk is ſo neceſſaire in the paſtours of the kirk, that althoght anie man ſuld haue the doctrine als pure as the A poſtles them ſelfs, with lyk knawledge; yet ſuld he not be receaued as à paſtour, except he haue the vocation of them, wha heth the power to gif it him, nemo poteſt in aliū conferre quodipſe non habet. I

am aſſured that the Miniſters wil not ſuffer within their iuriſdiction anie man to ſtart wp at his awin hand of his particulaire and priuat authority making aſſembles apart, althoght he ſuld preach the ſame doctrine, and adminiſtrat the ſacramentes in the ſam fashion grounded on the cōfeſſion of faith, now receaued by the hail Miniſterie of Scotland; whilk confeſſion they force, or wald force al men to ſubſcribe. The puritie of the doctrine wald not ſtope them to cōdemne him as à ſeditious ſchiſmatik ſeing he haid no authoritie, or (albeet he haid the authoritie) if he laiketh the vnity required in the kirk: for doubtles althoght he haid the vocation als lauful, as they can gifhim, yet becauſe of his ſchiſme, he ſuld be eſteemed to haue iuſtlie loſſed it, albeet in other things he keepeth the ſam doctrine in al reſpeckes; for the

nature of the ſchiſme is ſic, that as the diuiſion of anie member frome the body, bringeth certaine death &amp; priuation of lyf (whilk can not be haid but in, and with the haill) ſo doeth ſchiſme in the kirk, to him wha is devyded frome the kirk. The Donatiſts may ſerue for exemple, wha in the begining war but ſchiſmatiks, yet at laſt by there diuiſion did fall in corruption of doctrine and become heretikes; ewen as the member whilk is cut of, being depriued of the lyf (whilk it haid in the whol body) of neceſſitie at laſt man rote. Siclyk Lucifer bishope, before catholik, by his ſchiſme did loſſe him ſelf, althoght he did approue the concel of Nice in all poinctes; how deteſtable is the cryme of ſchiſme before God, may eaſelie be iudged by Core Dathan &amp; Abiron, who is punition was maire fearful and terrible, nor theis, wha

maid &amp; adored the golden calf, notwithſtanding of their idolatrie.
            But to retourne to our propos, it is altogether requiſed, that the true doctrine &amp; lawful power be ioyned together in thes, wha wald cōmand and rule in the houſe of God: the law maketh ws al ſubiect &amp; equal: the power and authoritie (whilk ſuld be geuen by him, wha hes it) maketh the diſtinction &amp; difference betwixt ws, and geueth charge to an aboue the otheris: for what domination or cō
               mandement haid S. Peter S. Paul &amp; the reſt of the Apoſtles aboue the kirk of God, till they receaued that charge &amp; authoritie of IESVS CHRIST him ſelf, to whome appertined the ſouuetaine domination. for al being his, no man culd command except he haid receaued power &amp; commiſſion of him: Nor yet anie man obey to an other, onles he war aſſured of

the commiſſion. We ſee that Princes punisheth ſeuerelie, but iuſtlie and neceſſairlie, ſic as tak on them to cō
               mand without charge: for of theis vſurpations (if they be ſuffered) commeth oppen rebellion againiſt the prince, oppreſſion of the ſubiects, &amp; wrak of the hail cōmoune wealth. Al is not donne at the firſt inſtant, piece &amp; piece men proceideth baith in vertue and vyce, nemo reprenté fit turpiſſimus. there be certaine degrees to that high wark of plaine rebellion &amp; outcaſting of the lauful and ſouueraine magiſtrat: he wha maketh the firſt ſlope, gaueth the firſt blaw to his prince. Wherefor if the beginnar ſuld fill wp with his awen dead body the braich that he haid maid, he ſuld find few followers: the prince ſparing the firſt inuiteth others, and at laſt is conſtrained to punish many, wha wald not, at the beginning punish

one: Crudelis eſt humanitas, quae dum vni parcit, multos perdit.
            
            In this general, I doubt not but the Miniſters and I wil agree verie eaſely: For I ſee Beza one of their brethring auoueth that none ſuld cōmand, or denotis accleſiae haue charge in the houſe of God except ſic as ar ſent by God, whilk ſending he wil haue rueled according to the order whilk God him ſelf hes eſtableshed in his kirk, and thinketh it nowayes lauful to anie man to violat this order: yet that our Lord and Maiſter is not bound thereto, but may diſpone on the houſe of his father as he thinketh beſt, notwithſtading of this order; if in caſe confuſion be entred in the place of order, that is, if the ordinaire vocation eſtablished by him ſelf in the perſonnes of the Apoſtles &amp; their ſucceſſours, shal faill &amp; inlaik (whilk, as we haue prouen before, can not be) for laick

of true paſtours; he may ſend extraordinairly and immediatly paſtours to guyd rule and gowerne his houſe and feed his flock. I wil weal it be ſo (for namaſuld or can deny that ſouerane power to IESVS CHRIST, althoht it be brought in here vpon an abſurd ſuppoſition, if true paſtours inlaik) prouyding there be no interruption in the gowernement of the kirk, that is, prouyding the kirk neuer want lauful paſtours neceſſaire for the edification of Chriſts myſtical body, whilk is but one, &amp; can not ſuffer ſo euident cōuulſion: for by diuiſion it man be twa bodyes. whilk muſt be if the extraordinaire ſucced not incōtinent to the ordinaire, when he shall inlaik. For we haue ſchawen before that Chriſts kingdome man be perpetual: it muſt alſo be granted of neceſſity that the true kirk can no mait wat the lauful paſtours, then she may

want the trueth it ſelf. For the true doctrine mā be in the true doctours &amp; paſtours or els it can not be haid in this warld. S. Paul ioyneth thes twa ſucceſſions together, as things whilk can not be ſeparat the one frome the other, to wit, the word, of whilk commeth faith, &amp; the paſtour wha is ſent with charg to preach the word hovv 
               Rom. 1014 
               shal they beleue in him of vvhō they haue not hard? &amp; hov shal they hear vvithout àpreacher? but hovv shal they preach onles they be ſent? we may ſee the band and connection whilk S. Paull maketh here, the faith be hearing of the word proceding frome the preacher or paſtour, wha hes gotten lauful power being ſent for that effect by him wha might ſend him. The firſt, to wit faith, pertineth to the ſucceſſion of doctrine whilkwear obliſt to beleue. The reſt appertineth to the ſucceſſiō of perſonnes: the faith commeth by

hearing, whilk can not be without ſpeeking (I mean ordinairly) &amp; ſpecking requireth à preacher, wha can not be lauful without miſſion. wherfor as the kirk militant is perpetuall (for God neuer wanteth his kirk) ſo hes shee perpetuallie true and lauful paſtours to gowerne hir; becauſe without them, there can be no kirk, ſeing that faith is requiſed, whilk cō
               meth by hearing, as ſaid is.
            Lat ws then ſpeek of this vocation, ſeing it is ſo neceſſaire that without it the charge can not be weal donne. I demand therefor wha ſent the Miniſters to preach in the kirk of God? wha hes geuen them that power vpō the Chriſtian people, to nurish the good and obedient by preaching, to punish &amp; cut of the wicked &amp; diſobedient by excōmunication? I haue ſaid alreddy (&amp; it is true) that the law maketh ws al equal: the cōmiſſion or power

meketh the difference, in gauing authority to ſome to cōmand, others remaining within the compas of obedience to beleue and do as they ar teached and commanded.
            This power and vocation, according de notis recleſiae &amp; cpiſt. Theologic. 5. to Bezais diſtinction, is ather ordinaire or extraordinaire. The ordinaire lauful (ſayeth he) conſiſteth in certain rules ordinat by God, whilk ar three: to wit Examination &amp; tryal of doctrine &amp; maners: Electiō maid by the kirk: And Impoſitiō of hands or ordinatiō. Lat ws apply thes three rules to the vocatiō of Knox, Caluin or Luther: for if it be not found lauful &amp; iuſt in the firſt authour, in the reſt it can not be better; Quod ab initio non valuit, tractu temporis conualeſcere non poteſt. The langar that vſurpation leſteth, the worſe. Now to ſay that anie of them haid their calling of the Catholik &amp; Romainekirk (as

ſome do is ſay, when they ar preſſed to ſchaw their halding) it is no thing to the propos; for the Miniſters, to lat the warld vnderſtand that they will not ſerue them ſelfs therewith, will haue al men refuſe &amp; abiure al right they may haue by the Paip and kirk of Rome: as may be ſeine in their confeſſion of faith. And Caluin with the reſt of the Miniſters of Geneua wald not ſuffer the Bishopes of Troy and Neuers (wha leeſing the Catholik kirk flaid to them) in any wayes to preach til they haid abiured al power receaued before, &amp; taken of new their commiſſion and authoritie of the Miniſters, becauſe in their opinion the former was not lauful. And in veritie the vocation comming of the kirk of Rome can ſerue them to no propos. For ather it was good or not: If it was good, doubles they haue loſt it by their ſchiſme and rebellion,

ſeing they haue left the kirk, of whome they haid their vocation. The lyf can not be communicatted not extended to members ſeparated from the whol body. No man gaueth power to be abandonatted, nor to arme men &amp; rebelle agains him ſelf, nor to be caſſe out of his a win place: Princes gaueth power to inferiour magiſtrats, but retineth ay ful power to them ſelfs, to diſcharge or punish all rebellious perſonnes whatſoeuer degree or preheminance they haue within the realme. the higher place the greater fal, &amp; greuouſer paines to follow therevpon. Potentes potenter tormēta patientur. If it was not good it was null of it ſelf, of no valour in the gauer, &amp; ſo nul in the receauer on force they man think ſo, if they wil abyd at the firſt principe of their religion, to wit, that the Paip is the great Antichriſt: whilk ground if it war

true (as it is maiſt falſe) it behoved their vocation to be null: for what cometh of the Antichriſt (wha shalbe as it war Satans eldeſt ſonne) muſt come of Satan: as whatſoeuer commeth of IESVS CHRIST commeth of God, becauſe he is Gods eldeſt &amp; onlie naturall ſonne. Wherfore hauing no ordinaire calling of the Catholik Romaine kirk, it followeth that they haue neane at al. for if they haid anie of the Catholik kirk (as in deed ſom of them haid being prieſts) they loſt it by their ſchiſme, and can haue neane from any other, but from them ſelfs. And ſo I may ſay of him whaſoeuer shalbe firſt amongs them, that whilk Optatus Mileuitanus ſayeth of Victor firſt bishope of the Donatiſtes: Erat ibi filius ſine patre, tyro ſine principe, diſcipulus ſine magiſtro, ſequens ſine antecedente, inquilinus ſine domo, hoſpes ſine hoſpitio, paſtor ſine grege.
               
               Epiſcopus ſine populo. Ther vvas there à ſonne vvithout à father, à nevv ſouldier vvithout à cōmander or ruler, à diſciple vithout à maiſter, à follovver vvithout any to go before, à tenant vvithout an houſe, an hoſte vvithout à lodging, à paſtour vvithout à flocke, à Bishope vvithout à people. For the three cōditions required by Beza in à lauful paſtour &amp; ordinair calling can not be found in any of them, if they be cōſidered out of the Catholik Romaine kirk. Lat wstak anie of them, whatſoeuer he be, and we shal ſee it to be ſo: For as to the examination &amp; tryal of doctrine, wha culd exame him, ſeing he haid no man aboue him, nor of higher power. And farther that proue culd not be maid vpon the firſt, ſeing he was the finderout of the doctrine, he preached: wherfor it was vnknawē to others, ſo they culd not exame him there vpon. ſure I am that they

wil not aſcribe this examination to the people ſeing the people ſuld be teached and examinated, not teach and examine: but of this ſchortlie at maire lenth. As to the maners, I find not that a nie of them war angels, nather any of thes wha hes followed efter them, I ſay no farther, I excuſe not the faults &amp; vyce of the cleargie; Iudas might tyn the Apoſtolat, he culd not defyl it, meekel leſſe tak it away or mak it inutile in others.
            The ſecond is the libre &amp; free election of the perſone examinat, maid with cōſent &amp; knawledge of the kirk where he fuld exercice that charge &amp; function. This can not be found in the firſt and ring leaders of this new kirk: for what kirk culd choiſe them ſeing they war before their kirk: for they wha leued in thos dayes knew no ſie doctrine, nor doctours; and ſwa nather culd exame the doctrine

nor elect the perſonnes, whois opinions war ſo new at that tyme, that they war not yet hard of.
            But ye will ſay that their doctrine was maiſt ancient of it ſelf, althoght not knawē ſo publikly. I anſwer that it can not be ancient nor auld whilk cōtinueth not fromethe begining; for that whilk dieth als ſon as it is borne, mereth not the name of auld aage, quod naſcens moritur, ſenectutis nomen non meretur. ye may weal ſay it is lang ſince it hes beine (if perchance it hes beine manie yeares before our aage) but it is not lang ſince it is. for being doeth include cōtinuation of à thing, whilk they acknawledge not to be in their doctrine, at leeſt publiklie and knawen to the warld. but that whilk is cōfirmed with one ſimple word, may ſufficientlie be refurted with an other. it was, it was not.
            The thrid qualitie to wit Impoſition

of hands (whilk Caluin acknawledgeth Inſt. lib. 4. cap. 14. ſect. 20. &amp; cap. 19 ſect. 28. &amp; 31. for à ſacrament) shalbe leſſe found in them: for who culd conſecrat or ordaine them paſtours by impoſition of hands, &amp; geue them power to command and rule the kirk of God, ſeing they war the firſt them ſelfis? There culd be neene before them, the ordinair ſucceſſion (as they Caluin in the preface of hs inſtit. and Beza epiſt. theologic. 5. alledge) being altogather perished &amp; loſt. Mairouer it is to be conſiderat that in our contray the impoſition of hands hes beine admitted within thes ſex yeares onlie, to wit, the year of God 1598. and that not without great difficultie and contention, and contraire to the opinion of ſindry of the miniſterie: where I wald glaidlie knaw of whom they receaued impoſition of hands, wha that yeare begane to impone the hands to others. As to the foolish concept of thes that thinketh the commoune people to

haue that power, they ar maire worthy of punition exemplaire as trompettes of ſedition ſubiecting al ſort of magiſtrats to à populair temerity and rage, then worthie of credet or anſwer as honeſt &amp; reaſonable men. out of thes factious boutiques agans the authoritie of lauful Princes and their heritable right ar come Franco-Gallia, Vindiciae contra tyrannos, the peſtilent pāphelet de iure regni apud Scotos, the firſt blaſt of the trompette, &amp; other ſic lyk vnhappie libelles verie cutthrottes of al Princes, that haith good and lauful right to any realme: becauſe ſic iuriſdictions ar, as it war, à ſtrang and mightie brydle to conteene within the compas of reaſonal ſeditious and ambitious ſpirits, of whilks our aage (to our great regrat) hes bein ouer plentiful &amp; abondant, ſomtym vnder one colour ſometym vnder an other. Lykwayes we haue

haid agains the Eccleſiaſtical order within thes 100. yeares, good ſtore of thes beaſie writters, &amp; amōgiſt other we haue found ſome lytil touch in aſſertionibus theologicis, aut veriùs, negationibus aſſertione 2 cacologicis cuiuſdam Britanno-Scoti, qui inconditae plebi ordinationem Eccleſiaſticam (licet in eo parùm ſibi conſtet) committit. The Miniſters (if I be not deceaued) wil not authoriz thes toyes, yea no mair then Beza doeth approue Ramus dreames in religion. Wherefor I will not enter farther therein, but wil retourn to thes wha ſo vnreuerantlie doeth traict their princes, as he does prelats. Thes men thē muſt ſuffer me to ſay that the ſubiect wha wil haue no ſuperiour ſauīg ſic as he finds good &amp; to his guſt, or ſic as he may change when he liſt, ſuld feare to find the gibbet to his ſuperiour or hell to his habitacle, non other place iuſtlie reſting for him wha

will not content him ſelf with his awen place, that is, whilk he is borne to, or whilk his Prince of his proper motiue avanceth him to. shal the cō
               tentement or miſcontentemēt of the vnconſtant multitude, or of anie factious and ſeditious head be à rule in ſo great and weghtie à matter? shall ſic foolish braines be the ſquare of al good and lauful governement? Thir maximes ſet doune to allure the people, ar to deſtroy baith the people &amp; Princes, and commeth of them, who beyond their merite looketh for avā
               cement to honours, to the whilks otherwayes they culd not atteine; ſo whill they aſpire thereto, they conſpyre agains their Prince and Maiſter. Certainelie as the inferiour magiſtrat is anſwerable to his Prince not to his inferiour, ſo the Prince is anſwerable to God, and not to his ſubiect. Otherwayes how often

ſoeuer thir trōpettes of ſedition ſuld blaw, we ſuld be als often in pain of Prince and commoune wealth, &amp; in place of one pretended tyranne, we ſuld haue ten thowſand, wha iuſtlie might be called tyrannes. Thir fyrbrands doeth rail &amp; cry out agans the lauful Princes, to put in that place many tribunes of the people, in hope to haue their part, as others, wha iniuſtlie ar entred there. for why may they not ſay with the naghrie woman, nec mihi nec tibi, ſed diuidatur, ſeing they 3. Reg. 3. 26 haue no iuſt part therin? But the iuſt poſſeſſour can not approue ſo perniſious à diuiſion. If we laiketh exemples of our awin, ther might be foūd out ouermanie in other realmes. But by what right (I pray yow) shal the ſeditious ſubiect (for na other wil vſurpe that place) be aboue his laufull Prince, to ſit as iudge on his eſtait, lyf, &amp; honour? Who is amonges ws that

wald willinglie ſuffer to be cōmanded (what ſal I ſay iudged?) by his awē ſeruant, by whome he war ignominiouſly accuſed? It is not lauful to the partie to ſit as iudge, nor to be witnes in à priuat mans cauſe: what shall it be then in Princes? We laugh and ieſt when we ſee anie priuat man that thinketh him ſelf monarche of the haill warld, as being ſicke of à pleaſant imagination and phantaſie, without any mans hourt or dommage. But it is na ſport nor bourd to ſee the furious multitude mel it ſelf with the eſtait, lyf, &amp; honour of their Prince, where many thowſands ar oppreſſed vnder colour of the comoune wealth and libertie, whilks doubtles ar loſt whē they fall in the hands of the multitude. If the Prince wald force ws to do anie thing agains God and good reaſon, we ſuld arme our ſelfis with patience, and not with rebellion, that

is, we ſuld follow Gods command; &amp; if the Prince wald be ſo rigourous as to punish ws therefore, we, to the exē
               ple of the A poſtles &amp; primitiue kirk ſuffer it, and not to tak armes againſt him: In patientia veſtra poſſidebitis animas 
               Luc. 21 19. 
               veſtras. In your patience yovv shall poſſeſſe your ſaulles, ſayeth our Lord. what good Chriſtian wald not rather choiſe to be for the trueth à martyre before God, then as à traittour for rebellion execute by men? we may without danger of conſcience ſuffer à wrang, but not do à wrang without danger of cōſcience: It is but by M. Fox new martyrologe that men become martyres for hereſie and rebellion. In the kirk that honour is gifin only to them, wha dieth for the trueth (as in the primitiue kirk) without any ſpot of rebelliō: cauſa martyrē facit, non poena. I wil pas thes opinions be cauſe they require à maire ſcharpe

maner of refutatiō, ſeing they bring with thē ſo many heapes of miſeries, if they be not ſpedelie ſmored in the beginning. For to lay aſyd the commoune &amp; publik calamities, wherein no man can be in ſuretie, often tyms choiſing à new, King we loſſe an auld kingdom. But to retourn to our propos: this ordinatiō of paſtoures culd not com of the people, becauſe at the beginning of this new religion al the people was Catholik, &amp; knew no ſic doctrine nor doctours, &amp; ſo culd not mak thē paſtors wha war firſt actors of this tragedie. Mairouer Beza in his Epſt. theolog. 83. epiſtles ſeimeth nowayes to approue this populaire forme of gowernemēt in the kirk. Wherefore ſeing the firſt Miniſters nather haid Examination, Election nor Ordination, or Impoſition of hands, it may be eaſelie concluded, that they haid no lauful ordinaire calling, and ſo culd not gif any

true vocation or calling to others, becauſe they haid it not them ſelfis.
            Lat ws go forward. the Catholik kirk (ſay they) hes tynt the ordinaire vocation, and they haue found the extraordinaire. We haue tynt one thing, and they haue found an other; it is iuſtly reancōtered with our tinſal. But ſeing they haue not found our gear, we can pretend no right therto: ſo as we pretend no right to their extraordinaire calling, they can pretēd no tytill to our ordinaire, as ſaid is.
            They ar called and ſent extraordinairly (ſay they) to gowern the kirk of God: if their vocation be extraordinair it paſſeth the boūds of the order Apoſtolik: For how can it be Apoſtolik without continuation ſince the Apoſtles, not hauing beginning nor authoritie of their vocation. If the race and ſucceſſion of the Apoſtles be loſſed, why waunt they them

ſelfis to follow the Apoſtles? at leeſt they follow them not in their vocation, and therefore: the tytils and euidents of the Apoſtles can ſerue them for no thing. They muſt ſchaw their new halding, ſeing the ancient tytles ar expyred and rune out; if there reſteth no man hauing the right of the Apoſtles the, Miniſters can not haue it. We muſt ſee their new charters paſſed vnder the great ſeel of IESVS CHRIST marcked with miracles wroght by the holy ſpirit: if they can ſchaw anie ſic thing, it will put them out of trouble, and ws out of doubt, and tak away al ſchadow of excuſe, whilk otherwayes we might iuſtlie pretend for our diſobèdience.
            But in good conſcience may we credet them, wha with their ſimple word wald mak ws beleue that the ancient ſucceſſiō of the Apoſtles is perished? Shal I not think (if that be true) that

the tribe of Leui was mair deare to God, then the ſpiritual poſteritie of the Apoſtles, yea then the poſteritie of IESVS CHRIST him ſelf, out of who is ſeedes mouth, the veritie ſuld Iſa. 59. 21. neuer depart. shal it ſerue for nothing that that wynzard was planted with our Maiſters awin hand, boght with his death, nurished by his Apoſtles, watred with their blood, &amp; with the blood of ſo manie thowſand martyrs, keeped by the aſſiſtence of the holie ſpirit, in the learned and Godlie fathers, &amp; in their poſteritie? Shal the order of Aaron be ſo far preferred to the order of Melchiſedech? the body to the ſpirit, the figure to the veritie, and man to God? Shal the miniſters haue the honour to haue reſtored the kirk, whilk the holie ſpirit by his negligence haid tynt? their onlie hand hes haldē our Lord in his right: Weal, geuing and not granting that

our Maiſter haid tynt his inheritance in this warld for à tyme throgh negligēce of his officers, or rather by their malice &amp; knaverie: he hes caſt them out: he hes placed in their place and charge others, more worthie. Yet or I ſee their letters of cōmiſſion, I wald glaidlie knaw why they war geuen: for it culd not be à light cauſe whilk moued God to geue à new charge. They wil ſay, perchance, to reforme the kirk, &amp; tak away the manifold abuſes that war baith in the doctrine and maners. A iuſt reaſon truelie &amp; à charge worthie of eternal memorie and thankes, and maiſt neceſſaire (if it be true) to be put in execution, for the publik good, ſaluation of many ſauls and (whilk is the principal) for Gods glorie, and he to be praiſed &amp; loued wha doeth his duety in the execution of the ſame: But with what ſinceritie and Godlie dealling it hes

bein fulfilled and accomplished, the miſerable eſtait of our contray may beire witnes: where many hes learned the ſcience of Adam and Eua in eating of the forbidden tree, knawing the good they haue loſt &amp; euill they haue found. and I fear that thes new paſtours hes vſed als litill diſcretion in gowerning mens ſauls as policie in doune caſting the material kirks.
            
               Jntempeſtiuas ſed ſupprime Muſa querelas.
            
            Put the caſe that they war ſent to reform the kirk in doctrine &amp; maners. Thes heauinly medicins then fand, à ſeik perſone before thē, but not dead, to procure whais health they war ſent. why haue they rent this body in peaces, &amp; maid wp ſo many others, ſo different &amp; contrarious euery one to an other, lyk the Cadmeiā brethrin▪ This agrees not with their letter patent, if they haue any: they ſuld not

haue paſſed the boundes of their legation. If they war ſent to reforme the kirk, according to my iudgemēt (I dar not be bald to pronunce anie farther for feare of offence) they ſuld haue remained in the kirk (fugiendo non curantur aegri, ſed medendo) and by vertue of their commiſſion taken away the cauſes of hir ſeeknes and deformities. he wha gaue thē the charg wald haue giuen them the ſtrenth, qui dat velle, dabit &amp; perficere: he wald not haue left them in ſo notable &amp; good interpriſe; they culd not haue laicked moyen nor wiſdom hauing ſo mightie à maiſter. If they feared the peſt, or rather the iuſt punition, I excuſe their flight, yet can not praiſe them, that they choiſed rather to ſeall their doctrine with other mens blood nor with their awin. But to paſſe this extraordinaire ſtoutnes (whilk hes moned them to ryf the kirk in peeces by

ſo many ſindrie ſectes, rather then to ſuffer martyrdome them ſelfis and ſo paſſe to heauin) why did they by their cōmiſſion? they diſcharged not them ſelfis in making an other kirk. To mak à kirk, and reforme or heall à kirk ar diuers things. They muſt acknawledge à double fault, whilk they haue cōmitted, the an in not doing that whilk they war cōmanded, whilk was in reforming the kirk; the other in doing of that whilk they war not commanded, in bulding à kirk. If there was no kirk at all, when they come, their commiſſion was in vaine &amp; ſerued for nothing: they ſuld haue paſſed bak &amp; taken an other, to mak wp &amp; buld of new à kirk, and not to reform that whilk was not: for reformation preſupponeth à ſubiect and matter laicking ſomething neceſſair to the perfection: ſo their procuration (if there was no kirk) was nul of

it ſelf, and can nather ſerue them nor their ſucceſſours for anie warrand of this wark, they haue taken in hand, how beutiful &amp; glorious à name ſoeuer they giue it.
            
               Aſpiciunt oculis ſuperi mortalia iuſtis. Think ye it reaſonable, that any man ſuld tak on him to caſt doune the houſe, whilk IESVS CHRIST him ſelf heth builded, becauſe it ſemeth to his vaine imagination to haue many deformities &amp; vncomlineſſes, &amp; build wp an other at his fantaſie, alledging that the Lord heth ſent him? I can not beleue that any man can be à better painter or maiſſon then God, wha ſaid tota pulchra es amica mea, &amp; macula 
               Can. 4. 7. Matt. 16. 18. 
               non eſtinte, &amp; wha builded his kirk vpō à rock. weal I knaw that it is Gods wil that his houſe ſtand to the end of the warld. But lat this be an errour of the ſecretaire, wha ſuld haue written formation of à kirk, or the fault of

the meſſenger, wha ſpak ouerlowlie in our firſt cōmiſſioners eare, where by, one word was taken for an other. But whidder it ſuld be Formation, Reformation or Deformation, for the preſent I ſtand not, provyding the cōmiſſion of this extraordinaire calling be good. They war ſent (ſay they) by God extraordinairlie. I deſyr they proue that: for ſimple and proueles ſaying, in mattres of ſa great conſequence (as where it is queſtion of eternal lyf and death) can not be receaued, except by them, wha wald hazard their part of paradiſe on à ſimple word, we muſt ſee the cōmiſſion alledged, if it be good and haue the beſt &amp; aſſured mark, that it may ſerue ws for our warrand, when we shalbe called to rendre compt of our mailles &amp; dueties in cōmanding or obeying. It is als dangerous to beleue euery ma, as to beleue no man. I ſee the Miniſters

hes diſpoſſeſſed thois, wha war paſtours by iuſt ſucceſſiō (as hauing receaued that charge frome hand to hand ſince the Apoſtles) and hes placed them ſelfis in their roome deſyring or rather cōmanding ws to acknawledge them as true paſtours, follow Knox appel lation 2. and obey them, geuing our ſauls &amp; cōſcience to be nurished by them in trueth &amp; pietic, of the whilk they haue the diſtribution delyuered to them by God him ſelf, as they alledge. Truelie ſeing that no man, no not of their maiſt zelous brethring will gif them à thowſand pound on their word without good &amp; ſufficient caution, ſuld we not be great fooles to giue them our ſaulles not asking of them any ſufficiēt warrand but their word? The matter is ſo weaghtie that they can not iuſtlie be offended with ws, if we deſyre to be aſſured that we shal haue no tinſal in beleuing them.

Lat ws ſee the great ſeall and mark of this extraordinair calling, that is miracles and winderful warks aboue nature, whereby we may knaw that it is God wha ſent them, and that it is his wil we receaue them with due reuerence and obedience. I knaw they wil anſwer me here, that they ar not obliſt to bring miracles, ſeing they teach no new doctrin. I pray al good &amp; Godlie Chriſtians conſider if this be à propre anſwer &amp; to the propos: For firſt they tak that for à proofe, whilk is in controuerſie betwixt the parties, as is ouer euidentlie knawen: for we ſay (as we shal be hable to proue by them ſelfis) that the doctrine they teach now is new, at leeſt in many heades of controuerſies, Secondlie the propheres, wha broght miracles, broght no new doctrine, other wayes they culd not haue bein receaued, the law being ſo formell agains them.

Thridlie it man be new to ws, ſeing that nather we, nor anie of our forefathers before Knox euer hard of it in our contray. Laſt of all, we ſeak miracles for their alledged extraordinair &amp; marveilous calling, &amp; not for their doctrine, whilk can not be true, ſeing it is ſo new, the veritic being ſo auld. Our Maiſter &amp; Lord cōmandeth ws in matters of religion to obey his kirk: and obey &amp; acknawledge none other. Why shal we now heare the Miniſters without anie aſſurence of their charge and commiſſion, ather ordinaire or extraordinaire? If anie man wald ask of the ſubiectes of à noble man (wha war out of the contray) the mailles &amp; dueties, alledging he haid commiſſion of their maiſter: Wald they not iuſtlie anſwer, that their maiſter before his parting out of the contray, haid put order to all his affaires giuing charge to certaine

men whome he haid choiſen for that effect and maid officers ouer his haill lands with ful power to ſete and raiſe, tak wp dueties and mailles, giue quittances▪ fence and hald courtes, and al other things neceſſaire, with expreſſe cōmand to acknawledge none other till his retourning: wherefore if he haid any cōmiſſion frome their maiſter, it behoved to be cōmunicat and ſein, yea aſſuredlie knawen to be valable &amp; ſufficient? Certainlie it wald not ſerue nor moue them (if they war weil aduyſed) to ſay that theis things, whilk he requireth war due &amp; awing to their maiſter, &amp; that he asketh no thing, to whilk they war not oblished: Nor yet to ſay that the officers haid neglecked their duetie baith in waiſting their maiſters gear and miſgoverning his houſe, &amp; alſo in oppreſſing his ſubiectes. wald they not anſwer, that they war ſorie for ſic mens

miſbehauiour, yet becauſe their maiſter haid gauen them charge to obey onlie theis officers, whome he haid eſtableshed, they culd not paſſe the boūds of their maiſters cōmand; and therfor wald on na way acknawledge him, wha ſchew no cōmiſſion, nor power of their maiſter? Shall poore men be maire wyſe and circū
               ſpect in à bol of meal or 40. shillings, then I in my ſaul? Shal they ſeak for good warrād in paying of their dueties, and I shal gife my ſaul to the firſt that craueth it? It shall not be neadfull to tel me here, what I aw to my maiſter, what I ſuld beleue, what reuerence I ſuld beare to the ſcriptures and paſtoures of the kirk. I beleue that maire is true, then anie man can telle: I ask onlie wherefra commeth thes extraordinaire officers, and what power they haue? I wald pray them to cleare me of this ſubiect. For in

matters of faith, the authoritie maketh all, whilk can receaue non other warrand, but God him ſelf, or elſe ſic as ar ſufficiently authorized by him. They wil ſay that ſindrie of the prophetes cōme without miracles, and therefor it can not be iuſtly asked of them, whilk hes not bein asked of others before them, cōming with lyk calling. I anſwer, that à great part of the Prophetes broght miracles with them to confirme, their ſending, and principally, when their vocation was, or might be called in doubt. Wherefor Moſes ſchew miracles not onlie in the beginning, when he was firſt receaued, but alſo againes Core Dathan and Abiron. Elias againes the prophetes of Bael in burning the ſacrifice vpon the Alter before the people. And to paſſe vnder ſilence al other, IESVS CHRIST acknawledgeth the miracles to be neceſſaire. If
               
               I (ſayeth he) haid not come and donne vvorks amonges them, that no other man 
               10. 15. 24. 
               hathe donne, they haid not haid ſinne. But novv they baith haue ſinne, and haue hated baith me and my father. To Sanct Iohn the Baptiſt aſking by two of his diſciples, if it was he wha was to come, he anſwereth, the blind ſee, the 
               Matt. 11. 5. 
               crippel vvalk, the lepers ar maid cleane, the 
               Luc. 7. 19. 
               deafe heere, the dead ryſe againe, to the poore the Euangelle is preached. Mairouer the prophetes, wha war ſent extraordinairelie neuer intermedleth them ſelfis with the office of preaſthaed and paſtours (except they war of the Trib of Leui) nor euer pat them out of their place. We neuer hard that any, becauſe he was ſent extraordinairlie, tuik the place of the high preaſt: or tuik the Ephod, or cenſeur out of the preaſts hands: For the ſacrifice was ay continued by the preaſtes &amp; by none other. So that the ancient

prophetes howſoeuer they was called extraordinairlie (as ſaid is) did neuer pretend thereby any charge in the ſacrifice as appertening to the prieſtes only. For the prophetes com as à new ſuccour &amp; helpe ſent by God to fortifie and confort the ordinaire officers, to waken them wp from negligence, to aduertish them of their duetie, to love honour &amp; ſerue their God wprightlie. Lykwayes to admonish the Prince and people of their office, reproche them their faultes &amp; ſinnes, with threatnings of punition and vengence therevpon to follow, except they did preuent the wrath of God with ſpeidy repentēce. In whilk charges miracles war not verie neceſſaire, ſeing they demanded but amedement of mens lyfes, and Godis ſeruice to be donne, by ſic as haid the charge, not melling therewith, notwithſtanding of their extraordinaire

ſending by God him ſelf. Euen as if à Prince or noble man abſent wald gif charge to anie man by mouth, to aduertish his ſeruantes and ſubiectes to be maire diligent in their office and duerie, ſchawing them wherein their maiſter war offended, and what punition he haid deliberat to tak of ſic as he fand culpable &amp; giltie; it ſuld not be neceſſaire therefor to bring his maiſters great ſealle. But if he wald enter to go werne and ruelle, he wald not be receaued vpō his ſimple word. Mairouer, althoght there be no mention in the ſcriptures of the miracles of ſindrie Prophetes, yet it is not to be concluded that they did no miracles: yea their prophecies war ſufficient warrands for their miſſion, they being, as it war, the ordinaire poſtes and meſſengers in thos dayes betwix God and his people, to whom Gods will was to be ſchawen according

to the peoples behauiour and new occurrantes. It can not be ſchawen where that anie prophete is com to execute anie great interpriſe without miracles, ather preſente, precedent, or ſubſequent. In S. Iohn the Baptiſt there be manie things verie miraculous, his mothers aage, his fathers domnes before his conception▪ and ſpeach reſtored at his birth, his education commanded by the angel, his lyf; and laſt of all the teſtimonie of IESVS CHRIST maire then all miracles, ſeing he was the authour of all miracles, whilk at that tyme for iuſt reaſon he haid keiped to him ſelf: whereby he might be knawen frome others. Now there come neuer anie prophete for ſo weaghtie à matter as this, for whilk, they ſay, that they ar come, to wit, to reſtore the ſpouſe to IESVS CHRIST, the body to the head, to mak à new flock to that heauinlie

Paſtour, to reſtore him to his auld &amp; ancient heritage, to buld wp the eternal houſe of God, to deſtroy the regne of Satā: to bring new light to the warld, to tak mankynd out of the throt, as it war, of the deuill: to publish the verity ſo lang vnknawē: to ſchaw the kirk ſo lang vnſeen and inuiſible And to be ſchort, to do that wherefore our Maiſter and Lord of his infinite goodnes come in earth, and tuik vpon him our mortall nature, and therein ſuffered death and paſſion, that is, to mak wsimmortals, and of ſonnes of man, whilk we war, to mak wsſonnes of God, to be partakers with him of the eternal inheritance, hauing nurished and broght ws wp in his a win houſe, the whilk to governe if Luther, Caluin or Knox pretēdes any right by new extraordinaire charge, is it not maiſt reaſonable that they ſchaw an authentique

commiſſion? Suld not the great ſeall be here imployed? Elias for leſſe cauſe maid the fyr come out of heauin. If à ſimple alledgence of reformation be à ſufficient varrand, we shall haue in continent good ſtore of reformers and extraordinaire paſtours to correct, or rather to corrupt, the harl warld. The Anabaptiſtes and Libertines with manie other ſiclyk perniſious peſtes ſuld ſchortlie occupie all places: For their word is als good as the others is, in matters of religion, if the word be inonch, &amp; the ſaying à ſufficient proofe. But if there be anie other thing requiſit to haue and procure credet, whateuer is neceſſair in one is neceſſaire in all, ſeing there can be no authoritie and power but in the ordinaire: becauſe it onlie was ſufficientlie authorized by IESVS CHRIST, and executed by his Apoſtles (wha receaued it immediatlie of

their Maiſter) and by their ſucceſſors to our dayes. Otherwayes the extraordinaire muſt haue als good and ſolid proofe as the ordinaire. If it be ſufficient to ſay that it was Gods will and pleaſour, that ſie men ſuld tak that wark of governement and reformation on hand, when they cotre the place, we shal ather anſwer or agree thereto. But IESVS CHRIST will diſavow ſick extraordinaire reformers. The Prophetes prophecie lees in my 
               Ierem 14. 14. 
               name. I have not ſent them, nather did I command them: nather ſpak I vnto them: but they prophecie vnto youu à fals viſion and diuination and vanitie and deceatfulnes of their avvne hart. Let them ſchaw (if they haue aniecharge) the expreſſe and particulaire command they haue of God to com: for the general and ancient commandement without doubt appertineth to the ordinaire officers of the houſe,

who is cōmiſſion is of lang tym both confirmed and acknawledged: Noueltie ſuld be ſuſpect to al men ſeing, as ſaid is, the veritie is ſo auld.
            Some anſwereth that it is à great miracle and ſufficient to proue Gods wil and pleaſour, that in ſo ſchort à tyme they haue drawen ſo manie to them frome the kirk of Rome. If that war à ſufficient reaſon and great miracle; then ſuld Mahomet &amp; Arrius be holie men ſent by God, &amp; his weal beloued; for certaine it is that the impietie of Mahomet, or hereſie of Arrius was maire myghtie then al thos, wha hes ſeparat them ſelfis in thir lait dayes frome the Catholique Romaine kirk: yet I am aſſured that no man of iudgement wil think that Mahomet, or Arrius did miracles by their ſeduction, or that ſic revoltes war ſufficiēt to proue them to be ſent by God with new cōmiſſion. Therefore

althoght Luther, Caluin, Knox and their ſucceſſours haid brangled the hail warld (as they haue not done and the Antechriſt wil do) with their authoritie and doctrine, it followeth not that it is à work approued by God and his extraordinaire ſending: For albeet it be contraire to al ordinaire courſe it ſuld not be cōcluded, that it is good &amp; procedeth frome à power extraordinaire geuen by God: For we fee manie extraordinair actions, and punished extraordinairelie, as things donne with violence and contraire to all good order. I can not beleue that the Miniſters them ſelfis wald now receaue any man wha wald com with an extraordinaire calling to reforme them, notwithſtand of their ſchort poſſeſſion: wherein there be manie thinges thoght (even by ſome of them ſelfis) worthie of à good reformatiō. I doubt not but they wald

alledge their order alreddie receaued, confirmed and eſtableshed. And in caſe he wald not deſiſt, I am aſſured, they wald imploy the force of their excommunication and actes of parliament, as à ſouueraine remeed agans al rebellious perſonnes. If it was lauful to à few vnquyet ſpirites to ryſe agains the hail Catholique kirk being in poſſeſſion 1500. yeares eſtableshed, why shal it not be laufull to ryſe againiſt à few new in come? might it not be iuſtlie ſaid here Patere legem quam ipſe tuleris? The iuriſcō
               ſult ſayeth weal, quod quiſque iuris in alterum ſtatuit, ipſe eodem iure vti debet. Shall it be permitted to them to do what they liſt againes whome they pleeſe in what matter &amp; maner they will, and shalbe lauful to no man to gainſay them. O duram aliorum ſortem ne dicam ſeruitutem. They wil alledge perchance the ſcripturs for their warrand

and that they teach the veritie contined therein. I anſwer, that euerie heretik ſayeth the lik, and that al our diſpute, for the preſent, is of their power and calling: &amp; that it is an other debate betwixt ws &amp; them touching the ſcriptures and veritie. as we haue ſaid before. we grant the ſcriptures and the veritie ſuld be receaued and imbraſſed, and all good reaſon do teach ws that there ſuld be paſtoures; but they giue ws no aſſurance yea no appeerance that Luther, Caluin or Knox, or anie of their ſucceſſours, can be thes true paſtours, but rather the contraire, as we haue prouen. Wald they then thus argument? I haue the bible, I ſay the trueth, I am then à true and lauful paſtour &amp; doctour of Godis kirk? I vnderſtand not this cōſequent, except they wald ſay that all (be they men, we men or childring, learned or ignorant) wha

heth the bible &amp; ſayeth the verity at true and lauful paſtours, that is, haue lauful power and authoritie in the kirk of God to preache, teache, &amp; admiſtrat the ſacramētes, bind &amp; loufe tak in and put out, excommunicate and abſolue, whilk I am aſſured, they wil not ſay. What wald be thought of me, if I ſuld argument thus? I haue the actes of parliamēt, I ſay no thing but according to the kinges M. lawis and ordinances, therefor I am à ſchiref or lieutenent for his Maieſtie: that is, I haue power to admiſtrat iuſtice, condemne and abſolue, head &amp; hang, banish and cal bak &amp;c. perchance this vaine imagination wald be tolerat and laughen at in me, as oftentymes ſic phrenetik ſpirites ſerueth for other mens recreation: but if therevpon I ſuld tak anie man wha haid committed à murther &amp; (keepping the ordinaire forme of iuſtice

in all other things, except in the power whilk I haid not) ſuld call in 15. or 20: honeſt men on his ſyes and by them, for the ſlaughter weal verifier, and confeſſed, condemne him in the mouth of the dempſter, and execute him by the hangman, wald it be à ſufficiēt warrand for me to ſchaw the actes of parliament or lawes of the contry and perpetuall practiſe in lyk thinges? It wald not be aſked of me what the law ordaineth, but what power and authoritie I haid to tak that man, call in à ſyes on him, cōdemne and execute him: my cōmiſſion wald be soght, and not the law. Yea for laick of à lawful commiſſion I ſuld be found not onlie à manſlayer with Syes, Dempſter &amp; Hangman (whom I haid drawen in that cry me with me) but alſo an vſurper of the King is authoritie, without his knawledge or wil, ſo I &amp; all my adherentes ſuld be

found in that action mair giltie and to haue offēded the Prince mair greavouſlie then the murtherer, whome I haid execut: For beſyd the ſlaughter, in my action ſuld be found vſurpation, oppreſſion and cōiunction of ſo manie perſones therin, whilk ſuld augment my cryme: For as in good thinges the maire the better, ſo in evil thinges the maire the worſe. Lykwayes we aſk not at the miniſters, if ther ſuld be any lauful paſtoures wha ſuld preach, teach, adminiſtrat the ſacramentes, exhort to vertue, reproue vyce, cut off rotten and rebellious membres: we knaw theis things may and ſuld be donne by them wha heth the lauful power: But we demand wha geaue them that power to exerciſe theis charges &amp; offices to enioye that priuiledge? Shal not the vſurper here be in greatter danger, as the matter is greatter? Or shal kinges and Princes,

nobles and gentilmen, conmoune wealthes and brughes, priuat &amp; ſimple men haue order and diſcipline, whereby ſome command and others obey without confuſion, &amp; God shal haue neene in his houſe? In the kirk shalbe no thing, but diſorder troble and diſcorde? that it may be ſaid of hir, whilk the poëte ſayeth of the ſea waves;
            
               Neſcit cui domino pareat vnda maris. If everie man wil command (whilk man be if the bible may mak à paſtour) wha shal not command? only they ſurely wha wanteth ather moyen or wil to haue à bible. It is permitted to everie man to ſchaw the law and trueth to any man: yea it is à wark of charity, to teach the ignorāt, principally in matters of ſaluatiō: but to tak on him the power &amp; iuriſdiction to cōmand aboue others as being à paſtour or magiſtrat; not hauing charg

of them, wha hath that power, nunquā licuit, nunquám
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   licebit. it was not, is not, nor euer shalbe lauful, The kirk is as Caſtrorum acies ordinata: Not lyk to the Chaos of poëtes where Frigida pugnabant calidis, humētia ſiccis, Mollia cum duris, ſine pondere habentia pondus.
            
            Sic cōfuſions aggrees not with Gods infinit wiſdome, quae attingit à fine vſque ad finem fortiter, &amp; diſponit omnia ſuauiter. The qualities that S. Paul requireth in à Bishope, shaweth how cairful God is to haue his houſe weal governed. Men wil not ſuffer everie man to medle with the keeping of their beeſtes. I think not that God heth leſſe regard to his kirk. It may be that they ſay that there was na paſtours in the kirk, when theis new Euangeliſtes come, ſeing they wha war in poſſeſſion had tynt their right, becauſe they haid not donne their duetie:

and therefor the miniſters quaſi in vacuum venerunt, did occupie à place vacant. Althoght it be à thing verie hard tobe beleeved, yea altogether not to be beleeved, that God cōtraire to his promiſe heth ſo abandonat his awen inheritance, that he heth no man, wha with lauful authority did his duetie, or might giue power to others to governe our Saluiors houſe, yet I wil paſſe it at this tyme. I tak onlie that paſtoures hoth not tynt their place by reaſon of non entry, in whilk caſe it behoveth them to haue recourſe to their maiſter, all retourning bak agane to him. If they haue failled becauſe they haue neglegentlie and vnproperlie donne their office, as the cryme was perſonal, ſo ſuld the paine &amp; punitiō be perſonal: ſeing in felonies the haires or ſucceſſoures be not perſewed for the cryme of their predeceſſoures, except they

be found ſocij criminis, or elſe that their predeceſſours haue commetted laeſ-maieſtie. Now ſeing the ſucceſſour is nowayes debarred for commoune cryme cōmitted by his predeceſſours: reſteth the cryme of laeſ-maieſtie, by rebellion or treaſon agains the Princes perſonne or eſtait, conſel taken with the enimie, aſpyring to the croune, or other ſic poinctes as theis. Now giuing &amp; not granting (for the Miniſters can neuer be hable to proue ſic thinges, as we haue ſchawen before) that the paſtoures of the Catholique kirk haith tynte their place by one of theis crymes: what ſyn? Followeth it that the miniſters heth the iuſt title? Quo iure? By publique authoritie and forme of iuſtice the charge, power and office of paſtours was geuene to the Apoſtles &amp; their ſucceſſores til the warlds end. Yet if they haue failled ſo greavouſlie,

that God hes called bak the gift maid to his onlie ſonne, let them be accuſed, examinat, iudged &amp; cō
               demned by publique authoritie and forme of iuſtice, and ſo diſcharged, diſpoſſeſſed and caſt out, as men orderlie convict and forfault: and lat others by lyk forme and authoritie be put in their place, by them wha heth the power thereto. The offence maketh men worthie of condemnation, but condemneth no man. The ſentence &amp; decreat of the iudge muſt firſt be pronunced. Manie men committeth great crymes, yet poſſeſſeth their lands til they be forfaulted: and ſindry getteth their remiſſion before they be accuſed: and others, notwithſtanding they be iuſtlie accuſed of treaſon, yet becauſe they ar not condemned and forfault, without anie remiſſion they ſtand ſtil in poſſeſſiō and their heires efter them.
            
               
Seing the Kingis authoritie and publique forme of iuſtice ar required to put anie man in iuſt poſſeſſion of his awne, shal it be permitted to every man at his phantaſy to caſt him out, wha is in poſſeſſiō? And when the act of forfaultrie is paſſed &amp; giuen out in due forme, the landes or offices ar not abandonat to euery one, wha wil occupie them: but they returne to the Prince or ouerlord. So whaſoeuer will iuſtlie brook and enioye theis lands or offices, muſt haue à new gift of the prince or ouerlord, new charters, evidentes, infeftments, commiſſions weal maid, ſubſcriued, and ſealled, with all other circumſtances (better knawē to men of law nor to me) whilks ar neceſſair; whereby he may be knawen to be the iuſte poſſeſſour or lauful magiſtrat: for the charters, evidentes, infeftments, cō
               miſſions or retours, or anie other tytles

whilk war before, ar anulled, as appertining only to the perſone forfault, &amp; therefor invtile for al other men, except perchance to his heires, if the Prince wald haue pietie of thē: or if he wald ſuffer the forfaultrie to be reduced of ſpecial grace &amp; fauour. Whaſoeuer wald ſtart to at his awen hand, and occupie the place vacant without conſent of the ſuperiour, might think aſſuredlie that his vſurpation wald be als heavy à cryme as the others was, wha hed tynt the place.
            Lykwayes (as ſaid is) if the paſtors hes failled, let them be accuſed before their lauful iudge, where they ar fond giltie, let them be cōdemned: thereefter ſic as shalbe found maire qualifiet, and worthie of ſic offices may be chooſen in their place and obtein à new commiſſion of them, wha heth that power in the kirk vpon earth. If ther be nein at al, wha heth that iuriſdiction,

they muſt tak new halding of God in the ſam forme and maner as the Apoſtles receaued it frome IESVS CHRIST, the poſteritie and ſucceſſours hauing failled, as they alledge, but not prouen. Now what forme of iuſtice heth bene keepped? Wha warned the paſtoures? Before what iudge war they accuſed? Wha cōdemned thē? wha gaue the new title to the Miniſters? I ſee the lauful paſtores accuſed, or rather abuſed, with out law or reaſon or iudge: condemned without any form of iuſtice; caſt out with violence, &amp; their places occupied by others without, yea agains al right. I ſee their contrairie partie mak him ſelf iudge, tak à cōmiſſion of him ſelf, and put it in execution on his priuat authoritie.
            
               Dúne hunc ardorem mētibus addunt Euryole? an ſua cuiq. Deus fit dir a cupido? If al things man be maid new before

they haue good right, it war beſt they maid à new God to authoriz their new procedinges &amp; practiſe of law: for if theis faſhions war good &amp; reaſonable, wha culd be aſſured, I ſay not of his geare, office or landes, but even of his verie lyf, every man making himſelf partie, witnes, iudge and executour of anie accuſation he ſuld forge aganiſt anie man it pleaſeth him? I might inſiſt here with manie other reaſons, if I feareth not to be tedious in vrging à matter ſo cleare of it ſelf.
            I knaw ſome, for defence of the Miniſters, ſayeth that their vocation is nather altogether ordinaire, nor altogether extraordinaire, partem capiens ab vtroq. that is (when al is weal conſidered) nather the one nor the other. There is not halflang religions, as ther is halflang dogges. They wald ſerue them ſelfis with the authoritie of the Catholik hirk to enter in Gods

houſe with order, &amp; afterward without order, whilk they call extraordinairelie, guyd, or rather miſguyd all at their phantaſie.
            But is it poſſible that they wil ſerue them with the kirk of Rome, ſeing they haue taken for à ground of their religion and lauful cauſe of their ſeparation, that the Paipe is the great Antechriſt? They man on force laying this ground, acknawledge that they haue their entry in the kirk frome the Antechriſt. Truelie if they haue no better porter then Satans eldeſt ſonne to let them in, I fear they shal not be vealcome to God, wha vſeth in his merciful warkis to imploy better ſeruantes. If that opinion war true, then ſuld Satan be half maiſter, ſeing that the half of the charge cō
               meth of him: yea he muſt haue (according to that doctrine) the maiſt apperant part, ſeing that the ordinaire,

whilk is weall authorized cō
               meth of him: where as the extraordinaire, whilk they wald aſcribe to God, commeth without anie avow, except of their bare ſaying. I wald be mair ample in the refutation of this branded vocation, if I thoght not that few, or neene wald cleame thereto.
            As to them, wha ſerueth them ſelfis with the wordes of our Lord, vvhere there be tvva or three aſſembled in my 
               Matth. 18. 20. 
               name, there J am in the meddeſt of them. I anſwer ſchortlie, firſt, that it is queſtion there, of the aſſiſtance of our Lord to the prelates of the kirk or people, and not of the calling of paſtoures in particulair And who doubteth but holie and Godlie men heth the aſſiſtance of God whidder theybe in ſmal or great nōber. Nixt, if that ſuld be taken generallie and for the vocation, wherſoever there be twa or three gathered in Chriſtes name▪
               
ther man be there power to mak à paſtour. Sua where there be twa or three in anie houſe they muſt conſtitut à à paſtour to them ſelf, and ſo change al priuat houſes in kirkes, contraire to that, whilk we ſee now in Scotlād where kirks ar turned in priuat houſes. Mairouer if that war the ſenſe of Chriſtes wordes, it ſuld appertine to the people to cal the paſtours, whilk the Miniſters of Scotland verie wyſlie, as yet hes never approued. And laſt of al, this culd mak no thing for the firſt Miniſter, wha being allone culd not be elected by twa or three.
            Notwithſtanding of al this, I will giue and ſuppon in this matter alſe far as I can without preiudice of the veritie. I wil ſo enter for the preſent to receaue the extraordinaire vocation (whilk with reaſon can not be receaued, except it haue à verie good warrand) if it can ſerue ws to anie vſe

as I fear it can not do: For if ſo many hondreth yeares vnion of the Catholik doctrine can not ſerue to maintaine ws in our ordinaire right, how shal ſo many hondreth day lie confuſions iuſtile maintaine them in their extraordinaire vſurpation? But to what vſe can their extraordinair calling ſerue ws, althoght we wald receaue it? There be maire then à hondreth diverſe religions (atleeſt opinions vſurping the name of religiō) everie one condemning an other, &amp; aſcriving to it ſelf that glorious title of true extraordinaire calling vnder pretence of the pure &amp; true word of God, and adminiſtration of the ſacramētes. What shal I do in this great confuſed multitude, where neine can ſtand ſeure, except al his compagnōs be declared vſurpers &amp; fals prophetes? Ye will ſay perchance that the Miniſters of Scotland hes neene of

thes ſectes amongs them, where of they ar verie glaid. I wil not for the preſent conteſt therevpon. But ſure I am, that they wha hes not the Miniſters of Scotlandis religion amongs them, ar alſe glaid, and ſindrie, wha hes it, wald be glaid to be quyt therof. I may truelie ſay with an ancient authour ſpeeking of the philoſophers of his tyme, that all theis ſectes may be falſe, but ſure I am there can be but one true. If al can not be true, whome shall I credet? Whome shall I follow? I can not credet nor follow them all, ſeing they ar cōtraire, every one cōdemning an other. The chooſe muſe be difficil, ſeing that everie one ſayeth ſtoutlie that he hes the trueth. Everie man pretendeth the verity, citeth the ſcriptures, confereth place with place, confirmeth his awen opinion (if ye wil beleeue him) ſolidlie and refuteth all others ſufficientlie.

But if ye will credet all the reſt, he ſayeth nothing to the propos, except ſo far as he agreeth with every one of them in particulaire.
            Swa whaſoeuer will agree with any of them, muſt on force diſagree with manie. And yet there can be but one trueth: &amp; if we wil beleue the greateſt parte of them, neane of them hes the trueth: becauſe for one wha affirmeth he haith the trueth, there be an hondreth wha gainſayeth him. For every one of them alledgeth that al the reſt goeth wrang, whilk is verie eaſie to be beleued, becauſe the Catholique kirk ſayeth the ſame of them all, shee being, whē they war not to ſay the lyk of hir. And how can any mā of iugement think otherwayes of them? We ſee the ſcripture taken by them al for an ordinaire proofe of their extraordinaire calling: it ſpeeketh (as they ſay) in al their fauoures. Yet can we

not be of ſo manie religions: nor acknawledge or obey ſo many paſtours of ſa extraordinair &amp; cōtrary opiniōs. But ye wil ſay that he ſuld be receaued, followed &amp; obeyed, wha agreeth beſt with the ſcripturs. That is maiſt reaſonable, if it can be knawē. But who is iudgemēt shalbe taken in the matter? Neane wil heare the Catholique kirk, becauſe they haue left hir: &amp; ſo as rebellious ſubiectes can abyd no thing but iuſt cōdēnation of their ſchiſme and errour. If we wil credit the parties, everie man interpretes the ſcriptures beſt. The craw thinketh hir awen bird faireſt: and vaine men eſteimeth maiſt of the birth of their awé braine. So shal I be in lyk paine and difficultie, as before, not knawing whome to follow, whome to flee. If they ſay that I muſt read the ſcripturs and follow thois, wha ſtandeth beſt by the veritie cōtined therein. What?

Man I be à profound theologue before I knaw my paſtoures? Man I be ſo deiplie learned before I knaw my maiſters ſchool? shall I be iudge extraordinair to this extraordinair calling? Man I read al theis wha hes written, before I enter in Gods houſe or acknawledge anie of his officers, for Quiſtatuit aliquid parte inaudita altera, aequum licet ſtatuerit, haud aequus fuit? Man I be ſoueraine magiſtrat in this matter to giue out the final decreet? Man I be the interpreter of our maiſter and Lords teſtament? Shall my foolish braine be à ſquare of his veritie? Truelie if I ſuld ſtand to that whilk I think beſt, I muſt be iudge: &amp; if my iudgemēt be à rule to me to obtine the veritie, and conſequentlie eternal lyf, al men ſuld follow my iudgemēt: For there can be but one rule ſeing ther is but one veritie, except we wald think that the trueth ſuld be

bowed to every mans fantaſie; whilk we ſee now is dōne throghout al Europe whereſouer this extraordinaire calling hes onie credit, whilk hes broght in this multitude of ſectes: For the iudgement being referred to the particulaire (wha for that cauſe is ſent to the bible, whilk he muſt haue to conſult with all, as if he war ſome profound doctour in Iſraël) according as he shal find by his iudgement, he pronunceth the ſentēce of true &amp; lauful extraordinaire calling in favour of his Miniſter. According to this forme, in Scotland the Miniſters following the doctrine of Sir Iohn Knox, or frere Iohn Crag ar thoght to haue à good calling. In Englād the Bruniſtes, Puritains, &amp; family of Luif, or any hid new invented fantaſy, thinketh their paſtors truely called. In France Caluin &amp; Beza with their adherentes ar thought to haue à

lauful vocation amonges the greateſt part of our ſimple Proteſtātes, except perchāce Monſieur du Pleſſis hes drawen anie to à maire recent imagination. I ſay the ſimple proteſtantes; for they wha haith any good opinion of them ſelfis taketh to them ſelf the free will whilk they refuſe to others—nullius iurant in verba magiſtri, they receaue no thing, but that whilk agreeth with the ſcripturs, that is, with their iudgement &amp; opinion, wher thir new holy fathers ar oftyms reiected by vertue of their awen rule, that is of every priuat mans opinion.
            In Almanie there be good ſtore of theis new extraordinair called me▪ the freedome of the townes maketh manie free vocations: For there they haue liberty to think, ſay, and follow what euerie man pleaſeth. There is no act of parliament to keep their vniō, nor force them to an accorde, whilk

can not be haid by anie otherway amonges them, wha wil haue the holy ſpirit ſpeeking no farther then he whiſpereth in their eare. True it is that where there is Princes wha commandeth, the people muſt change their religion with their maiſter: Als lang as their maiſter is Lutheriā, they muſt ſay with him: if he changeth opinion or dieth, they muſt be reddie to receaue ſome other faith. This hes beine ſindrie tymes experimented in that contray. But in free townes as euerie man hes receaued of his Miniſters preaching, he iudgeth the ſcriptures to ſay the ſame, where our comone prouerbe may iuſtly be imployed, as the fool thinketh, the bel clinketh. If their war publick place in Scotlād for Miniſters of other ſectes, I doubt not but they wald avāce their cauſe alſo. For that licence giuen to everie man to be iudge on the ſcriptures,

without anie acte of parliamēt to ty them to à certaine cōfeſſion of faith (whilk in Almanie hes maid this multitude of extraordinair vocatiōs) wald do the lyk amonges ws. How miſerable be the eſtait of Almanie in that diuerſitie of religions, if not openlie at leeſt priuatlie, I think euery man knaweth, wha hes beine there. It is maiſt certaine that in ſindry townes there be publicklie profeſſed ten, twelf, yea tuentie or 22. ſindry faithes everie one deteſting an other. As to the priuat opinions, I haid an evident experience my ſelf in our voyage of Italie, retourning to France throgh Almanie the yeare of God 1600. in the moneth of December. For being in Auſburgh (where publik exercice is granted onlie to Catholiques and Lutheriās) we war at the table à good nomber (I think aboue 12) of honeſt, lyk men of diuerſe nations, but meakle

maire diuerſe of religions, where one of the cōpany maire zelous then the reſt (as it appeared) taking occaſion of our being at the Iubilee, did ask ſindry curious queſtions there anent. A Frenche gentilman, wha was come frome Rome with ws, picked with the matter, mirrilie, &amp; yet courteouſlie, did pray the companie, if it might be without their offence to grant him à requeſt, whilk being accorded, he ſuld anſwer to their queſtions according to his knawledg, if he fand it agreable to thē: this being proponed ſo diſcreatly and honeſtly (as that nation can do it verie weall) it was not onlie accepted &amp; granted of all the companie, but alſo maid à great ſilence throghout all the table, everie man being deſirous to knaw his requeſt.
            Then hauing thanked them all, I am deſirous (ſayeth he) to knaw what

profeſſion of religion now adayes, euery an of yowdoeth maiſt approue, or what man ye think maiſt worthie of credit when it is queſtion of anie head of religion called in controuerſie. And that no man may think I deſyr of others whilk I wald not do myſelf, I wil ſpeik for my cōpagnons &amp; me (meaning of ws three) we approue aboue all others the Catholik Apoſtolik Romaine religion, &amp; eſteimes the reſolutions gevin be the ſiege Apoſtolik in Rome, pronunced by the Paipe, to be preferred to all other, becauſe we find ſo manie ſolemne promiſſes maid by God to S. Peters ſucceſſoures. As I pray the cōpanie not to be offended at my demād &amp; iudgement, ſo I promiſe not to tak in euil part when it shal pleaſe anie of yow ather to ask at me any question, or freely to pronunce what he meaneth.
            Skairſlie haid he ended his propos,

when an other (wha was à citizen of the towne) anſwered, that doubtles the true religion was cōteined in the confeſſion of Auſburghe, and that Luther haid beine one of the maiſt notable men of our aage in all his reſolutions, provyding he be taken as he ſuld be, becauſe as an other Elias he come to inſtruct the world in thes latter dayes. The towne (as it appeared) gaue him courage to ſpeik ſo far to the praiſe of Luther, &amp; maid him tell his opinion ſo freelie.
            His nightbour (ſo farre as we culd coniecture of his contenance) approued not his iudgemēt altogether, whilk, being required he did ſchaw by his words, ſaying that he acknawledgeth Luther for à verie notable man, yet wha haid not ſeene al, whilk was neceſſair for the reformation of the kirk of God, &amp; cheeflie touching the Lords ſupper. His reformed ſupper

maid ws al beleeve he was ather à Zuinglian or Caluiniſt. The Lutherian wald haue entred in defence of his maiſter, but being requeſted by the companie, deſiſted, althoght with difficultie.
            Nixt to him was ſitting à certaine man verie modeſtlie cled, wha maid à great owtward ſchaw of ſimplicitie of mynd, he with à law voice ſayeth thus: I think na man ſuld acknawledge anie religion but that, whilk cōmeth immediatlie of the holie ſpirit, wha only can be receaued as à true maſter in that matter, vnus eſt magiſter veſter; &amp; beatus homo quem tu erudieris 
               pſal. 93. 12. 
               domine. His anſwer ſchew him to be of the Suentfeldien ſect, wha wil here no thing but that, whilk their priuat ſpirit doeth teach them, hauing ay in their mouth, audiam quid loquatur in 
               Pſal. 84. 
                     •
                  . 
               me Dominus Deus.
            
            He wha was ioyning with him, ſayis

with à laughing viſage, that he haid never beene ſo curious, as to exame al other mens religions or deuotion, but was accuſtumed to tak thing is as he fand them, leeuing everie man at his freedome, thinking it very reaſonable that everie man ſuld haue the priuiledge whilk God had gevin him. It was not difficill to coniecture that he was one of the Libertins, wha in matters of religion thinketh laufull to contrefait &amp; diſſemble al thinges and beleeve, what they liſt, or rather beleeve no thing at all.
            Heer we haid ſome lytill ſilence, becauſe he, wha nixt followeth maid difficultie to tell his opinion, whilk neuertheleſſe he did vtter, ſaying he did no wayes approue diſcorde amō
               ges Chriſtians, ſeing our Lord &amp; his Apoſtles haid geven ws ſo notable exemples of vnion in making al thinges commoune, whilk war propre &amp;

priuat before, whilk might eaſelie be put in vſe againe, if men wald tak away meum and tuum, myn and thyn. We vnderſtood by his words that he was an Adamit, wha amonges other deteſtable errours, thinketh that wemen ſuld be commoune als we all as other things. The haill reſt of the cōpanie, as it appeared, did abhorre frome that opinion. Yet one ſayeth; at leeſt ſeing it was lauful to the people of God in auld tymes to haue manie wifes, why shal it now be forbidden? The Lutherian wha ſpak firſt, hauing anſwered that ſic lawes war never in practiſe amonges the Chriſtians, becauſe they war improued by IESVS CHRIST. Yet your Luther (ſayeth he) maid no difficultie to preach, Si non vult vxor, veniat ancilla. This anſwer maid the companie to laugh, and remembred ws that ſome of our contray men, haid good ſtore

of wyfis by à new forme of partiſing, the partie taking the cryme one him in eſperāce to haue à new wyf ſchortlie efter.
            He that was nixt wald glaidlie (as it ſeamed) haue halden his peace, yet for feare we ſuld tak worſe opinion of him, hydding his pernicious errour the beſt he culd, ſaid that it haid pleaſed God in our dayes to ſchaw thé light of his verity in Pole, Lithuania, and Tranſſyluania, althoght other nations haid not, as yet, receaued it. Theis words gaue ws to vnderſtand that he was one of the new Arrians whais errours war broght in by Grogorius Pauli Miniſter of Cracouia, Valentinus Gentilis, Seruetus (wha was brunt at Geneua by Caluins perſuite) and ſome others of lyk ſtoofe, wha is doctrine is ful of blaſphemies.
            The nixt following with à litill ſmylling, ſayeth, that he mervelled

not of ſa manie diuerſe opiniones whilk war entred in the warld, ſeing that men ſeeketh rather ſubtil interpretations, then the veritie. As to my part (ſayeth he) I bear my warrand about with me (ſchawing ws his bible he haid in his boſome) whilk is maiſt eaſie to be vnderſtand of it ſelf, and therefore onlie to be redde, all other bookes ather being falſe, or invtill, whatſoeuer eſtimatiō other men maketh of their lang cōmentaires auld or new. If it haid beine in England I wald haue taken him for à Bruniſt. onlie culd I iudge for the tym that he approued no mans ſentēce that haid ſpoken before him.
            To be ſchort thair was neane at the table (except ſo manie Catholiques as we war) wha agreed with an other. So everie one hauing ather openly or couuertlic ſchawen his opinion, we perceaued an honeſt man (wha haid

dyned with ws, and for ſome affaires haid beine occupied in the towne verie lait) ſitting at the head of the table. his honeſt &amp; homelie behauiour maid ws al caſt our eyes one him, &amp; as it war, with our ſilence &amp; looking deſyr the lyk of him. He being à mā of iudgemēt and doctrine, and wha was (as weal apeared by his diſcours) very weal travelled, efter he haid hard the hail matter and what we looked for, ſayeth in this ſort.
            Althoght the tyme &amp; place (good ſires) might iuſtlie excuſe my ſilence, yet that I ſeeme not to be by my fellowes, or refuſe your deſyre, I will ſome what ſay to the matter I heare hes bein amonges yow, rather to end the diſpute vnfite for the table, then to continue it. Whilk I willabour to do by the reciting of à notable hiſtorie of à maiſt noble and wyſe Prince.
            Being in France during the regne

of Charles the nynt, his brother Henry the thrid being then our King (whereby we knew him to be à Polonian) I paſſing throgh the contray chanced on à noble man of my auld acquentance at Rome, wha (efter he haid imbraſſed me with great affection, &amp; aſked of my other voyages ſinceparting) inuited me to his houſe whilk was hard by: whilk I did willinglie, not onlie becauſe I looued him tenderly, but alſo becauſe I haid hope by his moyen to knaw the ſingularities and cuſtomes of the cōtray (whilk was my principal earād there) by reaſon of his qualitie. Amonges many notable thinges I hard of him, I remarked this hiſtorie as he was reheirſing the ſingularities of the court of parliament of Paris.
            King Louis the 12. being earneſtly requeſted and prayed by one of his fauorits and greateſt courtiers (wha

haid an action of great importance before the court of parliament) to ſpeek the preſidentes and chief conſellers in his fauoure, giuing his M. to vnderſtand the great right he haid and what wrang he receaued of his aduerſe partie. The King on this information partly for iuſtice cauſe (of whilk he was verie zelous, and therefor called the father of the people) partlie for the affection he bure to the gentilman, did promiſe him all aſſiſtance, not onlie in ſpeeking to his iudges, but alſo with his awin preſence, if that might bring anic thing to his right. And ſo he did in deed. For the day appointed for that proceſe, being cume, the king with princes, and all other wha vſeth to aſſiſt his M. in ſic actions, repared to the palace, where being arryved he ſchew to the court of parliamēt that he was come there to ſee them do good iuſtice

according to their charge and aith, and chieflie to that gentilman, whais actiō was in hand, &amp; wha haid donne him good ſeuice ſindry tymes wherein he yet continued. They on the other part promiſt (with all ſubmiſſion and reverence) to do their duetie. Euerie man according to his rank hauing taken place, the aduocat, wha was for the gentilman, begane firſt, and with great eloquence defended his parties cauſe, wherewith the King was verie glaid, not only in him ſelf (as he ſchew by his continance) but alſo vtered the ſame by wordes, ſaying to the firſt preſident (wha was ſitting laigh vnder) il ha gaigné, Hehes vvin. The preſident anſwered modeſtly, it wil pleaſe your M. to heare the other partie, whilk the King granted the mair willinglie that he thought his fauorite haid alredie win his cauſe. The other aduocat

hauing entred in the matter with alſe great eloquence, but meakle better right, maid the king firſt to doubt, nixt to incline ſumwhat, and laſt of al to approue ſo his title, that before he haid pleaded out the cauſe, the King burſted out with theis words, Monſieur le preſident, ils ont tous deux gaigné. They haue vvin baith. Ye knaw by lang experiēce what is to be done in ſic thinges, I leaue it to yow and your companie. And ſo before the laſt aduocat haid ended, he paſt away. He haid beine verſed in the greatteſt affaires of Europe during his tyme baith in peace and weares, and haid experimented baith good and evill fortune before, and in his regne, yet not being trained wp in matters of law and iudging of proceſe, he was eaſelie moved to baith the ſyddes by eloquence filled wp with appearand reaſones. But as à maiſt worthie and

noble Prince he did acknawledge his awin imperfection, leaving the iugement of ſic affaires to the ordinaire officers of iuſtice, to iudge as they thoght maiſt reaſonable, as wha by lang and daylie experience, great knawledge of the law and examination of manie difficill actions paſſed by their hands, was ſufficientlie armed aganes fraudful craft of the parties, wha eaſelie may circumvine à new iudge. My advyſe is (good ſirs) that we imitat and follow this noble king (wha being ſo potēt à monarche durſt not raſhlie iudge on earthlie matters) in thir controverſies of religion referring the iudgemēt to the kirk, wha hes bein theis manie hondreth yeares in poſſeſſion of that office by Gods awin cōmiſſion, &amp; wha with ſick equitie hes decided ſo manie intricat &amp; difficil queſtions, wher doubtles, if we haid beine conſtitute

iudges we wald haue pronunced the ſentence for baith the parties, ſeing that many of ws hes done weal worſe hauing cōdēned the kirk the ſpouſe of IESVS CHRIST vnhard hir, following the firſt that hes accuſed hir and praiſed him ſelf.
            This hiſtorie was pronunced with ſic grace and authority that it appeaſed our diſpute, &amp; pleaſed verie weal the hail companie; and (if I be not deceaued) is not vnpropre to end our preſent diſcours, whilk is of the ſame ſubiect. Wherefor without anie farther, I wil pray yow and al good readers (if perchāce any man wil beſtow the tyme to read this rude diſcours of myn) to excuſe my language cōſidering my lang abſence out of my natiue contray: &amp; that the verity doeth beſt appeare, when it is leeſt painted, as the ſcripturs them ſelf do, vſing no eloquence, for ſimplex eſt veritatis oratio.
               
ſure I am if this ſubiect haid fallen in an eloquent mans hand, that it might haue beine traicted mair quicklie &amp; maire plainly and with greatter contentemente of the reader. I haue done what I culd, and not what I wald, except that in partie I haue done what I wald, ſeing I haue writtin to the ſimple &amp; vnlearned as I culd and according to my poſſibilitie, I knaw not if according to their capacitie. Howſoeuer it be I wil pray the good reader to tak my panes in good part. Perchance ſom other ſory to ſee a good cauſe ſo vnſkilfully hādled by me, wil tak occaſiō to do it, as it ſuld be done. whilk wilbe very eaſy to many learned mē, of whilks therbe guid nō
               bre (thanks be to God) in our Iland, wha may tak from me the victory of eloquēce, but not the honour of guid wil, wherin every mā may triomphe without preiudice of his cōpagnon.
            
               
Wherefor I pray the learned &amp; Godlie Catholik endeauour him ſelf to traict this ſubiect as it mereteth in the name of God, wha bliſſe ws all.
            AMEN.
         
      
      
         
            ERRATA
            
               
                  
                     pag. 36. kitk
                     kirk.
                  
                  
                     pag. 37. ſutter
                     ſuiter.
                  
                  
                     pag. 68. cōuenticules
                     conuenticles
                  
                  
                     pag. 70. mattres
                     matters
                  
                  
                     pag. 91. breuing.
                     brevving
                  
                  
                     pag. 88. mumdus
                     
                     
                        mundus.
                     
                  
                  
                     pag. 107. proue
                     proofe
                  
                  
                     pag. 108. libre
                     liber
                  
                  
                     pag. 109. mereth
                     mereteth
                  
                  
                     pag. 133. preiſthaed
                     preiſthead
                  
                  
                     pag. 155. hirk
                     kirk
                  
               
            
            
         
      
   

