
   
      
         
            A proclamation made by the high and mighty Fredericke by the grace of God King of Bohemia, &amp;c. Commanding all those his subiects which are now in the seruice of his majesties enemies, to repaire home within the space of 14. dayes, vpon paine of his highnes displeasure, and confiscation of goods and lands. Translated out of the Dutch coppie.
            Proclamations. 1620-08-18
            Bohemia (Kingdom). Sovereign (1619-1620 : Frederick I)
         
         
            
               1620
            
         
         Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01239
            STC 11352
            ESTC S119408
            99854615
            99854615
            20042
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01239)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20042)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 957:07)
         
         
            
               
                  A proclamation made by the high and mighty Fredericke by the grace of God King of Bohemia, &amp;c. Commanding all those his subiects which are now in the seruice of his majesties enemies, to repaire home within the space of 14. dayes, vpon paine of his highnes displeasure, and confiscation of goods and lands. Translated out of the Dutch coppie.
                  Proclamations. 1620-08-18
                  Bohemia (Kingdom). Sovereign (1619-1620 : Frederick I)
                  Frederick I, King of Bohemia, 1596-1632.
               
               [2], 6 p.   
               
                  [E. Allde],
                  Printed at Prague [i.e London] :
                  1620.
               
               
                  Dated at end: Giuen at our castle of Prague the xviij.th day of August, Anno Dom. 1620.
                  Actual place of publication and printer's name from STC.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Bohemia (Czech Republic) --  History --  1618-1848 --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-06
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-07
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-08
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2006-08
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               ❧ A Proclamation made by the High and Mighty FREDERICKE by the Grace of God King of BOHEMIA, &amp;c.
            Commanding all thoſe his Subjects which are now in the Seruice of his Majeſties Enemies, to repaire Home with in the ſpace of 14. dayes, vpon paine of his Highnes diſpleaſure, and Confiſcation of Goods and Lands.
            
               Tranſlated out of the Dutch Coppie.
            
            Printed at Prague, 1620.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            WEE FREDERICKE, By the Grace of GOD King of BOHEMIA, Count Palatine of the RHINE and Elector, Duke of BAVARIA, Marqueſſe of MORAVIA, Duke of LVTZELBVRG, and of SILESIA, Marqueſſe of Vpper and Lower LVSATIA, &amp;c.
            TO ALL moſt Illuſtrious Electors and Princes, our louing Cozens and Kinſmen, all friendſhip and good will to the outmoſt of our power: As alſo to the Right Honorable, Noble and generous, Earles, Barons, Lordes, and Gentlemen, together with the Mayors, Senate, Communalties, and all others whatſoeuer holding of vs and our Crowne of BOHEMIA, with the Inhabitants and Subiects of their hereditary Lordſhips, Lands, Teretories, Citties, Caſtles, Townes and Villages, Grace fauour and all welfare.
            
               MOST Illuſtrious Cozens, Electors and Princes, and moſt Honourable, Noble and generous loyall Subjects, Wee doubt not but that it is knowne and more then notorious vnto all aſwell within as without the Empire, into what moſt miſerable Eſtate this Crowne of Bohemia, with the incorporate Countryes thereunto adioyning, hath beene plunged and reduced by their Aduerſaries and their Aſſiſtants, Ayders and abetters, not onely without lawfull precedent cauſes, but alſo of meere enuy, &amp; an vnſatiable deſire of reuenge; whereby moſt cruelly &amp; barbarouſly, yea more then Turkes, Tartarians and Infidels there tyrannized vpon, and againſt the Bodies and goods of the Subjects and inhabitants of the ſaid Countries, and haue as it were recreated

their malicious mindes by ſhedding of innumerable innocent Chriſtian Blood, to the great and vnſpeakeable damage of many thouſands of poore people, and the moſt lamentable compaſſion of all confining Countries.
            And although in the meane while after lawfull and inforced abdication of Ferdinand the Emperour, and our Election, through Gods ſingular prouidence and ſpeciall Grace, by the vnanime, orderly, and vnreprouable conſent of our loyall Eſtates of Bohemia and the Countries appertaining thereunto, wee haue deſired and aymed at nothing more then that the moſt hurtfull and deuouring combuſtion, warre, and diſquietnes of theſe Countryes might ſpeedily bee appeaſed and redreſſed: As alſo that by the ripe, wiſe, prouident and carefull aduiſe and counſaile of our moſt illuſtrious Cozens, Allies and Friends, together with the conſent and wills of our loyall Eſtates, Subiects and Countries, wee haue not refuſed, but rather vpon ſerious well meaning motions (long ſince) haue accepted of and agreed vnto, and offered our Aduerſaries to enter into a comodious Truce, ceſſation of Armes, and peaceable treaty, and (aſmuch as poſſibly in vs lyeth, without impairing of our Royall Dignity, State, Honour and reputation) to proceed therein, That thereby the long deſired Peace &amp; tranquilitie of theſe Countries, by our helpe might bee reſtored and reeſtabliſhed, the moſt cruell and vnſpeakable tyranny, murtherings and deuaſtations auerted, the baniſhed wholſome Tranquility reobtained, and the Countries reſtored into their former priſtinate and peaceable

Eſtate. To the contrary we finde that our ſaid Chriſtian and moſt iuſt intent hath not onely ſlightly, but moſt ſcornefully bin altogether refuſed, and vtterly rejected, and which is more, not contented with the former barbarous and inhumane Tyrannies by the enemies already practiſed; they haue reſolued to ſtand vnto, and to continue in their ſaid forcible practiſes, proceedings and hoſtilitie.
            From whence it is eaſily to be gathered, and firmely to be concluded, that the intent and meaning of our Aduerſarie tendeth to this onely end and ſcope, that vnder the coulorable name of ſoueraigne Authority, together with many additions, hee may obtaine ayde and aſſiſtance, and thereby inſinuate himſelfe into the good will of diuers renowned Potenrates aſwell within as without the Empire, yea and of the meer vaſſailes and dependants of this our Crowne of Bohemia: wherunto they haue already made an entrance, by bringing in of forraine Souldiers, contrary to the ordinances and liberty of the Empire of Germany, and the Imperiall (by Oath) ratified capitulation.
            But for that our moſt conſtant Royall minde, neither will nor can indure to ſee our ſelues, together with the loyall and faithfull Eſtates and members of our Crowne of Bohemia, and the incorporate Countries thereof, as alſo ſo great a number of innocent poore people and godly Chriſtians longer to bee ſo moleſted, and by ſuch Calamities oppreſſed, being their lawfull King called by GOD, and Elected and Crowned by the Eſtates of the ſaid Kingdome, to whom by due and right true and ancient Cuſtome it belongeth.

And although wee haue already agreed and taken order with our aforeſaid obedient Eſtares, in what manner, by their helpe, counſaile and aſſiſtance, the Hoſtile dealing and vnchriſtianlike wronges might bee auerted, and redreſſed, further reſting in this confident hope, that none either of high or low eſtate or degree, being allyed vnto vs and our Crowne of Bohemia, either holding of vs in Fee, or by Oath of Allegiance, will in any wiſe, vnder any colour or intent whatſoeuer, hinder this our forcible defence and lawfull Action, nor yet attempt to inuade or oppreſſe vs and the Crowne of Bohemia with the incorporate Countries thereon depending, nor enter into the ſame by force of Warre and open hoſtility, eſpecially if hee will but vouchſafe to ponder and conſider the cauſes at large ſet foorth in our Deduction not long ſince Publiſhed: Notwithſtanding wee haue thought it conuenient to ſend forth this our friendly warning and admonition, as alſo our ſtrict Commaund and inhibition, (moued thereunto, aſwell by the Counſaile and aduiſe, as by the moſt humble and inſtant requeſt of our obedient Eſtates:) hereby friendly requiring and admoniſhing all and euery perſon and ſubiect of our ſaid Crowne of Bohemia, and ſtrictly Commaunding by vertue of our Royall Authority and Superiority as the Liedge &amp; Soueraigne Lord vpon that fealty, and Allegiance whereby they are bound vnto Vs and our Crowne of Bohemia, and the penalties and feodarie Ordinances therein made, that none of them of what Dignity, eſtate or Degree ſoeuer they bee, ſhall take part in any thing whatſoeuer with the Intimated

aduerſaries, againſt vs and the generall Eſtates of our Crowne of Bohemia, and the Countries appertaining thereunto, neither yet to ayde or aſſiſt them by any meanes with Men, money, Ordinance, Munition, Victuall, Intelligence, reliefe, or any other way that may be done, practiſed or ſiniſterly deuiſed. But rather (for that none will do nor attempt the ſame that is capable of Law and equity) if any ſuch or the like occurrances might happen &amp; fall out, to preuent, hinder and auert the ſame to the vttermoſt of their powers, and ioyne themſelues with all their Forces ſpeedily &amp; without all delay with Vs, our generals, Captaines, and Armies now imployed about the Freeing and releaſing of our ſaid Countries from ruyne, and ſubuerſion, to ayd and reſcue them, if neceſſitie require, and hereof not to faile as they will anſwer the contrary at their perils.
            Wee likewiſe hereby admoniſh and recall all and euery Captaine, Officer and common Soldier, Subiects vnto vs and the ſaid Crowne of Bohemia, mediately or immediately by fealty, Oath and ſeruice, or that haue and poſſeſſe any Territories, Lands, reuenues or goods either in Bohemia, or in the Fees thereon depending, bee it in any Citties, Townes, Caſtles, places or grounds, and are now in the pay and ſeruice of our aduerſaries, or their ayders and Aſſiſtants in this Warre againſt vs and the Crowne of Bohemia, and vnder the aforeſaid Penalties, moſt earneſtly and ſtrictly charge them, within the ſpace of Fourteene dayes next and imediately following vpon this our Royall inſinuation, and Mandate, ſignified and made knowne vnto them, to leaue, forſake, and abandon the ſaid ſeruice

and pay, of our Aduerſaries, (any Oath, promiſe, or Allyance by the which they are bound either vnto them or their ayders &amp; dependants notwithſtanding) hereby promiſing all ſecurity for Vs, and our Crowne vnto him, them, or any of them, that within the time herein limited, ſhall fully performe and obſerue this our will and deſire, and to the contrary continuing therein, certainly and fully purpoſing Irreuocably and without any reſtitution to proceed againſt them (according to the afore mentioned and menaced feodarie Penalties) that refuſe to imbrace this our gracious offer, Pardon and beneuolence, and goe on in their premeditated intents and purpoſes. Whereof let euery one hereby take notice, that will or intend to auoyde the Damage and perill, that may thereby enſue: for ſuch is our Will and pleaſure. In Witnes whereof, wee haue confirmed theſe our Letters with our Royall Seale.
            
               Giuen at our Caſtle of Prague 
                  the xviij.th. Day of Auguſt, Anno Dom. 1620. In the Firſt yeare of our Raigne of Bohemia.
                  
                Ad Mandatum Sacrae Regiae Maieſtatis proprium.
            
         
      
   

