
   
      
         
            A booke of christian ethicks or moral philosophie containing, the true difference and opposition, of the two incompatible qualities, vertue, and voluptuousnesse. Made by William Fulbecke, maister of Artes, and student of the lawes of England.
            Fulbeck, William, 1560-1603?
         
         
            
               1587
            
         
         Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01286
            STC 11409
            ESTC S105667
            99841393
            99841393
            5974
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01286)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5974)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 241:21)
         
         
            
               
                  A booke of christian ethicks or moral philosophie containing, the true difference and opposition, of the two incompatible qualities, vertue, and voluptuousnesse. Made by William Fulbecke, maister of Artes, and student of the lawes of England.
                  Fulbeck, William, 1560-1603?
               
               [88] p.   
               
                  Imprinted by Richard Iones, dwelling at the signe of the Rose and Crowne neere Holborne bridge,
                  At London :
                  1587.
               
               
                  Signatures: A-E F⁴.
                  Running title reads: Christian ethickes or morall philosophie.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Christian ethics --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-01
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-01
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-05
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-05
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A BOOKE OF
chriſtian Ethicks
or Moral Philoſophie:
Containing,
The true difference and
oppoſition, of the two incompatible
qualities, Vertue,
and Voluptuouſneſſe.
Made by William Fulbecke,
maiſter of Artes, and ſtudent
of the Lawes of England.
            At LONDON,
¶Imprinted by Richard Iones,
dwelling at the Signe of the
Roſe and Crowne neere
Holborne bridge.
1587.
         
         
            
            
            To the worſhipfull
and vertuous Gentleman,
M. George Seintpolle Eſquire:
William Fulbeck
wiſheth all proſperous
euentes.
            THe G
                  •
               aecians were wont to
conſecrate to their ſeuerall
Gods, ſeueral trees: as, to Apollo
the Laurell, becauſe he
was alwaies freſh in countenance:
The Oake to Iupiter, as being alwaies
ſtrong: the Oliue to Minerua,
as being alwaies fruitful of ſom
gallant inuentions: the Firre tree
to Neptune, as Preſident of ſhips,
alwaies ſwimming, and neuer ſinking:
the tree called Aeſculus to
the three ſonnes of Saturn, becauſe
the roote is in the bottome of the
earth, the trūck in the water, &amp; the
top in the cloudes. It behoueth me

(likewiſe) ſomwhat to the imitation
of them, to yeelde a reaſon why
I conſecrate to your worſhip this
Pamphlet, not as a maſſy Tree, but
as a ſlender fruit of a rooted good
will, though of a ſhort trauaile: in
it, I haue giuen pleaſure an ouerthrowe,
being not able for weakneſſe
to mannage in the fielde, and
not willing for wantonneſſe, to
giue carefull care to the bloodye
notes of the trumpet: and becauſe
it is vnpoſſible that you ſhould beholde
the face of one that flyeth
from you, therefore I am conſtrained,
but not much againſt my wil,
to preſent to your worſhippe, the
view of pleaſures back, vpō which
you may ſee ingrauen the picture
of hell, howſoeuer her viſage doe
repreſent the face of the firmamēt:
but becauſe you haue expreſſed
more in a godly life, then I haue
ſhadowed in a fewe godly lines, &amp;

becauſe your zealous conuerſatiō
is the image which my thoughtes
haue in this diſcourſe imagined:
therefore, I iudged it moſt conuenient
to ſubmit this book to your
fauourable conſtruction, not as a
monument of my victorie, but as
a memoriall of your ſingular modeſtie:
nor as a ſufficient counterpain
of your good behauiour, but
as a ſhort abridgement of your ample
ver
                  •
               ues: the friendlie countenāce
wherwith you haue alwaies
cheared my drooping fancies, was
the loadſtarre that drew me on, to
ſaile ſo far in this boyſterous Sea:
where, if the windes doe threaten
me aboue, and the water belowe,
yet as long as the ſtarre ſhineth, the
ſterne ſhall not faile. Leander loſt
his ankerholde for lacke of light,
and the Tunnies dare not ſwim
but when the moone doeth ſhine:
the light that I craue is your fauor,

the extinguiſhing that I am afraide
of, is mine own feare: wherefore,
changing feare with hope, I chāge
wordes with ſilence: beſeeching
God that your vertue may be extended
with your life, and your life
counterpaized with your happineſſe.
            
               Yours to the vttermoſt of his
power.
William Fulbecke
            
         
         
            
            To the curteous Reader.
            IT is reported of the Eagle, that
ſhe oppoſeth her yonglinges againſt the
face of the Sun, meaning therby, to make
trial, and haue certaine knowledge, which
bee natural Eagles, and whiche bee baſtardly
branches: they that can looke directly againſt
the Sun, ſhe admitteth for her owne,
thoſe that are conſtrayned to winke, ſhee extrudeth
out of her neſt. Her in I may reſemble
my ſelfe to the Eagle, who being the inuēter
of this treatiſe, haue laid it open to the eies of
alimen: that is, to the eies of the world: which
Ouid in his metamorphoſis applieth to the
Sun:Sol oculi Mundi. now if it be indewed with this felicitie,
that it can abide the ſtern viſage of ſeuere ſages,
the pearſing eies of curious Gentlemen,
&amp; the critical cenſures of the learned Academickes,
I wil chalenge and cheriſh it as a fortunate
iſſue: otherwiſe refuſe and reiect it,
as miſbegotten: hauing more of Amphitrio,
then of Iupiter: of fancie then of reaſō. I haue
long time ſacrificed my ſtudies to Angerona,
the Goddeſſe of ſilence, laying my finger on
my lippes, and ſaying nothing: foreſeeing
that if I ſhoulde rubbe the galle, rippe the
impoſtume, ranſacke the kannell of worldlye
opinions, (worldlye I tearme them,
as beeing bredde in the worlde, receiued
of the worlde, and practiſed by worldlings:
by worldlinges, I meane the moſt and the
worſte, moſt fonde and worſt minded), I
ſhoulde ſtirre vppe Waſpes, and haue my
wordes intertained with nipping gloſes, and

returned home with a bitter farewel: but ſith
it is no ſhame to write againſt ſuch, againſte
whome not to write is a great ſhame: I haue
taken courage vnto me, and brought againſt
thē a cōpleat legion. If I ſhold haue inueighed
by Satires, I ſhoulde haue ſeemed too curious:
if I ſhould haue ieſted by Epigrammes, I
might ſeem too captious: if by Commedies.
I ſhould coppy out their liues, they would accōpt
me too ſcurrilous: if by tragedies I ſhold
lamēt their maners, they wold iudge me too
ſcrupulous: therefore vſing the name of
Chriſtian Philoſophie, I doe meane nether to
fray thē, with the title, nor to flatter thē with
the treatiſe: but mine indeuour is ſpeciallie
bent, to allure them by lenitye, to win them
by parley, and to conuince thē rather by confeſſion,
then by confuſion: but if this firſt
trumpet which I haue ſounded againſt them
do giue me a ſigne of their obſtinate reſiſtāce
after this legion diſplayed, I will encounter
thē (by the grace of God) with a whole armie
of reaſons: ſetting thee curteous Reader on
the top of Tarpey, where thou maiſt eaſelye
behold the cōflict and warfar of the Romans
&amp; Sabines, fighting in the valleis of Hetruria:
neither bend thy body to the one ſide nor
wag thy hand to the other: but with both eies
behold both, ſo ſhal we both be beholden to
thee, and being iuſtified by a righteous ſē
               tēce,
giue thee the comēdation of an vpright
Iudge. Farewel &amp; be not partiall.
            
               Thine in Chriſt.
W. Fulbecke.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            The true difference
betweene Vertue,
and Voluptuouſnes.
            
               THere be ſeauen Artes whoſe
Principles are principallye
learned and practized of voluptuous
liuers: the art of diſſembling,
the Arte of blaſpheming: the
arte of deceiuing: the art of flattering:
the arte of diſdaining: the arte of louing:
the arte of dicing: ſeuen heades
of Hydra, ſeuen lewde ſiſters, and ſeuen
illiberall artes, not worthie the
name of artes, fith their beſt profeſſors
are the baddeſt men: &amp; they are
ſo much better in their artes, by how
much they ar worſe in their maners:
being therefore impudent, becauſe in
vanitie they are arteficial: and therefore
vaine, becauſe in their arts they
are impudent. Theſe be not the Muſes
inuentions, becauſe they are conioyned
with great diſhoneſtie, &amp; haue
a ranke ſmell of a lothſome impietie:
theſe be ye daughters of lady pleaſure,

neſtled in Pandoras boxe, and ſent
                  •
               
like Harpaies ouer the face of ye earth,
to take away from vs our wholſome
foode, and with their owne dunge to
defile 
                  •
               ur trenchers, being throughly
inſtructed of Circe to change men into
beaſtes, mens mindes into brutiſh
appetites, mens inuentions into fooliſh
dreames, and the reaſon of man
into a brutiſh paſſion. Circe drinketh
of theſe pottes to the worldlings, that
thirſt after pleaſures: but vertue hath
made a wall of partition betwixt the
pottes of Circe, &amp; the mouthes of the
vertuous: betwixt theſe Panther-like
odoures, and the noſtrelles of her followers:
betwixt theſe Cupids counterfeyting
Aſcanius, and the cloſette
of their mindes in whome vertue is
reſident. There is greate difference
betwixt Apollo his Schole, &amp; an olde
wiues Cottage, betwéen the Temple
of vertue, &amp; the Theater of pleaſure.
Pleaſure hath ſent abroad not long ago
thr
                  ••
                pretious works, and three delightful
cōments: the court of Venus,
the Caſtle of fancy, &amp; the Paradice of
pleaſure: books in which, ther is much

wit, and little vertue: whoſe ripeneſſ
                  •
               
heretofore, the frequent vſe in former
times, did ſufficiently argue: whoſe
rottenneſſe at this preſent, is by the vniuerſall
loathing and ſurfet of thoſe
that before were delighted with them
aboundantly teſtified. This is the property
of a voluptuous minde, when it
is ful gorged with honny, to caſt it vp
like galle: &amp; therefore it ſeemeth that
pleaſures iunkets would not haue turned
into any good blood, or wholeſome
nouriſhment. Diuers Poets haue
written for delight, but they haue alſo
written for profite: but many of their
readers being inchanted by pleaſures,
haue from their flowers gathered poiſon
like the ſpider, not honny like the
Bee: whereas contrariwiſe, the well
meaning mindes haue of theſe flowers
made ſoueraign preſeruatiues: let
ye 
               Troyan hiſtory be deliuered to a ſober,
wiſe, &amp; diſcreet ſcholler, he reapes
much honny, much delight, much cō
               moditie
by the reading thereof: if he
be examined what is the ſentēce, ſubſtance,
marrow, &amp; iuce of that hiſtory?
he wil anſwer wiſely &amp; ſincerely.
            
               
The ſtory which reports the Graekiſh wa
                  •
               
gainſt Barbary,Horat. Epiſtolarum. Lib. 1. for Paris loue vneleane:
            Doth ſtrange euents of Troian folly ſhewe,
and fruites of vliſſean pollicy containe.
            But if the ſence and ſignification of
that hiſtorie be demaunded of ſome
delicate ſtripling, of ſome Ouidiā Acontius,
an intēperate youngman, an
impure ſpider,Ouid in Epi. Acont. Non ſum qui ſoleam paridi
                     •
                   reprehendere factum. Nec quemque qui vir poſſit vt eſſe fuit. &amp; a ſecond Catiline: he
wil anſwere boldely, briefly, &amp; badly.
            I am not wont ſir Paris to reproue,
            Or any man that playes the man in loue.
            Beholde what aboundance of poyſon,
what ſtore of galle, what dregs of filthineſſe
this ſpider ſucketh out of the
flowers of this hiſtorie, with gréedye
&amp; vncōſecrate lips. Firſt, he gathereth
that the loue of Paris was not to bee
reprehended: next, that al they which
imitate the woeing of Paris are men:
they are men I graunt in name, but
in nature, they are lecherous goates,
and rutting Leopards: But as Alexander
the greate, did then moſt of all
tearme himſelfe a God, when he was
moſt eſtranged frō God, namely whē
hee was drunken: ſo theſe Acontij,
theſe ſ
                  •
               ctators of Paris, theſe men doe
then eſpecially boaſt of their māhood,

whē they become moſt brutiſh: what
thanks therefore, and what ſufficient
glorie can be rendred to vertue, that
preſerueth her ſcholers from ſuch peſtilent
poyſons, and ſuch froth of vices,
by godly admonitions, graue
preceptes, and ſolemne inſtitutes?
perſwading them by ſound reaſons,
whereof euery one is as ſtrong as Achilles,
that an hiſtory is not as it is
taken of the voluptuous, the trumpet
of Cupid, and the kalender of Venus:
but the library of knowledge, the vnſouldreſſe
of treacherye, the lanterne
of pollicy, ye doctreſſe of behauiour, the
regiſter of antiquity, the glaſſe of iuſtice:
But when ye voluptuous know
the bent of pleaſures bow, her browe
I would ſay, they are ready with full
ſaile, &amp; ſwift courſe to try theſe waies
that pleaſure hath chalked out &amp; preſcribed
vnto them, ſpending all their
rents, reuenues &amp; reuerſions vpon
the ſeruantes of Bacchus, vpon purpled
Apes, painted beggers, counterfaiting
R
                     •
                  ſcij Graduates in the
Epicures Schoole, horſeleeches of
money, the dogges of Verres, the

bloodhoundes of Fortune, which ranſacke
euerie corner for coyne, hauing
apte noſes for the ſmelling of
Golde and Siluer, and when they are
inſtructed and leſſoned by ſuch hungry
Gnatoes, profeſſors of all impudē
               cie,
and practiſers of all impiety, they
are matriculated, and nurſed in theſe
delightes, in which, none are conuerſant
but Venuſſes pullets and Neroes
whelps, politike, delicate, gallant tenderlings,
which are faſt linked to pleſure,
and vſe her at their luſt, but they
knowe not her diſeaſe, they know not
her companion, they knowe not her
ſauce. Her diſeaſe is impuritie, her cō
               panion
is penaltie, her ſauce is ſorrow:
they may for a while ſing thoſe
Caroles yt 
               Penelopes woers did ſing,
wreſting the ſweetneſſe of their Cytharne,
to the loſſe of their time, &amp; their
owne diſprofite: as Horace reporteth
of certaine young men which were
wonte to ſléepe till midday, and Ad
ſtrepitū cytharae ceſſatū ducere curā.
By ſound of harpe, to bring their cares to reſt.
            
            But this dittye will be cloſed vppe
with a dumpe.
            
            Nocet empta dolore voluptas.
            
               The pleaſure is nought that is bought with
payne.
               Horat. Epiſtola
                     •
                  . lib. 1. This I doe not ſpeake to diſproue
the delightfull harmony of muſike,
which I accompt moſt commendable,
but to glaunce at the idle life of
luxurious perſonnes, whoſe eares are
continually fedde with the hearing of
ſuch ſoundes. Orpheus his harp is not
to be diſpraiſed, which did draw men
frō death to life, but ye foulers whiſtle
is not to be heard, which allureth the
hearers to the ſnares of death, &amp; ye pit
of deſtructiō: Euterpes pipe deſerueth
audience, becauſe it is the pipe of one
of the Muſes: but the pipe of Leucoſia
is to bee debarred from our eares, becauſe
the piper is a Syren: the harpe of
Achilles ſounded with grauity, and
was a kinde of motiue to the warlike
courage: but on the effeminate
harpe of Paris, nothing was played
but amatorious ſonnets, and ridiculous
Iigges. Poetrie in former times
made a progreſſe through the worlde,
being deſirous to heare the ſoundes
of the Inſtrumentes, that in thoſe
dayes were vſed, and beeing

accompaned with the nine Muſes, ſhe
liſtned to their melodye, ſhee hearde
Pan puffing on a reed: the Arcadians
creaking with whiſtles: Triton roring
with a ſhell, in ſteede of a trumpette:
the ſhepheardes of Scithia,
winding an oaten ſtrawe: ſhe heard
the Coribants tinckling on their braſen
Baſons: ſhee hearde the Moenades
ſhouting in the aire with a clamarous
bellowing: Poetrie partlye taking
pittie, &amp; partlye being aſhamed
of this deformed and barbarous muſike,
gaue to mankinde, for the pipe
of Pan, the hiſtories of Clio: for the
whiſtles of the Arcadians, the tragedies
of Melpomene: for Tritons ſhel,
the Cōmedies of Thalia: for the ſhepheards
oaten ſtrawe, the pipe of Euterpe:
for the braſſe of the Coribants,
ye harp of Therpſicore: for ye howling
of the Moenades, the verſes of Calliope:
which ſhe did not beſtowe in cō
               ſideration
of the Epicures fanſie, neither
to inchaunt ye mindes of laſciuious
perſons with a ſenceles ſecuritie,
neither did ſhe make thē y• idle mans
Ephemerides, whereby he might deceiue

the long &amp; irkſome time, the redēption
of which, cannot by any value bee
procured.
            Nulla coelum reparabile gazâ.
            No golde can time reuerſe.
            The loſſe of which, if it were throughly
cōſidered, would make vs loath our ſtale
muſike in compariſon of the ſweet ſounding
melodie of time: which is the reporter
of things moſt deſired, the Corner
of trueth, whoſe deſcāt, though it be ſomwhat
crabbed, yet, that to which we apply
our attendance, we wiſh ſhoulde rather
be true, then forged: rather a matter
of certainty, then a flying fable. But the
ſecure &amp; voluptuous Epicure careth not
for this aduātage of time, ſo he may reſt
himſelfe in his Ladies lappe, and haue
his eares throughly tickled with a muſicall
concordance: he is content that the
circle of the Sun ſhould be rouled backward
&amp; forward, ſo that he continue ſtill
in iolitie, without anye interruption of
his pleaſures: Scilicet hoc eſt viuere: but
when the date of his time is almoſt expired,
&amp; arriued at the point, from which it
took ye beginning, then he ſtādeth bouud
before the tribunall ſeat of time, and he

thus accuſeth him: vnfruitfull ſluggard
didſt thou wake or ſleep all thy life time?
If thou didſt wake, what worke haſte
thou left behinde thée either viſible to the
eie or memorable to the minde? where
be the monuments of thy labours? wher
be the gaines of thy trauailes? where
are the fruites of thy life? If thou didſt
ſleep, and thy actions were only a dream,
that dreame was a paſſion but of action:
thou haſt not a print to ſhewe, but that
thou mayeſt ſée the bounty and riches of
time: awake out of thy ſléepe, waſh thine
eies, and thou ſhalte clearelye beholde
what opportunities haue eſcaped thee.
Thou ſeeſt on thy right hand, the fieldes
into the which thou didſt wander ſometime,
but I alway preſuppoſe as in a
dreame: thou didſt there onely ſuruay
the colours of flowers, thinking perhaps
of the tranſmutation of them into flowers,
whom the panges of loue did conſume:
thou didſt reſt on the gréene graſſe
as on a cuſhion, hauing a minde ſo dead
and deſtitute of the intellectuall facultie,
that thou didſt hide and burie thy ſelfe
vnder the ſhadowes of trées: not knowing
that the gréene Liceum was the

Schole of the Peripatetikes, and Vmbrifera
Academia, the Schoole of the Academikes:
but thou, wiſhing that all
thy body were changed into an eye, like
Argus, that thou mighteſt all thy lyfe
time, haue nothing els but coloures in
veiwe, or els wiſhing that all thy bodye
were made a noſe, as Catullus deſired,
that thou mighteſt ſpende
                  •
                all thie
daies in ſmelling to the fragrant flowers,
and perfuming hearbes, didſt make
a pauſe in theſe fancies: if thou haddeſt
bended thine eies but a litle from theſe
theſe things, thou mighteſt haue eſpied ye
ſeely Ant or Piſmire, of wich thou mighteſt
haue learned to haue takē paines, to
haue liued by thy pains, to haue reioyced
after thy paines: to haue takē paines by
ſeeing thē martch in the pathway to the
fieldes for their ſuſtenāce, carrying their
burthens on their ſhoulders, haſtning &amp;
returning wt great ſpéed, notwithſtāding
the great waight: to haue liued by thy
paines, by ſéeing thē to be ſo carefull of ye
nipping winter, hurding vp the corne in
the graniers, piling it in the barnes, cutting
it into partes, yt it maynot grow: to
haue reioiced after thy paines, in that
thou haſt preuēted the ſharpnes of hūger

and in that thou haſt ſufficient to ſatiſfie
natures demand: but look what ſhineth
ouer thy head, the gliſtering heauen, the
ſtarrie firmament, which thou didſt gather
to be nothing els then the candleſticke
of the world, made to none other
end, then to giue light, &amp; to diſcouer the
dennes of Moldwarpes in the earth: not
conſidering that by the acceſſe, &amp; departure
of the Sun, things increaſe and decreaſe:
that by the waine and full of the
Moone, the Sea ebs and flowes: that by
the particular influence of particular
Starres, ſuch and ſuch alterations are
framed in the earth: the diuers motions
and effectes of thoſe cauſes, might haue
led thée by the hand, to the firſt mouer, in
whoſe ample gouernment of all things,
thou mighteſt haue hadde a bottomleſſe
conſideration of peareleſſe value, that
would hane ſtirred vp an admiration in
thy minde, admiration would haue cauſed
inquiſition, &amp; inquiſition would haue
engendred knowledge: which wold haue
bene a great ornament vnto thée, and a
great 
                  •
               urtherāce to further matters: but
now that thou art ignoraunt, blame not
me, wrich haue often giuē thée warning
to call thy wittes together: When thou

waſt tending from youth to manhoode, 
                  •
               
drewe lines in thy viſage, which ſignified,
that thy life did waſte: and by them
I writ vpon thy face, the ſeconde age:
when, from manhood thou waſt twining
to old age, thy den
                  •
               s and riueled chéeks,
thy toothleſſe chaps, thy white and hoary
heares▪ I ſent as meſſengers vnto thee,
wherby I foreſhewed the third age, that
was approching: now therefore, bluſh at
thine owne ſluggiſhneſſe, be aſhamed of
thy lingring, and ſith there be no ſignes
or lineaments, of former knowledge in
thee, I propoſe thy dotage as a ſpectakle
to be laughed at. This ſharpe reprehenſion
may perhappes, leaue prickles in
the mindes of ſluggards, but the remorſe
quickly vaniſheth. Icarus doth not feare
his fall, til the greateſt part of his wings
be melted, and his bodie do kiſſe the face
of the water: but of all the knowledge
that ouerpaſſe them, the miſticall knowledge
of their ſaluation being hidden frō
their eies, &amp; debarred from their hartes:
is with a whole Ocean of teares to bee
lamented, if out of a Flinte any water
may be wreſted. It may be comprehended
in two lines, and yet the fleſhlie Epicure

could not afforde halfe an howers
ſtudy to the repetition and rehearſal of it
in his minde,1 Timoth. cap. 3. that it might be a perpetuall
monumēt imprinted in his memory:
God did appear in the fleſh, was iuſtified
in the ſpirite, was ſéen of Angels, was
preached to nations, was beléeued in the
worlde, was receiued in glorie. This being
perfectly had wtout booke, wold haue
bene a ſoueraign retentiue frō the luſtes
of the fleſh: but pleaſure, being a ſwéet &amp;
flattering Enchauntreſſe, doth ſmoothlie
inſinuate her ſelf into the mindes of mē,
&amp; there dwelleth as Helena dwelt in the
Citty of Troy: who pleaſed the Troyans
but to theire miſerye: whoe ſoung delightfully,
but was too delightfully hard:
for the honny of words, is a poiſon to the
heart: &amp; a ſwéet ſound in the a
                  •
               re, is a Siren
in the eare: Thus it is euident that
the ſtudy or exerciſe wherunto voluptutuous
&amp; effeminate perſons, do wholy addict
thēſelues, is nothing els but ye whetſtone
of vanity, the miſtres of miſdemenour,
&amp; coſſin germane to idlenes. Nowe
it remaineth to be diſcuſſed, what other
abuſes they haue in the cōmon courſe of
their life.Saluſt in coniur. 
               Saluſt did generally diſcribe ye
               
gluttony of delicate trēchermen, whē he
did particularly diſcipher the inordinate
appetite of the Romanes: the Romanes
(ſaith he) to ſatiſfye their bellies, ſought
out al thinges yt could be found either in
ſea, or on the earth: they did not tarry til
hunger or thirſt ouertook thē, but they did
preuēt theſe by an arteficial appetite: before
the diluge, the onely treaſure on the
earth was wine, the people did eate and
drinke, maried &amp; gaue in mariage, riſe vp
to play, and vſed all kinde of dalliance euen
vntill the daye wherein the windowes
of Heauen were opened vpon
them, till the waters had oueflowed and
diſfigured the earth, that the very ſhard
of a drinking cuppe could not be ſéene in
the worlde: It is a verye vnnaturall
thing that the belly béeing made by nature,
a place of excrements, ſhoulde bee
made an Idol: but it is a greater ſhame
that the Idoll of the beaſtlie Cyclops
ſhoulde be made a God to Chriſtians,
which the true GOD will at the
length confounde, together with all
them alſo that make it a God.
            It is ſtraunge to ſée the appetite of
man: that whereas beaſts are contented

with that food which nature hath appointed
for them, and take no more thereof,
then that quantity which nature hath alotted
vnto them: man ſhould ſo far ſurpaſſe
the limits of reaſon, and reuerence
due to nature: that with an vnſatiable deſire
he followeth thoſe things, which are
diſcommodious, pernitious, and peſtilent
vnto him. And although in the kinde of
beaſts, the Lion is moſt i
                  •
               cōtinent, moſt
rauenous, and gréedy of his pray: and be

                  •
               ide this,Ariſtot. lib de Hiſtor. animalium. 8. cap. 5. hath ā exceſſiue appetite, which
cannot be ſtanched without great ſuperfluitie
of nouriſhmēt: yet for the ſpace of
thrée daies, or at the leaſt two two daies
after, he is fully ſatiſfied: &amp; the Wolues
when they are gaunted with hunger, do
eat rather earth and clay, then they will
violentlie ruſh vpon the beaſtes of their
owne kinde.Ioſeph Ben Gord. This abſtinence is greater
then Mirianis, who though ſhe were of
ſingular behauiour amongſt the Iewes,
yet could not abſtain from gnawing the
bones of her owne childe: and man to
augment the gréedy worm whereof he is
poſſeſſed, doth inuent and vſe daily, ſauces,
ſirupes, brothes, mixtures: that may
pricke his ſtomacke forwarde, to craue

more then it may well containe,Iohn Baptiſt Gello incite
                     •
                  
                wherby
there ariſeth ſuch ſuperfluitye, and ſuch
ſuperabundance of naughty humours in
the bodie, that there bee more then fiftie
kindes of diſeaſes ingendred in the eies:
and by ſuch varietye of taſtes, wee are
prouoked to drinke ſo much, that a great
nūber of diſeaſes: as Catarres, rewmes,
ſwellinges, goutes, dropſies, doe ſhake
the foundation of our healthe, and the
whole frame of our bodie, and if the body
were only cloyd with the inconueniencies
that ariſe of ſurfeiting, the riot of
banquets, were more tollerable and leſſe
reprouable: but ſith Corpus onuſtum
Heſternis vitijs,
               Horat. 
               animū quò
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   praegrauat
ipſum. The bodie ſtuft with hoſterne cates,
doth ouercharge the minde.
            
            Our trenchers are to be waſhed with
our teares, our tables whereat we ſitte
drinking, beluing, and carouſing, are to
be accounted engines and ſnares, laid by
the deuils ſubtiltie, to intrap our ſoules:
our coſtly viandes are to be accompted
the lures of gluttonie: our muſicall and
ſwéete ſounding inſtruments which are
prepared to make the minde more cheerfull
and frollicke: are no better to bee eſteemed

then alluring Sirens, which eate
them whom they delight, and kill them
with their téeth, whom they haue called
with their tongues. It were infinite to
number the greate miſhappe that hath
chaunced, &amp; the outragious crueltie that
hath bin committed, after that the minde
hath bene ouercaſt with the miſte or exhalation
that riſeth from the ſtomacke
ſurcharged with delicates. The Cittie of
the Troyans was drowned in wine, before
it was burnt by fire: Hieruſalem
was ouerflowen of gluttonie and drunkenneſſe,
before it was ouerrun of the
Romanes and Turkes: the Aegiptians
were not ſo much ouercom'd by armed
men,
                  
                     •
                  irgil 
                     •
                  eneid▪ 1 as by the banquettes of Cleopatra:
Catiline did beſiege Rome with a troope
of pleaſ
                  •
               res, before he did threaten it
wt an army of ſouldiers: Dido was firſt
inchanted of Liber Pater, before ſhe was
bewitched of the boy Cupid: Nero was filled
with the wines of Campania before
he was poyſoned wt the counſail of Anicetus,
&amp; ther was in his ſtomack a flood of
Nectar, before ther was Furor in mente
or Ferrū in manu: ye principal cauſe why
ye 
               Perſians were enemies to the Lidians,
               
was becauſe of the good cheere that they
found iu Lidia.
               Herod o
                     •
                  . lib. 1. Now if any man thinke
that the mind being a ſubſtance immateriall
cannot be infected by any contagiō
procéeding frō the body, he ſhal perceiue
his iudgement to be erronious, both by
cauſe, &amp; by example: the ſoule I graunte
might liue-like an angell in the body, &amp; it
doth as yet ſhine in the corporall lumpe,
but tanquam coelum in coeno. Like an heauen
in a dunghill. It is ſo nigh the bankes
and borders of this earthly Tabernacle:
nay, it is ſo incloſed within the walles &amp;
gates thereof that it muſt of neceſſitie be
defiled with the duſt that ariſeth within
the walles: but to finde out the reaſon I
will vſe a very brieſe diſcourſe, which
notwithſtanding, ſhall carrye ſome taſte
of Philoſophie. There be ſome thinges
that belong to the ſoule alone, as reaſon,
meditation, reminiſcence: ſome thinges
to the bodie alone, as heauineſſe, augmentation,
diminution, and that ſtrēgth
which the Latines call Robur, the Graecians
Iſchus One thinge there is which
is common both to the ſoule and the body,
and that is, Appetitus or vis concupiſcentiae,
The appetite or force of concupiſcence
which being an ambidexter or

paraſite both to the ſoule &amp; body, inueagleth
the ſoule by the ſenſes of the body, &amp;
deceiueth ye body by the liking of ye ſoule:
for, when the minde hath made ye maior
propoſition of the ſillogiſme: Whatſoeuer is
pleaſant and ſweet, is to be liked of: the bodie
by the force &amp; vertue of ye ſenſes, maketh
the minor propoſition: (Dainty cheare is pleaſant
and ſweet,) the appetite doth ſtraightway
conclude: Ergo, Dainty cheare is to be
liked off. the natural &amp; carnal mā, hauing
learned this leſſon, triūpheth in his own
conceit, &amp; is both waies bent, either to cō
               fute
ye Stoicke, or defend ye Epicure. but
ye modeſt &amp; wel iudging mind, can make
a diſtinction of pleaſant thinges, as alſo
of pleaſure: there is a pleaſure that is,
Dulcis &amp; decocta, Sweet and liquid, which
melteth as ſoone as it féeleth the heat of ye
mouth, &amp; is digeſted as ſoone as it is deuoured:
ſo that being not able to abide ye
ſtamp of ye téeth, it is rather to be accoū
               ted
ſuperfluous droſſe, thē ſubſtātial mettel.
Ther is another pleſure: y• is, Auſtera
&amp; ſolida, Sincere and ſound: which though
it be not as pleaſant as ſpice, yet it is as
neceſſary as ſalte, &amp; though it do not ſlide
through the bodye as through a conduite,

yet it deſcendeth into the minde as y• euening
ſhower into the caues of the earth:
the true pleaſure is neither painted with
colours, nor blanched wt cookery, neither
ſod in a pot, nor roaſted on a ſpit, but the
dew thereof droppeth from heauen, &amp; the
fruitefull effectes thereof are euident to
the view of euery Chriſtian cogitation.
Now that we haue ſhewed the reaſon of
this Simpathy: it remaineth that ſome
examples be ſent for to illuſtrate this
treatiſe: to know therefore, that the diet
of the body doth leaue ſome colour, &amp; impreſſion
in the minde, conſider ye diet and
diſpoſitiō of y• 
               Gothes, &amp; Tartarians, who
becauſe they are 
                  •
               ed with mans bloode, &amp;
drink the gore of their anceſtors, in the
ſkuls of their anceſtors: are therfore cruell,
vnmercifull, &amp; ſauage: thirſting after
mans bloode, and ſucking at the ſkin for
blood, as the childe at his mothers dugs
for milke. The Parthians that licke water
like dogges, are couragious in warfare,
&amp; no whit effeminate: the Turkes
meaſuring, &amp; deuiding their cōmons by
waight and ballance, haue their wit and
magnanimitye freſh againſt the furie of
the enemies▪ but the Indians becauſe

they are continually nouriſhed with ſpires,
which kind of nouriſhment▪ is verie
ſlender: therfore they are melſh hearted,
fearful, &amp; fugitiue, to whom I may rightly
compare the men of Saba, which countrey
is very fruitful of ſumptuous delicates,
but very barren of good ſouldiers:
like vnto theſe are the Agrigutini, whoſe
mindes, whether proſperity flatter, or aduerſity
threatē, are continually in Patinis:
the ancient Britons are reported to
haue bin very valiant &amp; victorio
                  •
               s,
                  
                     •
                  ion in vita Neronis but
they are alſo reported to haue liued very
hardly, to haue vſed roots for their bread,
hearbes for their meat, the rawe iuice of
wilde fruites for their oyle, water for
wine, trées for houſes, &amp; y• foggy vapors
of fenniſh groundes, for the ſmell of perfumes.
And geuerally it is alwaies ſeene
y• in the coldeſt Climates &amp; frozen Alpes
which afforde no banquetting cheere, the
beſt ſouldiers haue giuē a notiſe of their
valiant courage. Now when the belly is
wel warmed with ſwéet iunkets, then
Venus ſpreadeth a delightful carpet, vnto
which the eie and affection giue a diligent
attendance, the mind beginneth to
burn in luſt▪ &amp; to make excurſion beyond
the limits of reaſon: Solomon who had

had experience of both, affirmeth y• ſame.
Look not vpon wine (ſaith he) when it glittereth
and the colour therof ſhineth in a glaſſe:
               Prouerb. 23. 
               it goeth
in with delight, but in the end it wil bite like a
ſnake, &amp; like the
                     •
                  cockatrice it wil ſprinkle poiſō
               
Thus far of glottony: but how doth Venery
follow, Thine eies (ſaith Solomon)
ſhal behold ſtrange women, and thy heart ſhall
vtter peruerſe things, thou ſhalt be like one that
ſleepeth in the midſt of the ſea, and like a ſleepie
gouernour hauing loſt the healme. Sith therfore
by the iudgemēt of this King, whoſe
minde was ful fraught with wiſedome:
theſe two inſtruments, made of the deuil
to ſeduce men from good behauiour to E
               
                  •
               icuriſme,
are linked &amp; conioyned. Miſe
               
                  •
               able
is ye ſtate of theſe, y• make pleaſure
the mother of theſe two) their Goddeſſe,

                  〈◊〉
                think no life happy, vnleſſe it be ſwéet
               
                  •
               ed
wt the ſugured iuice of a carnal dele
               
                  •
               ation,
ye ſeek for heauen in the center of

                  •
               ell, &amp; care not how brutiſh they become,

                  •
               o they be not couered with the hides &amp;

                  •
               orns of beaſts: but let him that mindeth

                  •
               o ſée good daies, &amp; followe Chriſte (which
ought to be y• principal profeſſion of chriſtiās)
make a couenāt wt his eies &amp; eares
frō beholding &amp; hearing of vanity: when
the epicures banquet is as bitter to our
taſt as gall, &amp; the ſwéet ſauour of fragrāt

pouders as lothſome as y• hēlock, then is
an arriual made at y• hauē of chriſtian ſecurity,
thē are we entred into y• ſtraight
way which is indéed a large field of happineſſe.
But yet when we haue attayned
this many incūbrāces wil be appoſed againſt
our quietnes, and the better our
ſtats is, the more is the deuils enuy and
hatred: but this muſt not diſcomfort vs.
None can climbe to the toppe of heauen
wtout ſweating: &amp; God (as Plato ſayth) ſelleth
his benefits for labour and trauaile.
Wée muſt conſider that the worlde will
neuer ceaſe to be deceitfull, the deuill neuer
to be malitious, and the fleſh wil neuer
intermit his combat &amp; conflicte with
the ſpirit, as long as we are in this painfull
pilgrimage. We muſt ſuffer the bluſtering
tempeſt of aduerſitie, the ſharpe
edge of temptation, and the fiery dartes
of the deuil, we fight againſt powers and
principalities, and therfore may be woū
               ded,
if not ouercome. Our affections may
become perfidious vnto vs, betraying vs
to our enemies, and therefore being in
daunger both of forraine and of domeſticall
foes: we had néed to be very vigilant
&amp; circumſpect, leaſt conſpiracy accoōpliſh
that, which violēce could not bring to pas

When a Chriſtian is beſieged with
temptation,Iacob. 1. let him reioyce, for the
Lorde proueth before hee approoueth,
and trieth before he truſteth, whom he
loueth them he chaſtiſeth, and his gold
is tryed in the middeſt of the furnace.
If we may obtaine glory by victory,
then we muſt fight to obtaine the victory.
No man is crowned before he ouercommeth,
and no man ouercōmeth
but hee that lawfully ſtriueth, let him
think as he is prouoked to fight, ſo hee
may be prouoked to a crowne of glory.
Yea, one can not miſſe of the promotion,
vnleſſe he willingly forſake it: his
hart cannot faint, his ſtrength cannot
fayle, except he wyll. To be willing to
fight, is to fight couragiouſly, and as
long as that will continueth, God will
countenaunce that courage. O the excéeding
felicitye of a Chriſtian manne,
whoſe onely wyll béeing directed by
Gods will, is more pearceable then
ſtéele, and more impenetrable then the
ſtrong Rocke, whoſe wiſhe atchiueth
the victorye, and whoſe victorye is far
beyonde his wyſhe. If wee ſuruey the
affaires of the world, we ſhall find that

there is no lucre ſo vile, nor any gayne
ſo groſſe, but ere wee can compaſſe it,
we muſte ſtretch ioyntes and ſinewes,
we muſt ſweate and breath, vſe reſtles
and endles laboure, which when it is
purchaſed, vaniſheth like a ſmokie exhalation,
and like a bubble in the water,
riſeth and faleth in an inſtant. The
Merchant man thinketh himſelf a Monarche,
and vaunteth of his increaſe,
when after a tenne yeeres nauigation
after a thouſand diſcommodities, daungers
and diſaduantages, he hath gotten
a little more treaſure then hee had before.
            The Souldier when he hath taſted
the bitter fruites of warfare, when he
hath worne his bodie, altered hys complexiō,
diminiſhed his health, loſt ſome
principall member of hys bodie, howe
large ſoeuer his ſtipend bee, yet he is
like a dead Truncke that hath loſt the
brauerie of his boughes. In ſéeking the
fauour of noble men, in getting and
reteyning the frendſhip of equalles, in
the ambitious labouring for honours
and dignities, in y• whording of coyne,
and ſcraping of commoditie, in cloſing

and diſcloſing, digging and deluing, turning
areable into paſturable, and paſturable
into areable, woodes into waſtes,
and waſtes into woodes, in building
and battering, in turning ſquare
into round, and triangles into quadrangles,
is ſuch an infinite labour, and a
world of buſines, that he which waigheth
in a ballance bothe the care and the
commoditie, ſhall find an ounce of commoditye
for a pounde of care, and hee
that putteth theſe thinges in practiſe,
ſhall lyke a peruerſe Al
                  •
               umiſt, diſtill
a pennie out of a portague. Therefore
let him that mindeth to be a true Chriſtian,
deſpiſe theſe tranſitory, corruptible
and contemptible things, for which
the worldly myzer giueth no truſte to
his eyes, hath the byrdes of the ayre in
ſuſpition, feareth leaſt his owne behauiour
doo bewray his baſe and barbarous
affections. Let him erecte and
life vp his mind to the celeſtiall and diuine
ſolaces, which neither eye hath
ſéene, nor eare hath heard, nor the hart
of man is able to imagine, to the purſuing
of which, the mindes of worldly
Mammoniſtes are ſlowe footed, drooping

and continually dreaming of the
eternitie of their barnes, when the very
Weaſels before their eyes doo deuoure
theyr corne, and euen againſt
theyr wylles they are drawne of God
to heauenly and ſpirituall things: vpon
which they looke as Cerberus looked
vpon the ſunne, when he was drawne
out of hell, verie ſtraungly &amp; vn
                  ••
               thly:
and in déede theyr blea
                  •
               ed eyes cannot
long behold the brightnes of the diuine
Maieſtie. Nowe if the worldly felicitie
could be attained without labour, as
it were in a traunce, &amp; as if we ſhould
let it in at a windowe: or if Fortune
would throw into our nets our ſelues
ſléeping, as ſhee is fayned to haue dealt
with her loue Polycrates, then there
might be a kinde of reaſon framed by
our fancye, and it might perhappes bee
beléeued with an vncircumciſed credulity,
that it were a great deale better to
ſerue the world then God: but if there
be more wearines in walking, as a
worldling, thē labouring as a Chriſtian,
if to be choaked and ſtrangled with
the cares of this world, be an infinite
torment: if to ſée the conſcience beſieged

with an hundred hels, and to feele
the racking and renting thereof, as it
were with a thouſande fleſhhookes, be
an intollerable griefe, then happie and
thriſe happy is the mortified Chriſtian
that is ſatiſfied with the ſwéete content
of a meane eſtate, and the moderate
portion that God hath allotted him. If
we be no where leſſe troubled then
in the wayes of God, and no where
more wearied then in the way of ſinners,
as that voice of damned perſons
beareth witnes: Laſſati ſumus in via
iniquitatis,
               Sapi. 5. 
               we were wearied in the way
of wickednes: is it not an extreame
madnes, rather to beſtow our labours,
landes and life vppon thoſe thinges
from which wee muſt very ſhortly depart,
not into a newe Paradiſe, but into
an eternall dungeon, where there is
continuall g
                  •
               aſhing of teeth, and the
worme neuer dieth, then to conſecrate
our liues and liuinges vnto the Lorde,
and for his ſake to abide the vttermoſt
brunt of tribulatiō, whē for our paines
wee ſhall haue a ſurpaſſing reward:
for the honour that wee héere loſte, an
vnchaungeable honour, for the pleaſure

that héere we forſake, an ineſtimable
felicitie? beſides all this, what a ſinguler
peace, and what a delicate banquet
is a good conſcience, not wexing pale
with villanous cogitations, which is
better then all the Epicures delights,
then all tranſitory pleaſures, then all
curious &amp; exquiſite inticements, wherwith
the iugling worlde doth ſophiſtically
delude vs. What pleaſure can
there bee in the riches of this worlde,
which before they are purchaſed, doo
weary vs, when they are poſſeſſed, doo
infatuate vs, and when they are loſte,
doo excruciate vs. Without queſtion,
the ſoules of the wicked are toſſed hether
and thether, with perpetual cares,
with moſte intricate perplexities, and
griefes innumerable. Thys the Lorde
hath affirmed, who as he cannot deceiue,
ſo he cānot be deceiued,
                  
                     •
                  ſay, 57, 
               Cor impii
quaſi mare feruens, the hart of a wicked
man is like a raging Sea, that can take
no reſt:
                Nothing is quiet vnto them,
nothing peaceable, the trenchers wheron
t
                  •
               ey cutte theyr meate with trembling
handes can beare witneſſe, the
meate yt ſtayeth in
                  •
               theyr chaps whilſt

they are thinking miſchiefe, can beare
witnes, their ſlow &amp; imperfit digeſtion
may beare witnes: the leanes, palenes,
and wannes of their chéekes may beare
witnes. They are affraid of all things,
ſuſpect all things, and euerye thing is
a meſſenger of death vnto them. Who
would therefore aemulate them, or immitate
theyr manners. Who hauing
forgotten theyr dignitie, their heroycal
nature, and theyr heauenly Monarche,
béeing made frée men are become bondſlaues
to the worlde, lyuing miſerably,
dying more miſerably, and moſt miſerably
like to be afflicted wyth eternall
flames. There is none, but he ſeeth
theſe things, as cleerely as hee beholdeth
the Meridian Sunne: but there is
not one amongſt a thouſande that doth
theſe thinges, which he knoweth are to
be practiſed, but we cleaue as yet to the
durt, wallow in the myre, and though
the loathſome ſatietie of pleaſures doo
breede a ſurfeit vnto vs, yet cure we
the poyſon of pleaſures with the hemlocke
of obſtinacie, and though our
myndes doo ſometime reclayme vs
from ſuch vanities, or rather impieties,
yet ſuch cogitations are ſoone extinet.

We aſſigne the regiment of our
mindes to a fooliſh Phaeton, namely to
the ſecure ſenſualitye of an appetite
charmed with pleaſures. Let a Chriſtian
man conſider, what a daungerous
thing it is, to liue amongſt them day
and night, whoſe life is not onely an
inticement to ſin, a wicked May-game
and a moſte pernitious example, but
doth wyth al endeuour, bende it ſelfe to
the ouerthrowe of vertue, vnder the
Emperour Beliall, vnder the ſtanderde
of death, and vnder the ſtipende of hel,
wageing battail againſt heauē, againſt
the Lord and againſt his annoynted.
            Theſe are they whom God hath deliuered
into paſſions of ignominie, into
a reprobate ſence, to doo thoſe thinges
which are vndecent,Rom, 1, ful of all iniquitie
full of enuy, hatred, deceite, malignity,
poyſenfull, blaſphemers of God, contumelious,
proude, diſdainfull. inuentors
of miſchiefe, vnwiſe, diſſolute, diſorderly
without affection, without mercye,
who though they ſée the iuſtice of
God, yet wyll not acknowledge it beeing
ſo far from excuſe, that they which
ſeeke to cloake and colour theyr impuritie,

are the ſeauenfolde ſonnes of the
deuill, &amp; are worthy to be racked wyth
wilde horſes till they confeſſe ye truth.
And therefore let them which are zealous
in the Lordes wayes, ſeperate
themſelues from the company of ſuch
to whom the name of God is odious,
vertue vnpleaſant, Religion a baſe profeſſion,
godlines a ſymple gyft, honeſtie
a ſtraunge monſter, and charitie a fooliſh
affection. Let a certayne holie ambytion
poſſeſſe our myndes, and let vs
diſdayne to take precepts of them,
which therefore offende becauſe they
lacke the vſe of godly precepts. It were
better farre that they taking example
of the godlie, by lyuing wel, may learn
to be Chriſtians, then that the godly omitting
theyr good purpoſe ſhoulde by
lyuing as they doo, bee tranſformed
to beaſtes. Let them bee aſſured, that
pleaſure when it moſte delighteth is at
an ende, that it falleth head-long into
the boſome of ſorrow, and that the greateſt
pleaſures wyll at the laſt be turned
into ſharpeſt tormēts. Gluttony is
the mother of cruditye in the ſtomack,
drunkennes breedeth the ache of the

ſinewes venereous practiſes bréed palſies,
ſtifnes of ioyntes, and a roaring
ventoſitie in the entralles. Pleaſures
are not ſound nor faythfull, they ſalute
vs with a fayre face, but behind theyr
backes is a grim deſolation. And therefore
let thē be ſhaken off in time: they
embrace fréendly, that they may ſtrangle
trayterouſly, and whoſoeuer performeth
this admonition, let him bethinke
himſelfe to what a number of
bad companions he hath gyuen a farewell.
Hys bodye is free from ougly diſeaſes,
his mind is deliuered from ignorance,
his appetite from ſenſualitie,
hys eſtate from daunger, hys houſe
from dyſcorde, hys ſoule from ye ſecrete
pange of a griping conſcience, al things
ſhall then turne to the beſte vnto him,
hys afflictions to preſeruatiues, hys
ſorrowes and briniſh teares, to an acceptable
ſacrifice: and the great vnconſtancie
of fréendes, to a great confidence
in God. I am plunged in a déepe and
vnſpeakable ſorrowe, when I thinke
vpō the fancies, or rather furies of mē,
which I can better deplore, then deſcribe,
and rather meruaile at then amend.

Is it not a great madnes, not to
beleue the word of God, whoſe trueth
is publiſhed by the bloode of Martyrs,
reſounded by the voyce of the Apoſtles
proued by myracles, confirmed by reaſon,
witneſſed by counſelles, by the heauens
declared, and by the deuils confeſed.
But is it not an excéeding madnes,
for a man not to doubt of the trueth of
the Goſpel, and yet ſo to liue as though
there were no doubt, but it were falſe?
If yt bee true which is ſayd in the Goſpell.
It is harder for a rich man to enter
into the kingdome of heauen,
               Math, 19 
               then
it is for a Cammell to paſſe through a
needles eye, why doo wee ſo gape for
rytches, why doo wee dedicate all our
labour to vniuſt Mammon, making
golde our patron and protector, as
though life &amp; death were in the vaynes
of that vile mettall: but here ſome profeſſors
of cauills wyll take thys exception.
Ryches are in the number of good
thinges, and are the bleſſinges of God,
and therfore there can bee no exceſſe of
them, becauſe there is no exceſſe of a
good thing. Thys reaſon becauſe it is
ſo well pytcht on the heads of worldly

cormorants, that they take it for a helmet,
muſt be wyth great conſideration
confuted. Ryches I graunt are the
bleſſynges of God, and a cleare light of
his fauourable countenance, neyther is
there any exceſſe in the Lordes beſtowing,
who dealeth vnto euery one according
to weight and meaſure: but the
exceſſe of riches procéedeth from ye outragious
appetite of man, as the heathens
dyd prefigure by ye couetous deſire
of Midas: by the infinite deſire of Alexander
Magnus, who imagined a pluralitie
of worldes, for the better inſtructing
of whō I am of opinion that
Ariſtotle did eſpecially wryte hys firſt
Booke de caelo. It is (I ſay) of the inordinate
appetite of man, which becauſe
it is exceſſiue, it muſt of force proſecute
an exceſſe of riches. And thus it may be
prooued, that it hath ſuch an obiecte to
worke vpon. Euery thing whē it hath
gotten a ſufficient and proper matter
to worke vppon, employeth his force to
that thing onely, as hauing a taſke preſcribed
to it of nature. Therefore if ryches
were the proper obiect and matter
of worldly deſire, then hauing gotten

the wealth that it firſte deſired, and
fully propoſed, as a cōtentation til the
end of lyfe, it would reſt in yt as in an
hauen &amp; be contented wt that only was
ſought for contentation: but we ſee the
contrary, for it flyeth frō ſufficiencie to
ſuperfluity, in ſuch fugitiue maner, that
it ſéemeth nothing wyll ſatiſfy it, but
exceſſe of ryches, and to that (indéede) al
the cogitations of ye couetous are bended,
euer labouringe, longing and
compaſſing, till they haue aſpired to an
exceſſiue ſubſtaunce: Ouermatching
him whom the Romaines thought
matchles in hys kind, the wealthy M.
Craſſus. Much like to theſe rauening
affections were the chaungeable imaginations
of the Heathens, who placed
at firſt in theyr Olympus but a fewe
Gods, yet when they wext ſo haughtie
that euery one would haue a God, for
himſelfe, and himſelfe a God, theyr
heauen wext ſo full of hée Gods and ſhe
Gods, that as Iuuenall ſaith,Iuuenal Satyr. 3. 
               Atlas
hath a heauie burthen, or to make hys
meaning more plaine, a knauiſh loade.
Nowe if exceſſe be the obiect of couetouſnes,
couetouſnes muſt of neceſſitye

be a vice, for all exceſſe and defect properly
taken is a vice, and al exceſſe and
defert as Ariſtotle ſaith,Ariſto. Libro, 2 
                     ••
                  hicor cap. 2, is to bee ſhunned.
Ryches therefore are abuſed by
the vntamed concupiſcence of man, and
are often wreſted by a ſiniſter interpretation
to abuſe.
            It is not to be doubted, but the ryches,
wherewith God aduaunced Iob,
were very ſingular, and the rare bleſſinges
of the Almighty, but the deuill
that erronious Serpent, vſed them as
a bayte and ſnare to intrappe the ſoule
of Iob. For he imagining that his ryches,
had lulled him in ſecuritie, and
intangled his conſcience, thought that
the ſpoyle of Iob hys ryches, woulde
haue béene the ſacking of the ſoule. So
riches were an inſtrument of abuſe to
the father of lyes. And though the patrimony
of Naboth, were ye ordinary
meane of God to ſerue the vſe of Naboth,
yet the ſame was an inſtrument
of abuſe to the deuill againſt the ſoule
of Achab. So likewyſe riches were vſed
of God for the allurement of Nabuchadnozer,
to the acknowledging of
of his mercies, but the deuill wrought

in him a diſcontented deſire, &amp; brought
him to this abſurditie, that hee thought
Babilon was a Heauen, and himſelfe a
God.
            There is nothing in the worlde ſo
precious, but it may be abuſed, as a glyſtering
Pearle, may bee placed in a
Swines ſnoute: the abuſe of ryches, is
the exceſſe of riches in mans minde,
which becauſe it is an abuſe, it muſt
not be vſed, and becauſe it is an exceſſe,
it muſt not be coueted, leaſt ſwelling
with Eſops Frogge, to become as byg
as a Bull, we burſt at length with deſire,
and vaniſh into nothing. The like
may be ſpoken touching the abuſe of
honours.
            It is no doubt, but they are the Enſignes
of Iuſtice, and the honourable
rewardes of vertue, but yet we ſée how
by ambition they haue béene abuſed,
and how by corriuall paſſions of mightie
menne, common. Weales haue
béene brought to great wrack. Was
not the gréeuous diſtreſſe of Thebes to
be lamented,Seneca in Thebaid, when Eteocles &amp; Polynices
iſſuing out of the ſame wombe, dyd
violentlie ruſh into the bowels of their

Countrey, as a Lyon and Leoparde:
when they, which by birth were equal:
by blood, were brethren: neither diſtant
by wombe, nor diſſeuered by Country:
they againſt the preſcript of nature,
whoſe ſinewous perſwaſion doth excéede
all the brauery of Rhetoricke againſt
the Lawe of Nations, againſt
the lawe of Armes, againſt all right
and reaſon: choſe rather mutually to
afflict themſelues, then not to deſpiſe
one another, as though contempt
had beene the crowne of Princes, and
as though to deſpiſe had béene as much
as to touche Heauen with theyr fingers.
            If yée will haue a witneſſe more
nigh vnto your memorie, looke vppon
Rome: which was ſo waſted and conſumed
by the immoderate contempt of
equalles, and did ſo languiſh by the exceſſiue
conflict of noble Péeres, that it
ſéemed rather to bee a ſhamble to the
carkaſſes of vertuous Cittizens, thē a
priſon to the voluptuous, and a graue
to the riotous. Pompeie did pleſantly
ieſt at Caeſar, Caeſar did more eſteeme
the paring of his nayles, then the honor

of Pompeie, both theyr ſwordes were
drawne againſt the naked common
Weale, one Shéepe was committed to
two Wolues, and the final end of their
contempt, was the funerall of theyr
common Weale. Theſe actions did folowe
and immitate the contentions of
Marius and Sylla. Marius made little
eſtimation of all the Nobility, Sylla
did take Marius for a vile &amp; baſe borne
creature, as an abiect or forlorne perſon:
but this light contempt was of
great waight, and the ſcalefire of pryde
could not be extinguiſhed or repreſſed
without the downefall of the common
Weale.Villeius Pater cul. 
               Marius béeing conſtrayned fled
to Carthage, in whoſe ruines and reliques
whilſt he lodged, Marius beholding,
defaced Carthage, Carthage beholding,
diſgraced Marius, one of them
might haue béene a comfort to the other.
            Thus were honours peruerſlye
drawne from their proper ende, to the
purſuing of an vnlawfull tyranny, and
yet it is moſt certaine, that they bee
God his ſpeciall benefites and ſignes of
his iuſt approbation. Saul was inueſted

of God with moſt excellent honor,
but the deuill racked the power of Saul
to the tyrannical perſecution of Dauid.
It is beſt therefore to ſéeke the glorye
that is of God, and not that which is of
men. Why doo we hang ſo vpon the
eſtimation of man? Why doo wee faſhion
our ſelues to this worlde? Why
doo we ſeeke to be cōmended for rych
and wealthie, howſoeuer wee bee dyſcommended
as ignoraunt and waywarde?
In nakednes we appeared at
firſt, and our laſt appearaunce ſhall be
in nakednes: therfore to care for the
morrow, which perhaps wee ſhall not
ſee, or cramme our Barnes, of whoſe
fatnes we ſhall not eate, is it not a follie,
a miſerie, and a madnes? If it be
true,Prou, 2, that the righteous ſhall inhabite
the earth, and the ſimple minded ſhall
continue in it. If the vngodly ſhall bee
wiped from the face of the earth,
and they that worke wyckednes
ſhall be taken from thence. Why doo
we liue in pleaſures, ſith wee cannot
continue in them, becauſe we liue in
pleaſures. If we haue any faith in vs,
why doo we not beléeue that the Lorde

wyll ſometime ſay: goe ye curſed into
euerlaſting fire, and contrariwiſe,
Come ye bleſſed, poſſeſſe the kingdom
that was prepared for you, from the
beginning of the world? Why doo we
feare nothing leſſe then hell? And why
doo we hope for nothing leſſe then the
kingdome of God? Why are wee in
name Chriſtians &amp; not indéede? Why
cry we Lord, Lord, but doo him no ſeruice?
Awake worldlings, caſt the foggie
miſt from your eyes, ſée and ſay the
truth, giue pleaſures theyr paſporte if
they fawne vpon you, beléeue them not
they are the fore-runners of death, and
they haue clapped hands with deſtruction.
Endeuour to enter at the narrowe
Gate, be not obſtinate, becauſe ye
are manie. Know that but a fewe ſhalbe
crowned, and it is as great a glory
to be crowned wyth fewe, as it is a
ſhame to bee condemned with manie.
But that they may the better bee perſwaded
by mee, and giue more credite
to theſe aſſertions which I haue ſette
downe, I will by the grace of God, vnfolde
the ſwéete treaſures of a ſolitarie
life, ioyning therevnto an exhortation,

whereby they may be mooued, though
not mended, &amp; loath their vices though
not leaue them: But heere at my firſt
entraunce, they will trippe mee wyth
this obiection. Woulde you haue vs
goe into the Wildernes, that is a place
for Hermites: to the Forreſt, where
Palmers doo macerate themſelues: to
the Hylles and Valleyes, where ſolitarie
Shéepe heardes doo abide: or to the
Woodes and Groues, where Outlawes
hide their heads? Their patience
in ſuch ſorte I meane not to offende,
becauſe I wyll not touche that
ſtring whereon they harpe ſo much.
            The continuaunce of this dyſcourſe
ſhall make manifeſt, that as I ayme at
a fayrer marke, ſo I meane to take my
ſtanding on a better ground. But for
the excuſing of the Hermites life, thus
much I doo aunſwere:Prou, 26 not as greatlie
vrging it, but as aunſwering fooles according
to their folly. The Hermite
hauing nothing, hath nothing to bee
robbed of, is not with cares ouer preſt,
nor with the multitude of the vniuſt
ouercrowded. The rich perſonages,
in whoſe houſes ſwarme troopes of

fréendes and ſeruauntes, haue ſo many
moathes commonly féeding vpon theyr
bagges, vnles they be altogether expenceles
Eoclioes, that the ſiluer falleth
out of them before it can well bee
ſpared. And in ſuch varietie of freends,
whereof ſome be cholericke, ſome melancholicke,
ſome ſage, ſome voluptuous,
ſome humble, ſome proude, ſome
mercileſſe, ſome pittifull, ſome enuious,
ſome faithfull, and this laſt ſome
is the leaſt ſome: in ſuch diſcorde of
affections, diſagréement of inclinations,
diſſent of motions, contrarietie of
humores, whether or whom wyll hee
pleaſe that hath ſhuffled himſelfe wyth
ſo manie: and entred into a league
with men ſo diuerſly diſpoſed. If hee
be a dauncer, his Stoicall fréendes are
at his elbowe, with a payre of pinſors
to kéepe him in tune. If he be no dauncer,
his Epicureall fréendes thynke
ſtraight way that hee is in a traunce,
that he is dyſpoſſeſt of his liuely ſpyrites,
that he is inflamed with a fooliſh
zeale, that he is allured by Pulpet perſwaſions,
as if they ſhould ſay, that hée
were tempted of God: and when he is

thus eſtraunged from their faſhions,
they are ready to be at defiaunce wyth
his fréendſhip.
            
               Charus erit Verri, qui Verrem tempore quo vult,
               Accuſare potest.
               Iunenall, Satyr, 3,
            
            
               Verres amongſt his freendes doth onely him recyte
               That beeing his confederate may him of crimes indite.
            
            Now there is an other ſort which
be of the meane pitche, and they alowe
to theyr fréend ſome kind of dauncing,
but ſome they abiudicate, hauing that
ſaying of Ariſtotle for a principle: Omnis
ſaltatio non est illicita,
               Ariſt. in arte poetica. 
               quemadmodum
nec omnis motus. All dauncing is not
vnlawfull, no more then euery motion.
               
There is a fourth ſorte, and they
can not abide their fréende to gyue hys
minde to anie thing, to which they doo
not addict themſelues, though they doo
not miſlike the qualitie wherein he delighteth,
ſaying that a fréende muſt bee
alter idem, ſo like, that if he ſpitte after
an other ſort, hee is to bee accounted a

Schiſmatike. Amongſt ſo many heads,
ſences, and ſentences, ſuch chaunge and
mutability doth enſue, that euery morning,
wherein a man ſo diſtracted by
diuers perſwaſions ariſeth out of hys
bedde, he ariſeth with an other minde,
and as an other man like to theſe animatio
diaria,
               Cicero. and horaria which continue
in their eſtate but for an howre
or a day: or like to Heraclitus his horſe,Ariſt. Metaphiſi. 3, c. 5
which going into a Ryuer, did neuer
returne out of the Ryuer, ye ſame horſe
that he was when he went in Though
this be an inconuenience, yet it is ſeaſoned
with this cōmoditie, that a man
in companie is merry, and paſſeth awaie
the time by ſome recreation or other.
Sée how wee triumph in our follie.
We laugh as loude as Iupiter dyd,Valer. Flaccus argonautic. Lib. 6.
when he was heard to laugh from the
heauen to the earth: but it is vnpoſſible
that our myrth ſhould not be ouercaſt,
with a clowde of ſorrow. Euerye
foreſight of ſome miſchiefe being at the
dore readie to arreſt vs, or remembraunce
of ſome ſorrow, hauing latelie
paſt by, and frozen our hartes with hys
ſtormie countenaunce, daunteth our

chéere, interrupteth our myrth, chaungeth
our Commedie into a Tragedye,
and our laughter into lamentation. Euerie
doubtfull rumor of a perillous
thing, maketh our hart to ſobbe, our
minde to feare, and ſmiteth the whole
man with ſuch an vniuerſall extaſie,
that we feele as it were a worme, féeding
on our hartes, and a threatning
that maketh vs to ſhake, and all our
ioyntes to tremble. How ſoone might
a man diſcharge himſelfe of this burthen,
if he would profeſſe a ſolitary and
chaſte life: which I will firſt illuſtrate
by a ſimilitude, and afterward by reaſons
and examples. When a man maketh
his Teſtament, he renounceth the
worlde, and in a little paper hee dooth
orderly and conueniently diſpoſe euery
thing. When he is dead, he is neuer
more likely to be troubled againe wyth
ſuch cares, or with any worldly buſines,
which is the fountaine of ſorrow,
of which, as often as we thinke, wee
cannot chooſe but ſighe. If a man wold
ordayne his will, take his leaue of hys
carnall fréendes, byd the worldly cares
and cogitations adewe, and betake him

ſelfe to a ſolitary or ſober life, I meane
amongſt men, not amongſt beaſtes: amongſt
men alſo, not as ſeperated from
their company, but as ſequeſtred from
their contagion, hee ſhould not in any
wiſe enioy leſſe quietnes and tranquilitie,
then if he were in his graue, the
doore whereof is alwayes ſhutte, that
no euill tydinges may enter. He that
ſitteth on the throne of wealth, compaſſed
with a large circle of freendes,
hath (as long as the ſun-ſhyne of Fortune
doth warme his bagges, and as
long as his gliſtering ſubſtaunce, maketh
euery man to caſt vppe hys eyes)
a great multitude of fréends, but when
Fortune beginneth to wage battayle
wyth him, when his riches be melted,
and his authority eclipſed, then euerye
fréende flincheth from him, and then he
is as wylling for ſhame and ſorrow to
forſake hys freendes, béeing then by
compulſion enforced to leade a ſolitarie
life. And ha
                  •
               de he not béene better to
haue choſen a ſolitary life at the firſt,
that is, not to haue repoſed his confidence
in freendes, but to haue wholye
relyed vpon his God, truſting freendes

as miſtruſting them, and ſo determining
of them, as hauing a doubt of thē?
To be chained to a fréende, is a ſeruitude,
and to follow him in all things, is
to leape beyond the line, to raunge out
of the way, and to leaue God for man.
Nowe, when after our pleaſures commeth
a chaunge, and after the dawning
of our ioy, enſueth a blacke and gloomy
night of care and ſorrow, then we wiſh
for death: but that deſire which encrocheth
vpon vs, by the violence of aduerſitie,
is nothing ſo welcome vnto vs, as
that we willingly admit. If the man
ſo debaſed, and throwne from the toppe
of a proſperous eſtate, had at the firſt
gyuen himſelfe to ſolitarines, he had
wanted, I graunt many pleaſures, but
he had lacked alſo manie ſorrowes, and
he had eſcaped that extreame ſorrowe,
into the bottome of which, aduerſitye
hath throwne him, and howe can it bee,
but that ſuch a life ſhould be better, thē
a life ledde in pleaſures, when he wyſheth
after the ende of his delights, neuer
to haue enioyed them,Auguſtus ſaying ſome
tyme as Auguſtus ſaid: O vtinam caelebs
vixiſſem, orbuſque periiſſem. I woulde I

had neuer beene a husbande, I woulde
I had neuer beene a father:
                ſometime
with a tragicall tune lamenting,Senec
                     •
                  
                
               durū
eſt ſeruire, cum didiceris dominari: It is
an harde thing to learne ſeruitude after
ſoueraignty.
                Sometime with dyſcontented
Cicero exclayming:Cicero. 
               Cum nō
ſis qui fueris, non est cur velis viuere. Sith
thou canſt not enioy thy lyuing, why
wouldeſt thou enioy thy life?
                If thou
haddeſt beene ſolitarie Cicero, thou
haddeſt not drunke of the poyſonfull
cuppe of enuy, thou haddeſt eſcaped the
ſwordes of Antonius and Herennius,
carrying thy heade vppon the poynt of
his ſworde, ſhould not haue made the
Romaines to haue gazed vppon it, as
Children ſtand wondring at a Puppet
erected on a pinnacle. Much eloquence
we had lacked, if thou haddeſt not béene
in Fortunes fauour: but yet many honour
thy eloquence, that care not for
thy fortune. If thou haddeſt declaymed
againſt a Piller of thine owne
houſe, within thy priuate walles, and
haddeſt imagined it to haue béene Antonie,
and haddeſt engrauen therevppon,
thy Philippicall Orations, neither

had we loſt the eloquence which we
contained in them, nor thou the dignity
in which thou diddeſt pronounce them.
Let euerie one conſider, to what courſe
of life he committeth himſelfe. If hee
make pleaſures his companions, hys
money cannot long keepe him companie:
if he make moneie his companion
he ſhall not lacke copartners. Hys Penelope
can not be without fiftye wooers,
a companie of good felowes, commonly
called théeues, will bee ready ad
conciliandam beneuolentiam, of his argenteall
aſſemblie, gathered together
from diuers coaſtes and quarters of the
world. If he ſéeke one lie to haue the
applauſe and approbation of the common
people, as a perpetuall Perithous
vnto him, hee followeth after flying
Byrdes, and beateth the winde wyth
his breath. The people is a chaungeable
ſocietie, and hee muſt bee a perfitt
Chamaeleon that retaineth their fauour.
Demoſthenes did thinke that the
Athenians good will, had béene for his
ſinguler eloquence in the higheſt degrée
toward him, and I thinke it was: but
as it is the vſe of humaine thinges,

which fall when they are at the higheſt.
Diogenes holding vppe his ſcrip
on his ſtaffe, whilſt Demoſthenes dyd
with an oratoricall diſcourſe allure the
eares of the Athenians, withdrewe
from Demoſthenes all his auditors,
and turned all their eyes to a vaine
ſpectacle, verifying that which he dyd
before ſpeake of them, that they were
Bellua multorum capitum, A beaſte of
many heades,
                to vſe a more ciuill interpretation,
men of many mindes.
Now he that 
                  •
               ancieth ſo much the peoples
fauour, muſt either ſerue theyr
humors, or els they will vtterly reiect
him: if he folow their affections, hee
muſt be a ſlaue to their wylles, and ſo
not be ledde by his owne reaſon, which
is proper to man: and in him contrarye
windes muſt blowe at the ſame
time, which combat is againſt nature.
He muſt holde with ſome of the people
one thing, and with other ſome y• contrary:
and ſo in inward affection. Hee
ſhall fight for himſelfe againſt himſelf,
béeing diuerſly diſtracted,Li
                     •
                  ius, Lib, 1 making a
Met
                     •
                  us Suffetius of his owne minde,
plunged in the hell of doubtes, and a

galla-mafrie of his conſcience, which if
he wounde, that is an other hell, and if
he die without repentaunce, hee muſt
looke for the third hell. But he wyll ſo
prouide, that he be in great fauor wyth
ſome honourable perſonage, and ſo hauing
gotten a golden vizarde to a badde
face, he thinketh hee may maſke in al
kind of pleaſurs, without any ſtayning
of his credite: for as for conſcience, that
is the leaſt queſtion, he thinketh his eſtimation
can neuer be impayred by any
chaunge of fortune, imagining that
he is ſecundus a Ioue,
               De moribus vltima fiet quaeſtio Iuuenal. 
               the next to Iupiter,
and like a fooliſh Weather-cocke,
turneth to euery proude imagination,
as his fancie windeth him, but he muſt
not thinke, that his minde can be faber
fortunae ſuae, the carpenter of his owne
fortune.
                He may imagine that he hath
golden Mountaynes, that he is a Cittizen
of the ſiluer world, that he is the
ſonne of the white Henne, and manye
ſuch gloſes he may make vpon a phantaſticall
text. But Fortune cannot bee
faithfull, ſhee is onely ſtedfaſt in vnſtedfaſtnes,
rowling continually hither
and thither, according to the circute of

her whéele. Plautianus was in hygh fa
               
                  •
               our
with Seuerus,
               Dion in vit. Seuer. but his eſtimation
was nothing ſo great as his ruine, hys
aduerſitie by many degrées excéeded his
authority: if he had not béene knowne
too manie, manie had not known hys
fall: if the light of the Moone were not
very great, who would watch halfe a
night to behold the eclipſe. To loſe at
one clappe the credite which he did purchaſe
by ſo great ſeruice, and ſo continuall
attendaunce, that hee did euen
ſerue out a ſeruitude to purchaſe a
kingdome, which bothe to obtayne and
loſe, almoſt in one moment, to chaunge
hys honney for poyſon, and hys blyſſe
for bale, muſte of force be a great anguiſhe
to Plautianus. A whetſtone to
his myſeries, a wormewood to hys remembraunce,
and a canker to his hart.
If he hadde dwelt in a meane Village,
vnder the name of a poore Gentleman,
he ſhould haue beene loued of his neigh
bours, but not enuied: and though hee
had beene a ſcandall vnto his enemies,
yet he ſhould not haue beene vnto them
a ridiculous ſpectacle. It is not my
meaning, to perſwade any manne to

dwell in Diogenes hys Tubbe, or Clearchus
hys Truncke, to liue onelye
by eating the ayre, or to repoſe hys
cheefeſt delight in the buzzing of a Bée,
but to exhorte euery one, that he ſingle
and ſeuerre his deſire from the worldly
delicates, to eſtraunge hys cogitations
from the allurements of the eye, to reſtraine
hys appetite from the deuills
triangle, Bacchus, Cupid, and Venus.
That is, not to be accounted a chaſte
and contemplatiue life, which is conſumed
in corners vpon a melancholicke
paſſion, or continued in deſertes vpon
an amorous deſperation, or which is
ſpent to loathing the ſocietie of menne,
but not in forſaking and renouncing
the company of vices. They which ſo
paſſe the time, that the print of theyr
foote-ſteppes cannot bee perceiued, to
tend eyther toward the Courte of Vertue,
or to the Court of Venus, but ſtand
ſtill in the méeting of theſe two waies,
are rather to be accounted Neutralles
thē Chriſtians, rather ſluggiſh drones,
then eyther godly Eremites, or celeſtiall
Eunuches, or ſolitarie Virgins, hating
rather men with Tymon, then

the ſinne of Man with S. Auguſtine.
The popiſh Monks make a gooly ſhow
euery one of them liuing ſolus cum ſola,
I would haue ſaid ſolo, but that they
ſerue not Bona Dea, and therefore they
vſe not her precept.
            Non intret faemina limen.
            Theſe are not the true profeſſors of
a ſolitarie and vertuous life, béeing nothing
els but the Popes Adamant, not
to drawe yron, but coyne vnto him.
But they onely are accounted the perfitte
Solitaria
                     •
                  ns, and they onely are precious
in the ſight of God, which behaue
themſelues in this world like Straungers
and Pilgrims, béeing as it were

                  •
               ncarnate Angels, hauing their mindes
fixt on the heauenly delightes, and on
the heauenly knowledge: which are
baſe in the ſight of Men, fooles to the
Stoikes, blockes to the Epicures, caſt awayes
to the contemptuous, and to expreſſe
all in one worde, wormes and
not men. They are like Beacons vpon
hilles, which ſtande in a ſolitarye
place, and yet giue light to the whole
Country rounde about, at whom euery
worldling doth gaze, as at a Stranger,

or outlandiſh perſon, meruailing whēce
he came, whether he will, or what
courſe he meaneth to take: but theſe
ſtraungers of the world, ſtand at a bay
with pleaſures, at a defiance with the
deuill: hauing crucified themſelues to
the worlde, and the worlde vnto them,
they put a great diſtinction betwéene
the Harpe of Paris, and the Harpe of
Dauid, betwixt the dauncing of Debora,
and the Iewiſh women,
               Statius in Achilie id, and y• dauncing
of Venus, and Lycomedes hys
Daughters, béeing neuer merrie, but
when it is ſaid vnto them, Come let vs
go into the houſe of the Lord,
               Pſal. 22. 
               becauſe
their feete ſhall ſtand within the gates
of Ieruſalem, neuer delighted to throng
with the multitude, but when they goe
ad domū dei cum frequentia,
               Pſal, 55▪
                
               to the houſe
of the Lord with a great aſſembly.
            
            They ſéeke not to haue theyr names
blazed by the Trumpet of the common
people, they doo not watch, nor care, nor
trauaile for a popular fréendſhip, they
doo not hauke nor hunt for lucre and
gaine, but if it pleaſe the Lord to place
them in ſeates of honour, they take it
as a frée gift, not as a merited reward,

vſing their honor to the Lordes honor,
ready at al times to reſigne it, when it
ſhall pleaſe him to remooue it: and if it
pleaſe the Lord to kepe thē in a low eſtate,
&amp; to barre them frō the waight of
honours, they are contented with his
grace, and making fréendes of the wicked
Mammon, vppon whom they doo
not relie, becauſe they muſt not make
ſuch a baſe matter their Bulwark, but
charitablie diſpenſing their ſubſtaunce,
to the vſe of their néedie Brethren, to
the diſcharge of their owne want, and
to the glorie of God: they ſo vſe y• world
as not abuſing the world. But in theſe
dayes, vnleſſe a man be frollicke, and
diſſolute, he is accounted melancholick:
vnleſſe he haue a round inuention to
returne a quippe, he is accounted lunaticke:
if he cannot cozen, he is a ſott:
if hee bée ſimple, hée is a foole:
if he be ſolitarie, hee is a 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , but
if he be a familiar companion, one that
is taught to the game, and a confederate
in venereous practiſes,Ouid▪
                ſuch a one,
as Ouid deſcribeth. Qui canit arte canat,
qui bibit arte bibat: he is accounted
immediatly a good fellow, a flowre of
this age, and he is inueſted with ſuch

ſible titles, that he followeth the race of
them that praiſe him, as the Ape dooth
the ſteps of them that trace him. The
ſolitarie man hath fewe fréendes, and
therfore fewe enemies: he taketh no
partes▪ and therefore is partaker of no
harmes. Cicero was once determined
to proſecute his ſtudie, and not to meddle
in the ciuill warre, betwixt Caeſar
and Pompeie, but alas he drewe hys
féete too late out of the myre, wherein
ſo long he had bedawbed them: for
ſhewing before a fréendly countenance
to Caeſar, and profeſſing great fréendſhip
to Pompeie, ſuch like affections to
perſons ſo diuerſly affectioned, he was
looked for of the one, and longed for of
the other: the one claymed him, the other
chalenged him: Caeſar was iealious
of him, and ſet Scoutes to prye
whether he applyed himſelfe any way
to the pleaſuring of Pompey, and Pompey
alſo watched him very narrowlie,
with an attentiue héede, examining his
procéedings, and doubting that hee dyd
more eſtéeme of Caeſar then of him: ſo
that Cicero then beginning to bee ſolitarie,
was debarred from his intent,

and the more cloſe and ſolitarie that hée
was▪ the more diligently and circumſpectly
was he watched: ſo that it is
not enough to ſhake of partialitie and
affection, and goe to his ſtudie, &amp; there
betroth himſelfe to his Minerua, hauing
the worlde before him, in a Coſmographicall
Mappe, and the ſtate of
the common Weale in the parliament
of his cogitations, but he muſt ſet vpon
his doore in the firſt yere of his Man
hoode: Hic ſitus est Vaſias: Vaſias lyeth
buried heere:
                as though he hadde
loſt his life, and had entred into a new
worlde. For if a man be halfe alyue
and halfe dead, to this wicked worlde,
full of contentions and cares, he purchaſeth
to himſelfe the name of Amphibion,
a beaſt that lyueth bothe on
water and on land, and ſuch a munke
is like to the bare ſcalpe of a Monkes
head, that is halfe an heade, and halfe a
ſkul: ſuch demi-worldlinges ſhould bee
vſed like the Batte, which was thruſte
both from beaſtes and byrdes, and haue
a garment ſhaped after two faſhions,
that he may learne of his coate what
deformitie there is in his mind, but the

linges are ſo charmed with the ſweete
coniuration of pleaſure, that they think
their delightes ſhal neuer haue an ebb,
that there ſhalbe no intermixion of ſorow,
no chaunge of fortune: that they
ſhall intreate age with a congie, death
with a kiſſe, the helliſh tyranny with a
deuoute placebo, and the God that maketh
the Temples of Heauen to ſhake
with thunder, by powring out a fewe
wordes in forme of a prayer. Syth
they haue aboundaunce of all thinges,
ioculiaritie at wyll, pleaſure in theyr
hands, pouerty vnder their féete, welth
in a chayne, which they plucke in, or let
out, as it ſhall pleaſe their fanſies: they
are fullie perſwaded, that they ſhal neuer
taſte the cuppe of ſorrow, that they
ſhall neuer be pricked with thornes:
that they ſhall neuer behold the ſworde
of vengeaunce. Theſe voluptuous
Thraſoes, thinke that they ſhine lyke
the greater ſtarres, which obſcure the
leſſe. And indéede they ſhine in a kind
of brauery: but how? Euen as y• glimmering
of a glaſſie ſubſtaunce, which is
darkened as ſoone as it appeareth, and
from the Orient to the Occident thereof

is a very ſhort ſpace, and a little diſtance.
In ye darke clowdes of miſerie,
in the ruine of proſperitie, in ye wayne
of fortune, in the confuſion of ſtates,
and the conuerſion of times: where bée
theſe ſparkling ſtarres Hector, Troylus,
Deiphobus, Paris, and Priamus?
where is the pompe &amp; maieſtie of that
great kingdome? where be theſe gorgious
Women, Andromache, and
Hecuba? where be theſe diuine walles,
built, erected, &amp; eſtabliſhed, by y• hands
of Neptune &amp; Apollo? where is there a
monument, print or ſigne of y• large
and famous region, which was called
Dardania? Troy is not in ſo good caſe
that it is turned into ſtanding Corne,
as the Poet imagined, when he ſayde
Iam ſeges est vbi Troia fuit:
               Ouid in Epiſtol. 
               but the
corne is cutte, and the ſtubble remayneth.
Theſe ſame ſtarres haue nowe
loſt their light, and are couered wyth
the mantle of darknes. They may ſay,
we were Troians, but now are aſhes:
we were ſtarres, but now are carkaſſes:
we were Grapes, but now are
dregges: we were the honour of Troy,
but now are the footeſtoole of the Grecians.
               
O wonderfull chaunge, importunate
times, and crooked fortune. The
Sheepeheardes doo ſing in the field, the
conqueſt of the Troians, and the Troian
warre is the Sheepeheards caroll. O
ſlipperie dignities, headlong honoure,
fugitiue glory: which in one moment
lighted vpon them and rebounded from
them. But theſe were mighty menne
that bare too high a ſayle, and therfore
had iuſtlie ſuch a ſtripe gyuen them,
and ſuch a penalty inflicted, let it bee
ſo: But ſhall Hector die, and Aſtianax
liue? Shall the thunderbolt of Ioue
ſtrike downe the Giants, and ſhal Phaeton
that proude boy ſcape the force
thereof? Shall the trees fall, and ſhall
not the leaues be mooued? Shall Citties
be ſhaken with earthquakes, and
ſhall cotages ſtande, it is impoſſible,
and incredible: but what is this againſt
the voluptuous? Troy was deceitfullie
ouercome by the Greekiſh craft, &amp; periurie:
but Troy was firſte bathed in
Wine, before it was circumuented by
fraude,Virgill. and drenched in blood.
            Inuadunt vrbem vino ſomnoque
ſepultam.
            
            
               The Greekes inuade a careles drunkē
Towne.
            
            When I cal to mind, how the ſumptuous
buildings, which the Romaines
did conſecrate to pleaſure, are turned
to nothing, how their Theaters, Amphitheaters,
Circi &amp; delightfull bathes
are withered with a light drynes, diſſolued
with a little blaſt, and rowlde
downe as it were with Fortunes da
                  •
               
               liance.
I meruaile that the Epicures
are ſo ſecure, that they thinke theyr
ioyes ſhall alway continue, or if they
thinke on death, yet they imagine, that
after their death they ſhall be renowmed
for ſome rare Trophee of pleaſure:
when death hath once ſeyſed vppon
them, all ſuch thinges are diſcontinued,
neither can they looke backe to
their former paſtimes: the Idolles of
of their Epicuriſme ſhall bee throwne
downe by the breath of his mouth, before
whoſe face, the Idols of the Gentles
were diſſundred into duſt, and now
in duſt are they buried. Let them therfore
before their death thinke of their
death, let them before they be embarcked,
meditate both of the Hauen, which

is the Porte of happines, and of the
Rocke, which is the receptacle of the
vnhappy: and let them in mind foreſée
the grim and bluſtering countenaunce
of the terrible and threatning day, in
which the Axletrées of the world ſhall
flie in ſunder, the ſtarres ſhall fall from
the heauens, when the Sunne ſhall be
ouercaſt with an yron colour, hyding
his head becauſe he hath loſt his light,
and the moone béeing depriued of her
light, ſhall ſtand aſtoniſhed, when the
reuenging fire ſhall droppe from Heauen,
and the ſparkes of the lightning
ſhall kindle in the ſtonye Rockes: whē
the Seas and fountaines ſhall burne,
when the ayre ſhall be inflamed wyth
burning clowdes: when this auncient
forme of the world ſhall bee chaunged.
Let them thinke of y• miſerable Dungeon,
which contayneth the powers of
darknes, that loathſome lake of hell,
where the deuills are plunged, as in a
ſwallowing gulphe, out of which there
is no egreſſe, buried in the bottome of
a vaſte fornace, and breathing out of
their noſtrelles the ſmoake of vengeaunce,
out of their mouthes an eternall

fire, to torment the diſtreſſed: with
one hande they ſtretche out bright firebrandes,
in the other they holde theyr
thrée forked fuſkins, both of them as fit
inſtruments of theyr tyrannous crueltie.
There is continuall gnaſhing of
téeth, ſighing and ſorrowing, both of the
deuill himſelfe, and thoſe whom hee
ſcourgeth, with whips that will neuer
be worne, ſcorcheth with fire that wyl
neuer be extinguiſhed, fettereth wyth
chaynes that will neuer be looſed, and
teareth with wilde Bulls that will neuer
be wearied, conſumeth with a
worme that will neuer be filled, dyſioynteth
with rackes which will neuer
be broken. The Prince of darkneſſe
howleth, becauſe he hath loſt the heauenly
manſion, wherein before hee had
the vſe of ineſtimable ioyes. And they
becauſe they left the happines, y• was
offered vnto them, if they woulde haue
left the waies that ledde to deſtruction.
Let them to whom God permitteth
the fruition of this vitall ayre, thinke
of theſe thinges, and lay them vp déepelie
in their hartes, let them lift vp their
eyes to heauen, and their hartes to the

heauenly comfortes, let them long to
be placed in the Parradiſe of bliſſe, and
to be cladde with the robes of glorye, to
be crowned with the garland of victorie,
to be initiated into the miſteries,
and admitted into the ſecrete treaſure
of that diuine contemplation, which is
not by any mans ſpéeche, or thought
counteruailable, by the benefit of which
they ſhall behold the ſhyning gates of
the heauenly Ieruſalem, the walles
ſtréetes, and dwellings thereof, y• troope
of Cittizens and theyr mightye Monarche:
whoſe Towres are of precious
ſtones, whoſe buildinges are adorned
with Saphire and Smaragdi: Then
they ſhall ſée the Sacrifice of their redemption,
the pure, holy, and immaculate
Lambe, with the quyre of Angels,
they ſhall glorifie God, amidſt ye bleſſed
number of Prophets, Apoſtles, Martyrs,
&amp; Confeſſors, with the righteous
Men and Matrons, with the innocent
Virgins and Children. Wherefore
let them deſire to bee deliuered from
theſe fleſhly bondes, let them be wyllingly
content to leaue their Tentes of
Ceder, that dwelling with Cherubins

and Seraphins, and the happy ſoules
of the Saintes, they may triumphantlie
ſing theſe hymnes vnto the Lorde,
which are vſed in Sion. Let them adde
to theſe thrée, three other contemplations,
very neceſſary and conuenient, let
them déepely I ſay deliberate of theſe
three thinges: Firſt, howe baſe our
eſtate is in this life. Secondly, howe
diſcommodious this worlde is vnto vs.
Thirdlie, how ſhort and momentarye
this life is. For the firſt, let them enter
into the conſideratiō of mans original,
who when he commeth into the world,
doth with great weakenes, imbecillity,
feare and trembling, enioy the earth▪
and receiue the ayre: hee ſhrinketh,
quaketh, and quauereth, ſtagereth and
ſtarteth backe, as though hee woulde
gladly returne, and reenter into the
cloſette of his mothers wombe. And for
the euident demonſtration of his myſliking
of this world, he beginneth to
weepe, and cry out in moſt rufull and
pittifull manner, with a ſkréeking and
dolefull gen
                     •
                  thliacon, which 
                  •
               s ſo proper
to the nature of man, when it firſt
ſprouteth in this world, that the learned

               Mirandula not vnwiſely ſayd,Ioan. Pic. Mirand. lib. 7, in Aſtro. that
a Child as ſoone as he is borne, giueth
out no ſigne, which is proper to man,
but onely weeping: and hath hee not
good cauſe of weeping, when hee commeth
into the Theater wherein Maliciouſnes
playeth her prize, when hee
commeth into a vayle of myſeries, into
a deſerte full of vncleane byrddes, into
the world (I meane) poſſeſſed of white
deuills and blacke deuils, into a place
that receiued him being actually innocent,
but wyll ſend him backe, béeing
ouerflowne of vices, and when hee
groweth in age, he groweth like a tender
hearbe, vnto which hee hath often
beene, and may well bee compared, not
for any internall power, wherein hee
reſembleth the herbes of the fielde, but
for an internall impotencie, for hys
fraltie, tendernes and weakenes, for
his great néede of vnderpropping, cheriſhing
and defending, ſubiect to the
coldnes of the ayre, ſubiect to the parching
of the Sunne, ſubiect to rage and
violence, and when he is euen at the
toppe of his perfection, how farre is he
excelled in many thinges of the brute

beaſtes, which he taketh vppon him to
mannage, to vſe at his pleaſure, and
with a lyon-like looke to deſpiſe.Ariſtot. R
                     •
                  etoric. 1. cap. 11. All
temporall and worldly delight, conſiſteth
in three thinges: in perceiuing
thinges preſent, which are delightfull
vnto vs: in remembring thinges paſt,
which haue béene pleaſant vnto vs: and
in hoping for thinges to come, which
may be pleaſant vnto vs. In theſe
three thinges, Man may challenge the
victory: but quietnes conſiſteth in thrée
other thinges. In perceiuing thinges
pleaſaunt, without hurt: in remembring
thinges paſt, without greefe: in
looking for thinges to come, wythout
feare. And in theſe three thinges, Man
is ouercomed of the brutiſh creatures.
Varietie likewiſe conſiſteth in three
thinges: in enioying many thinges:
aunſwering to many affections: in
finding out helpes to nature: in knowing
many thinges: in thoſe thrée, Man
is the victor. But contentation is repoſed
in three other things: in being fre
                  •
               
from mutabilitie of deſires, in beeing
ſatiſfied with that which natures bountie
doth exhibite, in knowing nothing

that might be wyſhed to bee knowne:
and heerein the ſauage beaſtes haue
preheminence. There bee foure ſmall
thinges in the earth ſayth Salomon,
and yet they are wyſer then men that
bee wyſe.Prou. 30 
               The Antes a people not
ſtrong, yet prepare they theire meate
in the Summer. The Connies, a people
not mighty, yet make they theyr
houſes in the Rockes. The Graſhoppers
haue no kinges, and yet they goe
all foorth by bandes. The Spider holdeth
with her hand, and is in kinges
pallaces. So the Lorde that hee myght
ſhewe howe weake mans power is,
beeing compared to other creatures,
that hys owne power might cleerelye
ſhyne in the creation and gouernment
of them, dooth thus expoſtulate wyth
Iob.
               Iob, 39, 
               Who hath ſett the wilde Aſſe at
libertie, or who hath looſed his bands?
It is I which haue made the wildernes
his houſe, and the ſalt places his dwellinges.
Hee mocketh the multitude of
the Cittie, hee heareth not the crye of
the dryuer. And againe. Haſt thou gyuen
the horſe ſtrength, or couered hys
neck with neyghing, he diggeth in the

valley, and reioyceth in his ſtrength,
he goeth foorth to meete the harneſt
man, he deſpyſeth feare, and turneth
not his backe from the ſword. Iob béeing
greatly apalled and daunted, wyth
theſe and ſuch like ſpéeches, doth confeſſe
his imbecillitie, acknowledgeth
his baſenes, and remooueth from hys
mind all opinion of ſtatelines, &amp; wyth
great humilitie, méekenes, and lenitye
of mind, frameth this aunſwere to the
Lorde. Beholde I am vile, what ſhall
I aunſwere thee, I wyll lay my hande
vpon my mouth.
            
            Thys may ſufficiently argue mans
ignobilitie and contemptible eſtate in
thys life: if we reſt onely in the naturall
manne, and goe no further: but
this notwithſtanding he will ſcarce beléeue,
that this worlde is diſcommodious
and daungerous vnto him, ſith
hee taſteth the fruites of moſt acceptable
fréendſhippe, and hath ſuch a large
title to ſo many freendes. By that
recorde I wyll be tryed, and as the
iudgement of freendſhypp is regiſtred
in the hartes of wiſe men, let definitiue
ſentence bee giuen. The diſcoloured

and mutable affection of fréendes hath
driuen many to that exigent, that they
haue beene ready to aduowe and betake
themſelues to a voluntary exile,
whereof Vmbricius the Romaine was
one, who made this proteſtation.
            proponimus illucIuuenal Satyr, 3,
Ire fatigatas vbi Daedalus exuit alas.
            Thither I meane to hie
Whither the wearied Dedalus conſtrained
was to flye.
            And he giueth afterward a ſubſtantiall
reaſon.
            Quis nunc diligitur, niſi conſcius, &amp; cui feruens
            Aestuat occultis animus ſemper
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                tacendis.
            What man is nowe beloued,
            but he whoſe guilty mind
            Dooth feele the flames of ſecrete ſins,
            and can no comfort find.
            Salomon did much lament the defect
of charitie, and the coldnes thereof,
when he conſidered that the poore and
innocent manne was fréendles and ſuccourleſſe.
            I behelde (ſayth Salomon) the

                  •
               eares of the innocent, and there was

none to comfort him, and hee coulde
not reſiſt the violence of aduerſaries,
beeing deſtitute of all mens ayde. Therfore I prayſed them that were deade,Eccle, 4,
more then them that were lyuing, and
happier then bothe did I iudge him
that was not yet borne. As it was in
Salomons time, ſo is it nowe, and I
feare worſe. What cruelty is daylye
committed of neighbour againſt neighbour,
brother againſt brother, fréend againſt
freende?
            
            non hoſpes, ab hoſpite tutus,
            Nec ſocer a genero, fratrum quoque gratia
rara eſt
            nor hoſte his gueſt doth ſpare.
Nor ſonne in lawe the father in lawe,
and brothers loue is rare.
            There is nothing more common in
theſe dayes, then fréendly ſalutations,
ſugered ſpéeches, large promiſes, fauning
faces, fauourable wordes, the fidelitie
of the forehead, and the charity of
the countenaunce.
            But a fréende that will take his hart
out of his breſt, and gage it for thy ſafetye,
to whom thy teares be as greeuous

as the droppes of hys own blood, which
accounteth thée his owne déere worth,
though thou be deformed by pouertye:
ſuch a fréend is the beauty of the world
and his fréendſhip is a rare myſterie to
the cōſideratiō of man. But ſuch fréend
ſhip is ye imagined fréendſhip of Ariſtotle,
which is (ſo haue we corrupted &amp; altered nature) an accident but not inhaerent in any ſubiect: an excellent thing,
&amp; diuinely deſcribed. But ye good Philoſopher
(peace be to his cinders) coulde
not giue an inſtance of a perfit freend,
though hee gaue many rules and documents,
which may direct to fréendſhip.
Nothing tinckleth more in the eares of
men, then the name of ſociety, and the
profeſſion of amitie, nothing ſeemeth
more delectable vnto vs, then the name
of fréendſhip, nothing more deteſtable
then the name of enimitie: yet in the
common practiſe of our life, that which
by wordes we doo ſo greatly dyſcommend▪
by déedes we doo confirme and
approoue, and in our hartes enimitye
hath a francke tenement: freendſhyp
is tenaunt at wyll, which in euerye
cholericke furie, we are ready to extrude.

This is the cauſe that freendſhip
is ſo clowded by anger, ſo diminiſhed
by ſuſpition, ſo weakened by emulation,
ſo corrupted by enuie, ſo ſupplanted
by trechery, ſo ſolde for commoditie,
ſo chaunged with nouelty, ſo farre
diſtant from conſtancie, that this onely
remaineth to a mā to beaſt of in fréendſhyppe,
that he is not deceiued nor be
trayed by his fréendes. Now if fréends
be ſo diſprofitable, and fréendſhyppe ſo
daungerous a thing in this Worlde,
what are then our foes in this worlde
our ſworne foes, our bitter enemies,
ſuch as are neuer ſatiſfied, tyll theyr
eies be glutted with beholding a whole
Ae
                     •
                  na of miſeries falling vppon vs. Let
him loath therefore this world, let hym
loath this life, let him deſire to leaue
this carkaſſe. This life is indéede a
death, and this carkaſſe but a Tombe
and Sepulcher of a ſhry
                  •
               ed ſoule.Phill. 1. Let
him deſire to bee diſſolued, and to bee
with Chriſt, for that is the beſt without
compariſon. Let him laſtly call to
account the ſhortnes of thys life. Let
him marke howe the Feathers are almoſt
as ſoone molten as they beginne

to growe.
            Man (ſayth Iob) is of a ſhort continuaunce,
and full of trouble,Iob, 14, hee buddeth
as a flowre, and is ſoone cutte
downe▪ he vaniſheth alſo as a ſhaddowe
and continueth not. Though a man
(ſayth Dauid) ſhoulde paſſe the compaſſe
of a thouſand yeeres,Pſal, 90 they are
but as yeſterday with thee, and as a
watch in the night. Thou takeſt them
away, as it were in the flowing of the
ſea, they are as a dream. They are in the
morning as graſſe, that vadeth away,
which vadeth in the fame morning
wherein it flowriſheth, in the euening
it is cutte vppe, and withereth away:
all our dayes, paſſe away from vs by
thine anger, we ſpende our yeeres, and
they are like vnto a tale, in the daies of
our life, be but ſeauentie yeeres, and
if we bee moſt healthfull, but eyghtye
yeeres, the greateſt excellency of them
is troubleſome and greeuous, which
when it paſſeth away wee doo immediatly
vaniſh. Let vs therefore make
great account how we ſpend ye dayes of
our peregrination in this worlde, and
the longer we liue, let vs liue the better,

God will not bee wanting to our
wyll, if our will be not wanting to our
ſelues, let the worldling weigh in hys
mynde, the reaſons and precepts that
of the ſacred worde of God I haue borrowed.
If he thinke them to burthenous,
let him thinke of the reward that
he ſhall haue for the carriage. The
weight wherewith he is charged, is the
waight of pearles, not of quarry ſi
                     •
                  nes.
Euery ounce hath a pound of commoditie:
and let the godly Chriſtian take
this poeticall clauſe, not as poetical but
true, and as a fréendly farewel of a contemplatiue
Chriſtian.
            
            
               Hîc ſumus extorres, alienaque regna tenemus
               ſub grauis exilii ſeruitii
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   iugo:Mantua
               
               Est illîc natale ſolum, ſedeſ
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   penatum,
               Regnat vbi magno maximus orbe pater.
            
            
               Heere vnder heauy yoke of ſeruitude,
               Like baniſht men, we runne a pilgrims race,
               There is our Country and our onely God,
               Where onely God doth beare imperial mace.
            
         
         
            
            The Authors Reſolution.
            SIncke downe into the bottome of thy graue,
            Into the dankiſh denne of Ueſtaes wombe
            Thou mildering lumpe of my diſpiſed coarſe:
            With greeniſhI Mantle let thy loynes be cladde,
            Beſtowe thyne entralles on the griping wormes.
            And at the dawning of that dreadfull day,
            When Chriſt as corronell of bleſſed Sayntes,
            Shall bee enuironde with a burning Sphere,
            A radiant Starre to his tryumphant Church.
            When hallowed ſoules ſhall to theyr bodies flye,
            And damned ghoſtes ſhall bee recorporate,
            Ryſe thou againe, and with theſe fleſhly eyes,
            Beholde the fleſhe of thy ſweete Sauiour Chriſt.
            Strike then thyne hart, and let thy teares diſtill
            Strayne then thy voyce to heare the Echoes ſounde,
            Which with a cheerefull chaunt may bidde thee come:
            May bidde thee come to taſte the ioyes of Heauen,
            To beare a Crowne, to take eternall reſt.
            And thou my ſoule which wandreſt heere too long,
            In deſert vaſte of worldly wylderneſſe,
            Flye to the vtmoſt Heauen, thy natiue ſoyle,
            To take thyne heritage among the Sayntes,
            To holde a plotte of Parradiſe for ſhare.
            And leaue the Wagon of this earthly moulde,
            To be diſſundred by the tooles of death.
            Make heauen thy Hauē, make Sions mount thy towre.
            Make there thy neſt, where Hermons dewe doth droppe,
            Make there thy tents where God of hoſtes doth raigne,
            Make him thine arme who is the God of hoſtes,
            Make there thy manſion where thou ſtill muſt liue.
            Let Salem newe by thy Ieruſalem.
            Let Abrams boſome be thy Paleſtine.
            For Mylke of Canaan taſt thou Angels foode.
            For Iordan 
                  ••
               oode let Criſtall Fountayne ſerue.
            Let mercie be thy meede: good happe thy hope:
            Nouriſh this hope good Lord, and graunt thys happe.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

