
   
      
         
            A direction or preparatiue to the study of the lawe wherein is shewed, what things ought to be obserued and vsed of them that are addicted to the study of the law, and what on the contrary part ought to be eschued and auoyded.
            Fulbecke, William, 1560-1603?.
         
         
            
               1600
            
         
         Approx. 300 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 98 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01287
            STC 11410
            ESTC S102759
            99838524
            99838524
            2906
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01287)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2906)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 510:02)
         
         
            
               
                  A direction or preparatiue to the study of the lawe wherein is shewed, what things ought to be obserued and vsed of them that are addicted to the study of the law, and what on the contrary part ought to be eschued and auoyded.
                  Fulbecke, William, 1560-1603?.
               
               [4], 95, [1] leaves   
               
                  Printed by [Adam Islip? for] Thomas Wight,
                  At London :
                  Anno Domini. 1600.
               
               
                  Dedication signed: Guilielmus Fulbeckus.
                  Actual printer's name conjectured by STC.
                  The last leaf is blank.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Law --  Great Britain --  Study and teaching --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-01
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-01
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-05
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-05
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A
DIRECTION
or
Preparatiue to the ſtudy
of the Lawe:
Wherein is ſhewed, what
things ought to be obſerued and
vſed of them that are addicted to
the ſtudy of the Law, and what
on the contrary part ought
to be eſchued and
auoyded.
            AT LONDON
Printed by Thomas Wight.
Anno Domini. 1600.
            
         
         
            
            
            
               ❧The contents of the
ſeuerall Chapters.
            
               CHapter 1. Of the worthines and
excellencie of the Lawe.
               Chapter 2. Of the good qualities
wherewith the ſtudent of the Lawe
ought to be furniſhed.
               Chapter 3. Of the choice which the
ſtudent of the Lawe ought to make
in his ſtudie.
               Chapter 4. Certaine rules to be obſerued
of the ſtudent in the reading
of his bookes.
               Chapter 5. Of the exerciſe and conference
which the ſtudent ought to
vſe.
               Chapter 6. That the vnderſtanding
of the ſtudent ought to be proportionable
to the intendement of the
Lawe.
               
                  
Chapter 7. That the ſtudent ought
well to conceiue the reaſon and
iuſtice of the Lawe in diſtinguiſhing
and eſtabliſhing the propertie
and communitie of things.
               Chapter 8. That the words or termes
vſed in bookes of Lawe ought to
be vnderſtoode and applied as the
Lawe doth expound and conceiue
them. Whereunto is annexed a
table of certaine wordes, in the interpretation
whereof, the Common
lawe of this Realme and the
Ciuill lawe do ſeeme to agree.
               Chapter 9. What methode is to bee
vſed in handling &amp; diſpoſing matters
of lawe.
            
         
         
            
            Lectiſsimis et generoſiſsimis
iuuenibus in hoſpitijs curialibus
connutritijs, &amp; Juris
Anglicani ſtudio operam nauantibus
aſsiduam. S.
            
               SI Theophrastum, vt
ipſum nomen indicat,
oratione diuinum,
circumſcripta
quaedam ſpatia, &amp;
angusti vmbraculorum
circuli á frequenti
auditorum corona, &amp; publico iudicum
conſeſsu detinuere: Si Socrates,
quem ſapientiſsimum virum, Apollo ſapientiſsimus
Ethnicorum Daemon iudicauit,
nihilo plura volumina edidit, quàm condidit,
id eſt, nulla: mihi quidem generoſiſſimi
iuuenes, non ſolùm in ſcribendi initijs,
ſed in vmbilico etiam &amp; crure valdé metuendum
eſt, ne prima medijs, media vltimis,
omnia omnibus, non appoſite reſpondeant:
Quae enim parcè nimìs traduntur
deſiderium, quae prolixè fastidium pariunt,
et medium quaeſitum inuenire difficile, inuentum
tenere difficillimum: Cum hanc

arduam ſanè prouinciam primò ingreſsus
fueram, istud me recreauit &amp; ſustentauit
ſolatium. Qui curas ſuſcipiunt grauiores
ſi manſuetis ingenijs vti volunt iudicibus,
eorum audere, est agere, velle est poſse,
velitari est vincere. Fateor in aliquibus
tenùs, vltrà, plus vltrà peruentum eſse: Sed
vel metam ipſam attingere, imò verò ad
eam contendere, ſudoris est et virtutis:
Quanquā hoc A Euo, in hoc praeſertìm Britanniae
Elyſio, nihil in delitijs habetur praeter
meras orationis illecebras: mira certè
quae placeant, vermiculata verba, nectareas
phraſes, eloquentiam Atticam expoſcunt,
omnia limata, arguta, ſententioſa eſse
volunt, planè Aristippéi ſunt ſinguli
prauè ſectum ſtomachantur ob vnguem.
Quarè ſeria &amp; ſubmiſsa prece, mihi vehementér
obſecrandi estis inſigniſsimi iuuenes,
vt hic potiùs otij mei foetus quám laboris
fructus (vacatio enim haec proxima
quám ſub aequinoctium autumnale Londini
non admodùm inuitus egi, cum ad priuata
ſtudia et negotia multum ſupereſſet
temporis, hanc vobis prolem peperit) ſub
candoris vestri radijs calorem et vires recipiat:

cuius ſi compos fuerit, debebit ille quidem
vigorem ſuum vobis, lucis vſuram
mihi, fortunam mundo. Valete: Ex hoſpitio
Graiano: pridie Nonas Septemb. An.
ſalutis humanae. 1599.
            
               Vobis addictiſsimus
Guilielmus Fulbeckus.
            
         
         
            
            Faultes eſcaped in the printing of
the Table of wordes annexed to the
eight Chapter, may be thus amended.
            
               
                  Fol. 74. b for Index read Iudex
                  fol. 75. a for Debito read Debitor
                  ibidem. for mixt read mixtae
                  fol. 76. a for Doto read Dolo
                  ibidē. b for Fideniſtor read Fideiuſsor
                  fol. 77. a for fato read ſalo
                  fol. 78. b for Maritinum read Maritimum
                  fol. 80. b for contumately read continuately
                  fol. 81. a for vacillaus read vacillans.
               
            
            The other faultes eſcaped in the printing
of the other Chapters, a curteous
eye and vnderſtanding may eaſily reforme.
         
      
      
         
            
            OF THE WORthines
and excellencie of
the Lawe.
            
               The firſt Chapter.
               
                  
                     AS nothing more
encourageth the ſoldior
to fight, and to
giue forth apparan
                     •
                  
ſignes of valor, then
the glorie &amp; renowne
which is gained by
exploits of warre: ſo
nothing is a greater ſpurre to the ſtudent of
any Arte or Science, then the iuſt reward of
fame and commendation, which belongeth to
thoſe, who by labor attaine to perfection in any
praiſeworthie ſcience. For as nature rewardeth
the Bee with hony, ſo Art recompenſeth
the painfull ſtudent with riches, praiſe or
honor. And howbeit ſome men make ſmall accōpt
of praiſe or good report, as being in their
owne conceit but an emptie ſound, yet wiſe
men haue thought &amp; written, that a good name
is better then Gold,Prouerb. 2
                        •
                      Aym. conſ. 145 viſo proceſ
                        ••
                      in fi. and that a mans credit
is the faireſt flower of his garden. Now if
praiſe be due to Arts and ſciences, as being the

beſt treaſure &amp; endowment of the mind, religion
only excepted, then ſurely the knowledge of
the law may in the firſt place challenge prerogatiue
of dignity, by whoſe righteous doome &amp;
decree it is prouided, ruled, &amp; ordered, that al other
ſciences ſhould haue their maintenance &amp;
ſupport, in ſuch plentiful &amp; condigne maner, as
by merite or equity doth to them of right aptaine.
But euery art receiueth his commendation
by the end &amp; ſcope which it propoſeth to it
ſelfe. And the chiefe end or laſt marke of ye law
aſwel as other ſciences is God his glory. But
ye next &amp; immediate end, which is allotted to it,
is to adminiſter Iuſtice to al, &amp; in that ſence it
may be called the rule of Iuſtice: For religion,
Iuſtice, and law do ſtand together, &amp; are together
trodde vnder foote by ſuch as neither care
for God, nor goodnes: ſuch as are rehearſed by
one of notable iudgment.Cyprian de 12. abuſio. A wiſe man without
workes, an old man without deuotion, a
yong man without obediēce, a rich man without
almes; a woman without chaſtity, a gentleman
without vertue, a contentious chriſtiā,
a proud begger, an vniuſt king, a negligēt Biſhop,
a cōgregation without diſcipline, a natiō
without law. But Iuſtice is then rightly adminiſtred,
when it is not ſold,Can. venden. q. 3. Canon pauper 11. q. 3. When there is
no reſpect of perſons.Deuteron. 1 Whē hatred is away &amp;
conſcience is preſent.Can. ſex. 23. q. 3. When rigor is tēpered
with mercy.Can. omnis &amp; ſequ. can. diſcipli. 45. diſt. And Iuſtice muſt be regarded of

the law as the load-ſtar is minded of the Seaman,
for without it can be no gouernment. An
other end of ye law is the good eſtate of the people.
For it is an Aphoriſme amongſt the lawes
of the 12. tables: Salus populi ſuprema lex esto:
Let the ſafety of the people be accōpted the
chiefe law.
                  
                  l. 12. tabula
                        •
                     . c. 6. And ye deſerueth not the name of
a law which hath no relation to publik profit.
Cicer. 2. de legi. For Hermogenes ſaid wel yt euery law was
made for the good &amp; profit of men.lib. 2. de ſta
                        •
                      homiū. And Plato
ſaith, that a Law-maker ought to haue regard
of 3. things eſpecially: namely, that the cōuenient
liberty of the comon weale may not be impeached
by the laws, that they may preſerue amity
amongſt the people, &amp; that they may furniſh
thē with wiſdome.lib. 2. de legi. Wherefore they that
diſpiſe laws, haue no care of comon profit,Cicae. pro Caecin. becauſe
they were made for comon vſe,lib. 2. de legi. &amp; without
law, which I interpret to be an order eſtabliſhed
by authority, neither houſe, nor city, nor
natiō, nor mankind, nor nature, nor world can
be.Cicer. lib. 3. de legi. And therfore Cicero ſaith, yt our anceſtors
were of ſuch vertue &amp; wiſdome, that in making
of their laws they had no regard, but of publike
good:Cicer. lib. 
                        〈◊〉
                      de inuent. For they would not write any thing
to hurt, and if they had written any ſuch
things, it would haue bin reiected as ſoone as
it had bin vnderſtood. It is manifeſt therefore
that the end at which the Law doth ayme
is the generall aduantage of common ſocietie

in a iuſt maner diſtributed and dealt to euerie
one. For, non ſufficit bonum fieri niſi bene fiat, It
is not ſufficient to doe that which is good vnleſſe
it be done in good ſort,
                   and therefore let
not any man, which vndertaketh this profeſſion
lay conſcience aſide: for though the charge
and calling be ſeculer, yet it muſt be religiouſly
handled. For God is the author of the Law,
and the reuenger of the abuſe thereof, The
weight and meaſure,
                  Pro. 16. ſaith Solomon, are God
his iudgments, and therfore if any man maintaine
any wrong by colour or pretence of Law
let him know, that though man be hurt, yet
God is offended, ye do not execute the iudgement
of Man,
                  Chroni. 2. c. 19 
                  but of God, ſaith Ioſaphat. God
is the beholder and vmpier of Counſailes and
Iudgements, and ſurely if a man do well diſcharge
this weightie and excellent function,
there is no man of any religious habit or vocation
in higher place or greater reckoning
with God. So much the more are they to bee
reprooued, who exerciſe ſychophancie, fraud &amp;
caueling in the handling of cauſes, being wreſters
of Lawes, and wringers of money, whoſe
conqueſt in bad cauſes maketh them triumphe
as much as Romulus did when he had killed
his brother: nay as Atreus did when he had cō
                  paſt
the death of his brother Thyeſtes, boaſting
and glorying.Senec in Thy. 
                  nunc parta vera eſt palma, nunc
meas laudo manus, Now haue I gotten an honorable

victorie, nowe I praiſe my handie
worke,
                   but they in whom conſcience beareth
ſtroke are farre otherwiſe addicted, and ſhalbe
hereafter otherwiſe rewarded. Nay euen in
their life time do they poſſeſſe ye enſigns of authoritie
&amp; dignitie, &amp; by good right may they
challenge many ſpecial fauors, immunities &amp;
indulgences. Conſtantine the Emperor gaue
to the profeſſors of the imperial Lawes, full &amp;
perfect freedome from all collaterall charges,
taxes, and other burdens of the cōmon weale,
L. medic. 1. 6 de profeſ. &amp; medi. and he decreed alſo that certain yerely penſions
ſhould be paid vnto them out of the Treaſury,
D. L. medicos. &amp; the Emperor Valent. would haue thē
which by the ſpace of xx. yeres were profeſſors
of the law, to be illuſtrated by the name of Comites,
a name of excellent dignity.l. vnica &amp; rubri. de profeſ. qui in vrbe Conſtantinopol. docent ex lege meruerūt. Comit. li. 12. c. tit. 15. Many other
priuiledges &amp; benefits are mentioned in
the Ciuil law, which belong as well to Studients
as to profeſſors, and hereupon had that
ſaying his originall.
               
                  Dat Galenus opes, dat ſanctio Iuſtiniana:
                  Ex alijs paleas, ex istis collige grana.Angel. Aretin in §. proaem. inſtitut.
                  
               
               Neither hath England bin vnkind or ſtrait
handed to men of that coat and calling: for in
old time as I find in M. Plowden, who was
credibly infourmed thereof, there were fower
Reporters of the caſes of Law, which were
choſen men, and had a yerely ſtipend for their

paines and trauaile therein, paied by the king,
Plowd. in Epi. a les eſtudents de le cō
                     mon ley. But ſome will ſay that God forbiddeth vs
to contend. Who denieth that? but he doth not
forbid to Iudge &amp; determine controuerſies: &amp;
there is great difference between iudging and
contending: for though God do forbid thee to
beate a poore traueling man: yet he doth not
forbid thee to bind vp his wound, when he is
hurt and maymed of others. So though he do
greatly abhorre the hatred, rancor, malice, and
diſagreement of men, yet he is wel pleaſed and
contented yt ſuch pernicious &amp; contagious diſeaſes
ſhould be cured. Let him that condēneth
the fault, approue the remedy. One mā rageth
with a burning deſire of reuenge: an other cō
                  ueieth
to himſelfe an others mans goods by
craft, whom when charity &amp; duty cannot bring
into the right way, his diſloial dealing muſt be
repreſſed by the ſeuerity of Iudges. Moſes,
Dauid Solomon, committed no ſin, when they
cauſed wicked men to be rigorouſly puniſhed:
&amp; though Chriſt do condemne a quarrelous &amp;
reuengeful perſon, yet he leaueth to the Iudges
their authority, whether they rule &amp; order
cauſes by the Lawes &amp; cuſtomes of nations, or
by the law of Moſes. Ioſeph, Daniel, Naaman,
the Centurion, did gouerne cōmon weales by
the lawes of the heathen. Surely the politicke
lawes of Kings &amp; Magiſtrates are greatly to
be heeded &amp; regarded, which Chriſt himſelf allowed,

when he paid tribute to Caeſar. And the
profeſſion &amp; practiſe of the knowledge of lawe
is warrāted by the example of great men, who
would not haue borne the names of profeſſors,
if the ſcience had not contained in it ſinguler
wit, excellent wiſdome, &amp; profitable directions
for the whole courſe of mans life. It is well
knowen that the Camilli, the Curij, the Fabritij,
the Fabij, the Claudij, the Scipioes, the Craſſi,
the Iulij the Ciceroes, &amp; the Scaeuolaes were ſinguler
men and ſingulerly ſkilled in law. And
to giue thē their proper appellation were lawyers.
Theſe men gouerned their cōmon weals
not in the ſhadow, in darknes or corners, as the
Grecians did, but in the cleare light of the
Sun, and in the face of the world, vſing experience
as a Pilot againſt the boyſterous &amp; turbulent
affections of the people. And therefore
Virgil when he diſtributethVir. Aeneid. 6. ſeueral ſciences
to ſeueral Countries, appropriateth the ſcience
of gouerning cōmon weales to the Romaines.
               
                  Tu regere imperiopopulos Romane memento,
                  Parcere ſubiect is &amp; debellare ſuperbos.
               
               
                  Mind thou O Romaine men by law to guide,
                  To ſpare the meeke, and ouer-maſter pride.
               
               But ſome accompt it a matter of too great curioſity,
yt the laws which ſhould be plain &amp; manifeſt
to al ſhould be reduced to an art obſcured
with difficult caſes, ſhadowed with conceited

termes, and as it were, couered with cloudes,
and wrapped in darknes: to whom I anſwere
that it is very expedient, that there ſhould be a
certaine art and ſcience of the Law, generall
rules &amp; preceptes, and conuenient diſcourſes.
For the particuler things which do fall vnder
the obſeruation of law ar infinite, &amp; the weaknes
of mans memorie cānot tollerate the multitude
of particular lawes: and therefore it is
conuenient that that which we call aequum bonum,
which in plaine termes is nothing elſe
but perfect reaſon, ſhould be comprehēded and
deliuered in certaine generall preceptes, and
Plato alleageth this for a reaſonPlat. in polit. becauſe it is
neceſſarie, that there ſhould be Regia diſciplina
a princely ſcience,
                   for he ſuteth it with that
name, which may by a generall cenſure, order
and diſpoſe of all things without regard of euery
particular circumſtance. For the certaine
knowledge of matters, it is good that the law
ſhould be bounded by certaine rules &amp; limits:
For a mā could not certainly know what were
his owne, and what an other mans, vnles the
Law ſhould as it were by finger point, &amp; ſhew
vnto him, what, when, and howe it were his,
and therefore true is that ſaying of Cicero,
                  Cicer. lib. 9. Epiſt. famil. 
                  Omnia incerta ſunt cum a iure diſceſſum est. If
you depart from Law there is no certain ſtate
of any thing.
                   And his opinion is in an other
place,Cicer. in ora. pro Caecin. that our inheritance rather cōmeth to

vs by the law, then by our aunceſtors: for
though they doe giue is, or leaue it vnto vs, yet
it is the law which doth ſettle it in vs, and
doth preſerue the poſſeſſion thereof free and
inviolate vnto vs. Wherefore it is to good
purpoſe, that the Law ſhould be definite in it
ſelfe, and ſhould conſiſt of certaine concluſions
which ſhould be as the liſtes and periodes of
the ſcience, by the contemplation of which, a
man may be inſtructed and ſufficiently furniſhed
for particuler cauſes and euents: For the
particuler caſe lyeth as it were embowelled,
and is implicatiuely contayned in the generall
learning, and there is nothing in the Law
which may not be reduced vnto ſome vniuerſall
theoreme, which may eaſily be conceyued
and remembred, becauſe it is generall.Marcell. 2. ff. de iur. et fact. ignor. And
though the profeſſors of the Law doe make-particuler
arguments of ſpeciall cauſes, and
do admire examples or caſes to the illuſtrating
of that which they do principally handle, yet
the Law it ſelfe is compriſed within certaine
rules. Neyther ought it to trouble vs, that
the Law bookes are ſo huge, &amp; large, and that
there is ſuch an ocean of reportes, and ſuch a
perplexed confuſion of opinions, becauſe the
ſcience it ſelfe is ſhort and eaſie to one that is
diligent, according to that ſaying: Industriae
omnia ſerua fiunt, All thinges are ſeruants to
diligence,
                   or come at her commaund, and artes

ar not to be eſtemed by the greatnes or ſmalnes
of the books, but by the goodnes of their rules.
And though ye lawes which do vind mens liues
&amp; maners ought to be vnderſtood of all, that
their preſcript being knowen, men may decline
frō that which is for biddē, &amp; follow that which
is commaunded: yet that may be done either
by their own means, or by ye meanes of others:
&amp; if a mans braine be no fit mould for the Law,
let an other mans mouth be his teacher. Hence
commeth the name of Counſailor, becauſe in
doubtful cauſes he may reſolue &amp; giue counſel:
Whereby appeareth aſwell the neceſſity, as
the excellent vſe of the calling: for what can be
more conuenient or of better oportunitie, then
that a man of experience ſhould ſhew the way
to one that is ignorant. It is therfore expediēt
that there ſhould be lawes written, &amp; that ſuch
lawes ſhould not be altered without vrgent occaſion:
for it is a fonde part to ſtriue againſt the
courſe &amp; ſtream of lawes, &amp; cuſtomes receiued.
A great queſtion it hath bin heretofore, whether
common weales were better gouerned by
written Lawes, or by the preſent &amp; voluntary
conceit of ye Magiſtrate: This matter, becauſe
religion it ſelfe hath committed ciuil duties to
the wiſdome and ordering of man, ought to be
meaſured by the examples of wiſe gouernors &amp;
by popular ſenſe. What good cōmon weal hath
there euer bin without written Lawes, which
haue bin vſed by the Egyptians, Cretenſians, Athenians,

Romanes, &amp; Iewes. The writing or the
engrauing of lawes in Tables is a principall
cauſe of ye certainty of the ſame, &amp; without certainty,
it ſhould be of ſmal credit: for what authority
or force ſhould it haue, if it did alwaies
change like the Moone, or like Vertumnus: but
when cauſes ar decided by the opinion &amp; wil of
the Magiſtrate, the power of gouermēt may be
in the hands of ſuch as be vnſkilful, or wicked, &amp;
ſo either for want of ſkil, or conſcience, Iuſtice
may faile of her courſe. How often might the
pretēce &amp; ſhew of iuſtice beguile vs? how often
might iuſtice be peruerted by fauor or malice?
But if Lawes were not generall, &amp; ſhould not
ſometimes reſtrain Magiſtrates &amp; gouernors,
great inconueniēce would enſue: euen as great
as happened in Athens by the violent domination
of the 30. tirants, who when they had cancelled
&amp; diſadnulled the Lawes, did exerciſe a
common butchery and ſlaughter of good men:
Wherfore, as in dangerous tempeſtes the ſhip
is not raſhly cōmitted to the winds: but there
is neede of a ſkilful Pylot by cunning &amp; carefulnes
to gouern: ſo the wauering &amp; paſſionate
mind of the Magiſtrate, muſt be ballaſſed and
weighed downe by Law, leaſt his own priuate
affections do driue him from doing Iuſtice as
from the hauen. Ariſtotle affirmeth, that God
ruleth that common weale which is gouerned
by a written Law, becauſe the Lawes are the

champions and defenders of conuenient libertie,
then which there is nothing more pleaſant
in this life: for what thing can be more happy,
then to be free from the feare of iniury, &amp; ſafely
to inioy the ſocietie of men, and therefore he
would not haue the gouerment of the common
weale to be committed to any one man,
though very vertuous, without the regiment
and direction of Lawes. Neither let any man
ſay, that I do ſiniſterly iudge of the natures &amp;
diſpoſitions of men, in that I accompt no man
of ſo approued and ſpeciall vertue, and fidelity,
that the mannaging of common affaires may
be offered vnto him to order them at his will
and pleaſure without the appointment &amp; warrant
of lawes: ſurely I could wiſh that euery
gouernor were a Numa: But yet I would
haue the law to be ioyned with the Magiſtrate
in the act of gouerment. Neither do I fancy
or figure in my minde any happier common
weale, then ſuch as may accord with the tenor
and progreſſe of humaine affaires. If a man
ſhould imagine that the aucthoritie of gouerment
were in the handes of the Stoikes, ſuch
as would neither be moued by hatre, nor fauour,
though they in other reſpects were very
vnfit to gouerne, how ſhall their humors be ſatiſfied,
who had rather be gouerned by written
lawes, then by vpright Magiſtrates? for ſuch
is the madnes and frowardnes of ſome, that

they wil not be contented with the equitie and
faithfull dealing of the Iudges, but will ſtill
contend by the rigor, and dint of law, and will
trie all extremitie, being often times more at
iarres &amp; at oddes with the Iudges, then with
the aduerſe partie: here the aucthority of Iudges
will be weak, vnleſſe the lawes publikely
receyued do ſtrengthen it: ſo that in the written
lawes there is not onely a ſafegard for innocency
againſt iniury, but alſo for the Magiſtrate
againſt the importunitie of the people:
But as wayfaring men whileſt they trauaile
are not afraide of going a ſtray, when Mercuries
image doth point out vnto them the way
that they are to goe: ſo good men when a certaine
law is propoſed vnto them, when by it
they know what euery man ought to perform,
what to auoyde, they are ſecured and do wholy
repoſe them ſelues in the protection of lawes.
To the intent that the Hebrewes might well
agree, &amp; haue good order amongeſt them ſelues,
God did enact and eſtabliſh certain lawes,
that they might iudge by preſcript, and rule,
leaſt the law being ambiguous might procure
diſſentions. And other people and nations haue
either by the tyrannons domination of Magiſtrates,
or the outragious diſcord of the people
bin enforced to receiue Lawes as the ſquare
and meaſure of their actions. In the Citie
of Athens when there was continuall debate

about the difficult points of ye law thē in force,
there aroſe three factions of men, not of the
worſt ſort, but yet not well agreeing in matters
of ſtate: the Citie by this meane being
greatly moleſted, and the hartes of men being
edged &amp; exaſperated by the feſtered ſore and
cankerworme of contention, the gouernment
was committed to Solon: he ſurueying by depth
of iudgement the weake, and impuiſſant eſtate
of the Citie, made Lawes, whereby peace and
contentment were reſtored: And when he ſaw,
that theſe Lawes were the ſinewes of the good
eſtate of the citie, he determined that whoſoeuer
ſhould hold any iudiciall place, ſhould in
preciſe tearmes take oath that he would iudge
according to the Lawes. This was alſo the
cauſe why the Romanes dyd flie to a written
law: the Magiſtrates dyd arrogate &amp; aſſume
too much to them ſelues, the people did exceedingly
grudge and murmure that their honeſt
libertie was impeached by the maner of their
ruling, and the beſt men were at variance in
matters of Law: ſo that it was thought meete
that ſome equall Lawes ſhould be in force,
whereby the raſhneſſe of the people, &amp; the violence
of the Magiſtrates might be moderated:
For this cauſe the Lawes called the Twelue
tables were preſcribed to the City, which yoak
was willingly receiued, becauſe without laws
they knew their common weal could not proſper,

nor continue. And as there ought to be a
certain forme of Lawes, ſo theſe lawes ought
not to be altered or abrogated wythout great
occaſion, &amp; the euident aduantage of the cōmon
weale. There was a Law amongeſt them of
Locros, that whoſoeuer would make a motion
or inuectiue againſt any receiued law, ſhould
therof deliuer his mind, hauing an halter about
his neck, &amp; if it were agreed by the aſſembly,
that the thing which he indeuored to perſwade
were for the good of the common weale, the
man was ſafe, &amp; receiued cōmendation: but if
it were diſallowed, and reiected as an vnprofitable
admonition, he was ſtreight way hanged
and receiued death as the guerdon of his
innouation. And in Athens there were a kind
of men called 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , who in all publike meetings
did ſit amongeſt the chiefe Magiſtrates,
&amp; did put them in mind not to decree any thing
againſt the Lawes in force. Thus it is euident
that both the making &amp; maintayning of lawes
is neceſſarie. And it is rightly ſaid of Cicero,
that the Law is as neceſſary for the gouermēt
of a ſtate, as the ſoule &amp; mind is for the preſeruation
of the bodie,in orat. pro Cluentio. this (ſaith he) is the bond
of all dignities, and degrees, which are in the
common weale, this is the foundation of libertie,
the fountaine of equitie. The will, counſel,
&amp; decree of the Citie is contained in the lawes,
as the bodie can doe nothing without the ſoule:

ſo a citie without Law cannot vſe her actions,
power, or aucthoritie. The Magiſtrates are
the miniſters of Lawes, the Iudges are interpreters,
the people are the Seruants, that they
may haue true libertie. The Law is thus defined
by Cicero,
                  3. lib. 1. de legi. 
                  Summa ratio inſita á natura,
quae iubeat ea quae facienda ſunt, prohibeat
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      contraria,
A principall reaſon ingrafted in vs by
nature, which commaundeth the things that
are to be done, and forbiddeth the contrarie,
                  
and all the particuler and ſeuerall lawes of diuers
nations, are but the branches of this law:
for the lawes be certain and cleere intelligences,
and rules, whereby the mind is addreſſed
to purſue that which is good, and to eſchew the
cōtrarie: and they offer to the mind the formes
and Ideaes of vertue and diſhoneſtie. So that
in the ſacred precepts of law, as in a chriſtall
glaſſe, a man may perceiue what he may doe
with praiſe, what he cannot doe without infamie:
for the common places, which be handled
by diuers, of common duties, of that which is
truly good, of that which is perfect happines,
of the beſt eſtate of a common weale, do not ſo
ſufficiently qualifie and inſtruct the vnderſtanding,
as the law it ſelfe. But here I ſhalbe
croſſed by an other obiection, that great &amp; tedious
are the labors which are to be ſuſtained in
the ſtudy of the law. Surely there is nothing
of weight or woorth, which may be compaſſed

without paine &amp; trauaile, and yet if the paine
be compared and ballanced with the profite,
it is but as a few drops of haile to a whole
ſhower of Manna. What would not a towardly
man do? what would he not vndertake by
his wiſedome &amp; warines, to keep all danger
from the bodies, heads, and lifes of the innocent:
to preſerue his memorie from obliuion,
and ſilence: to be of great accompt amongſt
the greateſt: to attaine to that knowledge,
which is the higheſt of all humane artes and
ſciences? and though it were as hard a matter
for a young gentleman to gaine the knowledge
of the lawe, as it was for Phaeton to
aſcend vnto the Chariot of the Sunne, who
ere he could accompliſh that, was to paſſe
through vncouth wayes, and by the ghaſtly
formes of deformed creatures, by the terrible
Signes of the Bull, the Lion, and the Scorpion
Quid. Metamorph., though (I ſay) a Studient ought to
haue all the lawe perfect, and to paſſe through
a multitude of caſes, iudgements, Statutes,
arguments, treatiſes, comments, queſtions,
diuerſities, expoſitions, cuſtomes of courtes,
pleadings, mootes, readings, and ſuch like:
yet ſith there is no arte nor ſcience, by which
the common weale receiueth ſo great benefit:
ſith there is no courſe of life, no time of age,
no eſtate of men, which can either floriſh or be
without the ſafeguard of lawes, and ſith the

difficultie of the ſcience is rewarded by the
dignitie, credit, and ample fortune which belongeth
vnto it: the hope of them which employ
themſelues in this ſtudie ought not to
waxe faint, nor their mindes to be daunted
with the labour and paine, which all artes
require: but they ought to be incited and
allured to proceede in their ſtudies by the
excellent and honorable rewardes of the
ſame.
            
            
               Of the good qualities
wherewith the Student
of the lawe ought to
be furniſhed.
               The ſecond Chapter.
               
                  BEcauſe many applie themſelues
to the ſtudie of the lawe, without
deliberate conſideration of their
qualities and ſufficiencie, ſo that
many times they finde not that contentment,
which otherwiſe they might enioy. It is very
conuenient that they ſhould know what qualities
are requiſite in him, who is to employ

his time in the ſtudye of the lawe: for
as Aristotle ſayeth,Ariſtot. lib. 10. Ethico
                        •
                     , ad Nicomach. 
                  Rules and precepts
haue not force in all, but the minde is to
be decked with good gifts, that it may take
ioy in things that be truly good, and abhorre
the contrarye. The firſt and chiefe thing
that I doe require in him, is, to haue the
true knowledge, and feare of God, without
which his other knowledge is but as a
ſword in the hand of a frantike perſon: and
where the light of truth is not, there is a
darke and tenne-folde mayſte about the minde.
But where God is not, there is no truth,
there is no light, there is no lawe. The
ſoule and ſences, are but the inſtruments
of his will, which hee bindeth and looſeth
at his pleaſure. And if they turne from beholding
him to the contemplation of any
arte and ſcience whatſoeuer, ſurely they
effect nothing but their owne deſtruction.
I knowe this is no pleaſant ſound to ſome
daintie eares, who cannot tollerate any naming
or mentioning of religion, which the
Paganes, whome they make as preſidents
of their prophane manners did not onely
regard, but in the very front and beginning
of theyr lawes (ſuch was their reuerence)
they prefixed a precept and caueat
for the obſeruation and keeping of holy rites
in a regardfull manner: Ad diuos adeunto

caste, pietatem adhibento: qui ſecus faxit, deus
ipſe vindex erit: Let them go to the worſhip
of God with a chaſte minde: let them vſe reuerence:
God will be the reuenger of him
that doth otherwiſe.
                  
                  Leg. 12. tabular. c. 1.. Some perhaps had
rather heare a curious diſcourſe handled by
ſome Aſtrologer, whereby they might haue
certaine notice and vnderſtanding what complexion
and conſtellation is moſt fit to enter
into the ſtudie of the lawe: with ſuch dregs
they would haue their minde ſatiſfied. They
perhaps, will beleeue (for what is more credulous
then fanſie) that they which are borne
vnder Iupiter, are not fit for the ſtudy of the
lawe, as Cocles teacheth them,Cocles in Phyſiognom. that they
which are borne vnder Mercury, are of
quick conceit, but quickly vnconceited, ſoone
ripe and ſoone rotten, eſpecially if Mars be
ioyned with Mercury in the conſtellation, as
it hapned according to the ſuggeſtion of ſome
in Hermogenes the Sophiſt, who writ of
Sophiſtry in his youth like a graue old man,
and was in his old age as a trifling boy. But
they which are borne vnder Saturne, are ſayd
to be more dull in the beginning, but in proceſſe
of time of more ſound and deepe knowledge
then others: ſurely I am not of opinion,
that the ſoule and the powers thereof are
ſubiect to the ſway and motion of the planets.
If I ſhould thinke, that it were a ſubſtance

flowing from the bodie, or ſo mingled
with it, that it might be accompted a kind of
bloud, as ſome Philoſophers groſſely conceiued,
this might ſeeme vnto me probable.Cicer. in Tuſc. queſt..
But I am fully and immoueably perſwaded,
that the ſoule commeth from aboue into this
ſtrange matter, whereof the bodie is compacted,
and is of an incorporeall nature, which
is not ſubiect to the impreſſion of the ſenſes.
For when ſicknes affecteth the bodie, the ſoule
is ſound: and when the bodie is racked, the
minde is free. Neither is it to be maruailed
at, that it conformeth not it ſelfe to the
change of the bodie, becauſe ſome materiall
parts of the bodie are not alway partakers of
the change. Let a man go abroade in the moſt
cold and freezing weather, yet his eyes will
neuer be frozen, let him ſtand by a moſt ſcorching
fire, yet they will neuer feele heate.
The ſtrange and different ſubſtance of them
from the other parts of the bodie, I take to be
the cauſe. Now the Planets do worke only
vpon corporall things, for their influence is
of the ſame ſort as the attractiue force of the
Adamant, or the Geate, which cannot worke
but vpon materiall things: and therefore I
may well conclude, that the Starres do not
qualifie the minde, but the bodie only, which
being a cotage of clay, muſt needs beare the
wind and weather, the alteration and impreſſion

of the Planets. Wherfore let not any mā
who aymeth at the knowledge of the lawe
as the marke of his deſire, make any eſtimatiō
of theſe Phyſognomicall fictions: let him not
goe to the houſe of Mars nor to the ſpheare of
Mercury for knowledge. Si quis indiget ſapientia,
postulet a domino: If any lack wiſdome,
let him requeſt it at the hands of God
                  
                  Iacob. c. 1.
               
               He muſt likewiſe obſerue, that the way to
the hight of knowledge is by humilities gate.
Let not the increaſe of his ſkil make his mind
to increaſe, and ſwell, after the maner of loftie
ſpirited men, who when they know nothing,
yet would ſeeme not to be ignorant of any
thing. Euery auditor muſt be willing to heare
Oportet diſcentem credere, ſayth Aristotle,
                  In Analytic. poſterior.,
who though he were a man of ſinguler knowledge,
yet gaue example of great modeſtie, by
this cenſure, Maxima pars eorum quae ſcimus
eſt minima eorum quae ignoramus, The greateſt
part of the things which wee knowe, will
counteruaile but the leaſt part of the things
which wee knowe not:
                   as if a man ſhould
compare one hundred to one. But none doe
more boaſt of knowledge, then the ignorant,
as nothing ſoundeth more then emptie
veſſels: and they nouriſhing in theyr
mindes a haughtie and ample opinion of
theyr ſuppoſed abilitie, are ſo bewitched
with ſelfe-loue, that they thinke they ſucked

eloquence with their nurſes milke, that the
bees which are feined to ſit vpon Platoes lips,
did flye to their lips whileſt that they were
dreaming in the cradle: that they were able to
teach old men before they had teeth: and triumphing
in this conceit, they admire themſelues,
&amp; diſdaine others, aduancing their own
doings, &amp; diſcommending the fruitful labours
of other men, like apes, louing their deformed
children, and like phantaſtick Pygmaleons
wo
                     •
                  ing their owne deuiſes. If any thing be
ſpoken of thē ſometimes clarkly, and acutely
as they thinke, they make an inward applauſe
vnto thēſelues, &amp; cheriſh their harts with this
acclamation, facete! lante! lepide! nihil ſupra!
but if any thing be ſpoken of others aptly and
ſenſibly, they ſtraightway inferre, Quanto tu
melius hoc inueniſſes Thraſo! But a diſcreete
&amp; aduiſed man, wil iudge none to be ſo meane,
but that he may learne ſomething of him: for
though he know more then others, yet hee
muſt thinke, that others knowe ſomewhat
which he knoweth not. The beſt and the moſt
graue man ſaith Cicero, will confeſſe, that he
is ignorant of many things.Cicer. Tuſcula. 3.. And Solon was
not aſhamed to ſay, that in his old age he was
a learner.Cicer. in Catone maior. And Iulianus the Lawyer ſayd,
that though he had one foote in the graue, yet
he would haue an other in the ſchoole.Lapud Iulianum de fide commiſſis liberal. in p.. The
next thing I require in a Student is temperance,

which I do not take ſo ſtrictly as Ariſtotle
doth, who defineth it to be a reſtreint
from corporall pleaſures, which are obiected
to the ſenſe of feelingAriſtoteles lib. Nicoma chior. 2. &amp; 3. &amp; in lib. magnor. morali., but would haue it ſo
largely vnderſtood as Plato
                  Plat. in Conuiui., Cicero
                  Cicer. lib. 1. officior., and
now of late timeScalig. lib. 3. poetic. Alberic. Gentil. lib. de leg. 3. c. 13. 
                  Scaliger, and D. Gentilis
haue taken it to be, a reſtreint of the minde
from all voluptuouſnes and luſt, as namely
from couetuoſnes, exceſſe of diet, wantonnes,
and all other vnlawfull delights. A Student
muſt in his diet be temperat, and abſtinent,
for as Muſonius ſayth, Continency in dyet is
the ſtep to wiſedome.Stobaeus de temperantia. A fat and full belly
yeeldeth nothing to a man but groſſe ſpirits,
by which the ſharp edge of the minde is dulled
and refracted, and too much meate caſt into
the ſtomack doth ingender nothing but cruditie
and diſeaſes. This meaſure muſt be vſed
in our diet, that no more be taken then will
ſuffice. Seneca preſcribeth a good rule,Senec. epiſtol. 111. 
                  Famem
fames finiat, Let hunger end hunger,
                  
which is nothing els in plaine termes, but
that a man ſhould riſe with an appetite, being
rather ſatiſfied then filled. Yet he that feedeth
more plenteouſly, is not to be reprooued, if his
bodie do ſtand in neede of more copious nouriſhment,
and a man muſt not ſo abſtaine, that
the functions and duties of the minde and bodie
be hindered. Good and moderate nouriſhment
doth quicken the ſpirits, and they do

giue ſtrength to the braine, but that which is
vnwholeſome and immoderate doth ſtop,
thicken, confound, and deſtroy them. As in
diet, ſo in other things, it is good for a Student
to haue the rule and maſtery of his mind
and appetite, neither ſo to let ſlip the reignes
to his deſire, that he will for any commodious
reſpect, bring himſelfe to ſhame and obloquie,
and for a preſent aduantage, incurre a perpetuall
diſcredit. Plato hath a ſentence worthie
of obſeruationPlato in Timae., Et dicere &amp; facere ea quae decent
ad ſobrium &amp; prudentem hominem tantum
pertinet, To ſay and to do the things that are
comely, belongeth only to a ſober and wiſe
man.
                   That example of rudenes vſed by certaine
Florentine Embaſſadors, is to be auoided.
Iouius reporteth itIoui. lib. 28. They were ſent as
Embaſſadors to Charles the fift, and Pope
Clement the ſeauenth ſtaying at Bonomia, and
being Macthants, caried with them (ſuch
was their extreame couetouſnes) certaine
wares to make gaine of, thinking they ſhould
be free from cuſtome, as going vnder the
name of Embaſſadors neceſſaries. But this
being perceiued to the two great Eſtates, moued
the Emperour to laughter, and the Pope
to anger, who was a citizen of Florence. The
Legates departed with infamy, which they
well deſerued for abuſing ſo honorable a calling
by ſuch baſe indignitie, which may be a

warning to all to preferre their credit before
their greedie deſires.
               Dilligence in the purſuing of any ſtudie
is of great weight and moment, and in
the ſtudye of the Lawe it hath principall
force and effect, for the caſes are many in
number, which muſt be read, remembred,
and applyed, which cannot bee compaſſed
but by extreame diligence. And whereas
ſome pretending a lumpiſh idlenes, would
haue the Lawe meaſured with narrowe limits,
and woulde haue the multitude of volumes,
caſes, rules, and diuerſities abridged
and made leſſe, ſurely they giue large teſtimonie
of their great deſire of eaſe. But
eaſe is a very badde medicine for difficultie,
and their pretenſe is wholy repugnant
to reaſon, yea to poſſibilitie. They that
would haue fewe lawes, muſt procure that
there be fewe cauſes, and little buſines,
which it is not poſſible for any to bring to
paſſe. If it were poſſible for theſe faint
ſtudents to take away the infinite and the
innumerable affayres and actions of men,
then that which they require might ſort
to good effect. But that lyeth not in their
power, and therefore they ſhould ſurceaſſe
theyr ſluggiſh ſurmiſe. For this cauſe Ludouicus
Viues is iuſtly reprehended of Albericus
Gentilis, in that he held, that all things

might be finiſhed by fewe lawes, whome
Gentilis
                  Albericus Gentilis dialogo primo de iuris interpretibus. affirmeth, to fight againſt common
experience. For if many contentions
or controuerſies ſhould happen, which none
can bridle or preuent, if the lawe ſhoulde
not handle, diſcuſſe, and determine them
all, the lawe ſhoulde doe iniurie, and it
ſhould not be the handmayd of Iuſtice, it
ſhould not Suum cuique tribuere. So that
in the Students minde this reſolution muſt
bee fixed, not to ſinke vnder the burden,
but with all conuenient induſtrie to followe
hys Studye, neuer to be wearie of
paynes, nor to ſlacken his endeuour, ſith
nothing of price and accompt is purchaſed
without great labour, by which hee
may attayne to the knowledge of many
excellent thinges more worthie of admiration,
then prayſe. Neither is it ſeemely
to pretende weakeneſſe of bodye, and tenderneſſe
of complexion, when health and
ſtrength doe well ſerue, and may well be
imployed in Studye. Ciceroes bodye was
neyther of yron, nor of oake, yet hee was
not broken, nor in manner altered by continuall
night-watchings, noone-ſittings,
and morning-riſings, by many laboures,
contemplations, and ſtudyes, by the great
charge of hys houſhoulde, by the weightie
care of the common-weale, by writing

manie bookes, and epiſtles without number,
as Cardanus well obſerueth.Lib. 4. de ſanitate tuend. c. 16.. and why
ſhould any man deſpaire to doe that which
another hath done, eſpecially hauing the like
diſpoſition of minde, the like faculties and
meanes to attaine to knowledge, and the like
deſire. This diligence doth chiefely ſhew it
ſelfe in reading and hearing. It is not fit
for him that heareth or readeth, to haue a mind
wauering from the purpoſe, and as it were
going on pilgrimage. A man is then ſaid to
floate in fancie, and to wander in thought,
when hee doth not bend his minde to that
which is handled, and when he is amongſt his
bookes in bodie, but not in minde, or when he
is preſent at ſome reading, and doth not ſhew
himſelfe attentiue, but doth number the tiles
of the houſe, or buildeth in the aire, or doth
nothing leſſe then that which he ſhould do:
but the force of the mind muſt bend it ſelfe to
that thing only which is to be conceiued. For
the power of our mind and vnderſtanding is
more ſtrong when it is vnited, then when it is
diſperſed, and diſtracted into many parts.
               Pluribus intentus minor eſt ad ſingula
ſenſus.
               But as theſe things forenamed are of great
conſequence and value to the Student, ſo
wiſedome that rare and excellent vertue of

the mind is of great importance, which I do
rather exact, then require in a Student, for
without it nothing can be done decently or
perfectly: and ſurely to a Student of the law
it doth ſpecially appertaine, for it doth conſiſt
in the cunning diſcerning of the truth of
euery thing.Cicer. Offic. lib. 1. And a Student ought not only
well to deliuer things conceiued, but well to
iudge of them, and in this part ſtandeth the
beſt part of a Lawyer. It is the propertie of
a wiſe man moſt ſharply to perceiue what is
true, what is falſe in euery cauſe and controuerſie,
not to be deceiued nor inueigled, not to
be vnconſtant in opinion, nor ignorant in the
circumſtances of things. The ordinarie
meane to attaine to wiſedome, is to vſe time
and diligence ſufficient for the conſideration
of things, to heare reaſons on both ſides contending
in his mind as it were armed and profeſſed
enemies, not to iudge of any thing raſhly
or haſtily, nor to giue a ſleight cenſure of
weightie matters. For as Fabius ſayth in
Lyuye
                  Liuius lib. 22. 
                  Omnia non properanti clara certaque
fiunt, feſtinatio improuida ac caeca eſt, 
                  All things
are plaine and certaine to him that is not raſh
nor headie. Haſte is improuident, and blinde,
which is therefore rightly termed of Plato
Nouerca Scientiae, The ſtepdame of knowledge.
                  Plato in politic.. And the Aetolian Magiſtrate ſayd
well,Liuius lib. 31. That there is nothing ſo great an enemie

to good aduiſe, as haſte, which bringeth
pennance ſwiiftly, but warning too
late, and without profit, becauſe counſaile
haſtilie giuen cannot be reuoked, neither can
the thing which is diſordered by badde aduiſe,
be entirely reſtored or brought into order
againe. But where a man taketh time
ſufficient, hee cannot be ſayde to doe any
thing raſhlie. Wherefore not vnfitlie hath
it beene defined by ſome to be the knowledge
of the oportunitte of doing things aright,
and the cauſe that all things be well
done,Diogen. Laer. in vit. Platonis. Cicer. lib. 1. officior., and it hath not onely a ſtroake in
worldly affayres, but euen in matters of religion:
for by it a man may be ſo directed,
that hee may neither decline to ſuperſtition,
nor to that which is contrary vnto it, namely,
impietie or atheiſme. And it is the leauill
or compaſſe of all other vertues in the accidents
and affaiers of this life. It will ſhewe
the times and meaſure of boldnes and audacitie,
leaſt it turne to raſhnes and impudencie.
It will ſo order Temperance the mother
of order, that it may not be accompted
rudeneſſe or inciuilitie. It will guide
Iuſtice which gouerneth all things, leaſt it
turne to crueltie: nay it wil moderate it ſelfe,
leaſt it be termed craft or deceipt. By theſe
effects the Student may eaſily perceiue, how
neceſſary it will be vnto him.
               
                  
The qualities aboue mentioned, do ſo directly
reſpect a Student, that they may be
numbred in the ranke either of adiuments,
or ornaments. One thing yet remayneth,
which is, to be placed and raunged amongſt
the ornaments only, being a meere ornament,
yet it doth as much adorne, as the other doe
helpe: and that is curteſie or mildnes, which
doth as much decke and illuſtrate any gentleman,
as the dyamond doth the gold to which
it is faſtned, or as the chaine of the necke
doth giue a luſter to the brauerie of the other
partes, it ſetteth in order, garniſheth
and graceth the other giftes of the minde,
without which they ſhoulde be vnſauorie,
and want applauſe. I diſtinguiſh it from
Ciuilitye called Vrbanitas, and 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , for
that is onely to be ſeene in publique meetings
and aſſemblyes, but this may ſhewe
it ſelfe within a mans priuate walles, or
chamber, and may be vſed betwixt man and
man. Moſt loathſome and deformed are the
manners of the Stoikes, who whileſt in
ſowernes of minde they ſeeke to ouercome
mans nature, do exceede it, and of men they
become beaſts. And ſuch manners haue diſgraced
men of excellent abilitie. Coriolanus
was by nature a Stoike, and his roughnes of
maners is iuſtly &amp; worthilie reproued of Dionyſ.
Halicarnaſtaus
                  Dionyſ. Halicarnaſt. lib. 8. 
                  Cato was both by nature

and profeſſion, whom for his bitter auſteritie
Eraſmus condemnethEraſmus in Encom. mo
                        •
                     ae.. And ſurely I thinke
that ſuch rugged behauiour doth reliſh harſhly,
and is ſometimes vnpleaſant to them who
by naturall inclination do fauour it. Heare
therefore a Stoike diſprayſing a Stoike.
Cu. Piſo (ſayth Seneca) fuit a multis vitijs integer,
ſed prauus, &amp; cui placebat pro constantia
rigor
                  
                  Senec. lib. 1. de ira. 
                  Cu. Piſo was free from many faultes,
but yet a froward man, and was delighted
with ſtifnes of minde in ſtead of conſtancie.
Florus
                   hath noted the curriſhnes of Romulus
with a perpetuall blot of infamie, Romulus ob
aſperitatem morum a Senatu diſcerptus eſt
                  Flor. lib. 1. hiſtor..
Romulus for the roughneſſe of his manners
was torne in peeces of the Senate. But mildneſſe
is of that ſweete and delectable nature,
that it pearceth the ſtonie harts of barbarous
people, it affecteth their eyes and eares, it
bendeth the moſt ſtubborne and inſolent ſpirits,
it findeth an eaſie way amongſt ſwords,
it ouercommeth wrath, and alayeth hatred.Valeri. Maxi. lib. 5. c. 1..
This I commend to the ſtudent as a principall
meane to gaine fauour, loue, and good
entreatie.
            
            
               
               Of the choiſe which a ſtudent
of the Law ought to make
in his ſtudie.
               The third Chapter.
               
                  NOwe that we haue ſhewed what
qualities are conuenient for him,
who purpoſeth to gaine knowledge
and credite by the ſtudie of
the Law, it remaineth to giue him ſome taſte
of that courſe which in purſuing his ſtudie
hee may not vnprofitably obſerue. For though
the way were plaine, yet to them that know
it not, it is harde and difficulte. And as the
firſt yoake is to the young Steere heauie, not
becauſe hee is not able to beare it, but becauſe
he is vnacquainted with the carying of
it, ſo yong Students though they be in age
and capacitie mature and perfit, yet becauſe
they aduenture vpon a new enterpriſe whereof
they neuer had triall, they are ſomewhat
troubled at the firſt: yet in continuance of
time, by labour and ſome direction of Veteranes
in the Art, they pearce through the thornie
fence or barre of theſe great difficulties:
but heere let the Student take courage vnto
him, and when the doore is opened, let him

not doubt to enter. As hee muſt not neglect
time, which is a conſuming treaſure, ſo hee
muſt make diſtinct choice of it, leaſt omitting
better opportunities, he doe caſt him ſelfe into
the ſtraites of time and neceſſities, whereby
he ſhall finde much incombrance, and his
proceedinges ſhall be croſſed by many interruptions.
And ſurely as in all matters of moment,
the place where a thing ought to be done
is greatly to be regarded: ſo likewiſe the time
wherein it is to be done. For the turning of all
temporall affaires doth depende vpon theſe
two hynges, and theſe circumſtances doe either
make or marre the ſubſtance of our actions.
It hath bin queſtioned of diuerſe whether
the morning or the night be more conuenient
time for the ſtudie of the Lawe, which
becauſe it is no moderne doubt, but either part
hath had fauorers and patrons in all ages, and
to the end that by ſome clerenes of reaſon the
truth of this matter may appeare, I will beſtowe
ſome paines in the opening of this
point.
               
                  Marſilius Ficinus a man of excellent learning
and iudgment doth by fiue reaſons proue
that a man ſhould rather riſe in the morning
to ſtudie, then watch in the night.Marſilius Ficinus lib. de vita ſana. c. 7. His firſt
reaſon is borrowed of the Aſtrologers, which
he doth not greatly vrge, becauſe he had ſmal
regarde of their vaine ſpeculations: but admitting

that they ſay to be true, he thus reaſoneth:
there be three planets which be verie
fauorable to Students in the courſe of their
ſtudies. Sol, Venus, and Mercury, all which in
the night are moſt remote from our Hemiſpheere,
and goe into the twelfth houſe of the
heauens, which is called the priſon, towarde
the Weſt. His ſecond reaſon is this. The
ſpirits of our bodies doe followe the ſtate and
diſpoſition of the aire. Now in the morning,
when the Sunne riſeth, the aire is ſubtilized
and made rhinne, pure, and free from al groſſe
vapours. But in the night time it is thickned,
and corrupted with contagious exhalations,
which poſſeſſing the ſences, doe pierce into
the braine. Thirdly, the day was made at
the firſt, for labour, and the night for reſt,
(and therefore it is ſaid in the 104. Pſalme.
Thou makeſt darkenes and it is night, wherein
all the beaſtes of the Foreſt creepe forth,
when the Sun ryſeth, they retire and couch
in their dennes. Then goeth man foorth to
his labour, vntill the euening.) And whileſt
the Sunne holdeth and conteineth his race in
our Hemiſpheere, with his beames he doth open
the poares and paſſages of our bodies,
and from the center, to the circumference of
the ſame, he doth enlarge the humors and the
Spirites which maketh vs more apt to labour
and ſtudie: but when hee departeth

from vs then all theſe thinges are bound and
ſtraitned, and then we are driuen and prouoked
to ſleepe. Fourthly, it is verie healthfull
vnto vs to vſe labour or ſtudie in the morning,
which if it ſhould be in the night the ſpirits
being greatly waſted and conſumed by
the motion in the day-time, the bodie becommeth
weake, and ſo is vtterly vnfit for any
kinde of labour. And he that giueth himſelfe
at that time to ſtudie, cauſeth the Spirits to
flie vp into the head, and they being ſo diſtracted,
cannot yeelde ſufficient ſeruice eyther
to the head or to the Stomache. Fiftely
if a man ſtudie ſoone after ſupper, the nouriſhment
is reſolued into groſſe vapors which
doe fill the bodie and are verie noiſome obſtupatiues
to the ſenſes. For the meate being
deſtitute of heate and ſpirit, doth waxe rawe
and doth putrifie in the ſtomacke. So that
the braine is offended and our ſtudie greatlie
hindred and impeached. It may be added for
a ſixt reaſon, if any thing may be added to Ficinus.
The ſpirits wherein all our agillitie and
dexteritie doth conſiſte, by which the braine
doth worke, are together with the other parts
of the bodie refreſhed and ſtrengthened. So
that in the morning they muſt needes be more
ſeruiceable then at night. Seuently, the phantaſie
or imaginatiue part of the Soule which
helpeth greatly in ſtudie, and principally in

the ſtudie of the Law, is in the night time
confounded and obſcured. Laſtly the bodie in
the night time waxeth more dulle, ſo that the
minde cannot vſe it as a conuenient inſtrument.
For when the ſtomacke is full and ſtuffed
with meate, the thicke aire being round about
vs, ſtopping the poores, the great ſtore
and abundance of humors is caried, as Ariſtotle
ſaithLib. de ſomno &amp; vigil. c. 3. to the head, where it ſticketh for a
time, and layeth as it were a lumpe of leade
vpon the braine, which maketh vs drowſie
and proane to ſleepe: then it diſcendeth by
ſteppes or degrees, and comming into the other
parts doth ingender ſleepe. And it is the
opinion of a learned Phiſition,Lemnius lib. 1. de complexion. c. 9 that the
nightlie ſtudie is vnſeaſonable, &amp; that it wearieth
and weakneth Students, making them
leane and exhauſting their bodies. For by late
watchinges their vitall ſpirits through too
much intenſion are weakened, and their natiue
humiditie dried vp. Demosthenes did ſtudie
much by candle light, and therfore his orations
were ſaid to ſmell of the Lampe: but he
did not begin to ſtudie till the firſt entrance of
the morning, and herein he did endeuor to excel
euerie man. But whoſoeuer will followe
Demosthenes in this, had need to be well aduiſed
of the ſtrength and conſtitution of his body
and to examin,
Quid valeāt humeri ferre, et quid ferre recuſent.
                  
For nature muſt not be oppreſſed, but meaſure
and meane muſt bee vſed, leaſt the ſtomacke
being made by too much fatigation
vnable to digeſt the meate receiued, the poares
of the bodie bee cleane worne out and extinguiſhed.
The whole Senate of Phiſitions
doe call the morning howers, the golden howers,
in regarde that the bodie is then in beſt
temper. This may ſuffice to perſwade, that
the morning is more fit for all kinde of ſtudie
in generall, and by conſequent for the
ſtudie of the Lawe. I hath bin prooued by
probable reaſons, and by aucthoritie of wiſe
men. If this will not ſerue, heare the voice
of wiſedome her ſelfe. I loue them that
loue mee, and they that ſeeke mee earely
ſhall finde mee.
                  Prouer. c. 8. ver. 17. I haue dwelt the longer
in this queſtion, becauſe it is very expedient
for a Student, to know the beſt time
of his ſtudie, which if it bee vſed in ſeaſon,
may proſper, and take good effect: otherwiſe
his labour may bee vnprofitable God (ſaith)
Solomon hath made all things good in their
time.Eccleſi. c. 3. And Eccleſiaſticus woulde haue euerie
man to obſerue time.Eccleſi. c. 4. This therefore
I will noe longer handle, being a matter
plaine, but will ſatiſfie the Student in
other difficulties, which are more frequent &amp;
doubtfull, and are occaſions, that many which
doe enter into this ſtudie doe breake off their

courſe, and bid the Law farewell. The bookes
of Law, ſay they, are not pleaſant to reade, the
wordes or termes are harſhe and obſcure, the
ſtile no whit delightfull, the methode none at
all. It is a ſcience void of all proper definitions,
artificial diuiſions, and formall reaſons.
To aunſwere this cauil, (for I cannot blainch
it whiter.) I will vſe a two-folde manner
of confirmation, and will ſhew that either the
Lawe hath thoſe thinges which they denie
vnto it, or if it doe want them, it needeth
them not. The writings of wiſe and graue
common weale men learned in the Lawe are
not to be cenſured by Grammarians, and Rhetoricians,
who make a gallant gloſſe of Clytemneſtraes
mules, Alexanders horſe,
                   and ſuch
friuilous vanities. For their ſtudie was farre
different being for the generall good and commodious
gouernement of the common weale.
And if any man reprooue them for want of
ſharpenes of inuention, and finenes of witt,
let him be well aduiſed, and conſider the ſubſtance
of their workes, and he ſhall find, that
they caried Mercurie in their braine, and not
on their tongue, and that they wanttd not
wiſdome, though they were defectiue in Rhetoricke,
which not to haue ioined with wiſedome,
is ſo far from fault, that if they had conioined
it they had cōmitted a fault, for who wil
not diſpraiſe &amp; deteſt curled haire, &amp; paynting

of the face in an aged Matron. And in their
writinges wherein their chiefe purpoſe and
addreſſe was, to ſearch out the truth of doubtfull
matters and to deliuer it to poſteritie,
there could be nothing worſe, then a curious
kind of ſtile, which is vſed commonly of them,
that ſeeke to flatter &amp; to diſſemble, and to bewitch
with a familiar kind of perſwaſion the
common people, with whom ſuch flowers are
of more accompt, then ſubſtanciall fruit. All
kinde of things is not conuenient for all ſorts
of men. Rethoricke I graunt is a pleaſant
thing, and full of delite. But in profeſſors
of grauitie, neither comely nor commendable.
Who would not allowe a tripping gate,
nimble handes, glauncing eyes in a Stageplaier
or dauncer. But in an auncient Citizen,
or graue Philoſopher, who would not
diſlike them, blame them, abhorre them. If
we ſee a young Dameſell pleaſant and talkatiue,
we doe not reproue it in her, but if we
finde that in a Matron, wee loath and condemne
it. And truely from the purpoſe and
practiſe of graue men, there ſhoulde bee nothing
more different, then that which ſauoreth
of too much daintineſſe or curioſity. Alcibiades
his ſhooe is not fit for Socrates his
foote, and it is not conuenient for graue men
to celebrate the feaſt of Bacchus in the Temple
of Veſta: there is great diſtance betwixt

the ſtyle of the Courtier, and the profeſſor of the
Law: For if the Courtier ſhould neglect delicate
ſpeech, he ſhould be no good Courtier: ſo
if the profeſſor of the Law ſhould affect it, he
ſhould not ſpeake like a Lawier. If Pythagoras
could haue lyued without meate, he would
not haue eaten ſo much as herbes, and if he
could haue expreſſed his meaning by ſignes or
geſture, or by any other meane then ſpeech, he
would neuer haue ſpoken, ſo loath was he to
offend in ſuperfluitie: Therefore the writers
of the Law are not to be reprooued for doing
that, which if they had done they might iuſty
haue bin reprooued. Cicero when he treateth
of matters of Law, ſpeaketh like a Lawyer,
and a Lawyer muſt ſpeake as the Law doth
ſpeake: Therefore Baro
                  in Epiſt. ad Com. Iuſt. ſaith well, the writers
of the Law would not haue left to poſteritie,
ſo many Law-bookes, if they had affected
a choice phraſe of ſpeach. And ſurely if when
the Latine tongue did moſt floriſh, the Caeſars
and Cicero him ſelfe, did not vſe any gorgeous
and fyled kind of ſpeech in matters of Law,
ſhall we deſire it of Bartolus, Bracton, Britton,
and Glanuill, when eloquence was in the Ecclipſe
or wayne, &amp; exceedingly decayed. Varro
ſaith, that by the diuerſe mixtures of people &amp;
nations, olde wordes grow out of vſe, and are
changed, and new do take place:Varro lib. 4. de lingua latin. How can it
then be, but that the Common Law ſhould

haue harſh, obſcure, difficult, &amp; ſtrange tearmes
by the commixtion of the ſeueral languages of
the Saxons, Danes, and Normans, the authors
of the ſame. Polybius reporteth, that there was
ſuch alteration of the Romane language ſoone
after the expulſion of their king, vntil his time,
that they which were moſt ſkilfull of antiquitie
could hardly vnderſtand a great part of the
wordsPolybius lib. 3. hyſtor. which doubtles was a great impeachment
to learning and knowledge. If the receiued
wordes of the Law ſhould be altered,
it may well be preſumed that many auncient
bookes of the Ciuill law, &amp; the old yeare bookes
would in ſhort time, be hardly vnderſtood: And
I am fully perſwaded, that if the auncient
Tearmes of the Law ſhould be changed for
more polite and familiar nouelties, the new
tearmes would be nothing ſo emphaticall and
ſignificant as the olde. The wordes of the law
may be compared to certaine Images called
Sileni Alcibiadis, whoſe outward feature was
deformed &amp; ouglie, but within they were full
of iewels &amp; precious ſtones: ſo the wordes of
the Law, though they be rude in ſound, yet are
they preignant in ſenſe. But ſome perhaps
will ſay mine eares cannot tollerate ſuch an
vnpleaſant ſound and ſo confuſed a ſtyle, O
delicate fellow, when you go to the Theater or
dauncing Schoole repoſe your ſelfe wholy in
your eares, but when you come to heare matters

of weight handled &amp; diſcuſſed, reſt not vpon
your ſenſes, but vpon your mind &amp; vnderſtanding.
Alcibiades was more moued by the
naked ſpeech of Socrates, then by the laboured
eloquence of Pericles: But this Rhetoritian wil
replie: I confeſſe the Law to be of it ſelfe a reuerend
&amp; excellent thing: but it would be no
whit worſe, if it were more finely and politely
deliuered. Who wil deny that which is comely
of it ſelfe, to be made more comely, if other
thinges be added to adorne it? To aunſwere
this briefly and plainly, many things there be
to which if you ſhould adde any other thing,
you ſhould take away their grace and beawtie.
They be of their owne nature in ſo good eſtate,
that you can not change them, but you muſt
needs make them worſe: A Tombe or pillar of
marble, if it ſhould be painted with any colour,
ſhould loſe the former grace, &amp; be a great deale
worſe: &amp; a beawtifull face is often diſgraced,
by a needles ointment, &amp; ſo it is of other things
which of them ſelues are fayre &amp; comely: the
thing which is added hydeth that which it findeth,
&amp; ſheweth that which it bringeth: &amp; theſe
thinges which ar handled in the law are not adorned
by the varniſhing of art, but are obſcured
by it. And it is not conueniēt in ſuch a ſerious
matter to dally with tropes &amp; figures, nor
to riot with ſuperabundāce of words, nor to floriſh
wt eloquēce &amp; diaperd phraſes: But yet he

will further obiect, Though it do not belong
to the profeſſors of the Law to ſpeake and
write figuratiuely; yet ſurely it behoueth
them to ſpeake and write in good congruitie,
which notwithſtanding they do not. I would
gladly know what congruitie it is which Curioſitie
doth require: The fine Rhetorician wil
ſay, abſurda conſuetudo diſrumpenda eſt: The
Lawyer, he will ſay, vſus contra rationem annullandus
eſt, he will ſay that this is not Romaine
latine, it is moſt true: therefore (will
he conclude) it is not well ſpoken, nor congrue,
the argument halteth. The Moſcouite will
ſpeak of a thing after one ſort: the Fleming after
an other ſort will vtter the ſame thing:
neither of them ſpeake in Latine, but in their
owne language: do they not therefore ſpeake
right? yes, they ſpeake right and congrue in
their owne language, and ſo do the Lawyers
in their owne dialect and language proper to
their Art. Doth any man thinke that theſe
wordes, Bellum, Exul, Sylua, Proſcriptio, manus
iniectio, were vnknowen to the auncient
writers of the Law? Yet ſometime they doe
not vſe theſe, but in ſtead of them they ſay,
Guerra, Bannitus, Boſcus, Attinctura, Arreſtū.
But it is conueniēt that they ſhould vſe theſe
latter wordes, being proper to their Art or ſcience.
Neither is it meete that they ſhould
change them for the wordes of a ſtrange language.

Wherefore Scaliger doth vpon good
cauſe diſpraiſe the Graetians, becauſe they doe
expreſſe things merely forraigne and external
by wordes of their owne Idiome: and commendeth
the Romanes, becauſe they did apply
forraigne wordes to forraigne matters.Iuli. Scaliger in exercitation. And
the common law being deriued from the Normans,
and other nations, doth conueniently
retaine the words of the firſt Inuentors. And
becauſe amongeſt Lawyers Latine wordes be
vſed many times in an other ſence then they
are vulgarly and commonly taken, it is not
good to haue the interpretation of ſuch words
from any other then the Lawyers themſelues.
And though the Grammarians and Antiquaries
do in the Etymologicall interpretation of
wordes excell: yet the writers of the Law in
the Analogical interpretation of ſuch Latine
wordes as do belong to their art do farr ſurpaſſe
them. I do not think any exquiſite ſkill
of the Latine tongue to be neceſſarie in 
                     〈◊〉
                  
Lawyer: but hold it ſufficient if he know ſo
much thereof, and in ſuch maner, as the common
ſort of men, which are conuerſant in the
reading of Latine bookes. And Plato hath a
good ſaying to this purpoſe, that theſe things
ought of neceſſitie to be knowen, whereof if a
man ſhould be ignorant, he ſhould be ſaid to be
ſhallowPlato lib. 7. de Legi. and ſuperficiall. So much therefore
of the Latine tongue ought to be knowne, as

will keepe a man free from ſuch reprochfull
tearmes. The auncient Reporters and handlers
of the Law whileſt they writ of Fines,
Vouchers, Remitters, Reſtitution, Releaſes,
and ſuch intricate matters, had no leaſure
to note the properties and rules of the Latine
tongue in Cicero, Plinie, Plautus, and
Varro: they inquired not which was good Latine,
but what was good Law: But they
were wiſe in their Iudgements, circumſpect
in their aduiſe, ſharpe witted in their arguments,
graue in their ſpeech, ſubtill in their
queſtions, cunning in their reſolutions: they
were excellently inſtructed to diſtinguiſh of
ambiguous thinges by moſt wittie diuerſities,
to open and to argue harde and enigmaticall
caſes by ſound and inuincible reaſons,
to confute that which was falſe, and
confirme that which was true. And whereas
they are impeached for the want of good and
proper definitions, let me aſke of theſe ſtrict
Logicians, what a definition is? I thinke
they will ſay that it is a briefe and plaine
declaration of the ſubſtance of a thing: and
be there none ſuch in the Law? ſurely many:
but they will haue ti to conſiſt of the proper
genus and the proper difference, as they
tearme it, wythout adding any thing els:
But it is ſufficient if it expreſſe the nature

of the thing, whereunto it is applied. May
May not theſe be admitted for good definitions,
A Fayre is a great Market: a Market is a
little Faire: a village is a multitude of houſes:
a Countie is a multitude of villages, Do not
theſe ſufficiētly expreſſe the nature of a Faire,
Market, Village, and Countie: yet if they
ſhould be tried by the touchſtone of the Logicians,
they wruld be vtterly reiected as not currant.
Some do ſpend a whole decade of howers
in doing nothing els, then ſeeking out the proper
genus and difference of one onely thing,
and when they haue done, they are ſcarſely ſo
wiſe as they were before, they may ſay of
them ſelues as Gentilis ſpeaketh of them verie
fitly: Confidentia aſtra petimus, ruimus in
praecipitia.
                  Abberie. Gentilis li. 4. de Iur. inter
                        •
                     p. Their diuiſions like wiſe are reprooued,
becauſe they doe not flow from the
eſſence of the thing diuided: Yet it is ſufficient
if they doe briefely diuide a thing into his
particulers. Who can diſallow of this diuiſion
vſed in the Law, whereby all cauſes are ſaid
to be eyther criminall, or pecuniarie: none
but ſuch as will finde a knot in a bulruſhe.
Againe, they ſay their reaſons are not artificially
concluded: Surely, it is not for any
man, vnleſſe he bee in the Schooles to tye
himſelfe to a preciſe kinde of ſyllogyſmall
logike: But if it go to the end of the controuerſie,
it is ſufficient, and that is the opinion

of Alciat.
                  Alciat. lib. vlt. parerg. c. vltim. Their Methode is amongeſt other
thinges reproued, or rather their want of Methode,
which exception wanteth trueth. All
bookes written of the Law may be reduced to
theſe fower heades: either they are Hiſtorical,
as the yeare Bookes of the Common Law:
and Zaſius his counſailes in the Ciuill law, in
which no Methode is requiſite, but it is ſufficient
to report the thinges done, and how they
were done: or explanatory, as Maſt. Stamford
his Treatiſe of the Prerogatiue, and the
diſcourſes of diuers Gloſſographers, &amp; Commentors
in the Ciuil Law, wherein no ſtrict
Methode can be obſerued: For the Commentor
muſt needes follow his authour euery way
that he goeth: And if there be no Methode in
the one, there can not iuſtly be any demaunde
of the other. For he that vndertaketh to comment,
or to confute, muſt applie himſelfe wholy
to the courſe of his authour, or the aduerſe
partie: And therefore Scaliger ſaid very aptly
to 
                     
                        •
                     ardanus, Sequor te non quò ducis, ſed quò
trahis:
                  Iul. Scalig. in exercitati. Or els they be Miſcellaneall, and in
ſuch there needeth no Methode, becauſe things
of diuerſe ſort, and not depending the one
vpon the other are laide together: And ſuch
are the Abridgements of the Common Law,
and the Pandectes of the Ciuill Law: Or els
they be Monological, being of one certain ſubiect,
as M. Stamford his booke intituled the

Pleas of the Crowne, Ma. Lambards Iuſtice
of peace, whom if any reproue for lacke of methode,
ſurely his iudgment is out of order, and
that excellent Booke of Albericus Gentilis, a
Ciuilian De legationibus, then which I haue
not ſeene any thing done with more plauſible,
artificiall, and exact methode which as it is
verie hard for any to imitate, ſo it were to be
wiſhed, that he would in ſome other like treatife
equall himſelfe.
               But yet an other obiection hauing more fauorers
then the former muſt bee auuſwered,
which is that the Law is vncertaine, and that
Lawyers in their opinions and arguments do
greatly differ, and diſſent. But here the matter
is greatly miſtaken. For the Law it ſelfe,
which doth conſiſt of agreable cōcluſions, and
of the iudgements, awardes and opinions, to
which reaſon and truth haue ſubſcribed, is not
vncertaine, how-be-it they which doe argue
of new queſtions, and cauſes neuer heard off
before, or ſuch as for their great difficultye
haue not yet bin decided, doe in argument contend
amongſt themſelues: but that which moueth
diſputation is not the obſcuritie or doubtfull
vnderſtanding of the Law, but the qualities
and circumſtances of the perſons, of the
actions, and accidents, of the time, the place,
the antecedents, and conſequents. And though
reaſon be oppoſed to reaſon, and circumſtance

to circumſtance, yet the Law is neuer oppoſed
to it ſelfe. And if a man will condemne an art,
becauſe the profeſſors and practiſers are diuers
in opinion, ſurely there is no art, nor ſcience,
which wil be free from condempnation.
Goe to the Hiſtoriographers, who ſhould report
the truth of euerie thing, you ſhall finde
them at great oddes: Lyuie againſt Polybius,
Plutarche againſt Liuie, Sigonius againſt Plutarche,
and Xiphilinus the interpreter and abridger
of Dio againſt his authour. Dio reporteth
a prodigious miracle, which Xiphilinus
altereth, ſetting a new face vpon it, and
diſcrediting his authour.Xiphili. in vita M. Anto. Philoſo. Goe to the Grammarians,
you ſhall find ſeuen great Maſters at
variance about this one word Anticomarita.
                  Eraſ. li. Colloquior. in Synod. Gramma. Goe to the Philoſophers, there is great diſſention
and a diametrical repugnance of opinions
amongeſt them: there you ſhall ſee the
Parepatetikes againſt the Academikes, the
Epicures againſt the Stoikes, the Cyrenaikes
againſt the Cynikes, the Nominalles againſt
the Reals, the Carpentarians againſt the Ramiſtes.
Goe to the Schoole of the Phiſitions:
you ſhall haue the like diſagreement:
Galen againſt Hipocrates, Auenroes againſt
Galen, Auicenna againſt Auenroes, Paracelſus
againſt them all, and Eraſtus againſt
him. Will any man nowe condemne Hiſtorie,
Grammer, Philoſophie, and Phiſicke?

If not, then it is euident, that an Art or Science
is not to bee reprooued, becauſe the
writers thereof doe in opinion or argument
diſagree. No more is the Law to be diſpraiſed,
but rather to be liked for the varietie of
opinions in it. For as by the colliſion or beating
together of Flint and Iron fire doth appeare,
So the truth is diſcloſed and made
manifeſt by the conflict of reaſons. A man
ſhall more eaſilie and diſcreetely iudge of
thinges (ſaith Aristotle.) If he haue hearde
the reaſons on both ſides contending like
aduerſaries.
                  
                  Ariſtot. metaphy Sicor. 2. c. 1. But if ſome men be more contentious
in points of Law, then others, that
is the fault of the men, but not of the art. The
knowledge of the Law (ſaith Cicero) is not
Litigious, but the ignorance thereof.
                  Cicer. lib. 
                        •
                     . de Fi
                        •
                     . And
if a man ſhould deferre his ſtudie of any art,
or ſcience, vntill the writers thereof did fully,
and vnitedly conſent, It woulde bee as
vaine a thing, as if a man ſhoulde purpoſe
his iourney from London to Yorke, but
ſhoulde make a vowe not to begin his iourney,
vntill all the clockes in London ſhoulde
ſtrike together.
               Now that I haue remoued out of the way
all ſuch obiections, as might be occaſion of impediment,
and interruption to the ſtudent, I
thinke it not beſide the purpoſe, to preſcribe
and commend vnto him ſome ſpeciall writers

of the Law, in the reading of which, he may
with aduantage and ouerplus beſtowe his
paines.
               He that frameth himſelfe to the ſtudie of
the Ciuil law, may very profitably imploy his
paines in reading of the Code, Nouellaes, and
Pandectes, which are neceſſarie for the profeſſion.
Of the auncient writers I thinke theſe
are moſt conuenient to be read, Bartolus, Baldus,
Paulus de castro, Philippus Decius, Alciatus,
Zaſius. Of the latter writers, Budaeus, Duarenus,
Cuiacius, Hotomannus, Donellus, and amonge
theſe, yea aboue theſe, him whom I
lately named Albericus Gentilis, who by his
great induſtrie hath quickned the dead bodie
the Ciuil Law written by the auncient Ciuilians,
and hath in his learned labours expreſſed
the iudgement of a great ſtate-man: the
ſoundnes of a deepe Philoſopher, and the ſkill
of a cunning Ciuilian: Learning in him hath
ſhewed all her force, and he is therefore admirable,
becauſe he is abſolute.
               The common Lawe is for the moſt part
contained in the bookes called the Annals of
the Law, or yere Bookes, all which are to be
read, if the ſtudent will attaine to any depthe
in the Law. In them he ſhall ſee notable arguments
well worthy of paines and conſideration.
The two late reporters are Ma. Plowden,
and Sir Iames Dyer, who by a ſeuerall and

diſtinct kind of diſcourſe, haue both laboured
to profit poſteritie. Some humors doe more
fancie Plowden for his fulnes of argument,
and plaine kinde of proofe: others doe more
like Dyer, for his ſtrictnes and breuity. Plowden
may be compared to Demoſthenes, and Dyer
to Phocion, both excellent men, of whome
Plutarche reporteth, that ſuch things as were
learnedly, wittily, copiouſlie, and with admiration
dilated, and deliuered at large by Demosthenes,
were ſhutte vp in fewe wordes,
compendiouſlie recited, and with admiration
handled of Phocion.
               
               There be certaine auncient writers of the
Law, namely Bracton, Britton, and Glanuille,
whom as it is not vnprofitable to reade, ſo to
relye vpon them is dangerous: for moſt of that
which they doe giue foorth for Law, is nowe
antiquated, and aboliſhed: their bookes are
monumenta adorandae rubiginis, which bee of
more reuerence then aucthoritie.
               
                  Ma. Forteſcue in his writing ſheweth a
ſharpe iudgement, and in this is exquiſite, and
artificiall, that where hee endeuoreth to bee
plaine, he ſpareth not to be profound. For he
writ to a King, who deſired to haue intricate
things plainly opened.
               
                  Ma. Littleton layde a ſure foundation of
the Law, and by his owne booke hath deſerued
more praiſe, thē many writers of note and

name by their ample volumes: out of the
great bookes of the Lawe hee gathered the
moſt ſpeciall caſes, which were either generally
agreed vpon, or by the Court awarded
to be Law, or elſe in all ages receiued for poſitiue
rules. For very few there be throughout
his whole treatiſe, which may not be ſigned
with one of theſe three markes: his booke
doubtleſſe is of ſuch ſingularity, that Littleton
is not now the name of a Lawyer, but of the
Law it ſelfe.
               
                  M. Fitzherbert muſt needes be commended
for great paines, and for well contriuing that
which was confuſedly mingled together in
many yeere Bookes: but he was more beholden
to nature, then to art, and whileſt he lab
                     •
                  
                  red
to be iudiciall, he had no preciſe care of methodicall
pointes: but as hee was in conceit
ſlowe, ſo hee was in concluſion ſure: and in
the treatiſes which bee of his owne penning,
hee ſheweth great iudgement, ſound reaſon,
much reading, perfect experience, and in
the whole conueyance of his diſcourſes giueth
ſufficient proofe, that hee ſought rather
to decide then to deuiſe doubtful queſtions.
               
                  Maſt. Brooke is more polite, and by popular
and familiar reaſons hath gained ſinguler
credite, and in the facilitie and compendious
forme of abridginge Caſes hee carieth

away the garland. But where Ma. Fitzherbert
is better vnderſtood, he profiteth more, and
his Abridgement hath more ſinewes, though
the other hath more vaines, but I am 
                     •
                  oath to
make them countermates, and therefore leaue
the iudgement thereof to others.
               In Ma, Parkins his booke be many commendable
thinges, deliuered by a readie conceit,
and pleaſant methode: many excellent caſes
which ſauour of great reading, and good
experience, his Treatiſe is to young Students,
acceptable and preciouſe, to wh
                     •
                  m
his verie faultes and errours be delightfull,
but it might bee wiſhed, that hee had written
with leſſe ſharpeneſſe of witte, ſo hee
had diſcourſed with more depth of Iudgement.
For hee breaketh the force of weightie
pointes with the ſhiuers of nice diuerſities,
yet many thinges are to be allowed 
                     〈◊〉
                  
him, many to be praiſed, ſo that the reade
                     •
                  
be carefull in his choice, wherein he was too
careleſſe.
               In Maſt. Stamforde there is force and
weight, and no common kinde of ſtile: in
matter none hath gone beyonde him, in
methode, none hath ouertaken him: in the
order of his writing hee is ſmoothe, but
yet ſharpe, pleaſant, but yet graue: famous
both for Iudgement in matters of his profeſſion,
and for his great ſkill in forraigne

learning. And ſurely his methode may bee a
Law to the writers of the Law which ſhall
ſucceede him.
               
                  Ma. Raſtall for his long and laborious trauaile
in collecting matters of weight, and moment,
which lay diſperſed, and reducing them
to a conuenient forme hath deſerued neuer to
be forgotten. And I know not whether I may
more iuſtly commende him for his greatneſſe
of knowledge, or for the largenes of his books
and labours, or for his ſpeciall care of doing
things exactly.
               In Ma, Theloall his Digeſt of writs, diligence
and deſire to profit is eminent. He endeuored
to be like M. Stamford: but he is ſo farre
diſtant from the delightfull progreſſe of his
ſtile, and methode, that he may ſeeme to haue
liued in ſome other age a long time before
Ma. Stamford. But as his ſtrength was leſſe,
ſo his labour was equal. For in handling one
title of the Law, he hath dealt ſo painefully,
that no point can be named concerning that
Title, which he hath not diſcuſſed, nay to giue
him right, hath not fully diſcuſſed.
               
                  Ma. Lambards paines, learning, and Law,
appeare by his bookes, which are conducted
by ſo curious methode, and beawtified by ſuch
flowers of learning, that he may wel be forted
amōgſt them to whom the Law is moſt beholden.
His ſtile runneth like a tēperate ſtreame,

his excellent knowledge and vſe of antiquities
argueth no ſmall reading, and a ſinguler
conceit: He hath bin ſo vniuerſally beneficiall
to the whole Realme, that whoſoeuer deſpiſeth
his workes, bewraieth himſelfe.
               
                  M. Crompton hath taken great paines in
this ſtudie, and his bookes are in euery mans
handes, which prooueth their generall allowance,
his caſes are verie profitable, and apt
for the title to which they are applyed, and
ſo compendiouſly collected, that a man may by
them in few houres gaine great knowledge.
            
            
               Certaine Rules to be obſerued
of the Student in the
reading of his bookes.
               The fourth Chapter.
               
                  NO actions haue good ſucceſſe,
which be raſhly and ex abrupto
vndertaken wythout direction:
for where aduiſe faileth, there
fortune is blind, and not in other caſes, and it
is farre greater trauaile to atchiue any matter
of difficultie by ſelfe labour, then by the preſcription
and inſtruction of others: Wherefore
it ſhall not be inconuenient to propoſe

certaine rules, by which the Student may hold
an euen courſe in the ſtudy of the Law.
               In the vnderſtanding of the Law the Student
muſt not vary or depart from the proper
ſenſe &amp; ſignification of the words, vnles therby
ſome abſurditie, inconueniēce, or vniuſtice may
appeare: for otherwiſe the propertie of wordes
is ſtrictly to be maintained, &amp; reteyned. Therfore
let him be diligent to ſearch out the proper
ſenſe of wordes: for as Celſus ſaith, Scire leges
non eſt verba earum tenere, ſed vim et proprietatem,
                  Celſus li. 9. digeſtor. Plowd. Comment. 82. per Saunders. 
                  To know the Law is not to know the
wordes of the law, but the force and property
of the wordes: for wordes are as it were ſeruants
to things, becauſe they were firſt inuented
for the plain &amp; perfect diſcription of things:
for though nature do make ſoundes, yet induſtrie
doth coyne words, without which our vnderſtanding
might be contemplatiue, but not
practicall: for without them the vnderſtanding
is in maner bound, or maimed, becauſe without
freenes of ſpeech, and plentie of wordes it can
not diſplay it ſelfe, nor extend his force to the
opening &amp; diſcouerie of any mean matter. And
as art maketh the mind to ſpeak, ſo the mind or
vnderſtanding maketh art to write. Certaine
it is, that without words a mans meaning may
not be certainly knowen: Of wordes ſome be
artificiall, &amp; ſome inartificiall: Inartificiall are
thoſe which the common or vulgar ſort of men

do vſe for the deliuerie &amp; declaration of theyr
intentions and meanings, ſeruing not for the
illuſtrating of artes and ſciences, but only for
mutual conference betwixt man &amp; man: Artificiall,
are theſe which the inuentors of artes
haue deuiſed for acquainting the mind with the
rules &amp; myſteries of their arts, becauſe words
fitly &amp; accomodatly vſed are the verie images
and repreſentations of thinges, which do lead
the vnderſtanding as it were by the hand, to
the apprehenſion &amp; perfect knowledge of the
thinges them ſelues: wherefore in this reſpect
diligence muſt be vſed of the Student.
               2 Where the Law is obſcure, that ſence
muſt be taken which is leaſt▪ preiudiciall: for
euery perfect ſpeech of man conſiſteth of two
thinges, of wordes, and of meaning, and when
both the wordes &amp; meaning are plaine and manifeſt,
he that doubteth of any thing is rather
fooliſh, then curious: But when the wordes
be directly repugnant to the meaning, the
whole propoſition or aſſertion is meerely
voide. Obſcuritie in writing or ſpeaking,
is when the ſenſe can not be gathered, 1. by
that which of the moſt part of men is vſually
done, 2. nor by that which was vſually
done by him that vttered the wordes, 3. nor
by the cuſtome of the countrie, 4. nor by the
common vſe of ſpeech, 5. nor by the pr
                     •
                  miſſes
nor by the 
                     ••
                  quel: And therefore if a man

will hyre workmen, and will couenant wyth
them that he will giue them as much as other
men of the ſame village or pariſh, if ſome giue
by day iii. pence, ſome vi. pence, ſome ii. pence,
the couenantor in this caſe ſhall giue but ii.
pence:Guido queſtion. 252. becauſe in obſcuris quod minimum eſt
ſequimur: Otherwiſe it had bin if it had bin
plainly &amp; expreſſely ſaid (as much as any other
man of the ſaid village or pariſh.) So if a man
promiſe vpon good conſideration to giue to
euery of the Canons of a Cathedrall church a
quarter of Wheat euery yere, and the number
of the Canons be augmented: yet the graunt
is reſtrained to that number, which was at the
time of the grant.Imo c. literas de reſſcript. 38. H. 6. 10. 39. H. 6. 6. Temp. E. 1. Common 28. &amp; 21. E. 3. 2. per Wilby. Yet the Law doth ſometime
conſtrue deuiſes by mediocritie:Philip. Dec. Comment. ad regul. iur. As if
a man deuiſe to one two cuppes for his table,
without expreſſing the mettall whereof they
ſhall be made, they ſhall neither be of gold as
the beſt mettall, nor pewter as the baſer mettall,
but of Siluer as a mettall betwixt both:
But that is, becauſe euery deuiſe ought to be
interpreted for the benefit of the deuiſee, &amp; yet
as neere the meaning, &amp; as farre from the preiudice
of the deuiſor as may be: Therefore in
deuiſes not words but meaning is followed, &amp;
a tranſpoſing of the wordes may be vſed if the
meaning require: confuſed thinges muſt be
diſtinguiſhed, generalitie reſtrained, ſeuered
things muſt be conioyned, implied things muſt

be explicated. But in bargaines &amp; contractes
we muſt not reſpect ſo much that which was
meant, as that which is ſpoken, becauſe bargaines
do properly conſiſt in facto, &amp; therefore
in matters of contract a mans will is rather
gathered by his wordes, then by his meaning:
for, propoſitum in mente retentum nihil operatur,
and as the wordes do ſound, ſo his will is to be
conſtrued: and the wordes of the contract be
the ſubſtance of the contract.
               3 When the opinions of the learned in the
Law are repugnant the one to the other, it is
the ſafeſt and beſt way to follow that opinion
which is moſt agreeable to reaſon: for if contrarie
reaſons be probable, the better of them
is to be choſen, and that which is more conſonant
to Equitie: and where the reaſon of the
Law doth faile, there the diſpoſall of the law
doth faile:li. adiger. § quamuis. de iur. patron. li. 7. P. tit. 14. c. cum ceſſante de appell. As of the contrary part where,
the reaſon of the law taketh place, her the law
taketh effect.l. non poſſunt et li. nam et ait Pedius de ll. in p. But if contrarie reaſons doe
ſeeme to be of great force, wherof the one tendeth
to a publique good, the other aymeth at a
priuate aduantage, that which is for the common
good is more to be imbraced, fauored, &amp;
followed: for that which is good to many muſt
needes be good to euery particuler perſon: and
theſe things which are generally expedient, ar
with good reaſon preferred before ſuch things
as do peculiarly profit.Iulian in l. ita vulnerat. § quod ſi quis abſurde ad leg. Aquilei. But that reaſō which

is for the profit of a priuat man, and doth not
preiudice cōmon right, may well be admitted.
Publike profit may be conſidered after fower
maners, 1. When profit doth accrue both generally
&amp; particularly, as by the gouernment of
Magiſtrates,l. i §. huius. ff. de inſti. et iur. 2, when the profit is general,
but not particuler: as locupletatio aerarij, the enriching
of the Treaſury in Cities &amp; Townes
corporate,l. pen. c. de princip. li. 12. 3. when the profit is priuate, but
yet a publike good commeth of it: as the dowry
of women, and the infranchiſing of Citizens,
4. when it doth ſo profit particulerly, as that
it doth not diſprofit generally: g. as when we
ſay that it is not expedient, that men ſhould
miſpend their goodes, or throw them into the
Sea: That reaſon therfore is of more force in
law, which is more generally commodious.
               At
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ipſa vtilitas iusti prope
mater et aequi.Horati.
               
               It is good therefore for the Student to fift
out the reaſon of the Law, &amp; that by very diligent
&amp; earneſt ſearch: for the reaſon of the law
is the life &amp; ſoule of the Law: Wherfore not
without good cauſe is Bartolus reproued of the
Ciuilians,
                  Alciat. li. 1. de verb. ſign. for that he denied reaſon to be of
the eſſence of the Law: And ſurely I thinke
there is no Law wholy without reaſon, I
mean which was not grounded vpon reaſon at
the fift making of it. Yet I will confeſſe that
the reaſon of many Lawes is ſo obſcure, and

vncertain, that it can hardly be found out, conceyued,
or deliuered. The Law is the inuention
of wiſe men, who would not make any
thing publique without reaſon, though the reaſon
of the Law may be hid from him, from me,
and from a number of men: Neither are we to
think that any Law is therefore without reaſon,
becauſe a reaſon therof can not be rendred:
for as Cicero ſaid well, Iniquum est quod accidit
non agnoſcere, ſi, cur id accidat, reperire nequeamus,
                  Cicer. in ora. ad Brut. 
                  It is an vniuſt thing not to acknowledg
the thing which hath happened, becauſe we
cannot find out the reaſon, wherfore it happened.
It is not good to affirme that the Lawes
made by wiſe men do want reaſon, becauſe we
can not diſcouer ye reaſon. But as I do not like
Plato his conceit, whē he forbiddeth yong men
not to inquire of the reaſon of the lawes:Plat. lib. 1. de leg. So
to be too curious in the inquiſition of it, wil be
rather matter of trouble then of praiſe to the
Students: Therfore it is a point of humility &amp;
modeſtie to think thoſe things, which by graue
&amp; ſage men haue bin eſtabliſhed for law, not to
be without reaſon, though ye reaſon therof can
not be diſcerned. And that which Gentilis wittily
ſpeaketh of the Ciuil law, may be affirmed
of the cōmon law of this realm, Rationem vbi
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                     
habet, ſed non vbi
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      conſpicuam.
                  Alber. Gentilis lib. 2. Epiſtol. c. 2. 
                  Caſtrenſis is ſo
peremptory for ye reaſon of the law yt he boldly
auoucheth, yt he neuer ſaw any law, wherof he
did not ſee the reaſon.Caſtr. in eo § item ſi reip. 
                  Theodoſius did aſcribe

ſuch aucthoritie to the deceaſſed profeſſors of
the law, that he would haue their anſweres in
doubtful matters to haue the force &amp; ſtrength
of a Law. And the ſame thing was done by
Auguſtus, as Pomponius reporteth.li. 2. de orig. iur. But yet I
could wiſh, as Gentilis
                  Abberic. Gentil. lib. 3. Epiſtol. c. 17. &amp; Alcitat
                  Alciat. lib. 4. perarerg. c. 17. do require,
that the aucthorities and caſes of the learned
writers of the Law ſhould rather be weighed,
then numbred: that is, ſhould rather be examined
how they accord with reaſon, then how
many they be in number: but if it ſo fall out,
that two men of great iudgemēt do diſſent, his
argument is to be held for Law, which reaſon
doth informe &amp; enforce to be agreeable to the
truth: For no man will intend the meaning of
the Law to be, that the opinion of any man,
though ſinguler in knowledge, ſhould be preferred
before the truth: For both the Lawyer
&amp; Iudge are the miniſters &amp; diſpenſers of Iuſtice,
&amp; of the giftes of God, &amp; are ſeruants to
God him ſelfe: but the ſeruant muſt not do that
which the Maſter will not permit: but neither
Iuſtice nor God will do any thing againſt
the truth: Therfore, neither the Lawyer nor
Iudge ought to do any thing againſt ye truth.
If Iuſtice ſhould iudge according to opinion, &amp;
not according to verity, it ſhould thē do iniury,
which thing is againſt her nature. And though
many arguments be made for the preſeruing
and maintayning of the rigor of Law, yet none

of them ought ſo to be admitted againſt iuſtice
and truth, as that occaſion of iniurie may
ſeeme thence to ariſe, whence right and equitie
ſhould proceede:l. meminerint. c. vn. vi. li
                        •
                     . 42. coll. 9. becauſe no reaſon of the
lawe, no courſe of equitie will tollerate, that
thoſe things which haue bene conueniently
introduced for the profit of men, ſhould be againſt
their profit with a more hard and rigorous
interpretation reſtreined. For theſe
things which be eſtabliſhed for a certaine end,
ought not to worke the contrarie.l. quod fauor▪ c. de legi▪
                   But ſome
perhaps will obiect, that a Iudge ought to determin
and a Lawyer ought to argue, according
to the knowledge which he hath by the
written lawe, and that is the reaſon and conſcience
of a Lawyer, as he is a Lawyer. But
ſurely ſuch arguments are not proofes, and
ſuch iudgements if they be not according to
the truth of the thing it ſelfe, in reaſon are
not ſound nor maintenable. For euery proofe
ſhould be a true aſſertion, and euery iudgement
the rule of truth. And how can that
ſeeme iuſt according to the lawe, which appeareth
to a mans conſcience to be vniuſt.
Surely the light of the truth in an honeſt
mind dimmeth and obſcureth all cauils and
quillets: And it is a friuolous dreame to
thinke, that a Lawyer hath one conſcience as
a Lawyer, and an other conſcience as a Chriſtian.
For he hath but one ſoule, and knowledge

of the truth, and therefore but one
conſcience: for conſcientia is cordis ſcientia,
and no reaſon will require that a lye, by any
diſtinction ſhoulde bee preferred before the
truth. The principall meane to enquire after
the truth of euery thing, is to examin of
two or more contrarie reaſons whether is
more probable. That which is plauſible to
common vnderſtanding is tearmed probable,
and whē the words of a couenant or deuiſe be
cleare &amp; manifeſt, we follow the literall ſenſe
of thē without farther inueſtigation, becauſe
in things that be certaine, and apparant, there
is no place for coniecture: but whē the words
be obſcure, or whē ſome thing is omitted, leaſt
the graunt, couenaunt, or deuiſe do faile, we
haue alwaies recourſe to that which is more
probable, and wee imagine that more was
ſpoken then written, and more intended,
then vttered. And it is not conuenient, that
in the affaires of men, the interpretation
which dependeth vpon probable coniecture
ſhould be excluded.l. non aliter. ff. de legat. 3. A thing may be probable
many wayes, firſt,deciſ. Neapol. 44. Numb. 26. by the common vſe of
ſpeech,Marius Salmonius ad. l. omnes populi ff. de iuſtitia &amp; iure. ſecondly, by comparing the conſequent
with the antecedent, thirdly, by the circumſtances
of a mans actions, fourthly, by the
concordance or agreement with the lawe, becauſe
euery one is intended to cōforme his wil
according to lawe, vnleſſe the contrary be proued:

                  quaero. §. inter locatorem. ff. locat. but it may be ſayde, that where the
words of the law do faile, the law it ſelfe doth
faile.L. 4. §. totie
                        •
                      ff. de damn. infer. And words were inuented, that they
might ſhew the meaning of the parties, therefore
we muſt not regard that which is probable,
but that which the words do ſound.l. ſi repetendi c. de condi
                        •
                     . ob cauſam.
To this I anſwere, that there ought to be
no departing from the words, and from the
true propertie, vnleſſe there bee apparant
proofe of an other meaning:l. non alit
                        ••
                      ff. de leg. 3. but where
an other meaning doth appeare, there the
toung yeeldeth to the heart, and the words
do giue place to the meaning.Bal. in c. mandat. de reſcript. The words
onely in ſuch caſe are not to be regarded,
but wee muſt conſider what was meant by
the perſon, quantitie, qualitie, place, time,
precedents, conſequents, and other circumſtances.
l. penult. ff. ad exhib. Alciat. in l. 1. ff. de verb. ſign. And where it is ſayd that if the
words faile the lawe doth faile, it is true,
vnleſſe there bee ſome ſecret intent of the
lawe to the contrarye,Tiraquell. in l. ſi vnquam ad verb. lib. Num. 35. C. de reuoc. donat. the ground whereof
is probabilitie. And though a mans ſenſe
and meaning be declared by his words,Quintilian. lib. 7. c. 7. yet
becauſe there bee more thinges which wee
thinke, then which wee ſpeake or write, the
ſpeech of a man is not alwayes the touchſtone
of the minde, but the concurrence of circumſtances:
and though a mans words ought
to be taken moſt ſtrongly againſt him,ad. d. l. ſi inguam in princi. num. 54. yet
they are wel to be ſifted &amp; examinedl. ſemper in ſtipulationibu
                        •
                      ff. eod. leaſt the

interpretation bee too burdenous in ſome
caſe,Loriotus de reg. axiom. 105. and ſo vniuſt againſt the partie. A
mans ſpeech doth conſiſt of words and meaning,
euen as a man himſelfe doth conſ
                     •
                  ſt of
bodie and ſoule, or to make the matter more
plai
                     •
                  e, the words are but the ſuperficies, and
the intent or meaning is the ſubſtance.l. tutor petitus §. 1. ff. de excuſ. tut. And
the lawe traceth the meaning of a man by the
circumſtances, euen as the hunter traceth the
hare by the print of his foote.Bartol. in l. ſi quis ſerio coll. vltim c. de fur▪ &amp; Conſ. 275. lib 2. num. 2. Yet I would
not that a mans deede or act in the countrie
ſhould be made fruſtrate by ſome Iewiſh or
miſticall interpretation: but ſuch an intendment
muſt be taken, as the words being compare
                     •
                  
with circumſtances will yeeld. For
words are not by violence to be racked, but by
circumſtance to be ruled. And wee muſt alwayes
ſo interpret, that a mans right may be
vpholden. But it may be further obiected,
that in graunts and contracts, and in other
priuate affaires Caſus omiſſus habetur pro omiſſo
                  l. ſi commodiſſim. ff. de liber. &amp; poſthu. l. poſt dotem. ff. ſolut. mat
                        •
                     im. and the inte
                     ••
                  ion or meaning of a man,
which is not apparant and manifeſt, is as a
child vnborne, which is of no account till he
be brought to light.l. Vlt. c. de poſth. haered. inſtit. Bald. ad l. 1. C. qui admit. ad bonor. poſt. &amp; col. 9. For a mans ſpeech is
an externall act, which is ordained for the
declaration of his inwarde meaning,l. Labeo ff. de ſupell. legat. and
therefore words are ſayd to be the limits of
our meaning.Socyn conſi. 4. lib. 41. Iaſon. Conſ. 140. lib. 2. To anſwere directly, theſe
words (Caſus omiſſus &amp;c.) are to be vnderſtood

onely in ſuch caſes where a thing is omitted,
both in reſpect of the not expreſſing of it, and
in reſpect of the not implying it. But where
the lawe will vphold the meaning of the partie,
there is no neede of words: and though
words were inuented, that they might expreſſe
our thoughts, yet by them onely our
meaning is not ſignified. But there be other
ſignesl. 3. ff. de teſti. l. de minore. ff. de quaeſt. namely, the circumſtances before the
acte, in the acte, and after the acte. Thus it is
euident, that the beſt and moſt probable reaſon
in the conflict of oppoſite arguments, is to be
ſought for by the Student, and how it may
be found.
               4 The beſt interpreter of the law is common
reaſon and intendement.l. ſi de interpret. ff. de ll. Wherefore if
any one mans opinion do differ from common
reaſon, let the Student auoide it. Neither are
ſuch things without cauſe to be altered, which
haue alwayes heretofore receiued a certaine
interpretation.l. minime ff. de legi. Neither is the common
lawe any other thing, then a determinate order
eſtabliſhed and ratified by common conſent.
Wherefore Bodinus ſaith not well, who
putteth this difference betwixt a lawe and a
cuſtome, in that a cuſtome is accepted by the
plauſible agreement of the multitude, but a
lawe ſpringeth vp in a moment,Bodin. lib. 1. de repub. c. 10. and is commaunded
by the authoritie of the Rular, many
times againſt the liking of them that are

bound by it. For common lawe is that which
is made and approued by common allowance,
and therefore it is lawe, becauſe it is
commonly vſed for lawe. Wherefore Athenaeus
                  Athenaeus lib. 12. c. 22. andPolibyus hiſtor. lib. 6. 
                  Polibius do vpon good ground &amp;
reaſon reproue the lawes of Plato, becauſe no
nation of Greece could be perſwaded to vſe
them: but as Plato faigned lawes, ſo he might
likewiſe faigne men to vſe them: therefore
Horace ſayd rightly, Quid leges ſine moribus
vanae proficiunt? Lawes without vſe are vaine
and profit not.
                  
                  Horat. lib. 4. 
                        •
                     arm▪ ode. 24. But here it is good for the
Student to be aſſured of what nature &amp; qualitie
the thing is which I call common reaſon
or intendement, for that may ſeeme to offer
doubt, whether we ought to aſcribe common
reaſon and opinion to the number of authors,
or to the worthines of them, or to the perſwaſion
of reaſon which doth concludenter demonſtrare
to the ſenſe &amp; vnderſtāding of ye moſt part
of men of indifferent capacitie. I would haue
cōmon opiniō takē according to this laſt brāch.
               5 The things which be odious in lawe muſt
be reſtrained, &amp; the things which be fauorable
muſt be enlarged. Priuat cuſtomes are odious
in the eie of lawe, &amp; whatſoeuer ſwarueth frō
common right:c. cum delect. de conſuetud. l. cum quidam. ff. de lib. &amp; poſth. for the cōmon law was framed
in fauour of publike tranquilitie, &amp; therefore
the departure frō it muſt needs be accounted
odious.Aymo conſil. 170. nu. 3. Baldus in l. non poſſunt ff. de legib. The lawe is more proane to acquite,

then to condemne:l. Arrianus. ff. de oblig. &amp; act. and becauſe it is
better with the reſtraint of an odious conſtitution,
to abſolue one that is giltie, then with the
enlarging &amp; amplifying of it to condemne one
that is innocent,l. abſentem. ff. de paenis. therefore there is nothing
that requireth more diligence &amp; conſideration,
then to deale warily where there is great danger
to any partie, that a man may not raſhly
determin of a mans credit, bloud, or life: ſith
theſe things be of that qualitie, that being
once loſt, they cā neuer be repaired.cap. vbi maius ſup. de elect. lib. 6. But to
know whether things be fauorable or odious,
the things are not to be cōſidered in thēſelues,
but theffects which proceed of thē
                  Alciat. ad l. 2. in num. 44. de verb. oblig. as dower
is fauored in reſpect of the widowhood, &amp; deſolatenes
of the woman whoſe huſband is deceaſſed.L. 1. ff. ſolut. matrim.
               
               6 It muſt likewiſe be obſerued, that when
a thing is forbidden, all things that follow
therof are likewiſe forbidden: as on the contrary
part when a thing is granted, all things
are implicatiuely graunted with it, whereby
we may attaine to the thing graunted:l. ad rem mobil. ff. de procur. l. 2. ff. de iuriſd. om. iud. Temps E. 1. Grauntes. 41. and
if the beginning of things be forbidden, the
end alſo is forbidden according to the rule,
Qui meditatur principiū meditatur etiā finem,
                  bald. ad L. quamuis. c. de fide comm.
and things are principally forbidden for the
end to which they are directed. But here a diſtinction
is to be vſed, for where the conſequēt
is of it ſelf auaileable, and doth not neceſſarily

depend vpon the power and vertue of the antecedent,
it may be of force, though the antecedent
be forbidden,Baldus ad d. l. non dubi. in 13. oppoſitione for then it is without
the cauſe of the prohibition: but if it depend
eſſentially vpon the antecedent, it is otherwiſe.
For the better vnderſtanding of this
rule, it is good to be ſeene what may properly
be ſayd a principall thing, and what an acceſſorie.
That is principall which is of greateſt
moment: an acceſſorie thing is that, which
by conſequence goeth with the principall.
If the Queene graunt vnto one Cognitionem
cauſae, her highnes graunteth vnto him the
hearing of the parties, and the examination
of witneſſes. So the margarites or pretious
ſtones that be in gold or ſiluer, do yeeld vnto
it, and do paſſe with it, becauſe they are but
the ornaments thereof, and were applied to
the decking and beawtifying of it. An acceſſorie
briefely may be taken to be that, which
is adioyned to a thing, and is leſſe then the
thing to which it is annexed, either in ſubſtance
or in valew, or in reſpect both of ſubſtance
and valew.
               7 The validitie of an act muſt be eſpecially
fauored, vnleſſe there be a manifeſt nullitie
in the proceeding.l. quoties ff. de verb. oblig. Therefore whenſoeuer
the nullitie of an act ſhall appeare by the
proceeding of the parties, which is ſayd to
be euident, and notorious and excluding all

cauill,Bart. in l. 3. parag. condemnat. ff. de re iud. it is to be held as voyd, but if the nullitie
propoſed do not ſo appeare, but requireth
a deeper ſearch, becauſe many times error is
obiected that the Sute may be protracted,
there conſideration muſt bee vſed. But in
doubtfull cauſes interpretation muſt bee ſo
made, that the acte may rather ſtand then fall.
But the obiection of error is alway to be fauored,
when the error aſſigned doth concerne
the figure &amp; ſolemnitie of iudgement.9. E. 4. 3. gloſſ. in verb. defenſiones in de ſaepe de verb. figu. And
therefore he that will diſpute of the validitie
of an award or iudgement, ought to be warie
and carefull, that he put the axe to the roote,
and that he firſt examin the iuriſdiction and
power of the Iudge, becauſe that being the
baſis and foundation of the iudgement, if that
fall, the reſt cannot ſtand. It is therefore to be
cōſidered whether he were a competēt Iudge
by reaſon of the cauſe, of the parties, of the
time, and the place. For by reaſon of the ſute
or cauſe, a Iudge may be incompetent, as if
the cauſe belong to a meere iuriſdiction, and
the Iudge be only a Magiſtrate in a certaine
corporation: or if the cauſe be ciuill, and the
Iudge who taketh connuſans of it be Iudge
of Gaole deliuerie, or if the Iudge be ſecular,
and the cauſe Eccleſiaſticall, or if the Iudge
haue ſome other limited iuriſdiction, and he
taketh connuſans of a cauſe not cōprehended
within the liſts &amp; bounds of his commiſſion,

he may be incompetent alſo by reaſon of the
place, as if he iudge of cauſes without his territorie,
or circuite, or els within his territorie,
but yet in a place exempted, he may be incompetent
by reaſon of the time, as if he did iudge
before he had his commiſſion, or after his commiſſion
expired, or if his iuriſdiction were ſuſpended,
as at feſtiuall times, which wee call
dies non iuridicos, or at ſuch a time, when a
greater Iudge was preſent: or if the Iudge
were called to a higher place, or if he were forbidden
to exerciſe his power. And alſo the perſon
&amp; qualitie of the partie is to be conſidered,
becauſe ſome by reaſon of a legall impedimēt
are vncapeable of the aduantidge of lawe, as
theſe that are outlawed, excommunicate, and
out of the Queenes protection. And there can
be no faſt roote or ſure ground of their proceedings,
for ſuch are to be denied audience, becauſe
their offence &amp; default ought not to find
patronage. Likewiſe there may be a default
in ye party making an Attorney, as if he could
not make an Attorney in that cauſe, or elſe by
reaſon of the Attorney himſelfe, as if he be vncapeable
of ſuch an office as being not lawfulby
aucthoriſed. But if a iuriſdiction be giuen
and graunted to one, it is to be intended to be
giuen him accumulatiue, &amp; non priuatiue, rather
to enlarge, then to diminiſh his power.
And though a Iudge of the Gaole deliuery

being appointed and ordained by commiſſion
to the hearing of cauſes criminall, may not
principally inquire of cauſes ciuill and pecuniarie,
becauſe it is a Iuriſdiction limitted,
yet incidently and as it were by the way, for
the better examining of capitall crimes, hee
may take notice of ſuch things. But if the
proceſſe and iudgement bee framed againſt
one, who is not onely not ſubiect to his iuriſdiction,
but is alſo free from the iuriſdiction
of euery man liuing, as if the partie be dead,
concerning whome, no acte can be conceiued
or vpheld, the Iudgement is voide.
               Thus haue I ſhewed to the Student in
ſo generall manner as the order of this treatiſe
doth require, and likewiſe ſo particularly,
as to his vnderſtanding may be playne and
manifeſt, what courſe hee ought to take in
examining the caſes, reaſons, opinions, arguments,
proceedings, and iudgements, whereof
he ſhall finde great ſtore and aboundance
in his bookes. Now I will by fauour diſcend
to deſcribe and delineate vnto him briefely
(for it is a matter which may be handled
plainely and in fewe wordes) what courſe
hee ought to obſerue in the exerciſe of his
ſtudie.
            
            
               
               Of the exerciſe and conference
which the Student
of the lawe ought to
vſe.
               The fifth Chapter.
               
                  EVery art and knowledge produceth
effects, and like a good weapon
is vnſheathed &amp; vſed in time
conuenient, otherwiſe it would be
quickly ouercaſt and eaten with ruſt. But
there is nothing that with ſo much brightnes
and glory illuſtrateth our knowledge, as the
orderly and iudiciall applying and accommodating
of that which we haue read. For as
a man knoweth by his bookes, ſo he is known
by his practiſe, and by that which he is able to
performe in the faculty which he profeſſeth,
and hee which knoweth to himſelfe is not
knowne of other men. Wherefore I ſuppoſe
it a thing of exceeding moment for the Student,
to demeane himſelfe well in his conference
and exerciſe, leaſt the multitude of
howers which he hath ſpent, do ſlip from him

without vſe, as the ſand falleth out of the
howre-glaſſe, when no man ſeeth or mindeth
it.
               1 The ſtudent of the lawe ought to haue
great regard of his ſpeech, and that he deliuer
his opinion or argument in conuenient and
orderly ſort, not after a rude confuſed and
impolite manner, and hee who is not onely
wiſe but eloquent, is without compariſon
the beſt in all profeſſions which conſiſt in
practiſe and in the forme of ſpeech. Therefore
parents and tutors in the Uniuerſity
ſhould haue principall regard, that he who
is to addreſſe himſelfe to the ſtudy of the
lawe, may be fitt with a plauſible grace to
diſcourſe and diſpute, and euen in the prime
of our yeares this care muſt be had. For
by nature we hold that faſt which in our tender
yeares we conceiue, and the worſe ſort
of things do ſtedfaſtly abide in vs, the better
is ſoone turned to worſe, but in this matter
it is good to follow the precepts of ſuch
as be neyther too curious nor too ignorant:
for there is nothing more like a may-game
then theſe vaineglorious perſons, who haue
decked themſelues with a falſe perſwaſion
of knowledge. To the Student of the lawe
I doe therefore thinke this courſe neceſſary,
becauſe he muſt liue in great celebritie in

the aſſembly of the people, and in the middeſt
of the common weale. Let him therefore
enure himſelfe from his youth, to frequent
aſſemblyes: let him not be afrayde
of men, nor appalled or tymerous through
a ſhadowed kinde of life, leaſt when hee
ſhoulde make vſe of hys ſtudye, hys eyes
daſ
                     •
                  e at mid-day, and all thinges bee newe
vnto hym, who ſeeketh that in hymſelfe,
which is to bee done and performed in a
multitude: Yet I woulde not haue hym
too curious and deynty in hys ſpeeche, for
wee muſt vſe wordes as wee vſe coyne, thoſe
which be common and currant. And it is
a great errour for a man to eſtrange himſelfe
from the common vſe of ſpeach, and
to exceeding preciſeneſſe in wordes, and
ſtile, doth quench the heate of our inuention,
and brideleth the courſe of our wittes.
Yet it is commendable to haue in our diſcourſes
both good wordes, and good matter.
For Cicero dyd not fight with armour
of proofe onely, but wyth bright-ſhining
harneſſe, when hee did not onely gayne the
admiration of the Romanes, but theyr acclamation
alſo and applauſe. But let good
wordes conteyne in them good matter, that
the Argument or diſcourſe may not ſhyne
as it were by oyle and oyntment but by

bloud and complexion. It is a feauer-like
payne to endure a mans ſpeech, loadned
with ſuperfluous wordes. In all thynges
decorum muſt be obſerued, leaſt that which
wee ſaye, doe turne to laughter, or loathing,
and purchaſe the name of folly, a
meane muſt bee kept, leaſt our ſpeach bee
drye and faynt, or elſe too copious, and full
of circumſtaunces: yet it is better for the
inuention to bee abundaunt and copious,
then to bee leane and poore. Wordes if
they bee not veſted with the ſubſtaunce of
thynges, are of no force: Rhetoricke which
is the Artificer of perſwaſion, if it bee ſeuered
from circumſtaunces, and raunge
without learning by a facile kinde of ſway.
It is called Atechina. If it bee applyed to
the deſtruction of good men, it is tearmed
Cacotechina, but if it bee beſtowed in vayne
and ſuperfluous matters, it may bee tearmed
Mataeotechina, a friuolous labour, and
a tryflyng arte. There is nothing whiche
more beawtifieth a mans ſpeeche, then an
apte diuiſion or partition of the thynges
which bee handled, whiche doth eaſe the
mynde of the hearer, prepareth the mynde
of the vnderſtander, and refreſheth the
memorye, and (as Iustinian ſayeth) the

obſcurytie which doth ryſe of a confuſed
text, is by ſeparation and diuiſion diſperſed
and remoued.Iuſtin. in §. alio. inſti. quib. modis tes. infirm. &amp; in §. ſed ne in primis de leg. And as the diuiſion of fields
doth make the tillage more plentifull and
ſightly, ſo doth partition in the handling of
cauſes, adorne and garniſh them. Theſe
things may be aptly deuided which haue
a ſeperate reaſon, and are ſorted to diuers
endes.
               2 Students ſhall not do amiſſe, if at
certaine times they meete amongſt themſelues,
and do propoſe ſuch things as they
haue read or 
                     •
                  eard by that meane to be aſſured
of the opinion of others in ſuch matters.
By this courſe it may be brought to
paſſe, that euery one may both better vnderſtand,
and more firmely reteine in memory
the thinges which hee hath read or
heard, and theſe things which be to good
purpoſe vttered of others, hee may enioy
as his owne. For priuate conference there
is no time amiſſe; Adrianus the Emperour
(as Dio reporteth) did handle and diſcuſſe
pointes of lawe at dynner tyme. M. Cat
                        •
                     
                  
euen in the Court whiles the Senate was
aſſembling, did buſie himſelfe in reading:
and ſurely, he that hath a minde to learne,
may learne at euery place, and at euery
tyme.
               
                  
3 Gentlemen ſtudents of the Law ought
by domeſtical Moots to exerciſe and conforme
themſelues to greater &amp; waightier attempts,
for it is a point of warlike policy, as appeareth
by Vegetius to traine young Souldiours by
ſleight and ſmal ſkirmiſhes for more valerous
and haughtie proceedinges,Veget. lib. 1. de re militari. for ſuch a ſhadowed
kind of contention doth open the way,
and giue courage vnto them to argue matters
in publique place and Courts of Recorde, and
it will not be amiſſe, ſometimes to reaſon together,
before men of more reading and greater
iudgement which may friendly admoniſh
them, and if they erre reduce them into the
right way, It is good to bring ſuch matters
into queſtion as be diſputable, &amp; may deſerue
argument, for it were a vaine thing to make a
doubt of that which is plaine and manifeſt, as
whether a rent or annui
                     •
                  ie ought to be paid to
a dead man, or whether a man may commit an
offence againſt the Law without puniſhment
and ſuch like, wherein if a man ſhould a
                     •
                  ke any
mans opinion, hee might perhaps receiue
ſuch aunſwere as Labio did of Iubentius Celſus:
Aut non intellig
                        •
                      quid ſit de quo me conſulis,
aut valde ſtulta eſt conſultatio tua.
                  l. Domitins Labio de teſtā. It is
euident that one Law may with good probability
heare ſeuerall interpretations, but that
ſence is moſt to be imbraced which doth take
away the occaſion of doubting, the way to remoue

doubt, is to examine well the reaſons
of the contrary part, wherefore Baldus ſaith
well.
               
                  Ferro aperire viam qui per contraria tranſit.
                  In l. precib. c. de impub.
And to looſe doubts is to find out the truth as
Aristotle ſaith,Ariſt. Metaphyſ. 3. but often conference and priuate
debating of points of Law, is the fountaine
and originall of exceeding profit, for by
it the wit, the memory and the tongue, are
greatly furthered and holpen, and a man is
made more ready &amp; bold for publike matters,
and the truth which is the marke of our ſtudy,
doth more eaſily appeare. Wherefore it is not
vnfitly ſaid of Marcellus the lawier, that euery
art by continual exerciſe doth receiue increaſe.
In l. legatis §. ornatri. de leg. 3. The wit if it be ſomewhat dull is by conference
more ſharpened, if it be ripe and ready
it is a great deale more furthered, and to the
memory nothing can be more profitable, which
of it ſelfe is ſo brittle and tender, that vnleſſe
it be renewed with continual exerciſe, it will
eaſily periſh. And in vaine ſhall a man paſſe away
the night without ſ
                     •
                  epe, or the day without
recreation, in vaine ſhall he run ouer the
volumes of the Law, in vaine ſhall hee inquire
after the opinions of the learned, vnles his memory
do repreſent and readily offer vnto him
theſe things being with great labor followed
and atchiued when time and occaſion ſhall require,
I neede not ſhew how much it doth benefit

&amp; poliſh the tongue: for conference is the
proper exerciſe of the tongue. I ſaid that boldnes
is procured by the frequent meeting and
communication of ſtudents, &amp; I wil auow that
which I haue auerred, for as by degrees a man
doth conuerſe and talke with his companions
and ſuch as be better then himſelfe, ſo by degrees
he groweth bolder, which may bee gathered
by that Fable of Eſope: The Fox did by
chance mete the Lyon whom he neuer ſaw before,
&amp; was ſo affrighted that his ſenſes were
almoſt loſt, when he ſaw him the ſecond time,
he feared likewiſe, but nothing ſo much as before,
but when he ſaw him the third time, hee
was ſo little afraid, that he went vnto him and
talked with him. I ſaid further that it was the
high way to diſcerne the truth of euery thing,
and therefore Archadius ſaieth of Herennius
Modestinus that by much diſputation he atteined
to excellent iudgement,In. l. mune
                        •
                     . §. miſta. de muneri. &amp; honori. wherfore let
the ſtudent often reſort vnto his fellow ſtudents,
and amongſt them let him be well aduiſed
of his choiſe.
               4 After priuate and home exerciſe, publike
exerciſe muſt enſue, which muſt not be raſhly
done, but there muſt be both maturitie of yeres
and aduiſe, leaſt the vnripe braine doe make
the forehead to bluſh, and in ſtead of praiſe we
reape contempt. Surely it is the beginning
and foundation of impudency, for a man to

becauſe the opening of the dore, and the holding
of the Candle was not parcel of the conſūmation
of the act, and ſo was the Law taken
3. of Queene Elizabeth.
                  3. Eliz. 186. Dyer. An adulterer did
counſell the woman to murder the child when
it ſhould bee borne, the child was borne and
murdered by the Midwife in preſence of the
Mother, and by her commandment, The Mother
&amp; the Midwife be principal, and the Adulterer
but acceſſary, becauſe his counſel was
before the birth, and he was not cooperant in
the act, but becauſe the force of his perſwaſion
and counſell did continue vntill the murder
it being not countermanded by him, therefore
he was held and adiudged an acceſſarie, but
whether in the ſame caſe if the woman be admitted
to be acceſſary, whether ſhe ſhould bee
a traitreſſe or no, becauſe the principall is no
traytour, is a queſtion which may well beare
argument on the one ſide vpon the letter of
the Law, and on the other ſide vpon the meaning
of the Law, but of this matter I haue
giuen the Student a ſufficient taſte, and my
meaning was in this treatiſe rather to drawe
the lineaments of things, then to diſcuſſe them
to the full. Theſe may ſerue to prepare the
minde of the Student to handle ſuch things
as may ſeeme to be contradictory in the body
of the Law.
               6 That the Student may with more eaſe

compas and accompliſh the things precedent,
it is good for him to haue great care of preſeruing
and continuing his memory, and therfore
it is a profitable courſe vnder titles to digeſt
the caſes of the Lawe, into which they
may tranſfer ſuch things as they haue either
heard or read, neither is it ſafe to truſt to other
mens Abridgements which are little auaileable
to ſuch as haue read little, but that which
we by our owne ſweat and labor do gaine, we
do firmely retaine, and in it we do principally
delight, and I am perſwaded there hath neuer
bin any learned in the Law, and iudicial, who
hath not made a collection of his owne, though
he hath not neglected the Abridgements of others,
The memory is ſpecially to be helped
and increaſed of the Student, for though it be
the gift of nature, yet by induſtry it becommeth
more excellent. For the integrity of
the memory it is good to haue ſound health &amp;
conuenient digeſtion of the meate, and a mind
free from all other thoughtes, It helpeth it
much to make good diuiſions, for he that deuideth
things aright, can neuer erre in the order
of things. There is nothing ſurely which doth
either more growe by diligence or by negligence
more decay then memory, It is not
good truſting to a ſuddeine memorie, but a
nights reſt will adde great ſtrength vnto it.

Of what force memory is by nature and labor
Themistocles may witnes, who in one yeares
ſpace did ſpeake the Perſian language verie
perfectly and Mithridates who did well vnderſtande
the two and twentie languages of
the nations whom he did gouerne. M. Craſſus
whiles he was Preſident of Aſia attained
to the fiue differences of the Greeke tongue.
Cyrus did remember the names of all his Soldiors
who were in his Campe. And if memory
be neceſſarie for any ſcience, ſurely to the profeſſion
of the Law, it is of weightie importance,
which becauſe it doth purſue accidentia,
and infinita requireth no helpe of nature ſo
much as memorie, for the vnderſtanding conueyeth
the caſes to that treaſury; out of which
it draweth them as often as vſe and oportunitie
doth demande. But if the vnderſtanding be
good, and the memorie nought, a man ſhall be
a Lawyer to day and none to morow. Wherefore
in this part the Student muſt excell, and
that he may excell, he muſt labor, and that hee
may labor, he muſt haue health, which I wiſh
vnto him.
            
            
               
               That the vnderſtanding
of the Student ought to be
proportionable to the intendement
of the Law.
               The ſixth Chapter.
               
                  THe Law conſidereth thinges according
to publique reſpect, that
is, as much as concerneth the
common weale, not according to
their contingencie in facto, which is euery
mans obiect, and familiar to common ſenſe,
and therefore needeth not any artificall handling:
And the Students vnderſtanding muſt
be ſo ſequeſtred &amp; re
                     ••
                  ued from vulgar opinion:
being the mother of error, and meaſuring
thinges onely by the ſkinne, and colour, that
he muſt comprehend &amp; conclude many things,
which are verie remote from the reach of the
the ſenſes, and from ordinarie apprehenſion:
in which contemplation the common Law of
this Realme of England aboue all other doth
ſhew wonderfull ſharpnes, and a moſt exquiſite
conceit, ſubtilizing thinges whereof common
ſenſe hath but a confuſe knowledge, being
guyded by the principall reaſon &amp; inſeperable

truth of euery thing, which the vnderſtanding
ſtraineth out of the ſecret and hidden cauſes
of thinges: for as in hearbes, if we touch them
outwardly, we do not finde nor feele any moiſture
in them, but rather take them to be vrie,
vntill by preſſing or diſtilling of them, we
wring out a iuyce proper to their nature: So
the Law doth conceiue and conclude many
things of ordinarie contingents, which common
ſenſe can not perceiue, but rather imagineth
them to be clean contrary to the truth,
whereas they may to a good vnderſtāding eaſily
appeare to be true by the certaintie &amp; neceſſary
coordination of their cauſes and reaſons.
That this may be made euident I mean to annexe
ſome particulars for the explaning therof.
               1 It is cleere by Law, that a terme and a
freehold of the ſelfe ſame thing may be both in
one man at one time, yet if this be deliuered to
a ſuperficiall vnderſtanding, it will ſeeme a paradoxe.
Tenant for terme of yeres maketh his
executors &amp; dyeth, the executors purchaſeth
the reuerſion, in this caſe both the terme &amp; fee-ſimple
are in the executor to ſeueral purpoſes:
for the terme ſhal be aſſets to the vſe of the teſtator,
&amp; the fee ſimple free inheritance for the
vſe of the executor &amp; his heires,43. E. 3. 27. et. Br. caſes. And if a man
be ſeiſed of land of an eſtate for life, the remainder
to his executors for yeres, he may deuiſe
this term or aſſigne it.16. E. 2. per Herle, Couenants 25. And if leſſee for yeres

grant his terme to the wife of him in ye reuerſion,
&amp; to a ſtranger, the inheritance of the huſband
can not extinguiſh the moitie of ye terme:
becauſe he hath the inheritance in his owne
right, &amp; the terme in right of his wife.14. Eliz. 416. Com. Bracebridges caſe. A man
ſeiſed of land in right of his wife is attainted
of felony, &amp; the king ſeiſeth the land pro vita
viri, the king hath but a chattel &amp; the wife the
freehold: for if a ſtranger enter, &amp; the huſband
dye, the wife ſhall haue an Aſſiſe.
                  4. E. 3. 47.
               
               2 Likewiſe it will ſeeme ſtrange, though in
Law &amp; reaſon it be true, that a man ſhould be
remitted to his land to ſome intent, &amp; yet not to
an other: As if a recouerie be had vpon a falſe
title againſt tenant in taile, the tenant in taile
dyeth, the iſſue entreth, he is in of his firſt right
againſt all but onely the recoueror.12. E. 4. 21. per Choke. So if tenant
in taile diſcontinue, &amp; his ſonne &amp; heir apparant
diſſeiſeth the diſcontinuee to the vſe of
the father, the tenāt in taile dieth, the ſonne by
M. Chookes opinion is in his remitter againſt
all, but onely the diſcontinuee.12. E. 4. 21. per Choke. et vide 7. R. 2. tit Entre en le Per, en le collect. de Bellew. the iſſue in
taile which hath good cauſe of a Formedon in
the diſcender, is of couin that A. ſhould diſſeiſe
the diſcontinuee againſt whom he recouereth:
he ſhall not be remitted in reſpect of him, but
ſhal be accompted a diſſeiſor:18. H. 8. 5. 15. E. 4. 4. but againſt all
others it ſeemeth that he is remitted. Tenant
in taile maketh a feoffement to the vſe of
his wife and his ſonne being heire apparant

to the intaile and dyeth, the iſſue is remitted
againſt all perſons but onely the woman.4. E. 6. 68. Dyer.
               
               A title may be executed to ſome intent, and
yet not executed to an other: And therefore
if there be tenant for terme of life, the remainder
in fee to a ſtranger, againſt whom a recouerie
is had pro loco &amp; tempore in a Warrantia
chartae, brought by a ſtranger of other land,
he in the remainder dyeth, the recouerer is impleaded
and voucheth the heire of him in the
remainder, and recouereth, tenant for life dyeth,
execution ſhall be 
                     •
                  ued againſt the heire of
the land whereof his aunceſtor had a remainder,
becauſe there was a remainder executed
in the father to this intent at the time of the
Warrantia chartae brought:15. E. 4. 13. per Littleton. but to all other
intents it was executory, for it was not executed
that the wife might be endowed, nor for
him in the remainder to bring a writ of right,
40. E. 3. 43. But the remainder in ſuch caſes is to ſome
intents executed: for if he in the remainder had
aliened his remainder in Mortmaine, the lord
might haue entred,15. E. 4. 13. and vpon ſuch a remainder
the lord may haue a Ceſſauit,
                  27. E. 3. 87. but the
heire ſhall not haue an Aſſiſe of Mortdaunceſter.
                  39. E. 3. 3. Mortdaunceſter 50. Fitzh. Na. bre. 196. k.
               
               4 A thing may be extinct or in ſuſpence in
one reſpect, and in Eſſe in an other reſpect: the
father being tenant in taile alieneth the land
with warrantie, and hath a rent charge in fee

iſſuing out of the land of his ſonne and heire
apparant, which rent diſcendeth to the ſonne,
this rent is a good aſſets for the value in reſpect
of the diſcontinuee: and yet it is extinct
in reſpect of the iſſue.31. E. 3. Garrantie 39. A man ſeiſed of a rent
ſeruice is bound in ſtatute ſtaple, and after
purchaſeth the land, out of which the rent is
iſſuing after execution, the rent is extinct, as
to the conuſor, but in Eſſe as to the conuſee.4. Eliz. 205. Dyer.
A corrodie is graunted to I. S. for life, who
graunteth it backe to the grauntor for terme
of yeares rendring rent, the corrodie is in Eſſe
as to the payment of the rent, but in ſuſpence
as to the taking of the corrodie.20. E. 4. 12. 22. E. 4. 17. 18. And it was
lately ruled in one Caires caſe in the Court of
wardes, that if a man held land of the Queene
by a certaine rent, and the Queene graunteth
the rent to a ſtranger, who graunteth it to the
tenant, the rent is extinct as to the payment,
but in Eſſe as to the tenure. The King ſeiſed
of a forreſt graunted the office of the forreſter
to one rendring rent, and he graunteth
the forreſt to an other, the forreſter forfayteth
his office, yet the grauntor ſhall haue the
rent:26. Aſſ. p. 60. So that it muſt needes be that the office
to the intendment of law is to that intent
in Eſſe. And if a man graunt to an other a rent
out of his land in fee vpon condition, that if
the grauntee or any of his heires dye, their
heire being wythin age, the rent ſhall ceaſe

during the minoritie, if the grauntee dye
hys heire wythin age, his wyfe ſhall haue
dower, but ceſſabit executio during the nonage:
10. H. 7. 13. per Keble. But in this caſe it ſeemeth that if
the heyre dye during his nonage, the wyfe
of the heire ſhall not haue dower of the rent:
becauſe it was neuer leuiable by the ſonne,
as it was by the father. A man ſeyſed of
two acres of lande hath iſſue two daughters
and dyeth, now the rent is in ſuſpence, as to
one moitie, and in Eſſe as to an other moitie.9. E. 3. Charge 4. 9. Aſſ. p. 22.
               
               5 The intendement of the Law is as
ſtronge in a matter of law, as the trueth it
ſelfe in a matter in facto: And therfore if A.
be diſſeiſed, and hys brother maketh a releaſe
with warrantie to the diſſeiſee, and afterward
entreth into religion, this warrantie
ſhall be a barre to A. although that hee
be lyuing:34. E. 3. Garrantie 72. for A. may haue his land by diſcent,
and therefore it ſeemeth to be reaſon,
that the warrantie ſhould diſcende vpon him
as his heyre. Note here of what validitie
the intendement of Law is touching a ciuill
death. The Wardein of the Fleete who hath
the office in fee dyeth ſeiſed, and the office
diſcendeth to his ſonne and heire, being then
in priſon, the Law doth preſently diſcharge
him of impriſonment, becauſe he is to be at

large the better to looke to others, that be in
pryſon.Plow. Com̄ Plats c. 37. A man maketh a leaſe to one for
terme of life, rendring the firſt ſeauen yeares
a roſe, and if he will hold the land any longer
then ſeauen yeares, that then he ſhall pay foure
Markes yerely: liuerie is made, the leſſee ſurrendreth
at the ende of the firſt ſeauen yeares,
his eſtate was adiudged to be but a terme ab
initio, and no freehold, and the writ of couenant
brought againſt him for not repayring
was qui tenuit ad terminum annorum.
                  50. E. 3. 27. If a
man make a leaſe of land excepting the trees
which grow vpon the land, the trees are ſeuered
in law: for he hath no reuerſion of them,
and if he ſell them, and after the ſale make
a feoffement, the feoffee ſhall not haue
them, becauſe they were ſeuered by the vendition
or ſale of them,20. H. 
                        •
                     . 22. for by the exception
they were ſeuered from the terme, but not
from the inheritance, but by the vendition
they were ſeuered from the inheritance. If
the Baylife of the land doe demaunde a rent
ſeruice, and the tenant denyeth it, and the
Baylife ſayth that hee will diſtraine for it▪
and the tenant ſayth that hee ſhall not diſtrayne,
wherefore the Baylife dare not proceede
further to take a diſtreſſe, for doubt of
death, thys is a diſſeyſtn of the rent in the
eye of the Lawe.49. E. 3. 14. Aſſiſe 66. And if a rent ſeruice be
warranted to one, and the land doth eſcheat,

the Law as M. Finchden thinketh tranſferreth
the warrantie to the land.45. E. 3. Voucher 72. per Finchden.
               
               6. One thing in the vnderſtanding of Law
may be of ſeuerall natures in ſeueral reſpects,
and ſo one writ may be two ſeuerall writs to
two ſeuerall intents: In an action of debt the
declaration was of x. li. vpon a ſale, and v. li.
which he had deliuered to the defendaut to redeliuer,
and it was held good, becauſe the action
was in the debet and detinet, and the warrantie
of atturney and the eſſoine in this caſe
ſhall be in placito debiti.
                  32. E. 3. Brief 288. 
                  Quaere, If a man
leaſe land to one for terme of yeares rendring
rent, and the leſſor graunteth his rent to a
ſtranger, and the leſſee ſurrendreth; this doth
not extinguiſh the rent, for now it is a rent
ſeck which doth not depend vpon the reuerſion,

                     
                        •
                     0. E. 4. 12. And ſo one man to the vnderſtanding of
Law may haue ſeuerall capacities or reſpects:
For if a man diſſeiſe a feme ſole, being an inheritrix
of certaine land, and after he taketh her
to wife, and they haue iſſue, and the huſband is
diſſeiſed, and the diſſeiſor leuieth a fine wyth
proclamations, the huſband dyeth fower yeres
after the proclamations, and before the fifth
yere be paſſed, the iſſue being of full age, and
after the wife dyeth, and the fifth yere paſſeth,
now the iſſue is bound as heire to his father,
yet he may haue other fiue yeres, as heire to
his mother, to be accompted from the death of

his Father.Plow. Com. Stowels c. 367 So if I. S. be tenant of land,
for terme of an other mans life, the remainder
to an other for life, the remainder to the ſaid
I. S. for terme of his life, or in fee: and he is
diſſeiſed, and the diſſeiſor leuieth a fine with
Proclamations, and the fiue yeares incurre,
now is I. S. bound for the preſent eſtate, but
if he in the meſne remainder for life die, hee
ſhall haue other fiue yeres for the other eſtate.
Ibid. So if a man haue an eſtate in land for the
life of A. the reuerſion to himſelfe for the life
of B. the remainder to himſelfe for the life
of C. and is diſſeiſed, and the diſſeiſour leuieth
a fine with Proclamations, he ſhal haue
fiue yeares ſeuerally after euerie ſeuerall eſtate
determined.Plow. Com. 368. Stow. cas. I. S. giueth land to A.
his daughter in taile, and hath iſſue B. another
daughter, and dieth, A. dieth hauing iſſue
C. a Precipe is brought againſt C. who
voucheth to warrantie her ſelfe and B. as
heires to the donour of the reuerſion to haue
the warrantie paramount, in this caſe is C.
both the vouchor and the vouchee.2. H. 6. 16. A terme
is deuiſed to one who is made executor, he entreth,
this is an adminiſtration and an execution
of the terme vnto him, and he is both deuiſee
and executor.20. Eli. Com̄ Weldens cas A. couenanteth by Indenture
with B. that the ſonne of A. ſhal marrie
the daughter of B. and that therefore B.
ſhall giue vnto A. an 100. li. &amp; if the marriage

did not take effect before ſuch a day that then
A. and his heires ſhould ſtand ſeiſed to the vſe
of B. and his heires vntill the hundred pound
be payed by A. his heires or executours B. dyeth,
and after the marriage taketh not effect,
the vſe and poſſeſſion of the land veſteth in the
heire of B. but Quaere ſaith Brooke whether
he ſhall be in ward or no, for he is an heire and
yet he is a purchaſor.3. Mar. Br. Feff. al vſes 59. &amp; vide 3. Mar. 128. Dy. Wilf. cas &amp; 13. E. 3. Br̄ Exting. 45. If I. S. be Deane of
P. I may giue him land to him and his ſucceſſours,
and to him and to his heires, there hee
taketh both as Deane and as a priuate man,
and is tenant in common with him ſelfe: ſo if
a rent charge be graunted in ſuch manner, he
ſhal ioine with himſelfe in an Auowry.24. H. 8. 30. per Pollard Likewiſe
the Lawe may deny one a benefite as he
is I. S. and yet allow it vnto him as he is executor
to I. N. and therefore if an executour
be Outlawed, or Excommunicated, which be
diſabilities in Law: yet as an executour hee
may maintaine an action, becauſe he ſueth and
is to recouer to the vſe of an other perſon.14. H. 6. 14. 21. H. 6. 3
and ſo an executour may haue an action of
treſpaſſe in his owne name, without nameing
his companion in the executorſhippe, if
goods be taken out of his poſſeſſion.42. E. 3. Execut̄s 67. For he
is poſſeſſed of them as a priuate man, but he
is poſſeſſed of them to the vſe of an other as
executour.11. H. 6. 35 And he need not in the caſe aforeſaid
name, himſelfe executour.12. R. 2. Executors 75. For if he do,

it may tend to the abatement of the writ according
to M. Kebles opiniō.16. H. 7. 4. ꝑ Keble 19. H. 6. 65. per New
                        •
                     . who ſaith that the
poſſeſſion of one of the executors (his meaning
is as he is executor) is the poſſeſſion of both,
and herewith agreeth the opinion of Newton,
but by their fauors though the propertie of the
executors in the goods of the teſtator be one
and the ſame, yet the poſſeſſion may be ſeueral,
for he that hath the cuſtody of goods may only
be ſaid to be in real and actual poſſeſſion of the
ſame, which kinde of poſſeſſion is onely heare
meant, for which cauſe a writ of Detinue that
concerneth the poſſeſſion of goods, ſhall bee
brought only againſt that executor who is poſſeſt
of the goods.
               721. H. 6. 1. 39 E. 3. 59. H. 5. 14 11. H. 4. 46 The Law may worke ſeueral thinges
in one inſtant as if a diſſeiſor make a leaſe for
yeres, and after he and the diſſeiſee releaſe, by
one deed to the tenant for yeres, the Law adiudgeth
the releaſe of the diſſeiſor firſt to take
effect, and after the releaſe of the diſſeiſee, for
there is no priuity nor eſtate in the leſſee, vpon
which the releaſe of the diſſeiſee may inure, if
the Law doe not make ſuch conſtruction.21. Eli. Com̄ 539. Para. cas.
If the tenant for thirtie yeres make a leaſe
for tenne yeares, and they both ſurrender to
him in the reuerſion, the ſurrender is good
for both eſtates, and yet the leſſee for tenne
yeares, coulde not ſurrender by himſelfe
for defaulte of priuitie, but when the other

ioineth with him, his ſurrender ſhall hee taken
to goe before and the other to followe
it.14. H. 7. 1. &amp; 4. Likewiſe if the tenaunt for terme of
life ſurrender to the grauntee of the reuerſion,
this is both an Attournement and alſo
a Surrender.19. Eliz. 258. Dyer. So if a man haue land by
diſcent by the Mother ſide, and leaſeth it for
yeares, the leſſee couenanteth and graunteth
to pay yerely to the leſſour and his heires
xx. s. the leſſor dyeth, the Law in a moment
will conuey the reuerſion, to the heire of the
part of the Mother, and the twenty ſhillings
to the heire of the Fathers ſide, becauſe it is a
ſūme in groſſe.Plow. Com̄ 132. Brow. cas
               
               8 By intendement and admittance of
Law a thing ſuſpended may bee reuiued, for
if the donour diſſeiſe the donee in taile, and after
maketh a feoffement, and the tenant in
taile reentreth, nowe the feoffee ſhall haue the
reuerſion.9. H. 7. 25. per Fineux So if the heire in taile entreth
vpon the diſcontinuee, and maketh a feoffement
vpon condition, and for the condition
broken reentreth, and after a recouerie is
had by the diſcontinuee, the iſſue in taile is
now reſtored to his firſt action, and the entaile
is reuiued, for by the breach of the condition
the feoffement is diſanulled.23. H. 8 Br. Reſtore al primer acc' 5. Tenant
for life, the remainder in taile, the remainder
in fee to the heires of the tenant for terme of
life, graunteth a rent charge in fee, this ſhall

charge the land during his life, but it ſhall be
ſuſpended during the entaile, and after the entaile
determined it ſhall be reuiued, and ſhall
charge the heire of the tenant for life.5. E. 4. 2.
               
               9 The Law altereth the nature or ſubſtance
of a thing by matter, ex poſt facto, A
man ſeiſed of lande in right of his wife, entreth
into religion, the wife alieneth, the huſbande
is deraigned, the huſband may reenter
into the land.33. E. 3. Ent̄ congeable 52. So if a man bee indebted to
a villaine, who recouereth in an action of
debt, and after the debtour purchaſeth the
mannor to which the villain is regardant, and
after alieneth it, the villaine may nowe haue
execution.12. H. 4. Execuc' 28. If a man make a leaſe for terme
of an other mans life rendring rent, and the arrerages
incurre, the leſſor ſhall not haue an action
of debt, becauſe he hath a franktenement
in the rent, but if Ceſty que vie die, now is the
freehold as to the rent conuerted into a chattell,
and nowe he ſhall haue an action of debt.
39. H. 6. 26. per Paſton Likewiſe a deuorce altereth the eſtate of
frankemariage into a bare freehoold.7. H. 4. 16. If a
man adde a condition to a ſingle Obligation
after the deliuery, this maketh the Obligation
void, for now it is not his deed, and
the ſame Law is of the raſing or enterlining
of a condition after the deliuery of the Obligation.
36. H. 6. 5 per Aſh. Iuſt. If land bee giuen to one in taile,
and the donee giueth the land to the donour,

and to a ſtraunger for terme of their liues,
this is a diſcontinuance conditionall, namely
if the ſtraunger ſuruiue.28. H. 8. 7 Dy. per Fitzh. If the Sheriffe
attache one by force of a Capias that is iuſtiſtable,
but if hee returne a Non eſt inuentus
vpon the writ, he is a treſpaſſour ab initio.
                  3. H. 7. 11
If I. diſſeiſe I. S. and leuie a fine to I. N.
and after I. S. entreth vpon I. N. and enfeoffeth
me, and I. N. entreth vpon me, and
I bring my Aſſiſe, and I. N. pleadeth the
fine in barre, I may auoide the fine by ſhewing
the matter aforeſaid.15. E. 4. 5 per Litt̄. If a fine be leuyed
of land in auncient demeſne, and the Lord
diſanulleth the fine leuied at the Common
Lawe, he hath reſtored the right to him that
leuied the fine.16. E. 2. cont̄ claime 10 If hee which abateth after
the death of the tenant in fee ſimple make a
Feoffement vpon condition to be perfourmed
within nine yeres enſuing, and after the feoffee
leuieth a fine with Proclamations, and
the fiue yeares incurre the condition is broken,
and the abator reentreth, now the heire
of him that dyed ſeyſed may haue an Aſſiſe of
Mordaunceſtor againſt the abator, whereas
before hee was bounde by the fine.Plow. Com̄ 358. b Sto. cas. Tenant
in tayle maketh a Feoffement and taketh
backe an eſtate in fee, and bindeth him
ſelfe in ſtatute Marchant, and then maketh a
Feoffement vpon condition, and after the recogniſance
is put in execution, and the tenant

in taile dyeth, and the heire in taile being within
age entreth for the condition broken, he is
remitted, and the recogniſans auoided, but otherwiſe
it had bin if he had bin of full age:
for then he comming in vnder the Eſtoppell
ſhould not haue auoided the Eſtoppel, nor by
conſequence the recogniſans.8. H. 7. 7. If my very
tenant be ſeiſed of a Manor held of the King
in Capite, and of an other Manor held of me
by knightes ſeruice, and he is diſſeiſed of the
Mannor helde of the King, and afterward
dyeth ſeiſed of the Manor held of mee, wherevpon
I ſeiſe the body of the heire, and after
the heire within age recouereth the Mannor
held of the King, nowe the King may haue
my lande alſo in Warde, becauſe the heire
ſhall nowe be adiudged to bee in by diſcent,
and the King ſhall haue the Wardeſhippe of
the body.15. E. 4. 14 per Littleton Skreenes cas If my Horſe ſtrike one, and after
I ſell the Horſe, and afterwarde the
partye that was ſtroken, dyeth of the ſtroke,
nowe ſhall the Horſe be forfayted as a Deodand.
                  Com̄ 290. ꝑ Car. dame Hales. cas If a villaine inflicte vpon himſelfe
a mortall wounde, and the Lorde ſeyſeth
his goods, and then the Villaine dyeth,
nowe ſhall the Queene haue his goods becauſe
hee is Felo de ſe.
                  Ibid. A man adminiſtreth
of his owne wrong, and after taketh
letters of Adminiſtration of the Ordinarie,
this ſhall relate to the death of the inteſtate.

                  9. E. 4. 33. the heire chargeth land which is after recouered
in a writ of Dower, the woman ſhal
holde it diſcharged.10. H. 7. Charge 3. Thus it is euident
that the vnderſtanding of the Lawe worketh
eſpecially vpon relations on the firſt cauſes
of thinges reducing through many ſtraites
of colourable pretenſes and obiections the
right of a thing to him to whom it appertaineth,
according to the qualitie and exigence
of the ſaid right and title, ſo that the vnderſtanding
of the Student when it entreth into
the ſuruey of theſe intricate and hidden
pointes, muſt bee of this abilitie to compound
thinges, and to reſolue them by imagination,
to builde and deſtroy, and to turne ſayle by
circumſtances and occurrences: for there is
no caſe which accidents may not alter, but
that one thing may counteruaile an other, or
that a defect may be ſupplied by enforcement
of reaſon, or that a wrong may bee purged
and tranſfourmed into right, and blacke as
it were changed into white, contrary to nature
is the worke of intelligence reflecting
vpon it ſelfe, ſome perhaps carry ſuch ſpiced
and ſcrupulus conſciences, that they cannot
abide any fiction or repreſentation of a thing
that is not in facto, but ſurely the ſuppoſall
admittance and intendement of the Law is
neceſſarie, without which neither the ſcience
of the Law, nor any other which conſiſt in

contemplation and abſtraction of the eſſences
of thinges from the confuſion and mixture of
circumſtances can be of any woorth or force.
And though I muſt confeſſe that euery thing,
which is imagined to be done, and is not actually
done is a phantaſie, or an vntruth, yet this
muſt be graunted, that, that which is not really
done, and yet for auoyding inconuenience muſt
be ſuppoſed to be done in facto is not a fault,
though it be falſe. Many things of thys kind
&amp; qualitie haue I before immediatly propoſed
which will be voide of all effect, if you take
imagination from the Law: Let it therefore
be conſidered what this imagination is whereof
we ſpeak, that by the deſcription thereof it
may be better knowen. It may thus appeare
vnto vs, Fictio a ſuppoſall or admittance of a
thing to be is, legis aduerſus veritatem in re
poſſibili ex iusta cauſa dispoſitio, the diſpoſing of
the Law againſt a matter of truth in a thing
that is poſſible, grounded vpon iuſt cauſe: and
there is great difference betwixt imagination
and preſumption, becauſe fictio iuris the imagination
of law tantum operatur quantum veritas
ipſa, in the concluſions and deciſions of
law, and the Law maketh ſometime ens ex
non ente in intelligence, though not in exiſtence:
but praeſumptio ſtat in dubio it is doubted
of, and yet it is accompted veritatis comes,
                  
the companion of trueth, qu
                        •
                     tenus in contrarium
nulla eſt probatio: And the vſe of ſuppoſall
or fiction in the Law is onely to ſupplie
that quod deſideratur in facto, which is wanting
in fact, vt ex ipſa produc
                        •
                     ntur veri i
                        •
                     ris
effectus, that true effectes and concluſions of
law may proceede from it. The Logicians ſay
that the vniuerſals are not in rerum natura,
for if they were they ſhould be monſtra: for an
vniuerſal man, or an vniuerſall tree comprehending
in it all trees, is r
                     ••
                  her by vnderſtanding
to be comprehended then by ſenſe to be
compaſſed, yet I would not haue any imagination
to be vſed: but where Equitie
and the orderly coherence of thinges doth require
it.
            
            
               
               That the Student ought
well to conceiue the reaſon and
Iuſtice of the Law in diſtinguiſhing
and establiſhing the propertie and
communitie of thinges.
               The ſeauenth Chapter.
               
                  THe ende and effect of the Law is
to ſettle the propertie and right
of thinges in them to whom they
belong: And to iudge thoſe things
common which continuance of time and the
entercourſe of parties hath diſtributed &amp; warranted
to many, for if all thinges ſhould be
common, there ſhould be nothing in order, and
if nothing ſhould be common, men would
hardly be kept in duitie, for then ſhould friendſhip,
ſocietie, and conuerſation, the comforts of
mankind faile, which would turne the whole
common weale into a wildernes: therfore the
moſt prudent and politike Law-makers haue
thought it moſt conuenient, that betwixt
theſe two extremities a middle &amp; euen courſe
ſhould be taken, whereby propertie myght
be reteigned, and yet communitie preſerued.

                  Plato, becauſe once he was of opinion that all
thinges ought to be common, hath therefore
many blowes of his ſcholler Aristotle writing
againſt him in hys Politikes, in which
booke he hath a learned difference, that all
that be common 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   in vſe but not 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   in
poſſeſſion and title, which notwithſtanding
is not generally and indefinitely to be admitted,
becauſe then it tendeth to the ouerthrow
and vtter ſubuerſion of all common weales:
But Plato being after better aduiſed did retractate
his former opinion, and laboureth to
confute it: for in his book of Lawes he writeth
in one place, Let euery man haue the free
vſe and poſſeſſion of his goodes by law, whether
he be citizen or ſtranger,
                  Plat. lib. 8. de legib. and in an
other place: The diſtinction of demeanes,
inheritances, and titles, is the foundation of
all priuate contractes, which muſt be ſeuerely
eſtabliſhed by Law: therefore meum and
tuum ought to be in euery common weale.
                  
                  Plat. lib. 11. de legib.
And againe, Let the inheritances and properties
of thinges be definite and certaine in
euery common weale, and let a certaine
manner of purchaſing them be preſcribed
by Law.
                  Plat. lib. 12. de ligib. Thus it is euident that a diſtinct
propertie of thinges is commodious and conuenient
for the good adminiſtration of a common
weale: It is of two ſortes, eyther an
abſolute and indefeaſible propertie, or els a

qualified propertie and ſub modo. An abſolute
propertie is ſuch which is not in any
ſort ſubiect to the claime of any other: but a
qualified propertie is that, which one man
may claime after one ſort, and wyth a certaine
limitation, and an other may claime after
an other maner, and wythout limitation:
As if a man doe hyre beaſtes of an other to
manure his land for a certaine tearme, hee
that hyreth them hath a propertie in the beaſts
pro tempore, and therefore if the beaſtes during
the tearme be taken away, he may haue
a generall Repleuine:
                  42. E. 3. 18. 11. H. 4. 17. 17. E. 4. 2. So he may haue of
beaſtes which bee in his cuſtodie and were
committed to his keeping:47. E. 3. 12. And ſo he may
haue a generall writ of Treſpaſſe for the taking
or dryueing away of beaſtes in his cuſtodie,
though the abſolute propertie bee in
an other man: But if hee whych hath the
verie propertie doth take them, an action of
the caſe will onely lye48. E. 3. 20. 11. H. 4. 23. And the Bailie of
corne or money, being out of ſacke or bagge,
hath ſo farre foorth a propertie in the thinge
deliuered, that if the Bailie be afterward attainted
of felonie, he ſhall forfait the corne
and the money: for it cannot be knowen whether
they be mine or no.3. E. 3. Corone 317. 323. 334. And the Lord may
haue a Repleuine of the beaſtes of hys villaine,
or bondman, if hee haue bin ſeiſed of

his villaine.42. E. 3. 18. Na. br. Fitz. 69. 9. H. 6. 25. per Bab. 19. E. 3. Repleuin 32. 33. E. 3. Rep. 43 And it appeareth by diuerſe
bookes, that in an action of treſpas, it is no
plea to ſay that the propertie, that is the verie
propertie, is in an other.12. H. 6. 19. 27. H. 8. 21. And it is ſayd
lykewiſe, that hee out of whoſe poſſeſſion
goodes are ſtolne, may haue an Appeal: and
he lykewiſe may haue an Appeal who is the
verie proprietarie.19. E. 3. Repleuin 32. And therefore it is a
firme concluſion in law, that if ſheepe be deliuered,
or leaſed to one for a certaine time to
marle his ground, the deliuerie or demiſe is
a good plea in barre of an action of Treſpaſſe,
or Repleuine, becauſe hee hath a propertie
modo et forma againſt the baylor himſelfe,
or leſſour, and may haue an action againſt
him for taking them away wythin the
time.21. H. 7. 14.
               
               2 And as the propertie of thinges may be
particuler or generall, ſo likewiſe it may be
ioint or ſeuerall: A ioint propertie is where
two or more are ioyntly intereſſed in a thing:
A ſeuerall propertie when they haue ſeuerall
intereſtes in ſeuerall thinges: and therefore
where the propertie or right in goodes
and chattels is ioint, there the action which
is brought to trie the propertie muſt not
bee ſeuerall: And therefore in a writte of
Rauiſhment of a warde the defendant ſayd
that the plaintife had nothing in the ſeygniorie

but onely in common wyth ſuch a one,
and this was helde a good plea, wythout
ſaying that hee had nothing in the warde
in ſeueraltie, or wythout ſhewing how hee
helde in common in parcenarie, or by iointenauncie.
6. H. 4. 6. 12. H. 6. 4. 22. H. 6. 14. &amp; 1. E. 4. 7. And ſo if the propertie bee ſeuerall,
the action muſt not be ioint but ſeuerall:
And therefore if in a writte of Repleuine
brought by two for certaine beaſtes,
if the propertie of ſome of the beaſtes belong
to one of them onely, and the propertie
of ſome of the beaſtes to the other, the
writte ſhall abate.28. E. 3. 92. 3. H. 4. 12. 34. H. 6. 37. 2. E. 4. 23. 10. E. 4. 2. 8. E. 3. 15. Thus it is euident that
the Lawe doth maintayne and vpholde the
ioynt and ſeuerall propertie of thinges, without
which the common weale could not conſiſt.
Now let vs conſider how the communitie
of thinges is lykewiſe reſpected by
Law.
               3 A man may obſerue and deduce hys
accompt from former times, that it hath bin
thought very neceſſarie and conuenient that
mutuall commerce and trafique betwixt Nation
and Nation ſhould be entertayned &amp; continued:
Plat. lib. 12. de legib. And therefore Plato wiſely admoniſheth,
peregrinorum commercia reſpub. né auerſetur:
And Amáſis the Egyptian king was ſo

glad of the commerce and reſort of ſtrangers,
that he graunted to the Grecian merchants
beeing meere aliens, the vſe and exerciſe of
their rites and religion in their owne language:
And to the ende that ſtrangers might
more commodiouſly practiſe their negociation
in that Realme, there was a certaine
place appointed in that kingdome, namely
Naucrate for the receit of forraine wares,Herodot. lib. 2.
which courſe is greatly approoued by Ariſtotle,
whoſe opinion is, that a principall Citie
muſt be erected in ſome conuenient place
whereto thinges which be neceſſarie to thys
lyfe may bee abundantly conueyed, and to
which there may bee eaſie paſſing for them
that be in league w
                     •
                  th vs, and hard for others:
Ariſt. 5. polit. cap. 7. 6. polit. ca. 7. et lib. 7. ca. 4. et 5. and therefore ſayth he it ought to be ſcituate
neere to the ſea.7. polit. cap. 5. And doubtles iuſt was
the quarrell and complaint of the people of
Megara againſt the Athenians, who had vtterly
barred and ſecluded them from theyr
hauens, and from all marting wyth them:
Plutarch. in Peric. for he whych breaketh and diſſolueth the
reciprocall entercourſe of nations, is an enimie
to the ſocietie of mankind. And Strabo
in hys laſt booke noteth it as the propertie
of the Barbarians, to repulſe and keepe out
of theyr territories all ſtraungers, which
cuſtome is agaynſt the Lawe of Nations,

what a great point of inhumanitie is it to
deny them the ſea which by nature is open to
all:Vlpian. lib. 8. Digeſtor. tit. 4. c. 14. yea, it ought to be as common as the
vſe of the aire:Celſus li. 43. Digeſtor. tit. 8. c. 3. and all creatures may claime
the free vſe of that, as may appeare by that

                     •
                  aying of Daedalus:
               
               
                  Omnia poſſideat, non poſſidet aera Minos.Ouid. in Metamorph.
                  
               
               
                  Though Minos all things do poſſeſſe,
the aire is not his owne.
               
               And the ſhore of the ſea is by nature common
to all, as Neralius ſayth,c. 14. tit. Digeſtor. de acquirend. rerum domini. and though Empires
and kingdomes be deuided, yet the vſe of
ſuch things remaineth ſtill in common, and
therefore the ſaying of Maro in the perſon of
one of his traueilers was vttered with good
reaſon:
Quod genus hoc hominū, quaeue hunc tam barbara more
                        •
                     
permittit patria? hoſpitio prohibemur arenae.
but yet to enimies, becauſe in them the league
of friendſhip doth faile, the right of fellowſhip
ſhould not be graunted. For groſſely are they
deceiued, who would without reſtraint haue
all things common, of which error the Anabaptiſts
are patrons, and do endeuour to
ground their error vpon ſcripture, but falſely,
for Abraham and the Patriarches were men
of great riches: Ioſua did publikely and priuately
diſtribnte his goodes to the people of

Iſraell. There be in Solomon precepts of the
proprietie of things. And God woulde not
haue ſayd, Thou ſhalt not ſteale, if he would
haue had all things common: for to ſteale, is
to take away goods wherein others haue a
propertie, and therefore theft is ſayd to bee
contrectatio rei alienae animo furandi, inuito illo
cuius illa res eſt.
                  Stamford. fol. 24.
               
               3 But yet the rule of charitie and ſocietie
requireth that ſome things ſhould bee
in regarde of vſe and benefit common to other,
and therefore by cuſtomes of Countryes,
and by lawe, the offſpring of theſe
cuſtomes, the earth is in parte appropriated
vnto ſome, and in parte participated
and made common to others. Therefore
the Common lawe doth well allowe and
mainteine the common vſe of certaine things,
as namely, the vſe of Fiſhing in another
mans Pond,18. H. 6. 29. &amp; 92. 17. E. 4. 7. 7. H. 7. 13. 18. E. 4. 4. of paſture for hys beaſts in
an other mans ſoyle,9. H. 6. 36. 27. H. 6. 10. 15. E. 3. Common. 12. 22. Aſſiſ. pl. 36. 36. Aſſiſ. pl. 3. 4. H. 6. 13. 37. H. 6. 34. 4. E. 4. 29. 10. E. 3. 15. 10. E. 3. 56. 4. E. 3. 4. 15. Aſſiſ. pl. 5. 14. E. 3. Barre. 277. 17. E. 2. Commō. 23. 22. H. 6. 51. of taking of an eſtouer
or maintenance of wood in another mans
groue,N. B. Quod permit. 11. Elizab. 281. Dy. of hauing a franchiſe and libertie in
an other mans Mannor or Seignorie,13. E. 45. 10. H. 7. 13. 7. E. 4. 10. 48. E. 3. 17. 30. E. 3. 20. 3. H. 6. 12. 34. H. 6. 43. and
laſtly, of hauing a way through an other mans
ground.33. H. 6. 26. 8. E. 4. 9. 6. E. 3. 23. 2. E. 4. 9. 20. E. 3. Admeaſ. 8. 21. E. 3. 2. 11. H. 4. 82. 2. H. 4. 11.
               
               4 Some thinges there are, the propertie
whereof the lawe can not veſt in any, and
therefore it leaueth them to the occupant,
that is in playne tearmes to hym that can

ſeiſe them, as things which are by nature
ferae naturae, as beaſts, birds, or fiſhes, being
in theyr owne libertie. And as to the propertie
it is not materiall whether they bee
taken in a mans owne ground, or in an other
mans, and ſuch things be his no longer then
they bee in hys poſſeſſion or cuſtodye: for
when they haue eſcaped and recouered their
naturall and priſtinate libertye, then they
ceaſe to be his, but then the lawe vnderſtandeth
ſuch things to haue recouered their naturall
libertie, when they are eyther paſt the
view, or els being in view they be hard to
be followed, and recouered. The nature of
Bees is wilde, and therefore when a ſwarme
of them lighteth vpō thy tree, they are no more
thine before they be couered with thy hiue,Iuſtinia. lib. Inſtitut. 2.
then hawkes, which haue made their neaſts in
ſome of thy trees, or doues in thy doue-houſe
for though the yong birds be thine, whereof
thou mayeſt bring an action of treſpaſſe, quare
vi &amp; armis pullos eſperueriorum ſuorum in boſco
indificantium, or columbas columbaris ſui caepit,
which writ is not only maintenable, whē the
doue-houſe is broken or the dore open, and the
young doues be taken out of their neaſtes, but
an action of treſpas wil alſo lye for ye troubling
or hurting of the old doues within the doue-houſe,
though they be ferae naturae, as wel as for
chaſing &amp; killing conies in a mans warren,16. E. 4. 7. 22. H. 6. 6. 67. 18. E. 4. 8.
                  
yet he ſhall not vſe this word ſuos,
                  43. E. 3. 24. 12. H. 8. per Newdig. 14. Eliz. 307. Dy. in his
writ, yet becauſe he hath them by reaſon of
his Warren or Doue-houſe wherein he hath
a propertie, he ſhall haue an action for the
chaſing or the taking of them.8. E. 4. 5. 22. H. 6. 55. N. B. Fitzh. en le briefe de treſpaſſe. The nature
of Cranes and Doues is wilde: neyther is it
materiall that by cuſtome they are wont anolare
&amp; reuolare, to flye from home, and returne
home. And in ſuch things which are
came, and by cuſtome are wont to depart and
yet to returne, this rule is allowed, that ſo
long they may be ſayd to be thine, as they
haue animum reuertendi. And felonie cannot
be committed in the taking of beaſts that be
ſauage, if they be ſauage and vntamed at the
time of the taking, nor for taking of Doues
being out of a Douecoate, nor for taking of
Fiſhes being at large in the riuer, for ſuch
taking is not contrectatio rei alienae ſed quae eſt
nullius in bonis.
                  18. H. 8. 2. 22. Aſſiſ. pl. 95. And the ſtealing of a Doe
which is tame and domeſticall is fellonie, but
then ſaith M. Stamford, it ſeemeth that hee
that ſtealeth it ſhould haue certaine knowledge
that it is tameStamf. lib. 1. c. 16. but if the Doe be killed
and then ſtolne, this is felonie.10. E. 4. 15. And
though a man may haue for the taking of his
Ferret an action of treſpaſſe, becauſe hee is
profitable to take Connies for the vſe of his
maiſter. Yet becauſe a Ferret is ferae naturae,
a man cannot haue an appeale of fellonie for

him, no more then he may haue for the ſtealing
of his Hauke and Popiniay, or ſuch like,
for ſuch things are ferae naturae, and a man can
haue no propertie in them, neither can he ſay
in his writ feras ſuas, for that implyeth a
contradiction, and becauſe they are ſauage,
therefore they are not tithable. But when
ſuch things are made came by my labour and
coſt, the propertie of them is changed, and the
nature altered, and then if a man take them
out of my poſſeſſion, I may haue an action.
For a man may haue an action quare moloſſum
ſuum cepit, becauſe he is neceſſarie for the keeping
of his houſe, or the keeping of his folde
or a fiſh pond.12. H. 8. 3. Fillowes C. per Brooke. Pollarde. Brudnell. Newport &amp; Newdigate. But the nature of hennes and
geeſe is not ſauage, and therefore if they ſhall
flye away, though they be paſt thine eye-ſight,
notwithſtanding in what place ſo euer they
be, they ceaſe not to be thine: and who ſo euer
deteyneth them, is puniſhable by way of
action.Iuſtini. lib. Inſtitution. 2.
               
               4 In the Ciuill lawe there is this caſe,
certaine Sheepe were caried away from the
Shepherd of A. by Wolfes, an huſbandman
of the next village hauing purſued them with
great and ſtrong dogs which he kept for the
ſafetie of his beaſts, recouered them from the
Wolfes, for the dogs did enforce the Wolfes
to leaue them, and when A. did demaund the
Sheepe, the queſtion was whether the ſheepe

became his that did ſo recouer them, or remained
ſtill the ſheepe of A, for the dogs did get
them by a kinde of hunting: yet Pomponius
thought in this caſe, that as thoſe things
which are taken either on ſea, or on land, do
ceaſe to be theirs that tooke them, when they
are come to their naturall libertie, ſo by the
ſame reaſon our goods takē away with beaſts
liuing either in the ſea, or on the land, do ceaſe
to be ours whē the beaſts that tooke them haue
eſcaped our purſuit. And who wil affirme that
that continueth to be ours which a bird flying
hither and thether, carieth out of our barne,
or out of our field, or by any meanes carieth it
away from vs, if therefore it ceaſe to be ours
when it commeth to the mouthes of beaſts,
in common apperance, irrecuperably, it muſt
needs become his who firſt recouereth it, and
ſo be made proper to the occupant, euen as a
fiſh, or bird, which hath eſcaped our power,
if it be taken of an other, is ſtreightway his,
but he thinketh it more reaſonable that it
ſhould continue ours, ſo long as it may be recouered.
Vlpianus lib. 19. ad edictum.
               
               5 Likewiſe a thing pro derelicto habita,
waiued &amp; forſaken, is nullius in bonis, as when
a man for feare of a tempeſt caſteth his things
into the ſea, or ſome danger being imminent,
leaueth them vpon the land, or els of his owne
free will leaueth that which is his owne ſine

ſpe rehabendi.
                  29. E. 3. 29. 12. E. 4. 5. If a thing be fallen out of a
chariot or wagon, it may be ſayd to be loſt or
waiued.Vlpia. lib. 56. ad edictum. And if a man haue a libertie to take
wayfes and ſtrayes in his mannor by preſcription,
and certaine beaſts be wayued or do ſtray
within the precincts of his mannor, and a
ſtranger taketh them, he that hath the mannor
ſhall not haue an action of treſpaſſe generall
for the taking of them before he hath ſeiſed
them,16. Elizab. 138. Dy. though the lawe be taken to be otherwiſe
by ſome.ibid. &amp; Fitzh. N. B. 19. But 13. E. 3. a writ was
mainteined by an Abbot by reaſon of his franchiſe
in the like caſe, but that was an action
vpon the caſe, which prooueth that the propertie
was not in him before ſeiſure.13. E. 3. Briefe 678. But
it hath been held for cleare lawe, that felonie
is not committed in the taking of treaſurie
found, wreck of the ſea, wayfe and ſtray, and
ſuch like, vnleſſe they haue been before ſeiſed,
and the reaſon is, quia dominus rerum non
apparet, ideo cuius ſunt incertum eſt, and therefore
the puniſhment in ſuch caſes is by fine,
and not by the taking away of life and member.
22. Aſſiſ. pl. 99. Such landes, the propertie whereof
hath been executed by poſſeſſion, cannot be
wayued but by matter of record.7. E. 4. 7. &amp; 20. And it is
a certaine rule and ſound reaſon, that ſuch
things as cannot paſſe but by matter of record,
cannot be wayued or relinquiſhed, but
by matter of record.8. H. 4. 13.
               
               
                  
6 Such things are ſaid to be nullius in bonis,
which haue not from time out of minde
bin knowne to belong to any man, as treaſures
hid in the earth, as when any money,
gold, ſiluer, plate bullion is founde in any
place, and no man knoweth in whome the
propertie is. The lawe beſtoweth it vpon the
King, and it becommeth res fiſcalis, parcell of
the treaſurie royall, and therefore it is called
in the common lawe treaſure troue, that is to
ſay, treaſure found, whereby it appeareth,
that the King is not proprietarie of it, till it
be founde, but it is before nullius in bonis.
But if any mine of mettall be found in any
ground, that alway pertaineth to the Lord of
the ſoyle, except it be a mine of gold or ſiluer,
or a mine which hath vaines of gold and ſiluer,
which ſhall alway be the Kings in whoſe
ground ſoeuer they be found:Expoſit. des tearmes de ley, Plowd. in le caſe de informat. pur mines. and in auncient
time, as M. Bracton ſayth, it belonged
by the lawe of nature to him that found it:
but now by the lawe of nations it is res fiſci,
and belongeth to the King: but heretofore it
hath bene ruled quod theſaurus non competit
regi, niſi quando nemo ſcit quis abſcondit th
                        •
                     
                     ſaurum:
                  Fitzh. corone 446. for then (as M. Stamford collecteth)
it ſhall belong to him in whom the propertie
was before, and if he dye before ſuch
finding, his executors ſhall haue it.Stamf. lib. 1. cap. 42. And becauſe
there might befall ſome ſquare or variance

betwixt the Lord of the ſoyle, and the
King about the propertie of ſuch treaſure,
it is therefore decided quod theſaurus competit
domino regi &amp; non domino libertatis ſi non
ſit per verba ſpecialia aut per praeſcriptionem.
                  Fitzh. corone. 281. 436.
               
               7 And things are ſayde to bee nullius in
bonis by common conſent, as things conſecrate
and religious: for though the goods
belonging to a Church, as belles, ſeruicebookes,
ſurplices, chalices, and other things,
muſt be ſuppoſed in a writ of treſpaſſe brought
by the Churchwardens to be bona parochianorum
in custodia nostra existentium.
                  8. E. 4. 6. 37. H. 6. 30. 12. H. 7. 27. 8. H. 5. 4. 11. H. 4. 12. 19. H. 6. 66. Yet in
that the lawe giueth the action to the Churchwardens,
and to their ſucceſſors, for the recouerie
of ſuch goods vniuſtly taken, and doth
giue the propertie to the pariſhioners, this
properlie muſt be intended to be to the vſe of
the church, that is, to the vſe of the parochians,
as they are the Church: for though it be
true that Rolfe ſayth, 8. H. 5. that a church parochiall
can not otherwiſe be intended, but
a houſe made of ſtones, and walles, and roofe,
and ſuch materiall things which can not take
by gift or feofment no more then a church
conuentuall which lacketh a ſoueraigne:8. H. 5. 4.
yet it cannot bee denyed that the pariſhioners
are incorporate for the purchaſing of
perſonall thinges, and that in regarde of

ſuch capacitie, they may be ſayde to be the
Church it ſelfe, as well as the Parſon and
his ſucceſſors in auncient time were ſayd to
be the Church in the purchaſe of land and
realties, which may appeare by this caſe:
Land was deuiſed to one for life, the remainder
to an other for tearme of life, the remainder
to the Church of S. Andrew in
Holburne, this is adiudged to be a good deuiſe,
21. R. 2. Deuiſ. 27. and this muſt needes goe to the Parſon
and hys ſucceſſors, becauſe the Churchwardens
and pariſhioners were neuer admitted
by lawe to purchaſe land to the vſe of
the Church. And Belknappe ſayde, that the
cloathes of a dead man being found dead in
the field, did belong to hys executors if hee
had made a will, otherwiſe that they ſhould
be deliuered to the Church for celebration of
diuine ſeruice for the ſoule of the dead: for
his meaning is (as I take it) that the Ordinarie
ſhould intermeddle with them for the
diſpoſing of them.48. E. 3. Enditement. 27. And if a man take a
coate-armor which hangeth ouer a dead mans
tombe in a Church, the enditement muſt be
bona executorum, of the dead man: but if a
graue-ſtone be taken away, the enditement
muſt be bona eccleſiae.
                  Lambard Eirenarc. 494. 495.
               
            
            
               
               That the words or termes
vſed in bookes of lawe ought
to be vnderstoode and applied
as the lawe doth expound
and conceiue them.
               The eight Chapter.
               
                  IT is not poſſible for a man to be
ſkilfull in any Science, vnleſſe he
do perfitly know the words which
do occurre and are often vſed in
that Science. I doe not meane wordes of
Arte onely, which by Lexicons and explanatorie
bookes may eaſily be conceiued, but ſuch
as do import and concerne the obiects of the
ſcience, about which it is principally conuerſant.
To purſue therefore briefely an interpretation
of ſuch words as in the lawe are materiall,
I take it not to be diſſonant from order
to begin with the diuerſitie of lawes, and
to ſhew how theſe words, the lawe of Nature,
the lawe of Nations, the lawe Ciuil, the common
lawe, the ſtatute law, the cuſtomarie law
ius merum, and aequum et bonum, are vſed in the
lawe bookes, and are to be vnderſtood, that ſo
it may be knowne how and in what ſort one
lawe differeth from an other, and of what

qualitie and condition that lawe is to which
the Student is addicted, or vpon which hee
doth grounde his reaſon. The lawe of Nature
therefore is that, which the Nature of
Natures, or the God of Natures of the Philoſophers
called Natura Naturaus, hath
caught all creatures that haue ſenſe by the
mediation of nature created of which they
conſiſt: for this lawe is grounded in the
roote and inwarde partes of Nature, and
therefore one ſayeth well, Habemus non
ſcriptam ſed natam legem, quam non didicimus
ſed hauſimus: This is according to
Iustinian his definition, in hys Inſtitutes,
to whom D. Hotoman may ſeeme at the firſt
to doe iniurie by obiecting that by this definition,
to eate, to ſleepe, to mooue, and to
reſt, are parcell of the lawe of nature: and
though this be aunſwered by ſome,Gou. lib. 1. lect. 
                        •
                     ur. c. 19. that
theſe thinges are excluded from the definition,
by this word ius, yet what abſurditie
woulde followe if ſuch thinges ſhoulde
bee graunted to bee parcell of the lawe of
Nature, why not as well as the repulſing
of force, which apparantly proceedeth from
the lawe of Nature. For in truth there is
no difference in the effect betwixt externall
force, and the force whiche a liuing
creature hauing ſenſe ſhould doe to it ſelfe,

if it ſhoulde not performe theſe aforeſayde
actions of Nature, as to eate, to ſleepe, to
mooue, and to reſt, whereby Nature is preſerued
and kept in time. This is playne
in men, who by the Ciuill lawe are ſayde
to kill, in denying nouriſhment to themſelues,
or others, whereby life and nature
may be mayntayned. And Ioſephus writeth
well, that it is againſt the nature of liuing
creatures for any of them to kill it ſelfe.Ioſeph. de bel. Iud. lib. 3.
But D. Hotom. doth further cauill, following
hys forefather Valla, that lawe cannot
bee applyed to beaſtes, no more then iniurie
may be done vnto them. To this may
be replyed, that iniurie in ſome ſenſe may
be done vnto them, if iniurie be taken for
that quod inre non fit, which is not done according
to that lawe, that is preſcribed vnto
them by nature. But if it bee done according
to the rule of nature, though it differ
from the nature of all other things, yet
it is not iniurious or vnnaturall, for example.
All birds except the Cuckoe, doe foſter
and bring vp theyr young, theſe doe it
by the lawe of Nature, this doth it not by
the lawe of Nature, and yet doth no iniurie
to her young, becauſe ſhee doth it by
the inſtinct and priuiledge of Nature. This
lawe is of all moſt auncient, beeing connaturall

vnto vs, and following immediatly
and indiſſolubly, the very principles of Nature
created, being an euen leuill, and moſt
iuſt lawe in it ſelfe, though wreſted and corrupted
by the corruption of things: but in
what kinde ſo euer it is vniformely executed,
it is without all blemiſh of vniuſtice, as
in mankinde it is vniformely apparant, that
euery man is inclined by nature to prouide
for poſteritie. But when ſome prouide too
much, ſome too little, ſome with pinching
from themſelues, ſome in ſeeking to make
their children farre greater then themſelues,
this is not vniforme, this therefore is vniuſt:
neyther doe I diſſent from the opinion of
them that thinke the lawes of Moſes doe
imitate and reſemble the ſimplicitie, integritie,
and vniformitie of the lawe of Nature.
               The lawe of Nations is that which naturall
reaſon hath propounded and appointed
in common to all men: I doe not ſaye
that nature hath appoynted, but nature with
reaſon, or naturall reaſon. And it is alſo ſeuered
from the lawe of nature, becauſe it
is appropriated onely to men, yet communicated
to all nations, for there is no nation
which vſeth it not. The diſtinguiſhing
of Demeſues, the diuerſitie of Realmes and

Kingdomes is parcell of the lawe of Nations.
Likewiſe warres, contracts, and ſuch
like, are braunches of that lawe, the definition
of it may be ſhortly this, a lawe in
which all Nations doe conſent. But this
pleaſeth not Bodinus, for ſaith he, all nations
haue conſented to Idolatry, yet who will accompt
that a lawe?Bodin. lib. de Repub. But this definition is
meant of humaine things, not of diuine, for
who will ſo vnderſtand it? For all the Nations
of the world may not preſcribe a lawe
to God, nor capitulate any thing touching
theſe thinges that concerne him, hee is a
law-maker for hymſelfe, and therefore hath
ſayde Quod praecipio tibi hoc tantum facito, non
addas, nec minuas.
                  Deuter. 12. v. 32 But in humane things
that whiche all Nations doe allowe for a
lawe that is for gouernment and publique
reſpect (for which intent the worde lawe
is vſed in the definition) that is to be receyued
and acknowledged for the lawe of
Nations.
               The lawe Ciuill I doe not take ſo largely
as ſome doe interpret it, to bee a lawe
which euery citie or people hath appropriated
to it ſelfe: for though the originall denomination
of it came from this word Citie,
yet by that was meant onely one Citie
where that lawe was practiſed and obſerued,

and that was the auncient citie of Rome, for
which cauſe the Ciuil law is at this day called
by ſome ius Romanum.
                  Alber. Gentil. lib. lecti. &amp; epiſtolar. 2. c. 14. And though many
Cities and Commonweales be now gouerned
by that lawe, yet therefore it can not be
ſayde to be ius Ciuile, ſith it had the name
before.
               The Common lawe is that which by
common vſe or common reaſon is made, not
by common aſſemblie, as Statutes or Actes
of Parliament are eſtabliſhed: And it differeth
likewiſe from ſtatute lawes in this, that
in ſuch lawes there are many times prouiſoes
and exceptions of certaine perſons. But the
Common lawe bindeth all alike, and is not
applyed and vſed as a plaiſter to one part,
but as a ſtrong purgation to all the partes
of the bodie politique, and it may challenge
a thirde difference, for that the Common
lawe ariſeth from the people and multitude,
but the Statute originally from the
King, becauſe before euery Parliament, writs
of ſummons iſſue from the King for preparation
to that ſolemne meeting of the States.
Againe, the King may diſpenſe with penall
Statutes,34. H. 8. 52. Dy. by clauſe of non obstante, but hee
may not alter the courſe of the Common
lawe,11. H. 4. 73. though the worde of Common lawe
extende by the generallitie of it, to any

lawe that is commonly vſed in any place,
yet vſe hath reſtreigned it to the Law of this
realme of England, to the dominions of which
it is confined, &amp; beyond this neaſt ſtreatcheth
not her feathers.
               The cuſtomary Law is nothing els but a
cuſtome long time continued, which may bee
thus more fully defined, Cuſtome is a law not
written, by the manners and vſage of a certain
people or the greater part of them vpon good
reaſon and iudgement, begun, and continued,
and hauing the force of a Law. I ſaid (a Law
not written) becauſe the bare memory of man
is the regiſter of cuſtomes. I ſaid by the manners
and vſage &amp;c.) becauſe no cuſtome doth
grow without the conſent of certains people
or the maior part of them▪ I ſaid (begunne vpon
good reaſon and iudgement) becauſe ſuch
things as are introduced by error, are not to
be obſerued. I ſaid (continued) becauſe without
diuturnitie of time, cuſtome can haue no
force or ſtrength. I ſaid (hauing the force of
Law) becauſe it muſt bee of equall power in
the place where it is vſed with the Law. Acuſtome
againſt the Law of nature is of no force,
becauſe naturalia ſunt immutabilia; A cuſtome
againſt the Law of nations is of no validitie,
becauſe that is grounded vpon the Law of
nature. A cuſtome againſt the Law poſitiue
is either againſt publi
                     ••
                   v
                     •
                  ilitie or priuate

profit, if it be derogatorie to publike vtilitie,
it is void: if it be onely againſt priuate profit
it is good and effectual, and a cuſtome once diſallowed
and defeated by Law, cannot be recontinued
or reuiued by any meanes. It hath
bin queſtioned how many Actes or deedes of
men be required to bring in a cuſtome, and the
opinion of the moſt learned hath bin, that ſo
many actes and ſo notorious, that the thing
which is done may be intimated into the notice
of the people, ſo that it may ſeeme to be allowed
by the ſecrete conſent or likeing of the people.
But one notorious act cannot induce a cuſtome,
for that is againſt the name of a cuſtōe:
for conſuetudo is nothing els but communis aſſuetudo.
It hath bin alſo doubted whether an
act contrarie to a cuſtome do interrupt the cuſtome,
to which it may be thus anſwered, either
the cuſtome was not yet perfitte, and
then it doth interrupt the cuſtome, for the
conſent of the people did not yet euidently appeare,
or els it was complete and perfit, and
then it cannot be defeated by one act, but by
ſo much time and in ſuch maner as it was
induced.
               
                  Ius merum is that Law which hath no mixture
nor regarde of circumſtances, but groundeth
a rigorous concluſion vpon thinges done
without further examination how or why they
were done, as if a man ſell a leaſe of lande

for yeres, and certaine cloth for tenne pound,
the contract is entier, and if the title of the
vendor be not good as to the leaſe, yet he ſhall
haue the entire ſumme though the vendee be
diſpoſſeſſed of the leaſe at the time of the action
brought for the money,24. H. 8. Br. Contract 35. 7. H. 7. 4 becauſe in ſtrict
reaſon the contract was entire, ſo if a man
ſel his owne horſe, and the horſe of I. S. to
A. for tenne pound, and I. S. taketh away
his horſe, yet an action of debt will lye for
the whole ſumme, becauſe the contract was
in it ſelfe entire.30. H. 8. Br. Apportion 7 But if a man reteigne
one in ſeruice for a yeare, for tenne pounde
to bee payed at two feaſtes of the yeare, and
the Maſter dyeth after the firſt feaſt, and
before the latter, the Seruaunt ſhall haue
his wages but for the firſt Feaſte, becauſe
the contracte was at the firſt time apportioned.27. E. 3. Br. Apportion 6.
               
               The Law which is termed aequum &amp; bonum,
is that which doth mildely interprete, amend,
and mollifie the hard and rigorus ſpeaches,
and cenſures of the other Lawes: and is
ſometime ſharpe and ſeuere, where the other
Lawes are remiſſe and conniuent: as may appeare
by that ſaying of Saluſt, ſentencing the
proceeding of the Romaines in a matter of
eſtate fit reus magis aequo bono
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      quam iure gentium
Bomilcar comes eius qui Romam 
                        •
                     ide publica
venerat, &amp; this is not ſo much comprehended

in writing, as in the true vnderſtanding of
that which is written. It is neceſſary by the
iudgement of an other Law, which ſaith Etſi
nihil facile mutandum est ex ſolennibus, tamen
vbi aequitas euidens poſcit ſubueniendum eſt.
                  l. 183. de Reg. iur.
and againe iustus iudex aequitatem ſolutius ſequitur.
                  l. 14. de reg. iur. § de relig. This though it haue place ſomtimes
in the precepts, rules, and caſes, of the ciuil and
common Laws: yet it hath more affinity with
the Law of nature, and the Law of nations,
which are ignorant of the knots, and intricate
points of theſe aforeſaid Lawes.
               Now that we haue diſcourſed of theſe ſeueral
Lawes, it remaineth that we ſhould ſhew
what things are the principall obiects of the
Law, which may be reduced to two heads, for
either they are real or perſonall. That which
is reall, is either land, or that which iſſueth
out of land: land is either firme and fixed
earth, or that which is immediatly and coherently
annexed to the earth, as houſes. By the
differences of this diuiſion a piſcharie or fiſhing
is excluded, whether it be libera piſcaria,
that is a libertie of fiſhing in an other mans
pondes, or waters, which he hath in common
with others. For xx. perſons may haue a fiſhing
after that ſort in one riuer, and it is therefore
called libera becauſe none may diſturbe
them to whom the fiſhing belongeth:17. E. 4. 7. Or
ſeperalis piſcaria, which in our bookes hath ſeuerall

ſignifications, for either it may ſignifie
a ſeuerall fiſhing, which one man alone hath in
an other mans ſoile.18. H. 6. 29. Or els where a man
hath a ſeuerall fiſhing to himſelfe in his owne
ground, and ſo it is a thing compounded of
water and of earth, and therefore it is ſaid,
that where a graunt is made of a ſtagne or piſcarie,
the land paſſeth.4. E. 3. 3. Feoffem̄r 79 And in a Formedon
brought of a gorſe, which in Latin is called
gurges, a gulfe or d
                     •
                  epe▪ Yarmouth, wherein
fiſhes are commonly taken, the demaundant
ſhall recouer the land and ſoile it ſelfe.14. E. 3. Formedon 34. And
it hath bin adiudged that a fiſhing ſo taken
lyeth in Tenure.40. E. 3. 44 And a writ of Aiell was
brought of a fiſhing as a thing lying in demeſ
                     •
                  e.
20. E. 3. Bre 685 And alſo of a ſtagne or poole:Temps E. 1. Briefe 861 But
it cannot be termed land, becauſe the water
is not coherently fired to the ſoile, but otherwiſe
it is of an acre of lande which is couered
with water: for though that be ouerflowed
with water, yet it is not naturally ouerflowed,
as a ponde or fiſhe-poole is.18. E. 4. 4 And
therefore it is ſaid 12. H. 7. that a man may
haue a Praecipe de vna acra terrae cum aqua cooperta,
or de vna acraterrae generally at his election.
12. H. 7. 4 But a tenement cannot be ſaid to bee
freehold, except it touche the earth, and therefore
a chamber built vpon a hallor parlor, cannot
be ſaid to bee freehold, becauſe it cannot
be perpetuall, for the foundation may periſhe,

and for that cauſe it cannot be demaunded by
plaint or Writ.3. H. 6. 1. Plaint 1
                        •
                     . Yet 9. E. 4. an exchaunge
was made of lande for a chamber,9. E. 4. 40. but that
prooueth it not to be freehold, for an exchange
may be of things of diuers natures, as of land
for rent.3. E. 4. 10. And ſo of a rent for a common.9. E. 4. 21.
A Caſtell whether it bee a thing either of it
ſelfe, or parcell of a ſeigniory or Mannor may
well be called land or freehold.7. H. 6. 36. For though
land may not be parcell of land no more then
one Leete or Hundred may bee parcell of an
other.3. Mar. 1. Com̄ 168. Hilles cas. 7. E. 6 Com̄ 80. Pa
                        ••
                     idg. cas. 23. H. 8. Br. 
                        〈◊〉
                     . 53. Yet land may be parcell of a Manor.
4. E. 4. 16. 42. E. 3. 22. 44 E. 3. 40. Feoff. 53. lib. 
                        •
                     undā. leg. fo. 70. And a parke may be parcell of a Mannor.3. E. 3. Br. Iuriſd. 39.
And land may be parcel of an Honor.26. Aſſ. pl. 60. And of
a Caſtle.4. E. 4. 17.
               
               It is nowe ſhewed what may properly be
called Land, and it is not impertment to declare
how many ſortes of land, which we haue
before called firme ground, may be demaunded
by Law, of which the Law hath a ſeueral
contemplation. Land therefore as it is ſubiect
to the conſideration of Law is ſixefold, Arua,
Florida, conſita, compaſcua mineralis, in frugifera.
Arua is the arable ground which is tilled
with the Plough. Florida, the garden ground,
which procreateth flowers, Herbes, &amp; all ſuch
thinges as the Bee doth feede vpon. Conſita,
is the wooddie ground which is throughly repleniſhed,
with trees, plants, ſhrubbes, and
ſuch like. Compaſcua is that which bringeth

forth graſſe and fodder. Mineralis is that,
wherein mines are conteigned whether they
be regall mines, as mines of Gold or Siluer,
or baſer mines, as braſſe, leade, copper, tinne,
coales, or the like. Infrugifera is that which is
barren, and cannot be helped by manurance as
the ſoile where ruſhes, weedes, ferne, and ſuch
things doe grow, and it is good to know the
diuerſitie of theſe ſeuerall ſortes of grounde,
that when ſuch thinges are to be demaunded
by writ, they may be demaunded by their proper
names and kinds, and therefore if a feoffement
be made of two roodes of land, and after
a houſe is built there vpon, and part of it is become
medowe, parcel paſture ground, and parcell
wood, the demaund muſt be by the name
of a houſe, medowe, paſture, and wood,3. H. 6. 8. and
there is a writ in the Regiſter, de minera plumbi
&amp; cuiuſcun
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         generis metalli cum pertinentijs.
                  
                  Regiſt. 165 and ruſcaria the ſoile where ruſhes do grow
muſt be demanded by number of acres.16. Aſſ. pl. 9. And
where a ſtagne hath bin, or land couered with
water, if the water be turned out of the courſe
or dried, the land may be demaunded by the
name of medow.33. E. 3. Entre 80.
               
               That which iſſueth out of land, or the profits
of land are of three ſortes, Naturall, Induſtriall,
and Artificial. The Naturall profits
of land are ſuch as doe riſe by the force and
benefit of Nature principally, and not by

the diligence and labour of man, as apples,
hearbes, trees, and ſuch like. Induſtriall profits
are ſuch as doe principally require the diligence
and culture of man, which vnleſſe it
be continually applyed, natura nihil operatur,
as corne, hoppes, woad, ſaffron, and ſuch like.
Artificiall profits are theſe, which are reſerued,
graunted or iſſuing out of land by the
Acte of man, and the approbation of Law, as
a common of paſture, a warren, a rent, and
thinges of like ſort. Common of paſture is
of fower ſortes appendant which is belonging
onely to arable grounde, or to land that
conſiſteth as well of arable ground, as of other
thinges, as a Mannor or meaſuage, but
the appendancy doth principally grow by reaſon
of the arable, and therefore it belongeth to
ſuch beaſtes onely as doe manure or marle the
grounde, as horſes, oxen, kine, and ſheepe.37. H. 6. 34
And if a man haue common to certaine arable
landes in one Village, hee cannot vſe
the Common with beaſtes that manure his
arrable in an other Village.10. E. 3. 56 And this
ought to bee intended of auncyent arrable
ground, not of land newely improued.10. E. 2. Cō
                     mon 22. 5. Aſſ. pl' 2. For
continuance of time immemoriall maketh the
appendancy, wherefore if the arrable land to
which common is appendant, do by purchaſe
come into the poſſeſſion of the owner of the
ſoile, in which the common is to be taken, the

common is extinguiſhed in his perſon: But
if after the tenements be ſeuered by alienation
as they were before, the common is reuiued
by ſome aucthoritie,4. E. 3. 45. 17. E. 2. Common 23. becauſe the ſame auncient
arable land to which before it belonged
ſtill continueth: But by ſome it is otherwiſe,
becauſe being once extinguiſhed it cannot be
de nouo and in an inſtant made appendant.14. H. 4. 2.
               
               
                  Common appurtenant is where a man
preſcribeth to haue common of paſture belonging
to his land with all maner of beaſtes,
it differeth from a common appendant in this,
that a common appendant is onely to be taken
by ſuch beaſts as manure or marle the ground,
and by ſuch number of beaſtes as will ſerue to
manure or marle the ground, to which the
common may be claimed, and belongeth onely
to them as long as they are demurrant vppon
the land: But a common appurtenant may
be taken by all maner of beaſtes.37. H. 6. 34. 9. E. 4. 3. Likewiſe
a common appendant muſt be onely claimed
by reaſon of land which may be marled or manured:
but a common appurtenant may bee
claimed by reaſon of a meſuage or houſe.22. H. 6. 43. 4. E. 4. 29.
Furthermore a common appendant groweth
onely by continuance of tune, and the eſſence
of it is preſcription ioyned wyth appendancie,
26. H. 8. 4. 5. H. 7. 7. 4. H. 6. 13. But a common appurtenant may bee
graunted at this day, and ſpringeth vp in an
inſtant.26. H. 8. 4. 15. Aſſiſ. pl. 5. Common 13. And a common appendant can not

be ſeuered from the land to which it belongeth:
5. H. 7. 7. But a common appurtenant may be
ſeuered:26. H. 8. 4. And they differ in this, that a common
appendant muſt be vſed and taken, according
to the rate and quantitie of ground, in regarde
of which it is granted or claimed.15. Aſſiſ. pl. 5.
But a common appurtenant may be claimed
for beaſtes ſans number: for by the opinion of
Monbray none ſhall haue a writ of Admeaſuremēt
of paſture, but he that hath a common
appendant:18. E. 3. 30. So that it may be probably collected,
that a common appurtenant becauſe it
cannot be admeaſured, may be wel enough ſans
number: And it may be likewiſe to a certaine
number of beaſtes, for if a man at this day will
grant one a meſuage with a common appurtenant
for tenne beaſts, I doubt not, but this is a
good common appurtenant to the meſuage.
               
                  Common by vicinage is where two townſhips
or moe do entercommon, and haue entercommoned
from time out of mind, which is
not to be vſed, by putting the beaſtes of the
inhabitants of one towne, into the landes of
the inhabitants of an other towne, for ſo they
may be diſtrayned damage feaſant: But they
muſt put them in their owne fieldes, &amp; if they
ſtray into the fieldes of the other village, they
muſt ſuffer them to be there, and they muſt
put in their beaſtes, hauing regarde to the
freehold of the inhabitants of that village

where the common is to be vſed.13. H. 7. 13. 15. Elizab. 316. Dyer. 16. E. 3. Common 9. 22. H 6. 51. 6. E. 6. 70. Dier. This kind
of common Maſt. Littleton maketh appendant,
7. E. 4. 26. but by other aucthoritie it is a feueral
and diſtince kind of common.
               
                  Common in groſſe is where a man claymeth
to haue common for all maner of beaſtes,
whether the number be certaine or vncertaine
by ſpeciall graunt in writing, or by preſcription
in him that claymeth or his aunceſtors, or
they whoſe eſtate he hath not by reaſon of any
particuler land: &amp; this common may be vſed by
the beaſts of a ſtranger, which the proprietarie
of the common may gieſt, as we tearme it.11. H. 6. per Babing. Mart. &amp; Paſton. 45. E. 3. 25. Aſſiſe 61. 36. Aſſ. pl. 3. 15. Aſſ. pl. 5. Perkins tit. Graunts.
               
               
                  A Warren is a profite likewiſe which may
be taken out of other mens ground by preſcription,
30. H. 6. 28. Dyer. and if the owner of the ſoile 
                     〈◊〉
                   any
one by his commaundement; or as his ſeruant
doe come vpon the ſoyle, and do 
                     •
                  haſe the Conies,
he cannot iuſtifie the chaſing,34. H. 6. 43. though he
may iuſtifie his entrie into the ground.3. H. 6. 12. And
a rent is alſo a profit iſſuing out of the ſoyle of
a ſtranger, and ſauoureth of the nature of the
land; out of which it iſſueth &amp; therfore if rent
iſſue out of land in auncient demeſne, it is auncient
demeſhe, &amp; ſo it is of rent granted out of
land in Gauelkind, it ſhalbe deuided as the lād
it ſelfe:4. E. 3. 53. 14. H. 8. 5. And ſo it is of rent graunted out of
land deuiſable by cuſtome, though the rent
bee graunted but of late time.22. Aſſ. pl. 78. And ſo if
rent be receiueable out of cuſtomarie land,

as borough Engliſh, or where dower is to be
had of the halfe part, and ſuch like, the rent
ſhall be of the cuſtome and nature of the land,
and therfore in the demaunde of ſuch rent by
Praecipe, or in a Repl
                        ••
                     in, the tenure by auncient
demeſne of the land is a good plea.14. H. 8. 5.
And ſo if land in taile be deuided amongeſt
parceners, the 
                     〈◊〉
                   reſerued to one of the 
                     〈◊〉
                  
parceners ſhall be in 
                     〈◊〉
                  , and of the ſame
condition as the land was.2. H. 7. 5. 15. H. 7. 14.
               
               
                  Parſonall thinges 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   thinges either in poſſeſſion,
or in action: Thinges in poſſeſſion are
either goodes or chattels: the name of goodes
is naturall and ciuill, by the naturall ſignification
all ſuch thinges are comprehended vnder
the name of goodes, which may profite.1. 49. de verb. ſignific.
But as the name of goodes is taken ciuilly,
it ſtretcheth to the whole he ape and bodie of a
mans wealth, together with the charge and
deductions: the reaſon of this differenceis becauſe
nature conſide
                     •••
                   thinges as 
                     〈◊〉
                   they are:
but a common weale or citie after ſuch ſort as
is moſt expedientAlber. Gentil. lib. 4. Epiſt. c. 7. And though the charge
which followeth goodes do de
                     •
                  race ſomewhat
from the value and eſtimation of the ſame, yet
becauſe it is to be diſcharged and ſatiſfied out
of the goodes, it is therefore ioyntly reckoned
and conſidered with the goodes themſelues.
               
                  Chattels which in the common Law are
tearmed Catalla, are diuerſly taken, for the

profits of land if they be gyuen generally vnto
the King by acte of law, they may be called
Chattels, and therefore the profits and iſſues
of the landes and 
                     〈◊〉
                   of them which
flie for felony are forfaited vnto the King, vntill
ſuch time as they be acquited, and that by
the Statute of Praetog. cap. 10. which ſayth
that the King ſhall haue omnia Catalla talium
fugitiuorum, and vnder the word Catalla is
comprehended the corne which was growing
vpon the land, at the time when the forfeyture
of the goodes did begin to take place,3. E. 3. Corone 3. 4.
And if a man be outlawed in an action of debt,
and the outlawrie be retourned, ſo that the
writte iſſueth to the Eſcheator to ſeiſe the
goodes, chattels, and land of the partie outlawed,
the iſſues of the land ſhall be taken to
the kinges vſe vntill he haue ſued his Charter
of pardon:8. R. 2. Superſedeas 19. for an outlawed perſon ſhal not
forfait any land, but the profites onely, as
rent and corne, if he be outlawed in a perſonall
action: Otherwiſe it is if he be outlawed
of felonie, for then the King ſhall haue the eſcheat
of the land, or the Annum, diem, &amp; vaſtum.
                  9. H. 6. 20. But if the profites of land be generally
graunted by the act of the partie, then
they are the ſubſtance of the land and doe not
paſſe without liuerie: And if a man graunt the
profites of land, the land it ſelfe paſſeth.14. H. 8. 5. 45. E. 3. 90. 4. Elizab. 210. Dyer.
And therefore it hath bin held by Forteſcue
                  
and Danby Iuſtices, that tenant in fee ſimple
may graunt veſturam terrae, and the grauntee
ſhall haue it after his death: But the tenant
in taile, for life, tenant in dower, and
tenant by the curteſie cannot make any ſuch
graunt, but if they dye the graunt is determined.
37. H. 6. 30. And if a feoffement be made of land
vpon condition that neither the feoffee nor his
heires ſhall take the profites, the condition is
voide, and the feoffement ſimple and abſolute,
21. H. 7. 24. and in ſuch caſes the profites of land
may not be tearmed Catalla, no more then the
landes themſelues: But vnder the word Chattels,
a leaſe for terme of yeares is compriſed.39. H. 6. 35.
And likewiſe a right of action for goodes: as
if goods be taken wrongfully from a felon:6. H. 7. 9.
Or when one is indebted to a felon by bond:19. H. 6. 47.
Or when he is accomptable to a felon by reaſon
of any receipt, or otherwiſe.28. E. 3. 92. et 50.
               
               
                  Thinges in action are ſuch in which a man
hath neither propertie nor poſſeſſion: as if a
man doe owe to an other xx. pound vpon a writing
obligatorie, though he haue a propertie
and poſſeſſion in the1. H. 7. 15. writing or charter, yet
the ſumme contained is a thing in action, in
which he hath neither propertie nor poſſeſſion:
and ſo it is of an Aduowſon when the church
is voide of an incumbent: for the patron can
not graunt it to any other, becauſe then he
ſhould graunt but fructum aduocationis, which

is a thing rather imagined by law, then ſubſiſtent
by nature: and therfore the patron can
not truely be ſaid to haue propertie or poſſeſſion
in it. But though ſuch thinges be to ſome
intent merely in action, yet in ſome caſes they
are taken as thinges veſted: and therefore if a
man be ſeiſed of an Aduowſon, and the church
become void and he dieth, his executors ſhall
preſent, and not the heire,Fitz. Na. br. 34. for the aduowſon
in regard of the executors was a chattel veſted
in the teſtator. The King may graunt things
in action,2. H. 7. 8. and ſo may a common perſon in
ſome caſes: As if a man bring an action of
debt againſt I. N. and the plaintife is indebted
to me, and promiſeth me that if I will
ayde him againſt I. N. that I ſhall be paied
out of the ſumme in demaunde: there it is lawfull
for me to ayde and maintaine the plaintifie
againſt I. N, becauſe by the promiſe I haue
intereſt in the ſumme demaunded.15. H. 7. 2. And
where a man is indebted to me in xx. pound,
and an other oweth him xx. pound by obligation,
he may aſſigne this obligation and debt
to me in ſatiſfaction: And I may maintaine
ſuit for it in the name of the other.
               
                  
                  A Table of certain words
in the Interpretation whereof
the Common Law of this Realme
and the Ciuill Law doe ſeeme
to agree.
                  
                     A.
                     
                        
                           ACcuſatio A bill of preſentment,
is a regular fourme of complaint,
whereby offences, are opened and
puniſhed.
                     
                        Acquiſitum purchaſed, that is ſaid to be
whereof the propertie is tranſlated from one
to an other.
                     
                        Affines are the kinſmen of the huſband and
the wife by mariage, ſo called, becauſe two
Kindreds which are diuerſe one from the other,
are coupled by marryage, and one of them
commeth to the borders or marches of the
other kindred.
                     
                        Ad nos pertinere is ſaid that which doth
belong vnto vs, eyther by way of propertie, or
by way of poſſeſſion, or by charge, or by adminiſtration.
                     
                        Aedes, plural: a houſe conſiſting of diuerſe
rowmes, (for domus may conſiſt onely of foundation,
wall, couer) as the integrall partes, or
as ſome briefly ſay, which conſiſteth of ſoyle
and ſuperficies,
                     
                        
                        Aeſtas ſommer, a part of the yeare, which beginneth
at the equinoctial of the ſpring, and
endeth at the equinoctiall of Autum, and ſo
ſommer &amp; winter are deuided by vi. moneths.
                     
                        Annona vittaile, is not referred onely to
corne, but to the meate of the ſhambles, aſ well
to fiſh as fleſh.
                     
                        Aperta vis, open force, which is manifeſt and
euident, and doth not receiue any excuſe of
ſimplicitie.
                     
                        Arborvento deiecta, hath not now the name
of a tree, but the name of wood. Arbor dum
creſcit, lignum cum creſcere neſcit.
                     
                     
                        Area, a floare is a vacant place, therefore called
Area quaſi exaruerit, and were not able to
bring forth any thing, it hath bin taken to be
ſuch an emptie place as doth lye diſcouered,
locus ab aedificio purus, and hath no ſuperficies:
it is called a plot of groūd, court or yard.
                     
                        Argen
                              •
                           um ſiluer, it is of three ſorts, infectū,
factum, ſignatum. Infectum is that which is
vnpolliſhed and not adorned with any particular
forme being in the ore, or bullion, newly
ſeuered and ſingled from the ore. Factum, is
that which is beutified with ſome particuler
forme, of which kind is a ſiluer cuppe, a ſiluer
goblet, a ſiluer bowle, or a ſiluer mazard. Signatum
is that which beareth ſome ſpeciall Image
or impreſſion, &amp; ſuch is the ſiluer that is
coined &amp; accompted currant, Argentum factū
                        
                        
muſt be deſcribed by the kinde or ſhape, Infectum
by the weight, Signatū
                         by ye number.
                     
                        Arreſtare, is by the authoritie or warrant
of the lawe, to hinder that either a man or his
goodes bee at his owne libertie, vntill the
lawe be ſatiſfied.
                     
                        Artifices, artificers, are they which ſell
things laboured by them, and by their labour
reduced into a particular forme, as Shomakers,
Smithes, Glouers, Taylors and Weauers,
but artificium if it be largely taken, extendeth
to ye knowledge of euery arte: artifex
and opifex differ, for in the one there is labour
and iudgement, in the other labour only.
                     
                        Aſſultus, an aſſault is a violence done to a
mans perſon, by the perſon of an other man.
                  
                  
                     B.
                     
                        Bona fides a ſincere conſcience, excuſing one
of ill meaning.
                  
                  
                     C.
                     
                        Carcer is taken two wayes, for it is eyther
locus cuſtodiae, or locus paenae.
                     
                     Cauillatio when a man turneth his ſpeach
ab euidenter veris, ad euidenter falſa.
                     
                        Cella becauſe there we do celare, we do hide
that which we would keepe ſecret or cloſe.
                     
                        Ciuitas, a citie: it is taken materially, and
formally: being vnderſtoode materially, it
doth ſignifie a multitude of houſes made of
ſtone and timber, being formally taken it is
ciuilis ſocietas quaſi ſocietas ſimul viuens, and

not viuens ſimplie, but viuens bene, for as
Cicero ſaith, ciuitas ſine legibus is corpus ſine
anima, and therefore Ariſtotle ſayth, non concedimus
vt homo imperet ſed ratio.
                     
                     
                        Cliens, is he that is in ſuite, ſo called quaſi
colens, and hee who dealeth for him in the
cauſe is called patronus, quaſi pater.
                     
                     
                        Codicillus, the declaratiō of a mās laſt wil,
which without the iuſt ſolemnitie of a teſtament
a man ob impedimenti neceſſitatem is
inforced to write, but now the vſe of codicills
or teſtaments are without any neceſſitie confounded,
which is contrary to lawe, for a 
                           •
                        odicill
ought to ſerue neceſſitie, &amp; not a raſh onſet.
                     
                        Cognatio kindred, it is deuided into three
parts; 1. into parents, 2. into childrē, 3. into
coſins. Parents are they of whom we are begotten,
as father, mother, grandfather, grandmother,
and theſe which are in degree aboue
them. Children are they which are begotten
of our bodies, as ſonne, daughter, grandchild,
and ſuch as he vnderneath them, Et nati natorum
et qui naſcentur ab illis. Coſins are they
which haue neither begotten vs, nor bin begotten
of vs, but haue a common roote and originall
with vs, as brother, ſiſter, vncle, aunt, and
ſuch as do diſcend from them.
                     Colludere, is in fraudem tertij conuenire.
                     
                        Commenda, the cuſtodie of a Church committed
and commended to ſome.
                     
                        
                        Commodare is to graunt the vſe of ſome
thing for a certain time, there is difference betwixt
commodare &amp; mutuo dare, becauſe cō
                           modare
is to lend, to haue the ſame againe, as
bookes, apparel, and ſuch like, but mutuo dare
is to truſt, hoping to haue the like againe, as
money, corne, ſalt, ſpices, and ſuch like.
                     
                        Compromiſſum, is the power that is giuen
to the arbitrator, ſo called becauſe both the
parties doe promiſe to obey the opinion of the
Iudge, &amp; therfore he is called compromiſſarius
index to whom the matter is referred.
                     Communitas, a comminalty, is ſocietas hominum
communi lege viuentium.
                     
                        Conditio, when a thing dependeth ſuper caſum
incertum which may tende eyther ad eſſe
or ad non eſſe.
                     
                     
                        Confeſſio, is double: either iudicial, or extraiudicial,
iudiciall is that which is done before
the Iudge, extraiudicial which is done in preſence
of good and honeſt men.
                     
                        Conſentire, is to meete in one opinion.
                     
                        Conſtitutiones, Iudgements, rules and awardes
concerning ſeueral matters whereupon
this verſe hath bin made.
                     
                        Quatuor ex verbis virtutem collige legis,
                        Permittit, punit, imperat, at
                              
                                 
                              
                              que
                            vetat.
                     
                     
                        Controuerſum ius, is that which is on both
ſides doubtful: certum ius is that which is certainly
determined &amp; is called poſitiue Law.
                     
                        
                        Copulatiua the coniunction copulatiue is
taken after two ſorts, either in a deuided ſenſe,
or in a compounded ſenſe, in a deuided ſenſe as
when I ſay, Sir Robert Booke, and Sir Iames
Dyer were Lord chiefe, Iuſtices of the Cōmon
pleas, for they were not chiefe Iuſtices together,
but at diuerſe times: in a compounded
ſenſe, as when I ſay two &amp; three do make fiue.
                  
                  
                     D.
                     
                        Debito is he of whom we may againſt his wil
exact money.
                     
                        Decimae are of three ſorts praediales, perſonales,
and mixt praediales are they which ariſe
of farmes or lands, as corne, hay, and the fruits
of trees: perſonal which are due by perſonall
labor, as by ſome trade, trafick, or miſtery, mixt
of which it may be doubted whether they be
predial or perſonal as wool, lambe, milke &amp;c.
                     
                        Defenſio, is the auoiding of a ſurmiſed &amp; pretended
offence.
                     
                        Delegatus a delegate, to whom a cauſe is cō
                        mitted
to be determined and ordered.
                     De plano, vel ſine figura iudicij, vel ſummarie.
                     
                        Deprehendere, is to take a man in ipſo
facto, ſo that he can neuer flye, nor denye the
facte.
                     
                        Diſcendere to diſcende or to ſpring of ones
body, hereupon they which are borne of vs are

called by the name of diſcendents, which with
them that aſcend make the right line, and the
aſcendents and diſcendents cannot marry together,
wherefore if Adam were now liuing
he could not marrie a wife.
                     
                        Diceceſis, the gouernment of a certaine
prouince by the Biſhop, for as a territorie is
ſo called, quatenus iudex ius terrendi habet,
ſo a dioceſe as farre as a Biſhop hath ius adminiſtrandi
ſacra.
                     
                     Diſpenſatio, a releaſe of common right, either
ex cauſa vtilitatis, neceſſitatis, or ingentis
praerogatiuae meritorum.
                     
                        Diuerſa, ſuch things whoſe ſubiect is not
alike, or whoſe definition is not alike.
                     
                        Dominium is a right to diſpoſe perfitly de
re corporali.
                     
                     
                        Domus inſtructa, a houſe furniſhed, if a
man deuiſe ſuch a houſe the houſehold ſtuffe
paſſeth, but not the wine that is within the
houſe, becauſe by common intendement a
houſe is not furniſhed by wine.
                     
                        Dubia cauſa, is that which is but ſemiplene
probata.
                     
                  
                  
                     E.
                     
                        Error, an opinion, whereby that is approoued
and allowed to be true which is falſe, and
that to be falſe which is true, and error may be
two wayes, eyther in iure conſtituto, or els

                        in iure quod quis in ſuo habet negotio, the
one is an error in lawe, the other in facto.
                     
                     
                        Euaneſcit actio, the action doth faile, or
abate, euaneſcit actio, by the power of the
lawe, or of the Iudges, remittitur actio, by the
will of the plaintife.
                     
                        Executor, an executor, which is after three
ſorts, executor teſtamentarius, executor legalis,
that is to ſay the ordinarie, executor datiuus,
the adminiſtrator.
                     
                        Election, is the certainetie of our will, it
may be of perſons, or of thinges, places, or
times: Of things, as if a man ſhould pay a
ſumme of money, or els a horſe or a hawke:
Or of perſons, as if he ſhould pay it to I. S.
or to I. N. Or of places, as if he ſhould pay it
at London, or at Lincolne. Or of the time, as
the firſt day of April, or the ſecond day of May.
                  
                  
                     F.
                     
                        Falſitas, falſhood is immutatio veritatis cum
doto &amp; damno alterius, the chaunge of truth
with falſehoode to the deceiuing and endamaging
of an other man.
                     
                        Fama, is a common report proceeding from
ſuſpition, and publiſhed by the voices of men,
and it differeth from rumor, becauſe that is a
diuerſe whiſpering of men, which is not ſo
effectuall as Fame. Fama conſtans is that
which is diſperſed abroade neither by men

vnknowen, nor of light credit, nec ignotis nec
improbis.
                     
                     
                        Fide
                              •••••
                           
                         is he which bindeth himſelfe for
another, quaſi inſſu alterius ponens fidem
ſuam.
                     
                     
                        Fortuitus caſus, a meare chaunce which by
mans counſaile, care, and diligence can neyther
praeuideri or praecaueri, be fore-ſeene or
forecloſed.
                  
                  
                     G.
                     
                        Generalis lex, a general law which comprehendeth
all caſes, except ſuch as be vnlawfull,
and vniuſt. For there is nothing more abſurde
then to draw a iuſt Lawe to an vniuſt interpretation.
                     
                        Germani fratres are they which are of the
ſame Father &amp; Mother, Conſanguinei which
haue the ſame Father, but not the ſame Mother,
Vterini which haue the ſame Mother, but
not the ſame Father.
                     
                        Geſtores negotionū, factors or procurators
be of three ſorts, voluntarij which gratis and
of their owne accord do regard the buſines of
their friend: Neceſſarij which by obligation
of their office doe follow matters: Quaſi neceſſarij,
which haue ſome colour to deale in
matters.
                     Graeca mercari fide. i. pecunia numerata
with money paied in hand.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     I.
                     
                        Illegitimi baſtardes, whereof there be three
ſortes, Inceſtuoſi which be begotten of kinſmen
and kinſwomen within the degrees prohibited:
Nefarij, which are begotten of deſcendents,
the chyldren of the ſame parent:
Spurij, or Adulterini, which are borne in adulterie.
                     
                        Iniuria whatſoeuer is done againſt law and
right, whether by wordes, as by ſlander: or by
deede, as by violence of hand.
                     
                        Inops ſine ope without helpe, which hath
no wealth nor maintenance, whereby he may
helpe himſelfe.
                     
                        Inſtaurare, is to bring a thing into his fourmer
eſtate.
                     
                        Inſula, a plot of ground compaſſed on all
ſides with the ſea, quaſi in fato poſita, it is of
two ſortes: Perpetua, and Natiua. Perpetua,
which hath bin from time out of minde part of
a Prouince: Natiua, which hath bin lately diſcouered
by the ebbe and drought of waters.
                     
                        Interlocutoria ſententia, which doth not define
or determine the controuerſie, for that is
called ſententia definitiua: an Awarde.
                     
                        Iudex limitaneus, which hath a limitted inriſdiction,
as the Lord in Court Baron who
onely holdeth plea of a ſumme vnder xl. ſhillinges,
and within the precinct of his Mannour.
                     
                        
                        Iuramentum an oath, it is the affirming or
denying of a thing with religious aſſertion, or
atteſtation, and it is double: Extraiudicial or
Iudicial. Extraiudicial, as Iuramentum conuentionale,
when vppon a bargaine one doth
ſweare to an other. Iudicial is of two ſorts,
Neceſſarium, &amp; Suppletiu
                              •
                           m: Neceſſarium,
which is ad litem aeſtimandam, when witneſſes
are produced by the parties. Suppletiuum,
when the Iudge doth enforce the partie himſelfe
to ſweare for want of other proofes.
                     
                        Inſeperabile, that is ſaid to be which is ſo
inherent in the ſubiect, that it cannot be remoued,
but they do either ſtand together or fall
together. A thing may be ſaid to be indiuidual
or inſeperable in many reſpects, 1. according
to the fourme required in the act: And therefore
if three be bound iointly, they muſt be ſued
iointly, 2. by reaſon of neceſſarie depending,
and therefore the principal being defeated, the
acceſſorie is alſo deſtroyed, becauſe it cleaueth
inſeperably vnto the principal: and therfore if
the marriage be not lawfull, the endowment
cannot be lawfull, 3. by the meaning of the
parties: as when a ſubmiſſion is made to two
arbitrators, it is not to be imagined that the
parties had an intent of ſeuerance, 4. by the
nature of the thing: as when a thing will not
ſuffer a particion: as a ſeignorie in groſſe, a
common, a condition, and ſo a iuriſdiction is an

entier thing: and therfore if a man will bring
an action in a baſe Court of a debt of 4. li. it
is not good for thirtie ſhillinges, or a leſſe
ſumme: for a Iudge or officer hath a preciſe
power of the Law, and if he paſſe his iuriſdiction,
his ſentence or act is voide.
                     
                        Integrum is that which is compounded of
diuerſe partes, for partes compacted &amp; ioyned
together doe make the whole, but an entier
thing may be diuerſly: for it may be eyther
totum numerale conſiſting of many numbers
lincked together, 2. totum vniuerſale, as the
general nature wherof the particulers ar comprehended:
as homo of animal, auis of brutum,
3. totum integrale which is made whole
and entier by many partes, and it is of two
ſorts, Heterogeneū, and Homogeneum: Heterogeneum
the partes whereof are not of the
nature of the whole thing, as a houſe which
doth conſiſt of ſoyle, ſtone, woode, morter, &amp; couer.
Homogeneum which is of the ſame nature
with ye whole, as water, fier, earth, wherof
euery part hath the name of the whole.
                  
                  
                     L.
                     
                        Lacus is that which hath perpetuā aquam.
Stagnum that which hath water at ſometime,
and is ſometime drie. Foſſa a receptacle for
water made by mans hand.
                     
                        Lana, wolle, which may be cloath, but
yet is not wrought in cloath. And if a man

by his will do deuiſe his wolle to any, be it
wrought or not wrought, dyed or not dyed▪ or
be it ſpunne, it is compriſed vnder the name of
wolle, and it is called by the name of Volle
vntill it be made cloth.
                     
                        Littus, that place to which the greateſt
floude of the ſea do
                           •
                        h come.
                  
                  
                     M.
                     
                        Maieſtas, a ſoueraigne honour: Maieſtie is
ſaid to be the daughter of honor &amp; reuerence.
                     
                        Marinum et Maritinum do thus differ, Marinum
is that quod Mare incolit, which lyueth
in the Sea, or which is bredde in the ſea, Maritinum
quod Mare accolit, which is adioyning,
or adiacent vnto the ſea.
                     
                        Mercator, a Merchant, is not as ſome think
tearmed a Merce, but of the word Mercor,
which ſignifieth to buy, and they are properly
tearmed Mercatores, qui res emunt quas in
eadem ſpecie cariús vendant.
                     
                     
                        Moneta, à monendo, Money, ſo tearmed,
becauſe by the impreſſion of the ſtampe it doth
giue vs notice, either of the prince whoſe it is,
or the price which it beareth: It taketh Legem
valoris, the rule of the value of the ſuperiour,
&amp; therefore it cannot be abaſed or refuſed,
but by the commaundement of the ſuperiour.
                     
                        Mortua res, that is ſaid to be by which a
man is not richer.
                     
                        
                        Motu proprio, ex certa
                              •
                           ſcientia, de plenitudine
poteſtatis, are praegnantes clauſulae,
clauſes of importance, againſt which none
may be heard.
                     Mutuum, quaſi ex meo 
                           ••
                        uum.
                  
                  
                     N.
                     
                        Narratio, a declaration of a matter eyther
ore tenus▪
                         or in forme of law: If it be ore tenus,
it is called a motion, &amp; thereof it is ſaid,
qui bene narrat, bene impetrat: If it be in
forme of law, it is a declaration grounded vpon
a writ, contayning the whole ſtate of the
matter, as the plaintife ſuppoſeth it.
                     
                        Naturaliter poſſidere he is ſaid, which poſſeſſeth
a thing corporally, &amp; taketh the profits
of the thing poſſeſſed, and this of the common
Lawyers is called poſſeſſio in facto: But if a
mans father die ſeiſed, &amp; the ſonne doth not enter,
nor actually take the profites, neither doth
any other diſturbe him to take poſſeſſion, this
is called a poſſeſſion in law, or eiuilis poſſeſſio.
                     
                     Negotium meum, that is ſaid to be, cuius

                           ••
                        erum &amp; damnum ad me pertinet.
                  
                  
                     O.
                     
                        Obuentio is a kind of re
                           •
                        enew: it differeth
from Reditus, being ſtrictly taken, in this, that
obuētiones are conting entiū
                           ▪ reditus certorū.
                     
                     Oculis res ſubijci dicitur when it is plaine &amp;
manifeſt, it is well ſaid of Eraſmus,
                         ad cognitionem
magis faciuntaures, ad fidem faciendam

certiores ſunt oculi.
                     
                        Officialis, an Officiall, who in a certaine
part of the dioceſſe is the Biſhops deputie.
                     
                        Opera labour, it is double, Officialis, and
Artificialis: Officialis, is that which is ſpent &amp;
beſtowed vpon the diligent attendance done
by the ſeruant to the Maſter. Artificialis, is the
labour of the trade, as Printing, paueing,
feeling, graueing, embrodering, &amp; ſuch like.
                  
                  
                     P.
                     
                        Pactum is the conſent of two or more in a
matter which pleaſeth both parties, Pollicitatio
is when there is not the conſent of two,
but onely one agreeth. Pactio nuptialis is a
Matrimonial contract. Pactum retrouendēdi
is when the vendee couenanteth, that if the
vendor or his heires or executors will within a
certain time pay ſo much money, as the vendee
doth pay, that then he ſhall haue the land again,
and be in his former eſtate.
                     
                        Palam fa
                              •
                           tū
                         is that which is done opēly. Publice
factū
                         is that which is done corā populo.
                     
                     
                        Paries, a wall▪ thereof there be diuerſe
kindes: Lateritius which is made of clay, Teſtaceus
which is made of bricke, Coementar
                              •
                           us
which is made of lime, ſtone, and water mingled
together, Cratitius which is made of wood,
boardes, or boughes, platted together.
                     
                        Paraecos, a pariſhioner, an inhabitant in a
certaine place, who hath brought his houſhold

to a certaine place, to reſide there.
                     
                        Praetor maior, he Maior of a city, as Rhodiginus
ſaith: for others ar called Praetores minores.
                     
                     
                        Priuilegium is ins 
                           •
                        ſingulare, whereby a
priuate man, or a particuler Corporation is
exempted from the rigor of common Law, for
that which is now called proprium, hath bin
called of olde writers priuum.
                     
                     
                        Proprium that which doth ſo belong to one
that it is not cōmon to an other, &amp; though that
wherein we haue a ioint propertie with others
may be called noſtrum: yet it cannot be called
propriū, for propriū
                         doth not admit any communion,
but proprium &amp; ſuum be equipollent,
and of the ſame ſenſe.
                     
                        Puer hath three ſignifications, either it ſignifieth
the eſtate of a man: as when we call ſeruants
pueros: Secondly the ſexe, as when we
call a male child puerum: Or els the age, as
when we call one that is yong puerum.
                     
                     
                        Pars is that wherby the whole is ſupported,
it is either pars diuiſa, or pars indiuiſa, this diuiſion
wil hold both in nature &amp; Law: In nature
that id a diuided part, which conſiſteth of
diuerſe parcels: as the wing of a bird, or the
clouen hoofe of a beaſt, or the finne of a fiſh are
ſaid to be parts diuided: In law there is alſo a
diuided part, as the third part wherof a woman
is indowed after the death of her huſbād, &amp; after
the aſſignment made, and the third part of the

land of the tenant in Capite, which the king
hath after his death: Likewiſe the partes of a
manor diuided by parceners: A part vndiuided
is manifeſt to the vnderſtanding &amp; to the eye:
to the vnderſtanding, as the moitie or third
part of iointenants, parceners, tenāts in common,
before particion: to the eye, as the vnclouen
hoofe of a beaſt, or the partes of the
earth cleauing contumately together.
                  
                  
                     R.
                     
                        Ripa, a banke, it is proper to a floude, as the
ſhoare is to the ſea. Ripa is that which doth
flumen continere, ſtay the natural force of his
courſe, and that is ſaid to be a banke, quae pleniſſimum
flumen continet, which ſtayeth the
water, when it is at the higheſt.
                  
                  
                     S.
                     
                        Sequeſtratio is either a ſeperation, by way
of compounding, or by interdiction of poſſeſſion:
It is voluntaria, or neceſſaria, Voluntaria,
when it is done by the conſent of the parties,
Neceſſaria, whe
                           •
                         it is done by one that hath a
competent aucthoritie to ſequeſter.
                     
                        Sylua caedua, which being cut may grow
againe.
                  
                  
                     T.
                     
                        Tugurium, quaſi 
                              •
                           egurium, it is taken of
ſome for euery countrie houſe, but not rightly,

for the houſe which doth conſiſt of walles and
tiles or bricke is no cotage, but a cotage is
that which doth principally conſiſt of reedes
or thatch or ſoddes, earth and twigs layed together,
and compacted by clay or ſlime, or
which hath in it a very ſmall deale of timber.
                     
                        Tumultus is taken for euery perilous commotion,
if it be publiquely and haſtely done.
                     
                        Turba, a multitude, conſiſting at the leaſt
of the number of tenne.
                  
                  
                     V.
                     
                        Vacillaus teſtis, which doth giue an inconſtant
and diuerſe teſtimonie.
                     
                        Vagabundus, which hath neither certaine
houſe, nor ſtedfaſt habitation, a man, as one
tearmeth him, ſine re, ſine ſpe, ſine fide, ſine
ſede.
                     
                     
                        Vel, a particle, it doth not alwayes diſioyne,
but ſometimes explane.
                     
                        Vis force or violence: it is of diuers ſorts,
vis detractiua, when a man taketh a thing
from one againſt his will: vis compulſiua,
when I compell a man to aſſent to a certaine
acte, vis diuina, commonly called vis maior,
whereof there is no reſiſtance: vis expulſiua,
which is done with weapon, and it is called
of ſome vis armata, vis inquietatiua, when I

am diſſeiſed by force, vis imminens the ſtriking
or aſſault of a man. Vis is not verbis, but facto,
for he is not ſaid vim pati, which is onely touched
by wordes.
                     Vniuerſale quod ad vniuerſos pertinet.
                  
               
            
            
               What methode is to be
vſed in handling and diſpoſing
matters of Law.
               The ninth Chapter.
               
                  OF methode it were better to write
nothing then little, for ſo many
diuerſe methodes are propoſed by
many diuers authors, that plentie
breedeth ſcarſity, and a man can hardelye
tell which to chooſe. Curioſitie as in all
other thinges it is vaine, ſo in methode it is
neceſſarie. For to proceede without equalitie
of tenor is negligence, and to obſerue methode
vnartificially is ignorance. They that giue a
reaſon of the beginning, continuance, and ending
of their tractats and diſcourſes, are without
doubte the moſt iudiciall and moſt plauſible
methodiſtes: or they which ſo temper and
moderate the courſe of matters, that though

they render not a preciſe reaſon of their doeings:
yet it is apparant to the reaſon and vnderſtanding
of others. A twofolde methode
is verie much talked of, and that is by proceeding
either a ſingularibus ad vniuerſalia or ab
vniuerſalibus ad ſingularia, the one of theſe I
accompt no methode at all, howſoeuer it hath
vſurped the name, being but a natural diſcerning
of thinges done in facto by the ordinary
direction of the ſenſes, and making thereof
a generall concluſion, which is eaſie and familiar
to euery mans capacitie, ſo that the
praiſe of that action is diligence and not art,
for is it any difficult thing to reaſon and conclude,
wood is heauie, ſtone is heauie, iron
is heauie, &amp; ſic in caeteris: therefore all thinges
made of earth are heauie? how pro
                     •
                  e and readie
is the perceauing of theſe particulars to
euerie mans ſenſe? and how eaſilie may the
concluſion be framed by his vnderſtanding?
but in deede the diſcourſing from vniuerſalles
to particulars is more hard, more artificiall,
more compendious, for it is done in leſſe compaſſe
and fewer wordes, which is a great
argument of a good methode, and therefore
I doe not agree to Ariſtotle that Athenian
Doctor, when hee ſaieth, Ars tum exiſtit,
cum ex multis experientiae notionibus vna
                        •
                     
quae ad vniuerſum genus accommodetur naſcitur
praeceptio.
                  Me
                        •
                     aphyſ. 1▪ c. 1. Vnleſſe hee meane it of

vulgar and mechanicall trades and occupations,
whereof onely I admit it to be true,
but I rather approoue that which he ſaith,
and doth likewiſe: progrediendum eſt ab vniuerſalibus
ad ſingularia.
                  Phyſicor. 1. c. 1. But there be ſome
which will not allow any diſcourſe but that
which is furniſhed with mathematicall and
demonſtratiue reaſons. Some would haue
euery thing handled by examples, as Ramus,
a man happier in writing, then in reproouing
one that writ better then hee: who
in handling Logicall places, doth illuſtrate
them with many examples, but with neuer
a rule. What manner of teaching is this, to
ſhewe vnto thee that others did thus: but not
to ſhewe why they did ſo: which default is
for want of rules, in which the reaſon and
knowledge of doing thinges aright is conteyned.
A man cannot make a ſhooe by a
number of laſtes, but hee muſt haue inſtruction
of one that is ſkilfull in the trade. Some
againe will haue euery thing confirmed by
the authorities and teſtimonies of them that
be learned, thinking that onely to be the fit
way of teaching. But the certaine and neceſſarie
reaſons of the Mathematikes, are not
in all artes to be required.Ariſt. Metaphyſ. 1. part. poſter. c. 3. Neyther is there
an 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   or accurate kinde of handling things
in all ſciences alike to be vſed and obſerued:
but in euery ſcience things are ſo to be ordred

and digeſted, as the ſubiect or matter doth
require where about it is employed, and ſo
farre forth as may be agreeable to the profeſſion
of the ſcience. For a Geometrician and
a Carpenter doe diuerſly handle and vſe a
right line, the one, as it may be profitable to
his worke which he carueth, the other ſearcheth
what kinde of thing it is, and of what
nature and ſo other ſciences muſt be ruled by
the ſubiect which they contemplate, leaſt
there be more 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   then 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   in them: neyther
is a cauſe or reaſon to be exacted in all
things, for of many it is ſufficient to haue this
knowledge quòd ita ſunt, though we cannot
know propter quod ita ſunt, as of principles
which are the firſt and higheſt rules in artes
and ſciences, and therefore no reaſon can be
yeelded, becauſe they are prima, the very firſt
in the diſcourſe of reaſon, and therefore 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
for thēſelues to be beleeued▪ Surely Methode
is ſo conuenient a thing in the ſtudie of the
lawe, that without it neither can the vnderſtanding
be well taught, nor the memorie
well directed. It is not enough to haue a
great heape of things that are to be read, vnleſſe
the vſe or order and manner of reading
them 
                     •
                  e well vnderſtoode: and as in things
that 
                     •
                  e fit for banquets, tho
                     •
                  gh there be great
varietie of ſweete meates, yet there is nothing
more vnpleaſant or vnholſome if they

be mingled together, ſo the Student muſt
haue a care leaſt the order of his reading be
confounded, leaſt the laſt things be handled
in the firſt place, and theſe thinges which
ſhould be in the middeſt be put in the laſt
place, whiche whoſoeuer doe, they cannot
onely not comprehende the thinges which
they ſtudie, but vtterly debilitate and weaken
the ſtrength of the memorie: therefore
it is good for Students to vſe an artificiall
Analyſis, or reſolution of things, into their
principles, which may teach to deuide the
whole into his partes, and to ſubdeuide partes
into parcells, and in the end to make a conſent
and coherence of the entire thing and
his partes: for though the ſkilfull partition
of things be profitable and pleaſant for the
memorie, yet the Syntheſis, that is the apt
compoſition, coordination, and mutuall dependance
of them doth more ſatiſfie the vnderſtanding.
Polyb. lib. 1. hiſtor. Therefore Polybius a iudicious
aucthor ſaith well, that they which thinke by
the knowledge of particulars diſperſed to attaine
to the full and perfit knowledge of the
entire thing, doe no leſſe erre, then hee who
viewing the partes of a handſome and comely
body ſeuerally and apart, doth therefore imagin
that hee knoweth the whole feature and
portraicture of the ſame man, who if hee had
beheld theſe parts ioyned together, and compacted,

and moued by the ſpirit of life, would
haue iudged farre otherwiſe. For though a
man may haue a confuſed notion, or conceite
of the whole, by viewing the ſeperate and diſioyned
partes, yet it is not poſſible that hee
ſhould haue certaine knowledge of the ſame,
no more then a man by ſeeing perticular
Mappes of Cities, may certainely perceiue
the figure, ſituation, and order of the whole
world. But he that can eaſily reſolue things,
may eaſily compound: for when he knoweth
the particular ſenſe and vſe of the thinges
reſolued, hee may eaſily gather a generall
knowledge of the whole thing, that is, a
generall knowledge of manye particulars,
whiche make one entire thing. The forme
of this Analyſis following, whiche is of
Maiſter Littleton his two Chapiters of fee
ſimple, and fee taile, I doe offer to the
Student, as a thing to be conſidered of, becauſe
it is incident to this purpoſe, which
though it gaine not his good liking, yet if it
miniſter but occaſion vnto him to aduenture
vpon the conueyance of ſome other Analyſis,
that may receiue the generall approbation,
and iuſt applauſe of the learned, I ſhall thinke
my labour herein well beſtowed, and woulde
gladlye reape profit by other mens preſidents.
               
                  
                  
                     The Analyſis of Littletons Chapiter of Fee ſimple.
                     Tenure in
fee ſimple
may bee
conſidered

                           By the definition

                                 Inuented.

                                       Fee ſimple is as much to ſay, as a lawfull and pure inheritance.
                                    
                                 
                                 Expounded.

                                       He that will purchaſe lands in fee ſimple muſt haue theſe wordes in his purchaſe, (To
haue and to hold to him and to his heires, for theſe words his heires make the eſtate of
inheritance, and he that lacketh this word (heires) and hath to haue and to hold to him
and to his aſſignes for euer, hath eſtate but for terme of life.
                                    
                                 
                              
                           
                           By the tenant
in fee ſimple
who is after
two ſorts to be
conſidered.

                                 Generally.

                                       Tenant in fee ſimple, is he which hath landes or teneme
                                             ••
                                          s to hold to him and to his
heires for euer.
                                    
                                 
                                 Particularly.

                                       By purchaſe as when a man both lands and t
                                             ••
                                          ements by his deede, or by his agreement,
to the poſſeſſion of which he commeth not, by title of diſcent from none of his
aunceſtors, or his 
                                             •
                                          oſins, but by his owne act.
                                       By diſcent
who may
be thus
deſcribed.

                                             He that is
tenant in
fee ſimple
muſt be of
the whole
bloud w
                                                   ••
                                                
may bee
proued by
two examples.

                                                   1 If a man haue iſſue two Sonnes by two venters, and the
elder purchaſeth lands in fee ſimple, and dieth without iſſue,
the yonger brother ſhall not haue the land, but the vncle of
the elder brother, or ſome other his 
                                                         •
                                                      ye coſins ſhall haue it,
for yt the yonger is but of the halfe bloud to the elder brother.
                                                   2. If a man haue a Sonne and daughter by one venter, &amp; a
Sonne by an other venter, and the ſonne by the firſt venter▪
purchaſeth lands in fee ſimple, and dieth without iſſue, the ſiſter
ſhall haue the land by diſcent as heire vnto her brother,
for that the ſiſter is of the whole bloud to the elder brother.
                                                
                                             
                                          
                                       
                                    
                                 
                              
                           
                           By the
properties
of fee ſimple.

                                 1
Inheritance in fee
ſimple may lineallie
diſcend but not
lineally aſcende
which may be
illuſtrated by ſixe
prerogatiues.

                                       1
By the vncles
prerogatiue

                                             If the fathers ſonne purchaſe land in fee ſimple, the vncle ſhal haue the
land as heire vnto the ſonne, and not the father, becauſe it cannot lineally
aſcende.
                                          
                                       
                                       2
By the fathers
prerogatiue
which
is threefold.

                                             1 If the foreſaid vncle dye without iſſue, the Father liuing, the Father
ſhall haue the land as heire vnto the vncle, and not vnto the ſonne, for that
he commeth to the land by collaterall diſcent, and not by lineal aſcention.
                                             2 If landes diſcend by the Fathers ſide, the Fathers ſide ſhall inherite,
and none of the Mothers ſide.
                                             3 If the ſonne die without iſſue, and haue purchaſed lands in fee ſimple
they of the bloud of the fathers ſide ſhall be heire vnto him before any of
the mothers ſide.
                                          
                                       
                                       3.
By the mothers
prerogatiue
which
is twofold.

                                             1 If the ſonne hauing purchaſed lands in fee ſimple haue no heires on
the fathers ſide, then ſhall the land diſcend vnto the heire on the mothers
ſide.
                                             2 If a man take a wife inheritrix in fee ſimple, which hath iſſue a ſonne
and then dieth, and the ſonne entreth into the tenements as ſonne and heire
to his mother, and after dieth without iſſue, the heires of the mothers
ſide ought to inherite the tenementes, and not the heires of the fathers
ſide.
                                          
                                       
                                       4
By the brothers
prerogatiue
which
is after two
ſorts.

                                             1 If there be three brethren, and the middle or yonger brother purchaſe
land and dye without iſſue, the elder brother ſhall haue the land by diſcent,
for that he is more worthie of bloud.
                                             2 If there be two brethren by diuers venters, and the elder is ſeiſed in
fee ſimple and dyeth without iſſue and his vncle entreth as heire vnto him
which alſo dyeth without iſſue the yonger ſonne ſhall inherite the tenementes
as heire to the vncle, becauſe hee is of the whole bloud to his
vncle.
                                          
                                       
                                       5
By the Siſters
prerogatiue.

                                             If a man be ſeiſed of land in fee ſimple, which hath iſſue a ſonne and a
daughter by one venter, and a ſonne by an other venter, and dieth: and the
elder ſonne entreth, and dyeth without iſſue, the daughter ſhall haue the
land, and not the yonger ſonne, but if the elder brother die before entrye
be made, then the yonger brother ſhall haue the land. Qui a poſſeſsio fratris
defe
                                                      •
                                                   do ſimplici facit ſororem eſſe heredem.
                                             
                                          
                                       
                                       6
By the prerogatiue
of
the whole
kindred.

                                             If a man purchaſe land in fee ſimple and dye without iſſue, euery one
that is his next couſin collateral for default of iſſue may inherite.
                                          
                                       
                                    
                                 
                                 2 Of ſuch thinges
whereof a man
may haue a manuall
occupation, poſſeſſion
or receite
as of lands, tenemēts,
rents, or ſuch
other, a man ſhall
ſay in his pleading
&amp; in way of barre,
that one ſuch was
ſeiſed in his demeſne
as of fee, but
of ſuch things that
lye not in manual
occupation, as of
an aduowſon of a
church, or ſuch maner
of things, there
he ſhal ſay, that he
was ſeiſed as of fee
and not in his demeſne
as of fee.
                                 3 Fee ſimple is the
largeſt &amp; greateſt
inheritance that a
man can haue.
                                 4 For default of
lawful heires the
lord ſhal haue the
land held in fee
ſimple by eſchete.
                              
                           
                        
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  Obſeruations vpon the
Analyſis.
                  
                     A.
                     THis definition, which Maiſter
Littleton vſeth, ſoundeth like a
good Logicall definition, as conſiſting
of the true genus, and the
proper difference: for this word (inheritance)
is the genus, which extendeth as well to fee
ſimple, as to fee taile, and this word (pure) is
a difference, whereby it is diſtinguiſhed from
fee taile: for fee ſimple is a pure inheritance,
that is without limitation or reſtreint, but
fee taile is a limitted or a reſtreigned inheritance.
This word (lawfull) in the definition
is not idle: but the meaning of it is, that it is
an inheritance according to the meaning of
common lawe, for if by (lawfull) ſhould be
meant rightfull, then a fee ſimple by diſeiſin
ſhould be excluded, which I thinke was not
Maiſter Littletons intent. And againe, if this
worde (lawfull) ſhoulde extend to all lawes,
inheritance ſhould be heere taken according
to the interpretation of other lawes alſo,

which cannot be. Maiſter Littleton well beginneth
with the definition, for there are but
foure things to be doubted of, firſt, whether
a thing be in rerum natura, ſecondly, what it
is, and of what nature, thirdly, whether it be
ſuch and ſo qualified or no, fourthly, why it is
ſuch, and ſo qualified: and he that wel openeth
theſe foure points▪ ſhall in all learned diſcourſes
ſhewe hymſelfe excellent and abſolute.
                  
                     B.The nature of fee ſimple may bee ſomewhat
vnderſtoode by applying it to the ſubiect
to which it apperteineth, for tenant in
fee ſimple, and tenure in fee ſimple, beeing
coniugata, hee that well knoweth the one,
muſt of neceſſitie well vnderſtand the other.
                  
                     C.Maiſter Littleton laſtly deſcribeth eſtate in
fee ſimple by certaine adiuncts or properties
which do greatly ſerue to illuſtrate, and explaine
the things whereof wee intreate: they
are of two ſortes, externall and internall.
Internall are they whiche flowe from the
nature of the thing it ſelfe: of ſuch ſorte are
the firſt and third properties mentioned in
the Analyſis, for in that fee ſimple may lineally
diſcende, and not lineally aſcende,
the nature of the tenure is the onely cauſe,
for it beeyng to a man and ſo hys heyres,

the more worthie heire is he that is of the
bodie, the leſſe worthie he that is of the bloud
and not of the bodie, but the father in regard
of the ſonne can be neither of theſe but in regard
and by mediation of the vncle he may
be heire to the ſonne, becauſe he is of the
vncles bloud, ſo that in the direct line it is
euident, that the fee ſimple cannot aſcend:
and it is a very eſſential propertie to fee ſimple
to be the largeſt and greateſt inheritance, becauſe
it is to a man and his heires without limitation.
Externall properties are theſe;
which do ſo go before a thing, or ſo follow it;
or ſo cleaue to it, that notwithſtanding there
is no neceſſitie of any of theſe: as for example,
before the killing of a man, commonly there
is ſome brawling and contention of words▪
With the acte doth concurre the ſighing or
groaning of him that is ſlaine, and the flight,
feare, lurking, trembling, and vnconſtant anſwere
of him that did kill him do follow the
acte, howbeit ſome be ſlaine, without the concurrence
of theſe circumſtances. There be
two ſortes of adiunctes, ſome belonging to
the perſon, ſome to the thing it ſelfe, to the
perſon as the kinred, countrey, ſe
                        •
                     e, age, education,
the habit of the bodie, the fortune, the
eſtate, the qualities of his minde, the manner
of his life. The adiuncts of the thing are the

cauſes, the place, the time, the manner of
doing a thing, and ſuch like. Of theſe, ſome
be common, and ſome be proper: common,
as if one ſhould commend Achilles, becauſe
he was of good birth, becauſe he was a great
captaine, becauſe he was in fight againſt the
Troians, for euery of whiche, Diomedes is
as much to be commended as Achilles. Proper
adiuncts be, as if thou ſhouldeſt commend
Achilles for his great valor in killing Hector
the ſtouteſt of the Troians, and for his good
fortune in killing Cygnus, who being inuulnerable,
did barre all the Gretians from comming
downe the wall, and becauſe beeing
young, and not bound by any othe or leageance,
he fought ſo valiantly for the Gretians.
Theſe two later of the proper adiuncts, I
call externall, as not flowing from the eſſence
of a thing, but befalling externally
to it when it is in eſſe. Of this kinde there
are two in the Analyſis, the ſeconde and
fourth.
               
               
                  
                  The Analyſis of Littletons Chapiter of Fee taile.
                  
                     Fee taile
may be diuers
waies
conſidered

                           By the
firſt originall.

                                 Tenant in fee taile is by force of the ſtatute W. 2. cap. 1. for at the common Law before the ſaid ſtatute, all
inheritances were fee ſimple.
                              
                           
                           A
By the
definition.

                                 Inuented.

                                       Feodum taliatum eſt haereditas in quadam certitudine limitata.
                                    
                                 
                                 Expounded
after ij. ſorts.

                                       1 If tenant in taile die without iſſue, the donor or his heires ſhall inherite as in their reuerſion,
for in euery gift in the taile the reuerſion of the fee ſimple is in the donor.
                                       2 If a man giue lands or tenements to an other to haue and to hold to him and to his heires
males or females, he to whom ſuch gift is made hath fee ſimple, for that it is not limitted by the
gift of what bodie the iſſue male or female ſhall be.
                                    
                                 
                              
                           
                           By the
diuerſe
kindes
thereof

                                 In reſpect
of
the nature
of
the entaile.

                                       Taile
general
which
is to be
conſidered
by
the

                                             Definition.

                                                   Inuented.

                                                         Taile general is where landes be giuen to one and to the heires of
his bodie begotten.
                                                      
                                                   
                                                   Expounded.

                                                         Therefore it is called generall taile, becauſe whatſouer woman
the tenant taketh to wife, if he haue many wiues, &amp; by each of thē
haue iſſue, yet any of theſe iſſues by poſſibility may inherite the tenements
by force of the ſaid gift, becauſe that euery ſuch iſſue is of
his body ingendred. So if lands be giuen to a woman, and to the
heires of her body, howbeit that ſhe haue many husbands, yet the
iſſue that ſhe hath by each husband may inherite.
                                                      
                                                   
                                                
                                             
                                             By an example
or ſpeciall kinde
thereof

                                                   If tenements be giuen to a man and to his wife, &amp; to the heires
of the body of the man ingendred, in this caſe the husband hath eſtate
in the general taile, &amp; the wife eſtate but for terme of life.
                                                
                                             
                                          
                                       
                                       Taile
ſpeciall
which
is to be
examined
according
to the

                                             Definition.

                                                   Inuented.

                                                         Tenant in taile ſpecial is where lands &amp; tenements be giuen to a
man and his wife (iointly or ſeuerally) &amp; to the heires of their two
bodies begotten.
                                                      
                                                   
                                                   Expoū
                                                      ded
after
two
ſorts.

                                                         1 In ſuch caſe none may enherite by force of ſuch gift, but thoſe
which be engendred betweene them two, &amp; it is called ſpecial taile:
for that if the wife die and he take an other wife, and hath iſſu, the
iſſue of the ſecond wife ſhal neuer inherite by force of ſuch gift, nor
alſo the iſſue of the ſecond husband if the firſt die.
                                                         2 In the ſame maner it is where lands &amp; tenements be giuen by a
man vnto another with a wife, which is the daughter or couſin to
the giuer in frankmariage, which gift hath inheritance by this word
(Frankma
                                                               •
                                                            ) vnto it annexed, howbeit they be not expreſſely ſaid
nor rehearſed in the gift, that is to ſay, that theſe donees ſhall haue

theſe lands or tenements to them &amp; to their 
                                                               〈◊〉
                                                             betweene them
two ingengred, &amp; this is called ſpecial tail, becauſe the iſſue of the ſecond
wife may not inherit, &amp; the woman donee in frankma
                                                               •
                                                             muſt
be of kin to the donor, &amp; they ſhal do no ſeruice but feal it, till the
4. degree to be accompted from the donor be paſt.
                                                      
                                                   
                                                
                                             
                                             Diuerſe
kindes
thereof.

                                                   1 If lands be giuen to the husband and to the wife, and to the heires of the
husband which he begetteth of the body of ye wife, in this caſe the husbād hath
eſtate in ſpecial taile, and the wife but for terme of life.
                                                   2 If the gift be made to the husband and to the wife, and to the heires of
the wife of her body by the husband ingendred, the wife hath eſtate in ſpecial
taile, &amp; the husband but for terme of life.
                                                   3 If lands be giuen to the husband &amp; the wife, and to the heires which the
husband hath by his wife in this caſe, both haue eſtate in taile ſpecial, for that
this word (heires) is not limited more to the one then to the other.
                                                   4 If lands begiuen to a mau &amp; his heirs wt he engēdreth on the body of his
wife in this caſe ye husbād hath eſtate in the tail ſpecial, &amp; ye wife nothing at al.
                                                
                                             
                                          
                                       
                                    
                                 
                                 In reſpect
of
the perſons
to
whom
the taile
belongeth.

                                       Taile to the
heire male
which is two
fold.

                                             1. If landes be giuen to a man &amp; his heires males of his body ingendred, in ſuch
caſe his heire male ſhall inherite, but his iſſue female ſhal neuer inherite.
                                             2 If lands be giuen to a man &amp; to his heires males of his body engendred, &amp; he
hath iſſu ij. ſonnes &amp; deceaſeth, and the elder ſonne entreth as heire male, and hath
iſſue a daughter and deceaſeth, his brother ſhall haue the land and not the daughter,
for that the brother is heire male.
                                          
                                       
                                       Taile to the
heire female
wt is to bee
cōſidered by
ye definition.

                                             Taile to the heire female, is where lands be giuen to a man &amp; to his heires females
of his body ingendred, in this caſe his iſſue female ſhall inherite by force and forme
of the ſaid gift, and not the iſſue male, for that in ſuch caſes where the gift is, who
ought to inherite, and who not, the will of the donor ſhall be obſerued.
                                          
                                       
                                    
                                 
                              
                           
                           By the
properties.

                                 1 Whoſoeuer ſhal inherite
by force of a gift in the taile
made vnto ye heires males it
behoueth him to cōuey his
diſcent by ye males wt may
be illuſtrated by 2. exāples.

                                       1 If lands be giuen to a man and to his heires males of his body ingendred,
and he hath iſſue a daughter, who hath iſſue a ſonne, and deceaſeth, in this caſe
the ſonne of the daughter ſhall not inherite by force of the taile, but in ſuch caſe
the donor ſhall enter.
                                       2 If lands be giuen to a man and his wife, and to the heires males of their two
bodies begotten, and they haue iſſue after the like ſort, the like ſhall happen.
                                    
                                 
                                 2 The death of a man taketh not away the eſtate of thoſe that be in the tail, as if a man haue iſſue a ſonne &amp;
deceaſeth, and land is giuen to the ſonne, and to the heires of the body of his father ingendred, this is a good tail,
and yet the father was dead at the time of the gift.
                                 3 The donees and their iſſue ſhall hold of the donor and his heires as he holdeth of the Lord Paramount.
                              
                           
                        
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  Obſeruations vpon the
Analyſis.
                  
                     THis definition, which Maiſter
Littleton maketh of eſtate taile,
conſiſteth likewiſe of genus, and
of a difference. The genus is haereditas,
which is common both to it and to
fee ſimple: the difference in quadam certitudine
limitata, by which it is diſtinguiſhed from
fee ſimple, for that is non limitata &amp; ſine certitudine,
and by this definition a man may
know what a fee ſimple is, and by the definition
of fee ſimple what fee taile is, ſo that the
rules of arte are well obſerued, which are that
Rectum eſt iudex ſui obliqui, and oppoſita iuxta
ſe poſita magis illuceſcunt.
                  
                  Though the diuiſion or tenure of eſtate taile
doth in the Table precedent conſiſt of two
members, or two differences, yet the eſpeciall
taile is deuided into more partes: and that
manner of deuiding is not contrary to the
rules of methode, for it is too much curioſitie
to exact in euery diuiſion two onely oppoſed
eſſentiall differences, and two diſtinct kindes.

There be three cauſes wherefore a diuiſion
cannot be made by two differences. Firſt becauſe
of noe kind of thing, both the eſſential
differences cannot certainly bee knowen, but
the one of them wee doe expreſſe by a negatiue.
Secondly, becauſe that difference which
wee ſet downe in the affirmatiue is not alway
the true difference. Thirdly, becauſe the
diuerſe nature of diuerſe immediate kindes
of one thing wil not alwaies permit a twofold
diuiſion, for though the diuiſion of Animal in
hominem &amp; brutum bee bimembris and according
to rigorous exaction, yet ſithe there be
many kindes of brutiſh creatures, ſome that
ſwimme, ſome that flye, ſome that goe, ſome
that creepe, and the particulars of theſe
kindes doe differ in the quinteſſence of their
nature, ſurely to comprehend all theſe diſtinct
thinges vnder two differences is not to be
required, becauſe it is either impoſſible, or
a thing of exceeding difficultie. But when
things are to be handled by way of diſputation,
as the arguing of caſes which is of great
vſe in the lawe, another methode and courſe
muſt be vſed then hath bene taken in the framing
of this Analyſis, for there the principall
caſe muſt be fully ſet downe, the points
of 
                        •
                     awe orderly diſtinguiſhed, the reaſons on
the one part muſt be firſt ſet downe, with anſweres
annexed vnto them, then the reaſons

on the other part, with anſweres likewiſe in
their due places: and laſtly, the concluſion of
the whole controuerſie debated, whether it
were by iudgement, adiournement, or by the
concord of the parties, or by other ſpeciall
meane, and for better direction herein (I am
deſirous to profit others if I could) I haue
ſet downe an homely paterne according to
the plaines of my conceit, in the diſpoſing
and ordering of a caſe, famous in our yeare
bookes, and of great weight and vſe, being
the Prior of Mertons caſe, being very often
at large argued, namely, in the eightenth,
ninetenth, twentith, and twentie one yeares
of the raigne of King Edward the fourth at
ſeuerall times, and was likewiſe touched the
ſecond yeare of Richard the third, and all the
contents of the arguments vpon this caſe deliuered,
as many as did concerne the principall
points then in queſtion (for by matters
are to be repoſed in a ſeuerall place by themſelues)
I haue brought into the compaſſe of
a fewe lines, if you reſpect the large leafes
wherein they are handled.
               
               
                  
                  Le caſe enter le Prior de
Merton plaintife, &amp; le
Prior de Bingham
defendant.
                  EN le. 3. an de H. le. 3.Scir. faci. 18. E. 4. 22. 19. E. 4. 2. 47. 20. E. 4. 16. 21. E. 4. 60. 2. R. 3. 5. vn fine fuit leuie parenter
le Prior de Merton pl. et le Prior
de Bingham deforceant ſur vn briefe de
couent, que fuit en ceux parolls: ceſt le finall
concorde parēter le Prior de Merton querentem
et le Prior de Bingham deforceantem de
5. Markes, et v. s̄. rent cū pertinentiis en S.
et R. ſur que vn brief de couenant fuit ſum̄on
enter eux que fuit que lauantdit Prior de
Bingham acknowledge et grante pur luy et
ſes ſucceſſors que touts iours, apres ils payer
cheſcun an al eſgliſe de Merton pur les tenemēts
queux il tient del dit prior et pur les tenemēts
queux W. de W. aſcun foits tient del
dit Prior en les villages auantdits cinque
markes, et v. s̄. a deux termes dans, pur touts
ſuites et ſeruices, et que il ferroit a le chiefe
ſeign̄or del fee pur lauantdit Prior de M. et
ſes ſucceſſors touts ſeruices queux apperteignont
a les dits tenemēts: et pur ceſt graunt le
dit Prior de M. grant pur luy, et ſes ſucceſſors,
que ils violent garrant̄ al auantdit Prior
de Bingham et ſes ſucceſſors touts lauantdits
tenements pur les auantdits ſeruices contra

omnes gentes: ſur que vient en le courte vn
I. Prior de Merton et prya ſcire faci. enuers
W. Prior de Bingham dauer execution darrerages
del dit rent, que fuerōt due en les ans
darrein paſſe, et il auoit: et fuit returne &amp;c.
a quel iour le Prior de Bingham vient eins,
et dit que le fine prooue le rente grant a le
predeceſſors del pl. deſtre vn rent ſeruice on
a
                        ••
                     une auter rent iſſuant hors de terre et nemy
vn annuitie, per que entant que il auoit
acknowledge, que ceſt rent fuit execute, il doit
auer vn Aſſiſe ou Diſtres, et nemy vn brief
que eſt en nature de briefe dannuitie▪ et ſur
ceſt ils demurront.
                  
                     Les quaestions de ley.
                     
                        1. Si le fine fuit bien leuie.
                        2. Si le rent ſoit vn annuitie.
                     
                     
                        1. Negat. Que le fine ne fuit bien
leuie.
                        
                           Littleton.
                           Fines he ſont bon e
                                 ••
                              eant leuies de choſes
queux ne ſont in rerum natura al temps del
fine leuie,A. et le rent de que ceſt fine fuit 
                                 •
                              eu
                                 •
                              e
ne fuit in eſſe al temps pe
                                 •
                               que &amp;c.Ratio prima.
                           
                        
                        
                           
                           Brian.
                           Ceo ne beſoigne.B. Car ſi ieo auoy in Iſlington
20. li. rent iſſuant de terres de twentie homes
per ſeuerall grauntes,Reſponſum. ſi ieo graunt per fine
a vous 20. li. rent hors de lour terres ou tenements
in Iſlington vous naueres 20. li. rent
queur ieo auoy in Iſlington mes vous aueres
vn nouell rent: mes eſt diuerſitie ou le choſe
de que le fine eſt deſtre leuie giſt en demeſne,
et ou nemy. Car lou giſt en demeſne, la doit
eſtre in eſſe al temps del fine leuie, come ſi ies
leuie fine de mon terre en dale lou ieo nauera
aſcun terre en dale, ceſt fine eſt voide, mes de
choſe que poit iſſuer hors de terre vn fine poit
eſtre leuie, coment que ne ſoit in rerum natura,
come de rent ou common in dale, ou en fait
il nauoit aſcun common ou rent in dale al
temps &amp;c. mes ſil auoit common in groſſe en

                                 〈◊〉
                               le ville, et graunt a moy vn common, et ne
monſtra quel common, ceo ſerra conſtrue le
common que il auoit en 
                                 〈◊〉
                               le ville.
                        
                        
                           Neale.
                           Ceſt fine eſt leuie de vn mere annuitie,C. et
pur ceo eſt male,Ratio. 2. cont̄ ſi de choſe naturallment
ſurdant hors de terre come ſi ieo conuſt tout
mon dr̄t en vn acre de terre auous et vous per

                                 〈◊〉
                               le fine graunt a moy vn annual rēt de 20. s̄.

hors de 
                                 〈◊〉
                               le terre, ceſt bon grant, vn
                                 •
                               ne fuit
aſcun originall de ceo: per que &amp;c.
                        
                        
                           Brian.
                           En auncient temps home puiſſoit auer
conus vn fine ſans originall,Reſponſ. et ſil ſoit leuie a
ceſt iour il poit auer ſcire facias et ſi aduowſo
                                 •
                              
diſcend al coparceners et ils ꝑ indenture enrolle
voilent agree de preſenter ꝑ turne, cheſcun
de eux quant ſon temps vient auera ſcire
facias: per que &amp;c.
                        
                        
                           Piggot.
                           En auncient temps fines fue
                                 •
                               leuie deo et
eccleſie,
                              Replicat ad hoc reſponſ. mes le ley eſtore alter: mes come ieo
penſa cheſcun fine doit auer originall et de
accorder a 
                                 •
                              . Car le note eſt placitum conuentionis,
et en noſtre caſe neſt aſcun couen̄ dun
annuitie, mes dun rent ſolement, et ſi le originall
ſeit de 20. acres et le fine ſoit leuie de
40. acres quant al 20. le partie ſer
                                 •
                               diſcharge:
car ne fuit aſcun originall de eux, et en praecipe
quod reddat le fine poit eſtre leuie del choſe en
demaunde, car le originall conteigne et concerne
c̄. Iſſint ſi brief de couen̄ ſoit de 20 acres
en dale et le fine eſt leuie, de 20 acres en ſale
le fine neſt bon, ou ſi le originall ſoit de terre
arable, et le counuſans de paſture.
                        
                     
                     
                        
                        1. Affirmat'. Que le fine fuit bien
leuie.D. Ratio 1.
                        
                        
                           Sulyarde.
                           Si en vn brief de couen̄ port dun mannor, le
plaintif graunt le mannor al le deforceant, et
graunt ouſtre a diſcharger le dit mannor enuers
le ſeignior del fee, ceſt bon fine, et vnc
                                 •
                               le
clauſe de diſcharging ne fuit en le briefe de
couen̄, donques en ceſt caſe &amp;c.
                        
                        
                           Sulyarde.
                           
                              E. Ratio 2.Si en vn briefe de droit de cuſtomes et ſeruices
le ſeignior poit releaſer per fine tout ſon
droit, que il ad en le terre, et le ten̄ poit graunt
per 
                                 〈◊〉
                               le fine 20. 
                                 •
                              . annualment, donques &amp;c.
                        
                        
                           Catesby.R. 3.
                           
                           Quant vn home acknowledge le droit de
terre a vn et vn rēt eſt reſerue ſur le graunt et
ren
                                 •
                              , ou vn common, ou tot carectae ligni deſtre
priſe del ter
                                 •
                              , ceſt bon, car ils ſont conteigne
implicatiue, en le originall, mes ſi le
fine eſt leuie dun choſe nient expreſſe ne implide
en le originall ceſt voide, donques en ceſt
caſe, pur c̄ que le fine eſt dun rent ſeruice, car
le fine eſt pro omnibus alijs ſeruitijs per ceſt
ꝑoll (alijs) eſt implide, que le rent eſt aliquod▪
ſeruitium.
                           
                        
                     
                     
                        
                        2. Negat. Que le rent en ceſt 
                              •
                           aſe
neſt vn annuitie.
                        
                           Piggot.
                           Le fine eſt que le Prior de Merton pur les
ſeruices auant dits acquite le Prior de Bingham
de touts ſeruices enuers le ſeignour del
fee,F. et pur ceo ceſt rent ſeruice et nemie
rent ſecke.Ratio. 1.
                           
                        
                        
                           Collowe.
                           Le rent eſt change per le fine,Reſponſ. Car ambideur
les parties ſerront eſtoppe de denyer leſtate
priſe ꝑ le fine, come ſi home ſoit ſeiſe de terre
en fee, et vn fine ſoit leuie perenter eſt
                                 •
                               et luy,
per que leſtraunge acknowledge m̄ le terre a
luy et a les heires de ſon corps ingendres, ore
ſon eſtate eſt change, iſſint ſi home tient per
ſeruice de chiualer, et le ſignior per fine acknowledge
que il tient en ſoccage ore le tenure
eſt alter, et il tiendra en ſocage, et en ceſt
caſe le rent ne poit eſtre rent ſeruice, car donques
le partie poit diſtr ſur le terre et ceo ne
poit eſtre. Car touts ſuits quant al terre ſont
diſcharge per le fine: et ne poit eſtre rent
charge. Car nul terre eſt charge oue diſtr: et
rent ſecke ne poit eſtre: car donques il ſerra

demaund ſur le terre: et annuitie ne poit eſtre:
Car le Priour ne poit charge lemeaſ
                                 ••
                              .
                        
                        
                           Pigot.
                           Si le Prior ne B. 
                                 •
                              e poit extinguiſher les
ſeruices per ſes parolles,G. on per
                                 •
                              ſon act,Rat. 2. le 
                                 •
                              ent
ſeruice continue, per q̄ &amp;c.
                           Si home tient de moy per xx. s̄,H. et ies confirme
ſon eſtate de tener per vn denier pur
touts maners de ſeruices,Rat. 3. il ferra fealtie, &amp; ceſt
rent eſt parcel del auncient rent, per que &amp;c.
                        
                     
                     
                        2. Affirmat'. Que le rent eſt vn
annuitie.
                        
                           Starkey.
                           Si vn home ne poit graunt al auter ceo ḡ
il auoit deuant,I. donques le rent ḡ le Prior de
Bingham graunt a le Prior de Merton ne
poit eſtre launcient rent,Rat. 1. mes vn nouel rent ou
vn annuitie, per que &amp;c.
                           Si ieo teigne de vous per homage,Con
                                    •
                                 ir. ratio. fealtie, et

                                 •
                              . s̄. rent, et ieo voile graunter a vous per fine
xii. d. rent pur les tenements queux ieo teigne
de vous, ceſt vn nouel rent, &amp; nemy launcient
rent, per que &amp;c.
                        
                        
                           
                           Vauiſor.
                           Si per fine ſur conuſans de droit come ceo,
vn nouel rent poit eſte graunt, car ceſty a que
le conuſans eſt fait poit graunt vn rent a le conuſor,R.
et le cauſe eſt pur ceo que il ſerra intende
que ceſty a que le coNuſans eſt fait eſt
ſeiſie vel terre:Rat. 2. Mes auterment eſt de fine ſur
graunt &amp; render, car le ley ne i
                                 •
                              tende que le
grauntee eſt ſeiſie del terre, donques en ceſt

                                 •
                              aſe le rent eſt vn nouel rent.
                        
                        
                           Choke.
                           Si ceux parolx, que le Prior de Bingham
ferra touts les ſeruices pur le Prior de Merton,Rat. 3.
ne prouant ceo deſtre rent ſeruice: Car ſi
ſoient ſeignior et tenant, et le ſeignior releaſe
a le tenant per fait indent tout ſon droit que il
auoit, reddendo vnum denarium, &amp; faciendo
capitali domino ſeruitia &amp;c. en le behalfe del
ſeignior 
                                 •
                              eux parolx ſont voides, Car per le
releaſe ſon ſeigniorie eſt extinct, donques en
ceſt caſe &amp;c.
                        
                        
                           Iudgement.
                           Trois des Iuſtices agarderont ḡ le pl poit
ſuer execution per Scire facias, et iſſint iudgement
fuit enter▪ e
                                 •
                              maintenant ſedente curia,
vn briefe Derror fuit miſe eins. Et fuit touche
en le bank del Roy 2. R. 3. mes neſt la decids,
ne argue.
                        
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  Obſeruations vpon the
precedent forme of arguing.
                  
                     A. The firſt reaſon made by Maſt. Littleton
is drawen from the cauſe of the thing generally,
and ſpecially from the material cauſe:
For if the onely material cauſes of fines be
thinges which are in eſſe, it is a probable concluſion
to ſay that of this rent being not in
eſſe, a fine could not be leuied. And as the rule
of Logicke is, Quae eadem ſunt eorum generationes
et corruptiones, cauſae constituentes et corrumpentes
eaedem ſunt:
                     Ariſt. Top. 7. c. 1. So of ſuch thinges
which be the ſame in kind, the cauſes material
are the ſame: and therfore the material cauſes
of fines, that is the thing whereof they are
leuied, ought to be the ſame.
                  
                     B. The aunſwere of Brian to Maſt. Littletons
reaſon is by way of diſtinguiſhing, for
euery aunſwere muſt be either by direct granting,
or direct denying, or els by diſtinguiſhing
which is partly a granting partly a denying.
                  
                     C. Maſt. Neale his reaſon is drawen from
the ſame place of Logicke, from which Maſt.
Littletons was deriued: for he ſuppoſeth that
an Ammitie is no fit materiall cauſe whereof
a fine may be leuied.
                  
                     
                     D. Sulyards reaſon is drawen à comparatis
patibus from thinges alike probable: For
if a man in a writ of Couenant brought of a
manor, may graunt and couenant to diſcharge
the ſaid mannor againſt the Lord of the fee,
though in the writ of couenant there were no
mentioning of any ſuch diſcharge: by the like
reaſon a man may leuie a fine of a thing which
is not mentioned in the writ of couenant, and
which was no
                        •
                      in Eſſe before. And this maner
of reaſoning is grounded vpon that rule in
Logike, Si duo duobus aeque conueniant, &amp; hoc
huic conueniat, etiam illud illi conueniet.
                     Ariſt. Top. 2 c. 4.
                  
                  
                     E. Sulyards ſecond reaſon is drawen á ſimili:
For like as in a fine leuied vpon a writ
of Right brought of cuſtomes and ſeruices, the
tenant may graunt a rent which was not in
Eſſe before: ſo likewiſe in this caſe the fine
might be leuied of a rent, which had no being
before. And this conſequens is warranted by
this rule, Si in vno eorum quae ſimilia ſunt aliquo
modo ſe res habeat, eodem etiam modo in
alijs ſe habebit.
                     Ariſt. Top. 2 c. 4.
                  
                  
                     F. The firſt reaſon whereby Pigot goeth
about to prooue that the rent is not an Annuitie
is deduced à genere: For if it be truely
named by the generall name of ſeruice in the
fine, it muſt be intended to be a ſpeciall kind
of rent ſeruice, and not a rent ſecke, according
to the rule, Si aliquid ſit genus, ſpecies ab e
                           •
                        
                        
comprehenſa participabit natura eius, ſed non
natura eius quod eſt contrarium generi. 
                     h.
                  
                  
                     G. Pigot his ſecond reaſon is drawen a
comparatis paribus.
                  
                  
                     H. His third reaſon is drawen a ſimili.
                  
                  
                     I. Starkey his firſt reaſon is drawen a
comparatis paribus.
                  
                  
                     K. The reaſons vſed by Vauiſour and
Choke to prooue the rent to be an Annuitie
are drawen a ſimili.
                  
               
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

