
   
      
         
            A myrrour or glasse for them that be syke [and] in payne. Translated out of Dutche in English
            Gnaphaeus, Gulielmus, 1493-1568.
         
         
            
               1536
            
         
         Approx. 217 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 101 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01348
            STC 11470.5
            ESTC S106762
            99842472
            99842472
            7128
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01348)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7128)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 448:06)
         
         
            
               
                  A myrrour or glasse for them that be syke [and] in payne. Translated out of Dutche in English
                  Gnaphaeus, Gulielmus, 1493-1568.
                  Coverdale, Miles, 1488-1568, attributed name.
               
               [200] p.   
               
                  By my Iames Nicolson, for Ian Gough cum priuilegio Regali],
                  [Prynted in Southwarke :
                  1536.
               
               
                  Imprint from colophon.
                  Translated by Miles Coverdale?--STC.
                  Signatures: A-M N⁴.
                  Formerly STC 17982.
                  Identified as STC 17982 on UMI microfilm.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Consolation --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-09
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-11
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-07
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2006-07
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A myrrour or glaſſe for them that be ſyke &amp; in payne.
            ¶Tranſlated out of Dutche in Engliſh.
            
               Mathei. xi.
               ¶Come vnto me all ye that laboure, &amp; are ladē and I wyll eaſe you.
            
            1, 5.36.
         
         
            
            The tranſlatour vnto the Chriſtian reader.
            CHriſt oure ſauioure in the .xxv. chapter of Mathew whan he had warned vs to watche, contynētly after ſetteth forth a parable of a ryche mā
               which (beyenge purpoſed to go from home for a ſeaſon) delyuered his goodes vnto his ſeruauntes, ſayenge: Occupe tyll I come agayne▪ Now as I dyd conferre this parable with the .iiii. chap. of the epiſtle to the Epheſians, I perceaued that Chriſt ment this by himſelf: For after that he hadde fulfylled his courſe or tyme that he ſhulde be here in earth, he is mounted or aſcēded vp in to heauen, (as it is written in the .lxv, Pſalme) &amp; ledde captyue captiuite, and hath geuen gyftes vnto mē, Theſe giftes doth Paui in ꝓceſſe declare what they be. And agayne in the .xiiii chapter, of the fyrſt epiſtle to the Corinthians ſpeakynge of the gyfte of tunges ſayeth: Whan ye come together eueryone hath a pſalme, hath doctrine, hath a tunge, hath an interpretation. Let al be done to the edyfyenge, Now whan I conſydered theſe aforeſayde places of ſcripture, knowenge hys ryghtuous requyringe agayne of his proper gyftes, beynge but lent vnto me for a ſpace: I haue endeuoured me ſelf to delyuere yt to the exchaungers, to the intent that whan my Lorde ſhall come he may receaue yt with vauntage. And that he may ſo do, yt ſhalbe in thy good Chriſtian reader. And let yt not moue thy that they be laye men that be the ſpeakers in thys treatyſe, for ſo doynge ye myght be cōpared vnto Chriſtes contremen Marc. vi. whiche hearynge his heauenly wyſedome, and ſeynge his excellent myrakles, ſayde ſkornfullye: Where hath he this wyſdome? and what wyſdome is thys that is geuen hym? is not thys the carpenter? the ſonne of Ioſeph. &amp;c. Do not thou I ſaye lykwyſe, in eſtemynge the matter of leſſe value, but wyſſhe rather that ſuch a worlde myght be, wherin the prophecy of Ieremy in the .xxxi chap, be fulfylled where as he ſayeth: I wyll be theyr God, and they ſhalbe my people. And from thence forth

ſhall noman teache his neghbure, or his brother, &amp; ſaye: Knowe the Lorde But they ſhall al knowe me from the loweſt vnte the hygheſt, ſayeth the Lorde. Wolde God thys worlde were come, for than ſhall the lambe go fedynge wyth the wolfe, that is the cruell with the innocent than ſhall all the goodneſſe of the holy cyte of Hyeruſalem come vpon vs, than ſhall it be a golden worlde, than ſhal it be a tyme of peace in what tyme Chriſt wolde be borne, Seynge then that ſo much goodneſſe doth folowe the word of God, let vs with one accorde praye the father of heauen ſayenge. Bowe downe thy heade Lorde, and beholde the caſe that we are in, marke how great nede we haue of thy mercy, ſe how farre we are gone aſtraye leauynge the ye wel of lyfe, and drynkynge the modde of our pouddels. Geue ſuch mynde vnto our princes (whoſe hartes be in thy hande) that the ſuperſtitiouſnes of Baal be roted out by them, and thy foteſteppes made eaſyer to be folowed Paul ſayeth: What cō
               pany haue Chriſt and Belial? Morouer where Chriſt wyll raygne there wyl he be alone. He ſayeth he wyl not geue his glory vnto another, he wyl haue no partyfelous. Wherfore good Chriſten reader, that thou mayeſt fulfyll Gods wyll the better in geuynge hym the glory prayſe &amp; worſhippe, I haue takē in hāde to trāſlate out of dutch in engliſhe thys lytell boke: whoſe worthyneſſe can not be eſtymed, For in yt ſhalt thou learne to fixe thy mynde vnto God only, geuynge hym his dewe honour, worſhippe, and prayſe all other ſuperſtitions auoyded: and vnto thy neghbure loue and charite declared with outward dedes of the ſame, Doynge this ye ſhal haue here quietnes of cōſciēce in God, &amp; here after fruition of glory with hym: the which graunte vs he that is kynge euerlaſtynge. Amē.
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶Timothe commynge from hys vicare which refuſed to come to the poore ſikman Lazarus ſayeth on this wyſe.
            
               Timothe.
               
                  
                     O CHRIST IESV very trewe heardmā and biſhope of our ſoull, how few heardmen be ther founde whiche beſtowe their ſoules for their hearde, as thou haſt done earneſtly: euē to ye ende. Oure heardmen do not now watche thy ſhepe: They couet not to entre in to the ſhepfolde by the dore: but rather runne awaye, as very hyrelinges whā they ſe the wolfe come. Yee they themſelfs helpe to inuade them. Ah they be not lyke vnto thyne wych thou ſandeſt as ſhepe amōge the wolues: ſeynge they be become as wolues amōge ſhepe. Is not this greatly to be lamented.
            
            
               Tobias.
               What is the cauſe neghbure of youre ſorow, of youre ſyghtes, and of youre cō
                  playntes by the ſtrete?
            
            
               Timothe.
               It pityeth me that we pooremen ſe ſo

few enſamples of loue, and that of them which be our heardmen, and gwydes.
            
            
               Tobias.
               Why ſo good brother, what is the matter?
            
            
               Timotheus
               Yee knowe that oure neyghbure Lazarus is very ſyke, whoſe grefe hath endured longe. Inſomuche that his impacience greueth me.
            
            
               Tobias.
               It is trewe, I tolde his wife, I wolde come and viſite him to morowe, and teache him ſome good thynge of dyenge, for he myght dye ear longe. But what wyll ye tell me of hym?
            
            
               Thimotheus.
               I deſyred euen now oure new vicare for Chriſtes paſſion to come and viſite oure poore Lazarus once, and to teache hym ſome good thynge of pacience, wich he ought to haue in his paynes, But alas yt was ſonge to a defe man.
            
            
               Tobias.
               Is yt ſo? what dyd he laye for hymſelf?
            
            
               Timotheus.
               Yow maye thynke it welynough: what were they wonte to laye for them as they

were moued to ſuch a good dede? He ſaide, I muſt ſaye fyrſt my matins, &amp; then ſaye maſſe: Veryly I am not now at leaſure, but as ſoone as I am, I wyll come.
            
            
               Tobias.
               What is yt that I do heare? I hadde went he hadde ben a man accordinge to the goſpell: for he behaueth hymſelf ſo in the pulpet, that it is maruayl to me. But I ſe wellynough he is but a diſſemblinge hypocrite: For he was wont to ſaye in the pulpit, that noman ſhulde ſpare him yee he wolde ryſe yf yt were at mydnight.
            
            
               Timothe.
               I reken the ſame, but it ſhalbe for to myniſtre the ſacrament, or anoylynge, and to gayne therby ſōme mony. Els wyll he remeue not one fote.
            
            
               Tobias
               Yt is a maruelous caſe ſurly, for the mā doth reaſon ſomtyme of the goſpell as yf he were an angell.
            
            
               Timotheus.
               He doth as many one doth beſydes, he beareth the goſpell in his ſleue, and vtereth it with his mouth, but nother in his

hart, nor his handes.
            
            
               Tobias.
               It is to be lamented verely that we be ſo redy to vſe the lybertyes of meates, clothinges, places, &amp; tymes, whiche the goſpel enyoieth. But we endeuer not thys liberty to the mortifyenge of our carnall deſyres, nor to the ſeruyce of oure brother. But ſhal I tell you what you ought to haue done?
            
            
               Timothe.
               I praye you what?
            
            
               Tobias.
               You ſhulde haue ſtrenghted the deuociō of oure vicar with a groat, ſo might you haue optayned him beſt.
            
            
               Timothe.
               It is ſure ſo. And that appeared wel laſt daye by the aldermannes wedowe wheare as it was no nede to bid hym come whan ſhe laye ſyke, for wyth her was he dayly, yee vnbydden, waytinge for the ſoull as a carmeraunte doth for the carien: and all was to optayne ſomwhat by teſtament, Be theſe feders? be theſe paſtores.
            
            
               Tobias.
               
                  No but rather wolues, wherof Ezechiel ſpeketh ſaynge: They haue eatē the mylke of their floke, and with the woll they be clothed, but they kepe them not from the wolues. My thynketh they be diſſemblynge Hypocrites, and paynted graues, which wyth longe bablinge, or ſeruyce ſaynge deuoure wedows houſen: wherfore they ſhall receaue the greater damnation. I thynke alſo theſe be the falfe prophetes ſemynge outwardly ſhepe. But inwardly they be rauenous wolues.
            
            
               Timothe.
               Yf theſe preſtes (and as they call thēfelf) religiouſmen knewe what a chriſten dedeyt is to comfort the ſorowfull to viſite the ſyke, to helpe the poore. They ſhuld preferre the helpynge of them before all other workes. For God ſhall eſteme yt which is done to ye leaſt of his as tough it were done to hymſelfe. But preſtes do not regarde yt: for they ſaye they haue ben longe ynough wyth the ſyke, whan they haue miniſtred the ſacramentes.
            
            
               Tobias.
               
                  Yf they yett miniſtred the ſupper of oure Lorde to the ſyke dewly, teachynge the Chriſtians what Chriſt hath optayned for vs: than myght the pacient geue thankes to God of the victory, wherin he hath ouercome death to the beleuynge. For that is the ſaynge of Chriſt, whā he ſayth: As oft as ye do ytt, ye ſhall do ytt in the remembraunce of me, which is acordynge to Pauls ſaynge. Whan the death of oure Lorde is ſhewed. But alas they do nought now but onely rehearſe ye xii. artikles of the fayth ſleghtly to the ſyke. And ſo myniſter the ſacrament wythout farther inſtrucciō of yt, thynkynge all thynges to be very well diſpached. I praye God they haue not of tymes more mynde on the yewel which lyeth perchaunce in the ſyght, than on the neceſſite of the poore. Or that they mynde not more a good teſtament.
            
            
               Tobyas.
               They muſt be very blynde ſeynge, they make leſſe conſcience of leauynge the breade of the poore (that is Gods worke) onbroken: than of leauynge theyr maſſe matins, and other ſeruyce onſay
                     ••
                  e, ſeynge

it is hongred ſo ſoore for. The Chriſtēman which is the lyuinge tempel of God muſt ſtonde by, and abyde tyll the preſt hath diſpached his matyns, or vyſited the dead mens graues, hath he neuer ſo great nede. Yf Chriſt had the yongeman which wolde be his diſciple to luffre the dead bury the dead, and yt he ſhulde not leaue Goddes worde ondeclared for burieng: what ſhal he ſaye thē thinke yow to them which excuſe them ſelfs with theyr rummelynge, and mummelynge of matyns, euenſonge, and ſuch lyke popyſheneſſe that they viſyte not the ſyke, or ſhewe the kyngdome of God where troubell and anguyſhe is?
            
            
               Tobyas.
               Yt hath not auayleth the yonge man ſurely that he wolde haue buried yt dead: &amp; much leſſe ſhal it auayle thē yt be marked with the beaſtes marke to leaue theyr neghboure onſerued, and onregarded, Yee Chryſt hymſelf, and that with the dedes of charyte, which muſt be preferred before all the works of the lawe, and promes, acordynge as Chryſt ſayth that

he is Lorde of the Sabbath. We alſo ſhalbe iudged after the declarynge of the dedes of charyte towarde oure neghboure.
            
            
               Tymotheus.
               Yt is well ſayde ſurely, and accordynge to the goſpel. Chriſt alſo rebuked the ſcribes iuſtly for theyr opinion of ceremonies, commaundynge them to go, and learne what that ſaynge of God is: I wyll mercy and not ſacrifyce.
            
            
               Tobyas.
               How vnderſtonde you that ſaynge? will God haue no ſacrifice then which he him ſelf commaunded ſo earneſtly to de obſerued? here ſemeth Chriſt to be contrary to the wyll of hys father.
            
            
               Tymotheus.
               I wyll tel yow. All ſacryfices and burnt offerynges of the lawe were ordeyned, and inſtitute vnto the Iewes for none other intent, ſaue onely for theyr ſygnifycacions. They dyd ſygnifie the trew offerynge of Chriſt to come: which out of very pury heate of loue, dyd offer hymſelf vnto death, by ſheddynge of hys owne

bloude, for vs poore ſynners, and thus is he become oure trewe and euerlaſtinge preſt. Seynge then we haue Chriſt, al other offerynges ceaſſe: and now we are come to the lyght all other ſhadowes vaniſhe. For Chriſt is the ende and fulfillinge of the lawe, wherfore we nede nomor the lawe with hyr ceremonies, and ryghtweſnes as a teacher leadynge vs to Chriſt: yee he onely commeth to the father which hath herd him, and is taught of hym. For ſo much then as the Phariſes dyd regarde, and had confydence more in ſacrifyces, and workes of ye lawe than they hadde reſpecte to hym yt was ſygnyfyed therby, whoſe dedes of charite alſo they counted leſſe then the ryghtwyſnes of the lawe: therfore warneth Chriſt them to learne, that God wyll haue mercy and no ſacrifyce, which he dyd lothe as Eſay doth clearly expreſſe.
            
            
               Tobyas.
               You haue declared that very well. But what ſaye ye to this worde of Chriſt. Theſe ought to haue bene done, and not leaue the other vndone? for oure preſtes and

lawers vnderſtonde hereby, that they may rather leaue the workes of mercy vndone, than to leaue their mattens, pattens, maſſes, diriges, and ſuch other mū
                  blinges vnſayde.
            
            
               Tymotheus.
               With this ſaynge rebuked Chriſt the Scribes, and Phariſes which at that tyme eſtymed theyr ſacryfices, feaſtes, tythes, and offeringes, as hygly: as oure Papiſtes counte maſſes, ſaynge of ſeruice, worſhippinge of ſayntes for the mooſt acceptable workes. The tythes were lymited vnto the preſtes of the olde lawe and graunted of God in the lawe: but ſeynge they ſought theyr deuty ſo narowly not wyllynge to tranſgreſſe the lawe in the ſame tythinge of mynt, comin, and anyſe, they declared theyr couetouſnes, and fayned loue of the lawe. For in that parte of the lawe (wherin theyr auauntage dyd conſiſte) they wolde haue no breache, but in other chefe pointes of the lawe, namely where they were comman̄
                  ded by the lawe to offer them ſelues to the ſeruyce of theyr neghboure, they were

as negligent as though it had not pertayned to them. Therfore ſayeth Chryſt: Wo vnto yow Scrybes, and Phariſes, ye ypocrytes, which tyth mynte, anyſe and comyn, and leaue the wayghtyer matters of the law behynde: namely iudgment, mercy, and fayth. Theſe ought to haue bene done, and not to leaue the other behynde, that is, So longe as the lawe hath her courſe (as yet ſhe hath) ſo longe ye maye receaue your dewty of ye tythes, yee of anyſe, mynte, and comyn: but the dedes of fayth, loue, and mercy which ye lawe requyreth of you as chefeſt maye you not leaue vndone, but rather do them afore all other. Beholde now we ther thys rebuke (which oure ſpyritualty applyeth to theyr excuſation) doth aptly ſerue to warne and to rebuke them: Seynge they be curſed with the aforeſade ypocrytes curſe. For they curſe and yaule more vpon them in theyr pulpet, that withdraw them theyr offerynge dayes, or prouent dewtyes (which notwithſtondynge God hath not graunted them in ye new teſtament, as he dyd in ye olde wyth

the tythes:) than they curſe thoſe that tranſgreſſe Gods commaundement in aduoutry, in dronkneſſe, and onmercyfulneſſe.
So that they maye well be lykened vnto the oxe in the prophet which go in the paſtures of Samaria, and eate vp the poore. Theſe be the prophetes which deceaue the people▪ ſhewynge peace, and bytynge with theyr teth, in whoſe mouth yf ye caſt not a pece of meate they rayſe an holy warre agaynſt yow, that is. They ſaye ye be a curſed heretyke, and that ye ought to be perſecuted, and to be condemned. As though ſuch warre and controuerſye were acceptable vnto God. Therfore (ſayeth the prophet Micheas) your viſion ſhalbe turned to nyght▪ &amp; your prophecienge to darkneſſe the ſonne that go vnder ouer theſe prophetes. But thy people of God 
                     •
                   ſaue you forgeue you your ſynnes, &amp; ſaye ye proſper ryght well, they deceaue you: for there is no ſaluacion in man. Theſe ye 
                     〈…〉
                   deuoure medowes houſes which in their 
                     〈◊〉
                   mawes 
                     ••••
                  rgeſt al that cometh to them, golde, many▪ houſe
                     •
                   gardens

londe, ſonde, rentes, grauntes, pardons Theſe be they that iuſtify the vngodly for gyftes denuncynge peace, and all is for theyr belys pleaſure.
            
            
               Tobyas.
               Soft brother Tymothe, conceaue not ſuch rācour agaynſt the wicked, ſeynge theyr iudgment doth not tary: let them go. They be blinde and leaders of ye blinde. We maye endeuoure vs to exhorte thē to come to the knowledge of God, &amp; to the loue of theyr neghboure, yf peraduenture they wolde geue eare to vs, and knowledge theyr ſynnes.
            
            
               Tymotheus.
               I praye the how wilt thou exhorte them? ſeynge they ſaye to the ſeinge, ſe not: &amp; to the vnderſtōdinge, perceaue not: yf they knoledged theyr blyndneſſe, they ſhulde haue no ſynne (as Chriſt ſaieth). But now they ſaye, we ſe: wherfore theyr ſynne remayneth with them. As namely whan we laymen begynne to exhorte theſe anoynted: laynge ſcripture afore them then will they heare by no meanes, takynge great ſcourne to be admoniſhed

of vs.
            
            
               Tobyas.
               Surely I beleue yt be euell ynough, whearfore me ſemeth it beſt for vs to walke henſforth in the waye of the Lorde diſcretely.
            
            
               Tymotheus.
               Yow ſaye ſouth, Yf we can do better than oure curates do, ſeynge they be ſlak in theyr dewty ſhall we not do the ſame? For a ſeruaunt that knoweth hys mayſters wyll, and doth yt not, ſhal be beaten much. What is then your aduyſe, that we ſhall do?
            
            
               Tobyas.
               Verely, that oure eye be not ſo ſore fyxed vpon another mans faulte, but endeuoured to folowe the Lorde, wherunto he calleth vs by a lyuely ſterynge of our hart wt hys ſprete. Now yf oure guydes of the churche do not rule wel the flocke (as ye do ſaye), yet wyll not we leaue them, and forſake them as though they were not pertaynynge vnto vs. For God hath charged euery man with hys neghboure as ſcrypture teſtyfyeth. Therfore let vs ayde oure neghboure comforte hym, counſell hym, as we ſe hys mooſt

nede. Thynke ye not thys to be the beſt brother. Tymothe?
            
            
               Tymotheus.
               Ye verely. And to this doth the parable of the goſpell featly agre, where the Samaritan (which is an abiecte in the ſight of the Iewes) is prayſed of Chryſt aboue the Leuyte or Preſt, becauſe he ſhewed mercy vpon the poore mamed: which alſo was therfore the Samaritans neghboure, becauſe he cheſfly had nede of him Although we laymen be reputed amonge the anoynted, and Leuytes as vyle as the Samarytans: yet ought we neuertheleſſe take cure of the poore, and ſhew all the ſeruyce neceſſary, whan all Leuytes, Preſtes, Monkes, Freres, do forſake, and deſpyſe them. The dedes of charyte ought we to charge none other mā withal accordynge to youre ſayenge.
            
            
               Tobyas.
               Now is the tyme that we ought to dyſperſe the grace which god hath geuen, vs, and poure yt out vpon oure neghboure in helpinge, comfortynge, and unſelynge hym. As Chriſt hath geuen

hymſelf for vs, he beynge in fourme of God, and equall with God. Yt is now tyme to beſtowe oure talent which God hath geuē vs to the intent that we ſhuld brynge it agayne with increace, and not to hyde yt in the grounde. He that is ryche ought to make the poore ryche alſo, for to that intent hath he receaued his cheſſe. He that is wyſe ought to teache the folyſſhe, and to brynge hym to vnderſtondynge, for to ſuch intente hath he receaued hys wyſdome. He that is great of abylite ought to ayde hym▪ that is vnabell, as the wedowe, fatherleſſe and motherleſſe, boninfances, for to that intent hath God geuen hym ſuperiote. Lo in ſuch lyke caſes ought we the one to be an helper, comforter, ſauioure, to ye other as oure fayth is that Chriſt is oure ſauioure, comforte, and health. Therfore alſo doth Chriſt commaunde that we ſhall ſo ſhewe the lyght of oure fayth before men, that they ſeinge oure good workes, maye prayſe and glorifye the father which hath geuen ſuch mynde▪ and godli purpoſe in our hartes, through his

holy gooſt: that is that we be gladde to ſerue oure neyghboure not for thankes, nor for prayſe, but of very loue. For who ſo euer ſeyth hys brother in neceſſite, and withdraweth hys hart from hym, how can the loue of God remayne in hym.
            
            
               Tymotheus.
               He that loueth not his brother beynge preſent in hys ſyght: how can he loue God whom he ſeyth not. We Chriſten men haue none other declaracion or boaſtinge that we be trew Chriſtians, but onely loue. Chriſt ſayeth: In that ſhall men knowe that ye be my diſciples yf ye loue one another. Wherfore the lyfe of a Chriſtian is not a lyfe of pleaſure, offleſhe, of wylthyneſſe, or of ſenſuall ap, petyte. Nor it is no lyfe of ceremonies: church goynges, or lyke ſuperſticions but it is a lyfe of the ſprete, of treuth, of loue and mercy, yt is a lyfe of mortifyed luſtes, and peace of the ſprete in God onely.
            
            
               Tobyas.
               That is the eternall Sabbath, and holy daye, which is left to goddes people,

which alſo they muſt kepe perpetually by the layenge down of theyr owne luſtes, and ſenſualyte, but all the trouble, labour, carefulneſſe, and bodely ſeruyce, outwardly done with wordes, or dede ought to be redreſſed to nothinge els but to ye glory of God and to the profyte of oure neghboure: for els is not God oure kynge, and we do not ſeke the welth of oure neghboure then, but oure owne, which is agaynſt the nature of the trewe &amp; onfayned loue which Paul teacheth.
            
            
               Tymotheus.
               Ye ſaye treuth, for though we haue the name of Chriſt, and though we be baptyſed ī the ſame, though we go to church and receaue the ſacramētes, yet are not all thynges dyſpached wythout fayth, by workinge in vs with charite: For they all that ſay Lorde, Lorde, ſhall not poſſeſſe the kyngdome of heauen, but onely they that fulfill the wyll of the father ſhall go in to the kyngdome of heauen.
            
            
               Tobyas.
               The one membre ought thus to helpe the other, orels are not we one body gathered,

wherof Chriſt is the heade. Let vs therfor beare echother in declarynge brotherly loue that we be incorporate one body in Chriſt, aydinge the vyleſt, &amp; leaſt before all other. For that which we do to the leaſt, of oure brethren yt haue we done to Chriſt. Chriſt is euen now ſufferinge honger, thyrſt, he is naked, in preſone, he is harbourleſſe, he is like and dyſeaſed, let vs go to hym to ſerue hym, to comforte hym, to receaue hym, that we maye heare herafter: Come ye bleſſed of my father to poſſeſſe the kingdom which is prepared for you ſence the begynnynge of the worlde. And treuly ryght welbeloued Tymothe ſeynge we be called goſpellyſhe or Euangelycall, therfore ought we to be the more diligent in doynge Euangelicall workes, leſt Gods worde be blamed trough oure vnruly be haue our of thē yt be vngodly. ¶Tymo. Ye ſaye treuth: wherfore I wolde that in euery towne, cyte, village, yee in euery cō
                  gregaciō or church there were a comune huche or cheſte wherin ſhulde be ſeperate ſuch goods as be geuē to the nedy acordynge

as ſaynte Paul teacheth in the i. Corinth. xvi. which now (alas for pyte) is rather myſpent in foundacions of chappels, churches, &amp; religyous houſes as they call them, in ſyngers, in coapes, belles, and ymages. I wyll not ſpeake now of the greate prouentes, and rētes, of vycaries, and ſuch other foundacions which mount to an innumerable ſumme yearly. With theſe goodes, and ſuch lyke that oure forefathers haue founded to the ſuſtayninge of the poore maye euery towne, cyte, vyllage, or paryſhe eaſely ſuſtayne theyr owne poore people: ſo that ther ſhulde not one begger or vagabounde nede to go by the ſtretes. And thus ſhulde gods commaundemēt Deuteronomy .xv. chapter be accomplyſſhed Morouer to this excellent dede ſhulde be choſen certayn honeſt men, fearynge God, which lyke trew deacons ſhulde diſpenſe, and dyſtribute theſe goodes accordyng the nede and conſcience. Out of this aforeſayed cheſte alſo ſhuld ſcoules be founded, wherin youth might be taught both Chriſt &amp; other good learnīg

For ſuch we comūly do ſauoure as was putt in oure freſſhe veſſels. Out of this cheſte alſo ſhulde all bonynfans, or fatherleſſe and motherleſſe chyldren be brought vp, vntyll they be abell to learn an occupatiō or craft. Out of this cheſte ſhulde honeſte youthe be maryed, leſt through pouerty they com to ſome myſuſe. For to brynge all this to effecte the afore ſayde goodes be ſufficient yf they were iuſtly and treuly gathered together. The bagge and ſtaffe, is an occaſyon that there is ſo much ydelneſſe, whordome, dronkneſſe, thefte, yee of all myſchefe, and euell maners it is the mother, whiche the aforeſayde congregations myght eaſely auoyde yf the loue of honeſty, and mercy were fyred in theyr hartes.
            
            
               Tobyas.
               Youre mynde welbeloued brother is good, yf it were ſo accepted, and fulfylled, than wolde I alſo prayſe yt wyth yow: But theſe ſtrōge, &amp; valiaunt wallet knyghtes wyl neuer admitte yt, for theyr religion is founded vpon theſame, &amp; the

ſorowleſſe breade ſauoureth to well in their mouthes. They loue much better to reape the harueſt that they haue not ſowē, that to get theyr owne foode, with the ſweate of their browes.
            
            
               Timotheus.
               We haue now cōplayned ynough, wherfore I wyll ſtraghtly go to oure poore Lazarus, &amp; teache hym ſome good thynge of ſufferynge paciently for he hath greate nede of it. And from thence wyll I go to the hoſpitall, to bringe thether yt which I haue ſuperfluous of my yeſterdayes laboure: For I am ſure they ſhall nede it there.
            
            
               Tobias.
               I praye you brother let yt be ſo, and let
                     •
                   yt not greue you to viſet ye ſyke, for thereby ſhall ye be ſtrenghted in the fayth accordinge to the ſcripture. But differ youre goinge to Lazarus a lytell whyle, yf perchaunce oure vicar come there, he ſhall not leaue it for very ſhame.
            
            
               Timothe.
               No no I knowe him to well, he wolde rather neuer come at hym, than to leſe one peny of his other auauntage, which of

thys poore mā he can not haue. He ſpeaketh much of the cure of ſoules, but it ſemeth that hys mynde is of the purſes ſoules: he beſemeth all the reſte. Wherfore I wyll thether warde, wyl ye cōmaū
                  de me ought?
            
            
               Tobias.
               Yee tell Lazarus that I wyll come to vyſet hym tomorowe afore noone, and teache hym ſomwhat of dyenge, as I haue promyſed hys wyfe.
            
            
               Timothe.
               I wyll do yt wyth a good wyll, &amp; God graunte vs hys mercy.
            
         
         
            A declaration and exhortacion to ſuffer all troubell paciently &amp; fayth fully, wether yt be anguiſhe, or ſykneſſe, which doubtleſſe be ſent vs of oure mercifull father.
            ¶Timothe vyſitinge ye poore mā Lazarꝰ lyenge ſyke in his bedde, ſayeth thus to him.
            
               Timothe.
               Peace be in thys houſe.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Who commeth in there?
            
            
               
               Timothe.
               Yt is I Timothe youre neighbure, how is it with you? is all thynges well?
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Alas no it is not well, for I lye here and can nether moue nor wrēche my ſelf, my yointes be ſo full of ſykneſſe and payne.
            
            
               Timothe.
               I beleue yt ryght well, for you haue had a greate tyme: but how cā ye quiete your ſelf therin?
            
            
               Lazarus.
               How ſhulde I quiete my ſelf? I wolde I were deade ſuch payne. I am in, Amy
            
            
               Timothe,
               I praye you neyghbure vexe not yourſelf ſo much with this ſykneſſe, for treuly yt is not Chriſtenly.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               It is eaſy for you to ſpeake of yt. For noman halteth of another bodies grefe. Yf you dyd lye in ſuch paynes as I do, you wolde ſaye otherwyſe.
            
            
               Timothe.
               Ye be farre wyde from Lazarus ſufferire ſo farre as I can ſe, whoſe name you haue, whiche toke his grefe paciently,

and without grudginge agaynſt God yt he myght not optayne the crommes frō the rychmans tabell, &amp; that he was fayne to lye vnder the broade open ſkye, his body beynge full of ſores and payn, and fynally to dye for very honger, for which thynge alſo he was brought in Abrahās boſome by the angels. But you haue an houſe to dwell in, ye haue yet God be thanked meate &amp; drynke: you haue good neghbours yt wold fayne cōforte you, &amp; helpe to beare youre grefe which Lazarus hadde not, Neuertheleſſe he was alwaye content, and ſo ought ye to be alſo.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Becauſe I am none ſuch as he was, therfore ſhall not I alſo be ſet vpon altars, &amp; haue an holy daye kepte for my as is done for hym.
            
            
               Timothe.
               Alas brother Lazare you be yet farre frō the kyngdom of heauen, ſeynge ye ſuffer youre grefe wt ſo euell a wyll you ought to remember that it is the good wyll of God that ye thus ſuffre: is it not al good that commeth of hym? be content therfore wyth his godly will, and youre burthen

ſhall fall the lichter for you.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               I muſt nedes be content the rewith for I can not remedy yt, nor yet auoyde it.
            
            
               Timothe.
               Although you coulde remedy it agaynſt gods wyll wolde ye do it? I thynke not: for you wolde not wreſtle with the wyll of God.
            
            
               Lazarus
               I ſhall tell you the very treuth, yf I coulde be red of this payne, I wold not kepe it one houre longer.
            
            
               Timothe.
               Wolde ye then rather be an enemy of God, than to ſuffre a lytle for hys ſake?
            
            
               Lazarus.
               I can tell you nothinge els but that I wolde fayne be ryd of this paſſion, for yt is to heuy for me.
            
            
               Timothe.
               So longe as ye ſuffre of compulſion &amp; not wyllingly, than do ye leſe youre rewarde of ſufferinge: &amp; ye ſtryue agaynſt God lyke a rebellious childe that diſobayeth his louynge father.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               I muſt ſuffre be yt wyllingly or not wyllyngly.
            
            
               Timothe.
               
                  Ye ſuffre grefe and payne but without deſeruynge for yt, and therfore the more one a flyer: for ye ſuffer onwyllingly &amp; vnfaithfully, ye ſuffer of cōpulſion euē as a ſeruaunt ſtondeth in awe of hys mayſter by yt reaſon of his rod or wande that he caſtiſeth hym withall, A ſeruaunt remayneth not is his mayſters houſe, but muſt voyde Ihon in the .viii. Chapter: But ye ſonne remayneth as a trew eyre. Yf ye now therfore were a ſonne of ye heauenly father: ye wolde receaue this correction of his wyllingly, and with trewe loue in a ſure fayth, and vnderſtonde yt to be his loue towarde yow: ſeynge he cā ſende to his chyldrē nothinge but ye beſt, nor ꝓcure ought els for thē but good.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               This ſoundeth very ſtraunge in myne ears, that God puniſheth me thus greuely of very loue, &amp; ſendeth me this for ye beſt gifte that he can geue me, I wolde rather thynke yt to be a horſly loue.
            
            
               Timothe.
               Alas brother how fearcely do you runne agaynſt the ſtone that is Chriſt? How

ſtraunge be Gods worde and workes for you to heare and vnderſtonde? mans wyt can not attayne yt that is ſpoken of God, The worde of God is as it were an hāmer that bruſeth the ſtones: Therfore muſt ye ſubmitte and captiue youre wyt and mans wyſdome wholy, tyll yt be clene preſoned and ſubdued to the wyll of Chriſt and pacifie yt ſelf in hym: afore ye can perceaue how great good &amp; mercy ye inwarde mā receaueth in depreſſinge &amp; mortifynge ye outwarde carcaſe.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               O Timothe youre wordes be to hyghe &amp; pythie for myn vnderſtōdīg, my memory &amp; wyt is greatly ſwaged wt this ſykneſſe of myn: wherfore you muſt ordre you otherwyſe yf I ſhall learne ought of you.
            
            
               Timothe.
               Yf ye hūger Gods worde &amp; can ſatle you ſo yt ye may heare yt, I wyll ſo ſhewe yt yow yt ye ſhall eaſely perceaue yt of me.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Yee verely and that gladly, reache my another cuſſyne and laye yt to my backe for gods ſake, that I maye ſyt eaſlyer to

heare, and anſwere you.
            
            
               Timothe.
               Are ye well ſo? or wyll ye ſyt hygher?
            
            
               Lazarus.
               No, I ſyt now eaſly &amp; I can not wel ſuffre much toſſinge and wrenchinge, My tonge is the wholeſt and lythyeſt of all my membres: beginne whan ye pleaſe.
            
            
               Timothe.
               That I may ſhewe you ye better ye meanynge of myne aforeſaide wordes I wil rote out youre infidelite, and ſhew you it afore youre eyes, that ye maye ſe how farre a man is ſeparate frō God trough hys infidelite: out of the which all other ſynnes do ſprynge as braunches and twigges out of an euel roote. For infidelite is ye chefe ſynne wherof ye holy gooſt ſhall iudge the worlde, as Chriſt ſayeth Ihō. xvi. Therfore is thys now my queſtion wether ye do vſe to rede youre pater noſter.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               What a queſtion is that? thynke you I be a Turke ſhulde not I rede my pater noſter?
            
            
               Timothe.
               How rede you yt in latin, or engly ſhe?
            
            
               
               Lazarus.
               I rede yt as I haue learnt yt of my father: pater noſter qui es.
            
            
               Timothe.
               Ye ought to rede it in englyſhe that ye maye vnderſtonde it the better, ſeynge ye can no latin. Tell my then that I ſhall axe of you yf ye pleaſe: Beleue ye wel ye fyrſt worde Pater, that is father?
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Shulde I not beleue that? Chriſt hymſelf hath taught vs ſo to praye.
            
            
               Timothe.
               If ye beleue God to be youre father, thā muſt you beleue youre ſelf alſo to be his ſonne and eyre, els ye diſſemble praynge contrary to youre harte and not iuſtly. Seynge then ye call hym youre father, (with which louely name you admoniſh hym to heare you his ſonne) and you haue not ſuch a lyuely perceauynge of hym as a good chylde ought for to haue: than ſaye you youre Pater noſter wythout fayth.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Without fayth? how ſo? what is fayth?
            
            
               Timothe.
               
                  Fayth is a gyft of God, which is not geuen to euery man, without which Romā is acceptable to God.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Haue not all Chriſten men fayth then?
            
            
               Timothe.
               There is two ſortes of Chriſtē mē, lyke as there is two ſortes of chyldren of Iſrael: ſome be Iſraelites after the fleſhe, ſome by promeſſe: euen ſo be ſome Chriſtē mē by name, ſome by ye dede by reaſon they be gyfted with the beleuynge ſprete of Chriſt. Theſe chriſtians haue al faith.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               What is ye faith than, wherby we Chriſten men be called beleuynge?
            
            
               Tymothe.
               Fayth is a ſure and lyuely felynge in oure hart that we be acceptable vnto the father, and that he is mercyfull vnto vs thorowe his ſōne Ieſu Chriſt, in al what ſoeuer can betyde vs, or that we do, wether it be in lyfe or death. This fayth is better perceaued inwardly of them that beleue treuly than it can wel be expreſſed outwardly.
            
            
               
               Lazarus.
               Is it a hydde myſtery? can not I perceaue inwardly by no token whether I haue fayth or not?
            
            
               Timothe,
               Yes verely I ſhal declare that vnto you by a ſymilitude or enſample: A chylde hath no perceauynge inwarde, nor ſheweth outwardly ony behaueoure wether he haue a ſure confidence towarde his father or not, vnto the tyme he is aſſayd in thys hyd fayth: But whā this chylde is ether beatē or miſdealt of a ſtraūger, thā lyfteth he is voyce in hys anguyſſhe, preaſſinge to his father through the myddes of his enemyes with a ſure fayth &amp; cōfidence to be delyuered and ſaued. Yee in his flyght &amp; haſtynge for reſcue which he ſhall ſurely optayne there, his mynde is certified that he ſhall be reſcued, and this is a greate quietneſſe of conſcience, and a ſpeciall eaſe at hys hart that hys enymyes ſhall nomore reioyce ouer him. After thys maner alſo is the matter wyth the chyldren of God: Oure heauenly Father hath geuen vs power to

be yu children of God, &amp; that through beleuynge in his name, which by the fathers commaundement is become man for vs, and hath choſen vs to be eyres wt him. Now we belyuinge this and knoleginge yt through the ſprete of trueth we wayte for all ayde, comforte, and ſubſidie of oure heauēly father, in what ſo euer temtacion can aſſault vs. So that yt is ſure token and ſpecialte that we be in the fauoure of God yf we abyde ſtedfaſt in prayſinge the name of God, and reioyce inwardly whā we be in troubel or anguiſhe, though God ſeme to haue vtterly forſaken vs. Here lo muſt the Chriſten faith fyrſt apeare. The ſauegarde &amp; quietnes of conſcience which we haue inwardly in the myddes of troubell, is a frute of the holy gooſt, ſuſtaynynge vs leſt we fall into myſbeleue or blaſpheminge of God, ye which oure puniſhmēt myght cauſe ryghtwell. Wherfore we nede not to ſhrēke or to drede our Lorde God whan he ſtryketh vs, as a ſeruaunt doth feare &amp; auoyde his maſter. For God nother cā be, nor is a ſcourger or tyrant

vnto his children. It is oure dewty to reyoice in him, and to prayſe hym in al his godly workes, knowenge that he is oure ſauegarde in the daye of troubell. Paul wrytinge to the Romanes in the .viii. chap. ſayeth: We haue not now receaued the ſprete of bondage to feare ony more: but we haue receaued the ſprete of adoption, wherby we call Abba, deare father wt a luſty corage &amp; a ſure faith. For ye ſprete of God which worketh ſuch faith in vs geueth wytneſſe vnto oure ſprete that we be the children of God. Seynge then we be the childrē of God, oure mercyfull father hath ſuch a delyte in vs as in his welbeloued children. So yt where the mooſt feare and yeopardy is, there is he mooſt neareſt preſent. It is ſurely the nature of a good father to be more feruē
                  ter in loue towarde hys children, where the mooſt nede is. Now whan ye conſydre this diligently, with a hartyfull luſt towarde God the father: than maye you beleue, and ſay truely that God is youre heauēly father, yf not, you ſay your Pater noſter faynedly, as al other ypocrites

do, whoſe hart is farre from their mouth although ye ſayde youre Pater noſter a thouſande tymes.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Is this the ſayenge of Pater noſter, thā dyd I neuer ſaye yt dewly in all my lyfe. I haue oft ſayde the .xii. artikles of oure fayth after the preſt in the pulpet: But I coulde neuer heare ſo much concerninge the pyth of them as I haue done now.
            
            
               Timothe.
               Such hyſtoricall fayth as ye be taught in the pulpet haue ye deuels alſo, for they beleue that God is almyghty, that ye ſonne of God is become man, that he is crucified and ryſen agayn, but they beleue not that he is ordeyneth to their ſaluacion. The deuell beleueth and trembleth: but a Chriſten man beleueth and reioceth in it. The fayth or knoleginge of the deuyls which they haue of God cauſeth them to feare and tremble: but oure fayth cauſeth vs to reioyce and be gladde in God, whom we knoledge euer to be oure father.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               
                  If he be our father why ſendeth he ſuch greueous paynes to vs then?
            
            
               Timothe.
               Youre aforeſayde fayth muſt be tryed trough ſufferynge, ſykneſſe, and aduerſite, as yt is written: That we ſhall not maruayll nether be moued that we be tryed trough the fyre of ſufferynge, for yt is done to proue vs. The lorde proueth al the electes after this maner, that their fayth may be founde 
                     •
                  ore precious than the golde that is tried through the fyre. And the ende of oure fayth whiche is not anulled, is the health of our ſoul. Wherfore as ye beleue that God is youre mercifull father: euen ſo muſt ye beleue alſo. and by fayth be aſſured, that all that be tydeth you, is hys fatherly wil and pleaſure. Thynke not that hys eyen be wythdrawen from vs, for ſo greatly are we accepted before him that he ſayeth. Whoſo toucheth you, toucheth the very appell of myn eye. Yee we be ſo earneſtly and tenderly, cared for and kepte of God oure heauenly father, that there is not the leaſt he
                     •
                  r of our heade but yt ys

tolde: no a ſparowe doth not fall on the groūde without the conſent of oure heauenly father. How much leſſe can thys ſykneſſe come vpon you without the conſent of the heauenly father, which hath ſanctified all troubell and ſufferinges: By the croſſe and humblinge dyd yt pleaſe God to exalte and glorify his owne ſonne. He yt dyd take care &amp; thought for you before ye were borne: ſhall lykwyſe prouyde for you beynge here: ſeynge he wolde you to be here. Wherfore all thoſe that ſuffre accordinge the wyll of God, ought to cōmitte the charge of their ſoules vnto the good creator of all creatures: in whoſe handes we are, as the claye is in the potters hande. Praye therfore vnto the father with youre whole hart, that his name maye be halowed in you, lyke as it is halowed and glorified thorow ye death and depreſſion of his ſonne But as for oure name it is full of diſhoneſty, ſhame &amp; dānacion.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               By the meaninge of youre wordes I perceaue yt not nedefull for me to deſyre

theſe paynes of myne to be auoyded: and to be healed other in ſoule, or body.
            
            
               Timothe.
               I coulde ſhewe you welinough that this praynge doth come nother of the ſprete of God, nor yet out of fayth, but of proper loue, which ſeketh rather hir owne eaſe and profite, than the glory of God: But I feare leſt it wolde be to tedious for you, &amp; alſo I reken ye can not wel ſuffre many more wordes.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               No hardly, it ſhall not be tedious vnto me, for euen now haue I a great deſyre to it, wherfore ſhewe me why I may not pray ſo?
            
            
               Timothe.
               A trew fayth wyll not cauſe you to praye ſo, for it is certified alwaye of the good will of God what ſo euer doth chaunche: All that is not of fayth is ſynne (ſayth Paule). Searche the grounde of youre harte, and ye ſhall perceaue that ye deſyre to be healed for none other cauſe, but only to be at eaſe. Therfore, ſeyng

that through this wyked nature ye ſet more pryce by youre ſelf than by God: ye had leuer youre ſenſualyte and wyll were accomplyſſhed in optayning of health than that God in this ſykneſſe ſhulde do in you, and with you accordinge to hys pleaſure. Wherfore I praye you what els do ye but rebelle agaynſt God, &amp; correke him in his iudgmēt, becauſe he worketh not accordynge your ymaginacion Where is youre pater noſter? do not ye praye and ſaye: Father thy wyll be fulfylled in earth as it is in heauen, that is in the earthy bodye, as it is in the ſoule which is an heauenly body. How lytell doye reſt hetherto in the workes of God? Heare how fully the kyngly prophet Dauid was mortifyed entyerly, and near in exceſſe of mynde, vpon all yt which God wolde ſende hym, he beynge dryuen out of his kyngdome by his owne beloued ſone Abſalon dyd ſaye: Yf I ſhal fynde grace before the Lorde, he ſhall fetch me agayne, and let my ſe it againe (meanynge the arke) and the houſe of it. But yf he ſaye thus: I haue no pleaſure in the

beholde, here am I let hym do with me as yt pleaſeth hym. Here was a mortifyed ſprete, which kept the trew Sabbath, that is the euerlaſtynge reſtynge daye, from this be ye farre wyde for all youre prayenge, and flatterynge.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               What good can I optayne by this wrechedneſſe, wherfore I ſhulde not deſyre to be ryd of it.
            
            
               Tymoth
                     •
                  us.
               It is ſtyll the olde trade, ye wyll not ſuffre but for auauntage, ye wyll vſe batterynge with God. God wyll haue no marchauntes, nor exchaungers in hys holy temple wherin he reſteth, as ye ſhall heare more herafter, yf we reaſon larger. As concerninge the good which we optayne by ſufferinge, we muſt vnderſtonde that God hatheth ſynne in that he ſēdeth mercy, and loue to hys chyldren, whych he doth chaſtyſe. Whan ye praye God than to take awaye thys chaſtenynge from you than be not ye content, that he ſhall ſhewe thys hys ryghtwyſnes in you: and herein ye declare, and vtter you to

be a frende of ſynne, and enemy to the ryghtuouſnes of God. Be not you very blynde and peruerſe harted, louynge thē that hate you, and hatynge thoſe that loue you. To that intēt ſendeth God payne anguyſſhe, yee and death vnto vs, that the body of ſynne and death ſhulde be roted out in ſufferynge, and ſlayenge of the olde Adam with all hys carnall concupiſcences and deſyres. This worke wyll not ye to procede in you, which notwithſtondinge muſt be accomplyſſhed yf we wyll be acceptable before God. Paule ſayeth. Knowe ye not, that all we which are baptyſed in to Chriſte Ieſu, are baptyſed in to his death? The chyldren of Iſrael myght not optayne the londe of promes, excepte they fyrſt hadde paſſed the reed ſee: Euen ſo we alſo muſt come to the hyghe Ieruſalem through paſſinge the reede ſee, that is troubell and ſykneſſe. For this cauſe we muſt cleue to the faythfull wordes of God as the Iſraelytes dyd: which beynge oppreſt, before of the read ſee, and behynde of Pharaos army, ſo that death was at hande wither

ſoeuer they turned theyr ſyght. Wherfore Moſes comforted them biddynge not to doubte in Gods beheſtes ſaynge: Feare you not, ſtond ſtyll, and beholde what a ſaluacion the Lorde ſhall ſhewe vpon you this daye. Thus haue they wentured it vpō Gods worde, &amp; paſſed through the read ſee wythout blemyſſhe. Be ye alſo a trew Iſraelyte goynge thorow thys ſufferynge with a ſure fayth, and ye ſhal ſurely be delyuered of i
                     •
                   with a valiaunt power: For he is faythfull that hath ſo promyſed you. Ceaſſe of your owne wyl, and deſpyſe not that which commeth of God. Whan the waters of troubell ſometyme be to greueous vpō you, ſo that thorow them ye begynne to waxe feble: than praye the heauenly father to geue you your daylye breade, ſtrenghtynge you with hys holſome worde, wherby your ſoule muſt be ſuſtayned.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               But brother this payne endureth to longe, for my thynketh it wyll neuer haue an ende. It hath ſo his recourſe.
            
            
               Tymotheus.
               
                  Be not moued at that, for Chriſt hymſelf dyd ſuffre before he came in to hys glory Is than a diſciple greater than hys mayſter? is a ſeruaunt aboue hys Lorde? Yf ther hadde bene another way to come to the trew glory and lyfe, Chriſt wolde haue rather choſen it: but now hath he fyrſt trodden and choſen thys waye of ſufferynge hymſelf that we ſhulde folow hym in yt. Lo thys is to take vp the croſſe of Chriſt, and to folowe hym, dayly to be mocked, deſpiſed, depreſſed, lyke as he hath boren his croſſe with all deſpyſyng, payne, and reuylinge. We be crucifyed with Chriſt whan we mortifye oure pleaſures and affections, which ought to be durynge oure lyfe. Now yf we be equall wyth Chryſt in ſufferynge, and dyenge: whe ſhall alſo be equall wyth hym in reioycynge, and ryſinge to ye new lyfe. Certifyed, that oure olde man is crucifyed with hym, to the intent the body of ſynne ſhulde be deſtroyed. Yf we then be dead with Chriſt, we beleue that we ſhall alſo lyue with hym. Paul ſayeth Roman. vi.. For a grane of corne caſt in

to the grounde can not brynge forth frute hūdreth folde, without it be mortifyed fyrſt, and auoyded his harde huſke: euen ſo we alſo beynge here in earth muſt firſt dye and refuſe the corrupcion of oure fleſſhe, yf we wyll lyue with Chriſt, and brynge forth frutes of lyfe. For this cauſe is the lyfe of a Chriſtian here in earth counted to be nothynge els (nor is none other) ſaue a continual croſſe, death, and deynge as Paul doth ſpecifie .ii. Cor. ix. ſaynge: That we which lyue are alwayes delyuered vnto death for Ieſus ſake, that the lyfe alſo of Ieſus myght appeare in oure mortall fleſſhe: for as longe as we lyue, we are delyuered vnto death for Ieſus ſake, that the lyfe of Chryſt be declared in oure mortall body. Dauyd alſo ſayeth: For thy ſake we are kylled all the daye longe, and are counted as ſhepe appoynted to be ſlayne. Yf ye wyll ſaye thys trewly wyth Dauyd, then muſt you be content with your punyſſhement, yee vntyll the death as the ſhepe is, which openeth not his mouth in ye ſlaghting. I praye you how can ye deſire

God to take from you this payne, yf ye beleue ſurely yt although your outwarde mā be corrupte and peryſſhe: yet your inwarde man is renewed daye by day. Paule ſayeth that this troubell, and ſufferynge (which laſteth but ye tuynklyng of an eye in comparyſon of the glory for to come) prepareth maruaylouſly for vs the eternall glory: yf we haue not oure ſyght fyxed vpon yt which is viſible, but vpon that which is inuyſyble and euerlaſtynge: yee all that we can ſuffre here in this tranſytory worlde is not to be cō
                  pared vnto the glory which ſhalbe declared in vs. By thys ye perceaue that all thoſe which ſuffre wt a ſure fayth, ought alſo to reioyce in theyr troubell, euen as Paule and other electes haue done.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Me thynketh ye preaſſe the meteyarde harde on: How can I reioyce in troubell which is nought but waylynge, and yaylynge. It is harde to laugh and to wepe
            
            
               Tymotheus.
               I ſhall enfourme you of it with a groſſe enſample: ye lye here now ſycke and dyſſeaſed,

ye wolde be fayne cured of ſome goode phiſician, now maketh he a drinck for you which is very bitter and miſpleaſaunt to receaue, neuertheleſſe thorow his informacion and promeſſe of health therby ye ouercome the bytterneſſe of it drynkynge yt with ſhoueringe &amp; chaūgging of coūtenaūce: though ye tears rūne down wt drynkīge of y
                     •
                  , yet endeuoure ye yourſelf to retayne a corage. Were it not a folyſhe felowe yt wolde be diſpleaſed wt the phiſician becauſe he doth miniſter ſo bitter drinke vnto him, which he geueth you not for ony hatered or euell wyll, yt you ſhulde fele the bitterneſſe of yt: but that ye myght recouer. Who wolde be ſo madde to deſyre the phiſician to auoyde the bitter recepte, knowenge and ſtedfaſtly belyuynge to optayne health by none other meanes?
            
            
               Lazarus.
               As for me ſurely I wolde rather thanke him, &amp; drynke hys recepte, though it were as bitter as regale yf I knewe to optayne health therby.
            
            
               Timothe.
               
                  Lo then, nomore ye ought to deſpiſe the hygheſt phyſiciō of your ſoule, nor to refuſe hys medycines, though they be bytter and paynfull vnto your olde Adam. But ye muſt haue an eye to his promyſes, &amp; ouercome that which is payneful to you wherby neuertheleſſe ye be ſaued. Thus haue martyrs ouercome in ſufferynge, and death, for dyenge they ſawe the trew lyfe, in ſykneſſe and diſeaſe of the fleſſhe they ſawe the power of God, which is fortyfied, and ſtabylyſſhed hereby. God of hys nature is merciful, but that he maye worke hys worke in vs, that is to heale, to make ſafe and ſounde, he doth fyrſt a thynge that is ſtraunge to hys nature which ſemeth vnto vs a token of hatered, that is, he ſcourgeth and beateth vs with ſykneſſes and grefe. Thus doth God a ſtraunge worke (as ſayeth Eſaye in the .xxviii. chapter) that he maye worke hys natural worke. By this ſtraunge worke of God that is the chaſtenynge or ſcourgynge of the father we leſe oure corage, goodes, bloude, health, welth, and lyuelode, and come euen in the myddes,

of the croſſe, deſpyſynge, and death. All thynges appeare here before our fleſſhly eyes as though we were enemies vnto God, and wholy deſpyſed of God, and wote not to conſyder how he ſhall delyuer vs. Yet do we perceaue the hande of God inwardly which doth ſo ſuſtayn vs that we fall not in deſ
                     •
                  ayre, myſtruſting or mumurynge agaynſt God: wythout the hande of God it were impoſſible for vs to ſtonde the twinklinge of an eye In the ende of the worke do we fyrſt perceaue the councell of God, than ſe we that he wyll mayntayne and fede his ſhepe in his lappe whom he wyll not haue to dye for hunger and dyſeaſe. He can tempte the ryghtuous, and alſo delyuer them agayne. By fayth may we be conquerers of all. Fayth is of thynges that be not apparent: now, where fayth ſhal haue a place, there muſt ſuch thynges be beleued as be inuyſyble. Thus is fayth of the lyfe to come chefely contayned, and declared in dyenge. Thus we beleue that God relyueth vs in kyllynge: that he ſaueth vs, and iuſtyfyeth

vs in ſynnynge: that he brengeth vs to heauē, whā he ſemeth to thruſt vs down to hell in that he forſaketh vs: and that he healeth vs in oure ſoule whan the body is vyſyted with al maner of ſykneſſes For he hedeth hys mercy vnder hys wrath. How wolde haue beleued that God wolde haue dealte ſo peteouſli with hys good frende Iob, in takyng awaye all hys beſt beloued thynges: but onely becauſe he was mynded to reſtore hym, all this agayne doubell? Let therfore youre eye of fayth preaſſe vnto ſaluacion, and reioyce, though God ſhewe you not his foreparte that is a chearfull countenaunce as he dyd vnto Peter beynge on the moūt Thabor: but hys hynder parte lyke as he appared vnto Moſes. For whan this worke of his is paſt, thā appeare his foteſteppes. Whā this chaſteſynge is paſt, than ſhall he ſmyle at you, and ſhew you his fatherly fauoure: though in this anger he ſeme to gerne, and loke grymly vpon you. Perceaue you this?
            
            
               Lazarus.
               
                  I can not perceaue perfectly ſo much at ones Neuertheleſſe, I perceaue that in youre wordes there is a Godly vnderſtōdynge, though I can not comprehend ſo much at once. Therfore I deſyre you to declare me more earneſtly, and ſleghtly which waye oure ſynnes be mortyfyed in vs by the croſſe and ſufferynge.
            
            
               Tymotheus.
               I wyll do yt gladly. Whatſoeuer a man loueth beſyde God, that is hys Idoll, therfore is yt nedefull to declare what thynges we ſett ſtoare by beſyde God, that we myght endeuoure vs the better, to fulfyll the fyrſt commaundement wherin we are commaunded to loue God, with all oure harte, power, and vnderſtondynge. Some leane to much to temporall poſſeſſions, which be withdrawen from them (as a pelowe from vnder a mans heade) by extorcion, with the fyre, by warre, or by ſome other loſſe: that hys hart beatt the more lyberte to be turned wholy to God. Another hath hys carnal affeccion fyxed to ſore vpon hys wyfe, chyldren, father, and mother, or frendes.

Theſe falſe goddes be withdrawē from them whan they ſuffre, ether in theyr name or fame, goodes or bloude: or whan they be taken from them by death, to rydde a man of hys carnall affection, and to open to a man hys infydelyte, that God may poſſeſſe the harte wholy and alone, lyke a gelous louer. The thyrde is wanton, and full of pleaſure, he ſetteth great ſtoare by hymſelf by reaſon of hys bewty ſtrength, honeſty, wyſdome, puyſſaunce vnto ſuch ſendeth God troubell, anguyſſhe, ſykeneſſe, ſores, onwholſōneſſe, or folyſſheneſſe, to the intent, yt he myght ſe how that all fleſſhe is nothynge but hey and all his glory as the graſſe of the felde: the graſſe wythereth, and the flore faydeth.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               I can not perceaue yet that God receaueth vs in ſcourginge, al we flye ſtrokes
            
            
               Tymotheus.
               Your myſbeleue is the cauſe of flyenge, which Paul rebuketh in the .xii. to the Hebrews ſaynge: Bretheren haue ye forgotten the conſolacion, which ſpeaketh

vnto you as vnto chyldren ſaynge: My ſonne, deſpyſe not the chaſtenynge of the Lorde, nother faynte whan thou arte rebuked of hym: for whom the Lorde loueth hym he chaſteneth, Yee he ſcourgeth euery ſonne that he receaueth. Yf ye ſuffre hys chaſteſynge, he offreth hym ſelfe vnto you, as vnto hys beloued ſonne. What ſonne is he whom hys father doth not chaſtyſe? Yf ye be farre from the chaſtenynge, which is comune to all chyldren: then be ye no chyldren, but baſtardes. Alſo yf we haue hadde carnall fathers of whome we ſtode greatly ī awe which chaſtyſed vs: how much more ſhal we be obedyent vnto the father of ſpretes, and ſhall lyue by hym? Oure carnall fathers haue taught, and enfourmed vs after theyr beſt mynde, and that for a lytle ſeaſon: But thys father of oures teacheth, and chaſtyſeth vs for oure profyte, that he maye make vs partakers of hys holyneſſe. All thys preſent chaſtyſynge ſemeth to be nothynge yoyfull but ſorowfull: but herafter ſhe geueth a quyete frute &amp; reward vnto them,

which be proued therby. Are not theſe ſayenges comfortable vnto them that be in payne? punyſhment is dewe vnto ſynne, and wythout ſynne is noman lyuynge: wherfore good Lazarus receaue all that is ſent vnto you, and ſuffre, though it be greueous. Be pacyent in youre depreſſynge. For as golde and ſyluer be tried in the fyre: ſo is man tried in the fornace of temptacion: Therfore, ſcrypture exhorteth vs to eſtyme it aboue all other frutes. And there is no frute ſo trewe as yf we be proued by many folde temptacions, knowenge that temptacion in faith bryngeth forth the frutes of pacience. Beholde all the martyrs, and chyldren of God in theyr ſufferynge, and let theyr conſtant fayth be an example vnto you, for as God hath delyuered them, euen ſo ſhall he delyuer you alſo.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               I maye not cōpare my ſufferynge wyth theyr paſſyons. They dyd ſuffre for their innocency: but I ſuffre for my ſynnes.
            
            
               Timotheus.
               Thynke you the ſayntes were no ſynners

alſo? before God is no fleſhe founde ryghtuous. Saye not that ye ſuffre with the wyked murtherer whan ye ſuffre paciently, and whan faythfully ye knowledge to haue well deſerued ſuch caſtygacion: which the good murtherer dyd alſo. The knowledgynge of youre ſynne doth iuſtifye you, yf it be done faythfully, and trewly. Ther can no trew knowlegynge be, wythout the ſprete of treuth, and youre punyſhment is cauſe of iuſtifycacion, yf ye confeſſe to haue deſerued yt well for youre ſynnes. The martyrdome of martyrs was not meritorious vnto them to to optayne the lyfe euerlaſtynge thereby for Paul ſayth, that the paynes of thys worlde be not ſufficient for ye glory which ſhalbe ſhewed vpon vs. For the tranſytory and faydinge thynges can not optayne durabell rewarde. But Chriſt hath ſuffred onely for his innocency, by the which innocent ſufferinge he hath rydde vs from all oure wykedneſſe. Chriſtes death hath deſerued lyfe eternall for vs this haue the marters beleued cōſtantly teſtyfyenge it vntyl ye death, conqueryng

by fayth: ſo that their fayth (wherby they were iuſtified before God) appeared lyuely in knoleginge the name of Ieſus, from the which they dyd not ſhrynke euē at ye poynte of death. For this cauſe dyd all ſayntes euer praye with the prophet. Not oure (Lorde) not oure, but vnto thy name be glory.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               You ouercome me which ſo many ſtronge and euident ſcriptures, that I wote not what to anſwere. Neuertheleſſe I wolde deſyre God once to ceaſſe ſcourgynge, lyke as many ſayntes haue done And I remēbre I haue herde preached that there was a kynge whoſe lyfe was prolonged fyftene yeares thorowe hys prayer.
            
            
               Timothe.
               We ſhall not folowe ſaintes ſo curiouſly in al their wordes, &amp; dedes: for we be not ſure how wel they haue ben accepted alway of, god. In yt they alſo haue ben mē, we may be deceaued in their foteſteppes Therfore in ſayntes we ought only to be hold their ſtrōge faith, &amp; ye giftes yt God had geuē thē. But chriſt is ſet to be our ſā
                  ple &amp; copie after whoſe lyf wordes &amp; doctrīe

we maye lyue, &amp; ſpeake: for he could not erre, nor cauſe other to erre, whiche ſayntes haue done ryghtwell. Paul ſayeth: Be ye ye folowers of my as I am a folower of Ieſu Chriſt. Now ſhall ye heare how Chriſt is oure ſampel in thys prayenge or wyſſhinge that ye ſpeake of. Whan he prayed in his agony he ſayde Father: yf this cuppe cā not be taken frome but ye I drynke of yt, not my will, but thyne be fulfylled. Praye ye lykwyſe wt Chriſt and ye ſhalbe ſtrenghted alſo no doubte from heauen in youre battayll, And now to anſwere you vnto youre example of Ezechias which (beynge dead ſyke) optayned by his prayer of God to be delyuered of his ſykneſſe: you muſt vnderſtande yt God doth puniſſhe vs diuerſly with the rodde of correctiō in oure body, Somtyme he doth it to puniſſhe our ſynnes &amp; wykedneſſes, yt our faith be ſtrenghted therby, as Chriſt ſayde to the ſykemā yt had lyē .xxxviii. yeares ſyke at Ieruſalē by ye ſlaughterhouſe pole: Behold thou art made whole, ſinne nomore leſt a worſe thīge happē vnto ye. By theſe

wordes he dyd geue him knoledge, that for his ſynnes he ſuffered this longe and greuous ſykneſſe: for the wich he ſhulde ſuffreyt more greueouſly yf he left not ſynninge. Sōtyme ſendeth God ſykneſſe and troubel to hys electe, whiche not withſtondynge be in his fauours, that ye glory and honoure of God maye be declared therby, as Chriſt ſayeth Ioh. xi. that Lazarus ſykneſſe was not vnto death, but for the glory of God, yt the ſonne of God might be prayſed therby. Chriſt ſay be alſo Ioh. ix. that the blynde was ſo borne, that the worke of God might be ſhewed vpon hym, Euen ſo daylye doth yet the glory &amp; honoure of God appeare in many places, by ſufferinge paciently, and dyenge gladly of many vertuous &amp; honeſt men: whiche occaſion other men to prayſe and to thāke God, that ſendeth ſuch grace and mercy vnto men, ſo that they haue cauſe to reoiyce, yee euen in ye myddes of death, Somtymes God viſiteth ye treſpaſſes of the rulers, &amp; parētes vnto the thirde, or fourth generatiō vpō their ſubiectes, and kynreddes: For whā
                  
Dauid had nombred the people formere vanite and miſbeleue, there were fayne to dye .lxx. thouſande of his people wt in thre dayes .ii. Regū. xxiiii. Hely alſo, becauſe he caſtiſed not his childrē, knowynge them to do euell: God ſware vnto the houſe of Hely that hys wykednes ſhulde not be put awaye foreuer by no maner of offerynge, and afterwarde was he puniſhed by the death of his ſonnes .i. Reg. ii All this is done accordynge iuſtice, and dewly, for the ryghtwoſe God cā do no wronge. Vvhan God ſuffreth ſuch as is ſayde afore to chaunce vnto vs, than ſemeth he and is ſayde to be angry with vs, where as he neuertheleſſe is immutable. Now whan we rede of ſome holy mē, which in their ſufferinge haue prayed to be ridde of their croſſe, &amp; anguiſhe it is not to be thought that they haue done it of ony hatered that they hadde to yt, becauſe yt is oneaſy and paynfull: but yt they by this prayenge myght once come to ye perfecte puniſſhynge of ſynne, which they hated and perſewed. And ſo prayed kynge Ezechias whan he was admoniſſhed

by the prophet Eſaye the .xxxviii. chap. that he ſhulde dye ſayenge. What ſhall I ſpeake or ſaye, that he maye do thys? that I maye lyue out al my yeares yee in the bitterneſſe of my lyfe. (Lo the bitterneſſe that came of ye hatered of his ſynnes). Verely Lorde men muſt lyue in bitterneſſe, and all my lyfe muſt I paſſe ouer therin: for thou rayſeſt me vp &amp; wakeſt me. But lo I wylbe cōtent with this bitterneſſe (marke that God by puniſſhinge of ſynne relyueth a mā: Marke ye fayth cauſeth Ezechie to haue peace, and to be at reſt in the middes of his bitter ſufferynge). Neuertheleſſe my cōuerſacion hath ſo pleaſed the, that thou woldeſt not make an ende of my lyfe, but yt thou haſt caſt al my ſynnes behynde thy bake. Beholde, how royaly the good kynge ſetteth forth the mercy of God in his ſufferaunce, that is that Eſaye ſayeth in his xxx. chapter: With ſtyll ſyttinge and reſt ſhall ye be healed, In quietneſſe and hope ſhall youre ſtrength be. That is in the ſilence &amp; reſt of youre owne wyl in Gods wil, and the hope of mercy of God, which

is promiſed you: yee in all ſufferinge ſhal youre ſtrenght be, ſo that ye ſhalbe able to ſuffre all grefe. Euen ſo is that peticion of our prayer to be vnderſtōde, where we deſyre not to be ledde in to temptacion, not that we deſyre to be rydde and fre of all temptacion, (which cā not be ſeynge, oure lyfe is a perpetuall battayll:) But the intent is that we be not ledde in to ſuch temptacion which myght ouercome, and ſo diſcomfite vs that we therby myght fall in miſbeleue, deſpayre, or blaſphemy of the name of God: Vvhich ſynnes be the greateſt and mooſt parelous, for they lye hydde in the entrayles of the harte. Vvherby we might ſynke to the botome of hell with Cayn, Iudas, &amp; kyng Antioche, without ye ſuſtaynynge &amp; vnderproppīge of God. Therfore praye ye holy prophetes alſo: Lorde put not me to rebuke in thyne anger oh chaſtē my not in thy diſpleaſure. In which prayer ye ſpret of god cōforteth vs, &amp; cauſeth God to graūte vs yt he is ye health of al people Of what trouble ſo euer we call to hī he ſhal deliuer vs &amp; be our god for euermore
            
            
               
               Lazarus.
               Youre ſayenge is confortable, and my thynketh I am refreſhed at my hart, ſo yt I fele leſſe grefe in my paines: Neuertheleſſe I muſt reaſone ſōwhat larglyer wt you ſeynge ye teache my ſo well. Vveſe dayly with oure eyes, yt yf a chylde beynge chaſtiſeth of his father do yelde hymſelf to his fathers wyl, axynge mercy, at the laſte he wyll leaue of chaſtenynge I truſt that he which is a father of mercye wyll alſo be mercyfull vnto my poore wrech: how thynke ye?
            
            
               Timothe.
               As concernynge which be the beſt waye to optayne mercy of God, therin doth youre ſimilitude lyke me verely wel. For as a father that hateth the wikedneſſe of his chylde dewly, not withſtōdinge loue, doth correcce hym wyth fatherly pytie, whan he ſeyeth him repyne at the chaſteſynge, he waxeth more furious and augmenteth the ſtrokes. In lyke maner alſo God in ſcripture is ſayde to be wrothful, whan we receaue not the chaſtigation of his hande wyth lowlyneſſe euen as we

rede in Eſaye the .ix. Chapter. After all this the wrath of the Lorde ſhal not ceaſſe, but yet ſhall his hande be ſtreched out ſtyll, For the people turneeth not vnto hym that chaſtiſeth them, nother do they ſeke the Lorde of hooſtes. Therfore ſhall the Lorde rote out of Iſrael both heade and tayle, braunche &amp; 
                     •
                  uigge in one daye By the which wordes the prophet aforeſayde meaneth, that God ſtryketh vs to the intent we ſhuld ſo much ſooner turne agayne to hym, and that he ſtrykinge vs ſhulde occaſion vs to ſeke ayde and helpe of hym. Now therfore, that we maye ſwage the wrath of the chaſteſynge father, we ſhall yelde oureſelfs lyke good chyldren vnto the ſtrokes of oure father, knowleginge our faulte, ſtyll pearſynge to hys fatherly boſome, endeuourynge to coll hym, yee to ſeke all meanes wherby we myght moue hym to pytye. For ye which lowly rendrynge of oure ſelf God loueth vs more then he dyd before. For ye prophet Abacuk ſayeth: Whan God is wroth than ſhal he remembre his mercy. Thus maye we thē praye wt the prophet

ſayenge: All that thou haſt done vnto vs O Lorde, that haſt thou done of trewe iudgment: for we haue ſynned and diſobeyed thy cōmaundementes. Lo ſuch good wyl and yeldinge is of more efficacite, and acceptable in the ſyght of God to optayne forgeueneſſe therby, than all pylgrimages, vowes, and other wayes, whyche a man can take vpon hym of his owne brayne, without ony groūde of euident ſcripture.
            
            
               ¶Lazarus.
               Good Lorde what haue I yet to demaū
                  de whiche I rather ought to kepe cloſe. Ye maye ſaye: One foole wyll demaūde more than al wyſe mē can aſſoyle.
            
            
               Timothe.
               You cā not are to much at me brother for I truſt I ſhal certifie you wel ynough in al thynges by the aſſiſtaunce of God.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Ye cauſe me there to remēbre pelgrimages: wherfore my queſtiō is wether they auayle ought to optayne health therby: For my frendes wil not ceaſſe without I make a vowe ether to faynt Leonart, or to our lady of walſyngā, or to ſome other

ſaynte after theyr affeccion. But as for me I haue no mynde more in this dede, for goyng of pelgrimage hath pilled my yf a good lyuelod in my dayes, &amp; yet haue I foūde none amēdmēt. Yf wyſdō had ben my frende I might haue ſpared that mony But I gaue to much eare vnto theſe olde tothleſſe mab
                     •
                  es, &amp; pilergnawers They were ſo earneſt in whyſperynge theſe thynges in myne eares, that I coulde neuer be rydde of them. But what ſaye ye of them Tymothe? yf they be Godly I wyll cauſe more to be gone for me.
            
            
               Timothe.
               Fyrſt ye muſt well vnderſtonde youre owne wordes where as ye ſpeake of pylgrimages. A plgrime is he yt wandreth in a ſtraunge country and from home, &amp; pylgrimage is ſuch a wandringe or wayfarīge. Now where fynde ye in ony ſcripture, that Goddes worde byddeth you to go &amp; ſeke holyneſſe in a ſtraunge coū
                  try or place? (ſeynge you be Gods tēple yf ye beleue faythfully, and ſeynge Paul wyll haue men to lyft vp pure handes

in euery place:) Or where be ye cōmaunded to choſe out one place more than another to offer prayer, ſence the ſhadowe of ye lawe vaniſhed? Yee how can you preſuſume ſuch praynge as is not agreynge with Gods worde? and all what is done without his cōmaundement is not acceptable vnto hym, Nother is it the glory and honour of God or his ſayntes to ſet ſuch ſtoare by youre mans wyſdome and inuencion, though yt ſeme neuer ſo godly &amp; fayre. But yf ye (ſayeth Chriſt) that wylbe my diſciples praye, you ſhall not pray lyke as the Heythen do: but go in to the chamber of youre hart, ſhut the dore vpon you, that is: ſhut all wordly troubell and cōbraūce out of youre hart, and praye vnto God in ſecrete, not in ye corners of the ſtretes, not in outchoſen places, and youre father which ſeyeth in ſecrete, and the entrayles of the hart, ſhal rewarde you openly. Chriſt hath ſufficiently forbidden the goynge of pylgrimage in the .iiii. chapter of Iohn, where he teacheth vs that we ſhuld not go to pray in Salomons tēpel, nor vpō the renowmed

hylles of the Patriarckes, but that we ſhall call vpon God in all places (not with waxe or flaxe, not wt ſyluer or golde not with corne or ſede, no not with cryenge and whyninge as the preſtes of Baal and the Heithen do, which thynke to be herde for their cryenge and much bablinge) but in ſprete and treuth. For the father which is a ſprete wyl haue ſuch worſhippers. The prophete Malachy alſo in his fyrſt chapter ſayeth: From the ryſynge vp of the ſonne vnto the goynge downe of theſame, my name is great amonge the gentyles: Yee in euery place ſhal there ſacrifices be done, and a clene meat offerynge offred vp vnto my name: for my name is greate amonge the Heithen ſayeth the Lord of hooſtes. What offringe doth he requyre of vs? wax or flax ſyluer or golde? No, but the mortifyenge of our carnall deſyres, and ſenſuall appetite. wherunto Paul exhorteth vs wryttinge vnto the Romanes in the .xii. chapter. It is a greate blyndneſſe that we ſeke ayde or comforte at ony ſaynte, whom oure ymagynacion is that we worſhippe

&amp; ſerue thē in their ſimilitud here in earth wherin we trāgreſſe ye fyrſt cōmaūdmēt of God, which forbyddth us all ſtraunge Gods, &amp; to make ony ſimilitude or ymage. Wyll ye knowe the cauſe &amp; ſpringe of the multitude of the Heytheniſhe Goddes? and why we Chriſten men ought to worſhippe but one God? I ſhall ſhewe it you
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Yee I praye you, for I am deſirous of it.
            
            
               Timothe
               Such men as were profitable to the comune welth were counted Goddes of the Heythen, &amp; worſhipped after their death This hath occaſioned the multitude of them. For health they called vpon Eſculapius, for he was a greate Phiſician: Vpon Hercules they called for ryches: Vpon Mercury they called for luck of marchaundyſe: Vpon Bacchus for wyne: Vpon Seres for corne: Vpon Venus for luſt of the body, yee the Egyptians God is become the ſtorke, for he deſtroyed the ſerpentes: The Romaynes haue worſhipped a Gouſe, becauſe yt at ye ſkrekinge of her, ye wachmē yt kepte the caſtel

at Rome called Capitoliū were awaked, &amp; ſo warned of their enemies: of like cōmodite &amp; ꝓfyte be ye Sōne &amp; Mone: water &amp; earth made goddes &amp; worſhipped. But we Chriſten mē knowe nor worſhippe none other God, ſaue him only yt worketh all in all thinges. It is written: ye ſhall ſerue youre lorde God &amp; worſhippe him only Whā we truſt in nomā but him only makīge of him our ſauegarde, redēption, wyſdō, ryghtwyſnes, hope &amp; welfare: than do we worſhip hī only, whā we caſt vs wholy down before him forſakīg &amp; deſpyſyng our holyneſſe, wyſdō, abilite &amp; natural ſtrēgth reputīge our ſelues fooles, wiked, &amp; feble, yt ſeke mercy at hī only thā praye we to him. Marke wether they yt turne thēſelues frō the creator vnto the creatures do ſo, ſekīge helpe wt their rū
                  ninge gaddīge hyther &amp; thyther a pelgrimage. I am thy God only, and without me is there is no redemer ſayeth the Lorde God. To ſaue belongeth only to hym, but the gentyles and vngodly make a mokage of yt, yeſtenge and ſayenge as is wryttē Deutxonomy. xxxii. Where

are now theyr Goddes wherin they hadde confidence, let them ryſe now and helpe you, let them ſuccour you in youre nede. But ye Lord maketh anſwere agayne ſayenge: I am he, and without me there is no God, I wyl ſlaye and relyue agayne: I wyl ſcourge &amp; heale agayne: there is no mā yt can plucke ought out of my hādes. Vvhere ſhal theſe ydolatrers thā and pelgromes remayne: Vvhat Goddes ſhalbe able to defende them, whan God ſhall puniſhe theyr miſbeleue and ydolatry (which they haue cōmitted with woode and ſtone) openly and before the whole world: Although he be now quiet and longe ſufferinge
            
            
               ¶Lazarus
               Vvil ye take it in worth yt I ſhal aſke of you, &amp; I wil ſhew you ye reaſons, whiche myn hypocritiſhe coūcelers were wōte to lay to me, whā they entyſed me to ye pelgrimages vnto ſaintes: Vvhō I (God forgeue me) haue ſhewed to much honour in myn ydolatry.
            
            
               ¶Timothe.
               Aſke what ye pleaſe, ſo yt I be not to tedious vnto you, it wold not greue me to ſyt thus an whole day wt you treatynge

of the ſcrypture.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               How fortuneth it then that ſayntes wyl be worſhypped, and ſought more in one place than in another, to heale ſuch diſeaſes as they be patrones of?
            
            
               Tymotheus.
               Chriſt ſaieth in the .xiiii. chapter of Ihon I am the waye, the treuth, and lyfe. Yf ye wyl not go aſtraye and erre, than with drawe you from ſayntes. Which haue receaued all theyr holyneſſe of hym, that ye name of God myght be gloryfyed in thē. Walke (I ſaye) in Chriſt for he is the waye, who ſo foloweth hym ſhall walke in no darkneſſe. Yf ye wyll not be deceaued with ony lye or falſhed, than holde you by Chriſt, abyde by Chriſtes worde, ſtyke by yt, for it is the treuth. Yf ye wyll not dye in ſynne nor peryſhe in youre owne wycked wayes: than ſtryue by the mortifyenge of the fleſſhe to lyue eternaly with hym, for he is the lyfe. Paul ſayeth that oure lyfe is hydde with him vnto death. The waye of ſufferynge is narowe and ſtrayght, but you muſt go thorowe

it yf ye entende to come vnto yoie. The treuth muſt delyuer you of youre thraldome of ſynne, yf ye ſhalbe delyuered in dede▪ Why do ye then ſeke another 
                     •
                  odye, another lyfe, another ſaueour beſyde the waye of treuth and lyfe? As concernynge, that ye do ſaye that ſayntes wylbe vyſitted more in one place, than in another. I anſwer that yf ſayntes wylbe worſhypped, and diſcerne places of worſhippe and honour, that they be rather deuyls than ſayntes: for they deſyre honour and worſhippe, which belongeth onely to God, that is ſupreme heade of all thynges. Morouer ſayntes, that be heauenly ſayntes ſaye conſtantly: Not vnto vs o Lorde not vnto vs, but vnto thy name geue the glory. Now how will you honour, and geue vnto ſayntes this glory, which they do refuſe ſo earneſtly? or thynke ye they ſhewe God this fayre face, and yet neuertheleſſe robbe hym of hys honour. Wherfore yf yt be ſayde vnto you Chriſt is here, there is pardon of all ſynnes, there is a ſoule delyuered out of purgatory, here is an ymage of myracles,

there be many reliquyes of ſayntes here is this or that ſaynt worſhipped, go not thyther: ſeke the kyngdome of God wythin you: ſeke the kynge of glory in youre harte, which all ſayntes haue done. The kyngdom which God hath in oure hartes is not deckt with wax nor flax, golde nor ſyluer. The dekynge of it conſyſteth in thynges ſpirituall, and inwardly as in mekeneſſe, pacience peace, yoie, fayth, and loue: where ſuch gyftes and ornamētes be perceaued, their maye you ſaie boldly that Chriſt is kynge, and that becauſe in ſuch ornamentes he is founde. Thus is it euydent to be put vayne yanglynge that they ſaye: Sayntes wyll be worſhypped more in one place than in other, for it is without ground or ſtaye of ye treuth of ſcrypture. Yee it is a more blaſphemy to aſſygne vnto euery ſykneſſe a peculiar patrone &amp; ſaueour as ye peſtylēce vnto ſaynt Roke, ye pockes vnto Iob, ſaynte Appolony for ye tothache. &amp;c. Do theſe hypocrites thīke God to deuyde his kingdō to princes and lordes as mortall men do? No, for God ſayeth.

I wyll geue myn honour, and glory to none other. Yf oure God were ſuch one as hadde nede of rulers vnder hym than dyd not ſcrypture ryght in callynge hym God onely, and kynge of all kynges, Lorde of all lordes. Now yf he nede no helpe with hym, why do ye aſſigne then vnto the one ſaynte the peſtylence, vnto another the fallynge ſykneſſe, &amp; ſo forth to euery ſykneſſe a ſeuerall patrone, yt is come ſo farre (God amende it) that there is ſcarce a vyllage of .viii. or .ix houſes but there is ether one Idoll or other. Wherto is Chriſtendom come? what do ye make of the bleſſed company of electes? which be planted and gathered in ye loue of God with all faythfull and beleuynge, which were pacient here in theyr troubel, and haue receaued a louely ſprete of God, deſpyſynge all honour, prayſe goodes, &amp; worldly preemynence, be they (I ſaye) now ſo vnpacient, wykedly dyſpoſed, and couetous of honour that they muſt be appeaſed and reconcyled againe with gaddynge a pelgrymage, with offerynge, of candels, or egges? Is the ſaluation

of ſayntes become now a houſe of plages wherout all myſery floweth? All the diſeaſes wherof ye make you ſondery patrons are naturall, and were in the worlde before youre ſaintes were borne. Oure myſbeleue and great infydelite is the cauſe that we haue fayned vs ſo many Idols. Becauſe we haue not knowne the onely eternal, and trewe god but be enclyned to blynde ceremonies, though we ſhulde worſhippe a calfe ther with, as the chyldren of Iſrael dyd: therfore is it come to pas, that we haue oure purpoſe in that we haue done worſhippe vnto the calfſkynne the popyſhe bulles ſtickynge candels to it. O Lorde loke vpon the afflyction and punyſhment of the doughter Syon: and haue pytie vpō the deſtruccion of Ioſephs heretage.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Frō henſforth wyll I ſet vp not one lytel candell to ony ymage what ſo euer it be I haue hetherto lyghted thre candels to ſaynte Anne euery tewſdaye, and on the thyrſdaye haue I worſhypped the holy ſacrament with half a pounde of waxe:

but I am now ſo enfourmed of you, that henſforth. I wyll do it nomore: but rather geue it to the poore and lyghten ſo the lyuynge temple of god, wherin he dwelleth no doubte with hys mercy. Is not that beſte brother Tymothe?
            
            
               Tymotheus.
               Yee it is a thouſande tymes better, for Chriſtes ſaynge is: Loke what ye haue done vnto the leaſt of mine, that haue ye done vnto me. He ſayeth not what ye haue done vnto my picture or ymage, or vnto the picture of my ſayntes which I haue forbidden to make or to honoure. Wherfore, whan theſe ſayntes ſpechmē come to perſuade you to your olde ſuperſtition, than anſwer you them: Is it not a great blyndneſſe of you to ſeke the ſayntes in woode and ſtone contrary to the fyrſt commaundement? Is it not a great foly to lyght the Sonne at brode day with a candell? The ſayntes wyll ſay to this: Lorde in thy lyght ſhall we beholde the lyght. The lyght of the Godly vyſage lyghteth the electes alwaye: how wyl ye then lyghten them with your lyght

that is made for the ſolace of darkneſſe? Thynke ye they be in darkneſſe that are lyghtened of the ſonne of ryghtwyſneſſe? Yf ye wyll nedes ſet candels before them than geue them eyes alſo that they maye ſe them: than maye ye optayne thākes of them, els do ye but leſe your laboure, and coſt. Baruch alſo ye prophete doth greatly rebuke this vngodly honoure, &amp; worſhippe of ymages. Now whan ye haue thus rebuked them of this Idolatry, thā ſhew them where they ought to beſtowe theyr candels, offeringes, &amp; other almes that they be acceptable vnto God. Alſo yf they wyl go on pelgrimage, thē ſhewe them a nearer way which they maye go with leſſe coſt, &amp; ſay Seynge you be mynded to viſyte the ſayntes, it is no nede to runne to Rome, or to Ieruſalē, or to ſaynte Iannes in Spayne, for that were loſſe both of expences, and tyme. Seke Chryſt in the graue of ſcrypture: ſeke hym in the chamber, of youre harte, there ſhall ye be mooſt ſureſt of hym: Seke the ſprete of Peter, and Paul in theyr wrytynges, and Epyſtles.

Seke Iames in his ſtronge fayth that he continued in vntyll hys death. Morouer God is no bodely thynge, and therfore wyll not he be worſhipped with bodely thynges: he is a ſprete, and regardeth no perſone, place, candell, or ſuch good workes: But his deſyre is onely that we put awaye the wycked thoughtes, from oure harte as namely myſbeleue, deſpayre, vnclenneſſe, hate, enuye, couetouſneſſe, and pryde. For they that haue a clene harte from theſe, and a lowely ſprete ſhal ſe God, and be called the children of God where as all theſe holyneſſe ſekers ſhall remayne wythout: For God which is a ſprete wyll not be worſhypped but in the ſprete and treuth, where as theſe hypocrytes ſeke hym in outchoſen places, in ſeuerall dayes, with certayne oyntment boxes, to declare theyr good intent towarde hym in bodely workes: but they ſhall not touche hym, for he is ryſen, and lyfted aboue all that is outwarde, and in mans ſyght.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               I ſhall kepe well youre declarynge, and

as I can. But I knowe what ſhall be theyr anſwere here vnto.
            
            
               Timotheus.
               What I praye you?
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Why than do they myracles more in one place than in another? but onely that they wylbe worſhypped and ſought there.
            
            
               Tymotheus.
               To that ſhall ye anſwere: where a ſure fayth is, there nede no tokens but onely the token of Ionas the prophet? In the which token the lyfe and death of Chriſt and alſo the death and reſurrecciō of euery Chriſten man is featly fygured. For with Ionas and Chriſt muſt we deſcende in to the whal fyſhe, &amp; ſee of tribulacion and death before we can ryſe agayne in to the lyfe euerlaſtynge. Lyke as Ionas dyd not remayn in the ſee, nor Chriſt in the graue, but were relyued agayne: euen ſo ſhall not God ſuffre vs to be ouercome with no grefe, nor death, but ſhall rayſe vs out of this myſery vnto the reſurreccion of lyfe. Therfore ought we to voyde oure mynde of all myracles, all

patrons, and beholde this token of Ionas onely, ſettynge oure confydence vpō yt onely, ſayenge with the prophet Pſal. lxi. My ſoule wayteth onely vpon God, for of hym commeth my help. He onely is my ſtrength, my ſaluation, my defence, ſo that I ſhall not greatly fall. Lo, to thys Ionas ſhall ye ſende all theſe myrakel gaſers, as Chriſt hath ſent thē awaye which of curioſyte deſyred to ſe tokens from heauen. As for the myracles, which ſayntes be ſayde to ſhewe by theyr ymages, they be but a mockage and gabbynge of the dyuell. There can no myrakles be done of God agaynſt hys holy worde Treuth it is that Moſes hath comfyrmed the then commaundementes, and lawe, and hath made them autenticall with wonders and tokens: It is treuth alſo that the Apoſtles after the paſſion, and aſcendynge of Chryſt to heauen, haue comfyrmed theyr wordes, and preachynges with ſome myrakles in the name of Ieſu: (for that name beynge deſpyſed as a malefactor and condemned, had great nede of theſe). But theſe myracles

of ſayntes or ymages can not confyrme the worde of God nor they happen not to that intent, but rather to a falſe Gods ſeruyce. They cauſe nothynge els ſaue a decyuerynge of Gods worde, Idolatry: which beynge vſed and had in pryce amonge the Chriſtians hath preſoned theyr blyndneſſe and myſbelefe. For by the occaſyon of myrakles, men rūne to the Idols 
                     •
                  r ymages as though they were myndleſſe: to the intent they myght be healed of ſuch ſykneſſes, and dyſeaſes and be ſent them for theyr amendment. Now where ſuch fayth, and confydence is geuen vnto ymages, and theyr myracles, there can it not well be beleued that thys bytter chalyce of ſufferynge be geuen vs of the father as an acceptable thynge, and worthy to be receaued wyth a good wyll. Neuertheleſſe that Chryſte wyll haue yt ſo to be receaued, is euydent by the wordes that he ſpake vnto Peter, what tyme as he wolde defende Chryſtes cauſe wyth the materiall ſwearde ſayenge:

wylt not thou that. I ſhal drinke the chalice which my father hath ſent me? as though he wolde ſaye: Ye ought to ſeke no meanes nor counſell, nor not once to ſaye agaynſt ye drynkynge of this chalice or cuppe which my heauenly father hath ſent me. Hereby is geuen vs to wyte that all oure trouble is ſent vs alſo of oure heauenly father, to accepte it wyllyngly, and with a good wyll to drynke it. How much leſſe than ſhall we runne a ſtraye here or there to ſeke thys helpe or that, this counſell or that, to be redemed, and made fre of oure burthen. Moſes warnynge vs not to be moued at ony myrakle ſayeth Deut. xiii. yf there ryſe vp a prophet or dreamar amonge you, and geue the a token or wonder, and that token or wonder which he ſpake of come to paſſe, and than ſaye: Let vs go after other Goddes (whom thou knoweſt not) and let vs ſerue them: Thou ſhalt not herken vnto the voyce of ſuch a prophete or dreamer. For youre Lorde youre God proueth you, to wete wether ye loue hym with all youre hart, and with all

youre ſoule. For ye ſhall walke after the Lorde youre God, and feare hym, and kepe his commaundementes, and herken vnto his voyce, and ſerue hym, and cleue vnto hym. Theſe wordes do playnly deſpiſe the ſeruynge or worſhippynge of ſtraunge Goddes or ymages: They caſt awaye all myracles and tokens that chaunce by Gods ſufferinge to proue vs wether oure truſt, a
                     ••
                   confydence be onely in God. They ſhewe vs to God of whom we muſt hope al goodneſſe. Wherfore regarde not theſe pelgrymage goers, and myrakell gaſers, for yf ye folowe theyr councels, ye teſtifie you not to be a trewe beleuer. It is a trew prouerbe that is comunly vſed: wo to that londe where many myracles do chaunce, for that is a token that great vnbeleue is there. And where as ye thynke ſayntes to choppe, and chaunge ſo with myracles, that is not ſo. For the deuell can alſo chaunge hymſelfe into an angel of light as ſaieth Paul. This is euydent in the fyrſt boke of the kynges in the .xxviii. chapter where Samuel the good prophete beynge

dead was conyured of the ſoythſayenge woman at Sauls inſtaunce at the whych charmynge the deuyll appeared in the lykneſſe of Samuel. Therfore alſo doth Paul warne vs ſayenge, to the Colloſſians the .ii. chapter. Let noman make you to ſhute at a wronge marke, whych after his owne chouſynge walketh in humblyneſſe, and ſpyritualyte of angels, thynges which he neuer ſawe. Wherin we are warned of all holyneſſe of men for theryn maye we lyghtely be deceaued. Morouer it happeneth ſomtyme that God taketh his worde out of hys trew preachers and prophets mouth and geueth it vnto lyenge ſpretes, which lyes the people doth lyghtely accepte by reaſon of theyr erroure: as we rede .iii. Reg. xxii. God ſayde vnto the lienge ſprete that he ſhulde deceaue kynge Achab Go thy waye thou ſhalt deceaue them, (ſayde he) and be able. Thys example teacheth vs not to reſt nor truſt in ony mans holynes, wyſdome, or worthyneſſe. Theſe and ſuch lyke deceates chaunge vnto vs by the ryght wyſneſſe of God

becauſe we turne ſo lyghtely to ſtraunge Goddes, to ſayntes, to falſe tokens, and myracles, whych be ſet vp by the occaſyon of ſome lyenge dreame of a falſe prophete, or as comunly they be by ye wylyneſſe of the dyuell. Wherfore loke where Chryſt, and hys worde be ſhewed, and the fayth accepted, though Chriſt be but newe come in Egypte and yōge: there decaye incontinently ſuch auaūtages, and yearly rētes of pilgrimage goinges, and myracles, which is dayly to be ſene. For gods worde is a fyre: and therfore conſumeth it all ſuch workes as be nothynge but ſtouble, ſtrawe, and hey, and it ſelfe endureth for euer. Yf ſuch mokage of miracles &amp; pylgrimages were agryenge wt the worde of God, than ſhulde they remayne doubtleſſe: but ſeinge they be not, therfore muſt al plātacions which ye heauēly father hath not plāted be roted out.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Yt is treuth, for ther is not ſo much reſorte to the bloude of Hayles, oure lady of Walſy mgā, to this or that ſainte as ther hath bene: By reaſon the myrakles haue

not now ſo much fayth geuen vnto them But how happeneth it that the ſoules, and ſpretes of the dead deſyre of tymes ſuch going on pelgrimages? in ſo much that bokes alſo be made of it?
            
            
               Tymotheus.
               Brynge ye forth now youre ſpretes, and dreames? Beleue not euery ſprete, but 
                     •
                  rye them wyther they be of God. Such ſpretes as wyll drawe you awaye from Chriſt, vnto your owne workes or holyneſſe, flye them as venyme. We muſt abyde in Chriſt that is his wordes, and doctryne yf we ſhalbe his diſciples, We muſte diſcerne, and herken to his voyce onely, yf we ſhalbe hys ſhepe. All that which is not conteyned, and founded in the ſcrypture ſhall not ye beleue. All bodely exercyſe which as ye ſaye is requyred of you profyteth lytell, but Chriſten vertuouſnes, and godlyneſſes is profytable to all thynges. The father poyntynge vs to hys ſonne in whom he delyteth ſayeth, that we ſhall heare hym, and not the ſpretes: for the apparitions of ſpretes are wholy agaynſt the ſcrypture, wherfore

they can be nothynge but illuſyōs, of the dyuels that be in the ayre We rede in the goſpell of the ryche glutton, that he deſyred hys fyue brethren in earth, to be warned of the daungers, and payne that he was in: but what anſwere was made hym agayne? euen ſuch as is made to euery man, that is now lyuynge, Let them heare Moſes, and the prophetes. He ſayde no 
                     •
                  et them heare the ſpretes. Yt foloweth: yf they wyll not heare them, then wyll not they alſo beleue yf ony dead roſe agayne and appeared: we haue Moſes, and the prophetes, theſe wyll God haue vs geue ear vnto, and al curiouſe ſearchynge of ſpretes with their anſwers vtterly to be deſpyſed. A pure fayth truſteth onely in Gods wordes couetynge none other viſyons or apparition to the ſtrenghtynge of hym, ſaue only the othe, which was made to Abraham, and hys ſede in hym, what tyme as God was mynded to geue hymſelf vnto vs, which through fayth in God are become chyldren of Abraham and heyres of God. Thys inwarde or gooſtly ſyght of

a pure harte paſſeth all other certifyenges eyther of ſpretes, angels, or deuels. For ſo much as God is faythfull in his promyſe aboue all other creatures. This illuſion of ſpretes doth God alſo rebuke by Eſay ye prophet in ye .viii. chapter ſayenge: And therfore yf they ſaye vnto you: Aſke coūcel at ye ſoythſayers, witches, charmers, and cōiurers, then make thē this anſwere: Is there a people ony where that axeth not councel at his God wether it be concerninge the dead, or the lyuinge? Yf ony mā want lyght let him loke vpon ye law &amp; the teſtimony, wether they ſpeake not after thys meanynge. Therfore let vs not regarde dreames &amp; fantaſies, nor yet care for no ſpretes, nor ſeke ony certifyenge of trewth through their apparitions for it is forbidden in ſcripture. Let vs turne rather to the law and his wytneſſe, for in it is no deceate. But alas for pytie infidelite is roted ſo depe in mens hartes by the reaſon of ignoraunce of Gods worde that they beleue rather the viſions of Tundall, the tales of legenda aurea, or ſuch fantaſies &amp;

dreames in dede: than that whiche God will haue learned of vs as namely right wyſnes and iudgment in crucifyenge of oure ſynfull apetites, mercy in declaringe ſeruyce to oure poore neghbure. In which two poyntes be cōtayned the law and prophetes.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Seynge I haue begonne to aſke, I will laye to you all that I reken may be obiected vnto me in this matter. Tell me thā good Timothe how chaunceth it yt many religious and holy men be canoniſate for their myrakles and approbate to be ſayntes.
            
            
               Timothe.
               The canoniſation of ſayntes which Popes &amp; Cardinals do vſe is a ſlecht &amp; vngodly thynge, wherin is manteyned greate deceate and couetouſnes. Truſt not in ye canoſation of men, not in ye worthyneſſe, holyneſſe or wyſdome, of thoſe yt be canoniſate, for you ſhal be deceaued therin. For the popes kyngdome whiche is groūded in al welthyneſſe, glory, ryches, and puſſaunce cā geue no trew iudgmēt in godly thynges, or concerninge Gods

kyngdom. But ſeynge it is an outwarde kyngdome whiich doth cōſiſt in myters, croſyers, coapes, albes, croſſes, banners, ſhauynge, anoyntynge, ſyngynge, readynge, ryngynge, yanglynge, yee in horſes and moyles, and other baggage, yt can not be iudge but in outwarde thynges, after whiche iudgement ſpirituall thīges ought not to be iudged. The diſcretion or iudgment betwene holy &amp; vnholy belongeth only to the ſonne of God which doth iudge not after the ſyght of the eyen, nor after the hearynge of ye ears but accordynge to the treuth: thys treuth can not the worlde comprehende, becauſe ſhe is ful of lyes, and (as Iohn ſayeth) ye treuth is not in the lye. Thys is ye cauſe why Chriſt warneth vs to beware of the leuen of the Phariſes, that is, for the hypocryſy, diſſemblinge, and doctrine of the Phariſes: for they deceaue the ſymple hartes, and ſeduce them with their lyenge which they do craftly vtter. They ſeke not youre ſaluation in the canoniſynge of ſayntes, nor the honour and hygh reputation of them: for their ſayntes be

not one heare the holyer for yt, nor we the nearer ſaluatiō, ſeynge it belongeth only to God to ſaue. But they ſeke in thys dede ether theyr owne auauntage, or theyr carnal glory: for by canoniſynge they get much mony. Nor there is none canoniſate without it be procured by a ſingularite or parcialte, yee a folyſhe gloriation wether it be of one towne, cyte, or ony other cōmunaltye. Yt is to be doubted there be ſome whoſe bodyes be canoniſate and worſhipped here in earth, and theyr ſoules buryed in hell. Sence the Pope hath vſed to make ſayntes, the ſaynte of all ſayntes is ſet bakwarde: for as it is ſayde that a new brome ſwepeth clene, euen ſo be the newe ſayntes the beſte in the opinion of the comune people. Therfore maye Ieremy complayne ryghtwell vpon this, ſayenge in the .vi. chapter. For amonge my people are founde wyked perſonnes, that preuely laye ſ
                     •
                  ares and wayte for mē, to take them, and deſtroye them. And lyke as a net is full of byrdes, ſo are theyr houſes ful of that, which they haue gotten with falſede and deceate.

Herof cōmeth their great ſubſtaunce &amp; ryches, herof are they fat and welthy, &amp; are runne awaye fro me with ſhamfull blaſphemyes. (it foloweth continently) The prophetes teach falſly, and the preſtes folowe them, &amp; my people hath pleaſure therin. What wyll come therof at the laſt. Wyll ye nedes knowe wether there by ony ſayntes canoniſate? I wyl ſhewe you Of Dauid ſayeth the Lorde: I haue founde a man accordynge to my harte. Of Paul, ſayeth that he was a choſen and elect weſſel. Of Peter that he was bleſſed. Of Simeon the old preſt wytneſſeth the holy gooſt that it was a iuſt man full of the feare of god, playne, &amp; one that abode the delyueraūce of Iſrael. Of Steuē that he was ful of grace, and that he ſawe Ieſu ſtondynge at the ryght hande of God. Lo in the canoniſation of theſe, and ſuch lyke ſayntes are not ye deceaued: to the profe of ye ſe canoniſatiōs ye haue no nede of Popiſhe bulles, ye rede of their myrakles ſufficiently in ye boke of trewth, Of theyr trewth beareth god hymſelf recorde. In theſe ſaintes

ſhal ye prayſe the Lorde as ſayeth ye prophet, Prayſe and thanke God in hys ſayntes.
            
            
               Lazarus
               If ye Popes matter be not better ſtayed by the ſcripture thā I haue herde of you I maruayll that it coulde endure ſo longe. Neuertheleſſe yf ſome had herde you they wolde haue called youre reaſons new learnynge, &amp; that they folowe theyr fathers.
            
            
               Timothe.
               No vſe or cuſtome can derogate the worde of God, els myght it be ſayde, Mahometes lawe hath ben ſo many hundreth yeares, and approbate by ſo many learned men, and of ſo many nacions I wyll rather abyde by that lawe than by thys newe learnynge. Yf ye wyll continue by an erroure becauſe it hath continued ſo longe, than abyde by the originall ſynne, which remaneth yet ſence oure fyrſt parē
                  tes in euery one that cōmeth in to thys world, If you wil nedes abyde wt the olde &amp; ſaye ye olde is beſt thā ſhyft not your worne garmentes, eat nought but ſtale

and rotten egges what blynde anſwers do theſe blynde bytels brynge forth? Beholde ſayeth the Lorde Eſaye. lxv. I ſhal make a new heauen and a newe earth. And the prophet prayeth ſayenge: Make a clene hart (o God) and renew a right ſpirite within me. Paul alſo ſayeth: Be ye renewed in ye ſprete of youre mynde. Wherfore wyll you be bounde thus to yt olde? Do not ye knowe that ye muſt be borne agayne before ye ſhall come in the kyngdom of God. The ſonne muſt redeme you from the olde deuyll, from his deceates, from his olde death before ye be redemed in dede: Euen as Chriſt ſayde vnto the Phariſes, which gloried and reyoiced in their olde father Abraham after the fleſhe: Yf ye ſonne delyuer you frō the thraldome of ſynne than be ye delyuered in dede, Yt is no new learnynge whan ye be taught to truſt in God, to be redy to ſerue youre neghbure, to ſuffre your aduerſite paciētly, to deſpiſe ye falſe Gods ſeruice: for that alſo haue all ye prophetes, al euāgeliſtes, al apoſtles taught more thā thouſande yeres agone. They

be new doctrines which the Popets diſciples &amp; ſworne ſeruaūtes haue brought vp within theſe thre or foure hundreth yeares. That which Paul preached to ye Athenians was alſo counted for newe learnige, for they ſayde: Lo here cōmeth he the preacher of new deuels. There is nother old, nor new God, but there is an euer
                     •
                  ſtige God which is, which was, &amp; ſhalbe. There is no newe nor olde learnynge of God, Gods worde endureth for euer. Ieſu Chriſt is yeſterdaye &amp; to daye he endureth for euer. Stycke faſt to hys worde and ye ſhall not be deceaued, for hys worde is trewth. He hath the wordes of lyfe, ſuffre no doctour, no apoſtle, no angell of heauen to drawe you from hym. Buylde your houſe ſure vpō ye rock Chriſt, that ye maye with ſtonde all tempeſtes and aſſaultes. Be not lyghtely turned from the good learnynge, whiche ye be taught in the fayth accordynge to the ſcripture: what ſo euer ye be taught beſyde it let that be accurſed. What can we tell what oure forefathers haue beleued or not? What cā we tell whiche workes

he hath imputed thē for ſynne or not? are we ſworne to their fayth? are we chriſtened in ye name of our fathers? why wil we then abyde by their fayth ſo earneſtly which is vncertayne to vs? Is not faith a gyfte of God? Perchaunce god hath poured yt alſo in them we not knowenge whan, or who, forſomuch as yt is a gyft of God? He that beleueth in my (ſayeth Chriſt) though he dye, he ſhall lyue. Her is not promyſed yf he abyde by the fayth of hys forefathers. Who is ſo preuy of Gods iudgmētes that he knoweth why God ſuffred the worlde thus longe to cō
                  tinue in this great darkneſſe? It hath chaunced of tymes in the olde teſtament amonge the Iewes that the trewe Gods ſeruice, and the knoledge of ye lawe was forgotten for a great ſeaſon: ſo that no man knewe of the lawe, nor cremonyes. As for the cauſes hereof or iudgement we wyll referre them to God, thankynge hym for hys benefete in reſtorynge vnto as agayne the pure goſpell, ſhall we not brother?
            
            
               Lazarus.
               
                  Yee verely brother with all oure hartes. I am now (thāked be God) ſo wel eaſed in conſciencie that I fele no heuyneſſe nor troubell more at my harte. Before was I neuer quiete, now wolde I do thys, than that, nowe wolde I haue thys pylgrymage gone for me, than that candell offred, which I haue not made you preuy of hethertho. I haue alſo cauſed oftymes golden maſſes be ſayde for me to optayne health: I feare me I haue offended alſo therin. I muſt make a playne confeſſion to you.
            
            
               Timothe.
               What be theſe golden maſſes?
            
            
               Lazarus.
               They be ſeperate maſſes that profyte greatly ſayde agaynſt peſtilence, derth and ſuch lyke plages, dyſeaſes, and vrgēt grefes. They be ſayde or ſonge for ye cōmunalty and thereby they optayne golde of them that they be ſayde for. They haue coſt my large ſixe pounde ſēce my diſaſe begāne, though they haue profyted my lytell.
            
            
               Timothe.
               
                  I perceaue well ynough ye haue ben a veſſell full of ſuperſtition: ye haue ſo bē laden with theſe pylergnawers &amp; ſayntes minions as ſaynt Iames with hys moſkelſhelles. I praye you tell me were ye neuer in the brotherheade of oure ladyes pſalter? Were ye neuer written in the brotherheade of Caims kynne, that is ye foure orders of the popes ſouldyers?
            
            
               Lazarus.
               I haue not named thē al yet: yet I was mynded to haue ben buryed in a graye freres cote, to haue ben releaſt of ye thirde parte of my ſynnes. But now I byd this brablynge fare wel. I loth the hearynge of them. Shewe me youre mynde of the maſles wether a man may cauſe them to be ſayde for hym whan he is in yeopardy? ſeynge Chriſt hymſelf hath inſtitute them.
            
            
               Timothe.
               I am not aduiſed that euer I dyd once reade the name of maſ
                     •
                  e in the whole ſcripture of God, I reade of the ſupper o
                     •
                   the lorde, which Chriſt wt his apoſtles and the apoſtles with other beleuynge

haue kepte and vſed. Whan I entende to cōpare the maſſe and ye ſupper of our Lorde together, I can not perceaue it to be one thynge. But ſeynge yt will be to longe to ſhewe the difference betwene thē I wyll deferre that vntyll oure nexte metynge. As for to anſwere vnto your queſtion, I ſhall leaue the worde maſſe vntouched, and anſwere you ſcripturely wt wordes of the ſcripture. You haue ared of the maſſe and I ſhall anſwere you wt the ſupper of our lorde. The vſe of ye ſupper hath Chriſt inſtitute for none other intent ſaue only that the breade of oure Lord ſhulde be diſtributed, and the chalice of Chriſtes bloude ſhulde be miniſtred to euery man, in a remembraunce of hym, which hath offred hys body vnto death, and ſhed hys bloude for vs, for a forgeueneſſe of ſynnes: As he ſayeth himſelf: As oft as ye ſhall do thys, (namely that whyche I do here to youre enſample) do yt in the remembraunce of me (that is) that we ſhall ſhewe the death of oure Lorde as Paul ſayeth. Than do we declare the death of oure

Lorde, whā we preache and ſhewe vnto the comunalty or cōgregation how chriſt hath offred hys body vnto death for vs, and that becauſe we ſhulde not remayne in the euerlaſtynge death, and ſo is he become a death vnto death, that we ſhulde be taken from death vnto lyfe. Yf ye now cauſe the ſupper of oure Lorde to be vſed for you to ſuch intent as (Chriſt hath ordeyned yt: than are you admoniſhed to deſpyſe thys bodely death, whiche ye muſt abyde after youre ſykneſſe, and to thyrſt the lyfe tocome. Now yf ye vſe yt to optayne health therby, and to abyde longer in thys ſynfull lyfe: than do ye turne the vſe of yt and compell Chriſt to daunſe after youre mynſtrelſy, ye make a game of Chriſtes paſſion and glorious death, whoſe frute &amp; operation ye ſpurne from you, ſekynge therin to fulfyll youre ſenſualite, Thynke ye it be not a greate foly and dyſhonorynge of God, that you wyll haue the paſſyon of Chriſt called vpon and remembred for you to optayne bodely health therby or proſperite: Is it not a groſſe blyndneſſe

and folyſhneſſe to requyre ye health of your ſynfull body of ye death of chriſt? ye ought rather to conſyder the ſlayenge of youre carnall appetite in thys preſent ſufferynge through the croſſe, that now ye beare wyth Chriſt, becauſe yt through thys ſufferynge, and deynge wyllyngly ye maye lyue eternaly with chriſt. Ye ſeke eaſe and longe lyfe in Chriſtes croſſe, ye ought rather to ſeke pacient ſufferynge, and victory of death. What dede is this that ye hyer preſtes for golde or ſyluer to ſaye preuy maſſes for you? ye ſeke the kyngdome of God with marchaundyſe which is ſpirituall &amp; inwarde, and it cō
                  meth in vs without ony cōuention or cō
                  tracte precedīg yt. Knowe ye not that ye byers and ſellers are chaſed of God? Or wyll ye haue chriſt to come vpon earth agayne to bringe lyfe to you by a newe waye and maner and not thorowe death &amp; the croſſe. We lyue &amp; dye in God, what maketh it matter than wether ye lyue or dye in body? The father hath geuen chriſt all power, both in heauen, &amp; earth: than hath he alſo power ouer death, hel,

and all deuels. If ye ſeke eaſe another waye, other thys or that, more than of Chriſt, which is a trew phiſicion of oure ſoull, than ſhall ye be lykened vnto the woman that hadde ben ſyke ſo longe, and ſpent al hir ſubſtaunce in phiſyke to optayne health, and yet hadde no eaſe, whiche ſhe optayned mooſt ſureſt in Chriſt. It is a great plage and an horrible worke of Gods iudgmentes, that he ſuffreth vs to walke thus blyndfylde in oure owne inuented wayes, wherin we haue more cōbraunce of conſcience than reſte or yoie. The cauſe no doubte is that we wyll not herken to Gods worde, but ſtoppe oure eares whan we be admoniſheth therof, eſtimīg it as lyes. Wherfore god ſayeth pſal. lxxx. My people wolde not heare my voyce, and Iſrael wolde not obey my. So I gaue them vp vnto their owne hartes luſtes, &amp; let thē folowe their ymaginatiōs. Leſt we come to this let vs praye earneſtly wt the prophet ſayenge: Ordene me wayes in thy preſence my lord my god. Whā ye ſeke delyueraū
                  ce &amp; releaſe wt maſſ
                     •
                  s, &amp; pilgrimag, than

be not youre wayes redreſt in Gods preſēce: For theſe wayes hath not he ſhewed nor gone them hymſelfe. We repyne at hys wayes of the croſſe, of dyenge, of hū
                  blynge, we ſhoue them from vs wyth hande and fote. Oure wayes be eaſy to go they pleaſe vs beſte, all were well yf we coulde optayne releaſe therby, ye though the deuyll ſhulde helpe to it. Wherto is oure Chriſtendome become?
            
            
               Lazarus.
               I haue hadde now a ful anſwer of al: I am ſory I am gone ſo farre wyde from God My pardon letters, my reliquyes, my folyſſhe treatiſes of meditation, my beedes, and all ſuch ſuperſtitions, wherein I haue hadde a falſe confydence wyll I cauſe to be brent wythout delaye in wytneſſe that I counte it abominacion which hetherto I haue done wyth thē I yelde my ſelf to my Lorde God, In him wyll I lyue, in hym wyll I dye, he is the tower of my ſtrength, noman ſhal drawe me out of hys handes henſforth. Oh Lorde remembre not the myſdedes of my youth, and ignoraunce. O Tymothe yf

I were now whole, yf I coulde go, and ſtonde what luſt ſhulde I haue to ſerue God: how ſhulde I runne to them that lye bedryd, there to dyſtrybute myn almes: which now I can not do, ſeynge I am Gods preſoner.
            
            
               Tymotheus.
               Lo, ye come forth agayne with youre ſenſualyte, you begynne to diſpute agayne with God, you wyll checke hym in hys iudgment, knoweth he not how you maye ſerue him beſt, in ſiknes or health? And yf he knewe it not, ſhall ye teache it hym? It is hys wyll at this tyme that ye ſerue hym wyth ſufferynge mekely, and that ye receaue both thys, and other aduerſyte that he ſhall ſende you wythout grudgynge. Theſe be the pureſt and mooſt acceptable workes, of all that can be done without oure addinge therunto, For all that is added to this of men that is vncleane and ſynne. Where we onely do ſuffre, god workynge wythout hynderaunce there is the mooſt principall vertue, and the beſte worke. For as it is written: The obedience of the lawe, and the

wyll of God is better than al offerynges. and to be at hys commaundement is better than to offer all fat ſacryfyce. Be therfore ydle, ſtonde ſtyll, aſſaye, and ſe how good the Lorde is. Yf ye dyd conſydre the botome of youre harte a lytel whyle, you ſhuld perceaue what a falſe, and wylye felowe were hydde there cloked: you ſhulde fynde that in that ye ſaye: yf I were whole. I wolde ſerue God and my neghboure, ye entende not the ſame: but your owne loue, which cauſeth you to wyſh ſo for youre owne eaſe of this payne, and that ye myght lyue ſomwhat longer. It is now tyme to praye, and not onely in ye tyme of health. He yt nedeth is occaſioned to praye. The hypocrytes do praye wythout nede, for they be full, and ſatiſfyed, they be holy in theyr ſight. Ye praye dewly, whan ye offre youre wyllynge ſprete vnto God, and are redy to beare all that he pleaſeth to lade you wythall. Thys doth alſo the worde deuotion ſounde for Deuotion is a yeldynge or geuynge ouer of hymſelf to an other thynge: Happy is he that hath a trew

deuotion or yeldynge of hymſelf to God Such a man hath hys wyll alwaye: for hys wyll is fulfylled in all that can retyde hym, by the reaſon hys wyll is wholy yeldeth to God. For yt cauſe is he euer ſo wel cōtent, he wolde not ſtarte though he ſawe the deuyll, no though he muſt deſcende the hell. He that hath ſuch deuotion prayeth wythout ceaſſynge, wether he wake, ſlepe, go, ſtonde, reſte, laboure, although hys lyppes moue not, though he knocke not his breſte, though he 
                     •
                  alye not wt God wyth hys fyſry ſtykes, which all is but an hypocrytiſſhe game. It is great ſkyll to praye, and to ſaye much: To geue ouer the harte vnto God, and to make much rummelynge wyth the mouth dyffer much. Paul hadde leuer fyue wordes ſpokē in ye vnderſtōdinge: thā fyue thouſande wordes ſpoken wyth the breth of the mouth. God is a ſprete, and in ſprete and treuth wyll he be worſhypped. The almes dedes that you wolde geue yf ye where whole, doth not God eſteme for theyr multitude, but he regardeth the luſt, and wyll that ye haue to

them. A cuppe of colde water ſhall not God forgette, not for cauſe of the water, but for the good wyll of the geuer, which perchaunce is of no greater abylite. He that geueth one drawght of water vnto a prophet, in the name of a prophet, ſhall receaue the rewarde of a prophete. And why? For God regardeth the harte, and mynde, but man regardeth the outwarde worke. Thys teſtyfyeth the wedowe in the goſpell, that caſte onely cone farthynge in the Gods cheſte: which neuertheleſſe hadde geuen more than they that gaue great ſummes. Paul alſo ſayeth: Yf there be a wil
                     •
                  inge mynde, it is accepted accordynge to that a man hath, not accordynge to that he hath not. The pooreſt creature liuinge male geue as much almes as the rycheſt. Almes is a greke worde and ſignifyeth a mercyfulneſſe, or declaringe of a pytyful harte. Can not thynke ye the poore haue a mercifull, and compaſſionable harte towarde the, that be in pouerte, &amp; anguyſſhe, though theyr power can not extende to declare it? Yf theyr harte be thus moued to a lyuely

compaſſion, than haue they done almes ynough before God. Al that ye geue wythout ſuch a redyneſſe of harte is not counted for an almes before the Lorde. Of this redyneſſe of harte (which loue doth cauſe) commeth outward geuynge of almes. Whom I loue not, vpon hym haue I no compaſſion, nor I do no more ſuccoure hym than though hys pouerte, and grefe were not pertayninge to me. Wherfore Paul ſayeth though I gaue all my goodes to fede the poore, and yet haue no loue, it profyteth me nothynge. Thus be they not externall almeſſes, that make a man Chriſtian: But by geuynge almes he declareth hym to haue the loue of his neghboure and that he is a Chriſtian. Be content to be thus preſoned in body acordinge the wyll of God▪ praye to God in ſpirite, geue almes, viſyte ye poore wt your hart, ſeynge ye can not do it with the body, and God ſhall ſo accepte it as though, ye had done it wt ye dede. For he regardeth the harte.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Wold God I myght do it ſo well as I

wolde fayne. This fleſſhe is ſo ſlothfull. I can not bringe it to the croſſe, &amp; dyenge, which greueth me. Oh where tarieth he that ſhal redeme me? Oh whan I thynke thys, how narowe is the gate, &amp; how ſtrayght is the paſſage vnto death?
            
            
               Tymotheus.
               Be not diſcoraged in this aſſault, and battayll, but rather cōforte you wt the example of Chriſt ſayenge: I muſt be baptyſed wt another baptyme, but Oh how tedious am I before I can fulfyl it? This tedious baptyme beginneth now to wor worke in you, that you beynge clenſed of your olde ſinfulnes might become a new creature in god. As ye bodely byrth of our mother in this worlde is paynful: euē ſo ye goynge of it out agayne vnto the lyfe euerlaſtyng is on eaſy. But it is a cōforte agayne, yt like as a womā by brynging a new creature in to this worlde, is delyuered of hir burthē &amp; payn: euē ſo are we deliuered of this body by death, which is knitte wt ſinne, &amp; cauſeth vs alwaie to go aſtraie frō goe Morouer thīke (as it is in dede) yt ye do not ſuffre this grefe alone,

but that the Lorde doth aſſiſt thoſe that haue a contryte harte, and thē that be of a lowly ſpyrite ſhall he releaſe. The inwarde man (that is your ſprete) doth ſuccure your ſufferynge. Heare what is contayned in the Pſal. xc. Becauſe he hath ſet hys loue vpon me. I ſhall delyuer hym. I ſhall defende hym, for he hath knowen my name. Whan he calleth vpō me, I ſhall heare hym: Yee I am wyth hym in hys troubell, wherout I wyll delyuer hym, and brynge hym to honour. Satle youre mynde, God is faythful of hys promyſes: He ſhall not ſuffre you to be tempted aboue that ye maye beare. God ſendeth euery man temptaciō with meaſure, and not aboue hys power. Therfore ſayeth the prophet Dauid: you ſhall fede vs with the bread of teares, and geue vs teares to drynke with meaſure. Conſidre the ſayenge of the prophet Eſaye in hys .
                     •
                  iiii. chapter. A lytell wyle haue I forſaken the, but wyth great mercyfulnes ſhall I take the vp vnto me. Thys knowleged very well the prophet whan he ſayde: Accordynge to the multitude

of my woundes, haue the multitude of thy conſolations bene yoyfull vnto my ſoule. Whan ye be prayenge to the father fayth at your nede, how can ye father geue hys ſonne a ſtone? and yf you deſyred a fyſſhe how can he geue you a ſerpent? Seynge he hath promyſed to geue a good ſprete vnto thē that requyre hym Luc. xi. As the eyen of a handmayden be continualy fyxed vpon hyr mayſtres hā
                  de, ſo let oures alſo be vpon the Lorde oure God, vntyll he haue mercy vpō vs: Yt is ſufficient that youre inwarde man cōſenteth vnto the lawe of God, that it is good, which correcketh you in your ſynnes, and cauſeth you thus to ſyght. Paul alſo myght not do ye good which he wolde, but the euyll which he wolde not.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Where ſayeth Paul the ſame I praye you? for I fele it in me.
            
            
               Timotheus.
               In the .vii. chapter to the Romanes.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               I wyll cauſe the ſame chapter be red to me at leaſure I praye you ſhew my byen

ſamples how ſome are become ſtronger in fayth by temptacion, ſufferynge, ſykneſſe, and death: and agayne ſome offended &amp; weaker: for examples teache beſt.
            
            
               Tymotheus
               I wyll do it gladly at your inſtaunce. It was promyſed vnto Abraham by God, that in hys ſede all kinreds of the worlde ſhulde be bleſſed, &amp; yt he wolde multiplie hys ſede as the ſtarres of heauen. Abraham lyke a father of the faythful hath accepted theſe promyſes wt a ſure faith, truſtynge, it ſhulde ſo come to pas as God ſayde: though it was ſtraunge, becauſe he was olde and his wyfe baren▪ Now becauſe Abraham beleued thys, contrary to the hope of nature (for who wyll loke for frute of a womā of .xc. yeares) in that hope of the trew promyſes of God, was he counted ryghtuous, But wherfore is this wrytten of hym? Not onely for Abraham, but alſo for vs as ſayeth Paul in the .iiii. to the Romanes. For it ſhalbe rekened vnto vs alſo for a iuſtyfycatyon, yf we beleue in hym, which rayſed oure Lorde God Ieſu Chryſt, which was betrayed

for oure myſdedes, and is rayſed from the dead for oure iuſtyfycation. Thys fayth was perfectly good before god, but it muſt be proued and aſſayed for oure inſtruccion, by the temptacion folowenge. It is wrytten Geneſ. xxii. God hath tempted or proued Abraham, ſayenge: Take thyne onely ſonne Iſaak whom thou loueſt, and thou ſhalt 
                     〈◊〉
                   hym vpon an hyll, that I ſhall ſhewe thy Whan thys commaundement or temptacion was declared to hym, he myght haue repyned, and reaſoned, ſayenge: that God were not trew in hys promyſe: ſeynge he commaunded hym now to ſlaye that ſede, wherin he promyſed hym that all the ſedes of the worlde ſhuld be bleſſed. But he dyd not ſo, hys fayth remayned trew, and ſure in God, wente on ſtreght wyth a ſure confydence vpon Gods worde to offre vp hys ſonne, and to fulfyll Gods commaundement theryn. For he was ſure that God wolde rather rayſe hym vp a ſonne agayne of the very ſacrifice aſſhes, than that he ſhuld be founde a lyar. After thys

maner alſo was Iobs fayth tried, which had a wytneſſe of God, that he was a iuſt and ſymple man, fearynge God. Now whan thys goodman was ſtryken of Sathan in hys chyldren, goodes, and body, he fell to the grounde, and worſhipped god ſayenge: Bleſſed be the name of god: We haue receaued good of the hande of god, why ſhulde not we than alſo receaue the euyll? As it hath pleaſed god ſo is it happened: hys name be bleſſed. Lo folowe the pacience of thys man Iob in your ſufferynge, and ye ſhall not ſynne wyth youre mouth. Morouer good Tobias was not moued at hys blyndneſſe, but abode ſtedfaſt in the feare of God all dayes of hys lyfe, ſayenge God be thāked. For he perceaued welynough that temptacion was a ſure token that he ſhulde be counted in the nombre of the ryghtwyſe. The which Raphael the angell declared openly ſayenge: And becauſe thou waſt accepte and beloued of God yt was neceſſary that temptation ſhulde trye the. Thus haue they that pleaſed God euer den proued for eure comforte

that we alſo ſhulde not deſpayre, whan ony troubell is ſent to vs of oure welbeloued fathers hande. The carnall wyt can not perceaue nor comprehende, that trouble is profytable, and a tryall of our fayth: but as ſone as they get ony troubell, they be offended with the workes of god, ſayenge to all the ryghteous that ſuffre, as Iobs wyfe dyd: Do ye yet continue in your perfectneſſe? Curſe god &amp; dye As though they wolde laye: It is playn now that he is no god that thus ſcourgeth you, and vtterly forſaketh: why do ye truſt hym yet? Saye much good of hī that bryngeth death vpon you, for he is as worthy of youre bleſſynge as a wylfull murthurer to be ſaued. Shrenk frō hym, denye hym, and remembre ye be mortall, and that with thys lyfe ye paſſe all yeopardyes, truſt ye yet to optayne good thynges of youre Lorde? Theſe and ſuch lyke wordes enſpyreth oure wyfe ſenſualite into oure myndes, whan we be aſſaulted of troubel. For as than doth not the fleſſhe knowe nor fele that god vnder correction, and vnder the ſhyne of

hys wrath hath hydde louely countenaunce, and couereth ye trew lyfe in death, The frendes of the afore ſayde Iob alſo were offended through hys great myſery ſayenge: Whan dyd euer the innocent peryſſhe? whan were the ryghtwyſe deſtroyed? Call, loke wether ther be ony body now to geue you an anſwer, of the hope that ye had in the Lorde? Turne ye to ony of the ſayntes, and beholde wyther ſuch lyke dyd happen vnto them? Now ſe ye how the vngodly frendes, which take parte with oure fleſſhe, iudge oure acceptabelnes to God, by theſe worldly proſperytes. Beholde how carnall wyt eſtemeth that for a curſe, which fayth receaueth as a godly reioycynge. The frendes that loued Toby after the fleſſhe, dyd alſo mock the good man he beynge blynde, euen as thoſe that vnderſtonde nor the worke of pacyence, and the glory of the croſſe, ſayenge: Where is thy hope, for the which thou haſt done almes, and buryed the dead? this is the rewarde that ye haue for doenge good. But herken how Tobyas rebuked them

ſayenge: Saye not ſo, for we are the chyldren of holy men, and loke for the lyfe which God ſhall geue vnto them, that neuer turne theyr beleue from hym. Beholde thys ſtronge fayth of Tobyas: wyth ſuch an anſwer ſhall ye ſhoue, and auoyde the wycked in ſperacion of Sathan, that alwaye entyſeth you ſayenge: Are ye wytleſſe that ye loke for remiſſyon of ſynnes by the bloude, of Chryſte? and loke for the lyfe by death? Ye ſhalbe deceaued, for who is ryſen from death? Do not ye ſe how the fayth of youre Chryſt is denyed? Yf he loued you as ye thynke, wolde not he do you good? Yf he were a trewe ſauyoure, and trew god, he wolde not ſuffre you to lye here thus, he wolde not ordre you thus. I counſell you to let thys Chryſt go, what haue ye to wyth hym ſeynge he doth you no good, he doth onely fraye you, wyth hell, and lyfe tocome, herewyth wolde he fayne lede you as wyth a lyne. It is not as he maketh you beleue. Eate drink and be mery, ſatle youre harte vpon a ſwete grounde, as yt was yeſterdaye,

ſo ſhall it alſo be now. Lette vs eate, and drynke for what ſhall we haue more, tomorowe muſt we dye. Be not abaſhed with the folyſſhe fayth of Chriſt, I can accōlyſhe al youre deſyre here on earth Do not ye ſe how my ſorte is exalted in the worlde, and lyue at eaſe? they be welthy of ryches, they haue many frendes theyr houſes be wythout care, and they be not ſcourged, theyr cattell encreaſe, theyr flocke multiplyeth, theyr chyldren playe, and be mery, they play on inſtrumentes. What do ye gayne vnder the banner of the poore, wreched, naked, diſfygured, and crucyfyed Chryſt, ſaue onely pouerty, anguyſſhe, and cōtinuall croſſe? Lo, How hys diſcyples go by the ſtretes wyth ſore hyles, the be fooles, and nygardes, they be not able to geue a mouſe a meales meate, and whan they haue lōge ynough ſerued theyr maſter obeyenge hys commaundementes, at the laſt they be hewē, &amp; chopped, ſtykt, burnt, drowned, or come to ſuch lyke ſhamfull ende, what victory hath he thē gotten? Where do ye ſe him riſe agayne?

where ſe you the ſwearde ſhrenke from hym? The fyre conſumeth hym, and water ouerwhelmeth hym, where abydeth hys God, that ſhall not forſake him in ye poynt of death?
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Ah brother how ſhalbe able to eſcape theſe ſnares of the ſuttel fynde? Verely ſuch temptations haue of tymes made me ſo doubtfull and perplexe of harte yt I wyſte not wyther to ſhifte me ſelf. Yf God hadde not ſuſtayned me I myght haue ben fallen into deſpayre, and ben choked in myn vnbleue. I haue bē oft diſpleaſed with God ſeynge all thynges proſpered ſo well with them: and I, with them that be lyke me ſtroue agaynſt the moone and ſeuē ſtarres, labourynge and toylinge, cōmynge out of the one croſſe into another My thought yf I were god I wolde haue ordered the game other wyſe.
            
            
               Timothe.
               Verely brother the deuyll wyth his fleſhly pleaſures (which he layeth before mē to entyce them) hath a pleaſaunt begynnynge as a bye charged with hony: but

in ye ende is there a ſtynge. Yf ye behold ye luſtes of the fleſhe before with the heithē, than be they very pleaſaunt in the eye, as a fayre woman trymly deckte: but yf hyr bake be turned, than is it all horrible what ye ſe. Thys is the brode luſty waye wherof Chriſt ſpeaketh, ſayenge that many walke it yt, but ſhe bringeth to eternal dānation. The chyldrē of thys worlde yt lyue ſo welthy, paſſe theyr tyme in yoie, it is trew: but what foloweth? ſodēly they go downe to hell ſayeth Iob. xxi. dauid pſal. lxxii. ſayeth yt he alſo was nye ouercome with beholdīge of ye worldly men and was nye ouercome of the tēptacion of welth, as we all be ſomtyme ſayenge? My fete (that be the thoughtes where with the hart moueth) were almooſt gone, my ſteppes were neare ſleded. And why? I was greued at the wyked, to ſe the vngodly in ſuch proſpyte. For they are in no parell of death, but ſtonde faſt as a palace. They come in no myſfortune lyke other men, nother are they plaged lyke other folke. &amp;c. Wherfore brother I exhorte you not to be moued

at ſuch inſpirynges of the deuell, &amp; be not greued not offended with ye vngodly: for ye ſhall ſe theyr ende, how that they ſhall wyther lyke hey, and decaye as flores in the felde. Be renewed in the Lorde, and he ſhal accompliſhe the deſyres of youre harte. Say alwaye with the prophet It is good for me to continue by God, and to ſet my hope &amp; confidēce vpon my Lorde my god. The chyldren of god though they ſeme here in ye ſight of the ignoraunte to dye: yet is theyr porcion and herytage endurynge foreuer. Thys ſhall the wyked fynde trew herafter, and complayne whan yt ſhalbe to late, and wan they ſhalke counted amō
                  ge ſayntes, whom they ſomtyme haue taken here for mad men as the boke of Sap. ye .v. chapter doth playnly expreſſe. O Lazare yf it ſhulde be after your mynde, yt ſhulde not be well. If ye ſhulde rule the wagen one daye, yet one oure, heauē &amp; earth ſhulde runne on an heape, lyke as poetes do fayn that Phaeton dyd. Entre not to depe in gods iudgmentes, Let hym rule, he ſhall

ordre it better than we can deuiſe.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Ye ſaye trewth, We wyll haue a ſayenge in the matter, and wolde fayne by Goddes alſo: But yf we perceaued what yt meaneth, we ſhulde let god alone hardly Neuertheleſſe I cā ſkant truſt him to be my lorde my god my father: for he ſemeth ſomtyme ſo vtterly to haue forſaken me as though I were none of hys.
            
            
               Timothe.
               It is no ſtraūge thynge yt God ſemeth ſomtyme to haue forſakē you. Chriſt him ſelf hath felt it in hym, and ſuffred temptation wyllyngly to oure enſample and comforte, whā he hangynge on the croſſe for very great ſtrayghtneſſe of payne &amp; ſufferynge ſayde: My Lorde my God wherfore haſt thou forſaken my? Not yt he was euer forſaken or deſtitute of the godheade: but thys dyſeaſe hath he takē vpon hym wyllyngly, that we (as he geueth vs here a ſample) ſhulde call to the father in oure anguiſhe, which doubtleſſe ſhall hear vs, yee hath herde vs already in Chriſt before we call vpō him. For

it is written in the prophetes that he ſhal heare vs before we call vpon hym, and before oure prayer be finiſhed ſhal he haue herde vs. It is not poſſible a father cā leaue his chyldren in their mooſt neceſſite, Though a mother maye forgette the chylde, that is borne of hyr body: yet ſhal not I forget you ſayeth the Lorde God. That wytneſſeth the prophete ſayenge: The Lorde hath not wythdrawen hys viſage fro me, and whan I called vpon hym he herde me. Marke in the pſalter how pyteouſly Chriſt cōplayneth to hys father hys nede, whan he was come in ye depeſte of the ſee of tribulation. Beholde how Dauid complayneth hys neceſſite before God. I haue ſayde in the exceſſe of my mynde, I am caſt awaye Lorde. Therfore haſt thou herde the voyce of my prayer whan I called vpon the. Seynge youre temptacion and payne is comune with Chriſt and all other ſayntes. Therfore render thē to god: for he is more that is in vs, than he that is in ye worlde. Therfore maye he alſo comforte, helpe, and ayde more than health, ryches,

or frendes. Whā ye fele youre fayth wax feble and ſlacke, than drawe to chriſt wt the apoſtles hauynge a harty deſyre and ſaye: Lorde augment my fayth, and all youre ſykneſſe ſhall not be imputed you for ſynne.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               I thanke you now brother Timothe of youre vertuous and louely exhortation, which ye haue ſhewed my very brotherly Praye God inſtantly for me wreched ſynner that he wyll helpe myne vnbeleue, &amp; geue my pacience in all my ſufferynge: that I may ſet my harte at reſte in hym only, whiche is parte of myne herytage and paſſion, which ſhal alſo geue me mene heretage agayne, though by ſynne it is once taken awaye.
            
            
               Timothe.
               I wyll do it gladly and with all my hart good brother, Pardon me for I haue bē ouer longe with you.
            
            
               Lazarus
               No verely ye haue not: Come agayne ſoone or to morowe to enforme me more larglyer of the maſſe.
            
            
               
               Timothe.
               I wyll do yt. Oure neghbure Tobias wylbe with you to morowe, to teache you ſomwhat of dyenge.
            
            
               Lazaarus
               Let be yt ſo, I praye you let that honeſt man come.
            
            
               Timothe.
               He cometh euen nowe, God be wyth you
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Feare well good brother Timothe.
            
         
         
            
            ¶A dyaloge betwene Tobias &amp; Lazarus, wherin Tobias teacheth the ſyke Lazarus, that death is to be deſyred wyth a ſure fayth of the lyfe for tocome.
            Tobias cōmynge before Lazarus bedde ſayeth.
            Peace be in thys houſe. How is it wyth you Lazare?
            
               Lazarus.
               Ye be welcome brother: for I dyd longe for you: Take a ſtoole and ſyt by my yf ye pleaſe.
            
            
               Tobias.
               I wyll. How is it wyth you? Is it all after one?
            
            
               Lazarus.
               No no brother, It is well amended God be thanked of yt.
            
            
               Tobias.
               I am gladde of yt ſurely: I truſt it wyll amende once For the lorde is mercyfull, he forgeueth ſynne in tyme of trybulation, and is a defence to all them that call vpon hym wyth trewe deſyre. Whan ye father hath occupied ye rod ynough, than caſteth he her in to the fyre. Whan God hath ſtryken, than healen he agayne.

Do ye perceaue ony eaſe? your face pleaſeth not me beſt.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               I beleue ryght well that ye carcaſe doth rather fayde, yee I yelde it, for death is dew vnto it: but ye ſpirite &amp; fayth be ſure (thanked be God) and augment dayly, ſo that the longer I am ſyke the leſſe grefe I fele: My thynke I begynne euen to ſaye with the prophet: Thy rodde &amp; thy wande haue comforted me.
            
            
               Tobias.
               Good Lorde how fayne do I heare ſuch wytneſſe of fayth: Now ſpeake ye as a Chriſten man: I wolde not haue beleued that I ſhulde haue founde you ſo vertuouſly diſpoſed. I ſe well the hande of the lorde is not ſhortened. He can dayly cauſe men to ſpeake with newe tunges as he dyd hys diſciples on the wytſondaye. As I was laſt with you I departed ſorowfull, becauſe I herde nothynge of you but blaſphemyes &amp; murmurynges agaynſt God, ye were ſo vnpacient. But God hath now ſo endued you with hys mercy, yt ye maye ſynge a

Chriſtenly prayſe vnto his name.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Treuly brother, that as than I was ſo wyde from God, cauſed myne vnbeleue and the diſquiete conſcience of myne, for ſo much as I was preſoned and captyue with mans conſtitutions, and workes of myne owne choſynge: But now is the ſnare deſtroyed, and I am rydde of them: God hath geuen encreaſe vnto the worde that oure brother Timothe hath miniſtred vnto me.
            
            
               Tobias.
               God graunte you hys full knoledge, yt he maye be glorious in you foreuer. God hath geuen oure brother Timothe a ſingular grace in expoundynge ſcripture. I am ſure he hath geuē you many good exhortations of Chriſten pacience, and of mortifyenge of the olde Adam.
            
            
               Lazarus
               That hath he done earneſtly, and hath rebuked my conſcience of hyr hypocriſy, and looſed her by the workinge of God. I ſe now the blyndneſſe and errore that I haue ben ſeduced wythall hetherto. I

defye them in myn harte. Wyll ye know what I dyd yet yeſterdaye at euen.
            
            
               Tobias.
               What? I praye you brother?
            
            
               Lazarus.
               I ſhall tell: As ſoone as Timothe was gone out of my houſe, I coulde not kepe ye ioye of ye worde lōger cloſe in my hart: But I cauſed al my houſholde be called together, and rehearſed before them all that I herde of Timothe, inſomuch th
                     ••
                   they were ſtered therwyth, thankynge God for hys workynge it in vs. After that cauſed I be burnt all my pardon letters, my folyſhe treatyſes of deuotion. my beedes with all ye reliques and gooſtly gyftes that freers and nōnes ſent me, now one than another. Theſe cauſed I be burnt in the preſence of al my houſholde, becauſe that they whyche were offende by me in them, ſhulde ſe the wytneſſe of my fayth, to theyr ſtrenghtynge. Ought I not to haue done ſo?
            
            
               Tobias.
               In that haue ye done accordynge to

the goſpell This was a trew ſhryft, &amp; a trewe ſatiſfaction for youre ſynnes, I doubte not but ye haue receaued a trewe abſolution of hym that only can forgeue ſynnes, that is God.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Now is my deſyre of you good Toby, that ye alſo wyll teache me ſome good thynge out of the holy ſcripture to deſpyſe death, and to receaue it wyllyngly by fayth: For I haue receaued the ſentence of death. Fulfyll that which ye promyſed my by Timothe, and I wyll praye God entterly to geue me eares to heare, which hytherto haue ben ſtopped wt the fleſſhe, the whiche I feare not but he wyl do yt.
            
            
               Tobias
               Seynge ye hunger ſo ye worde of God. I wyll breake it vnto you in the name of God, ſo farre forth as he ſhall ſende me ſprete &amp; vtteraūce. Syt ye eaſſy ynough, or ſhall I rayſe you ſom what hygher▪ ye ye maye ſyt a
                     •
                   more eaſe.
            
            
               Lazarus
               No I praye you, for I was ſhyrted euen now. Begynne in the name of God muſt

ye wyll.
            
            
               Tobias.
               The philoſophers haue had diuerſe opinions of death, But in this the mooſt parte agreeth, that death is a partynge of the body and ſoule. In thys naturall departynge ſhall not we Chriſten men ſixe oure philoſophical eyen, nor iudge wt a hetheniſhe iudgmēt in this behalf. For as longe as we 
                     •
                  eſouie
                     •
                   our ſelues with ſuch conſyderation of 
                     〈…〉
                   ſight of death trayeth vs, ſo that we beg
                     •
                  nne to hate death therby, becauſe 
                     〈◊〉
                   taketh awaye the body which we loue, and ſo cauſeth vs to hate death naturally. Of which euell wil to ye natural death 
                     〈…〉
                   lefe the cauſe, which wyl 
                     〈◊〉
                   that naturaly death ſemeth to take awaye, as ſhalbe more euident herafter 
                     〈…〉
                   conſydre the death in ſuc
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  ig
                     •••
                   
                  
                     〈…〉
                   it were a paſſage frō death to 
                     〈…〉
                   conſyderation or beholdyng 
                     〈…〉
                   in vs, and that we ſha
                     •
                   not 
                     〈◊〉
                   in death, but ſhalb
                     •
                   rather 
                     〈…〉
                   Euen as Chriſt ſayeth 
                     〈…〉
                   and truſteth in the 
                     〈…〉
                   ſhall lyue, For 
                     〈…〉
                  ,

is counted lyfe to the beleuynge: but vnto the vngodly is it death euerlaſtynge. By this is appeareth vnto euery Chriſtē mā to be a lyenge word yt the Phyloſophers do ſaye, namely: That death is ye mooſt horrible thynge of all horribleneſſes. The cauſe why they ſayde ſo, was, that in their opinion by death man is depreued of the mooſt pleaſaunt thinge for euermore, which is not trewe. For a Chriſten man hath no greater charge, heuyer burthen, nor more enmy than the body of ſynne as ye ſhall heare more herafter. As ſuꝑſtition hath houghly faſhioned ye deuell to refrayn ſynninge euē ſo hath yt figured death alſo fearful, as ye rewarde of ſynne Accordīge to ye deſyre of ye lyfe to come ī vs, is death acceptable vnto vs &amp; pleaſaūt. Put awaye ye opinion of death frō your hart, &amp; you ſhal not feare death. The ſikneſſes &amp; the febelneſſes, which be tedious for our fleſhe to beare, &amp; make ye fleſhe euer weaker agaynſt the aſſault of death, they be not death: But the figure of death, that pearſeth in to vs before death by reaſons of vnbelefe, that is the

mooſt greueous and haynous death. So that we cauſe death vnto oure ſelues, as we cauſe other grefes alſo in our hartes. The very ſufferynge and departynge of the ſoule from the body is not in the poynte of death: but that we by conſyderynge of death we are drawen, compelled to leaue the body, that we ſet ſe great ſtoare by, and thys cauſeth death to be ſo bytter. Wh
                     •
                  rby ye maye perceaue yt the death, of ſynners is the worſt, &amp; mooſt bytter: ſeynge they mu
                     ••
                   forgo the beſt beloued thinge, that is the ſels. Now is the Chryſten fayth which we as chyldren of ſayntes haue confeſſed in baptyme) of ſuch nature, that it promyſeth, and ſheweth a ſure fayth of the lyfe euerlaſtynge through Chryſt
                     ••
                   death. Which faith and hope 
                     〈…〉
                   in vs all, that we ſa
                     •
                   great pryce by 
                     〈◊〉
                   kepte dylygently afore tyme, le
                     •
                  t it myght be taken from vs by death. This goodly ye well oure body, that we made ſo great of are we wyllynge 
                     〈…〉
                   to forgo by reaſon of ye 
                  
                     •
                  oue that we haue gottē to ye heauēly 
                     〈…〉
                  
                  
hath ſwalowed vp all worldy thynges: So that we do eſtyme it a great vauntage to be delyuered from this wreched body, that cauſed vs to wander and be abſent from God. The ſure waytinge for the glory tocome in vs deſpiſeth, ouercometh, and refuſeth all paynfull grefes, wherof ye vnfaythful (which feare death) be aſtonyed, and al the wayes poſſible they withſtonde death. Wherfore it is a trew ſayenge he dyeth well, that dyethyer he dye. As much fayth as a Chriſten man hath of the lyfe tocome, ſo much deſpiſeth he this tēporal death. And agayn As much vnbeleue as a Chriſtian hath towarde God and loue to hymſelfe ſo much doth he feare &amp; flye bodely death. Lo thys is the ſumme brefely touched of all, that can be ſhewed you of dyenge. By this ſhall ye alſo perceaue welynough that death is not to be feared, in ſo much as ſhe is rydde of hyr ſtynge and venym: yt is ſwalowed vp in the victory of Chriſt, which hath ouercome hym that had power of death (that is the deuyll) to ye health of all faythfull which

ſhall optayne heauen accordynge to the abylite of theyr fayth.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Alas brother ye haue geuen me ſo much atonce to eate, that I can not ſwalowe it all: ye muſt geue it me by peces, as Tymothe hath done, that I maye come to the playne vnderſtondynge.
            
            
               Tobyas.
               That I may do it comely I muſt begynne where Timothe hath left. I tolde you that he dyeth well which dyeth before he dye. Thys fyrſt dyenge is in the mortifyenge or ſlayenge of the olde Adam that is oure ſenſuall appetytes. The ſen, ſual appetytes that liue in you, and muſt be ſlayen in you are loue of thy ſelf, luſt to ydelneſſe, pryde and boaſtynge, appetyte to vengeaunce, prouokynge to anger, inordinate loue to your wyfe, chyldren and frendes deſyre of bodely health wyſſhynge of temporall fortune, loue of thyſelf, and bodely or gooſtly worke. In theſe thynges doth oure olde man couet to lyue longer and longer. Theſe deſyres are mortyfyed, and ſlayē in vs by the

ſpryte of God, in the new byrth of the inwarde man, which reſteth in God, and is at once with God what that euer betydeth him wether it be in body, in goodes, in lyfe or death, in frendes, in name or fame: Yee though hys body were grounde all to poulder, yet wolde not he gaynſaye it, nor departe from God therfore, which cauſeth hym to aſſaye inwardly, thorowe the ſpyrite of fayth, howe ſwete and good the Lorde is. To thys dyenge exhorteth vs ſcrypture. To thys reſt and Sabath draweth vs the ſpyrite of God. So much as ye be crucyfyed in the aforeſayed ſenſuall appetyte, ſo much gooſtly increaſe gett you in the inwarde man, which doth not ſhrenke for all that, nor ſuffre the croſſe to ouercome hym, but aprocheth rather nearer, pearſynge vnto death, wherhy his truſt is to gayne lyfe, which fayth, and hope ſhall not be gayn ſayd as ſayeth Paul in the .ii. to the R
                     •
                  
                  ▪ Thys vnderſtondynge or diuynyte that ye haue herde here is declared vnto you, in the ſcryptures folowenge▪ Namiy: Go forth with Chryſt Ieſu youre brydegrmoe

wythout the tentes of your ſenſualyte, and beare the lowlynes of youre brydegrome with you in youre body vnto death: For yf we dye with Chryſt, we ſhall alſo lyue wyth hym: yf we ſuffre wt hym we ſhal raygne wt hym. Ye thanke the father yt he by thys ſufferynge hath made you apte to enyoie one parte wyth all ſayntes, that he hath redemed you from all power of darkneſſe, and ſet you in the kyngdome of hys beloued ſonne, thorowe whoſe bloude we haue obtayned forgeuynge, and redemption, of ſynnes. Seynge then ye 
                     •
                  e become a party membre of Chryſt, fulfyll therfore in you that, which is wantynge of the paſſyons of Chryſt that the power of God maye abyde in you
            
            
               Lazarus▪
               
               How ſhall I vnderſtonde that hath not Chryſte ſuffred ynough? what 
                     〈◊〉
                   I fulfyll that is lackynge in his paſſions ſeynge there is no parte of 
                     〈…〉
                   
                  
                     •
                  ounde, from the toppe of the 
                     〈…〉
                   
                  
                     •
                  o the 
                     •
                  o
                     •
                  e of the 
                     〈…〉
                  
                  
Yt is Paul that ſayeth ſo, namely, that he dyd fulfyll in hys body that, which was lackynge of Chryſtes afflyction, yee he durſt ſaye alſo that he dyd beare the markes of Chryſt in hys body: Which be not the .v. woundes that Francis dreamed to haue receaued in hys handes, and fete: But they were the markes that he hadde receaued of the ſcourgynge, weeryneſſe laboure, and the croſſe that he was fayne to beare paciently for the goſpell. In which pacience he was ſayde to beare Chryſtes paſſion, and to receaue hys woundes: for Chryſt had fyrſt boren ſuch payne, perſecutiō, markes, and croſſe, In ſo much yt he was drawen out, and emptyed wt ſufferynge, As ſayeth Eſaye. liii. Whan we loke vpon hym there ſhal be no fayrneſſe, we ſhall haue no luſt vnto hym. He ſhalbe the mooſt ſymple, and deſpyſed of all, which yet hath good experience of ſorowes, and infirmites. We ſhall reken hym ſo ſymple and ſo vyle, that we ſhall hyde oure faces from hym. How be it (of a treuth) he onely taketh awaye oure infyrmyte, &amp; beareth awaye

oure payne. So that he myght wel aſke wether there were ony payne lyke vnto hys payn? For he ſemed a worme and no man. Seynge Chryſt the head of ye whole congregation of Chryſten men toke vpon hym to ſuffre, yt was nedefull than that he ſhulde aſcende the hygheſt degre to the which greate loue hath dryuē him that he ſhulde ſanctifye hys congregation beynge pure, and waſſhed with the fountayne of water in the worde that he ſhulde gloryfye it hauynge no ſpot, nor wrenkle, nor ony ſuch blemyſſhe but that it ſhuld be holy and wythout blame The head Chryſt ſuffreth yet dayly in hys membres. Thys paſſion ſhall he be fayne to ſuffre, till the tyme that he ſhall haue caſt all his enemies vnder his fete. That is: whan he ſhall delyuer vp hys kyngdome vnto his father .ii. Corin. xv. Who ſoeuer therfore is crucified with Chryſt (that is) who ſoeuer ſlayeth, and kylleth his carnall appetites, and perſueth them hatefully, as oure ſynnes be hatefully perſued in Chryſt vntill death he doth ſupple in his body that which is

lackynge of Chryſtes paſſyon. For Chryſt is ſayde to ſuffre that, which hys membres do ſuffre, or ſhall ſuffre. Euen as Chryſt ſayde to the commune perſecutor of the Chryſtiās: Saul, Saul, I am that Ieſus whom thou perſecuteſt. How coulde he perſecute Ieſu, which ſat at the ryght hande of hys father ſaue onely in hys membres.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               I haue vnderſtonde that very well now that it is a paſſyon which fyrſt Chriſt as head, and ſo all other trewe Chryſten men as membres haue ſuffered, or ſhall ſuffer: For whan the head is ſyke, than mourne all the membres, and whan the membres be dyſeaſed, the heade is not well nother.
            
            
               Tobyas.
               You haue vnderſtonde me well, wherfore let it be for you conſolation that you be not forſaken alone, but that Chryſt hymſelf as head, and all Chryſtians as members are ſufferynge with you. In Chryſtes communalty is no ſtryfe, nor parcialyte, but a communion or felowſhyppe

of al that is good or badde, ſwete or ſowre, the one membre careth for another. Whan the one ſuffreth, al do ſuffre, whan the one is glorifyed than be they all glorifyed. So great a thynge is the communion of ſayntes, that we maye glory and reioyce the one in the goodneſſe of the other, as though they were oure owne. By the glory of Chryſt ſhall oure diſhoneſty be glorifyed. And by his fulnes ſhal we be loſed of our pouert, his merytes ſhal put awaye oure myſdedes. Who is he now yt is in paine yt wold not be mery, ſeynge man beareth not his ſynnes, or yf he beareth thē he bearethē not alone, for he hath Chryſt hīſelf to helpe hī, &amp; ſo many chyldren of God. Paul ſayeth .i. Corinth. x. One breade, and one body are we many. Thys all commeth vpon vs out of the ſpyrytuall maryage, which God oure father hath made wyth hys onely beloued ſonne, and vs. For thereby are we made one wyth God as man and wyfe are twain in body, and all other thynges are commune. A chylde is borne vnto vs, and a ſonne is geuē
                  
vs Eſaye .ix. Wherfore he is oure owne Chriſtes victory: is oure victory: Chriſtes ryſynge is oure ryſynge. Morouer yt which we are, we are not of our ſelues for we haue yeldeth to Chriſt oure fayth already. Paul ſayeth .i. Corin. vi. Knowe ye not that your body is the temple of ye holy gooſt? Whome you haue of God, &amp; are not your owne. For ye are dearly bought. Prayſe ye God therfore in your body and in your ſprete, which are Gods We be deliuered ouer in writinge vnto the lawe of God, and hys promiſes, and he is agayne delyuered in wrytinge vnto vs to ſaluation and welfare. The bonde of matrymony muſt be knowen on both partyes orels is it of none effecte. Thus is it reſonable yt we beare Chryſt in oure body, euen as he beareth vs, and maketh vs partakers of all hys goodes So that the Chryſtenly bryde may ſay. My loue is myn, and I am hys.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               That ſame is very comfortable, that Chriſt hath accepted vs, and geuen hym ſelf vnto vs. Wherby we haue receaued

hys lyfe for oure death, his ſtrength for oure weakneſſe, hys ryghtwyſneſſe for oure ſynnes. But whan beare we Chriſt in oure body?
            
            
               Tobias
               Where we be contrary to Chriſt and folowe not hys learnynge, enſample, and ſpirite, ther do not we beare Chriſt. Ther be we ryd of Chriſt▪ Paul ſayeth .ii. Cor. xiii. Knowe ye not your ſelues, that Ieſus Chriſt is in you? Except ye be caſtawayes. Thoſe than that through the ſpirite of God be obeyenge in all pacience, redy to obey Gods cōmaundements, in redringe and delyuerynge thēſelf to the wyll of God, compelled and made luſty harted, They maye ſaye wt Paul: I lyue now, not I, but chriſt liueth in me: Paul had alſo crucified hys fleſhe with his cō
                  cupiſcences, ſo that the worlde became hym a croſſe, and he a croſſe vnto the worlde agayne. He was ſayde to beare Chriſt in his body, for his body was dayly deſtroyed through the croſſe, lyke as the body of Chriſt was ſlayne by the croſſe and ſufferynge. To ſuch lyke mortifyenge

exhorteth vs Paul Rom. xii. ſayenge: I beſeke you brethren by the mercyfulneſſe of God, that ye geue ouer your bodyes for a ſacrifyce that is quyck holy, and acceptable vnto God which is youre reſonable ſeruynge of God. Thys is an acceptable ſacrifyce which is conſumed of the brande of ſufferynge (which we do beare wyllingly with Chryſt) lyke a trew burnt offeringe. For in the daye of trybulation we offer vnto God a trew ſacryfyce of prayſe (that is) the frute of oure lyppes in knoledgynge hys name. That we (as the payne of oure body cō
                  meth plentuous vpon vs) knoledge the name of Chryſt, that is a token, that we be Chryſtes diſciples &amp; guyded by hys ſprete by the which he hath bene obedient to hys fathers wyll vnto the death of the croſſe. Orels ſhulde we be lyke them that beleue ſo longe as all thynges proſper, but in tyme of temptacion than do they ſhrynke. The ſpyryte of fayth teacheth, and aſſureth vs that Chryſt in oure ſufferynge is oure comforte, and in oure dyenge oure lyfe. The

ſacrifyce of prayſe ſhall worſhyppe me (ſayeth the Lorde) and there is the waye wheryn I ſhall ſhewe my ſaluation. A dead, and mortifyed harte is a ſacrifyce very acceptable before God. He that hath mortifyed hys naturall body here in earth, he that is dead in hys harte▪ he that beareth Chryſt in hys body, becauſe he wyll go wyth Chryſt wythout the tentes of hys harte, wythout the gate, bearynge the rebukes of hys ſauyour wyth hym on hys ſhulder: he ſhall not fear death, he ſhall not eſtymed death hys enmy, nor flye yt: For ſhe taketh not it, which he wolde rather kepe but ſhe geueth hym that, which he wolde kepe wyth all hys harte. The lyfe temporall is ſwete vnto the fleſſhe, but oure lyfe yt we ſhall lede with Chryſt is ſweter.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Treuth it is, and therfore is death vnto vs paſſage to lyfe. Wherfore we ought to praye hartely that he let not vs fall in ſuch temptacion that myght ouercom vs: but that he wyll delyuer: in vs that euell daye, from all euell that myght

drawe vs from the fayth. For it is the myghty worke of God to beleue that we be hys, yee euen in the poynte of death, the which as yet I do not fele in me. For I fele yet another lawe in me which is contrary to the inſpyracion of the holy gooſt. I loke aboute for the fleſſhe pottes of Egypte, whervpon I was wont to ſytte. Whan the fygure of death offereth it ſelf from afore, than do I ſearche wether, I can not eſcape behynde out of thys wreched lyfe. Seynge I am ſo bounde with ſynne. I ought to be obedient at Gods callynge and wythout lokynge aboute departe: but I beſeme the wyfe of Loth. I can not leaue the lokynge aboute, though my neke laye theron. My wyfe the fleſſhe wherwith I am laden, is yet very feble to withſtonde ſuch temptacion. Alas brother I can not awaye with thys wyfe.
            
            
               Tobyas.
               Feare not good brother feare not, for ſuch totynge and lokynge backwarde, ſuch battayll, and febelneſſe dyd alſo Paul fele, whan he beholdynge hys wrechedneſſe

ſayde in the .vii. to the Roma. O wreched man that I am, who ſhall delyuer me from the body of thys death. It is neceſſary ſuch aſſaultes come vpō vs. Victory commeth by fyghtynge agaynſt ſynne, and of victory commeth tryumphe, but noman ſhalbe crouned ſaue he that fyghte deuly. Yf ye wyll triumphe with Chryſt ouer ſynne, &amp; death wythout battayl, that can not be: for ſuch waye hath not Chryſt ſhewed you. Fight lyke a trew ſouldyer of Chryſt. That we feare death, and ſhrenck at it is naturall weakneſſe the cauſe, Which is not damnable: for ſhe is not imputed to vs for ſinne. Yee Chryſt hyemſelf hath taken ſuch weakneſſe vpon hym for vs, whan he beganne to ſhouer, to tremble, and to be heuy for the death tocome, ſayēge: My ſoule is heuy vntyll death. Mat. xxvi. Why dyd he ſo? ſeynge he knew death coulde not hurt hym. He knewe well he ſhulde ſe no corrupcion. Why was he afrayed? He knewe hys death ſhulde brynge lyfe vnto vs all, and ouercome death, why dyd not he rather reioyce in that death,

wherof ſhulde come ſo much goodneſſe? what ſhulde it greue hym than to dye? wold he rather haue had delaie of it? dyd not he wyſſhe vs ſuch mercy and welfare ſeyng he ſemed to couet to be looſe of this ſufferynge. Alas no, that be farre. But ſeynge he toke vpon hym bare man heade, yt pleaſed hym to aſſaye the weakneſſe of manhode, becauſe we ſhulde not faynte yf lyke temptacion aroſe agaynſt vs: Wherof no man lyuynge (be he neuer ſo holy) is fre. For how ſore the inwarde man is lyghtened of the ſpyryte, yet doth the olde Adam, the wyfe of Loth not forſake hyr kynde in fyghtynge, and deſyrynge agaynſt the ſpyryte. Which battayll and deſyres we ouercome, and haue ouercome by fayth, that aſſureth vs to haue a trew byſſhoppe by God the father, namely Ieſu Chryſt, which hath bene tempted in all poyntes, that he myght knowe how to helpe them that be proued. The Lorde is trew, for he can proue, and delyuer the good Chriſtians out of temptations agayn. Chriſt which knewe no ſynne, is become ſynne for vs,

that we ſhulde be the iuſtyfycacion, or ryghtwyſneſſe of God in hym. Chryſt hath damned ſynfulneſſe of ſynne in hys fleſſhe. Synne is dāned, and put awaye in Chryſt: ſhe can not damne vs ſhe muſt be auaylynge vnto ryghtweſneſſe, ſo farre is ſhe come. Chryſt iuſtyfyeth vs, and who can blame vs? Chryſt diſchargeth vs of all ſynne, what deuell, or what fleſſhe is it than that can laye ony ſynne or fault to vs, The ſykneſſes and weakneſſes that ye haue after ye be Chryſtened, haue ye commune with al ſayntes, them ſhall ye fele other more or leſſe, vntyl the body of death be whole, and clene put awaye. Be not moued at the ſmall Babylonyans, that is the worldly thoughtes or hys pleaſures: but knocke them agaynſt the trew corner ſtone Chryſt, wherby ye ſhalbe ſaued. What do we loke for after thys lyfe? What pleaſaunt thynge perceaue ye in it, that myght cauſe you to deſyre a longe lyfe? What is thys lyfe, ſaue a contynuall battayll and croſſe, a deadly enemyte, and continuall hatred? What is it but a preſon

of ſynne? For the euell that we hate, that we do: and the good that loue, that we do not. The grace and mercy through Ieſu Chryſt muſt delyuer vs, orels ſhall we ſtyck faſt by the fete. We haue here no abydynge cyte, but ſeke and longe for another that is commynge. For we know (yf at the leaſt we be beleuynge) that yf the earthy dwellynge place of oure body be corrupte, and deſtroyed we haue a buyldynge ordeyned of God, an houſe not made with handes: but euerlaſtynge in heauen. ii. Corinth. v. That we now therfore ſygh and grone, lokynge about before we can be ryd of this body, that is becauſe we wolde fayneſe, and couet to be clothed with the heauenly duellynge place wythout puttynge of, and auoydynge of thys earthy cloth and dwellynge place. We wolde fayne retayne thys fylthy ſack, becauſe of the company that we haue had wyth it, ſo that it which is mortall myght be ſwaloued vp of the lyfe immortall, wythout aſſayēge of death. But that can not be: Seynge it is ordened for man once for to dye. And that we

ſhulde leaue herein earth by partynge of the ſoule that, which we haue receaued of the earth. And well is vs, that God ſeynge oure myſery hath pytyeth vs, makynge our death ſafe through his death: For he is become a death vnto death, ſo that death hath no fearfulneſſe in her, ſaue onely hyr vyſure to fray them that be chyldyſſhe in fayth, and vnderſtondynge But vnto the faythful and them that haue vnderſtondynge, is ſhe depryued of hyr ſtynge, and venyme. Yf ye auoyde youre mynde of the grymneſſe and vtter appearaunce of her, than ſhall ye fynde no death more in her. Go boldli to death, breake open hys yawes, loke what is in hym. Yow ſhall fynde no lyfe, no power or ſtrength in hym to byte you. Prouoke hym boldely to mete you in the fyghtynge place, and he ſhall flye from you. Defye death with all them that can holde wyth hym, for they can not harme you, they can not mynyſſhe one heer of you. Saye hardely wyth the prophet Oſe. O death where is thy ſtynge? O hell where is thy gloriation or reioycenge

The death is ſwalowed vp in Chriſtes victory. And therfore is death called in ſcripture a ſlepynge more thā death. Of this haue you a goodly fygure, The braſen ſerpent that Moſes made Numeri. xxi. ſemed afarre of to haue ben a ſerpēt in dede, but yf ye dyd aproche vnto yt, than might ye perceaue welynough that it was a dead ſerpent, and that it had no venym, that it coulde nother byte nor ſtynge. Euen ſo is it wt death, outwarde it hath a fearfull viſage, but the power of it is take awaye by Chriſt: For he hath ouercome him yt had power of death, ye deuyll, as ye ſhall heare more herafter.
            
            
               Lazaarus
               Youre declaration that ye haue ſhewed here is very ſpirituall, I beleue it be all as ye ſaye: yee &amp; I am well pleaſed there with. Yet do I perceaue that goodmen, which haue ſuch felynge and knoledge in themſelues (that is to wete that the death of Chriſt is death vnto ye natural death) as well as the euell and bad, do ſhrenke &amp; wrenche at ye poynt of death as though death had yet power vpō them.
            
            
               
               Tobias
               Treuth it is that the waye which bryngeth vs to lyfe is ſtrayght, &amp; the porte of death narowe. Wherfore we cā not paſſe vnto death by ſufferinge wtout ſtrayghtneſſe &amp; pearſynge: but what is yt vnto the lyfe &amp; health: The body muſt fulfyll hys naturall courſe, it ought not nor can do otherwyſe, it cā but wrenche, pinche, ſhouer &amp; kyke. Let ye aſſe beare ye truſhe hardely, it maketh no matter, yet for all this wyl not we feare death. Yf death can do nought more, what awayleth much repinynge &amp; wrenchynge: it is light to be ouercome, thys wrēchinge may be permitted him welinough, al is for one euell houre, Let ye fleſhe ꝑceaue in it ſelf ye teſtamēt of Adā vnto ye laſt houre. We haue nought now to walke in ſaue hope: this hope &amp; abydīg of ye life tocome, ſhal cauſe vs rightwel to ouercome ye ſorow &amp; wo of death, &amp; hayſtely to forget it. It is but yt bytīge of a fle, yt hurteth not ye ſoul. The death is better for vs thā we can thynke: ſhe loſeth vs of al miſery, ſhe ioyneth vs to god, &amp; ſendeth vs forth to euerlaſtynge

lyfe Let Heythē and Turkes feare death which haue no fayth of the lyfe tocome: But oure conuerſacion and thoughtes are in heauen, for from thence do we abyde our Lorde Ieſu Chriſt, which ſhall reſtore oure caſtawaye body agayne, makynge it cōformable vnto his glorifyed body. Yf we hadde not this hope of the partynge of the body, truſtinge no lenger in Chriſt than durynge thys lyfe: than ware we as ſayeth Paul. i. Corint. xv. the mooſt abiecte and refuſe of al mē: But now is Chriſt dead &amp; ryſen agayne, yt we ſhuld alſo ryſe again in hī in a new life Death is oure laſt enmy yt holdeth vs frō the lyfe, thys muſt once be ouercome me in vs alſo. Chriſt dyed for nought yf he hath not anulled the power &amp; lawe of death. Chriſt is not ryſen from death yf we muſt abyde in death. Yf Chriſt be not ryſen, than is oure fayth vayne, than abyde we damned in oure ſynnes, than is ſcripture a lye, than be the apoſtles alſo and ye prophetes falſe wytneſſes of God, That be farre. For Chriſt dyed and is ryſen agayne, that he ſhulde haue dominion

ouer quycke and dead. Wherfore, as we all dye in Adam, ſo ſhal we be relyued agayne in Chriſt, of which relyuyng agayne Chriſt hath made a profe in him ſelfe, Therfore ſayeth Paul: If the ſprete that hath rayſed vp Chryſt from the dead dwell in you, thā ſhal ye ſame ſprete relyue youre mortall body, by the ſpirite that dwelleth therin.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Than wyll not I be moued, though the fleſhe do ſomtyme ſygh and mone becauſe of death, and the fayntneſſe of payne, but wyll abyde alwaye the redemption tocome with a lyfted vp heade that is wt a mery ſpirite. For yf I ſhulde conſydre all thynges, what els is in this valley of teares ſaue payne and anguiſhe, ſynne and wyckedneſſe.
            
            
               Tobias.
               The poetes and Phyloſophers eſtymed death to be a good thynge, becauſe yt is the ende of all wrechedneſſe, and a reſt of all euell. Many Heythen haue bē leſſe abaſſed for the death than we are. Socrates dyd drinke his death laughynge.

He tought yt death is not to be feared, yt which he dyd fortify with the dede. Yf the fleſhly affection, and hye mynde of Socrates to fortyfy and to ſtrength hys doctrine, myght not ouercome the naturall feare of death: What ſhall than do ye certaynte of oure fayth that be Chriſten men, (that is) they that knowe they can not dye? Ought not than the hope of the lyfe tocome take from vs the beholdinge of death? Though the iuſt and faythfull ſeme to dye in the ſyght of ye ignoraūte, whā they be burned, drouned, beheaded, yet do not they once ſe death: I wyll not ſaye aſſaye ye death, for they dye in peace· They were dead afore in God by geuīge themſelues ouer to God, and he yt dyeth in God, lyueth eternally. Happy are they that dye in the Lorde, for their dyenge is chaunged in to lyuynge. That is it that Chriſt ſayeth: He that kepeth my worde, ſhall not dye foreuer.
            
            
               Lazarus
               They haue alwaye made hell ſo whote 
                     •
                  nto vs and the deuell ſo blake, that we 
                     •••
                  ſte not whether to turne oure ſelues.

They made vs ſo afrayde of death, and chefely in that they ſayde that the deuell appeareth vnto vs very horrible commynge to tempte vs of thys or that euell wherby euery mā feared death. But where was the worde of God thā which promyſeth: That we that beleue in Chriſt ſhal neuer aſſaye, nor ſe death. Haue theſe falſe teachers, and blynde leaders neuer ſene ſuch euangelicall ſcripture, nor red, nor herde thē.
            
            
               Tobias.
               Though they haue ſene, herde, and red it, yet haue not they beleued it: For the prince of this worlde hath blynded their myſbeleuyng hartes. Where is no faith there is a perpetuall diſquietnes of conſcience, there is a hell, a fearfulneſſe, yee a ſee full of all fearfulneſſe, remorſe, and myſbelefe. There is hell whote, and the deuell blake, there is a perpetual rackinge place of a ſynfull conſcience. In the waye of the ſynners is greate trauayll &amp; laboure, as wytneſſe they thēſelues ſayē
                  ge: We be weryed in ye waye of wyckedneſſe, we haue trauayled many wayes, and the waye of trueth hath not ouerſhadoweth

vs. That is it that the wyſe man ſayeth: The harte of the wyked mā is lyke a ſee toſſed with the waues. And becauſe theſe hypocrytes and workholyons ſeke peace where as they fynde no peace, but greate diſquietneſſe and troubell, for the vngodly haue no peace ſayeth the lorde God: therfore thynke they it be ſo with euery man as it is with thē. They thynke euery man be ſo doubtfull and vnſtedfaſt harted as they be, yee becauſe they eſtyme them ſelues more holyer and better than other, therfore thinke they other muſt fele whoter fyre than they themſelues, and that other muſt fele the gnawenge worme more in theyr conſciences than they. Wherfore they augment and make the lawe, the deuell, and death more haynous before mens eyen. They that be the mooſt fearfulleſt (as theſe be) vnto them wyll they be more horrible and dredefull with wordes and other thynges: wherby they be become nothynge but rackers of the ſimple. I beleue their worme neuer reſt, &amp; their fyre be neuer quenched. I beleue right well

they go aſtraye, fyndyng no reſte wyth ye manſlayer Cayn. I beleue they runne faythleſſe with Iudas to the preſtes and freers to be ſhryuen, for cōfort and reſte, but they abyde ſtyll deſperate. I beleue right well they be ready to do ſatiſfactiō for theyr ſynnes with Antiochus, and of miſtruſt geue mony to praye for thē: But al theyr faſtynge, prayenge, goynge wolwarde and barefote, all their mulynge and bablynge ſhall not helpe thē. Whether ſoeuer they turne them ſelues, they fynde alwaye ſynne preſent, they mete al waye the deuyll and death in the tethe. Howe can theſe teache otherwyſe than they finde? How ſhuld they preache ye goſpell of peace yt neuer tayſted peace? How ſhulde they inſtructe another in Gods behalfe of his atonement, of his reſt and victory of death, and his aſſuraunce frō hell, whiche haue no fayth therof? Let none of theſe deuel martyrs make you thus folyſhe, or wytleſſe. If ye haue the worde of God, yt ſheweth you peace &amp; forgeueneſſe, you haue God. Where reſt is there is God, there is an euerlaſtynge cō
                  uenaunt.

There is roted out the feare of death, ye deuell, &amp; hell. For feare is not in loue, but ſhe excludeth feare. Paul ſayeth: We that be iuſtifyed by fayth haue peace by God. He that is iuſtified thyſwyſe by the trew fayth of Chriſt, though he ſawe the deuell, death, &amp; hel with hys eyen, yet wolde not he be abaſhed, yee he wolde rather fyght agaynſt them &amp; ouer come them, than he wolde flye one fote, And why? for the gates of hell, that is ye power of theſame, can not optayne the victory of Peters fayth. Sayntes haue ouercome kyngdomes by faith, wrought ryghtweſneſſe, and optayned the Godly promyſes. The prophet ſayeth: Though a battayll a roſe agaynſte me in that wyl I hope. Though I muſt go through the myddeſt of death, yet ſhall not I feare, for thou art with me lorde. Thou haſt prepared a tabel before me againſt myne enmyes. Be of good cymforte (ſayeth Chriſt) for I haue ouercome the worlde. That is ye victory yt ouercōmeth ye world euē your faith ſayeth Iohn. ¶Lazarus you haue declared me that ſo clearly

that! I euen reioyce therin and feare death leſſe than afore. Let here come. whan it ſhal pleaſe God. I knowe by experiēce welynough, what fearfull cōſcience I haue had in myn vnbelefe, &amp; ī my mooſt vertuous workes, ye nede not to make farther declaration in this behalf. Neuertheleſſe this I require yet of you, yt ye wil ſhew me how I ſhall behaue my ſelf beſte henceforth, whā the tēptaciō of ſyn, death, or hell ſhal aſſault me.
            
            
               Tobyas
               In ye .iiii. of mat. is it eyudēt how ye ought to behaue yourſelfe agaynſt tēptaciō of the deuell, or of ſynful deſyres, which alſo be one kīde of deuels. Lo how chriſt ſuffered himſelf to be tēpted of glutony, of preſumptiō, of couetuoſneſſe, to proue yt we be dayly tēpted of the ſame deuel or rather worſe, &amp; to an exāple &amp; cōfort yt ſuch tēptaciō can not harme vs no more thā they haue ouercome Chriſt. Marke how Chriſt hath ouercome &amp; chaſed the ſame deuell wt al hys tēptacions, to an exāple that we muſt kepe theſame ſure grounde, yf we entende alſo to ouercome

the deuell, and to chace hym from vs wythſhame. Chriſt hath ouercome wt none other weapons ſaue only Gods worde, all thoſe that dyd withſtande him other hell, death, or the deuell, for all theſe haue ben enmyes to God as you maye rede in the .xvii. pſalme. The ſorowes of death haue compaſſed me, and the brokes of vngodlyneſſe made me afrayed. The paynes of hell came about me, ye ſnares of death toke holde vpon me. But what foloweth. Yet in my troubell I called vpon the Lorde, and complayned vnto my God. So he herde my voyce out of hys holy temple. Learne to take your flyght to the Lorde with Chriſt, whiche beynge man, and proued in all thinges that he myght ſuccour them that be tēpted, hath done ſo before. Learne to defende youre ſelues with the weapons of Gods worde: for as Chriſt hath ouercome the deuell, ſo maye you ouercome hym alſo with all hys ſuttel wyles. To this exhorteth you Paul ſayenge to the Epheſiās. the .vi. Put on the armoure of God, that ye maye ſtōde ſtedfaſt agaynſt

the crafty aſſaultes of the deuell. For we wreſtle not agaynſt fleſhe &amp; bloude, but agaynſt rule, agaynſt power, namely, agaynſt ye rulers of the world, of ye darckneſſes of this worlde, agaynſt the ſprite of wykednes vnder heauē. For this cauſe take ye ye armour of God that ye maye be able to reſyſt in the euel daye, &amp; ſtonde ꝑfecte in all thynges. As theſe enmyes are ſpirttuall and inuiſible, euen ſo haue we no nede of fleſhly weapons, but the weapons of the ſpirite, which be myghty in God, to deſtroye al ſtrōge fenſes and holdes of the deuell, pearſynge vnto the partynge of body and ſoule. Wherfore put on the ſhylde of fayth, wherwith ye ſhall quēche the fyrie dartes of the wycked enmy, and take ye helmet of ſaluation, and the ſwearde of the ſpyrite whiche is the worde of God. And praye vnto the Lorde, callynge alwaye vpon hys name in the ſpyrite, that ye maye ouercome Sathan the tempter and enmy: whiche ſeketh all aboute euen as a roarynge lyō whou he maye deuoure, but you muſt withſtonde hym manly in fayth.
            
            
               
               Lazarus.
               You haue opened now the caſe, and ſhewed me the weapons therwith I maye ouercome myn a foreſayed enmyes. But ſeyng I am an vnexpert ſouldyer, yt hath not ben vſed greatly to hādell ſuch weapon: I praye you to ſeperate my the dartes and arowes of Goddes worde, that I may ſhute euery enmy ſeuerally, namely ſynne, death &amp; hell. And fyrſt ſhewe my howe to defende my ſelfe, whan my ſynfull lyfe cōmeth to my remēbraunce.
            
            
               Tobias.
               I wyll do it gladly, but I feare leſt I be to tedious for you. The ſicke ought not to be ouerlonge taried withall. I wil rather returne agayne another tyme, and procede in thys matter.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               No good Toby, it is not to tedious for me, me thinketh ye be come but now. Timothe was .iiii. houres with me yeſterday &amp; yet ſemed it me not to be one houre.
            
            
               Tobias.
               In the name of God. Neuertheleſſe yf I be ouerlōge with you, warne me hardely.

Or yf ye deſyre ought I wyll reache it you.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               No no, go on with youre matter where ye lefte, for ye can do me no greater pleaſure.
            
            
               Tobias.
               As concernynge the fyrſt aſſault that ye ſhalbe aſſayed with, namely youre forepaſt ſynnes, which ſhall procure to bringe you in deſpayre: Agaynſt them arme you with ſuch ſcriptures that ſhewe you how the innocency and rightwyſnes of Chriſt hath put awaye al youre vnrightweſneſſe and wyckedneſſe. Euen as God ſayeth Eſay. liii. of his ſonne Chriſt thorowe out the whole chap. Caſt ye multitude of youre ſynnes vpon the lambe of God, which putteth awaye ye ſynnes of ye worlde. Remēbre yt God hath cloſed all vnder vnbeleue, that he myght haue mercy on all. Take holde vpon the good Samaritane, whiche taketh cure of the ſoule. Take your flyght wt the prodigall ſōne vnto your merciful farther, though ye be naked, ſeabby, &amp; ragged: for he ſhal receaue you fatherly, wt ſpred out armes,

and put on you the garment of innocēty Though you be loſt by reaſon of ſynne, the Lorde hym ſelfe ſeketh after you. Though ye go aſtraye with ye ſtraynge ſhepe, y
                     •
                  t doth the good ſhepehearde take you vpon hys ſhulder and bringeth you to ye ſhepetolde. Herkē how ſwetely and louengly God calleth you vnto him ſayenge Math. xi. Come to me al ye that laboure and are laden, and I ſhall eaſe you of your ſynnes. Remember ye Chriſt is become oure wyſdome, ryghtwyſnes, redemption, and ſanctification .i. Cor. i. Remember that he is a trew phiſicion of oure ſoules. Yf ye were no ſynner, what were Chriſt nedefull to you? yf ye were not wounded, ye ſhulde nede no ſurgeon A phiſicion or ſurgeō is prayſed becauſe he doth an excellent cure. The kynde &amp; naturall worke of Chriſt is to ſaue hys people, and heale thē of al their ſynnes, for that is his profeſſion: yee &amp; he doth yt in dede, ſo yt our vnrightwyſnes maketh gods right wyſnes be prayſed, as wytneſſeth paul Ro. v. Neuertheleſſe wher abū
                  daūce of ſyn was, there was yet more plē
                  teouſnes

of grace. In that hath god declared hys loue, that we, whan we were ſynners Chryſt dyed for vs. We ſhalbe ſo much the more accepted before God, in that we be clenſed by hys bloude, and iuſtified. Happy is that man, not he that hath no ſynne, for he that ſayeth he hath no ſynne, deceaueth hymſelfe, and the treuth is not in hym: But he is happy to whom ſynne is rekened no ſynne. The lawe, that is the knowledge of oure ſynne is geuen by Moſes: but grace and trewe Saluation by Ieſus Chryſt. For he hath anulled the handwrytinge that was contrary to vs, and faſtened it vpō the croſſe, wherby he hath taken awaye all power of the princes of darkneſſe. Coloſſ. ii. and hath triumphed ouer them in hys own perſonne. The hye preſt of the olde lawe myght not offre ony offerynge for the peoples ſynne wythout he had firſt offred an offeringe for hymſelfe, and wythout bloudſheddynge was no forgeueneſſe, But Chryſt oure trewe byſſhoppe (which hath an euerlaſtyng preſthode after the ordynaunce of Melchyſedech)

had no nede to offer for hys ſynnes, (for he neuer ſynned) nor he hath not procured forgeueneſſe of ſynnes by the father, by ony ſtraunge bloude, of orē or calues, but with hys owne bloude. Thus was he vnſpotted that hath clenſed vs from all vnclennes. And ſeynge we haue thys Ieſu that paſſed the heauens, let vs holde oure profeſſion, and go boldely vnto the ſeate of hys grace, that we maye receaue mercy, and fynde grace to helpe in the tyme of nede. Hebr. v Al the waies of the Lorde are mercy and treuth. He promyſeth it mercyfully, that which he ſhall geue vs treuly. Of thys mercy hath God left and geuen vs the worde of atonemēt Ieſu Chryſt. Yf ye knowe the ſame promyſer, and geuer of mercy treuly, then maye ye truſt welynough that ye ſhall optayne forgeuenge, and remyſſion of ſynnes. Which forgeueneſſe you ſhal alſo optayne, that he be founde trew in his wordes of promyſe, and that he maye ouercome your ſynne, whan he is iudged of the vngodly to be no Saueour. The manheade of Chryſt ſhal couer your myſdedes,

ſo that the deuel your accuſer ſhal fynd nothīg in you blameable. Forget wt Paul that which is behinde you, &amp; couet to that which is before, namely, to the token of this victory of ſynne &amp; death tocome. To this do ye great enſāples of mercy ſhewed to peter, to mary magdalene to ye murtherer ſerue, I wil leaue of dauid, of paul, &amp; many more Submitte your ſelues &amp; rendre you to god confeſſynge you to ſuffre worthely and iuſtly for your ſynnes, &amp; that Chriſt died vniuſtly. Beleue yt in ye deſpiſing of Chriſt is hidde ye godly glory, &amp; in ye death is hidde ye kyngdō of Chriſt, which ye aforeſayd murtherer did &amp; it ſhalbe ſayde vnto you: To daye ſhall ye be wt me in paradiſe. Cōſidre your wyckedneſſe &amp; Chriſtes goodneſſe. Cōſidre ye damnacion that ye haue deſerued, and agayn the loue of Chriſt, which hath recōcyled you by the father. This doynge you ſhal heare wt Mary magdalene: Many ſynnes are forgeuē you, for ye loued many, your faith made you ſafe: Peter remēbred ye wordes of chriſt bi his lokyng vpō hī, &amp; at ye coks croēg bewayled he his

ſynnes. The Lorde almyghty doth now beholde you with this preſente ſyknes, and by ſendynge of death, and perchaunce letteth the ſoūde of the worde come in youre harte. Knoledge your ſynnes, knoledge the trew iudgment of God, that he letteth paſſe vpon youre myſdedes in your ſufferynge, and he ſhall not forſake you in youre callynge and mournynge: But ſhall appeare vnto you with a comfortable worde of hys reſurreccion which ſhall make youre conſcience luſty, and to reioyce in hope of the lyfe tocome, as he hath done with Peter. Happy are they that wepe with Peter (bearynge of very loue the yocke, and power of ſynne in theyr bodyes with greueouſneſſe) for they ſhalbe conforted. Thys is the promyſe of God yt cā not lye vnto you nor yet wyll do. Loke vpon thys, truſtynge to it, you ſhall rightwell ſubdue youre enmy ſynne.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               O Lorde geue me thy godly grace, that I maye beleue thy holſome worde, by ye which my harte may be purifyed of all

ſynfull deſyres, which are innumerable in me.
            
            
               Tobyas.
               Amen. God graunte you theſame.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Inſtructe me now farther good brother, how I maye behaue myſelfe in ye death tocome whan I begynne to myſtruſt, wether death ſhall than wholy ſwalowe my vp?
            
            
               Tobyas.
               The nature of the myſbeleuynge is ſuch that they can not beleue there be a ryſynge agayne of the fleſſhe: by reaſon thys bodely death ſemeth to conſume a man wholy and all. Wherfore they ſaye wyth mouth and harte as it is wrytten in the boke of wyſedom: The tyme of oure lyfe is but ſhort and tedious, and whan a mā is once gone, he hath no more ioye nor pleaſure, nother know we ony man that turneth agayne from death: for we are borne of naught, and we ſhalbe herafter as though we neuer had bene (and ſo forth). Ouer theſe men that be of ſuch fayth commeth damnation worthely: for

as they lyue and their opinion is ſo doth it chaunce alſo vnto them. The goſpell is yet wholy hydde vnto them, for the God of this worlde hath blynded theyr hartes ſo, that the lyght of the goſpell, &amp; the glory of Chriſtes ryſynge can not ſhyne in theyr hartes. Such men were they of Athē that ſayde of Paul that he was a declarer of new deuels. Act. xvii. whā he declared them Ieſu, and ſhewed them of hys reſurreccion. Of lyke natural blyndneſſe dyd it come that they of Athen axed at Paul ſayenge: Maye not we knowe what new doctryne this is that thou teacheſt? For thou bryngeſt ſtraunge tydynges, in to oure eares: We wolde knowe therfore what thys meaneth? Vpō which queſtyon. Paul made a goodly ſermon, cōcernynge the fayth in Chryſt, and hys ryſynge agayne. The myſtery of the reſurrecciō of Chryſt, is the chefe, and princypall poynt of our fayth. For what ſhulde it haue had auayled vs that Chryſt dyed, and ſuffred for vs, yf he hadde not bene ryſen agayn. This reſurreccion of the fleſſhe that we alſo abyde in Chryſt

maye not be rekened a dreame becauſe we ſe it not: For yf we ſawe it with oure eyen than were it no fayth: for fayth is of thynges inuiſible and not apparaunt Wherfore, though all men ſeme to begynne the lyfe, and fyniſhe it agayne in thys preſent worlde: yet are we aſſured and beleue that we all ſhall ryſe agayne from death in the daye of dome, euen as Chryſt is ryſen firſt. This aſſuraunce of trew fayth paſſeth all ſureties that can be perſuaded by ony ſutelty of mās ymaginacion. By this fayth (Not by the outward opinion) ſpeake we of the reſurreccion of fleſſhe: euen as the prophet ſaieth Pſal▪ 
                  
                     ••
                  v. I beleued and therfore haue I ſpoken. Paul taketh vp this worde ſpeake ſayenge .ii. Corin, iiii. Seynge we haue the ſame ſprite of faith (accordinge as it is written: I beleued and therfore haue I ſpoken) we alſo beleue, and therfore we ſpeake, for we knowe yt he, which rayſed vp the Lorde Ieſus, ſhall rayſe vs vp alſo, by ye meanes of Ieſus &amp; ſhall ſet vs with you, (it foloweth) For ye thinges which are ſene, are temporall: but

the thynges which are not ſene, are eternall. Wherfore al that we beleue of god, all that we ſpeake of the reſurreccion, &amp; the lyfe tocome ſemeth not to be ſo. Euen as God hymſelf, and hys honour, &amp; worſhyppe, be alſo inuyſyble, and not appataunte to be trew vnto ſuch carnall wyſemen that haue not receaued the ſame ſpryte of the prophete and Paul. By the afore ſayed ſprite of fayth ſpeaketh Paul of the reſurreccion ſaienge: The body is ſowen here in corrupcion, and ſhall ryſe in vncorrupcion: Yt is ſowen in dyſhonoure: and it ſhall ryſe agayne in glory: Yt is ſowē in weakneſſe, and ſhal ryſe in poure: Yt is ſowen a naturall body, and ſhall ryſe a ſpirituall body. For fleſſhe, &amp; bloude ſhall not poſſeſſe the kyngdom of God, and that which is tranſytory, can not poſſeſſe eternal heretage. Thus muſt the grane of the fleſſhy body, that is ſowen here in eath fyrſt dye in the groūd before it can brynge forth new frute into lyfe euerlaſtyng: which lyfe we do abyde certaynly by fayth in the reſurreccion of the fleſſhe though it appeare impoſſible

vnto vs. For becauſe Chryſt is ryſen, therfore ſhall we ryſe alſo, and not abyde in death: For God is no God of the dead, but of the lyuenge Abraham, Iſaac, and Iacob.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               I wyll graunte it ryght wel that we ſhal all ryſe agayne at the daye of dome, nor in that am not I tempted: but I am more afrayed of the ſeconde, and eternall death. Inſtructe my agaynſt that I pray you, that I may perceaue that I feare, and drede the ſeconde death by the reaſon of my great myſbelefe.
            
            
               Tobias.
               Wherto thynke ye the reſurreccion of Chryſt be ſtabyliſſhed with ſo many tokens and wonders, but onely that we ſhulde ſtedfaſtly beleue therin? To beleue in the reſurreccion of Chriſt, is to beleue that he raygneth, and is a kynge, and that in his ryſynge, death, and ſynne be ſubdued vnto hym. Death is the wages of ſynne. Seinge than we be clenſed by the ſheddynge of the bloude of chriſt, we are alſo aſſured of death, which

els ſhulde haue folowed death. Therfore all thoſe that be yet myſbeleuynge, ſad, and heuy harted, and walke before God in bytterneſſe, they be yet in ſynne. And becauſe they beleue not the reſurreccion of Chryſt, therfore can not they reioyce in Chryſt, nor come to ony hope of the lyfe tocome. Herken how royally the reſurreccion of Chryſt is ſet forth vnto vs in ſcripture. Paul ſayeth in the .x. chap. to the Romanes. Yf thou knowlegeſt Ieſu with thy mouth that he is the Lorde, and beleueſt in thyne harte that God hath rayſed hym vp from the dead thou ſhalt be ſaued. Yf ye dye in Chryſt ye ſhall alſo ryſe in him and lyue foreuer lyke as he now lyueth eternally. For God hath begotten vs agayne vnto a lyuely, hope, by the reſurrection of Ieſus Chryſt from the dead .i. Petri. i. Whā that which is mortall in you ſhall haue put on all immortalyte by the departynge of death, than ſhal death be ſwalowed vp in the victory. For Chryſt hath ouercome hym by his death which had the lordſhyppe in this worlde by the diſobedience

of Adam, as Chryſt ſayeth hymſelfe: The prynce of this worlde is come, but in me hath he nought. For ſo much than as Chriſt beynge ye trew ſede of Eua hath deſtroyed and bruſed the ſerpentes heade, that is death, wherby the ſerpent raygned myghtely vpon all mankynde: then maie ye now hardely triūphe inwardely ſayeng: Death, where is the ſtynge? o hel where is thy glory? prayſed be god which hath geuen vs victory by Ieſu Chriſte. Lyke as it was impoſſible, that Chriſt not ſhulde pleaſe god in his ryghtweſnes: euē ſo is it impoſſible we ſhulde not pleaſe God by fayth in Chriſt. Thys confirmeth Chriſt ſayenge. The father loueth you, for you loued me. Of this miſery of the reſurreccion, &amp; hyd lyfe coulde I brynge you forth manye ſcripturely reaſons and enſamples, but I fear leſt it wyl be to tedious for you beynge ſyke.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               No brother, fear not. I loue ſo well to hear ye enſamples of ſcrypture, whych teache vs how lyfe is hyd in death.
            
            
               
               Tobias.
               We haue many figures &amp; enſāples in ye ſcripture, which teach and declare vnto vs, that lyfe is fyrſt declared in dyenge. Whan the lorde God had fyrſt created Adam our father, he cauſed hym to ſlepe, that out of the ſlepers ſyde he might make a lyuynge creature, namly Heua, to be a helpe vnto man (Gene. ii.) the whiche alſo he dyd. Lo how ſtraunge ſeme the workes of God to be in oure ymagination? Adam ſlepeth, and is in the figure of death: for ſlepe is very well compared vnto death, and of him cōmeth the lyfe vnto Eua, lykwyſe alſo in oure dyenge appeareth oure lyfe fyrſt wyth Chriſt. Death of ye Chriſtians is called in ſcripture a ſlepe or a peaceable reſt. Lazarus reſted in the boſome of Abraham. Steuen the fyrſt martyr dyd ſlepe in the Lorde, whan he was ſtoned. Is it not cōfortable that the holy gooſt doth call oure dyenge here but a ſlepe or a reſt? Steuen dyd ſlepe in the Lorde, (that is) he is departed hence with a ſuete reſt and eaſe at the harte, wherin he felt no paynfulneſſe

at the harte as a mā yt ſlepeth a naturall ſlepe, ſlepeth without ony paſſion or felynge of ye ſame. That death is not paynfull to the beleuenge, cōmeth of Chriſtes death. The ſoul of a Chriſtian beynge full of the lyuynge worde of God, feleth not death, nor regardeth it more than though ſhe were paynted on the wall, which appeared by the apoſtles yt wente meryly from the iudgmēt ſeates, becauſe they were founde worthy to ſuffre for the name of Ieſu. Act. v. Another enſample is this: What tyme as God had cō
                  maūded Abraham to offre hys only ſōne Iſaac, he wente thre dayes iourney vpō the word of God, leauenge his owne vnderſtondynge and wyt, yeldynge himſelf wholy in the handes of God, ſo that in ye meane ſeaſon was Iſaac dead and forgotten: For Abraham was fully determyned to offre hys ſonne vpon the hyll, which he ſawe afar of on the thyrde daye But finally whan Iſaac was neareſt vnto death, and Abrahā drew the ſwearde to ſmyte hym, thā was the ſonne wholy in ye harte of hys father, and fully delyuered

vnto death. Where Abraham now ſawe the death of his ſonne in lyftynge vp ye ſwearde, there appeared vnto him the life of his ſonne: for the ſwearde was ſtayed by the angel, of the which he was not ware dat it ſhulde happē, After this enſāple alſo was Chriſt rekened dead of the whole worlde, what tyme as he laye in the graue: But on the thyrde daye he roſe agayne, ſhewenge hymſelfe alyue. This wyſe ſhall it be wyth vs. Death ſemeth to take vs wholy and put vs out of mans remembraunce: but thā ſhall fyrſt oure lyfe appeare, accordinge as Paul ſayeth: Youre lyfe is hyd wyth Chriſt in God. Farthermore you rede that Moſes was cōmaunded Nume. xxi (whan a greate multitude of the people was ſlayne with the venymous ſerpentes, becauſe of their murmuringe agaynſte God) to ſet vp a braſen ſerpent in a token, that whoſe behelde it, ſhulbe recouer and lyue, whiche alſo chaunched. What is the meanynge of thys? Chriſt Ieſu is ſignifyed by this braſen ſerpent, which beynge lyfted from the earth and

hāged vpō ye croſſe as a treue tokē of forgeueneſſe, that whoſe beholdynge hym with the eyen of fayth, and ſure confidē
                  ce and hope to optayne health, maye be healed and relyue agayne in the ſoule, be he neuer ſo ſore wounded and bytten with the venyme of ſynne. Thys is yt that Chriſt alſo ſayde Iohn. iii. And lyke as Moſes lyft vp the ſerpent in the wylderneſſe, euen ſo muſt the ſonne of man be lyft vp, that whoſoeuer beleueth in him ſhulde not periſhe, but haue euerlaſtynge lyfe. Take this figure to youre doctrine good brother. You lye here bitten of the ſerpentes your ſynnes, whiche haue kylled with bytynge oure forefathers with all their progeny: For by the enuy and venym of the deuyll is death come in the whole worlde. Wherfore beholde now your ſaueoure on ye croſſe: Beholde the lyō of the kynred of Iuda that hath ouercome all. Beholde this ſerpent as a ſure tokē of the good wil of God to you warde, &amp; ye nede not to feare death, for it geueth you lyfe. Ionas the prophet was rekened for dead, what tyme as

he laye thre dayes in the whals belly dead drouned: But afterwarde was he alyue againe ſhewed ye Niniuytes, for he was ſuſtaineth from death by god which relyued hym agayne. By this Ionas is Chryſt alſo fygured, wytneſſynge it hys owne ſelfe in the goſpel to aſſure vs that we ſhall alſo ryſe with him agayne, yf we abyde ſtedfaſtly beleuynge vnto the ende. What more aſſuraunce can ye haue of God, than that he hath not ſpared hys owne ſonne: but hath geuen hym ouer vnto death for vs, to ouercome death, &amp; to opē agayne the gates of lyfe. Fynalbeholde how Chryſt declareth hys lyfe in dyenge, to ſtabyliſhe oure fayth, that we ſhulde not doubte in the lyfe tocome no not in the myddes of death. For Chryſt hangynge on the croſſe, geuenge vp hys ſpryte vnto hys father, teſtyfyenge with the bowenge downe of hys heade that he was euen dead: he ſhewed yet ſome tokens of lyfe that were hyd in hym, whan hys bleſſed ſyde was opened wherout cā runnynge water and bloude Wherfore doubt not in ye lyfe tocome: for

ye haue receaued a pledge of this lyfe by the loue of Chryſt, which is poured in you by the knoledge of God. Chryſt dyed and is crucifyed for oure weakneſſe, but he lyueth by the power of God. We are alſo weake with hym, and dye by reaſon of weakneſſe, but we ſhal lyue afterwarde with Chryſt by ye ſame power of God. Searche and proue yourſelfe whether ye haue alſo thys hope, &amp; fayth in the Lorde, and in hys promiſes, which ſhall geue you hys ryghtweſneſſe for youre ſynnes, and lyfe for death.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Now as concernynge hell what ſhall I ſaye of it? Yt is a commune ſaienge: it we good dyenge, yf man knewe where to become. Thus muſt alſo come of a myſbeleuynge harte that we be thus abaſſhed for hell.
            
            
               Tobyas.
               Yt is ſure ſo, greate myſbeleue cauſeth vs to fear hell. But knowe ye what is hell? Hell is nothynge els ſaue feare, and drede of death, and a tremblinge againſt the iudgment and ryghtwyſneſſe of God

The vngodly, and damned can neuer eſcape thys death and hell, for they haue no luſt nor loue to God, whom they beholde as a fearfull iudge, and feare hys ryghtwyſneſſe. He is ſayde to be in hell, that perceaueth wythin hymſelf how wycked and wreched he is, wherby he is enfourmed, and perſuaded the fear of death, and damnation. So that the mooſt damnation, and payne of hell, is the deſpyſynge, and blaſphemynge of God. For ſo longe as we haue no lyuely wytneſſe inwardly of the ſpryte of God, that we be the chyldren of God: ſo longe do we hate him, and can not beholde his ryghtwyſnes, ſo doth oure haynous conſcience of ſynne dryue vs. By theſe afore ſayde wordes is it playne vnto you, that the hell of the vnryghtwyſe begynneth here in earth, ſeynge the worme of theyr wicked conſciencie dyeth not, and the fyre of theyr wrath is not quenched. Wherfore, as the kyngdom of God is iuſtification, peace, reſt, and godly corage: euen ſo is hel, ſynne, troubell, and raygne. In this hell was Caym, whan he fled here

earth no man perſuynge hym. In this hel alſo was Iudas ye traytour, &amp; abode therin to his damnation. Pether ſayeth Act. ii. that God hath rayſed vp Chryſt, looſed the ſorowes of death: for ſo much as it was impoſſible that he ſhulde beholden of her (that is) Chriſt hath redemed vs and made vs ſawe from all oure enmyes. The deuell is a puſſaunte Lorde, and well weapened with all hys traynes, erroures, and fearfulneſſes. Math. xii. But the ſonne of God was a myghtyer Lorde, which hath torne the powers of hell, for all thynges were geuen hym, in hys hande as Chryſt ſayeth. Math. xxviii. Vnto me is geuen all power, in heauē &amp; in earth. Yf al thinge be geuē vnto hym, thā is alſo ye ouercōmynge of hell geuē him. Chriſt deſcēded down to hel before, &amp; hath troubled the kīgdō of ye deuel he hath alſo brought glad tydīges vnto thē yt were p̄ſoned ī hel: The gates of hell cā not withſtōd ye faith of Peter: this was Paul ſure of which cauſed hī to ſaye to ye Ro. viii. I am ſure the nother death, nor lyfe, nor angell, nor rule, nor power, nor

thynges preſent, nor thynges tocome, nor heyght, nor, depth, nor ony other creature ſhalbe able to ſeperate vs from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Ieſu our lord. Chriſt ſayeth in ye boke of pſalmes. Lorde, out of hell haſt thou drawen my ſoule. This redemynge &amp; delyuerynge of Chriſt, is happened to oure profete For as Chriſt was a conquerer of al: euē ſo ſhal we alſo be ouercomers &amp; winners through him, for ſo much as we be in corporate in hym: Before we were ſundered but now are come neare by the bloude of Chriſt: For he is become our peace he hath made vs cyteſens with the ſayntes, &amp; of the houſholde of God. Seynge we are gathered in ye houſe of God, we haue here altogether a kyngdō, an heretage a victory, and all ſaluation. To this ſerueth the prayer of Chriſt, which he made to the heauēly father Iohn. xvii. I praye not only for thē. (meanyng his apoſtles) but alſo for them whiche ſhall beleue by theyr preachynge, yt they all maye be one lyke vs thou father art in my, and I in the, that they alſo maye be one in vs.

Thynke ye thys prayer is ſpoken for nought? Thynke ye God the father hath not herde his beloued ſonne in the houre of hys ſufferynge? A good father deſpyſeth not the peticions of his chyldren, Be of good cheare (ſayeth Chriſt) I haue ouercome the worlde. In Chriſt ſhal we conquere ſuenge that which is promyſed vs in the prophet pſal. xc. Thou ſhalt go vpon the lyon and adder, the yonge lyon and draggō ſhalt thou treade vnder thy fete. that is all power of the deuels and alſo hell.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               I truſt I ſhall mynde and remēbre your exhortacions very well, ſo farre as God doth not depriue me of my fyue wyttes.
            
            
               Tobias.
               Yf it come ſo farre that you be depryued of youre fyue wyttes by reaſon of the feruentneſſe of youre ſikneſſe, be not moued therat, Let God worke hys worke vntyl the ende. Suffre God to accompliſhe hys wil, for he dyeth not euell that dyeth in God. Yt is no force vnto the beleuynge wether he dye onwares or wares, for

they abyde the Lordes cōmynge alwaye which ſhal come ſodenly vpon the myſbeleuynge as a thefe in the night. How bitter is the remembraunce of death vnto him that hath eaſe and reſt in hys ſubſtaunce and goodes?
            
            
               Lazarus.
               How happeneth it that it is comunely ſayde: lyfe is happy: for ſo farre as I perceaue death is more happy?
            
            
               Tobias.
               The cōmune by worde is not to be vnderſtonde of the bodely lyfe, which we neuer can lede without ſynne, but you muſt vnderſtonde it of ſuch a lyfe, as we lede in God, wherin we ſhall lyue for euer though we wandered in death, Wherfore yf ye require a longe temporall lyfe of God, than deſyre you to ſynne longer, &amp; to moue god to more wrath. But that life which we lede in God by fayth wherby the ryghtwous lyueth, that is happy.
            
            
               Lazarus
               Now do I knowe nothyng in myne opynion that can kepe my back frō dyenge willīgly, ſaue only my wyfe &amp; children,

which yet haue nede both of my helpe &amp; counſell.
            
            
               Tobias.
               Cōmitte your wyfe &amp; chyldren vnto the Lorde almyghty, which hath geuē or lēt you vnto thē to care for thē, ſo longe as it ſhall be his Godly wil to ſuffre you to be a carer or prouyder for thē. But now doth death diſcharge you of this office &amp; ſorowfulneſſe. Rendre god ye charge ioyfully. Go you forth now wt Abraham in ſtraūge coūtryes, leauynge youre kynne &amp; fathers houſe, &amp; come in ye londe ye God ſhall ſhew you, Obey gods callinge. He yt loueth more father, mother, wyfe, chyldrē, lōdes or poſſeſſions than my, is not worthy of my, ſaieth Chriſt. As longe as ye were able you haue ſhewed loue and good wyll vnto your houſholde: Of this maye be boaſte right wel, &amp; that becauſe ye wolde paſſe ye bondes of your cōmiſſion of loue. But what myſbelefe is yt, that ye do not truſt god wt the kepenge of his owne chyldren? What was youre helpe care, and kepynge wythout hys ouerſyght? yf the Lorde do not buylde the cyte: they laboure in vayne that buylde it.

Put ye your confydence in God that he ſhall helpe you? and truſt ye him not the kepynge of your children? Though it ſeme that your children departe from you, in dyenge, and ye of them, yet do they kepe theyr heauenly father, which taketh more care for them than euer you coulde This will I tell you, your fayth may be ſuch, that God wyll rayſe ten fathers or weldoers in ſteade of you of whom wt partynge of death, they be depryued. Dauid ſayeth I neuer ſawe a ryghteous mā forſaken, nor hys ſede ſeke breade. Auoyde now all ſenſualyte out of your mynde Commytte youre wyf, thylderen, and all that ye loue, vnto God, who onely ſhall kepe them beſt. The myſtruſt &amp; murmurynge of parentes, is of tymes correcte, and punyſhed in the chylderen, as namely whā they myſpēde ye goodes in ryot, or ſuffre loſſes, and domages in them, the which theyr frendes buſyed to leaue thē great plenty of, and to prouide them ſubſtancialy of them.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               Let it be ſo, God graunte that I maye

yelde both me and mine willyngly in the hondes of God. My thynketh my tyme doth aproche. Oh I longe ſo ſore to be embraced of my brydegrome Chryſt. Cantic. ii. His left hande is vnder my heade, and hys ryght hande ſhall cleſpe my necke. I deſyre with Paul to be lowſed, and to be with Chryſt. Heale my Lorde and I ſhalbe healed.
            
            
               Tobias.
               That is well &amp; Chryſtenly prayed, God ſende you hys ſtronge ſpryte, which ſhal ſtrength you in all ſufferynge, yee and alſo in death. But now brother yf I perchaunce ſhall ſe you nomore in this lyfe: Haue ye ony quarell with ony man? or haue ye ony thynge that greueth your mynde ſhewe on?
            
            
               Lazarus.
               What occaſioneth you to aſke the ſame? haue ye herd ought therof?
            
            
               Tobyas.
               The cauſe of my queſtyon is, that yf ye haue ony variaunce, or ony ſkyll wyth your brother: before all other thinges ye ought to diſpach theſame and to be recōcyled

agayne wt hym. In thre thinges (ſayeth Sydrac) haue I pleaſure which alſo be alowed before God and mē: The vnite of brethren, the loue of neghbours, and man and wyfe agreynge well together. And that ye maye forther and ſett forth ſuch loue and vnite, ye ought to be ware leſt ony variaunce come after your departyng by reaſon of the goodes amō
                  ge youre frendes, and kynred.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               I haue diſpached and prepared all this lōge before ſo neare as I might. I truſt there ſhall ryſe no ſtryfe betwen my frendes or chyldren. I was mynded to haue geuen vnto the church or temple, to the iiii. orders of ſtronge valeaunt beggers, and vnto our vicare and pariſhepreſt of ſuch as ſhulde haue ben ouerplus: But that mynde is altered, for God hath geuen me a better mynde. I thanke hym hyghly therof.
            
            
               Tobias..
               All teſtamentes that be made to the fortheraunce of the loue of oure neghbure are good. There be of tymes churches

founded, maſſes, &amp; great doles to Gods great diſhonoure: For God is not honoured with ſuch thynges, but only with yt he hath cōmaunded himſelf. Some thinke to do an hygh pleaſure vnto God yf they diſheret their chylderen, frendes, &amp; kynred amonge whom afterwarde ther aryſeth a great ſtrife. They bequiet their goodes to founde holydayes, trentals, maſſes of requiem, wherwyth they fede the ſpiritualty. They thynke to pleaſe God with ſuch foundations and make an atonement with ſuch goodes as they haue ſkrapen and raked together by wronge, falſede, gyle, vſury, and ſuch lyke wayes ſpared them. Where as God hateth in hys offerynge al ſuch robbery. They founded alſo altares, and monumentes and coſtly graues, to haue theyr names in eſtymation amonge the people and to lyue longe in their mouthes &amp; be prayſed for theſe dedes. To thys entent be tabels and ſuch memorials hanged vp in euery churche as a byrders net is ſpred. O tabel of exchaungers caſt out of ye tēpel by Chriſt. O yeartyde. O

Corbam corbam how dewly arte thou practyſed yet dayly of oure ſcribes &amp; phariſes, which lyke paynted graues deceaue the onwyſe and ſymple: For they ſaye it is offered vnto Gods honour &amp; ſeruice that which is withdrawē from the poore chyldren and heires. Now brother, is it not tyme for me to departe? my thynketh I haue ben longe ynough here. I muſt alſo go yet to the poore houſe or hoſpital, for ſo haue I promyſed.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               I thanke you hartely good brother for youre kynde vyſitinge of me, and louely teachyng me. Come agayne to ſe how it is with me at your leaſure.
            
            
               Tobias.
               I wyll do ſo. And now I cōmitte you to God, which I praye to be youre guyde vnto the lyfe euerlaſtynge. Yf ye haue nede of me, ſende for me, and I wil be glad to come vnto you.
            
            
               Lazarus.
               The Lorde be bleſſed and thanked ouer all foreuer.
            
            
               Tobias.
               Feare well good brother.
            
            
               
               Lazarus.
               Fare well good Toby, God kepe vs all and be oure guyde, and counceler vnto lyfe eternall.
            
            
               Tobyas.
               Amen.
            
            The ende of thys treatyſe.
         
         
            ¶The ſumme, and intente of this treatyſe:
            
               NOw haſt thou ſene good reader the maruelous worke of God in hys two electes, namly, Tymothe &amp; Toby: which to theyr power haue planted and watered the ſede of Gods worde in theyr neghboure Lazarus, beynge at ſcole, wherin is the wyll of god taught, that is adfliction, ſykneſſe, and ſubieccion of the fleſſhe vnto the ſprite. They now beynge occaſyoned by knoledgyng their deuty, to theyr neghboure endeuour to make hym to dye in the Lorde and make hym apte vnto the ioye euerlaſtinge after his troubell. Wherin I praye the to marke the ordre and waye:
            Fyrſt Tymothe commynge the one

daye &amp; inſtructynge him to take his troubelous ſykneſſe paciently, in the which admonitiō he doth treuly, and pythfully declare the ſeuen petitions of the Pater noſter, reprouynge by the waie his impaciency, myſbeleue, and ſuperſtitiouſneſſe wherin he was ſo drowned, that it ſemed to haue bene impoſſible he ſhulde euer bene come out of. But the Lorde, which kylleth &amp; relyueth again, ledeth to hel, &amp; bringeth vp again, hath alſo ſhewed his maruaylous power wt this ſykmā, whō he hath called to hym by repētaūce, as he wyll alſo do the mooſt ſynner, and myſdoer of vs, yf he repente treuly.
            Secondarly Tobias commynge the ſecōde daye as hys promyſe was inſtructeth hym how to take his death paciētly. And in the meane ſeaſon expoundeth certayne of the artikles of oure fayth, namely, the power of God in creatynge al thynges, ye frute of Chriſtes ſufferynge, death, reſurrecciō, aſcenſyon, of the holy gooſt, which be the treu churche, of communiō of ſayntes, of remyſſion of ſynne, of ryſynge agayne of the fleſſhe, and of the lyfe

eternall or euerlaſtynge. And fynally he ſheweth what be oure enemyes death, ſynne, and hell, and how we maye beſt withſtonde them. This with other ſuperſtitions and abuſes doth he ſo featly, and ſcripturly declare and teacheth to eſchue as in myne opynion no rabby, magiſter noſter, or puffet vp doctor coulde do, though he had ſpent the beſte parte of hys lyfe ī ſearchyng Chryſt at Paris. Take therfore this treatyſe oft in thyne handes, loke diligently vpon it, and vſe it as it is offered vnto thy. I wyl not buſy my ſelfe greatly in prayſynge of it, for the commune prouerbe is veryfied in it, that is: good wyne nedeth no garlande: for yf thou rede it diligently, and folowe it ſo neare as God wil lēde ye grace, thā ſhalt thou receaue the profyte that is ſought both in dytynge and tranſlatynge of it, namly, ye health of youre ſoul and herafter lyfe euerlaſtynge, which graūte you god the father, &amp; ſonne, &amp; holy gooſt. Amen.
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶Prynted in Southwarke, By My Iames Nicolſon, for Ian Gough Cum Priuilegio Regali.
            
         
      
   

