
   
      
         
            The mirrour of maiestie: or, The badges of honour conceitedly emblazoned with emblemes annexed, poetically vnfolded.
            H. G., fl. 1618.
         
         
            
               1618
            
         
         Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01375
            STC 11496
            ESTC S102778
            99838541
            99838541
            2923
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01375)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2923)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1098:10)
         
         
            
               
                  The mirrour of maiestie: or, The badges of honour conceitedly emblazoned with emblemes annexed, poetically vnfolded.
                  H. G., fl. 1618.
                  Goodyere, Henry, Sir, 1551 or 2-1629.
               
               [4], 63, [3] p. : ill.  
               
                  Printed by William Iones, dwelling in Red-crosse-streete,
                  London :
                  1618.
               
               
                  "To those noble personages ..", [A]2a, signed: H.G.
                  Sometimes attributed to Sir Henry Goodyere.
                  In verse.
                  Signatures: [A]²  B-I⁴.
                  Last leaf contains "A catalogue of those names vnto whom this worke is appropriated".
                  Variant: [A]2r contains dedication "To the Kings most excellent Maiestie"; [A]2 a cancel?.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Heraldry --  Early works to 1800.
               Emblem books, English.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-09
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-09
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-10
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-10
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               THE MIRROVR OF MAIESTIE: OR, THE BADGES OF HONOVR CONCEITEDLY EMBLAZONED: WITH EMBLEMES ANNEXED, POETICALLY VNFOLDED.
            
               —Nec his Plebecula gaudet.
            
            LONDON, Printed by William Iones, dwelling in Red-croſſe-ſtreete. 1619.
         
         
            
            
            TO THOSE NOBLE Perſonages rancked in the CATALOGVE.
            
               MY feebler Muſe farre too too weake to ſing,
               Ha's got your Honours on her flaggring wing,
               And borne them to the loftiest pitch ſhe may:
               Therefore (ſubmisſiue) ſhe do's humbly pray,
               That when her tongue reeles, or Inuention haults,
               Your Fauours will giue crutches to her faults.
            
            
               Your LORDSHIPS in all dutifull obſeruancie, H. G.
            
         
         
            
            
            
               ❧ A CATALOGVE OF THOSE NAMES VNTO WHOM this worke is appropriated.
            
               THE Kings Maieſtie.
               The Queene.
               The Prince.
               The Lord Arch-Biſhop of Canterburie.
               The Lord Chancellor.
               The Lord Treaſurer.
               The Lord Priuie Seale.
               The Lord Admirall.
               The Duke of Lenox.
               The Marqueſſe of Buckinghame.
               The Lord Chamberlaine.
               The Earle of Arundell.
               The Earle of South-hampton.
               The Earle of Hertford.
               The Earle of Eſſex
               The Earle of Dorſet.
               The Earle of Mountgomerie.
               The Viſcount Liſle.
               The Viſcount Wallingford.
               The Biſhop of London.
               The Biſhop of Wincheſter.
               The Biſhop of Ely.
               The Lord Zouch.
               The Lord Windſor.
               The Lord Wentworth.
               The Lord Darcie.
               The Lord Wootton.
               The Lord Stanhope.
               The Lord Carew.
               The Lord Hay.
               The Lord Chiefe Iuſtice of the Kings-Bench.
               The Lord Chiefe Iuſtice of the Common-Pleas.
               The Lord Chiefe Baron of the Excheaquer.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            TO THE KING.
            
               
                  I R
                  QVI MAL Y PENSE HONI SOIT
               
            
            
               THoſe (mighty Soueraigne) are your Graces text,
               Right King of Heralds, not to any, next:
               You might their myſticke learning blazon beſt,
               But you reſerue your knowledge vnexpreſt:
               As being moſt peculiar to you:
               And yet becauſe the people may allow
               That which concernes your ſelfe: Let me to them
               Vnlocke the value of this prizeleſſe Iem:
               The Lyons trebled thus, may repreſent
               Your equall fitnes for the Regiment
               Of this faire Monarchie: Brittaine then
               Which euer ha's bin ſtuft with valiant men,
               May fitteſt beare a Lyon, vrg'd to ſpoile:
               Your Iriſh Kernes, who neuer vs'd to toyle,
               Are in their ſilver-ſtudded Harpe explain'd.
               Theſe Splendent Beauties limm'd by Natures hand,
               By grace of Ancient Kings, made Royall flow'rs,
               
               But now thrice Royall made, by being Yours.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 1
            
               
                  REX ✚ ET ✚ SACERDOS ✚ DEI ✚
                  
               
            
            
               VVHy be theſe marſhal'd equall, as you ſee?
               Are they diſ-rankt, or not? No: they ſhould be
               Thus plac'd: for Common-weales doe tottering ſtand,
               Not vnder-propt thus by the mutuall hand
               Of King and Prieſt, by Gods and humane lawes:
               Divine aſſiſtance moſt effectuall drawes
               Kings to confeſſe, that t'heav'n they homage owe;
               Which conſequently leads a King to knowe,
               That, that Ambition's by dead Embers fir'd,
               Which ha's no▪ beyond earth to heav'n aſpir'd:
               Earth can but make a King of earth partaker,
               But Knowledge makes him neereſt like his maker.
               For mans meere power not built on Wiſdomes fort,
               Dos rather pluck downe kingdomes than ſupport.
               Perfectly mixt, thus Power and Knowledge moue
               About thy iuſt deſignes, enſphear'd with loue;
               
               Which (as a glaſſe) ſerue neighbour-Kings, to ſee
               How beſt to follow, though not equall thee.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 2
            
               
                  NVLLVM BONVM INREMVNERATVM
               
            
            
               SEated on this three-headed Mountaine high,
               
               
                  Which repreſents Great Brytaines Monarchie,
               Thus ſtand I furniſht t'entertaine the noiſe:
               Of thronging clamours, with an equall poyſe:
               And thus addreſt to giue a conſtant weight
               To formall ſhewes, of Vertue, or Deceit:
               
               Thus arm'd with Pow'r to punniſh or protect,
               When I haue weigh'd each ſcruple and defect:
               Thus plentifully rich in parts and place
               To giue Aboundance, or a poore diſgrace:
               But, how to make theſe in iuſt circle moue,
               Heav'n crownes my head with Wiſedome from aboue.
               Thus Merit on each part, to whom 'tis due,
               With God-like power diſburſed is by you.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE QVEENE.
            
               
            
            
               OF all proportions (Madam) diuers dare
               Conclude that abſolute, which is moſt ſquare:
               Well may they proue that Theoreme: for I know
               Square Bodies doe the moſt perfection ſhow:
               Perfection ſtill conſiſting in this beſt,
               To ſtand more ſure, the more it is ſuppreſt.
               Which ſpeciall vertue chiefly doth belong
               Vnto ſquare bodies, or right do's them wrong:
               Your Scutchion therefore, and the Honours due,
               May conſtantly ſupport your Worth and You;
               Whoſe life's drawne out (vnſoild with ſubiects hate)
               By ſuch a Samplar, none can imitate.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 3.
            
               
                  ❀ VNICA ✚ ETERNA ✚ AL ✚ MONDO ✚
                  
               
            
            
               HEre aboue number, doth one wonder ſit;
               But One, yet in her owne, an infinit:
               Being ſimply rare, no Second can ſhe beare,
               Two Sunnes were neuer ſeene ſtalke in one Spheare.
               From old Eliza's Vrne, enricht with fire
               Of glorious wonders, did your worth ſuſpire:
               So muſt, from your dead life-infuſing flame,
               Your Multiplyed-ſelfe riſe thence the Same:
               
               She whoſe faire Memories, by Theſpian Swaines
               Are ſung, on Rheins greene banks, and flowrie plaines.
               Thus Time alternates in its ſingle turnes;
               One Phaenix borne, another Phaenix burnes.
               Your rare worths (matchleſſe Queene) in you alone
               Liue free, vnparalle'd, entirely One.
               
            
         
         
            
            TO THE PRINCE.
            
               
                  C P
                  ICH
                        •
                      DIEN
               
            
            
               YOur Princedome's Enſigne here (Right-Royall Sir)
               May pinion your vp-ſoaring thoughts, and ſtirre
               Them to a pitch of loftier eminence,
               Then can be reached by baſe vulgar ſenſe.
               Theſe Plumes (charact'red liuely ſignifie
               
                  Valour in warre, ioyn'd with velocitie.
               
               The blacke Prince (bearing Plumes) approues this true,
               When through the French he like win'gd-lightning flue,
               And pull'd downe liues about him to the ground,
               Till he himſelfe with death had circled round;
               His very looke did threaten publicke death:
               With every ſtroke fell from him, fled a breath.
               Arm'd in the confidence of his iuſt cauſe,
               Thus freely feareleſſe his foes overthrowes.
               Thoſe high-borne acts which from his valour flue,
               With new-additions are impreſs't in you.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 4.
            
               
                  POST ✚ NVBILA ✚ PHEBVS ✚
                  
               
            
            
               VVHen Peace (ſuſpecting he would warre inferre,)
               Tooke Henry hence, to liue aboue with her,
               She bade Ioues Bird returne from's quicke convoy
               Of his faire ſoule, left in Heav'ns laſting Ioy,
               And mildly offer to your Princely hands,
               This Embleme of ſoft Peace and Warlike bands:
               
               Both vvhich (vſ'd rightly) their large cares extend.
               To gaine o're others, and their owne defend.
               Though all bright Honours did their Beauties ſhroud
               In his Ecclipſe, like Phoebus in a cloud:
               Yet at your Riſing, they more cleare againe
               Peept-forth, like Sun-ſhine after clouds and raine.
               And in your worth their worthineſſe diſplayes
               To worthieſt Princes; as the Sun, his rayes.
            
            
            
               〈1 page duplicate〉
            
            
            
               〈1 page duplicate〉
            
         
         
            
            TO THE ARCH-BISHOP OF CANTERBVRY.
            
               
            
            
               HOw well theſe ſacred Ornaments become
               One, who by earth walkes t'his celeſtiall home:
               The Staffe of Comfort this, to leane vpon,
               This, Pall of peace▪ theſe, Croſſes vndergone:
               How eaſily good men (knowne well by this)
               Lodge at the Inne of their eternall Bliſſe:
               Theſe Fruits, are workes, from Bounty ſpringing found,
               Perfuming Heau'n, &amp; with Heau'ns bounties crown'd:
               Theſe ſhadow'd fruits, but by a figure, ſhew
               The Ioyes of Paradiſe prepar'd for you.
               Saile thither with good ſpeede then, yet make ſtay;
               Good Angels guide you, y'are i'th Abbots way.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 5.
            
               
                  MORIR ✚ PIV ✚ TOSTO ✚ CHE ✚ MANCAR ✚ DI ✚ FEDE.
               
            
            
               THeſe Hands connext, engird Religion,
               
               Deciphring th'holy Concords vniſon,
               
               Of faiths full harmony: this ſpiny pale
               
               Sharpe conflicts are, who ſtill the Truth aſſaile:
               This Heart the Church is, th'holy Ghoſt being Center,
               
               Afflictions may ſurround, but cannot enter.
               You are the prime linke of this manuall chaine,
               
               Whereby Religion do's its ſtrengthmaintaine:
               O! may the Reuerend Reſt to you ſticke faſt,
               That Truth (though long) yet conquer may at laſt.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE LORD CHANCELLOR.
            
               
            
            
               THe North and Southerne Poles, the two fix'd Starres
               Of worth and dignitie, which all iuſt warres,
               Should ſtill maintaine, together: be here met
               And in your ſelfe as in your Scutchion ſet:
               The halfe Moone 'twixt, threatens as yet no change,
               Or if ſhe doe, ſhe promiſes to range,
               Till ſhe againe recouer what ſhe loſt:
               Your endleſſe fame, (ſo) gaines your Bounties coſt.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 6.
            
               
                  SVB ✚ VMBRA ✚ ALARVM ✚ TVARVM ✚
                  
               
            
            
               NEuer ſhould any thinke himſelfe ſo ſure
               Of friends aſſiſtance, that he dares procure
               New enemies: for vnprouok'd they will
               Spring out of forg'd, or cauſeleſſe malice ſtill.
               Elſe, why ſhould this poore creature be purſu'd,
               Too ſimple to offend, a beaſt ſo rude.
               Therefore prouide (for malice danger brings)
               
                  Houſe-roome to find vnder an Eagles wings.
               You are this Eagle, whcih ore-ſhades the ſheepe
               
               Purſu'de by humane wolues, and ſafe doth keepe
               The poore mans honeſt, though might-wronged cauſe,
               From being cruſhed by oppreſſions pawes.
               Faire Port you are, where euery Goodneſſe findes
               Safe ſhelter from ſwolne Greatneſſe, ſtubborne winds▪
               
               Eager to drench it: but that feareleſſe reſt
               Dwels in your harbour, to all good diſtreſt.
               I bid not you prouide, you are compleate,
               The good for to protect, or bad defeate.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE LORD TREASVRER.
            
               
                  HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE 
               
            
            
               YOur ſable Creſcent might to ſome (whoſe lips
               Speake ignorance) portend a blacke Ecclipſe:
               I rather thus diſcerne, how Time would ſhroud
               Your radiant Creſcent in a ſable Cloud:
               And hold thoſe enuious, ignorant, or dull,
               That cannot ſee, your Creſcent growing full.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 7.
            
               
                  QVI ✚ CVRAT ✚ VIGILANS ✚ DORMIT.
               
            
            
               THe carefull States-man, who the Key doth carie
               Of a a Kings Treaſury, muſt not (partiall) varie:
               But to iuſt cauſes compaſſe ſtill be ti'de:
               For Iuſtice (vniuſt ſhutting) opens wide,
               And lets in hard Opinion, to diſgrace
               His Soueraignes ſelfe, his Perſon, and his place.
               
               Nor muſt he careleſſe ſlumber: but thus keepe
               His lids vnſhut-vp by ſoft-fingred Sleepe:
               
               And hold a Counſell with the ſaddeſt howres
               Of ſilent Night: and ſpend his pureſt powers
               In care, to render to whom dues belong,
               That Subiects may haue right, and Kings no wrong.
               But you (Great Lord) beare vp this waight of Trust.
               
               With a moſt eaſie Care, becauſe moſt iuſt.
               
            
            
            
               〈1 page duplicate〉
            
            
            
               〈1 page duplicate〉
            
         
         
            
            TO THE LORD PRIVY SEALE.
            
               
                  HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE
               
            
            
               THoſe dreſsings that adorne both parts of Nature,
               Firſt, is expreſt in this Maieſticke Creature:
               
               Next, in theſe Flowres of Light both which preſent
               Your Honours at full height of complement,
               And Clearneſſe, which runnes through your noble Blood,
               
               Mixt with this two-fold tincture, Great and Good:
               
               What's here but ſhadow'd then, by outward kind,
               
               Bedeckes the 
                     
                        •
                     nner Roomes of your braue mind.
               
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 12.
            
               
                  ET ✚ DEO ✚ ET ✚ PATRIAE ✚
                  
               
            
            
               VVHen ere thou draw'ſt out thy reuenging rod,
               Let be for Countrey, and the cauſe of God:
               
               Elſe thy Oblations will thy curſes be,
               When thou encountreſt with thine enemy.
               Nor is it ſacrifice that can appeaſe
               Gods wrath, vnleſſe the mans obedience pleaſe
               More then his offering: for if his dull heart
               Thinkes he inricheth God in any part,
               By offering Hecatombs, he looſeth all:
               Nay further yet, he giues a ſword with all
               To Heau'ns high Iuſtice, by inuoking downe
               
                  Reuenge, in lieu of Guerdon, or a Crowne.
               
               Such as were ſacrifices once, ſuch bee
               Our prayers ſtill, and our true Sanctitie:
               
               Which is your In-mate, and familiar gueſt,
               More clearely ſeene in You, then here expreſt.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE LORD ADMIRALL.
            
               
                  HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE
               
            
            
               YOur ſable mullet like a Starre in blacke,
               
               Shewes what our honour'd Admirall doth lacke:
               And ſhewes as if that Starre of Effingham,
               
               Were thus bemourn'd in a briefe Epigram:
               
               This may your Pole-ſtarre be, moſt noble Lord,
               And guide you vnto that (ſo much abhorr'd)
               The mournfull, yet the bleſſed, Port of death,
               Blowne by the prayers of all good mens breath.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 9.
            
               
                  QVEL CHE DRITTO DA IL CIEL ✚ TORCER NON PVOSSI ✚
                  
               
            
            
               SVppoſe a Globe were faſt'ned in the skie,
               With cordes depending on it quarterly,
               And men ſhould ſtriue by violence to wreſt
               That cordage to what crooked forme they liſt,
               All wiſe men would conceiue them madly bent,
               Why ſhould they elſe impoſſibles attempt?
               And we may thinke it as abſurd a drift
               In him, who craftily ſhall hope to ſhift
               When Fate forbids him, or ſhall hope to thwart
               The good intentions of an honeſt heart.
               For that which heau'n directs (all ages ſee)
               May iniured, but not diuerted be.
               Seeke then no further, honeſt meanings can
               Make a plaine minde beſt policy in man.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE DVKE OF LENOX.
            
               
                  HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE
               
            
            
               VVHat neede I further ſtriue to amplifie
               Your high-borne worths, and noble dignitie:
               Then by theſe beautious flowres, which declare:
               Your mind's faire puritie, vnſtain'd, and bare:
               Theſe golden Buckles bordring them about,
               A Palizado, to keepe Fouleneſſe out.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 10.
            
               
                  NON MANCA AL FIN SE BEN TARDA. A VENIRE.
               
            
            
               THe Wolfe and Lyon once together met,
               And by agreement they their purpoſe ſet
               To hunt together: when they had obtainde
               Their bootie long purſude, the Wolfe refrainde
               No more then formerly, from greedineſſe:
               The Lyon apprehending, that much leſſe
               Might ſatisfie a beaſt no bigger growne,
               Thought all the purchaſe rather was his owne:
               And thought ſuppreſſion of a beaſt ſo baſe
               Was Iuſtice, to preſerue the common race
               Of harmleſſe beaſts; then ſpeedily he teares
               The Wolfe, to take away their vſuall feares.
               Eu'n thus when our great Monarch clearely ſaw,
               How that inſatiate Wolfe of Rome did draw
               More riches to his coffers, then deare ſoules
               To Heau'n, he like this Lyon then controules
               His vſurpation, deeming him a ſlaue,
               Who more intended to deuoure, then ſaue.
               But you know beſt to follow, in free courſe,
               The Beſt in beſt things, and paſſe by the worſe.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE MARQVESSE OF BVCKINOHAM.
            
               
                  HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE
               
            
            
               ALL that we ſee is comely, and delights▪
               
               The eyes; which ſtill are pleas'd with pretious ſights:
               And (as your golden Scallops) You appeare
               To promiſe (that which we may value deare)
               More then a glorious out-ſide, which containes.
               Meate, not to be diſclos'd without due paines:
               Thus is it ſcarce to be imagin'd how
               Deſert ſhould paralell your worth, or You.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 11.
            
               
                  INVIDIA ✚ SVVM ✚ TORQVET ✚ AVTHOREM.
               
            
            
               THis glorious Starre attending on the Sunne,
               
               Having, from this low world, iuſt wonder wonne
               For brightnes; Envie, that foule Stygian brand,
               T' extinguiſh it thruſts forth her greedie hand:
               
               To catch it from its mounted moving place,
               And hurle it lower to obſcur'd Diſgrace:
               
               But while ſhe ſnatches, to put out the flame,
               Fooliſhly fiers her fingers with the ſame.
               Who others glories ſtriuet' eclipſe (poore Elues)
               Doe but drawe downe ſelfe-miſchiefe on themſelues.
               You waiting on the Sunne of Maieſtie
               
               May that elamping Heliotropium be:
               Still bright in your Eclipticke circle runne,
               Y' are out of Envies reach, ſo neare the Sunne.
               
               Moue fairely, freely in your wonted Orbe,
               
               Aboue the danger of Detractions curbe,
               And her ſelfe-burſting Brood: ſit there, contemne,
               Nay laugh, and ſcorne both their deſpight, and them.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE LORD CHAMBERLINE.
            
               
                  HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE
               
            
            
               NOt becauſe you are given to rage or ſpoile,
               Like rampant Lyonse, which deſerue a Toyle:
               Nor yet becauſe your gifts devided be,
               Do Lyons thus divide themſelues in three:
               But (when provok'd) to ſhew you can reſiſt,
               Or ſhew your courage when Your Honor liſt:
               Or thus in number they doe looke one way,
               To ſhew, what You command, your friends obey.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 12.
            
               
                  CANDIDA, ✚ SAL DA, ✚ ET ✚ IMMOBILE ✚
                  
               
            
            
               FIxt heere ſnow-veſted Pietie remaines
               Al-pure, and in all pure, purg'd from the ſtaines
               Of all falſe worſhip, chaſte as aire, vntainted
               With the foule blemiſhes of that al-painted
               
                  Proude Curtizan: nor wander do's her mind,
               Shee beſt content in Conſtancy doth find:
               To Alethea's pillar cloſe ſhe clings,
               Maugre the rapting ſtraines Romes Syren ſings:
               Who is athirſt, and do's but touch her Cup,
               
               Drinkes, with delight, his ſoules ſaluation vp.
               Thus comprehends ſhe ioyes, which moſt would buy
               At the high'ſt rate, in this one Conſtancy,
               
               So aboue others may your Honours ſhine,
               As paſt all others, do's this Forme Diuine,
               
               With her ingenuous Beames blaze bright in you,
               Who's doubly gilt, with Her, and Learning too.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE EARLE OF ARVNDELL.
            
               
                  HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE
               
            
            
               ON Gules you beare the figure of a Bend
               
               Betweene croſſe croſſelets fixt: which all intend
               Rightly to ſhadow Noble birth, adorn'd
               With valour, and a Chriſtian cauſe, not ſcorn'd
               By any but by Infidels, and they
               Miſtaking this, their hel-bred hate diſplay.
               But to leaue ſhadowes, you (ſubſtantiall) ſhine
               With thoſe good things, which make a man diuine.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 13.
            
               
                  PACE ✚ FERMEZZA, ✚ E ✚ FRVTTO ✚ ALL' ✚ ALME ✚ APPORTO. ✚
                  
               
            
            
               KNow (honour'd Sir) that th'heate of Princes loue,
               Throw'n on thoſe reall Worths, good men approue,
               Doth, like the radiant Phoebus ſhining here,
               Make fruitfull vertue at full height appeare:
               T'illuſtrate this in you, were to confeſſe
               How much your Goodneſſe doth your Greatneſſe bleſſe,
               By its owne warme reflexe: Thus both ſuruiue,
               And both i'th Sunne of Royall fauour thriue.
               O may's reuerberating rayes ſtill nouriſh.
               Your noble Worths, and make your Vertues flouriſh.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE EARLE OF SOVTH-HAMPTON.
            
               
                  HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE
               
            
            
               NO ſtorme of troubles, or cold froſts of Friends,
               Which on free Greatnes, too too oft, attends,
               Can (by preſumption) threaten your free ſtate:
               For theſe preſaging ſea-birds doe amate
               Preſumptuous Greatnes: mouing the beſt mindes,
               By their approach, to feare the future windes
               Of all calamitie, no leſſe then they
               Portend to ſea-men a tempeſtuous day:
               Which you foreſeeing may before hand croſſe,
               As they doe them, and ſo prevent the loſſe.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 13.
            
               
                  IN ✚ VTRAQVE ✚ PERFECTVS ✚
                  
               
            
            
               VVHat coward Stoicke, or blunt captaine will
               Diſ-like this Vnion, or not labour ſtill
               To reconcile the Arts and victory?
               
               Since in themſelues Arts haue this quality,
               To vanquiſh errours traine: what other than
               Should loue the Arts, if not a valiant man?
               Or, how can he reſolue to execute,
               That hath not firſt learn'd to be reſolute?
               If any ſhall oppoſe this, or diſpute,
               Your great example ſhall their ſpite confute.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE EARLE OF HERTFORD:
            
               
            
            
               THeſe Lyons gardant wiſely ſeeme to take
               The name of gardant, for the flowers ſake:
               As if they kept the flower-de-luces thus
               From them, who any way obnoxious,
               Might gather them: it is a noble part,
               To keepe the glories purchaſ'd by deſert.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 12.
            
               
                  VNVM ✚ COR ✚ VNVS ✚ DEVS ✚ VNA ✚ RELIGIO ✚
                  
               
            
            
               THis Triple Cloſe, if diſ-united, none:
               But knit by faith, an indiuiduall One.
               
               Standing vnmoou'd, like an heroicke rocke,
               Affronts the batt'ries of fierce Enuies ſhocke.
               God, Heart, Religion, theſe, One, made of three,
               Ioyn'd in vnſeuer'd threefold Vnitie,
               
               Royall paire-royall (ſee) three are the ſame,
               He that hath this paire-royall wins the game.
               View, how this heart, and how theſe hands agree,
               Whoſe heart, and hands are one, thrice happy hee.
               And though two hands, yet but one are theſe two,
               Both doe the ſame, and both the ſame vndoe.
               
                  Concord makes in a million, but one heart,
               Whereat ſterne Hate may leuell her fierce dart,
               And deepely wound too, yet cannot that wound
               Diſanimate, or her free thoughts confound:
               But with a double Valour ſhe vp-beares
               Such hearts, aboue the ſtroke of baſer feares.
               Thus you within haue rais'd vp ſuch a fort,
               As keepes out Ills, and doth your good ſupport.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE EARLE OF ESSEX.
            
               
            
            
               THe chiefeſt of this Scuchion comprehends
               Three Torteaux, which vnto all commends
               A firme and plenteous liberality,
               Proper to you, and to your familie:
               And this one vertue, in you (cleare as day)
               All other vertues elements diſplay.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 16.
            
               
                  QVIS ✚ CONTRA ✚ NOS ✚
                  
               
            
            
               NO wild, or deſperate foole can hence collect
               Proofe to applaud his vice, or to protect:
               Nor can this Figure civill warre portend,
               Whither oppoſe, or whither it defend:
               But auntient Valour, that which hath advanc'd
               Our Predeceſſours, (while fine Courtiers danc'd)
               That's heere infer'd, to re-informe the mind
               By view of inſtances, wherein we find
               Recorded of your Aunceſtrie, whoſe fame
               Like forked thunder, threaten'd cowards ſhame;
               Who fearing, leſt on their deboſh'd baſe merit,
               Heav'n ſhould drop Bolts, by a flame-winged ſpirit.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE EARLE OF DORSET.
            
               
            
            
               TIs true, your various Bend thus quarterly
               Deſcrib'd, poynts out the great antiquitie,
               Of Honour, and of Vertue truely claim'd
               By You, who haue preſeru'd them free, vnmaim'd.
               Let none that's generous thinke his time ill ſpent,
               To imitate your Worths ſo eminent.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 17.
            
               
                  D'ODORE ✚ IL ✚ MONDO ✚ E ✚ D'ACVTEZZA ✚ IL ✚ GIELO. ✚
                  
               
            
            
               THe world whoſe happineſſe, and cheife delight,
               Nay more, whoſe 
                     ▪Wiſedome lies in Appitite,
               
               Rather then Knowledge; claimes the largeſt ſhare
               Of that which pleaſeth moſt: nor doth it care
               To comprehend a higher myſterie:
               And therefore well doth nature dignifie
               Th' aſcending point, with heau'ns neere neighbour hood
               Leauing to earth what's great, to heau'n what's good.
               
               Which you perceiuiug, wiſely doe beſtow,
               Your thoughts on Heav'n, your wealth on things below.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE EARLE OF MOVNTGOMERY.
            
               
                  HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE
               
            
            
               THe Creſcent to a ſecond Houſe belongs,
               The golden Creſcent (worth a Poets ſongs)
               Well appertaines vnto thy Houſe and thee,
               
               Thou Arch-ſupporter of Mountgomery.
               
               For not the vaprous breath of bad report,
               Can cloud the ſplendour thou deſeru'ſt in Court:
               But as in gold no ruſt can finde a place,
               So hath thy Creſcent no enforc'd diſgrace.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 18.
            
               
                  MVSICA ✚ DII ✚ PLACANTVR ✚ MVSICA ✚ MANES.
               
            
            
               AS buſie Bees vnto their Hiue doe ſwarme,
               So do's th'attractiue power of Muſicke charme
               All Eares with ſilent rapture: nay, it can
               Wilde Reaſon re-contract, diuorc'd from man.
               
                  Birds in their warblings imitate the Spheares:
               
               This ſings the Treble, that the Tenour beares:
               
                  Beaſts haue with liſtning to a Shepheards lay,
               Forgot to feed, and ſo haue pin'd away:
               
                  Brookes that creepe through each flowr-befretted field,
               In their harmonious murmurs, muſicke yeeld:
               Yea, ſenſeleſſe ſtones at the old Poets ſong,
               Themſelues in heapes did ſo together throng,
               That to high beauteous ſtructures they did ſwell
               Without the helpe of hand, or vſe of skill:
               
               This Harmony in t'humane Fabricke ſteales:
               And is the ſinewes of all Common-weales.
               In you this Concord's ſo diuinely placed:
               That it by you, not you by it is graced.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE LORD VISCOVNT LIS
                  •
               E.
            
               
                  HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE
               
            
            
               LEt there be no addition, this alone
               Will make an Embleme, and a perfect one.
               Conceiue it thus then: A Darts forked head
               
               Apt to endanger, though not ſtriking dead.
               Such is, or ſhould be every noble mind,
               
               Prepar'd like this in moſt reſolued kind
               To wound, or kill offenſiue iniury,
               And though vnurg'd, yet threatens dangers nie.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 19.
            
               
                  ORDINE ✚ TEMPO ✚ NVMERO ✚ EMISVRA ✚
                  
               
            
            
               HEre Sience do's in contemplation ſit,
               Diſtinguiſhing by formes, the ſoule of wit:
               Knowing, perfection ha's no proper grace,
               
                  If wanting Order, Number, Time, or Place:
               The Theoricke and Practicke part muſt be
               As heate and fire: the Sunne, and Claritie:
               Such twins they are, and ſuch Correlatiues,
               As the'one without the other ſeldome thriues.
               How can a man the feates of Armes well doe,
               If not a Scholler, and a Souldiour too?
               If either then be miſſing in's due place,
               Defect ſteps in, and ſteales from all their grace:
               On good acts you employ the practicke part,
               The Theory lies lodg'd within your heart.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE LORD VISCOVNT WALLINGFORD.
            
               
                  HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE
               
            
            
               VVEll may you neuer find the want, or loſſ
               Of that moſt hallowed, and inſtructing Croſſe,
               
               On which our Saviour di'de: for theſe will ſhew
               The many bleſſed thoughts of that, in few:
               Heere you may over-looke the world, and ſee
               Nothing ſo plentifull, as croſſes be:
               Thence you may take occaſion to prepare
               Your ſoule, to beare thoſe that worſe croſſes are.
               Theſe are the badges of Your noble breſt,
               That will conduct You to heave'ns quiet reſt.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 20.
            
               
                  SOTT ✚ HVMANO ✚ SEMBIANTE ✚ EMPIO ✚ VENENO ✚
                  
               
            
            
               THus playes the Courtly Sycophant, and thus
               Selfe-pleaſing Sinne, which poyſons all of vs:
               Thus playd the whore whome the wiſe King deſcribes:
               Thus he who rayles at, and yet pockets bribes:
               Thus playes the Polititian, who will ſmile,
               Yet like this Serpent ſting your heart the while.
               Bung vp thyne eares then, or ſuſpect the harme,
               When ſweete Cyllenian words begin to charme.
               But you, can theſe vnmask by knowing beſt
               How to keepe ſuch from lurking neere your breaſt.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE BISHOP OF LONDON.
            
               
            
            
               TWo ſwords there be, which all Diuines ſhould take,
               E're they this victory can perfect make:
               Preuailing Language is a powerfull one,
               
                  Zeale for the truth, the other: theſe haue done
               More noble acts, then warre could euer boaſt:
               Both are in your Field found, though elſe-where loſt.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME. 21.
            
               
            
            
               ME thinkes (Right Reuerend) here you ſilence
               Viewing this Embleme, &amp; it thus beſpeake: (breake.
               Ride on Triumphing, make a glorious ſhew,
               Catch thoſe, who onely but thy Out-ſide know:
               Hold forth thy witching Cup, aduance thy Crowne,
               
               And' Mounted thinke thy ſelfe paſt pulling downe:
               Yet after all, thou canſt be prou'd no more,
               Then a deluding, and deluded whore.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE BISHOP OF WINCHESTER.
            
               
            
            
               THe Sword and Keyes to Church-men beene bequeathed,
               Since Paul and Peter were of life bereaued:
               The Keyes, a type of Prayers, which unlocke
               Heau'ns glorious gates, to let in thoſe that knocke.
               The Spirits zealous, and ſoule-ſauing Word,
               
               Is ſhadow'd by the ſinne-ſubduing Sword:
               
               Of Word and Sword th'incorporate qualitie
               Ha's power to heaue baſe earth aboue the skie.
               Your powerfull, and victorious elegance,
               Which ouercomes bold vice and arrogance,
               Do's proue, no weapons to the Church belong,
               But ſuch as Heau'n makes to encounter wrong:
               Nor do's your Gentry differ: Lozenges
               
               Are curing Cordials: Gentrous thoughts like theſe.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 22.
            
               
                  SERO ✚ IVPITER ✚ DIPHTHERAM ✚ INSPEXIT ✚
                  
               
            
            
               BEhold, on what the Romaine Faith conſiſts:
               So toſt by Errours winds; ſo lapt in Miſts;
               That their Arch-pilot ſcarſe can rule the ſterne▪
               
               He lackes foundation, therefore ſtill to learne
               How to make's Ship his Harbour. O I wonder
               Th'ore burden'd Veſſell crackes not quite aſunder,
               And ſinkes not downe, oppreſt by its owne weight,
               With ſinfull ſoules ſo ſtuft, and over-freight.
               The high Auenger (though he ſeemes to faile)
               With winged wrath will ſplit their proudeſt ſaile.
               Heau'ns yron-hand (moſt ſlowly heau'd aloft)
               Falls quicke, dead-ſure, and home, although not oft.
               All wiſh, for their ſakes of Romes ſimpler ſort,
               That you might ſteere their veſſell to the Port:
            
         
         
            
            TO THE BISHOP OF ELY.
            
               
            
            
               HOw much more better may you challenge theſe,
               Then all your Predeceſſors, who in eaſe,
               And ſloath (you being conſider'd) did neglect
               That which deſerues a Crowne, or good reſpect:
               Theſe then the Heralds may thinke rather due,
               Not to your place of ſtate, but vnto you.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 23.
            
               
                  VNVM ✚ ET ✚ ALTERVM ✚ DIVINVM ✚
                  
               
            
            
               
                  REligion ſtill its owne, cannot be loſt,
               Nor from it ſelfe diuorc'd, though to the moſt,
               Who iudge by gueſſe and ſlight formality,
               There might appeare ſchiſme in Diuinity:
               
               When not Diuinity, which cannot change,
               But humane reaſon to ſchiſmes vild doth range:
               For ſo the fruites of diuers plants may ſeeme
               Diuers in quality: and men may deeme
               
                  Nature hath err'd in ſuch a ſerious courſe,
               When both conſider'd be the ſame in force.
               You, that beſt iudge of Schiſmes, can clearely ſee,
               Error term'd Truth, and Truth term'd Hereſie.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE LORD ZOVCU:
            
               
            
            
               SEe, how a worthy ſpirit not imployde
               May ſeeme to lookers on, or vaine, or voyd:
               Theſe golden peeces thus vnſhap't, vncoin'd,
               Seeme as if worth and they were quite diſioyn'd:
               When braſſe or copper being ſtamp't or fram'd
               Into the ſhape of plate, is oft miſnam'd,
               And oft miſtaken for the pureſt gold:
               But you are ever actiue, and vnfold
               Your pretious ſubſtance, that your ſelfe may take,
               
                  Honours true ſtampe; what's counterfeite forſake.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 24.
            
               
                  CHIARO ✚ QVIETO ✚ PROFONDO ✚ E. ✚ DIVINO.
               
            
            
               HEere Phoebus and the Sacred Siſters ſit,
               Chiefely attending Harmonie, and Wit:
               
               Who ſtay to heare the dying Swans to ſing
               Sad Epods; riding on the Theſpian Spring.
               Heere the Wingd-Horſes hoofe digs vp that Well
               
               Whence gurgle ſtreames of Art, and ſacred Skill.
               
               
                  Divines (like Pegaſus) divinely mooue
               In Man, ſprings of profound, and precious loue
               To heav'nly Wiſedome; who t'ech paſſing by,
               Poynts out the path-way to Eternitie.
               
               And whilſt You doe your noble thoughts confine
               To what Divines preach, You become Divine.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE LORD WINDSOR.
            
               
            
            
               ME thinkes, I ſee in this, the true eſtate
               Of man ſtill ſubiect to a luckleſſe fate:
               As if the greateſt Croſſe did repreſent
               The generall curſe, which even all over went.
               From Adam to his wretched progeny:
               The leſſer Croſſes which accompany
               The greater, be each ſeverall hapleſſe chance:
               And all together ſhew, that ignorance
               Is irrecoverably blind, where none
               Prevents what happens thus to every one.
               But You doe well ſupport the waightieſt croſſes
               With Patience, and eſteeme them but light loſſes.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 25.
            
               
                  PACE ✚ A ✚ GLIELETTI ✚ E ✚ GVERRA ✚ A ✚ GLIEMPI ✚ E ✚ REI.
               
            
            
               YEe, whoſe blind folly doth not ſo maintaine
               A former choice, but yee may chuſe againe:
               And yee, whoſe innocence (not knowing yet
               The worſe from better) careleſly doth let
               Both reſt vnchoſen: now begin to make
               Your new, or firſt choiſe, and heere wiſely tak e
               The patterne: if you would encline to Peace,
               Loue bookes with Vertue ſtor'd, ſo will decreaſe
               Your troubles: thoſe will bring ſuch powerfull fame,
               As ſhall the ſterneſt Lyon ſooneſt tame.
               Experience leades thee to this certaine choice,
               Chuſe then at firſt, to grieue, or to reioice.
               You haue already choſen true Content:
               
               Nor needs your Honour euer to repent.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE LORD WENTVVORTH.
            
               
            
            
               
                  LEopards haue euer ranked bin among
               Thoſe nobler beaſts, which are both ſwift &amp; ſtrong.
               
                  Swiftnes alludes to a dexteritie,
               Or quicke diſpatch without temeritie.
               Their Strength alludes to Iudgement which indures,
               When flaſhing Wit no long delight aſſures.
               Make theſe your owne, and then you beare diſplay'd,
               Your Scutchions morrall, in your ſelfe pourtray'd.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 26.
            
               
                  IOVIS ✚ APOLLINIS ✚ ET ✚ MINERVAE ✚
                  
               
            
            
               
                  IOue, Phoebus, and Minerua were aſſign'd,
               To be the three chiefe ornaments of mind.
               Ioue figur'd Prouidence, Minerua, Wit,
               
                  Phoebus, Content: and all that purchaſ'd it
               Well are they ſeated in a holy place,
               To ſhew the Continent of all, is grace:
               It ſeemes that you haue well conſider'd thus:
               The fair'ſt of titles is, Religious.
               
            
         
         
            
            TO THE LORD DARCIE.
            
               
            
            
               THeſe health-preſeruing leaues thus inly fixt
               Amongſt the Croſſelets; ſhew, heau'ns fauours mixt
               With all calamities that ſeaze on man,
               If patiently he entertaine them can.
               To find cure then for Croſſes, looke aboue:
               See, ill made well by heau'ns all-curing loue.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 27.
            
               
                  ET ✚ TENEBRAE ✚ FACTAE ✚ SVNT ✚
                  
               
            
            
               SLeepe, being the type of death: darkneſſe muſt be
               The ſhade of that, which we euaniſht ſee:
               Men ſo departed, that it may be ſaid,
               A Bird, as well, as ſuch a man, is dead:
               Chaſe, while thou liu'ſt, the cloudes of death away:
               Or dying, neuer looke to ſee more day.
               You haue on earth, ſo ſtudied heau'ns delight,
               That you can neuer be obſcur'd: though night
               Should threaten to obſcure noone-day, yet will
               Your Noble mind vanquiſh deaths darkeſt ill.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE LORD WOTTON.
            
               
            
            
               SEtled afflictions may be well expreſſ't
               Vnder this forme of Croſſes, which men bleſt
               Haue ſtill indur'd to proue their patience:
               But I would rather in another ſence
               Haue this appli'de to ſuch a man, whoſe vowes
               Haue fixt him to the faith Chriſts Church allowes:
               And ſuch a man (ſcorning vngrounded wrongs)
               Are you, to whom this fixed Croſſe belongs.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 28.
            
               
                  TEMPVS ✚ CORONAT ✚ INDVSTRIAM.
               
            
            
               TH'aſcending Path that vp to wiſedome leades
               Is rough, vneuen, ſteepe: and he that treades
               Therein, muſt many a tedious Danger meet,
               That, or trips vp, or clogs his wearied feet:
               Yet led by Labour, and a quicke Deſire
               
               Of faireſt Ends ſcrambles, and clambers higher
               Then Common reach: ſtill catching to holde faſt
               On ſtrong'ſt Occaſion, till he come at laſt
               Vp to Her gate, where Learning keepes the key,
               And lets him in, Her beſt Things to ſuruay:
               There he vnkend (though to himſelfe beſt knowne)
               Takes reſt, till Time preſents him with a Crowne:
               In queſt of this rich Prize, your toyle's thus graced:
               Euer to be in Times beſt Border placed.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE LORD STANHOPE.
            
               
            
            
               THis enterchang'd variety of Furre,
               
               And naked quarters, fitly doe concurre.
               To ſhew the ſeaſonable contenting ſtore
               That rich wiſe men inioy, alike with poore:
               Both are prouided (leſt they might take harme)
               To keepe their innocence, both ſafe and warme.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 29.
            
               
                  BIS ✚ INTERIMITVR ✚ QVI ✚ SVIS ✚ ARMIS ✚ PERIT ✚
                  
               
            
            
               IMagine heere, Chriſt ſtrongly fortifi'd,
               Againſt the Popes bold herefie and pride:
               And thinke, whilſt his Accomplices combine
               The Caſtle of Chriſts truth, to vndermine;
               A flame breakes forth, which doth conſume them all:
               So ſeeking his, they meete with their owne fall.
               And thus whilſt heretickes (like wretched elues)
               Out-ſtare the Truth, they doe condemne themſelues,
               Subiected to the twofold victory
               Of Truth, and of their owne impietie.
               Take refuge then, in Heau'ns eternall reſt,
               And ſee Chriſts foes againſt themſelues addreſt.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE LORD CAREVV.
            
               
            
            
               THe nobleſt parts of Wiſedome, as cleare wit,
               
               High Courage, and ſuch vertues kinne to it:
               Should ever be proceeding, and goe on
               Forward, as ſeeme theſe Lyons; vrg'd of none.
               So (like to theſe) You keepe a paſſant pace,
               Till Wiſedome ſeate You in your wiſhed place.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME. 30.
            
               
                  VIRTVS ✚ VNITA ✚ FORTIOR ✚
                  
               
            
            
               FOrces vnited geminate their force,
               And ſo doth vertue: never ſhould remorſe
               Nor obſtacle reſtraine that man, who may
               Strengthen his vertues by a noble way:
               Who cannot perfect be, needes not repent
               To add his owne t' anothers Preſident.
               And he that is entire may therewithall,
               By others helpe proue more effectuall.
               So helpe me Learning, as I doe not know,
               Where I this Embleme fitter may beſtowe.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE LORD HAYE.
            
               
            
            
               
                  BEauties chiefe elements of White and Red
               
               Is all that in your Coate is figured:
               Nor is it needfull, any thing ſhould be
               Added to this moſt copious myſterie:
               
                  Gules vpon Argent to conceit are playne,
               And pourtray out a life without all ſtaine.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 31.
            
               
                  MERITVM ✚ SIBI ✚ MVNVS ✚
                  
               
            
            
               SEe Bountie ſeated in her beſt of pride,
               Whoſe fountaines never ebbe, ever full tide
               At every change: ſee, from her ſtreaming heart,
               How rivulets of Comfort doe impart
               To Worth dryde vp by Want; and to aſſwage
               The drought of Vertue in her pilgrimage.
               Looke, how her wide-ſtretcht, fruit-befurniſht hand
               Vnlockt to true Deſert, do's open ſtand:
               But if ſhe ſhould not be Deſerts regarder,
               Yet is it, in itſelfe, its owne rewarder.
               This Emblem's not preſented (Noble Sir)
               Your bounteous nature to awake, or ſtir:
               For you are Bounties Almner, and do's know,
               How to refraine, deſtribute, or beſtow.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE THREE LORDES CHIEFE IVSTICES.
            
               
            
            
               BY theſe life-lengthning Lozenges, are ſhow'n
               
                  Cares to cure Ills, by times corruption grow'n▪
               
               To comfort Vertues heart, at point to die
               Of a Conſumption, and doth bed-rid lie:
               This Starre, that Iuſtice is, which is not blind,
               (As th'ancient Hieroglyphickes her defin'd)
               But ſearcheth out with quicke diſcerning eye
               Th'hard difference twixt Faith and Fallacy.
               
               Theſe Birds, as yet vnlearnt to light on earth,
               Figure that Iustice, which from Heau'n ha's Birth,
               And ſcornes to looke ſo low, as baſe reſpect
               
               Of its owne priuate ends, and Truth neglect.
               
                  Care, Truth, and Iuſtice thus vnite, we ſee
               Make in their Goodneſſe mixt, a Sympathy,
               On whoſe ioynt pinions the Realmes Peace vp-towres
               T'her Chaire of State, ſubſiſteted by your powres.
            
         
         
            
            
               EMBLEME 32.
            
               
                  SIC ✚ VBIQVE ✚
                  
               
            
            
               SHe that illuminates the midnight, may
               Be well admitted to take reſt all day:
               Yet haue our antique Poets rather made
               Night-wandring Luna t'haue a daily Trade;
               Reporting, that by day ſhe takes delight
               To hunt wilde creatures, and then ſhines at night:
               Teaching (or I miſtake) how Magiſtrates
               
               Should quell Diſorders in all ciuill States.
               In darkneſſe they ſhould watchfull inſight keepe,
               To hunt out Vice, when men are thought aſleepe:
               For Miſchiefe (as in darkneſſe) skulkes diſguis'd,
               And therefore needs ſome watchfully aduis'd,
               Who hauing ſented out this ſecret game,
               May then purſue them to a publicke ſhame.
               But your deepe wiſedomes, better know, then this,
               What in our Common-weale moſt needfull is.
            
         
      
   

