
   
      
         
            The mourning of Mount Libanon: or, The temples teares A sermon preached at Hodsocke, the 20. day of December, anno Domini, 1627. In commemoration of the right honourable and religious lady, the Lady Frances Clifton, daughter to the Right Honourable the Earle of Cumberland: and wife to the truly noble Sir Geruas Clifton of Clifton, in the county of Nottingham, Knight and Baronet, who deceased the 20. Nouember, 1627. By William Fuller Doctor of Diuinity, one of his Maiesties chapleines in ordinary.
            Fuller, William, 1579 or 80-1659.
         
         
            
               1628
            
         
         Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01347
            STC 11468
            ESTC S102826
            99838588
            99838588
            2972
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01347)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2972)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1098:07)
         
         
            
               
                  The mourning of Mount Libanon: or, The temples teares A sermon preached at Hodsocke, the 20. day of December, anno Domini, 1627. In commemoration of the right honourable and religious lady, the Lady Frances Clifton, daughter to the Right Honourable the Earle of Cumberland: and wife to the truly noble Sir Geruas Clifton of Clifton, in the county of Nottingham, Knight and Baronet, who deceased the 20. Nouember, 1627. By William Fuller Doctor of Diuinity, one of his Maiesties chapleines in ordinary.
                  Fuller, William, 1579 or 80-1659.
               
               [6], 37, [3] p.   
               
                  Printed by Thomas Harper for Robert Bostocke, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the Kings Head,
                  London :
                  1628.
               
               
                  Running title reads: The temples teares.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Clifton, Frances, --  Lady, 1593 or 4-1627.
               Funeral sermons.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-01
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-01
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-08
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-08
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE
MOVRNING
of Mount Libanon:
OR,
THE TEMPLES TEARES.
A
Sermon preached at Hodſocke, the 20. day of
December, Anno Domini, 1627.
In commemoration of the Right Honourable and Religious
Lady, the Lady FRANCES CLIFTON,
Daughter to the Right Honourable the Earle
of Cumberland:
And Wife to the truly noble Sir Geruas Clifton of Clifton, in the
County of Nottingham, Knight and Baronet, who deceaſed
the 20. Nouember, 1627.
            By WILLIAM FVLLER Doctor of Diuinity, one of his
Maieſties Chapleines in Ordinary.
            ECCLES. 40. 19.
            Children and the building of a City continue a mans name, but a
blameleſſe wife is counted aboue them both.
            
               LONDON,
¶Printed by Thomas Harper for Robert Boſtocke, and are to
be ſold at his ſhop in Pauls Church-yard, at the ſigne
of the Kings Head. 1628.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE MVCH
honoured,
Sir GERVAS CLIFTON,
Of Clifton, in the County of Nottingham
Knight and Baronet, my most
noble Patrone.
            
               Noble SIR,
            
            
               HOW much J ſtand
obliged to your loue
and bounty, ſhould I
be ſilent, others would
testifie: to conceale it,
were to call witneſſes;
and to denie it, to proclayme
ingratitude.
Neither hath your reſpect come ſingle or alone.

For thoſe excellent Ladies, of pious memorie,
which ſucceſsiuely made your bed happy, and I
hope your houſe proſperous, as they were to you
moſt deare, ſo to me moſt noble: neuer ſtranger
found either more encouragement in his labors,
or more ample remonſtrance of an honourable
loue. But there is no earthly contentment, but
hath interruption or intermixtion: wee muſt
leaue it, or it muſt leaue vs. I onely, now inſtance
in this, that God hath taken thoſe ornaments
of their ſex, as fit for heauen, too goo
                  •
               
for earth, to both which liuing, I was indebted
and for both dead (by your election) the ſad▪
membrancer. Others might haue ſet out their
perfections better, none more mournfully or
more truely. In which the rareneſſe of the ſubiects
haue had the power to make my weakneſſe,
not onely to paſſe without cenſure, but the publiſhing
to bee importuned with an earneſt zeale,
both by your ſelfe and others of their and your
honorable friends. The firſt long ſince went out
in written copies: this laſt (it ſeemeth) muſt
not be reſtrained within ſo narrow bounds, nor
the deſire of many ſatisfied without more ample

notice. Which ſithence it muſt come to publique
view: to whom ſhould I preſent it, but your ſelfe,
who haue the loſſe, and knowe the truth, from
whom I haue receiued my meanes, and to
whom I ſhall euer remaine thankfull,
and faithfull in all Chriſtian
duties.
            
               William Fuller.
            
            
            
               〈1 page duplicate〉
            
            
            
               〈1 page duplicate〉
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            
               ZACHARIE 11. 2.
               
                  Ʋlula abies, quia cecidit Cedrus, &amp;c.
Howle thou firre tree, for the Cedar is fallen.
               
            
            
               ALl the former Prophets (one only
excepted) did ſee, or foreſee
the Temples deſolation, the
holy Cities widowhood; how
ſhe that was ſo great among the
nations, the princeſſe among
the prouinces, was become tributary,
weeping continually euen
in the night,Ier. La. 1. 1 and the teares running downe her
cheekes, whileſt the people ſigh, and ſeeke their bread
abroad, the elders ſit vpon the ground and keepe ſilence,
caſt duſt vpon their heads, and gird themſelues
with ſackcloth, whileſt the virgins hang downe their
heads:La. 2. 10. all crying the ioy of our hearts is gone, our
daunce is turned into mourning, the crowne of our
head is fallen,La. 5. 15. 16. woe now vnto vs that we haue ſinned.
But Haggai, Zacharie, and Malachie, are rayſed as
meſſengers of glad tidings to tell the comfort of a
bleſſed deliuerance: that the gold ſhould be no more
ſo dimme, nor the fine gold ſo changed, that the

ſtones of the ſanctuary, ſhould no longer bee ſo ſcattered
in the corner of euery ſtreet. But it is the nature
of all earthly hopes to be like ſicke mens pulſes
full of intermiſſions, there being rarely ſeene, ſperate
miſeri, in the ſuperſcription, hope ye wretched, but
it is ſubſcribed with cauete foelices, beware ye happy.
No day ſo fayre without ſome cloud, nor life ſo ſucceſſefull
without ſome croſſes:Exod. 12. the ioyfulleſt feaſt the
Iewes had was eaten with ſowre herbes, and the
bleſſed Euangeliſts themſelues as they preach Chriſt
and his mercies, ſo his croſſe and our afflictions. And
this our Prophet ſent to proclayme reſtauration to
the people:cap. 9. to his exulta ſatis filia Zion, &amp;c. reioyce
greatly, O daughter Zion; ſhout for ioy, O daughter
Ieruſalem; behold thy king commeth vnto thee &amp;c.
in preſcience of that aduent which wee are within ſo
few dayes to celebrate, annexeth an interruption in
my text, and ſome verſes following. Vlula abies, quia
cecidit Cedrus howle thou firre tree, for the Cedar
is fallen.
            I may terme my text the mourning of mount Libanon,
               1. Reg. 5. 8.
a hill repleniſhed with firres and cedars: or the
temples teares, for it was builded of that wood fetched
from that mountayne: and Hector Pintus interpreting
the 17. of Ezekiel and the 3. verſe, where an
Eagle is ſaid to come vnto Libanon and take the higheſt
branch of the Cedar, maketh Libanon to bee the
Temple, and prooueth it out of the Chaldee paraphraſt,
which readeth the former verſe to my text.
Open thy doores, O Libanon, thus: Open thy doores,
O temple, and the fire ſhall deuour thy Cedars: ſome
meane the holy City, ſome the land of promiſe, but

all agree that it may inſinuate the lamentation of
Gods people for ſome great one fallen. And God we
know doth often cloath his will in parables,Gerſon ſer. 19. poſt pentec. 
               vt noua
minùs fastidiat variet as, that variety may delight and
make a deepe impreſſion in him that heareth: Nathans
tale of the poore mans ſheepe that was his
whole flocke,2 Sam. 12. went to the quicke with Dauid: nor
is there a more piercing paſſage in the whole booke
of God, then Iothams parable of the trees chooſing
their king,Iud. 9. and all refuſed the troubleſome honour,
but onely the ambitious bramble, meaning Abimelech
the vſurper. Omnis homo arbor inuerſa: euery
man (they ſay) is a tree with the root vpward and
the armes downeward. Suppoſe mee then to be this
houre vpon mount Libanon condoling with the firre
trees, becauſe a Cedar is fallen.
            In the words of the Prophet are three probleme
queſtions, (as parts obſeruable) to be both diſcuſſed
and reſolued. 1. Why it is ſayd Vlula: howle, a ſigne
of ſorrow without meaſure. 2. Quare abies, why the
firre tree ſhould howle, it being the hieroglyphicke
of a childe of God, who is in no caſe to ſorrow as a
man without hope. 3. Quare, quia cecidit Cedrus:
why, for the Cedars fall. Sithence it is cut down only
for the building of the Sanctuary, and to its owne
increaſe of glory. This is the compaſſe I am to ſayle
by, vntill I land vpon the ſhore I ſteere to, which is
the ſad occaſion of this dayes meeting.
            A wiſe-man ſhould not vſe much paſſion,Quare dicit, vlula. nor a
good man perſwade it, for the one argueth weakeneſſe
of iudgement, the other wickedneſſe of minde. Affections
being thoſe vnruly beaſts, which reaſon and

religion ſtriue to bridle. But there is a great difference
betwixt quid agitur, and quid deletur; what is done,
and what ſhould be done: as is betwixt contemplation
and practiſe; the one liuing in politiâ Platonis,
the other in faece Romult: they are but in a dreame
that conceiue a common wealth without corruption,
a Church without errour, or a man without paſſion.
It is an eaſie matter for one in health and plenty to
crie ſhame on him that is diſtracted with payne and
care: and for the wanton on his couch to diſeſteeme
the ſoldier in his tent, becauſe not more hardy both
in cold and danger, when tu ſi hic eſſes, change but
the condition of the parties and the caſe is altered. A
publicke loſſe is a generall ſorrow, to the bewayling
whereof the greateſt expreſſion is required: a teare
is not held ſufficient, where there ſhould be an inundation;
nor a ſigh, where howling. Rachel in childbirth
called her ſonne of which ſhe died ben-oni,
               Gen. 35. 18. the
ſonne of ſorrow. Naomi biddeth her friends call her
no more Naomi, that is beautifull, but Mara, that is
bitterneſſe,Ruth 1. 20. out of the ſence of her miſery: but Phineas
his wife had iuſt cauſe to name her ſonne Ichobod,
that is,1. Sam. 4. 21. where is glory? becauſe the glory was departed
from Iſrael, for the Arke of the Lord was taken,
O that my head were full of waters, and mine
eyes a fountayne of teares, to weepe day and night
for the ſlaine of the daughter of my people, (ſayd the
Prophet Ieremy;)
               9. 
                     •
                  . and thence it was, that our Prophet
in the chapter following would haue the mourning
of Ieruſalem like the mourning of Hadadrimmon in
the valley of Megiddon,
               verſ. 11. yet not euery family apart,
and their wiues apart,verſ. 12. (as it there followeth) but their

forces ioyned both of teares and ſhrikings to mooue
heauen to pitty, and earth to imitate. Abyſſus abyſſum
inuocat: one depth calleth for another; great ſinnes
muſt haue great repentance, and great iudgements
great acknowledgement. Mine eyes doe fayle with
teares, my bowels ſwell, my liuer is powred vpon
the earth, for the deſtruction of the daughter of my
people, becauſe the children and ſucklings faint in the
ſtreets of the city,Ier. La. 
                     •
                  . 11. 12. and ſay to their mothers, where is
bread and drinke, as the Prophet complayneth: although
reaſon and religion ſhould forbid, yet nature
and neceſſity wou'd inforce a howling. Yet is not all
this a note of diſtruſt of Gods prouidence, but a manifeſtation
that we are ſenſible of his iuſtice and our
demerits:Aug. dever. Apoſt. ſer. 33. 
               Quid miraris quod Maria dolebat, tuno
cum ipſe Dominus flebat? It is no maruell if Mary
greeued, when as her Lord himſelfe wept; not as bewayling
the dead man whom hee preſently intended
both to rayſe and to recouer, but the dead mans ſinne
which had attracted death for puniſhment. Sicut mors
animae praeceſſit deſerente Deo,
               Idem ibid. 
               ſic mors corporis ſecuta
eſt deſerente animâ. Thus then in all ſorrow this is
the higheſt note.La. 5. 1
                     •
                  
                  ▪
                Woe vnto vs that we haue ſinned.
The death of the ſoule was firſt when God forſooke
it; and the death of the body ſoone followed, the
ſoule forſaking it in condigne recompence. Whence
in the truth of iudgement, the iuſt cauſes of extreme
ſorrow in a man are, vel cum ipſe, vel cum proximus
offendit Deum: when either himſelfe or ſome other
offend his God. And though a man may ſeeke, yet
ſhall hee neuer finde any true cauſe like vnto this.De miſeriâ hominis.
Which cauſed Anſelmus to phraſe it in theſe termes:

when I conſider the multitude of mine offences, I
ſhame to liue, I feare to die; then what remayneth,
ô ſinner, in thy whole life, but only vt ipſa tota ſe ploret
totam, to bewayle thy whole life: ſo waſhing (as
Saint Bernard ſpeaketh) the barrenneſſe of his ſoule
with the floods of teares,Serm. in Cant. 20. 
               quia magis frugiferae lacrymantes
vineae: the bleeding vines for the moſt part
are moſt fruitfull.
            And yet in this we muſt not ſorrow as men without
hope: for with God there is mercy that hee
might be feared: maiores motus impediunt minores:
the greater wheeles doe hinder the leſſers motion, and
the ſonne of God the ſinnes of man. Subordinate
powers hauing but limited authority, mooued from
aboue as is the inferiour by the higher orbe, the proconſull
can doe nothing but what the Conſull pleaſeth
either to command or to permit: as praeſumptio
ſuperbiae de proprio ingenio, is a courſe held without
carde or compaſſe, a mans owne works being a weak
ſtaffe to leane vpon. And ſo I ſee not how a Romaniſt
ſhould die comfortably, yet praeſumptio confidentiae
de diuino adiutorio, is the pole that cannot alter;
and ſo I ſee not how a true Chriſtian ſhould die deſperatly.
Moſt excellent is the counſell which the
Chancellour of Paris giueth: Before thou ſinneſt,
thinke of diuine iuſtice,Tract. de remed. contra puſillanimitatem. and thou wilt abſtayne: when
thou haſt ſinned, thinke of diuine mercy and thou
wilt not deſpayre. Síc
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ponderent ſuam negligentiam,
vt praeponderent Dei infinitam clementiam: So weighing
our owne negligence, with the counterpoyſe of
Chriſts indulgence.In 4. ſent. diſt. 16. It is a ſubtle queſtion that is
made by Deniſe out of Bonauenture, whether it bee

poſſible that contrition for ſinne can exceed the meaſure
of duty,Item Aquarius in 4. ſent. ex S. Thom. or we be more penitent then there is occaſion:
it being a rule that as much as the preſence
of any good is to bee beloued, ſo much the abſence
of it is to be lamented, but God and his grace cannot
be too much in one kinde, therefore neither the loſſe
in the other. Certainely (me thinkes for anſwer) quoad
diſplicentiam rationis, in eye of reaſon (if wee goe
no further) after ſinne we may weepe and diſpayre,
diſpayre and die; for how ſhould infinite ſinnes expect
any but infinite puniſhment:Aug. ſerm. 189. de tempore. but quoad deſperationem
fidei, in the apprehenſion of faith we may be
comforted, for that is the euidence of things not
ſeene, whence Chriſtians are called fideles, not rationales.
And it is contrition not attrition (as the
Schoole diſtinguiſheth) that affoords vs comfort.Idem lib. de verâ &amp; falſâ poenitent. cap. 9.
               Doleat, ſed ex fide doleat, ſaith Saint Auguſtine. Hence
it is Hector Pintus his obſeruation commenting vpon
Ezekiel,
               In 1. ſent. (yet borrowing it from Aquinas) that if it
were reuealed to any one that hee were a reprobate
to be condemned, that man were bound to eſteeme
of it, not as diuine reuelation, but a diabolicall illuſion.
Nay, if God himſelfe ſhould ſpeake it, it were to
be interpreted with an exception of repentance. And
in the 33.Ezech 33. 14. 15. of that Prophet, verſe 14. 15. it is made
manifeſt. Gods bleſſings pronounced in the preſent
tenſe doe intend praeſentiam extenſam, an act without
backſliding, continuing to our liues endings, and
his iudgements threatned are not abſolute, but conditionall,
if wee repent not: God can eaſily ſtay his
hand, could we as willingly amend our liues. If wee
doe ſuruey the booke of God, euery word that is vſed

to inſinuate his mercy will bee found effectuall.Panigarola ex Bonauent. in l
                     ••
                  . 5. For
conſider ſinne, as the bondage to Sathan, redimitur,
it is redeemed:Dan. 4 24. as the ſpoyle of grace, tegitur, it is
couered:Pſ. 32. 1. as the blot and blemiſh of nature, mundatur,
it is clenſed:Pſ. 51. 2. as the wound of conſcience, ſanatur,
it is healed:Pſ. 41. 4. as an offence againſt the higheſt, remittitur,
dimittitur,
               Matth. 9. 2. it is forgiuen. Then euen in this
great cauſe of ſorrow,Matth. 6. 14. our ſorrow muſt bee bounded.
Much more in humane croſſes, for they rightly apprehended
are but healthfull, (howſoeuer bitter) potions,
in which a ſeruant of God may in time finde
comfort, as Sampſon found hony in the Lions belly,
which lately menaced death: thus the waters which
Iſrael feared would haue drowned them, are on both
ſides as rampiers to defend them: the Lions fawne
on Daniel and deuour his aduerſaries: and the dogs
that ſhould haue bawled at Lazarus did licke his
ſores. The Drumme beaten a farre off, maketh a
fearefull noyſe; come neere and open it, and it ſhews
its owne emptineſſe, and our Panicke feare. Thus euery
paſſion hath bounds and limits; a man may be
tranſported too much both in ioy and ſorrow, as hee
that windeth vp the ſtrings too high, and he that letteth
them downe too low, doeth marre the muſicke.
Pope Leo the tenth that died for ioy was as erroneous,Ouicciard. lib. 14.
as others that dyed with griefe.Lib. 2. nat hiſt. 
               Plinie telleth
of a Lake, that although you powre in neuer ſo
much, it runneth not ouer, and let out abundance, yet
it ſtill is full. Mans heart ſhould bee ſo tempered, as
that affections ſhould neither runne out of it, nor ouer
it: for the one would make men ſtony hearted,
the other effeminately minded. As a man may vſe

pleaſure but not enioy it:Lib. 1. ſent. art. 5 Item Aug. lib. 11 deciuit. Dei, cap. 25. (ſo Lumbard diſtinguiſheth
betwixt uti and frui;) ſo ſuffer griefe but not ſink
vnder it. How well doe teares become the eyes in
the houſe of mourning, ſo that moderation lendeth a
napkin to drie vp exceſſe of weeping? And S. Ambroſe
ſpeaking of the death of Valentinian the Emperor
ſayth, that to pious affections there is a kind of
content euen in teares, &amp; plerumque graues lacrymas
euaporare dolorem, and that much weeping did euaporate
much ſorrow. Sure griefe oft times is like fire,
the more it is couered,Pet. Bleſſ. ep. 49. the more dangerouſly it burneth,
as the wound concealed rankleth inward. Saint
Bernard bewayling the death of Gerardus the monk
and his deereſt brother, ſayth, at his death my heart
fayled me,Serm. 26. in Cant. 
               ſed feci vim animo, with much adoe I diſſembled,
leſt affection ſhould ſeeme to ouercome religion,
and whileſt others wept abundantly ſecutus ego
ſiccis oculis inuiſum funus &amp;c. My ſelfe followed
with drie eyes the happy herſe. By-ſtanders with
watry cheekes admyring, whileſt they did not pitty
him, but me that loſt him. Indeed whereas teares
and words fayle, the blood leaueth the cheekes to
comfort the heart, and ſpeech giueth place to amazement;
like Niobe in the Poet, a woman turned to
marble, no difference betwixt men and ſtatues, but
that they are ſofter. That obſeruation of Saint Peter
is good,Ambr. ſerm. 46. 
               fleuit ſed tacuit, he wept but was ſilent:
as if his eyes would in ſome ſort tell what his tongue
could in no ſort vtter:Item lib. 10. in Lucam cap. 
                     •
                  6. 
               Leues dolores loquuntur, ingentes
ſtupent: They are ſmall miſeries, when hee that
hath them can preſently tell them. Thus hee that
howleth may haue leſſe ſorrow then hee that is mute

and ſilent, vox rationis pierceth heauen ſooner then
vox orationis: and God regardeth ſad hearts when
he doth not heare puling voyces. I come to the ſecond
part, Quare abies, to ſhew the cauſe of the firre
trees howling.
            Paſſion oft times commendeth what reaſon doth
diſallow,
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                and reaſon as often willeth what Religion
gayneſayth; ſo that the howling of briers and brambles
is no preſident for the firre trees mourning: that
is, a tree ſtraight and tall (not like the ſhrub, ſhort
and crooked) dwelling on mount Libanon, neighbour
to the Cedar, and both louingly ioyne to build
vp Gods Temple, the true types of Saynts in the
Church militant,1. Theſſa. 4. 13. which muſt not ſorrow as men
without hope:De verb. Apoſt. ſerm. 32. 
               Non vt contriſtemur, ſed non ſicut caeteri,
qui ſpem non habent, ſayth S. Auguſtine vpon that
place; Not that we ſhould not ſorrow, but that wee
ſhould not exceed in ſorrow: the beſt members of
Chriſts Church mourne for the neceſſity of the loſſe,
and yet are comforted with the aſſurance of a ſecond
meeting. Inde agimur, hinc conſolamur, inde infirmitas
afficit,
               
                  
                     •
                  dem vbi ſupra. 
               hint ſides reſicit: inde dolet humana conditio,
hinc ſanat diuina promiſsio: on the one ſide wee
are deiected, on the other cheriſhed; there affected
with infirmities, here erected by faith▪ there humane
condition woundeth, here diuine promiſe healeth,
as the ſame Father hath it. A man (ſaith Hector Pintus)
muſt not expect the medicine of time (time giueth
eaſe to all afflictions) when wee may preſently
haue that of reaſon;In Ezech. 24. nay of religion rather. For Gerſons
conſolation of Theologie doth farre exceede
Boëtius his conſolation of philoſophy, becauſe the ſupreme

part of the elementarie world, dependeth vpon
the inferior part of the celeſtiall, More concatenationis,
as links in chaines are ioyned; and robur Socraticum
is farre ſhort of robur Chriſtianum, the rules of
reaſon, of the principles of religion: where philoſophie
endeth, phyſick beginneth, and where reaſon faltereth,
Religion maketh good the place. As the traueller
in a long voyage, when hee looſeth the Northerne,
rayſeth the Southerne pole. To beleeue paſſion
aboue reaſon, were to ſubiect iudgement to affection;
and to incline to reaſon rather then religion,
were to preferre nature before God, ſuppoſition before
fayth, humanity before Diuinity.
            Certaynty of adherence doth as farre ſurpaſſe the
certainty of euidence, as faith doth ſence, or Gods
meanes mans intelligence: hence it is that ſo many
are deiected, not becauſe their troubles are ſo great,
but becauſe their faith is ſo little. Although Peter
might iuſtly tremble when he felt himſelfe ſinking (if
we looke no further) yet is he as iuſtly termed one of
little fayth, ſithence Chriſt was by to helpe him. So
as the Prophets counſell in my Text (mee thinks) rather
ſheweth the firre trees cauſe, then the firre trees
practiſe, which alwayes goeth betwixt thoſe two extremes,
aſtoicall ſtupidity not capable of ſorrow, and
deſperate infidelity vncapable of comfort, alwayes
confident in Gods prouidence, howſoeuer vſually
weeping out of one of theſe fowre occaſions: eyther
for contrition, compaſſion, deuotion, or oppreſſion:
and euery Saint is another Auguſtine,
               Aug c
                     •••…
                   12. 
               filius lachrymarum,
a childe of teares; heere is the difference, he
was ſo for his conuerſion; they (and hee afterward) in
conuerſation. For the firſt,

                Repentance is a kinde of reuenge a ſinner taketh againſt
himſelfe,Aug de ver
                     •
                  d &amp; ſal. p
                     •
                  n
                     ••
                  . cap. 8. 
               puniens in ſ
                     •
                  quod dolet commiſiſſe, puniſhing
with griefe what hee committed with folly.
And therefore the Father deriueth poenitere quaſi
poenam tenere:
               Io
                     •
                  d ca▪ 
                  
                     •
                  2. 
               vt ſemper puniat vlciſcendo quod commiſit
peccando: for euery ſeuerall ſinne yelling out a
ſeuerall ſorrow.
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   ſent. As loud as our ſinnes haue beene, ſo
loud ſhould be our cries; deepe wounds muſt haue
long and carefull cures. Poenitentia crimine minor non
ſit:
               Cyprian. ſer. de lapſis. betwixt foule crimes and ſuperficiall mourning
there is no due proportion. Dauid could do no leſſe
then water his couch with the teares of his complaint,
and make them his bread day and night, conſidering
his tranſgreſſions.Anſelm. de ſi militudine, cap 102. For hee muſt of neceſſity
haue ſorrow for them that expecteth pardon of them;
reioycing that he can ſorrow, and ſorrowing if he repents
that ſorrow,A
                     •
                  g vbi ſupra cap. 13. weeping becauſe he cannot weep,
and that much more becauſe he can weepe no more.
And all this not impatienter habitus, ſed deſiderio ſuſceptus:
not impoſed by neceſſity, but aſſumed by deſire,
as knowing that repentance is the ſuper ſedeas
that diſchargeth ſinne, making God to bee mercifull,
angels to be ioyfull, man to be acceptable; an heauenly
gift, an admirable vertue, ouerruling the rigour of
Gods iuſtice and the force of Law: whoſe validity
conſiſteth mente non tempore, not in length of time,
but in true ſincerity. Euen at the laſt gaſpe, cum iam
anima feſti
                     •
                  et ad exitum,
               Cyprian. de coena Domini. when the ſoule laboureth
for paſſage, and almoſt ceaſeth to informe the body;
the eares of the Lord are open to the cries of his
people; as no ſinne ſo great but may be pardoned, ſo
no time heere ſo late but may be accepted. Neyther

the faults greatneſſe,Idem ibidem. the liues wickedneſſe, the houres
ſhortneſſe, if there be true contrition, true conuerſion,
exclude from pardon. Et ideo vlulat abies: and therfore
in the firſt kind Gods ſeruant mourneth.
            Nor is he weeping for himſelfe alone, but lendeth 
a groane for anothers miſery: of all paſſions compaſſion
is the beſt, becauſe it hath a fellow feeling of a
brothers griefe; eyther by a ſecret ſympathy, participating
with his loſſe (for miſericordia dicitur quaſi
miſerum cor habens, quia alterius miſeriam quaſi ſuam
reputat:
               Aug 
                     •
                   de 
                     〈◊〉
                   cap. 5. mercy hath her denomination from participation)
or fearing that in himſelfe which hee ſeeth
in others. As the good old Father that hearing of
his friends ſinne,Gerſin. ſerm. pro hum
                     •
                  l. cried out, ille heri ego bodie, hee yeſterday
and I to day. Particular accidents (much
more publike ruines) will wring pitty from any but a
Nero that could ſit and ſing at Romes burning: it being
held a ſhame to an Athenian (much more to a
Chriſtian) neuer to haue beene in the Academic of
Philoſophers, nor in the temple of mercy.
            It is an obſeruation that the doores of the Tabernacle
which is called the holy of holyeſt,Bellarm. lib. 3. de bonis operibus in particulari. cap. 4. was of Oliue,
the hieroglyphicke of mercy; but the gates of
hell,1. Kin. 6. 21. of braſſe and iron, the ſignes of hard hearts, and
inſtruments of deſtruction:Pſ. 107. 10. to ſhew that the way to
heauen was by pitty, and to hell by inhumanity.
And therefore that act of Licinius the tyrant
was ſtrange:Euſeb. de vita Con. lib. 1. cap. 47 to forbid mercy to Chriſtians vpon pain
of the ſame calamity to bee inflicted vpon them that
ſhould dare to ſhew it, as was in thoſe happy wretches
that were to receiue it. Miſerable man that hee
was; as if he could hinder Gods Saints from ſuffering

with them, that dayly ſuffer in them. Malice armed
with power may hinder that we cannot bee (as Iob
ſaid he was) eyes to the blinde,Iob. 29. 15. and feet to the lame:
which is the mercy of conſolation. Yet can it not
hinder the teares and prayers of Samuel for Saul, and
Moſes for the people,
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   Bleſſ. ſer. 53. which is the mercy of interceſſion.
In a word, they will (maugre all oppoſition)
reioyce with them that reioyce, and weepe with
them that weepe,Rom 12 
                     •
                  1. being of like affection one towards
another: and ſic vlulat abies. Thus the firre tree
mourneth.
            
                Nor thus only: for the deſire of the ſoule is neuer
ſatisfied, vntill it commeth to the end it aymeth at; a
maine argument for the reſurrection (ſay the Schoolmen)
which can neuer be vntill Chriſts ſecond comming,
that the dead body by the reioyning of the
bleſſed ſoule be reinformed.Aquin
                     •…
                  . 4. contra gent. cap. 81. So Saints in the Church
militant, vpon conſideration of the future perfection
and the preſent vanity, in deſpite of nature, grone vntill
they be diſſolued, and the number of Gods elect
may be haſtened. It is onely ignorance that maketh
vs dote vpon earth, and diſſolutio continui that is ſo
troubleſome,Hieronymus in vita eius, lib. 3. epiſt. fayth and reaſon ſtriue againſt it. Egredere
anima mea quid dubitas, ſeptuaginta prope annis
ſeruîſti Deo, &amp; iam mori times? ſayd old Hilarion.
Goe out my ſoule why doubteſt thou, ſeuenty yeeres
almoſt haſt thou ſerued God, and feareſt thou now to
die in the vpſhot? And Platoes ſcholers out of iudgement
(as they thought) offered themſelues violence
ſo to compaſſe immortality, which was all one to deſire
to come to the end of the race and to run a courſe
quite contrary. But the mortified members of Chriſt

that tarry the Lords leyſure, do ioyne with the creatures,
that groane and trauell in payne vnto this preſent,
wayting when the ſonne of God ſhall be reuealed;Rom. 3.
and the Saints in heauen pray continually for
haſtning that number, whileſt the ſpirit it ſelfe maketh
it a requeſt with ſighes that cannot be expreſſed.
The bride too crieth,Apoc come Lord Ieſu, come quickly.
There is recorded in holy Writ a threefold longing
of the faythfull, firſt to dwell continually (although
but as a doorekeeper) in the houſe of the Lord:P
                     •••…
                  . ſecondly
to be deliuered from the body of ſin.Ro. 7. Laſtly
to be diſſolued and to bee with Chriſt.Philip. 1▪
                Howſoeuer
the parting of ſoule and body is harſh to nature, yet
future happineſſe (as one that drinketh a bitter potion
to procure his health) biddeth preſent ſorrow welcome.
A wiſe man cheerefully holdeth out his arme,
willing the Chyrurgion lance and ſpare no
                  •
               ; when
that way and no other,Cyprian de immortalitate. the cure is certayne. Eius eſt
mortem timere, &amp;c. Hee ſhould onely tremble at the
name of death that will not goe to Chriſt, and he only
be vnwilling to go to him that deſpayreth of reigning
with him; for the whole life of a good Chriſtian
is nothing elſe but a continued deſire of diſſolution:
My ſoule thirſteth for God, when ſhall I come and
appeare before the preſence of God?Pſ. 42. ſayd the Pſalmiſt.
Chriſt is my life and death aduantage,Phil. 1. ſaith the
Apoſtle. Then what haue we to doe with this light,
for whom a light neuer eclipſed with any darkneſſe
is in reuerſion?De laude martyrij. ſayd S. Cyprian. And that of Ignatius
going to martyrdome, is a ſpeech moſt excellent.
Being exerciſed with iniuries (ſayd hee) I am made
wiſe (though not iuſtified by them;) O how I wiſh

for your wilde beaſts,Fuſeb. lib. 3. eccleſ. hiſt. c. 33. how I would flatter them to
deuour me,Platina in vita Anacien 1. and if they will not, I will compell them▪
Pardon me, I know what is good; now I begin to be
Chriſts diſciple, I regard neyther things viſible nor
inuiſible, neither fire nor croſſe: let the fury of beaſts,
the breaking of bones, the conuulſion of members,
the deſtruction of the whole body, and all the torments
that Satan himſelfe can impoſe, ruſh vpon me,
modo Ieſum Chriſtum acquiram: ſo I may gayne my
Sauiour. A quiet death is the vſuall ſymptome of an
honeſt life: humane fraylty euen then ſtriuing to accord
with Gods iuſt pleaſure. But hee is a man after
Gods heart that liueth in a kinde of payne, and d
                  •
               eth
with deſire and comfort, as one that ſeeth worldly
vanity, knoweth the future reward, and thirſteth for
the accompliſhment, as the Hart doeth after the riuers
of water: life being to him as irkeſome as death
to others: ſuch a one non patienter moritu
                     •
                  , ſed patienter
viuit, delectabiliter moritus, ſayd S. Auguſtine
ſpeaking of S. Pauls deſire of diſſolution. Should the
hand of diuine bounty conferre vpon me all the contentments
the world ſo aſpireth to, did the ſpheres
ioyne with the elements to make me happy, yet there
is nothing in the earth that I deſire but him, nor any
thing in the whole heauens that I deſire in compariſon
of him, omnino me non ſatiaret Deus, niſi promitteret
ſemetipſum Deum: God himſelfe could not ſatisfie
my ambition, except he gaue himſelfe vnto mee▪.
Beauty is not ague proofe, wealth will leaue mee, or
I muſt leaue it, honor muſt borrow poore mens eies
to ſee its excellency. Earth, ſea and ayre are but creatures;
and ſo by conſequence both vayne and corruptible.

But God is 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                and 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , that is, and was, and is
to come; in whoſe preſence is ioy for euermore. It
is no maruell then ſi ululet abies, if this be reckoned
among the firre trees mournings.
            But theſe three are voluntarily aſſumed; there is 
a fourth (the more both ſhame and pitty) by neceſſity
impoſed, in which the reaſonable man is more
brutiſh then the vnreaſonable beaſt. O the deteſtable
cruelty of humane malice! (ſaith S. Cyprian ſpeaking
of Elias ſed by Rauens, and Daniel ſpared by Lions)
ferae parcunt, aues paſcunt, &amp; homines inſidiantur
&amp; ſaeuiunt: fowles of the aire they bring meat, beaſts
of the field they bring comfort, whileſt man againſt
man doth rage and tyranniſe: Now, vertue it ſelfe
that reioyceth in the obiect, yet findeth trouble in
the act; no patience ſo ſtrong but it is ſenſible, nor
ſanctification ſo perfect as to extirpate nature. When
the glorified Saynts in heauen do crie,Reuel. 6. 10. 
               vſquequo Domine
&amp;c. How long Lord faythfull and true, doeſt
not thou iudge and auenge our bloud on them that
dwell on the earth? and Abels murder ſpeaketh loud
a brothers iniury. No maruell then if heere on earth,
good mens wrongs, cauſe good mens howlings: the
one being ſo frequent, the other cannot be altogether
vnuſuall. As is the head, ſuch are the members:
Heere is the difference, the children of the bridechamber
did not mourne whileſt the bridegroome
himſelfe was with them; malice was ioyned with policy,
ayming by the death of the Generall to disband
the Army; as long as Chriſt liued, wee reade of no
perſecution againſt his Diſciples, but he once remooued
Stephen is ſtoned, Peter crucified, Paul beheaded.

Some burned, ſome ſtrangled, ſome broyled, ſome
brayned;Hieronym. cont. Iouin. lib. 2. all (but only S. Iohn) murdered. And euer
ſince that is too true, amara eſt veritas, &amp; qui eam
praedicat repletur amaritudine: bitter is the truth, and
he that preacheth it is filled full of bitterneſſe. The
woes of Saynts hauing no eaſe but cuſtome; and that
paſſage of S. Bernard is good:Ser. in Cant 47. the ſpouſe louingly
(ſayth hee) inuiteth the beloued to her bed; and hee
her againe to armes and trouble: illâ monſtrante lectulum,
ille vocat ad campum, ad exercitium: hence
it is that in her garden doe grow Roſes as well as Lilies,
becauſe the Church is both operibus candida &amp;
cruore purpurea:
               Cypr. ep. 9. hauing this vnſeparable lot to doe
good and ſuffer euill.Ioh. 20. 21. As my Father ſent mee, ſo ſend
I you, ſayth our Sauiour to his Diſciples. That is, as
Bellarmine doth well expound the place:Lib. 3. de poenit. cap. 18. 1. To binde
and looſe. 2. To reconcile God and man. 3. To beare
my croſſe and ſuffer afflictions. Indeed why ſhould
we looke for loue when our head found hatred? If
the world hate you, it hated mee before you: (as
himſelfe ſpeaketh.) Moſt comfortable is that of S.
Auguſtine:
               Ep. 49. 
               In ipſum Chriſtum non crederemus, ſi  fides
Chriſtiana cachinnum metueret Paganorum: that
man will neuer be Chriſtian, that can be diſmayd by
the ſcoffes of a Pagan. And it is as vſuall to ſee vntouched
conſciences, and vntouched fortunes to
dwell together, as for men that know no ſorrow, to
know no God. It is oppoſition that giues the triall,
and cauſeth argent ſeem bright in a ſable field, as the
fun pleaſeth breaking from a cloud. It is the portion
and vertue of goodneſſe, to ſuffer and ſhine in great
extremities. Et hïc vlulat abies. Whether the fall of

Cedars will prooue another cauſe, is my third part
and queſtion.
            Of all the ſorrowes that the firre tree hath,
                  
                     •
                  . Quare, quia cecidit Cedrus. the fall
of Cedars is the leaſt (if any.) It may ſeeme enuie
that they inioy heauen, or ſelfe-loue that wee enioy
not them, when wee are ſo tranſported to the degree
of howling for ſuch as know no ſorrow. Doeſt thou
lament the body from which a ſoule is parted (ſayth
Auguſtine:) rather deplore the ſoule from which
God is ſeparated. A Saint (you ſay) is fallen. It is
impoſſible, Si iustus quomodo cadit, ſi cadat quomodo
iuſtus? If ſo how fell hee, if he fell how ſo? Veſpaſian
ſayd of himſelfe, that he was not a dying, but a diefying.
And Bleſſenſis of a friend, abijt non obijt, receſsit
non deceſsit:
               Ep. 27. heeis but gone aſide a while, but
not departed. The garment that was taken from Ioſeph,
was but a falſe argument of his death or loſſe:
for he then not only liued, but gouerned Egypt. Nor
doth the ſenceleſſe body prooue any thing more,
then that the ſoule hath left that ſinfull priſon, and is
fled to heauen, which whoſo doth ſooneſt is happieſt:
as the traueller that hath taken vp a good lodging,Greg. Nazian▪ oratione de funere Patris.
feeleth not the trouble of him that is comming
to him in the rayne and dirt. As in Paradice, there
was a liberty of life or death, ſo in the world a neceſſity
of death, not life. But in heauen and hell a neceſſity
of life that can neuer be extinguiſhed. For in one,
death would bring eaſe which cannot be granted; in
the other, loſſe which cannot be imagined. The corolary
is this: Saynts are not to bee lamented as loſt,
but beloued as abſent. If bryers or brambles fall,
weepe for them: they muſt bee burned. If Cedars,

they were planted to be tranſplanted from the hill of
Libanon to the Sanctuary of God. Dauid had iuſt
cauſe to exclayme: O my ſonne Abſalom, my ſonne,
my ſonne Abſalom: would God I had died for thee,
O Abſalom,
               
                  
                     •
                  . Sam. 1
                     •
                  . 33. my ſonne, my ſonne. Hee was both a
priuate ſinner and an open traytor. But Chriſts was,
O daughters of Ieruſalem, weepe not for mee, but
weepe for your ſelues, and for your children. It was
good for the Church that Paul ſhould abide in the
fleſh,Luk. 23. 28. but better for him to be diſſolued and bee with
Chriſt. What ingratitude were it to repine at our
friends promotion, and for our pleaſure to debarre
his preferment? when there is more then hope, that
wee ſhall meet agayne with vnſpeakeable ioy and
comfort. Iacob, I ſuppoſe, was more refreſhed at the
newes of Ioſephs life and greatneſſe, then deiected
with the ſorrow of his conceyued loſſe. Non moeremus
quòd tales amiſimus, ſed gratias agimus quòd
habuimus, immo quòd habemus: We doe not lament
thoſe we haue loſt,Ep. 27. but giue thankes becauſe wee had
them,Ep. 2. nay ſtill haue them, ſayth S. Hierome. And in
another place, bewayle your dead, but ſuch as hell
receiueth, not ſuch as angels doe accompany to heauen,
and Chriſt meeteth: and there bringeth in God
himſelfe thus ſpeaking: Thou denyeſt thy ſelfe meat,
not out of a deſire of faſting, but of ſorrow. Non amo
frugalitatem iſtam: I like not this frugality: your
faſts are both aduerſaries to mee and to your friends.
Nullam animam recipio, quae me nolente ſeparatur à
corpore: I receyue no ſoule, but ſuch as with my
will is ſeuered from the body. But alaſſe, it is a Cedar,
the hieroglyphicke of greatneſſe, aſwell as goodneſſe,

and the cutting downe of ſuch make thoſe deep
impreſſions both of griefe and wonder. Vanity of
vanities! The heathen themſelues that implored as
many dieties, as they conceiued chimaeraes in their
fancies, yet were neuer knowne to erect an Altar to
death, becauſe that was euer held implacable.Gen. 25. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . What
is my birth right ſeeing I am almoſt dead? ſayd Eſau.
What profit is there in my blood, when I goe down
into the pit? ſayd Dauid. Philoſophers make ſport
with great Alexander, (as hares may play with the
beards of dead Lions) being intombed in a poore
vrne, whoſe ambition before the whole world ſufficed
not. And Nature maketh no other difference,
then doth the potter, that of the ſame clay maketh
veſſels of honour and of diſhonour; the one more
poliſhed but as brittle as the other. Or the Maſon
that from the ſame quarry diggeth ſtones both for
the pauement and for the Altar; although wee trample
the one and kneele to the other. The ſame wood
may make ſome goodly image, and a plough or fewell:
and the figure is the ſame, that ſtands for one
and for one thouſand, they being meere ciphers, nothing
in themſelues that alter the accompt. The
Prince is as corruptible as the pooreſt beggar; lay aſide
dying and dreſſing, painting and pruning, and
all are but earth, the wormes meat, and graues inheritance.
Diadema non fanat caput, nec annulus digitum:
The crowne cannot helpe the headache,Paniga. nor the
ring the finger. What then is the Prophets meaning
to aduiſe this ſadneſſe? It muſt be truth vnqueſtionable
that ſuch men vtter. All the Scripture being credibilis
vt credibilis, to bee beleeued without a reaſon.
            
               
Holy men inſpired did but pen what God did dictate.
It is moſt true and for all the premiſſes there is
great cauſe of howling, not becauſe the Cedars fall,
was the Cedars harme, but the whole mountaynes
both loſſe and danger, like the comet portending ruine
to Ieruſalem. A good man is a common good,
that brings not bleſſing for himſelfe alone, but for all
about him. Themiſtocles ſetting his houſe to ſale prized
it much deerer then ordinary, propter bonum vicinum,
becauſe ſeated by a good neighbour: and
Chriſtians alwayes accompted their peace more ſure
by the life of Saynts, as knowing that the world it
ſelfe muſt fayle when the elect are finiſhed. Sodome
muſt neceſſarily periſh when Lot is out of it. Tenne
righteous could haue guarded it, not againſt the powers
of men and earth only, but of heauen and angels
alſo. Whileſt Iacob ſerued Laban, he and his proſpered;
once parted, the one grew rich and the other
poore. And his ſonne Ioſeph was not Putaphars only,
but all Egypts bleſſing. The righteous like Moſes
ſtand in the gappe, and hold the Almighties hands
from ſtriking: the very chariots of Iſrael and horſemen
of the ſame. Iudges on earth cut off offenders,
to ſecure the innocent, holding it a cruell mercy to
ſpare one to manies ruine: but God in heauen cuts off
his children for the wickeds ſorer puniſhment; that
their defences being ſurpriſed, hee might haue none
to giue ſtoppage to his intended vengeance. Troy
(they ſay) was impregnable whileſt they had the Palladium,
or Hector liued. But it may bee better auerred
that families, cities, kingdomes (for one is the modell
of the other) are more proſperous, whileſt they inioy

the godly. For it is preſuppoſed that God remoueth
them but from the anger to come. And therefore no
maruell if Dauid cryeth,Pſ. 12. 1
                     •
                  . 
               Salvum me fac, Domine:
Helpe or ſaue me, O Lord. Giuing ſuch a pregnant
proofe of imminent danger, quia defecit ſanctus, there
is not one godly man left, the faythfull are miniſhed
from the children of men. The Phyſitian ſometimes
letteth the arme blood to cure and correct the head;
and God did as much in the three dayes peſtilence
ſent to the people for Dauids numbring them: Hee
crying,2. Sam. 24. 27. I haue ſinned, yea I haue done wickedly, but
theſe ſheepe what haue they done? But when the
head is wounded, all the members are likewiſe ſmitten
with it, (as the ſheepe are ſcattered when there is no
ſhepheard) the eyes grow dimme, the armes weake,
the tongue doeth falter and the legges doe tremble.
If the buſhes bee ſtubbed vp, the Cedars proſper
more, and flouriſh better; but if the Cedars fall, eyther
the ſhrubs are beaten downe with the weight, or
ſtanding are likely to bee blaſted by the ſtormes and
tempeſts for want of ſhelter. I need not trouble you
with further application, ſince hee that runnes may
read the meaning.
            I haue beene tedious in a theme that relliſheth not,
neuertheleſſe I muſt proceed without apology or crauing
pardon: loue and ſorrow admit no ceremony.
And you, I know, will not be weary to heare me deſcending
to particulars, which more affect then do all
generall, eyther notions or inſtructions, but ſometimes
accompany me with ſighes (if not teares) and
all the way with ſad attention, whileſt I relate with
griefe how our Cedar is fallen.
            
               
A ſubiect in which a iuſt Orator might incurre the
imputation of flattery, with ſtrangers, did they not in
charity and iudgement remember, that God is his
ſpectator and angels auditors. But to men acquaynted
with the perſon and her vertues, all will fall ſhort that
one man can ſpeake; and euery one may affoord
ſome thing worthy memory omitted by the Preacher.
Nazianzene commending Athanaſius ſayd,Oratione in laudem Athanaſ
                     •
                   j. that
commending him he ſhould commend vertue. Idem
enim eſt illum dicere, quod virtutem laudibus efferre:
I might well applie it, yet neyther ſow pillowes vnder
the elbowes of the liuing, or ſhoulders of the dead.
She was the Lady Frances Clifton, (well were it for
moſt heere could I ſpeake it in the preſent tenſe) a Lady
of thoſe endowments as might bid detraction it
ſelfe, Belch her poyſon: ſhe would ſo liue (as Socrates
once anſwered a backbiter) that none ſhould credit it.
The cupping glaſſe which draweth none but impure
bloud, and the flie that lighteth vpon nothing but
vlcers, this heere would famiſh, that be vſeleſſe. Hee
that ſhould dare to ſnuffe this taper, would but defile
his owne fingers and make her light the cleerer; as
the waters (ſayth Stella) that by ouerflowing▪ their
bounds, make the bankes cleane and themſelues
dirty.
            A flouriſhing branch ſhe was, of a ſtocke as honorable,
as ancient; and as it to her, ſo ſhe to it an ornament:
knowing that vertue with much adoe might
begin a houſe, but vice with little labour eaſily end it▪
that Cham and Eſau had noble parents, &amp; themſelues
were baſe: that there is no greater argument of pouerty,
then to boaſt anothers worth or vertue. And

therefore ſtroue to be ſide nobilis, quae omnibus ornatibus
ornamento eſt: noble in faith, which to all honors
is an ornament. Who knoweth not that great births
haue the ſtrongeſt ties to chayne them to thoſe duties,
by which the anceſtor roſe or flouriſhed? And
the greateſt liberty for to loſe themſelues in courſes
that are both irregular and vnlawfull, which begets
a ſoloeciſme in great houſes: that is, honoris titulum
ſine homine: much ſtile, and little man. Shee therefore
knowing both the rocks and channell, ſayled in
the one and waued the other; there being not any
noble vertue befitting her blood and ſex, that ſhe did
not in high meaſure practiſe; as if ſhe had beene ambitious
to be verè nobilis, that is, virtute prae alijs notabilis,
as ſome deriue the word, exceeding others as
much in the gifts of minde, as fortune. Nor is it maruell
ſhe ſhould bee ſcarlet in the cloth that was dyed
ſo in the wooll, ſucking Religion with her milke, the
excellency of her nature being perfected by education.
It were very improbable ſhee ſhould degenerate,
hauing ſuch a ſiſter to accompany, and ſuch a mother
to lead the wayes of godlineſſe, both demonſtrating
in life and death, how ſhe following ſhould learne of
them to liue and die. So as it were no arrogant chalenge
to bid Rome (which maketh traytors Saints,
and ſtrawes miracles) to ſet from foorth their legend,
ſuch a parent, with ſuch a payre of ſiſter Saints. Sure
I am, many a ſuperſtitious knee hath beene bowed to
inferior worthies.
            From the time of her marriage to her death, few
can giue more ample teſtimony then my ſelfe; for
from that time I had good cauſe to know and to obſerue,

and cannot but with comfort remember the
happy both fruit and incouragement of my weake indeuours,
as a poore labourer that lookes with ioy vpon
ſome goodly pile of building, becauſe hee can ſay,
he brought ſomething to it, although but ſtone or
morter.
            Shee was a woman full of noble curteſies, eyther
when ſhee did viſit others, or her ſelfe were viſited.
One that could ſtoope low by the rules of Religion,
and vet knew her diſtance in the truth of reaſon; ſo
ſhe had alwaies the rich mens applauſe, and the poore
mans praiers: with the one ſhe conuerſed not but with
an honourable familiarity; nor with the other but
with a charitable reliefe. Hee muſt haue beene of an
euill life ſhe would not haue deigned to ſpeake to, and
of an euill diſpoſition that would not be content with
her anſwers. Iudicious in all diſcourſe beyond the degree
of her ſex, yet pleaſant to; interlacing mirth
with earneſt, both in ſuch a poſture as did well become
her, and ſuch a manner as was beyond exception:
her preſence would not grace either the Cynicks
rudeneſſe, or the wantons boldneſſe. Well ſeene in
Hiſtory and other humane knowledge; but ſo as her
mayne ayme was at Religion and to be skilfull in the
Law of God. For that father that chaſteneth euery
childe that he receyueth, had giuen her a long infirmity,
bred with her from her childhood, bringing as
much payne to her, as ſhame to the Phyſitians. And
this though the bodies hurt, yet the ſoules phyſicke:
filling thoſe empty parts, that appeared at her diſſection
with inuiſible graces,M. Foelix. in Octav. that there might bee no vacuity.
Calamitas ſaepius diſciplina virtutis eſt: Her

calamity directed her virtue. So mortifying all her
affections as ſhe valued not the world, relyed not vpon
arte, truſted not her ſtrength, nor euer was vnprepared
to entertayne death ſo long expected. I haue
diuers times heard her ſay, that ſhe neuer went to her
bed but as to her graue; nor euer ſaw that morning,
that ſhe did thinke ſhe ſhould liue to ſee the euening.
Thus what ſome make eaſie with patience, ſhe made
eaſie with preparation and prouidence; and Quicquid
expectatum eſt diù, leuius accidit: what ſo is foreſeene
before it happeneth, falleth lightly when it
commeth, when hee that is ſurprized is halfe beaten
before a blow bee giuen. Omnia nouitate grauiora:
All things ſeeming more greeuous as they are more
ſudden. She, if any, might truly take vp that of the
Apoſtle,1. Cor. 15. 
                     ••
                  . I die dayly, hauing ſo many and ſo bitter
fits, as all attendants as well as her ſelfe thought them
mortall; yet borne with that vndanted reſolution, as
might well demonſtrate how ſhe had learned Chriſt;
her tongue neuer venting the leaſt word of murmur
or repining, but continually vttering heauenly 
                  •
               inculations
to God, and comfortable aſſurances to thoſe
about her. Nor were her many deliuerances paſſed
ouer in ſilence, as if ſhee would receyue the fruit
and not looke to the tree, that dropped it to her,
for God had alwayes due praiſes, and the poore large
almes and bounty. One time (among many others)
was moſt remarkeable: hauing conceyued and a fit
taking her when ſhe was quicke with childe, the extremity
was ſuch, as within her ſhee felt no motion,
and but ſmall ſigne of life eyther of her ſelfe or that
ſhe went with. From which danger when God had

preſerued her, ſhe vowed a vow vnto the Lord, and
performed it truely, that that day ſhould be annually
holy vnto his name, which ſhe ſpent in her priuate
Chamber with faſting, reading, Pſalmes and prayer:
her faſt indeed, but the Poores feaſt, they might well
write that day in red letters, as their greateſt Feſtiuall
So as what ſhe was in euery relation as a daughter,
ſiſter, wife, mother, Ladie, Miſtreſſe, neighbour,
Chriſtian both in life and death, neede not ſeeme
ſtrange, although tranſcendent in each particuler, the
goodneſſe of her nature being ordered by education,
that rectified by grace, grace exerciſed by afflictions,
and they purged out all vanities, and thence ſhe was
as fine gold often tried, fit for her Makers Temple.
            Such a Daughter as would make a Father wiſh to
be aged, to haue the comfort of that reſpect and dutie,
euer attending him with a bended knee, and a
carefull loue, humble obeiſance, and a ioyfull heart,
as if ſhe had receiued a ſecond life by his preſence,
from whoſe bloud the firſt was taken. Such a Siſter,
as if the bloud were ſtill in the old vaines vndiuided.
Such a Wife, as might be an argument againſt a vow,
her ſociety rather perfecting then interrupting deuotion.
She ſeldome parted from her noble Huſband
in any iourney without a ſad heart, and ſometimes
bedewed cheekes in his abſence, in her Cloſet
ſhe praied for him, at the Table remembred him, againſt
his returne was zealouſly carefull nothing
might offend him, the Meſſenger that brought newes
of his comming neuer vnrewarded, and then with
what open heart and armes would ſhee entertaine
him? Such a Mother as moſt dearely loued her tender

Progenie, yet knew full well that all Children
were borne alike, and that vertues onely gaue diſtinction,
and therefore with a carefull eye ſurueyed each
naturall diſpoſition, cutting off with diſcipline the
courſe of humors, not ſuffering thoſe little bodies to
haue ſetled infections, ſeaſoning them in minoritie
with goodneſſe and religion, that in riper yeares it
might be another nature; for inſtructions then inſtilled
enter eaſily, but depart with difficultie. And
theſe Oliue branches produced a great care of domeſticke
affaires, as not ignorant that theſe challenged
prouiſion anſwerable to their births, and prouidence
to be the leader to entertainments: there was not
that weeke in which ſhe exacted not an account of
all expences, deſcending to ſuch trifles as in a houſe
ſo plentifull is ſcarce imaginary; yet did this care leſſen
her bountie, neuer any of her Seruants departed
without gratuity, nor office looked into without reward:
and if ſhe were inforced to complaine, it was
ſo as that the fault might be amended (I haue it from
his mouth that can beſt relate it) but the faulter pardoned.
For a Neighbour though I ſay nothing,
your ſelues can ſpeake it. Neuer was hoſpitality accompanied
with a more cheerefull looke, nor an open
hand with a more open heart.
            Super omnia vultus acceſsêre benigni.
            As if that Conduit had had no Ciſterne, and that abundance
no prouidence. But O you poore, to you
what was ſhe? when was any hungry (if ſhe knew
it) and ſhe did not feed him; thirſty, and ſhe ſent
not drinke; nay, the naked too ſhe ſometimes clothed;
was any ſicke or ſore, this houſe was an Apothecaries

ſhop open to all commers, without mony,
or exchange, how many diſeaſed, how many hurt
haue here beene helped, neither medicines nor cordials
were euer ſpared if want were knowne, or vnknowne
demanded. Were euer thoſe eies ſeene
without pittie, or hands without bountie? ſhe beleeuing
certainly that God bleſſed their ſtore that ſpent
on their brethren, as running ſtreames are fed that
they may continue. The neighbour Townes and Villages
are now as ſad witneſſes that I lie not, as before
ioyfull receptacles of her almes and charitie: and
yet all this without the leaſt cackling of merit, her
left hand ſcarce knew what her right hand did, and
her tongue accuſing her ſelfe for an vnprofitable ſeruant,
euery day promiſed a further reformation; as
if ſhe had not beene good, except ſhe had beene perfect,
which degree in this life may bee aſpired vnto,
but not accompliſhed.
            Then what ſhe was to man you may make ſome
ſcantling, as he that by Hercules his foot gueſſed at
the proportion of his whole body; and you may aſſure
your ſelues her deuotion to God was nothing inferiour.
In which ſhe was neither fooliſhly factious,
nor Popiſhly ſuperſtitious, ſhe did not ſo ingeminate
the firſt Table of the Law, that vnder that gloſſe (as
Hypocrites doe) ſhe might take occaſion to neglect
the ſecond, nor yet ſo conceiued of the ſecond, but as
a rule to be applied according to the lines of the firſt.
In a word, her beleefe and life were each others
counterpane, a true light that did both ardere &amp; lucere,
burne with inward zeale, and ſhine with outward
practiſe. Euery morning about fiue of the

clocke, ſhe had a light and went to her priuate prayers,
lying in her bed. When ſhee was vp and halfe
ready, ſhe called for meat (ſuch was the weakneſſe
of her vitall ſpirits as ſhe could abſtain no longer) and
then oft times ſome read by her: no ſooner dreſſed,
then ſhe and her women went to prayer, from the
chamber to the Chapell to call vpon God with the
whole family, in which ſhe neuer fayled (if ſhe were
able) although ſhee often reſted her weary legges in
ſo ſhort a paſſage. After dinner ſhe was for company,
her booke, or exerciſe, as there was occaſion. Before
Supper againe to Chapel to her God; after Supper
and in her bed ſhe &amp; her women went to praiers.
            Vpon the Lords day in the morning, as before, and
being ready, all the mayd ſeruants were called into
the next roome to pray for the diſpoſing of their
hearts to heare reuerently; and for the Preacher that
he might ſpeake powerfully, that both hee and they
might practiſe truth and godlineſſe. From thence
hither to pray and to attend; Sermon once ended,
if ſhee her ſelfe could not, yet her women went priuately
to giue God thankes for their inſtruction; and
in few words to pray for a bleſſing. After dinner in
her chamber ſhe and her women ſunga Pſalme, read
a Sermon, and againe ſung a Pſalme after it; and then
children and the maydes were catechized. Then hither
againe and ſo as before; and this courſe ſhee ſo
affected, as ſhe gaue the ſame directions to her noble
neece whom ſhee moſt deerely loued, almoſt as her
laſt legacy. A ſoule (ſayth S. Chryſoſtome) guarded
with prayers, is ſtronger then a City with walles and
rampiers. Then how armed ſhee was againſt ſinne

and Sathan is euident to the impartiall hearer.
            The Sacrament of the Lords Supper ſhee highly
prized and receiued often, vnderſtanding well that as
long as we are here capable of augmentation and ſubiect
to diminution of grace, that meanes was as neceſſary
for our ſoules as for our bodies, meat or medicine:
and that ſhe might receiue it worthily, excellent
was her preparation before, and contemplation
after it. But in the act a geſture and poſture ſo humble
and reuerent, that I for my part neuer doubted,
but I deliuered and ſhe receyued Chriſt our Sauiour;
as if vpon her knees ſhee would haue ſayd with learned
Hooker in the determination of the queſtion
which hath coſt ſo many liues,Lib 5. Eccleſ. poli. ſec. 67. O my God thou art
there, O my ſoule thou art happy. The word preached
was her delight and comfort, in hearing wherof
ſhe ordered her body to attend, her vnderſtanding to
intend, and her memory to retayne what ſhould bee
ſpoken, laying vp the words, not as the lazie ſeruant
his talent in a napkin, but as Ioſeph his corne to releeue
in neceſſity. I muſt not omit (for the example
is not vſuall) that the meſſenger was ſo reſpected
with her, for his meſſage, and both for his ſake that
ſent them, as maugre the well knowne contempt of
the world (the vndoubted demonſtration of irreligion,
I had almoſt ſayd Atheiſme) ſhe had a vehement
deſire, if God ſhould ſend her another ſonne to dedicate
him to God and make him a Miniſter; as if ſhee
had read Salvian:
               Lib. 4. de gubernat. dei. 
               Si quis ex nobilibus conuerti ad
Deum coeperit, ſtatim honorem nobilitatis amittit: If
any of the nobility turne to God, they are reputed to
haue loſt the honour of nobility. And it preſently followeth,

               O quantus in Chriſtiano populo honor Chriſti
eſt, vbi Religio ignobilem facit: How little honour
do Chriſtians ſhew their God when the profeſſion of
the Religion maketh the profeſſor to be held ignoble.
Let me adde that no nation vnder heauen of what religion
ſoeuer if they acknowledge a God, doe vndervalue
their Prieſts and orders but only the Reformed
Churches. I pray God it may portend no iudgement.
I haue now breathed her courſe of life, and proceed
to a concluſion, (if I bee tedious you muſt blame her
vertues.) As her life was nothing but a care for death,
ſo her death an entrance to a better life. She hauing
beene a Mary to God, a Martha to the world, a Sara
to her husband, a Lois, an Eunice to her children,
a Lydia to the Diſciples: in a word an elect Lady
borne for the good of many. So as ſhee might well
vtter S. Ambroſe his ſpeech to his people of Millan
which S. Auguſtine ſo much admired: Non ſic vixt
vt me pudeat apud vos diutius viuere, nec mori timeo
quia bonum Dominum habemus: I haue not ſo liued
as that I ſhould be aſhamed to liue longer, nor feare I
to die becauſe wee haue a gracious Lord. Sure it is
that death which was ſo long expected and prepared
for, could neither be ſuddaine nor grieuous when it
happened. About a moneth before her childebirth
ſhe had a dreame which ſomething troubled her,
and ſent for me (a bad interpreter) if I could to tell
the meaning. Her body (ſhe thought) was paſt all
cure, her vitall ſpirits ſpent, ſhe had taken her leaue
of the world and reconciled her ſelfe to God, and
was euen giuing vp the ghoſt into the hands of her
redeemer, and ſo awaked. I told her, dreamed came

either from the diſpoſition of the body, or the ſollicitude
of the minde, and that queſtionleſſe her meditations
were much vpon mortalitie, and that ſome of
thoſe broken ſpecies remained in the fancie vndiſcourſed,
and the ſoule which cannot bee idle, did
worke vpon them.
            She replied in few words to this effect. I doe, or
ſhould daily think to die, &amp; ſure I am, not I only, but
all ſhould doe ſo, and occaſion being offered of ſome
thing to be done a moneth after by, that time, ſaid ſhe,
ſhall I be in my graue. And indeed within three or
foure daies of her account ſhe was ſo, (as I compute
the time) as if God (rather then nature) had revealed
it to her. After her deliuery, ſucceeding a painfull
labour, it was well hoped ſhe had at once parted
with her Childe and danger, and that her many
faintings were ſignes of a weake (but not a dying)
body. Lord, how a little glimpes of comfort giueth
light to deſire and loue, and maketh men thinke they
ſhe when they doe but dreame, hope being the firſt
thing that taketh vs, and the laſt that leaueth vs: but
ſhe that had often ſeene the face of death, and had as
often wreſtled with his forces, ſeldome comming off
without great paine and hazard found him now manifeſtly
preuailing, and cryed out, farewell vaine
earth, I embrace thee Heauen. Then calling for her
noble Husband, tooke her leaue of him, and prayed
for him, bleſſed her Children, and ſ
                  ••
               tching her little
Sonne into her dying armes, deſired God to make
him true to him, and iuſt to man, and at other times
(although not then) that he might reſemble his great
Grandfather in all noble vertues, for he (ſaid ſhe)

was likewiſe a Cliffords Sonne, then caſting her eyes
vpon all together, with a zealous exclamation beſought
God for them, that the ſeedes of his grace
might be ſo ſowen within their hearts, that they
might bud and bloſſome, and bring forth fruit, and
become in time broad ſhades for the poore afflicted
members of Chriſt to ſit vnder and receiue comfort.
In the morning before ſhe died, ſhe had conuulſion
and the ſignes of death: and I comming to her, although
ſhe had not ſlept foure or fiue nights before,
(an infirmity able to haue weakned the ſtrongeſt
braine) yet preſently, without the leaſt diſtemper, diſtraction
or ſhortneſſe of breath, (her old diſeaſe) ſhe
recalled all her vitall ſpirits, to doe that laſt office,
comfortably and confidently made the profeſſion of
her faith, auowing that there was no name either in
Heauen or in Earth that ſhe hoped to be ſaued by,
but that of Ieſus Chriſt the righteous. She was not
then to learne either the principles or practice of Religion,
ſo that I ſtood rather to behold the vſe, then
teach the theory. From that wee went to prayers,
ſhe repeating with wonderfull feruency the words
after me, vntill perceiuing her weakneſſe, I beſought
her to ſpare her decayed ſpirits, telling her that both
ſhee and wee might receiue as much comfort by
her ſilent aſſiſtance in the length and vocall aſſent
in the concluſion. When all was done that could
be required of a Chriſtian in that extremity, I boldly
proceeded to the office of my Miniſtry, and pronounced
her abſolution, and am very confident that
it was olaue non errante, with a Key that erred not,
and that God did ratifie in heauen, what I his vnworthy

Miniſter declared on earth: ſhe receiuing
it as comfortably as I deliuered it faithfully. After
this ſhe ſeemed to ſleepe, and a great care was had
for feare of interruption, and ſo continued vntill the
afternoone, when her ſpeech left her, and the meſſengers
of death againe appeared: And we (as was our
duty) renued our prayers, which for a time ſhe anſwered
with ſignes vntill her memory as well as her
tongue did faile her. Nor did we then giue ouer, as
knowing well with S. Auguſtine, that God differreth
ſometimes to grant, to teach vs to beg, and ſo promiſeth
to beginners, as that he will giue to none but perſeuerers.
My ſelfe and another Miniſter (that came
in that perplexity) continually ſolliciting his Diuine
Maieſty for mercy, vntill in the middeſt of one of my
prayers, in which I deſired him to giue his Angels
charge ouer her, in that her agonie againſt ſinne and
Sathan, ſhe departed; going her ſelfe to vndoubted
ioy, and leauing vs to vnfayned ſorrow. And thus
(O firre trees) our Cedar is fallen; If ſuch a fall bee
not an exaltation rather, for it ſhall bee my ambition
to liue ſo, that I may die ſo. And now ſhe lieth low, by
the ſide of that other excellent Lady her predeceſſor;
two ſuch parcels of earth, as the earth that couereth
them may ſeeme proud of. What remayneth but a
generall ſorrow, not for her, but for our ſelues; in
which each order may beare a part of mourning: the
firre trees becauſe all the mighty are ſpoyled (as it followeth
the words of my text) and the oakes of Baſhan
to, for their defenced forreſt is come down. I ſhall
not need to bid the ſhepheards howle, for the next
verſe ſayth, that their voyce is already heard (and

good reaſon) for their glory is deſtroyed: nor the Lions
whelps, their roaring is preſuppoſed, becauſe the
pride of Iordan is deſtroyed. Queſtionleſſe, all that
but remember that the righteous are taken away
from the anger to come, howſoeuer they haue no
part in our priuate loſſe, may ioyne themſelues in our
publicke feare, knowing that the death of Saints trencheth
to further danger. God for his infinite mercy
grant grace in our liues, pardon at our deaths,
and after both, the fruition of his
bleſſed viſion. Amen.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            In obitum praematurum praeclariſsimae
Heroinae D. Franciſcae Clifton, quae obijt
in pace paulò poſt puerperium.
            
               Ad turgeſcentem tumuli molem.
               
                  Qu. CVrita turgeſcis moles? vnúmne cadauer,
               Aut multa hâc ſacrâ contumulantur humo.
               
                  Reſ. Hic ſita nobilitas &amp; quicquid nobile, virtus,
               Ingenium, probitas &amp; pietatis amor.
               Hic ſita faeminci ſexus laus, deliciúm
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  :
               Hïc Franciſca ſita eſt: deſine muſa, ſat eſt.
            
            
               Ad patrem de quinâ tantùm defunctae
matris prole.
               QVin
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   tibi caſti chariſsima pignora lecti
               Donauit coniux nobilis, at
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   obijt.
               Non auxit numerum, ſed ſenſibus omnibus vnum
               Ex aequo tribuit, diſce quid hic numerus.
               Vt videas, tangas, guſtes at
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   oſcula figens
               Coniugis olfacias dulcia dona tuae.
               At
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   etiam aſcultes, cùm blando murmure pappant;
               Tu nobis mater quin
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   patér
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ſimul.
               
                  Per Sam. Simſon.
               
            
         
         
            
            Pietati, virtuti, honori &amp; foelici memoriae
illuſtriſsimae D. D. Franciſcae Clifton
Ampliſſ. Comitis Cumberlandiae chariſſimae
filiae, atque honoratiſsimi viri D.
Geruaſij Clifton Militis &amp; Baronetti coniugis
ſpectatiſſ.
            PEtrarum in clivis gaudent habitare columbae,
            Hoc eſt quod Chriſti ſponſa columba cluit.
            Chriſtus enim petra eſt, Chriſti
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                in vulnere clivus,
            Geſtit vbi ſolum figere ſponſa pedem.
            O te foelicem idcirco Franſciſca Columbam,
            Quae tota in cliuis vixeris &amp; moreris.
            A cliuo ad clivum mortalis ſponſa volabas,
            Nunc eadem in clivo, caelica ſponſa lates.
            Vt
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                ille in terris ampli tibi portus honoris,
            Hic itidem aeternae porta ſalutis erit.
            
               Io. Crauen.
            
         
         
            
            VVHat means this mourning on mount Libanō
                  ▪
               
            
            Why howle ye firre trees? O a Cedars gone,
            Whoſe hallowed boughs to vs ſuch ſhade had lent,
            As ſhepheards ſang, and trees made merriment;
            Which being fallen, the hils would equall faine,
            
               Hadadrimmons mourning on Megiddons plaine:
            Yet know we well it's but remoued hence,
            To holy Zion, where with deare expence
            Of Shiloes bloud, God raiſed hath a quire,
            To which all Firres and Cedars doe aſpire.
            It is our loſſe, foule crimes haue cauſed theſe throes,
            For preſent want and feare of future woes.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

