
   
      
         
            The argument of Master Nicholas Fuller, in the case of Thomas Lad, and Richard Maunsell, his clients Wherein it is plainely proved, that the Ecclesiasticall Commissioners haue no power, by vertue of their commission, to imprison, to put to the Oath ex officio, or to fine any of his Maiesties subiects.
            Fuller, Nicholas, 1543-1620.
         
         
            
               1607
            
         
         Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01338
            STC 11460
            ESTC S102744
            99838511
            99838511
            2892
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01338)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2892)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1024:04)
         
         
            
               
                  The argument of Master Nicholas Fuller, in the case of Thomas Lad, and Richard Maunsell, his clients Wherein it is plainely proved, that the Ecclesiasticall Commissioners haue no power, by vertue of their commission, to imprison, to put to the Oath ex officio, or to fine any of his Maiesties subiects.
                  Fuller, Nicholas, 1543-1620.
               
               [4], 32 p.   
               
                  Imprinted [at William Jones' secret press],
                  [S.l.] :
                  1607.
               
               
                  Printer identified by STC.
                  Running title reads: The argument of Nicholas Fuller.
                  With one erratum on pi2v. Variant: with three errata.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Mansell, Richard, 17th cent.
               Lad, Thomas.
               England and Wales. --  Ecclesiastical Commissioners --  Controversial literature.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-05
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-08
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-09
            John CordsSampled and proofread
         
            2005-09
            John CordsText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE ARGVMENT OF MASTER NICHOLAS FVLLER, IN THE CASE OF THOMAS LAD, AND RICHARD MAVNſell, his Clients. Wherein it is plainely proved, that the Eccleſiaſticall Commiſſioners haue no power, by vertue of their Commiſsion, to Impriſon, to put to the Oath Ex Officio, or to fine any of his Maieſties Subiects.
            
               Pſal. 2.10.
               Be wiſe now therefore ye Kings: be learned ye Iudges of the earth.
               2. Chron. 19.6.
               Take heede what ye doe: for ye execute not the iudgments of man, but of the Lord; and he will be with you, in the cauſe and iudgment.
               Prov. 24.11.12.
               Deliver them that are drawne to death: and wilt thou not preſerue them that are led to be ſlayne?
               If thou ſay, Behold, we knew not of it: he that pondereth the heartes, doth not he underſtand it? and he that keepeth thy ſoule, knoweth he it not? will not he alſo recompenſe every man according to his workes.
            
            Imprinted. 1607.
         
         
            
            THE PRINTER TO THE READER.
            CHriſtian Reader, there came to my hands, by the good providence of God, this Argument of M. Fullers, accompanied with ſome few lines, wherin, as it ſhould ſeeme, it was ſent incloſed to a Gentleman of good worth and worſhip on this ſide the Seaes. Having read it over, &amp; perceiving it to be of very neceſſarie uſe for my Countrimen (whoſe good I deſire from my heart, and whoſe welfare I take my ſelfe bound to procure, as I may, though now I be in a part farre remote from them) I haue adventured to publiſh it to the view of the world: the rather, becauſe therein both the uniuſt uſurpation of the Prelates over his Maieſties Subiects is notably diſcovered, and the lawes and liberties of the land (the high Inheritance of the subjects) are worthily ſtood for and maintained, maugre the malice of the Prelates; who, as I heare ſtudie, and ſtriue, even with might and maine, to beare downe all before them, to the ruine of that ſometime-flouriſhing Church and Common-wealth. How the publiſhing of it wilbe liked I cannot tell; how ever, I ſend it abroad to thy view even as it came to my handes: which I doe (I profeſſe in the preſence of that great God) altogither without the privitie either of the Gentleman himſelfe (whoſe bandes I would be loth any maner of way to increaſe) or of the silenced Miniſters, who haue felt the weight of theſe lawles proceedings too too long in the handes of the Prelates. Reade it, and conſider well of it: and if thou reape any benefite by it, giue all the glorie to God alone; who can, if it ſeeme ſo good unto him, by weake meanes bring great matters to paſſe. Farewell.
         
         
            
            To my worshipfull frend. W.W.
            WOrſhipfull Sir, I ſend you here-incloſed the thing which you ſent for ſo long ſince. What the drift of it is I underſtand in part, as having read it over. How well it is performed, I am not able to iudge, becauſe it is out of my Element. The Gentleman arguing the Caſe is knowne to many, but diverſly both thought and reported of, upon occaſion of his preſent troubles. His per
                  •
               on and cauſe I leaue to them, to whom it belongeth iuſtly to determine of ſuch great matters. But touching the poynt it ſelfe, I hope that as you (out of the depth of your iudgment &amp; great experience) are able to ſpeake much, both for the matter and manner of it, ſo you will not be unwilling to declare your minde, as occaſion ſhalbe offered, either in the like or diſlike of it. And ſo having no more at this time to trouble your Worſhip withall, but patiently waiting for your opinion herein (if you ſo thinke it good) and wiſhing alwayes all maner of good unto you, I humblie take my leaue.
         
         
            Gentle Reader, becauſe the French (quoted in this Argument) is ſomewhat miſ-printed, and the Latine (though it be not much) may yet notwithſtanding ſtumble the ſimple and ſuch as be unlearned: I haue thought it not amiſſe to engliſh both the one and the other; referring thee every where to the page, and line, where either of them is.
            
               Pag. 5. line 9. Becauſe the Kings power ought not to be wanting to holy Church.
            
               Ibid. line. 19. but by the lawful iudgment of his Peeres, or the law of the land.
            
               Pag. 7. line 7. as before, pag 5. line 9.
            
            
               ibidem line 27. &amp;c. Supplication is made to the moſt excellent and gratious Prince, our Lord the King, on the behalfe of your humble Orators, the Prelats and Clergie of your kingdome of England, that whereas the Catholike faith founded upon Chriſt, and by his Apoſtles, and Church &amp;c.
            Which petitions of the Prelates &amp; Clergie before expreſſed, our Lord the King, with the conſent of his Nobles and other Peeres of his Realme aſſembled in preſent Parliament, hath graunted: and in every of them according to the forme &amp;c.
            
               
               Pag. 8. line 8. Alſo the Commons pray, that ſith it is conteyned in the great Charter, that none ſhould be arreſted, or impriſoned, without anſwer, or due proceſſe of law, which Charter is confirmed in every Parliament, &amp;c. And besides they intreat, that if any be arreſted or impriſoned contrary to the forme of the Charter aforeſayd, that he may come and appeare to his anſwer, and take his iudgment, even as the law requireth: alſo that no ſuch Arreſt or Impriſonment may be drawne into cuſtome, to the deſtruction of the law of the King.
            
               Ibidem, line 16. Let the Statutes, and the common law be kept.
            
               Ibid. line 20. &amp;c. Alſo the commons beſeech, that whereas a ſtatute was made in the laſt Parliament, in theſe words, It is ordeined in this Parliament, that the Kings Commiſsions be directed to the Sheriffes, and other officers of the King, or to other ſufficient perſons, after and according as the certificates of the Prelates were wont to be in the Chauncery, from time to time and that ſuch preachers, their favourers, abettours &amp;c.
            Which was never aſſented unto, nor graunted by the commons, but that which was done therein was done without their aſſent, and ſo the ſtatute is of no force. For it was never their meaning to iuſtifie it, nor to binde themſelues, nor their ſucceſſors, to the Prelates any more then their Aunceſtors had done in times paſt.
            It pleaſeth the King.
            
               Pag. 10. line 31. Becauſe no man is bound to betray himſelfe.
            
               Pag. 11. line 9. An Oath in a mans owne cauſe is the deviſe of the Devill, to throw the ſoules of poore men into Hell.
            
               Pag. 12. line. 19. Nature is a preſerver of it ſelfe.
            
               Ibidem line. 27. Without a certaine Author of the Bill exhibited no accuſations ought to haue place, for it is both a thing of very evill example, and not the manner of theſe times.
            
               Pag. 14. line. 26. &amp;c. The King can doe nothing upon earth (ſeeing he is the ſervant and lieuetenant of God) but that which he may lawfully doe: becauſe that power belongeth onely to God, but the power of doing wrong belongeth to the Devill, and not to God, and the workes of which ſo ever of theſe the King ſhall doe, his ſervant he is.
            
               Pag. 15. line. 12. condemned for what cauſe ſo ever.
            
               Pag. 18. line. 2. We will not haue the lawes of England to be changed.
            Gentle Reader, in pag. 29. line 21. there is gone puruſed, for purſued, the which I pray thee to amend.
         
      
      
         
            
            THE ARGVMENT OF MASTER NICHOLAS FVLLER, IN THE CASE OF THOmas Lad, and Richard Maunſell, his clients. Wherein it is plainely proved, that the Eccleſiaſticall Commiſioners haue no power, by vertue of their Commiſsion, to Impriſon, to put to the oth Ex Officio, or to fine any of his Maieſties Subiects.
            
               THE CASE.
               
                  THomas Lad, a marchant of Yarmouth, in Norfolke, was brought before the Chauncellor of Norwich, for a ſuppoſed Conventicle; becauſe that he, on the Sabbath dayes after the Sermons ended, ſojourning in the houſe of M. Iackler in Yarmouth, who was late Preacher of Yarmouth, joyned with him in repeating of the ſubſtance and heads of the ſermons that day made in the Church, at which Thomas Lad was uſually preſent: and was forced upon his oath to anſwer certaine articles touching that meeting, which he could not ſee untill he was sworne; and having anſwered vpon his oath twice before the Chauncelor there, he was brought to Lambeth before the Eccleſiaſticall Commiſsioners, to make a further anſwer, upon a newe oath, touching the ſuppoſed Conventicle: which he refuſed to doe, without ſight of his former anſwers (becauſe he was charged with perjury) and therefore was imprisoned by the Commiſsioners a long time, &amp; could not be bayled; whereupon the writt of Habeas Corpus was granted out of the Kings bench, to bring the priſoner to the Barr.
               
                  
                  Richard Maunſell, the other priſoner, being a Preacher, was charged to haue been a partaker in a Petition exhibited to the Nether houſe of the Parliament: and for refuſing to take the Oth ex officio, to anſwer to certayne articles, which he could not be permitted to ſee, he was impriſoned by the Cōmiſsioners at Lambeth, where he remayned very long, and could not be bayled, and was brought to the barr, upon the writt of habeas Corpus.
               
               Theſe impriſonments of Thomas Lad, and Richard Maunſell by the Cōmiſsioners, for the ſuppoſed contempts aforesayd, were unlawfull (as the ſaid Nicholas Fuller ſaid) and therefore he sayd that the prisoners ought to be diſcharged; And, before he began his Argument, he the sayd Nicholas Fuller did confesse, that it was a blessed thing, in all kingdomes, to haue the Church, and Common wealth to agree together as Hippocrates twinnes: And the meanes to continue a perfect agreement betweene them was (as he sayd) to giue to Caeſar that which is Caeſars, and to God that which is Gods. Which right diſtribution of the Iuriſdiction of the Church in England, and Iuriſdiction of the Common lawes in England, ſett forth and proved upon good groundes of the auncient lawes and ſtatutes of the Realme, would (as he thought) cōtinue a peace between the Church and Common wealth of England for ever; which he deſired from his heart, and it was his labour to effect by this his Argument. Wherin, for the better underſtanding of his purpoſe and drift of his Argument, he did devide the ſame into 5. partes.
               1 And (firſt becauſe the Eccleſiaſticall Cōmiſsion is groū
                  ded upon the Statute of Anno 1. Eliz. cap. 1. the title and intent of which ſtatute is, the reſtoring to the Crowne the

auncient Iuriſdiction over the Eccliſiaſticall &amp; ſpirituall office, and the aboliſhing of all forreyne Iuriſdiction repugnant to the ſame) he declared what that auncient ſpirituall Iuriſdiction was, which was ment in that Act to be reſtored, and by the Cōmiſſioners to be executed; and therein he proved, that the power to impriſon ſubjects, to fine them, or to force them to accuſe themſelues upon their owne enforced oathes, there being no accuſer knowne, was no parte of the auncient Eccleſiaſticall juriſdiction, nor uſed in England by any ſpirituall Iuriſdiction, before the Statute of 2. Hen. 4. cap. 15. which was procured by the Popiſh Prelats
               
               2 That the Statute of 2. Hen. 4. cap. 15. which firſt gaue  authority to the Biſhopps to impriſon ſubjects, fine thē, and force them to accuſe themſelues, was procured by the Popiſh Prelates in the time of darknes (if not without a full conſent of the Cōmons, yet to their great miſlike) and that the ſayd Statute, and every thing in the ſame conteyned, is revoked, as being againſt the rule of equitie and common juſtice, and againſt the lawes of the lād, and very hatefull to all the ſubjectes of the Realme: and in that 2. parte he proved, according to the words of the ſtatute, that the Oath ex officio was againſt the law of England, and againſt the rule of equitie and Iuſtice.
               3 That the lawes of England are the high inheritance  of the Realme, by which both the King and the ſubjects are directed; And that ſuch grants, Charters, and Commiſſions, as tend to charge the body, lands, or goods of the ſubjects, otherwiſe then according to the due courſe of the lawes of the Realme, are not lawfull, or of force, unles the ſame Charters and Commiſſions, doe receaue life and ſtrength, from ſome Act of Parliament.
               
               
                  
                   4 That, in this Commiſſion Eccleſiaſticall, there are ſome thinges tending to charge the body, lands, &amp; goods of the ſubjects, otherwiſe then according to the courſe of the lawes of the Realme; and eſpecially in impriſoning them, fyning them, and forcing thē to accuſe themſelues (upon their owne oath) without any accuſer.
               5. That the Act of Parliament of Anno. 1. Elizab. cap. 1. 
                   whereupon the Eccleſiaſticall Commission is founded. doth not giue life or ſtrength to ſuch partes of the Commiſſion, as concerne impriſonment of ſubjectes, fyning them, or forcing them to accuſe themſelues; but doth make voyd and aboliſh the ſame, as repugnant to the ancient Eccleſiaſtical juriſdiction which by the Statute was to be reſtored. And ſo he ſayd that the impriſonment of his clients was unlawfull &amp; the proceeding of the Commiſſioners, upon the Oath ex officio, without an accuſer, not warranted by law, but erroneous and voyd.
               Touching the firſt parte of the division, which was to proue, that, before the ſtatute of 2. Hen. 4. cap. 15. the Ordinaries had no power to impriſon the ſubjects, or to fine them, it appeareth both by the preamble of that Statute, where it is declared, that, before that time, they could not by their spirituall Iurisdiction, without ayd of the Royal Majeſtie, ſufficiently correct perverſe people, who did contemne their ſpirituall jurisdiction and Keyes of the Church (which was, at the uttermost, to locke them out of the Church by Excomunication) and alſo by the booke caſe of 10. Hen. 7. arguing upon that poynt of the ſame ſtatute, where it is ſet forth, that the Ordinaries, before the Statute of 2. Hen. 4. had no power to impriſon ſubiects, but the Keyes of the Church: and the like is alſo confeſſed by the Statute of 1. and 2. of Philip and Mary.
                  
which was made after the former Statute of 2. Hen. 4. was revoked by 25. Hen. 8. cap. 14 which doe ſhew as much, viz. that the Ordinaries had no power but the Keyes.
               And by the Common law it is apparant, that when the Ordinary or Eccleſiaſticall Judge had proceeded ſo farr as they could, by Excomunicating the offendor to locke him out of the Church, then the Cōmon law, upon ſignificavit, did aſſiſt them by the writt of Excōmunicato Capiendo: Quia poteſtas reg
                        ••
                      ſacro ſanctae Eccleſiae d
                        ••
                     ſſe non debet, as is ſayd in the Regiſter. But in this caſe the Comō law ſtill reteyned power to diſcharge the ſubjectes ſo impriſoned (upon an Excōmunicato capiendo) without aſſent of the Ordinary,Fitz H. f. 4
                        •
                     . both by the writt of Cautione admittenda, and by the writt of ſcire facias, upon an appeale; where a ſuperſedeas was usually awarded, to diſcharge the perſon impriſoned, againſt the will of the Ordinary. For the lawes of England did ſo much regard and preſerue the liberty of the ſubjects, as that none ſhould be imprisoned, niſi per legale iudicium parium ſuorum aut legem terrae, as it is ſayd in Magna Charta cap. 29. which Charter,4
                        •
                      Edw. 
                        •
                     . cap. 3. by divers other ſtatutes after, is confirmed, with ſuch ſtrong inforcements in ſome of them, as to make voyd ſuch ſtatutes, as ſhould be contrary to Magna Charta.
               
               And, in the 15. Ed. 3. the firſt article of the Commons Petition in Parliament, was,In the Tower amōgst the Parliament 
                        〈◊〉
                     . 15 
                        ••
                     . 
                        •
                     . that the great Charter may in all poynts be obſerved, ſo as ſuch perſons as are neither appealed, Indited, nor followed at the ſute of the party, and haue their goodes, landes, or poſſeſſions taken away, may be restored thereunto agayne.
               
                  Whereunto the King anſwered thus.
               
               The King granteth for him &amp; his heires that if any perſon cōmit an act againſt the forme of the great Charter,
                     
                        〈…〉
                     .
                  
or any other good lawe, and he ſhall anſwer in Parliamēt or elſe where; he ought to anſwer according to law. And therfore if any free ſubject were wrongfully impriſoned, the Common law did not leaue him to an action of falſe impriſonment onely, but provided the writt De homine replegiando,
                  Fit
                        ••
                     . fo. 40 E
                        •
                     . 
                        •
                     . fo. 36. to ſet him free of his impriſonment, vnles he were imprisoned for ſuch particular cauſe, as is expreſſed in the ſame writt de homine replegiando: which writt is part of the ſubjectes inheritance, and ſhould not be denyed them. And this freedome of the ſubjectes did make Markham the Iudge, in the 4. Hen. 7. tit: prerog. 139. Brook: declare that the King could not arrest a ſubject upon ſuſpicion of felony, as a common perſon might doe; becauſe that againſt the one an action of falſe impriſonment would lye, but not againſt the King (for the ſubiects liberty muſt be preſerved) and by the Statute of Win: 1. cap. 15. whoſoever ſhall deteyne ſubjects in priſon, who are bayleable by law, ſhalbe grievouſly amerced.
               And to ſhew that it was thought an unmeete thing to leave power in the Ordinaries to commit ſubjectes to prison, although they contemned their decrees never ſo much, appeareth partly by the ſtatutes of 27. Hen. 8. ca. 20. and 32. Hen. 8. ca. 7. which were made after the revocation of the former statute of 2. Hen. 4: by which latter ſtatutes power is given to two Iuſtices of peace, or to ſome of the Honorable privie Counſell, uppon certificate of the Ordinary, to commit ſuch offenders to prison, who should contemne the decrees of the Ordinary: denying to the Ordinary, that made the decree, that he ſhould haue any ſuch power to commit the ſubjects to priſon: &amp; in 5. Eliz. ca. 23. which ſtatute, not allowing Excōmunicate perſons to be impriſoned by any Eccleſiaſtical Iuriſdiction, limits

by very ſpeciall manner, how they ſhall be apprehended by the tēporall power. For although the Biſhop of Rome uſeth two ſwordes, the ſpirituall and temporall; yet the common lawes of England, and the Parliament in divers ages, thought not ſo meete, for the Biſhopps or Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction in England to uſe two ſwordes, but according to the Regiſter, Regia poteſtas ſacro-ſanclae Eccleſiae d
                        ••
                     ſſe non deb
                        •
                     t.
               
               2 Touching the ſecond part (wherin he was, to proue that the ſtatute of 2. Hen. 4. cap: 15: which firſt gaue authority to the Ordinaries to impriſon ſubjects, or to ſet fines on them, and force them to accuſe themſelues upon their owne oathes, was procured by the Popiſh Prelates in the time of darknes) he ſayd that the very Act it ſelfe did very playnely ſhew it; it being thus; And where it is ſhewed to the King, on the behalfe of the Prelates and Clergie of England etc. And that the ſame was procured to ſuppreſſe the gospell, which then began to ſpring or revive, both the body of the Act, and the booke of Acts and Monuments written by M. Fox, and other Chronicles doe ſhew it playnly; for that thoſe perſons, whom they tearmed heretickes, preached in thoſe dayes againſt the Sacrament of the Church, which was their Maſſe. And that the ſayd Statute of 2. Hen: 4. cap. 15. was procured by the Prelats, with out aſſent of the Commons, thus much appeareth by the Records of the Parliament, remayning in the Tower.
               
                  Excellentiſsimo ac gratioſiſsimo Principi, Domino noſtro Regi,
                  
                     Ex-rotulo Parliamenti, de an. 2. H. 4. Petitio cleri c
                           •
                        ntra hereti
                           ••
                        s.
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        
                     
                   
                  ſupplicatur, ex parte v
                        •
                     ſtrorū humilium oratorum, prelatorum et cleri regni veſlr
                        •
                     . Angliae, quod cū fides catholica ſuper Chriſtū ſundata, et per Apoſtolos ſuos, et Eccleſiam etc. rehearſing all the words of the Act. Qu
                        •
                     s quidem petitiones prelatorum et cleri ſuperius expreſſ
                        •
                     tas dominus u
                        •
                     ſter Rex, de conſ
                        •
                     nſu magnatum,

et aliorū procerū r
                        •
                     gni ſui in preſenti ꝑliamento exiſtē
                     tiū conceſsit, et in ſingulis iuxta forma etc: wherin the Commons are not mentioned. And it is the more likely that the Cōmons gaue no aſſent to this ſtatute of 2. Hen: 4. both for that in the Parliament rolls of the ſame yeare of 2. Hen. 4. in the Tower, there is to be ſeene the Petition of the Commons to the King, thus.
               
                  Item prient les comens, depuis q'uill eſt contenu en la grande chartre,
                  The Petition of the Commons. 
                  quenul ſera areſte ne enpriſone ſans reſponce, ou due proceſſe de la ley, quell chartre eſt conferme en charmi ꝑlement, et ore ils ſupplient, que ſi aucun ſoit areſte ou enpriſone encontre la forme d
                        •
                     l charte avant dict q̄ ill veigne, et appierge a ſa reſponce, et preigne ſon Iugement, ſicome le ley demande, anſsi q̄ null tiel areſte ne impriſonement ſoit trait en̄ cuſtome, en̄ deſtruction de la ley du Roy. Wherto the King anſwered.
               
                  Soient les ſtatutes eila comen ley tenus; As also for that the Prelats had not long before procured an other act againſt the Lolards,
                  
                     The anſwer of the King.
                   in Anno 5. Rich: 2. cap: 5. without aſſent of the Commons; as appeareth by the Parliament Rolles, in the Tower, of anno 6. R. 2. which is thus. Item ſupplient les comens, q̄ comē vn eſtatute ſuit ſait en darrein ꝑlement, en ces paroles: Ordone eſt en ceſt ꝑlement, q̄ Comiſsions du Roy ſoient directes a viſcountes et autres miniſtres du roy, ou autres ſuffiſantz perſons, apreset ſelon que les certificates des prelates eut affaire in chancellerie, du temps en temp̄s, touts tiels precheurs c
                        •
                     lour fautours mamtenours. etc.
               
               
                  La quel ne fuit un
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      aſſente, ne grante ꝑ les Comens, mes ce q̄ fuit parle de ce▪ fuit ſans aſsent de lour q̄ celi eſtatue ſoit an
                        •
                     a ati car il neſtoit mi lour entent iuſtiſiez ne obliger lour ne lour ſucceſſorers as Prelates plus q̄ lour auncesſtres nont eſte en temps paſſez.
               
               Reſp: Il pleſt au R
                        ••
                     .
               
               
                  And it is alſo reported by M. Fox in the ſayd booke of Acts and Monuments, that the ſame Act of 2. Hen. 4. ca. 1
                        •
                     . was procured without aſſent of the Commons;Act. &amp; Mo fol 539. and that the Commons did greatly repyne at it frō time to time, many godly men writyng againſt it, ſome of them terming it a bloodie law, and a cruell law. And becauſe the Prelats (out of the wordes of that law which gaue them power to impriſon ſome ſuſpected of hereſie, untill they ſhould canonically purg themſelues) did ſtreinedly force ſubjectes without any accuſer to accuſe themſelues, therfore the title of that Act is ſett downe in the booke of Acts &amp; Monuments, the ſtatute Ex officio;Act. &amp; Mō. fol. 481. at which time it was not commonly uſed to giue titles to Acts of Parliament.
               And, to ſhew how much the ſubjectes miſliked that kind of proceeding, appeareth by ſeverall Petitions of the ſubjectes to the Kings of the Realme, and to the houſe of Parliament, by the ſtatute of 25. Hen. 8. cap. 14. by which ſtatute it is ſayd, that the proceeding by the oath Ex officio, to force a man to accuſe himſelfe, is contrary to the rule of right and good equity, and contrary to the lawes of England, and unreaſonable that, upon ſuſpition conceaved upon the fantaſye of the Ordinaries, men ſhould be forced to anſwer &amp;c. And therefore they then revoked, and made voyd the ſtatute of 2. Hen. 4. cap: 15.
               
               And to proue, that, according to the opinion of that Parliament houſe, the oath Ex officio is againſt the lawes of England both Eccleſiaſticall &amp; temporall, and againſt the rule of Iuſtice and good equitie, he ſayd, that by the lawes of England (if a ſubject had been cyted, by the Ordinary or Eccleſiaſticall Iudge, pro ſalute aīae, which is the oath Ex officio, to accuſe himſelfe) a Prohibition did lye at

the cōmon law, and an attachment against the Ordinary, if he did proceed in that case contrary to that prohibition▪ as appeareth in Eliz. H. fol. 42. and the ſtatute of 2. H. 
                  
                     〈…〉
                   made ſoone after the ſayd ſtatute of 2. Hen. 4. (giving warrant to graunt a prohibition to the Ordinary for default of a libell) doth croſſe the proceeding by oath Ex offi
                        •
                     i
                        •
                     
                  ; where he is forced to a libell, as appeareth 4. 
                        •
                     d. 4. fol. 3
                        •
                     . and Fitz. H. fol. 43. etc.
               And by the words of the ſtatute of 42. Edw. 3. cap. 3. (which was made before thoſe ſtatutes procured by the Prelates, when Ordinaries had no power to impriſon ſubjectes) it is expressed, in what manner the proceeding should be againſt ſubjectes upon accuſations, thus viz. It is aſſented &amp; accorded, for the good governement of the Commons, that no man be put to anſwer, without preſentment before Iuſtices, or thing of Record, by due proces, and writt originall, according to the ould law of the land; And if any thing be done from henceforth to the contrary; it ſhalbe voyd in law &amp; holden for error; wherin it is worthy the nothing, that it is ſayd according to the old lawes of England.
               
               And to proue the old law of England to be ſo, the ordinary caſe of dayly experience, touching the challenge of Iurors, doth ſufficiently declare. For if the Iuror be challenged for kindred to either of the parties, or for wāt of freehould, the Iuror ſhall anſwer upon his oath, to cleare that matter; becauſe it toucheth not the Iuror in loſſe or credit: but if the challenge doe tend to touch the Iuror any way in his credit, or his loſſe, he ſhal not be forced,
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     . Edw. 3. fol. 2. upon his oath, to anſwer, although his anſwer might tend to further Iuſtice; quia nemo tenetur prodere s
                        •
                     ipsum, as is ruled 49. Edw. 3. fol. 2. And the caſe of wager of law,
                  
which is allowed to the defendant in no criminall caſe, which might bring imprisonment to the partie by the course of the common law as in trespas &amp;c: but onely in debt and detinewe: and the ſtatute of Magna Charta 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  . 28. inacting, that no Bailife ſhall put a man to his open law, nor to an oath, upon his owne bare ſaying, without faithfull witneſſes brought in for the ſame, tōdoth to like effect: and S. Edward Cooke, in his argument made in Slades Caſe, ſayd well, that in criminall cauſes (iuramentū in propria cauſa eſt inventio diaboli ad detrudendum animas miserorum in infernum) according to whoſe ſaying it appeareth, that when thoſe oathes were uſed by the parties accuſed, by the border lawes between England &amp; Scotland, thoſe oathes did bring no furtherance to the truth, but manifeſt perjury every day; as was confeſſed by all that knewe the practiſe there: and therefore that manner of triall was ſoone rejected.
               And to proue it againſt Iuſtice and good equity, he ſayd that this oath Ex officio, to force a man in a criminall cauſe to accuſe himſelfe, was (he thought) directly againſt the rule of the law of God. For it is ſayd in Deut. cap. 19. 15. that one witnes ſhall not ariſe againſt a man for any treſpas, or for any ſin, or for any fault that he offēdeth in; but at the mouth of two witneſſes or .3. witneſſes shall the matter be eſtabliſhed. Which rule is confirmed under the Goſpell, as appeareth Math: 18.16. 2. Cor. 13.1. where it is ſayd, In the mouth of two or three witneſſes ſhall every word ſtand; and Chriſt ſayd to the woman accused of adultery, where be thine accuſers? &amp;c. But without any witnes or accuſer to eſtabliſh the matter, upon the inforced oath of the partie, hath no coherence with the rule of Gods law, which ſhould be a direction to all Chriſtian

Princes in making of their lawes, we being now the people of God the Iewes being cut of; the Iudgments being now the iudgments of God, and not of men alone.
               But here may be objected, that by the lawes of England one witnes is ſufficient: to which he anſwered, that the Iurors being all ſworne to trie the particuler matter in fact, wherewith the party defendant is charged, may well ſupplie the want of one witnes, being 12 perſons in different, without any affinitie to either partie, who better knowe the witneſſes then the Iudge, and may perhaps know the cauſe in queſtion, aſwell as the witnes: which kinde of triall is ſo behouefull for the ſubjectes, as it may prevent much wrong and oppreſſion from high authoritie, if the Iurors be iuſt &amp; faithfull perſons, as they ought to be; and their verdit alſo may be redreſſed by attaint, if they ſhould doe wrong therein: which writts of attaint, and error, are parte of the ſubjectes inheritance.
               Alſo this oath Ex officio hath no coherence with the law of nature. For, as Ariſtotle ſaith, natura eſt conſervatrix ſui, as is ſayd in 40. Edw, 3. fol. 2: but this tendeth to a mans owne overthrowe; &amp; it hath no coherence with the lawes of Nations, as he gathered by the writing of Traiane the Emperour, being a very wiſe &amp; juſt man; who writing to Plinie the ſecond, his lievetenant of ſome Provinces in Aſia minor, for direction in his governement, againſt thoſe, who at that time were oppoſite to his religion, ſaith thus (Sine authore certo propoſiti libelli nulli crimini locū habere debent; nam et peſ
                        •
                     imi exempli, nec noſtri ſeculi eſt) According to which direction, Felix the governer of the Iewes under the Emperor,Acts 23.35. when Paul the Apoſtle was brought before him, ſayd to Paul; that he would heare him, when his accuſers were come; holding it as unjuſt, without an accuſer, to charge him.
               
                  And it is much worſe then auricular confeſſion; becauſe that is voluntary, this by conſtreint; that to be concealed, this to be revealed to the parties ſhame; that to induce pardon, this to induce puniſhment to himſelfe. And where an oath ſhould be the end of ſtrife, this oath Ex officio is often times the begining of ſtrife; yea it hath been ſo hatefull as ſome Martyrs haue written againſt it, as a bloudie law; and therefore not without juſt cauſe, that the whole eſtate aſſembled in Parliament in an. 25. Hen. 8. held it not to be agreeing with the rule of right and equity, and to be contrary to the lawes of England, and therfore revoked the ſayd ſtatute of 2. Hen. 4. and did therby limitt another forme of proceeding againſt perſons accuſed or ſuſpected, thus, viz. upon Inditement or two witneſſes at the leaſt (according to Gods law) with wordes of reſtreint, not to proceed otherwiſe: ſince which time, no cuſtome, or colour of preſcription in the Eccleſiaſticall Courts, can take place againſt that law, to uphold the oth Ex officio in caſe of hereſie.
               And touching fines, by the ſtatute of Articuli cleri cap. 1. by the Regiſter and by Fitzh. Natura brev. fo. 51. &amp; 52. and by the ſtatute of 15. Edw. 3. cap. 6. it is ſo ſhewed, that, by auncient Eccleſiaſticall jurisdiction, they ought not to ſet fines of mony upon ſubjectes, unles it were upon cō
                  mutation of penaunce; ſo as it need no further proofe of that matter.
               The third matter which he endevored to proue, was, that the lawes of the kingdome of England, and the manner of proceeding in caſes of law and juſtice, are ſetled in the Realme, as parte of the inheritance of the ſubjectes, and rightly termed by ſome Iudges in 10. Hen: 6. fo: 62. to be the moſt high inheritance of the Kingdome, by which

both King and ſubjects are guided:Bra
                        ••
                     . fol. 5. cap. 
                        ••
                     . &amp; that without lawes there would be nether King nor inheritance in England. Which lawes, by long continuance of time and good indeavor of many wiſe men, are ſo fitted to this people, and this people to them, as it doth make a ſweete harmony in the goverment; all things being as readily obeyed on the one parte which are agreeing to law, as they are willingly commanded on the other parte according to law: every officer, by the rule of the law, knowing the duties of their places, as Sheriffes, Bayliffes, 
                  Stamf. fol. 
                        ••
                     . 
                  Conſtables, Coroners, Eſchetors; &amp;c. the band of an oath, both for goverment and obedience, being mutually made on each parte.
               For the lawes in a common wealth are like the ſinewes in a naturall body, by which the hand, foote, and other partes of the body doe readily moue, by the direction of the head; but if the hand, or foote, be forced aboue the ſtrength of the ſinewe, it eyther taketh away the uſe of that parte, or els it maketh it a weake or halting member: ſo is it, if the lawes be ſtreyned againſt any part of the comon wealth, aboue it right, and naturall ſtrength, it will make that parte weake, or halting: and therefore it is excellently ſayd in 8. Hen. 4. fol. 19. in the com. fol. 236. and in the Caſe of Alton woodes,8. Hen. 4. fo. 19. com. fol. 236. that the law admeaſureth the Kings prerogatiue, ſo as it ſhall not extend to hurt the inheritance of the ſubjectes on the on parte: and as Bracton ſaith, nihil aliud poteſt rex in terris, cum ſit Dei miniſter et vicarius, quam quod de iure poteſt: quia illa poteſtas ſolius Dei eſt; poteſtas autem iniuriae diaboli eſt, et non Dei; et cuius horum opera 
                        •
                     ecerit rex, eius miniſter eſt.
               
               And the law doth reſtrayne the liberall wordes of the Kings grant, for the benefit both of the King and the ſubjects, and to the great happines of the Realme; eſpecially

when the Iudges are mē of courage, fearing God; as is to be proved by many Caſes adjudged in theſe Courtes of Kings Bench, and Common-Pleas; which Courtes are the principall preſervers of this high inheritance of the law: whereof he rehearſed ſome few Caſes on the parte of the King, and on the part of the ſubjectes diverſe Caſes; as in 45. Aſs. p. 15. where the King did grant to I.S. &amp; his heires, the manour of Dale, &amp; all the woodes, and underwoods, and Mynes within the ſayd mannor; yet Mynes of gold and ſilver did not paſſe: and in the 22. Aſſ 40. the King did grant to. I.S. the goods and chattells of perſons with▪ in Dale, qualitercunque damnatorum; yet the goodes of perſons attainted of treaſon did not paſſe, for the benefit of the King: becauſe the ſame are ſo annexed to the crowne, as by no generall words they may paſſe frō the Crowne, by the rule of law. And of late yeares what great benefite hath growne to the Kings and Queenes of this Realme, upon conſtruction, according to the rules of law, of the Kings graunts, the caſe of Alton woods, the ſtatute lately made for confirmation of Charters granted to the Citizens of London, and the many caſes preferred by Tipper &amp; his fellowes, doe ſufficiently proue.
               And, on the other ſide, if any graunt or Commiſſion from the King doth tend to charge the body, landes, or goods of the ſubjects unlawfully, the Iudges will redreſſe the ſame. For if the King graunt the lands or goods of. I.S; that is ſo manifeſtly againſt law, as it needes no proofe.
               But (he said) he would put ſuch Caſes as, being groū
                  ded upon prerogatiue, haue a ſhew of good to the Common wealth, and yet are not allowable, becauſe the tend to charge the ſubject, without the aſſent of the ſubject: as the Caſe, 1
                        •
                     . Hen. 4. where the King did graunt

an office of meaſuring of cloath in London to I. S. with a Fee to be receaved for the ſame meaſuring: and although the office tend to further commutatiue Iuſtice, whereof the power is in the King for weight and meaſure; yet becauſe this fee did tend to charge the ſubject, without his aſſent, it was adjudged, by the learned Iudges, upon long debate, to be voyd: and the caſe of Protection, 39. Hen. 6. fol. 39. where the King did grant a protection to A. B. his ſervant, quia proſecturus, for a voyage to Rome, for ſervice of the King and Common wealth for weightie cauſes, to continue for three yeares; and yet it was diſallowed by the Iudges, becauſe it was for three yeares, where, by the rules of the law, it ſhould be but for one; &amp; becauſe there was no exceptiō of dower, Aſſiſe, and quare impedit which by law ſhould haue been excepted: and that protection did not barr the ſubjects right, but only delayed his ſuite.
               And in 3. Edw. 3: 14. Nort. Aſsiſe. 445. com. fol. 48. the King did pardon I.S. the making of a bridge: and becauſe the ſubjectes had intereſt in the paſſage over that bridge: the Kings pardon was not ſufficient, to diſcharge I. S. frō the making therof. In the caſe of 42. Aſſ. 5. a Commiſſion from the King, under the great ſeale of England, was directed to A. and B. to take I. S. and him impriſon in the Caſtle of P. and to take his goodes; which was done accordingly by the Cōmiſſioners: and becauſe it was done without any inditment, or due courſe of law, the proceedings of the ſame Commiſſioners were adjudged voyd.
               The like caſe was 42. Aſſ. p. 12. Where, upon the Kings writt directed to the Iuſtices of laborers, I.S. was indited for ſome thing not perteyning to the Iuſtices of laborers, and therfore adjudged voyd, they having no Cōmiſſion ſo to doe. For although the Sheriffe, or officer, cannot

judge of the Kings writt, but muſt execute it: yet the Iudge may refuſe to execute the ſame writt, when it is againſt law, or impoſſible to be done, according to 1. Edw. 3. fol. 26. and in the 1. &amp; 2. Eliz. Scrogges his Caſe;1. Ed. 
                        •
                     .
                        ••
                     .26. where a Cōmiſſion was awarded to ſome Iudges, and perſons of credit, to heare the cauſe concerning the Office of exigent of London, which Scrogges did challenge; &amp; if Scrogges refuſed to ſubmit himſelfe to their order, to commit him to priſon: upon which Commiſſion Scrogges was cōmitted to priſon; and he was diſcharged, by the Iudges, of his impriſonment, by writt of habeas corpus, becauſe his impriſonment was not lawfull: which writs of habeas corpus are uſually graunted in the ſayd Courts of Kings bench, and Common pleas, thereby to releeue the ſubjectes, which are many times in other Courtes, and by ſome Commiſſioners, unlawfully impriſoned: yea many times, although the Commiſſions be grounded upon Acts of Parliamēt▪ as the Commiſſion of Sewers, the Commiſſion of Banckrupts, and the Eccleſsiaſticall Commiſsion: and many times they graunt Prohibitions to the Eccleſiaſticall Court, to the Admirall Court, and to the Court of Requeſts, and other inferior Courts, when they exceed their authority.
               And many other Caſes he would haue put to proue thoſe poynts, but that in a former argumēt made by him in the court of Kings bench, againſt Monopolie Patents of M. Darcie, Mich. 44. Eliz. all the Iudges then ſeemed to yeeld the ſame to the law, without any doubt, as he conceived;Fitz H.f. 31. H. 8. prohib. which high inheritance of the law the Common wealth hath alwayes ſo preſerved, as without Act of Parliament it cannot be changed, as appeareth by the anſwer of the Barons, when the Biſhops ſought to haue the law changed, touching children borne before mariage, although the

mariage after enſued, to be held as baſtards: the LL. ſayd, Nolumus leges Angliae mutari; and as is apparant by booke caſes, where it is adjudged, that the King, by a non obſtante may diſpence with a ſtatute law, but not with the cōmon law, nor alter the ſame as is adjudged 49. Aſſ. p. 8. and Boſoms Caſe; nor put the ſubjectes from their inheritance of the law,Boſomes Caſe Cooke fol. 35. as is 8. Hen. 4. fol. 19. which was alwayes accompted one of the great bleſſings of this land, to haue the law the meat-yeard, &amp; the Iudges the meaſurers. For, in all well governed Common wealthes, Religion and Iuſtice are the two principall pillars, wherein the power of God appeareth; and many times weake weomen doe rule, and command many thouſand ſtrong men, touching their liues, lands, and goods, without reſiſtance; which the loue and regard of Iuſtice procureth.
               
                   For the better proofe of the fourth part, he did reade verbatim the partes of the Eccleſiaſticall Commiſsion, which he thought to be againſt the lawes of England, and liberties of the ſubjects; remembring firſt to marke and conſider, how, whereas the whole drift of the Act of Parliament. 1. Eliz cap. 1. was, to reſtore to the Crowne the auncient iuriſdiction over the Eccleſiaſticall &amp; ſpirituall eſtate, and, for that purpoſe, did giue power to the Eccleſiaſtical Cō
                  miſſioners, to execute the premiſſes in the ſayd Act conteyned, for the correcting, and amending, and reforming of ſuch hereſies, errors, ſchiſmes, contempts, and enormityes, as by the Eccleſiaſticall lawes might lawfully be reformed, according to the tenour and effect of the ſayd Letters Patents, this Commiſſiō is ſince enlarged, and how it giveth power to the Commiſsioners, to enquire not onely of the permiſſes, mentioned in the ſtatute of 1. Eliz. cap. 1. but alſo of all offences, and contemps: againſt the ſtatute of 1. Eliz. cap. 2. intituled,

                  an Act for uniformitie of Common prayer, and ſervice of the Church, and adminiſtration of the ſacraments, and of all offences, and contempts againſt theſe ſtatuts following, which were all made ſince anno 1. Eliz. viz. the ſtatute of 5. Eliz: ca: 1. intituled, an Act for the aſſurance of the Queenes Maieſties power, over all ſtates and ſubiectes, within her dominions; the ſtatute of 13: Eliz: cap: 12. intituled, an Act to reforme certayne diſorders, touching the Miniſters of the Church; the ſtatute of 35. Eliz: cap: 1. intituled, an Act to reteyne her maieſties ſubiects in their due obedience; the ſtatute of 35 Eliz. cap: 2. intituled, an Act to reſtreyne ſome Popiſh recuſant to ſome certeyne places of aboad; the ſtatute of anno. 1. Iacobi. intituled, an Act for the due execution of the ſtatutes againſt Ieſuits, Seminaries, prieſts, recuſants &amp;c.
               
               Alſo power is given to the Cōmiſſioners, or any three or more of them, not only upon theſe penall lawes, and upon every offence therein conteyned, but also upon all ſeditious bookes, contempts, conſpiracies, private conventicles, falſe rumors or tales, ſeditious misbehaviours, and many other civill offences particulerly named in the letters pattens, to call before them all and every offendor in any of the premiſſes, and all ſuch, as, by them or any three or more of them, ſhall ſeeme to be ſuſpected perſons in any of the premiſſes; and every of them to examine, upon their corporall oathes, touching every or any of the premiſſes, which they ſhall object againſt them; and to proceede againſt them and every of them, as the nature and quality of the offence or ſuſpicion, in that behalfe, ſhall require; And to inquire of adulteries, fornications, outragious misbehaviours, and diſorders in mariages, and of al other grievous and great crymes, and offences, within any parte of the Realme, which are puniſhable or reformable by the Eccleſiaſticall

lawes of this Realme, according to the tenor of the lawes on that behalfe, or according to their wiſedomes, and diſcretions, or the diſcretions of any three of them.
               The Commiſsioners, or any three of them, are further authorized, willed, and commaunded to uſe and deviſe all ſuch good, lawfull, reaſonable, and convenient wayes, for the triall and ſearching out of all the premiſſes and proceedings therin, as by any three or more of them ſhall be thought moſt expedient, and neceſſary.
               They, or any .3. or more of them, haue authority to order &amp; award ſuch puniſhment to every ſuch offender, by fine, impriſonment, cenſures of the Church, or other lawfull way, or by all or any of the ſayd wayes; and to take ſuch order for the redreſſe of the ſame, as to the wiſdomes and diſcretions of any three or more of them ſhall be thought meete, and convenient.
               For contempt in not appearance, or not obeying the decree of any three of them, they haue power to fine thē at their diſcretiōs, and to commit them to ward, there to remayne, untill, by any three of them, they ſhalbe inlarged, according to their diſcretions.
               They haue power to take recognizance of every offendor; and ſuſpected perſon, aſwell for their perſonall appearance, as for the performance of ſuch orders &amp; decrees, as to any three of them ſhall ſeeme reaſonable, and convenient in that behelfe.
               They haue alſo power to commaund all &amp; every ſheriffes, Iuſtices, and other officers, and ſubjects within this Realme, in all places, aſwell exempt as not exempt, by their letters and other proces, to apprehend, or cauſe to be apprehended, any perſon or perſons, which they ſhall

thinke meete to be convented, and take ſuch bonds for their appearance, as any three of them ſhall preſcribe, &amp;c. or to committ them to priſon.
               They haue power to execute the premiſſes, notwithſtanding any appellation, provocation, priviledge, or exemption; any lawes, ſtatutes, proclamations, other grants, priviledges, or other ordinances, which be or may ſeeme contrary to the premiſſes, notwithſtanding.
               Vpon which parts of the ſayd Commiſſion, being ſo indefinite without limitation or reſtraynt, he noted, that if the Commiſſion ſhould be executed according to the letter thereof; the ſubjects, notwithſtanding any lawes or cuſtomes to the contrary, might be cited out of their owne Dioces, yea from the furtheſt parte of the Realme, for any cauſe, or ſuſpicion conceaved by the Commiſſioners, or any three of them, and forced to attend the Commiſſioners, where they will appoynt, in time of harveſt, or time of plague, with the danger of a mans life: as he was forced to attend many weekes in daunger of his life; they refuſing to delay the cauſe, untill the terme, upon any bayle or bond. And they may force any ſubject to appeare, at what dayes and howers any three of them ſhall appoynt, for ſuch matters ſometimes, as are more proper to be heard in other Courts.
               And although the penalties of the ſtatuts be never ſo great, as Premunire, Abiuration, forfeyture of lands &amp; goodes, whereof ſome offences are by the ſame ſtatute limitted to be tryed onely in the Kings bench, yet the party ſuſpected may be forced, by this Commiſſion, to accuſe himſelfe upon his owne oath, upon ſuch captious Interrogatories, as the witt of man can deviſe, when there is neyther accuſer, nor libell of accuſation: And that in many things

they may inflict what puniſhment any three of them ſhal thinke meete in their diſcretions, and force men to performe ſuch order as they ſhall make, by the parties bond, before any order made: and that their judgments, or decrees whatſoever, ſhould not be ſubject to any writt of Error, attaint, or appeale: and that they may deviſe meanes, at their owne diſcretion, for the triall and finding out of any the ſayd offences. Which kind of proceedinges how farr they doe differ from the common lawes of England, which is the inheritāce of the ſubjects, and what Iarres &amp; harſh tunes they make in the ſweete harmony therof, ſetled by ſo long continuance, with a moſt happy ſucceſſe, any wiſeman may ſee, without any inforcement frō him; and how much of this they doe dayly execute, he did leaue to see it.
               Only ſo much as came under his owne viewe, he ſaid, that, the laſt day of Eaſter terme, he moved at the Exchequer barre, for 20. perſons, his Clients, dwelling in Yorkeſhyre; wherof ſom, as they told him, were very poore, who were fined by the Eccleſiaſticall Cōmiſsioners for not appearing at their dayes appoynted, many of them to 30. pounds a peece, one only at ten, and all the reſt at twenty a peece, which was not ſalvo contenemento, according to the ſtatute of Magna Charta cap. 14. And one client, being an houſholder in Fleeteſtreete, named William Goulder, prayed adviſe for his hard &amp; cloſe impriſonment many dayes, with great Irons on him, by the Commiſsioners, upon ſome ſuſpition conceaved by ſome of the Commiſſioners, that ſome perſon was hid in his houſe; and was after freed without any conviction of his ſuppoſed offence. And becauſe the ſayd Nicholas Fuller did except againſt the Commiſsioners, as not competent Iudges, in their owne cauſe,

of him and of his argument, made againſt them at the Kings bench barre, they threatned to ſett 500. pounds fine on him, and to impriſon him. And when (he finding their proceeding by the oath Ex officio to vary from the Common lawes, which he had long tyme practiſed) he ſaid to them, it ſeemed to him, that he was in a new world, or other Common wealth: thereupon they threatned to impriſon him, if he ſpake one word more to the diſgrace of the Commiſsion.
               
               Wherefore he held it ſtrong, in his opinion (becauſe his Majeſties Commiſſion, which they terme High, is, by the true intent of the ſtatute, only a Commiſsion executorie, but for ſo long time onely as ſhall pleaſe the King, and is no ſetled court for continuance for ever, as they would haue it, comparing the authority thereof with the Kings bench, and preferring it aboue it) that, in all the partes and poynts aboue rehearſed, the Commiſsion is not of force in law, nor warranted by law, except ſome Act of Parliamēt doe giue it life.
               And now touching the laſt and principall parte of his diviſion, viz, that no Act of Parliament doth giue life  to the Commiſsion Eccleſiaſticall, in the parts aboue mentioned, it is to be noted, that the Commiſſion is founded only upon the ſtatute of an. 1. Eliz. cap. 1. and that this Act of an. 1. Eliz. neyther doth, nor can giue life to this Commiſſion, by any right conſtruction, in theſe partes aboue rehearſed, but contrarywiſe doth expreſly aboliſh their Iuriſdiction to impriſon ſubjectes, fyne them, and force them to accuſe themſelues, as repugnant to the Auncient Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction, which, by this Act, is reſtored to the Crowne: and he hoped to make that poynt ſo playne and apparant to all the hearers, that would attentiuely

regard it, as that they might be fully ſatisfied therin. For, beſides the Booke Caſes, which he ment to put, in that poynt, to proue his aſſertion, he ſayd, that the title in the Act of an. 1. Eliz. the preamble of the Act, and the matter preceding the preamble in that Act, and the body of that Act, which giveth power to the Commiſſioners to execute the premiſſes (by colour wherof they challenge this great power to impriſon ſubjectes etc.) doe all concurre, by their being rightly applyed, to condemne and overthrowe theſe poynts of the Commiſſion Eccleſiaſticall, before ſpoken of and rehearſed by him, as unlawfull, and unjuſt.
               The title is, an Act, reſtoring to the Crowne the auncient Iuriſdiction over the Eccleſiaſticall and ſpirituall eſtate, and aboliſhing all forren Iuriſdiction, repugnant to the ſame. What the auncient Iuriſdiction over the Eccleſiaſticall and ſpirituall eſtate is, he hath ſufficiently before declared, and proved it to be that Eccleſiaſticall juriſdiction (viz. Keyes or cenſures of the Church) which was lawfully vſed in Englād, before the ſtatute of 2. Hen. 4. the uttermoſt whereof was, to locke men out of the Church by excommunication, termed, the keyes of the Church. Which ſtatute firſt gaue power to the Ordinaries, to impriſon ſubjects, to fine them, and force thē to accuſe thēſelues by their owne oathes, which was ever hatefull to the ſubjects of England.
               And to proue plainely, that this Parliament of an. 1. Eliz. ment to aboliſh that power to impriſon ſubjectes, &amp; force them to accuſe themſelues, the matter precedent before the preamble doth fully proue; for that, in this very ſtatute of an. 1. Eliz. the law makers, as wiſe framers of a Common wealth, before they goe about to annexe the auncient right Eccleſiaſtical Iuriſdiction to the Crowne,

doe by expreſſe words, at the requeſt of the ſubjects, eſtabliſh and inact, that the ſtatute of 5. Rich: 2 c
                        •
                     p. 5 and 2. H. 4. cap. 15. (which did giue authority to the Ordinaries to impriſon, fine, and force the ſubjects to accuſe thēſelues, as aboue) and all and every branches, articles, clauſes, and ſentences conteyned in the ſayd ſeveral ſtatutes, and every of thē, ſhould, from the laſt day of that Parliament, he utterly repealed, voyd, and of none effect, any thing in the ſayd ſeverall Acts, or any of them, conteyned, or any other matter or cauſe to the contrary notwithſtanding. So as the impriſonment of the ſubjects, finyng of them, and forcing of them to accuſe themſelues, being the matters, branches, and articles of thoſe ſtatuts, howſoever they came into the power of the Clergie of England, by theſe ſtatutes or otherwiſe, being thought, by the Parliament, to be repugnant to the auncient Iuriſdiction Eccleſiaſticall (as revera they are being a temporall ſword) were repealed, and made voyd by expreſſe words of this ſtatute of anno 1. Eliz as repugnant to the auncient Spirituall Iuriſdiction.
               
               And to make the meaning of the law-makers more apparant, that they allowed not, that any offences ſhould be tried by the parties owne oath, but by witneſſes; as in the begīning of this ſtatute of an. 1. Eliz. cap. 1. it doth aboliſh the oath Ex officio, by making voyd the ſtatute of 2. H. 4. cap. 15. which firſt gaue life to that kind of proceeding; ſo in the end of the ſayd ſtatute it addeth this clauſe, And be it further inacted by the authoritie aforeſayd, that no perſon, or perſons, ſhalbe hereafter indited, or arraigned for any the offences, made, ordeyned, revived, or adiudged by this Act, unleſſe there be two ſufficient witneſſes, or more, to teſtifie and declare the ſayd offence, whereof he ſhalbe indited, etc. and the ſame witneſſes, or ſo many of thē as ſhalbe living, and within the Realme,

at the time of the arraignement of ſuch perſons ſo indited, ſhall be brought forth in perſon, face to face, before the partie ſo arraigned, and there ſhall teſtifie &amp; declare what they can, againſt the party ſo arraigned, if he require the ſame.
               
               By which words ſith it is playne, that no offence, ordeyned or revived by that ſtatute, ſhould receaue triall, but by two witneſſes brought face to face; that they mēt not to giue power, by any Commiſsion grounded upon that ſtatute, to haue the offences of the ſubjectes (which touch ſo deepe as Premunire, abiuration, and forfeiture of lands and goodes) ſhould be tried by the parties owne forced oath, againſt his will, without any witnes or accuſer, as this Commiſſion limitts; and yet it is pretended to be grounded upon this ſtatute. And therfore it were a moſt violent conſtruction, and abſurd, that the generall words in this ſtatute, viz. to execute the premiſſes according to the tenor and effect of the letters patents, ſhould reviue that by an intendment, which was, by ſo playne wordes of all the aſſemblie in Parliament, revoked and aboliſhed, as a moſt hatefull thing to the ſubjectes of England, and of which they ment to purge the Church and Eccleſiaſticall goverment. For that were to make one parte of the ſtatute contrary to the other, and to conſtrue the wordes of the law, indefinitely ſett downe, directly againſt the meaning of the law makers plainely expreſſed by wordes; which Iudges never did, nor, as he hoped, ever would doe.
               And the title and preamble of the ſtatute doe further reſtrayne the overlarge conſtruction of thoſe generall wordes, to execute the premiſſes: becauſe the premiſſes, being the auncient juriſdiction Eccleſiaſticall and ſpirituall, purged from that temporall Iuriſdiction, as aboue, is mēt to be reſtored onely over the Eccleſiaſticall and ſpirituall

eſtate, and not over all the ſubjects of the Realme; and becauſe, in the preamble, the Commiſſioners, who are to be named, are inabled, touching Eccleſiaſticall or ſpirituall Iuriſdiction only, to reforme, correct, and amend all ſuch hereſies, errors, ſchiſmes, contempts, etc: which by any ſpirituall or Eccleſiaſticall power, authoritie, or Iuriſdiction, might lawfully be reformed, and not all abuſes of the common wealth mē
                  tioned in their Commſſion, or any abuſe not proper to the Eccleſiaſticall or ſpirituall Iuriſdiction, whereof there are many named in their Commisſion, which are temporall Iuriſdictions, viz. to impriſon and fine ſubjects, and to execute lawes upon thē; for that the ſpirituall law ſhould not meddle with that, for which there was remedye by common law, as is 22. Edw. 4. fol. 20. and the ſtatute of 24. Edw. 1. cap: 1.
               
               And to proue, that the titles and preambles of other ſtatutes doe many times, in conſtruction of ſtatutes, reſtrayne the generall words of the ſame ſtatuts following, he put the caſe upon the ſtatute of perjurie, anno. 5. Eliz. where the wordes of the ſtatute are, that every perſon and perſons who shall commit voluntarie and corrupt periurie, shall forfeit twentie poundes. And becauſe the preamble and matter precedent touched witneſſes only, therefore that penaltie is reſtreyned, by conſtruction, to charge witneſſes onely therwith, and not ſuch perſons as ſhall commit voluntary and corrupt periurie, in their owne caſes. And ſo upon the ſtatute of 7. Edward. 6. againſt Receivers, Bayliffs, etc. although the wordes of that ſtatute extend generally, to lay a penaltie of 6. ſhillings 8. pence for every peny that receivours ſhall take unlawfully; yet becauſe the preamble of that ſtatute touched only the Kings officers, It is, in conſtruction, reſtrayned to take force againſt the

Kinges officers onely, and againſt none other receivers, or bayliffes.
               And to conclude this poynt of the expoſition of the wordes of the ſtatute, he did demaund, why the expoſition and conſtruction of all ſtatutes is left to the Iudges of the law, but for this cauſe, for that they are, and alwayes haue been thought the moſt carefull, iudicious, and jelous preſervers of the lawes of England? And is it not apparant, that, to uphold the right of the lawes of England, the Iudges in ages paſt haue adviſedly conſtrued ſome wordes of divers ſtatutes contrary to the common ſence of the words of the ſtatute, to uphold the meaning of the common lawes of the Realme? as in the ſtatute of 25. Ed. 3. where it is ſayd, that, non tenure of parcell ſhall abate the writt but for parcell; yet if by the writt an entier manour be demaunded, non tenure of parcell ſhall abate the whole writt. And where, by the ſtatute of Marlbridg ca. 4. it is prohibited, that no diſtreſſe ſhalbe driven out of the County where it is taken, yet, if one manour extend into two Counties, there the diſtreſſe may be drivē from one County into another Countie. And, upon the ſtatute of Prerogatiue, which toucheth the King, although the wordes be generall, that the King ſhall haue the cuſtodie of all the landes of his tenaunt where parte is holden in Capite, yet if part of the landes of his tenaunt doe deſcend to ſeverall heyres, on the parte of the Father, and on the parte of the Mother, there the King ſhall not haue all the landes of his tenaunt, during the minoritie of the heire; for that, in all these Caſes, the great regard of the rule and right of the common lawes doth controll the generall or common ſence of the wordes of thoſe ſtatutes.
               And why then ſhould this ſtatute receiue conſtruction,

by the Iudges of the law, contrary to the rule of all other ſtatutes, to this effect, that by in intendment gathered out of the generall wordes of the Act, according to the tenor of the ſay
                        •
                      letters Pa
                        •
                     ents, there might be erected, in this common wealth of England, a courſe of an arbitrarie governement at the diſcretion of the Commiſſioners, directly contrary to the happie long continued goverment and courſe of the common lawes of the Realme, and directly contrary to Magna Charta: which if the ſtatute of 24. Edw. 3. did ſo highly regard, as to make voyd Acts of Parliament contrary to the ſame, it would, a fortiori, make voyd all conſtruction of ſtatuts contrary to Magna Charta, which haue no expreſſe wordes, but an intendement or conſtruction of words, with much violence to be wreſted to that end. And for ſuch as would make ſuch conſtruction of the ſtatute, as that whatſoever ſhould be conteyned in the letters Pattents ſhould be as a law; he would haue them remember, that the King may make new letters Patents for theſe matters (Eccleſiaſticall cauſes every day altering the ſame in the penalties and manner of proceeding) and that, if the letter of the ſtatute ſhould be puruſed, the King may change the Commiſſioners every day, and make any perſons Commiſſioners, being naturall borne ſubjectes to the King, although not borne in England: which were againſt the meaning of the Act; which meaning of the Act is the life of the Act, and not the letter of the Act.
               And, beſides thoſe former errors of the Commiſſion before remembred, he ſayd, that he did not ſee, how, by colour of the ſtatute of 1. Eliz. which gaue power to the Commiſſioners to execute the premiſſes conteyned in that Act, they ſhould inlarge their Patent to enquire of offences

cōtrary to other ſtatuts, made thirtie or fortie yeares, and more, after an. 1. Eliz. which then were not dreamed of, nor meant to be any part of the premiſſes conteyned in the ſayd ſtatute of anno. 1. Eliz. and of other civill and temporall thinges, for which if the Eccleſiaſticall court had held plea, a prohibition did lye at the common law, according to the ſtatute of 24. Edw. 1. cap: 1. and 22. Ed. 4. fol 20. and in 13. Hen. 7: fol: 39. Brooke and Fitzh. fol. 43. 22. Hen. 8. becauſe, for the ſame thinges, redreſſe may be had at the common lawes: and in 7. Hen. 8. fol. 181. the Biſhops of the Convocation houſe, for medling againſt Doctor Standiſh for a temporall cauſe by him diſputed before the LL. of the Councell, were adiudged, by all the Iudges, to be in danger of Premunire. But it wilbe objected, that uſe is the beſt expoſitor of the ſtatute: and then the continuance of this Commiſſion, ſince the ſtatute of 1. Eliz. being aboue 40. yeares, will prevaile much; to which he anſwered, that long uſe, in a ſetled court, maketh it the law of the court; and the iudgments in one Court are not examinable in every other Court, or in any, but in the proper Court, by writt of error, falſe iudgement, or appeale: vnles the inferior Court meddle with that which is not within their power; and then in many caſes their iudgment is coram non Iudice, and ſo voyd.
               But this Eccleſiaſticall Commiſſion is but a Commiſsion executorie, by the intent of the ſtatute of 1. Eliz. to continue ſo long as ſhould pleaſe the Queene, or King, &amp; no ſetled Court: and was meāt at the firſt (as he thought) to haue continuance for a ſhort time, to ſtrengthen the authoritie of the Biſhops, againſt whoſe Ordination and inſtallmēt the Papiſts did at the firſt except. In which caſes of things done by Cōmiſſions, whatſoever the Cōmiſſioners doe, it is examinable in every Court where it ſhall

come in queſtion, at any time after; whether that they haue purſued their Cōmiſſion or authority, in due forme or no. For their Decrees and ſentences are not pleadable in law, as Iudgments in Courts of Record are: and the many yeares uſe of the Commiſſioners, eſpecially being Eccleſisſticall men for the moſt parte, who know not the lawes of the Realme, will giue no enforcement to their proceeding, if it be contrary to law.
               But as in this Commiſſion (touching cauſes of Premunire, Abiuration, and other Caſes where the forfeiture of landes and goods doe enſue) the Commiſſioners Eccleſiaſticall ſay, they uſe not in theſe caſes to force any ſubject to accuſe themſelues, although the words of their Commiſſion doe extend ſo farr; becauſe they ſee it apparantly contrary to law and right: ſo the Iudges may ſay the like, that, in other caſes of leſſe penaltie (to their knowledge) untill of late yeares, the Commisſioners uſed not either to force any to accuſe themſelues, or to impriſon them for refuſing ſo to doe. And he did further anſwer, according to the learning and difference which is taken in 44. Edw: 3. fol: 17. that albeit the allowance in Oier of ſome Commſſion may be of great force to giue ſtrength unto the ſame Commiſſion, yet the allowance, or toleration in ſome other Court of ſuch Commisſions many times (if it after appeare to be contrary to law) bindeth neither the right of the King, nor ſubjects, but that the Iudges of the law may judge thereof according to law.
               Vpon all which matters he did conclude, that although the Commisſion be of force to execute the auncient Iuriſdiction over the Eccleſiaſticall and ſpirituall eſtate; yet becauſe this Commisſion, and the proceedings of the Commisſioners, did much vary from the courſe of

                     〈1 page missing〉
                  
                  
It is, in conſtruction, reſtrayned to take force againſt the the ould Common lawes of England, expreſſed in the ſtatute of 42. Edw: 3. cap. 3. and from the auncient Iuriſdiction Eccleſiaſticall; for that no pretended cuſtome, againſt thoſe ſtatutes which prohibite ſuch kind of proceeding, can be of force; and eſpecially for that the Act of Parliament of 1. Eliz. did not giue life or ſtrength to the ſayd Commisſion, in thoſe parts ſo varying, but the contrary: therefore he did hold the proceeding of the Eccleſiaſticall Commisſioners againſt the ſubjectes, by force of the ſayd Commisſion, in theſe poyntes, to be voyd, and erroneous, according to the wordes of the ſayd ſtatute 42. Edw. 3. and did humblie pray, that his Clients may be diſcharged from their Impriſonment, and the ſubjects freed from ſuch erroneous proceedings, too too heavie and burdenſome to them.
               FINIS.
            
         
      
      
         
            
               Lev. 19.15.
               Ye ſhall not doe uniuſtly in iudgment. Thou ſhalt not favor the perſon of the poore, nor honor the perſon of the mightie; but thou ſhalt iudge thy neighbour iuſtly.
            
            
               Deut. 1.17.
               Ye ſhall haue no reſpect of perſon in iudgment, but ſhall heare the ſmall, as well as the great: ye ſhall not feare the face of man; for the iudgment is Gods.
            
            
         
      
   

