
   
      
         
            An answer to VVithers motto Without a frontispice. Wherein, Nec habeo, nec careo, nec curo, are neither approued, nor confuted: but modestly controuled, or qualified.
            T. G., Esquire.
         
         
            
               1625
            
         
         Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-07 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01389
            STC 11509
            ESTC S102784
            99838546
            99838546
            2928
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01389)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2928)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1024:06)
         
         
            
               
                  An answer to VVithers motto Without a frontispice. Wherein, Nec habeo, nec careo, nec curo, are neither approued, nor confuted: but modestly controuled, or qualified.
                  T. G., Esquire.
                  Gainsford, Thomas, d. 1624?
               
               [92] p.   
               
                  Printed by Iohn Lichfield, and William Turner,
                  Oxford :
                  1625.
               
               
                  Signed on A4v: T.G. Esquire, i.e. Thomas Gainsford?.
                  A reply to: Wither, George.  Withers motto.
                  In verse.
                  Signatures: A-F (-F7,8).
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Wither, George, 1588-1667. --  Withers motto.
            
         
      
      
         
            2003-03
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-04
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-05
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2003-05
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-06
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            AN
ANSWER
TO
VVITHERS
MOTTO.
            
               Without a Frontispice.
WHEREIN,
Nec HABEO, Nec CAREO, Nec CVRO,
are neither approued, nor confuted:
but modestly controuled,
or qualified.
            
               QVAESTIO.
               —Quid dignum tanto feret hic promissor hiatu?
            
            
               RESPONSIO.
               —Sic invat indulgere fugacibus horis.
            
            OXFORD,
Printed by IOHN LICHFIELD, and
WILLIAM TVRNER. 1625.
         
         
            
            
            The Booke to the Reader.
            WEll may you muse why I came
no sooner to light, but lay obscure
so long; vnderstand therefore
that I haue in time past sought to
come vnder the presse, to shew my selfe
to publike view, but by Mr. Wither's
meanes, who sought to smoother mee in
my birth, haue lyen sometime hid, but
now hauing got strength to come forth
to declare my selfe to the world, I leaue
thee to censure the rest.
         
         
            
            Virgilius de litera Pythagorea.
            LItera Pythagorae discrimine secta bicorni
            Humanae vitae speciem praeferre videtur.
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
               
            
            Nam via virtutis dextrum petit ardua callem,
            Difficilem
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                aditum primū spectantibus offert,
            Sed requiem praebet fessis in vertice summo:
            Molle ostendat iter via lata, sed vltima meta
            Praecipitat captos, voluit
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                per ardua saxa:
            Quisquis enim duros casus virtutis amore
            Vicerit, ille sibi laudem
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                decus
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                parabit:
            At quidedsiam, luxum
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                sequetur inertem,
            Dum fugit oppositos incauta mente labores,
            Turpis inops
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                simul miserabile transiget aevum.
         
         
            
            To Master Wither himselfe.
            
               MAster Wither; When I first
tooke vp your Booke to
reade, (which I confesse I
did not out of curiositie,
Criticisme, or any desire to
bee your Antagonist) I
thought to make the same
vse of it for Collections and
obseruations, as I haue accustomed out of other
mens endeauours: but when I found a certaine
confusion in the same, besides many repetitions, I
compared it to Protogenes pencill, that throwne
away in a rage, effected that worke, which with
all his cunning hee knew not how to contriue;
and so in my conscience, you writ this in
anger,
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                (I will not say in fury) and fortune hath
giuen way to your good spirit, which though
(if men were as angry as your selfe) might be called
presumption, yet out of iudgment consonant to

to you: non recte dixisti, nec habeo, nec careo, nec
curo: How I proued that, it is so many yeares agoe,
I cannot tell: but how I shall proue yours, it is
so few dayes agoe, since I attempted it, that I can
almost say it without booke: yet because a mans
memory may faile, I haue here sent it you written,
if not p
                  •
               inted: now if the worst come, we shall doe
no worse then Lawyers, who fall out with one another
at the Barre, and are friends when they meete
at the Temple Hall at dinner: For I can assure
you, I pray that your Muse may haue a Plautus
plaudite,—and though I am so vnfortunate a man
in these compositions, that I may stil exclaime, Nemesis
in tergo—, yet doth my hart leape at the thriuings
of other men, and I wish you, the reward of
your worth, remaining to you, to others, to my
selfe, to all, honest:-
            T. G. Esquire.
         
         
            
            To the Reader.
            
               
                  REader- And you marke
it, all men are more afraide
of you then of thunders:
For a Garland wreathed about
the head of Lawrell,
is a preseruatiue against
lightning: but there was
neuer any Antidotle for the
Aconite of a malitious tongue, except you could doe
as Iuvenall sayes (and yet corrupt times haue preuented
that to) but you shall haue it:
            Vivendum est recte,Satyr.
                     •
                  
                cum propter plurima, tum his
Praecipuè causis, vt linguas mancipiorum
Contemnas: nam lingua mali pars pessima serui:
and therefore there is a kinde of inclination vsed
toward you with many facetious attributes, or Epithetons
of gentle, courteous, iudicious, learned, noble,
worthy, and such like; all which I disclaime,
               
onely I desire you to be honest, which I doe both for
your selfe, and my selfe. For your selfe, that you may
haue the reward of an immaculate soule: for my
selfe, that if you doe me no good, I hope you will doe
me no harme.
            —Heere I beleeue you will not finde such mirth as
you expect, for there is no beare-baiting toward,
where the boyes clap their hands to set the dogges
together: but a fiery zeale against sinne, Vanity,
and the corruption of mens manners, where in
if any of you bee transported with the vulgar
multit
                  •
               de, you neede no other punishment then
your owne confusions, and the various changes of a
ridiculous violence: if impostured with the Syrens
song of priuate respects, except you tye your selues
to the mast of Religion and Piety,
                  
                     •
                  ct and 
                     •
                  om
                  
                     •
                  ions 
                     •
                  ed so 
                     
                        •
                     irces.
                be sure to be transhapt
into Lyons, Beares, Wolues, Tigers, Goates, and
what not:—if ouer-heated with the fauour of
Princes, take heed of catching colde, according to the
Italian prouerbe-non discoprir animalato, quando
suda: For enuy and malice haue snatching handes
to pull away the mantle of your greatnesse, and
then your deformity will quickely appeare,—if resolute,
out of a couetous ambition to make money
your guide, whereby at last you may come to places of
honour and office (which indeed is a kinde of Cannon

shot through a stand of Pikes) take heede of ouercharging
your selues, lest like some crased new cast
peece in the tryall and discharging, you flie in pieces.—
If subiect to a womans imperiousnesse, or flattered
by her wantonnesse, take heed of the forbidden
fruit, shee will bring it, praise it, deceiue you, and
make you eat it:—If catched in the net of the
world,Epi
                     ••
                   defor
                     •
                   Dem
                     ••
                  derid
                     ••
                   Hera
                     ••
                  deflet
                     •
                  
                and so resolued against singularity, or other
nicke-name, by being religious: Remember the Philosophers
banquet, where Epicte
                     •
                  us put a Coxcombe
vpon the Globe of the world, and the strange prohibitions
in the word of truth, where the world and
the fashions of the same are no more reputed of then
durt and drosse, or any vilder thing, which must be
purged by fier: If any thing else diuert you to transpasse
the limits of your owne Spheres and Orbes,
take heede of prouing Meteors and Exhalations,
whereby you will quickely vanish to nothing; and so I
leaue you to the faire regard of your selues, for if you
be honest, you will loue vertue for vertues sake, and
wipe away all aspersions with a gentle hand, which
may bee laide vpon mans infirmities:—if otherwise;
neither vice nor vertues will serue your
turnes, but as your owne humours, make them savery
to your pallats, wherein because I am no Empiricke
               
of this kinde, I pray you be your owne Phisitians,
and make the trials your selues: for I
that neuer was a friend to my selfe, am not
worthy to be yours so much as in particular
application.
            T. G. Esquire.
         
      
      
         
            
            THE INTRODVCTION.
            VVHat's here? what's here? A peremptory man?
            That cares not who his books &amp; labors scan:
            But if men storme, will make the Muses storme,
            With thundring tempests to procure more harme:
            As if the power's Diuine were at his becke,
            Inferior fury for to countercheke;
            Much like Maedeas charmes,Flecte neque
                     ••
                   supero
                     •
                   cheron
                     •
                   moueb
                     •
                  
                who then durst tell
            If heauen did faile, she would command all Hell.
            —Why man? what needs this quoile? fret not thy soule
            About thy free-borne lines? who doth controule
            Thy worthy labours? or traduce thy name?
            Or who befooles themselues at thy faire fame
            To fume, or knit the brow?—Nay? who will vexe
            Their conscience, of any age or sexe,
            About thy poore 
                  ••
               uectiues, when thy haue
            That sacred Word, which doth all sinne depraue,
            Nor Prince, nor Pesant sparing in their kinde,
            Nor rich, nor poore, nor proud, nor humbled minde,
            Nor Atheist, Hypocrite, nor any other
            That will their sinnes, or hide, or falsely smother
            From those all-seeing eyes, which vengeance take
            Vpon delinquents, who a sport can make
            
               
At Gods high Iustice, or sweet Mercy: when
            He opens either treasure-house to men:
            —Now if the Gospell tell the rich man thus,
            He that beleeues no Scripture,
               6. 29 would discusse
            Vpon the Prophets: or the holy writ
            Deride, deny, or in some franticke fit,
            Make doubt of either, sure will ne're beleeue
            One raised from the dead, or seeme to greeue,
            Be his discourse more harsh then hellish groanes
            Or Hecats charmes, breaking the marble stones:
            —Then dost thinke thou they care for thy best 
                  •
               imes,
            Which onely ayme at foule enormous crimes
            Of present sway, or once will startled be,
            Although they doe thy heart transparent see:
            What dost thou then of resolution tell,
            Of Libels, Satyres?— Doe thou ne're so well
            To scourge the Ages villany, they say
            It is their work to sinne, to sport, to play:
            —But when thou talkest of making the world mad
            
            They laugh and wonder,
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                whence that terme is had:
            As for the guilty times, that all torment,
            Why should mens fashions so thee discontent?
            Was it not thus when that the Prophets saw
            The world on mischiefe set, did they not draw
            In seuerall models, that deformed face,
            Which vice look't out with all without disgrace?
            —One doth the Women for apparell chide,
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
               
            
            Another great men, for great cost deride:
            Another tels the Iudge of taking fees,
            Another his false seruant ouer-sees,
            
               
Another checks the Swaine for selling Corne,Amos 
                     •
                  
               
            
            And grieues the poore man is so ouer-borne:
            Another talks of Vsury and wrong,Ezek. 
                     •
                  
               
            
            Another to the Sabboth doth belong,Isai. 58.
            
            Another dares doe more, then thou dare doe,
            Reuiles the pompous Priests,
               Ezec. 3. adding thereto
            Their riots, vomits, lies and filthinesse,Hosh. 4.
            
            Their auarice,Mal. 1. 1 their lust and greedinesse:
            Yea,Mal. 1. 1 in the end thou there shalt this out finde,
            Their Orizons came not at all behinde
            Their fowlest sinnes:—For Priest and people then
            Did God deceiue,Mal. 2. as well as simple men
            By offering the leane beasts, selling the best,
            And yet supposing to sit downe in rest:
            —Thus was it full two thousand yeare agoe,
            Yet now forsooth you would not haue it so,
            Nor will you be a slaue to times, or sinne:
            But call them Criticks, who dare once begin
            To censure thy faire Muse, or taxe thy pen
            As if thou could'st doe more then other men,
            For to diuert vs from outragiousnesse:
            
               Alas? alas? though that I should confesse
            Thy worth were great, and that thou hadst a charme
            For that foule Gorgons head:—It would thee harme,
            Either to vexe thy soule,- thou couldst not speed,
            Or fret thee more to laugh at thee indeed:
            —As for thy scorning of the poore and base?
            
            They would out-raile thee to thy very face.
            
               
As for the better sort in honors seare?
            They doe thy betters in this sort intreat,
            With foole or mad-man, if they once transcend
            Their callings to finde fault: and in the end
            They turne thee off with busie-bodies name,
            Vsing these speeches Vertue to defame:-
            —A poore mans tale's soone told, who low doth lie
            Still enuies others that doe sit on high,
            Come, giue him liuing; he will hold his tongue,
            And terme that right, which now he counteth wrong:
            The Tyrants hand, that rais'de him vp shall be
            The gentle hand of fairest charity:-
            The villaines tongue, that fumbles in his throat
            Shall then a diapason make his note,
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
               
            
            Yea all transhap't will honour worke that man,
            Who in his poore estate doth curse and ban:
            With such like speeches are good men put off,
            And many tawnts endure, with vilder scoffe:
            —Then talke not of a Iaile, or wrongs of State,
            
            When our owne hands doe ope foule mischiefes gate,
            When we presume to tell the rest of sinne,
            And are our selues as faulty still therein,
                  
                     ••
                  o laedi
                  
                     •
                  isi a 
                     •
                  .
            
            When priuate ends affect vs with delight,
            Then we complaine of other mens despight:
            
               Come, come; It may be, he that writeth this
            Can tell the world, what a close prison is,
            And iustly doth himselfe thus farre consute,
            He seldome thriues that doth with Lords dispute:
            
               
Whom Princes will haue wise, are wise indeed,
            And mongst the Polliticks, it is agreed,
            They that do specious attributes transferre;
            And yet find fault with gouernment, may erre:
            Therefore be ruled by me, threaten no more,
            That either you haue forraine news good store,
            Or could from rumour tell ys of such things,
            As vnto Europe this disturbance brings:
            But cause it may offend or France or Spaine,
            
            You leaue it of, and come to vs againe,
            With Furies tyed in chaires, and whips of steele
            As though Briareus hands could turne the wheele
            Of Fortune quite about: and your fierce straines,
            
            Well season'd could controule, or tame the braines
            Of franticke men: Oh that it were your fate
            To worke conuersion euen quite through the state:
            As for your dogs; that dare on Monsters flie,
            By baiting Buls and beares, the boldest dye.
            Therefore desist, and let your temprature
            The sweet content which we expect, procure.
            —Be better pleas'd, who spits against the winde
            Shall soone his face all to be smeered finde,
            And he that will assume more then his owne,
            Shall either for presumptuous be knowne,
            Or an intruder: then thanke God for this,
            Thou hast a great deale more then common is:
            But giue no milke with a repining hand,
            Nor looke thou spill it, as it there doth stand,
         
         
            
            
            AN ANSWER TO WITHER'S
NEC HABEO.
            
               —HEre you begin with a calme humbled minde,
               As if all Vaunting you were farre behinde,
               Confessing such defects, as make men see,
               In weake infirmities how poore they be.
               
                  —You haue no grace, but by infused power,
               
               No strentgh at all to write another hower,
               
               No f
                     •
                  ee-borne goodnesse, nor a cleansing hand
               To wipe away corruptions of the land,
               Or purge your sinnes by your owne purity:
               Yet you confesse you haue a charity
               With sweeter currents of an honest minde
               To beare with some, and be to others kinde:
               Nay? Ile goe further, if the truth were known,
               You somethings haue, which I doe call your own,
               
                  Affection, passion, ing
                        •
                     ny, delight,
               Feare, sadnesse, ioy: For sure you are not quite
               Exempt from those things with which man was borne,
               Though age in time youths franticknesse doth scorue,
               But more then this aboue the rest you know
               From iudgement to condemne the world, that so
               
                  
We may the passages of goodnesse learne,
               And Vice and Vertue different discerne,
               And can all this be done? except you had
               Those faculties, which make the heart full glad.
               —Then you confesse a power to doe ill,
               And many times a peruerse haire-brain'd will
               To ouer-beare the motiues of your soule,
               Whereby your frailties doe the rest controule,
               Of such 
                     •
                  le not dispute; It is a point
               Farre from my reach, and may full soone disioint
               The frame I would erect. For in each state
               
                  Free-will confusion suffers and debate;
               —But now take heed: if in this humbled sceane
               You goe not farre beyond the golden meane,
               Catching at glory, as you wish to thriue,
               Or for some higher reputation striue,
               O
                     •
                   hope to match your ment with reward,
               As other men your labours doe regard,
               Or worke for priuate ends: then sure you haue
               
               
                  Some portion in the world, and know to saue
               Your selfe from vexing wants, or foule annoy,
               And so on earth possesse, wherein you ioy.—
               
                  —You haue no Lordships, nor high reaching Piler,
               
               Nor mocking structures, nor deceitfull wiles,
               Nor large demeanes, nor titular renowne,
               Nor any hope which may your vertue crowne
               With place of honour:—Yet you haue a minde
               To haue all those, and doe corruption finde
               In stranger wishes, that you had more liuing:
               Then to depend on any others giuing.
               
                  
For though Concupiscence be writ a sin,
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
               
               Yet either men may so the world begin
               To come to seeled houses in the end,
               By their owne industrie, or haue a friend
               Bestow a Leg
                     •
                  cie, or natiue right
               May them establish
                     •
                  n some formall might,
               Or from the custome of each mor
                     •
                  ll nation
               The Prince may men enrich with some donation,
               Wherein vntouch't, vnfoild, the soule may see,
               How she may somethings haue, and yet be free:-
               —Nay more; if wealth increase, it lawfull is
               (So in the same we practice nought amisse)
               To purchase land, or office, as we finde
               The Patriackes remembred in this kinde:
               Yea, the wise man pleades, as I doe conceiue,
               Better it is to giue, then to receiue,
               Which cannot well be done, except our store
               Augmented be more then it was before:
               Oh say not then; you haue none of these things,
               If you would haue them; For a w
                     •
                  sh so stings
               The conscience, that as swelling blisters rise
               Vpon the face to blemish both our eies:
               So sinnes creepe on vs, by our foule desires,
               And sends in fuell to augment the fires,
               Which by degrees actiue imployment make,
               Vntill to custome we our selues betake,
               —As for the spirits freedome, which you boast,
               Take heed you reckon not without your hoast.
               For mischiefe lies like rocks in seas vnseene,
               Splitting the greatest ships that come betweene:
               
                  
Yea, the proud head which lifts it selfe on high
               Through small displeasure doth disgraced dye:
               But sure afflicting wants distract vs more,
               Then our owne patience can endure: therefore
               Let none presume to say, they can abide
               In pouerty, when all the world beside
               Abounds in wealth: For Dauid bids vs pray
               Gainst these extreames; Oh doe not then say na
                     •
                  ,
               For as the rich, the poore man he doth sin,
               And with more terrour frets himselfe therein.
               
                  —You haue no suites in Law, nor need once sweat
               After your plodding Councellor to treat
               Of bils, procurements, titles, and such like,
               Which in discussing much amazement strike;
               This sure is want of meanes,
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                   or wealth, or state,
               Or that on earth you are not fortunate
               But from this want you haue a busie minde
               To tamper with the Courtes some fault to finde,
               Checking the pride, or auarice of men,
               Laughing at follies and corruptions, when
               Greatnesse doth ouer-sway the meaner side,
               Or quicker wits simplicity deride,
               Or prolongations do a cause deferre,
               Or groser sinnes traduce men, that so erre:
               Thus we doe smile when others faults are knowne,
               Yet cast vp worser recknings of our owne,
               The soule we free from shifts, the tongue from tales
               Defacing right, contriuing cunning sales,
               And if we can escape the Law in sinning,
               We then are safe, when from the first beginning
               
                  
We pride of heart possesse, with enuy swell,
               Repine at others, liuing passing well,
               Proue factious in our thoughts, striue with our wits,
               Till they burst out into some madding fits
               Against good order of the gouernment,
               And so we run away in meriment,
               That we haue hit it home: but what say they
               That would not so their modestie betray,
               Either we haue some singular conceit,
               Bewitching vs with holinesse deceit,
               Or itching eares to heare each Sirens song
               Of things, which no way do to vs belong:
               Or itching h
                     •
                  nds to reach the fruit on high,
               Vntill the Dragon doe it vs denie:
               Or itching feet to gad, where none should goe
               That know not how themselues for to bestow:
               Or itching hearts forbidden things that craue:
               Thus wise men see, that still we somethings haue.
               
                  —You haue no foppish tricks, nor apish to
                     •
                  es
               Nor complementall congees fit for boyes,
               And not reposed men:—You say 'tis pittie,
               That either trauellers of Court, or Citie
               Bring home such follies out of France or Spaine,
               
               Or Italy: and yet you doe againe
               Commend good manners, &amp; good fashions to,
               Well I perceiue we shall haue much adoe
               To please you in these things:▪But now take heed
               The same impostume doe not in you breed,
               That either you dissemble must this guise,
               Or forced be with men to temporise;
               
                  
Why; why good Sir: if thou dost this at all;
               Whom canst thou praise, or so right worthy call;
               Or whom canst thou traduce for such extreames,
               But others glowing heates haue the like beames;
               As for the heart, descrie it if you can,
               It hath and will deceiue an honest man.—
               —But now I see you haue a tricke in this
               To tell vs,
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                   what's in Poesie amisse,
               Because you would haue ignorants to know,
               How variously a learned man may grow
               Deformed in his wits:—But if againe
               I tell you when necessities constraine;
               We are excus'd; what needs this partiall vaunting
               Of scorne or 
                     •
                  lattery, we still are graunting
               The selfe-same thing: that vertue should not make
               A false account, but patiently betake
               Her selfe to her owne Items, whether poore
               Or rich she liue: yet men from dore to dore
               Are loth to beg, yet by your rule they must,
               If to reward of vertue they doe trust:—
               Then cease a while, and let me heere conclude,
               That gaines and profit doe the best delude:
               
                  —You haue no partialitie, nor loue
               That man, which must your obseruation moue,
               From his owne greatnesse, or augment your scorne
               As in the world neglected, and forlorne
               He lies: but meane goodnesse for to respect,
               Who e're the same condemne, or yet neglect.
               
                  —You haue no soothing humour to make good
               The iests of men, or warme them in their blood,
               
                  
When they would haue applauses: but you take
               One euen course, and all for vertues sake▪—
               
                  
                     •
                  ay, if he gentrie boast you would pull downe
               That ostentation with an angrie frowne,
               Except his actions doe proportion keep
               With their great fame, which in their graues doe sleep—
               —What greater partiality can be
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
               
               Then this wherein you so much disagree
               With common sense, as though one selfe-same st
                     •
                  ne
               Obscured in base lead, or horne were one
               With that, which is embellished by Art,
               
                  
                     •
                  et out in gold, as workman plaies his part,
               By adding lustre to the same:—So men
               
                  
                     •
                  oe grace their natiue vertues farre more, when
               They noble are, or comelie to the eie.
               —Thus in the Sunne we doe a glorie spie,
               When he doth shew his fullest radiance,
               
                  
                     •
                  nd not when through a cloud we see him glan
                     ••
                  ,
               —As for the rest, I know not what you call
               Applauding of great men, but this is all
               We shoot at her, for to augment our state,
               And higher rise, though it be nere so late;—
               How shall such ones then be fairelie intreated,
               
                  
                     •
                  hat are alreadie so transcendent seated?
               
                  
                     •
                  r would you be transported in this kinde,
               Not to affoord respect, although you finde
               
                  
                     •
                  ome things to crosse your humours, Cyni
                        •
                     ke fits;
               
                  
                     •
                  re therefore men the worse for our fond wits?
               —Now come to dignitie, and outward show?
               You faine would men by their owne actions know,
               
                  
And for because you thinke it ill or well,
               You would a lesson to their Lordships tell,
               As though you had some workeman been of old
               In honours Pallace; as though times doe hold
               One selfe-same course, and not admit of change
               Euen in mens manners, when a Countrey grange
               Doth from her owners wealth scorne base to lie,
               But Pallace-like her Turrets reares vp high:
               What thinke you then? dare not men goe astray,
               Because you looke at high designes, a way
               Which must confine them to the glorious deeds
               Of Dauids Worthies: this prescription breeds
               Such grudging mongst them all,All tim
                        •
                     s 
                        •
                     re not for 
                        •
                     mployment. and to say truth
               We haue no such imployment for our youth,
               And if we had, rewards are not so rife,
               Therefore doe Lords act out another life
               Of peace and plenty, welcomming with all
               The Vices which attend the same, and call
               Them what you will, this phrase I vse
               (Not that I would impiety excuse)
               It is the times fault, and the fruit of ease
               That meaner men then Lords themselues doe please
               With barren pleasure,
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                   gaming, lust, and smoake,
               Which blacks their braines, as they their senses choa
                     •
                  
               
               Swelling their bodies with ranke humours vp,
               As they carowse of Bacchus wanton cup,
               To fill their vaines with strange lasciuious blood,
               Working at last no other end or good
               Then soule diseases: For as hot ranke ground
               
                  
Doth ouer-choake the corne with ranker weeds:
               So in mens bodies such corruption breeds
               (For want of martiall exercise) that harme
               Which neither Physicke, nor Elixars charme:
               Ile name no more, but let them 
                     •
                  ere alone,
               Nor g
                     •
                  ieue not you, or make so great a moane
               For their vnworthinesse: because the Law
               (Which keepes the lauishnes of tongues in aw)
               Intends that Princes fauours doe bestow,
               For that in peace men doe more vertuous grow,
               And though thou fret, others doe yeeld a reason,
               When any great offender out of season
               Hath life afforded: this they learne of God,
               Who out of mercy spares, or sends a rod,
               And as God from mens questions doth surmount:
               So Princes of their actions yeeld no count:—
               
                  —You haue no friends, but such, as shall be so
               Endeer'd at all times, whether weale or woe,
               Nor doe you prise mens loues by out-ward state,
               Whether afflicted, or made fortunate:
               Nor doe you care for such, as meane to loue
               For their own ends.—How friends may be forsake Whence comes it, that you moue
               Such Paradoxes? what alwayes alike?
               The Smith you see doth not his iron strike
               When it is cold—Nor can the Sunne preuent
               The Moones Ecclipse:—Therefore be thou content
               To looke at friendship, as it lookes on thee
               With Vertues raies: for if thou doe agree
               To Passion, it will make thee passionate,
               
               And with encombrances confound thy state.
               
                  
—But if againe thou wilt be so precise,
               All friendship vnder vertue to comprise,
               And so condemne distinction by a name,
               Which lookes not after char
                     ••
                  ie, but fame;
               Which shuts out▪nature, and would seeme diuine
               Then looke about for seuerall Sunnes to shine,
               Or else goe from the earth. For if thou liue,
               Thou must obserue some methode, and so giue
               Reason her due, and not contented be
               With euerie friend, 'cause he was friend to thee.
               —For in plaine tearmes, say that he slacke his hand,
               Doest not thou slacke thy loue? Say that he stand
               A Leper in thy sight, wilt thou imbrace
               Or cling vnto the kisses of his face?
               Say that Religion kept him once in awe,
               Wilt thou keepe still to him against the Law?
               Say that he froward proue with griefe, or age,
               And turne sweet blessings into furious rage;
               What still thy friend?—Sure though thou didst so say,
               I know thou knowest the safe, and better way,
               Not that I would haue honest men be left
               In their extreames, when they are quite bereft
               Of worldlie succour; but to be content
               If vicious life bring vices punishment.
               —As for reuealing secrets, or discouer
               The doting frenzie of a sodden louer;
               I well beleeue, thou hast no minde to doe it,
               Except a riualship may put thee to it,
               Or some crosse courtship to preuent a sonne,
               Or other chance hindring what's well begunne.
               
                  
But say thou come to argue with faire reason,
               What wilt thou do about concealing treason?
               Or other terrours, shaming thee to be
               A secret friend to such necessitie.
               —You haue no d
                     •
                  ting humour, loue sicke vai
                     •
                  e,
               To follow that, which runnes away amaine,
               Nay you doe scorne a mela
                        •
                      cholly sit,
               Or angry passion, to be mou'd with it;
               As though you could confine infirmitie
               Within the compasse of sweet modestie;
               And trust your owne strength in these sinfull daies
               To wrestle with corrupt on, which alwaies
               Hath fon'd your betters?—Nay you haue no cause,
               No priuate cause against the publike lawes,
               No enu
                     •
                  e, malice, or a wretched minde
               To be distasting, froward, or vnkinde
               Through filthie luc
                     •
                  e, and abortiue gaine,
               Which the faire liues of greater men doe staine.
               —And yet you know that God hath thus proclaim'd,
               These be the latter times for sinne defam'd:
               And yet your Satyres haue you famous made
               For speaking freelie against euerie trade;
               And scourging vanitie, though great ones striue
               By power, by right, by wrong, to make it thriue:
               And yet you know, because you were so hardie
               To passe your bounds, the State did take you tardie.
               
                  —You haue no minde aduancement to intreat
               For your admission into honours seat,
               Nor with a Fauourite your state to change,
               Though nere so fortunate.—Why this is strange;
               
                  
Say that the wise sit wringing of her hands,
               Because she wants the iointure of her lands,
               The children cry for bread, and in the durt
               Trot bare foot by her side, or other hurt
               Affront thee; be it scorne, or harsh disgrace,
               Or quipping at thy follies to thy face;
               With exprobration of improuidence,
               Where's now thy brauerie, and confidence?—
               —I ouerpasse natures Antipathy,
               
               Or by a contrarie fond sympathy,
               
               They secrets are, and 'twill be out of season
               Of either side to yeeld a hansome reason:—
               —Why Nations are affected,
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                   I let goe,
               Or why abhor
                     •
                  'd, I say, nor yea, nor no;
               As for the English, A pish in each kinde,
               Fant
                     •
                  sticke, foolish, wauering as the winde:
               I could as well as you finde faul
                     •
                   withall,
               If finding fault may them from faults recall:
               But in these things experience teacheth thus,
               And I with you the matter so discusse,
               That exprobration of a custom'd sinne
               Hardens the heart, and sets them fast therin:
               As in reuenge in Irel
                        •
                     nd we chace
               The Wolf
                     •
                   for slaughtering sheepe in euerie place,
               The following night we looke for further spoile:
               So wise men lesse doe gaine the more they toil
                     •
                  ,
               A prison is a punishment to mend
               Such refractarie sinners, who offend;
               But who can say, that any man was better
               By liuing in a iaile a wretched debter:
               
                  
So Iuuenal complaines, and so may we
               The like effect of Poets, 
                        •
                     atyres see;
               For if that God in
                     •
                  use not inward grace,
               I see no man giue to your charming place.
               
                  —You doe not feare, who your religion know,
               Nor meane to make thereof a better show,
               Then is in proofe. You will weare truth in graine,
               And such a minde possesse, as all in vaine
               Deuices shall attempt: Nay, you haue not
               Presumption to finde fault with a small spot,
               And blurre the paper worse your selfe, and so
               From step to step you to high seates doe goe,
               Where quicke you 
                     〈◊〉
                   vpon the Magistrate;
               
               Who meane and poore offenders exprobrate,
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
               
               Searching the vnswept corners of their liues,
               And rating them, as they lie chaind in giues,
               When their owne soules all maculate appeare
               Vnto that 
                     〈…〉
                  , which sees so cleere:
               For this you angry grow, and fiet, and 
                     •
                  ume,
               And could inuectiue-like some vaine assume.
               —Sure this is well, if that it wo
                     •
                  ld thus last,
               But say the State another reckning cast,
               And crosse your zeale, either you alter now,
               Or must perforce to stronger bendings bow:
               Yea in religious case, whether you 
                     〈◊〉
                  
               
               At home, or doe your sel
                     •
                  e to trauaile giue,
               There is you know, but one prepared right,
               Now if imploiment bring you to a plight;
               Where Inquisition bindes you to a post,
               What will you presently as Martyr boast?
               
                  
No hansome silence, but a hairebraind wi
                     •
                  l:
               The Scripture bids you rather saue then kill,
               And flie from towne to towne, not that I meane
               You should Apostate proue, when that the sceane
               Of Christianity you act, and trie
               Your faith indeed: then doe a Gods name die;
               But with vaineglorious hardinesse to runne
               Into each danger so to be vndone,
               Is not by God allow'd, and thus you see
               Wise men for rashnesse may condemned be.
               —As for fault finders,
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                   who be
                     •
                  meered are
               With durt and fi
                     •
                  th, and yet presume 
                     〈◊〉
                   farre
               To brush anothers dust:—Sure 'tis a time,
               In which the best are guiltie of this crime:
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
               
               Our Sauiour it condemnes, and saies, its true
               There shall be such: why may not one be you?
               Ther's no deceit like to deceit of heart,
               And we are prone to play anothers part,
               Either forgetting, that we hau
                     •
                   a share
               Wi
                     •
                  hin the Play, or willinglie doe spare
               Our selues:—Thus when we heare some smart reproofe
               We thrust our neighbours forward, but aloofe
               We stand our selues:—As for the Magistrate,
               If any such there be to moue debate,
               Present him now, or else traduce him not,
               Ther's nothing by diffused cunning got:
               
                  Christ did not glance at any sinne in generall,
               But Hypocrite the Lawier did call,
               The Pharisee he brought within his woe,
               The Scribe was taught his guiltinesse to know,
               
                  
The deuils were cast out by name: the king
               
                  Herod, the king was tearm'd a Fox: to bring
               The rest, it endlesse is. Therefore when th
                     •
                  t
               At such a point your shaft is aimed at,
               Either desist from shooting wide at all,
               Or hit the man, that you so sinfull call.
               For he that dare say this, sure doth not feare
               Though of Magnatum scandalum he heare.
               —You haue no good opinion of such men,
               As with excuse of had I wist c
                     •
                  y, when
               Their proiects saile, nor doe you take delight
               In scoffing at infirmities: you wr
                     •
                  te
               Not gainst the Arts, nor worldlie things imbrace,
               For which all men are troubled in the race.
               
                  You haue no beauty, nor attracting forme,
               A Ladies eies, or wanton loue to charme.
               
                  You haue no Sampsons strength, great weight to beare,
               Nor would a Lions skinne with Her
                        •
                     'les weare;
               Why what a quoile is here? Yet for the first,
               How doe you know your deeds shall not be curst?Fato pr
                        •
                     dent
                        •
                     a
                        •
                     nor.
               
               Can humane wisdome be so prouident
               The end of things before hand to preuent?—
               If you had thought so to displease the King,
               You would haue sure forborne such rimes to sing.
               So that you see your selfe your selfe correct,
               And may for many other things be checkt.
               
                  You will not scoffe at weake and slender rimes,
               And yet inueigh gainst vanitie of times.
               You scorne what earth affoords,—yet take in worth▪
               
               What so your wit and labours can bring forth:
               
                  
Come, if you get it, purse the gold, and spare not
               But run not forth so fast to say, you care not:—
               As for your strength and beaut
                     •
                  e; they are gifts
               Not in your power to take, or chuse: no shifts
               Can shun them, when God tends: but you must haue
               Euen that, which in your heart you would not craue:
               And why haue you them not, as you do say,
               Because you would the i
                     •
                  sting wanton play,
               With Statesmen, Ladies, Milstones, Porters strong,
               Or Packehorses; Come leaue, 'tis a poore song.—
               —I ouerpasse your knowledge of such things,
               As doe belong to Common-wealths, or Kings,
               I will not word your wisedome in this kind
               That without Method many things I find
               Smarting enough, and worthy of your name,
               Which if they had been brought to one faire frame,
               Would sure haue made a farre more glorious show,
               Whereby their hearts must needs h
                     •
                  ue long'd to know
               The owner of the place, that with their eies
               Had gaz'd vpon the same; but now it lies
               A little further of from enuious reach,
               Or shot of malice: nay, it feares no breach:
               And let it lie; that none may finde this out
               Of your 
                     •
                  ood meaning, to raise any doubt.
               —You haue no money, nor lands falsly got
               From Churches, Orphans; Widowes, and what not?
               How can you tell? you sure receiue some coine,
               And doe you know who did the same purloine?
               But you will say, such act was none of yours,
               And him you hate, that any such procures:
               
                  
I like it well, but if it should be so,
               W
                     ••
                  e should your sinne your children ouerthrowe:
               The law is changed. For if you list to trie,
               Our God hath said the soule that sinnes shall die.
               —You haue no fowle diseases, nor great debts,
               Nor wife, nor child, nor many other 
                     •
                  ets,
               Nor wealth enough for hospitalitie,
               Nor free expences out of 
                     •
                  olitie,
               And yet in posse you may h
                     •
                  ue all these.
               For man is subiect when his maker please,
               To Petrachs fortunes, though he cannot finde
               Those sauing remed
                     •
                  es he there assign'd:
               —But then you buffle vp your selfe and sa
                     •
                  e,
               You haue a wealth which none can get awaie,
               And hope your wit a womans may excell,
               Though for her owne ends she dee ner' so well.
               Nay, as it seemes,Riches without vertue. I will not call it spleene,
               Some wondrous heire hath sure your riuall beene,
               With whom you combate by comparison,
               That as his yeares increase, vices grow on
               His blacke corrupted soule, like wennes in trees,
               Which bunch out with deformitie: yet sees
               He nought, but on a golden out-side lookes,
               Turning the leaues of his ill cast vp booke
                     •
                  :
               But other men a better reckn
                     •
                  ng knowe,
               That lust and riot will him overthrowe.
               —For as st
                     •
                  ffe claie is hardned in the Sun,
               And yet with water easie made to runne:
               So riches rammed with a griping hand,
               Or strange oppression, cannot safely stand
               
                  
Without dispersing. For when once they flie,
               Like water 
                     〈◊〉
                   vpon the ground they lie,
               And then such foolish owners cannot tell,
               Which way to liue, except they pawne or sell
               Their patrim
                     •
                  nies: so they perish must,
               Whereas you doe to noble vertue trust,
               Framing your life to wisdome, which is sure,
               Like some strong rock, that can all stormes endure:
               —Nay by this meanes you hope to get a wise,
               Who shall iudicious proue, making your life
               Conformable to hers, and hers to you:
               Oh that these things might come within my view!
               —For (as I hope for blisse) I wish you well,
               Yet would another did the story tell,
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
               
               To adde more lustre to your faire renowne,
               Because a man venturing oto farre may drowne
               Himselfe: but if a friendly helping hand
               Support him vp, he then may safely stand:
               Thus praise and honour haunt men by degrees,
               And follow worthines, as wisdome 
                     •
                  ees
               To whom her attributes belong: yet as againe
               The prouerb is, who snatcheth, workes in vaine:
               So he that will haue glory fore his time
               May faile with him, who doth too hastly climbe.
               —As for your wife,
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     
                     ▪
                   which yet I doe but name
               Because within your scrowle I finde the same:
               You yet haue none not, knowing what to haue,
               Vnlesse you might in brasse her manners graue,
               And fashion vp a peece of your owne making:
               Then peraduenture she were worth the taking.
               
                  
                  
                     •
                  hus haue I read l'igmalion made a shrine
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   marble so well shap't in euery line,
               
                  
                     •
                  hat he did dote on that he had begunne,
               
                  
                     •
                  nd fell in loue er'it was fully done:
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   you would haue a wife, if she were faire,
               
                  
                     •
                  oung, comely, rich, religious, debonaire,
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   stated in some large inheritage,
               
                  
                     ••
                  tracted from some worthie parentage,
               
                  
                     •
                  umbled at all times to obedience,
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   man is made the head in conscience:
               —What need more words, or being further headie?S. Thomas O
                        •
                     erbury▪
                  
               
               
                  
                     •
                  e haue a worthie knights good wife alreadie,
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   which I thinke you cannot add much more,
               
                  
                     •
                  hen with applause he hath prescrib'd before.
               —Now in good truth, you would some wonder shoe
               
                  
                     •
                  our selfe on such a woman to bestowe.
               
                  
                     •
                  ould not some one or two good qualities,
               With other reasonable abilities,
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  Catalogue your name with honest friends:
               
                  
                     •
                  ut you must needs contriue vnheard of ends.
               
                  
                     
                        •
                     ome. Come, what God appoints shall surely be,
               
                  
                     •
                  o which your pious heart doth soone agree.
               
                  
                     •
                  or as our Marchants know n
                     •
                  t what may chance,
               When they their longer votages aduance,
               But must endure the tempest of the Sea,
               The furies of the winde, heauens thundring plea,
               The rage of stormes, shipwracks, and dangerous l
                     •
                   kes,
               The shallow sands, the rock which all things b
                     •
                  eak
                     ••
                  :
               
                  
                     •
                  ome fearefull harbours, passages vnknowne,
               And thousand pe
                     •
                  ills, which are ye
                     •
                   vnshow
                     •
                  e,
               
                  
For rage came on with raigning, and his power
               Increased with his furie euery howre:
               Frailtie had got of reason vpper hand,
               And greatnes weaker, wisdome did withstand,
               And when was this, euen when he did disclaime
               To haue his vertue foil'd with any maime.
               —And what are you? that may not haue all this,
               Although you now suppose nought is amisse,
               You see what in your Catalogue I name,
               If then you blot it, who shall read the same?
               You doe write mortall man, and I am sure
               No constant goodnesse doth in man endure,
               But by a working grace to him vnknowne,
               As by the passages of life is showne:
               —Then take you heed; presumption canker like
               Eats on our flesh, aiming our soule to strike.
               And so I end; yet neither rage nor raue:
               For what we haue not now, anon we haue.
            
            
               Sum faelix,Remember this Caution. quis enim neget hoc? faelix
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   man
                     •
                  bo,
               Hoc quo
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   quis dubitet, tutam me copiafecit,
               Maior sum, quam cuipossit fortuna nocere.
            
            Ovid. Met. lib. 6.
         
         
            
            AN ANSWERE TO WITHERS
NEC CAREO.
            
               —YOu are not now so humble as you were,
               But doe your selfe more high, &amp; prowdly beare:
               Or else the Motto carries such a st
                     •
                  aine,
               As that you must not of your wants complaine:
               Yet all you doe is without complement
               To bring it vnto this, you liue content,
               And thus you want nothing which life doth craue,
               Or man against necessitie would haue,
               And thus you want no quietnesse of mind
                     •
                  ,
               To take in worth what you at home doe finde:
               And thus you want no gouerment to season
               Those tumours, which may swell beyond faire reason,
               But gladly welcome, what God doth bestowe,
               Whether your cup haue ought or ouerflow:
               —Take heed, you want not now a temperature
               Of moderation crosses to endure
               Without insulting; for there is a pride,
               Which God in poverty doth still deride.
               —When Plato made a Feast vnto the rest▪
                  
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  Diogenes came in among the best,
               
                  
Saluting none▪ but like a dogue did sit,
               Snarling at gesture; and each want on fit,
               Till rising in a rage he tooke his Plate,
               His hangings, linnen, carpets, robes of state,
               And cast them vnder foot, saving beside,
               Thus I doe
                     •
                  trample vpon Plato
                        •
                     s p
                     ••
                  de.
               —All were amased except the master, who
               Did smile at that he did, o
                     •
                   meant to doe,
               Replying with a pleasant modestie,
               His imperfections he could not denie:
               But Cynicke, Cynicke, to thee I appeale
               This is not out of worth, or honest zeale,
               But in m
                        •
                     iorif
                        •
                     stu,
                  
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                   that I knowe▪
               
               I doe not so offend with hansome show,
               As thou with dogged heart, and ragged weeds,
               Where vnder arrogance, and selfe-loue breeds.
               Therefore desist, and either be a man,
               Or let men liue according as they can.
               —Thus thus; when 
                     •
                  ou compare with Eastern king
                     •
                  
               
               And make the world beleeue, that patience brings
               An argument for outward pouertie
               To parallell a strong felicitie,
               And equall beggers with a r
                     •
                  ch mans state,
               And the deiected with the fortunate.
               —The wiser sort doe smile at this your fault,
               Saying you would before a criple halt,
               Nor doe they thinke that mortall man can be
               So moderate in harsh extremitie,
               Vnlesse he stupid were, and numb'd in sence,
               Hauing nor spleene, nor gaule to breed offence.
               
                  
—For take the patterne of some worthie men▪
                  
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
               
               Was peerelesse Iob no more distempred, when
               Gods rod did lash his sides, and he did roare
               With greiuous botches, wounds, and 
                     •
                  etters store,
               Then when he was welcomb'd to double wealth,
               To honour, riches, strength, and perfect health,
               Besides you saw God made a difference
               Betweene his blessings, as he did d
                     •
                  spence
               With his extreames, say therefore what you will,
               Or rich, or poore, doe want something 
                     •
                  till:
               And though you could not sleep, with some mēs wealth
               Amased vp by fowle oppressions stealth
                     •
                  
               
               Yet better's better, and it is a follie
               To make the world beleeue you are so holy.
               —But what haue other men to doe with this,
               That the composure of your bodie is
               So strong, so iointed, healthfull, and such like,
               As if you would vs with amasement strike
               At the relating of some wonderment,
               Or exhelation in the Firmament,
               Or expos'd meteor: thus you la
                     •
                  e about
               You want nothing, though others goe without.
               —Your selfe you answere, you are young, and strong,
               Possessing all, that therevnto belong,
               And so doe thousands moe, who yet complaine
               Of man
                     •
                  e wants, and that they crie in vaine,
               Whereas you God doe praise, and dailie blesse
               For your great comforts, and true happinesse,
               For life, for strength, for libertie and all,
               Whereby you want nothing, nor euer shall▪
               
               
                  
—And yet you want another to say so,
                     
                        ••
                     iendly 
                        ••
                     men 
                        •
                     on.
               
               Pointing vnto some Lady as you goe
               Along the street-see yond 
                     •
                  r Gentleman
               
               (Besides the qualities, where with he can
               Enrich the prowdest beautie) hansome is,
               Young, comely, sound, possessing n
                     •
                  ught amisses
               He neither liues distemper'd with disqu et,
               Nor surfets in his riot, or his diet,
               He maketh not his house a dicing roome,
               Nor welcome gries to any pander groome,
               His chamber smoakes not with Tobaccoes stench,
               
               Nor are they spewing vpon every bench,
               No othes prophaine the place where he doth lie,
               No time's consum'd in sloth, and surquedrie,
               No frantick iestures after fearefull losse,
               Nor execration vpon every crosse:
               No bloodie quarrells for a word let slip,
               No wile, or c
                     ••
                  ning sillinesse to trip,
               No Sabboths breach, nor mocks to such as goe
               To Church, and so with God their time bestow,
               While others worke for fowle damnation,
               Calling their vices recreation.
               —He welcomes not a strumpet which a slaue
               May stride if that he so much monie haue,
               Nay manie times the pander, who attends
               Hath that, which some braue prodigall dispends,
               He taketh not E
                        •
                     ixers for his lust,
               Nor heats himselfe wi
                     •
                  h amber, nor doth trust
               His bodie with an Emprick: his hand
               Knowes not where any Surgeous box doth stand,
               
                  
But as you see he liues, and walkes, and eats,
               And fairely still the companie intreats,
               Where he frequents:—Here were a husband now
               To make your beautie blush, and pride to bow,
               And though h
                     •
                  s meanes be small, and in his roofe
               The horne of Ach
                        •
                     lous hangs not aloofe.
               Yet is his minde a treasure-house of wealth,
               Which cannot be purloind by any stealth.
               —This, or such like, if that some friend did saie,
               He surely might a great expense defraie,
               Making you farre more happie by report,
               Then you your selfe can doe in anie sort:
               Therefore desist from running 
                     •
                  orth so fast
               With your owne praises, but let others cast
               The mantle of reward upon your head,
               Till honour doe your vertue ouerspread:—
               —You want no iudgement difference to make
               'Twixt man and man, and that for orders fake
               You want to griefe for your true freinds misdeeds,
               But his distresse in you some passion breeds:
               You want no loue in
                     ••
                  rmities to spare:
               Nor courage if the cause be good - you dare
               Maintaine your confidence, expresse your minde,
               And saie the multitude will proue vnkinde,
               Whom yet you scorne, and may indeed compare
               To rascall deere, that die vpon the bare,
               Or rot consumes.—Nay I am sure they be
               Like Crowes on carrion, where they 
                     •
                  ll agree
               To fill their cropps while the best flesh doth last,
               The bones for saking, when the hunger's past.
               
                  
—But here you want or memorie or will
               To minde what repetitions you vse still.
                     
                        •
                      is a 
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        •
                     rder
               
               For one selfe thing you doe a subiect make
               In d
                     •
                  uer
                     •
                   places and still vndertake,
               To dash the multitude, as with a blurre,
               Spurning their tumults, and the wrangling sturre
               They doe procure.—Againe, you first did saie
               You care for none for his great outward swaie,
               And yet to keepe decorum where you liue,
               You must v
                     •
                  to the wicked honour giue.
               —This sure you doe of purpose to make good
               That for this time all method you withstood,
               And would not formerlie compile the booke,
               Least euery one, who did it ouerlooke,
               Your meaning might misconster when they saw,
               Your muse resolu'd enormities to draw
               Before the barre of vertue to reforme,
               What might and did the better for deforme,
               Making the beautie of faire innocence
               Adulterate by rapes and violence,
               Oppression, bribes, reuenge, stealth, and what not,
               As sinne of times the vpper hand had got.
               Thus still you aime at generall misdeeds,
               Because no wrangling hand shall sowe the seeds
               Of discord in your waie, or throwe a blocke
               To hinder your smooth walk—As for a mock,
               You cast it slight lie off with noble storne,
               As if you were to higher reaches borne.—
               —Whie this is well, if it be taken so,
               But yet you carelesse are, and onward goe,
               
                  
Saying, you want not knowledge to discouer,
               Who of true wisdome is a constant louer,
               Then presentie you fall to this againe,
               That seeming honestie doth leaue a staine
               Vpon the conscience, and an outward show
               Without a purer heart doth ouerthrow
               The large effect of sad devot on,
               And soone diuerts from each good motion,
               From whence religion is hipocrisie,
               As ill, or worse then any heresie,
               So you inferre that wiser men beginne
               With ciuill courses which doe end in sinne.
               —W
                     •
                  ll though you want not now an honest heart
               To act your selfe a worthie Christian; part,The 
                        〈…〉
                      quan
                        •
                     
                  
               
               Yet cannot you descrie the fowle decent
               Of strange dissembling men, that from conceit,
               Though not from malice, open both their armes,
               As if they were bewitched with your charmes,
               And at next turne repine at arrogance,
               Which puft you thus your labours to aduance:
               —Nay, you are not alone, I haue men seene
               Euen in their graspings make a mock betweene,
               Their curresies, and as they laie along
               Vpon their shoulders loll a scuruie tongue.
               Another yeelds his friend his praises due
               Vnto his face, but meeting with a crue
               He better likes, he tells them, he is weake,
               And farre from that, of which doth rumour speak:
               Another vaunts, wherein he haue releeued
               His friends distresses, but retracts as greeu'd
               
                  
He hath bestow'd his cost in such a sott,
               And then againe puts all off with some sport▪—
               —As for religion, I doe feare to name it,
               Or how so manie false professours shame it,
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     
                  
               
               Thronging to Church for priuate ends, or looke
               With want on roling eies quite off their booke,
               The rest I could recite, but this I saie,
               He that for forme doth come, were well awaie,
               And he that serues not God meerelie for loue,
               I doe his best deuotion disapproue.
               —From whence I point it 
                     •
                  hus, you needs must lacke
               A cunning strength to laie men on the rack,
               Or wrest from them confession of this treason
               'Gainst God, to serue h
                     •
                  m out of sensuall reason.
               For if saluation commeth by our faith,
               As in a manie places Scripture saith,
               How shall we knowe the faith of any man,
               Which doth it not expresse doe what you can,
               These rules haue passiue contradiction,
               And you and I shall be but lookers on.
               —As for those arts, and sciences you knowe,
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
               
               With whose s
                     •••
                  ciencie awaie you goe:
               Both you and I want many secret things,
               Which with great studie men to learning brings.
               For though we glance and some what by the waie,
               'Tis like the dogges that running dare not staie
               For feare of Crocadiles but water lap
               A
                     •
                   
                  Nilus bankes: 
                     〈◊〉
                   if that we perhap
               May blesse
                     ••
                   God for an infu
                     •
                  'd light
               Sufficient to bring vs to the right.
               
                  
Yet is it farre from that glorious sun shine,
               Which shewes both humane, and all things diuine:
               Then saie not to thy soule, set downe and rest,
               Thou hast enough of knowledge with the best,
               Least others doe that parable recite
               Of him, that all his wealth lost in one night,
               Because he boasted wha
                     •
                   he had in store:
               Few words are best, and so I saie no more
               But this what er' the heart possesse
                     •
                  h so:
               More is vnknowne then anie man can knowe:—
               —You want not sense their s
                     •
                  re downefall,Not 
                        〈◊〉
                      preiu
                        •
                     
                   which
               Liue in the heat of pride, and are so rich
               With plentie, that they sw
                     •
                  ll like full growne grapes,
               Vntill they burst, so none of them esca
                     •
                  es,
               A vengeance due vnto their riots lust,
               Or high looking ambition, till the dust
               Of Kings displeasure flie into their face
               With some strange whire winde blowing vp digrace
               Vpon their heads, vntill they sinke so loe,
               That those they scorn'd doe oer their honours goe
                     •
                  
               
               All which is but coniecture; for I finde
               The spirit saie, no spirit in his kinde
               Can tell before hand, though it be begunne,
               What shall hereafter happen vnder Sunne:—
               —We well may guesse—as from contagious heat,
               That on some dunghill doth reflect and beat
               To pu
                     •
                  refie the aire, a plague may breed,
               With burnings; feauers, drought, to worke some deed
               Of terrour in a land,—Thus when we see
               A man resolu'd to sursets, or to be
               
                  
Strong to drinke wine, and ouer liberall
               To satisfie his lust, we may conclude,
               These wanton courses will his health delude,
               And so corrupt the bodie that the same
               Diseases shall attend with paine, and shame,—
               —So fa
                     •
                  es i
                     •
                   with the soule, and working minde,
               If pride, revenge, or si
                     •
                  ne in any kinde
               Praedominant, doe drawe it by degrees
               To open action:—who is purblinde, sees,
               Gods wr
                     •
                  th must fall more heauie then this frame
               Of heauen and earth, as Poets call the same,
               On Hercules and Atlas shoulders lights,
               Who beare all vp with strange vnusuall mights.
               —You come at last by waie of negatiue,
               
               Which in effect doth proue affirmatiue,
               
               For to the wants, as you applie a no,
               We by the processe haue it nothing so:
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     
                  
               
               Bu
                     •
                   rather for deficiencie we finde
               A sort of blessed graces in your minde:
               —Such as a iov to joy in hope of blisse,
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      me fecit.
               
               A true cont
                     •
                  ition to mend all amisse,
               A godly feare for shrinking vnder sinne,
               A care 
                     〈◊〉
                   keepe the conscience cleane within,
               A constant heart to beare with penurie,
               A resolution againt m
                     •
                  serie,
               A braue Heroick spirit to endure,
               Wh
                     •
                  t pu
                     •
                  blinde Forrune euer could procure.—
               —Wounds though they smart are borne with cheerfulnesse,
               The thoughts prepar'd are 'gainst heauinesse,
               The 
                     •
                  ies are vigelant, and so can wake,
               
                  
An Ague or the palsie doth not shake
               You with distemperature:—And whereas we
               Hane heard braue Orators plead for a Fee,
               Gracing their Clients with comparison
               Of worthy Peeres informer ages gone:
               You challenge all the world for a strong heart
               To brooke, what ere despight from it impart.
               —In hauing these, thus sure you doe not want,
               Nor of Gods blessings is your portion scant,
               Vnlesse (as I haue said) you temper lacke
               To binde vp close into one handsome packe
               These benefits of nature for more vse,
               Then in exposing them to mens abuse:—
               For either they will wonder at your store,
               Or verily suppose, you vaunt of more
               Then euer man did, as one man possesse;
               Be therefore quit with them more or lesse.
               —You come at last to some affection,
               Which you want not: so from conuection
               Of the discourse we finde, that this you haue:
               A hate of sinne, be it in foole or knaue,
               A courteous hand for to salute another,
               As when a louing brother greets abrother;
               A free forgiuing heart vpon submission,
               A Christian libertie, from a Commission
               Which God hath sign'd.—Great comforts yo possesse,
               Which may as great afflictions soone redresse,
               To these you adde a faith which cannot moue,
               But lookes vpright to heauenly things aboue:
               A hope, which no aduersitie can wrong,
               
                  
But all I haue I carry to the graue
               I meane a vertue flourishing about me
               For I haue naugh: of worldly wealth without me,
                     
                        ••
                     niamea 
                        ••
                     umpar.
               
               And thus you scoffe the proud 
                     
                        •
                     onarkes of state,
               With whom you doe compare at highest rate:—
                     
                        •
                     cat 
                        •
                     ast.
               
               —if they haue guardes and no harme feele,
               You innocence 
                     •
                  ioy, and coate; of armed steele,
               —If they be be Princes sonnes—you are the child
               Of God Almighty euer vndesiled:
               —If they of followers boast vntoucht, vncast,
               A troope of Angels followes you as fast:
               —If they in friends delight: Abram was call'd
               The friend of God:—so good men are enstall'd.
               What other things you speake, I will not speake,
               Because I purpose not order to breake:
               —You want no office—For a Christian life
               Is well imploid, hauing both toile and strife:
               You want no pleasures:—For what God doth please
               Affords you all things with delight and ease:
               You want no company—For Christians finde
               Society enough of euery kinde:
               You want no armour for a martiall fight.
               You haue the armes of a spirituall Knight:
               You want no scaling ladders gainst a wall,
               By faith and prayer you to heauen call:
               Nay in a word a thousand blessings more
               The God of blessings addeth to your store;
               So you conclude, that if the King did know,
               How rich you liue, he would on you bestow
               
                  
                  
                     •
                  his wish, that if he were not he
               
                  
                     •
                  e might desire then your selfe to be.
               —The selsfe same-word did Alexander say
               
                  
                     •
                  nto Diogenes,
                  A Dialogue betweene Alexand
                           ••
                        
                      and Diogenes.
                   when as he lay
               Within his tub, as a fierce kenneld 
                     •
                  ur,
               
                  
                     •
                  corning the King, deriding all the stur
               
                  
                     •
                  is Army made, geeting at f
                     •
                  o
                     •
                  llies, which
               
                  
                     •
                  he world prepared gainst the poore, and rich,
               
                  
                     •
                  enying all things that might him controule,
               
                  
                     •
                  xcept the immortality of soule—
               —The Monarch told him, he could to him giue
               
                  
                     •
                  onour and wealth: he answered he could liue
               
                  
                     •
                  ithout them both: he could bereaue his life.—
               
                  
                     •
                  hat were a way to stint the wondrous strife
               
                  
                     •
                  etweene his soule and body:—he could make
               
                  
                     •
                  he people him obey— that were to take
               
                  
                     •
                  is owne obedience from him to the gods,
               
                  
                     •
                  nd set his heart with better things at ods:
               —Well sayes the Cynick seeing you are so free,
               
                  
                     •
                  hat which y cannot giue, take not from me
               
                  
                     •
                  e sunnes deere light: but stand beyond my Cell,
               
                  
                     •
                  nd I without you shall doe passing well;
               
                  
                     •
                  hat quoth the King, I can command thee sterue,
               
                  
                     •
                  hen little will be left the wormes of serue:
               
                  
                     •
                  y very word bereaues thee of thy sight,
               
                  
                     •
                  o shall I scape the dangers of delight:
               
                  
                     •
                  hy tongue I can pull out; Then shall not I
               
                  
                     •
                  laspheme the gods, no
                     •
                   shew a feare to die.—
               
                  
                     •
                  his and much more the king and he did chat,
               
                  
                     •
                  ea diuers times he from his Army gat.
               
                  
To commune with him; — when he saw him surt▪
               
               That no temptation could a change procure,
               He turned about, and told Ephestion thus:
               This man alone hath cleare'y conquered vs:
               If I great Alexander were not now,
               To be Diogenes I would know how.
               —Yet for all this be you more milde, then so
               And thinke, that God on man did once bestow
               This goodly world, and his braue furniture
               To serue his turne,
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        •
                     utifull. while he did there endure;
               —Yea for theis sakes, whom you doe boast so mu
                     •
                  
               
               The free Elected: th
                     •
                  ugh we know none such
               By outward show, all things were brought in frame,
               Them to en
                     •
                  tich, and praise God for the same
               —Then vse them freely, but be no mans iudge,
               Nor at their greatnesse either storme or grudge:
               As for the blessings, which you glory in,
               I like them well, if that it were no sin
               Presumptuous so to be - For sure the best
               Came short of that, wherein you safely rest:
               King Dauid liued in feare:- lob did mistrusts
               Himselfe a greater sinner, when in dust
               He lay—Abram fell downe, and would not looke
               Vp vnto God, vntel he mercy tooke,
               The Prophets all disclaimed their worthinesse,
               The Patriarkes confest their filthinesse:
               
                  Peter wtll with his feet, wash head and hands,
               Who shall deliuer me from sinnes hard bands,
               
                  Paul himselfe; and yet you nothing want,
               Except in one place, where your heart doth pant
               
                  
When that you say,—you w
                        •
                     nt no faults indeed:—
               O doe so still; and we are soone agreed.
            
            
               —Deni
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   teipsum
               Concute, num tibi quid vitiorum inse
                     •
                  erit olim
               Natura a aut etiam conswetudo mala. Nam
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  
               
               Neglectis vrenda silix innascitur agr
                     •
                  s.
            
            Hor at lib. 1. Satyr. 3.
            
               —Discite
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   o miseri &amp; causas cognoscite 
                     〈◊〉
                  
               
               Quid sumus, aut quidnam victuri gignimur, or d
                     •
                  
               
               Quis datus aut metae quam mollis flexus &amp; vnde,
               Quis modus argento, quid fas opture, quid asper
               Vtile nummus habet patriae, chari
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   propinquis
               Quantum elargiri habet, decent, quem te Deus esse
               Iussit, &amp; humana quae parte locutus es in redisce.
            
            Persius: Satyr▪ prim.
         
         
            
            
            AN ANSWERE TO WITHERS
NEC CVRO.
            
               VVHat? worse &amp; worse? and must it needs be so,
               That now I doe a carelesse Christian know:
               And all because he doth pretend a care,
               Which God doth take, why this is not so rare,
               —From all beginnings men did honour God,Pram
                        •
                      Pana.
               
               Both for his mercie and correcting rod:
               —The Indians where the Idol De
                        •
                     il sits,
               Yet doe allow in their true tempred 
                     •
                  its
               A power farre superior vnto his:—
               The Sauages, where all things are amisse,
               Pray vnto God,—America's vast land
               One God adore, whether they kneele or stand:
               The Negro's and Synegas people say
               The soule's immort
                     •
                  ll, and to God they pray:
               The Mahumetans thinke so well of God,
               That not an Image hath with then abode:
               The Moores do punish blasphemy with death,
               When against God they heare prophaned breath:
               The Iewes yet tremble at Iehovahs Name,
               And call his workemanship this wondrous frame,
               
                  
—But when our Sauiour did to Martha say,
                     
                        ••
                     all 
                        ••
                     ings.
               
               One thing was onely needfull, as the way
               Vnto saluation: he did not exclude
               All humane wisedome, learning, nor conclude
               'Gainst ciuill honesty, or hopefull arts,
               Wherewith so many Worthies plaid their parts,
               Nor gainst, Aegypts great library he spake,
               Nor other volu
                     ••
                  es bad he vs forsake,
               And therefore you need not so carelesse be,
               Who are of all men of your knowledge free:
               —If you respect nothing but Gods deare word,
               How comes it, that you to the world afford
               These Verses, Poems, and high straines of wit,
               Which I am sure were neuer found in it:
               Therefore I know you doe for somethings care,
               Hauing in learnings treasure-house a share,
               —For presently you fall into a vaine,
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      ult 
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
               
               O
                     •
                   selfe-commending Poesie, and straine
               Your passion, to reproue and chide all such,
               As will not with considerate iudgement touch
               Your well writ books:—And thus them you diuide
               First into idle Guls, who doe deride
               You verses out of base and nasty breeding,
               Or spoile them with some harsh and ragged reading
                     •
                  
               
               Then into Criticks, who the Tauern's haunt,
               And out of some distemperature doe taunt
               Your well-composed Muse with tattered rimes,
               According to their fits, and drunken times:
               —Lastly to Poetasters, who presume
               On thier owne frothy stuffe, and so assume
                     •
                  
               
               
                  
A cunning vnbefitting shallow braines,
               Which nought but ballat sustinesse retaines.
               —And why should thes
                     •
                   things 
                     •
                  tartle you in ought,Hon
                        ••
                      profi
                        •
                     
                  
               
               As though in spleene you for reuengement sought?
               If they be poore and base, let them alone;
               If they be drunke with 
                     ••
                  ot, all is one;
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
               
               If by endeauours they doe something get,
               And so their mindes to triuiall courses set
                     •
                  
               
               It is but money, and Vespasians p
                     •
                  sse
               Brought in a large reuenew;—So it is,
               With da
                     ••
                  tie Merchants, and their clothes of gold;
               And such, by whom bo
                     •
                  h pitch and tarre are sold.
               It is but money, and who difference makes
               Twixt selling flesh, or fell: There's none 
                     〈…〉
                  
               
               His profit, but as he himselfe applies
               To homelie courses; thus he liues and dies.
               It is but money, and for toies of wit,
               Rediculous deuices fondlie writ
               Come often to the Printer with successe,
               When sollide labours will nere passe the Presse:
               Therefore desist, and let them to their vaine,
               For my part I doe like such honest gaine.
               —You carelesse are of the dispersed newes,
               Which either Pauls,
                  
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      Trend Knigh
                        •
                     
                   or our exchange doe vse:
               Nay, though the Court doe iustifie the same,
               You yet are carelesse of a Courtiers name;
               Such Courtiers I doe me
                     •
                  ne, as boast of wit,
               And like some M
                        •
                     micks in a pleasant fit,
               Penuriouslie frequent each good mans table,
               And there befoole themselues, as they are able
               
                  
To catch at ouershppings of m
                     •
                  ane men,
               Triu
                     ••
                  phing so with 
                     •
                  oll
                     •
                  tie: but when
               The snailes doe meet with harder ob
                     •
                  ects, Oh
               How poorely doe they then their iests bestow,
               Pul
                     •
                  ing thei
                     •
                   ho
                     ••
                  es in, putting all t
                     ••
                  ngs off
               Either wit
                     •
                   laughter, or some sillie scoffe.
               —Thes
                     •
                   wits (
                     •
                  or 
                     〈◊〉
                   the tearme doha goe) doe hunt
               Those Officers, that out of custome grant
               Them
                     •
                   certainment, where in impudence
               The
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   vnto their meat with great offence
               V
                     •
                  to the Master. For he many times
               
                  
                     〈…〉
                   tell his guests, bef
                     •
                  re their rimes
               Come to his hearing. Then if numb
                     •
                  r hold
               Proporti 
                     ••
                  n with the roome, 
                     •
                  hese fli
                     •
                  s are bold
               To s
                     •
                  cke 
                     〈…〉
                  —Thu
                     •
                   as smooth as o
                     ••
                  e
               They looke againe, or as great horses soile
               The
                     ••••
                  lues in their owne durt, they all besmeere
               B
                     •
                  t 
                     〈◊〉
                   finger with this courtlie cheere.
               —
                     〈◊〉
                   full fed Mu
                     ••
                  cians they sit still
               A 
                     〈◊〉
                   in silence, till some darling well
               B
                     •
                  g
                     •
                  n the chat, and then they neuer cease,
               N
                     •
                  y tho
                     •
                  gh the Master bids them hold their peace.
               
                  
                     〈…〉
                   are great with childe with 
                     •
                  ests, and so
               Must b
                     •
                  ing the bath 
                     •
                  orth, left it stifled grow.
               L
                     ••
                  ke how 
                     •
                  ou see corruption swell the va
                     •
                  es,
               And 
                     〈◊〉
                   both bloud, sinewes and braines,
               Vntill so
                     •
                  e boiles and bot
                     •
                  hes doe appeare,
               Whose rup
                     •
                  ures must the rotten carkase cleere:
               So 
                     •
                  ares it with our w
                     •
                  ts, till gibes and taunts
               Burst sorth, and many times the presence daunts,
               
                  
When men as hot, though not so quicke, as they
               Bid them befoole them
                     •
                  elues some other way;
               And then let these their iests be nere so good,
               They terrour bring if they doe end in blood.
               —But why should you thus carelesse be? when all
               The earth for news a scrutime doth call:
               Besides,
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                   who euer mastred nature so,
               But he was well content since to bestow
               Vpon faire rumour of the worlds designes,
               Which either men, or their prepar'd assig
                     •
                  es
               Hunt after with full greedinesse, till they
               Doe vnd
                     •
                  rstand what other men can say;
               And so doe rectifie their ignorance,New
                        •
                     .
               
               As 
                     •
                  ither custome, or some fai
                     •
                  er chance
               The Common-wealths rich curtaines draw aside,
               That they may see, what therein doth abi
                     •
                  e:
               The Churches vnswept corners doe discouer,
               That they may kn
                     •
                  w who is Gods deerest louer:
               The Courts high hangings doe hold vp full high,
               That they may view who comes or passeth by:
               The Citie gates and State-house cleanely ope,
               To vnderstand the Common-counsels scope:
               The Countreys carpet lay abroad, to view,
               That they mistake not, what is false or true:—
               —And this is Nature, Custome, Preachers guise
               To be to others and themselues so wise,
               That they may well adopt each application
               Vnto the Auditors of euerie nation:—
               Nay, 'tis no new thing to harke after newes,
               For the Athenians still the same did vse,
               
                  
Yea, those harsh Stoicks, who were stricter men
               Beyond our age or people, vs'd it then:
               And why should you so singular professe
               Your selfe, your life, your libertie, vnlesse
               Some pow
                     •
                  r diu
                     •
                  e, infused hath a spir
                     •
                  t
               Of Reuelation for you to inherite
               Beyond all other, that you may indeed
               Tell, what is in Apoc
                        •
                     lyps agreed
               Concerning Rome, or other roomes of Hell,
               
               Or (as the best newe
                     •
                  ) who in Heauen dwell.
               
                  —You carelesse are of obseruation,
                  
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
               
               Or any rules of health, or fashion,
               Or whether manners, custome of a Table,
               Dreames, prophesies, denices, and are able
               To put off cleanelie frightings of the sense;
               As if on earth you had no residence:
               But could so manage frailtie with your reason,
               That it should neuer yeeld to any sea
                     •
                  on,
               Griefe, paine, or sicknesse, or seeke out a cure,
               Which should your strength maintaine, or ease procure.
               —Why this is strange, that any man should crosse
               The order of our fate, with such a losse
               Of physicke bookes, of husbandrie, of health,
               (For which is still dispensed, so much wealth)
               Of Arts, of morall rules, Astrology,
               
               Of the abuses of Tautology,
               
               With all the rest.—Nay, verie Scriptures tell,
               The st
                     •
                  rres within the firmament excell
               Both Sunne and Moone, and are therein expos'd
               As signes to men:—For God hath so disclos'd
               
                  
His Counsell to our vse:—Thus comes the spring,
               Where in the flowers sprout, and birds doe sing.
               Thus Summer doth approach to ripen corne,
               
                  
                     •
                  nd countrie blessings to our barne; are borne:
               
                  
                     •
                  hus Autumne yeelds a vintage, and prepares
               The plowing ground with other worldlie cares:
               Thus Winter keepes the sap within the root,
               Hardens the ground with frost and snow to boot,
               Haile, raine, and storme, the fields to oue
                     •
                  flow,
               
                  
                     •
                  nd yet this man cares not what windes doe blow:
               —Thus Solomon sets downe the Pissemires toile,
               The plowmans labour to manure his soile,
               The Marchants traffick with the Artisan,
               
                  
                     •
                  nd all the duties which belong to'man.
               Thus you shall finde Physicks necessitie,
               With other sciences conformity,
               What strength hath bread, what mirth yeeldes bruised grapes,
               What cheerfulnesse in Oile, yea nothing scapes
               
                  
                     •
                  he holy word, but it doth shew vs all,
               And yet this man cares not what euer fall:
               —I speak not of Antipathies, though he
               
                  
                     •
                  s carelesse whither any such there be,
               But you shall further finde, Christ tells vs this,
               That fiery mornings threaten stormes 'ywis,
               And by the skie, or troubled firmament,
               Men guesse at that which God hath thereby meant,
               And why may not coniectrall dreames accord
               To some presage warranted in the word,
               Why may not somethings be Propheticall,
               
               Though the preuention doth not rightly fall
               
                  
Within mans reach: yet sure we are to knowe,
               The course of times doth alter all things so,
               An
                     •
                   we may well thereby our hearts prepare,
               And yet this man for this doth nothing care.
               —Then doth he talke of welcome.
                     
                        •
                     e m
                        •
                     s of such 
                        •
                     ntlemē 
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                   and of d
                     •
                  et.
               Wherein nothing shallon
                     •
                  e his minde disquiet,
               L
                     •
                  t Lords and Ladies sume, or chide him so,
               He from the chamber to the hall doth goe,
               Let Steward grudge his presence, what cares he,
               He meanes as he was wont still there to be,
               Let seruants wh
                     •
                  sper curses in his eare,
               He 
                     •
                  ests it out, and can the same forbeare,
               Let an inseriour be before him placed,
               So he make on
                     •
                  , 
                     •
                  e saies, he's not disgraced,
               Nay though he 
                     •
                  is▪ vpon some fret, or fume,
               He suddenly new courage doth assume,
               What torment worse then this? and yet there be
               Good men euen chain'd to such necessitie:—
               —What though he be condemned as he sits
               And so affronted with some prowder fits
               Of an old toothlesse Lady, or her g
                     •
                  oome,
               Or scabbed children, he yet cares not whom:
               All thi
                     •
                  gs are welcome to his open heart,
               Nay though he see a pander plaie his part
               Within the house, a frenzie iest he heare
               To quip him to his teeth, he can forbeare
               All taunts and gibes; no scornes vnto his face,
               Nor surly lookes can make him leaue the place.—
               —Saie that the young ones paint, or smoak the haire
               With powders sweet to make them seeme more faire,
               
                  
                  
                     •
                  hat's this to him? the fond attires that be
               
                  
                     •
                  oth whorish and immodest he doth see,
               
                  
                     •
                  nd neuer ca
                     •
                  es, nor how they sport and plaie,
               
                  
                     •
                  rophane, dance, reuell, throwe their soules awaie,
               
                  
                     •
                  ingling each word with a false hearted oath,
               
                  
                     •
                  e keepes his silence, and to check is loath.
               
                  
                     •
                  or if he once mention a matrones name,
               
                  
                     •
                  t him they geere, and doe deride the same.
               
                  
                     •
                  f he a word of priuate praiers glance,
               They thinke him mad, or else in some strange trance,
               
                  
                     •
                  f from their bias throw them to serue God,
               And keep the Sabb
                     •
                  th, they their heads d
                     •
                  e nod,
               
                  
                     •
                  ol
                     •
                  ng their tongues, disclaming so to be
               
                  
                     •
                  epu
                     •
                  ed Puritans in leas
                     •
                   degree:—
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   this he sees and care
                     •
                  esse lets it passe.
               
                  
                     •
                  or so it will be, is, and euer was:
               And yet this man writes man, hath gifts good store,
               As oncing ged to natures bounteous lore:
               And yet this man proceeds from gentle blood,
               And by his writings hath the world with stood:
               And yet this man write, Christian, honest, wise,
               Though now he carelesse be of any guise,
               And yet this man religious writes, and so
               Liues better sure, then these his words doe shew—
               —The next step that you make is gainst the care
               Of certaine superfluities, which are
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
               
               Produc'd from Credit, pleasures, money, time,
               
               Reputing euery one a seuerall crime,
               Which doe not giue attendance on the soule,
               As vertue may motiues of sinne controule,
               
                  
Or a pure heart resolue neuer to yeeld,
               Though honestie be foiled in the feeld,
               Nay as it seemes, you rather sinke and die,
               Then be a slaue to raging villanie:
               Sure you doe well if you could haue it so,
               But then you must out of this compasse goe,
               And either not conuerse with men at all,
               Or stumble at such things, as make them fall.
               For this dishonestie you hate so much,
               Hath amongst worldlings such a common touch,
               That it i
                     •
                   vsed, though it doe not thriue,
               And o
                     •
                  t of passion doth each man depriue
               O
                     •
                   vnderstanding: But what shall be done?
               When it the race of gaine and profit runne,
               When it doth sringe the skirts of great mens coats,
               And glides as smooth as oyle downe in their throats,
               Whereby a powerfull tongue checks innocenee,
               And by inuersion names it impudence;
               And yet you care not, so your soule be pure,
               How can a pure soule such outrage endure.
               —Nay in my soule, when that you see it so,
               You greeue at heart.—But now you onward goe
               With carelessenesse at statesmen raised by Kings,
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
               
               As if it danger were to reach at things
               Beyond our strength:—Yet shall we venter this
               To crie alowd, that great men doe amisse,
               And not be gr
                     •
                  iued, how the gouernment
               Concussion suffers:—When we knowe they ment,
               Either to paint their coats with fuming fame,
               As their ambition doth bedawb the same,
               
                  
And as their hearts are prowd, their glorious eies
               Will looke on nothing but the high
                     •
                   built skies:
               —Or for some priuate ends to make such men,
               As formerly distasted them: but when,
               When they were taught wing'd Pegasus to stride,
               And braue it, mounted in a pompous pride.
               —Or out of sordide, and obsceane delight
               Of riches plaie the tyrants in despight.
               —Or out of care of faire posteritie,
               Doe neither care for truth; or charitie,
               But to turne o're a greatnesse to their stock,
               Split their owne barks vpon the craggie rock
               Of a bad conscience, which cause no man sees,
               They doe proceed in 
                     •
                  inne by all degrees,
               Raising their bulwarks out of Princes powers,
               Whose sacred titles stand like strong built towers.
               —Then who dare once contro
                     ••
                  e what they will haue,
               For Kings breath honour, life, and credit saue.
               —But Kings may be abused, either from pass
                     •
                  on,
               Or will, or some misled affection:
               But worst of all from poisoning flatterie,
               Suggesting actiens 'gainst their dignitie,
               As if it treason were for to contest
               For any cause against their high behest.
               —What shall a subiect dare (say they) to finde
               A fault or scruple 'gainst the Princes minde?
               Whie are they called Gods, while 
                     •
                  hat t
                     •
                  ey li
                     •
                  e,
               And all must stoop, and knee'e, and honour giue,
               (As reason is).—But now i
                     •
                   all this coile
               Be to diuert their faire aspects, and soile
               
                  
Their first pure hearts with spots of others sinne,
               Better it were that such had neuer bin
               To blister a sweet face:—Oh this flatterie
               Is worse then Cannon shot in batterie.
               For open enimies may be withstood,
               But bruses dangerous are, that drawe no blood.
               —This vice as I remember is compared
               To certaine Asps, who when they are prepared
               To po
                     •
                  son m
                     •
                  n, as they lie fast asleep,
               Doe softhe on their bellies to them creep,
               Sword
                     •
                   about vntill they get some bare,
               Whic
                     •
                   sti
                     •
                  g they will not, but hauc greater care
               To tickle, and to licke vpon the place,
               As t
                     •
                  ey con
                     •
                  inue in their wanton race,
               Vntill they bruse their gummes, and bladders breake,
               From whence a moisture doth vpon them reake,
               Wh
                     •
                  ch at the first doth itch: but by degree
                     •
                  ,
               Before the poisoned partie knowes, or sees,
               It rankles worse then Deian ras shurt,
               And end
                     •
                  th not without or death, or hurt.
               —Euen thus good gouernment may be abused
               By 
                     
                        •
                      rinces fauorites, who still haue vsed
               This cunning tricke to keep the rest in awe
               By such strong hands as countermaund the law.
               —But to the point, if that it should be thus,
               Doe you not care, that can so well discusse
               Of vertue, goodnesse, pietie, and truth,
               Wherein you haue brought vp your fearefull youth.
               Come, come, you doe, saie what you will, you doe;
               And 
                     •
                  o, and more, doth euerie good man too,
               
                  
                  
                     •
                  ho cannot looke vpon enormities,
               
                  
                     •
                  ith such hard hearts, or stiffer dried vp eies,
               
                  
                     •
                  ut in religious sorrow send out teares,
               
                  
                     •
                  hen the good soule of such ill tiding heares:—
               
                  
                     •
                  nd saie the Eagle lifts her young ones high
               
                  
                     •
                  o look against the Sun, that she might spie,
               
                  
                     •
                  hich are not bastards, weaklings against kinde,
               
                  
                     •
                  ut if by proofe she any such doe finde,
               
                  
                     •
                  he dasheth them to ground out of the nest,
               Whereby they perish:—Thus if Kings finde out
               Who bastards are to vertue making doubt
               Of their true worth:—Themselues most worthie when
               
                  
                     •
                  hey doe discouer such polluted men,
               Casting them out like lepers from the c
                     •
                  mpe,
               Or traitours, that abuse their monie, stampe:—
               —Doth not this moue you, to see fortunes spi
                     •
                  ht
               
                  
                     •
                  y such exchange on 
                     •
                  railtie for to light,
               —Hath not our common mother nature taught,
               That men with mens afflictions are caught?
               —For though we truelie may reioice in heart,
               When Princes act so good a Princes part
               
                  
                     •
                  o punish wicked men, though they be great,
               As once Cambises did a Iudge intreat:—
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      flead 
                        •
                      Iudge.
               
               —Though we lament, when vicious men doe rise
               Within the Realme to rage and t
                     •
                  rannise:
               Yet sure men moued are with those extr
                     •
                  ames,
               As we looke strangely at the Sunnes faire beames
               Eclipsed by the moone: and though our faith
               Be nere so strong:—yet sure the Scripture saith,
               That we must feare and tremble, when we see
               
                  
By Signes and meteors, that God angrie be.
               —Here once againe you of religion talke,
               And many times doe trace in one selfe walke
               Of scorning still the rascall multitude,
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
               
               Of great mens errours, who themselues delude,
               Of praising vertue, hating auarice,
               Of selfe commending, as if none were wise,
               But such as with you could be still content
               With any fortune in her worst extent,
               Of the sure secret in diuinitie
               Mans free election h' gainst humanitie,
               And manie such like, which you oft repeat
               I think of purpose, that the purer wheat
               Banked vp with the chaffe might vndiscried,
               Or vnsnatcht at safe in the heape abide:—
               —But what doe you for your religion more,
               Then Moores &amp; Turks, who hate the worlds great sto
                     •
                  
               
               Of books, except their holie Alcheron,
               
               Which none but Priests and Doctours looke vpon:
               Nay barbarous nations are beyond you farre,
                     
                        •
                     usty.
               
               That rather will maintaine seditious warre,
               Then break a superstitious foolish rite,
               Though all the world should other truth recite.
               —But how comes in this vncouth Paradox,
               
               (To split your iudgement on presumptious rocks,
               That no man as an honest man is fit
               Either in Church or Common wealth to sit,
               That for his monie doth an office buie:
               Sure this is harsh, and no man will relie
               Vpon your censure, but remaine a loofe,
               
                  
Though that you cunning had to make the proofe.
               For either out of Scripture you must frame
               Your dang'rous structure, or maintaine the same
               With strange confusion of all Countries fashions,
               Who nere will yeeld vnto such rules and passions:
               Nay though you say, you meant Iudiciall seates,
               Where equall tongue for the poore foule intreates:
               For this distinction cannot you excuse,
               Since many great men doe all bribes refuse.
               
                  —As for preferment purchased with wealth,
               Which little better is (you say) then stealth:
               Or honours fames for preseruations sake,
               For which the world so great a stirre doth make,
               Or Countries swetnesse, when a wiseman may
               Make euerie Countrie a mans worth display:—
               —Yet what a world of men did deerelie loue
               Their Countries aboue all,
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                   scorning to moue
               One forward step into anothers land,
               But for imploiment as their case doth stand:
               Nay, though they sate in Kinglie seat,
               Yet home they must, and make a faire retreat;
               Or courtlie Office, which both good and bad
               Doe equall get, as fauours may be had;
               Or lordlie loue, which for some priuate end
               Would entertaine you for a welcome friend.
               —All these you care not for, yeelding a proofe
               That mischiefes hang in honours glittering roofe,
               Readie to fall vpon a poore mans backe,
               Worse then the tortures of a cruell racke,
               And so in these you are but thus farre grosse,
               
                  
To gaine the 
                     •
                   ore co
                     •
                  tent by suc
                     •
                   a l
                     •
                  sse:
               But 
                     •
                  s I 
                     〈◊〉
                  , haue the same repeated,
               Why is man in this earthlie house so seated?
               But to auo
                     •
                  de an idle carelesnesse,
               And make his time a map of blessednesse;
               The Church and Common weal
                        •
                     h must haue
               The
                     ••
                   seuerall rulers, to maintaine and saue
               Their faire estates, from the tumultuous hands
               Of strange disordered men, who gazing stand
               To take ad
                     •
                  antage of confusion;
               If none were rais'd for preseruation,
               If all were quiet in their Countries rest,
               Where were the state of Courts? If none addrest
               Themselues to heare a Lawier plead his case,
               What emptinesse would be in euerie place?
               If none vnto the Citie did resort,
               As now they doe for businesse, wealth, or sport;
               
                  Morositie would grow as weedes, and men remaine
               More brutish then the ha
                     •
                  sh or dogged swaine:
               Then leaue so to confine all men at home,
               Nature, and course of times make some men rome.
               —As for offences which be personall,
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
               
               Or policie which you dishonest call,
               Or other crimes, hanging on all mens cloakes
               Like shuffled dust, which blindes our e
                     •
                  es, or choak
                     •
                  s▪
               
               What can a Parliament reforme, or be
               The better to preuent necessitie:
               The world hath custo
                     •
                  es which can nere be broke,
               And men haue manners, which (though you in
                     •
                  oke
               The heauens to redresse) will haue no change,
               
                  
Though that you chide, and with inuectiues range▪
               
               In washing of a Negro, 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   not true?
               Your labou
                     •
                   m
                     •
                  ke, not any other hue:
               You may hold downe a bough, but le
                     •
                   it goe,
               And it will quickl
                     •
                  e spring, and vpwa
                     •
                  d grow:
               So play mens faults with an offensiue tong
                     •
                  e,
               They let 
                     •
                  ou talke, and thinke y
                     •
                  u doe them wrong,
               And though you ca
                     •
                  elesse are, yet all their ca
                     •
                  e
               Is for their pride of life, and be
                     •
                  ter fare;
               Say you remoue an
                     •
                   d
                     •
                  e re
                     •
                  o
                     •
                  me some men,
               What doe you purifie the places then?
               Come, come, while men their lessons doe repeat,
               The Master heares the stammering in his seat:
               Looke on faire glistring gold, it doth besmeare
               The fingers, though you thinke it nere so cleare:
               As Curtezans to fiery co
                     •
                  les compar'd
               (If men vnto their wiles are once insnar'd)
               Whi
                     •
                  h either burne, or make the fingers blacke,
               So policie for profit workes like wrack▪
               
               —And th
                     •
                  nke you Lords will sit dull at their table,None mirth Iowab
               
               If they for s
                     •
                  lace 
                     •
                  o prouide are able?
               Or Ladies want their Monkies, 'cause that you
               Est
                     •
                  eme them foppish:—They say, this is true,
               All things were made for man him to obey,
               And (as the best sort doe) why should not they
               Enioy their pleasures? Nay they can recite
               A place of Scripture to maintaine delight,
               From that same speech, or dialogue, chuse whether,
               When Barzillay and Dauid met together.—
               And thus in all things which you would depraue,
               
                  
Though you be carelesse, they a great care haue:
               As for your soule, that cannot put the
                     •
                   off,
               They to their owne must looke, at yours doe scoffe.
               
                  —You care not for a villaines confidence,
               Nor against vertue, vices impudence;
               Nor any vpstart groome, who still doth rise
               As him his gracious Lord doth Patronise,
               Nor any gentrie which of armes doe brag,
               When worth and vertue doe so lamelie lag;
               Nor to command a Prouince, though it be
               A kinde of honour due to soueraigntie.
               What of all this? You descant one true song,
               Aiming at that which goodnesse brings along,
               And you doe well:—But vertue telleth this,
               That all her triall from temptation is.
               —As women may be honest, who sit still,
               Pend in a house against proud natures will,
               Not brought abroad, or suffred once to see
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
               
               The hanging labels of dishonestie:
               So may your vertue thriue.—But swell with he
                     ••
                  
               
               O
                     •
                   pride and lust, let honour you intreat
               To sit aloft, and lie on iuorie beds,
               As noble Peeres doe rest their braine-sicke heades;
               To drinke in cups of gold, fat lambes to kill,
               Then let me see how you your selfe could will?
               We know not as you say, how your true soule
               Is wrought vpon, abuses to controule?
               So I doe say, you know not how you may
               Your resolutions alter in the day.
               
                  —Here you annex a prettie argument,
               
               
                  
In praise of valour, and with same intent,
               Against dishonest cowardice complaine,
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
               
               As a polluted wice goodnesse to staine.—
               —Yet none of both can either saue or kill
               That soule, For which did Christ the Law fulfill.
               When mongst the Iewes none were chose out to fight,
               If anies heart did faint, returne they might
               Vnto their houses, and the Gospell thus
               
                  Peter controules: still dealing so with vs,
               That we should humble be, bearing with wrong,
               Leauing reuenge to him it doth belong:
               If it be so, damnation doth not fall
               Vpon his head that will not fight at all.—
               —I speake not this by way of send excuse,
               But by degrees to come to the abuse,
               For as in valour there may be a pride,
               Which good and true reposed men deride;
               So may a coward, whom the world mistakes,
               Vertue possesse, which braine-sicke 
                     •
                  urie shakes.
               —I hope you doe not by this valour meane
               Some furious Aiax in a Tragicke Scene,
               Who rauing runnes to stricke, to kill, to stab,
               For euerie word, or lie, or mocke, or drab,
               And when he findes not any so to kill,
               With souler hands vpon himselfe fall will:—
               —Nor such you meane, that after heated braines,
               With furious eies, and raging tongues complaines
               Vpon the man, that durst abuse him so,
               Without a pledge the health to ouergoe,
               Although he see him spewing ripe alreadie,
               
                  
With 
                     •
                  taggering steps and rauings ouer headie:
               —Nor such you meane, who lo
                     •
                  king round about,
               Discouers some weake man among the rout,
               And either fals to flout him, or to 
                     •
                  corne,
               Or with some brauing gesture ouerborne,
               
                  
                     •••
                  umphs against him in an angrie fit,
               Because vnmo
                     •
                  'd, he doth in silence fit:—
               —Nor su
                     •
                  e you will that man a coward call,
               That for his God, religion, countrie shall
               Powre out his bloud: Yea for his deare friends sake,
               Or honest cause himselfe to armes betake;
               Nay though the Law be dang'rous in this kinde,
               When accidents doe chance, lags not behinde,
               And this you doe expresse,—As for the rest,
               Of traitor, villaine, base, you are not prest
               For any thing I heare for them to care,
               Therefore you may sull w
                     •
                  ll such speeches spare.
               —Now you co
                     •
                  ne in against a miserie,
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     
                  
               
               Which doth belong to Fortunes my sterie,
               The pride of 
                     •
                  ise, arising out of wealth,
               To wh
                     •
                  ch you doe oppo
                     •
                  e content with health,
               Boasting you
                     •
                   selfe to be the only man,
               That of content resound the 
                     〈◊〉
                   can,
               An
                     •
                   still you bring in vertue, of the minde,
               W
                     ••
                  ch wordly greatnesse needes must come behinde:
               All this, morall Philosophy do
                     •
                  h teach,
               But you from Scripture would the doctrine preach:
               Sure, i
                     •
                  't be so, you are a happy man,
               And may say more then any other can.
               For true content is worth a Monarchie,
               
                  
And troubles with great mischiefes hit the high:
               But as small fire suf
                     ••
                  ceth to small rost,
               So who want more then they that such things boast:
               As if a pleasure were, pleasure to scorne,
               When yet to modest pleasures we are borne:—
               —For in d
                     •
                  light
                     •
                   (as I haue often said)
               Man may reioyce, and God may be obaid:
               Yea man may hauel is fancy in each thing.
               Which doth him ease, profi
                     •
                  , or pleasu
                     •
                  e bring,
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
               
               Whether it bookes, or hawkes, or horses be,
               Or shooting, hunting, or a pl
                     •
                  y to see:
               I make no doubt a man may doe all this
               Without offence:—So that his ai
                     •
                  e not misse,
               And he which sha
                     •
                  l oppose his faire delight,
               Censured will be 
                     〈…〉
                   s
                     •
                  ight.
               For how can man in vertue so exce
                     •
                  l,
               That he is certaine alwayes to d
                     •
                  e we
                     •
                  l.
               
                  —The next of note,
                  
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                   you carelesly deny
               Is kinred whom the State hath rais'd on high:
               Who in their pride vouchsafe not to looke back
               Vpon their poore all
                     •
                  e, that all things lacke:
               Nay, now they scorne to iustifie their blood,
               But will 
                     •
                  ome auncient Pedegree make good:—
               —And though a brothers sonne approach him neare,
               Yet will not he his cause by that name heare,
               Sure, 'tis not well; if any such there be,
               That are asham'd their poorest kin to see.
               —But if that God will meane men so aduance,
               Whether for vertue or some other chance;
               
                  
What's that to you; they care not for your care,
               Nor ye
                     •
                   regard, how that you carelesse are.
               —For if you stand to boast how you were borne,
               As well as they, take heed of spight and scorne:
               The better course is their good will to try,
               And not by carelesnesse them to defie.
               What doe you know, as Mordichai did saie,
               Whether that God did bring them to this waie
               Euen for your good:—It may be that his p
                     •
                  ide
               With other Vices, which in him reside:
               Shall turne to all the profit of his kin,
               For thus with God the former crimes haue bin.
               
                  —You follow then to hunt a Prodigall,
               
               As he is glorious, and a foole withall:
               Faith spare your labour, and you soone shall s
                     •
                  e,
               How for the sa
                     •
                  e he punished will be:
               —If yet you will reforme him without cost,
               There is a while nought but your labour lost;
               Vntill his franticke humour be out spent,
               And the
                     •
                   comes shame and wants incontinent:
               Yea such as worshipt him vnto his face,
               Will, if they meet him, geere at his disgrace:
               But if you would vnto the world descrie,
               Your carelesse resolution to denie
               Such simple Guls, what cares the world for this;
               They wish you were better emploide iwis.
               —Next thing you talke of is Opinions blast,
               Which suddenlie is spent and ouer-cast;
               And so not to be cared for:—Yet still
               Your fingers itch at Vertue with a will
               
                  
                  
                     •
                  o haue the world regard your deerest loue,
               
                  
                     •
                  o that which God and godlie men approue.
               
                  —You add
                        •
                     
                   withall, how no harsh discontentDisconttent.
               
               Can weake your bow, that is so strongly bent,
               
                  
                     •
                  ut rather make you fit for such a triall,
               
                  
                     •
                  s shall maintain
                     •
                  y your faith without deniall.
               —I little say,—For twentie times at least
               
                  
                     •
                  ou haue invited vs to such a feast;
               
                  
                     •
                  esides; I manie things do ouer-passe
               
                  
                     •
                  r feare of mischiefe, which must ne
                     •
                  ds alasse
               
                  
                     •
                  icken a cloud of some displeasure, when
               
                  
                     •
                  nsorious searchers bring iudicious men
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   ouer-looke the fardell of your braine
               
                  
                     •
                  king it ill, that thus you dare maintaine
               
                  
                     •
                  ch arrogant positions against reason,
               
                  
                     •
                  eing that wisedome may come out of season:—
               —For so a dangerous passage next you make,
               
                  
                     •
                  d doe a slender barke to stormes betake
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   a stu
                     •
                  'd Ocean, bringing on a stage
               
                  
                     •
                  ur former fortunes, but in such a rage,
               
                  
                     •
                  at you spare none that in your Tragedie
               
                  
                     •
                  ere Actors to encrease your miserie:
               —But I will spare to talke of this at all,
               
                  
                     •
                  d grant the weakest be not thrust to wall:
               I wish you Vertue thriue: but as I liue.
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   hot a zeale will many scandals giue,
               
                  
                     •
                  sedome directs good Counsell to bestow,
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   man must not proclaime all he doth know.
               
                  
                     •
                   For when the Frog did with the Bullocke swell,
               
                  
                     •
                  dash't his braines out, and so dead he fell.
               
                  
                  —You draw at last to some conclusion,
               
               But stronger then the whole confusion
               You haue failed in:—No griefe shall you amate
               No sorrow,
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                   discontent, your mind rebate,
               No pouerty, distresse, you
                     •
                   friends despight,
               As if in misery you tooke delight:
               —Su
                     •
                  e th
                     •
                  s is much: Iob dealt not with vs so,
               He did with humbler steps and paces go,
               He cride his flesh was not a chimney stocke,
               His bones of brasse, his head a bea
                     •
                  ing blocke,
               His sides of Adamant, his eies of stone,
               His heart of marble hard:—Yet you alone
               Dare challenge terrour to fight hand to h
                     •
                  nd,
               As in the Giants warre:—Where men did stand
               To tosse the rocks against the lightning 
                     〈◊〉
                  ,
               And with Typhaeus, Iupiter defie:—
               
                  —You doe not care for Fortune in her glory,
               To pull downe prouder hearts:—It is your story
               To be recorded for a man of wonder,
               That could as well liue Atlas burthen vnder,
               As once endure such mischiefes you relate,
               Or anxious sorrowes appointed by Fate:
               —Why, what are you, that dare aduenture thus,
               Did euer man the matter so discusse:
               —The Prophets in times past did beare it out,
               Yet of their frailties vrged many a doubt:
               The Iewes who daily for their Law did 
                     •
                  ight
               Allowed their errours, and the stronger might:
               The blest Apostles had as great a faith,
               And yet they stagger'd, as the Scripture faith:
               
                  
                  
                     •
                  he Martynes I con
                     •
                  esse did constant die,
               
                  
                     •
                  ut yet they were afraid in Giues to 
                     •
                  e,
               
                  
                     •
                  ther good Saint
                     •
                   were glad of some reliefe,
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   many times aff
                     •
                  o
                     •
                  t d at the
                     •
                   griefe.
               —If Ieremy were with you face to face,
               
                  
                     •
                  e tell you would the dungeon were a place
               
                  
                     •
                  f mire and death: and so I make no doubt,
               
                  
                     •
                  e was full glad, when he was helped out:
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   Whales vast belly was another hell,
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  Ionas, thinke you, merrily there dwell:
               
                  
                     •
                  nd yet you care not, if your case were such,
               
                  
                     •
                  ou could endure:—Well, this is too too much,
               
                  
                     •
                  nd may with lesser smarts your vertue tire:
               
                  
                     •
                  hy man, you haue but toucht a smoaking fir
                     •
                  :
               
                  
                     •
                  t take you heed of such a Monarches rage,
               
                  
                     •
                  at shall an Ouen heat, or you engage
               
                  
                     •
                   fury of wilde beasts:—How then you fare,
               
                  
                     •
                  annot tell, but I beleeue you care:—
               
                  
                     •
                   As for your Muse which you do boast so much
               
                  
                     •
                  d carelesse are who it pe
                     •
                  use, or touch:
               
                  
                     •
                  m your example I do ouerpasse,
               
                  
                     •
                  d gentlie leaue it wi
                     •
                  h you, as it was:
               
                  
                     •
                  ur Epilogue, Postscript, and Epigram
               
               
                  
                     ••
                  ane not now in any sort to name.
               
                  
                     •
                   I protest, if you do
                     •
                   wish the same
               
                  
                     •
                  oke more after Charity, then Fame:
               
               
                  
                     •
                  d pray with all my hea
                     •
                  t, faire calmes may be
               
                  
                     •
                  spicious to your iournie, that you see
               
                  
                     •
                   blacker skie:—For Ahabs little cloud
               
                  
                     •
                  d quickly raise the windes to speake aloud.—
               
                  
And so farewell.—Yet would you would prepar
                     •
                  
               
               Another song, that you hereafter 
                     •
                  are▪
               
            
            
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   honor, &amp; laudes, &amp; laeto glori
                     •
                   vultu,
               
                  
                     •
                  tdecus, &amp; niue is victoria concolor alis.
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   cunctus lauro perducit ad astra triumphus,
               Castam
                     •••
                   d
                     •
                  mus, &amp; celso stant colle penates.
            
            Silius Ital. lib. 15.
de bel: Punico.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

