
   
      
         
            A sermon preached on Sundaye, being the .17. of March Anno. 1577. at S. Alpheges Church within Creplegate in London, by William Fulke doctor in diuinitie. Seene and allowed, accordyng to the order appoynted in the Queenes Maiesties Iniunctions
            Fulke, William, 1538-1589.
         
         
            
               1577
            
         
         Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2004-08 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01331
            STC 11454
            ESTC S112799
            99848042
            99848042
            13115
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01331)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13115)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 243:02)
         
         
            
               
                  A sermon preached on Sundaye, being the .17. of March Anno. 1577. at S. Alpheges Church within Creplegate in London, by William Fulke doctor in diuinitie. Seene and allowed, accordyng to the order appoynted in the Queenes Maiesties Iniunctions
                  Fulke, William, 1538-1589.
               
               [72] p.   
               
                  [By T. Dawson and T. Gardiner] for Lucas Harryson,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  [1577]
               
               
                  Printers' names from STC; publication date from colophon.
                  Running title reads: A learned and fruitful sermon preached by D. Fulke.
                  Signatures: A-D E⁴.
                  reproduction of the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  16th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2004-02
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2004-03
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2004-04
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2004-04
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2004-07
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               ❧A SERMON
preached on Sundaye,
being the. 17, of March
Anno. 1577. at S. Alpheges
Church within Creplegate in
London, by William Fulke
Doctor in Diuinitie. 
            
            Seene and allowed, accordyng
to the order appoynted in
the Queenes Maiesties
Iniunctions.
            ¶Imprinted at London
for Lucas Harryson.
            
         
         
            
            
            To the Right worshipfull
M. Robert Foorth
of Butley in Suffolke
Esquyer.
            
               YOur good
wyl towardes
mee testifyed
by
many benefites
(ryght
woorshypfull)
hath
many wayes deserued that I should
shewe my selfe thankfull vnto you
for the same. But chiefly your great
loue of the Gospell, ioyned wyth
many godly vertues accompanying
the same, procureth the loue
and good will not onely of such as
haue tasted of your beneuolence,
but also of manye other which
knowe you not in person, wherby
both thankes is giuen to God by

manye for your godly zeale and
prayers to him are made for your
encrease therein, and preseruance
vnto the ende. And for a publike
signification of my good wyll and
thankfull mynde towardes you, I
haue thought good to present this
Sermon vnto you, which by great
importunitie of diuers of my godly
friendes, I was constreyned to
put in writing, nothing doubting
but you wil accept it as thankfully,
as it was ment of mee duetifully.
The Lorde preserue you and all
yours in his feare, with increase of
godly worship in this lyfe, to the
rewarde of eternall felicitie at the
commyng of our sauiour Christ,
which you with al the children of
God, both loue &amp; pray for, to whō
be all honour and glory both nowe
and euer.
            
               Your worships to commaunde in
the Lord William Fulke.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
               ❧A Sermon preached
on Sunday, being the. 17. of
Marche, Anno. 1577. at S.
Alpheges Churche within
Creplegate in London, by
William Fulke, doctor
in Diuinitie.
            
               Galat. 4.
               
                  
                     Vers. 21 Tell mee you that wyl be vnder
the Lawe, doo yee not heare
the Lawe?
                  22 For it is written that Abraham had
two Sonnes, one by a bōdwoman,
and one by a free woman.
                  23 But he whiche was of the bondwoman,
was borne after the flesh: and
he whiche was of the free woman,
was borne by promise.
                  24 Whiche thinges are figuratiuely vnderstoode.
For these are the two
Testamentes, the one from mount
Sinay, begettyng vnto bondage,
which is Agar.
                  25 (For Agar is the mount Sinay in Arabia,
and answeareth to that Ietusalem
which is nowe,) and is in

bondage, with her chyldren.
                  26 But Ierusalem whiche is aboue, is
free: which is the mother of vs al.
                  27 For it is written, Reioyce thou barren
that bearest no chyldren:
breake foorth and crye, thou that
trauaylest not: for the desolate
hath many mo chyldren then shee
which hath an husbande.
                  28 Therefore brethren, wee after the
maner of Isaac, are children of the
promise.
                  29 But as then he that was borne after
the flesh, persecuted hym that was
borne after the spirite, euen so is it
nowe.
                  30 But what sayth the Scripture? Put
out the seruaunt and her sonne:
for the sonne of the seruaunt shall
not be heyre with the sonne of the
free woman.
                  31 Then brethren, wee are not children
of the seruaunt, but of the Free
woman.
               
            
            
            
               AFter that the Apostle
hathe by
many pithie and
substantiall reasons
proued the
abrogatiō of the
Lawe, and the
Iustification of
man by fayth only
in Christ: Now dooth he in this Text by
the example of the two Sonnes of Abraham,
describe and set foorth before theyr
eyes, the state of both sortes of men, as wel
them that seeke to be iustified by their own
woorkes, as of them that trust only in the
mercy of God. His purpose is not by
this comparison to proue eyther the abolishing
of the lawe, or the iustification by
fayth, for that he hath done plentifully before,
but onely to shewe the Galathians
what they shall gayne, if they proceede as
they beganne, to lay vpon themselues the
vnnecessary and vntollerable burden of the
lawe, namely the rewarde of Ismael, that
is, too bee banished from the Church of
GOD, and the Heauenly inherytaunce▪
               
whereas they that wyll obteyne the inherytaunce
with Isaac, must become as hee
was, altoogether Children of the promise.
            And firste of all hee imputeth their errour
too ignoraunce: Come of, sayeth hee,
and Tell mee, you that will needes bee
vnder the Lawe, when you neede not, doo
you heare the Lawe: doo you knowe the
Lawe? as though hee shoulde saye, I
see verily, that you are ignoraunt of the
Lawe, although you woulde neuer so fayne
bee vnder the Lawe: for if you knewe the
Lawe, and whyther it woulde brynge you,
and from what it woulde hynder you,
doubtelesse you woulde not be, so ready too
take the yoke vppon you. You imagine
too gette freedome by submyttyng your
selues vntoo the Lawe, but that is the very
waye too brynge you intoo perpetuall
bondage. You haue an eye too rewarde,
when you seeke too meryte, but whyle you
seeke too haue it by deserte, which you can
not, you leese it, beeing offered by gyfte,
which you myghte atteyne. And all thys
commeth, bycause you knowe not the
Lawe, for no man wyll wyttingly and
willyngly depryue hymselfe of rewarde,

and thruste hymselfe intoo eternall chraldome.
See therefore what commeth
of ignoraunce the Mother of Popyshe deuotion,
and of all errour and superstition,
false Doctrine, and Idolatrie.
            The Papistes are wyse in theyr generation,
when they will not haue the people
too knowe the mysteries of their owne
Popishe Religion. For I am perswaded,
that a great number which nowe contynue
in blyndenesse, if they dyd see that
which they handle in the darke, they would
repent that euer they touched it, yea, they
would detest it as much as he that for lacke
of lyghte putteth a toade in hys bosome,
in steade of a byrde, or which taketh vp
dounge in steade of goulde, or drynketh
Poyson in steade of Wyne, when hee
seeth howe hee hath beene deceyued.
And therefore I maye saye too them, as
the Apostle dooth too the Galathians.
Tell mee, you that long too bee vnder
the Pope, doo you knowe what Popery
meaneth? Doo you knowe whyther it
wyll carye you? I am perswaded, if
you knewe, a great number of you would
soone haue doone with it. But alas howe

should you knowe? Your masters hold best
you should not knowe, fearing you woulde
not follow them,Iohn. 4. if you sawe whither they
led you. And of vs you will not learne, for
so your masters teache you to worship you
wote not what, and wilfully to refuse all instruction,
whereby you myght be learned
to worship God aright: Howbeit this is
most true, thinke of it as you will, The ende
and drift of Poperie is to carye you from
Christ, and so from God, vnto whom there
is no accesse but by Christ. For that I may
bring so many cōtrouersies as are between
the Christians and the Papistes into one,
what other thing doo wee striue for in all
our preachings, but that Christ onely should
be our perfect sauiour &amp; redeemer? What
other thing is sought throughout al partes
of Poperie, but that Christ onely shoulde
not be our King, Sauiour, Redeemer,
hygh Priest, sacrifice and propiciation for
our sinnes, mediatour and aduocate, and his
worde our onely sufficient instruction? But
that the Pope, the Masse, our owne merites,
the merites of Sainctes and inuocation
of them, Popishe ceremonies, traditions,
counsels, decrees and decretals, pardons

and Images, &amp; such like, must needes
challenge no small portion of that honour
and glory, which the holy scripture maketh
proper to God and our sauiour Christ alone.Apoca. 7. 10.
               Saluation be ascribed to him that sitteth
vpon the throne of our God, and to the
Lambe. It is the voyce of all them that
are saued by Christ: And therefore all the
Angelles of God, and all the creatures of
God, ioyne with them in confessyng, that al
blessyng, glorye, wisedome, thankesgeuyng,
honour, might, and power ought
to be ascribed to hym for euer and euer.
Consider this you papistes for your owne
benefite, learne to knowe what poperie is,
before you determine to dye therein. And
as in this general controuersie I haue called
the papistes to knowledge and consideration
of their owne groundes and principles,
so might I runne through euery particular
errour of theirs: But one or two
may serue for examples: Tell me you that
would eate the naturall body of Christ in
the sacrament, doo you knowe what absurdities
doo followe of it? O you thinke it a
goodly matter to receiue the body of Christ
into your mouthe. But if you had wit, you

woulde thinke it muche better to receiue
Christ into your hartes, and so to receiue
him, that he should neuer depart frō thence,
for he dwelleth in our hartes by fayth.
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  . 3. 17.
And so doo wee teache men to receiue the
body of Christ by fayth, that he may dwell
with vs for euer: Whereas they that teach
you to receiue the naturall body into your
mouthes, giue no more to fayth, then to infidelitie:
for wicked men, as they saye, receiue
the body of Christ as well as the godly:
you will say, yea, but it taryeth not with
the wicked. No more it doth with the faithfull
by your owne doctrine, for you haue not
yet determined howe farre it goeth downe
into the stomacke of man, nor howe long it
abydeth, but you all agree, that it abydeth
no longer then the fourmes of breade and
myne remayne vncorrupt, which is not
long after they come into the stomacke: but
this is not all the absurditie that followeth
of that eating. For whyle you streine the
body of Christ into so small a compasse, and
multiply the same into so manye places,
what else doo you, but ouerthrow the truth
of his naturall body? Which if it be not
like ours in all things, except sinne, then

coulde it be no redemption of our bodyes.
Then haue we no hope of resurrection, nor
assumption into heauen, which is grounded
vpon the truth of this naturall body, being
fleshe of our fleshe, and bone of our bone, in
which our nature he suffered death, rose againe,
and ascended into heauen for vs.
But I may not stand vpon these matters.
Tell me you that woulde fayne heare your
olde Latin seruice, doo you knowe what it
was? Uerely a great part of it was such
as you woulde bee ashamed to heare it in
Englishe. But if it had bene nothing else
but the Scriptures of God, and godly
prayers, yet the Apostle in his Epistle to
the Corinthians telleth you plainly, that
beyng in a tongue vnknowen, it were not
meere for the Church of God. But to leaue
the Papistes, and returne to the Galathians:
Tell mee, sayth S. Paule, you that
would be vnder the lawe, doo you heare
the lawe, or haue you read the lawe? &amp;c.
As if he should say, take no heede what men
beside the booke teache you of the lawe, but
looke to the lawe it selfe. The false Apostles
would haue borne the Galathians in
hand, that they must ioyne the obseruation

of the lawe with the fayth of the Gospell:
They woulde not bring them altogether
from Christ, but they woulde match the ceremonies
of Moyses lawe, with the fayth
of Christ. Wherefore the Apostle wylleth
them to looke what the lawe sayth, and not
what these counterfeyt lawyers sayde. He
willeth them to examine the lawe, whether
it admitteth or alloweth any such mixture
as they woulde bring in, or no? The lyke,
and in a manner the same controuersie, wee
haue nowe with the Papistes, sauing that
the Papistes as verie Antichristians, are
worse then the false Apostles. They agree
both in this, that they ioyne workes wyth
Christ, merits with mercy, man with God,
in the meane of our saluation: but herein
the false Apostles were lesse hurtfull, that
they ioyned the workes of the lawe which
God himselfe required, the Papistes ioyne
works of Superero
                  •
               ation, which are such
as God neuer commaunded, and preferre
them as much more meritorious, then any
workes which God hath prescribed. They
both agree in this, that they place righteousnesse
in the obseruation of Ceremonies:
but the Papistes are more blasphemous

then those false Apostles. For they, although
they placed righteousnesse in Ceremonies,
yet it was in such ceremonies as
God himselfe appoynted to be obserued for
a time: but the Papistes place instification
in ceremonies which were neuer of Gods
institution: for Circumcision, the passouer,
with other sacrifices, and rytes of the olde
Testament, had God for their Author: but
holy water, holybread, Pilgrimages and
such like, had neither God nor good man
for theyr founder, but came from Antichrist
the enemye of GOD and Christ.
            And therefore you that would be vnder
the Lawe, looke well to your footyng whether
you stande vpon good grounde, for if
righteousnesse come by the Lawe, then
commeth it by suche deedes onely as the
Lawe commaundeth. And if a man may
be iustified by obseruation of Ceremonies,
they must bee such Ceremonies as GOD
hath required, when euen of those which he
hymselfe required, beeing doone otherwise
then hee meant them, hee sayeth:Esay. 1. 1
                     •
                  . 
               Who
hath required these thyngs at your handes?
At whose handes doo you looke too
receyue the rewarde of righteousnes? is it

not of hym that hath taught you the rule of
ryghteousnesse? Therefore if you wilbe iustifyed
by the Law, looke what be the workes
&amp; Ceremonies of the lawe &amp; keepe thē,
for god hath not promised the reward but to
hym that obserueth them. The man (sayth
hee) that dooth them, shall lyue in them.
Geue not eare therefore too the Papistes,
but geue eare too the Lawe, if you hope
too wynne rewarde by obseruing the lawe.
And especially in that poynt, wherein the
false Apostles of Sainct Paules tyme, and
the false Apostles of our tyme, agree, that
is, ioyning mans merit with Gods mercy.
Tell mee, you that refuse too bee cleerly see
at lybertie from the bondage of the Lawe
by Christe, and wyll needes bee vnder the
Lawe, doo you know the Lawe? Can you
tell whether God wyll allowe suche a mixture,
or no, of woorkes and grace, of mercy
and merits? If the condition of the lawe
will beare suche a medley, no man forbiddeth
you, but that you maye seeke righteousnes
where it may best bee founde: but if
the condition of the Lawe bee so streight,
as it will admit nothyng but a perfecte obseruation
in him that shall haue the reward,

why will you seeke too establish your owne
righteousnes, and so void your selues cleane
of the righteousnes of God in Christ? And
so whyle you wyll bee iustifyed both by
Christe and by the woorkes of the Lawe,
you shalbee iustifyed neyther by Christe,
nor by the woorkes of the Lawe. For the
Lawe can abyde no transgression, nor the
grace of Christ any satisfaction. And yet
there is perfect righteousnesse in the obseruation
of the law: And a mā is iustified by
faith, without the works of the law. Wherupon
the deuils sophistrie concludeth, that
if iustification be by either of these meanes
by it selfe, much rather it must be whē they
are both ioyned together. Wherefore wee
must see whether they may be ioyned together,
or no. Let vs therefore first heare the
lawe. The lawe in deede is a perfect rule
of righteousnesse to iustifie, not the hearers,
but the obseruers: The man that dooth
all thinges commannded by the Lawe,
shall lyue thereby, that is, by his ryghteousnesse
hath deserued eternall lyfe. But
here is a perfect obseruation requyred, or
else no ryghteousnesse obteyned, no life deserued:
for cursed is hee that abydeth not

in all the preceptes of the lawe to doo them.
So that here appeareth a double condition
annexed to the lawe. The one is an absolute
and perfecte obseruation required of
them that shall be rewarded: the other euerlasting
curse and damnation threatned
to him that hath transgressed. By which
it is most euident, that the Lawe and the
Gospell, grace and woorkes, merite and
mercye, bee of so contrarie nature, as
it is impossible they shoulde bee ioyned together
in the atteyning of eternall saluation.
One transgression if there were but
one in a mannes whole lyfe, and that
neuer so small, yet such is the rygour of the
lawe, as it barreth vs from ryghteousnes,
and maketh vs subiect to the sentence of
Gods cursse. Now let vs on the other side
consider the Gospell, and see whether that
admitteth any mixture of deedes of the
Lawe. By the Gospell we are assured,
               Ephes. 2.
               that wee are saued by grace: but grace is
a woorde of such freenesse, as it ceasseth
to bee grace, if you adde anye thyng to
it. If it bee of woorkes) sayth the Apostle)
then is it not of grace, and if it
bee of grace, then is it not of workes: for

grace were not grace, if it were not free.
And it coulde not bee truely sayde, that
we are iustified freely by his grace through
the redemption of Christ Iesus, if anye
thyng in the worlde came in place of satisfaction
besides the redemption of Christ
Iesus▪
               Rom. 3. But let vs heare what the lawe
sayth: It is written in the lawe (for so are
all the fyue bookes of Moyses accompted)
that Abraham had two sonnes, one of a
bondmayde, another of a free woman,
the one called Ismael, the other named
Isaac. Ismael was borne of Agar the Egyptian,
which was a bondwoman,
Isaac was borne of Sara the wyfe of Abraham,
which was a free woman: such
as Agar the mother was, such was Ismael
her sonne, and Isaac was free, as
his mother Sara was.
            
            Fyrst wee must obserue here, that this
comparison is altogether within the familie
of Abraham, that was a fygure
of the Churche of GOD. And therefore
wee muste not seeke Ismaell and
hys posteritie among them that are altogether
wythout the Churche, and professe
open hatred agaynst the same:

But euen in the bosome of the visible
Churche, euen in the family of Abraham,
those that professe themselues to bee the
sonnes of Abraham, that is, the sonnes of
God, and occupie no small ro
                  •
               mes in the
Churche, but euen the highest oftentimes,
as Ismael for a season beyng the first borne
of Abraham was accompted as the heyre
of Abraham, and so the most principal person
in all the housholde. Wherefore if we
wil at this day know who be the Ismaelits,
we must not looke to the profane nations of
the Turkes and misereantes, that openly
despise the Churche of God, but euen to
those that make the boldest and lowdest
clayme to be heyres of the Churche, euen
the Papistes. They haue their profession,
so had Ismael, they haue their tytle, so had
Ismael, they stand vpon their prerogatiue,
and so dyd Ismael. They will haue a place
in the familie of Abraham, yea they wyll
thrust out Isaac. They claime (they say) by
the elder tytle, to be heyres of the Churche,
yea they weene they haue the Churche it
selfe in possession. And here it is marueilous
howe they swell and stande vppon typtoes,
if you seeme to allowe them any place

at all in the Church, though it be but in the
Belfrey, they will streight way perke vp
into the Chancell. But softe a whyle my
masters, we allowe you no other place in
the Churche of God, then that which Ismael
sometymes occupyed in the familie of
Abraham. And that in deede was no base
roome in outwarde appearance, and in the
iudgement of men. For who was thought
to be the heyre of Abraham for sixteene or
seuenteene yeeres, but Ismael, the eldest
sonne of Abraham? You, who seemed to
haue more right vnto the inheritance of Abraham,
then he that had the prerogatiue of
the first begotten. But all the sonnes of Abraham
are not the heyres of Abraham.
For it is written: In Isaac shall thy seede
be called. Wherefore we must not regard
who maketh clayme to the inheritance of
Abraham, but who is rightly begotten to
be the heire of Abraham: for a bond man is
capable of no inheritance. And the child is
accompted in the ciuill law, of such condition
as his mother is. Therefore Ismael being
borne of a bond woman, hath no iust tytle
to be the heyre of Abraham, though he
pretend to be his eldest sonne. And he that

was borne of the free woman, though hee
were younger by many yeeres, yet by the
prerogatiue of his free byrth, became the
heyre of Abraham his Father. Wherefore
if the Papists and all they that seeke to bee
iustifyed by their workes, be proued to bee
the sonnes of the bond woman, it wyll not
helpe them any thing in the world, that they
haue of long tyme beene accompted as
principal members of the familie of Abraham:
for it will fall out in the ende, that
they shall be found no better then Ismaelits
and Agarynes, and haue the same rewarde
that Agar and Ismael had.
            We haue heard now, that Abraham had
two sonnes, of which, the one only was hys
heire. And now let vs see why Ismael being
the naturall sonne of Abraham, &amp; the first
borne, was not the heire, either before Isaac
or at leastwise ioyntly with him: here indeede
standeth all the matter of controuersie,
although there be two sonnes, why there
is but one heyre, but it is soone answered,
because there is but one way to come to the
inheritance, and that is onely by promyse,
only by mercy, only by fayth. So the cause
now followeth, why Ismael could not be Abrahams
               
heir, and only Isaac was: because
Ismael was borne after the flesh, and Isaac
was borne by promyse. The inheritance
depended wholly vpon the promise, and the
promise altogether vpon the grace of god.
Therefore he that was borne after the promise,
was the heire, &amp; not he that was borne
after the flesh. But this at the first view, seemeth
to be straunge, why S. Paule shoulde
say, that Ismael was borne after the fleshe,
&amp; Isaac by promise. Wheras there seemeth
to be no difference, but that Isaac was born
after the fleshe, as Ismael was, for he was
conceiued after the maner of al the worlde,
as Ismael was. It is the only priuiledge of
our sauiour Christ to be cōceiued by the holy
ghost. Wherfore Isaac might be thought
to be borne after the flesh, on the other side it
seemeth that Ismael was borne by promise.
For Abrahā
                was not moued by fleshly lust
to take Agar to his wyfe, but by the suggestion
of Sara, that he might haue an heyre of
the promise. Why should not Ismael then
(whose byrth was sought by so good an intent)
bee saide to be borne after the promyse?
And wherefore should Isaac bee denyed
to be borne after the flesh, whē he was

conceyued and borne as Ismael and all other
men are? But let vs heare what the
Apostle sayth: He that was borne of the
bond woman, was borne after the fleshe,
and hee that was borne of the free woman,
by promise. Nowe let vs see howe
Ismael was borne after the fleshe, &amp; Isaac
by promise. If we looke to the conception
of Ismael, we shall see nothing in it, but
carnall and fleshly, not only because it was
altogether according to the course of nature:
but also &amp; chiefly because this deuise
of Sara, wherunto Abraham consented to
beget children of Agar, though it seemed to
come of a good intent, yet was it altogether
carnall and fleshly. But God woulde haue
mans deuise to haue no place in the Natiuitie
of Isaac, because he should be a ryght
figure and patterne of them that are heires
of the promise. For thus the case stood, God
had promised to Abraham to giue him the
lande of Canaan, and to his seede, which
shoulde be as the starres of heauen, and as
the sande of the sea innumerable, that hee
should be the father of many nations, and
that in his seede all the nations of the world
should be blessed.
            
               
Now Abraham beleeued this promise
of God, and it was imputed to hym for
righteousnes, bu
                  •
                whyle he contynued stedfaste
in this Fayth, GOD seemed too suspend
of long tyme the performance of hys
promyse, for Abrahā
                waxed old, Sara was
both olde and barreyne, so that all hope of
Children betweene them seemed too be cut
of: at laste, thys deuyse came intoo Saraes
head, that Abraham shoulde take Agar the
Aegiptian her bondemayde too wyfe, and
so of her should begette Childrē that should
bee heyres of the promise. No doubte her
ende and purpose was to obteyne that
which God had promysed, and in suche respect
and none other, dyd Abraham agree
too her deuise. And here we see what good
intents are, if they be not directed by Gods
woorde. For surely the intent of Abraham
&amp; Sara in this matter, was exceeding good:
but theyr mean which they had deuised, was
starke nought. For it was altogether beside
the word of God: it proceded not frō the spirit
of God, but frō the spirit of man, frō flesh
and blood, and therefore it was a mere carnall
and fleshely deuise, &amp; although it hath
a shewe of great godlynes, yet is there no

spark of godlines in it, for it proceeded not of
faith, but of infidelity: for although Sara beleeued
the promise of God to bee true, yet she
thought it could not otherwise be performed
but by this carnall deuise of hers: she would
helpe god to perfourme his promise, whē she
thought he was flack in perfourmāce, &amp; saw
more &amp; more difficulty to grow dayly by the
age of Abrahā
                encreasing in weaknes &amp; old
yeares, vnapt for generatiō, &amp; such are al the
deuises of mē, by which they sek to obtein the
promised inheritāce of the kingdom of heauē
they be altogether carnal &amp; fleshly, &amp; procede
ōly of infidelity. For why do they sek to adde
any thing of their own to the most free &amp; gracious
promise of god, but that they doubt eyther
of his strength or goodwil to perfourme
that which he hath promised? &amp; therfore they
wil help the one wt laying to the shoulders of
their own strēgth &amp; the other they wil procure
by cōmending the dignity and worthines of
their owne persons, as though God were not
throughly wel pleased in his only begottē son
our Lord &amp; sauiour Christ. By this that hath
been said, I trust you do now vnderstād, how
Ismael was born after the flesh, namely that
in his conceptiō &amp; generation, there can nothing
be cōsidered that is heauēly &amp; spiritual,

but altogether natural &amp; carnal. For notwithstāding
ther was an intēt &amp; purpose to beget
an heir of the promis, yet euē this intēt &amp; purpose,
being gouerned by a carnal &amp; fleshly deuise,
proued nothing els, but an earthly, carnall,
&amp; fleshly matter. Wherfore he that was
borne of the bond woman, was borne altogether
after the flesh. Now let vs see how Isaac
was borne by promise. Isaac was born of Sara
the free womā: not by her carnal deuise as
his brother Ismael was, but by faith in gods
promise. For Abraham was now old, &amp; past
the strength of begetting childrē, Sara was
both old &amp; barren, here nature had denied thē
children: flesh &amp; blood had denied thē childrē:
humayn reason had denied thē childrē. Therfore
the childe that was now conceyued and
borne, came altogether by promis of God, &amp;
not by strength of man. Abrahā
                waxed nowe
strōg in fayth, though weake in body, &amp; considered
neither his own body as good as dead,
nor the dead wōbe of Sara his wife, but only
beleeued that he which had promised, was also
able to perfourme it. And Sara by faith receiued
strēgth to cōceiue seed; &amp; brought forth
a son when she was past childbearing &amp; barrein,
bicause she compted him faithful,Ebru. 11. 
                     ••
                  . which
had promysed so, that the whole woorke in

the conception and birth of Isaac, was proper
to God, and not to man, and so dyd the
whole prayse red
                  •
               unde to God, and not to
man. For Abrahams body beyng now as
good as dead for age, receyued new strēgth
for generation, as if he had been restored
from death to lyfe. Sara, beside her natural
impediment of barrainnesse being taken
away, whiche kept her from bearyng
of chyldren when shee was young, beyng
nowe nyentie yeares of age, was endued
with newe strength to conceyue Isaac, and
therefore here is nothing of mans strength
or wisedome in Isaackes natiuitie to bee
considered, but onely the perfourmance of
Gods promise. And therefore God onely
deserued to haue al the prayse▪ Whereas
if Ismael shoulde haue inherited the promyse,
the lea
                  •
               t portion of the prayse should
haue been geuen to God. For nature
shoulde haue had one part, because Abraham
although he were old when he begate
Ismael, yet he was not so olde, that he was
past the strength of generation. And as
for Agar, shee was lusty, and in the flowre
of her age. What singuler prayse shoulde
God haue had in this cōception, other then

in all naturall woorkes? But the chiefe
parte of the commendation, shoulde haue
been challenged by the wysedome of man.
For if this deuise of Sara had taken place,
howe muche thinke you woulde shee haue
pleased her selfe in that witty inuention?
And Abrahams diligence and indeuour to
put in practise this inuention of theirs,
might haue been thought woorthy of no
small cōmendation. And in Ismael the title
of First begotten, woulde haue thrust in it
selfe, for some dignitie and portion of glorye.
            Amongest these matters, euery one setting
foorth it felfe as worthy of the prayse,
I pray you howe small a pittance shoulde
haue been leaft for the promise of GOD?
And as you see it here in the patternes,
so is it moste clearely to be seene in them
that followe these patternes. Whereby the
Papistes shewe them selues most playnly
to be after Ismael, chyldren of the fleshe,
the naturall sonnes of the bondwoman,
borne after the fleshe. For that they may
be heyres of the promyse, they ascribe
somethyng to nature, somethyng to mans
wisedome, somethyng to theyr owne industrie,

and by no means they wilbee perswaded,
to receyne the inheritāce altogether by
Gods promyse. To nature with the heathen
Philosophers, they attribute the beginning
of al vertues in themselues, &amp; such strength,
as without the grace of God they maye dispose
them selues to an aptnes to receiue the
grace of God, but wyth the grace of God
they may be able to perfourme whatsoeuer
God requyreth at theyr handes. By mans
wisdome, they haue founde out woorkes of
greater price and worthinesse to winne the
fauour of God, then God himselfe in hys
Lawe hath prescribed and appointed. And
as for their own labour &amp; industry, it dooth
in a manner all in all, for thereby nature is
applied to winne grace, grace is exercysed
to merite rewarde, wisdome is practised to
increase merite, which shal not only be sufficient
for those that labour in them, but also
dooth ouerflowe too the satisfaction of other
mens sinnes, and too the obteyning of
righteousnesse for other men which fayle
in the measure of their owne. In the
meane tyme, they saye they doo not exclude
the grace of God. No more dyd Ismael
the promise of God, but Ismaell coulde not

inherite the promyse of God, bycause hee
was borne after the fleshe, no more can
they hee partakers of the grace of GOD
bycause they seeke to procure it by camall
and fleshly meanes. And they only are after
Isaac heyres of the promyse, which pretende
no tycle too the promysed inherytaunce
but only the promise of GOD,
which seeke it only by grace, and not by
workes, which obteyne it by Fayth and not
by desertes.
            For neyther nature, nor the wisdome of
man, nor the strength of man, nor the worthinesse
of man, made Isaac heir of the promise,
but only Faith in the promyse. These
thynges (sayeth sainct Paule) whych are
written of the two Mothers in Abrahams
house of contrary condition, and the issue
of them both, are Allegoricall, that is figuratiuely
or typically to bee vnderstoode.
            For in as muche as Abrahams house
was the Churche of GOD, suche notable
euentes as happened in that householde,
were fygures and examples for vs
too see the state of the Churche, and dyuerse
kyndes of men therein, for all ages
followying. Wherefore as there

was a bonde woman ingendring into bondage
him that is borne after the fleshe, euen
in that familey, so hath there alwayes bene
in the outward face of the Church, a great
seede and multitude of Heretykes and Hypocrytes,
which haue sought iustificatiō by
their owne merytes. Suche wer before the
comming of Christe a great number of the
frowarde and obstynate Iewes, and in the
tyme of Christe, the Scribes and Phariseys,
which abusing the doctrine of the law,
contrary to the scope and ende of the Lawe,
sought to establishe their owne righteousnes
in obseruation and keepyng of the law:
but in the meane tyme, they became voyde
of the righteousnes of God. And yet thy did
not pretend to exclude the grace of God, as
appeareth righte well in that Phariseye of
whome our Sauiour Christ telleth the Parable
Luke. 18. against them that trusted in
themselues that they were ryghteous, and
despised other. This Pharisey trusted in
himselfe that hee was righteous, and yet
not without the grace of God. For hee geueth
God thankes that he was not as other
men were, or &amp;c. And such for al the world,
as this Pharisey was, are the whole generation

of Papistes. For they wil seeme too
ascribe much to the grace of God, in forme
of words, and almost altogether, and so dyd
the Pharisey. But yet neuerthelesse, hee
with them, and they with hym, are Ismaelites,
sonnes of the bonde woman, borne after
the fleshe, bycause they ioigne any thing
with the grace of God, which only doth triumphe
in the Saluation of all the Children
of promyse. For by grace you are saued
(sayeth the Apostle) through Fayth,
               Ephes. 
                     •
                  . 
                     •
                  . 
               and
that not of your selues, it is the gyfte of
God, not of works, least any man should
boaste. And howe is boallyng excluded?
by the lawe of workes? No but by the lawe
of Fayth. But let vs procede in the Texte.Rom
                     •
                  . 
                     •
                  . 27.
               The two Mothers (sayth s. Paule) are the
two couenāts or Testaments, that is, they
represent vnto vs the two Testamentes, or
couenants, that God hath made with mankinde
touching their Saluation. For God
hath made two couenantes, one in the
Lawe, the other in the Gospell, the one, the
couenant of Iustice, the other the couenant
of mercy. In the one he requireth perfect
righteousnesse, in the other hee offereth remission
of sinnes. And both these couenauntes

haue a necessary vse to bring vs to
saluation. The Couenauntes of Iustice,
doe shew vs what perfection of rightuousnesse
God requireth, and how farre we are
from it, to humble vs &amp; inforce vs to seeke
rightuousnesse els where then by our owne
desertes. And so the law when it is rightly
vsed, is sayde to be a Schoolemaster vnto
Christ. For God dyd not make that couenaunt
of rightuousnes with vs, to the intent
that we should obteyne righteousnesse
by obseruation of the Law, but by settinge
before our eyes, the impossibilytie of the
condition which is required to be obserued,
and the extreeme sentence of Iustice,
when the condition is broken, to driue vs
altogether from hope of attayning to the
rewarde of righteousnes by workes, and
to cause vs most ioyfully to receiue the seconde
Couenaunt of his mercy offered in
Christ. So that the law indeede prescribeth
a rule of perfect rightuousnes, if men
could obserue it, but in as much as no man
was euer able to obserue it (except our sauiour
Christ) no man euer was or shall be
iustifyed by it, but by Christ onely. And as
the couenant of Iustice doeth require perfect

righteousnesse and geueth no pardon:
so the couenant of mercy giueth righteousnes
freely, &amp; admitteth no satisfactiō. These
are those two Couenants that GOD hath
made with mankynde concerninge their
iustifycation &amp; saluation, &amp; more then these
two, he hath not made: so that he which wil
be iustifyed by the law, must looke for no
mercy: and hee that wyll be iustifyed by
grace in Christe, must not thinke of any
merit, worthynesse, or satisfaction of his
owne, but only in Iesus Christ.
            What place then haue these mongrels that
make a confusion of grace and merites,
of Fayth and Workes, of the Law and
the Gospell? They haue no place in neyther
of the two Testamentes, the olde nor
the new. If they wyll haue a thyrde way
of Iustifycation, they must shew a thyrde
Couenaunt: yf they cannot shew a thyrde
Couenant, they cannot haue a middle way
of Iustifycation.
            Wee haue shewed good euydence for
the two Couenants, the one of Iustice, the
other of mercye, and how the one Couenaunte
neyther beareth wyth anye transgressyon,
nor alloweth anye pardon,

the other admitteth no dignity of the person,
nor alloweth any satisfaction of his, for
his vnworthinesse. Let the Papistes which
wilbee iustified partly by the grace of God,
and partly by their owne merites, let them
I say nowe stande foorth, and shewe vs the
Tables of suche a couenante, if euer God
made any such with men, that he would forgyue
them halfe their sinnes, and allowe
them to make amends for thother halfe: let
them shewe their euidence if they haue any,
if they haue none, as there is none mentioned
in the Scripture, but the two Testamentes,
the two Couenantes, the lawe and
the Gospell: what tytle or clayme can they
make to the heauenly inherytance, whereof
they haue no promyse, no Testament, no couenāt,
but only a carnal perswasion of their
owne fleshely reason, an earthly Imagination
of humayne wysedome, yea an hellishe
presumption of their prowde worldly affection:
whereby they shewe themselues to bee
nothing els but Agarens and Ismaelytes,
Children of the bondewoman, and borne
after the fleshe, as Ismaell their Father
was, whose tytle and clayme vntoo the spirituall
inheritance, was altogether earthly

and carnall, vtterly voyde of the promise
and woorde of God.
            But let vs heare the Apostle descrybing
the two Couenantes. The one (sayeth
hee) is from mount Sinay, gendrying into
bondage, which is Agar. The Lawe
therfore which is the fyrst couenāt, is cōpared
to Agar, bycause it begetteth into bondage
as shee dyd, yea mount Sinay from
whence the Lawe was published, is compared
too Agar. And then the Lawe is
as it were the seede, by which, of Sinay,
that is the Church of Hypocrites, are begotten
no Children but vntoo perpetuall
bondage.
            But here nowe aryseth a doube, howe
of the lawe of GOD which is holy and
good, suche wycked and vngodly Chyldren
shoulde bee conceyued. For answer vntoo
thys doubte, wee muste vnderstande,
that not of the lawe rightely vsed, suche
vnhappie Children are begotten, for wee
knowe that the lawe is good,Tim. 1. 8. Rom. 7. 1
                     •
                  . if a man vse
it lawfullye. But when righteousnesse is
soughte by obseruation of the lawe, which
is not attayned by any man, but through
grace only, then is the lawe abused, and of

the Lawe so abused, are begotten no Children,
but hypocrites, vnto euerlasting bondage.
The Lawe is vsed rightly, when it is
made our Schoolmaster vnto Christe,Galat. 3. 2
                     •
                  
                
               that
wee may be iustified by Fayth. But when
Iustification is not sought by Fayth without
the deedes of the Lawe, but eyther by
the deedes of the Lawe onely, or by the
deedes of the Lawe and Fayth: then is the
lawe which is holy of it selfe, by this abuse,
made a corrupt seede, of which is conceyued
these bastardly Hypocrites that falsely
chalenge to bee the Sonnes of GOD.
whereas they are in deede the sonnes of eternall
sclauery and bondage. You will say,
they seeke lyberty by this meanes, and not
bondage, but certayne it is, they fynde nothyng
but bondage: what soeuer they
pretende too seeke. For such is the nature
of the lawe, that it bryngeth all men
intoo bondage, that are not set at lybertye,
by the onely meane which GOD
hathe appoynted for theyr infranchismente,
whiche is the Redemption of the
Sonne of GOD. Now when these
men that seeke too bee vnder the Lawe, refuse
the onely charter of infranchismente,

which almightye GOD dooth most mercifully
offer to gyue them freely, they are
intangled wyth double bondage, and
thraldome both that which is by nature,
whereunto all the sonnes of Adam are subiecte,
that are not set at libertie by the sonne
of GOD: and also that which groweth by
theyr omne confession, while they refuse
the freedome offered, and voluntaryly put
their neckes vnder the yoke of the Lawe,
which promiseth no lybertie, but vpon the
keeping of an impossible condition, and
threatneth certein and perpetual bondage,
for euery voluntary, &amp; yet necessary transgression.
So that it is impossible for al thē
that are vnder the Lawe, eyther to obteyne
the reward which it promiseth, or to avoyd
the punishment which it threatneth. Wherfore
mount Sinay which is Agar, &amp; the law
thus abused, begetteth no childrē, but hipocriticall
sclaues vnto euerlasting bondage.
(For Agar is mount Sinay in Arabia, and
answereth in figure too that Hierusalem
which is now, &amp; is in bondage, with her
children.) First let vs here obserue, that
manner of speeche whyche the Apostle
vseth, when hee sayeth that Agar is

the mount Sinay, whereas it is euydent
that he meaneth that Agar dooth figure or
signifie the mount Sinay. The Papistes
make great exclamation agaynst those Interpreters,
which in the woordes of consecration
as they cal them, This is my body,
doo expounde est for significat. This is my
body, that is, this bread dooth signifye my
body. And a great matter they make of the
verbe substantiue est, as though that when
soeuer it is vsed is Scripture, it declareth
a substaunce, and no fygure or sygne of a
substaunce. Howbeyt there bee infynite
places of Scripture, where thys verbe
substantiue est, can not bee otherwyse interpreted,
then for significat, and thys our
Texte is one very manifeste place. Agar
(sayth hee) is the mount Sinay in Arabia.
What? was Agar nowe chaunged into
the substaunce of a Mount? who is so
vayde of reason or sense, but he must needes
confesse, that hys meanyng is, that Agar
dooth sygnifye Mount Sinay, or is
a fygure of Mount Sinay in Arabia:
            
            Yea: but I knowe what will bee replyed.
Sayncte Paule speaketh not
here of the Sacramentes. That is true,

but when the holy Ghoste speaketh of Sacramentes,
which are holy and Heauenly
signes, it were more probable too vnderstande
hys speache fyguratiuely, and
not litterally. Yea it is most vsuall in the
Scripture, when the spirite of God speaketh
of the Sacraments, to say they bee
those thinges which they doo but represent
and signifie. As Circumcision is called
the couenant, the Lamb is called the Passouer,
Baptisme is called the newe byrth,
and S. Paule speaking of the Sacrament
of Christes blood sayth, The Rocke was
Christ: And our Sauiour Christ himselfe
sayth, This cuppe is the newe Testament.
In al which speaches there can be no transsubstantiation
and chaunge of substances
be vnderstoode, but a signe, a figure, or representation.
What then? Doo we make
the Sacramentes nothing else but bare
signes, naked figures, and imaginatiue representations?
God forbyd, it is not in
vaine that the ontwarde elementes in the
deuine Sacramentes doo beare the names
of those things which they doo represent,
but that God doth truely and in deede perfourme
his promises vnto the faithfull, of

which these Sacramentes are the seales, to
confyrme their fayth. So God in Baptisme
which is the Sacrament of regeneration,
dooth worke effectually to the mortifying
of the olde man, and renuing of the
newe man, whereby the man that is baptised,
is made the childe of God. And Christ
in the Sacrament of his bodye and blood,
dooth truely feede vs wyth hys bodye
and blood which is the onely foode of our
soules, wherby wee are nourished and preserued
vnto eternall lyfe. But to returne
to the matter: Agar in this fygure, dooth
signifye the Mount Sinay in Arabia, from
whence the Lawe of bondage was giuen,
as Sara dooth signifie the Mount Sion in
Hierusalem, from whence the Gospell of
freedome proceeded. And wee must note
here, that Sinay is a mountayne in the desart
of Arabia, where the lawe of bondage
was proclaimed. Namely we must vnderstand,
that it was altogether out of the compasse
of the land of promise. It was in the
barren wildernes, not in the land that flowed
with milke &amp; honye, It was in Arabia, &amp;
not in Canaan. So that god would signifie,
euen by the place where hee published the

law, that it perteined not to the promise of
his mercy, but to the pacte or Couenant of
his iustice. For the land of Canaan, was
the land of promise, a very fruitfull land, abundant
in all commodities and pleasures
of this lyfe, which GOD professeth oftentymes
vnto the people, that hee gaue it
them, and that without all desert or worthinesse
of theyrs, of his onely goodnesse
and mercy towards them, to fulfyll hys
promyse made to their Fathers. Forbydding
them alwayes to thinke or saye that
for theyr owne ryghteousnesse God had
chosen them, to cast out those nations before
them, putting them ofte in mynde
that they were a frowarde and stiffnecked
people, and howe many wayes they had
deserued that God shoulde vtterly haue reiected
them, as Moses preacheth to them
in Deuteronomie.
            
            Wherefore the lande of Canaan was
to them a Sacrament of the Kingdome
of Heauen, which beyng an inheritance
of most gloryous and eternall felicitie,
no man shall attayne vnto, by his owne
merytes or woorthinesse, but onely by
the mercye of God. No more then the

               Israelites were brought into the lande of
promise in respecte of their owne deseruings,
but only by the promise of GOD.
Now farre without the bondes of this holy
lande, in a deserte and solitarie place, in a
barraine and vnfruitefull soyle, where nothing
grewe for the sustentation of mannes
life, where water wanted for the necessarie
vse of man and beast, euen there God chose
a harde stonie and craggie rocke to be the
pulpet from whence he thundred out the
Lawe of Iustice, with most terrible lightes
and noyses, to signifie that by the Cavenant
of his ryghteousnesse, no man shoulde
looke for any fauour or grace, but that all
they that were founde transgressors of this
law, should vndoubtedly incurre the paines
of eternall condempnation. This was
Mount Sinay in Arabia, This was Agar
the Egyptian, This was the mother of Ifmael,
This is the nobilitie of the sonnes of
bondage.
            But he proceedeth, and. sayth that Agar
or Sinay answereth in figure or similitude
to that Hierusalem which is nowe, and is
in bondage with her children. Some translations
reade that Sinay bordereth vppon

               Hierusalem, but that is neither true in the
litterall sense, nor agreeth with the meaning
of the Apostle in this figure, nor expresseth
the Greeke worde which the Apostle
vseth. For mount Sinay dooth not border
vppon Hierusalem, but is farre distant
from it by certaine hundreth myles. But
the worde which the Apostle vseth, doth signifie
a respect or relation of one thing to an
other. And so he meaneth that Mount Sinay
hath respect to that Hierusalem which
is nowe, which is, to the earthly Hierusalem,
because the earthly Hierusalem did answer
in figure to Agar, &amp; not to Sara, to Sinay,
&amp; not to Sion. And why so? Because she
was now degenerated &amp; gone out of kind,
as the Prophet complayneth:Esay. 1. 
                     ••
                  . 
               How is the
faithfull Citie become an Adulteres?
Because she sought to bee iustified by the
Lawe that was giuen in Mount Sinay, and
refused the grace of Christ, that was preached
on Mount Sion. She should haue been
a liuely Image of the heauenly Hierusalem,
if shee had accepted the Gospell of
Christ, but nowe by refusing the same, shee
answereth in figure to Sinay the mountaine
of Arabia, to Agar the mother of

               Ismael, and is in bondage, with her Children.
Shee was called with her children to
libertie and freedome by the sonne of God,
who onely hath authoritie to set at libertie
those that were in bondage, but they proudly
refused it, and stoode vppon their prerogatiue,
saying, We are the seede of Abraham,
wee haue not serued any man, howe
sayest thou that wee shall bee made free?
They woulde not vnderstande that euerye
one that committeth sinne, is the seruant of
sinne, and cannot haue eternall abyding in
the house.Iohn. 8. 67. They woulde not acknowledge
that the Sonne of GOD who alwaye abydeth
in the house, hath Authoritie to infranchise
them, and that they could not be
delyuered from the bondage of sinne, but by
him. Therefore they ramayne styll in
bondage without hope of deliuerance. For
the Adultresse Hierusalem theyr mother,
hauing nowe embraced a seruyle doctryne
and Religion, is become Agar or Sinay,
whose qualities and condition she doth properly
represent. Wherefore although they
doo with full mouthe neuer so proudlye
boast themselues to be the seede of Abraham,
they are neuerthelesse, the sonnes of

               Agar. And no greater priuiledge they haue
by beyng the sonnes of Abraham, then Ismael
had, who also was the Sonne of Abraham,
but after the fleshe onely, and not
after the spirit. Wherefore though Sinay
in distance of place be farre of from Hierusalem,
yet in qualitie and condition they
are altogether lyke, for they are both seruyle,
the doctrine of them both ingendreth
to bondage.
            Thus you see how Hierusalem which is
nowe, that is, the earthly Hierusalem,
by reteyning the doctrine and religion of
bondage, and refusing the doctrine and
Religion of freedome, is become Sinay
of Sion, Agar of Hierusalem. A good
admonition for vs al, to take heede, that
wee doo not imbrace the doctrine of bondage,
but most ioyfully and thankefully
receyue the glad tydings of libertie. That
wee maye beware by the punishment of
Hierusalem, to refuse freedome offered,
least wee bee chrust into perpetuall bondage.
No Citie nor people in the worlde
had greater priuiledges of honour, then
the Citie and people of Hierusalem: And
yet we see nowe, how iustly Hierusalem is

turned into Sinay, freedome into bondage,
glory into shame, that we should not stande
vpon any prerogatiues or priuiledges, as
though any thing could exempt vs from the
seueritie of Gods iudgement, if wee reiect
the grace of God when it is freely offered.
If Hierusalem escaped not punishment for
all her dignitie, what shall become of Sodome
or Babilon which haue no prerogatiue
of dignitie, if they being called to libertie
doo still continue in bondage? And here
we haue an example whereby to shape the
Papistes an answere, for all that they can
bring, to commende the dignitie of theyr
Churche of Rome. For the present time, or
that hath been these many hundreth yeres,
they can speake little good of her, if they
will speake the truth that all men doo see
with their eyes in this age, or may reade in
stories of the former ages, written by their
owne Registers: but they haue a great
glory to bring forth the auncient commendation
of fayth which the Scriptures and
olde doctors doo ascribe vnto the Churche
of Rome, the godly conuersation of the Anrient
Christian Romanes, the multitude of
Constant Martyrs which that Churche did

yeelde in the space of two or three hundreth
yeeres, but all in vayne, yea all to their
greater shame, except they can proue the
same fayth, conuersation, and Christian
constancie, to remaine now in the Churche
of Rome, that was in those golden dayes of
the primitiue Churche. S. Paule in deede
commendeth the fayth of the Romanes, to
be celebrated in all the world, which place
the Papistes thinke to make much for the
dignitie of the See of Rome. But let them
shewe that the Pope and hys Churche of
Rome doo nowe hold the same fayth whych
S. Paule praysed in the Romanes of hys
time, or else it maketh nothing in the world
for the Churche of Rome nowe, but to her
shame and reproche, which is degenerated
from that doctrine of libertie which of olde
time was wont to be imbraced in those places.
The fayth of the Romanes of that time,
which S. Paule commended, was this, that
a man is iustified by faythe without the
deedes of the lawe. Is this the doctrine of
the Churche of Rome according to the true
meaning of S. Paule and the whole discourse
of his Epistle to the Romanes? Do
they not teache the contrarie directly, that

a man cannot be iustified by faith only without
the workes of the lawe? Wherfore seeing
the Romanes that are nowe, haue a contrarie
faith to the Romanes of olde time,
there is no cause why they should claime the
aunciēt prayse, which haue not retained the
auncient fayth. And forasmuch as they
are fallen from the grace of Christ to
seeke ryghteousnes by their owne merits,
there is no reason why they shoulde haue
the commendation of the fayth of the Gospell,
which haue submitted themselues to
to the bondage of the Lawe.
            And if Hierusalem that is nowe, be turned
into Agar, and the earthly Sion into the
barreyn Sinay, because shee hath despised
the promise of mercy &amp; redemption which
the auncient Hierusalem and Moūt Sion in
the tyme of the godly Parriarches and
Prophetes most ioyfully receyued: why
shoulde Rome that is nowe, wyth her seuen
hylles, appointed for the throne of Antichryst,
enioye the prayse of the auncyent
Romanes and the Christian Churche
that sometyme was a straunger in that
place, whom nowe shee persecuteth, and
condemneth their fayth for Heresie? Shee

cannot bee taken for the heauenly Hierusalem,
that professeth the seruyle doctrine and
Religion of the earthly Hierusalem. Neither
can her children the Papists, be taken
for Citizens of the heauenly Hierusalem,
which thinke so great a part of religion to
consist in going a Pilgrimage to the earthly
Hierusalem. The Apostle here vtterly
reiecteth Hierusalem that is nowe, and
thrusteth her out of the lande of promyse,
into Arabia the desatte. The Papistes
make no accompte of Hierusalem that is
aboue, but all their delight is in Hierusalē
               
that is on earthe, so they shewe themselues
right Agarens &amp; Ismaelites. What a great
matter is made in Poperie of Hierusalem
that is now? yea although it be in the hands
of Turkes &amp; Paganes, yet they so esteeme it,
that they thinke they should haue the greatest
treasure in the world, if they coulde get
the possessiō of that citie, out of the Paganes
handes. And for that purpose howe manye
thousand men haue lost their liues in the enterprises
that haue beene aduentured, to
gayne that place out of the Turkes &amp; Souldans
dominions?
            
               
What an hygh poynt in Religion is
it made of the Papistes, to visite Hierusalem,
that is nowe? yea it is a matter of
so great importance, that the vowe which
one hath made to go on Pilgrimage to
Hierusalem, cannot be dispensed withal,
by any other inferiour person, but euen by
the Popes owne holynesse hymselfe. Such
a goodly matter it is to be a Citizen of the
earthly Hierusalem.
            
            But let the Papistes alone with theyr
holy mother the earthly Hierusalem mount
Sinay or Agar, and let vs returne to the
comparison of the Apostle, which saith: But
Hierusalē which is aboue, is free, which
is the mother of vs al: wee heard before,
that there were two mothers in the familie
of Abraham, Agar, and Sara: the one begetting
into bondage, the oher vnto libertie,
wee harde also that these mothers doo
signifie two Couenants, or two Churches,
and that Agar signifieth the Couenant of
Iustice, or Hierusalem that is nowe, the
Churche of Hypocrites, which abuse this
couenant in seeking to be iustified therby,
which was giuē to direct vs to the couenant
of mercy: Now must we consider Sara the

seconde mother, which was a freewoman,
how she was a figure of the new couenant,
and of the heauenly Hierusalē, that is the
mother of all the Children of God. The
first couenant in Mount Sinay what it was,
namely the Couenant of righteousnesse, we
haue sufficiently declared alreadie. The
seconde Couenant of mercy is excellently
well described, by the Prophet Ieremie.
               Ieremie. 31.
               Chap. 31. alledged by the Apostle to the
Hebrues.
               Hebr. 8. 
               Chap. 8. Beholde the dayes
come (sayeth the Lorde) that I wyll
accomplishe with the house of Israel
and Iuda a newe Couenant.
            
            9. Not accordyng to the Couenant
which I made wyth theyr Fathers in
the daye when I tooke them by the
hande to bryng them out of the
lande of Egypt: for they themselues
abyde not in my Couenant, and
I regarded them not (sayeth the
Lorde.)
            10. For this is the Couenant that I will
make with the house of Israel. After
those dayes (sayth the Lorde) I wyll
gyue my Lawes into their myndes,
and wryte them in theyr hartes:

And I wil be their God, and they shal
be my people.
            11 And they shall not teache euery man
his neyghbour, and euery man hys
brother, saying, Knowe the Lord: for
they shall al know mee from the least
to the greatest of them:
            12 For I wyll bee mercyfull to their vnryghteousnesse,
and I wyll no more
remember their sinnes, and their iniquities.
            Beholde this is the newe Testament,
this is the seconde Couenant of mercy, not
written in Tables of stone as the first Couenant
of iustice was, but in the fleshely
Tables of our hartes, by the spirite of
GOD. Of this Couenant Sara was a
lyuely fygure, when shee brought forth
Isaac, not by course of nature, or Carnall
deuyse as Ismael was begotten: but
by the power of GOD, accordyng to
hys promyse. For by the doctrine of this
couenant, the children of God, are borne vnto
libertie, through faith. For to those that
receiue Iesus Christ, he giueth this dignitie,
that they should be the sonnes of God,
euē to those that beleeue in his name, which

are not borne of blood, nor of the will of the
fleshe,Iohn. 1. 12. 13. nor of the will of man, but of God.
And this is that lawe that commeth out of
Sion. that word that proceedeth out of Hierusalem,
which proclaimeth libertie &amp; freedome
from Sion. to all them that embrace
Christ by faith. The same godly matrone
Sara, being the mother of the faithfull, is also
a figure of the true Church of god which
is no earthly Citie flourishyng in worldly
dignity, but is altogether heauenly and spirituall,
Hierusalem that is aboue, is the
mother of vs all. For although a great
number of children be dispersed ouer al the
worlde, yet is shee heauenly, because shee
hath her beginnyng of the heauenly grace,
and dwelleth aboue by Fayth: and those
her Children which are in the worlde,
are but Pilgrymes and straungers on the
earth, for their conuersation and dwelling,
theyr Franchise and libertie is in heauen,
from whence they looke for a Sauiour.
               Philip. 3. 2
                     •
                  
               
The word of promise and couenant of mercie,
is that incorruptible seede, by which
she conceiueth children, &amp; heires vnto God:
In the same she hath milke for hir infantes,
and stronger meate for them of ryper age,

shee cherisheth and bryngeth them vp vntyll
they come of yeeres apt to enioye their
Fathers inheritance, perfourming all offices
and duetyes of a most kynd and naturall
mother. And therefore it is truely said,
hee shall not haue GOD to his Father,
that refuseth the Churche to bee his mother.
And here wee must note, that
there is but one true Churche, namelye,
Heauenly Hierusalem the mother of vs
all, that are Gods Children, and therefore
all Heretikes and Scismatykes that
bee not Chyldren of thys one mother, are
excluded from beyng Chyldren of God.
Here also wee see that the Churche is
Catholike or Uniuersall, and howe shee
is Catholike or Uniuersall, not in respecte
of euerie great multitude, that
challengeth her to bee theyr mother, but
shee is the mother of all the faythfull, of
all the free borne Children of God, that
are borne accordyng to the promyse, accordyng
to the Couenant of Gods mercie,
and not of the wyll or workes, merites
or worchynesse of man, but of the spirit
of God.
            The thyrde condition, she is heauenly,

shee is from aboue, shee is not bounde to
any place vpon the earth. No she hath forsaken
earthly Hierusalem, to dwell in heauen.
And thinke you she wil forsake heauen
to come downe and dwel in Rome? No no,
all the inchanters and Sorcerers of Aegipt
and Babilon, cannot drawe her down from
Heauen too place her seate at Rome. If
wee wilbe Children of the freewoman, wee
muste looke vp intoo Heauen by Fayth,
where our Mother dwelleth, and not too any
place on earth, neyther too Hierusalem
in Iuda, nor to Rome in Italy, nor to Constantinople
in Thracia, nor to Alexandria
in Aegypt, nor to Antiochia in Syria, but
to Ierusalem in Heauen, for she is the Mother
of vs al, that are the Children of God.
We learne here, that if we be true children
of Hierusalem that is aboue, what manner
lyfe and conuersation becōmeth vs, namely
such as our Mother is, yea and our Father
also, heauenly, Godly, Spirituall. Besides
thys, in that Hierusalem is aboue, wee see
howe madde the furie and rage of Tyraants
is, that thinke by persecutyng her Children
which are straungers on earthe, they
can destroye and vanquishe her that is in

Heauen, whereas when they haue done the
vttermost that their rage leadeth thē vnto,
that is, to kyll their bodies, they do but send
home the Children to theyr Mother, who
as long as shee is great with Childe, by the
seede of the Gospell, shee still traueleth in
birth in bryngeth foorth men Chyldren,
which vnder their Prince and eldest Brother
the Sonne of GOD, shall treade
downe that Dragons head, that persecuteth
the mother and the Children, vntill hee
bee caught by the heeles, and throwne into
the bottomlesse lake that burneth with fyer
and brymston.
            The fourthe condition of the Church is,
that she is free, and therfore bringeth forth
Children vntoo freedome. Shee is free, in
that she is redeemed and bought out of bondage,
by the blood of the Sonne of God,
that she might be holy and vnspotted before
hym, not hauyng her owne ryghteousnesse,
wherewith she is adorned, but the garment
washed in the blood of Christ, which is the
righteousnesse of Sainctes, Thus is shee a
glorious mother, and bringeth foorth Children
that are made free from sinne and wickednesse,
to serue the Lorde GOD their

father in holynesse and rlghteousnesse all
the dayes of their lyfe. By this that hath
beene sayde, it is manifest, that the Church
of Rome, is not the Church of Christ, for
she is earthely, glysteryng in Earthly glorye,
maynceyned by carnall strength and
wysdome, mainteyning the Doctrine of
bondage, and persecutyng the Gospell of
lybertye. Here also is decyded a great
controuersye betweene the Papystes and
vs, whether the Catholyke Churche of
Christe bee vysible yea or no. The Papystes
stoutely mainteyne, that the Catholike
Churche is vysible, that is, apparant and
open to bee seene to the eyes of all men, and
they thynke it the strongest reason they haue,
eyther too defende their Churche, or to
impugne ours, that their Church hath alwayes
beene and yet is vysible, and in the
open veywe of the world, when our Church
wythin these hundreth yeares, was dryuen
intoo Corners and not too bee spyede
excepte it were in a fewe persecuted members.
The grounde they stande vppon
is a wrong Interpretation of the saying of
our Sauiour Chryste in the. 5. of Saincte
Math.
               Math. 5. 14. A City that is builded vpon an hill

               cannot be hidde. But thys perteyneth nothing
to the Cytie of Rome, although it be
builded not on one, but vpon seuen hils, For
our Sauiour Christ (as the whole contexte
of his speach doth euydently declare) speaketh
not there of the Catholike Church, but
of hys Apostles that were appoynted to be
the light of the world, &amp; therfore must needs
be seene, were as a Cytie which is buylded
on a hyll, and therefore coulde not bee hydden,
exhorting them therefore to gyue good
example of lyfe and doctrine, bycause their
place was such, as their example could not
bee secret, but open and manifest, and therfore
eyther very profitable or very hurtfull.
But this place, (which euery man must
confesse to bee vnderstood of the Catholyke
Church) doth most clearly declare, that the
Catholike Church neither is, nor can be visible
and subiecte too the eyes of any man,
but onely them, that are indewed with the
eyes of Fayth. For hee sayth that Hierusalem
is aboue, shee is in Heauen, euen
shee that is the Catholyke and vniuersall
Mother of vs all, and therefore shee is not
to be seene but by the eye of Fayth. Let the
Papists still glorie in their visible Church,

let them acknowledge none other Mother
but their visible Church of Rome, we will
boldly defy them and the whoore their mother,
for the Heauenly and Spirituall Hierusalem,
that is aboue, is the mother of
vs all. And thys the Apostle proueth by the
Testimonie of Esaye, taken out of the. 54.
Chapter, that the Church bryngeth foorth
lawfull sonnes and heyres too God accordyng
too the promyse, euen of the gentiles.
For in as muche as the Galathians were
Gentiles, hee bringeth foorth the comfortable
promyse made vntoo the Church of
the Gentyles, that (although of long tyme
shee were barreyne and had no husbande,
and therefore brought foorth no Children
too GOD, yet the tyme should come, that
God woulde ioyne her as a chaste virgyn
in mariage vntoo Chryste, and then shee
shoulde bee more fruitfull, and brynge forth
moe Children vntoo God, then euer dyd the
Church of the Iewes, when shee was the
spouse of God so many hundred yeares, all
which time the other was barren, desolate,
and had no husbande. So brethren (sayeth
he) we are after Isaac Children of the promise.
Not only those that are the carnall

seede of Abraham by Isaac, but all those
that take holde of the promyse of God by
fayth. For what prerogatiue of dignity had
Isaac too bee the Sonne of God more then
Ismaell: bycause hee was the carnall leede
of Abraham: so was Ismaell: Bycause hee
was the firste begotten of Abraham, that
was hee not, but Ismaell was: nothyng
then but the promyse of GOD made Isaac
the Sonne of GOD, and the same
promyse extendeth too all nations of the
worlde as largely and in as ample manner,
as too the carnall seede of Abraham
Isaac or Iacob. In thy seede shall all nations
of the worlde bee blessed.
            Therefore Brethren wee are after Isaac,
not by carnall generation, but by spirituall
regeneration, Children of the promyse.
            For the onely Pryuyledge that made
Isaac the Sonne of GOD, was the promyse
of GOD, and that also maketh vs
the sonnes of GOD. What made Iacob
too bee preferred before Esaw, who was
the Sonne of Abraham and the Sonne
of Isaac, yet Iacob was loued, and Esaw
was hated? Whereby (I saye) was Iacob
preferred to bee the heyre of Isaac his

Father, but by the election of GOD? It
is therefore of the election, grace, mercy,
and promyse of GOD, that any man is
aduanced to this honour to bee the Sonne
of GOD, and not of any meryte, dignity,
or worthynesse of a man.
            
               But euen as then hee that was borne
after the fleshe, persecuted hym that
was borne after the Spirit, euen so is
it nowe. By these woordes the Apostle
comforteth the Galathians and all other,
that were true Children of the Church, and
armeth them to patience, assuryng them
that of the Hypocryticall Churche of meritmongers,
they should looke for nothyng
else but persecution. For it is no marueyle
if those proude sclaues, the Chyldren
of the Earthelye Hierusalem, dyd
vntoo the Sonnes of the Heauenly Hierusalem
as Ismaell theyr Father dyd to
Isaac the true heyre, boastyng of hys byrth
righte. For suche is the swellyng pryde
of that slauysh generation, that although
they bee altogether bondemen and thrall
vnto perpetuall distruction, yet doo they
moste arrogantly contemne and despyse
all other, that professe not the same waye

of Iustification that they doo.
            Therefore our Sauiour Christe telleth
a parable agaynste them that trusted in
them selues, that they were ryghteous,
and desprsed other. For they that be once
so proude as to iustifie them selues, they
will also contemne and despyse others. Of
this contempte aryseth their cruell mynde,
whereby they doo also persecute them.
            Thus the false Apostles that preached iustification
partly by Christe, and partly by
obseruation of the Lawe, raysed persecution
agaynst the true Apostles, that taught
iustification by grace of Christe only, embraced
by Faith alone without the deeds of
the law, and al them that receyued the same
moste cōfortable doctrine. And their successours
the Papistes, are nothyng behynde:
for they neuer cease to the vttermost of their
power, too persecute and afflicte the true
Children of promyse with all kynde of tormentes
that they can deuyse, to maynteyne
the proude perswasion of their owne righteousnesse,
and too deface the glorye of the
mo
                  •
               te free and plentyfull Redemption of
Christe. But for as much as the Apostle
here sayeth, that hee that was borne after

the fleshe, persecuted hym that was
borne after the spirite, wee haue to see,
what kynde of persecution this was, by
which Ismael persecuted Isaac. For in al
the story of Ismael there is no mention of
persecution, but onely in the 21. Chapter
of Genesis, where it is written, that at
such time as Abraham made a great feast
at the weaninge of his sonne Isaac, and
there was great ioye and reioycing on euery
syde for Isaac that was Abrahams
sonne by Sara according to the promyse of
GOD, Ismael which was then in the
house, a prowde Ladde of syxteene or
seuenteene yeares olde, scorned and mocked
his younge Brother Isaac.
            
            This derysion and skorninge, the Apostle
compteth for persecution, and not
without great cause, for it shewed the
prowde stomacke of Ismael that contemned
and dispised hym whom GOD had
chosen, secondlye it declared his inwarde
hatred and cruell minde that hee bare against
his Brother whom he so contumelyoustye
deryded, workynge hym all the
spighte and villanye that hee could and
durst. And chiefely it deserued to bee

called persecution, because he scorned and
mocked the grace and election of GOD.
Wherefore though hee dyd not persecute
hym with the Sword which he coulde not,
yet hee persecuted him with his scornefull
reproches, which is worse, because he contemned
and trode vnder his feete, the promise
of GOD whereof Isaac was made
an heyre by the mercy and grace of God.
And verely there ought no persecution to
be so greeuous vnto vs, as when wee se the
grace of GOD vpon which our vocation
is grounded, to be trodden vnder foote and
defaced with the prowde tauntes &amp; scornes
of the vngodly: yea it is the fountayne and
beginninge of all persecutions, when the
wicked doe hate and despise the grace of
GOD in his chosen, as appeareth moste
playnly in the story of Caine and Abel: yea
our Sauiour Christe hymselfe no doubte
was more greeued with that blasphemous
mock of the proude persecuting Iewes, He
trusted in God, let hym take hym if hee
wyll haue hym. &amp;c. then with their buffetinge,
scourginge, and naylynge of hym.
And as the glory of GOD ought to bee
more deare vnto vs then our owne lyues,

so ought we to be more greeued at the defacing
of Gods glory by the scorning and
deriding of the vngodly, then at any bodilye
Tormentes, or at the losse of our owne
liues. For there is no kinde of persecution
more detestable, then that, by whiche the
saluation of our scules is assaulted, as it is
by the proude taunts &amp; scornes of gods enimies
both Papistes and Atheistes, who
when their cruell rage is restrained, that
they cannot persecute vs by fire and sword
as their desyre is, then they blaspheme the
grace of GOD, in our election and vocation,
with most bitter and contumelious
scorning and derisyon. So that the children
of GOD and all they that wyll liue
godlye in Christe Iesus, shal neuer want
persecution. For if the bloody sworde bee
wrung out of the Tyrauntes handes, yet
wyll they not cease to persecute, vnlesse
their tongues also were pulled out of their
heades. For they that are borne after the
flesh, that is, al Hipocrites and Iustifyers
of them selues, wyll euer playe Ismaels
parte, if they can doe nothinge els against
the Children of promise.
            And this is the grounde of the hatred of

the papistes against vs. But to conclude,
what shall be the ende of these persecuting
scorners? Aske not the worlde, for the
world thinketh that such holy Hipocrites
are the chiefe pillers of the Church, and
principall members of the same. They
them selues saye: that they onely are the
Churche, and that the sonnes of promise
shall haue nothinge to doe there, but by
there licence. But what saith the scripture?
The scripture will not flatter them, the
scripture wyll not dissemble with them.
            
               Cast out the bond woman &amp; her sonne,
for the sonne of the bondwoman shall
not inherit with the sonne of the free
woman. These were in deede the wordes
of Sara vnto Abraham, but they were confyrmed
by the Oracle of god, which willed
Abraham to follow the worde of Sara in
al that she had sayde. Therefore this is the
sentence of GOD, though Ismael keepe a
sturre in the house a longe time, and beare
hymselfe bolde on his birthright as though
he wolde bee the onely heyre, persecuting
the right heyre Isaac with tauntes &amp; scorninge,
yet at the length he is thrust out of
dores with that prowde dame Agar hys

mother, that dispised her misteris Sara, and
vtterly reiected from the inheritaunce.
            There were a great number of s
                  •
               ruauntes
which taryed in the house when Ismael the
first begotten was thrust out. What was
the cause that they taryed? Because they reuerenced
the grace of God in Isaac, which
Ismael contemned. The same e
                  •
               de remaineth
the popish Agar and all the Ismaelites
her children, though they boast themselues
to be the onely Churche, so that they
woulde seeme to thrust Isaac and his seede
out of the dores, yet the scripture hath determined
their ende longe a goe, and of all
other hypocrites whiche now are mixed
they shall be seuered, which occupye great
rowmes in the Church, they shal be cast out
of the dores, they shall haue none inherytance
with the sonnes of God.
            Let vs therefore thankfullye embrace the
Couenaunt of GODS mercy the doctrine
of the Gospell, and free remission of
sinnes, by which we are sure to be set at lybertie
from sinne, made the sonnes of
GOD and heyres of eternall felycitye,
which GOD of his mercye graunt vnto
vs all for Christe his sake, to whom with

the Father and the holy ghost, bee
all honour and glory for euer
and euer. Amen.
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            ¶Imprinted at London
for Lucas Harrison.
1577.
            
         
      
   

