
   
      
         
            A sermon intended for Paul's Crosse, but preached in the Church of St. Paul's, London, the III. of December, M.DC.XXV. Vpon the late decrease and withdrawing of Gods heauie visitation of the plague of pestilence from the said citie. By Tho: Fuller, Master of Arts in Pembroke-Hall in Cambridge
            Fuller, Thomas, Master of Arts.
         
         
            
               1626
            
         
         Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-07 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01346
            STC 11467
            ESTC S102824
            99838586
            99838586
            2970
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01346)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2970)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1098:06)
         
         
            
               
                  A sermon intended for Paul's Crosse, but preached in the Church of St. Paul's, London, the III. of December, M.DC.XXV. Vpon the late decrease and withdrawing of Gods heauie visitation of the plague of pestilence from the said citie. By Tho: Fuller, Master of Arts in Pembroke-Hall in Cambridge
                  Fuller, Thomas, Master of Arts.
               
               [8], 56 p.   
               
                  Printed by B. Alsop and T. Favvcet, for Nathaniell Butter, and are to bee sold at his shop at St. Austines Gate,
                  London :
                  1626.
               
               
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Plague --  Great Britain --  Sermons.
            
         
      
      
         
            2002-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2002-10
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2002-11
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2003-02
            AptaraRekeyed and resubmitted
         
            2003-04
            Jennifer KietzmanSampled and proofread
         
            2003-04
            Jennifer KietzmanText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-06
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A
SERMON
INTENDED FOR PAVL'S
CROSSE, BVT PREACHED IN
THE CHVRCH OF St. PAVL'S,
LONDON, THE III. OF DECEMBER,
M.DC.XXV.
            Vpon the late Decrease and withdrawing
of GODS heauie Visitation
of the Plague of Pestilence
from the said
Citie.
            By THO: FVLLER, Master of
Arts in Pembroke-Hall in
Cambridge.
            
            LONDON,
Printed by B. ALSOP a
                  •
               d T. FAVVCEY, for Nathaniell
Butter, and are to bee sold at his Shop at
St. Austines Gate. 1626.
         
         
            
            
            TO
THE RIGHT HONble:
ALLANE COTTON, Lord
Major of the Hon: Citie of London, and
to the Right Wor: Sir IOHN GORE, his
worthy Predecessour: THO: FVLLER wisheth
length of prosperous dayes here, and
fruition of Eternall prosperitie with
the Antient of dayes
hereafter.
            
               
                  Right HON: and Right Wor ps
                     •
                  ll:
            
            
               THis Sermon not
long since preached
in your
publique Assemblie,
is besides,
though
not against my
will publisht: The seuere censure of

the eare amazed me, but that more
exquisite Test of the eye, doth little
lesse th
                  •
               n confound me: Euen Manna
in this kinde is distasted of our corrupt
natures; And but that I know
there are stomackes, that will desire
Fruit when they refuse wholsommer
dyet, I must not haue aduentured so
ill a cook't dish to so various pallats;
Some, I hope, will looke vpon this
piece without any thought of the
worthlesse Author; and if in it they
finde ought either for Information
of judgement, which I dare not hope,
or Reformation of life, which is
the All of my ambition, the Whole
neither to them, nor me may proue
vnfruitfull.
            The subject of it being our late heauy
Affliction, with it's ill cause

our Transgressions, and it's good
effect our Sorrow, together with
GODS gratious deliuerance and
our heartie Thanksgiuing for it,
this Citie, the Stage of those scoenes
may justly challenge it as her owne;
And to whom then within these
Walls doth it of right belong, but to
your Lordship the present, and that
other worthy Gent: the last principall
Magistrate therein? whose
sad eyes were witnesses of what this is
onely a rude and vnpolisht draught;
He had the happinesse to out-liue
those many Deaths, to finish his
course not more in safetie then Honour:
You haue the Honour to enjoy
the yeare of Thankfulnesse, to rule
in a cleare and faire skie, wherein
it will bee your Crowne to destroy

the Cockatrice in the egge, seuerely
at first to punish these Transgressions
and Iniquities, which like
Garden-weedes will spring vp in
a sun-shine after a storme, and, if
not preuented, will o're-runne the
whole Plot, and bring againe the like
desolation;Heb. 13. 8. God is the same yesterday,
to day and for euer, the same
to see, to hate, to punish Malefactors;
Hitherto onely the hands or
toes of Adonibezick haue beene
cut off,
               Iudg. 1. 6. his life spared; Worse things
then what wee yet haue suffered, may
befall vs: You are at the Sterne, and
may be a great meanes to preuent
Ship-wracke: Good lucke haue
you with your Honour, ride on
prosperously, and let the Word
of Truth guide, and it will defend
you.
            
               
Bee pleased to pardon his boldnesse
that meanes and wishes well,
and humbly offers not onely This
but himselfe
in all due respect:
            
               At your Seruice,
THO: FVLLER.
            
         
         
            
            Faults escaped.
            PAge 3. line 1. reade 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . p. 8. l. 15. for Foole, r.
Fooles. p. 10. l. 9. for these r. theirs. p. 12. l. 6. r. opera.
p. 16. l. 16. r. ebriosorum. p. 19. l. 8. r. En. l. last,
r. interimat. p. 23. l. 12. r. paruas. l. 16. for out the, r. out
of the. p. 40. l. 1. for enfused, r. infused. p. 41. l. 13. after
Remembrance, put in of. p. 43. l. 18. for respects, r.
expects. p. 44. l. 12. r. 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . l. 13. r. 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                p. 45. l.
8. for condicions, r. condition. p. 47. l. 5. r. longe. l. 28.
for repented. r. reported. p. 49. l. 5. for against, r. to p.
55. l 1. r. 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . line 4. decursus.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            PSAL. 107. VERSE 17. &amp;c.
            
               17. Fooles because of their transgressions, and because
of their Iniqu
                     •
                  ties are (nou: Trans:) afflicted.
(vet:) Plagued.
18. Their soule abhorreth all meate, and they drawe
neere to the gates of death.
19. Then they crye vnto the Lord in their trouble, hee
saueth them out of their distresses.
20. Hee sent his Word and healed them, and deliuered
them from their destructions.
21. Oh that Men would therefore praise the Lord for
his goodnesse, and for his wonderfull workes to the
children of men.
            
            
               WHat Euripides spake in Hecub
                     •
                  
               
concerning a noble and vulgar
person deliuering the same
speech, Eadem oratio non aequè
valet: The same doe I hold true
of an antient and a younger Diuine
should they preach, for
matter and forme totidem verbis, the same Sermon;
it would finde a farre different acceptation.
Lue. 5. last. 
               No man when hee hath tasted old Wine will desire
new, for he saith the old is better.
            
            
               
I freely acknowledge this chayre of Moses should
rather bee furnished with Masters in our Israel,
men of such grauity and learning, whose awfull
presence alone might stop the mouth of all, either
censorious Criticisme, or enuious detraction:
But so heauy hath the hand of Heauen beene vpon
vs, as not onely the sheepe, but the shepheards themselues
haue beene scattered; Those greater and
more glorious Luminaries are retired to their
more priuate orbes, there praying and interceding
withGen. 18. 
               Abraham in the fields for threatned
Sodome; wisely carefull, according to the aduise
of Salomon
               Prou. 27. 12 not to expose their bodyes to these
arrowes of God, which as if they had chosen this
Citie for their proper ayme, haue thus long, thus
mortally wounded vs; so that this Night of our
desolation hath beene inlightened onely with lesse
and weaker constellations. And those reuerend
and worthy ones that haue stayed, haue found
their owne Pastorall charges a double labour
vnto them. So that young Samuel, or none must
supply the place of old Eli, and in the absence of
the Prophets, their children of seruants must discharge
this duty. It will be your charity to expect
from Children no more then what such weaklins,
and Nouices can produce; to pardon weake if
there be no wilfull aberrations; St. Paul
               1 Cor. 13. 11. himselfe
when he was a childe, spake as a childe,Psal. 8. 2. and out
of the mouthes of babes and sucklins is God often
pleased to make his praises issue forth: What
then the Heathen were wont to proclaime in the

beginning of their sacrifices 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
so wee desire none but equall eares and milde censurers
at our Sermons.2 Kings 7. Good newes is good
newes though from a Leaper, and truth though
vttered out of weake and vnworthy lips ought to
lose nothing of it's worth and acceptation.
            The Prophet in this Psalme describes foure seuerall
sorts of men that stand indebted to God for
deliuerance from earthly and temporall dangers,
and afflictions.vers
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  . The first whereof are they that
haue suffered banishment, as the beloued Disciple
Reuel. 1. 9. 
               Iohn in Pathm
                     •
                  s, are exiled from their natiue
soyle, and may say with them in the Poet,
Virg▪ Ecclog. 
                     •
                  
                  ▪
                
               Nos Patriae fines &amp; dulcia linquim
                     •
                  s ar
                     ••
                  , Their
natiue Country with all the pleasures thereof they
forsake, and are driuen to liue among strangers,
to seeke their bread in an vnknowne Land, to
conuerse with such people, whose language is
riddles vnto them, yet there they crie vnto the
Lord,
               Zach. 4. 10. whose eares as his eyes goe through the
world, and hee heareth them and brings them
home in safety.
            The second are they that haue withAct▪ 12▪
                
               Peter bin
lockt vp in Prisons, and withler. 37▪
                
               Ieremy throwne
into the Dungeon, and fettered, not onely in
chaines of Iron, but which is worse, in fetters of
darknesse, not hauing so much happinesse as to
see themselues miserable, yet thence from those
disconsolate places, they crying vnto the Lord, he
also heareth them and deliuereth them, breakes
those bonds in sunder, and set
                     •
                   their 
                     〈◊〉
                  
                  ▪ in a larger
r
                     ••
                  me.
            
            
               
The third being the Text which at this time I
haue chosen to bee the subiect of my weake discourse,
Verse 17. are they that haue beene brought so lowe,
with the harbinger of death; sicknesse, that their
soules abhorred all meat, and all pleasure is as the
gall of Aspes vnto them, vnwelcome and vnsauorie,
yet they also with
                  
                     •
                   Reg. 20. 
               Hezekiah, crying vnto the
Lord, their strength is renued, and there are dayes
and yeares added to their liues.
            The fourth are they that goe downe to the sea in
Ships, and occupie their businesse in great waters,
Sea-faring men, that are neither Inter vi
                     ••
                  s 
                     •
                  ec
inter mor
                     •
                  uos, betweene the liuing nor the dead,
and are ready to offer vp their soules to euery
flaw of winde, and billow of water which assailes
them, yet these at last are ioyfully deliuered, and
safely brought to that hauen where they would bee.
The A
                  ••
               aebeum or burden of each one is this,
Oh that men would praise the Lord for his goodnesse,
and for his wonderfull workes to the children
of men.
            
            It was the saying of Salomon
               Pro. 25. 
                     •
                  1. 
               A word spoken
in due time is like apples of gold with siluer pictures,
whose outside is faire, but the inside glorious; if
euer text was seasonable, this is now at this time,
being a liuely description to our eares, of what our
eyes haue beene wofull witnesses and spectators,
here is a reall narration, and a true demonstration
of our owne lamentable estate, whether we consider
our misery we haue beene plagued and afflicted,
or the cause of those sorrows our Transgressions

and iniquity, or the effect of those disasters, our
fasting and crying vnto the Lord, or the happy euent
of our humilia
                  •
               ion and contrition. He heard
vs in our distresses, hee sent his Word and healed vs,
hee hath spoken and wee haue escaped from the noysome
Pestilence. Or lastly the good end and conclusion
which we all should make our thankfulnesse,
Oh that men would, &amp;c.
            
               Ciprian. 
               Plus profic
                     •
                  tur, cùm in rem presentem venitur,
when we see and feele the truth of what we heare,
the words cannot but moue and proue eff
                  •
               ctuall.
Horace. 
               Illi 
                     ••
                  bur &amp; oes triplex c
                     •
                  ra pectus, his sinewes
are of I
                  •
               on, and his soule of Marble, who, when
he heares the sad relation of those miseries wherein
himselfe and his brethren haue beene miserable
sharers, shall not haue his heart pricked, as the
Act. 2. 37. Iewes had at Peters Sermon, t
                  •
               lling them their
sin past, and their iudgement to come, so againe,
that heart is as 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   as Brawne, and himselfe not
worthy the ayre hee breathes in, that is not taken
with this great deliuerance of our gratious God,
that hath not his soule rauisht with ioy, and indeauours
not to expresse the fruites of his gratitude
in his life and conuersation, in reall acts of charity
and obedience: For if euer Death triumphed,
'twas this yeare in the streets of our forsaken City,
and if euer Mercy againe victoriously ouercame,
it was now in this sudden and vnexpected declination
from the deaths of so many thousands in
one weeke, to so few hundreds within a few we
                  •
               kes
after, it was onely thePsal. 118. 23 
               Lords doing, and it ought to

bee meruailous in our eyes. Wherefore as Tully spake
of a booke which Cran
                     •
                  or wrote, it was Paruus, sed
aureolus, &amp; ad verbum ediscendus, with better reason
may I say of this Text of Scripture, it deserues
to bee engrauen vpon the palmes of our hands, or
rather on the tables of our hearts, neuer to bee forgotten,
to be worne as a bracelet vpon our armes, or
rather as a 
                     •
                  ron
                     •
                  let betweene our eyes, still to bee
thought vpon and still to magnifie God for it.
            But because
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  
                
               Pleni sumus r
                     •
                  marum as hee in
the Comedie, and the thought both of sorrow
and deliuerance equally slips out of our memories
with the sense of them, giue me leaue to thrust
my finger into an al-most-healed soare, to drawe
fresh blood from our late wounds; to discourse
a while of our afflictions, that so our extremitie
duly and often considered, our owne escape, and
miraculous preseruation may bee more welcome
to vs, and we more thankfull for it. And so I come
to my Text.
            Fooles because of their Transgressions, &amp;c.
            
               Psa. 101. The subiect of Dauids song Mercy and Iudgement,
as of all holy Writ in generall, so it is the
chiefe matter of this Text in particular, heere is
Iudgement in the punishing, and Mercy in deliuering
againe from that Iudgement, or rather here is Mercy, then Iudgement then mercy againe; for
what was it that suffered these fooles so long to
runne on in the wayes of their foolishnesse, till
they added Transgressions to their F
                     •
                  lly, and Iniquitie
to their Transgressions, till they heaped one

sinne vpon another, that their regions were forborne
not onely till they were Albae ad messem, but
Siccae ad ignem, white for haruest, but drye for the
fire, till the measure fo their wickednesse was not
onely full, but heaped vp, pressed downe, and running ouer,
but those Viscera misericordiae as they
are tearmed, the bowels of his compassion, his
long suffering patience, who wills not the destruction
of any; He could in the infancy of their sin

                  •
               aue throwne them not onely to the gates of
Death, but euen the belly of Hell, but yet He stayed,
and stayed, till there was no end of their rebellions,
so that laes
                     •
                   patientia fit furor, patience
too long, too much abused becomes fury: yet a
little while and his bow will be bent, and his arrowes
drawne to the head, and He is as it were compelled
to strike. And yet see and wonder at Mercy in the
middest of Iudgement, they are not swallowed vp
quite of this deuourer, they are but at the gates of
death,Psal. 1 18. 1
                     •
                  . 
               He hath chastened them sore, but hee hath
not giuen them ouer vnto death. Hee plagues none
ad destructionem sed ad correctionem, to amend,
not to destroy vs; loath to begin, and yet in the
proceeding procuring our good and aduantage.
O quam vellem nescire literas,
               Sue
                     •
                  . in vita Nero
                     •
                  is. said Nero in the
beginning of his raigne, when he was to subscribe
for the execution of a Malefactor; ten thousand
times more loth is our gouernour, the Father of all
comfort, and God 
                     •
                  f all mercy to strike, much more
to kill.Ez
                     •
                  k. 18. 32. 
               Hee wills not the death of a sinner, but
rather their conuersion and saluation.
            
               And because prosperity doth rather breed corruption
then amendment, asDeu
                     •
                  . 3
                     •
                  . 15 
               Ges
                     •
                  urun waxing

                  •
               at will kicke, and wee see that standing waters
will soone grow noysome. Aduersity must then
succeed, as when2 Sam. 11. 29. 
               Absolom could not draw Ioab vnto
him by faire intreats, he fired his Barley 
                  •
               ieldes
to make him come, so that here is the course, God
blesseth, they sin, God strikes, they pray, and then
He presently heares and helpes them.
            Thus then my Text falls in sunder: First, as all
Phisitians comming to their Patients examine
the cause of the disease; so here wee haue the
ground and the originall of all our sorrowes our
Transgressions and Iniquities.
            
            17. Foole because of their Transgressions, and
because of their Iniquities, are afflicted.
            Then secondly we haue the nature of the disease,
the new Transl
                  •
               tion saith in generall they
are afflicted. The old hath it, they are plagued
which by the symptomes of it may be thought to
b
                  •
               e the same disease vnder which wee haue thus
long groaned▪
            
            18. Their soule abhorreth all meate, and they
drawe neere to the gates of death.
            Vomiting I am sure is one of the certainest
signes of the plague.
            
            Then thirdly the seeking to the Phisi
                  •
               ian.
            19. Then they cry vnto the Lord in their trouble.
            F
                  •
               u
                  ••
               hly the cure intended in the same verse
applyed in the next. Hee saued them out of their
distresses.
            
            
               
20. Hee sent his Word and healed them, and deliuered
them from their destructions.
            And lastly the conclusion of all, the onely Fee
and gratification which our Phisition expects for
the cure.
            21. Oh that men would therefore praise the Lord
for his goodnesse, and for his wonderfull workes to
the children of men.
            These are the parts, The cause, The disease,
The seeking to the Phisition, the Cure, and the
discharge, or satisfaction.
            As the ProdigallLuc. 15. 18. when hee returned to his
Fathers house freely confessed hee had sinned against
Heauen and against him, and was no more
worthy to be called his sonne, and so reduced all
his delinquencyes to these two heads, God, and
Man; So are all our sinnes wee can bee guilty of,
included in these two, our Transgressions and our
Iniquities; our Transgressions, as all interpreters
doe agree, smiting against the first Table, and
our Iniquities violating the second; our sinnes of
knowledge, our sinnes of ignorance, our sinnes
of weaknesse, our sinnes of wilfulnesse, our secret,
our open sinnes, of our thoughts, of our mouthes,
of our hands, are all here comprised, whatsoeuer
the diuell can suggest, or to which our hearts can
consent, or our hands act are all here vnderstood.
            Should I take vpon me to number the Transgressions
of our Iudah, and reckon vp the particular
Iniquities of our Israel, I might as easily
call all the 
                  
                     ••
                  arres by their names, and giue a true

and exact accompt of the sand vpon the Seashore;
not onely the ends of the world as1 Cor. 10. 11. Saint
Paul saith, but the ends of all goodnesse are met
vpon this last and worst age of ours.
            The sinnes which in former ages were but in
their Infancy, are now in ours, growne to their
full height and strength, those which whilome
were but in the Egge, are now come to be fiery flying
Serpents; All these wee haue and more of our
owne, more horrid; Euery new day almost brings
in a new way of offending; Were Salomon now aliue,
he would recant, in thatEccles. 1. 9. he said, He saw no
new thing vnder the Sun, Et dictum, &amp; factum quod
non prius, wee offend both in word and workes
in such kindes, such fashions, as former ages were
neuer guilty of the knowledge of, and

                  Non habet vlterius quod nostris moribus addat.
                  Posteritas—
               
Posterity will neuer be able to paralell our exorbitancies;
As in the time of the Plague wee wondred
not so much at those that dyed, as at those
that escaped: so in this generall Infection, they
deserue no admiration that offend, but they that
are found innocent, vt Pueri Iunonis au
                     •
                  m, are
wondred at as a Bird of diuerse colours.
            Should euery Leaper in this kinde be enforced
as those other Leapers in the oldNum. 5. 2. Law were, to go
out of our Cities, and rend their clothes, and cry
I am vncleane, men would swarme in our fieldes
like those Grashoppers in Aegypt, our Townes
and houses should onely be places forIsa. 13. 21. 
               Zim and

               Iim, Owles and Ostriches to inhabite in; our
streetes should bee left so desolate, that grasse
might there grow, and aIbid. ver. 1
                     •
                  
                
               man should bee more
pretious then the purest gold of Ophir.
            
            
               2 Sam. 24. Not a man amongst vs but may cry as Dauid
did Peccaui, nay Stul
                     •
                  è seci, wee haue sinned and
done very foolishly; Stocke and branch, Cedar
and shrubbe, Prince and Priest and People, all of
vs are digged out of one and the same pit of Adams
disobedience, and hewen out of that rocke
of Infidelity.Ez
                     •
                  k. 16. 3. The father of vs all was an Ammorite,
and our mother an Hittite; in sinne haue they
begotten vs, and in Iniquity haue they produced
vs. and we our selues sucke not the ayre faster, nor
Behemoth drinkes downe Iordane with more greedinesse
then weIsa. 5. 18. 
               hale on sinne with cart-ropes, and
pull it vnto vs euen by violence: TheIsa. 1. 5. 
               whole head
of man-kinde is sicke, and the whole heart faint of
this malady. There is none that doth good, no not
one,
               Ps
                     •
                  l. 14. 1. saith Dauid; there is none that doth not
cuill, say I, and very euill, no not one. Salomon
               1 King 8. 46 at the Dedication of the Temple concluded vs
all vnder sinne; Omnes aliquid, Nemo nullum. All
of vs offend in some things, and some of vs offend
in all things;Pro
                     •
                  . 24. 16. 
               The most righteous in all the cluster
of man-kinde falls in his happiest day seuen tim
                     •
                  s.
Hee hath Breuia, leuiaque peccata, quam
                     •
                  is pauca,
quamuis parua, non tamen nulla, so that omnes odit,
qui malos odit, His sword must needs be against euery
man that fights against wicked men. For our skin
cleaues not faster to our flesh, nor our flesh to our

bones, then Transgressions and Iniquities to the
hearts and hands of vs all.
            But to reduce my In
                  •
               ectiue into some method,
as Caesar comprised his Victories in three words,
Veni, vidi, vici. So will I reduce all our extrauagancies
to three other, Corda, ora, opa; our hearts,
our tongues, our▪ hands, are the three weapons
with which we fight against our God, our neighbour,
and our selues, with our hearts wee contemne,
with our tongues we defie, with our hands
we worke against the God of Heauen. Or if you
please, because my Text hath but two words,
Transgressions and Iniquities; I will confine my
selfe also to two particulars, our Transgressions against
the first, and our Iniquities against the second Table.
            The former Table briefely containes in it foure
seuerall Precepts, the first whereof commands internall
pietie, that in our hearts we haue one, and
but one God alone; The second externall worship of
that one God, and sorbids vs to bow our
knees, or prostrate our selues to any grauen or
carued Image, or likenesse of any creature, but
onely to himselfe: and because ex abundantia cordis
os loquitur
               Luc. 6. 45. as our Sauiour saith, as wee conceiue
in our hearts, our tongues will expresse, therfore
the 3. Commandement orders that, which is
the principall member we haue, either to honour
or dishonour our Maker; in it is both life and
deathProu. 18. 21. saith Salomon; that commands vs to exercise
them 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                in blessing and praising

his holy Name, not in swearing, cursing, and blaspheming,
but to speake reuerently as befits the
seruants of so great a Maiestie. And as at all
times we ought to be busied in the celebration of
his praises, so especially on that day which he hath
set apart for his diuine worship, in the Tabernacle
and great congregation; for which the fourth
Commandement takes order, which sets one day
apart wherein we should meete and pray to him
for things wanting, and praise him for benefites
receiued at his hands.
            Giue me a man that hath not transgrest against
these foure words, and I will say and pronounce,
that he needs no Sauiour, nay himselfe shall become
a kinde of a Sauiour of his fellow-brethren.
I may not be long in particulars, I shall but onely
touch them leui digito, asNum. 6. 13. the 12. Searchers of Canaan
brought some of the fruit of the land to their
brethren, for a taste, so must I onely trouble you
with a few, and in briefe of our rebellions in this
kinde, yet so as ex vnguê Leonem, yee may ghesse
at the Lyon by his clawes, wee shall see that, what
the most are by act, all of vs are by nature.
            To taxe vs with the cōmon Idolatry of bowing
our selues asExod. 32. the Iewes to their golden Calfe,
to any carued or grauen Image, it shall now be
altogether vnnecessary, sith the glorious shine
of the Gospell hath quite dispeld all those mists
of ignorance and superstition; those Idolatrous
Micha's that are, dare not, (thrice blessed bee that
power by which they dare not) shew themselues

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
abroad, but like Owles and Batts in obscuritie, or
Be
                  •
               sts in their dennes, they bury themselues in
their secret and vnknowne Houses, and there
more blinded, then the
                  
                     •
                   King. 11. 
               Syrians were when they
were led into Sa
                     •
                  aria, fall to their abominations;
But such order is happily taken, by direction from
his sacred Majestie to his Iudges and principall
Officers of state, that these Cacus-dennes shall bee
more narrowly searched into, and these Wooden

                     •
                  riests, and wooden Saints, together with their
wooden Gods, shall be excluded our Israel, and
sent to eate their bread in those places where first
they suckt their contagious Poyson, or liuing
here, they shall be serued as theIosh. 9. 
               Gibeonites were,
so kept vnder and supprest, as they shall neuer endanger
our State and Common-wealth. When
the head hath thus well ordered and commanded,
may those hands forget their cunning that shall either
be carelesse, or negligent in the execution.
Cursed may he be, and may the curse cleaue to his
seed, that shall doe this worke of his Lord and
Master perfunctorily with a double heart, or a
double eye, carrying fire in one hand, the authority
and command of the King, and water in the
other; his owne timorous or 
                  •
               upine conniuence.
            But there is another Idolatry more common,
no lesse dangerous then that other, if theCol. 3. 5. Apostle
deceiue vs not, Couetousnesse is Idolatry, and
there are whose backes andPhil. 3. 19. 
               Belly is their God.
Mammon is the God of the Couetous, and Belial
of the Voluptuous; these are thy Gods ô England,
               
to which the greatest part of the Inhabitants are
votaries and Idolaters; in these respects wee may
complaine as the Prophet did of Iudah and Ierusalem,
               Ier. 11. 18. 
               According to the number of thy Cities O
Iudah haue they set vp Altars, and according to the
number of thy streets O Ierusalem haue they erected
Images, so according to the number of men are
their Idolatries. The Heathen were justly taxed
for burdening the poore shoulders of Atlas with
so many Deities, for euery seuerall purpose they
had one, for Peace, for Warre, for Corne, for
Wine, houshold-Gods, aud Country-Gods, and
Citie-Gods, and field-Gods; 
                  •
               ay, Rome was so
base in it, as to erect a god-head for their draughthouses,
Cloacina was the Goddesse for that purpose.
Tantum religio potuit suadere malorum,
Wherein are we inferiour, and in what are they
better that dei
                  •
               ie their throates or bellyes? that
ob vnius horaehilarem insaniam, as Drunkenesse is
called, diuest themselues of all hope of eternall
happinesse: Whose Temple is the Tauerne, and
the Drawers their Priests, the Flaggons of Wine
their sacrifice, which they poure downe their
Throates, as the Heathen did to their god Bacchus,
and so giue a drinke-offering to the Deuill.
            That Epicure that wished his necke as long as
a Cranes, that he might haue the longer pleasure
of his meates and drinkes, compared to many a
man in our times might bee thought temperate,
andLuc. 16. 19. 
               Di
                     •
                  es his dain
                     •
                  y fare; or Apitius dyet would
be thought penurious.
            
               
The Diuells walke is vndertaken,Iob 1. Seas and
Lands are compassed for the satisfying our appetites
in this kinde; and as
                  
                     •
                   Sa
                     •
                  . 24. 17. 
               Dauid called the water
of Bethlehem fetcht with the hazzard of the liues
of his men, the blood of those men, so the blood
of many men is daily drunke, and drunke in excesse,
that blood of the Grape fetcht from farre
alwayes with the hazzard, and many times with
the losse of many a mans life. Nor doth the variety
so much offend, as the abominable superfluity
in the abuse of them, making them indeed the liquors
of blood, beginning them to the healths of
ourrfriends, but often ending like Tragedies in
one anothers Massacre.
            As Seneca complained in his times, vidi ebrioserum
sitim &amp; v
                     •
                  mentium famem, haue we as much
reason to complaine in ours, there being obiected
daily to our eyes, as was to the blinde mans in the
Mark. 8. 24. Gospell at the first recouery of his sight, Men
walking like trees, shaking like the tops of them in
a winde, reeling like a vessell in a tempest at Sea,
cutting indentures with their inconstant feete
without sense or shame, or controlement.
            I haue read that Cleopatra beat a Iewell valued
at 50000. pound to powder, and drunke it off at
one draught to the Health of Marke Anthony,
such summes few of our Drunkards are guilty of,
but as Christ said in theM
                     ••
                  k. 16. 43. Gospell, that the Widow
in offering but two mites, offered more then
the rich Pharisees did, because she offered all she
had, so in this respect wee haue among vs, that

drinke more then that vaine woman did, ventring
their whole estates through the 
                  
                     ••
                  raytes of their
throate, and haue lost it all in the bottome thereof
their Bellyes, themselues hauing beene after
such shipwracke forced with Belisarius in Rome to
beg a farthing, and glad, with theLuc. 15. Prodigall, of
Huskes and Acornes for want of other food.
            And for our Tables, how are they surcharged
with the weight of dishes vpon them; One fowle
is fed 100. times, that it may feed vs but once, aud
Rom. 5. 22. 
               all the creatures groane vnder that burden, Ha
                     •
                  d
necessitatem deprecantes sed iniuriam, They willingly
like thoseNum. 11. Quayles in the Wildernesse, offering
themselues to our slaughter for our necessity,
onely desiring the excessiue abuse of them to
be forborne. I know there must be Feasts for the
honour of Kingdomes, of States, of Magistracy,
publike persons must haue such publike meetings
as their worth and place requires, but for1 Sam. 25. a Luc. 16. 19. 
               Nabal
to feast like a King; for homo quidam as Diues was
called, a certaine rich man, to fare daintily quotidie,
he is the Belly-God, and this is his Idolatry;
whose Kitchin is his Temple, whose Priest is the
Cooke, whose Table is the Altar, and whose meat
his Sacrifice which he daily offers vp to that god,
as the Babilonians sometime did to their Idoll
Bel.
            
            So weighty is the Idolatry of the backe, carrying
thereon whole Farmes and Mannor-Houses
that Clemens Alexandrinus said, it was a a meruaile
they were not killed, Cùm tantum onus baiulent,

Augustus the Emperour tearmed this vanity vexillum
superbiae, nidumque luxuriae, they are tokens
of a naked and a wanton minde, which because
their soules want that inward clothing of grace
and good workes must thus like Sepulchers paint
and beautifie their bodies for want of better ornaments;1 Tim. 2. 10
they are fruitlesse twigs that aspire aloft
when the fertile bowes humbly descend to the
earth. They who thus vainely set out their bodies
as it were to sale, meerely discouer the pouerty of
their spirits.
            It is a pretty picture that points out an English-man
naked, with a Taylor standing by with a
paire of Sheeres in his hand, ready to shape him
into any dresse, sometimes he is French alone,
then Spanish, then Dutch, then Italian, then altogether
like them all, and in all so vnlike himselfe,
that when the true God that made him comes to
see him, hee must needs say Non novi, depart
from me, you have so disguised and mishapen
your selues, as I doe not know you.
            Their faithfull Taylors are the Priests to these
Idolaters, and their Bills their Bibles, which
sometime for want of discharging they keepe by
them, but when they are payd, they profanely cut
them in pieces, but yet so happy are their Priests,
that their tenths grow to a greater heape in the
close, then all their Patrons 9. parts besides.
            But there may bee some reasons for these Idolatryes,
the pleasing of our senses, and the satisfaction
of our flesh, but the other that we should

               Iob 31. 24. 
               say to a wedge of gold thou art my hope, or to siluer,
thou are my confidence, that wee should make
our selues seruants to that which euery beast
treads vnder his feet, this, as it hath lesse shew of
reason in it, so is it farre more hatefull; an abomination
which the Indians themselues abhorred in
Christians, when holding vp a piece of gold,
they cryed Eh De
                     •
                  s C
                     •
                  ristianorum. I cannot but
thinke how soone a couetous man would bee
downe on his face, and▪ vp with his hands to the
diuells worship, should he but say to them, I will
not say as the Deuill did to Christ,Mat. 4. 9. 
               Omnia hac
dabo,
but the least Mole-hill almost that it containes,
which is not more base in it selfe, then vncertaine
for the continuance▪ The holy Altars of
God shall be sacrilegiously robd, and his Sacred
Reuenews purloyned to fill full their Coffers, the
Temples of their Mammon. And so thrifty are
these Beads-men, as they will not be at the charge
of a Priest, themselues will doe that office, or at
least they doe as Micah, Iudg. 17. Consecrate one
of their Sonnes, who looking to their Temples
and golden Gods, sometime play false with them,
as Micah with his Mother, and they with others;
what they get with the sweat of their brow, and
the sorrow of their heart, their sonnes like those
of1 Sam. 2. 
               Eli, spend as merrily. The father grindes
the faces, and grieues the heart of the poore, the
sonne glads the heart, and decks the body of an
Harlot. What Agrippina said of Nero her sonne,
Interim at modò imperet, so the Father hee will

kill, burn, destroy, so he may but get1 Tim. 5. 6. 
               gaine, which
is his godlinesse, and the Sonne kills, burnes, destroyes,
to satisfie his mistresse, which is his Saint,
and the onely matter of his Religion.
            Thus wee violate the two first Commandements,
now for the third and fourth, let our horred
oathes, tearing God in pieces with blasphemy,
withIohn 20. 27. 
               Thomas, putting our fingers into the
wounds of our Sauiour, making new blood thence
to issue afresh, witnesse: Words come not faster
then oathes, and those newly coyned, old ones
are scorned as obsolete, and the forge of our
braines is still on worke for new ones, such as will
make the eares of euery honest Christian man to
tingle and shake, if it were possible, the foundations
of Heauen and Earth.
            So likewise our prophane violation of the Sabaoth;
I will not strictly vrge a ceremoniall abstinence
from all moderate and lawfull recreations
at seasonable houres, but I onely could wish this
day were as happy in its kinde as the other sixe
are in theirs, then are the manuary Trades exercised,
euery man is busie in his vocation, buying or
selling, or the like, few or none are idle, onely this
day wherein our humane Lawes 
                  •
               orbid workes,
and the Diuine lawes command sanctity, men
take more liberty to doe euill, being longer and
with farre greater content in the Tauerne, and
sometime in worse houses then the Temple of
God.
            Thus we multiply our Transgressions as the

hayres of our heads, and there is no end of our
Rebellions the euening of our carelesnesse, and the
morning of our presumption makes the first and
second and third, and all the dayes of our liues.
            And if we thus deale with our God, how doe
wee vse our neighbour? if the first Table bee thus
profaned, how is the second violated? if we swallow
downe these Camels, surely what followes are
but G
                     ••
                  ts, and while we with such facility passe ouer
these Mountaines, Mole-hills will neuer keep
vs in our bounds, and so I come to consider our
Iniquities against the second Table.
            I will but run them ouer. 1. Wee scornefully
cast the cords of superiority from vs, and breake the
b
                     •
                  nds of all subiection in sunder, our Fathers that
begat vs, our Mothers that bore vs, our earthly
gods are neglected and forsaken, should they but
command ought contrary to our humours;
            2. Nay, is life spared when anger and fury is
prouoked? Caligula among the Romans was called
Lutum sanguine maceratum, are there not many
among vs that haue made Blood touch blood?
a wry looke, a misplaced word, a mistake
sometimes hath spilt the blood of him for whom
Christ dyed; Man was made at first to bee as
Exod. 4. 16. 
               Moses to Aaron, a God, a friend, a helper, but
nowIsa. 1. 
               our siluer is become drosse; the beasts de
                  •
               uour
not one the other more fiercely then one
man doth another.
            3. So for the third, How are our bodyes that
should be vessells of honour,1 Cor. 6. 19. 
               Temples for the

Holy Ghost to dwell in, giuen ouer to all vncleannesse,
menIer. 5. 
                     •
                  . 
               neighing with the horse after his female,
and thinking noProu. 9. 17. 
               waters so pleasant, nor any bread
so sweet, as what in that sort is purloyned.
            4. Those Pronounes Meum and Tuum are rased
out of our Grammers, many violently stealing,
but more fraudulently cozening their
Neighbours of their estates;Prou. 20. 14. 
               It is naught, saith
the buyer, and comming to sell it, hee as much
commends it, and in both equally deceiptfull.
            5. How greedily doe our eares sucke in false
Reports of our brethren, and how are our
mouthes with childe till againe they be deliuered
of them to the detraction of their repu
                  •
               es; The
Diuels name comes from such practice Diabolus
is Divulgator, a spreader abroad of euill reports,
so that they that report them, haue the Diuell in
their tongues, and they that receiue and beleeue
them, the Diuell in their eares, both in their
hearts. Nay, are there not found among vs1 King. 21. 
               Sons
of Belial, such as Iesabell procured to sweare against
Naboth, who for a small salary will sweare
downe Innocence it selfe, and condemne it? The
Temple-walkes in the Tearme-time are seldome
vnfurnisht of such necessary mischiefes.
            6. And whence come all these? what is the
ground of all these Iniquities, but our owne concupiscence,
the sinne against the last Commandement,
which as St. Iohn
               1 Ioh. 2. 24. diuides it, is either
carnis or occulorum, withIosh. 7. 21. 
               Achan wee see a Babilonish
garment, and a wedge of gold, and so wee

desire to be fine, or rich, or to enjoy such a beautie,
or to be reuenged in such a kinde, for such an
iniury, and loe all these actuall Iniquities follow.
            These are in grosse our grosse Transgressions
and Iniquities, against which being to declaime, I
could wish I had Stentors voyce, and more sand
to runne out, but there are other things which
call for my labour and your attention: But yet
ere I leaue this verse, with the practice of which
sinnes we so much please our selues, giue me leaue
to doe as the Finers of gold and siluer, who non
solùm aurimassas, verum &amp; bracteolas parvus tollunt,
not onely make vse of the Wedge it selfe,
but euen of the smallest rayes or foyles which
their mettall casteth, so heere giue mee leaue to
note out the first word of the verse, the censure
which the Wisdome of God giues vpon men,
when they are in their greatest Ruffe, in the toppe
of their Pride, as Nebuchadnezzar in his Galleries,
and say withExod. 5. 2. 
               Pharaoh, who is the Lord
that I should obey him, or with
                  
                     •
                   King. 19. 
               Rabsaketh to
Hesekiah, he shall not be able to deliuer thee out
of my hands, I say though they like the Dromedary
weary themselues in the race of their abominations
and yet triumph, thinking that Wisedome
shall onely liue and die with them: Yet see what a
blacke coale they are marked with by the finger of
the Spirit, the honourablest stile they can haue, is
but Fooles, that's the best and most charitable
construction can be giuen of all their actions, and
the fayrest tytle they can deserue. One builds and

thinkes to get him a name that way, another
lades himselfe with thicke Clay to vse the phraseHab. 2. 6. of
the Prophet, and hopes that way to get him a
name, another ventures his life to get him a name
after his death, and there are Catilanary dispositions,
who by mischiefe thinke to procure a
name, as those Inventors of the Powder-treason,
but see here what name they get, this is the denomination
which they haue in their liues, and shall
without repentance be written on their Tombes,
Foole and vnwise to heart, and without vnderstanding
shall each of them be called, and so recorded
to Posterity. As1 Sam. 25. 
               Abigal spake of her
Husband, Nabal is his name, and folly is with
him, so it is with vs all by nature, we are all bound
vp in a bundle of folly together, were wee as wise
as Achitophell
               2 Sam. 16. 23. whose counsell was thought as
the Oracles of God, or as1 Kings 4. 33. 
               Solomon who could
dispute of euery thing, from the Cedar to the
shrubbe, or asGen. 2. 10. 
               Adam, who had the wisedome to
impose names according to the seuerall natures
of euery creature, yet is all1 Cor. 1. 20. the wisdome in the
world folly with God, whoPsal. 2. 
               sits in Heauen and
sees the actions of men, and laughs them to scorne,
and will at last openly discouer their nakednesse
to themselues, that they themselues shall bee enforced
to acknowledge their folly, and bee ashamed
of it.
            Though the sword of Gods vengeance long
rests in the scabberd of 
                  •
               his patience, as it did to
these men here in my Text, yet at last it will bee

drawne forth, The Heathen shall know themselues to
bee but men, and these men to bee but Fooles, the
day of their pleasure is now past, and the night
of their Tribulation comes, they were well
and in health and merry, but see now they are
afflicted, nay, Tarditatem supplitij gravitate compensat,
for see the manner of it; Their soule abhorreth
all meate, and they drawe neere to the
gates of death, and so the second part comes in,
the Disease.
            The cause of our disasters you haue heard, our
Transgressions and our Iniquities, hinc nostri fundi
calamitas, hence is the source of all our sorrowes,
the originall of all our afflictions.
            Had our first Parents continued in that Innocency
wherein they were created the name of affliction
had beene a stranger vnto them, they had
neuer suffered, had neuer dyed, but they starting
aside like a brok
                     •
                  n bow, and falling from that Integrity,
haue not onely brought a death, and that a
double one vpon themselues and their issue Mori
                     •
                  nd
                     •
                  
moriemini, but also encumbred that short
life which was alotted them with a world of sorrow
and vexation. Hence come that infinite
number of diseases which begirt and enuiron this
body of ours, so that not one part from the sole
of the foot to the top of the head may challenge
any freedome and immunity, some whereof ambitiously
aspire to the seate of Maiesty the head,
and there despightfully triumph ouer vs, while others
more humble, no lesse cruell, content

themselues with the Iniury they offer vs in our
more inferiour members; Others there are who as
if they had receiued that commission of his1 King. 22. 31. to
his Souldiers, fight neither against small nor
great, saue the King onely, so these bend all their
forces against the onely fountaine of our life, our
heart, where yet more kindely cruell, they strike
vs with present death, while others to shew the
virulency of their disposition, are many yeeres in
killing vs, during all which time, our whole life is
but labour and sorrow, and the graue is more desired
then all the treasures of the world; One hee
complaines of his head as2 King 4. 19 the Shu
                     •
                  a
                     •
                  it
                     •
                  s Son,
another of his belly,Ier. 4. 19. as the Prophet, another is

                  •
               icke in his legges,1 Kings 15. 
                     •
                  23. as Asa, another of a soare, as
2 Kings 20. 7. 
               Hezekiah, all of vs haue some way or other to
bring vs to these gates of death here spoken of.
            I am not able to call all the seuerall Arrowes of
this quiuer by their proper names, but surely the
least, and most gentle of them is sufficient to rob
vs of the best of natures Iewels our life. We haue
all experience in this kinde of as much as I can
relate, wee see that all the Cities and Townes of
the earth, so farre as the line of them is stretched,
are but humanarum cladium mis
                     •
                  randa consepta, and
though there is but 
                  
                     〈…〉
                  , yet there are
I
                     •
                  numeri exitus, but one way of comming into
the world, yet there are a world of wayes of going
out, and if any question the cause of these
our maladies, let him at his leisure but reade ouer
the 28. of D
                     •
                  ut. and there hee shall see that the
            
               
sinne of his soule is the onely cause of the suffering
of the body. It was the word of the Sonne
of Syrach, Let him that sinneth against his Maker,Ecelesiast. 38. 15.
fall into the hands of the Phisition. And experience
tells vs daily, that there are some Diseases
which grow vpon men meerely by their sinne and
wickednesse; OurLuc. 21. 34. Sauiour bids vs take heed
that our stomacks be not ouer-charged with surfeiting
and drunkennesse. Plures gulâ quàm gladi
                     •
                  ,
a true, though as olde Prouerbe, the Graue
hath beene as much beholding to Intemperance,
as any other thing whatsoeuer. Whence come
our Agues and Feuers, and that other, which was
once out-landish, but may now be called our natiue
disease, not fit to bee named, which breedes
corruption in the bones, and consumes the marrow
in the loynes, but by excesse and voluptuousnesse?
            For this cause2 Cor. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . 30 saith St. Paul, speaking before
of the neglect and abuse of the Sacrament,
many are weake and sicke among you, and many
are fallen asleepe.Ier. 23. 10. For vaine Swearing the
whole Land mournes, and the Heathen did obserue
that 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                as the
Israelites were discomfited for the offence of
Achan.
            
            But for this disease which thus long hath troubled
vs, and which, if any, is particularly meant
in this place, you shall obserue tha
                  •
                that neuer
came, but for some great and grieuous precedent
sinne, in the 11. of Numbers and 16. there the

people were so plagued, the cause is set downe,
their murmuring and impatience, one time against
God, a second time against Moses and Aaron,
So when Dauid lost 70000.2 Sam 24. of the same disease,
the Text saith, for his sinne in numbring the
people. This is calledPsal. 91. 5. 
               the arrow of the Lord
that flyes by day, and when this once comes, the
Text hath it, that Wrath 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                is gone out
from the Lord, as Moses said to Aaron, as if
all other diseases were but whipping with Roddes;
light, and slight afflictions this whipping with
Scorpions, the worst, the terriblest, the most seuere
of all other. It is not the Infection of the Ayre,
nor distemperature of the body, nor the heape of
Inhabitants, nor the Influence of the Stars which
Phisitions could or would euer apply this disease
vnto, but as theExod. 8. 19. Aegyptians said of the Plague
of Lice, Digitus deiest hic, and that for some great
some grieuous offence.
            Wherefore let vs all strike our selues with amazement
vpon the thigh, and say, what haue wee
done, let vs resolue a Christian alteration and reformation,
otherwise though this bee remoued,
yet a worse thing will befall vs, which surely must
be in the other life, for heere naught worse can
come, for see how it is described. Their soule abhorreth
all meate, and they draw neere to the gates of
death. All pleasure, all delights proue hatefull to
them, nay, their necessary foode which should
preserue their being, keepe life and soule together
is loathsome, and then no meruaile though they

bee neere death, for can a fire continue without

                  •
               ewell, and nature bee sustained without its appointed
food?
            But they whom God hath deliuered out of it,
can better expresse the nature of this disease then
my selfe, onely thus much, it is in the most mortall,
in all fearefull and vncomfortable, when a
friend is barred from a friends visite, when hee
shall haue none to close vp his dying eyes, nor to
say to him leaue thy fatherlesse children to mee,
when hee not onely suffers himselfe, but it any be
so aduentrously kinde to come to see him, he may
bee a pe
                  ••
               iduct and an occasion of the like misery
to him.
            But wee haue not changed the colour of our
haire, not added one inch to our statures since
our wet eyes and heauy hearts were witnesses of
more then what my tongue is able to relate; when
naught was heard but crying and complaining in
our streetes, no fights but some carrying others
to their graues, and not many dayes after, others
doing the like necessary office for them.
Gods arme is not yet shortned, nor his strength
so much weakened, but that if wee still sinne, hee
will surely smite againe.
            The onely way to make a perfect cure, is to
humble our selues vnder the hand of heauen, who
hath wounded vs, and who can heale vs, the Soare is
but skinned, not perfectly healed without that
plaister be applyed, this did these in my Text.
            Then they cryed vnto the Lord in their troubles.
            
               
               Prou. 26. 3. A whippe for the Horse, and a Bridle for the
Asse, and the Rod is for the backe of a Foole.
They haue sinned and smarted, and now they
feele it and cry for helpe.
            The wilde Asse vsed to the Wildernesse snuffeth
vp winde at her pleasure, who can turne her
backe? they that seeke after her will not weary
themselues, but they will finde her in her moneth,
Ier. 2. God sees and obserues at all times the vntamednesse
of the wicked, wearying themselues
like an Asse in the by-paths of vngodlinesse, but
hee takes them in their Moneth, and happy are
they that are so taken.
            As St. Austin of necessity, so say I of miserie,
Foelix qua in meliora cogit, happy misery that
driues vs to eternall happinesse. Aduersity makes
them seeke to that God whom their prosperitie
made them forget. In the time of their trouble
they will say, Arise and saue vs saith God, Ier. 2.
27.2 Chron. 33. 12. Binde Manasses with Chaines, and load him
with Irons, bow downe his nceke, and his backe
with bonds, and hee will soone know himselfe;
Pull the King of Babilon also from his Throne,Dan. 4. lay
his honour and insolency in the dust, banish him
the company of men, turne him to eate grasse
with the Oxe in the field, and he will at last learne
to praise the King of Heauen: Let Moab settle
her selfe vpon her Lees, and not be emptyed from
vessell to vessell, and her sent will remaine in her,
Ier. 48. doth the wilde Asse bray when hee hath
grasse, or the Oxe low when hee hath Fodder?
            
               
               Iob 6. giue but any of the sonnes of men, peace,
plenty, and prosperity, all things at his hearts desire,
let but the Sunne of happinesse still shine vpon
him, how like Waxe will he melt into all pleasure,
and cast off the yoake of all obedience, but
let stormes and frownes seaze on him, then hee
will say,Hos. 6. 1. 2. Come and let vs returne vnto the
Lord, for he hath spoyled vs and he will heale vs,
he hath wounded vs, and he will binde vs vp. I
doubt not but there are many who heretofore
haue beene wilde like the vntamed Heifer, that the
Lord hath by this rod of chasti
                  •
               ement reduced
home, and made them his, who had they not thus
suffered perierant nis
                     •
                   perijssent, had they not lost
their liues or their healths, had lost their soules.
And thrice woe to that soule that shall not make
this vse of this his preseruation, and of Gods correction.
It is a fearefull complaint that God hath
in the second of Ier. I haue smitten their children
and they haue receiued no correction, that heart
must needs bee seared as with an hot Iron, that is
not sensible of these stripes, and wee cannot but
iudge him, deliuered vp to a reprobate sense, that
is not mollified at these afflictions. What can
preuaile when neither Mercy nor Iudgement are
auailable?2 Sam. 
                     •
                  0. 16. They were wont to enq
                  •
               ire of Abel,
saith that mother in Israel to Ioab, when hee besieged
that Citie, before they destroy it, so doth
God, the grand Captaine of Heauen and Earth,
as Tamberlaine was wont to doe, first hang
out his white flagge to any Citie hee enuironed,

his proffer of peace and mercy if they will yeeld,
then the red Flagge of threatnings, yet so as if
yet they would submit, there was hope, but lastly
the blacke Flagge was displayed, and then no
way but death and destruction if he preuailed; so
doth God first offer mercy, which if abused, then
he threatens, and long it is before hee strikes, hee
was 120. yeares before he smote the old world, if
those preuaile not, then he strikes, but so gently as
it shall but bee a taste as it were of what hee can
doe, which if that also be in vaine, Immedicabile
vulnus ense recidendum, that man is incurable, and
must needs be cut off. Wee haue had so long, so
large, so flourishing a time of peace, as our G
                     •
                  
                  shen
hath beene as it were the enuy of all the Nations
of the world besides, this little fleece of ours
hath beene dry, when all the earth round about vs
hath beene ouerwhelmed with the Deluge and
Inundation of Warre; Germany groaning vnder
persecution, France encumbred with her fatall infelicity,
Ciuil wars, Italy burdened with the tyrannie
of Antichrist, Spaine ambitiously desiring to

                  •
               athom all, like to keepe nothing▪ The Hollanders
continually at warre, onely we, by the blessing of
our God, and the happy meanes of our late Soueraigne
of euer blessed memory haue sit vnder
our Vines and Fig-trees; But yet this peace hauing
bred corruption, we haue had light and small punishments
many times inflicted, by Water, by
Fire, and by the Pestilence, and all but to reclaime
vs, which if we doe not seriously lay to heart, the

sable flagge will be displayed: Our Candle will bee
extinguishe, a night will come, an eternall night
of destruction both of body and soule. But such
was our happinesse, as in the time of our generall
sufferings, wee had a generall sorrow commanded,
a Fast was proclaimed by the King and his
NoblesIon. 3. as it was at Niniueh, and wee all wept
and mourned, and prayed, and cryed vnto the
Lord, and, I hope and dare say by the happy effect,
it was serious and in earnest, with these in my
Text we cryed, and wee are deliuered.1 Sam. 2. 9. 
               Annah
in a part of her song tells vs, that it is the wont of
the wicked in the time of Affliction, to lay their
hands vpon their mouthes, and hearts too, they
fret with indignation, and repine to themselues,
letting neither voyce nor groane come forth, nor
any token of submission to him that hath cast
them downe. But saith St. Gregory, Tolerare &amp; odisse
non tam virtus mansuetudinis, quàm velamentum
furoris, which because they dare not vtter,
Murmura tunc secum &amp; 
                     •
                  abiosa silentia rodunt,
they bite the lippe with an impatient silence,
which comes from no other but from the Diuell
himselfe, as Tertullian witnesseth, Impatientiae natales
inipso diabol
                     •
                   deprehendo, but here as there
was outward smart and inward sorrow, so there
was a vocall expression of it, no way giuing any
discontent, as2 Kings 6. 13. that King said, this euill commeth
of the Lord, why should I waite any more
vpon him? but onely a vociseration and hearty
inuocation for mercy.
            
               
In the great Famine of Samaria, a woman came
and cryed vnto the King, Helpe
                  Ibid 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  . 27. my Lord ô
King, the King wisely and soundly replyed, How
should I helpe with the Barne, or with the Winepresse,
seeing the Lord denies vs, In vaine shall we
goe to Gilead for Balme, to the Apothecaries for
Oyntment, to Physitions for receipts, to any for
helpe, vnlesse withall wee cry vnto the Lord, it is
not the plaister of Figges, nor bathing in Iordane,
nor washing in the Poole of Bethesda, that will here
cure, but onely seeking to the Lord, and yet the
other are not to be neglected:1 King. 15. 
               Asa was not condemned
for seeking to Phisitions, but because he
neglected the Lord.Eccle. 38. 1. Phisitions are honourable,
and the act of the Apothecary is to bee made vse
of. Wherefore hath God infused vertue into
Plants and Mettals, but to be vsed?2 King. 20. Did not he
command Hesekiah's Plaister?2 King. 5. And was not
Naman willed to wash? they are onely here condemned,
that altogether neglect the Lord, and
onely rely vpon these who can doe nothing without
him, Nec Deus oratur nisi dignus vindice nodus,
Inciderit,
               1 Cor. 3. 6. 
               Paul may Plant, and Apollos may
in their kinde water, Phisitions may prescribe,
and Apothecaries may apply, but our health onely
comes from aboue.
            
               Virtus est in herbis plus gemmis, maxima verbis,
there may,Chap. 38. 9. and there is power and efficacie in
Herbes, and Mettals, but Prayer is the chiefe, and
principall efficient. Pray vnto the Lord in thy
sicknesse saith the Son of Syrach, and he will make

thee whole, And it isIam. 5. 15. 
               St. Iames his counsell,
if any bee sicke, let him send for the Elders of
the Church, and let them pray ouer him, and so
the prayer of the faithfull shall saue the sicke, and the
Lord shall raise him vp. A reall experience whereof
these men had, for no sooner did they cry vnto
the Lord but he deliuereth them out of their distresse.
Hee sent his Word, &amp;c.
            I remember a certaine speech by Bias vsed in
iest in that earnest, when certaine Marriners were
in distresse, and were euery one like those in Ionas
crying vpon his God, sile
                     •
                  e ne audiant dij vos
hac preterire,
               1 King. 20. 31. The Kings of Israel, say the seruants
of Benhadad are mercifull Kings. I am sure the
God of Israel is a mercifull God, who will heare
the vnfeigned cry of the most wicked in their afflictions.
            As the cold of Snow in the time of Haruest, so
is a faithfull messenger to him that sends him, for
hee refresheth the soule of his Master, saith Salomon,
Prou. 25. 13. Here is a faithfull Mercury, a
winged Messenger, that in so short a space hath
climbed vp into the highest Heauen, and gotten
Audience. What manicles to the hands of Gods
iustice are the cryes of poore afflicted penitent
men, that will not suffer him to proceed in his intended
vengeance! Nay, rather then they shall
faile, God himselfe shall seeme to bee mutable,
who though he threatneth Niniueh without any
hope of escape, yet vpon those prayers is intreated
to spare them. Or rather how gratious is our

God, and willing to be thus intreated, who vpon
the first call answers and performes, hee in the
Luc. 11. 17. Gospell when his friend did but knock at an vnseasonable
time, answered, the doores were lockt,
the children were in bed, &amp; so did not satisfie his
desire, but for a loafe of bread; But no such thing
here, no time in all our life is vnseasonable; the
first, the second, the third 
                  〈◊〉
                hee heares and
opens. Bis qui citò, the bene
                  •••
                is double, that is
speedily performed.1 Kings 18. 28. The Priests of Baal prayed
from morning till noone, and could get no answer,
but the first word of Elias fetcht fire. And
indeed how should such suppliants praying to
such deities be heard, for what taste is there in the
white of an Egge, or how can Baal, or any other
liuing or dead creature heare or helpe, when they
cannot helpe themselues? It is onely the infinite
Maker and creator of the eare that can heare all
men, at all places, at all times altogether. No
Saint, no Angell, no forged or feigned god-head
can doe that, but onely the God of all power and
might, the mightie God of Heauen and Earth.
Vna eademque manus vulnus opemque tulit, He that
bruised can againe binde vp, hee that made the
wound can, and onely did cure it, now the means
which he vsed was his Word. Hee sent his Word
and healed them, &amp;c.
            This is that Delphian Sword, or vniuersall Instrument
which hee vsed in framing the World
with all that therein is; Hee said, let there bee
Light, and there was light; Let there be Firmament,

let the Waters be gathered into one place,
and let the drie Land appeare, and all was fulfilled;
and Hee still vpholdeth all things by the Word
of his power, Heb. 1. What is his Word now but
the reall and effectuall performance of what hee
intends, he but speakes, and all things in Heauen
and Earth, and the great Deepes presently are obedient.
I see now as manMat. 4. 
               liues not by bread alone,
but by euery word which proceedes out of
the mouth of God, so hee is not cured by Phisicke
alone, but by the onely blessing of the omnipotent
Word of God. No meanes can preuaile
without that, and that with, without, besides, yea,
against all meanes can easily bee preualent. No
God can deliuer asDan. 3. 19. the God of the three Children
can, as the King confessed, whose Dicere is
his Facere. His onely Word is able to bring
mighty things to passe. Whatsoeuer seeme impossibilities
to man, are easily brought to passe by
him that can doe all things. The Sea will bee
calme, Diseases vanish, all the Creatures are morigerous,
yea Diuels themselues are obedient to
this Word, onely Man dares to rebell against it,
but hee that will not bend at the Word of his
command, shall bee broken at the Word of his
Power.
            They that allegorise this part of Scripture, as
Hugo Cardinalis, and Lorinus, make this Disease a
farther proceeding in the wayes of impiety, a
sitting downe in the chayre of vngodlinesse, a deliuering
vp from one sinne to another, and are at

last growne to that height, that they care no more
for their soule, then if they had none, the Word
and Sacraments, the onely food of their soules
they neglect and despise, it is as Wormewood
to their taste, or smoake to their eyes, they so
wholly deuote themselues to sensuality, as it
might seeme to grieue them, non quadrupedes esse
natos, that they might freely take their pleasure
and delight, yet at last God hath a hooke to
drawe these in, a meanes to enlighten and preserue
them. Though they bee dead in sinnes and
trespasses, and with Lazarus buried in the graue,
yet if the Lord doe but say, Exi foras come forth
of that Mare mortuum, wherein like Ionas in the
belly of the Whale, or rather of Hell, as himselfe
called it, they are entombed, their Fetters
fall presently from them, as they did from Peter
in the Prison, they come to acknowledge themselues
Fooles, wicked and rebellious, to say with
Exod. 10. 16 
               Pharaoh, I haue sinned against the Lord. This
is wrought by the power of his Word, that cibus
inconsumptibilis as Ciprian called it, that immortall
Word whichIoh 1. 
               St, Iohn saith, was in the
beginning,
the onely begotten Sonne of God our
blessed Sauiour. Hee like theNum. 21. 9. 
               Brasen Serpent
cures all foule-diseased, that looke vp to him.
            I vrge not this Interpretation to any, I know
one sinne is oftentimes the punishment of another;
as when Israel had2 Sam. 24. prouoked God, hee
stirred vp Dauid to number the people, and it is
the fearefullest judgement that can bee, to heape

more coales vpon the head of the delinquent by
giuing them ouer to their owne hearts lust I know
also, that there is a death of the soule as of the body,
Etiam viuens mortua est, saith1 Tim. 5. 6. St. Paul
of a woman
liuing in pleasure, there is a death spirituall
as temporall, out of which God is able to deliuer.
Nay, his Word, that is the second Person in Trinitie
came for that end into the world, was made
flesh and tooke our nature vpon him, not for the
righteous butMat. 9. 14. 
               to call sinners to
repentance, yea,
though they were twice dead, as hee was called
twice a Murtherer, Semel consilio iterum spectaculo.
Once in the act, and a second time in the glorying
in it. Yet there is a blessing in this dead Elme, though
he be consumed as a Sheepe in the mouth of a Lyon
to a legge or an eare, or as a blocke in the fire to a
stumpe, yet the least breath of his mouth is able to
reuiue him. But the context me thinkes giues no
great warrant for this exposition, hauing both before
and after spoken of temporall dangers and
deliuerances from them. I see no reason why it
should be thought, that herein onely he speakes of
spirituall danger and a spirituall deliuerance.
            I haue hitherto shewed you this disease, with
the cause and the effect of it, The Phisition also I
haue brought you acquainted with, together with
his Phisicke, that if euer there bee the like need againe,
wee may with boldnesse approach the same
throne of grace, and obtaine the like mercy, Probatum est
may be subscribed to this Recipe▪
                so many
sighes mingled with teares, and a quantity of

faith enfused, taken in poculo charitatis, and the
blessing of our Doctor is a 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                for all diseases,
a 
                  •
               ure Antidote against all infection, all amulets
and preseruatiues compared to this, are meere
toyes of Mountebankes. This neuer failes.
            Many heere in this place haue experimentally
tasted of the efficacy of this Medicine, All of vs
haue beene Testes occulati, eye-witnesses of it, some
haue smarted, and all I hope haue beene admonished.
The like cause breeds againe the like disease,
Relapses are most dangerous, Wee haue sinned,
with Dauid, wee with Dauid haue smarted, with
him wee haue sorrowed, and with him wee haue
beene deliuered.Psal. 4
                     •
                  . 
                     •
                  . 
               Abyssus abyssum inuocat
saith
he, the depth of our misery I hope, caused the
depth of our sorrow, and I hope it was according
to the occasion, hearty and vnfeigned; if like1 Kings 21. 
               Ahabs,
it were but feigned and temporary, and like
the carelesse Boy wee forget the rodde with the
smart, and so returne to the vomite; Woe, woe to
that man, the latter end of that man will bee worse
then the beginning. None are now deliuered, but
either to their greater happinesse, or greater miserie.
They who are now spared, are either spared
to redeeme the time that formerly they haue carelesly
lost, or till their sinnes are more ripe for a seuerer
Iudgement. The Israelites were kept out of
the Land of Canaan so long, till the sins of those
Inhabitants were fulfilled.
            
               Luc. 13. 3. Our Sauiour told the Iewes, that they were
not greater sinners vpon whom the Tower of

               Siloa fell then those that escaped, but vnlesse they
repented, they should all likewise perish. De mortuis
nil nisi bonum, saith the Canon; Our Predecessors
sinnes haue not beene more great against
God, but Gods mercy hath been more towards vs;
Many greene and fruitfull Trees haue beene cut vp,
when leauy and barren Trees are let alone; Wee
haue seene Death like an vnskilfull Archer shooting
at Rouers, hath hit our superiours aboue vs,
our inferiours beneath vs, our friends on our right
hand, our foes on our left. The Cedars haue beene
pluckt vp, and the shrubbes haue continued. Nay,
to make the remembrance this fatall yeare for euer
weare a sable liuery, hee of whom wee may
say as the Israelites did of Dauid,
               2 Sam. 18. 
               hee is worth
10000. of vs, our blessed Peace-maker vnder whose
branches we haue 22. yeares sate shadowed from
the scorching heate of Warre, which hath parcht
and withered most of our neighbour
                  •
                Nations.
Yet now, though not of this, yet of another as
violent a disease hath beene taken away, and but
that reliquisset nobis semen, he hath left vs of his
seed, the flourishing estate of our Kingdome
might haue dyed with him. Wee haue also beene
bereft within the space of two yeares of many of
the principall Peeres, and Pillers of the State, two
Dukes, one Marquesse, fiue or sixe Earles, some
Barons, and most of them Priuie Counsellours,
all which were, as if our armes had been cut from
our bodyes, or our eyes pluckt out of our heads.
And then so many thousands of inferior subiects,

as the memorie of man cannot equalise it. And
loe, all we that are aliue this day, are escaped as a
bird out of the snare of the Fowler. But let mee tell
you, we may be deliuered in sixe troubles, and the
seauenth may dispatch vs, we may escape the pit,
and be taken in the snare, as Ier. 48. 44. Wee may
flee from a Lyon, and a Beare shall ouertake vs, or
leane our hand vpon a Wall, and a Serpent shall
bite vs, Amos 5. 19. Him that escapeth the Sword
of Hasael shall Iehu slay, and him that escapes the
Sword of Iehu, shall Elisha slay, 1. Reg. 19. Though
our Master hath thus long deferred his comming
to vs, yet at last the time of our Audit will come,
we must all Reddere rationem, we must stand at the
barre, and answer to what shall be obiected.Luc. 12. 18. 
               To
whom much is giuen, of him much shall bee required.
The longer life afforded, we must either performe
more dutie, or expect more paine; our Lord will
take an accompt of our Talents bee they more or
lesse, and in what kinde soeuer. Wherefore seeing
our sinnes are the cause of Gods anger and our
sufferings, and hauing had but the lappes of our garments
in comparison1 Kings 2
                     •
                  . cut off, as Dauid did to
Saul, to shew what he might haue done. As wee
haue sorrowed outwardly, so let vs shew the fruits
of it. It is not the wearing o
                  •
                customary blackes,
the absteining from one meale in the weeke, or the
bowing of the head like a bulrush, that God respects,
it is the absteyning from our Transgressions and
Iniquities that he regards, Oportet aliquid esse intus
as he said of a dead body to make it stand; So

there must be a true sorrow attended with visible
workes, which argue sound repentance. It is true,
we did fast and pray, and mourne, and cry, while
the rod was vpon vs, and did not God regard vs?
he beyond expectation spake to the Destroying
Angell to desist. Now therefore as the effect of
Iudgement was compunction, and sorrow, and wee
did expresse that heartily and really in the liberall
and freely relieuing the necessity of our brethren,
for which double honour shall euer attend this
honourable City, which may be a patterne and example
to all the Kingdome of liberall and Charitable
contribution: So now after mercy receiued,
let us expresse the thankfulnesse of our hearts,
in vocall thanks-giuing, and actuall obedience to
his behests. And so I come to the last part of all
The Fee which the Preseruer of men as Iob called
him, our God respects from vs. Oh that men, &amp;c.
            Wherein wee haue qui, quem, quid, quarè, the
partyes, Who, Men, the dutie what, Praise, the
obiect whom, The Lord; the reason why, for his
goodnesse and wonderfull workes, endeared vnto vs
by the mention of the partyes to whom this goodnesse,
these wonderfull workes were extended, The
Children of Men. I shall racke your patience but a
very little while to runne ouer these, and I shall
conclude.
            1. The first Who, Men. They who erewhile
when they thought themselues wise were called
Fooles, are now, being humbled at the sight of their
sinne, and sense of their sorrow called Men. They

haue lost nothing by losing all they had, they
haue gained now their true denomination. The
nature of Man in his fi
                  •
               st Creation, before that
lumpe was soured with the leuin of sinne, was full
of glory and grace, and as God said to Dauid, I
made thee King ouer Israel, and if that had beene
too
               2 Sam. 12. 
               little for thee, I would haue done more; So Man
was made King, and put in Lord-like dominion ouer
all the earth, not of some cantons or corners,
but ouer it all; Nay, the ayre and the Sea also were
put vnder his dominion, with all the creatures in
them all, all things were created for vs2 Phisi
                     •
                  . 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
as Aristo: wee are in a manner the
end of all things. And if this be too little, God
hath yet done more for vs, for our sakes were the
Heauens created, and for our sakes were the Heauens
bowed, and propter hominem Deus homo factus
est, God was made Man to pleasure Man. The wise
men in the world, who could neuer looke so farre
into the nature of Man, as wee can, yet euermore
commended that Creature aboue all others; One
called him a little world, the world a great man, another
a mortall God, God an immortall Man, another
all things, because he partakes the nature of
Plants, of Beasts, and of spirituall Creatures. Phauorinus
merueiled at nothing in the World besides
man, in man at nothing but his minde. Abdala
the Sarazen being asked what he most admired
in the Stage of the world, answered Man; and
Augustin saith, that a man is a greater miracle then
all the miracles that euer haue beene wrought

amongst men. When Vedius Pollio a Romane at
a supper prouided for the Emperour Augustus,
would haue throwne a seruant of his into a Fishpond
wherein hee kept his Lampries, because
he had broken a Cup of Christall, the Emperour
with-held him, &amp; controld him with these words,
Homo cuiuscunque conditionis, &amp;c. Aman of whatsoeuer
conditions, yet if for no other reason, yet
because a man is more worth then all the Cuppes
and Fish-ponds in the world. Great reason then
there is for the performance of this dutie, that
Man should praise and magnifie his Maker, if for
no other reason, yet because hee hath made him
Man; he hath giuen him a soule to gouerne his
body, and reason to rule his soule, and a Religion
to direct that reason, and he himselfe who is all
Good, all Wise, all Religious is the Lord of that
Religion, and expects that homage and onely
Man can performe it, faile not then. Other creatures
haue bodyes but no soules, mouthes and
tongues, but not the gift of speech, onely that is
proper to Man, and that is the instrument wherewith
we are to praise him, and so the second; the
duty, Praise.
            
            The word in the originall which signifies laudare
is also Confiteri, for that is a part of the praise
which God requires, we must humble our selues at
his presence, acknowledge our owne vnworthinesse,
and that all his punishments are farre lesse
then our deseruings.Iosh. 7. 19. 
               Ioshua wished
Achan to confesse
his fault, and so to giue glory to God. We commend

the proceeding of the Almighty when wee
condemne our selues, our falling low before him,
exalts him the more; and when we lay open our
weaknes, is his power made more illustrious.
                  
                     〈…〉
                  . 
               We
must in all things giue thankes, saith St. Paul, if in our
Aduersity, then much more in our prosperity, if
like the beast we looke onely downward for what
we receiue. Os homini sublime dedit coelumque tueri
Iussit, when our faces are erect, &amp; we should onely
minde Heauen, if we onely look to secondary causes
&amp; meanes for our blessings, and so neglect the
God that gaue them, the earth it selfe will spue vs
vs out as an vnworthy burden: But now it is not
onely theHeb. 13. 15. 
               fruit of our lips as the author to the
Hebrews
calls them, which is here expected;1 Sam. 15. 22.
               Obedience
saith Samuel to Saul is better then sacrifice. It is
in Thanks-giuing, the onely Christian sacrifice, as
in the old Sacrifices, nunquàm in odoribus sacrificiorum
delectatus est, Dominus, nisi in fide &amp; desiderio
offerentis, saith St. Augustine, the outward act
neuer was acceptable without inward piety and
deuotion, Cain and Abel both sacrificed and externally
both alike; but the soule of a sacrifice a faithfull
heart was wanting inGen. 4. 
               Caines which God saw
who looks as with Cresset-light into the closet of a
mans heart, &amp; so refused it, &amp; accepted the other.
            They are men that may be deceiued with words,
but God is a God of spirits, as of bodyes, and so will
be magnified in both. Mens cuiusque est quisque, &amp;
so the meaning and inward intention of an action
is the reality of it. To blesse God with our lips, and

blaspheme him in our 
                  
                     •
                  hearts, is to honour him ex
vsu magis quàm sensu, rather of custome then deuotion.
God is weary of this lip-labour, it is as if
you offered a dog in sacrifice. Honorant me labijs
               Isa. 29. 13. saith God in the Prophet, cor autem eorum longi
àme, God hath the Tongue and Mammon, or Milchrom,
or Belial hath the heart, what is this but to
mocke God? but be not deceiued God will not bee
mocked; he searcheth the inward parts of man, and
there findes the dissimulation of the heart which
cries to the tongue, make a shew of piety, do something
to get me credit among men. But alasse Adam
was not more naked when God called him
after his fall, then the hipocrisie of these men shall
be discouered. Praise him with our tongues, and
blesse him with our hearts, and serue him with our
hands, this is the true praising of him; For as hee
made all these parts, so hee will be serued in them
all, and he hath power of all, for he is Lord of all,
which is the third; Praise the Lord. A Lord that
hath power ouer vs, as the Potter ouer his vessell, if
it distastes him; Hee challengeth duty and obseruance
of vs, first by creation, then by preseruation; he
stil defends &amp; prouides for vs, then by protection he
keeps vs in all our wayes, so that no euill shall be
                  •
               ide
vs, but chiefly in our assured hope of glorification.
Him that honours me,
               1 Sam. 2. 30. saith himselfe: I will
honour.
Scipio repented that he had not a Souldier in all
his Army, who if he commanded would not cast
himselfe headlong from a steep Tower to the Sea;
a powerfull Lord▪ &amp; an obedient Army, no doubt

we owe as much seruice▪ to our Lord as Scipio's
Souldiers did him, and hee will as amply recompence
it. When Gedeon had deliuered the Israelites
out of the hands of Mad
                     •
                  an, they came to him and
said, Thoushalt be Lord ouer vs for thou hast deliuered
vs. Iudg. 18. 28. Whether God hath mightily
deliuered vs, let our selues be iudges, and whether
euen by those deliuerances hee may not challenge
superiority ouer vs; Nay, these deliuerances are but
earnests and pledges of what he yet will doe, that
glory that shall be reuealed to those that truly glorifie
him, is farre beyond the shallow heart of man
to conceiue, glory and Immortality, and life, and ioy,
and pleasure at his right hand for euermore. If these
certaine hopes will not allure; yet let feare stirre
vs vp, the consideration of what is due to the neglect
of it. What a reprehension did our Sauiour
giue those vnthankfull Leapers,Luc. 17. 17. 
               Were there not
ten healed, where are the other nine? a fearfull thing
when the Creator shall aske where the Creature is,
as God asked Adam in the Garden after his fall,
Where art thou?
               Ioh. 1. 18. our Sauiour saw Nathaniell vnder
the Fig-tree; so no doubt he knew where those
nine ingratefull men were, but by their ingratitude
they were lost in themselues, and so were quite
out of his protection. He will be a Lord no longer
to defend and protect vs, then we are seruants
to obey him; Not a seruant here below that will
endure his Masters disgrace,
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  . 
               ais aio, negas nego,
saith hee in the Comedy! Their Masters word
goes still for a lawe, and hee will be more iealous

of his Masters honour then his owne peace, shall
earthly seruants be so obseruant of their earthly
Masters from whom time may release them, or distance
of place secure them, and shall we dare to
neglect our obeisance against him, against whom
there is no priuiledge? No place, nor any time
can exempt vs from his Dominion.Mat. 25. The vnprofitable
seruant that gaue his Master his owne Talent,
yet was condemned because hee did not increase
it, where shall they then appeare that doe
not giue him what of right belongs to him?
Mat. 22. 21. When the Pharisees tempted Christ by asking
him whether they should giue tribute to Caesar or
no, he called for a penny, and seeing Cesars image
and superscription vpon it, iudged it his, giue saith
he to Cesar the things which are Cesars, and to God
the things which are Gods; Honour, and glory and
praise, is that which of due belongs to him, and
that which all the host of Heauen, Angells and
Saints, daily sing vnto him; Holy, holy, holy Lord
God of Sabaoth, Heauen and Earth are full of thy glory,
the glorious company of Prophets praise thee, the
noble army of Martyrs praise thee, The Holy Church
throughout all the world doth acknowledge thee.
               Luc. 2. 14. In
the Angels song there went gloria in Excelsis, before
Pax in terris, no peace on earth, if no glory to
Heauen, and yeeld but that Peace shall be within our
Walls, &amp; plenteousnes within our dwellings. Would
yee yet know a farther reason wherfore yee should
praise him, my Text tels you; For his goodnesse▪
                &amp;c.
            
               Meruailous are thy workes saith Dauid, in Wisdome

hast tho
                     •
                   made them all, the earth is full of thy goodnesse,
so is the broad Sea also, not the least creature
in the Ayre, or the Earth, or the Water, but if we
rightly consider, it is fearefully and wonderfully
made, &amp; the least part or member of them is more
then the weake and shallow reach of Man is able
either duly to commend or to comprehend rightly.
It is a true position in morality, nimia familiaritas
parit contemptum, it is also true in Diuinity,
Perseuerantia consuetudi
                     •
                  is amisit admirationem;
quàm multa vsitata caleantur, qua considerata stupent?
saith Augustine, how many things doth custome
make vile, which consideration would
make admirable? Did wee but with Dauid truly
consider the creation of our selues, that wee are
wonderfully made, and that our bones were not hidden
from him, though they were formed in a secret
place, it would enforce vs to giue acclamation to
the workmanship of our Maker, as that sweet singer
of Israell there did, Meruailous are thy workes
O Lord, and that my soule knowes right-well.
            
            Then haue the wondrous workes of God their
true end, when we take them for wonders, when we
tremble at the sight of them, and feare that mighty
Lord that hath wrought them, God doth not
miracula propter miracula, but for our sakes, not caring
so much himselfe to doe them, as that wee
consider and beare them away. The gratious God
saith Dauid, hath made his wonderfull workes to bee
had in remembrance. O Lord how gratious art thou,
thy workes are very deepe, an vnwise man knoweth it

not, and a foole doth not vnderstand it; So that all
his Goodnesse is extended to vs, and his Meruailous
workes are done for vs, which are the Children
of men. The last part of all. O that Men, &amp;c.
            
               Tantus ille, tantilli nos, this addes to our engagement;
That he should so consider vs, and
thinke vpon vs, that neuer thinke vpon him; that
he should regard vs that neuer minde him; for vs
that haue deserued so little at his hands, nay, rather
so much, so much misery, &amp; so many plagues,
being non prius nati quàm damnati: that are not
onely strangers but enemies, and that the most despightfully
conditioned that can bee, vessells of
wrath, and sonnes of perdition, that he should doe
all these things for vs; how are we honoured, that
he will vouchsafe to be honoured by vs so vile, so
vnworthy as we are? All that we can doe is a thousand
times lesse then a drop of raine to the Ocea
                     •
                  ,
he is infinite of himselfe, and nothing can bee added
to him, it is onely our happinesse, our welfare
and aduantage.
            The wonder which Dauid here instanceth in, is
the recouery of vs out of sicknesse. Wee little consider
how daily and hourely wee stand beholding
to God for our liues and healths, when wee haue
such enemies within, the Elements wherof we are
composed, heate and cold, moisture and drought,
which being brethren of one house, as one called
them, but withall the Fathers and Founders of
vs, as it were of our natures, if they but fall at variance
within vs, how will they rend and teare vs

like wilde Boares, how many haue beene buryed
aliue in the graue of their earthly and melancholike
Imaginations? how many burnt in the flames
of pestilent and hot diseases? their bowels set on
fire like an Ouen, their blood dried vp, their inwards
withered and wasted with the violence
thereof? The vapours and fumes of their owne vitious
stomacks, like a contagious Ayre how many
haue they poysoned and choaked vp? and finally
how many haue been glutted and ouercharged
with water betweene their owne skinne and
bones? And therefore we must conclude and cry
with the Prophet; It is the wonderfull mercie of
God, that we are not consumed.
            
            
               When a grape-gatherer comes, will he not leaue some
grapes! if ought in the opening of this Scripture
hath escaped me, as my ignorance &amp; weaknes dare
hope for no other, it wil be your charity to impute
it to multitude of other priuate businesse, and breuitie
of time, in which as Agabus with the girdle
of Paul I am confined, these few sands are too little
to expatiate my selfe in these many and various
points which offer themselues to our consideration,
though not all of some, yet somewhat, I hope
I haue spoken of all; I would gladly conclude with
some short application.
            How many are there now in this City aliue,
that haue beene summoned as Hezekiah was, to set
their house in order, for they thought no other
but they must die? that haue seene before them,
the greedy and inexorable Graue with open

mouth ready to receiue them; that friends and
Phisitions haue all forsaken, giuing them for dead,
yet haue escaped, and are recouered, and many
there are also, to whom God hath giuen continuance
of health in this generall Deluge of infection,
when so many thousands haue fal
                     •
                  e round about
vs; To what shall we attribute this? were we
not in the same Ayre? did wee not conuerse with
the same men? are not our bodies equally subiect
to the like diseases? was it not onely as our Sauiour
saith, that the workes of the Lord might be manifest?
who spake to this Infection, as sometime to
the Sea, hitherto shalt thou goe and no farther, Diuide
in one house betweene brother and brother,
in one bed betweene Husband and Wife, in one
Family betweene seruant and seruant; These shalt
thou absolutely take, these thou shalt but touch
their bodyes and spare their liues, as he said to the
Di
                     •
                  ell concerning Iob; Thus long shalt thou raigne
and no longer; if euer we liue to forget this goodnesse,
this wondrous worke of God, (I will sooner
wish we should forget to take our daily food)
how iustly should God forget vs, when wee stand
in the like need of mercy againe. As the Emperour
had his Boy that cryed euery morning to
him, Remember thou art but a man; so let vs still
haue something or other to put vs in minde of
this great deliuerance; Let euery man write it vpon
the doores of his house, as theExod. 12. Israelites in
Aegipt sprinkled their posts with blood, that if euer
God should againe strike, he againe may spare

vs. IGen. 18. 19. know, saith God of Abraham, that he will
tell his children what great things I haue done. Let
it be our talke to our children, that they that are
yet vnborne may know, though not by sight, yet
by hearesay, what great things the Lord hath done
for vs. Scipio Africanus the Elder hauing made the
City of Rome exanguem, &amp; morituram, as himselfe
called it, ready to giue vp the ghost, Lady of Affrik
at length being banished into a base Country-Towne,
his will was, that his Tombe should haue
this Inscription, I
                     •
                  grata Patria ne ossa quidem mea
habes, let not the God of Heauen complaine so of
vs, that we should haue no thought, no memory,
of our great preseruations, let him not bee exiled
our thoughts, and buried in obliuion, but let
some remnant and foot-print bee left, to witnesse
to the world, that we haue beene deliuered. Let
him not haue cause to complaine as he sometime
did, Isa. 1. Heare O Heauens and hearken O Earth, I
haue brought vp and preserued children, and they
haue despised me: Can a mother forget her child saith
God; no childe so deare to the mother as wee
haue beene to him, he hath tendred vs as the apple
of his eye, and preserued vs, as the Signet vpon his
right hand. Oh then let vs obserue and respect him.
It is a good thing saith Dauid,
               Psal. 92. 
               to praise the Lord,
and to sing vnto the name of the most High, to declare
his louing kindenesse in the morning, and his truth in
the night season. It is good touching the act it selfe,
for it is better to blesse then to curse, and to giue
thankes, then to giue out a voyce of grudging. It is

               good, because of the retribution, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                giue
and thou shalt receiue, and all that wee can giue
to him, is our thankes (for can our goodnesse extend
to him? saith Dauid) and cessat de cursus gratiarum
vbi non fuerit recursus, the course and descent
of the graces of God ceaseth, and the spring
is dryed vp, where there is not a recourse and
tide of our thankfulnesse, Wherefore let vs alwayes
be thankfull to the Lord, for it becommeth
well the iust to bee thankfull. Had I the power, I
would doe as Dauid did, begin aboue, and call the
Heauens, the Sunne, and Moone, and Starres to
praise the Lord for this our deliuerance, then
would I descend to the Ayre, and call all those
winged Messengers of God, all Birds and feathered
Fowles to beare a part with vs, then would I
come to the Earth, and haue Mountaines and all
Hills, fruitfull Trees and all Cedars, Beasts and
Cattell to ioyne with vs, then would I goe downe
to the Deepe, and there summon all those Sea-citizens
of those brinie Regions to come with vs,
and magnifie his great and glorious Name. In a
word, I would conclude as Dauid doth, Let euery
thing that hath breath praise the Lord.
               Psal. last. The Lord
whose goodnesse is without quality, whose greatnesse
is without quantity, infinite in both; but all
of vs that are the sonnes of men, especially I would
haue to learne, the song of the blessed before hand,
that hereafter wee may bee able to sing it with
more perfection,Reu. 5. 13. 
               Praise, honour, and glory bee
vnto him that sits vpon the Throne, and to the

Lambe▪
                that Immaculate Lambe of God which
once offered himselfe for vs, and at last will assume
vs to himselfe in that place where he 
                  •
               its and
Raignes for euer. To the which place hee
bring vs, that onely bought vs, and can
saue vs, IESVS CHRIST
the Righteous.
Amen.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

