
   
      
         
            Agaynst the possessyons of the clergye Harkyn what great auctorytes shall nowe folowe, for proffe thereof.
            Fyloll, Jasper.
         
         
            
               1537
            
         
         Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01366
            STC 11489
            ESTC S109825
            99845469
            99845469
            10371
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01366)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10371)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 67:11)
         
         
            
               
                  Agaynst the possessyons of the clergye Harkyn what great auctorytes shall nowe folowe, for proffe thereof.
                  Fyloll, Jasper.
               
               [32] p.   
               
                  J. Skot,
                  [London :
                  1537?]
               
               
                  Caption title.
                  At end: Geddered and compylyd by Iasper Fyloll.
                  Imprint from STC.
                  Signatures: A-B.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Catholic Church --  Clergy --  England.
               Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.
               Catholic Church --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-01
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-01
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-07
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-07
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            Agaynſt the poſſeſſyons
of the Clergye.
            HArkyn what great auctorytes
ſhall nowe folowe / For
proffe thereof.
            VNder reformacion of holy and deuoute
clerkys it ſemyth that all ye
reaſons which any of ye clergy be
able to make for ye kepyng of theyr temporall
poſſeſſions be but weyke &amp; of ſmall
auctoryte / conſyderyng that the contrary
therof is cōmaundyd and approuyd by ye
olde teſtament by the new teſtament / &amp;
in many of theyr canon lawes / and by ye
ſeyenges of the apoſtels and many holy
doctors. And alſo that the reformacion
and correccyon of all enormytees in the
clergy belongeth to pryncys and here in
Englande vnto the Kynges grace our
moſte drad ſouerayne lorde.
            
               
               ¶Fyrſte by the auctoryte of the olde
teſtamente it aperyth that the clerge
ought nat to haue poſſeſſiōs. Cap. .i.
               ¶It is wryten numeri .xviii. god ſayd
to Aaron. (Pactum pacis eſt ſempiternum
tibi). &amp; .c.
               The pacte &amp; couenaunt of peace is euer
laſtyng before god to the and to thy ſonnes
in a perpetuall ryght / In theyre
lande ye ſhall poſſede nothynge / nor ye
ſhall haue no parte amonge them / I am
thy parte and herytage amonge the chyldrene
of Iſſraell / To the chyldrene of
Leui I haue geuyn all the tythes of
Iſſraell in poſſeſſion for the mynſtraciō
that they ſerue me in ye tabernacle .&amp; .c.
               ¶They ſhall poſſed nothynge els but be
contente with the offrynge of tythes
And as it is ſayd Eſai .xliiij. there ſhall
be no herytage to them, I am theyr herytage
/ ye ſhall gyue them no poſſeſſion
in Iſſraell / I am theyr poſſeſſion.
               ¶Alſo it is ſayd. hier .xlviii. Curſed be

he that doth the worke of god fraudylently
or neclygently.
               ¶Alſo exodi .xxiii. thou ſhalte nat take
rewardes which blyndyth wyſe men &amp;
ſubuertyth the wordes of iuſte men.
            
            
               ¶Secondarely it apperyth by y• new
teſtamente that the clergy ought nat
to haue poſſeſſions. Ea. .ij.
               ¶Alſo in the holy goſpell Chryſt ſayde
Io .xii. he that myniſtryth to me let hym
folow me / and primo Io .xii. he yt ſeyth
he wyll dwell in Chryſt muſt walke as
he walked but Chryſt walked all his lyfe
in pouerte without hauyng any tēporall
poſſeſſions and alwey refuſed them / th
                     •
                  
it muſt nedys folow that they that haue
poſſeſſiōs folow nat Chryſt ¶Alſo .i. pe
.ii. Chryſt ſufferyd for vs / leuyng yo
                     •
                  
exāple that ye myght folow his ſteppys
¶Alſo hebre .xii. let vs beholde the auctor
of ye feyth and fulfyller thereof Ihū
which dyd put a wey all Ioy / &amp; ſuffred 
                     〈◊〉
                  
                  
croſſe content with confuſion.
               ¶Alſo Mathew .xvi. he that wyll come
after me lett him forſake his wyll &amp; take
his croſſe and folow me.
               ¶And Luc .xiiij. onleſſe that a man renounce
to all men that, that he poſſedeth
he can nat be my dyſſyple.
               ¶Alſo Luc .xij. ſell your poſſeſſyōs and
gyue almys Alſo Math .xix. Lowe haue
forſakyn all and haue folowed the
               ¶Alſo Actu .ij. The appoſtels ſolde
theyr poſſeſſyons and ſubſtance and deuydyd
it to them that had nede.
               ¶Alſo it appereth that Chriſt wyllyd his
appoſtels and dyſſyples to haue payne in
this world and no pleaſure whē he ſayd
Mathew .x. Lo I ſend you into the
world to be lyke to ſhepe in the myddys
of the cōpany of wolfes and Math .vij.
Entre you by the paynfull gate it is A
ſtreyt and paynfull wey which leadyth
to lyfe and there is but few that fynd it.
               ¶And Mathew .x. Be ye nat wyllyng

                     •
                  o haue poſſeſſiōs of golde nor ſyluer nor

money nor two cotes / Alſo Colo .iii. ſauer
ye thoſe thyngys that be a boue and
nat thoſe that be vpon the erth / and many
other placys of ſcrypture affyrme the
ſame that the clergy which call them ſelfes
the ſucceſſors of Chryſtes appoſtels
to whome Chryſt ſayd that they were the
lyght and ſalte of the yerth ſhuld haue
no poſſeſſions.
            
            
               ¶Thrydly it apperyth by many o
                     •
                  
theyr owne lawes in ye decres that the
clergy ought nat to haue poſſeſſions.
               ¶Alſo it appyryth by ye canons of theyr
owne lawe that they ought nat to haue
poſſeſſions / for there it is ſayde thu
                     •
                  
Dyſt .xlvii. omnes.
               The louers of the worlde be ſtronge in
wordely thynges and weyk in heuenly
thynges / Alſo in the councell of toletane
it is comaunded by many auctorytes
as it apperyth .xii. 
                     •
                  .i. that clerkes
ought to haue no poſſeſſions .Ca. clicos
                  
nich
                     ••
                   / and there .xij. 
                     •
                   .i. clericus 
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  i / and
there / Ca. duo ſūt genera criſtianorum
/ And in euery of the ſayd places it
appereth &amp; is / prohybyt to them / to haue
any poſſeſſions.
               ¶Alſo they that be conſtytutyd in holy
orders ought nat to take ſeculer cures / dyſt.
lxxxviij. E
                     •
                  us / aut ſacerdos.
               ¶Alſo a byſſhop may nat take y• tuycion
of teſtamētes nor the charge of wordly
thyngys / but ought to gyue hȳ ſelfe only
to redyng prayer / and prechyng ye worde
of god / dyſt .lxxxviij. E
                     •
                  us nullam.
            
            
               ¶Fourthly it appereth that tēporall
poſſeſſyōs ben forbedyn to the clergy
by the ſeyeng of the appoſtels and of
many other holy doctours. Cap .iiij.
               ¶Fyrſt ſaynt Auſten de cōtemptu mūdi
ſeyth / he y• poſſedeth any thȳg in erth is
remoued frō ye diſcyplyn of Chryſt / Frō
whens do they arrogaūtly take to thē the
power of loſȳg &amp; bȳdyng which ī ye yerth

preſume to poſſede any faculte / &amp; why be
nat they aſſhamed to ſay / that the lorde
is the part of myne herytage / the which
wyll nat forſake yerthly poſſeſſyons / Why
do they ete y• ſynnes of the people / yf
they take tythys with the chlidyrne of
Leui / how ſhall they take parte among
other trybus / Auguſtinus de contemptu
mundi.
               ¶And yet he ſeyth there farder / where
god is the auctor of all good thynges / yf
the wordely thynges were verely good
thynges / he wolde neuer haue dyſpyſed
them / nor wolde neuer haue comaūdyd
them to be dyſpyſed of his folowers.
               ¶Alſo ſaynt Auſtē ī his .xxxvi. &amp; .xxxvij.
ſermon ad fratres in Heremo / ſeyth he
that ſerueth ye alter muſt lyue of ye alter / let
hym nat be proude / nor let 
                     〈◊〉
                   nat be
made ryche by his clerkchip / &amp; .i. Tiō .vi.
Kepe ye iuſtyce be nat wyllyng to make
wynnygꝭ but ye hauyng fode &amp; cloth / be
ye cōtēt therwith / for he yt doth celebrat or
prechyth or baptiſyth for yt / yt he ſhuld ge
                  
                     •
                  uere

there by. with out doute doth put a
wey hym ſelfe from the heuenly goodes
of thou let to gyue the ſacrament / what

                     •
                  ouerte ſo euer thou be in, thou arte no

                     •
                  heperde / nor mynyſter of Chryſt but a
Marchāt / for he that for the munyſtraciō
                  
                     •
                  f ye ſacramēt taketh money or rewarde
or maketh any couenaunte is a geayſite
&amp; ſellyth the ſacramente and betrayeth

                     •
                  is ſauiour with Iudas.
               ¶Alſo ſaynte auſten wrytyth in the, ix.

                     •
                  oke of his confeſſion, ye ſeke a bleſſed

                     •
                  yfe in ye regyon of deth / &amp; there it is nat
¶Alſo agaynſt ſuch tēporall poſſeſſions
of the clergy ye may rede an nother lytel

                     •
                  reatyſe called ſpec
                     •
                  m epiſcopo
                     
                        
                     
                     rum
                   ſeu preatorū,
wherin it is ſuffycyently ſhewed
that ye clergy ought to haue no poſſeſſiōs
¶Alſo ſaynt auſten in his .xxxvii. ſer
                  
                     •
                  on
(ad fratres in heremo) ſeyth let vs

                     •
                  ut forth our ſelfe in all our myndes in

                     •
                  ych trybulacyon / in knolege in charite

                     •
                  at feyned / in watchynges ī preſoninē
                  es
/ in plages / in the word of truth / and

ſo hauyng no thyng / poſſedyng Chryſt
let vs poſſede all thynges / This is y• lyte
of bleſſyd men / This is the helth of preſtes
/ This is the reſt of the ſeruauntes
of god / This is the wyll of the fryndes
of god / and this is our ſanctyfycacyon / That
we may put forth our ſelf
                     •
                  ꝭ in all
thynges as ye mynyſters of god in mych
ꝑacience / in trybulacion in neceſſite gyuynge
to no man any offence / that our
ſeruyce / or myneſtery ſhuld nat be reproued
nor rebukyd.
               ¶And here to agreyth ſaynte Peter .i.
pe .ii. ſeyeng This is grace whē any mā
for the conſentyng to god doth ſuffre pacyently
iniury / what grace or thanke is
it yf ye beyng ſynners / ſuffre wronge
as who ſeyth none / but yf ye doyng well
do ſuffre pacyently / That is thankful to
god / in to that thyng ye becalled.
               ¶Alſo .ii. Thi .iii. All they that wyll lyue
makely in Chryſte ſhall ſuffer / perſecucyon
pacyently. ¶And ſaynt Bernard
ſeyth in his declamacyons / A clerke

hauyng his part in yerth ſhall nat haue
his parte in heuyn / And Io .xv. I haue
choſyn you from the worlde / and Math
.xxiiii. and Luc .xxi. ſe that none begyle
you / Many one ſhall come in my name
ſayeng that I am Chryſt, and they ſhall
begyle many folkes / And Ro .viii. yf ye
lyue after ye fleſhe ye ſhall dye. Alſo rede
more of this Matter. Col .iii. Iac .iii. &amp;
iiii. &amp; .i. Corynthe .vi. and .ii. Coryn, iiii.
And ſaynt Bernard, in his declamacyōs
and in ye lxvi. ſermon ſuper cant ſeyeth,
The worſt hereſy / of all is to make lyes
vpon the trew doctryne, nat with tonge
only but in lyuyng And ad Philypenſes
iii. Clerkes lyuyng pleſantly be called enmyes
of the croſſe of Chryſt, and glorye
ſhalbe to there confucyō / whiche ſauore
yerthly thynges.
               And ſaynt Bonauēture (in ſtimulo din
                     •
                  
                  amoris
ſuꝑ expoſicione oracionis dn̄ice)
ſeyth / yt it is more ſhame to a clerke to deſyre
hōour ryches or poſſeſſiō ī this world
thā it ſhuld be to ye ſōe of an Emꝑrour, to

deſyre the offyce of A gonge farmere.
            
            
               How the clergye haue theyr goodes
by a wrong wey and kepe from ye pore
folkys ye goodes of ye church. Cap .v.
               ¶Alſo ſaynt Barnarde in his declamacyons
ſeyth / the goodes of the church be
the patrymonye or inherytāce of pore mē
and they be kepte from them by cruell ſacrelege
/ And how the Clergy hath long
tyme woluptuouſly deuoured the poſſeſſions
and goodes of Chryſtes church ye
may rede well fygured in the olde lawe
Danielis. .xiiii. by the preſtes of an
Idoll / called / Bell / the ſtory whereof
nowe folowith.
               ¶There was ſumtyme, an ydoll called
Bell the which the Kyng with his people
and preſtes worſhyppyd euery day for a
god / to whom was geuen euery day as
the maſter of the hyſtoryes ſeyth .iii. buſſhels
of flowre .xl. ſhepe .vi. meſurs of
wyne / The Kyng and ye people beleuyd

that Bell / had ben a lyuyng god / and
that he had Eten all / but of trouth The
preſtes with theyr wyffes and chyldren
deuouryd all in theyr voluptouſnes whereupon
ye Kynge ſayd to Daniell. thynkeſt
nat thou that Bell is a lyuyng god
Seeſt thou nat / how moch he etyth and
drynketh / and danyell ſayd / kyng ſee yt
thou Erre nat / This Idoll Bell is Clay
withinforth / and braſſe withoutforth / he
neuer etyth ne drynketh / and the kyng
beyng dyſpleſyd and angry therewith
called hys preſtes and ſayd to them / on
les ye tell me who etyth this dayly fode
ye ſhall dye / But yf ye can ſhewe and
proue to me that Bell etyth it / this Daniell
ſhall dye / becauſe he hath blaſphemed
Bell / and Daniell ſayd let yt be as
ye haue ſayd / and the kyng and Daniell
went to the temple of Bell &amp; the preſtes
ſayd / loo we ſhall go forth &amp; now thou
kyng put here the mete and the wyne
and ſet them to gether and ſhyt the dore
and ſeale it with thy Ryng &amp; when thou

ſhalte enter this temple agayn to morowe
/ but if thou fynde all eten we ſhall
dye / or els Daniell yt hath lyed agaynſt
vs / Theſe preeſtes had made craftyly vnder
the borde a ſecrete dore or entre / and
thereby, they came in always / &amp; deuouryd
that vytell It was ſo / yt after yt thoſe
preeſtes were gone forth / the Kyng ſett
that accuſtomed vytell before Bell and
Daniell comaūdyd his Chyldryn to brȳg
hym aſſhys / and ſyftyd it in the flore of
the temple before the Kyng and ſo the
Kyng / and Daniell went owt and ſhytt
the dore / and ſealed it with the Kynges
rynge and ſo departed / The preeſtes after
theyr olde cuſtome / Entred therein
yt nyght with theyr wyfes and chyldren / and
dyd ete and drynke all that ye Kyng
had there ſett ouer nyght / The Kynge

                     •
                  oſe erly on ye next mornȳg and Daniel
with hym / &amp; they came to the dore yt was
ſealed ouer nyght / &amp; the Kȳg ſayd to Daniell
Daniell is this Seale hole and he
ſayd all is hole and ſafe / and as ſone as

the dore was opened / y• kyng loked on y•
table &amp; cryed out wt a lowd voyce, Bell / thou
arte grete / &amp; in the is no crafte, nether / gyle / and
Danyell lawghed / And
held ye Kyng, yt he ſhuld enter no farder / and
ſayd be hold the pauyment or flore / And
wyſelye / thynke woſe ſteppys be
theſe / And the kyng ſayd / I ſee ſteppys
of men, womē, &amp; of childryn, &amp; therewith
the kyng was angrye / &amp; toke thoſe preſtes,
there wyuys, and theyre chyldryll,
&amp; then they ſhewed theyr ſecrete Dorys / by
ye whiche they were wont to enter / &amp;
to cōſume all the ſayde ſacryfice / then the
Kyng kyllyde thoſe preſtes / and gaue to
Daniell, the power ouer Bell, and he
ſubuertyd and ouer threwe Bell and his
temple (Morally) Now / In this maner
yt ſtandyth with manye of the Clergye
at theſe Days / ſpecyally with ſymonyte
Clerkes / craftylye and vniuſtelye ētrȳg
In to theyre curys / to ye voluptuoꝰ Dyſpendyng
of the goodes of the churche / for
where it ys wrytyn Iohā .x.
               
                  
Qui non intrat) &amp; .c. he that entreth nat
by the dore in to the fold of ſhepe but elswhere / he
is a theffe &amp; a lurker / he that
entryth by the dore / he is the ſheperd of
the ſhepe / but ſuche ſymonyte clerkēs enter
nat by the dore that ys / Chryſte / but
by a backe dore or by the wyndowe / Soentrynge
with a very purpoſe to cōſume
the offerynges &amp; goodes of ye Churche,
In theyre vanytes / and voluptoꝰ lyfe / And
they procure to them ſelfe many thȳ
                  ges / bothe
temporall and ſpūall, vnder y•
pretence that god in his poore membrys
ſhall ete &amp; ſpend yt / And no dowte / many
thynges be geuyn to them on this hope,
and truſte / that they may the more
quietly Attend to the ſtudy of contemplacion,
and to the prechyng of the worde
of god / and becauſe that of the temporall
goodes / geuyn them for that porpoſe / they
ſhuld haue but a ſtrayte and a bare / lyuyng / accordyng
to the ſeyeng of ſaynt
Paule .i. 
                     •
                  iō .vi. Habētes. &amp;c. we hauyng
fode and coueryng / let vs be with theſe

thynges content and of the remnaunt
Chryſt in his pore people ſhulde be fed
accordyng to ye ſeyeng of Chryil. Math
.xv. (Quod v
                     •
                  i) That which ye haue done
to one of myne ye haue done to me / But
yet I meane nat that euery preſte
ſhuld haue a lyke lyuȳg For a byſſhop &amp;c.
or other put ī offyce and romys of charge
oughte to haue ſufficyente to maynteyn
theyr neceſſary charge wtout ſuperfluite
/ And that men of the church ſhuld
geue the goodes of the church to pore mē
that remaynyth ouyr and a boue theyre
neceſſary fode and clothyng / Iohn̄ abbot
de villa) witneſſyth in a ſermon that
begȳnyth thus / Tulerunt lapides vt iacerent
in eum.
            
            
               How the goodes and poſſeſſions be
miſpendyd and myſuſed by many of
the clergy. Ca .vi.
               ¶Vnder the auctoryte of ſaynt ambroſe
and ſaynt / Hierom, they wry
                     •
                  e thus

They be theues &amp; Rauenours &amp; extorcinors
that miſuſe y• goodꝭ of the church / They
raueyn and plucke trome the pore
men / the greate plenty that they haue / for
all ſhulde be the pore menys ſyuyng
that is lefte a boue theyr neceſſary fedȳg
and clothyng / and therto Agreyth ſaynt
Bernard as it is before ſayd &amp; an other
holy doctore called Flore ſeyth yt all that
thou kepeſt or reteynyſt to thy ſelfe / aboue
neceſſary fode &amp; ſymple clothyng
of the goodes of ye aulter it is nat thyns
but it is Thefte Rauen Extorcyon / an
                     •
                  
ſacrelege / &amp; ſo now ſeyth an holy doctor
called / (Filius fabrilingnarii in diſtructoriū
vicō
                  
                     
                        
                     
                     rum
                   parte .vi. Cap. .xxi.
               ¶Volde god that the Kyng / and othe
                     •
                  
noblemen. &amp; .c. Founders of the gret
                     •
                  
almys geuyn to the churche / wolde d
                     •
                   lyke
as ye kyng before wrytyn wt Dani
                     ••
                  
dyd as to ſete theyr ſeales ſo that the
                     •
                  
wolde ſet there ſeales of ryght conſideracion
and of diſcrecion and then the
ſhulde well. Fynde on the one ſyde 
                     〈◊〉
                  
                  
                  
                     •
                  he grete waſtfull ſpēdyng of ye oblaciōs
of the churche in muche vayne apparell
and wordely pompe / and ſo they ſhulde
well ſe and perſeyue ye ſteppys &amp; pathys
of ſuch voluptuous And ſymonyte cler
                  
                     •
                  es / which
ys theyr manyfeſt affecciōs,
In the Duſte of ye vanite of this world / 
                     •
                  hat
is to ſey / In y• vanite of ſuꝑfluous
apparell of them ſelfes / theyr ſeruātes / And
theyr Horſys, and therewithall the

                     •
                  yng and his Noble men on the other

                     •
                  yde myght well ſee And conſyder ma
                  
                     •
                  y
good poure men and women compel

                     •
                  yd and forſyd for nedynes, hunger, and

                     •
                  hurſt / by lamenes &amp; blȳdnes / to begge

                     •
                  om Dore, to Dore, and no dowte but

                     〈◊〉
                   doyng the Kynges grace &amp; hys noble

                     •
                  en, fownders and geuers of ye greate

                     •
                  emperall poſſeſſions to ye churche, ſhuld

                     •
                  y theyr dyſcreciōs ſone ſee and ꝑceyue

                     •
                  hat Chryſte in / his pore people hath had

                     •
                  till or none of theyr ſuperfluous / and

                     •
                  perabundant poſſeſſions / but that the

                     •
                  oluptuous minyſtres of ye temple, nat

enteryng by ye Dore that is Chryſt / bu
                     •
                  
by preuey poſter
                     •
                  e gates / and wyndous
and by ſecrete weys theuyſhly haue clymed
therto and haue ſtolen and deuo
                     •
                  
                  ryd
the ſacrifys and goodes of the churche
that hath ben offred to god / And do
                     •
                  
                  tours
as ſaynt Auſten / ſaynt Bernard
and other ſey that ſuche preſtes be not
onely theuys / And the worſt ſacreleges
but alſo ſymonytes Herytyks / And traytours
to god / And how god thretenyth
ſuch yll cura
                     •
                  ꝭ / ye may rede Hiere .xxiii.
               ¶And it muſt now be remembred and
conſidered yt whē Conſtantyne y• Emperour
gaue his temporall poſſeſſions and
Empyre to the churche / and when pope
ſylueſter thē Receyued / yet after warde
at that tyme ther was a grete doute contrauercy / and
altercacion / amonge the
Clergy / wether yt gyfte &amp; the receyuyng
thereof yf any ſuch were / were lauful
                     •
                  
or no as it apperyth ī faſciculo temporū / And
then thoſe that were of ye couetous
clergy concluded yt it was both lawfully

geuyn / And lawfully receyuyd / agayns
ye mynd of thoſe which were good / And
for the cōtynuance and maynte naunce
thereof / They thē put and lefte in wrytyng
theyre opynyons / and weke aucrorites
to remayne ꝑpetuallye / The effect
wherof is ſet in ye ſeyd boke callyd / Faſciculus
temporum &amp; therefore / It ſemyth
that yf theſe forſayde wrytynges with
theyre opynyos &amp; weke Auctorytes were
Dyſcretelye red and newlye lokyd on / And
ſo were layde In one ſyde, of the
balance of any deuout Clerkes conſcyence / nat
corruptyd with Auaryce (That
is rote of al yllys and the ſeruyce &amp; bondage
of Idolles) Nether with arrogācy
and pryd of this world / And on ye otherſyde
of the ſayd balance were layd ye manyfolde
Auctorytees before wryttyn / to
the contrary therof thē yt wold appere / that
there ys none euyn weyght betwene
them / And that the furſt wryttyn opinyons
and weke Auctorytes, of that
Clergye alowyng both the geuyng and

Receuȳg of theſeyd temporall poſſeſſiōs
to be lawfull / be ouer weke / &amp; natable
to counterpeyſe the other ſyde of the balance / which
ſettyth and takyth Auctoryte
of .iiii. moſt ſtronge and moſt ſuffycyent
groundes of goddes lawes / That
ys to ſaye / Of the olde teſtamēt and the
newe teſtamēt / the goſpelles of Chyrſt
ſome decrees of the lawe canon / And of
wrytynges of dyuers of the apoſtelys / And
of many other holye doctours now ſeyntꝭ
in heuyn / as ys before wryttyn / where
the other do nat ſo / nor haue no
ſuche auctoryte / and in cōfyrmacyon hereof / The
reuerend fader in god Iohn̄
now byſſhoppe of Rocheſter in a ſermō,
which he made for the confutyng of the
hereſyes which he ſayde were of Martyn
luter ſeyth among other of his good
ſeyenges ther that ſaynt Ambroſe ſeyth
of ſaynt Peter that he is called Petra / becauſe
that he furſt amonge the gentylys
dyd eſtablyſhe the grounde of our
feyth / and as a ſton vnmoueable or no
                     •
                  
                  
aſye to be remouyd he cōteynyth ī him / 
                     •
                  nd
ſtayeth all the frame and gretnes
of the worke of Chryſt.
               ¶Nowe ſaynt Peter ſo conteynyng &amp;

                     •
                  ayeng all the frame of Chryſtes werke
i. pe .ii. Bydyth y• clergy to be ſubiectes

                     •
                  o euery humany creature for god / and
not to be lordes of Caſtelles &amp; Townes

                     •
                  nd of other temporall poſſeſſions / and

                     •
                  aynt Paule / ſaynt / Iames / ſaynt / Ma
                  
                     •
                  hewe / and
manye other holy doctours / 
                     •
                  onferme
the ſame / that pouertye / Mi
                  
                     •
                  erye
and ſubieccyon ought to be in the
clergye / as before ys ſayde.
               Wherefore yt ys to be thought that no
clerke ſhuld vſurpe to ſpeke / ne to wry
                  
                     •
                  e / in
mayntenāce of the foreſayd weke
opynyons which thoſe of the clergye dyd

                     •
                  olde at that tyme, which ſemeth to bere

                     •
                  o ſtrength / For they be now by many
                  
                     •
                  old
and grette auctorytes vtterly cō
                  
                  
                     •
                  owndyd.
               ¶And here yt is to be conſyderyd that

                     •
                  myghty god / in the olde lawe and in

the new lawe hath by his worde and ordynaunce
prouydyd for preſtes and clarkys
a lyuyng in pouerte and in tribulacion
forbedyng to them the hauynge of
temporall poſſeſſions. as is before wrytē
And Chryſt ſo lyued hym ſelfe here in
this worlde .xxxiii. yeres / and after his
aſcencion his appoſtels and dyſcyples / and
other clerkes whiche that ſuccedyd
them dyd ſo lyue &amp; dyd ſo teche by ye ſpace
of .iii. C. yeres &amp; god ſayth y• his ordinaunce
&amp; worde ſhall ſtand &amp; be permanēt
for euer. Num. xviii. pactū &amp;.c. the pact
and couenaunte of peace is euer laſtȳg
before god (&amp; ps̄. C. C. xviiii. thy wor
                     •
                  
good lorde ſhall a byde for euer, and ps̄.
C. x. he hath comaūdyd for euer his teſtamente / and
the Euangelyſtes / Math.
Marke and Luke ſay (Verba mea non
preteribunt. &amp;.c. my worde ſhall nat pas
A way / and ſaynt Paule ſeyeth. Ro. xiii
they that reſyſte the ordynaunce of god
getteth damnacion to them ſelfes and
ſaynt Iohn̄ euāgelyſt ſeyth that godde
                     •
                  
                  
worde is god hym ſelfe (et deus erat ver
                  
                     •
                  um)
And he ſeyth alſo (Sermo tuus ve
                  
                     •
                  itas
eſt) Thy ſermon is veryte / And

                     •
                  aynt / Auſten in his meditacyons ſeyth
Principium. &amp;.c. The begynnyng of

                     •
                  hy word is truyth / that is y• begȳnyng
of thy word which was thy word in the

                     •
                  egynnyng, Wherefore it ſemyth to fo
                  
                     •
                  ow
that who ſo euer denyeth the word
of god he denyeth god hym ſelffe, that is

                     •
                  ery trueth and ſo he is made ſtraunge

                     •
                  nd alenatyd from ye ſpryt of truth, that

                     •
                  s god the holy goſt / and Chryſt hath promyſyd / Math.
x. to denye all ſuche perſons
before god his fader that is in he
                  
                     •
                  yn,
That denye hym in this world / wherefore
euery good man ſhulde pray
and ſaye with ye pſalmyſte / Ps. cc. xviij.
Good lorde take nat from my mow the / 
                     •
                  he
worde of truyth / and all ye apopſtels

                     •
                  nd holy Doctors before reherſyd dyd

                     •
                  uer preche / and haue lefte behynd thē
In wrytyng ye ſayd word &amp; ordynaunce
of god / &amp; haue made thereof cōſtytucyōs

and holy canōns affyrmyng pouertye / and
for beddyng alwes tēporall poſſeſſyons
to be in the Clergye, and haue ſet
them In the boke / of holy decres to be
perpetuallye obſeruyd and kepte by the
clergy / affyrmyng ye bokes &amp; vyolators
thereof to be blaſphemours / in the holy
goſt, which as ſaynt / Mathew, wytneſſyth / Math.
xi. Is Irremyſſilbe in
this worlde and In the world to cōme / All
this nat withſtōdyng ſythen ye tyme
of the Emꝑoure conſtātyne and of pope
Sylueſter which was .iii. C. yers after
Chriſtes, byrth, The couetous ſorte of
the clergy do wrytte yt tēporall poſſeſſiōs
and tēporall auctorytes hath cūme to th
                     •
                  
by myraclis, wheruppon ye pope hath cō
                  maūdyd
that no man ſhalbe ſo hardy to
ſpeke there agaynſt / yet, a generall coū
                  cell
hath affyrmyd this ꝓpoſicion / Luc.
xiiii. (Niſi 
                     •
                  s renūciaūit oībꝰ que poſſidet
non poteſt meuꝰ eſt diſcipls) which
ſemyth to be heretycal in his lyterall ſēs
as it apperyth ī a boke of Eneas ſiluius

of ye councell of Baſyll / in ye cōdēnacyon
of the .xii. artycle of Iohn̄, wykelyff.
In thes matters ſemeth to be a great
ſeyſme &amp; cōtrariete &amp; where .ii. ſuche contraryes
be / bothe of thē cā nat be trwe / and
it may wel be ſayd, that ye holy gooſt
was nat preſēt at ye makyng of thē both / whereby
the kynges laye ſubiectys be
brought into a merueloꝰ ꝑplexite &amp; daū
                  gere
of hereſye / for nat knowyng whether / of
thoſe .ii. cōtraryes is to be beſt
beleuyd / For we haue but one god / one
fayth / and one kyng to whome of neceſſyte
all we his laye ſubiectes muſt praye
and hūbyll make interceſſyō to be eaſyd
of ye ſayd ꝑplexyte Scyſme &amp; cōtraryte / for
it may be well ſayd to ye clergye ī this
caſe as Chriſt ſayd to the pharaſyes &amp; fals
Ipocrytis / Math / xv. ye haue nat ratifyed
nor alowed nether regardyd the commaūdemēt
of god / but your owne tradycions / wherfore
it may pleaſe ye Kynges
hyghnes to ſay to ye clergy with Chriſt all
plantynges or graffynges yt my heuēly / fader

hathe nat plantyd / or graffyd / ſhalbe
pluckyd vp be the rote.
            
            
               That the correccyon of all ſuch and
other enormytyes in ye clergy belongyth
to the Kyng and to his ſeculer
power. Cap. .vii.
               xxiii. q̄. iii. (Qui poteſt obuiare) there it
is ſayd that he that may punyſhe malefactours
and doth it nat / is the very fauorer
of theyr wykednes.
               xxiii. q̄. v. (Sunt quidam enormia)
               There it is ſayde that all outragyous
offenſys ſhall be punyſhyde by ſeculer
Iugys.
               xxiii. q̄. v. (de Liguribus et venetecis)
There it is ſayd that the ſeculer power
ſhall conſtrayne and correcte all ſciſmatykes
and heretykes
               xxiii. q̄. v. (Regum officium) there it is
ſayd the kynges offyce is to punyſhe all
yll folkes and to releue good folkes
xxiii. q̄. i. (Si apud carnales dn̄os)

There it is ſayd that he that refucyth or
dyſpyſyth to bere or to gyue reuerence
to ye powers of rulers, ſhall lacke his rewarde
in heuyn.
               xxiii. q̄. v. (Qui malos ꝑcutit) there it is
ſayde that he is the very miniſter of god
that punyſſheth and ſtrykyth yll folkes
for theyr offencys.
               xxiii. q̄. v. (Si propterea) there it is ſayd
that the wronges of the ſacramentys of
Chryſt / muſt be auengyd by kyngys.
ſaynt Paule / ad tit. .i. byddyth / vpon
cauſe geuȳ to punyſh offenders ſtraytly
and hardely to make them hole &amp; ſound
in the feyth. And there he ſayeth farther
Take no hede to theyr Iwyſſhe fables
nether to the comaundementes of
men that turnyth them ſelfe from the
trowth for as well theyr myndys as the
conſciences ben fowle ſpotted.
               They knowelege them ſelfe to knowe
Chryſt and yet in theyr dedys they deny
hym for they be abhomynable And vnfeythfull
&amp; frowardly dyſpoſyd to euery

good werke Et ps. xviii. it is ſpoken of
them thus (Narr / auerunt michi) &amp;.c.
wyckyd men haue tolde me fables but
nat as the law / &amp; ſaynt Paule. Ro. xiii.
ſeyth. (Omnis anima) .&amp;.c.
               Euery ſoule is ſubiecte to the ſuperyour
powers / There is no power but of god
they that be / be ordeyned of god / ſo yt he
which reſiſtyth power reſiſtyth the ordynaunce
of god / they yt reſyſt get to them
ſelfes damnacyon / for pryncys be nat
ordynyd to the fere of good werkes but
of euyll / yf thou wylte nat dred power do
good / and thou ſhalte haue laude therof
He is mynyſter of god to the in good
thȳges / yf yu do euyll dred / he beryth nat
the ſwerde without cauſe / he is ye myneſter
of god, vengaunce in wrath to hym
that dothe euyll / therefore of neceſſyte be
ye ſubiecte nat only for wrath / but alſo
for conſcyence.
               ¶And ſeynt Peter ſeyth. i. Pet. ii.
(Subiecti igitur) &amp;.c.
               Therfore be ye ſubiect to euery humayn

                  
                     •
                  reature for god to the vengaunce of
euyll doers &amp; laude of good men.
               ¶Now for the loue of god. That clerke
yt luſtyth to reproue or īpugne y• forſayd
auctoryteſe or the applyyng of ye ſame let
hym do it louyngly and charytably ye &amp;

                     •
                  t y• leſte by lyke auctorties &amp; by no leſſe.
which yf they can nat do / let thē forſake
theyr abuſys &amp; cōforme thē ſelffys to the
word of god / and to lyue thereafter God
graūt ye ſame / Amen.
            
         
         
            ¶Tabula.
            ¶Fyrſte by the auctoryte of the olde
teſtament it aperyth that the clergy
ought nat to haue poſſeſſiōs. Cap. i.
            ¶Secondarely it apereth by ye new
teſtamente that the clergy outh nat
to haue poſſeſſions. Ca. ij.
            ¶Thyrdly it appereth by many of
theyr owne lawes in the decres that
the clergy ought nat to haue poſſeſſions.
Cap. iij.
            
               
¶Fourthly it appereth that tempora
poſſeſſions ben forbedyn to ye clergy
by the ſeyeng of the appoſtels an of
many other holy doctours. Ca. iiij.
            ¶How the clergy haue theyr goodes,
by a wrong wey and kepe from y• pore
folkes ye goodes of ye church. Cap. v.
            ¶How the goodes and poſſeſſions
be myſpendyd and myſuſed by many
of the clergy. Ca. vi.
            ¶That the correccyō of all ſuch and
other enormytees in the clergy belō
               gyth
to the Kyng, and to his ſeculer
power. Cap. vij.
         
         
            ¶Geddered and compylyd by
Iaſper Fyloll.
            ¶Impreſſum / Cum priuilegio regali.
            
               
               
            
            
         
      
   

