
   
      
         
            The minte of deformities
            C. G., Gent.
         
         
            
               1600
            
         
         Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01369
            STC 11491
            ESTC S105723
            99841449
            99841449
            6034
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01369)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6034)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 294:05)
         
         
            
               
                  The minte of deformities
                  C. G., Gent.
               
               [24] p.   
               
                  [By G. Simson] for VVillyam Iones dwelling neere Holburne Conduite at the signe of the Gunne,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  1600.
               
               
                  Dedication, C3v, signed: C.G. Gent.
                  A satire in verse.
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Signatures: A-C⁴.
                  The last leaf contains "To the fauorable readers".
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2006-06
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-06
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-10
            Celeste NgSampled and proofread
         
            2006-10
            Celeste NgText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2007-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE MINTE
of deformities
            
               G S
            
            Imprinted at London for William
Iones dwelling neere Holburne Conduit at
the Signe of the Gunne.
1600.
         
         
            
            
            To the gentle Peruſers of my
vnpoliſht Primitiae,
            THe neuer vewing warehouſe of conceipt,
            like (ould Silenus aſse) would faine repeate,
            Vnto the open world, darke ignorance,
            Making it glowe with harſh intellegence,
            You ſhall not ſurfet on the guilded crummes,
            which with vncapable conceipts begunne,
            Making the world beleeue their high pitcht vaine,
            renowmed eloquence admired ſtraine,
            With ſounding tearmes to cracke the open vault,
            of vnconceiued labors, and to walke,
            The ſtatly round of all ſought loftineſſe,
            daining fayre entrance to each common meaneſſ,
            This doe I hate, all men may me conceiue,
            I ſeeke to pleaſe, and not your wits beicaue.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            
               No Thraſion harpe, but a ſteeld ſurious whippe,
               no Nightingales, but Mandrakes ſhreeking ſound,
               
                  Adaſtors ſnakes to make theſe Thraſors ſkippe:
               whoſe cages, vultures, limewands, to confound:
               the reeking limits of an vnſtayd head,
               with aſpiſh toyes to bring greene wits to bed.
            
            
               Oh I am mad to ſee the chopping ſtile,
               and cheating ſlaueries of theſe muſtie dayes,
               The woordes of arte (yet artleſſe which beguile)
               deepe diuing vathrifts of their honeſt prayes,
               yet not their owne, for one ſhort yeere wil boord
               what their progenitors did fortie hoord,
            
            
               Vertues-decayed-world is out of vſe,
               and honeſt trading mindes are cleane extinct,
               Downe goes all vertuous meanes, ſet vp a ſtuiſe:
               a broking brothell is delicious drinke:
               a broker (quoth you) oh tis an honeſt trade,
               twill be defended who ſo ere gayneſayd.
            
            
               Groſe ſwalowing termes diſdayne a brokers name,
               which doth ſupport baſe drudging vnderlings,
               Whoſe ſilken robes varniſh their baſtard ſhame:
               and foggie clowring-birth-enamilingsh.
               whoſe ſtatling-twelue-pence makes the ſhine as bright,
               as Cynthias beames in a ſtorme-wintring night.
            
            
               
               Whoſe maiſtring termes lies in their ſattan ragges,
               a purchaſt ſhift will make them gentlemen,
               Though not a peny in their woorſhips bagges,
               yet are they noblier borne then better men:
               their ſuits will guild their gentrie, and the rather,
               the diuell is become their godfather.
            
            
               I knewe a Piper in a ſilken coate,
               ſo farre inamord of his peacockes plumbes,
               That needes his paynted picture muſt afloate,
               or els his gentle minde with griefe conſumes:
               who drewe it but his father? fie fond man,
               to name his father, hees a gentleman.
            
            
               I woonder (Orpheus) thou didſt neere commence?
               thou couldſt haue plaid foure organs roundelaies,
               And yet thou neuer hadſt preheminence?
               though thou ſurpaſſedſt in aſtoniſht brayes.
               Now by the Trenitie twas not welldone,
               to make a gentleman a paynters ſonne.
            
            
               But who more proud then beggers mounted hie,
               Whoſe three yeeres gentry from a brokers ſhoppe,
               Will proue his ſtenching-ſilke ſtampt pedigree,
               from C. ſol. fay. vt. or an organes ſtoppe.
               beware, beware, the knauiſh beadle waytes,
               to beare you to the conſiſtorie ſtates.
            
            
               
               A Taylers ſheares clips of this brokers ſhape,
               a perfumd-croſſeleged-rare-artificiall,
               Whoſe gentrie's paynted in a womans cape,
               a gentleman? why its common vn o all,
               he takes part with thē both, therfor't muſt follow
               he hath a broking vayne, a ſinging ſwallow.
            
            
               If any enuious diſalowing tongue,
               ſeeke to depreſſe this auncient cuſtomdvſe,
               Which with the downfalne Adam firſt begun,
               I craue the ſingle combate for his abuſe,
               our armes ſhal ſoone decide that doubt, &amp; then
               Taylors I hope are no meane gentlemen.
            
            
               In azure rampant ſticks a payre of ſheares,
               our coate (out of a thouſand) one weele ſorte,
               A ſpaniſh needle pendant, and that beares
               our creſt, which is our ornamentall port:
               a bodkin iacent with a lowſe doth hould,
               makes our impreſſion in honors mould.
            
            
               Our tongues we ſhape not to each common crie,
               we keepe our reſidence, ſtirre at no call:
               We vſe no what do you lackes, what iſt you buy?
               but ſit ſecurely on our ſhopboord ſtall:
               nobles attend vs for our iudgements, then
               who will denie vs to be gentlemen.
            
            
               
               Become our harrold (gentle mayſter ſcribe)
               enormous pens we hate, and ruſtie boaſts,
               Blaſe our antiquitie? and for a bribe
               feare not: weele fee you to the vttermoſt,
               here take this veluet romnant what you neede,
               our vnderboording box ſupplies with ſpeede.
            
            
               Our perſumes ſmell not like the ſlauering crewe,
               of middy take paynes, or ſuch vnſauory ſway,
               Our garments vndiſfigured and new:
               Vnlike December floriſhing as May.
               
               our hamering heads tir'd with inuention,
               ſcorne baſe vpbrayding reprehenſion.
            
            
               A codpeece breech cleane out of faſhion,
               a ſwim-ſwamd flapping-lagging ore the knee,
               A coſt-deuiſed-admiration.
               Is vſed of all: oh ſpightfull forgerie.
               when God fayre faſhion'd partes, vnfaſhioning,
               they both deforme thoſe gratious parts, &amp; him.
            
            
               O that young heads ſhould haue ſuch ſlender wit,
               to yeeld their humors to theſe odious baites,
               Their careleſſe moodes wayes nought, but more fit
               and new ſtampt faſhions their vndoing waites,
               what ſtrange deformes lurkes in theſe motions,
               muſt needes be ſtamped in their faſhions.
            
            
               
               Vnfit conceipts ſhipt from the Perſians,
               
               all chriſtians hating Pagan fantaſies,
               Remote attires of the Graeſians,
               
               are enterteynd as ſolemne cerimonies,
               
                  Perſians, Turckes, Graeſians, all faſhions I beleeue,
               are ſafe compiled in one Engliſh ſleeue.
            
            
               Let one attire creepe in our heads to day,
               to morrow twill be common, odious,
               It muſt be ſingle or it beares no ſwaye,
               if two poſſeſſeit oh tis ſcripulous,
               ſome ſtrange-imaginarie ſhape alone,
               muſt fit my humor, or I will haue none.
            
            
               To day like a French gaiboile, round and flat,
               to morrow like a Spaniard, naught but britch,
               Then in the ſtrange Italian natiue plat,
               then in the whotte Barbarians ſwelting pitch,
               that I doe wonder that in London trades,
               like Kit chinſtuffe (what faſhiōs haue you maides.
            
            
               I know a trifling ſtudent three houres ſpace,
               contriuing in what forme to make his ſhooe,
               Firſt he would haue it ſquare, with a pinkt race,
               then round, then ſtreight, at length all would not doe,
               at laſt he found a faſhion pleaſd him moſt,
               but wanted money to defray the coſt.
            
            
               
               What muſt he doe? his wants muſt be ſupplyed,
               the ordinary ſhapes diſlikt his minde,
               Money he wanted, but what ere betide,
               he muſt haue that with labor he did finde,
               but at the laſt, when the beſt meanes were ſcand,
               he brooke the ſhop, &amp; for thoſe ſhooes was hangd.
            
            
               Tis ſtrange to ſee the nature of our clime,
               our faſhion-mongers paſſe all other worlds,
               The cloſe-reſeruing orders of ſtrange times,
               are in contempt all into England hurld,
               that neither Spaniard, Duch, Polonian,
               
               can be diſſtinguiſht from an Engliſhman.
            
            
               Each Countrie keepes his natiue faſhion,
               ſame England, which doth reuell with them all,
               No method in his attired function,
               will make his pampered ioynts vnbeſtiall:
               a ſtraite Polon ſleeue, large Italian ſcerting,
               a Spaniſh belly cloſe, and a French wing.
            
            
               A right Camelions, no perfect Ioſephs ſhape
               what God made perfect, that they will amend,
               There lewd opinions priſd at a higher rate,
               then their owne goodnes, or good finiſht ende,
               inuenting trifles now keepe ſuch a quoile,
               what God made good, they making better ſpoile.
            
            
               
               Babels new built, confuſion rules the toung.
               their racked wits aſpire to lothſome crimes,
               
                  Sodoms foundation is a freſh begunne,
               to make our falls warnings to after times,
               oh this inhumaine fault's propitious,
               portending wracte vnto our weale and vs.
            
            
               What doe theſe cutting ſutes portend but ſhame,
               enſinges to bawdie tauerne-boulſteres,
               The ſtayned mapp of a looſe gouernd name,
               and ſwaggering crew of hatefull chauilers,
               whoſe onely grace is blurd in periurie,
               with mouthing othes to blaſe there infamie.
            
            
               Skimd ſuperficies of this crew is ripe,
               and riper would be, but for Tiburns rod:
               The ſaint they worſhip a Tobacco pipe,
               and their bedawbed looſenes is their God,
               yet let me giue this counſell to that ward,
               that maiſter Tiburne capers very hard.
            
            
               One ſnurts Tobacco as his noſe were made,
               a perfumd Iakes for all ſcurrilities,
               Another with his haire (as if a iayde,
               had loſt his tayle to feede his enormities,
               hanges ore his ſhoulders with a fond deuiſe,
               to make a warmer couert for the lice.
            
            
               
               An other ſlaue which long time hath beene chaind,
               and got an eare-ſtamp for his filching trayde,
               To clowde this ſhame, a Iewell muſt be hangd,
               at the ſame hole the burning iron made,
               who then dare call him rogue, who ſeemes to ſauor,
               the vndeſerued bliſſe of his miſti is fauor.
            
            
               If iewellings obſcure ſuch fowle diſgrace,
               and will eclipſe the lawes due puniſhment,
               Who will not leade this iolly ſwaggering race,
               to be inthrald in the worlds blandiſhment,
               but (gentle Roiſter) bridle your iolly ſcope,
               or els the next degree will be a rope-
            
            
               The next that marcheth in this cutting crewe,
               noble Dicke Swaſh, with ſworde and buckler othes,
               He ſweares the Spaniards his braue valure knew,
               and ſayes his terrifieng frights them moſt:
               oh how he lies? for ile beſworne that Dicke,
               
               nere tooke a pray, vnleſſe a hedging trick.
            
            
               Oh infamie vnto a ſouldiers name,
               oh ſcandall to our predeceſſing worth,
               Thy death ſhall burie this diſgrace and ſhame,
               and rue thou ſhalt the houre of thy birth,
               but (ſignior Bragadino) aduiſe you better,
               a ſlitting coller is a plaguie debter.
            
            
               
               Tut he is well inough aduiſed of that,
               if without companie he be alone,
               He will not draw to hurt a man, thats flat:
               what he a quarriler? tut heele ſaue one.
               but it a tauerne crew together meete,
               heele be the firſt to drawe, but laſt to feight.
            
            
               Where hath he not beene where Belona ſwayes,
               in the Low countries, there his name's known beſt,
               In Britanie and Gaſcoine many dayes,
               and gaynſt the Turkes his ſeruice hath beene preſt:
               all theſe renowned countries did he ſkip,
               when ſcarce he knowes the inſide of a ſhip.
            
            
               Yet will he roundly tell the honored names,
               of the cheefe leaders, wher's their regiment,
               Their worthes ceclipſe his vndeſiphered ſhames,
               perfume his baſe thoughts to an ornament,
               his victories are regiſterd in the booke,
               whē I dare ſweare he knowes no enimies looke.
            
            
               Then with his ruby-pumpeld-wine-fir'd ſnout,
               a quaffing health muſt to his captayne flye:
               He that denies the acceptance in the route,
               his valure-hating poniard makes him dye,
               their villanous attempts may well be ſayd,
               that Chaueleiring-murtherings growne a trayd.
            
            
               
               Iudgment they feare, God neuer comes in minde,
               if iuſtice frowning-guerdon were not death,
               Then good mens hauokes, their purſuing kinde,
               would by their hating-goodneſſe clip their breath,
               and hell, rape crueltie, would beare ſuch ſway,
               that good-reformed mindes ſhould quite decay.
            
            
               It that a man denie to quaffe his ſcoure,
               or would leaue off before he be ſtarke drunke,
               Nay if he will not drinke ſo many houres,
               after his braynleſſe ſence to ſickneſſe ſunke:
               then ſtreight they vow mutuall coniunction,
               he dyes a foe to a belching fraternion.
            
            
               When groſepate chaplaines of deuouring ſinne,
               doe channel their lewd corps with ſcandold ſhame,
               And ſteeles the broken iſſue of there ſkinne,
               whoſe ouerweining looſenes racks his name,
               then is he mad, and to this Marſhall crewe,
               will make coniunction with his Prieſtlike hew.
            
            
               If any man will drinke till be dead,
               Lincolne black pots wil crie Amen to it,
               A chriſtian-ſeiming ſoe will make him ſweate,
               with Lees of drunken homiles ſcoures his wit,
               whoſe text doth fume out of a ſmoking toaſt,
               lining his belching craſt in a good ſeimd boaſt.
            
            
               
               But tis no maruell, when all trades are done,
               the onely refuge is to be a prieſt,
               When all prophaned vice, and murthers ſcumme,
               maſkt in thoſe honored robes are counted bleſt,
               But I would wiſh this Marſhal keep his daughter
               leaſt that a wraying ſong procure his ſlaughter.
            
            
               There was a certayne vnreformed ſtraine,
               And baſe corrupted-broking of a place,
               Crept in the head of an vnhallowed braine,
               Where he ſecurely might obſcure his race:
               ah Nicholl, Nicholl, that a quóiſtring roome,
               ſhould be ſubiected to a bloodie ſcumme,
            
            
               But where gould ſtamps, there vertue fals aboord,
               he that out biddes, merites the higheſt ſcailes,
               Fiue trades will driue one back, (though nere ſo good)
               and ſhag-rackt-wits though golden force preuailes,
               fiue places, when fiue houſes he doth maſter,
               and to each one three, Scullion, Collier, Baker.
            
            
               When he doth preach, not gainſt, but on good ale,
               whē he doth ſtorme, not gainſt, but on good ſoules,
               He not againſt, but on preciſe doth rayle,
               ſtill his (againſt) is fixed on goodneſſe moulds,
               he enuies good, yet ſeemes not ſuch a one,
               this is a church-like epigramation.
            
            
               
               He readeth much, and yet he cannot ſee,
               he ſtudies much, and yet he cannot ſpeake,
               He gayneth much, yet all by periurie,
               he ſweareth much, tut thats a ſillie cheake:
               he reads on Angell letters, ſtudies euill,
               his brocage gayne corrupts, ſweares like a diuell,
            
            
               Many may aske who this damn'd ſlaue may be,
               And may by great inquire finde his name,
               Rather ſeeke vertue then impietie?
               Seeke not too much, too ſoone coms lothſom ſhame
               
                  HANG-LET this Marſhall, hate his deformed euill,
               And thou expelſt him, &amp; in him the diuell. 
            
            
               Let not the feind maske ſafe in Samuels robes,
               Let not the pulpet-hater, and Gods woord,
               Let no prophaner Gods ſacred Temple robbe,
               Let no bloodthirſtie ſlaue with fury ſpurd,
               to triumph or the ſilly-cheated flocke,
               by ſuch an vntaught-domineiring blocke.
            
            
               Hees an Idolator indubitate,
               for like a carued image nere remoues,
               vnleſſe a ſutors goulden fees do prate,
               a goulden eloquence is all he loues:
               many good Angels doth he ſtand poſſeſt,
               and yet one deuill thinks his part is beſt.
            
            
               
               Oh that a ſeruant (as he thinkes him ſelfe)
               ſhould for preferment) good-corruptings ſlaue)
               Diſgrace his maiſter for a little pelſe,
               daſh of the bleſſed light, and darknes craue,
               and though that God offer ſuch gratious proffers,
               he wayes them not, ſo he may fill his coffers.
            
            
               He reads Gods word (yet thinkes there is no God)
               he ſerues the diuell (as his vnknowne friend),
               And though his priuate-lurching harts abode,
               be fixed at home, on his ſinne ſwallowing ende,
               yet are his heauen-heaud eyes with ſuch a grace
               though God, &amp; his own thoughts, forſwere the place.
            
            
               Looke to thy children, and reforme thy race,
               the time yet ſerues, be not too obſtinate,
               Refrayne thy lewd pathes in this time of grace,
               with true contrition: be not obdurate.
               now is the ſauing time to make thee bleſt,
               and dye thou mayeſt a ſaint, who liued a beaſt.
            
            
               If that a ſpleening minde, and ſtorming race,
               ſhould countermure my furious ſwelling brayne,
               And with a wounding ire bedawbe my face,
               to make my pen depaint thy miſcheiues vaine,
               twould make thee ſwere in a reuenging fire,
               whole do it as well, as any in Linconſhire,
            
            
               
               Oh that groſſe pates whoſe reaſons ſtampt in ſinne,
               ſhould fetter goodnes with vncurbed ſhame,
               With vnreſiſted yeelding to let in,
               the ſhamefull ſhew of a looſe gouernd name,
               this therefore ſhall remayne my laſt aduice,
               loue faire incountred vertue, and hate vice.
            
            
               Roome, roome, my maiſters, for a lethern pelt,
               tapſter ſix pots? here Tom, hers three for thee,
               Since thou haſt challengd me, ile make my belt,
               breake out her bounds ere we part company.
               charge &amp; diſcharge (for weele drink for the heauens,)
               till one or both purchaſe the feeld vneuen.
            
            
               A health to my miſtris (downe on thy maribones)
               oh prophand name common in euery mouth,
               Who would erect good phraſes, when ſuch ones
               as Coblers, tapſters, waterbearers route,
               who with their rotten-liſping-ſtumpes vnſould,
               what gentlemen for their due cuſtomes hould.
            
            
               Each ruſtie ſect of baſe artificers,
               will rob their baſe hides with the braueſt ſhowe,
               And pitch their pleaſures ſeate as high, as theirs,
               who triumph in the coſt-fantaſtick hew:
               for their preſumptions this aledge they can,
               when Adam digd who was a gentleman.
            
            
               
               Poore-tankard-ſlaues? who think them ſelues as great,
               whoſe preſt-downe-backes continuall weight inures,
               Whoſe grunting labour, for a peny ſweats,
               whoſe halfe houres toile one moment but indures.
               yet do they in as ſweete contentment reſt,
               and ſpend and drinke Tobacco with the beſt.
            
            
               Let a new faſhion once come ſtarting in,
               they with an open ſent deuoure the pray,
               Their ragged ioynts though freeſe, whoſe open skinne,
               feeles no could-icy ſtormes in winters dayes,
               they retchleſſe ſtand ſo they may haue ther ſwaie,
               though their benummed corps with could decay.
            
            
               The land Lord with a baſe deienerate ſhifte,
               to paint his carcaſſe rackes his tenants rent,
               Sinke in their downfall, (ſo he get a lift)
               he wayes not their vndoing languiſhment,
               their backes be gaye, their minds though lothſome be,
               ſilke robes diſmember hoſpitalitie.
            
            
               A laſſe who nameth hoſpitalitie,
               hees baniſht for returning to our clime,
               When hoſpitali's ſcorne deſteind penurie,
               and egent cripples ſwagger with the time;
               this worlds faire-countred vice is ſo alowd,
               baſe beggers luſtie, ſtearne controwlers prowd.
            
            
               
               Now luſtfull youth with a bard ſwelting crye,
               purſues his eager-burning-fire of luſt,
               Foſtring his held faſt clogge of crueltie,
               to gayne a remnant-limit, which he muſt,
               needs circumuent, for whoſoere denies,
               his wrath will butcher, parents or deareſt allies
            
            
               If that his minde ſtand to a lothſome ſoule,
               whoſe dowrie's but an ounce of durtines,
               His baſe-ingendred minde without comptrowle,
               muſt ſhrowd impreſſion of his beaſtlines.
               or els grace-hating vice will clip him ſhorte,
               intoumbing ſage aduice, which ſhould dehorte,
            
            
               When ſhallow purchaſe of a broken ſtile,
               ſhall ſhipp a ſhifting name to worthines,
               Whoſe ſenſuall miſcheifes rubiſht with a file,
               of fond-vaine glorie, hides his ſcuruines,
               what muſt this ſenſuall affectation yeeld,
               when vertue hateth ſhame, ſhame wins the field.
            
            
               What hath he got, a Moore, his mind's content,
               what hath he wonne, a whore, his humor's pleaſed,
               What hath he loſt, his parents, twas his conſent,
               whome did he hate, his friends, his hart is eaſed,
               let his deep-ſwallowing ſins think of this cheare,
               doomes day will come, &amp; then his woes appeare.
            
            
               
               Our youthfull mindes, is like a poyſoned glaſſe,
               which being broken by ſome caſuall meanes,
               A ſtander by (which fayne would bring to paſſe
               reiunction of the loſſe: thoſe poyſned ſtreames,
               impartiall eyther to his foe or friend,
               wil woork his ſenceles baine which ſought amēd.
            
            
               Let vs beware leaſt that our cuſtomd ſinne,
               which the true goſpell long hath couered,
               Be not erepted, and our ſhame beginne.
               to ſtaine our mindes, (which long hath houered)
               and Gods iuſt frowne on our lewd corps be ſeene
               taking the goſpell, and our gratious Queene.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            To the woorſhipfull my very louing
Coſen M. Thomas Rickarde of Hatfield-chaſe,
in Yorkeſhire.
            GOod coſen, not any deſert of mine owne woorth,
but hoping to be countenanced by your woorthines,
maketh me thus bould to relye on your acceptance
of this idle woorke, compounded (as the French
nod) of ſundry faſhions, a thing (which if it proue pleaſing
to you in the leaſt reſpect) I ſhall thinke it valuable
to my coſt and labour: I doe not doubt but as alwayes
you haue looued me, ſo you will not now reiect
this inſtance of my zealous affection which I haue
had from my cradle to gratifie you, proteſting (if you
wil boulſter me in this) neuer to ſtep ſo farre into the
preſſe agayne, and thus withall reſpectiue ceremonies
I take my leaue.
            
               Your louing Coſen
C. G. Gent.
            
         
         
            
            To the fauorable readers.
            GEntlemen) I do not immitate the new ſtart vp faſhion
of writings in theſe dayes, who ſo obſcurely will beginne,
and ſo duſkely end, as it will both ſtraine their
owne conceipt, &amp; the peruſers knowledge, for a man to write
that which none ſhall conceiue but himſelfe, is to make a laborinth
to catch euery idle br ayne in: that which I doe, I doe to
pleaſe, which muſt be by vnderſtanding: I do not ſeeke to
take flies, but to remoue fleas, which as I would not troble my
ſelfe with the one, ſo I would willingly reduce the other. Our
countries good, the vnfit education of baſe mindes, the arrogancie
of Peaſants, the pride of paynters, (like Don Hiltonio
knaue of the Trenitie) prouoke my vnpoliſh ſtumbling
pen, to exaſperate the vndecentneſſe of their nurture, and
vnfitneſſe of my owne nature. If any ſcorne my labour, he doth
me no wrong, becauſe I looked for no other, yet I hope true
gentles, will gently conceiue ſome better hope of better fruite
from ſo vnripened a bloſſome, my induſtrie and toyle with my
ſelf, I humbly ſubiect to euery mans cenſure, crauing none to be
earneſt to know him, who will not acknowledge them, or
hardly himſelfe.
         
      
   

