
   
      
         
            A godly and learned sermon, preached before an honourable auditorie the 26. day of Februarie. 1580
            Fulke, William, 1538-1589.
         
         
            
               1580
            
         
         Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2004-08 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01312
            STC 11434
            ESTC S112721
            99847966
            99847966
            13037
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01312)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13037)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 242:10)
         
         
            
               
                  A godly and learned sermon, preached before an honourable auditorie the 26. day of Februarie. 1580
                  Fulke, William, 1538-1589.
               
               [64] p.   
               
                  Imprinted by Henrie Middleton for Thomas Man,
                  [London] :
                  [1580?]
               
               
                  By William Fulke.
                  Publication date conjectured by STC.
                  Running title reads: A godly sermon preached in Lent 1580.
                  Signatures: A-D.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  16th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2004-02
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2004-03
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2004-04
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2004-04
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2004-07
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A GODLY
and learned Sermon,
preached before
an honourable auditorie
the 26, day of
Februarie. 1580.
            ¶ Imprinted by
Henrie Middleton
for Thomas
Man.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            A GODLY AND
learned Sermon, Preached
in Lent last.
1580.
            
               THE place of scripture
(moste honourable and
welbeloued in our Sauiour
Christ) which I haue
chosen to entreate of, is
written in the 24. Chapter of the second
booke of Samuel in these words.
Vers`l'
            And the wrath of the Lorde was yet
more kindled against Israel, and he moued
Dauid against them, in that he saide, goe
number Israel and Iuda, &amp;c.
            The whole Scripture of God (as the
holy Apostle S. Iames teacheth) is cō
               pared
to a glasse, wherein al estats and
degrees may see, what to imbrace and
what to eschew: and it is cōmonly said
of al histories, that they are ye looking

glasses of mans life. Therefore this
text beeing both a story and parcel of
holy Scripture, must needes be a most
cleare glasse, in which are represented
vnto vs diuers things worthie to bee
seene &amp; looked vpon. Among which I
haue thought good to shew vnto you
three especiall and most notable images.
The first, is the iustice and righteousnes
of God, the second, is the malice
of Sathan, the thirde is the frailtie
of man: not meaning to describe them
all at large, which would require much
longer time then is graūted to this exercise:
but onely to shewe euerie one
of them so farre foorth as it is set forth
with in ye compasse of this text which
I haue read vnto you. Concerning the
firste therefore, which is the iustice of
God, it is described in these wordes.
            
               And the wrath of the Lord was yet more
kindled against Israel, &amp;c. By the wrath
of the Lorde is here ment, the iustice of
God prouoked to punish sinnes, as in
an hūdreth places of scripture besides.
By the wrath of the Lorde therefore,
wee must not vnderstand any passion,

or disordered affection, such as is the
wrath of man, of which the Apostle
saith, that it worketh not ye righteousnes
of God, but is often prouoked
with small causes, or with no worthie
causes at all, and yet boileth immoderately
in the hart of man, whereby he
is vnmeasurablie desirous of reuengement:
but the iustice of God, which is
figuratiuely called his wrath, is neuer
stirred vp to reuengement, but vppon
great and waightie causes, neither rageth
with blinde furie, but keepeth a
most perfect moderation in all things.
And there are two reasons which may
be yeelded of this figuratiue speache,
wherefore Gods righteousnes is called
his wrath, the first is to strike through
our heartes with terrour of his iustice,
for the name of wrath is more terrible
then the name of iustice, and our nature
is more familierly acquainted with
the one, thē with the other, ye wrath of
a mā if he be of power to hurt, is greatly
feared. The wrath of a Prince saith
Salomon in the 16. chapter of the prouerbs
is the messenger of death: howe

much more ye wrath of ye Lord of hosts
in cōparison of whose power &amp; glorie
al earthly princes are but dust &amp; ashes.
The second reasō why ye iustice of god
is called the wrath of God, is that we
may learne and vnderstand, that as the
wrath of mā wherwith we are acquainted
is not pacified but by two meanes,
either by reconciliatiō or reuengemēt,
so it is with the iustice of God. Therefore
when soeuer wee haue prouoked
ye wrath of God against vs by our sins
and wickednes: (which we doe daily
and hourely) we must either seeke to
be recōciled to him by true repentāce,
or else looke for sharpe punishment:
we must either humbly submit our selues,
acknowledge our offences &amp; hū
               bly
desire pardon, or els we must assure
our selues yt the wrath of the Lord being
once kindled against vs, there is no
way to escape vengeance. We see now
wherefore the iustice of God is called
the wrath of God. Now must we looke
for what cause the wrath of God was
kindled against Israel: &amp; how the Israelites
had prouoked the iustice of god
to punish them. The cause in deede is

not set downe in expresse wordes, but
it is easie to gather by the effect: for it
is manifest, yt when the iustice of God
is kindled against Israel, it is for none
other cause but for their sinnes, &amp; it is
needles to inquire what particuler sins
were the cause: for it was not one or
two, but all kind of sinnes, &amp; especially
their vnthankefulnes: for the Lord had
giuen them Dauid a most excellent gouernour,
who both had established the
puritie &amp; sinceritie of Gods true religion,
and also had kept them in peace
&amp; trāquillity, for many yeres together.
But as it vsually cōmeth to passe through
the corrupt nature of man, which
is made insolēt with prosperitie, ye people
not considering those gret benefits
of God, were not onely vnthankful to
him for so happy a gouernmēt, but fol
lowed euery one the lustes of his owne
hart, not fearing to trāsgresse ye cōmandements
of the Lord: but yet retaining
an outward forme of Godlines by external
exercise of religion, the vertue &amp;
power whereof they denied in life &amp;
cōuersation, and so prouoked ye wrath

of the Lord of hoastes to be kindled against
thē: but we must consider wherfore
ye scripture saith The wrath of the
lord proceded or was yet more kindled, you
must vnderstād as we read in ye 21. cha.
of this booke, yt the wrath of the Lorde
was kindled before this time against ye
people, so yt he plagued thē with three
yeares famin for the crueltie that Saul,
to gratifie them, committed gainst the
Gibeonites whō he had slain, &amp; sought
to root our cōtrarie to a couenant whiche
their auncetors had made, &amp; confirmed
with a solemne oath, in yc days
of Iosua. These three yeeres of hunger
were now past, &amp; this was the fourth
yeere in which God after he had auenged
the bloud of the Gibeonites vpon
the posterite of Saul, had restored plē
               tie
and aboundance of al things for the
maintenance of mans life, with externall
peace &amp; prosperitie: for which benefits
&amp; blessings of God bestowed vpō
thē, they were boūd to haue serued
God in holines and righteousnes before
him all ye dayes of their life: like
as by the former plague they were

admonished to forsake their sinnes,
which were the cause thereof, and truly
to turne to him. But they cleane cō
               trariwise
abusing his mercy, tooke occasion
to prouoke his iustice, euen as
the froward nature of man is: so long
as they are plagued, and the hande of
the Lord is heauie on them, they humble
them selues before him, or at least
pretend so to doe: but when the plague
is seaced, and they find them selues relieued,
they returne againe to their former
wickednesse. So was it with the Israelites,
they had bene punished with
famine, but they were not thereby reformed,
and therefore the wrath of the
Lord is still kindled against them. By
which example we ought to be admonished,
that we deceiue not our selues
after the maner of the world, to thinke
that the wrath of the Lord shall be turned
from vs before we turne from our
sinnes: wherefore let vs not flatter our
selues as the reprobate doe, when they
haue escaped some particular punishment,
this daunger is ouercome, this
brunt is past, this storme is blowen ouer

&amp;c. For so long as we continue in
our sinnes, and seeke not ro be reconciled
vnto the Lorde, the wrath of the
Lorde will be still kindled against vs,
yea more and more prouoked to punish
vs: and if one plague be ceased,
an other shall beginne: when famine is
stayed, the pestilence shall rage: and if
that will not reforme vs, some other
plague shall be sent vpon vs. The Lord
can want no whippes, so long as his
wrath is bent to scourge vs, therefore
let vs not obstinately set our selues against
him, to trye whether he will be
soner wearied in striking, or we in bearing
his stripes: but let vs humbly and
at once cast downe ourselues, acknowledge
our sinnes, be sorie for them, and
forsake them: and then the way to reconciliation
shall be opened by our
Lorde and Sauiour Iesus Christe, in
whome the Lorde shall be pleased
with vs, and his wrath pacified towards
vs. We haue further to note the
reason of the metaphor, when the holy
Ghost saith: The wrath of the Lord was
kindled, which kinde of speach is very

often vsed in the Scripture, to compare
the wrath of God to fire, whose force
when it hath taken strength, can not
easily be stayed, and whose propertie
is to consume all things that ministreth
matter vnto it: and for that cause the
Lord him selfe in respect of his iustice,
is called a consuming fire. To the end
therefore that we should stand in feare
of Gods iustice: and that we should
be as carefull not to prouoke his wrath
against vs, as we are carefull not to
minister matter vnto fire, which
will be readie to consume our selues,
and all that euer we haue: our GOD
is saide to be a consuming fire: and the
wrath of the Lord is saide to be kindled
against vs. Therefore as there is no
dallying with fire, when any light substance
is neare which is readie to take
flame: so there is no dissembling before
God, the fire of whose wrath and iustice
is kindled with our sinnes &amp; wickednes:
for as ye Lord hateth &amp; abhorreth
all sinnes and vngodlines, so his iustice
is kindled like fire against ye same,
to purge and cleanse the world of all

vnrighteousnesse. Let not sinners therfore
thinke to stande in his presence,
which is a consuming fire, before whō
they shall melt euen as waxe, and vanish
away as smoake, before whome
they shall be as stubble and chaffe, that
is set on fire, and can not be quenched.
And let vs which trust in his mercy,
not be high minded, but stande in
awe of his iustice, and prouoke not his
wrath to bekindled against vs through
our manifold sinnes and wickednesse,
whose wrath if it be but a little kindled
as the prophet saith, no man is able to
stand in the presence of his iustice, but
it will appeare howe happie they are
which put their trust in his mercy. And
if the wrath of God being but a little
kindled hath so notable effect: what is
to be looked for, when it is wholy inflamed
in furie against vs, for grosse &amp;
manifest contempt of his glorious maiestie?
For as contempt in men is the
chiefest cause in prouoking them to
anger, and the greatest contempt prouoketh
the greatest anger: so it is with
the Lorde, whose iustice is despised in

all sinne, and disobedience of his lawe:
but chiefly in that prophane and professed
contempt, which we see to beare
the sway among great numbers of the
wicked, which openly and without all
feare of his iustice, haue solde them
selues like Achab, to commit all manner
of sinne with greedinesse. Thus we
see what the spirite of God meaneth,
when he saith: The wrath of God was
yet more kindled against Israel.
            
            Nowe we haue to consider howe it
standeth with the iustice &amp; righteousnesse
of God, that Israel hauing prouoked
the wrath of God, the heart of Dauid
is moued to number the people:
that the wrath of the Lord being kindled
against Israel, he stirred vp Dauid
against them. For it seemeth contrarie
to reason, that the people hauing deserued
punishment, the Lorde should
deale with the Prince for them. But
for so much as the Prince is as it were,
an helme or sterne, by which the Lord
gouerneth the whole comminaltie of
people which the Lord hath committed
to their charge, it standeth well

with his iustice and wisedome also, to
moue and stirre vp the Prince against
them, when so euer their transgressions
shall prouoke his righteousnesse to
chasten them. And euen so saith Salomon,
Prouer. 21. As the streames of waters,
or as it is nowe translated, as a vessell
in the streams of waters, so is the kings
hart in the hand of the Lord, &amp; whethersoeuer
he will he inclmeth and moueth it,
eyther to the hauen of prosperitie, if the
people serue him, or to the shoare of danger
and aduersitie, if they prouoke his wrath against
them. Therefore as the stirring
of a shippe by the master directeth the
shippe whither he thinketh good: euen
so the Lord moueth the heartes of
all Princes, which are as the sterne of
the shippe of the common wealth in
his hand, that they are not carried at all
aduentures whither the stream of waters
will driue them, but whither so euer
it pleaseth him: either to the great
and singular benefite of that people
which feareth the Lord, or for the correction
and punishment of them which
transgresse his lawes, and contemne

his iustice. Ye heare nowe howe well it
agreeth, not onely with the iustice, but
also with the wisedome of God, that
he should moue the heart of the king
according to the disposition of the
people. Besides this, we must also vnderstand,
that as Princes are publique
persons in respect of their gouernemēt
of whole nations committed to their
charge, so also before the Lord, they
are priuate persons, to be called to account,
not only for such things as they
do in their publique gouernement, but
also for such offences as they commit
priuatly, as the sonnes of Adam: Among
which there is none found so
righteous, but that in many things they
transgresse the lawe of God: and therefore
the iustice of God is not to be accused
of any vnrighteousnesse, when
the people haue prouoked his wrath,
and Dauid can not iustifie him selfe
before him, if he stirre vp Dauids heart
againste the people for their punishment,
and take occasion of the
peoples sinnes to punish Dauid him
selfe.
            
               
For although here is no transgression
of Dauid expressed, wherby he might
seeme to haue brought this punishment
vpon him, yet Dauid him selfe
will confesse, that there was alwayes
sufficient cause in him, why the Lorde
might chastise him: for so he acknowledgeth
in the 51. Psalme, that not only
for that grosse and notorious sinne
of adulterie and murther, he had deserued
Gods vengeance, but generally he
accuseth his whole life of sinne, and
transgression of Gods lawes, that the
wrath of God in his punishmēts, what
so euer it should please him to lay on
him, might of al the world be acknowledged
to be iust and righteous. For
thus he cryeth, Against thee, against
thee (O Lorde) I haue sinned: that is, I
haue done nothing but sinned, &amp; done
that which is euill in thy sight, that
thou mightest be iustified in thy sayings,
and haue the vpper hande when
thou art iudged. And least we should
thinke that he speaketh of some short
time of his life, in which the diuell had
so greatly preuayled with him, he declareth

in the next verse, that it was euen
from his natiuitie, yea frō his conception,
that this corruption hath remayned
in him, which is contrarie to
the righteousnesse of God. Behold (saith
he) I was borne in sinne, and in iniquitie did
my mother conceiue me, whereas thou louest
trueth in the inward partes. This cō
               fession
of Dauid therefore, is sufficient
to cleare the Lorde from all vnrighteousnesse,
and to shewe manifestly, that
Dauid is not punished for the peoples
sinnes as an innocent, which hath deserued
nothing in his owne person, nor
is beaten altogether for the faultes of
other mē, which could not stand with
Gods righteousnesse, except in that
case, where our sauiour Christ willingly
offered him selfe to be punished for
our transgressions. But here the Israelites
prouoking the wrath of the Lord,
deserued ye a good gouernour should
decline out of ye right course for their
punishment. And Dauid him selfe can
not deny, but ye when so euer the Lord
shal chastice him, he shal not do it with
out his deserts. So yt euery way it standeth

with Gods righteousness, that Israel
hauing caused his wrath to be kind
led against him, he should stirre vp Dauid
whome he had giuen to them, being
a most excellent Prince for their
benefit, nowe to giue occasion of their
punishment. But against this doctrine
of the iustice and righteousness of
god, two kind of aduersaries do rise vp.
The first are the Pelagians, and Papists
so farre as they agree with the Pelagians.
The second are the Atheistes: the
former sort reason after this manner. If
you say yt God moued Dauid to number
ye people, which was sinne, do you
not thereby make God ye author of sin?
God forbid: let God onely be righteous,
and all men sinners. For he only is
holy, he only is pure frō al corruptiō,
and there is no vnrighteousnes in him.
But howe can you auoyde that inconuenience
(say they) that followeth of
this assertion: God moued Dauid to do
that wherwith he was displeased, therfore
he was the cause of the sinne in
Dauid. It is easily auoyded. For the
same storie is set downe in 1. Chro. 21.

Chap. where it is said, that Satan or the
aduersarie stoode vp against Israel, and
moued the hart of Dauid to number ye
people: by conference of which place
of Scripture with this my text, we may
see how God moued Dauid to number
the people, and yet moueth him to no
sinne. For whereas it is here saide, that
the Lorde was angrie with Israel, and
moued Dauid against them (for we can
not aptly vnderstand any other, but either
the Lord, or the wrath of the Lord
which moued him) and in the Chronicles
it is saide, that Sathan moued him,
it is manifest, that God and the diuell
concurre in one action. God as a most
righteous iudge, and Sathan as a most
malicious enimie. By which wese that
there proceedeth nothing from GOD
but iustice, and that the sinne which is
euill commeth from the diuell: so that
the Lord God, although he be the first
mouer in all our actions (for in him we
liue, and moue, and haue our being) yet
he is not authour or cause of any euill
in vs. Neuerthelesse, hee vseth Sathan
to punish vs, who although hee

be a malitious enimie, yet is he a minister
of ye righteous iudgement of God,
although against his will: and euen
then when he opposeth him selfe against
God. For Sathan is not suffered
to reigne and rage at his pleasure against
the elect of GOD, for then he
would in one moment ouerthrow the
whole Church of Christe, but kept in
chaines of darknesse, so that he can not
stirre, but where and when it pleaseth
God in iustice to vse his ministerie and
seruice. Therefore when the wrath of
the Lorde was kindled against Israel,
Sathan also standeth vp against Israel
as a minister of Gods wrath, by necessitie
of Gods ordinance, though a cruell
aduersarie by his owne will and malicious
affection. So that neither by
colour of this texte, nor of any oother
in the whole Scripture, the Lord
can be charged as the cause of the same
euill which he punisheth either in the
elect, or in the reprobate, for what so euer
proceedeth from him, as it proceedeth
from him is good, and to a good
end, who vseth well euen Sathan the

aduersarie of all goddnesse, and his
members the reprobate: and so ordereth,
brideleth, and gouerneth their
sinnes and wickednes, that euen their
euill he turneth to good, &amp; out of their
wickednesse as it were, light out of
darkenesse bringeth his glorie. So he
hardened the heart of Pharao, yet was
he not the cause of Pharaos sinne, but
the cause was in Pharao him selfe, who
of his owne corruption did set him self
against God: and of Sathan who ruleth
in the reprobate, and stirreth him vp
to rebellion, and obstinate resisting of
Gods commandements. Thus was the
heart of Pharao hardened by God, as
by a righteous iudge: by Sathan, as by a
malicious enimie against God &amp; mankind:
by Pharao him selfe, as by a man
who being cleane voyde of Gods spirite
by corruption of his owne nature,
is inclined to nothing but to contempt
and disobedience of God, and ye whole
matter so ordered in all pointes by the
diuine prouidence, that the glory of his
iustice might be set foorth in Pharaos
destruction, euen as ye Lord saith vnto

him euen for this cause haue I stirred thee
vp, that I might shewe foorth my power in
thee, &amp; that my name might be renouned
in al the world. Therefore the same God
which maketh an hypocrite to reigne
for the sinnes of ye people, and giueth a
king in his furie whom he taketh away
againe in his indignation (as ye prophet
saith) euen the same God, by the same
authoritie, wisdome, &amp; iustice, moueth
Dauid a good king against Israel, yt he
might punish them without all contagion
or infection of yt sinne and euil by
which he was moued to number ye people,
which caused god to punish them,
so yt although god giueth the first mouing,
power, and strength, in al maner
of actions, which we must confesse to
be good, as proceding from him, &amp; ordreth
&amp; disposeth al euil, which is a per
uerting of yt good which cōmeth from
God, &amp; proceedeth from Satan &amp; the
corruptiō of mans nature, so yt he conuerteth
ye same alwayes in ye end to his
glory, &amp; the benefite of his elect, as we
see in ye persecution of ye wicked, &amp; the
infirmities of the godly: yet is he by no

meanes to be charged as the author &amp;
cause of sinne &amp; euill. If this wil not satisfie
you, but yt you will further vrge
me with that questiō of the Maniches,
whence cōmeth euil, seing nothing but
good cōmeth from God, &amp; yet you affirme,
yt God is the cause of all things. I
wil answer as I haue learned out of the
anciēt writers, who wer troubled with
yt sect of ye Maniches, which affirmed, yt
there were two beginnings. When it
pleased ye almightie to shew foorth his
infinit power, wisdom, &amp; goodnes in ye
creation of things visible and inuisible,
bodily &amp; spiritually, it pleased him for
ye illustratiō &amp; setting forth of ye glorie
of his goodnes, to ordeine (for so they
haue taught me to speake) yt euil shuld
proceed out of ye frewill of his reasonable
creatures. And this his ordinance is
good. For although euil be naught, and
cursed be he yt saith euill is good, yet yt
there shuld be euill (which is Gods ordinance)
it is excellēt good. If this seem
strange to any man, I wil make it plain
by two manifest reasons: the first is, the
excellencie of goodnes can not so well

appeare &amp; be knowne, as by ye comparison
of the contrarie, which is euill.
Therefore it is perfect good, that euill
should be for the manifestation of that
which is good, we see that in all ye creatures
and workes of the world, GOD
hath ordained that his glorie should
shine in contraries. As to the intent yt
the beutie and glory of light should be
seene and knowne to be such as it is, he
hath ordained darkenesse. For if he had
created light to be perpetual without
any change of darknes, how had it ben
possible for men, although liuing in the
light, to haue knowne the excellencie
of light, &amp; so should God haue ben defrauded
of ye glory of so beutifull, profitable,
and cōfortable a creature. Therfore
euen as by darknes we learne how
to esteeme light, and by bitter that
which is sweete, and euery other thing
by his contrarie: euen so by the deformitie
of euill we are taught, howe great
is the excellent comlines of that which
is good, therfore the ordinance of god,
that there should be euill, is perfect
good. Althtugh this reason be plaine

inough, yet the second reason is more
manifest, euen to ye meanest capacities.
For yt the glorie of gods mercie might
appeare in the saluation of his electe,
and his iustice in the condemnation
of the reprobate, it was necessarie that
there should be euil and so necessary
that otherwise there should haue bene
no matter for the mercie and iustice of
God to worke vppon: For if there
shoulde haue beene no sinne nor euill,
wherein shoulde the mercie of GOD
in pardoning and forgiuing of sinnes
haue bene seene? if there should haue
beene no transgression, howe shoulde
the glorie of Gods iustice haue shined
in punishment? Ye see therefore
that God by no means may be compted
the author of euill, which he hath
not created, made or wrought, but ordeined
that it shoulde proceede from
the freewil of his reasonable creatures
for the illustration of his glorie. Let
vs therefore tremble at his righteous
iudgementes who doth all thinges according
to the good pleasure of hys
will: and hath made the wicked man

for the daye of his wrath (as Salomon
testifieth) and yet by no meanes is the
cause of his wickednes. If any man bee
not satisfied with this answere, he may
enter further into ye vnmeasurable deapthe
of Gods iudgement, into which
he may rather finde an entraunce, thē
a way out, except it bee to his euerlasting
destruction for his horrible presumption.
You haue heard nowe the
iustice of God defended againste the
Pelagians and Papistes, it followeth
that I speake some thing to the confutation
of the second enemies thereof
which are the Atheistes, who because
they will not bee troubled with such
thornie &amp; doubtful questions, as these
are, imagine that they haue founde an
easie way vnto wisedome, and a solutiō
for all controuersies of religion when
they say in their harts there is no God.
Against whose impietie &amp; madnes, the
time wil not serue me to spek so much
as their wickednes deserueth, &amp; yet if
time wold permit neuer so large a discourse,
I could say in effect no more against
thē, then ye prophet Dauid writeth

in the 14. Psalme. Amar Hanabal.
The greatest and most doltish foole of
all fooles hath said in heart, there is no
God. But what meaneth the prophet
so to befoole them, when of all other
men they are, or woulde seeme to bee
the finest witted, the best learned, and
most full of all wisedome and knowledge:
euen because of all other they
are most voide of all true wisedome,
which although they fansie to thē selues
that they only haue found, yet is there
not one among an hundreth that dare
acknowledge it. A goodly wisedome
that they are ashamed to professe and
stand in defēce of it, for although they
nourish that monster in their hearts &amp;
are bold sometimes to shew foorth the
same, where they thinke themselues to
be the best learned: yet is ther not one
of them that dare encounter with a
Christian Philosopher, to mainetaine
by reason that which they holde againste
all reason, they obiecte perhappes,
you will oppresse them with
the authoritie of Gods worde and
the holye Scriptures, where vnto

they giue no credit, nay we wil lay the
Bible aside, and dispure with them
out of the great booke, euen out of the
beutifull theater of the world in whose
creation and preseruation if they can
not reade written in great capitall letters,
the almightie power, wisedome &amp;
goodnes, and the iustice and mercie of
God in the gouernement thereof, they
are the most blind, blockishe and vnsensible
of all other creatures. And yet
they fancie in their frensie that they
haue founde out the greatest and the
deepest point of wisedome, when they
are fallen into the greatest absurditie
or follie that can be. For what can bee
more contrary to reason thē to affirme
an effect without a cause or to followe
their dreames, an eternall effect without
an eternall cause? Therefore the
holy Ghost most aptlie exprobrateth
vnto them extreme follie, because by
their monstruous position of denyinge
God, they take away the fountaine of
all knowledge and wisedome, that is,
the cause of all thinges. But as the asse
yeeldeth to no other reason, but to a

clubbe, so they are more worthie to be
knocked downe with a betle, then to
be confuted with anie reason, which
no lesse then the authoritie of Gods
word written in the scriptures, and the
law of nature written in the hearts of
all nations, is most contrarie and repugnant
to their most folish and damnable
persuasion. The Lord deliuer vs
from the deuices, practises, and doings
of the Atheistes: as for their witt, learning,
wisedome and reason, in which
they please them selues aboue other
men, we are nothing afraide of, it they
durst take vppon them the defence of
their diuelish persuasion, and let them
assure them selues that the iustice of
God which nowe they contemne, they
shall hereafter feale, and howe soeuer
they woulde flye from it, it shall finde
them at the length, wherof a restimonie
also remaineth stil in their conscience
which the prophet in the Psalme
forgetteth not to note where he saith,
There haue they feared, where there is no
cause to feare: For of all other these
prophane Atheistes that can so boldlie

&amp; lustily despise God and his righteousnes
in any appearāce of daunger,
yea where no daunger at all is, are most
fearefull cowardes and trembling dastards,
and no meruaile: for what good
courage can there be, where there is no
hope but in this life, nor comforte of
helpe, but in men which are not able
to helpe themselues. But I am to blame
to vse to much speach against thē, who
either heare it not, or though thei herd
it, wold make no accompt of it, saying
that it is not vnprofitable for the godly
and religious to haue the madnesse
of these men made manifest, that they
maye the more deteste them, and
better beware of them. Thus haue you
heard the iustice of God deliuered frō
the malice of the gretest enemies therof.
God graunt that as manie of them
as be recouerable, maye in time see against
whome they haue beene bold to
oppose them selues, and vnderstanding
howe little it is possible for them
to preuaile, they may no more kick against
the pricke, nor striue againste
the streame, but in all humilitie and

submission acknowledging their haynous
rebellion, they may desire rather
to bee releeued by his mercie, then by
contending anye longer to trie the rigor
of his iustice. One other thinge
more to bee noted in this example of
Gods iustice, which the scripture testifieth:
that the Lorde in his wrath remembreth
his mercie towardes his elect,
and that appeareth in this history.
For when the people had prouoked
the wrath of the Lorde to bee kindled
againste them, and that hee in iustice
was to procure a punishmet and correction
for their amendement: yet hee
so ordered the whole matter by his
merciful &amp; deuine prouidence, that in
the end it turned to ye singuler benefit
of his Church, so that euen the rod by
whiche he scourgeth thē, was a demō
               stration
of his mercie towardes them.
For as it appeareth in the 22. Chap. of
the booke of Chronicles, by occasion
of the plague which God sent for the
punishment of the peoples sins, Dauid
found out ye place which ye Lorde had
appointed for ye building of his tēple.

Marueilous therfore is the prouidence
of the Lorde, which (as the wise man
saith) extendeth it selfe from ende to
ende mightelie, and disposeth al things
sweetlie, and wonderfull is the louing
kindnes and mercie of God towardes
his electe, which euen then when his
wrath is kindled against them, forgetteth
not like a moste louing father in
chastening of their faults to seeke their
amendement, and to change the verie
correction and punishment it selfe into
a singuler benefite and blessing. For
what a singuler benefite was it to all
the Church of Israel, when the Lorde
had appointed his resting place in Sion,
and the building of his Temple
in Hierusalē, which place the Lord reueiled
by occasion of this punishment
and Dauid perceiued that the Lorde
had hearde his prayer, when he sacrificed
in the threshing floure of Aranna
the Iebusite so that the angell was cō
               maunded
to put vp his sword, and the
pestilence was stayed from raging any
longer among the people. Wherefore
we see that although the iustice of god

in his punishment bee terrible for the
time, yet in the ende he turneth all to
the benefite of the faithfull, By which
we learne not to be faint harted or discouraged,
when the Lordes wrath is
kindled against vs: but with patience
to beare his anger, whē we haue sinned
against him, and with the eyes of faith
to beholde his mercie, which he neuer
forgetteth towardes his chosen, no
not when hee dealeth moste sharply
with them. For not onely his rodd &amp;
staffe (as the Prophete saith) shall cō
               forte
vs, as they are the tokens of his
fatherly chastisement for our reformation,
but also the verie meanes whiche
he prouideth for our punishment hee
conuerteth oftentime to our benefite:
thus doth faith ouercome the terrour
of Gods iustice, when it assureth vs,
that it is so far off, that the same should
take any place againste vs for our destruction,
in as much as it is satisfied by
the death of Iesus Christ: that contrariewise
his punishmentes are merciful,
and his chastisemēts are beneficial
vnto vs. Onely let vs take heede that

we despise not his long suffering in his
fauourable correctiō, least with ye wicked
we procure his warth to be vpon
vs vnto ye end. An other lesson, we haue
to learne in this exāple of gods iustice,
as profitable in all ages, so most necessarie
in our time. The wrath of ye Lord
was here kindled against Israel, for
whose punishment Dauid is moued to
number the people whence now proceedeth
ye cause of this punishmēt? not
frō ye gouernmēt of Dauid, but frō the
sins of the people. For while the people
please God, &amp; serue him according to
his word, he blessed Dauid for their benefit
in all his consultations &amp; affaires:
but when ye people prouoke the wrath
of God against thē, then is Dauid made
an instrument for their punishment. It
is not vnlike but the people in Dauids
time among other their sinns by which
they prouoked Gods punishmēt, were
also infected in this vice, yt they tooke
vpon them, as it is vsuall with people
that are vnthankful for the great trauel
which princes bestow in their gouernment,
to enter into finding of faulte

with ye state of regiment, &amp; to remoue
the cause of their punishments frō thē
selues, vnto him which had lesse deserued
it. Neuertheles the holy ghost testifieth
plainly yt the cause of this plague
was not the ill demeanor of Dauid, but
the sinnes of Israel. Let Israel therfore
walke in the ways of the Lord &amp; serue
him with an vpright hart, &amp; there shall
be no error in ye gouernmēt of Dauid,
but he shal haue a prosperous raigne ouer
them. A lesson verie needfull for ye
people of our dayes, who were neuer
so curious to enquire of princes causes
and matters of the state, of which for
want of knowledg they are meet to be
no Iudges although they had authoritie,
as they be in this time. But sirs you
forget your place, God hath made you
subiects and not gouernours, to be gouerned,
and not to rule, enter not therfore,
neither intermedle you with princes
matters, but enter into your selues
&amp; looke yt your sinns &amp; wickednes do
not cause an error to be in the gouernment,
for if there be any at any time, it
proceedeth frō you, your sinns are the

cause as it appeareth plainly in this exāple.
The sinnes of Israel prouoked the
Lord to wrath, and then Dauids heart
is moued to number the people. From
whence proceede ill humors which
trouble the head and cause it to ake,
out of the head? no, they ascende out
of the bodie into the heade, and so causeth
the heade to ake, and then the aking
of the head is ye disquietnes of all
the body, and yet the cause is not in the
heade, but in the il humors which proceede
from the bodie. Take heed therfore
that ye minister no ill humors out
of the body into the heade, and the
head shall be well inough, able to gouerne
the bodie. Looke therefore to ye
purging of the bodie from sinne and
wickednesse, that no distemperature
thereby doe rise into the heade, and
doubt you not, but the Lorde God as
he hath alwaies hitherto, so he will frō
hence foorth direct the heade to your
singuler benefite, quietnes, and commoditie:
And in this behalfe wee haue
earnestly to pray to the Lorde for the
preseruation of our soueraigne, considering

howe greatly wee haue prouoked
his wrath, and giuen him iust cause
to withdrawe his bountifull graces frō
her, which hithert to it hath pleased him
moste plenteously to bestowe vppon
her highnes to our singuler benefites
and comfort, and likewise we haue to
praise and magnifie the Lorde, for his
infinite mercie, declared in his longe
suffering and patience toward vs, who
notwithstāding we haue so often, and
so much prouoked him to indignatiō
through our manifolde transgressions,
contempt of his worde and vnthankefulnes:
yet hath he so blessed her estate
and gouernement, and that for so long
time ouer vs, that searching all monumentes
of stories from the beginning,
the like examples of prosperous and
peaceable regement shall neuer bee
founde, I say the like happie and quiet
gouernement in all godlinesse and honesty
for so many yeres together, is not
to bee shewed in this Iland out of any
recordes of antiquitie. Turne ouer the
booke hardly and spare not, and bring
me foorth no small examples, but onlie

such as our moste soueraigne Ladie
may vouchsafe to excel, if euer the like
prosperous &amp; godly estat can be shewed
of so long continuance. Let vs therfore
yeeld glorie vnto his maiestie, frō
whose onely goodnes this, as all other
goods gifts haue proceeded, &amp; thankfull
obedience vnto her highnes whō
he hath vsed as a meane and instrumēt
to procure all this happines vnto vs.
And as wee haue thus longe enioyed
this blessed gouernmēt, so that we may
enioye it twise as many yeares or more
if it be his will, let vs become humble
sutors to our heauenly father, that hee
will blesse her maiestie with longe life
to the glorie of his name, and the benefite
of his Church, but especially
considering wee haue prouoked the
Lordes wrath to bee kindled againste
vs, let vs make hast to bee reconciled
vnto him by vnfayned and heartie repentaunce
and amendement of life, for
when the Lorde shall see vs turned
truely vnto him, hee will turne from
the fearcenesse of his wrath, and turning
awaye from vs all such plagues

and punishmentes as wee moste righteously
haue deserued, hee will turne
vnto vs the cheerefull light of hys
countenance in Iesus Christ, in whom
and for whome hee is well pleased
with vs. And thus muche touching
the righteousnesse of God, which
is the first part.
            The seconde poynte wee haue to
consider is the malice of Sathan, whiche
is noted to vs in the 21. Chapter
of the first booke of Chronicles where
it is saide, that Sathan stoode vppe againste
Israel, and moued the hearte
of Dauid to number the people. Althoughe
the malice of Sathan bee manifold,
and almost infinite: yet I will
note it in two pointes onelie, out of
this texte. Firste in the person with
whome he dealeth, and secondly in the
sinne wherevnto hee prouoketh him.
Concerning the first, it is said that Sathan
stoode vp againste Israel and moued
the hearte of Dauid. For when
Gods wrath was kindled agaynste
Israel, Sathan was Gods minister to
execute his iuste iudgemente, not of

obedience to God, but of malice to
Israel. Therfore howe doth he execute
it? he goeth streight to Dauid. For Sathan
findinge himselfe loosed of that
chaine by which he is restrayned from
assaulting the people of God, whome
he defendeth with his grace, and boyling
in malice againste the Church of
GOD, whose prosperitie hee enuieth,
and seeketh her destruction, imediately
he setteth vppon the chiefe gouernour
thereof. All his malice is against
the Church of God, and therfore
it is said, Sathan stoode vp againste Israel:
but he knowing wher to do most
mischiefe, beginneth to shew his malice
against Dauid, he seeketh to infect
the heade that he might destroye the
whole body. He knoweth that a godly
and vertuous prince is the principal instrument
that God vseth amongst men
to procure ye wealth of his Church and
chosen people: and therefore of hatred
against ye church, &amp; rankor against gods
people he seeketh by al meanes to corrupt
a good prince, &amp; to cause a godly
gouernour to bee vnprofitable to thē:

see therefore how great cause we haue
with earnest and daily praiers, to commend
vnto the gratious protection of
our God, the preseruation of our godly
Prince and Souereigne. Bicause we
see the malice of Satan to be so great, yt
whensoeuer he is let loose to stand vp
against Israel, he will begin his assault,
where he knoweth he may doe most
hurt to the Church of GOD. And
therefore not without cause the Apostle
so vehemētly exhorteth, that prayers,
supplications, intercessions, and
thankesgiuings be made, specially for
Kings, and all that be in authoritie, bicause
Sathans malice which he beareth
against Gods Church, he seeketh specially
to execute by them whose power
is greatest, and whose example carieth
the multitude after them. For euē
as the Lorde in wisedome and iustice
vseth to punish the people by their
Princes, euen so Sathan of hatred and
malice, seeketh the ouerthrowe of the
Church by the same persons. The second
point, wherein the malice of Sathan
is to be considered, is the vice or

sinne wherevnto he moued the heart
of Dauid. The text saith, he moued Dauid
to number the people. For a prince
to nūber &amp; muster his people, of it self
it is no sin, but a thing indifferēt of his
owne nature, which at sometime is not
only lawfull to do, but also necessarie:
and therefore it is no hard matter to
gather what sinne Dauid committed
in numbring the people, namely his
heart by Sathan contrarie to his former
faith and humble trust in Gods
promises, was lifted vp with pride and
presumption. For hauing no lawfull
cause either Ecclesiasticall to leuie a
subsidie for the maintenance of Gods
religion, as Moses prescribeth in the
30. of Exodus, or else ciuill, as was oftentimes
lawfully practised in time of
warre: he alledgeth only his vaine curiositie
(that he might know the number
of them): thus did Sathan beginne
to plant the roote of pride and insolencie
in the hart of Dauid, which as it
is a vice in al men most odious, so to be
in a Prince is most daungerous, and
that for many causes. All which Sathan

did well foresee, when he maketh his
assault vnto Dauid with the sinne of
presumption first of all, for that of all
othervices Princes are most easily
drawne to pride and insolencie, both
bicause the nature of all men is most
prone and apt to fall into pride in prosperitie,
and for that Princes and high
estates, being aduaunced to such greatnesse
aboue all other men, haue so many
occasions to be pfst vp with presumption,
if they be not mightily and
maruelously defended by the singular
grace of God. So that a Prince that is
humble and lowly in heart, is one of
the greatest miracles of the world: and
in deede so great a wonder, that it can
not be brought to passe, but by him
which onely worketh great maruelles.
Thus Sathan beeing most malicious
and moste subtill in his malice, to
bring his purpose to effect more speedily,
vseth such a meane, by whiche
hee may worke most easily. Neyther
hath hee regarde onely to the easinesse
of his enterprise, but that the
same also is most apt to ouerthrowe

the Churche and people of GOD.
for by pride and insolencie, most of all
other vices, a Prince is made vnapt to
exercise his office and duetie. The office
of a King standeth in two pointes.
The first is, in maintenance of true religion:
the second is prouision for the
common wealth, and publique peace
of his subiectes: but neither of these
can he exercise to the glorie of God, &amp;
benefite of men, if his heart be ouercome
with presumption: for touching
the first, if pride possesse the heart of a
King, he will either neglect religion altogether,
or else thinke that he may
doe and decree in religion what he list.
If he neglect the cause of religion, he
will haue no regard to set out Gods
glorie, he passeth not whether ye worde
of God be preached or not preached,
whether the sacramentes be ministred
or not ministred, discipline exercised
or not, or whether all thinges be well
done or yll done: finally he careth not
whether religion goeth backward or
forward. But if he will intermeddle
with religion with a presumptuous &amp;

insolent minde, he wil imagine, that all
things in religion are subiect to his wil
and pleasure. Vzzia otherwise not the
worst Prince, was so lifted vp with
pride, that he vsurped the Priestes office,
and would needes offer incense:
but he was plagued for his presumption,
and stricken of the Lorde with a leprosie.
Achas commaunded Vrias the
high Priest to remoue the altar of the
Lord out of his place, and to set vp an
other altar of an other fashion, according
to the patterne which he sent him
from Damasco. Ieroboam, thinketh it
lawfull for him to chaunge the decree
of GOD concerning worshipping at
Hierusalem, and setteth vp an newe
forme of worshippe in Dan and Bethel.
Saul thinketh long to tarie for
Samuel, and offereth sacrifice without
him. These examples and many other
doe shewe how dangerous to the state
of religion, is the sinne of pride and
presumption in the heart of a Prince.
No maruell therefore, if Sathan which
maliceth most the good proceedings in
religion, that he might vndermine the

tower of the church to the vtter ouerthrow
of ye same, prepareth his way by
puffing vp ye Kings heart with pride &amp;
insolencie, knowing that he which is
proude and insolent towards men, can
not be humble &amp; obedient vnto God.
The second part of the office of a king
is, to prouide for the common wealth,
the peace and prosperitie of his subiectes,
which can not be without great
trauell and labour of minde and body.
But if the Prince be ouercome with
pride, he will neuer abase him selfe to
take such great paines as he ought to
doe, for the benefite of other men in so
difficult &amp; dangerous a matter. Therefore
Moses in the 17. of Deuteronom.
where he describeth what manner a
King is to be chosen by the Israelites,
and what is the office of a King when
he is elected, ioyneth both these partes
together, and for the performance of
the later, especially admonisheth them
to beware of presumption, when the
King (saith he) shal sit vpon the throne
of his kingdome, he shal write out by a
copie receiued of the Priestes, a booke

of the law of the Lord, and that shal be
with him to read therin al the dayes of
his life, yt he may prosper, and learne to
feare the Lord his God, &amp; to keepe al ye
words of ye lawe to do thē: thus hauing
prescribed the booke of ye lawe to be ye
directiō of his gouernmēt, as wel in religiō
as in affaires of ye cōmoon welth, to
which burdē yt the king might submit
his shoulders, and not thinke scorne to
beare it, he addeth īmediatly, yt his hart
be not lift vp aboue his brethren, what
meaneth Moses by this, yt a king should
not shew him selfe to be a king. When
by Gods ordinance he is aduaunced &amp;
lifted vp aboue all other men? no verily,
he meaneth not so: but that the king
is lifted vp aboue his brethren, to be a
father vnto them, and to haue a fatherly
care, which hee can not haue, if his
heart be lifted vp aboue them to contemne
them, whereas he ought not only
to reteine his loue to them which he
had before he was a king, as vnto his
brethrē, but also to put on a greater affection
of loue when he is a king, as of a
father towards his children. Wherfore

the meaning of Moses is, that the Kings
heart should not be lifted vp aboue
his brethren, to cōtemne them, to tread
them vnder feete, to exercise tyrannie
ouer them, but to be humble and lowly
minded of loue, willingly, &amp; chearfully
to take such trauels, and to ouercome
such difficulties, as is necessarie for all
them which shall gouerne well, and to
the profite of others. We see that naturall
parentes, which haue the greatest
authority ouer their children of whom
they are to be honoured, notwithstanding
their dignitie, doe willingly and
gladly indure any trauell, which they
thinke may be profitable and beneficiall
to their children: euen so ought the
parents of the countrie (whose honour
&amp; obedience is confirmed vnto them
by none other, but euen by the same
commandement) not disdaine any labour,
trauell, or industrie which is necessarie
to be imployed, for the wealth
and preseruation of their subiects. But
such Princes as haue not learned out of
Gods lawe to be humble, neither are
led with the meeke spirit of Christ, but

with the proude spirit of Sathan will
either thinke scorne to take paines for
the safetie of their inferiours, or else by
violence oppresse them, and treade
them vnder feete. As though to gouerne
were nothing else but to commaund,
whereas cleane contrariwise,
(as that noble Emperour Theodosius
saide) to gouerne, is to take charge of
the health, wealth, and prosperitie of
other men, which charge is so much
the greater as they are more in number,
which are vnder their gouernment.
And wheras euery man findeth inough
to do to take care for him selfe, and his
owne well being, we see how heauie is
ye burthen of Princes, and them that be
in authoritie, which haue the charge,
and are to prouide for the safetie of so
many, and that with such condition, yt
if any one do perish through their negligence
or misgouernement, his bloud
shall be required at their handes. That
vice therefore by which they are made
vnapt and vnwilling to take so great
a charge vpon them, howe daungerous
it is, Sathan was not ignoraunt,

when he tempted Dauid with pride, as
we may easily see. But all the danger is
not yet expressed. For whereas it is not
possible, that any one person, though
his wisedome, care, and diligence be
neuer so great, should beare the whole
burthen him selfe of any greate gouernement
or kingdome, all good gouernours
haue thought it necessarie to
vse the assistaunce of wise and faithfull
counsel: so that in matters of religion
they would decree nothing
without the aduice of them which are
learned in the worde of GOD: and in
matters of the common wealth, they
would attempt nothing, but by the
counsel of them that are wise in politique
affaires, thinking truely that to
be subiect to wisedome, is to rule most
honourably. But where pride preuayleth
with any Prince, hee will neither
giue eare to the messingers of God yt
shall speake vnto him out of the law of
GOD touching religion, nor followe
the prudent aduice of trustie Counsellours,
which shall informe him in
matters pertayning to the Common

wealth: by which it is not possible that
either the one or the other can be well
ordered and gouerned. Therfore great
is the daunger both vnto the Church
and to the Common wealth: where
the Prince groweth to be insolent and
opinatiue, that alwayes thinking him
selfe to see most clearely in euery matter,
hee disdaineth to be directed after
any counsell or aduice that can be giuen
by any man. And therefore Salomon
saith, seest thou one that is wise in
his owne conceit, there is more hope
of a foole, then of him: and this began
to appeare euen in this example of
Dauid. For when Sathan had stuffed
his minde with a proud desire to know
his forces, hee giueth no eare to Ioab,
that with some reasons sought to dissuade
him from so vaine an enterprise.
Thus presumption causeth Princes to
shut their eares against godly and prudent
aduice of their Counsellours.
And that which is worsse, when pride
hath ouercome the Princes heart, hee
shall hardly finde any that will giue
faithfull and profitable counsell.

For when the Kinges humour is once
perceiued, that he will heare no counsell
which is contrarie to his affection,
fewe or none will aduenture to speake
the truth, which they knowe will purchase
them selues displeasure. So the
King being not defended with faithfull
and trustie Counselours, lyeth open
to clawbacks and flatterers, which
will deuour him whilest hee is aliue
worser then any wilde beastes, which
pray onely vpon deade carcases. You
see the drift of Sathans malice, in prouoking
the Prince to pride, to leaue
him bare of all such necessarie helpes
as he may haue rightly to discharge his
office. But being destitute of all assistaunce
vpon earth, is there any ayde
trowe you to bee looked for out of
heauen? no verily: for by pride the king
maketh him selfe vncapable of that,
whereby all Princes in solemne title
professe that they doe reigne, namely
the grace of GOD, without which
as it is not possible for any Prince
to gouerne well, so no Prince can be
partaker thereof that is thrall to pride,

and enimie to humilitie. For God hath
saide in expresse wordes, that he resisteth
the proude, and giueth grace to
none but such as are humble of heart,
howe then can they prosper which
haue God to their open enimie, which
are voyd of all the grace of God, without
which no King dare affirme, that
he is able to gouerne well? wherefore it
were a good remembraunce for all
Kings and Princes, when so euer they
read or heare their style rehearsed, that
they would be admonished howe necessary
it is for them to be indued with
humilitie, which if they be not, they
may be well assured neuer to partake
of Gods graces, to the good gouernement
of their realmes, and discharge of
their conscience, whatsoeuer they pretend
in their titles. Last of all, the conuersion
from this peryod of pride and
presumption is so daungerous, no lesse
for the state of a Prince, then for the
safetie of euery other person, that the
most wise King Salomon, who well
considered the beginning, proceeding,
and end of al things (which is ye ground

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
of wisedome) doubteth not to affirme
in the I6. of his Prouerbes, that pride
goeth before destruction, and a high
mind before ye fall. This when Sathan
knewe by experience of his owne fall
and destruction, he tempted Dauid to
pride, wherof not only the inconueniences
before rehearsed might insue, but
also the finall ouerthrowe and confusion
of Dauid and his kingdome might
followe. The Lorde which preserued
Dauid, that Sathans malice had no full
effect in him, defendal Christian Princes
from the like temptation, and giue
them true humblenesse of heart, with
all such graces and giftes of his holy
spirite, as are needfull to discharge so
high a calling.
            The thirde and last part I promised
to intreate of, is the frailtie of man,
which in this text is offered to be considered
in two persons. First in the
person of Dauid: and secondly in the
person of Ioab. Concerning Dauid,
I need not to stand long in discouering
his frailtie, not onely at this time, but
at other times also, as it is set foorth in

the Scripture, Howe excellent a man
hee was, and howe plentifully indued
with the graces and giftes of God, how
noble a King, and howe godly a Prophet,
I shall not neede to describe, hee
is sufficiently knowne vnto you: and
yet he is not exempted from the common
fragilitie of men. Hee is highly
commended in the Scriptures, and
his example alledged for a patterne of
all good Kings that followed him, and
yet you see his Chronicle is blotted
with this, &amp; two or three other offences.
Of whose fall we ought to make
this profite to our selues, yt therein we
may see our owne weaknes, and when
we see our owne frailtie in an other
mans faultes, we may be admonished
thereby to pray vnto the Lord for the
continuall &amp; mightie assistaunce of his
holy spirite, yt seeing our weaknes is so
great, we may alwayes finde his grace,
whose power is made perfect in infirmitie
to bee sufficient for vs, so that although
of frailtie wee fall often, yet by
grace wee may alwayes rise againe,
so that wee neuer fall away.
            
               
Finally, we haue need (I say) in respect
of our infirmitie, to pray for strength
earnestly of God: for if Dauid being a
man after Gods owne heart, did but
trip, surely we are readie to fall downe
right, &amp; yet we see yt Dauid did not only
slide out of the way of humane slipprinesse,
but also did fall into some
great and notorious offences. Dauid
therefore was a Saint, but he was no
Angell: it is an Angellike perfection
to doe the wil of God in al things. The
Saintes vpon earth must pray for the
same, and contend to come as neare it
as they can, and by their imperfection
be instructed to humilitie, vntill by the
grace of God in Iesus Christ they be
brought into the same estate of perfection
with the Angels. In the person of
Ioab we haue to consider two thinges,
first the aduice which he giueth: and
secondly his execution of the Kinges
commaundement, Ioab was a man as his
storie declareth, indued with great
courage, and diuers other good qualities▪
&amp; yet not simply to be commended,
for there were great faults in him.

He was a man in whō vertues &amp; vices
were almost equal, such a one as Alcibiades
is discribed of ye Greciās, &amp; Marius
of the Romanes. But his chiefest vertue
was valiancie &amp; courage, yet in his example
he is noted by the holy ghost in
giuing counsel to Dauid to be faint harted
&amp; cowardlik. For first ye holy ghost
testifieth yt he vtterly misliked this interprise
of Dauid, and as a man wel acquainted
with the affaires of ye realme,
and knowing there was not iust cause
why the people should be mustred, he
did easily coniecture yt the kings commaundement
proceaded of vaine prid
and presumption: &amp; therefore hee had
no good will to execute it. In so much
that it is shewed in the booke of Chronicles
that he did performe the Kings
precept negligently, for he not onely
omitted to number the tribe of Leui
for which he might haue some excuse,
because they were addicted to the seruice
of religion, but also he left out the
tribe of Beniamin. The reasō is alledged
because the kinges cōmandement seemed
abhominable vnto him, and as he

did abhorre and detest the kings commandement,
so he shewed diuerse reasōs
of his misliking: for after protestation
of his goodwil &amp; desire of ye kings
honour, in yt he wished the Lord might
increase the people an hundreth times
as many as there were, yt the king might
not suspect him as one that refused to
take paines in his seruice, first he sheweth
that there was no sufficient cause
of this muster, when hee saith, wherefore
doth my lord the king desire this
thing: And againe hee saith are not
they all the seruauntes of my Lord the
king, For one cause of numbring the
people was vsed euen of heathen princes,
that the sublectes thereby should
professe their obedience, but at this
time there was neither suspition of war
abrode, nor rebellion at home. Moreouer
he did also insinuate that the kings
transgression would be ye cause of Gods
punishment to fall vppon the people,
where he saith, and why shoulde this
be an offence or guiltines vnto Israel?
by vsing these reasons to diswade the
king from his euill purpose hee mght

seeme to some men, to haue discharged
the dutie of a trustie and faithfull
counsellour. But the holy Ghoste
noteth him of great frailtie and fainte
hartednes, when he saith, neuertheles
the kinges commaundement preuailed
with Ioab and with the capitaines of
the hoste. The rest seeing the kings humour
held their peace &amp; said nothing
onely Ioab vseth some speach to alter
the kinges minde: but perceiuing with
what affection the king was carried, he
thought it was not best for him in policie
to set himselfe altogether against
the kinges affection, though hee bare
the kinge good will, and wished to
haue him remoued from that vnprofitable
attempt, yet hee durst not aduenture
to incurre the kings displeasure
by doing his duetie throughly, and
discouering ye hidden wound which he
thought was to sore to abide any sharp
medicine, for in such a case as this hee
thoght it was not best to be to earnest
&amp; vehement a persuader &amp; so followed
Machiauils philosophie 2000. yeres
and more before Machiauil was borne.

His cowardnes in this case is rather to
be noted, for that at other times he had
shewed great courage and valiantnes
and giuen such faithful aduise &amp; counsell,
that his example is worthie to bee
followed of all good counsellours. For
in the I9. Chap. of this booke we read
that when Dauid after the slaughter of
Absalom yeelded so much to the naturall
affection of a father, in lamenting
for the death of his vnnatural son,
that he forgot the duetie of a king, whiche
was to encourage and rewarde his
good subiectes for their seruice, in somuch
that when ye people heard what
lamentation hee made for Absalom
they were clean discouraged and came
by stealth into the Citie, more like to
men that had fled from the feelde, thē
such as had obtained so notable a victorie
against the kings enimies. Assone
as Ioab heard thereof hee came boldly
into the kings presence, and with great
courage he did the duetie of a faithfull
counsellour: for he tolde the Kinge of
his fault plainely, and shewed him
the daunger throughly, you haue discouraged

(saith he) the hearts, &amp; made
ashamed the faces of all your faithfull
seruauntes which haue deliuered your
life; and the liues of your wiues, and of
your sonnes and daughters, and haue
established the kingdome this daye in
your hand: you loue thē that hate you
&amp; hate thē that loue you. For you haue
shewed this day that you make no accompte
neither of your princes, nor of
your people. For I perceiue if Absalom
had liued, and all wee had beene slaine
this day, you woulde haue beene well
pleased with it. But nowe I aduise you
leaue your mourning and goeforth &amp;
speake comfortably vnto the people,
or else I sweare vnto you by the Lord,
you will vtterly alienate the minds of
your subiectes from you. So that you
shal not haue one man tarrie with you
this night. And this affliction shall bee
greater then all the troubles and daungers
you haue susteined euen frō your
youth. Wherevpon Dauid arose, and
went &amp; encouraged his souldiers, so ye
kingdom was established in his hands.
you se how roughly &amp; effectually Ioab
               
dealt with the king in that case. But at
this time he is noted to haue dealt faint
lie and timerously. For although hee
apposed some reason against the kings
vnlawfull desire, yet hee did it with a
weake arme and so of frailtie fayled of
his duetie. Concerning the execution
of the kinges commaundemente there
is some controuersie. Whether Ioab
shoulde haue obeyed the kinges precept,
when he knewe it proceeded frō
an euill affection. The time will not
serue me to discusse the reasōs on both
the sides: therfore I will speake of the
case briefly and generally. If the prince
commaund any thing to be done whiche
of it selfe is vnlawefull and
against the commandement of God;
that commandement of any subiecte
is not to be excuted, for we are so boūd
to obey earthly princes, that we disobey
not the God of heauen &amp; earth, &amp;
therfore Ioab shold haue suffered death
rather then to haue obeyed Dauids cō
               maundement
in betraying &amp; murdering
of Vrias with ye sword of ye Amonites,
which was a faithfull subiect &amp;

a valiant captaine, I say he should haue
suffered death rather then to haue executed
such a commandement: because
ye fact was altogether vngodly &amp; vnlawfull
of his owne nature. But in this
case where the fact of his owne nature
was indifferent and lawfull of it selfe,
as to number the people in some cases
is not onely lawfull but also necessarie.
If Ioab had done his duetie
throughly in admonishing the king of
his corrupte affection and of the vengeance
of GOD like to ensue if hee
proceeded therein, and that when hee
had done all that he could &amp; ought to
haue done to disswade him, his aduice
woulde take no place, but the kinge
would stil vrge his commandement, &amp;
enforce Ioabs obediēce, I see no cause,
but yt he might haue executed ye kings
cōmandemēt: the conclusiō of ye whole
matter, because I see ye time is past, &amp; I
would be looth to abuse your honorable
patience too long, in few wordes is
this. The iustice of God is set foorth
to this ende, that wee might bee affraide
by sinne to prouoke his wrath,

the malice of Sathan is described, that
we might be carefull to beware of it
and by faith to withstande it, the frailtie
of man is shewed, that seeing our
weakenesse wee might bee humbled
thereby, and taught to seeke for
strength only at the hands of GOD,
whose grace through our Lorde Iesus
Christ shall bee sufficient for vs, To
whome with the holy Ghost one
eternall and euerlasting God
bee all honour and glory
wolde without end.
            Amen.
            
         
      
   

