
   
      
         
            The end and confession of Iohn Felton who suffred in Paules Churcheyeard in London, the. viii. of August, for high treason. 1570.
            F. G., fl. 1570.
         
         
            
               1570
            
         
         Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01373
            STC 11493
            ESTC S121825
            99856987
            99856987
            22644
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01373)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22644)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 384:13)
         
         
            
               
                  The end and confession of Iohn Felton who suffred in Paules Churcheyeard in London, the. viii. of August, for high treason. 1570.
                  F. G., fl. 1570.
               
               1 sheet ([1] p.)   
               
                  In Fleetstreete, by VVilliam Hovv: for William Pickering: and are to be solde at his shop at S. Magnus corner,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  [1570]
               
               
                  Signed: (q[uod]) F.G.
                  Verse - "Eche man desiers to haue reporte,".
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Felton, John, d. 1570 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-12
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-01
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2007-01
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2007-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            The end and Confeſſion of John Felton who ſuffred in Paules Churcheyeard in London, the .viii. of Auguſt, for high Treaſon. 1570.
            EChe man deſiers to haue reporte,
            of newes both ſtrange and rare:
            And couits for to know thoſe thinges,
            whereby they may be ware.
            For to avoyde thoſe doynges greate,
            that might on them befall:
            For by example are they taught to do,
            and what they ſhall
            Receiue for their malicious mindes,
            and wicked Treaſons greate:
            As now of late it hath been ſeen
            through Iuſtice iudgements ſeate.
            That holdes the ſworde to do the right,
            and ſtrike where blowes ſhould fall:
            And puniſh for their wicked liues,
            eche one whom ſhe doth call.
            The poore, the ritche, the learnd, ye wiſe
            the begger and the ſnudge:
            The Kynge ſomtime too hath it felt,
            aſwell as hath the drudge.
            Wherefore be lawes decreed and made
            but for to puniſh thoſe,
            That will not by theyr Prince be rewld
            but ſeemes to be theyr foes.
            As now is ſeene by Felton lo,
            that lately here did die,
            In Paules Churchyarde he left his life,
            on Galows taule and hie.
            Who from the priſon where he lay,
            was drawne on Hardell there:
            For good example of all ſuch,
            that they might take the feare.
            For to beware of ſuche like facte,
            as well in worde as deede:
            Leaſt they for theyr like hier at laſt
            no better like to ſpeede.
            * Now marke his ende and what I ſhall
            reporte here of his death:
            For why theſe eares of mine did here,
            and iyes while that his breath
            Remained in his wicked corps,
            which ſtubbornly did die:
            As one me thought ſomthing beſt raught
            through Treaſons crueltie.
            His Gowne of Grograin he put of,
            which on his backe he had:
            And eke his Doublet which was made
            of Sattin ſomwhat ſad.
            Into his Shirte he then was ſtript,
            and vp the Ladder he
            Did mount, for to receaue that death,
            that eche man there might ſe.
            Theſe wordes he ſpake, and ſaid alowde
            my Maiſters all and ſome:
            One thinge I haue to ſay to you,
            now that I here am come.
            That is, I pray you all with me
            beare recorde what I ſay:
            I here proteſt before you all
            , this preſent dieyng day,
            That I was neuer Traytour ſure,
            nor Treaſon to my Queene
            Did neuer do, nor neuer thought,
            that euer hath been ſeene.
            And for the facte wherefore I die,
            I can it not denie:
            But at the Gate where as the Bull
            was hanged, there was I,
            In company, on more with me,
            did hange it vp together:
            And though in place, I had not bin,
            it had not ſcaped euer.
            From hanging vp, for ſuredly,
            for that ſame preſent day:
            It had bin hanged, in that place,
            though I had been away.
            Then ſayde the Shreue, vnto him,
            Oh Felton do remember:
            That thou haſt bin, a Traytour great
            and to the Queene offender.
            And ſurely thou moſte Trayterouſly,
            and ſtubbornly haſt thou ſought,
            The beſt thou couldſt to go aboute,
            thy Prince to bringe to nought.
            And eke the Realme and all the reſt,
            as mutche as in thee lay,
            Thou ſoughſt by thy Traiterous harte,
            to bringe vnto decay.
            Therfore call vnto God the Lord,
            and pray him from thy hart:
            That he receaue thy ſoule to reſt,
            when thou from hence ſhalt part.
            Well ſo I do, and here I craue,
            you all good people pray
            For me, that ready is to dye,
            and then began to ſay,
            Into thy hands, Oh Lord my God,
            I yeeld my Soule and Breath:
            For thou haſt me redeemd, I ſay,
            with thy moſt precious death.
            
               In manus tuas Domine,
            
            and ſo the reſt he ſayde,
            The Hangman then did throwe him of,
            and ſo his breath was ſtaide.
            He hanged theare vpon the Tree,
            and in a litle ſpace:
            They cut him downe incontinent,
            that Iuſtice might take place.
            Wher as he quartred ſhoulde be,
            according to the Lawe:
            And to the Iudgement that he had,
            to make thoſe ſtande in awe.
            That be of his affinitie:
            and ſurely there be ſome,
            That thinkes that he deſerude not death
            in all that he hath don.
            He then diſmembred was ſtraight way,
            when he had ended that:
            His Belly ripped open wide,
            his Bowels all he gat.
            And to the fire he ſtraight them threwe,
            which ready there was made:
            And there conſumed all to duſt,
            as is the fiers trade.
            His Head cut of, the Hangman then,
            did take it vp in hand:
            And vp alofte he did it ſhowe,
            to all that there did ſtand.
            And then his body in Fowre partes,
            was quartred in that place:
            More pitty that his Traytorous Hart,
            could take no better grace.
            And thus he had his iuſt deſarte,
            as well he had deſerued:
            I would the reſt that not repents,
            were likewiſe alſo ſerued.
            Beware you Papiſts all beware,
            be true vnto your Queene:
            Let not your Traiterous hartes be bent
            as here tofore hath been.
            Stand not againſt the liuing God,
            ſpurne not againſt his Law:
            Kicke not againſt the Pricke I ſay,
            but haue him ſtill in awe.
            Be not aſhamde to torne in time,
            ſet ſhamefaſtneſſe aſide:
            No ſhame it is to turne to God,
            though you haue gon far wide,
            The farther you haue gon aſtray,
            and wicked wayes hath led,
            The erneſter you ſhould returne,
            from that moſt wicked Bed,
            Wherin you lay a ſleape long while,
            forgetting of his grace:
            Now call the refore vnto the Lord,
            to ſet you in that place,
            Where you may haue eternall reſt,
            and liue in heauen hie:
            And reſt in Abrahams boſome too,
            when that you needes muſt dye.
            And for that grace that God may geue,
            as I haue ſayde before:
            I humbly pray continually,
            both now and euermore.
            Our Prince, our Queene Elizabeth,
            a happy ſtate to haue:
            Let vs all pray with one accord,
            her noble grace to ſaue.
            And hir to keepe from all hir foes,
            and ſheild eternally:
            From wicked wights that go about,
            to ſéeke continually:
            Hir whole decay: the Lord defend,
            hir noble royall hart:
            From yeelding to thoſe Foes of hirs,
            that daily plaies their parte.
            For to be reeue her of her right,
            and of hir ſtately Crowne:
            All thoſe (I ſay) that ſo doth ſeke,
            God ſhortly throw them downe.
            Thus here I end, and once againe,
            the liuing God I pray:
            Our noble Quéene Elizabeth,
            preſerue both night and day.
            
               (ꝙ) F. G.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            ¶ Imprinted at London, in Fleetſtreete, by VVilliam Hovv: for William Pickering: and are to be ſolde at his ſhop at S. Magnus corner.
         
      
   

