
   
      
         
            A supplication to Eldertonne, for Leaches vnlewdnes desiring him to pardone, his manifest vnrudenes.
            Fulwood, William.
         
         
            
               1562
            
         
         Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01363
            STC 11486
            ESTC S121820
            99856982
            99856982
            22639
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01363)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22639)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1172:11)
         
         
            
               
                  A supplication to Eldertonne, for Leaches vnlewdnes desiring him to pardone, his manifest vnrudenes.
                  Fulwood, William.
               
               1 sheet ([1] p.)   
               
                  At the long shop adioining vnto Saint Mildreds Church in the Pultry by Iohn Alde,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  [1562?]
               
               
                  Signed: q[uod]. Willyam Fulwod.
                  Verse - "Good gentle maister Eldertonne,".
                  Publication date conjectured by STC.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Elderton, William, d. 1592? --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-01
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-01
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-02
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2007-02
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            ¶ 
A Supplication to Eldertonne, for Leaches vnlewdnes:
               Deſiring him to pardone, his manifeſt vnrudenes.
            
            
               
                  GOod gentle maiſter Eldertonne,
               may I not you intrete?
               To pardō Leache yt he hath dōne,
               and not with him to frete?
            
            
               For I confeſſe and know the ſame,
               It was for lack of lewdnes:
               That he ſo blaſde abrode your name,
               therfore forgiue his rudenes.
            
            
               For you maye ſee he is in deed,
               an vnrude ſimple man:
               Therfore of him take you no heed,
               ſithe nurture none he can.
            
            
               A ſeely ſimple man hee is,
               as proof may well be made:
               For nomore wit he hath ywis,
               but to call a ſpade, a ſpade.
            
            
               Therefore though that your filthy rymes,
               he filthy name to bee:
               Accuſe him not I ſay of crimes,
               you heare his qualitie.
            
            
               It was no doubt vnhomely donne,
               to chalenge in ſuch caſe:
               So fyne a felow as Eldertonne,
               that hath ſo fayre a face.
            
            
               But though your face be neuer ſo riche,
               ſo precious or ſo gay:
               Yet wil he ſcratche it if it itche,
               the paines for to delay.
            
            
               Wherfore you ought him thankes to geue,
               that worketh you ſuche good:
               And not to ſhake him by the ſleeue,
               to wreke your angry moode.
            
            
               I may wel muſe and meruel much,
               what might be your intent:
               Sith that you proue your ſelfe one ſuch,
               as truthe cannot content.
            
            
               You ſhowe that Leache you doo contemne,
               euen by the ſelf ſame reed:
               Wherin you doo your ſelf condemne,
               I wiſhe you wolde take heed.
            
            
               You binde it vp with othes inow,
               in faith, in faith, ſaye yee:
               But by ſuch frutes a man may know,
               the goodnes of the tree.
            
            
               A ſhame it is that you ſhould bring,
               the rample of Chriſt I ſay:
               And eke forthwith the ſelf ſame thing,
               ſo ſore to diſobey.
            
            
               For with the breache of charitie,
               you doo him ſharply charge:
               And by and by outragiouſly,
               you raile on him at large.
            
            
               Thus Sathan alſo for his turne,
               the ſcriptures can out pike:
               And as you wel his leſſon learne,
               ſo are your deedes a like.
            
            
               Your harte is vaine and bent to euill,
               your toung alſo is naught:
               How can it be then but the deuil,
               muſt rule both toung and thought.
            
            
               But hereby men may eaſely ſpie,
               how you doo Leache abuſe:
               Sith that your quarell for to trie,
               by ſcripture you refuſe.
            
            
               Therfore you go about I ſee,
               the ſcripture ſet aparte:
               Vnto your toies and vanitie,
               his penne for to conuart.
            
            
               And if in deed you could him cauſe,
               from ſcripture for to flie:
               No doubt for ſoth but clauſe by clauſe,
               much brauery ſhould we ſee.
            
            
               Then wolde you leke then wold you laffe,
               as you doo make reporte:
               Then wold you anſwere euery ſtaffe,
               and that in ſugred ſorte.
            
            
               In ſugred ſorte? nay poiſened then,
               I might it better call:
               Although it ſugred ſemes to men,
               which are in ſinfull thrall.
            
            
               A worthy worke it is doubtles,
               and ful of lerned ſkill:
               Wherby appeareth your ſhameles,
               and wilful wicked will.
            
            
               And where you write that ſecretly,
               your fault he ſhould haue tolde;
               That might not be ſith openly,
               your ſelfe did it vpholde.
            
            
               And where as he ful ſkilfully,
               takes ſcriptures for his ſtaie:
               You ſay in deed that wickedly,
               he vſeth them alwaie.
            
            
               It is not ſtreight way proued ſo,
               when that you haue it ſaid:
               Except you bring a profe therto,
               which cannot be denaid.
            
            
               As if, that I ſhould ſay in deed,
               you were an honeſt man:
               All wiſe men might me then deride,
               ſith proue it not I can.
            
            
               I wolde now wiſhe you ſhould forget,
               his ſcience to deface:
               For honeſtly a man may get,
               his liuing in that race.
            
            
               Muche better then the witte to ſpend,
               a Paraſite to play:
               The bad to pleaſe, the good to offend,
               and play the foole all day.
            
            
               And him me thinkes you ſhould not blame,
               that can wel ſhape a hoſe:
               For he may likewiſe cut and frame,
               a caſe for your riche noſe.
            
            
               To make a hoſe is no ſuche ſhame,
               to Leache in his degree:
               As is your noſe a glorious fame,
               vppon your face to ſee.
            
            
               It doth become you very ill,
               to talke ſo of your taile:
               But you ſhal there your toung hold ſtill,
               as fitte for tounges that raile.
            
            
               And if you ſtill thus doo deny,
               your knauerie to forbeare:
               You ſhal therin haue victory,
               the garland you ſhall weare.
            
            
               But heere I muſt ful ſore lament,
               the counſel you ſtill geue:
               To your vile Jone, not to repent,
               but beaſtly ſtill to liue.
            
            
               O wicked man darſte thou be bolde,
               ſuche ſinful ſeed to ſowe?
               And eke the ſame for to vpholde,
               in ſinful hartes to growe?
            
            
               Oh Lord ſhal whoredom thus preuaile?
               ſhal men thus ſinne mainteine?
               Is this a chriſten common weale,
               and can ſuch filth ſuſteine?
            
            
               O magiſtrates play Phinehes parte,
               towardes ſuche be not to milde:
               Which may procure moſt greuous ſmart,
               to many a mothers childe.
            
            
               The whoredom of one heretofore,
               Great plagues to many hath brought:
               Although the lord eftſones therfore,
               in him repentance wrought.
            
            
               What ſhal our lot be then Oh Lord?
               which foſter ſuche foule ſwine:
               As liue a life to bee abhorde,
               yet glory and ioye therein?
            
            
               Repent (O wretche) and cal for grace,
               leaue of theſe wicked toyes:
               Leſt Sathan reache thee ſower ſauce,
               to theſe thy pleaſant ioyes.
            
            
               Now ſir, if Leache, as you doe tell,
               ſemes fondly thinges to knit:
               It is becauſe you cannot well,
               them home with reaſon hit.
            
            
               A homely cloke wold ſerue full wel,
               is there none to be had?
               If Eldertonne of none heare tell,
               I doubt he will goe mad.
            
            
               But if as you doo threaten, ſo
               you fall for to bee wood:
               You ſhall ſtreight waies to Bedlem go,
               to tame your madding mood.
            
            
               Now Eldertonne I muſt deſire,
               you to hold Leache excuſde:
               For that no reaſon doth appeere,
               why he ſhuld ſo be vſde.
            
            
               And ſith that I thus curteouſly,
               for Leache doo you intreat:
               Your phrenſie ſo to ſatiſfy,
               you need no more to freat.
            
            
               Wherfore gentle Maiſte Elderton,
               as I may doo you pleaſure:
               Graunt this my ſupplication,
               which is not out of meaſure.
            
            
               And thus ſubſcribed,
               The firſt day of June:
               At which time you ſaid,
               Beginneth your fume.
            
            
               ꝙ. Willyam Fulwod.
            
         
      
      
         
            ¶ Imprinted at London at the Long ſhop adioining vnto Saint Mildreds Church in the Pultry by John Alde.
         
      
   

