
   
      
         
            Davids hainous sinne. Heartie repentance. Heavie punishment. By Thomas Fuller Master of Arts of Sidnye Colledge in Cambridge
            Fuller, Thomas, 1608-1661.
         
         
            
               1631
            
         
         Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01341
            STC 11463
            ESTC S102822
            99838584
            99838584
            2968
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01341)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2968)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 887:16)
         
         
            
               
                  Davids hainous sinne. Heartie repentance. Heavie punishment. By Thomas Fuller Master of Arts of Sidnye Colledge in Cambridge
                  Fuller, Thomas, 1608-1661.
               
               [80] p.   
               
                  Printed by Tho. Cotes, for Iohn Bellamie, dwelling at the three Golden Lyons in Cornehill,
                  London :
                  1631.
               
               
                  The words "hainous .. punishment." are bracketed together on the title page.
                  In verse.
                  Signatures: A-E.
                  The last leaf is blank.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               David, --  King of Israel --  Poetry.
            
         
      
      
         
            2002-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2002-10
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2002-11
            Judith SiefringSampled and proofread
         
            2002-11
            Judith SiefringText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2002-12
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            DAVIDS 
                  HAINOVS SINNE.
                  HEARTIE Repentance.
                  HEAVIE Punishment.
               
            
            
               EXODVS 35. 23.
               And every man, with whom was found—Goates

                     •
                  aire, and red skins of Rammes, and Badgers skins,

                     •
                  rought them. [to the building of the Tabernacle]
            
            
               Ad Zoilum.
               Thy Laies thou vtt'rest not, yet carpest mine,
               Carpe mine no longer, or else utter thine.
            
            By THOMAS FVLLER Master of Arts of Sidnye
Colledge in Cambridge.
            
            
               LONDON,
Printed by Tho. Cotes, for Iohn Bellamie, dwelling at the
three Golden Lyons in Cornehill. 1631.
         
         
            
            
            To the Honorable Mr. Edwar
                  •
               
Mr. William, and Mr. Christopher Montagu,
Sonnes to the Right Honorable,
Edward Lord Montagu,
of Boughton.
            
               FAire Branches of a Stock as faire
               Each a sonne, and each an heire:
               Two Ioseph-like, from Sire so sage,
               Sprung in Autumne of his age;
               But a Benjamin the other,
               Gain'd with losing of his Mother.
               This fruit of some spare hours I spent
               To your Honours I present.
            
            
               A King I for my subiect have,
               And Noble Patrons well may cra
                     •••
                  
               
               Things tripartite are fit for three,
               With Youths, things youthful best 
                     〈◊〉
                  
               
               Take thē therfore in good part,
               Of him that ever prayeth in heart,
               That as in height ye waxe apace,
               Your Soules may higher grow 
                     〈◊〉
                  
               
            
            
               Whilst your Father (like the greene
               Eagle in his Scutcheon seene,
               Which with bill his age doth cast)
               May longer still and longer last:
               To see your Vertues o're increase
               Your Yeares, ere he departs in Peace.
               Thus I my Booke, to make an end,
               To You: and you to God commend.
            
            
               Your Honours  in all service
Tho. Fuller.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            DAVIDS Hainous Sinne.
            
               1.
               
                  HOw Zions Psalmist grieuously offended,
               How Israels Harper did most foulely slide,
               Yet how that Psalmist penitent amended,
               And how tha
                     •
                   Harper patient did abide
               Deserved chastisement, (so fitly stil'd,
               Which wrath inflicted not, but love most mild,
               Not for to hurt, but heale a wanton child.)
            
            
               2.
               How one by her owne Brother was defiled;
               And how that Brother by a Brother slaine;
               And how a Fa
                     •
                  her, by his Sonne ex
                     •
                  led:
               And by a Subject, how a Soveraigne:
               How Peace procured after Battels fierce,
               As Sol at length doth sullen cloudes dispierce;
               My Muse intends the subject of her Verse.
            
            
               
               3.
               Great God of might, whose power most Soveraigne,
               D
                     •
                  pends of none, yet all of thee depend,
               Time cannot measure, neither place containe,
               Nor wit of man thy Being comprehend:
               For whil'st I thinke on Three, I am confin'd
               To One, and when I One conceive in minde
               I am recal'd to Three, in One combin'd.
            
            
               4.
               Thy helpe I crave, thy furtherance I aske,
               My head, my heart, my hand direct and guide,
               That whilst I vndertake this weighty taske,
               I from thy written lore start not aside:
               Alas, 'tis nothing Lord with thee to breake
               The strong, 'tis nothing to support the weake,
               To make men dumbe, to make an Infant speake.
            
            
               
               5
               EAch one begotten by immortall seed,
               Becomes the pitcht feild of two deadly foes,
               Spirit and Flesh, these never are agreed,
               With trucelesse warre each other doth oppose;
               And though the Spirit oft the Flesh doth quell,
               It may subdue but can it not expell,
               So stoutly doth the Iebusite rebell.
            
            
               6
               Now David when on Bathsheba loose eyes
               He fixt, his heavenly halfe did him disswade;
               Turne, turne away thy sight from vanities,
               Exchange thy object, else thou wilt be made
               Vnmindfull of thy Soule, her corps to minde,
               Made for to lose the truth, such toyes to finde,
               By looking long, made at the last, starke bli
                     •
                  de.
            
            
               
               7.
               What though her face, and body be most faire,
               Behold, the Sun her beauty doth surpass;
               His golden beames surmount her yellow hayre,
               As far as purest Cristall, dyrtie glasse:
               Her skinne, as is the skie, not halfe so cleare,
               Her curious v
                     •
                  ines, for colour come not neare
               Those azure streaks, that in the Heavens appeare,
            
            
               8.
               There let thy hungry sight her famine feede,
               Whereon it cannot surfet with excesse:
               Whil'st tongue, heart, harp are tuned vp with speed,
               The grand-contrivers glory to expresse:
               Framing with words, to rayse his mighty name,
               That with a mighty word, did rayse this frame,
               And by his providence preserves the same.
            
            
               
               9.
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   let no lustfull thoughts lodge in thy minde,
               
                  
                     ••
                  fore that they be borne, they must be kill'd,
               Or else the man is cruell that is kinde,
               To spare the foes, wherewith his Soule is spill'd▪
               
               And if a wanton motion may request,
               Leave for to lodge a limbe, th'incroaching guest,
               Will soone command roome to receive the rest.
            
            
               10.
               Looke towards the midday Sun, and thou shalt see,
               A littleThe Tower of Eder, nigh Bethlē, 7. miles from Ier
                           •
                        sale
                           •
                        .
                   tower, o're topps of hills to peepe;
               That is the birth place of thy pedygree:
               Full oft there hast thou fed thy fathers sheepe,
               And kept his flockes vpon the flowry plaine.
               But now the Sheepe-hook of a country swaine,
               Is turn'd the Scepter of of a Soveraigne.
            
            
               
               11
               God made thee great, oh doe not him disgrace,
               And by his weighty Statutes lightly set,
               Hee honour'd thee, oh doe not him debase,
               Hee thee remembred, doe not him forget:
               Why should fatDeut. 32. 15. Ieshurun so wanton grow,
               As at his Maisters head, his heeles to throw?
               Maister; that all his feeding did bestow.
            
            
               12
               Behold high Cedars in the valley set,
               They in thy eyes like little shrubbs doe show,
               Whil'st little shrubbs vpon mount Oliuet,
               Seeme lofty Cedars; men whose states are low
               Their sinnes are not so obvious to sense,
               In Princes persons of great eminence,
               A smaller fault doth seem
                     •
                   a great offence.
            
            
               
               13
               But grant, no man thy wickednes espies,
               Surely the Searcher of the reines doth marke
               Even infant luft, can figg-leaves bleare his eyes?
               Or can thy shame bee shrowded in the darke?
               Darknes shall then be turned into light,
               Yea Darknes, is no Darknes, in his sight,
               But seeme the same to him, both day and night.
            
            
               14
               The Spirit had resolved more to speake,
               But her halfe-spoken words, the Flesh confounds,
               Nor wonder is it, she so vs'd to breake
               Gods Lawes, not passing for to passe their bound
                     •
                  ,
               Against mans rules of manners should offend,
               Which now impatient longer to attend,
               Began before her Rivall made an end.
            
            
               
               15.
               If euer Nature la
                     •
                  ishly did throw
               Her gifts on one, which might haue served more,
               Yet make them comely, if shee e're did show,
               The prime, and pri
                     •
                  e, and plenty of her store.
               Loe, there's the forme wherein she hath exprest
               Her utmost power, and done the very best,
               Her maister-peece surpassing all the rest.
            
            
               16.
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   if 
                     •
                  hose carelesse tresses were attired?
               Sure then her face for comelines tra
                     •
                   scends,
               What now seemes lovely, then wo
                     •
                  ld be admired▪
               
               If Art might but begin, where Nature ends.
               Alas, ten thousand pitties 'tis indeed,
               That Princes, on so common fare should feed,
               Whilst Common men, on princely meat exceed.
            
            
               
               17.
               Alwayes the same doth glut the appetite,
               But pleased is our palate, with exchange,
               Variety of dishes doth delight,
               Then give thy loose affections leave to range:
               Forbidden things are best, and when we eate
               What we have slily gotten by deceit,
               Those morsels onely make the daynty meate.
            
            
               18.
               But oh, reserve thy selfe, my maiden Muse,
               For a more modest subject, and forbeare
               To tune such wanton toyes, as may abuse,
               And give distaste vnto a Virgins eare:
               Such rotten reasons first from Hell did flow,
               And thither let the same in silence goe,
               Best knowne of them, that did them never know.
            
            
               
               19
               Thus hee that conquer'd men, and beast most cruell,
               (Whose greedy pawes, with fellon goods were found)
               Answer'd Goliah's challenge in a duell,
               And layd the Giant groveling on the ground:
               He, that of Philistims, two hundred slue:
               No whit appalled at their grisly hue,
               Him one frayle womans beauty did subdue.
            
            
               20
               Man is a Shippe, affections the Sayle,
               The world the Sea, our sinnes the Rocks and Shelves,
               God is the Pylot, if hee please to sayle,
               And leave the stearing of us, to our selves,
               Against the ragged Rocks wee run amaine,
               Or else the winding Shelves doe us detaine,
               Till God the Palinure, returnes againe.
            
            
               
               21
               YEt Da
                        •
                     id bold to sinne, did 
                     •
                  eare the shame,
               He shunn'd the sheath, that ran upon the knife,
               With a fine fetch, providing for his fame,
               
                  
                     •
                  ee fetcheth home Vriah to his wife:
               So under his chaste love, to cloake his owne
               Vnlawfull lust, to fault most carelesse growne,
               Most carefull that his fault should not be knowne.
            
            
               22
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   in their plots, God doth befoole the wise,
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   wayes that none can trace, all must admire:
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   of his house that nigh Vriah lyes,
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  David so came short of his desire:
               The man a nearer l
                     •
                  dging place did use,
               (Which made the King on further plots to muse)
               And sent home, home to goe, did thus refuse.
            
            
               
               23.
               The pilgrime Arke doth so journe in a tent,
               In open fields, Ioab my Lord dothlye,
               And all the souldiers of his Regiment,
               Have Earth their beds, the Heaven their Canopy:
               Where bitter blasts of stormy winds are rife.
               Shall I goe feast, drink, dally with my wife?
               Not, as I live, and by your Lordships life.
            
            
               24.
               Then by his servants David did conspire,
               
                  Vriahs lust so dull, with wine to edg
                     •
                  :
               (Venus doth freeze, where Bacchus yeelds no fire)
               By their constraint, he condescends to pledge
               One common cup that was begun to all
               Captaines incamped nigh to Rabba wall;
               O
                     •
                  e specially, vnto the Generall.
            
            
               
               25
               
                  Abishay next is drunke to, Ioabs brother,
               And this cupp, to a second paves the way,
               That orderly doth vsher in another;
               Thus wine once walking, knowes not where to stay▪
               
               Yea such a course methodicall they take,
               In ordering of cupps, the same did make
               
                  Vriah quite, all order to forsake.
            
            
               26
               His false supporters soone begin to slipp,
               And if his faltring tongue, doth chance to light
               On some long word, hee speedily doth clip
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   traine therof; yea his deceitfull sight,
               All obiects paired doth present to him:
               As double faces, both obscure and dim▪
               
               Seeme in a lying looking-glasse to swim.
            
            
               
               27.
               My prayers for friends prosperity, and wealth,
               Shall ne're be wanting, but if I refuse;
               To hurt my selfe, by drinking others health,
               Oh let ingenious natures mee excuse:
               If men bad manners this esteeme, then I
               Desire to be esteem'd unmannerly,
               That to liue well, will suffer wine to dye.
            
            
               28.
               Well did blind Homer see, for to expresse
               This vice, that spawnes all other; when he faines,
               Dame Circe, an inchanting Sorceresse,
               Who
                     •
                  e cupps, made many men forgoe their braines▪
               
               Whilst with the witlesse Asse, one purely doats,
               Others mishaped are, like lustfull Goates,
               Or swil-ingrossing Swine, with greedy throats.
            
            
               
               29
               Though bad, yet better was Vriah left,
               Not quite a beast, though 
                     〈◊〉
                   a man, disturb'd
               In minde, but not distracted, nor bereft
               Of witt, though 
                     〈◊〉
                  , yet sob
                     ••
                  ly h
                     •
                  e curb'd
               His lust, being wise, though ignorant, to crosse
               The Kings designes, who now new thoughts doth tosse,
               Finding his former project at a losse.
            
            
               30.
               The Night with mourning weeds, the world be
                     •
                  ladd,
               When re
                     •
                  tlesse David, for to mend his matter,
               Did make it worse; his na
                     •
                  ed sinne was bad,
               More Monstrous being mas
                     •
                  t; they oft doe scatter
               The chayne, that of Gods lawes vnloose a linke:
               Hee swam before in sinne, nigh to the briuke,
               But now he meanes in midst thereof to sinke.
            
            
               
               31
               Then for a light, hee speedily did call,
               (Thou Dark
                     •
                  es with his project best agree'd)
               For paper, pen, and inke, to write withall,
               Though sure a poniard, might have done the deed,
               Better if hee in blood had dipped it,
               And on a sheet of paper what he writ,
               A winding sheet far better did befit.
            
            
               32
               This certs I know, as Sepian juice did sinke
               Into his spongy paper, sabling o're
               The same, with various-formed specks of inke,
               Which was so pure and lilly-white before:
               So spots of sinne the writers soule did staine,
               Whose so ylie tincture did therein remaine
               Till brinish teares had washt it out againe.
            
            
               
               33
               Next day, when day was scarce an infant growne,
               
                  Vriah, (that no mischiefe did mistrust,
               As none hee did deserve, but by his owne
               Did measure all mens dealings to bee just)
               Bearing this letter, on his journey past
               With speed, who needed not to make such hast
               Whose death, had he gone slow, did come too fast.
            
            
               34
               Thus crafty Maisters, when they minde to beate
               A ca
                     •
                  elesse boy, to gather birch they send him;
               
                  
                     •
                  he little lad, doth make the rod compleat,
               
                  
                     •
                  hinking his Maister therefore will commend him:
               B
                     •
                  t busily imploy'd, he little t
                     •
                  ough
                     •
                  ,
               Hee made the net, wherein himselfe was caugh
                     •
                  
               
               And must be b
                     ••
                  ten, with the birch hee brought.
            
            
               
               35.
               His journey came well to the welcome end,
               Safe to the
                     Rabba, 2 Sam. 12. &amp; 27. Towne of Waters hee attaines,
               Towne which to force, Ioab his force did bend,
               (Nought is so hard, but vincible by paines)
               Some with their heads did plot, some with 
                     〈◊〉
                  
               
               Did practise, yea as ready was the band
               To serve, as was the Captaine to command.
            
            
               36.
               So busie Bees, some fly abroad at large,
               Of f
                     •
                  owry Nectar for to fetch their fill,
               Some stay at home, for to receive their charge,
               And 
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     •
                  stily, the liquor doe distill:
               Or bottle it in waxe, whilst others strive,
               Like 
                     ••
                  urdy Martialls, far away to drive
               The drowsy Droanes, that harbour in the hiue.
            
            
               
               37
               The strong-arm'd Archer, from his crooked Bow,
               Made a strait shaft, with dismall newes to speed
               Into the towne which ne're return'd to show,
               The sender, how his message did succeed:
               Yea heavie bodies, mounted were on high,
               Dull ston
                     •
                  s, to which Dame Nature did deny
               Feet
                     •
                   for to goe, Art made them wings to fly.
            
            
               38
               Whilst i
                     •
                   the towne, one with his friend did talk,
               A sudden stroake did take his tongue away,
               Some had their leggs arrested, as they walke,
               By Martiall law, commanding them to stay:
               Here falls a massy beame, a mighty wall
               Comes tumbling there, and many men doth ma
                     •
                  le,
               Who were both slaine, and buried by the fall.
            
            
               
               39.
               Were there not vsed in the dayes of yore,
               Enough men-murdering Engines
                     •
                   But our age,
               Witty in wickednes, must make them more,
               By new found plotts, mens malice to inrage:
               So that fire-spitting Canons, to the cost
               Of Christian blood, all valour have ingrost.
               Whose finding, makes that many a life is lost.
            
            
               40.
               Whilst thus the well appointed array sought,
               Winding in worm-like trenches neare the wall,
               To humble the proud towers, Vriah brought
               The speaking paper to the Generall.
               Who when such language hee therein did finde,
               H
                     •
                  e thought himselfe, or els the king was blinde,
               Himselfe in body, or the king in minde.
            
            
               
               41
               Then hee the letter did peruse againe,
               The words, the words of David could not bee,
               And yet the hand, for Da
                        •
                     ids hand was plaine,
               Hee thought it was, and thought it was not hee:
               Each little line, he thorowly did view,
               Till at the length, more credulous he grew,
               And what he thought was false, he found too tr
                     •
                  e.
            
            
               42
               Now Ioab let thy valour be display'd,
               Act not a midwife, to a deed vnjust,
               
                  
                     •
                  y feare or fauour, be not ouersway'd,
               
                  
                     •
                  o proue a Pandar, to a Princes lust;
               Returne a humble answer back againe,
               Let each word breath submission, to obtai
                     ••
                  
               
               By prayers, a conquest of thy Soueraigne.
            
            
               
               43.
               Shew how when God and countries good requires,
               Then substance, soule and body to ingage,
               Is the ambition of thy best desires,
               Foes forraine to resist, to quell their rage,
               How willingly would'st thou thy selfe despise,
               Count losing of thy goods, a gainfull prize,
               Lavish thy blood, and thy life sacrifice?
            
            
               44
               But when Gods lore, directly doth withstand,
               And where his lawes, the contrary convince,
               Wee must not breake the heauenly kings command,
               Whilst we do seeke to please an earthly Prince:
               The burdens they impose on us to beare,
               Our dutie is to suffer them; but where
               Kings bid, a
                     •
                  d God forbids, we must forbeare.
            
            
               
               45
               Behold the man, whose valour o
                     •
                  ce surmoun
                     •
                  ed
               In sacking Zions mount, (mount not so high
               As men therein were ha
                     •
                  ghty) and accounted,
               Of Worthies chiefe, doth most unworthily:
               He
                     •
                   that to summe the people of the land
               Withstood the King, now with the King doth stand
               Too buxome for to finish his command.
            
            
               36
               Next morne, when early Phoebus first arose,
               (Which then arose last in Vriah's sight)
               Him Ioab in the forfront did dispose,
               From whom, the rest recoyled in the fight:
               Thus of his friends, betray'd by subtill traine,
               Assaulted of his foes, with might and maine,
               He lost his life, not conquered, but 
                     •
                  laine.
            
            
               
               47
               His mangled body, they expose to scorne,
               And now each cravin coward dare defie him,
               Outstaring his pale visage, which beforne
               Were palsy-strook, with trembling to come nigh him▪
               
               Thus heartlesse hares, with purblind eyes do pee
                     ••
                  
               
               In the dead Lyons pawes, yea dastard Deere,
               Over his breathlesse corps dare domineere.
            
         
         
            
            Davids hearty Repentance.
            
               1
               THE tongue of guiltlesse blood is never ti'd
               In the earth's month, &amp; though the greedy ground
               Her gaping crannies quickly did provide,
               To drinke the liquor of Vriah's wound,
               Yet it with moanes, be scattered the skies,
               And the revoicing Eccho, with replies,
               Did descant on the playn song of the cries.
            
            
               2
               Hereat the Lord, perceiving how the field,
               Hee sow'd with grace, and compast with an heape,
               Of many mercies, store of sinnes did yeild,
               Where he expected store of thankes to reape,
               With flames of anger, furnace-like he burn'd
               For patience long despis'd, and lewdly spurn'd
               Is at the length to raging fury turn'd.
            
            
               
               3
               Then all the Creatures, mustered their traine,
               From Angells vnto worms, the biinde did see
               Their Lord disgrac't, whose honour to maintaine
               Things wanting life, most liuely seeme to be;
               R
                     •
                  fusing all to serve Man, that refus'd:
               To serve his God, all striving to be us'd,
               To punish him, his maker 
                     •
                  hat a bus'd:
            
            
               4
               Please it your Highnes, for to giue me leave,
               Il'e scorch the wretch to cinder
                     •
                  , said the Fire;
               
               Send me, said Aire, him Il'e of 
                     •
                  reath bereave;
               No, quoth the, earnest Water, I desire
               His soylie sinnes with del
                     •
                  ges to scoure;
               Nay, let my Lord quoth Earth; imploy my pow
                     ••
                  
               
               With yawning chapps, I will him quick deuou
                     ••
                  
               
            
            
               
               5
               Soone with a word, the Lord appeas'd this strife,
               Injoyning silence, till he did vnfold
               That precious volume, cald The booke of life,
               Which the the Printer, priuiledg'd of old,
               Containing those he freely did imbrace,
               Nor ever would I wish an higher grace,
               Than in this Booke to have the lowest place.
            
            
               6
               Within this Booke, hee sought for Davids name,
               Which having found, he prof
                     •
                  ered to blot,
               (And David surely well deserv'd the same,
               That did his nature so with sinne bespot,
               Though none are blotted out, but such as never
               Were written in, nothing Gods love can sever,
               Once written there, are written there for ever.)
            
            
               
               7
               Strait from his throne, the Prince of peace arose,
               And with embraces did his Father binde,
               Imprisoning his armes, he did so close,
               (As loving 
                     〈◊〉
                   on an oake did winde,
               And with her curling flexures it betraile)
               His father glad, to finde his force to fayle,
               Strugled, as one not willing to prevaile.
            
            
               8
               Thus then began the Spotlesse lambe to speake,
               (One wo
                     •
                  d of whom, would rend the sturdy rocke;
               Make 
                     〈◊〉
                  -scorning Adamant to breake,
               And vnto 
                     〈◊〉
                  , perswade the sensles stocke,
               Y
                     •
                  a God hims
                     ••
                  f
                     •
                  , that knowes not to repent,
               Is made by his petitions, penitent,
               Hi
                     •
                   
                  
                     ••
                  stice made, with Mercy to relent)
            
            
               
               9
               Why doth my Fathers fury burne so fierce?
               
                  
                     •
                  hall Persian lawes vnalterable stand?
               And shall my Lord decree, and then reverse,
               
                  
                     •
                  nact, and then repeale, and countermand?
               Tender thy credit, gracious God, I crave,
               And kill not him, thou didst conclude to save,
               Can these hands blot, what these hands did ingrave?
            
            
               10.
               Hath not thy wisdome, from eternity,
               Before the worlds foundation first was lay'd,
               
                  
                     •
                  ecree'd, the due time once expir'd, that I
               
                  
                     •
                  hould Flesh become, and Man borne of a Maide?
               To live in poverty, and dye with pa
                     •
                  ne,
               That so thy Sonne, for sinners vilely slaine,
               Might make vile Sinners b
                     •
                  e thy Sonnes againe.
            
            
               
               11.
               Let me, oh let me, thy feirce wrath asswage,
               And for this sinner, begg a full di
                     •
                  charge,
               What though hee justly doth prouoke thy rage?
               Thy Iustice I will satis
                     •
                  ie at large.
               If that the Lord of life must murder'd bee,
               Let 
                     〈…〉
                  , this murd'rer may goe free,
               My Meritts cast on him, his Sinnes on me.
            
            
               12.
               Thus speaking, from his fragrant cloaths there went
               A pleasant breath, whose odour did excell,
               Myrrh
                     •
                  , Al
                     ••
                  s, and Cassia for sent,
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   all perfum'd his Father with the smell,
               Whereat his smoothed face most sweetly smil'd,
               And hugging in his arms, his dearest child,
               Return'd these welcome words, with voyce 
                     〈◊〉
                   mild
                     •
                  
               
            
            
               
               13
               Who can so pleasing violence withstand?
               Thy crauing, is the hauing a request,
               
                  
                     •
                  uch mild intreaties, doe my heart command,
               The 'mends is made, and pacifi'd I rest:
               As far as Earth, from Heaven doe distant lye,
               As Ea
                     •
                  t is parted from the Westerne skye,
               So far his sinnes, are sever'd from mine eye.
            
            
               14
               
                  
                     •
                  ereat the heavenly Quire, lift vp their voyce,
               Angells and Saints imparadis'd combine,
               Vpon their golden Violls, to rejoyce,
               
                  
                     •
                  o rayse the prayse of the coelestiall Trine,
               All in their so
                     •
                  gs a sacred strife exprest,
               Which should sing better, and surpasse the rest,
               All did surpasse themselves, and sang the best.
            
            
               
               15.
               Then said the Fire, my fury I recant,
               Life-hatching warmth, I will 
                     •
                  or him provide:
               I
                     •
                   
                  Davids breathlesse lungs do chance to pant,
               Said Aire, Il'e fanne them with a windy tide:
               With moisture, Il'e said Water, quench his heat,
               And I his hunger, quoth the Earth, with meat,
               Of marrow, fatnesse, and the flower of Wheat.
            
            
               16
               Thus when a Lord, long buried in disgrace,
               A King 
                     •
                  o former favor doth restore,
               With all respect the Court doth him embrace,
               Fawning as fast, as they did flowte before:
               Whose smiles, or frownes, are but the bare reflex
                     •
                  
               
               Of the Kings face, and like to this direction,
               Where hee affects, they settle their affection.
            
            
               
               17
               PLaine-dealing Natha
                        •
                     , prese
                     •
                  tly was sent:
               
                  Nathan, than whom, was none more skil'd to lanch
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   festred soule, and with a se
                     •
                  rching tent,
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   sound the sore; more cunning none to stanch
               A bleeding-hearted sinner, nor more kinde,
               With swadling cloaths of comfort, for to binde
               Vnjoynted members, of a troubled minde.
            
            
               18
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   did not flow with wealth, which envye breeds,
               
                  
                     ••
                  or yet was he with pe
                     •
                  ury opprest;
               
                  
                     ••
                  ant is the cause, from which co
                     •••
                  mpt proceeds:
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   meanes were in the meane, and that's the best.
               High hills are parcht with h
                     ••
                  te, or hid with snow,
               And humble dales, soone drown'd, that lie too low,
               Whilst happy graine, on hanging hills doth grow.
            
            
               
               19.
               For sundry duties, he did dayes devide,
               Making exchange of worke, his recreation,
               For prayer, he set the precious morne aside,
               The midday he bequeath'd to meditation:
               Sweete sacred stories, he reserv'd for night▪
               
               To reade of Moses meeknes, Sampsons might,
               These were his joy, these on
                     •
                  ly his delight.
            
            
               20.
               But now dispensing with his dayly taske,
               To court he comes, and wisely did invent,
               Vnder a parable, his minde to maske,
               Seeming to me
                     •
                  ne nought lesse, than what he meant▪
               
               And Lapwing-like, round fluttering a while,
               With 
                     〈…〉
                   praeface and a witty wile,
               Hee made 
                     〈◊〉
                   King himselfe for to beguile,
            
            
               
               21
               Thus he that thought all mortall men to cheate,
               And with false shewes, his secret sinnes to shade,
               Was couzned by the innocent deceite,
               Of one plaine Prophet, and directly made,
               As he a Iudge sate on the bench, to stand,
               At barr a prisoner, holdingThou art the man. up his hand,
               
                  The man that hath done this thing shal dye. But first condemned by his owne command.
            
            
               22
               Go
                     •
                   fond affectors of a flanting straine,
               Whose sermons strike at sinnes with slenting blowes,
               Give me the man that's power
                     •
                  ull and plaine,
               The Monste
                     •
                   Vice, vnmasked to expose:
               Such Preachers doe the soule, and marrow part,
               And cause the guilty conscience to smart,
               Such please no itching eares, but peirce the heart.
            
            
               
               23.
               This made King Davids marble minde to melt,
               And to the former temper to returne,
               
                  
                     •
                  hawing his frozen breast, when as he felt
               The lively sparks of grace therein to burne,
               Which vnder ashes cold, were choakt before;
               And now hee weeps, and wayles, and sighs full sore,
               Though sure such sorrow, did his joy restore.
            
            
               24.
               So have I seene one slumber'd in a swound,
               Whose sullen soule into his heart did hye,
               His pensive frien'ds, soone heave him from the ground▪
               
               And to his face life-water doe apply:
               At length, a long-expected sigh doth strive
               To bring the wellcome newes, the man's alive,
               Whose soule at last, doth in each part ariue.
            
            
               
               25
               
                  
                     •
                  hen to his Harpe, he did himselfe betake,
               
                  
                     •
                  His tongue-tide harpe, long growne out of request,)
               
                  
                     •
                  nd next to this his glory must awake,
               
                  
                     •
                  he member he of all accounted best:
               Then with those hands, which hee for griefe did wring,
               Hee also lightly strikes the warbling string,
               And makes one voice serve both to sob and sing.
            
            
               26
               
                  
                     •
                  hat heavenly voyce to heare, I more desire,
               
                  
                     •
                  han Syren's sweetest songs, than musicke made
               
                  
                     •
                  y Philomele chiefe of the winged quire;
               Or him, whose Layes so pleasing, did perswade
               Stones for to lack
                     •
                  y, when he went before,
               Or that brave harper, whom unto the shore,
               His hackny Dolphin safely did restore.
            
         
         
            
            Davids Heavie Punishment.
            
               1
               MOst true it is, when Penitents by grace
               Acquitted are, the pardon of their sinnes,
               And punishments release, do 
                     •
                  oth imbrace,
               Like to a paire of vndivided twinns,
               Parted they cannot be, they cleave so fast,
               Yet when the tempest of Gods wrath is past,
               Still his afflicting hony-shower doth last.
            
            
               2
               But let the Schooles, these thorny points dispute,
               Whose searching sight can naked truth discry,
               Sculking in Errors arms, and are acute,
               
                  
                     •
                  ine-
                     •
                  ingred with distinctions to 
                     •
                  ntye
               Knotts more than Gordian, these men never mist
               The slender marke, like
                     
                        ••
                     dges 20. 16. those in whose left fist,
               There did so much dexterity consist.
            
            
               
               3
               Meane time, my Muse, come see how prettily
               The patient Infant doth it selfe behave,
               Infant, but newly borne, now neare toThe death of King David's Child. dye,
               That from the cradle, posted to the grave,
               See with what silent signes, and sighes full faine,
               Poore heart, it would expresse where lies the paine,
               Complaining, that it knowes not to complaine.
            
            
               4
               Stay cruell Death thy hand for pitty hold,
               Against some aged grand-fire bend thy bow,
               That now hath full, twice forty winters told,
               Whose head is silver'd or'e, with ages snow:
               Dash out this Babe, out of thy dismall bill,
               And in exchange, let him thy number fill,
               So may be life, his friends enjoy him still.
            
            
               
               5.
               Those hands to hurt another, never sought,
               Which cannot helpe themselues, they are so weake;
               His heart did never hatch a want on thought,
               His tongue did never lye, that cannot speake:
               By wrong and violence, he ne're did wrest
               The goods, wherewith his Neighbour is possest,
               Whose strength scarse servs to suck his nurse's brest
            
            
               6
               
                  
                     •
                  ut ah, this Infant's guilt from him proceeds,
               T
                     •
                  at knew the least, when most he sought to know,
               Who was most nak't, when cloathed in his weeds,
               Best cloathed then, when naked he did goe:
               In vayne the wit of wisest men doth strive,
               To cut off this intayle, that doth derive
               Death unto all, when first they are alive.
            
            
               
               7
               As when a tender Rose begins to blow,
               Yet scarse unswadled is, some wanton maide
               Pleas'd with the smell, allured with the show,
               Will not reprive it, till it hath display'd
               The folded leaves, but to her brest applie's
               Th'abortive budd, where coffined it lye's
               Losing the blushing Dye, before it die's▪
               
            
            
               8
               So this babes life, newly begun, did end
               Which sure receiv'd the substance, though not sign'd
               With graces seale; God freely doth attend
               His ordinance, but will not be confin'd
               Thereto, when'ts not neglected, nor despis'd,
               They that want Water are by Fire baptiz'd,
               Those sanctifi'd, that ne're were circumcis'd.
            
            
               
               9
               Sweet Babe, one Sabboth thou on earth didst see,
               But endles Sabboths, doest in heaven survive,
               Grant, Death of joyfull howers deprived thee,
               Thou hadst seene yeares of sorrowes, if alive:
               True, thou we
                     •
                  t borne a Prince, but now art crown'd
               A 
                     •
                  ing by Death, sleepe therefore in the ground
               Sweetly, vntill the Tr
                     •
                  mpet last shall sound.
            
            
               10
               By this childs death, King David did sustaine
               One losse; but wh
                     •
                  re this misery did end,
               More miseries began: as in a chayne,
               One linke, doth on another linke depend:
               His l
                     •
                  st, with lust, his slaying with a slaughter
               Must punish't be: proportion'd therafter
               To Mother sinne, is punishment the Daughter.
            
            
               
               11.
               
                  AMnon advis'd by Ionadab, a fit
               Of sicknesse faines: Men wickedly inclin'd,
               Worse counsellers, (that with great store of wit
               Have dearth of grace) most easily may find;
               And Thamar's
                  The deflowring of Thamar.
                   hands, his meate must onely make:
               Ah happy age, when Ladies learn't to bake,
               And when Kings Daughters knew to knead a cake.
            
            
               12
               
                  Rebecka was esteem'd of comely hew,
               Yet not so 
                     •
                  ice 
                     •
                  er comelinesse to keepe,
               But that shee wa
                     •
                  er for the cammells drew;
               
                  Rachell was faire,
                     •
                   et fedd her fathers sheepe,
               But now for to supply Rebeck'as place,
               Or doc as Rachell did, is counted base,
               Our dainty dames, would take it in disgrace.
            
            
               
               13
               But quickly did his 
                     •
                  ea
                     •
                  tly lust declare,
               That he, to eate her daynties, had no neede,
               He for the cooke, not for the cates did care,
               Shee was the dish, on whom he meant to feed:
               Oh how she pray'd, &amp; strove with might &amp; maine
               And then from striving, fell to prayers againe,
               But prayers, and striving, both alike
                     •
                   in vayne.
            
            
               14
               Thus a poore Larke imprison'd in the cage
               Of a Kites claws, most sweetly sings at large
               Her owne Dirge whilst shee seeks to calme his rage,
               And from her jaylor, sue's for a discharge;
               Who passing for no musick that surpast,
               To feede his 
                     •
                  ares, whilst that his gutts doe fast,
               On her that pray'd so long, doth prey at last.
            
            
               
               15
               Then with dust-powdre'd haire she sore bewayles,
               And punisht on he
                     •
                  selfe, her brothers sinne,
               Parting her maiden livery with nayles,
               That parted was with colours, and wherein
               
                  White streaks, their owners innocence did show;
               The bashfull Red, her modesty; the row
               Of Sable, sorrowed for the wearers woe.
            
            
               16
               Comfort thy selfe more vertuous, than faire,
               More faire, than happy virgin, mourne with measure,
               Sinnes unconsented to, no soules impaire,
               That must be done perchance with bodies pleasure,
               Which with the griefe of soule may be constrain'd
               The casket broke, the jewell still remain'd,
               Vntoucht, which in the casket was contain'd.
            
            
               
               17.
               IN his brestThe murdering of Amnon.
                   
                  Absolon records this wrong:
               Out of our minds, good turns doe quickly passe,
               But injuries there in remaine too long,
               Those scraul'd in dust, but these ingrav'd in brasse,
               One Sun-set for our anger should suffice,
               Which in his wrath set oft, oft did arise,
               With yearly race, surrounding twice the skies.
            
            
               18.
               Now when his fruitfull flocks, which long had wor
                     •
                  
               
               Their wollen coates, for to make others hot,
               Were now to forfeit them, and 
                     •
                  o be shorne,
               (Sure from the silly sheepe, his 
                     •
                  ivelish plott,
               Their owner never learnd) hee finds a way,
               To worke revenge, and called on that day,
               His brothers to a feast, which pro'vd a fray.
            
            
               
               19
               What Amnon drunke in wine, in blood he spilt,
               Which did the dainties marre▪ and meate defile,
               Cupps▪ carpetts, all with goary streakes were gilt,
               Seeming to blush, that cruelty so vile▪
               
               So fowly savage, should the banquet staine:
               Thus he that being well, did sicknesse faine▪
               
               Not being sicke, was on a suddaine slaine▪
               
            
            
               20
               The rest refused on the meate to feede,
               Whose bellies were so full with griefe, and feare
               To feele, what they had seene; away they speed
               To ride: but Fame did fly, fame that doth weare
               An hundred listning eares, an hundred eyes,
               An hundred prating tongues, she dayly plies,
               Tongues, that both tell the truth, and tattle lyes▪
               
            
            
               
               21.
               She gets by going, and doth gather strength,
               As balls of snow, by roling more doe gaine,
               She whispr'd first, but lowdly blaz'd at length,
               All the Kings Sonnes, all the Kings sonnes are slaine:
               The pensive Court, in dolefull dumps did rue
               This dismall case, till they the matter knew,
               Would all bad news, like this, might prove untru
                     •
                  
               
            
            
               22.
               Goe silly soules, that doe so much admire,
               Court-curious incertainment, and fine fare,
               May you for mee obtaine what you desire,
               I for your fowles of Phasis do not care,
               If that such riots at your feasts be rife,
               And all your meate, so sowrely sauc'd with strife▪
               
               That guests to pay the shot, must lose their life.
            
            
               
               23
               Happy those Swaines, that in some shady bower,
               Making the grasse th
                     •
                  i
                     •
                   cloath, the ground their board,
               Doe feede on mellow fruite, or milks fine flower,
               Vsing no wine, but what their wells afford:
               At these did malice never bend her bow,
               Their state is shot f
                     ••
                  e, it is set so low,
               They overlooke, that would them overthrow.
            
            
               24
               FAst unto Geshure, flies the fatricide,
               To shelter there himselfe, the sentence sore
               O
                     •
                   angry justice, fearing to abide,
               Oh happy turne had he return'd no more,
               Who wonted guise, kept in a country strange,
               Those that abroad, to forraine parts do range,
               Their climate, not conditions doe exchange:
            
            
               
               25.
               Return'd: at entrance of the Court heAbsolons aspiring to the kingdome. stands,
               If any sutors there he chanc't to finde,
               Hee steales their hearts, by taking of their hands,
               And sucked out their soule, with kisses kinde:
               He of their name, cause, citty cloth inquire,
               Proud men prove base, to compasse their desire,
               They lowest crouch, that highest do aspire.
            
            
               26.
               Before such kisses come vpon my face,
               Oh, let the deadly Scorpion me sting,
               Yea rather than such armes should me imbrace,
               Let curling Snakes about my body cling:
               Than such faire words, I'de rather heare the fowle
               Vntuned schreeching of the dolefull Owle,
               Or heare the direfull mountaine Wolfe to howle.
            
            
               
               27
               Some men affirme, that Absolon doth sound
               In the worlds oldest tongue [of peace a father]
               But certs I know that such mistake their ground▪
               
               [Rebellious sonne] sure it importeth rather:
               And yet why so? sith since I call to minde,
               Than the Clementes none were more vnkind,
               Then Innocent, more nocent none I finde.
            
            
               28
               Then borrowing the plausible disguise
               Of holinesse, he mas'kt his plot so evill,
               Vnder the good pretence of sacrifice,
               (A Saint dissembled is a double Devill.)
               But sure were these the vowes, he went to pay▪
               
               His Sire, that harmelesse sheepe he vow'd to slay,
               Who o're mount Olives weeping fled away.
            
            
               
               29.
               This makes mee call my Saviours griefe to minde,
               Who onLuk
                        •
                      19. 4
                        •
                     . this mount, because the Iewes were growne
               So wicked, those that said they saw, so blind,
               Mourn'd for their sins, that mourn'd not for their own:
               Much did hee weepe for others that forbad,
               Others to weepe for him, whose being sad
               Hath made his Saints, for ever since, full glad.
            
            
               30.
               Downe comes the King to Iordan: on the sand
               
                  
                     •
                  f that the saylors chance to ground the boat,
               
                  
                     •
                   flood of teares they straitwayes did command,
               Whos
                     •
                   large accession, made the vessell floate:
               And if a blast of winde, did chance to faile,
               So greivously the people did bewayle,
               Their very 
                     •
                  ighs might serve to stuffe the sayle.
            
            
               
               31
               Thus was the King▪ in his owne land exil'd,
               His subjects were his hoast, and he their guest,
               Whose place was ill supplied by his child,
               (Vnhappy Bird defiling his owne nest)
               That tooke his fathers wives, in open 
                     •
                  ight,
               Those that do want of grace the shun-shine bright,
               Extinguish oft dim Natures candle light.
            
            
               32▪
               
               The blushing Sun, no sooner did behold
               
                  
                     •
                  o beastly lust, but sought his face to shrowd,
               And shrinking in his beames of burnish't gold,
               Was glad to sculke within a sullen cloud:
               The shamefac't birds, with one wing faine to fly,
               Did hold their other fanne before their eye,
               For feare they should such filthinesse espie.
            
            
               
               33
               What needed he, to keepe alive his name,
               Erect a pillar? Sure this damned deed,
               Makes us remember, and detest the same,
               That in the worlds last doating age succeed:
               Yea when that Brasse, that seemeth time to scorne,
               Shall be by all-devouring time out-worne,
               His name they'se beare in minde that are not borne▪
               
            
            
               34▪
               
               But
                     Ac
                           •
                        itophel hanging himselfe. he that gave this counsell, did not speed▪
               
               Who speeding home on witlesse asse amaine,
               (Asse that for wit, his rider did exceed,)
               'Cause he his will at Court could not obtaine,
               Did make his Will at home: the peevish el
                     •
                  e
               Amongst his houshold parts his cursed pel
                     •
                  e,
               Carefull of that, but carelesse of himselfe.
            
            
               
               35
               Oh suddaine thought of thy mortality!
               Thou art not yet so thorough worne with age,
               None in thy sace such Symptoms can espy,
               Which should so neare approaching death praesage:
               Thy state is not distempered with heate,
               Thy working pulse doth moderatly beate,
               All outward things seeme whole, seeme all compleate.
            
            
               36
               But ghostly is thy g
                     •
                  iefe: thou that by treason,
               Against thy Leige, so lately wast combin'd,
               Thy passions now rebell against thy Reason▪
               
               Reason, that is the Soveraigne of thy minde,
               And seeke for to disturbe it from the throne:
               Strive, strive to set these civill broyles at one,
               Order thy selfe, and let thy house alone.
            
            
               
               37
               A chayne of hempe, he to his necke made fast,
               By tying of which knot, hee did vntye
               The knot of Soule and Body, and at last
               Stopping the passage of his breath, thereby
               A passage for his Soule, wide opened hee:
               Thus traytors, rather than they should goe free,
               Themselves the hangmen of themselves will bee.
            
            
               38
               His friends, to balme his body spare no cost,
               With spices seeking to perfume a sinke,
               For certs I know, their labour was but lost,
               His rotten memory, will ever stinke,
               His soule thereby was nothing bettered,
               Because his corps were bravely buried,
               Tombes please the living, profit not the dead.
            
            
               
               39
               How many worthy Martyrs vilely slaine,
               Made meate for fowles, or for the fire made fuell,
               Though ground, they could not for a grave obtaine,
               Were not lesse happy, but their foes more cruell,
               Vnburied bodies made not them unblest,
               Their better halfe, did finde an heavenly rest,
               And doth injoy, joyes not to be exprest.
            
            
               40
               Leave we the Traytor thus, vpon whose hearsse,
               My Muse shall not a precious 
                     •
                  eare mis-spe
                     •
                  d,
               Proceeding to bemoane in dolefull verse,
               HowThe battell betwixt Absalon and Davids men. two great bands, with cruell blowes contend,
               Whole clouds of arrowes, made the skye to lowre,
               Dissolv'd at length, into a bloody showre,
               Till Steele kill'd many, wood did more devo
                     •
                  re.
            
            
               
               41
               Oh, let it not be publish't in the path▪
               
               That leads unto th' incestuous seed of Lot▪
                  
               
               Tell not these tidings in the towne of Gath,
               
               In Ascalon, see ye proclaime it not,
               Least these rejoyce at this calamity,
               Who count your fame, their greatest infamy,
               Your wofull jarrs, their wellcome melody.
            
            
               42
               Had Rachel now reviv'd, her sonnes to see,
               Their bloody hands, would make her heart to bleed,
               Each a Benoni unto her would be;
               Had Lea
                        •
                     
                   liv'd to see herselfe agree'd
               To fall out with herselfe, with teares most sure,
               She would have made her tender eyes past cure,
               Who ever wonn, she must the losse endure.
            
            
               
               43
               The conquest (which her verdict long suspended)
               Hover'd aloft, not knowing where to light;
               But at the last, the lesser side befreinded
               With best successe; the other put to flight,
               More trusted a swift foote, than a strong fist,
               Most voices oft of Verity have mist,
               Nor in most men, doth Victory consist.
            
            
               44
               The gracelesse sonne was plung'd in deepe distresse,
               For earth his weight, no longer would endure,
               The angry heavens denied all accesse,
               Vnto a wretch so wicked, so impure:
               At last the heavens and earth with one consent,
               A middle place, vnto the monster lent,
               Above the earth, beneath the firmament.
            
            
               
               45
               His skittish Mule, ran roving in the fields,
               And up high hills, downe dales, o're woods did prance,
               Seeming with neighing noyse, and wanton heeles,
               In token of great joy to sing and dance,
               That now her maister, she should beare no more,
               (An heauy bulke, whose sinnes did weigh so sore)
               Now rid of him, that rid on her before.
            
            
               46
               Cry Absolon, cry Absolon amaine,
               And let thy winged prayers, pierce the skye,
               Oh to the spring of pitty, soone complaine,
               That ne're is dammed up, not drained dry,
               Thy fault confesse, his favour 
                     〈◊〉
                   implore,
               Much is thy misery, his mercy more,
               Thy want is great, but greater is his store.
            
            
               
               47
               Condemne thyselfe, and he shall thee acquitt,
               Doe thou but pray, hee'le pitty thy estate,
               Confesse thy debt, he will the same remit,
               It never was too soone, its ne're to late:
               Alas; long sinners scarse at last relent,
               Hee gives not all offenders to repent,
               That granteth pardon to all penitent.
            
            
               48
               Whilst thus his life suspended was on high,
               Bold-ventrous loab opened his heart,
               (Heart, where much treason lurked privily)
               And peir'ct his body with a triple dart:
               Then Crimson blades of grasse, whereon he bleeds,
               Did straitwayes dye, and in their roome succeeds
               A fruitfull wildernesse, of fruitlesse weeds.
            
            
               
               49.
               When David heard the Victory was gain'd,
               But his sonne lost (as Iordan waxing ranke,
               Or'e flowes the land, and scornes to be restrain'd,
               To have his Tide, ti'de in a narrow banke)
               Surges of sorrow in his heart did rise,
               And brake the watry sluces of his eyes,
               Who lightned thus himselfe, with heauy cryes▪
               
            
            
               50
               My sonne, whose body had of grace the fill,
               My sonne, whose soule was so devoid of grace,
               Without my knowledge, and against my will,
               My sonne, in cause so bad, so strange a place:
               My sonne, my sonne, for which I most complaine▪
               
               I feare in soule, as in the body slaine,
               Would I might dye, that thou migh'st live againe▪
               
            
            
               
               51
               Now when this griefe was swallow'd, not digested,
               The subjects 
                     •
                  lock't, King David to restore,
               Who in an instant, love what they detested,
               Detest in th'instant▪ what they lo
                     •
                  'd before:
               People like weather-cocks wav'd with the wind▪
               
               We constant, in unconstancy may finde▪
               
               As time counts minutes, so they change their mind.
            
            
               52
               Amongst the rest, that came the King to meete,
               Lam
                     •
                  -
                     •
                  egd Mephibosheth, but loyall hearted,
               Was one, that never washt his cloaths, or 
                     •
                  eete
               (Except with teares) since David first departed▪
               
               Feete, which by fall from nur
                     •
                  e
                     •
                   armes began
               To halt, with him a child▪ so fast she ran,
               That he could never goe, when growne a man▪
               
            
            
               
               53.
               Not much unlike, if it give no distaste,
               That reall truths. I doe with trifles match,
               Whilst that my posting Muse, with headlong haste
               Doth strive her rurall Layes for to dispatch,
               Halting Invention, for the want of heede,
               And lame unjoynted lines from her proceede,
               And seldome things done speedily, doe speed.
            
            
               54.
               But here an vnexpected jarre arose,
               Whilst people, for most part in Prince contended▪
               
               Which grew from bitter words to bloody blowes,
               The King, quoth Iudah, of our Tribe descended,
               Hee of our flesh is flesh, bone of our bone:
               Nay, answer'd Israel, in the King wee owne
               Ten parts, a single share is yours alone.
            
            
               
               55
               Whilst sparkes of discord thus began to smoake,
               To 
                     •
                  inde the bellowes, Sheba did conspire,
               (The sonne of Belial.
                   
                  Sheba that proudly did disdaine the yoke)
               And blowing of a trumpet, blew the fire:
               Then those that claimed ten, disdain'd all part
               In David, taught by his seducing art,
               They discontented to their tents depart▪
               
            
            
               56
               This Rebell, Ioab whilst to quell he strives,
               A nameles woman (in the booke of life
               Her name is kept, that kept so many lives)
               Procur'd that he, who stirred up the strife,
               The body of the Common-wealth to rend
               From Prince the head, whereon it did depend,
               With head, from body rent, his life did end.
            
            
               
               57
               By his death many Citizens surviv'd,
               The losse of Traytors blood, did prove their gaine,
               Soone cea'st the flood of Discord, thence deriv'd,
               When they the factious fountaine did restraine.
               This warre, a vile man withWhat part have we in David, &amp;c. a word did rayse,
               Vnto his shame, which to her endlesse prayse,
               A worthy Woman with aHis head shall be thrown, &amp;c. word allaies.
            
            
               58
               So in our land, a noble Queene arose,
               As we have heard our fathers oft relate,
               A Maide, yet Manly to confound her foes,
               A Maide and yet a Mother to the State:
               Which she weake, like to crumbling bricke did finde,
               Which strong, as lasting marble she resign'd,
               Gold and Gods worship, both by her refin'd.
            
            
               
               59
               She having florished in great renowne,
               In spite of power, and policy of Spaine,
               
               Did change her earthly, for an heavenly crowne,
               And cea'st to rule o're men, with God to raigne:
               Fourty and foure Novembers fully past,
               (Aie me that winged time should post so fast)
               To Christ her love, she wedded was at last.
            
            
               60
               This Sunne thus set, there followed no Night
               In our Horizon, strait another Sunne,
               Most happily continued the light,
               Which by the first was hopefully begunne:
               And, what might most amaze all mortall eyes,
               Never before out of the Northen skies,
               Did men behold bright Phoebus to arise.
            
            
               
               61.
               Arts did increase his fame, he did increase
               The fame of Arts, and counting twice eleven
               Twelve months upon his throne, this Prince of peace,
               By falling to the Earth, did rise to Heaven:
               Then downe our chee
                     •
                   stears hot &amp; cold did flow,
               Those for the Sire decea'st, expre'st our woe,
               Those joy, for his succeeding Sonne did show.
            
            
               62.
               Live gracious Leige, whose Vertues doe surmount
               All flattery, and Envy them admires,
               C
                     •
                  nter of grace and greatnesse, liv
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  o Cou
                     •
                  t,
               Till that thy kingdome with the world expires:
               Wee subjects wish thee worst, that love thee best,
               Who here long to injoy thee, 
                     •
                  oe request,
               That late thou mayst injoy an heavenly rest.
            
            
               
               63
               And thou young Prince, hope of the future age,
               Succeed to Fathers Vertues, Name, and Crowne,
               A new Starre did thy Saviours birth praesage,
               His death, the Sun eclipsed did renowne:
               But both of these conjoyned to adorne
               Thy wellcome birth, the Sun with ag
                     •
                   so worne,
               Did seeme halfe dead, and a young starr was borne.
            
            
               64▪
               
               But what dost thou, my ventrous Muse, praesume
               So far above thy dwarf-like strength to straine?
               Such soaring soone will melt thy waxen plume,
               Let those heroike sparks, whose learned braine,
               Doth merit chapletts of victorious bayes,
               Make Kings the subjects of their lof
                     •
                  y layes,
               Thy worthlesse praysing doth their worth dispraise
            
            
               
               65
               Strike saile, and to thy matter draw more neare,
               And draw thy matter nearer to an end▪
               
               Though nought prayse-worthy in thy verse appeare,
               Yet strive that shortnesse may the same commend:
               Returne to see, where Ioah homeward goes,
               To see his Friends, that had subdu'd his foes;
               His souldiers, and himselfe there to repose.
            
            
               66
               Thus when two adverse winds, with strong command,
               Summon the Sea, the waves that both do feele,
               Dare follow neither, but in doubt do stand,
               Whilst that the shipps with water drunke doe reele
               With men, for griefe of drowning, drown'd in griefe,
               Vntill at length, a Calme brings them reliefe,
               And stills the storme, that had so long beene briefe.
            
            
               
               67
               Oh that I might but live to see the day,
               Day, that I more desire, than hope to see)
               When all these bloody discords done away,
               Our Princes, in like manner might agree:
               When all the world, might smile in perfect peace,
               And these long-lasting broyls, at length might cease
               Broyles, which (alas) doe dayly more increase.
            
            
               68
               
                  
                     •
                  he Neatherlands, with endlesse warrs are tost,
               
                  
                     •
                  ike in successe, to their unconstant tide,
               
                  
                     •
                  osing their gettings, gaining what they lost.
               
                  
                     
                        •
                     enmarke both sword, and Ba
                        •
                     tick seas divide:
               More blood, than juice of grape nigh Rhine is shed;
               And Brunswicke Land will not be comforted,
               But cryes, My Duke, alas, my Duke is dead.
            
            
               
               69
               The warrs in France, now layd aside, not ended,
               Are onely skinned ouer with a scarre,
               Yea haughty Alps, that to the clouds ascended,
               Are ouer-climbed with a bloody Warre:
               And Maroes birth place Mantua, is more
               Made famous now for Mars, and battell sore,
               Than for his Muse, it famed was before.
            
            
               70
               
                  Sweden to stopp th'Imperiall flood provides,
               (May his good cause, be crown'd with like successe,
               And they, that now please none, to please both sides
               May they themselves, his trusty friends expresse.)
               But Turks the Cobweb of their Truce, each howr
                     •
                  
               
               Doe breake, they wayte a time, but want no powre
               Nor will, warr-wearied Christians to deuoure.
            
            
               
               71
               But let the cunning Chymicke, whose exact
               
                  
                     •
                  kill, caused Light from darknesse to proceed,
               Out of disorder order can extract,
               Make in his due time all these jars agree'd,
               Whose greiuances may be bemoan'd by men,
               By God alone redressed; and till then
               
                  
                     •
                   hey more befitt my Prayers than my Pen.
            
            
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               .
            FINIS.
         
      
   

