
   
      
         
            Theyr dedes in effecte my lyfe wolde haue Stephen Wynton. Your dedes in effecte that made your lyfe braue / H.S.
            Gardiner, Stephen, 1483?-1555.
         
         
            
               1548
            
         
         Approx. 3 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01467
            STC 11593.5
            ESTC S2992
            29641393
            ocm 29641393
            28052
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01467)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28052)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1861:14)
         
         
            
               
                  Theyr dedes in effecte my lyfe wolde haue Stephen Wynton. Your dedes in effecte that made your lyfe braue / H.S.
                  Gardiner, Stephen, 1483?-1555.
                  H. S.
               
               1 sheet ([1] p.).   
               
                  s.n.,
                  [London :
                  1548?]
               
               
                  In verse.
                  Place and date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).
                  Two poems on recto of sheet, the first signed "Stephen Wynton", the second signed "H.S."
                  Reproduction of original in the Society of Antiquaries.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Gardiner, Stephen, 1483?-1555.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-04
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-05
            Andrew KusterSampled and proofread
         
            2006-05
            Andrew KusterText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
               THeyr dedes in effecte, my lyfe wolde haue
               Theyr wordes do pretende, my lyuynge to craue
               Theyr dedes I drede not, theyr wordes beynge ſuche
               I drede and regarde, in maner as moche.
            
            
               My lyfe is but vyle, I eſteme as lyght
               Then ſhulde I in gooddes, or lyuynge delyght
               Whom matters and dedes, nought moueth at all
               Shulde wynde and vayne wordes, his courage appall.
            
            
               Not man vnto man, can threaten I wote
               More greuous then death, the horryble lote
               And be it that death, by ſentence of man
               I ſuffre and that, well ſuffre I can.
            
            
               What ſhulde I regarde, this tranſytorie ſtate
               Regarde and thynke on, both early and late
               I muſte a newe lyfe, that euer ſhall laſte
               Subiecte to no death, no ſyckeneſſe, no waſte.
            
            
               Than welcome be death, the entrye of lyfe
               And dewe to the worlde, the ſtage of all ſtryfe
               Lyfe loſt in this wyſe, releuyth agayne
               For euer in blyſſe, to lyue without payne.
            
            
               From hence and herein, my comforte and ſtaye
               Repoſed I haue, that can not decaye
               God graunt me ſuche loſſe, that rayſeth this gayne
               God graunt me that death, ſuche lyfe to retayne.
            
            
               In meane tyme and ſpace, ſaye properly this
               I maye and in place, Vana ſalus hominis.
               
                  ☞Stephen Wynton.☜
               
            
         
         
            
            
               YOur dedes in effecte, that made your lyfe braue
               Hath cauſed your wordes, the truth to depraue
               Your dedes ye forget not, your wordes beynge ſuche
               You dryue on and drede not, all men ſe to moche.
            
            
               Your lyfe hath ben lewde, whiche ye eſteme lyght
               Of force to leaue gooddes, no thanke to go quyght
               Thoughe matters and dedes, nought moue you at all
               Let God and his threates, your ſtowtenes appall.
            
            
               For man vnto man, can nought threate ye wote
               More greuous then death, that horryble lote
               But yf ye haue death, that Iuſtyce gyue can
               Drede then your deſertes, and blame ye not man.
            
            
               Amende and repente, your ſtobourne eſtate
               That truthe hath neare tryed, but almoſte to late
               A patarne moſte popyſſhe, from fyrſte to the laſte
               As wylfull, as wyttie, whiche wante worketh waſte.
            
            
               I doubte the welcome of death, to that lyfe
               Plaſed for Popes pageantes, in ſtage of moche ſtryfe
               Lyfe loſt in this wyſe, releuyth agayne
               As he that from blyſſe, returneth to payne.
            
            
               From hence and herein, your comforte and ſtaye
               Repoſed you haue, whiche nedes muſte decaye
               If God for this loſſe, do graunt ye dewe gayne
               God ſhylde ye from death, ſuche lyfe to retayne.
            
            
               In meane and ſpace, our prayer is this
               As we maye in place, God tourne to his.
               
                  ☞H. S.☜
               
            
         
      
   

