
   
      
         
            Characters and essayes, by Alexander Garden
            Characters upon essaies morall, and divine
            Breton, Nicholas, 1545?-1626?
         
         
            
               1625
            
         
         Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01470
            STC 11595
            ESTC S118826
            99854033
            99854033
            19439
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01470)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19439)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 958:01)
         
         
            
               
                  Characters and essayes, by Alexander Garden
                  Characters upon essaies morall, and divine
                  Breton, Nicholas, 1545?-1626?
                  Garden, Alexander, 1585?-1634?
               
               61, [3] p.   
               
                  Printed by Edward Raban, printer to the citie and both colledges,
                  Aberdene :
                  1625.
               
               
                  A verse version of: Breton, Nicholas.  Characters upon essaies morall, and divine.
                  The last leaf is blank.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2003-10
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-11
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-12
            Jonathan BlaneySampled and proofread
         
            2003-12
            Jonathan BlaneyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2004-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            CHARACTERS And ESSAYES,
            
               By Alexander Garden.
            
            ABERDENE, Printed by Edward Raban, Printer to the Citie and both Colledges. 1625.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE TRVELY HONORED, and worthily worshipfull, SIR ALEXANDER GORDON, Knight-Baronet of Clunie, &amp;c.
            
            
               
                  WHen these CHARACTERS curt, and short ESSAYES,
               Right Worshipfull, vnworthie of Your view,
               At some successiue Hours, on ydle dayes,
               My Pen, for Pinsell; Coale, for Colours, drew,
               I stood, and studi'd, whose praeponed Name▪
               
               Should dye in Graine, and Luster lend to Them▪
               
            
            
               My Wits conven'd, and in my Braine combynd,
               The free and friendlie Favours that I fand,
               With th'ever-courteous Countenance and kynd,
               That I haue alwayes at Your Honours Hand;
               Advise mee onlie, that Your Worship shall
               Giue Luster, Life, Dye, and adorne Them all.
            
            
               
               Deigne then t'accept Them with that wonted Grace,
               Smoothe Front, and Face, that I did ever find:
               Which perfectlie doth point out, and expresse
               The Gen'rose Sprite, the wise and worthie Mind,
               Which doth before the Worke, and Work-mans Skill,
               In given-Gifts, regard the Givers Will.
            
            
               Your Worships ever Devoted, ALEXANDER GARDEN.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE READER.
            
               
                  EN
                     •…
                   I and tenderlie entreat,
               If you haue teasure, and th'Effayres not great,
               To take some tyme, and to survey this Table:
               VVhich well perused, shall prooue profitable.
               VVhere thou thy selfe in some of these shalt see
               Portrayd, if eyther Good or Bad tho
                     •…
                   bee.
            
            
               If good, insist, and make a Progresse still:
               And if perverse, pray, and repent thine ill.
               But I would wish, that thou thy selse find foorth,
               Amongst the best and worthie for thy worth.
               Disdaine not then, nor loathe thou for to looke
               Vpon the Tenor of this tabled Booke.
            
            
               
               Nor scorne thy Misses mongst these Maps to marke,
               Albeit they bee not cut in curious VVorke:
               As these, Apelle
                        •…
                     
                   
                  
                     •…
                  o 
                     •…
                  he Lyfe had limm'd
               Or Hondius hand had them attyrd and trimm'd,
               Yet sagely searched thou in These shalt see,
               The not to please, yet what may profit thee.
            
            
               Even as justly you merit
               So AL GARDEN inherit.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            CHARACTERS AND ESSAYES.
            
               A worthie King.
               
                  
                     A Worthie King, of GOD OMNIPOTENT,
                  Is in the Nature of Governament,
                  The verie Figure and the Image: Then
                  Hee is the Chiefe and Quintescence of Men.
                  The Champion of the Church next GOD is Hee,
                  And the Protector of the Policie.
                  The Lator of the Lawes and of the same
                  The strength and force, of those that hee doth frame.
                  The Sword of Iustice is the King to kill,
                  And Mercies Scepter too, when ere Hee will.
                  The Glasse of Grace, the eye of Honour, and
                  The Blessing of the LORD vnto his Land.
                  Lyfe vnto Loyaltie, to Treason Terrour,
                  To Reason Rule, and Arbiter to Errour:
                  His power Soveraigne is, and his Command,
                  Most absolute, and vncontroll'd must stand.
                  His frowne is Death, keene as a killing Knife,
                  And in the favour of his looke, is Life.
                  Hee is a Pilote, and His Bounds the Barge:
                  And all His Subjects therein, are His Charge.
                  Their Peace, His Pleasure, Q
                        •…
                     etnesse his Care,
                  And their kinde loue, doth his content declare.
                  
                     Hee hath no Paralele, since in degree
                  None is, nor with Him in aequalitie.
                  His Royall Crownes prae
                        •…
                     ogatiue 
                        •…
                     one ever
                  Can from his sole Sov'ra
                        •…
                     gnitie dissever:
                  Hee is th' Anointed of the Lord, and such
                  None should therefore presume 
                        •…
                     t attempt to touch.
                  Hee of a Bodie is the he
                        •…
                     d, heerefore
                  As sacred should vnwrong'd reigne evermore.
                  Hee is the Scourge of Sinne, the Rod of Vice,
                  And rateth Vertue at the highest price.
                  God His Vice-Roy, Hee's o're His people Supreme,
                  And vnder him whole Governour to them.
                  His Safetie must bee all his Counsels Care:
                  His Health and Honour, all His Peoples Prayer.
                  His Pleasure must bee pleasant to his Peeres,
                  And His Content His Kingdomes glads and Cheares.
                  His Presence must with Reverence be respected,
                  His Person strongl' attended and protected.
                  His Court must bee adorned and decor'd,
                  And still His State must b'intertain'd and stor'd.
                  None must presumpt'ouslie pry in, nor pea
                        •…
                     so
                  Into His Bosome, nor his Secrets Search.
                  His Will none should with-stand, nor it retard
                  When hee directs, but do't with great regard.
                  Since hee's (tho not a God) more than a Man.
                  And next to God for to bee honour'd than.
                  A Wall of Iasper, and an House of Golde
                  Hee is, that doth an Heavenlie Treasure holde:
                  Whose strong foundations are of precious Stone,
                  That Gates and entresse bot of Pearle haue none.
                  And all is precious passing ev'rie Thing,
                  Into a Godlie, Wise, and Worthie KING.
               
            
            
               An vnworthie King. 2.
               
                  A Wicked, vitious, and vnworthie King,
                  Th'Vsurper is of Power in governing:
                  Where Tyr no
                        •…
                     s rule into Authoritie,
                  Losseth the Glorie of true Majestie.
                  
                     While dread and feare of Terrour frighteth hence,
                  In subjects hearts, Loue from Obedience:
                  For when the Lyon Wolfe lyke liues, the Lambe
                  Murdred but mercie, dyeth with the dambe.
                  Hee is a piece, of too much pow'r and worth,
                  To ryot, and to lavish Furie foorth▪
                  
                  Hee is the scourge of sinne, altho the same
                  Shall bee for sinne, cast in the fierie Flame.
                  Hee th' Actor is, clad with the Cloake of Law,
                  That all good Acts, and Order doth orethraw.
                  Hee Fautor is, and Father of th'offence
                  Whereat hee winkes, or doth therewith dispence.
                  His Reason in the acting of his furie
                  Hee in the Bellie of his Will, doth burie.
                  And in his Temper best, and calmest Case,
                  Hee's desperate, and in a doubt of Grace.
                  His People and Kingdomes hee destroyes and wastes,
                  And all but Care, to Ruine helpes, and hastes.
                  Himselfe a Prey to's Followers, and Foes,
                  Hee makes: and all in ende to Ruine goes.
                  Himselfes a 
                        •…
                     ortor to his loathsome lyfe,
                  And feares, each keepes to cut his Throat, a Knife.
                  Hee scorneth GOD, and is to Him a Traytor,
                  And makes a God, and Idole bot of Nature.
                  Hee vseth Reason bot to ruine Sense,
                  And speaketh faire vpon a foule pretence.
                  His Will, his Wit, it violen
                        •…
                     lie carries,
                  While Death, and Wrong, together mixt, it marries,
                  And jugulates, 
                        •…
                     ot with Injustice hand,
                  To bib their Blood the best Men of the Land.
                  Vnlimitable his Lust is, and desires,
                  And to worke Tragicke Vengeance never tyres.
                  Inevitable is his Envie and Spight,
                  Hatcht in his hollow Heart, both Day and Night.
                  That should bee best of Men, the worst of Things,
                  Are tyrannous and cruell bloodie Kings.
                  His Blood-swolne Eyes, Darts ire; his banefull breath,
                  Breathes with the Basiliske vntimous death.
                  The hand of him is the vnrighteous Rod,
                  That smites the Godly, in the spight of GOD.
                  
                     The Tyrants heart, it is a Court of evill,
                  The dwelling and Divano of the Devill.
                  His feete as th' Eagle flies, and spurs the post,
                  To execute his mall inventions most.
                  His Heaven his Pleasure is, his God, his Gold;
                  His face aff
                        •…
                     ights, and 's horrid to beholde.
                  The exercise that hee delighteth in
                  It only is, Iniquitie, and Sinne.
                  His words are wicked, and vncomfortable,
                  And all his Actions are intollerable.
                  In summe, hee hatefull 
                        •…
                     s, and inhumane,
                  The Curse of Crowns, of Royall State the Staine.
                  The Clogg of Court, and all the Counsels Crosse.
                  A publicke Plague, and all the Kingdomes losse.
               
            
            
               A worthie Queene. 3.
               
                  A Godly Queene, a Gift, is good, and great,
                  Vnto the King, the Countrey, Crowne, and State:
                  Shee is th' vmpeered Mistresse, by her Merit,
                  And Grace of all her Sexe in Royall Spirit:
                  Shee is the chiefe of Women, and the chose,
                  Lyke to the Moone, amongst the Starres shee shoes:
                  And in her Spheare of Brightnesse giues none place,
                  Bot to the King, her Sunne, in anie case.
                  Shee is his Diamond, that's never dimbe,
                  Bot clearely shynes, to all the Worlde and Him.
                  Shee is that rich, and precious Pearle, that Hee
                  Vnprisable esteemeth in his Eye.
                  The Ioy of Courts, and Comfort of the King,
                  From whence Content, all Peace, and Pleasure spring.
                  Shee th' Orbe is where, his loving Motions moue,
                  In the effects, reciproake of their Loue.
                  Shee's Wisdomes fairest Loue, Shee's Vertues Grace:
                  In Naturs first, and Honours highest place.
                  Shee is the Hand-mayde of the LORD most hie.
                  And th' other halfe vnto the King must bee.
                  Last, by her worthie carriage shee gaines
                  To bee the Kingdoms Beautie, where shee reigns.
               
            
            
               
               A worthie Prince. 4.
               
                  A Worthie Prince, hee is 
                        •…
                     h' Extreame, the Scope,
                  The Altitude, and Kingdomes highest Hope.
                  The richest Iewell, reckned of Renowne▪
                  
                  That Kings can haue 
                        〈◊〉
                      in their Crowne:
                  And is the fairest 
                        •…
                     lowre, for to bee seene,
                  That growes into the Garden of the Queene.
                  Hee is the 
                        •…
                     ym'd 
                        •…
                     t-Object of the Eye
                  Of all the Kingdome, in his Infancie:
                  Hee 
                        •…
                     s the M
                        •…
                     rrow of the Mothers care,
                  A loving Sy
                        •…
                     es solisitude, much m
                        •…
                     ire.
                  Hee is the Theame the Counsell oft thinks on,
                  In the succession of the Royall Throne.
                  Hee is the Loue, Delight▪ and Ioy of all,
                  This great Incorporation Generall.
                  Hee's Natures Master-piece, and 
                        •…
                     oue no lesse,
                  Of Wisdome, in the lyfe of Worthinesse.
                  Hee is a Massie-precious Ivor Boxe,
                  Full of Rubies, of the richest Rockes:
                  Attending Tyme, to emptie and vnlose.
                  Such deare and daintie Wares as 't doth inclose.
                  These are the Royall deeds, that hee shall doe,
                  In his succeeding lyfe, and Raigne into.
                  Hee prickes in's Wisdome, Expectations Sprite,
                  And layes Ambitions Heart before his Fee
                        •…
                     e▪
                  
                  And by his Vertue wins, and Valour both,
                  The Noblers Loue, and in their Bosome go'th,
                  His bountie strongly binds, and not Constraint,
                  The service of the most sufficient.
                  Hee is the Chrystall Glasse, where Nature may
                  The Quintescence of all her Arte display.
                  He th' Index is, and Reasons Booke indeede,
                  Wherein true Vertue may her honour reade▪
                  
                  Hee is the Morning-Starre, that blazeth bright,
                  And doeth from the Sunne receiue its light.
                  Hee is the first wisht Fruite that doth aryse
                  From the blest Tree, of th' earthly Paradise.
                  
                     Hee is the Subject of the most Import,
                  And Studie of the best, and wisest sort▪
                  
                  Vnto the Learned, and the sharpest wit,
                  Hee is a Matter admirable to it.
                  Last, hee is Wisdomes Sonne, and Honours hight;
                  Vertues Choyse, and Valou
                        •…
                     s working Spright.
               
            
            
               An vnworthie Prince. 5.
               
                  A Prince corrupt, hee is the Kingdomes feare,
                  And the Precursor of Corruption there:
                  A Pest to the Peace, and Rest of the Realme,
                  And the Concusior of the common Calme.
                  A Precedent that bad example giues,
                  And much mischiefe, and wickednesse contriues.
                  A naughtie Ductor, that great numbers drawes
                  Vnto Contempt, and to the breach of Lawes,
                  When Will and Power, Pryde in furie horse,
                  To act Ambitions bad designes perforce.
                  Hee's lyke a dreadfull Dreame to one that's vext,
                  And in the sprite much troubled, and perplext.
                  H'affrights, and most into his humours then,
                  The very mindes and hearts of prudent Men,
                  And for too much delight in Vanities,
                  Hee (carelesse) quites the loue of all the Wise:
                  And with th'advise of grosse and giddie Heads,
                  His Actions all imprudently proceeds.
                  Hee's lyke a little mist, before the Sunne
                  His Carriere and dayly course beginne:
                  Which aye the more, and greater that it growes,
                  Lesse good it doth, and operation showes.
                  Hee is the griefe of the King, the Queenes sorrow,
                  And the Crosse of the Court, both even and morrow.
                  The Curse of Crownes, the Seede of Vnhappinesse,
                  And the vngracious Fruite of Vngodlinesse▪
                  
                  The Canker hee's that Kingdomes cleane consumes,
                  And Treasure Boxes empties all, and toomes.
                  His Countrey last, it may with Care him call
                  An vndigesting Bolle of bitter Gall.
               
            
            
               
               A worthie Counseller. 6.
               
                  A Worthie Counseller into a Land,
                  Supporting it, doth lyke a Pillar stand:
                  And from th'Anoynted one, that reigneth there,
                  His is the greatest, and the chiefest care.
                  The paines of his person, pa
                        •…
                     sing of his Sprite,
                  Into the state Effaires▪ are infinite.
                  Hee is a Guarde. Watch tower and Sentinell,
                  The Enemies approach t'a
                        •…
                     end and tell.
                  Hee's a Provisor, to provide in straites▪
                  
                  The Weale and preservation of the States.
                  An Oracle hee
                        •…
                     s in th
                        •…
                      Princes eare,
                  And in his fist him as a Brand doth bear
                        •…
                     .
                  An equall Weight, in Iustice ballance hee,
                  And light of g
                        •…
                     ace, in loue of trueth, must bee▪
                  
                  In the carriage and the course of the Law,
                  As a cleare rayd eye, himselfe hee doth shaw,
                  And in his fervor, in playing of his part▪
                  
                  In's Soveraigne service, beholde, hee is an Hart.
                  A minde of Honour, a braine of Inventions,
                  For his Countreyes good, are all his Intentions.
                  His place is powerfull, and his Arme is strong,
                  While his service is faythfull, and doth no wrong▪
                  
                  His Honours, his Place, and Calling doth claime,
                  Due by desert, and competent to them.
                  Hee, a Planet is, plac'd in the firmament,
                  Of the politicke Heav'n of Government.
                  Which through the cloudie, grosse, and thickest aire,
                  The nature of his light doth kythe, declare.
                  In summe, and last, such a one is hee,
                  That never can bee spar'd in Policie.
               
            
            
               
               An vnworthie Counseller. 7.
               
                  A Publicke Poyson, and pernitious thing,
                  And hurtfull harme, to the Crowne of a King,
                  Is a corrupted Counseller, and evill,
                  The Sonne of Shame, and Suppost of the Devill.
                  The danger of the State, and oft the fail,
                  When Iudgement wants, or weaknesse wryeth all
                  The Eares of the King, hee doth enchant, and charme.
                  And doeth so, the whole▪ Republicke harme.
                  False in effect, tho most faire in his word,
                  And in th'advise of tyrannie, a sword
                  Pridefull, and pe
                        •…
                     lious, his power still,
                  And partiall proues his voting, with his will.
                  His heart is hollow, for his owne behoue,
                  In protestation of a feigned loue.
                  Hypocrisie the Cloake hee carries on,
                  His colde and counter
                        •…
                     et Religion.
                  Trayterous invents, the onlie Agents are,
                  That sti
                        •…
                     re in him, a bolde Ambition dare.
                  Hee's ly
                        •…
                     e a cloudie and a threatning Storme,
                  That seemes to haue a Nat'rall cause and forme:
                  When that it Raines, dissolues, and foorth doth fall,
                  It striketh dead, and ofttimes drowneth all.
                  Disloyall to his Lord, ingrate to GOD,
                  To both vnworthie, and of Vertue voyde.
                  Hee is no person proper for his place,
                  But doth the grandour of that Rowne disgrace.
                  Vnworthie alwayes, and therefore, vnfit
                  For to looke once, on Majesti
                        •…
                      from it.
               
            
            
               A worthie Noble-Man. 8.
               
                  HEe's a true Noble, that is noblie borne,
                  Whose gracefull Vertue doth Descent adorne.
                  
                     Nobilitie consistes not aye in Blood,
                  But in a personall, and practicke Good.
                  When as the Noble-borne, by actiue worth,
                  Decores, and crownes, and beautifies his birth.
                  Hee Noble is, that nev'r to Vertue, Wealth,
                  Nor to his Honour, doth preferre his Health.
                  For Countrey, King, and for the Christian Fayth,
                  Hee's truely Noble, that doth disdaine the Death.
                  And never doth regarde (for loue of these,)
                  His Hazards, Paines, his Losse, his Gaine, nor Ease▪
                  
                  And hee is Noble the noblest Nobles among.
                  That will not doe, nor will receiue, a Wrong.
                  Hee is compleatlie Noble, in everie Case,
                  Whose Nature is nobilitate with Grace.
                  And hee is Noble, that prudentlie, and wyse,
                  Doth hugg Humilitie, and Pryde despyse.
                  Graue Wisdome justlie doth most Noble esteeme,
                  The temperatelie Iust, and Magnaneim.
                  A verie Noble, a King, a Prince, or Earle,
                  In Natures Shop, is lyke a polisht Pearle:
                  Whose reasonable Soule is rapt aboue
                  Terrestr'all Trash, with hopefull holy Lone.
                  Hee's wholly Noble, into his Heart that hath
                  Strong holding Hope, true Loue, and living Fayth.
                  Hee's meerly Noble, whose Sprite aspiring springs,
                  Nev'r blinking backe▪ to Baggage basest things.
                  Hee is the Heart of Hospitalitie,
                  Bounties Lyfe, and Nurse of Charitie.
                  Hee's Learnings Loue, Necessities Reliefe,
                  Valours Fame, and Wisdomes constant Cliefe.
                  The Falcon hee's, that on no Carrion feeds,
                  And th'Eagle that after no Spider speeds.
                  Hee is the Dolphin true, that feares no Whale,
                  And never will for terrour turne his Taile
                  Hee is in Reasons Heaven, a stately Starre,
                  And chosen Sainct in Vertues Kalendar.
                  Hee's in the Royall Round and Hemispheare,
                  A sure and setled Cynosura there.
                  Hee's Rector in Reasons Philosophie,
                  Load-starre of Light, in Loues Astronomie.
                  
                     In Honours Court, hee hath the Marshals place,
                  And's Royall Gallant into greatest Grace.
                  In briefe, hee is the Beaut' of his Abode,
                  Belov'd of Men, and gracious vnto GOD.
               
            
            
               An Ignoble-Man. 9.
               
                  TH'Ignoble are, that bee in Noble Roomes,
                  Putrid within, without faire painted Toombes,
                  Lyke th'Apple of Sodome, that is ash within,
                  Altho it haue a gold-lyke glancing Skin.
                  It is to Reason an exceeding Gr
                        •…
                     fe,
                  When Glories Styles, and Honours Tytles chiefe,
                  Birth, Fortune, Fate▪ or Chance, doth put or place,
                  In, and vpon the Subjects of Disgrace.
                  Base, naught
                        •…
                     esse, and th'ignoble Mynds of them,
                  Nobilitie, doth falsif', and defame.
                  When the Follie of Will, and want of wit,
                  For Vert' advancing, frames Nature vnfit.
                  Th'Ignoble are Bulks and Bodies of Basenesse,
                  The verie Mynde, and Spirit of Grossnesse.
                  Into his Indevours and Disposition
                  Of right Generation, hee's in Suspition.
                  Wisdome never knew, and Vertue nev'r bred him,
                  Learning nev'r taught, nor Honour nev'r led him.
                  To waste and consume, his course and inclination,
                  Without respect, to his place, or Reputation.
                  Vanitie and Wrong, are the whytes of the But,
                  Where-at the Ignoble doe ayme, and doe shoot.
                  Wastrie and Avarice, tho both b'extreame,
                  Are dearest, desir'de, delightsome to Them.
                  Th'ignoble are the Sorrow and the Shame
                  Of Kinsmen, Parents, Pedegree, and Name.
                  The staine of their Title, the Plague of their Place,
                  Wracke of their House, and Ruine of their Race.
               
            
            
               
               A worthie Bishop. 10.
               
                  ALL worthie BISHOPS, Ambass'dours they are,
                  To plot, and preach Peace, in the midst of Warre:
                  From th'Almightie to miserable Man,
                  Most worthily worthy these Worthies are Than.
                  They make th'Attonoment▪ take vp the Trews,
                  From th Heaven, to th'Earth, they bring the best newes.
                  Where mercies Patience, doth practise, and prease,
                  Nature cor
                        •…
                     upted, to call vnto Grace.
                  They are the sweet sounding Trumpets of loue,
                  That Fighters of Fayth, to fight it out moue.
                  And Heralds of wrath, that thunder-lyke threates,
                  For sinfull Trespasses, all manner of States.
                  Praying, imploring, with folded vp Hands,
                  Before the Holiest, humblie Hee stands.
                  Charie of their charge, and war'lie they watch,
                  From forcing their Flockes, and stands in the breach.
                  Th'are Pastors comple
                        •…
                     t, that None can reproue,
                  Full of a faythfull, and fatherly Loue.
                  Yet dreadfull, and deadlie Denuncers of Woe,
                  To sinfull Secure, in their Sermons they show.
                  These vigilant, wyse, and worthie Divines,
                  Are Sunnes to our Soules, but setting that shines.
                  In the Night of Nature, before vs they pace,
                  To leade vs to Goshen, to light vs with Grace.
                  Hee's vnreprooueable, whole of his Lyfe,
                  The Houseband and Head, of an only Wyfe.
                  Hee's prudentlie prompe▪ and apt for to preach,
                  To confirme, confute, instruct, and to teach.
                  Hee's harbrous, hee is helpfull, hee is holie,
                  To Wisdome woo'd, to Vertue wedded wholie.
                  Hee doth direct, by his workes and his word▪
                  
                  And squares his lyfe, by the Law of the LORD.
                  Hee's a Physician, and vseth (Therefore,
                  For the loue of the Soule) to search everie Sore:
                  Lansing what Leprose, or Festred Hee finds,
                  And so He remeads the Mallad' of Minds.
                  
                     Searing some-times, and Corrosiues in cure,
                  Hee vseth for Putrids, till they bee pure.
                  Hee is fore-pacer, in the path-gate to Grace,
                  And worthie of Honour, respect of his Place.
                  For preaching of Lyfe, hee's worthie of Loue;
                  And hee for his Paines Prayse-worthie doth proue.
               
            
            
               An vnworthie Bishop. 11.
               
                  A Bastard that the Ephod doth abuse,
                  And is of faythfull Pastors the Refuse;
                  Hee's th'Out-cast, the Scroofe, the Scumme, &amp; the Shame,
                  Yea, th'Ignommie, of a worthie Name.
                  A Dog that is dumbe; a Drudge, and a Drone,
                  Vnworthie the Charge hee is chosen one.
                  When sparing of Paines, of Knowledge misuse,
                  Vnfaythfull Effects, but Profit, produce.
                  Idolatrous Seeds hee seminates, so
                  Sowes in the Soule, a Furie▪ and a Foe.
                  Vnhappie, for lorne, and light-lesse the Sheepe,
                  That Bishops so bad, haue credite to keepe.
                  When these they shall, for wanting Food bee found
                  To perish, pastring in a barren Ground
                  Hee breeds a Warre, Distrust, and Diffidence.
                  Into the Wittes of all his Audience.
                  Good Pastors aye, hee preasseth to supplant,
                  A Devill indeede, and bot in show a Sainct▪
                  
                  Hee makes Religion bot a Cloake of Sinne,
                  That covertly hee walks, and walloweth in.
                  And with a feign'd Humilitie doth hyde,
                  A passing and imcomparable Pryde.
                  His Flesh doth fret, and all his Bones doe itch,
                  To raze the Poore, and for to rob the Rich.
                  Ev'n Wise-mens Eyes, hee leades, blind-folded foorth,
                  Bot with Conceit of his imagin'd Worth.
                  And drawes their thoughts to call Accompt, esteeme
                  (Tho hee bee not) him such as hee doth seeme.
                  Hee lookes lyke a Lambe, hee liues lyke a Foxe,
                  And cruellie, craftie, kils all his Flocks.
                  
                     Hee is the person of Hypocrisie,
                  Th'vnpure Spirit and Heart of Heresie.
                  Griefe to the Good, to the Faythfull a Foe,
                  Crosse to the Church, and to the World a Woe.
               
            
            
               A worthie Iudge. 12.
               
                  THe worthie Iudge, doth well his Calling knaw,
                  And is the Grace and Glorie of the Law.
                  Hi Stomacke is a Treasurie of Trueth▪
                  
                  And pondereth all, with Reasons Scalls of Rueth.
                  Hee is indeede a Doome, whose Blast of Breath,
                  On breach of the Law, is dreadfull as Death.
                  Where criminall Faul
                        •…
                     s must cleanly bee cut,
                  And from the Peace of the Publict-weale put.
                  A worthie Iudge, is a Sword in the Hand,
                  (To kill or conserue) of the Lord of the Land.
                  In the Countreyes Cause hee ev'r hath an Eye,
                  That doth the weale of the Common-wealth see.
                  His Studie and Paines, (Proportion to keepe)
                  Bereaues him of Rest, and of his sound sleepe:
                  Betwixt Commanding and Obedience,
                  To keepe the Crowne on the Head of the Prince.
                  And safelie and sure, of the Subject als,
                  To hold on the Head, vnhewne from the Hals.
                  The worthie Iudge, is feared bot of Fooles,
                  Curst bot of Knaues, and hated bot of Snools.
                  Hee's honour'd of Wise, of Prudent approv'd,
                  Gratefull to the Good, of the Godly belov'd.
                  Hee judges all Right, revenges all Wrong,
                  And doing these both, hee's steadfast and strong.
                  His word is the Law, his Power is Grace;
                  His Merit, Honour; and his Labour, Peace.
               
            
            
               
               An vnworthie Iudge 13.
               
                  
                     IS IVSTICE griefe, in judging when Hee erres,
                  And partiallie, the Wrong, to Right preferres:
                  And when through Ignorance, Wrath, or Envy,
                  Th'Innocents Life, vpon his Lip doth ly.
                  His Handes are full of Brybes, defyl'd with Blood,
                  The guiltlesse Gore, it fatts him most of Food.
                  His Heart is full of Hypocriticke Hate,
                  His Tongue of Treason, Vntrueth, and Deceit.
                  His face is feign'd, and Smooth as smoothest Oyle,
                  Politickly, more to oppresse and spoyle.
                  Hee is a Man more morall, than divynd,
                  Iudicious more, than to bee just enclynd.
                  His Mercie mercinarie is, and solde,
                  His kyndest countenance, vncoft, is colde.
                  His Lips doe lavish, Legendes of the Lawes,
                  Yet giues colde comfort, to the Poore mans cause.
                  The weightie Angell doth over-weigh his Grace,
                  And turnes him Devill on his Tribunall place.
                  Altho the liverie of the Law, hee weares,
                  His Processe all vnlawfull led appeares.
                  His holinesse, is superficiall,
                  And seemeth to bee so, and that is all.
                  Into the preached word, hee hath no Pleasure,
                  And for the Worlde, to heare it, hath no leasure.
                  His appetites, as they his Mynde doe moue,
                  Is the Religion, that hee best doth loue.
                  His goods, they are his Glorie, and his Gaine,
                  And hee impure, doth bot his place profane,
                  While Iustice sacred Seat, hee makes to bee,
                  By his abuse, nought bot a Boucherie.
               
            
            
               
               A worthie Knight. 14.
               
                  A Worthie Knight, is hee that doth inherit,
                  The proper Vertues of a perfect Sperit:
                  Whom Power can not appall, nor Crosse foot chance,
                  Oppos'd▪ depresse, nor prosprous veles, advance.
                  True worthinesse is eminent in him,
                  That sa
                        •…
                     elie in most dangerous deeps can swim.
                  Hee is a Magnanime and worthie Knight,
                  Into the Worlds vp-roars that walks vpright:
                  And not with Fortunes Change, nor Griefe of Minde,
                  Confounded, nor perplext in Sprite wee find.
                  Hee worthie is, that wis
                        •…
                     lie giues his word,
                  And keepes it too, th'vnsheathing of his Sword,
                  And not with light Escapes, or bastard bracks,
                  As Some snuffe Pepper, soone exceptions takes.
                  Hee worthie is, that bitter Things can beare,
                  And ov'r his Stresses Patience Tropheas reare.
                  True Magnanimitie, his Sword, and Horse,
                  Convoy, and hewes, his passages perforce.
                  And th'onlie Paradise, into his Eye,
                  Are Fields defeat. Tryumphs, and Victorie.
                  To pardon the Submissiue, and Distrest
                  Relieue, his Glorie is, and conquest best.
                  Hee will bee free from everie Blott and Blame,
                  That may imply Dishonour to his Name.
                  His pardon granting, to his prostrate Foes,
                  Most rich and famous him, in Mercie shoes.
                  Hee's voyde of Spight, and not with Hate defylde,
                  In Spirit stout, and in his Nature mylde.
                  Hee is not One, with Loue and Hate, that's mixt,
                  Nor wavers, as One fast, and loose betwixt.
                  Bot hee is Constant, true, and Bellicall,
                  Heroick like, and honorable with all.
                  Bot worthie Knights, Note this, in Number are,
                  In vnities, and now, bee singulare.
                  And like th'Arabian Bird, doth bot abound,
                  For They with vs, as there, these Fowls are found.
               
            
            
               
               An vnworthie Knight. 15.
               
                  THe foule Refuse, and the defect of Nature,
                  To Fortitude, and Honour true, a Traytor.
                  When to advance, his Valour it occurs,
                  His Blade is blunt, and hee wants ravell'd Spurres.
                  A Cypher in Court, a Sheepe in the Campe▪
                  
                  Yet lyke TYTIDES in the streetes will stampe.
                  Hee is amongst Men, lyke Owles amongst Birds,
                  Shaming the Sword, to his side that hee girds.
                  Hee counts for no Promise, nor Honour, nor Fayth
                  (Gaine once hee his point) that hee plighted hath.
                  A Friend, or a Foe, hee finely can faine,
                  Grace thee even now, and gloome on thee againe.
                  Hee's worshipt for his Wealth, not for his Wit,
                  Neyther was Valour the worker of it.
                  Where Courage for Honour doth enterpryse,
                  Th'vnworthie Knight lyke to a Lubbard lyes.
                  When Magnanimitie with Courage strong,
                  Through Perill passes to repare a Wrong.
                  Hee faintly feares, and Couragelesse hee quakes,
                  And to heare these Attempts such Terrour takes,
                  That all his Sprites, they post from him apace,
                  And Lead-lyke, Liue-lesse, hee lookes in the Face.
                  Hee is the Chylde of Pryde, that doth despise,
                  The truelie Worthie, that through Vertue ryse.
                  Hee's Follies Fav'rite, full of Ostentation,
                  And onlie mightie in Imagination.
                  In Honours Court, yet there bee no such Apes,
                  Knights bot in Cloathes, and Cavelliers in Shapes.
                  Vnto the Mould whereon they moue, bot Masses,
                  And God forbid our Countrey breed such Asses.
               
            
            
               
               A worthie Gentleman, 16.
               
                  HEE is a bearing Branch of Honours Tree.
                  And Gentle Germen of Genuitie.
                  Whose Fruites for to be▪ Vertues Actions fall,
                  As pleasing to the Eye of Iudgement all.
                  As truely Rellishing and Smelling sweet,
                  Vnto the Soule, and vnderstanding Sprite.
                  The De
                        •…
                     ds and Actions fitting him to doe,
                  Hee is not forc'd, nor is compeld there-to:
                  Except they bee Things naughtie, ill, and bad,
                  Where-to in Heart hee nere Intention had:
                  Bot eyther doth vnwittinglie such Acts,
                  Or forc'd vnwillinglie vnto those Facts.
                  Most effable, and in his Nature kynde
                  And flexible, yet with a Genrose Mynde.
                  In his Alleadgeance is, and Loue most Loyall,
                  Vnto th'Authoritie, and Power Royall.
                  Religious, hot, and fyrie in his Zeale,
                  Most kyndlie carefull for the Common-weale:
                  And what is his, hee heedfullie regards,
                  And bount'fullie bestoweth his Rewards.
                  Hee's Confident, resolved, and Enteare,
                  From Foeminine, from Base, and Bairnlie Feare.
                  Hee's not compos'd, nor come of Cur
                        •…
                     ish kynd,
                  Bot cast in Vertues Mould, pure, polisht, fyn'd.
                  And by the Sprite of Wisdome, drest and squar'd,
                  In Honours House, for to bee plac'd, prepar'd.
                  Hee in Apparell doth more comelie goe,
                  Than costlie, for a Pharasaicke sho
                  More healthsome is his Fare, and daylie Dyet,
                  Than Exceffiue, Profuse, and given to Ryot.
                  Hee Exercise, for Pleasure, more do
                        •…
                     h loue,
                  Than that the same should to him painfull proue.
                  His Studies all, are for Instruction more,
                  Than Ostentation, Pryde, or worldlie Glore.
                  His I oues not wanton, no, nor f
                        •…
                     itting are,
                  Bot faythfull, vertuous, chaste, and regulare.
                  
                     Hee is no Niggard, no, nor Prodigall,
                  But treades the Temprates steps, the best of all.
                  His Carriage is not Carledge, nor austere,
                  Nor Apishly doth hee his Bodie beare.
                  His Pedegree, Descent, and gentle Blood,
                  By courteous Carriage hee doth make them good.
                  And by the vertuous Course, and Lyfe hee liues,
                  H'example good, to his Succession giues.
               
            
            
               An vnworthie Gentleman 17.
               
                  IS the Derision and the Scoffe of Wit,
                  True Honours Scorne, and the ydle Ape of it.
                  Where Wealth much more than Worth and Wit wee see,
                  Is vainly worshipt with Simplicitie.
                  Hee's One of Vices Varlets, that delights
                  In Vanities excessiue Dayes and Nights.
                  And one that all doth prodigallie spend
                  Imprudently, but eyeing ev'r the ende.
                  And ydlie more on worthlesse workes and Vaine
                  Doth waste, than would a Temprate STATE maintaine:
                  Or well husbanded, or managed, might
                  Attaine to Honour, in the Vertuous sight.
                  All his Delight's in Vice and Vanities,
                  His Cogitations ydle, and inanities.
                  His Heart is hollow, hardned, and vnholy,
                  His exercise, is fecklesse, frivole, folly.
                  His pleasures imp'ous are, and all prophane,
                  His studies such as yeelde no Grace, nor Gaine,
                  His Conversation, bairnly is, and base,
                  Degenrate from a Iennet, to an Asse.
                  His Rayment and Apparell out of forme,
                  His dyets are inordinare, enorme.
                  Out of all Square, his Carriage is almaist,
                  And None his companie at all requeast.
                  Since Buzzard-lyke hee's with a Falcons Bell,
                  Or lyke a Iade, spread with a golden Pell.
               
            
            
               
               A worthie Lawyer 18.
               
                  IN Vertue Conscience, Grace, and Iudgements grouth,
                  Hee is the Indagator of the Trueth:
                  Hee painfully PLEAS, doth practise, and preasse,
                  To bring them into Conclusions of Peace.
                  The Time hee divides in vses to knaw,
                  From Ignorance, the knowledge of the Law.
                  Obscurities, h'vnlockes and open layes,
                  And truely th'Orator pleading hee playes.
                  With emptie hands, a pittying Sprite, and pure,
                  In Conscience Court, hee patrones aye the Poore.
                  In Resolutions, and Responses plaine,
                  And quicke in giving, But all greede of Gaine.
                  A CORRYPHaeVS in his Clients Cases,
                  And still the Best, and not the Bad, imbraces.
                  Hee doth not loue to holde a Client long,
                  Nor will defende what well he viewes is wrong.
                  The Case, and not the Client, hee respects.
                  And not what's wrong, but Verities protects,
                  His labours are to make his Calling bee,
                  (Even as it should) seene in Sinceritie.
                  Hee doth despyse, both Falsehood, and Delayes,
                  And others Knaveries, in their PLEAS displayes.
                  H'abhors Advantage, by ore-sight, or sleuth,
                  Of Others, if the Matter bee of Trueth.
                  Hee wearies not his Poore-men, with depending,
                  Nor to the Iudges, or the Wryters sending.
                  But all that these bad Patrons puts Them to,
                  Hee by his Servants o
                        •…
                      himself
                        •…
                     , doth doe.
                  And more for Conscience, Credite, and his Name,
                  Than for their Money, hee doth doe for Them.
                  Still of his Calling hee doth Conscience make,
                  And bot what They may gladly giue, will take.
                  Hee doth not sucke their Substance by slim Shifts,
                  As Thiefe-lyke some doe vse, and yet Vnthrifts.
                  Hee by his faythfull Labours (not by Stealth)
                  And gotten, guided well, doth grow to Wealth.
                  
                     Yet all the Goods with Honestie hee gains,
                  Hee prudentlie in ployes, and nought prophanes;
                  So worthily, most worthie, hee doth grace,
                  Wher
                        •…
                      h
                        •…
                     e doth passe, and is imploy'd the Place.
                  Of 
                        •…
                     ll men hee's respected for good parts,
                  And gets for gracious Guiding, Good-mens Hearts,
                  For hee is faithfull, efauld, vpright ever;
                  Dissimulate, nor false, nor feigned never.
               
            
            
               An vnworthie Lawyer. 19.
               
                  HEE is a Lawlesse, Perdite, and a Lost,
                  The Figure bot of a foot-faring Post;
                  That carries, not knowing (a Bag full of Billes)
                  The Tenor, Contents, their Mynds, or their Wills:
                  Only can reade their Tytles, and direct,
                  Sans knowledge vnto what farder effect.
                  To bee inform'd hee troubles nor travels much,
                  Since that the Trueth hee nere intends to touch.
                  Hee'll agravate and make the Matter great,
                  And many Maximes of the Law repeat:
                  To cause his Client thinke his Cases are
                  Pronounced PRO, before hee breast the Barre,
                  Hee speakes bot Problems, Sentences, or Phrases;
                  Quotes Acts, and Lawes, till Rustickes hee amazes.
                  Yet what hee speakes, or quotes, be words bot waste,
                  And waird bot as the Blinde their Clubs doe cast:
                  Or as the Bairnes their Lessons learne by rat,
                  So hee but farder knowledge rymes bot that.
                  Hee hath an Heart to Greedinesse so given,
                  That hee will perill all, and hazard Heaven,
                  Before hee shall not (O Vngodlie gaine!)
                  By beggering his Clients, Wealth obtaine.
                  Hee nev'r with his Conscience comes to count,
                  So that hee see his Meanes and Honour mount.
                  Hee glores in Geare, Gold-Angels are his Gods,
                  For which his Trueth, hee tramples on, and troads.
                  Hee studies all, to Sophistrie and Shifts,
                  Protracting Time, still hee delayes, and drifts.
                  
                     And empties so his long Dependers Purses,
                  Till they, by weeping Crosse, with Sighs, and Curses,
                  Departe: when what they had prepar'd is spended,
                  Their Causes ill persude, and worse defended.
                  They never haue compassion on the Poore,
                  Bot like a Prostitute and publicke Whoo
                        •…
                     e,
                  From both the Parties, but a sense of Shame,
                  And all that Silver sets they take from them.
                  They Trickers are, and Tyners of a Cause,
                  But Conscience, and Knowledge of the Lawes.
                  They haue no Soule, they haue no Shame, nor Eyes,
                  Bot such as sole their present Profit sees.
               
            
            
               A worthie Souldiour. 20.
               
                  A Worthie Souldiour worthily is stylde,
                  VALOVRS Genuine, and naturall Chylde.
                  Predestinate train'd vp, and borne to bee
                  Fit for the service of Necessitie.
                  And th'Ensigne to advance and carrie foorth,
                  Of Honour in the actiue Acts of Worth:
                  Hee dyes the Earth, in crimson with his Handes,
                  While hee the Violence of Wrong with-stands.
                  Hee ruines that which prowde Ambition reares,
                  And Tyrants Statutes into Tags hee teares.
                  Hee is a warie Watch man, and with Wit,
                  Advantage takes of Time, and vseth it
                  Into the Projects and Designes hee hath,
                  For executing of his lawfull Wrath:
                  While Cowards base make Flight their foule Refuge,
                  Hee makes his Blade his Arbiter and Iudge.
                  And with the Pike Objections hee impoungs,
                  When others bot retort them with their Tongues.
                  The dint of Death, altho before his Eyes,
                  Hee obviates, before Indignities.
                  Hee is a Lyon, awfull to Ambition,
                  And lyke a loving Lambe, vnto Submission.
                  Hee holdeth Hope, in hazards by the Hands,
                  And on the Head of Feare, triumphing stands.
                  
                     Hee is the Peace, Preserver, and a Shield,
                  Vnto his king and Countrey in the Field.
                  Vnto disloyall Subjects hee is seene,
                  
                     A Persecuter constant, and a keene.
                  Hee leades to Battell chearfull, as hee past
                  Vnto a Banquet, for to breake his Fast.
                  Hee knowes not Cowardice, nor fainting Feare,
                  On Resolution, hee his Rest doth Reare.
                  Search all his Forts, his strongest you shall finde,
                  To bee the Magnaminit' of his Minde.
                  Looke to his Life, and Thou shalt see't, a way,
                  Where Dangers obviate, and meete Him ay.
                  Yet with vndaunted Sprite hee forward fares,
                  And to no Fortune stoups, nor perill spares.
                  In midst of Martiall Broyls, and braue Alarms,
                  Hee with his Armes, there floutly wins his Armes.
                  And by his Merits, in the Fields, and Plains,
                  In Court at home, his Honors hee obtains.
               
            
            
               An vntrained Souldiour. 21.
               
                  A Souldiour but skill, and an vntrain'd,
                  Is like a young Hound, or a Whelpe new wain'd,
                  That can not doe, when first hee falles to hunt,
                  Lay downe his Nose, as other Hounds are wont:
                  Nor put vpon a piece of Service, knoes
                  His Pike, nor Peece, nor Person, to dispose.
                  The manner of his March is like as whan
                  Tyr'd at the Plough, trudge home is seene a Man.
                  Hee beares his Blade, before his Bellie tyde,
                  For to bee sure, hee lose't not from his Syde.
                  His Pike hee lyke a Pyke-staffe lifts aloft,
                  As Boors their Bacon carrie, when it's coft:
                  And with a minicke minsing of his owne,
                  A kynde of Carriage, yet in Camps vnknowne.
                  Hee so presents his Peece, with speciall Grace,
                  Which makes his Fellowes flout him in the Face.
                  On goes his Arms, VVaste-coat-lyke, ore his Ears,
                  And hee his Murrion, lyke a Night-cap weares.
                  
                     When to bee quarterd, to the Fielde hee's led,
                  As with his Bobbie hee lookes for his Bed.
                  And when prepar'd his Provant hee espyes,
                  Hee Kyte-like craving, for his Victualls cryes.
                  And ere he scarce be come, or knowne, he will
                  Wish to bee home, at's Mamie, or the Mill.
                  And hanging downe his Head, hee drouping goes,
                  As if hee had his Heart into his Hose.
                  And in his Hut, when hee to rest doth take him,
                  Hee sleeps, till Drums or deadlie Pellets wake him.
                  Thus hee himselfe hee carries, and descryes,
                  In all Imployments, in all Companies.
                  Till Martiall Discipline this Milk soppe raw,
                  Doe season▪ and to vnderstanding draw.
                  
                     A Cypher hee's, mongst Figures, and is nought,
                  Bot a Shadow, and not a Substance thought.
               
            
            
               A worthie Physician 22.
               
                  IS open Enemie, and Foe profest,
                  To Sicknesse, Disease, to Plagues, or to Pest:
                  Purging from Nature Corruptions, and what
                  Infects destroyeth, or weakneth, yet that.
                  In feeling of Pulses, or groaping of Wrists,
                  Or viewing of Water, his Actions consists.
                  Discourses that chiefelie fits him, and pleases▪
                  
                  Are of the Causes and kinds of Diseases.
                  In Physicall things, hee frets till hee finds,
                  And searcheth of Simples, Sorts, and the Kinds.
                  And then of these all, accordingly takes,
                  Advisedly, so his Mixtures hee makes.
                  Vnto his Patients, hee Patience perswades,
                  And with a modest Mirth, their Griefes hee glads.
                  Much hee doth moue, allow, and advance,
                  And praiseth oft in Purpose, Temperance,
                  Both to avoyde all Wastrie of Wealth,
                  And for vpholding of bodily Health.
                  Purging and Bleeding his Counsellours bee,
                  Into conserving of sound Sanitie.
                  
                     His two Attendants and On-wayters are,
                  The choyse Chyrurgion, and Apothecare.
                  Resolv'd with these, of Time, and Seasons sure,
                  Hee temprate tryes, and cunning in his cure.
                  Surfets, Excesse, and Venerie both,
                  Agents alwayes for his Imployments go'th.
                  When as from one-an-others weaknesse hee will,
                  Straine Strength to himselfe, by Knowledge and Skill.
                  Thus they are needfull, and necessare Men,
                  To cure Diseases vnnecessare then.
               
            
            
               An vnworthie Physician. 23.
               
                  AN Asse turnd Ape, his Office hee vses,
                  Yet Artlesse, both Practise and Parties abuses.
                  Bayard-lyke blind, hee bloodeth with the Lance,
                  Doe hee cure, or kill, hee cares not what chance.
                  Witlesse with Vomit, or Purging hee will,
                  Giue Health in haste, spoyle presentlie, or spill.
                  Hee cracks of his Cures, his Travels, and where,
                  Such Wonders hee wrought, seene seldome or rare.
                  Bot so farre a-Field, that there are found few,
                  Will tye them, to try his talking, if true.
                  Hee vaunts of Rewards, and venteth out Wonders,
                  That his Receipts, were nere lesse than hunders,
                  In Markets and Faires, hee is not away,
                  Walking, and viewing, some Vrinals ay.
                  Where if hee find Hot, Grosse Humors, or Raw,
                  Albeit that Liech hee little doth kn
                        •…
                     w;
                  Yet some thing to seeme, some-what hee will say,
                  Lyn'd with some Latine, that lykelie it may.
                  And if hee hit, and to a Purpose speake,
                  Then l
                        •…
                     ks hee lyke One to salue all the Sicke.
                  This Fellow effronted, hee never fayles,
                  In telling stale Iests, and olde merrie Tales.
                  For olde Ones to laugh, and the Young to allure,
                  Peares hee hath pocked, and Sweeties bee sure.
                  
                     Peartly hee speakes, as having Inspection▪
                  
                  And skilfull in knowing of evrie Complection.
                  And if a strange Cure hee stumble on, or chance,
                  Out of his Artlesse vse, and Ignorance;
                  Yet saucie, and shamelesse, sweareth this Ann▪
                  
                  That easily cure Incurables hee can.
                  Bot being vnlearnd, vnhonest, and als,
                  Oft times found foolish, found fraudfull, and false;
                  Indeed, if not Death, it's Danger to deale,
                  With such Quacke-salvers, for sicke Men, or Whole.
               
            
            
               A worthie Merchand, 24.
               
                  IS th'Heire of Adventure, whose Hopes doe hing,
                  On Gaine, that the Winds from the Waters bring:
                  With Halters of Hempe, and Horses of Tree,
                  Through the watrie waste Region rydeth hee:
                  And with a Merrie Gale chearfull hee is,
                  Furrowing the Foame, and shearing the Seas:
                  In Trading by Toyle, and Travell hee takes,
                  Discoveries of Coasts and Countreyes hee makes.
                  N'Hazard this Worthie from Ventring exempts,
                  Bot stablie hee stands in all his Attempts.
                  Hee spares not Expences, expecting his Gaines,
                  So Traffique and Trade, the Merchand maintaines.
                  His Studie is Number; his Care, his Accounts,
                  To know how 
                        〈◊〉
                      Meanes diminish, or mounts▪
                  
                  His effauld-Faythfull Formes are his Defence,
                  And greatest Comfort▪ is, his Conscience.
                  Hee trades not with a Measure false, his Fame
                  Is whole, and all▪ his Wealth, is his good Name.
                  Hee feares no Sill', and by Charibdis sayles,
                  Nor for a Wracke, hee out of measure wayles.
                  Altho with Tempests, hee bee tost and strest▪
                  
                  Yet hopes in the Hav'n to ryde, and to rest.
                  And by his Trade, and Labours long at leasure,
                  Hee gets his Goods, and finds the Key of Treasure.
                  Hee bringes, from th'Observations of his Eye,
                  The Modeles best, of Architecturie.
                  
                     And from a bought Exper'ence, and the Sourse
                  Of Knowledge high, hee draweth his Discourse.
                  What comely is abroad, and good, hee knowes,
                  Most circumspectly that at home hee showes.
                  In h
                        •…
                     s Apparell, hee is neat, and cleane,
                  And modest in demeanure, hee is seene.
                  Not daintie, nor too delicate, in Dyet,
                  Vsing the meane twixt Parcimon▪ and Ryot.
                  Full of Civilitie, and alwayes, (Note)
                  Hee Holy is, Religious, and Devote.
                  And to the Citie, Countrey, Court, and King,
                  What cannot wanting bee, doth daylie bring.
               
            
            
               An vnworthie Merchand. 25.
               
                  A Cheater hee is, that with a full Purse,
                  Will with the Best to the Board, and the Burse:
                  Then soberly bargaine, and promise to pay,
                  Peremptorly keepe his houre, and his day.
                  So craftily thus in Credite hee creepes,
                  For once hee or twise his Covenants keepes.
                  But Pedlar-lyke yet how ev'r hee begins,
                  More with his Wit, than Honestie, wins.
                  Hee lifts what hee can, from Coap-men, and Strangers,
                  While Credit hee cracks, and Conscience indangers.
                  At greatest rate, hee buyes the worst of Wares,
                  But for the Payment, neyther counts nor cares.
                  Yet with faire words tho false, these Forraigne Goods,
                  As trustie Stuffe, at Home, on Friends, h'obtrudes.
                  His Measures double are, and wrong his Weights,
                  And seldome holds (suppose he sweare) his Heights.
                  Hee passes not for Pietie, if Poore;
                  And if hee bee Rich, none dow him endure.
                  Hee in the Streets derayd, aboue his State,
                  A-gadding goes, and vp and downe doth jet.
                  Olde CHAVCERS Cooke, hee likned is vnto,
                  That busie seemes, where there is nought to doe.
                  Hee is a cogging Knaue, and craftie aye,
                  Over-Roguing all, that over-reach hee may.
                  
                     T'impone the Simple, 
                        〈◊〉
                      oft times are wittie,
                  Yet they dishonour, and they shame their Citie.
                  And with their Fashions 
                        〈◊〉
                      tho false, deface,
                  And are vnto all Merchands good disgrace.
                  Yet time decyphers these Deceivers all,
                  When they debosh, and play Bankrupt, with all.
               
            
            
               A Good Man, 26.
               
                  THat feares for Loue, his GOD, and in His Light
                  Of Trueth doth trace, and walks His Wayes aright;
                  And as in Loue, through Fayth, his GOD hee knaws,
                  To keepe in him the compasse of the Laws.
                  Of GOD, a Good Man is th'Idea, and
                  
                     A Lord ore all Hee create to Command▪
                  
                  To worship Him, and serue Him holy made,
                  Tho from Sinceritie, to Sinne, hee slade.
                  With Reason borne, to know Things Naturall,
                  Inspir'de by Grace, for Metaphysicall▪
                  
                  Hee hath a Face, that vp to Heaven doth bende,
                  
                     A Soule to Sense, that all the Life doth lende.
                  And to the Worlde is a Stranger given,
                  While of his Sprite the Home is onlie Heaven.
                  His Life a Time of Toyle, is strangely strest,
                  His Death, againe, the Walke and Way to Rest.
                  His Studie is, into the Word of Trouth,
                  Which carefullie hee keepeth in his Mouth:
                  And in his Life to practise it doth proue,
                  For his Delight is in the Law of Loue.
                  Hee doth provide bot for Necessitie,
                  And casts his Care in th'vse of Charitie.
                  Hee doth converse with divine Prophets, more
                  Than worldly Profits, to increase his Store.
                  In the Law of the LORD is all his pleasure,
                  And in His Knowledge, all his Wealth and Treasure.
                  His Bosome thus the best of Wit inclouds,
                  And thus hee's rich, into the best of Goods.
                  Heaven of his Eye, it is th'Extent and Scope,
                  And Life through CHRIST there-in his highest Hope.
                  
                     Humilitie, the Scale it is, where-by
                  Hee having Pride deprest, doth mount on hy.
                  His Patience is Procurer of his Peace,
                  That guyded is with Vertue, Wit, and Grace.
                  Hee is the Seede of Loue, and by th'effect
                  Of Grace, hee's Heire of Heaven, and Life Elect.
                  For all that hee doth care for, craue, and claime,
                  Is for that Heavenlie High IERVSALEM.
               
            
            
               A bad Man, or Atheist. 27.
               
                  WIth GOD, with Man, the World, himselfe, at Warre,
                  And what not, all hee to Damnation dare.
                  In Nature like a Dog; in Wit, an Asse,
                  And Beast-like hee doth in his Passion passe.
                  Into his Actions, which are alwayes evill,
                  Hee is a Corporall Incarnate Devill.
                  Hee maketh Sinne a Mocke; the BYBLE, a Bable,
                  GODS Grace, an Humour; and His Trueth, a Fable:
                  And calles it Cowardice, for to keepe Peace,
                  For troubled Tymes, hee holds his Happinesse.
                  His Castle hee doth call his Sword; and Pride,
                  The Horse, where-on this Hell-hound haunts to ryde.
                  His Purchase, Pyckrie is; his Language, Lyes;
                  His Longing, Lust; his Puncke, his Paradise.
                  And with a Whore, and a polluted Punke,
                  His Glorie is, to bee debosht, and drunke.
                  Hee is the Patron of Impietie,
                  And deadly Danger of Societie.
                  Hee Vertue loathes, and loveth Vanitie,
                  And is the Horrour of Humanitie.
                  In Bawdrie, and in Barratrie, h'abounds;
                  Till Bodie, Soule, and Fame, hee all confounds.
                  Hee boasts the Good, and hee vpbraids them broadly,
                  And spights at all the Gracious and Godly.
                  His Paunch is his Prince; the Taverne, his Towre;
                  Mahound, his Master; his Mistres, a Whore.
                  
                     Oathes are his Graces, and Woundes are his Badges:
                  Rebell, and Rogue, and Picke-purse, his Pages.
                  Hee knowes not GOD, nor goes where Grace doth dwell;
                  Bot walks through the World, like a Devill to Hell,
                  Hee Treachrous is, and a Truethlesse Detractor,
                  The Fellon, the Foole, the Fiends Benefactor.
                  Vntymely Begotten, and backwardly borne:
                  Vnworthilie waxes, and liveth forlorne.
                  A Monster to Men, a Foole to the Wise:
                  In doubting, Despare, and damned hee dyes.
               
            
            
               A wise Man, 28.
               
                  IS Like vnto a Clocke, that nev'r doth chyme,
                  Bot at the Houre, and striketh still in Tyme:
                  Or as a Dyall just, set with the Sunne;
                  Or Glasse that well doth keepe, and restlesse runn
                        •…
                     .
                  So will hee never ware a Word, bot whan
                  To speake pertains, vnto a Prudent Man.
                  Hee measures Time, and all in Season does:
                  Hee tempreth Nature, and doth Reason vse.
                  Sense hee commands, and Will hee keepeth vnder:
                  And all with Knowledge, hee doth pose and ponder.
                  None can his Eares with Charmes blow vp, and batter;
                  For fast They are, when Parasites doe flatter.
                  Closse is his Mouth, vnto detracting Tongues:
                  And no false Imputations hee impungs.
                  An humble Heart, an open Hand, and free,
                  Hee hath to Want, and vnto Pietie.
                  To Observation aye his Labours tende,
                  And wise Experience is his Ayme and Ende.
                  To Contemplation, and to meditate,
                  His Thoughts are oft devote, and dedicate.
                  The Divine VVord made Man, his VVill, his Law▪
                  
                  Is all that hee doth call for, cares to knaw.
                  Swolne Pride hee knowes no
                        •…
                      of Prosperitie,
                  Nor yet the Mis
                        •…
                     rie of Adversitie.
                  Bot takes the one, as if the Day, or Light,
                  And th'other, as the Darknesse, and the Night.
                  
                     Hee knowes not Fortune, and no Fate hee feares,
                  Bot builds, and all, on Providence hee reares.
                  And through the hope of Fayth, that Grace hath given,
                  Hee reaches high, and doth lay hold on Heaven.
                  His Workes are good, and Godly, as his Mynde,
                  His Words and Thoughts to Honour all inclynde:
                  For hee in Loue th 'Elect is of the LORD,
                  
                     A Master to the Worlde, that cares not for't.
                  And tho heere borne a Stranger, bot on Earth,
                  In Heav'n a Burger, by a second Birth.
               
            
            
               A Foole. 29.
               
                  A Foole hee is, the'Abortiue Birth of Wit,
                  And the vnfashiond Embrio of it:
                  Where Nature had more Power, than Reason Vse,
                  The Fruit of Imperfection to produce.
                  His Actions all, are almost all Extreames,
                  Of Meanes, nor Endes, hee never doubts, nor dreames.
                  Nature taught Fooles, to Eate, to Worke, and Sleepe,
                  Tho they there-in no Time nor Measure keepe.
                  Fooles haue no feare of GOD, respect to Men,
                  And voyde of Reason, they no Duetie ken.
                  Bot as their Passion, and their braine-sicke Wits,
                  Transport them, they doe play their foolish Fits.
                  His Exercise, it is foure▪folde alway,
                  H'eats, drinks, and sleepes, or then is laughing aye.
                  Fyue thinges doe humor him, and much doe moue,
                  And not bot these can hee thinke of, nor loue.
                  And what are they? a Bauble, a Bell, and bot
                  A pupped Pudding, or a pyed Coat.
                  His Wordes want Wit, and Reasonlesse his Will;
                  For it resolv'd, doth neither good nor ill.
                  Hee Wisdome and Instruction doth despise,
                  Since hee can nought, or hee will not bee wyse.
                  His Front, his Index is, and doth expresse,
                  His Mindes distemprature and giddinesse.
                  His foolish Fits, neyther the Bad doe please,
                  Nor can the Good bee seene content with these.
                  
                     Hee out of Measure is in Motion ever,
                  And bot when hee doth sleepe, hee resteth never.
                  Hee is vnhappily begotten and borne,
                  (Tho not his fault) Reason and Wisdomes Scorne.
                  A Shame to's Syre, a Blott vnto his Brother:
                  A Curse to's Kin, a Mischiefe to his Mother.
                  Hee liues a Beast, and doth no better die,
                  But Wit and Reason, Natures Infamie.
               
            
            
               A plaine honest Man 30.
               
                  LIke IACOB is, and dwelleth into Tents,
                  Not full of Congi
                        •…
                     s and Court Complements:
                  Bot hee is faithfull, efauld, free, and plaine;
                  And so but change, immobile doth remaine.
                  Like to a Coat, that is so well prepar'd,
                  To fit the Wearer plaine, but Welt, or Gard.
                  When as the Stuffe where-of the same is made,
                  Nor is the forme, in more request is had:
                  So th'honest Heart, but Fraude (that breedes Offence)
                  The Credit keeps of a good Conscience.
                  Fred from infernall Brands of Infamie;
                  From Scandall, and deserved Obloquie.
                  His works are vert'ous, and his Words are Trueth:
                  His Progresse plaine, and all his Practize Rueth.
                  His Life is Labour past with Patience,
                  His Rest is Death, and his Sprites Passage hence.
                  His Travell is from Infancie to Age,
                  A painfull Passage, and a Pilgrimage.
                  His Wayes yet plainnesse, and his Pleasure, Peace;
                  His whole delight, is loue, his Glorie, grace.
                  His Crdit, is his Coyne, Reason, his Square:
                  Content, his Kingdome, Conscience, his Care.
                  His Carr'age courtous is, and no waies vaine:
                  His Heart is humble, holie, and humane.
                  Hee 
                        〈◊〉
                      is Churlish, ever Charitable:
                  In Talking, and Discourses, delectable▪
                  
                  
                     Hee ever was, and ever will bee found,
                  Amongst rich Iemms, the rightest Diamond.
                  
                     A Phenix amongst Fowles: yea, hee is borne,
                  Mongst Men a Sainct, mongst Beasts an Vnicorne.
               
            
            
               A Knaue, 31.
               
                  THe Worst of Wit, and the Scorne of Reason,
                  Begot but Grace, and syne borne▪ out of Season.
                  Hee is the Shame of good Societie,
                  And Promptuarie of Impietie.
                  Hee doth dishonour all the humane Race,
                  And is past helpe of GOD, past Hope of Grace.
                  Hee corrupts Age, and hee infecteth Youth:
                  Hee hateth Wisdome, and detracts the Trueth.
                  His Words are false, his Oathes proue perjuries:
                  His Studies, Trickes; his Practise, Villanies.
                  His Wealth, for Wit and Honour, hee doth holde:
                  
                     
                        •…
                     or Glorie, Gaine; and for his God, his Gold.
                  To Trust, a Traytor; t'Amitie, a Thiefe:
                  Prompe in the Plots, and Practise of Mischiefe.
                  A Friend to none, or found to few is hee,
                  And yet hee is aye his owne Enemie.
                  An Vnthrift since his Breathing first, and Birth;
                  Abhorr'd in Heav'n, vnhallowed on the Earth.
                  His Heart of Poyson is a Pond that springs,
                  His Tongue deceitfull, and lyke Dragons Stings.
                  And lyke a Limbecke is his fleeting Braine,
                  That doth distill Inventions vilde and vaine.
                  Hee loues no Lawes, nor counts of their Commands:
                  For Hell, Mahound, and hee hath shaken Hands.
                  And as hee VVolfe-lyke liues, false like a Foxe;
                  
                     
                        •…
                     ee Dogg-lyke dies, or in the Streets, or Stockes.
               
            
            
               
               An Vsurer, 32.
               
                  THe Character and Patterne is expresse,
                  Of worldly Miserie, and VVretchednesse.
                  The Gold and Money that these Misers haue,
                  Their Master is, and they their Silvers Slaue.
                  What they doe call, and for their owne doe claime,
                  They haue it not for it bot holdeth Them.
                  They haue no Grace Divine, nor God, bot it,
                  VVhich robs their Reason, and bereaues their VVit.
                  The more they come by, more and more they craue;
                  And wish their Gardivyots were their Graue.
                  For where their Heart and Treasure is, there would
                  They ly, and bee engraveld with their Gold.
                  Their Greed it is, s'vnsatiate, and such,
                  Gaine what they lyke, they cannot get too much.
                  Their ev'r vnbounded Pleasure in their Pence,
                  Makes them but Soule, but sight, but Shame, but Sence.
                  Their Feare, is VVant, and for to get, their Care:
                  Their Dyet is, plaine Fasting, or poore Fare.
                  Their Studie, Sparing; and their loathsome lyfe,
                  Still with it selfe is at Debate and Stryfe.
                  Their Habit, and their Cloathing, oft declares,
                  They were the Hang-mans, or of rouped VVares.
                  Their Teeth of Interest destroyes and eates,
                  And is a Canker vnto all Estates.
                  They swill, they sucke, and like Loach-Leeches Bloods,
                  And drinke their Debters Substance, and their Goods.
                  They loathed liue, and vnlamented die:
                  Drudges to Drosse, and Mappes of Miserie.
               
            
            
               A Beggar, 33.
               
                  A Laysie Lout, that doth himselfe professe.
                  The Fellow, Pheire, and Mate of Idlenesse.
                  His Lyfe a Resolution is of Ease:
                  High-wayes, his VValke, hee travels most in these.
                  
                     Bot th' Ale-house is the Place of his Retreat,
                  Where with his VVhore hee will not misse to meete.
                  And there ore-turnes, and freely tosse the Pot,
                  That with a feign'd Infirmitie they got.
                  For busily his Studies are all bent,
                  To counterfit th'Infirme, and Impotent.
                  And all his Practise, is espyde to bee,
                  To cogg, and coozen simple Charitie.
                  Of all the Rabble of all ranging Rogues,
                  None are more noysome, than th
                        •…
                     se swarming Frogs.
                  For into everie Hamlet, Towne, and Farme,
                  Lyke Caterpillars they doe flocke and swarme.
                  At Bed, at Board, from Home, and in the House,
                  Their Fellow and Companion is a Lowse.
                  VVith Blessings they begin, and pray for all;
                  Bot into Cursing ofttimes ends their Call.
                  None lives on th'Earth Religious lesse than they,
                  They prey on Men, yet nev'r to GOD they pray.
                  Thanks none, or few, to Him they giue; and lesse
                  Regard they giue their Givers in Distresse.
                  No, none more 
                        •…
                     ewdlie liues, and more impure,
                  And none are worse, and vicious more bee sure.
                  They carnall are, and lustfull, out of Measure,
                  And brutish in the acting of their Pleasure.
                  They Marrie seldome, baptize nev'r their Brood,
                  And others know, but Caring, Kynd, or Blood.
                  Th'are Atheists almost all, and in effect,
                  God nor the Devill, Hell, Lord, nor Law respect.
                  They trade by Beggrie, many tymes by Stealth▪
                  
                  And alwayes VVasters of the Common-wealth.
                  His Birth, his Lyfe, and Death, oft falleth thus,
                  Hee's gotten and borne into a Barne and Bush.
                  Then ydlie dryues his Dayes, and leads his Lyfe,
                  VVithout all Law, and her that for his VVyfe
                  Hee holds, a VVhore, a Th
                        •…
                     efe is, or a VVitch;
                  And last, hee ends and dyeth in a Ditch.
               
            
            
               
               A Virgine, 34.
               
                  IS like the Lillies, and the Crimson Roses,
                  When PHOEBVS force their luked Leaues v
                        •…
                     loses:
                  VVhich kythe in Colours pure, and all Ingraine,
                  But anie Macule, Tash, or anie Staine,
                  Shee's Natures Beautie, in her chiefest Pryde,
                  In Chastitie, and Vertues Tinctures dy'de:
                  VVhere th'vnpolluted Spirit Gracious,
                  Doth make her Angell-like, and Glorious▪
                  
                  Shee's Vertues Darling, VVi
                        •…
                     domes Milk-whyte Doue,
                  Reasons Care▪ and shee is Honours Loue.
                  The Grace of Youth, the Comfort of the Age,
                  In both discreet, in both digest and sage.
                  Her Studies, and her Exercises, holy;
                  But Petulance, lascivious Sports, or Folly.
                  An handsome, humble Gravitie, her Grace,
                  VVith comely Carr'age, and a constant Pace.
                  Louely her Looks, and yet most chaste her Eye,
                  Her Countenance severe, yet sweet to see.
                  Her Actions all, are with her VVords, that's Trueth,
                  Her Constancie, her Fame, in Age, and Youth.
                  Her Wealth, her Vertues are, her Grace, her Glore,
                  Her Labour, Patience, and Content her Store.
                  Her vsuall Dyet, it is Abstinence,
                  Her Ornament, and Crowne, is Continence.
                  Her Lawne-like Loue, vnspotted is▪ and cleane,
                  Her Orisons devote, her Hopes divine.
                  Her Parents Pleasure, Honour of her Kin,
                  And Phoenix of the Land shee liveth in.
                  Of Female kinde, shee is the first and fairest,
                  And one of all the Rationall, that's Rarest.
                  And to bee found the Heavens beneath, and vnder,
                  The choysest Iewell, and the chiefest Wonder.
               
            
            
               
               A wanton Woman. 35
               
                  A VVanton VVoman, 's Vicious, and strange,
                  The type of Imperfection, and of Change.
                  In Qualitie a VVag-taile, and in shape,
                  A Siren; in her Nature, bot an Ape.
                  Her Vult, a Witch; inviting to all Evill:
                  For shee into Condition is a Devill.
                  Her Words are Charmes, and everie Nod, a Net,
                  To snare the Foole; and for the fleshlie set.
                  Her Looks are Hooks, and Baits, bot to Abusion:
                  Her Companie is Death, Iosse, Confusion:
                  Her lustfull Lips, like Hybla-Honey Drops;
                  Bot loathsome sowre these Liquors haue their Sops.
                  Her Mouth is soft, and smoother more than Oyle:
                  Bot what it speaks, doth poyson, spill, and spoyle.
                  Her Ende is worse, and bitterer by farre,
                  Than Worme wood, Gall, that tarte and bitter are.
                  Her Heart with Pride, and with Deceit doth swell:
                  Her Feete to Death, her Steps treade downe to Hell.
                  Her kynde Imbraces, and her Kisses killes:
                  Her Breath for Balme, bot bitter Venome stilles.
                  Her wav'ring Wit, bot naughtie Fancies nowrish:
                  And all her Thoughts are wanton, vaine, all Whorish.
                  Her Life is lewde, all Ydlenesse, and Play:
                  Her Dyet is th'excesse of Dainteis aye.
                  Her Loue is Vanitie; and still in Change:
                  And as her Eyes, so her Affections range.
                  Her Excercise, bot Rest; and yet are whollie,
                  Busied about Inventions bot of Follie.
                  Her Fancies are for Fashions, Toyes, and Showes:
                  Her VVeale in Colours, and her VVealth in Cloathes.
                  To catch, and cozin Men, is all her Care,
                  Her House, an Hell, and all 's vnholie there.
                  Her VVayters on, are Bauds, for Beasts and Bables:
                  Her Friendship false, and her Discourses Fables.
                  She is the Plague of Youth, Repentance Storie,
                  Th' Abuse of Tyme, and Ages Purgatorie.
               
            
            
               
               A Quyet Woman, 36.
               
                  IS lyke a Winde, low, quyet, calme, and still,
                  That blowes no Dust, nor doth the Bodie chill:
                  Whom nev'r Impatience doth provoke, and moue,
                  Bot with her Patience wins the Heart of Loue.
                  Her VVisdome makes her VVill to bee preferd,
                  And worthilie to get a great Regard.
                  Shee feares the LORD, flees Sinne, and loveth Peace:
                  Shee walkes to Heav'n; her Guyde thereto, is Grace.
                  Shee helpes and aydes, into Asperitie,
                  And takes a parte into Prosperitie.
                  Her Tongue is still vnto Discretion tyed:
                  Her Face with modest Shamefastnesse is dyed.
                  Shee is her Husbands Heart, his Loue, his Chose,
                  And Doane-Bed, where his Spirites doe repose.
                  Her braue Behaviour, is a Glasse, where-by
                  Her Children may their owne Miscarr'age see.
                  She treades vpon the Tortoys, never strayes
                  From Home, nor ydlie walkes vpon the Wayes.
                  Her Vertuous Doings, they doe her adorne;
                  Shee cares not Change, and Fortune shee doth scorne.
                  A Turtle to her Husband, in her Loue;
                  And meeke to him, shee lyke a Lambe doth proue.
                  No, nev'r what hee concludeth, doth controule;
                  An Angell, and a Sainct into her Soule.
                  Shee is a Pearle, that is vnprizable;
                  A Pleasure great that is vnspeakable,
                  A Comfort too, that is Incomparable,
                  And in the Worlde, a Wyfe Inimitable.
               
            
            
               An vnquiet Woman, 37.
               
                  SHee is a Thing, much worse to keepe than Knaw;
                  A Beast that brooks Subjection to no Law.
                  The Mischiefe, and the Miserie of Man,
                  That scarcely can descrybed bee: and whan
                  
                     It is, into the verie Hearts and Heads
                  Of Law and Reason, Detest
                        •…
                     aion breeds.
                  For her Demeanures, they indeede are Theams,
                  Which aye and onlie stand into Extreams.
                  Her Words and Voyce, the scrighing of an Owle,
                  That to affright Men, on the Night doth yowle.
                  Her Eyes, even as the Cockatrice, doe kill:
                  Her Hands, the Clawes are of the Crocadill.
                  Her Heart, a Cabinet, that doth containe
                  All that is naughtie, vicious, and prophane.
                  Tyme shee abuseth, and shee woundeth Wit:
                  No Reason shee regards, bot wrongeth it.
                  Shee is impure, her Pryde vnsupportable:
                  Her Malice, matchlesse; Will, vnsatiable.
                  Shee doth respect, nor anie person spares:
                  Defame shee fears not, nor for Counsell cares.
                  Her Wit is Will, Command, is, Must, not No:
                  
                  Her Reason, Shall; her Satisfaction, So.
                  
                  Shee cannot loue, lyke, nor allowes no Lord,
                  And doth from Law and Order both debord.
                  Shee is a Crosse, bot not of CHRIST, a Crosse:
                  
                     A Griefe to Nature, and to Lyfe a Losse.
                  And from her Birth, shee's emptie of all Grace:
                  
                     A Plague to Pietie, a Foe to Peace.
                  
                     A Wracke of Wealth, a Wrangler, full of Wrath:
                  Most Tarte in Taste, and in Digestion, Death.
               
            
            
               A GOOD WYFE. 38.
               
                  A World of Wealth, a Iewell good and great,
                  And to her Lord, a Kingdome, in Conceat:
                  An Heavenlie Blessing, and Mans Happinesse,
                  That nought, not Death, can minish, nor make lesse.
                  Her Husbands Iewell, and her Childrens Ioe:
                  Ever Vertues Friend, and ever Vices Foe.
                  Her Conversation, is solacious:
                  Her Count'nance graue, yet ever gracious.
                  Her Tongue is temprate, and her Eye is warie:
                  Her Carriage is kynde, yet chaste and charie.
                  
                     Shee's gracefull graue, a Mirrour to her Mayds:
                  Her Beautie naturall, but Arte, but Ayds.
                  Shee with no Pomate paints her Face, nor fairds:
                  Nor doth not vse with Oyle to smooth't▪ and smeard,
                  To make it show before the Sunne, and shyne,
                  To helpe pure Nature, wrong the Worke Divyne.
                  But shee doth count it well, and best decor'd,
                  As fashion'd with the Finger of the LORD.
                  Shee's Mistres of her Passions, and her Tongue
                  To Reasons Girdle it is tyde, and hung.
                  Next Heaven, her House shee holds her chiefest Care,
                  And that her good Houswyfrie doth declare.
                  Shee goes not gadding, bot at Home shee dwells:
                  And when shee goes shee goes on Tortois Shells.
                  Shee in Apparell is, and cloathed cleanlie;
                  Not too magnificke, no, nor yet too meanlie.
                  Her Words are wyse, her Voyce is Musicall,
                  And al
                        •…
                      her Actions are Harmonicall.
               
            
            
               An Effoeminate Man, 39.
               
                  IS lyke a Man, to see, in shape, in sho,
                  That hath the Forme, and in effect is no.
                  Hee is a primped Piece, and therefore than,
                  Is Womanish, and bot a Chyldish Man.
                  Into his Relish, hee is Liquorous:
                  In Loue, and his Desires, Libidinous.
                  Hee tryfles Tyme, and bot with Puppets playes:
                  
                     A-Wenching walks, and ydlie dryues his Dayes.
                  Hee covets for to looke in Mirrours oft:
                  For to sleepe sound, and to lye long, and soft.
                  Hee loues to bee imbrac'd, and to bee kist;
                  And then, aboue the Best, hee thinks him blest.
                  Hee'inanelie talks, a Looke demure hee shoes:
                  Hee mirds too much, and too-too nycelie goes.
                  Hee Iuncates loues, and Dainties much desyres;
                  And for to Ball, and Banquet, never Tyres.
                  To bee his Mistres Man, hee vrgeth still:
                  Bot to bee a Master to her Mayde hee will.
                  
                     To frame lewde Lines, and sing Loue Songs, hee loues:
                  To smell Perfumes, and haue sweete watred Gloues.
                  Hee coyneth Purposes, and telleth Lyes:
                  Hee studies Daunces, and Riddles doth devyse.
                  Hee loues Good-morrowes, and yet doth delight
                  To sleepe the Morning, and to watch all Night.
                  Hee doates to heare, and wandring Newes to chace:
                  And hunting for Them, haunts the Market place.
                  Hee sighs for Loue, and will for Kyndnesse greete:
                  Yea, with each Humor will a Cadance keepe.
                  His Game with Girls is most at Barla-breakes:
                  And after, on his Bed Tobaccho takes.
                  And then with Frictions, and with Cloathes fyre hot,
                  Full of these Fumes, breathes lyke a boyling Pot.
                  This Ganimede, soft, nyce, and Man-turn'd-Woman,
                  In verie deede, and in effect is No-man.
               
            
            
               A Parasite, 40.
               
                  HEE is the Picture of Impietie;
                  To gaine a Groat, avowde to Villanie.
                  For with a flattring Tongue hee will not fayle,
                  To picke Mens Pockets, and their Money steale.
                  His Face is Brazed, that hee cannot blush:
                  Shame set asyde, none hee regardes a Rush.
                  And what hee lighteth on with both his Hands,
                  Hee holdes; for they are lym'd, and lyke Bird Wands.
                  His Tongue vntymous, clinketh lyke a Bell,
                  And nought but Tryfling Truethlesse Tales doth tell.
                  Hee playes the Pandare, and with Gracelesse Greetings,
                  Hee carries Messages, for Evill Meetings.
                  And with smoothe Wordes, which hee is cunning in,
                  Perswades a sorte of Sweetnesse into Sinne.
                  Hee is much lyke a Dogg without a Doore;
                  Where-at the Devill to daunce, went in before.
                  Or lyke a mounted Spyder hee doth show▪
                  
                  And yet but liues on Poyson heere Below.
                  So hee may gayne, hee lookes not who doth losse,
                  And for a Crowne his Credite hee will cosse.
                  
                     Hee hath no Honestie, and doth no Duetie:
                  Hee spoyles the Youth, and is th'Abuse of Beautie.
                  
                     A Knaue at Court, a Cheater in the Citie,
                  That should bee punisht, and expell'd but Pittie,
                  
                     A Iester alwayes, (tho his Iestes bee stall)
                  Hee is, and is a Iacke-an-Apes in all.
               
            
            
               A Baude. 41.
               
                  A Baude, shee is a kynde of Woman-beast,
                  That spoyles Virginitie, and Mayden-heads maist:
                  For dissolutelie when shee was bot young,
                  Shee vitiate, and did her owne a Wrong.
                  And ever since, without Remorse or Feare,
                  Shee vseth sundrie Men, and Merchands Geare.
                  And for vntymous Trading with their Wares,
                  Into her Age Post to the Fiend shee fares.
                  To Damsels shee is dangerous, lest these,
                  Shee with th'Oft-Falling-Sicknesse and Disease,
                  Doe fyle them, and infect; for shee was ever
                  Since shee was twelue yeares, touched with that Fever.
                  The Youth to spell, nev'r trust her for to teach,
                  (Altho for Proofes and Practise she might Preach)
                  Lest that shee doe, scarce well weand from the Mother,
                  Learne them too soone to Poynt, and put Together.
                  Shee playes the Surgeon, that can ease no Smarts,
                  Bot only swellings in the lower Parts.
                  Shee hath one song, and it shee soundeth aye;
                  
                     Tyme is, Tyme was, and Tyme will weare away.
                  Sweet Daintie Things, therefore, neglect not You,
                  To vse the Tyme, and take your Pleasure now,
                  Incace when it is past, Occasion gone,
                  You sit vnsought, and courted bee with None.
                  And while this Toothlesse vents her vicious Voyce,
                  From a waste Wombe, and Brest with birnings bosse,
                  T'affright the Fiend, flat falne, and low-lyke shoes,
                  (As eldren Apes) her Cheeks, her Chin, her Nose.
                  
                     The Humour that shee's most displeasing in,
                  Is at her Disabilitie to Sinne.
                  And shee is nev'r more joviall, than when
                  Shee is perswaded, Shee is young for Men.
                  Shee cares for nothing, nothing bot her Ease,
                  Loues bot her Lust, pains bot her Panch to please.
                  She sels her Soule, for Sacke, for Bottle-Ale;
                  For to lay downe her Flesh, Shee will not faile.
                  In nought bot one, is shee Industrious,
                  In th'Hospitall, or in the Baudie House.
                  To see the Wenches well set all to Warke;
                  Bot almost ever, and oftest in the Darke.
                  Her Breath corrupt, her Head is balde, her Eyes
                  Rheumaticke, running thou beholds and sees.
                  Shee's Vertues Spoyle, and Graces great Regrate,
                  The Wracke of Wealth, Natures Disdaine, and Hate:
                  For SHEE is stomached, and still doth storme,
                  That so deform'd a Monster shee should forme.
               
            
            
               A Drunkard. 42.
               
                  A Drunkard, to define him, is a Beast,
                  Tho hee the Figure haue, and bee Man-fac't.
                  Man Cup-shot, is no Man, no, scarce in part;
                  For hee hath neyther Hands, nor Head, nor Heart.
                  Hee is a Nowne, and an Adjectiue One,
                  That by himselfe, well can not stand alone.
                  And yet a Tryer, and Contestor great,
                  Into his Weakenesse, and that stau'ring State.
                  If that in Surfets, Health, or Sicknesse shall,
                  The Mastrie haue, command, and o're-rule all.
                  Hee is the Figure of Deformitie:
                  And th'evidence of all enormitie.
                  H'abuseth Time, and Natures Rights ore-turns,
                  Hee wasteth Wealth, at Reason spights, and spur
                        •…
                     ns.
                  All Modestie h'anoyeth, and hee 
                        •…
                     oarres,
                  All temp'rate Sprites hee frights from him and skarrs.
                  
                     Civilitie hee doth disturbe, and trouble;
                  And all Disorder Orderlesse doth double.
                  Hee's Woe to his Wife; to his Children Griefe:
                  His Neighbours Skoffe, and to himselfe a Thiefe.
                  His Feete doe reele, his Tougue at Randon runnes,
                  Hee doth, hee sayes, and knows not what, yet sinnes.
                  Hee blasts, hee braiks, hee bans, and hee blaspheams:
                  Hee shouts, or sleeps, and still is in Extreams▪
                  
                  Hee wastes, and wots not how, and so doth weaken,
                  His Stomacks strength, altho that it were oaken.
                  The Sober sigh, and for his Fashions flees him:
                  And all beside they scoffe and scorne that sees him.
                  And so hee serues for nought, except to shame,
                  Himselfe, and slay his Bodie, Soule, and Fame.
               
            
            
               A Coward, 43.
               
                  THe Fruite of Feare, Suspition, and of Dreed,
                  Whom Nature got, bot in colde Blood did breed.
                  And had too much a-doe, to make vp than,
                  A Creature, that should resemble a Man.
                  And that is all hee keepeth of his Kind,
                  For beastly base dejected is his Minde.
                  His Life a Sicknesse is, that doth resemble,
                  A sort of Palsie, for his Ioyntes doe tremble.
                  And but a Cause, such Terrour hee will take,
                  That hee will faint, and all his Members shake.
                  His Death then by debased Diffidence,
                  It is a Terrour to his Conscience,
                  His feeble Faith, no kinde of Hope it beares,
                  And therefore Death hee out of Measure feares.
                  All Persons hee suspects, and everie Place,
                  And therefore wretched is the Cowards Case.
                  Hee much affecteth Peace, for feare of Warres;
                  The thought of which his Sprite affrights and sca
                        •…
                     res.
                  And if hee bleede his Finger, hee anone,
                  Looks for the Signe, and layes, his Life is gone.
                  
                     And if his Tooth but ake, incontinent
                  Hee makes his Latter Will, and Testament.
                  The Roaring, and Report, that Cannons giues,
                  Prostrates him flat, and neare of Sprite depriues.
                  And Thunder-claps doe him discourage so,
                  That hee can neyther stand, nor stirre, nor goe.
                  Before hee fight, or to Combate hee kythe,
                  Content is hee, and to bee beaten, blythe.
                  And if his Feete may succour him, bee sure
                  His Head, nor Hands, no danger shall endure.
                  Hee of no Hazard heares, nor hardie Feats,
                  Bot, fy for Shame, hee shudders, and hee sweats.
                  Hee will b'affrayde, with flying of a Bird,
                  Or noyse of Wands that with the Winds are stird.
                  Marrie hee will, and marrie bot with Such,
                  As are bot Meane, and not of Might too much.
                  Nor will hee haue a Wife that's faire: For why?
                  Some Broyls may bee, and Quarrels come there-by.
                  And when hee getts her, if hee finds her frowne,
                  Then hee's abash'd, dejected, and cast downe.
                  If shee bot chance to chyde him, than hee weepes;
                  And comes as Spanels, when they couch, and creepes.
                  Where Dogs doe barke, hee comes not neare that House,
                  Bot flees, as from the Catts th'amated Mouse.
                  If hee bee rich, for feare hee nev'r concludes,
                  How to dispose vpon, or vse his Goods.
                  And in his Nature, NATVR
                        •…
                      doth defame,
                  For hee doth Manhood both disgrace and shame.
               
            
            
               An Honest Poore Man, 44.
               
                  HEE is a Proofe and Map of Miserie,
                  In patient porting of his Pe
                        •…
                     urie.
                  With Wants vnknowne, hee doth resolue to sterue,
                  Than those relieue, and with Discredit serue.
                  
                     Hee prooues his Patience▪ and her strength hee tryes,
                  In suffring Griefe but grudge, even while hee dyes.
                  His Little is Much, his meane and sober Rent,
                  Affords him Store, rich quyet, and content,
                  Yet some times so the Touch of Want him plyes,
                  That from his Heart Teares burst out at his Eys
                        •…
                     :
                  And from his Soule such Pailes of Sighs, and smoake,
                  Are sent, that would impatient Spirits choake.
                  Bot so his Reason his hote Passions temper,
                  That it controules, and moderates them Semper.
                  Yet blushes oft for shame of Beggarie,
                  Or with the Sense of his Necessitie.
                  For Rich Men shun, and flee him like Infection,
                  His Wants refuse, his Sutes, finds all Rejection.
                  And with a Frowning, cold and carelesse Eye.
                  Or with a Skoffe th'vpbraide him going by.
                  His Lodging is the Earth, and oftimes even
                  The Banke his Bed, his Courtanes clouds of Heaven.
                  Rootes his Repaste, bot fending or'e his Fare,
                  And such poore Portion as the Godly spare,
                  The Sunne his Summer-Comfort vntill Night,
                  The Moone his To
                        •…
                     ch, his Lampe, and Winter Light.
                  His Mournings are the Musicke of his Breath
                        •…
                     
                  
                  His Songs are Swan-like, sung before his death.
                  His studie, Patience, and his Labour Prayer:
                  And yet with-all, meeke are his Forms, and faire.
                  His Life below a Pilgrimage doth prooue,
                  His Resting Rowme and Home, is Heaven aboue.
                  Hee lightlie liues, and as no Man, neglected,
                  And dyes not moand, not mist, no, nor respected;
                  Yet tho the Worlde his Wants and State contemne,
                  Hee shall inherite th'High IERVSALEM.
                  And more nor hee (stands in the State of Grace,)
                  That hath the Worlds Prosperitie and Peace.
                  Hee fullie hath the Favour of the LORD,
                  And hee with Faith, with Hope, and Loue is stor
                        •…
                     d:
                  And there-in hath for him reserv'd a Treasure,
                  Past Reckning, Rich, Great, past all Meanes &amp; Measure.
               
            
            
               
               A Iust Man, 45.
               
                  THe Childe of Trueth and Vertue both, a Birth
                  That shall inherite Heaven, inhabite Earth.
                  For Nature in a meane and temprate Mood,
                  Bred and brought foorth this Fruit, as Rare, as Good.
                  His Eyes from wilfull Blindnesse they are cleare;
                  His Hands from Blood and Brybrie are enteare.
                  His Will is voyde and free from Wilfulnesse;
                  His Heart most holy, hath no Wickednesse.
                  His Word and Deede are ev'r and alwayes one:
                  Hee violates, nor this, nor that, to None.
                  His Lyfe doth show the Nature of his Loue,
                  Whose Aime, whose Ende, and Object is Aboue.
                  His efauld Dealing, and his Deeds declare,
                  To keepe his Conscience cleane, his constant Care.
                  The chiefest Comfort that such happie haue,
                  Th'assurance is of Lyfe, and to bee saue.
                  When as hee on the Bench a Iudge doth sit,
                  Hee ponders all, and powders all with Wit
                  With closed Hands, and Single eyes hee shawes,
                  That there hee sits to grace as giue the Lawes.
                  And thus in judging, so his Iudgement proues,
                  Hee honours Reason, and hee Iustice loues.
                  Hee feares not Power t'Equall, and to Place,
                  With Iustice, Rigour; Mercie myld, with Grace.
                  Hee feares the LORD, and as hee loues Him too,
                  His Worship hee, in Feare, and Loue doth doe.
                  His Walks are v
                        •…
                     rt'ous, in his Makers Sight,
                  Hee treads not by-Rods, bot hee traces Right.
                  Hee loues the Good, the Bad hee cannot by de:
                  Hee loues Humilitie, and hateth Pryde.
                  His Works are alwayes worthie for his Deeds:
                  As Honour bringes Them foorth, so Vertue breeds.
                  And Wisdome fostring war'lie weaneth Them,
                  For his rich Vertue, to renowne his Name.
                  So that hee hath an vnderstanding Braine,
                  And Sprite of Knowledge, more than is Humane.
                  And thereby is One from Aboue that's Bl
                        •…
                     st,
                  And on the Earth, One earthly, that is Best.
               
            
            
               
               A Repentant Sinner, 46.
               
                  OF all Forlorne, hee finds himselfe the First,
                  And vowes hee is of Wretches all the Worst:
                  So bad is the Estate hee standeth in,
                  While hee is sowsed in the Seas of Sinne.
                  Hee sighes, therefore, and for his Guilt doth groane,
                  And sends Remorsefull thoughts to MERCIES THRONE;
                  To pray for Pardon, Pittie, and Compassion,
                  For CHRISTS most bloodie, and most bitter Passion.
                  And offers with a broken Heart contreete,
                  Of Prayse and Thanks a Sacrifice most sweet.
                  Whose sad Remembrance, all his Entralls teares,
                  And makes him weepe, and wash his Couch with Teares
                  The hate of Sinne, is figur'd in his Face,
                  By th'operation of the Sprite of Grace.
                  Hee covets nothing, bot such things that are
                  Conducent for him, and most necessare.
                  Superfluous, and vaine hee doth abhorre,
                  And nev'r delights in these that's transitore▪
                  
                  Hee lusts not after more, than hee would haue,
                  Yet more contemplates▪ than hee can conceiue.
                  The sharpe Recording of his Sinnes doth search,
                  His secret Soule, and to the Spleane doth pearse.
                  While in the Detestation of them all,
                  Woefull hee weepes, for his Offence and Fall.
                  Yet still his Hopes for Mercie springs Aboue,
                  Despare and Feare, through Force of Fayth and Loue.
                  His Senses tyre his Sprites, and thus distrest,
                  His Soule in Natures Course can finde no Rest.
                  The Slough of Sinne, and Rags of Vice hee wore,
                  Hee shifts him off, and mynds to vse no more.
                  Bot as that Snake, that slayeth with the Sight,
                  All Sinne, all Wrong, and Vice, hee doth despight.
                  Hee laboures still in Loue, and liuely Fayth,
                  To liue to GOD in Feare, and at his Death
                  To die in favour, that hee may in Heav'n
                  Enjoy the Glorie GOD hath freely given.
               
            
            
               
               A Reprobate, 47.
               
                  HEE is the Worke of Violence and Wrath,
                  The Sonne of Sinne, but Hope, but Loue of Faith:
                  Who beeing borne, for Service of the Devill,
                  But Care doth all, and all hee doth is Evill.
                  No Villanie escapes him, that hee can:
                  For loathsome Sinnes delighteth most this Man.
                  His Wits are wandring, weake, and still vnstable,
                  His Speech prophaine, impure, vnprofitable.
                  His Actions orderlesse, and scelerate;
                  Corrupted all, curst, and contaminate.
                  With all these Ills, that with the Fiends downe fell,
                  From th'highest Heaven, vnto the lowest Hell.
                  For Wisdome, stands his Will: which while its so,
                  Bot Furie, or bot Follie, flows there-froe.
                  Hee's full of Infidelitie, Mistrust,
                  And onlie doth delight t'injure the Iust.
                  The Simple hee deceiues, and sucks the Blood;
                  And vnder Trust, of th'Innocent and Good.
                  His Breath is bot the Blast of Blasphemie,
                  And all his Practise proues Impietie.
                  His Conscience cauteriz'd, his Senses 
                        •…
                     eard,
                  His Heart is hardned, and hee is not feard
                  To Fault and Fall, bot like a Free-man fares,
                  And nev'r in Publicke his Trespassing spares.
                  Hee worships seldome, and it is in vaine,
                  Like Cains Sacrifice, because prophane.
                  Hee is indur'd, an Out-cast from the LORD;
                  Impenitent, vnmyndfull to remord.
                  His wicked wishes are the wracke of those,
                  That Vertous, godly are, and Vices Foes.
                  Hee loues Confusion, and desires Disorder,
                  And Boucher-like, bathes in the Blood of Murder.
                  T'oppresse and spoyle, hee bot a Mirding makes,
                  And scorns the Law, when hee her Statutes breaks.
                  And bee hee put in a respected Place,
                  The Good they smart, the guiltie gets the Grace.
                  
                     Remorse, regarde, nor Pittie hee hath none;
                  For Feare of GOD and Hope of Grace is gone.
                  This Peace-Oppressor, Lawlesse, Litigious;
                  This damn'd Reprobate, and Irreligious,
                  Is a Man-Monster, and an Humane Evill;
                  A Diabolicke, and Incarnate Devill.
               
            
            
               An Holie Man, 48.
               
                  HIs heart is Heavenly, and his Hopes are hie,
                  Ev'r over-mounting all Mortalitie.
                  Things that's corrupt, hee doth contemne, and hold
                  All Mammons Meanes, bot Mucke, Goods, Treasure, Gold.
                  No Honours heere, nor Pleasure hee respects,
                  Bot thinks they are of Fancies, frayle Effects.
                  The Soli-loquies of his Soule are sweet,
                  His Mouth and Mynde in Meditation meet.
                  Natures Perfection, is an Holie Man,
                  And the best Good that Shee exhibite can.
                  For what hath Earth more perfect than that Spright,
                  In Sanctitie that serues his GOD aright?
                  Yet Nature perfects no such Peace alone,
                  But Grace and Fayth their working there-vpon.
                  The Holy Man, is only hee that's wyse,
                  For only Heav'n hee holds before his Eyes.
                  And what is heere Below, and Earthly, hee
                  That vses only for Necessitie.
                  And so, as that they finde him and afford,
                  To serue his Needs, while that hee serues his LORD.
                  His Senses so hee tempreth and commands,
                  That they t'obey his Spirit readie stands.
                  Which in an Orbe Aethereall doth moue,
                  Stirr'd by a Strength and Power from Aboue.
                  And by observing Natures Course and Lawes,
                  The Arte of Reason, hee acquires, and knawes.
                  And Treads on the th'Earth, and trav'ling, doth remaine,
                  While hee turne Earth; and bee trod on againe.
                  
                     Altho his Soule, inlarg'd from Carnall Stryfe,
                  Doe liue in Heav'n, that gaue his Senses Lyfe:
                  Vntill the Resurrection of the Flesh,
                  That from the Earth shall ryse, refynd, and fresh:
                  When all the World is waltring vp-syde-downe:
                  When Fortune fawnes, or when the Fates doe frowne:
                  Hee happie doth his Sprite possesse in Peace,
                  Because supported with the Power of Grace.
                  His Charitie, and librall Handes declare,
                  Of Others Want, his kynde and Christian Care.
                  Hee gladlie giues, of what his GOD hath given,
                  Which shall to him redoubled bee in Heaven.
                  To liue to GOD, his Practise all doth proue:
                  Heaven is through Fayth, his Hope; the LORD, his Loue.
                  His Exercise is Prayer, his Studies bee
                  Into the Volumes of Divinitie:
                  And There hee meditates, admiring most,
                  Th'Vnit' of the FATHER, SONNE, and Holie GHOST;
                  VVhich nev'r in all the numbers of his Dayes,
                  Enough can hee admire, extoll, and prayse.
                  His Heart, (to watch his Eye) hee ordaines it:
                  And to his Mouth a Doore hee makes his Wit.
                  And both hee ordaines ev'r, and doth direct,
                  His Sprite from sinfull Pleasure to protect.
                  Hee liues not lyke a VVorldlie VVorme, that does
                  For Permanent, Things perishing, heere choose.
                  No, no, his Loue is set on Thinges vnseene,
                  And ravished with VVares that are Divine.
                  His Loue is Heavenlie, Holie, and doth hold
                  No Holie Dayes with Loue of Mundane Mold.
                  VVherefore hee's lyable to manie Losses,
                  And oft incurres and combred is with Crosses.
                  Yet Heavenlie Helps, and Hope vp-holds him so,
                  That Losse no Losse, nor Crosse hee counteth no.
               
            
            
               An Olde Man. 49.
               
                  THe Instance of a Tract of Tyme of Yeares,
                  VVhere-in declyning, Natures Power appeares:
                  
                     VVhen by Defect of Senses see wee may,
                  The vse of Reason both restraind, and stay.
                  Bot yet his Knowledge with his Tyme conferre,
                  And hee shall prooue Experience Kalendar.
                  Tho in the power of Action hee is not,
                  As't were a Blanke, extracted from a Lot.
                  Hee is a Subject bot of Sicknesse now,
                  And VVeaknesse Agent, that the Backe most bow.
                  Crost with the Coagh, and a corrupted Breath:
                  And so Praecursor to approaching Death.
                  An Olde Man, 
                        •…
                     s bot halfe a Man, and twyse
                  Hee turnes to bee a Bairne, and childish lyes.
                  Hee's bot the living Picture of a Man,
                  And is a verie dying Creature than.
                  Beholde him well, and in effect you'll finde
                  Him bot a Bladder, blowne and stuft with VVinde.
                  Hee's lyke a withred Tree, and arride Root,
                  That buds not, flowrisheth, nor beares no Fruit.
                  And lyke a VVeather-worne, and Tyme-torne House,
                  Decaying fast, and falling ruinous.
                  Tho in his dying and declyning Grouth,
                  Yet is hee Pepper in the Eyes of Youth.
                  Hee is the jest of Loue, and for Infirmitie
                  Hee may the Mirrour bee of Miserie.
                  Yet Aged Lockes, and Silver Haires, deserue
                  That Youth should reverence, regard, and serue.
                  For Honour often tymes, and VVisdome both,
                  Into an Olde Mans Gowne and Garment go'th.
                  Ag'd Gravitie, and great Experience,
                  Doth challenge both Respect and Reverence.
                  His wyse Advyse, his Counsell true and sage,
                  By Practise long, oft proov'd, from Youth to Age,
                  Should with all States and Persons bee respected:
                  And not in Honourable Age neglected.
                  His Wordes are Oracles; they should bee Noted
                  In Kalendars, for Common vse, and Quoted▪
                  
                  His Actions should bee imitate, and choosed,
                  To bee there-after for Exemples vsed.
                  But as the Tyme, and Torch of Waxe doth waste;
                  So, liue hee nere so long, hee dies at last.
               
            
            
               
               A Young Man. 50.
               
                  THe Spring of Time, when Nature mindes to vent,
                  Her Pride, and best of Beauties, excellent:
                  And to the Worlde show and exhibite will,
                  Her Arte Divine, in-Imitable Skill.
                  Hee is the Loue, and the Delight of th'Eye▪
                  
                  And well considred, singular to see.
                  His Flesh and Sprite, are at a Iust and Iarring,
                  And hee is all in Making, or in Marring.
                  His Wit and Will, stands at intestene Stryfe,
                  If This, or That, shall Lord and leade his Life.
                  His Vertues bee in Waxing, or in Waining,
                  And all his Good, in losing, or in Gaining.
                  His Thrift is as hee guydes him, and begins,
                  If Tentlesse, sure hee tynes, if Wisel', hee wins.
                  His Credit is (what ever bee his Calling,)
                  And Honour in the Mounting, or the Falling.
                  His Life is in th'Increasing, or Decay,
                  And hee walks in the VVyde, or Narrow VVay.
                  Hee is a Bloome, that's blasted in the Bud,
                  Or growes to bee a Fruite that's faire and good.
                  Hee's like a Bird, that dies ere Nature brings
                  Her to make vse, and venture to her Wings.
                  Or like a Colt, that is Fensce-fed, and Ydle,
                  And None can breake, without a Stryping Brydle.
                  Or Falcon-like, must bee well Mann'd, and Fram'd,
                  Els hee can nev'r, or hardly, bee reclam'd.
                  Hee is Dames Natures Darling, and her Io,
                  And cheefest Charge of Reason is also.
                  His Exercise is Studie, in his Youth,
                  Or it is Action, in his elder Grouth.
                  His Studies are vnto his Pleasures most,
                  Or vpon Knowledge is bestow'd his Cost,
                  The Disposition marked of his Mynde,
                  Declares him Iade-lyke, or of Iennet kynde.
                  His Carr
                        •…
                     age is a Trying Table, or Touch.
                  That proues him Gentle, or degenred much.
                  
                     For Youth is lyke to Lumpes of Lead, or Waxe,
                  That at the Workers Will th'Impression takes.
                  Which being hardned, and becomming cold,
                  Th'Indented Dints and forme it hath, doth hold.
                  The Qualit of his Birth, frames him perforce,
                  In his Vpbringing better, bee or worse.
                  And while Experience fine, and Reason fit,
                  His Vnderstanding, hee's no Man as yet,
                  No, rather bot a Chylde; and I may say,
                  With Flatterie to bee deprav'd, a Prey:
                  And doth consist and stand in such a Case,
                  As eyther hee, is in the Way of Grace,
                  To proue a Sainct; or walking in his Evill,
                  And Path of Sinne, shall doubtlesse grow a Devill.
               
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

