
   
      
         
            The secretaries studie containing new familiar epistles: or directions, for the formall, orderly, and iudicious inditing of letters. ... By Thomas Gainsford, Esq.
            Gainsford, Thomas, d. 1624?
         
         
            
               1616
            
         
         Approx. 267 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 71 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-07 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01403
            STC 11523
            ESTC S102834
            99838596
            99838596
            2980
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01403)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2980)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1024:09)
         
         
            
               
                  The secretaries studie containing new familiar epistles: or directions, for the formall, orderly, and iudicious inditing of letters. ... By Thomas Gainsford, Esq.
                  Gainsford, Thomas, d. 1624?
               
               [8], 124, [4] p.   
               
                  Printed by T[homas] C[reede] for Roger Iackson, and are to be solde at his shop in Fleetstreet, ouer against the Conduit,
                  London :
                  1616.
               
               
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  The final two leaves contain "A dumpe or passion" (verse).
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Letter writing --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2003-03
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-04
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-05
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2003-05
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-06
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE SECRETARIES STVDIE: CONTAINING NEW familiar Epistles: OR DIRECTIONS, for the formall, orderly, and iudicious inditing of Letters.
            
               Whether Amorous. OR Louing.
               Whether Morall. OR Ciuil.
               Whether Oeconomicall. OR Houshold busines.
               Whether Politicall. OR Wittie.
               Whether Obiurgatory. OR Chiding.
               Whether Excusatory. OR Excusing.
               Whether Petitionary. OR Requesting.
               Whether Gratulatory. OR Giuing thankes.
               Whether Nuncupatory. OR Relating Newes.
            
            By Thomas Gainsford, Esq.
            
               Sic iuuat indulgere fugacibus horis.
            
            
               LONDON Printed by T. C. for Roger Iackeson, and are to be solde at his shop in Fleetstreet, ouer against the Conduit▪ 1616.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHT HOPEFVL YONG GENTLEMAN Maister Iohn Mounson at Charter-house, and as likely to aduance his Vertues to Honorable eminency, as any expectation can warrant.
            
               
                  GEnerous Youth,
            
            without other ceremony or complement, I am now to aduēture a iourney (and a fearefull one) as the first voiage that euer I made into the streights of opinion, or seuere Censure: so that pollitick and temporising-men would contract a sure bargaine with some rich marchant, honorable patron, or sufficient Statist to protect and countenance the enterprise: But in despight of aduerse Fortune, or calumniation, I haue made choyce of your loue, fauor, vertue, and good condition, of which I take the aduantage in your virgin chastitie, and soules puritie, and wherein I will as much reioyce, as if larger embraces had opened themselues to make me credulous of sincere welcome: Bee therefore your selfe, (expectable Gentl:) and doe but loue mee for olde loues sake; and I shall bee so proud, yea, presumptuous in your acceptation, that neyther windes nor seas shall affright mee, vntill I haue made a satisfactory voyage; or (beeing ouer-freighted with heauy Fortune) sincke the whole Stocke or Remaine of mine abilities in this kinde, in other like aduentures: which if it should so fall out, I could but conclude,
            
               Hic finis Priami.
               Yours assured, though there be no assurance amongst men: Tho: Gainsford.
               
            
         
         
            
            Non opus est digitis, per quos arcana loquaris?
         
         
            Errata: pag: 5. lin: 4. read tracted.
            Pag: 10. m. read loose. p: 13. l: 24. read sturd. p, 17. l. 6. r. euen. fol. 19. l. 15. r. sorer. f. 26. l, 5. r. adornation. f. 27. l. 7. r. country life. f. 30. l. 7. r. goe p. 31. l. 26. r. fiue. p. 34. l. 2▪ besides, for so. p. 34. l. 33. r. stake p. 35. l. 16. r. work. p. 36. l. 26 leaue out to. p. 43. l. 27. r. sedation l. 29. r. inuitations, p. 45. l. 13. re▪ a bettering. f, 46. l. 26. r. grow. l. 32. r. Lords fauor, p. 47. l, 30. r. hold vp p. 50, l. 11, r, you might gather, l, 14, r, hauing p, 53, l, 12. r. for the, p, 57, in the mar. following &amp; described, l, 21, r, O God! that p, 107, l, 30, r, obsolete.
         
         
            
            THE TABLE.
            
               
                  Amourous, or louing Letters.
                  THe Louer afraid to loose his friend contracted.
                  The Louer troubled with suspition of hazarding his desire.
                  The Louer iustifieth his loue from inward vertues, and outward comelinesse.
                  The Louer findeth fault with neglect of titles.
                  The louer complaineth of sequestration.
                  The louer cannot endure a riuall.
                  The Louer cannot soone forget his loue, after firme rooting.
                  The louer desires secrecie, not ouer liberall discoueries.
                  The louer doth not tye his affection to outward beautie.
                  The louer is afraide to loose his contentment.
                  The louer maintaineth that a little iealousie will season affection.
               
            
            
               
                  Morall or Ciuill Letters.
                  True Friendship.
                  Friendly precepts.
                  An other of the propertyes of friendship.
                  Friendes would haue no vnkindnes taken for any thing.
                  Necessitie causeth importunitie.
                  Friendship is broken through denyall of trifles, and presuming of anothers weaknes.
                  Friendship is lost through vnkindnesse and discontinuance.
                  Ingratitude is not befitting a Gentl:
                  A man out of good manners must answer Letters.
                  Iealousie should not be showne without iust cause.
                  The difference between a willing and compulsed absence.
                  Friendship is afraid to be forgotten.
                  A good Wife compared to a Shippe at Sea.
                  A friend desireth a Gentle-woman to vnite the inward vertues to outward comelinesse.
               
            
            
               
                  Oeconomicall Letters, or of houshold businesse.
                  A Gentleman must take heede how hee settles himselfe in the Countrey as a Farmer.
                  If a Gentleman will bee a Farmer, it is best to obtaine the principall House, or credite of the highest place in the towne.
                  
                     Concerning the building &amp; ordring a house, with retaining of seruāts
                  Whether a Gentle-woman may with her credite let out Lodgings for money.
                  The danger of disagreemēt betweene man &amp; wife, with their duties.
                  How Children ought to be brought vp.
                  How Seruants are to be instructed.
               
            
            
               
                  Politicall, or witty Letters.
                  Women in yeares should rather look for rich aduancement, then wanton satisfaction.
                  A Gentl: should not be seruant to any, that hath a sufficient estate of his owne: and if he be, with what pollicy he must contriue it.
                  No Oathes must be belieued before marriage.
                  He that will enrich himselfe by seruice, must follow some thryuing Officer.
                  The Lady must be obserued, by such as mean to thriue vnder the lord.
                  Some Lord or other must bee made an Agent, to obtaine a sute of the Prince.
                  Suites in Court are not dispatched without great attendance.
                  A military pollicie to restraine insolent mutiners.
                  What policy soeuer ambition buildeth vpon, it is cast downe with death and destruction.
                  Men must submitte to their Fortune.
               
            
            
               
                  Obiurgatory or chiding letters.
                  Against a sonne, for his disordered life.
                  Against inconstancie, and following a strumpet.
                  Against swearing.
                  Against couetousnes.
                  Against denyall of trifles amongst friends,
                  Against idle excuses.
                  Against pride, and tyrannous behauiour in great persons.
                  Against foolishnes and dishonesty in a seruant.
                  Against Drunkennes.
                  Against the breach of Wedlocke in the man.
                  Against Whoredom in the woman.
               
            
            
               
                  Excusatory or defensiue letters.
                  Excuse for not lending money.
                  Excuse for being importunate in the behalfe of a friend.
                  Excuse for keeping company, and going to Court.
                  Excuse for sheltring with a stranger in a storme.
                  Excuse for not dispatching a suite of importance.
                  Excuse for tarrying too long from a Wife.
                  
                     Excuse for not dispatching of businesse.
                  Excuse for not writing &amp; attending vnwilling persons to bee spoken with.
                  Excuse for not forbearing a friend, presuming to disgrace another.
                  Excuse for not beeing surety for a friend.
                  Excuse for not entertaining a friend as hee ought to be.
                  Excuse for not soothing vp of humors.
               
            
            
               
                  Petitionary, or Letters of Request.
                  A Request to requite discurtesie.
                  A request for Money.
                  A request to entertaine a daughter.
                  A request for assurance of a Farm
                  A request to forbeare a debt.
                  A request to forbeare a dangerous Ladyes company.
                  A request to be charitable.
                  A request to entertaine a Scholler for a Souldier.
                  A request for the Knighting of a friend, and worthy Gentleman.
                  A request to defend a Widow in her right, against all wrong and calumniation.
                  A request for an office for another
                  A request for aduise in matters of difficultie.
               
            
            
               
                  Gratulatory, or Letters of giuing thankes.
                  Thankefulnes for a daughters good bringing vp, and well-bestowing.
                  Thankefulnes for recompencing the giuing of a Booke.
                  Thankefulnes for an office.
                  Thankefulnes for defending one against a great aduersary.
                  Thankefulnesse for not belieuing a false report.
                  Thankefulnes for lending of Money.
                  Thankefulnesse for a timely good turne.
               
            
            
               
                  Nuncupatorie, or Letters of Newes.
                  Newes from Xante and Candie.
                  Newes from Constantinople.
                  Newes from Scio.
                  Newes from Metelline.
                  Newes from Malta.
                  Newes from Venice.
                  Newes from Turine.
                  Newes from Zidon &amp; Ierusalem.
                  News from Ciprus.
               
            
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            AMOROVS LETTERS
            
               
                  To the onely Life of his desires.
               
               
                  
                     SWeete Soule? What meane you to do with me?
                     The louer is affraide to lose his beloued.
                   or what thinke you I shall doe with my selfe; considering your vertues, which I tearme excellencies haue beene Adamants of my feruentnesse, and I erected my building vpon so good a foundation, that you haue compared the Sympathy of our loues, to well tuned Musicke. From whence comes then this retraction? or how can you be so cruell to terrifie me with suspition? Oh doe not thinke that I haue praised those eyes, which my supposes, in absence, imagine to reflect a very Sunlike lustre? that I haue doted on that fauor and comelinesse, which in the contemplation did euer transport me beyond my selfe? that I haue bene enamored on your beauty, which in the gazing hath ouercome mee with admiration? that I haue beene rauished with those kisses, which seemed an infused life to my distracted heart? that I haue bene amazed on that face, which me thought was a very mappe of louelinesse, and all in vaine? as though I could passe ouer the remembrance of my contentment with slightnesse, and frame my selfe to beleeue contraries. No no, (Sweet soule) I shall not, may not, nor cannot. For it is not the fathers frownes, nor the brothers storming, that I respect, but your sadnesse and teares, your sorrows and complaints, which me thinks resemble spots disgratiously

chancing to pure linnen: be therfore the patterne of your selfe: Let vertue remaine vnmaimed: continue constant &amp; well satisfied: &amp; for my part, what euer goodnes may arise frō our allowable proceedings, I will iustifie. To be plaine, let the assurance of your desires warrant my hopes, remoue my ielousie, and I will lose this life, rather then thus hazard the life of my life. But I hope I haue encountred with an vnderstanding woman, and there shall need no such expostulation. Nay I am assured I haue cast my selfe into the lap of vertue, which like the square Die being euery way throwne standeth vpright, so that if there should be any blockes in the course of our iustifiable desires; either a strong arme of policy shall tumble them aside, or a noble resolution spurne them away in scorne: in which assurance I will rather breathe with ioy, then pant for feare; and at last proclaime to the world, there bee women will remember their vowes, and can be loyall in spight of contradiction or calumniation.
               
                  Your afflicted friend.
               
            
            
               
                  To his fulnesse of Contentment.
               
               
                  
                     The Louer distracted with feare of hazzarding his desire.
                  
                  MY onely Beloued, I had not thought loue, especially in such youth, had bin capable of moderation, that already you can be contented to dispute the matter with reason, and to consent to the peeuish restraint of ill concluding arguments; which some enuious tongue hath whispered vnto you. Oh that our first meeting had receiued this restraint: then with small griefe I might haue ouer passed my feare: or had the fire bene kindled with artificiall degrees, I might haue preuented the flaming outright. But now when I am in the violence of my speed, when the heart burneth with passion, when my very life dependeth on the hope of your assent, and that,

in a manner, you resolued my cure and redresse, to stand at a stay, to dispute the matter, to find cause of distasting, worketh in me impatience, so that I know not how to demeane my selfe. Oh, do not slightly passe ouer these things, or with an vnkindly grauity censure my proceedings. Remember I haue, will, and must loue; and what cannot or dare not loue effect? Is there a suspition of prodigality? loue wil be a shepheard, nay a slaue. Is there a mistrust of incontinency? loue will settle desire, and quite extinguish all flames of vniust concupisence. Is there a breaking out of folly? loue worketh discretion, &amp; reformeth abuses. Is there a feare of want? loue hath no want, and contriueth impossibilities. Is there a doubt of any thing else? loue attaineth any thing else, and facilitateth any difficulty. Alas, what could I not say to pleade for my selfe? what would I not say, nay what would I not doe to please my selfe, especially when such louelinesse enamoreth? Do not therfore beleeue: faith and honesty bids you not beleeue? myselfe bids you not beleeue these slanderous enemies of affection, these brokers of misreports: for I protest you shall finde it otherwise, and they in the disceptation proue ashamed of wronging the innocent. Let me therefore come to appease them, let mee come to satisfie you, let me come to iustifie my selfe: nay let me come to die quickely or liue happily: for this is intollerable, and I cannot credit my feares, nor beleeue these tormenting apparitions.
               
                  Your liuing dying friend.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To the onely hope of his Fortunes.
                     
                        Loue occasioned through a vnity of inward vertues and outward comelinesse.
                      Mrs. B.
               
               
                  MY Soules life, When I beheld you first, me thought nature determined to open a storehouse and shew vs some excellent workemanship, and so as a man longing

for nouelties, I looked and gazed on the same, yea with admiration commended her handiworke: but after I had considered what inward vertues caused the motion of this outward woorth, and louelinesse, I could not but compare it to a rich casket, containing within it more richer iewels: so that you must not wonder at my likeing the same; but rather maintaine the cause of my iudgement, for bestowing it selfe on so wel deseruing a subiect: nor is this flattery or idle discourse, but iustice in yours, and necessitie in my case: for as you haue inflamed mine affection, so there must be vsed som meanes of satisfaction. Thus requesting you to consider me, as a man, whose thoughts, words, actions, life, soule, and all attend you, not darinng to behold the Sun of the world, till they receiue comfort from the Sunne of your sauours, I remaine
               
                  The honourer of your matchlesse perfection.
               
            
            
               
                  To her chiefeest Contentment.
               
               
                  
                     The Louer findeth fault with neglect of titles.
                  
                  MY Loue and Ioy, I haue read, that the Emperours of Rome did commonly looke on the date and superscription of their Letters; whereat, if they were distasted they reiected the same, and would not ouer-view them further: but yet I will not serue you so by taking such state and imitation vppon mee; but impute your neglect of our couenant concerning reciprocall titles, to a gentle triall of my simplicitie and loue; withall, intreating henceforward, not to let forgetfulnes, or contempt put in a finger, lest by intrusion or sufferance it bring in a hand, and so the whole body. For why should you giue me any cause of suspition, when a warrant is sealed of our happinesse; or assume to your selfe a counterfeit

libertie of trying my patience, when you know I will pul out mine owne heart, before it shall entertain a thought of alteration? Therefore I pray you remember your selfe, and those vowes you haue conttacted; remember mee, and that affection you haue inflamed; remember vertue, and that goodnesse which you haue commended; and remember loue with that honesty you haue professed: and so I expect, that as you are my chiefest content, your next Letter shal confirme me your choisest delight.
               
                  None but yours.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To the Honourable Lady, T.G.
               
               
                  HONORABLE,
                  
                     Loue complaineth of sequestration.
                   
                  and worthily honoured Lady: Although fame hath set open the enclosure of your praises, whereby Honour and Vertue remaine exposed to the world, as you see a rich Diamond augmented in his lustre by the cunning of the workeman: yet is misfortune so tyrannous vnto me, that I am necessited to an vntimely banishment, euen when there appeared life in your patronage, and delight in your louelinesse: so that now to sequester my selfe is an absolute walking in darknesse, and a miserable staggering without supportation. Yet againe, when I consider, with whom I haue encountred, and that I am falne into the hands of a generous spirit, and heroicke worthinesse; I conceiue great pleasure in my confidence, and I begin to grow prowd, that I may publish your vertue, I dare say loyall Constancie. Be therefore then your selfe great Lady: and let the opinion I conceiue of my fortunes, encourage my endeuor, that al the actions my industry shal vndertake may receiue life frō the beams of your name. Then though I might raise my glory equal with the Sun I would not faile

to lay it prostrate to your high acceptatiō: &amp; so I request you giue me leaue to diuulge to the world, that the sphere, in which I moue, is gouerned by your influence▪ that I cannot liue without your fauour; that I will not loue, except you vouchsafe it; that I haue no other Lady, but your selfe; no other world then the place of your residence. And thus I bid you fare as vvell as vvishes can enlarge, leauing my soule in your tuition: vvhich if you preserue for her ovvne, yours, or my sake; Oh hovv happy shall I bee, and vvith glad tidings vvill it returne vnto me, and (I hope) command me to returne vnto you: and so I rest in the best expectation, and bascia la honorata manu.
               
               
                  Your Honors deuoted.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To the Honorable and his highly respected Lady, B. S.
               
               
                  RIght honorable Lady, I cannot deny but a Diamond is a pretious stone,
                     Loue cannot indure a riuall or competitor.
                   though imbased in lead: but excellently polished, and set out to the best becomming, it must needs constraine a farther praise and admiration: so fareth it vvith Vertue, vvhich no question is allovvable in the meanest persons: but vvhen there is a vniting of many graces, as beauty, generous minde, noble birth, setled vvisedome, affable demeanour, and such like; it not onely approcheth absolute perfection, but bindeth vs to high and strict obseruation: of all vvhich I must &amp; dare publish you a instāce, so that it is the pride of my life to iustifie my soules desire to serue you; and the glory of my bondage, that I am made seruile to such vvorthinesse: command therefore (great Lady) but vvith all command me to loue; for I cannot liue except I loue; nor care to die so I may loue you onely, vvho are vvorthy of all loue. Yet my dearest happinesse, I beseech you mistake me not; for hovvsoeuer I haue subiected my selfe, I

(like a Soueraigne) can indure no cōpetitor: &amp; although it cannot be chosen, but the very starres ouervvatch you, and therefore many eyes on earth looke tovvard you, &amp; many hearts vvish you vvel; yet shall I neuer endure anothers claime, much lesse a daring hand to take you in possession: be therefore thus circumspect for humanities sake; not betray your vertue to corruption, nor my poore valor to ineuitable danger. For if you frustrate my hopes either by vvillingnesse or vvantonnesse, I renounce the vvorld, all vvomen, and my selfe. But if the high strongest arme stretch it selfe tovvard you vvith inhumanity, or compulsion; my rest is vp to make it shrinke backe again, or cut it off in the extension.
               
                  Yours in death it selfe.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To the Noble and truely vertuous Lady, F.M.
               
               
                  MOst worthy Lady had not my loue receiued life from the breathing heate issuing from your gracious acceptation;
                     Loue will hardly bee supprest, after it hath taken firme rooting.
                   it might vvell haue recoyled vvith the first violent reiection, and taken out a nevv lesson of restraint, vvith a ciuill acknovvledging your greatnesse, and confessing that the starres are onely to be looked vpon vvith an abasing reuerence; but you knovv, (and none but you shall knovv) that vvhen I made my selfe a stop, as afraide to go further then either my strength or policie could direct me, a louely hand tooke me by the arm, and drevv me along to the height of my happinesse, vvherein I vvil sit as glorious, as the Sunne in his strength, &amp; in despite of maligne circūstances, or maleuolent aspects, embrace my fortune vvith gladnesse. Therefore I pray you desist frō questioning my presumptuous attēpt, or affrighting me vvith your greatnes, or tormenting me vvith discouery, or murthering me vvith suspition, or sending me to hell vvith terror of your losse. For I dare, &amp; vvill thus answer

euery particular. Concerning my presumption, It is easier to reach at a high bough then to stoop to a low straw; it is glorious to be busied in honourable designes: and he is made famous in the attempt, though he faile in the conquest. It is a worthy resolution to aime at a wel deseruing obiect: and how euer the hazzard be, there is a show of a generous spirit; sith fortune and loue are painted blind in their portraitures. Concerning your greatnesse, we haue many instances of Queenes and Princes pulling vp inferior persons to honour: nor is loue tyed to such lawes of priuacy; but being naked, himselfe shewes plainely, that flesh and blood lies as naked to the incursions of his passions in high and lowe: the lowe not ouer-awed with titular dignities, or outward shows; nor the preheminence of the hie priuiledged frō amorous affecting the lowe. For my selfe, I am in blood generous, and in affection fully contracted to loyalty: concerning discouery, who shall betray vs but our selues? nay, who dare whisper against vs but iealousie? and in that lies the secret of our prosperitie. For what is difficult to get, is carefully preserued; and where there is danger in the aduenture, there is sweetnesse, and ioy exceeding other ioyes, when the perill is ouerpassed: therefore be you reposed, and let me bustle with mischance; for I am resolued to loue you against all ouerwatchings. Concerning suspition, Oh giue not wings to my feares, that some other will intrude and participate my immunities; or doe you it onely to make a triall of my spirit? Beleeue it; before I will consent to such basenesse, I will pray for Sampsons strength to pull downe the house on all our heads together. And concerning your losse, Oh there is death in the verie sound, and it cannot bee raised out of any other circle, then enuy at my prosperitie, or your owne desire of a more worthy seruant, whereat I

am now strucke silent: and vnlesse you confidently resolue me what to trust vnto, I will not liue to write you another Letter.
               
                  Yours, not to liue without you.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To her best choyce, C.D.
               
               
                  MY loues Pride,
                  
                     Loue desires secrecie, not ouer liberall discoueries.
                   Although I am enformed, that by your liberall praises of me, some quicke apprehension discouered your liking, yet cannot I take it so ill, as to draw you within the compasse of reprehension, because I would not slacke the first vehemency, wherein loue hath nobly displayed his colours on all sides. Let vs therefore continue resolute; and if by some small absence we sometimes slacke the burning of these fires, shall it not resemble a Smiths forge, who casteth water on his coales to strengthen the heate, and make the flame more glorious? Yet by way of caution, it is not alwaies befitting to speake what wee thinke, nor report what wee know, lest a captious eare mistake our discourse, and a passionate heart set the tong at randome. As for our selues, there hath bene made a reciprocall trial: &amp; for my owne part, as you expect constancy in me, I request secrecy in you, and so am resolued to loue you, and none but you, while I am warme in my hearts blood.
               
                  Yours in the midst of feare.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To his vertuous and dearely beloued, M.A.
               
               
                  SWeet Heart,
                  
                     True loue is not tyed to outward beautie.
                   What a strange countermād did you send me, not to visite you, because your late sickenesse had cast a defiance in beauties face, as if my liking depended on outward shewes! Why, good Soule? when reason had won the field of passion, I loued a vertuous Cassandra,
                  
not a faire Hellen; a noble spirit, not an outward feature; a constant resolution, not a fading comelinesse: and yet I am perswaded no disaster whatsoeuer can haue power to controwle thy beauty or bounty; onely time excepted, which must weare vs out with death, and then shall our soules welcome a perpetuitie: therefore I pray thee let me come, if it be but to shew my selfe a man a louer of vertue, and maintainer of all constant and honest resolutions.
               
                  Yours euer resolued.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To the Mistresse of his thoughts, F.D.
               
               
                  
                     Loue is affraid to looke his contentment.
                  
                  MY Loue and life, I hope it is not come to that passe, that you can bee contented to dispute the matter with discretion, as though it lay in your choice, which way to trauell to the palace of Felicitie; as though wisedome had taught you to wipe away the forces of Fancie, with a commanding hand; as though some diuine inspiration had forewarned you of ensuing mishaps. For sure no obiection can now be made, which long since receiued not a foile in the encounter; therfore I pray you (if my fortunes be so bad, that I must reuiue your memory) goe to that groue where we called the trees to witnesse, and sware by the pleasant shade, that nothing but the fruite of enioying one another, should coole the fiers of loue, and there recount the words wee counterchanged, the vowes we contracted, the teares wee drunke vp from each others faces. But I can say no more, vnlesse I shall bee inforced to exclaime. I am vnworthy to liue; because my dearest life supposeth me vnworthy to loue, or be beloued: which if it bee but in shew; as you breake the seales of these Letters, you breake the strings of my heart.
               
                  Yours dying in constancie.
               
            
         
         
            Ciuill Letters.
            
               
               
                  
                     To his best beloued and more then much respected Mrs. G.Z.
               
               
                  WOrthily beloued, These pretty crosses and contradictions make Loue the sweeter,
                     A little iealousie seasoneth true loue
                   and strengthen Fancie the more, when the vaile of iealousie is taken away, and an honest heart hath taught a strong arme the cunning to turne aside all obstacles of our delight: yet beleeue me, it was a miserable temptation, for you to sweare my falshood, and lay the weight of disloyaltie on the brest of an honest man. especially to raise your suspition, from so vnworthy a person, and degenerating a cause, when there was no motiue to startle my resolutions, nor thoght to disparage your worth. Say the course of the Danse brought mee with her to a turning change, and that afterward I commended her graces and comelinesse, I could doe no lesse out of courtship and good manner: but to say that either procceeded from amorous passion, is to be ouer passionat, &amp; vnwarrantable by reason, or laws of loue. Besides, some tongues haue traduced her for a wanton: and then is beauty as ill bestowed, as valure in a prophane swaggerer: so that me thinks you should rather haue challenged any other for deprauing me in this kind, then beene challenger your selfe to raise a greater disease. But I hope you are now satisfied, as no such misprision shall euer endanger the vnitie of our loues againe.
               
                  Yours fearefully louing.
               
            
            
               
                  To the worthiest of all my friends.
               
               
                  MY other selfe, You haue commanded me to write, and I durst not but obey:
                     A letter describing true friendship.
                   nay, you haue prescribed the method, and therefore I wil not alter the maner: but make

you beleeue I haue apprehended your wil, and would thus satisfie your desire. True friendship is an vndissimuled consent of our affection towards one another, and a very transportation of two hearts into one body: so that two friends in a manner loue with one minde, speake with one tongue, execute with one hand, liue with one life, and sometimes die with one death. Amongst friends must be no contradiction, no disproportion of conditions, no dissimilitude in manners, nor talke of mine and thine. Doth hee sorrow? thou must mourne: doth hee reioyce? thou must not repine: doth hee complaine? thou must not accuse: doth hee demaund? thou must not denie: doth hee want? thou must not murmure: doth hee contriue? thou must practise: doth hee desire? thou must not reproue. For though priuate thoughts are proper to our selues, yet the fortunes, goods, persons, and estate of friends, are to remaine in a pleasant communitie: vpon this, some Philosophers haue maintained, that one man can haue but one friend; framing thus an argument, A contrariis. If there be danger in many enemies, by reason of the many and vncertaine courses to reuenge: there is trouble in many friends, by occasion of diuisions in consent. According to the opinion of Aeschines, there was no such griefe as to be diuided from him we did loue. For looke what properties loue euer contained, were in friendshippe maintained: and because loue could not receiue her estimation frō vntoward liberty to change; friendship hath bene denied her desires to alter. Tully, the light of eloquēce, had friendship in such account, that he preferd it before kindred, because in the dissolution of loue, the name of a kinsman remained, but in the priuation of friendship all titles and goodnes ended. If then with these properties you can bear with my imperfections, I with these conditions will tolerate your defects, and so shall this name of friendship passe and repasse reciprocally between vs.
               
                  Yours vnseparable.
               
            
            
               
               
                  To his highly esteemed.
               
               
                  WOrthy Sir,
                  
                     A letter of friendly precepts.
                   Whereas you complaine of my slownesse in visiting you, and slacknes in writing concerning your selfe, I am determined to remaine with the same faith and order I euer accustomed; &amp; touching those latter motiues, I will come as neare your satisfaction as I can in this slender discouery. Vnderstand me then, that my poore experience would open the mystery of this knowledge vnto you: that fortune, which we so often prophanely remember, is no way to bee ouercome but with Vertue: that Vertue is neuer so well to be entertained, as in youth: that youth is but some speciall flower in a curious garden, kept by extraordinary diligence, till an vntimely blast perish the stalke, and impouerish the beauty: that beautie is like a white wall curiously trimmed, which if an enuious hand do besprinkle with a few vncleane droppes, a present alteration daunteth the company: that company is like a strange net catching all fish, vnlesse they slip into some vnknowne nookes, or auoide the danger by other cunning: that cunning is like holding the Woolfe by the eare, which if you wrest hard, you are bitten; if you let go, you are in perill of life: that life is like a strong timbred tree, which at the maisters appointment is cut downe in a small time: that time is resembled to sweete smelling flowers, which must be staid to please the sense, and stilled to heale the body, or else they will bee faire to the eye, and as vnprofitable as ill disposed friends: that friends are like childrens sports, who for a new Counter refuse an old Angell, and to go to a strange nurse, forsake the nearest kindred: and that kindred are like Tantalus apples, which keepe their shew till they be touched; but once pressed, crumble to powder.
               
                  These be principles to my griefe experienced, and may without offence be to others good embraced; not that I go about to draw you into suspition: but because I would preserue your remembrance toward me, whereby I must needs be satisfied, if you be not displeased.
               
                  Yours as I haue professed.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To his esteemed friend, C.N.
               
               
                  
                     The properties of true friendship.
                  
                  SIR, Had not our friendshippe receiued reciprocal strength from true vertue, and worthy conuersation; I could slightly haue passed ouer your last deniall of trifles, and quietly gathered the raines of discretion to restraine the forwardnesse of impudency or combersomnesse: but when I remembred our combination, and with what conditions we contracted a league, especially the nature and propertie of friendship, me thought there was a pleasure to name you so, and a comfort to finde you so: therefore from hencefoorth let vs vnderstand one another better; either firmely to maintaine the cause of kindnes, or lightly to leaue it vnder the colours of courtesie. For the best Philosophers haue chained loue and friendshippe with equall goodnesse, so that as loue can endure no competition, friendship must abide no community: as loue can haue but one fauorite; friendshippe should admit but of one companion: as loue pardoneth, friendship forbeareth; as loue commandeth all, friendship is denyed nothing: as loue entreth when he list, friendship doth so vncontrowled: as loue triumpheth ouer the heart and affection, friendship raigneth ouer body &amp; goods: no excuses, no drawings backe, no contracted brow, no delaies, no hiding the head, no daintinesse, or absurd ceremonies; but a happy Sympathy to strengthen goodwill, and an absolute power to command, and readines to obey one other. If

then with these conditions, you can bee contented to march arme in arme to the house of contentment, I am yours as you mine; and both to shew the world an example of happy imitation.
               
                  Yours indissoluble.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To his assured friend, F. L.
               
               
                  SIR,
                  
                     The properties of true friendship.
                   To craue pardon were to submit, and more then you looke for: obstinately to offend were iniurious to you, and not befitting a Gentleman. To auoyd therefore the one, and to eschew the other: For not writing, imagin want of skill: for not comming, suppose my businesse to hinder me: for not sending, thinke I could not conueniently: thus you see I am willing to be excused, where I am loth to be accused; &amp; considering I loue you better then other men, I would not distast you if it were possible: especially because I haue tyed my selfe to true obseruation, as you haue professed a happy contract of kindnesse. In hope or rather assurance hereof, I pray you present my seruice to that louely party, whom I compared at our last meeting to a rich Diamond orderly inameled, and extraordinarily set out to the best grace; and all to shew the cunning of the workeman: so that if my fortune could but conduce me to the way of entertainment, it would sure exceed the worlds happines, and I durst search the whole earth for AEsculapius bones to restore her eyes: but if you play the truant with me to shew her this letter, giue mee leaue to be my owne interpeter, and let not your excellent wits triumph ouer my simplicitie.
               
                  Euer your owne.
               
            
            
               
               
                  To her tried and trusty friend.
               
               
                  
                     Necessitie causeth importunitie.
                  
                  WOrthy Sir, Hauing relyed on your noble promises, and knowing my selfe on a sure and honest ground, concerning the secrets of my discontents, I rested some way satisfied in the expectation of the performance; and thought my selfe happy in this vnhappinesse, that I had falne into the hands of so noble a Gentleman: so that if there were no more in it, then loue and assurance of your selfe, I would haue bene silent, till your owne leasure had serued you rightly to consider mee. But necessities knocking so hard and so fast, and conspiring with the suddennesse of time against my patience and quiet, I am enforced to ouerpasse all limits, and step to an earnest importunitie, to request both your confidence of my honestie in this businesse, and suppliment to keepe mee out of the hand of misery and despaire. This humanity challenges at your hand, this occasion compelleth mee to request: so that if I find you no lesse then I hope, nor no worse then I deserue, we shall both be pleased; and I haue cause to proclaime your worth euen to my best friends: and thus I haue cast my selfe downe into the scale of equall consideration; take vp then an vpright hand, and peize me accordingly: but withall, I pray you let no indirect strength turne the beame aside. For I haue euer loued you truly, and therefore rely on your friendship at this time absolutely.
               
                  Not liuing without you.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To his assured Friend, G.M.
               
               
                  
                     Deniall of trifles, and presumption of anothers weakenesse, maketh a breach in friendship.
                  
                  SIR, I would not willingly haue our friendship receiue any maime, lest my wounds grow festred for want of a

skilfull Chirurgion; considering I haue loued you aboue all men, and found you many waies true and free-hearted: yet I am afraide we doe both faile in iudgement and true vse of cōuersation. For you see, that that hand which hath, or should couer my nakednes, hath not only left me bare, and subiect to cold: but euer turned the worst side to the view and derision of passengers; insomuch that your last deniall of trifles, and glorious liberty of deceiueable speeches to please your selfe, hath made me contemptible to seruile creatures, and debarred my desires, when I determined but a small satisfaction, which with a little suppliment had had a free passage. But now I see my selfe more miserable for the want of Vertue, then want of money; therefore I am resolued to bee reposed: and if you thinke me woorth the keeping, I pray you hereafter forbeare those disloyall and palpable discoueries, vndecent contradictions, vnkinde denials, and triuiall excuses. For a small helpe will stay a fainting man, when a strong arme cannot lift him vp, that is falne flat on the ground. I vrge not this, to draw you to any inconueniences concerning your purse, but to keepe vs both vpright touching our credits, and so with a meere disturbed hand, and troubled minde, I bid you farewell; but I am resolued to endure no further vnsauory iests against me, for any hopes of worldly helpes.
               
                  Yours, as I haue cause.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To his Honorable friend, Sir G.S.
               
               
                  WOrthy Sir,
                  
                     Discontinuance and vnkindnes loseth friends in the end.
                   Had not my life receiued heate from the Sunne of your fauours, and as I may say, from the first influence, wherewith that Noble Lord so graciously beheld me, I might quietly go forward without

                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
once looking backe to see, wherefore I am despised, &amp; why, without offending, debarred from the same. But because I must and will acknowledge it, and in a maner confesse my selfe all darkenesse without it, yea readie to bee plunged into euery durty bogge &amp; irrecouerable danger: I humbly beseech you therfore, either to extend a gracious hand to stay a fainting soule from sinking, or giue mee leaue to blame my misfortune, that hath thus subiected mee to the violence of so dangerous displeasure; whereby if you be not the more noble, discontinuance shall make me worse, then water spilt out of a vessell neuer to be taken vp againe. For what a terror is this? nay, how vnexcusable, for my selfe to haue you in towne, and I not to visite you, or so much as once to bee thought vpon? yet it may be, this eternall horror of gentle minds (shame and wants) haue onely stirred vp iealousie to afflict me without cause; considering you will be still your selfe, and loue me for being honest, and endeuouring to make vertue proud, that pouertie cannot abase her: In which hope I send you my true and faithfull heart, howeuer I remaine most miserable in the feare of your losse.
               
                  Yours in true friendship.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To his Honourable friend, Sir. T.B.
               
               
                  WOrthy Sir, In those times, when Dracon the tyrant of the East, aduanced himselfe to the height of soueraignty,
                     Ingratitude is not befitting a gentleman.
                   ingratitude and iniustice were punished with death: so that if he vnderwent the imputation of cruelty, it was not for satiating a blood-thirsty-minde, but reuenging the neglect of his statutes: now if examples endure longer then precepts, had not wee neede in these corrupt times to stand on a guard of circumspection, not to vilipend vertue lesse then the heathen, nor practise impietie

worse then idolaters; and if they thought ingratitude worthy of death; I hope we shall (at least) suppose it vnbefitting a Gentleman. Wherefore without further complement, or larger circumstances for those many fauours, wherewith your plentifull hand hath euen laden me; I open the exchecquour of the poore, and thanke you with a publike acknowledgement of the same. Yet giue me leaue (considering mischances are multiplyed vpon me) to resemble my selfe to a man tumbling downe a staires, who neuer leaues falling, till he come to the bottome. And concerning your last promise vnperformed, how can I be compared better then to a man lying faint and wounded on the ground, whom some courteous hand seemeth to aduance, but lifting him vp halfe way, letteth goe his hold, and so he falleth backe againe to his sore hurt? therefore, good Sir, either giue my hope fuller wings, that it may take a higher flight of security, or let me die at once, to auoide an euerliuing misery: and this I vrge the rather, because in cases of vntoward distresse, there is courtesie in quicke dispatch; as in the benefits of friendship there is a double pleasure in the timelinesse, and orderly disposing of fauour. Now my request is, if any vngentle hand hath cast durt into the pure streame of your loue; Oh, let it not so remaine, but either cleanse it your selfe, or giue me leaue to pull it out, what danger soeuer I incurre: and if my fortune be so malignant, that a slauish report hath ecchoed against my peace, Oh, let me know the particulars, and answer for my selfe accordingly. And thus assuring my selfe, that I shall fall into the hands of iudgement, with quicke apprehension, I leaue all to fauourable construction, and commit you to his hands, who can aduance you to the height of your desire, and merit of your woorth.
               
                  Post scriptum, Gratia ab officio, quod mor a tardat, abest. Your thankefull friend.
               
            
            
               
               
                  
                     To his much esteemed Friend, C.G.
               
               
                  
                     A man out of good manners must answer letters howeuer they proue vnsauory in the acceptation.
                  
                  SIR, I am sorry that my letters were either vnsauory for the matter, or tedious for the length, considering that out of the rules of ciuilitie I was to answer yours, and the necessitie of my businesse to importune further, then you thought good manners. But such is the misery of wants; and poore men are resembled to ruinous walles, which euery man shunneth for feare of falling vpon them; otherwise I could excuse my selfe many waies. First, to auoide idlenesse, wherein the Persians were so obseruant, that they would rather whittle stickes, or rip the seames of their coate, and sewe them vp againe. Secondly, to eschew ingratitude, which is a vice vnbefitting a generous minde of all other. Next, to exercise my vnderstanding; for to write to so delicate a iudgement, and apprehensiue a wit, craueth study and a carefull foresight: then, to better my knowledge: For if I doe well, your commendation can confirme me; if I fall into errors, your wisedome can reforme and restraine me. Fifthly, to make you beleeue, there is some good thing in me allowable and iustifiable, and therefore worthy of a small regard, as noble Sir Phillip Sydney was wont to say, Let vs loue him for one good qualitie; for a great many haue none at all, and no man hath all. Lastly, to know what to trust vnto; for to hope for a thing which commeth not, and to loue them that care not for vs, be two of the liuing deaths in this world. Therefore, Good Sir, let me not pleade in vaine, that pleade so truely, and vrge these reasons, rather to know how your loue shall bee inlarged, then my vaineglory published: and if you please to second my enterprise, I shall with a further cheerefulnesse proceede in my businesse; if not, as good fall at first, and all at once, as liue in expectation of

more mischiefe, and greater troubles. Thus I bid you farewell, and to fare better then I can fare, vnlesse you wish me well.
               
                  Yours, as a louer of Vertue.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To her newly displeased Friend, M.I.
               
               
                  GOod Sir,
                  
                     Iealousie should not be shewne without cause.
                   How commeth it to passe, that you draw my loue and modesty in question, for my ciuill entertaining of a Gentleman last night, as thogh I could do lesse, then affoord him a salutation, and performed too much in continuing our morall discourse? Beleeue me, I am not ignorant, that loue is seasoned with a little iealousie, but beeing out of Italie, grow prowd of Englands libertie, where the practices of humanitie teach vs the true vse of cōuersation. So that an vncorrupted heart is Canon-proof against a slanderous tongue, but a wanton minde will turne vertuous sentences to laciuiousnesse: if then you were well perswaded of my vertue; to put all out of doubt, there passed not one word, which a diuine might not haue bene partaker of; otherwise bee resolued, that if I had not bene limited with the bands of respecting you, I would haue bene tyed to the conditions concerning my selfe, and neither haue giuen eare to immodest parlee, nor way to any vndecencies: and so if you are satisfied, I am pleased. But from hencefoorth bee more confident of my worth, and lesse suspicious of my loyaltie.
               
                  Yours, if you wrong her not.
               
            
            
               
               
                  
                     To her best resolued friend, F.G.
               
               
                  MY true and worthy friend, Your late discourse concerning absence and iealousie,
                     The differēce betweene a willing and compulsed absence.
                   as if they were rather inflamers, then extinguishers of loue, hath almost startled my resolutions concerning the negatiue: that is, whereas I held an opinion that iealousie &amp; absence were rather deficiencies in themselues, and meerely obstacles to continuing kindnesse, I am now perswaded, they may so march in the army of passions, as to haue the Vauntgard in the encounter of affection: but withall I haue learnd so much cunning in morality, as thus to distinguish betweene their abuses. Concerning absence, there is a difference in that which is constrayned, and that which is voluntary. For there may be honourable causes of the one, when the other at (the best) is but an vntoward triall of one another, as imployment in martiall affaires, legation to forraine Princes, trauell to enrich experience, necessitie of trafficke and such like: to all which no worthy party beloued, but will affoord a helping hand, and admit of hope of returne; patience to endure, and wisedome to harken after his endeuours: but voluntary absence, if it could bee veiled vnder the adulterate shew of trials, hath so many ill companions, that it can neither doe well it selfe, nor bring them to any good order. For commonly, it is accompanyed with carelesnesse, slacknesse in obseruation, suspition, feare of idle humours, vnkindnesse; and, at last, meets with vtter obliuion, with diuers of that sort: and what shall the party beloued conceite, if she first demand reasons of his departure, and after finde a breach of vowes for his returne? so that alledge what philosophicall inference you may, and guild it ouer with the imposturing Art of Oratory: I absolutely conclude, that howeuer pleasure is the stronger in

his rarity; loue, true, honest, and perfect loue is no way beholding to a wilfull absence. Touching iealousie, I confesse I haue read of a holy-day in hell, when loue and iealousie were marryed together: but howeuer they feasted for that day, I am sure, all the time after they were turmoyled with despight: For except a great discretion ouermaster suspition; feare, rage, madnesse, watchings, disquiet, absteining from meate and rest, torment of minde, and vntoward distractions accōpany vs, especially if there be the least cause giuen of the breach of vowes. Oh then, loue prooues like a beautiful glasse, which once broken, can neuer be cemented againe: yet I confesse, there may bee a ciuill emulation concerning a Riuals worthinesse, and honest feare to hazzard the thing vnobtained: but once, wiued and contracted vnseparable, there can be no man iealous, but vpon his wiues disloyalty; and she that giues the occasion, must aduenture her honour. I will not therefore haue the marryed man iealous; and would tye the amorous suiter within certaine bounds, lest by transcending, he transshape his owne discretion into fury, and quarrelsome humours, of which, a well disposed Gentlewoman would, nor should be any way guilty: and so, till I heare further, I leaue what you haue heard, to a fauourable construction.
               
                  Yours wheresoeuer.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To the worthie and Noble. L.B.
               
               
                  MY best Lady, I wold not now proue recreant to my former cōstancy,
                     Friendship is afraide to bee forgotten and so pleadeth in her owne behalfe.
                   considering I haue not only plaid the wanton with affliction; but haue had you a looker on to my great encouragement: yet some vnkinde feare begins now to stagger my resolution, because I finde a falling away amongst your selues, like loose earth from a maine banke; and am resolued that this banishment will vtterly

disioynt the frame of our long acquaintance, and at last pull in peeces the bands of true friendship: else how can it be, that I am vnworthy the remembrance? and who would haue thought I should so long haue passed vnregarded? But this is the corruption of greatnesse, either you thinke to make vs slaues by obseruation, or dare not bee your selues vertuous, for feare of cōbersomnes: as for friendship, kindnesse, loue, faith, loyalty, respect, and generous dispositions: they are but voyces and smoake, and as you all vse the same, like Tantalus Apples, which once touched, turne into cinders, and yet hang with glorious shews to the eye. But will you serue me so indeed? and as the diuell seduced the woman, the womā enticed the man, the man offended his Maker; run arme in arme in the race of contempt, and at last triumph in my deiection? Why, doe a Gods name; and then shall you see mee smile in distresse, and reach at the helpe of all helpes out of heauen it selfe: yet for al this, I pray you do not mistake me, but rather impute all to the distraction of my owne feares, then your defects: for I haue euer loued your worth, and while I liue, will thinke you worthy to bee beloued: so that if amongst your other vertues, you can pardon this vnsauorinesse, I shall receiue a new life, and with a further chearefulnesse present my duty once againe vnto you.
               
                  Yours, if you prooue worthy.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To his much esteemed Mrs. P.
               
               
                  
                     A good wife cōmended &amp; compared to a ship at sea.
                  
                  MIstresse, Me thinkes I behold you like a goodly ship at sea; so that, I which am a stander on the shore, must needs be afraide, when I consider the danger of boysterous winds and raging billowes; the perill of the shelfes and sands; the terror of rockes and shores; the inconueniences of harbors and long voyages, and the hazzard of incounters

with pirats and men of warre. Yet againe, when I remember the excellent workemanship in your contriuing, the strength of your building, the comelines of your raising vp, the delicacie of your trimming, and aboue all, the cunning and experience of your Pilot and steersman, I am somewhat pacified, and had rather expose you to the glory of famous voyages, then see you lie still in safe harbour, where time and many inconueniencies shall weare out your keele, and obscure your beautie: therefore go foorth a Gods name, and let me see you vnder saile. For the wisest of men, hath compared a good wife to a ship at sea, which bringeth her food from a farre; and so I make no doubt you will esteeme your selfe, and not aduenter abroade without care, order, and good prouision. In which hope, I leaue you to the fortune of the world, and send my good wishes after you, to fill your sailes with the best winde, and bring you home againe with the fulnesse of prosperitie.
               
                  Yours, and Vertues.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To his well aduised Friend, Mrs. H.
               
               
                  GOod Mistresse,
                  
                     A friend desireth a Gentlewoman to vnite the inward vertues of the mind to outwardlouelinesse.
                   Obedience is better then sacrifice; and therefore doe I send you these triuiall letters according to your command imposed, requesting you not to be too quicke in apprehending any thing amisse, nor stupide in not conceiuing what belongs to your portion: For I protest, I meane to say nothing, to draw your worthinesse in question: nor will leaue out any thing, which may manifest my good opinion of you. I then must begin with a certaine custome of the Schoolemaisters in Lacedemon, who at the first admittance of their schollers, brought them a glasse to looke in: If they were faire and comely, they then aduised them to take heede, that the inward vertues answered the outward louelinesse;

otherwise they might resemble painted sheaths couering onely wodden swords, so that true beauty and handsomnesse consisted in noble parts, not outward feature. If they were mishapen, or outwardly deformed, to endeuour for the adoration of the minde, the light of vnderstanding, and the load-starre of wisedome, whereby they should see no man except against the first shape: and here may man ouerpasse the imperfections of nature, by extolling the conditions of nurture. Now I hope I shall not neede to apply this to your selfe, because I am assured you look in a glasse euery day; and although you do not with Narcessus doate on your owne forme: yet you cannot choose, but be thankefull to nature for so extraordinary benefits conferred; and withall, remember, what a happinesse will make you perfect in this world, if you vnite such inward graces, as begin already to take you by the hand, to pase out the measures of worth and modestie. Go on therefore, go on, that I may liue to say, Yonder goes the wonder of time, and the true example of noblenesse and beautie But I dare not enlarge my wishes, lest I fall into an extasy, and from giuing good counsell to others, crosse mine owne iudgement for not doing as I should my selfe: yet I sweare, if my fortune were worthy the name of a fortune, I durst triumph amongst other masters of earthly contentments, that you thinke me of deseruing to bee commanded by you, and put me in the Catalogue of your chiefest friends. The businesse you inserted, shall bee dispatched, and the next letters discouer, what I thinke of the choise of a husband, and to what conditions I would tie man and wife, liuing in a generous libertie.
               
                  Yours well aduised.
               
            
         
         
            Houshold Letters.
            
               
               
                  
                     To his dearely beloued friend, M.T.
               
               
                  GOod Sir,
                  
                     A gentleman must take heede how he settles himself in the counitry as a farmer.
                   I well perceiue by your worthy disposition, that obliuion cannot get the mastery of vertue in iudicious and honest friends. For howeuer we are remote in body, you haue iustified your remembrance toward mee, yea continued a good opinion, and strengthened it with a conceit of my vnderstanding somwhat; concerning your retired country, tis so, that some thing must now be said, drawing neare to satisfaction, but especially to discharge the dutie of a friend, and faithfull well-willer. Beleeue it then, that in diuers persons a country life neighboureth contemplation and quietnesse, according as we adapt our selues to the same. For a Gentleman, of any reasonable estate, desiring to free himselfe of citie vanities, continuall resort, extraordinary expences, superfluous diet, curiositie of apparell, and alluring temptation, may so seate himselfe and persecute his passion, as to meet with profite and reposednes, in the countrey: but then his resolution must be, not for any occasion to ouerpasse the limits of his intended expences; because, if hee once step into the vaineglorious reputation of a housekeeper, a giuer of almes, and desire of salutations from russet coates: his verie Hall will eate vp his Parlour, and hee shall bee drawne in to spend more at a Christmasse, then his vpper chamber in the citie did in a tweluemonth. But for a free spirit, and a liuer onely vpon a stocke, to bee emboldened with the hope of commoditie, and bettering his estate by a husbandly paines-taking, is as farre from expectation, as to feede a hunting horse on the commons, and yet presume to run with him for the best game. For hee that must say to his seruants, Go, and to his men, Doe this, must be a Centurion, who liues vpon an annuall entrade: but 
                     〈…〉
                  
                  
a vine-dresser, must labour and take paines himselfe, yea haue both art and discretion to manage his affaires, that when he sees a barren figge-tree, he may not in a rage goe and cut it downe, or stocke it vp: but prune it, dung it, dig the earth about it, and make triall of another yeere. Besides, for a Gentleman of worth, to liue in any towne in suspition of a decaied estate, or necessitie to increase himselfe by industry: especially where they doe but seeme better men of eminence, is, as if a man should goe from his vnderstanding friends, who out of ciuilitie would neither disteeme him, nor reueale his secrets: and proclaime the same in publike, exposing himselfe so to derision. For beleeue it, howeuer the country man may bid you good morrow, and stubbornely bend his knee, his heart is full within, and at home hee cares not what he murmures against you; except you are in office to controwle him, as a Iustice of peace: or in abilitie to pleasure him, as Lord of the Mannor: or incredite to terrifie him, as some officer at Court: or in estimation to master him, as some noble mans man or other; especially, a priuy counsellours. Besides, the seruants will loyter, the Bailiffe will sooth you vp with flattery to deceiue you; the cattell will famish or diminish, the plough will go vntoward, the whole family liue in confusion, and the best by-word shall be for you: a poore Gentleman Farmer. All which considered, I could be contented to see you here again, where you may eate meate with the best, and sort out your pleasures at as easie a rate, as you list.
               
                  Your plaine and true Friend.
               
            
            
               
               
                  To his louing and long expected Friend.
               
               
                  GOod Sir,
                  
                     If a Gentleman will be a Farmer, it is the best to obtain the principall house: or the credite of the highest place in the towne.
                   I would not haue you play with me, as the Iewes did with Ieremie about their going into Aegypt, asking his opinion, and swearing a conformitie, till his resolution was contrary to their owne mindes, &amp; so they retracted, scorning the Prophets aduice: thus it may be you expect at my hands to iump with your desires, and please you by way of soothing, and applaud your pretences: surely I onely cast but a doubt, and therefore will thus plainely tell you my opinion. The house and Farme you haue taken, as I vnderstand, is the Mannor house, and hauing many Tenants, you haue as many priuiledges by their seruiceable tenures. Here questionlesse you did verie well: for by this occasion you shall keepe the stubborne man in awe, and confirme the well disposed with securitie: besides, whereas peraduenture you cannot take paines your selfe, or attend the plough in person; the principall point of husbandrie and tricke to winne the game for a meane estate: you shall be sure that the very best husbands will ouer-looke your grounds for you, as glad to spie a fault in them, or come with a tale to pleasure you, euen with offering his seruice to amend it himselfe for you. But withall, is not the house of too great receipt, costly to furnish, chargeable to repaire, dangerous to keepe, and drawing on extraordinarie expences euen for fewell and maintenance? besides, is there not a certaine expectation of extraordinary house-keeping, and entertaining of passengers? Wherein to proceede, it will drinke vppe the profite of the Farme like a Spunge; wherein to drawe backe, will drowne your reputation in vilipending. This is that I would say vnto you, so that if you meete with discretion,

and iudgement in so intricate a businesse; surely I must applaude your choise for taking the mannor house; but if you chance vpon iollitie, or vaine-glory, determining to thriue, you will take as wrong a course in being a farmer, as I haue done in aduising you against your minde, and desires.
               
                  Yours, with good wishes.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To his well aduised friend, S. G.
               
               
                  
                     Concerning the building and ordring a house with retaining of seruants.
                  
                  SIR, When I opened your last letter, and ouerviewed the sentences diuided into interrogatories, I was almost affrighted, as if there had bene a citation sent for me: but after I considered the particulars, and saw they were onely houshold aduertisements, or (if you will) husbandly questions, for the better setling a man in the possession of contentment: I cheered my selfe, and thought it good manners thus to answer them; wherein, if I pay you in your owne coine, and not once to looke into the treasure house of Oratorie for any rhetoricall amplification, remēber the iustice of my cause, and the low flight of my subiect. But to the purpose: VVhereas you demand, how you should build your house? I answer thus; That though former times esteemed it better to haue a house too litle for a day, then too bigge for a whole yeare, and cared for no conueniencie of lodgings, so the hall and kitchin were bigge enough to dresse meate, and entertaine company; yet doe not you so, but discouer a good spirite by the outward fashion of your building, choose a handsome prospect and wholesome scituation; let your lodgings bee warme and light, for you may darken them at pleasure; your staires easie, and your roomes of entertainment large &amp; delightsome; the out-houses conuenient, the gardens and orchyards to the South and your owne chambers neere your

husbandrie, yet as farre from annoyance as you may. In a word, let the whole frame discouer your willingnesse to do well, rather then brand you to hereafter memory for couetous and basely disposed; and if you can leaue an estate of a thousand markes behinde you, let the passers by, viewing the house imagin it a 1000. pound a yeare. For so a second good husband &amp; a good family to match in, may raise it in another age, and then followeth a kinde of repining, that my father or grandfather was not well aduised, and esteemed more of money, then the reputation of his family. But, aboue all, take heed you exceed not this proportion, lest either you incurre derision, for beginning a worke you were not able to finish; or leaue the house to emptinesse and decay, if your next heire be not sufficient to adorne and furnish it. Whereas you demand what retinue to keepe? I answer, Haue rather one too few, then two too many, &amp; of al other things, take heed to an idle seruāt for corrupting the rest: for I cannot but resemble him to a stinking broad spreading burre, who is not onely bad in it selfe, but hinders the rest of the grasse growing round about it. And concerning outward shew, by that time your Clearke, Coachman, Butler, keeper of your Wardrobe, chiefe Bailiffe, and better sort of husbandmen be instructed the houre of attendance, and haue also an honest care and cunning, cleanely to shift themselues, there may be a sufficient ostentation for a hundred pound a yeare. Wheras you demand what fare you should keepe: I answer thus; let not the Sunday so exceed, as there be scarcitie in the weeke following: giue the laborer sufficient, for dainties fill not the belly: allow not euery one a breakefast, nor euery day three meales: haue your meate warm and good, but do not reserue the best dish, till it be starke naught: if a neighbour come in about businesse, let him tarry a Gods name; if he be inuited, set before him, what he hath not

at home; rather haue a litle &amp; fresh, thē return a great deale to smell of the dry larder; and aboue all, let not the end of the table be so forgotten, either to be serued with blowne drinke, stale bread, or refuse meate: (For goers and commers by the dore will looke for that, and better) because such a heart and tongue may sit at your boord, as will repine at his nasty entertainment; and be bold to publish your reproach. Wheras you demand what cattell to keep, I answer thus. For a Gentleman, Oxen are better then Horse, because after any mischance they may be fed for the butcher, and few men of sort would cart for mony, or attend the court with a Teeme: let such doe that, as loue toile and mony, and tast any paines taking with the sauerines of profit: those geldings you keepe, let them be wel &amp; orderly kept: so that if your country must be serued, you haue one in readines: the seruāts which ride with you, let them be honest, carefull, and well prouided, and take heed of basenes, as plowing cattell, broken saddles, patcht bootes, vnmatched spurres, a sword without a chape: nay I would not haue the sword and hangers of one fashion, and girdle or dagger of another, with infinit such disparities, and meerely ridiculous nastinesse. Wheras you demand what gouernment to obserue? I answer generally thus: and for particulars, you shall heare more heereafter: Aboue all, remember the Sabboth, and rather feast of any day, then of that: not but that the Sabboath is a continuall feast, but how? for spirituall purposes, not filthy gurmundice: more then necessity of life, and good vse of conuersation: let no swearer nor prophane person, once or twise admonished, tarry with you: giue good examples by your owne praiers: and rather by gentle exprobration, then filthy vndecncies reprehend your seruants, but suffer them not to be masters amongst themselues. To conclude, be charitable towards offenders, gentle to inferiors, willing

to giue, carefull of good neighbours, and remember the sicke labourer, and fainting soule.
               
                  Yours, with a true heart.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To his respected Friend, Mrs. G.
               
               
                  MY old acquaintance,
                  
                     Whether a gentlewoman may with her credit let out lodgings for money.
                   I vnderstand by your first seruant, that you haue enlarged your minde with your house, determining to lodge ciuill Gentlemen, and to raise a benefit from their entertainment: besides, you adde for excuse, want of company, and that your house is ouer-great for your owne family: here is now a subiect of plentifull matter, and in dilating the same, I must needes incurre displeasure on all sides. But there is now no remedy; you haue in a manner enioyned me to deliuer my opinion, &amp; I will be briefe and plaine, according to my skill. I then would with one blow cut off the Hydraes head of confusion, and ouerthrow all distinction by the negatiue, thus; That a Gentlewoman, whether widdow or wife, liuing in the freedome of reputatiō, is not to be seruile in any thing, nor to bedurtie herselfe with the dregges of any couetousnesse, or sinister practises against her credite. For as it is vnbefitting to a Gentleman to bee guiltie of any seruile crime; so it is vndecent to a Centlewoman to incurre the hazzard of her honestie by any base inclination. Now what can the best lodging and lodgers maintaine, but the inconueniences depending will quickely ouer-sway the the profite following? For if they be onely men, they must haue seruants, and commers, and goers; the seruants shall bedurty your carpets and couerlets (if the masters themselues are tied within the circle of respect and ciuilitie) wipe their bootes and scabberds on your best furnitures, tosse your kitchen, commaund your vtensels, turmoyle

your house, and vpon the least contradiction burst out into violent and offensiue tearmes: and for your selfe at the best, you shall passe with the character of Hostesse, Land-ladie, Sweete heart, or some such inuention. The commers and goers shall bee of all sorts, yea many times Seamsters, Launderers, kinsewomen, and such like, not without some venomous inclination to incontinencie and riot, vnder the handsome greene grasse and colour of businesse, and entertainement. If they bee onely women, I can say no more, but women will bee women, who cannot liue without the company of men; and then if the fire and tow be put together, there must needes be combustion, what glorious shew soeuer the flame appeare with; or what admirable cunning is vsed in the kindling or extinguishing: so that, hold the ballance of an vpright conscience how you will, you shall not scape the imputatiō of dishonest practises from base calumniation, howeuer the better sort hold their peace to make you an instrument for their pleasures. If they bee men and women, so a doubling of many inconueniencies; there is but onely this excuse affoorded, that Opportunitie is a baude to Corruption, and vncleane persons are now safe, being so conueniently lodged. This is briefly my opinion touching a Gentlewoman that lodgeth for money. But for others that are tradesmen, and must aduance their estates from the gaines of their profession, I dispute not at all, but leaue it as a thing indifferent to my approbation, howeuer I would not haue them lose the benefits of their endeauours, when they may make double vse of them. First, in the rent of their chambers, next, in the encrease of customers for the venting such wares as they expose to sale, wherein their credite lyeth, onely at the state in those customary vsances of swearing,

lip-labour, and the secrets of their businesse, so that letting their lodgings, may seeme lesse offensiue through a cunning ignorance, then many indirect speeches through a customary dissembling.
               
                  Yours, well affected.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To his assured friend Mr. S.S.
               
               
                  GOod Sir,
                  
                     The danger of disagreement between man and wife with their dueties.
                   It was an vnsauory news to me, when I heard that some ominous action had diuided the mutuall agreement betweene you and your wife, wherein I cannot resemble you better, then to a churlish husbandman, who putteth some head-strong horse into his Teeme, and when they go forward, he striueth backeward, the seruants beating him to greater rage, and the Master wanting discretion to take him away, till a more conuenient season, so that howeuer they disquiet themselues, I am sure the war in hand, is rather hindered then forwarded. Thus is it, when man and wife are not fast tyed in the bands of loue and discretion, but subiect the whole house to confusion, and send disgracefull rumor abroad to busie idle tongues, with many vntruths amongst some certainties. For alas, what man will be so foolish that loueth cleanlinesse, as to besmeere himselfe with durt and filth? what husband will be so senslesse as to reuile his wife, and bring his owne name in question? what shall the children thinke to heare their mother called whore? what shall the seruants imagine to see their mistresse distracted with iealousie and suspition of one side, and shame and calumniation on the other side? what shall the neighbours imagine, to bee acquainted with such disgraces, and whisper that a Gentleman so abused himselfe, or durst discredit his wife. Come, this must not be; For as women must admit of an honorable obedience, rather then imperious controwle, of

sweete and gentle perswasion, rather then contentious exprobation: of a modest disposing themselues to all household affaires, then a busie entermedling with their husbands affaires; of a fashionable entertainement at all seasons, especially a wise obseruation according to time and occasion: rather then a sudden apprehension of their husbands distemprature, either in passion or affection: so must men abandon themselues from home inconueniences, beare with their wiues imperfections, not taunt before seruants, not burst out into filthy and scurrilous chiding, or reproches at all; be charitable euen concerning offence, not churlish for trifles, not deny necessaries, and in no sort giue ill example by leaud life, or bad husbandry: lest wants knocke at the doore, and then will bitternesse and displeasure enter. So that concerning falling out betweene man and wife, I thus conclude; If it bee possible to auoyde all eruptions against ciuill life, louely behauour, or necessarie businesse: but if disagreements begin to shew a face, let the man leaue the wife for that time, and not endure the contention: let the wife retire her selfe, if the man begin, and not dare to reason the matter.
               
                  Yours, in religious care.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To his approoued Friend, R.S.
               
               
                  
                     How children ought to be brought vp.
                  
                  GOod Sir, Your last letters were so passionate, that sure in the writing you vented sighes, if you did not shed teares, and I cannot blame you: For, a father that hath an irrigular sonne, and a dangerous daughter, not only weareth out his time to prouide them maintenance, and leaue a competency behind him, that they may ranke in the foreward of ciuill people: but watcheth his houres, and growes gray with care, lest one will not be reclaimed,

and the other step aside into wantonnesse. Therefore saith the wise man, that hee that setleth his sonne, hath layde a strong foundation, and he that marrieth his daughter, hath dispatched his chiefest businesse. Whereupon I would aduise you, concerning your sonnes, not to cocker them too much, or be ouer-nice, either at their vprising or dyet: not to let slip their yeares, but commit them as soone as you can into the hands of instruction: bee not of that minde, that the rod must be a tyrant to them, but rather endeuor that they feare to offend for the loue of vertue, then feare of punishment: suffer neither oath nor vncleanely speech to profane or defile their mouth, nor let them presume proudly to insult, or vnmannerly to reuile the meanest seruant. Comming forward, and growing to vnderstanding, make not nature a slaue to cunning or profit; that is, enforce them not against their owne inclination to follow that which is irkesome vnto them. For, if you tie a great spirit to a seruile trade, hee will neuer proue good chapman; or contend with dul capacitie about mistical secrets, he will neuer grow good scholler, &amp; so in the rest: let them euer be, where either the best company shal giue good example; or if inconueniences follow, they may haue the shadow of honourable purposes: but aboue all, let them neither practise deceit nor dishonestie: for, when a mind is once corrupted with basenes, it resembles a stinking vessel, which will neuer be througly sweetned. Concerning your daughter, presume not too much of our countrey liberty; for wantonnesse standeth at the corner of euery Street, to inuite the commers-by: yet do not so restraine her, that shee may eyther murmure at the same, or complaine to her neighbours of her Parents hard hand, as though shee were viciously inclined by nature. If it bee possible, rather school her within dores, thē aduenture her

with a pedant abroad; and for dancing, courtship, and such like: let thē be vsed rather like a feather to a litle dust, which may be brushed from the garment, the guard or seame, which shall weare out with the cloath: giue them warning of familiarity with the seruants: For a curteous ciuility becommeth the children of Gentlemen, but wanton embraces, sitting on the knee, bearing in armes, and such like, be fearefull signes of following confusion, and too forward desires: sitting vp late, allow not; nor giue way vnto night banquets: For they resemble the stolne bread in the Prouerbs: and a strumpets Title is the nethermost hell, wherein the name of Virgine is perpetuallie damned: make them not proud, either of natures portion, or the fathers dowry. For women will looke in a glasse, and shal not want any flattering to seduce them to vanity: and concerning the vpshot of all reckonings, which is mariage, let her neither assume so dangerous a liberty, as to run at randome without your consent: nor be you so transported with a variety of selfe-loue, as to draw her perforce to vnpreuentable inconueniences, yea many times mischifes, and confusion. For, these matches in infancy, as (contracts for mony without liking; enforcemēts, to vnequall yeeres, or nasty disparily, with diuers of that kind) are meerely, pullies to winde vp care, sorrow, and discontentments, and at one letting flippe the hold, to hurry them on the head of a poore afflicted virgin.
               
                  Yours, in true libery.
               
            
            
               
                  To his ill aduised friend, I. M.
               
               
                  SIR, I am not ignorant, that the two mastring corbes, that gouern the reines of the whole world,
                     how seruants ought to be instructed.
                   are praemium and Poena, reward, and punishment. I doe also know, that in a statute against stabbing and wilfull murther,

there is a clause of exception inserted, for fathers and masters in correcting their children and seruants: yet will I giue no such way to the violence of passion, as that a Gentleman, or otherwise ciuill disposed liuer, should strike or wound his seruant with any dangerous weapon: nor can I any way colour your temeritie, for contending so long with that boysterous knaue, as to bee compelled to free your selfe: (for such be the words of your excuse out of his robustious closing with you) by the stabbe of a dagger, which ranne 9. inches vpward ouer his pappe. Beleeue me, it was a fearefull falling off, and I wish in my heart there had beene no such occasion giuen to draw your discretion in question, nay to endanger your person and estate. For if he had miscaryed, the king hauing lost a subiect, you must needs haue beene brought to iudiciall triall, &amp; then lawes are according to the Iudges construction, or Iurors interpretation. Well, I hope from henceforh you will be better aduised, and rather bring vp your seruants so, that either they shall not offend, or after the offence be apprehensiue of instruction with more gentle correction. Therefore choose the sonnes of such men, as rather will second their fathers honesty and credite, then follow their owne wantonnesse and riot: let euery one haue instruction for their feuerall places, yet teach them al to obey when you command, and not one to command another: haue an eye vnto the honest diligence of the meanest, and grace him with a cheereful reward. If you chide for good occasion, ler the ptowdest be the subiect of your first admonition; wherein be so temperate, that vndecent reuilings heate not your mouth, but words sauouring of wisedome and iustice. Thus shall the rest stand in awe, when they see you are not partiall or fearefull: if aduice serue not, spare not a smarting blow; which if it prooue a sturrer vp of rage or contēpt in him, bring him to publike

iustice, but be not you on him, your own executioner: suffer neither oathes nor prophanation: no gaming on the Sabbath, nor for much mony at any time: nay, let it be rather a recreation, with a modest acknowledging your wincking at small faultes, then any comaunding voice to passe away the time, or please themselues: let them not slack the houres of attendance, nor the entertainment of friendes: giue eare to no busie bodies, tale-tellers, nor flatterers of your imperfections, least gouernment, turne to confusion; and recreation to dissipation: as pride is a drawer on of filthy enormities, so nastines and vncomely adorning themselues brings surquedry, and loathsomenes. To conclude, in one word, let your seruants be such of all sortes, as shall doe what you prescribe, rather then make vse of the time to maintaine their owne pleasures, and licentiousnes: as for such as must performe inferior seruill duties, pay them truly, and send them to their worke orderly: neglect no seruice of God for any cause: and if you haue (as you ought) priuate praiers, let all come, and know what reuerence meaneth: hearken to the time of sicknes, and let them not complaine for want, nor cry out to God for susteyning more then they can away with: vpon good deseruing, adde a recompence, and let none presume to strike or reuile another. Infinit other particulars would draw on many lines, but these shall sufice, till better conueniency to shew my loue and duty, and serue for caution and aduertisement.
               
                  Yours, in charitable aduise.
               
            
         
         
            Politike Letters.
            
               
                  To his noble Lady and Vertuously respected, T.G.
               
               
                  WOrthy Lady, I thinke it not befitting the time, nor the tendernes of your sex, to giue such life to your memory, as Catalogue the praises of that worthy knight

deceased,
                     Women in yeares should rather looke for rich aduancement, then wanton satisfaction.
                   or draw in question his want of iudgement in this one point, or peraduenture abilitie, in leauing you thus wrapped vntowardly in accounts, and bringing you (as hauing fiue daughters to marry) to the house of care and sadnesse, further then the sorrow of his losse, and the ceremonies of his exequies pretended. But I would rather open the store-house of instruction and comfort, and shew you the Embleme of Fortune, or Time shadowed with a hairy foretop, as if we might take hold thereon for any purpose; and a bald head behind, as if opportunity let slip, were not to be recouered. Therfore without ceremony, if there were not necessitie, yet out of a necessary policy, let not the noble Iudge be dallyed with in his honorable purposes: and considering the heat of youth is spent; and as the Poets sing, that Hiperions fires burne not with a wonted blase, be rather cautelous for a well disposed life, then indirect satisfaction of fancy: this I would say if you were rich and childlesse, good helpes in all times both good and bad: but as time hath brought you to wrastle with some inconueniences, you must learne if it be possible to giue a fall, rather then a take foyle: &amp; both for your own and childrens sake, dispence with wantonnesse, and be rather prouidently ambitious, thē ambitiously improuident. For by this match, your quietus est shall be obtained, your peace shall be made without disquiet; your accounts shut out of the kings Exchequer; your houshold affaires reducted to an vniformity; your lap filled with money; your eares with submissiue petitions; and your chamber with the better sort of visiters; your daughters shall still walke in the schoole of courtlinesse and befitting suters, and rather be taught to step vp to honor, then fall downe to feare of preferment: euen their youthfull desires for ornament and cost shall bee so supplyed, that you shall graunt without grudging, and they demaund without

timorousnesse or combersome importunity: their portions shall be sure of augmentation. For though he do not open the strings of his owne purse, yet from custome, the vnder officers will bring in presents: and such Gentlemen as before would make question of some incombances, shall now attend your house for resort and noble conuersation: so that without controuersie there is no refusing his loue, nor disputing with any maligne circumstances of his yeares and humours.
               
                  Yours, in honest aduise.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To his much disquieted Friend, A.S.
               
               
                  
                     A Gentlemā should not bee seruant to any man that hath a sufficient estate of his owne: but if he be with what policy he must contract it.
                  
                  SIR, I am ashamed to shew my selfe a traitor to gentry, and binde a free spirit to the seruitude of controwle: for the wisest &amp; greatest must faile through imperfections, and he which submits to the command of another, cannot tell how he may bee driuen to impatience: so that I could sweare, that it were vnbefitting to a man of your estate, a Gentleman of blood, a housekeeper of account, a Iustice of peace, and a commander of many seruants, to fall backe into the contemned estate of seruitude, &amp; weare anothers blew coat. Yet because pollicy hath some secret walks into which Vertue will not enter, and that I see errors hale vs along to dangerous inconueniences, without satisfaction of humours, I am contented at this time to deceiue your apprehension with the mist of pollicie, with guilefull feeding of ambitious and contentious humours. If then your feare be so great of the knight your adioyning neighbour, and Lord of the mannor, that either you must come to triall of the law, and profuse expences, or meet with contracted browes, and perillous encounters: there is no such way to wipe away the feare of these encombrances, as the

supportation of the great Lord you speake of, whose seruice must be orderly implored, but cunningly obtained: wherein I would haue you resemble the Lapwing, which cryeth farthest from her nest; and so fasten your selfe vpon him, rather with admiration of his vertues, which haue altogether attracted your submission, then feare of your owne defects, or desire to bee, by his helpe, reuenged on your aduersary: and this you must strengthen a while with attendants and presence, marking whom he admits to his secret familiarity, and consorting with them, not so much for fellowship, as to be a mediation betweene your Lord and your self when occasion shall burst out; &amp; shew some particulars of your wrongs, where by way of discourse you may intimate, that you wonder at your aduersaries audaciousnesse, not to forbeare you now for his honors sake, considering one vertue enclined to another, and he would not maintaine any iniustice for a world. As for those controuersies impending, his Lordship should command him as his seruant, and ouer-rule all, as should seeme good to his honourable pleasure. This is the surest channell, as I take it, to lanch foorth your ship in the troublesome Sea of contentions, with your betters, or at least such, whom the worldes estimation reputeth in a higher eminence: So that if you can dispence with some disgraces, which may chance by distemperature of your Lord, and calumniation standing on the tip of idle tongues abroade, you may meet with sedition of countrey troubles, and peraduenture carry the sway of applause and obseruation, euen at publike imitations, as your credit with your master is subiect to report or opinion.
               
                  Yours, in honourable loue.
               
            
            
               
               
                  
                     To her louing Neece, G. B.
               
               
                  
                     No oathes to be beleeued before marriage.
                  
                  MY dearest Loue, There hath passed and ouer-passed a rumour of the young Counts affecting you, wherein loue hath dealt like himselfe, and chained him to certaine streights of passion: so that by voluntary oath he hath protested conditionall mariage, if you please to afford him a primordiall satisfaction: wherein loue may Simpathise between you I know not, but meerly out of honest &amp; honorable policy, goe into the open channell, rather then come neere the bankes of Nylus, where Crocodiles may deceiue you with teares; &amp; of all other things, let no man boast of diuiding you, til you yeeld him possession of al together: &amp; this is a caution euen amongst wantons, not to marry with him to whom dotage or misfortune hath prostituted them. For what hope is there but a following eternall iealousie? &amp; when a breach is so made, a continuall roaring and thundering of whole vollies of checkes, taunts, and opprobrious tearmes, of whore, strumpet, filth? What had I, but another might haue gotten? and what know I, but thou art still a broken glasse neuer to be cemented againe? Therefore sweete Neece, stand vpon a strong guard of circumspection, and doe not expose the certaintie of your honorable merite and high attracting worthinesse, to the vncertainty of deceiueable promises: I care not, though I tearme them fully resolued oathes. For one way they are yet in the pleasure of the first maker: another way, in the danger of better resolued conceit, when the heate of wantonnesse is reclaimed, and some new displeasure shall open a gappe of both your ouer-sights. But I hope I neede not ambiguously handle the cause of your vertue, and modest inclination; considering you haue many

times cast a defiance in the face of temptation: and will now surely, when you are to bee tryed pure gold indeede, not make it adulterate by ambitious desires, or foolish credulitie.
               
                  Yours, in preuailing truth.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To his louing Cousin at Court, H.A.
               
               
                  GOod Cousin, Seeing you are resolued to follow the sway of time,
                     He that will enrich himselfe by seruice must follow some thriuing officer.
                   and become a Courtier, with an intent to depend vpon the fauourite of the kingdome, that noble and generous Count: you may take your owne race to leape, as high, and farre as you can: But as my aduise and experience whispers to pleasure you, there is no policie in it at all, considering your proiect to your selfe of bettering your estate, and husbandly desires to fill your purse, and not vaine-glorious ostentation, or publike glistering with feathers and colours, which many times beare better men then your selfe, to dangerous inconueniences; and at the best, draw on expences without other satisfaction, then courtly smiles, and deceitfull smoke-promises. Besides, there shall be so many before you hanging on expectation of sute preferments, that when you shall thinke to step forward, there will scarce bee roome for you to lay on a finger on the preuailing end of the beame of prosperitie. Therefore be ruled by me, considering some good parts may adde to your youth reputatiō, and to good carriage more respect; place your selfe as neere some quiet officer as you can, and by seruiceable attendance, not obscuring your qualitie; giue him notice of your willingnesse to bee commanded, and aptnesse to bee imployed, as he shall thinke conuenient.
               
                  Thus shall you contriue and winde your selfe into some profit at home, and be knowne well enough abroad: yea so well, that performing your duty for the priuat affaires of your Maister, when alteration shall happen, you may by some voices be called to the publike managing affaires for the state.
               
                  Yours, as you can desire.
               
            
            
               
                  To his deerest brother, G. D.
               
               
                  
                     The Lady of the house must be obserued of such as meane to thriue under the Lord.
                  
                  GOod Brother, as I am glad, that you haue extracted the loue of your honourable Lord: so would I be the gladder, if you did contriue the continuance of the same. For there is no lesse cunning in keeping a thing well gotten, then in attaining it before it be in possession; but if it be as I heare, you are so far from true pollicy in this kind, that I am afraid presumption will trip your expectation on the ground, and giue your forwardnes a foile. For they say, that you disagree with my Lady, and vnder colour of my Lords profit, oppose her in triuiall demaunds: take heed (I pray you) in time, and if you meane to stand firme, as you sometime, for reuerence of her estate, take her by the arme to lead her along, let her likewise take you by the hand, to settle you in securitie. For if women wrought Salomon the wisest and greatest of all Princes, out of his full course of vertue and pietie, such a woman as she will quickly conceiue, if she be disesteemed of you, and as quickly gone to mislike of your perēptorines, or audatiousnes, and as quickly desire to be reuenged, wherein if she be resolute, you shall not know who hurt you, nor she care, how you are ouerthrowne: therefore good brother, be not deceiued in this contumacy, but reduce your selfe to vnderstand, there is no aduauncing the colours of establishment on the citadel of your Ladies fauor, if the Lady

Barricado the entrance, or seeme enuious after your proceeding.
               
                  Yours, in all occasions.
               
            
            
               
                  To the honourable L. and his high esteemed Patron.
               
               
                  RIght Honourable, Although all the rivulets of fauour and grace,
                     Some Lord or other must be made an Agent to obtaine a suite of the king.
                   haue their sowrce and flowings from the fountaine and spring of Maiestie: (for neither is honour bestowed, petition granted, commission sealed, nor any things disposed without the kings liking and firme:) Yet is there a kinde of policie to bee vsed in contriuing and compassing the same. For to step bluntly to a king, and vrge him to a grant, or peraduenture expostulate the matter with him, may seeme vnsauery, and without the sure ground of a high exalted fauorite, receiue a protraction, if not a deniall: therefore your honor must be contented to doe as the Lords of France amongst themselues, one to preferre the suite and request of another: so that if this Baron would haue an addition of honour, that Counselseller is engaged, and intimates to the Prince his woorth, his valure, his vertue, his former imployment, and such like. If that Earle would haue such a grant, then doth the other take a time to illustrate the latters praises, and inferre the necessitie of acknowledging &amp; rewarding the same, with all the gratious properties of liberalitie incident to a Prince. Thus must your Lordship make some second meanes, and how euer Honour could be contented to repine to depend vpon the liking of inferiors: yet must policy restraine passion, and discretion giue you notice when the king is disposed to grace: and so though a present must be exacted, you need onely hold your head, and be contented till your businesse bee determined, in which you must apply your selfe to the time, so farre as in

honestie you may: But you must speake them faire whom you like not; and smile where the heart swelles, and goe along euen with the obseruation of Court, though you shuld take a iourney another way to better purpose. These be the passages to which time and fortune driues all attendants in Princes courtes, and so it is fit so farre as policie may not hinder the peace of a good conscience. For God hath said, they are Gods, and there is no such proximity to a godhead, as with a breath to aduance whom they will, to haue mercy on whom they please, and to cast downe the presumption of such who abuse their fauor for vnhonest pretences. And thus I leaue your honor to the order prescribed, and successe of affaires.
               
                  Your Honors obseruant.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To the Right Honorable and worthy L. G.
               
               
                  RIght Honorable, seeing you haue vouchsafed to descend so low a degree of humiliation, as to make me partaker of your secrets:
                     Suites in court are neuer dispatched without great attendance.
                   I will surely raise vp my selfe (as farre as I dare) to yeelde you some reason for our last conference; and warrant your honor, that there is no vnkindnes thrust vpon you, though your busines seeme detracted, and (as you supposed) procrastinated: For beleeue it, there is a pollicy of state, not to dispatch suiters too fast, for diminishing the glory of the present court, and weakning the maiesty of the Prince: if euery one should be admitted at their owne pleasure: &amp; as in the height of martiall dissipline, some things must be absolutely commaunded, not disputed vpon, all secrets are not to be reuealed, and euery man that dare aske a question, must not be resolued: so in the Counsell of kinges, and their best ordered courts, no man ought to contest with the iudgement, that the Chancellor shall pronounce: or traduce the last

verdict after he hath appealed to the Prince. For if you seldome bring a Phisition in question, that knowing his patient out of danger of death, and of such a constitution, that some excellent potion will quickly aduance him to the pristinate state of health, and yet dallieth with him awhile, peraduenture to shew some secrets of arts: peraduenture to make him beleeue a difficulty in the recouery, and perauenture to inrich his purse by an often resort to him that is able to giue. There is no reason to presume so farre, as to cal in question the affairs of great Counsellors, especially determining for the common good, without partiall interposing either their own purposes or passions: nor can any man come vnto them at any time, but diuers shall bee found afore him, who challenge a dispatch of their businesse, according to the priority of their suites: therfore your honor must lay no such burthen of the state, to thinke, if there were such an interposition, that any mans priuate malice could preuayle with the authoritie, grauitie and wisedome of the rest. Besides, it may be there is a further policie to draw out the thred of this cloth of businesse at the greatest length, to keep you from a further suite, or troubling the king with other matters of importance, till this be dispatched, and hung on the file of assurance in your behalfe. This I presumed to write vnto you, because you commanded: but in regard there bee some things you will not command, nor I can iustisie in the answer; I meane to reserue them till I haue opportunitie to present my dutie vnto you, as you haue shewed a generous minde, to manifest your good opinion toward me.
               
                  Your Honours deuoted.
               
            
            
               
               
                  
                     To his well experienced friend, and noble minded Gentleman, G. P.
               
               
                  
                     A military policy to restraine insolent mutinies.
                  
                  NOble Sir, Whereas at your last conference you told me comming from Germany to Antwerpe, you saw no watch set, and a kinde of fearefull stilnesse amongst the souldiers, wherein I could not resolue you so suddenly, because you spread no larger cloth of nouelties, and peraduenture durst not in that place raise any suspition by demanding many questions: I haue now thought good to adde to your experience some intelligences of my owne, whereby as you well sayd, then I doe gather the occasion of that defection, and desisting from their martiall ceremonies: You must then vnderstand, that the Garrisons haue newly mutined, and from insolent attempts drawne a fearefull execution on some principall offendors: the Gouernour of the towne and citadell, did put in practise an ancient vsance and policie of martiall discipline, to command a cessation from orderly watch, and souldier-like seruices: And this was an absolute custome euen amongst the Romans, that when insolent and tumultuous souldiers had looked with grimme and traiterous visages on the face of good order, and made a repugnant disobedience against all law and restraint, the Captaines presently prohibited any calling to the watch, any preparation to the Parado, beating the drums, attending the colours, or to vse any ceremonious brauerie: whereby the mutiners, that were so lusty before, seeing what a confusion they had wrought, and how they presented a sort of Padlarie reapers in a scattered field, beganne to bewaile the want of their honourable customes, and to confesse their former rudenesse and ouersight. And this was the cause of the stilnesse in Antwerpe, at your lodging

in the towne. And amongst other policies of warre, according to the seuerall businesse in hand, of which you shall heare more hereafter, when we haue further leisure to dispute of other occurrents.
               
                  Yours, in terror of death.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To his well disposed Friend, Mr. M.D.
               
               
                  GOod Sir,
                  
                     Wat policy soeuer ambition build vpon, it is at last cast downe with death and destruction.
                   Conceiue of me what you please, there is not a man in this kingdome shall haue more interest in me, then your selfe; and that you shall well perceiue by my plain and true satisfaction of your demands, although it be somwhat too intricate to deale in such confused questions, and dangerous relation of businesse; Whereas then you demand the reason, why so many great and noble persons haue (as it were) met with death and destruction, in the violent race of their turbulent innouation, and insolent wilfulnesse: not taking warning by precedent examples, nor terrified with the euer-impending reward of treason, which is the ouerthrow both of themselues and families. I answer, that truely I can yeeld you no reason, because all they pretend, is not onely against reason, but many times against policie, and at all times against honesty and religion: yet can I giue you some false fires, and (as it were) contriue adulterate excuses out of fauour and partialitie. You haue read then that the diuell in compassing the earth, did consider mens frailties in his progresse, and as the principall marke of the world, hee most gloriously attempts, principallities and powers: so that sometimes hee pleadeth the axiomes of Philosohers, and reciteth a pestilent position out of Euripides: that if faith and loyaltie be to be rent asunder, it is excusable, in compassing

a Diademe, and reaching at a Crowne. Thus Stephen, Earle of Blois, vsurped the kingdome of England, and made warres on the faction of the Empresse. And thus Henrie the fourth in fringed his first vowe, to steppe no further then the Dutchie of Lancaster: but when hee found no hinderances, hee quickely ranged ouer all other territories and iurisdictions. Sometimes hee dilates Matchiuilian policies, and telleth men that are cruell and ambitious, that they which meane to haue a smooth walke to contentment, yea to passe the time in any Orchard or Garden of pleasure, must not onely remooue the greater blockes, stickes, and stones: but as occasion serues, picke out the sharpe pibbles, and rowle the same smoother. Thus Athaliah destroyed the kings stocke to gaine the Diademe. And thus Richard the third, first remooued the Queenes kindred, after vsurped the persons of the two Princes. Sometimes hee whispereth in the eares of moderate kings, that they may bee iealous in pointes of soueraigntie; and who shall controwle them, if they settle their feares and peace, though they see the bleeding neckes of such as they feare? Thus Adoniah fell vnder his yonger brother. Thus Nero put Corbulo and Germanicus to death, because they were reputed worthie of the kingdome. Thus was Mortimer in Henrie the fourths time, as it were, banished from the Court. Thus was long before that, Robert Duke of Normandie depriued of his eyes. Thus was Edward Plantagenet Earle of Warwicke imprisoned and destroyed: with many such like. Sometimes hee maketh the iustifying of a faction, and the louing of one another, and honest cause of rebellion: As you saw in the Barons 
                     〈◊〉
                  , in the beginning of Henrie the fourth, when the king should haue bene

destroyed at Oxenford, and afterward when the Percies maintayned the coadiutements of Worcester and Mortimer. Sometimes hee rayseth innouation and treason out of the circle of ambition and vaine-glory, vpon any pretence of a title, as you saw in the first claime of Richard Plantagenet, Duke of Yorke: and in the last tumults of the Earl of Warrewicke, in Edward the fourths time. Sometimes hee deceiueth honour with couetousnesse, and bogges the mindes of generous spirits with hope of increase of liuing, and augmentations of titles. Thus was the Duke of Buckingham caught in a snare of the Earledome of Hertford, and not onely streched his arme out to helpe Richard the third to mount on the throne of Maiestie, against all religion and pietie: but to spreade the colours of his owne reuenge against the tyrant himselfe: whereby hee lost his head. Sometimes hee impostures men with the fanaticall hopes of diuellish promises from forcerie, and witchcraft: As you may reade of Elinor Cobham, who well expected the preferment of the Protector her husband, and of H
                        •••
                     ford Duke of Buckingham, whom the Cardinall ouerthrew in Henry the eights time. Somtimes hee bloweth the bellowes of popularitie, and swelleth men ouer bigge with the windy breath of opinion: as in diuers worthy presidents, and instances of our owne, wherin euen the best subiects haue yet taken a wrong course to curbe their Princes, and making good causes (as reformation of disorders, remoouing of euill Councellours, protecting of Iustice, and maintaining the honour of martiall discipline, &amp;c. Baudes to wicked and troublesome spirits, haue in the ende pulled on death and insupportable affliction on themselues and families: and sometimes he inciteth euen cōmon persons to presumptuous darings

and dangerous troubles, falsifying their wicked pretences, on the glorious shewes of the kingdomes good, as in the Irish expeditions, the rebellions of Straw, and Cade: the wicked purpose of Perkin Marbeck: the clamours of Ket, the insurrections of the North, and such like: In all which, from the beginning to the ending, there is no one sound and substantiall reason, but must needs be ouerthrowne with the shoulderinsg of truth and vprightnes. And thus could I fill you volumes with precepts and instances, and both diuide and subdiuide to infinit particulars, wherein greatnes and pollicy resemble poison in the hearts of corrupt persons, which runneth from veine to veine, and neuer desisteth till all be infected: and at last the very life blood contaminated: Nay, I could haue spread your letter to a greater bredth, euen with modern examples, and daily positions: but I cannot name them without offence, and traducing of many of their imperfections and follies: and therefore I will leaue what I may not write, to a priuate relation, when we may meet with securitie.
               
                  Yours, to trust onely.
               
            
            
               
                  To her deerest husband.
               
               
                  MY onely life, I may not write at large, nor one word but what another ouersees: therefore I pray you consider of me and your children,
                     Men must submit to their fortune.
                   and how euer your vertue fill your heart with constancy; yet remember, that in all ages, and with all persons, vertue doth not thriue alike; nor must a man proclaime all he knowes, or divulge what he thinkes: so that there is no remedy for your enlargement, but a patient enduring, a politike silence, an humble submission, and plausible casting your selfe and cause into the lappe of the Queenes fauor, and vnder the shadow of that great Lords mantle. No more: neither I dare, nor must: but that I am and will be,
               
                  Your euer louing wife in distresse.
               
            
         
         
            Chyding Letters.
            
               
               
                  
                     To his ill aduised Sonne, T.G.
               
               
                  MOst foolish and idle headed,
                  
                     A sonne reprehended for his disordered life.
                   I haue heard thee sometimes discourse of historicall relations, because I should strengthen my opinion, that thou hast not bene a truant at schoole, nor a traitor to nature, in ouerthrowing some good parts alotted as thy portion. But I wonder, that amongst the rest, thou dost not remēber a certain law of the Lacedemonians against disobedient children, who were publikely whipt, and when they continued refractary, they were despightfully hanged, as enemies to the commonwealth: so that if thy profuse expences, riotous courses, disobedient wilfulnesse, irregular conditions, dangerous company, and intemperate abusing the time, were in those dayes to follow thee to that barre of censuring, I should surely take no further care for thy punishment, nor feare for thy hereafter ouerthrow. But because thou liuest in a corrupt age and commonwealth, belike thou thinkest thy selfe disgraced, &amp; out of the fashion, if thou be not corrupt too; nay monstrously wicked, &amp; degenerating. For, what hope can I haue of the preseruation of my estate and family after death, when thou darest presume in my life to carry an absolute sway against my prescriptions, and runne three hundred pounds in debt, to all our troubles; And if thou come to particulars, how bare and poorely will thy excuse seeme? how vgly and deformed will thy vanity appeare? I brought thee with a gentle hand to the study of the law, whereon both profite and honours depends: and thou hast not onely neglected the same; but with a kind of contempt and despight, abandoned thy study, and because we should be sure of thy hate and vilipending such a iewell, thou art bold to boast of pawning thy bookes, and that thou wilt not curbe a braue

spirit, (thou mayst say a diuellish ruffinlinesse) with stupid and dull inclosing thy selfe in a Cabinette, and poaring on harsh and vnpleasant lines. I taught thee a way to handsomnesse and ciuilitie, shewing thee (like a Father) the difference betweene pride and comelinesse: and thou art so farre from the modest vse of Gods creatures, in this kinde, that thou hast transshaped thy selfe with filthy disguises, of long-haire, diffused Apparell, coloured Bands, gaudie Ornaments, ridiculous fashions: yea, thy very heele and spurre-leathers shew the lightnes of thy minde, vanitie of thine affections, and deformities of both: So that from top to toe, the best excuse is the fashion: the best of these fashions so out of frame, that wisedome hateth them, and pietie pittieth them. I instructed thee with the modest oratory of good demeanour, and how weakly they were armed, that stood at defiance, with patience and vertue, building a poore frame on the high exalted Title of valure: as though vice must either be carryed vp with the strong arme of robustiousnes, or coloured ouer with the sophisticate paintings of good-fellowship; courage, not disparaging of Gentrie: and that a man liuing in eminence and expectation of glorie, must not giue way to any discredite. But thou like a resty-iade, hast runne backwards, and affrighted thy owne good spirite, with fearfull blood-sheddings, quarrells, and contentions: exposing thy selfe to barren and beastly destructions, in despight of order, and good gouernment: So that I cannot compare that valour, which thou wouldst haue graced with such an Epithite, better then to the beautie of a strumpet, who is eyther mercenarie to all commers, or so kinde, that shee cannot gainsay any, asking the question: and at last, maketh her self abhorred or vilipended. There be other matters of offence wherewith I could loade you, but these for this time, shall startle you a little, and prepare you to

some better consideration, against I examine you further, or absolutely determine to shew you a stronger hand of reformation: therefore be aduised you were best, and if you dare forget I am your father, and must maintaine you: remembet you are a Christian; and liue vnder a religion and law, which will clip the wings of such licentiousnes, and deplume the feathers of all such consuming birds of prey.
               
                  Your displeased Father.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To her wilfull and seduced friend, M. G.
               
               
                  VNkinde, and ill aduised. To what purpose haue you made me beleeue,
                     Loue findeth fault with inconstancy and follow a strumphet, who is desired.
                   that you neuer spake sentence, but loue ioyned the wordes: neuer breathed vow, but vertue instructed the heart: neuer performed action, but my worth was the magnes to draw you into industry: and yet you can bee contented to wipe away all with the slight hand of carelesnes, and to forsake me without a cause; yea, to despight me the more, to abandon a faithfull and true friend, for the beastly shew and loue of a strumpet, whose eies sparkle with deceit, &amp; very smiles are more dangerous then Crocadiles teares, which commonly weepe ouer such, they meane to destroy. O that thou either hadst discouered this falshood before, whereby I might haue taken the way of better assurance, and conformable honesty; or wilt thou yet defend the poore troopes of chastity, against the mighty armies of incontinency and wantonnes? then should this wanton know, what it were to betray modesty into the handes of filthy vnconstancy, and to bring simplicity into the bondage of passion and affection. But I preethee let me dispute with thee a little: Haue I not seene thee laugh a fellow to scorne, as a buffone, or iester, for wearing great guilt rings full of coulerd glasses, garded cloaths, capons feathers, and a ridiculous aspect? and what

is a strumpet, but sutable in euery thing? Haue I not read of a foole, that was led like an Oxe to the slaughter, and went in the shutting of the euening into the house of a strumpet? Haue I not heard thee tell the tale of a passenger, who comming ouer a dangerous water vpon a narrow bridge, being drunke, and returning the next day to to see what aduenture hee had escaped, died with the apprehension? And what is a whores conuersation, but a sudden perill ouerpassed with feare and trembling? And so in infinite particulars; whereby it cannot choose, but either you are insensible of good, or desperate of all bad; otherwise you would not come within the reach of heauens vengeance, and vertues curses: I meane my owne poore cries, and teares, which if they once should be vented with bitternesse of my soule, beleeue it, they would preuaile with the God of mercy, to draw thee and thy perfidiousnesse into the house of vengeance, for thy cruelty &amp; mischieuous abusing so constant, and innocent a friend.
               
                  Your poore abused Friend.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To his much disordered Friend, F.M.
               
               
                  
                     Against 
                           〈…〉
                        
                     
                  
                  GOod Sir, If I were not tyed by the band of friendship, to all those duties, wherein honest men are, or should be actors; yet am I bound by the lawes of Christianitie to pleade Gods cause, and not to suffer (as farre as in me lies) so great a iustice to be ouerthrowne with the violent thrust of desperate and irreligious shouldrings. To what end then dare you so prophane the name of God? or to what purpose do you breath out the smoke of oathes, yea common periuries? as if the sulphure of that infernall furnace, were raised vp to darken the light of the firmament. Doe you know what danger you incurre? the vengeance prepared, the threatnings denounced, and the punishments

appropriate to such idle and defiling wantonnesse? Do you not reade, that you shall be guilty before Gods seate, for taking his name in vaine? Doth not the Prophet tell you, that plagues shall inuade that house, where the swearer remaineth? Hath not our Sauior instructed vs, with yea, and nay? shewing plainly, that whosoeuer digresseth out of that path, walketh to perdition. And are not the Apostles the voyces of many waters, and the sounds of Gods trumpets against further irreligion, and vndecent oathes? And how dare you then continue in horrible prophanation, and either not beleeue, or not apprehend this truth? Besides, if Sathan had taught vs cunning enough to excuse other vices: The glutton may say, he is a hungred: the vncleane person, he is ready to burne: the couetous man, he is afrayd to want: the murtherer, reuenge is sweete: the drunkard, that his drought is great: the theefe, that he is in distresse, and such like. But the swearer hath neither reason, nor excuse for his idlenesse: no man enforceth him, the flesh inticeth not, the world prouoketh not, onely custom and the diuell raise a commotion against pietie and sinceritie. So that it is almost come to passe, that a swearer and a lier moue in the same orbe of incredultty, and as the shepheards ranne so often in vaine to the boy, that told them the Wolfe was come into the fold, that when he came indeed, they did not beleeue him. So doth euery man abandon a swearer in his most vrgent occasions, because vnurged he made no conscience of an oath. Therefore, if not for Gods loue, Christian duety, sweetnesse of conuersation, and assurance of our contracts &amp; friendship; yet for feare of hell, and in regard of saluation, let mee diuert you from this horrible, and hatefull vice.
               
                  Yours, in reformation.
               
            
            
               
               
                  
                     To her miserable rich Friend, P.D.
               
               
                  
                     Against coueteousnesse.
                  
                  SIR, Although it appertaineth not to our sexe to take the rodde of restraint into our hands, and seeme free Denizons in the kingdome of wisedome, &amp; good counsel, more then men: yet because I am engaged for you to that honourable Lady: &amp; ser open the enclosure of your praises from my owne iudgement, and experience of your worth: I must needes presume (beyond your expectation) and craue pardon, if I seeme to haue a more daring confidence in this reprehension. To what ende then haue you cast durt and filth into the streame of your spirit, where a confluence of many vertues make a flood of perfection, and euen now, when a very mizer should set at large his hardbound heart for expences, haue damned vp the same, with the mudde of auarice: you that haue carryed away good opinion with you in times past for courteous, affable, courtly, well-descended, free, noble, and (aboue the rest) a liberall Gentleman: now to make a stoppe, and darken all that lustre with a miserable sparing, and niggardly conuersation. And when in a time of professing loue, which seemeth to shed teares at your degenerating condition, and to whom? to a Ladie of honour and iudgement: whose very presence may command presents and extraordinary expences; and where? in both your countreys, where reproach stands watching for any occasion, and enuious eyes behold you with repining, and would faine looke iustly awry vpon the least deformity. Be therefore (good Sir) better aduised, and remember, that in religion couetousnesse is resembled to Idolatrie: in Philosophy, to all wickednesse, and ouerthrow of the best resolutions: in moralitie, to the dropsie, an insatiate disease, which the more corruption it hath, the

more it desires? in ciuill conuersation, to a nastie combersomnesse, which terrifieth one another, and breaketh the band of true friendship. Alas, what doe you gaine by vnmeasurable hoording vp of wealth? but a base report, and a ridiculous pointing at, euen as you ride along. Nay, you shall be compared to a barking Dogge at cattle, feeding on hay, which will neither let them take a repast, nor can helpe himselfe to satisfie nature. O, good Sir, though I am no Scholler, yet can I reade what other men doe write: and of all the vices which are enemies to a quiet soule, and free borne Gentleman, couetousnesse is the worst, basest, and most ridiculous. For, besides that, it detaineth vs from the ciuill vse of Gods blessings in the world, so that neither in diet, nor ornament, a man is master of himselfe: it maketh vs vnapt to the entertainment of such vertues, as commonly helpe vs out of the filthy puddles of disreputation, &amp; keepe vs secure from calumniation, and bewitching corruption of profite: therefore, for honours sake, for vertues sake, for friendships sake, for my sake, for your owne sake, for posterities sake, remember where about you goe, and how a good and free demeanour will preuaile, when these hard enclosed hands seeme rather to threathen stroakes, then promise hopefull entertainment.
               
                  Yours, if you can be mine.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To her vnkinde Friend, R.S.
               
               
                  SIR,
                  
                     Against deniall of trifles amōgst friēds and feare of combersomnesse.
                   I perceiue by my selfe, that poore and vnfortunate persons may well be resembled to threatning tempests, from whose violence euery man seeketh a present shelter: else would one neuer haue bene so discourtuous, as to haue denied me a small request, or continued your despight, in

ababandoning my companie, for feare of combersomenesse, or importuning you to more, then your owne free-will should condiscend vnto. Is this the law of friendship? Or what doe you imagine can bee the ende of such vnkindnesse? Who taught you such rules? Or can humanitie thinke well of such peruersnes? Well, I am a woman, and therfore will be so farre from immodesty, that I will impute it to my ill deseruing, not your bad disposition: but if I were a man, howeuer I disclaime quarrels, I would make this a matter of complaint, wherein if your wit did not winde you out, by the scrue of sufficiēt excuse, it should surely turne to displeasure, and cause other maligne circumstances to threaten you further. Therefore from henceforth I will bee so farre from louing you, that I will hate my selfe, for deceiuing my kinde hart in affecting so vnkinde a friend. And thus I bid you fare-well; yea, to fare as well as I did, in the want of that I write for, and the discomfort I endured, to think how ill I had bestowed my first liking.
               
                  Yours, if you will haue it so.
               
            
            
               
                  To his ill respected friend.
               
               
                  
                     Against idle excuses.
                  SVspitious sir, what cause haue I giuen you to deny your selfe? or how could I deserue so ill at your hands, as to driue you frō your own house, whē you were lockt in your study? belike you thoght I came to borrow mony, or beg a dinner, in neither of which, a friend, &amp; such a friend as I presumed you to be, by reasō of your own protestatiōs, ought to be denied: which makes me remember, a tale in the Italian courtier, of a gētl: who cōming to aske for his friēd, was only answered by a seruāt, he was not within: whervpō (for his better intelligence) he departed satisfied in shewe,

till some occasion directed the other to demand for him: whereupon he answered aloud in his owne behalfe, hee was gone from home: Not so sayd the other; for I heare your voyce, and know it too well to be mistaken. But (sayd he againe) you are a strange man, I beleeued your maide when she told me you were not within: And are you so incredulous, that you will not beleeue my selfe? But, as I remember, there hath bene no such passages betweene vs; therefore I wonder at this sodaine dispatch, and cannot be perswaded, but you wish a dissolution of our combined loues. For (my owne part) I will not come to the house of my friend to receiue any affront of deniall; and he that wil take occasion of sequestration, to make such a man of my condition stand without doores, is not worthy to reioyce in true neighbourhood, though there had bene a wanton in your armes, or any Bagge a telling.
               
                  Yours, if you be worthy.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To the worthy Lady, R.C.
               
               
                  GOod Lady, If your honour and vertue resemble not the primum mobile,
                  
                     Against pride and tyrānous behauiour in great persons
                   of the Spheres; to carry about the lesser circles of our duty and obseruation: I see no reason why a generous and free borne Gentleman, should betray the cause of GOODNES into the hands of GREATNES, with degenerating conditions. For, to what end hath a voyce from heauen proclaimed the Godhead of Princes, and higher aduanced persons; but to resemble thē in perfection, and highly exalted vertues? as for shews and outward ceremonies, they bee meere'y tumors of vanity, pride, &amp; ambitious desires, and the best of your liues may be cōpared to a gaudy maske at Christmas, which if it cary more state, &amp; last a litle longer in the kings court, then another place; yet must it haue a melancholy farewel, &amp;

is forgotten, like water spilt out of a Bucket: whereas affabillity, pious inclination, liberall compensation, regard of the afflicted, raising the weake, mercy, compassion, and such like, be indeed faire resplendant starres, worth praise and obseruation; from whose influence can proceed nothing, but auspitious presages; and are sure to make you famous to posterity, euen from the mouthes of widowes and orphanes, when your painted sepulchers shall lye troden to dust, and your proudest edifices be turned to other vses. Be not therefore good Lady, so transported with passion, or open eard to euery flattering insinuating groome, that I shall neuer be heard in my iustifications, though worthy to cliame my owne, nor enioy such priuiledges and immunities, as my auncestors haue filed on record to their owne credit, and posterities immitation. For beleeue it, there is no such corasiue to a gentle minde, as to be deceiued in the expectation of anothers worth, and where he hoped of support and countenance, to be menaced with threatnings, and contracted browes, which if you saw, how ill they became your louelines and beauty, you would quickly admit of a sweeter cheerfulnes, and make me happie with a plausible alteration.
               
                  Yours, as a louer of honor.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To his seruant, F. M.
               
               
                  
                     Foolishnes and dishonesty in a seruant condemned.
                  
                  ALthough I haue plentifull matter of reprehending you affoorded me, yet will I onely at this instant redeeme your foolishnes, and dishonesty: foolishnes, in winding your selfe further into such intricate busines, then either your cunning or strength can help you out of dishonesty: in conuerting the mony appointed to generall imployment to your owne aduantage, whereby the Tenants are disabled, my selfe discredited, and you stand vnder the

burthen of my as iust (and peraduenture) heauy displeasure. Therefore, I charge you take some other course, and that sodainly, to preuent a further account and aggrauatiō thereof; or you shall finde, that as I can be a kinde Master, so I know how to punish a lesse grosse crime, and make you an obedient seruant.
            
            
               
                  
                     To his miserable and most wretched sonne, R.B.
               
               
                  THou cupshot, stain to my name, &amp; torture to my thoughts, All the while I looked on the filthy &amp; menstrous cloth of thy vices,
                     Against drunkenesse.
                   I remēbred the story of the old man of Lions, who enquiting after his sons misdemeanours, with a fond partialitie, began to cloud them with one excuse or another; as that gouernement and discretion would moderate his riot, time would coole his blood, and danger of the law terrifie him from swaggering: marriage and the attractiue condition of a good wife would diuert him from lasciuiousnesse, with such like: till vnderstanding hee was a drunkard, he wrong his hands, &amp; washt them wirh teares, as desperat of his recouery. For in this vice, custome &amp; age are so forcible, that men are so far frō reformation, as they grow from bad to worse, &amp; from worse, to be loathsome to thēselues and al ciuil company. So played I with thee, and dryed vp thy mother cheekes with my kisses, kept her rage from desperate furie with excuses; held her hands from wringing with sweet perswasions; shewed her instances of many licentious yong men redused to gouernment, till we heard of this eruption of beastiality, past all limitation, or hope of amendment: A drunkard! that I haue liued to see this day, and my owne shame and disgraces ripened in thy rottennesse. Let mee tell thee, how the Lacedemonians were woont to do, after they had found a drunkard wallowing in the durt, and (like a Swine)

besmeered in his filthines, to bring forth their children, to beget in them a deadly detestation of the spectacle they beheld. But how? that if any fore-warned, and by such exēplary cautions terrrified, fell into the bogges of such by-wayes, out of the tract of Temperance, and pathway of discretion, they were publikely whipt: but I am afraide thou wilt serue me like the beastly younker of Strasborough, who when his father led him to such a spectacle, where besides the loathsomnes of the party wallowing in his vomit, the ridiculousnes of the action, set the spectators on worke, to the clapping their hands, and extraordinary iollitie: was so farre from misliking of the same, that hee onely demaunded, where the good wine was, which had made the good man in such a taking. And wilt thou serue me so indeed? Are the pleasant voyces of my fatherly instruction discords vnto thee? Is there no remedy, but I must see thee irrecouerably plunged in a quagmire of so loathsome a vice? Oh that I might rather see thy death, then this disorder; and cease to bee a Father, then to haue so vntoward a sonne. My prayer is, Eyther mend, or end: And so I leaue thee.
               
                  Your Father, if you be sober.
               
            
            
               
                  To her vnkinde Husband.
               
               
                  WRetched and miserable man: How darest thou lift vp thy Adulterate eyes to heauen, and behold the pure and christalline Firmament,
                     Against the breach of wedlocke in a man.
                   wherein that euerlasting Law-giuer sits in Triumph, against the day of vengeance, to iudge such perseuerāt delinquēts, as thy self? or dost thou imagine, that those strict duties (commanded from the beginning) were but matters of pollicie? or that position of man &amp; wife, being one flesh, was meerly breath and exhalation? Surely it must needs bee so with Atheists and prophane liuers; And I am afraide to the hereafter horror of

thy soule, that thou wilt tumble into the pit of burning lasciuiousnes: from whence it is easier to be kept frō falling, then once fallen, to recouer out. But O foole, looke againe with brighter eyes, and reade with more iudiciuos vnderstanding: the lips of a whore are as sweete as honie, to the taste of fooles; but in her heart is the sting of scorpions, yea, the poyson of aspes, lies vnder her lips: and wilt thou then aduenture the stinging, when there is no Cataplasme for the soare? Wilt thou forget the honest wife of thy youth, for a disloyall and impudent stranger? Wilt thou despise thy children, resembling oliue branches about thy Table, being buds of the Blessings promised a good man, for Bastards plants, which the hand of Diuine Iustice will soone roote out? wilt thou runne into the sincke of lustfull confusion, that maist trace the faire walks of contentment, with chast embracings? Oh doe not so I charge thee: nay, by the contracts to our first vowes, I coniure thee, returne to the pleasant springs of our amity: and I will wash thee cleane againe, and make thee sweete, with teares and kisses of a louing wife.
               
                  Your true wife, in your vntruth.
               
            
            
               
                  To his periurde and lasciuious wife.
               
               
                  THou for sworne wretch: To what end hast thou prostituted thy selfe to filthinesse,
                     Against whordom in the woman.
                   &amp; abandoned the strong and certaine supportation of grace, for the momentarie ticklings of pleasure: so that by this filthy dashings of lusts lothsome chariots, we are all bemyred, deformed, &amp; made odious to the world: thy selfe art branded for a strumpet, and in the best excuse but a brokē glasse, neuer to be set together againe. I am made a by-word, &amp; a pointing-stocke; not that the disloialty of a whore can ouerthrow the reputation of a vertuous &amp; honest man: but because corrupted times haue taught men a mischieuous lesson, of taunts &amp; contēptuous scornings: thy children appeare not but with

suspitious faces; and I dare not looke vpon them for feare some harsh news should whisper in mine eare their bastardy: our friends and acquaintance dare not meete without murmuring; and me thinks I heare them say, what shall we do in the house of shame, and eate at the table of incontinency? Oh that thou hadst remembered Iudah against Thamar, that she should be burnt for playing the whore; &amp; yet a widow, and before the law: But when the Iewes were reduced to obedience, adultery was punished with death. But me thinks I heare the diuell to prompt thee, that they which dare aduenture their soules, dare hazzard their liues: and now it is not so strict as it was in the time of the law: For Christ himselfe forgaue the woman taken in adultery, and we liue in a commonwealth far from such extremity Is this your sophistry? take heede of cousening your owne soule, and deceiuing the trust which Christ hath reposed in thee, making thee therby partaker of his pretious blood, and thy own redemption. But how? neither to spill the one by casting it abroad with vncleane and polluted hands; nor betray the other by conspiring with presumptuous sinners, to rebel against grace, repentance, &amp; newnes of life; wherin if thou dost not examin thy selfe, &amp; prepare to better conformity, I need not breath out vengeance against thee, or seek a greater iustice, then thy mischeeuous will, &amp; vnpenitent life shall pull vpon thy disguised shamelesse face, and defiled mishapen soule.
               
                  Your husband if you do not diuide him.
               
            
         
         
            Excusing Letters.
            
               
                  
                     To his best Friend, G.L.
               
               
                  GOod Sir, I would not haue you stagger in your opinion of me, considering I haue alwaies with an vpright hand held vp the beame of our friendship:
                     Excuse for not lending money.
                   &amp; would neuer giue my heart leaue to entertaine a thought of politicke

misdoubt, either of your abilitie or honesty. For the very name of a friend shal cōmand my person, much more my goods: but such a man as your selfe hath interest in my life &amp; spirit. Therefore beleeue it, I was so destitute of mony at that time, that casting vp an irkesome account of my brothers departure, necessity enforced the pawning of my vtensels to furnish him; wherein if any experience, or example haue taught my tung the cūning of excuses, let it hereafter grow too big for my mouth, &amp; when my wants knock at the doore for supply, let hands of Adamant admit them no entrance to my insupportable afflictiōs. But wheras you lay a further imputation vpon me, that my credit caried an ouerswaying command of my rich neighbor: true it is, that in former times, as Doues resort to glistring painted houses; as Farmers bring their seed into fat ground; as Beasts &amp; cattle resort to feeding places; &amp; as all the world is transported with priuat respect, I carried vp a head of thriuing wantonnes, &amp; he looked vpon me with a correspondent alacrity, but no sooner came the pulling hooke to throw down the fruit of my fertile trees, wherby he perceiued the boughs bare, and saw the knots and branches battered in peeces: but he suspected my prosperity, and added withall a fearefull prophesie of hereafter canker-eating, &amp; decay both of root and rinde. Thus are my hopes abortiue concernining my interest in him: &amp; to speake the truth, I am so fearefull of a deniall, that I had rather sit still with some ease, then rise and fall with vtter dispaire. Thus if I haue wonne the field against your incredulitie, and brought vp preuailing forces to strengthen your loue, and good will still on my side: I am then my selfe againe, and protest I reioyce more truely in your sweete conuersation, then a wanton could doe, if his mistresse were to hang about his necke with deceiueable kisses, and counterfeit embraces. For they cōmonly resemble the Yuy, running vp

a tower with dangerous loosening the stones, when true friendship is like Atlas and Hercules, supporting of the heauen of prosperitie, and life from falling, yea from failing.
               
                  Your iustifiable Friend.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To his Honourable, L.G.
               
               
                  HOnourable Lord, Whereas I vnderstand, that you excepted against my last importunitie, as if I transcended the bounds of good manners;
                     Excuse for being importunate in the behalfe of a friend.
                   and abased your greatnesse with carrying too slight a respect toward you; I hope I shall finde you so fauourable, both to admit of my iustifiable excuses, and to distinguish betweene presumption and necessitie. Wherefore I pray you, remember the story of Aurelianus the Emperour, who once proclaimed a stately sequestration of his person from common intruders, inhibiting all soldiers and subiects, to aduance themselues in his presence for any suit whatsoeuer: Yet notwithstanding, when a Captain had infringed the edict, and was attached by the guard to receiue a condigne punishment; the Emperour stepped foorth, and sayd, if hee come for himselfe let him die; if he determine for his friend, let him be released. In like manner doe I ouerthrow this obiection at the first charge, &amp; besides your Lordships apprehension, say plainly, that if I had not bene tyed by the laws of friendship, to expose vnto you the desires of another, I wold not haue diuerted you frō more serious affairs, by my tedious discourse, and vnmannerly importunitie. And thus making no doubt of your worthy and noble disposition toward a man, that doth study nothing, but to loue and honour you, I commit my selfe to that part of your vertue, which can make extention of pardon and fauour, as I haue done of submission and dutie.
               
                  Yours, as you will be mine.
               
            
            
               
               
                  To her ouer suspitious Friend.
               
               
                  GOod Sir, I am not ignorant, how the Poets haue inuented a marriage betweene Cupid and Iealousie:
                     Excuse for keeping company, and going to court▪
                     
                   and true loue is many times seasoned, and made sweeter by prettie contradictions, and softly raised suspition: but to be ouervehement in accusation, and absolutely to conclude a negatiue by fond supposes and cruell constructions, are beyond my reason, &amp; your faire demeanour. For, be it, I went to the play with my sister, I endured the maske, I danced the measures: I will not much stand vpon the commendations of such customary practise: Yet was there any thing here worthy the traducing? or could a Gentlewoman doe lesse, considering the circumstances and commanding maiestie of the place? But you will obiect, that fancy now setled, and the minde contented with anothers controwle: it was idlely done to goe at al. I could say so too; if a mothers well-wishes, a sisters importunitie, a solemne festiuall, a time of reuels: and aboue all, a presumption of your noble disposition and free hearted discretion, had not mustred themselues farre stronger then my weake denials: wherewith at first I came so forward, that they wondred at my mortification, and sware it was a counterfeit retiring to more dangerous businesse. Besides, I was not (as I take it) vnder any penalty of infringing your will, you not imposing such a taske on me: nor would I be so absolute a slaue, though the name of husband and wife had linked vs together with the Churches ceremonies. Be therefore I pray you satisfied with my iustifiable excuses, and beleeue it; I will rather forsweare the hopes of mariage, and the glory of costly ornaments, before I will leaue you againe in such an hell of affrighting iealousie.
               
                  Yours, so you be resolued.
               
            
            
               
               
                  To her iealous Friend.
               
               
                  SVspitious Syr: I perceiue that ignorance is many times a mistrisse of quietnes,
                     Excuse for taking shelter in a shower of raine, with a strange gentleman.
                   and too much learning laieth the heart open to leaud example, and idle instances. Thus because you haue read of the Hunting which Dido prepared for Aeneas, and that opportunitie, and a strange accident brought them to an Amorous encounter, in that solitary caue (whither they retired) to auoid the peril of the storme: therefore must I be suspected, for that at the last Hunting I met with S. G. in the thicket, and not able then to indure the shower, mounted vp into the stand: If there were no other excuse then necessitie, and the accidentall proffer of ciuill curtesie, me thinkes it might carry credite with vnderstanding: but least I cannot handsomely gather together my forces to satisfie you, I will tell you true: There came both my brother, and his man, to preuent any ouerflowings of a wanton tongue, or idle conference: so that wee were so farre from any occasion of Loues encountering, that we were glad to shake our hattes, and wring our cloathes, for feare of catching colde: yet say, that the accident had preuented other company: hath the opinion of his worth, so ill a ground in your thoughtes, that you can so quickly cast it out from any sound rooting? Or am I such a truand in the schoole of modesty, that you stand in doubt of my loytering, or at least of my insufficiencie, to proue an honest proficient? But I will answer for you, it is loues fault and not yours: and there can be no good will, where many questions arise not to contrarieties: yea, somtimes to distastings, &amp; fallings out: which if it be so, I am contented to offer my Taper, at the altar of his deitie, and hope to finde you the faster hereafter, by letting mee lose a little, and giuing some small liberty to the feares of my losse, and prouing counterfeit.
               
                  Yours in her very thoughts.
               
            
            
               
               
                  
                     To his worthy Friend, Sir I. D.
               
               
                  SIR,
                  
                     Excuse for not dispatching a suite of importāce, according to expectation &amp; promise.
                   it pleased mee much, that you supposed mee ouer shadowed with the high exalted fauor of such a Queen, who as shee is the mirrour of all ages, for her magnificent gouernmēt: so is she the presidēt of all actions for her vertues &amp; maiesticall properties. But withall, you must cōsider the condition of her greatnesse, and the custome of Princes, who doe not allow of too much easinesse in accesse, or facility in subscribing to petitions, for feare of diminishing the glory of their pallaces, and making vs carelesse in our seruice and obseruation. Therefore I pray you bee resolued, that I neglect no opportunitie to inferre your former merit, and present aptnesse to the place, nor found her any way obdurate, more then in her plaine resolution you might tarry a while: As for that imputation, that I was tempted with a thousand angels to speake for D.C. and so bare you in hand to feele Esaus roughnesse, when yet Iacobs voyce was deceitfull: do not beleeue it. And let one protestation serue for all, that no man but your selfe shall alter my iourney to her Maiestie: nor any businesse but this set the loome of my industry a worke, till the web of your preuailing be dispatched: or at least, what I can warpe out, made vp accordingly: as for the report, or, if you will, suggestion of your murmuring, that you attended ouer-long, and yet went away not speaking with me: I can assure you, the fault depended not on my greatnesse, or willingnesse to distast any man, much lesse your selfe, who are as welcome to me as any man: and (if I might speake it without flatterie) in a farther degree of acceptation with me then any man: but meerely the misprision of your person from the groome, that turned the key: who mistaking you for another, which had reuiled him, put this poore tricke of

reuenge vpon you to make you beleeue, I was busie, when I neither knew of your being without, nor would haue had any businesse, to haue ouerborne my respect toward you if I had knowne it. If this may draw toward a satisfaction, &amp; keep you frō contracting a brow of displeasure against me, I am proud we shall agree, and glad there was occasion of this prety contradiction.
               
                  Yours in despight of suspition.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To his louing wife, B.G.
               
               
                  MY onely beloued, I am now to deale with a woman, that can spread the mantle both of loue and discretion.
                     Excuse for tarrying too long from a wife.
                   Of loue, not to giue way to any sinister and indirect conceit for my tarrying so long from you. Of discretion to apdrehend the difficult passages, wherein Court-suters trauerse their grounds, and are sometimes like a ship vnder saile, ready to enter the hauen of their desires, driuen farre backe by contrary gusts, into the troublesome and turbulent Ocean of crosses &amp; vnexpected changes. Thus as you haue often told me your selfe, are men sometime protracted, examined, promised, denied, and many times afronted with competitors, whose particeans would gladly preferre their friends before a strangers. But for the giuing raines to any extrauagant and licentious corruption, either for incontinency, gaming, or pleasure, more then what the better sort of men may draw me along vnto by the cords of conuersation, doe not beleeue it, though it should bee reported; nor report it, though some vntoward suspition may hasten you to beleefe in this kinde. And thus relying on your wisedome, more then my owne fortunes or good merit, I commend these ciuill excuses to your fauourable construction, and commit that little, which the poore remainder of my discretion hath compassed to your care and gouernment.
               
                  Your husband resolued.
               
            
            
               
               
                  
                     To his loued louing wife, C.G.
               
               
                  MY dearest and best beloued,
                  
                     Excuse for not dispatching of busines
                   Although your vnsauorie letters are framed on the foundation of vnkindnesse, so that you seeme to iustifie the aduancing the pile of your grudges and repinings vpon good occasions inforced: yet I hope by that time I haue filled your eares, and impressed your heart with honest excuses, you will quietly gather together the disperced forces of your care and dutie to affright misreport and sinister vnderstanding. First thē concerning the money to be paide to your cousen; I was so far from receiuing it then, that there is no hope euer to haue it hereafter. Concerning the not accompanying your brothers in his suites, and attending with him in the court, you know how vnsauory such a seruitude is vnto the freedome of my spirit; and how vntoward he is in his spleenefull wilfulnesse, otherwise I wil ride, run, or go, yea lacky by him to doe him good: but to make my selfe seruile vpon euery occasion, and waite on those daies, wherein no busines is determined, cannot stand with policie or discretion. Concerning the not hauing the things from the Mercer, whereby you thinke your selfe more then forgotten, yea forsaken and vilipended; I answer truely, there is but one you know, to the warmth of whose bosome I can repaire, and he being out of towne, I cannot presume on any other: so that forbearance being no quittance, you must bee contented to attend a more thriuing howre. Concerning the sending your sonne ouer, there is no hope of him in any befitting courses of a man. For all

that he practiseth is meerely repugnant to vertue, and my willingnesse to see him doe well; As for sauoring martiall affaires, some vnciuill and erronious report hath affrighted him with painfull marches and watchings, hard lying, vnpleasant fare, carelesse regard, (what hunger ot sicknesse euer chance:) and aboue all, slight entertainment, with sudden steppings before him, through the fauour of Letters, or Officers, of men inferior to his supposes, and presumption of his owne worth. Therefore I can doe no more, then speake to the Capt: and engage my selfe for his attendance, draw out extraordinary promises of respecting him, &amp; encourage him what I may: but hee being a backe retirer, and pleading insufficiencie of body, I haue left it, without further vexation: howeuer I could for your sake enforce my vnwillingnes; and considering his vnsupportable humors, to set him on foote, to preuailing according to his owne desires.
               
                  Your carefull Husband.
               
            
            
               
                  To his best, and Noble Lady.
               
               
                  
                     Excuse for not writing &amp; attending, unwilling persons to bee spoken with.
                  
                  MY best Lady, whereas you wonder at my slacknesse in writing: &amp; attendance of your Father, without complement or ceremonie; I answer both thus: The best letters resemble but the passage of a Shippe, who leaueth behinde no impression of her course; and if they sauour of cumbersomnes, they seem as poyson represented in a golden cup: so that howeuer we entertaine the thing containing, we quickly reiect what may be noysome to the taste, and dangerous to the stomacke: As for my personall performing my dutie; Shall I now walke in a Hall, that was wont to come vp stayres, without controwle? Shall I now be afraide to speake to a groome, who will smile in my

face, and bring counterfeit excuses to my sight? Shall I betray my vertue to basenesse, when he is willing to make his greatnes to looke bigge vpon mee? Shall I come to a man ennobled with report, who yet disableth his worth, by a womans malice? Oh, I may not doe so! For though hee can strike away the secrets of friendship with a commanding hand, I may not forget the properties of a man, the libertie of my life, the royaltie of my profession: So that till I can recouer my pristine glorie, and iollity of familiaritie, I will submit to these disasters, and make this vnworthy banishment, the author of Contemplation, and triall of affliction: In which, if my prayers ascend like a smoake of a sweete-smelling Sacrifice, I will thanke the God of comfort, for his Fatherly correction; and remember in the same, that you may flourish in the worlde, like a faire fruitfull Tree, and prosper in your desires: as if Iacobs seede did sowe in the Land of Abimelech: where hee receiued an hundred for one. As for your Mother, I wish her the blessings of Rahel and Lea: to be honored of her Husband, reuerenced by her Children, esteemed of her Neighbours, famosed by strangers, respected of Friends, and aboue all, loued of GOD; who will neuer leaue to loue such as vnderstand, what true loue importeth.
               
                  Yours, though I thriue not.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To his Honourable Friend, Syr G.L.
               
               
                  WOrthy Syr,
                  
                     Excuse for not forbearing a friend, presuming to disgrace another.
                   I am loath to vse a further preamble with you, then may stād in equall poyse with your iudgement, and my dutie: yet because I would not seeme too peremptory, in iustifying my selfe, I will confesse, that vertue looketh with a more confident aspect, in the maintaining a well gotten possession, then in the first Fortune of kinde embraces: so that I infer according to your own

proposition, that there is more cunning in keeping, then getting a Friend. But withall, if a Friend will so presume on the weaknesse of another, to tye him ouer-strictly to obseruation, or burden him with intollerable impositions, because there hath passed vpon him some descendings of gratuities: I see no reason to curbe his manhood, or libertie in such a fashion: especially, if the standers by be ignorant of their combination, or iealous that hee is subiect to some maligne circumstances of Fortune or Time: and thus much in generall. Now to the particulars: As you wonder at my repugnancie, and absolute contradicting your arguments in the last conference: I maruell that you would so apparantly maintaine such a Paradox: and amongst all the rest, draw mee into the circle of wrastling with our wittes, whereby either I must cowardly leaue poore truth in the hands of venomous, and corrupted Sophystrie: or fearfully bring my preuailing forces forward, to foyle your vnderstanding &amp; iudgement; whereby, in the contention, friends must needs fall out: wheras you wonder that I would hazard your loue, by so sudden a deniall, of such an easie commaund, wherein better and greater Friends neuer disputed.
               I maruell why you should at that time, aboue all others, and before such persons, burst out to shewe your greatnes and power ouer mee, or discouer my weaknesse, onely to be insulted on, when you had attendants of your owne for seruile businesse; or might haue made some groome an actor in the same, to preuent all exceptions? Otherwise I sweare for honourable purposes, when the whole bodie shuld be exposed to your seruice, I would not haue denyed the Legges from going of an errand into the Kitchin for you. Whereas you wonder that I departed discontented, without ceremony, or making you once acquainted, when

all the companie wished mee well, and expected a conclusion of the discourse. I maruell both at your putting mee to it, before such curious eares, and solid iudgements, and at the strange entertainmēt of a man, whom you know could not looke vpon mee, but with Basiliskes eyes: nor I endure him, without dislike and discontent. Therefore to preuent, vntoward disturbance, and to scatter my iealousie abroad, least it should gather a head of assurance, that you did it of purpose; I left you to murmure at my vnmannerlines, but pleased my selfe in a supposed preuention of further mischiefe. Thus, if these sad lines haue better fortune then their maister, it may be you wil admit of them as excusatory, and of mee in them, as willing to please you in noble and iustifiable actions.
               
                  Your seruant and assured.
               
            
            
               
                  To his suddenly displeased Friend.
               
               
                  GOod Syr;
                     Excuse for not beeing Surety for a Friend.
                   you saw at the beginning, that the diuell was so enuious of mans felicity, that hee neuer desisted, till the bands of his first contract were dissolued, &amp; the hope of saluation abandoned: and so hath hee continued euer since, as an aduersary to all goodnes, and vertuous dispositions; whereof (euen at this instant) I am a poore witnes, and in this foyle, which our friendship is likely to receiue an vnhappy instance: else could not you haue demanded the onely thing I haue forsworne: nay, am legally bound to take heede of: nor I haue denied you any thing which might seem dissonāt to our contract: so that I request you, with tears (if a man can shed them without ridiculousnes) make triall of mee, if it stood with the secrets of our loue, in any thing (Surety-ship excepted,) commaund my person, rifle my goods, pawne my Leases, open my purse, and take whatsoeuer I call mine: but to drawe mee

and my posteritie into the terrour of bondage: Nay, to fasten, and (as it were) to sigillate, and affixe vs to the vnmercifulnesse of men, and crueltie of Cut-throats, is so terrible to a poore estate, that I start at the naming of a Statute, and am afraide of mine owne shadowe, least my hand should bee counterfeit. For, I haue knowne the debt discharged, and for want of honesty in some, &amp; cunning in others, to cancell the Recognysance, a new enformation hath made a hurliburly in the family: and the Law hath claimed for the Prince, against all prescription of time, &amp; releases of men: because the record was a liuing voyce: and ecchoed out, you must discharge the debt againe: Therfore I request you, let not this denyall make any breach against the fortification of our loue: nor let the banks of out friendship bee so slightly cast vp, that so small an Inundation shall eyther ouerflowe the same, or burst downe with violence, that which we once presumed was strong enough against most impetuous shouldrings, eyther of Riuers, or Seas.
               
                  Yours, when you commaund.
               
            
            
               
                  To his well resolued Friend.
               
               
                  
                     Excuse for not entertaining a friend, as hee ought to bee.
                  
                  GOod Syr; let it not seeme strange vnto you, that I neither durst bidde you welcome: nor open my mouth with so pleasing a voyce as the harmonie of our hearts was wont to tune together. For you know I am subiect to an others controwll, and this name of a seruant, hath in me ouermastred the condition of a Friend: so that I can but curse the occasion, when first my Lord let in an ill opinion of your worth, into the closet of his former affection, and blame that ominous night of feasting, which ended so mischieuousty, ro distast you both: but I hope time will eyther weaken these inflictings, or your faire demeanor work

vpon a better Anuile of constancy, and regard of vertuous noblenes in you both; so that I shall performe the part of a Friend, in working your reconciliation: and you the part of a wise man, in giuing way vnto some humors, that otherwise might confound all our quietnes. Be therefore (I pray you) your selfe, and pardon me a while: if my dutie to him restrain me a little, from running too violently in the race of our friendship: otherwise bee assured, that no other restraint could keepe mee from flying into your armes, and prostrating my selfe to your second commaund in any thing.
               
                  Yours when mine owne.
               
            
            
               
                  To his well deseruing Friend.
               
               
                  MOst deare Friend: If I could preuent my disgraces, as well as I can excuse my bad disposition, you should neither complaine,
                     Excuse for not soothing vp of humors.
                   nor I bee terrified with feare of my vtter ruine: therefore I pray you bee satisfied with this assured confidence of my loue, that I neither opposed to your brothers peremptorinesse, out of any pride of my owne, or willingnes to ouer-thwart him: nor crossed your mother in her peeuish insultings ouer my decayed estate, from any preiudicated malice, or desire of contradiction: but meerely to countenance the cause of vertue, and establish the right of truth: Therefore I pray you consider of mee, and as you were wont, maintaine that olde goodnes which hath made you famous to all well-willers, and mee happie in your worthines and kindnesse. For to come to particulars, who could haue sworne, that vertue was seeldom or neuer innated in a poore person, or of mean condition: if he had said, it was little esteemed, as the wise man maintaineth, that wisdome in a poore man, maketh a slender oratory, it had carried some reasonable colour of argument: but to discharge it quite from the seruice of inferior

persons, is meerly swellings of pride, contempt, and filthy desires. Again, wheras your mother resolued that no estimation could arise to any man, but frō an aggeration of wealth, and raising his Fortunes from land and greatestates, I had reason to sweare they were both base &amp; corrupt positions, from ignoble and degenerating burstings out of frailty: So that howeuer the duties of a childe may restrain you frō publike condemning your mothers wilfull esteeming of the world, before religion, or a brothers pittiful opinion of true vertue indeed: I hope you know better how to raise vp the frame of goodnes, &amp; whē it is raised, to keepe the possession against all disseasures, or intrusions of sinne and wickednes.
               
                  Yours assured.
               
            
         
         
            Requesting Letters
            
               
                  
                     To his honourable Lord: The L. C.
               
               
                  
                     A request to requite a discurtesie.
                  
                  RIght Honourable, In those poeticall fictions, such were the prerogatiues of deitie, that whatsoeuer one god confirmed, no other would disallow: nor by any contradictory courses, weaken the reuerēce due to their sufficiencie. So that if Teresias were striken blinde, there was no restoring of his eyes, howeuer hee might be helped with the gift of diuination. If Iupiter giue again the sight to Ianuary, (as in Chaucers Tale) to discouer his wiues incontinēcie, Iuno could quicken her spirits to such a wittie answer, as might pacifie all indignation: and so in diuers other particulars, from whence I recollect thus much in this ciuill administration of Common-wealths: that when the Law hath had a passage from authoritie, there is no stopping it by a subiects hand, howeuer the prerogatiue of a Prince may coū
                  termand the same, in another kinde: Therefore my Honourable Lord, I dare not attempt so farre, that you shuld ouerthrow the verdict against me, or by sinister course of greatnes, wrest aside the penaltie inflicted, but humblie request

you to raise as great a punishment on my aduersarie, by reason of his wilfull abusing your Honour: and mee your poore seruant, and tenant, as may answer in proportion my forfeiture, and oppose against his malicious inclination to ouerthrow my poore estate. And whereas these trialls in Lawe are meere distractions both of our peace and purses: you will giue him this notice, that except hee condiscend to faire conditions of agreement, you will open a larger flood of dipleasure against him, considering the circumstances. For truely my good Lord, hee beganne with mee, as that wicked man in the Gospell, who, when infinit summes were remitted him, notwithstanding ranne and tooke his fellow by the throate, and most cruelly demaunded 500. pence: These things I leaue to your particular consideration, and am resolute to relie more on your wisedome, in the managing the same, then my Fortunes, in ouercomming the affliction.
               
                  Your Honors in respectiue duty.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To his honorable Friend, Syr D. L.
               
               
                  NOble Syr: Howeuer there hath lurked some dangerous poyson of incombrance,
                     A friendly request for money.
                   vnder the tufted green-grasse of ciuill complement, and other protestations: yet I was neuer an absoute and apparant beggar till now, nor had thought to haue stepped so rudely, as to presse your curtesie. Therefore I request you, lay the blame on necessitie, and pardon this eruption of ill manners: but withall, so farre to consider my businesse, that these lines remaine vncancelled, &amp; my suite be not tripped down, in the first setting forward. For (good Syr) if you vouchsafe not to send me x.ll, as wel to defray the charges of the suit, as to helpe toward the paimēt of the other debt, I shall not only lose the benefit of our first proceedings, but endanger my poore estate, which beeing a morgage, hath a time of forfeiture annexed, and day of terrour couenanted in the Articles.

So that I cannot compare my selfe better then to a man holding the Wolfe by the eare, which if he pull hard, hee is bitten: if hee let go, he is in danger of further mischiefe. Therefore I request you, hold vp so far an aduancing hand of supportation, that I may wade through the current of these troubles, and land on the banke of securitie and contentment: which, for that it is not to bee effected without your assistance, I am the bolder to make you beleeue (as it is indeed) it is a worke both glorious and charitable.
               
                  Your expectable friend.
               
            
            
               
                  To her much esteemed good Lady.
               
               
                  
                     A request for the entertaining of a daughter.
                  
                  GOod Ladie, I desire not willingly to deale with you, as iealous husbands with their wiues, who commonly looke for that they would not find: So that if I should suspitiously make triall of your many worthy promises, and finde them Court vapours, or formall protestations, it would prooue an vnsauory search, and dull my desires in their forwardnesse toward you. Therefore I will proceed more confidently, and frame my request on the iustifiablenesse of the motion, and the worthinesse of your merite. I beseech you therefore good Lady, take this poore gentlewoman by the hand, my onely daughter, and settle her in the schoole of obseruation, that shee may looke toward you, as the eyes of Dauids handmaid; and toward her selfe as that good seruant, that doubled his talents; to which purpose I haue instructed her with a mothers loue, and a womans experience; wherein I hope she will proceed rather for the loue of vertue, then feare of displeasure. But good Lady, withall, I humbly request you, that she may be orderly led to the sight of her errors, and know with what face displeasure can looke when she doth amisse, especially in the desire of liberty, or acquaintance with wantonnes,

two such dangerous gulphs, that I haue seen very tall and well built ships swallowed in their whirlings: and therefore I haue reason to feare so slender a barke, and ill prouided, as she is. Besides, there are some things, wherein ignorance hath a priuiledge: For man was neuer vnhappie, but in the knowledge of good and euill: not that there is any harme in vnderstanding to doe well, and auoyd the mischiefe of practising ill: But because we are rather prone to vice then goodnesse, and (quickly seduced) runne violently into the breake-necke race of precipitant iniquitie. My last request is, that you will pardon my presumption, and impute it rather to the confidence of your worth then my owne bad disposition: and so emboldned accordingly, I leaue her and my selfe to those vertues, that can beare imperfections, &amp; regard our dutifull seruice toward you.
               
                  Your Ladiships in all impositions.
               
            
            
               
                  To his Honourable Lord.
               
               
                  HOnourable Lord, Among all the blessings afforded man in this world, none may equall mutuall societie, nor come neare the beautifull motions of worthy neighbourhood,
                     A request for assurance of a farme.
                   and friendship: and of this I am an instance, and may well resemble diuers trees and plants which prosper the better, when the cunning gardner hath rooted by them, such kinde of fruits and hearbes, as in nature they desire, and in growing aduance their heads in iollity. For as Phylosophers affirme, all things are distinguished and gouerned by Sympathy and Antipathy. This made me affect the place, wherein (as a poore tenant, Gentleman, and neighbour) I would willingly doe you such seruice, as befitteth my condition and quality to yeeld vnto: and your honour and grauity to command. I humbly therefore request you,

that I may haue some certaine assurance of the farme in possession, as you haue frō me of my best loue, &amp; then (no doubt) I shall with chearefulnesse and sufficiency make my approches in such manner, that you shall neither be afraid of combersomnesse, nor I ashamed of any desparagement. But withall, I (againe and againe) desire, that you subiect me not to inferior groomes, and tie me to so strict a behauiour, as that the falling of a tree, the plashing of a hedge, the killing of a Partridge, &amp; such like accidental occasions, draw my actions within your seruants censuring, or indirect information of busie bodies. And thus with a submissiue resolution to loue and honour you, I commit you to his hands that can adde to your merits, honor vpō honor, and make me happy in the fulnesse of your opinion, and your noble respect, according to that I shall indeauour to deserue.
               
                  Your Honours humbled.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To his louing Friend, Mr. G. M.
               
               
                  
                     A request to forbeare a debt.
                  
                  SIR, I dare not ouer-guild with quaint tearmes, and rhetoricall Phrases (though I had such a prerogatiue by nature) my sute vnto you at this instant, lest you grow suspitious of some bad inclination, and secret cunning in crying with the Lapwing furthest from her nest; that is, making a shew of one thing, and determining another. Therefore I will plainely desire you to forbeare the debt another yeare, that I may with a more cheereful looke consider the spots and staines of my durty face, and so at leisure make it cleane, or with a stronger arme cast it lightly from my shoulders, when I shall haue time to rest my self; and prepare to stand firmely vnder the loade: otherwise, I may fall in making too much haste, and besmeere me the more in attempting with a foule &amp; filthy clout, rashly

to purifie me. Herein likewise you shall shew your selfe free from hard and griping exaction, wherein diuers vsurers are compared to Harpies, who neuer seize on any thing, which they let goe without carrying something away; nor ouermaster at all, where they doe not vtterly destroy. Besides, I shall proclaime you a charitable Gentleman, and enlarge my wishes for your prosperity, as you tie me to loue and respect you for so vndeseruing a curtesie.
               
                  Yours, if you be not offended.
               
            
            
               
                  To her vnkind Friend.
               
               
                  GOod Sir,
                  
                     A request to forbeare a dangerous Ladies cōpany
                   Howeuer these dangerous practises of yours may be at the best veiled ouer with excuse of trials, &amp; as it were touchstones of my constancy: yet I pray you deale not with me, as som strange Physitions do with their patients, who, because they find the body strong and well composed to some endurances, will therfore adde violent potions, and raging poisons to their receipts: and so peraduenture to see you visited of friends, accustomed to ciuill conuersation, courting of Ladies, and affording pleasant changes, as time and place requireth: I can passe ouer as things of course, and make my heart beleeue, there is no perill in such aduenture, nor hazzard of true loue in circumstances: but to heare, that you daily conuerse with that fantasticall Lady, whose eyes are nets to intrap wiser men, and whose hands haue with the Spiders web wouen twisted threds to tie the rouing fancy to straiter admirations: concerning her beauty: of stronger &amp; more wary men thē your selfe: I cannot endure, nor will afford my opinion of you, so strong a presumption, that you can come away vnsnared or vncorrupted with allurement. Therefore I humbly request you, if not for loue, yet for pitties sake, leaue me not in this suspition, nor throw me so violently

into the turbulent sea of iealousie. For I am a poore slender barke, and built for shallow waters: no man of Warre, nor high decked ship to endure all winde and weather. I am a slender reede placed in lower grounds to auoyd the boysterous puffes that assaile the highest mountaines: no Cedar of Lebanon, to aduance my head against all menacing stormes and tempests: I am a true hearted louer, who can be contented with onely one honest man, and haue taught my soule a lesson of beleefe, that you are master of your selfe, and a conqueror of affection; nay a follower of truth, and good remembrance concerning our contracts and mariage. To what end then doe you affright me with these indirect straglings abroad, and set my patience on the tainter-hooks of cruell expecting your returne, and how you will reason the matter to pacifie this displeasure? Well, I pray you bee a little more reposed, and take some sodaine course to come and satisfie me better: otherwise I will not beleeue, but you wish an alteration, and I must prepare for some pittifull, either change or distresse.
               
                  Yours and yet displeased.
               
            
            
               
                  To his Honourable good Lord, and Patron.
               
               
                  
                     A request to be charitable.
                  
                  RIght Honourable, I am very vnwilling to make a perilous mixture of diuine precepts, and ciuill introducements; for feare I shuld not with sufficient reuerence settle my selfe, and prepare you to heare the same: otherwise, I could with Saint Paul to Agrippa, demand, whether you belieue the Scriptures: and answer for you, that I know you doe beleeue them: and out of them can collect thus much; that by mercy we approch to God, and from compassion are led to the barre of acceptation with the diuine Maiestie. This made Saint Paul write to Philemon, to pardon the misled seruant, and soundeth out the tune of charity, as

the sweetest note in all the Scriptures: and this hath incited me to request your Honor to come as freely forward to the remission of my friend, as you can; and once againe admit him vnder the couert of your fauour, and good opinion: For I know his hart is not onely impressed, with an acknowledgement of his fault, but (as it were) cast in a new mould to amend his life, and entertaine a true conuersion into the new built house of his conscience. Therfore, good my Lord, I beseech you againe for him, that he be not oppressed with despaire, and so cast downe on the bed of affliction irrecouerably: and againe and againe, for my selfe, that I bring him not worser tidings of your displeasure toward me, for vrging you beyond either my duty, or your owne will and worth. But I am perswaded, that so great a blood and generous mind will not looke with a tyrannous brow vpon such submission: nor greatnesse proue implacable, where humilitie is suppliant. In which confidence, I leaue your honour to a noble consideration of vs both, and worthy acknowledgement of many apparant benefits.
               
                  Your honors in all duetie.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To the Honourable Colonel, Sir F.P.
               
               
                  WOrthy Sir, Although martiall men naturally affect not either complement or rhetoricall ampliation, as knowing that wisedome it selfe is sometimes vnseasonable:
                     A request to admit a scholer for a soldier.
                   yet hauing good experience of your owne sufficiency many waies: and remembring a noble speech concerning the commendation of (M.R.) whose onely oratory, and eloquent perswasion, kept the troops whose together, and reunited the dispersed forces flying away, whereby those vnexpected fallies of our strong enemie were defeated, and a new life infused into our souldiers fainting courages; I am now the bolder to present this worthy Gentleman

&amp; scholler vnto you, in whom a great spirite, and true desire of honor hath preuailed against industry, &amp; peaceable addiction to ciuill imployment: so that if he proue as good a proficient in this martiall schoole, as he hath done in the exercises of seuerall Artes, I make no doubt, that as a double Band bindes stronger then a single, so shall hee giue that harshnes of a soldier, a further lustre: &amp; besides, a generall good to his countrey, by such endeuors, gaine a particular grace from your self, for well applying such gifts as nature hath admitted him to receyue out of her chiefest store house. Thus much emboldened from the secrets of our former friendship, and the merit of this my kinseman; whome I am so well perswaded of. I commit you to his hands that hath helped your hands to reach at honor: and and commend our selues to your good consideration, of so reasonable a request.
               
                  Yours, sworne to worthines.
               
            
            
               
                  To his right Honourable Lord.
               
               
                  
                     For the knighting a friendly &amp; worthy Gent:
                  
                  RIght Honorable Lord, I would be loath to open any enclosure of ridiculous follie, or dangerous ambition, in the prosecution of of my suit, and iustifiable request, for the Knighting of M.G.S. considering many captious tongues, and enuious eyes, are busied on the Theater of the world, to prye into the demeanors of men, and burst out with calumniation, against the least imperfection: so that if a man stand not vpright indeed, vpon the sure frame of prosperitie, and good opinion: a poore vertue shall be easily shouldred aside, and quiet spirit made the Tenis-ball of boysterous contempt, which commonly laugheth men to scorne with vilipending, not for any insufficiencie in the other:

but because idlenesse and presumptuous conceits runne at random without controwle in themselues. Thus might I be terrified, because I haue heard some make a Tush at the motion, and knowe others ouer-daring to traduce him in priuate, and yet touched to the triall, disclaiming the least conceit of mislike.
               But if it please your Honour to bee your selfe, and recollect your owne memory, I hope you will answere for vs both: For my selfe, that being my friend, and such a friend into whose bosome (when I shiuered for colde,) I haue shrowded my selfe for warmthe: I could doe little, if I would not preferre so easie a petition, to so noble a Lord, and such, as had brought mee long since, out of the narrow entrie of suspition, to a manifest confidence of loue, and tyed his honour to the performance of a greater matter for my sake. Concerning him, he is in blood, so generous, that his grandfather was the thirteenth Knight of his Familie: in reuenues so inriched, that hee may improue his liuing, when he will, to an 1200. poūds a yeare, in stock so plentifull, that a 1000. pounds cannot counter-poise the same: in iudgement so reposed, that howeuer his great enemie hath kept him from beeing Commissioner: yet hath hee ended diuers contentions amongst his Neighbours, and regained the best opinion: in demeanour so delicate, that his house seemeth a well ordered and furnished Pallace, and his Stable, a store-house of excellent and well appointed horses: in conuersation, so pleasing, that the best Ladies haue taken paines to revisite him, and went away with admiration rather then satisfaction: and in eloquence so facet, that though he haue not bin a traueller, or souldiour: yet can he dispute of both, and ouer-beare a good resolution, to confirme it in either.
               All which being considered, I make no doubt but I

haue reason to inferre the same: he is worthy to be remembred with the immunities of his ancestors: and your Honour so respectiue, that neither flattery nor detractiō shall pull vs within the danger of your displeasure: And for the maine point, which is disbursement of money, hee hath sworne the contrary, and is not determined to spend your friendship so mercinarily; because hee can so dispatch it by meaner men, meaner trouble, and a meaner account, or giuing reckoning of his fortunes.
               
                  Your Honors, as you can deuise.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To her highly respected Friend, Sir T.B.
               
               
                  
                     For to defend a widow gentlewoman in her right against all wrong &amp; calumniation.
                  
                  HOnourable Sir, I haue read, or at least, giuen eare vnto other folkes reading, that in ancient times, when honor and armes were mounted on a throne of estimation, there was a military oth prescribed to souldiers &amp; knights with diuers limitations: amongst which, repulsing of iniuries, and defending of Ladies were principall; &amp; truely if a woman might bee admitted vnto a court of warre, mo thinketh it was necessarie and honourable. For what is vertue, but a naturall inclination to charitable actions, and noble resolutions? and how dare a Gentleman take vpon him the title of Chiualry, that will defile his heart with malicious and dangerous reuenges, open his mouth to vndecent speeches and filthy opprobry, stretch his hands to entertaine fury and reuenge; yea frame the whole course of his life, either to a bestiall liberty, or barbarous doing of iniury? Therefore Noble Sir, remember your selfe, and from whence you are extracted, neere in alliance to me, and one, on whom I haue leaned for supportation, and relyed in all these eruptions of misfortune. Remember mee a poore Gentlewoman, a widdow in distresse, and groaning vnder the heauy and cruell hand of

a great and mercilesse aduersary. Remember the cause, that it is vertues, the defence of chastity, and keeping vs al from penury and wants; and remember my aduersary, that he is meerely malicious; and because he could not obtaine, what he vnlawfully desired, hee now soundeth out no note but reuenge: and sweareth he wil make me repent, that I either denied, or contested with him. Therefore deare Sir, let me flie to you for refuge, and as farre as true manhood may auoyd the imputation of quarrels, and dangerous bloodshedding, cling to your side vnder the shield of your noble protection: wherin I will desire you to proceed no further, then by petition to my H. G. and orderly attendance on the high Commissioners: And this I take both waies to be iustifiable, and assure my selfe, this you would doe for a stranger, that had not estranged her selfe from good demeanour, and faire courses of a vertuous inclination.
               
                  Yours, and sworne to be so.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To his Honour able good Friend; L.
               
               
                  HOnourable Sir, I would not now resemble the fish Caepia, which cast into any water troubles the same;
                     A friend entreateth for an office, for another.
                   nor be compared in my importunity to your Court tapers, which burne out themselues to pleasure others: so that in pleading thus in my friends behalfe, I may peraduenture doe him no good, and yet spend the splendor of your worthy loue to as little purpose concerning my selfe. But presuming still to finde you more and more generous, as you more and more approch vnto honour and dignitie, I am the bolder to expose vnto you the honest request of Master H. and make it the marke of my aime, wherein if I cā come but so neare as your kind acceptation vpon those

conditions, which in a manner you gaue life vnto: I shall then thinke my selfe much bound vnto you, because of many blessings cast into my lap at once by that meanes: as the confirmation of your loue and regard, the gratuitie of two hundred pound besides the summe appointed for you: the discharge of the dutie of a friend; the answering certaine friuolous obiections against my credit: the corroboration of his good opinion and neighbourhood: the assured establishment of his alliance, and the preferring of true vertue and desert to noble and orderly entertainement. For I can assure you, hee is not onely worthy of the place, but extraordinarily quallified to moue (like a faire Planet) in his owne Orbe for sufficiencie. Besides, when he knowes it is your pleasure to admit him to more priuate familiaritie; you shall finde him reposed in iudgement, quicke in conceit, witty in discourse, pleasant in conuersation, and, aboue all, a louer of vertue, and ciuill in all his actions. Therefore I haue reason to plead in so good a cause, and for your sake in some sort am proude, that I haue such interest in the businesse: whereby if you nobly consent to dispatch, then shall you double the fauour, and make vs both obliged vnto you for euer. For, as in harsh and vnpleasant newes, a quicke deliuery easeth much the heart, which otherwise would weary with expectation. So in all good turnes, a timely sending forth, makes the benefits gratious, &amp; the benefactor to resemble a sweet swelling spring to a thirsty soule.
               
                  Yours, if you thinke me worthy.
               
            
            
               
               
                  To her assured friend.
               
               
                  GOod Sir, Common experience hath brought women into the field of this knowledge,
                     For aduice in matters of difficulty.
                   that it is an easie task to giue good counsell, and priuate trials of your great vnderstanding hath assured me, that you know when to aduise your friend; with all the other circumstances of place and persons: whereupon I am now inforced to ouer-burden you with petitions, and make one request for all, that you deny not the bèst directions, though I seeme to examine you on particulars. I pray you then consider on the assurance of my dowry, and whether it be not preiudiciall to my estate, if in surrendring I make a change for the manor of F. which may bee for any thing I know subiect to some encombrances. Secondly, remember the conueiance of those lands for my daughters portions, and yonger sonnes annuities: and I pray you be carefull that the pleasing of our selues in present times, endamage not the Orphants in future changes. Thirdly, send me word, what enquiry you haue made of Sir G. P. who would make me beleeue, a second mariage cannot bee preiudiciall to my fortunes, and may adde to my comfort and augmentation of estate mutuall society of a worthy husband, and setled prosperitie, when the minde is contented, and a woman satisfied in her last desires. Fourthly, let your former care I pray you extend thus farre, that this secret enemy to the thriuing of all Gentlemen (10. in the 100.) doe not steale vpon vs like a priuy thief, &amp; cary such a mastring hād ouer our prosperity, that we bee not able to eate meat in good order, nor hold vp a cheerfull face of entertainment, as we were accustomed: and last of all, that my rents may bee

duely sent vp, and without further trouble or danger, then the stewards fee, &amp; the tenāts dinner, not that I wold enter into any league with couetousnes, or sparing, but because I would leaue no president of encombring my Children, nor their presumption to claime an vnbefitting priuiledge. Thus as farre as I am beholding to remembrance, I haue patched together (as you see) my requests, and make no doubt but you will accordingly, endeuor to continue my assured Friend, as I resolue to bee your well-willer in any thing to my power.
               
                  Yours, relying on your aduise.
               
            
         
         
            Gratulatory Letters.
            
               
                  
                     To her carefull Friend, M. S. H.
               
               
                  
                     A thankefulnes for a daughters good bringing vp, &amp; good bestowing.
                  
                  WOrthy Syr: I perceiue by you, that custome is as great a preseruatiue of vertue, as furtherer of vice: For as in abuses, it oftentimes falles out, that those sinnes, which at first we were afraide to touch, we afterward make a pastime to handle: so in worthy proceedings, a continuall progression maketh the race so pleasant, that a generous man walketh in no other tract, nor practiseth other actions then noble and heroicall.
               Thus haue you begun with friendship to the Father, setled regard toward the mother, continued with care to the daughter, and put charity on her best wings, to flye for vs all: Thus haue you remembred a dying friend, supported a distressed Widow, relieued a succourlesse Virgin, and taught farre more neerer kindred a lesson of true charitie: Nay, thus haue you holpe the fatherlesse, defended the innocent, raised vp the fainting soule, and loued vertue, for vertues sake: so that my poore childe may thinke her selfe happy to be borne in such an houre, when you were a witnesse of the same; and I blesse the time in which I obtained

your fauor to christen her. But is this sufficient? or shall I thanke you recompence such an inestimable benefite? I confesse it cannot: considering you haue not onely prouided for her infancie, ouer-watched her childehood, instructed her youth, taught her good manners, and brought her out of the darknesse of ignorance, to the light of vnderstanding: but haue also made it the worke of your owne hands, to marrie her to a worthy Husband; as if therein lay the secret of all businesse, and that it were the perclost of eache action: Therefore, as a small aduātage, I adde the publike acknowledging of the same, and the continuall presenting our selues and endeuors to your acceptation; wherein I am the rather emboldned, because I hope I haue encountered with such a man, that did not so much glory in the pleasuring of vs, as reioyce in bringing his owne good purposes to perfection.
               
                  Your true obseruant.
               
            
            
               
                  To his Honourable Friend.
               
               
                  WOrthy Syr,
                  
                     A thankfulnes for recompencing the giuing of a Booke.
                   Amongst many others, Martiall hath a prety Epigram against an hypocriticall Moecenas of learning: who, when a reasonable Poeme was presented vnto him, accepted the same, but returned the author without recompence: which when Martiall perceiued was a tricke of couetousnes and bad disposition: hee called him cousener, and vrged the reason; hee said, hee had cheated him of his Time, labour, wit, spirits, and passion: For how could a poore Scholler but repine at the miserie, and curse the occasion, that had preuented him from a further benefit else-where? But on my soule: you were not affrighted with this: For I haue knowne you requite the writing of a Letter, and when you rendered great recompence

for a small kindnesse, I haue heard you say:

                     Sic paruis componere magna solebam.
                  
               
               As for my poore businesse: I wondered at your profusenes, and thought it a donatiue from heauen: and when I was telling of three pound, for three sheetes of paper, I suspected my selfe for dreaming, till a creditor came in, and not onely awaked my feares, with assurance it was golde: but was contented to take the most part of it away, in part of payment of a greater summe.
               Thus from your Noble bountie was I releeued, a debt payed, your Honour divulgued, a good example discouered, and all of vs assisted: And thus must I sweare you worthie of all worth, and bee my selfe prowd, that euer I knewe your name, and participated of your good condions: wherein (I hope) as a Magnes, you will draw others to imitation, and teach me to take out a new lesson of loue, dutie, and obedience, toward you.
               
                  Yours, as you haue restored him.
               
            
            
               
                  To the right Honourable Lord. L.
               
               
                  
                     A thankefulnes for an office.
                  
                  MOst Honorable Lord, As often as I was comforted with the glorious sight of golde, so often must I needes remember your Honour, but when I make vse of the same, to worthy purpose, I blesse the cause, and pray the giuer of all blessings, to establish you as firmely, as wishes and worldly meanes can contriue. Oh what a difference is there betweene wants, and aboundance, betweene preferment, and standing at a stay, betweene imployment, and idlenesse? whereas before I walked vnre-garded, now I fitte at ease admyred; and how euer the heart,

is corrupted, I am sure of an obsequious ceremony, and cheerefull countenance; where as before I was scarce welcommed to any, I am now entertained of all; and in steed of fretting my selfe for lacke of presents to giue my friends, am now made cheerefull with many gratuities, euen from my enemies: whereas before I could not preuent necessities with great paines taking, and trouble, I now supply euen wantonnes with cheerefulnes and pleasures. So that the feare is as great to be corrupted with felicitie, as the vexation was greeuous to be tormented with aduersitie: whereas before my sonnes were affraide to bee called the children of a beggerly Gentleman, and the daughters sequestred themselues for want of outward ornaments, the boyes dare now floorish with the best fashion; and the girles take vpon them to demand, what liuings shall equall their dowry: and all this heate commeth from the Sun-shine of your fauours; all this glorie from the raies of our regard; all these riuulets of spreaching graces, from the sweetning spring of your effectuall loue toward me: so that as I liue I am beholding to nature, but as I liue well, I am beholding to you, and (the highest onely excepted) none but you, nor will acknowledge any vpholder of my state but your selfe, while I liue.
               
                  Yours, howeuer established.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To the worthy of Honourable titles, Sir F. H.
               
               
                  NOble Sir,
                  
                     A thankefulnes for defending one against a great aduersary.
                   I perceiue that vertue and discretion is so predominant with you, that you keepe equall correspondencie in all things. For as I walked in your orchard, I saw a yong tree scarcely rooted, and doubly defenced for feare

of a shaking wind, and boysterous shouldring of carelesse commers and goers; whereby▪ remembred my selfe and businesse, and when I recounted, that in my last presumption by plunging my selfe into a turbulent sea, (that is, in aduenturing to contend with my great and malicious aduersary) I was readie to sinke vnder water, had not your streched out arme held my head vpright: I blessed heauen for sending such succor; I blessed you for taking such compassion; I blessed the cause that thriued so wel; and I blessed my selfe, that had obtained such fauour; so that I must not onely be thankefull for the same: but request the perseuerance to your continuall glory. Oh how happy is hee that runneth well: but ten times more happy, that obtains the reward. The good desires of men haue some allowance, their charitable actions great estimation, their noble beginnings warrantable hopes; but a constant resolution and perseuerance assurance of felicity. Therefore (worthy Sir) as much for your owne honour, as my good, I humbly request you to consider still of mee, and as you holpe me out of a dangerous tempest, so now vouchsafe to pull me out of a raging fire: not that I would haue any contumacy in me abetted by your greatnesse; but see true noblenesse in you spring vp to the eminentest height. For, Sir G. threatneth further, and when he was not to be answered, told me in publicke, that neither I, nor my Champion should cary it away, as we presumed. But, good Sir, you pleade for vertue and innocency, and therefore I know will not be out-dared; with power made wilfull by peeuishnesse, in which confidence I will neither accumulate your praises, nor flatter my well deseruing; but settle my resolution, to desire nothing at your hands, which is vniustifiable; nor despaire of any thing, which your loue to mee, and regard of the iustnesse of the cause, may contriue.
               
                  Yours resolued.
               
            
            
               
               
                  
                     To the Honourable Lady, M.
               
               
                  MOst worthily honored, when Dauid gaue only care vnto Zibas complaint,
                     A thankefulnes for not beleeuing a fals report.
                   lame Mephibosheth was wronged, and halfe his land was giuen to a Parasite: which made Salomon more cautelous, and from his fathers vniust proceeding in this kinde, preuented the calumniation in himself: and so admitting the harlots face to face, decided the controuersie for the liuing child. So that it cannot choose but that you haue thriued in searching the Scriptures, and made vse of the same to your eternall comfort. For which I thanke you; and beleeue it, it was nobly done, both to send my accuser away without entertainement, and not condemne mee for any triuiall enforcement before you heard my iustifications. Why (my best Lady) you know, and many better men, then he, haue told you, that I am so farre from wronging you with a falshood, that I haue maintained your honor against any, as farre as truth would giue me leaue: when (as the time was) that you gaue mee cause to distast your vnkindnesse; I would not permit another to whisper against your iniustice: Nay more, when I was threatned for being a supporter of your disobedience, I plunged my selfe into a gulph of troubles, to keepe you from falling into the danger. Therefore I pray you continue your owne worthines, and good opinion toward me. For howeuer out of passion I may suspect my thriuing in your estimatimon; beleeue it, out of iudgement, and the true dutie of loue and friendship, I will not suffer any other to traduce you.
               
                  Yours, onely to be commanded.
               
            
            
               
               
                  To her well esteemed Friend.
               
               
                  
                     A thankefulnesse for lending of mony.
                  
                  MY dearest Friend, Although I am a woman, &amp; should rather busie my self with houshold affaires, wherin a good wife is resembled to a wel manured ground, yeelding increase to a rich aduantage. Yet can I not choose but hear of many discourses, especially touching thriuing businesse, whereby friendship hath bene maintained in the lending of money, for which great recompence hath beene made by interest and other gratuities: so that now we do not dispute of the vnlawfulnesse of vsury, but suppose him well satisfied, that can haue money lent him at any reasonable rate: which seeing necessity and corruption of time hath brought so to passe, Oh how blesssed was that occasion! how happy were those steps? how fortunat was that houre? how carefull was that Genius? and how compassionate was that ouerwatching eye, that brought you to my house? whereby you did not onely heare my complaints, commiserate my griefe, releeue my wants, and cheared me in discomfort: but lent me mony; and how much? 500. marke, and how long? without limitation: &amp; vpon what securitie? my honest word, &amp; my seruants bond: &amp; wherfore? gratis, without a pennie vsurie or augmentation of profit. O rare and worthy example! more fitter for Fames golden Clarion to eccho in the world for admiration, then a sillie womans thankefulnesse to acknowledge to her friends of necessitie. So that beleeue it, if praiers could preuaile by ceremonie, I would not onely kneele, but kneele so long as I could, till God had heard my request to grant you your desires. Nay I would hold vp my hands and mine eies, and lift vp my heart and all, and neuer leaue looking, till I saw comfort from heauen, spreading ouer your head the mantle of prosperitie. In which assurance I bid you farewell;

because I fare so well from the assurance, wherby you haue warranted your loue and friendshippe vnto all of vs for euer.
               
                  Yours, most dutifull if you would accept of the humiliation.
               
            
            
               
                  To his true helping Friend.
               
               
                  GOod Sir, This last was a timely fauour, and represented the first and second raine to a thirstie ground:
                     A thankefulnes for a timely good turne.
                   whereby as you haae afrighted all imputation of formallitie and smoake promises: I haue, and must acknowledge the same as a worthy kindnesse, and duty of a true Gentleman. For howeuer men may runne away with the titles of honour and greatnesse; yet (beleeue it) in the professing of friendship, there is a manifest dutie to bee obserued toward the meanest. This caused Poets and Philosophers to describe a friend from the effects of his actions, and suppliment of others in aduersities: this raised the difference betweene a good neighbour and a bad in holy Scripture: this taught the Italians to crie out, that Dono multo aspettato è venduto è non donato: a gift long expected, is sold and not bestowed as a kindnesse: and this hath taught you the way to true worthinesse, whereby I stand supported by a strong arme, and you remaine exposed to the world, as a faire mouing planet in a serene firmament.
               
                  Your recouered Friend.
               
            
         
         
            
            Letters of Newes.
            
               
                  To his worthy Friend, Aduenturer into the Straights.
               
               
                  WOrshipfull Syr: The fame of Warde (our English Pyrate) hath the same passage here, as all rumors commonly enter into:
                     Newes from Xante and Candy.
                   so that if there be the least certaintie of some occurrencies, many lyes shall bee augmented, and a mint of foolish triuiall absurdities set on worke: but because there is but one Truth, and that you expect something at my handes may come somewhat neere the same, I will deliuer what I knowe of my selfe, and am enformed from others: Out of the closet then of mine owne knowledge, I gather thus much, that beeing in Xante, and attending my passage for Constantinople, certaine Italian shippes bound for Cyprus &amp; Scanderon, durst not styrre out of harbour for feare of Warde, who was supposed to lye on the other side of an Iland called Sapientia, and watched but the opportunitie of their setting forwards: which they so procrastinated for feare of surprising, that two English ships went to Candy, vnladed their goods, made vp theyr accounts, and came backe againe for Currens at Xante, before the other could ouermaster their feare, or durst make tryall of their fortune: but when these shippes had made relation of a newe marchant man of London, cast away on the coast of Candy for want of a good Pilote, or orderly direction to preuent a northeast wind, which is most dangerous at the spring of the yeare, wee were somwhat perplexed, and the Posts were sent immediately ouer-land, to aduertise the marchants not to come into the straights, so slenderly prouided as they did. For questionles since our peace with Spaine, diuers of your company presuming on the same, haue improuidently set out weake shipping, and

slenderly prouided; so that what with piracy, shipwracke, and the Florentines, and Maltesses, wee lost more within these fiue yeares, then we did in fortie before, when wee stood on our guard, &amp; prepared to encounter with experted foes. From the aduertisemenrs, of others we gather together abundell of these occurrences, that Ward had the fortune to take a Venitian Galeas, which hee brought into Tunis, cthad raised an estate by it, but that it miscarryed in harbour; that he liued there in great feare &amp; iealousie, both of the Bashaw, whom he was faine to bribe extraordinarily; of the Turkes, whom he onely corrupts with reward; &amp; of his owne followers whom hee suspected vpon the least discontentment would betray him to the Venetian, or send him to his Maiesties Embassadours: as for that smoaky report he carryed, it is nothing so; onely he liues in a house when he comes on shore, and is reasonable politicke, if he had any wealth, not to make shew of it for feare the Ianisaries themselues should rob him altogether. But in truth the spoyle hath bene farre greater of his piracies, then the goods orderly brought to land, and out of them so maextractions, as there can little remaine to his owne share. For by that time the Bashaw is compounded with: the charges defrayed, the Turkes payed, and his owne company contented, there will be such an abatement, that out of ten thousand pound, his share and part groweth to an height of pride, if it raise it selfe to fiue hundred pound: and how deerely he must liue in the rate of housekeeping, euery passenger can tell. Concerning your particular businesse, your factor both in Xante and Candy hath sent you many letters and bils, which I leaue with this of mine to receiue speedy dispatch and orderly pardon, if any errors are committed.
               
                  Yours vndiuided, though farre off.
               
            
            
               
               
                  To his noble Friend, S. I. S.
               
               
                  WOrthy Sir; There need no filling a letter of newes, with preamble, complement, or circumstance, and therefore I will onely tell you,
                     Newes from Constantinople.
                   I am proud of any remembrance, when I expose your worth, to my conceyt, &amp; glad of any good fortune, when I can auoyd the imputation of ingratitude, by acknowledging your many fauors, and writing the same vnder my hand and seale: This I will doe still, euen in this letter from Constantinople, entreat you to admit of my coustome, and pardon me, if I take the plaine high-way of reciting particulars: without stepping into any ambiguous nookes of phrases, and eloquent aduantages: I came then to Const. in Aug: and found Syr Tho: Glouer, and his Ladie so well setled, in an honourable correspondencie to their estates, that I was proud in my countreys behalfe, that a man had raised his Fortunes meerely by worthinesse and desert; and a woman had shewed such an heroick spirit, that she was neuer distempered with the tediousnes of her iourney, nor affrighted, though she met with Cap: Ward, at the passage to Nigroponte: For whē 
                  M. Clarke the master of the Ship &amp; she went in, they disputed the matter, as if it were Ward indeed, and seeming to make a stoppe at the same, shee tolde him, there was no remedie but to fight, and hee might be made for euer, if he had the good fortune to bring his fame on the ground, and deliuer our Confederates from so great a feare:— Touching the Cittie it selfe, it is in a manner a Triangle, double walled, with beautifall Towers, and may resemble a painted Curtezan, deceiuing you, with sophysticate comelinesse, and adulterate shewes, but within corrupted, and full of confusion

and beastialitie: yet are many excellent things remarkable in the same: namely, within the Towne it selfe, called of the Turkes Stanbole, or comely: the Turkes, Seraelio, or Pallace, containing two miles about: the seauen Towers, a goodly Prison towardes the South-East: the Wall it selfe, without any Suburbes: the Mosquees, or Churches, to the number of 800. amongst whome, the Sophia, Almorata, and Sultanina, are the principall beautifull Fabrickes? the Besisteine, a place like our Exchange, or Rialto at Venice, for delicate commodities: but for aduantage, there are men and women solde, like horses in Smithfield.
               The Iewes Sellers are all vnder-ground, with iron gates, where the whole treasures of the Common-wealth are secured, both from Fire and Earth-quakes: the Conduits of water at many corners of streets, where a kinde of Officer attends, to giue to all commers. Diuers monuments of Porphyrie, Brasse, Marble, Obeliscos, Pyramides, and such like, shewing some face of Antiquitie, and placed where the auncient Greekes were woont to celebrate their Turniaments. The Balneas, which through corruption of time, and manners, are meere Brothells and stewes: The Bashawes houses, Pallaces of state, and of great capacitie: as containing diuers places of sequestration, according to their number of Wiues &amp; Concubines, which they maintaine. A place called Iobs-Toombi, celebrated for the buriall of the Emperours children.
               Diuers Seralias for men and women, as Hospitalls, to keepe them till they come to age. Constantines Pallace, and the Patriarkes houses, as solet edifices, and shewing the ruines of time, and memorable Antiquities: the guard of Ianissaries, to the number of 50000, when the Armie is at home, and the burying places, both of Iewes and Turks,

remote, at least a mile from the Wall, and superstitiously, Dedicated to the memorie of the dead. Without the Citie, the admirable hauen, called Sacra porta, 20. fadome deepe, close to the wall of both the Cities.
               
                  Galata, a Citie walled ouer against Constantinople, onely diuided by sea, as broad as our Thames: the vines of Pera, a great Suburbes to the same, where the English, French, and Venetian Embassadors were resident. Towards the North, the Arsinall of galleys, toward the South, the office of artillerie, called Tapinau: the passage to Pompeyes pillar, and the blacke tower, 20. mile orderly, beautified with Bashawes houses, and other edifices, proud of comely exornation, till you enter the blacke-Sea it selfe, which extendeth a great breadth northwardes, and a 1000. mile to the East, as farre as Trebizond.
               
               But if you would heare of a worke of wonder and magnificence, you must ride into the Countrey, some 15. miles off, and ouer-looke the Aquae-ductus, which are raised in the Valleyes, to the toppes of certaine hilles, about 500. foote high, and so carrie the water leuell, from one to another, till they fall into a Cesterne: from whence it hath a passage through diuers Pipes, to many Conduicts in the Citie.
               I dare not enlarge my Letter greater, with these triuiall things, because I knowe you haue read many discourses more peculiar and pertinent, and expect at my hand a farther discouerie, when we shall meete at more conuenient leisure.
               
                  Yours, amongst Infidells.
               
            
            
               
               
                  
                     Te his respected worthy Friend, Sir L.
               
               
                  WOorthy Sir, I was almost ashamed to write any thing from these parts,
                     Newes from Scio.
                   as newes, or matter worth the inquiring after, but that I receiued a letter from you while I was in Scio, which seemed to command me, and taught me the way of good manners to satisfie your pleasure. I would hasten to an end, lest some curious eye make a tush at these papers, when they examine, that I would fill a letter with such poore and common intelligences. I then came to Scio, of purpose to tarry for maister Bradshaw, whom we expected from Scandaron, but such was the miserie and trouble of these times and places, that the Florentines and Maltessis had sent out diuers ships to intercept the transportation of Turkes in any Christian vessell whatsoeuer, and lighting vpon him, put him to a dangerous fight, in which hee was sorely wounded, and had much adoe to come off with vtter destruction: so wee lost our passage, and spent our money in this Iland, where the Greekish women are extraordinarily beautifull, rich, and handsome: and the English Marchant liueth at great expences not daring to trust any of vs without good billes of Exchange, or good sufficient assurance of a better estate, then most commonly a traueller can enlarge. Wee did also heare that Maister Pindar our Consull at Aleppo, behaued himselfe very worthie of the best report indeede, and had much adoe in those Turkish tumults for to saue his life, and keepe the towne and Merchants from spoyling. Besides, at Scanderon a most intricate businesse about Maister E, a Merchant,

and a Frenchman, who had contracted a bargaine for Gawls to the valew of 10000. dollers, raised his fame for the well contriuing, in sauing all their liues. For the Turkes maintaining iustice in the strictest manner, and punishing the least corruption that way with death, found an occasion to bring these parties to iudiciall triall, because it was supposed, that the Moore which sold them was deceiued in the weight by a corrupted Turke, who was the officer of the customes, and broken vpon the wheele vpon the first complaint: so that there was a present demand of the like iustice both on the English and French merchants; and was not determined without a great summe of money, and bribing the Bashaw: wherein there was no other face of preuention to be seene, then disbursment of a fine, and acknowledging a fault, and so with great difficulty the matter was concluded. About the same time Master M. hauing beene some two yeare before surprised by the Maltesses, and then protesting neuer to be so ouermastred, or ouershot, vndertooke a dangerous encounter betweene Sicilia and Candy with a Venetian Galeas, in a shippe called the Corslet. For comming toward the gulph, &amp; hauing some vncustomed, or peraduenture prohibited goods aboord: as also neglecting those nauall and marine ceremonies appropriate to the State, hee held it stubbornly out, rather then he would be searched, or abased in vailing his bonet, and so the fight continued a whole day, till he was hurt, &amp; many of his men slain, but being taken and ouer mastered he was carryed to Venice, where with much adoe his libertie was obtained, to the great honour of Sir Henrie Wotton our Embassador, and contentment of the merchants, both here and at home.
               
                  Your memorable friend.
               
            
            
               
               
                  
                     To the Worthy Doctor, T.
               
               
                  REuerend Sir,
                  
                     Newes from Meteline.
                   While I lay ill at ease in Meteline, I receiued a letter from you, by the hand of Sir H. B. as hee came a shore to see the Iland, and belike taking easie iourneys in a Turkish Carmisan, heard at Gallipolis and the castles, that I was sicke there. Notwithstanding, I raised vp a pale face with a chearefull heart, and vnderstood by the same, that you desired a kinde of account concerning the Greeke Church, and Turkish gouernment. Truly your letter was most acceptable vnto me, as vnderstanding thereby the health of him I loue so well: but the contents affrighted me, as knowing nothing could come from mee worthy your view, or bearing any shew of delight, especially satisfaction, considering the iudicious apprehension and great reading of the receiuer: yet againe, when I knew (if the worst fell out) I was to encounter with loue, and ciuill acceptation, I tooke aduantage of a day wherein my Feauer did not rage, and thus hudled vp this vnfashionable peece, which if it resemble the confused lumpe, wherein nature helpeth the Beare in the deliuerance of her burthē, you must with her industry, either reduce it to fashiō, or your owne goodnesse winke at the deformities. I will therefore begin with the Greekes, who are so enuious and malignant toward the Latines, that they had rather liue in seruitude vnder the Turkes, then require either aide or assistance of the Romish Bishop, contesting with him euen from prioritie of place, and auncient possession of the Christian religion: so that in their account hee is but a meere vsurper of their glory and promotion, which hee hath ouermantled with diuises and mens traditions, that neither they can acknowledge him a father in the true Church, nor he them, as obedient children to his holy

Consistory. Concerning their ciuill gouernment, it is a meere mangled body. For no man possesseth either lands, goods, or scarcely their liues in securitie; but either the Turkes command makes them slaues, or the Timatriots or quartering of souldiers by the name of Capoges, or Spahies subiecteth all to licentiousnesse and incontinencie: they haue no munited cities, but vpon the frontires of Transiluania and Hungary, nor permitted the possession of armour or munition: onely Gratianopolis, Andrinopolis, Philopolis, Salenica, Galipolis, and some townes in the Ilands are populous and ful of Edificies, but farre from their ancient beauty, or other cities of Europe. To conclude in a word, they are the meere pictures of miserable confusion, and ruines of time. Concerning their religion, it is so corrupted with age &amp; pride of precedency, that it will entertaine no reformation; saying plainly, that Antioch was the first Christian Church, and the Greekes made the sheepe of Christs fold before euer Paul was carryed prisoner to Rome: as for Peters persecution, or being there at all, they absolutely deride it: and assure vs, that he was twenty year elders of Antioch, and appointed the Apostle ouer the Iewes. In pouertie they almost come neere the Primitiue Church. For their Monasteries are much diminished, and their Churches and Congregations very small, and of little entrade: they denie purgatory, and the Popes supremacy, saying plainly, that if such a title were extant or necessary, it belonged to Iohn Patriarch of Constantinople, with whom Gregory the Great of Rome, had many encounters to suppresse that tumour: they baptise with oyle and water, haue foure Lents, fast precisely, weare long haire like the Nazarites, allow of no Saints but in the Bible, nor haue pictures in the Church but from thence: yet do they celebrate certaine feasts to Saint George. Nicholai and Demetrius, they are much giuen to mirth, and exceede in contraries. For

at their mariages they haue great pleasure and pastime: in their buryall great sorrow and lamenting, euen to the groueling on the ground, and watching night and day ouer the graues. Many Countreys acknowledge their religion, as Russia, Georgia, Mengrelia, Armenia, and the people of Aethyopia, vnder Prester-Iean: Of whose particulars, you haue whole volumes; Amongst whom an vnderstanding wit may select the best, though many absurdities are entermingled with some truthes.
               Concerning this Turkish gouernment, neuer came Monarchy to the height of such a preuailing. For there is no subiect of hereditary eminence but himselfe, and this Emperor Sultan Achmat, is the 14. of the house of Othoman: the doctors of their Law called Alcharon, and the Mufty the principall Priest, rule the Empire, although it seeme managed vnder the gouernment of the 5. Vizeeres, &amp; other Bashawes: the strength of his kingdome is meerly supported by the Ianissaries &amp; souldiers, who are the sonnes of Christians, and depend vpon the pleasure of their Emperour, as without eyther Friend or Parent, but the Turkes pension: They loue Iustice: punish Adultry with death: hate Drunkennes, and Blasphemy: doe nothing but to purpose: eate no swynes-flesh: nor should drinke any wine: They weare long garments: neuer vncouer the head, which is all shauen, except one locke on the toppe, by which they suppose to be pulled vp to heauē by Mahomet their great prophet: They haue many wiues &amp; cōcubins to preuēt adultry: they write bias, and read backward, as the Hebrues; and neglect all languages but their owne, Persian, and Arabian: None but of Mahomets race weareth greene, and all are obedient to their Bashaws: &amp; they absolute slaues to the Emperour; For their religion, it is full of great reuerence: They call to their churches or mosquees 4. times a day, by the voyces of men, on the top of a tower: and on friday (their sabboth)

5. times: No liuing thing is pictured or engrauen in theyr churches or mosqueis, to auoyde idolatry. The principall Priest is the Musti, of great account with the Emperour: For he &amp; the doctors of their law, ouer-rule in many ciuill things. The order of Deruices is sutable to the Capuchine friers, and are called Turners: They allow God the Father, but denye the Trinitie: They reuerence the three professors of the three religions: Moyses for the Iewes: Christ for the Christians: &amp; Mahomet for themselues: They hate in others prophanation or blasphemy, and obserue naturalls, mad-men, and fooles: They bury their dead with a singing noyse, and watch ouer the graues, with mourning &amp; howling. Infinit other particulars may be obserued, but these shall suffice, till a larger discourse can bring mee within the reach of your acceptation▪ and shewe, how I haue not employed my time amisse: and am willing to giue you notice of the same; whome of all other men I would content in this kinde.
               
                  Yours, with a true heart.
               
            
            
               
                  To his honorable Friend, Captaine S.
               
               
                  
                     Newes from Malta.
                  
                  MY noble Companion, without further complemēt; when we parted from Messina, you for Venice, and I for Constantinople: Newes came to our English Consull, that the Vineyard (a ship of London) was surprised by the Malteses, the goods confiscate, and one Harris the Maister, terribly threatned, for transporting Munition, or other prohibited merchandise to the Turks: wherein the Gran-Prior is so resolute, that he hath presumed to write into England, to iustifie the action: and added withall, that the next offender shall loose ship and all. For you must consider, that there is a kinde of Confederacie betweene the Pope, the Duke of Florence, and these Malteses, gainst the Turke: and whereas all other Princes are now as it were vnder a protection of a

peace: these onely dare to proclaime a warre: And what they cannot perform with the brauery of open hostilitie at land, they will execute with the cunning of priuate surprises at Sea: and by reason the Knights of the Rhodes abated their florishes in the losse of that Iland, they are retyred to Malta, to recouer their credit: &amp; euer since that happy repulsing the Turkes, by that miraculous defending their citie and Castle, haue stood at defiance, both with this enemie of Christians, &amp; all such as shall support him, to make him a stronger enemy, then they suppose he can be of him selfe: And heerein the Pope is so charitable, that he blesseth their enterprises, and encourageth many Gentlemen, (of diuers Nations) to enrowle themselues vnder the Holy Banner: &amp; account it a glorie to be a true Souldier for religion: So that a Knight of Malta holdeth vp a countenāce of such reputation, that hee supposeth his Honour to precede any temporall dignity vnder a Baron: and the Gran-Prior himselfe will not abate a iote of a Princes estimation.
               
                  Yours for euer, though we neuer meete againe.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     To his approued Friend, G. A. Esq.
                  
               
               
                  GOod Syr:
                  
                     Newes from Venice.
                   There is no one thing in the world, in which I desire to haue an honorable contention with you, as in curtesie and good conditions: So that whether it be emulation, or a naturall motion to doe well, I care not: but am assured you haue exposed such a pattern of true friendship, that I must answer the proportion, and frame my selfe to an orderly satisfaction: you haue loued mee, therefore I must affect you: you haue visited me, therfore I must not seeme strange: you haue bene bountifull, therefore I must be thankfull: you haue written, and therfore I must answer: yea, and that from Venice, the wonder of Europe, and the glorie of Italie: where I haue encountered with Newes,

which I am proud to make you partaker of: because within the memorie of man, neuer was so remarkable an accident. Know then, that after the Pope had swelled, with the repining against the Venetian contumacy, Frier Paul of the order of Serui, was cōdemned for an heretike, burnt in his image at Rome, and attēpted many times to be murthered: his offence raised from certaine books against the Popes secular iurisdiction, ouer Princes and free states: his discourses grounded on the loue of his Countey, at such time as the Venetians determined a stopping of certaine Mortmaines, with pretences of money satisfaction: least time and seduction should weaken their glorie by diminishing their lands, &amp; giuing away their territories to monasteries: his reward, an annuall pention of 500. ducates, and glorious Title by sound of Trumpet of Theologo designato: At which the Clergie so stormed, that they made it a matter of treason, against God and his Angells, thus to extenuate the authoritie of the Mother-Church, by such presumptuous restraints, against the will &amp; pleasure of the Pope and his Cardinalls. Wherevpon, without further disputing, a seuere fulmination passed forth against them: which also so vilipended them, that fier &amp; sword was proclaimed, and nothing but submissiō and absolution could deliuer them from the sauage stroakes of reuenge.
               This so startled the Venetians, and rowsed vp the drowsie eyes of other Princes, that they al looked vp to see with what face these controuersies and accidentall displeasures, would terrifie the world: and not contented with verball protestations, they mustred their Armies, and at my comming into Italie, I heard nothing else but the clamours of warre, and warre against the Pope himselfe. In which hurliburly, a noble man of Venice, of the house of Donatus now Duke, hauing bene long since Bandited by the State, for murthering a Gentl: to whose wife loue had formerly

enthralled him, determined to worke out his reconciliation, by prostrating his seruice to the State: and attending the same (if need and occasion required) with 50. Horsm: at his owne charge; and because they should not lay imputation vpon him of formalitie, and ceremonious brauerie, from winde and smoake, he brought them by Sea into the Citie it selfe, and had licence to make a Martiall shew before the Ladies and better sort of the people: And thus in a sequestred place, at their fundamento nuouo, he mustred 50.Horsm: with reasonable equippage, and proportionable discipline, which was neuer seene in Venice before. For there is neither horse nor cart, neither fresh-water, nor wholsome-ayre, neither sword nor cloake for the Gentl: of Venice himselfe: nor any pleasant walke to passe the time with recreation, more then the delicate entertainment in their Gondolas, and some comicall showes on their Grand-Canal: Amongst which, the rarest that euer I sawe, was a costly and ostentous triumphe, called a Regatto, presented on the Grand-Canal, to entertaine the Princes of Piedmont and Mantua, who came hither of purpose to see the Citie, and the pleasures of the same: which I must needs say for liberty of life and conscience, Curtesans, Mountebanks, Musike, and Monasticall presumption, surpasseth any Citie in the world. The shew it selfe was briefly thus: diuers young Gentlem: according to their abilitie and willingnes, were selected by the order of their Balls, as Capt: of seuerall Barges, which were decked vp in orderly representations, of whales, vnicornes, dolphins, elephants, woods, fountaines, and such like: wherein all the Marriners and attendants, with seuerall warlike instruments, and musicke of lower sound, were placed, both for ornament, glorie, magnificence, and adapted congruity, to the thing they attended: and thus they passed all in order, 2. English mile in length, vnder the Rialto-bridge: attended with infinite Gondaloes,
                  
and Boates, who rowed for wagers, and striued for the mastrie of the best and speediest passage.
               
                  Yours, in all places and times.
               
            
            
               
                  To his honourable Friend, S. I.
               
               
                  WOrthy Syr: I perceiue by you, that wise men will smile sometimes, and the best grauitie can giue care to triuialll discourses:
                     Newes from Turine.
                   yea, and I am afraid, t'is mans naturall imperfection, to hunt after Nouelties, and the minde is much delighted with varietie: elfe could you neuer haue giuen way vnto such triuiall letters as I sent you, and with a kinde of cheerfulnes welcommed them, discoursing onely of the passages of Sauoy, the height of the Alpes, the snowe in Iulie, the falling of the water with such impetuosity, &amp; dangerous rupture, the pines on the mountaines, the plowing on the hilles, the strength of the Fortes and Ramparts: especially Agabella, Mount-Melian, Moriana, and Saint Katherines: and the brauery of the Spanish Garrisons in those parts.
               Because therefore I perceyue you of such faire demeanour, and willingnesse to support your Friend in his weaknesse: I will goe forward in my passage of thankfulnes▪ and make you beleeue I write to you still more for to expresse my loue, then come neere your satisfaction. Beleeue it then how-euer, I haue seene the admirable Castles of the Hellespont, which be the keyes, to open and shut in the glorie and strength of the Turkish Empire, the naturall scituation of Corfu, the Forte of Xante, the Cittadell of Naples, the many Fortifications of Italie, and other strengths of Sicilia, Rhodes, Cyprus, and such like: yet may

none of these compare with the Castle of Millaine, for Garisons glorie, greatnesse, Munition, Bulwarkes, Counter-scarphs, Casamattes, and all things pertaining to the managing of Martiall ostentation, and Military necessitie: So that this one place is the Anchor-holde of the Spanyards vsurpation in Italie: and the affrighting countenance, which keepeth many worthy Princes and Prouinces in awe, from attempting an inuasion in the Gouernment, howeuer their hearts are affected, if any mischiefe should burst out against him: and this is most apparant in Sauoy it selfe: For the Spanyard vnderstanding of a contract betwene Piedmont &amp; Mantuá, with an other combination of Modena, sent diuers agēts to Turine: yea, employed many Knights of Malta, and the better sort of Genoa, to worke a means, that the Sauoyen Princes might be sent into Spaine, vnder the tuition of the Grandes and Cleargie: To which when the Secretary seemed to encline, he was imprisoned for his Spanish affection: and till the Cardinals Aldabrandino and Caesario, with the Popes Nuntio, had streightened these crooked measures, and confirmed the Italian mariages, vnreleased: But the truth is, that, concerning the displeasure which these great personages beare one another, it ariseth both from couetousnesse and ambition.
               For the Sauoyen hauing marryed a Daughter of Spayne, and seeing long since the Enfanta quietly setled in the pride of the seuenteene Prouinces: much repined, that eyther Naples or Millaine, especially Millaine for the proximitie, was not proportioned vnto him. And so, as (farre as hee durst, or could,) both repined against the same: and hath laboured with his Holynesse to be led, and inuested in a greater field of dominion and soueraigntie. But for all this, I am resolued, no one thing troubles him more, then the escape of Geneua, from his proude attempts, and reaches.
               
                  So that if eyther pollicie, or strength could preuaile, with time and successe, to make him maister of the same, hee would quietly cast himself into the armes of contentment, and seeme proud in the glory of such an atchieuement.
               
                  Your euerlasting Friend.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     
                        Newes from Ziion, and Ierusalem.
                     
                     To his especiall Friend, Capt: Abr: Yo.
               
               
                  NOble and worthy Friend: you and I may well vent out the breath of common prouerbs, that men may meet, but not Mountaines. For as I remember, we embraced in France: raunged ouer Ireland: yea, stamped in the durt, at Kinsale: encountred in Germany: saluted one another in Italie: played the wantons at Venice: and diuided our selues againe; as if the armes of the north &amp; south, should open a larger embracing: For you prepared for Sweden and Ruscia: and I for Zidon, &amp; the bottom of the streights; where I receyued a letter from you so compendious and well compacted, that I protest I made vse, concerning the occurrences of those times and places: and receyued delight from your inuention and phrase: not desisting, till I read and read it againe and againe; but when I came to your demaund of another of mine, for particulars, concerning the passage to Ierusalem, I started backe, as if I had seen an adder in a path, and was afraid, as if some mischiefe indeed were threatned or intended; Not that there was any difficultie in writing to my Friend, a Souldier and apprehensiue man, who could both pardon out of loue, and bearewith imperfections out of fauour: but because the papist will repine at my truth; the traueller complaine of my simpicitie; and the curious desirer of Nouelties make a tush at my information: For good Syr, howeuer the Templars out of their pollicie, and imposturing cunning, erected a kinde of structure, to make Ierusalem looke with some face of nouelty, and framed a Vault, in which they

deceiued the world, with the Tombe of our Sauiour: So that the adulterate daughter of religion, superstition, filled their Monastery and pallaces with infinite wealth and Ornaments, wherewith they made libertie and licentiousnes wanton with custome, &amp; filthy abuses: and for which they were condemned by a general councell, and the Papall decree: and howeuer some corrupted Pope hath since giuen way to diuers Pilgrimages, and permitted certain friers to reuiue former memories, and gather together the scattred stones of the first Monastery, whereby there is a way open to simple credulity, to belieue some thing, &amp; pay much for the same: yet without controuersie, since the last deuastation, and that the Turke hath piece-meale rent asunder the goodly edifices of those places, as wee were woont to exclaime Nunc seges vbi Troiafuit: now corne growes where Troy stood: we may well crie out, now are there heapes of dust, &amp; some barren vines where Ierusalem florished: and according to his prophecie, that cannot erre, there is not one stone left vpon another: only the crafty Turks, &amp; the couetous Bashaw of Aleppo, the gouernor of those parts, are contented to beare with things euen contrary to the lawes of their Alcheron, impugning altogether the Godhead and incarnation of Christ: as the Iews against his pouerty and humiliation: &amp; for great sums of mony, &amp; annuall entrado, suffer stil diuers friers &amp; religious persons to entertain pilgrims, trauellers, ignorant deuotists, superstitious papists, and simple credulists, with impudēt, lying, &amp; deceitfull relicks. For otherwise if riuers might be turned, there is neither show of Citie, temple, edifice, nor the brooke 
                        ••
                     dron it self: no, an vnderstāding man dare not say (by any seeming probability) that it is the same ground where Ierusalē
                   was builded, &amp; the glory of the Iewes established; nor is there one Iewe remaining, nor honest man to maintain a veritie: yet is Zidon a harbour town, some 28. English mile frō the

same: &amp; after the traueller or Marchāt hath performed his deuotion, for great hyre, certaine guides &amp; Ianissaries will conuoy him to Gran Cayro, Arabia, Persia, Damasco, or whither you please: so that sometimes you shall haue 400. camells loden with prouision, merchandize, &amp; men, to take a iourney into Persia, and Ormus in the mouth of those Seas, against the fishing for Pearle: sometime the Christian for nouelties sake, will apparel himselfe like a Turk, with a Turban, to view the city of Mecha in Arabia, where Maehomet was entombed: Sometimes the passage is made easie into Aegipt, and wee come this way to Nylus, from whence by Boate wee visite Cayro, Alexandria, and Athyopia it selfe. Sometimes we take another course, &amp; goe by sea to Scanderon and Aleppo, and so trauell by Damasco to Babylon and Armenia: and somtimes haue the fortune to go to Tauris, and those places neere the Caspian-Sea: but this is very seldome, and neuer but when 4. or 500. Merchants make themselues strong, both in arms and prouision. For otherwise the Thieues of those places, especially Arabia, would make a prey and spoyle of all passengers. This is all I can say, this is all I dare write, for feare of interruption: but if euer the sunne will make our shadowes meete in England, I will iustifie further particulars, and make you wonder, that so many wise and vnderstanding men as haue bene in these partes, will bee transported against the veritie of Scripure, and the infallible congruitie of iudgement and reason.
               
                  My owne, in your memorie.
               
            
            
               
               
                  To his worthy Friend, M. T.
               
               
                  GOod Syr,
                  
                     Newes from Cyprus.
                   I neuer had such cause to remember the Phylosophers Banquet, as when I lay in Nicosia in Cyprus. For as I take it, Epictetes hauing inuited certain Stoyck phylosophers to dinner: for a latter bāquetting-dish brought out the globe of the world: &amp; after they had called a councell, Epictetes ouercouerd it with a fooles-cappe, whereat Heraclites wept bitterly, and Democrites laught heartily.
               The first bewalling the miserie, the latter, deriding the vanitie of the same: but if they had liued in Cyprus, and seene such confusion of gouernment; all yet ouershadowed with the Canopy of order and obedience to the State, it would questionlesse haue put them cleane out of patience, and turned their myrth into sorrow, and their sorrowes into raging and phrenzie. For the Bashaw expecting nothing but Tribute and legall iurisdiction, is carelesse how other Nations eyther liue with vpright conscience, or thriue with lawfull profite: So that the better sort practise what they list, because no man dare controwle, and inferiours follow all libertie and licentiousnes, because the others make way with ill example: The church-men confirme religion, but for pollicie, and are onely proud: they can terrifie the simple with feare of damnation, and dazell the eyes of the ignorant with the gawdy colours of superstition. The Iewe is grown so cruell in his vsurie &amp; extortion, that wheras before it was much to forfeit goods and lands, now hee exacts vppon their very flesh and blood: glorying at nothing more, then to see penurie and wants eate vp a Christian: and coldnesse of charitie trouble his very soule. The Lawyer insults with the peace of the time, and to wring the gold out of mens purses, wrests the Law to theyr owne Fancies: so that they iustifie their actions

onely with legall authority. The Cittizen is bountifull in faire words, and so hee may make his merchandize vendable, hath learnd the tricke of aequiuocating, and deceyuing his best customers. The crafts-man studieth for nothing, but to be craftie in his cunning. The Courtezan resembles the horsleach, who neuer falls off till he be full: and when hee hath suckt the blood from the veynes, leaues a man to looke pittifully, on his sores and deformity. The Souldier sweates with rage, at that hee cannot remedie, and curseth peace, because it warres with his profit, nor will apprehend any goodnes, but in the ill of licentiousnes.
               The Noble-women study for nothing but to seeme not to bee honest, yet haue they a clawse to affright inferiors for calling their actions in question: so giuing the more scope to their greatnes, to runne the more at random in pleasure. The Turkish wiues vnderstanding these particulars, repine at their Prophet, &amp; so murmur at their sequestration, that to haue some vse of the world, they visite the Balneas, come to buy iewells, make maskes in English atttyre; vse perfumes, and rather then they will not please themselues, allure their very slaues to carnall pleasure.
               To conclude, if euer the Diuell compassed the earth, and considered men, to make them subiects of hell, Cyprus is now a patterne; and the Turks there despise their Alcaron: the Iewe smileth at their Religion: the Christian derideth the scripture, and all men and people make a mocke of purity and sanctifying graces, or the true-way to saluation: So that I am weary of this prophane countrey, and desire nothing more then the blessednesse of our owne England, where the very soyle is the reuiuer of our spirits, and good gouernment the load-starre to eternall felicitie.
               
                  Yours, in the midst of temptation.
               
            
         
         
            
            A Dumpe or Passion.
            
               
                  I Cannot sing; For neither haue I voyce,
               Nor is my minde nor matter Musicall:
               My barrē pen hath neither form nor choyce
               Nor is my tale, or tales-man comicall,
               Fashions and I were neuer friends at all:
               I write, and credit that I see, and knowe,
               And mean plain troth; would euery one did so.
            
            
               I cannot faine mee vnto subtile faction,
               No prompt affection to an idle ghost,
               Nor doe I fauour any in detraction,
               Nor do I praise them, that themselues dos boast
               Small fire sufficeth vnto little roast:
               A poor mans tale's soon told, as soon reproou'd
               Neuer assisted, though neuer so much soothd.
            
            
               For credite is not of a common stampe,
               The fairest gamesters are not alwayes winners:
               The strōgest ioynts are troubled with the cramp
               And many good men are reputed sinners,
               Yet shallow foords seem best for yong beginners.
               The water's surest, where we feele the ground
               But all are not as safe as they be sound.
            
            
               Conceyt's a current forcible and deepe,
               Simplicitie a shiftlesse shippe of feares:
               A man may dream amisse, &amp; sinne asleepe,
               And foxes may accuse the asses eares:
               Patience and plainnesse euer burdens beares:
               And best they may, For custom doth invre it,
               And he is fit to beare that will endure it.
            
            
               Not euery stomacke brooketh euery meate,
               A dainty mouth can ill affect plaine fare:
               All appetites at all times cannot eate,
               Nor compleat merchant that hath euery ware
               Nor thriues hee euer that doth euer care:
               "Wishers and woulders practise &amp; conspire,
               "all haue their hopes, not euery hope their hire
            
            
               For some are blessed, other some corrected,
               Some for their worke, and some for their intent:
               Nor are all, whō our GOD hath made, elected
               Nor can all that offend, as well repent:
               Nor hath he pardond all, whom he hath shent,
               Nor mad them happy, whom he doth forbeare
            
            
               And so much wiser in so much mistrust, 
               They haue most hope that haue most doubt of tim
               "the best assured hart must beare, or brust,
               Bare honesty is poore as Ballet-rime:
               And somewhile counted for an heynous crime;
               "Yet store's no soare, because the honest-wise,
               Are feasted, when they haue what will suffise.
            
            
               "Content's a royall portion for a Prince,
               "A minde at peace excelleth gouernment:
               "Hee hath abundance, that hath competence,
               "Pleasde is a treasure neuer to be spent,
               "The patient man did neuer yet repent:
               "Nor hope in vaine, nor yet in vaine repine,
               "For sufferance is sufferantly diuine.
            
            
               And yet it is a hinderance to my Creede,
               That neither sexe nor sorts in meanes or minde:
               Neither for cause, matter, desert, or deede,
               Should haue a care of loue, or loue of kinde,
               Lost-labour so to seeke, and such to finde:
               Then seeke no more to finde such labours losses
               "Tis better not to liue, then liue with crosses.
            
            
               For touching life, that we doe loue so much,
               And court with such variety of fauour:
               If that our wisedome and our grace were such
               To weigh our losse of time, with losse of labour,
               And iudge the mischiefe of our misbehauiour:
               In both the courts of conscience &amp; repentance
               Our selues might giue both euidēce &amp; sentēce
            
            
               And scape the scrupule of a froward minde,
               And clense the filth of our corrupted sence:
               And in the molde of vanity soone sinde
               The foule occasions of our vilde offence,
               Purging diseased sinnes with some pretence:
               Wherby we liue so wretchedly so wrought on
               as neither GOD, nor any good is thought on.
            
            
               O wicked world! growth of inconstant passions,
               Wherein no vertue is at all abiding:
               If now at ease, streight sicke at least of fashions,
               With whose impatience there is no desiding,
               From whose deuises there is no diuiding:
               Now this, then that▪ euē as the humor bread.
            
            
               
               Now honor'd much aboue our small desert,
               Anon more low then is the seruile slaue:
               In whom ther is no hope, no worke, nor Art,
               To purchase, or prolong, to wish, or craue;
               Oppression's humble, and opinion's braue:
               All things vncertaine: yet most certaine too
               That what so ere Time made, it shall vndoo.
            
            
               Times past &amp; present, teach vs what's to come
               That fraile mortality is as fruitlesse aire:
               Thogh much desirde, &amp; honord much by some
               By some lesse happy, in as much despaire,
               In some most fowle, in other some most faire:
               Most fowl, most fair, most desprat, most desird
               And all but with infection most inspirde.
            
            
               So all alike the Noble and the Clowne,
               Dye, and with them their deeds, as well as they:
               For after-ages put the former downe,
               Their murthred monumēts haue nought to say
               Their beauties with their bodies, ayre, &amp; clay:
               
                  Caesar and Alexander, dead &amp; rotten,
               The actors and their actions quite forgotten.
            
            
               
                  Dauid, the Darling of th' Almighties-heart
               
               Predominant in pleasure and in power:
               Most worthily, till wickednes did thwart
               That heauenly Sunshine, with a worldly showre
               "The greatest winner hath a loosing hower.
               For GOD did neuer yet make that man liue
               That hath not in his life some cause to grieue.
            
            
               How trust we then to vaine abilitie?
               The breath of howrs, &amp; giddy Fortuns fauors:
               Whose alterations worke debilitie,
               And our loose-hopes, with loosing happes mislabours,
               time hūteth fools, as fools hūt hares with tabers
               Beating vpon the toppe of stiles and stockes,
               Tlll in the fire of pride they burne like blocks.
            
            
               Sencelesse of all sence, but sencelesse pleasure
               And that it selfe euen as it is affected:
               Subscribing onely to the humors leisure,
               By which alone they wholly are directed,
               Till ill by worse be worthily detected:
               Then car'd as little for, as they haue car'de
               They feele the differēce to be spoyld, or sparde.
            
            
               Beauty and strength are but a vulgar blast,
               And shape a subiect vnto euery beast:
               Euen sence it selfe, will leaue our selues at last
               When this shall be the subiect of the feast,
               That vertues store will neuer be decreast:
               Wher good men may recoūt without controule
               The golden reckoning of an humble soule.
            
            
               And to dilate the matter somewhat more,
               Let's looke a little ore the world againe:
               And see, if that we haue not causes store
               to fret our selues, and on our selues complaine,
               that any worldly Soyle our soules should staine,
               When nothing in the world is good or sure:
               ther's nothing good that can the world endure.
            
            
               Princes of state, the game of Fortunes wheele,
               Are treasons subiects, thralls to base despight:
               tormented in their soules, when as they feele
               A guilty conscience open inward sight
               to see, how wrongs haue ouergrowne the right:
               And how so ere theyr titles make them proud
               Yet must they (dye like mē) GOD saies aloud.
            
            
               Nobles (the breath of Kings) are vaine in pride
               And vainer in opinion of vaine men:
               Swelling with factious hearts gainst wind and tyde
               If they be crost, or countermanded, when
               The Lyon mongst the beasts coms from his den
               And peraduenture takes the Ape to play,
               When Beasts of nobler kinde are chasde away.
            
            
               Great Officers (the wantons of the time)
               Sifting theyr sences through sleight vanitie:
               Teaching poore vertue, that this durt &amp; slime
               Must worke our worldly base felicitie,
               And further pleasures in iniquitie:
               As for the soule, let simple men regard it,
               For being simple, simple worths reward it.
            
            
               Friends yet vntryde, like golden hanging fruite
               With wordes of fauour, and as smooth as oyle,
               Smoake promises to helpe thee in thy sute,
               But all to countnance pride, and to beguile
               Simplicitie with many a fained smile:
               For touch them once, they crumble vnto dust
               like burnt cole-fruit, which Tātalus did trust
            
            
               
               Acquaintance onely bubbles in the ayre,
               Made out of sope and water by young boyes:
               Swelling a while with pleasant shape and faire,
               As long as our owne breath augments the ioyes,
               but blown on burst prouing thēselues slight toyes
               For if that our misfortunes are espide,
               They quickly shrink, &amp; hang their heads aside.
            
            
               Children the care of cares, and harts disease
               In such a time of brauery and sinne,
               Where disobedient sonnes must needs displease,
               And daughters faire, themselues to know begin
               Seeking a dangerous libertie to winne:
               For what a Feuer makes the Father quake,
               whē daughters hāds with fool or whore do take.
            
            
               Women the torments of vnsetled hearts,
               The very Fewell vnto burning lust,
               Yet in themselues doe acte contrary parts,
               Against such men as doe them truely trust,
               For if they swell with wantonnesse vnburst:
               They practise slye deceyts: if they be good,
               Yet oft with chafings they doe vexe thy blood.
            
            
               Strūpets most dangerous baytes, a burning fire
               Blacke coales consuming, or for to bismeer:
               Trothles to trust, wrought vp with greater hire
               A foule consumption of the soule most deere,
               Yet making boyles and botches to appeare:
               O that fond mā wold liue with sweetned breath
               For their darke stincking houses lead to death▪
               
            
            
               Beautie, a pleasing ornament to sight,
               Ordainde to shew the Makers noble glorie:
               But see how Pride and Nature doth delight,
               To ouerthrow the goodnes of a story,
               Although decaied with time, when head is hory
               Yet is it made adulterate hy arte,
               When a false hand hath playde a cunning part.
            
            
               Opinion is a Monster amongst vs all,
               Yet doth not terrifie with outward shape:
               Onely our selues doe as we rise and fall,
               After the censures of the people gape,
               And therevpon by force of vicious rape
               Bereaue sweete uertue of her chastitie,
               With anxious hearts swelling in vanitie.
            
            
               Life and the best life but a topping tree
               Set in the midst of a confused grange:
               Which whē the Lord thinks good he doth agree
               to fell, or roote it vp for some newe change,
               Or trie some stranger form, by such exchange.
               Yea peraduenture burned in the fire,
               subiects must yeld to what their kings require
            
            
               Apparell monstrous by our monstrous wills,
               Disguising our defests▪ seeking to hyde
               Natures deformitie, when purse fulfills
               An humorous wantonnesse on euery side:
               Yet frō substantiall truth most largely wide.
               For when that we must naked goe to graue,
               What will become of that wee seeme to haue?
            
            
               Vertues and vices, neither good nor bad,
               But as the owners states giue them their test:
               For, who in estimation can be had,
               For greatest vertues if they doe not rest
               In wealth, or good opinion of the best:
               And vicious who, but he that cannot hide
               And keepe his faults from being soone espide?
            
            
               Buildings of sumptuous cost, the prey of Fire,
               are somtimes curst, with sobbing poor mes cries:
               When to erect what greatnesse doth desire
               A hundred cottages in rubbish lyes,
               And many an Orphan vnrelieued, dyes:
               But where the morter of an house is mixt
               With blamelesse bloud, it cannot long be fixt.
            
            
               Pearls, pretious stones, the glasse of plēties pride
               Riches and Friends, vnstaid in mood &amp; minde,
               Kinred, but Natures chaffe, Whē they are tride
               For they will flye away with Stormy winde,
               In whom nor loue, nor truth at all we finde:
               These shapefull monsters daily alter so,
               as wee can hardly credite, what we know.
            
            
               The fraudfull Fox deals friēdly with her whelps.
               There is no beast that to her owne is cruell:
               All things were by creation made for helpes
               And kinde to kinde is still a friendly iewell:
               The Fire doth giue him fire, that giueth Fuell;
               Euen there where contraries enforce despight
               Nature in nature teacheth 
                     〈…〉
                  
               
            
            
               
               Then, if thou wilt be man, and not be kinde,
               Disdaine thy needlesse int'rest in creation:
               Be to instruction, deafe, to nature blinde:
               With neioher man nor beast haue conuersation,
               Abandon hope of grace, abiure saluation:
               Be both aliue and dead harmfull and hatefull
               Be any thing, if thou wilt be ingratefull.
            
            
               And lay aside absurde Affinitie,
               Vnlesse to hell thou wilt allye thy selfe:
               And so the Diuell graunt immunitie:
               As is thy trust in him, and in thy wealth.
               Abortiue potion of foule poysoned pelfe:
               Sorrrow of soule, and surfet of vile sinne,
               Man had bene happy if thou hadst not hin.
            
            
               An honest minde informer time did show
               More pietie then now the best of kinne:
               That was because the time was honest to,
               Much better then this age, that wee are in,
               Such are the putrefactions of sinne:
               Our almes, our neighbor-hood, our humanity,
               Turnd diuell, discord, and immanitie.
            
            
               Neighbour indeed is now by stranger nam'de,
               Cousen by cousnage, kindenesse is vnknowne:
               And friends of friendship are so much ashamde
               As custome hath concluded there is none,
               None that doth good, the Psalmist saith, not one.
               It is the Prophet, it is GOD, doth say it,
               And man were much to blame to disobey it.
            
            
               As hee's as much to blame that doth belieue
               Any that liues in ioy, vnusde to moorne:
               Doth loue, can loue, commiserate, or grieue,
               Father or brother haplesse and forlorne,
               For pitty onely is to plenty sworne:
               And hee's a bastard vnto worldly blood,
               That doth a poore man eyther grace, or good.
            
            
               Yet GOD forbid, that GOD should causer be,
               That wee for lacke of knowing him do erre:
               He gratious suffers, whilest that gracelesse wee
               His tollerance into negligence trans-ferre,
               Whereby it makes the Atheist to auerre:
               The soule of man immortall in the least,
               
                  
                     〈…〉
                   as it doth in beast.
            
            
               Men cannot doe, what cannot be vndone,
               Nor suffer more then flesh and blood can beare:
               Who playes with fortune, sildom times hath won
               T'is labour lost to worke aganst the haire,
               Then not preuaile, its better to forbeane:
               "A thing vndone, is easily preuented▪
               
               Doe to vndoe is neuer vnrepented.
            
            
               Glorious designes are ammelled in blood,
               The way to greatnes is vneuen and hard:
               He neuer was that for preferment stood,
               That was not often with mischaunces barrd,
               The body of attempts haue crosses scarrd:
               Who liu'de and sought for honest labours hyre
               And was not forst to worke it out of Fire.
            
            
               Courts and occurrences of Kings &amp; Pallaces,
               Where some soone rise, to fall againe as fast:
               Show the conditions of the fallaees,
               Whose fruits doe scantly blow before they blast,
               Planted with care, and with repentance past:
               So that cōpare the gains with losse surmoūting
               And saue a labour, and auoyd accounting.
            
            
               T'is pittie Warre were not at warre with this
               But let the worthlesse Souldier be aduanced:
               The better times made better seruices,
               Where best endeuors best rewards enhanced,
               But now the best of Beggars is best chaunced:
               A heauy Fortune that such hazard yeelds,
               Either to starue at home▪ or die in Fields.
            
            
               But heare my counsell in a Grand-sires phrase,
               All doe amisse, let all amisse amend:
               Self sauing workes are best deseruing praise,
               And praise on workes in prudence done, attend
               All actions are approoued as they end:
               Who made the feast will fast to mind the pay,
               whē vnthrifts care▪ not who the charge defray.
            
            
               Then sith the ende is good of these my Rimes;
               Theyr plainnesse showes no vainnesse, but the Times.
            
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

