
   
      
         
            The rutter of the see, with the hauons, rodes, soundynges, kennynges wyndes flodes and ebbes, daungers and coostes of dyuers regyons with the lawes of the yele of Auleton, and the iudgementes of the see. With a rutter of the northe added to the same.
            Routier de la mer. English
            Garcie, Pierre, called Ferrande, ca. 1435-ca. 1520.
         
         
            
               1560
            
         
         Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2006-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01436
            STC 11553
            ESTC S119708
            99854915
            99854915
            20373
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01436)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20373)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 568:03)
         
         
            
               
                  The rutter of the see, with the hauons, rodes, soundynges, kennynges wyndes flodes and ebbes, daungers and coostes of dyuers regyons with the lawes of the yele of Auleton, and the iudgementes of the see. With a rutter of the northe added to the same.
                  Routier de la mer. English
                  Garcie, Pierre, called Ferrande, ca. 1435-ca. 1520.
                  Copland, Robert, fl. 1508-1547.
               
               [88] p.   
               
                  T. Colwell,
                  [London :
                  1560?]
               
               
                  Imprint and suggested publication date from STC.
                  Translated from the earlier and shorter form, "Le routier de la mer", rather than from "Le grant routtier". In title: "with the hauons" --Cf. STC.
                  Signatures: A-E F⁴.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Maritime law --  France.
               Navigation --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-08
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-10
            Andrew KusterSampled and proofread
         
            2005-10
            Andrew KusterText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-01
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               ❧The
Rutter of the
See, with the hauons, rodes
ſoundynges, kennynges
wyndes flodes and ebbes,
daungers and cooſtes of
dyuers regyons with
the lawes of the yele
Auleton, and the
iudgementes
of the
ſee.
            ¶With a Rutter of the
Northe added to
the ſame.
(✚)
*
         
         
            
            
            ¶The prologue of Robart Copland
the tranſlatour of this ſayde Rutter.
            EVery ſcyence artyfycyal or
mortal is moeſt commenlye
enuretd with reaſon, ſpeculacyon,
and practyſe, by the whyche is
knowen and tryed the parfyte doinges
of the ſame, formallye to the behote at
the doers, and to them, whiche of neceſſite
muſte ſet to worke ſuche as ben
practyſed and auctoryſed ī euery ſuche
ſcyence as thus.
            Euery man that entendeth to buyld be
it habytacyon, fortreſſe or other edifice
on lande or water, behouethe to haue
ſuche worekemen that can caſt the plat
and know the ſubſtaūce and the groū
               de
for the foundacion: and that can ſaflye,
and dyrectlye frame, and rayſe the
hole worke. For whoſo hathe not
the veray ſcyence of Arſmetryke, and
geometry to ayme &amp; meaſure ye platte
and coniecture of the hyght, drede and

lenght, and to fortifye it with Pryncypalles,
giſtes, beames, tenaūtes, morte
                  •
               ſes,
coūtrebraſes. and not knowing
the nombre in eueri piece duely framed
is in doute &amp; peryll to leſe all the frame
and wtout tooles therto belonging, as
rule ſquyre, cūpas, lyne, prychel, tryangle,
&amp; ſuch other, &amp; for the ſafegard &amp; reparaciō
therof, to ſtore it with brick, or
ſtone, lime, ſand, l
                  •
               me, lath bord, nayle
tyle, leade, &amp; other Howbeit yt by reaſō
a man that neuer was builder bi ſpeculaciō
may reaſe and edifi, but nothing
like yt entired practiſe. In lyke maner
I coniecte that in the feate and courſe
of Nauigacyon or ſealyng a man may
preſume &amp; take vpon him by his ſpeculacyon
to cōducte a veſſell, as a blynde
man ī a deſolate wyldernes doth walk
tyl he be loſt. But ye ſure wiſe &amp; enured
maiſter mariner, or lode
                  •
               inā, not ygnorauntly
truſting his own ſēſual reaſō
dylygently for the ſafegarde of his doynges
and aſſuraunte of his practyſe,

conſydereth yf his beſſell be ſure, and
decked at all poyntes, and wi
                  •
               h greate
ſolicitude ſequeth enquyreth, &amp; geteth
ſuche neceſſary inſtrumentes as behoueth
to the induſtry of his practyſe, as
the carde, compaſſe, rutter dyal and other
whiche by ſpeculate practyſe ſheweth
the place, that is to ſay, the coſtes
hauens rodes, ſoundinges, daungers
floodes, ebbes, windes k
                  •
               ninges courſes
and paſſages fro land to land, and
to be the more ſure in the conductynge
of his vyage, he buſyly purueyeth for
all takelynges &amp; ſtore therto behoffull
as cables, roopes, ankers, maſtes, ſayles,
ores, artyllery, vytayle, freſſhe water,
fewell, and other neceſſaryes.
            *All this diſcretely pondred by a ſad
ingenyour and cyrcumſpecte maryner
of the Citye of London beynge in the
towne of Bourdewes bought a pretye
booke Imprynted in the Frenche language
called the Rutter of the ſee conteynyng
many propre feates of his ſcyence.

And conſyderyng that it was expedient
and neceſſary for all Englyſhe
men of his facultye to haue it in theyr
owne language to the erudicyon, and
ſaue gard of our marchaūtes as other
hauntynge the ſee, not knowynge the
content therof. The whiche booke he
inſtāted me lo tranſlate into Englyſh.
which ouer ſene, me thought veray d
                  •
               ffycyle
to me, not knowynge the termes
of mariners, and names of the cooſtes
and hauens, for I came neuer on the
ſee, nor by no coſte therof. But folowyng
my copye by the aduyſe, and ouerſyght
of certayne cōnyng men of that
ſcyence whiche bolded, and informed
me in many doubtes, I did vntertake
in doing my diligence: as a blind horſe
in a myl turnyng the querne ygnoraū
               tly,
ſaue by conductynge of the mylner
that ſetteth hym on worke. Deſyryng
all experte mayſters to correc
                  •
               e
this and make other for the comon vitlite
and ſafegarde of theſe our natyfe

countrey men and goodes flotynge in
dyuers regyons, In the whych doyng
they ſhall not onely obtayne thankes,
laudes and be prayed for in thys world
and alſo in the other, but he hyghly rewarded
of almyghtye God whyche is
chefly mayſter and lodeſman of and to
euery ſtreme and cooſt. To whom be
gyuen laude and glorye in the worlde
of worldes. Amen.
         
         
            ☞The tranſlatour.
Robart Copland.
            Gentyll maryners on a bonne vyage
            Hoyce vp the ſalye, and let god ſtere.
            In ye bonauē
               
                  •
               ure makīg your paſſage
            It is ful ſee the wether fayre and clere
            The nepetydes ſhall you nothing dere
            A ſee bordmates S. george to borow
            Mary &amp; Iohn, ye ſhal not nede to fere
            But with this boke, to go ſafe thorow
         
      
      
         
            
               
               *Of the tides, that is to wyt, the ſtode
and ebbes fro the raſe of Sayne
into Flaunders.
               AT the raſe of Sayne the moone
in the ſoutheweſt and poynte of
ſouhtful ſee, &amp; in the ſoutheaſt &amp;
a poynt of eaſte lowe water.
               At ſaynt Mathews ye moone north
eaſt, ful ſee. And ſouth weſt low water
               At the fourne the moone northeaſt a
poynt of eaſt full ſee, and in the ſouthweſt
a poynt of weſt lowe water.
               At Portſall and at Bergroagh the
moone in the eaſt northeaſt ful ſee, &amp;

                     〈◊〉
                   the ſouth weſte lowe water.
               At Lyganan the moone in the eaſt
northeaſte full ſee, and ſoutheaſt lowe
water.
               With in the yle of Baſepole the
moone in the eaſt northeaſtfull ſee, and
wythoute in the chanell the moone in
the eaſte, and the moone in the ſouthe
lowe water.
               At Melenem the mone in the ſouthe

apoint of ſouthweſt low water, and in
the weſt a poynt of Northweſt full ſee
*At the .vii. yles the moone in the eaſt
ſoutheaſt full ſee, and ſouth ſouthweſt
low water.
               *Fro the yle of baſepole to ſaynt Malowes
al alonge the cooſt vnto Carteras
the moone in the ſouth lowe water
and the moone in the weſt full ſee.
               *At Cauſe, Graneſey, Iarſei, fourne
and Clerke the moone ī thy ſouth lowe
water to the grouende, and in the weſt
full ſee.
               *At Roktowethe moone in the ſoutheaſt
a poynt of the eaſt full ſee, and in
the coſt of garneſey wythout the mone
in the ſouthe eaſt lowe water.
               *At the race of Brehac the moone in
the eaſtful ſee, &amp; in ye ſouth lowe water
☞At Ferrere the moone in the ſouthe
eaſt full ſee.
               At the race of Blanchey bytwene the
Hag &amp; Aldreney the moone ī the ſouth
eaſt, a poynt of the eaſt ful ſee.
               
                  
Bytwene Creke &amp; alderney is a bāke
called the banke of ſhare, and ouer it is
ix. fadomes wythout the caſketes the
moone in the eaſt ſoutheaſt full ſe, and
in the ſouthweſt lowe water.
               At the Hag and aldreney the moone
in the ſouth a poynt of ſouthweſt lowe
water to the ground.
               At the ſherbrugh, at Barflewe and
at the Hag the moone in the ſouth
ſouthweſt low water to the grounde.
               At Carteras the moone in the ſouth
ſouth eaſt ful ſee, and in the weſt ſouthweſt
lowe water.
               From the chefe of Cauſe to Diepe
the moone in the ſouth ſoutheaſt ful ſe
               In Sayne at the folle deleure, alſo
for the landuange and the mone auay
lynge fro ſoutheaſt full ſe.
               Without antifer or Lantrygat vnto
the baſſe of Somme the moone in the
eaſt full ſec. In ſome the moone in the
ſouth full ſee, and with nepetydes, and
northwynde the moone in the ſouthe

ſoutheaſt full ſee.
               At Staples and boleyn vnto the
ſtabler of Tenet yt moone in the ſouth
ſoutheaſt full ſee.
               At the ſtrayte of Calays the moone
in the ſouthweſt full ſee.
               Fro the ſtrayte of Calays to Ostende
the moone in the ſouth ſoutheaſte low
water. Fro Oſtende to Blankborowe
the moone in the ſoutheaſt and a point
of ſouth low wather, &amp; ouer al the baukes
of Flaūdres the moone in ye ſouth, full
ſee. At the Cape Loupin the moone
in the ſouth full ſee.
            
            
               
                  ❧Courſes fro the raſe of Sayne in
to Flaūders, &amp; how the tydes towarde
Brytayne beareth.
               WYthin the Chanell of yra is the
flode bereth in the eaſte and, the
ebbe into the weſt.
               Bytwene Moyles, &amp; Vſſhant the
floode beareth into the eaſt northeaſte
&amp; the ebbe īto weſte ſouthweſt, wt oute
ye yles ye ſhall fynde .xlv. fadomes, and

ſmall grauell. Bytwene Vſſhant and
Sylley the floode bearethe in the eaſte
northeaſt. In the gutter of Vſſhant ye
ſhall fynde good road at .xxv. fadoms
&amp; beware of a rocke that is in the myndes
of the baye Bytwene fourne, and
Bergroagh vnto the yle of Baſepoole
the flowe bearethe to northeaſte, and a
poynt of eaſt &amp; the ebbe agayne warde
               At the coſte of the yle of Baſepole
the flowe beareth into the eaſt ſoutheaſt.
Within &amp; wythout ye .vii. yles the
flowe beareth into the eaſt &amp; poynt of
ſoutheaſt, Wythout Brehac the flowe
beareth in the eaſt &amp; the ebbe againſt it
               From Brehac the flowe to Saynt
Malo the flode beareth eaſt ſoutheaſt
Bytwene caſket &amp; alderney ye flow cō
                  meth
out of ſouthweſt vnto halfe flod
From Alderney to Barflewe the water
cometh out of the eaſt.
               Fro Barflewe to the yles of Marcoll
the water cometh out of the ſouth ſon
theaſt all longe the ſayde cooſt.
               
                  
Fro barflewe to Lantrygat and the
thefe of Cauſethe water cometh out of
the eaſte northeaſt, and in the route ye
ſhall finde the ſoundyng .xvi. or .xviii.
fadomes, with a good botome &amp; ſande
               For Lantrygat to the baſe of Sōme
the water cometh fro northe northeaſt
               Fro the baſe of Sōme vnto Boloyne
the water cometh fro northe northeaſt
               Fro Boleyne to the Hurdels the water
cometh fro the north.
               Fro the Hurdels to grauelynge the
courſe without the Baſe the water cometh
north northeſt, and with out grauelynge
to Dunkyrke ye water cometh
fro the northeaſt.
               Fro the bay of the downes to oſtende
the water cometh fro the northeaſt,
a poynt of the eaſt. Fro Oſtende to
blankborow the water cometh fro the
eaſt northeaſt.
               Fro Blankborowe to the poynt of
ſaynt Katherine the water cometh fro
the eaſte and by eaſt northeſte.
            
            
               
               ☞Routes and courſes fro the raſe of
Sayne in Flaunders.
               ROutes and courſes fro the raſe
of Sayne to com to ſaint Mathewes,

                     •
                  e muſt go northe warde
&amp; bere the poynt of the nedle ſomwhat
aftere borde.
               Fro ſaynt Mathewes to Fourne goye
on the north northeaſt and beyonde
ſaynt Mathewes wythout ye poynt in
fayre lande. But take good heade, the
Fourne &amp; the nedles of ye yle of myght
lyeth northeaſt &amp; ſouthweſt.
               The yle of Baſepole and Garneſey
lieth northeaſt and ſoutheaſt. Roktow
and Garneſey lyeth north and ſouth.
Garneſey &amp; Aldreney lyeth northeaſt
and ſoutheaſt. Alderney, and the Caſkettes
lyeth northeaſt, and ſouthweſt
a point of the eaſt &amp; a point of the weſt
               The Caſkettes, &amp; Lantrygate lyeth
eaſt and weſt, and if ye wyl go to Harfewe
in Sayne go eaſt ſoutheaſt.
               Lantrigat &amp; the ſhef of Caus lyeth

north and ſouth, and yf ye wyll go fro
Lantrigat in Somme and ſtaples the
courſes lyeth northeaſt, and ſoutheſt.
               yf ye wyl go fro the ſtrayte of Calays
into flaūders go northeaſt wyth
the floode and agaynſt water goo eaſt
Northeaſt as farre as the baye of the
Downes, &amp; whē ye be at .xvi. fadomes
ye be in the right courſe of the Chanell
of Fla
                     •
                  nders, and whē ye haue .xii. fadomes
of water ye ſhal be hard aborde
the baſe, and forth with ye ſhall fall to
thre or foure.
            
            
               ☞Entringes and Harborowes
of the coſte of
Normandye.
               YF ye wyll lye at Sherburgh eaſt
auker at .vi. fadome, and ye ſhall
fynde fayre botome, &amp; ye ſhal go north
weſt fro the point of the ſouth and beware
of the ſayde poynt, for there it is
daungerous.
               ☞yf ye wyll lye at Hagge caſt anker
beneth the churche at .xii. fadomes.
               
                  
Yf ye wyll lye at the foſſe of Coluyll
caſt anker wtout at .vii. or .viii. fadōs.
               Yf ye wyll lye in the roode of the ſhefe
of Caus go in &amp; caſt anker at .vi. fadomes,
and ye ſhal haue the north fro the
land as ye entre, and haue no landuāg
of the north northeaſt.
               If ye wyl lye in the rode of Dyepe
caſt anker at, vii. fadōs before ye towne
               If ye will lye at the baſe of Sōme
caſt anker without the bankes, &amp; take
hede that the monaſtery of Cayo be in
the eaſt northeſt, and caſt anker at ſyxe
or at ſeuen fadomes of water.
               And yf ye wyll go in take hye water
vnder you, and take youre markes beyonde
the caſtell of Crotey, a lytel with
out Lordell, and ye ſhall go at two fadomes
and an halfe or thre.
               yf ye wyll lye beforeſt aples caſte
anker at .vii. fadoms or .vi.
               yf ye wyll lye at anker before Beloyn,
before the heauen, and caſte anker

at .viii. or .vi. fadoms.
               yf ye wyll lye before the Hurdels
wyth a north wynde, caſt anker before
Ordecellus at .x. or .xii. fadoms and ye
ſhall haue landuang of the north commynge
fro hurdels, and ye ſhall haue
a good botome. And yf ye caſt anker
in the depeſte, ye ſhal fynde rocke and
euyl botome.
            
            
               
                  ❧Floodes fro Sylley and England
into Flaundres.
               AT ſylley a poynt in ye northeſt a
poynt of eaſt full ſee, and wyth
out ſilley the moone in the eaſt full ſee.
¶At Mouſhole the moone in the eaſt
northeaſt full ſee to lande. And without
the moone in the eaſt ſoutheaſtful
ſee alſo.
               *At Falmouth the moone in the eaſt
and. by north eaſt ful ſee to the lande;
and in the eaſt ſoutheaſt without ful
ſee alſo.
               *At Fowy, &amp; at. Plummouth the moone
in eaſt full ſee to lande, and wtout

in the eaſt ſoutheaſt ful ſee, alſo.
               At Dartmouth the moone in the
eaſt full ſee to land, and without, in the
eaſt ſoutheaſt.
               At Portlande, without, the moone
ſoutheaſt, and a poynt of the Eaſt ful
ſee, at the ankerage of Portlande, thee
moone in the eaſt ſouth eaſt full ſee,
               At Hounde faſt, and at Poole the
moone at the ſoutheaſt ful ſee, and
ſouth weſt full ſee.
               At the Nedles of the yle of wyghte
wythout the mone at the Southeaſt,
and a poynt of ſouth full ſe, at the coſt
of the ſayd yle at an hygh ſprynge the
moone at the ſouthweaſt full ſee.
               At Shorham the Moo
                     •
                  e at ſouth
and a point of ſoutheaſt ful ſee.
               At Bewchey the moone in the ſouthe
ful ſee. At the chambre of wynchelſe ye
moone in the ſouth ful ſee.
               At the thwart of romney the moone
in the ſouth ſouthweſt full ſee.
               At the ſtrayte of Calays the moone

in the ſouthweaſt full ſee,
               Courſes from ye Cape of Cornewale
into flaunders, and how the tydes dobere.
               Fro the Cape of Cornwayle to Lezarde
the water cometh out of the eaſt,
towarde ſoutheaſte.
               Fro Lezard to Dodman and vnto
Bodeſters called the Sterte the water
commeth from the eaſt northeaſte.
               Fro the Sterte to Portland the water
cometh from the ſoutheaſt, and as
well is the tyme knowen that the flode
ſhall bere in to ſutheaſte by reaſon of
that ebbe at Portlande.
               At the yle of Wyght the water commeth
from the eaſt towarde northeaſt
and yf ye beat the cooſt of the ſwingles
at two fadomes, the water ſhall come
from the eaſt northeaſt.
               ¶Vnto Douer the water commeth
from the eaſt towarde northeaſt.
               From ſaynt Margare
                     •
                  e to 
                     〈◊〉
                  
the water commeth from the north.
               
                  
Into the Temſe the water commeth
from the eaſt ſoutheaſt.
               Routes from, Sylley, &amp; Englande
into Flaunders.
               SYlly and Longſhyppes ly eaſt northeaſt
and weſt ſouthweſt.
               Syllye and Lezarde, lye eaſt, and
weſt. Bytwene Sylly, and Lezarde is
a Rocke called Reynoylde ſtone, called
golffe in brytyſſhe.
               And who ſo departeth fro the cape
of Cornwaile muſt ſail eaſt ſoutheaſt
for the double Lezard. For ſo lyeth the
two landes.
               Mouſhole, &amp; Lezarde lyeth ſoutheaſt,
and northweſt.
               Lezarde, and Dodman lye northeaſt
and ſoutweſt, a poynt of the eaſt, and
a poynt of weſt Dodman, &amp; the ſtarte
lie eaſt northeaſt, and weſt ſouth weſt.
               The Starte and Portland lye eaſt
and Weſt, a poynt of Northeaſt, and a
poynt of ſouthweſt.
               Portlande, and the yle of Wyght

ye eaſt and weſt.
               The yle of wight: and Bewchey lye
eaſt and weſt, a point of northeaſt and
a poynt of ſouthweſt.
               Benchey and the poynt of Romney
lye eaſt northeaſt and weſt ſouthweſt.
               Saynt Margaretes point &amp; Tenet
lye north, and ſouth.
            
            
               ¶Entrynges and Herborowes al a
longe the cooſt of Englande.
               IF yt you will lye at the trauers
of Mouſhole go nygh ye land, &amp;
caſt anker at .vi. fadomes &amp; ye
ſhalbe in a good place at .vii. fadome,
it is al rocke.
               yf ye wyll entre into falmouthe ye
ſhal fynde a rocke in the myddle of the
entrynge, Leue it on the larborde ſyde
and go towarde eaſte by ſhore, &amp; whā
ye be paſt it go ſtreight in. For the bay
is great ſound and large, and caſt anker
where ye wyll at .xi. or .xii. fadoms
amyd the baye, and if ye wyll go at the
tornynge of the full ſee. For there is abanke

to paſſe whiche ye ſhall fynd a
                     •
                   low
water and at ful ſee at .ii. fadomes
and a halfe or thre ankeryng, and if ye
lyſt ye may go into the town of peryn.
¶If ye wyll entre at Plummouth,
go in ſtreight, and come not to nere the
yle for there is daunger, and if ye wyll
lye drye go before the towne and holde
towarde the Tour for the cauſey, and
yf ye wyll paſſe towarde the weſt, goo
nyghe to the mayne lande, and caſt anker
at .xx. fadomes.
               ¶If ye wyll entre at Dartmouthe,
go beneyth ſaynte Patrykes mynſter,
that you ſhall ſe at the entrynge of the
hau
                     ••
                  , and holde you toward the weſt
with a ſouth wynd, &amp; giue ſomewhat a
burth fro the pay at of ſaynte Patryke
for bycauſe that there is the flatte of a
rocke, and take hede of the rock on leer
borde ſyde. For this rocke is thwarte
of ſaynt Patryke amyd that chanell,
and at the ebbe of a ſprynge tyde reſteth

                     •
                  uth .iii. quarters or a fadō, and

caſt anker nigh the town at .vi. or. 
                     〈◊〉
                   fadomes.
               Yf ye wyl paſſe to portland caſt anker
at .viii. fadomes, and ye ſhall haue, landuang
of ſouthwind through that yle.
               yf ye wyl entre wythin the poole go
nygh the ſhore, &amp; ayme the ſt
                     •
                  ple of the
Poole throught a litle houſe that is at
the entrynge of ye hauen, &amp; go betwene
the two bankes, &amp; ye ſhall fynd at low
water .ii. fadomes and a halfe or thre.
               If ye wyll entre wtin the nedles of
the yle of w
                     •
                  ght, go harde aborde ye nedles
right in &amp; beware of ye rocke in the
myddes of ye chanel, &amp; amyd ye chanel,
ye ſhal finde viii. or .ix. fadoms &amp; hard
aborde, ye nedles is .iii. or .iiii. fadomes
               If ye wyll lye at ſaynt Heleyns, caſt
anker at .vii. or .viii. fadoms &amp; beware
the poynt that 
                     〈◊〉
                   hee lytle without.
               If ye wyl lye without ſaynt Helens
take the floode, &amp; go ſouth ſoutheaſt, ſo
farforth 
                     〈…〉
                  .
               ¶If ye wyl lye at. 
                     〈◊〉
                   go to the

ſorde and caſt anker at .viii. fadomes
and ye ſhall haue laduange of weſte
ſouthweſt, in the myddle of Bewchey:
*If ye wyl enter into the chambre of
weynchelſe, take halfe flode vnder you
and ſe that bewchey be northe of you
without Fayrle and goo by the ſhore
and ye ſhall goo alonge by it, and beware
of the poynte that lyeth a lytle
without.
               ¶If ye wyl lye at anker by Romney
lye before a ſmall vyllage that ye ſhal
ſe, and caſt anker at .viii. or .x. fadoms
For. at .vi. ye ſhall haue landuange of
ſouthweſt and rockye botome, and at
x. fadomes ye ſhal haue no landuange
of ſouthweſt. And at the anker ynge of
Romney is a banke wel halfe A quarter
of a lyege fro the Dun
                     •
                  onneſſe, and
there is ofte depthe betwene the banke
and the Dunionneſſe harde abord the
banke .xvi. fadomes. And the banke, &amp;
the poynt of Romney lye eaſt northeſt,
and weſte ſouthweſt and there remayneth

at the ebbe of a hye floode but one
fadome of water ouer that banke, and
ye ſhal fynde good harborow fro Romney
to the Dounes al alonge the ſame
coſt at .xvi. or .xx. fadom, and ſhal haue
landuange of the weſt ſouthweſt.
               ¶If yt ye wyl lye before ſaynt Margaretes,
caſte anker at .xvi. fadomes, &amp;
ye ſhall haue landuang of the ſoutheſt
*If ye wyll lye in the downes caſte
anker at .vi. or .vii. fadomes.
               Howe the portes and hauens of England,
brytay and Normandye do lye
&amp; how many leiges fro one to another
               Fourney and Vſſhant do ly eaſt, and
weſt; and betwene theym there is two
leyges.
               Vſſhant and Sylley do ly northeaſt
and ſoutheaſt, apoint of the north, and
apoynte of the ſouthe, and there is bytwene
them .xx v in leynges.
               *Fourne and Long ſhypes lie 
                     ••
                  orth

eaſt, and ſouth ſouthest. And there is
bytwene them .xxvii. leyges.
               *Fourne and Darthmouth ly north
northeſt, &amp; ſouth ſouthweſt, and there
is betwene the
                     •
                   .xxxviii. leyges.
               Fourne &amp; dodman lye north &amp; ſouth
&amp; there is betwene them .xxxiii. leyges
               The yle of Baſepole, and Garneſey
lye northeaſt and ſouthweſt.
               Melenen
                     •
                   &amp; Bodeſtour or the ſtarte
lye northe and ſouthe, and there is bytwene
them .xxviii. leyges.
               Garneſey, &amp; Dodmā lye eaſt &amp; ſouth
eaſt, and weſt northweſt, and there is
betweene them .xxxviii. leyges.
               *The Caſkets and Portlande do ly
north; and ſouth, apoynt of northweſte
and a poynt of ſoutheaſt, and betwene
them is .xx. leyges.
               *Portlande: and Barflete lye northeweſt,
and ſoutheaſt, and betwene them
is .xxviii. leyges.
               ¶Sainte Heleynes, and the Cule of
Haglie northeaſt, and ſouthweſt. And

betwene them there is .xxiii. leyges.
*Saynt Heleyne &amp; barflete lye north
&amp; ſouth, &amp; betwene thē is .xxiiii. leiges.
*Saynt Heleyne &amp; ſhef of Caus lye
northweſt, and ſoutheaſt, and betwene
them .xxviii. leyges.
               *Bewchey, &amp; Barflete lye northeaſt,
and ſouthweſt.
               *The poynt of Romney, and Dyepe
lye north, &amp; ſouth, apoint of northweſt
and a poynt of ſoutheaſt. And Bitwen
them is .xxvi. leyges.
               *Soundynges that ye ſhall fynde
comyng fro ſpayne, Leuaunt, or Portyngale
to ſeke Vſſhant.
               A Ship that cometh from Portingale
ta ſeke vſſhant or Lizard in
this route at, c. or. lxxxx. fadomes
and ye ſhal fynde byg ſounding, &amp; ſhal
be nygh aboute to the 
                     •
                  ayntes. And
in this 
                     •
                  onte at. lxxx. fadomes ye ſhall
fynde cockle ſhelles and dyntes in the
leed. In this route holde on the north
tyl ye chaung ſoundyng.
               
                  
If ye be at. lx. or. lxv. fadomes ye ſhall
fynde ſmall ſande, &amp; mathey grount &amp;
ye ſhalbe at the coſt of Vſſhant.
               And yf ye haue tyme &amp; day, go ſeke it,
in the northeaſt, and ye ſhalbe aboute
x. leyges of the yle.
               If ye come makyng your Rout about
the Bas frede ye ſhall fynd courſe
ſande reed and browne, ye ſhal finde
ſoundynge of .xl. fadomes.
               And yf ye be towarde the banke of
Sylley ye ſhall haue. lxxxvi. or. lxxxx.
fadomes, and ye ſhall fynde in the leed
ſtony ground, &amp; ye ſhall make a great
way towarde the banke of Sylley.
               ☞When ye be at. lxxx. fadom ye ſhal
fynde ſmall blacke ſande, and ye ſhall
be at the towarde of Lezarde.
               When ye be at. lx. or. lxv. ye ſhal fynd
whyte ſande, and whyte ſofte wormes
And ye ſhall be very nygh to Lezarde.
               Bytwene the cape of Cornewayle &amp;
Vſſhant amyd ye chonel ye ſhal fynde.
lxx. fadome, &amp; nere ynough the ſhore.
               
                  
Betwene Dodman, and Fourne in
the chanell ye ſhall fynde lx. fadomes.
               When ye be thwarte of Plōmouth
or the Starte ye ſhall fynde ſtreymye
ground, and dyntes in the 
                     •
                  alowe, and
ſoundinge of .xli. or .xlii. fadomes.
               ¶At the cōmyng fro Portlād ye ſhal
haue .xxxv. fadomes, and ſmal ſhingle
               And yf ye be nyghe Portlande ye
ſhall fynde .xxx. fadomes, and ſtones
lyke beanes. And this ſoūde laſteth to
ſaynt Aldam and in the ſayde ſoūding
ye ſhall fynde whyte ſtoones lyke broken
aules, and other be grater.
and then ye ſhalbe warte of ſaynt Aldam
or of the yle of wyght. And from
thenſe go eaſt warde fro the ſwyngles
               Two leyges or thre from the yle of
wyght ye ſhal fynd .xxv. fadome, wyth
dyntes and clyftes in the talowe lyke
ſmall threde
               Two or thre leyges frō the caſkets
ye ſhall fynde .xl. fadomes, and bygge
ſtones, rugged, and blacke.
               
                  
Bytwene the yle of wyght and ſhe
Hagge the depeſt is but .xxxv. or .xl. fadomes.
               Betwene the yle of wyght and La
                     •
                  
                  trygat
the depeſt is but .xxv. or .xxx. fadome
               Betwene Bechey, and the yle of
wyght at leyge from the lande ye ſhall
fynde .xxxviii. Fadomes and popples
bygge as beanes.
               Bytwene fayrle, and ſomme in the
depeſt but .xxv. fadomes.
               Bytwene fylſtone, and Boloyne is
a banlie that is called Ryppe rappe, &amp;
is in the myddes of the route as nygh
Pycardye as Englande, and harde aborde
by it is .xxvi. or .xxvii. fadomes.
               Beneth the Caſtell of Douer ye ſhal
fynde .x. fadomes.
               In the ſtrayte of Calays ye ſhall
fynde .xxx. fadomes.
               Betwene Calays and Thenet, ye ſhal
fynde .xxv. fadome.
               In the rode of Calays is .xvi. fadome
               
                  
In the coſte of Flaundres at the
depeſt ye ſhall fynde but .xx. fadome.
            
            
               The kennynges from Sylley, and
England vnto Flaundres.
               ¶From Sylley to Longſhyp 
                     〈◊〉
                   is a
kennynge.
               Fro Longſhips to Lezarde viii. leiges
               Fro Lezarde to Dodmā a kennynge.
               Fro Dodman to Rams heade there is
a kennynge.
               Fro Rainshed to the Cape of Beures
there is a kennynge.
               Fro cape of Beures to Torres there
is a kennynge.
               Fro Torres to Portlande .xiiii. leyges
               Fro Portland to ſ. Aldam .iiii. leyges
               Fro Saynte Aldam to the nedles.
vi. leyges.
               Fro Nedles to Saynte Helyns .vi.
leyges.
               Fro Saynt Heleyns to Bewechey
xviii. leyges.
               Fro Bewchey to fayrle .vii. leyges.
               From fayrle to Romney.
               
                  
Fro Romney to douer .vii. leyges.
               Fro Douer to Calays .vii. leyges.
               Fro Calais to Sluce .xxi leyges.
               ¶Floodes &amp; Ebbes, fro the foreland
or Cape of cornwayle, into wales all a
longe by the ſee cooſt.
               At the Cape of Cornwayle the
moone in the eaſt northeaſt ful ſee,
and in the ſouth weſte lowe water.
               At Paſtowe the moone in the eaſt
and apoint of northeaſte full ſee.
               At Londaye the moone in the eaſt ful
ſee, and in the ſouth lowe water.
               At Caldaie the moone in the eaſte, and
apoint of the ſoutheaſt lowe water.
               Ad Graſhormes the moone ī the eaſte
ſouth eaſt full ſee.
               In the Rams eyes, at ye poynt of kardygan
the mon in the ſoutheaſt ful ſee
               At mylfort the moone in the eaſt ſouth
eaſt full ſee.
               At the yle of Fer at ye ile of Colompes,
and at Naſkingeoles the moone in the
eaſt ſoutheaſt full ſee.
               
                  
¶In the route of the yle of Mag
                     ••
                  
                  ſykes
in the mountaynes of Gaſwaye
ye moone in the ſouth ſoutheaſt ful ſee.
And in all the rout of the yle of Man
and vnto arglas, and ſo forth into
Scotland the moone in the ſouth.
               *Routes for Sylley and Englande
into wales alonge the cooſt of wales.
               SIlley, and Lōdey lye northeaſt
and ſouthweſt &amp; betwene them
is .xxviii. leyges.
               The Cape of cornwayle, and Londay
lye northeaſt, &amp; ſouthweſt, a point
of north and a poynt of ſouth, and betwene
them is .xxv. leyges.
               Londay and Calday lye north and
ſouth, and bytwene them is .x. leyges.
               Cape of Cornwayle, and Conſquere
lye north and ſouth, a poynt of northweſte
and apoynt of ſoutheaſt, and betwene
them is xxxiii leyges.
               Cape of Cornewayle and Maſkin
geoles lye north and ſauth, &amp; bytwne
them is .xxxiii. leyges.
               
                  
Maſkyn geoles and Graſhormes ly
eaſt northeaſt and weſt ſouthweſt, and
betwene them is. two. leyges.
               The yle of Fer, &amp; Mylforde lye eaſt
&amp; weſt, a poynt of northeaſt &amp; a peynte
of ſouthweſt and betwene thē is .ii. leig
¶Courſes fro the cape of cornewayle
into wales alonge by the ſee coſt
               From the cape of cornwayle the flod
commeth fro the ſouth, and ye ebbe fro
the north, and wythoute at two or thre
leyges the tyde cometh from the ſouth
weſt. ¶And fro the cape of
cornwayle to Londay the ebbe cōmeth
fro northeaſt, &amp; the flode fro ſouthweſt
&amp; without Londay the flood commeth
fro the weſt, and the ebbe commeth fro
the eaſt. Betwene Lōday and Calday
the floode cōmeth fro the eaſt northeaſt
and the ebbe fro the eaſt ſutheaſt.
               Fro calday to, Scalmay the flod commeth
frō northeaſt, and the ebbe ſouth
weſt.
               Bytwene Scalmay and graſhormes

the floode commeth fro the ſouth, and
the ebbe fro the north.
               And fro graſholmes all the coſt vnto
Hol
                     •
                  heed the flod cometh from the
ſo
                     •
                  th, and the ebbe agaynewarde, and
wythout in the rout it taketh of the
northeaſt and of the ſouthweaſt.
               Fro Holyheed to the yle of Man the
flode cōmeth fro ſoutweſt and the ebbe
cōmeth fro northeaſt, &amp; alōge the yle of
Man vnto without, the flowe cōmeth
fro ſouthweſt, and the ebbe northeaſte
               Bytwene the yle of man and Scotland
the flowe commeth fro the eaſt.
               Bytwene the coſtes of Scotlande,
and the mountaynes of Galwaye the
floode cōmeth fro the eaſt northeaſt, &amp;
the ebbe fro the weſt ſouthweſt.
               And fro the moūtaynes of Galway
to the peynt of Lokeſtene cōmeth the
floode fro north northweſt, &amp; the Ebbe
contrary, fro the poynt to tarke it commeth
ſouth ſoutweſt, and the ebbe cō
                  trary.
            
            
               
               *Routes fro Sylley, and Englande
vnto Ireland a long
the coſte.
               SYlley and c
                     •
                  pe of Clare lye Eaſt
ſoutheaſt and weſt northweſt &amp;
bytwene them is L. leiges.
               ☞Cape of Cornwayle and the Cape
of Veyll lye northweſt and ſoutheaſt,
and a poynt of eaſt, &amp; a poynt of weſt,
and bytwene them is .xxiiil. leyges.
               Cape of Veyll and the cape of clare lye
caſt northeaſt, and weſt ſouthweſt, and
bytwene them is .xiiii. leyges.
               Cape of Clare, and ye Muſenes lye
eaſt and weſt, &amp; bytwene ye is .vii. leyge
Muſenes and Dulfay lye eaſt ſoutheaſt
and weſt northweſte and betwene
them. is .vii. leyges.
               Dulfay and the ſonde of Blaſkaye
lye North &amp; ſouth &amp; a point of northweſt
&amp; ſoutheaſt, take hede of ye ne
                     ••
                  les
bytwene them is .xvii leyges.
               *Blaſkaye and thy yles of Darē lye

                     •
                  orth northeaſt, and ſouth ſouthweſt.

and bytwene them is .xviii, leges.
               Blaſkaey &amp; blakrocke lye north, &amp;
ſouth, &amp; bytwene them is, xl, leyges,
               And from Blakrocke ſayle north, &amp;
ye ſhall go out of Irelande.
               Bytwene blakrocke and cantere is,
vi. kennynges,
               Courſes from the cape Veyll vnto
cantere, and how the fo
                     •
                  ldes towarde
Ireland to 
                     •
                  ere.
               Frome cope of Veyll vnto the yles of
wiltay the floode commeth from ſouthweſt
and taketh of the eaſt and without
in the ſouth commeth the flood fro
the weſt ſouthweſte &amp; the ebbe fro the
eaſt northeaſt.
               Betwene Saltaye, and Vkelo the
floode commeth out of the ſouth ſouth
weſt, and the ebbe agayne warde
               Bytwene Vkelo and Lambaye the
flood commeth from the north and the
ebbe from the ſouth.
               And fro the yle of Lambay along
the coſte the flode cometh fro the ſouth

ſoutheaſt, and the ebbe agaynwarde.
fro Malynes to the poynte of Arglas
the floode cometh fro the ſouth ſouthweſt
and the ebbe agaynwarde.
               Fro the poynt of Arglas to Cantere
cometh the floode fro north, northeaſt,
and the ebbe fro ſouth ſoutheaſt.
            
            
               ☞Routtes fro the 
                     •
                  oy of Bayone
along the coſt of Gaſgoyn vnto
the race of Spayne.
               HE that wyl ſayle fro the baye of
Bayone alonge by the coſt into
gyrone, ſayle northward and by
northweſt for to double Alcaſſone, thē
go north, &amp; by the northeaſt, &amp; ye ſhall
go in the Aſues or pole head, to ye way
of Anthyoche go on the northweſt, the
way of Anthyoch lieth weſt ſouthweſt
and eaſt northeaſt, If ye departe from
ſaynt Martyn your ryght courſe is to
go by Bretons way in the weſt northweſt,
and ye ſhall goo out of the yle of
Eus.
               The way of Brytons lyeth eaſte,

ſoutheaſt, and weſt northweſt.
               The yle of Eus &amp; Bel yle lye northweſt
and ſoutheaſt. And fro Byl yle to
glenam goo weſt northweſt, to double
the rockes of glenam, and ye ſhall goo
ferre ynough fro Penwarke.
               Groye and glenam lye eaſt and weſte,
a poynt of northweſt and ſoutheaſt.
               If ye wyll ſayle wythoute whyte
Rocke take mooſte of the weſte, and to
beware of ye white rocke take ſure markes
beyonde ſaynt Nycolas wythout
Penfrede and then fere not. And whē
yo are in glenā leue the two partes towarde
the yle of muttō, ye thyrde parte
toward Glenam, and go weſt by ſhore
The yle of Mutton, &amp; ſaynt Nicolas
lye north and ſouth.
               ☞The route of glenam lyth eaſt, and
weſt Depart from the rout of glenam,
and fayle weſt, and nortweſt, and ye
ſhal come before ſaynt Tudy.
               ☞And wha that parteth fro the route
of Glenam, and wil double P
                     •
                  marke.

his courſe is weſte, &amp; by ſouthweſt, for
the route of Glenam, an the fourke lyeaſt
and weſt.
               Penbroke, and fountenance lye,
northweſt and ſoutheaſt.
            
            
               The kenynges fro rochell into.
Flaunders.
               Fro la Palace to Bylyuers is .vii,
leyges.
               Fre Bylyuers to Holonue is .vii.
leyges, Frome holonue to the yle of
Eus is .vii. leyges.
               
                  Betwene thy yle Eus and Bell yle is,
xx. leyges.
                  Fro bell yle to Groye vii. leyges
                  Fro Groye to Glenam vii. leyges
                  Fro Glenā to pēmarke vii. leyges
                  Fro pēmarke to the Race, ix. leiges
                  Fro the Race to. S. Math .ix. leyges
                  Fro S. Mathew to fourne vii. leiges
                  Fro ſouthe to Bergroagh, vii. leyges
                  Bytwene Bargroagh and the yle of
Baſepole is .xiiii leyges.
                  Bytwene the yle of Baſepole, and the

vii, yles is vii, leiges.
                  Betwene the vii. yles and Brehac .vii.
leyges.
                  Betwene Brehac and Freel x. leyges
                  Bytwene freel and ſaynte Malo, iiii.
leyges.
                  Fro ſaynt malo to Chauſe vi. leyges
                  Fro Cauſe to Iarſey vii. leyges
                  Fro Iarſey to Hagge viii. leyges
                  From the Hagge to the yle of wyghte
xxviii. leyges.
                  Fro ye yle of wyght to Calas .xlij. leyg
                  Betwene Calais &amp; S. luce xxi. leiges
               
               Theſe are the. Soundynges cōminge
fro ſpayne on the outwarde pa
                     •
                  tes to
the yles north warde, &amp; abau
                     •
                   Rochel.
               IN this ſaylynge at. l. fadomes
ye ſhal be, xvii. leyges fro and
❧If ye be at .xl. fadome ye
ſhall be at, vii, leyges fro land.
               *And yf ye be at, xxx, fadoms ye ſhal
be at .vii. leyges. fro lande.
               If ye be at, xxii. fadoms ye ſhall 
                     〈◊〉
                  
at, iiii, leyges fro lande.
               
                  
In this route ye ſhall fynde Oſe. &amp;
ye ſhall be towarde Maumuſſon, and
nyghe the lande, &amp; ye ſhal fynd ſtones
lyke peaſon, &amp; then ye ſhall be towarde
Balyuers or toward Hol
                     •
                  nne, but go
no nighe excepte it be thy daye in this
ſoundyng of .xv. fadomes of water.
               If ye be ſouth at of the yle of Eus at
lx. fadomes ye ſhall fynde ſmall ſande
and be .xiiii. leyges fro land.
               If ye be at. l. fadomes, ye ſhal be at
x. leyges fro land.
               At .xxx. fadomes ye ſhall ſee the yle
clerely.
               If ye be in the ſee of Layre at .xl. fadome
is Oſe, tyl ye be at .xxv. fadome.
               ¶At ye ſouth of Bellye at .xl. fadome
ye ſhal be at .x. leyges of it, &amp; come not
nerer then. l. or .xl fadome but by day.
For in the rout of Bellye, and glenam
at. l. fadome ye ſhal be nygh the lande
And take good hede, for there be falſe
ſoundynges in the thwart of glenam.
and Penmarke.
            
            
               
               ☞How the land of Brytayne and of
Spayne do lye and how many
leyges is frome one to
a
                     •
                  other.
               BAſefrede and caplye north northeaſt
and ſouth ſoutheweſt pellem
Penmarke and Syſſerges lye
northeaſt &amp; ſouthweſt apoynt of ſouth,
a poynt of north, and bytwene them is
xvi, kennynges,
               Glenain and ſaynt Vyncent de laberker
lye north &amp; ſouth, and bytwene
them is. lxxxv, leyges.
               Groye &amp; ſaynt Andrew lye north &amp;
ſouth betwene them is, lxxxv, leyges.
               Bel yle, &amp; lar
                     •
                  don lye north &amp; ſouth
and betwene them is, lxviii, leyges,
               The yle of Eus &amp; Martrychaco lye
north &amp; ſouth bitwene thē is, in. leiges.
               Holonne &amp; ſaynt Sebaſtyā lye north
and ſouth.
               Theſe leyges be fro the buckewe of
Gyronde to the buckewe of bayone along
the coſt of, Spayne, &amp; portyngale
               
                  
                  THere is betwene the Buckew
of Gyronde and the Buckewe
of Bayonne xxv. leiges
                  Bytwen Bayonne and fountaraby is
vii. leyges.
                  Bytwene fountaraby and ſaynte Sebaſtyan
is, iiii, leyges.
                  fro, ſ, Sebaſtian to quytayre, iii, leyg,
                  fro quitayre to, Montrygo .iii, leiges,
                  fro Montrygo to Vermio v. leyges
                  fro Vermio to Bylbame vi, leyges
                  fro bylbawe to Caſtres iii, leyges,
                  fro Caſtres to the Rade iii, leyges,
                  fro the Rade to S. Andrew vi. leyges
                  fro ſaynt Andrewe to ſaynt Vyncent,
dela bekete .v, leyges
                  fro ſaynt Vyncēt to Lagues v, leiges
                  fro lagues to Rybdecell v, leyges
                  fro Rybdecel to vyll vicious v. leyges
                  fro vicyous to Gynnon iiii. leyges
                  fro gynnō to pēnes de gōſen ii, leyges
                  fro Gonſon to veylles ii, leyges
                  fro veylles to pronne ii, leyges
                  fro pron to Lyenarke, ix, leyges
                  
                     
fro Lyenarke to Rybaydue v. leyges
                  fro Rybaydue to ſ. fabyan v. leyges
                  fro ſ. fabyan to Vmero ii. leyges
                  fro Vmero to cap de Vere ii. leyges
                  fro cap de Vere to Ortiguer ii. leyges
                  fro Ortiguer to Sydera .iii. leyges
                  fro Sidera to cap de prieui .iiii. leyges
                  fro cap de pryenl to colome .iii. leyges
                  fro Colome to Siſſergues v. leyges
                  fro Siſſergues to cormes iii. leiges
                  fro cormes to Mongye v. leyges
                  fro mongye to ye cap of feuyſter there
is .iiii. leyges
                  fro the Cap fenyſtre to cea v. leyges
                  fro Cea to Mores v. leyges
                  fro mores to bayōe de moror viii. leigs
                  fro Bayone to camino iiii. leyges
                  fro comino to Vyenne iiii. leyges
                  fro Vyenne to Vyll de count .v. leiges
                  fro Vyl decount to Porto in Portyugale
is .iiii. leyges
                  fro Porta de vere de Mōdego .ix. leyg.
                  fro Mondēgo to paradeū .ix. leyges
                  fro Parades to barlynges ix. leyges
                  
                     
fro Berlyngues to rocke de Semper
there is .xii. leyges.
                  fro Semper to Cap de fycher .x. leygs
                  fro fycher to Cap. ſ. Vyncēt .xxviii. ley
                  Bytwene cap. ſ. Vincēt and cap ſaynt
Maryis .xviii. leyge
                  Bitwene the cap of ſaynt Mary &amp; the
abbeye of Dolues is .xvii leyges
                  Bytwene the Abbaye of Dolues, and
ſaynt Lucas de bemeredo is .viii. ley.
               
               ¶Routes fro Pontewe de Feron vnto
the flome Iordā and how many leyges
is bytwene them.
               POntewe de feron and the yle of
cales lye eaſt and weſte, and bytwene
them is .xx. leyges.
               The yle of Cales and Trefaldogar
lye eaſt ſoutheaſt, and weſt ſouthweſte
and betwene them is .viii. leyges.
               Trefalga
                     •
                   &amp; the ſtraytes of marock
lye eaſt &amp; weſt, apoynt of ſoutheaſt &amp; of
northweſt, &amp; bytwene them is .xii. leyg
               The ſtraytes of Marock and cap of
Gad lye eaſt and weſt, a point of north

eaſt, and of ſouthweſt, bytwene them.
lxv. leyges.
               Cap de gat and the formynges lye
northeſt, and ſouthweſt, and bytwene
them is. lx. leyges.
               The formynges &amp; Mayerke lye north
eaſt, &amp; ſouthweſt, bitwene thē .xxx. legs
               The yle of Mayerke conteyneth in
length .xxviii. leyges.
               Mayerke and Sardayn lye eaſte &amp;
weſt, &amp; bytwene thew is. lxxxx leyges.
*Sardayn &amp; Fozyl lye eaſt and weſt
and a poynt of Southeaſt, a poynt of
northweſt, bytwene them is .xxii. legs.
The yle of fozyl in lenght is. lxii. leigs
               The yle of cecyll, and the yle of ſapyence
lye eaſt, and weſt betwne them is.
ii. leyges.
               The yle of Sapience and the yle of
Candrye lye eaſt and weſt, a poynt of
ſoutheaſt and a poynt of northweſt, betwene
them is. lxii. leyges.
               Candre in length is. lii. leyges.
               The yle of Candre, and the yle of Famagos

lye eaſt, &amp; weſt betwene them.
cxv. leyges. The yle of Famagos in
length. c leyges. Famagos and capde
Danaco lye eaſt &amp; weſt. Cap dedinaco
and Flo
                     •
                  e Iordā lye north and ſouth
and betwene them is lxxxx leyges.
            
         
         
            *Thus endeth the Rutter of the ſee
and here foloweth, the courſes
of the moone, and iudgementes,
of the yle of
Auleron.
            
               TO reken the Courſes of ye moone
truly, it behoueth to take for euerie,
quarter of the moone .xxxii
houres and a half. For two quarters.
xlv. houres. For the quarters. lxviii.
houres and a halfe.
               For foure quarters. lxxxx. houres.
               *Note one cours before the ſon in the
ſouth the moone in the eaſt.
               For fyue quarters. c .xii. houres, and
a halfe.
               For .vi. quarters .cxxxv. houres.
               For .vii. quarters. c .lvii. houres, and a

halfe.
               Fro .viii. quarters. c .lxxx houres.
               ¶Two courſe before the ſonne in the
weſt the moone in the ſouth.
               For .ix. quarters. cc .ii. houres.
               Fro xi. quarters. cc .xlvii. houres.
               for .xi. quarters .xlvii. houres.
               for .xii. quarters. cc .lxx. houres.
               *The courſe before the ſonne in the
weſt, the moone in the ſouth
               For .xiii. quarters. cc .lxxxxii. houres.
and a halfe.
               for .xiiii. quarters. ccc .xv. houres.
               for .xv. quarters. ccc .xxxviii. houres &amp;
a halfe.
            
            
               ¶Another courſe before the ſonne in
the ſouth the moone in the north and
ſo of other. Note it well and ſhal
fynde .vii .c .xx. houres.
               HE that wyl rekē the moone well
by the dayes, oughte to take for
euery quarter of the moone thre
quarters and halfe a quarter of a daye
and an houre and an halfe.
               
                  
And for two quarters there is a day &amp;
thre quarters, an halfe a quarter of a
daye. For thre quarters there is two
dayes, thre quarters, an houre and an
halfe. For .iiii. quarters is thre dayes,
and thre quarters of a day.
            
            
               ¶One courſe before.
               
                  ❧And for .v. quarters there is foure
dayes and a halfe foure houres and a
halfe. For vi. quarters is v. dayes, and
an halfe, and halfe a quarter.
               For .vii. quarters there is .vi. dayes, &amp;
a halfe. an houre and a halfe.
               For .viii. quarters there is .vii. dayes,
and a halfe.
            
            
               ¶Two courſe before.
               ¶For .ix. quarters .viii. dayes &amp; halfe
a quarter, an houre and a halfe.
               Fo .x. quarters .ix. dayes, and .ix. houres
and a halfe.
               For .xi. quarters .x. dayes .vii. houres
and a halfe.
               For .xii. qaurters .xi. dayes and a quarter
of a daye.
            
            
               
               ¶Thre courſe before.
               ¶For .xiii. quarters .xii. dayes foure
houres and a halfe.
               For .xiiii. quarters .xiii. daies and half
a quarter of a daye.
               For xv. quarters .xiiii. dayes, an houre
and a half.
               For .xvi. quarters .xv. dayes &amp; nomore
               ¶Thus ye ſhal fynde but .xxx. dayes
in euery moone.
            
            
               *Note this well.
               *At .xviii. dayes and .xviii. houres of
the Moone, the Sonne in the ſouth,
what ſhall ye tyde be at glenā. Anſwere
It ſhalbe lowe water, and the moone
ſhall be in the north and ye ſhal haue
thre wyndes bitwene the Moone, and
the ſonne.
            
         
         
            *Theſe be the cuſtomes of the
Vicoūtyes of Brytayne.
            ALſhyppes or other veſſelles when
they go to wracke by aduenture on the
cooſtes of Brytaine be as yf they were

wonne to the ſayde Vicount ſo that no
marchaūt nor other ſhal take nothing
but they that ſaueth thē which oughte
to be rewarded after theyr deſeruyng.
That is to wytte, yf they goo at auenture
of the ſee to fetche them ferre they
haue the thyrd part. And if they take it
on ſhore they ſhall haue but a cōpetent
rewarde, as iuſtyce requyreth.
            And bycauſe the countrey of Brytaine
is ſo ꝑeryllleous that, ſcantly a ſhip cā
ſayle thyther the ſpare of .ii. yeres with
outcommynge in daūger of the ſayde
fordſhip. Therfore it was accorded bytwene
the ſayde Duke and all maner
of ſhyppes, by the aſſente of the Kynge
of fraunce, at the prayer, requeſt, &amp; ſupplycacyon
of all the countrey, that the
ſayde erle ſhuld giue ſeales the whiche
bene called bryfes to whome he would
in his grounde, and ſo where holdē all
the ſhyppes that laded in the duchy of
Brytayne vnto the realme of Spayne
to take the ſayd bref
                  •
               s on payue to leſe

the ſayd ſhyp and the goodes.
            ¶It was a greed therefore amonge
theym that what ſhippe that auētured
into this ſayde ground, &amp; fyndenge the
brefes in wytneſſes of the regiſtres of
the places where they doo lye that the
ſayde Lordſhyp ought not to take nor
ſuffre to take any of the goodes that is
in it, nor of the wares that is ſaued, ſauyng
the ryght of the ſauers yt was agreed
bycauſe thy laboure to ſaue the
goodes, &amp; by theſe couenauntes of brefes,
al maner of ſhyps &amp; marchaū
               
                  •
               yſe
bē aſſured of ryght &amp; nobleſſe of ye ſayd
prynce, &amp; they ought to ſhewe to the admyrall
or his lieftenaūte ye brefes of al
the vyages that they haue made in a
hole yere, at al tymes yt he wyl requyre
thē or elſe he maye holde thē as for fayt
&amp; bycauſe yt the kynge of Spayne nor
his portes, nor Englyſhe mē were not
at his agrement to ſayle vnder ye fyrſte
condycyon, in caſe yt they come laded or
voyde from theyr coūtreyes, yf they by

charged where the bryfes be they muſt
take of them. for yf they be without thē
they be at the prynces pleaſure bodye
and goodes.
            THe ordinaunces wherfore the vycount
of Leon is acuſtomed to ye
ſeales called ſeales of cōducte and not
brefes was becauſe the ſayd Vycoūte
was at the paſſage there as it behoued
al veſſels to aſſemble, laden or empty,
to thēde that none ſhould miſdo other
bycauſe thei were of ſtraūge coūtres it
was agreed yt he ſhuld kepe veſſelles to
ſaue &amp; cōducte them toward theyr landes
frō the ſayd harborowe, &amp; to ſuffer
that all maner of people myghte take
vitailes on his foreſaid groūd, it was
accorded therfore that he ſhuld haue a
certayne ſomme for the ſeales. And in
caſe yt any ſhip paſſed forth without takyng
vytayle on his ſaid grounde not
hauing the ſayd ſeales, to be forfayt in
body &amp; goodes. And ye ſaid vicoūt may

folowe then what parte ſoeuer they go
and leade them wyth hym as thynges
forfayted to iuſtyfie in his ſaid ground
and they beholden to ſhewe all the ſeales
of vyages that they haue made for
yeares, &amp; by thys the ſayde Vycoūt is
holden to kepe the ſayd veſſels in peace
within this ſayd ground to hyr power
And this is his ryght wyth the mynde
of many Syth the Lordes of Brytain
haue conquered the ſayd Vycount, and
theſe be the two nobleſſes of the prince.
And ſyth the ſayde nobleſſes were hole
to hym hath wylled that the Spanyerdes
and other that they maye take harborowe
in his ground without aduenture
charged or to be fraught fro ſtraunge
landes, yt where the brefes ſhould
be ſaufe to them to demaunde the ſayd
brefes wyth in the thyrd tyde after that
they haue caſt yt anker, on lande in the
hauen to reſt, or els to fetche thē, what
parte ſoeuer they be, in caſe that they
ſhoulde not haue paſſed by the race of

ſaynte Mathewe, but yf they do not
paſſe, they ſhall not be ſaued by ſuche
wyll and maner.
         
         
            ☞Here begynneth the iudgementes
of the See, of ſhyppes, of mayſters
of maryners, of marchauntes,
and of al
theyr doynges.
            
               FYrſt one mā is made mayſter of
the ſhip and the ſhip belongeth to
many parteners &amp; departeth frō
the coūtey of whence it is, and cōmeth
to London or o another place, and is
fraught to go into a ſtraunge coūtrey
the mayſter ought not to ſell the ſhyp
without he haue a procuracyon or lycence
of the owners. But yf he haue
nede of money for the expenſes of the
ſhyppe, he maye laye to guage ſome of
the take lynges, by the counſell of the
maryners of the ſhyppe.
            
            
               This is the iudgement.
               
                  
A Shyp lienge in a hauen, and
taryeth for ye freyght &amp; tyme to
departe, the mayſter ought take counſell
wyth his felowes, and ſaie, mates
howe lyke ye this wether, Some wyll
ſaye it is not good, let it ouer paſſe.
               Other wyll ſaye the wether is good &amp;
fayre. The mayſter ought to agre to ye
mooſte, or els yf the ſhyp peryſhe he is
boūde to reſtore the value as it is prayſed,
yf he haue wher with.
            
            
               This is the iudgement.
               IF a ſhyp pereyſh in any place the
maryners ought to ſaue the moſt
parte of the goodes in the ſhyp &amp;
in ſo doyng the mayſter ought to gyue
them theyr coſtes reaſonable to good to
lande, yf they haue ſaued ſo much that
the mayſter may do it. And the maiſter
may lay to bledge of the ſaued goodes
to ſome honeſt man for them. And if he
can not helpe them ſo he is not boūde
to rewarde them, but they to loſe theyr

rewardes whē the ſhyp is loſt. And the
mayſter maye ſell no takelynge of the
ſhyp but yf he haue procuracyon or lycence
of the owners. But he ought to
put them in ſaufgarde to the tyme yt he
do'th knowe the wyll of the owners, &amp;
he ought to do it the mooſt truely that
be can, &amp; yf he do otherwiſe he is holdē
to make amēdes if he haue wherwith.
            
            
               This is the iudgement.
               ALſo yf a ſhyp departe fro Burdewes
or another place laden, it
chaunceth ſomtyme that it wracketh
and the moſte parte of the goodes that
may be his ſaued, the marchaūtes &amp; ye
mayſter be at greate ſtryfe, &amp; the marchaūtes
aſke their goodes of ye maſter
They ought well to haue thē, hauyng
the freyght as yf the ſhyppe had made
the vyage kēnyng, by kēnyng, &amp; cours
by cours, if it pleaſe the mayſter &amp; if ye
mayſter wyll he may amende hys ſhip
yf it be in caſe to be lyghtlye mended, &amp;

yf not he may hyre another ſhyp to fynyſhe
his vyage, and the maſter ſhall
haue his freyght, as yf he had ſaued
the goodes, and the freight of the ſayd
goodes yt be ſaued ought to be rekened
poūde by pounde, &amp; the goode to paye
the parte of the coſtes that were done
in ſauinge of the ſayde goodes, &amp; yf ſo
were that the mayſter &amp; the marchaū
                  tes
do promiſe to tolke that ſhuld help
to ſaue the ſhyp &amp; goodes, to haue the
thyrde part or halfe by thē ſo ſaued for
the peryll yt they be in the iuſtyce of the
coūtrey ought well to regarde what labor
&amp; payne they haue done in the ſauynge
and after that payne (not contē
                  tynge
the promiſſes made by the ſayde
mayſter &amp; maryners) to rewarde them
               YF a ſhyp departe fro any place laden
or not, &amp; aryuethe at another
place the maryners ought not to
go out without lene of the mayſter, for
yf the ſhyp ſhulde peryſhe or hurte by

any aduēture, thei be holdeen to make
amendes. But yf the ſhyppe were in a
place where it were ankered wyth two
or thre Cables they maie well go oute
wythout the mayeſters leue, leauynge
ſome of the maryners to kepe the ſhyp
and goodes, and they to come betyme
to the ſhyp and yf they tary longe they
oughte to make amendes yf they haue
wherwyth.
            
            
               Suche is the iudgement.
               MAriners bynde them wyth theyr
mayſter &amp; anye go out wythout
leaue of the mayſter and drynke dronken
and make noyſe and ſtryfe ſo that
anye of them he hurte, the Maieſter is
not bounde to cauſe them to be healed,
nor to puruey oughte for them, but he
maye well put them oute of the ſhyppe
But yf the maiſter ſende them in anie
erande for the profite of the Shippe,
and that they ſhoulde hurte theym, or
that anye dyd greue them, they oughte
to be healed at the coſtes of the ſhyppe
            
            
               
               This is the iudgement.
               IF it chaunce that any mariner
be taken with ſickenes in ye ſhip
doing ſeruyce therto belōgyng
the Maſter ought to ſet him out of the
ſhyp, and ſeke lodgyuge for hym, and
ought for to fynde hym light, as talow
or candel and gyue to hym a lad of the
ſhyppe for to take hede of hym, or hyre
a woman ſo kepe hym, and oughte to
puruey hym of ſuche meate as is vſed
in the ſhyp that is to wite as muche as
he toke when he was in health and nomore
but yf the mayſter wyl. And if he
wyll haue deyntyer meates, the mayſter
is not bounde to gette him any, but
to be at his toſtes. And yf the ſhyp be
redie to departe it ought not to tary for
hym, and if he recouer to haue his hire
in prayeng and rebatyng that the mayſter
layde out for hym. And if he dye
hys wyfe or nexte kyn or frēde oughte
to haue it for hym.
               
                  
The iudgement, is ſuche.
               ALſo a ſhyp is freyght to go toward
London, or elswhere and yf it do chaū
                  ceth
that tourmēte taketh it beinge on
the ſee, and it can not eſcape but yf the
goodes becauſe out the mayſter ought
to ſaie, mates it behoueth to caſte ouer
theſe goodes to ſaue the ſhyp, &amp; if there
be any marchaūt that wil anſwer and
wyll be contrary of the caſtyng out by
theyr reaſons &amp; wyl not agre, the mayſter
neuertheles oughtnot to leaue but
caſt ouer ſo much as he ſhal ſe nede. He
&amp; the thyr departe of hys felowes makyng
theyr othes on ye holy goſpel whē
they become to the right place of theyr
diſcharge yt he did it for to ſaue the bodi
of the ſhip &amp; the other goods that is yet
in it &amp; ye wynes yt were caſt ouer ought
to be prayſed at the value of them ye be
come ſaufe, &amp; when they ſhall be lo
                     •
                  de
they oughte to be deuyded pounde by
pounde among the ſayd marchauntes
and the mayſter ought to deuyde, and

teken the ſhyppe or thre freyght as his
choyſe and for recouerynge of the domages
the maryners oughte to haue a
tonne fre, and any other ought to haue
parte after hys deſeruynge, and yf he
hath not behaued hym as a good man
to haue nothyng of the franchyſe. And
the marchauntes may charge the mayſter
for it by his othe.
            
            
               This is the iudgement.
               SO maye chaunce that ye mayſter
muſte cutte of his maſt by force
of ye wether, but he ought to cal ye marchauntes
that owe the goodes, yf anye
of them be there and ſaye. The maſte
muſt nedes be cut to ſaue the ſhyp, and
goodes, it were reſonable by trouthe.
And ſomtyme behoueth to cut a ſōder
Cables and leaue the Ankers and rothers
to ſaue Shyppe and goodes all
theſe thynges bene rekened pounde by
pounde. And whē god ſendeth the ſhip
to dyſcharge in ſaufte the marchaūtes

ought to paye eche theyr rate without
delay, or to ſell or guage for money, or
euer the goodes be out of the ſhip. And
yf the ſhyp be at hyrynge, and the mayſter
tarye by reaſon of ther debate and
perceiueth lekage, he ought not to part
with the loſſes but haue his freight as
yf the tones were full.
            
            
               This is the iudgement.
               WHen a ſhyp cōmeth ſaufe to the
ryght dyſcharge ye maſter ſhuld
ſhewe ye marchaūtes the ropes yt
they haue to hoyſe withal. And if they
ſe nede, the mayſter ought to amende
them. For yf the tonne leſe bycauſe of
the hoyſinge or of the ropes the mayſter
and the Ma
                     ••
                  uers amonge theym
muſte paye the marchauntes, and the
maſter ought to pay after as he ought
to take for the vnladyng, and the vnladynge
to be ſet fyrſt to recouer the loſſes,
and the reſydue to be departed amonge
them. But yf the ropes breake

without that the Maiſter ſhewe them
to the marchaūtes they are bounde to
recompence the domage. But yf the
marchauntes ſaye, the ropes be ſure, &amp;
good, if they breake eche of thē ought
to haue parte of the domage, that is to
wite ye marchaunte that oweth yt wine
onely, and the mayſter &amp; the maryner
            
            
               This is the iudgement.
               A Shyp beinge charged at Burdewes
orels wher, &amp; hoyſeth the
ſayſe for to go wyth the wines, &amp;
the mayſter and hys maryners trymmeth
not theyr ſayl as it ſhulde and yl
wetherynge taketh them in the ſee, in
ſuche maner yt the takelynge cruſheth
or ſiniteth out the botome of ye tonne or
pype, the ſhyppe beyng ſaufaryued at
the ryght dyſcharge, the marchauntes
ſayeth to the mayſter, that 
                     •
                  y his take
lynge there wyne is loſt. The mayſter
ſayeth nay, and yf he wyll ſweare, and
thre or four or halfe a doſyn of his maryners

or any of them whiche the marchauntes
wyll that the wyne was not
loſt by theyr defaute nor by thyr takelynge
as the marchaūtes put on them
they ought to be quyt. But yf they wil
not ſwere they be boūde to ordre theyr
ſayle well and truely or they parte fro
theyr charge.
            
            
               This is the iudgement.
               A Mayſter hyreth hys maryners
and ought to kepe them peſably
and oſtre to be theyr Iudge and
yf any ſay yt hys felows lyeth, hauinge
breade and drynke at the table, ought
to paye .iiii. d. And yf anye belyeth the
mayſter to pay .viii. d. Or yf the mayſter
belye any alſo to pay .viii. d. And yf
the maiſter ſmite anye of the mariners
the mariner oughte to abyde the fyrſte
buffet be it with fyſte, or ſtath with his
hande but if he ſmite any more he may
defende hym. And if a maryner ſmite
ye maiſter to pay .v. s. or. to leſe his fyſt.
            
            
               The iudgement is ſuch.
               
                  
ANye ſhyp freyght at burdewes
or any other place &amp; cometh to
his right diſcharge, and be charged
halfe party tonnage and ſmal lodmans
ſeruaūtes ben to the marchauntes.
The cuſtom of Brytayn is all they
that be taken ſteth they paſſe the yle of
Bas, &amp; bepayuz la main. And they of
Normandie and Englande, and flaundres,
ſyeth they paſſe Garneſey, &amp; they
of ſyeth they paſſe Garneſey do not.
            
            
               This is the iudgement.
               IF variaunce fal betwene the mayſter
of a ſhippe, and the mariners
the mayſter oughte to take the torwell
a waye that is afore the mariner
or he put hym out, and if the maryner
offer to make Amendes at the Agrement
of hys mates that be at the table
and the mayſter wyll not but putteth
him oute, the mariner maie folowe the
Shippe till it come to the ryght dyſcharge,
and ought to haue as good wawages

as, yf he had gone in the ſhyp,
amendynge the treſpace at the verdite
of his felowes, And yf ſo be that ye maiſter
take not in as good a maryner as
be, and the ſhyp by chaūce take harme
the mayſter is boūde to reſtore the ſhyp
and the goodes, yf he be able.
            
            
               This is the iudgement.
               IT may ſo be that as a ſhyp lyeth
ankered at rode, another
ſhyp cometh oute of the ſee, and
by myſguiding hitteth againſt the ſhip
that is in the waye, ſo that the ſhyp is
domaged with the ſtrocke that ye other
ſhyp gaue it, and there is wyne ſhedde
on both bartes, the loſſe ought for to be
prayſed and deuyded halfe to halfe bytwene
the ſhyppes and the wines loſte
in the ſayde ſhyppes alſo amonge the
marchauntes, and the mayſter of the
ſhip that hyt the other muſt ſwere on a
booke, and hys marchaūtes wyth him
that he dyd not with is wyll. The reaſon

why this iudgement was made is
that an old ſhyp wyllynglye lyeth not
in the waye of a better ſo ferforth as it
knoweth not to domage it by greuyng
but whē it knoweth well that it muſte
parte byhalfe, it wyl paſſe by out of the
waye.
            
            
               Suche is the iudgement.
               TWo ſhyppes or mo lyenge in A
hauen, at ſcante water, and one
of the ankers lye to nere another
ſhyp, the mayſter of the ſayd ſhyp ought
to ſay. Mayſter take vp your anker
it is to nere vs and maye do vs harme
And if they wyl not remene it, the mayſter
and hys maryners that myght haue
the domage maye take it vp, and ſet
it ferther from them, but yf the other
wyll not ſuffre them, and it do them domage,
the other muſte reſtore it, and yf
ſo be yt they had faſtened to it, no. But
and yf it do hurte they be holde to yelde
the hurte all alonge, &amp; yf they lye drye
in a hauē, thy ought to ſet markes at

theyr ankers that may playnly be fene
aboue the water
            
            
               The iudgement is ſuch.
               IF a ſhippe be ariued to be charged
at Burdews or at any other place
the mayſter is holden to ſay ta his
felowes. Mates wyll ye freyght by
youre ſelfe, or be alowed at the freyght
of the ſhyp. That is to be at theyr own
prouyſyon. They muſte anſwere what
they wyll do, yf they take at ye freyght
of the ſhyp, they ſhall haue as the ſhyp
ſhall haue. And yf they wyl freyght by
them ſelfe they oughte to freyght it in
ſuche wyſe as the ſhyp do not tary.
               And yf it chaunce that they fynde noo
freight the maſter is not to blame, and
oughte to ſhewe theym theyr fare, and
may ſet ye weyght of theyr ſhyp meate
to eche of them, &amp; yf they wyll laye in a
tonne of water they maye▪ for a tonne
of wyne, and yf throwynge ouer into
the ſee happen the ton of water oughte

to be for a tonne of wyne, or for other
goodes, pounde to pounde, wherby the
maryners maye healpe them in the ſee.
And yf ſo be that they freyght it wyth
marchaundeyſe, ſuche fraunchyſe as
the maryner hath ought the marchaūt
to haue.
            
            
               That is the iudgemente.
               THe mariners of Bri
                     •
                  ain ought
to haue but one meale a day, by
reaſon of that they haue drynkes goynge,
and commyng, and they of Normandye
oughte to haue two meales of
the kytchyn on the daye, bycauſe they
haue but water goyng at the ſhyppe coſtes.
And when the ſhyppe is at the
ſhore the maryners to haue wyne to
drynke and other at the fyndyng of the
mayſter. This is the iudgement.
A Shyp cōmeth to dyſcharge, the maryners
will haue theyr fyndynge ſome
there be yt haue neither bedde nor caben
in the ſhyp, the mayſter maye retayne

of theyr hyre fyll the ſhippe be there as
they toke it, yf their put no good ſuerty
to furniſſhe theyr viage.
            
            
               This is the iudgement.
               ALſo the mayſter of a ſhyp hyreth
his maryners in the town that is
of ſome of theyr owne fyndynge,
and other at hys cooſtes. It chaūceth
that the ſhyppe can fynde no feyght
to go where he wold be, and they muſt
go ferther. They that fynde them ſelfe
ought to folowe hym, but they that be
a thys coaſtes he ought to rayſe theyr
wages, kennynges by kennynge, and
courſe by courſe, after the rate of theyr
hyre for to go to a tertayne place. And
yf they go nerre then the place, or well
as ferre as they were hyred to all to be
alowed but they muſte yelde the ſhyp,
where they toke it, and ſet it at the aduenture
of god.
            
            
               This is the iudgement.
               
               WHhen a ſhyp cōmeth to Bryſtow
or any other place Of ſuch meat
as is in the ſhyp, two of the maryners
may beare to ſhore a meaſe or an
halfe meaſe, ſuche as they be cut in the
ſhyp, and ſuch breade as they haue, as
maye eat at one tyme, but no drynke.
And thy oughte to haſte them ſhortly
aborde agayn that the mayſter leſe not
the erneſtes of the ſhyp, for yf the mayſter
haue domage by that loſſe, they be
holden to alowe it. Or yf any of theyr
felowes hurte hym ſelfe for lacke of
helpe, they be holden to heale hym and
to make a fyne at the verdyte of one of
the maryners, and of the mayſter, and
of them of the table.
            
            
               This is the iudgement.
               YF a mayſter freyghte his ſhyppe
to a marchaunt, and ſette a certaine
terme within the which at ye marchaunt
ſhoulde lade, redy to departe, yf
the marchaunt doth it not, but kepe the

the Maiſter and hys maryners by the
ſpace of .xii. or .xv. dayes or more, ſomtyme
he leſeth his wetherynge &amp; tyme
by defaute of the marchaunt, the marchaunt
is holden to make the mayſter
amendes. And of ſuch amendes as the
mayſter hath the maryners ought to
haue the fourth parte, and the mayſter
the other iii. partes, bycauſe he findeth
theyr expences.
            
            
               This is the iudgement.
               CErtain marchauntes or one freighteth
a ſhyp, &amp; ſetteth it in way
The ſayd ſhip entreth into a hauen,
and is there ſoo lōge that money
faileth them. The maiſter ought for to
ſend in haſt into his coūtre for money,
but he ought not to leaſe hys armogā
for yf he do he is boūd to redreſſe al the
domages of ye marchaūts. But he mai
take of the wyne, &amp; of the marchaſites
goodes, &amp; make ſale for his ſtore. And
whē ye ſhyp cōmeth to ye right diſcarge

the wyne that the wayſter hath ſo taken
ought to be prayſed after the rate
as the other ſhalbe ſolde comenly and
neyther more nor leſſe. And the maiſter
ought to haue his freyght of the wyne
that he hath taken.
            
            
               This is the iudgement.
               A Lodeſman vnder taketh to
lade a ſhyp to hulle or to other
places, yf he fayle, &amp; the ſhyp
peryſſhe to the marchaūtes domages
he is bounde to reſtore the domages
yf he haue wherwith. And yf he haue
not wherwith to loſe his heade, and yf
the maſtes or anye of the maryners or
Marchauntes do ſmyte of hys heade
they be not bounde to make amendes,
but they ought fyrſte to knowe before
they do it if it be able ta make a mēdes
            
            
               This is the iudgement.
               TWo veſſels be felowes to take
Herynges or Makerelles, they

ought to laye as many gynnes one as
another. and they be a greed to parte
the gayne by halfe bytwene them, and
yf it chaunce that one of them peryſhe
bothe men, gynnes and other thynges
and the other ſcapeth and cometh ſauf
to ſhore, the frēdes of hym that is ded
aſketh part of the gayne that they haue
made, of the gynnes, hearynge, and
veſſell. They ſhal haue parte &amp; gayne
of the gynnes and hearynge, by the othes
of them that be ſcaped. But of the
veſſell they get nothynge.
            
            
               This is the iudgement.
               
                  A Sippe hoyſſeth vp at the diſcharge
and lyeth dry where ſhe
is ſo iocoud that the Maryners
taketh at the mayne. Maſte, or at the
ſcurtyll before or behynde the mayſter
ought to encreaſe hyre theyr kenninge
for kenneynge, and in wyndying of wynes
it chaunceth that they leaue a pipe
or other veſſell open, &amp; haue not wel faſtened

it with roopes at the ende of the
ſhyp and it ſlyppeth and falleth vpon
another, and marreth them bote, the
Mayſter and maryners ought to reſtore
the marchauntes, and the Marchauntes
muſt paye the freyght of the
two pypes, bycauſe they ſhal be payed
at the pryce that other beſolde. The
mayſter and maryners ought to ſette
theyr hoyſſynge fyrſt to recouer the domage
pounde to pounde. The owners
of the ſhyppe ſhall take nothynge, for
it was faut of the mayſter, and maryners
in faſtenyng of the pype.
            
            
               This is the iudgement.
               WItneſſe the ſeale of ye ile of aulerō
eſtablyſſhed by the contractes of
the ſayde yle, the Tueſday after the
feaſt of ſaynt Andrewe. The
yeare of our Lorde.
M.CC.lxvi.
            
            Finis.
         
         
            
            ¶A newe Rutter
of the See, for the Northe;
partyes. Compyled by
Rycharde. Proude.
M.D.XLI.
            BArwyke lyeth ſouthe &amp; northe,
of the Colde ſtone lande, and
Barwyke hauen lyeth weſt
nor weſt &amp; eaſt ſouth eaſt &amp; frō bābewe
vnto the poynt of the land. The courſe
lyeth north &amp; ſouthe, but beware of the
Golſtones, it flowes north nor weſt, &amp;
quarter tyde vnder roder from Tynmouth
to fayreylād, ye courſe is northe
Northweſt, and ſouth ſouth eaſt. And
Tynmouth is tyde northeaſt, &amp; ſouth
weſt betwexte the headland and honde
clyf the courſe is norweſt &amp; ſoutheaſt &amp;
it flowes weſt ſouthweſt eaſt northeaſt
&amp; at Why thy is half tyde, &amp; from Hōdclyf

clyf ſo forth to humber the courſe is
ſoutheaſt and by ſouth and nortweſte
and by northe, from Lyerneſſe to the
heade lande the courſe nor nor weſte,
&amp; ſouth ſouth eaſt, at the heade land
the ſtremes ſet norweſte and ſoutheaſt
and it flowes on the heade Lande of
holdernes northeaſte &amp; quarter tide in
the fayre way and at the heade Lande
quarter tyde, &amp; halfe quarter and, yf ye
go fro Lyerneſſe to the ſhelde ye ſhal
go eaſt ſouth eaſt, for to go cleare of to
ſand and if ye halfe a neb go ſoutheaſt
and by eaſt, and yf ye go from ſporne
the ſhelde And wynde be at Northe
weſt, your courſe is ſoutheaſt, tyll ye
be paſte well Bankes in the welles
flowes weſt, and Eaſt, and there goeth
alſo ſtreames vnder other, and at the
ſheldes it flowes on the Lande, Weſt
nor weſte halfe ſtreames Vnder other
by the Lande to ye come to Wynter
townes, and fro Wynter townes to
ye, come to Kerkely Roode, it flowes

on the land, it flowes northweſt and
quarter &amp; half quarter tid vnder other
&amp; yf ye go frome ſhelde to the Helmes,
and it be in the nyghte ye ſhall go but
x. fadom of the coſte tyll ye geſſe be
paſſe the Lymber &amp; vry. And ſo go the
eſtemmar courſe tyll ye come to .xiiii.
fadome and goo your courſe ſodtheaſt
tyll you be paſt the holmes. But
the mooſte wyſdome is to byd tyll daye.
From Kerkeley roode holmis
to orforde, and be weſtin, it flowes on
the lande ſouth ſoutheaſt, and at the
halmes heade quarter tyde fro or fordnes
to or wyll wannes the courſe is.
ſouthweſt, and floweth ſouth eaſte,
and in or wyll hauyn within the were
ſouth and north and ye go fro or wyll
wannys to the neſſe ye weſte go ſouthe
weſt fro the naſſe of makres, of ye ſpette
youre courſe is weſt ſouth weſt, and it
flowes ſouth and by eaſt brynge your
markes togither: That is the paryſhe

church ſteple out be eaſt the abbaye of
ſaint Vſſeys, then go your courſe ouer
the ſpetes ſouth tyl you come in ten fadoms
or .xii. fadome thē go your courſe
with the ſho ſouth ſouthweſt. Yf it be
flode come not within eyghte fadomes
And ye bryng you to .xi. fadome or .xii.
fadoms then goo youre courſe into the
Tēmes with ye grenebanke weſt ſouth
weſt and at the ſho it flowes ſouth and
north, and out of Orwilwandes to go
out at the flod your courſe is eaſt ſouth
eaſt for cauſe of ye roge and the 
                  •
               ackes
tyl ye come to .xv. fadomes dep
                  •
               , &amp; for
the landefang, then ye may go ſouthe
ſoutheaſt tyl ye come to .xviii. fadomes
thē ye muſt go ſouthe one glaſſe or two
glaſſe for cauſe of the knocke. Then go
ſouth ſouthweſt and fetch vp Tenete &amp;
tetch vp .vii. fadomes on the breke thē
go your courſe ſouth, it is your fayre
way, &amp; take the knok in Kentiſee it flowes
ſouth, and at the north hed of god
win the ſtreames rēneth to ſouth ſouth

weſt and at the ſouth heed of goodwin
the ſtreme renis to ſouth weſt, and by
ſouth it flowes fro tenet to wyze on
both ſydes on the mayne Lande ſouth
ſouth eaſt, at ſandwych at downes goo
to ſouth by eaſt, And in the downe goo
halfe tyde vnder other, and yf ye ryde
in the downes And wyll in to Sandewych
hauen ye muſte ryre and it be tonynge
wynde at eaſt, ſoutheaſt moue.
And yf it be a folowing wynde ye may
bide to ſouth eaſt mone. And ye bowne
to Calays hauē, and ryde in dowues,
&amp; the wynd be weſt ſouthweſt or ſouth
weſt, ye muſt rere I north eaſt moone
and get you into your markes, the ſtepell
in the Fanne, then go your courſe,
eaſt ſoutheaſt ouer &amp; after your tyde
ſerue your wende, And Loke you ſeke
Cales hauen, at ſouth ſoutheaſt mone
or ſouth and by eaſt And yf ye turne in
the Downes, come no neare goodwyn
thē .ix. fadome, ne no neare the brakes
them fyue fadome, from ſaint Margaretes

ſtayre and ye wil go to donginas
your way is ſouth, ſouthweſt &amp; retch
xviii. fadome depe betwixt-ſaynt Margaretes
ſtayre and Donginas goeth
halfe tyde. And fro dongynas to hyld
ninas youre courſe is eaſte and weſt.
Donginas and the water of ſinn lieth
eaſt ſoutheaſt, and weſt norweſt, Dunginas
and depe lieth ſouth eaſte and by
eaſte, nor weſt and by weſt and Donginas
and ſaine heed ſouth ſouthweſte
go from donginas and ye haue .xx.
fadome depe. go weſt ſouth weſt, that
is your courſe alonge ſee. And at donginas
is half and is halfe quarter tyde
And vnto Haſtynge halfe tyde, and at
Becheffe quarter tyde, Becheffe and
Depe ſouth eaſt, and norweſt becheffe
and ſayne heed ſouth and north the hyland
of a Rondel and ſtrouttart ſouth
ſoutheaſt, and nor nor weſt, the ſayne
hed and wolues hed ſoutheaſt, and nor
weſte Barflette nas and wolneſerde
ſouth ſoutheaſt, and nor norweſt.
            
               
The ſchapel hogges and neldes ſouth
and northe. The hagge be eaſt, Rokys
neſe, and Wolneſord ſouth and by
weſt, north and by eaſt. Wolneſorde
and Garueſaye ſouth ſoutheweſte and
quarter tyde vnder other at Wolneſord.
From Wolneſord to the Begge of
ſaynte telynes halfe tyde vnder other
And from ſaint Telines to chaike ſord
is halfe tyde, and a ſouth mone make
hyeſt water with in wight nedelles.
            And they forne lieth ſouth weſt and by
weſt, and northeaſt and by eaſt the neldes
and ye cornelāde weſt and eaſt and
the nedylles it flowes ſouth eaſt, and
by ſouth from the nedelles to portland
weſt ſouth weſt, and eaſt north eaſt at
the Poll within Hauen it flowes nor
weſt, and ſoutheaſt, and in the fayre
waye ſouthe ſoutheaſt &amp; north north
weſt, at Waymouth within the hauen
eaſt and weſt at the byll at Portlande
ſouth ſoutheaſt and north north weſte.
The ſayne heed and Portelande lyeth

weſt northweſt, &amp; eaſt ſoutheaſt. Portlande
and Garnſay ſouth and north.
Sayne heed and the Hyunde by weſt
dartmouth eaſt and by ſouth weſt and
by north Portland and bery lande eaſt
and by north, weſt and by ſouth Bery
lande and Sterte-weſt ſouthweſt and
eaſt north eaſt. Bytwyxte Portland
and ſtart euery hauen is tyde eaſt weſt
Bytwyxte Berylande and the landes
ende of Englande that is halfe tyde in
the fayre waye Bytwixte the ſtart and
Leſſart the courſe is eaſt and weſt and
beware of the Edy ſtones al the hauens
he ful Bytwixte the Starte and
Leſſarte the courſe at weſte ſouthweſte
moone the landes end and Leſſarte lyeth
eaſt ſouth eaſte and weſt Norweſt
at the landes ende lyeth the. Raynolde
ſtone a lytle yurth of but .xii. fadomes
ſhal lede you wythout hym And ſouth
ſouth weſt of the landes ende lyeth the
Golfe the Lange ſhyppes and the landes
ende lyeth nor nor weſt, and ſouth

ſouth eaſt, the lange ſhypes and ſaynt
Mary 
                  •
               oūde of Sylly lieth weſt ſouth
weſt and eaſt northeaſt. Saynt Mary
ſtound and Viſhāt lyeth nor weſt, and
by north ſouth eaſt, and by ſouth. Sylly
and the ſayne lyeth ſouth ſouth eaſt
and nor norweſt, The ſayne &amp; Vſſhant
lyeth ſouth and north. Vſſhant and
the Popyll hope lyethe north and by
weſt, and ſouth and by eaſt. Vſſhant
and Lyſſart north and ſouth, Lyſſart
and ſaynt Mary ſtounde of Sylly lyeth
weſte and eaſte, but beware of the
Gulfe, but Saynt Mary ſtounde and
the Forne nor weſt and ſoutheaſt. The
Forne and Popyl hop nor north weſt.
and ſouth ſouth eaſt. The Forne and
Lyſſart north and by eaſt, and ſouth &amp;
by weſt. The Forne and the Gred by
eaſt. Falmoth north and ſouth. The
forne and the Ramhed nor north eaſt,
and ſouth ſouthweſt. Vſſhant and the
Ramhed north eaſt and by north ſouth
weſt and by ſouth. The Forne and Bery

lande north eaſt and by north, ſouth
weſt and by ſouth. The Starte and
Baſpal north and ſouth. Baſepal
and Ramhede north
and by weſte, &amp; ſouth
&amp; by eaſt. Garnſay
and the Hiwnd
by weſt
Dartmoth weſt north
weſt, and eaſt
ſoutheaſt.
(*)
⸪
            
               ❧FINIS.
         
      
   

