
   
      
         
            A detection of the Deuils sophistrie wherwith he robbeth the vnlearned people, of the true byleef, in the most blessed sacrament of the aulter.
            Gardiner, Stephen, 1483?-1555.
         
         
            
               1546
            
         
         Approx. 280 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 153 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2006-06 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01464
            STC 11591.3
            ESTC S102849
            99838611
            99838611
            2996
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01464)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2996)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 45:07)
         
         
            
               
                  A detection of the Deuils sophistrie wherwith he robbeth the vnlearned people, of the true byleef, in the most blessed sacrament of the aulter.
                  Gardiner, Stephen, 1483?-1555.
               
               cxx, cxxiii-cliii, [1] leaves   
               
                  In Aldersgate strete, by Ihon̄ Herforde, at the costes &amp; charges of Roberte Toye, dwellynge in Paules churche yarde, at the sygne of the Bell],
                  [Printed at London :
                  1546.
               
               
                  Foreword signed in the heading: Steven Bisshoppe of Winchester, i.e. Stephen Gardiner.
                  Place of publication and printer's name from colophon.
                  This edition has colophon on T4r and no errata.
                  The leaves of Greek, E5-8, are in the same setting as those in STC 11591; signature-mark "E" has a "v" hand-stamped after it.
                  Identified as STC 11590 on UMI microfilm.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-12
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-02
            Andrew KusterSampled and proofread
         
            2006-02
            Andrew KusterText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-04
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A DETECTION OF THE Deuils Sophiſtrie, wherwith he robbeth the vnlearned people, of the true byleef, in the moſt bleſſed Sacrament of the aulter.
            
               Timeo ne ſicut ſerpens euam ſeduxit aſtutia ſua: ita corrumpantur ſenſus ueſtri, &amp; excidant aſimplicitate.
               2. Cor. 11.
            
            1546.
         
         
            
            
            ¶STEVEN Biſſhoppe of Wincheſter to the reader.
            
               COnſyder gentle reader, how ful of iniquite this tyme is, in whiche, the hyghe myſterie of our religion is ſo opēly aſſaulted. Byleue not euery ſpirite, and myſtruſte thyne owne iudgement, aboue the reache of thy capacite. If thou beeſt hungry for knowledge, take hede thou falleſt not on euery careyn. Be deſyrouſe of the very truth, and ſeke it as thou art ordered, by the direction of Chriſtes churche, and not as deceytfull teachers, wold leade the, by theyr ſecrete waies. Folow God and his myniſters, whom he ordereth to rule, and rather conforme knowlege to agre with obedience, where goddes truthe repugnethe
 not vnto it, then with violation of obedience, which is a diſpleaſaunt fault to enterpriſe the ſubuerſion of goddes honoure and glory. Finally reade whē thou readeſt, with fauour, to that truth, whiche the conſent of Chriſtes churche, hath from the beginnynge commended vnto vs, and reuerentlye at theyr handes receyue the true vnderſtā
               dynge of ſcriptures, whoſe true teſtimonie hath certified vs of the ſelfe ſame ſcriptures. And haue alwaies in remembraunce the wordes of ſaint Iames, howe God reſiſteth the preſumptuouſe and arrogant and geueth grace to ſuche as be in ſpirite, meke and lowly, whiche gyfte, God graunte the, and well to feare.
         
      
      
         
            
            A DETECTION OF the Deuyls Sophiſtrie, wherwith he robbeth ye vnlearned people, of the true belefe, in the mooſt bleſſed Sacrament of the aulter.
            
               THe firſt chiefe and pryncypall poynt of deceyte and ſophiſtry is, to make euery mā thīke of him ſelfe, further then is in dede in him, by this perſuaſiō,The deuell deceyuyth moſt craftely when he pretendyth truth. that god graunteth true vnderſtandinge and wiſedome, to euery man, that wold haue it, hath nede of it, &amp; aſketh it, in his name, whiche hathe ſuche an euydente truth in it, as no man can dyrectly deny it, and gaineſay it, for ſo god doth in dede, &amp; yet not ſo as the vnlerned do take it, &amp; thinketh it to be
 vnderſtanded. For albeit god giueth al knowlege, to fede the ſoule, as he giueth alſo all foode and nourriture to the corporall bodies, and it is for both, generally ſayd, Iacta ſuper dominum curā tuam,
               Pſalm. 54. 
               et ipſe te enutriet▪
                wherin god hath alſo, to ſhew his omnipotency giuē ſodenlye, ſpeche to them that could not ſpeake,lerimae. 1. as to Ieremy, geuen the vnlerned, ſodenly knowlege, to confound the great clerkes,Ioan. 2. chaunged water into wine in a moment, to make chere to geſtes of the feaſt, and multiplied by his bleſſing,Math. 14. the fiue loues to the neceſſary releef of the hungry,Exodi. 16. fed his people with manna in deſert,Exodi. 17. and geuen thē for releef, out of the hard dry ſtone water: Yet we may not hereof preſume, that god, bycauſe he can alwaies, therfore alſo he wil alwaies contynually worke new myracles, and giue his giftes out of ordre
 and make herueſt in February, or children and rude ignorantes, lerned before they go to ſcoole. And in dede, we myght aſwel and better aſke our bodely foode without our labour, and ſeſonable time as aſke the knowledge of lernynge, to inſtructe the ſoule, without tyme or 
                  •
               ue endeuor, wherwith to attayne the ſame. It is goddes worke, that we come by it when we come by it with our labour and teachynge of other,I Cor. 3. for neque qui plantat eſt aliquid, neque ꝗ rigat, ſed qui incrementum dat, deus. And we that in our Pater noſter,
               Math. 4. aſke our daylye bread, knowledge it to come of god when we haue it, and yet no man boſteth him ſelfe to haue it, by cauſe he hath aſked it, or loketh otherwiſe for it, but by thapplyeng of his labour and induſtry thervnto, which perſuaſion if theſe ſymple vnlerned, had in the atteinynge of
 wiſedome, they wold miſtruſt their owne iudgement and thinke themſelf (as they be) vnlerned, and with out longe exerciſe and diligent endeuor, with a veſſell mete and apte to receiue the ſame, not thinke thē ſelfe to haue obteined that gifte of god, ne be able for want therof, to diſcuſſe of lerning. This falſe perſuaſion of lerning, wherewith the deuyll inueigleth the ſimple and ingendreth in them a pryde of conninge and vnderſtandinge, whiche they haue not, is the foundacion &amp; roote, wherupon is buylded and groweth falſe doctrine in the high miſteryes of our religion, &amp; ſpecyally in the moſt bleſſed Sacramēt of thaulter, wherin diuerſe haue of late peuerſely reaſoned, &amp; vnlearnedly ſpoken wt ſuch preſūptuouſe pride, &amp; intollerable arrogancy as declare plainly the ſame to procede of the ſpirite of the deuyl ful of errours,
 &amp; lyes, blyndenes, &amp; ignoraunce, by reaſon wherof, they ſtū
               ble in the playne way,Chriſoſt. ho. 60 Non ſunt humane uirtutis hee opera, que tunc in illa cena confecit, iyſe nunc quo
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   operatur, ipſe perficit, nosmi niſtrorum ordinem tenemus qui uero hec ſā
                  ctificat, &amp; trāſ mutat, ipſe eſt. &amp; can not ſee in the mydde day. For what can be more euidently ſpoken of the preſēce of Chriſtes natural body and bloud, in the moſt bleſſed ſacramēt of the aulter, thē is in thoſe wordes of ſcripture whiche our Sauioure Chriſt ones ſaid, and be infallible truth, and ſtyll ſayth, in conſecration of this moſt holy Sacrament, by the cōmon miniſtre of ye church. This is my body. But againſte this truth, the deuyll ſtriueth, and fyghteth by his miniſters, &amp; lewde apoſtles, with ſophiſtical deuyſes, wherwith he troubleth the groſſe imaginaciōs of the ſymple people. And hauynge ones enchaunted, the rude wyttes with this charme of preſūptuouſe knowledge (wherof I ſpake before) wherby the ignoraūt, waxeth ſo arrogāt, as he
 maketh himſelf able to iudge and diſcerne, betwene playnnes and craft, bytwene reaſon and ſophiſticacion, betwene argument and argument, expoſition and expoſitiō, ſuche as be thus ouerthrowen in their iudgement, and ſo blynded in themſelfe, the deuyll eaſely entangleth and byndeth faſt to him, with carnall reaſons, deceitfull expoſitions, crooked argumentes, and counterfet cōtradictiōs, and therby leadeth them away, captiue and thralde, from the true catholtque byleefe in this mooſt holye ſacramente, which ſophyſtry and deceptes, be diuerſely tempered, after theſe ſortes.
            
               AND FYRST to the carnall man, the deuyll bringeth carnall reaſons, and for conformation, and proufe of them calleth to witnes, the carnall ſenſes, both of the bodye and ſoule. And ſtreyght
 thyne eye ſayeth, there is but bread and wyne. Thy taſt ſaith the ſame. Thy felinge and ſmellynge agre fully with them. Herevnto is added the carnall mans vnderſtandyng, whiche bycauſe it taketh the begynning of the ſenſes, procedeth in reaſoning ſenſually. And (as the Epicures dyd) concludeth that ye ſenſes togither, can not be deceyued. wherevpon alſo the Epicurians ſaide the ſonne was but two fote brode, becauſe theyr eye iudged it to be no bygger. And from this they wolde not be brought, but remayned as ferme, in that foly, as ſome heretiques do, in this miſcheuous deuellyſh miſbeleefe, againſt the mooſt bleſſed Sacrament of the aulter. Wherefore all ſuche as ground their errour, agaynſt this mooſt bleſſed Sacrament, vpon the teſtimonye of theyr ſight, their taſte, felyng, or ſmell, or
 otherwiſe vpon their carnall vnderſtandinge, bycauſe they can not by their carnall reaſon, comprehēd it, all ſuch be beſtly and blynd, and farre from the knowledge of the miſeries of our religion, as wherin our ſenſes and reaſō, be vy faith condempned and reproued, finally declare them ſelue to be ſuche men, as ſeme to require teachinge in the principles and begynnynges of our religion, wherin their groſſe carnall reaſons, yf they were truly mortified, they ſhulde not ſo ſtobbernly and arrogantly meddle, in the diſcuſſion of the inſcrutable miſterye in the moſt bleſſed ſacrament of thaulter. For yf theyr ſenſes were by true faith, ouerthrowen &amp; put to confuſiō, in the bylefe of ye holy trinite, ye father of heauē, the ſon̄e, &amp; holy ghoſt, to be inſeparably deuided in thre ꝑſons, &amp; diuiſibly eioyned ī one godhed &amp; eſſece
 which Gregorye Nazianzene ſpeaketh thus in greke.Grego. Naizan. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                Wherein we knowe by faith, the truth, ſo to be, howe ſo euer our reaſon ſpurneth and tentech vs to the contrarye, If theſe mennes ſenſes were tamed, in the beleuynge ſcripture of creation of the worlde, by god in time, and of nothynge, contrarye to the diſcuſſion of mans reaſon, whiche the philoſophers coulde not temper, to agre, that of nothynge, was anye thynge made, If in the miſterie of the incarnation of our ſauioure Chriſte, the rebellion of mans ſenſes, were throughlye trode vnder fete, and brought in due ſubiection, to gyue place to faythe, wherby we byleue that the ſonne of god (which we confeſſe truly) to be immenſus, was yet conteyned in the holy virgins wombe, &amp; a creature,
 to conteyne the creatour, and as the churche reioyſing, doth daylye acknowledge, in worſhypping the bleſſed vyrgin Marye.
            
               Quem totus non capit orbis,
               In tua ſe clauſitviſcera, factꝰ homo
            
            Whiche to mannes reaſon implieth an inſoluble contradiction, to ſaye that in her wombe, ſhulde be ſhut in, that al the world could not conteyne. And then further the true ſtory of Chriſtes goſpel wherin is truely reported to vs howe Chriſt entred to his diſciples, after his reſurrection the gates beynge ſhut, and role out of his graue the ſame remaining ſtyl ſhut, which to our vnderſtandyng, maketh a ſignification of two bodies to be in one place togither and occupie the ſame place, at one tyme, And is to mannes ſenſuall and carnal knowledge impoſſible, and is neuertheleſſe in ye ſaid myraculouſe paſſage
 of our ſauyour Chriſt mooſt truly verified. But if in theſe, and many other, the carnall man had in the foundacion of our faith fully acknowleged his weaknes, his blīdnes, his imbecillitie &amp; ignoraunce, the ſame wolde neuer preſume agayne,Chriſo. bo. 60. Credamus ubi ꝙ deo, ne
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   repugnem
                     •
                  s ei. etiam ſi ſenſvi &amp; cogitacioin noſtrae abſus Lum eſſe widetur quod dicit, ſuperet
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ſenſum &amp; rationem noſtram quod in omnibus, &amp; pr
                     •••
                  pue imyſteri
                     ••
                   h
                     ••
                   qu
                     •
                   ante nos iacent ſolum. mo
                     •
                  o ſpicientes ſed uer
                     ••
                   quo
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   eius todmentes. Nam uerbis eius defreudari non poſſumus, ſenſus uero noſter deceptu facilli mus eſt, illa falſa eſſe non poſſunt, is ſaepius acſaepius decipitur. Quoni amergo ille di xit, Hoc eſt corpus meum, nulla teneamur imbiguitate, ſed credamus 
                     〈◊〉
                  
                eyther to improue the preſence of the naturall body of our Sauiour Chriſte, in the moſt bleſſed Sacrament of the aulter, in fourme of bread &amp; wine, by carnal deuyſes, ne trauayle to be ſatiſfied in conſideration of the circumſtaū
               ces of the ſame. For lyke as in the other miſteries of the Trinite, the creation of the world, the incarnation of Chriſt, and alſo reſurrection of the fleſhe, (wherof I haue not ſpoken, but may ſay, as I haue in the other) carnal reaſon is excluded, by certentie of faith: ſo ſhulde it be in all other myſteries, whiche all together, be the body of our reeigion,
 wherein we haue the true knowledge of god, which the deuil laboureth to ſubuerte and ouerthrowe, and vſeth therin the inſtrument of mannes preſumptuouſe arrogance, to know all as god doth, and to comprehēde in his capacite, the ſame, and what ſo euer excedeth it, or repugneth thervnto, to call that falſe folye, lyes, and vntruth. After whiche ſorte, mans foolyſhe wyſedome, hath enterpriſed at ſundry tymes, to impugne the ſecrete miſteries of goddes hyghe wyſedome, &amp; incomprehenſible workes, And ſo the deuyll by the Arrians, (as he doth by the Turkes at this daye) hath aſſaulted the caſtell and forte of our religion, by denyall of Chriſte to be very God, and with truthes falſly applied, gone about to make batterye and entrye, to ouerthrowe the ſame, lyke as he hath alſo attempted manye other
 miſteries. But beinge in them by goddes power reſiſted, the deuyll aſſayeth to make entry nowe, by ſubuertinge the truthe in the moſt bleſſed Sacrament of thaulter, and to allure ye multitude of moſt carnall and rude capacities diuulgeth abrode, groſſe carnall reaſōs, and wolde perſuade the vnlerned that their ignoraunce in the circumſtaunce (how,) ſhould playnely proue to them, that the thing is not, &amp; therwith whiſtleth in their eares, this enchauntment. If it were true that is taught in the ſacramēt of thaluter, by the papiſtes (whiche terme ſerueth for a token to thē, to proue ye matter nought) ſuch and ſuch incōueniēces, ſhould not to our ſenſes folowe. Do we not ſe (ſaith the deuyll) the ſacrament of thaulter that they call god their ydol, (o blaſphemous tōgue) ſometyme eaten of a mouſe, ſometyme
 waxe grene moulde, redde moulde, and blue mould? and here the deuyll refreſſheth his yonglynges with manye abhominable tales, ſuche as a ſcoffinge leſtynge witte could deuyſe, to haue benne done. Doth it not enter (ſayth the deuyll) into the body, and ſo furth, and ſpeaketh that lyketh him, more then honeſt eares can endure? And then the deuyll frameth the matter in faſhion of lerninge, and firſte with a counterfet religiō of mayntenaunce of gods truth, propoueth god, to be impaſſible, incorruptible and immortal, which is a moſt vndoubted truth, &amp; thē foloweth thintended lye, thus, That which theſe papiſtes make God, &amp; call ye ſacrament of thaulter, that is corruptible, And here the ſenſes beare witnes, The papiſtes god, (the deuyll ſayth) is alſo paſſible. And here ye ſenſes be alſo redy, &amp; ſhall affirme,
 they haue ſene the mouſe eate it, mans hande breake it, &amp; mans teth teare it. It is alſo mortal (ſaith the deuyll) for the ſēſes beare teſtimony, they haue ſene it with a ſodayn fire in a churche, cōſumed, Ergo then, (&amp; with this the deuyl triumpheth &amp; 
                  •
               cludeth) there is not god, but it is an ydol, whiche wordes they vttermoſt blaſphemouſelye &amp; falſely. But cōſider (chriſtē reader) how far is it out of ye waye, to examyne mens ſenſes or carnall reaſō, what they can depoſe of god; or his high ſecrete workes. This reaſoning might ſerue to proue yt eyther Chriſte was not God (whiche no chriſtē eare can endure) or els not to be true (which is moſt true &amp; certeine) that Chriſte dyed or ſuffered for vs. And thus the deuilles diſciple, wyll reaſon. God is impaſſible, Chriſte ſuffred: Ergo he was not god. Or thus. God is impaſſible,
 Chriſte was god: Ergo he ſuffered not. So as by theſe reaſos, and reaſonynges, wherin the ſenſes ſerue for a proufe, or carnall reaſon frameth thargumēt: eyther we muſt with the Arryans denye Chriſt god blaſphemouſely, or conſent moſte folyſhly, to other falſe dreames, that Chriſt ſuffred not at al. But as we be learned moſt truly &amp; certeynely in faith, that Chriſt was very God and perfyght mā, and without iniury to his godhed (whiche is impaſſible (ſuffered neuertheleſſe naturall death, for he was naturall man without ſynne, and when we knowe this truth aſſuredly by faith, regarde not what all our ſenſes repugne to the contrarye, ne we do not leane to their teſtimony in it: So in this high myſtery of the ſacrament of thaulter, when we knowe by faith the preſence of Chriſtes naturall body
 and bloud, by the mighty operaciō of his word, prouoūced in the conſecratiō by ye miniſter: what a tentation is it of the deuyl, to kepe a court wt our ſēſes &amp; carnall reaſoning (which be blind, &amp; can not vnderſtāde it) &amp; of thē to make an enqueſt to knowe whyther my byleef therin be right or no? which ſenſes, if they had bē enquired of chriſtes body, being cōuerſaūt in erth, theyr teſtimony had bē of chriſt, yt he was but a man, as other were, euen as they now affyrme the Sacrament to be but brede, as other brede is. Theyr capacite is no further, and therfore it is a madnes, and ouer rude groſſenes, to commen with them in a matter (I knowe well) they can no ſkille of. But herin we ſhulde leane to our faith, groūded vpon goddes truth, and confeſſe all to be ſo, as god worketh by his omnipotēcy, and therwith acknowledge
 the weakenes of mans capacite, not able to comprehende it, &amp; foraſmuch as the plaine wordes of ſcripture, declare, and teſtifie vnto vs, the preſence of ye moſt preciouſe bodye and bloud of our Sauiour Chriſt, in the ſacramēt of thaulter, we ſhould not be ſhaken or altered from that byleef, what ſo euer oure ſēſes or carnal vnderſtāding, ſhuld barke to the cōtrary. If myne eye, ſeeth the hoſt cōſecrate broken (whiche is dayly done in the maſſe) or deuoured by a mouſe, or otherwiſe percaſe abuſed (whiche happeneth rarely) is this a iuſt cauſe, why my faith, ſhulde by and by wauer, and myſtruſt the truth, by god declared vnto me? Or els muſt carnal reaſō and vnderſtāding be ſatiſfied, how it commeth to paſſe, that ſtandyng our faith in the moſt bleſſed ſacrament of the preſence of the natural body and bloude of our ſauioure
 Chriſt, the ſame ſacrament may be broken, the ſame may be deuoured of the mouſe, the ſame maye be corrupte, or otherwiſe myſuſed? Whervnto fyrſt I ſaye this, that if after the wordes of conſecratiō, the hoſte conſecrate, were ſo by god preſerued, from the iniuries, and violences of other creatures, as it eoulde not be brokē, deuoured, or corrupt, it were ſuch an outwarde myracle, to the open confuſiō of our carnal ſenſes, as wherby to take away the merite of our faith. For vnto the faithfull, ſuche myracles (as ſaint Paule ſaith)1 Cor. 14. be not ſhewed but to the infidels. And a good true chriſten beleuyng man, knoweth this by faith, that good is inuiolable, impaſſible, incorruptible, immortall, and that our ſauyoure Chriſt, the ſeconde perſon in trinite, very god, hauynge the humayne nature, nowe vnite to the godhed
 and gloryfied, can not any more ſuffre in that bodye, violence or corruptiō, ne be violate or brought to mortalyte.Pſal: 15. 
               Quia nō dabis ſanctū tuum videre corruptionem. And therfore what ſo euer mans ſenſes affyrme of the violation, corruption, or deſtruction of the hoſte conſecrate, a chriſten mannes faythe knoweth moſt certeinly, that the moſt preciouſe body of chriſt, there preſent in that hoſt, is not violate, is not corrupted, is not deſtroyed, for the faithful is aſſerteyned, that Chriſtus reſurgens ex mortuis,
               Roma. 6. 
               iam non moritur, mors illi vltra nō dominabitur. And therfore the ſame beynge truely taughte, and enfourmed of goddes omnipotēcie conſydereth, that as Chriſt beynge conuerſaunt in earth, amonge the maliciouſe Iewes, before the tyme of his paſſion, and when the ſame was not yet come (as the goſpell
 ſaith) when the furiouſe Iewes wolde haue precipitate him.Luc. 4. 
               Tranſiens per medium illorū ibat. And whē Herode ſlew al ye reſt of ye children, Chriſt beyng a child,Mat. 2. was preſerued: So in ye moſt bleſſed ſacramēt of ye aulter, how ſoeuer ye ſame be abuſed by mans malice or negligence, or otherwiſe broken in the myſtical vſe of it, yet the very body of our ſauiour Chriſt there preſēt, continueth inuiolate, impaſſible, and is beyond the reach of any violence to be inferred by man, beſte, or any other accidental occaſion, of any other cauſe, ne ye true faithfull man can be induced by any worldly demonſtration, to departe or ſwarue from his true faith, &amp; what ſo euer reaſons may be made to the contrary, he taketh them onely as tentacions of the deuill, wherby to ſubuerte, and ouerturne his ſtedfaſt faith, being ſo firme &amp; ſtronge
 in a good chriſten man, as the gates of hell can not preuaile againſt it, &amp; muche leſſe, worldely fanſies, reaſons or demonſtraciōs, and ſpecially ſuch, as be grounded, vpon the ſenſes and carnal argumentes, whiche can not atteine the ſecretes of gods myſteries. The deuyl now a dayes, diuulgeth by his wycked mynyſters, his leude tales, of the abuſes of the hoſt conſecrate, when by to impugne the faith of the preſence, of the bodye of our ſauyoure Chriſt. And here is made mention of moulding &amp; mouſe deuouryng, with ſuch lyke myſuſes, which the preſēce of chriſtes natural body, if it were there (as they ſay) ſhuld defende, wherein I wolde aſke ſuche ſorte of men, as be moued by theſe reaſones, how moch theſe inconueniences ſo abhomynably tolde, do excede and be more ſtraunge, wherby to ſhake our fayth but the wonderynge and murmurynge of our
 ſenſes, then thoſe thynges whiche the churche doth daylye ordayne and openly do, wherewith the true beleuers haue not ben offended?
            Doth not the preiſte daylye in the maſſe, &amp; hath done alwaye, breake the hoſt conſecrate, in the ſyght of the people, without offence or ſclaū
               der, of ſuche as haue theſe xv.c. yeres and do at this daye byleue the preſence of the naturall bodye of Chriſt? Haue not men of weake ſtomackes (fearing they could not cōteine, ye they receyued) vſed reuerētly to forbeare to receyue, ye moſt bleſſed Sacramēt, where they certeynly beleued ye preſēce of chriſtes natural body to be able &amp; of power to heale body &amp; ſoule? And haue eyther of theſe reuerēt vſes amōge good mē, empayred ye beleef amōg thē, or good men ben inquiſitiue, howe god could be broken, beynge impaſſible and preſente in
 the ſacrament of the aulter, or bencuriouſe to aſke, whye men ſhulde forbeare to receyue the ſacrament, for feare of any weakenes of ſtomack, ſeinge god (whome they beleue there preſent) is able to heale al: Good men were neuer offended, with brekinge of the hoſt, whiche they dayly ſaw, beyng alſo perſwaded Chriſtes body to be preſent in the ſacrament naturally and really, whervnto with worſhyppinge they lyfted vp their handes, and therewith nothinge doubted, but god was inuiolable, &amp; impaſſible, when they ſaw the hooſt broken in the maſſe, ne vſed not to my ſtruſte goddes immortalite, when they haue ſene a ſycke man receiue the ſacramēt not a quarter of an houre before his natural deth, as though in that man, the hoſt conſecrate (wherein the body of Chriſt in preſent) ſhulde with goddes iniury
 moulde, or corrupt, waſt and conſume. And yet theſe right vſes of the moſt bleſſed ſacrament, cōteyne as ſtraunge matter, to mans ſēſes and carnall iudgement, as do the leude and blaſphemouſe tales, deuiſed and tolde wherby to inueigle mens vnderſtādynges, and ſpoyle them of their true byleef. And yet alſo theſe breakinges and vſes of the mooſt bleſſed ſacrament, were neuer hyddē in the churche, ne kept ſecrete, as thoughe the true belefe ſhulde therby decay, or be diminiſhed. The churche hath not forborne, to preache the truthe, to the confuſion of mans ſenſes and vnderſtanding, whervnto men faithfull and obedient, haue yelded, acknowleginge gods omnipotency, which mans reaſō can not matche, The true churche hath taughte plainly, and teacheth that by the omnipotencie of gods worde, the
 ſubſtaunce of bred is conuerted to the ſubſtaunce of Chriſtes natural bodye, whiche is there then by his myghty power, not by mutacyon of place, by leauynge of heauen, where he is euer preſent, but by his infinite power (wherby he can do all) and of a ſpecyal fauour to wardes vs, worketh continually in his churche, this myſterye and miracle, and in forme of bread and wyne, exhibiteth and preſenteth himſelf, to be eaten &amp; drunken of vs, So as there is in the ſacramēt of thaulter, none other ſubſtaunce, but the ſubſtaunce of the body and bloud of our ſauiour chriſte, &amp; yet remayneth the fourme and accidentes of bread and wyne, not altered by this myracle frō knowledge of the ſenſes, wherwith they were before known &amp; alſo by gods ſufferaunce ſubiecte to the ſame paſſibilite, they were in before. And yet
 here in this myſtery and myracle wrought by gods power, we acknowledge, yt contrary to the comē ordre of nature, the ſubſtaunce of bred, beyng conuerted into the naturall bodely ſubſtaūce of our ſauiour Chriſt, the other accidētes of bred &amp; wyne, as quantities &amp; qualities remayne ſtil &amp; without iniury of Chriſtes moſt preciouſe body, be (as we dayly ſe) altered &amp; broken, and remaynīg &amp; abyding without theyr owne fourmer ſubſtāce of the creatures of bred &amp; wine, whervnto they were by nature adioyned do now ſeruice theyr creatoure there preſent the very ſubſtaūce of all ſubſtaunces, vnder which accidentes, that is to ſay (as we truely ſpeake) vnder fourme of bred and wine, the naturall body &amp; receyued of vs, ī the ſacramēt of thaulter, who ſo ordred himſelfe to be eaten and dronken of vs, in his laſt ſupper,
 whiche continueth ſtyll,Chriſo. ho. 60. Illa nō alia mē
                  ſa eſt, hec nulla re minor 
                     
                        
                     
                     quam
                   uls eſt. Non enim illam Chriſtus, hac homo quiſ piam facit, ſed utran
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ipſe. tyll the worldes ende, with a perpetuall continuaunce alſo, of the meruelouſe workynge of the ſame feſtemaker &amp; preſence of the ſame moſt preciouſe meate Chriſte him ſelfe (cum ipſe ſit cōuiua &amp; conuiuiū
               ) wher wt he cōtinually fedeth,Hier ad
                     •
                  ebidiā
                ſuch as come vnto hym in his churche, which church according to his commaundement, by ſpecial myniſters deputed thervnto, vſeth and exerciſeth the ſame feſt, in the moſt holy maſſe, where vnto good chriſten mēhaue daily acceſſe, which moſt holy feſte when men abuſe,1. Cor. 11. (as the Corynthians dyd) it is their condemnation, and can be nothyng preuidiciall or daungerouſe, to good mennes true beleef. Suche I ſaye as haue their faith eſtabliſhed vpon the true teachyng of the church, that after the wordes of conſecration, the ſubſtaunce of bread, is turned
 into the ſubſtaunce of the natural body and bloude of our Sauiour Chriſte. Againſt which teachyng, good men kicke not, with howes, and whattes, for that is a token of incredulite, &amp; if the chaū
               cell were with fyre, ſodenly burned (as hath happened by diuerſe chaunces) they thinke not chriſt that is god immortall, there killed, becauſe he was there, in the hoſte after conſecracion, or forbeare anye whyt leſſe, to worſhyp chriſt, whom with theyr eyes of faith, they ſe preſent in the ſacrament of thaulter, becauſe their bodely ſyght, perceyueth not any viſible alteracion of the hoſt, before the conſecracion &amp; after, fynally ſuch good mē, beleue moſt ſtedfaſtly, without ſclaunder of theyr ſenies, that the breakynge of the moſt bleſſed ſacrament, by the miniſtre in the maſſe doth no violaciō to chriſtes moſt precious
 body there preſent, 
                  •
               e breaketh the moſt precyouſe body, whiche is impaſſible, but only the fourme of bread, vnder whiche it is cōteyned, and that the ſame moſt precyouſe bodye, is after hooly in eche of the partes of the hoſt broken, without any encreaſe in nūber: as thoughe there were thē many chriſtes preſēt, but alwayes one chriſt, &amp; the ſame chriſt. But ye deuyl taketh his oportunite of mans carnall lyuynge, &amp; whiles the bely hath the vpperhād among a great many of the world, by reaſon wher of the ſenſes be had in eſtimation, ſturreth vp this abhominable hereſy, againſt the moſt bleſſed ſacrament of the aulter, &amp; vpon the ſenſes maketh the chyefe groundes wherby now, that afore was paſſed ouer in ſylence, when mennes ſenſes were brought in obedience with true byleef, is queſtioned and enquyred of as a newe
 matter. And nowe men be aſked how a mouſe can eate god, &amp; howe god can corrupt, and waxe mo uld: &amp; how god can be broken in p
                  •
               eces, which be fondly framed queſtiōs, And to ye great prouocatiō of gods hygh indignation, blaſphemouſly vttered. Anſwer me then (ſaith the deuyll by his apoſtels) wherunto a true aunſwere is this, and the ſimplicitie required in a chriſtē mā ſufficient. Beleue, that a mouſe can not deuour god, byleue that god can not corrupt. Beleue that god can not be broken, now after he is ones riſē, and beleue alſo therwith, that Chriſt, god and man, is naturally preſente in the ſacrament of thaulter, For ſo Chriſte ſaith. So the church of god teacheth, So we be bounde to byleue. If thou beeſt further taughte of the deuyll, to replye, yt if there remayne in ye hoſt no ſubſtaunce, but the ſubſtaunce
 
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
                
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
                of the body and bloude of Chriſt, it muſt nedes be then,Theſe be the doubtes of incredulite. that the ſame corrupteth, or elles when goth it awaye? or where haue ye ſcripture, to declare the going away and departyng of Chriſt, from the hooſt? And if Chriſt departe, then is there no ſubſtaunce remayning, &amp; where is no ſubſtaunce, is nothynge, And ſo, thou wylte ſaye (as the deuell lerueth the,) that by this teaching, we ſhall haue nothynge ſomwhat, And in dede the deuyl hath taught the, to ſpeake ſomewhat, that is in effecte nothynge, or worſe then nothynge, wherunto if men in theſe dayes can not aunſwer probablye (as I doubt not a great number can) and yet in this tyme the world is rather occupied in garnyſhynge the tonge with wordes, thē to entre the further conſyderatiō of ītricate ſophiſtication, wherby to be able to refell the ſame. Shall the true
 faith of the churche, in this hyghe myſtery periſh in the, by the deuyls ſecrete tentation, bycauſe I, or ſuch other, can not aunſwer thy ſophiſticall argument. If mennes wordes do not perſuade our faith,Non in perſuaſibilibus humanae ſapienciae uerbis, but only the power of god, ſhal the framing of an argumēt, wreſted out of olde matter,1. Cor. 2. ſubuerte the true byleef, by cauſe thou canſt not be aunſwered to thy ſatiſfaction in it? whiche is as moch to ſaye, as thou wylt only byleue thy ſelfe: For if thou wylte not bileue more thē thyne owne capacite can comprehende, then haſte thou no byleef at all of god, which can not be of man comprehended, and haſte only a vayne deceytfull ymaginacion of thyne owne, without grounde or foundation, redy to be turned as the wynde chaungeth his coſt, and bloweth ſlackely or ſtraineably, as is occaſioned by the ayre, And ſo is there fynally by
 thy concluſion, no ſtedfaſte faith in our religion, but wauering opinion, whiche is the deuyls ſpeciall craft wherwith to wype out al. For if it were neceſſarely requiſyte, to ſatiſfie mans ſenſes and ſenſuall reaſons, in the myſtery of the moſt bleſſed ſacramēt of thaulter, could the ſame carnall reaſon (trowe ye) ſtaye there but wolde deſyre ye lyke ſatiſfaction in the myſtery of Chriſtes incarnation, our reſurrection, and the myſterie of the Trinite. Coulde the philoſophers (beynge without true faith, as they were) ſtaye naturall reaſon, but ſhe wold penetrate al ſecretes, and for want of ſatiſfaction, finally amonge a number, deny god which is thende for puniſſhement, of ſuch curioſite, And therfore it is to be noted, that ſaint Auſten ſaith in theD. Auguſt. de Trinitate .iii. boke, in his worke. De trinitate. Mihi omnino vtile eſt, vt meminerim
 viriū mearū, fratres 
                     
                        
                     
                     quam
                   meos admoneā, vt &amp; ipſi meminerint viriū ſuarū, ne vltra 
                     
                        
                     
                     quam
                   tutū eſt, humana progrediatur infirmitas. It is expediēt for me (ſaith S. Auſtine) to remembre myne owne ſtrength and to admonyſhe my brethrē lykewiſe, that they remember theyr ſtrength, that mans weakenes wade no further, thē it may with ſafetie. Accordinge wherunto Salomon ſaith. Scrutator maieſtatis,
               Prouet. 15. 
               opprimetur a gloria. He that ſercheth the maieſtie, ſhalbe ouerwhelmed of the glorie. And it is written in Eccleſiaſtico.
               Eccle. 3. 
               Altiora te, ne quaeſieris, &amp; fortiora te, ne ſcrutatꝰ fueris, ſed quae preaeci pit tibi Deus, illa cogita ſēꝑ, &amp; in pluribꝰ operibꝰ eius ne fueris curioſus. Queſtiō not (ſaith Eccleſiaſticus) of theſe thynges that yu cāſt not reach. Search not for thinges aboue thy ſtrēgth &amp; force, but what ſo euer thynges god commaunde
 the to do, thynke of them euer, and in many of goddes workes be not ouer curiouſe, wherunto it may be ſayd further (as ſainte AuguſtyneAuguſtine. writeth) and ſpecially gyue no credence to thy ſēſes, and ſenſuall reaſons, to impugne the myſteries of faith, howe ſo euer they preſſe the, and prycke the, to enterpriſe the ſame, wherin I trauayle not ſo moche with the (reader) bycauſe this thwarting of mannes carnall reaſon, were an harde obiection, which if thou markeſt, I haue before aſſ
                  •
               yled by the waye, or that I thought it any daūgerouſe matter to be aunſwered vnto, wherin as I wolde wiſhe no ſuche trifelynge argumētes in ſo hygh and graue a matter, to haue ben made, &amp; thinke it a greate plage of god, to ſe ſo high preciouſe miſteries, ſo cōmenly, ſo rudely, and groſſely ſpoken of: So I thynke the ſolucion very
 eaſy, I meane to ſenſes exerciſed in knowledge and learnyng, (as S. Paule ſaith) beyng able to digeſte ſtrōg meate, and to diſcerne ſophiſtery, in the myſtakynge of ſpeach, and conceyue the fyne differences in conſyderation of the thynges whiche in dede excede the capacite of the rude people. And therfore when they heare it, beinge angry that they perceyue it not, improue it commenly, and call it ſophiſtery, where in dede, they be already with this groſſe carnal argumentes ſophiſtically entangled. But to the purpoſe ſhortly: Firſt I ſaye this, (wherof I haue ſpokē before) that the deuyll in his vile examples, of the abuſe of the moſt bleſſed hoſte conſecrate, although he troubleth the eye of the rude man, and the eare alſo, with matter of newe circumſtaunce, wherwith the ſimple witte, is ſodenly cōfounded: where
 in dede the very matter in thoſe tales depely conſydered, is no ſtraunger then the olde, and hath no cauſe to trouble or moue, but only bycauſe it is a newe facion, newly vttered and tolde. Fewe men (and thoſe but rarely) haue ſeen a mouſe deuoure ye hoſt, or churches burnt, wherin the hoſt was then reſerued, and with the churche conſumed to mans ſenſes, or the hoſtes, by neglygēce moulded or other wyſe abuſed. Theſe haue chaunced ſeldome, &amp; haue comen to the knowelege of few, but many haue knowē (as of Iudas ſpecially we be learned and taught) that euyll men hauing the deuyl in them in that they be euyll, haue yet receyued into theyr bodyes the hoſte conſecrate, wherin was then preſent the moſt precyouſe body and bloude of our ſauiour Chriſt. Many alſo haue ſeen good mē, being ye tēple of god,
 receyue the moſt bleſſed ſacrament in to theyr body, and dye ſhortelye after. Moreouer the hole churche hath ſeen, and dayly doth ſee (ſuche as forbere not to come to churche) the moſt bleſſed ſacrament broken, by the myniſter, both in the maſſe for a myſterie cōtinually, and ſome tyme when hoſtes haue wanted for cōmunion of other. In which cōſideraciōs, of yt al or many haue ſeen mās ſenſes &amp; carnal vnderſtāding ſhuld haue ben aſmuche aſtoyned, for the matter repugnaūt to theyr capacite then, as now in the deuils vile tales. wherfore this I ſay vnto the for a ſolutiō, that yf the true churche of Chriſt hath ſo ſubdued theyr ſēſes, &amp; carnal ymaginaciōs, as in it, good men haue with the true faith of the preſence of the naturall bodye and bloude of our ſauiour Chriſte, ſeen continually with theyr bodylye eyes, a notable
 repugnaunce, to their carnall ſenſes and vnderſtandynge, and yet not be moued and altered in theyr faith therwith: why ſhuld the ſame matter tolde in a vyle tale &amp; fylthy demonſtratiō, moue any mā now? For why ſhulde any man thinke worſe of the moſt bleſſed ſacramēt, when he ſeeth a mouſe take it, then when he heareth of a theef (as Iudas ye deuilles mēbre) to haue takē it? Or why ſhuld he myſtruſte the preſence of Chriſtes naturall body in the hoſte, beynge in the churche when the ſame is burnt, more then when he ſeeth the man incōtinently after he hath receyued ye hoſt, dye, and wrapped vp in earth. And as for the breakynge, why haue not good men aſmoche ben offended in theyr ſenſes, in the ryght vſe and myſtery of the churche, whiche is dayly done in the maſſe, as in ſuch new tales, as the deuyll now deuiſed,
 to declare paſſybilite? Certeynly, none other cauſe is there but this, that in thē true faith reygned, and had the ſenſes in captiuite and bondage, and in godly ſimply cite, beleued gods omnipotency, farre excedynge the weakenes of mans capacite. And thus conclude I, one playne ſolucion to the matter. The churche of god teſtifieth and teacheth this to be the true byleef of the moſt bleſſed Sacrament of the aulter, that there is preſent the natural body and bloud of our ſauiour Chriſte. Good men in the ſame churche with theyr bodylye ſenſes haue ſeen and herde, as moch matter repugnaunt to theyr ſenſes, in the myſticall and deuoute vſe of the bleſſed ſacrament, as the deuyl now telleth in ſcoffynge tales, and yet therwith reteyned ſtyl the ſame faith inuiolably, wherfore al good men ſhulde lykewiſe do the ſame
 nowe, without curioſite or ſerche, how the ſame myght be, whiche to good men ſhulde be a ſolucion for the hole matter: For true byleuers knowe that as the handes of the myniſters that breake ye ſacramēt in the maſſe, the teeth alſo of them that receyue it, ne ye naturall heate of theyr body wherin it deſcēdeth, doth no violence of paſſibylitie, bringeth no corruption, alteratiō, or cōſumptiō to the moſt precyouſe bodye of our ſauiour Chriſte: no more can any beeſt yt ſhulde touche the hoſt irreuerently, or any temperature of the ayre and place, in the moulding or alteryng of the hoſte.
                  
                     〈…〉
                  . And further more I aunſwer that beinge in the moſt bleſſed Sacrament of thaulter, two conſiderations, one that it is a ſacramēt, another yt it is alſo the thing it ſelf of ye ſacrament, that is to ſaye Chriſtes moſt preciouſe body &amp; bloud, albeit
 there is in ye hoſt no ſubſtaūce of bread, but only the ſubſtaunce of ye moſt precious body &amp; bloud of our ſauiour Chriſt: yet there is (which appere to our bodelye ſenſes) the forme of bread and wyne, vnder whiche, the moſt precyouſe ſubſtaunce, of the bodye and bloude of our ſauiour Chriſt, is couered, and hidden, from our bodely eyes, for our weakenes and infirmitie as Theophilus Alexandrius ſayeth. And when we call the Sacrament of the aulter, God, we vnderſtand the ſubſtaunce of that ſacrament, which is Chriſt, God and mā there preſent, and accordinge to that vnderſtandynge, attribute all godly honour vnto it, and in this ſpeach, the worde (Sacramēt) ſygnyfieth and gyueth vnderſtandynge, by a ſpeciall ſignification, and by excellencye (as learned men ſpeake of it) the thynge ſignified there
 preſent, that is to ſaye, the bodye &amp; bloude of our ſauiour Chriſt, whiche can not be broken with hande, can not be torne with teeth, or be altered, conſumed, moulded, or deuoured of beeſte, or putrified, ne herein the bodely ſenſes can beare any witnes to the contrarye, for they can not atteyne that. But whē we vſe, the worde (Sacramente) or the worde (hoſte) and apply the ſpeache of it, to ſuche a matter as maye not be ſaide of the naturall body of Chriſt, then the ſpeache is verefied in thoſe fourmes of bread and wyne, vnder whiche, the moſt precious body of chriſt is couered. As when we ſay, that the ſacramēt is broken or moulded, or altered, it is only vnderſtanded of the ſayde forme of bread and wine, beyng the outward accidentes, as the qualities, or dimenſiōs, which god there preſerueth not otherwiſe by outward
 miracle, beyng thē ſuſteined by his moſt preciouſe bodely ſubſtaunce, then when they be naturally ioyned, to the ſubſtaunce of bread, wherof that god thus doth not, mannes ſenſes (becauſe thoſe accidentes be ſenſible) may iudge, for we ſe it ſo, and thoſe accydentes be perceptible, by the bodely ſight and ſence, and with the eye of the ſoule in fayth, we ſe the preſence of the moſt preciouſe body of our ſauioure Chriſte, who there, is the only ſubſtaunce of the ſacrament, ſo longe remaynynge vnder thoſe accidentes, as the fourme of bread and wyne (vnder whiche (by the omnipotency of his worde) it pleaſeth hym to exhibite hym ſelfe vnto vs) doth remayne and cōtinue. Here the deuyll whyſpereth: If god were there he wolde not ſuffre, thaccidentes corrupt, or be violate by any outwarde violence.
 Wherunto (as I haue before touched) I ſaye, this is verely the deuils ſuggeſtion, to make the foundacyon of our ſayth, not vpō godly teachynge, but vpon the continuall outwarde myracle, and nothynge to be in my
                  ••
               ery, whervnto mylde ſimplycite yeldeth,Sainte Au guſtine ſaith outward ſignes draw to chriſt, which in them that 
                     〈◊〉
                   drawē be not neceſſary but in al open violent ſignes, ſuche as the vnfaythfull, could not reſiſte. And yet yf the accidentes of the hoſte, were by goddes power, for declaration of his preſence, made impaſſible, and incorruptible, the deuyll wolde fur her require, that mans body receyuynge the ſame. ſhulde alſo be made impaſſible and incorruptible, by the myght of Chriſtes preſence,Exod. 7. For els Magi Pharaonis wolde preſume to coūterfet the other myracle, &amp; call it witchecrafte, For the deuyl is calumniator, and laboureth to depraue all thynge. But good meane haue yelded to
 goddes true teachyng in his churche, and ſubduyng the carnall vnderſtandyng haue auoyded by his grace this tentacion of the deuyll, to requyre outwarde ſignes, as thoughe god ſhuld teſtify his preſence, in the mooſt bleſſed ſacrament, with preſeruation of thaccidentes, in the ſacrament and theyr bodely ſtate, frome preſente corruption and immortalitie, that receyue hym, and ſo the ſycke manne by the holy communion, to attayne ſtreyghte bodely helthe, wherin al though, god hath ſomtyme for encreace of his glory, and to the edification of his churche ſhewed his power, yet it hath not ben requyred as neceſſary among good men and for the increaſe of our merite in faythe not expedient, ſo as the holy martyrs, who after they had, for theyr ſtrength in martyrdome, which they ſawe imminēt, receyued
 Chriſtes mooſt preciouſe body, in the ſacrament of thaulter, continued neuertheleſſe in their bodies, ſubiecte to outwarde violence to be ſlayne (as they were by tirauntes) wherwith the reſte of ſuche as truely beleued, were not offended. For if the carnall ſenſes, ſhall haue ſuche a preeminence and prerogatrue, as the want of a newe outwarde myracle to theyr ſatiſfactiō, ſhall empayre the true faythe of goddes inwarde workynge with vs, and for vs: we maye worthely be called Gens incredula,
               Mat. 
                     •
                  2. Ruc. 11. Eph. 6. 
               quae ſignum quaerit, &amp; non dabitur e
                     •
                  . By ſuche myſtruſte the Capharnaites, loſte the fruite of Chriſtes teachynge, but we ſhulde knowlege (as the diſciples of Chriſte dyd that Chriſtes wordes be lyfe, euerlaſtynge, And ſurely ſuche as beleue not ſymply oure Moyſes chryſte, and the holy prophetes of
 his churche, they wyll gyue ſmall credence to any other newe myracles, though men roſe agayne frō death to ſpeake with them, but rather ſtudy to dyſproue all thynge, that repugneth to theyr opynion, who beyng lyfted vp by ye deuil in vayneglory, of knowlege, aboue ye pinacle of the temple, thynke they had more wytte &amp; learning then al byſſhoppes &amp; prieſtes that be myniſters of the temple But now cō
               meth the deuill, as a mediatour, in an other cote, and vnder pretence to ſatiſfye all vnderſtandynges, he wolde haue the beleef in the ſacrament in one poynt releaued, &amp; wolde we ſhuld beleue, the remaynynge, of the ſubſtaunce of bread, wherwith to aſſoyle the argumentes of the mouſe, and yet graunte the ſubſtaunce of the body of chriſt to be there, for the ſubſtaunce and foode of chriſten men, which kinde
 of beleef good chriſtē men, taugh by the ſpyrite of god, haue not receyued, for it can not be maynteyued of Chriſtes wordes, who ſpake playnely,Mat. 26. 
                     〈…〉
                   11. 
               This is my body, makynge demonſtratiō of the bread, when he ſayd, This is my body, by the myghte of whiche wordes of Chriſte that was demonſtrate by the demonſtratiō (this) which was the bread, was altered and chaunged into his body, wherby the ſubſtaunce of bread was conuerted in to the ſubſtaunce of his moſte preciouſe body, wherin was declared, Chriſtes meruelouſe power,
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                wherof Theophilus ſpeaketh in this wyſe. Our lorde condeſcendynge to oure infirmitie altered not the fourme of bread and wyne, but cō
               ſerueth them, &amp; turneth the bread and wyue into ye truth of his fleſhe and bloude, and this is the true vnderſtādyng of Chriſtes ſpeach,
 whiche and yf we vnderſtande ſo as the breade ſhuld remayne, then folowe many abſurdyties, and chiefely that Chryſte hath taken the nature of bread, as he toke the nature of man, and ſo ioyned it to his ſubſtaunce. And then as we haue God verely incarnate, for our redemption, ſo ſhulde we haue God impanate, and then ſhuld we haue in Chriſte (beſydes the diuine eſſence) two other ſubſtaū
               ces, abſ
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  
                
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , and be compelled to fayne to the truthe, that chriſten eares abhorre, to the ſubuerſion of the ſame, as we haue ſeen amonge other come to paſſe. Wherfore as the truthe, whiche the churche hath and dothe playnly and ſyncerely teache, is mooſt certeyne and ſure, grounded vppon the playne wordes of oure Sauyoure Chriſte, in the mooſt
 bleſſed ſacrament, ſo euery chriſten man ſhulde receyue it, and beleue it fyrmely, without wauerynge, or diuiſyng any addition to the ſame. Let men forſake theyr carnal erthlye ſenſes, and the wycked kynred of malicious ſeducers, get the out thenſe good reader, and reſorte to the company of true faythful men, and knowledge with them the reuelation in the moſte bleſſed Sacrament, of the preſence of the naturall bodye and bloude of oure ſauyour Ieſu Chriſt, whiche, caro et ſanguis, can not declare, but onlye, Pater noſter,
               Mat. 1
                     •
                  . 
               qui eſt in coelis, who hath declared it, and taughte it oure mother the churche.
            ANother point of the deueliſh ſophiſtrie, is betwene ye wordes and meanyng, wherein the deuyl ſhyfteth ye matter thus. Where the wordes of ſcrypture, be playne, euydente, manyfeſte, and confyrme
 the catholique truth, there the deuyll deuyſeth an other meanynge, and aduertiſeth his ſcholers, that the wordes be nothynge withoute the meanynge, and therfore (ſayth he) we muſt vnderſtande Chryſtes wordes, as he ment them, and therfore (ſaith the deuyl) beware of the wordes, and take hede of the meanyng. Chriſt (ſayth the deuyl) ſayd This is my body, but take hede (ſayth ſathan) what Chriſt ment. O abhominable Sathan, full falſely doeſt thou meane. O good chriſten faythful man, marke thou this ſophiſtrye. For it is in dede a true leſſon, that the very worde of god is the true meanynge of ſcripture, and who hath that true meanyng (which is not taughe by mās wyt and deuyſe of vnderſtanding but by declaration from god, reueled to the churche) he hath goddes wordes, to hys comforte and conſolation
 and who hath the wordes of ſcripture peruerſely taken, is therwith infected and poyſened to his cōfuſion, as the Arrians Sabellyans, and an infinite numbre of heretikes haue ben. So as it muſt nedes be graūted, that in the meaning of ſcripture is the marie, the carnel, the ſwetnes, ye fode, the hony of ſcripture, without whiche the wordes be a bytter ſhale, and an harde bone, without foode or ſuſtenaunce. This muſt nedes be confeſſed of all men, as an euident truthe, whiche the deuyll abuſeth by cauyllacion and ſophiſtrie, to ouerturne the truthe in the mooſt bleſſed ſacrament of thaulter. For openynge of which ſophiſtrie it is to be conſydered, that ſomtyme in ſcripture, the wordes be ſo placed and ordered, as the meanyng is vttered, and opened with the wordes at ones, and hath ſuch lyght of the
 wordes, as they appere bothe togyther, and without further ſerche, be ſtreyght cōueyed to our vnderſtandynge Somtyme agayne the wordes be ſuch, or ſo vſed and placed, as they brynge not theyr meanynge ſtreyght with them in the ſame lyght, but more darkely, and as it were hydden vnder the wordes. Nowe in the fyrſte ſorte of wordes, whiche brynge theyr ſenſe with them yf we ſhuld in them cal for a meanyng, And when we rede, Humiliauit ſemetipſum dominus noſte leſus Chriſtus,
               Philip. 2. 
               factus obediens vſ
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ad mortem. Our lorde Ieſus Chriſte hath humbled hym ſelfe beynge obedyent to the deth, we ſhulde call for a meanyng and ſaye, we muſte vnderſtande theſe wordes, as ſayncte Paule mente them, Can we meane any thynge by callynge ſoo for a meanynge, but to calle the certayne meanynge 
                  〈2 pages missing〉
               
                
               
                  
                     
                        
                     
                     quam
                   aenigma ſit, loēm Heliam eſſe, &amp; intellectu opus, ad intelligendum, inquit. Qui habet aures ad audiendù, audiat. Ita inducens eos vt interrogent ac diſcant. Whiche wordes in latin be in englyſh this ſentence. And yf ye wyll receyue it, he is Helias, whiche ſhulde haue cōme. If ye wyll (ſayth Theoph.) receyue it, that is to ſaye, iudge it ryghtly, and not with an enuiouſe mynde, he is Helias whom the prophet Malachie ſayd, ſhulde come. For ſaincte Iohn̄ that came before Chriſt and Helias. haue ben bothe allotted to one office. The one to go before ye fyrſt comyng of chriſt, and the other before the laſte commynge, And then ſhewynge howe this was a darke ſpeache, yt Iohn̄ was Helias, &amp; conteyned a ſecrete vnderſtandynge in it, and requyred therfore another ſenſe to be perceyued, ſayd, He that hath eares of
 hearynge, let hym heare, ſo inducyng them, to aſke &amp; learne. Thus ſaith Theophilacte, by whome we be learned of the circumſtance, to note the meanyng, if it be hydden, and ſo not onely the wordes to be noted, in theyr common ſenſe, but the meanyng to be aſked and learned, which leſſon neglected, (as the deuyll medleth with ſuch as marketh it not engendreth in ye knowledge of truth, a greate perplexite, wherof the deuyl taketh opportunite to inueigle them, and ſomtyme preacheth, ſomtyme writeth to the vnlearned on this wyſe: Chriſtes wordes be true, when he ſayde, This is my body, but as he mente them. For ſo he ſayde, he was a waye, he was a vyne, he was a doore, but he was not a naturall vyne, he was no ſuch way as men walke in, no ſuch doore, as men cō
               monly entre into, but only a reſemblaunce
 of all theſe, bycauſe he is our waye to heauen, oure doore to entre in to lyfe, our vyneſtocke, in whome, we as braunches be nouryſhed &amp; kepte in lyfe. And ſo lyke wyſe (ꝙ the deuyll) when Chriſte ſaith, This is my body, he meaneth that it is onely a reſemblaunce, a figure a tokē, a ſigne of his body, which ſemeth a ſtronge argumēt, to ſuche as haue not theyr ſenſes exerciſed,Nob. 5. (as ſ. Paule ſaith) to diſcerne good &amp; euyll, that is to ſaye, truthe from falſehode, and ſophyſtry from playnnes. But it is mere ſophiſtry, for in thoſe other places the matter ſheweth, they be ſpoken in a parable, &amp; bycauſe chriſt ſpake ſomtyme in parables we maye not ſaye, he ſpeaketh alwayes in parables. And bycauſe when he ſayde, Ipſe eſt Helias,
               Mat. 11. 
               (eſt) ſingified a reſemblaunce, &amp; not the beynge, as the verbe ſubſtātiue properly doth
 ſignifie) that therefore it ſignifieth ſo in Chriſtes wordes, whē he ſaid. Hoc eſt corpur meum,
               Mat. 16. in whiche (eſt) is declared the verye beynge.Mar. 14. And although when Chriſte ſayd.Luc. 12. 
               Soluite templum hoc, &amp; in triduo reediſicabo illud, Deſtroye this temple and I ſhall in thre dayes,Io. 
                     •
                  . buylde it agayne. The worde (templum) ſignifieth not there a verye temple, but Chriſtes bodye (which argument, one ignoraunte made) we maye not ſaye that therefore the worde (corpus) ſhall not here ſignifie Chriſtes very body, when chriſt ſayde, Hoc eſt corpus meum,
               Rom. 13. And when ſcripture ſaith, we muſt cloth our ſelfe we Chriſt, in which is not ſignified Chriſtes naturall body, but Chriſtes teaching, &amp; ſo the word (Chriſt) hath his ſenſe hydden, we may not ſay, that therfore the ſame worde (Chriſt) ſhall not in another place, haue his owne open euident
 ſenſe, of the ſignification of Chryſtes naturall perſon, Theſe maner of argumētes, may circumuent the vnlerned, and vnſtable, and ſuche as be prone to chaunge though it be ior the worſe but lerned men, ſe thē trifles (ſuch lerned mē I meane as vſe thē not for paſtime, as ſome haue done) 
                  •
                good men, can not be ſhaken or moued wt thē. But heare what ſ. C
                  •
               pri
                  •
               ā ſaith. Panis iſte, quē dominus diſcipulis porrigebat, nō effigie, ſed natura mutatus, omnipotentia uerbi factꝰ eſt caro, This bread whiche our lord gaue, to his diſciples, chaunged in nature, but not in ye outward fourme, is by the omnipotency of gods worde made fleſhe. Which miſterie when chriſt ſpake of,Io. 6. before the vnfaithfull Capharuaites, They aſked, howe god roulde giue his fleſſhe to be eaten, and went their waye, but the diſciples, whō god had prepared by the
 formet myracle of fiue loues, and the miraculouſe multiplication of them, to beleue this, they taried &amp; confeſſed Chriſte, to haue the wordes of lyfe. And where as in other places of ſcripture, where Chriſte ſpake in parables, the diſciples deſired Chriſt to open thē,Matt. 13. &amp; ſaid: Ediſ ſere nobis parabolā. Shewe and declare vs this parable: So when Chriſte, conſecrated his body, and gaue it vnto them to eate, ye demonſtracion of the thynge, neaded no further explycation, to vnderſtand it, but faith to beleue it. For chriſte takinge the breade in his handes,Mat. 26. bleſſinge it, and geuinge thankes,Mar. 14. ſaid,Luc. 12. 
               Take ye, eate ye, this is my body,
               1. Cor. 11. What other meaninge ſhulde here be ſought for, wher be ſo plain wordes, wt ſuche circumſtaunce as can haue none other meaninge, to cōceiue which meaning (as I ſaid) chriſte hadde prepared the myndes
 of his diſciples, when he ſayde. Panis quē ego dabo vobis, caro mea eſt,
               Io. 6. 
               pro mundi vita. The bread that I ſhall geue you, is my fleſſhe, for the lyfe of the world. So as in the very cōſecration, becauſe it was ye exhibition of that, Chriſte had promyſed, and they had confeſſed hym to haue the wordes of lyfe, when they ſawe him, and harde hum execute the ſame, they vnderſtode with his wordes, his meanynge, and beleued hym. But I thinke it muche better to pretermytte further occaſion, of that might be my praiſe, to expound vnto you, the ſcriptures, &amp; omytrynge myne owne ſpeache to lay before you, ſuch expoſition, and opening of the holy, and incōtaminat myſteries of Chriſte, as other haue lefte wrytten, whych I do afterwarde in a ſpeciall place for it, &amp; yet me thinketh here is offered an opportunitie, to write that Ihon
 Damaſcene ſayth alone, For he alone openeth the matter, ſo plainly as he might alone ſuffiſe, for declaration of the thynge, and confutation, of the deuylles ſophiſtrye, deuyſed to impugne the ſame. This Ihon Damaſcene, was a greate clerke, and one of the greke church and wrote in greke, ſo as they nede not to be offended, that loue not ye latyn tongue. Two thinges in him ſhal offendſome. One, that he ſtout lye defended the maintenaunce of ymages, and vehemently inueyed againſt them, that brake them, and wold not haue them ſtand, wherin he wrote ſo vehementlye, as vpon falſe accuſemēt for another matter deuiſed, &amp; cōtriued againſt him, his ryght hande was ſtriken of, &amp; hanged in the market place as ye hand of and offender, whych neuertheleſſe after he had obteined incontinentlye by grace, and fauoure, libertye
 to take it downe, the ſame hande was by myracle reſtored to his body, and ioyned agayne to his arme in perfitte vſe, as it was before, for reſtituciō wherof, he prayed to our ladye, in wordes of this ſentence. Domina &amp; ſanctiſſima mater, quae deum meū peperiſti, amputata eſt dextera mea, ob ſanctas &amp; diuinas imagines, tu qua de cauſa Leo ſeui at non ignoras, proinde 
                     •
                  iocius ſuccurre, dextera enim altiſſimi, quae de te incarnata eſt, per tuas in terceſſiones, multas facit uirtutes, ſanet oro &amp; hanc meam dexteram tuis praecibus. The englyſſhe of whiche prayer is this O Ladye and mooſte holye mother, the whiche haſt brought forth my god, my ryghte hande, is cutte of for ymages, ſuch as repreſente godlynes, &amp; holynes vnto vs, thou knoweſte for what cauſe, Leo (themperoure) is ſo fierce, &amp; therefore helpe ſpedely,
 The ryght hande of the higheſt whiche is incarnate of the, hathe wroughte manye vertues, by thine interceſſions. I praye the therfore, that he may by thy prayers, heale this my right hand. Whereby appeareth, what opinion this man had of images, &amp; praier to ſaintes &amp; by his teſtimony alſo what was vſed in the church, in his tyme, whiche myghte releaue ſuche as can not abyde images, or allowe prayer to ſaintes. For this we haue written of hym, and in greke, and tranſlated by Oecolampadius the Germaine, and printed within theſe ſixe yeares, in Baſile in Germanye, where the contrary opinion, amōg the cōmon people, is mayneteined, ſo as no mā ſhal haue cauſe to diffame it, as ſet forth by any papiſt. But to ye purpoſe. This Damaſcene hath wryttē an excellēt worke vnder this tytle. De orthodoxa
 fide, of the right catholyque fayth, in the .iiii, boke whereof, the .xiiii, chapter,Damiſ. 4. li. de fide orthod
                     •
                  xa. ca. 14. he entreateth reuerentlye thinſtitution of the moſt holy ſacrament of the thaulter deducyng the conueniency therof, from the beginning of our participation of gods goodnes, and bicauſe it is worthye many readynges, I haue ben the rather perſuaded, to write in, the originall in greke, and therwith the tranſlaciō, in laryn &amp; alſo engliſh. Ie ſhal not greatly augmente the boke, and bycauſe ſome children learne greake in this time, it maye ſerue them for a leſſō wherwith to occupy their tender wittes, and conferme them againſte the malyce of the deuyl. The chapter of greake begynneth thus.
            
                
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
                
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
                
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
                
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
                
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
                
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
                
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
                
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               .
            
                BOnus ille, &amp; omnibonus, ac omnem ſuperans bonitarem, deus, cum totus ſit ipſa bonitas, propter immenſas diuitias bonitatis ſuae, non tulit ſolam manere bonitatem, hoc eſt, ſuam ipſius naturam, a nemine participari, quinetiā huius rei gratia, nempe communicandi boni, fecit primum quidē intellectuales &amp; coeleſtes virtutes, deinde viſibilem &amp; ſenſibilē mū
               dum, poſt haec, qui ex intellectuali ſenſibili
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                conſtaret, hominē. Ita
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                omnia, quae ab ipſo ſunt facta, bonitatem ipſius, hactenus certè cō
               municāt, quatenus ſunt. Ipſe enim eſt eſſe, ſiue eſſentia omnibus, quandoquidem in ipſo ſunt, quaecū
               
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                ſunt, non ob id ſolum, quòd exnihilo in eſſentiam ea adduxit, ſed quòd ipſa actio ipſius, quae ab eodem ſuntiam facta, cōſeruat &amp; cōtinet, praecipuè verò ea, quae ſunt animalia, quae ita bono communicant,
 vt cū eſſentia, participent &amp; vitam. Rationalia autem praetereà, etiam rationem, at
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                adeò hac parte, dei bonitate, cōmunicantur multò magis. Sunt enim iſta quodammodo cōiunctiora deo, &amp; propriora, qui tanto tamē interuallo, omnia ſuperat, vt nihil cum eo cōferri, aut de eo ferri iudicium vllum poſſit. At verò homo, ratione iam praeditus, &amp; 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                effectus, (hoc eſt) liberi arbitrij, facultate ea donatus eſt, qua ſe deo, iudicio &amp; electione ſua, perpetuò uniret, videlicet ſi in bono collato, hoc eſt, in obedientia creatoris permanſiſſet. Poſt
                  
                     
                  
                  quam
                autē tranſgreſſus mandatū eius, qui fecerat illum, morti &amp; corruptioni ſuccubuit, creator ille &amp; opifex generis noſtri, propoter viſcera miſericordiae ſuae, ſimilis factus eſt nobis, &amp; extra peccatum, caetera omnia factus homo, noſtrae eo modo naturae vnitus eſt.
 Cum enim communicaſſet nobis, tum imaginem, tum ſpiritum ſuū, quem non adſeruauimus: aſſumpſit ille pauperem iam &amp; imbecillē naturam noſtram, ut nos videlicet purgatos, &amp; incorruptos redderet, ac in integrum reſtitutos, efficeret denuò participes ſuae diuinitatis. Oportebat autem non primitias ſolum, naturae noſtrae, de meliori fore participes, ſed &amp; omnem uolentem quidem certè hominem, cum naſci ſecunda natiuitate, tum nouo nutriri cibo, huiuſmodi natiuitati accōmodo, &amp; competenti, at
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                ita adibito demū ſtudio, aſſequi perfectionis modum. Perna tiuitatem ergo ſuam, id eſt incarnationem, per baptiſmum, paſſionē, &amp; reſurrectionem, naturā noſtram a peccato primi parētis, reddidit, li berā, à morte praeterea, &amp; corruptione. Reſurrectiōis uerò primitiae factus, ſeipſum viam formā &amp; exemplar
 cōſtituit, vt &amp; nos eius veſtigia inſequētes, id efficiamur ad: optione, quod eſt ipſe natura, nimirum dei tum filii, tum haeredes, ipſius autem Chriſti cohaeredes. Dedit ita
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                nobis (vt dixi) natiuita tem ſecundam, vt quemadmodum ab Adam progeniti, illi ſimiles effecti, iure etiam haereditario, maledictionem &amp; corruptionem conſe quuti ſumus: ſic ex chriſto nati, eū referamus, &amp; haeredes efficiamur, incorruptionis, benedictionis, &amp; gloriae eius. Cum verò Adam iſte ſpiritualis ſit, conueniebat etiam natiuitatem ſpiritualem eſſe, ſimiliter &amp; cibum. Porrò autem quoniam nos duplices quodammodo ſumus, &amp; natura compoſita, oportet &amp; natiuitatem ſimiliter duplicem eſſe, &amp; cibum etiam aeque cō poſitum, &amp; duplicem. At natiuitas quidem per aquam &amp; ſpiritum, da ta eſt nobis, dico vti
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                ſanctū baptiſma.
 Cibus vero iſte, eſt Dominus noſter Ieſus Chriſtus panis vitae qui de coelo deſcendit. Subiturus enim ſpontaneam pro nobis mortem, eadem nocte, in qua ſeipſum tradidit, teſtamentum nouum diſpoſuit ſanctis diſcipulis &amp; apoſtolis ſuis, ac per ipſos, deinceps in omnes qui eſſent in eū credituri. Igitur in coenaculo ſanctae &amp; glorioſae Syon, poſt
                  
                     
                  
                  quam
                cōmediſſet vetus paſcha, cum diſcipulis ſuis, &amp; teſtamētum vetus idem impleſſet, lauit pedes diſcipulorum, ſymbolum in eo praebens, baptiſmatis ſacri, deinde panem cum fregiſſet, dedit illis dicens. Accipite, cōmedite, hoc eſt corpus meum quod frangitur in remiſſionem peccatorum. Similiter &amp; poculū, ex vino &amp; aqua poſt
                  
                     
                  
                  quam
                accepiſſet, tradidit illis dicens, Bibite ex eo omnes, Hic eſt ſanguis meus noui teſtamenti, qui pro vobis effunditur, in
 remiſſionem peccatorum, Hoc facite in meam commemorationem, Quotienſcun
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                enim manducatis panem hunc, &amp; calicem hūc bibiris, mortem filij hominis annuntia tis, &amp; reſurrectionem ipſius con fitemini, donec ueniat. Si igitur ſermo del, uius eſt &amp; efficax, &amp; omnia quae cun
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                uoluit dominus fecit, Si dixit fiat lux, &amp; facta eſt, fiat firmamētum, &amp; factum eſt. Si verbo domini coeli firmati ſunt, &amp; ſpiritu oris eius omnis uirtus eorū. Si coelum &amp; terra, aqua &amp; ignis, et aer, &amp; vniuerſus ornatus eorum, uerbo dn̄t perfectus eſt, at
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                hoc adeò per celebratū animal, homo. Si deus ille verbum, ſua voluntate factus eſt homo, &amp; ſanctae, ac perpetuae virginis, purum &amp; immacu latū ſanguinē, ſibijpſi ſine ſemine, carnē ſubſtituit: nunquid qui haec fecit, poterit panem ſuijpſius efficere corpus, ac uinū aqua, etiā
                ſanguinē? Dixit in initio: Producat terra herbam uirentē, &amp; in hūc uſ
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                diem, cum fit pluuia, ſua germina producit, diuino uti
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                praecepto ſimul impellēte, uim at
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                uigorem ſubminiſtrāte. Dixit deus, Hoc eſt corpus meum, &amp; hic eſt ſanguis meus, &amp; hoc facite in meam cōmemorationem, at
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                omnipotenti illius praecepto, donec ueniat, fit. Sic enim dixit: donec ueniat. Fit autem nouae huic agriculturae pro pluuia, ſancti ſpiritus obumbrans uirtus, per inuocationem. Quemadmodū enim omnia quaecū
               
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                deus fecit, cooperāte ſpiritu ſancto, facta ſunt: ſic &amp; nunc ſpiritus energia &amp; actio eſt, quae haec operat̄ ſupra naturā, quae haud poteſt capere niſi ſola fides. Quomodo erit mihi hoc (inquit beata uirgo) quoniā uirū nō cognoſco? Reſpōdit Gabriel archāgelus, Spiritus ſctūs ſuperueniet in te, &amp; uirtus
 altiſſimi obumbrabit tibi. Et tu itidem nunc quaeris, quomodo panis fit corpus CHRISTI, &amp; uinum cum aqua, ſanguis Chriſti? Reſpondeo tibi &amp; ego. Spiritus ſanctus accedit, &amp; haec operatur, quae rationem ſuperant &amp; intelligē tiam. At uerò panis et uinum adſumuntur. Nouit quippe deus humanam infirmitatē, quae plurima quidem uſu &amp; conſuetudine, minus trita, &amp; moleſtè fert &amp; auerſatur, ad noſtram ergo conſetudinē ſe demittens, quae nobis in natura aſſueta ſunt, utitur, ut efficiat ea, quae ſunt ſupra naturam. Et quemadmodum in baptiſmate, quoniam in more eſt hominum, tum lauari aqua, tum oleo ungui, oleo ſimui &amp; aquae gratiam adiunxit ſancti ſpiritus, ac ipſum effecit lauacrum regenerationis: ſic quoniam aſſuerunt homines, panem commedere &amp; bibere uinum, adiugauit illis ſuam
 ipſius diuinitatem, &amp; eadem fecit corpus &amp; ſanguinem ſuum, videlicet, vt per aſſueta, &amp; quae ſecundum naturam ſunt, in hijs collocemur quae ſunt ſupra naturam. Corpus vere vnitum eſt diuinitati, illud dico, quod ex beata virgine eſt corpus, non quòd ipſum ſuſceptum corpus, è ccelo deſcendit, ſed quòd ipſe panis &amp; vinum tranſmutātur, in corpus &amp; ſanguinem dei. Quòd ſi modum quaeras, quomodo fiat, ſat ſit tibi audire, ꝙ per ſpiritū ſanctum ad eum modum fiat, quomodo ex beata deipara, per ſpiritum ſanctum, ſibiipſi &amp; in ſeipſo dominus carnem ſubſtituit, breuiter, plenius &amp; amplius nihil cognoſcimus, 
                  
                     
                  
                  quam
                ꝙ verbum dei verum eſt, efficax etiam &amp; omnipotens, modus autem inſcrutabilis. Quan
                  
                     
                  
                  quam
                haud perindè alienum fuerit etiam illud dicere ꝙ quomodo panis per commeſtionem, vinū ve
 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                &amp; aqua, per potionē, in corpus &amp; ſanguinem edentis &amp; bibentis, naturaliter mutantur, &amp; aliud efficiuntur corpus, a priori ſuo corpo re diuerſum, ſic panis propoſitionis, uinum etiam &amp; aqua, per inuocationem, &amp; acceſſum ſancti ſpiritus, tranſmutantur ſupra naturae modum, in corpus &amp; ſanguinem Chriſti, nec ſunt iam duo, ſed unū &amp; idem ipſum, fit autem hijs qui cum fide dignè ſuſceperint, in remiſſionem peccatorum, &amp; aeternam uitam, in cuſtodiam porrò &amp; tutelam animi &amp; corporis. Incredulis uerò qui
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                minus dignè participauerint, in poenam &amp; ultionē, non aliter ac Chriſti etiam mors, ijs qui eredunt, fit uita &amp; incorruptio, in fruitionem aeternae beatitatis, incredulis uerò, &amp; domini occiſoribus, in punitionem &amp; ultionem ſempiternam. Non eſt panis &amp; uinum, figura corporis &amp; ſanguinis
 Chriſti, Abſit, ſed eſt ipſum corpus domini deificatū, ipſo domino dicente, HOC EST nō figura corporis, ſed corpus, nō ſanguinis figura, ſed ſanguis, qui i
                  •
               ē ante dixerat Iudaeis. Quoniam niſi manducetis carnem filij hominis, &amp; ſanguinem eius bibatis, non habetis uitamlin uobiſmetipſis.
            Caro enim mea uerus eſt cibus, &amp; ſanguis meus uerus eſt potus. Et rurſum: Qui manducat me, uiuer. Quapropter, cum omni timore, &amp; cōſciētia pura, ac fide minime haeſitabunda accedamus, &amp; omnino erit nobis quēadmodū credimus, ſi certò credimus ſine fluctuatiōe. Veneremur etiā illud omni puritate, animi uidelicet &amp; corporis, quaſi geminata ueneratione. Eſt enim &amp; ipſū quod ueneramur, duplex (Chriſti nimirū diuinitate, &amp; carne cōſtans) Accedamus ad illū ardēti deſiderio, &amp; manꝰ in crucis
 ſpeciem formantes, corpus crucifixi excipiamus. Applicatis autē oculis, labijs, et fronte diuinum car bonem concipiamus, vt noſtri deſiderij ardor, huius carbonis ignitione arrepta, tum peccata noſtra exurat, tū corda illuminet, deni
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                participatione diuini ignis, et igni amur ipſi et deificemur. Carbonē uidit Eſaias. Carbo uerò lignum ſimplex nō eſt, ſed unitum igni.
            Sic et panis cōmunionis, non panis ſimplex eſt, ſed unitus deitati: Corpꝰ uerò unitum diuinitati, non una natura eſt, ſed una quidem corporis, unitae uerò illi diuinitatis altera. Adeò ꝙ utrum
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                ſimul, non una eſt natura,Gene. 14. Heb. 7. ſed due. Melchiſedech cum eſſet ſacerdos dei altiſſimi, pane et uino excepit Abrahā, à caede alienigenarum iam reuerſum. Illa ſiquidem mēſa, myſticam hanc praefigurabat menſam, quem admodum etiam ſacerdos ille, veri
 ſacerdotis Chriſti, figuram praeſeferebat &amp; imaginem. Tu enim (inquit) es ſacerdos in ſeculum, ſecū
               dum ordinem Melchiſedech. Hūc autem panem, etiam panes propoſitionis figurabant. Hoc praeterea eſt purum ſacrificium &amp; incruentum, quòd ab ortu ſolis, uſ
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                ad occaſum, ipſi offerendum, per prophetam, dominus eloquutus eſt.
            Corpus eſt &amp; ſanguis chriſti, ad animi &amp; corporis ſtabilimentū, ſuſcepta à nobis, quae non conſumū
               tur, non corrumpuntur, non uadūt in ceceſſum. Abſit, ſed in noſtram ſubſtantiam, &amp; cōſeruationē pertinent. Omnis autem noxae profligatio ſunt, &amp; ſordis omnis purgatio. Si enim aurū acceperint adulterinum, ignitione illa ſua (ut ita'di cam) cenſoria, quae purum a corrupto diuidit, omnino purgant, vt ne cum hoc mūdo in futuro damnemur. Purgat autē hoc ſacramentum,
 morbos &amp; incōmoda omnia, quemadmodū inquit diuinus apoſtolus. Vti
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                ſi nos ipſos iudicaremus, non iudicaremur. A domino uerò iudicati, corripimur, ut nō cū mundo cōdempnemur. Et hoc eſt quod dicit, quoniam qui participat corpus &amp; ſanguinem dn̄i indignè, iudicium ſibi manducat &amp; bibit. Per hoc purgati, unimur corpori dn̄i, &amp; ſpiritui illius, &amp; efficimur corpus Chriſti, Iſte panis eſt primitiae illius panis futuri, qui eſt 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
               Varia nobis ſignificat 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   uidelicet pro compoſitionis ratione, quam ſ
                     •
                  ab 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   &amp; participio ſubſtantiui uerbi eſtimes: ſonat quaſi dicas imminens, quod autem imminet etiam ſ
                     •
                   nō longe abſit, nō eſt tamen praeſens ſed futurum eſt caeterum quoniam proximum eſt graecis eſt craſtinum. Sicen
                     •
                   legitur in act: Apoſto. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   i. poſtero die, hoc eſt craſtino, a
                     •
                   quan rationē cōpyetēter ſonat futurū Quod ſtuerbi cōpoſitionēab 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   et nomine 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   accipias, analogia deducti in adiectiuum ſup ſubſtātiale uerteris, uelſt 
                     •
                   ābiguitatem praepoſitiōis liceret, inſubſtātiale, queſt dicas, inſubſtā tiāmigrās, &amp; quod hic 
                     •
                  pic expreſſit, ſubſtantiā cōſeruans. Ergo in oratiōe dominica panē 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   petimus, hoc eſt, futurū qui nun
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   deſinet, &amp; quae noſtrā ſubſtantiā uare fulciat at
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   conſernet. Illud enim 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , ſignificat, uel panem futurum, hoc eſt panem futuri ſeculi, aut panē ad conſeruationem noſtrae ſubſtantiae ſuſceptum. Siue igitur hoc, ſiue illo modo. Chriſti corpus conuenienter dicetur.
            (S. 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                utra
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                ratione. Nam &amp; in patris Chriſtus nobis cibus futurus, eſt idem, qui nunc paſcit in uia, &amp; uere cum hic, tum ibi, co
                  •
               ſeruat noſtram ſubſtantiam Eſt enim uita noſtra in Chriſto abſcondita)
            Spiritus enim uiuificans eſt, caro
 domini, quoniam ex ſpiritu uiuificante, cōcepta eſt. Quod enim natum eſt ex ſpiritu, ſpiritus eſt Hoc autem dico, non auferens naturam corporis, ſed ꝙ hoc &amp; uiuificū &amp; diuinum etiam ſit cupiam oſtendere. Quod autem panem &amp; vinum exemplar dominici corporis quidam appellarunt, quemadmodum deifer Baſilius, locutus eſt, non id poſt conſecrationem dixerunt, ſed ante ſanctificatam oblationem, ſic nominarunt, Participatio dicitur, quoniā per hoc diuinitatis domini noſtri Ieſu reddimur participes. Dicitur praeterea communio, &amp; eſt reuera, quoniam per hoc Chriſto communicamus, &amp; eius carnē, ac diuinitatem participamus, communicamus etiam dum inuicem vnimur, hac communione. Quandoquidem enim ex vno pane participamus omnes, unum Chriſti corpus, &amp; vnus ſanguis: &amp; concorporei
 chriſto exiſtentes, mutua inuicem membra efficimur. Omni igitur cautione obſeruandum eſt, ne ab hereticis participationē admittere ſuſtineamꝰ, ſed nec illis dare. Et enim ne detis ſancta canibus,Matt. 7. (dn̄s inquit) ne
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                proijcite margaritas ueſtras, ante porcos, ut non participes erroris, &amp; malae eorum fidei, efficiamur, &amp; condempnationis. Si uerò omninò eſt unio nobis ad Chriſtum, &amp; inuicem nobiſ cum eſt, deni
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                omnibus omninò eadem nobiſcum conſentionem et uoluntatem participantibus etiam unio eſt. Ipſa enim unitas ex libera animi electione fit, non abs
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                noſtra ſententia &amp; uolūtate. Omnes enim unum corpus ſumus, quod ex uno pane participamus, vt inquit diuinus apoſtolus. Exemplaria uerò futurorū dicuntur, nō tā
               
                  
                     
                  
                  quam
                uere non ſint,
                  
                     •
                  . Cor. 10. corpus &amp; ſanguis Chriſti, ſed ꝙ nūc per illa participamus,
 Chriſti diuinitatem, tunc autem intellectualiter, per ſolam uiſionem.
            
               THe good, and all good, (ſaithe Damaſcene) and t
                  •
               , excellyng good god, beynge altogether goodnes, wolde not ſuffre the ſame goodnes, that is to ſaie, his verye nature, to remaine ſole withoute participation made thereof, by other. And therefore god, firſte made the intellectuall and heauenlye vertues. After that, the viſible and ſenſible world, and then man of a nature that hath both ſenſe and vnderſtandynge.
            So all thinges whiche be made of god, be ſo farre forth partakers of his goodnes, in that they haue all a beynge, for of hym, and in hym ſelfe, all thynges be, not onely for
 that he brought thē from nothing, to haue a beinge, but alſo for that his operation continuynge lykewiſe conſerueth and mainteineth all thinges that he made. But in this participation ſuche thinges aboue other participate, as haue lyfe, which communicate of gods goodnes, not onely in that they be partakers of their beinge, but alſo of their lyfe. Reaſonable creatures forſoth beſides beinge and lyfe, furthermore participate of gods goodnes in that they haue reaſon, which reaſonable creatures, be ſomewhat more nere and familier vnto god then the other, and yet god ſo excelleth all, aboue all proportion, as neither can there be comparyſon with hym, nor iudgemente of hym. Neuertheleſſe man a reaſonable creature, and conſtitute in fredome with the gyfte of free wyl, receiued therwith alſo power and facultie,
 through his owne choyſe and election, to be vnited to god continually, yf he had remained and perſeuered in that goodnes, that is to ſay, the obedience of hym, that created hym. But after man had tranſgreſſed the precepte of hym that made hym, and was thereby ſubiecte to death and corruption,God vnited to oure nature in chriſt. the maker and workeman of mankynde (ſuch is the tendernes of his mercy) beynge made in all thinges lyke vnto vs, was made man withoute ſynne, and ſo vnited to our nature, And bycauſe he had delyuered vnto vs, his owne image and ſpirite, whiche we haue not preſerued and kepte he hathe taken vpon hym oure nature, thenne poore and weake, to the intente he ſhoulde pourge vs, and make vs incorruptible, and reſtore vs alſoo againe, to be partakers of his godhed &amp; deitie. It behoued moreouer
 not onely the fyrſte fruytes of our nature,Chriſt is the firſt fruites of oure nature. to be brought to be partaker of the better, but alſo all ye hole kynde of man,The better that is to ſay the deite ſuche as are wel willyng both to be borne againe, with a newe natiuitie, and nouryſſhed with a newe meate agreable to ye natiuite, and ſo with endeuoure to attayne the meaſure of perfection. wherfore by Chriſtes natiuite that is to ſaye, his incarnation and baptiſme, paſſion and reſurrection, he hath delyuered our nature, frome the ſynne of our firſte father, from deathe alſo and corruption. And beinge hym ſelfe made the cheife and firſt, and (as it were) the firſte fruites of reſurrection, he hath appointed hym ſelfe to be the waye, forme, and example, to this ende, that we folowynge his ſteppes, ſhulde by adoption, be made the chyldren &amp; heyres of god, as he is by nature, and ſo become coheretours with
 hym: for which purpoſe (as I haue ſaide) he hath geuen vs the ſeconde natiuite, whereby as we beynge borne of Adam, reſembled Adam, &amp; enherited thereby curſe and corruption: So beinge borne of god, we ſhulde reſemble hym, and ſhoulde atteyne by enheritaunce, incorruption, bleſſynge, and his glory. And bycauſe Chriſte is the ſpiritual Adam, it is ſemely that oure natiuite ſhulde be ſpirituall, and lykewyſe alſo our meate. In aſmuſche alſo as we be doubble, that is to ſaye, of body and ſoule, and ſo not of one ſingle nature,Double of byrth of the water &amp; holye ghoſte. but compounded, it was mete oure byrth ſhulde be doubble likewiſe, and our meat  dubble alſo. Our birth then,Double meate, that to Chryſtes fleſh vnitied to be diu
                     ••
                  itie. is giuen vs by the water, and the holye ghoſte. The meate forſothe, is the foode of lyfe, our lord Ieſus chriſt, that deſcended from heauen. For our lorde Ieſus Chriſte, when he
 ſhulde take on hym his death, wy
                  ••
               lyngly for vs, in the nyght in whiche he gaue hymſelfe, he ordred a newe teſtamēt to his holy diſciples and apoſtels, &amp; by them to al othe
                  •
                yt bileue in him. In a chambre ther
                  ••
               fore of ye holy &amp; gloriouſe Syon, eatynge the olde paſchall with his diſciples, and fulfillynge the olde teſtamente, he waſſhed his diſciples feete, giuinge them therin a token of holye baptiſme. Afterwarde breakynge bread gaue it to them, ſayeng, Take ye, eate ye, this is my body, that is broken for you, in remyſſion of ſynne: Lykwyſe takynge the cuppe of wyne and water▪ deliuered it vnto them ſayeng, Drinke of this al, this is my bloud of the newe teſtamēt, that is ſhedde for you into remiſſiō of ſynnes, Do
 this for remembraunce of me, For as often as ye eate this breade &amp; drinke this cuppe, ye do ſhew forth
 the death of the ſonne of man, and confeſſe the reſurrection of him, whiles he cōmeth. If the worde of god, be lyuely and effectuall, and all thing yt our lord wold, he made, If he ſaide, Be ye light made, and light was made. Be the firmamēt made, and the firmamēt was made If the heauens be eſtablyſhed by ye wo
                  •
               de of god, and alſo the ſtrength and vertue of them, is lykewyſe eſtablyſhed by the breathe of his mouth: If heauen and earth, water fier, and ayre, and all thournamente of them, be perfited by the worde of our lorde, and not onelye theſe, but alſo man him ſelf, a beaſt of al other moſt renowned &amp; ſpokē of: If the eſſentiall word, very god (wyllyng ſo to be) was made man, and made the pure and vndefyled bloud, of the holy and perpetuall virgin to be hys fleſſhe, withoute any ſeede of man: Can not he make
 the breade his body? And the wine and water his bloude? He ſaide in the beginning. Let the earth bring forth grene graſſe, And vnto thys day the earth when it raineth, bringeth forth his owne buddynges, beynge by goddes precepte ſtyred &amp; ſtrengthened to do the ſame. God ſayde: This is my body and this is my bloud, and doo this in remembraunce of me, whiche by his precepte that is omnipotente, is done vntyll he commeth. For ſo he ſayde vntyll he came, vnto whiche newe kynde of tyllage the vertue of the holye ghoſte ouerſhadowyng it, is by ſpeciall inuocation, in the ſtead of raine, for lyke as all thyng that god hathe made, is made, by the operation of the holy ghoſt: So nowe the efficacye of the ſame holye ghoſte, worketh theſe thynges that be aboue nature whiche can not be comprehended, but by
 faith onely. How ſhall this be (ſaid the holy virgin) ſeinge I know no man? The archeangel Gabriel anſwered. The holy ghoſt ſhall come downe to the, and the vertue of the higheſte ſhall ſhadowe the. And nowe thou aſkeſt, howe this bread is made the bodye of Chriſte, and the wyne and water the bloude of Chriſt? Wherein I aunſwere alſo vnto the. The holye ghoſte commeth and worketh theſe thinges aboue reaſon and vnderſtandynge. The breade and wyne be taken to this myſterye. For god knowethe mans weakenes whiche with ſome diſpleaſure eſchueth many thinges that be not before by vſe, made ſmothe &amp; familier vnto hym, wherfore our ſauiour Chriſt ſo condeſcendeth to our infirmitie, as he vſeth thinges to vs accuſtomed and agreable, wherewith to make thinges that be aboue nature. And
 lyke as in baptiſme, ſeinge men commonlye vſed to waſſhe them ſelues in water, and annoynte thē ſelues with oyle, Chriſte added to the oyle and water, the grace of ye holy ghoſte, and made it the waſſhynge of regeneration: So for that men were accuſtomed to eate
 breade, and drynke wyne and water, Chriſte ioyned vnto them,The breade and wyne made bodye and bloude, after which makynge there is no more breade or witie, but the bodye &amp; bloude. his godhed, and made them his body and bloude, that by thynges accuſtomed and agreable to nature, we myght be placed in thinges that be aboue nature. The body is verely vnited to ye Godhed, I meane
 the ſame body, that was taken of the holy virgin, not that the ſame body taken, deſcended from heauē but that the bread &amp; wyne be tranſfourmed into the body and bloude of God. If thou doeſt aſke me the maner how it is done? it ſhuld ſuffyce the to heare aunſwered, that
 by the holy ghoſt, lyke as of the holy mother of God, by the holye ghoſte, oure lorde made to hym ſelfe fleſſhe, and in hym ſelfe, withoute ſeede of manne: In whiche matter we know no more, but that the worde of god, is true, of efficacie and omnipotent, but as for the maner is vtterly inſcrutable, and ſuch as can not by ſerche be deprehēded &amp; foūde. And yet it were not amiſſe to ſay thus, that like as the breade by eatynge, and wyne by drynckynge, is naturallye chaunged into the bodye and bloude of hym that eateth and drinckethe, &amp; nowe are become another body, other then their owne body whiche they had before, euen ſo the breade prepared to be conſecrate, and the wyne and water, by inuocatyon and commynge downe of the holy ghoſte, be aboue nature chaūged into the body &amp; bloude of Chryſte,

                and be not two, but one, and the ſame. Whiche worke is wroughte and is to the, that worthely receiue it in fayth, the remyſſyon of ſynne, for lyfe euerlaſtynge, and to be a ſafegarde for bodie and ſoule. And to them that be vnfaithfull and receiue it vnworthely, to their puniſh mente and vengeaunce. For ſo is lykewyſe the deathe of oure lorde. That is to ſay, to ſuche as beleue lyfe and incorruptiō, with the fruition of euerlaſtynge bleſſe, and on the other parte, to them that be vnfaithfull, and were murderers of our lorde, punyſſhement, and vengeaunce
 euerlaſtynge. The breade and wyne be not a figure of the body and bloud of Chriſt, That may not be ſayde, but the very body of our lorde deified, that is to ſaye, made god. For our lorde ſaide, this is not the fygure of my body, but my body, and, not the fygure of my
 bloude, but my bloude. And before that, ſayde to the Iewes, that yf ye eate not the fleſſhe of the ſonne of man, and drinke his bloud, ye haue not lyfe in your ſelfe, For my fleſhe is very meate, and my bloud is very dryncke. And agayne, he that eateth me, ſhall lyue. Let vs then come to it wt a fearfulnes, a cleane conſcience, and ſtedfaſt fayth, and then in al thynges ſhalbe to vs as we byleue conſtantly. Let vs honour  it with all clennes, bothe of the body and ſoule alſo, as it were with a double worſhyppynge. For  the ſame we worſhyp is alſo double, that is to ſay, the fleſhe of our ſauiour Chriſte, and godhed alſo. Come we vnto it with an ardent fyry deſyre, and facyonynge oure handes in the figure of a croſſe, let  vs ſo receaue the body of hym that was crucified, fynally approching with our eyes, lyppes and forehed,
 let vs receiue that godlye cole, ſo as the fyre of our feruent deſyre, receyuynge the fierynes of that cole, maye burne vp our ſynnes, and lyghten our hartes, and by partetakynge of that godlye fyre, be throughly enflammed and deified Eſaias ſawe a cole, A cole is not wood onely, but woode vnited vnto fyre. So the foode of our communion is not foode onelye, but foode vnited to the godhead. The
 body vnited to the godhed, is not to be ſayed one nature, but the nature of the body is one, and the nature of the godhed vnited vnto it, is an other. So as both together, be not one nature, but two. Melchiſedech
 the preiſt of god that is higheſt, receiued and chered Abraham,Gene. 14. with bread and wyne, when he returned from the ſlaughter of the foraine ſtraungers.Heb. 9 That table fygured this myſticall table,
 lyke as that preiſte was ye fygure and ymage of our true preſt chriſt, Thou arte (ſayth god) a preiſt for euer,Pſal. 109. after the ordre of Melchiſedech. Thoſe loues whiche in the olde lawe, were called the breades of propoſicion,Exod. 
                     ••
                  
                that is to ſaye, the breades appointed to an holy vſe, were a figure of this bread. This ſacrifice is the pure &amp; vnbloudy ſacrifice,Bycauſe bloud is not ſhedde, it is called vnblouddy. which god ſayde by his prophet, ſhuld be offered vnto hym, from the eaſt to ye weſt. The bodye and bloude of Chriſte, for the eſtablyſhmente of body and ſoule receiued, be not cōſumed or corrupted, nor paſſeth with our corruptions through vs, into ye vyle place  (fy on ye ſpeach) but encreaceth our ſubſtaunce, and preſerueth it. It is tharmour of defence, frome all maner of annoyaunce, and lykewiſe the purgation and cleanſynge of all fylthe. Certaynlye if it fyndeth
 the golde adulterate, that is to ſay, corrupt with any other mettall, it purgeth it, by the ſame vertue whiche is apprropriate to fyre, wherby it diſceuereth frō the gold, and putteth away that is corrupt, to thintent we ſhulde not be condemned in the worlde to come. It purgeth diſeaſes and all ſortes of annoiaunce. And as ſaith the godly apoſtle, If we iudge our ſelf, we ſhall not be iudged, when we be here iudged of our lord, we be therby chaſtiſed, that we ſhulde not be condempned with the worlde. And thus it meaneth that he ſayth, who ſo euer is partaker of the body &amp; bloud of our lorde vnworthely, he eateth and drynketh condemnatiō vnto hym ſelfe. By whiche ſacrament, beyng purged, we be vnyted to the holye body, and the holy ſpirite of hym, and be made the body of Chriſte. This fode is the fyrſte
 fruytes of the foode to come, which is called 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                in greke. For 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                ſignifieth eyther the foode to come, that is to ſay, of the world to come, or the foode we receyue, for the preſeruation of oure ſubſtaunce. And bothe ſignifications, may be aptly ſayde, for whither it be taken in the one ſignification or the other, it maye well be ſayde of the body of our lorde. For the fleſh of our lorde, is ſpirite that gyueth lyfe, beynge conceyued of the holy ghoſte,Ioh. 4. that gyueth lyfe, for that is begotten of ſpirite, is ſpirite. And thus moche I ſaye, not myndynge by theſe wordes to take awaye the nature of the body, out of this ſacramente, but onely myndynge to  ſhewe, how the ſame gyueth lyfe, &amp; is godly. And yf any call the ſacrament the example or token, of the body and bloud of Chriſt (as ſaint Baſyle ſayde) they ſpeake it not of
 thoblacion after the conſecracion, but before the ſame be ſāctified, It is alſo called participation, for by it we be made partakers of ye godheade of Ieſu, It is alſo called cō
               munion, and is ſo verely, for by it we communicate with Chriſt, and be partakers of his fleſſh and god hed, we communicate al by it togither, in that we be thereby made one. For ſeinge we participate all of one breade, we be made thereby one body &amp; bloude among our ſelf &amp; beyng of the ſame body with our ſauiour chriſt be alſo to our ſelfe eche others mēbres. Let vs thē beware as much as we may, that we neither geue communion to hererikes, ne receiue it of them. Giue not your holy thynges,Matt. 7. to dogs (ſayth our lord) nor caſt not youre precious ſtones before hogges, leſt ye be made ꝑtakers of their euyll beleef, and of their condēnation alſo
 conſideringe that being an vnitie throughlye, betwene vs and chriſt &amp; alſo betwene our ſelues, we ſhal likewiſe be vnited throughly with all ſuche, as we ſhall choſe to participate with vs. For this vnitie is made by oure choyce, and free wyll, not without oure mynde and determinacion, and we all one bodye, in that we participate of one breade (as the holy apoſtle ſaith). This ſacrament is called alſo, the examples of that is to come, not in ſuch an vnderſtanding, as though the very body and bloude of chriſt were not preſent, but that nowe by this ſacrament, we be made partakers of the godheade of chriſt, and in the worlde to come, ſhall participate with onely contemplacion, in the ful lyght of knowledge and vnderſtandynge.
            
                NOw ye haue hearde Damaſcene ſpeake, who well hearde with the eares of hearynge, were ſufficient for the matter too declare, howe chriſtes wordes, as they were playne, for the ſubſtaunce and foū
               datiō of our byleef: So haue they in theyr playnneſſe, maynteyned ye true byleef of the churche, as this author for .viii.C. and .xvi. yeares paſte, declareth euidently, and teſtifieth playnely, yf thou wylt vſe hym, for comfyrmatiō of that thou doeſt fyrſte truely beleue, and not abuſe hym, after the facyon of the worlde, to wrythe hym, &amp; myſtake hym, as ſome men do the ſcripture. And to thintent thou mayſte be the more able, to mete with ſuche as wolde abuſe them ſelfe in hym, and thy ſelfe the depelyer conceyue the godly lerned conſideration, of this writer in the matter: I wyll note certayne thynges vnto the, worthy
 to be noted. Fyrſte this man teſtifyeth, the preſence of the naturall body and bloude, of oure ſauyour Chriſte, in the ſacrament of thaulter, and expreſſely reproueth the vnderſtandynge of them that wolde ſaye, there ſhulde be but a figure, as at this letter G. in the margyn thou ſhalte fynde, ſo as thou heareſt by this author, truth affirmed and falſehed cōdemned. This man teſtifyeth alſo the worſhyppyng of the ſacrament, with inward &amp; outward clēneſſe, deuotiō of the ſoule, &amp; outwarde geſture of the body, as thou mayeſt ſe, in ye letter H. wherin thauthor declareth a cōgruence, and conuemency, that as the meat, which we receyue and worſhyp, is dubble, and conteyneth Chriſtes fleſſhe and godhed, ſo ſhulde oure worſhyppyng be dubble, that is to ſay, of our two partes of body and ſoule, whiche bothe be nouryſhed,
 by this precious meat. And where thou findeſt this letter. A. the author ſheweth that as we be dubble and of two partes, yt is to ſay, body and ſoule: ſo ſhulde we haue a dubble natiuite, &amp; a dubble meat. The dubble natiuite, is of water and ye holy ghoſte, of water agreable to our body, as corporall, and the holy ghoſt to our ſoule, which alſo agreeth, with that Gregory Naziā
               zene writeth, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . As he was ſpirite &amp; fleſh: ſo god perfiteth wt water &amp; the holy ghoſt. And as for this precious meat, ye author ſheweth that it is a meate dubble &amp; not one, as where thou findeſt this letter. L. where he ſaith. The bodye vnited to ye godhed, &amp; deitie, is not made one nature, but remaineth .ii. natures. And bicauſe ye natures be two he calleth chriſtes body our meate
 in ye ſacramēt, a dubble meat. And yet thou maiſt finde in the letter. F yt he calleth it but one, as where he ſaith yt the bread &amp; wyne, chaūged by gods myghty word into the body &amp; bloud of chriſt, be not two but one, and ſo there remayneth the only ſubſtaunce of the body &amp; bloude of chriſte, where as yf the nature of breade remained alſo, he wolde haue called it in that reſpecte, two as he doth in the other places in two natures vnited. And ſo thou ſeeſt where remaine two natures vnited, they be called in yt reſpecte two &amp; double, and not one, and yet againe bicauſe in the conſecration there is not an vnion of breade to the body of chriſt, but tranſmutation, &amp; as the worde tranſmutatiō expreſſeth an alteratiō of ſubſtaūce the ſacrament is not called two, but one. And concernynge worſhyppinge, this is to be noted that
 this great clerke was not ignorāt of the wordes of the goſpel. Io. iiii. that Veri adoratores adorabūt patrem in ſpiritu &amp; veritate. True worſhyppers ſhall worſhyp in ſpirite and truth. And yet ſpeaketh this author of worſhyppyng with the body, for by the texte of the goſpell, is not denyed outwarde adoration with the body, whiche body is with the ſoule created of god, &amp; ſhalbe hereafter glorified with the ſoule, but the ſenſe of that texte declareth the true order of adoratiō, whiche muſt be rooted, grounded, and directed by the ſpirite &amp; truth, and from thence it muſt procede, &amp; where that fayl
                  •
               th, the reſte is hypocryſye. But els yt the body ſhuld not folowe and obey the ſoule, and be affected as ye ſoule is, and with outward ſemely geſture repreſente the ſame, that we myght not ſay as Dauyd dyd,Pſal. 
                     •
                  8. 
               Cor meum &amp; caro
 mea exultauerunt in deum viuum, My harte &amp; my fleſh hath reioyſed in the lyuinge god, there is no ſuch ſcripture, but Chriſtes hauoure in ye tyme of his prayeng teacheth the contrary, for he fell downe on his face and praied. And the publicane commended in the goſpell, knocked on his breſte and prayed. And in this auctor thou ſeeſt an exhortacion for men to laye their handes on croſſe. And good men haue taken greate comforte in, the ſigne of the croſſe, wherewith they haue bleſſed them ſelfe, and haue bene glad to receaue the bleſſinge of other with the token of the croſſe▪ And therevpon Tertullian in his worke,Tertulian. 
               De reſurrectione carnis, ſaith: Caro ſignatur, vt anima muniatur. The fleſſhe is marked that the ſoule may be defended. But to returne to my purpoſe to note vnto ye that is notable in Damaſcene
 in the letter C. to thē that aſke, and humbly queſtion, how theſe miſteries be wrought? lyke aūſwer may be made, as Gabriell made vnto our Lady, by occaſiō wherof thou mayeſt marke two ſortes of queſtions, wherof one proceding of pride arrogancie, doubtfulnes and myſtruſte, declareth incredulitie, ſuch as the Capharnaites made when they ſaid,I
                     •
                  an, 6. How can this man gyue vs his fleſhe to eate? And another in mekeneſſe and humilite, with deſyre of ſo moche knowlege only, as the ſecrecie of ye thinge permitteth, wherin ye hole is remytted to goddes power and omnipotencie▪ with which our Lady contented herſelf, &amp; ſayde, Ecce an
                     •
                  illa dn̄i, fiat mihi ſecundū verbū tuū. Lo the handmayd of our lord, be it to me, according to thy word, which was goddes worde, by the omnipotencie of which whē we ſe, how many thīges
 aboue mans capacitie haue bene wrought, why ſhulde it not ſuffice to ſtay men from further arguing and reaſonynge, in the moſt bleſſed ſacrament of the aulter? Another thing thou maieſt marke in the letter D yt this auctor teſtifieth howe Chriſt made the breade and wyne with water, his body &amp; bloud, wherby thou maiſt perceiue how it hath ben taughte in the churche conſtātlye, that after the conſecration the ſubſtaunce of bread remaineth not and yet it is called breade, for it is called that it was, as I ſhal ſpeake hereafter. And albeit when thauthor alludeth to the cole ſene by Eſaye, as thou mayeſt ſe in the letter K. he maketh thys reſemblaunce, that as the cole is not wood alone, but wood with fyre, ſo the foode of communion whiche is in latin, panis communionis, and in greake, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                hath ye dietie adioined vnto it, thou maieſt perceiue,
 by that ſtreight foloweth, howe he vſed the worde Panis, to ſignifye the body and fleſſhe of Chriſt wher
                  •
               vnto the deitie is annexed, whiche body and fleſſhe, is the ſubſtaunce of the nourriture in this holy meat accordynge as Chriſte ſayde.Io. 6: 
               Panis quem ego dabo vobis, caro mea eſt, and, Caro mea vere eſt cibus, whiche fleſſhe, hauyng the godhed annexed vnto it, is of two partes as the cole is, and remayneth two natures, and ſo is a dubble meate▪ to fede the body and ſoule of man, whiche be lykewiſe two partes of man. And when he ſayde in the letter. D. the breade hath the deitie annexed vnto it, he ſignifieth the body and fleſſhe of Chriſt into which by goddes omnipotency, the bread is conuerted, as thou mayeſt plainly ſee declared by hym, in the place, where thou fyndeſte the letter F. and the ſentence before, in whiche
 he ſpeaketh ſo playnely and openly, as can not be deſyred more euydence for the matter. I can not pretermytte alſo to note vnto the this, that maye ſerue for a leſſon to ſuch as be captiouſe of wordes, and by the outwarde apparaunce of them note contradictions, thou ſhalte fynde in the letter M. that the ſacramēt is two, and not one, and in the letter. F. one and not two which be no contraries. Fyrſte in that place, where he ſayth they be not two, is ſignified that there is not two ſubſtaunces, of the breade and the body of Chriſt, but onely of Chryſtes ſubſtaunce. Againe, there be not two bodyes of Chriſte, one in heauen, anothere in the ſacrament, for as he ſaythe after in the letter. E. the body of Chriſt deſcended not, but as we truely beleue in the article of our Crede, he ſytteth on the ryghte hande of the father, and thē
                yf thou aſkeſt, how can it be ſo? the aunſwere is, goddes worde is omnipotent, &amp; the maner inſcrutable: In the other place, where he ſaith the ſacrament is two &amp; dubble, as in the letter F, there he declarethe him ſelf, that he ſpeaketh of two natures, the humanitie &amp; the godhed. Thou maieſt note alſo, that albeit in one place, he ſayeth, Chriſtes body is verely in the ſacramēt, &amp; it is not a figure: yet in the latter parte, he ſheweth how it may be called a figure, not ſo, but there is the very body of chriſt, but yt it is in ye ſacrament a pledge of the glory to come, and his feadinge vs here, a fygure of that feadynge we ſhall haue in heauen, whiche in the thinge is all one, for Chryſte is the feaſte here and there, but the maner differeth. For then we ſhall haue full fruytyon by knowledge and contemplacion, in the ſteade of oure faythe
 and hope, wherby we receaue frutefully Chriſtes feadyng here. Thou maieſte note alſo in the letter. O. howe afraied he was, to be myſtaken, bycauſe he ſpake of the generacion, of the ſpirite, whereof Chriſtes fleſſhe was conceiued, leſte he ſhulde be ſene to agree wt the Marcioniſtes, and deny Chriſtes naturall bodye. So captious haue noughtye men euer ben, that ſtudy to make of truthe, matter of contentiō. In the letter. N. thou ſhalte ſe the carnal reaſons aunſwered in fewe wordes, with a (
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ) in greake, whiche ſygnyfyeth a deteſtacyon of the ſpeache before, as we ſpeake wyth one ſyllable in englyſhe, fye. And fye &amp; worſe on thē, that ſo ſay, and amend not. And of the cōpany of ſuche, he amoniſheth all to beware in thende, and note his reaſon whye, with that alſo ſaynt Paule alleged of the ethnike
 author. Corrumpunt bonos mores colloquia praua. Euyll talke corrupteth good maners. I wryte now, to the multitude in whiche be manye to whom I neaded not, to haue made theſe notes, onleſſe I wolde for formalitie, gather notes as lawiers do in their leſſons, but yet I take, my ſelfe, ſuche pleaſure in redynge of the author in thys place, who ſo lyuely &amp; godly ſetteth forth this matter, and ſo fully aunſwereth al thwartinges to the contrary, that I my ſelfe delyte to tary in him, and wolde haue the reader do the lyke. For thauthor is notable, and of a great auncientye, that is to ſay, viii.c. and, xvi. yeres, and he writeth in the greake tonge, for a furder teſtimonye, &amp; vnder title, De orthodoxa fide, of ye right catholique faith, whiche hath nowe bene troubled, in this the hygheſt myſterye. And herein they can not
 tel what they meane, nor what they wolde haue: they begyn to ſpeake of an other meanynge in the vnderſtandynge of Chriſtes playne wordes, when he ſayde, This is my body, whych be the foundation of our fayth in their right catholique vnderſtandynge, as the churche hath taught, and good chryſten men beleued hitherto.
            THe deuyll hath another peece of ſophiſtrye, whiche is in coū
               terfette contradictions, wherein he vſeth for a preface and introduction, a moſt certayne truth, which is, that truthe agreeth in it ſelfe, and hath no parte contrarye to another Wherfore ſeing the worde of god, is an infallyble truth, it hath no cō
               trarieties in it ſelfe. All the worlde muſte aſſent herevnto. But thus ye deuyll procedeth to his cauyllaciō 
               ab euidenter ueris, per breuiſſimas mutationes ad euidenter falſa.
            
            
                From thinges euydently true, by lyttle chaunginges to thinges euidently fals, Heauē and earth haue a kind of contradictiō, Chriſt is in heauen, where ſaint Steuen ſawe hym, Ergo he is not in earth,Act. 7. in the ſacramente of the aulter.A reherſall of the dyuylles ſophyſme. Chriſte aſcended into heauen▪ Ergo he tarieth not here.Act. 1. He ſyttethe on the right hand of the father,Hebr. 1. Ergo he is not in the ſacrament of thaulter.Hebr. 1. He is the creature,Io. 1. for Omnia per ipſum facta ſunt, All thinges be made by hym, Ergo he is not a creature made of breade. He dwellethAct. 17. not in temples made with mans hande, Ergo he is not in the boxe vpon the high aulter. Chriſt ſhall deſcende from heauen to iudge the quycke and the deade,1. Theſ. 4. Ergo he cō
               tinueth there and is not in the ſacrament of the aulter. And theſe be taken for notable contradictions and inſoluble ſophiſmes, and in effecte,
 in all theſe argumentes, there is no contrarite or contradiction in ye thinges, but only a repugnaūce and impoſſibilitie to mans carnall capacite. And therefore here is occaſion to admoniſh men by the wordes of the prophet, Niſi credideritis, nō intelligetis. yf ye beleue not, ye ſhall not vnderſtande.
                  
                     •
                  aſ. 7. In this hygh myſterye where god worketh his ſecrete ſpeciall worke myraculouſly, it is ſuffycient to know it is wroughte, thoughe I can not tell howe it is wroughte ne howe it agreth with other of his workes, and yet it agreeth. But in this ſophiſtrye the deuell maketh a man forget goddes omnipotencye, excedynge our capacite, and cauſeth vs to meaſure goddes doinges by our naturall imbecillite. Becauſe we can not be in two places at ones, diſtaunte one from an other, we iudge the ſame repugnaunt in god
 but chriſtes beyng in heauen, whiche ſaint Steuen truely confeſſed,Act. 7. was nothinge contrarye to ſaynte Paules true affirmatiō that chriſt1. Cor. 15. was ſene after thaſcention, to hym in earth. It repugneth not to chriſtes power, to ſyt on the right hand of the father in heauen, and yet fede the infinite number of his people with the ſame his mooſt precyouſe body in erth. It is no repugnaūce, to goddes goodnes, being creator of al, therwt in the fourme of bread to fede vs his creatures, In which we ſay not, god is become the creature of bread (as ye deuyl inſpyreth his mēbres to report blaſphemouſlye) but that chriſt familiarlye, and of a merueilouſe entier loue towardes vs, conſecrateth him ſelfe, in thoſe formes of breade and wyne, to be ſo eaten and drunken of vs.Hier. 2. God fylleth heauen and earth, &amp; is not comprehēſible, to be conteined
 in temples made with mans hand,Act. 17. ne man can lymitte goddes dwellynge place. God hath power ouer man, but man hath no power ouer God. And therefore Salomons godly temple,Mat. 4
                     •
                   9. 26. was no habitation to reſtrayne goddes preſence from other places.Mar. 14. And yet ſcripture telleth vs howe our ſauyoure chryſteLuc. 13. 21 god and man, hath taught in tempels,Ioan. 7. taried in temples,Io. 10. made with mannes hande, and that he dwelleth with good men, and alſo in tē
               ples made with mans hande, for the aſſembly of good menne, where good men truſte to be releiued wt common prayer, and refreſſhed wt the mooſte precyouſe foode of hys bodye and bloude, he preſenteth and exhibiteth hym ſelfe to be receiued and eaten, and there is preſent, and tarieth in the hoſte conſecrate, not by mans ordinaunce (as the deuyll inuyouſly, and ſpytefullye
 ſpeaketh it) but by his owne inſtitution, to be a continuall and daylye foode, wherwith beinge nouryſhed we maye ſtrongely walke tyll we come to the mounte of god, where is euerlaſtynge lyfe. And thys beynge of Chriſte in the moſt bleſſed ſacrament, repugneth nothinge to the continuinge of Chriſt in heauē tyll the daye of iudgemente, whoſe moſt preciouſe humaine body, now glorified and vnited to the diuinitie, is not diuiſible, by time or place ne by multiplication of tyme or place can be multiplied in number, but remaineth in the ſame number and in variacion of tyme▪ or alteration of place, kepeth ſtyll thappellacion, to be called the ſame. And notynge this well to be true, althoughe we can not diſcuſſe it by oure reaſon, we ſhall eaſely auoide the deuylles ſophyſtrye in thys behalfe, wherevnto we maye be
 ſomewhat induced, by conſideration of yt god worketh otherwiſe in vs, who by his gifte of imaginaciō and thinkinge in our ſoule, may repreſent our ſelfe, althoughe not in oure groſſe bodye, whiche is corporall, yet in our mynde (I ſaye) we may repreſent our ſelfe, in dyuerſe places at ones, and one diſtante farre from another, The philoſophers that ſayde. Anima was tota in toto, and tota in qualibet parte, the hole in the hole, and the hole in euery parte, they coulde not ſe how it was, and neuertheles toke it ſo to be, and yet what a contradiccion is it, to call the parte the hole? And furder, do not the wordes ſpoken of men, to a multitude, paſſe holye to euerye one of the hearers eares indifferētly, that ſtand with in the compaſſe of hearyng? And if ye matter be intelligible to thē al, do not eche one heare and vnderſtand
 one as moche as another, beynge the ſpeache but one, and not diminiſhed, by the participation of the multitude? Theſe ſimilitudes, do nothing atteine to expreſſe the high myſterye of the moſt bleſſed ſacrament, and in many thinges vnlike and ſpecially in this, that in al theſe ſimilitudes be no corporal thinges ſpoken of, and in the ſacrament is preſēt chriſtes very body, but theſe ſimilitudes only ſerue to declare yt in theſe lower workes of god, whiche we may call Poſteria eius, there be many thinges excedyng our capacities to diſcuſſe thē how they be yt we know very certainly to be, &amp; yet becauſe they be common &amp; quotidian, maruaile not at thē, &amp; much leſſe doubt of them, &amp; ſuch fondnes hath mans curioſitie, as was noted by this ſayenge. Quod ante pedes eſt non vident, coeli ſcrutantur plagas, that is afore the feete, they
 ſe not and ſerche the coſtes of the heauen. The deuyll tempted chriſt in a rare miracle, to make of ſtones directly breade,Matt. 4. whiche to be the power of god, the deuill then confeſſed, and yet god dyd it not, bycauſe it ſhulde not haue furthered his glorye to the deuyl, who was indurate. Neuertheles god, whoſe power ruleth, gouerneth and tempereth the workes of nature, doth cō
               tinuallye in the worke of nature, make of ſtones breade, when corne is nouryſhed of the ſtones, and ſtones altered and reſolued into erth, whiche nouriſheth the corne ſedes, and encreaſeth the ſame, and lykewyſe in other workes of nature, ſheweth dayly manifold wonders of his power, whiche we conſyder not, becauſe they be commēly done and onely for raritie and newenes maruayle, when we maruayle at ye is done, and not for the thinge.
            
                And herein the deuill vttereth his ſophiſtrye, and maketh vs forget that is continuallye done before our eyes, and by impoſſibilite of our carnall imaginacions, in thinges aboue our capacitie, ſeduceth vs, and deceiueth vs, in the beleef of goddes high myſteries, and ſpecially in the miſterie of the ſacramēt of thaulter, wherby to hynder vs, and depryue vs, of oure great comforte and conſolation, in the ſame, wherein God inſtituted, Memoriam mirabilium ſuorum &amp; eſcā ſe dedit timentibus eum, that is to ſay, a memorie of his maruailes &amp; gaue hym ſelfe mete to them that louingly feare hym.
            THere reſteth now to open the deuils ſophiſtrie, in the peruerſe, croked &amp; craftie expoſitions of dyuers places of ſcripture, ye ſaienges of holy writers, and of ſuch wordes, as be attribute to ſingifie
 and name that mooſt bleſſed ſacrament vnto vs, wherin hathe ben moche paine taken, &amp; moch craftie imaginacion deuiſed, to abuſe the ſimple vnlerned wyttes, and vpholde in errour, the maliciouſe, arrogant and newe fangled iudge menetes. As touching ſcriptures,Theſe fond fooles were caled amōg the garmaynes Toutiſtes for notable folye obteinethe names for memorye of reproche as wyſedome doth honor and glorye I wyl paſſe ouer, the franſies of them, who writhe the principall theife texte, (This is my body) frō conſecration of the ſacrament, to the demonſtration of Chryſtes body, there ſittinge, and then myniſtringe vnto the apoſtels, where in they declare their malyce, that they care not to chaunge the right ſenſe, with any other, were it neuer ſo fonde and falſe. The truth they abhorre, and ſeke vtterly for lyes, &amp; them they embrace, who ſo euer bring them and leane to ſuche expoſycions of the ſcriptures, as helpe to the ſubuertion of the
 truth. But let vs conſyder how ſophiſtically they handle the wordes that Chriſt ſayde.1. Cor. 11. Do this in remē
               braunce of me, for here is made a greate matter of the word (remembraunce) whiche (they ſaye) declareth, that Chriſte him ſelfe is not preſente in the ſacrament, and that the ſacrament is but a memorye of hym, but a remembraunce of hym. And here the deuyll lurketh in a litle worde (but) for in often repetition of remembraunces, the but is taken in, and the ſpeache goethe rounde as though the wordes imported, that the ſacramente is but a remembraunce of Chriſt. In whiche ſpeache if (but) were lefte oute (as the ſcripture hath it not) the worde (memory or remembraunce) is nothinge repugnaunt to Chriſtes preſence in the moſt bleſſed ſacramēt. For ſeing chriſt is the eternal word of god, and deſcēded frō
                heuen into earth not only to ſuffre for man, but alſo to declare the wil of god to be obſerued, folowed, and obeyed vnto of man, whiche wyll of god beyng taught vs by Chriſt we ſhulde not forget, but day and nyght wt the benefites alſo of chriſtes paſſyon, remember therwt the wil of god, taught vs in the ſame paſſion: can there be ſo effectuall a memoryall of Chriſtes death &amp; teachynges declared and taught in ye ſame death, as if with the eyes of oure faith, we ſe preſent the naturall body of our ſauiour chriſt, the ſelfe ſame body that ſuffered? If ye hearing of chriſtes death, entringe at a mannes eares, or the ſeyng of a picture or image grauen, repreſenting chriſtes deathe to ye bodely eyes, doth ſtyrre vp mans memory to haue remembraunce of that is done by chriſt for hym: how moche more doth the liuely preſence of
 chriſtes natural body ſtyr ſuch as perfytely beleue the p̄ſence of the ſame, to the remēbraūce of chriſtes paſſion? And if among men, where honeſt loue reigneth as betwene ye man &amp; wife, ſuch as be godly conioyned in maryage they vſe to leaue for memory of eche other in their abſence, an image of thē ſelues, as lyuely ſet forth, as mans crafte can attayne, knowynge by experience that ye image ſtyrreth vp the memorie moſt effectually: Shulde we not thinke that oure ſauiour Chriſt moch more affected and ioyned in loue to his ſpouſe, the chyrch, than any man is to his wife, hath lefte the ſame churche his ſpouſe, a moſt perfitte image of him ſelfe, that is to ſay, hym ſelf for a memorye, who by his omnipotencye, can exhibite and preſent hys very ymage, hys owne verye bodye without chaunge of place,
 or leauynge his ſeate in heauen, when &amp; as oft as it pleaſeth hym? Who alſo ſo loueth his churche, as we haue cauſe to thīke, he wold do it, and by ſcriptures maye vnderſtand (yf we cloſe not our owne vnderſtandynges) that he doth it in dede in this mooſt bleſſed ſacrament, wherein his preſence dothe moſt effectually ſtyrre vp in good mens hartes, ſuch a remembraūce of hole Chryſt hys benefytes, and preachynges together, as in thys mooſte holye communyon good men be ſo comforted, ſo ſtrenghtened, ſo confyrmed in Chriſtes doctryne, as thereby ſhall in their manours, theyr hauyours, theyr conuerſation and lyuynge, ſhewe and ſette forth in them ſelues, chriſtes deathe with hys reſurrection alſo, whyles the day of iudgement when ſhall be Chryſtes ſeconde commyng in maieſtie and glorye,
 And thus the holy vertuous man Baſile, expoundeth the wordes of ſaint Paule. As often as ye eate this bread, and drink the cuppe of our lord, ye ſhall ſhew the death of our lorde tyl he cometh, which wordes of ſ. Paule declare the ſtrēgth of this heuēly foode to worke this effecte, and brynge forth ſuch frute in vs, not that euerye man receyuyng the ſacrament, ſhulde with his tonge then make a ſermō, how Chriſt dyed for vs, whyche the preſence of the ſacrament it ſelf, preacheth, yf men vnderſtande who is there preſent, and this poynt ſhuld be learned at ones, and ſo perfitly beleued, as it neaded not to be learned againe. For it is the grounde, foundacion,Heb. 6. and begynnyng. But the ſermō preaching, and ſhewing of Chriſtes deathe, of ſuche as receaue thys mooſte bleſſed ſacramente worthely, ſhulde be in their
 maners and lyuynge, theyr loue and charitie, theyr contempt of the worlde and deſyre to be with god, wherby ſhuld appere that by receiuing this moſt preciouſe fode, we remember chriſtes death &amp; paſſion for vs, &amp; practiſe it effectually, and frutefully in vs. For ſuche only, celebrate this holy communiō, with an effectual remembraunce of him And yet euyll men do receaue the ſame, to their owne condemnation whiche good men do with a perfit remembraunce of chriſt, whoſe benefites wt his preceptes, they haue in effectual remembraunce. Wherin foraſmuch as the Corinthyans abuſed them ſelfe, Saynt Paule threteneth them with gods ſharpe iudgement, whyche euerye manne procureth hym ſelfe, when he receiueth the bleſſed ſacrament vnworthely, not conſyderinge nor vnderſtandynge, that there is in that
 feaſt, the very naturall bodye and bloud of our ſauiour chriſt, which ſ. Paul ſignifieth in thoſe wordes non dijudicans corpus domini.
            
            Whiche wordes be tranſlate in englyſhe,1. Cor. 11▪
                puttynge no difference betwene the lordes bodye. And this place by ſuche as preſumynge of their owne knowlege, frame alſo a ſenſe of their owne makynge, or folowinge ſuche as willingly abuſe their knowledge to ſubuerte the truth, hathe ben myſtaken, and of ſome ſo taken, as though the Corinthiās were in thoſe wordes blamed, becauſe they (which is a fond imaginacion, and yet men that wā
               der alone go eaſely farre wide out of the right waye) toke the ſacrament, to be the very body of chriſt, and put no difference, betwene it &amp; breade. But ſaint Paule contrarywyſe (as tholde authors expounde that place) declareth in thoſe wordes,
 
               non dijudicans corpus domini,
               1. Cor. 11 howe ſuche as eate vnworthely do not acknowledge, whom they receiue. For if they dyd, they could not ſo abuſe them ſelfe, and therefore the worde (dijudicans) ſignifieth not, puttinge no difference, but not vnderſtandynge, not conſyderynge, as the greake interpreters ſay. 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , not conſiderynge, not vnderſtandynge who is in that feaſt to be receiued, whoſe preſence if men conſidered, they ſhoulde neade none other admonyſhment, howe to prepare them ſelf to come thither, and howe to vſe them ſelues at the ſame. And other ſcripture, is lykewiſe miſconſtrued and crokedly expounded. Spiritus viuificat caro non prodeſt quic
                     •
                  ,
               Io. 6. As thoughe it were to be vnderſtanded, that the preſence of the natural bodye and bloude of our ſauiour
 our chriſt, were not fruteful to vs, &amp; therefore by theyr reaſon ſhulde not be there, where in dede our ſauyour Chriſt, refelled in thoſe wordes the groſſe vnderſtandinge of ye Capharnaites, as though oure ſauiour chriſt had ment to diſtribute his natural body in lumpes of fleſſhe, and ſo make them a feeſt of it, and thervpon gaue a generall leſſon vnto them, whiche ſerueth for ye true vnderſtandyng of our hole relygion, which is that our godly lyfe is engēdred in vs, not of the fleſſhe, but of the ſpirite, for quod natum eſt ex carne, caro eſt, quod autē ex ſpū ſpiritus eſt,
               Ioan. 6. yt is borne of the fleſſhe, is fleſh, and that is borne of the ſpirite is ſpirite, and the faithfull men be not borne of the fleſſhe, nor the fleſſhe reuealeth not the truth of god, for the fleſſhye manne can not ſe goddes myſteries, and they that dwell
 in the fleſſhe can not pleaſe god,Rom. 8. and thus ſcripture ſpeakethe of the fleſſhe, the carnal parte of man not illuminate by ye ſpirite of god, and the Capharnaites fanſied of Chriſtes fleſſhe groſſly to be cutte as buchers do in the market, whiche ſo cōſidered, profiteth nothing, but onely the ſpirite giueth lyfe. And ſo ſpiritus viuificat, caro non prodeſt quicquam, the ſpirite gyueth lyfe, and the fleſſhe profitethe nothing. By which maner of ſpech the fle
                  •
               ſhe of our ſauyour chriſtes mooſt precious bodye, beinge caro viuifica, lyuely fleſſhe, and whiche hath the holy ſpirite inſeparablye annexed vnto it, is not improued but as it is by goddes hygh power miniſtred vnder fourme of breade &amp; wyne, is alſo moſt holſom &amp; moſt confortable vnto ſuch, as receyue it worthely, of which chriſt ſpake Caro mea vere eſt cibus &amp;Io. 6.
                
               ſanguis meus uere eſt potus, &amp; panis quem dabo uobis caro mea eſt, My fleſſhe is verely meate, and my bloude verely drinke, and the breade whiche I ſhall geue you is my fleſſhe. And the ſpeache of this ſcripture. Caro non prodeſt quic
                     •
                  
                is in ſuch wiſe to be taken as whē ſaint Paule ſaith, Scientia inflat, charitas edificat.
               1. Cor. 8. wherein knoweledge is not vtterlye condemned, but onely ſuche knowledge as wā
               teth, and is not tempered with charitie. And lykewiſe, littera occidi ſpiritus viuificat.
               1. Cor. 3. wherein not all letters and wrytinges, be noted to do hurte, but onely ſuche as be deſtitute and want right &amp; ſpiritual vnderſtandinge. And after ye ſame fourme ſaid chriſt. Spiritꝰ viuificat caro nō prodeſt quic
                     ••
                  
                The ſpirit giueth lyfe,Io▪ 6. ye fleſſhe profiteth nothyng, whiche is as muche to ſaye after the order of vnderſtāding, in
 the former ſpeaches, that the fleſh porfiteth nothynge, where the ſpirite of god wanteth, whiche in the moſt bleſſed body of our ſauiour Chriſt, is alway preſent, &amp; can not be ſeperate from it. Thus I haue ſomwhat trauailed in thexpoſitiō of this text Caro non prodeſt quic
                  
                     •
                  , whiche in dede ꝑteyneth not to ye purpoſe of ye matter, but only as the deuil wrangleth with it, as he doth in ſuſteining hereſyes with many other, and amonge other in this matter, theſe. If I go not from you (ſayth Chriſte) the holy ghoſte ſhall not comme to you. And in an other place: ye ſhall not ſe me, for I go to my father. And alſo in an other place. I leaue the worlde, and go to my father. With ſuche lyke, whiche ſounde to improue the preſence of Chriſtes naturall body and blood in the ſacrament of thaulter, but ſounde
 ſo onely to ſuche, as before they marke this ſoūde of wordes, wold haue them to ſounde ſo. For that meane the deuyl vſeth to inueigle men, fyrſte to allure them by▪ ſome worldelye temptation, to be incline able rather to this or that opinion and in many men, not for anye reſpecte they haue to any truthe or falſeſhed, but onelye bycauſe they had rather haue it vnderſtanded ſo, as they fanſye, then otherwyſe. And beynge ſo waywardlye affected, they conceaue then of the ſcripture, as they do of a confuſe ſoūde of belles, that is to ſaye, the ſelfe ſame ſentence and meaning which they wolde haue taken, and eſtemed for truth, and none other. And to ſuch men, ſo inueigled by the deuyll, it is harde to induce the perſuaſion of truthe, for they care not for it, or be maliciouſe and euyl
 wyllynge againſt the truthe.Sapi. l. And therfore wyſedome (as ye wyſe man ſaith) can not entre into them. The deuyl,Io. 7. 8▪ 11 14. 16. for mayntenaunce of his errour, he ceaſſeth not to note to the ſimple reader, how Chriſt ſpeaketh of goynge his waye, and goyng to his father,Ioh. 14. and in an other place of leauynge the worlde, &amp; in an other place, that he wyll be ſeene no more of thē. And when ye ſpouſe is gone then we ſhall wayle and faſte.Ioā. 16. Matt. 9. All whiche in the true vnderſtandyng, ſignifie to vs the abſence from vs of Chriſte, in his bodely cōuerſatiō among vs, in ſuch ſorte as he was before his paſſyon, and before his aſcention (that is to ſaye) to ſpeake to vs, and companie with vs, as he dyd with his apoſtelles and diſciples,Io. 20. or to be felte of vs, as he was of ſaynte Thomas, to the ſatiſfaction of oure bodely ſenſes, whiche abſence of Chriſte in conuerſation
 repugneth not to ye truth of our catholyke faith, whiche is that chriſt preſenteth and exhibiteth vnto vs, his natural body and bloud in the ſacrament of thaulter. For the diuerſyte, in the maner of beynges preſent, taketh away the cōtrariet
                  •
                that ſhulde ſeme in the matter. Now as touchyng the myſcōſtruynge &amp; wronge takynge, and ſomtyme falſe bearing in hand, of that the good holy fathers of Chriſtes churche, haue written of the moſt bleſſed ſacrament o
                  •
                thaulter. Firſt I ſhall ſaye this, that howe ſo euer the ſame holy doctours do agre, in the moſt certeyne truth of our beleef moche labour hath ben taken to p
                  •
               ke out wordes and ſentences, and diſ
                  •
               eueryng them out of theyr places, by cyrcūſtaūce, wherof they had theyr true vnderſtandynge to make them ſound, to ſuch as wold haue it ſo, to the cōfirmatiō of their
 vntrue and falſe doctrine, in this moſt bleſſed ſacrament. And lyke as ſuche as labour, to cōfound the truth, be the chyldren of darkenes: So in the ſcriptures and doctours alſo, they reſorte to ſerche the truth ī obſcure darke places, where they maye haue opportunite to iuggle and deceiue the ſymple reader. For where the doctors ſpeake playnly againſt theyr falſehead, they fare, as though they knewe not yt place, or had not redde it, and then reſorte to an other place not ſo open and playne, and there fall to cōiectures and conſtructions of theyr owne, and labour in expoſition of thoſe obſcure places, as thoughe they could there more certeynly declare the mynde of the doctours to conferme theyr lyes, then the doctours thē ſelf do in another place of theyr owne workes, where they playnly, openly, manifeſtly, and without
 ambiguite, declare them ſelfe to agre with the truth. And where as the truth grounded in ſcriptures, and opened more clerely by holy writers, hath ben in Chriſtes churche▪ after diſcuſſion and triall ſette forth in a holſome faſhion, and cō
               uenient ordre of wordes, whiche wordes, the true meanyng and vnderſtandyng purged from all ambiguities, whiche mans buſy witte hath alſo in holy wordes engendred, to thintent as we beleue one truth, we myghte alſo in wordes &amp; ſpeache, vniformely agree in the ſame truthe. Suche as labour to breake this godly agremēt in harte and tonge, they neuer ceaſſe, tyll by ſpeache, they maye brynge the truth agayne in a corner and with pretence they meane well &amp; ſpeake ſymply without obſeruation, euen as they haue redde forſoth, in that holye man, for example, (&amp; in dede
 a holy martyr) ſaint Cipriane, for hym they alledge. Whiche ſainte Cyprians ſpeche as it was by hym deuoutly vttered,Ciprianus. not diſagreyng from the truth, ſo is it by theſe men maliciouſly brought forth, wherby to interrupte the conſente truely agreed on, bothe in the ſpeache and vnderſtandyng. I wyll ſomwhat ſpeake of this one ſpeach of ſaynte Cypriā particularly, wherby thou mayeſt eſteme (good reader) the deuyls ſophyſtrie, in handelyng of ye reſte. We beleue truely as the catholyke church teacheth, that there remayneth no ſubſtaunce of bread in the ſacrament of thaulter, but ye onely ſubſtaunce of the body and bloud of our ſauiour Chriſte. And yet ſainte Cyprian, ſpeakynge deuoutly of the food and nourriture, whiche good Chriſten men receyue in the communion of this mooſte holy Sacrament, whereby the body
 and ſoule, be conioyned with Chriſte, vſeth the worde Panis,
               Panis. and calleth ye bleſſed ſacramente, ſacramentalē panem, whiche wordes be not perfitely expreſſed in englyſh, if in trāſlatiō it were termed ſacramētal bread (as malicious fayned ſimplicitie pretendeth) but rather ſacramētal fode, for Panis in latyn is a general word, &amp; ſignifieth not only bread, wherewt mē be fed, but alſo al other nourriture, wherwt man is ſuſteined, which the word (bread) doth not in englyſh, but ſoundeth to vs a name of ſpecial nourriture &amp; foode made of corne. Now if any man ſhall vnder pretence of ſymple playne ſpeache, cal always that breade, in engliſh which he findeth in laten, called panis, he myghte of well, whereſoeuer he founde ſella in latyn, call it in englyſh a ſaddell and then in tranſlatinge ſome places oute of latyn into englyſhe, he
 ſhuld ſomtime ſet ſodenly on horſebacke in englyſh, him that he redde in latyn ſitting in a ſeat on ye groūd Herin the ignoraunt, that perceiue not this, wyll ſaye, I vſe ſophiſtrye but I open the deuyls ſophiſtrye herein, wherwith he doth abuſe the people in ſpeache, and entangle them ſo in it, as they for want of other knowlege, can not wade out, &amp; therfore alloweth him, that whē he readeth in ſaint Cypryan ye ſacramente of the aulter, called ſacramē
                  talem panem calleth it in engliſſhe ſacramentall bread. And here he ſpurneth, and wyll ye make me beleue (ſayth he) that panis ſignifieth not breade? &amp; then for confirmacion, adde this, Say we not in oure Pater noſter, Panē noſtrū quotidianem da nobis hodie?
               Matt. 6. whiche is tranſlate in engliſſhe. Gyue vs to day, our dayly breade? And in dede if I wolde replye throughly herevnto,
 I muſte ſaye more, then it were neceſſarie now to entreate, &amp; yet I may not paſſe it all ouer. For I muſte ſaye that panis in our Pater noſter, ſignified not only bread but all foode, bothe for the body &amp; ſoule, and is ſo well knowen by the expoſition that in thenglyſh, when it is tranſlate bread, we may eaſely conceyue by a parte, the reſte, and by ſignification of ſome parte, the hole. But where as there is an extour ſpredde by the deuyll abrode againſt Chriſtes myracle, in conſecration of his mooſt preciouſe body, in the ſacrament of the aulter▪ whiche errour is, that there ſhulde after ye conſecraciō remaine bread, in this time of errour to tranſlate in euery place the word panis, that ſignifieth in ſome place (foode) into the engliſh worde (bread): can that be without a maliciouſe purpoſe to aduaunce the deuilles enterpriſe
 with his ſophiſtrie, cloked vnder pretence of plaines? After whiche ſorte of outwarde ſimplicite, wherwith to cloke malice: Some when they ſhulde ſpeake of the bleſſed ſacrament, &amp; with the catholike churche confeſſe the truth therin plainly &amp; openly, then they ſay, they will ſpeake as ſaint Paule ſpake, &amp; his wordes they wyl vſe, whiche were writtē by the holy ghoſt, and for ſo muche they ſay true, and herewith they wyll aſke diſdainefully, whyther any man wyll correcte ſaynte Pauls teachinge? as though there were any ſuche ſacrilege intended againſt gods ſcripture, where in dede this is onely deſyred, and neceſſary in Chriſtes church, that one ſhulde vnderſtand another, &amp; al cō
               ceiue one true meaning of S. Paul whoſe moſte holy true wordes, diuers (as ſ. Peter ſayth)2. Pet. 3. haue for ye hardnes of thē, peruerſlye vnderſtanded
 them, for the exchewynge whereof, it is neceſſarely requiſite, that preſeruyng the wordes of S. Paule inuiolable, as they be moſt holy, we ſhuld in other wordes &amp; faſhiō of ſpeche truely agreed on in ye church, confeſſe in all tonges, the truth playnly, in ſuch wyſe as ſuch as haue their beleef eſtablyſhed in one vnderſtandynge, ſhuld alſo vtter the ſame in one maner of ſpech, wherby the ſpeache whiche is ordered of god, to do ſeruyce to expreſſe the inwarde meanyng of the harte, to the knot and coniunction of men in vnitie, be not by the variaction &amp; diuerſitie in it, matter and occaſion of diſcorde and confuſion, wherin the deuyll by his membres trauayleth by all meanes, to diſſeuer that chriſt hath congregate, &amp; to diſſolue that chriſt hath knyt together. But to returne to the doctors and fathers of ye church, who
 lefte moſt playne, and euydent teſtimony in their writinges, of their beleef in the ſacrament of thaulter euen the verye ſame that amonge good men continueth ſtyll. Hathe not Fryth for all that, in a deteſtable boke remaynynge after hym in Englyſſhe, defamed Tertulian, Chriſoſtome, and ſaynt Auſten in that matter? And hath not before hym Oecolampadius in our tyme moſt maliciouſely and vntruelye, in falſely reportynge thoſe holy mē attempted the ſame? And hath not this ben their crafte herein, to ſeke out places of derkenes and ambiguitie, wherewith to deceyue them ſelue &amp; other alſo. As for example. If they redde any doctour in anye place of hys boke, cal the ſacramēt of ye aulter, a fygure, or a ſigne, that place they brought forth, and they put to the deuylles ſyllable (but) and ſayde, thoſe doctours take
 it to be but a ſigne, but a figure, &amp; but a memorie, herein the but, hath done moche hurt, for it is ſleighly brought in, and a ſmal ſillable, For this is in dede cōuenient that chriſt in his body lyuing, ſhulde be a fygure, ſigne, and memory of his body deade vpon the croſſe for vs, &amp; Chriſt in the ſacrament of thaulter to be a figure of his miſticall body the churche, whiche he vnitethe to him in that ſacrament, and of that effecte, the ſacrament of thaulter is named the holy communion,Vnus panis 
                     •
                  num corpus multi ſumus qui de uno pane &amp; uno calice participamus. and becauſe the maner of Chriſtes beinge in the ſacrament, differeth frō his maner of beynge as he ſatte at the borde with his diſciples,1 Cor. 10. althoughe the ſelfe ſame body was in the ſacramente, that ſatte at the boorde, and the ſelfe ſame body is now in the ſacrament, that is nowe in heauen, not by ſhyftynge of places, but by omnypotencye whereby
 god maye do all, for theſe conſiderations in all theſe reſpectes, the ſpeache hath not ben abhorred to call the ſacrament of thaulter a fygure, and to call it a ſigne, and a memoriall,Beware of the excluſyues, that they exclude the not frō the frute of the truthe, for ſo it is, but not only a fygure, not onelye a ſigne, not onlye a memoriall, but therewith the thynge it ſelfe, as the ſame doctours that haue vſed, thoſe wordes (ſygne) and (fygure), do plainely teſtyfye. Nowe yf mans wytte, by the deuylles inſtygacyon, ſhall trauaile with ſophiſticacion in wordes, to ſubuerte the truthe: what can remaine vntouched, of that we ſhoulde haue mooſt ſure? We beleue truelye, that Chryſte is the ſame ſubſtaunce with his father, to the condemnacion of tharrians. And yet ſaint Paule in his epiſtle to the Hebrewes, calleth chriſte, the image of his fathers ſubſtaunce.Heb. 1. Then (ſaythe the deuyl) yf Chryſt
 be but the ymage of his fathers ſubſtance (do ye not ſe howe (but) crepeth in) then is he not the ſame ſubſtaunce. Nowe bycauſe Chriſte ſheweth vs the father, as he ſayde to Philip,Ioh. 14. 
               Philippe qui videt me, uidet &amp; patreim, Phylyppe, he that ſeeth me, ſeeth my father, and in another place.Luc. 10. 
               Nemo nouit patrem niſi filius, et cui voluerit filius reuelare, No mā knoweth the father but his ſonne, and to whom he wil reueale it. Et deū nemo uidit un
                  
                     •
                   vnigenitus filius, ipſe ennarrauit.
               Io. 1. Neuer man ſawe god, his onelye begotten ſonne, hathe ſhewed him forth: For theſe effectes, chriſte is the ymage of the fathers ſubſtaunce and we may not therfore, make the deuyls addition of (but), or make the captious ſophiſme of Me
                  •
               demus.This was a notable ſophiſte. 
               Alterum ab altero, alterum eſt, The image is not the thing wherof it is ye image, as mā
                is not god, of whom he is ye image Ergo Chriſt, is not the ſame ſubſtaunce with the father, beyng (as Saynte Paules wordes before reherſed purport) the ymage of his ſubſtaunce. And as this argumēt is folyſſhe in this pointe, and yet captious to deceiue the vnlearned: So be the argumentes, made againſt the ſacrament of the aulter, of the worde (fygure) or the worde (ſygne) or the worde (memorye) or the worde (Symbolum) token, whiche wordes for a certeine relatition, may be ſpoken of it, withoute preiudice of the true ſubſtaunce, there preſent,Luthers ſecte in wordes graunte the preſēce, and yet in dedes deny it, whē they forbyd the worſhyppynge of it. of ye body and bloude of Chriſt, beſydes thoſe relations. And thus Luther, and all that folowed hym haue defended againſt Oecolampadius, and enforced Bucer, by declaration of the places, to yelde vnto hym in it, and to confeſſe the preſence of the
 natural body of our ſauiour chriſt, notwithſtanding thoſe termes of (figure, ſigne, and memorie) the miſconſtruynge wherof, was but mere cauillacion &amp; ſophiſtrie. So as to cōdemne the madnes of ſuch as folowe Frith, or Oecolampadius, or ſwinglius, or amonge vs, Ioye, Bale, Turner, or ſuch like, ye deuils lymmes: the truth of Chriſtes church hath thayde of al Luthers ſecte, But wtout their ayde the truthes ſtrength is ſufficient. &amp; bycanſe thou mayſt ſe (reader) how playnly ye holy fathers haue ſpoken of ye moſt bleſſed ſacramēt, wherby the more to abhorre the blaſphemy of ſome, ſuch wretches, as moſt vyllainouſly write, ſpeake (and as they dare) ieſt at this day: I wyl of certaine notable writers, ſuch only as were before one thouſand yere paſt take out theyr playn confeſſion of this moſt bleſſed Sacrament,
 by redyng wherof, good men may cōceiue as much ioyfull pleaſure, to the confirmation of their beleef, and ſwete meditation therin, as lewde, lyght perſons, take wanton delite to here ſcoffing &amp; 
                  •
               eſtinge, to the deprauation of the ſame, non diiudicātes corpus domini.
               1. Cor. 11. And fyrſt, I ſhall reherſe, yt hath bē ſpoken of this preciouſe ſacramente, by one of the firſt ſince chriſt,D: Andreas. Apo. as of ſaint Andrewe thapoſtle, who continuing cōſtantly, in the true confeſſion of chriſt, and abhorryng ydolatry, when he was moued therunto, by Egeas, ſaid in this wiſe. Omnipotenti deo, qui unus &amp; uerus eſt, ego omni die ſacrifico, nō thuris fumū, nec taurorū mugiētiū carnes, nec hircorū ſanguinē, ſed immaculatum agnū, quotidiè in altari crucis ſacrifico. cuius carnes, poſt
                     •
                   omnis populꝰ credentium, manducauerit, &amp; eius
 ſanguinem biberit, agnus qui ſacrificatus eſt, integer perſeuerat &amp; vnus, Et cum verè ſacrificatus ſit, &amp; verè carnes eius manducatae ſint a populo, &amp; verè ſanguis eius bibi 
                     •
                  us: tamen (vt dixi) integer permanet, &amp; immaculatus &amp; vnus. I do euery day (ſayd ſaint Andrewe) ſacrifice to God almyghty,Here is eatinge &amp; dri
                     •
                   king, which to our ſenſes is aſmuche to ſaye, as tearing and cōſuming, ioyned with the true cō
                  fiſſ
                     •
                  on of Chriſtes imp
                     •
                  ſſibilite immortalytie. whiche is the true and one god, not the ſmoke of incenſe not the fleſſhe of lowing bulles, not the bloude of gootes, but I ſacrifice dayly in the aulter of the croſſe, the lambe withoute ſpotte, whoſe fleſſhe after all the faythfull people haue eaten it, and droncke the bloude of it, the lambe that is ſacrificed,He ſaith not in fygure, but verely eaten 
                     •
                   v
                     •
                  rely dronken. contynueth hole and on lyue. And all be it this lābe is verely ſacrificed, and the fleſhe of it verelye eaten of the people, and the bloude of it verelye drunken: yet, as I ſayde, it remaynethe hole, without ſpotte, and ſtyll
 on liue. Theſe be the wordes of the holye Apoſtle and martyr ſainte Andrewe, who knewe the truth of that is written by the euangelyſtes, before the Euangelyes were wrytten, and he knewe it taughte of our ſauiour Chriſte, and ſpeakethe herein conſonantlye, to the wordes of ſcrypture and the faythe of the catholyque churche, wherein yf thou wylte ſpurne, becauſe Saynte Andrew ſpeaketh of daylye ſacrifice, and Sainte Paules true doctryne is that, Chriſt was but ones ſacrificed on the croſſe, &amp; then it was (as ſaint Paule ſayeth to the Hebrewes) perfited for euer,Heb. 8. beynge a hole and ſufficient ſacryfice, for all the ſynnes of the world: Thou doeſt herein reherſe a true ſayeng of ſaynt Paule, ſuche as all the worlde muſt confeſſe. For the ſacrifice of Chriſte, is eternall and is one, perfyte, conſummate, ſuffycient,
 auayleable ſacrifice, and nedeth no repetitiō, or iteracion, for the more validitie of it. And yet this truth, is nothing touched or preiudicate, with ye dayly ſacrifice of Chriſt in the aulter, whiche to him yt beleueth is eaſely declared, &amp; to hym that will wrāgle againſt all truthe, is in vayne entreated of, and (as Hylarius ſayth (Non eſt humano aut ſeculi ſenſu,
               Hilarius. 
               in rebus dei loquendū. Godly matters ſhulde not be commened of, after carnall vnderſtandynge▪ But as ſaynte Andrewe ſpake, ſo ye church doth practyſe it. For Chryſte is daylye offered and ſacryficed on the aulter. If thou aſkeſt by what auctorytie, it may be aunſwered, by thauctorytie of Chryſtes word, who ſaid,Luc. 22. 
                     〈◊〉
                   11. 
               Hoc facite Do this, and ſaynte Paule as Damaſcene noteth it, ſheweth howe longe, in the wordes donec ueniat, tyl he come,
 &amp; hath from the beginning taught his church ſo to vnderſtande hym▪ If thou aſkeſt, howe can (ones) &amp; (manye tymes) ſtande togyther? This (howe) declareth, yf if it be contencyous, thou doeſt not yet beleue, but arte in myſtruſte of the churche, that teacheth the, and if thou aſkeſt in humilitie. Sainte Chryſoſtome in expoundinge that place of ſ. Paule to the Hebrewes, where he ones offeringe is ſpoken of,D. Chriſoſt. ſup epiſtl. ad Hebreos. openeth and dyſcuſſethe thy doubte, as foloweth. Nonne per ſingulos dies offerimus? Offerimꝰ quidem, ſed ad recordationem facientes mortis eius. Et una eſt haec hoſtia, non multae. Quomodo vna eſt, &amp; non multae? Et quia ſemel oblata eſt illa, oblata eſt in ſancta ſanctorum: hoc autem ſacrificium, exemplar eſt illius, idipſum ſemper offerimus. Nec nūc quidem alium agnum, craſtina aliū
                   ſed ſemper idipſum. Proinde un
                     •
                   eſt hoc ſacrificium. Aliquin hac ratione, quoniā in multis locis offertur, multi Chriſti ſunt? Nequaquā, ſed unus vbi
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   eſt Chriſtus, &amp; hîc plenus exiſtens, &amp; illic, plenus, unum corpus. Sicut enim qui vbi
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   offertur, vnum corpus eſt &amp; non multa corpora: ita etiam &amp; unum ſacrificium. Pōtifex autem noſter ille eſt, qui hoſtiam mundantem nos, obtulit, ipſam offerrimus &amp; nunc quae tunc oblata eſt, conſumi non poteſt. Hoc autem quod nos facimus, in commemorationem quidē fit eius, quod factū eſt. Hoc enim facite (inquit) in meā cōmemorationē. Nō aliud ſacrificiū, ſicut pontifex,Heb. 9. ſed idipſum ſemper facimus, magis autem recordationem ſacrificij operamur. Sed quia ſacrificij huius mētionem feci, uoeo pauca ad vos dicere, quae recor damini, pauca quidem menſura,
 magnam autem habentia virtutē &amp; vrilitatem. Non enim noſtra ſūt, ſed diuini ſpiritus, quae dicuntur. Quae ergo ſunt. Plurimi ex hoc ſacrificio, ſemel accipiunt in toto anno, alij bis, alij ſaepius. Ad omnes ergo nobis ſermo eſt, non ad eos qui hîc ſūt tantum, ſed etiam ad eos qui in eremo ſedent, Illi enim ſemel in anno perticipantur, fortaſſis enim &amp; poſt duos annos. Quid ergo eſt? Quos magis acceptamus? Eos ne qui ſemel, an eos qui ſaepius, an illos qui rarò accipiūt? Ne
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   illos qui ſemel, ne
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   qui ſaepius, ne
                  
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   qui rarò, ſed eos qui cum munda cōſcientia qui cum mundo corde, cum uita irreprehenſibili, iſtùc ſemper accedunt. Qui verò tales nō ſunt, ne
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ſemel. Quid ita? quia iuditium ſibi accipiunt, &amp; damnationem &amp; ſupplicium. Et nō mireris. Sicut enim cibꝰ, naturaliter nutritorius
 extans, ſi in eum qui prauis cibis corruptus eſt, incidat, omnia perdit &amp; corrūpit, efficitur occaſio morbi: ſic etiam iſta quae ad haec terribilia pertinent ſacramenta. Frueris menſa ſpiritali, menſa regali, &amp; iterum polluis coeno os tuum, perungis vnguento praecioſo, &amp; iterum foetoribus illud imples. Dic mihi rogo, poſt annum, perceptionem participaris, quadraginta dies putas tibi ſufficere, admundationem peccatorum totius temporis, &amp; iterum ſeptimana tranſeunte, trades teipſum ſcrdibꝰ primis? Dic enim mihi, ſi ſaluus factꝰ quadraginta diebus ab egritudine longa, iterum te illis morbificatoribus cibis tradas, nonne &amp; primum laborem perdes? Si enim naturalia ſic mutantur, quanto amplius uoluntaria? Vt puta ueluti quid dico. Naturaliter uidemus, &amp; ſanos habemus oculos, ſecundum naturam
 ſed aliquando ex mala quadam affectione, leditur noſter obtutus, Si igitur naturalia mutantur, quanto amplius quae ad voluntatem pertinent? Quadraginta dies, tantum tribuis ſaluti animae tuae, arbitror autem quia neꝰ quadraginta dies, &amp; ſperas propitiari deum. locaris magis. I wyl trāſlate al this place for it maye edifie the reder, in this, &amp; other matter. Do we not (ſaith ſ. Chriſoſtome) offer daylye? We do in dede offer,It is ſpecially to be marked how ſ, Chriſoſtom 
                     •
                  alleth it the ſame ſacrifice, but in remēbraūce of his death. And it is one ſacrifice &amp; not many? Howe is it one, and not many. For being ones offered, it is thē preſēted, in ye inward moſt holy place, wherof this our ſacrifice, is a repreſētaciō, ſo as we offer alway the ſame, not one lambe now, &amp; another at another tyme, but at all tymes ye ſame. So as it is but one ſacrifice, or els by the ſame reaſō, bycauſe chriſt is offred in many places
 we myght ſaye there were many Chriſtes,The ſame one Chriſte offered in euery place. whiche is not to be allowed, for in eueryplace of offering is but the ſame one Chryſt, here ful &amp; hole Chriſt, and there full &amp; hole chriſt,The circū
                  ſtaunces of tyme and place encrcaſe
                     ••
                   acompte in nūber whē wa ſpeake of the ſacryfice of chriſt and euery where, ye ſame one bodye, And as the ſacrifice, euerye where, where it is offered, is one body, and not many bodyes, ſo it is alſo, but one ſacrifice. And our chiefe byſhop, is he that offred the hoſte, that clenſed vs, and the ſame hoſte, we offer alſo nowe, whiche beinge then offred, could not be conſumed For that we do, is in remembraūce of that was done. For Chriſt ſaide Do this in remembraunce of me: Wherein we do not make another ſacrifice, as the byſhop of the olde lawe dyd, but make alwaies the ſame ſacrifice, or rather worke the repreſētatiō of ye ſame, But becauſe I haue made mention of this ſacrifice. I wil ſpeake a fewe wordes
 to you, whiche ye remember, a fewe wordes in meaſure, but conteynynge greate pyth and commodite for you. That I ſhal ſay, procedeth not of my ſelfe, but of thinſtigatiō of gods holy ſpirite. What wyll I ſay then? This it is, that many be partakers of this ſacrifice ones in the yere,This is to be noted for the vſe of the churche in his time ſome twyſe, and ſome oftener. My ſpeache is directed to all, not only to thoſe that be here, but alſo thoſe that ſyt in wyldernes. For ſuch be houſeled ones in the yere, peraduenture not in two. What is the matter then? Whome do we mooſt allowe? Thoſe that receyue ones in the yeare, thoſe that receiue oftner, or thoſe that receiue ſeldome. Neither thoſe that receiue ones, nor them that receiue oftner, nor them that receyue ſeldome, but thoſe that alwayes comme to be partetakers of thys ſacryfyce, with a cleane conſcience, with a
 clene harte, and a lyfe wythoute reproche. And thoſe that be not ſuche,He required not onelye faythe, but faith with a company of manye vertues, I allowe them not to come ones, Why ſo? Bycauſe they receyue iudgement, damnacion and puniſhment. And hereof maruaile not. For as meate beinge naturally nouriſhynge, when it happeneth to come into hym, that is corrupted with euyl meates, marreth and corrupteth all, and is occaſion of a ſycknes and diſeaſe: So lykewiſe, yt is cōteined in this dredful ſacramēt, where thou haſt fruition of ſpirituall foode,He callethe it a dredful ſacramente haſte fruition of the kynges table, and after defyleſt thy mouthe againe wt fylthy mire, yu art throughly anoynted with ye precious anointmēt, and fylleſt thy ſelfe againe, with euyl ſauering ſtēches, I pray the tel me. Ones in the yere, thou repareſt to this holy communion. Doeſt thou thinke .xl. dayes ſufficient,
 to clenſe thy ſynnes of all that tyme paſt,Thus was the lente ſpent in the prymatyue church, and nowe ſome wold vſe it like other tymes. &amp; within a weke after, returne to thy former filthynes? How ſaieſt thou to me, If yu wart in .xl. daies, healed frō a long bodely diſeaſe, &amp; ſhuldeſt returne to that meate, that was cauſe of thy diſeaſe, haddeſt thou not loſt thy former labour? If the natural partes of man, be ſo ſone altered, with moch leſſe, the partes of mās wyll, may be chaunged, wherein I mene this, that as we naturally ſe, and haue by natures ordre hole eyes, yet by ſome alteration oure ſyghte is hurte. And yf thynges yt be natural in vs, be ſo ſone chaū
               ged: moch more that is ordred by our wyl &amp; is voluntarie. Spareſt thou onelye .xl. dayes to to prouyde for thy ſoule helthe? I thinke not al togither ſo muche, and yet thou hopeſte, to haue god pleaſed with the. Thou doeſt rather tryfle. Hitherto
 I haue tranſlate Chryſoſtomes ſentence, and to note vnto the theſe fewe wordes, laſte ſpoken.
            What wolde Chriſoſtome ſaye, to the ſtate of this worlde, nowe? in whiche a nombre do not onelye neglecte, to appoint ſo much tyme, as the lente is (whiche Chriſoſtom meneth) to attayne goddes fauoure againe, but thinke it al ſuperfluous and not neceſſarie. And boſt onlye the mercy of god, without feare of his iuſtice. Marke this place of Saynte Chriſoſtome and compare it to onely faith, marke this place of ſaynte Chriſoſtom, &amp; note how the .xl. dayes in ye lēt, were ſpēt not by the byſhoppe of Romes ordinaunce, but by directiō of ye true diſcipline in chriſtes church, in whiche, Miſecordia &amp; veritas,
               Pſ
                     •
                  . 34. 
               abuia uerūt ſibi, iuſtitia &amp; pax, oſculatae ſūt As wherin mercy was ſo preached, as ye truth of gods iuſtice, was not
 neglected, &amp; iuſtice in due order of al thinges, was ſo decētly obſerued as peace and concord remained in chriſtes church. But this matter is beſides the principall purpoſe, and yet not out of al purpoſe, for this time. In ſ. Chriſoſtoms interpretation concernyng daily ſacrifice of chriſtes body &amp; bloud, thou maiſt ſe (reader) how the church hath obſerued this moſt preciouſe continual ſacrifice of Chriſt hym ſelfe, by himſelfe the high preiſt for euer, after the order of Melchiſedech offred on the aulter, where the miniſter of the church by Chriſtes commaundemente executethe the ſame, whiche commaundement (as Chryſoſtome ſaythe) is conteyned in theſe wordes. Hoc facite, Nowe I returne to reherſe other,Luc. 22: 1. Cor. 11. that haue ſpoken of the mooſt bleſſed ſacrament of the aulter, among whome Ignatius, a gloriouſe martyr andIgnatius.
                
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
                
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
                nexte vnto the apoſtles, in an epiſtle that he writeth to ye Romaines ſaith in this wiſe, Panem dei uolo panē coeleſtem uitae, qui eſt caro Ieſu Chriſti, filij dei uiui, qui natus eſt in nouiſſimo, ex ſemine Dauid &amp; Abrahae, &amp; potum volo ſanguinem eius, qui eſt dilectio in corruptibilis, &amp; vita aeterna. I deſyre, ſaith Ignatius,Chriſtes doctrine is foode &amp; called panis, but in the ſacrament of thaulter in the fleſſhe of Chriſte, &amp; therefore he ſpeketh here of the ſacramente. the fode of god, the heauenly foode of lyfe, whiche is the fleſſhe of Ieſu Cyriſt, the ſonne of the lyuynge god, who was borne in the laſte tyme, of the ſede of Dauid and Abrahā, and I deſyre for drincke the bloud of hym, who is loue without corruption, and lyfe euerlaſtinge. And to thintent thou mayeſt perceiue, reader, that this nourriture is vnderſtanded of the body and ſoule togyther, ſo as in this holy communion mans fleſſh is alſo comforted herewith: Note what Ireneus ſayth.Iron
                     •
                  us. 
               Quomodo
 negant carnem capacem eſſe donationis dei, qui eſt uita aeterna, quae &amp; ſanguine &amp; corpore Chriſti nutritur, &amp; membrū eius ſit? quēadmodum Apoſtolus ait, in ea quae eſt ad Epheſios epiſtola: Quoniā membra ſumus corporis eius,
               Ephe. 5. 
               de carne eius &amp; de oſſibus eius, non de ſpirituali aliquo &amp; inuiſibili, homine dicens haec. Spiritus enim ne
                  
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   carnem ne
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   oſſa habet,
               Luc. 24 
               ſed ea diſpoſitione quae eſt ſecundum hominem, quae ex carnibus &amp; neruis conſiſtit, qui de calice, qui eſt ſanguis eius nutritur, &amp; de pane qui eſt corpus eius augetur. Whyche may be englyſhed thus. Howe cā it be denied that mans fleſſhe may be partetaker of the gifte of god,Mans fleſh partaker of the gifte of god. who is lyfe euerlaſtynge, conſyderynge it is nouryſſhed wyth the bloude and body of Chriſte, as the apoſtle ſayth in his epyſtle to the
 Epheſians: For we be membres (ſaith the apoſtle) of his bodye, of the fleſſhe of hym and of the bones of hym,Ephe. 5. whyche thynges thapoſtle ſpeaketh not of anye ſpirituall or inuiſible man, for a ſpirite hath neither fleſſhe nor bones, but it is ſpoken of ſuche an habitude, diſpoſicion and compoſition, as man in his owne nature hathe, whiche conſyſteth of fleſſhe and ſenewes, beynge nouriſhed of the cuppe, which is Chriſtes bloude, and encreaſed of the breade, whyche is his bodye. This ſayth Ireneus. And Tertulian as foloweth.Tertull. 
               Videamus nunc de propria chriſtiani nominis forma, quanta huic ſubſtantiae friuolae ac ſordidae, apud deum praerogatiua ſit, etſi ſufficeret illi, ꝙ nulla omnino anima ſalutem poſſit adipiſciniſi dum eſt in carne, crediderit, adeò caro ſalutis eſt cardo, de qua
 cum anima deo alligatur, ipſa eſt quae efficit, vt anima alligari poſſit Sed &amp; caro abluitur, ut anima emaculetur. Caro inungitur, ut anima conſecretur, Caro ſignatur, ut anima muniatur. Caro manus impoſitiōe adumbratur, ut anima ſpiritu illuminetur. Caro corpore &amp; ſanguine chriſti ueſcitur, ut &amp; anima de deo ſaginetur. Theſe wordes be writtē in a worke made by this author for confirmation of the article of oure belefe for reſurrection of the fleſhe, whereby to refel ſuch as denied the ſame, and in englyſh they haue this ſenſe. Let vs nowe (ſaith Tertulian) conſider the platforme of a chriſten mans ſtate, and ſe what preeminence is gyuen by god, to the brykle &amp; vyle ſubſtaūce of the fleſſhe, althoughe to it this prefermēt myght ſuffice yt no ſoule can attaine euerlaſting lyfe, onles
 it beleue, whiles it is in the fleſhe, ſo euident is it, that the fleſſhe is (as it were) the groundeſelpece of mannes ſaluacion. In whiche, when the ſoule is knytte to god,This is verified in the ſacramente of baptiſme In the ſacramentes of cōfirmation, ordre and extreme vnction. As with the croſſe in benediction. In confyr
                     •
                  mation and ordres. The ſacrament of the aulter. it is the fleſh that bringeth to paſſe, that it maye ſo be knytte, yea alſo the fleſh is waſſhed, that the ſoule may be clenſed of her ſpottes. The fleſh is annoynted, that the ſoule may be halowed. The fleſhe is marked, that the ſoule maye be defended. The fleſhe by impoſition of the myniſters handes is ſhadowed, that the ſoule may be illuminate with the ſpirite. The fleſhe is fedde with the body and blood of Chriſt, that the ſoule may be made fatte of god. In theſe wordes be conteyned many good thynges, declarynge the vſe of the viſible ſacramentes, in the begynnynge of the churche, ſuch as in theſe dayes ſome 
                  •
               eſte and rayle at commenly,
 beſides the intollerable preſumption agaynſt the moſt bleſſed ſacrament, wherof how this man ſpeaketh it is euident, how ſo euer, the deuyll vſed Frith as a mynyſtre, to depraue him, in this behalfe. And yet this nourriture that mans fleſſhe hath by chriſtes precious body, is after an other maner as ſainte Auguſtine ſaith, then our cōmen nourriture is, for non digeritur in carnis noſtre, ſubſtantiam, ſed ipſe nos in corporat ſibi. Chriſtes body is not digeſted into the ſubſtaunce of our fleſſhe, but it incorporateth vs vnto it, And note ye word digeſted appropriate to other common meates This moſt preciouſe foode conſerueth our ſubſtaunce, &amp; as Damaſcene ſayth, maye therfore be called ſuperſubſtantialis, but it is by incorporation of vs into it, wherof here what Saint Cyprian ſaith,
 that holy martir, who expounding the (Pater noſter) and declaringe the fourth petition in it, Panē noſtrum quotidianum da nobis hodiè, vnderſtandeth it to conteyne a deſyre of the holy communion in the bleſſed ſacrament, and ſaythe. Ideo panem noſtrum id eſt, chriſtū dari nobis quotidiè petimꝰ, ut qui in chriſto manemus &amp; uiuimus, à ſanctificatione &amp; corpore eius, non recedamus.
               Cyprianus Therfore we aſke our daylye breade, that is to ſaye Chriſte, to be gyuen vnto vs, that we which abyde and liue in Chriſt go not backewarde, from the ſtate of holynes, and communion of the bodye. Here Saynte Cypryan, calleth the ſacrament, Chryſte, as he is in deede, there preſent really, and ſhewethe therewith an effecte of this holy communion, that beynge ſo partakers, of his moſt precyouſe naturall body, we maye be
 preſerued, in the continuaunce of our ſanctificacion, and not depart frō the felowſhyp of Chriſtes myſticall body, the churche, whiche churche Chriſt vniteth to him, not onely ſpiritually, by faith and charitie, but alſo corporally: by eating of his precious body, &amp; drinkinge of his bloude, declarynge that he loueth his churche, as his fleſſhe, as Saynte Paule writeth to the Epheſians,Ephe. 5▪
                where admoniſhinge the huſbādes, to loue their wiues as their owne bodies, he ſayeth. No mā euer hated his owne fleſh but nouriſheth it, as Chriſte dothe his churche, for we be membres, of his bodye, of his fleſſhe and of his bones. To whiche purpoſe, Cirillus,Cyrill. vpon the .xv. of Saynte Iohn, writeth againſt an heretike as foloweth. Non (inquit) negamus recta nos fide charitate
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ſyncera, Chriſto ſpiritualiter coniūgi
 ſed nullam nobis coniūctionis rationem, ſecundum carnem cum illo eſſe id profectò pernegamus, id
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   a diuinis ſcripturus, omnino alienum ducimus. Quis enim dubitauit Chriſtum etiam ſic uitem eſſe, nos palmites, qui vitam inde nobis acquirimus? Audi Paulum dicentem, quia omnes, vnum corpus ſumus in Chriſto, Quia &amp; ſi multi ſumus vnum tamen in eo ſumus,
               1: Cor. 10. 
               omnes enim vno pane participamus: An fortaſſe putas ignotā nobis, miſticae benedictiōis virtutē eſſe, quae cum in nobis fiat, nonne corporali ter quo
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   facit, communicatione carnis Chriſti,
               1. Cor. 6. 
               Chriſtū in nobis habitare, cur enim mēbra fidelium, mēbra ſūt chriſti Neſcitis (inquit) quoniā mēbrav
                     •
                  
                  ̄a mēbra ſūt chriſti mēbra igitur Chriſti, meretricis faciam membra? Abſit, Saluator etiam, qui manducat carnem meam, &amp; bibit ſanguinem meum, in me
 manet, &amp; ego in eo. We deny not (ſaith Cyril againſt the heretique) but we be ſpirituallye ioyned, to chriſt,we be conioyned to Chriſte not onelye by faith &amp; charitie, but alſo by participation of his fleſh in the ſacrament of the aulter. by faith, and ſincere charitie but that we ſhulde haue no maner of coniunction, in our fleſſhe with chriſt, that we vtterlye denye, and thinke it vtterlye diſcrepant from goddes holy ſcriptures. For who doubteth but chriſt, is ſo the vyne tree and we ſo the braunches, as we get thence our lyfe. Here what S. Paule ſaith: we be al one body with Chriſte.1. Cor. 10. For though we be many, we be one in hym. All we participate in one foode.
            Thinketh this heretique, that we know not the ſtrength and vertue of the myſtical benedictiō (ſo this autor expreſſeth the holy ſacramēt of thaulter,Cyryll calleth the ſacrament of the aulter the myſtical benediction calling it the miſticall benedictiō) which when it is made in vs, doth it not make Chriſt, by cōmunicacion of his fleſh to dwel
 corporally in vs? Whye be the mē
               bres of faithfull mens bodyes, called the membres of Chriſt?Chriſt doth cōmunicate his fleſſh in the ſacrament of the aulter, and ſo dwelleth corporallye in vs. knowe ye not (ſaith S. Paule) that your mēbres be the members of Chriſt? And ſhal I make the membres of chriſt, partes of the hores bodye? God forbydde. And oure ſauyour alſo ſaith: He that eateth my fleſh, &amp; drinketh my bloud, dwelleth in me, and I in him. Hitherto be Cirylles wordes, whereby is declared our corporall habitacion, in chriſte, by this precious ſacrament wherein is preſent chriſt him ſelfe▪
               Hilarius. 8. li. De trinitate. wherof here what Hilarius Pictauienſis, an olde author in chriſtes churche, in the .viii. boke, de Trinitate, vpon diſcuſſion of this queſtion, whither chryſte be in vs, by the veritie of nature, or cōcorde &amp; agreaunce in our will, aunſwereth in this wiſe. Si enim uerè uerbum caro factum eſt, &amp; nos uerè uerbū
                   carnē, cibo dominico ſumimꝰ: quo modo non naturaliter manere in nobis exiſtimandus eſt? qui &amp; naturam carnis noſtrae, iam inſeparabilem ſibi homo natus aſſumpſit, &amp; naturam carnis ſuae ad naturam aeternitatis, ſub ſacramento nobis cōmunicādae carnis admiſcuit? Ita enim omnes unum ſumus, quia &amp; in chriſto pr̄ eſt, &amp; chriſtus in nobis. Quiſquis ergo naturaliter patrē in chriſto negabit, neget prius nō naturalit
                     
                        
                     
                     er
                   uel ſe chriſto uel chriſtū ſibi ineſſe, quia in chriſto pr̄, &amp; chriſtus in nobis unū, unū in hijs eſſe nos faciūt. Si uerè igitur carnem corporis noſtri chrūs aſſūpſit, &amp; uerè homo ille, 
                     
                        
                     
                     qui
                   ex Maria natꝰ fuit, chrūs ē, nos
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   uero ſub miſterio carnē corporis ſui ſumimꝰ, &amp; per hoc unū erimꝰ, quia pater in eo eſt &amp; ille in nobis, quomodo volūtatis unitas aſſeretur, cū naturalis per ſacramentū proprietas perfecta, ſacramentum
 ſit unitatis? If the worde was made verely fleſhe, and we verely receyue the worde, beinge fleſhe in oure lordes meate: how ſhal not chriſt be thought to dwell naturally in vs, who being borne man, hath taken vnto him, the nature of our fleſſhe, that can not be ſeuered, and hath put together the nature of his fleſhe, to the nature of his eternitie, vnder ye ſacrament of the communion of his fleſſhe vnto vs, For ſo we be al one, by cauſe the father is in Chryſte,Note the myſterye of the ſacrament of the aulter. and Chriſt in vs. Wherefore who ſoeuer wyll deny the father, to be naturally in Chriſte, he muſte deny fyrſt, eyther hym ſelf, to be naturally in Chriſte, or Chriſt not to be naturallye in hym, for the being of the father in Chryſt, and the being of Chryſte in vs, maketh vs to be one in thē. And therefore, yf Chryſt hath taken verelye the fleſſhe of
 oure body, and the man that was verelye borne of ye virgyn Mary is Chriſt: &amp; alſo we receyue vnder the true myſterie, the fleſhe of his bodye, by meanes wherof we ſhal be one (for the father is in Chriſt, and Chriſt in vs) how ſhal that be called the vnite of wyll, when the natural propriete brought to paſſe by ye ſacramente, is the ſacramēt of vnite? I haue thus tranſlate this holy fathers teſtimony, farre exceding the capacite of the ſymple vnlearned, and yet moſt euidently declaringe the myſterie of the ſacrament of thaulter, not to be thinuention of mā, as theſe beaſtes now a dayes fayne, but the godly tradicion of the truthe, expreſſed in Chriſtes wordes, plainly &amp; truely receiued, alſo taught and continued in the church, ſyns the beginning, &amp; by this mans teſtimony, aboue .xii c. yeres paſt. And were it not, that
 I thinke good men wyll delyte to reade the truth: I wolde eſteme it labour loſte, to ſuche as be obſtinate. For they be (as ſaint Paule ſaith) ouerthrowen in their owne iudgement, and ſo full of malyce, as nothinge els, can entre. But I wyll not omytte for them to proſecute my purpoſe, And nowe ſhall ye here what Theophylus Alexandrinus, a noble author in chriſtes churche,Theop. Alex. ſuper Marc. and in the begynnynge of chriſtes churche ſaieth, who declaringe the goſpel of ſ. Marke, and expoundyng the wordes of chriſte writeth in this wiſe, Benedicens fregit. i. gratias agens fregit, quod &amp; nos facimus,
               Mar. 14. 
               orationes ſuper addentes, &amp; dedit eis dicens, Sumite hoc eſt corpus meum, hoc ſcilicet quod nunc do, &amp; quod nunc ſumitis. Non autem panis figura tantū corporis chriſti eſt, ſed in propriū Chriſti corpus tranſmutatur. Nam
 Dominus ait, Panis quem ego dabo, caro mea eſt, ſed tamen caro chriſti, non uidetur, propter noſtrā infirmitatem, panis enim &amp; uinum de noſtra conſuetudine eſt, ſi uerò carnem &amp; ſanguinem cerneremus ſumere non ſuſtineremus, propter hoc. Dominus noſtrae infirmitati condeſcendens, ſpecies panis &amp; vini conſeruat, ſed panem &amp; uinū, in veritatē conuertit, carnis &amp; ſanguinis. Thenglyſſhe whereof is this, Chriſte bleſſinge, brake, that is to ſaye, gyuynge thankes, brake, whiche alſo we do adding praiers thervnto, and gaue it thē ſaieng, Take this is my body, the ſame that is to ſay, that I nowe giue, &amp; you nowe take. For the breade is not an only figure of the body of chriſte, but it is chaunged into Chriſtes verye bodye. For oure lorde ſaide, The breade whiche I ſhall giue, is my fleſſhe, &amp; yet the fleſſhe of chriſt, is
 not ſene,Note this. in reſpecte of oure infirmitie, for the breade and wine, be accuſtomed vnto vs, but if we ſhuld ſe the fleſſhe and bloude, we ſhulde not endure to receiue it, and therfore our lorde, condeſcendynge to our infirmitie, conſerueth the fourmes of breade and wine, and turneth the breade and wyne into the veritie of his fleſſhe and bloude.
            Thus teſtifieth Theophilus, and who can deſire, a more playne teſtimonye, in whiche thou mayeſt alſo note, howe the fourme of breade and wyne, by goddes goodnes remaineth in reſpecte of oure infirmitie, and yet the breade and wyne is turned, in to the body and bloude of oure ſauyoure Chriſte, whiche ſpeache, implyeth a difference betwene the ſubſtaūce of breade and the fourme, that is to ſay, apparaunce of breade whiche euery ſymple wytte can not
 cōceiue, but euery witte ſhuld humbly &amp; reuerently beleue. For Chriſt ſayde. This is my body, as appeareth teſtified by ſuche as I haue reherſed, being witneſſes of tholde worlde, when there reigned in chriſtes churche, ſimplicitie, faith, charitie, mekenes, deuotion, with feruent religion, when goddes worde dwelt in mennes hartes, and came neuer abrode to walke in mennes tunges, but with maieſtie and reuerence, accompanied with all vertuous lyuynge, where as nowe ieſters, raylers, rimers, players, ianglers, pratelers, and ſimperinge parettes, take vpon them to be admynyſtratours and officers, to ſette forthe goddes worde, whereof they make a plurell number of wordes without all fruyte and effecte. But I wyll leaue theſe, and praye god amende them, and adde the deuout writinges of ſaint Auſten, ſaynte
 Iherome, and ſainte Chriſoſtome, touchinge the mooſt preciouſe ſacrament of the aulter. And fyrſt of ſaynte Chriſoſtome, that he writeth vpon the .vi. chapter of ſ.Chriſo ſuper 6. ca. Ioannis Iohn in this matter. Neceſſariò dicendum quam admiranda myſteria, &amp; cur data ſint, &amp; quaenam eorum vtilitas. Vnum corpus ſumus,
               Epheſ. 5. &amp; mēbra ex carne &amp; oſſibus eius. Quare initiati, eius praeceptis parere debent, Vt autem non ſolum per dilectionem, ſed re ipſa in illam carnē conuertamur, per cibum id efficitur, quem nobis largitꝰ eſt. Cum enim ſuum in nos amorem indicare uellet, per corpus ſuum ſe nobis commiſcuit, &amp; in unum nobiſcum redegit, ut corpus cum capite uniretur. Hoc enim amantium maximè eſt. Hoc Iob ſignificabat de ſeruis à quibus maximè amabatur, qui ſuum amorem praeſeferentes dicebant. Quis daret nobis ut eius carnibus
 impleremur? Quod Chriſtus fecit, ut maiori nos charitate ad ſtringeret, &amp; ut ſuum in nos oſtē
               deret deſiderium, non ſe tantum uideri permittens deſiderantibus, ſed et tangi, &amp; manducari, &amp; dentes carni ſuae infigi, &amp; deſiderio ſui omnes impleri. Ab illa igitur menſa, tan
                  •
                leones ignem ſpirantes, ſurgamus diabolo formidoloſi, &amp; caput noſtrum intelligamus, &amp; quam in nos praeſetulit charitatem Parentes ſaepenumero, liberos ſuos alijs alendos dederunt, ego autem, mea carne alo, me hijs exhibeo, omnibus faueo, omnibus optimam de futuris ſpem praebeo.
            Qui in hac uita ita ſe nobis exhibet, multo magis in futura. Veſter ego frater eſſe uolui, &amp; communicaui carnem, propter uos &amp; ſanguinem, &amp; per quae uobis coniunctus ſum, ea rurſus uobis exhibui. It is neceſſarye to ſhewe,
 howe maruelouſe theſe myſteryes be, why they be gyuen, and what profit is of them. We be one body and membres of his fleſſhe and bones. Wherefore ſuche as be receiued into this religion, muſte obeye his preceptes. And to the intente we ſhulde not onely by loue, but alſo in dede, be turned into that his fleſſhe, it is brought to paſſe by the meate, whiche he hath gyuen vnto vs. For when he wolde ſhewe his loue towardes vs, he hathe myngled hym ſelfe with vs, by his bodye, and hath brought it, to be one with vs, that that bodye, myght be vnited with the head, whiche is a ſpeciall point of ſuche as loue together. And that Iob ſignified of ſuche his ſeruauntes as mooſt loued hym,Iob. 
                     •
                  1 who for declaration of their loue ſayde. Who can graunte vs that we may be fylled with his fleſh? whiche Chriſte hath done, &amp;
 to bynde vs with the more charitie to him and to declare his deſyre towardes vs, hath not onely ſuffered hym ſelfe to be ſene, of ſuch as haue deſired to ſe, but alſo to be touched and eaten, and the teth to be thruſt, into his fleſſhe, and ſo all to be fylled with deſire of him. Wherefore lette vs ryſe from this table, ſnuffynge fire with oure noſethrilles, lyke lions, lette vs riſe both fearefull and terrible to the deuyll, conſiderynge who is our head, &amp; what loue, he hath ſhewed vs. The father and mother, many times haue giuen their chyldren to other, to nourſe and be brought vp, but I (ſaith Chriſt) feede them with my fleſhe, I exhibite my ſelfe vnto thē I fauour all, and giue all mooſte beſte hope, for that is to come.
            And he that in this lyfe, ſhewethe him ſelfe, ſo to vs, he wyll muche more do it in the lyfe to comme. I
 haue (ſaith Chriſt to vs) wyllyngly ben your brother, and for youre ſake,The ſame fleſh chriſte toke of the virgin, the ſame he gyueth vs in the ſacramente of the aulter. communicate in fleſſhe and bloude with you. And wherein I am knytte &amp; conioyned vnto you, I do agayne exhybyte the ſame vnto you. Thus ſayth Chriſoſtome (the mouth of gold) of this matter more preciouſe then gold, and ſweter then hony, and hony combe, of whiche holy man, yf thou haddeſte aſked (howe) he wolde haue aunſwered, as he writeth in the ſame place.Idem Chriſo Io. 3. 
               Quando ſubit quaeſtio (quomodo aliquid fiat) ſimul ſubit &amp; incredulitas. Ita &amp; Nicodemus perturbatus eſt, inquiens. Quomodo poteſt homo, in uētrem matris ſuae iteratò introire? Itidem &amp; hij nūc, Quomodo poteſt hîc nobis carnē ſuam dare,
               Matt. 14. Mar. 6 Luc. 9▪
                
               ad manducandū? Nam ſi hoc inquiris, cur non idem in quin
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   panum miraculo dixit, quo modo eos, in tantum auxit? Quia
 tunc, tantum ſaturari curabant, non conſiderare miraculum. Sed res ipſa tunc docuit, (inquiens,) Ergo ex eo &amp; haec credere oporcuit, ei facilia factu eſſe. Propterea id prius fecit miraculum, vt per illud, non eſſent amplius increduli, hijs quae poſtmodum diceret.
            
            When ſo euer this queſtion commeth to mynde (howe anye thynge ſhuld be done?) there entreth therwith vnbel fe and incredulite. For ſo was Nicodemus troubled ſayenge. Howe can a man entre agayne into his mothers wombe? And lykewiſe the Caphernaites in this goſpell nowe queſtioned with them ſelfe of Chriſte. Howe canne this man, gyue vs his fleſſhe to be eaten? But yf thou Caphernaite, aſkeſte this queſtion nowe, why dyddeſt thou not aſke lykewyſe in the myracle of the fyue loues, how he encreaſed theym ſo muche? I
 myghte aunſwere for the thus, that then thou caredſt only, to be fylled and dyddeſt not regarde the myracle. But thou Capharnaite, wilte percaſe ſay, the thyng there ſhewed it ſelfe. Wel by that then, thou ſhuldeſt beleue, that he that dydde that myghte eaſely do this, and therefore he wroughte that myracle before▪ that thereby they ſhuld not be myſt ruſtynge, and withoute belefe of that he ſhulde afterwarde ſaye▪ which wordes of ſaynt Chriſoſtom well pondered and wayed, ſhulde not on
                  •
               ly be ſufficient, to ſtoppe ye mouthes of queſtioners and doubters, but alſo conuerte the hartes of thoſe that hedlinge haue tunne downewarde, to the myſerable pit of the deuyls blindnes, &amp; become his miniſters,
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   ad Hedibiam to perſuade this abhominable falſehode, to the world. Let vs come now to S. Iherome who Ad Hedibiam, writeth thus.
 Nos audiamus panem, quem fregit Dominus, dedit
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                diſcipulis ſuis, eſſe corpus domini ſaluatoris, ipſo dicente ad eos, Accipite &amp; comedite. Hoc eſt corpus meum, &amp; calicem illum eſſe, de quo iterum loquutus eſt. Bibite ex hoc omnes hic eſt ſanguis meus noui teſtamē
               ti, qui pro multis effundetur, lſte eſt calix de quo in propheta legimus. Calicem ſalutaris accipiā.Matt. 26. Mar. 14. 
               Et alibi. Calix tuus inebrians, quam praeclarus eſt? Si ergo panis qui decoelo deſcendit, corpus eſt domini,
               Pſal. 115. Pſal. 22. Io. 6 &amp; vinum quod diſcipulis dedit ſanguis illius eſt noui teſtamenti, qui pro multis effuſus eſt, in remiſſionem peccatorum: Iudaicas fabulas repellamus, &amp; aſcendamus cum domino coenaculum magnū, ſtratum at
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                mundatum, &amp; accipiamus ab co ſurſum,Luc. 22. calicem noui teſtamenti, ibi
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                cum eo paſcha celebrantes, inebriemur ab eo vino
 ſobrietatis. Non enim eſt regnum dei, cibus &amp; potus, ſed iuſtitia &amp; gaudiū &amp; pax in ſpiritu ſancto:Rom. 14. Nec Moyſes dedit nobis panem uerū, ſed d
                  •
               
               ̄s Ieſus, ipſe conuiua &amp; conuiuium. Ipſe comedens &amp; qui commeditur. Illius bibimus ſanguinem, &amp; ſine ipſo potare non poſſumus, &amp; quotidiè in ſacrificijs eius, de genimine uitis uerae &amp; uineae So rec,Mat. 26. Luc. 22. 
               quae interpretatur (electa) rubentia muſta calcamus, &amp; nouum ex hijs uinum bibimus, de regno patris, nequa
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   in uetuſtate litterae, ſed in nouitate ſpiritus, cantantes canticum nouum, quod nemo poteſt cantare, niſi in regno eccleſiae, quod regnum patris eſt. Lette vs here this, that the breade which our Lorde brake, and gaue to hys diſciples, is the bodye of our lorde, our Sauyoure he hym ſelfe ſayenge vnto them. Take ye and eate this is my body, And the cuppe is
 that whereof he ſpake agayne.
            
               Drynke of this all, This is my bloude of the nevve teſtamente, vvhiche ſhall be ſhedde for many This is the cup of whiche we rede in the prophete.Pſal. 115. Pſal. 22. I ſhall take the cup of the ſauyour. And in another place. How excellent is thy cuppe, that is ſo plentifully filled. If thē the body of our lorde, be the breade that deſcended from heauen, and the wine that he gaue his diſciples is his bloude of the newe teſtamēt whyche is ſhedde for manye in remyſſyon of ſynnes, lette vs putte awaye the Iewes fables, and lette vs aſcende wyth oure lorde,Luc. 22. into the greate chaumber, ſtrowed and clenſed, and lette vs take of hym alofte the cuppe of the newe teſtamente, and kepynge our Eaſter let vs with him be made drunke, with the wine of ſobernes. For the kyng dome of God,Rom. 14. is not meate and
 drinke, but iuſtice, ioy, and peace in the holy ghoſt, Nor Moſes dyd not giue vs ye true foode, but our lorde Ieſus him ſelfe, beynge the geſte, &amp; feaſt it ſelfe, him ſelfe that dyd eate &amp; is eaten. His bloude we drynke, and withoute him can not drynke, &amp; dayly, in his ſacrifices, we preſſe out redde muſte, newe wyne of the grape, of ye true vyne tree, the vyne of Sorec, whiche is interpretate, choſen, and hereof we drinke newe wine, of the kyngdom of the father, not in the oldeneſſe of the lettre, but in the newenes of ſpirite, ſyngyng the newe ſonge, that no man can ſynge, but in the kingedome of the church, which is the kingdome of the father. Nowe ye haue herde ſ. Iheromes wordes, full of myſteries, but ſo to the pointe to teſtify the miſterie of the ſacrament of thaulter, as the more coulde not be deſired for our inſtruccion, in the true
 vnderſtandynge or rather, a true Eccho of that is truely vnderſtanded. For the original truth, procedeth of Chriſtes wordes, the true ſound wherof, redoundeth in good mens breſtes, being apte and mete to receyue the ſame, &amp; ſo rendre the noyſe, as they receyued it frome the mountayne of truthe, oure ſauiour Chryſt, by ye holye ghoſte, taughte, vttered &amp; ſpredde abrode, by whom good men be ledde into all truthe, lyke as euyll men, by the deuyll &amp; his aungelles, be ledde into all falſehed and lyes, Of whome beware, and regarde not Ioye, Bale, Turnoure, Frith, whome theyr owne malyce, with the deuylles ſuggeſtion hath ſubuerted. Regard not, what peruerſe obſtinacie worketh in refuſinge god, and reſiſting his powers of the worlde, thexample whereof hathe latelye appeared in ſuch as ſuffered, who being ouercome
 with intollerable preſumpti
                  ••
                on and diſperate malyce, obſtinately continued in their peruerſitie to thende openly. The deuyl hath his wytneſſe as ſ. Auſten ſaith, and frowarde obſtinacye in falſeheade, hath in the world, counterfeted the conſtancie of martyrs as vyce, with ypocriſy in many, hath reſembled vertue. Therfore in Chriſtes true martirs, not the paynes onelye, wherein they were tormented, but therwith the cauſe, wherefore they were perſecuted, was ſpecially regarded. For els as werynes of this lyfe hathe wrought among many, a vehemēt deſyre to be hence eſteming no paines, to achue, their entente, and therefore haue mooſte cruelly deuyſed theyr owne death, &amp; many times letted, haue wilfully cōtinued in proſecutiō of the ſame: ſo hath froward ſtubbernes mixte with vaineglory, done the lyke, as
 
               
                  •
               mong many in our tyme, hath manifeſtlye appeared. In whiche the Anabaptiſ
                  •
               es, and Sacramentaries, haue with a deuelyſh pertinacy mainteined their hereſies, whoſe wilfull death in obſtinacie, yf i
                  •
                ſhulde ſerue for an argumente, to proue ye truth of their opinion: the truth of gods ſcriptures, ſhuld be brought in muche perplexite, and men drawen hither, and thither, as peruerſe malyce ſhulde leade.
            But god that is mercyfull ſuffreth not man, to be tempted with theſe argumētes more thē may be borne of mannes infirmitie, And yf ſuche as lately ſuffered, were ſeuerallye conſidered, there maye appeare tokens ſufficiente, beſides the condicion of the matter, they ſuffred for, to declare their zeale, not to haue proceded of the ſpirite of god, but of arrogaunt pryde and preſumption, &amp; the ſpirite of ye deuyl, which
 
               is no tyme to ſpeake on nowe, but I ſhall adde what ſainte Auſtine ſaith, the readyng wherof is frutefull, and leaue the remembraunce, of theſe monſtruouſe proude people, whoſe doynges be vnfruteful, to them ſelfe and other. S. Auſten ſaith thus vpon the .xcviii. Pſalm, in thexpoſition of this text, Et ad
                  •
               srate ſcabellum pedum eius, quoniam ſanctum eſt, worſhyp ye foteſtole of his ſeat, for it is holye. Quid habemus adorare? Scabellū pedum eius, Suppedaneū dicit̄ ſcabellum, quod dicūt graeci (
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ) dixerunt Latini ſcabellum, &amp; alij dixerunt ſuppedaneum. Sed videte fratres, quid nos iubeat adorare. Alio loco ſcriptura dicit.Eſa. 66 Coelum mihi ſedes eſt, terra autem ſcabellum pedū meorum, Ergo terram iubet nos adorare, quia dixit alio loco, q ſit ſcabellum pedum dei? Et quomodo aborabimus terrā, cū dicat apertè
 ſcriptura,Deut. 6. Lut. 4. Dominum deum tuum adorabis, &amp; hîc dicit, Adorate ſcabellum pedum eius? Exponens autem mihi quid ſit ſcabellū pedum eius, dicit: Terra autem ſcabellum pedum meorum. Anceps factus ſum, timeo adorare tertam, ne damnet me, qui fecit coelū &amp; terram. Rurſum timeo, non adorare ſcabellum pedum domini meiquia pſalmus mihi dicit. Adorate ſcabellum pedum eius. Quaero quid ſit ſcabellum pedum eius? Et dicit mihi ſcriptura, Terra ſcabellum pedum meorum. Fluctuās conuerto me ad Chriſtum quia ipſum quaero hîc, &amp; inuenio quomo do ſine impietate adoretur terra, ſine impietate adoretur ſcabellum pedum eius. Suſcepit enim de terra, terram, quia caro de terra eſt, &amp; de carne Mariae carnem accepit, Et quia in ipſa carne hîc ambulauit, &amp; ipſam carnem nobis
 
               manducandam, ad ſalutem dedit nemo autem illam carnem mandu
                     •
                  
                  cat, niſi prius adorauerit, inuentu
                     •
                   eſt quemadmodum adoretur tal
                     •
                   ſcabellum pedum domini, &amp; nō ſo
                     •
                  lū non peccemus adorādo, ſed pe
                     •
                  
                  cemus non adorando. What haue we to worſhyppe? The ſtole of his feete, for ſo we call, that ſtayeth vnder the foote, That the greakes call (
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , the laten men call Scabellum, But let vs ſee brethren what we be bydde to worſhyppe. In another place, the ſcripture ſaieth. Heauen is my ſeate, and the earthe, is the ſtoole of my feete, Ergo then god byddeth vs to worſhyppe the earth, for he tolde in another place, what was the ſtoole of his feete. And how ſhall we worſhyppe the earth, ſeynge the ſcripture ſayth euidentlye. Thou ſhalt worſhyppe thy lord God, and here he ſayeth, Thou ſhalte worſhyppe
 the ſtoole of his feete. Expoundynge moreouer vnto me, what is the ſtoole of his feete, ſaith. The earth is ye ſtole of my fete, Here I am in a daubte, I am afrayde to worſhippe the earth, leaſt he ſhuld cōdemne me, that made heauen &amp; earthe. Againe I am afrayde, not to worſhippe the ſtole of my lordes feete, becauſe the Pſalme ſayethe vnto me▪ Thou ſhalte worſhyppe the ſtole of his feete. I aſke what is the ſtole of his feete? and ſcripture telleth me. The earth is, ſayth god, the ſtole of my feete. Beynge thus toſſed to and fro, I turne my ſelfe to Chriſt, for hym I ſeke here and fynde, howe without violatyon of goddes honoure, the earthe maye be worſhypped, and ſo wythoute vyolacyon of goddes honoure, the ſtoole of his feete, maye be worſhypped. Chryſte tooke of the earthe, earthe, for the
 fleſſhe is of the earth, and he toke fleſſhe of the fleſh of Marye, and becauſe in that fleſſhe he walked here,Chriſt gaue theſame fleſh to be ea
                     ••
                   of vs. and gaue the ſame fleſſhe to be eaten of vs, for oure ſaluation, no man agayne eateth that fleſſh, but he fyrſt worſhyppeth it. It is ſo founde out how the foteſtole of our lorde, ſhulde be worſhypped, and therwith alſo this that not only we ſhulde not ſynne in worſhippynge of it, but contrary wyſe, we ſhuld ſynne, and we ſhuld not worſhyp it. Thus ſpeaketh ſaint Auſten, of the Sacramente of thaulter, &amp; thus ſpeaketh he of the worſhyppynge of it, ſo plainely, as the deuyll hath no poynt of ſophiſtrye to iuggle in it, but to ſaye, ſainte Auſtine was a man, whiche is one of the general ſhyftes in an extremite, &amp; an other, that the worke (if the place make againſt hym) was not his, it is named to be. But this
 worke is ſaint Auguſtynes without any ſuſpicion to the contrarie. Mary a man, I muſte confeſſe, he was, and ſo were all tho I haue ſpoken of before, whome I haue not brought to proue the truth of the natural bodye of Chriſt, in the ſacrament of thaulter, For the few wordes of ſcripture ſpokē of chriſt him ſelfe, when he ſayde, This is my body, to good men proue that ſufficiently, and any other ſtudied corroboration, to good men, neadeth not, &amp; to euell obſtinate men, is ſuperfluouſe. Accordyng whervnto ſaint Baſyll inſtructed hys ſcolers, with what feare, faith, and affection, they ſhulde come to the holy cōmuniō.B
                     •
                  . ſillius. He bad them lerne feare of ſaynt Paule, ſayenge to the Corynthyans: He that eatethe vnworthelye,1. Cor. 11. eateth iudgemente and condemnatiou. He bad them learne fayth of Chryſtes wordes,Matt. 26.
                when he ſayde. Take ye, and eate ye, this is my body, And as for deuotion and affection of mynde, he bad them loke of the loue Chriſte bare to his churche. And therfore I trauaile not herein to learne mē faith by authoritie of men, but bycauſe I ſee, what a companye they be, that impugne oure true faithe, with lyes and ſophiſtrye: I haue taken payne to reherſe theſe, that ye maye reade of another company that mainteyned the true faith with the truthe, whiche were ſo no table clearkes, ſo greate learned men, ſo exercyſed in ſcriptures, ſoo rychelye endued with the ſpecyall gyftes and graces of god, as men ſhulde haue more comfort, to kepe companye with them, in the open lyghte of truth, goddes high way, then to lurke in darke corners, or folowe the leadynge of ſuche, as beynge blynde of the ryght eye, for
 want of grace and learninge, and more blynde on the lefte eye, with malyce and enuye, fall them ſelfe in the pitte of goddes indignacion and drawe other after them. One thynge I wyll note, whiche is worthye notynge, that there hath not ben, in any tyme, any one Maiſter teacher, or otherwiſe, the deuylles ſtoute champion, to impugne our true beleefe in the ſacramente of the aulter openlye, but he profeſſed therwith, ſome other opinion, ſo euidentlye abhominable, as he myght be knowen, by that other lye, to be ſent from the deuyll, And fyrſte that we reade of, be the Maniches, whoſe deteſtable opinion, is vniuerſallye abhorred, Second the Meſſalyans, who ſayde, the ſacrament dydde neither good nor hurte, muche like Fryth, who after all his conflicte, wold gladly haue come to thys, neyther to graunte
 the ſacramente, nor denie it. Now theſe Meſſalyans profeſſed thys for truth alſo, that it was an euyll thinge to laboure with their handes, and gaue them ſelfe onely to ſleape, and called their viſions in there dreames, prophecies, and pretended to be ſaued by onely prayer as Luther affirmeth by only faith Were not theſe men marked on both ſydes (trowe ye) to be knowen for noughte? Wyclefe denied the Sacrament of thaulter, and on ye other ſyde affirmed, all thynges to come to paſſe, by mere and abſolute neceſſitye, with whiche opinion all ſuche be infecte at this day, as impugne the ſacramente. And is not that an euident marke, that god hath ſuffered them to fall (in reprobum ſenſum) ſo as they ſpeake,Rom. 2. they wote not what, ſpeciallye when they waxe angrye, as ſome do, that men wyll not folowe
 them, when by their opynyon, the ſame neceſſytie, that maketh them to ſpeake ſo angerly maketh other alſo if they ſo do (and it be as they ſaye) by ye ſame neceſſitie to laugh them to ſkorne. And further if abſolute neceſſite reigned ouer man, then ſhulde a thefe or a murderer, be as muche made of, and commē
               ded for playenge his parte, accordinge to his place of neceſſitie, as he that liueth ſoberlye. For bothe worke by neceſſite. And if they wil by this opinion, reſemble god, to ye directour of a playe (as they do in dede) appoyntynge euery man a parte to playe, as lyketh him: then becauſe to lyue viciouſly and abhominably, is more troublouſe, &amp; fuller of vexacion, and the buſier part, then to liue wel &amp; vertuouſly whiche hath leſſe care in dede, becauſe he hathe a buſier parte appointed him, that is neceſſitate to
 liue euil, then he that is neceſſitate to lyue well, the ſame playenge his part aptely, as he can not do otherwiſe ledde by neceſſitie ſhoulde in that rule be more rewarded, then he that lyueth well if any thynge myght be called wel. And if there were any difference betwene vyce and vertue, vice ſhoulde be preferred vertue, and more rewarded becaue it is the more laborouſe part to playe, and ſo ſhulde all be ouerthrowen, as in deede all ſhall be, where the holy ſacramēt of thaulter is neglected. Whervnto ſuche other opinions, ſuche malice, ſuch enuy, ſuch hatred is ioyned as worketh in it ſelfe the ſubuerſion of al. Wherof god giueth euident markes and tokens, yf men neglecte them not, and the deuyll ſhewethe him ſelfe ſo openlye, as al maye ſe him, that be not wilfully blynde. And muche more euidentlye, the
 ſame ſhall appeare vnto you, by conſideracion of theſe good vertuouſe holy mens writinges, in this matter, whiche I haue reherced, &amp; myndinge to be ſhorte, paſſe ouer the great number, that is to ſaye, in this place al, that ſyns theſe. Myeres, haue ben teachers, and written for the edificacion of Chriſtes churche, beſides a great manye of them that wrote before.
            THyrdely let vs conſider how the deuyl toſſeth the wordes, and firſt theword, ſacrament, wherby he wolde it ſemed, that by that name, it was euer mente, that it is onely a ſigne and tokē, of an inuiſible grace, and in as muche as it is a ſigne, it is not the thing it ſelf, as the churche teachethe: For a ſigne, and a thinge, whereof the ſigne is, muſte neades differre.
            Wherevnto▪ I ſaye, that the worde (Sacramente), (as manye
 other wordes in ſpeache, haue the like) hath thre ſignifications, to oure vnderſtandynge. One moſte general, in whiche it ſignifieth any ſecrete hidden thyng, without difference, whither the ſame hydden thing, be holy or no. And after that acceptiō, it is applyed to many ſecrete matters and miſteries, both godly, &amp; natural. Another acceptiō is ſpecyal, &amp; is reſtrained to ſignifi the ſeuen ſpecial holy miſteryes in our religion, which we cal and be, the .vii. ſacramentes, vnto whiche ye name ſacrament, is in the comen ſpeache onelye applyed, whervnto this diffinitiō is truely attribute, a ſacramente to be a viſible ſigne of an inuiſible grace. Another acception, is in a moſt ſpecial ſignification, whē we ſpeake of the ſacrament of the aulter, whych doth vs vnderſtande, a ſpecyall difference of excellencye from the other ſacramentes,
 as wherein is preſent, the plentye of all grace, and the purchacer of all grace, receyued in the other ſacramentes, Chryſte hym ſelfe. Whereof when men be thus lerned and taughte, and the thing ſo ſet forth, truely (as it is in dede) it is then mere ſophiſtrie, to reſort, to diſputacion of the word, wherwith, to ouerthrowe, the truth of the thynge. After whiche ſorte they daly alſo, that make foundacion of argument to proue ye ſubſtaūce of bread, to remaine in the mooſte bleſſed Sacrament, bicauſe S. Paule calleth ye ſacrament, breade, and yet in dede ſaynt Paul calleth it this breade, whiche importeth a ſpeciall vnderſtandinge, and to ſuche as truely beleue, the myracle of chriſtes cōſecration, of his moſt preciouſe bodye, turnynge by the omnipotency of his myghty word the ſubſtaunce of breade, into the
 ſubſtaunce of his naturall bodye to ſuche men of true belefe, ye, thing remayneth as it is ne is in their conſcience altered, with expreſſion of ye name of that it was. And that whiche before the conſecration was commen breade, with the naturall ſubſtaunce of bread, is now by goddes ſpeciall myracle, in his ſecrete operation omnipotent, the onelye ſubſtaunce of the bodye of our ſauyoure Chriſte. And ſo maye be called with an addition wherewith to marke the miſtery, this breade. But whye ſhulde the name, trauayle vs when we rede ſo ofte in ſcripture, thinges to be named not as they be, but as they were? and the rod turned in to a ſerpent, by gods miracle, before Pharao, ſtyl to be called a rodde when it was a ſerpent,Exo. 7. but the rodde was conuerted by gods power into the ſerpent and ſtyll
 called it a rodde, when it was not ſo. But why ſhould men be ſo ſcrupulouſe in names? After god had ſignified to the patriarche Iacob that he ſhulde be called no more Iacob but Iſraell,Gene. 32. yet afterward the ſame ſcripture teſtifieth howe god ſpake to Iſrael. ad puteum iuramenti,
               Gene. 46. and called Iacob, Iacob: Here if a man wolde trifle, in the ſounde of the worde, Iacob, ſhulde he not make an argumente to improue the truthe of that god had ſpoken, wherewith the deuyll myghte inueigle the preſumptuouſe ignoraunt, that eſtemeth him ſelfe ſo muche, as he meaſureth al knowledge by his rude capacitie. But here thexerciſed ſenſes in learninge, can conſider how names be of two ſortes, ſometime they do onlye ſignifie anye litle token of the thynge, whervnto they be added, and then we may not make foundacion of the name as declarynge
 hollye the thyng ſignified, or to be demed the propre name, After whiche ſorte, Chryſt was called ſynne, bycauſe he dyed for ſynne, and yet had not ſynne in hym, as the word ſhold import. And when we ſpeake thus, that Chryſte ſaueth ſynners, we ſygnify by the worde (ſynners) ſuche men as were ſynners, and be by Chryſt, waſhed, &amp; purged from ſynne, mete to be receyued to ſaluacyon. For as Saynte Paule ſayth to the Epheſians, Chryſt purgeth his churche, and leaueth neyther ſpot, ne wrincle. And when we call noughtye men, chriſten men, we ſignify not by the name, what they be now in dede, for they be the deuyls men, and not Chryſten men, but callynge them nowe Chriſtenmen, we ſignifie yt they were ones in the ſtate of grace, at the tyme of their baptiſme. We call a mans writinge alſo his hande, onely becauſe
 his hande wrote it. In whiche ſorte of naminges, the ſignificacion extendeth no further, for declaracion of the thinge named, thē the pointing or direction of a mās finger, with a parte of ſpeache called a pronowne, as this or that.
            Mary other names that be added to geue lighte and knowledge of the ſubſtaūce, nature or chiefe qualitie of the thynge, thoſe be ſo ioyned and knytte to the thynge, as they do not onely poynte it, but open it alſo, and be not onely an out warde marke of the thinge, but preſente to oure vnderſtandynges, what is conteined in the thinge it ſelfe. And therf
                  •
               re as the name Iacob, was onely an outward marke of the corporall man of the patriarche. So Iſrael declared the ſpeciall fauoure of God, wherby Iacob ſawe god wh
                  •
               che the word Iſraell doth ſignifie the continuaūce
 whereof god promyſed, ſaienge he ſhulde no more be called Iacob, but Iſraell. Accordinge whervnto after the breade is conſecrate by ye preiſte, goddes miniſter, and by the omnipot
                  •
               cye of Chriſtes myghtye worde is conuerted into the bodye of Chriſte, the name that 
                  •
               ignifieth the ſubſtaunce of that ſacramente, is the body of Chriſte. And therefore the ſame ſacramēt, can no more be called breade, but the bodye of Chriſte, as Iacob ſhulde no more be called Iacob, but Iſrael. And yet as ſcrypture ſayth in the hyſtory o
                  •
                Iacob, God called after that Iacob againe, by the name Iacob without preiudice of the truthe of goddes worde, ſpoken before, that he ſhulde be no more ſo called. So Saynte Paule calleth the ſame holy ſacrament, breade, becauſe it was ſoo, before the conſecracyon, and yet ſo he calleth it, withoute
 preiudice of the truth, that it is in dede, beinge not breade, but the very body of Chriſt, at the time, when it is by hym neuertheleſſe called breade, As Iacob was in dede Iſraell by goddes fauoure, when he was after by gods mouth againe, called Iacob whych latter callinge of Iacob, dydde nothynge preiudicate the truthe of gods worde vttered before. Foraſmuch as this laſte maner of callynge, was not a through namynge of hym, but only, as it were a pointing to diſtinct outwardly the man, and becauſe he was ones Iacob, is called Iacob againe, As the ſacrament, becauſe it was ones breade, is called bread againe. And now I returned to this that yf mens fayth were ſuch, as is required of chriſten men, they wold be wiſelye deefe, as the ſerpente, that ſtoppethe her eares; and nothynge be altered, with the deuyls
 intricacions or incantaciōs in wordes and names euen as we beleue certainely,Eſa. 5
                     •
                  . Pſal. 11. Apoc. 5. that Chriſt, is perfytte god, and perfyt man, what ſo euer names, be attribute in ſcripture vnto hym, as he is called a ſhepe, a worme,Ioan. 14. a lyon, and many other. And althoughe Chriſte ſaith hym ſelfe, his father is greatter then he, yet this is true, that his father &amp; he be equall, and yet (equall) and (greater) be in apparaunce contrarye. And ſo beleuynge, as euerye good Chriſten man muſte beleue, that Chriſt is equall to his father in ſubſtaunce and deitie, we beleue the contrary in apparaunce, to ſenſes vnexercyſed of that Chriſt ſayd hym ſelfe. But theſe notwithſtandynge, howe ſo euer thapparaunce of wordes be in ſcriptures, we beleue the truth taught vs by ye churche, &amp; as euery man lerneth to ſpell that ſometime (c) with a 
                  •
               yttell
 ſpelleth, eſt, &amp; in another place (e) with a title, ſpelleth / en/as when we write / Amē,/and another tyme e / with a tytle, ſpelleth / em/as / mē brum/whiche varietie, goeth by rule in place, whereunto an humble ſcoler obeyeth, and not by reaſon, as an arrogant witte wolde requyre: So in all the ſecretes, and contractions (as we myghte call them) and miſteries hydden of our religion, good men haue euer leaned to the rule of teachinge in chriſtes churche, and taken a title, ſome tyme for, n, and ſometyme for, m, as they were taught the place to require, and not to ſpell after theyr owne iudgemente, as euerye man weneth it ſhulde be, after his vehement reaſon of his owne diuiſe.
            Doth not ſ. Paule (ſaith he) call it breade? and be not theſe wordes of ſcripture? And be any words truer or better, then the wordes of ſcripture?
 Of whome I aſke this queſtion agayne. Hath not the churche had, and vnderſtanded theſe wordes of ſcrypture, that ye ſoo vehementlye alledge? Hathe not the churche deliuered thoſe wordes vnto vs? And hath not the ſame churche notwythſtandynge, taughte thys truthe, howe the breade, by conſecratyon, is conuerted into the precyouſe bodye of Chryſte? and condemned thoſe that wolde affyrme, breade to remayne, and with that theyr condemnation, reteyned and kepte in honoure, ſaint Paule who wrote theſe wordes, that ye make ſo greate matter of? The churche hathe condemned the Arryans, that denyed Chryſte, to be equalle wyth his father, and yet the ſame churche, hathe ſtylle kepte in honoure the Euangelyſt, that wrote howe Chryſte ſayde, his father was greatter then he.
            
                And yet the Arryans ſayde, they ſpake none other, then the Euangelyſtes, teſtyfyed in playne wordes,Io. 14. as ſome wyll ſaye nowe a dayes, they ſpeake none otherwyſe then Saynte Paule dothe. But ſuche heretyques, wyll heddelye ſpell as they lyſte, and not folowe the rule of ryghte vnderſtandyng, without whiche, men muſte neades wauer and ſwarue in their owne coniecture, beynge the coniecture, the rule of leade that men now a daies ſenſually folowe, plyable to theyr fanſyes euē ſo fondely as ſome, like worſhipful clerkes haue taken the wordes of ſcrypture, written by the euangeliſtes, for god him ſelfe, and thoſe haue gyuen thankes, to the lord, for their hyghe knowledge, acheued by continuall readynge, by them ſelfe alone, and hauynge a newe teſtamente, by theyr gyrdell, wherby they haue boſted them ſelf,
 deliuered, from the greatte ignoraunce, wherwith other were blinded for by their owne deuiſe, ī their wyſe imagination, they had ſeene god, and harde god, euen face to face, by hearinge and ſeinge, the wordes of ſcripture, which they fanſied to be god hym ſelfe, becauſe of the wordes of ſainte Ihons goſpel where it is written. The word was god.Io. 1. I do not herein fayne, reader, but wrytte the matter in dede, and in dyuerſe men deprehended and founde, whiche fonde errour hathe ben engendred of blynde arrogancye amongeſt thoſe that thinke thē ſelfe able to wade throughe the ſcriptures, withoute direction of ſuche teachynge as the churche taught by ye ſcripture of god, hath gathered of ye ſame ſcryptures. Damaſcene,Defide orthodo
                     •••
                  
                of whome I haue before ſpoken, hath this good leſſon, that as it is ſignified to vs by ſcripture
 that we ſhall be all taught of god, ſo by the ſame ſcripture we be admoniſhed, to aſke of our elders,Interrogama iores &amp; dic
                     •
                  e ti
                     •
                  i. &amp; they ſhall tell vs, whiche declareth a maner of reachyng, not to be cō
               tempned of men, who deſpiſinge al other men for teachers, as they ſolyſſhly vnawares learne other to contemne them: ſo do they deſpiſe god, accordynge to Chriſtes wordes,Lui. l
                     •
                  
                
               Qui vos ſpernit, me ſpernit. He that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me Here may come in percaſe in thys high matter a ſcoffe with, a queſtiō which you? And then, why ſhal not I teache you, aſwell as you me? or rather I you, For doth not Chryſt ſaye? I knoweledge to the father, thou haſte hydden theſe thinges from the wiſe,Matth. 11. and ſhewed them to the yongelinges? And Paule ſaith the wyſedome of the worlde,1. Cor. 3. is folyſſhenes afore god? And then an other queſtion, in what vniuerſitie
 was ſainte Peter made doctoure, And ſo ſhall aryſe the controuerſy, whiche the deuyll engendreth, who ſhall teache other? who ſhall be the ſcoler, and who the maiſter? wythout eche man ſhulde playe bothe partes, as of ſome number eche mā
               nowe a dayes wolde playe alone al partes, and euery man be mayſter to him ſelf, &amp; to himſelf ſcoler alſo, with requeſte to god that he wyll voucheſaue to teache hym ſecretelye by often readynge and ſpelling after his faſhion, for he may not be inſtruct by man, nor for ſhame ſubmytte hym ſelfe to hys felowe, to make his mate his maiſter, to haue power ouer hym, accordynge to Saynte Paules wordes (as he raketh them) where he is faſhyoned to ſaye to the Corynthians,
                  
                     •
                  . Co
                     •
                  . 12. I wyll be vnder no mans power. For ſoo thenglyſſhe hathe, althoughe the
 ſence be otherwiſe. And this concluſion, do theſe queſtions engendre, where euery man muſte be ſo aunſwered, as his ſenſualite may be cōtented, which is impoſſible. But to the purpoſe. The churche is a bodye diſtincte, as ſaynte Paule ſaith to the Corinthyans,1. Cor. 1
                     •
                  . wherein euery member, hathe not one office confuſelye, but ſome be prophetes and ſome be paſtours and teachers. &amp;c. And where ſome be appointed to reache,Epheſ. 4. ſome other muſte alſo be appointed to be taught, howebeit to auoyde this contentyon, betwene this queſtyoner and me, and to eſchue all comparyſon, for this time, I am contente to be with hym in ye place of a ſcooler, and aſke wyth hym of other, that is to ſaye, of thoſe that haue bene, before vs accepted and allowed for teachers, and of theyr ſcoolers alſoo, good chriſten people, who haue accepted
 humblye their teachinge, in the truthe of the preciouſenes and ſubſtaunce of the mooſt bleſſed ſacrament of the aulter, and take thē altogether, repreſentynge Chriſtes churche, for ſcoolemaiſters in thys matter, And yet there is no cauſe to aſke, whiche ſhulde ſeme to implye matter of doubte, but conſtantly to continue in that we haue here in truely receyued, without whyes, or whattes, whiche engendre altercation, without edificacion or fruit Shall we, after, xv.C. yeare, begin to enquyre, whither the ſtate of our relygyon, be eſtablyſhed in meere ydolatrye, as they do now a dayes terme it blaſphemouſlye? Can we take ſuche a ſerche and examinacion, otherwyſe, then to be a quarell moued to the hole, to prepare the way to Mahomete? of whoſe lawes ſome in ſome thinges write nowe abrode indyfferentelye. For (as I
 ſayd before) if reaſon, or rather vnreaſonablenes, may nowe conquer oure fayth herein, the vyctory wyll hardely be ſtayed from conqueſte in the reſte, whiche puniſſhemente we may ſe in other, yf we haue grace to conſyder it. Let vs ſtande ferme therefore in our fayth, receiued in the moſte bleſſed ſacramente, and kepynge our ſelfe in ſauegarde, by the ſtrength of the ſame faith, note howe the deuyll aſſaulteth the ſymple, to ouercome them, in the ſame. The deuyl (ye knowe) is but plaine (Iwys) and where playnnes maye deceyue, makethe his pretence to ſpeake playnely, and profeſſeth ſimplycytie, ſpeakynge alwaye (as his poſtles ſaye) of this ſacrament, as S. Paule ſpake, and call it bread. And albeit (as I ſpake before) of ſpellynge with one tyttle diuerſely: ſo lykewyſe one worde is taken diuerſely: yet the deuyll pretendeth
 ſymplycite, and wyl haue one word taken but one way, which is a craft to leade men out of the waye. For if in ſainte Iohn̄s goſpell, where it is written, that Chryſte was in the worlde,Io. 1
                     •
                  . the worlde was made by hym, and the worlde knewe him not, yf there the word (world) ſhuld haue one ſignyfycation, it ſhoulde engender a meruaylous confuſe ſenſe, And in the worde (bread) whē Chriſte ſayde. He was the breade that diſcended from heauen, the worde, breade, maye not there ſignifie the ſame it dothe, where the goſpell ſpake of fyue barlye breades. And therfore to the rude can be nothinge more daungerouſe, then to be entangled,Io. 6▪
                with this the deuyls ſophyſtrye, inſygnificacyon of names, the dyſcuſſion whereof, requireth learninge, and the conceiuing of the true faith by gods gift only ſimplicitie to beleue, wtout howes,
 as is preached vnto the by the churche of chriſt. But beſides this point of ſophiſtry, cometh in another of ye rude ignoraunt, &amp; ſodenly forgettyng the name of the holy maſſe, only pretendeth knowledge, of ye lordes ſupper. And herein is muche a do, and the name of the maſſe reiected, all is applyed to the lordes ſupper, and yet they wolde ſteale away the precyouſe foode, of the body of our ſauyour Chryſte, &amp; in thende make it a bare drinking, of onely breade and wyne. And where they wyll paſſe noone of their owne priuate ſuppers, euen on the greatteſt faſtynge day, without fleſh for deintyes: yet in thys ſupper of the lord (as they call it) they deuyſe a deitie without delicacies, to haue nothīg preſent but bread and wyne, A merueilouſe matter of the inclination of mannes nature, for declaracyon of inſtabilitie to be fonde of innouacions.
 nouacions. What the word (maſſe) meaneth they can not tell, and ſoo re
                  •
               u
                  •
               e they wote not what, by their owne confeſſion. And the name (ſupper) they allowe, with a lytle knowledge what they ſaye, callynge it a ſupper, but only becauſe it varieth from the name of the Maſſe. For that whiche in the fyrſt inſtitucion, was called, Coena domini, and the ſupper of oure lorde, by reaſon the worde (Coena) becauſe of the tyme, towardes euenyng, ſignified a ſupper, Nowe the churche hathe ordered all men, to receyue theyr holye communion afore all other meates faſtynge: it ſhuld nowe more conueniently be called in Englyſſhe, the feaſt of oure lorde, or the dyner, then a ſupper, wherwith the worde Coena, wyll agree, and requirethe not any ſuche tranſlacion in ſpecyal to be called a ſupper, but coena domini may be called. Conuiuiū
                   ſacrum, as the churche ſyngeth deuoutly, wherin Chriſt is receiued, and therwith a memorye celebrate of his mooſt bleſſed paſſion, and a pledge is lefte with vs, of lyfe euerlaſting. And Gregory Nazianzene noteth, that albeit in this holy communion, ye churche chaungeth the tyme, yet the thinge is all one, whyche he ſpeaketh after this ſorte. 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
                
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               .
            Quandoquidem &amp; alia multa, aliter tum prodita fuere, 
                  
                     
                  
                  quam
                ut nunc ſe habere conſpiciuntur. Veluti Ieiunauit chriſtus paululum ante tentationem,Matt. 4. nos verò ante Paſcha
                  •
                Quòd ad ieiunia attinet, utrobi
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                idem, temporum uerò utriuſ
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                ieiunij, non modica diſcrepantia.
            
               Chriſtus enim ieiunium, tant
                     
                        
                     
                     quam
                   propugnaculum adhibuit contrà tentaciones, nobis uerò ad id ualet, u
                     •
                   Chriſto cōmorîamur, &amp; itē purgatio
 quaedam eſt, quae feſtū praecedat Porro chriſtus ieiunauit dies quadraginta, erat enim Deus, nos verò ieiunium, ad facultatis noſtrae modum attemperauimus, etiamſi quidam zelo affecti,
               Mar. 14
                     •
                  
                
               nōnihil ſupra uires conati ſunt. Rurſum chriſtus ſacra Paſchae myſteria, cum diſcipulis celebrat in coenaculo, et poſt coenam &amp; pridie
                     
                        
                     
                     quam
                   pateretur, nos verò in aedibus orationis, &amp; quidē ante coenam, ac poſt reſurrectionē Surrexit item Chriſtus poſt triduū nos autem poſt multum temporis, ne
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   tamen cōmittūtur cum illius noſtra, ſed ne
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ad temporis rationem coniungantur, quatenus uerò ad exemplum eorum quae nos age remus tradita ſunt, exactā per omnia ſimilitudinē effugerunt. The ſenſe wherof is this in englyſſhe. There be many mo thinges, other wyſe ſet forth, thē they appere to be now. Chriſt faſted a litle before his
 temptacion: we faſt before Eaſter. As touchynge the faſt, that is all one, but in the tymes of the faſtes: there is a greate diuerſitie. For Chriſte vſed faſtinge as a defence and bulwarke againſt temptatiō, and in vs, faſting auayleth, that we myghte dye wyth Chriſt, and it is a clenſynge &amp; purgation byfore the feaſt. Chriſt faſted fourty dayes, for he was god, we haue meaſured our faſting with our power, although ſome moued with zeale do attempt herein aboue their power. Chryſt kepte his paſcal feaſt, with his diſciples in a chambre after ſupper, and the daye before he ſuffered: we do the ſame in houſes of prayer, before ſupper, and after the reſurrection. Chryſte roſe after, thre dayes, &amp; we ryſe ageine after a longe tyme. And yet that we do, in ye myſteries, repungneth not with Chryſtes doynges, but
 they be not conioyned in tymes. And in aſmuche as they were deliuered vnto vs, to be our exāple, their through lykenes and ſimilitude in euery part was not obſerued. Theſe be Gregory Nazianzenes wordes, the ſentence wherof I haue in this place, reherced, to this purpoſe, to ſhew howe the church hath altered the tyme, in the receyuing of our holye communion, I myghte haue in fewer wordes reaported it, but becauſe thauctour is very notable for learnynge and vertue, and a famouſe clerke of ye Greake church, and of auncientie aboue .xii.c. yeres. I haue here inſerted his wordes at length, as they be in greake, and haue added a tranſlation both of laten and englyſh to thintent I myght note vnto the reader, ſuche frutefull leſſōs, in other matters, as ye ſame conteyneth. Whereof one is of the
 auncientie of the feaſte of Chriſtes faſt, in the tyme we call in englyſh, Lent, which Chriſten men haue vſed to obſerue, before Eſter, wherwith to purge them ſelues againſt theaſter. And I doubt not but in ſome mennes eares, it ſoundeth merueylouſelye in this tyme, to call faſtynge a purgation, whiche worde (purgation) ſhulde onelye appertaine to Chriſtes bloude, wherein and wherewith men be purged, whereof this author was not ignoraūt, &amp; therfore I note vnto ye, how he yt can tel what he ſaith ſpeaketh thus, which hath a good catholyke ſenſe &amp; vnderſtandinge where Chriſt is taken for the foundacion, whervpon &amp; in whom, &amp; by whoſe helpe, this faſt is celebrate For in chriſtes faith, it purgeth, &amp; thervnto men ſhuld be ſo exhorted For there is a kind of deuils,Math. 7. chriſ
                  •
                ſaide, ye is not caſt out, but in prayer
 and faſtinge, whiche good men, know by vnderſtanding &amp; experience, but yet I can not pretermyt, what ſophiſtry the deuyll hath vſed to induce men to eate, and ſo to eate, as though men lyued to eate and ſo diligently as thoughe ſaint Paule had written affirmatiuely, Regnum dei,
               Rom. 14. 
               eſſe eſcam &amp; potum And then commeth in compariſon and the true faſte is extolled, to thruſt out the bodely faſte. Faſte from ſinne (ꝙ he) that is the true faſt, that is the excellent faſte, that god commaundeth. And ſo the deuyll ſetteth good thinges at contention, one to face oute another and one to putte another oute of the dores: For he may abyde no cōpany of vertues in degrees, one vnder another, one ſeruing to and ther, one helping another, or belonginge to another, but he wyl haue all alone, accordinge to the foote
 of the ſonge, whiche was faithe alone. In faſting therfore, they ſhal extoll and commende moderacion, and worthelye, for it is the chiefe point of bodely 
                  •
               aſte, but this moderacion ſhall be muche made of, whereby to dryue out at the dores abſtinence from fleſh. And ſo that whiche is done of knowledge, for an inductiō to ſobernes: to abſtain certaine dayes frome eatynge of fleſh, that is called ſuperſtition, &amp; by the name condemned. I cal faſt (ſaith he) forbearinge of a mans pleaſure and ſhall therein ſpeake religiouſely, but the concluſion is that fiſſhe faſte may be done away and for declaration that the other were but pretences, to bring thenterpriſe to paſſe, where fleſheating hath fre courſe, ſobernes, moderation, and the faſte of the ſoule, be clerely banniſhed and exiled, and the bely enioyethe the conqueſte
 without lette or interruption, and for a more triumphe therin, when we ſhuld ſpecially dye with Chriſt (whiche this author ſaieth is theffecte of faſtinge) ſome haue hadde vpon good friday, notable and ſpeciall bankers, with pretence to reioyce in Chriſtes mercy, wroughte with vs, that daye. And it is good in dede to reioyce in goddes good tydynges, but neceſſary therewith to remember his iuſtice, and with what tēperature thereof, he miniſtreth his mercy, and whiles thou learneſt one thinge, forget not another. God made al thing in weight number, and meaſure, &amp; we ſhulde learne, how to vſe them, after their eſtimation, withoute ſuche compariſon and contencion, as the deuyl maketh, euer with one better, to expelle another, not ſo good, whereof muſt nedes enſue the confuſion of all. Faſt therefore the cheife faſt
 of the ſoule, to abſtaine from ſinne with the bodely faſte, to abſtaine from meates, with moderation &amp; ſobrenes, takinge ſcarcitie of that is neceſſarye, in ſuche fourme alſo, of forbearinge certaine meates, as the churche hath without ſuperſtition obſerued and accuſtomed. Al whiche wyl agre together, if thou wilte agre with them, and ſo they will be profitable, and a purgatiō mete and requiſite before the feaſt as Gregory Nazianzen wrytethe callynge it, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . In whom, I will alſo note vnto the howe at thoſe dayes, their places of aſſembly (for whiche vſe, we haue oure churches) were called, houſes of prayer, and Chriſt when he keſt out the byers and ſellers out of the temple, he alleged ſcripture to ſhewe it ſhuld be the houſe of prayer.Matth. 21. 
               Domus mea, domus orationis uocabitur. My houſe ſhall
 be called the houſe of prayer. I wyll not encreaſe my boke with accumulation of places, to conferme the commendation of praier, for I truſte it nedeth not, but as ſaynte Paule ſaide,1. Timot. 2. 
               Volo viros in omni loco orate.
               1. Ch
                     •
                  ſ. 5. And in another place, Orate ſine intermiſſione, So Chriſoſtome noteth prayer is much effectuall in the time of maſſe, where chriſt is preſent, by whoſe mediacion all our praiers be acceptable &amp; hearde of god. This is not out of my purpoſe entended, to ſhewe in this pointe the deuilles ſophiſtrye to diminiſhe and extincte praier, with temptacion of atteininge knowledge by ſtudy and ſermōs. So as nowe amonge manye, the houſe of god, which Chriſt called the houſe of prayer, hath (as many practiſe it) chaūged ye name wt yt thing▪ For many yf they come to churche, either it is to heare one
 talke and rayle after theyr fanſye in a pulpet, whiche they call a ſermon, and learne onlye thereby other mens faultes &amp; care nothinge for their owne, or elles in readinge or muſyng of that they vnderſtād not, but wolde learne, they ſpende all the tyme they tarye there. A ſermon is good, and ſo is ſtudye alſo to atteine knowledge, but Gregory Nazian. ſayd. 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                Good is not good, when it is not well done, to whiche well doing, tyme is a ſpeciall circumſtaunce,Eccl. 
                     •
                  . Euerye thinge hath time ſaith Salamon. And in thactes of the apoſtles, it appeareth they had their tymes appointed to prayer.Act. 5 For Petrus et loānes aſcendebant in templum, ad horā orationis nonam, Peter and Ihon aſcended into the temple, at the .ix. houre of prayer, whiche deſtinction of tyme, hath no ſuperſticion in
 it, but a conueniente ordre and diſtribution of the vſe of tyme, whiche with a certaine appointement, is neceſſarye in a body vnited and congregate, as chriſtē men be, that we myght declare the ſame vnite, by conformitie of operation, at one tyme.Col. 2. Wherein ſaint Paules texte forbyddinge diſtinction of dayes. is not offended, who condemned onelye the ſuperſticion, and lefte the vſe of diſtinction, indifferente to be receiued for good ordre and ſemelines, with a ſignification, alſo of our myſteries. And therefore Gregory Nazianzene, hath his ſentence, in his ſermon, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . There be other thinges of ye Iewes, perfited with them in fygure whiche be reſtored againe vnto vs, in myſterye, So as all the
 thinges vſed in tholde lawe be not vtterly reproued and cōdempned, not to be doone, but not to be ſo done, for the figure ceaſſethe when truthe is come, and the lawe &amp; prophetes were vnto ſaint Iohn baptiſtes tyme, as Chriſt ſaide, Neuer theleſſe as Gregorye Nazianzene ſaith, ye ſame thinges may be nowe reſtored miſtically, not at euerye priuate mannes pleaſure and deuiſe (as ſaint Auguſtyne writeth, ad Ianuarium) but by teachynge of the churche and orderinge ye ſame,Aguſt. ad Ianuarium. not for 
                  •
               uperſtition, but direction, as thapoſtelies dyd in the begynninge, when they decreed it by inſpiration of the holy ghoſte, that men ſhulde abſtaine,Act. 15. frome that was ſtrangled, and bloude, whych repugned not wyth the vyſyon to ſaynte Peter, that all t
                  •
               ynge was cleane,Act. 10. to them that in cleannes receiued it, ne diſſented from chriſtes
 teachinge, that not to defile the mā that entreth in at the mouthe, but it was a diſpenſacion of the truth,Math. 15. betwene the ceaſſynge of the lawe and ſpringyng of the goſpell, with ſuch a tēperamēt, as the chaunge for compaſſion of weake conſciences, ſhulde not be ſodayne and at ones, but by lytle and lytle, as the daye ſpringeth and the night goeth away. Upō which conſideratiō ye ſame thinges were in the church of Chriſt forbydden, yt were before for another ende, forbidden in Moſes lawe, onely the cauſe of prohibicion varied, but the thynge was alone. But to returne to the purpoſe whervpon this was broughte in. Diſtinction and ordre in tyme, is not ſuperſticiouſe, but neceſſarye, and therfore with ſermons or ſtudye (whiche bothe be in their tyme good) to interrupte the tyme of praier, that is not good, &amp; greatlye
 worſe, when the ſermons be ſuche, and ſo faſhyoned, as they mayntayne talke and communication, and be not directed to ſtirre the peoples dulle and ſluggy endeuor to folow vertue and flee vyce, and leauynge a parte matter of contention or reformacion, to be ordered by the high powers, to tell the audience of their ſpeciall faultes; and to diſwade them from the ſame, by alwaies and meanes. Such were the ſermons, in the primatiue churche. So preached Sainte Chriſoſtome. Sainte Auguſtine, Soo preached Gregory Nazianzene, &amp; where in a ſermon he made of the feaſt of Eſter, he hadde entred to ſpeake of the ſecrecye of god, lefte that matter with this ſpeache.
            
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                I purpoſe not, ſaith he to diſpute or reaſon of god now but to diſpenſe his truth, that is to
 ſaye, diſtribute it conueniētly with al circumſtaunces mete, of whiche office in cyrcumſpecte diſtribution S. Paule calleth the cheife mynyſtres, diſpenſatores, and him ſelfe ſometyme,1. Cor. 4. fedde them with mylke and ſometyme with ſtronger meates, which is not euery mans gifte and therefore hath ben in the churche cōmitted to few, and in reſpecte of the number, verye fewe, and of late ouer fewe, and ouer many alſo Ouer fewe of them that cryeth out of mens maners, and ouermany of thoſe, that flatter the multitude, wt vtteringe ſuche matter, as the number of nature variable, is glad to here. Nowe many nowe a dayes be ſo trauayled in them ſelf, with hearyng the ſermon, as they wepe and waile, and ſaye. Quid faciemus uiri fratres?
               Act. 2. Ionas. 3. Who preacheth lyke Io
               
                  •
               as to warne men of their deſtruction, both in body and ſoule, if they
 amende not their maners and lyuynge, In a miſerable ſtate of iniquitie and ſynne, ſome wolde haue nothinge preached but mercy, with onely Chriſte, and howe he beareth all ſinne, payeth all, purgeth all, and clenſeth all whiche is true, and 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                of it can not be blamed,The diuinitie. but 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                hath a great faulte.The ſteward dſhyp For albeit this be truth, &amp; is good meate: yet it is not well diſtribute, for it wolde ſerue better at ſupper, then at dyner. To men luſty, drowned in the worlde, and ouerwhelmed with ſynne, and in the mydde daye, whiles there is tyme of wakynge the iuſtice of god, is to be cryed out. Chriſtes ſecond cōming to be beaten in peoples eares, hys terrible iudgement to be layde before mens eyes which is a truth, as the other is, and profitable to be learned, taught, and thoughte on, wherevpon men ſhulde be exhorted
 to confeſſe their ſynnes to god and his mynyſter, to do penaunce for ſynne, to faſt for ſynne, to praye for ſynne, to do almes for ſynne, to wayle for ſynne. Dauyd confeſſed and felte goddes mercy and yet cried. Amplius laua me ab iniquitate mea &amp; a peecato meo munda me,
               Pſal. 50. 
               quoniam iniquitatem meam ego cognoſco, &amp; peccatum meum contra me eſt ſemper, and therewith ſaide,Pſal. 6. 
               turbatus eſt a furore oculus meus, his eye was troubled with goddes diſpleaſure, at the tyme he myſtruſted not goddes mercy, and therfore ſaid. Laboraui in gemitu meo lauabo per ſingulas noctes lectū
                meū,Ibidem. he trauailed in wailing &amp; waſſhed his couche with teares. But nowe ſo be men enueigled by the deuylles ſophiſtry, as mercy extolled and ſette forthe, with onelye fayth, and onelye ſauyour, and ommiſufficiēt
 niſufficiēt ſauiour, ſerueth to make men forget goddes iuſtice, &amp; waxe wantons (as they be termed) babes and youngelynges, and clerely fal from dreade and feare of god, whiche where it wanteth, ſynne muſte nedes encreaſe and ouerflowe, and by cuſtome mennes conſciences ſo blynded, as they diſcerne them not to be ſynnes and faultes, And thus muche I haue ſpoken of ſermons, whiche and they were neuer ſo well made and conceiued, yet ſo to vſe them, as they ſhoulde occupie the tyme of prayer requiſite,
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  
                S. Gregory in an Omilie noteth not good And therefore on Chriſtemas day, when the churche hath thre maſſes, he ſaid he could not ſpend ſo much tyme with his audience that daye, as he was wonte to do. And yet ſermons at thoſe dayes, as appeareth by ye ſermons they made, were not longe. But longe or ſhorte, as they
 be good holeſome and requiſite, &amp; in the churche, at their tyme neceſſary, ſo hauyng not theyr tyme, but with iuſteling an other good thing out of ordre, that is not well, and moche leſſe ſtudy to be vſed in time of prayer, whiche prayer and ſtudy as they haue a diſtincte nature: ſo they ſhulde be in tyme diſtinct.
            And theunomians opinion, by contrary exerciſe reproued, to thinke that readinge, is the onely waye to heauen. But herein I haue taried ouer longe, as ſome wyll fynde faulte at me, and aſke what is prayer and faſtinge to the ſacramente of the aulter? and muche leſſe ſermons or ſtudy in tyme of prayer? Wherevnto thus I aunſwer, that hauynge occaſion mynyſtred, by this greate clerke, Gregorye Nazianzene, I haue ſpoken of them.
            And becauſe the deuyll entendeth to ſubuerte all: I ſhewe alſo, his ſo
 phiſtrie in lower matters, then is the ſacramente of thaulter, towardes deſtruction whereof he made him ſelf and entry, by ouerthrowing that might ſtande in his waye, and ſo the more facyly to aſſaulte the higheſt, as he hath done, and therein (as I haue ſaid) maketh a great matter of the name of the maſſe, &amp; wyll haue it called our lordes ſupper, wherein he wyll haue all obſerued, as chriſt miniſtred it, whiche this Gregory Nazianzene ſaith, is not neceſſarye. But we ſhulde here in gyue credite to oure mother the churche, the piller of truthe, &amp; who truelye teacheth vs, that is truthe. Who foraſmuche as with the obſeruation of this feaſte, in receyuyng eatynge and drynkynge Chriſtes mooſt preciouſe bodye and bloude,Malachi▪ 1. is alſo celebrate, the perpetual only pure ſacrifice, prophecyed by the prophet Malachie, to be obſerued
 and kept, continually in the churche of Chryſte, whiche ſacryfyce, is the body and bloude of our ſauyour Chriſt. The ſame church hath receyued one worde of Hebrewe, to ſignifie altogether, and vſed in the latyn (Miſſa) &amp; in englyſſh (maſſe) wherein beſides the gloriouſe preſence of the body &amp; bloud of Chriſt the holy circumſtaunces vſed, and ceremonies doone, be alſo manye godly and mooſt deuoute prayers, ſpoken and vttered by the preiſte, as a common miniſter to the hole churche, for and in the name of the hole churche, by whyche churche, Chriſt, as heade is offered, and the churche alſo, as member of his miſticall bodye, is offered to god the father by hym, as Saynte Auguſtine ſayethe. Ipſa per ipſum, &amp; ipſe per ipſam, ſuetus offerri. The church by hym, and he by the churche, accuſtomed to be offered. So
 as the maſſe conteininge the hole ſupper, that is to ſay, the hole feaſt, with the continuall oblation of the churche, is by the deuylles inuention aſſaulted diuers wayes. Some deny the maſſe, becauſe they reade not the worde maſſe in ſcrypture, whiche and it were a good cauſe of deniall, it ſhuld ſerue to renewe the Arryans hereſye, and to put out of the crede, called Symbolum apoſtolorum (whiche all Chriſten men receyue without contradictiō) where filius is called conſubſtantialis patri. Other allow maſſe they ſay, but not priuye maſſes, as though there were two ſortes of maſſes, where in deede the maſſe beinge but one, and alwayes executed in the name of ye hole churche, may by reaſon of the place, be called priuate, as it maye be by reaſon of ſaieng, called a low maſſe, and ſo differre from a maſſe ſunge, but els, the churche by the
 common mynyſtre the preiſt, executeth the maſſe her ſelfe, howe fewe ſoeuer, or howe manye be preſente, and whyther it be done at churche before ye multitude, or in an oratory before fewe. And yet with the name of priuate maſſes, and deniall of them, the vnlearned be ſlaundered as ſome be alſo with requeſte of cō
               munion vnder both kyndes, as neceſſarye, and not to be pretermitted In whyche pointe the deuyll goth aboute, craftely to ſeduce the ſymple, addynge a wordly inſtigation of enuye, as thoughe the preiſtes had withdrawen the one parte of ye Sacramente, of verye dyſdaine to put a difference betwene the ſtate of preiſtes, and the ſtate of lay men where in dede, the obteyninge of communion vnder bothe kyndes, ſhulde ſerue the deuyll onelye, for an introduction, to ſubuerte ye true belefe, in the moſt bleſſed ſacramēt
 Whiche matter only he entendeth, &amp; leaueth nothing vntouched to obteine ye ſame. For where the church teacheth truely, yt vnder eche kind, is cōteined hole chriſt, &amp; therefore now vnder the one kind, eche man receiueth as much as vnder bothe vpon which groūd good deuoute mē, haue abſtained frō cōmunion vnder both kyndes, &amp; cōtēted them ſelfe wt one king, of their good deuout mind: if now vpon grudge of ſuch as contente not thē ſelfe with the order they find in the churche, ye church ſhuld graunt communion vnder both kindes, to ſatiſfye the falſe complaynt of neceſſite, it muſt nedes engender a ſlaunder in the truth of the faith, as thoughe hole chriſt were not vnder eche kinde, which by the denil is only intended And in this matter of cōmuniō vnder both kyndes, it was neuer denied but all ſtates of men euer might
 and al ſtate of mē in the beginning haue communicate in both kindes and among them children alſo, n
                  •
                there hath ben any lawe made to ye contrary, as the deuyll ſurmyſeth. Onely this hath bene, that good chriſten men beinge certainely perſwaded vnder eche kinde of bread and wine, to be cōteined hole chriſt All ſuche chriſten men, aſwell preiſtes as other, beſydes the preiſte that celebrate, haue bene contente to receiue their communion vnder one kynde, Whiche deuout cuſtome, when the deuyll by his miniſters hath gone aboute to improue, there was ones a lawe made to mainteine ye good cuſtome againſte the deuilles enterpryſe, as in thys realme▪ the hole perlyament hath made the like, whereby thoſe be onely put to ſilence, that ſay, communion vnder bothe kyndes is neceſſary, whiche is an opinion
 damnable, and worthelye reproued, but elles that by order of ye churche, all men might communicate vnder bothe kyndes, no man contendeth, For firſt in the deuout cuſtome of communion vnder one kynde, wherein was profeſſed the truth taughte by the churche in the ſacramente of thaulter, onely charitie was the rule, whereby good men were moued for a ſemelynes &amp; decency in the church, and eſchewynge that they ſawe ſometimes vnſemely chaunce, of th
                  •
               mſelfe, without conſtraint of a law, to forbeare that they mighte haue required, &amp; no man by law expelled, from that he myght haue aſked. Whiche charitie, becauſe it is now waxed cold and ſome men for ſingularite wold differre from the reſte, it is for conſeruation of ordre well prouided by the lawe, that no man ſhall preſume to require furder then is neceſſary,
 to the ſlaunder and offence of his neighbour, but with humilitie conteine him ſelfe within the limit
                  •
               es of common ordre, whiche is the beautie and comelye ſtate or euery number aſſembled, beinge ſo muche regarded of ſainte Paule, as he willed men to forbeare to cō
               panye with any brother that walketh out of order. But here will be replied that chriſtes ordre is to be preferred all other deuiſes. And here commeth in the common place of ſcripture.Math. 14: 
               Fruſtra colunt me doctrinis hominum,
               Mar. 7. They worſhyp me in vayne with the teachynges of men. And theſe good me I ſpake of, ſhall be called good fooles, the whiche had, zelum dei, ſed non ſecundum ſcientiam,
               Rom. 1▪
                the zeale to god but not accordynge to true knowlege, whiche now appeareth (they wyll ſay) when men ſe clerely Chriſtes inſtitution of this ſacrament,
 whiche when it is vſed accordynge to Chriſtes inſtitution is the ſacrament, and otherwiſe as they ſaye, not. And this worde (inſtitution) is often repeted, &amp; yet ye ſame word (inſtitution) is not in ſcripture by thoſe ſyllables, but Saynt Paule ſpeakethe of tradytyon, of the vſe of this Sacramente, as he receyued it of oure lorde. Ego enim accepi à domino,
               1. Cor. 1
                     •
                  . 
               quod &amp; tradidi uobis. I haue receyued of our lorde, whiche I haue by tradition delyuered vnto you. Whereby and by that foloweth. when he ſaith. Cetera cum venero diſponam. I ſhall ordre the reſte when I come:Ibidem it appereth he hadde taught the Corrinthians, the ſumme of this hygh miſtery, and the vſe of it, without writyng before, and wolde adde more whē he came, whichmore, he taught and yet we haue no wrytynge of it, but the churche hath not forgotten
 it, but hath taught it without writynge, as ſhe receiued it. And it appeareth in that epiſtle of S. Paule that reherſynge ſuche tradicion as they had receiued of hym, he blameth and reproueth them, for the not obſeruation of it. And thus muche, for the worde (inſtitution) that pleaſeth, which ſcripture hath not and the worde, tradicion, abhorred, that ſcripture hathe, ſo as wordes go but by fauour, as this matter is hādled. But ye matter of this obiectiō muſt be aunſwered ſeriouſely, which is grounded vpon the texte of ſcripture, Fruſtra colūt me doctrinis hominum, They worſhippe me in vayne, wyth the doctrine of men, the true ſenſe wherof, is all oute of thys purpoſe, and the vſe of thys ſcrypture, as it is myſvnderſtanded, ſerueth to ouerturne all, For the churche is congregate of men and women, whyche
 both be comprehended vnder that worde (men), And all the outwarde teachynge in this churche, hathe ben by men. All thappoſtles ſent to teache the goſpell, were mē. Saynt Paule at his conuerſion frome darkenes to lyght,Act. 9: when it was ſaid to him yt it ſhuld be tolde hym what he ſhuld do, then was Ananias by god ordred to go to Paule, and declare what he ſhuld do. Moyſes, leader of ye ſynagoge ye figure of our church, was a mā. And the prophetes were men. So as if god be worſhypped in vayne, by teachinge of men: Inanis eſt fides noſtra,
               Rom. 10. our fayth is a vayne thynge, whiche is, ex auditu, of hearing, and taughte vs by men, men I ſaye, as miniſtres to god, wherof god is thauthor, à quo omne datum optimum
               Iacob. 1. 
               et omne donum perfectum, &amp; Chriſt ſayd. Sine me nihil poteſtis facere. But
 hereby appereth yt this text, hath another vnderſtandynge, and the worde (men) not to ſignifie the hole numbre of men, ſo as it ſhuld comprehend eche man throughly, how ſo euer they be qualified, but onely the corrupte ſtate of man, ſeuered from god and his church in chriſt, of whiche hole ſtate not endued wt goddes grace,Pſal. 11
                     •
                  . it is ſayde Omnis homo mendax. All men be lyers. That is to ſaye, all ſuche as haue not putte vpon them Chriſte, who is truthe. And fruſtra colunt me doctrinis hominū. They worſhyp me in vayne, with the teachynges of ſuche as remayne in the ſtate of men onelye, and then teache their owne, &amp; of them ſelfe. For all ſuche teachynge is lyke the teacher, that is to ſay, carnall. For the carnall man,1. Cor. 2: Io. 4. 
               non percipit ea quae ſunt ſpiritus, &amp; deus eſt ſpiritus, &amp; in ſpiritu adoratur, and therefore god
 is worſhipped in vaine with the teachinge of men. For it hathe the pretence of worſhyppe, and is not directed to hym, but onelye deuyſed to vpholde worldelye polycye Suche deuiſes had Numa pompilius, with the Romaines, and afore him, Licurgus, with the Lacedemonians, and of late, Mahomete with the Turkes, and more lately all ſuch as haue taken vpon them to vnderſtande the ſcriptures alone, and them ſelfe alone deuiſed, howe they wold haue god worſhipped, after their faſhion, withoute noyſe or brute, without the compaſſe of our eares or eyes, only by readynge that they vnderſtande not, ſauyng ſome be ſo ful of knowledge, as they encombre the companye more with their harſe rude voice in prattelynge, then the paryſſhe clerke with his horſe breſte,
 in ſinginge. Of all theſe ſortes of mens teachinges, which be mens deuiſes, ſeuered frō Chriſtes churche, maye be ſayde fruſtra me colūt doctrinis hominum. But ſuch men as be membres of Chriſtes myſticall body, in his churche, and haue the place of ordering and teaching in the ſame, vnto whome other, are bounde to obeye and gyue eare vnto them, ſuche men be comprehended in this text. Fruſtra colunt me doctrinis hominum, But he that cōtemneth thoſe thinges that they teache, agreablye to the truthe receyued:1, Theſ, 4. Heb, 13, 1 Reg, 15, 
               non hominem ſpernit, ſed deū, who ſaith, Obey ſuch as haue the ordre of you, and obedience is preferred al other ſacrifices, wherwt god is worſhipped not invaine, but meritoriouſelye. And therefore that texte alledged, agaynſte the teachinge in chriſtes churche, is as
 groſſely abuſed, as a key to cleaue logges. For if the doctryne be not repugnaunt to the ſcripture, or the cuſtome ſuche as hyndreth not gods glory, it can not be in vaine that maketh to oure edificacion, &amp; procedeth from authoritie, which hath power to rule and leade vs, whereby we be all directed, to do one thyng, to declare &amp; ſette forthe, that we be one bodye, wherein god is glorified, accordynge as Chryſt ſayd.Matth. 5. 
               Vt videāt opera veſtra bona, &amp; glorificent deū, qui in coelis eſt. And ſo when S. Paule ordered the women to be couered in ye churche,1 Cor. 11. to ſignifie her ſubiection, and that ſhe had ones offended, in her preuarication agaynſt her huſbād and god, and with preſumption to haue knowledge, was the ruine of mankynd, and furder ordered her, to kepe ſylence in ye congregation: this text of fruſtra colūt me doctrinis
               1. Timot. 2.
                
               hominum, yf it had bene then written, wold not haue ſerued the women to replye and ſaye, Theſe were ſmall matters, whyche god regardeth not, and therfore ſayd. Fruſtra colunt me, doctrinis hominum. They worſhyppe me in vayne, with the doctrines of men. For ſaint Paule was not in the numbre of theſe men (as I ſayde before) and his authorite was of god, and the thynges ordered for a godly purpoſe, wherwith god is in the decente ſemely ordre of his people, duely worſhipped and alſo pleaſed. This matter I haue now ſpoken, wyll be called a digreſſiō, and out of the matter of the ſacrament, &amp; in dede, it is not all togyther in it, but toward it, for I truſt hereby, that commen weapō ſhall be layde aſyde, of fruſtra colunt me, doctrinis hominum, whiche manye had in their mouthe, as
 they haue a blunt dagger by their ſyde, to be ſene to ſpeake ſcripture, though it be nothing to the purpoſe. And now I wyl com to the inſtitution of chriſt of the holy ſacrament. And here men muſt take heede that they be not deceyued, in the word (inſtitutiō) as ſignifieng furder vnto them, then the ſcriptures do teſtyfye. For yf by the worde (inſtitution) ſhulde be ſignyfyed a preciſe ordre, ſette forth with all the circumſtaunce in the nature of a precyſe lawe, ſignifienge that it muſte be frome thenſeforth, ſo obſerued and none otherwiſe, whych matter, the worde (inſtitution) ſemeth to include, and ſoundethe ſo in common reaſon: there appeareth not in ſcripture, any inſtitution of this nature, For we rede not in ſcripture, that Chryſte dydde preſcribe, any ſuche precyſe ordre of receiuing or miniſtryng▪ but as
 in his ſupper he in dede conſecrated both kindes, &amp; miniſtred bothe kyndes,Luc, 24, whereby appearethe that all myghte receaue bothe kindes, as all ſometime haue done: Soo lykewiſe when he mynyſtred the ſacrament to his diſciples in Emaus,Act. 2
                     •
                  
                and other amonge the apoſtles, who vnderſtode Chriſte: we reade of the miniſtracion of the one kynde, wherby appeareth, that the one kynd vnder forme of bread may be miniſtred alone. And therefore of any ſuche inſtitucyon, as ye worde (inſtitution) doth ſounde at the firſt hearing, is not teſtified in ſcriptures. But yf we meane, by inſtitution, the firſte conſecration of it, when by goddes mighty worde the miracle was wroughte in the conuerſion of breade and wyne, in to the body and bloud of chriſt, wt commaundemente to the churche,
 to do the ſame tyll he comme: Of this the euangeliſtes beare wytneſſe, which the church hath receiued. And as ſ. Paule ſaide. Ego accepi à domino, quod &amp; tradidi vobis: So the hole churche may ſaye the ſame wordes, with lyke credite by whoſe mynyſtery, the ſame feaſt is dayly prepared for ye hole church with conſecracion of the body and bloude of Chriſte, whereof good men reioyſynge them ſelf, with the preſence of the hole myſtery, which they ſe in the maſſe, at which tyme good mē alſo ſpiritually eate and drynke the ſame, with the common mynyſtre, and beleuynge the hole to be in eche kynde: haue by example of chriſtes diſciples in EmausLuc. 24▪
                contented them ſelf in the ſacramental communion with the one kynde, not repelled as vnworthie to receyue the other kynde, but forbearynge of them ſelfe reuerently,
 for the more ſemelye diſtribucion, and ordre amonge them, whiche the churche hath allowed, as our mother and nourſe, who contynually feadeth vs, with the foode of truth. And therfore ſeing we be aſſured, that as Chryſt dyd inſtitute the ſacrament, ſo he inſtituted the church, to be fedde with the ſame ſacrament, and to haue the miniſtracion, diſtribution, &amp; ordre of it, tyll he came. And vnto this daye, we be onely aſcertayned by tradicion of the church, in the true vnderſtandyng of theuāgelyſtes, of our ordre in cōſecracion of the ſaid ſacrament, and the cyrcumſtaunce of the pronunciation of chryſtes wordes, wherby the ſame is wrought. What can it meane but confuſion, to wrangle with the church in this matter, &amp; by cauilaciō of wordes, trouble ye ſymple vnderſtandynges? What a worde is
 (inſtitution) with the vnderſtandyng they geue it, to aſtoine the rude eares? For who can ſuffre, to here ſpoken that Chriſtes inſtitution, ſhulde be broken or altered? conſidering the word carieth with it a ſonnde of precyſenes, and commaundemente in Chriſte of this or that ordre, whiche can not be verified, ſpeakynge of the inſtitution of the ſacramente, and the worde well vnderſtoode, maye be ſuffred ſygnifienge the fyrſte exhibicion and miniſtracion of it, And ſo ſome wryte, that as Chryſte dydde in the ſyxte of Iohn̄, promiſe the inſtitution of the ſacramente, ſayenge.
            
               Panis quem dabo uobis, caro mea eſt, pro mundi vita.
               Ioā, 6. The breade I ſhall gyue you, is my fleſh, for the lyfe of the worlde: So dydde he inſtitute the ſame in his laſte ſupper of whiche inſtitucion men wolde
 nowe make a preciſe lawe, as the ordre ſhulde be taken awaye from the churche mother of truthe, whiche folowynge Chriſtes example, and the apoſtels, hath ſuffered cō
               munion vnder one kynd, and hath reiected ſuche, as wolde improue the ſame, as men onely ſtudiouſe to impugne an eſtablyſhed ordre, whiche faulte is now moche ſpred abrode, both in this high matter, &amp; alſo in ceremonies, and namelye ſuche as garniſſhe Chriſtes religion, wherein the deuyl vſeth a merueilſouſe point of ſophiſtry, by diuiſion, and examininge partes alone whiche partes ſo conſidered ſeuerallye,Note this difference, howe thynges may be called &amp; be neceſſary in relatiō, whiche els might be omytted. be nothynge, and yet ioyned togither, be ſomewhat, and verye neceſſarye, and here I ſaye neceſſary for our eſtate, although not neceſſarye, in reſpect of the pryncypall thynge.
            I wyl open this point of ſophiſtry
 whyche conſyſtethe in dyuyſyon, in whiche the ſmalenes of the part deuyded from the reſte, and conſydered alone, is in reſpecte of the hole, called nothing. And in comen ſpeache it hath obteined to cal that nothinge, which by compariſon of a farre greater, is very lytell. As yf one were aſked, whither a farthinge wolde make a ryche man? A ſimple man wolde aunſwere.
            Naye, and in dede a farthing conſidered alone is nothinge regarded, and yet of ſuche lyttell farthinges, in numbre ſet togither, ryches cōſyſteth, &amp; by the ſame diſſeuered, is induced pouertie. A quantitie maye be ſo minutely deuided, that his partes be accompted nothinge &amp; yet thoſe ſame together ioyned, make the greate maſſe, and haue an eſtimation. And therfore in the dyſcuſſion of ceremonies, ſemelynes, and orders, the deuyl frameth
 his queſtions by diuyſion, and aſketh of eche thynge alone, diſſeuered from the reſte. As for example. Whither a ſhauen crowne maketh a preiſte? where vnto a man muſte aunſwere, as he wolde do to the queſtion of a farthinge before moued, and ſaye, Naye. Well ꝙ the deuyll, then awaye with youre crowne, and calleth it a fleſhmarke becauſe he wyl with a nycke name deface it. Then he aſketh whether a longe gowne maketh a preiſt, of that colour or that faſhyon, &amp; then it muſt be aunſwered, Naye. And then there muſt be a ſonge made of it, with awaye with it. Then the deuyll commeth to the ceremonies in ordres geuinge, and aſketh of ceremonies ſeuerallye alone, whervnto as he diſſeuereth them, ye aunſwere muſt be no, whervpon he concludeth. Ergo they be nothinge requiſite, After whyche
 ſorte, he ſhall alſo diuide you the ſacramentall wordes, and aſke of euery worde of them alone, And as it is graunted, how that one word doth it not, that worde is layde aſide, And ſo he wyll peruſe all, and by ſophiſtrye in deuiſion wipe out all, as nothinge. And in other matters lykewiſe frame this queſtion, for example. Shall forbearinge of meates ſaue a man? The aunſwer muſt be. No. And then, Ergo eate all daye longe. Dothe watchinge bringe a man to heauen? Naye, Ergo ſlepe and ſpare not. Is ye place cauſe why a mans praier is good? The aunſwere muſte be, Nay, And what nedeſte thou comme to churche then, ſayth the deuyll, onles it be to heare my falſe teachynge ſet forthe. And thus by theſe ſubtle queſtions the deuyll robbeth ſimple men, euen of the ſubſtaunce by degrees of true religion, as paraſites
 and flatterers robbe wanton heyres of their worldlyge ſubſtaūce, by alluring them to prodigall and waſtefull diſtribution of their go
                  •
               
               des and landes, in ſeueral litle portions, with theſe queſtions to the wiſe yonge mā, what is this to you ſir? a ſmall matter in your purſe, and nothinge to youre ſubſtaunce But by ſuche nothinges, we haue ſene yonge heyres, ſodēly brought to nothinge, and made verye beggers, As we ſe lykewyſe, by the deuylles ſophiſtical entiſementes by ſeueral inquiſitions, of the validitie of this or that ceremony alone, ceremonies ſo contempned of many, as the ſubſtaunce of oure religion, is amonge manye prodigall chyldren, waſted and conſumed, &amp; by contempte of the preiſt and his garmentes aparte, by ſmall regarde to the place, and other ceremonyes neglected: Chryſte hym
 ſelfe in the ſacramente of the aulter is deſpiſed mocked &amp; ſkorned, with ſuche toyes and termes, as the Iewes deuiſed not more ſpiteful, euen when they ſaluted him, wt 
               Aue rex Iudeorum,
               Matt. 27. Mar. 15. Ioan. 19. and ſpette in his teeth: But after the ſame ſorte reuerence decaieth towardes all eſtates and innocencye, as one writeth, departeth from man by degrees, no man begynneth with the greateſt abhominacion, but where ſmall faultes be not duely corrected, the greate and abhominable ſhall neuer be eſchewed. The marchaunte that wyll thryue, eſtemeth his farthynge, &amp; is therin throughlye wyttie to matche with the deuylles ſophiſtry, and can eſpy that althoughe a farthinge conſidered alone is nothinge, yet he is therein as wyſe as Heſiodus, who for a leſſon of thriuinge ſayeth, Lytle to litle, maketh a great heape. So
 wyſe be the chyldren of this world in theyr generation, to ordre ye wicked Mammona, And for conſeruation of our religion, whiche ſhulde for euer conſerue vs: we be ſo foolyſſhe, to be deceyued with the deuyls falſe ſophiſtrye in diuiſion, and call all nothinge, that conteine not the hole ſūme, wherof enſueth the diſſipation of all amonge many to the deſtruction of body and ſoule, for euer, as we haue latelye ſene in a few yt died moſt miſerably, to the terrible example of other, to beware by them. The wrath of god hath lighted on them, but they onelye were not in faulte.Eſa, 55, 
               Derelinquat impius uiam ſuam &amp; uir iniquus cogitationes ſuas. Beleef hath ben ſo moch talked on, &amp; with talking, men fallen into ſuche ydelneſſe of workes, that the deuyll hath taken his opportunitie, to ſpoyle men of their true beleef, for onelye beleefe
 wāteth that hath ben ſo much tratteled of, onelye to ſuffyſe. Cato the Romaine as a worldely, wyſe man vttered a prudent ſentence, that he feared the youth of the Romaines, ſhulde leaue their valyaunte actes after they beganne ones ſo muche to talke of them. The ſpeache was not the cauſe thereof, for then we ſhoulde ſaye, learninge were not good, but yet we often ſee them concurre togither, wherby appearethe ſuche corruption in manes nature as ſpeache in a cōmon welth, ſhuld be committed to fewe, and the multitude in ſylence, to ſpeake of vertue with their dedes. Accordinge wherevnto ſaint Paule ſaid.1, Cor, 14
                     •
                  
                Two or thre of the prophetes, ſhoulde ſpeake in the cōgregacion, and the reſte holde their peace, and none ſpeake agayne, onleſſe he hadde a newe reuelacion, If men waxe as wanton in their ſpeache, as wemen
 why ſhulde not ſuche, be vnder the precepte of ſcylence, aſwell as wemen, and if they be deſirouſe of knoweledge, aſcende to the mountayne, where it is placed by ſuche degrees, as Gregorye Nazianzene ſpeaketh of, very neceſſarye to be obſerued? For els in the tonge and knowledge, is moche looſenes and temeritie, oneles the ſame be ordered and ſtayed by the feare of god. For where is the feare of god, there is keping of his comaundementes, Where the comaundementes be kepte the carnall parte is purged,Eccle 2. whiche elles maketh mannes ſoule cloudye, and ſuffreth it not to ſe clearely, ye beame of godly light. Where is ſuche purgynge: there is clearenes, whiche cauſeth muche deſyre euermore to aſcende. frome vertue to vertue, which is the ſtay of knowledge, and confirmaciō of it, and ſo by theſe degrees, doinge
 is the waye to knowledge. But this ordre is pretermytted,Doynge is the meane 
                     •
                  waye to knowledge 1, Cor, 8. wherof foloweth ſuche effecte of knowlege as ſainte Paule ſpeaketh of. How knoweledge ſwelleth and puffethe vp mennes ſtomackes, the faulte whereof is not in learnynge, but in the indiſpoſiciō of ſuch, as preſume vnto it, which fault, god of his infinite mercye amende, for he onely can and wyll, when his pleaſure ſhalbe, whiche our behauyour towardes hym maye haſte or delaye. If requeſte, interceſſion, &amp; deſyre to all, enterlaced, with ſharpe punyſhmente to ſome, and mercye plentifullye mynyſtred to other, can refourme yt is amyſſe, all hath ben aſſayed and attempted on the kynges maieſties behalfe. As he is a prynce furnyſhed with knowledge and power, goddes ſpecyall gyftes and great: ſo he hath vſed both for the reformacion of his people.
 The conſeruation of true belefe is only deſyred, for the maynetenaunce of gods glory, wherin ye deuyll alſo pretendeth to laboure and trauayle, but deceytfullye and alſo ſophiſtycally, as I haue purpoſed to declare vnto you, whiche howe I wold haue done for the releif of other, I knowe, and howe I haue done, ſhal leaue it to youre iugement, which god direct, to the atteyninge of al truth, which is only in our ſauiour Ieſus chriſt, and by hym, whom all good chriſten mē haue from the beginning, &amp; do ſtill beleue, moſt aſſuredly, to be preſent really, in the ſacrament of thaulter, without leauinge his ſeate in heauen, where he is alſo continuallye our aduocate, to relieue our infirmities, as he is in the ſacrament of thaulter, to fede our weake bodies &amp; ſoules, wherby to make vs ſtrōg to come to him, &amp; liue without end.
            Amen.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            Prynted at London in Alderſgate ſtrete, by Ihon̄ Herforde, at the coſtes &amp; charges of Roberte Toye, dwellynge in Paules churcheyarde, at the ſygne of the Bell. 1546.
         
      
   

