
   
      
         
            The communication betwene my Lord Chauncelor and iudge Hales being among other iudges to take his oth in VVestminster hall. Anno. M.D.Liii. Vi. of October.
            Gardiner, Stephen, 1483?-1555.
         
         
            
               1553
            
         
         Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2004-08 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01457
            STC 11583
            ESTC S102823
            99838585
            99838585
            2969
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01457)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2969)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 294:07)
         
         
            
               
                  The communication betwene my Lord Chauncelor and iudge Hales being among other iudges to take his oth in VVestminster hall. Anno. M.D.Liii. Vi. of October.
                  Gardiner, Stephen, 1483?-1555.
                  Hales, James, Sir, d. 1554.
                  Bale, John, 1495-1563.
               
               [8] p.   
               
                  Printed by John Day,
                  [London? :
                  1553]
               
               
                  A reported conversation between Stephen Gardiner and Sir James Hales, sometimes attributed to John Bale.
                  Imprint from STC.
                  Signatures: a⁴ (title page printed as a4).
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Hales, James, --  Sir, d. 1554.
            
         
      
      
         
            2004-03
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2004-03
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2004-04
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2004-04
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2004-07
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            ¶THE COMMVNICAtion
betwene my Lord Chauncelor
and iudge Hales, being among
other iudges to take his oth
in VVestminster hall.
Anno. M.D.Liii.
Vi. of October.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            Chauncelor Hales.
            MAster Hales, ye shall vnderstand
that like as the
quenes highnes hath hertofore
receiuid good opinion
of you, especiallie, for that
ye stoode both faithfullie and laufulli
in hir cause of iust succession,
refusing to set your hande to the
booke amonge others that were against
hir grace in that behalfe: so
nowe through your owne late desertes:
against certain hir highnes
dooinges: ye stande not well in hir
graces fauour. And therfor, before
ye take anie othe, it shal be necessarie
for you to make your purgation,
            
               Hales.
               I praie you my Lorde, what is
the cause?
            
            
               Chauncelor,
               Informatiō is geuen▪ that ye haue
indicted certain pristes in Kent,
for saiing of Masse.
            
            
               Hales.
               Mi Lorde it is not so, I indicted
none, but in dede certaine indictamentes
of like matter wer brought
before me at the laste assises there

holdē, and I gaue order therein as
the lawe required. For I haue professed
the law, agaist which, in cases
of iustice wil I neuer (god willinge)
procede, nor in ani wise dissemble,
but with the same shewe
forth mi conscience, and if it were
to do againe, I wolde doe no lesse
then I did.
            
            
               Chauncelor.
               Yea master Hales, your cōsience
is knowne wel inough. I know ye
lacke no conscience.
            
            
               Hales.
               Mi Lord, ye mai do wel to serch
your owne conscience, for mine is
better knowne to mie selfe then to
you, and to be plaine, I did aswell
vse iustice in your saide Masse case
bi mi cōscience as bi the law, wherin
I am fulli bent to stand in trial to
the vttermost that can be obiected
And if I haue therin done ani iniuri
or wrōg: let me be iudged bi the
lawe, for I will seeke no better defence,
considering chiefli that it is
mi profession.
            
            
               Chauncelor.
               
                  
whi master Hales, althoughe ye
had the rigour of the law on your
side, yet ye might haue hadde regard
to the quenes highnes presēt
doinges in that case. And further
although ye seme to be more then
precise in the lawe: yet I thinke ye
wolde be veri loth to yelde to the
extremitie of suche aduantage as
mighte be gathered againste your
procedinges in the lawe, as ye haue
some time taken vppon you in
place of iustice. And if it were well
tried, I beleue ye shuld not be wel
able to stand honestli therto.
            
            
               Hales.
               Mi Lord i am not so perfect but
i mai erre for lacke of knowledge.
But both inconsience &amp; such knoledge
of the law as god hath geuē
me, i wil do nothing but i wil maintain
and abide in it. And if mi goodes
and all that I haue be not able
to counterpaise the case: mi bodie
shal be redi to serue the turne, for
thei be all at the quenes highnesse
pleasure.
            
            
               Chauncelor.
               
                  
Ah sir, ye be veri quicke &amp; stoute
in your answers. But as it shoulde
seme, that which ye did was more
of a will, fauouring the opinion of
your Religion against the Seruice
nowe vsed, then for ani occasiō or
zeale of iustice, seinge the quenes
highnes dooth set it furthe, as yet
wishinge all hir faithful subiectes
to imbrace it accordingli: &amp; where
ye offer both bodie and goodes in
your triall, there is no such matter
required at youre handes, and yet
ye shall not haue your owne will
neither.
            
            
               Hales.
               My Lord, I seke not wilful will,
but to shew my self as i am bound
in loue to God, and obedience to
the quenes maiestie, in whose cause
willīgly for iustice sake (al other
respectes set apart (i did of late (as
your Lordship knoeth) aduenture
as much as i had. And as for my religion,
i trust it to be suche as pleaseth
God, wherin i am redy to aduenture
aswell my life as my substaūce,
if i be called therunto. And

so in lacke of mine owne power ād
wil, the Lordes wil be fulfilled.
            
            
               Chauncelor.
               Seing ye be at this point Master
Hales, i wil presently make an end
with you. The quenes highnes shalbe
enfoutmed of youre opinion,
and declaration. And as hir grace
shal therupon determine, ye shall
haue knoledge, vntil whiche tyme
ye may depart, as ye came without
your oth, for as it appeareth, ye ar
scarse worthi the place appointed
            
            
               Hales.
               I thancke your Lordship, and as
for my vocation, being both a burthen
and a charge, more then euer
i desired to take vpon me, whensoeuer
it shal please the quenes highnes
to ease me therof: i shall moost
humbli with due contentation
obei the same.
            
            And so departed from
the barre.
         
      
   

