
   
      
         
            Solenne decretum a nationali ecclesiarum Gallicarum Synodo (celebrata Gapinci apud Delphinates) proclamatum &amp; publicæ confessioni earumdem adscriptum A solemn decree of the nationall synod of Gap, in the province of Delphine, in France, publikely proclaimed, and ascribed to the publique confession of the Church.
            Synod of Gap.
         
         
            
               1607
            
         
         Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01430
            STC 11548.7
            ESTC S3062
            29900394
            ocm 29900394
            28122
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01430)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28122)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1861:70)
         
         
            
               
                  Solenne decretum a nationali ecclesiarum Gallicarum Synodo (celebrata Gapinci apud Delphinates) proclamatum &amp; publicæ confessioni earumdem adscriptum A solemn decree of the nationall synod of Gap, in the province of Delphine, in France, publikely proclaimed, and ascribed to the publique confession of the Church.
                  Synod of Gap.
               
               1 sheet ([1] p.).   
               
                  Per Edwardum Allde &amp; A.J.,
                  Londini :
                  1607.
               
               
                  Reproduction of original in the Society of Antiquaries.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            lat
         
         
            
               Synod of Gap.
               Councils and synods.
               Broadsides --  London (England) --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-10
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-01
            Pip WillcoxSampled and proofread
         
            2008-01
            Pip WillcoxText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
               SOLENNE DECRETVM, A
nationali Eccleſiarum Gallicarum Synodo
(celebrata GAPINCI apud
Delphinates) proclamatum, &amp; publicae
Confeſsioni earumdem adſcriptum.
               
                  CVM Vero Epiſcopus Romanus, erecta
ſibi in orbe Chriſtiano Monarchia, ſibi
arroget Principatum in omnes Eccleſias
&amp; Paſtores: vſque adeo inflatus, Diſt. 96. Can. 7. Satis euidenter. Lib. 1. Sacrar. Cerem. Sect. 7
§. 6. De Enſe benedicendo. Vt
Deum ipſe ſe appellet. Concil. Lateran. vlt. Seſs. 1. 3. 9, &amp; 10. Velit adorari:
Ipſe ſibi tribuat omnem poteſtatem
in coelo &amp; in terra: Res Eccleſiaſticas ad libitum componat:
Cōdat articulos fidei: Authoritatem Scripturae velit
pendere a ſua, eamque ad libitum interpretetur: Animarum
mercaturam exerceat: Liberet adſtrictos votis &amp; iuramentis:
Nouos Dei cultus inſtituat: Et (quod ad Ciuilia
attinet) legitimam Magiſtratuum auctoritatem conculcet;
dans, adimens, &amp; transferens Regna: Credimus &amp; aſſerimus,
eum eſſe verum illum &amp; germanum ANTICHRISTVM,
Filium perditionis, praedictum in Verbo
Dei: Meretricem purpuratam, inſidentem ſeptem
montibus in magna Ciuitate; Obtinentem Regnum in
Reges terrae: Et expectamus donec Deus (prout promiſit,
&amp; iam coepit) eum fractum &amp; victum Spiritu oris ſui,
tandem deleat fulgore aduentus ſui.
               
                  Ʋiſum &amp; approbatum.
               SERƲET REGEM IACOBVM,
FIDEI DEFENSOREM DEVS.
            
            
               A SOLEMNE DECREE OF
the Nationall Synod of GAP, in the prouince
of Delphine in France, publikely proclaimed, and
aſcribed to the publique Confeſsion of the Church.
               
                  WHereas the Biſhop of Rome, hauing
erected a Monarchie in the Chriſtian
world, doth chalenge and arrogate
vnto himſelfe, the Principallitie
ouer al Churches and Paſtors,
being ſo extreamely proud &amp; puffed
vp, Diſt. 96. Can. 7. Satis euidenter. Lib. 1. Sacrar. Cerem. Sect. 7
§. 6. De Enſe benedicendo. That he calleth himſelfe
God. Concil. Lateran. vlt. Seſs. 1. 3. 9, &amp; 10. That he will be worſhiped: And alſo attributeth
vnto himſelfe all power in Heauen and in
Earth: ordereth Eccleſiaſticall matters at his
owne pleaſure: frameth new Articles of Faith:
will haue the Anthoritie of the Scriptures to depend
of his own Authority, &amp; interpreteth them as
he liſteth: exerciſeth the marchandizing of ſoules,
abſolues men from their vowes and oathes; Inſtituteth
new worſhip of God. And in like manner
(as cōcerning Ciuil affayres) treadeth vnder foote
the lawfull authoritie of Magiſtrates, giuing, taking
away, and tranſlating Kingdomes: We
doe ſtedfaſtly beleeue, and conſtantly affirme, that
Hee (the Pope of Rome) is that GREATE AND
PROPER ANTICHRIST, that Sonne of Perdition,
foretolde in the word of God, that purple
Harlot ſitting vpon ſeauen Hilles in the greate
Cittie, hauing obtained the kingdome ouer Kings
of the earth. And we wait and expect, whilſt that
God according to his promiſe, and as hee hath begunne
alreadie, to weaken and ouercome him
by the Spirit of his mouth, doth at laſt vtterlye
confound and deſtroy him, by the brightneſſe of his
comming.
               SEENE AND ALLOWED.
            
         
      
      
         
            Londini per Edwardum Allde &amp; A. J.
1604.
         
      
   

