
   
      
         
            The glasse of gouernement A tragicall comedie so entituled, bycause therein are handled aswell the rewardes for vertues, as also the punishment for vices. Done by George Gascoigne Esquier. 1575. Seen and allowed, according to the order appointed in the Queenes maiesties iniunctions.
            Glass of governement
            Gascoigne, George, 1542?-1577.
         
         
            
               1575
            
         
         Approx. 201 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01520
            STC 11643A
            ESTC S105718
            99841444
            99841444
            6028
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01520)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6028)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 528:11)
         
         
            
               
                  The glasse of gouernement A tragicall comedie so entituled, bycause therein are handled aswell the rewardes for vertues, as also the punishment for vices. Done by George Gascoigne Esquier. 1575. Seen and allowed, according to the order appointed in the Queenes maiesties iniunctions.
                  Glass of governement
                  Gascoigne, George, 1542?-1577.
               
               [106] p.   
               
                  [By Henry Middleton] for C. Barker,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  [1575]
               
               
                  Colophon reads "Imprinted at London in Fleetestreate at the signe of the Faulcon by Henry Middleton, for Christopher Barker. Anno Domini. 1575.". A later state (STC 11643) has N1 in a different setting; Middleton is identified only by his initials, and errata are printed below the colophon.
                  Signatures: A⁴ ² A-M⁴ N²  (-N2).
                  The first leaf is blank.
                  Running title reads: The glasse of gouernment.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2002-10
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2002-11
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2002-12
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2002-12
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            ¶ The Glasse of Gouernement. A tragicall Comedie so entituled, bycause therein are handled aswell the rewardes for Vertues, as also the punishment for Vices. Done by George Gascoigne Esquier. 1575.
            Blessed are they that feare the Lorde, their children shalbe as the branches of Oliue trees rounde about their table.
            Seen and allowed, according to the order appointed in the Queenes maiesties Iniunctions.
            ¶ IMPRINTED at London for C. Barker
            
         
         
            
            The names of the Actors.
            
               
                  Phylopaes and Two parents being nigh neyghbours.
               
                  Philocalus Two parents being nigh neyghbours.
               
                  Gnomaticus a Scholemaster.
               
                  Phylautus Sonnes to Phylopaes.
               
               
                  Phylomusus Sonnes to Phylopaes.
               
               
                  Phylosarchus Sonnes to Phylocalus.
               
               
                  Phylotimus Sonnes to Phylocalus.
               
               
                  Seuerus the Markgraue.
               
                  Eccho the Parasyte.
               
                  Lamia the Harlot.
               
                  Pandarina Aunt to Lamia.
               
               
                  Dick Drumme the Royster.
               
                  Nuntij two Messengers.
               
                  Onaticus seruant to the Schoolemaster.
               
                  Fidus seruant to Phylopaes.
               
               
                  Ambidexter seruant to Phylocalus.
               
               
                  Chorus 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   graue Burghers.
            
            The Comedie to be presented as it vvere in Antvverpe.
         
         
            
            The Argument.
            TVVo riche Citizens of Andvverpe (beeing nighe neighboures, &amp; hauing eche of them tvvo sonnes of like age) do place them togither vvith one godly teacher. The scholemaster doth briefly instruct them their duetie tovvardes God, their Prince, their Parents, their cuntrie, and all magistrates in the same. The eldest being yong men of quicke capacitie, do (Parrotte like) very quickly learne the rules vvithout booke: the yonger beeing somevvhat more dull of vnderstanding, do yet engraue the same vvithin their memories. The elder by allurement of Parasites and levvde company, beginne to incline themselues to concupiscence. The parents (to preuent it) sende them all togither to the Vniuersitie of Dowaye, vvhereas the yonger in short space be (by painefull studie) preferred, that one to be Secretarie vnto the Palsegraue, that other becommeth a famous preacher in Geneua. The eldest (turning to their vomit) take their cariage vvith them, and trauaile the vvorlde. That one is apprehended and executed for a robbery (euen in sight of his brother) in the Palsgraues courte: that othervvhipped and banished Geneua for fornication: notvvithstanding the earnest sute of his brother for his pardon.
            
               The whole Comedi
                     •…
                   a figure of the rewardes and punishmentes of vertues and vices.
            
         
         
            
            The Prologue.
            
               WHat man hath minde to heare a worthie Iest,
               Or seekes to feede his eye with vayne delight:
               That man is much vnmeete to be a guest,
               At such a feaste as I prepare t
                     •…
                  is night.
               VVho list laye out some pence in such a Marte,
               Bellsauage fayre were fittest for his purse,
               I lyst not so to misbestowe mine arte,
               I haue best wares, what neede I then shewe woorse?
               An Enterlude may make you laugh your fill,
               
                  Italian toyes are full of pleasaunt sporte:
               Playne speache to vse, if wanton be your wyll,
               You may be gone, wyde open standes the porte.
               But if you can contented be to heare,
               In true discourse howe hygh the vertuous clyme,
               Howe low they fall which lyue withouten f
                     •…
                  are
               Of God or man, and much mispende theyr tyme:
               VVhat ryght rewardes a trustie seruaunt earnes,
               VVhat subtile snares these Sycophantes can vse,
               Howe soone the wise such crooked guyles discernes,
               Then stay a whyle: gyue eare vnto my Muse.
               A Comedie, I meane for to present,
               No Terence phrase: his tyme and myne are twaine:
               The verse that pleasde a Romaine rashe intent,
               Myght well offend the godly Preachers vayne.
               Deformed shewes were then esteemed muche,
               Reformed speeche doth now become vs best,
               Mens wordes muste weye and tryed be by touche
               Of Gods owne worde, wherein the truth doth rest.
               Content you then (my Lordes) with good intent,
               Graue Citizens, you people greate and small,
               To see your selues in Glasse of Gouernement:
               Beholde rashe youth, which daungerously doth fall
               On craggy rockes of sorrowes nothing softe,
               VVhen sober wittes by Vertue clymes alofte.
            
            
               This vvorke is compiled vpon these sentences following, set downe by mee C. B.
            
               1
               Feare God, for he is iust.
               Loue God, for hée is mercifull.
               Truste in God, for he is faythfull.
            
            
               2
               Obey the King, for his a
                     •…
                  cthoritie is from aboue.
               Honor the King, for he is in earth the liuetenant of the moste hygh God.
               Loue the King, for he is thy protector.
            
            
               3
               Aduenture thy life in defence and honor of thy cuntrie, for the quarrell is good.
               Be not vnthankfull to the soyle that hath nurished thée, for it is a damnable thing.
               Studie to profite the common wealth, for it is commendable with God and man.
            
            
               4
               Reuerence the minister of God, for his office sake.
               Loue the minister that preacheth the Gospell, for it is the power of God to saue thée.
               Speake good of the minister, for the Gospelles sake.
            
            
               5
               Thinke wel of the magistrates, for it pleaseth god wel.
               Be not disobedient to the magistrates, for they are the 
                     •…
                  ies of the King.
               Loue the magistrates, for they are the bones &amp; s
                     •…
                  nowes of the Common wealth.
            
            
               6
               Honor thy parents, for God hath commaunded it.
               Loue thy parents, for they haue care ouer thée.
               Be assisting vnto thy parentes with any benefite that God hath indued thée, for it is thy duetie.
            
            
               7
               Giue place to thine elder, for it is thy prayse.
               Let not a gray head passe by thée without a salutation.
               Take counsell of an elder, for his experience sake.
            
            
               8
               Be holie, for thou art the Temple of God.
               It is an horrible sinne to pollute Gods Temple.
               The buyers and sellers were driuen out of the Temple with violence.
            
         
         
            
            In Comoediam Gascoigni, carmen B. C.
            
               Haec noua, non vetus est, Angli comoedia Vatis,
               Christus adest, sanctos nil nisi sancta decent.
               Graecia vaniloquos genuit, turpes
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   Poetas,
               Vix qui syncerè scriberet vnus erat.
               Id vereor nostro ne possitdicier aeuo,
               Vanaprecor valeant, vera precor placeant.
            
            
               
            
         
      
      
         
            The Glasse of Gouernment.
         
            Actus primi
            
               Scaena prima.
               PHYLO PAES and PHYLOCALVS Parentes, FIDVS seruaunt to PHILOPAES. they come in talkinge.
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  
                     SUrely Phylocalus I thinke my selfe indebted vnto you for this fréendly discourse, and I do not onely agrée with you in opinion, but I most earnestly de sire, that wee may with one assente deuise which way the same may be put in executiō, for I delight in your louing neighbourhood, and I take singular comfort in your graue aduise.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  It were not reason Phylopaes that hauing so many yeares contineued so neare neighboures, hauing traffiqued (in maner) one selfe same trade, hauing susteyned like aduentures, and being blessed with like successes, we should now in the ende of our time become any lesse then entiere frendes: and as it is the nature and propertie of frendshippe to séeke alwaies for perpetuity, so let vs séeke to bring vp our Children in such mutuall societie in their youth, that in age they may no lesse delight in theyr former felowship, then wée theyr parentes haue taken comfort in our continuall cohabitation. It hath pleased Almighty God to blesse vs both with competent wealth, and though we haue atteyned therevnto by continuall payns and tra
                        •…
                     ayle, rising (as it w
                        •…
                     re) from meane 
                        •…
                     state, vnto dignity, yet d
                        •…
                     e I thi
                        •…
                     e t
                        •…
                     t it were not a
                        •…
                     isse to bring 
                        •…
                     p our children with s
                        •…
                     ch 
                        •…
                     tion as 
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        •…
                     ay excell in knowledge of liberall 
                        〈◊〉
                     , f
                        •…
                     r if we 
                        •…
                     g vn
                     
                        •…
                     ed

haue by industrie heaped vp sufficient store, not only to serue our owne vse, but further to prouide for our posterity, then may they by learning aspire vnto greater promotion, and builde greater matters vppon a better foundation. Neither yet would I haue you conceiue hereby that I am ambicious. But if I be not deceyued, Al desire of promotion (by vertue) is godly and Lawfull, where as ambition is commonly nestled in the brestes of the enuious.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  I am of your opi
                        •…
                     n Phylocalus, and since we haue ech of vs two Sonnes of equall age and stature, I would we could be so happie as to finde some honest and carefull schoolemaister, who might enstruct them togither: I say honest, because in the house of the vertuous there is seldome any vice permitted, and carefull, because the care of the teacher is of no lesse consideration then his skill: thē do I wish him both honest and carefull, because the coniunction of two such qua
                        •…
                     ities, may both cause the accomplishment of his dutie, &amp; the contentations of our desires. Our eldest Sonnes are neare the age of xxi. yeares, &amp; our younger Sonnes not much more then one yeare behinde them. So that as they haue hitherto bene thought toward enough at such common schooles as they haue frequented, and therefore wil shortly be ready for the vniuersity, yet would I thinke conuenient that they spent some time together, with some such honest and careful Schoolemaister, who might before theyr departure lay a sure foū
                     dation to their vnderstanding.
               
               
                  Fidus.
                  Although it becommeth not a seruaunt to come vnto his masters counsell before he be called, yet for that I am no way ignoraunt of your tender cares, which both of you haue alwaies had ouer your children, and also for that I do now perc
                        •…
                     iue the continuaunce of the same by this your fatherly conference, I presume to put my selfe forward vpon a dutifull desire to further so godly an enterprise

I am a seruant, and shall sometimes heare of thinges before my Maister, the which I speake, because I can presently 
                        〈◊〉
                      you of such a schoolemaister as you both do desire to finde.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  And who is that, gentle fellowe Fidus?
                  
               
               
                  Fidus.
                  Sir his name is Gnomaticus, he dwelleth in Saint Antlines, a man famous f
                        •…
                     r his learning, of woonderfull temperance, and highly estéemed for the diligence and carefull payne which he taketh with his Schoolers.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  Then can he not be long without entertainment, since now a dayes the good wyne néedeth none Iuye garland, and more parentes there are that lacke such Schoolemaisters for their children, then there are to be founde such Schoolemaysters which séeke and lacke entertainment.
               
               
                  Fidus.
                  Sir you haue reason, and therefore (if I were worthy to counsell you, I would entertain him with spéed, since he came but this other day from the Lord of Barlemontes house, whose children he hath in small time made excellent Schollers, and now hath dispatched them to the Uniuersitie of Doway.
                  
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  Doest thou know him Fidus? or canst thou tell where to finde him?
               
               
                  Fidus.
                  Yea Sir, and if it so please my Maister and you, I doubt not but to bring him hyther immediatly.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  Surely Phylopaes you shall doe well to send for him.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  There is no man more desirous then I, and since it so lyketh you I am redy to dispatch it, go thy waies Fidus, and tell Maister Gnomaticus, that my neighbour Phylocalus and I desire to speake with him, and make as much hast as thou canst.
               
               
                  Fidus.
                  It shalbe done Sir.
                  Fidus departeth.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  I am not the worst furnished of a seruaunt with this good fellow, for though his capacity be not great,

yet do I finde him trustie, and towardes my children he is both louing and carefull.
               
               
                  Philocalus.
                  Then haue you a iewell of him, for I hau
                        •…
                      one in whom I finde contrary conditions, I am seldome out of the dores but at my returne I finde him playing with my Sonnes at some vain pastimes.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  Beware of him then, for such a seruant were better payed double wages in your traffique abrode, then allowed barley breade in your shoppe at home, since nothing is more perillous to seduce children or young men, then the consorte and councell of a lewde seruannt. But is not this my Fidus which returneth so quickely? It is, and he bringeth with him a graue personage, I hope hée hath found Gnomaticus by the waye.
                  Fidus commeth in with Gnomaticus and his seruant.
               
            
            
               Actus primi,
               Scena secunda.
               FIDVS, PHYLOPAES, PHYLOCALVS, GNOMATICVS, and ONATICVS his Seruaunt.
               
                  Fidus.
                  SIr it is to be thought 
                        〈◊〉
                      Almighty God doth loue you, and meaneth to helpe your 
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        •…
                     sire in the good education of your children, for it 
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      chaunce to meete Maister Gnomaticus by the way, 
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        •…
                     as going towardes the Bowrce to harken of entertainement, and it is not like that he should haue returned from thence vnplaced, wherfore I would wish that you let not slippe this happie occasion.
                  They adresse their talke to the School
                        •…
                     ister.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  Sir we haue ben so bolde as to 
                        〈◊〉
                      this bearer for you, the cause hath procéeded of an 
                        〈◊〉
                      desire which this worthy man my neighbour and I haue to sée

our children placed with a vertuous enstructer, and hearing great fame aswell of your integritie, as also of the diligence you haue vsed with the Lord of Barlemontes Children, we are desirous to entreate you that you will take the like paines with ours, all which shalbe recompensed according to our own demaund: For as there is no iewell so deare vnto man, as the ofspring wherewith it pleaseth God to blesse him, so is there no money so well spent as that which is giuen to a good Schoolemaister.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  You shal vnderstand sir that my neighbour here and I haue foure Sonnes, of equall age and stature, the eldest excéedeth not twenty yeares, and the youngest is about ninetéene yeares olde, they haue ben already entred in grammer at such schooles as we haue héere in the City, and if, we be not abused by reportes they haue shew
                        •…
                      themselues forward enough to take enstructions: so that we are partely perswaded to send them vnto some vniuersity, and mine opinion is (as I lately declared vnto my neighbour here) that we should do very wel yet to retain them a while longer, vntill they may be perfectly en
                        •…
                     ructed by some godly teacher, the summe of their duty first towardes God, then to their Prince, next to their parents, and consequently aswell towardes the benefite of their countrey, as also how to behaue themselues to all magistrates, and officers in the same. In conclusion wherof they may also learne what they are of themselues, and how they may be most acceptable both to God and man, and for that we haue hard very good report of your skill and also of your 
                        〈◊〉
                     , we thought good to require that (if you be not otherwise already entertained) you would take some pa
                        •…
                     nes to 
                        •…
                     ructe them in these pointes, and the same shalbe 
                        〈◊〉
                      and deserued by measure of your owne contentation, as my neighbour Phylopaes hath before profered.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Worthy Gentlemen I yéelde you 
                        〈◊〉
                     
                     
humble thankes for your curteous profers, and I render in
                        •…
                     nite thankes vnto almighty God that my name hath ben so reported vnto you, truly I would be lothe to deserre any lesse, then the name of a faithful and diligent teacher, so farre forth as it hath pleased GOD to endue me with knowledge. Touching your proffer and request, I do most willingly embrace the same, confessing euen simply, that it was mine errand to séeke such entertainement, hauing of late dispatched out of my handes, the sonnes of the Lord of Barlemont towardes 
                        •…
                     he Uniuersiti
                        •…
                      
                     
                        •…
                     f Doway and if the touch of your zeale be not contrary to the fame which is s
                        •…
                     ed of your estates, I shall thinke my selfe wel occupied, in teaching or reading to the children of such worthy men as you are.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  Well then s
                        •…
                     r, we will be bold to send for the youngmen, to the end that no time be lost or deferred in bestowing of them. Fidus, go your waies to our houses, and bring hether our Sonnes.
               
               
                  Fidus.
                  Moste willingly sir I shal accomplish your commaundement.
               
               
                  Gnomati.
                  If it please you sir, my seruant shall asist him.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  It will not be amisse to acquaint hym wyth them.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Sirha, go with this gentlemans seruant, and helpe him to conduct their children hyther.
               
               
                  Onaticus.
                  Well Sir it shalbe done.
               
            
            
               Actus primi
               Scaena tertia.
               PHYLOPAES, PHYLOCALVS, GNOMATICVS, PHYLAVTVS, PHYLOMVSVS, PHYLOSARCVS, PHYLOTIMVS, FIDVS, and ONATICVS.
               
                  
                     Phylopaes.
                  IT shall nowe bée our partes to vnderstand what stipend may content you for your paines
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Sir in that respecte take you no care, but let me pray vnto almighty God, that he giue me grace so to enstruct your children, as you may hereafter take comfort in my trauayle, that done, I can no wayes doubt of your beneuolence, sithens your inward desire doth already manyfestly appeare: and furthermore, I would be lothe to make bargaines in this respect, as men do at the market or in other places, for grasing of Oxen or féeding of Cattle, especially since I haue to deale with such worthy personages as you séeme and are reported to be.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  Well, yet Sir we would be glad to recompence you according to your owne demaund, but in token of our ready will to please you, we shall desire you to take at my handes these twenty angels as an earnest or pledge of our further meaninge, &amp; as I am the first that presume to open my purse in this occasion, so I beseech the Father of Heauen that I may not be the last which may reioyce to sée his children prosper, thou knowest (O Lord) I meane not hereby my neighbours detriment, but alas, the shadow of a mans selfe is euer nearest to him, and as I desire to be the first that may heare of their well doinge, so yet if they hearken not diligently vnto your enstruction, but obstinately reiect your precepts, then I desire you, and on Gods behalfe I charge you, that I may yet be the first that shall thereof be aduertised: but behold where they come, these two (I thanke the Father of Heauen,) are the tokens of his mercifull blessing towardes me, the Eldest is named Phylosarchus, and this younger Phylotimus.
                  
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  And these too sir are mine onely children, and God for his mercy graunt that they may be mine onely comfort, the Eldest is called Phylautus, and the younger Phylomusus.
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
               
               
                  
                     Phyl
                        •…
                     utus.
                  Sir according to your commaundement expressed by Fidus I am come hither to know your pleasure, and haue by warrant of the same cōmission brought with me my Brother Phylomusus.
                  
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  And I in like maner Sir haue brought with me my Brother Phylotimus destring to knowe your pleasure, and being ready to obey your commaundement.
               
               
                  Gnomatic
                        •…
                     s.
                  Surely these young men giue none euill hope of their 
                        •…
                     wardnes, and declare by their séemely gesture and modest boldnesse to be both of good capacitie, and to haue bene well enstructed hyther 
                        〈◊〉
                      in humanity.
                  The Fathers adresse their talke to their children.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  The cause that we haue sent for you is to committe you vnto the gouernement of this godly man, whom we haue entreated to take paynes with you and to enstruct you in some principall poyntes of necessary doctrine, to the ende that after you haue ripely disgested the same, you may be the more able to go boldely into some Uniuersity, and I for my part do here commit you vnto him, charging you in Gods name (and by the authority which he hath giuen mée ouer you,) to hearken vnto him wyth all attentiuenosse, and to obey him with all humillity.
               
               
                  Phyl
                        •…
                     paes.
                  The same charge that my neighbour Phylocalus hath here giuen to his childrē, the same I do pronounce vnto you, and furthermore do charge you that you become gentle and curteouse to each other, humble to your betters, and affable to your inferiours in all respectes.
               
               
                  Phylautus.
                  Sir I trust we shall deserue your fatherly fauour.
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  And I trust to deserue the continuance of your goodnesse.
               
               
                  Phyl
                        •…
                     tus, &amp; Phylomusus.
                  We hope also to immitate the good in all moral examples of vertuous behauiour.
               
               
                  Ph
                        •…
                     lopaes.
                  The Father of Heauen blesse you with the blessing which it pleased him to pronounce vnto Abraham,
                     
                     Isaac, and Iacob.
                  
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  Amen, and now let vs depart, leauing here in your custody the choyce lambes of our flocke, defend them then (for Gods loue) from the rauening, and raging lus
                        •…
                     es of the flesh, and vanities of the world.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Sir by Gods power I shall do my best diligence.
               
               
                  Fidus.
                  My louely Gentlemen, GOD guide you by his grace, and though I be somwhat romoued from your dayly company, yet spare not to commaund my seruice, if at any time it may stand you in stéede to vse it.
               
               
                  Phylotus.
                  Gr
                        •…
                     mercy gentle Fidus.
                  
               
            
            
               Actus primi
               Scena quarta.
               GNOMATICVS, PHYLAVTVS, PHYLOSARCVS, PHYLOMVSVS, PHYLOTIMVS, and ONATICVS.
               
                  Gnomaticus
                  MY dearely beloued schollers, since it hath pleased your Parentes (as you haue heard) to put mée in trust with you for a time, it shall not be amisse before I enter further in enstruction, to knowe how farre you haue already procéeded in learning, that there vpon I may the better determine what trade or Methode shalbe most conuenient to vse in teaching of you: tell me therefore what you haue redde, and in what maner the same hath bene deliuered vnto you?
               
               
                  Phylautus.
                  Sir, my Brother here, and I haue bene taught first the rules of the grammer, after that wée had read vnto vs the familiar comunications called the Colloquia of Erasmus, and next to that the offices of Cicero, that was our last exercise.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  It hath bene well done, &amp; haue you not also

ben taught to ver
                        •…
                     y?
               
               
                  Phylautus
                  Yes truly sir, we haue therein bene (in maner) dayly enstructed.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  And you Phylosarchus how haue you passed your time?
               
               
                  Phylosarcus.
                  Sir: my Brother and I haue also bene taught our grammer and to make a verse, we haue redde certaine Comedies of Terence; certaine Epistles of Tully, and some parte of Uirgill, we were also entred into our greeke grammer,
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Surely it séemeth you haue not hytherto lost your time, and the order of your enstruction hath bene such, that you might presently be able to take further procéedinges in an Uniuersiry, so that it should be (vnto me) but labour lost to stand still vpon those pointes, since it seemeth that you haue bin therein perfectly grounded: neuerthelesse wée will continue the exercise of the same, and wée will therevnto ioyne such holesome preceptes, as may become a rule and Squire, wherby the rest of your lyfe and actions may be guyded. For alchough Tully in his booke of dewtyes doth teach sundry vertuouse preceptes, and out of Terence may also be gathered many morall enstructions amongst the rest of his wanton discourses, yet the true christian must direct his steppes by the infallible rule of Gods woord, from whence as from the hedde spring, he is to drawe the whole course of his lyfe. I would not haue you thinke hereby that I do holde in contempt the bookes which you haue redde heretofore but wée will (by Gods grace) take in assistance suc
                        •…
                     nt so many of them as may seeme consonant to the holy scriptures, and so ioyning the one with the other, we shalbe the better able to bring our worke vnto perfectiō. Sirha go you to my lodging, &amp; causeHe speaketh, to his seruāt (in the meane tyme) both bedding, and dyet to be prouided for these young men, that I may sée them vsed according to my charge in euery respect.
               
               
                  
                     Onaticus.
                  Well Sir it shalbe done with dilligence.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Now let vs in the holy name of God begin, and he for his mercy geue me grace to vtter, and you to disgest such holesome lessons as may be for the saluatiō of your soules, the comfort of your lyfe, and the prositte of your Countrey.
                  You shall well vnderstand my well beloued schollers, that as God is the author of all goodnesse, so is it requisite that in all traditions and Morall preceptes we begin firste to consider of him, to regard his maiestie, and search the soueraigne poyntes of his Godhead. The Heathen Philosophers (although they had not the light to vnderstand perfect trueth) were yet all of them astonyed at the incomprehensible maiesty and power of God, some of them thought the ayre to be God, some other the earth, some the infinitenesse of things, some one thing, some another, whose opinions I shall passe ouer as thinges vnméete to be much thought of, but by the way, the opinion of Plato is not vnworthy here to bee recited vnto you, who taught plainely that god was omnipotent, by whom the world was made, and al thinges therein created and brought vnto such perfection as they be in. Xenophon affirmed that the true God was inuisible, and that therefore we ought not enquire what or what maner of thing God is. Aristo the Stoicke, affirmed lykewyse that God was incomprehensible. To conclude, Simonides being demaunded what God was, required one dayes respect to answer, and then being again demaunded the same question, he required two dayes respet, at the third apointment of his answere, he came &amp; required thrée dayes, and being demaunded wherefore he did so breake his apointments, and require alwayes further time, he aunswered, that the more déepely that he did consider the matter, the more infinite he found it, and therefore remained alwaies astonyed what to answere, and always craued further time. Truly to leaue y• heathen opinion
                        •…
                     
                     
and to come vnto the very touchestone I thinke it not amisse if we content our selues to thinke that God is omni
                        •…
                     otent, and yet his power vnsearchable, and his goodnes vnspeakable. And to be briefe, I wil deliuer vnto you the summe of your dutyes in foure Chapters, the first chapiter shalbe of God and his ministers, the second of the King and his Officers, the third shall conteyne the duties that you owe vnto your Countrey and the Elders thereof, and lastly you shalbe put in remembraunce of your dutyes towardes your Parentes, and what you ought to be of your selues. In these soure chapters I trust (by Gods help) to enclud
                        •…
                      as much as shalbe necessary for the perfect gouernment of a true Christian.
               
               
                  Phylo
                        •…
                     us.
                  Sir wée beseech you that for as much as this order of teaching is both very compendious, &amp; also much different from the lectures which haue bene redde vnto vs, you will therefore vouchsafe to stand somwhat the more vppon euery point, to the end, that aswell your meaning may be perspicuous, as also that we may the better beare away the same, and not onely learne it without the booke, but also engraue it in our mindes.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Your request is reasonable, and it shalbe by mée as readyly graunted, as it hath bene by you necessarily required. Your first chapter and lesson shall then be, that in all your actions you haue an especiall eye and regard to almighty God, and in that consideration I commend vnto your memory, first God himselfe, and secondarily his ministers. As touching your duties vnto God him self, although they be infinite, yet shall we sufficiently conteine them in thrée especiall poynts to be perfourmed: that is to say, Feare, Loue, &amp; Trust. And first to begin with feare, it shalbe necessary and aboue all thinges your bounden duty, to 
                        •…
                     eare God and his omnipoten power. Linus that auncient Poet wryteth, that with God all thinges are easie to be accomplished, and nothing is vnpossible. Tully in

his Oration Pro Roscio amerino saith, that the commodityes which wée vse, the light which we enioy, and the breath which we haue and drawe, are giuen and bestowed vppon vs by God: then if with God all thinges be possible (according to Linus) he is to be feared, sithens the least part of his displeasure being prouoked, the greatest part of his will is to him right easie to accomplish: and if we haue our light, our lyfe, and all commodities of his gift (as Cicero affirmeth) then is hée to be feared, least with the facillity of his omnipotency he take away as fast as he gaue, or turne light into darknes, life into death, and cōmodities into discōmodities. I might recite you many heathen authorities, but it is most néedlesse, since y• very word of God himself, is most plaine in this behalfe, and yet I haue here set downe these fewe, because they are not repugnant to holy Scriptures. Wée finde written in the xx. chapter of Exodus, that God is a Ielous God, and doth visit the sinnes of the Fathers vppon the children vnto the third and fourth generation. Feare him then for he is most mightie. Againe: who shall defend me (saith the Psalmist) vntill thine anger be past? Feare God then, since against his power no defence preuayleth. Agai
                        •…
                     , both the heauens and the earth obay the voice of his mouth. Feare him then for althinges are subiect vnto his mighty power.
                  
                  And yet with this feare you must also ioyne loue, for it is not with God as it is with Princes of the worlde, which to make themselues feared do become Tyrantes, but theLoue God. goodnes of almighty God is such, that he desireth no lesse to be loued, then he deserueth to be feared, and though his might and power be vniuersall, and there withall his Ielousie great, and his displeasure soon prouoked, yet delighteth he not in the distruction of mankind, but rather that a sinner should turne from his wickednes and liue. Tully in his second booke de legibus saith, that God being Lord of al things doth deserue best of mākind, bicause he b
                        •…
                     holdeth

what euery man is, and with what deuotion he worshippeth the Gods, and kéepeth an accompt aswell of the good as the badde: whereby appeareth that the heathen confessed yet t
                        •…
                     at the Gods were to be loued, bycause they cared for mankind, and truly that opinion is neither cōtrary to Gods word, nor dissonant to naturall reason. For wée sée by common experience that we loue them best of whom we are most fauoured, &amp; haue receiued greatest benefits. I meane hereby those that rule their doinges by reason, for other
                        •…
                     se wée sée dayly wicked men, which (forgetting their duty) do least loue wher they haue most cause. When I my s
                        •…
                     lfe was a scholler in the Uniuersity, I remember that I did often tymes defend in Schooles this proposition. Ingratitudo (tam versus. 'Deos immortales quam apud homines) peccatum maximum. Ingratitude is the greatest faulte that may be either towards god or man. Let vs cōsider the good 
                        •…
                     ies of almighty God, who first created vs to his owne Image and similitude, indued vs with reason and knowledge, preserued vs from innumerable perilles, and prouided thinges necessary for our sustentation, and to consider more inwardly the exceeding loue which he bare towardes mankinde, he spared not his onely begotten Sonne, but gaue him (
                        •…
                     uen vnto the death of the crosse) for our redemption. Oh what minde were able to conceaue▪ or what to
                        •…
                     gue able to vtter the loue and goodnes of almighty God towardes mankinde? And since his loue towardes vs, hath bene and yet doth continue infinite, our loue should also be infinite, to r
                        •…
                     nder him thanks for his goodnes. But though the causes be infinite which might bind vs to loue GOD, yet is there no cause gr
                        •…
                     ater then the manifolde mercyes which he hath she 
                        〈◊〉
                      wayes to mankind. In the first age when iniquity kindled his wrath to destroy the whole world, he yet vouchsafed to preserue Noe and his family, Loue him then since he preserueth the good, though it be but for his mercyes sake▪ When the people of Israell prouoked

him at sundry times, he did yet at euery submission stay his hand from punishment, Loue God then since he is ready to forgiue, and though he pronounceth his Ielousie in the twentith of Exodus saying, that he visiteth the sinns of the Fathers vppon the children, vnto the third and fourth generation, yet ther withal he addeth, that he sheweth mercy vnto thousandes in them that loue him and kéepe his commaundementes. Loue him then since his mercy is ouer all his works. To conclude, when his vnsearchable Maiestie by his diuine foresight did perceyue, that by the very sentence of the Lawe we stoode all in state of condemnation, he sent down his owne and only Sonne, to be slaundered, buffeted, and cruci
                        •…
                     d for our sinnes, to the ende that all which beléeue in him, should not perish but haue lfie euerlasting. Loue God then since mercy is aboundant with him, and he shall redéeme Israell from all his iniquities.
                  And héere vnto this feare and loue you must ioyne a sureTrust in God. trust and confidence. The promises of mortall men are often times vncertaine, and d
                        •…
                      fayle, but the promises of the Almighty are vnfallible. For the wordes of his mouth returne not voyd and without effect. Tully in his offices doth vse great arte in declaration what sortes of promises are to be obserued, and which may be broken. But the diuine prouidence and foresight doth promise nothing but that whichGen. 17 he will most assuredly performe. When he promised vnto Abraham that S
                           •…
                        ra his wyfe should beare him a childe, Sara laughed bycause she was then foure score &amp; ten yeres o
                        •…
                     e, but the almighty remembred his couenant. Trust in him then for his woords shall neuer fayle. When he promised Moyses to conduct his people through the desertes, they began to doubt and murmure, saying: would God that weNum. 14. had dyed in the land of Aegypt or in this wildernesse &amp;c. and the lord was angry, but yet remembring his promise, at the humble petition of Moyses he perfourmed it. Trust in God therefore, since no displeasure can make him alter

his determination, he perfourmed his holy promyse in Ismaell,
                     Gen. 31. although we read not that he praied vnto God therefore. I would not haue you think hereby that I condemne or contemne prayer, since it is the very meane to talke with God, but I meane thereby to proue, that God is most iust and faithfull in all his promises, and by repeticion I say, Feare God for he is mighty, loue God for he is mercifull, and trust in God for he is faithfull &amp; iust. Herewith all you must also learne to performe duty towardes the seruaunts andMinisters ministers of God. For as you shall onely be saued by hym, and by cleauing to him in all your actions, so yet are hys ministers the meane &amp; instruments of your saluation, and d
                        •…
                      (as it were) leade you by the hand through the waues of this world vn to 
                        •…
                     ernall 
                        •…
                     elicity, vnto whom you shall owe 
                        •…
                     hree seueral duties, that is to say, Audience, Reuerence, and Loue. The Children of Israell by harkening to Moyses, and Aaron, were not only enstructed and taught their dutyes, but were (as it were) made at one with God when they had at any time purchased his heauy displeasure. ByActes. 8. harkning vnto Phyllip the Apostle, the Enuch was conuerted. By harkning vnto Peter, Cornelius y• captain was confirmed &amp; strengthned in the faith. By harkning vnto Paule and Sylas, Lidia, and the gaylour of Phylippos were baptised,Actes. 16. the holy scriptures are full of examples to proue this proposition. Harken you therfore vnto the ministers of God, forHarken to Gods Minist
                           •…
                        rs they are sent to enstruct you, so shall it also become you to do thē reuerence in al places, re mēbring that as he which sent them is in all thinges to be honoured, so are they to be had in reuerence for their office sake. Such was the zeale of Co
                           •…
                        elius the Captaine, that he fell downe prostrate atActes. 10. 
                     Peters féete when he entered into his house, the which though Peter refused saying that he was also mortall, yet did it signifie vnto vs, that the ministers of God cannot bée too much reuerenced. The Priestes in the olde Testament were exempt from tributes and impositions, they were

not constrained to go into the battaile, they were prouided for sustenance and all thinges conuenient, and the peopleReuerēce gods ministers. were commaunded to do them reuerence. Do you likewise reuerence vnto Gods ministers in al places, for it shal become you well. So shall you also loue them bycause they preach the gospel of him which hath power to saue you. If the sensual apetite of man be such as engēdreth affection towards thehandmaide bicause she is of familiar cōuersation wt the Mistris: or bréedeth loue towards them which are in office with Princes, bycause they may also procure vs fauour: how much more ought the mindes of men to be kindled with loue towardes the ministers of God, which enstructs vs diligently, minister vnto vs painfully, and pray for vs faithfully? yea how much are we boūd to loue them, whichLoue the ministers by their hol some preceptes do make vs worthy (through Gods mercy) of his holy loue and fauour. To conclude this chapter, you shall feare God for his might, loue him for his mercyes, and trust in him for he is faithfull. You shall also harken vnto his ministers bycause they are sent of God, you shall do them reuerence because it becometh you, and for their office sake, and you shal loue them by cause they feede you with the breade of lyfe. And this I thinke sufficient for explanation of this first chapter at this time.
               
               
                  Onaticus.
                  Sir I haue done as you commaunded, and there is meate redy for your dinner, if it please you that it be sette on the table.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Well we wil then defer the rest of our labour vntill dinner be past, go we togither, for I thinke it tyme.
               
               
                  Phylosarcus.
                  We followe when it pleaseth you.
                  They depart.
               
            
            
               Actus primi
               Scoena quinta.
               
               LAMIA, ECCHO, PANDARINA, and DICK DROOM.
               
                  Lamia.
                  COme on my good friendes, for were not your frendly help, I could rather content my self to be buryed in my flowing yeares, then to liue in such a miserable and precise world as this is, Oh what Superfinesse are we now grown vnto? a gentlewoman may not now adaies séeme to speak to her frende at the dore passing by, she may not looke at him in the window, she may not kisse him if she méete him as a straunger, nor receyue his letters or presentes, but euery pratling minister will record it in the pulpit.
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  In déed faire Lady Lamia, they are both too curious and too much suspicious, for if they do but sée two in bedde togyther, they will say that it was for to committe some wickednesse, fye fye vpon such tongues.
               
               
                  Lamia.
                  Ha ha, by my troth Eccho wel said, but by your leaue, let master minister tattle what he will, for I will take my frendes present when it commeth, and shall I tell you? if I could haue bene contented to be so shutte vp from 
                        •…
                     ight and spéech of such as like me, I might haue liued gallantly and well prouided with my mother, who (though I say it) is a good old Lady in Ualentia, but when I sawe that I must weare my good apparell alwayes within doores, and that I must passe ouer my meales without company, I trussed vp my Jewelles in a casket, and (being accompanyed with my good Aunte here) I bad Ualentia 
                     
                        •…
                     arewell, for I had rather make hard shifte to liue at lyberty, then e
                        •…
                     ioy grea
                        •…
                      riches in such a kind of emprisonment.
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  A good Aunt in déede, I would I had such an Uncle.
               
               
                  Pand
                        •…
                     ina.
                  Content your selfe niece, it were now but folly to spend time in bootelesse complaints, nor to lament the thing which may not be remedied, you must rather

learne the way that may maintaine your estate, 
                        •…
                     or beauty will not alwayes last, and if you prouide not in youth, you may be assured to begge in age, take example at me, I tell you I thought my halfepeny good siluer within these few yeares past, and now no man estéemeth me vnlesse it be for counsell.
               
               
                  Dicke.
                  Counsell quoth you? mary sir and good counsell is much worth now adayes.
               
               
                  Lamia.
                  I pray you Aunt since you are so good a councellour, giue me some aduise how to behaue my selfe.
               
               
                  Pandarina.
                  As for that another time shall serue betwéen you and mée.
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  Why, and shall I be cast vp for a hobler then? I am sure I was neuer yet vntrusty to any of you both.
               
               
                  Dicke.
                  Well Ladyes, and if you looke well vppon the matter, I think that I am as worthy as one to be of counsell, well I wot if any gentleman offer you the least parte of iniury, then Dicke must be sent for to sweare out the matter, Dicke must byde all brontes, and therfore it were not amisse that he were of counsel in all your conferences.
               
               
                  Lamia.
                  By myne honesty Aunt to confesse a troth, both these are our very approued fréendes, &amp; therfore you may be bolde to speake your minde before them.
               
               
                  Pandarina.
                  Well content then, I will tell you mine opinion, you take not the way to liue, you are too much subiect to your passion, for if you chance to be acquainted with a gentleman that is in déed courtlike and of good desertes, you become straight way more destrous of him, then he is of you, and so 
                        •…
                     arre you dote vpon him, that you do not only sequester your selfe from all other company, but also you become so franke harted, that you suffer him not to bestow vpon you any more then is necessary for present vse, yea 
                        〈◊〉
                     , I pray you learne these thrée pointes of me to gouerne your steppes by. First Trust noman how faire so euer he speake, next 
                        
                           〈◊〉
                         no 
                           •…
                        an (that hath ought) how euil

fauored so euer he be. And lastely Loue no man longer then he geueth, since lyberall gyfts are the glewe of euerduring loue.
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  O noble Dame, why were not you mother of the maydes vnto the Quéen
                        •…
                      of Hungary? by the fayth of a true B
                           •…
                        gondyan you had wrong, for you well descrued the place.
               
               
                  Dyck.
                  I warrant you if the King our master had store of daughters, such a matrone could not liue vnknowen, but was it not therfore (thinke you) that ambassadours were sent this other day to the old Duchesse?
               
               
                  Lami
                        •…
                     
                  
                  Well Aunt, I were worthy of great reprehension, if I w
                        •…
                     uld reiect the good documents of such a frende, and if I haue heretofore done contrary, impute it to my youth, but be you sure that hereafter I will endeuour my selfe to follow your precepts.
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  And I fayre Lady will stande you in some stead, to driue byrdes to the Net. If I be not much deceyued, I saw a frosty bearded scholemaster iustructing of four lusty young men erewhyle as we came in, but if my iudgement do not fayle me, I may chaunce to read some of them another lecture.
               
               
                  Dyck.
                  Lush, what needeth such open talke here in the streate? let vs go to the Lady Pandarinaes house, and there we may deuise at better commodity vpon these causes.
               
               
                  Lamia.
                  He speaketh reason, let vs go Aunt, for it is not meele that euery dancer heare our musike before the maskers be ready.
               
               
                  Pandarina.
                  Well, I sayde so at the first, but when you wyll, let vs departe.
                  They depart to their howses.
               
            
            
               The first Chorus.
               
                  WHen God ordeynd the restlesse life of man,
                  And made him thrall to sundry greenous cares:
                  
                     The first borne griefe or Sorow that began,
                  To shew it self, was this: to saue from snares
                  The pleasant pledge, which God for vs prepares.
                  I meane the séede, and ofspring that he giues,
                  To any wight which in this world here lyues.
               
               
                  Few see themselues, but each man séeth his chylde,
                  Such care for them, as care not for themselfe,
                  We care for them, in youth when witte is wilde,
                  We care for them, in age to gather pelf:
                  We care for them, to kéepe them from the shelf
                  Of such quicke sands, as we our selues first founde,
                  When headdy will, dyd sett our shippes on grounde.
               
               
                  The care which Christ dyd take to saue his sheepe,
                  Hath bene compard, to fathers care on child,
                  And as the hen, her harmles chicks can keepe
                  From cruell kyte: so must the father shylde
                  His youthfull Sonnes, that they be not beguylde.
                  By wicked world, by fleshly foule desire,
                  Which serue the deuill, with Fewell for his fire.
               
               
                  Fyrst parentes care, to bring their children forth,
                  To breede them then, to bring them vp in youth,
                  To match them eke, with wightes of greatest worth,
                  To see them taught, the trusty tracks of trueth:
                  To barre excesse, from whence all s
                        •…
                      ensueth.
                  And yet to geue, enough for common néede,
                  Least lothsome lacke make vise for vertue breede.
               
               
                  Let shame of sinne, thy Childrens bridle be,
                  And spurre them foorth, with bounty wysely vsed:
                  That difference, each man may plainly see,
                  Twéene parentes care, and maisters bodes abused:
                  So Terence taught, whose lore is not refused.
                  
                     But yet where youth is prone to follow ill,
                  There spare the spurre, and vse the brydell still.
               
               
                  Thus infinite, the cares of Parentes are.
                  Some care to saue their children from myshappe,
                  Some care for welth, and some for honours care,
                  Whereby their Sonnes may sitte in fortunes lappe:
                  Yet they which cram them so with worldly pappe,
                  And neuer care, to geue them heauenly crommes,
                  Shall sce them sterue, when happe of hunger comes.
               
               
                  Said Socrates: that man which careth more
                  To leaue his chyld, much good and rych of rent:
                  Then he for seeth, to furnish him with store
                  Of vertues welth, which neuer can be spent:
                  Shall make him lyke, the steed that styll is pent
                  In stable close: which may be fayre in sight.
                  But seldome serues, such horse in field to fight.
               
               
                  So Xenophon, his friend Dan Tully told,
                  And so do here, Phylopaes and his pheare
                  
                     Phylocalus, that selfe same lesson hold:
                  They rather loue to leaue their sonnes in feare
                  Of God aboue: then wealth to wallow heare.
                  Which godly care, (O God) so deigne to blisse,
                  That men may sée how great thy glory is.
               
            
            Finis, Actus primus.
         
         
            Actus Secundi▪
            
            
               Scoena prima.
               GNOMATICVS, PHYLAVTVS, PHYLOMVSVS, PHYLOSARCVS, and PHYLOTIMVS.
               
                  
                     Gnomaticus.
                  
                     MY well beloued, as tyme is the greatest treasure which man may here on earth receiue, so let vs not le
                        •…
                     se time, but rather séeke so to bestowe the same, that profitte may thereof be gathered. I will nowe return to enstruct you what dutyes you owe vnto the King, whose place is next vnto Gods place in consideration of your duty. And as I haue taught you thrée principall poyntes in seruice of God almighty, so will I also conuey into thrée pointes, as much as shalbe necessary for this tradition: for I feare least I haue bene ouer longe in my first deuision, but I was drawne thervnto by the request which you made of your selues, and therefore beare with me.
               
               
                  Phylotus.
                  Sir our desire is such, to beare away perfectly your enstruction, that your prolixity séemeth vnto vs very compendious.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Well then to return vnto the matter, you shall performe vnto the King thrée especial dutyes, that is to say: Honour, Obediencae, and Loue. Hypodamus in his booke of a common welth, saith that a kingdome is a thing compared to the imitation of gods power. Diotogenes the scholler of Pytagoras in his booke of gouernment, saith that a king representeth the figure of God amongst men. Lykewise he sayth, that as god excelleth the most perfect things of nature, so the king excelleth amongst men and worldly matters: so that he is to bee honored as the lieutenant of God here vpon earth, both because he hath power of commaundement, and chiefly because he representeth that heauenly King, who is king of kinges, and aboue all Kynges to be honoured: Euen so is hee also to bee obayed in all seculer constitutions and pollitike prouisions. This obedience doth consequently follow hono
                        •…
                     re, as the shadow solowes

the body, for whatsoeuer he be that gyueth vnto his king that honor which to him apperteineth, will (no doubt) lykewise obay him with all humilitie. Erasmus teacheth in his Apothegmes, that obediēce expelleth al seditiō &amp; maynteyneth concorde: the which may also appeare by naturall reason and common experience, neyther shall they euer become able to beare rule them selues, whiche cannot bee content to obay the aucthoritie of others. Wherfore it shal be most conuenient that you obay the King, synce his aucthoritie is frō god, &amp; as this obedience dependeth vpon the honour wherewith ye shall reuerence the King as Gods lieutenant, so must you also ioyne therunto an vnfayned loue, for as almightye God is to be loued because hee is mercifull: so the King beeing apoynted by God muste be loued bycause he is thy pretector heere on earth. Salamon sayth, that the kings indignation is the messenger of death, whereby I would frame myne argument from the contrarye, that hee is to be loued, least his indignation being iustly kindled, thou bee not able to beare it. Next vnto the king we are to consider the Magistrates which are appoynted for administration of iustice, and pollityke gouerment: these Magistrates must also bee honoured, obeyed, &amp; loued: honored because they are y• substituts of y• king vnto whom all honour (on earth) apperteyneth, obeyed because theyr office is appointed by the Kings aucthoritie, and loued because they are the graue and expert personages, which deuise lawes and constitutions for continuaunce of peace and tranquillitie. The apostle Paule in his xiii. chapter of his Epistle to the Romaines, teacheth playnely, that Rulers beare not the sworde in vaine, saying: Let euerie soule be subiect vnto the higher powers, for there is no power but of God. Againe, the ruler (sayth he) doth not beare the sworde in vayne. Wherefore you must néedes be subiect, not onelye for feare, but also for conscience▪ And Sanct Peter in hys fyrst Epistle and the seconde chapiter, doth sufficientli
                        •…
                     
                     
teach vs this point, saying▪ 
                     Submit your selfe vnto all manner ordinaunce of man for the Lordes sake, whether it bee vnto the king as hauing the preheminence, or vnto the rulers as vnto them that are sent of him for the punishment of euill dooers, but for the laude of them that do well. Whereby appeareth, that the magistrates are not onely to be feared, because they punysh offenders, but also to be loued because they cherish the verteous: and for conclusion of this poynt, if you desire to be good men, then learne to performe duety towardes all magistrates. As Sophocles, well sayde, it becommeth a good man to haue due respect vnto all magistrates. I might nowe take your Parentes in hande, for the next pointe of your enstruction but I will first touch the duety which you owe vnto your countrye, and that is conteyned also in three especial pointes: that is to saye, in Thankefulnesse, Defence, and Proffit. And as ingratitude is the most heinous offence against God, so haue I taught you that it is the greatest faulte in humayne actions, amongst the which it sheweth it selfe no way more vntollerable, then if you shoulde happen to bee vnthankefull vnto your country. Tully in his offices sayth, that wee are not borne onely for our owne perticuler cause or profit, but parte (sayth he) our cuntrey challengeth, parte our Parentes think due vnto them, and our friendes ought lykewise to enioye some parte of our trauailes. There are dyuers Philosophers, whiche maynteyne in argument that all cuntryes are frée for a noble mynde, and I agrée thereunto, but yet thereby they conclude not, that a noble minde by chusing a new cuntrey to enhabit, maye lawfully forgett the cuntrey wherein hee was natiue. Zopirus is condempned in all histories, for the vnthankefulnes he vsed in betraying his cuntrey. The truth of the Troyan historie accuseth Aeneas, Antenor, &amp; certeyne others, as most vnthankefull traytors to theyr cuntrey. Cillicon for betraying of Miletus, Lasthenes for deliuering of Oli
                           •…
                        thus, Nilo for selling of Epirus, and Apollonius
                     
for neglecting of his charge in Samos, are generally noted with the names of vnthankeful and vntrustie traytors to theyr cuntreyes: so that you must alwayes remember to become thankefull to your cuntrey, and myndefull to maynteyne the honor of the same, least neglecting your dueties in that behalfe, you deserue the oprobrious names of traytors, which are odius to God and man. You muste also spare no peril or trauaile to defende the same, for your countrey challengeth not onely that you be thankfull vnto the soyle which hath bredde you, but furder also, that you defende the state, wherein you haue béene nourished. Tully, in his Tusculanes questions recyteth one Lascaena, who when he receiued tydings of his sounes death, whom he had sent into the warres in defence of hys countrey, answered: therefore did I beget him (quoth hee) that hée might be such an one, as woulde not doubt to dye for hys countrey. In his booke entytuled the dreame of Sipio, he affirmeth that there is a certaine place appointed and ordeined in heaueu, for all such as defende their countrey. Euripides warneth that we shoulde neuer bee wearye in those trauailes, which tende to the restitution or defence of our countrey. Platoes opinion was, that wee are more bound to defend our countrey, then our own Parents▪ Like argumentes haue béene defended by many Phylo
                        •…
                     ophers, saying, that although thy Parentes and proper family b
                        •…
                      ouerthrowne, yet (the common welth of thy cuntrey standing) thou mayst florishe and ryfe againe: but the state of thy countrey being ouerthrowne, both thou and thy Parentes must lykewise come to vtter subuertion. Then as thou shalt fynde it thy bounden duety to honor thy country with all gratitude, and to defende it with all thy power, 
                        •…
                     o must thou likewise endeuor thy selfe to be profitable to the same: whereof many notable examples might be rehersed. Lycurgus,, when he had by extréeme dilligence aud trauayle

reduced the Spartanes vnto cyuillytie, by sundrie holsome lawes and pollityke constitutions, and that they began to murmure, saying: that his lawes were vntollerable, hée feyned that he woulde go to Delphos, to consulte with the God Apollo, whether his lawes were to be obserued or not promising to abide his sentence, &amp; requiring no more of the Lacedemonianes, but to sweare y• they would obserue those lawes vntill his retourne: which when they had solemly sworne, tooke his iurney without entente to returne home againe, and ordeyned before his death, to be enclosed in a great chee
                        •…
                      of Lead, and so to be throwen into the sea, to the ende that hée neuer retourning, the Laucedemonians might be bound by theyr othe to continue the exercise of his profitable lawes, suche care he had to become profitable vnto his countrey. Curtius the Romayne, when there apeared a greate gulfe in the market place, whiche could by no meanes be stopped, and answere was géeuen from the Oracle, that it was onely to bee stopped by that which was of moste worth vnto the citye of Roome, he déeming that the cittie had nothing so precious, as stoute &amp; valyant men, armed him selfe, and leapte into the Gulfe, which stopped immediatly: declaring thereby, howe lyght men ought to estéeme theire life, when as the same maye yelde profitte or commoditie to theyr countrey. Menecius, the Sonne of Craeon, refused not voluntary death, when he vnderstoode that the same might redéeme the citye of Thebes from vtter subuersion. I might trouble you with infinite stories to proue this proposition, but let these few suffice, and in your countrie haue allways especiall respecte to the elders, to whom you must also performe thrée seuerall deuties: that is, Reverence, Loue, and Defence. Lycurgus, ordeyned, that no young man should passe by an elder without reuerence fyrste doone vnto him, namelie if he were set, he rose to do reuerence vnto the elders, and if they were alone, he was bound to proffer them the comfort

of his company. Plato, in his nynth dyalogue of lawes and constitucions doth thus propound: al men must grant (sayth he) that age is much to be preferred before youth, aswell in the sight of God, as also in the sight of men, which will lyue orderly: for it is abhominable (sayth he) that an olde man shoulde geue place vnto an young man, and the Gods them selues do hate it, since youth ought with paciente mynde to beare euen the strypes of their elders. You shal also loue them, because of them you may learne good preceptes, and of them you may be bolde to aske councell: for as Euripides, in his tragedy called Phaenissae, doth teache, prudence will not be gotten with fewe dayes seeking for, and the apostles teach vs our deuty dyrectly in that behalf, who ordeyned amongst them elders in euery congregation, to decyde all matters in controuersie, of whome they were resolued of all doubtes in conscience. It shal also becom you to defend the elders from al vyolence and outrage, since it is a thing as comly and comendable to defende the weake, as it is glorious and tryumphant to ouercome the mightie: whereof I myght recite many famous examples out of the Romain histories, but I will partlie include the same in the dueties which you owe vnto your Parentes, which are also, Honor, Loue, and Reliefe. And of the first parte, although I might bring in sundry worthy examples, yet because the case is of it self familiar, I wil be briefe, and vse no other persuation then the expresse commaundement of God, who biddeth you to honor your Father and Mother, that your▪ dayes maye bée long in the land which the Lord your god hath giuen you. And Sain
                        •…
                     t Paule in the sixt chapiter of his Epistle to the Ephesians, sayth. Chyldren obay your Parents in the Lord, for that is right and wellpleasing to the Lorde. As he testifieth in the thirde chapiter to the Colossianes, you shall loue them also because you are engendred of their owne fleshe &amp; bloud, as also you may not forget your Mothers paines

in bearing of you, you muste alwaies meditate in your minde, fyrst the cares which they haue had to preserue you from bodily perils in the cradell, from daunger of dampnation by Godly education, from néede and hunger by administring things necessarie, and from vtter destruction by vigillant foresight &amp; Godly care: all these with infinit other things considered, you shall finde your selues bounden by manyfolde occasions to loue your Parentes, and to be assistant vnto them in the necessities of their age. For well sayd that Poet, which affirmed that children were tenderly swadled in their cradels, to the ende they mighte susteyne their aged Parentes and supplie their wantes. Meruelous is the nature of the Storke, which féedeth the damme in age, of whom it selfe receiued nouriture béeing young in the neast. Tully in his booke of the answers of sothsayers sayth, that nature in the beginning hath made an accord betwéene vs and our Parents, so that it were damnable not to cherish them. And to conclude, ther is nothing that can worse become a comon welth, then to sée y• youth florish in prosperity which suffer their parents to perish for lack of any cōmodity. Now that I haue rehearsed vnto you asmuche as I thinke requisit, for the enstruction of your dueties, fyrst towardes god, and his ministers, next to the Kyng and his Magistrates, thirdely to your countrey and the Elders thereof and lastly towardes your Parentes: it shall not be amisse that you remenber of your selfe how you are the Temple of God, kéepe your selues holy therefore in your conuersation, and vndefiled, for if our sauiour Christ did rigorously rebuke and expell the buyers &amp; sellers out of the outward Temple, how muche more will hée punishe them which pollute and de
                        •…
                     le the inwarde Temple of their bodies, and geue ouer their delight to concupiscence and van
                        •…
                     es? thus may you for breuitie remember that you.
                  
                     
                     1 Feare God because he is mig
                              •…
                           le,
                        God.
                     
                     2 Loue God because he is mercifull,
                     
                     3 Trust in God because he is iust.
                     
                  
                  
                     1 Heare his ministers hecause they are sent to enstrust you,
                     
                     2 Do reuerence vnto them because of their office,
                     
                     3 Loue them because they feede you with heuenly bread▪
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     1 Honor the King because he is Gods lieutenant▪
                        
                        King.
                     
                     2 Obay him because his power is from aboue,
                     
                     3 Loue him because he is thy protector.
                     
                  
                  
                     1 Honor hys Magistrates because they represent his person,
                     
                     2 Obay them because they haue their aucthoritie from him,
                     
                     3 Loue them because they 
                              •…
                           inteine peace.
                     
                  
                  
                     1 Be thankefull to thy countrey that hath bredde thee▪
                        
                     
                     2 Defende it because thou art borne to that ende, and
                     
                     3 Profytte it because thou shalt thereby gayne honour.
                     
                  
                  
                     1 Reuerence thy elders for their grey heares,
                     
                     2 Loue them because they councell thee and
                        Country.
                     
                     3 Defend them because they are feeble.
                     
                  
                  
                     1 Honor your Parentes beca
                              •…
                           se God commandeth so▪
                        
                     
                     2 Loue them bycanse they tendred you, and
                     
                     3 Releeue them because it is your duety.
                     
                  
                  Lastly forget not your selues▪ neyther make any le
                        •…
                      account of your selues then to be the Temple of God, whiche you ought to keepe holy and vndefiled. I myghte stand in dilatacion hereof with many moe examples and aucthorities, but I trust these (being well remembred) shall suffyce, and now I will leaue you for a time, beséeching allmyghty God to guyde and kéepe you now &amp; euer. So be it.
                  Gnomaticus goeth out
               
            
            
               
               Actus secundi,
               Scaena secunda.
               PHYLAVTVS, PHYLOMVSVS, PHYLOSARCVS, PHYLOTIMVS, and ONATICVS.
               
                  Phyl
                        •…
                     .
                  AH sirha, I sée wel the olde prouerbe is true, which saith: so many men so many mindes, this order of teaching is farre contrary to all other y• euer I haue heard, &amp; shal I tell you? it hath in it neither head nor foote.
               
               
                  Phyl
                        •…
                     .
                  Truly brother it hath in it great reason &amp; vertue, and though it be at y• first vnpleasant in comparison to T
                           •…
                        es Commedies and 
                        〈◊〉
                      like, yet ought we to h
                        •…
                     e good regarde therunto, since it teacheth in effect 
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      of our 
                        〈◊〉
                     .
               
               
                  Phylotimus.
                  Yea, and that very compendiously.
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  Surely I am of 
                        
                           •…
                        ylautus opinion, for who is ignorant that▪ God is to be feared aboue all things▪ or who knoweth not that the Kinge is 
                        〈◊〉
                      of God to rule here on earth▪
                  
               
               
                  Phylautus.
                  Is there any 
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      of 
                        〈◊〉
                     , that he knoweth not that in all 
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      must or will) be reuerenced? and sée we not daily, that all parents challenge obedience and loue?
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  Yes, and more to, for some parentes 
                        〈◊〉
                      neuer 
                        •…
                     ented what dutie soeuer the childe performeth, they 
                        •…
                     et what they once were themselues: But to the purpose. I l
                        •…
                     ked for some excellent matter at this newe Schoolemasters handes, if this be all that he can say to vs, I would for my part that we were in some Uniuersitie, for here we shall but loose our time, I haue (in e
                        •…
                     ect) all th
                        •…
                      geare without booke already.
               
               
                  
                     Phylautus.
                  And I lacke not much of it.
                  Onaticus commeth in.
               
               
                  Onaticus.
                  Well sayd young gentlemen, it is a good hearing when young men are so toward, and much ease is it for the teacher when he findeth scollers of quicke capacity.
               
               
                  Philotimus.
                  Surely I am not yet so forwarde, neither can I vaunt that eyther I haue it without booke, or do 
                        •…
                     usficiently beare away the same in such order as I woulde.
               
               
                  Phylomusus.
                  For my parte, I beséech God that I may with all my whole vnderstanding bee able to beare away that which our Master hath deliuered vnto vs, and that I may so emprinte the same in my memorie, that in all my lyfe I maye make it a glasse wherein I may beholde my duetie▪: wherefore Phylotimus, (if you so thinke good, you and I will go aparte, and medytate the same to our selues, to the end we ma
                        •…
                      be the perfecter therein when our enstructor shall examine vs.
               
               
                  Phylotimus.
                  Contented, let vs go where you will.
                  They go apart.
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  Let them go like a couple of blockheads, I would we two were at some Uniuersitie, and then let them do what they list.
               
               
                  Phylautus.
                  Euen so would I, for at the Uniuersitie we should hear
                        •…
                      other ma
                        •…
                     er of teaching: There be lectures daily read of all the liberall sciences, of all languages, and of all morall discourses. Furthermore, at the Uniuersitie we should haue choyse company of gallant young gentlemen, with whom we might acquaint our selues, and passe some times in recreation: yea, shall I tell you? if a man list to play the good fellow and▪ be mery sometymes, hée shall not want there (as I haue heard) that wyll accompanie him.
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  And what Uniuersitie (do you suppose) we shall be sent vnto.
               
               
                  Phyl
                        •…
                     tus.
                  I thinke vnto Doway, for that is néerest.
               
               
                  
                     Phylosarchus.
                  Haue you béene in Doway at any time?
               
               
                  Phylautus.
                  No surely, but I haue harde it praysed for a pr
                        •…
                     per citie, and wel replenished with curteous people and fayre women.
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  Marr
                        •…
                      Sir ther would I be then. Oh what a pleasure it is to behold a fayre woman? surelie they were created of God for the comfort of man, but beholde, I sée a passing fayre woman come downe the stréete, and if I be not much deceiued, Eccho is her gentleman vsher: it is so in déede.
               
               
                  Phylautus.
                  What is that Eccho?
                  
               
               
                  Philosarchus.
                  Know you not Eccho? why thē you know no man, the best fellow in all this towne, and readie to do for all men: I will bring you acquaynted with him.
               
            
            
               Actus secundi
               Scaena tertia.
               PHYLAVTVS, PHYLOSARCHVS, ECCHO, LAMIA, DICK DROM, and PANDARINA.
               
                  Eccho.
                  YOu shall sée (Lady Lamia,) how I will worke this geare lyke wax, but is not this Phylosarchus? it is euen hée, in good time I haue espied him, kéepe your coūtenance in any wise.
               
               
                  Pandarina.
                  
                     Eccho doth geue you good councell, kéepe your co
                        •…
                     ntenance.
               
               
                  Lamia.
                  As though I were to learne that at these yeares.
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  Master Phylosarchus, God saue you.
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  And thée also gentle felow Eccho. whether walkest thou?
               
               
                  
                     Eccho.
                  Hereby Sir with this gentlewoman.
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  Abide I pray thée, here is a young gentleman a friend of myne, which desireth to bée acquaynted with thée.
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  Sir I am at your comm
                        •…
                     dement and his also, I will be so bold as to kisse his hands, Dyck go thou on with these gentlewomen before, I will ouertake you immediatly.
                  The Ladies passe by, with a reuerence to the gentlemen.
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  And I pray thée tell mée Eccho, what gentlewoman is this?
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  Sir she is of Valentia, and hath presently some businesse in this citie with her Aunt which accompanieth her.
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  Ha, ha, businesse in déede, tell mée Eccho, here are none but God &amp; good friendes, is shée of the right stampe?
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  Sir, beléeue mée I know no such thing by her, I haue not béene long acquaynted with her, and (to tell you what likely hoodes I haue hitherto séene) shée is very demure and modest, neyther is there any company resorteth to her lodging, but what for that? all thinges haue a beginning, shée is a woman, and nothing is vnpossible.
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  Trust mée truely she is a gallant wench, &amp; but yong, that Fryer which would not cast off his cowle to catch such a sowle, shal neuer be my cōfessor, but I pray thee deale playnly with me: might not a man entreat master Eccho to carry her a present if néede were?
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  Sir there is neuer a gentleman in this citie, shall make Eccho stretch a stringe sooner then your selfe, but of a very truth, hetherto I haue séene no such likelyhood, but Sir, you are a gallant yong man, me thinkes you myght 
                        •…
                     o well to walke somtimes by her lodging, and geue her the Albade, or the Bezo las manos, and by that meane you may acquaint your selfe with her: afterwardes if any

thing may be furthered by Eccho, commaund him.
               
               
                  Philosarchus.
                  Gramercie gentle Eccho, but where aboutes is she lodged?
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  Not farre from S. Myghels Sir, at a red houseI will take leaue of you for this time, least she thinke me verie slacke in attendance.
               
               
                  Philosarchus.
                  Fare well friend Eccho. Did I not tell you what he was? there is not such a felow in a world againe, surely it shall go hard but I will haue a sling at this damsell: but let vs goe in, for our companions are departed long sithens, and we shal perchance giue some cause of suspecte, if we tarie long here▪
                  
               
               
                  Philautus.
                  Go we.
               
            
            
               Actus secundi
               Scaena quarta.
               GNOMATICVS, ONATICVS, ECCHO.
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  SUrely these yong men are not hitherto to be mislyked, and I trust in God they will proue toward scholers.
               
               
                  Onaticus.
                  Yea syr out of dout, &amp; especially the two elder, but the other two are nothing so quicke sprited, I came by them earewhile, soone after ye had done reading vnto thē, and the two. eldest could euen then (in maner) record without booke as much as you had taught them.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Yea but what is that to the purpose? the quickest wits proue not alwayes best, for as they are readie to cōceiue, so do they quickly forget, &amp; therewithall, the finenesse of their capacitie doth carie such oftētimes to delight in vanities, since mans nature is such, that with ease it inclyneth to pleasure, and vnwilling it is to indure pain

or trauell, without the which no vertue is obteyned.
                  Eccho commeth in.
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  This geare goeth well, for whereas I was casting with my selfe howe to entrap this yonker, he is falne into the nette of his owne accorde, and desireth that of me whiche I was carefull howe to profer cleanely vnto him. But is not this the old scholemaster? euē the same, wel, we must find some deuice to bleare his eye for a while: let me alone, I knowe howe to bring it to passe.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Doth this felow come to me thinkest thou?
               
               
                  Onaticus.
                  It may be syr, but I know him not.
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  I will salute him. God saue you maister scholemaister.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Welcome gentle brother.
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  Syr, I am sente vnto you by the Markgraue, who vnderstanding that two of his kinsemen are lately placed vnder your gouernement, hath a desire to sée them, and therefore sent me to intreate you that you would gyue them lybertie this afternoone, to the end that he may common with them.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Surely I did not know that they were the Markgraues kinsemen, and they haue yet bene but verie small time with me, but since it so pleaseth him, I am content to graunt them libertie, and I will 
                        •…
                     end them out vnto you presently to go where it liketh him.
                  Gnomaticus goeth in.
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  So so, they are as much a kynne to the Markegraue, as Robyn Fletcher and the swéet Roode of Chester, but yet this was a cleanely shifte vpon the sodeyne, for by this meanes shal I take occasion to bring this yonker and the Ladie Lami
                           •…
                        
                      better acquainted, &amp; much good do it him, for out of doubt she shall be his, as long as his purse maye be myne. But behold where they come altogither, now let me bestirre me and vse my best wittes.
               
            
            
               
               Actus secundi
               Scaena, quinta.
               PHILAVTVS, PHILOSARCHVS, PHILOMVSVS, PHILOTIMVS, and ECCHO▪
               
               
                  Philautus.
                  I Am glad that we haue libertie this afternoone to take recreation, not for that I lacked time to meditate that which hath bene read vnto vs, but bycause I take pleasure in walking abroad.
               
               
                  Philosarchus.
                  And I hope by this meanes to haue further communication with my friende Eccho, and beholde where 
                        〈◊〉
                      is.
               
               
                  Philomusus.
                  Amongst all that our instructer hath rehearsed vnto vs, there is nothing sticketh better in my remembrance, than that which he sayde of time: for surely as it is the greatest treasure which God hath giuen vnto man, so ought he to be verie curious and warie how he bestoweth the same, wherefore Philotimus I thinke we can not better do, than to spende some time by the way in meditating &amp; rehearsing these wholsome precepts, which our instructer hath to vs deliuered, for I assure you, although he hath bene therein verie compendious and sentencious, yet in my iudgement euery sentence is suchas requireth a rype deliberation, and weightie consideration of the same.
               
               
                  Philotimus.
                  Surely Philomusus I am of your opinion, and therefore let vs bestowe the time therein, althoughe percase our brethren here will vse this afternoone in some other exercise.
               
               Philosarchus beckneth Eccho, Philomusus and Philotimus go t
                     •…
                  gether.
               
                  Eccho.
                  Sir it is vnto you that I addresse my selfe, for although

I be not the rediest man on liue to deale in such affayres, yet such is the great good liking which I haue alwayes had in you, that since I spake with you earewhile, I haue not béen vnmindful of you, &amp; surely I suppose that God doth fauour your desires, for euen now when I departed from you, and as soone as I ouertooke the gentlewoman, I cast in my braines how to pleasure you, and meaning to haue deuised some subtilty wherby the thing might be brought into communication, the gentlewoman of her▪ selfe proffred the occasion, for shee demaunded of me what yong gentlemen those were with whom I stayed, I tolde her that ye were Sonnes to two of the welthiest burghers in this citie, and be you sure I left out no commendation which might aduaunce you, whereat she séemed to bite on the bridle, and commended you for your curtesies▪ in that yée saluted her so gently as shee passed by, but especially shee marked you by sundry thinges and gestures, and coulde describe you vnto me by your apparell. Short tale to make, I neuer saw her shew so much lykelyhoode of affection, since I first saw her, as shée bewrayed presently, and shall I tell you in your eare? if Eccho be any better then a foole, she hath a monethes minde vnto Phylosarchus, wherfore play you now the wise man, &amp; strike the Iron whiles it is hot, she returneth this way presently, and thereupon I haue aduentured to come vnto your Scoolemaster, to craue you a libertie in the name of the Markegraue, saying that you were his kynsemen, and this haue I done, to the ende that you might take occasion to salute her e
                        •…
                     nes as she returneth: and if you vse the matter wisely (as I know you can) you may take oportunity also to talke with her, yea and to conduct her to her lodging.
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  Surelie Eccho thou shewest playnlie what good will thou bearest me, but what shall we do with the Markgraue?
               
               
                  
                     Eccho.
                  Tush, folow you your bu
                        •…
                     nes now that you hau
                        •…
                      libertie, and let me alone with that matter, if euer hereafter the thing come in question, lay all vppon me, and I will say, that I mistooke both the Scoolemaster and the Skollers vnto whom I was sent.
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  Well friend Eccho I know not how to deserue thy gentlenes, but in token of gratefull mind, holde, receiue these twentie gildres vntil I haue greater abillity, and be sure that if euer I liue to enherit Phylocalus, then Eccho shall not be vnprouided for.
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  What meane you sir? stay your purse vntill another time, well if you will néedes enforce me, I will neuer refuse the curtesie of a gentleman, but behold where the Ladie Lamia commeth, Sir me recomandez, I will not be séene to talke with you, for I stale from her to▪ pleasure you priuilie.
                  Eccho departeth.
               
            
            
               Actus primi
               Scoena sexta.
               PHYLAVTVS, PHYLOSARCHVS, ECCHO, LAMIA, DYC
                     •…
                   DROM, and PANDARINA.
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  
                     OH my friend Phylautus, behold here a péerelesse péece, doth it not delight your eyes to gaze vppon such a shyning starre? on my
                        •…
                     e honor she hath a swéet face, &amp; by al likelihood she is much to young to haue béen hetherto comonly abused, but wherfore am I abashed? I wil go and salute her. Fayr lady God saue you, and send you that your hart most desireth.
               
               
                  Lamia.
                  Worthie gentleman, I thanke you most heartely

for your good wil, and if God hear 
                        〈◊〉
                      prayer, he shal do more than he did for me a good whyle, but it is no 
                        〈◊〉
                     , 
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      hath taken his pleasure of punishing, he will at last haue pitie on the poore.
               
               
                  Philosarchus.
                  Surely mystresse, it were great pitie that such a one as you, should indure any punishment without great cause, and hardly can I thinke that any heart is so hard as to see you sorowfull, if remedie maye be therefore obteyned.
               
               
                  
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     .
                  Syr, I coulde be content that all men were of your mynde, but I finde curtesie verie colde nowe adayes, and many there be which woulde rather depryue a poore gentlewoman of her right, then 
                        •…
                     ue vpon her pi
                        •…
                     eous plyght: the good king Amadis is dead long sythens, whose Knightes vndertooke alwayes the defence of Dames and Damselles.
                  She whyneth.
               
               
                  Phylautus.
                  Alas what ayleth the yong gentlewoman to complayne?
               
               
                  Pandarina.
                  Syr and not without cause, since she is by great wrong dispossessed of riche Signiories which belong to her by right and inheritance, and complayning here vnto the magistrates, she receyueth small comforte, but is rather hindered by malice and detraction.
                  Philosarchus taketh her by the hand to comfort her.
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  Fayre gentlewoman: although I haue hitherto had no great acquaintāce with you, yet if I might craue but to knowe the cause of your griefe, be you sure I woulde vse my best indeuer to redresse it, and therefore I coniure you by your curtesie, that you change your opiniō, for all Amadis Knightes are not 
                        〈◊〉
                      deade, onely bewray your griefe, and prayse thereafter as you finde.
                  She beginneth to tell a tale.
               
               
                  Lamia.
                  Syr I haue not power to reiecte your curtesie, you shall vnderstand then, that being &amp;c.
                  Pandarina interrupteth her.
               
               
                  
                     Pandarina.
                  Neyce it séemeth that you haue not your honour in such comendation as I would wish you should, I pray you let vs begon homewardes.
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  Why Mistres, are you offended that 
                        •…
                     hée should herken vnto such, as séeke to reléeue her estate.
               
               
                  Pandarina.
                  Sir you are a gentleman well nurtured, and you know this is no place to talke in, without discredyt.
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  Well Mistres, if it please you we will waite vppon you vnto your lodging, and there you shall sée what desire I haue to comfort this fayre Ladie.
               
               
                  Pandarina.
                  As for that sir at your pleasure, I pray God sende her good friendes in her right, for God knoweth she hath neede of such at this present.
                  They follow the L
                        •…
                     dies.
               
            
            
               The second Chorus.
               
                  BEhold behold, O mortall men behold,
                  Behold and sée, how soone deceipt is wrought:
                  How s
                        •…
                     ne mens mindes, of harmefull thinges take hold,
                  How soone the g
                        •…
                     d, corrupted is with nought.
                  Beholde the cares whereof our sauiour spake,
                  
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     Mathew telles, in thirtéenth chapter playne,
                  Such wicked means, malitious men can make,
                  The frutfull séede, with worthles wéedes to stayne.
                  Beholde the deuill, whose ministers are prest:
                  To stir an ore, in euery forward boate:
                  Beholde blynd youth, which holdeth pleasure best,
                  And 
                        〈◊〉
                      the payne, which might their state promo
                        •…
                     e.
                  Great is the care, which grauest men endure,
                  To sée their Sonnes, brought vp in Godly wise:
                  And greate the paines, which teachers put in vre,
                  To trade then still, in verteous qualities:
                  
                     But oh how great, is gréedie lust in youth?
                  How much mischiefe, it swalloweth vp vnséene?
                  With reckles mind, it castes aside all truth,
                  And féedeth still, on that which is vncléene.
                  These parasites, and bawdes haue quickly caught,
                  The careles byrds, who sée not their deceyptes:
                  with such vile wares, the worlde so full is fraught,
                  As fewe can scape, their subtilties and sleights:
                  Yet mighty God, vouchsafe to guyde the rest,
                  That they may sh
                        •…
                     n the bad, &amp; sew the best.
               
            
            Finis, Actus secundi.
         
         
            Actus tertij
            
               Scoena prima.
               DICK DROOM alone.
               
                  THere there there, this geare goeth round as it shuld go, these young gallants are caught without a net, &amp; shall I tell you one thing? no man gladder then I, for as long as that chimney smoketh, I am sure I shall not go hungrie to bed. An Inheritrix quoth you? marie that she is a Meritrix I warrant her, of great burdens, birthrightes I would say, no doubt of it, he that marieth her shalbe sure of great ecclamation, and that good olde gentlewoman her Aunte. Why though the young woman had neuer a groat in the worlde, yet a man might be glad that coulde match his Sonne in such an abhominable (honorable) stocke: these are Auntes of Antwerpe, which can make twentie mariages in one wéeke sor their kinswoman, O noble olde gyrles, I lyke them yet when they be wise, for it is an olde saying, one

shrew is worth two shéep. Wel, let me looke about me how I prate, and let me espie what is become of their brothers according to their commaundement, but are not these two they which come debating of the matter in such earnest? it is euen they, and wot you what? their brethren are otherwise occupied, but yet surely they argue as fa
                     •…
                  t as they, when God knoweth a small entreatye might serue, but I will step aside and herken to these yonkers.
            
            
               Actus tertij
               Scaena secunda.
               PHYLOMVSVS, PHYLOTIMVS, DICK.
               
                  Phylomusus
                  SUrely Phylotimus, I wonder what is become of our brethren, I pray god they be not entised to some vanitie by some lewde companie.
               
               
                  Dick.
                  You might haue gessed twise &amp; haue gessed worse, I beshrew your braynes for your busie coniecture.
               
               
                  Phylotimus.
                  Truely it may be, but I trust they will beare in mind the last precept which your Master gaue vs, at y• least I would we had their companie, that we might meditat the matter together.
               
               
                  Dyck.
                  I perceiue it is time to call them, I wilbe gone.
               
               
                  Phylotimus.
                  If our enstructor shuld examine vs, and finde them to séeke, it would gréeue me asmuch for my brother as if the fault were myne owne.
               
               
                  Phylomusus.
                  Surely and I would also be very sorie if my brother shuld be found slack in his duetie, but in my iudgement we neede not to cast these doubtes, for our brethren séemed vnto me to be very perfect and redy in the especial poyntes of our enstruction, and could (in maner) make rehersall therof immediatly after we had receiued the same.
               
               
                  Phylotimus.
                  Yea marie, but I wil tel you one thing I know by experience in my brother, he wil as soone conceyue or

beare away a thing as any that euer I sawe, and surely to confesse a trueth, he hath an excelent ready wit, but doubtles he will sometimes forget as fast, as he learneth redily, and yet for myne owne part, I would to God that my memorie were as capable as his is, for then I would not doubt but to reteyne sufficiently.
               
               
                  Phylomusus.
                  It may be that his minde is much geuen to other plesures and delights, which do so continuallie possesse his brayns, as they suffer not any other conception to be emprinted in his memorie: for my brother Phylautus doth in a manner meditat nothing els but setting forth of him selfe, and in what soeuer he be occupied or conuersaunt, yet shall you perceiue him to haue a singuler regard to his owne prayse, the which doth sometimes carrie him as farre beyond all reason, as his desertes might séeme to aduaunce him.
               
               
                  Phylotimus.
                  To bee opinionate of h
                        •…
                      selfe is vitious, but surely I am of opinnion, that it is commendable for a young man in all his actions to regard his owne aduauncement, and with all to haue (resonably) a good opinion of him selfe, in exempting of such thinges as he vndertaketh, for if he which coueteth in the latyne tung to be eloquent, shoulde so farre embase his thoughts as to conceiue that he spake or wrot like olde Duns or Scotus, surely (in my iudgement) it would bee verie hard for him to excell or to become a perfect Rethoritian, or if hee which employeth his time in the exercise of ryding, should imagine with himselfe that he sat not comely on his horse backe, it would be long before hee shoulde become a gallant horseman: for in all humaine actions we delight so much the more, and sooner attayne vnto theyr perfections, whenas wée thinke in our mindes that in deede the exercise therof doth become vs: but behold now wher our brethren do come.
               
            
            
               
               Actus tertij
               Scaena tertia.
               PHYLAVTVS, PHYLOSARCVS, PHYLOMVSVS, PHVLOTIMVS and GNOMATI
                     •…
                  S.
               
                  Phy
                        •…
                     us.
                  THis was a proper messanger in déede, hée myght haue mocked others though he mocked not vs.
               
               
                  Philosarchus.
                  O syr you do him wrong, for it séemeth vnto me that the poore fellow is as sorie for it as we are miscontented, and that he rather faulted through ignorance, than of any set purpose, but looke where our brethren are▪ Brother wher haue you bin whilest we were at the Markgraues house?
               
               
                  Phylotimus.
                  Truely brother I walked on with my companion here, hoping that we should haue followed you to the Markgraues house and we were so earnest in meditating such matter as our instructer deliuered vnto vs, that mistaking the way, &amp; not marking which way you went, we were constreyned to returne hether, and to attend your returne, to the ende we might go altogither.
               
               
                  Phylomusus.
                  And you (brother) where haue you bene?
               
               
                  Phylautus.
                  Where haue we bene quoth you? why we haue bene with that good olde gentleman the Markgraue, vnto whome we were as welcome as water into the ship, the olde 
                        •…
                     roward 
                        •…
                     rowner would scarce vouchsafe to speak vnto vs, or to looke vpon vs, but he shall sit vntill his héeles ake before I come at him againe.
               
               
                  Phylomusus.
                  O brother, vse reuerent speach of him, principally bycause he is a Magistrate, and therwithal for his greye haires, for that is one especiall poynt of our masters traditions.
               
               
                  Phylautus.
                  Tushe what tell you me of our masters traditions? if a Magistrate, or an elder would challendge reuerence

                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                     
                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                     
of a yong gentleman, it were good reason also that they should render affabilitie, and chearefull countenance to all such as present them selues before them with good wi
                        •…
                     l. When we came to him he knewe vs not, neyther would he knowe vs by any meanes, but with a grim countenance turned his backe, and desyred vs to goe ere we dranke: a Markgraue quoth you?
               
               
                  Phylotimus.
                  That is strange, that hauing sent for vs, he would seeme to vse such enterteynment when we came.
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  I will tell you brother, it séemeth vnto me that it was rather the faulte of the messanger, and yet heeA fine ex cuse did but ignorantly mistake it neyther: For he was (as it should seeme) sent by the Markgraue, but he did oyther mistake the scholemaister. or the scholers, or both, and therevpon I thinke that the Markgraue was partly offended.
               
               
                  Phylotimus.
                  Truely and not without cause, but behold
                        •…
                      where our maister commeth.
               
               
                  Phy
                        •…
                     .
                  Let vs say then that we were together▪ least he be offended.
               
               
                  
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     .
                  Nowe my welbeloued, and what sayth the honorable &amp; reuerende Markgraue vnto you? or howe doth he like the maner of your enstruction? haue you recyted or declared any part thereof vnto him since your going?
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  Syr no▪ for it seemeth that the messanger did mistake his errande, and was sent to some other scholers, and not vnto vs.
               
               
                  Gnom
                        •…
                     cus.
                  Is it euen so? well then let vs not altogether lose the golden treasure of the time: but tell me, haue you perfectly disgested and committed vnto memory the articles which I deliuered vnto you, for especiall consideration of your duetie?
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  Syr I thinke that I cā perfectly rehearse them.
               
               
                  Phylautus.
                  And I syr do hope also that I shal not greatly 
                        •…
                     ayle.
               
               
                  
                     Philomusus &amp; Philotimus.
                  Syr this yong man and I do partly beare them in mynde, although not so perfectly and readily as we desire.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Well, to the ende that you shall the better imprint them in your memorie, beholde, I haue put them briefly in wryting as a memoriall, and here I deliuer the same vnto you, to be put in verse euerie one by himself and in sundrie deuice, that you may therein take the greater delight, for of all other Artes Poetrie giueth greatest assistaunce vnto memorie, since the verie terminations and ceasures doe (as it were) serue for places of memorie, and helpe the mynde with delight to carie burthens, which else would séeme more grieuous: and though it might percase séeme vnto you, that I do in maner ouerlode you with lessons and enterprises, yet shall you herein rather find comforte or recreation, than any 
                        •…
                     comberance: let me nowe sée who can shewe himselfe the pleasant
                        •…
                      
                     
                        •…
                     et, in handeling therof, 
                        〈◊〉
                      yet you must also therein 
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     d
                           •…
                        rum, for 
                        •…
                     ing allegories or pleasant 
                        〈◊〉
                      in serious causes are not most comely. God guide you 
                        〈◊〉
                      and euer.
                  Gnomaticus goeth out.
               
            
            
               Actus tertij
               Scaena quarta.
               PYLOSARCVS, PHYLAVTVS, PHYLOTIMVS, PHYLOMVSVS, AMBIDEXTER
               
                  Philosarchus.
                  OH that I had now the 
                        •…
                     ayne which Uirgill had in writing of a delectable verse.
               
               
                  Philomusus.
                  God is good and bountifull, yelding vnto euery man that is industrious the open way to knowledge

and s
                        •…
                     ience, &amp; though at first it séeme difficile, yet with trauell euerie thing is obteyned▪ we see the hardest stones are pearced with soft droppes of water, whereby the minde of man may be encouraged to trust, that vnto a willing hart▪ nothing is impossible, but to performe the charge which is giuen vs, we must withdrawe our selues from each other▪ since we are enioyned euerie of vs to deuise it in 
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        •…
                     ortes of poemes, wherefore I will leaue you for a time.
               
               
                  Phylotimus.
                  And I will also assay what I can do.
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  God be with them, shall I tell you Phylautus, wherfore I desired the excellencie of Ui
                           •…
                        gil, in compounding of a verse? not as they thinke God knoweth, to conuert our tedious traditions there into: for a small grace in a verse wil serue for such vnpleasant matter, but it was to furnish me with eloquence▪ for the better obteyning of this heauenly dame, whose remēbrance is swéet vnto me, neyther yet am I able to expresse such prayses as she doth deserue. Oh how it delighteth me to behold in myne imagination the counterfeyt of her excellent face, me thinkes the glimsing of her eyes haue in it a reflexion, farre more vehement than the beames of the Sunne it selfe, and the swéetnesse of her heauenly breath, surpasseth the spiceries of Arabia. Oh that I ha
                        •…
                      skill to write some worthy matter in commendation of her rare perfections, surely I wil tell you Phila
                           •…
                        us, I doe both reioyce in your doings, and much wonder at your inclination. I wonder bicause I can not per
                        •…
                      that you are any thing moued with affection of mynde towards her, and yet I reioyce therein least the same might haue become an hinderance to my desires, oh, howe only loue will admit no companion.
               
               
                  
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     .
                  
                     Phylo
                           •…
                        us, you may happely be deceyued in me, and therefore I would not wish you hereafter to 
                        〈◊〉
                      your selfe in any man at the first acquaintance, but in déede to confesse a truth vnto you, although this gentlewom
                        •…
                     n be beautifull, yet, haue I refreyned hitherto to become

affectionate on her, as well bycause I would therein giue place vnto your desire, as also bycause I haue not perceyued that euer she lent any glaunce or liking looke towardes me, and as I can be content to loue where I finde my selfe estéemed, so be you sure that I thinke my halfepeny as good siluer as another doth, and she that séemeth not with gréedie eye to beholde me, it is veri
                        •…
                      likely that I wil not be ouerhastie to gaze at her. But to returne vnto the purpose, as you do nowe earnestly desire to get victorie ouer her affection: so doe I euery day beseeche of God, that our parentes may at last determine to sende vs vnto some Uniuersitie, that there the varietie of all delightes maye yelde vnto each of vs his contentation.
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  Alas, and I am of another mynde, for though I desire no lesse than you to be at some vniuersitie, yet to lose the sight of my Lamia séemeth no lesse griefe vnto me, than if my heart were torne out of my bodie. But behold where Ambidexter commeth, my minde giueth me that I shall heare some newes by him. Howe nowe Ambidexter? what newes?
               
               
                  Ambidexter.
                  Good syr, and such as I dare say you will be glad of.
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  And what are those? tell me quickly I pray thée.
               
               
                  Ambidexter.
                  Syr I will tell you, there came a tatling fellowe to your father erewhile, and told him a tale in his eare which séemed to like him but a little, what so euer it was, where vpon your Father mumbled a while as the Cade which cheweth the Cudde, and in the 
                        •…
                     de with a great sigh he sayde. Well, then (quoth he) there is no remedie but sende them with spéede to the Uniuersitie: which words whē I ouerheard, I smyled to my self and thought, (by God, and so you may dresse them) for I dare well say, they will be the most ioyfull newes that they heard this halfe yeare, aud to gratifie you with the same, I came immediatly

to séeke you out, but where 
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      brother?
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  He is gone that way walking, 
                        •…
                      pray thée followe him, and make him pertaker of these newes.
                  Ambidexter goeth out.
                  Oh howe much is Ambidexter deceyued in me at this present? No no, I can not so content my selfe to forget the swéete face of that worthy Lady Lamia, neither can I euer hope to reioyce, vnlesse I might be so happy, as to enioy the continuall sight of her heauenly countenance, the vniuersitie is in déede the place where I haue of long time bene desirous to be placed, especially for the varietie of delights and pleasures which there are dayly exercised: but alas, what néedeth the riche man to become a théese? or what néede I to wander vnto the vniuersitie for to séeke pastime and pleasurs, when I may euen here in Antwerp without further trauel, enioy the dayly comfort of such consolation? and if I be not also much deceyued, she loueth and lyketh me no lesse than I desire her, I pray you tell me Phylautus, do you not playnely perceyue that she hath an affection towardes me?
               
               
                  Phylautus.
                  Surely Phylosarchus, I dare not sweare it, although in déede the franknesse of her entertaynement was much, but when I consider that it was at the verie first sight, it maketh me thinke that her curtesie is commō, and may be quickly obteyned.
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  Why did she not then make as fayr
                        •…
                      semblant vnto you?
               
               
                  Phylautus.
                  Marie, bycause she perceyued you to adresse your selfe most directly vnto her, and there is no woman so kynde, that she can deale with mo than one at once, but be you sure if I had bene there alone, she would haue lent me as fauourable regard as she séemed nowe to giue you, it is the tricke of them all, and therefore neuer set your mynde so much thereon, I warrant you, when we come to the Uniuersiti, we shall haue store of such there, and I am

glad to vnderstande that your father determineth to send
                        •…
                      you thether, for I am sure that my brother and I shall accompanie you, since our fathers haue alwayes bene destrous that we should spend our youthes together. But beholde where our fathers come both together, let vs go in, least they espie vs, and thinke that we loyter here.
               
            
            
               Actus tertij
               Scaena, quinta.
               PHILOPAES, PHYLOCALVS, FIDVS, GNOMATICVS
               
                  Phylopas.
                  SUrely neyghbor Phylocalus, I can not blame you though you be moued at these tidings, but in things which come contrarie to expectation or desire, the wisedome of men is best seen, &amp; therefore I would aduise you to forecast in time howe you may preuent such a mischief, for greatest woūds are at the firste more easily cured, than if they continue vntill some aboundance of humour or other accident doe hinder the benefite of nature, and surely it grieueth me in maner as much, as if the like had bene found in myne own sonne.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  So haue you great reason to say, for your sonne Phylautus was there with him also, and though the Harlot séemed not to lende liking vnto any but my sonne, yet be you out of doubt that being in such companie, he shal hardly escape the snares of temptation.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  Well, howe so euer it be, we shall best doe to consult with their teacher herevpon, and beholde where he 
                        •…
                     mmeth. Syr we were about to sende for you, being ad
                     
                        •…
                     tised that my neighbors sonne Phylosarchus doth haunt

a very dishonest house in this towne, and my sonne Phylautus hath also ben there in company with him, the which giueth vs iust occasion to lament, &amp; most glad we would be to deuise some comfort in tyme, since the thing hath (as yet) bene of no long continuance. Wherefore we beséech you to deale faithfully with vs, and to declare if you haue s
                        •…
                     ne any such behauiour, or likelyhood in them, and furthermore to aduise vs, which way we might best redresse this mishappe betimes.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Sir to declare of your sonnes behauiour, trewly I haue neuer séene any thing to misselyke of them, neyther could I euer perceine that they were slowe in apprehending myne enstructions, but rather more forward then their brethren, true it is that here came one to me in name of the Markgraue, saying that he was theyr kinseman and very desirous to sée them, wherevpon I did willingly giue them leaue, and when they came ther they say that the messenger misse tooke the matter, and should haue gone to some other schollers. But doubtles my mind giueth me, that if they haue bene allured to any euill company, it hath bene by that same fellow which came to mée on that message.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  Do you not know him, or what his name is?
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  I do not knowe him, but he said that hys name was Eccho.
                  
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  
                     Eccho? Nay then you haue not iudged amisse, for it is one of the lewdest fellowes in this towne, a common Parasite and a seducer of youth.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Surely my harte did not greately like him at the first sight, but since thinges done cannot be vndone, I lyke well that you should (according to your owne deuise) prouide in time before they wade déeper in such enterprises, and to speake mine opinion, you may doe wel to send them vnto some Uniuersity, before they haue further acquaintance or haunt in such company, for whether

it be loue, or lust that hath infected them, there can be no presenter remedy then to absent them from the thinges which they desire, and therewithall I promise you (not to flatter) they are already very sufficiently able for the Uniuersity, and the en
                        •…
                     ructions which I haue giuen them, may serue rather for precepts of their perfect duty to God and man, then for any exercise of the liberall sciences, wherein they are so wel entred, and haue bene so throughly traded, as there lacketh nothing but conuenient place where they might procéede in Logike and such lyke.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  And me thinkes we might better doe to enfourme the Markgraue. Who vppon such meanes as we shall make, may banish the harlot with her traine out of the City, and may also punish the parasite for so entysing the younge men.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  I graunt you that all this maye be done 
                        •…
                     ery well but then you are to consider, that the hartes of young men, are oftentimes so stout, that they can not abid publiquely to heare of a faulte, the which (being priuatlie and gentlely admonished) they woulde peraduenture willingly amend: and great difference there is betwéene children and young men, for in childhoode all punishment is terrible, but in florishing youth euery punishment may not be vsed, but discretion must foresee what kynde of punishment wil most preuaile and best gayne reformation in the mind of the offender. Wherefore myne aduice shoud be that you send them to some Uniuersitie, and as neare as you can forsée to place them with such a Lutor as may alwaies haue an eye to their exercises, and may haue especiall care how they shall bestow their vacant tymes. For idlenesse is the cause of many e
                        •…
                     ils in youth, whereas beeing occupied or exercised in any thing that is verteous or commendable, they shall not haue so great occasion to thinke of vanities.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  All that is true, but what Uniuersitie do you

thinke meetest?
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  For mine owne opinion I lyke Doway very well, bothe for that it is neare, and from thence you maye allwayes within shorte tyme be aduertised, and also because I do knowe very learned and faythfull men there, and herewithall it is but a lyttle Towne, and the Uniuersytie but lately erected, wherby the roote of euill hath hetherto had least skope, and exercise hath béene (and is) th
                        •…
                      more streightly obserued.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  And could you dyrect vs vnto any such faithfull Tutor, that we myght be bolde to thinke our selues sure of their well doing? and that they should not be susfred to run at large about wanton toyes and lewdnes?
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Truely I can tell you of two or three which are both faythful and carefull of their charge, but to assure you in such sort as you require were verie hard to do, sythens no Tutor can vse such vygilant industrie, but that sometimes he may be deceiued, neuerthelesse I know them to be carefull.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  Well for my part I can be content to folow your aduise, &amp; what thinke you neighbour Phylopaes.
                  
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  I do lykwise agrée to as much as hath beene sayd.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Well then marke yet a little furder myne entent, I would thinke good that the yong men themselues should not knowe therof vntyll the Iorney were prepared and they redye to depart, and my meaning is this, in so doing you shall antyeypate all occasions that they might haue to conferre with lewde company, who paraduenture would not spare to follow and accompany them wheresoeuer they go.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  Surelie that is well considered, and therfore neighbour. I pray you geue streight charge vnto your seruant least he do bewray our entent herein.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  Sirha do you heare not one worde for

your lyfe of that which we haue here communed together.
               
               
                  Fidus.
                  Sir I trust you haue neuer hetherto found me 
                        •…
                     acke to do that which I haue ben commaunded, nor rash to dysclose any thing which I thought might dysplease you.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  Well I pray you let vs go together vnto my house, and there let vs more at large debate this matter.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  Go we where best liketh you.
               
            
            
               Actus tertij
               Scaena Sexta.
               PHYLOMVSVS, PHYLOTIMVS,
               
                  Phylomusus.
                  WOuld God now that I could mete with Phylotimus that vnto him I might recount what I haue done in the theame which our Master gaue vs earwhile, for cō
                     ference is comfortable vnto schollers, were it no more but to vse eache others aduise and opinion in such thinges as they shall vndertake: and though in compiling of verses, all company is combersome, yet when the same are made and finished, then is it a singuler comfort to haue acompanion with whom (as with thy selfe, (thou maist be bold to confer for iudgement. And behold wher Phylotimus commeth in good time.
               
               
                  Phylotymus.
                  
                     Phylomusus I haue finished the charge which our enstructer gaue vs in verse, &amp; I would be glad to haue your opinion therein.
               
               
                  Phylomusus.
                  Hée telles the tale that I should haue told.
               
               
                  Phylotimus.
                  I pray you giue eare a while, and I will reade vnto you what I haue done therin.
               
               
                  Phylomusus.
                  With right good will Phylotimus, reade them I pray you.
               
               
                  
                     Phylomusus.
                  Giue eare then, but first I must thus much declare vnto you. I haue no more but conueied in to verse the verie briefe which our Master deliuered vs in prose, adding neither dilatations, allegories, nor examples: and thus it is.
                  
                     FEare God alwais whose might is most, &amp; ioyn thy feare with loue
                     Since ouer all his worthy workes, his mercie standes aboue:
                     In him thou mayst likewise be bold, to put thy trust alwaie,
                     Since he is iust and promyse kéepes, his truth cannot decay.
                  
                  
                     Giue eare vnto his Ministers, which do his worde professe,
                     Disdayne them not due reuerence, their place deserues no lesse.
                     And loue them eke with hartie loue, bicause they féede thee still,
                     With heauenly foode, wheron thy soule, his hungrie hart may fill.
                  
                  
                     Then next to God true honor giue, to Gods anoynted king,
                     For he is Gods lieutenant here, in euerie earthly thing:
                     his power comes from heauen aboue, the which thou must obay,
                     And loue him since he doth protect, thy life in peace alway.
                  
                  
                     To Magistrates in their degrées, thou must like duties beare,
                     Loue, honor, and obedience, since they betoken heare,
                     The maiestie: and represent the king him selfe in place,
                     And beare his sword, &amp; maintayn peace, and déeme ech doutfull case.
                  
                  
                     Be thankefull to the countrey soyle, wherein thou hast béene bred,
                     Defend it alwaies to the death, therefore thy life is led:
                     And seeke by all thy skill and powre, to do such deedes therin,
                     As may therto some profit yeld, so shalt thou honor win.
                  
                  
                     To elders for their hoarie heares, thou shalt do reuerence,
                     And loue them since they councell thée, in euery good pretence:
                     Defend them eke bicause they be, as feeble (for their might)
                     As stout and strong in good aduice, against the flesh to fight.
                  
                  
                     
                     Thy father and thy mother both, with other parents 
                           〈◊〉
                        ,
                     Thou shalt in honor still esteme, for God commandeth so:
                     And loue them as they tendred thee, in cradle and in kind,
                     Releiue their age (if it haue neede) for duety so doth bind.
                  
                  
                     Thus shalt thou beare thy self alwaies, if y• wilt prosper wel
                     And from thy selfe if thou desire, all mischiefe to expell:
                     Thē kepe thy self both chast &amp; cléen, in déed &amp; eke in thought,
                     Embrace the good, &amp; leaue y• bad, for thou art dearely bought.
                     Thou art the Temple of the Lord, which must be vnde
                           •…
                        de,
                     More dere to him thē Tēples are, which mortal mē do build.
                     And since he cast frō Tēple once, which was but lime &amp; stone
                     The biers and the sellers both, &amp; bad them thence be gon,
                     How much more thē wil he require, y• y• shuldst kepe thy selfe
                     Both cleane &amp; pure from fylthy sin, much worse thē worldly
                     Be holy thē, &amp; kepe thesewords, in mind both night &amp; day (pel
                           •…
                        
                     
                     For so be sure that god himself, thy stagring steppes wil stay.
                  
                  Finis quoth Philotimus.
                  Thus haue you now séene Philomusus, my simple skill in poetry, and I pray you tell me your opinion therein.
               
               
                  Phylomusus.
                  Surely Phylotimus. I like your verses verie well, for they are compendious: and to be playne with you, I haue lykewise framed a verse or poeme vpon y• same matter, marie I haue some what more dilated and enlarged euerie point, but such as it is, I will likewise craue your opinion therein.
               
               
                  Phylotimus.
                  With right good will: I pray you reade them.
               
               
                  Phylomusus.
                  
                     THe man that meanes, by grace him selfe to guyde,
                     And so to lyue, as God may least offende:
                     These lessons learne, and let them neuer slide,
                     
                        
                           •…
                        rom out his mynde, what euer he pretende.
                  
                  
                     
                     Since God is greate, and so omnipotent,God.
                     
                     as nothing can withstand his mighty powre,
                     he must be fearde, least if his wrath be bent:
                     we perishe all, and wither lyke a flowre.
                  
                  
                     Yet with such feare, we must him loue lykewise,Loue▪
                        
                     
                     Synce he hath store, of mercyes in his hand:
                     And more delights, that Sinners shuld aryse,
                     then still to fall, and neuermore to stand.
                  
                  
                     In him also, we maye be bolde to trust,Trust▪ 
                           
                              〈◊〉
                           
                        
                     
                     In him we may, put all our confidence:
                     For he is true, and of his promise iust,
                     He neuer fayles, the pyth of his pretence.
                  
                  
                     His Ministers, and such as prech his word,Minister.
                     
                     Because they be, from him (to teach vs) sent▪
                     
                     We shuld to them, giue eare with one accord▪
                        Audiēce.
                     
                     And learne their lore, which leads vs to repent.
                  
                  
                     All reuerence, to them shalbe but due,Reuerēce
                     
                     As well because, their office so requires:
                     As there with all, because there doth ensue,
                     A iust rewarde, to humble mennes desires.
                  
                  
                     And loue them eke, with fast and faithfull loue,Loue▪
                        
                     
                     Because they féed, thy soule with heauenlie bread:
                     Which cannot moulde, nor from thy mouth remoue,
                     Untill thou haue, thy fill there on ysed.
                  
                  
                     Next God the king, doth challeng second place,King▪
                        
                     
                     And him we must, both honor and obay:
                     
                        
                           •…
                        ause he hath, (from God aboue) 
                           •…
                        is grace,Obediēce
                     
                     And is 
                           
                              〈◊〉
                           , on earth to beare the sway.Honor.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     Yet as with hart, we shall him honor yeld,
                     And must obay, what he commaunds with feare
                           •…
                        
                        Loue▪
                        
                     
                     So loue him eke▪ bicause he is our shield,
                     And doth protect, our life in quiet here.Magis
                              •…
                           es.
                     
                  
                  
                     Lyke duties do, to Magistrates belong,
                     Because they beare, the sworde, and representOb
                              •…
                           
                        
                     
                     The king him selfe, &amp; righten euerie wrong,Honor.
                     
                     And mainteine peace, with all their whole entent.Loue.
                     
                  
                  
                     Unto the soyle, wherin we fostred were,Country.
                     
                     We must alwaies, be thankeful children found:Thankefulnes.
                     
                     And in defence therof we must not feare,Defence.
                     
                     To venture life, as we by birth 
                           •…
                        e bound.
                  
                  
                     For to that ende, our life to vs was lent,
                     And therewith all, we ought the same t'aduaunce.Profit.
                     
                     And do such déedes, as may be pertment.
                     To profit it, and eke our selues enhance.Elders.
                     
                  
                  
                     The siluer heares, of Elders euery where,Reuerēce
                     
                     Clayme reuerence, as due therto by right:
                     Their graue aduise, and precepts which we leare▪
                        Loue.
                     
                     Doth challeng loue, the same for to requit.Defence▪
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Their weake estate, when force is gon and past,
                     Doth craue defence, of such as yet be strong:
                     Since they defend, the force of fortunes blast,
                     From weakest wytts, which harken to their song.Parentes.
                     
                  
                  
                     The parents they, which brought vs vp in youth,Honor.
                     
                     Must honord be, since God commaundeth so:
                     And synce therby, a gratious gyfte ensewth,
                     Euen longe to lyue, in earth whereon we go.
                  
                  
                     
                     They ought lykewise, our harty loues to haue,
                     As they loued vs, in cradle when we laye:Loue.
                     
                     And b
                           •…
                        ake their sleepes, our sely lyfe to saue,
                     When of our selues, we had no kind of stay.
                  
                  
                     And if they néede, in age when strength is gone,Releife.
                     
                     We ought r
                           •…
                        ue, the same with all our powre:
                     We should be gréeud, when as wee heare them grone,
                     And w
                           •…
                        yle their wantes, and helpe them euerie howre.
                  
                  
                     And he that thus, can well direct his wayes,Our selfe
                     
                     And 
                           〈◊〉
                         himsefe, in chast and holy life:
                     Shall please the Lord, &amp; shall prolong his 
                           〈◊〉
                        ,
                     In quiet state, protected still from stry
                           •…
                        e.
                     Be holie thus, and liue in good accord,Gods Temple.
                     
                     Since men one earth, are Temples to the Lord
                  
                  Thus may you sée Phylotimus, that one selfe same thing may be handled sundrie wayes, and now I pray you tell me your opinion, as I haue told you myne.
               
               
                  Phylotimus.
                  Surely Phylomusus your verses do please mee much better then mine owne, and verie glad I am that wée haue eche of vs so well accomplished our dueties, nothyng doubting but that our enstructer will also like the same accordingly: &amp; now if you thinke good, let vs go in and present the same, when soeuer hée shall thynke good 
                        •…
                     o demaund it.
               
               
                  Phylomusus.
                  With right good will, go you on &amp; I wil folow▪
                  
               
            
            
               The third Chorus.
               
                  THe Shed is great, and greater then the show,
                  Which séemes to be, betwéene the good and bad:
                  For euen as wéedes, which fast by flowres do grow
                        •…
                     ,
                  (Although they be with comely collors clad:)
                  Yet are they found, but seldome swéete of smell,
                  
                     
                        •…
                     o vices brag, but vertue beares the Bell.
               
               
                  
                  The prauncing stéede, can seldome hold his flesh,
                  The hottest greyhound leaues the course at length:
                  The finest Silkes, do séeld continue freshe,
                  The fattest men, may fayle sometymes of strength:
                  Such déepe deceiptes, in faire pretence are founde,
                  That vices lurke, where vertue séemes t'abound.
               
               
                  A Spanish tricke, it hath ben counted oft,
                  To séeme a thing, yet not desire to be:
                  Like humble bées, which fly all dayes aloft,
                  And tast the flowers, that fairest are to sée:
                  But yet at euen, when all thinges go to rest,
                  A foule cowe sharde, shall then content them best.
               
               
                  Well yet such bées, bycause they make great noise,
                  And are withall, of sundry pleasaunt hewes:
                  Bee most estéemd, alwayes by common voyce,
                  And honourd more, then Bées of better thewes:
                  So men likewise, which beare the brauest Showe,
                  Are held for best, and crowched to full lowe.
               
               
                  But vertue she, which dwelles in secret thought,
                  Makes good the séede, what euer be the smell:
                  Though outward glose, sometimes do séeme but nought,
                  Yet inward stuffe, (of vertue) doth excell:
                  For like a stone, most worthy to estéeme,
                  It loues to be, much better then to séeme▪
                  
               
               
                  
                     Phylautus héere, and Phylosarchus eke,
                  Did séeme at first, more forward then the rest:
                  But come to proofe, and nowe they be to séeke,
                  Their brethren no we, perfourme their duty best▪
                  
                  Thus good from badde, appeares as day from night,
                  That one takes paine, that other loues delight.
               
            
            Finis, Actus Tertij.
         
         
            
            Actus quarti
            
               Scaena prima.
               PHYLOPAES. PHYLOCALVS, GNOMATICVS.
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  
                     I Haue for my parte set al thinges in redynesse for my Sonnes departure, and if my neighbour haue done the lyke, they shall departe immediatly: but behold where he commeth, how now sir? What haue you done or dispatched?
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  Al thinges necessary for my Sonnes are in readynesse, and you, what haue you done?
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  Doubt you not of my diligence, I am ready were it within this houre, but I would be glad to talke with Maister Gnomaticus, as well to vse his aduise, as also to haue his letters of commendation vnto some faithfull Tutor at the Uniuersity: and looke where he commeth in haste.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Gentlemen I haue founde you both in good houre, and I would wish you to dispatch the younge men your sonnes with all conuenient speede, for the thing which you suspected is doubtlesse too true.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  And how knowe you?
               
               
                  G
                        •…
                     omaticus.
                  I will tell you sir, care while assoone as I departed from you, I examined thē al concerning a taske which I had giuen them, and that was to put in verse a b
                        •…
                     iefe memoriall of the chiefe poyntes wherein I did enstruct them, and I found that Phylomusus and Phylotimus
                  
                  (whom I thought not so quicke of capacity as the other)
                  had done the same very well: on that other side, I founde Phyl
                           •…
                        us and Phylosarchus to haue done there in nothing

of all, and marueyling at their straunge and vnaccustomed slackenesse, I searched them vppon such suspicion as I had conceyued, and founde that Phylosarchus had spent the time in wryting of louing sonets, and Phylautus had also made verses in praise of Marshiall feates and pollycies.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  O God, and haue you not punished them accordingly?
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  As for that sir be you contented, there is time for all thinges, and presently in my iudgement you could deuise no punishment which would so much gréeue them as to departe from this Citie, hereafter I doubt not but to deuise the meanes that both they shalbe rebuked as appertaineth (though they be out of my handes) and the causers of these mischieues may also chaunce to heare thereof when they thinke it quite forgotten, but at thys point wée will hold no longer discourse therein, onely prepare for your Sonnes departure to the Uniuersity.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  The chiefe thing wherevpon wée 
                        •…
                     tay, hath bene both to vse your aduise, and to desire you that you will take paines to wryte your letters vnto some faithful Tutor there, who may both rebuke them for that which is past, and haue care to gouerne them better in tyme to come.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Mine aduise you haue heard already, and touching the letters which you require, they are in maner ready, for I had so determined before you required me, and now if it please you to walke vnto my lodging, wée will from thence dispatch them before they heare any further newes of the matter.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  Go we with good will.
               
            
            
               Actus quarti
               Scaena secunda.
               
               ECCHO alone.
               IT is a wonderous matter to sée the force of loue, sauing your reuerence. I dare say the Lady Lamia since she saw this young gentleman, could neuer sléepe vntill her eyes were shut, and there withall she taketh such thought, that assone as euer shée is laid she falleth on snorting: and God knoweth, her chéekes are become as leane as a pestill of porke, and her face as pale as a carnation gilofloure. Fye 
                     〈◊〉
                  , what meaneth shée? Will she cast away her selfe on this fashion for his sake? She beareth but euill in remembraunce the good documentes of that vertuous olde Lady her Aunte. I warrant you it would be long before that 
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     
                   would dye for loue. Tush tush shall I tell you? It is folly to stand meditating of these matters, euery man for him selfe and I for one, these yonkers shall pay for the rost, and Eccho by your leaue will take part of the coste, but behold where commeth doughty Dicke. Howe now Richard what newes?
               Dicke Drom commeth in.
            
            
               Actus quarti
               Scaena tertia.
               DICKE, DROM, ECCHO.
               WHat newes? mary Phylosarchus hath sent a fat brest of veale, a capon, a dosen of pigeons, a couple of rabets, and a stoupe of wine vnto the lady Pandarinaes house, and promiseth to be there at supper to talke more of the matter which you wot of.
               
                  Eccho.
                  And hath he sent no more?
               
               
                  Dicke.
                  Why is not that well for a footeman? By our lady sir, it doth me good to thinke what cheare I wil make with the leauinges, and wotte you what? Be you sure hée shall lacke no cleane trenchers, for assone as he hath laide

a good morsell before him, Dicke wilbe at an inche with a cleane plate to pro
                        •…
                     er him.
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  Well said Dicke, and I trowe that I will skinke in his cuppes as fast on the other side, but heare me Dicke, as for these matters neyther of vs both will bee to seeke, but there are other thinges to be remembred which are of more weighty con
                        •…
                     eration.
               
               
                  Dicke.
                  And what I pray thee?
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  Marie thou must marke whensoeuer he casteth a glaunce at the Lady Lamta, and round him in the eare, saying: beware sir how you look, least her Aunt espie you. And again, if he speake a word wherein he séemeth himsel
                        •…
                      to take pleasure, extoll him streight with praise, and say tha
                        •…
                      
                     
                        
                           〈◊〉
                        
                      hath to 
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      as hee. Lykewise 
                        〈◊〉
                      to whet 
                        
                           〈◊〉
                        
                      forward, as 
                        〈◊〉
                      shee shewed not 
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      enough. These and a thousand such other 
                        〈◊〉
                      must be 
                        〈◊〉
                      and practised, to make him come off, and whatsoeuer he giueth thee let vs share betweene vs, for I promise thee Dicke by the faith of a true B
                           •…
                        rgondyance, I will be as true to thee as thy coate is to thy backe.
               
               
                  Dick
                        •…
                     .
                  By the masse Eccho and that is true enough, for it hath 
                        〈◊〉
                      so long to my shoulders, that a lowse can not well clyme the clyffes thereof without a pitchforke in her hand. But I trust maister 
                        
                           〈◊〉
                        
                      fees will be suf
                     
                        •…
                     ient to set both thée and me a floate, and make vs as braue as the best.
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     , as for that matter, if he do not another shall: hee were w
                        •…
                     se enough that would leane altogether vnto one 
                        〈◊〉
                      these dayes, no no Dicke; be ruled by Eccho, and 
                        •…
                      warrant thee wée two will 
                        •…
                     iue howe soeuer the world wag
                        •…
                     e, hast thou not often heard, that change of pasture maketh fatte ealues?
               
               
                  Di
                        •…
                     ke.
                  Ha ha ha, by God and well sayde, but who commeth 
                        〈◊〉
                     ?
               
               
                  Eccho,
                  Ha? mary it is the olde Phylopaes and his neighbour

                     Phylocalus, what is the matter tro
                        •…
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      vs stand aside and heare their talke a while.
               
               
                  Dycke.
                  Best of all stand close.
               
            
            
               Actus quarti
               Scaena quarta.
               PHYLOPAES, PHYLOCALVS, PHYLAVTVS, PHYLOM
                     •…
                  SVS, PHYLOSARCVS, PHYLOTIMVS, GNOMATICVS, AMBIDEXTER.
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  SInce tyme is the greatest treasure which God lendeth vs, and yet he doth but lend vs the same to the end that we should well employe it, it shalbe therefore the bounden duty of euery man so to bestowe the same, as may returne to most commodity and profitte. And since your enstructer héere doth commend your towardnes much more, (I feare) then you deserue, it séemeth that wée should haue lost time in longer deteyning you from the Uniuersity, &amp; therfore we haue prepared (as you sée) to send you thither, trusting that you will there vse such diligence, as may be to the profit of your Countrey and for your own aduancementes. The which to perfourme, I beséech the Father of Heauen that he will alwayes giue you the spirit of wisedome, and powre his grace vppon you continually.
               
               
                  Phylautus.
                  Sir it shall become vs to obey whatsoeuer you commaunde, although in very déed the sodaine of our departure séemeth somewhat straunge vnto me, but it becommeth me not to be enquisitiue thereof, and in déed for mine owne part, there is nothing which could better content me then to go vnto the Uniuersity.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  
                     Phylosarchus, you and your Brother shall also accompany my neighboures Sonnes here to Doway,
                     
for since you haue hitherto bene brought vp togither, I thinke not méete now to parte you. Wherefore I charge you that you so behaue your self, as I may alwayes heare that you be diligent and studious, since that is the meane to bring you vnto estimation.
               
               
                  Phylosarchus.
                  As touching my diligence, I trust that IMurmurers disobe dient seldome proue wel. haue neuer yet bene behinde any of my companions, but this sodaine of our departure séemeth to procéede of some alteration in your minde, the which I haue not deserued. It had bene a smal matter to haue had thrée or foure daies respitte and leasure to prepare our selues, and to haue bidden our friendes farewell, I thinke no mens children are thus set out.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  As for your preparation, all thinges are made ready for you, and your friendes shalbe gladder to sée your retourn home again learned, then they would haue bene pensiue to departe with you.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  My welbeloued, since it pleaseth your parentes thus to dispose your iourney, I cannot otherwyse doe but commend you to the tuition of almighty GOD, whom I beséech nowe and euer to guide you by his grace, and I exhorte you for Gods sake, that you beare well in minde the preceptes which I haue giuen you, assuring my selfe that ruling your actions by that measure, you shalbe acceptable to GOD, pleasing to the world, profitable to your selues, and comfortable to your parentes.
               
               
                  Phylomusus, and Phylotimus.
                  Sir it is no small griefe vnto vs to depart from such a louing enstructer, but since it becommeth vs to obey our parentes, we contend not contrary to their commaundementes, hoping by Gods grace so to employ our tyme, and so to contynue in the trac
                        •…
                     e which you haue trodden vnto vs, that you shall alwayes commend our diligence and good will.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  Sirha? are the wagons ready? And is their cariage therein placed with all thinges conuenient?
               
               
                  
                     Ambidexter.
                  Yea sir all thinges are dispatched.
               
               
                  Phylocalus:
                  Then go your wayes with them, and the Father of Heauen be their guide and yours now &amp; euer.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus:
                  Fellow mine, you must deliuer me this letter when you come to Doway according to the superscription thereof.
               
               
                  Ambidexter.
                  It shalbe done sir God willing.
                  The youngmen kneele down.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  The God of peace vouchsafe to blesse you now and euer.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  And giue you grace to become his faith
                        •…
                     ull seruauntes. Amen.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  My well beloued, I beséech the Heauenly Father to graunt you a prosperous iourney, and well to bestowe your time nowe and euer.
                  Phylautus, Phylomusus, Phylosarchus, Phylotimus and Fidus departe.
                  Did you not perceiue that onely the two elder séemed to grudge and repugne? it is a meruelouse matter, they two are of an excellent capacitie, and able to beare away (in manner) more then can be layd to their charge, but an old saying hath béene Chi tropo abraccia niente tiene. Well now, it shal not be amisse if wée consult of our affayrs here at home, for as for them take you no doubt, they shal vnderstand at Dowaye, wherefore they were sent so soone from Antwerpe, &amp; because in all thinges Secresie is a great furderaunce, it shalbe best that we draw our selues apart vnto one of your houses, where we may more commodiously confer vpon that which is to be done here.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  I lyke your counsell well, &amp; when it pleaseth you let vs go to my house.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  With good will, I will accompanie you.
                  They depart.
               
            
            
               
               Actus quarti
               Scaena quinta.
               ECCHO and DYCK DROOM.
               
                  Eccho.
                  FEllow Rychard, how like you this geare?
               
               
                  Dick.
                  Marie friend Eccho, I lykeit but a little.
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  And why I pray you?
               
               
                  Dyck.
                  Why quoth you? marie because I am sorie that such a swéete morsell is plucked out of my mouth.
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  And I am glad that I shal féede my fill on such a swéete morsell, for since there is now no remedie, but these younkers muste néeds bee gone, God bee with them. Dyck and Eccho, with the Ladies will eate &amp; drinke as fréelie for their sake, as if they were here present, and heare me Dyck, if they had béene here, wee should haue béene fayne to wayte on the table, and to bee contented with their leauings after supper, whereas now wée wilbe so bold as to sit downe with the rest, since we be (as thou well knowest) of housholde with that good gentlewoman, and by our Ladye, I was neuer so deintyly brought vp but I could eat a hote Cap
                        •…
                     n, aswell and as sauorly as a cold messe of porage, especiallie where the bread &amp; drinke is good.
               
               
                  Dyck.
                  All this I confesse also to be good &amp; sound doctrine, but yet it gr
                        •…
                     ueth me to thinke that wee haue lost so good customers which might haue continued such banquits often times.
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  Tush Dyck hold thy peace, if we haue not them, we shall haue others as good as they, thou mayst bee sure that as long as Lamia continueth bewtifull, she shall neuer be without Sutors, and when the Crowes f
                        •…
                     te groweth

vnder her eye, why then no more adoe but ensineuate thy selfe with such another. Yea and in the meane time also, it should be no bad councell, if a man had foure or fiue such hauntes in store, that euermore when one house is on sw
                        •…
                     eping, another spytte may cry creake at the fire: store is no store as the prouerbe saith, and now adayes the broker which hath but one bargaine in hand, may chaunce to weare a thred bare coate.
               
               
                  Dyck.
                  Sayst thou so Eccho? and I promyse thée I had such a lyking to this young man, that I was partly in mynd to haue followed him to Doway.
                  
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  To Doway? nay get me further from Antwarpe, then I may sée the smoke of the chymnies, and they haue good lucke. Tush tush, Doway is a pelting towne packed full of poore Skollers, who thinke a payre of cast hosen a greate reward, but Antwarp for my money. I tell yée trueth, there are not many townes in Europe that mainteyne more iollytie then Antwarpe, but behold where the Markgraue and his officers come. I wilbe gone, I like not the smell of them.
               
               
                  Dick.
                  By the masse neither I, they are going to cast off some bloodhound to séeke a vagabond or some like chase, and let them hunt tyll theyr hartes ake, so I bee once out of their sight first.
                  They run a side.
               
            
            
               Actus quarti
               Scaena sexta.
               SEVERVS the MARKGRAVE, with the officers.
               MUch is the mind of man deceiued, which thinketh that rulers &amp; officers haue the meriest liues, for although it séeme vnto some men a swéete thing to cōmaunde, yet whosoeuer cōpareth the burdē of such cares as are insidēt

vnto his 
                     〈◊〉
                  , vnto the lightnes of the pleasure which cō
                  meth by com
                     •…
                  undement, he shal find, that much greater is the payne of that 
                     •…
                  ne, then the profit of that other. For what pleasure redoundeth vnto an honest minde, to pronounce sentence of death vpon an offendor? or what profit ariseth by punishing of malefactors? but on that other side, what griefe wanteth where a quiet mynde is encembred with gouernment? what howre of the day is exempt from toyle? in the morning the prease of Suters at the chamber dore do breake the sweetest sleepe, the rest of the forenoone is lyttle enough for the ordynarie howres of courtes and decydyng of contentions, at diner you shall hardly dysgest your meate without some sauce of complaynts or informations, wherin lykewyse the rest of the day most be occupied: and the night suffyzeth not to forecast what polityke constitucions are needful to be deuised or renewed, for to meete with the dayly practises and inuention
                     •…
                  s of lewde versones: So that in fine thyne office will neither suffer thee to sléep, nor yeld thee contentmēt when thou art awake, neither geue thée leaue to eate in quiet, nor permit thee to follow thine owne profitte when thou art fasting. I set a side to declare what trade of other priuat gaynes a man must omit when he is in aucthority: but well sayd the phylosopher, which concluded that we are not borne onely for our selues, but parte our contrey also doth chalenge. Well goodfellowes, one of you shal go to Saincte Mighells, and there at a howse with a red lattyce you shall finde an old ba
                     •…
                  de called Pandarina, and a yong damsell called Lamia, take them both and carie them to the coupe, geuing charge that they be safely kept vntill my further dyrection be known, and another of you shall s
                     •…
                  ek out Eccho the parasite, al men know him wel enough, take him and bring him to mée.
               He departeth, as the Skoolemaster cometh in.
            
            
               
               Actus quarti
               Scaena septima.
               GNOMATICVS, NVNTIVS.
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  IF none other thing were required in a faythfull 
                        •…
                     
                     tor but onely that he should teach his s
                        •…
                     hollers grammer or such other sciences, then with lesser trauaile might wée attayne vnto perfection, sythens Gammer and all the liberal Sciences are by traditions left vnto vs in such sort, that without any greate difficultie the doubt thereof may be resolued: but the Schoole M
                        •…
                     ster which careth 
                        •…
                     or none other thing but onely to make his schollers lerned, 
                        •…
                     y in some respect be compared to the horsecourser, which one lie careth to féede his horse fat, and neuer delighteth to ryde him, manage him, or make him handsome: and when such palfryes come to iorneyng, they are comonly so 
                        •…
                     
                     der proude, that they praunce at the fyrst exceedingly, but being put to a long iourney or seruice, they melt thei
                        •…
                      owne greace and are not able to endure traua
                        •…
                     le. E
                        •…
                     n so y• mindes of yong men being onely trained in knowledge of artes, and neuer perswaded in points of moral reformation, become often times so prowde &amp; so headie▪ that they are caried rather away with a vaine imagination of their owne excellency, then setled in y• resolutions which might promoote them vnto dignitie: and wandring so in a vayne glorious oppinion of their owne wit, they do (as it were) foūder and cast them selues in their own halter. Su
                        •…
                     h hawe 
                        〈◊〉
                      philosophers bin in time past, who haue so far gone on pilgri
                        •…
                     age in their owne pee
                        •…
                     ish concei
                        •…
                     s, y• they haue not shamed, by a vaine shew of learning to defend s
                        •…
                     ch propositions, as seeme most rediculous &amp; 
                        •…
                     stranged from reason.

                     Anaxagoras def
                        •…
                     ded that snow was black and yet was accompted a philosopher of greate grauitie &amp; iudgement. Pherecydes, prog
                        •…
                     icated y• an earthquake was at hand, because he saw the water drawen out of a fountayne, and yet was he the Master of Pythagoras, &amp; accompsed a pro
                     
                        •…
                     ound phylosopher. Protagoras, also affirmed that mē might well affirme all that to bee true, which vnto them seemed true. And infinite others might bee rehersed, whose opinionate iudgementes did eclipse the rest of their comendable capacitie: w
                        •…
                     rupon also hath sprong the damnable opiniō of Atheysts. For the mind of man is so heauenlie a thing and of such care excellēcie, that it alwaies worketh and can not be idle. And if with the quicknes of conceyt it be tempred by a modest moderation, to haue regard vnto vertue, and moralitie, then proueth it both goodly &amp; godly: wheras if it run on hedlong, only led by natural cō
                     siderations of causes, it may proue admirable for some passing quallitie, but it seldome is séene commendable or allowed for perfection▪ The consideration wherof hath oftē moued me rather to enstruct youth by a pr
                        •…
                     scribed order out of gods own w
                        •…
                     rd, thē to nuzzle thē ouer déepely in philosophicall opinions. And yet is the mind of young men so prone and prompt to vanitie &amp; delight, that all proueth not as I would haue it. For example behold my late schollers, who forgetting their duetie and neclecting my precepts, are fallen into the snares which I least of al 
                        〈◊〉
                     : But surely to confesse a trueth, I iudge that it rather procéeded by the entisements of others, then by their own default. Oh how perillous is lewde company vnto youngmen? Well, I haue deuised yet a meane wherby both the Parasites here may bee punished, and the youngmen may also be rebuked at 'Doway: In such sort, that their sodain seperation may preuent all meanes to escape it, and yet that one being ignorant of that others punishment, shall neuer grudge or snuffe at the same. And Phylopaes with his neighb
                        •…
                     ur

                     Phylocalus promised me eare while to put my deuise in execution, I long to heare what may be done therin, for still I feare me least the crafty Parasite should get knowledge thereof, and so both escape himself and further enfect some other with newe deuises. But who is this that commeth héere in such haste?
               
               
                  Nuntius.
                  Good lord what a world is this? Iustice quoth he? mary this is Iustyce in deed of the new fashion.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  And what Iustice good fellow I pray thée.
               
               
                  Nuntius
                  Naye none at all Sir, but rather open wronge, an honest old gentlewoman with her kinswoman are commaunded to the coupe, onely because they suffered an honest youngman (and Sonne to a welthy Burgher) to suppe with them yesternight, and a good fellowe which is well knowen here in the City, and hath dwelt here these seuen yeares past, is also cast in prison bicause he serued them at supper, I haue seldome heard of such rigor vsed, especially since they prosfer good suretyes to bée alwayes forth comming vntill their behauiour be tryed.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Well good fellow speake reuerently of the Magistrates, peraduenture there was some further matter therein then thou art aware of, but when was it done?
               
               
                  Nuntius.
                  Euen now sir, I doe but come from thence.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  This geare hath bene pollitiquely vsed, and I will go sée how it is come to passe, for these are euen those lewd companions which seduced my schollers. Good fellow gramercy for thy tydinges.
                  exit.
               
               
                  Nuntius.
                  Why? Do they lyke him so well? I holde a grote the parties are not halfe so well pleased therewyth, but I wil go further vntil I may declare them vnto some pitiful minde, which moued with compassion, may speak vnto the Markgraue in their behalfe.
                  Finis Actus Quarti.
               
            
            
               
               The fourth Chorus.
               
                  THe toiling man which tilles, his ground with greatest paine,
                  Hath not alway such crops theron, as yéeld him greatest gain.
                  Nor he the fairest house, which laies thereon most cost,
                  Since many chips of chance may fall, to proue such labours lost.
                  In vaine men build their fortes, with stone with lyme and sand▪
                  
                  Unlesse the same be founded first, with Gods owne mighty hand.
                  Though Paule himself did plant, whose trauelles did not cease,
                  And then Apollo watred eake, yet God did giue encrease:
                  The grace of God it is, whereon good gyftes must growe,
                  And lacke of God his grace it is, which makes them lye full lowe.
                  How often haue bene séene, both watch and ward well kept,
                  And yet into the strongest holdes, hath treason lightly lept?
                  The héediest hen that is, the puttocke oft beguiles,
                  Such wolues do walke in wethers felles, y• Lambes mistrust no wiles▪
                  
                  The for can preach somtimes, but then beware the géese,
                  For seldome failes a théeuish hand, but that it takes a fléese.
                  The deuill hath many men, to gather in his rentes,
                  And euery man hath sundrie meanes, to bring vs to their bents.
                  Some puffe vs vp with pride, and some set men aloft,
                  Whereby the most by princely pompe, forget themselues full off.
                  Some giue vs worldly good, and some giue beauties grace,
                  That one bréedes care, y• other lust, which train vs to their trace.
                  In fine and to conclude, what minde of man desires,
                  That same the deuil can set to sale, which stil maintains his fires
                  Beholde Gnomaticus, which learnedly had taught:
                  His schollers here such good preceptes, as were with wisedome
                  And therewithall did care, to sée them spend their time, fraught:
                  In exercise that might be good, and cleane deuoide of crime.
                  But then behold selfe loue, and sparkes of filthy lust,
                  Which made them streight despi
                        •…
                      his wordes, &amp; cast thē down in dust.
                  And now beholde he cares, to cure it if he might,
                  But all too late the water comes, when house is burned quite.
                  Wherefore who list to learne: Obstaprincipijs.
                  
                  Since vertue seldome can preuaile, where vice so rooted is.
               
            
            Finis Chori &amp; Actus quarti.
         
         
            
            Actus quinti
            
               Scaena prima.
               DICKE DROOM alone.
               
                  NAy if you play such play fare well altogyther, of all weapons I can not abyde these siluer daggers, I, with a mace quoth you? I will not stand one blowe with a mace, they haue caught my fellowe Eccho, but I promise them they shall haue good lucke if they catch me, you will say that I ought not so to leaue Eccho in the bryers, in deed we were sworne brethren, but what for that? I know not now how I was aduised when I tooke that oth, but surely as I am now aduised my Brother shall daunce alone in prison, it is no biding heere for me, but to be plaine I will trudge after these yenkers to Doway, and trye howe the ale tasteth in those Coastes, for I like not the drinke in Antwerpe, now a dayes it is vengeable bitter, this was a supper in déed, no maruel though Eccho and I were so glad of it, but we triumphed before the victory, for whiles we were preparing the banquet, came in an officer and laide hold of the women and Eccho all at once: that sawe I, and to go. Whether nowe sirha quod one of the sargeantes to me? To buy oliues for my M
                     •…
                  stres quod I. T
                     •…
                  e knaue catchpole replied nothing but l
                     •…
                  ughed, as who should say, the Supper might be 
                     •…
                  ten without sause well enough, but how madde am I to stand prating here so long? I will be gone, to Dow
                        •…
                     y, to Doway, on mine honestie beheld wher the old men come, I meane the Fathers of these yankers, adue my maisters, and say yo
                     •…
                   sawe not me.
            
            
               
               Actus quinti
               Scaena secunda.
               PHYLOPAES, PHYLOCALVS, NVNTIVS, FIDVS.
               EUen now neighbour Phylocalus I finde what it is to be a Father, a Father? Nay a carefull father, for I must confesse vnto you, that since the departure of my Sonnes I haue found no quiet in my thoughtes: one whyle I séeme to doubt least they haue been distressed by the way, another whyle I séeme to doubt least they be eftsoones entised vnto vanities by euill company, and how much the more I think here
                     •…
                  , so much the more I am perplexed with dout. God for his mercy send vs comfortable newes, to 
                     •…
                  
                  fort my sorowfull and doubtfull harte.
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  Truly neighbour, and I am not altogither frée from such imaginations, but whiles I recomfort my selfe by the hope which I haue in those letters that maister Gnomaticus did wryte, I am straight wayes tormented againe with another doute, the which is such, that I may be ashamed to vtter it considering mine owne solly.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  O neighbour kéepe nothing from me for Gods sake.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  I will tell you then, I condemne my selfe of exceeding 
                        •…
                     lly, in that I haue 
                        〈◊〉
                      the cariage of those letters to my seruaunt Ambidexter, whose doublenesse I haue often tryed, and therefore my simpl
                        •…
                     city was the greater: and bicause he is not (long sithens) 
                        〈◊〉
                     
                     ▪ my minde 
                        〈◊〉
                      some doubt of his 
                        •…
                     dellity.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  Tr
                        •…
                     ly and not without cause, for he mig
                        •…
                     t haue retourn
                        •…
                     d long 
                        〈◊〉
                     . O what a dolte was I that I sent not Fidus (here) with them also? Surely Phylocalus my mynde giueth me t
                        •…
                     t he hath 
                        〈◊〉
                      vs.
               
               
                  
                     Nuntius.
                  Letters, letters, letters.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  What cryeth this good fellow?
               
               
                  Nuntius.
                  Letters from Doway letters from Doway. Hey
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  Mary this séemeth to be some Carier which commeth from Doway. Commest thou from Doway good fellow?
               
               
                  Nuntius.
                  Yea sir doutlesse.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  And what letters hast thou?
               
               
                  Nuntius.
                  Nay that can not I tell, there are to many strange names for me to remēber, but here is my register, and so may you knowe better then I what letters I haue in my packe.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  Is that the fashion to write in a role a note of their names to whom thy letters are directed?
               
               
                  Nuntius.
                  Yea Sir that is a custome which I and such ignorantfellowes must vse, for I cannot read my selfe. &amp; to shew all my letters were folly, but I do alwaies beare such a role in my hand, wherin are written the names of those vnto whom my letters (for that tyme) are directed, &amp; then when I shew it, euerie man can soone tell whether I be for him or not.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  A good order surely, and I pray thée let vs sée thy role of names.
               
               
                  Nuntius.
                  Here it is Sir.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  To begin with all here is a letter for you neighbour, I trust I shall also finde another for my selfe.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  Oh how this comforteth my hart, thys letter commeth from my younger Sonne, I will breake it vp.
                  He goeth a side with it.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  Lo now I haue lykewise found one that is directed to me, &amp; it is also ye orthographie of my Sonne Phylotimus, let vs sée what it conteyneth in Gods name.
                  He readeth also.
               
               
                  
                     Nuntius.
                  Who shall pay me for the bringing of them?
               
               
                  Fidus.
                  Stay a while good fellowe, thy paines shalbe considered well I warrant thée.
               
               
                  Nuntius.
                  Yea but I may not long tary, for I must go about and deliuer the rest of these letters this night.
               
               
                  Fidus.
                  All that maist thou doe well enough, they will not be long before they haue done, but I pray thée tell me, doest thou not knowe my Maisters Sonnes?
               
               
                  Nuntius.
                  What should I cal them by their names?
               
               
                  Fidus.
                  The eldest is named Phylautus, and the younger called Phylomusus.
                  
               
               
                  Nuntius.
                  I thinke I know maister Flautus, a tall yong gentleman, small in the middle, is he not?
               
               
                  Fidus.
                  Yes surely he is but slender.
               
               
                  Nuntius.
                  Mary and I sawe him in déed at Doway, braue (by the masse) and lusty, there was another gaye young gentleman in his company, and a seruing man, wotte you who? olde Ambidexter the best fellowe in all Antwerpe, I promise you they are mery and well.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  What newes neighbour?
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  Good and badde.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  Euen so haue I in my letter, hold good fellowe ther is a reward for bringing of these letters, &amp; gramer
                        •…
                     y.
               
               
                  Nuntius.
                  I thanke you sir, I retourne to Doway wyth in these two dayes, and if it please you to commaund me any thing thither I will repayre to your house.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  I pray thée do, for peraduenture I wil wryte by thée.
                  Nuntius exit.
                  O God neighbour, how vnhappie were wée to send your lewd seruaunt Ambidexter with our Sonnes? My Sonne writeth vnto me that his brother Phyla
                           •…
                        tus &amp; your Sonne Phylosarchus are seldome from the Bordelles or Tauerns, and that Ambidexter is their companion, and meaneth to tary there with them and to retour
                        •…
                      no more.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  My Sonne wryteth so in effect, but hée séemeth

to do
                        •…
                     t least they prepare themselues to abandon the Uniuersity, and to go gadding about the world a little, for he 
                        •…
                     teth that they stay on hope that Eccho &amp; certaine other of his companions will shortly be with them, othermyse they had bene gone long sithens. Of himselfe I haue 
                        〈◊〉
                      newes, for he wryteth vnto me that the Palsegraue hath written vnto the chauncellour of the uniuersity for a secretary, and that he standeth in clection.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  And my Sonne Phylomusus is entered into the ministrie, and hath preached in the Uniuersity, and meaneth thortly to go vnto Geneua, such comfort we haue yet vnto our calamity. But as euery mischief is most casely cured and redressed in the beginning, so if you will followe my counsell, we will immediatly dispatch Fidus vnfo them, who shall both aprehend Ambidexter and cause him to be punnished, and shall also staye our two wandring Somes and bring them home vnto vs.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  I like your councell well, and for the l
                        •…
                     ue of God let it be put in execution immediatly, for insuch cases nothing is so requisite as expedition.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  Holde Fidus take these twenty crownes, and get thee away with all spéede possible, take post horses from place to place, and if they should chaunce to be gone from Doway before thou come, yet followe them, and neuer cease vntill thou haue founde them, and bring them home vnto vs.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  
                     Fidus spare for no cost, and holde thée there are twenty crownes more if néede require.
               
               
                  F
                        •…
                     us.
                  Well Sir you shall sée that no diligence shall want in me to recouer them. Will it please you to commaund 
                        〈◊〉
                      any other seruice?
               
               
                  Phylop
                        •…
                     s.
                  No, but God send thée good successe.
                  Fidus departeth.
                  In the m
                        •…
                     ane time neighbour let vs go see what is done for the staying of E
                           •…
                        cho, that we may yet preuent all mischeefe

as much as in vs lyeth.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  I lyke you well, your witte is very good vppon a so
                        •…
                     aine, but beholde where maister Gnomaticus commeth, by him we shall partly vnderstand what is done.
               
            
            
               Actus quinti,
               Scaena tertia.
               GNOMATICVS, PHYLOPAES, PHYLOCALVS.
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  GEntlemen, I haue sought you round about the Town, this geare is in maner dispatched, Eccho is apprehended with his traine and all.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  Wel, that is some comfort yet to our heauy hartes.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Why haue you any cause of heauinesse? Tell me I pray you Sir, what meane you to stand thus amased?
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  My neighbour and I haue receyued newes which are both sorowful and comfortable. Our two elder Sonnes (by the lewde assistance of my seruaunt whom I sent with them) do bestowe their time very wantonly in Doway, and do determine (as séemeth) to be gone from thence very shortly.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  To be gon? whether in Gods name?
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  Nay that hee knoweth, to seeke aduenfures abrode in the world by all lykelyhoode, and they stay but for the comming of Eccho and his companyons.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Wel as for their c
                        •…
                     ming thanked be god it is preuen
                        •…
                     ed wel eneugh, but I pray you Sir tell me how know you this to be certeynly so?
               
               
                  Phyloc
                        •…
                     lus.
                  Why w
                        •…
                      haue receiued letters from our other two Sonnes, hold
                        •…
                      you here is mine, you may read it.
                  He d
                        •…
                     uereth him the letter.
                  
                     How now neighbour? what muse you? your wittes were good (erewhile) vpon the sodayne, plucke vp your spirits, you shall see by Gods grace Fidus will bring vs good newes.
               
               
                  Phylop
                        •…
                     s.
                  Oh neighbour I am not able to expresse the sorowes which my heart conceiueth, alas the goods of the world (although they be gotten with great trauaile, and kept with great care) yet the losse of them doth neuer torment a wise man▪ since the same deuice or brayne that coulde contriue the gathering of them, is able againe to renew the like: but the misgouernmēt of a mans children, or to sée them cast away by lacke of grace or for lacke of vigilant foresight, that onely is vnto the wysest mynde an vnmedicinable wounde. Oh that my harte is not able to beare nor to abide the furious assaults of this misfortune.
                  He sowneth.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  What man stand vp and take a mans harte vnto you.
               
               
                  Gnomati
                        •…
                     s.
                  What Sir for the loue of God do not take the matter thus heauily, by his grace you shall haue no such cause, your neighbour here hath cause of comfort: for I perceiue that his Sonne hath so well spent his time, and so well profited at his booke, that 
                        •…
                     e standeth in election to bee Secretarie vnto Palsegraue.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  Yea and his Sonne Phylomusus is also become a famous preacher, &amp; meaneth shortly to go vnto Geneua.
                  
               
               
                  Gnomatic
                        •…
                     s.
                  Wel then ech of you hath some cause of cō
                     fort yet, and by the grace of God you shall see that the rest will fal out better then you looke for, but if it should not, you must yet arme your selfe with pacience, and giue god thankes in all thinges, since he can send tribulations and vexations when pleaseth him, and can also send comfort when seemeth mete to his deuine maiestie, but what haue

you done for the preuenting hereof?
               
               
                  Philocalus.
                  Mary we haue dispatched my neighbours seruant Fidus to stay both them and Ambidexter, that the one may be punished in example of all others, and that the oth
                        •…
                     r may also be brydled from their hedstrong race which they meane to run.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  
                     Ambidexter? Why what hath h
                        •…
                      doone?
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  Do you not marke the letter? it séemeth that his onelie leudenes hath ministred matter vnto their misbehaui
                        •…
                     ur, for he is their lodes mate &amp; c
                        •…
                     mpaniō in all places, and hath setled himselfe with them, meaning neuer more to turne vnto me.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Surely Phylocalus you were not well aduised to sēd such a fellow with your Sonnes, I pray god he haue deliuered my letters faythfullie, for I dyd yet neuer receaue answere of them. By whome receaued you these letters?
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  By a carrier which trauayleth wéekely to Doway.
                  
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  And had hee no letters for me? Phylocalus. Surely I cannot tell, for I was 
                        •…
                     o glad when I founde in his role, letters to mee and my neighbour, that I sought no furder for any other, but you shall soone finde hym out if you aske for the Carryer of Doway.
                  
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Well by your leaue then I will goe séeke hym, for I long sore to haue answere of my letters.
               
               
                  Philocalus.
                  You shall do well, and in meane tyme my neighbour and I will go vnto his house, for I perceiue he is not well.
               
            
            
               Actus quinti
               Scaena quarta.
               
               SEVERVS the MARGRAVE with his officers, and ECCHO.
               
                  Seuerus.
                  COme on sirha, what acquaintance haue you with these Ladyes?
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  Sir I haue but small acquaintance with them.
               
               
                  Seuerns.
                  No? What did you there then?
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  Sir I had wayted vppon them into the Towne that day (as I doe vppon diuers other for my lyuing) and they prayed me to suppe with them in part of recompence for my trauaile.
               
               
                  Seuerus.
                  Mary sir your fare was good as I vnderstand, and méete for much better personages then eyther of you. Tell me who prouided it? And who paid for it?
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  I knowe not Sir, it was enough for me that I knew where it was, I neuer asked from whence it came for conscience sake.
               
               
                  Seuerus.
                  Well iested fellow Eccho, but I must make you sing another note before you and I part. Tell me how came you acquainted with Phylosarchus?
                  
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  I haue knowen him long since sir, as I knowe diuers other young gentlemen in this Towne.
               
               
                  Seuerus.
                  Yea but howe came it to passe that he should haue bene there at supper that night?
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  That cannot I tell, neyther do I knowe wheth
                        •…
                      he should haue bin there that night or no.
               
               
                  Seuerus.
                  Yes that you can, did you neuer sée him there before?
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  I saw him there once, in other honest company, but what is that to me? Had I any thing to do with his being there? or doth it followe of necessity that béecause he was there once before, therfore he should haue béen there that night also?
               
               
                  
                     Seuerus.
                  No, but you know well enough if you lyst that he should haue béen there, and that the banquet was prepared for him. You were best to confesse a trueth.
               
               
                  Eccho.
                  Sir I will not confesse that which I knowe not, neither for you nor for neuer a man on liue. He might haue beene there for all mee, &amp; he might haue béene away also if he list, for any thing that I know.
               
               
                  Seuerus.
                  Well, it were but lost labour to talke anie longer with you, go take him, and carrie him to the mill, and there let him be whipped euerie day thryse, vntill he confesse the cyrcūstances of al these matters, wee may not suffer the Sonnes of honest and welthy Burghers to bée seduced by such lewde fellowes, and they to skape skotfrée.
               
            
            
               Actus quinti
               Scaena quinta.
               GNOMATICVS▪ alone.
               O God how a man may bee deceiued (at the first) in a youngman? the capacitie of this Phylos
                        •…
                     rcus and hys yokefellow Phylautus was so quick and so sufficient to receiue any charge, that a man would haue beléeued them to haue béene two of the best and towardest youngmen in thys citie, and yet behold how 
                     〈◊〉
                   and vayne delight hath caried them to run another race. I haue receyued letters here from my frind Master in Doway, who deelareth vnto me thereby, that they are sufficyently able to conceiue any tradicion or Science, but therwithall that they are so geuē ouer to pleasures &amp; light pastimes, y• it is in maner vnpossible to bridle their 
                     •…
                  ādring desires. On that other side he prayseth the other two f
                     •…
                  r the sobrest yong men that euer came vnder his charge, &amp;

confirmeth in effect asmuch as they had writtē for newes vnto their parentes, whereof I haue greately to reioyce, that (hauing passed through my handes) they are so lykely to come vnto promotion. And as I reioyce in them, so an
                     •…
                   I most hartely sory for the two elder, that their misgouernment may become not onely a great grief to their parents▪ but also a hinderance to such commendation as I might else haue gayned by the others: but thus wée may sée, that in euery comfort there may growe some 
                     •…
                  uiet, and no herbe so cleane but may be hindred by stinking wéeds that gro
                     •…
                   by it. Well I will go talke with their parentes, and if they wilbe ruled by my councell, they shall giue them leaue a little to see the world, and to followe any exercise that be not repugnant vnto vertue, for vnto some wittes neyther correction, nor frendly ad
                     •…
                  tion, nor any other perswasi
                     •…
                  n will serue, vntil their owne rodde haue beaten them, and then they proue oftentymes (though late) men of excellent qualities. But beholde where they come to discharge me of this trauaile.
            
            
               Actus quinti
               Scaena sexta.
               PHYLOCALVS, GNOMATICVS, and PHYLOPAES.
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  HOw nowe maister Gnomaticus, haue you receiued any letters from Doway?
                  
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Yea sir I haue receiued letters from thence.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  And what newes I pray you?
               
               
                  Gnom
                        •…
                     us.
                  Euen the same in effecte that you haue receyued.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  Why then I perceiue that our two younger sonnes haue not deceiued vs, nor boasted more in their

letters then is true in effect.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  No surely, for my frend aduertiseth me that they are two of the towardest young men that euer came in that Uniuersity, and that he hath great hope to sée them in the end become famous through all the lowe countreys.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  Well that is some comfort yet, and what wryteth he of the two 
                        •…
                     lder?
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Surely he writeth as much cōmendation as may be of their capacity, mary there
                        •…
                     al he saith that they bée marueilously bent vnto concupiscence, therefore I wil tell you mine aduise. As soone as they come home, first rebuke them sharpely for the misse bestowing of their excellent wittes, and it shall not be a
                        •…
                     e if you adde there vnto also some correction, that being done, I would wish you to put in their choyce what kinde of lyfe they will followe, so that it be vertuous, and not contrary to Gods worde, and let them sée the worlde a while: for such fine wittes haue such an vniuersall desire commonly, that they neuer proue stayed vntill the blacke oxe hath troden on their toes.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  Yea mary but how are we sure to recouer them againe? When as I feare much that they are gone from the Uniuersity already?
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Why doubt you of that?
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  Because my neighbours Sonne Phylotimus wrote vnto him that he much douted they would abandon the vniuersity, and that they taried but onely to heare from Eccho and his complices.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Yea, but Eccho and the rest are safe enough for comming at them, and beholde where commeth the honourable Markgraue with his Officers, you were best to go vnto him, and to giue him thankes for hys greate care and diligence.
               
            
            
               
               Actus quinti
               Scaena septima.
               PHYLOPAES, SEVERVS, PHYLOCALVS, GNOMATICVS.
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  RIght Honourable, we are bound to yéelde you humble and harty thanks, for that (as we vnderstand) you haue 
                        •…
                     sed great paine and diligence in apprehending of a lewds company, who haue (as wée sée now) seduced our children, and made them to neglecte the holsome preceptes which their faithfull enstructer had giuen them.
               
               
                  Seuerus.
                  Surely I haue done my best (in discharge of my duty) to apprehend them, and I haue examined them also, but truly I can not finde hitherto any proofe against them, whereby they ought to be punished: and though I desire (as much as you) to sée them condingly corrected, yet with out proofe of some offence I should therin commit a wrong. True it is that Eccho is knowen commonly in this Town for a Parasite and a flattering fellow, and the young woman also doth not séeme to be of the honestest, but yet there is no body which will come in and say this or that I haue séene or knowen by her. Shée confesseth that Phylosarchus and Phyl
                           •…
                        us 
                     
                        •…
                     re there one night at a banquet, and that Phylosarchus should haue supped there the same night that they were taken, and when I aske her to what end, she answereth that he was a suter to her for mariage, and for witnesse bringeth in her Aunt as good as her selfe, in the meane time I haue no proofe of euill wherwith to burthen her. And then maister Eccho (on that other sid) he 
                        〈◊〉
                      as stiffe as may be, and saith that he knoweth not whether Phylos
                           •…
                        us should haue supped there or not, and for lack

of proofe I am able to go no furder.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  Yea Sir but doubtles that Eccho was the first cause of their acquayntaunce, for the first tyme that my Sonne was there, was one afternoone, at which tyme Eccho came to their Schoole Master in your name, and craued liberty for them to come and speake wyth you.
               
               
                  Seuerus.
                  With me?
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Yea Sir doubtlesse, and when I gaue them leaue to come vnto you, they returned (after two or thrée howers respyte) and sayde that you knew them not when they came there, and that Eccho said he had mistaken the Scholemaster and the schollers.
               
               
                  Seuerus.
                  Sayd they thus of me?
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Yea truely sir.
               
               
                  Seuerus.
                  And sayd they that they had béen with me?
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Sir I woulde bée lothe to say so if it were otherwise, and furthermore they séemed angry.
               
               
                  Seuerus.
                  And wherefore I pray you?
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  For that you gaue them no better countenaunce.
               
               
                  Seuerus.
                  Before God they neuer came at mée, but thys is somewhat yet, for by this meanes I haue good cause to punish Master Eccho, and I pray you Master Gnomaticus go with me vnto him, and you shal 
                        •…
                     are what answer he is able to make vnto these matters.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  With right good will sir I wil wayte vpon you. Worthy gentlemen, you shal do wel to consider in the meane time vpon that which I last tolde you as myne oppinion.
               
            
            
               Actus quinti
               Scoena octaua.
               
               PHYLOPAES, PHYLOCALVS.
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  THe aduice which master Gnom
                           •…
                        ticus hath geuen vs, doth not mislike mee altogether, but still my minde is more and more vexed with doubt, least in the meane time (and 
                        •…
                     efore Fidus can come at them) they fall into some notable mishap by theyr misgouernment.
               
               
                  Phylocalus.
                  You do well to doubt the worst, but if it were so, what remidie but patience? and geue god thanks that hath sent to eche of vs such a Sonne as may become the comfort of our age.
               
               
                  Phylopaes.
                  Truely it is in deede a great comfort that eyther of vs may take in our yonger Sonnes, but if wee haue lost the elder (as I feare it much) what a corrosiue will that be vnto vs? Oh how I feele my fearefull harte panting in my restles brest? the Father of heauen vouchesafe to send mee ioyfull newes of Phylautus. O wretched Phylopaes thou are like vnto a couetous man, which hauing aboundance is yet neuer contented, thou art alreadie sure of such ofspring as may giue thee cause to reioyce, and yet thy minde is not satisfied, vnlesse all thinges might fall out vnto thine owne desire, and thou maist be compared to the patiēt which crieth out before the Chirurgiens instrument do 
                        •…
                     ouch him, because thou conceiuest in thy imagynation, the dread which tormenteth all thy thoughts. But alas why do I not prepare this wretched corpes of mine, to be a present witnes what is become of my Phylautus? I will surely, go prouide all thinges necessarie for my iourney, and neuer giue rest vnto these bones vntill I may sée him. I will do so.
               
               
                  Phylo
                        •…
                     alus.
                  What abide Phylopaes, I am a shamed to sée you so impa
                        •…
                     , what man, I am as sorie to heare of

my Sonnes l
                        •…
                     wd behauiour as you are of yours, and 
                        〈◊〉
                      a truth. I thinke he wilbe f
                        •…
                     wnde more fa
                        •…
                     ltie then yours, b
                        •…
                     t be it as God pleaseth, I haue one especiall comfort, and that is, that I performed my du
                        •…
                     tie in carefulnes and in foresight (as much as in me laye) so guide him vnto promotion, it is comendable in a parent to haue a care for his children, but this womanlike tendernes in you deserueth reprehention.
               
               
                  Phylopes
                  Se how euerye man can geue good councell, and few can followe it, well I praye you let vs withdraw oureselues to our houses, to see if change of place may also change my melancholike passion.
               
               
                  Phylocalus
                  Go we, I will go to your house for companie.
               
            
            
               Actus quinti
               Scaena nona.
               SEVERVS, GNOMATICVS, FID
                     •…
                  S. AMBIDEXTER.
               
                  Seuerus.
                  WEll since he is found culpable of thus much, I would but talke with these neighbours of mine (I meane Phylopaes and Phylocalus) and wee will deuise such punishement for the malefactors, as may be a terror hereafter to all parasites how they abuse the name of an officer, or entyse the children of any burghers.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Sir I dare say they will be pleased what soeuer you do therein, and if it so please you I will go vnto their houses and call them vnto you, for mée t
                        •…
                     inkes they are departed synce we went. But what is hee that commeth here in such haste?
               
               
                  
                     Fidus.
                  Oh that I coulde tell where to fynde my Master.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  It is Fidus, God graunt he bring good 
                        •…
                     idings.
               
               
                  
                     
                        •…
                     idus.
                  I would rather fy
                        •…
                     d him in any place then at hys howse, that he might haue some company (yet) whych might comforte him, for I dare say these tidings will break his harte with Sorowe.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  I will go to him. How now Fidus, what newes?
               
               
                  Fidus.
                  O master Gnomaticus I knowe no man whom I wuld rather haue presently then you, O Sir I am vnhappy, for I am the messenger of the most wofull newes that euer my master receyued, for gods loue accompanie me vnto him that you might yet by your wisedom aswage the extremitie of his grief.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  I will willingly beare thée companie gentle Fidus, and surely thou deseruest greate commendation and thankes, aswell for thy fidelitie, as also for the excéeding greate spéede which thou hast made, but I pray thée tell vs first (in the presence of the right honorable Markegraue) the whole circumstance &amp; effect of these thy newes, which thou sayest are so s
                        •…
                     rowfull.
               
               
                  Fidus
                  Sir since you will néedes haue it, my master hath lost his eldest Sonne, and Master Phyl
                           •…
                        calus hath little better 
                        •…
                     en lost his also.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Alas these are heauie newes in deed, and must ne
                        •…
                     des afflict the poore parents with extréeme grief, for they are vnto me (almost) vntollerable: but since it becommeth a christian to beare pa
                        •…
                     ientely what soeuer God doth prouide, I pray thee tell on the whole circumstance of euerie thing as it fell.
               
               
                  Fidus.
                  I will tell you Sir, I vsed all the dilligence possible on my way, and yet before I coulde come at Doway, they were 
                        •…
                     rom thence departed.
               
               
                  
                     Gnomaticus.
                  What all togithers?
               
               
                  Fidus,
                  No sir, but Phylomusus was sent by the whole consent of the vniuersity vnto the Palsgraue to be his secretary, whereas he yet remaineth in good estimation, and Phylotimus was gone vnto Geneua, moued with an earnest zeale and spirit, and there he is in singuler commendation and much followed.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  and what was become (the meane while) of Phylautus and Phylosarchus? They were still at Doway were they not?
               
               
                  Fidus.
                  No sir they were gone also, but no man could tell me whether they were gone, and they were gone somewhat before their brethren.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus
                  Why then they taryed not for Eccho, as the letters emported that they would haue done.
               
               
                  Fidus.
                  O Sir they had aduertisement that Eccho was apprehended, and that hastened their departure.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  And by what meanes knew they of it?
               
               
                  Fidus.
                  There was one Dicke Droom a companion of Ecchoes, which came vnto them and tolde them the whole discourse, wherevppon they fledde with him immediately.
               
               
                  Seuerus.
                  Such a one was presente in déede when Eccho was taken, and because mine officers knew him not, nor had any commission to search for him, therefore they suffered him to departe.
               
               
                  Fidus.
                  Out vppon him, I would to God they had made him safe also, for he hath bin the casting away of Phylautus. Phylautus, Phylosarcus, Dick Droom with my frend Ambidexter here, went out of Doway together, and bicause my maisters charge was that I should followe where so euer they went, I followed as fast as I could by enquiry, and with in thrée or foure dayes iourney, I heard that Phylosarcus by the helpe of this good companion Ambidexter had gotten a fair minion for sooth, and stayed with her at Brusselles, fron
                        •…
                      whence Phylautus and Dycke Droom departed, and tooke

their wa
                        •…
                      togither vp towardes Germany, now Phylosarchus and his cari
                        •…
                     ge held their way (as it was saide) towardes 
                        
                           〈◊〉
                        
                      W
                        •…
                     n I sawe that they were so par
                        •…
                     ed, and that I could not followe both companies at once, I thought best to holde on my way towardes the Palsgraues Court, &amp; hoped that by the way I might yet chance to heare of Phy
                        
                           •…
                        tus, and in very deede I heard of such a one at sundrie places, and at last I heard of him expressedly, for the day before I came to the Palsgraues Court, he was there e
                        •…
                     ecuted for a robbery with Dicke Droom, yea euen in sight of his Brother, and notwithstanding the fauour that hee is in there, such seuere execution of iustice is there administred.
               
               
                  S
                        •…
                     erus.
                  It is a happy common wealth where Iustic
                        •…
                      may be ministred with seueritie, and where no mediacions or sutes may wrest the sentence of the Lawe.
               
               
                  Fi
                        •…
                     us.
                  When I had there recoyued these heauy newes, I tooke letters of dispatch and aduertisement from Philomusus to his Father, &amp; crossed ouer the Countrey towards Geneua. And long before I came thether Phylosarchus had bin there (for fornication) whipped openly three seuerall dayes in the market, and was banished the Towne with great infamie, notwithstanding that his Brother Phylotimus was an earnest suter vnto the congregation for him. When I perceyued that none other issue could be had of my trauaile, I tooke letters from Phylotimus, and sought no further after Phylosarchus, but thought my duty first to aduertise my maister of the certainty, and by my way homewardes I ouertooke this good fellowe Ambidexter in such aray as you sée, and haue brought him with me to abide such punishment as the worthy Markgraue here and other magistrates shall thinke meete for him.
               
               
                  Ambidexter.
                  Oh Sir be good vnto me and pardon this offence.
               
               
                  Seu
                        •…
                     .
                  Pardon? Nay surely thou rather deseruest

death, for it séemeth vnto me, that these young men had not so lightly gone astray, had it not bin through the helpe of thée and such as thou art, such lewde seruauntes as thou art, are the casting away of many toward young personages, and therefore since thy good happe hath retourned thée hether, thou shalt with the rest serue as an example to all seruaunts. But thou canst tell what is become of Phylosarchus?
                  
               
               
                  Ambidexter.
                  He was so sore whipped that I feare hée be dead. I lefte him in a village fyue leagues distant from Geneua, so sore that he was not able to stir either hande or foote.
               
               
                  Seuerus.
                  Well Master Gnomaticus, since onley this fellow is recouered, I think méete to hold this course of iustice, he together with Master Eccho shall bee whyped aboute the Towne three seuerall market dayes, with papers declaring their faults set vpon their heds, and afterwards they shalbe banished the Citie, vppon payne of death neuer to returne, &amp; Mistresse Lamia with her Aunt shall likewyse be set on the Cucking stoole in publique thrée market daies, &amp; then to be banished the Towne also.
               
               
                  Gnomaticus.
                  Surely you haue well deuised, and I besech you Sir vouchsafe to assist mee in comforting the wofull Parents Phylopaes and Phylocalus, who I dare say will be so sorowfull for these tidinges, that it shall bee harde to perswade them to patience.
               
               
                  Seuerus.
                  It is but a reasonable request, &amp; I will moste gladly accompany you, go we togethers, and thou Fidus hast well deserued thy freedome, with a better turne for thy faythfull seruice in this behalfe, and I wilbe a meane vnto thy Maister that thou maist bee considered accordingly.
               
               
                  Seuerus.
                  I thanke you Sir. My Masters, the common saying is clap your handes, but the circumstance of this 
                        •…
                     
                     full tragicall comedie considered, I may say iustly vnto

you wring your handes, neuerthelesse I leaue it to your discretion.
               
               Finis.
            
         
      
      
         
            Epilogus.
            
               WE liue to learne, for so Sainct Paule doth teach,VVhat soeuer is written is written for our learning.
               
               and all that is, is doone for our auaile:
               Both good and bad, may be the wisemans leach,
               The good may serue, to make him beare like sayle,
               The bad to shun, the faults wherin they fayle.
               Good wyndes and bad, may serue in sundry sorte,
               To bring our barkes, into some pleasant porte.
            
            
               Who liste to learne, what dilligence may do,
               what humble minds, by studies may attayne,
               Let him behold, these younger brethren two,
               Whose wits at first, did séeme to bee but playne,
               Yet as you see, at last they got with payne,
               The golden fléese, of grace and cunning Skyll,
               Before the rest which folowed wanton will.
            
            
               And such as brag, of quicke capacitie,
               Or thinke the field, is woone withouten blowes,
               Let them behold, the youthfull vanitie:
               O
                     •…
                   th'elder twayne, 
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     •…
                  ncies lightly chose,
               To séeke delight, in garish grounde that growes.
               Yet had by hart, their masters wordes in hast:
               But thinges sone got, are lost againe as fast.
            
            
               For proofe whereof, behold how soone they fell,
               From vertues path, to treade in vices tracks,
               
                  And therwithall, (I pray you marke it well)
               Their falles were foule, they fell vpon their backs.
               Which gaue their bones, so many brusing cracks:
               That afterwardes, they neuer rose again
                     •…
                  ,
               Till shamefull death, did ende their greuous payne.
            
            
               Who falles on face, hath elbowes hands and all,
               To saue himselfe, and therwith eke to rise:
               To fall on backe, betokens such a fall,
               As cannot rise againe in any wi
                     •…
                  e▪
               
               For when he falls, his face wide open lies,
               To euery blowe: and cannot fend the same,
               Such falles found they, which brought them sone to shame
            
            
               And in meane while, their Brethren rose as fast,
               Much like the snaile, which clymes the Castle wall,
               With easie steppes▪ when souldiers do
                     •…
                  ne be cast,
               With furious force, and many a hedlong fall.
               Assaultes are hotte, but yet if therewithall,
               Some temperance, and pollyey be vsed,
               They winne those fortes, which hotter heades refused.
            
            
               I meane but this: you sée the younger twaine,
               (Because they did in vertue take delight)
               They clombe at last (and that with pleasaunt paine,)
               To honours Court, wherein their place was pight.
               You sée againe, their Brethren (by delight,
               In fi
                     •…
                  thy lust, selfe loue, and such like nio)
               Did fall as fast, to shamefull death and wo.
            
            
               You sée the bend, for faithfulnesse made frée,
               You sée the frée, for doublenesse disdaind:
               You sée the whippe, the cucke stoole, and the trée,
               Are thought rewardes, for such as vice hath staind:
               You s
                     •…
                  e that right, which euer more hath raignd,
               
                  And iustice both: do kéepe their places still,
               To cherish good, and eke to punish ill.
            
            
               These thinges my muse, did meane to make you knowe.
               By proofe in acte, of that which you haue séene
               These thinges my muse, thought méete to set in showe,
               But otherwyse, then common wont hath bene.
               This christall glasse I polisht faire and cléene,
               For euery man, that list his faultes to mend,
               This was my mind, and t
                     •…
                  s I make an end.
            
            Finis.
         
         
            ¶ IMPRINTED▪ AT London in Fleetestreate at the signe of the Faulcon by Henry Middleton, for Christopher Barker. Anno Domini. 1575.
            
         
      
   

