
   
      
         
            The tragedie of Antonie. Doone into English by the Countesse of Pembroke
            Marc Antoine. English
            Garnier, Robert, 1544-1590.
         
         
            
               1595
            
         
         Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01502
            STC 11623
            ESTC S105701
            99841427
            99841427
            6008
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01502)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6008)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 243:11)
         
         
            
               
                  The tragedie of Antonie. Doone into English by the Countesse of Pembroke
                  Marc Antoine. English
                  Garnier, Robert, 1544-1590.
                  Pembroke, Mary Sidney Herbert, Countess of, 1561-1621.
               
               [112] p.   
               
                  [By P. Short] for William Ponsonby,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  1595.
               
               
                  A translation of: Garnier, Robert.  Marc Antoine.
                  Colophon reads "Printed at London by P.S. for William Ponsonby. 1595."; printer's name from STC.
                  Signatures: A-G.
                  The last leaf is blank.
                  Running title reads: Antonius.
                  First published with Philippe de Mornay's "A discourse of life and death", 1592.
                  Variant: title page has "Done into englishe".
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Antonius, Marcus, 83?-30 B.C. --  Drama.
            
         
      
      
         
            2002-05
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2002-06
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2002-07
            Judith SiefringSampled and proofread
         
            2002-07
            Judith SiefringText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2002-08
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE
TRAGEDIE OF
Antonie.
            Doone into English by the
Countesse of
Pembroke
            Imprinted at London for William
Ponsonby 1595.
         
         
            
            
            ¶The Argument.
            
               AFTER the ouerthrowe
of Brutus
and Cassius, the
libertie of Rome
being now vtterly
oppressed, and the
Empire setled in
the hands of Octauius Caesar and
Marcus Antonius, (who for knitting
a straiter bonde of amitie betweene
them, had taken to wife Octauia the
sister of Caesar) Antonius vndertooke
a iourney agàinst the Parthians, with
intent to regaine on them the honor
won by them from the Romanes, at the
discomfiture and slaughter of Crassus.
But comming in his iourney into Siria
the places renewed in his remembrāce

the long intermittedloue of Cleopatra
Queene of Aegipte: who before
time had both in Cilicia and at Alexandria,
entertained him with all the
exquisite delightes and sumptuous pleasures,
which a great Prince and voluptuous
louer could to the vttermost desire.
Wherevpon omitting his enterprice,
he made his returne to Alexandria,
againe falling to his former loues,
without any regarde of his vertuous
wife Octauia, by whom neuertheles he
had excellent children. This occation
Octauius toke of taking armes against
him: &amp; preparing a mighty fleet, encoū
               tred
him at Actium, who also had assembled
to that place a great nūber of Gallies
of his own, beside, 60. which Cleopatra
brought with her from Aegipt,
But at the very beginning of the battel
Cleopatra with all her Gallies betooke
her to flight, which Antony seeing
could not but follow: by his departure

to Octauius the greatest victory which in
any Seabattell hath beene hard off. Which
he not negligent to pursue, followes them
the next spring and besiedgeth them with
in Alexandria, where Antony finding
al that he trusted to faile him, beginneth to
growe iealouse and to suspect Cleopatra.
She therevpon enclosed her selfe with two
of her women in a monumēt she had before
caused to be built, thence sends him worde
she was dead: which he beleeuing for truth,
gaue himselfe with his Sworde a deadly
woūd: but died not vntil a messenger came
frō 
               Cleopatra to haue him brought to her
to the tombe. Which she not daring to open
least she should bee made a prisoner to the
Romaines, &amp; carried in Caesars triumph,
cast downe a cord from an high window, by
the which (her womē helping her) she trussed
vp Antonius halfe dead, &amp; so got him
into the monumēt. The stage supposed alexandria:
the chorus first Egiptians, &amp; after
Romane souldiors: The history to be read at
large in Plutarch in the life of Antonius.
            
         
         
            
            ¶The Actors.
            
               Antonius.
               Cleopatra.
               Eras and
Charmiō. Cleopatras womē
                  
               
               Philostratus a Philosopher.
               
               Lucilius.
               Diomede Secretarie to Cleopatra.
               Octauius Caesar.
               Agrippa.
               Euphron, teacher of Cleopatras
children.
               
               Children of Cleopatra,
               Dircetus the Messenger.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            ANTONIVS
            
               
                  SInce cruell Heau'ns
against me obstinate,
               Since all mishappes
of the round engin doo
               Conspire my harme:
since mē, since powers diuine
               Aire, earth, and Sea
are all iniurious:
               And that my Queene her selfe, in whome I liu'd,
               The Idoll of my harte, doth me pursue;
               It's meete I dye. For her haue I forgone
               My Country, Caesar vnto warre prouok'd
               (For iust reuenge of Sisters wrong my wife,
               Who mou'de my Queene (ay me!) to iealousie)
               For loue of her, in her allurements caught
               Abandon'd life, I honor haue despisde,
               Disdain'd my freends, and of the statelye Rome
               Despoilde the Empire of her best attire,
               Contemn'd that power that made me so much fear'd,
               
                  
Aslaue become vnto her feeble face.
               O cruell, traitres, woman most vnkinde,
               Thou dost, forsworne, my loue and life betraie:
               And giu'st me vp to ragefull enemie,
               Which soone (ô foole!) will plague thy periurye.
               Yeelded Pelusium on this countries shore,
               Yeelded thou hast my Shippes and men of warre,
               That nought remaines (so destitute am I)
               But these same armes which on my back I weare.
               Thou should'st haue had them too, and me vnarm'de
               Yeelded to Caesar naked of defence.
               Which while I beare let Caesar neuer thinke
               Triumph of me shall his proud chariot grace
               Not thinke with me his glory to adorne,
               On me aliue to vse his victorie.
               Thou only Cleopatra triumph hast,
               Thou only hast my fredome seruile made,
               Thou only hast me vanquisht: not by force
               (For forste I cannot be) but by sweete baites
               Of thy eyes graces, which did gaine so fast
               
                  
vpon my libertie, that nought remain'd.
               None els henceforth, but thou my dearest Queene,
               Shall glorie in commaunding Antonie.
               
               Haue Caesar fortune and the Gods his freends,
               To him haue Ioue and fatall sisters giuen
               The Scepter of the earth: he neuer shall
               Subiect my life to his obedience.
               But when that death, my glad refuge, shall haue
               Bounded the course of my vnstedfast life,
               And frosen corps vnder a marble colde
               Within tombes bosome widdowe of my soule:
               Then at his will let him it subiect make:
               Then what he will let Caesar doo with me:
               Make me limme after limme be rent: make me
               My buriall take in sides of Thracian wolte.
               Poore Antonie! alas what was the day,
               The daies of losse that gained thee thy loue!
               Wretch Antonie! since Maegaera pale
               With Snakie haires enchain'd thy miserie.
               The fire thee burnt was neuer Cupids fire
               
                  
(For Cupid beares not such a mortall brand)
               It was some furies torch, Orestes torche,
               Which somtimes burnt his mother-murdering soule
               (When wandring madde, rage boiling in his bloud,
               He sled his fault which folow'd as he fled)
               kindled within his bones by shadow pale
               Of mother slaine return'd from Stygian lake.
               
                  Antony, poore Antony! since that daie
               Thy olde good hap did farre from thee retire.
               Thy vertue dead: thy glory made aliue
               So ofte by martiall deeds is gone in smoke:
               Since then the Baies so well thy forehead knewe
               To Venus mirtles yeelded haue their place:
               Trumpets to pipes: field tents to courtly bowers:
               Launces and Pikes to daunces and to feastes.
               Since then, ô wretch! in stead of bloudy warres
               Thou shouldst haue made vpon the Parthian Kings
               For Romain honor filde by Crassus foile,
               Thou threw'st thy Curiace off, and fearfull healme,
               With coward courage vnto Aegipts Queene
               
                  
In haste to runne, about her necke to hang
               Languishing in her armes thy I doll made:
               In summe giuen vp to Cleopatras eies
               Thou breakest at length frō thence, as one encharm'd
               Breakes from th'enchaunter that him strongly helde.
               For thy first reason (spoyling of their force
               the poisned cuppes of thy faire Sorceres)
               Recur'd thy sperit: and then on euery side
               Thou mad'st again the earth with Souldiours swarme
               All Asia hidde: Euphrates bankes do tremble
               To see at once so many Romanes there
               Breath horror, rage, and with a threatning eye
               In mighty squadrons crosse his swelling streames.
               Nought seene but horse, and fier sparkling armes:
               Nought heard but hideous noise of muttring troups,
               The Parth, the Mede, abandoning their goods
               Hide them for feare in hilles of Hircanie,
               
               Redoubting thee. Then willing to besiege
               The great Phraate head of Media,
               
               Thou campedst at her walles with vaine assault,
               
                  
Thy engins fit (mishap!) not thither brought,
               So long thou stai'st, so long thou dost thee rest,
               So long thy loue with such things nourished
               Reframes, reformes it selfe and stealingly
               Retakes his force and rebecomes more great.
               For of thy Queene the lookes, the grace, the words,
               Sweetnes, alurements, amorous delights,
               Entred againe thy soule, and day and night,
               In watch, in sleepe, her Image follow'd thee:
               Not dreaming but of her, repenting still
               That thou for warre hadst such a goddes left.
               Thou car'st no more for Parth, nor Parthian bow,
               Sallies, assaults, encounters, shocks, alarmes,
               For ditches, rampiers, wards, entrenched grounds:
               Thy only care is sight of Nilus streames,
               Sight of that face whose gilefull semblant doth
               (Wandring in thee) infect thy tainted hart.
               Her absence thee besottes: each hower, each hower
               Of staie, to thee impatient seemes an age.
               Enough of conquest, praise thou deem'st enough,
               
                  
If soone enough the bristled fields thou see
               Of fruitfull Aegipt, and the stranger floud
               Thy Queenes faire eyes (another Pharos) lights.
               Returned loe, dishonoured, despisde,
               In wanton loue a woman thee misleades
               Sunke in foule sinke: meane while respecting nought
               Thy wife Octauia and her tender babes,
               Of whome the long contempt against thee whets
               The sword of Caesar now thy Lord become.
               Lost thy great Empire, all those goodly townes
               Reuerenc'd thy name as rebells now thee leaue:
               Rise against thee, and to the ensignes flocke
               Of conqu'ring Caesar, who enwalles thee round
               Cag'd in thy hold, scarse maister of thy selfe,
               Late maister of so many Nations.
               Yet, yet, which is of griefe exrreamest griefe,
               Which is yet of mischiefe highest mischiefe,
               It's Cleopatra alas! alas, it's she,
               It's she augments the torment of thy paine,
               Betraies thy loue, thy life alas!) betraies,
               
                  
                  Caesar to please, whose grace she seekes to gaine:
               With thought her crowne to saue and fortune make
               Onely thy foe which common ought haue beene.
               If her I alwaies lou'd, and the first flame
               Of her heart-killing loue shall burne me last:
               Iustly complaine I she disloyall is,
               Nor constant is, euen as I constant am,
               To comfort my mishap, despising me
               No more, then when the heauens fauour'd me.
               But ah! by nature women wau' ring are,
               Each moment changing and rechanging mindes.
               Vnwise, who blinde in them, thinkes loyaltie
               Euer to finde in beauties companie.
            
            
               Chorus.
               The boyling tempest still
               makes not Sea waters fome:
               nor still the Northern blast
               disquiets quiet streames:
               
                  
Nor who his chest to fill
               sayles to the morning beames,
               on waues winde tosseth fast
               still kepes his ship from home.
               Nor Ioue still downe doth cast
               inflam'd with bloudie ire
               on man, on tree, on hill,
               his darts of thundring fire.
               nor still the heat doth last
               on face of parched plaine.
               nor wrinkled colde doth still
               on frozen furrowes raigne.
               But still as long as we
               in this low world remaine,
               mishapps our daily mates
               our liues doe intertaine:
               and woes which beare no dates
               still pearch vpon our heads,
               none go but straight will be
               some greater in their steads.
               
                  
Nature made vs not free
               When first she made vs liue:
               When we began to be,
               To be began our woe:
               Which growing euermore
               As dying life doth growe,
               Do more and more vs greeue,
               And tire vs more and more.
               No stay in fading states,
               For more to height they retch,
               Their fellow miseries.
               The more to height do stretch.
               They cling euen to the crowne,
               And threatning furious wise
               From tirannizing pates
               Do often pull it downe.
               In vaine on waues vntride
               To shun them go we should
               To Scythes and Massagetes
               
               Who neere the Pole reside:
               
                  
In vaine to boiling sandes
               Which Phaebus battry beates,
               For with vs still they would
               Cut seas and compasse landes.
               The darknes no more sure
               To ioyne with heauy night:
               The light which guildes the days
               To follow Titan pure:
               No more the shadow light
               The body to ensue:
               Then wretchednes alwaies
               Vs wretches to pursue.
               O blest who neuer breath'd,
               Or whome with pittie mou'de,
               
                  Death from his cradle reau'de,
               And swadled in his graue:
               And blessed also he
               (As curse may blessing haue)
               Who low and liuing free
               No princes charge hath prou'de.
               
                  
By stealing sacred fire.
               
                  Prometheus then vnwise,
               prouking Gods to ire,
               the heape of ills did sturre,
               and sicknes pale and colde
               our ende which onward spurre,
               to plague our hands too bolde
               to filch the wealth of skies.
               In heauens hate since then
               of ill with ill enchain'd
               we race of mortall men
               ful fraught our brests haue borne
               and thousand thousand woes
               our heau'nly soules now thorne,
               which free before from those
               no! earthly passion pain'd.
               Warre and warrs bitter cheare
               now long time with vs staie,
               and feare of hated foe
               still still encreaseth sore:
               
                  
our harmes worse dayly grow,
               lesse yesterday they were
               then now, and will be more
               to morrow then to day.
            
         
         
            Act. 2.
            
               Philostratus.
               What horrible furie, what cruell rage,
               O Aegipt so extremely thee torments?
               Hast thou the Gods so angred by thy fault?
               Hast thou against them some such crime conceiu'd.
               That their engrained hand lift vp in threats
               They should desire in thy heart bloud to bathe?
               And that their burning wrath which noght cā quēch
               Should pittiles on vs still lighten downe?
               We are not hew'n out of the monst'rous masse
               Of Giantes those, which heauens wrack conspir'd:
               
                  Ixions race, false prater of his loues:
               
                  
Nor yet of him who fained lightnings found:
               Nor cruell Tantalus, nor bloudy Atreus,
               
               Whose cursed banquet for Thyestes plague
               Made the beholding Sunne for horrour turne
               His backe, and backward from his course returne:
               And hastning his wing-footed horses race
               Plunge him in sea for shame to hide his face:
               While sulleine night vpon the wondring world
               For mid-daies light her starrie mantle cast.
               But what we be, what euer wickednesse
               By vs is done, Alas! with what more plagues,
               More eager torments could the Gods declare
               To heauen and earth that vs they hatefull holde?
               With souldiors, strangers, horrible in armes
               Our land is hidde, our people drown'd in teares.
               But terror here and horror, nought is seene:
               And present death prising our life each hower.
               Hard at our ports and at our porches waites
               Our conquering foe: harts faile vs, hopes are dead:
               Our Queene laments: and this great Emperour
               
                  
Somtime (would now they did) whom worlds did fear
               Abandoned, betraid, now mindes no more
               But from his euils by hast'ned death to passe.
               Come! you poore people ti'rde with ceasles plaints
               With teares and sighes make morunfull sacrfice
               On Isis altars: not our selues to saue,
               But soften Caesar and him piteous make
               To vs, his praie: that so his lenitie
               May change our death into captiuitie.
               Strange are the euils the fates on vs haue brought,
               O but alas! how far more strange the cause!
               Loue, loue (alas, who euer would haue thought?)
               Hath lost this Realme inflamed with his fire.
               Loue, playing loue, which men say kindles not
               But in soft hearts, hath ashes made our townes.
               And his sweet shafts, with whose shot none are kill'd,
               Which vlcer not, with deaths our lands haue fill'd,
               Such was the bloudie, murdring, hellish loue
               Possest thy hart faire false guest Priams sonne,
               Firing a brand which after made to burne
               
                  
The Troian towers by Graecians ruinate.
               By this loue, Priam, Hector, Troilus,
               
               
                  Memnon, Deiphaebus, Glancus, thousands mo.
               Whome redd Scamanders armor clogged streames
               Roll'd into Seas, before their dates are dead.
               So plaguie he, so many tempests raiseth,
               So murdring he, so many Citties raiseth,
               When insolent, blinde, lawles, orderles,
               With made delights our sence he entertaines.
               All knowing Gods our wracks did vs fortell
               By signes in earth, by signes in starry Sphaeres,
               Which should haue mou'd vs, had not destinie
               With too strong hand warped our miserie.
               The Comets flaming through the scat'red clouds
               With fiery beames, most like vnbroaded haires:
               The fearfull dragon whistling at the bankes:
               And holy Apis ceasles bellowing
               (As neuer erst) and shedding endles teares:
               Bloud raining down frō heau'n in vnknow'n showers:
               Our Gods darke faces ouer cast with woe,
               
                  
And dead mens Ghosts appearing in the night.
               Yea euen this night while all the Cittie stood
               Opprest with terror, horror, seruile feare,
               Deepe silence ouer all: the sounds were heard
               Of diuers songs, and diuerse instruments,
               Within the voide of aire: and howling noise,
               Such as madde Bacchus priests in Bacchus feasts
               On Nisa make: and (seem'd) the company,
               Our Cittie lost, went to the enemie.
               So we forsaken both of Gods and men,
               So are we in the mercy of our foes:
               And we henceforth obedient must become
               To lawes of them who haue vs ouercome.
            
            
               Chorus.
               Lament we our mishaps,
               Drowne we with teares our woe:
               For Lamentable happes
               Lamented easie growe:
               
                  
and much lesse torment bring
               then when they first did spring.
               We want that wofull song,
               wherwith wood-musiques Queen
               doth ease her woes, among,
               fresh springtimes bushes greene,
               on pleasant branch alone
               renewing auntient mone.
               We want that monefull sound,
               that pratling Progne makes
               on fields of Thracian ground,
               or streames of Thracian lakes:
               to empt her brest of paine
               for Itys by her slaine.
               Though Halcyons do still,
               bewailing Ceyx lot,
               the Seas with plainings fill
               which his dead limmes haue got,
               not euer other graue
               then tombe of waues to haue:
               
                  
And though the bird in death
               that most Meander loues:
               so sweetly sighes his breath
               when death his fury proues,
               as almost softs his heart,
               and almost blunts his dart:
               Yet all the plaints of those,
               nor all their tearfull larmes,
               cannot content our woes,
               nor serue to waile the harmes,
               in soule which we, poore we.
               to feele enforced be.
               Nor they of Phaebus bredd
               in teares can doo so well,
               they for their brother shedd,
               who into Padus fell,
               rash guide of chariot cleere
               surueiour of the yeare.
               Nor she whom heau'nly powers
               to weping rocke did turne,
               
                  
whose teares distill in showers,
               and shew she yet doth mourne,
               wherewith his toppe to Skies
               mount Sipylus doth rise.
               Nor weping drops which flowe
               from barke of wounded tree,
               that Mirrhas shame doth showe
               with ours compar'd may be,
               to quench her louing fire
               who durst embrace her fire.
               Nor all the howlings made
               on Cybels sacred hill
               By Eunukes of her trade,
               Who Atys, Atys still
               with doubled cries resound,
               which Eccho makes rebound.
               Our plaints no limits stay,
               nor more then do our woes:
               both infinitely straie
               and neither measure knowes
               
                  
In mea sure let them plaine:
               Who measnr'd griefes sustaine.
            
            Cleopatrra. Eras. Charmton. Diomede.
            
               Cleopatra.
               That I haue thee betraide, deare Antonie,
               
               My life, my soule, my sunne? I had such thought?
               That I haue thee betraide my Lord, my King?
               That I would breake my vowed faith to thee?
               I aue thee? deceiue thee? yeelde thee to the rage
               Of mightie foe? I euer had that hart?
               Rather sharpe lightning lighten on my head:
               Rather may I to deepest mischiefe fall:
               Rather the opened earth deuoure me:
               Rather fierce Tigers feed them on my flesh:
               Rather, ô rather let our Nilus send,
               To swallow me quicke, some weeping Crocodile.
               
               And didst thou then suppose my royall heart
               
                  
Had hatcht, thee to ensnare, a faithles loue?
               And changing minde, as Fortune changed cheare,
               I would weake thee, to winne the stronger, loose?
               O wretch! ô caitiue! ô too cruell happe!
               And did not I sufficient losse sustaine
               Loosing my Realme, loosing my libertie,
               My tender of-spring, and the ioyfull light
               Of beamy Sunne, and yet, yet loosing more
               Thee Antony my care, if I loose not
               What yet remain'd? thy loue alas! thy loue,
               More deare then Scepter, children, freedome, ligh
                     •
                  
               
               So readie I to row in Charons barge,
               Shall leese the joy of dying in thy loue:
               So the sole comfort of my miserie
               To haue one tombe with thee is me bereft.
               So I in shady plaines shall plaine alone,
               Not (as I hop'd) companion of thy mone,
               O height of griefe! Eras why with Continuall cries
               Your griefull harmes doo you exasperate?
               Torment your selfe with murthering complaints;
               
                  
Straine your weake brest so ost, so vehemently?
               Water with teares this faire al ablaster?
               With sorrowes sting so many beauties wound?
               Come of so many Kings want you the hart
               Brauely, stoutly, this tempest to resist?
            
            
               Cl.
               My eu'lls are wholy vnsupportable,
               No humain force can them withstand, but death.
            
            
               Eras.
               To him that striues nought is impossible.
            
            
               Cl.
               In striuing lyes no hope of my mishapps.
            
            
               Eras.
               All things do yeelde to force of louely face.
            
            
               
                  
                     ••
                  
               
               My face too louely caus'd my wretched case.
               My face hath so entrap'd, so cast vs downe,
               That for his conquest Caesar may it thanke,
               Causing that Antonie one army lost
               The other wholy did to Caesar yeld.
               For not induring (so his amorouse sprite
               Was with my beautie fir'de) my shamefull flight,
               Soone as he saw from ranke wherein he stoode
               In hottest fight, my Gallies making saile:
               Forgetfull of his charg (as if his soule
               
                  
Vnto his Ladies soule had beene enchain'd)
               He left his men, who so couragiously
               Did leaue their liues to gaine him victorie.
               And carelesse both of fame and armies losse
               My oared Gallies follow'd with his ships
               Companion of my flight, by this base parte
               Blasting his former flourishing renowne.
            
            
               Eras.
               Are you therefore cause of his ouerthrow?
            
            
               Cl.
               I am sole cause: I did it, only I.
            
            
               Er.
               Feare of a woman troubled so his sprite?
            
            
               Cl.
               Fire of his loue was by my feare enflam'd.
            
            
               Er.
               And should he then to warre haue led a Queene?
            
            
               Cl.
               Alas! this was not this offence, but mine.
               
                  Antony (ay me! who else so braue a chiefe!)
               Would not I should haue taken Seas with him:
               But would haue lest me fearefull woman farre
               From common hazard of the doubtfull warre.
               O that I had beleeu'd! now, now of Rome
               
               All the great Empire at our beck should bende.
               All should obey, the vagabonding Scythes,
               
               
                  
The feared Germaines, back-shooting Parthians,
               
               Wandring Numidians, Brittons farre remou'd,
               And tawny nations scorched with the Sunne.
               But I car'd not: so was my soule possest,
               (To my great harme) with burning iealousie:
               Fearing least in my absence Antony
               
               Should leauing me retake Octauia.
               
            
            
               Char.
               Such was the rigour of your desteny.
            
            
               Cl.
               Such was my errour and obstinacie.
            
            
               Ch.
               But since Gods would not, could you do withall?
            
            
               Cl.
               Alwaies from Gods good haps, not harms, do fall.
            
            
               Ch.
               And haue they not all power on mens affaires?
            
            
               Cl.
               They neuer bow so low, as worldly cares.
               But leaue to mortall men to be dispos'd
               Freely on earth what euer mortall is.
               If we therein sometimes some faults commit,
               We may them not to their high maiesties,
               But to our selues impute; whose passions
               Plunge vs each day in all afflictions.
               Wherwith when we our soules do thorned feele,
               
                  
Flatt'ring our selues we say they dest'nies are:
               That gods would haue it so, and that our care
               Could not empeach but that it must be so.
            
            
               Char.
               Things here below are in the heau'ns begot,
               Before they be in this our wordle borne:
               And neuer can our weaknesse turne awry
               The stailesse course of powerfull destenie.
               Nought here force, reason, humaine prouidence,
               Holie deuotion, noble bloud preuailes:
               And Ioue himselfe whose hand doth heauens rule,
               Who both to gods and men as King Commands,
               Who earth (our firme support) with plenty stores,
               Mouses aire and sea with twinckling of his eie,
               Who all can doe, yet neuer can vndoe
               What once hath beene by their hard lawes decreed.
               When Troyan walles, great Neptunes workmanship.
               Enuiron'd were with Greekes, and Fortunes whele
               Doubtfull ten yeares now to the campe did turne,
               And now againe towards the towne return'd.
               How many times did force and fury swell
               
                  
In Hectors veines egging him to the spoile
               Of conquer'd foes, which at his blowes did fly,
               As fearefull sheepe at feared wolues approch:
               To saue (in vaine: for why? it would not be)
               Poore walles of Troy from aduersaries rage,
               Who died them in bloud, and cast to ground
               Heap'd them with bloudie burning carcases.
               No, Madame, thinke, that if the ancient crowne
               Of your progenitors that Nilus rul'd,
               Force take from you; the Gods haue will'd it so,
               To whome oft times Princes are odious.
               They haue to euery thing an end ordain'd;
               All worldly greatnes by them bounded is:
               Some sooner, later some, as they thinke best:
               None their decree is able to infringe.
               But, which is more, to vs disastred men
               Which subiect are in all things to their will,
               Their will is hid: nor while we liue, we know
               How, or how long we must in life remaine.
               Yet must we not for that feede on dispaire,
               
                  
And make vs wretched ere we wretched be:
               But alwaies hope the best, euen to the last,
               That from our selues the mischiefe may not grow.
               Then, Madame, helpe your selfe, leaue of in time
               
                  Antonies wracke, left it your wracke procure:
               Retire you from him, saue from wrathfull rage
               Of angry Caesar both your Realme and you.
               You see him lost, so as your amitie
               Vnto his euills can yeeld no more reliefe.
               You see him ruin'd, so as your support
               No more henceforth can him with comfort raise.
               With-draw you from the storme: persist not still
               To loose your selfe: this royall diademe
               Regaine of Caesar.
               
            
            
               Cl.
               Sooner shining light
               Sall leaue the day, and darknes leaue the night:
               Sooner moist currents of tempestuous seas
               Shall waue in heauen, and the nightly troopes
               Of starres shall shine within the foming waues,
               Then I thee, Antony, Leaue in deepe distres.
               I am with thee, be it thy worthy soule
               
                  
Lodge in thy brest, or from that lodging parte
               Crossing the ioyles lake to take her place
               In place prepared for men Demy-gods.
               Liue, if thee please, if life be lothsome die:
               Dead and aliue, Antony, thou shalt see
               Thy princesse follow thee, folow, and lament,
               Thy wrack, no lesse her owne then was thy weale.
            
            
               Char.
               What helps his wrack this euer-lasting loue?.
            
            
               Cl.
               Help, or help not, such must, such ought I proue.
            
            
               Ch.
               Ill done to loose your selfe, and to no end.
            
            
               Cl.
               How ill thinke you to follow such a frend?
            
            
               Ch.
               But this your loue nought mitigates his praine.
            
            
               Cl.
               Without this loue I should be inhumaine.
            
            
               Ch,
               Inhumaine he, who his owne death pursues.
            
            
               Cl.
               Not inhumaine who miseries eschues.
            
            
               Ch.
               Liue for your sonnes.
            
            
               Cl.
               Nay for their father die.
            
            
               Ch.
               Hardharted mother!
            
            
               Cl.
               Wife kindhearted I.
            
            
               Ch.
               Then will you them depriue of royall right?
            
            
               Cl,
               Do I depriue them? no, it's dest'nies might.
            
            
               Ch.
               Do you not them depriue of heritage,
               
                  
That giue them vp to aduersaries hands,
               A man forsaken fearing to forsake,
               Whome such huge numbers hold inuironned?
               T'abandon one gainst whome the frowning world
               Banded with Caesar makes conspiring warre.
            
            
               Cl.
               The lesse ought I to leaue him lest of all.
               A frend in most distresse should most assift.
               If that when Antonie great and glorious
               His legions led to drinke Euphrates streames,
               So many Kings in traine redoubting him;
               In triumph rais'd as high as highest heau'n;
               Lord-like disposing as him pleased best,
               The wealth of Greece, the wealth of Asia:
               
               In that faire fortune had I him exchaung'd
               For Caesar, then, men would haue counted me
               Faithles, vnconstant, light: but now the storme,
               And blustring tempest driuing on his face,
               Readie to drowne, Alas! what would they say?
               What would himselfe in Platos mansion say?
               If, I whome alwaies more then life he lou'de,
               
                  
If I, Who am his heart, who was his hope,
               Leaue him, forsake him (and perhaps in vaine)
               Weakly to please who him hath ouerthrowne?
               Not light, vnconstant, faith lesse should I be,
               But vile, forsworne, of treachrous cruelty.
            
            
               Ch.
               Crueltie to shunne you selfe-cruell are:
            
            
               Cl.
               Selfe-cruell him from cruelty to spare.
            
            
               Ch.
               Our first affection to ourselfe is due.
            
            
               Cl.
               He is my selfe.
            
            
               Ch.
               Next it extends vnto
               Our children, frends, and to our country soile.
               And you for some respect of wiuely loue,
               (Albee scarce wiuely) loose your natiue land,
               Your children, frends, and (which is more) your life,
               With so strong charmes doth loue bewitch our witts:
               So fast in vs this fire once kindled flames.
               Yet if his harme by yours redresse might haue,
            
            
               Cl.
               With mine it may be clos'de in darksome graue.
            
            
               Ch.
               And that, as Alcest to her selfe vnkind,
               You might exempt him from the lawes of death.
               But he is sure to die: and now his sword
               
                  
Already moisted is in his warme bloud,
               Helples for any succour you can bring
               Against deaths sting, which he must shortly feele.
               Then let your loue be like the loue of olde
               Which Carian Queene did nourish in hir heart
               Of hir Mausolus: builde for him a tombe
               Whose statelinesse a wonder new may make.
               Let him, let him haue sumptuous funeralls:
               Let graue thereon the horror of his fights:
               Let earth be buri'd with vnburied heaps.
               Frame their Pharsaly, and discoulour'd stream's
               Of deepe Enipeus: frame the grassie plaine,
               Which lodg'd his campe at siege of Mutina.
               
               Make all his combats, and couragious acts:
               And yearely plaies to his praise institute:
               Honor his memory: with doubled care
               Breed and bring vp the children of you both
               In Caesars grace: who as a noble Prince
               Will leaue them Lords of this most glorious realme.
            
            
               Cl.
               What shame were that? ah Gods! what infamie?
               
                  
With Antony in his good haps to share,
               And ouerliue him dead: deeming enough
               To shed some teares vpon a widdow tombe?
               The after-liuers iustly might report
               That I him only for his Empire lou'd
               And high estate: and that in hard estate
               I for another did him lewdly leaue?
               Like to those birds wafted with wandring wings.
               From foraine lands in spring-time here arriue:
               And liue with vs so long as Somers heate,
               And their foode lasts, then seeke another soile.
               And as we see with ceaslesse fluttering
               Flocking of seelly flies a brownish cloud
               To vintag'd wine yet working in the tonne:
               Not parting thence while they sweete liquor taste:
               After, as smoke, all vanish in the aire,
               And of the swarme not one so much' appeare.
            
            
               Eras.
               By this sharpe death what profit can you winne?
            
            
               Cl.
               I neither gaine nor profit seeke therein.
            
            
               Er.
               What praise shall you of after-ages get?
            
            
               
               Cl.
               Nor praise, nor Glory in my cares are set.
            
            
               Eras.
               What other end ought you respect, then this?
            
            
               Cl.
               My only end my onele duty is.
            
            
               Eras.
               Your dutie must vpon some good be founded?
            
            
               Cl.
               On vertue it, the onely good, is grounded.
            
            
               Er.
               What is that Vertue?
               
            
            
               Cl.
               That which vs beseemes.
            
            
               Er.
               Outrage our selues? who that beseeming deemes?
            
            
               Cl.
               Finish I will my sorrowes dieng thus.
            
            
               Er.
               Minish you will your glories doing thus.
            
            
               Cl.
               Good frends I pray you seeke not to reuoke
               My fix'd intent of folowing Antony.
               
               I will die. I will die: must not his life,
               His life and death by mine be followed?
               Meane while, deare sisters, liue: and while you liue,
               Do often honor to our loued Tombes.
               Straw them with flowers: and sometimes happely
               The tender thought of Antony your Lord
               And me poore soule to teares shall you inuite,
               And our true loues to dolefull voice commend.
            
            
               Ch.
               And thinke you Madame, we from you will part?
               
                  
Thinke you alone to feele deaths ougly darte?
               Thinke you to leaue vs? and that the same sunne
               Shall see at once you dead, and vs aliue?
               Weele die with you: and Clotho pittilesse
               Shall vs with you in hellish boate imbarque:
            
            
               Cl.
               Ah liue, I praie you: this disastred woe
               Which racks my heart, alone to me belongs:
               My lot longs not to you: seruants to be
               No shame, no harme to you, as is to me.
               Liue sisters, liue, and seing his suspect
               Hath causlesse me in sea of sorrowes drown'd,
               And that I cannot liue, if so I would,
               Nor yet would leaue this life, if so I could,
               Without his loue: procure me, Diomed,
               
               That gainst poore me he be no more incensd.
               Wrest out of his conceit that harmefull doubt,
               That since his wracke he hath of me conceiu'd
               Thogh wrong conceiu'd: witnes you reuerent Gods,
               Barking Anubis, Apis bellowing.
               Tell him, my soule burning, impatient,
               
                  
Forlorne with loue of him, for certaine seale
               Ofher true loialtie my corpse hath left,
               Tencrease of dead the number numberlesse,
               Go then, and if as yet he me bewaile,
               If yet for me his heart one sigh fourth breathe
               Blest shall I be: and far with more content
               Depart this world, where so I me torment.
               Meane season vs let this sad tombe enclose,
               Attending here till death conlude our woes.
            
            
               Diom.
               I will obey your will.
            
            
               Cl.
               So the desert
               The Gods repay of thy true faithfull heart.
            
            
               Diomed.
               And is't not pittie, Gods, ah Gods of heau'n
               To see from loue such hatefull frutes to spring?
               And is't not pittie that this firebrand so
               Laies waste the trophes of Phillippi fieldes?
               Where are those sweet alluremēts, those sweet lookes,
               Which gods the ̄ selues right hart sick wuld haue made
               
                  
What doth that beautie, rarest guift of heau'n,
               Wonder of earth? Alas! what do those eies?
               And that sweete voice all Asia vnderstoode,
               And sunburnt Africke wide in deserts spred?
               Is their force dead? haue they no further power?
               Can not by them Octauius be suppriz'd?
               Alas! if Ioue in middst of all his ire,
               With thunderbolt in hand some land to plague,
               Had cast his eies on my Queene, out of hand
               His Plaguing bolte had falne out of his hand:
               Fire of his wrath into vaine smoke should turne,
               And other fire within his brest should burne.
               Nought liues so faire. Nature by such a worke
               Her selfe, should seeme, in workmanship hath past.
               She is all heau'nly: neuer any man
               But seeing hir was rauish'd with her sight.
               The Allablaster couering of her face,
               The corall coullor hir two lips engraines,
               Her beamy eies, two Sunnes of this our world,
               Of hir faire haire the fine and flaming golde,
               
                  
Her braue streight stature, and her winning partes
               Are nothing else but fiers, fetters, dartes.
               Yet this is nothing th'enchaunting skilles
               Of her celestiall Sp'rite, hir training speach,
               Her grace, hir maiesty, and forcing voice,
               Whither she it with fingers speach consorte,
               Or hearing sceptred kings embassadors
               Answere to each in his owne language make.
               Yet now at neede it aides her not at all
               With all these beauties, so her sorrow stinges.
               Darkned with woe her only study is
               To weepe, to sigh, to seeke for lonelines.
               Careles of all, hir haire disordred hangs:
               Hir charming eies whence murthring looks did flie,
               Now riuers grown', whose wellspring anguish is,
               Do trickling wash the marble of hir face.
               Hir faire discouer'd brest with sobbing swolne
               Selfe cruell she still martirith with blowes,
               Alas! It's our ill hap, for if hir teares
               She would conuert into her louing charmes,
               
                  
To make a conquest of the conqueror,
               (As well she might, would she hir force imploie)
               She should vs saftie from these ills procure,
               Hir crowne to hir, and to hir race assure.
               Vnhappy he, in whome selfe-succour lies,
               Yet selfe-forsaken wanting succour dies.
            
            
               Chorus.
               O sweete fertile land, wherein
               
                  Phaebus did with breth inspire
               man who men did first begin,
               formed first of Nilus mire.
               whence of Artes the eldest kindes,
               earths most heauenly ornament,
               were as from their fountaine sent
               to enlight our misty mindes.
               whose grose sprite frō endles time
               as in darkned prison pente,
               neuer did to knowledge clime.
               
                  
Wher the Nile, our father good,
               father-like doth neuer misse
               yearely vs to bring such food,
               as to life required is:
               visiting each yeare this plaine,
               and with fat slime cou'ring it,
               which his seauen mouthes do spit,
               as the season comes againe.
               making therby greatest growe
               busie reapers ioyfull paine,
               when his flouds do highest flow.
               Wandring Prince of riuers thou,
               honor of the Aethiops lande,
               of a Lord and maister now
               thou a slaue in awe must stand.
               now of Tiber which is spred
               lesse in force, and lesse in fame
               reuerence thou must the name,
               whome all other riuers dread,
               for his children swolne in pride,
               
                  
who by conquest seeke to treade
               round this earth on euery side.
               Now thou must begin to send
               tribute of thy watry store,
               as sea pathes thy steps shall bend,
               yearely presents more and more.
               thy fat skumme, our fruitfull corne,
               pill'd from hence with theuish hāds
               all vncloth'd shal leaue our lands
               into forraine country borne.
               which puft vp with such a pray
               shall thereby the praise adorne
               of that scepter Rome doth sway.
               Nought thee helps thy hornes to hide
               far from hence in vnknown groūds,
               that thy waters wander wide,
               yerely breaking banks, and bounds.
               and that thy Skie-coullor'd brooks
               through a hundred peoples passe,
               drawing plots for trees and grasse
               
                  
with a thousand turn's and crookes.
               whome all weary of their way
               thy throats which in widenesse passe
               powre into their mother Sea.
               Nought so happie haplesse life
               
                  in this world as freedome findes:
               
               
                  nought wherin mor sparkes are rise
               
               
                  to inflame couragious mindes.
               
               
                  but if force must vs inforce
               
               
                  needes a yoke to vndergo,
               
               
                  vnder foraine yoke to go
               
               
                  Still it proues a bondage worse.
               
               
                  and doubled subiection
               
               
                  see we shall, and feele, and know
               
               
                  subiect to a stranger growne.
               
               From hence forward for a King,
               whose first being from this place
               should his brest by nature bring
               care of country to imbrace,
               We at surly face must quake
               
                  
of some Romaine madly bent:
               who our terrour to augment.
               his Proconsuls axe will shake.
               driuing with our Kings from hence
               our establish'd gouernment,
               iustice sword, and lawes defence.
               Nothing worldly of such might
               but more mighty Destiny,
               
               by swift Times vnbridled flight,
               makes in end his end to see.
               euery thing Time ouerthrowes,
               nought to end doth steadfast staie.
               his great sithe mowes all away
               as the stalke of tender rose.
               onely immortalitie
               of the heauens doth it oppose
               gainst his powrefull Deitie.
               
               One day there will come a day
               which shall quaile they fortunes flower
               and thee ruinde low shall laie
               
                  
in some barbarous Princes power.
               when the pittie-wanting fire
               shall, O Rome, thy beauties burne,
               and to humble ashes turne
               thy proud wealth and rich attire,
               those guilt roofes which turretwise,
               iustly making enuy mourne,
               threaten now to pearce Skies.
               As thy forces fill each land
               haruests making here and there,
               reaping all with rauening hand
               they find growing any where:
               from each land so to thy fall,
               multitudes repaire shall make,
               from the common spoile to take
               what to each mans shaire may fall.
               fingred all thou shalt behold:
               no iote left for tokens sake
               that thou wert so great of olde.
               Like vnto the ancient Troie
               
               
                  
whence deriu'd thy founders be,
               conqu'ring foe shall thee enioie,
               and a burning praie in thee.
               for within this turning ball
               this we see, and see each daie:
               all things fixed ends do staie,
               ends to first beginnings fall.
               &amp; that nought, how strong or strāge
               chaungeles doth endure alwaie,
               But endureth fatall change.
            
         
         
            M. Antonius. Lucilius.
            
               M. Ant.
               
                  Lucil. sole comfort of my bitter case,
               The only trust, the only hope I haue,
               In last despaire: Ah is not this the daie
               That death should me of life and loue bereaue?
               What waite I for that haue no refuge left,
               
                  
But am sole remnant of my fortune left?
               All leaue me, flie me: none, noe not of them
               Which of my greatnes greatest good receiu'd,
               Stands with my fall: they seeme as now asham'd
               That heretofore they did me ought regard:
               They draw them backe, shewing they folow'd me,
               Not to partake my harm's, but coozen me.
            
            
               Lu.
               In this our world nothing is stedfast found,
               In vaine he hopes, who here his hopes doth ground.
            
            
               An.
               Yet nought afflicts me, nothing killes me so,
               As that I so my Cleopatra see
               Practise with Caesar, and to him transport
               My flame, her loue, more deare then life to me.
            
            
               Lu.
               Beleeue it not: Too high a heart she beares,
               Too princely thoughts.
            
            
               An.
               Too wise a head she weare
               Too much enflam'd with greatnes, euermore
               Gaping for our great Empires gouerment.
            
            
               Lu.
               So long time you her constant loue haue tri'de.
            
            
               An.
               But still with me good fortune did abide.
            
            
               Lu.
               Her changed loue what token makes you know?
            
            
               
               An.
               
                  Pelusium lost, and Actian ouerthrow,
               Both by her fraud: my well appointed fleet,
               And trusty Souldiors in my quarrell arm'd,
               Whome she, false she, in stede of my defence,
               Came to perswade, to yelde them to my foe:
               Such honor Thyre done, such welcome giuen,
               Their long close talkes I neither knew, nor would,
               And trecherous wrong Alexas hath me donne,
               Witnes too well her periur'd loue to me.
               But you O Gods (if any faith regarde)
               With sharpe reuenge her faithlesse change reward.
            
            
               Lu.
               The dole she made vpon our ouerthrow,
               Her realme giuen vp for refuge to our men,
               Her poore attire when she deuoutly kept
               The solemne day of her natiuitie,
               Againe the cost and prodigall expence
               Shew'd when she did your birth day celebrate,
               Do plaine enough her heart vnfained proue,
               Equally toucht, you louing, as you loue.
            
            
               Ant.
               Well; be her loue to me or false, or true,
               
                  
Once in my soule a cureles wound I feele.
               I Ioue: nay burne in fire of her loue:
               Each day, each night hir Image haunts my minde,
               Her selfe my dreames: and still I tired am,
               And still I am with burning pincers nipt.
               Extreame my harme: yet sweeter to my sence
               Then boiling Torch of iealous torments fire:
               This griefe, nay rage, in me such sturre doth keepe,
               And thornes me still, both when I wake and sleepe.
               Take Caesar conquest, take my goods, take he
               Th'onor to be Lord of the earth alone,
               My sonnes, my life bent headlong to mishapps:
               No force, so not my Cleopatra take.
               So foolish I, I cannot her forget,
               Though better were I banisht her my thought.
               Like to the sicke whose throte the feauers fire
               Hath vehemently with thirstie drought enflam'd,
               Drinkes still, albee the drinke he still desires
               Be nothing else but fewell to his flame.
               He cannot rule himself: his health's respect
               
                  
Yealdeth to his distempered stomacks heate.
            
            
               Lu.
               Leaue of this loue, that thus renewes your woe.
            
            
               An.
               I do my best, but ah! can not do so.
            
            
               Lu.
               Thinke how you haue so braue a captaine bene,
               And now are by this vaine affection falne.
            
            
               An.
               The ceasles thought of my felicitie
               Plunges me more in this aduersitie.
               For nothing so a man in ill torments,
               As who to him his good state represents.
               This makes my rack, my anguish, and my woe
               Equall vnto the hellish passions growe,
               When I to mind my happie puisance call
               Which erst I had by warlike conquest wonne,
               And that good fortune which me neuer left,
               Which hard disastre now hath me bereft.
               With terror tremble all the world I made
               At my sole word, as Rushes in the streames
               At waters will: I conquer'd Italie,
               I conquer'd Rome, that nations so redoubt.
               I Bare (meane while besieging Mutina)
               
                  
Two consuls armies for my ruine brought.
               Bath'd in their bloud, by their deaths witnessing
               My force and skill in matters Martiall.
               To wreake thy vnkle, vnkind Caesar, I
               With bloud of enemies the bankes embru'd
               Of stain'd Enipeus, hindring his course
               Stopped with heapes of piled carcases:
               When Cassius and Brutus ill betide
               Marcht against vs, by vs twise put to flight,
               But by my sole conduct: for all the time
               
                  Caesar hart-sicke with feare and feauer lay.
               Who knowes it not? and how by euery one
               Fame of the fact was giu'n to me alone.
               There sprang the loue, the neuer changing loue,
               Wherin my heart hath since to yours bene bound:
               There was it, my Lucill, you Brntus sau'de,
               And for your Brutus Antony, you found.
               Better my hap in gaining such a frend,
               Then in subduing such an enimie.
               Now former vertue dead doth me forsake,
               
                  
Fortune engulfes me in extreame distresse:
               She turnes from me her smiling countenance,
               Casting on me mishapp vpon mishapp,
               Left and betraide of thousand thousand frends,
               Once of my sute, but you Lucill are left
               Remaining to me stedfast as a tower
               In holy loue, in spite of fortunes blastes.
               But if of any God my voice be heard,
               And be not vainely scatt' red in the heau'ns,
               Such goodnes shall not glorilesse be loste.
               But comming ages still there of shall boste.
            
            
               Lu.
               Men in their frendship euer should be one,
               And neuer ought with fickle Fortune shake,
               Which still remoues, nor will, nor knowes the way,
               Her rowling bowle in one sure state to staie.
               Wherfore we ought as borrow'd things receiue
               The goods light she lends vs to pay againe:
               Not hold them sure, nor on them build our hopes
               As on such goods as cannot faile, and fall:
               But thinke againe, nothing is dureable,
               
                  
Vertue except, our neuer failing host:
               So bearing saile when fauoring windes do blow,
               As frowning tempests may vs least dismaie
               When they on vs do fall: not ouer-glad
               With good estate, nor ouer-grieu'd with bad.
               Resist mishap.
            
            
               Ant.
               Alas! it is too strong.
               Mishappes oft times are by some comfort borne:
               But these, ay me! whose weights oppresse my hart,
               Too heauie lie, no hope can them relieue.
               There rests no more, but that with cruell blade
               For lingring death a hastie waie be made.
            
            
               Lu,
               
                  Caesar, as heire vnto his fathers state.
               So will his Fathers goodnes imitate,
               To you ward: whome he know's allied in bloud,
               Allied in mariage, ruling equally
               Th' Empire with him, and with him making warre
               Haue purg'd the earth of Caesars murtherers.
               You into portions parted haue the world
               Euen like coheirs their heritages parte:
               And now with one accord so many yeares
               
                  
In quiet peace both haue your charges rul'd.
            
            
               Ant.
               Bloud and alliance nothing do preuaile
               To coole the thirst of hote ambitious brests:
               The sonne his Father hardly can endure,
               Brother his brother, in one common Realme.
               So feruent this desire to Commaund:
               Such iealousie it kindleth in our hearts,
               Sooner will men permit another should
               Loue her they loue then weare the crowne they weare.
               All lawes it breakes, turnes all things vpside downe:
               Amitie, kindred, nought so holy is
               
                  
                     •
                  ut it defiles. A monarchie to gaine
               None cares which way, so he may it obtaine.
            
            
               Lu.
               Suppose he Monarch be and that this world
               No more acknowledg sundry Emperours,
               That Rome him only feare, and that he ioyne
               The east with west, and both at once do rule:
               Why should he not permitt you peaceablie
               Discharg'd of charge and Empires dignitie,
               Priuate to liue reading Philosophy,
               
               
                  
In learned Greece, Spaine, Asia, any land?
            
            
               An.
               Neuer will he his Empire thinke assur'de
               While in this world Marke Antony shall liue.
               Sleepeles Suspicion, Pale distrust, cold feare
               Alwaies to princes companie do beare
               Bred of reports: reports which night and day
               Perpetuall guests from court go not away.
            
            
               Lu.
               He hath not slaine your brother Lucius,
               
               Nor shortned hath the age of Lepidus,
               
               Albeit both into his hands were falne,
               And he with wrath against them both enflam'd.
               Yet one, as Lord in quiet rest doth beare.
               The greatest sway in great Iberia:
               
               The other with his gentle Prince retaines
               Of highest Priest the sacred dignitie.
            
            
               An.
               He feares not them, their feeble force he knowes.
            
            
               Lu.
               He feares no vanquisht ouerfill'd with woes.
            
            
               An.
               Fortune may chaunge againe.
            
            
               L.
               A down-cast foe
               Can hardly rise, which once is brought so low.
            
            
               Ant.
               All that I can is donne: for last assay
               
                  
(When all means fail'd) I to entreaty fell,
               (Ah coward creature!) whence againe repulst
               Of combate I vnto him proffer made:
               Though he in prime, and I by feeble age
               Mightily weakned both in force and skill.
               Yet could not he his coward heart aduaunce
               Basely affraide to trie so praisefull chaunce.
               This makes me plaine, makes me my selfe accuse,
               Fortune in this her spitefull force doth vse
               'Gainst my gray hayres: in this vnhappy I
               
                  
                     •
                  epine at heau'ns in my happes pittiles.
               Aman, a woman both in might and minde,
               In Mars his schole who neuer lesson learn'd,
               Should me repulse, chase, ouerthow, destroy,
               Me of such fame, bring to so low an ebbe?
               
                  Alcides bloud, who from my infancy
               With happy prowesse crowned haue my praise
               Witnesse thou Gaule vnus'd to seruile yoke,
               Thou valiant Spaine, you fields of Thessalie
               
               With millions of mourning cries bewail'd,
               
                  
Twise watred now with bloud of Italie.
               
            
            
               Lu.
               Witnes may Afrique, and of conquer'd world
               All fower quarters witnesses may be.
               For in what part of earth inhabited,
               Hungry of praise haue you not ensignes spred?
            
            
               Ant.
               Thou know'st rich Aegipt (Aegipt of my deedes
               Faire and foule subiect) Aegypt ah! thou know'st
               How I behau'd me fighting for thy kinge,
               When I regainde him his rebellious Realme:
               Against his foes in battaile shewing force,
               And after fight in victory remorse.
               Yet if to bring my glory to the ground,
               Fortune had made me ouerthrowne by one
               Of greater force, of better skill then I:
               One of those Captaines feared so of olde,
               Camill, Marcellus, Worthy Scipio,
               This late great Caesar, honor of our state,
               Or that great Pompei aged growne in armes;
               That after haruest of a world of men
               Made in a hundred battailes, fights, assaults,
               
                  
My body thorow pearst with push of pike
               Had vomited my bloud, in bloud my life,
               In midd'st of millions felowes in my fall:
               The lesse her wrong, the lesse should my woe:
               Nor she should paine, nor I complaine me so.
               No, no, wheras I should haue died in armes,
               And vanquisht oft new armies should haue arm'd,
               New battailes giuen, and rather lost with me
               All this whole world submitted vnto me:
               A man who neuer saw enlaced pikes
               With bristled points against his stomake bent,
               Who feares the field, and hides him cowardly
               Dead at the very noise the souldiors make.
               His vertue, fraud, deceit, malicious guile,
               His armes the arts that false Vlisses vs'de,
               Knowne at Modena, where the Consuls both
               Death-wounded were, and wounded by his men
               To get their armie, war with it to make
               Against his faith, against his country soile,
               Of Lepidus, which to his succours came,
               
                  
To honor whome he was by dutie bound,
               The Empire he vsurpt: corrupting first
               with baites and bribes the most part of his men.
               Yet me hath ouercome, and made his pray,
               And state of Rome, with me hath ouercome.
               Strange! one disordred act at Actium
               
               The earth subdu'de, my glory hath obscur'd.
               For since, as one whome heauens wrath attaints
               With furie caught, and more then furious
               Vex'd with my euills, I neuer more had care
               My armies lost, or lost name to repaire:
               I did no more resist.
            
            
               Lu.
               all warres affaires,
               But battailes most, dayly haue their successe
               Now good, now ill: and though that fortune haue
               Great force and power in euery worldly thing,
               Rule all, do all, haue all things fast enchaind
               Vnto the circle of hir turning wheele:
               Yet seemes it more then any practise else
               She doth frequent Bellonas bloudy trade:
               And that hir fauour, wauering as the wind,
               
                  
Hir greatest power therein doth oftnest shewe.
               Whence growes, we dailie see, who in their youth
               G
                     •
                  tt honor ther, do loose it in their age,
               Vanquisht by some lesse warlike then themselues:
               Whome yet a meaner man shall ouerthrowe.
               Hir vse is not to lend vs still her hande,
               But sometimes headlong backe a gaine to throwe,
               When by hir fauor she hath vs extolld
               Vnto the topp of highest happines.
            
            
               Ant.
               well ought I curse within my grieued soule,
               Lamenting daie and night, this sencelesse loue,
               Whereby my faire entising foe entrap'd
               My hedelesse Reason, could no more escape.
               
                  It was not fortunes euer chaunging face:
               
               
                  It was not Dest nies chaungles Violence
               
               
                  Forg'd my mishap. Alas! who doth not know
               
               
                  They make, nor marre, nor any thing can doe.
               
               
                  Fortune, which men so feare, adore, detest,
               
               
                  Is but a chaunce whose cause vnknow'n doth rest.
               
               
                  Although oft times the cause is well perceiu'd,
               
               
                  
                  But not th'effect the same that was conceiu'd.
               
               
                  Pleasure, nought else, the plague of this our life,
               Our life which still a thousand plagues pursue,
               Alone hath me this strange disastre spunne,
               Falne from a souldior to a chamberer,
               Careles of vertue, careles of all praise.
               Nay, as the fatted swine in filthy mire
               With glutted heart I wallowed in delights,
               All thoughts of honor troden vnder foote.
               So I me lost: for finding this sweet cupp
               Pleasing my tast, vnwife I drunke my fill,
               And through the sweetnes of that poisons power
               By steps I draue my former wits astraie.
               I made my frends, offended me forsake,
               I holpe my foes against my selfe to rise.
               I robd my subiects, and for followers
               I saw my selfe be set with flatterers.
               Mine idle armes faire wrought with spiders worke,
               My scattred men without their ensignes strai'd:
               
                  Caesar meane while who neuer would haue dar'de
               
                  
To cope with me, me sodainely despis'de,
               Tooke hart to fight, and hop'de for victorie
               On one so gone, who glorie had forgone.
            
            
               Lu.
               Enchaunting pleasure Venus sweete delights
               Weaken our bodies, ouer-cloud our sprights,
               Trouble our reason, from our hearts out chase
               All holie vertues lodging in thir place:
               Like as the cunnig fisher takes the fishe
               By traitor baite whereby the hooks is hid:
               So Pleasure serues to vice in steede of foode
               To baite our soules thereon too liquorishe.
               This poison deadly is alike to all,
               But on great kings doth greatest outrage worke,
               Taking the roiall scepters from their hands,
               Thence forward to be by some stranger borne:
               While that their people charg'd with heauie loades
               Their flatt'rers pill, and suck their mary drie,
               Not rul'd but left to great men as a pray,
               While this fonde Prince himselfe in pleasur's drowns
               Who hears nought, sees noght, doth nought of a king
               
                  
Seming himselfe against himselfe conspirde.
               Then equall Iustice wandreth banished,
               And in her seat sitts greedie Tyrannie.
               Confus'd disorder troubleth all estates,
               Crimes without feare and outrages are done.
               Then mutinous Rebellion shewes her face,
               Now hid with this, and now with that pretence,
               Prouoking enimies, which on each side
               Enter at ease, and make them Lords of all.
               The hurtfull workes of pleasure here behold,
            
            
               An.
               The wolfe is not so hurtfull to the folde,
               Frost to the grapes, to ripened frutes the raine:
               As pleasure is to princes full of paine.
            
            
               Lu.
               There nedes no proofe, but by th' Assirian kinge,
               On whom that Monster woefull wrack did bring.
            
            
               An.
               There nedes no proofe, but by vnhappie I,
               Who lost my empire, honor, life thereby,
            
            
               Lu
               Yet hath this ill so much the greater force,
               As scarcely any do against it stand:
               No not the Demy-gods the olde world knew,
               
                  
Who all subdu'de, could Pleasures power subdue.
               Great Hercules, Hercules once that was
               Wonder of earth and heauen, matchles in might,
               Who An
                        •
                     eus, Ly
                        •
                     us, Geryon ouercame,
               Who drew from hell the triple-headed dogg,
               Who Hydra kill'd, vanquishd Achelous,
               
               Who heauens weight on his strong shoulders bare;
               Did he not vnder Pleasures burthen bow?
               Did he not Captiue to this passion yelde,
               When by his Captiue, so he was inflam'd,
               As now your self in Cleopatra burne?
               Slept in hir lapp, hir bosome kist and kiste,
               With base vnseemely seruice bought her loue,
               Spinning at distaffe, and with sinewy hand
               Winding on spindles threde, in maides attire?
               His conqu'ring clubbe at rest on wal did hang:
               His bow vnstringd he bent not as he vs'de:
               Vpon his shafts the weauing spiders spunne:
               And his hard cloake the fretting mothes did pierce.
               The monsters free and fearles all the time
               
                  Throughtout the world the people did torment.
               And more and more encreasing daie by daie
               Scorn'd his weake heart become a mistresse play.
            
            
               An.
               In onely this like Hercules am I,
               In this I proue me of his lignage right:
               In this himselfe, his deedes I shew in this:
               In this, nought else, my ancestor he is.
               But goe we: die I must, and with braue end
               Conclusion make of all foregoing harmes:
               Die, die I must: I must a noble death,
               A glorious death vnto my succour call:
               I must deface the shame of time abus'd,
               I must adorne the wanton loues I vs'de,
               With some couragious act: that my last day
               By mine owne hand my spots may wash away.
               Come deare Lucill: alas! why weepe you thus!
               This mortall lot is common to vs all.
               We must all die, each doth in homage owe
               Vnto that God that shar'd the Realmes belowe
               Ah sigh no more: alas! appeace your woes,
               
                  
For by your greife my griefe more eager growes,
            
            
               Chorus.
               Alas, with what tormenting fire
               Vs martireth this blind desire
               to stay our life from flieng!
               How ceasleslie our minds doth rack,
               How heauie lies vpon our back
               This dastard feare of dieng!
               
                  Death rather healthfull succour giues,
               
                  Death rather all mishapps relieues
               That life vpon vs throweth:
               And euer to vs death vnclose
               The dore whereby from curelesse woes
               Our weary soule out goeth.
               What Goddesse else more milde then she
               To burie all our paine can be,
               What remedie more pleasing?
               Our pained hearts when dolor stings,
               
                  
And nothing rest, or respite brings,
               What help haue we more easing?
               
                  Hope which to vs doth comfort giue,
               And doth our fainting harts reuiue,
               Hath not such force in anguish:
               For promising a vaine reliefe
               She oft vs failes in midst of griefe,
               And helples lets vs languish.
               But Death who call on her at neede
               Doth neuer with vaine semblant feed,
               But when them sorrow paineth,
               So riddes their soules of all distresse
               Whose heauie weight did them oppresse,
               That not one griefe remaineth.
               Who feareles and with courage bolde
               Can Acherons black face behold,
               Which muddie water beareth:
               And crossing ouer in the way
               Is not amaz'd at Perruque gray
               Olde rusty Charon weareth?
               
                  Who voide of dread can looke vpon
               The dreadfull shades that Rome alone,
               On bankes where sound no voices:
               Whome with hir fire-brands and her Snakes
               No whit afraide Alecto makes,
               Nor triple-barking noises:
               Who freely can himselfe dispose
               Of that last hower which all must close,
               And leaue this life at pleasure:
               This noble freedome more esteemes,
               And in his heart more precious deemes,
               Then crowne and kinglie treasure,
               The waues which Boreas blasts turmoile
               And cause with foaming furie boile,
               Make not his heart to tremble:
               Nor brutish broile, when with strong head
               A rebell people madly ledde
               Against their Lords assemble:
               Nor fearefull face of Tirant wood,
               Who breaths but threats, &amp; drinks but bloud,
               
                  
No, nor the hand which thunder,
               The hand of Ioue which thuder beares,
               And ribbs of rocks in sunder teares,
               Teares mountains sides in sunder:
               Nor bloudy Marses butchering bands,
               Whose lightnings desert laie the lands
               Whome dustie cloudes do couer:
               From of whose armour sun-beames flie,
               And vnder them make quaking lie
               The plaines wheron they houer:
               Nor yet the cruell murth'ing blade
               Warme in the moistie bowels made
               Of people pell mell dieng
               In some great Cittie put to sack
               By sauage Tirant brought to wrack,
               At his colde mercie lieng.
               How abiect him, how base thinke I,
               Who wanting courage can not dye
               When need him thereto calleth?
               From whome the dagger drawne to kill
               
                  
The cureles griefes that vexe him still
               For feare and faintnes falleth?
               O Antony with thy deare mate
               Both in misfortunes fortunate!
               Whose thoughts to death a spiring
               Shall you protect from victors rage,
               Who on each side doth you encage,
               To triumph much desiring.
               That Caesar may you not offend
               Nought else but death can you defend,
               Which his weake force derideth.
               And all in this round earth containd,
               Powr'les on them whome once enchaind
               
                  Auernus prison hideth:
               Where great Psammetiques ghost doth rest,
               Not with infernall paine possest,
               But in sweete fields detained:
               And olde Amasis soule likewise,
               And all our famous Ptolomies
               
               That whilome on vs raigned.
            
         
         
            
            Act. 4
            Caesar. Agrippa. Dircetus.
the Messenger.
            
               Caesar.
               You euer-liuing Gods which all things holde
               Within the power of your celestiall hands,
               By whome heate, colde, the thunder, and the wind,
               The properties of enter chaunging mon'ths
               Their course and being haue; which do set downe
               Of Empires by your destinied decree
               The force, age, time, and subiect to no chaunge
               Chaunge all, reseruing nothing in one state:
               You haue aduaunst, as high as thundring heau'n
               The Romaines greatnes by Bellonas might:
               Maistring the world with fearefull violence,
               Making the world widdow of libertie.
               Yet at this day this proud exalted Rome
               
               
                  
Despoil'd, captiu'd, at one mans will doth bend:
               Her Empire mine, her life is in my hand,
               As Monarch I both world and Rome commaund;
               Do all, can all; foorth my command'ment cast
               Like thundring fire from one to other Pole
               Equall to Ioue: bestowing by my word
               Happs and mishappes, as Fortunes King and Lord.
               No towne there is, but vp my Image settes,
               But sacrifice to me doth dayly make:
               Whither where Phaebus ioyne his mourning steedes,
               Or where the night them weary entertaines,
               Or where the heat the Garamants doth scorch,
               Or where the colde from Boreas breast is blowne:
               All Caesar do both awe and honor beare,
               And crowned Kings his verie name doth feare.
               
                  Antony knowes it well, for whome not one
               Of all the Princes all this earth do rule,
               Armes against me: for all redoubt the power
               which heau'nly powers on earth haue made me beare.
               
                  Antony, he poore man with fire inflam'de
               
                  
A womans beauties kindled in his heart.
               Rose against me, who longer could not beare
               My sisters wrong he did so ill intreat:
               Seing her left while that his leud delights
               Her husband with his Cleopatre tooke
               In Alexandria, where both nights and daies
               Their time they pass'd in nought but loues and plaies
               All Asias forces into one he drewe,
               And forth he set vpon the azur'd waues
               A thousand and a thousand Shipps, which fill'd
               With Souldiors, pikes, with targets, arrowes, darts,
               Made Neptune quake, and all the watry troupes
               Of Glanques, and Tritons lodg'd at Actium,
               
               But mightie Gods, who still the force withstand
               Of him, who causles doth another wrong,
               In lesse then moments space redus'd to nought
               All that proud power by Sea or land he brought.
            
            
               Agr.
               Presumptuous pride of heigh and hawtie sprite,
               Voluptuous care of fond and foolish loue,
               Haue iustly wrought his wrack: who thought he helde
               
                  
(By ouerweening) Fortune in his hand.
               Of vs he made no count, but as to play,
               So feareles came our forces to assay.
               So sometimes fell to Sonnes of mother earth,
               Which crawl'd to heau'n warre on the God to make,
               Olymp on Pelion, Ossa on Olymp,
               
                  Pindus on Ossa loading by degrees:
               That at hand strokes with mightie clubbes the might
               On mossie rocks the Gods make tumble downe:
               When mightie Ioue with burning anger chaf'd,
               Disbraind with him Gyges and Briareus,
               
               Blunting his darts vpon their brused bones.
               For no one thing the Gods can lesse abide
               In deedes of men, then Arrogance and pride.
               And still the proud, which too much takes in hand,
               Shall fowlest fall, where best he thinkes to stand.
            
            
               Caes.
               Right as some Pallace, or some stately tower,
               Which ouer-lookes the neighbour buildings round
               In scorning wise, and to the starres vp growes,
               Which in short time his owne weight ouerthrowes.
               
                  What monstrous pride, nay what impietie
               Incenst him onward to the Gods disgrace?
               When his two children, Cleopatras bratts,
               To Phaebe and her brother he compar'd,
               
                  Latonas race, causing them to be call'd
               The Sunne and Moone? Is not this follie right
               And is not this the Gods to make his foes?
               And is not this himselfe to worke his woes?
            
            
               Agr.
               In like proud sort he caus'd his hed to leese
               The Iewish king Antigonus, to haue
               His Realme for balme, that Cleopatra lou'd,
               As though on him he had some treason prou'd.
            
            
               Caes
               
                  Lidia to her, and Siria he gaue,
               
                  Cyprus of golde, Arabia rich of smelles:
               And to his children more Cilicia,
               
               Parth's, Medes, Armenia, Phaenicia:
               The kings of kings proclaming them to be,
               By his owne word, as by a sound decree.
            
            
               Agr.
               What? Robbing his owne country of her due
               Triumph'd he not in Alexandriae,
               
               
                  Of Artabasus the Armenian King,
               Who yeelded on his periur'd word to him?
            
            
               Caes.
               Nay, neuer Rome more iniuries receiu'd,
               Since thou, ô Romulus, by flight of birds
               With happy hand the Romain walles did'st build,
               Then Antonyes fond loues to it hath done.
               Nor euer warre more holie, nor more iust,
               Nor vndertaken with more hard constraint,
               Then is this warre: which were it not, our state
               Within small time all dignitie should loose:
               Though I lament (thou Sunne my witnes art,
               And thou great Ioue) that it so deadly proues:
               That Romaine bloud should in such plentie flowe,
               Watring the fields and pastures where we go.
               What Carthage in olde hatred obstinate,
               What Gaule still barking at our rising state,
               What rebell Samnite, what fierce Phyrrhus power,
               What cruell Mithridate, what Parth hath wrought
               Such woe to Rome? whose common wealth he had,
               (Had he bene victor) into Egypt brought.
            
            
               
               Agr.
               Surely the Gods, which haue this cittie built
               Steadfast to stand as long as time endures,
               Which keepe the Capitoll, of vs take care,
               And care will take of those shall after come,
               Haue made you victor, that you might redresse
               Their honor growne by passed mischieues lesse.
            
            
               Caes.
               The seelie man when all the Greekish Sea
               His fleete had hid, in hope me sure to drowne,
               Me battaile gaue: where fortune in my stede,
               Repulsing him his forces disaraied.
               Himselfe tooke flight, soone as his loue he saw
               All wanne through feare with full sailes flie away.
               His men, though lost, whome none did now direct,
               With courage fought fast grappled shipp with shipp,
               Charging, resisting, as their oares would serue,
               With darts, with swords, with pikes, with fiery flames.
               So that the darkned night her starrie vaile
               Vpon the bloudy sea had ouer-spred,
               Whilst yet they held: and hardly, hardly then
               They fell to flieng on the wauie plaine,
               
                  All full of soldiors ouerwhelm'd with waues.
               The aire throughout with cries &amp; grones did sound:
               The sea did blush with bloud: the neighbour shores
               Groned, so they with shipwracks pestred were,
               And floting bodies left for pleasing foode
               To birds, and beasts, and fishes of the sea,
               You know it well Agrippa.
               
            
            
               Ag.
               Mete it was
               The Romain Empire so should ruled be,
               As heau'n is rul'd: which turning ouer vs,
               All vnder things by his example turnes.
               Now as of heau'n one onely Lord we know:
               One onely Lord should rule this earth below.
               
                  When one selfe pow're is common made to two
               
               
                  Their duties they nor suffer will, nor doe.
               
               
                  In quarell still, in doubt, in hate, in feare;
               
               
                  Meane while the people all the smart do beare.
               
            
            
               Caes.
               Then to the end none, while my daies endure,
               Seeking to raise himselfe may succours find,
               We must with bloud marke this our victory,
               For iust example to all memorie
               
                  Murther we must, vntil not one we leaue,
               Which may hereafter vs of rest be reaue.
            
            
               Ag.
               Marke it with murthers? Who of that can like?
            
            
               Cae.
               Murthers must vse, who doth assurance seeke.
            
            
               Ag.
               Assurance call you enemies to make?
            
            
               Cae.
               I make no such, but such away I take.
            
            
               Ag.
               Nothing so much as rigour doth displease.
            
            
               Cae.
               Nothing so much doth make me liue at ease.
            
            
               Ag.
               What ease to him that feared is of all?
            
            
               Cae.
               Feared to be, and see his foes to fall.
            
            
               Ag.
               Commonly feare doth brede and nourish hate.
            
            
               Cae.
               Hate without pow'r comes commonly too late.
            
            
               Ag.
               A feared Prince hath oft his death desir'd
            
            
               Cae.
               A Prince not fear'd hath oft his wrong conspir'd.
            
            
               Ag.
               No guard so sure, no forte so strong doth proue.
               No such defence, as is the peoples loue.
            
            
               Cae.
               Nought more vnsure more weak, more like the winde,
               Then Peoples fauour still to change enclinde.
            
            
               Ag.
               Good Gods! what loue to gratious prince men  beare!
            
            
               Cae.
               What honor to the Prince that is seuere!
            
            
               
               Ag.
               Nought more diuine then is Benigntie.
               
            
            
               Cae.
               Nought likes the Gods as doth Seuerity.
               
            
            
               Ag.
               
                  Gods all forgiue.
            
            
               Cae.
               On faults they paines do lay.
            
            
               Ag.
               And giue their goods.
            
            
               C.
               Oft times they tak away
            
            
               Ag.
               They wreake them not, ô Caesar, at each time
               That by our sinnes they are to wrath prouok'd.
               Neither must you (beleeue, I humblie praie)
               Your victorie with crueltie defile.
               The Gods it gaue, it must not be abus'd,
               But to the good of all men mildely vs'd,
               And they bethank'd: that hauing giu'n you grace
               To raigne alone, and rule this earthly masse,
               They may hence-forward hold it still in rest,
               All scattered power vnited in one brest.
            
            
               Cae.
               But what is he that breathles comes so fast,
               Approching vs, and going in such hast?
            
            
               Ag.
               He seemes affraid: and vnder his arme I
               (But much I erre) a bloudy sword espie.
            
            
               Cae.
               I long to vnderstand what it may be.
            
            
               Ag.
               He hither comes: it's best we stay and see.
            
            
               
               Dirce.
               What good God now my voice will reenforce,
               That tell I may to rocks, and hilles, and woods,
               To waues of sea, which dash vpon the shore,
               To earth, to heauen, the woefull newes I bring?
            
            
               A.
               What sodaine chance thee towards vs hath broght
            
            
               Dir.
               A lamentable chance. O wrath of heau'ns!
               O Gods too pittiles!
            
            
               Caes.
               What monstrous hap
               Wilt thou recount?
            
            
               Dir.
               Alas too hard mishap!
               When I but dreame of what mine eies beheld,
               My hart doth freeze, my limmes do quiuering quake,
               I senceles stand, my brest with tempest tost
               Killes in my throte my words, ere fully borne.
               Dead, dead he is: be sure of what I say,
               This murthering sword hath made the man away.
            
            
               Caes.
               Alas my heart doth cleaue, pittie me rackes,
               My brest doth pant to heare this dolefull tale.
               Is Antony then dead? to death, alas!
               I am the cause despaire him so compelld.
               But soldior of his death the manner showe,
               And how he did this liuing light forgoe.
            
            
               
               Dir.
               When Antony no hope remaining saw
               How warre he might, or how agreement make,
               Saw him betraid by all his men of warre
               In euery fight as well by sea, as land;
               That not content to yeeld them to their foes
               They also came against himselfe to fight:
               Alone in court he gan himselfe torment,
               Accuse the Queene, himselfe of hir lament,
               Call'd hir vntrue and traitresse, as who sought
               To yeeld him vp she could no more defend:
               That in the harmes which for hir sake he bare,
               As in his blisfull state, she might not share.
               But she againe, who much his fury fear'd,
               Gat to the tombes, darke horrors dwelling place:
               Made lock the doores, and pull the hearses downe.
               Then fell she wretched, with hir selfe to fight.
               A thousand plaints, a thousand sobbes she cast
               From hir weake brest which to the bones was torne.
               Of women hir the most vnhappy call'd,
               Who by hir loue, hir woefull loue, had lost
               
                  Hir realme, hir life, and more the loue of him,
               Who while he was, was all hir woes support.
               But that she faultles was she did inuoke
               For witnes heau'n, and aire, and earth, and sea.
               Then sent him word, she was no more aliue,
               But lay inclosed dead within her tombe.
               This he beleeu'd; and fell to sigh and grone,
               And crost his armes, then thus began to mone.
            
            
               C.
               Poore hopeles man!
            
            
               D.
               What dost thou more attend
               Ah Antony! why dost thou death deferre.
               Since Fortune thy professed enimie,
               Hath made to die, who only made thee liue?
               Sone as with sighes hee had these words vp clos'd,
               His armor he vnlaste and cast it off,
               Then all disarm'd he thus againe did say:
               My Queene, my heart, the griefe that now I feele.
               Is not that I your eies, my Sunne, do loose,
               For soone againe one tombe shall vs conioyne:
               I grieue, whome men so valorous did deeme,
               Should now, then you, of lesser valor seeme.
               
                  So said, forthwith he Eros to him call'd,
               
                  Eros his man; summond him on his faith
               To kill him at his nede. He tooke the sword,
               And at that instant stab'd therwith his breast,
               And ending life fell dead before his feete.
               O Eros thankes (quoth Antony) for this
               Most noble acte, who pow'rles me to kill,
               On thee hast done, what I on mee should do.
               Of speaking thus he scarsce had made an end,
               And taken vp the bloudy sword from ground,
               But he his bodie piers'd; and of red bloud
               A gushing fountaine all the chamber fill'd.
               He staggred at the blow, his face grew pale,
               And on a couche all feeble downe he fell,
               Sounding with anguish: deadly cold him tooke,
               As if his soule had then his lodging left
               But he reuiu'd, and marking all our eies,
               Bathed in teares, and how our breasts we beate
               For pittie, anguish, and for bitter griefe,
               To see him plong'd in extreame wretchednes:
               
                  He prai'd vs all to haste his lingring death:
               But no man willing, each himselfe withdrew.
               Then fell he new to cry and vexe himselfe,
               Vntill a man from Cleopatra came,
               Who said from hir he had commaundement
               To bring him to hir to the monument.
               The poore soule at these words euen rapt with ioy
               Knowing she liu'd, prai'd vs him to conuey
               Vnto his Lady. Then vpon our armes
               We bare him to the Tombe, but entred not.
               For she who feared captiue to be made,
               And that she should to Rome in triumph goe,
               Kept close the gate but from a window high
               Cast downe a corde, wherein he was impackt.
               Then by hir womens help the corps she rais'd,
               And by strong armes into hir window drew.
               So pittifull a sight was neuer seene.
               Little and little Antony was pull'd,
               Now breathing death: his beard was all vnkempt,
               His face and brest al bathed in his bloud.
               
                  So hideous yet, and dieng as he was,
               His eies half-clos'd vppon the Queene he cast:
               Held vp his hands, and holpe himselfe to raise,
               But still with weaknes back his bodie fell.
               The miserable ladie with moist eies,
               With haire which careles on hir forhead hong,
               With brest which blowes had bloudily benumb'd,
               With stooping head, and body down-ward bent,
               Enlast hir in the corde, and with all force
               This life-dead man couragiously vprais'd,
               The bloud with paine into hir face did flowe,
               Hir sinewes stiff, her selfe did breathles grow.
               The people which beneath in flocks beheld,
               Assisted her with gesture, speach, desire:
               Cride and incourag'd her, and in thier soules
               Did sweate, and labor, no whit lesse then she.
               Who neuer tir'd in labor, held so long
               Helpt by her women, and hir constant heart,
               That Antony was drawne into the tombe,
               And there (I thinke) of dead augments the summe.
               
                  The cittie all to teares and sighes is turn'd,
               To plaints and outcries horrible to heare:
               Men, women, children, hoary-headed age
               Do all pell mell in house and streete lament,
               Scratching their faces, tearing of their haire,
               Wringing their hands, and martyring their brests
               Extreame their dole: and greater misery
               In sacked townes can hardlie euer be.
               Not if the fire had scal'de the highest towers:
               That all things were of force and murther full;
               That in the streets the bloud in riuers stream'd;
               The sonne his sire saw in his bosome slaine,
               The sire his sonne: the husband and rest of breath
               In his wiues armes, who furious runnes to death.
               Now my brest wounded with their piteouse plaints
               I left their towne, and tooke with me this sworde,
               Which I tooke vp at what time Antony
               
               Was from his chamber caried to the tombe:
               And brought it you, to make his death more plaine,
               And that thereby my words may credite gaine.
            
            
               
               Cas.
               Ah Gods what cruell hap! poore Antony,
               
               Alas hast thou this sword so long time borne
               Against thy foe, that in the end it should
               Of thee his Lord the cursed murth'rer be?
               O Death how I bewaile thee! we (alas!)
               So many warres haue ended, brothers, frends,
               Companions, coozens, equalls in estate:
               And must it now to kill thee be my fate?
            
            
               Ag.
               Why trouble you your selfe with bootles griefe?
               For Antony why spend you teares in vaine?
               Why darken you with dole your victory?
               Me seemes your selfe your glory do enuie.
               Enter the towne, giue thanks vnto the Gods.
            
            
               Cae.
               I cannot but his tearefull chaunce lament,
               Although not I, but his owne pride the cause,
               And vnchast loue of this Aegiptian.
               
            
            
               Agt.
               But best we sought into the tombe to get,
               Lest she consume in this amazed case
               So much rich treasure, with which happely
               Despaire in death may make hir feede the fire:
               
                  Suffring the flames hir Iewells to deface,
               You to defraud, hir funerall to grace.
               Sende then to hir, and let some meane be vs'd
               With some deuise so hold her still aliue,
               Some faire large promises: and let them marke
               Whither they may by some fine cunning slight
               Enter the tombes. Caesar. Let Proculeius goe,
               And feede with hope hir soule disconsolate.
               Assure hir soe, that we may wholy get
               Into our hands hir treasure and her selfe.
               For this of all things most I do desire
               To keepe her safe vntill our going hence:
               That by hir presence beautified may be
               The glorious triumph Rome prepares for me.
            
            
               Chorus of Romaine
Souldiors.
               Shall euer ciuile bate
               gnaw and deuour our state?
               
                  shall neuer we this blade,
               our bloud hath bloudy made,
               lay downe? these armes downe lay
               as robes we weare alway?
               but as from age to age.
               so passe from rage to rage?
               Our hands shall we not rest
               to bath in our owne brest?
               and shall thick in each land
               our wretched trophees stand,
               to tell posteritie,
               what madd Impietie
               our stonie stomacks led
               against the place vs bred?
               Then still must heauen view
               the plagues that vs pursue.
               and euery wher descrie
               Heaps of vs scattred lie,
               making the stranger plaines
               fat with our bleeding raines,
               
                  proud that on them their graue
               so many legious haue.
               And with out fleshes still
               
                  Neptune his fishes fill
               and dronke with bloud from blue
               the sea take blushing hue:
               as iuice of Tyrian shell,
               when clarified well
               to wolle of finest fields
               a purple glosse it yeeldes.
               But since the rule of Rome,
               
               to one mans hand is come,
               who gouernes without mate
               hir now vnited state,
               late iointly rulde by three
               enuieng mutuallie,
               whose triple yoke much woe
               on Latines necks did throwe:
               I hope the cause of iarre,
               and of this bloudie warre,
               
                  and deadly discord gone
               by what we last haue done:
               our banks shall cherish now
               the branchie pale-hew'd bow
               of Oliue, Pallas praise,
               in stede of barraine baies.
               And that his temple dore,
               which bloudy Mars before
               held open, now at last
               olde Ianus shall make fast:
               and rust the sword consume,
               and spoild of wauing plume,
               The vseles morion shall
               on crooke hang by the wall.
               At least if warre returne
               It shall not here soiourne,
               to kill vs with those armes
               were forg'd for others harmes:
               but haue their points addrest,
               against the Germaines brest,
               
                  The Parthians fayned flight,
               the Biscaines martiall might.
               Olde Memory doth there
               painted on forehead weare
               our Fathers praise: thence torne
               our triumphs baies haue worne:
               therby our matchles Rome
               
               whilome of Shepeheards come
               rais'd to this greatnes stands,
               the Queene of forraine lands.
               Which now euen seemes to face
               the heau'ns, her glories place:
               nought resting vnder skies
               that dares affront her eies.
               So that she needes but feare
               the weapons Ioue doth beare,
               who angry at one blowe
               may her quite ouerthrowe.
            
         
         
            
            Act. 5,
            Cleopatra. Euphron. Children of Cleopatra.
Charmion. Eras.
            
               Cleop.
               O cruell fortune! ô accursed lot!
               O plaguy loue! ô most detested brand!
               O wretched ioyes! ô beauties miserable!
               O deadly state! ô deadly roialtie!
               O hatefull life! ô Queene most lamentable!
               O Antony by my faulte buriable!
               O hellish worke of heau'n! alas! the wrath
               Of all the Gods at once on vs is falne.
               Vnhappie Queene! ô would I in this world
               The wandring light of day had neuer seene?
               Alas! of mine the plague and poison I
               The crowne haue lost my ancestors me left,
               This Realme I haue to strangers subiect made,
               
                  And robd my children of their heritage.
               Yet this is nought (alas!) vnto the price
               Of you deare husband, whome my snares intrap'd:
               Of you, whome I haue plagu'd, whom I haue made
               With bloudy hand a guest of mouldie tombe:
               Of you, whome I destroied, of you, deare Lord,
               Whome I of Empire, honor, life haue spoil'd.
               O hurtfull woman! and can I yet liue,
               Yet longer liue in this Ghost-haunted tombe?
               Can I yet breath! can yet in such annoy,
               Yet can my soule within this body dwell?
               O Sisters you that spin the thredes of death!
               O Styx! ô Plegethon! you brookes of hell!
               O Impes of Night!
               
            
            
               Euph.
               Liue for your childrens sake:
               Let not your death of kingdome them depriue.
               Alas what shall they do who will haue care?
               Who will preserue this royall race of yours?
               Who pittie take? euen now me seemes I see
               These little soules to seruile bondage falne,
               And borne in triumph.
            
            
               Cl.
               Ah most miserable!
            
            
               
               Euph.
               Their tender armes with cursed cord fast bound
               At their weake backs.
            
            
               Cl.
               Ah Gods what pitty more!
            
            
               Euph.
               Their seely necks to ground with weaknes bend
            
            
               Cl.
               Neuer on vs, good Gods, such mischiefe send.
            
            
               Euph.
               And pointed at with fingers as they go.
            
            
               Cl.
               Rather a thousand deaths.
            
            
               Euph.
               Lastly his knife
               Some cruell catiue in their bloud embrue.
            
            
               Cl.
               Ah my heart breaks. By shady banks of hell,
               By fields whereon the lonely Ghosts do treade,
               By my foule, and the soule of Antony
               
               I you besech, Euphron, of them haue care.
               Be their good Father, let your wisedome lett
               That they fall not into this Tyrants hands.
               Rather conduct them where their freezed locks
               Black Aethiops to neighbour Sunne do shew;
               On wauie Ocean at the waters will;
               On barraine cliffes of snowie Caucasus;
               
               To Tigers swift, to Lions, and to Beares;
               And rather, rather vnto euery coaste,
               To eu'ry land and sea: for nought I feare
               
                  As rage of him, whose thirst no bloud can quench.
               Adieu deare children, children deare adieu:
               Good Isis you to place of safety guide,
               Farre from our foes, where you your liues may leade
               In free estate deuoid of seruile dread.
               Remember not, my children, you were borne
               Of such a Princely race: remember not
               So many braue Kings which haue Egipt rul'de
               In right descent your ancestors haue beene:
               That this great Antony your father was,
               
                  Hercules bloud, and more then he in praise.
               For your high courage such remembrance will,
               Seing your fall with burning rages fill.
               Who knowes if that your hands false Destinie
               
               The Scepters promis'd of imperious Rome,
               
               In stede of them shall crooked shepehookes beare,
               Needles or forkes, or guide the carte, or plough?
               Ah learne t'endure: your birth and high estate
               Forget, my babes, and bend to force of fate.
               Farwell, my babes, farwell my heart is clos'd,
               
                  With pittie and paine, my selfe with death enclos'd,
               My breath doth faile. Farwell for euermore,
               Your Sire and me you shall see neuer more.
               Farwell sweet care, farwell.
            
            
               Chil.
               Madame Adieu.
            
            
               Cl.
               Ah this voice killes me. Ah good Gods! I swound.
               I can no more, I die.
            
            
               Eras.
               Madame, alas!
               And will you yeld to woe? Ah speake to vs.
            
            
               Eu,
               Come Children.
            
            
               Chil.
               We come.
            
            
               Eu.
               Follow we our chance.
               The Gods shall guide vs.
            
            
               Char.
               O too cruell lot!
               O too hard chaunce! Sister what shall we do,
               What shall we do, alas! if murthring darte
               Of death arriue while that in slumbring swound
               Halfe dead she lie with anguish ouergone?
            
            
               Er,
               Her face is frozen.
            
            
               Ch.
               Madame for Gods loue
               Leaue vs not thus: bid vs yet first farwell.
               Alas! wepe ouer Antony: Let not
               His bodie be without due rites entomb'd.
            
            
               Cl.
               Ah, ah.
            
            
               Char.
               Madame.
            
            
               Cl.
               Ay me!
            
            
               Ch.
               How fainte she is?
            
            
               Cl.
               My Sisters, holde me vp. How wretched I,
               How cursed am: and was there euer one
               
                  By Fortunes hate into more dolours throwne?
               Ah, weeping Niobe, although thy heart
               Beholds it selfe enwrap'd in causefull woe
               For thy dead children, that a sencelesse rocke
               With griefe become, on Sipylus thou stand'st
               In endles teares: yet didst thou neuer feele
               The weights of griefe that on my heart do lie.
               Thy Children thou, mine I poore soule haue lost,
               And lost their Father, more then them I waile,
               Lost this faire realme; yet me the heauens wrath
               Into a stone not yet transformed hath.
               
                  Phaetons sisters, daughters of the Sunne,
               Which waile your brother falne into the streames
               Of stately Po: the Gods vpon the bankes
               Your bodies to banke-louing Alders turn'd.
               For me, I sigh, I ceasles wepe, and waile,
               And heauen pittiles laughes at my woe,
               Reuiues, renewes it still: and in the ende
               (Oh cruelty!) doth death for comfort lend.
               Die Cleopatra then no longer stay
               
                  From Antony, who thee at Styx attends:
               Go ioyne thy Ghost with his, and sob no more
               Without his loue within these tombes enclos'd.
            
            
               Eras.
               Alas! yet let vs wepe, lest sodaine death
               From him our teares, and those last duties take
               Vnto his tombe we owe.
            
            
               Ch.
               Ah let vs wepe
               While moisture lasts, then die before his feete.
            
            
               Cl.
               Who furnish will mine eies with streaming teares
               My boiling anguish worthily to waile,
               Waile thee Antony, Antony my heart?
               Alas, how much I weeping liquor want!
               Yet haue mine eies quite drawne their Condits drie
               By long beweeping my disastred harmes.
               Now reason is that from my side they sucke
               First vitall moisture, then the vitall bloud.
               Then let the bloud from my sad eies outflowe,
               And smoking yet with thine in mixture grow.
               Moist it, and heat it newe, and neuer stop,
               All watring thee, while yet remaines one drop.
            
            
               Ch.
               
                  Antony take our teares: this is the last
               
                  Of all the duties we to thee can yelde,
               Before we die.
            
            
               Er.
               These sacred obseques
               Take Antony, and take them in good parte.
            
            
               Cl.
               O Goddesse thou whom Cyprus doth adore,
               
                  Venus of Phaphos, bent to worke vs harme
               For olde Iulus broode, if thou take care
               Of Caesar, why of vs tak'st thou no care?
               
                  Antony did descend, as well as he,
               From thine owne Sonne by long enchained line:
               And might haue rul'd by one and selfe same fate,
               True Troian bloud, the stately Romain state.
               
                  Antony, poore Antony, my deare soule,
               Now but a blocke, the bootie of a tombe,
               Thy life thy heat is lost, thy coullour gone,
               And hideous palenes on thy face hath seaz'd.
               Thy eies, two Sunnes, the lodging place of loue,
               Which yet for tents to warlike Mars did serue,
               Lock'd vp in lidds (as faire daies cherefull light
               Which darkenese flies) do winking hide in night.
               
                  Antony by our true loues I thee beseeche,
               
                  And by our hearts sweete sparks haue set on fire,
               Our holy mariage, and the tender ruthe
               Of our deare babes, knot of our amitie:
               My dolefull voice thy eare let entertaine,
               And take me with thee to the hellish plaine,
               Thy wife, thy frend: heare Antony, ô heare
               My sobbing sighes, if here thou be, or there.
               Liued thus long, the winged race of yeares
               Ended I haue as Destinie decreed.
               Flourish'd and raign'd, and taken iust reuenge
               Of him who me both hated and despisde.
               Happie, alas too happie: if of Rome
               
               Only the fleete had hither neuer come.
               And now of me an Image great shall goe
               Vnder the earth to bury there my woe.
               What say I? where am I? ô Cleopatra,
               
               Poore Cleopatra, griefe thy reason reaues.
               No, no, most happie in this happles case,
               To die with thee, and dieng thee embrace:
               My bodie ioynde with thine, my mouth with thine,
               
                  my mouth, whose moisture burning sighes haue dried
               To be in one selfe tomble, and one selfe chest,
               And wrapt with thee in one selfe sheete to rest.
               The sharpest torment in my heart I feele
               Is that I stay from thee, my heart, this while.
               Die will I straight now, now streight will I die,
               And streight with thee a wandring shade will be,
               Vnder the Cypres trees thou haunt'st alone,
               Where brookes of hell do falling seeme to mone.
               But yet I stay, and yet thee ouerliue,
               That ere I die due rites I may thee giue.
               A thousand sobbes I from my brest will teare,
               With thousand plaints thy funeralls adorne:
               My haire shall serue for thy oblations,
               My boiling teares for thy effusions,
               Mine eies thy fire: for out of them the flame
               (Which burnt thy heart on me enamour'd) came.
               Wepe my companions, weepe, and from your eies
               Raine downe on him of teares a brinish streame.
               Mine can no more, consumed by the coales
               
                  Which from my brest, as from a furnace rise.
               Martir your breasts with multiplied blowes,
               With violent hands teare of your hanging haire,
               Outrage your face: alas! why should we seeke
               (Since now we die) our beauties more to keepe?
               I spent in teares, not able more to spende,
               But kisse him now, what rests me more to doe?
               Then let me kisse you, you faire eites, my light,
               Front seat of honor, face most firce, most faire!
               O neck, ô armes, ô hands, ô breast where death
               (O mischiefe) comes to choake vp vitall breath.
               A thousand kisses, thousand thousand more
               Let you my mouth for honors farewell giue:
               That in this office weake my limmes may growe,
               Fainting on you, and fourth my soule may flow.
            
            
               At Rams bury. 26. of Nouember. 1590.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
               Printed at London by P. S.
for William Ponsonby. 1595.
            
         
      
   

