
   
      
         
            True contentment in the gaine of godlines, with its self-sufficiencie A meditation on 1. Timoth. 6. 6. By Thomas Gataker B. of D. and pastor of Rotherhith.
            Gataker, Thomas, 1574-1654.
         
         
            
               1620
            
         
         Approx. 230 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01551
            STC 11678
            ESTC S102989
            99838748
            99838748
            3136
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01551)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3136)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1066:08)
         
         
            
               
                  True contentment in the gaine of godlines, with its self-sufficiencie A meditation on 1. Timoth. 6. 6. By Thomas Gataker B. of D. and pastor of Rotherhith.
                  Gataker, Thomas, 1574-1654.
               
               [8], 87, [1] p.   
               
                  Printed by Edward Griffin for William Bladen, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Bible, neere the great north dore of Paules,
                  London :
                  1620.
               
               
                  Also issued as part 2 of: Certaine sermons first preached and since published: London, 1622.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Contentment --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-10
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-11
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-05
            Judith SiefringSampled and proofread
         
            2006-05
            Judith SiefringText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            TRVE CONTENTMENT IN THE GAINE OF GODLINES, With its SELF-SUFFICIENCIE.
            
            A MEDITATION ON 1. TIMOTH. 6. 6.
            By THOMAS GATAKER B. of D. and Paſtor of Rotherhith.
            LONDON Printed by Edward Griffin for William 
                  〈…〉
                ſold at his ſhop at the ſigne 
                  〈…〉
                great North dore of Paules, 
                  ••••
               .
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHT WORTHY AND HIS MVCH HONOVRED LADY, the Lady DOROTHY HOBART, Wife to the Right Honorable and his ſingular good Lord, Sr HENRY HOBART, Knight and Baronet, Lord Cheife Iuſtice of the Common Pleas, True Contentment in the Gaine of Godlines, with its Self-Sufficiencie.
            
            
               
                  GOOD MADAME,
            
            It is a point by all generally agreed vpon, that 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Ariſtot. ethic. Ni
                        •••
                     . l. 1. c. 2, 4, 7. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Stob. tom. 1. 
                     
                        •
                     . 
                        •
                     . 
                        •
                     . 3. 
               Happineſſe is the maine end and aime of all mens Actions. And it is a Truth no leſſe generally confeſſed and acknowledged, that 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Ariſtot. ethic. Ni
                        •
                     om. l. 1. c. 7. Non eſt b
                        •
                     at
                        ••
                     , eſſe ſe qui non 
                        •••
                     at. P. Syr. Si 
                        ••
                     i ſua non videntur ampli
                        •••
                     ma, miſer est Epi
                        •••
                     . Miſer eſt, qui ſe non beati
                        ••
                     i
                        •••
                      i
                        ••
                     ic
                        •••
                      Sen. ep. 10. Nemo foelix eſt, qui iudicio ſuo miſer eſt. Sa
                        ••
                     . de prov. l. 
                  
                     •
                  . 
               Without Contentment
               
               of Minde there can be no true Happines. It is 
                  Omnlum certa ſen tentia eſt, beatos eſſe o
                        •
                     s homines velle. Aug. de civ. Dei l. 10. c. 1. &amp; Epiſt. 21. &amp; 121. Miſerè viuere nemo vult. Idem de lib. arb. l. 1. c. 14. Happines then that all men without exception deſire, and Contentment that all conſequently ſtriue to attaine. But here in the moſt faile, that they are miſtaken in the meanes, that they take wrong courſes for the compaſſing of this their end and aime &amp; ſo vai
                  •
               rely weary &amp; tire out themſelues in 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Arr
                        ••
                     n. diſſert
                        •
                     l. 2. c. 16. ſeeking Happines and Contentment there, where neither of them is to be had. To reforme this error, the Spirit of God in the Word hath directed vs the right way to either, to wit, Pſal. 86. 11. &amp; 144. 14. by conjunction with God, the author and fountaine of all good, 
                  Deut. 30. 20. Pſal. 73. 26, 28. Bonum noſtrū nullum eſt aliud quàm Deo adherere, cuim vnius anima intellectualis incorporeo amplexu impletur. Aug. de civit. Dei l. 10. c. 4. by adhering vnto him, in whō only the ſoule of man can find ſu
                  •
               e &amp; ſound contentment. Now this is done Deut. 30. 20. Ad 
                     •
                  um dilectione tendimꝰ, vt perven
                     •
                  ē
                  d
                     •
                   qu
                     ••••
                  am
                     ••
                  , i
                     ••
                  e
                     •
                   b
                     ••••
                  , 
                     〈…〉
                  
                by louing him 
                  Pſal. 
                  
                     〈…〉
                   
                  &amp; 
                  
                     〈…〉
                   &amp; 
                     ••
                  9. 
                     •
                   
                  
                     •••
                  . 
                     〈…〉
                  . 
                     •
                  3. by fearing him, 
                  Pſal. 
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                by truſting in him, 
                  Deut. 1
                     •
                  . 
                     •
                  7. &amp; 30. 
                     ••
                  . 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  
                     
                        〈…〉
                     .
                by obeying him▪ 
               
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                by conformitie vnto him, or more breiefely in a word, by 
                  
                     〈…〉
                  . 1. P
                     ••
                  . 1. 11. Holines, by 
                  
                     •
                  . Ti
                        •••
                     . 
                  
                     •••
                  . 
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                Godlines: for theſe two are in ſubſtance one and the ſame. So that there is 
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                no compaſſing of

Contentment or Happines without God, and there is no way vnto God but by Godlineſſe. For N
                     •
                  t
                     ••
                   omne conſilium, ne
                     •
                   implere no
                     •
                   vll
                     •
                   f
                     •
                  licit
                     ••
                   poteſt, donec 
                     •
                  oorenerimas ad bonum illud imm
                     ••
                  uſum &amp; inſuperabile, 
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     ••
                  ceſſe eſt reſist
                     ••
                   volunta
                     •
                  
                  ▪ noſtra, quia 
                     〈◊〉
                   ſu
                     〈…〉
                  non eſt locu
                     •
                  . Se
                     •
                  . epiſt. 74. God alone being the chiefeſt good, and the chiefeſt good each ones vtmoſt aime; our deſires cannot be ſtayed till we come home vnto him, beyond whom we can not poſſibly go. He being onely 
                  Gen. 17. 1. 
                     
                        •••
                      niſt 
                        〈…〉
                      a
                     
                        ••••
                      indigen
                        •
                     i
                        •
                      
                     
                        ••
                     pl
                        ••••
                      
                     
                        〈…〉
                      explend
                        •
                     , 
                        ••
                     ſt 
                        〈…〉
                      ſufficit. Aug. de 
                        •••
                     . l. 12. c. 1. 
               All-ſufficient; (and there can be no Contentment where any want is, nor freedome from want where Sufficiencie is not;) we can haue no true Contentment, till we haue once gained Him; we can haue no full Contentment, till we come wholy to enjoy Him, that he may be 1. Cor. 15. 28. all in all vnto vs. And this being Neceſſe eſt vt home inde beatu
                     •
                   ſit, vnde fit bonus. Aug. ep. 121. by Holilnes, by Godlines onely effected, it muſt needs follow, that the holier men are, the happier they are; and the more godly they are, the more true and ſound Contentment they are ſure of. 
                  Ap
                        ••
                     . 20. 6. Pſal. 119. 1. Math. 5. 8. We ſhall neuer be truly Happy, till we be ſincerely Holy, nor fully Happy, till we be perfectly Holy. We ſhall neuer attaine true Cōtentment till we be truly Religious, nor full Contentment till we be conſummate in Godlines. The

conſideration whereof ſhould encite all, that deſire Happines and Contentment, (and 
                  Vitā beatā omnē hominem modi
                        •
                      omnibus velle quis dubitat? Aug. de lib. arb. lib. 1. c. 14. Beatitudinem nemo eſt qui non expetat. quī enī vel poteſt, vel p
                        •
                     t
                        •
                     it, vel poterit i
                        ••
                     e
                        •
                     iri, qui eſſe nolit beat
                        ••
                     ? Aug. in Pſal. 118. co
                        ••
                     . 1. who is he, be he neuer ſo brutiſh, that doth not?) to bend their maine ſtudie and endeuor this way, for the compaſſing of this Grace and profiting in it; as the onely meanes availeable to bring them to that end; Omnes 
                     •
                  e
                     ••
                  it
                     •
                  
                  dinē concupiſo
                     ••••
                  
                  ſed quomodò ad eā p
                     〈…〉
                  , pl
                     •••
                  
                  
                  
                     ••
                   neſciunt. idem ibid. which, howſoeuer they may wander from, miſtaking the way, their whole deſire is to attaine vnto. To prouoke all ſorts hereunto, is the maine project propounded in this preſent diſcourſe. Which (what euer it be; and I wiſh it were much better;) I humbly preſent to your Ladiſhip, deſiring that it may helpe to ſupply ſome part of that dutie and ſeruice, which partly mine owne infirmitie and imbecillitie of bodie, and partly alſo other neceſſarie and vnauoidable imployments, will not ſuffer me to performe anſwerably to mine owne deſire, and mine Honorable Lords and your Ladiſhips deſert. And ſo wiſhing againe and againe vnto your Ladiſhip, (for what other, or what better thing can I wiſh?) that which the worke

it ſelfe importeth, true Contentment from God in this life, and full Contentment with God after this life; I take my leaue for the preſent, but ceaſe not to continue
            
               Your Ladiſhips euer to be commanded in the Lord, THO: GATAKER.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            TRVE CONTENTMENT.
         
            1. TIMOTH. 6. 6.
            Godlineſſe is great Gaine, with Selfe-ſufficiencie; or, with the Sufficiencie of it ſelfe.
         
         
            THE FORMER PART. The Gaine of Godlineſſe.
            
               THe Stoick Philoſophie, which Act. 17. 18. 
               Luke the Euangeliſt maketh mention of, Lege Cicer. parad. &amp; Lipſij 
                     •••
                  
                  nud
                     •
                  ct. was famous for Paradoxes, ſtrange Opinions, improbable, and beſides common conceit, Seneca paſſion, &amp; Arrian. in diſſert. &amp; alij. admired much for them by ſome, Plu
                     •
                  . in Stoic. contradict. &amp; quod Poet
                     •
                   Stoicis probabiliora la
                     ••
                  antur. controlled and taxed for them by others. Howbeit not Stoiciſme onely, but euery art and profeſſion, euery courſe of life and learning hath ſome Paradoxes or other; the

world not a few, and▪ 
               In hic creber est Chryſoſtomus: quod notavit Six
                     •
                  ꝰ Sen: biblioth: l. 4. Chriſtianitie many more, as ſtrange, yea ſtranger, than any that the Stoicks euer held, and yet 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Agatho. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Ariſtot. rhetor. l. 2. c. 26. Veriſſima
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      ſunt non pauca, quae tamen ſunt minimè veriſimilia.
                no leſſe true than ſtrange.
            A worldly Paradox the Apoſtle had mentioned in the verſe next before going, to wit, that ſome men ſhould hold Gaine to be Godlineſſe: vnto which he oppoſeth a contrary Chriſtian Paradox in the words of my Text, to wit, that Godlineſſe is the onely true Gaine.
            
            For the former: It is a very abſurd conceit indeed, and though too too rife in the world, yet ſuch as few or none will be acknowne of, and either openly father, or ſeeme outwardly to fauor. But as God at the laſt day, when the wicked ſhall go about to excuſe and defend themſelues, he will not onely take hold of their words, Ex ore tuo indicab
                     •
                   te, ſerue nequā. Math. 25. 26. Luk 19 22. 
               By thine owne mouth will I iudge thee, thou thriftles ſeruant; and aduantage of their actions, Math. 25. 42, 43. 
               I was naked and yee clad me not, hungry and yee fed me not, &amp;c. and thereſore had neither Faith nor Loue; but he will conuince them by their owne Conſciences too, Rom. 2. 15. 
               Their ſecret thoughts ſhall either excuſe or accuſe them in that day: In like manner muſt we deale with thoſe that will ſeeme to abhorre and deteſt this Opinion, and yet do thoſe things that maintaine and vphold it.
            
               Pſal. 14. 1. &amp; 53. 1. 
               
                  
                     •
                  he 
                     •
                  oole ſaith i
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   heart, There is no God; and that is ſufficient to proue him an Athe
                  ••
                though he neuer openly maintaine any Poſition of Atheiſme. And there be ſome that Tit. 1. 16. 
               profeſſe they know God, but denie him in their deeds: and 
                  Quieſcat lingua, loqua
                        •••
                      vita. Aug. in 1. Ioan. hom. 3. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . E
                        •
                     ſ
                        •
                     h. prepar E
                        •
                     a g. l. 1. c. 1. Efficacius est vita teſtimonium quā lingue▪ Cypriā. do dupl martyr▪ Et 
                        〈◊〉
                      v
                        ••
                      
                     
                        •
                     peris quàm 
                        •••
                     . 
                        •
                     ern. in C
                        •
                     nt.
                that is enough to proue them irreligious, though they neuer vtter that their impietie in ſpeech. So in this caſe, the Couetous

mans heart ſaith it, and his practiſe proclaimeth it, that Diuites facultatibus ſuis alligates mag
                     ••
                   aurum conſueuiſſe ſuſpic
                     •
                  re quàm coelū. Minut. Octav. Quid f
                     •
                  cisti quod iuſſit Deus? quid nō facis quod auaritia iubet? Aug. de diuerſ. 12. 
                     •
                  uam ſi ſacrificem ſummo Jovi, At
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   in manibus exta teneam vt porriciam, intereà loci. Si lucr
                     •
                   quid detur, potius r
                     •
                  m diuinā deſerā. Plaut. Pſeud. 1. 3. 
               his Gold is his God, and that his Gaine is his Godlineſſe; and that is ſufficient to proue him an Idolater, though he neuer outwardly bow his knee to an Idoll. In regard whereof, the Apoſtle expreſly pronounceth Coloſſ. 3. 5. 
               Couetouſnes to be Idolatry, and the Epheſ. 5. 5. Lege Chryſ ad Eph. hō. 18 
               Couetous man an Idolater.
            
            To reaſon then in this point, as our Sauiour himſelfe doth: Vbi theſaurus, ibi &amp; cor. Math. 6 21. Nemo enim potest niſi cogitare de theſauro ſuo, &amp; quodā cordis itinere diuitias ſuas ſequi. Aug. de diuerſ. 44. 
               Where a mans Treaſure is, theire is his Heart; and where a mans heart is, there is his happineſſe; and where his happineſſe is, that is his God. Since the couetous man therefore Pſal. 62. 12. 
               ſetteth his heart on his riches; 
               Pſal 49 6. Job. 31. 24. 
               putteth his trust in his treaſure: and whereas 
                  Pro. 18. 10. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Baſil. in Pſal. 45. the faithfull make the name of God their ſtrong towre, wherevnto they reſort in time of trouble for ſafetie, Pro. 18. 11. the worldly rich man maketh his wealth his bulwark &amp; fence, wherevpon he repoſeth himſelfe and wholy relyeth: It muſt of neceſſitie follow herevpon, that as the Apoſtle ſaith of the fleſhly-minded man, that Phil. 3. 19. Rom. 16. 18. Clem. p
                     •
                  dag. l. 2. c. 1. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . ventrē colūt, quē pro Deo habent. Cypr. de dupl. Martyr. Quibꝰ Deꝰ venter est, &amp; pulmo tēplū, &amp; aqualiculꝰ altare, &amp; ſacerdos cocꝰ, &amp; Spiritus ſanctꝰ nidor, &amp; codimēta chariſmata, &amp; 
                     •
                  uctꝰ prophetia: agape in cacab
                     ••
                   fervet, fi
                     •••
                   in c
                     •
                  l
                     ••
                  i
                     •
                   calet, ſpes in ferculis iacet. Tertull. de i
                     •
                  iun. Whoſe gut their God, whoſe luſt their law. Sylveſt. week. 2. day. 1. Viſe Euſeb praepar. l. 7. c. 2. 
               his belly is his God; ſo of the worldly-minded man, that 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Theog
                        •
                     . 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Euripid. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Antiphan. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  So phoel. Creuſa. Quod autem quiſque prae caeteris colit, id ſibi Deum conſt
                        ••
                     iſſe probatur Bern de bonis deſer. Ergo vt voracium Deus venter est; ita cupidorum pec
                        ••••
                      Deus iuſtiſſ
                        •
                     mè dicitur. Hieron. in Epheſ.
                
               his money, or

               his penny is his God: And if his Money be his God; his Gaine muſt needs be his Godlineſſe.
            
            But the Apoſtle here telleth vs a quite contrary tale, and learneth vs here a flat oppoſite leſſon; that, howſoeuer worldly men may thinke that Gaine is Godlineſſe; yet in deed and truth it is not ſo; but Godlineſſe rather is Gaine, and great Gaine.
            
            So that the Apoſtle doth 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , propoſitionem invertere; he turneth the propoſition cleane backward, and bringeth it about, as it were. Gaine is Godlineſſe, ſaith the worldly man. Nay, Godlineſſe is Gaine, and great Gaine, ſaith the Apoſtle, and the Spirit of God by him.
            But this peraduenture will ſeeme a Paradox as ſtrange as the former. As very few that will outwardly avow the former; ſo as few are there that are inwardly perſwaded of the latter. It ſeemeth a Paradox with the moſt.
            For, Godlineſſe great Gaine? may ſome man ſay. The contrary rather ſeemeth vndoubted and vndeniable, to wit, that Iſto t
                     •
                   pauperes, cùm nimis ſanctè pius. Plaut. Rudēt. 4. 7. Varro, reguſtatum digito terebrare ſal
                     •
                  num contentus perages, ſi vi
                     •
                  ere cum love te
                     •
                  di
                     •
                   P
                     •
                  rſ. ſat. 5. 
               Godlineſſe is a great enemie to Gaine. Balaam loſt great wealth and honor, becauſe he would not diſobey the word of God: 
                  Num. 24 11. 
               I had thought, ſaith Balak, to haue aduanced thee, and made thee a great man; but thy God hath kept thee from honour. Michah might haue bin a great man in Ahabs bookes, and very richly and royally reward
                  •
               d by him, if he would haue ſpoken but two words onely, as ſome other did; if he would but haue ſaid, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Aſcende in pace. 1 King. 22. 12, 13.
                
               Goe vp in peace. But his Godlineſſe hindred his Gaine; and not ſo onely, but was a meane to bring him into much trouble. So that it may ſeeme,

that Godlineſſe is altogither gaineleſſe, and Vngodlineſſe the more gainefull of the two.
            For the Nehem. 13. 16. Merchants of Tyre and Zidon for lucre and gaine ſtraine courteſie with Gods commandement, to vtter their fiſh and wares on the Sabbath. And no doubt of it, Facilē eſſe cui
                     •
                   ad diuitias viam, quo die bon
                     •
                   mentis poenituerit. Demetrius apud Senecam natur. queſt. l. 4. pr
                     •
                  fat. Gods children, if they would not be ſo ſtrict and ſtrait laced; if they would not ſtand vpon nice points and termes; if they would not ſticke to lye and diſſemble with Act. 5. 1, 2. 
               Ananias and Sapphira; to belye and beguile, as Ziba, Mephiboſheths man did his Maſter; to ſweare and forſweare,y 1 Sam. 16. 1, 2. with 1 Macc. 1. 61, 62. prophane Antiochus; to ſteale and purloine with yong Iudg. 17. 2. 
               Micah of Mount Ephraim; to oppreſſe and murther, when they haue ius in manibus, the law in their owne hands, with 1 King. 21. wicked Ahab, and curſed Iezabel; they might as well come to wealth, as many worldly men do, that ſcrape and gather much goods togither by theſe meanes. But they may well ſay, as the Pſalmiſt ſaith, Pſal. 67. 7. Eu
                     •
                   qui ſit iuſtus ac bonus, ſtultum eſſe. Carneades apud Ci
                     •
                  . de repub. l. 3. Viſe Lactant. inſtitut. l. 5. c. 12. 14. 
               For thy ſake, O Lord, are we counted fooles; becauſe we ſtand ſo much vpon matter of conſcience.
            
               1 Cor. 9. 15. 23. Holy Paul ſaith he might haue done this and that, but he would not, becauſe he would not make the Goſpell euill ſpoken of. And the keeping of a mans word turneth oft-times to his loſſe. The Pſal. 15. 4. godly man ſweareth and faileth not, though it be to to his owne hindrance: that which a worldly man will not willingly do. So that it may ſeeme then that Godlineſſe is rather a great enemie to Gaine, and Vngodlineſſe a great deale the more gainfull.
            
            But thoſe that define Loſſe and Gaine on this wiſe, do not try them by the right touch-ſtone, do

not weigh them out in the Ballance of the Sanctuarie, at the Beame of Gods word: and therefore no maruaile, if they take the L
                     •
                  k. 16 11. Diuitie nec vere nec veſtr
                     •
                  . Aug. de verb. Dom. 35. &amp; de diuerſis. &amp; Bern. de bon. deſer. 
               falſe Riches for the true Treaſure.
            
            For Geneſ. 2. 19. man indeed had auctoritie giuen him to name the Creatures, and he hath named worldly Wealth, Gaine: But God that is aboue man, and that gaue man this auctoritie, he hath named Godlineſſe, Gaine, and not Wealth. As the Apoſtle therefore ſaith, 2 Pet. 3. 9. 
               God is not ſlacke, as men count ſlacknes: ſo Godlineſſe is not Gaine as men count Gaine, but as God counteth Gaine. For 1 Sam. 16. 7. 
               man ſeeth not as God ſeeth; 
               Eſai. 55. 
                     •
                  . 
               nor thinketh as God thinketh. But as Luk. 16. 15. thoſe things that are pretious in mans eyes, are abominable in Gods ſight: ſo 1 Cor. 1. 28. Pſal. 51. 17. thoſe things that are contemptible in the eyes of man, are 1 Pet. 3. 4. of high account many times in the ſight of God. And euery thing is, not as man valueth it, but as God eſteemeth it; not as man reckneth it, who is Pſal. 62 9. &amp; 39. 5. 
               vanitie it ſelfe, and therefore may eaſily be deceiued, yea Galat. 6. 3. Jam. 1. 26. oft-times deceiueth himſelfe; but as God rateth it, Tit. 1. 2. Si v
                     •
                  
                  lunt in
                     •
                  enire, quod 
                     〈◊〉
                   non poteſt, habent prorſus, 
                     •
                  entiri non poteſt. Aug. de ci
                     •
                  it. l. 22. 
                     •
                  . 25. Potenter hoc non poteſt. Idem de Trinit. l. 15. c. 14. Magna potentia mentiri non poſſe. Ibid. 15. who neither doth deceiue any, Galat. 6. 7. nor can by any be deceiued, being 
                  Iob. 14. 6. 
               Veritie and truth it ſelfe.
            Either then we muſt ſay as God ſaith, or we muſt ſay as the World ſaith. Either we muſt ſay, that Godlineſſe is no Gaine, or elſe we muſt ſay, that Gaine is no Gaine, when Godlineſſe and Gaine ſhall ſtand forth togither, either in way of compariſon the one with the other, or in way of oppoſition the one vnto the other.
            Now, when Godlineſſe and Gaine ſhall in this manner contend, that Godlineſſe ought to haue

the day of it, will euidently appeare, if it may be ſhewed vnto vs:
            Firſt, that Godlines is Gaine rather than Gaine: and
            Secondly, wherein this Gaine of Godlineſſe doth conſiſt.
            For the former, to wit, that Godlineſſe is rather to be accounted Gaine, than Gaine, may be proued to vs by theſe three Arguments.
            Firſt, Godlineſſe may doe a man good without gaine, but worldly gaine can do a man no good without godlineſſe. As the Heathen Orator ſaith of bodily might, that 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Iſocr. ad Demonic.
                
               ſtrength of bodie ioyned with diſcretion and wiſdome, may do a man much good; but without it, it is but 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plut. de muliebri diſciplina apud Stob. tō. 2. c. 90.
                
               as a ſword in a child, or in a mad mans hand, rather a meanes to miſchiefe a mans ſelfe than otherwiſe: as we ſee an example in Milo Crotoniates, the ſtrongeſt man of his time, - viribus ille cō
                  
                  
                     ••
                  ſus perij
                     •
                  , admirandiſque lacertis. Iuvenal. ſat. 10. Legatur Gellius l. 15. c. 16. &amp; Val. Max. l. 9. c. 12. Qui concludit, Nimio robore memb
                     •
                  o
                     •
                  ū 
                  
                     •
                  igorem mentis hebeſcere, quaſi abnu
                     •
                  nte natura vtriuſque boni largitionē, ne ſupra mortalem ſit foelicitatē, eundem &amp; valentiſſimum eſſe &amp; ſapientiſſ
                     •
                  
                  mum. who vnwarily aſſaying, on truſt of his ſtrength, to riue a peece of timber with his hands, which ſome others with wedge and beetle could not cleaue, was caught faſt by the fiſts, and ſo deuoured by Wolues. So Riches ioyned with godlineſſe and good Conſcience, are the Omnia iſta bon
                     •
                   ſunt, ſed vnde
                     •
                  acias be
                     •
                  e, non quae te faciant bonū. Aug. de temp. 238. good bleſſings of God, a meanes Deus b
                     •
                  nadat, vt b
                     •
                  nos faciat. Salvian. de prouid. of good to our ſelues, and of doing good vnto others: but being ſeuered from godlineſſe and the true feare of God, are rather 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Euripid. Ple
                        •
                     ſthen. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Menand. 
                        •
                     opes iritamenta malorum. O
                        ••
                     d. Metam. l. 1.
                occaſion of euill than otherwiſe, rather 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Iſcer ad Demon. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Eurip. Phaethon. Magna cognatio vt rei, ſic nomi
                        ••
                     s, diuitijs &amp; vitijs. Eucher. ad Valer.
                an inſtrument of vice, than any furtherance to virtue, a meane to make as our ſinnes the greater here, ſo

our condemnation accordingly the more grieuous hereafter.
            So that as the Heathen man ſaith, that Damnū non lucrum eſt cum mala fama lucrū. P. Syr. 
               Gaine gotten by loſſe or hazard of a mans good name, is no gaine but loſſe; becauſe a man looſeth therein more then all his gettings can counteruaile: ſince that 
                  Prou. 22. 1. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Iſocr. ad Dem
                        •
                     . 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Menād.
                
               A good name is (as Salomon ſaith) aboue riches and treaſure; of greater worth than any wealth. So Gaine gotten with the breach or hazard of a good Conſcience, when it is Luk. 16. 9. 
               mammona iniquitatis, the Mammon of iniquitie, or Iud. 11. 
               merces iniquitatis, the wages of wickedneſſe, it is 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . titulus ſine re. Chryſost. in Pſal. 111. 
               no Gaine, but loſſe indeede: It is, as the Greekes ſay of 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Heraclit. apud Euſtath. ad Iliad. 
                     •
                  . 
               a Bow, Life in name, but Death indeede; ſo Gaine in name, but Loſſe in deede: (
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Heſiod. 
                        〈…〉
                     
                   
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Chilo. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Peri
                        ••
                     d. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Eurip. Cyclope. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Idem Ant
                        •
                     gon. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Me
                        •
                     and. Periculoſum ſemper reputa
                        •
                     i lucrū. Ph
                        •
                     drꝰ fab. 85. Heathen themſelues ſo eſteemed it; not Nemo habet i
                     •••
                  ſ
                     ••
                   lucrū ſint iuſte dān
                     •
                  . Aug. de temp. 215. Lucra in
                     •
                  i
                     •
                  ſta putes iuſtis aqu
                     •
                  li
                     •
                   dam
                     ••
                  . Dū 
                  
                     ••••
                  tura per
                     ••
                   per male parta peris. G. Goodwi
                     •
                  . Luc
                     •
                  ū improbè partūm
                     •
                  rū eſt in
                     〈…〉
                  . R
                     ••
                  
                  ter
                     ••••
                  . Chriſtian men onely:) Since that a man doth in theſe caſes but, as that Romane Emperor had wont to ſay, 
                  
                     ••
                  s qui mi
                     ••••
                   c
                     •••
                  da nō minime ſectarētur diſcrimine, ſi
                     •
                  iles ai
                     •
                  bat eſſe 
                     〈…〉
                   
                  
                     ••
                  r
                     ••
                   piſca
                     •
                  tib
                     ••
                  , 
                     〈…〉
                   nulla c
                     •
                  p
                     ••
                  r
                     •
                   penſari poſſet. S
                     •
                  et
                     •
                  n. Auguſto 
                     •
                  . 25. 
               fiſh with a golden hooke, and that for a googeon: 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . De
                        ••
                     tr. Phal
                        •
                     r. apud. Athen. l. 6. he hazardeth more than his whole prey, though he catch it, and 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Democrit. Turpe lucrum vi
                        ••••
                     u eſt de
                        •
                     rime
                        ••
                     um. Ambr. in Pſal. 118. Plus in ipſa ini
                        •
                     ri
                        •
                      detrimenti eſt, quàm in 
                        〈◊〉
                      rebus 
                        〈…〉
                     . Ci
                        •••
                      
                     
                        •
                     e 
                        •••
                     ib. l. 
                  
                     •
                  . Neque tantum eſt co
                        •••
                     d
                        •
                      quia 
                        •
                     
                     dip
                        •
                     ſ
                        ••
                      ſe p
                        ••••
                     , quantum 
                        〈…〉
                      ac
                        ••
                     rſat. Ambroſ. offic. l. 3. c. 4. ver
                        •
                      itaque Antipha
                        ••
                     s, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . he may miſſe of his purpoſe therein too, can make amends for it, if it miſcarry, be

that he get and gaine neuer ſo much. And for a man to get and gaine neuer ſo much one way, if by the compaſſing of it he looſe far more an other way, it is in truth no Gaine at all.
            For this cauſe as the Apoſtle asketh the Queſtion; Rom. 6. 21. 
               Quid profuit? What profit had yee then of thoſe things, whereof you are now aſhamed? nay, Si ſecundū merita tibi daret, dā
                  naret te. Aug. in Pſal. 102. for which now you ſhould be damned, if you had your deſert; for the end of ſuch things is death: And the damned Spirits demand of themſelues; Wiſdom. 5. 8. 
               Quid prodest? What profit haue we now of all our profits and pleaſures, that we enioyed in the world, when we are hurled headlong into hell? So our Sauiour himſelfe asketh, Matth. 16. 26. 
               Quid proderit? What will it profit a man to winne the whole world, 
               Luk 9. 35. 
               and deſtroy himſelfe, 
               
                  Mark 8. 36, 37. 
               or looſe his owne 
               Iſte omnis huius queſtus ſeculi animarum diſpendium est. Ambroſ. epist. 44. Caue itaque ne dum acquiras pecuniam, perdas animam. Aug. de temp. 215. 
               ſoule? 
               Non poteſt vlla compendij cauſa cō
                  ſistere, ſi conſtet animae diſpendium intervenire. vbi ſalutis damnum, illic vtique iam nullum lucrū eſt. quo enim lucrū capiatur, niſi capiendi ſedes inconcuſſa ſeruetur? Eucher. ad Valer. O ſi lucreris totum, quid proderit, orbem, Dum iacturam anima feceri
                     •
                   ipſae tuae. Tale tibi foe
                     ••
                   fert lamentabile fun
                     ••
                  : Hic
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   illex quaſtus queſtus &amp; 
                     •
                  ſtus erit. Ne perdas perdenda, animam, ſtultiſſime, perdes: Nunc ſanum inſan
                     •
                   ſynciput opto tibi. G. Goodwin. to get all the world beſide himſelfe; but by gaining it to looſe himſelfe: for Animus cuiuſque ipſe est quiſque. Cic. de amicit. euery mans ſoule is euery mans ſelfe: to doe as Jona. 1. 12. 
               Ionas, 
               
                  At contra Ariſtippus in nare piratica agen
                        •
                      cùm aurum in mare proieciſſet, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Laert. Et Crates miſſo in mare, auro, Abite, inquit, peſſum mala cupiditates, mergam vos, ne mergar à nobis. Hieron. in Iovin. l. 2. Pereat mundi lucrum ne fiat anima damnum. Aug. in Pſal. 103. Perde ne pereas. Idem de verb. Dom. ſerm. 35. that ſuffred himſelfe to be caſt ouerbord into the ſea, that the ſhip with her lading, when he is loſt, may come ſafe to the ſhore.
            On the other ſide, as another ſaith, Pecuniam in loco negligere, maximum interdum eſt lucrum. Terent. adelph. 2. 2. Non ego omninò lucrum omne eſſe vtile homini exiſtimo: Eſt etiam vbi profecto damnum praeſtet facere, quàm lucrum. Plaut. Capt. 2. 2. 
               For a man handſomely to refuſe money, and forgo gaine, it is no ſmall gaine ſometime. So for a man in ſome caſe to forgo his gaine, to refuſe gold, to neglect his owne

good, though Quis niſi mentis in
                     •
                  ps oblatum reſpuat aurum? ſo to do may ſeeme 
                  •
               olly, when Game and Godlineſſe will not agree togither, when Aug. de tēp. 215. 
               lucrum in arca facit damnum in conſcientia, and Ambroſ. in Pſal. 218. ſer. 5. 
               lucrum pecuniae diſpendium 
                     •
                  it animae; when profit in a mans purſe would procure a broach in his Conſcience, and the gaine of gold proue the break-neck of his ſoule; 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Georg. Pr
                        •
                     id. de vanitat. vita.
                ſuch refuſall of gaine is the greateſt Gaine that can be. For ſaith an ancient Father well, Quan
                     •
                  ūlibe
                     •
                   magna amittere, vt m
                     •
                  iora acquiras, nō eſt damnum ſed negotiatio. Bern. de bon deſ. 
               To let goe, though neuer ſo great a matter, for the compaſsing of a greater, is no looſing bargaine, but a gainefull negotiation. To which purpoſe the Apoſtle Paul hauing related, what a great man he might haue bin among his owne People, had he held on in Iudaiſme as he began; he concludeth at length, that he deemed all
               Philip. 3. 7, 8, 9. that, and all elſe, but as 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               loſſe, and as 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               droſſe and donge; as ſome Grammarians expound the word there vſed, as 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               Dogs-meat, or as others rather, as Dogs-donge, in regard of the aſſurance of Gods ſauour toward him in Chriſt, the hold he had of him, his conformitie with him, and his intereſtk 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  H
                        ••
                     ych. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
                     
                        ••
                     yolog. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . in him.
            Secondly, Worldly 
                     〈◊〉
                   may be a
                     •
                   occaſion of euill to vs from others; God
                     ••
                  eſſe 
                     ••••
                  r but of good. Riches, I ſay, proue o
                  •
               t their owners owne bane, his vtter 
                  〈…〉
                and o
                  •••••
               row. 
                  Eccleſ. 5. 12. Sed pl
                        •
                     r
                        •
                     s 
                        〈…〉
                      conge
                     
                        •••
                      p
                        •••
                     n
                        •
                     a 
                        •
                     ura 
                        〈…〉
                     , &amp; cun
                     
                        •••
                      ex
                        •
                     p
                        •
                     r
                        •
                     n
                        •
                      pa
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                     
                        •
                     enſus. I
                        •
                     v
                        •
                     n ſat. 10. Quanti e verſi ſunt per 
                        〈…〉
                     , pr
                        •
                     da forti
                        •
                     ribus facti? Aug in Pſal. 
                  
                     •
                  3. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plut▪ P
                        •
                     
                     
                     
                        ••
                     g.
                
               I haue ſeene riches, ſaith Salomen, reſerued to the hurt of him that hath them. 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   Di
                     •
                  gen
                     •
                  s apud 
                     •
                  a
                     •
                  rt. 
                     〈…〉
                  
                  ▪ ma
                     •
                  ꝰ Do
                     •••
                  ꝰ, pr
                     •
                  di
                     ••
                  r ſerv
                     •
                  t nemo 
                     〈◊〉
                   habet, niſi qu
                     •
                   ſemper abſcondi
                     •
                  ; in 
                     〈…〉
                  . Aug. de verb. A
                     •
                   26. They make their owners life oft-time to

be laid for. It was the Heathen mans obſeruation, that Tyrannies deale with their ſubiects and ſeruants, as men are wont to do 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . de Diony
                        •
                     io Diogenes.
                
               with bottles, which they let ſtand vnder the tap till they be filled, and hang them vp ſo ſoone as they be full: or as Procuratorē rapaciſſimum quem
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ad officia amplior
                     •
                   ex induſtria pr
                     •
                  
                  movebat, quo lo
                     •
                  upletiores mo
                     •
                   condemn
                     •
                  ret, &amp; pr
                     •
                   ſpongijs v
                     •
                  eretur, quos ſicco
                     •
                   madefacimꝰ, 
                     •
                  umen
                     •
                  es exprimimus. de Veſpaſian
                     •
                   Su
                     ••
                  on. c. 16. Idem de popule Athen. Ariſtophan. Equitib. 
               with Spunges, which they ſuffer to lye ſoaking, till they haue ſucked in ſome good ſtore of water, and then ſquize them out againe. 1 King. 21. 1, 2. Exitialu erat apud principem hui
                     •
                   laxior dom
                     ••
                  , illi am
                     •
                  nior villa. Plin. pa
                     •
                  egyr. 
               Naboth might well haue liued longer, had it not bin for his vineyard: but that was it that ſhortned his dayes, and brought him to an vntimely death. And 
                  Pro
                        •
                     . 1. 19. Acceſſit vt ſauiti
                        •
                      cauſ
                        •
                      auariti
                        •
                      praeberet, &amp; modus culpae ex pecuniae modo conſtitueretur; &amp; qui fuiſſet locuples fieret n
                        •
                     cens, fieret ꝙ quiſque merces mortis ſu
                        •
                     . Velleius hiſt. l. 2. Diviſa percuſſoribus occiſorum bona, v
                        •
                      etiam de ſu
                        •
                      perirent. Senec. ad Mart. 
                        •
                     . 20. 
               This, ſaith Salomon, is the courſe of euery one that is greedy of gaine, to come by it, he would take the life away of thoſe that are poſſeſſed of it. 
               Pirat
                     •
                   navigijs vacuis non inſidiantur, mercibus 
                     •
                  nuſta vi omni invadunt. Chryſost. de Ozia ſerm. 3. It is not empty barks, or poore fiſher-boats, but ſhips returning with treaſure, that Pyrates ſeeke to ſurprize. P
                     •
                  ucula ſi portes argenti vaſcula puri, N
                     •
                  c
                     •
                  e i
                     •
                  er ingreſſus, gladium contumꝰ, timebis: Cant
                     •
                  bit vacu
                     ••
                   coram latr
                     •
                  ne viator. Juve
                     •
                  . ſat. 10. Si
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  im
                     •
                  t inſidi
                     ••
                  , qui ſe ſcit ferre viator Quod time at, tutum carpitinanis iter. Ovid. Nuc
                     •
                  .  It is the fat Graſier, or the rich Clothier,  Nudū latro tranſmittit: etiam in obſeſſa via pauperi pax eſt. Sen. de pauper
                     •
                  . ex epiſt. 14. not the poore pedler, or the bare paſſenger, that is in danger of looſing lim and life in his owne defence againſt theeues.
            But Godlineſſe is neuer an occaſion of any euill, but of all good to him that hath it. It is 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Tyri
                        ••
                      Ma
                        •
                     . 
                        •
                     r
                        •
                     t. 
                        •
                     . murus aheneu
                        •
                     . Nil conſcire ſibi. Horat. epiſt. 2. lib. 1. Ier. 1. 18. the ſureſt fort and fence, it is 
                  Epheſ. 614. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Chryſoft in Epheſ. hō. 24. the firmeſt armour of proofe againſt all euils that may be. For, Who will harme
               
               you, ſaith the 1 Pet. 3. 13. Et in hoc ſeculo quis nocebit nobis plenis charitate? Aug. in 1. Ioan. Tract. 9. Apoſtle, if you follow that that is good? Who will harme you? Nay, Tu ipſe tibi 
                     •
                  i aliquid faciat, malus quid faciat? Aug. homil. 
                     •
                  9. 
               Who can harme you? For ſome would it may be, if they could; ſo peruerſely and malitiouſly-minded, that they hate the godly, euen for this cauſe becauſe they be godly, and Pſal. 38. 20. 
               becauſe they follow that that is good. But 
                  Rom. 8. 31. Pſal. 27. 1, 2. Ier. 1. 18, 9. Act. 18. 10. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  S
                        •••
                     . tom 2. 
                     •
                  . 9. 
               if God be with them, who can be againſt them? who can hurt them? who can harme them? 
                  S
                        •
                     it
                        •
                      Sim
                        •
                     catus epiſt. 40. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Men may attempt to wrong them, and wrong themſelues while they thinke to wrong them; but them they cannot wrong. Though others may ſeeme to wrong them, yet 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . S
                        •
                     mo
                        •••
                     . 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Tyr. Max. orat 2. Sio 
                        〈◊〉
                     , 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . are they not wronged, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   Occidere 
                     〈◊〉
                  , lad
                     •
                  re non poſſ
                     ••
                  nt. S
                     ••
                  rates a 
                     〈◊〉
                   Epictetum Enchi
                     •
                  id
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈…〉
                  . &amp; Tyr. Max. Orat. 2. no not when they are murthred, becauſe they are nouer a whit the worſe for their wrongs. No hurt therefore, Luk. 21. 18. Illi de animab
                     ••
                   ſuia pertimeſceba
                     ••
                  , Chriſtu
                     ••
                  tiam 
                     〈◊〉
                   ſ
                     ••
                  uritatem ipſi
                     •
                   d
                     •
                  bat. quid 
                     •
                   p
                     •
                  reat, cui 
                     〈…〉
                   Aug. 
                     〈◊〉
                   Pſal. 96. &amp; 109. 
                     •
                  
                  ▪ 
                 
               not an haires harme can be fall a man for being good, or by being godly; Nihil accidere bon
                     •
                   wire 
                     〈◊〉
                   poteſt. S
                     •
                  n
                     ••
                  
                  ▪ de provid. c. 2. no euill can accrew vnto any by it.
            No euill can; but much good may; yea all good ſhall. For Rom. 8. 28. 
               All things worke togither, and conſpire in one, for the good of the godly, of theſe that loue God, and 
               
                  
                     〈…〉
                  . 
               whom he loueth. 
               
                  
                     〈…〉
                   Dr
                     •
                   l. 13. 6. 8. 
               Omnia? What? all things? ſaith an ancient Father, as if he could hardly beleeue it, or made ſome doubt of it: Etiam mala 
                     •
                   what? euen euills and afflictions too? Mala 
                     〈◊〉
                  . Yea (ſaith he) euen euills and afflictions; 5 
               bonis bona, malis mala: though euill to the wicked, yet good they

are, yea exceeding good to the godly. For, Audi Apostolum, audi vas electionis; Heare what the Apoſtle ſaith, heare what the elect veſſell of God ſaith: 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 2. Cor. 4. 18. 
               This light and momentanie affliction, that is but for an inſtant; procureth vnto vs, 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               an exceeding exceſsiue eternall weight of glory. He moueth the queſtion the ſecond time, as not fully reſolued: Omnia? what? all things? etiam peccatum? euen ſpirituall euils? euen ſinne it ſelfe too? And he maketh anſwer againe: Etiam peccatum ipſum, tametſi non bonū, tamen in bonum. Yea, euen ſinne it ſelfe, though it be not of it ſelfe good, yet it tendeth to their good, 
               Vide e
                     •
                  nd. Aug. de corrept. &amp; grat. cap. 9. to the good of all Gods elect. For heare what the Apoſtle ſaith of himſelfe: 2 Cor. 12. 7. 
               There was a 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      in carne. Beza.
                
               ſplint left in my fleſh to humble me, that I might not be puft vp with pride. 
               Nonne cooperatur nobis in bon
                     •
                  m, vnde &amp; humiliores &amp; cautiores efficimur? Bern. in Pſ. 90. His infirmities were a meane to make him the more humble; and 
                  Quant
                        •
                      quis humilior in ſe fuerit, tanto apud Deu
                        •
                      maior erit. Aug. de temp. 213. &amp; Greg. de paſt. p. 2. cap. 6. &amp; mor. l. 18. c. 22. as the more lowly in his owne eyes, ſo the more gracious with God. He asketh yet a third queſtion, as the vpſhot of all: Omnia? etiam mors ipſa? What? all things? euen death it ſelfe, 
               1 Cor. 15. 26. 
               the vtmoſt enemie of all? And he anſwereth himſelfe as before, or rather further than before; Mors bonis b
                     •
                  n; plurimum confort. Aug. ad Bonif. l. 4. c. 4. 
               Etiam mors vel maxime: Yea, death as much as any thing, nay most of all. For ſo ſaith the ſame Apoſtle againe; 
                  Philip. 1. 21. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Quod 
                        •
                      prim
                        •
                      exp
                        •
                     
                     fur
                        ••
                     e Ad
                        •
                     ur. A
                        •
                     
                     ray in Philip. 
                        ••
                     ct. 17. 
               Chriſtus mihi vita, &amp; mors lucrum; as he readeth the words; Chriſt is my life, and Death is my gaine. That Pro
                     •
                  . 11. 7. which is the greateſt loſſe that can be to the worldly man; is Philip. 
                     •
                  2. 3. the greateſt matter of gaine that can be to the godly.
            Thirdly, Wordly wealth abideth with vs but for a ſhort time: whereas Godlineſſe and
               
               Illud ſolum eſt lucrum, vbi fructus perpetu
                     •
                  s, vbi merc
                     •
                  s
                     •
                  st 
                     •
                   
                  
                     •••
                  na. An
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈…〉
                   
                  
                     ••
                  eſt 
                     〈◊〉
                  , 
                     〈◊〉
                   quod habet ſecum 
                     〈…〉
                   poteſt. quod enim hic 
                     〈…〉
                   noſt
                     ••
                  m, ſed ali
                     •
                  num eſt. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . epiſt. 9. 
               the Gaine of it will ſticke by vs, &amp; ſtay with vs for euer. This worlds wealth, I ſay, can laſt but a while with vs, &amp; muſt needs therfore leaue vs after a while. Non ſunt 
                     〈◊〉
                   diui
                     •
                  i
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   poſſiden
                     ••
                   deſerunt, 
                     〈◊〉
                   poſſident
                     •
                   deſeruntur. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . in Eccloſ. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . 
               Either it will leaue vs, 
                     •
                  r we must leaue it: 
               Finā 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   iſta 
                     〈…〉
                   ſuum. Bern, de b
                     ••
                  , deſer. Habebūt ſuū, non tuum, finē. Sen. 
                     •
                  atur qu
                     •
                  ſt. l. 3. 
               either it will haue an end of vs, 
                     •
                  r we an end of it. 
               1 Tim. 6. 17. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   Ch
                     •
                  yſoſt. to
                     •
                  . 
                     •
                  . ſer. 19. 
               Riches are vncertaine: 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Ibid. ſerm. 18. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Ihid. 19. there is no hold of them: they are ſlippry ware; 
                  Pro
                        •
                     : 
                  
                     ••
                  . 24. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   Ch
                     •
                  yſoft. ſ
                        •
                     rm. 18. the faſter we gripe them, the ſooner they ſlip oft out of our hands; 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Ibid.
                they are fugitiue ſeruants, ready to runne away from their maſter, whom they leaue many times, by their meanes, depriued, not of liuing onely, but of life too: Pro. 23. 6. 
               they take them wings, ſaith Salomon, like an Eagle that flieth vp into the ayre, &amp; get them a way from vs far out of our reach, and beyond all hope o
                  •
               re
                  •
               oueri.
            But though they haue al as aquilinas, great Eagles wings to flie from vs withall while we are here; yet haue they ne paſſerin as quidem, not ſo much as litle ſ
                     ••
                  r
                     •
                  wes wings to flie after vs, and follow 
                  〈◊〉
                when we go hence. 
                  
                     •
                  
                  ▪ Tim. 6. 7. Nihil 
                     〈…〉
                   &amp; ibi
                     •
                  . 41. As when we came into the world▪ we brought them not with vs; ſo when we goe out of the world againe, we cannot beare them away, but Cede
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  , &amp; dom
                     •
                  , Villaque; -Cedes: &amp; 
                     ••
                  tructis in altum Divit
                     •
                  s 
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     ••
                  
                  res. H
                     •
                  rat carm. 
                     •
                  . 3. 
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  , 
                     〈◊〉
                  , &amp; 
                     〈◊〉
                  , &amp; 
                     〈…〉
                  , quas c
                     •
                  lis, 
                     〈…〉
                  . Ibid. 14. 
                     〈◊〉
                   ad 
                     〈…〉
                  . muſt leaue them behind vs. 
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                  ▪. 16, 17. 
                     〈◊〉
                  
                
               Admire not the
               
               man that is riſen ſodninely to great riches and honour, ſaith the Pſalmiſt. No? why, who would not admire one that liueth in ſuch ſtate and pomp as Nihil eſt inſolentius noviti diuite. Sen. lib. 2. controv. 1. ſuch are vſually wont to do? Vides viu
                     •
                  ntem: c
                     •
                  gita mori
                     ••
                  tem. quid hic habeat, a
                     •
                  
                  tendis: quid ſecum tollat, ar
                     •
                  ēd
                     •
                  . Aug. &amp; Ruffin. in Pſ 48 Yea but, when he dieth, he ſhall carrie none of that his wealth away with him; nor ſhall his pompe and ſtate deſcend with his corps. 
               Eccl
                     •
                  ſ. 5. 14, 15. 
               As he came naked, ſo ſhall he go naked againe, and leaue all that by his care and induſirie he had raked togither and heaped vp, behind him; and in all reſpects goe euen as he came.
            
            It is with vs in this world, as it was in the Iewiſh fields and vineyards; Deut. 23. 24, 25. plucke and eat they might what they would, while they were there, but they might not pocket or put vp ought to carry away with them: Or Mund' iſte gardinus eſt, nos p
                     ••
                  ri, mors ia
                     ••
                  t 
                     •
                  . &amp;. Gvil. Pariſ. ſumma de vi
                     •
                  ijs, &amp; Al
                     •
                  o
                     •
                  . Carpent. deſtruct. vit: p. 4. 
                     •
                  . 
                     •
                  . as with boyes, that hauing gotten by ſtealth into an Orchard, ſtuffe their ſleeues and their pockets full with apples and peares, well hoping to get out with them, but when they come to the dore, they finde one there that ſearcheth them, and taketh all their fruit away from them, and ſo ſendeth them away with no more than they brought in: Or Guil. Pariſ. &amp; Alex. Carp. ibid. as poore men, that invited to a rich mans bord, haue the vſe of his plate to drink
                  •
                in, and ſiluer ſpoones to eat with while they are there; but if any of them preſume to put vp a peece of plate or a ſpoone, there is ſearch made by the Porter, ere they are let out, for what is miſſ
                  •
               ng among them, and ſo are they turned out againe as they came in: In like manner is it with vs in regard of theſe temporall bleſſings; we haue free libertie to vſe them as we will while we are here; but when we are to goe hence, 
                  Mors mund
                        •
                      
                     
                        ••
                     
                     ſor; qui oues elus in 
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     , &amp; a
                        •
                     conſas 
                        〈◊〉
                      mū
                     dam 
                        〈…〉
                     . Iacob. 
                        •
                     e
                        •
                     , do
                        ••
                     n. 2. poſt Pa
                     •
                  th. ſerm. 1. 
                     •
                  ors 
                     〈◊〉
                   eſt, qui 
                     〈…〉
                   o
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  . 
                     〈◊〉
                  . 
                     〈◊〉
                  . mort. tract. 1. 
                     •
                  . 6, 
                     〈…〉
                   
                  
                     •••
                  
                  tos. Chryſoſt. in Pſat. 4
                     •
                  . there is one waiting on vs,

that will be ſure to ſtrip vs, and ſuffer nothing to paſſe with vs, vnleſſe it be ſome ſory ſheete, or a ſeare rag to rot with vs, 
                  Non magis h
                        •
                     c ad defunctum pertinent hominem, quàm ſecundae ad editum infantem. Sen. epiſt 92. Iſtud non ſentienti ſupervacuum eſt, ſentienti onus. Nō defunctorū cauſa, ſed vivorum, inventa eſt ſepultura, vt corpora viſu &amp; odore foed
                        •
                      amorerentur. Idem de remed. fortuit. Exhibentur iſta nō ſentienti: tanquā or
                     
                        •
                     atꝰ dormie
                        •
                     ti, qui in pannis eſſe ſ
                        •
                      ſomniat. Aug. in Pſal. 48. Sed &amp; vnguentum accipis diues, poſtquā mortuus es, &amp; foetidus es. Perdis alienam gratiam, nec acquiris tuam. Ambr. de Nabuth. c. 1. that which yet we ſhall haue no ſenſe of, nor be any whit at all the better for, than if we were wholy without it.
            But Godlineſſe, and the gaine of it, will abide by vs for euer. 
                  Sicut charitas 1. Cor. 13. 8. ſic pi
                        •
                     t
                        ••
                      non excidit. Ier. 32. 40. Pſal. 85. 8. H
                        •
                      ſunt vere diviti
                        •
                     , quas cum habuerimus, 
                        •••
                     dere non 
                        〈◊〉
                     
                     ▪ Aug, de verb 
                  
                     〈…〉
                  . 76. It is a grace that we cannot looſe or fall from; 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Pl
                        •
                     t. d
                        ••
                     thi
                        •
                     . virt. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Pl
                        •
                     t. de p
                        •
                     dag. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
                     〈…〉
                   poteſt vnquam: 
                     〈…〉
                  , 
                     ••
                  
                  que 
                     〈…〉
                   nec, 
                     〈…〉
                  . 6. a benefit that we cannot be abridged or bereaued of by any. As Jo
                     •
                  . 1. 
                     •
                  . Heb. 13. 5. 
               God will neuer forſake thee; ſo Godlineſſe will neuer leaue thee, if thou beeſt once ſoundly and ſincerely religious. 
                  
                     〈…〉
                   ad 
                     〈…〉
                  , ad 
                     〈…〉
                  . Viſe Cicer. T
                     •
                  ſ. 
                     〈◊〉
                   5. 
               It will goe vp with thee to the wheele, it will goe downe with thee to the rack: it will keepe with thee while thou liueſt; 
                  Apoc. 14. 13. it will away with thee when thou dieſt. For 
                  Prov. 11. 7. Iob. 
                  
                     •
                  7. 8. 
                     〈…〉
                  . 
               when the worldly man dieth, his hope dieth with him; 
               
                  Prov. 14. 32. Iob. 13. 15, 16. 
                     〈…〉
                  
                  ▪
                but the godly hath hope euen in death. And 
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                  ▪
                
               the Feare of God, that is Godlineſſe, and 
               
                  
                     〈…〉
                  . 
               the righteouſneſſe of it, in 
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  . 19. 
                     ••
                  
                  ▪
                
               the reward of it, that is the gaine that commeth by it, endureth for euer, and extendeth it ſelfe to all eternitie, laſting not onely paſt this liues end, but paſt the whole worlds end, with which all worldly wealth and gaine; muſt needes haue an end.
            This world is compared to a Fiſhing; the 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   1
                     •
                  . 
                     •
                  7. end of it, to the drawing vp of the nets: while the nets are downe, there is nothing ſaid to be caught; for

the nets may breake, and the Fiſh eſcape. But at the end of the world, when the nets are drawne vp, it will then euidently appeare what each man hath caught. And then thoſe that haue fiſhed here for riches and gaine, may ſay with Peter, 
               Luk. 5. 7. 
               Domine, tota hac nocte laboravimus, &amp; nihil cepimus: Lord, all this night haue we laboured, and caught nothing at all. For Praeſentia amantes praeſentibus indormiunt, theſaur
                     •
                  s ſomniant, tantiſper divites, quamdiu non vigilent: vbi transijt delectabilis ſ
                     •
                  mnus iſte, nihil in manibus ſuis inv
                     •
                  
                  niunt. Aug in Pſ. 76. 5. 
               the worldly rich, when they awake out of their preſent ſleepe, wherein they dreame of gold and gaine, ſhall finde nothing in their hands. But thoſe that haue here fiſhed for Godlineſſe, may ſay, as Luk. 5. 7, 8. he might afterward haue ſaid; Domine, in verbo tuo retia demiſimꝰ, &amp; cepimus: Lord, at thy word, haue we let downe our nets, and haue caught, yea we haue caught abundantly: we haue fiſhed for Godlineſſe, and haue gotten Life eternall. For Rom. 2. 7. 
               Vnto thoſe that by patience and perſeuerance in well doing haue ſought for glory and honour and immortalitie, will the Lord giue eternall life in that day.
            
            But let vs ſift out, and ſee ſomewhat more particularly, wherein this ſpirituall Gaine conſiſteth.
            Firſt then, the ſpeciall Wealth in this World, is that which commeth by Inheritance. 
               Prov. 19. 14. 
               Riches and poſſeſsions, land and liuing, ſaith Salomon, come from a mans aunceſtors. And among thoſe things that may make a man happy, the Heathen man putteth this in the firſt place, as the chiefe, Res non parta labore, ſed relicta. Martial. l. 10. epig. 47. 
               Wealth and goods, not earned with ones hands, but left a man by his friends.
            
            But as Virtus nō eſt h
                     •
                  
                  redit
                     ••
                  ia▪ ſed nec pieta
                     •
                  . Philoſophia non eſt res benefici
                  
                     ••
                  ia. Senec. ep. 90. 
               Virtue, ſo Pietie is not haereditarie. The one commeth not by kinde; neither is the other left by will: It is a greater legacie, than the mightieſt Monarch that is, can bequeath to his heire.

For Pſal. 16. 5. 
               God himſelfe is the inheritance of thoſe that haue it.
            
               Pſal. 111. 5. 
               God (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) hath giuen a portion to them that feare him. If a Rich man giue one a Childes part, it is like to be a matter of ſome worth: Much more then if God giue a man a Childes part. But more then that, Pſal. 142 5. 
               he himſelfe is the portion that he giueth vnto his. 
               Pſal. 119 57. 
               Portio mea ipſe es, Domine; ſaith Dauid; O Lord, thou art my portion. And, Qui dedit me mihi, d dit &amp; ſe mihi. 
                     ••
                  rn in Pſal. 90. 
               He that beſtowed my ſelfe vpon me, hath beſtowed himſelf alſo vpon me, ſaith Bernard. And if Deut. 10. 9. &amp; 18. 2. the Levites neede haue no inheritance among their brethren, becauſe God is their portion; (it is ſufficient, they haue him, that is, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  G neſ. 17. 
                     ••
                  . 
               El ſhaddai, God all ſufficient;) and yet that was but in a temporall manner: Much more then is the godly man wealthy enough, though he haue nothing in the world, though he haue no part among worldly men; ſeeing God is his portion in a ſpirituall manner, in a much better ſort. He whoſe portion God is, cannot be poore.
            We vſe to ſay, that, He cannot lightly want money, that is Maſter of the Mint: and he can neuer be poore, 
               
                  Qui 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , vt eſt in Prouerbio; &amp;, cum Plauti Miſite, Auri mon
                        •
                     es, nō maſſas, habet.
                
               that hath a well-ſpring of wealth. 
               
                  Pſal. 34. 9. &amp; 84. 11. Beatꝰ home, cuius eſt Dominus ſpes eius, cui nihil deficit, quia Chriſtꝰ ei ſufficit. Petrus Bleſ. epiſt. 102 Quantumlibet ſis auarus, ſufficit tibi Deus. Etenim vult avaritia terrā poſſidere totam, adde &amp; coelum; plus eſt qui fecit terram &amp; coelum. Aug, in Pſ. 55. Deum habens, omnia habes. Aug. de temp. 146. Quid tibi ſufficit, ſi Deus non ſufficit. Idem ad fratr. in crum. 51. 2 Cor. 6. 10. Much leſſe then can that man want ought that is good, who is poſſeſſed of God himſelfe, 
                  Iam. 1. 17. Omne enim bonū aut ipſe est, aut ab ipſe. Aug. de doct. Cor. l. 1. c. 31. 
                     •
                  6. 11. 36. the fountaine of all good. In regard whereof, Dauid hauing prayed for many temporall bleſſings in the behalfe of his people, Pſ. 144. 12, 13, 14. 
               that their Sonnes might be 
                     •
                  all and hardie like goodly yong Cedars; and their Daughters faire and comely, like the curious caruings about the Temple; their Oxen ſtrong to labour, and their ſheepe fertile and fruitfull; that there might 
                     〈…〉
                   nor foraine invaſion:
               
at length he windeth vp all indeed with this Epiphonema or Concluſion, Pſal. 144 15. 
               Bleſſed be the people that are in ſuch a caſe: but on the neck of it he commeth as with an Epanorthoma, or a Correction of his former ſpeech, Yea rather bleſſed are the people that haue Iehova for their God; that haue the Lord for their portion: This one bleſſing alone is better worth than all thoſe. So that as when the woman in the Goſpell cryed out to Chriſt, Luk. 11 27. 
               Bleſſed is the wombe that bare thee, and the paps that gaue thee ſuck: Our Sauiour, as correcting her ſpeech, (and yet Luk. 1. 48. true alſo that was) ſaith, 
                  Luk. 11. 28. Beatier Maria percipiendo fidē Chriſti, quàm concipiendo car
                        •
                     em Chriſti. Luk. 1. 45. Inde foelix quia verbum Dei cuſtodivit. Luc. 2. 19. non quia in illa verbum caro factū eſt &amp; habitauit in nobis; ſed quia cuſtodiuit Dei verbū, per quod facta est, &amp; quod in illo caro factum eſt. Aug. in Joan tract. 10. 
               Bleſſed are thoſe rather that heare Gods word and keep it. So the Pſalmiſt haning pronounced them bleſſed that be in ſuch a caſe, as eating in and revoking his words againe, as if he had ſpoken otherwiſe than well, Yea bleſſed (ſaith he) are they rather whoſe God is the Lord: As if he had ſaid, That is indeed an happineſſe in ſome kinde, in ſome caſe: but yet that happineſſe is nothing to this bleſſedneſſe: for that is but externall, this is internall; that is but temporall, this is eternall.
            Secondly, the greateſt wealth in this world is of a Kingdome: and therefore ſaid he ſometime in the prophane Tragedie, that 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Eteocles apud Eurip. Phoeniſſ. Nam ſi violandum eſt ius, regnandi gratia violandum eſt: alijs rebus pietatem 
                        •
                     olas. Cic. offic. l. 
                  
                     •
                  . Nulla ſancta ſocietas, nec fides regni eſt. Enniꝰ apud eund l. 1. Nulla fides regni ſocijs. Lucan. l. 1. 
               If a man might breake his word for ought, it ſhould be to atchieue a Crowne, to compaſſe a Kingdome. Yea not to be a King onely, but to belong to a King in ſome place neere about him, is eſteemed a matter of great worth and dignitie, and ſuch as may proue a meane of much wealth and commoditie to one that can wiſely make vſe of it. 1 King. 10. 8. They were held happy men that could get into Salomons ſeruice. And it is the greateſt matter that

               Prou. 22. 29. 
               S
                     •
                  l
                     •
                  mon could promiſe the man that is diligent and induſtrious in the managing of his affaires, that he ſhall ſtand before, 
               
                  Sic 
                  
                     •
                   
                  Reg. 17. 
                     •
                  . &amp; Dan. 7. 10. that is, attend vpon Princes, and not ſerue or waite vpon any meane man.
            
            If it be held ſuch a matter then to retaine and belong to ſome one of the Princes of this world: De
                     •
                   ſeruire regnare eſt. B
                     •
                  rn. de temp. 110. Nō maligno aut mundano princ
                     •
                  p
                     •
                  , 
                     ••
                  d Chriſt
                     •
                   vtique ſeruire regnare eſt. Idem, de bon. deſer. What is it to appertaine and belong to GOD, 
               Apoc. 19. 16. 1 Tim 6. 15. 
               the King of Kings, and 
               Apoc. 1. 5. 
               the Prince of Princes, 
               Pſal. 83. 18. 
               the highest Soueraigne 
               Luk. 10. 21. 
               Lord of Heauen and Earth; 
               Deponit reges, diſpouit regna Dan. 2. 37. &amp; 4. 22. 
               that depoſeth Kings and diſpoſeth of their Kingdoms at his pleaſure; that aſſign
                  •
               th euery earthly King the liſts and limits both of his regiment and of his reigne? That which the Apoſtle Paul therefore prefixeth as no ſmall credit before ſundry of his Epiſtles; and King Dauid as a great grace before ſome of his Pſalmes: 
                  Rom. 1. 1. Philip. 1. 1. Tit. 
                  
                     •
                   1. 
               Paul a ſeruant of Ieſus Chriſt: and, Pſal. 36. 1. 
               A Pſalme of Dauid the ſeruant of God: as if it were 
                  Sanctitate maior quàm p
                        •••
                     ſtate. Salnian, de prouid. l. 2. Quomodo de M. Ant
                        •
                     n
                        •
                     no Pe
                        •
                     rare. fam ep. 15 l. 7. Imperium adep
                        •
                     ꝰ philoſophi nomen ro
                        •
                     inuit, maiu
                        •
                      
                     
                        •
                     ſtimās philoſoph
                        •
                      eſſe quā principem. Et de Theod
                        •
                     ſio Aug. de ciuit. l. 5. c. 28. Eccleſi
                        •
                      Dei ſe membrū eſſe magis quā regnare gaudebat.
                a greater dignitie to him, that he was Gods ſeruant, then that he was ruler and gouernor of Gods people.
            But becauſe Joh 8. 35. 
               the Seruant is oft-times turned out at dores, whereas the Sonne abideth in the houſe for euer: And therefore the Father telleth his Sonne in the Goſpell; Luk. 15. 31. 
               Sonne, thou art euer with me: and all that I haue is reſerued for thee. The godly man is not onely Seruant to a King, but he is 1 Pet. 2. 9. Sonne to ſuch a King, and Luk. 12. 3
                     •
                  . borne, or rather 
                  Ioh. 3. 3, 5. 
               new-borne, to a Kingdome.
            And whereas earthly Kings, if they haue many Sonnes, can leaue the Crowne but to one. 
                  
                     •
                   Chron. 21. 3. 
               Iehoſaphat (faith the Holy Hiſtorie) gaue great gifts to his other Sonnes, but the Kingdome gaue he to 
                     •
                  oram; becauſe he was the eldeſt God 
                  〈◊〉
                
               
                  Apoc. 1. 6. &amp; 10. 6. all his Sonnes

Kings and Apoc. 21. 7. Heires alike. For Rom. 8. 17. 
               if we be Sonnes, ſaith the Apoſtle, we are Heires too; euen coheires with Chriſt, 
               Hebr. 1. 2. 
               who is Heire of all.
            
            But how can the Godly be ſo rich may ſome ſay, when he hath, as it may fall out, not a penny in his purſe?
            Thirdly therefore: A man may truly be ſaid to be Rich in writing; the monied man, though he haue neuer a penny in the houſe, but 
                  Hinc illud Pallade: 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Et Po
                        ••
                     iani illud; 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  apud Stob. tō. 2. c. 10 all ou
                  •
                at intereſt; and the landed-man, though he hold not his lands in his owne hands, but haue all let out and in the occupation of others, ſo long as he hath good ſecuritie for the one, and good euidence, if neede be, to ſhew, for the other. And as in Writing, ſo in Reuerſion. Great ſummes of money do many giue for the reverſions of offices, of lands and leaſes; and as much may they make them againe away for, if they will.
            And in like manner may the Godly man be ſaid to be rich both in Writing, and in Reuerſion: yea in either kinde he is Affatim diues. eſt, qui cum Chriſto pauper eſt. Hieron. ad Heliodor. Diues pax, piet as, fides: fideli enim totus mundꝰ poſſeſſio eſt, Ambr. ep. 10. Quibus l
                     •
                  cis circumſcribitur, cui totꝰ mundus diuitiarū poſſeſſio eſt? Idem offic. l. 
                     •
                  . c. 1. the richeſt man in the world. For he hath all in the world, yea 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Antiſtbenes &amp; Zeno apud Laert. Vnꝰ eſt ſapiens, cuius omnia ſunt. Senec. de benef. l. 7. c. 3. Fideli l
                        •
                      mi
                        •
                     i totus mundus diuit
                        •
                     
                     arū eſt: totus planè; quia tam aduerſ
                        •
                      quam preſper a 
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        •
                     què oīa ſeruiunt ei, &amp; cooperantur in bonum. Bern
                        ••
                      Cant. ſer. 21. 
               all this world, and the next world confirmed and aſſured vnto him by the word and promiſe of God, yea by his deede and bond vnder his owne hand and ſeale, who cannot goe from his word, or diſclaime his hand Tit. 1. 1. 
               to lye, or 2 Tim. 2. 13. 
               to denie himſelfe; though it be much of it in other mens hands yet for a while. For 1 Tim. 4. 8. 
               Pietie or Godlineſſe hath the promiſes both of this life, and of the life to come, ſaith our Apoſtle. And againe; 1 Cor 3. 22, 23. 
               Be it Paul or Apollos, or things preſent, or future, or this
               
               world; 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Diogeues apud Laert. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Clem. Al. protrept. Oīa Chriſto tradita. Math. 11. 27. ten
                        •
                      eum per quem facta ſunt omnia, &amp; cum ipſo omnia poſſidebis. Rom. 8. 23. a
                        •
                     are, ecce habes omnia. Omnia qu
                        •
                      
                     
                        •
                     mas, vt non impendiaris à Chriſto, contemne, &amp; ipſum tene in qu
                        •
                      p
                        •
                     ſſis omnia poſſidere. Aug. hom. 34. Viſe in Pſal 48. 
               all is yours, and you Chriſts, and Chriſt Gods. All the wealth both of this world, and of the world to come is theirs, (as 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 2. Cor. 6. 10. Auarus terrena eſ
                        •
                     rit, vt mendicu
                        •
                     ; fidelis contem
                        ••
                     t, vt dominus: ille poſſidendo mendicat, ille contemnend
                        •
                      poſſidet. Bern. in Cant. 21. Commune eſt omnibus Chriſti fratribus, quod de ſe Chriſtus dixit, Ioan. 1
                        •
                     . 32. quod ſi ita est; non putent diuites 
                        •
                     uius ſeculi fratres Chriſti ſola poſſidere coel
                        •
                     ſti
                        •
                     ; poſſident &amp; terrena; &amp; quidem tanqu
                        •
                     m nihil habentes, ſed omnia poſſidentes, non mendicantes vt miſeri, ſed vt Domini poſſidentes; 
                        •
                     o pro cer
                        •
                     o magis Domini, quo minus cupidi. Bern. in Cant. 21. An non omnia poſſidet, cui omnia cooperantur in bon
                        ••
                     ? Idem be b
                        •
                     n. deſer.
                
               hauing nothing, ſaith the Apoſtle, and yet poſſeſsing all things) though it be Rom. 8. 28. Solertir attende, quod non ad libitum famulari, ſed cooperari dicit ad bonum, neque enim ad voluntatem ſeruiunt, ſed ad vtilitatem, non ad voluptatem, ſed ad ſalutem, non ad votum, ſed ad ad commodū noſtrum. Idem de diuerſ. 1. for their good alſo, with-held from them for a while.
            
               
                  Fidelis homini
                        •
                      totus mundus diuitiarum eſt: infidelis autem nec 
                        •
                     b
                        •
                     lu
                        •
                     . Aug. Epiſt. 54. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Pindarus apud Clement. padag. lib. 3. cap. 12. The wicked in right haue iuſt nothing, hauing made forfeiture of all, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Dion. Chryſ. orat. 65. though it pleaſe God Mat. 5. 45. Luk. 5. 35. Act. 14. 17. not to take euer the aduantage of it inſtantly, &amp; Legatur Fr. à Victoria relect. 5. § 1. n. 7, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19. where he doth not, man may not. They are but Hoc cert
                     •
                   alien
                     ••
                   non eſt quod iure poſſidetur; hoc autem 
                     •
                  ure, quod iuſte; &amp; hoc iuſte, quod bene. Omne igitur quod malè poſſidetur, alie
                     ••
                  m eſt, malè autem poſſidet, qu
                     •
                   malè vti
                     ••
                  r. Aug. epiſt. 54. Re
                     •
                   quemque terrena rect
                     •
                   à quoquam poſſideri n
                     ••
                   poteſt, niſi vel iure di
                     •
                  i
                     ••
                  , quo c
                     ••
                  cta i
                     •
                  ſterum ſunt, vel iure 
                     〈◊〉
                  , quod in poteſtate reg
                     •••
                   eſt. Idem epiſt. 48. intruders vpon and vſurpers of Gods goods, and ſhall one day anſwer for their vſurpation and abuſe of them: or Gen. 39. 5. Exod. 12. 8. Act. 27. 
                     •
                  4. M
                     •
                  l
                     ••
                   
                  
                     ••
                  l
                     ••
                   
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   D
                     ••
                  ; 
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     •
                  a 
                     〈◊〉
                  : 
                     •••
                  tingunt 
                     〈◊〉
                   etiam malis, quia ſepar
                     •
                  ri non poterant. ſatiꝰ est autem prodeſſe etiam malis propter bones, quam bonis deeſſe propter malis. Sen
                     ••
                   
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   benef. l. 4. 
                     •
                  . 28. entercommoners by ſufferance with Gods children and ſeruants, whom he principally intendeth

them vnto: or 
                  Gen. 30 27, 30, 43. &amp; 3
                     •
                  . 9, 16. Iſai. 45 2, 3, 4, 26, 28. Iob 27. 16, 17. Prou. 13. 22. Dei diſpe
                        •
                     ſator
                        •
                     s; non ſibi, ſed alijs diuites. quod de bonis Hi
                        •
                     rō ad Pelag. l 1. Stewards and Treaſurers, as ofttimes, for the good of the Godly.
            And for Reverſion; to omit what he hath in preſent poſſeſſion, beſides 1 Cor. 1. 5, 7. ſpirituall riches, of worldly wealth, as much Math 6. 32, 33. as he hath neede of, &amp; as much Pſal. 84. 12. as it is good for him to haue: Euery Godly man, as he is Iam 2. 5. 
               Rich in faith, ſo he is far richer by Faith. For Heb. 14. 1, 7. Iam 2. 5. by it he holdeth and hath right to the reverſion of ſuch 1 Petr. 1. 4, 5. 
               an euerlaſting inheritance, reſerued for him in the Heauens, as cannot be purchaſed with all the wealth of this world; and as goeth in worth farther beyond all the wealth of this world, than the pureſt gold doth the droſſieſt durt.
            And thus haue we ſeene, both that Godlineſſe is gainefull; and wherein the Gaine thereof doth conſiſtſt.
            Now the Vſe hereof is two-fold, for Exhortation, for Examination.
            For Exhortation firſt; to ſtirre vp all men to labour and take paines to get Godlineſſe. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  .—Sophoc. Creuſa. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Theogn. g
                        •
                     ō. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Eurip. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . A
                        •
                     tiphanes. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Demoſth Olynth. Totus populus in aliam diſcors, in hoc convedit: 
                        〈◊〉
                      ſuſpic
                        •
                     
                     unt, hoc ſuis op
                        •
                     ant. Senec. epiſt. 115. quem viſe ſi
                        •
                     .
                All men gape after Gaine. It is almoſt euery ones ſong, that the Pſalmiſt hath; 
                  Pſal 4 6. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Theocr. idy
                        •
                     . 16. Prima fere vota, &amp; cunct is notiſſima templis: Diuitiae vt 
                        •
                     reſcant, vt opes. Iuve
                        •
                     al ſat. 10. Lucri bonus eſt odor ex re Qualibet illa tuo ſententia ſemper in ore Verſe
                        •
                     ur, Dijs at
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      ipſe love digna, poetae. Hoc monſtrant pueri
                        •
                      vetulae poſcentibus aſſem, Hoc diſcunt omnis ante alpha &amp; beta puellae. Vnde habeas quaerit nemo, ſed oportet habere. Iuven. ſat. 14. 
               Quis oſtendet nobis boni aliquid? Who will tell vs of any matter of gaine and commoditie? 
               Audi
                     ••
                  , 
                     〈◊〉
                   Adam, 
                     •••
                  
                  rum &amp; ambit
                     •
                  oſum genus. Bern. de tempor. 4. 
               Hearken, ſaith one well, yee ſonnes of Adam, a couetous race, an ambitious brood: Here is Honor, and true Honor; here is Gaine, and true Gaine: ſuch as

the Pecuniam vt t
                     •
                   haberes, alius ante perdiderat. Sen. de remed. fort Bonum est, quod vt ad 
                     •
                  e tranſeat, alius dare debet, alijs ami
                     •
                  tere? Idē queſt. nat. l. 3. pr
                     •
                  fat. Lu
                     •
                  rum ſine damno alterius haber
                     •
                   non potest. P. Syrius. world cannot ſhew the like; Sic ab omnibus capitur, vt nil ſingulis minuatur Ber. in Cant. 79. Gaine without any loſſe to, or hindrance of any: here is good Gaine, and great Gaine; here is infinite gettings. Labour for Godlineſſe; labour to get and keepe a good Conſcience: It is the gainfull'ſt Trade in the world. Who ſo followeth this Trade, ſhall not venture vpon vncertainties, he ſhall be ſure to thriue, and to get infinite Gaine. For, Prou 21. 21. 
               He that followeth after righteouſneſſe, as a man followeth a trade, ſhall finde Honour, and Life, true Honour, and eternall Life.
            And here come there two ſorts of men to be admoniſhed.
            Firſt, the Rich, that they content not themſelues with their worldly wealth, but that they ſeeke withall to get the true ſpirituall Riches, that Animus hominis dives, non area appellari ſolet quamai
                     •
                   illa ſit plena dū te inanem videbo divitē non pu
                     •
                  abo. Cic. parad. 6. Ex anim
                     •
                   rem ſtare 
                     •
                  
                  quam puto, 
                     •
                  ō animam exre. Auſon. themſelues may be rich, and not their purſe or their cheſt only; that they may not be Luk. 12. 21. Eſt
                     •
                  te Deo divites, nō 
                  
                     ••
                  m facturi di
                  
                     •
                  item, ſed de 
                     •
                  o futuri divite
                     •
                  . Aug. de verb. Dom. 6. 
               rich to the world onely, but rich alſo to God. Elſe their earthly Gaine will proue their loſſe; their worldly wealth will be but a meanes to hinder their happines by keeping them out of Heauen, where alone is true and entire happineſſe to be had. It is that which our Sauiour himſelfe ſaith of the worldly. Rich man, that hath nothing to truſt vnto but his riches: (for ſo to his Apoſtles Mark. 10. 24. he expoundeth it himſelfe:) that Math. 10. 24. Mark. 10. 25. Luk. 18. 25. 
               It is eaſier for e a Camell; or, as ſome read the word, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Suid, Viſe 
                        〈…〉
                     , &amp; 
                        〈◊〉
                     .
                
               a cable rope, to paſſe through the eye of a Needle, than for ſuch a rich man to enter into the kingdome of Heaven. As if our Sauiour ſhould haue ſaid; It is as eaſie a matter, nay an eaſier, to thred a ſmall Spaniſh Needle with a thicke Cable, or a great Cart-rope, then to
               
               get ſuch a Rich man in at heauen gate: 
               In
                     •
                  pta enī ſunt, quae ex Lyra
                     ••
                   Autor Dialogi inter Divitē &amp; Pauperem, de portagarrit Hieroſ
                     •
                  lymitana, cui Acꝰ nomen, per quā Cameli, 
                     •
                  iſi ſ
                     •
                  cinis prius depoſitis introire 
                     •
                  eutiquam poſſent. 
               That great bunched beaſt, a Camell, may as ſoone, yea ſooner be driuen through an needles narrow eye, than ſuch a rich man be drawne vnto God, and be brought into the ſtate of Grace. For ſo the moſt and the beſt reade it; and it is an ordinarie by word both with Syrians &amp; Greeks, when they ſpeake of a thing that they thinke altogither impoſſible, to ſay, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Caſaubou. in notis ad N
                        •
                     Teſt.
                
               An Elephant, or a Camell may as ſoone creepe through an Needles eye, as this or that come to paſſe. But not ſo ſoone, ſaith our Sauiour, but Difficilem dixerat, impoſſibilē iam di
                     •
                  cit. Hieron. in Math. 3. i
                     •
                  ò impoſſibili magis impoſſibilem. Euthym. in Math. c. 41. ſooner may that be done, which Math. 19. 26. Mark. 10. 2
                     •
                  . with man is altogither impoſſible, than ſuch worldly rich men attaine to true happineſſe. 2 Cor. 8. 9. Diuilia illius quid nobis facturae, cuius paupertas no
                     •
                   divites fecit? Aug. de verb. Apoſt. 15. 
               Christ (ſaith the Apoſtle) became poore, to make vs Rich. 
               
                  Quomodo pauper factus eſt? quomodo divites facit? Aug. de temp. 
                  
                     〈…〉
                  . 
               How became he poore? ſaith one of the Ancients: 
                  
                     ••
                   how maketh he vs rich? The ſame Apoſtle (ſaith 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   ſheweth vs, and expoundeth himſelfe, where he ſaith; 
               2 Cor. 
                  
                     〈…〉
                  . 
               He that knew no ſinne, for our ſake became ſinne, by taking vpon him the guilt of our ſinne, that we might become the 
               Puto quod Chriſti paupertas non pecuniam nobis attulit, ſed iuſtitiam &amp; immortalitarē. Aug. ibid. 
               Righteouſnes of God in him. And indeed, to ſpeake properly and preciſely, as the truth is, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Chryſoſt. tom. 6. ſerm. 78. de poenit. 2. not as the world, but as God reckneth, Mai
                     •
                  r &amp; miſerabilior egeſtas nulla eſt, quàm egere ſapientia, &amp; qui ſapientia non eget, nulla re omni
                     •
                  ò egore poteſt. ſtultitia ergò egeſt at eſt. Aug. de beata vita diſput. 3. Paupertas in animo eſt, non in ſacoulo. Idem in Pſal. 131. Paupertas in inopia mentis eſt, non in quantitate poſſeſſionis. Greg in Ezech. l. 2. hom. 18. the onely pouertie is Sinfulneſſe, and In animo diuitia ſunt, non inpatrimonio. Sen. ep. 108. Pa
                     •
                  u
                     •
                  ne divitia ipſa innocentia? ſi arcam plemā auro habueris, diues eris: ſi cor habueris plenum innocentia, pauper er
                     ••
                  ? Aug. in Pſal. 83. Righteouſneſſe the right Riches. And the rich man therefore that hath

not a religious heart, is but like Apoc. 3. 17. proud Laodicea, 
               
                  Quid tibi proſunt exteriores diuitia, ſi te interior premit egeſtas? Aug. in Pſal 52. Tanto enī verius, quanto interiꝰ indigentes ſum
                        ••
                     . Greg. M. mor. l. 21. c. 14. a poore beggarly wretch in Gods ſight, and in the ſight of thoſe that ſee ſo as he ſeeth, howſoeuer he may ſeeme rich and glorious in worldly mens eyes.
            Yea to him that hath it too, that is both rich and religious, may we well ſay, as our Sauiour did to his Diſciples, when they vaunted at their returne from preaching the Goſpell, that euen the Diuels were ſubdued vnto them; Luk. 10. 20. 
               Reioyce yee not herein, that the Diuels are ſubdued vnder you: ſo were they vnder Iudas too; but herein reioyce, that you haue your names entred in heauen. So Viſe ſupra quod de Theodoſio Aug. deciuit. Dei l. 5. c. 22. reioyce not herein that thou art rich to the world, or that thou art great in the world, and haſt others vnder thee, and at thy command; that thou art clad gorgeouſly, and fareſt deliciouſly; (for Luk. 16. 19. ſo did that reprobate Rich man in the Goſpell:) but herein reioyce that thou art rich vnto God, and 1 Pet. 3. 4. Verè diues, qui in Dei conſp
                     •
                  ctu poteſt diues videri. Ambr. epiſt. 10. ſed ſolum illum divitem D
                     •
                  us novit, qui ſit diues aternitati. Ibid. in his ſight, that thou feareſt and ſerueſt God, and 2 Cor. 1 12. laboureſt to keepe a good conſcience, that thou art a 1 Pet. 4. 10. 
                 carefull diſpenſer and faithfull diſpoſer of that treaſure that God hath entruſted thee withall. Then thou art 
                  5 Paulo ſap
                        •
                     e is omnis liber, 1 Cor. 7. 22. Peire etiam diues eſt. 1. Pet. 3. 4. Ambroſ. epiſt. 10 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                      Plato Ph
                        •
                     done. S lu
                        •
                      ſapient diues eſt Ci
                        •
                      parad. 6. &amp; apud Apul de philoſ. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . &amp;c. Philo de Nee. Qui pre
                        •
                     loſiſſi
                        •
                     a qu
                        •
                      ſunt poſſidet, is diues est. 
                        •
                     iqui pretioſiſſi
                        ••
                      res virtus eſt: hanc ergò cùm ſapions ſolus poſſideat; ſapions ſolus diues eſt. Empir adv. Mathem.
                truely Rich, when thou art ſincerely religious, when thou art truly righteous.
            Secondly, the poore, they are likewiſe to be admoniſhed, to labour for Godlineſſe: that though they be not Luk. 12. 21. 
               rich to the world, they may be rich yet to God; and their worldly pouertie ſhall be no hindrance to their ſpirituall preferment. For

               Iam 2. 5. 
               God (ſaith the Apoſtle) hath choſen the poore of this world to be rich in grace, and heires of his kingdome.
            
            And here is great comfort for the poore man, that liueth a godly life, and maketh Conſcience of his courſes, hath a care to pleaſe God and to doe his will in all things, and to approue himſelfe and his wayes to him, walking faithfully and painfully in the works of his calling, be it neuer ſo meane; that though he be neuer ſo poore and bare, though he liue but from hand to mouth, as we ſay; yea though he haue not one good rag to hang on his backe, or one good morſell of meat in a twelue-month to put in his mouth, though he haue not the leaſt patch of land in the world to ſuſtaine him, or the leaſt hole that may be to hide his head in; Diuites dicimus ſapientes, iuſtos, bonos; quibus pecunia vel parua vel nulla: magis enī ſunt virtutibꝰ diuites: pauperis verò auaros dicimus, ſemper inhiantes, ſemper egentes. Aug de ciu. l 7. c. 12. Pauper eſt pius? etiam ſic diues eſt. intus diues, foris pauper: pauper in cella, diues in conſcientia. arcam reſpicis auro inanē; conſcientia reſpice Deo plenam: non habet extrinſecus facultatem; ſed habet intrinſecus charitatem. Aug. in Pſ. 36. &amp; de temp. 212 Inops auri, Deo diues eſt. quid hac virtute pauperius? quid hac pauperiate ditius? Math. 5. 3. Idem de verb. Ap. 26. Nemo apud Deum pauper est, viſi qui iuſtitia indiget: nemo diues, niſi qui virtutibus plenus eſt. Lactant. inſtit. l. 5. c. 14. yet is he a rich man for all that, richer than Craſſus or Croeſus, or the wealthieſt worldly man again in the world. For they haue but Luk. 16. 11. 
               the falſe Riches, he the true treaſure; they haue but the counterfait Vitreum margaritum, non verum. Hieron. poſt Tertull. 
               glaſsie pearle; he hath that precious orient pearle, which Math. 13. 46. 
               the wiſe Merchant, when he hath found, is content to ſell all that euer he hath to purchaſe it, to forgo all that euer he is worth for the compaſſing of it; and yet is he no looſer by the bargaine neither. For as he is a Merchant, ſo is he alſo a wiſe Merchant; and therefore knoweth well what he doth in ſo doing: he knoweth that in buying it, he buyeth himſelfe and his owne ſafetie, his own eternall ſaluation, togither with it.
            Againe, this ſerueth to ouerthrow the opinion of ſuch perſons as thinke that there is litle or no Gaine

to be gotten vnder God, litle or no good at all to be gathered in Gods ſeruice. So the worldly men in Iobs day; Iob. 21. 15. 
               Who is the All-ſufficient, ſay they, that we ſhould ſerue him? or what profit ſhould we haue by praying vnto him? And the wicked in Malachies time; Malac. 3. 14. 
               It is but in vaine to ſerue God: there is nothing to be gotten by keeping his commandements, and walking humbly before him.
            
            Yea but, may ſome ſay, ſure there be none ſuch now a-dayes, eſpecially among vs that make profeſſion of Chriſtianitie; and therefore this vſe of the point might well be ſpared.
            If it be ſo with vs, Quieſcat lingua, loquaturvita. Aug. in 1. Ioan. Efficaciꝰ eſt teſtimonium vita quam lingua. Aut
                     •
                  r de dupl martyr. let our Actions anſwer for vs; let our practiſe proue it: And ſo we will turne the Vſe from Reprehenſion to Examination, from Confutation to Conviction.
            Let euery one by theſe Notes then examine himſelf, whither he be of this Opinion or no.
            Firſt, did men deeme Godlineſſe to be a matter of Gaine, they would neuer thinke they had enough of it. For 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   Euſebius apud Stob. t
                     •
                  m. 2. c. 
                     •
                  0. 
                     •
                  quantūlibet improba, Creſtant diuitiae, tamē Curtae neſci
                     •
                   quid ſemper abeſt rei Hor
                     •
                  a
                     •
                  m. 3. 23. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Epictet. enchir. c. 61. Eccleſ. 6. 7. Nemo eſt cui foelicit
                     •
                   ſ
                     ••
                  , etiāſi curſu veniat, ſatisfaciat. Senec. Epiſt. 115. non poteſt expleri cupiditatibus, et
                     •
                  am
                     •
                  i expleatur diuitus. Ambr. de bono mert. c. 
                     •
                  . Auarus animus nullo ſatiatur lucre. S
                     •
                  n. 
                     •
                  p. 49. 
               Riches are ſtintleſſe; there is no end of them. We neuer thinke that we haue wealth enough; we are ſtill labouring for more. Fortune multis 
                     〈…〉
                  dat, 
                     ••
                  lli ſatis. Martial. l. 12. epigr. 10. 
               Many men haue too much, and yet no man enough. There is no ſtint of wealth; but as Non aliud an
                     ••
                  al eu 
                     ••
                  nore origine in ma
                     ••
                  
                  
                  
                     •••
                   cr
                     •
                  ſcit magnitudinē 
                  
                     〈…〉
                   Plin. hiſt. 
                     •••
                  . l. 8. c. 25. ſome write, though 
                  
                     •
                  iſe 
                     •
                  ul. 
                     •••
                  ig d
                     •
                   ſubtil 
                     〈…〉
                  . fabulouſly, of the Crocodile, that he groweth ſo long as euer he liueth: ſo it is too too true of this myſticall Crocodile, the deſire of gaine and wealth, and of aduancing or enlarging mens worldly eſtates, hath no

               acme, nō pitch, but groweth ſtill more and more with men as long as they liue, Auaritia morbꝰ ſenum proprius, lu
                  
                     •
                  uria iuvenum: libidinis ſiquidem ignis pau
                     ••
                  tim extinguitur, &amp; cum ſenectute conſeneſcit: at auaritia augeſcit continuò, &amp; cum ſenectute ipſa iuveneſcit. Kolloc. in 1 Tim. 6. 10. Quid auaritia, quae rad
                     ••
                   eſt omnium malorū, nonne in frigidis ſenibus tanto ad acquirendum feruentiꝰ inardeſcit, quā
                  to eitius relictura eſt quod acquirit? Aug. de temp. 246. rifer oft with them then euer, when they are euen going out of the world, and haue one foot, as we vſe to ſay, already in the graue.
            But with Godlineſſe men are ſoone ſatisfied; they haue ſoone enough of it. If they haue attained to but a litle ſuperficiall ſprinkling of common Grace, or ciuill honeſtie, that commeth as far ſhort of ſound ſanctification and ſinceritie, as the ſhadow doth of the ſubſtance; they begin preſently to ſuppoſe, with ſelfe-conceited Apoc. 3. 17. 
               Laodicea, that they are rich enough and neede nothing; that Quomodo proficis, fi tibi 
                     •
                  am ſufficis? Bern. de conſider. l. 2. Omnia i
                     ••
                   deſunt, qui ſibi nihil deeſſe putat. Ib. they haue no neede to labour for any further matter, they are euen as well as well may be, as neede be, at leaſt.
            No man is afraid of being too wealthy: but Noſti illud, Ne
                  
                     ••
                   p
                     •••
                   eſt, qui pietatem cauet. Caue qui ignam petes eſſe verius Cic. de ſin. lib 2. Qui time
                     •
                   eſſe bo
                     •••
                  , nō times eſſe malus. Miſocoſm. de contempt mund. many are afraid of being too godly, Eccleſ. 7. 18. Modum eſſe religionis: nimium eſſe ſuperſtitisſu
                     •
                   nō oportere Cic. prodomo ſua. Religeutē eſſe &amp; portet, religioſi 
                     〈…〉
                  . G
                     •
                  ll. l. 4. c 9. 
               Ne ſis nimium iuſtus; Be not too iuſt, ſticketh ſhrewdly on many a mans ſtomacke: though ſpoken Notata eſt non iuſtitia ſapientis, ſea ſuperbia praeſumentis. Aug in Ioan. 95. not of true Godlineſſe or Righteouſnes indeede; but of nouriſhing in vs an ouer-weaning conceit of our ſelues; or of Si quem rigidū &amp; trucē ad omnia fratrū peccata conſpexeris, &amp;c. hunc ſcito plus iuſtum eſſe quam iuſtū eſt. Hieron in Eccleſ. Iuſtitia enim, niſi miſericordi
                     •
                   temperetur, in crudelitatem degenerat, Lav
                     ••
                   in Eccleſ. Huc illud Plinij hiſt. nat. l. 18. c. 6. Nihil minus expedire, quam agrum optim
                     •
                   colere. Et, Agrum bend colere neceſſarium, optimè damnoſum. being ouer-rigorous in cenſuring of others; like Luk. 18. 11. 
               the Phariſee in the Goſpell, who, ſaith an ancient Writer very pithily and wittily, Dum in ſe ſingulariter 
                     ••••
                  tat, aliji arroganter inſultat; &amp; ſe ſolum decipit, quem ſolum excipit, dum al
                     •••
                   damnat. Lern. de grad. humil. 
               exulting arrogantly in himſelfe inſulteth inſolently ouer others, and deceiueth himſelfe alone, whom alone he excepteth, while he
               
               contemneth and condemneth all beſides himſelfe.
            
            Secondly, Men would ſtriue one to go beyond an other in Godlineſſe, if they counted Godlineſſe a matter of Gaine. For as the Heathen Writer well obſerueth, 
                  ▪ 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Heſiod. Vicimus diues cupiditatem irritat. Sen. epiſt. 7.
                there is a kinde of emulation commonly among worldly neighbors, whereby they emulate ſuch as goe beyond them in wealth: one neighbour ſtriueth to out-build an other, one to get and purchaſe more than another. The couetous man caſteth his eye on his rich neighbors, 
                  ▪ 
                  hunc at
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      hune ſuperare laborat: Vt quum carceribus 
                        ••
                     ſſ
                        •
                     s rapit vngula currus Inſtat equis auriga ſuos vincentibus illum praeteritum temnens eutremos inter euntem. Herat. ſerm, l. 1. ſat. 1.
                as a man in a race doth on thoſe that haue won ground of him, he ſtriueth to get euen with this man, whom he is yet behind, to out-ſtrip that man, whom he hath got euen withall. And the enuious man (as thoſe two vices are ſeldome aſunder) looking through the ſpectacles of enuie on his neighbours goods, Fertilier ſeges eſt alienis ſemper in aruis: vicinumque pecꝰ grandius vber 
                     •
                  abet. Ovid. artis l. 1. 
                     〈◊〉
                   nobis, noſtra 
                     〈…〉
                  t. P. Syrus.-maior
                     •
                   videtur, Et melior vi
                     ••
                  na ſeges. Juven: ſat. 14. thinketh euery thing that his neighbor hath better than his own and it may be better than indeed it is, his grounds fertiler, his beaſts fairer, his revenues larger, his gaines greater &amp;c. and is ready enough oft to ſay with himſelfe, Why ſhould not my beaſts looke a
                     •
                   
                  
                     ••
                  ire a
                     •
                   hi
                     •
                  ? why ſhould not my grounds yeeld as much as hi
                     •
                  ? why ſhould not I thrine as well as he, hauing as good 
                     ••
                  dnes to thrine by a
                     •
                   he hath
            
            And euen 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plat
                        •
                      d
                        •
                      
                     
                        〈…〉
                     . 
                        •
                     .
                ſo wo
                  ••••
                be with vs, held we Godlineſſe to be gainefull. We would haue a kinde of godly emulation and ambition among vs, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, in matter of Godlineſſe; we would euen 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 1. Cor. 12. 31. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 1. Cor. 14. 1. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 2. Cor. 9. 2. 
               emulate, and 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Rom. 15. 2
                     •
                  . 
                     •
                   
                  Cor. 5. 9. 1. Theſſ. 4. 11. 
               ambitiouſly, as it were, ſtriue
               
               and contend to out-go one an other in goodnes and grace. And this were 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Heſiod.
                
               a good and godly emulation, a goodly and a commendable ſtrife and contention indeed. We would be eying of thoſe that are got beyond vs in grace, and endeuour to get euen with them, yea, if it be poſſible, to out-ſtrip them, and to caſt them behind vs, Qui ſtadium currit, eniti &amp; contendere debet, quàm maximè poſſit, vt vincat: ſupplantare eum qu
                     •
                  cum certet, aut manis depellere nullo modo debet. Chryſippu
                     •
                   apud Cicer. offic. l. 3. not by hindring their progreſſe, but by mending our owne pace, and Faciamus quod in itinere fieri ſolet: qui tardiꝰ exierūt, velocitate pe
                     •
                  ſant moram. Senec. nat. quaeſt. l. 3. praefat. Quod facere ſolent, qui ſerius exeunt, &amp; volunt tempus celeritate reparare, calcar add
                     •
                  mus. Idem epiſt. 68. by ſtraining our ſelues to runne the faſter, the later it was ere we entred into this race. We would be as ready as they are to ſay to our ſelues; And why ſhould not I be as forward in the feare of God, as Zealous, as religious, as I ſee ſuch and ſuch are, ſince I haue as good meanes of being godly as they haue, as many inducements as either they or any other can haue?
            
            But ſo ſtand the moſt affected, that they will not by their good will ſuffer any man to out-go them in wealth, in the way of the world: but they will let any man willingly out-go them in grace, and in the good wayes of God: there onely we ſtraine courteſie, and giue euery one the way of vs. And as our Sauiour telleth the Scribes and Phariſees, that Math. 21. 31. 
               the very Publicans and Harlots might go into the kingdome of Heauen before them: So not a few among vs will ſuffer the very Pagans, and Papiſts, litle better than Pagans, if not worſe many of them than they, the very Heathen and Heretikes to go into heauen before them, ere they will ſtriue to out-go them in goodnes and godlineſſe.
            Thirdly, men would be more affected with it, if they ſuppoſed any matter of Gaine to be in it. Populus me ſibilat; at mihi plau do Ipſe domi, ſimulat nummos contemplor in arca. Horat. ſerm. l. 1. ſat. 1. The couetous miſer, ſaith the Heathen man, while the

people either curſe or hi
                  ••
               e at him abroad, yet he pleaſeth and cheereth himſelfe the whileſt with the ſight or the conſideration of his ſubſtance at home. It doth a man good at the very heart, euen to thinke vpon his riches, and but Eccleſ. 5. 10. 
               to looke vpon his treaſure. It will make our hearts to ſpring and leap within vs for ioy, to haue ſodaine newes brought vs of ſome rich legacie, or large patrimonie by ſome meanes befallen vs.
            But of this ſpirituall wealth and gaine moſt men are meerely ſtupide and ſenſeles: No more moued commonly or affected, when either, (if any time at leaſt they ſo do,) they thinke on it, or when they heare it ſpoken of in the Pulpit; then (as a Philoſopher ſaid ſometime of an ignorant Dol
                  •
                
               
                  •
               itting in the Theater, where the ſeats were of marble, that 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Ariſtipp
                        ••
                      apud L
                        •••
                     tium l. 2. 
               One ſtone ſate vpon an other:) then, I ſay, either the benches that they ſit vpon, or the pillers that they leane againſt: Not once ſtirred at all to heare of the heauenly inheritance, or of holineſſe, the meanes that muſt bring them to heauen, yea that worketh in mens hearts a kinde of Philip. 3. 20. 
               heauen vpon earth, and giueth Chriſtian men ſeizin of heauen euen while they liue here. An euident argument that either they beleeue not the Gaine of it, or they beleeue not themſelues to haue any ſhare in it.
            Fourthly, men would be oft taking account of their Gaines in this kinde, of their thriuing in Godlineſſe, if they held Godlineſſe to be ſo gainefull. 
               
                  
                     〈…〉
                  . Worldly men are very frequent and diligent herein, very carefull to keepe their bookes of receipt and expenſe, poaring euer and anon on them, running

oft ouer their reckonings, and caſting vp their accounts, to ſee how they thriue or pare in the world, how they goe forward or backward in wealth.
            But where we ſhall finde a man that hath the like care of keeping &amp; caſting vp his ſpiritual accounts, of 
                  Pſ 4. 4 &amp; 119. 59. Zeph. 2. 1. 1. Cor. 11. 28. 2. Cor. 13. 5. examining himſelfe for his ſpirituall eſtate, how he thriueth or pareth with the graces of Gods Spirit, how he goeth forward or backward in goodnes or Godlineſſe? And yet would our care be alike for either, did we equally apprehend the gaine of either. But let vs looke vnto it. For whither we call our ſelues to account here or no, God will queſtionleſſe one day call vs to an account. And then not onely Luk. 15. 13. 
               the prodigall Sonne, and the 
               Luk. 16. 1. 
               vnfaithfull Steward, that hath the one vnthriftily lauiſhed out his patrimonie, and the other riotouſly waſted his maſters wealth; but Math. 25. 30. 
               the idle and vnprofitable Seruant to
                  •
               , that hath not gained with his Talent, that hath not thriuen with the Grace of God beſtowed on him, ſhall be bound hand and foot, and cast out into vtter darknes, where ſhall be weeping and wailing, and gnaſhing of teeth.
            
            Fiftly, men would make more account of Godlineſſe, if they counted it as Gaine. Did they indeed account Godlineſſe more gainefull than Gaine, they would not put Godlineſſe away for Gaine, they would not prefer Gaine before Godlineſſe. Yea did they deeme Godlineſſe the gainfulleſt thing in the world, they would not forgo Godlineſſe for a world of wealth, or for ought elſe that were in the world.
            But it is with it, as it is with Time. It is a common

ſaying in euery mans mouth, that 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Theophraſtus apud L
                        ••
                     rtium &amp; Anti
                        •
                     ho apud Plutarch. Antonio.
                
               There is nothing in the world more precious than Time, and yet 
                  Quem mihi dabis qui preti
                        •
                      aliquod tempori p
                        •
                     nat. 
                        •
                     en. epiſt. 1. Non exig
                        •
                     ū temp
                        ••
                      is habemus, ſed multū perdimꝰ: non 
                        •••
                     pes eius, ſed prodigi ſumꝰ aſtricti ſunt homines in con
                        •
                     inend
                        •
                      patrimonio: ſimul ad temporis iactur 
                        •
                     m 
                        •
                     e
                        •
                     tum est, prof
                        •
                     
                     ſiſſ
                        •
                     mi in eo, 
                        •
                     uius vnius auari ia honeſta eſt. Idem de brev, vit. c. 1 &amp; 3. there is nothing generally more trifled away than it. So of Godlineſſe the moſt will (in word at leaſt) acknowledge, that there is nothing in the world more gainefull than it, and yet the moſt of them that ſo ſay, ſticke not to make it away for meere trifles. 
                  Ad mere
                        •••
                      
                     
                        •
                     ij ſumus; ad mercedē impij. honeſta q
                        •
                     ā
                     d
                        ••
                      aliqua illis ſpes ineſt, ſequi
                        •
                     ur: in co
                        ••
                     ra
                        •
                     ium tranſi
                     
                        •••
                     i, ſi plus ſcelera promi
                        •••
                     nt. Senec. epiſt 113. Et genus &amp; virtus, niſi cum re, vilior alga est. Horat. ſerm. lib. 2. ſat 5. 
               Godly they are content to be for aduantage, ſo long as Godlines bringeth in any worldly Gaine with it, or ſo long as there is no hope of any the like Gaine by vngodlineſſe. But let Godlineſſe ceaſe to bring in ſuch Gaine, they grow ſoone weary of it: or let but the leaſt hope of ſuch Gaine by vngodlineſſe ſhew it ſelf, &amp; they are ready preſently to exchange Godlineſſe for it.
            
               Matth. 16. 26. 
               What ſhould it auaile a man, ſaith our Sauiour, to winne the whole world, and looſe his owne ſoule? It were no Gaine for a man to get the whole world by vngodlineſſe; ſince he muſt withall looſe himſelfe, his life, his ſoule for his labour. But we are ready and willing, the moſt of vs, to part with Godlineſſe, and forgo good Conſcience, for far leſſe matters then that commeth to, for a penny or an halfe-penny toy now and then; to exchange it for ſome ſmall peece or patch of the world, for ſome ſory ſnip or ſtired of the pelfe of it, or for ought elſe that we haue ſome fond fancie vnto, the couetous worldling for a litle temporarie treaſure, and the laſciuious wanton for a litle tranſitorie pleaſure: like Hebr. 1
                     •
                  . 13. ex Gen. 25. 33. prophane Eſ
                     ••
                  , that ſold his birth-right for a meſſe of broth, and 
                  Pr. 28 21. Fruſto pa
                        •••
                      cō
                     
                        ••
                     ci poteſt, vel vti tac
                        •
                     at, v
                        •
                     l vti loqu
                        ••
                     ur. 
                        •
                     ato in C
                        •
                     liu
                        •
                      apud G
                        •
                     lliū l. 1. c. 15. 
               Salomons vniuſt iudge, that would d
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈…〉
                   
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   a 
                     〈…〉
                  ſe
                     ••
                   of bread, and

               Ezech. 13. 9. the falſe Prophets in Eechiels time, that would pollute Gods name for an handfull of barly.
            
            That which euidently ſheweth at how low a rate moſt men value Godlineſſe. For as a Abſt
                     •
                  m: in fabulis. ſcoffing companion ſometime told the Biſhop that would giue him his bleſſing when he would not giue him an halfe-penny, that If his bleſsing had bin worth an halfe-penny, he ſhould not haue had it. So if worldly men thought Godlineſſe, and the Feare and Fauour of God worth but an halfe-penny, they would not venture to put either away for an halfe-penny matter: they would not ſo readily exchange either for trifles, did they not make but a trifling matter of either.
            Neither may the greater ſort of ſuch men auoide this imputation, and waſh their hands with Math. 27. 24. 
               Pilate from the ſoile of this ſinne, becauſe they are wont to make Godlineſſe away for greater matters. To omit 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plato apud Plut. de vtil. ex inimic. Theſaur
                        ••
                      omnibus pretioſior eſt vir
                        •
                     ꝰ. Apul. de Philoſoph. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Euripid. apud Stob. tō. 2. c. 1. Vilius argentum eſt auro, virtutibus aurū. Horat. epiſt. Virtus praemium eſt optimum: virtus omnibus reb
                        ••
                      anteit. Plaut. Amphitr. 2. 2. that euen the greateſt of them will beare no weight at all, if they be laid in the ballance againſt Godlineſſe, when the whole world it ſelfe is too light to weigh againſt it. Thou thy ſelfe, who euer thou art, wilt cry out ſhame on ſome poore ſilly wretch, that ſhall forſweare himſelfe, and ſo damne his ſoule, as thou thy ſelfe ſaiſt, for a penny, when thou doſt thy ſelfe, it may be, in effect as much for ſomewhat more. But do thou conſider, as 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Ariſtippus apud Laert. l. 2. 
               Ariſtippus ſometime told Plato, that a penny may be as much to him as a pound is to thee, and a pound no more with thee than a penny with him: and therefore doeſt thou value Godlineſſe at as low a rate in ſtretching and ſtraining of thy Conſcience

for the one, as he in tentering it for the other.
            Laſtly, men would be content to take more paines for the compaſſing and increaſing of it in themſelues, if they held Godlineſſe to be gainefull. Men can well endure to ſit telling and taking money, and it were all day long, from morning to dark night: But to heare the word, but an houre, whereby the ſpirituall Gaine is gotten, the moſt can hardly endure: they ſit all that while on thornes, and thinke euery minute an houre, and are neuer well till all be done. They say, or thinke at leaſt with themſelues, as the prophane Iewes ſometimes ſaid, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Malac. 1. 12. 
               What a toyle, or a tediouſnes is here? what needeth ſo much preaching? what needeth ſo long praying? they thinke they might be as well, if not much better, without either: Yea many can not endure ſo long as till the houre be at an end. To whom God may well ſay, as our Sauiour to his drowſie Diſciples, Math. 26. 40. 
               What, could yee not watch an houre with me? So, Can yee not endure to waite an houre on me, that watch ſo many ouer you? On Si ab iſia hora, qua verbum Dei praedicare ceperim, gemm
                     •
                  s, vel annulos, vel monilia erogarem, an non filij mei ſtare &amp; accipere vellent? &amp;c. Aug. homil. 26. worldly Mammon they could be well content to waite all day long, with forbearance not of diſport onely, but of ordinarie diet too, that would thinke much but halfe an houre in the day to waite vpon him.
            Againe, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Antipha apud Stob. c. 10. Cogit auarities miſer
                        •
                     s &amp; caca cupido Noctes at
                        •
                      dies niti praest
                        ••
                     te labore, Lu
                     
                        ••••
                     . de nat. rer
                        •
                     m lib. 3. for worldly wealth men can toile and moile all the weeke long; and yet are they not wearie; they thinke not the whole weeke long enough neither: But for the heauenly Gaine, for the ſpirituall thrift, we haue but one day of ſeuen, and we

thinke that too much too: we thinke the day all too long, the labour all loſt, and the whole time caſt away, that we imploy and ſpend to this purpoſe. We ſay as the ſame Iewes at an other time ſaid; Amos 8. 5. 
               When will the New Moone be past; and the Sabbath once ouer? that we may returne againe vnto our worldly affaires. Yea many among vs haue not the patience to tarry ſo long, but ſpend a great part of the Sabbath, that is Gods Market or Mart-day, for the getting of this ſpirituall Gaine, either about their worldly affaires. or their bodily delights.
            
               The Sabbath day, I ſay, is Gods Market-day. And thoſe that ſeeke to take away the Sabbaths, attempt to put downe Gods Markets, and ſo do the Deuill good ſeruice, whatſoeuer their intent be. As frequenting of Markets maketh a Rich man; ſo keeping of Sabbaths maketh a rich Chriſtian. And as we count him a bad Huſband, that followeth Game on the Market-day: ſo may we as well count him a ſpirituall vnthrift, that ſpendeth the Sabbath in that ſort.
            But may ſome ſay, when we haue bin at Church, and heard the Sermon and Seruice, is not Gods Market-day then done?
            I anſwer: If the Sabbath be Lecit. 23. 32. Matth. 28. 1. 
               a day, then is it not ſo ſoone done. Debet totus dies feſtium à Chriſtiano expendi in operibus ſanctis. Rob. Groſthed Lincoln. Epiſt. in Decalog. pracept. 3. 
               Gods Market laſteth all day long.
            
            Yea, grant the principall, becauſe the publike, of it bee paſt: yet as Market-folks returning from Market will bee talking of their Markets, as they goe by the way, and be caſting vp of

their penny-worths, when they come home, reckon what they haue taken, and what they haue laid out, and how much they haue gotten: So ſhould we, after we haue heard the word publikely, conferre priuately of it with others; at leaſt meditate on it by our ſelues, and be ſure to take an account of our ſelues, how we haue profited that day by the word that hath bin ſpoken vnto vs, and by other religious exerciſes that haue bin vſed of vs. And as the Marketman counteth that but an euill market-day, that he hath not gained ſomewhat on more or leſſe: So may we well account it an euill Sabbath to vs, whereon we haue not profited ſomewhat, whereon we haue not either increaſed our knowledge, or bin bettred in affection; whereon we haue not bin further either informed in iudgment, or reformed in practiſe, whereon we haue added no whit at all to our Talent.
            To winde vp all in a word. If we hold Godlineſſe to be, as the Apoſtle here ſaith it is, a matter of Gaine, and of great Gaine, that which maketh Gaine to be Gaine, and without which Gaine it ſelfe is no Gaine indeede; that Omnia adſunt bona, quem penes eſt virtus. (pietas.) Plaut. Amphitr. 2. 2. it bringeth all good with it to him that hath it; and that it neuer leaueth him, but abideth with him, and ſticketh by him for euer: Oh let vs labour then to get of it, and to grow more and more in it; let vs endeuor to out-go one an other in Godlineſſe; let vs call our ſelues to a reckoning how we thriue or pare in it; let vs 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Solō apud Plut. d
                        •
                      
                     
                        •
                     ig
                        •••
                      
                     
                        〈…〉
                      &amp; d
                        •
                      
                     
                        •
                     tili
                        •
                     .   
                        〈…〉
                     . &amp; do tranquill.
                not put it away for ſuch trifles and toyes as the

world or the 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Chryſoſt. tom 7. eclog. 30 &amp; tom. 6. ſerm. 73. &amp; in Math. hō. 3.
                Deuill ſhall tender vnto vs to bereaue vs of ſo pretious a pearle; Eſpecially let vs haue a care of frequenting Esai. 55. 1. Gods markets, of obſeruing Gods Sabbaths, the principall meanes of increaſing this ſpirituall wealth in vs. So ſhall it come to paſſe that we ſhall haue God to be our portion; we ſhall be heires of his Kingdom, and coheires with his Chriſt; we ſhall haue all the good things both of this life and the next aſſured vnto vs here, and the full fruition of them for euer hereafter.
            The end of the first Part.
         
         
            
            
            THE SECOND PART. The Sufficiencie of it in it Selfe.
            
               HItherto of the maine Point, to wit, that Godlineſſe is great Gaine. Now becauſe this Propoſition will not either eaſily enter into mens mindes, or ſinck ſodainely into their hearts: The Holy Ghoſt by the Apoſtle is content to bring a double proofe of it.
            The one drawne from the time preſent; becauſe it is able alone to giue a man Contentment here, that which all the world elſe is not able to do, expreſſed in this verſe:
            The other taken from the time to come; becauſe it will continue with and abide by a man for euer hereafter, that which no worldly wealth, or ought elſe in the world can doe, implied in the Verſ. 7. next verſe.
            
               Godlineſſe with Contentment, or, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                
               with Self-ſufficiencie: For ſo it is word for word in the Originall; and the word ſo properly importeth. As if he had ſaid: Godlineſſe and Contentment are two inſeparable Companions, that continually harbour and keepe houſe
               
               togither, that go euer hand in hand the one with other: ſo that a man can not haue the one without the other, he cannot want the one if he haue the other. There is no true Godlineſſe, where there is not Contentment of Minde; no true Contentment of Minde, where Godlineſſe is not.
            So that the Apoſtle ſeemeth to reaſon on this wiſe.
            
               That which of it ſelfe is ſufficient to content the minde of Man, that is true Gaine, and great Gaine indeed: For it is no ſmall matter that will ſuffice to ſtay and ſettle Mans minde.
            
            
               But Godlineſſe is of it ſelfe ſufficient to content the Minde of Man, and doth euer bring true Contentment with it to him that hath it.
            
            
               Godlineſſe therefore is true Gaine and great Gaine indeede.
            
            Hence then may we deduce theſe three Concluſions to be conſidered of in order:
            1. That Contentment of Minde is a moſt pretious Treaſure.
            2. That Godlineſſe alone can produce and procure this Contentment.
            3. That true Contentment is an vndoubted Argument of Godlineſſe.
            For the firſt: 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Epicur. ap ud Laert.
                Contentment of Minde is an vnvaluable, an ineſtimable Treaſure. For it is that indeed that maketh Riches to be Riches. 
                  Quis diues? qui nil cupiat. quis pauper? auarus. Bias apud Auſon. in 7. Sap. Divitia grandes homini ſunt vi
                     
                        ••
                     re parc
                        •
                      Aequo 
                        ••
                     im
                        •
                     
                     ▪ Lucret. l. 5. Nom eſſe cupidum pecunià eſt: nō eſſe emacē 
                     
                        •
                     ectigal eſt: contentum verò ſuis vebus eſſe maxima ſunt certiſſimaqus diuitiae. 
                        〈◊〉
                     . parad. 
                  
                     •
                  . 
               Who is rich, ſaith one well, but he that liueth content with his eſtate? who is poore, but he that neuer hath enough. 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Democrit. apud Stob. c. 95. That is true wealth indeed, that freeth a man from want. But 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Chryſoſt. in 1. Cor. h
                        •
                     m. 13. Ex an
                        •
                     m
                        •
                      re
                        ••
                      ſtare 
                        •
                     quum puto, 
                        〈…〉
                     . Auſon. Non qui parum habet, ſed qui pl
                        •
                      cupit, pauper eſt. Sē. ep. 2. Inſtructa. 
                        ••
                     pi
                        •
                      eſt in di
                     
                        •
                     i
                        •••
                      cupiditas. P. Syr.
                what w
                  •••
               th call we that, when a man

is alwaies in want? Or 
                  Semper auarus eget. H
                        •
                     r. epiſt. 2. l. 1. Semper inops, quicun
                        •
                      cupit. Claud. in Ruff
                        ••
                     . Egen
                        ••
                      hoc nō abundātis ſignū eſt. Cic. parad. 6 how is not that man alwaies in want, that is not cōtent with what he hath?
            And on the other ſide, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Chryſ. in Eph. h
                        •
                     m. 21. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Dires á 
                        ••
                     vꝰ, qui vt Deus, nihil indigere videtur. Varro de ling. Lat. l. 4. Ita tu pauperem iudicas, 
                        •
                     ui nihil d
                        ••
                     st? Sen. ep. 119. Locuples eſt, qui paupertati ſu
                        •
                      aptu
                        •
                      eſt, &amp; paruo ſe divitem fec
                        ••
                     . Ibid. 108. Cui cum paupertat
                        •
                      benè convenit, dives eſt. Ibid. 2. &amp; Greg. in Ezech. l. 2. hom. 18. how is he poore, that ſuffreth no want? Or 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Diviti
                        •
                      ſunt maxim
                        •
                      divitijs no
                        •
                      indigere. Chryſ. in Pſal. 111. Qua ſunt maxima divitiae? divitiae non deſider
                        •
                     r
                        •
                     . Mart. Dum. de morib. Ibi vera copia, vbi nulla eſt indigentia. Aug de temp. 212. I
                        •
                      maximè diaitijs fruitur, qui minimè divitijs indiget. Sen. ep. 14. Locupletem illum facie
                        •
                     at non multa poſſidere, ſed modi
                        •
                     a de
                        •
                     iderare▪ de Fabricio Val. Max: l. 4. c. 3. Oīa nimirum habet, qui nihil conc
                        •
                     piſ
                        •
                     it. Ibid.
                what wanteth he, that reſteth content with what he hath? 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 2. Cor. 6. 10. Sapientem nulla re indigere. Chryfippus apud Sen. ep. 9. Quid deeſſe poteſt extra de
                        •
                     iderium omnium pofite? quid extrinſ
                        •
                      
                     
                        〈…〉
                      eſt ei qui omnia ſua in ſe collegit? Sen. de vit. beat. c. 16. Is mini
                        ••
                      eget mortali
                        •
                     , qui mini
                        〈…〉
                     cupit. Quod vult habet, qui velle quod ſatis eſt, poteſt. Idem ep. 108. Sanctus ergo quiſ
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      terreni
                        •
                      non indiget, etiamſi haec non habet. pauper eſt autem qui eget eo quod non habet. 
                        〈◊〉
                      &amp; qui non habens habere non appetit, dives eſt. Greg. in Ezech. hom. 18. Hinc illud Socratis; Quam multis ego non indigeo? Laert. &amp; Cic. Yuſ
                        •
                     . 5. Many things may he be without, and yet Carere enint eſt egere 
                     •
                  o quod habere velis. Cic. Tuſc
                     ••
                  . l. 1. Et Indigentia libido inexpl
                     ••
                  ilis. Ibid. 4. wanteth he nothing; no more than Non tu dives, &amp; Angelus pauper, quia non habet 
                     ••
                  
                  menta &amp; r
                     ••
                  da
                     •
                   &amp; fam
                     •
                  los. quare? quia non indiget. tu
                     ••
                   verè dives eris, quand
                     •
                   nullius indigens eri
                     •
                  . Aug. de temp. 74. the bleſſed Spirits and Angels in Heauen want foode or ſuch fare as we can in no wiſe liue without here vpon earth. He is no more poore or vnhappy, becauſe he hath them not, than 
                  Socrates dicere ſolitus eum Dijs eſſe ſimillimum, qui qua
                        ••
                      pauci
                        ••
                     i
                     
                        ••
                     is egeret, cum Dij nullius egeant rei. Animus eſt qui divitem facit. pecunia nihil ad an
                        〈…〉
                     pertinet; non magis quam ad Deos immortales terrena pondera iſta omni
                        •
                      quae ſuſpiciunt mortales Sen. ad Helv. c. 11. Quae parat
                        •
                      nobis ſunt, nō habet in vſ
                        •
                      Deu
                        •
                     . Idem ep. 74. Si quis de f
                        •
                     licitate Diogenis dubitat, quod non aurum, non opes hab
                        •
                     at, poteſt idem dubitare de Deorum immortali
                        •••
                      ſtatu, an parum beatè degant, quod illis non pr
                        •
                     di
                        •
                     , non 
                        ••
                     rti, non rur
                        •
                     preti
                        •
                     ſ
                        •
                     , non grande in 
                        〈◊〉
                      foenus. Idem de vit. beat. c. 8. God is, or the Angels are, becauſe they haue not heaps of gold and ſiluer, and other ſuch earthly traſh horded vp by them in Heauen.
            Againe, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Ariſto
                        •
                     . rhetor. l. 1. c. 5. Quo mihi divitiae, quarum 
                        •
                     i dempſeri
                        •
                      vſ
                        ••
                     , Qu
                        〈…〉
                     divet 
                        〈◊〉
                     , ſ
                        〈…〉
                     egenus ero. Maxim. eleg. 1. Legatur hac de re Teletis diſſertati
                        •
                      apud St
                        •
                     b. c. 95. 
               Riches, as the Heathen man truly obſerueth, conſist not ſo much in the poſſeſsion of tem, as
               
               in the fruition of them. But it is Contentment a lone that giueth a man a comfortable vſe and fruition of what he hath, that procureth him profit and pleaſure of what he poſſeſſeth. For Vltra ſe cupidttas porrigit, &amp; falicitatem ſuam nō attendit. Sen. debe
                  
                     •
                  efl
                     ••
                   27. Novis ſemper cupiditatibꝰ occupati, non quid hab
                     •
                  amus, ſed quid petamus inſpicimꝰ: non ad id quod est, ſed ad id quod appetitur, intenti. lb. l. 3. c. 3. Quid est quod faciat obliuionem acceptorum? cupiditas accipiendorum, Idē epiſt. 8
                     •
                  . Quid aveantꝰ, quā quid habeamꝰ, mēs frequentiu
                     •
                   cogitas. where a man reſteth not content with what he hath, there is the minde ſo caried after that he further deſireth and hath not, that he no more regardeth or joyeth in what he hath, Avaro tā d
                     •
                  est quod habet, quam quod 
                     〈…〉
                   multa, av
                     •
                  riti
                     •
                   o
                  
                     •
                  nia, Idem Sen. op. 108. than if it were not at all. And where a man is diſcontent with his preſent eſtate, there is all that he hath, be it neuer ſo much, rather a burden than any way a benefit vnto him; like meat that a, greeing not with the ſtomacke, lieth in it vndigeſted, and not only proueth vnpleaſant and vnprofitable, affording neither good relliſh nor ſound nouriſhment, but noyſome alſo and burdenſome to the whole bodie. So that where Contentment is not, a man regardeth nothing: and where Diſcontent is, it infecteth and tainteth all things, and ſo maketh them, as if ſome malignant blaſt had blowne on them, vnſauoury and diſtaſtfull to him that ſo hathr Non domne &amp; 
                        〈…〉
                      a 
                        〈…〉
                      corpor
                        〈…〉
                     Non animo cu
                        •
                     as, No
                        •
                     
                     ▪ op. 2. l. 1. them, rather ſicke of them, than endowed with them. And certainely as a man diſeaſed in bodie can haue litle ioy of his wealth, be it neuer ſo much; ſince as the Heathen man ſaith, A golden Crowne cannot cure the Head-ach, nor a veluet ſlipper giue eaſe
               
                  
                     •
                   
                  
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Plut. de tranquill.
                
               of the Gow
                     •
                  , nor a Purple robe fray away a burning Feuer. And, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . S
                        •
                     ct. apud Stab. c. 92. Non magnis 
                        〈…〉
                      corpora c
                        •••
                     nt: Nec calida citiꝰ 
                        〈◊〉
                      corpore 
                        ••
                     bres, Tentilibꝰ ſi in picturis oſtro
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      
                     
                        〈…〉
                      quā 
                     
                        •
                     i plebe
                        ••
                     i
                        •
                      veſte cubandū eſt. 
                        〈…〉
                     dū, nihil differt, v
                        •
                     r
                        〈…〉
                     lecto, an in aur
                        •
                     o coll
                        •
                     ces; quocun
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      illū tranſtul
                        〈…〉
                     ſ
                        ••
                      ſecū transfert: ſic nihil 
                        〈…〉
                      age
                        •
                     i
                        •
                      divitijs an in paupertate pon
                        ••
                     ur; malū ſ
                        •
                     ū illū ſequitur. Sen. ep. 17. 
               A ſicke man is alike ſicke, whereſoeuer ye
               
               lay him, on a bed of gold, or on a pad of ſtraw, with a ſilken quilt or with a ſory rug on him. So no more can riches, gold and ſiluer, land or liuing, had a man much more than euer any man had, miniſter vnto him much ioy, yea or any true and ſound ioy at all, where the minde is diſtract and diſcontent: without Contentment there is no ioy of ought; there is no profit, there is no pleaſure in ought. Eccleſ. 2. 10. 
               All without it is but vanitie and vexation of Spirit.
            
            Will we ſee this by an Example or two further confirmed to vs? Haman, was he not a moſt happy man, as the world accounteth happineſſe, 
                  Nemo foelix eſt, qui iudicio ſuo miſer eſt. Salvian. de provid. lib. 1. Non est beatus, eſſe ſe qui non putat. P. Syr. Miſer eſt qui. ſe non beatiſſimum iudicat. Sen. ep. 10. if he could haue thought ſo himſelfe? Eſter 3. 1, 2. the next man in the Kingdome to the King himſelfe, the greateſt one of them that then was; he tooke place by the Kings appointment of all the Princes his Peeres, and all the Kings Court, by the Kings expreſſe command, bowed and did obeyſance to him: Eſter 5. 13. he vaunteth himſelfe of his glory, the multitude of his children, the abundance of his treaſure, his eſpeciall fauour and inwardnes both with the King and the Queene: enough a man would thinke to content any man Egens aquè eſt is qui non ſatis habet, &amp; is cui nihil ſatis poteſt eſſe. Cornif. ad Herenn. l. 4. that had not an vnmeaſurable minde. And yet, ſaith he, that is the concluſion of his diſcourſe, Eſter. 5. 13. O dives, neſcis quam pauper fis. quam inops tibi ipſi videris, qui te divitē dicis? Ambr. de Nabuth. cap. 2. 
               all this doth me no good: It was all as good as nothing to him; he was neuer the better for all this, ſo long as he wanted a cap and a courteſie of Mordecai; becauſe Mordecai bowed not the knee vnto him, nor adored him, as other the Kings Courtiers did. It was with him, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Plut. de tranquill.
                
               as with litle children, (ſaith an Heathen man well of ſuch) playing in the ſtreets, who,

if ſome man as he paſſeth by take one of their toyes from them, are ready to caſt all the reſt away from them, though they haue many more left, and ſit crying and whining for that one that is gone.
            Paſſe we from a Kings fauourite to a King himſelfe. King Ahab had land and liuing enough and enough, (much more than 1. King. 16. 16. his Father Omri was euer borne to,) had he not wanted this Contentment of minde. But 1. King. 21. 1, 2, 3, 4. the litle Vineyard of his poore Neighbour was ſuch an eye-ſore to his greedy affection, that the diſcontent that he conceiued, becauſe he could not preſently compaſſe it, Duos ſinitimos hiſtoria vetus deſcribit, Regem A. &amp; pauperē N. quē horum pauperiorem, quem d
                     •
                  iorem credimus? alter regali fulcro divitiarum praeditus, exiguam pauperis vineē deſideravit: alter animo deſpiciens regias gazas, ſuo erat contentus palmite. an non hîc magis dives, magis Reu, qui ſibi abundabat, cupiditates ſuas regiba
                     •
                  , vt alieni nihil concupiſceret: ille autem egentiſſi
                  
                     •
                  us, cui aurū ſuum vilt, al
                     ••
                  nus palmes pretiofiſſimus erat? Ambr. epiſt. 10 Rex ſibi egere viſu
                     •
                   eſt, quia vineam habebat pauper vici
                     •••
                  . ille regni opibus affluebat, &amp; tamen ceſpitē pauperis ſlagitabat: pauper nihil depoſſeſſionibus concupivit divitis. al
                     ••
                  r certè cenſu pauper videtur, alter pauper eſt affectu. Idem de Nabuth c. 2. made him poorer than poore Naboth, that deſired nothing that he had; and depriued him of his whole Kingdome that he had no profit of it, tooke no pleaſure in it; but, like a man that were in extreme want and neceſſitie, he getteth him home to his houſe, &amp; ſhutteth himſelf vp in his Chamber, like one that durſt not be ſeen abroad for feare of arreſts; he caſteth himſelf on the bed and refuſeth his meat, like a man that tooke thought for the payment of his debts: He fareth, in a word, as the former Author ſaith of ſuch, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plut. de tranquill.
                
               like a ſullen Hen, that hauing ſtore of barly lieng by her, getteth her aſide into ſome corner, and forſaking her meat, ſcrapeth alone by her ſelfe, there to finde ſomewhat that ſhe may be picking vp out of the dunghill.
            Yea come we to them that were indeede Lords of the whole world, not in title onely, but in truth, hauing and injoying that by Gods free gift, that none ſince them were euerable to come any thing

neere, much leſſe to attaine vnto. Geneſ. 3. 1, 2, 3. 
               Adam and Eve our firſt Parents, albeit they were in the garden of Eden, (a place abounding, as 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Paradiſii voluptatis. Vulg. hortos delicatiſſimos. Leo Iud.
                the word importeth, with matter of pleaſure and delight) amids all earthly happineſſe; and had the whole world in their hands, and all the Creatures at command: yet no ſooner had the Diuell ſowen this vnhappy ſeede of Diſcontent (the very firſt ſinne of theirs, as I take it with ſome other Reuerend) in their hearts, but they began preſently to deeme themſelues poore &amp; in want, becauſe they had not what they would; they account themſelues as depriued and debarred of all things, if they may not haue the fruit of that one tree that was only denied them, and Gen. 2. 17. of which God had foretold them, that whenſoeuer Gen. 3. 3. they touched it or taſted of it, it would be their bane. As if ſome great rich man, or mighty Monark, hauing wealth in abundance, and the world at will, euen whatſoeuer heart could wiſh, yet ſhould thinke himſelfe ſtreitned and cut ſhort, but a miſerable creature, or not ſo happy as he might be, becauſe he can not, with Harpalum Alexandro mandante omni modo admiſū, vt hederam in paradiſis Babyloni adiacentibus ſereret, fruſtra fuiſſe, narrant Theophr. hiſt. plaut. l 4. c. 4. Plinhiſt. nat. l. 16. c. 34. &amp; Plut. in Alex. 
               Alexander, get greene Iuie to grow in his Gardens at Babylon; or becauſe he may not, with Cum medico monente, p
                     •
                  rcina non apponeretur, vt pot
                     •
                   podagra, qua Papa laborabit, inimica, Aff
                     •
                  r, inquit, mihi ferculū, al diſpetto di Dio. Balaus in Iul: 3. 
               Pope Iulius, feede vpon Swines fleſh, or ſome other diſh by his Phyſitians forbidden him in regard of ſome diſeaſe hanging vpon him, likely to be his bane if he do; and ſo lye languiſhing and 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Quod 
                        •
                     nopolae ſervus de her
                        •
                      ſuo, quicum vinum venderet, Vippa
                        •
                      ipſe potabat. Plut. de tranq.
                longing after his owne euill, when he hath good enough at hand, as if it were miſerie for a man to want that, though he haue no neede of it, that would but hurt him if he had it. Ye ſee, that a man may be in Paradiſe, (I might well ſay, in heauen too, as the Diuell

once was,) and yet not be happy, if he haue not a contented minde.
            As on the other ſide, where this Contentment of Minde is, there is wealth euen in want, much more cheerefulnes in wealth: There is, as a ſtay of the deſire, ſo a reſting and a reioycing in that a man enjoyeth: and therefore a comfortable vſage of it, be it more or leſſe, becauſe content in it. It is that alone that ſeaſoneth all: it is that alone that ſweetneth all: It is that that is able, not onely to ſeaſon thoſe things that are ſweet and pleaſant in their owne nature, but euen Animus 
                     •
                  q
                     •••
                   optimū eſt 
                     •
                  rum
                     ••
                   condimentū. Plaut. Rudent. 2. 3. Nihil t
                     •
                  m acerbum eſt, in quo non 
                     •
                  qu
                     ••
                   animus ſolatium in 
                     •
                  e
                  
                     ••
                  at. Sen, ad Helv. cap. 10. to ſweeten alſo thoſe things vnto a man, that are harſh and vnpleaſant in themſelues.
            It is Contentment therefore onely that maketh a man truly wealthy, becauſe it freeth him from want, and giueth him comfort of that he hath. And as a 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plut. de tranquill.
                peece of dry bread is more ſauoury to a man when he is in health, than all the dainties in the world are when he is heart-ſick: So a litle, ſaith Sal
                     •
                  man, euen 
                  Pro. 17. 1. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  
                     
                        〈…〉
                      St
                        ••
                     . 
                        〈…〉
                     
                   2. c. 
                  
                     •
                   5. 
               a morſell of dry bread is better and more with quiet and content, than a whole houſe full of fat beaſts with an vnquiet heart, than a whole world of wealth with a diſcontented minde.
            Now two wayes may this point bee vſefull vnto vs.
            Firſt, to informe vs, what cauſe they haue to be thankfull vnto God, be they rich or poore, whom he hath vouchſafed this grace vnto, whom Philip. 
                     •
                  . 11, 12. he hath taught, in whatſoeuer eſtate they are, therewith to be content. For euen the pooreſt man that liueth content with his preſent eſtate, is richer than the richeſt

man in the world that hath not a contented minde: he is happier than Adam and Eve were ſometime in Paradiſe, when they longed to eat of the fruit forbidden them: Senſit Alexander teſt a cum vidit in illa Mag
                     •
                  ū habitatorem, quanto foelicior is, qui Nil cup
                     •
                  ret, quàm qui totum ſibi poſceret (poſſidet) orbem. Iuven. ſat. 14. Si cui ſua non videntur ampliſſima, licet totius mundi dominus ſit, miſer eſt. Epicuru
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  pud Sen. ep. 9. he is a greater man than great Alexander himſelf, and in far better plight than he, euen for the preſent. For 
                  Vnus Pelleo i
                        •
                     
                     ueni non ſufficit orbis. Aeſtuat infoelix anguſto limite mū
                     di, Vt Gy
                        •
                     ri clauſus ſcopulis, paruaque Seripho. Iuven. ſat. 10. Numquā parū eſt, quod ſatis est: numquā mul
                        •
                     ū eſt, quod ſatis non eſt. Poſt Darium &amp; Ind
                        •
                     s pauper eſt Alexander Macedoquaerit quod ſuum faciat; maria ignota ſcrutatur, mundi clauſtra perrumpit. Quod naturae ſatis eſt, homini non eſt. Inventus eſt qui concupiſceret aliquid poſt omnia: detecto fine terrarum per ſuu
                        •
                      r
                        •
                     ditu
                        ••
                     s orbem triſtis eſt Sen. epiſt. 119. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Arrian. diſſert. l. 3. c. 9. he, ſor want hereof, when he had won the whole world, yet as if he had bin pinched and ſtraitned for roome, or penned vp in a corner or in a priſon, as if the whole world were not able to hold him, (whereas Mors ſola fatetur Quantula 
                     •
                  int hominum corpuſcula. mortuus idem Sarcophago contentus erit. Juven. ſat. 10. he could not take vp ſo much as ten foote of ground, as In paleſtra prolapſus, cum in pulu
                     •
                  r
                     •
                   corporis veſtigium vidiſſet, Pap
                     •
                  , inquit, vt minimam terrae partem natura ſortiti, orbem appetim
                     ••
                   vniuerſum? Eraſm. apophth. l. 4. his Father Philip ſaw, when he fell in the wreſtling place, and viewed the print and proportion of his body there in the duſt) 
                  Cum Anaxagoram audiſſet mundos innumerabiles aſſer
                        ••
                     
                     tem, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Alexander apud Plut.
                he ſa
                  •
                weeping and wailing, like a forlorne perſon, that he could not finde out a new world to be winning. Whereas, by benefit hereof many a poore Childe of God, that hath not halfe that that he had, yea that hath not a patch of land in the world, but liueth from hand to mouth by his daily labour, yet paſſeth his time as merrily, (as that Cynick ſometime told his hoaſt at Athens) as if 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Dioge
                        •
                     . apud Plut. de tranquill.
                
               euery day were Holyday, or a Feſtiuall day with him: According to that alſo which Salomon ſaith, that
            
               
               
                  Prov. 15. 15. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
                     〈…〉
                   
                  
                     ••
                  . 36. 
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   Ph
                     •••
                   A
                     ••••
                   
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Schol. idem fere Prou. 17 22. 
               A merry heart, or a contented minde, (for it is not ſpoken directly of a good Conſcience, as it is commonly taken; (though it be true alſo of that, and that be a meane to procure this;) as may appeare both by the oppoſition of the other member, and by the ſequele of the context) is a perpetuall banquet, a continuall feaſt.
            The poore man then hath as great cauſe to be thankfull to God for his Contentment of minde, as
                  
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  omnes 
                        •
                     ies afflict
                        •
                      mali. Sic
                        ••
                      Gen. 47▪ 9. &amp; Math. 6. 34. the Rich man for his riches. Conceiue it by this Compariſon. Suppoſe two men lye ſicke of the ſame diſeaſe, a burning Fever, or ſome ſuch like hot diſeaſe, as cauſeth drought and deſireth drinke, and call both inſtantly for cold water to quench their thirſt with. The Phyſitian comming to them, biddeth giue the one that is more impatient, a good quantitie of cold drinke, and yet he cryeth and calleth ſtill for more. To the other he miniſtreth himſelfe a litle conſ
                  •
               rue on the point of a knife, that ſlaketh his thirſt and aſſwageth his drought. Whether of the twaine in this caſe is more beholden vnto him? So here; euery one almoſt cryeth to God for wealth: few pray with wiſe
                  Prov. 30. 8 paſce me 
                        •••
                     o demenſi mei 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                
               Agur for a competent eſtate. Now A 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  A
                        ••
                     ian. diſſert. lib. 
                  
                     •
                  . 
                     
                        ••
                     p. 
                  
                     •
                  . 
                     
                        〈…〉
                      
                     
                        ••
                     c
                        •
                     t 
                        〈…〉
                      
                     
                        •••
                     quam 
                        〈…〉
                      i
                        •
                     e
                        •
                     plobilē 
                     
                        〈…〉
                      non magis quàm vllus 
                        〈…〉
                      ad ſa
                        •
                     i
                        ••
                     
                     
                     
                        •••
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     , 
                        〈◊〉
                      deſiderium 
                        ••
                     n 
                        〈◊〉
                      inopia, ſed ex 
                        •
                     ſt
                        •
                      
                     
                        ••
                     denti
                        •
                     m viſc
                        •
                     rum 
                        ••
                     it
                        •
                     r. non 
                        〈…〉
                      illa, 
                        ••
                     d mor
                        ••••
                      eſt. quicqui
                        •
                      illic congeſſeri
                        •
                     , 
                        ••
                     n 
                        〈◊〉
                      erit cupidi
                        •••••
                     , ſ
                        •
                     d gra
                     
                        〈…〉
                     Helv. c. 11. to one that thus prayeth, God giueth abundance of wealth, as a deale of cold water to quench his thirſt, and yet he h
                  •
               th gaping ſtill Ex m
                     •
                  guis vt 
                     •••
                  eſt, 
                     〈…〉
                  di. Se
                     ••
                  c▪ 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   benef lib. 3. cap. 
                     •
                  . for more, as inſ
                  •
               ti
                  •
               ble, ſaith Salomon, 
               Prov. 30. 16. 
               as the graue, or the barren wombe, or the dry land, or 
               Savior ignibus Aetna 
                     •••
                  rens amor at
                     ••
                  et h
                     •
                  b
                     ••
                  di. 
                     •
                  o
                     •
                  t. c
                     ••
                  fol. l. 2. 
                     •••
                  tr. 5. 
               the f
                     •
                  re that
               
               neuer haue enough. To another 
                  
                     •
                   multa petentibus Deſunt multa. bene eſt cui Deus obtulit parca quod ſatis eſt manu. Hor. carm. 3. 16. he giueth a Competencie, ſome ſmall pitance, but Contentment withall, as a litle Phyſicall Confection, that ſtinteth and ſtayeth his deſire. Whether of the twaine, thinke we, haue more cauſe to be thankfull vnto him, and to acknowledge his goodnes towards them? The latter doubtles, as he enioyeth the greater benefit, ſo he hath greater cauſe of thankfulnes to him from whom he hath it.
            Againe this may ſerue to incite vs to labour earneſtly for this Contentment, and to pray inſtantly vnto God for it.
            And it is hard here to ſay, whether a man had more neede to perſwade the poore man to be content with his pouertie, or the rich man with his riches. For as Matth. 2. 9. the Star that went before the Wiſemen, went when they went, and ſtayed where they ſtayed: So H 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Chryſo
                        •
                     t. in 1. Cor. h
                        •
                     m. 14. N
                        •
                     minem pe
                        ••
                     nia divit
                        ••
                      fecit; im
                        •
                      nulli non maiorem ſui cupidita
                        •
                     em incu
                        ••
                     it: plus incipi
                        •
                      habere poſſe, qui plus habet. Sen. 
                        •
                     p. 119. Nunquam diues e
                        •
                     i
                        •
                     , nunquam ſatiab
                        •
                     re qu
                        •
                     ſtu: Se
                        •
                     per inops, quicun
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      c
                        •
                     pit. Claud. in 
                        ••
                     ſin. l. 1. Magn
                        ••
                      inter opes inops. 
                        •
                     or. car. 3. 16. Qui vult eſſe dives, p
                        ••
                     per eſt. Aug. d
                        •
                      temp. Nunquā par
                        •
                      eſt, quod ſatis eſt, nunquā multū eſt, quod ſ
                        •
                     tis non eſt. Sen. ep. 119. Qui conti
                        •••
                     it ſe intra natur
                        •
                     lem modum, paupertaten
                        •
                      non ſe
                        •
                     ti
                        •
                     t: qui naturalem modum 
                        ••
                     cedit, eum in ſummis opibus quo
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      paupertas ſequetur. Idem ad Helv. c. 11. riches flie the faſter from a man, the more eagerly he followeth them, but then ſtay, when a mans minde is ſtayed. Till that be, 
                  
                     ••
                  gg. 1. 6. 
               all is put (as the Prophet ſpeaketh in another caſe) into a broken bag, that will hold nothing, or 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Dion. Chryſoſt. 
                        •
                     ra
                        •
                     . 47. 
               into a bottomles barrell, as the prouerbe is, that is neuer a whit the fuller for all that is put in: And we are but like thoſe that haue a flux, that take in much, but retaine nothing, and ſo thriue not with their meat, are nothing fuller or fatter for it, till this 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  ani
                        •
                     i proſt
                        •
                     
                     nium, qu
                        •
                      laborant, iſti, quomodo 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  illi Athen: l. 4. ſpirituall looſeneſſe of ours be by Contentment ſtayed with vs.
            
               As Num. 9. 17, 18. the Children of Iſrael therefore paſſing along the wilderneſſe, marched forward on their way when the Cloud went that conducted them, but there ſtood ſtill where it ſtayed. So may our affections walke on, while Gods hand goeth before them: but looke where God ſtayeth his hand and ceaſeth to giue, there ſhould our heart ſtay likewiſe, and we ceaſe to deſire.
            To perſwade our hearts the rather hereunto, vſe we a double conſideration, concerning others, and concerning our ſelues.
            Concerning others, either thoſe that go beyond vs in riches, or thoſe that come ſhort of vs in wealth.
            For the former; Nihil habet diues de diuitijs, niſs quod ab illo poſtutat pauper; vict
                     •
                  m &amp; reſtitum: Caetera omnia eius ſuperſtua ſunt. Aug. de verb. Dō. 5. -nil Divitiae poterūt regales addere maius. Hor. ep. 12. l 1. he that hath more then thou haſt, can but liue and eate and drinke as thou doeſt. And therefore 1. Tim. 6. 8. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Pythagor. apud Stob. cap. 99. In quantum ſitis at
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                     , fames, &amp; frig
                        •
                     ra poſcunt. Iuuen. ſat. 14. Corporis exigua deſideria ſunt 
                        •
                      frigu
                        •
                      ſubmover
                        •
                      vult, alimē
                     tis famer
                        •
                      as ſitim extinguere: quicquid extra concupiſcitur, vitijs, non vſibus laboratur. Sen. ad Helv. c. 10. 
               if thou haſt, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, but food and apparell; (he ſaith not 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               cates or 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               delicates, but 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               foode, that that may feede: he ſaith not 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , ornamenta.
                
               ornaments or abillements, but 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  operimenta.
                
               couerings or Garments quaſ
                        •
                     
                   Gard nents. Minſhew.
                
               garments, 
               
                  
                     ••
                   toga que defendere frigus, Quamvis craſſa, queat. Horat. ſerm. lib. 1. ſatyr. 3. ſo much as may couer thee and keepe thee from cold) thou haſt as much as the mightieſt Monarke, as the wealthieſt man in the world can haue.
            As Exod. 16. 17, 18. the children of Iſraell gathered Manna, ſome more, ſome leſſe, but euery man of them, hee that gathered moſt, had no more then his Homer. So here, though men gather wealth ſome more, ſome leſſe, yet hath euery man but his 
               Demenſans portionem, a menſura, non
                     •
                   menſe dictam, vt Donatus ad Terent. 
               de
                     •
                  ea
                     •
                  e,
            
            
               
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Xenoph, paediae l. 8. Quid opes opibꝰ aggeritis? non vultis cogitare, quam parua vobis ſint corpora? nonne furor &amp; vltimꝰ mentiam error eſt, cum tam exiguum capias, cupere multum? licet cenſus augeatis, fines promoveatis, nunquam tamen corpora veſtra laxabitis. Senec. ad Helv c. 10. heape he neuer ſo much vp, he can for himſelfe, for his owne perſon haue no more then one mans ordinary allowance: 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Epiclet. enchir. c. 61. &amp; Clem. Al. pae dag. l. 3. c. 7. Millia frumenti tua triuerit area centum; Non tuus hoc capiet venter plus quàm meus. Horat. ſerm. lib. 1. ſat: 1. Quid proſunt multa cubicula? in vnoiac
                        •
                     tis. Non eſt veſtrum, vbicun
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      non eſtis. Sen. epiſt. 89. Legatur idem epiſt. 61. Though he threſh a thouſand quarters of corne, though he haue thouſands of fat oxen and fed beaſts in his ſtalls and paſtures, and ten thouſands of ſheepe in his folds and his fields, yet can his belly hold no more then an other mans may: the reſt of it goeth to others, and is nothing to him.
            
               
                  Eccleſ. 5. 11. '
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  de Alexandro Xenocrates apud Laert. Et Pheraulas apud Xenophontem paediae lib. 8. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                
               Where there is much meate, there are many mouths; there are many eaters: ſaith Salomon; and where there is much wealth, there are there many Partakers: And what good hath the Owner by it, but the name and 
               
                  Cu. L
                        •
                     ntulus Augur, divitiarum maximum exemplum, quater millies H
                     •
                   
                  ſuum vidit: propriè dixi; nihil enim amplius quam vidit. Senec. de benef. lib. 2. cap. 27. 
               the ſight of it? Yea to ſpeake as the truth is, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Hieroni Pindarus Pyth. ode 1. Diſpenſatorē publicum eſſe ſe. Alex. Severus apud Lamprid.
                the rich man is but a Steward to prouide and 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Philippus Macedo renunciantibus iumentis pabulum defore ſi pro libi
                        ••
                      ſuo caſtra metarentur. Plut. apoph.
                take care for thoſe that appertaine to him and haue dependance vpon him: 
                  
                     •
                  vt ſi Reticulum panis venales inter o
                     •
                  uſto Forte vebas hu
                     ••
                  ro, nihilo plus accipias, quam Qui nil portaris. Horat. ſat. 1. as a beaſt or a Slaue that beareth provender and food for himſelfe and his fellowes, hauing but a ſingle ſhare of it onely himſelfe.
            
               If he haue more then thee and vſe it moderately, he hath no more himſelfe then thou haſt, vnleſſe it be that he taketh more Creſcentē ſequitur cura pecuniam: Maiorum
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   fames. Hor. carm. l. 3. ode 16. Diues à paupere nō diſtinguitur niſi ſolicitudiae ſola. Pauperes ditioribꝰ co plerumque latiores, quo animus corum in pauciora diſtringitur. Sen. ad Helv. c. 12. Intelligo me, non opes, ſed occupationes perdidiſſe. Ibid. 9. —miſera eſt, magni cuſtodia cenſus. Iuven. ſat. 14. care then thou takeſt. If he vſe it immoderately, with the rich Glutton in the Goſpell, Luk. 16. 19. faring euery day deliciouſly, (to omit that Cibi condimentū fames, potionis ſitis. Socrates apud Cic. de finib. l. 2. Deſiderijs iſta condiuntur. Idem Tuſcul. 5. Et Ibid. Confer cum iſtis (Anacharſt, cui pulpa
                     ••
                  ntum fames, Laconibus Perfis
                     •
                   quibus curſ
                     ••
                  , ſudore, fame, ſiti condiebantur epulae) ſudantes, ructantes, refertos epuli
                     •
                   ta
                     ••
                   opi
                     •
                  os bov
                     ••
                  , qui nunquam ſitientes bibunt, nunquam eſurientes comedunt; tū intelliges, qui voluptatem 
                     〈…〉
                  e ſequantur, eos minim
                     •
                   conſequi; iucunditatem
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   victus eſſe in deſiderio, non in ſati
                     •
                  tate. Epulis immenſis gloriantur, non delectantur. Sen. ad Helv. c. 11. he findeth the leſſe delight in it,) 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Tel
                        •
                     s de divit. &amp; virt. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Socrates apud Stob: c. 91. Levior 
                        •
                     eiunio mors est, cruditate diſſiliunt. Sence. de provid. c. 4. he doth himſelfe the more harme, Iſta ſi quis deſpicit, quid illi paupertas nocet? ſi quis concupiſcit, illi etiam paupertas prodeſt. Sen. ad Helv. c. 10. and it were better for him that he had leſſe: For that is verified of him that Salomon ſaith, 
                  Eccleſ. 5. 10. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Teles de divit.
                
               The poore labouring mans ſleepe is ſweete vnto him, whether he eate more or leſſe; but the rich mans ſaturity will not ſuffer him to rest: 
               vides vt pallidus omnis c
                     •
                  ua Deſurgat dubia? Quin corpus 
                     〈◊〉
                   Heſternis vitijs, ani
                     ••
                  i quo
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   pragranat vnâ, At 
                     •
                   affligit humi divina particulā 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  . After vbi citius cura
                     ••
                   ſ
                     •
                  pori Membra dedit, v
                     •
                  geius praſcripta admunia ſurgit. Horat. ſerm. l. 2. Hinc p
                     •
                  llor, &amp; g
                     •
                  na pondule, aculorum vlcera, tremul
                     •
                   man
                     ••
                  , furiales ſomni, &amp; inqui
                     〈…〉
                  . Sol
                     〈…〉
                  non vident, &amp; 
                     〈◊〉
                   di
                     •
                   vi
                     ••••
                  . Plin. hiſt. nat. lib. 15. cap. 22. it breaketh him of his ſleepe, it bereaueth him of his reſt, it impaireth his health, it is a meanes not to lengthen, but to ſhorten his life.
            Againe conſider with thy ſelfe, how many an one wanteth that that thou haſt, and yet deſerueth as well at Gods hands as thou doſt. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  
                     
                        〈…〉
                      apud Stob. c. 93. Thou lookeſt on thy rich neighbours to miſlike thine own eſtate,

and to murmur for that thou wanteſt: Looke rather on thy poore brethren, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plut. de tranquill. —maiori ſe pauperiorum Turba compares. —Hor. ſat. 1. Aſpice quanto m
                        •
                     
                     ior pars ſit pauperū. S
                        •
                     n. ad Helv. c. 12. Pauper fiam? inter plures 
                        ••
                     o. Idem epiſt. 24. the far greater number, and compare thine eſtate with a many of theirs, to be thankfull for what thou haſt.
            Yea I may well ſay; Looke ſometime euen on thy rich neighbour, that lieth grieued with the goute, not able to ſtand on his legs, or to ſtir him without much paine on his pallet; thou haſt health and he hath wealth; 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Euripid. Telepho.
                whether of the two, thinkeſt thou, is the greater bleſſing of God? Thou wouldſt thinke thy ſelfe happy, if thou hadſt his worldly wealth and abilitie; and 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Arrian. diſſert. l. 4. c. 9. he would thinke himſelfe happy, and that with much better reaſon too, if he had that health and abilitie of body that thou haſt.
            But to returne to the poorer ſort, liker thy ſelfe. When thou ſeeſt a rich man, ſaith one, caried in his chaire or on mens ſhoulders, haue an eye withall to them that cary him, and that run through thicke and thin by him: 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                When thou eyeſt Xerxes that mighty Monarke with his endleſſe army Velificatus Athos, epota
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   flumina Medo Prandente. Iuven. ſat. 14. Sic Eſai 37. 2
                     •
                  . diggingk 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plut. de tranq.
                downe hills, and drying vp deepes, building bridges ouer the ſea it ſelfe, and lincking ſhore to ſhore, Aſia to Europe, making the dry land nauigable, and the Ocean paſſable on foote: caſt thine eye withall downe on thoſe miſerable ſlaues, that dig downe mount Athos vnder the whip, and that are maimed and disfigured, their noſes and eares cut of, becauſe the bridge they made brake as the army paſſed ouer it: thou counteſt him happy; and 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Plut. ibid.
                they count

thee happy. As if he had ſaid, applying it to vs and our times: Thou heareſt of the King of Spaine, what millions of treaſure he hath euery third yeere from his Indies: and thou thinkeſt him an happy man. I ſay not to thee, though I might ſo ſay, conſider withall, how many mouthes he hath to feede, how many Followers, how many Fauourites, how many ſhips and gallies to ſet out, how many gariſons to keepe, how many Souldiers to pay, how many Intelligencers to maintaine, &amp;c. But, thinke withall vpon thoſe poore wretches that row in his Gallies, that tug at the oare end vnder the whip, or vnder worſe then it, hauing ſcarce a bit of good bread to put in their mouthes, or a whole rag almoſt to hang on their backes, enduring all the miſery there that can be imagined. Thou thinkeſt him happy that hath that that thou haſt not: and they thinke thee happy that haſt not that that they haue, and yet haſt that that they haue not.
            Or, (becauſe 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                ſuch exceſſiue great ones are not ſo much regarded, 
                  Stella terrā propi
                        •
                     n in occidente vel oriente locat
                        •
                      
                     
                        ••
                     iores apparent, quàm cùm ad coeli mediū elevat
                        •
                      fuerint. Ex Alh
                        ••
                     eni perſpect. l. 7. Author Oculi mor. c. 6. mirab. 13. the ſunne ſheweth not ſo great when hee is at his higheſt as he doth when hee is neerer the edge of the Horizon, and the Faulcon ſeemeth leſſe ſtill, the higher he ſoreth, when hee is once gone aboue that that our weake eie-ſight can well reach. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Ariſtot. rh
                        •
                     t. l. 2. 
                     •
                  . 12. thoſe that come neerer vs, and are neerer at hand with vs, are more in our eye, oftner Inviden
                     •
                  i ver
                  
                     •••
                   doct
                     •
                  m eſt à 
                     〈…〉
                   in
                     ••
                  en
                     ••
                   f
                     •
                  rt
                     ••
                  am alterius. Ci
                     •
                  . T
                     •
                  ſ
                     •••
                  . qu
                     •
                  ſt. l. 3. eyed, and conſequently more enuied of vs:) 
                  Vi
                        •
                     in
                        ••
                      divos cupiditat
                        •
                     m irritat. S
                        ••
                     . Ep. 7. —
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Hoſ
                        ••
                     d. oper. lib. 1. A rich neighbour or two not much aboue thine owne rancke, that dwell by thee, ſet thy teeth on edge,

and are a ſhrewd eye-ſore vnto thee, and make thee thinke thy ſelfe but in euill caſe, that thou art not as they are, that thou haſt not ſo much comming in yeerely as they haue, that thou canſt not fare as they fare and doe as they doe. But thou conſidereſt not withall for thoſe two or three rich, how many poore and needy ones are on euery ſide of thee, that come as far ſhort of thee as thou doeſt of them. Which if thou didſt, thou mighteſt iuſtly ſay, as the Pſalmiſt, 
                  Pſal. 147. 20. 
               The Lord hath not dealt ſo with euery Nation; ſo, The Lord hath not dealt ſo with euery one, no nor with many an one, as he hath done and doth with me. As the 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                
               Cynick, when he found a mouſe in his ſachell, ſaid, he ſaw well that he was not yet ſo poore, but that ſome were glad of his leauings: So many a poore hungry ſoule, yea many a deere childe and ſincere ſeruant of God, would be glad of thy leauings, and yet deſerueſt thou no more than any of them do.
            Laſtly, conſider thine owne vnworthines. Thou deſerueſt nothing at Gods hands but hunger and ſtripes. All that thou haſt from him thou haſt it of free gift. And therefore are we taught to pray, Math. 6. 12 D
                     •
                  , non, redde. Quia niſi Deo d
                     •
                  na
                     •••
                   noſter 
                     〈◊〉
                   eſt. Aug. hom. 14. 
               Giue vs our bread. If we deſerue not then ſo much as a bit of bread at Gods hands, can we not be content, when God giueth vs aboundantly both bread and meat to feede vs, and good clothing to couer vs, and conuenient houſing to harbor vs, &amp; friends &amp; fauour and credit and countenance in the world, ſo much of that that ſo many want, and ſo much more than we are worthy of; vnleſſe we may haue Jam. 4. 3. 
               to waſte on our 
               Colo
                     ••
                  . 3. 5. 
               inordinate and extrauagant luſts,
               
and to revell and not, as we ſee ſome others do?
            We would thinke that begger intolerably impudent and inſolent, that comming to our dores to aske an almes, when we haue beſtowed on him ſome broken bread and meat, or ſome ſory (caſt coate, yet, like thoſe importunate perſons the Pſalmiſt ſpeaketh of, that 
                  Pſal. 59 15. De talibus ex Callimach
                        •
                      Zenodotus, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                
               grudge and grumble if they be not ſatisfied, if they haue not their owne fill, and their owne will, he ſhould not be quiet and hold himſelf contented therewith, vnleſſe he might haue one of the beſt diſhes of meat from our bord, or one of▪ our owne ordinarie wearing ſuites giuen him. And yet is this the caſe of the greateſt number of vs. Quantum vis diues es, Dei mendicus es. Aug de verb. Dō
                  ▪ 4
                     •
                  . &amp; in 
                     〈…〉
                  
                  ▪ An 
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     〈…〉
                   Idem homi
                     •
                  
                  ▪ 14. We come all as Beggars to Gods mercy gate▪ and God giueth vs out 
                  
                     •
                  . Tim▪ 
                  
                     •
                  . 17. aboundance of many good things, life, libertie, health of bodie, ſtrength and abilitie of limmes, foode and rayment, &amp;c. a courteſie and competencie of each, as he ſeeth to be fitteſt for vs: and Imprude
                     •
                  ti
                     •
                   eſt (Imprude
                     •
                  tia etiā) vt á Deo divitias pet as: vt panē petas quotidianū imprudentia non eſt. aliud eſt enim vnde ſuperbias, aliud vnde viuas. Aug. in orat. dom. yet, forſooth, can we not be quiet, nor thinke our ſelues well, vnleſſe we may ſare as deliciouſly as Dives did, or go in ſilks and 
                  •
               attins as ſuch and ſuch do.
            
               
                  
                     ••
                  Iaco
                     •
                  
                as good a man as any of vs, was far otherwiſe minded: he prayeth to God but for 
                  Geneſ. 28. 20. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  in Gen. hom. 14. 
               bread to eat, and rayment to cloth him: that if he might haue onely, he thought himſelfe well apa
                  ••
               . And what made him ſo ſparing 
                  〈◊〉
                his petition, but the ſight and conſideration of his owne vnworthineſſe: Gen. 32. 10. Inferior ſ
                     ••
                   quibuſ
                  
                     •••
                   benefic
                     ••
                   
                  
                     〈…〉
                  . 
               I am leſſe, 
               
                  •
               aith he, than the leaſt of all thy mercies. He knew he deſerued nothing, and was therefore content with any thing: he would aske no great matter, but would hold himſelfe ſatisfied▪ with whatſoeuer

it ſhould pleaſe God in mercy and goodnes to allot and allow him. In a word; Beggers, as I ſaid before, we are; no better then beggers the very beſt of vs: And Beggers, we vſe to ſay, muſt be no chooſers, they muſt not be their owne caruers. Reſt we muſt therefore contented with what God ſhall ſee good to aſſigne vs, be it more or leſſe, being more by much than euer we either do or can deſerue any of vs.
            But is Contentment ſo neceſſarie, and ſo pretious a Iewell? let vs in the next place then conſider by what meanes may we compaſſe it: And ſo paſſe we the ſecond point before propounded, to wit, that Godlineſſe onely can procure and produce true Contentment.
            
            
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Plus. de auar.
                A man would thinke that as meat aſſwageth hunger, and drinke allayeth thirſt; ſo riches ſhould ſatisfie, and by ſatiſfying ſlake and quench the immoderate and inordinate deſire of wealth. But it 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                is herein far otherwiſe, as Salomon himſelfe, and it may well be, vpon his owne experience informeth vs: 
                  Eccleſ. 
                  
                     •
                  . 10. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Plut. ibid.
                
               He that loueth money, ſaith Salomon, ſhall neuer haue enough of it. 
               Creſcit am
                     •
                  r nū
                  
                  
                     ••
                  , quantum ipſa pecunia creſcit. Et minus hane optat, qui non habet. Iuvē. ſat. 14. Auri nā
                  
                     •
                  
                  ▪ fames part
                     •
                   ſit maior ab auro. Prudent▪ pſychom. Et creſcit cupido cenſu creſcente cupido. Autor Oculim
                     •
                  r. c. 12. 
               The deſire of more groweth, as a mans riches ariſe. 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Teles de collat. div. &amp; virt. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Chryſost. in 1. Cor. hom. 14. Sic quibus intumuit ſuffuſa venter ab v
                        •
                     da, Qu
                        •
                      plus ſint potae, plus ſitiuntur aquae. Ovid. faſt. l. 1. Habes aurum, habes argentum; &amp; concupiſcis aurū, concupiſcis argentum: Et plenus es, &amp; ſitis. morbus eſt, non opulentia. Sunt homines in morb
                        •
                     : bumore pleni ſunt, &amp; ſemper ſ
                        ••
                     iunt. Quomod
                        •
                      
                     
                        •
                     actas opulentiam, qui habes hydropē conſcienti
                        ••
                     ? Aug. de verb. Dom. 5. As the Dropſie-man, the

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
more he drinketh, the dryer he is, and 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Ariſtoph. Pluto.
                thoſe that are ſicke of the greedy diſeaſe, canina appetentia, the doggiſh deſire, as they terme it, the more they deuoure, the more hungry they are▪ ſo the richer men grow, the more commonly they deſire, more greedy do they wax ordinarily of the world, then they were when they had leſſe of it. As  
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                when the fruits of their ground come in aboundantly on them, they make their barnes bigger, and their ſtorehouſes larger to hold more: ſo withall they beate out the walls of their hearts to couer more, and 
                  
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈…〉
                  . 30, 15, 16. 
               inl
                     •
                  rge their deſire as the Grave, or as Hell; that neuer cryeth, Ho, becauſe it never hath enough; 
               V
                     ••
                   
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   de 
                     〈◊〉
                   flu
                     •
                  ina terra; Sic 
                     •
                  n
                     ••
                  es anim
                     •
                  s 
                     〈…〉
                   
                  
                     ••
                  cipit ille; ne
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   Ex
                     •
                  g
                     •••
                   populo eſt, 
                     〈…〉
                   
                  
                     •
                  icedere ſentit. O
                  
                     •
                  id me
                     •
                  l. 4. is neuer the fuller for all the ſoules that deſcend downe into it, no more than the ſe
                  ••
               is for all the riuers that empty themſelues into it.
            
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  
                     
                        〈…〉
                      de 
                        〈…〉
                      indulg
                        •••
                      ſibi d
                        •••
                      
                     
                        〈…〉
                     , Nec 
                        〈…〉
                      pellit, niſi 
                        〈…〉
                     
                     ▪ Fugerit 
                        〈…〉
                     , &amp; 
                        〈…〉
                      
                     
                        •
                     orpore 
                        〈…〉
                     . carm. 2. 2. As thoſe diſeaſed perſons therefore before mentioned, haue neede rather to be emptied, to haue ſomewhat purged out, than to haue more powred in
                  •
                the one muſt be 
                  •
               id of the watry humor that poſſeſſeth his bodie, ere his drought can be ſlaked, the other of the ſalt and ſlimie ſubſtance that peſtereth his ſtomack, ere his rauenous appetitie can be ſtayed: So the Couetous perſon, that is ſo greedy of the world, and ſo immoderate and inſatiable in his deſires, hath

               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Plato apud St
                        •
                     b. c. 10. Et Socrates vt Laertiꝰ l. 2. Cleanthes, vt S
                        •
                     ob. c. 92. interrogatus 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                      S
                        •
                     d &amp; Epicur
                        ••
                     ,  
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Ibid. cap. 17. Si vu Pytho
                        •
                     lea diuitem facere, non pecuniae adijciendū, ſed cupiditatione detrahendum. Ex Epicure Sen. ep 21 Scitè Arriā. Epict. diſſert. lib. 3. cap. 9. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                      Et verè Clemens paedag. l. 2. 3. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                      Et Democr. apud Stob. c. 95. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                not neede of more to be heaped vpon him, but hath neede rather of ſome thing to be taken away from him: he muſt haue that diſcontent humor of his purged out of his head, that couetous affection of his wrought out of his heart, that is the cauſe of this his greedy and inſatiable deſire, ere he can attaine to any true Contentment of minde, ere he can come to haue his fill. Till then all this worlds wealth will be but as 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Chryſoſt. in Rom. hom. 13. Scitum est Scytharum legali, Quanto plus biberint, tanto magis ſitire Parthos. Plin. hiſt. nat. lib. 15. cap. 22. Viſe Simocatum epiſt. 52 wine and ſtrong drinke to the drunkard, that further inflameth him, and increaſeth his drought; 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Euſeb. apud Stob. c. 10. Cupidita
                        •
                      auari v
                        •
                      ignis eſt, cui divitiae ſunt vt lignae, qu
                        •
                     bus iniectis is vehementius exardeſcit. Vorag
                        •
                     de temp. 134. Eo maior
                        •
                      cupimus quo maiora venerunt: multo
                        •
                      concitation eſt auaritia in magnarum 
                        •
                     p
                        •••
                      congeſtu collocata; vt flamme infinito acrior viseſt, quo ex maiore incendio emicuit. S
                        •
                     . de benef. 
                        ••
                     . c. 27. as oyle or fewell to the fire, that doth not quench or ſmother it, but feede it, and make it burne fiercer than at the firſt.
            If no wealth then can ſtay, or ſatisfie the minde of man, what muſt? or what may? The Apoſtle pointeth vs to it, as here, ſo els where. Heb. 139. 
               It is good, ſaith he, to haue the heart ſtayed, or ballaced as it were, with grace, and not with meats, nor with money neither. That that muſt keepe the ſhip ſtiffe and ſteedy on the Sea, muſt not be leauers &amp; ſhores without it, but 
                  Nam
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      labant curvae iuſto fi
                        •
                     e pondere naves, Per
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      mare inſtabiles nimia l
                        •
                     
                     uitate 
                        •
                     eruntur. Ovid. met. l. 2. weight and ballaſt within it. So

that that muſt ſtay a mans raging and ranging deſires, muſt not be the outward ſupporting of his worldly eſtate, but the inward ballacing and ſetling of the heart and minde; that which Gods grace alone can do, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh there, which is the ſame in effect with Godlineſſe, of which he intreateth here. And in regard hereof it is that the Pſalmiſt ſaith, that Pſal. 37. 16. 
               A ſmall matter to the godly, the man that feareth God, is much better than the greatest wealth and riches, that the vngodly and the mighty hath or can haue. And Salomon, that 
                  Prov. 15. 16. 
               a litle with the feare of God is much better than great treaſures and trouble or vexation therewith.
            
            In which words alſo Salomon cloſely and couertly rendreth a reaſon of that which his Father Dauid had before him ſaid, why A litle to the godly man ſhould be of more worth, euen the ſame in effect that the Apoſtle here hath, becauſe there is no trouble or vexation of minde, but quietneſſe and ſweet contentment withall. According to that which the ſame Salomon els-where ſaith; 
                  Pro. 10 22. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Aeſchyl. Theb.
                
               It is Gods bleſsing that maketh a man truly rich, and he addeth no ſorrow with it. 
               1. Chr. 29. 11, 12 Without Gods permiſſion and prouidence no man can haue riches: For Deut. 8. 18. it is God that giueth euery man power to get wealth. But Et 
                     ••
                  atus dat, &amp; propitiꝰ negat. Aug. de diuerſ. 20. 
                     •
                   Pſal. 106. 15. God giueth a man money many times in his wrath: as in the wildernes he gaue the Iſraelites meat in his anger: And ſo the curſe of God many times maketh a man rich: But thoſe riches are but accurſed riches; 
                  Multis paraſſe divitias non fini
                        •
                      miſeriarū ſuit, ſed mutatio. S
                        •
                     n. ep. 17. Dū maiore tormē
                     to pecunia poſſidet
                        •
                     r, quàm queritur. 
                        •
                     a
                        •
                      epiſt. 115. Nemo ſolicito bono fruitur. Idē. ep. 14. Ta
                        •
                     lis parta mal
                        •
                      
                     
                        〈…〉
                     tu
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     . Miſera eſt 
                        〈…〉
                     . J
                        •
                     v
                        •
                     n. ſa
                        •
                     . 
                  
                     ••
                  . there is a curſe and car
                  •
               ing care, euer accompanying ſuch wealth. But where Gods bleſſing maketh a man rich, there he giueth euer

withall contentment, that cauſeth comfort and quiet of minde, and maketh a man reſt ſatiſfied and well apaid with that portion of wealth, be it more or leſſe, that God hath aſſigned him.
            Neither is this a common courteſie that God caſteth on all ſorts indifferently; but a peculiar bleſſing that he beſtoweth on thoſe onely that loue and feare him, and that are his beloued ones. Pſal. 128 1, 2. 
               Bleſſed is euery one, ſaith the Pſalmiſt, that feareth God, and that walketh in his wayes: For thou, that ſo doeſt, ſhalt eat of the 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Sept. quod vetus interpr. Labores fr
                        •
                     ctuum tuorū, malè reddidit: Cùm 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                      illic non fructum ſignificet, ſed partem corporis eam, dè qua Ariſtot. de part animal. lib. 1. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Id quod Auguſtinū, Proſperū
                     que Latinos latuiſſe parum fuerit; Origenem Gratum in Rō. c. 1. fe
                        ••
                     lliſſe mirum.
                
               labours of thine hands: happy ſhalt thou be, and it ſhall go well with thee. But, c 
               Vnleſſe the Lord build the houſe, they labour but in vaine that build it: It is vaine for you, as worldly men are wont to do, to riſe vp early in the morning, and ſit vp late at euening, and toile and moile, like an horſe, all the day long, and to eat the bread of ſorrow and care; for, it is God that giueth his beloued rest: It is he alone that can giue ſweet comfort, and quietnes, and contentment of minde, and this grace he vouchſafeth to none but his beloued, to the Godly that loue him, and are beloued of him.
            It is Godlineſſe then alone, that can cauſe true Contentment; and that can cauſe true Contentment alone.
            Godlineſſe alone is able to cauſe true Contentment: becauſe Godlineſſe alone bringeth man home vnto God, out of whom true Contentment can not be had. For the ſoule of man, as 
                  Geneſ. 1. 26, 27. &amp; 9. 5. 1. Cor. 11. 7. Epheſ. 4. 24. it beareth the image of God; ſo 
                  Pſal. 17. 15. Omnis copia qu
                     •
                   non est Deꝰ meus, mihi eſt egeſtas. Aug. ſoliloq c. 13. Dei imaginem animam niſi Deus nil implet. Viſe Aug. de civit. lib. 12. cap. 1. nothing can ſatisfie it, but he whoſe image it beareth.

               
                  
                     
                        •
                     eciſti nos ad te
                        •
                      &amp; inquietum est cor noſtrum, donec requieſcat in t
                        •
                     . Aug. confeſſ. l. 1. c. 1 Humana quippe anima ad illum est ſuſpenſa, à quo formata. Et quia ad Deum ſolum appetendum facta est, omne autem quod infra appetit minus eſt, iure ei non ſufficit, quod Deus non est. Greg. mor. l. 26. cap. 36. 
               Our Soule, ſaith Auguſtine well, was created as by God, ſo for God, and is therefore neuer quiet till it reſt in God. As Hinc eſt quod huc illuc diſpergitur, &amp; ab vnaqua
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   re faſtidio impellente re
                  
                     ••
                   vetur. Delecta
                  
                     •••
                  is ſcil. auda qua
                     •••
                   quo pa
                     •
                  ſet; 
                     〈◊〉
                   ver
                     •
                   quem ſuffiti
                     ••
                  ter habere poterat a
                     ••
                  ſit. Vnde 
                     〈◊〉
                   per multa du
                  
                     ••
                  ur, vt quia qualitate 
                     〈◊〉
                   non p
                     •
                  
                  
                  
                     ••
                  ſt, ſaltem varie
                  
                     •
                  ate ſa
                     •••
                  tur. Greg. Ibid. man fell at firſt into this reſtleſnes by falling away from God; ſo Hoc adepto beata eſt, quo amiſſo miſer
                     •
                  eſt. Aug. ciuit. l. 12. c. 1. he can not be recouered of it, but by returning to him againe. It is with mans ſoule in this regard, as it was with Noahs Dove in the Deluge. As Geneſ. 8. 9. the Dove, after ſhe left the Arke, found no reſt for the ſoale of her foote in the wide world, being then all a-floate, till ſhee betooke her againe thither, from whence before ſhee came forth: So neither can man, fallen from God, finde any ſure reſt for the foote of his ſoule in the whole world beſide, till he come backe to him againe Eccleſ. 12. 7. Geneſ. 2. 7. from whom it came at the firſt. But it is Godlineſſe alone, that bringeth man home vnto God; that tyeth and knitteth the ſoule faſt vnto God; whereof Hoc vin
                     •
                  ulo pietatis obſt
                     ••••
                  , Deo relig
                     •••
                   ſumu
                     •
                  , vnde &amp; ipſ
                     •
                   Relig
                     〈…〉
                  accepi
                     •
                  , 
                     〈…〉
                  . L
                     ••
                  ant. 
                     •••
                  . 28. Ad 
                     〈…〉
                  , &amp; 
                     •
                  i vni religantes a
                     •••••
                   noſtra▪ vnde Religio dicta 
                     〈◊〉
                  , omni superſtitio
                     ••
                   
                  
                     〈…〉
                  relig. cap. 55. Qu
                     •
                   taman a religendo, 
                     •
                  iue religendo D
                     •••
                  , qu
                     〈…〉
                  , dictā tradit Idem de civi
                     〈…〉
                  . Sed 
                     〈…〉
                  . 13. 
               Religion, ſay ſome, hath its name; that findeth reſt and repoſe for the whole man in God, which can no where elſe be found. That which Salomon, out of his owne experience, confirmeth vnto vs, who Eccleſ. 
                     •
                  . 
                     ••
                  , 11. hauing ranged abroad through all thoſe creatures and courſes, vnder the cope of heauen, wherein any hope of contentment ſeemed to ſhew forth it ſelfe, is in concluſion inforced to retire backe againe to God, Eccleſ. 
                     ••
                  . 1. directing them all to him that deſire to finde true contentment, and pointing them the way to him Eccleſ. 
                     •
                  2. 
                     ••
                  . by the feare of

him; that is, by Godlineſſe leading them vnto God, that they may with him and in him finde true Contentment, as being no where elſe to be had.
            Godlineſſe then, you ſee, is alone able to cauſe true Contentment. But is Godlineſſe, may ſome ſay, able to cauſe true Contentment alone, without helpe and aide of theſe outward things? Can it make a man content as well in want as in wealth? whither he haue worldly wealth or no?
            Yea vndoubtedly. That that is ſufficient of it ſelfe alone to make a man truly happy, is of it ſelfe alone ſufficient to giue true contentment, though a man haue nothing elſe but it. For 
                  Ariſtot. ethic. l. 1. c. 7. Sed &amp; Aug. confeſſ. l. 10. c. 20. &amp; Epiſt. 121. c. 4, 5. &amp; de lib arb. l. 1. c. 18. &amp; de Triuit. l. 13. c. 3, 4, 5, 7. &amp; in Pſal. 118. conc. 1. Happineſſe is euery mans vtmoſt ayme: and he that hath attained to it, can not but reſt content with it: 
                  Nemo beatus qui eo quod amat (quod avet, quod habet) non fruitur. Aug. de civit. l. 8. c. 9. Fruimur autem eis in quibꝰ voluntas delectata conquieſcit. Aug. de trinit. l. 10. c. 10. &amp; Aquin. ſū. p. 1
                     a.
                   2
                     a. q. 11. a. 3. Vnde Sen. Nemo fruitur bono ſolicito.
                he were not happy, if he found no content in his happineſſe. Whatſoeuer thing therefore is able to bring vs vnto happines, can not but bring to vs Contentment togither with it. But Godlineſſe is of it ſelfe alone able to make a man happy. That which 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Plutarch. Ad viuendū beatè virtus ſola ſufficit. Sē. de vit beat. cap. 16. Beata vita virtus ſatisfacit. Idē epiſt. 87. Virtus ad explendam beatā vitam ſola ſatis effica
                        •
                     . Ibid. 45. the Heathen men ſaid of their morall Virtue, a meere ſhadow of it, is indeed true of true Godlineſſe, it is ſufficient of it ſelfe to make him that hath it truly happy, though he haue nothing elſe but it. For Apoc. 20. 6. Inde beatus, vnde bonus. Aug. epiſt▪ 
                  
                     •
                  2
                     •
                  . Impius &amp; f
                     •
                  li
                     •
                   ſic ſimul eſſe cupit, vt nolit pius eſſe, velit tamen eſſe beatus; Quod natura negat, nec recepit ratio. d
                     •
                   Macrino apud Capitolinum. holineſſe and happineſſe, Godlineſſe and bleſſednes are inſeparably lincked togither, and can not be ſeuered the one from the other. 
                  Pſal. 1. 1. &amp; 112. 1. &amp; 119. 1. &amp; 128. 1. Etſi videantur ignatis miſeri, tamen non poſſunt aliud eſſe quàm beati. Saluian. de prouid. l. 1. 
                     •
                  . 2. Euery holy man is an happy man, euery godly man is in a bleſſed eſtate, be he rich or poore, be he in wealth or in want,

whatſoeuer his worldly eſtate outwardly be. So that of true Godlines, we may well ſay, as he ſometime of diuine knowledge, the ground of it, it is not earthly gaine, nor worldly wealth, nor gold, nor ſiluer, nor corruptible treaſures, but Die t
                     •
                  iſta neſcire, ſed noſſe quomodo etiam ſine iſtis hom
                     •
                   poſſit eſſe beatus. Aug opiſt. 56. 
               it is that that that can make a man happy without all theſe. And the Godly man, though he haue not theſe or the like, yet hath he that that can make him truly happy without them, and ſo conſequently that can giue him contentment in the want of them. And certainely if God be 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Geneſ. 17. 1. 
               El-ſhaddai, All-ſufficient; then 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   2. Cor. 12. 9. 
               Gods grace and Godlineſſe that bringeth a man home vnto God, and giueth him intereſt in God, can not but be likewiſe of it ſelfe ſufficient to make a man truly happy, and to procure vnto him true Contentment.
            But will we ſee yet more particularly by what meanes Godlineſſe worketh this Contentment in thoſe that are truly▪ poſſeſſed of it?
            Firſt, Act. 15. 9. &amp; 26. 18. it purgeth the heart of him that hath it:e 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Socrates, ex Ariſtonymi 
                        ••
                     marijs Stob. c. 92. Sin
                     
                        •
                     erum eſt niſi vas, quodcun
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      infundis, aceſcit▪ Horat. epiſt. 2. lib. 1. and ſo bringeth with it a ſanctified vſe of the creature. For vnleſſe the veſſell be ſeaſoned, it tainteth all that commeth into it; and how can ought taſte well then, that commeth out of it? So 
                  Hagg. 2. 14▪ 15. V
                        •
                     ſe f
                        ••
                     ido, vel oleum, vel vinum facilè corrumpitur. Ambr. ep. 3. vnleſſe a mans heart be ſeaſoned with grace, it pollu
                  •
               eth and de
                  •
               ileth all that a man dealeth with. Tit. 1. 15. 
               Vnto the pure, ſaith the Apoſtle, all things are pure, but vnto the impure and the vnbelee
                     •
                  ing all things are impure, becauſe their mindes and conſciences are defiled. Since the worldly man then doth but moile and ſoile and defile himſelfe with his wealth, doth but taint and pollute it, and himſelfe in the vſe of it, no meruaile,

if he finde no comfort or contentment at all in it.
            
               Nothing is pure to them, ſaith the Apoſtle, becauſe their heart is impure. 
               
                  Quid relliquiest quin habeat, quae quidem in homine dicuntur bona? Parentes, patriam incolumem, amices, genus, cognatos, diuitias? Atqui haec perinde ſunt, v
                        •
                     i illius animus, qui ea poſſidet. Qui vti ſcit, ei bona, illi qui non vtitur rectè, mala. Terent▪ heautont. 1. 2. Malo nihil prodeſt, quia prauo vſu corrumpit, quicquid ad illū pervenit. quemadmodum ſtomachꝰ morbo vit
                        •
                     atus &amp; colligens bilē, quoſcun
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      accepit, cibos mutat, &amp; omne alimentum in cauſam doloris trahit: ita animus caecus, quicquid illi commiſeris, id 
                        •
                     nus ſuum &amp; pernictem, &amp; occaſionē miſeria facit. Senec. de benef. l. 5. c. 12. Ideò nihil poteſt ad malos pervenire, quod proſit; imò nihil quod non n
                        •
                     ceat. quaecunque enī illis contigerūt, in naturam ſuam vertunt; &amp; 
                        •••
                     ra ſpecioſa profutura
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                     , ſi mellori darentur, illis peſtiferaſunt. Ibid.
                As a foule ſtomacke, ſtuffed with Choler, turneth all into Choler, euen the fineſt and daintieſt meats ſooneſt of any, by meanes whereof no good nouriſhment can accrew to the bodie by them, nor it grow to any good plight and health: So a foule heart turneth all into ſpirituall Choler, a bitter humor and vnſauoury, that impaireth and hindreth the health and welfare of the ſoule as much, yea much more than that materiall choler doth the health and welfare of the bodie.
            Whereas Godlineſſe ſanctifying and cleanſing the heart, and purging out that corruption that before tainted and polluted it, and ſo made all vncomfortable, becauſe noyſome and hurtfull, vnto vs, reſtoreth vnto vs 1. Cor. 7. 14. 1. Tim. 4 4. a pure and ſanctified vſe of the creature, and enableth vs to ſuck ſpirituall nouriſhment and wholeſome iuyce euen out of temporall bleſſings; which the ſoule beginneth now to finde ſweet comfort and true contentment in, becauſe it vſeth them as it ought.
            Secondly, it quieteth the Conſcience; which in the wicked, in the worldly man is euer vnquiet; and no true Contentment can be till it be quieted.
            
               Job. 15. 20. 
               The wicked man is continually like a woman in trauaile, ſaith Eliphaz. 
               
                  Etiamſi poenar
                        •
                      ad tempꝰ immunes videātur &amp; exortes reatꝰ, grauiores t
                        •
                     mē intra ſe poenas luunt, &amp; ſibirei ſun
                        •
                     , qui alijs non videntur, at
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      in ſegra
                        •
                     iorē conſci
                        •
                     tiae ſententiā, cū de aliorū peccatis iudicāt. Ambr. de bono mort. c. 7. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Pl. de
                        •
                     r
                        •
                     .
                His guilty Conſcience is

euer and anon inwardly griping him, and with priuy pangs and throwes pinching and twiching him there, 
                  Prov. 18. 14▪ 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Plut. ibid.
                where paines are moſt vnſupportable, and where Prov. 14. 10. none feeleth or 1. Cor. 2. 11. ſeeth ſaue himſelfe. And Eſai. 57. 20. 
               the wicked mans ſoule, as the Prophet compareth it, is as a raging Sea, full of ſoile and filth, that is neuer at reſt, whoſe waters caſt vp mire and dirt. 
               Eſai. 48. 22. &amp; 57. 21. 
               Vnto the wicked therefore, ſaith the Spirit of God, there is no peace. 
               
                  D. Hall of Tranquill. §▪ 4. 
               A ſeeming truce they may haue, true tranquillitie they cannot haue: 
               
                  Contra quam Sē. epiſt. 105. Tutum aliqua res in mala conſcientia praeſtat, nulla ſecurum. n
                        •
                     
                     cens habuit aliquā
                     do latendi fortunā, n
                        ••
                     quam 
                        ••
                     duciam. Verum iſtud qu
                        ••
                     d homines; ex adu
                        •
                     rſo qu
                        ••
                     d Deum. Scelus quis tutum, 
                        ••
                     llus ſecurū tulit, P. Syr.
                
               Secure they may ſeeme; but they can neuer be ſafe. If at ſome time they ſeem to haue reſt, and to be at eaſe; it is but as with the Sea, that ſeemeth ſtill ſometime, but indeede neuer ſtandeth ſtill, but is euer riſing or falling, ebbing or flowing, inceſſantly rolling to and fro from ſhore to ſhore: It is as with the Sea, 
                  Noli huic tranquillitati confidere. m
                        •
                     m
                        ••
                     to temporis m
                        •••
                      
                     
                        ••••
                     titur; &amp; 
                        ••
                     d
                        •
                     m die vbi luſerunt navigia, ſorbentur▪ Sen. epiſt. 4. that ſeemeth calme and ſmooth ſometime, but vpon euery breath of ayre or blaſt of winde, is ready to riſe and to rage, yea vpon ſome ſodaine guſt ſometime ſwelleth ſo, that ſhips are there ſwallowed vp ſodainely, where they lay becalmed but a litle before. Their ſeeming tranquillitie is but as the health of a feverous perſon when he is out of his fit, or the lightſomnes of a Lunatick that hath his lucida intervalla, and talketh by times as a man well in his wits.
            Now what Contentment can there be in ought, while the minde is thus affected, while the Conſcience is vnquieted? 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Plut. de tranquill.
                So long as a man is heart-ſick, he can haue no joy of ought, finde no relliſh in

ought, be it neuer ſo pleaſant and delightfull otherwiſe, be it neuer ſo acceptable to him at other times; his wonted companie is then but tedious &amp; troubleſome to him, his bed hard and vneaſie, his chamber too cloſe, his vſuall fare, yea or fare more dainty than vſuall, is diſtaſtfull, he findeth no good taſte in ought that he taketh: but 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plut. 
                        •
                      valeat poſſeſſor oportet, Qui comp
                        •
                     rtatis rebus benè cogitat vti. Horat. epiſt. 2. lib 1. Sanis ſuavior eſt panis, quàm pulpamentū aegrtis. Aug. de verb. Dom. 4. come health once, and that ſweetneth all againe; and then liketh he his company well againe, and can endure his bed well, and can feede ſauourly on a dry peece of courſe bread, that loathed his panada of fine manchet before. 
                  Qui dolet, aut metuit, iuvat illum ſic domus, aut res, Vt lippum pictae tabulae, fomēta podagram, Auriculas cithar
                        •
                      collecta ſorde dolentes. Horat. ep. 2. lib. 1. Nihil est miſerius quàm animus hominis cō
                     ſciꝰ. Plaut. Moſtell. 3. 1. Nec 
                        •
                     iculigrauiu
                        •
                      gemu
                        ••
                     unt aera iuvenci; Nec magis auratis pen
                        •
                     ens laquearibꝰ enſis Purpureas ſubter ceruices terruit.- Perſ. ſat. 3. Alludit ad Damoclis hiſtoriā, 
                        •
                     ui ea ratione Di
                        •
                     
                     
                     
                        •
                     yſius confirmauit, Nihil eſſe ei beatum, cui ſemper aliquis terror impendat. Ci
                        •
                      Tuſ
                        •
                     ul. l. 5. Perpe
                        •
                     ua anxietas, nec menſae tempore ceſſat, 
                        •
                     aucibus, vt morbo, ſiccis, inter
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      molares Difficili ereſcente cibo: ſed vina miſell
                        ••
                      Expuit: Albani veteris pretioſa ſenectꝰ Diſpl
                        ••
                     et▪-luvenal. ſat. 13. In like manner here: So long as a man is ſoule-ſick, he can haue no ioy of ought; be his outward eſtate what it will, it can no more miniſter ſound comfort vnto him, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plut. de virt &amp; vit.
                then hot cloths or blanckets can giue inward warmth to a dead corps, where naturall heate is vtterly extinct: He may force himſelfe ſometime to ſome ſeeming mirth; but, Prou. 14. 13. 
               Euen in laughter, ſaith Salomon, the heart is heauy. 
               Spem vultu ſimulat, premit altū cord
                     •
                  d▪ lorem Virg. Aen. Non benè mendaci riſus componitur ore▪ Nec benè ſolicitis ebria verba ſonant. Tibul. 3. 6. He may ſet a good face on it in outward ſhew to others, when his heart is full of heauineſſe and bitternes within him, and Calceus iſte non
                     •
                  e vobis concinnus ſatis videtur? ſed vbipedem mihi torqu
                     •
                  at ipſe ſolus perſentiſco. Aemylius apud Plut▪ de vxore. wringeth and pincheth him priuily there Prov. 14. 10. Imus praecipites, qui qu
                     •
                   ſibi dicat, &amp; intus Palleat infoelix, quod proxima neſciat vxor. Perſ. ſat. 3. where none is aware of it but himſelfe onely that ſuſtaineth and endureth it.
            
               And vndoubtedly, let a man ſtriue to ſmother it and ſmooth it ouer all that euer he can, let him ſtraine himſelfe to lightſomnes by all meanes that may be, let him want no outward matter of worldly either ſupport or delight, yet ſo long as he hath his guilty Conſcience racking and griping him within; though Sardonius hic riſ
                     ••
                   eſt: intus interī eos mordet conſcienti
                     •
                   vermis cauterijs omnibꝰ acrior. Caluin. inſtit. l. 1. c. 3. § 3. 
                     •
                  quos diri cō
                  ſciafacti Mens habet altonit
                     •
                  s, &amp; ſurdo verbere caedit O
                     •
                  cultum quatiente intus t
                     •
                  rtore flagellum. Juven. ſat. 3. he may geere and grin outwardly, while he is nipped and galled inwardly, he can take no more true ioy and delight, can finde no more ſound comfort and contentment in all his wealth and his treaſures, or in his delights &amp; his pleaſures, than 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Plut. de ſera vindict.
                a priſoner or condemned perſon, that ſitteth drinking and ſwilling, or playing at cards and tables in the laile, while the halter that he is to be hanged withall, hangeth ouer his head.
            But on the other ſide, to a quiet minde, to a good Conſcience, any thing is acceptable, yea and comfortable, as to him that is now in health. Let the minde be truly ſetled, let the Conſcience be once quieted; and the ſame man that before tooke no ioy at all in a large eſtate, found no relliſh at all in great varietie of dainties, walked melancholike to and fro in his gardens of pleaſure, had no comfort of friends and acquaintance, or of wife &amp; children, can now finde much ſweetneſſe in a farre poorer pitance, giue God hearty thanks for an homely repaſt, walke cheerefully abroad, liue comfortably at home, rejoyce with his wife, be merry with his friends, be comforted in his children. And this quietnes of minde and Conſcience can nothing procure but ſincere Godlineſſe. Which therefore, as it giueth true eaſe, and worketh ſound cure of thoſe

inward gripes and galls, not by benumming of a guilty Conſeience, nor 1. Tim. 4. 2. ſearing it, and making it ſtupid and ſenſeles, as for a time it is ſometime in the wicked; but by remouing the ground of them, Rom. 5. 1, 2, 3. by giuing a man aſſurance of the remiſſion of his ſinne, and of reconcilement vnto God, and ſo freeth a man from that inward diſquiet of minde, that baniſhed and kept out all true comfort and contentment before; ſo it bringeth with it a ſweet and comfortable vſe of all Gods good creatures; which a man now enioyeth Pſal. 41. 11. as fruits of Gods loue, as effects of Gods fauour, and Non tam don
                     •
                   quàm abs te datū: non tam munere, quàm abs te miſſum. Id 
                     ••
                  rè triumphat ſer
                     •
                  ò. Terent. Eunuch. in that regard more delightful than the things themſelues in themſelues are, as a preſent ſent a man from his Prince.
            Thirdly, it bringeth with it aſſurance of a greater benefit than all the world is able to counteruaile; to wit, of Gods fauour, and of his fatherly loue toward a man in Chriſt.
            It is the moſt heauy and the moſt vncomfortable thing that can be for a man to be forth of Gods fauour. 
                  Prov. 19 12. &amp; 20. 2. 
               The wrath of a King, ſaith Salomon, is as the roaring of a Lion; 
               Prov. 16. 14. 
               as the meſſengers of the Death. And what is the wrath of him then, 
                  Pſal. 18. 7. &amp; 104. 32. whoſe angry looke alone is able to ſhake heauen and earth? And if Eſter. 7. 6, 7. 
               Haman had litle ioy of all his wealth and his treaſures, when Aſſuerus frowned on him, when he was fall'n forth of his fauour; no maruaile if a man haue no ioy of ought, finde no comfort or contentment in ought, ſo long as God frowneth on him, ſo long as he is diſpleaſed with him, while the blacke clouds of Gods heauy Ioh. 3. 18, 36. wrath hang ouer his head?
            
               And on the other ſide, by Contrarlorum eadem eſt ratio. the law of Contraries, as Gods wrath is moſt hideous, ſo his loue and fauour is moſt gracious. As there is nothing more diſcomfortable than the one; ſo there is nothing more comfortable than the other. Pſal. 30. 5. 
               In thy fauour, ſaith Dauid, there is life. Yea, Pſal 63 3. 
               Thy louing kindneſſe, it is better than life. 
               Matth. 6. 25. 
               The bodie is better than rayment, and life of more worth than meat that maintaineth life, ſaith our Sauiour. And, Job. 2. 4. 
               All that a man hath, as the Deuill ſometime ſaid, will a man giue for his life. But Gods fauour and the aſſurance of it is a greater bleſſing than life it ſelfe, and much more then greater then any worldly wealth, that is not at all truly deſirable, but as an help and prop to this preſent life: Able therefore alone of it ſelfe to ſtay and ſupport a man, to comfort and cheere vp a man, to giue him true contentment, Quid hac Jobi miſeria miſerius? quid tamen hac infaelicitate felicius? perdiderat oīa qu
                     •
                   dederat Deus: ſed habuit ip sū qui oīa dederat, Deū. Aug. Data perdiderat, ſed non datorem. Idem Pſal. 66. Oīa perdiderat, &amp; ple
                  
                     •
                  u
                     •
                   erat. Id
                     •
                  m de diverſ. 12. to make him an happy man, in the want of all worldly wealth, though he haue nothing elſe but it.
            The old Gracians that had 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Euſtath. in Iliad. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Inde Arcades 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Plut. Caio Gr. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Tyr. Max. 
                        •
                     rat. 11. Fagus &amp; eſe
                        •
                     l
                        ••
                      arbores glā
                     diferae ideò vocatae 
                        •
                     reduntur, qu
                        •
                     d harum fructibus 
                        •
                     lim homines vixer
                        ••
                     t. Iſid
                        •
                     r. orig. l. 17. c. 9. fed altogither on acornes before, 
                  Ceres frumentae invenit, cùm anteà glande veſcerentur. Plin hiſt. 
                        •
                     at. l. 7. c. 56. after that bread-corne came in among them, 
                  Sic odium c
                        •
                     pi
                        •
                      glandi
                        •
                     . —Lucret. lib. 5. 
                        •
                      gratae poſt munus ariſtae Contingunt homines veteri
                        •
                      faſtidia quercus. I
                        ••
                     en. ſa
                        •
                     . 14. Inde 
                        •
                     ata Diverbia, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Satis quercus. Et, Poſt f
                        •
                     uges inventas glandibu
                        •
                      v
                        •
                     ſ
                        •
                     s. Legatur Plim. hiſt. l. 16. praefat. &amp;c. 5. made no reckning of their maſt any more, but kept it onely for their Swine: and 
                  Cori
                        •••
                      publica forma perc
                        •
                     ſſ
                        ••
                      apud Laced
                        •••
                     ni
                        ••
                      vſum numeratae pecuniae praeſtat. Sen. de 
                        ••
                     nef. l. 5. c. 15. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                      Nicol
                        •
                      D
                        •
                     maſc. Form
                        •
                     t
                        •
                     s 
                        •
                      corio orbes auro m
                        •
                     dico ſignauerunt. A
                        •
                     on
                        •
                     mus de reb. be
                        ••
                     . Hinc Hicron. ad Ru
                        •••
                     n. Aur
                        •••
                      montes pollicitus ne ſcorteum quidem 
                        〈…〉
                      profer
                        •
                     .
                leathren and De 
                     〈…〉
                   ferr
                     ••
                   videndus Plutarchus in Lycurg
                     •
                  . Legatur &amp; Pliv. hiſt. nat. l. 33. c. 3. &amp; Alex. ab▪ Alex. gen. dier. i. 
                     ••
                  
                  ▪ 15. iron coyne began to grow out of requeſt, after that gold and ſiluer once came in vſe.

So when a man hath once found the fauour &amp; loue of God in Chriſt, hath lighted once on it, and got aſſurance of it, he ceaſeth then to be greedy of this worldly traſh, that is in regard of it but as droſſe or peble ſtones to Gold and Diamonds, as maſte to the beſt bread-corne, yea rather of far leſſe worth and value to that, than either of theſe are to it.
            To which purpoſe Dauid ſaith, that whereas the worldly mans ſong is, Pſal. 4. 6. 
               who will ſhew vs any good, who will tell vs of any matter of profit? his wiſh or requeſt rather was, (with other the Godly) Lord lift thou the light of thy face, or thy fauour, on vs. For that Pſal. 4. 7. he had found more true ioy and contentment in the aſſurance of Gods loue, in the view of his louing countenance towards him, then they had or could reape comfort by their worldly commodities, their corne and their wine, wherein their wealth chiefly conſiſted, though they came in neuer ſo plentifully vpon them. Pſal. 4. 8. &amp; 27. 1. &amp; 3. 5. There was ſound reſt and aſſurance of ſafetie by the one, no ſecuritie in, or ſurety at all of the other.
            Laſtly; In that 
                  Socrates ab 
                        •
                     rchelao ad facultates ampli
                        •
                     res accerſitꝰ, 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , inquit, 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                      Arrian
                        •
                      in protrept. apud Stob. c. 95. it fitteth a mans minde to his meanes, while it aſſureth him both for the time preſent, that that eſtate, whatſoeuer it be, that he is then in, is the beſt and fitteſt for him; and for the time to come, that God will continually prouide for him, and neuer ſee or ſuffer him to want ought that he ſhall ſtand in neede of.
            
               Heb. 13. 5. 6. 
               Let your converſation, ſaith the Apoſtle, be without couetouſnes; and be Content with what you haue. For God hath promiſed that 
               Gen. 28. 15. Ioſh. 1. 5. 
               he will neuer leaue nor forſake you. So that you may boldly ſay, as the Pſalmiſt,

               Pſal. 27. 1. 
               The Lord is my protector, I neede feare nothing; ſo, Pſal. 23. 1. 
               The Lord is my Shepherd, I am ſure to lacke nothing. For Math. 6. 33. who ſo ſeeketh Gods Kingdome and the righteouſnes thereof, ſhall be ſure to haue all other things caſt vpon him, that may be for his good, he ſhall haue the one as an ouer-plus in to the other.
            It is a great ſtay of minde to a man for himſelfe or his ſonne, if the King ſhall ſay to him, as Dauid 
               2. Sam. 9. 7. to Mephiboſheth, or 2. Sam. 19. 38. to Barzillai the Gileadite, I will ſee that thou, or he ſhall neuer want, or, you ſhall neither of you euer want, if I may helpe it: What a ſtay of minde muſt it needs be to the Godly man then, when the King of heauen and earth ſhall ſay as much vnto him, Pſal. 146. 3, 4, 5, 6. he that is able to make his word good at will, and Hebr. 7. 25. liueth for euer to performe whatſoeuer he hath promiſed?
            Againe, the Godly may ſay it, and aſſure himſelfe of it, that whatſoeuer eſtate he is in, that eſtate for the preſent God ſeeth to be beſt and fitteſt for him. Quaremulta bonis viris aduerſa eveniunt? nihil accidero bono viro mali poteſt, non miſcentur contraria. Sen. de▪ provid. cap. 2. If he be poore, pouertie is beſt for him, or elſe he ſhould not ſo be: if he be ſick, ſicknes is beſt for him then, otherwiſe God would not ſuffer him to keepe his ſick-bed: if in priſon, reſtraint of liberty is then fitteſt for him, otherwiſe the priſon ſhould no more be able to hold him, then 
                  Act. 5. 23, 19. &amp; 12. 6, 7. it was to hold 
                  
                     •
                  eter, when the dores were faſt locked on him, and a guard of ſouldiers ſet to keepe him ſure. If riches were good for him, he ſhould be ſure to haue them: if health were good for him, he ſhould be ſure not to want it: if liberty, Pſal. 118. 5. God without delay would enlarge him and reſtore it. Pſal. 34. 9, 10. 
               For there ſhall nothing be wanting to thoſe that feare God: The Lions ſhall
               
               lacke and ſuffer hunger; but thoſe that ſeeke the Lord, ſhall want nothing that is good. 
               Pſal. 84. 11. 
               God their Sunne and Sheild will giue them grace and glory: and no good thing will he, 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Gen. 17. 1. &amp; 15. 1. 
               who is God all-ſufficient, denie vnto them, that walke vprightly before him.
            
            Marke the Apoſtles argument, that he vſeth for the proofe of this point: 
                  Rom. 8. 32. Qui miſit vn
                        •
                     ge
                        •
                     itum, immiſit ſpiritum, promiſit vultum: quid tandē tibi negaturus eſt? B
                        •
                     rn. de temp. Nihil vnquam ei negaſſe credendum eſt, quem ad vituli hortatur eſum. Hieron. ad Damaſ. de Luc. 15. 31. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ; Chryſoſt, in Rom. 
                        ••
                     . 15. 
               He that ſpared not his Sonne, but beſtowed him vpon vs, how can he but giue vs all things togither with him. And conceiue we the force of it by this compariſon: Suppoſe a man haue a frend, who hauing but one pretious Iewell of great price, that he maketh ſpeciall reckoning of, is content to part with it, and beſtow it on him for the ranſoming and redeeming of him out of captiuitie: he is content againe, when he is ſicke, to be at any charge with him for Phyſitian and Phyſick; and yet when he is in the fit of a burning Feuer, he will not by any meanes ſuffer him to haue a cup of cold water. May not ſuch a one in this caſe reaſon thus with himſelfe? Surely, if it were good and ſafe for me, yea were it not certainly dangerous and preiudiciall vnto me to drinke ſuch cold and raw drinke, this my friend that thinketh nothing too good or to deere for me that may do me good, that is content to be at all this cost and charge with me for Phyſick, would neuer denie me a cup of cold water that ſtandeth him in nothing. And conſequently, if he be wiſe, he will ſtriue againſt his owne deſire of it, and bend himſelfe patiently to endure the want and deniall of it, as done in wiſdome by his friend, and out of a tender regard of his good. And in like manner doth the Apoſtle teach the Godly man to reaſon: God, that hauing

but 1. Petr. 1. 18, 19. one pretious Iewell, to ſpeake of, 
                  Ioh. 3. 16. his owne Sonne and his onely Sonne, was content to beſtow him vpon me, to ſhed his heart-bloud for the ſauing1. Ioh. 4. 9. of my ſoule, if he ſaw health or wealth to be good for me, he would neuer denie it me, Hagg 2. 9. 1 Chr. 29. 11, 12. being no more than as a crum of bread or a drop of water with him. So that ſo long as he with ▪holdeth it, I know well that it is better for me to want it than to haue it; and therefore 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ; 
                     
                        •
                     uſus apud Arrianū diſſert l
                        ••
                      c. 1. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . l 2. c. 
                  
                     •
                  6. I will endeuor to keep my ſelfe quiet, and reſt content with the want of that, which I want for my good.
            This Godlineſſe perſwadeth euery Chriſtian vnto; and this Godlineſſe enabled the ſame Apoſtle to do: Philip 4. 11, 12, 13. 
               I haue learned, ſaith he, Magnus ille est qui fictilibus ſic vtitur quemadmodū argento▪ nec ille minor eſt qui ſic argē
                  to vtitur, quemadmodum fictilibus. infirmi animi est pati non poſſe divitias Sen. epiſt. 5. 
               to abound: and I haue learned to be in want. (Taught it a man muſt be, ere he can attaine to it; and it is a leſſon, that is not eaſily learned.) 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Georg. Piſid. de va
                        •
                     it. vitae.
                
               I haue learned to be hungry; and I haue learned to be full. (The one had neede to be learned as well as the other: and till a man haue learned it, he ſhall neuer be filled.) I haue learned in whatſoeuer eſtate I am, therwith to be contēt. I am able to do all things, yet Ille fortis eſt, qui non in ſe, ſed in Deo fortis eſt. Aug. in Pſal. 31. Bonus vir ſine Deo nemo eſt. an poteſt aliquis ſapra fortunā niſi ab illo adintus exurgere? ille dat conſilia magnifica &amp; erecta. In vnoquo
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   bonorum virorum, qui Deus, ineertum eſt, rabitat Deus. Animū excellentem, moderatū, oīa tanquam minor a tranſeuntem, quicquid timemus optamus
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ridentem coeleſtis potentia agitat. Non potest res tanta ſine adminiculo numinis ſtare. Sen. ep. 41. not of mine owne ſtrength, but through the power of Chriſt enabling me. And ſo paſſe we to the third Point, that at firſt we propounded, to wit hat true Contentment is an vndoubted argument of Godlines.
            A Contented minde argueth a religious heart;

and a diſcontented minde argueth an irreligious ſpirit. It is a ſigne that a man ſeeth not Gods goodnes, conſidereth not his owne vnworthineſſe, when he is euer murmuring and repining, miſliking and finding fault with his owne eſtate, and enuying thoſe that be aboue him. So that where diſcontent, ment is lodged in the heart, there is Godlineſſe excluded and ſhut out of dores. And hereby may a man know himſelfe to be truly religious, if he haue a minde contented euer with his preſent eſtate: not 
                  Feras, non culpes, quod vitari nō poteſt. P. Syrus. Optimum eſt pati quod emendare non poſſis. Sen. epiſt. 107. 
                        •
                      leve fi
                        •
                      patientia, Quicquid corrigere eſt nefas. Hor. carm. 1. 24. barely becauſe he can not mend the matter, or eaſe himſelfe by being diſcontent at it; (that is a kinde Affectio humana caninae aequanimitatis ſtupore firmata. Tertull. de patient. 
               of doggiſh ſtupiditie, rather than Chriſtian aequanimitie, as one well ſaith:) but becauſe 
                  Pſal. 39. 9. &amp; 119. 75. Deū quo authore cuncta proveniunt, ſine murmuratione ſequi. Sē. ep. 107. Quicquid inciderit, non tanquam malum aſpernabitur, &amp; in ſe caſu delatum, ſed quaſi (à Deo) delegatum ſibi (lubens amplexabitur.) Idē ep. 120. God hath placed him in it, and ſeeth it fitteſt and beſt for him, whoſe 
                  Matth. 26. 39. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Arrian. Epictet. diſſert. l. 2 c 17. Placeat homini, quicquid Deo placuit. Sen. ep. 74. ob hoc ipſum quod Deo placeat. Hieron. alicubi. Deus quod vult, qui vult is ſemper eſt foelix.
                holy will he deſireth to conforme his owne to, and 
                  Thymarides Pythagoricus, cum diſceden
                        ••
                      quidam quaſi bené precatus, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Dij tibi dent, inquit, quae
                        •
                     un
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      volueris; at ille, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Bona verba; inquit; Velim
                        •
                     go potius quaecun
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      Dij dederin
                        •
                     . Jamblych. de vita Pythag l. 
                        •
                     . c. 28. Magnus eſt animus, qui ſe Deo tradidit: puſillus &amp; degener, qui obluctatur, &amp; de ordine mundi male exiſtimat, &amp; Deos mavult emendare quàm ſe. Sen. epiſt. 107. not to writh and wreſt Gods to his; and therefore 
                  Iob. 2. 10. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Marc. leg. ſpir. 159. is willing to receiue as well euill as good from God, and 1 Sam. 3. 18. Si Deus bonus, Diabolus mal
                     ••
                  , nec à maloboni qui
                     •
                  q
                     •••
                  , nec à bono mali quicquā poteſt pr
                     •
                  ve
                     •
                  ire. Aug. to reſt content with whatſoeuer he doth; whom he knoweth Eſai. 39. 8. to do nothing but good, and Pſ. 119. 71, 67. to do all things for his good: that which is true piety, and a good note of ſinceritie whereſoeuer it is found.
            
               But here euery man will be ready to ſay, that he may ſeeme religious, that he is well content with his eſtate, and thanketh God for it with Iob 1 21. 
               Iob, whatſoeuer it be. Well; if it be ſo, as Saint Iames ſaith, Iam. 2. 18. 
               Shew me thy faith by thy works: ſo let vs Aequanimitas veſtra nota ſit. Philip. 4. 5. ſhew our Contentment by the effects, by the fruits of it.
            Of a Note or two of Contentment then a word or two, and ſo an end.
            One ſigne of Contentment then is, the vſe of lawfull meanes onely; When a man deſireth not, nor endeuoureth to better his eſtate by indirect and vnwarrantable courſes: when a man doth Pſal. 37. 1, 8. &amp; 73. 12, 13. 
               not fret to ſee wicked men riſe by bad meanes, nor is ſorry that he may not do as they do: much leſſe is moued to do wickedly, and to take ſuch courſes as he ſeeth wicked ones thriue withall, while himſelf and other godly, as himſelfe ſeemeth to obſerue, either decay, or elſe ſtand at a ſtay.
            
               Gen. 14. 23. 
               Abraham, when the King of Sodome offred him ſome part of his ſpoiles, refuſed to take ſo much as a ſhoe-latchet of him, that the King of Sodome might not ſay that he had made Abraham rich; that men might not ſay, that Abraham had bin made rich, not by Gods bleſſing, but by the Kings meanes; he might thanke the King of Sodome for his wealth. So a Godly man will not gaine, nor deſire to gaine ſo much as a ſhoe-ſtring or ſhoe-thred by prophaning Gods Sabbaths with N
                     •
                  hem. 13. 16. the Zidonian Merchants, by fraud or deceit, by oppreſſion and extortion, by biting vſury, the Deuils brokery, or by any other vnlawfull and indirect courſe; that the Deuill may not ſay, that, he hath made him rich; as

he ſaid ſometime to our Sauiour, Matth. 4. 9. 
               All this will I giue thee, if thou wilt fall downe and worſhip me. For Illas tibi divitias Diabolus dat, quas per furtum, quas per fraudem acquiris. Operis imperf. apud Chryſoſt. hom. 5. it is of the Deuils gift all that is gotten by ſuch meanes, that is compaſſed by ſuch courſes: and he hath neither a contented minde, nor a religious heart, that will ſeeke or take ought at the Diuels hand.
            As the Num. 9. 22, 23. 
               Iſraelites therefore trauailing through the wildernes towards the land of promiſe, (which, to haue gone the next way, had not bin a iourney of many dayes, yet were they many yeeres about) they were to go as God led them, as they ſaw the Cloud go before them, and not to take that way that ſeemed beſt or moſt compendious in their owne eyes. So muſt we 
                  Obſeruare vias Domini. Pſ 18. 22. Hebr. 11. 8. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Philo de migr. Abr. Idem &amp; Arrian. diſſer
                        •
                     . l. 1. c. 20. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Pythagor. apud Boeth. de conſol. lib. 1. proſ. 4 Laudat &amp; Plut. in conviv. &amp; Cit. de ſin l 4. &amp; Sē. de vita beata c. 15. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Cleanthes, &amp; Epictet. enchir. Duc me, parens celſi
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      dominator poli, Quocun
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      placuit: nulla parendi mora eſt: Aſſum impiger. fac nollo: comitabor gemens; Malus
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      patiar, quod bono licuit pati. Ducūt volentē fata, n
                        •
                     lentē trahūt. Sē. ep. 107. obſerue Gods wayes in our trading &amp; trafficking, in our walking towards wealth: we muſt keepe the way that God leadeth vs; go no other way than we can ſee him going in before vs, follow the line of his law, though it ſeeme to lead vs in and out, backward and forward, as if we were treading of a maze; and not take thoſe wayes, leauing the guidance of it, that ſeeme gainer and neerer in our owne eyes, and much more compendious than the other. Though we might compaſſe wealth with a word or two, with the bowe of a knee only the one way, whereas we muſt trauaile, and toile and moile much ere we come by it the other way: tho we might attaine to it within a day, or a weeke, the one way, whereas we are like to ſtay long, many yeeres, it may be, ere we come at it, the other way: yet this way muſt we keepe, and Math. 4. 10. refuſe all the world with our Sauiour, if it be offred vs to intice vs out of it.
            
               Otherwiſe as the Num. 14. 44, 45. 
               Iſraelites, when they went out of Gods precincts, they went withall out of Gods protection, and ſo fell before their foes, into whoſe hands they fell, forſaking Gods ſhelter and ſauegard. So 
                  Qui properat di
                     
                        •
                     eſ
                        ••
                     re. Pro. 28. 20, 22. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Menand. Nam dives qui fieri vult, Et cito vult fieri: ſed quae reuerenita legum, Quis metus aut pudor eſt vnquā properantis auari. Iuvē. ſat. 11. 
               thoſe that make more haſte then good ſpeede to be rich, that balke Gods paths, and ſtep aſide out of Gods way, to compaſſe wealth, ſhall vndoubtedly come to euill. For 
                  Qui volunt ditari. 1. Tim. 6. 9 Nō ait, qui ſunt, ſed qui fieri volunt. B
                        •
                     rn. de diuerſ. 36. Qui volunt, nō qui ſunt. cupiditates accuſat, nō facultates. Aug. hom. 13. &amp; de temp. 205. Qui augere opes ambit, vitare peccatū negligit, &amp; more aviū dum eſcam terrenarum rerum auidè conſpicit, quo ſtrā
                     guletur peccati laqueo non agnoſcit. Greg. paſtor. lib. 3. cap. 1. § 21. 
               thoſe that will be rich, ſaith the Apoſtle, that ſet this downe, Vnde habeas, quaerit nemo; ſed oportet habere. Iuuenal. ſat. 14. rich they will be, howſoeuer they come by it, per fas &amp; nefas, by hooke or crook, as we ſay, by right or by wrong, they pierce their hearts through with many ſorrowes, peſter their mindes with many fond and noyſome lusts and deſires, and plunge themſelues into many dangerous ſnares, that at length drowne their ſoules in deſtruction.
            
            Yea the very deſire of bettring a mans eſtate by ſuch meanes, is an euident argument of diſcontent: when it grieueth a man at the heart, that his conſcience will not giue him leaue, or that Gods law will notſuffer him to vſe thoſe meanes that he ſeeth worldly men grow wealthy withall. 
                  Malus miles eſt, qui Imperatorem gemens ſequitur. Sen. epiſt. 107. &amp; de vita beata cap. 15. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Arrian. diſſert. l. 2. cap. 16. He is out of Gods way, though he ſeem to be yet in it, though he ſtride not outwardly out of it, that miſliketh it, that liketh any other way better than it, that walketh in it with an euill will. And Malū opus non eſt factū niſi ab ijs qui ia
                     •
                   mali erant. Aug. de civit Dei l. 14. c. 13. as Adam and Eve ſinned and were euill euen in deſiring to eat, before euer

they taſted of the forbidden fruit: So the very deſire of libertie for ſuch courſes argueth euidently ſo far forth a minde irreligious, though the heart neuer conſent to put them in practiſe.
            A ſecond Signe of a Contented minde is the vſe of ſuch lawfull meanes without Care and Couetiſe, without diſtruſtfull care, without greedy deſire.
            It is the ſaying of ſome of the Ancients, and it is a true ſaying, that 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Alex. paed. l. 2. c. 10. Adulter eſt in ſuā vxorem amator ardentior. Xyſtꝰ Pythag in ſentent. Iu aliena vxore omnis amor turpis eſt; in ſua nimius. Hieron. ad Iovin. lib. 1. c. 1. Intemperans in cō
                     iugio adulter eſt vxoris ſuae. Ambr. de Philoſoph. cōtra Platon. Adulterum dicit vxoris eū eſſe, qui in ipſo quoque vſu coniugij nullam verecundiae vel honeſtatis curā habet. Aug. contra Iulian. l 2. Libido appetitꝰ est ſine iudicio, ſine modo, vt ſi vxorem amem amore meret
                        •
                     icio. Jul. S
                        •
                     al. de ſubtil. exerc. 317. § 2. 
               A man may commit adulterie with his owne wife: So a man may commit ſpirituall fornication with the lawfull meanes, that he vſeth and lawfully may vſe, if he vſe them in vnlawfull manner. For the preuenting and auoyding whereof our Sauiour Chriſt biddeth vs, Math. 6. 25. 
               Take no care, (or, no thought rather, if you will) what we ſhall eat or drinke, or wherewith we ſhall be clad. In which precept, or prohibition rather, he forbiddeth not the vſe of lawfull meanes, but the diſtruſtfull affection in the vſe of thoſe meanes. Which appeareth both by ſome of the inſtances that there he maketh vſe of, as that Math. 6. 26. of the fowles, that yet 
                  Math. 24. 28. ex Iob 39. 31, 32. Legatur Aug. de oper. Monach. c. 22, 23, 24. labour and flie about for their foode and their liuing, but without couetouſnes and care; as alſo by 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                the word that he there vſeth, ſignifying properly ſuch 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Euſtath. Iliad. d.
                
               a carking care, as euen diuideth the minde in twaine, and cutteth the very ſoule as it were aſunder.
            
            For the better and fuller conceiuing hereof, we muſt know, that there is a twofold Care: there is 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               a ſtudious care, and there is 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               a carking care, which we call commonly a taking of thought: there is cura de opere, and cura de operis ſucceſſu; a care for our
               
               worke it ſelfe, and a care for the ſucceſſe of it, for the iſſue and euent of it. And it is not the former, but the latter of the two, that is there inhibited.
            There is a Care for the worke it ſelfe, when a man is carefull to do his dutie, and to do well that he doth, and accordingly doth painfully and faithfully endeuor to effect it the beſt he can. And thus there is no man more carefull than the childe of God, than the Chriſtian man; becauſe Epheſ. 6. 6. he doth of Conſcience all he doth. There is another Care about the iſſue and ſucceſſe of the worke, which our Sauiour Chriſt calleth els-where, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Luk. 12. 29. 
               an hanging in ſuſpence, and doubt for the euent of it, as the meteors do in the ayre, vncertaine whither to ſtay there, or to fall downe to the ground. This is then, when a man is not content to do his beſt endeuor, but he caſteth doubts, and taketh thought for what the iſſue of it will be; he fore thinketh with himſelfe, that if he gaine not by ſuch a bargaine, he ſhall be vndone; if ſuch a debtor breake or keep not touch with him, he ſhall be vtterly ouerthrowne; if his grounds take not, or his cattle ſtand not, he ſhall not haue bread to put in his belly; if he can not get the fauour of ſuch a Iudge, or ſuch a great man, he ſhall neuer haue any good ſucceſſe in his Law ſuites, or, if he be toward the Law, his Counſell will grow out of requeſt. &amp;c.
            Conceiue it yet further by theſe two Examples. Mark. 13. 11. Our Sauiour forbiddeth his Apoſtles both 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                
               to take care, and 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                
               to take thought before hand, when they are to appeare before great perſons; both to fore-cast with themſelues what to ſpeake when they

come before them, and to fore-thinke how that they ſhall ſpeake will be taken when they haue ſpoken it. Yet the Miniſters of the word now a daies are 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  vnde meditari. Lat.
                
               to ſtudie before hand what to ſpeake either in Church or Court, if they be there to appeare, becauſe they haue it not now ordinarily by immediate inſtinct at an inſtant, as Math. 10 9. they then had: But they are not 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                
               to take thought how their ſpeeches will ſpeede, but leaue the iſſue of it to Gods good will.
            Againe, Math. 28 13, 14. the Prieſts bid the Souldiers ſay, that CHRISTS corps was ſtolne away by night while they ſlept, and promiſe withall 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                
               to ſecure them, or ſo to ſaue them harmleſſe, that they ſhall not neede to take further care in that kinde. The Souldiers were yet to plot and deuiſe how to tell their Tale ſo, as it might carry moſt ſhew of truth with it, and hauing ſo done, they were to relie on the Preiſts credit for the reſt, who had giuen them their word before for the iſſue of it, that it ſhould no way proue prejudiciall or jeapordous to them. In like manner it is our part to take care how to performe thoſe offices and duties that God hath called vs vnto in the beſt manner that we may: but for the ſucceſſe of it, when we haue performed our part, and done our dutie and our endeuor, we muſt, as the Apoſtle willeth vs, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Philip. 4. 6. 
               be wholy ſecure or careleſſe; take no thought for ought, but leaue all to God, and relie wholy vpon him, who hath commanded vs 1 Pet. 5. 7 
               to cast 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                
               all our care in this kinde vpon him, and promiſed withall that he will take this care for vs.
            
            This diſtruſtfull care breedeth that 1. Tim. 6. 10. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                      Biō apud Stob. c. 10. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                      Clem. Alex padag. l. 2. c. 3. Auiditas materia malorum omnium Amm
                        •
                     an. hiſt. lib. 31. parens. Latus Mauritio. Sicut radi
                        •
                      bonorū omnium eſt charitas, ita malorum omnium cupiditas. Aug. hom. 8. 
               Couetouſnes that is the Roote of all euill. Not amiſſe termed the

Roote, as ſome well haue obſerued: becauſe as there is life oft in the roote, when there is no ſap in the branches: ſo this vice oft liueth, when other die and decay. For Libidinis ignis paulatim extinguitur, &amp; cum ſenecture conſeneſcit: at avaritia augeſcit continuò, &amp; cum ſenectute iuveneſcit, quando vitia reliqua conſen
                     •
                  ſcūt. Rolloc. ad 1. Tim. 6. euen old men, Auaritia ſenilis quid ſibi velit non intelligo. poteſt enī quicquam eſſe abſurdius, quàm quo minus reſtat viae, eo plus quaerere viatici? Cic. de ſenect. Mirabilis ſanè dementia 
                     〈…〉
                   vnim ſamptibus ſe o
                     ••
                  rare faſtinat, cū iam par
                     〈…〉
                  quo tendebat, Aug. de temp. 246. againſt reaſon, that haue leaſt time to liue, are oft-times moſt carefull for, moſt couetous of the things of this life: they thinke, though they haue neuer ſo much, that vnleſſe they gather ſtill more, they ſhall want or ſtarue yet ere they die; they ſhall not haue meate, ſaith one, to put in their mouths while they liue, nor money to burie them with when they be dead.
            
            But neither will ſuch Philip. 4. 5, 6. 
               Carefulnes, or ſuch Hebr. 13. 5. 
               Couetouſnes ſtand with Contentment: and therefore muſt be both far from vs, if we would be accounted truly religious. We muſt baniſh all ſuch diſtruſtfull thoughts, we muſt abandon all ſuch greedy deſires. We muſt learne, as Matth. 6. 12. we pray but for daily bread; ſo to reſt content with it when we haue it; yea to reſt content too, when we haue it not, with the want of it. We muſt learne, when we haue done our beſt endeuor, to leaue the iſſue and euent of our labors to God. As Ioab ſaith to his ſouldiers; 2. Sam 10. 12. 
               Let
               d 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Plut. de ov
                        •
                     r.
                
               vs be of good courage, and fight valiantly for our King and our Country; and let the Lord then do what ſeemeth good in his ſight. So muſt we do what God hath enjoyned vs to do; and when we haue ſo done, Pſal. 37. 5. 
               commit our way for the iſſue of it to him, and relie vpon him, and he will bring it about; he will be ſure then to giue ſuch iſſue to it as ſhall be for our good.
            The third and laſt Note of Contentment may be Pſal. 13. 7. 
               Silence before the Sheerer. When God commeth

to ſheere a man of his ſubſtance, of his wealth and his riches, if he haue a contented minde, he will not murmur and repine at it, as Pſal. 106. 25. the Iſraelites euer and anon when they wanted Exod. 17. 3. water, or Exod. 16. 2, 3. bread, or Num. 11. 4, 5, 6, 7. fleſh in the wildernes: but rather praiſe God with Iob; 
               
                  Iob 1 21. Abſtulit, ſed &amp; dedit. Sen. epiſt. 64. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                      Arriā. diſſert. l. 1. c. 11. Tuliſti liberos quos ipſe dederas. non contriſtor, quod recepiſti, ago gratias quod dediſti. Hierō ad Iulian.
                
               God gaue it, and God taketh it: bleſſed be Gods name. 
               Vitam repoſcen
                     ••
                   naturae, tanquam debitor bonae fidei, red
                     ••
                  turus exulto. Iulian. apud Ammian. l. 25. 
               I returne my life to Nature requiring it back, ſaid that Apoſtata, as ſome report of him, when he lay a dying, as a faithfull debtor, with a good will. So 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Epictet. Enchir. Vita data est v
                        •
                     enda, data eſt ſine 
                        •
                     oenore nobis Mutua, nec certe perſoluenda die. Pedo ad Liv. Non est quod nos ſuſpiciamus, tanquam inter noſtra poſiti. mutuò accepimus: (non tam data, quam commodata. Primaſ. ad 1. Cor.) vſus fructus noſter est: cuius tempora ille arbiter muneris ſui temperat. nos oportet in promptu habere, quae in incertum diem data ſunt, &amp; appellatos ſine querela reddere. Sen. ad Marc. cap. 10. ſhould we returne God his owne againe, that he hath pleaſed to lend vs, as faithfull and thankfull debtors with hearty good will; Non moeremus quod talem amiſimus; ſed gratias agimus, quod habuimus. Hieron. epitaph. Pa
                     ••
                  ae. rendring thanks vnto him, that we haue had them ſo long, not repining becauſe we can haue them no longer.
            But we contrariwiſe, when we haue had a long time the vſe of Gods bleſſings, are wont to lay claime to them, and to account them as our owne by preſcription; and ſo, P
                     •
                  ſſimi eſt debitoris creditori facere convitium. Sen. ibid. as it falleth our ofttimes by bad borrowers and worſe pay-maſters, God looſeth a frend with vs for asking his owne of vs.
            
               Pſal. 39. 9. 
               I was dumbe, ſaith David, and opened not my mouth, becauſe it was thy doing. It is a ſigne that a man ſeeth Gods hand on him for his good, if he can be ſilent when God ſtraitneth and impaireth his eſtate.
            And Hebr. 10. 34. the faithfull Hebrewes, ſaith the Apoſtle,

               with ioy, not quietly onely but cheerefully, ſuſtained the loſſe of their worldly goods, knowing that they had better treaſure and more durable laid vp for them in heauen. It is a ſigne that Hebr. 11. 25, 26. a man looketh at a better matter, when he can ſo readily and ſo cheerefully part with his wealth: as Gen. 45. 20. 
               Iacob regarded not his houſhold-ſtuffe and ſubſtance in Canaan, when he had all the fat of Aegypt before him.
            Shut we vp this laſt point with this familiar ſimilitude. A garment that hangeth looſe about a man is put off with eaſe; but ſo is not the skin that ſticketh faſt to the fleſh, nor the ſhirt that cleaueth faſt to the vlcerous leper; a tooth if it be looſe, it commeth out with eaſe, but if it ſticke faſt in the head, it is not pulled out but with paine, yea many times it bringeth away ſome peece of the gumme or the jaw with it. So here, Tunc verè oftendimus, quia accepta recté tenuimꝰ, quū aequāimiter ad momentum ſublata toleramus Greg. mor. l. 2. c. 42. Mihi diuitiae ſi effluxerint, nihil 
                     •
                  uferent niſi ſemetipſas: tuſtup
                     •
                  bis &amp; videboris tibi ſine terelictꝰ, ſi illa a te receſſerīt. apud me diuitia aliquim locū habent; apud t
                     •
                   ſummum: ad poſtremum divitiae 
                     •
                  eaſunt, tu diuiti
                     •
                  rum es. Senec. de vita beat. c. 12. a man is content willingly to part with his riches, when Pſal. 62. 10. Sapiens divitias non amat, ſed mavult: non in animū illas, ſed in domum recipit. Senec. ibid. 21. Omnia iſtae nobis accedant, non hareant: vt ſi abducā
                  tur, ſine vlla noſtri laceratione diſcedant. Idem epiſt. 74. his heart is not ſet vpon his wealth: but 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Baſil. ad divit. hom. 7. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Heſiod. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Antiphanes. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Antipho apud Stob. cap. 10. Vip
                        •
                     te quibus pecu
                        •
                     ia ſua 
                        •
                     bhaſit, nec ſine ſenſu avelli poteſt. Sen. de tranquill. c. 8. if his heart be glewed to it, it euen renteth his heart in two to part with it, it pulleth as it were a peece of his ſoule away with it. And that is the reaſon why Iob. 1. 21. 
               Iob bleſſed God, when he took away all that euer he had from him, whereas moſt men, if God take from them but a ſmall pitance of that they haue, are ready, as Iob. 1. 11. the Diuell

vntruly ſaid that Iob would do, euen to curſe him to his face.
            
            To conclude then: Would we be eſteemed truly Religious? Philip 4. 5. 
               Let our contentment of minde 
               nota ſit omnibus. 
               appeare to the world; in not ſeeking of theſe outward things, either by indirect courſes, or with diſtruſtfull deſire; in patient enduring the want of them, when God ſeeth good to denie them, and in quiet parting againe with them, when God ſhall call againe for them: Aſſuring our ſelues that God doth all for our good, as well in with-holding or with-drawing of them from vs, as in conferring them vpon vs, or in continuing them vnto vs: So ſhall we be ſure of a comfortable vſe of Gods good bleſſings in this life, and of certaine enjoyment of eternall bleſſednes togither with God himſelfe in the next life.
            FINIS.
         
      
   

