
   
      
         
            The gallants burden A sermon preached at Paules Crosse, the twentie nine of March, being the fift Sunday in Lent. 1612. By Tho. Adams ...
            Adams, Thomas, fl. 1612-1653.
         
         
            
               1612
            
         
         Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01573
            STC 117
            ESTC S100383
            99836225
            99836225
            483
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01573)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 483)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 606:02)
         
         
            
               
                  The gallants burden A sermon preached at Paules Crosse, the twentie nine of March, being the fift Sunday in Lent. 1612. By Tho. Adams ...
                  Adams, Thomas, fl. 1612-1653.
               
               [2], 34 leaves   
               
                  Printed by W. W[hite] for Clement Knight, and are to be sold at his shoppe in Pauls church-yard at the signe of the Holy Lambe,
                  London :
                  1612.
               
               
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2003-06
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-06
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-08
            Jonathan BlaneySampled and proofread
         
            2003-11
            AptaraRekeyed and resubmitted
         
            2003-12
            Jonathan BlaneySampled and proofread
         
            2003-12
            Jonathan BlaneyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2004-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               THE
Gallants Burden.
            
               A
Sermon preached at
PAVLES CROSSE, THE
twentie nine of March, being
the fift Sunday in Lent.
1612.
            
               By THO. ADAMS, Preacher
of Gods Word at Willington
in Bedford-shire.
            Published by authority.
            
               LONDON
Printed by W. W. for Clement Knight, and are to
be sold at his Shoppe in Paules Church-yard
at the Signe of the Holy Lambe. 1612.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE HONORABLE
SIR WILLIAM GOSTWICKE
Baronet, and his worthy Lady, the
Lady IANE GOSTWICKE.
            
               HOnorable Sir, I acknowledge freely that
the World is oppressed with the Presse, a
                  •
               d
the confluence of Bookes hath bred a confusion
of errours, of Vices; so hard is it to
distinguish betwixt profitable and vaine
Writinges; and hauing culled out the best, so easie is it
with much good Meate to surfet; yet is not therefore Meate
vnnecessarie: It is no sober inference, because both Text
and readers haue been corrupted with false Glosses, to reiect
all Expositions, all Applications: both are fitte, this latter
most necessary; for our Vnderstanding is better then our
Conscience: there is some light in our Minds, litle warmth
in our Affections: So against Nature is it true in this, that
the essentiall qualities of Fire, Light, and Heat, are deuided;
and to say, whether our light of Knowledge be more,
or our heate of Deuotion lesse, is beyond me: Let this (considered)
plead for me, that I (doe but) rubbe this sowning
Knowledge in vs, to bring it backe to some life of Obedience:
If any feele their thicke eyes hence to receiue any
clearenesse, or their nummed Affections to gather (the
least) Spirit, let th
                  •
               m at once, giue God the glory, and take
to themselues the comfort. Sinne hath got strength with
age, and against all naturall order, is more powerfull, subtile,

and fuller of actiue dexteritie now in the dotage of it,
then it was in the nonage: Both Pulpit &amp; Presse are weake
enough to resist it. It therfore this small Arrow of Reproofe
can wound (but euen) one of his Limbes, it shall a litle eneruate
his tyranny. Whatsoeuer this Sermon is, it is wholly
yours, and he that made it: whose Patronage, I could not be
ambitious of, if I should onely fixe my eyes on my owne deseruinges:
but in the affiance of your good natures, mature
iudgementes, and kind constructions of my weake endeauours,
I haue presumed to make you the Patron of my Labours,
who was freely the Patron of my selfe. I know, that
Gods word can countenaunce it selfe, and needes not the
shelter of an humaine arme, not, though it had as many
Edomites to deride it, as it hath Patrons to defende it:
But I find not onely the best Writinges of the best Men, but
euen some of those Holy Bookes, inspired from Heauen, bearing
in their foreheads (as from the pen-men) a dedication.
I confesse, it is not all for your Protection, somewhat for
your vse; and you are blessed in fauouring that, which shalbe
best able to fauour you: May I therefore intreate your
Honors, to giue it happy entertainement to your owne
heartes, fauourable protection to the worldes eyes; so shall
that, and my selfe be (yet more) yours. The God of all power
and mercie, be as f
                  •
               ythfull a shadow of refreshing to your
soules, as your kindnesse hath been free to my wantes, who
must euer remaine.
            
               Your Honors in all
faythfull obseruance,
Tho. Adams.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            THE GALLANT'S BVRDEN.
            
               Esay 21. ver. 11. 12.
               The burden of Dumah. He calles vnto me out of
Seir, Watchman, what was in the night? Watchman,
what was in the night? The Watchman
sayd: The morning commeth, and also the night.
If ye will aske, enquire: returne, and come.
            
            
               
                  QVò breuior, 
                     •
                  ò obscurior: the
shorter this Prophesie is, the
more mysticall. In holy Writ,
these two thinges euer concurre:
(Sententia breuis▪ res ampla)
a finite Sentence, an infinite
Sense: As in a little Map
we see a world of Countries,
and what the Foote cannot measure in many dayes, the
Eye peruseth in a moment: this is the little Mappe of
Idumea or Edom, (wherein we may suruey the state of
that whole Region) not much vnlike the situation of
it, standing in this Chapter betwixt Chaldea and Arabia:
The Burdens against them both are heauy, and the
Plagues aggrauated with more circumstaunces: The
burden of Dumah, (though short) shall weigh with
them graine for graine.
            As you trauaile with me into this Countrie (by the
guidance of that inlightning spirit) tie your considerations
to two especiall thinges;Diuision. 
               the Mappe, the Morall.
In the Mappe you shall finde 1. an Inscription, 2. a Description:
In the Inscription obserue,Mappe. 1. the name of the

Countrie: 2. the nature of the Prophecie. The Description
restes it selfe on 3. Obiectes; 1. a Mountaine,
2. a Watchman, 3. an Edomite: where is shadowed 1.
vnder the Mountaine, Securitie: 2. vnder the Watchman,
Vigilancie: 3. vnder the Edomite, Scorne. Now,
if you aske (as they did the Prophet Ezekil) what these
thinges meane?Morell. the Morall directes you 1. by a Q
                  •
               estion,
2. by an Answere: The Question would know,
what was in the Night: the Answere declares it 1. by a
Resolution, 2. by an Aduice: The Resolution (Venit
manè et vespè) The 
                     ••
                  orning c
                     •
                  mes, and also the night: the Aduice,
If ye will aske, enquire: returne, and come.
            
            In the Inscription,Dumah. we propoūded to be considered 1.
the name of the Country, 2. the nature of the Prophecie:
For the Country, there is some question what this Dumah
should be: some affirme it to be the Country of the
Ishmaelites, and to receiue the name from Dumah, that
sonne of Ishmaell, mentioned Gen. 25. 14. but that Dumah,
with other the sonnes of Ishma
                     •
                  ll inhabited Arabia,
which is burdened in the Prophecie following, distinctly
seuered from this: this Dumah then was the
Countrie of the Idumeans or Edomites, the place where
Esa
                     •
                  
                and his generation dwelt: this is cleare by the
Mount Seir, which was an Hill of the Ed
                     •
                  mu
                     •
                  s: Ezech.
35. 15.
            This Idumea is heere called Dumah:
               Pearphaer
                     •
                  sin. thus God insinuates
his contempt of that rebellious and accursed nation,
by cutting short the name, as vnworthy to stand
in his Booke, graced with the full length: the estimation
which the wicked beare with God is heere expressed:
he thinkes the mention of them a blurre to his sacred
leaues: now, shall their persons sit in his Kingdome
with honour, whose names may not stand in his Booke
without disgrace? Sometimes they are concealed, as
Diues:
               Luk. 16. 19. that reall Parable giues no other title to the condemned

churle:Luk. 13. 32. Christ allowes the Tyrant Herod no
other name then a Foxe: Goe tell that Foxe, &amp;c. God
calles those Princes,Amos. 4. 1. the Bulles of Bashan on the Mountaines
of Samaria: they would be blottes to his holy
Booke, if they were expressely named. Sometimes
they are named, (but) with abbreuiations; Dumah for
Id
                     •
                  mae
                     •
                  :
               Ruth. 4. 19. Thus Aram is called Ram: Ephesdam
                     •
                  im, a
coast of the Philistines, neuer spoken of without contempt,
is twice thus curtalled. 1. Cro. 11.1. Chron. 11. 13. it is called Pasdaemmim:
and 1. Sam. 17. Dammim.
               1. Sam. 
                     〈◊〉
                   .1.
            
            Let not this Obseruation slippe from vs without our
vse, If God take letters from the name, he intendes to
take blessings from the person,Ier. 22. 28. when Ieconiah's curse is
written in the cutting off his Posteritie from the throne
of Dauid, and himselfe from the prosperitie of the earth,
he is called Co
                     •••
                  h: the reason is added, He is a despised
person, let him haue a shortned name: a broken Idoll, and
an vnpleasant Vessell, &amp;c.
            
            Thus God crosseth the worlds fashion, by putting
them in his Chronicle, which are not heere thought of,
and leauing those out, which the world boastes of as
her glorie: to a soule that hath more Affection in her,
then Religion, it seemes a great matter of pitty: that
Plato, Cato, Alexander, &amp; some of those mighty Romane
Cesars, honored with the graces of Nature, the bounties
of Fortune, &amp; the greatest glory, the fore'd world could
yeeld them, should yet want a name in Gods Booke, a
place in his Kingdome. Greatnes is the fairest obiect
to the eye of the world, Goodnes to the eye of Heauen:
There is a glorious splendour in pompous Honour, to
draw the eyes of admiration after it; it litle affectes the
sight of God, if Vertue giues it not a Lustre: hee that is
goodnesse and greatnesse it selfe (when others haue it
in the concrete, good and great, he hath and deserues it
in the abstract) is pleased (to preferre his title of Optimus,
before that of Maximus) and first to be called Good,Exod. 14.
               
and then Great. His affections should be ours: he is
the absolute precedent of our imitation.
            There are infinite wayes that conduct to seeming
Honour, excluding Vertue; the end of them al is shame:
since of a naturall man it is true, that (Quan
                     •
                  ò ornatior,
tantò nequ
                     •
                  or) The more adorned, the more wicked: our
Bonnets vaile, our Knees bow to many, whom the
sight of Heauen and Vertue, scornes: This imparitie
of men lyuing, is made euen by death, who sweepes all
(Beggar and Prince) with his impartiall Beesome, into
one Bagge: and when Iudgement comes, they are made
odde and vnequall againe; for then, the least in the
worldes estimation, shall sit downe with the blessed
Kinges and Patriarches in Heauen, when Kinges and
Patriottes without grace, shalbe excluded. If you desire
your names to be registred with the pen of Eternitie,
write them your selues with the pen of Charitie: the
Booke of Grace, is the counterpaine to the Booke of
Election: they are written in Heauen first, and there
God reades them: Wee cannot see into this Booke
through the thicke cloudes of the Ayre and Sinne; let
vs write them in the leaues of Obedience, and there read
them:1. Tim. 2. 19. they stand sure with God before, not sure to vs
till now:2. Pet. 1. 10. Write them in the entrals of the Poore, in the
ruines of the Church, by you bettered, repayred, maintayned,
(Non norunt haec monumenta mor
                     •
                  ,) and you shall
one day heare the Iudge himselfe, read them in the audience
of all the world,Math. 25. to your ioy, crowne, eternitie
of blisse.
            Christ diuerted his Apostles triumph to an other honour:
they were litle lesse then proud,Luke. 10. 17. that the Deuils
were subdued vnto them through his name whom they
serued: True (sayth Christ) I saw Sathan fall from heauen
like lightning; neuerthelesse reioyce not that the spirits obey you,
but reioyce that your names are written in Heauen.
               ver. 20. Reioyce
not of your innobled bloodes, admired with liuing

praises, &amp; rescued from the iawes of obliuion by sumptuous
Sepulchers: there is small matter of ioy, that the
name liues in bright honour on Earth, when the Soule
lyes in the rusting miseries of Hell: but reioyce on your
assurance of memoriall with God:Prou. 10. 7. 
               The memorie of the iust
shall be blessed; but the name of the wicked shall rotte. A great
name commonly ariseth either from Blood,1. Descent▪
                popular applause,2. Ho
                     •
                  our
or Golden trappinges:3. Wealth. the last vseth a man like
a Counter that standes now for a Million, instantly for
a Penny: The first findes Honour, perhaps deserues it
not, leaues it by succession: The middlemost is vnconstant,
as the causes are: the vulgar opinions, whose distracted
voyces seldome hit on the same tune, or neuer
keepe it long. The Monarches of the world haue large
and tedious Titles, according to their seuerall Dominions:
good lucke haue they with that Honour, which
the hand of God reacheth foorth vnto them: there is a
Title that betters all theirs; those are foulded vp in
time, that perisheth: this bringes Honour without end
or limits, to be a Christian; such haue their names producted
in Gods booke, to shew that they stand written
with Golden letters in the Lambes booke of Heauen:
Abram shalbe called Abraham: Iacob, Israell. The Hebrewes
well obserue, that God to those he loued, added a
letter of his owne name (that tetragrammaton) Iehouah:
as the letter He, to Abrahams and Sarahs name the letter
Iod to Iehoshua's, who was before called Hoshea.
            
            It was happy for Mordecaj that his name stood in
the Persian Chronicles, that Ahashverosh might read him:
his seruice shalbe found out with rewardes, array him
with the Kinges Robe, set him on the Kinges Chariot,
and proclaime his name through the popular streetes,
This is the man,Ester. 6. 9. whom the King will honour. It is more blessed
to stand in the Chronicles of Heauen, registred by
the Penne of that eternall Spirit; wee shall one sit with
the King in his Throne (Vnicenti dabitur sedere,Reuel. 3. 21. &amp;c.) and

put on his robe of Glorie;Philip. 3. 
                     •
                  1. 
               (Be fashioned like his glorious
body,Psal. 149. 9.) Such honour haue all his Saintes. It is the decree and
promise of him, whose word is more stable then the
foundations of the Earth: Those that hon
                     ••
                  r me, I will honour.
Reuolue then his sacred Name in your sanctified
mouthes: sing Hosa
                     •
                  na's to it heere, that you may 
                  •
               ing
Halle
                     •
                  uia's hereafter: &amp; hauing drunke heartie draughts
of his Waters of Mercie, blesse with Dauid his great and
glorious Name: the honour of your owne names is attayned,
nay consistes in this: maintaine the glory of
it with your strengthes, sound it with your prayses, and
(if need be) seale it with your bloodes; and God shall
write your Names (not shortned like Dumahs,) but at
full length, in a Booke neuer to be blotted out.
            The nature of the Prophecie followes, being that
other branch of the Inscription;Burthen. 
               A Burden: a matter
not easily portable, but will weigh heauie on whom soeuer
imposed: the Burden is in 2. respectes: 1. of the
Prophet that beare it: 2. of the People that were to suffer
it.
            1. The Word of the Lord is to the Prophets a heauy
Burden till they are deliuered of it: there is no rest in
the bones to the surcharged Conscience, no more then
to the pregnant Woman till she be eased: I confesse,
that Securitie, Vanitie, abundance of Wealth, setting
their shoulders to this Burden, make many a Prophet
forgoe all sense of the weight: Ionas loden with his
Commission for Niniueh, lay as securely in the sides of
the Shippe, as if the God of Israel had layd no Burden
on him: but himselfe was a Burden to the Shippe, and
the furie of the Waues, Windes, and his Anger that
mooues all, was not appeased, till the Shippe was disburthened
of Ionas, that had disburthened himselfe of
the Message of God. Let me speake it with griefe and
feare; We are the sonnes of those Prophets, (I meane)
their successors in Gods Ministeriall worke: and the

Word of the eternall God is no lighter a Burden to vs
then it was to them: nay let me adde (that, which is not
to be thought of without trembling) there is the Burden
of a Curse threatned to them that neglect this Burden;
Cursed is hee that doth Gods businesse negligently. Least I
should seeme bitter in applying this too generally, let
me freely speake what Paul applyes to his owne person,
if he slighted this ponderous charge: A necessitie
(which is no lesse then a Burden) is layd vpon me, and woe
vnto me, if I preach not the Gospell.
            
            I know that our Haruest aboundes with plentifull
and painefull Labourers, that beare the heat and burden
of the day, and according to their seuerall offices (whether
in Ouerseeing, Planting, or Watering) with the
sweate of their browes, they labour in Gods Vineyard:
but to complaine o
                  •
                the euill that is, is no wrong to the
good that is: 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   excellent thinges are sp
                     •
                  ken of thee, Oh
thou Citie of God; Oh thou Church of England: Oh
might it be no wrong to thy Perfections, no staine to
thy Beautie, to condole some wantes in thy Sonnes: It
is sin to be silent, where an impartiall speach may take
good effect: the sweete deawes of holy Admonitions
may from this place, (as the Liuer) spread into all the
Vaines of the Land.
            The Ministerie is a matter of both Honour and Burthen:
Are there none, that catch at the Honour, will not
meddle with the Burden? whose pined Flockes must
either content themselues with a bare Pasture, or else
stray foorth into neighbouring Commons; whiles they
forget to breake their Maisters Bread; yea perhaps to
set the whole Loafe before his guestes: Are there none
that loade their mindes with the Burden of Cares, too
heauie for a Christian soule to beare? the loade of Ambition,
the burden of Couetousnes so pressing them
downe, as if they were exonerated of the Burden of the
Gospell: But if any soule be sensible of this Burden, (as

one, into whose bowels God hath put the compassion
of distressed soules,)Esay. 62. 1. for Zyons sake he will not hold his
peace: yea, let me speake it of him, that Iob of himselfe;
He is full of matter, and the spirit within him, compelleth him:
the word is in him,Iob. 3
                        •
                     . 18. like new Wine in Bottles, which must be vented,
or will burst foorth: And if we slippe our shoulders
from vnder this Burden, God can make the whole
world too hotte for vs, and at last impose a Burden of
another nature, on our then weaker and more vnable
soules (the Mountaines and Rockes (if weighed in the
ballance) will be found lighter) the Burden of all their
sinnes, whose soules haue bled to death by our negligence:
We may, through our impatience and weakenesse
with Ieremy, curse the dayes of our Natiuitie, and
cry woe worth the time,Ier. 20. that euer we were borne, to
so troublesome an Office: but a greater woe and curse
attendes vs, if we attende it not: passiue Corruptions
in our selues, actiue Reproches, Iniuries, Oppositions
of others, impulsiue temptations of the Deuill, may
make vs wearie of our callinges: but his Word is in our
heartes, as fire shut vp in our bones, and we shall be
weary of forbearing; we cannot smother the flames of
it, but with tearmes of defiance to the stoutest that beare
a forehead, we must declare it: God giues vs the prouision
of this Burden, before hand, that we may stoope
the shoulders of patience and zeale to it: Thus to Ezekiell:
Sonne of man,
               Ezek▪ 1
                     •
                  
                I send thee to Israel; What are they?
I will not dissemble with thee: They are a rebellious house:
contumelies against thy selfe, blasphemies against thy
maker, the bitinges, smitinges, woundinges of tongues,
handes, and swordes: this is the Burden thou must
beare; if any lighter and better thinges come, let them
be (praeter spem) beyond thy expectation: Thus is the
Word a burden to the person that beares it.
            2. It is no lesse to them that must suffer it: the Iudgementes
of God are heauie on whomsoeuer they light: a

Milstone bound to the sinner, &amp; throwne with him into
the Sea, will not sooner sinke him to the bottome, then
these bound to the soule, will sinke it to the depth of
dephtes;Math. 18. 6. therfore Christ sayes, B
                     •
                  tter a Milstone, because
lighter. The wrath of the Lambe, at the consummation
of the world, is acknowledged more heauie then Rocks
and Mountaines;Reuel. 6. 16. and happy were it for those reprobates,
if such intollerable pressures could dissolue them
into emptines: These on the body are more sensible, on
the soule more miserable. In the infancie of the world,
Gods blowes were most outward; in this ripe (or rather
rotten) age of it, they are most inward &amp; spirituall:
We haue no Beares to deuoure the Mockers; no fierie
Serpents to strike the Murmurers: Gods punishments
reach most to the Conscience: (T
                     •••
                  plex circa prae
                     ••••
                  a
ferrum,) a sensuall and senseles heart without apprehension
of Gods incensed anger, (Cor nuliis violabile telis) not
made of penitrable stuffe: if Gods finger touch the body,
we grone vnder the weight; let his whole hand lie
on the soule, we feele nothing: If this be not our Burden
&amp; Miserie, what is? Like curious Visitors, will ye not
beleeue this age to labour of this Sicknesse, (vnles you
behold some Symptomes? Let your eyes take notice
(and that not without griefe of soule) the deadnesse of
heart among vs: We ply the World hard, dallie with
Religion: We serue God in iest; our selues, with all respect
&amp; earnest: Our Deuotions are like Winter, frosty,
misty, &amp; windy of many natures, none other then cold:
Nothing armes, charmes, and confirmes our senses with
attention, spirits with intention, actiue powers with
contention, but vanitie. Are not the Benches in Tauernes,
and Theaters, often wel replenished, when these
Seates are thinne and almost empty? Are not the Allies
in this Temple often fuller of Walkers, then the Quire
of Petitioners? Conference with prophane ostentation
of Cloathes; perhappes plottes of mischiefe, as frequent,

as sutes to God: (making it little lesse then a den
of Theeues:) If men stumble into the Church, as company,
custome, recreation, or (perchance) sleepe inuites
many, they feed their eyes with vanities; if any drops
he admitted into their eares, they are entertayned vnder
the nature of conceates: Iudgements (they thinke)
be none of their lessons, they will not suffer their consciences
to apply them: Mercies they challenge and
owne, though they haue no right to them: If this estate
be not a misery, iudgement, burden, there is none: The
fire of the Pestilence is well quenched, the rumours and
stormes of Warre are layde, the younger brother of
death, Famine, doth not tyrannize ouer vs: But here it
is; our sinnes and Gods wrath (for them) meete, and the
heart is hardned: this is the sorest iudgement. Let me
speake a Paradoxe, but a trueth; it is the plague of manie,
that they are not plagued: euen this is their punishment,
the want of punishment: &amp; the hand of God
is then heauiest, when it is lightest: heauiest on the
Conscience, when lightest on the Carcase: it is true on
them, what the Philosopher sayd of himselfe (Perieram
misi perijssem) they are vndone, that they are not vndone:
God suffers their bodyes to possesse, and be possessed
of rest: they sing to Viols, daunce to Measures: their
Heades ake not, Much lesse their Consciences: But (as
to Israel, fatte with Quailes) God withall, sendes Lea
                  •
               
               nesse
into their soules: the present indulgence, giues
sufficient argument of future woes: they surfet on pleasures,
till death puts them out of breath: that worthy
Father saw this their (selfe-commended) estate, and
prayed against it;Aug. Domine, hic 
                     •
                  re, hic seca, vt in 
                     •
                  ternum parcas. 
               Lord, heere plague, cut, massacre, burne
me, so that for euer thou wilt spare and saue me. This is (O
                     •
                  u
                     •
                  
grauissimum,) the most grieuous Burden. Securitie is the
very suburbes of Hell: (Miseri
                     ••
                   nihil est miser
                     •
                  , se non
miserante,) there is nothing more wretched, then a
wretched man, that reckes not his owne miseri
                  •
               : an

insensible Heart is the Deuils Anuile, he fashioneth all
sinnes on it, and the blowes are not felt.
            You wounder at the frequencie of Burdens, and
that the Turtles of this Land grone out of this place,
the sadde tunes of woe and miserie. Alasse, how should
we sing the songes of Syon to a strange people? The Pulpit
(I confesse) should be the Mercie seate; but your
sinnes haue made it a Tribunall, or Bench of Iudgement:
Nothing but the thunders of Sinaj, (and scarce those)
can waken vs from our dead sleepe: this is (Ima S
                     •
                  curitas)
deepe Securitie, fitly applyed to vs, whose is (Sine
cura aetas) an Age without care; or rather, if you will,
(Se curans 
                     •
                  tas) that loue none but our selues, and that
not enough to seeke our owne peace: Let me speake it
in the tune of Ieremie (Non habet vlterius, quod nostris moribus
addat posteritas) we flow with those sins, to which no
following posteritie shalbe euer able to adde; so spreading,
an infection of sinne is among vs, that, as in a great
Plague, we wonder not so much at them which die, as
at them whch scape; so there is nothing a Wonder, a
Mirror, a Miracle in Nature, but he that liues vnspotted
of this world. If you thinke I speake too bitterly,
I would to God, it were not worse then I speake: I
would your reformation might conuince our shame,
and giue vs cause to recant this in the Pulpitte: this
turnes the Message of Edome vpon vs; the Burden of
Dumah, the Burden of England: we cast from our shoulders
the Burden of the Law, God layes on vs the burden
of Iudgement: we load God with our sinnes,Amos. 2. 13. and
presse him as a Cart with Sheaues: we packe vp a bundle
of Lyes, Blasphemies, Adulteries, Periuries, Extortions,
Fraudes, and then hasten to the Crosse of Christ
to vnload them; as if pressing our soules to Hell with
wilfull sinnes, yet Christ on the least warning, must
ease vs:Math. 11. 28. But the Promise is not to men laden with sinne,
but with sorrow for sinnes: It is such a load as must

make vs weary, or we haue no promise to be eased.
            But alasse, sinne (which is Burden enough to sinke
the world) is made light by custome; as if resting in
mans heart, it did (Quiessere in propriam sedem) settle it
selfe in the owne naturall place: It is a philosophicall
Axiome (Nullum elementum suo loco pondurat) no element
is heauie in the proper place: Though Sinne be as
weightie as a Talent of Lead,Zachar. 5. 7. (sayth the Prophet) yet
it is at the Center, (when) got into the corrupted heart,
and weighes light: and except the wrath of God fall
vpon the naked Conscience, Sinne lyes at the doore,
and Cain neuer cryes, It is greater then I am able to beare.
Iudas had Burden enough of treason, hypocrisie, malice,
couetousnesse, to sinke him downe; it was no Burden,
till the finger of Gods wrath touched the tender
heart-stringes, and then it pressed him downe to his
owne place.Act. 1. 25. How many haue in curuate and oppressed
soules, bowed downe with the spirit of infirmitie (nay of
ranke iniquitie) more then 18. yeares, that are not yet
sensible of their owne crookednes, nor the cause thereof:
for it can not be, but the de
                  •
               owred Patrimonies of
many Orphans, the ruines and depopulations of
Townes, the deuastation of Holy thinges, should be
Burd
                  •
               ns too heauie for a poore crasie Soule to stand
vnder: Piles of V
                  •
               urie heauier then Ae
                     •
                  na, Burdens of
Bribes out ballancing the Axeltree, are more then the
Gyants, Geonaxo, Monsters of Men, and Prodegies of
Nature were able to beare. We could not see a corrupted
Lawyer, Citizen, Cormorant, goe so nimbly, and so
bolt vpright vnder such a masse of sinne, if they had not
some helpe: Heere it is, the strong man Sathan (so it pleaseth
Christ to tearme him) puts vnder his shoulder, and
makes the Vessell goe tight and easie, with an equall
Ballance, which could not else swimme vpon the Waters
without sinking: Pride could not else carry a
whole Towneship on his backe, which his father Couetousnesse

had (but newly) deuastate, clambring vp
to Honour, (as Ionathan to the Garrison of the Phi
                     •
                  istens
by the raggednesse of these two Rockes, Bozez and
Seneh; so these) by the desolation of our two maine
Rockes, the Church, and Common-wealth. The vnmercifull
Monopolies of Courtiers, the vnreasonable
Prices of Marchantes, the hoordes (if not transportation)
of Graine with Cormorantes, the aduantages
made of the poores necessities, vnconscionable sinnes,
and Rentes, wringing the last Penny from their Purses,
and drop of Blood from their Heartes, (Oh durum
et importabile pondus) an intollerable weight. These wretches
were neuer able to beare it without the ayde of the
Deuill, who, whiles they draw with him in the same
yoake, is content to beare all the Burden.
            At last, when Presumption hath left the Stage, and
Desperation begins to knit vp all with a direfull catastrophe,
the Pulses beating slowly, the Head akeing vehemently,
Body and Soule refusing all proffered comfort,
then the Deuill castes the whole Load on them, that
at once they may despaire and die: then that which
was lighter then Corke and Feathers, becomes heauier
then Lead &amp; Earth: God hath often stroue with them
by his Word; they would neuer yeeld (Avinces) Thou
shalt ouercome Oh Lord: Now (perhaps with Iulian too
late) they pant out (
                     〈◊〉
                  ) Thou hast ouercome: Our
cryings in the day, could not wake them; that cry at
midnight, shall fetch them vp, With the Burden of Enuie,
Couetousnesse, Drunkennesse, &amp;c. And as it was doomed
to Babilon;Reu
                        •
                     l. 13. 7. Looke how much her glory and pleasure
hath been giue be
                     •
                   so much torment and sorrow. Nay, then
the De
                  •
               ill gettes vp too (like a mercilesse lay our)
with the addition of his owne weight, to aggrauate
their woes. Striue then euerie one to abate the Burden
of Iudgement, by lessening the Burden of
Sinne: Euery repentant Teare that falles, washeth a

Talent from this Burden: euery remorcefull sigh, and
faythfull Prayer,2. Cor. 4. 9 diminisheth the Load; that which remaines,
may presse, shall not oppresse: Christ will put
vnder his shoulder; Come all ye laden (exonerate animas)
vnload your soules: he bore them on his Crosse, and
our beleeuing soules shall neuer feele the weight of
them: the Crosse onely is left heauy to blood and flesh,
but to a heart (made) spirituall,Math. 11. 30. 
               Thy yoake, Oh Lord, is
easie, and thy burden light: our owne heauy, but thine
light.
            Wee haue perused the Mappe to the end of the Inscription,
the Description standes next to our speach;
where we haue an Edomite standing on Mount Seir and
calling to the Watchman, with the voyce of derision,
What he saw in the night, &amp;c. a proude Edomite securing
himselfe the strength of his owne armes, deriding the
Prophet of God, which came against him with the
burden of Warres: this is the sense I fasten on. I haue
read other Expositions, as if it was a question of feare:
I approue and dwell on the former: from the perswasion
then of immunitie, impunitie, and safe standing out
of the reach of Earth,Seir and Security. of Hell, of Heauen, proceedes this
Question. Edom hath shaken off the yoake of Israel,
and begins to crowne his dayes with the Rose buddes
of Peace, and not to feare the Sword of Egipt, nor Ashur,
nor Gods himselfe in Heauen: their conceite was
(though faignedly) as strong of this Mount Seir, as the
promise of God was really true to Mount Syon, neuer to
be moued, though the battlementes of Heauen shotte
Thunder, and the pillars of the Earth quaked.
            There is question about the name of this Seir;
               Hierom. some
affirme it deriued from Esau,
               Gen. 36. 9. as being the place where
he and his generation dwelt: Indeed the nature of Esau,
and the name of Seir, agrees fitly, for both signifie, Brisseled,
or Hairy: but it had the name of Seir, before Esau
came thither. Some Hebrewes thinke the Mountaine

was called Seir, from the apparition of Deuils, who shewed
themselues in the shapes of hayrie men, such as the
Fawnes were imagined to be:Mercer, But most like to take denomination
from Seir the Horite, Gen. 36. 20. who inhabited
there long before Esau:Gen. 14. 6. And the Horites in their
mount Seir, vnto the plaine of Paran; it being the Countrie
of the Ho
                     •
                  i
                     •
                  s or Horites: Esau was drawen hither for
many reasons; 1. because that corner of Canaan about
Hebron,
               Mercer. where he and his brother Iacob dwelt, were too
scant for their Flockes: 2. because Mount Seir fitted
Esau's minde,Perer. being a place of excellent hunting: 3. his
Wiues were of that Countrie: 4. Gods prouidence so
disposed of Esau's remouall, that Iacob might liue in safetie:
And euen in this, God wrought Esau's good, by
putting him out of Canaan; for then with the rest of the
Canaanites they had been destroyed by Israel;
               Gen. 27. 39. 40 but God
made good that temporall blessing vpon Esau and his
seed, which his father Ish
                     •
                  c gaue him. Indeed the Amalekites
(though deriued from Esau) were destroyed by
Israel; but the reason may be thus gathered, because
Amalek was the Sonne of Eliphaz (the sonne of Esau) by
a Concubine:Mercer. the Idumaeans, that were legitimate successors,
were preserued: such was the different respects
to the tight, and to the bastard seed; for God is sayd to
giue Mount Seir to Esau;Ioshuah
                        •
                      4. 4 I gaue vnto Esau mount Seir to
possesse it; therefore the Israelites among their spoyles of
Canaan,
               Deut. 2 5. were expressely forbidden to destroy it: Yee
shall not prouoke them; for I will not giue you of their Land, so
much as a foote breadth, because I haue giuen mount Seir to Esau
for a possession: Such was Gods mercie to Esau for his Fathers
sake, that his posteritie was made great and honourable:
But if the Horites first inhabited Mount Seir,
how comes the posteritie of Esau to enioy it? It is answered
in the 2. of Deutr.
               Deut. 2. 
                     •
                  2. 
               The Horims dwelt in mount Seir
before-time, whom the children of Esau chased out, and destroyed
them before them, and dwelt in their stead: So doth Sinne

quench the very cinders of naturall affection, after it
hath put out the flames of Religion, that the children of
Esau ceased not till they had extinguished their owne
kindred: the respect of blood must giue way to Rapine
and Malice: too weake is Nature to restraine the furie
of Sinne, when it is stung by that fiery Serpent, the
Deuill. The Romish Mountaine doth claime some kin
of this Mount Seir, (at least in the opinion of the Iewes:)
There is one place in Edom, called Magdiell; this the
Rabbines take for Rome, and say, that of the Idumeans
came the Romans: it is not so locally; it may be well
spiritually; For, for persecution of the Saintes, there is
no such Edome in the world, as Rome: But Magdiell signifies,
Praysing God: Oh blessed were Rome, if in this, she
could be called Magdiell. This Seir was a Mountaine of
great strength, not infertile; and as great probabilitie
giues it, graced with either one or many goodly Cities:
Who will bring me into Edom,Psal. who will lead me into the strong
Citie? Neither may we thinke, that the offspring of
Edom, when once made Dukes, nay Kinges, contented
themselues to dwell in Tentes.
            But what if a Mountaine, what if a Citie, or the
strength of Edom, is it able to grapple with the Wrath
of God, or buckle with his Iudgementes? If any peece
of the broad Earth were shot proofe against the Anger
of God (as they faine the 
                  •
               arden of Hisperides against
the Planets) it would not be vnsought, vnbought: there
haue been Mountaines and Cities before and after Seir,
prouder and stronger then shee, that haue measured
their length on the ground, and been dissolued to dust
and rubbish; and Edom her selfe hath daunced the same
measure. The world hath gloried in her seuerall ages
of many goodly Cities; 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  
                the pride of Assyria,
Troy the pillar of Asia, Babilon more a Region then a
Citie, Carthage graced with 17. tributarie Kingdomes;
and let not Ierusalem be shut from both the glory and

sadnesse of this relation: may we not say of them all
now (Etiam periere ruinae) That litle of them is dissolued
to nothing. Thus God cooles and dampes the glory of
Israel: Goe you vnto Calneh, and see: and from-thence goe vnto
Hamath the great:Amos. 6. 2 then goe downe to Gath of the Philistines:
be they better then these Kingdomes, or the border of their land
greater then your b
                     •
                  rder?
            
            
               Constantius spake of old Rome, that Nature had emptied
all her forces on that one Citie: the time came, she
was ouerthrowne, and her Walles made euen with the
ground. The titles of new Rome are greater, not her
Priuiledges: (shee is called, Vrbs aeterna,) yet that
Eternall Babilon shall fall, and her honour be layde in
the Dust: her doome is past, and in the decree of Heauen,
she is already fallen for the more surenesse; and all
her Marchants (petty Leases taken out of her graund
Lease) shall mourne bitterly for her: shee shall be
made a Cage of vncleane Birdes, Owles and Vultures;
as she is now a Denne of vncleane Beas
                  •
               es, Lyons and
Tygers. If any Citie on earth might boast her Priuiledges,
let Ierusalem speake; shee was called the Holy
City, and the City of God: the Temple in her, a figure of
the Church militant; as Salom
                     •
                  n the buylder of it,
was a type of Christ: Beholde, her House is left vnto
her desolate: Sinne layde her Pinacles in the dust: At
the murder of his Sonne, God with his owne handes,
rent the Vaile, and after gaue the whole Fabricke a
spoyle to the Gentiles: They that haue trauayled the
lower Prouinces, testifie, that the rude heapes of
ruined Churches, Monasteries, and Religious places,
are no lesse frequent then pittied spectacles: Deuotion
built them, kept them; Sinne polluted them, Hostility
subuerted them: Sinne prepared the way for Ruine and
Blood: the Idolatry within ouerthrew the Walles without:
they could plead more then Dumah, they and their
pleas are perished.
            
               Let me not speake as a Prophet, but as an Admonisher:
Is it impossible for the Sinne of England, to haue
the like effect? Wee are ready to say in pride, what
Dauid spake in the assurance of Fayth, I can not fall thou
oh Lord of thy goodnesse, hast made my Hill 
                     〈◊〉
                   strong: Let
vs prayse God for that we haue, and pray that our
sinnes auert it not: Let Dumah speake with his pride;
though our Priuiledges be more, let our Presumption
be lesse: it is wise and safe, to possesse more then wee
boast of: though Nature hath bound vp the loynes of
our Kingdome witha girdle of Waues, &amp; Pollicie raysed
another fence of woodden Walles, yet God must
put about vs a third Girdle, the bandes or circle of his
Prouidence, or our strength is weaker then the waters.
It is an old and sure rule against the Atheist, against the
Worldling, that whole cannot be perpetuall, whose
partes be alterable: If the members of this great body,
the World, change, faint and grow old, it argues a creeping
decay to the whole: Let the Cormorant know
(that would build his neast heere for euer) that parts of
this land are alterable, therefore the whole not permanent.
If the Plague takes away men, the fields grow
barren; nay, the wearied earth (after much industry)
is dull in her fruits; like an vnnaturall Stepdame, she
produceth not good things of her selfe: if a Deluge
ouer-run vs, wee and our glory vanish: God hath more
meanes then one, to inflict his iudgements. It is with no
lesse admiration then trueth reported, that a whole field
in England, is turned in one moneth from a fertile
soyle, to a most Barren wast: It lyes from the danger of
innundation, from the reach of the hand of warre;
what then can turne it to a perpetuall barrennes? Thus,
God raiseth a mighty winde, that vncouers a mountaine
of sande, which ouerspreads the fruitfull valley to
a great thicknes; and it is made worse then Carmell,
which God thus threatens: I will turne L
                     •
                  banon into Carmell,

and Carmell into a Forest:
               Esay. it lyes in the power of
mans sins, to make God curse his very blessings.
            The Burden of Dumah is warre, Mount Seir feares it
not: if the booke of our hearts lay open to be read, I
thinke our feare of warre is lesse then theirs. God graunt
our presumption, our securitie be not as great: Wee sitte
vnder our owne Figge-trees, and eate the fruites of our owne
Vineyards: Our Children goe out by flockes and daunces, and
flourish like the Oliue branches round about our tables: Our
Oxen are strong to labour, our Sheepe bring foorth thousands
and ten thousands in our streets: There is no leading into captiuity,
no dashyng of our Children against the stones, no complayning
in our streetes. If this one blessing exceed not our
thankfulnesse for all, my obseruation is deceiued; but
what a bold inference is this? there is no warre, therefore
may be none, nor can we be ouerthrowne: It is a
speech as common as the stones in our streetes, when
consideration of warre is offred: Wee need feare no Enemies,
if we be true amongst our selues: Vaine security, that
is built vpon if's and and's: Who shall make vs true to
our selues, that haue beene false to God? Are there no
sonnes of Behal amongst vs, that curse the prosperitie of
Syon, and gape for the day, to cry Downe with it, downe
with it, euen to the ground? wee know they haue openly
and priuately with coate of Armour, and coate of
Maile, assaulted the peace of Ierusalem, but (praise to our
God) receiued shame in putting of their Harnesse: Let
this make vs thankefull, not secure; as if God could not
reach his arme ouer our narrow Seas: Behold France
made a Cock-pitte for massacres, by the vnciuill ciuill
warres thereof: Thinke of the vnquiet bread long eaten
in the Low-countries: and when thou sayest, wee lay
our heads on the Pillowes of peace, and eate the Bread
of plenty, kisse his hand with praises that feeds thee
with these blessings, but let not thy owne strength
make thee carelesse. The Papists thus re-hearten themselues

against all their ouerthrowes giuen them by this
litle Iland, that our time is not yet come, our sinnes are
not yet full: That Ignatian Sectarie Pererius so notes in
Gen. 15. The wickednesse of the Amorites is not yet full▪ &amp;c.
He giues it by way of Comment; but it is a false glosse,
I trust, and carryes no more trueth with it, then other
the fictions of Rome; his wordes are these: Let no man
wonder why God suffers the persecution of the Catholikes in
England, (the sinnes of the Amorites are not yet full) their
wickednesse is not yet compleat; when it is, the diuine reuenge
shall fall: They expected this day at the last change;
God changed their expectation to follie: and as it was
our griefe,Mira cano: sol occubuit, nox nulla secura est. that (Sol o
                     •
                  cubuit) our Sunne-set, so it is our
ioy, wonder, (Nox nulla secuta est) no night followed.
I hope his Prophecie is as false for the euent, as I am
sure his application is for the thing: wee are neither
those vncircumcised Amorites, vnchristened Pagans, nor
doe we persecute the Catholikes; except to haue libertie
of Law grow rich, purchase Lands, beard and braue
the Ministers of God to their faces, be called Persecution:
(Heere I cannot but mention, what is well obserued
by a most reuerend and honoured Iudge of this
land,L. Cooke. that) whereas haue been 300. burnt by Q. Mary
for Religion, there haue scarce 30. Papistes been executed
by Q. Elizabeth for Treason: yet, I hope, there is
some difference betwixt 300. and 30. Religion, and
Treason; betwixt the fiue yeares raigne of the one,
and the 44. of the other. I know their rebellions, treasons,
conspiracies, meete with execution, no persecution
to their Religion: Happy would our Martirs haue
thought themselues, if on such tearmes they might haue
redeemed their Consciences: no, the iniquities of Babel
haue filled vp their measure rather, and their iudgement
long agoe was not farre off, and their damnation sleepeth
not. Pererius is his owne Prophet against vs, we
speake not against them of our selues, the Holy ghost

speakes for vs, Who shall shortly consume that m
                     •
                  n of sinne
with the breath of his nost
                     ••
                  ls: Let their eyes stare for our
ouerthrowes, till they fall out of their vnfortunate
heades;Deut. 18. 32. God hath blessed, and the Balaam of Rome shall
neuer be able to curse: onely let not our zeale be wanting
to our God, to our Church, to our selues, and God
shall not be wanting to vs, nor all the hostes, which he
fightes with: and once againe, if need be, Coniurati venient
in classica ven
                     ••
                  ) the Windes and Seas shall take our
part: Let not our Peace make vs wanton, nor our
Wealth, proude; our helpe standes, in the name of God,
not in Fortes and Swordes.
            To speake more particularly, Bee not too confident
(who so euer) in thy Mount Seir; euery wicked soule
hath her Mount Seir to trust in: they that haue no assurance
of rest in Heauen, haue their Refuges and Mountaines
of helpe of Earth; Dauid so returnes it vpon the
wicked:Psal. 11. 1. 
               In the Lord put I my trust, how then say you to my
soule, flee as a Bird to your Mō
                  
                     •
                  taine. Why should I seeke to
forraine helpes, that haue setled my selfe in the bosome
of Rest it selfe? Riches are a Mount Seir to the Couetous,
they rest on them, as the Arke on the Mountaines
of Armenta: Honour is a Mount Seir to the Ambitious,
against all the beseeginges of riuals: Sensualitie to
the Voluptuous, against all the disturbances of a clamorous
Conscience: Pride, Fraude, Drunkennesse, is a
Mount Seir to the louers; but alas, how vnsafe? if stronger
against, and further remooued from the hand of
man, yet neerer to Gods hand in Heauen: though we
acknowledge no place (Procul a
                     ••
                  o
                     •
                  e, or, procul a fulmine)
farre from God, or from his thunder: But we say, it is
not safest sailing on the toppe of the Mast, to land on
the mountainous height of a temporall estate, is neither
wise nor happy: Men standing in the shade of humble
Valleys, looke vp and wonder at the height of Hilles,
and thinke it goodly liuing there, as Peter thought Tabor,
               
but when with weary limbes they haue ascended,Bonum est esse hic.
and finde the beames of the Sunne melting their spirites,
or the cold blastes of Winde making their Sinewes
starke, flashes of Lightning, or crackes of Thunder,
soonest endangering their aduanced heades, then
they confesse (decking their proud Conceit,) the low
valley is safest: for the fruitfull Deawes that fall first
on the Hilles, stay least while there, but runne downe
to the Valleyes: and though on such a promontorie a
man further sees, and is farther seene, yet in the Valley,
where he sees lesse, he enioyes more: Take heed then,
least to raise thy Mount Seir high, thou deiectest thy
soule low:Am. 6. 1. 
               Woe vnto them that are at ease in Zyon, and trust
in the Mountaines of Samaria: If we build our Houses by
Vnrighteousnesse, and our Chambers without 
                  •
               quitie,
though as strong as Mount Seir, they shall not be able
to stand in the Earth-quake of Iudgement: God so
threatens Iehoiakim:Ier. 22, 15. Shalt thou reigne because thou closest
thy selfe in Cedar? did not thy father eate and drinke and prosper,
when he executed iudgement and iustice. &amp;c. Thinke
not your Houses, Fortresses; when your Soules are vnarmed
of Christian weapons, Fayth and Obedience:
You had, and shall haue peace, whiles you pursue it
with righteous liues, whiles your guide all your actions
by the line of the Sanctuarie, and stirre your Attempts
by the compasse of the Gospell: Plentie shall spread
your Tables, whiles Charitie takes away, and giues to
the Poore. These holy courses, shall make you continue,
in despight of Hell and Rome; your Mountaine
shalbe hedged about with the Mercies of God, &amp; your
Children shall defie their Enemies in the Gates.
            The Person must not be omitted, to whom this scoffing
Question is mooued; The Watch-man. It seemes
the Prophet had denounced against Edom,
               Watchman, &amp; Vigilancie. Warre; they
deride his message, as a leafing, and his person vnder
the name of a Watch-man: nay, therefore they

scorne him, because a Watch-man. I will not insist on
the duties of Waich-men: euery common Souldier can
schoole the Watch-man: Many presume to teach vs
our duties, that will be ranged within no order themselues:
that which a Watch-man is to the Citie, or Centinell
to the Leagure; a Minister is to the People: to
Watch ouer your selues, is euery particular mans dutie;
to watch ouer all, (Opus Ministrj) is the worke of the
Ministry: If our Eyes be blinde in descrying Dangers,
our Tongues dumbe to giue Warning, the Citie or
Fort is easily taken:
                  
                     •
                  reg. Now, (Quam clamoris vocem daturus
est praeco mutus?) What warning shall a dumbe
Watch-man giue? Some will not speake, the Fountaine
of their knowledge is shut vp, like Labans Well, with a
great Stone of securitie, saturity, statelinesse: others
will speake too much, making the Pulpit a Pasquill, to
ease their spleenes, to traduce superiours: (Medio
tutissimus ibis) The meane and honest way, is the safest.
            But what say we to Vsurpers, Wolues, Tyrantes, that
call themselues Watch-men? that (Bi-nominis, bi-linguis)
Double-named, double-tongued, double-sworded; and
not single hearted. Demi-god of Rome, calles himselfe
sometimes a Watch-man, sometimes a King: the Seruant
of seruants, the King of Kinges: as if there was
no difference betwixt the seruiceable Watch-man, and
the commaunding Prince; betwixt the Centinell of
the Leagure, and the Generall of the Armie, (Ad duo
qui tendit, non vnum, nec duo prendit) Whiles he claimes
both, vsurpes one, trueth allowes him neither: His
actions shew him no Seruant, (F
                     •
                  riendo non ferendo agit,)
Hee giues blowes, but takes none. To be such a Watch-man
as he desires, possibility is denyed him, since his
eyes can not looke so farre, as hee would extend his
arme; not to watch ouer Rome onely, but so farre as the
world is Christned: Behold, sayth he, I haue two Swords;
               
one of them he lets rust, I meane, the sword of the Spirit:
the other, he keepes bright with the blood of Saints,
and makes it shine with the Gall of Martirs: (Principa
                  
                     •
                  is
principatus a triplici corona) the principall principalitie
is from the triple Crowne: As the Sunne exceedes the
Earth, so the Pope all Christian Princes; other Kinges
are but his Bayliffes. Did you euer heare a Watch-man
speake thus? or arrogate to himselfe such a reigne (In
foro pol
                     •
                  , in foro pluij, in foro conscient
                     •
                  ae) In the court of
Heauen, in the court of Hell, and in the court of euery
Conscience? If any resist his tyranny, he snacheth from
Christ that his Word,Luk. 19. 27. and vsurpes it: Bring those mine
enemies, that would not haue mereigne ouer them, and slay them
before me: If he can not behold it in action, he will see it
in picture, as the massacre of Paris on S. Bartholomewes
night, was pictured in the Popes Pallace, to entertaine
his holy eye with pleasure: so would the Powder-treason
haue been, if the matter had hit right: as horred,
as the thought of it is to an honest minde, the hoysting
vp of Buildinges, shiuering of Bodyes, tearing vp of
Monuments, dissipation, massacre, murder of olde,
young, Prince people, Senators and Senate, drawne to
the life by the art of a Painter, would haue been a contenting
spectacle, for so holy an eye to contemplate:
sure there is honesty in Hell, if this be Religion: if the
Deuill can deuise more execrable stratagems, let him
change Seates with the Pope. Christ medled with neither
Herod, nor Emperour, King nor Cesar; no Emperours
held his Stirrop, no Kings kissed his blessed feete;
hee onely fought with the weapons of the Spirit against
Sinne and Satan. This is a Watch-man indeed;
but he watcheth to inuade, beseidge, enter and spoyle
the Citie of God: hee liath other Watch-men vnder
him, Vncleane birdes, fluttring from that Vulture of
Babilon, and flying like Battes and Owles vnder the
eues of night, to vomite the poysons of Heresie and

Treasons from their swolne gorges: Watch-men like
the Chaplens of Mars at Rome in the dayes of Idolatry,
that practised to tosse Fire-brandes from Campe to
Campe, to inflame euill affections; that care not whose
blood they sacrifice to their Romane God, without distinction
of Troian, of Tyrian: nor out of whose Sepulchers
they digge themselues an estate: They watch indeed,
for they keepe a Register of all our proceedinges
against them, in these ltaleyon dayes of ours; and if euer
the S
                  •
               nne of Alteration shine on their faces, they will
repay vs tenne blowes for one vpon our Burgonets:
meane time (our Prayses to Heauen) they watch their
owne bane: and (as one writes of Parry,) so I may of
the end of them all (Itala gens sceleri te dedit, Angla cru
                     ••
                  )
Italy giues them their villanie, England their Gallowes;
this is (their malus, but meritus sinis) the euill, but deserued
end of them all: England is sinfull enough, but she
professeth not her selfe a Schoole-mistris of Sinne,This their Chamber of meditation doth testify. as
Rome doth of Treason: there it is professed, taught, learned,
and (as on the sandy Theator) exercised before it
come to the fatall execution.
            The Priestes of peruerted Israel,
               Hos. 6. 9. were but shadows of
these of apostate Rome: As Theeues waite for a man, so the
company of Priestes murder in the way by consent. Hence that
Prouerbe carryes no lesse trueth, then antiquitie with
it: An Englishman Italianate, is a Deuill incarnate: these
are those Iesuites, Iebusites, Incendiaries, Traytors, and
not lesse then Deuils, but that they haue bodyes. God
blesse vs from such Watch-men: if these be Watch-men,
who are enemies?
            We see then the vanitie of their laboures, that would
vndertake to bring vs to a composition: if Heresie can
be made Sinceritie, Idolatrie true Religion, Treason
Obedience, we may be vnited: but it is a sure rule,
Contraries in the abstract, can neuer be reconciled:
God put an vn-appeasable Contention betwixt the

two Seedes of the Woman, and Serpent, when hee put
Enmity betweene them▪ for an Enemy may be made a
Friend, but Enmitie can neuer be made Frendship: the
Ayre that is darke, may be made Light; but Darknesse
cannot be made Brightnesse; a Papist may be conuerted
to a Christian, but Papistry can neuer be made
Christianitie, no more then Antichrist can become
Christ: our strife with them is not for the extention of
Limits, but for the possession of the Inheritaunce, whether
Grace or Nature, the Popes Law or Gods, shall
take place in the Conscience: So I haue read of that
audacious and sottish Hermite, that would vndertake,
to make God and the Deuill friendes: the impossibilitie
of which attempt, the Deuill could tell him; God is
all Light, and I am all Darknesse, that my foule nature
can not be hidden: our affections, seates, persons, are
so opposed, that I haue no hope of peace. They will
not, we may not yeeld; except the Sheepe shall compound
with the Wolfe, or the Mise with the Catte;
which the old tale forbids, though the Catte gette on a
Monks Cowle, &amp; cries demurely through the creuices,
Quod fueram, non suw, fra
                     •
                  er, caput aspice tonsum.
               
                  Good broth
                        •
                     r Mouse, creepe out thy house, come foorth, &amp; let vs chat:
                  Behold my Crowne is shauen downe, I'm now a Priest, 
                        •
                     o Cat.
                  When Cats say Masse, the Myse (alas) must pray against their will:
                  Kind Pus
                        •
                     e, your pate is smoth of late, your heart is rugged s
                        ••
                     ll.
               
            
            Experience would teach vs the answere of the verse,
though we had neuer read it.
            V
                  •
               x ti
                  •
               i 
                  •
               raesto fidem, cor tibi restat id
                  •
               m.
            To leaue the incorrigible Watch-men of Rome, since
we would haue cured Babel, and she would not be cured,
let vs looke home to our selues. The Wolues of
Rome haue not more honour, then the Watch-men of
England scorne: the Edomites of the world can not abide
Ministers:Heb▪ 1
                     •
                  . the best is, they are but Edemites, heires of

               Esau, and as prophane as their Father; that make Religion
their Minstrell, to giue them sport and sleepe, no
iest in such laughter, as that which is broken on a Priest;
the proofe is plaine on euery Tauerne and Theater.
We serue indeed contrary Maisters; wee Christ, they
Lust and Sathan: and (Hinc illae rixae of theirs, hinc illae laechrimae
of ours,) hence their flowts, &amp; our teares: we bite
them with the salt of Reproofe, hence they storme: we
cast Incke and Gall on their Tetters, hence they startle:
(Veritatem lucentem multi diligunt, arguentem reijciunt:
dum s
                     •
                   ostendit columus, dum nos ostendit, odio
habemus:) The trueth shining▪ many loue; reprouing,
they reiect: whiles it shewes it selfe, we imbrace it;
whiles it shewes vs, we can not endure it: euen in this
consistes at once, our Happinesse, their Damnation:
our Happinesse, Blessed are yee, when for me porsecuted:
their Damnation, That Light being in the world, they
imbrace and are gladde of Darknesse: though their
wronges done vs, be against the Law of Armes and
Nature; for an Ambassadour should be (Inter hostium
tela incolumis) safe among the Weapons of the Enemies:
            But doe the Edomites onely take up these Weapons
of scorne against vs? No, I speake it betwixt shame
and griefe, euen the Israelites scorne the Prophets. There
are some sicke of a wantonnes in Religion, so hot about
the question, De modo, that the Deuill steales the matter
of Religion from their heartes: if we cannot wrangle
with Formes and Shadowes, and shew our selues
refractarie to established Orders, we shall, Malè audire,
our Sermons shall be slighted, our persons derided:
thus, this is the mischiefe; men of name, professors of
note, when they speake bitterly of vs, their credite
carries it strong with our scandals: one Arrow of these
Israelites, wounds deeper then a hundred Cannon-shot

of the Edomites: I confesse I speake Stones, but if they
hitte, as they are intended, they shall heale some, hurt
none: (Dicatur veritas, rumpatur inuidia) Let Trueth be
spoken, and Enuie burst her Gall: let all these Scorners
remember, that the contempt done to vs, redowndes to
God himselfe: Hee that despiseth vs, despiseth men: hee that
Christ, despiseth his Sauiour: Is all this nothing? But hee
that d
                     •
                  spiseth mee and you, despiseth him thot sent mee and you:
It comes to somewhat then, and more then euer mortall
man shalbe able to answere; is it not enough for them,
that they haue drawne out the life-blood of our Liuinges,
but they must expose our persons to contempt?
So the Iewes spoyled Christ of his Vestmentes, and then
mocked him with basenesse. Our pouertie of flouted
by them that haue our Liuinges: surely, if repentance
and restitution preuent it not, they shall haue a Tith
one day, which they haue more right to, the tenth
Sheafe of that Haruest, which is reserued for Reprobates
in Hell. The Turkes lay it is an imputation on
our Religion, that we spoyle our Gods: for shame, doe
not the Turkes, and shall the Christians? Dauid would
not haue Areunah's Threshing-floore without money;
if these men should haue no roome in the Church, but
what they pay for, I thinke they would quietly suffer
themselues to be turned foorth of dores.
            The last branch of the Mappe, and first of the Morall,
are not vnfitly conioyned, the Edomite, and his
Question:Edomite, and Question. the Question then calles mee from the
Watch-man, What is in the nigh
                     •
                  ? And to make the Derision
fuller and fowler, it is doubled, like Phara
                     •
                  hs
Dreame, What is in the night? Did they seeke for some
prodegie or portent? Some diuine Reuelation, which
should be receiued by Vision? Were the like Israel, of
whom Christ thus testifies; This adulterous generation
seekes for a Signe?
               Math. 12. 39. Thus Diues despayred of his brethrens
beliefe, except one rose from the dead. I confesse wee

haue some in the world sicke of this disease, a Iewish
infection, The Iewes require a signe, &amp;c. (Plus ocu
                     •
                  o, quam
oraculo:)
               1. Cor. 1. 22. miseries shall worke more on them then misteries:
palpable actions of Gods mercie, iustice, power,
shall conuince them, the contemplation of them all
in the theory of the word mooues them not: astonish
them with wonders,S. Thomas, vnles he felt. heale their diseased, open their
blinde eyes, raise their dead, and they will beleeue: Are
there none among vs, that couch a willing &amp; close eare
to the charmes of Rome, in admiration of their feigned
miracles? lying Apostles, that worke strange things by
exorcismes? but our Church now is not in the Cradle of
her infancie: One cuppe of wine brought by Christ,
is worth all the cuppes of cold water by Moses:
as S. Augustine alluding to that Marriage in Galile, sayes:
All the adumbrations, tipes, figures, signes, were but that
cuppe of cold Water,Ioh. 2. Christ reserued the good Wine (of the
Gospell) till he came him selfe: and they that will not beleeue
without a Signe, without a Signe must perish.
But I trauell no further in this, least it bring me out of
my way.
            It was no Signe they inquire for, no Prodegie they
feare; they are onely pleased to make sport with the
menaces of God: You talke of a Night, and an houre
of Calamitie; but threatned men draw long breathes:
You pretend Visions in the night, which portend our
ruines; come tell vs the tale of the night: What is in
the night? There haue been in all ages, some of these
Frogges, to throate it out against God, so long as the
weather was faire, as if he could not send a storme: the
tempestes of Gods Wrath haue been derided to the last
moment of a calme: the venime of Prosperitie so impoysons
a carnall minde, (Eilia diuitiarum superbia) the
daughter of Riches is Pride: the Philosopher could
teach vs that (Faelicitas &amp; humillitas diuiduum haebent

contubrinium: raro bona mens &amp; bona fortuna homini
datur,) Happinesse and Humblenesse are not chamber-fellows:
seldome a good Minde, and a good Estate,
is giuen to the same man: God seemed to mistrust this
in Israel, that the increasing of Goodes, and multiplying
of Cattle,Deut. 8. 13. 14. would lift vp their heartes against him:
The peaceable dayes of the Wicked, and their lucky
proceedinges in this world (by the testimony of Iob,)
durageth their impudence against Heauen:Iob. 21. 15. 
               Who is
the Almighty, that we should serue him? depart from
vs, wee will none of thy wayes. That of the Psalme is of
full strength to this:Psal. 10. 5. 
               His wayes prosper: thy iudgements
are farre aboue out of his sight: therefore defyeth he all
his enemies: Man onely? no, God himselfe: I shall
neuer be mooued.
               Mal. 3. 14. Let Malachi for all the Prophets,
Peter for all the Apostles, make vp this cloude of witnesses:
It is in vaine to serue the Lord:2. Pet. 3. 4. and where is
the promise of his comming? All thinges are still (Statu
quo) continued in the same course: there is no alteration,
no new thing done (Quaecun
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   sub axe) vnder Heauen.
We say, (Non bonum ludere cum sanctis) it is no safe
iesting with holy thinges: It is dangerous for an Edomite
to make himselfe merry with God; this is the way
to come short home: thou hadst better haue mourned
all thy life, then made God thy play-fellow. When the
vessell of Dust shall encounter with the arme of Omnipotence
(Siue percutiat,Imus gradus &amp; Limen 
                        •
                     nferni. siue percutiatur, frangi necesse est)
whether it smite, or be smitten, it is sure to be broken:
The Chayre of the Scorner, is the seate of Sathan, the
lowest staire and very threshold of Hell, as Dauid describes
it:Psal. 1. 1. 
               Blessed is the man that doth not walke, &amp;c. His
first plot is, to get vs, to walke a turne or two with him:
hauing perswaded this, he moues vs to stand still a litle;
but so long as we are standing, we are going, therefore
at last he intreates vs (for our ease) to sitte downe: but

if we take our seate in that inchaunted Chaire, we grow
to that impudence to deride God, and his iudgements.
I will single you out foure fortes of these Edomites,
Scorners (for I iustly paralell them) and propound
their natures and conditions to your pitty and detestation.
            1 Atheistes, such as haue voluntarily, violently, extinguished
to themselues, the Sun-light of the Scripture,
Moone-light of the Creature; nay, the sparkes and
cinders of Nature, that the more securely (as vnseene
and vnchidden of their owne heartes) they might prodigally
act the workes of darknesse; not Athenian-like,
dedicating an Altar to an vnknowne God, but annihilating
to themselues, and vili-pending to others, Altar,
Religion, God; and suffocating the breath of all Motions,
Argumentes, manifest Conuictions, that heauen &amp;
earth haue produced: for the reasons of Hell onely
shall one day euince it (Deum esse) that there is a God:
they affirme it impossible, that flesh should be turned
to rottennesse, rottennesse to dust, and dust to glorie:
Against whom,Qui potuit formare nouum, non poterit reparare mortuū? Facilior est restitutio constitutione. Sect. 9. 4. well, S. Augustine; He that could forme
vs of nothing, can reforme vs decayed: it is easier to
repaire, then prepare. That Atheisme in the dayes of
Salomon was the same in opinion, that ours is in practise:
we doe (not say but) liue, as if it was better to a liuing
Dogge, then a dead Lyon: which I would yeeld true among
Beastes; but among men, a dead Beast is better
then a lyuing Atheist: let them aske Nature, it will tell
them, (Insculptum est omnibus esse deum) It is ingrauen in
all hearts, that there is a Deitie: let them aske the Creatures,
they will witnesse, they had a Creator: nay, let
the Deuill speake, to shame and conuince the Atheist,
who beleeues a God, and trembles at his owne beliefe:
the nature of his essence prooueth it:Qui negat esse deum, mihi negat et tibi, non sibi. &amp;c. to know there is
a Witch, may satisfie vs, that there is a God; for if the
destroying power were not controuled, manacled,

maistred,Oculos, quos culpa clausit, paena aper
                     •
                  et. how stand we vndeuowred? Let them aske
(lastly) their owne dying hearts; for the eyes that sinne
hath shut, Damnation shall open.
            2 Epicures, that deny not a God, and a day of Iudgement;Amos. 6. 3.
but put it farre off, with (
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ) giue
me the present, take thou the hope of future ioyes: these
see a night comming, and therefore make haste to be
drunke with Pleasures: Let vs eate and drinke, for to merrow
we shall die:1. Cor. 15. (Cras ridendo moriuntur, hodiè bibendo sepeliuntur) they will not die till to morrow, but be buried
in Riot to day. They sleepe on their Beddes of Downe,
rise to their Tables of Surfet, and from thence to their
sportes of Mischiefe; sleeping, playing, eating, dauncing,
drinking, dallying, (Motu circu
                     ••
                  rj) they runne
round in a Ring: onely (Nulla interualla piando) no time
must be spared from Sathan: they inuert the Order
God hath disposed to the times preposterously, makeing
the night day, and the day night; at midnight they
reuell, at noone they sleepe: though the day was created
for labour, the night for repose: The Sunne is
scarce beholding to their eyes to looke vpon him: the
Moone and Starres haue (onely) their attendance; the
workes and the houre of darknesse meete; they will be
contrary to all men and all thinges but themselues, because
they will be contrary. If euer they begin any
worke with the day, they dispose it on this fashion;
First, they visit the Tauerne, then the Ordinarie, then
the Theater, and end in the Stewes: from Wine to Ryot,
from that to Playes, from them to Harlots,
Iste dies pulchro distinguitur ordine rerum.
Here is a day spent in an excellent methode: If they
were Beasts, they could not better sensualize, it would
be but lost labour to tell them, that their course shall be
so proportioned below: from Snakes they shall turne
vpon Adders, from both to Scorpions, from all to vnquenched
flames; where they shall spend not houres

but ages, nay that eternity of time, in waylinges and
howlinges, grones and torments; when for euery ounce
of Vanitie, they shall receiue (downe weight) a whole
pound of Sorrow: Smoakes, blacknes, boyling Cauldrons,
fierie burninges of Brimstone &amp; Sulphure, kindled
and continued by the breath of an offended God,
shall haue their interchanged courses: oft this torment,
and then that, and indeed all, that a soule &amp; body made
immortall, can suffer:
Iste dies misero distinguitur ordine rerum.
Heere is a day to be spent in a miserable methode: Oh
how (yet) was it some happines, if in a day or set time,
these woes could be determined: these are the Epicures,
not so impudent as to deny the night, not so honest
as to part with their sinnes.
            3 Libertines, that neither affirme no Night, nor put
it farre off; but onely the strength of sinne preuailes
ouer all: and come Sorrow, Death, Graue, Hell, they
must haue their pleasures:Video meliora probo
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  , deteriora sequor, metam. they haue a pride in accomcomplishing
their owne willes, as shee in the Poet;

                  I see the good, and giue allowance to it:
                  The euill is my choyce, I loue and doe it.
               
They can not be noted for Vertuous; but they will be
Famous, though for Infamie: as that wicked Church-robber,
that to doe some memorable act, pulled all the
Lead off the Churches roofe, and thacked it: they must
be mentioned, though like a Traytors name in the
Chronicles. These sweare away all reproofes, &amp; drinke
away all the chidings of their owne Conscience: it shal
be the worse for them, that euer they had a conscience:
their Hell shalbe the hotter for the multitude of their
neglected motions to good: their Mercies haue not bin
more numerous, then shall be their Miseries: their
Nurture or Learning (to omit those, that neuer read
any other Booke then Vanitie) at once makes them
better and worse; better in vnderstanding, worse in

manners; whiles their contemplation is a Theater, and
their study, new sportes, new fashions: Oh how farre
better is the simple, honest, innocent Soule without
knowledge, then that which is beautified with learning
and debauched with vices?
            
               Beatus ille qui procul negotijs,Horace.
               
               Paterna rura bobus exercet suis.
            
            More happy are those poore wretches confined and
contented with a rurall charge: whiles they know not
so much of good, they know lesse of ill: they skill not
what the studying of oathes, the trickes of pride, the
pollicie of Atheisme meanes: they make not sense the
rule of their beleefe with the Gallant, but their Catechisme:
Religion is their Queene, the Gallants drudge:
they haue not so much of reason, therefore abuse the
lesse: their sinnes proceed most from ignorance, the
Gallants from knowing wilfulnesse: Now, which of
these shall be beaten with most stripes? they worke out
a poore lyuing with the sweate of their browes and
nerues, these can play out a rich one from the quicknes
of their wittes: they know not the detractions of slaunder,
vnderminings of enuy, prouocations, heates, enluringes
of lustes: the foule secrecyes of Idolatry,
hypocracy, sacriledge, cleaue not to their consciences:
they haue a kinde of happinesse, in that they are not so
miserable: our impudent, imprudent, insolent Youngsters
looke on these, betwixt contempt and anger, call
them Clownes, Ideots, and the dregges of Nature, and
thinke themselues Angells, if these be men; (Quorum
prae
                     •
                   crdia Titan de priore luto sinxit) as if God had tempered
them of a baser mould. But whiles Acteons Bondslaue
grindes securely (though laboriously) at the Mill,Hart. Hounds.
his braue riotous, gallant, Hunting-maister is turned to
a beast, and for his sensuallity eaten vp of his owne
lusts: you all know the Storie, this is the Morall. Thus,
this is the proper cause, that the auncient Houses fall;

and what the long Industry of the progenitors haue
gotten, the short Ryot of the Gallant, wastes: Wee are
loth to heare of this; but it is too true, hee needes not
drinke vp all the Sea, that will iudge of the 
                  •
               aste: hence
young gentlemen by wilde vnthriftines become sports
to Theators, and cannot sitte on their Fathers seates to
doe good in the Common-wealth: they abounde with
the guiftes of Nature, but like Fig-trees growing ouer
deepe Waters, full of Fruite, but the Iayes eate them:
Ruffians, Harlots, vicious Companions enioy those
Graces, that might honour God.
            4 Common Prophane persons, that will suffer
themselues to weare Gods Liuery, though they serue
the Deuill: these are they, that make the profession of
the Gospell haue an euill name: hence that Prouerbe,
Pater noster, set vp Churches, Our Father, pulles them
downe. I will not fauour (with a partiall conuiuence)
these Scorners, though they nussell themselues in the
Churches bosome: nay, I will speake most plainely;
these are the worst Edomites, if not to them selues, to vs.
Let the Atheist deny, the Epicure remoue, the Libertine
forget, that there is any other Day of peace or sorrow,
besides or beyond the present; what is this to beleeuers?
Wee are reedy to brand and howte at them (as
they did to the Lepers in Israel,) nay to raine them to
death with a showre of Stones, (as they serued Idolaters
and Blasphemers:) But be our owne handes vndefiled,
that take vp these weapons of Death against others,
as Christ charged the Iewes, that charged the adulterous
Woman? If we be sicke, our sicknesse is more
dangerous then theirs:Interius, &amp; in cute malum. The other Diseases are without
the body, but this comes neere
                  •
                the heart of the
Church: we know what it is, to haue a Sicknesse come
neere the heart: there is more griefe to the Mother of
the Familie, in the miscarying of one of the Children,
then of many Strangers, Edomites, vnbeleeuers, or misbeleeuers:

these haue learned to speake the language,
to scorne the manners of Canaan; for, their liues testifie,
that they beleeue not our report.
            We haue gone the better halfe of our Iourney,The Answere. let not
your attentions fayle to the end: Wee haue seene the
nature of Edom, and Mount Seir, Atheisme, Scorne,
Abhomination; wee are now entring an other Mountaine,
the Hill of Syon, the Citie of God. The Question
of the Edomite was not more peruerse, then the Answere
of the Watch-man is graue and sober. The Answers of
God are not doubtfull, like the Heathen Oracles; nor
obscure and tetricall, as Mahomets Riddles; nor ambiguous,
like the mixt, the motley, epicaene, equiuocating
conclusions of Rome, but plaine, sweete, profitable: I
call therefore the first part of it,The Resolution. 
               A Resolution: They aske
as if they despised to know; hee resolues them iustly, as
if he would force them to know against their willes.
They aske him what is spiritually seene in the night of
Vision? He tels them, what shall really come in the
night of actuall Desolation: The Morning commeth, and
also the Night, Let your vnderstandinges keepe pace
with me through these 4. Circumstances. 1. The length
of their Peace;Finitum pro indefinito, breuitatem temporis, dies exprimit. one whole day, the space betwixt morning
and euening: a short time. 2. The Certaintie of
their Iudgement; The night (infallibly) commeth. 3. The
qualitie of it, when it is come; (Nox dicitur) it is
called, a Night. 4. The Inuersion of this, to the Righteous.
            1. The Happinesse of Edom is but a Day; The Morning
comes, and the Night followes: It is but the distaunce
of the Sun-rising from his setting. There is to
all thinges liuing, such an alternation decreed; a morne,
a noone, a night: a beginning, a stronge age, a declination
or full poynt: as the Historians write of certaine
Flyes bred by the Riuer Hispanis, that are generated in
the morning, at noone in full strength, at night make

their endes, and are gone: Paul sayes, Our life is but a
Tabernacle, it is all, if this standes a yeare: Esay calles it,
Grasse; which growes but a Summer: Dauid, a Flower;
that hath but his moneth: heere it is called, a Day; that
hath but the Sun-rising and setting: Nay, Iob compares
it to a Shadow; that hath (neither Yeare, nor Summer,
nor Moneth, nor Day,) but an Hower: Nay, Moses to a
Thought; whereof there may be a hundred in an hower:
This is none of the shortest Comparisons, (Manè et vespèrè)
the measure of one day.
            What then meane those Greedy Dogges in this Prophecie,Esay. 56. 12.
to barke so madly, Bring more Wine, for to morrow
shall be as to day, yea, much more abundant. Mee thinkes, I
heare the gallant Epicures (the christned Atheistes) of
this Citie, knocke thus in Tauerns, for yet more Wine,
crowning the day with Riots, and blessing the morrow
with promised Surfets, as if the Night should neuer
come: alas (Nescis quid serus vesper ferat) thou knowest
not what sadde newes the Euening will bring: thou
braggest with Cesar, the Day is come; Wee tell thee, as
Cesars friend, It is come indeed and begun; it is not ended:
the Lease of Vanitie, is but a Day; it may be not
a moment, the tenure of this world is vncertaine.
Medio de fonte leporum, surgit amari aliquid:
From out of the midst of the fount of Delicacies, ariseth
euer some Bitternesse: when you haue spent your
strengthes, your estates, bloodes, soules, vpon Vanitie,
all is but (Vnius diej hilaris insanta) the merry madnesse
of a day;Non semper sequuntur viuentem, mori entem nunquam. which to buy with the eternitie of insufferable
Torments, is a deare purchase: If they be not short
of content and satisfaction, I am sure, they are of continuance:
They do not alwaies follow a man lyuing,
euer forsake him when he dyes.
            2 You haue measured the shortnesse of their day,
heare the certainetie of their night: The morning comes,
and (without preuention) night followes. You shall shake

off the yoake of Israell, but put on you the yoake of
Persia: The Edomites were long tributaries to Israell, according
to Ishae's prophecie and blessing of Esau. Thou
shalt be thy Brothers Seruant;Gen. 27. 40. but it shall come to passe, when
thou shalt get the masterie, thou shalt breake his yoake from thy
necke: The Prophet heere assures them of this masterie.
(Israell rebells against God, therefore Edome against
Israell.) Ishae as Gods Prophet, subiects Edom to Canaan,
the seede of Esau to the seede of Iacob:Ambr. (Intemperanti praefecit
sobrium) he sets the sober man ouer the intemperate:
and this seruice of the elder Brother to the younger, lasted
in the posterity 700 yeares. Yet twice after, they
shooke off this seruitude: the first in Iorams time, which
libertie they made a troublesome shift to hold till Hircanus,
               2. King. 8. 20.
who subdued them, and made them be circumcised:
this slauery they ouercame againe, and held it, euen
till Herod,
               Ioseph. the sonne of Antipater, an Idumaean borne,
obtayned to be King of the Iewes: heere Edom got the
full mastrie. The first, was this Morning the Prophet
speakes of; this Morning of freedome shall come, but
last for a Day, and then be ouerclouded with a Night, a
worse Captiuitie, because to a worse people, (Qui Deum
et misericordi
                     •
                  m nesciunt) that know neither God,
nor Mercie: as those priuations are inseperable, there is
no Mercie, where no Religion.
            
               Edom is but a particular instance of a generall doome,
which all the Sonnes of Adam, as the Daughters of
E
                     •
                  e, I meane, all the Glories of this World shall beare;
as sure as the Euening succeedes the Morning, Death
shall seaze on Life, Iudgement on Sinne: you haue the
sappe of Health in your Bones, the Riches of the world
in your Coffers, your Life is in the Noone of pride, but
(we say) prayse a faire day at Night. (Happy are they,
whose life is hid with Christ in God, that this Night may
not finde them out:)Col. 3. 3. your Sunne shall set, Beautie, Riches,
Glory, shall decay, as by the inuiolable law of

Nature, night succeedes day; so by the eternall law of
God, Death Sinne. If you could indent with the Sunne
to stand still,Iosh. 10. 1
                     •
                  . as in the dayes of Ioshua; or to goe backe
ten degrees, as to Hezekiah; or with his Orbe to mooue
slowly, yet it shall sette: Be the day neuer so long, yet
at last, comes euening-song. The Sonne of God himselfe,
in this condition of mortall descent, was equall to
his Breathren. That great Sunne of Righteousnesse,
had his rising and his setting: Wee must all walke into
the West, as well as he; and be our Day longer or shorter,
Night must come, our Priuiledges are not beyonde
others.
            Heare this yee Edomites, that floute our presagings
of a Night: you speake of a Night, and houre of Iudgement;
When comes it? We tell you againe, The Morning
commeth, and also the Night. You haue had a time of
Light and delight, and what your heartes could wish;
you shall haue a time of Sorrow and Darknesse: Your
Noone shall be turned to Midnight. Tender and delicate
Babilon,
               Esay. 47. 7. that boasted her selfe a Queene, and free
from mourning, shall weepe in the wydow-hood of her
glory; and heare at last, (Aduenit sinis tuus,) thy end is
come.ver. 9. 
               You that will not set your mindes to these thinges, nor
remember the latter end, miseries shall come on you in their perfection:
so absolute as the Iustice of God, &amp; the Malice of
Sathan can make them. So Salomon schooles the art-les,
heart-les, supine courses of vaine Youth: Reioyce, O
Youngman, &amp;c.
               Eccl. 1
                     •
                  . 9. Reioyce in your day of Pride, let Pleasure
rocke you on her indulgent knee, you shall be
brought to the night of Iudgement: The Surfets of the
old World, the Mirth of the Philistins, (when Sampson
was their laughing stocke) the carowsinges of that
Caldean Monarch in the sacred Bowles of Ierusalem, had
their Night: Salomon with his 1000. Wiues and Concubines, Belshazzar with his 1000. Princes, Ahashiuerosh
with his 127. Prouinces, had their Night: High-looked

Honour, and pursie Riches; the one diseased in his
Eyes, the other in his Lunges, shall haue their Night:
The fauour of Noble men, is the fauour of moueable
men;Fauor nobilium, fauor mobilium. the Ignis fatuus of Riches is long ingendring,
soone extinct: let Ioab and Iob, be our precedentes in
both these: the first, was great and euill, the chiefest
Captaine about Dauid; yet by Dauid designed to execution;
The second was great and good; yet behold,
the mightiest man of the East,As poore as Iob. is poore to a Prouerbe:
What euer florished and had not this night? The rich
Churle enlarging his Barnes proportionably to his desires,Hiatu laborantes.
had his Night; hee heard that soule knell, Thou
foole, this Night, shall they fetch away thy soule. The World
it selfe shall haue this Euening: the Morning was in
the dayes of the Patriarches; Christ boore the heate and
Noone of the day, and wee are those vpon Whom the
latter endes of the world are come. The World groweth old, and
we grow old with it:2. Esd. 14. 9. the bodyes of men in old age,
waxe cold and want the heate of Nature; the soules of
men in this decrepite age, grow cold in zeale, (Deficiente
feruore charitatis) the nourishment of old age turnes into
cruditie, through want of heate to concoct, digest,
and driue it into the Vaines; the nourishment of our
soules turnes into Vanitie, because we want the heate
of Grace to digest it: By all these symptones, you see
the Sunne of this World ready to sette, and the Night
drawing on: the declination of Goodnes, the fainting
of Religion, sayes, that the World lyes bedrid, drawing
on, looking for the good houre (to some,) and fetching
a thicke, sicke and short breath: I am no Prophet (or
what if I were, yet vnable) to define the time: but this
I conclude (though more particularly) from the rule of
my text; Wee had our Morning at the first preaching of the
Gospell: it now flourisheth with vs, as at high Noone; Who
shall say, the Euening will not follow, or our Sunne is without
setting.
            
            
               3 That it shall come, you heare; heare shortly the
qualitie of it, when it is come: A Night. Miserie is not
fitlyer shadowed, then vnder the name of a Night:
Sorrow lastes for a Night, sayes the Psalmist, but ioy comes in
the Morning. A sadde, heauie, and disconsolate time, full
of horrour and amazement; when there is no obiect
to withdraw the eye, thereby to diuert the minde from
the thought and meditation of bitternesse. Sathan himselfe
is not sayd to be bound with any other Chaines
but these of Darknesse: as the Ioyes of Heauen are described
by that eternall daylight of glory and Sunshine
of the Lambe,Reuel. 
                     •
                  1. and it is added in expresse wordes;
There shall be no Night there: So the tormentes of Hell
are called by Christ,Mat. 8. 1
                     •
                  . 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , Vtter Darknesse:
No maruell, if there ensue, weeping and gnashing of
teeth, when miserie shalbe extreame, and no day-hole
of hope, to afford one glimpse of comfort: this is that
Night of nightes,
               Nox noctium. Io
                     •
                  l. 2. 2. worse then the palpable Darknesse of
Egipt, as full of intollerable horrour, as Caliginous blacknesse:
I find not onely the time of Iudgement generall,
but of temporall and particular calamities, tearmed by
the Night of horrour: the downefall of Dumah, a Night:
the destruction of Israel, A season of blacknesse, darknesse,
cloudes and obscurities. Therefore (as Christ to the Iewes,
Pray that your flight be not in the Night,) pray that your
departure out of this life, be not in the Night of your
securitie and ignorance; and then feare not this Night,
for you are redeemed from the land of eternall Darkenesse.
            
               Caligula (in im ta
                     •
                  on of Zerxes, that passed his Armie ouer the streight of Hellespont vpō a wooden bridge) vpon ships moared together with Cables &amp; Anchors, made a bridge of boords, with so much earth on it, that it seemed firme ground, like one of the streetes in Rome. Dion. It was the foolish pride of that Romane Emperour,
hauing made a Bridge of grappled Ships ouer a narrow
Arme of the Sea, and triumphing at midnight with innumerable
torches, to boast that he had (wrough two
Miracles,) made the Sea dry Land, and the Night Day:
but our Emperour of Heauen and Earth, did performe
it indeed, when he dryed vp the Redde sea of his Fathers

wrath, and changed our present Night of Ignonaunce,
and future of torment, into the eternall daylight
of his Grace and Glory.
            4 The last part to this Suruey, is the inuerting of
this vpon the Righteous: Where, behold the different
beginnings and endes of both Holy, and Vnholy: to
the children of Disobedience, the Morning is before
the Euening; and this is Dumahs woe at Sun-set (Fuisse
faelicem) that she had her Day: To the Faythfull, the
Euening is before the Morning; as at the Creation, The
Euening and the Morning were the first day.
               Gen. 1. The Iewes were
commaunded to begin their Feast of Reconciliation at
Euen;Leuit. 23. 32. and, From Euening to Euening, shall you celebrate your
Sabboth. It was Christes comfortable Answere to his
Church, intending the date when the prophanation of
the Temple should cease, to set the Morning of their
peace, after the Euening of their troubles, by a sweete
and mysticall allusion: Vnto the Euening, and the Morning,
               Dan. 8. 14.
               two thousand, and three hundred: then shall the
Sanctuarie be clensed: and the vision of the Euening
and the Morning is true:
               ver. 26. The Euening of their sorrow
precedes the Morning of their ioyes. Our Prophet so
compares the tempest of the Assirians rage, to a Storme
in the Night, which vanisheth at the rysing Sunne:
Loe,Esay. 17. 14. in the Euening there is trouble, but before the
Morning it is gone. Our Night lastes during this wretched
life: the troubles of Miseries, stormes of Persecutions,
and rage of that great Leutathan, disturbes our
Ayre,Per varios casus, per tot discrimina rerum, tendimus in caelum. darkens our Day, and makes it a gloomy Night;
cloudes, tempestes, obstacles, stumbling-blockes, temptations,
machinations of Enemies, deceiuinges of
Friends, through so many dangers and difficulties sayle
we to our hauen of Peace: our assuraunce is, that ioy
comes in the Morning, when we shall rise in the East,
and beholde the Sonne of Glory shine in our faces.

The Morning of the Edomites, Atheistes, Reprobates,
comes first smiling on their browes; but (Nox sequitur)
they haue a Night behind.
            This disparitie consistes not onely in the counterposition
of their order, but in the circumstantiall difference
of their length and shortnesse: Our Night is irkesome,
but short; (Compensatur acerbitas breuitate) What
is ill in the bitternesse, is eased by the shortnesse: But
our Day is euerlasting, from new Moone to new
Moone, from Saboth to Saboth, wee shall prayse the
Lord: Myriades of yeares and ages, shalbe expired,
and our Sunne as farre from setting, as at our first entrance;
for time and mortalitie, and distinction of age,
shall cease: there is nothing but eternitie aboue: It is
not more blessed in being a Day, then in being endlesse:
Their Morning is short, their Night euerlasting, their
Debt never p
                  •
               yde, their Fire neuer quenched: Here is
their vnhappines, (Florent ad tempus, pereunt in aeternum:
florent fa
                     •
                  sis bonis, pereunt veris tormentis:) They flourish
for a time, they perish for euer: they flourish with false
ioyes, perish with true and substantiall tormentes:
thinges that are soonest bred, haue the shortest continuance:Psal. 73. 18. 19.
a puffe of Winde rayseth the Chaffe from the
earth, and a puffe scatters it away: the Wicked are
soone raised, and with like speede depressed: How
quickly is Esau's posteritie aduanced to a Kingdome,
how immaturely cast downe? The Crowne is scarse
warme on their temples, their eyes haue scarse taken a
passing glaunce of their glories, but all is dispersed: the
Godly are long kept vnder couert; but when they doe
rise, their eleuation is permanent.
            Loe, now cast a sober and intelligent eye on this
strange opposition, and let the very enemie of Heauen
and Grace, iudge, whether the vaine shadowes of Ioy,
and those for a Day, liable to true and substantiall tormentes,
and those for euer, be comparable with, or desirable

before, a momentany Affliction (and that not
without the best of comfortes) followed with an excellent
and eternall weight of glory. It's confest; I speake
for you, I thinke your Consciences are conuinced: but
(Vbi signa?) Where are the signes of it? If this be so,
and you so acknowledge it, why lead you so dissonant
liues? shall the voyce of your owne tongues, censure of
your owne heartes, witnesse against you? Tacitus reportes,
that in the ciuill Warres betwixt Vitellius and
Vespasian, a Souldier had killed his owne Father, which
was of the enemies Armie; no sooner was this published,
but euery man begins to abhorre, condemne, execrate
that Warre, the cause of such an vnnaturall fact;
yet how little effect this wrought in their proceedings,
that Author describes; for their rage, rapine, crueltie,
was not lessened, in spoyling Neighbour, Friend, Kinsman,
Brother, Father, when they had slaine them. Wee
abhorre the miseries and sinnes incident to this life; we
loue it still, nay preferre it to Heauen: our condemnation
will be easie and iust, what need is there of more
Witnesses (Ex ore tuo) thy owne lippes haue spoken against
thee. For shame let our heartes and tongues be
cut out of one peece, that what we allow in opinion, we
may prosecute in practise.
            You heare how the Day slippes from vs, and the
Night steales on; what remaines, but in the Day to prepare
for the Night. No maruell, if men sleepe in the
Night; but in the broad day, to shut our eyes (with
the Dormouse) is vnnaturall. There is a Night, when
thou shalt rest,Esay. 57. 
                     •
                  . euen on thy bed of Peace: onely walke,
worke; loyter not in thy Day. Christ taught and obserued
the Rule himselfe, to trauell his Day and all his
Day; For the Night comes, wherein no man can worke.
There are thinges, which if the Night findes vndone,
we are vndone, because we haue not done them: if we
deferre to prouide lodging, sustenaunce, safetie, the

Night findes and leaues vs destitute. How madde is
hee, that bound to some speciall designement, confined
to his day, and then furthered with light, ayde, companie,
and conueniencie of all thinges, spendes one houre
in catching Flyes, another after Feathers, and all the rest
in seuerall toyes and leasinges, that on a sodaine the
Sunne settes, and his chiefe worke is not done, nay not
begunne.
            The worke of our day, is the working vp our saluation;
it is a speciall worke, Heauen &amp; our Soules are
vpon it, and we haue but our day to worke it; (Tempus
vitae, tempus paenitentiae) The time of life, is the time of
Repentance. Wee spend one peece of our Day in Couetous
scrapinges, another in adoring that wee haue
scraped; some houres of our Day in working vanitie,
and some in sleeping security; instantly the Night of
death comes, &amp; we haue neglected the maine chaunce:
our Saluation is not finished like Courtiers, that hauing
light to bring them to bed, play it out at Cardes, and
goe to bed darkling: Woe to them that goe to their last
rest thus: How vnworthy are wee of a Day, thus to
spend it? It is pittie that euer the Sun of Grace shoone
on our faces: Quake and feare, what soeuer thou art, to
suffer the sinne of thy soule, and the end of thy life to
come so neere togeather: If men stumble in the darke,
it is not strange; to fall at euery stubbe in the day, argues
wilfull neglect, or want of eyes. It is enough for
those poore Romanistes, that liue vnder that Egiptian
darkenesse of the inquisition, to fall into grieuous absurdities,
where the Sunne shines, to see men fall in
heapes, is astonishing: Oh that euery baite of drunkennesse,
obiect of couetousnesse, presented glaunce of vanitie,
should make vs wander and stumble, stumble and
falle, falle and content our selues therein without rysing:
What (would wee? what) will wee doe, if our
Sunne settes? For shame cast away the deedes of darknesse

with the time:Ephe. 51. 4. 
               Awake and stand vp, the light of Iesus
Christ shines on thy face. As men from sleepe opening
their eyes, and seeing day broke, cast away their
cloathes, wherein they were wrapt warme, and starte
vp to their seuerall callinges; the Sinnes and Vanities
of this world haue kept vs warme, as Caiphas kept Peter,
whiles we were folded in them; but our maine worke
lay dead for want of execution: Prouide then for this
Night,Psal. 118. 27. ôh thou whose cheeke the Sunne of mercie and
forbearance, kisseth: The sleepe of him that trauaileth, is
sweete,Eccl. 5. 11. whether he eate little or much: but the satiety of the
rich will not suffer him to sleepe. If the Day be well spent,
the wearied bones reioyce in their earned repose; and
the contented Conscience, applaudes it selfe in the
thought of her carefull obedience; body and soule receiues
rest. Whiles the Day is slouthfully spent, Night
bringes no reioycefull ease to either spirits or corpes:
The Day of thy life worne out in the well disposed
houres of a religious obedience, thy body shall rest in a
perfumed Graue, and thy soule in the bosome of Abraham,
when Night comes: but whiles pride, surfets, oppressions,
wantonnes, haue shared the Day, the Night
comes with no lesse suddennesse then sorrow; thy rest
shalbe vnrest, neither easier then smoake and thornes,
and flames, nor shorter then the eternitie of all these can
make it: Oh then, what folly, madnes, selfe-enmitie is
this, to play out our short Day, and howle vnder the
pressure of working tormentes for an euerlasting
Night.
            Wee are come to the last fruite that I shall gather you
from this Tree,The Aduice. and it growes on three branches: the
whole body of it, being applyed to the maner, not the
matter of the Question: the matter is first satisfied, The
Morning comes, &amp; the Night; the maner is now touched:
If ye will aske, enquire, returne and come. You aske in derision,
keepe the Cloth, but reiect the Fashion: Aske

still, but to repentance: Let your demaundes manifest
your desires of resolution: If ye will aske, and needes
be acquainted with your sorrowes, Enquire, with humilitie,
reuerence, fayth: Returne from your sinnes, by
repentance, and come home to God by obedience,
(Triplex ex arbore fructus) heere is a threefold fruite from
this Tree; whereon let your soules feede, and then depart
to refresh your bodyes.
            
               Enquire:
               Enquire. Wee must not looke, that God should seeke
vs with his blessinges; as Elias was charged to runne by
the way of the Wildernesse,
               1. king. 19. 5. in quest of Hazael to annoynt
him: No, Seeke yee the Lord, whiles he may be found: the
rule of the Prophet is iust: the Rich man comes not to
the Beggars dore with reliefe in his hand; but the Beggar
to his for it: there is small reason, to expect it from
God, that he should both giue, and seeke: I confesse he
doth, as Christ testifies of himselfe; I came to seeke and to
saue that which was lost;
               Luk. 19. 10. but withall he conueyes into our
heartes, a (preuenting) Grace to seeke him: Hence the
Condition is annexed to the Graunt, by the giuer himselfe;
Aske, and you shall haue: Enquire, and you shall be
satisfied: But if any will be ignoraunt,Resonant responsa roganti let them be ignoraunt
still.
            If you aske mee, 1. Where you should Enquire? Our
Prophet directes you; To the Law, to the Testimonie:
Where should a people enquire,Esay. 8. 20. but at their God? 2. If how?
With Humilitie, Reuerence, and desire of Knowledge:
(Inter Iuuenile tuaicium, et senile praeiudicium multa veritas
corrumpitur.) There must be in vs an equall auoyding
of both Rashnes, and Preiudice: Young men apprehend
not the necessitie of Knowledge; Old men presume
of a plerophorie and abundance: hence neither
young nor old enquire. 3. If when? The Wise-man answers;
Enquire, seeke; Remember thy Creatour in the dayes
of thy youth: Begin this search, in the Morning of thy
yeares: (Mane, is the Lordes Aduerbe, the Deuils

Verbe:) the Lord sayth, Earely; the Deuill sayth, Tarry:
to whom you harken, iudge your selues: One thing
onely, take heed you stay not too long; the Deuill is a
false Sexton, and settes the Clocke too slow, that the
Night comes ere we be aware: tarry not then till your
piles of Vsuries, heapes of Deceites, mountaines of
Blasphemies, haue caused God to hide himselfe, and
will not be found. There is a (Sera nimis hora) time too
late, which Esau fell vnluckily into, when hee sought the
Blessing with teares, and could not find it. It may be the
Statues,Word, Minister, Vnderstanding. or the Guides, or thy owne Eies, may be denied
thee, &amp; then too late thou Enquirest. Whiles the Booke
of God is not perused, his Temples not freuented, nor
his Throne sollicited by Prayers, hard heartednesse
steales on vs, and like Sampson bound by the Philistims,
wee would breake their Bondes, and cast their
Cordes from vs; but our Dalilah, our Folly hath beguiled
vs.
            Is this all? no, there is second Fruite growing on
this Tree,Returne. of equall necessitie, greater vse. After Enquiring,
followes Returning: you are gone wrong, returne
into the way of Peace; Enquire it first, and hauing
found it, Returne, put your feete into it. God warnes
you by the reuelation of his word,Math. 
                     •
                  . 12. (as the Wise-men by
the vision of a Dreame) to Returne into your Country, whither
you would arriue, and where onely is your rest,
another way. If euer this exhortation was necessarie for
Edom, let mee thinke it fitter for England: (as sin-full as
wee are, let mee yet say, there is more hope of our repentance,
then of Edoms:) our Iniquities as great, our
Instructions greater then theirs; what remaines, but
our Repentance? neuer more need: Our sinnes are
not low, slow, few, or sleightly done; negligence sinnes,
security sinnes, contempt sinnes, presumption and
hard-heartednes sins: here is the Scorners Chaire, the
Drunkardes Bench, the Idle-mans Cushion, the Vsurers

Studie: Oh where is Repentance, to rowse these?
God is angry; we haue been smitten, not in the Skirts
and Suburbes of our Common-wealth onely, our Citie,
Body, and whole vnitie hath been pearced to the soule,
The whole Head hath been sicke, and whole Heart heauy:
Where is the phisicke of Repentance? I can shew you
many Actors presenting themselues on the Theator of
this World; I see not Repentance play her part: I can
point you to Vsurie, robbing, grinding, sucking blood,
cutting throates, whiles he sittes in the Chimney corner,
&amp; heares of his Zani's, whelpes, vnderling Theeues
ending their dayes at the Gallowes. I can shew you
Couetousnes sweating for gaine, crowching, ramping,
playing Ape, Lion, or Deuill, for Money: I can discouer
to you Drunkennesse, rising early to the Wine,
Malice making haste to the death of Ammon, Ambition
running after Honour, faster then Peter to the Sepulchre;
Pride whirling in her Charriot, Wantonnes shutting
vp the windowes; Bribery creeping in at the Keyhole,
euen when the doore of Iustice is locked vp against
her. Among all these I see not repentance: Doth
she stay till the last act? I feare the tragedy of many
Soules ruine will be done first. This land is full of
sinnes, (let me speake impartially) this Citie: as many
Lines meete at the Center; so all sinnes by a generall
confluence to this place: Glomerantur in vnum innumerae
pestes Erebj: The mischiefes of Hell are swarmed to one
Crowde, and we haue it. I know there are some names
in Sardj, some that make Conscience of their wayes: the
same ayre is drawn by men of as contrary dispositions,
as is the opposition of the two Poles: that I may say of
the liues of this Citie, as one doth of Origen's writinges:
(Vbi bene, nemo melius:
               Nil fuit vnq uam sic impar sibi. Hor. 
               vbi male, nemo peius,) Those that
are good, are exceeding good, and those that are euill,
are vnmeasurable euill: nothing was euer so vnlike it
selfe. You are as contrary as fire to water; but al the water

of the one's deuotion, will not quench the Fire of the
others wickednesse: This latter is so monstrously
growne on vs with the times, that it is all, if the Idolatrie
of Rome, or the Atheisme of Turkey can goe beyond
it. They are rare heartes, that care not more to seeme,
then to be Holy, if perhaps, they will either seeme or
bee: Rare handes, that are free and cleane from either
blood or filthinesse: rare Tongues, that doe not vie
Oathes with Words; making scoffes, scornes, flatteries,
vaine speaches, the greater part of their tongues exercise;
that if their Words could be weighed, their Prayers
of a yeare, are not so substantiall and ponderous, as
their Oathes of one day: It were no wonder to see these
abominations in Dumah, Egipt, Babilon; to find them in
England is matter of amasement. It was an admirable and
astonishing speach (the Prophet him selfe thought, by
his aduertisement prefixed,Esay.) The virgin Israel hath done
filthily. If Harlots and Brothels be vnchast, they doe not
degenerate from their kind; in so pure a Virgin, no
imagination would haue dream't it. It is no newes to
find the Deuill in Hell: to haue him thrust into Paradise,
tempting and preuayling with our first Parents, is
horrible. Let Rome and Turkey swell with the poysons
of Sathan till they burst, who wonders? to finde the
sputteringes of his venime in the Church is grieuous:
If we be accused for accusing of sinnes, let the Physition
be blamed for discouering Diseases in the sicke bodie:
we must speake; Oh yet—Si nostra sperem prece posse
mouer
                     •
                  , that wee could hope with any sayinges to moue
you: If the worst come, I can but speed, as others before
me. Be there no Vsurers, that say to the Gold in secret,
You are my Confidence? (Populus me sibilat, at mihi plaudo
ipse d
                     •
                  mi,)Hor. the world hisseth at me, but I hug &amp; applaud
my owne soule, &amp; fat my spirits in the sight of my Bags.
Is there neuer a Broker to comfort this sinne of death,
in the distresse of his Conscience with? Vsury is no sinne,

many learned men are of this opinion: But I aske him, if his
Conscience can be so satisfied: would he not willingly
giue one hundred pound bagge, to be secured in this
poynt? Sure, it is (at the least) not safe wading farre in a
questionable Water; if it could be safe to some, yet how
many haue been drowned in this Whirlepoole? I confesse
that flesh and blood puts the Bladders of Wealth
and Promotion vnder their Arme-holes, and the Deuill
holdes them vp by the Chinne, till they come to the
deepest, and then, as the Priestes serued Iudas, they bid
them shift for them selues; and wanting the helpe of
Repentance of swimme, downe they sinke (In profundum
inferni) to the bottomlesse bottom of Hell. These two,
are not vnfitly compared to two Milstones; the Vsurer
is the nether Stone, that lyes still; he sittes at home in
his warme Furres, and spendes his time in a deuillish
Arithmeticke, in numeration of houres, dayes, and
moneys, in substraction from others estates, and multiplication
of his owne, till they haue diuided the earth
to themselues, and themselues to Hell: The Broker
runnes round like the vpper Mill-stone, and betwixt
both these, the poore is grinded to powder.
            Vsury (you say) is exploded among Saintes, I would
you would deale no worse with couetousnesse: But
alasse, this is too generall a fault, to giue any hope of
amendment: He that railed on Beelsebub pulled al Ekrom about his eares: He that sleighted Melchom, prouoked
the Ammonites: But he that condemnes Mammon,
speakes against all the world. This is the delight, the
loue, the solace of many, the God of some: Pouertie,
sicknesse, age, are all the Deuils they tremble at, and Beliall,
Melchom, Mammon, Pleasures, Honours, Riches,
all the Gods they worshippe: These three vsurping
Kings, like the three seditious Captaines in Ierusalem, or
those three Romane Tyrants, Casar, Crassus, and Pompey,
haue shared the world amongst them, and left God

least, who owes all. Lactantius speakes of one Tullus Hostilius,
that put Feare &amp; Palenes into the number of Gods:
It is pittie that euer his Gods should goe from him, it is
(not pittie, but) iustice, that these Gods, and the true
God too, should forsake such reprobates, that idolatrize
the honour to Creatures, wherewith they should worship
the Creator. But alas, how is Pharaobs Dreame verified
among vs? The leane Kine eate vp the fatte: Gods
leane blessinges, riches, and pleasures, deuowre his fatte
ones, Grace and Religion: How it dishonours God,
disparageth our selues, and our creation, to put Lead in
a Cabinet of gold, base desires in a faire and precious
soule. We neuer yet attained the toppe of Mount Syon:
He that stands on the Towre of Diuine meditation, will
iudge those Pigmeys, which below he thought Giants:
but we desire not Heauen,Ignoti nulla cupido. because we know it not; we
neuer looke beyond our Horizon: we liue in our contented
slauery of Egipt, and neuer dreame of the freedome
of Canaan, (Vbi amor, ibi oculus:) where the loue
is, there is the eye. This S. Augustine shortly and soundly
reproues: (Si sursum os, cur deorsum cor?) hath Nature giuen
vs an vpright 
                  •
               ace,Preaepostera dissimili
                     •
                  udo vultus et animae. &amp;c. and a groueling heart? this is a
preposterous dissimilitude of the minde and countenaunce:
doe but compare (as lifting vp thy soule with
thy eyes) heauen with earth, and thou wilt change thy
opinion: Through want of these meditations, these
earthly vanities carry away our inchaunted hearts, to
neglect those better things of our eternall peace: and
by the testimony of our Sauiour, It is hard for a rich man
to get into Heauen: The Prouerbe sayth, There is no earthly
Gate, but an Asse laden with Gold can enter: and this onely
loding, hinders our entring the gates of Glory. A wealthy
and great man, serued vp to Gods table in his kingdome,
is as rare as Venison at our Boardes on earth:
there are sometimes such seruices, not often.
            Is this all? no,Sen. (Vidi Ebriosorum sitim, &amp; vomentium

famem) I haue seene Drunkennesse reeling from Tauerne
to Tauerne, (and not seldome,) from thence to
his Stewes. It was the sinne, nay the shame of Beggars;
it is now the glory, the pride of Gallants: They should
daily be transformed to the image of God, they come
neerer and neerer to beasts, (let me say) to Diuells: For
Saint Bernard sayth, (Ebrietas est manifestissimus Daemon)
Drunkennesse is a most manifest Diuell: They that are
possessed with Satan, or with drunkennesse, fall alike
into the fire,Math. 17. 16. 21 into the water, they gnash alike, alike they
foame: And as all the Disciples could not cast out that
one sort of Deuils; so nor all the Preachers this.
            Gluttony is not much lesse generall, no lesse euill:
Drunkennesse makes a man so giddy he can not stand,
and Gluttonie so pursie that he cannot goe: That old
Verse and Rule is forgotten in our Feastes:

                  Too soone, too fine, too daintily:
                  Too taste, too much, is gluttony.
               
            
            There is an appetite naturall, when the stomach can
extract no more iuyce from meates receiued, it couets
more: There is an appetite sensuall, when the rich sayes,
My Soule eate, not my Body: nay, are not some in this
Citie, like those Horace speakes of? when their estate
can reach but to Herrings,Sed prohibent grandes patinae. they long for fresh Samon.
Wee desire the strength of bodyes, and the length of
dayes; our full Dishes forbid it: If euer that Verse was
true, now is the time:
Non plures gladio, quam cecidere gula:
               The enemies Sword kils not more, then their owne Throate.
            
            Swearing and Whoredome I will ioyne togeather,
(as most sinnes goe by couples) so the Prophet, The
Land is full of Adulterers, and for Oathes the Land mourneth.
Adde vnto Swearing, (the twin-brone brother of it)
Cursing;Carnificem &amp; Lictorem vindictae nostrae. a sinne that makes God (the summum bonum
the base executioner of our reuenge: How strange?
when men grieue vs, to turne our teene vpon God,

and rent him to peeces. Blasphemers against mortall
Princes are killed with the sword, and all their estates
confiscate: against the Prince of Heauen it is not regarded.Gladio 
                     •
                  eriuntur, bonis f
                     •
                  co datis &amp;c.
            
            I must not forget my Edomite, the Gallant: If you
would see an Impostume conflate and swolne vp with
all these rancke corruptions, all the former mischiefes,
reconciling themselues to a wretched vnitie in one
soule, a packe and bundle of sinnes, snatched from their
seuerall owners, (Enuy from the Malitious, Haughtines
from the Proude, Derision from the Scorner, &amp;c. and
engrossed to one heart, an Embleme, a Pageant, a short
Commentarie of all the Deuilles proceedings, a Mappe
of his walkes, plottes, and actions; behold the Gallant:
I taxe not the generous Spirit, whose birth and accoutrementes
are worthy and high, his minde humble. Oh
how comely are good Cloathes to a good Soule, when
the Grace within, shall beautifie the Attire without;
and not gay Ragges, impudently beare out Wicked
actions: Farre be it from me to thinke these Edomites, or
any other thing, then the Diamondes, that grace our
Ring, no, they are the gallant Esauites, the profane Roysters,
to whom I speake, and that from a text of Repentance,
desiring from my soule, that they may scape the
Burden of Dumah, by reiecting the manners, and make
more account of their Birth-right, then sell it for messes
of Pottage, Lustes, and Vanities: But if they will note
themselues with the Cole and Brand of Prophanesse,
they must not looke to escape our Censures: wee cannot
heare their Oathes, beating the vnvulnerable
breast of Heauen, not see their Pride, testifying to their
face, if they should plead innocence; nor be vnwillingly
conscious of their Atheisticall Iestes,Hos. 7. 10. Libertine Feastes,
worse then Pagan Adulteries, and charme our tongues
with silence; when the glory of our God, the price of
their Redemption, and the danger of their owne soules

lye at the stake.
            There are other open, and infinite secret sinnes, which
they thinke no eye sees: But there are witnesses, the
Angels good and bad, the Conscience of the committers,
and the iudge of the Conscience: Si nemo, non tamen
nullus) if no man, yet not none: therefore what thou darest
not to doe thy fellow seruant looking on thee,Quod non audes facere aspiciente conseruo: hoc ne cogites inspiciente deo. that
dare not to thinke thy heauenly Master looking in thee.
I confesse, wee haue a face of Religion, and lookes of
profession, making toward Ierusalem; but how many
make the noble Liuery of our Maister, a shelter to these
abhorred corruptions? and till the tryall comes, it is not
knowne whom many serue: A man that followes two
Gentlemen, is not discerned which to serue, till they
part companie: so long as wealth and religion goe togeather,
it is not apparant, to which of them most adhere,
till the crosse parts them, and then it is plaine and
easie.
            Were these the sinnes of Edom, and are they not the
sinnes of England? The sinnes saide I? nay, the Gods of
England: For the Vsurer adores his mettalles, the Epicure
his Iunketts, the Drunkard his Gallons, the Voluptious
his Lusts, the Adulterer his Harlottes, the
Proude and gallant Edomite his gaye Cloathes, and studyed
carriage: And as the Israe
                     •
                  ies cried to their Calfe
made of golden Eare rings, These are thy Gods oh Israell:
So wee may speake it with horror and amasement, of
these foolish,Exod. 3
                     •
                  . 
                     •
                  . bestial, diuelish, sinnes, Thesè are thy Gods oh
England: weake, wretched, vnhelpefull Gods: For
shame, what, where are wee? could Edom euer be
worse? Haue we deuoured so many yeares of peace,
ease, plentie, and saturitie, (if I may so call it) of Gods
word; and are we still so lame, le
                  •
               ne, and ill fauoured in
our liues? what shall I say? hath the sweet Ghospell,
and the sober preaching of it, made vs sensuall, senseles;
impudent, franticke? as the nature of that Countrey is

wonderfull,Siccita
                     •
                   dat Lutum, imbres puluerem. Plin. if true, that Raine causeth Dust, &amp; Drought
Durt: Haue the sweete Deawes of Hermon, made the
Hill of Syon more barren? Hath the Sunne of Plenty,
from the filth of our Securitie, bred monsters of sinnes?
Haue Gods mercies made vs worse? what shall I say?
            Fathers and Breathren, helpe: Pittie the miscarrying
soules, that haue no mercy on themselues: our Wordes
are thought ayre, let your Hands compell them to the
seruice of God:Verbum informans, virga reformans. The word of Information hath done
his best, Where is the rodde of Reformation? Let Moses
Rodde, second Aarons Word. The loues of Sinners,
the strength of Sinnes; nay, Principalities and Powers
are against vs, and we come armed with a few leaues of
Paper: The keenest Sword is with vs, but it is in our
lippes onely, The sword of the Spirit; and though it can
deuide the Marrow and the bones,
               Heb. 4. of an awaked Conscience,
alas it moues not the stony hearts: it shall sooner
double vpon our selues, then enter such Mayled Consciences:
our blowes are filliped backe in contempt:
be not wanting ye that haue the ordinaunce of God:
You are his surrogates, and the Preachers hopes: good
lawes are made, the life-blood of them is the execution:
the Lawe is else a woodden Dagger in a faire Sheath:
when those that haue the charge imposed, and the
Sword in their hands, stand like the picture of S. George,
with his hand vp, but neuer striking: wee complaine
not of the higher Magistrates, from the benches, of
whose Iudgement, impietie departs not without disgrace,
without stroakes: the blame lyes on inferiour
Officers, who thinke their office well discharged, if
they threaten offendours: these see, and will not see:
Hence Beggars lase themselues in the fields of idlenesse;
hence Tauernes and Tap-houses swarme with Vnthrifts;
of whom, whether they put more sinne into
their bellies, or vomite more foorth, is a hard question;
I meane, whether their oathes, or ebrieties exceed:

Hence wee looke to haue Vagrants suppressed, Idlenesse
whipt, Drunkennesse spoke withall; but the execution
prooues too often like the Iuglers feast, the
Guests sette, the table's furnished, meate in dishes, wine
in flaggons; but putting forth their hands to take them,
they apprehend nothing but ayre.
            The medecine to heale all this, both for Patient and
Physitian, is repentance; not a iaculatory crye of Lord
forgiue me, nor the flash of a melancholy passion, but a
sound, serious, and substantiall repentance. Rome hath
an holy water of vertue, they say, to purge and wash
away all her spottes: England hath her holy water too,
which, too many trust in for sufficient, we looke vp and
crye, Lord thy mercie, and wipe our lippes, as if we had
not sinned: yet by and by to our former vomite. But
the repentance, that resolues for Heauen, throwes away
all impediments▪ if Gold, if pleasure, if a Throne
were in the way, she would fling them aside: she hath
an eye bent on the Mercie
                  •
               seate, and a foote that runnes
straight to it: she turnes not into Samaria, because she
is offered lodging there, nor into the Court of Egipt, to
be called the Sonne of Phar
                     •
                  os Daughter: the pleasures
of Babilon stay her not, the Good-fellowes of Sodome
make her not looke backe: she forgets what is behind,
and neuer rests, like the Kine that carryed the Arke,
till she comes to the fieldes of Bethshemesh, the haruest of
grace and goodnesse; nor ceaseth lowing with sorrow
till she be sped of the mercies of God: she hath felt the
weight of sinne and sorrow, and abhorres the cause of
them both: she hates not the diuell worse then her former
iniquities, and if it were possible, she would neuer
more offende: Thus, this is to returne; what you want
of this, you come short of repentance.
            The thirde degree followes to make vp our perfection:Come.
If Returning might serue as a labour of (but) indifferent
trouble, we could afford it, but we must come:

You haue heard the Whence,
               Vnde &amp; quo
                     •
                  
                heare the Whither. Thou
hast not done with Enquiring, with Returning; Vp and
e
                     •
                  te Elias, thou hast a greater iourney to goe: strengthen thy
heart, ôh Christian, R
                     •
                  stat tibi tertia meta) thou hast a
third marke to ayme at. Come, home to thy God, by a
Chast and Holy life; it is not currant pay with God, to
part with our Vanities, except we imbrace a Religious
conuersation. Paul makes it as necessarie a part of
Christianitie, to Put on the New man, as to put off the Old:
It is not enough to cease doing euill, but it is damnable
not to doe well: Hee that gathers not with Christ, scattereth.
It was the threatning doome in Iohn Baptists Sermon,
not to the Barren, but to the Euil-fruited Tree. Christes
speach carries the same sense and force against the Pharises,
though spoken to his Disciples: Except your Righteousnesse, &amp;c.
he sayes not, Vnlesse your righteousnesse
be lesse then theirs; but, Except your righteousnesse be more,
exceed, you shall not see heauen. Hee that inquires the way
to Heauen, and turnes toward it, hath past two degrees
of my Text, and his owne Pilgrimage; but he gets litle
of either prayse or comfort, except he come home to it:
Heere is not so much perseuerance lessened, as perfection:
there is extreme wrong, extreme right and mercie.
The 2. first, shalbe shut out of Heauen; the last onely,
hath a promise of entraunce.Summa iniuria, summum ius, et mise
                     •
                  
                  cordia. 
               Iudgement without mercy,
shalbe to him that sh
                     •
                  wes no mercy; not to the cruell onely,
but to him that is but meerely iust: The want of 
                  •
               ustice
is not onely damned,Iam. 2. 13. but the want of Mercy: the Rich
Churle went to hell for not relieuing Lazarus, though he
wronged him not. If the vsurer part with his extortions,
the Wanton with his Minions, the Cheater with his
Frauds, the Tradesman with his Oathes, he thinks himselfe
by this time a high Christian, and that God must
nedes blesse him, he is so repentant. If the long perswasions
of many Sermons, can worke this on vs, that wee
abate of our former outragious licentiousnes, we straite

spunge vp our selues; and with a conceite, that we haue
done much for God, out-face all reproofes: but he that
hath much forgiuen him, loues much. The Prodigall does
not onely turne from his Harlottes and vices, but comes
home to his Fathers house: There was no stinte in that
sinfull Womans penitence, till she had powred 
                  •
               loods
of teares on the feete of our Sauiour: The conscience
of Zacheus was not disburdened, by ceasing his extortion,
but by restitution to the wronged, commiseration
to the distressed, euen to one halfe of his goods, and
these are the commended penitents.
            How sortes our practise with this Doctrine? shew
me a sacrilegious Patron, a Pyrate of the Church, that
(if his hand cease from spoyling God of his Tithes, yet)
will repayre the breaches, his rapine hath made: shew
me a Bribe-guilty Officer, seeke out with wette eyes,
and reward with a full hand, the wronged Suitors: how
many are more cruell-hearted then Iudas, that neyther
on repentance nor despaire will bring backe the price
of the Poores Blood, which they haue sucked? Behold
the earthly Churle, to make his sonne a Gentleman,
prostituting his honesty, conscience, soule, and forsaking
his owne mercie: (as the Prouerbe is vile, if euer
true, Happy is that Sonne, whose Father goes to the Diuell:)
After he hath mowed Corne, or fatted his Oxe, on the
very place, (
                     〈◊〉
                   Trotafuit) where the Towne stood; nay,
kenneled his Dogges within the walles of the Sanctuary;Non ignota cano.
and turned the Hall of Charitie into the Parlour
of Pride; his Body sinkes to the Graue, and (it is to be
feared)
his Soule to Hell, being rung thither with the
peales of Belles and curses. The better instructed
Heire, (to omitte those that exceed the tiranny of their
Fathers) seeing and detesting his dead Fathers deader
courses,Q
                     •
                  is talia 
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     •
                  mperet a lad 
                     〈◊〉
                  ? lud. 5. 23. withdrawes his hand from extortion, from
depopulation, but what reasons can make him a restorer?
it is enough (he thinkes) to cease wronging. But

               curseye Meroz, sayth the Angell of the Lord, curse the inhabitantes
thereof, because they came not foorth, to h
                     •
                  lp
                     •
                   the Lord
in the day of battaile: Did they fight against God? No,
they helped him not:Math. 18. that Seruant was condemned for
clayming his owne debt: the Prayers and Fastinges of
the Iewes were despised, for clayming their owne debts;
and standing vpon Sacrifice with men,Esay. 58. 3. Whiles they
would haue mercie with God.Neh. 5. 
               Nehemiah threatned
the same people with a stricter taxation: They must restore
the extorted Landes and Houses of their breathren; nay,
remit some part of the debt, or they were cursed with that fearefull
sacrament, the shaking the lappe of his Garment, so to be
shaken out of Israell, all the congregation crying, Amen. Lastly,
beyond all exception, the manner of the Lambes comming
to Iudgement, testifies as much; Goe ye Cursed: For
what cause? Because ye denyed the Labourer his hire, or
tooke Bread from the hungry, &amp;c. No, these are crying
Sinnes, and Hasten before vnto Iudgement: But, You
gaue them not, therefore, (lie maledictj) Goe ye cursed; so
Come yee blessed. What, because ye dealt iustly, and gaue
euery man his due? no, these vertues may be in morall
men that want Fayth and Christianitie: But, You gaue
them your owne bread; Hungry, and clad them Naked,
with your owne cloathes; therefore, Come ye blessed.
            
            What vse you will make of this, I know not; what
vse you should make, I know: If the Tree without
good fruite shalbe burned, what shall become of the
Tree that hath euill? If Barrennesse be cast into the fire,
what doth Rapine and Robberie deserue? If it be damnation
enough to deny our owne Bread, what is it to
take away the onely Loafe, Coate, or Cottage of our
poore brother? Woe to the Backe that weares the Garment,
to the Bellies that deuowers the Food, they neuer
sweate for; I meane, that by force or fraud, tooke them
from the owners. If Naball and Diues burne for not giuing
their owne, what shall become of Ahab and Iesabell,
               
for taking away the Vineyard of Naboth? If the righteous
be scarcely saued,
               1. Pet. 4. 18. 
               where shall the vngodly and the sinner appeare?
            
            Now if after this Phisicke giuen, I should aske many,
how they feele the Pulses of their Consciences beate? I
presume on this reply: (Notum loq
                     •
                  eris) you but guild
Gold, and minister to vs such Phisicke, as we haue taken
before. All this we know; (we doe not euermore
ply your vnderstandinges with new thinges; but lay
old, almost dead &amp; forgotten, fresh to the Conscience:)
I aske further, how much of this haue you practised?
and still looke for an affirmatiue answere, All this, haue
I kept from my youth.
            
            Let vs reason &amp; discusse this matter a litle. To Enquire,
is hearing, or rather harkning to the word to Returne, is
repenting: to Come, is beleeuing, or rather looking more
toward perfection, proceeding into the ripenesse of
Fayth. This latter is so necessarie, that we can not come
to God with his acceptance; our comfort, if wee leaue
our Fayth behind vs; without this, impossible to please him,
to be rewarded of him: This our Charter wherby we hold
all our Priuiledges, our Title in Capi
                     •
                  e to Earth and Heauen:
But (Sub 
                     •
                  udice Lis est) the great Iudge of Heauen
shall one day censure it: meane time, giue me leaue to
helpe thee, peruse this euidence of thy Fayth, whereon
thou so presumest. Christ dying, made a Will, sealed it
with his owne Blood, wherein he bequeathed a certaine
Inheritaunce to his breathren: the Conueyance is the
Gospell, (this his Testament:) the executor of this
Will, is the Holy ghost: our Tenure and Euidence, is
our Fayth. Now, thou layest title to Ierusalem for a childs
part: What's thy title? in Christes name and right:
what conueyance did Christ euer make thee of such a
portion? Yees, he conueyed it to mee by Will: What,
by a speciall name? no, but by a generall title to all beleeuers:
That I am one of these heires, my euidence;
my Fayth. Let God alone to try thy Fayth: If thou

commest to me for counsell, sayth S. Iames, thou must
shew me another euidence: Shew me thy faith by thy works.
            
            If thy heart be corrupt, thy hands filthy, thy tongue
false, thy euidence is but counterfaite. Christ giues not
title of inheritaunce in Heauen, to such as haue no holinesse
on Earth:
                  
                     •
                  . Cor. 6. 9. 
               Know ye not that the vnrighteous shall not
inherite the kingdome of God? Be not deceiued, neither Fornicato
                     •
                  s,
&amp;c.
               Reu. 21. 27. 
               And there shall enter into it no vncleane thing,
nor any thing that worketh abhomination, or lyes. Perhappes
thou wilt yet stand vpon it: produce thy witnesses:
they are onely two, thy Life, thy Conscience: they
cannot speake with thee, against their maker and thine.
Thy life speakes lowde, and plaine: Thy pride, drunkennesse,
oppression, cousenage, lustes, blasphemies,
manifest thou hast but a broken title: and Paul pleads
against thee,Tit. 3. 8. from this cleere aduantage: Protest to them
yee beleeue in God, that they be carefull to shew foorth good
workes. They that haue the euidence of faith, must haue
the witnes of workes: It is a poore deed, without witnesses.
Thy conscience speakes plaine too, that thy
faith is but a carnall perswasion, bred of securitie; a forged
Euidence, made by a false Scriuener the Diuell, to
deceiue thy owne eyes and the worldes, not Gods.
Now where is thy claime? stand vpon good assurance,
lest when that subtile winnower Satan, comes to fift
thee graine after graine, thou prouest Chaffe: we may
come with this carnall perswasion, little better then reprobate
hope, to the Temples, to the Pulpittes to the
Sacraments, but if we come so to the tribunall of Christ,
woe vnto vs: the too much trusting to a verball, leane,
sicke, starued faith, deceiues many a Soule: whiles we
couet to be solifidians in opinion, wee prooue nullifidians
in practise: no matter for wisedome in the Soule,
grace in the conscience, honesty in the life, if the profession
of faith be in the tongue: but the Poore may
say as he in the Comedie: (Oculatae mihi sunt manus, credunt,

quod vident:) My handes haue eyes, and they beleeue
what they see: wee carry the formes and outsides
of Christians, and thinke God beholding to vs, for gracing
his materiall, earthly Temples; when in the Temples
of our owne heartes, wee sette vp the Idolls of our
owne affections,H
                     •
                  s
                     •
                  e Deus templis gaudet. &amp;c. yet are these the Temples, wherein he
is best pleased to dwell: But if we be come to God by
faith,2. Cor. 13. 5. he is also come to vs by grace: The spirit of Christ is
in vs,Rom. 8 9. 10. if we be not Reprobates. And if this spirit be in vs, the
body of sinne is dead. At least hath his deathes-wound:
But alasse, in how many of vs doth sinne liue, dwell, (I
would I might stay there, nay euen) raigne? as if Christ
had come to destroy the Diuell,Dominandi vim▪
                and not the workes of
the Diuill, to free vs from the damnation and not the
dominion of sinne:Damnandi vim. but he that tooke from sinne the
power to condemne vs, tooke also the power to raigne
in our mortall Bodyes. And the second, is but a consequent
of the first,Rom. 7 25. &amp; 8. 1. postscribed with that word of inference,
now then▪ &amp;c.1. Ioh. 3. 8. Thus Christ came not onely to
binde the Diuell, but to loose and dissolue his workes.
            
            I haue read and obserued in the Historie of Scotland,
a certaine controuersie betwixt that Kingdome and
Ireland, for a little Iland that lay betweene them; eyther
claimes it as theit due, and the strife growing hotte, was
falling from wordes to blowes: but reason moderated
both sides, and they put it to the decision of a Frenchman;
who thus iudged it: he caused lyning Serpents to
be put into that Iland; if they liued and thriued there,
he iudged it Scotlands; if they pyned and dyed, he gaue
it for Ireland. You can apply it easily: If the venemous
Serpents, poysons, and corruptions of our natures
batten and thriue in vs, wee are Satans; if they
languish and consume, wee are Gods: thus is the title
ended for the freehold of our Soules, by what sure rule
wee may know, whether they belong to Hell or Heauen.
If our harts be vnstabled of these beastiall lusts, and

trimmed vp with Sanctimony to entertaine our holy
Guest, there shall be a reciprocall and enterchangeable
comming of vs to Christ, and Christ to vs: and we shall
as surely suppe with him in his Court of glory,Reu. 3. 20. as he hath
supped with vs, in our house of Obedience.
            
            Let vs only feare, least our want of Repentance hinder
this. I should haue earst obserued it, as a materiall
instruction from this place, I could not find a fitter
time to insert it, then here, to draw your comming
with more alacritie. There is a reseruation to repentance,
euen to abhorred Edom: let the sonnes of the
prophanest Esau repent, and they shall not be forsaken
of mercie: Returne and come, and your night threatned,
shall be made a ioyfull warning, though it had as certaine
&amp; defined a time, as euer had Ionas doome against
Niniueh, the sett bounds of 40. dayes, with a Non vltra:
yet be you humbled and this iudgement shall be dispensed
with: If there be such mercie to Edom, let me
say boldly, repenting Israell shall not faile of it: the
night shall linger, and the Sun be kept from setting, if
wee will returne in our day: the threatnings of God
haue a condition included; that generall, that promised,
that neuer refused interposition of repentance. As absolute
as the speech might seeme to Abimelech, withholding
Abrahams wife, thou art but a dead man, yet it
had an implicite condition, except thou restore her vndefiled,
as appeares by the sequele. It is a common Fountaine
where at euery repentant soule may drinke, at
what time soeuer, what sinner soeuer, repent of what sinne
soeuer, &amp;c. And if yet any feele themselues thirsty,
weake, and not throughly resolued, let him for euer
confute the distrust of his owne heart▪ the malice of Sathan,
the present difficulties,Ier. 18 7. with that of Ieremiah,
Where in expresse wordes, our repentaunce is sayd to
make GOD repent, euen of his threatned, and intended
Plagues.
            
               God hath threatned to all sinners, a Night of sorrow,
and it shall as surely come, as euer Euening succeeded
day: but there is an Except, that shall saue vs, a seasonable
and substantiall repentance: if we turne from those
winding Labyrinths of sinne, and come home to God,
hee will saue vs from this Night, that wee perish not:
there is no comming to God, but in &amp; by Iesus Christ;
through his Sonne must God looke at vs, and wee at
him; that he may be mercifull, we hopefull.
            Come then beloued, to Iesus Christ: behold him
with the eyes of Fayth, standing on the Battlementes
of Heauen, and wafting you to him: come freely, come
merrily, come with speede; come betimes, least when
you would, you cannot for want of direction, dare not
for want of acquaintance with him: he that comes not
till the last gaspe of extremitie, knowes not how to
come, because he begins but then. How prone are our
feete to forbidden pathes? the Flesh calles, we come▪
Vanitie calles, we flocke: the World calles, we flye:
Let Christ call earely and late, and either we not come,
or vnwillingly, or late, or with no purpose to stay.
How iustly may he take vp that complaint against vs,
that against the Iewes: after all my Promises, assurances,
reall performances of Mercies;Ioh. 5. 40. 
               You will not come vnto me,
that you might haue life: Perhappes, when we are weary
of sinne and sinne of vs, then let God take vs; hee will
none of the Deuils leauinges. Some would come, but
for some impediments; that either Childes Portion to
be made vp; such a House to be builded, such a Ground
to be purchased: this same But, marres their comming,
as he in the Gospell, But for burying his Father; and
that other, But for bidding his Friendes farewell: so, But
for Mammon, and that we cannot be rich with a good
Conscience; But for Pleasures, that we cannot be wanton,
yet nourish the hope of saluation: But for these
(veruntamens) But's, they would come, (S
                     •
                  d v
                     •
                  x sunt

vsi, qui carnere nisi,) we haue all one But, one exception
or other, to keepe vs from our Christ: yet Paul countes
all these but drosse, but dung: And if any thing seeme
fayrer in thine eye then Christ, (Detur digniori) giue thy
soule to the worthyer: We can extreamely affect no
earthly thing▪ but the Deuill (at one time or other) will
bring it into opposition with Christ, as the Moone and
the Sunne, to see which of them shalbe eclipsed. Alas,
how ordinary (yet how vile is it (Post-ponere Christum
bonibus, qui nos 
                     •
                  qua
                     •
                  it angelis;) to set Christ after our
Oxen, that hath made vs equall to the Angels: yet all
those Friends, whom we so trust, shall soonest faile vs,
and at our most need run from vs, as Vermines from
an house on fire. Giue me lea
                  •
               e to shew you this indignitie
offred to Christ by a metaphor; familiar comparisons
giue the quickest touch, to both vnderstanding
and conscience.
            A certaine Gallant had three Friendes: two of them
flatter'd him in his loose humours; if in this, I may
not rather call them Enemies: The third, louingly desswaded
him from his follies: on the two flatterers, he
spent his Patrimony; the third he castes off with contempt:
his ryot and wealth gone, his Friendes went
too; for they were friendes to the Riches, not to the
Rich man: Debt was required, hee arrested, and the
Prison not to be auoyded: in this calamitie, he studies
refuge; hence bethinkes himselfe of his two Friends,
of whom he desires reliefe: the first's answere is cold
and short, Alas, I can not spare it, you should haue preuented
this 
                     •
                  arst: The other speakes a litle more comfort; I haue
no Money to helpe you, yet I will beare you company to
the Prison-doare, and there leaue you: The distressed
man findes small satisfaction in all this; therefore as
his last refuge, hee calles to minde his third Friend,
whom he had euer scorned, wronged; and after much
wrastling betwixt shame and necessitie, hee sendes to

him, with no lesse earnestnesse, then humilitie, discouers
his exigents, requires helpe: the Message scarce deliuered,
hee comes with speed, payes the Debt, sets him
at libertie, nay repayres the ruines of his estate. The
Rioter, is Man; the two flattering Friends, are Riches
and Pleasures; these the soule of man embraceth,
spends her strength and time, most precious Riches, on
them: The third Friend, that rebukes his sinnes, is
Christ; this because distastefull to blood and flesh,
without regard to his sauing health, is reiected: at last,
all the time of Grace spent, the soule (so farre) in Gods
debt, is arrested by one of Gods Serieants, Sicknesse,
or Calamitie, or an afflicted Conscience; then those
Friends begin to slinke; Pleasure is gone sodainely,
so soone as the Head begins to ake: Riches (perhaps)
will offer to goe with him to the Prison doare the gates
of Death, the preparation to the Graue: the fainting
Soule fore-seeing their falshood, weakenesse, aggrauation
of his miseries; with an humbled Heart, remorsefull
Conscience, Teares in his eyes, Prayers and Cryes
in his tongue, sollicites his neglected Sauiour, to pittie
his distresse, and haue mercie vpon him: these Messengers
haue no sooner pierced the Heauens, but downe
comes the spirit of Grace and Mercie, with Pardon
and free Remission, payment of all Debts, &amp; discharge
of all Sorrowes.
            If euer you meet with Friend more able, more willing,
more certen, to doe you good, reiect this counsell;
The breath of all men is in their nostrilles, and there is
no helpe in them,Psal. 146. though they were Princes; when not onely
their materiall partes, Flesh, Blood, Bones, and Marrow,
but euen part of the inward man, so farre as their
worldly intendementes went, Their Thoughtes perish.
But GOD was, is, and is to come; not onely in
Power,Heb. 13. 8. but in Mercie, Sweetnesse, Protection. Iesus
Christ yesterday, and to day, and the same for euer.
            
            
               That Iesus Christ put into our mouthes a tongue to
Enquire, into our heartes a purpose to Returne, into our
liues a grace to Come home to holynes, and himselfe.
            This God graunt for his mercies sake, Iesus Christ
for his merits sake, the Holy ghost for his
names sake, to whom be ascribed
all honour and praise, for
euer and euer. Amen.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

