
   
      
         
            Maskil le-David = Dauids instructer A sermon preached at the visitation of the Free-Schole at Tunbridge in Kent, by the wardens of the Worshipfull Companie of Skinners; by Thomas Gataker B. of D. and pastor of Rotherhith.
            Gataker, Thomas, 1574-1654.
         
         
            
               1620
            
         
         Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01530
            STC 11655
            ESTC S102889
            99838651
            99838651
            3037
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01530)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3037)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1099:09)
         
         
            
               
                  Maskil le-David = Dauids instructer A sermon preached at the visitation of the Free-Schole at Tunbridge in Kent, by the wardens of the Worshipfull Companie of Skinners; by Thomas Gataker B. of D. and pastor of Rotherhith.
                  Gataker, Thomas, 1574-1654.
               
               [8], 34, [2] p.   
               
                  Printed by Edward Griffin,
                  London :
                  1620.
               
               
                  First two words of title in Hebrew characters.
                  The last leaf is blank.
                  Also issued as part 7 of: Certaine sermons first preached and since published.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2003-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-09
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-10
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2003-10
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-12
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            משכיל לדוד
DAUIDS Instructer.
            A
SERMON
PREACHED AT
THE VISITATION OF
the Free-Schole at TVNBRIDGE
in KENT, by the Wardens of the
Worshipfull Companie of
SKINNERS; BY
THOMAS GATAKER B. of D.
and Pastor of Rotherhith.
            LONDON,
Printed by EDWARD GRIFFIN.
1620.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHT
WORSHIPFVL AND
MVCH HONOVRED,
Sr THOMAS SMITH Knight, Gouernor
of the famous Companie of Merchants
trading to the EAST-INDIES,
&amp;c.
            Long life and health here, with eternall
happinesse els-where. *⁎*
            
            
               
                  RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL;
            
            Being requested lately by my
kinde Frends, the Wardens of the
Worshipfull Companie of Skinners,
to assist them in their Visitation of the
free Schole at Tunbridge, founded long since
by that worthy Knight, of blessed memorie,
Sir Andrew Iudde, your Grand-father, and
committed to the charge and ouer-sight of that
well-deseruing Society; I made choise of such a
portion of Scripture there to entreat of, as

seemed not altogither vnfitting an occasion of
that kinde. After the handling whereof, being
then presently solicited by some, and since
further importuned by others, to make these my
weake labors more publike, as not vnlikely (so
they deemed) to doe some further good; I was
at length drawne, regarding more their opinion,
then mine owne conceipt thereof, as well knowing
it to be but a tumultuary worke, amids many
distractions hastily peiced togither; and to giue
them satisfaction therein, that seemed so desirous
of it; to let it goe abroad, and make tryall
what benefit either Teacher, or Scholler, or
other might make of it. This resolued on, I began
to bethinke my selfe, obseruing the vsuall
manner of the times, whom I should make
choise of for the patronizing of it. In all respects
none seemed so fit as your Selfe, whom I haue
therefore made bold to addresse it vnto. The
Schole was first erected and endowed by your
Worships Ancestor. And you haue worthily
built vpon his foundation, and added liberally
to his gift. So that through your munificence it
is very likely to flourish, and not to come behind
some of those that be of cheife note. Your bounty
herein, and in other works of the like nature, is

the rather to be regarded; for that you do not,
(as the manner is of the most, vnwilling to part
with ought, till they must needs leaue all;) defer
wholy your well-doing to your deaths-bed, or
your dying day; but bend your selfe thereunto,
while you may yet surviving your owne donation,
your selfe see things setled in a due course,
and receiue comfort by view of the fruit and
benefit that may therby redound both to Church
and Common-weale. And certainly, to omit,
thatBen
                     •
                   sicium nisi à v
                     •
                  lente non 
                     •
                  atur. Sen. de ben. l. 5 
                     •
                  . 19 Beneficium est qu
                     •
                  d qui
                     •
                   dedit, c
                     •
                  m p
                     •
                  sset &amp; non dare. lb. l. 3. c. l 9. the good that men do in their life time is a
surer note of true bounty, then that they do at
their deceasse; asLegatur Ambr. exhort. ad p
                     •
                  nit &amp; August. homil. 41. there is greater euidence of
sincere repentance, in the abandoning of vice,
while men haue liberty and abilitie to continue
the practise of it, then in leauing of sinne then,
when sinne it selfe leaueth them, and they can
no longer follow it: Howsoeuer the benefit to
others may be equall in either, to the Doner
himselfe in the former is the comfort far greater,
Good done at our end is like a Lanterne
borne after vs, that directeth them that come
after vs, but affordeth vs litle light; whereas
the good done in our life time is like a light
borne before vs, that bothBeneficiū dando accepit, qui digno dedit. P. Syrus. benefiteth them
and vs also alike, imparting light equally vnto

either. Yea, of such beneficence I may well say
more: it benefiteth the giuer in diuers respects
much more then the taker; it is a far greater
pleasure to the bestower, then it is to the receiuer.
Act. 20. 35. 
               It is a more blessed thing, saith our
Sauiour, to giue then to take. Yea
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Epicurus. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plut. de philoseph. apud dutes disser. Non honestius tan. 
                     •
                  um, sed &amp; tucundius est ben ficium dare quàm accipere. 
                     〈◊〉
                   Ita
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   Sen. de ben. l. 1 c. 1. Ma
                     •
                  m n
                     •
                  n recipere benefi
                  
                     •
                  ia, quàm non dare. 
               to giue
then to take, saith the Heathen man, it is the
pleasanter of the twaine: to bestow a benefit
vpon an other, then to receiue a benefit from
an other, it is more delightsome to any man of a
free and ingenuous disposition. So that, to passe
by the religious consideration, of the rich and
royall reward and recompence of well-doing
from God and with God, which may be alike
vnto either; the very light of Nature sheweth,
that in true Beneficence there is more pleasure
and contentment, and consequently more comfort
and benefit euen for the present, to the giuer
then to the taker: that which is a great part
of it, wanting vnto those, that defer their well-doing,
though they do neuer so well then, till
their deceasse. You, worthy Sir, do otherwise,
and long may you liue so to do, to the increase
of your ioy and comfort here, and the furtherance
of your account and reckoning els-where.
With which wish I seale all vp, that I be not

ouer-tedious and troublesome to your Worship,
amids your other manifold more serious and
weightie affaires; and requesting onely your
fauourable acceptance of this sory trifle,
rest,
            
               Your Worships to be commanded
in the Lord,
Tho: Gataker.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            DAVIDS
INSTRVCTER.
            
               PSALM. 34. 11.
               Come, Children, hearken vnto me: I will teach
you the feare of the Lord.
            
            
               ALL
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 2. Tim. 3. 16. Scripture, saith the Apostle,
is diuinely inspired, and is profitable
to instruct. And
               Prov. 30. 5. Euery word
of God, saith Agur, is pure: euen
               Psal. 12. 6. 
               as pure as gold or siluer that
hath past seuen times through
the fire in the furnace.
            But yet, as some gold and siluer is finer then other;
and some golden vessels are more vsefull then
others are: so betweene Scripture and Scripture
(though all pure, pretious, and profitable) there is
great difference: some is of greater excellency, and
of more ordinarie vse.
            AndLicit 
                     〈◊〉
                   Scriptura diuina Dei gratiam spiret, praecipuè tamen dulcis est Psalmorū liber. Ambr. praefat. in Psalm. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Basil. praefat. in Ps. Psal
                  
                     ••
                  rū liber quaeconque vtilia sunt ex omnibus continet. August. no one Booke of Scripture more excellent,
orPsalmꝰ omnibus &amp; vbi
                     •
                   prasto est. Lege Ambros Aug. Ruffin. &amp; Euthym. praefat. in Psal. of more frequent vse both in publike and

priuate then this of the Psalmes; wherein the holy
men of God, as theyPsal. 424. &amp; 102 ut. 1. Sā. 1.15. 
               powre out their soules vnto
him, so they portrait and paint them out vnto vs.
            Among the rest of the Psalmes, some of them
there are, about which the Holy Ghosts pleasure
was, that the penmen thereof, should take more
paines then vsuall, and more Art then ordinarie
should be shewed, in the framing and contriuing of
them: And where he vseth more Art, we may well
expect more excellence; where they haue taken
most paines in teaching vs, there should we vse most
diligence in learning that, that is taught vs.
            Of this kinde are the 25. the 37. the 119. and this
34 Psalme;
               Psalmi 
                     〈…〉
                   Psal. 118 in fi
                     •
                  e. composed according to the order of
the Hebrew Alphabet, the verses of them beginning,
as in Acrostichall Poems, with the letters thereof in
their vulgar and vsuall order: partlyVt memoriae consuleret. Muscul. in Psal. 119. to helpe memorie;
and partly,V
                     •
                  autmadm
                     •
                  di
                     •
                   parvutorum inger
                     ••
                   primis literarū elemētis assu
                     •
                  scunt vsum dicendi assumer
                     •
                  ; itanos etiam vsam vtuendi discamus. Ambros. in Psal. 118. that euen Children and learners,
togither with their first Elements of other
learning, might haue an Alphabet of piety and godlinesse
taught them.
            This Psalme, one of those thus artificially framed,
is a Psalme consisting partly ofVers. 1, 2. Celebration, of
praise and thanks-giuing to God; and partly of
Vers. 3, 5, 7, 8. Exhortation and instruction to vs.
            The words propounded for the subiect-matter
of my present discourse, are parcell of the latter part.
For inVers. 9, 10. the verses next before-going, the Psalmist
had encited men to the feare of God: and in these
words he vndertaketh to teach them this Feare.
            In the words there are these foure parts: Invitatio,
Compellatio, Exhortatio, &amp; Pollicitatio.
            
            
               
1. An Invitation; Come.
            
            2. A Compellation; Children.
            
            3. An Exhortation; Hearken to me.
            
            4. A pollicitation or a promise; and therein
againe these foure particulars:
            The Agent, the Act, the Obiect, the Subiect.
            1. The Agent; King Dauid himselfe, the penman
of this Psalme; I.
            
            2. The Act; teaching or instructing: I will
teach.
            
            3. The Obiect, or persons to be taught; Children;
whom before he called vpon; You.
            
            4. The Subiect-matter of his teaching, that
wherein he would instruct them; the Feare of the
Lord.
            
            And of these parts and points in order, as breifly
as conueniently I may.
            In the first place then there is prompta Invitatio,
               Part 1. 
               a
free Invitation: affording vs this Lesson, (to omit
all others) that
            We had neede of all invitements &amp; incitements,Doctr. 1.
               inticements and allurements to goodnes and godlines.
Hence so many mementoes in the word of
God:Eccles. 12. 1. 
               Remember thy Creator: and,Deut 9. 7. 
               Remember,
forget not: &amp;c. so many Caveats;
               1. Tim. 4. 16. 
               Cave tibi;
Take heede to thy selfe: and,Deut. 4. 23. 
               Cavete vobis, Take yee
heede to your selues: &amp;c. so many Invitations;
               Esai. 2. 3. 
               Come, let vs goe vp to Gods house: and,Esai. 2. 5. 
               Come, let
let vs walke in the light of the Lord: and in this place,
Come, Children; hearken to me: &amp;c.
            All needfull, and all litle enough:
            1.Reason 1. In regard of our naturall auersenes to good

things.Iob. 11. 12. 
               Man by nature, saith Zophar, is like a wilde
asses Colt: as an Asses foale, for rudenes; a wilde
Asses, for vnrulinesse: vntamed and vntractable,
Ier. 2. 24. 
               as the wilde Asse in the wildernes.
            
            2.Reason 2. In regard of the difficultie of the worke.Prov. 15. 24. 
               The
way of the wise, saith wise Soloman, is vpward. We are
bred in Hell: (
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Ephes. 2. 3. 
               by Nature vessels of wrath:) and
we must climbe vp to Heauen:
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Hesiod. L
                     •
                  , Ardua virtutis via. Horat. carm. l. 3. ode 24. Sed &amp; Ovid. de Pont. 3. eleg. tendit in ardua virtus. Et S
                     ••
                  us b. l. Pun. l. 2. Ardua virtut
                     •
                  
                  ̄ profert via. 
                     •
                  Et, cilsum virꝰ. petit ardua collem. Lege Se. nec. epist. 123. 
               a long way and a
steepe. We areMens
                     •••
                   ad mel
                     ••
                  ra em
                     •
                  itur, quasi contra ictis fl
                     •
                  minis con
                     •
                  tur. &amp;c. Greg. Rom. m
                     •
                  ral. l. 11. c. 28. like those, that row against winde
and tide; we striue against the streame and current
of corrupt nature, of euill custome; we struggle
against the strong counterblasts, of bitter scoffs, and
bad counsell. We haue neede therefore of all kinde
of incouragement.
            3.Reason. 3. In regard of our pronenes to grow slacke.
2 Thess 3. 13. Galat. 69. 
               And you, my brethren, saith the Apostle, be not
weary of well-doing. We are too prone, euen the
best of vs, to wax weary on this way, to grow slacke
at this worke. It is true of vs, thatAlphius foener
                     •
                  t
                     •
                  r, cuius m
                     •
                  minit Hora
                     ••
                  ꝰ epod 2. 
               Alphius the
Usurer sometime said of his Clients,Optima n
                     •
                  mina no appellādo mala f
                     •
                  eri, Alphius 
                     〈◊〉
                   v
                     •
                  rissimè f
                     •
                  rt
                     •
                  r. Colum. de re rust l. 1. c 7. 
               Euen good
Debters will grow slacke Pay-masters, if they be let
alone, if they be not now and than called vpon.
            
            The consideration whereof may serue, First,Vse 1. to
admonish vs of our dutie one to an other.Hebr. 10. 24. 
               Let vs
obserue either other, saith the Apostle,
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               to whet on,
or to egge on, to loue and good works. So the Holy
Ghost describeth the manner of Gods Saints, quickning,
calling on, and incouraging either other.Esai. 2. 3. 
               And
many people shall goe, and say; Come, and let vs goe
vp to the Mountaine of the Lord, to the House of the
God of Iacob: and he will teach vs his wayes, and we
will walke in his paths▪
                And,Esai. 2. 5. 
               Come, ô yee house of

Iacob, and let vs walke in the light of the Lord. And
againe;Zech. 8. 21. 
               The people of one Citie shall go to another,
and say; Vp, and let vs pray before the Lord, and seeke
the Lord of hosts: and I will goe my selfe too.
            
            Now this,Application. as it is the dutie of all, so more specially
of those that conuerse familiarly togither;
most especially of those that haue care and charge
of others, Ministers and Magistrates in publike,
Parents, Scholemasters, and Masters of Families in
priuate,
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                
               to whet vp their inferiors, (it is the terme
thatDeut. 6. 7. Si
                     •
                   Prov. 27. 17. 
               Moses vseth, and the Apostle imitateth him in)
to be oft calling vpon those that be vnder their
charge, and enciting of them to those things that be
good. Remembring, that as the Heathen man saith
that those that correct but instruct not, are
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plu. praecept. polit. 
               like
those that snuffe the light oft, but put no oyle into the
lampe; so those that instruct but incite not, are like
those that put in oyle enough, yea enough it may be
to drowne the light, (that which may oft soone be
done,) but are not carefull or mindfull to raise and
pull vp the weeke, which vnlesse it be in due time
still done, the light will of it selfe soone decay and
wax dimme, though there be no defect of liquor to
feede it withall.
            Secondly,Vse 2. as we must our selues call vpon others;
so we must be content to be called vpon by others.
Inferiors especially and learners, children, seruants,
or others, must not thinke much to be frequently
called vpon by their Superiors: they must not account
it any disgrace or disparagement vnto them,
that they are oft admonished, incited and called vpon
in this kinde.2. Pet. 1. 12. 
               I will not be negligent, saith Peter,

to put you in mind of these things, though you haue knowledge,
though you know the truth already, and be
established in it. Yea,R
                     •
                  m. 15. 14, 
                     ••
                  . 
               Though I be perswaded of you,
saith the Apostle Paul, that you are full of goodnes, and
of all knowledge, &amp; able to admonish one an other: yet I
am bold by writing to put you in minde of these things.
Yea,
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                
               It is not tedious to me to goe ouer the same
things oft with you; and it is the safest course for you.
So that
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                euen those that are best grounded, that
haue aboundance of sound knowledge, that are full
of grace and goodnes, that are the greatest proficients,
and forwardest Schollers in Christs Schoole,
yet may stand oft in neede of being whet vp, and
put on: much more such as are but rude and raw,
as are but nouices and dullards, as are scarce, it may
be, yet of the first forme in Christs SchoolePlantas ne
                     ••••
                   
                  
                     ••
                  quemius adaq
                     ••
                  re pr
                     ••
                  erit. P
                     ••
                  
                  m
                     •
                  s. in Pi
                     ••
                  ip. 
                     ••
                   Greg. Rom. m
                     •
                  ral. l. 27. c. 14. Tender
plants and new planted haue neede oft to be watred;
they are in danger else to windle and wither
away. And Gods grace and good things in vs are
like a dull sea-cole fire, which if it be not now and
then blowen orH
                     •
                  u
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  m
                     •
                  nemur 2. Timo. 1. 6. stirred vp, though there be no
want of fewell, yet will of it selfe at length dye and
goe out.
            
               In the next place there is as prompt
                  •
               
               Part 2. Inuitatio, so
blanda Compellatio: as a free Inuitation, so a sweete
and louing Compellation: Children.
            The Name of Children is a most sweet Name,
sauouring strongly of Loue; and vsed therefore so
oft by
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  . 13. 23. &amp; 21. 7. that Disciple of Loue, and of Christs loue in
that Epistle of his that breatheth nothing but Loue:
1. Iohn 3. 17. &amp; 4. 7. 
               
                  
                     •
                  ittle Children, let vs loue one another, not in word
and tongue, but in deede and truth: and,1. Ioh 3. 7. 
               Little Children,

let no man deceaue you: And,1 Iho. 5. 21. 
               Little Children
keepe your selues from Idoles, &amp;c.
               Dectr. 2. And it sheweth
what louing affection ought to be betweene teacher
and taught: euen such as is betweene naturall Parents
and Children. That which the Apostle Paul
so oft, and in so liuely manner expresseth in himselfe,
when he compareth himselfe, sometime to a
Father;
               1. Thess. 2. 11. 
               I exhorted you and besought you, as a Father
his Children: sometime to a Mother;
               Galat. 4. 19. 
               My little
Children, of whom I trauaile againe, till Christ be
formed in you: sometime to a Nurse;
               1. Thess. 2. 7. 
               Wee were
gentle among you, as a Nurse cherisheth her Children.
            
            And great reason is there that so it should be:Reason. 1.
            
            For first,Exod. 20. 12. Deut. 5. 16. God hath giuen the name of Parents
vnto them: he hath comprehended all Superiors
vnder that head.
            And surely, if other masters haue the name of
Father giuen them: as2 King. 5. 13. 
               Naamans seruants giue it
him: Schoole-masters much more. They are in
some kinde, vnder God, (to vse the Apostles tearm)
Hebr. 12. 9. 
               patres spirituum, the Fathers of mens Spirits. Our
Parents are instruments vnder God, for the producing
of our Bodies the baser part: they are instruments
vnder him, for the framing and moulding of
our mindes and soules, the better and more principall
part of vs.
            Yea,Reason. 2. as the Apostle Paul saith of the Corinthians,
that1. Cor. 4. 15. he was their Father, because by his Ministery
he had begotten them to God: so such Schoole-masters
as are carefull and conscionable of their dutie in
that kinde, may well say of their Schollers that they
are their children in Christ, as the same Paul stileth

               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 1 Timo. 1. 2. 1. Tit. 1. 4. 
               Timothie and l 
               Titus else-where; since that many
(no doubt) of them receaue the first seedes and
graines, and beginnings of faith and feare of God,
and other sauing and sanctifying grace from them.
            Againe,Reason. 3. this the rather is as equall, so needfull;
because that where no loue is, there is little hope
of learning. Little hope there is, that the master
should doe his Schollers good, if hee loue not
them: and as little hope is there, that the Schollers
should receaue good from him or profit by him,
vnles they loue him.
            That which serueth in the First place to admonish
all teachers and instructors,Vse. 1. either publike or priuate,
how they ought to be affected toward those
that are committed to their charge. As one saith of
a good Prince, thatPrinceps pius nunquam carebit l. b
                     •
                  ris: Totius est regni pater. Princeps abunda
                     •
                   ergò faelicissimus Tet liberis, quot subditis. Th. Morus in epigram. 
               he hath as many Sonnes as hee
hath subiects, and is therefore as a kinde and louing
Father to them: so should the Schoole-master make
account that he hath in some sort, as many Children
as Schollers that be vnder his charge;
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Homer de Vlysse Odyss. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Xenop
                     ••
                   Cyripae. l. l. 8. and therefore
cary himselfe toward them in kinde and louing
manner, euen as if he were a naturall Father
vnto them.
            Which kinde and louing cariage,Cantion. or Fatherly
affection, yet is not so to be interpreted, as if it were
vtterly to exclude and cut of all just reproofe and
due correction, when occasions shall require it.
That was the fault of1 Sam. 2. 2
                     •
                  . 
                     •
                  euis obi
                     ••
                  gatio 
                     〈◊〉
                   satisfe
                     •
                  erat discipli
                     ••
                  . Salpit. hist. sacr. l. 1. 
               Eli, and1 King. 1. 6. 
               Dauid too, though
worthy men of God otherwise; and it prooued
1 Sam. 4 18. a breake-necke to the one, and2 Sam. 15. 12. 1 King. 1. 5. an heart-sore to
the other.Pro
                     •
                  . 29. 15. 
               The r
                     •
                  d and correction giue instruction,
saith Salomon; but a childe left to himselfe is the

confusion of hir that bare him. And,Prov. 13. 24. 
               He that spareth
the rod, hateth his Sonne; but he that loueth him, chastneth
him betimes.
               Mango blanditur, vt corrumpat; Pater minatur, vt corrigat. Aug. in 1. Ioan. tract. 7. The seducer speaketh the childe
faire to marre him; the Father handleth him roughly
to amend him:Pius est f
                     •
                  riendo; crudelus esset parcendo, ldem de 
                     •
                  ēp. 94. He is kind in correcting him;
he were cruell in sparing him.
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Aristotel. ethic. Nicom. l 2. 
               Correction is a kinde
of cure. A faire hand, we say commonly, maketh a
foule wound.
               Quid tam pium quā medicus ferens ferramentis? saeuit in vulnus vt homo sauetur: quia 
                     〈◊〉
                   vult
                     •
                  ꝰ palpetur, homo perditur. Aug. de verb. Dom. 15. The Surgion searcheth the wound
to the quicke, that he may saue the mans life: for
he should endanger the one, if he delt but superficially
with the other.
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , (1. Cor. 15. 55) 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Basil. in ascet. q. 4. 
               He is not cruell that diggeth
and gasheth the flesh, to get out a sting, or a splinter,
that will not out otherwise: he is cruell rather, that
(out of a fond pitifulnesse) letteth it alone: Nor
he cruell, that giueth correction, when it is requisite
and needfull, but he rather that then withholdeth
it.
            
               Reproofe therefore, yea correction too, may well
stand with Loue.
               Apoc. 3. 19. As many as I loue, I rebuke, saith
our Sauiour. And, God, saith
               Hebr. 12. 6. 
               the Apostle after
               Prov. 3. 12. Salomon, whom he loueth, he correcteth; and he scourgeth
euery Sonne that he receiueth.Molestus est &amp; Medicus furenti phrene
                     •
                  ico, &amp; Pater indisciplinato filio, ille ligando, ille caedendo, sed ambo diligendo. Si autem illos negligant, &amp; perire permittant, ista poti
                     ••
                   mansuetudo falsa, crudelis est. Aug. epist. 50. The Physitian is
troublesome to the frantick Patient, and the Father to
the vnruly Childe; the one in binding him, the other in
beating him: and yet both doe what they doe out of
Loue.
            Yea seueritie and sharpnes may in some cases
well agree with it.Tit. 1. 13. 
               Rebuke them
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . rigidè Biza i
                     •
                   not. 
               sharply, saith Paul
to Titus of some, that they may be found sound in the
Faith. And, to vse an Hethen mans comparison;
            
               
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . &amp;c. Dion Chrys
                     •
                  st. orat 78. A Surgion had he two persons to cut for the stone,
the one his deere Frend, the other a meere Stranger,
would he be so foolish, thinke we, out of loue and
fauour to his frend, as to cut him with a blunter
toole or razer then he would cut the other with?
            It is not ment therefore, when kind and louing
cariage is required of Instructors and Teachers, that
they should not therefore either correct or reproue:
But thatSrie tateas, dilectione taceas: sine cl
                     •
                  m
                     •
                  s, di
                     •
                  ectione clam 
                     ••
                  si
                     •
                  eparcas, d
                     •
                  iect
                     ••
                  n
                     •
                   parecas: sine corrigas, dilect
                     ••
                  e corrigas. A
                     •
                  i disciplinū si
                     •
                  ni 
                     〈◊〉
                   di
                     ••
                  ante 
                     •
                  h
                     •
                  ritate. Omnia de charitatis pro
                     •
                  d
                     •
                  nt rad
                     ••
                  e. D
                     ••
                  ge, &amp; quod
                     ••
                  s fat. Aug. in 1. Ioan. tract. 7. whither they teach, or instruct, or reproue,
or correct, they1. Cor. 16. 14. 
               do, according to the Apostles rule,
all in Loue, and in louing manner: That they striue
in the first placeVeluti pueris dant crus
                     •
                  ula 
                     •
                  landi D
                     •
                  ctores el
                     •
                  m n
                  
                     ••
                   velint vt discere trim
                     •
                  . Hor. sat. 1. by all milde and gentle vsage to
win them, and by faire words and rewards to entice
and allure, as
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   A
                     •
                  ciet D
                     •
                  us la
                     •
                  etū Gen. 9. 27 E: H
                     •
                  sh 2 14. Alliciā eā, &amp; 
                     •
                  quar ad cor eiꝰ God himselfe is wont to deale with
vs. And againe, when they shall be constrained to
take rougher courses with them; yet that then also
theyL
                     •
                   seuerita
                     •
                  ē mansuetud
                     •
                   condiat, 
                     〈◊〉
                   mansuetuainē, ne disselu
                     •
                  a sit, di striction
                     •
                   seueritas ac
                  
                     ••
                  ndat Greg. 
                     •
                  o. in Euāg. bō. 17. Ne aut districtio sit rigida, aut 
                     ••
                  etas remissa. Idem de pastore part. 2. cap. 6. Remissio no vitians, correptio nō cruemans: &amp; seueritas etiam tēperamenti, quae nō sit titra, 
                     〈◊〉
                   te
                     ••
                  ca. Sidou. epist. 9 lib. 4. &amp; Radevic de gest. Frid. l. 2. Quae sangnin
                     •
                  m effundat p
                     •
                  u tius g
                     •
                  m effund. 1. Tertull. ap
                     •
                  l
                     •
                  g temper seueritie with lenitie, and allay the
sharpnes of the one with some mild dash of the
other:
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Galat. 6. 1. tanquam membrum luxatum in lo. um proprium, ad situm na
                     ••
                  vum reducrte. Sirigel. ad Gal. 
               Restore the offendor, saith the Apostle, with
the spirit of lenitie; as
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Paul. Aegin. the Surgion setteth and restoreth
a limme dislocated to his proper place and
due site againe, with as litle paine, as needs must, to
the party: Do as
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . D
                     ••
                  n C
                     ••
                  risest. orat. 33. - v
                     •
                  luti pueris a
                     •
                   sin
                     ••
                  ia tetra midentis Cum dare conantur, prius oras p
                     ••
                  ula 
                     〈…〉
                   dulci mellis sta
                     ••
                  
                  
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   liquore, Vt puerorum atas improuida ludificetur Labr
                     •
                  rum tenus; interea perpotet amarum Absinthi laticem, decepta
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   non capatur, Sed potius tali facto recereata val
                     ••
                   it. Lucret de r
                     •
                  r, nat. l. 4. those that giue Children wormwood

or aloës for the wormes, they sweeten the
brims of the cup with honie, or mix it with wine or
milke, or some other such sweet thing to make
them take it the more willingly, and giue them a litle
sugar after to sweeten their mouths with againe: or
as
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Basil. &amp; Euthym. praefat. in Psal. Sapientes mediei, siquando vsus popescerit, vt austeriora medicamenta agris o
                     ••
                  erant mortalibꝰ: ne aeger vtilitatem pr
                     •
                   austeritate refugiat, ora ac sammitates poculi quo remediū perrigūt, m
                     •
                  lle 
                     ••
                  cuml
                     •
                  nunt. Aug. ibid. those that giue bitter pils to queesie stomached
patients, they wrap them vp in some conserue, or in
the pap of an apple, that they may with as litle offence
as may be take them in, and the better 
                  •
               eepe
and retaine them when they be downe: So order
and temper their reproofe and their correction, that
it may appeare not to proceed from spleene, or
grudge, or choler, or some other such peeuish and
sinister humor; but that euen by the very manner
of it, and the affection shewed in it, it may be seene
to issue from a louing minde, and to aime at nothing
but the well-doing of the party either corrected or
reproued.
            In a word, let Teachers and Instructers remember
what the Heathen man truly saith, thatNull
                     •
                  
                  ̄ est animal morosius homine, quod
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   arte mai
                     •
                  re tract
                     •
                  ri debeat. Sē. de clement. l. 1. c. 17. 
               there is no
liuing creature more wayward naturally then Man, nor
that neede to be managed with more discretion and
skill.
            
            Secondly,Vse 2. let Schollers learne hence how they are
to esteem of their Teachers, and how to cary themselues
towards them; euen to reuerence them, &amp; to
affect them as Parents.1. Thess. 5. 12, 13. 
               I beseech you, saith the Apostle,
that you would take notice of them, that take paines
with you, and that admonish you; and that you would
haue them in singular loue for their worke sake.
            
            The Heathen themselues could say, thatDijs, Paren
                     •
                  ibꝰ, &amp; Praeceptoribus nihil pro merit
                     •
                   posse rependie. 
               to God,
a mans Parents, and his Teachers, sufficient requitall

could neuer be made. And no maruaile. For if the
Teachers do as they ought, and the Schollers likewise
make that vse of them that they should, they
may well say of them as Paul doth to Philemon,
               Philem. 19. 
               Etiam animam mihi debes, that they owe them their
very soules; as hauing bin a meanes euenProv 23. 14. Iam. 5. 20. 
               to saue
their soules. And how ought they to loue them
from the heart, whom they owe their very soules
vnto?
            Far be it from any here then, to be like those
wicked wretches, whom the Prophet inveigheth against,Am
                     ••
                   5. 16.
               that hate those that reproue them: to hate
their Instructors, because they are sometime also
necessarily Reprouers or Correctors, to hate them
for that, for which they ought rather to loue them.
You must not, asPsal 32. 9. this our Psalmist speaketh, be as
Horse or Mule that are without vnderstanding. Horses
and Mules can well endure and are wontEsai. 1. 3. to take
notice of those that feed them, and stroake them,
and make much of them; butIumenta eos calce morsu
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   appetunt, à q
                     •
                  bus corum curā. da vul
                     ••
                  ra contrectantur. Aug epist. 
                     •
                  0. &amp; hemil. 24. they cannot endure
those that come about them to drench them, or
bleed them, or to meddle with their sores, though
they entend nothing therein but their good: because
they haue sense, whereby they perceaue some present
good in the one; but they haue no reason to
apprehend any future good in the other. Creatures
endued with reason, must be wiser then they: and
loue their Teacher, as well reproouing and correcting,
when just occasion is, as speaking faire and
commending: asMedicum 
                     ••
                  vr
                     •
                  n em &amp; secam
                     •
                  m 
                     〈◊〉
                   quem &amp; a
                     •
                   r
                     •
                  endum a
                     •
                   s
                     •
                  
                  
                  
                     ••
                  nd 
                     •
                  mem
                     •
                  uci
                     •
                  ꝰ 
                     •••
                  res. in Psal. men were wont to esteeme
themselues beholden to the Surgion, as well for opening
the vlcer, and letting out the corrupt matter,

as for healing vp the wound againe.
            They must remember what the wise man saith,
thatProv. 12. 1. 
               he that hateth Instruction &amp; Correction, and so
he that hateth his Instructors and Correctors, is a
Foole: yea,Prov. 15 10. 
               he that hateth either, shall die.
            
            In the third place followeth,Part 3. 
               Seria exhortatio,
               Doctr. 3. 
               a
serious Exhortation: Hearken vnto me. Wherein is
expressed, the principall duty of Children, Schollers
and Learners, to hearken vnto their Parents,
Instructors and Teachers. That for which Salomon
so oft calleth vpon those that hee dealeth with:
Prov. 4. 1. 
               Heare, O yee Children, the instruction of a Father,
and giue eare to learne vnderstanding: and,Prov. 4. 20. 
               My Son;
hearken vnto my words, and encline thine eares to my
sayings. and,Prov. 5. 7. 
               Heare me now therefore, O Children,
and hearken vnto the words of my mouth, &amp;c.
            
            And great reason they so should.
            For first,Reason 1. it is their wisdome so to doe,Prov. 13. 1. 
               A wise
Sonne, saith Salomon, will hearken to his Fathers instruction.
And,Prov. 12. 15. 
               Hee that hearkneth to good aduice
is wise.
               Prov. 3. 7. &amp; 26. 12. B
                     ••
                  d
                     •
                  sipi
                     •
                  , quisibi sap
                     •
                  t. No greater folly in young people, then
to thinke themselues wise enough,Corsilij satis est in 
                     〈◊〉
                   m
                     •
                  mi
                     •
                  i. Aracl
                     •
                  ne apud Ouid. met. l. 6. able enough
to aduise and to guide themselues well enough, and
to stand in no neede of direction or aduice. You
know well what the famous sentence so oft cited
saith:
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Hesiod. oper. l. 1. &amp; Arist. 
                     •
                  thi
                     •
                  . l. 1. c. 4. Paucis animus sui rector optimꝰ. Moeneri v
                     •
                  lle ac posse s
                     •
                  cunda virtus est. Senet. de benefic. l. 5. c. 25. 
               He is the best man that can of himselfe discerne,
what is fit and meete to be done. He is the next
him, that can hearken to good aduice giuen him by others:
But he that neither can see what is fit of himself,
nor will follow the good counsell that others shall
giue, such a one is as an vnprofitable limme in the bodie,
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
                     〈◊〉
                   invtile pondu
                     •
                  . Homer. Il
                     •
                  ad. 6. &amp; Odyss. 
                     •
                  . 
               and a very burden to the earth that beareth him.
               
Children and young people, since they cannot bee
in the first ranke: (because
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . S
                     •
                  phccl. 
                     •
                  seru venit vsu
                     •
                   ab a
                     •
                  nis. Ovid. m
                     •
                  
                  tam 1. 6. Quisquis sen
                     •
                  x ad sapientiam per venit, annis p
                     •
                  rvenit. Sen. ep. 68. age bringeth experience,
and skill requireth yeeres:) they must be content
to be in the second; least they come within
compas of the third.
            Secondly,Reason 2. it is impiety in some sort to doe otherwise,
Ezech 3. 7. 
               They will not heare thee; saith God to the
Prophet: for they will not heare mee. And surely

                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Philo de Decalog. the fift Commandement, (as Philo the Iew well
obserueth, who therefore also maketh it a branch of
the first Table, and so diuideth the Tables equally,
assigning fiue precepts to either:) it is a mixt Commandement,
and differeth somewhat from the rest
of those in the Second Table; they consider Man
as our neighbour, in nature like vs, this as Gods Deputy,
standing in his steed, by him set ouer vs, and
in his name, and by his authority, performing offices
about vs. And therefore when such instruct and
admonish,2. Cor. 13. 3. God doth it by them.Quicquid obedientiae exhibetur, et exhibetur, qui dicit: Qui vos qudit, me audit. Bern. de grad. obed. Luk. 10. 19. When wee
hearken to them, we hearken to him in them: when
we refuse to regard them, wee contemne him in
them. Neither can such contempt be cleered from
some taint of impiety.Vse.
            
            Let this briefely then admonish Children, to
hearken to, and take to heart the good and wholesome
admonitions of their Parents, Instructors,
Tutors, and Teachers,Aur
                     •
                   prima mortis 
                     〈◊〉
                  , prima ap
                     •
                  riatur saluto. Bern. a
                     •
                  i
                     •
                  ubi. 
               Let the Eare, saith Bernard,
that was once opened to let in death and destruction, by
hearkning to euill counsaile; be now set wide open to
let in life and Saluation, by giuing eare to good aduice.
Let your eares withHomer. Odyss. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Sapiens 
                     〈…〉
                   aures quibus cer
                     •
                  m pari
                     •
                   est obdere. spissament
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  pus est, qu
                     ••
                   vsumin s
                     •
                  cijs Vlyxē ferunt. Sen. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . 31. 
               Vlysses (to deale with
you out of your owne learning) bee close shut

against the Sirens songs of such as shallRom. 16. 18. by faire
words and smooth language, goe about to seduce
you, and to with-drawe you from that, wherein
consisteth your speciall good; that shall seeke to
bring you out of loue with your Instructors, or
with those courses that are by them taken with you
for your good. But let your eares bee open, and
your hearts pliable to attend vnto them, their instructions
and admonitions, andQuia vtile est i
                     •
                  ventuti regi, impositi sunt 
                     〈◊〉
                   quasi Magistratus d
                     •
                  mestici, sub quibus contineretur. S
                     •
                  n. de ben. l. 3. c. 11. yeeld your selues
wholy vnto them to be ruled, guided and directed
by them.
            There is a Blessing of God promised on those
that so doe:Prov. 8. 32, 33. a Blessing of wisdome, a Blessing of
long Life.Prov. 15. 31. 
               The eare, saith Salomon, that hearkeneth
to the instruction of life, shall lodge among the wise.
And,Ephes 6. 2, 3. 
               It is the first Commandement, saith the Apostle,
in the Decalogue, that hath a speciall promise
annexed to it;Exod. 20. 12. Deut. 5. 16. Math. 15. 4. &amp; 19. 9. 
               Honour thy Father and thy Mother;
(and Instructors, as we heard before, are as Parents:)
that it may goe well with thee, and that thou
maist be
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               long-liued.
            
            As on the other side, there is a Curse of God denounced
against those that do otherwise, thatPsal. 58. 4, 5. 
               stop
their eares, like the deafe Adder, against good admonition,
and refuse to heare the Charmers voice,
charme he neuer so sweetly, to be ruled by their
Gouernors, deale they neuer so kindly and louingly
with them.Prov. 30. 6. 
               The eye that scorneth the Father, or setteth
light by the Mothers admonition,
               Effosses oculos roret a
                     •
                  ro gutture corvus. Catull. in Comin. 
               let the rauens of
the valley dig it out, and the young Eagles devoure it.
They are cursed with a witnes, whom the Holy
Ghost thus curseth, in such emphaticall manner, in

such exquisite termes, as may well make ones heart
quake to heare.
            Yea, to do otherwise it is made a note of a reprobate
and a cast-away, of one that God is fully determined
euerlastingly to damne and destroy;2 Chron. 25. 16. 
               I know,
saith the Prophet to Amaziah, that God is determined
to destroy thee, because thou doest thus, and wilt not
hearken to mine advice. And of Elies Sonnes, saith
the Holy Ghost,1. Sam. 2 25. 
               Notwithstanding they obeyed not
the voice of their Father, because the Lord was bent to
slay them. We are wont to say of those that haue
Plague-spots, that they haue Gods tokens vpon them,
and such are seldome knowne to scape or recouer.
Of such vngratious Children we may much better
say, that they haue Gods tokens indeed on them; and
such (obserue it when you will) you shall seldome
see come to good.
            In the fourthPart 4. and last place commeth benigna pollicitatio,
a kinde pollicitation or promise.
            And in it consider we, according to our former
Division;
            First,Branch 1. 
               the Agent, or person teaching, King Dauid
himselfe. AsEccles. 1. 1, 12. 
               Salomon his Sonne, thought a King,
scorned not the title of a Preacher; so Dauid his
Father, though a worthy Prince, thought no scorne
to play the part of a Scholemaster, to be a Teacher
of Children,
               Doctrine 4. euen of pety Schollers, of litle
ones.
            Whence obserue we, that Teaching euen of Children
is no base profession; it is that, that may well
beseem euen the greatest Abraham, though aGen. 23. 6. 
               Prince
of God, orSic Montes Dei. i. ingentes. Psal. 
                     •
                  6. 6. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Arat. in diosem. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . T
                     ••
                  on. in schol. a great Prince, yet was carefull himself

               Genes. 18. 19. 
               to teach his sonnes and his seruants (God himselfe
testifieth it of him, and commendeth it in him) to
keep Gods commandements. Dauid, thoughPsal. 78. 71. the cheife
Gouernor of Gods people, andPsal. 18. 43. the Head of many
Heathen, yet inviteth Children here to come to him,
and promiseth himselfe to instruct them: as also elswhere,
Psal. 32. 9. 
               I will instruct &amp; teach thee what way to take,
I will guide thee with mine eye. And Salomon,
               1. King. 3. 12. 2. Chron. 2. 12. the
wisest meere man that was euer since Adam, thought
it no disparagement either to his place or his person
Prov. 4. 1, 2. to giue instructions &amp; directions to the Children
that God gaue him. Yea, as our Sauiour saith,Matth. 12 42. 
               Behold
one greater then either
               Math. 22. 43, 44▪
                
               Dauid or Salomon. Our
Sauiour himselfe,Math. 19. 13, 14, 15. when Children were presented
vnto him, and his Disciples would haue kept them
backe from him, as supposing it too meane a busines
for him to be employed in, was displeased with
them for so doing, and called the Children vnto
him. And he that was so forward to embrace them
and blesse them, was (no doubt of it) as ready also
to teach and instruct them, so oft as oportunitie was
offred him.
            Neither ought any to disdaine or thinke meanly
of this office. For
            1.Reason 1. It is an office that hath bin formerly performed
to them by others. We are all naturally as
wild trees, that by manuring and husbandry become
fruitfull &amp; vseful. We brought neither Grace,
nor Art into the world with vs. If we haue ought of
either, we haue bin taught it by others. And we
should not think much to perform that office vnto
others, that by others hath bin formerly performed

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
vnto vs. Salomon thinketh no scorne to instruct
his Sonne,Prov. 4. 3, 4. because his Father instructed him in
like manner before.
            2.Reason 2. It is an office most necessarie and of singular
vse.Op
                     •
                  rum Fastigia s
                     •
                  ectantur, latent Fandamenta. Qui. til. institut. prasat. Pius 
                     •
                  abet 
                     •
                  peris 
                     〈◊〉
                  . mostentatio
                     ••
                  . Ibid l. 1 c. 4. It is the foundation, that lieth lowest, vnder
ground, out of sight, that though it maketh least
shew, yetNon sunt cont
                     •
                  
                  nenda qua
                     •
                  si para
                     •
                  , fine quibus magne constare 
                     〈◊〉
                   ssunt Hierom ad laetam Ad nullius res summem ni
                     •
                   prae edenti us intiijs pervenatur. M
                     •
                  n ra
                     •
                  sta si negligantur, n
                     •
                  n 
                     •
                  rit mat
                     •
                  ribus 
                     •
                  o
                     •
                  ꝰ. Q
                     •••
                  til. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . praefat. De
                     ••
                  le fundamentū fal. 
                     •
                  t opꝰ. 
                     〈◊〉
                   de 
                     •
                  r
                     •
                  mm
                     ••
                  ca. Nec stqui
                     •
                   di
                     •
                  cere satis nō est, Quin
                     •••
                   
                  
                     ••
                  st
                     •
                  t. l. 1. c. 1. beareth vp the whole building. As
Kingdomes and States consist of Cities &amp; Townes,
so these of priuate Families; the well-being whereof
mainely dependeth vpon the carefull education
and training vp of the youth in them.
            The consideration whereof may serue first to
take away the vnjust and frivolous aspersions, that
either rude &amp; ignorant, or prophane and irreligious
persons do vsually cast vpon this profession. Where
it is strange to see, (and it argueth the great corruption
of mans nature,) how that those Callings that
God hath most graced in the Word, are commonly
most disgraced and contemned in the World. How
meanely do most men think of a Preist or a Pedant?
as in scorne they vse to terme them the one and the
other.Vse 1. And yetLevit. 10. 3. N
                     •
                  m. 16 9. who come neerer to God then the
Ministers of his word? Or who come neerer to
Ministers then Schole-masters do? What is their
Schole but a priuate Church? if it be ordred as it
ought. If1. Cor. 16. 19. Christian Families be so, Christian
Scholes much more. Or what are they themselues,
(if they be at least that they should be) but priuate
Catechists, but priuate Preachers? But as he saith,
Scientia non habet iuimicum nisi ignorantem. 
               Skill hath no foe of any, but such as are vnskilfull
themselues: so none will thinke basely of so worthy
and honourable a Calling, but those that are themselues

either rude dolts or debauched rake-hels.
            Secondly, it may serue to approue and commend
the prudent and pious practise of those,Vse 2. that are
carefull to giue incouragement to those of this profession,
and to prouide such meanes for the maintainance
of them, that men of worth and good parts
may be employed in such places: As also, to incite
others, whom God hath blessed with meanes and
abilitie, to all due care and caution in this kinde, as
being a businesse, wherevpon the good both of
Church and State mainely dependeth. AsEccles. 5. 9. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Socrates. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Xenoph. 
                     ••
                  conom. 
               Salomon
saith, that the Throne (or the Chaire of Estate) is vpheld
by the Plough: so we may truly say, that both
Church and State are vpheld by the Schole. For let
priuate Scholes be neglected, whence shall the Uniuersities
be supplied? whence shall the Ministerie be
prouided? how shall they teach others, that were
themselues neuer taught? how shall the cheife
Offices be furnished with men of abilitie either in
Church or Common-weale? Both Religion and
Learning will soone dye and decay, if life be not
kept and maintained in the roote.
            And here can I not wholy passe by in silence,
nor forbeare to put you of this place, in minde,Application. of
those two Honourable Knights,Sr Andrew Iudde. the Grand-Father,
andSr Thomas Smith. the Grand-Child, the one long since
deceassed, the other yet liuing; whom God hath
made Instruments of a great blessing, in this kinde,
to this place. The former of them first founded
a free Schole among you, for the training vp of
your youth in vertue, religion, and good learning,
and left land and meanes to maintaine

it, with stipends (such as were in those times ordinarie)
for Schole-master and Ushier. The latter
of them hath added liberally to his Grand-Fathers
gift, hath increased the salaries of the Teachers, and
beside sundry yeerely pensions to the poore both
of this place, and of diuers others neere about you,
to incourage Parents the rather to set their Children
to learning, and the Children to bend their minds
and endevours thereunto, hath giuen aSeuenty pounds per annum. large and
liberall exhibition for the maintainance of seuen
Schollers in one of the Uniuersities, to be chosen
successiuely each yeere from your Schole. The
Lord reward this his bounty and liberalitie aboundantly
into the bosome o
                  •
                Him and His; giue you
grace to make a good v
                  •
               e of it; and stir vp many
more whom he hath b
                  •
               essed with abilitie,Branch 2. to shew
their thankfulnes in like maner to him from whom
they haue it,Doctrine 5. by setting apart and consecrating some
part of their meanes, to the furtherance and aduancement
of religion and learning.
            Hitherto of the Agent: the Act followeth, and
that is Teaching or Instruction: I will teach.
               Reason 1.
            
            Here is the Scholemasters worke to teach, to instruct.
Psal 32. 9. 
               I will instruct thee, and teach thee, saith our
Psalmist els-where. And,Prov 4 3, 4. 
               when I was young and
tender, my Father taught me, saith Salomon. A worke
and dutie of great necessitie.
            For the soule of man is naturally instar tabulae
abrasae, as a cleane paire of tables, that haue nothing
at all written in them.Nemo nase
                     •
                  tur art
                     •
                  sex. Non dat natura virtutem. Ars est bonis s
                     ••
                  i. Virt
                     •
                  s nō cont
                     •
                  ngil animo nistinstituto &amp; edocto, &amp; ad summum assidua exercitatione perducto. Ad hoc quidem, sed non cum ho: nascimur. Et in opti
                     ••
                   etiam, an
                     •
                  equam erudias, virtutu materia, nō virtus est. Senec. epist. 8. There is no grace or goodnes,
learning or art naturally written in it: howsoeuer
some grounds there are, whereby these things

may through industry &amp; Gods blessing be attained.
            Yea in regard of grace and goodnes,Reason 2. it is instar
codicis depravati, as a booke blurred and blotted, or
depraued and misprinted, that must haue much rased
and done out, ere it can be well corrected, or that
written into it, that it ought to haue.
            It isVt og
                     •
                  r quam vi
                     •
                   fertilis fine cal
                     ••
                  ra fructu
                     •
                  sus esse non p
                     •
                  test: sic fine doctrina an
                     •••
                  us. Cic. T
                     ••
                  cul. l. 2. Cult
                     •
                  t
                     •
                   a
                     ••
                  mi plalos phia est, quae ex
                     •
                  ra
                     •
                   it v
                     •
                  tra radicif
                     ••
                  s; &amp; praeparat anim
                     •
                  s ad satus accipend
                     ••
                  ; ea
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   mandat his &amp; s
                     •
                  rit, quae adul
                     •
                  a fructus vberrimo
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  erant. Ibid. 
               instar agri inculti, as an vntilled ground,
whereinlucultis vrenda filix innascitur agris. Horat. sat. 2. Et iniussa viresc
                     ••
                  t Cra
                     ••••
                  . Virg. Geog. l. 1. weedes of all sorts come vp of themselues
naturally, but no good thing will grow without
mucking &amp; manuring, without much trauell &amp;
toyle: it is a mother, (as
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Terra sponte nascentium mater, consitorum est neuerca. Aesop. apud Planudem in vita ipsius. he said of the Earth sometime)
to the one, it is but a stepdame to the other.
            And first, what a great mercy of God then is this
to this Land, and more specially to this place and
many others, that vouchsafeth such meanes, and
stirreth vp the hearts and mindes of worthy men to
establish such courses, whereby instruction and learning
may be conveighed to vs and our Children,
may be wrought into vs and them, that we may not
be like sauage people, no better then brute beasts;
yea in some regard worse; since
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . P
                     •
                  tus est comparati 
                     •
                  umento, quàm nas
                     •
                  i i
                     •
                  mentum. Chrys. 
                     ••
                  mil. in Asc
                     •
                  us. Domini. 
               It is worse, as that
Auncient Father well saith, to be like vnto a beast, then
to be a beast indeede. O learne, if you be wise, to
know your owne happines before many others, to
acknowledge Gods goodnes to you aboue many others,
and to shew your selues thankfull both to
Him, and to Those, that he vseth as Instruments to
prouide such things for you.
            Againe, let this admonish Teachers of their Dutie,
and encite them vnto the diligent performance
of it; as they beare the name, so to execute the
Office; as they receiue the wages,Vse 2. so to doe the

worke; as they haue vndertaken the charge of it,
so to vndergo the burden of it, and discharge faithfully
the trust of so great a weight, that the Parents
of their Children haue entrusted them withall, euen
the soules of those their Children, not their bodies
onely, as deare to them as themselues.
            Otherwise, if they shall beare the name of Teachers,
and not execute the Office, they shall be but
Idols; or, as the Prophet saith,
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   11.17. 
               Idol-shepherds, so
Idol-Teachers: like Idols, that haue
                  
                     〈…〉
                  . 5. the name, but
Galat. 4. 8. not the nature of God; that haue limmes and lineaments
of a man, but no action nor life;Psal. 115. 5, 6, 7. that
haue mouths, but speake not; hands but feele not; feet,
but stir not. &amp;c.
            If they take the wages, and do not the worke, they
shall be no better then Theeues. As he said sometime
in Socrates, that
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Socrat 
                     〈◊〉
                  . Eccles. lib 4. c. p 23. Mon
                     ••
                  c
                     •
                  us ut 
                     ••
                  per
                     ••
                  us f
                     •
                  urtis prae
                     ••
                  
                  
                  
                     •
                  i 
                     •
                  ar cens
                     •
                  tur. Cassio
                     •••
                  . i. est. tr
                     •
                  part. l. 
                     ••
                   1. 
               the Monck that laboured not with
his hands for his liuing was a Theife: so the Scholemaster
that laboureth not with his tongue in instructing
his Schollers; yea though he labour with his
hands otherwise neuer so much, yet if he tend not
his Schole, and the instruction of those vnder his
charge in it, he is as very a Theife, as he that taketh
a purse by the high-way side; he might as well pick
their Parents purses or pockets.
            Yea, if he be wholy carelesse of the discharge of
his dutie herein, he is litle better then a Murtherer▪
               
he becommeth guilty of soule-murther: as Bernard
truly saith of Parents negligent in the education
of their Children, that they arePeremptores potius quàm parentes. Bern. in Epist. 111. 
               rather Paricides
then Parents. For he is a murtherer, not onely
that knocketh a man on the head, or cutteth his

throat with a knife, or runneth him through with a
Rapier; but he also that by detention or deniall of
due foode starueth him whom he stood bound to
feede and releeue, and so suffreth him to perish
through his default.
            As therefore you are called Teachers, and are called
to teach, so be you carefull toN
                     •
                  men tuum attend
                     •
                  . I
                     ••
                  o quod 
                     〈◊〉
                   Hieron. ad 
                     〈◊〉
                  . answer your
Name, to be that, that you are termed. Apply your
selues with all alacritie, sedulitie and diligence, to
this necessarie, to this worthy worke. Neither let it
discourage you, if you meete with some foolish and
vnthankfull persons or Parents, that shall either
slenderly consider your trauell, or con you litle
thanke for your labour. It is with you in this case,
as with Tailors, that make garments for Children:
though the Children pay them not, yet their Parents,
they are sure, will. Do you your dutie faithfully
and constantly; and as the Prophet said of
himselfe,Isai 49. 5. 
               Your worke shall be with God, and your wages
with him: He will regard and reward you,
whither men do or no. For1. Cor. 3. 8. 
               Euery man shall receiue
his wages from him according to his worke.
            
            Nor againe let it dishearten you, if you meet with
some vntoward ones, whom notwithstanding all
your paines and toyle you can do no good vpon.
Curam exigeris, n
                     •
                  n curationem. Bern de consid. l. 4. 
               It is the care, not the cure of them, that is required of
you. Do your best endeuour, andSecurus labor, qu
                     •
                  m n
                     •
                  l
                     •
                  us valet eua
                     •
                  uare defectus. l
                     ••
                  d. let the euent be
what it will, you shall haue from God, whose worke
you do, when you do conscionably what you do,

                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Secundum laborē, non secundum proventum Bern. Ibid. 1. Cor. 3. 8. 
               according to your paines, not according to the issue
or euent of it.
            But who are they,Branch 3. that King Dauid vndertaketh

to teach? And so passe we on from the Act to the
Obiect, (the third particular in his promise;) the persons
taught, You. They are the Children, that before
he called vpon, and invited vnto him.Doctrine 6.
            
            Children are to be taught.Prov. 22. 6. 
               Teach a Childe, saith
Salomon. And,Prov. 4. 3, 4. 
               When I was a Childe, my Father
taught me. And,1. Io
                     •
                  . 2. 12, 14. 
               I write to you, Children; saith the
Apostle Iohn,
               Reason 1. among others.
            And that not without good cause. For
            1. We are then aptest to learne.Fingit eq
                     •
                  ū doc
                     ••
                  em tenera c
                     •
                  ruice magister, Ire v
                     •
                  om quam monstrat eques. Horat epist. 2. Vt corp
                     •
                  ra ad quosdam membroris ste
                  
                     •
                  us sormari nisi tener
                     •
                   non possunt: sic animos qu
                     •
                   qu: ad plera
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   luriors r
                     ••
                  ur ipsum facit. Quinisl. inst. l. 1. c 1. In cunctu fere rebꝰ citius assuescit o
                     •
                  e quod tenerum est. Novelles adhuc &amp; vix firma radicis arbuscules, dum ad emuem ductum sequaces sunt, in quā
                  libet partem slecti facile est: quaetura plarum
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   curnatae citò ad arbitrium celentis corriguntur. Tenerve adhuc &amp; primae aetatis animalia fine labore domari solent; quanto
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   citius à vagandi aetatis liberti 
                     •
                   edissucta sunt, tanto facilius vel collaiugo, vel 
                     〈…〉
                   tunt. Pelag. ad Dem
                     ••
                  r. The foale is
easier broken and brought to a pace,Reason 2. that is taken
while it is yet young, then that is let alone till it
haue more yeeres. The plant is easily bowed and
bent any way, while it is but a twig, that will sooner
breake then bend, when it is growne a strong
tree.
            2.Altius praecepta descendunt, quae teneris imprimuntur 
                     •
                  tatibus. Sen. ad. Hel
                     •
                  . c. 16. Natura tenacissimi sumus eorum quae rudibus annis percipimus. Vt sapor, quo n
                     •
                  na 
                     〈◊〉
                   durat: nec lauarum colores, quibus simplex ille eand
                     •
                  r mutatuss est, elui 
                     •
                  ossunt. Quintil. institut. l. 1. c. 1. What we then learne, sticketh best by vs.Quo semel est imbuta recens, scruabit oderē Testa din. Horat. epist. 2. Difficulter eraditur, quod rudes animi perhiborunt. Lanagum concliylia quis in pristinum condorem revocek? Recens testa diu &amp; soporem obtinet &amp; oderem, quo primum imbut
                     •
                   est. Hieron. ad Laet.
Any vessell will retaine long the sauour of that liquor,
that it was seasoned first withall. And the
cloth best keepeth its color, that was died in the
wooll, that it tooke in, ere it came to the wheele or
the woofe.Prov. 22. 6. 
               Teach a childe, saith Salomon, in the
trade of his way; and he will not depart from it when
he is olde.
            
            3.Reason 3. We haue much to go through with, and but

litle time to learne;
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Ars longa, vita brevis. Hippocr. aphor. 1. a long taske and a short time.
Perge &amp; proper
                     ••
                   ne tibi accidat, vt senex dis ca
                     •
                  : imò ideò magis properar, quontam id iuver
                     ••
                   aggressus es, quod perdiscere vi
                     ••
                   
                  
                     •
                  enex po
                     ••
                  is Sen. ep. 77. Though we set vpon it while we are young, we
can hardly attaine to any perfection in ought ere
we be old: and therefore can neuer begin too
soone, nor soone enough neither.
            4.Reason 4.
               Turpis &amp; ridicula res est elementarius senex. Ibid. 36. Quid rurpius qu
                     •
                  m senex viuere (discere) incipiens? Ibid. 13. It is a shame for an old man to be then learning
his first elements, that, that euery Childe may
and should know. Not that they should not then
learne, that haue not before learned.
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Socrat. apud S
                     •
                  ob. 
                     •
                  om. 2. c. 29. 
               It is better to
learne late then neuer.
               Stult
                     •
                  m est nolle discere, quia di
                     •
                   nō didiceris. Sē. ep. 36. It is a folly for a man to refuse
to learne at all, because a long time he hath not
learned. And if it be a shame for a man not to
haue learned till then; it is much more a shame for
him not to learne then neither. ButSed propera, ne
                     •
                   it venturas differ in horas; Qui non est bodie, eras minus ap
                     •
                  ꝰ erit. Ovid, remed, l. 1. Moc est discendi tempus, nō quod aliquod sit, quo non sit discendum: sed qu
                     •
                  madmodum omnibus anni
                     •
                   studere hono
                     ••
                  um est, ita non omnibus institui. Sen. ep. 36. the longer we
defer it, the more paine it will be to vs, the more
shame it will be for vs, not a shame, I say, so much
that now we learne, as that before we haue not
learned.
            Lastly,Reason 5. Children if they be taught no good thing,
they will of themselues learne euill things.Omni mobili mobili
                     ••
                   consistere non potest, sed molendiui instar, impigr
                     •
                   voluitur. &amp;c. Bern. medit. cap. 9. The
minde of man or childe is like a restles Mill, that cannot
stand still, will neuer be without worke.Nihil agend
                     •
                   malè agere homines discunt. Catonis oraculum, quo nihil verius. colum. de re rust. lib. 11. cap. 1. 
               By
doing nothing, saith the Heathen Man, men soone
learne to do euill things. AndIncultis vrenda fili
                     ••
                   tunascitur 
                     〈◊〉
                  . Horat. sat. 3. euill weeds come
vp apace,Vse 1. and grow soone ouer ranck in vs, if
some diligent husbandry be not constantly vsed
with vs.
            And here first Children are to be admonished to

vse their time and meanes well, that Gods goodnes,
and the care and bounty of Frends and Parents affordeth
them, and
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                to apply themselues to their
learning, while their senses are liuely, their wit
quicke, their memorie fresh and strong; take that
in now that may sticke by them hereafter;
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                lay that
vp now that they haue comfort of, and benefit by
hereafter: Do as wise trauailers, that haue a long
dayes iourney to make, that get them vp betimes,
and take the day before them, and not
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                like foolish,
improuident, and vnaduised persons, that with friuolous
delayes trifle out the time, and burne daylight.
You know what is said commonly, that

                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                
               Time and Tide tarieth for no man. Neither is it possible
to recall any one day or houre, when it is once
ouer, nay nor the least minute or moment of our
life, when it is once past and gone. It will be too
late for you to say hereafter,O mihi praeteritos ref
                     •
                  rat si Iupiter ann. 1. &amp;c. 
               Oh were I as young
againe as once I was; or, Were I to begin againe as
sometime I was, and had that time and those meanes
that then I had, or might haue had, I would then doe

thus and thus. Preuent it now therefore, while you
may, by following good counsell, and taking your
learning, that now seeketh you, and offreth it selfe
vnto you;Prov. 5. 11, 12, 13. least you mourne hereafter in your latter
dayes; when you haue spent your time and your
strength in folly and vanitie; and say, How haue I
hated instruction, and in mine heart scorned correction;
and haue not obeyed the voyce of them that taught me,
nor inclined mine eare vnto them that instructed me:
yeaIob 20. 11. when your bones, it may be, as he speaketh in
Iob, are so filled with the sinnes of your youth, with
the fruits of those loose courses that then you took,
that they leaue you not, till they lye downe with you
in the dust.
            
            As also many Parents come here iustly to be reproued,Vse. 2.
that are too too careles in this kinde; Let
their children go on without instruction and correction
so long, that afterward when they would
themselues, they can do no good with them; but
through the just judgement of God vpon them by
their stubbornnes and vntowardnes, they become
Gen. 26. 35. &amp; 27 46. such a corrosiue and an heart-sore vnto them, that
they make them euen weary of their liues, and oft
bring their grey heads with excessiue greife for
them to the graue.
            
               Let them alone, say they, yet a while; they are but
young yet: there will be time enough to teach them, and
to nurture them hereafter. Yea, but for the body
of thy Child, thou wouldst be wiser and more warie.
Were any limme mishapen, or did any part
grow awry, thou wouldst be sure to take it betimes,
while the nervs are gentle and pliable, the flesh soft

and waxie, and the bones tender, and gristly, so as
they may be easily wrought and moulded any way.
Be no lesse wise then for the soule of thy Childe.
Thou canst not begin too soone.Ad neminē ante bona mens venit quàm mal
                     •
                  : omnes prae
                     •
                  ccupats sumus. Virt
                     •
                  tes descere est vitia dediscere, Sē. epist 51. Ad virtutem cont
                     •
                  udimꝰ inter vitia distr
                     •
                  cti. Ibid. 75. 
               Forestalled we
are all of vs; the Heathen themselues saw and said
as much. We bring vice into the world with vs,
that must be wrought out of vs; and the sooner
we are delt with, ere it take deeper roote with vs, or
grow to stronger head in vs, the more easily it will
be done.
            What shall we say of those, that all their whole
time traine them vp in idlenes, in nothing but vanitie
and naughtinesse? That which proueth afterthe
very bane and vtter ouerthrow of them. For
hauing bin brought vp to nothing, and hauing no
kinde of imployment to passe their time away with,
they light commonly into lewd company, whom
they waste themselues and their meanes with, and
so come at length to confusion. What shall we
say, I say, of such, but what Bernard before said, that
such arePeremptores potius quàm parentes. Bern. epist. 111. V
                     •
                  inam liberorum nostrorum mores nō ipsi p
                     ••
                  deremus. Infantiam, statim delucijs solumꝰ. Mol. lis illa educatio, quaem indulgentiam v
                     •
                  amus, neruos cēs &amp; mentis &amp; corporis frangit Quintil. ins
                     ••
                  . l. 1. c. 2. rather Paricides then Parents? And the
bloud of their Children shall be one day required
at their hands, which though they perish deseruedly
through their owne voluntarie default, yet by their
diligent endeuour and care might haue done much
better.
            But what is it that Dauid would haue these litle
ones to learne?Branch 4. And so come we at length to the
fourth and last Branch; the Subiect-Matter of his
teaching; the Feare of the Lord.
            
            The last point then that we obserue hence is,Doctrine 7.
that, The Feare of God, religion, and godlinesse is

to be taught Children, and to be learned as well of
young as of old.Genes. 18. 19. 
               Abraham, saith God of him, will
teach his Sonnes and his whole houshold, to walke in
Gods wayes.
               Eccles. 12. 1. 
               Remember thy Creator, to wit, to feare
and serue him, saith Salomon, in the dayes of thy youth.
And,Ephes. 6 4. 
               Yee Fathers, saith the Apostle Paul, bring vp
your Children in instruction and information of the
LORD.
            
            And great reason for Parents so to traine them vp,
if they desire or regard their good.
            For 1.Reason 1. there is no true wisdome but in it.
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   Prov 9. 10. Virtutum omn
                     •
                  um fandamentum 
                     〈◊〉
                  . Cic. pro Planc. 
               Timor
Domini principium sapientiae. The Feare of God is the
Beginning of Wisedome; saith Salomon. Yea, Timor
Domini caput, or praecipuum sapientiae;
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   sicut Prov. 3. 9 &amp; 4. 7. 
               The Feare of
God is the cheife and principall point of Wisedome;
saith bothPsal 111. 10. 
               Dauid, and the sameProv. 1. 7. 
               Salomon. And Iob
long before either of them,
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   Iib. 28. 28. Qu
                     •
                  d &amp; idē ferè Solomon Pro. 15. 33. 
               Timor Domini est sapientia
ipsa: The Feare of God is wisedome, euen wisedome
it selfe. No true wisedome without it, no true
wisedome but in it. To be taught our Children
therefore, if we would haue them wise, if we would
not haue them fooles and ideots, as they must needs
be without it.
            2.Reason 2. There is no true happinesse without it, no
blessednesse but by it. For it is that, that Gods blessing
is entailed vnto; euen all the good blessings
both of this life▪ and the next; and Blessednesse it
selfe, not temporall onely, but eternall. For,Psal. 112. 1. 
               Blessed
is the man that feareth God: and,Psal. 128. 1. 
               Blessed is euery one
that feareth the Lord; and,Prov. 28. 14. 
               He is a blessed man that
standeth alwayes in awe. For,1. Tim. 4. 8. 
               Godlinesse (that is,
the Feare of God,) hath the promises both of this life,

and of that that is to come. Of this life. For,Psal. 34. 9, 10. 
               There
shall be no want to those that feare him: they shall lacke
nothing that is good for them. And of the life to
come too. For,Psal. 103. 17. 
               The louing kindnes of the Lord is for
euer and euer vpon them that feare him; and his
               Ita verto 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   pr
                     ••
                  t vsurpatur, Psal. 112. 3, 9. &amp; 2. Cor. 9. 9, 10. 
               bounty or mercy vpon their Childrens Children. And
therefore no maruaile if Salomon, as in the Entrance
into his Prouerbs he maketh the Feare of God, the Beginning
of all; so in the Conclusion and shutting
vp of his Ecclesiastes, he maketh the same Feare of
God, the very Summe and the End of all.
               Eccl
                     •
                  s. 12. 15. 
               Summa,
or Finis rei. Will you heare, (saith he) what is the
Summe, or the End of all: Feare God, and keepe his
Commandements: For that is the whole dutie of man:
and that is the only meanes to make man truly happy,
the maine matter that Salomon there intended to
teach.
            Now this First may teach you that be Parents,Vse 1.
Masters and Teachers, what to labour in, if you desire
the true welfare and happinesse of those that
be vnder your charge, or Gods blessing vpon
them, and your labours and endeuours with them;
euen to teach them the feare of God. You are not
to thinke it enough, that you haue taught them
some trade, that you haue giuen them learning, (humane
learning, I meane) that they may liue by an
other day; but you must withall, or else you come
far short of that you should do, teach them also to
feare God, and so to serue him here, as they may liue
with him eternally, when they go hence.
            To which purpose it is well obserued, that the
promise of a blessing to be continued to posteritie,

though made to the obseruance of all Gods precepts,
yet isExod. 2
                     •
                  . 6. Deut. 5. 10. more specially annexed to the second
Commandement in the Decalogue, which is concerning
the seruice and worship of God; God
thereby intimating what Parents &amp; others should
principally apply themselues to haue planted in
their Families, if they would haue Gods blessing entailed
vpon their issue. For as for other things, euen
Heathen and Infidels, or meere Ciuill and naturall
men, will be ordinarily teaching and instructing
their Children, to forbeare and abhorre lying, and
stealing, and loosenes of life, and surfeting, and excesse,
and the like; because such things may make
them vnfit for common and ciuill society, or may
be a meanes to waste them, and that, that they shall
leaue them. But God would haue vs, (and those
that be truly godly will regard it,) to go a st
                  •
               p further,
and to teach them a lesson beyond all this,
not ciuilitie alone, but true piety too; that we may
be blessed in them, and they inherit Gods blessing
with vs.
            And surely what difference will there be betweene
a Christian Parent and an Heathen, a Christian
Schole-master and a Pagane; if the Parent or
Schole-master teach his Children and Schollers,
matter of ciuilitie or humane learning alone? Do
not Heathen euen the same? As the Apostle speaketh
in an other case,1. Tim 5. 8. 
               He that prouideth not for his
Familie, is worse then an Infidell: So here, that
Parent that bringeth vp his Childe idly, is worse
then many an Infidell: he that traineth him vp in
some worldly trade onely is no better then they.

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
That Schole-master that teacheth them not at all
that be committed vnto him, is worse then many
an Infidell; he that giueth them humane learning
onely, is litle better then they. That Parent
or Teacher that doth not teach them Ciuilitie,
comes far short of many Heathen ones; he that
doth teach Ciuilitie, and not Piety withall, goeth
no further then they haue gone.
            Lastly,Vse 2. Children also must learne to feare and
to serue God. If your Gouernors must teach you
it, then questionlesse you must learne it.Eccles. 12. 1. 
               Remember
thy Creator, saith Salomon, in the dayes of thy
youth. And,Psal. 119. 9. 
               Whereby shall a boy, or a Child, saith
Dauid, make his path pure, but by taking heede to it
according to Gods word?
            
            It is an idle conceipt of many, that Religion
and Godlinesse is not for Children, that such
things concerne them not. There is no age freed
from it. And therefore Iohn writeth vnto, and
directeth, what he writeth, vnto all,1. Ioh. 2. 12, 13, 14. not to olde
men, and young men, strong growne men onely,
but to Children and litle ones also. And surely
most equall it is,Vt primiti
                     •
                   reris, ita primitiae dieris. Greg. in Evang. that as the first-fruits of other
things, so the first-fruits of our yeeres should go also
to God.
            It is but a Diuelish Prouerbe, A young Saint,
and an old Diuell. The Holy Ghost by Solomon
assureth vs the contrary:Prov. 22. 6. 
               Teach a Childe, saith
he, in the trade of his way, and he will not depart from
it, when he is old. It is true indeed, that those that
haue made most shew of piety,2. Pet. 2 20. Math. 11. 45. when they fall
away againe, proue vsually most prophane. But

               1. Pet. 1. 23. 1. Ioh. 3. 9. Sapientia nō 
                  
                     〈…〉
                   non revolvitur. Sē. epist. 76. where it hath once truly taken roote in the heart,
there it will continue constantly euen to all eternity,
and neuer dye or decay againe.
            Let this therefore, good Children, be your principall
care and studie: (For what shall it availe
you to be cunning in Tully, Virgil, Homer, and other
profane Writers, if you be vnskilfull in Gods
booke? to haue learned Greeke and Latine, if you
learne not withallEsai. 19. 18. 
               the language of Canaan? to
haue your speech agreeable to the rules of Priscian
or Lilie, if your liues and courses be not consonant
to the rules and lawes of Christianitie? to haue
knowledge of the Creatures, when you are ignorant
of the Creator? to haue learned that whereby
you may liue a while here, and neglect that
whereby you may liue eternally hereafter?)
Learne to feare God, to serue God; and then
God will blesse you. ForPsal. 115. 13. 
               He will blesse those
that feare him, be they great or small. Yea he will
take charge of you, and prouide for you, if your
Parents be taken from you.Psal. 27. 10. 
               Though my Father and
Mother, saith Dauid, should leaue me, yet would God
take me vp.
               Psal. 68. 5. He will be a Father vnto you:Psal. 23. 1. he
will see you shall not want. If your Parents haue
wrought the Feare of God into you;Psal. 37. 25, 
                     •
                  6. they shall
be sure to leaue Gods blessing to you; they may
boldly bequeath it you; and you shall be sure to
partake with them in it.
            To end where we began; it is the commendation
of Timothie, and of his Parents withall, that
2. Tim. 3. 15. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               he had knowne the holy Scriptures from a Childe;
and had bin euen1. Tim. 4. 6. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               nursed vp in the words of faith

and good doctrine;
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . H
                     •
                  mer Sophista in Monod. Ru
                     •
                  i
                     •
                  s. sucking piety and godlines in,
with his Mothers milke, and beginning to be acquainted
with it euen at the breast. Let the like
course be taken of, and with others, and it will
make them proue in time also like Timothie,
               2. Tim. 3. 15, 17. 
               wise to saluation, and
enabled to euery good
worke.
            
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

