
   
      
         
            Tvvo mariage sermons the former on Prov. 19. 14. By Thomas Gataker B. of D. and pastor of Rotherhith. The latter on Iohn 2. 1--12. By that learned and judicious divine Mr William Bradshaw some time fellow of Sidney Colledge in Cambridge.
            Gataker, Thomas, 1574-1654.
         
         
            
               1620
            
         
         Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01553
            STC 11680
            ESTC S102990
            99838749
            99838749
            3137
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01553)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3137)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1066:09)
         
         
            
               
                  Tvvo mariage sermons the former on Prov. 19. 14. By Thomas Gataker B. of D. and pastor of Rotherhith. The latter on Iohn 2. 1--12. By that learned and judicious divine Mr William Bradshaw some time fellow of Sidney Colledge in Cambridge.
                  Gataker, Thomas, 1574-1654.
                  Bradshaw, William, 1571-1618. aut
               
               [10], 23, [9], 18, [2] p.   
               
                  Printed by Edward Griffin for Fulke Clifton, and are to be sold at his shop on New Fish-street hill vnder Saint Margerets Church,
                  London :
                  1620.
               
               
                  Bradshaw's sermon was edited by Gataker.
                  Gataker's "A good vvife Gods gift" and Bradshaw's "A mariage feast" each have separate dated title page and pagination; register is continuous.
                  Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: pi¹ A-G⁴ H² .
                  Also issued as part 5 of: Certaine sermons first preached and since published: London, 1622.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2003-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-09
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-10
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2003-10
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-12
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            TWO
MARIAGE
SERMONS:
THE FORMER
ON
PROV. 19. 14.
            By THOMAS GATAKER B. of D.
and Pastor of Rotherhith.
            THE LATTER
ON
IOHN 2. 1-12.
            By that learned and judicious Divine
Mr WILLIAM BRADSHAW some
time Fellow of SIDNEY COLLEDGE
in CAMBRIDGE▪
            
            LONDON,
Printed by Edward Griffin for Fulke Clifton, and are to be
sold at his shop on New Fish-street hill vnder Saint
Margerets Church. 1620.
         
      
      
         
            
               
                  
                  
                  A Good Wife Gods
Gift.
                  A
MARIAGE
SERMON
ON
PROV. 19. 14.
                  By THOMAS GATAKER B. of D.
and Pastor of Rotherhith.
                  LONDON,
Printed by EDWARD GRIFFIN for
FVLKE CLIFTON. 1620.
               
               
                  
                  
                  TO THE WORSHIPFVLL
MY LOVING
COSENS, Mr IOHN
SCVDAMORE of Kenchurch in Hereford-shire,
and Mrs ELIZABETH
SCVDAMORE his Wife, many
happy dayes togither with all true
Blessednes both temporall
and eternall.
                  
                     RIght deere, and
vnfeinedly beloued
in Christ Iesus,
I haue a long
time much desired
some good
occasion of testifying
mine hearty affection to your
selues in particular among others of

that Familie, which I acknowledge
my selfe so deeply indebted vnto. And
I seeme now at length to haue lighted
on that, that I haue so long longed for.
Being to publish a wedding Sermō
                     
of a worthy Frend deceassed,Mr. W. Br. (which
I wish, if Gods good will had so bin,
he had liued to doe himselfe) conteyning
matter concerning the holy disposition
&amp; Christian managing of Mariage
Feasts; I thought good to adioyne
to it (being it selfe but short)
some Meditations of mine owne, of
somewhat a neere subiect, the occasion
of such Feasts, to wit, A good Wife,
by Salomon said to be Gods Gift.
That which here I addresse vnto you,
as to remaine a Monument of mine
hearty well-wishing vnto you, so to
abide by you, as a Monitor to put you
both in minde, what a blessing of God

you enjoy either in other, and what
cause you haue to be thankfull to him
either for other. Since it pleased God
by his prouidence and your Frends agreement
to bring you togither, and to
knit that sacred knot betweene you, I
haue not yet bin so happy, as to be an
eye-witnes of your Christian &amp; religious
cohabitation &amp; conversation: but
haue by many bin informed of it, to
my great ioy, that you tread both in
the steps of your pious Parents, and
therein shew your selues to be their
Children,Rom. 9. 8. not according to the
flesh onely, but (which would haue
bin their greatest comfort, had they
survived to haue seene it, and shall be
your cheifest happines both here and
hereafter) according to the promise,
euen of eternall saluation, annexed
to the gratious Couenant of

Faith in Christ; which by your godly
practise you shew your selues to haue
common interest in with them. And
indeed to speake in the Holy Ghosts
language, thenEorum filij dicimur, quorum actus imitamur. Origen. in Ezech. hom. 4. &amp; Greg. Rom. mor. lib. 20. cap. 17. are we truly the Children
of our religious Parents and Ancestors,
when in goodnes and godlines
we take after those that we come of.
Ioh. 8. 39. Etiam virtus fecit mihi fratrem Iesum, patrem Abraham. Origen. in Ezech. hō. 8. &amp; in Rom. c. 4. They are Abrahams Children,
that doe Abrahams works; and
Rom. 4. 12, 23. Israel spiritalis à carnali, non nobilitate patriae, sed nouitate gratiae, nec gente, sed mente distinguitur. Aug. doctr. Chr. l. 3. c. 34. that tread in the steps of Abrahams
Faith, who is the Father of
all the Faithfull. Those that take
other courses, and degenerate, (as
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Homer. Odyss. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Eurip. Heracl. Hīc Demosthenes, 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Aristid. in Cimon. Et inde diverbium, 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Neminem prope magnorum virorum filium optimum reliquisse satis claret Tales pleri
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         habuerunt, vt melius fuerit de rebus humanis sine posteritate discedere. Spartian in Severo. too
many do,) from the Faith and Piety
of their Parents, are in Gods account,
as our Sauiour termeth the Iewes, but

                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Matth. 12. 39. &amp; 16. 4. Spuria soboles: vt rectè Piscat. 
                     a bastardly brood; ratherEzech. 16. 3. non de eorum semine, sed de imitatione generati. Greg. mor. l. 20. c. 11. quibus eos non necessitudo, sed morum similitudo iungebat. Origen. in Rom. 4. 
                     Hittites
                     
and Canaanites, thenRom. 6. 6, 7. Vide Aug. epist. 200. 
                     right
Hebrews, orIoh. 1. 47. 
                     true Israelites, though
they come of Abraham or Israel either
after the flesh. They are not
Galat. 6. 16. Psal. 128. 6. &amp; 125. 5. 
                     the Israel of God, vnto whom the
blessing is promised of mercy and
peace; yea ofEsai. 26. 3 &amp; 57. 19. 
                     peace, peace; that
is, ofPsal. 119. 165. 
                     much peace,
                     Ioh. 14. 27. 
                     true peace,
                     Pacem omnimodam. Iun. 
                     all manner of peace, such peace
as no
                     Esai 48. 22. &amp; 57. 21. 
                     wicked one euer had or can
haue. WhichPhilip. 4. 7. 
                     peace far surpassing
all humane conceipt, that you may
constantly retaine in part here, and
attaine finally vnto the full fruition
of it hereafter; hold on, I beseech
you, in that good course, that by Gods
goodnes you haue already entred into,
and haue made some good progresse in.
Hold on, I say: yea hold out: For
Matth. 24. 13. Apoc. 2. 10. it is holding out to the end, that
must bring you to1. Petr. 1. 9. 
                     the end of your

                        
                           〈1 page duplicate〉
                        
                        
                        
                           〈1 page duplicate〉
                        
                        
Faith, the saluation of your
Soules. And that you may so do; (because
standing still is dangerous; and
Vnum è duobus necesse est, aut proficere, aut prorsus deficere. Bern. in Cant. vnlesse daily we win ground, we soone
fall behind hand and goe backward;)
let it be your continuall care and constant
endeuour2. Pet. 3. 18. 
                     to grow in grace &amp;
in the knowledge of our Lord and
Sauiour Iesus Christ; to whom be
glory both now and for euer: And
to whose holy protection committing
you and yours now and for euer, I take
leaue of you for the present, and rest
in Him.
                  
                     Your affectionate Kinsman and
hearty well-wisher,
Thomas Gataker.
                  
               
               
                  Faults of moment to be amended.
                  Pag. 5. lin. 5. for clipped read slipped. p. 6. l. 4. after
those put in his. p. 7. l. 2. for her read heere. p. 21.
in marg. for 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                         read 
                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     .
               
            
            
               
                  
                  A GOOD WIFE
GODS GIFT.
                  
                     PROVERBS 19. 14.
                     Houses and Riches are the Inheritance of the
Fathers: But a prudent Wife is of the Lord.
                  
                  
                     THERE be two things especially that
commend a worke,Autor opus laudat.-Ovid. de pont. lib. 4. eleg. 9. 
                     the Autor, and
the Matter. Both of them conspire to
commend this Booke, as in the Title
of it they are both expressed.
                  
                     Prov. 1. 1. The Proverbs, or Parables of Salomon,
the Sonne of Dauid, King
of Israel.
                  For the Autor,
                     Autor. (to omit the Principall,
                     2. Pet. 1. 21. 
                     Gods Spirit:
for,
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . 2. Tim. 3. 16. 
                     All Scripture is inspired of God:) the Penman
of it was Salomon,
                     2. Chron. 1. 12. 1. King. 3. 12. the wisest meere man that
euer was in the world since Adam, by the testimonie
euen of wisedome it selfe.
                  For the Matter;
                     Matter. it is Prouerbs or Parables, (as the

word in the Originall signifieth)
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                         à 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                         quod 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                         &amp; dominari significat. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                         sive dignitates, quae vitae Dominae &amp; moderatrices esse debent. Cartwright in Prov. 
                     Master-sentences,
such as rule or sway, and are or may be of principall
vse in mans Life.
                  Now consisting for the most part of such Aphorisms
and short Sentences, from the beginning especially
of the tenth Chapter; it is not necessary, that
they should haue any coherence one with an other;
neither indeed for the most part haue they.Coherence.
                  
                  Yet this and the next before it, haue some connexion:
vers. 13. the former being of the inconuenience
that commeth by a bad wife;
                  
                     vers. 14. This latter of the benefit that a good wife, that
a wise and a discreet woman bringeth with her.
                  There Salomon compared two grand euils togither,
and made a bad wife the worse of the twaine:
                  Here he compareth two great benefits togither,
and maketh a good wife the better of the two.
                  For the former;vers. 13. 
                     A foolish Sonne, saith Salomon, is
his Fathers sorrow: and a brawling wife as a continuall
dropping.
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Plut. de tranquill. Dolores eo acerbiores, quo interiores. Aug. in Psal. 45. 
                     Mala intestina grauissima. Euils are the more
greiuous, the neerer, and the more inward they are; as
diseases in the entrailes. AndMolestissimū malum intestinum &amp; domesticum. Bern. in Cant. serm. 29. 
                     mala domestica, domesticall
euils, vex a man most, whenMatth. 10. 36. 
                     a mans enemies,
as our Sauiour speaketh,Mica. 7. 6. 
                     are those of his owne
house.
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Hesiod. oper. Hinc Themistocles 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Plut. 
                           〈◊〉
                        . Et v
                           •
                        tus verbum, Aliquid mali esse propter vici
                           •
                        um malum. Plaut. Merc act 4. sc. 4. It is no small inconuenience to dwell neere a
bad neigbour; were such a one further of vs, he
would be lesse troublesome to vs. And surely if to
haue good neighbours be a matter of no small moment,

then somwhat also it must needs be for a man
to want such, and much more for a man to haue
them that dwell neere him euill-affected toward
him. An euill at the next dore may be bad enough,
and may proue ouer troublesome; an euill within
dores, at home, in a mans owne house much
more.
                  But againe within dores there are degrees also:
in a mans owne familie there are some neerer then
others. A sonne is neerer then a seruant, and a wife
then a sonne.Quot serui, tot hostes. Sen. epist. 47. Macrob. Sat. lib. 1. c. 10. &amp; Fest. lit. Q. Quot. serui, tot fures. Serv. ad Virg. eclog. 3. It is a sore crosse to be troubled, and
it be but with bad seruants. It is no small vexation
to finde vntoward and vnfaithfull cariage toward
himPsal. 41. 9. Ioh. 13. 18. 
                     in those that eat his bread, that feed at his bord;
much more to sustaine it at the hands of her, that taketh
vp the same bed with him,Mica. 7. 5. 
                     that lieth in his bosome.
No euill to a bad bed-fellow,
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Aesopꝰ apud Gabriam. Coluber in sinis. to a bosome-euill,
to that euill that lieth within or about the
breast.
                  Though true mercy and compassion in some
measure extend it self vnto all those, whose miseries
and calamities we are acquainted with: yet the
misfortunes of our deere frends affect vs more then
of meere strangers: AndQui ignotos laedit, latro appellatur; qui amicos, paulò minus quàm pari
                           •
                        ida. Petron. satyr. the wrongs and iniuries
offered vs by professed and pretended frends we are
wont to take more to heart.Psal. 55. 12, 13, 20. 
                     It was not mine enemy,
saith Dauid, that did me this wrong; for then I could
haue borne it. But it was thou, ô Man, my companion,
my guide, and my familiar frend.
                  
                  But Brethren are neerer then Frends. And howsoeuer
Salomon truly saith, thatProv. 18. 24. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Dion. Chrysost. orat. 3. 
                     a Frend sometime
sticketh closer to a man then a Brother: yet in nature a

                     
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        ; (Psal. 133. 1.) 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Menand. Vide Hieroclē de amore fratern. &amp; Muson. de lib. to l
                           •
                        end. apud. Stob. tom. 2. cap. 82 Hirc vetus verbum, 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Plato polit. 2. Brother is neerer then any Frend is or can be.
There is a ciuill knot onely betweene Frend and
Frend; there is a naturall band betweene Brother
and Brother. And therefore,Prov. 18. 19. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Aristot. polit. l. 7. c. 7. 
                     A Brother offended
is harder to win then a strong Citie; and their contentions
are as
                     Vectes arcis: qui ferrei aut anei esse solent. Psal. 107. 16. Esai. 45. 2. 
                     barres of brasse. It is easier glewing of
bords togither, that haue bin vnglewed, againe; then
healing vp the flesh that is gashed and diuided: and
the reason is, becauseContiguum ibi, istic continuum soluitur. there was but an artificiall
connexion before in the one, there was a naturall
conjunction in the other.
                  But Children they are yet neerer then either
Frends or Brethren. They arePars
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         tui latitat corpore clausa meo. Ovid. epist. 2. 
                     partes nostri, viscera
nostra; they are asPignora nostra, Viscera nostra; potius quàm opes, v
                           •
                        i Ovid. ep. 1. 2. Sā. 16. 11. Philem. 12, 20. 
                     our very bowels, and part of our
selues. And therefore no maruaile if Salomon say,
thatProv 10. 1. 
                     A foolish Sonne is a sorrow to his Father, and
an heauinesse to his Mother. And,Prov. 17. 21. 
                     He that begetteth
a Foole, begetteth himselfe sorrow: and the Father of
a Foole
                     Nemo quisquam ferè vnquam sic dolet, vt non idē aliquando gaudeat. Sedenim qui omni momento dolet, is verè dicitur non gaudere. Drus. observ. l. 1. c. 22. Vise &amp; Agell. nect. Attic. l. 2. c. 6. 
                     shall haue no ioy.
                  
                  But behold here a further euill then any of the
former. An euill wife, a contentious woman worse
then any of them all. Husband and Wife are neerer
then Frends, and Brethren; or then Parents and
Children. Children, though they spring from their
Parents, yet they abide not alwayes with them.
They are asProv. 5. 16, 17. riuers rising from one head, but taking
seuerall wayes, making seuerall streames, and running
apart in seuerall Channels. But man and wife
must bide by it. They are as two streames, that rising
from seuerall heads, fall the one into the other,

                     Prout Alpheum Arethuse aiunt commisceri. mingle their waters togither, and are not seuered
againe till they are swallowed vp in the Sea. Children
are asGenes. 49 22. Psal. 128. 3. branches shooting out of one stemme,
diuided and seuered either from other, or as grifts
and siences cut of, or boughes and branches clipped
of from their natiue stocke, and either planted or
engraffed els-where. Man and Wife are as the stock
and sience, the one
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Rom 11. 24. ingraffed into the other, and
so fastned togither, that they cannot againe be sundred,
or asEzech. 37. 17 Vno Vt siquis geminos cōducat cor
                           ••
                        ce ramos, Crescendo iungi, pari
                           •
                        er
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         adoles
                           •
                        ere cernit. Ovid. metam. l. 4. those two peeces in the Prophets hand
inclosed in one barke, and making both but one
branch. AndGenes. 2. 24. 
                     Therefore, saith the Holy Ghost,
shall a man leaue Father and Mother, and
                     
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                         Christꝰ Mat. 19. 5. 
                     be glewed
vnto, or
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Moses. 
                     cleaue fast to his wife: and They
                     Ita Mosen supplet Christus: quomodo &amp; Math. 4. 10. ex Deut. 6. 13. &amp; 10. 20. 
                     two shall
be one flesh.
                  
                  The neerer the bond then, the greater the euill,
where it falleth out otherwise then it ought.Prov. 19. 14. 
                     A
foolish Sonne, saith Salomon, is the calamitie of his Father.
And how is he his calamitie? He is
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                         Prov. 10. 5. &amp; 17. 2. &amp; 19. 26. &amp; 29. 15. 
                     filius
pudefaciens, such an one as shameth his Parents, and
maketh them glad to hide their heads in the house.
ButProv. 19. 13. an euill wife is as the raine dropping in through
the tiles, that maketh him weary of the house, that
vexeth him so that it driueth him out of dores.
                  YeaProv. 27. 15. 
                     as a dropping in a rainy day, when it is foule
without and it droppeth within. So that it maketh
a man at his wits end, vncertaine whither it be better
for him to be abroad in the raine, or to bide within
dores in the dropping. And for this cause Augustine
compareth an euill Conscience to a badwife, (and it
may seeme that he pleased himselfe somewhat in
the similitude,August in Psal. 33. &amp; in Psal. 35. &amp; in Psal. 45. &amp; alibi. he maketh vse so oft of it:) which

when a man hath many troubles &amp; afflictions from
without, and would looke home, hoping for some
comfort from within, is much more troublesome to
him then any of those outward crosses are; is as a
rocke or a shelf to Sea-men in a storme, where they
hoped to haue found harbor and shelter against it.
                  Yea further, not as a dropping onely that driueth a
man from his house and home, and that when it
raineth; butProv. 19. 13. 
                     as a continuall dropping in such a day:
So that a bad wife is worse then a quartane ague,
wherein a man hath two good dayes for one euill.
He that hath an euill wife, is as one that hath an euill
soule, a guilty conscience, that euermore sticketh by
him, that euery-where accompanieth him, is a continuall
euill companion with himIn cubiculo, in cubili ipso. Aug. in Psal 45. at bed and bord,
Quā nec fugere, nec fugare licet. Lips. in politic. Conscientiā enim à Deo (comitē individ
                           •
                        ā) accepimus, quae diuelli à nobis non potest. Cic. pro Cluent. such as he cannot shift of or shun. And no meruaile
therefore if it be deemed the greatest temporall
euill, because the most continuall, and the most inward,
for a man to be matched with an euill wife, or
a woman with an euill husband: For what is said
of the one, is as true of the other, the relation betweene
them being alike.
                  To draw all to an head then. An vnkind Neighbour
is a crosse: but an vnfaithfull Frend is a great
crosse; an vnnaturall Brother a greater: an vngratious
Childe yet a greater: but a wicked, vnquiet,
or disloyall wife is the
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Menand. Penus malorum est omnili mulier mala. greatest of all, and if we beleeue
Salomon, goeth beyond them all. In regard
whereof he also els-where pronounceth, thatProv. 21. 9. &amp; 25. 24. 
                     it is
better to abide on a corner of the house top without,
then to continue with such a one in a wide house: yea
thatProv. 21. 19. Sirac. 25. 18, 22. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Menand. Mala mulier quauis fera truculentior. H. Steph. 
                     it is better to liue in the wildernes with the wilde
beasts, then with such.
                  
                     
But to leaue this that is without my Text, and
yet next dore to it, (so neere her do good and bad
neighbour togither,) and to come neerer home:
Some it may be hearing Salomon speake on this
manner, might say, as our Sauiours Disciples sometime
said,Matth. 19. 10. Summe. 
                     If the case so stand betweene man and
wife, it is good then not to mary.
                  
                  Now to such Salomon seemeth to answer in the
words of my Text, that It is not euill to mary, but it
is good to be wary: that it is not the abuse or badnes
of some, that ought to make Gods ordinance the lesse
valued, or the lesse esteemed, being in it selfe and of it
selfe a matter of great benefit: that as the inconuenience
is great and grieuous that a bad wife bringeth with
her; so the benefit on the other side is no lesse that commeth
by a good wife, by a wise and a discreet woman:
who is therfore here commended as a speciall Gift,
as a principall Blessing of God, such as goeth beyond
any other temporall Blessing whatsoeuer.
And surely
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Hesiod. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Simonid. apud Clem. Alex. strom. l. 6. Sors potior maliere proba non 
                           •
                        btigit vnquam Vlla viro; contra
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         mala nil tetrius vsquā est. Erasm. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Menand. Salus &amp; exitium mulier est aedibus. H. Steph. as there is no greater temporall crosse
or curse then the one; so is there no greater temporall
blessing then the other.vers. 13.
                  
                  Now this Salomon to shew, as before he compared
two great euils togither, and found a bad wife
to be the worse: so here he compareth two great
benefits togither, and affirmeth a good wife to be
the greater.
                  House and possessions, wealth and riches, land
and liuing isPsal. 4. 6. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Antiphanes. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Sophocles. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Hesiod. Prima ferè v
                           •
                        ta &amp; cunctis notissima templis, Divitiae vt crescant. -Iuven. sat. 10. Totus populus in alijs discors, in hoc convenit: hoc suspiciunt; hoc sibi, hoc suis optant. Sen. epist. 115. that, that most men regard, and looke

                     after: yea men are wont to seeke wiues for wealth.
But saith Salomon, as
                     Psal. 22. 1. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Menād. a good name, so a good wife, a
wise and a discreet woman is better then wealth; her
price is far aboue pearles: For House and possessions
are the inheritance of the Fathers; but a prudent wife is
of the Lord.
                  Which yet we are not so to vnderstand,Meaning. neither
the former part, as if worldly wealth, and riches and
possessions were not Gods gifts: forProv. 10. 22. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Pindar. Pyth. 8. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Aeschyl Theb. 
                     It is the blessing
of God that maketh a man rich:
                     Psal. 127. 1, 2. 
                     vnles he build
the house it will neuer be built: andDeut. 8. 18. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Pindar. Pyth. 8. 
                     it is he that giueth
men power to gather wealth togither.
                  
                  Nor yet againe the latter part; as if Parents had
no hand, right or power in disposing of their Children,
or in aduising them and prouiding in that
kinde for them.Iudg. 14. 2. 
                     Sampson requireth his Parents
consent. AndDeut. 7. 3. God chargeth his people not to
make matches betweene their Children and the
Canaanites, either by giuing their Daughters vnto
the Sonnes of the Canaanites, or by taking the
Canaanites Daughters vnto their Sonnes: which he
would not doe, were not they at all to deale in the
disposing of them. And many, no doubt, would
they take aduice of their Parents, and not follow
their owne fancies, and make their wanton eye, or
their wandring lust, their chooser and counsailer in
such cases, might do much better then for want
hereof they doe.
                  But the meaning of Salomon is this onely, that
the one is a more speciall gift of God then the other;
that there is a more speciall hand of God in
the one then in the other. As that is a lesse benefit

then this: so that is in mans power more then
this.
                  So that two points then here in Solomons words
offer themselues vnto vs:
                  The former, that A good Wife is Gods gift.
                  
                  
                     The latter, that Gods prouidence is more speciall in
a Wife then in Wealth.
                  For the former. A good wife is Gods gift.
                     Point 1. For a
prudent wife, saith Solomon, is of the Lord. AndProv. 18. 22. 
                     He
that findeth a wife, (that is, a good wife, as, a
                     
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                         Eccles. 7. 1. Prov. 22. 1. &amp; Genes. 11. 4. Ellipsi
                           •
                        , qualis est &amp; Esai. 1. 18. &amp; Mal. 1. 14. Vise Camium ibid. 
                     name
for a good name,
                     Tanquam vxor mala ne vxor quidem sit. Drus. as if an euill wife were no wife, deserued
not the name of a wife:) hath found a good
thing; and hath obtained a speciall fauour from God.
                  
                  It was one of the first reall and royall gifts that
Genes. 2. 22. God with his owne hand bestowed vpon Adam.
And it must needs be no small matter that God
giueth with his owne hand.Reason. The Kings Almoner
may cast small siluer about: but if the King giue a
man somewhat with his owne hand out of his
purse or pocket, it is expected it should be a peece
of gold at least. The woman was Gods owne gift
to Adam. And shee was Gods gift bestowed on
himGenes. 2. 18. to consummate and make vp his happinesse.
Though he were at the first of himselfe happy, yet
not so happy as he might be, vntill he had one to
partake with him in his happines.
                  It was God that at first gaue Adam his wife; and
it is God that giueth euery man his wife to this
day.Genes. 24. 7, 56. 
                     God, saith Abraham to his seruant, will send
his Angell along with thee, and will prosper thee in thy
iourney; when he sent him about a wife for his Son
Isaak. AndMatth. 19. 6. 
                     Those that God hath ioyned togither,
                     
saith our Sauiour, let not man seuer. As Augustine
saith, that
                        
                           〈…〉
                         
                        
                           ••
                        
                        minem sineh mine, pr
                           •
                        creat hominem ex homine. Aug. de verb. Ap. 11. Ier. 1. 5. 
                     He that at the first created man without
man, doth now procreate man by man: so he that gaue
man a wife at the first immediately, doth still giue
men wiues by meanes;Prov. 18. 22. good ones in mercy,Eccles. 7. 26. euill
ones in wrath; the one for solace and comfort, the
other for tryall, cure, correction, or punishment.
No mariages are consummate on earth▪ that were
not first concluded and made vp in heauen: and
none are blest here, that were not in mercy made
there.
                  For the latter;Point 2. 
                     There is a more speciall prouidence
of God in a Wife then in Wealth. Humane wisedome
and fore-cast, endeuour and industry may strike a
greater stroke and haue a more speciall hand in the
one then in the other. Men of wealth may leaue
their heires land and liuings but
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Menād Haud facile coniugē nanciscier bonam. H. St
                           •
                        ph. they cannot so
easily prouide fit wiues for them.
                  For first,Reason. they may be deceiued in their choise.
Many haue good skill in choosing of wares, in valewing
of lands, in beating a bargaine, in making a
purchase, that are yet but blind buzards in the
choise of a wife. Yea the wisest that are may be
soone here ouer-reached▪ Since all is not gold as
we say, that glistereth.
                     Ierem. 17. 9. 
                     The heart of man, saith the
Prophet, is deceitfull aboue all things. And,1. Cor. 2. 11. Corda humana alienis oculis clausa snut. Greg. Rom. mor. lib. 25. cap. 9. Non est hominis scire quid sit in homine, nisi forte quis ad hoc ipsum fuerit vel sti
                        
                           •
                        itu Dei illuminatus, vel angelica informatus industria. Bern. in Cāt. 65. 
                     None
can tell what is in man or woman▪ but their owne Spirit
that is within them.
                  
                  Secondly, they cannot lincke hearts as they list.
A Father may finde out a fit wife, and thinke such a
one a meete match for his Sonne▪ and her Parents
may be also of the same minde with him, as willing

to entertaine the motion as he is to make it; and
yet it may be, when they haue done all they can,
they cannot fasten their affections. AsFides suadenda nō imperanda Eern. in Cant. 66. Religionem imperare non possumꝰ: quia nemo cogitur vt credat invitus. Theodori
                           •
                        ꝰ apud Cassiod. var. l. 2. ep. 27. Non est religionis cogere religionē, quae sponte suscipi debet. Tertull. ad Scap. Quis enim imponat mihi necessitatem vel colendi quod nolim, vel quod velim non colendi? Lactant. institut. l. 5. cap. 13. credendi. Lipsiu
                           •
                         polit. l. 4. c. 4. 
                     Faith, so
Nescit amor quo (non) libe
                           •
                         cogi. Tertull de pudic. 
                     Loue cannot be constrained.
                     Cant. 8. 6, 7. non extorquebis amari. Claud. Honor. Coss. 4. As there is no affection
more forcible; so there is none freer from
force and compulsion. The very offer of enforcement
turneth it oft into hatred. There are secret
lincks of affection, that no reason can be rendred
of: asNon amote, Sabidi, nec possum dicere quare: Hoc vnū possum dicere, Non amote. Martial. ep. 33. lib. 1. there are inbred dislikes, that can neither be
resolued, nor reconciled. When Parents haue a
long time beaten the bush, an other oft, as we say,
catcheth the bird: affections are set some other
way, and cannot be remoued. And things fall out
many times so vnexpectedly, such strong liking taken
to some sodainly not once thought on before,
and such strange alienation of affections, where
there hath bin much labouring to linck them, and
that where outward inducements of person estate,
yeeres &amp;c. haue concurred, that euen a naturall
mans dimme eye may easily see &amp; discerne a more
speciall prouidence of God oft carying things in
these cases: And the tongues euen of such are
enforced sometime to confesse, as the Aegyptian
Magitians of Moses his miracles,Exod. 8. 19. 
                     Digitus Dei hic
est, There is a finger of God here; so with Rebekkaes
prophane frends, in such Mariage matches;Genes. 24. 50. 
                     A Domino
factum est istud; This is euen Gods owne doing;
and there is no contradicting of it.
                  
                  To make some Use of these Points.
                  First,Vse 1. Is a good wife such a speciall gift of God?
then is Mariage questionles a Blessing, and no small
one, of it self: one of the greatest outward Blessings

                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                     
                     
                        〈1 page duplicate〉
                     
                     
that in this world man enioyeth.Psal. 128. 1, 2, 3, 4. 
                     Blessed is euery
one, saith the Psalmist, that feareth God, and that walketh
in his wayes. For thou shalt eat of the labour of
thine hands: happy art thou, and it shall goe well with
thee. Thy wife shall be as the fruitfull vine by the sides
of thine house: and thy Children like the Olive plants
round about thy table. Lo, thus shall the man be blessed
that feareth God. In the first place commeth the
Wife as the first and principall blessing, and the
Children in the next. And surely to reason backward
to that the Apostle doth:Rom 11. 16. 
                     If the roote, saith
he, be holy, the branches also be holy: and, If the
branches, say I, be holy then the roote that beareth them
much more. So here, If the branches be blessed, the
roote that beareth them much more. If Children be a
Blessing, then
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                         
                        
                           •••
                        rocles de nupt. apud Stob. tō. 2. cap. 65. the roote whence they spring ought
much more to be so esteemed.Psal. 127. 3. 
                     Behold, Children
and the fruit of the wombe, are the gift of God, saith
Is enim ex titulo Autor videtur. 
                     Salomon. Children are the gift of God; but the
Wife is a more speciall gift of God: shee commeth
in the first place, they in the second: And gifts are
vsually answerable to the greatnes of the Giuer. It
was a witty answer of a great Prince, when he was
disposed to be rid of a bold begging Philosopher:
he asked a groat of him, and the King told him,
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Drachmam dare nō est regium. 
                     It
was too litle for a Prince to giue; he requested the
King then to giue him a Talent, and the King told
him,
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Talentum petere non est Cynicum. Antigonus Thrasyllo apud Plut. in apophth. Et Sen. d
                           •
                         benef. l. 2. c. 17. 
                     It was too much for a Begger to craue. And
surely God indeed in his speciall gifts to vs, is wont
Non quaero quid te accipere deceat, sed quid me dare. Alexand. apud Sē. de benef. lib 2. c. 16. Idem Perillo amico cū ad filias elocandas talēta quīquaginta assignasset, is autem decem suffi
                        
                           •
                        ere affirmasset, 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Plut. in apophth. to regard not so much what is fit for vs to aske or
to expect, as what standeth with his goodnes and
greatnes to giue.
                  
                     
                     Genes. 1. 31. 
                     God, saith Moses, looked vpon all that he had made
and behold all was very good. And
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . 1. Tim. 4. 4. 
                     Euery creature,
or ordinance of God, saith the Apostle, (and he had
spoken of Meat and Mariage in the words before-going:)
is good. All Gods Creatures and Ordinances
are good then;Vse 2. but some are more excellent
then others. And Mariage being of this latter
sort, it is not holy onely, but euen honorable also.

                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Hebr. 13. 4. 
                     Mariage, saith the Apostle) is honourable among all
men: and no disgrace then to any man. So are we
to esteeme of it, and not to contemne what God
hath graced, or to dishonor what he hath honoured.
We shall but wrong the giuer in debasing his
gift.
                  Againe, is a good Wife such a speciall gift of God?
Then if we finde in mariage, inconueniences, hinderances,
distractions, disturbances: Let vs learne
what we are to ascribe it vnto: Not to Gods gift
or ordinance, butSi Dei beneficia vtentium prauitate perpendimus, nihil non nostro malo accepimus. Nihil invenies tam manifestae vtilitatis, quod non in contrarium transferat culpa. Sen. quaest. natur. l. 5. c. 18. to mans corruption abusing
Gods gift, peruerting Gods ordinance, and turning
that to his owne euill, that God hath giuen him for
his good. ForIam. 1. 17. Si Deus bonus, Diabolus malus, nec à bono quicqnā mali, nec à malo quicquā bon
                           •
                         potest provenire. Aug. there is nothing but is good as it
commeth from God. But as
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Aristot. de sens. c. 4. Cum aqua ipsa nec saporem nec odorem habeat. pure water may take
a taint from the pipe that conveigheth it, andTinguntur, eorum
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         trahunt similitudinē, in quorum oram subeundo venere. Plin. hist. nat. l. 2. c. 18. the
Sunne beames receiue a tincture from the coloured
glasse that they passe through: so our foule hands
and filthy fingers oft soile and sully Gods Ordinances,
and our filth and corruption doth oft so taint
and infect them, that they loose not onely much of
their natiue grace, and so strangely transformed,
thatEsai. 58. 5. &amp; 1. 11, 12, 14. Secundum libidinem suam celebrando, sua iam, non Dei fece
                           •
                        ant. Tertull. advers. Marc. lib. 2. God himselfe can scarcely discerne his owne
in them, but they misse also of their fruit and efficacie,

andImprob
                           •
                         nihil prodest; quia quicquid ad illum pervenit, prauo vsu corrumpitur. Senec. de benef. lib. 5. c 21. Nihil potest ad malos p
                           •
                        rvenire, quod prosit, imò nihil quod non noceat. Ibid. of good and commodious, through
our owne default, become euill and incommodious
vnto us. And asPotestas à Deo, abusus ab homine. Antō. sum. part. 3. tit. 22. c. 2. Tyrannie in gouernment is not
the fault of Gods Ordinance, but of mans corruption
abusing it: so in these cases, the euill and inconuenience
is not the fruit of Gods Ordinance,
but of mans corruption accompanying it.
                  If we shall finde then in the maried estate troubles
and distractions, &amp;c. (asQui non litigat caeleb
                           •
                         est. Hieron. adv. I
                           •
                        vin. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Menand. Semper habet lites alternaque iurgia lectus, In quo nuptaia
                           •
                        et, minimum dormitur in illo. Iuven. sat. 6. the single life is commonly
commended for quietnes;)Non queramur de autore nostri Deo, si beneficia eius corrumpimus, &amp; vt essent contraria, efficimus. Sen. quaest. nat. l. 5. c. 18. let vs not accuse
God; as Adam sometime closely did;Gen. 3. 12. 
                     The
woman, saith he, that Thou gauest me; shee gaue me
of the tree, and I ate: as if he had said, If thou hadst
not giuen me the woman, shee had not giuen me of the
fruit; and if shee had not giuen me it. I had not eaten
of it.
                     
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Homer. Iliad. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Gods gifts are all good. But let vs lay the
fault where it is; vpon our selues and our owne
corruption, thatMal
                           ••
                         animu
                           •
                         
                        
                           •
                        mnia in 
                           〈◊〉
                         verti
                           ••
                         
                        
                           〈◊〉
                         quae optimi specie venerant. Sen▪ epist▪ 98. turneth honie into gall, and good
nutriment,Tit. 1. 15. Vis
                           •
                         Galen. de facult. aliment. lib. 1. Dulcia s
                           •
                        in bilem vertent, stomacho
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         tumultum Versa ferent. Horat. sat. 2 lib. 2. Quemadm
                           •
                        d
                           •
                        m stomachus morbo vitiatus &amp; colligens bilem, qu
                           •
                        scun
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         accepit cibos mutat, &amp; 
                           •
                        mne 
                           〈…〉
                         causam doloris trahit: ita animus ca
                           •
                        us, quicquid illi 
                           〈…〉
                         suum &amp; perniciam, &amp; occasionem miseriae facit. Sen. de benef. l. 5. c. 12. as the foule stomacke into choler, or,
Quaecun
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         illi
                           •
                         contigerunt, in natura
                           ••
                         suam vertunt, &amp; ex se speciosa profutura
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         si meliori darentur, illis pestifera sunt. Ibid. as the spider and toade, into venime and poyson.
Els shall we be like those of whom Solomon saith;
Prov. 19. 3. 
                     The folly of a man perverteth his way, and his foolish
heart fretteth against God.
                  
                  Secondly, Is a good wife Gods gift? then let
those that want them, learne how and where to

seeke them. Doest thou want a wife? and wouldest
haue one, and such a one, as thou maist haue comfort
in? Seeke her of God, seeke her with God.
                  Seeke her,Vse 3. I say, first at Gods hands, seek her where
shee is to be had. Humble thy selfe in the sight of
God, and betake thy selfe by prayer and supplication
vnto God.Iam. 1. 17. 
                     Euery good gift, saith Iames, is of God
from aboue: and to be sought therefore at his hands:
and if euery good gift, this more specially, that is so
speciall a gift, and of so principall vse. And,
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . 1. Tim. 4 4. 
                     Euery
Creature or Ordinance, saith Paul, is to be sanctified by
prayer. And if euery Ordinance of God should be
sanctified by prayer; and it ought
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Marc. regul. spirit. 
                     to vshter all our
actions, be they ciuill or sacred▪ then this also among
others, yea this aboue and before others,
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Menand. as that
which (through the blessing of God vpon it) may
proue a matter of the greatest benefit vnto vs, and
without it a meanes of the greatest euill.
                  Yea, seeke her as of God, so with God.Vse 4. Aske
counsell at the mouth of God, when thou goest about
any such businesse.1 Tim. 4. 4. 
                     The Ordinances of God,
saith the Apostle, are sanctified vnto vs, as well by the
word of God, as by prayer. Then are they sanctified
vnto vs by prayer, when we craue leaue for the vse
of them, and a blessing vpon the vse of them by
prayer at Gods hands. Then are they sanctified vnto
vs by the word of God, when we haue warrant,
and take direction, for what we do in them, out of
Gods word, when we aske counsell at Gods mouth.
Then we seeke them with God, when we seeke
them by good meanes, when we seeke them in due
manner.
                  
                     
For when it is said that a good wife is of God; we
are not so to conceiue it, that we are in such cases to
vse no meanes at all; but we are to vse none but
good and lawfull meanes, such as God hath appointed,
either prescribed or permitted.1. Cor. 7. 39. 
                     The wife is
bound, saith the Apostle, while her husband liueth:
but if her husband be dead, shee is at liberty to marry
where she will, but yet,
                     
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . 
                     in Domino, in the Lord.
                  
                  Wherein they offend, either that goe too neere,
matching within those degrees thatLevit. 18. God hath inhibited:
or that go too far of, matchingDeut. 7. 3, 4. 1. King. 11. 1, 2. with such
as they are by religion prohibited to mary; and so
transgressing those rules and directions that the
word of God giueth.
                  As also those that be vnder the gouernment of
others, or that desire those that be in the power of
others to dispose of; they then seeke in the Lord,
when they aduise with, and are content to be disposed
of by those, whom God hath giuen power ouer
them; or when they seeke not to them in the first
place, but to those, by whom God will haue them
to be disposed. That which not Gods people alone,
butGenes. 34. 6, 11. Virginitas non tota tua est: ex parte parentū est; Altera pars patri, data pars est altera matri; Tertia sola tua est▪ Catull. carm. nupt. the Heathen also, by the light of Nature, saw
to be equall and right. When they take other courses,
they seeke beside God, and cannot hope or expect
any blessing from God, whose order and ordinance
therein they breake. In a word, wouldst thou
be blessed in thy wooing, in thy wiuing? Take God▪
with thee in wooing, invite him to thy wedding.
He, if he be pleased, will turne thy water into wine;
if he be displeased, he will turne thy wine into
vinegar.
                  
                     
Thirdly,Vse 5. learne hence what principally to aime
at in the choise of a wife: to wit, at virtue and wisdome,
discretion and godlines: for that is indeed
true wisedome.
                  
                     Solomon saith not, a faire wife is the gift of God.
And yet is
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Act. 7. 20. de Mose. divinitus venustus. Beza &amp; Pisc. beauty Gods gift; and
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Menand. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Plat. polit. lib. 3. Gratior est pulchro veniens in corpore virtus. Hinc Aristoteles, 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Idem
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                         Stob. tom. 2. c. 63. a gift of good
regard. Neither saith he, a wealthy wife is the gift of
God: And yet is1. Chron. 29 12, 14. 2. Chron. 1. 12. wealth also Gods blessing, where
it is accompanied with well-doing. But, a discreet,
or a wise woman is the gift of God.
                  
                  Many indeed there are, that choose their wife by
the eye:Genes. 6. 3. 
                     The Sonnes of God saw the Daughters of
Men to be faire: and they tooke them wiues of them
where they liked: as if they were to buy a picture or
an image to hang vp in the house, or to stand somewhere
for a shew. But
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Nescio quis apud Eustath. 
                     Beauty, saith the Heathen
man, without virtue, is like a baite floating without an
hooke; it hath a baite to entice, but no hooke to
hold. And,Prov. 11. 12. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Veteres apud Eustath. Iliad. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Eurip. Chrys. 
                     A faire woman, saith Salomon, without
discretion is like a gold ring in a swines snout.
                     Prov. 31. 30. Color terrae bonitatis incertus est autor. Pallad. de re rust. lib. 1. cap. 6. 
                     Fauour
is deceitfull, and beauty is but
                     
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Clem. Alex. paeag. l. 3. c. 1. Resest forma fugax: quis sapiens bono Confidat fragili? Sen. Hippol. Florem decoris singuli carpuntdies. Sen. Octav. Forma bonum fragile est; quantum
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         accedit ad annos Fit minor, &amp; spatio carpitur ipsa suo. Ovid. art. l. 1. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                         Isocr. ad Demon. 
                     vanitie: but a woman
that feareth God is praise-worthy indeed.
                  
                  Others againe regard wealth onely; as if they
went about a purchase, as if they were to mary not
them but their money, as if they were to wed not
the wife, but her wealth. But Solomon, when he saith,

                     Houses and Riches are the inheritance of the Fathers:
but a prudent Wife is of the Lord: he implieth that
these things may bee seuered, the one may bee
without the other. Lands may come by inheritance;
whenVirtus non est haereditaria. Non est res beneficiaria. Sen. epist. 89. virtue may not.Bona, vnde bonū facias, non vnde bonus fias. Aug. de temp. 238. 
                     Goods they are
wherewith men may do good, but not such as make
those good that haue them.
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Themistocl. apud Plut. apophth. Malo virū qui pecunia egeat, quam pecuniā quae viro. Cic. offic. l. 2. 
                     Better it is, said the
Heathen man, to haue a man without money, then to
haue money without a man: so better it is to haue a
wife without wealth, then to haue wealth without a
wife. And surely, what comfort can a man haue of
wealth with such a wife, that shall be as a corrosiue
to his heart,Prov. 12. 4. Sicut in ligno vermis, ita perdit virum suum vxor malefica. Hieron. cont. Iovin. l. 1. 
                     as corruption and rottennesse in his
bones?
                  
                  Againe, let Parents learne here what to aime at
in the education of their Children, whom they desire
to dispose of,Vse 6. and to dispose of so as they may
be a blessing, not a crosse or a curse to those that
shall haue them: Not studie onely how to prouide
portions for them: though an honest care also is to
be had in that kinde.2. Cor. 12. 12. 
                     Parents, saith the Apostle,
ought to lay vp for their Children. And,1. Tim. 5 8. 
                     He that prouideth
not for his issue, is worse then an Infidell. Nor
how to trim them vp, and set them out, in whorish
or garish manner, to make them baites to catch
fooles with; but labour to traine them vp in true
wisedome, and discretion, in the feare of God, and
such graces as may make them truly amiable, as
1. Pet. 3. 3. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Clē. Alex. paed. l. 3. c. 1. well in Gods sight as in mans eyes; in houswifry,
and industry, and skill to manage houshold affaires:
that so they may be helpers to their Husbands, (and
not hinderers;) asGenes. 2. 18. to that end they were made
at first.
                  
                     
Yea hence let the wife learne what she is to striue
to,Vse 7. and labour for, that she may be indeed a good
gift of God:1. Tim. 2. 9, 10. 1. Pet. 3. 4, 5. Cultus magna cura tibi magna virtutis incuria. Cato Cens. apud Ammiā. hist. l. 16. Cul
                           •
                        us corporum nimius &amp; formae cura prae se ferens animi def
                           ••
                        mitatem. Sen. ben. l. 1. c. 10. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Crates. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Sophocl. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Lysander apud Plut. in praecept nupt. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Clem. Alex. paed. l. 2. c. 12. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Ibid. l. 3. c. 2. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Ibid. c. 11. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Ibid. lib 2. cap. 9. Not so much to decke and tricke
her selfe vp to the eye, as to haue her inner man adorned
with holy skill and discretion, whereby to
cary her selfe wisely and discreetly in that place and
condition that God hath called her vnto: That she
may with the wise woman,
                     Prov. 14. 
                           •
                        . 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Menand. 
                     build vp the house;
and beProv. 12. 4. Dignae suo co
                           •
                        iux fida corona viro. 
                     a crowne andProv. 31 2
                           •
                        . a grace to him that hath her.
ThatPro. 31. 28. her Husband and Children may haue cause
to blesse her, and to blesse God for her; and
count it a blessed time when they came first togither.
                  Let her consider what a fearefull thing it is to be
otherwise. For her that was
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Basil. Sel. made for a helpe, to
proue not an helpe but an hurt: for her that was
giuen for a blessing, to proue a crosse and a curse.
As one saith of Eve,
                     Gen. 2. 18. 
                     reaft from Adam as a rib,
                     Vse 8. 
                     and
shot by Satan at him as a shaft: bestowed on him by
God to consummate his felicitie, but made by Satans
slight and her owne default, the meanes of his
extreame misery.
                  Fourthly, let men be admonished hence, whom
to ascribe it vnto, if ought haue bin done in this
kinde for them: euen to God himselfe principally,
whose speciall gift a good wife is. Let vs take

heede how in this caseHabba. 1. 16. we sacrifice to our yearne,
or burne incense to our net. Ascribe not what is done
for thee, to the mediation of frends, or to thine
owne plots and policies, smoothnes of language,
fairenes of looke, or the like. No: acknowledge
God to haue bin the principall agent in the busines:
regard man and thine owne meanes, but as his Instruments.
Of him shee is, saith Salomon: notGen. 2. 22. &amp; 1. 27. as a
Creature onely made of him, bnt asGen. 2. 22. one matched
vnto thee by him: nor as knit to thee by his ordinance,Vse 9.
but as
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                         To
                           •
                        us vtvi at
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         foeminae fatalis est. Aes
                           •
                        hyl. Eumen. Hae
                           •
                         scilicet res vna, si v
                           •
                        a, fato gub
                           •
                        rnatur. Dunaeus ad Lys. assigned thee by his prouidence:
For that is it, that Solomon here principally aimeth
at.
                  Yea let them hence learne what they owe vnto
God, whom God hath vouchsafed such a blessing
vnto. Hath God bestowed such a Wife on thee, as
Salomon here speaketh of? It is a pretious Iewell;
such as thy Father could neuer leaue thee. It is a
greater Treasure then the greatest Prince on earth,
then the mightiest Monarch in the world is able to
bequeath to his Heire. We see how Parents are oft
troubled in making search for their Sonnes, and yet
when they haue done their best endeuour, misse of
that they desire. We might here rise by degrees
on the better side, as we did before on the worse. As
euils, so good things, the more inward the greater.
AProv. 17. 2. &amp; 14. 35 Luk. 12. 42. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Menand. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Eurip. Mel
                           •
                        agr. De beneficijs ac fide servorū in Domin
                           •
                        s, consule sis Senec. de benef. l. 3. c. 18. 27. Et Valer. Max. l 6. c. 8. trusty seruant is no small blessing; a
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Hesiod. Hinc de vicinis prospici Cato praecepit, apud Plin. hist. nat. l. 18. c. 6. kinde
neighbour is a great one;Prov. 17. 17. &amp; 18. 24. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Amicus alter ipse. Zeno apud Laert l 7. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Anima vna corporum duorum incola. Aristo
                           •
                         ibid l. 5. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Menand. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Pi
                           •
                        d. Nem. 8. a faithfull frend a greater;

                     Prov. 10. 1. &amp; v. 20. &amp; 17 6. &amp; 23. 15. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Menand. a wise sonne yet a greater; and a prudent
wife the greatest of all: a greater blessing then any
of the former, that yet for temporall blessings may
seeme of the greatest. And how do maried persons
then stand engaged to God aboue others, whom
he hath blessed in their choise? A great measure of
thankfulnes owe they vnto him, proportionable in
some sort to the blessing bestowed on them.
                  Yea as there is a greater measure of thankfulnesse
required of them, then of others whom God hath
not blessed in that manner: so there is a peculiar
kinde of thankfulnes required on their part. All
Gods fauours require thankfulnes: and the more
fauours the more thankfulnes: but some speciall
fauours require some peculiar kinde of acknowledgment,
proportioned to the quality of the fauour
receiued.Psal. 127. 3. Genes 33 5. Children are Gods gift: and our thankfulnes
to him for them is to be shewed in such duties,
as he requireth of vs in the behalfe of them,
Ephes. 6. 4. in the carefull education and training them vp in
good courses. In like manner: Thy Wife thou hast
of Gods gift: and thy thankfulnes to him for her,
must be shewed in the performance of such duties,
as he requireth of thee in regard of her,Ephes. 5. 25, 28, 29, 33. Coloss. 3. 19. of loue, of
kindnes, of concord, counsell, contentment &amp;c.
                  Fiftly,Vse 10. Is the Wife giuen vnto her Husband by
God? then must shee resolue to giue her self wholy
to him as her Owner, on whom God hath bestowed
her, to whom he hath assigned her. When Parents
haue put out their Children, the Children
must be content to be guided by those to whom
they commit them: and when God hath giuen a

Daughter, she must be content to liue with him, and
be guided by him, whom God hath giuen her vnto.
Neither is she to forsake him. ForMatth 19. 5, 6. they are not to
be sundred, nor seuered, whom God hath conjoyned
and made one. And there is a foule brand therefore
vpon her,Prov. 2. 17. 
                     that forsaketh the guide of her youth,
and forgetteth the Couenant of her God. Nor to refuse
to be ruled by him: butEphes. 5. 22. 1. Pet. 3. 1. 
                     submit and subiect her self
vnto him, vnto whom God hath giuen her: for
Coloss. 3. 18. 
                     that is comely, saith the Apostle, in the Lord: and
to be imbraced therefore of her, as her Lot by God
assigned her.
                  Yea,Vse 11. is the Wife giuen the Husband by God?
then should he esteeme her as a gift of God: and
1. Pet. 3. 7. 
                     liue with her, as with one giuen him and bestowed
vpon him by God. We cannot abide to see any
thing that we haue giuen an other euill-vsed. And
it be but a dog, an hound, or a whelp, if we see it neglected,
where we bestowed it, we are wont to take
it euill. But if we should see a jewell of some value,
bestowed by vs on a frend as a token of our loue
toward him, set light by him, or should finde it cast
aside in some corner, would we not much more be
grieued at it, and iudge that he set as light by our
loue, as he doth by our loue-token. And hath not
God then iust cause to take it euill at thy hands,
when he shall see his gift abused, euill entertained,
and worse vsed; when he shall see her misused of
thee, whom he hath as a speciall fauour bestowed
on thee, and hath therefore giuen theeEphes. 5. 33. Coloss. 3. 19. a speciall
charge well and kindly to vse? How are we wont
to be grieued, when we see matters fall our amisse,

where we haue bin meanes to make the match? If
the wife be misused, that we haue holpen one to, we
are wont to count it a wrong to our selues. And no
maruaile then, if God himselfe take to heart the
wrongs done by vs, to those that he hath joyned to
vs, ifMalach. 2. 13, 14, 15. he haue a quarrell against him that shall transgresse
against her, whom he hath inseparably joyned
to him, to be his Companion and his wife by
                     Pactum salu, pro inviolabili. Num. 18. 19. 
                     a Couenant
of Salt.
                  
                  Lastly,Vse 12. if a good Wife be such a speciall gift of
God, then a good Husband is no lesse. For the
Husband is as needfull for the Wife, as the Wife is
for the Husband.Gen. 3. 16. 
                     Thy desire, saith God, shall be
vnto him. And if the Husband then be so to esteem
of his Wife, and to be thankfull to God for her;
then is the Wife no lesse to esteeme so of her Husband,
and to be thankfull likewise to God for
him.
                  In a word, let both man and wife so esteeme either
of other, as joyned by Gods counsell, as giuen
by Gods hand; and so receiue either other as from
God, be thankfull either for other vnto God, seek
the good either of other in God; and then
will God vndoubtedly with his
blessing, accompanie his gift,
to his owne glory,
and their mutuall
good.
                  FINIS.
               
            
         
         
            
               
                  
                  
                  
                     A MARIAGE FEAST.
A
SERMON
ON THE FORMER
PART OF THE SECOND
CHAPTER OF THE EVANGELIST
IOHN;
                  
                  By that learned and judicious Divine
Mr WILLIAM BRADSHAW sometime
Fellow of SIDNEY COLLEDGE
in CAMBRIDGE.
                  LONDON,
Printed by EDWARD GRIFFIN for
FVLKE CLIFTON. 1620.
               
               
                  
                  
                  TO THE WORSHIPFVLL
AND RELIGIOVS,
Mr GEORGE WILMER
Esquire, and Mrs MARGERET WILMER his
Wife, increase of spirituall grace, and mutuall
comfort in CHRIST
IESVS.
                  
                     WORSHIPFVLL AND
beloued in Christ; At the
solemne knitting of you
togither, was this Sermon
preached by that worthy
Seruant of God, and our common frend,
now with God, then first (as I haue heard
him say) performing that office that then
he did. Which of late lighting vpon, among
other his loose papers, I thought it would
not be amisse rather to send it abroad, then
to suffer it (as it might soone perhaps otherwise)
to miscary and so perish▪ The piety

and pithines of the discourse it selfe seemed
to require no lesse of me: that which any
indicious &amp; religious, I assure my self, will
with me easily acknowledge. The rarity
likewise of the subiect the rather encited
me thereunto. He treadeth a tracke not so
vsually beaten. Of Mariage Sermons, that
entreat of Mariage duties, there are extant
not a few. Such as handle the religious managing
of Mariage Feasts, I suppose not
many; I remember not to haue seene any.
It is that, that this holy Man of God doth
here principally insist vpon: and it is a
point very necessarie, and of no small vse.
For to let passe that grosse abuse, too too
frequent among the prophaner sort, that
esteeme such meetings neuer well seasoned,
or aright celebrated, vnlesse filthy discourse
andQualia fuerunt veterum quorundā Epithalamia: &amp; Iescenini versus de quibus Festus &amp; Seruius ad Aen. l. 7. non, vt illi, ab opido Campano; nec à fascino, credo, depellendo sic dicti; sed à fascino, quod obscoenitatis notio
                        
                           •
                        em habeat apud Horat. epod. 8. &amp; Varro orig. lib. 6. obscene songs be as common as any
ordinarie seruice; as if they were not dealing
with a sacred ordinance of God, but
were about the sacrilegious rites of some
impure Idoll; and so, like the idolatrous
Iewes, that turned b 
                     Bethel into c 
                     Beth-aven,
making a Brothel-house of a Bride-house:
As also to passe by the brutish and swinish

disposition of those that thinke there is no
true welcome, nor good fellowship, as they
tearme it, vnlesse there be deepe carousing
and drinking of healths to Bride and Bridegroome,
and euery idle fellowes Mistris, till
the whole companies wits be so
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Synes. de insom. Mergit mentē extrema potatio. Sen. ep. 12. Vnde 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                         dixit Pythagoras; 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                         Chrysippus; Ebrietatē insaniam voluntariam Augustinus ad sacr. virg. &amp; Basilius Ebriū 
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . drownd
in drinke, that not religion onely, but
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . quod de Ira. nescio quis apud Plut. reason
it selfe is vtterly exiled, and the meeting
may well seeme to be rather a drunken
match then a Mariage Feast. To let passe,
I say, the palpable loosenes and lewdnes of
such: euen the best at such meetings are
too prone by ouer-sight, and forgetfulnes
of their dutie to ouer-shoot themselues, and
to exceed that Christian decorum that in
such solemnities ought to be obserued. It
was not without cause thatIob 1. 5. 
                     Iob was so iealous
of his Children, what time they held
their mutuall meetings of somewhat the
like nature.Eccles. 11. 7, 10. Youth, andProv. 23. 31, 32 wine, and mirth,
and other delights, are pleasing and enticing
obiects, andHinc Prouerbiū 
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Vinolentia clavum non habet. Eustath. Odyss. l. Et 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Insanire facit sapientes copia vini. Sthenelus apud Athen. dipnos. l. 10. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Homer. cary the wisest oft vnawares
further then Religion well warranteth.

                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Clom. Alex. paedag lib. 2. cap. 1. L
                           •
                        gatur Plut. sympos. lib. 7. cap. 5, 7, 8. Which yet is not spoken simply to

condemne such solemnities: (It was wisely
and wittily said of the Heathen Man,
that
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Demoerit. 
                     Amans life without festiuities, 
                           〈◊〉
                         like along
and wearisome w
                           ••
                         without Innes:) but
to shew what neede there is o
                        •
                      direction
and admonition for Christian cariage in
that kinde.
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Plut. de aud. poet. 
                     Lycurgus did not well nor
wisely, when he cut downe all the vines in
his countrey, because the wine that came
of them was too much abused by many.
Neither ought Mariage Feasts to be vtterly
abandoned, nor Musicke, or other honest
mirth be exiled and banished from
them, because too many ordinarily exceed
in the one, and not a few wretchedly abuse
the other. Yea, if mirth and festiuitie be
euer seasonable, it is at such times:Math. 9. 15. &amp; 22▪ 1, 2. Genes. 29. 22. Ier. 7. 34. &amp; 16. 9. &amp; 25. 10 &amp; 33. 11. Legatur Plutarch. sympos. l. 4. c▪ 3. Christ
himselfe and the Spirit of God yeeld and
approue it. Onely Christian
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Hi
                           •
                        
                        rax de Iustitia apud Stob▪ cap 5. 
                     Sobriety ought
then to be both our
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . loan. 2. 8, 9. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Plut. sympos. l. 1. c. 4. qui tamen 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                         pronunciat. Arbiter bibendi Horat. 
                           •
                        arm. 1. 3. In convivijs potandi (malè, putandi) Modiperat
                           •
                        res magistri. No
                           •
                        nius ex Varrone rerum human. lib. 20. 
                     Feast-Master, and our
Mirth-Master, our Lord of Rule, not of
Misrule, to moderate both our diet and
our mirth at such meetings. And the rather
should Sobriety and Modestie be at

such times obserued, not onely in regard of
Heb. 13. 4. the holinesse and honourablenes of that
blessed Ordinance of God that then we
deale with, that we mayAct. 10. 15. not pollute that,
that God hath purified, nor dishonor that,
that he hath honoured; but for that also
we are then laying as it were the first foundation
of a new Familie: and
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Eurip. Herc. fur. the building
proueth commonly as the foundation is
well or euill laid.In solido extruendum. Vitruv. architect. lib. 1. cap. 5. &amp; lib. 3. cap. 3. It is euill building on
a quagmire; and laying a foundation in
wet weather. A sober and a modest entrance
giueth good hope of the like progresse;
as
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Hinc Diogenes stolido &amp; amenti adolescentulo, 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Ebrius pater te genuit. Plut. de liber. educ. the contrary is a foule presage
of euill after-demeanure. This how to
preuent is breifely, but effectually here
shewed. That which I haue therefore
thought fit to present You rather with, then
any other of the Authors frends; that
vnder your names that might come abroad
to the vse of others, that was principally
at the first intended for your good;
and partly also thereby to renew with you
the remembrance of him, by whose holy
hand you were publikely at first ioyned
togither. Which coniunction God in mercy

of his good pleasure long continue, and
so blesse and sanctifie vnto you, that you
may haue mutuall comfort either in other
by sincere holinesse here, and eternall coniunction
either with other in perfect happinesse
els-where.
                  
                     Yours in Christ,
Thomas Gataker.
                     
                  
               
            
            
               
                  
                  A MARIAGE
FEAST.
                  
                     IOH. 2. 1—12.
                     
                        1. And the third day there was a Mariage in Cana of
Galile; and the Mother of Iesus was there.
                        2. And both Iesus was called and his Disciples to
the Mariage.
                        3. And when they wanted Wine, the Mother of Iesus
said vnto him; They haue no Wine.
                        4. Iesus said vnto her; Woman, what haue I to doe
with thee? mine houre is not yet come.
                        5. His Mother said vnto the Seruants; whatsoeuer
he saith vnto you, do it.
                        6. Now there were set there six water-pots of stone,
after the Iewish manner of Purification, conteyning
two or three firkins a-peece.
                        7 Iesus said vnto them; Fill the water-pots with
water. And they filled them vp to the brim.
                        8 And he said vnto them; Draw out now and beare
vnto the Gouernor of the Feast. And they bare it.
                        9 When the Ruler of the Feast had tasted the Water
that was made Wine, not knowing whence it
was, (but the seruants that drew the water

                           
                              〈1 page duplicate〉
                           
                           
                           
                              〈1 page duplicate〉
                           
                           
knew) the Gouernor of the Feast called the
Bridgrome,
                        10. And said vnto him; Euery man at the beginning
setteth forth good wine; and when men haue
well drunke, then that that is worse: but thou
hast kept the good wine till now.
                        11. This beginning of Miracles did Iesus in Cana of
Galile; and manifested forth his glory: and his
Disciples beleeued in him.
                     
                  
                  
                     I Cannot handle euery thing
in this Storie, which shall
offer it selfe: But must only
insist vpon those parts therof,
that may most directly
concerne this present solemnitie.
                  The maine scope &amp; drift
of this whole Narration seems to be this.Scope. To shew,
what an honourable estimation and account our
blessed Sauiour Iesus Christ, doth make of the holy
and honorable estate of Mariage, notwithstanding
that himselfe was borne of a Virgin, and did himselfe
in his owne person liue and die a Virgin.
                  This honourable estimation of his, is manifested,
In his gracing and countenancing, the solemnization
of this speciall Mariage, mentioned in this
Storie.
                  Our Sauiour graceth and countenanceth it two
manner of wayes.
                  
                     1. By his presence and companie at the Feast.
                     
                        
2. By working a miracle at it, and that the first
miracle that euer he wrought.
                  
                  Of both these in order; omitting to speake any
thing, of the matters that passe betweene Christ and
his Mother, betweene Christs Mother and the
Wayters, betweene Christ and the Wayters, and
betweene the Gouernor of the Feast and the Bridegroome.
Because the Doctrine flowing from these
particulars, is not so pertinent to this present
Occasion.
                  But before that we descend into particulars, let
vs first in the generall obserue from the maine scope
and drift of this Storie, this instruction.
                  That the more that Sathan and his accursed
Imps,The generall Doctrine. shall labour to disgrace and discountenance
any sacred Ordinance of God; the more will God
grace and honour the same.
                  The truth of this appeares in no one thing more,
then in this matter of Mariage. It is wonderfull to
consider, how the Diuell hath euer laboured to
disgrace and put it out of countenance: How he
hath made the day of ones Mariage, as ignominious
and reprochfull, as if it were the day of ones
publique penance or execution; what laughing and
scoffing, what flearing, jering, and nodding the head
is there, not onely of such as are yet single, but of
those that are themselues maried persons; not only
of profane swaggerers, and those of the damned
crue (as they are called) but of those (many times)
that haue the reputation of Ciuill honest men, yea
of Professors of Religion. In so much, as if those
that are to be knit togither in this sacred bond, were

to measure their estate by the mindes, words, and
ordinarie behauiours of the Spectators, yea many
times of those, who seeme to honor the Solemnitie
with their presence and attendance: It were better
for them to stand as long in a white sheet, or to be
carted thorow the streets, then to present themselues
into the Congregation to knit this holy and inviolable
knot. For in that case lightly you should haue
none but vnhappy boyes, and such persons as are
naught themselues, to make signes of disgrace; good
mindes vse to pitie them that are so publikely
(though deseruedly) disgraced. But here, for the
most part, all, good and bad, old and young, set
themselues, though not with their hands, yet with
their hearts, countenances, and words, to cast durt
and puddle water in the faces of those that are to
enter into this Calling, as if they were to enter into
a Calling most sinfull, and shamefull, and most odious
and vile both in the eyes of God and man.
                  This is indeed a hellish and damnable iniquitie;
but behold yet a greater iniquitie then this: Sathan
hath so wouen his owne impuritie, with the pure
Ordinance of God, that a Mariage, is accounted no
Mariage, if it be not solemnized with beastly and
profane Songs, Sonnets, Ijggs, indited by some hellish
Spirit, and chaunted by those, that are the publique
incendiaries of all filthy lusts; and these are
ordinarily made in the scorne and derision of this
Holy Estate, to delight and solace the Guests withall.
But indeed they tend to no other end, but to
despite and disgrace this worthy Ordinance of
God, and to make it seeme in the eyes of men,

nothing else but a matter of obscenenesse and filthinesse.
So that if God himselfe had not had a speciall
care, to vphold, to grace and countenance this
Estate, by how much more Sathan laboureth to
make it odious and vile, all the world long before
this, had bin a very Stewes and Brothel-house. See
then, the care that God hath to honour this ancient
Ordinance of his; how (notwithstanding that Sathan
hath euer done his vttermost to disgrace it, and
make it vile) God subjecteth the whole world vnto
it, not fooles onely, but wise, not poore, but the
richest, not profane persons onely, but the holiest
and the religiousest that euer were, not base persons,
but Kings and Emperors: So that not onely all
sorts and degrees of men, but in a manner euery
man and woman in the world, he bringeth vnder
this yoke; so that the whole world (to account of)
is as it were, but a maried person: And this is so
much the more to be wondred at, that the Diuell
can make that so shamefull, which is so common.
It is not so in sinnes, nor it would not be so in this, if
it were not a speciall diuine Ordinance.
                  This should incourage vs,The Vse. with all alacritie and
confident Spirits, to submit our selues to any of
Gods Ordinances, and with so much the greater
courage and heart, by how much the more contemptible,
&amp; despised, they shall appeare to be amongst
men. For the more that men do despite Gods
Ordinances, the more will God honour the same,
and those that with honest hearts shall vndergo the
same. You may see Gen. 2. that the very first worke
that God did, after the very first creation of man

and woman, was his marying of man to woman:
and you see here, that one of the first Wonders
that Christ wrought was in honour of a Mariage.
                  We come now to the first point, wherein Christ
graceth and honoureth Mariage, and that is, by
vouchsafing his presence at the solemnization of it,
or at the Mariage Feast.
                  Wherein these two points are to be considered
in order.
                  
                     1. The inviting of Christ vnto the Mariage.
                     2. His comming vnto it, being invited.
                  
                  From the first point let vs learne these Instructions
in order.Invitation.
                  
                  That the Mariage Feasts,The 1. Doctr. in speciall. and Solemnities of
Christians, ought so to be ordered, that nothing
ought to be done or committed therein, that may
not beseeme the presence of our Sauiour Christ.
                  Of this iudgement and affection were these Parties,
that at this time invited our Sauiour Christ, else
they would neuer haue invited him. For far be it
that we should thinke, (yea the Storie shewes the
contrary) that these Persons called Christ to this
Feast, to vex and greiue his Soule, with scurrile and
ribald merriments, and with wanton and vnchast
sports &amp; delights; or that for reuerence of Christs
presence, they excluded and laid aside any lawfull
delights fitting such an Exercise; and therefore,
though there was a solemne Feast at this Mariage,
and though out of question the day was spent in
delights and pleasures, (as is most meete for such
matters) yet they were such delights and pleasures,
as they durst call our Sauiour Christ vnto, yea and
make him a partaker of.
                  
                     
Fie therefore and a shame of such mirth as doth
not beseeme the presence of Christ,The Vse. of such words,
as beseeme not his eares, of such actions and exercises
as beseeme not his holy eyes; such mirth and
pastime is not befitting any Solemnitie, much lesse
so honorable a Solemnitie, as Mariage is or ought to
be, which is a sacred knot, whereby two persons are
inviolably knit togither by the hand of God. As
therefore this day, many of you are called to feast
and rejoyce with these Parties, that are to be vnited
in a faithfull bond: So I beseech you, as you will
answer it before the Lord, and looke for a blessing
vpon these Parties, in loue of whom you are assembled,
that you would looke to your mirth, and see
whether it be such, as in your Consciences you are
perswaded, that Christ Iesus himselfe, if he were present,
would not be offended, but well pleased with it.
Consider whether thy mirth and laughter be such, as
Christ Iesus would be delighted therein with thee:
For Christ our head, mourneth with those that
mourne in him, and rejoceth with those that rejoyce
in him: Otherwise assure thy selfe, that that pleasure
of thine, with which Christ Iesus is displeased,
shall be turned into paine; that that ioy of thine,
wherein Christ doth not ioy with thee, shall be turned
into sorrow; that laughter of thine, that is offensiue
to him, shall be turned into teares. There
cannot be a greater wrong offred▪ to a man, then for
any to make themselues merry with that, which shal
greiue and vex him: How much more is it an hainous
wrong vnto God, when men shall be assembled
to solace &amp; delight themselues in those things,

which doe anger and displease him. Especially at
such a time, when he should be moued to bestow
a blessing vpon the Parties married; and then, when
we begg all joy and comfort for them at the hand
of God. Verily, the monstrous profane abuses that
ordinarily vse to be vpon such Occasions, are no
doubt the speciall causes, of so many curses, that the
Lord layeth vpon many that enter into this honourable
state, when the same shall in such vile manner
be profaned and abused by them.
                  Secondly,The 2. Doctr. in speciall. the example of these virtuous persons
that were maried in Cana, and of them that made
this Feast, is to be imitated of all true Christians,
that haue giuen their names to Iesus Christ: they
must call Christ Iesus to their Wedding, they must
invite him to their Mariage Feast.
                  And great reason it is, that among others, nay
aboue all other Guests, Christ Iesus should be
one.
                  For 1.1. Reason. If you that are to be maried be Christians,
Christ Iesus is the greatest frend that you haue
in the whole world, in heauen, or in earth: And
nature and custome hath taught men this, to call
their cheifest and best frends to their Weddings. So
that inviting others and passing by him, it shewes
that they make higher account of others then of
him, and that (at the least) he is none of their dearest
frends. And they are deadly enemies to Christ that
take not him to be their dearest frend.
                  2.2. Reason. As Christ is the dearest frend to euery true
Christian, so is he the neerest neighbour: Thou
needs not send far for him, he is deere alwayes, and

at hand to those that call vpon him: And it is the
vse euer to invite our neerest neighbours, if they be
our frends. Now the Diuell is his Inmate, who
hath not Christ for his neerest neighbour.
                  3.3. Reason. There is none hath more interest in the Bride
and Bridegroome, then Christ Iesus. He first gaue
them both to their Parents; He hath kept and preserued
them to this estate; He it is that hath giuen
them their health, wealth, strength, beauty, &amp; whatsoeuer
is worthy or louely in them: He could take
it away at his pleasure againe; yea he could in a
moment take the Bride from the Bride-Grome,
and on a sudden, and in the twinckling of an eye,
turne all this preparation of joy into heauinesse
and greife.
                  4.4. Reason. All Christians, are the Sonnes and Daughters
of God, and they are married in the house of God:
Their Parents vpon earth are but Gods deputies.
What a shame were it then to exclude Christ Iesus,
and not to invite him?
                  5.5. Reason. He sends all those things, wherewith thou
solemnizest thy feast: they are all his presents. And
wilt thou faile to invite him, that sendeth prouisions
in so franckly and liberally to thee?
                  6.6. Reason. Who is it but Christ Iesus, that can blesse
any Mariage, and make it comfortable and joyfull
to the Parties? Who but he can curse it, and make
it an yron yoke to both the parties? Therefore
great cause there is to invite him aboue all other.
                  But alas (it will be said) Christ is now in heauen,
and will not come, though he should be invited;
That for our parts wee would count our selues

happy, if he would vouchsafe to come to vs.
                  I answer, that though Christ Iesus be locally absent
in regard of his bodie, yet in regard of his Spirit
he is present: and if mens hearts were set vpon
him, as they ought to be; if they did but desire
his presence, they should finde his presence, euen
in as comfortable a manner, as if he should descend
from the Right Hand of his Father, and in his bodie,
goe with the Bridegrome and Bride to Church,
and sit downe at the table with them.
                  You therefore that are interessed in this present
Action,The Vse. where so many Guests are invited, examine
your owne Soules and Consciences, whether you
haue not forgotten the principall Guest: It were
better that the day of thy Mariage had bin the day
of thy Buriall, then that it should be said, Thou
wast married, and Christ Iesus not remembred:
And therefore if your Consciences smite you in
this, see that before you goe out of this place you
invite him: It is not too late; thou art now in his
presence, lift vp thy heart and minde, and desire
him, that he would be present, and that thou maist
haue his blessed companie; and then you shall be
sure of a blessed and joyfull issue.
                  Thirdly,Doctr. 3. Christians that would haue Christ Iesus
present, at their Feasts and Mariage-Solemnities,
may learne hence, what persons they are to invite
to keep Christ company. For in the Text it is
specified of this Wedding, that the Mother of
Christ was there, and the Disciples of Christ; all
godly persons, all speciall frends vnto Christ. We
say in the Prouerbe, Its merry when frends meet;
                     
And we know by experience, that if men invite
their speciall frend, they will haue a care what
company they entertaine him withall. If it may
be, they will take order that some that they
know he loueth shall be invited to keepe him
company, at least such as they thinke he doth not
hate. Neither can a man doe his frend a greater
wrong, then to invite him to feasting and merriment,
when togither with him, he inviteth such as
will by all possible meanes disgrace &amp; despite him.
                  Beloued,Vse. Christ Iesus is the dearest frend thou
hast in the world, what interest he hath to be a bidden
Guest, to all Christian Mariages, I haue shewed
before. There's none but will say, they haue called
Christ Iesus to their Mariage, and do desire aboue
all things, that he would bestow a blessing vpon
them; you come to the Church in this solemne
manner, to that very end and purpose to call him:
But how doe Christians vse Christ Iesus at such
times? Certainly men vsually prouide Christ such
companions, as if they should rake hell for them.
Such as set themselues, by blasphemie, ribaldrie, and
all kinde of profanesse, to despite Christ Iesus, and
to offer all indignities possible to Him and his Religion.
Is it therefore any wonder, that Christ his
own ordinance to some should proue a curse; when
he himself, in the solemnization thereof, shall be in
such a manner cursed and blasphemed, and when
men at such times in steed of inviting the Mother
of Christ and his Disciples, to keepe Christ companie,
shall bid Annas, and Caiphas, and Malchus,
and other such like mates, whom they know will

set themselues to disgrace and scorne Iesus by all
possible meanes.
                  In the second place it is to bee considered,Christs presence.
that Christ commeth to the Mariage Feast being
called.
                  Whence in order, let vs obserue these Instructions.
                  First,1. Doctr. the wonderfull meeknesse and lowlinesse of
Iesus Christ; that being called, would vouchsafe
his presence, to countenance and grace the mariage
of these two Persons, who as it seemes were but
some poore couple, else they would in all likelyhood
haue forecast to haue had wine enough. It
would be thought a folly worthy to be chronicled,
if a Swineheard or a Shepheard, should presume to
invite the King, and his Councell, to his wedding.
All the Kingdome would be in a wonderment, if
being so invited, they should come and grace his
Mariage with their Presence and with Gifts. Is it
not much more to be wondred at, that the King of
Glory, the Eternall Sonne of God should descend
so low, to grace with his high and holy presence, so
base and lowly a Couple.
                  As Christ was,Vse. so ought much more all his Ministers
to be: Kings and Princes may and ought in
such Cases to keep State; but it must not be so with
the Ministers of Christ; They must be as Christ
and his Apostles were,1 Cor. 9. 22. 
                     All vnto all, that they may
gaine some. Though they ought to rebuke Kings
and Emperors when they are called vnto it, yet
they ought also to subiect themselues to the meanest
and lowest of Gods people, and should not

thinke much to goe to the meetings of the meanest,
if a Christian Soule should desire it.
                  Obserue secondly,2. Doctr. what a wonderfull grace and
countenance herein Christ sheweth to this Ordinance.
Verily, if he had done no more, but this,
to sit downe at the Table with them, to eat of their
meats, and to drinke of their cups, it had bin a far
greater honour, then if he had sent a Companie of
Angels from heauen visibly to haue waited vpon
and serued the Bridegroome and Bride, that same
day. If the Antichristian Papist had but such a
president, to grace their impure Votaries, their
Monks, and their Nunns▪ if Christ had but gone
in that manner, being invited, to a Monasterie, a
Priorie, a Nunnery, or a Hermitage, it had bin
enough to haue cried downe Mariage for euer, and
to haue aduanced their loose single life infinitely
aboue it.
                  This should teach vs to make the same vse of it
for the magnifying of Mariage,Vse. which they would
haue made of it, if they had it for their counterfeit
Virginitie; though its most probable, that the Papists
would not haue shewed themselues so forward
for it, if they should haue perceiued that
Christ had bin such a frend vnto it.
                  Note thirdly from hence,3. Doctr. that Christ Iesus is no
enemie to honest mirth &amp; delight, at such meetings
and solemnities as this, but hath by his owne presence
and precedent approued it. Though we doe
not read in the Scripture, that Christ euer laughed,
yet we neede not thinke that he was so rigide and
austere, that he could indure no mirth and delight;

As though men in his Presence were in their silent
dumps, and made dumbe shewes onely one to another.
Surely then would not Christ haue bin so
often invited to Feasts as he was; or if he had, he
would not haue frequented them so often: For the
speciall vse of Feasts are for frends to rejoyce and
make merry togither in; and therefore in the Holy
Tongue haue their
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                         Chaggim. name, from leaping and rejoycing.
                  So that we see hence,Vse. That there is a season and a
time when Christians may rejoyce togither, yea and
that in the presence and before the face of Christ
Iesus himselfe; he sitting by, and looking on. Seruants
vse to be most merry amongst themselues,
and the presence of Master and Mistris damps their
mirth. But the Seruants of Christ may be as merry
in his presence as behinde his backe. Yea they are
more merry when he sits at table with them, then
when he is absent.
                  I obserue this the rather, to crosse an illusion of
Sathan, whereby he vsually perswades the merry
Greekes of the world; That if they should once
devote themselues to the Seruice of Iesus Christ,
that then they must bid an euerlasting farewell to all
mirth and delight; that then all their merry dayes
are gone; that in the kingdome of Christ, there is
nothing, but sighing and groning, and fasting and
prayer. But see here the contrary: euen in the
kingdome of Christ, and in his House, there is
marrying and giuing in mariage, drinking of wine,
feasting, and rejoycing euen in the very face of
Christ. Nay its not possible, that any person vpon

earth, should joy as the seruants of Christ doe. Doe
but consider the joy of a condemned person, when
at the place of Execution he hath receiued a pardon:
Such is the joy of Christs seruants, especially
then, when Christ comes vnto them. For before
he vses to come, he suffers men to be as persons at
the point of Execution, he brings them euen to the
pit of Hell, to Hell mouth, and then when he
comes to them, he brings a Pardon with him.
Christs seruants indeed haue many greifes, and
qualmes come ouer their heart; but it is then with
them, as with women neere their time of bringing
forth; they are in trauaile with some joy. Cleane
contrary it is with wicked ones; who haue ofttimes
many flashings of joy: but when they are
in the height of it, they are then big-bellied, and
ready to trauell of some sorrow: and their owne
wofull experience makes them expect it. For its
very vsuall with them in the extremitie of their
mirth to say, I pray God I heare of no sorrow, I haue
bin this day so merry. And good cause they haue
so to feare, that cannot be merry, except the Diuell
play the Musitian; that cannot sing, except the
dittie be made in Hell. Let all our jolly Gallants
and merry Companions therefore know, That the
Children of God can be merry and pleasant, though
they cannot cog, lie, sweare, swagger, talke lasciuiously,
and filthily, &amp;c. And they shall then be euerlastingly
merry,Esai. 65. 13, 14, 18, 19. when the wicked that now seeme
to be made of nothing else but mirth and pleasure,
shall gnash their teeth and howle in Hell for euer
and euer.
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                     
4ly.4. Doctr. Sith Christ is ready to come to our Mariages
and Weddings; This should teach vs, to prouide
for him, those dishes, that himselfe best loues, and
that he vseth most to feed vpon. In which prouision,
thou needst not to put euer the more in the Pot for
him, or vpon the Spit, or in the Ouen. But the Table
that thou art to spread to Christ must be in thy
heart; see that thy heart stand syncerely affected
vnto him; yea thou must dresse and prepare thy
Soule for him.Ioh. 4. 32, 34. For as the speciall meat that he prepared
for himselfe to feed vpon, was, his doing of
his Fathers will; so the best dish that thou canst
prepare for him, is, Thy obedience to his will.
                  Those therefore that call Christ to their lewdnes,Vse.
ribaldrie, blasphemie, &amp;c. they call him to a banket
of Carrian, or a worse matter then that; and offer
him a bowle of vineger and gall to drinke.
                  The second meanes,Miracle. by which Christ dignifieth
Mariage, is, by working a Miracle, yea the first Miracle
that euer he wrought, a Miracle whereby he
turnes water into wine, yea into most excellent
wine. I must in regard of Time, handle all these
points togither confusedly.
                  1.1. Doctr. Hence obserue that Christ being called to
the Mariage, cometh thither God as well as man;
yea and graceth the Mariage with the manifestation
of his Deity; so that those that haue this grace to
call Christ Iesus to their Mariage, (and all such call
him, as heartily call vpon him,) they shall feele his
presence, yea and his diuine power in his presence;
for Christ neuer comes being called, but he leaues
behinde him some prints of his Godhead &amp; divine
power.
                  
                     
And this may be a signe vnto thee;Vse. That thou
neuer didst heartily call Christ Iesus, vnto thy house,
and vnto thy table, if thou hast had no sense and
feeling of his diuine power, doing a greater worke
and more powerfull within thy selfe, then is the turning
of water into wine.
                  Secondly,Doctr. 2. Obserue how Christ recompenceth
those that are kind vnto him, how in their necessitie
he worketh a Miracle to supply their want. So that
they, that haue this grace, to invite Christ Iesus, and
to call him to their Feasts, rather then they shall
want any thing needfull for them, he will worke
Miracles.
                  What greater incouragement can men haue then
this, to make Christ Iesus alwayes their cheefest
Guest? For then, rather then they shall die for hunger
or thirst, he will raine milke, and honie, and
Quailes from Heauen, to feede and nourish
them.
                  Thirdly,Doctr. 3. In that Christ vpon present necessitie
turnes Water into Wine, the present Feast requiring
it; It teacheth vs, That Christs extraordinarie works
are not for gazing and wonderment, but for speciall
vse, according to the seuerall necessities of his Seruants.
They wanted wine, the soule and life of a
Feast; and Christ by Miracle makes wine.
                  And first this againe,Vse 1. should be a wonderfull incouragement,
especially to persons entring into
the state of Matrimonie, which seemeth to bring
many necessities with it, to make speciall account
of such a Guest, who will not onely supply their
wants in generall, but their speciall wants, belonging

to their speciall places. He that but in a matter
of ceremonie and complement, turned water into
wine, that there might be no dishonor to that Feast,
where he was a Guest: Will he see any needfull
thing wanting to them that marry in his feare?
                  Secondly,Vse 2. this should comfort men against the
ouer-much cares of this world, for Wife, and Children.
He that now turned water into wine, can
turne stones into bread▪ lead into siluer, brasse into
gold, &amp; will do it rather then thou shouldest want,
and if in his wisedome he did see it good for these
he can also as, easily turne a bad Husband into a
good, and a bad Wife into a good, a Poore man into
a Rich, a Base man into a Noble, a Cottage into a
Pallace &amp;c. Make much therefore of Christ. For
on the contrary side, exclude Christ out of your
Feasts, and he will turne thy wine into water, if not
in the glasse, or in thy mouth, yet in thy stomack; so
that it shall do thy Spirits no more good, then if
thou hadst drunke a cup of cold water.
                  Thirdly,Vse 3. this should teach vs to imitate Christ.
Doth he in this manner honour Mariage by a Miracle?
Surely, those persons that are maried, should
honour him with the like-Miracle. They should endeuour
also to turne water into wine. But how?
Surely, whereas their former lives and conversations
haue bin vnto Christ but (as it were) a cup of
heartlesse water; they should be vnto him
by their amendment, as a cup of
wine to cheere vp his
heart.
                  FINIS.
                  
               
            
         
      
   

