
   
      
         
            The Christian mans care A sermon on Matth. 6. 33. Together with a short catechisme for the simpler sort. By Thomas Gataker, B. of D. and pastor of Rotherhith.
            Gataker, Thomas, 1574-1654.
         
         
            
               1624
            
         
         Approx. 185 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2005-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01529
            STC 11654
            ESTC S102885
            99838647
            99838647
            3033
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01529)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3033)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1099:08)
         
         
            
               
                  The Christian mans care A sermon on Matth. 6. 33. Together with a short catechisme for the simpler sort. By Thomas Gataker, B. of D. and pastor of Rotherhith.
                  Gataker, Thomas, 1574-1654.
               
               [12], 53, [7] p.   
               
                  Printed by Iohn Haviland, for Fulke Clifton, and are to be sold at his shop upon new Fishstreet Hill,
                  London :
                  1624.
               
               
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
               Catechisms, English.
            
         
      
      
         
            2004-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2004-10
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2004-11
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2004-11
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2005-01
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE CHRISTIAN MANS CARE.
            A SERMON ON MATTH. 6.33.
            Together with A Short Catechisme for the Simpler Sort.
            By THOMAS GATAKER, B. of D. and Pastor of Rotherhith.
            LONDON, Printed by IOHN HAVILAND, for FVLKE CLIFTON, and are to be sold at his Shop upon new Fishstreet Hill. 1624.
         
         
            
            
            TO MY VERY KIND AND LOVING VNKLES, Mr. NICOLAS CRISPE And Mr. ELLIS CRISPE, with theirs.
            
               BEloved in Christ Iesus; that which was preached sometime at the request of the one of you, unto A meeting of the Worshipfull Cōpany of Skinners. a solemne Assembly, whereof he then was Chiefe, is now further presented joyntly to you both▪ (and well to you both, by 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Chrysost. in Rom. hom. 19 Fra
                        •
                     res in seculo; fratres in D
                        •••
                     ino; quae posterior major est et melior fraternitas: uti Autor Ambr. nom. Serm. 9. &amp; 79. Aug. de verb. Apost 25. &amp; Max. de divers. 4. 
               a double bond, as well of Nature as Grace, Brethren) together with the rest of yours, as all Branches of one

               Stocke, through Gods gracious provision, neither farre severed in aboad, and combined sweetly in the holy band of true Love. The maine subject Matter of it is nothing in effect, but a Motive or incitement unto that, which it standeth us all upon, in the first place, and with our best care and endevour, as well to seeke after, as to seeke into: To seeke into, that wee may know it, and learne it; to seeke after, that we may be possessed and seized of it. Since it is that alone wherein 
                  Psal. 84.4, 5, 10, 11, 12. Matth. 5.3. Luke 14.15. &amp; 22.29, 30. Act. 20.6. &amp; 22 7. 
               Mans Happinesse wholly consisteth: and it is 
                  Aliud est divitias multas nosse, &amp; aliud possidere: nec notitia divitem facit, sed possessio, Ber. in Cant. 23. not the bare notice of it, but the owning and enjoying of it, that can make men truly and eternally happie. That we may therefore know and understand what it is, wherin it consisteth, and by what means it may be attaineds (And 
                  Praeparatio enim rerum cognitio est, Bern. ibid.
                till wee bee thus acquainted with it, wee can never come to be possessed of it) we must make diligent 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Ioh. 5.39. 
               search and enquirie into Gods Word. for it is that alone that can 2 Tim. 3.16, 17. In 
                        •
                     js quae aper
                        •
                     è posita sunt in scripturis, inveniuntur illa omnia, quae continent fidē mores
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      vi
                        •
                     ēdi, Aug. Doct. Christ. l. 2. c. 9. 
               fully and 
                  Ioh. 17.17. Iam. 1.1
                     •
                  . 2 Pet. 1.19. Ego solis Scripturarum libris Canonicis didici hū
                     
                        •
                      honorem timoremque deferre, ut nullum 
                        •
                     orum Autorē s
                        •
                     ribendo aliquid errasse firmissim
                        •
                      credā. Alios autem ita lego, ut quantalibet sanctitate doctrinaque praepolleant, non ideò verum putem, quia ipsi ita senserunt, sed quia mihi vel per illos autores Canon
                        •
                     cos, vel probabili ratione, quod a vero non abhorreat, pers
                        ••
                     dere potuer
                        •
                     nt, Aug. epist. 19. &amp; apud Grat. dist. 
                  
                     •
                  . 
               infallibly informe us of it: Other

               writings only so farre forth as they are drawne out of it, agree with it, and are grounded thereupon. This Word therefore ought to be 
                  Psa. 1.2. &amp; 119 47, 48, 97· the constant Matter of our daily Meditation; (as containing the fundamentall Lawes and Constitutions of the Kingdom here propounded; together with the Conditions and Capitulations required on the part of all those that are to partake in it, and the roiall Priviledges and Prerogatives annexed thereunto;) if we desire or expect ever to have part and portion therein. But because 
                  Ar
                        •
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      a
                        •
                     s
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      Magistro discitur, Hieron. ad Rustic.
                
               no Art is easily without a Teacher attained▪
                and, in this more specially, all 1 Cor. 3.7. 1 Ioh. 2.20, 27. Spiritus Sanctus necesse est operetur intrinsecꝰ, ut valeat medicina quae adhib
                        •
                     tur extrinse
                        •
                     us, August. in 1 Ioan. 
                        •
                     r. 3. Melius
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      dicit &amp; d
                        •
                     cet, qui intus habitat, quam qui foris clamat, Idem in Ioan. tr. 3. Nolite putare quenquam hominē quicquā discere ab homine. Sonus verborum nostrorū aures percutit; Magister qui docet, intus est. Inanis
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      
                     
                        •
                     it strepitus sermonis nostri, nisi qui doceat, intus sit, Idem ubi sup. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Plut. de Socr. daem.
                
               outward teaching without the inward is uneffectuall: As 
                  Coloss. 3.16. all holy helpes are to bee used, the 1 Thess. 5.20. 
               publike Ministerie especially to be diligently frequented; (
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . the Church is 
                  Christi docenti
                        •
                      Auditorium, B
                        •
                     rn. in Cant. 23. 2 Cor. 13.3. the place wherein hee ordinarily teacheth, who hath 
                  Magister unꝰ qui corda docet, 
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        •
                     abet in 
                        〈◊〉
                     , c
                        •
                     
                     thedram in coelis, August. in 1 Ioan. 3. &amp; de divers. 12. &amp; 41. &amp; de Sanct. 23. his Schoole on earth, though 
                  Esai. 66.1. Hebr. 12.25. his Chaire in Heaven:) so earnest praier is to be used for a blessing from God on all such our courses and endevours either publike or private, that he will be pleased

with his good Spirit to second and assist his owne Ordinances, that thereby 
                  Psal. 119.18. the eyes of our minds may be opened, &amp; 
                  Ephes. 1.18. Luke 24.45. our understandings so illightened, that we may be able in some due measure to see and discerne this estate what it is, and to conceive &amp; apprehend the Mysteries appertaining unto it. Again, because it will little availe us to know it, unlesse we have our share in it▪ to be wel seene in the Statutes &amp; Ordinan
                     •••
                  
                of it, unlesse we have part in the Immunities and Roialties that are therin to be enjoyed: (It is but a double misery for a man to know what is to be had, if he have it not himselfe:) Our next endevour therefore must be (for the effecting whereof also 
                  Psal. 86.11. &amp; 119.33, 34, 35, 36. Eph. 3.14—19. the assistance of Gods Spirit is humbly and instantly to be craved) to have that which we have learned, or do learne, out of Gods word, concerning this Roiall &amp; blessed estate, to be effectually 
                  Iam. 1.21, 2
                     •
                  . 1 P
                        •
                     t. 1.23. 
               wrought into us: (and indeed till it be so wrought into us, it is 
                  Io
                        •
                     . 6.45. Ephes. 4.20, 21, 22, 23. Vide 
                        〈◊〉
                     . 
                        •
                     ez. ibid. 1 Io
                        •
                     . 
                  
                     •
                  .3, 4. 
                     •
                   4.7, 
                     •
                  . never truly, soūdly, or effectually learned of us:) That is, we must strive &amp; labour to have true faith, repentance, and other spirituall

graces surely 
                  Iames 1.2
                     •
                  . Ephes. 3.17. 
               setled in our soules; wherby we may both have a right and title to this Kingdome, and be in some good sort and measure also possessed &amp; seized of it. The rather since that 
                  Apoc. 20.6. Matth. 19.28. Iohn 3.3, 5.after this life none shall partake in it, but those only that in some d
                  •
               gree or other were possessed of it, while they lived here. As it is with us therefore in regard of worldly possessions; so should it be in regard of this heavenly Inheritance. For worldly possessions, we wil get, if we can, a title to them; when we have it, we will be sure that our title be good, and use all meanes to make it sure: and when we have so done, we are not yet then at rest neither; wee cannot bee quiet, till we be seized and possessed of it, yea til we be in an absolute, quiet, &amp; peaceable possession, not of some part of it, but of the whole. In like manner should it be with us for this 
                  Hebr. 3.1. 1 Pet. 1.4. 
               heavenly Inheritance: we must first labour to get a 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Ius, Bez. Iohn 1.12.
               right and title unto it: which by 
                  Ibidem.
                
               faith must be procured: for it is that alone on our part, that by 
                  Rom. 3.23, 24, 28. &amp; 5.1, 2. 
               Iustification &amp; free 
                  Galat. 3.26. 
               Adoption giveth us a title thereunto. In the next place we

must endevour to get some 2 Pet. 1.10. 
               good assurance that this our title to it is good: that which must by the 2 Cor. 13.5. 
               triall of our faith be effected▪ For See the Signes of Sinceritie on Psal. 97.11. (to omit, that by seeming titles many oft are deluded) though our title to it be never so good, yet we may not be aware of it, and so misse may wee of much comfort, until we have taken some due triall of it. And lastly, we must strive and contend to get our selves more and more possessed of it: which must be done 2 Pet. 1.4—8. by the 2 Tim. 1.6. 
               exercise &amp; 
                  Luke 17.5. 1 Thess. 4.1, 10. 
               growth of our faith, and other the graces of God in us, and by 1 Thess. 5.19, 20 a constant usage of all good means wherby the same may be 2 Pet. 2.1, 2. 
               nourished,
               
                  Ephes. 3.16. 
               corroborated, &amp; 
                  Ephes. 4.15, 16. 
               encreased. For 
                  Rom. 6.6, 14. Col. 3.5, 8, 9, 10. the more spirituall grace spreadeth &amp; groweth powerful in us, the more ground get we of our corrupt nature: And 
                  Rom. 6.11, 22. the more cōquest we make of this our inward corruption, the further proceed wee in possession of this our 
                  Ephes. 2.5, 6. Philip. 3.20. 
               heavenly Inheritance. Now because so long as wee live here in 
                  Philip. 3.12. an estate of Imperfection, (for 
                  Philip. 3.13. 1 Cor. 13.9, 10, 11. no perfection is to be had, or to be hoped for of us while we are here) we can never fully be acquainted
               
with the Rules and Rights of this Kingdome, or the parts and parcels of this Inheritance: For so long as 1 Cor. 13.9, 11. 
               we know these, as 1 Cor. 8.1, 2. all other things, but in part,
               
                  Maxima pars corum quae scimus, est minima eorum quae ignoramus, Aug.
                we cannot but of some part of them remain ignorant still: Nor can we attain to such a full and plenary assurāce of our right to it, but that some doubt &amp; scruple about it wil be somtime troubling us: For since that as our other parts, so 
                  Mat. 6.30. &amp; 8.26. &amp; 14.31. &amp; 16.8. Luke 17.3, 4. our faith also is imperfect; and our notice of it as weake ordinarily, as our faith it selfe is; &amp; that where faith is so imperfect, there must needs be some 
                  Mark. 9.24. Idem simul, qui nondum perfecte crediderat, &amp; credebat, &amp; incredulꝰ erat, Greg. in Ezech▪
                   15. 
               infidelity more or lesse mixt with it; it can hardly be avoided but that some 
                  Fides vera cum dubietatis aura, Idem Mor. l. 10. c. 8. 
               wavering should be: especially cōsidering that we have to deal with a most wily Adversary, that is wont oft to be questioning of this our right &amp; title, &amp; by many subtil quirkes, and fallacies, &amp; colourable pretences, endevouring to shake this our assurance: And much lesse can we attaine to any full and absolute; (while but 
                  Rom. 8.23. &amp; 7.25. 
               in part as yet we are sanctified, &amp; but 
                  Rom. 5.2. &amp; 8.24. 
               in hope only glorified;) yea or quiet and peaceable possession of it▪ 
               
                  Rom. 7.17, 20. the enemy being &amp; abiding

yet within our gates, &amp; 
                  Rom. 7.23. Gal. 5.17. daily working our disturbāce: For this cause therfore, and in regard hereof, is our Seeking of this Kingdome, not to be practised for a spurt, or taken up for some time, &amp; then to be let fall and laid downe againe, as if no further need were of it, but 
                  Psalm. 24.6. &amp; 27.8. &amp; 105.3, 4. last it must, and continue 
                  Apoc. 2.10, 26. so long as this life lasteth. Still 
                  Prov. 2.3, 4. Rom. 12.2. 
               searching we must be into it, that we may 2 Pet. 3.18. grow better acquainted with it: and still 
                  Apoc. 32. 
               strengthning our assurance, that we may take 
                  Apoc. 3.10, 11, 12. 2 Thess. 2.15. 
               faster hold of it: and still striving to 
                  Phil. 1.9, 10, 11. 2 Pet. 3.18. 
               grow in grace, that we may 2 Pet. 1.11. get further possession of it: And a principall part must it be of our daily Prayer, that 
                  Matth. 6.10. 
               This Kingdome may come; that not only it may 
                  Luk. 17.21. Vt in nos veniat, Ambr. Dion. de Sacr. l. 5. c. 4. Et in nobis maneat, Tertull. ad Marc. l. 
                  
                     •
                  . 
               come into us to take possession of us, but that 
                  Matth. 25.34. Ne forte veniat, &amp; nobis nō veniat. Multis enim non est obventurum, quod est tamen venturum, Aug. hom. 42. 
               we may come at length also to a full fruition of it, 1 Pet. 1.9. attaining to the 
               
                  Rom. 8.22. 
               end of our faith, and hope, and sanctification, the eternall 
               2 Thess. 2.13. 
               salvation of our soules and 
                  Rom. 8.23, 24. Philip. 3.21. 
               bodies. This is the course that in this discourse you are encited unto; which I doubt not but that you have also made both an happie entrance into, yea and good progresse in

already; yet if any spurre may be found therein, that may helpe to pricke you on (or any of you, or any other that have more need than you) to a more eager 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Phil. 3.13, 14. 
               pursuing, putting on, and pressing hard (with the Apostle) to the marke-ward, for the prize of the high calling of God in Christ Iesus; or if any rub may thereby be removed, that either hath beene, or hereafter may be cast into your way, either by the World, or 
                  Iohn 12.31. &amp; 16.11. the Prince of it, or any homebred confederate of his, whereby you might bee (as the people were by 2 Sam. 
                  
                     •
                  0.12. 
               Amasaes corps) either stayed, or turned aside, or disheartned, or slacked in this your religious course; a plentifull recompence I shall esteeme it of my paines therein taken, and I beseech God to that purpose to give his blessing thereupon. I have unto the Sermon annexed a short Catecheticall Summe, which may helpe, though not your selves, being now past such helpes, yet your younger ones, that are 1 Cor. 3.1, 2. Hebr. 5.12, 13. not past the breast yet, (for which sort in mine owne Family at first I contrived it;) in the enquiry after, and discovery of

the way to this Kingdome▪
                wherein from the grounds of sacred Scripture is briefly declared, how at first we were 
                  Constituti.
                
               possessed of it▪ how we came to be 
                  Destituti.
                
               deprived of it, and by what means we may be 
                  Restituti.
                
               restored againe to it: As also it may helpe to fit and prepare them for the participation of the Sacramēt of the Lords Supper. Commending both to Gods Blessing, and my selfe to your Prayers, I take leave, and rest
            
               Yours in the Lord Iesus, THOMAS GATAKER.
               
            
         
         
            Faults escaped.
            
               Reade p. 8. l. 1
                  •
               . linne seeking. p. 9. l. 11. &amp; 20. Disquisition. p. 11. l. 15. they must be▪ 
               p. 12. l. 17. then any beast p. 
               
                  •
               0. l. 10. which way. p. 23. l. 21. Kingdomes.
            
               In the Margin
                     •
                  
               
               
                  Page 10 l. put Manducant &amp;c. before Sic ergo &amp;c. 
                        〈…〉
                      l. 1 reade 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . l. 
                  n 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . p. 
                  
                     •
                  2. • 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . p. 13. l. 
                  k 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , ibid. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . p. 1
                     •
                  . • 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . p. 28. l. 
                  
                     〈…〉
                   
                  p. 33. 
                     〈…〉
                   fregerit. p. 37. l. 
                  m. libidini. l. 
                  n 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . p. 38. l. 
                  t 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . p. 40. l. 
                  o Aeschil. p. 44. l. 
                  
                     〈…〉
                  , ibid. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  .
            
         
      
      
         
            
            THE CHRISTIAN MANS CARE.
            
               
                  
                     MATTH. 6.33.
                  
                  Seeke first the Kingdome of God, and his Righteousnesse: and all these things shall be added unto you.
               
            
            
               IT is the wonted manner of Physitians, 
               
                  Erumpens sanguis vena secta s
                        •
                     
                     stitur. Fernel. method. med. l. 2. c. 6. when bloud issueth out immoderatly one way, to open a veine elsewhere, and so 
                  Dum revulsionis vi revocatur. Ibid.
                by revulsion, as they terme it, to stay it, by diverting the course and current of it another way:
                  Occasion.
                The like course doth our Saviour Christ take in this place. For observing 
                  Vers. 31, 32. the minds and hearts, the thoughts and cares of most men, to be wholly addicted unto, and caried after the things of this world; he endevoureth in this place to withdraw them

there-from, &amp; so to cure them of this running disease, by diverting and turning the tide and streame of them another way.
                  Drift.
                And as the Apostle would have us turne al our worldly griefe into 2 Cor. 7.10. 
               godly griefe, into sorrow for our sins; and our Sauiour else-where, all our worldly feare into godly feare, into 
                  Matth. 10.28. Timor
                        •
                      timore pellit, ut clavum clavo
                feare of offending and displeasing God almightie; so here he willeth us to turne all our worldly care into godly care, our care for this life,
                  Summe.
                and the things of this life, into care for the things of another, of a better life.
            
               
                  Branch 1.
               Seeke first the Kingdome of God, and his Righteousnesse.
            
            Now because many 
                  Lu
                        •
                     . 12.29. doubts and distrustfull thoughts might hereupon arise in weake or worldly mens minds, how they should be provided for, &amp; furnished with meat, drink, &amp; apparell, and other necessaries of this life; that they may beg or starve, if they looke not after the world: Our Saviour for the better strengthning of their faith herein &amp; further encouragement hereunto, assureth them that upon their due and diligent pursuite of the one, God himselfe will be mindfull of them, to supply them with the other; these things that they now thirst after, and take so much thought for, shall upon their so doing, without their further care bee cast in upon them, and 
                  Non ait, 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , dabuntur; sed 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , addentur, 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , velat add
                        •
                     tamentum: Metaphora ab eis qui poma, pyra, &amp;c. emunt. Piscat. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Chrysost. in Matth. 22. Non ait, dabuntur, sed, adj
                        •
                     cientur. Aliud est enim quod principaliter datur, aliud quod superadditur. Greg. Moral. l. 15. c. 20. 
               added as an ouerplus or an advantage thereunto.
            
               
               And all these things shall be added unto you.
               
                  Branch 2. Division. Parts 2. Part 1. Part 2.
            
            So that the words, you see, divide themselues into two Generall Parts;

                  An Exhortation,
                  
                  And a Motiue to induce thereunto.
               
            
            But for further light and helpe we may subdiuide them into these foure Particulars;
                  Members 4. Member 1. Member 2.
               
                  1. An Act, what we must doe, Seeke:
                  
                  2. The Object of this Act, what it is that we must seeke, Gods Kingdome and his righteousnesse:
                  
                  3. The Order and Manner,
                     
                        Member 3. how and when these things must be sought, in the First place:
                  4. The Benefit that thereby will accrew unto us 
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Chrysost▪ in Mat. hom. 22. 
                     And all these things shall be added unto you.
                     
                        Member 4.
                  
               
            
            To begin with the First, Seeke.
            
            
               Spirituall things must be sought.
            
            
               
                  Coloss. 3.1. 
               Seeke the things that be aboue, saith the Apostle Paul. And,
                  Member 1. Act. Observat. 1. 
               
                  Rom. 2.7. 
               To those that by continuance in well doing seeke glorie, and honour, and immortalitie, saith the same Apostle. And, 
                  Matth. 13.45. 
               The Kingdome of Heauen is like a Merchant that seeketh pretious Pearles, saith our Sauiour.
            
               Sought thus they must be in two respects,
            
               
                  Ratione difficultatis.
                In regard of the Difficultie,
               
                  Respects 2.
            
            And 
                  Ratione d
                        •
                     gnitatis.
                in regard of the Dignitie of them.
            First in regard of the Difficultie of obtaining them:
                  Respect 1. 
               
                  Prius est quaerere quā acquirere.
                because Without seeking they will not be had.
            
            1. Things must be sought,
                  Reason 1. that cannot easily

be compassed; such 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plato Cratyl. &amp; Hippia maj. &amp; de rep
                        •
                     b. l. 4. Plut. de Paedag. Difficilia quae praeclara. Sine studio et ardore quodā mētis in vita nihil qui
                        •
                     
                     quam fit egregium. Cic. de orat. lib. 1. all things of worth and weight are ordinarily, and such also these are. They are compared to a Kingdome both here, and oft 
                  Mat. 3.2. &amp; 5.3. Iam. 2.5. 2 Pet. 1.11. Apoc. 1.9. elsewhere: And a Kingdome, we know, is not easily conquered: a Crowne is not ordinarily compassed with ease. It is not wonne commonly without battaile; nor bought but with bloud. They are compared to 
                  Matth. 13.44. 
               treasure, and matter of 1 Tim. 6.6. 
               gaine. And worldly Wealth, wee well know, (and the heavenly much more) will not be gotten but with labout and trauell.
            2. Things must be sought that are not naturall,
                  Reason 2. that come not by kinde. So 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Aristot. Ethic. Nicom. l. 2. c. 3. 
               Arts and Sciences, (because 
                  Nemo nascitur artifex. Nemo nascitur sapiens. Sen. de Ira, lib. 2. cap. 10. 
               no man is borne an Artist) must by studie and industrie be attained. And much more then this 
                  Ars artium regimen animarum. Gerson. de Recid. pecc. Ars est bonum fieri. Ad hoc, sed non cum hoc nascimur. Sen. ep. 9. 
               Art of Arts; this 
                  Ars regnandi.
                
               Art of reigning; this 
                  Ars benè beate
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      vivendi. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Epict. Arian. l. 3. Ars vitae. Cic. Tuscul. l. 2. Ars vitae rectè agendae. Sen. ep. 94. Ars benè vivendi. Idem ep. 90. Virtus ars est benè vivendi. Aug. de ciuit. l. 4. c. 21. Art of happinesse. Rowse. 
               Art of living well and happily, yea of living everlastingly, 
               
                  Non dat natura virtutem. Non contingit virtus animo nisi instituto &amp; edocto, &amp; ad summum assidua exercitatione perducto. Sen. ep. 9. will not without much studie and industrie be learned: especially lighting upon such blockes, as we all are naturally, being borne 
                  Iob 11.12. Psal. 73.22. Prov. 30.2. Ier. 10.14. starke ideots, and of our selves wholly 1 Cor. 2.14. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               uncapable of ought in it.
            3. Things must be sought, that are not everie where to be had: as forreine commodities that must be farre fecht. But such is 2 Pet. 3.13. Mat. 13.45. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Macar. homil. 38. Praeclara rara.
                the Righteousnesse spoken of in this place.
                  Reason 3. It is a simple that every soile will not beare: a rare drugge
               
that every countrie or climate will not afford. 
                  Eccles. 7.29. It grew once in Paradise. But upon the fall of our first Parents, —Terras Astraea reliquit. Ouid. Met. lib. 1. Neglecta terras fugit Astraea. Memor. Octav. 2.1. —ad sup
                        •
                     ros Astraea recessit. Iuven. sat. 6. Terra cessit, in coelumque migrauit. Lact. Instit. l. 5. c. 5. 
               it left this world; and it is 
                  Iob 28.13, 14. 
               not now to be found here on earth, in the land of the liuing. It must be fetched againe, as (
                  Hesiod. Oper. l. 1. they say) fire was by Prometheus from heaven. 
                  Iam. 1.17. 
               Every good giving, and every perfect gift, saith S. Iames, commeth 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , ut Act. 14.17. vel 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Mat. 21.25. i. à D
                        •
                     o. Drus. in prov. &amp; q
                        •
                     aest. l. 2. c. 61. 
               from above.
            
            4. Things lost must be sought ere they can be againe found. So our Saviour saith, 
                  Luk. 19.10. 
               he came to seeke what was lost. And 
                  Luk. 15.8, 9. 
               the Widow in the Parable, by seeking found her lost 
               
                  Drachma enim valebat 7. denarios cū dimidio. Breerwood de num. Iud. cap. 1. 
               test
                     •
                  r. Such are these, we had them once, but we have now lost them. Our first Parents were 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  i. in ostro nati: uti Claudian. nup. Honor. &amp; Mar.
                
               borne, as I may so say, with this 
                  Gen. 1.26, 27. Eccles. 7.29. 
               royall robe;
                  Reason 4. they were created with this 
                  Psal. 8.5. 
               imperiall Crowne. But the Devill stript them of it; 
                  P
                        •
                     rrexit pomum, &amp; surripuit paradisum. Bernard. de Grad. humil. 4. he cheated and coosened them of this Crowne, as wee vse to doe Children, with 
                  Gen. 3.5, 6. the Apple, or 
                  Ficum vult Moses Bar-Ceph. &amp; Theod. in Gen. quaest. 28. Mal
                        •
                     granatum Machmed. in Alcoran. Malum Medicum alij, alij Persicum, quod Pe
                        ••
                     e G
                        •
                     ll. Alij pomum Paradisi, prout fructum quendam Syri indigetant. Sed &amp; Malum ex Hebr
                        •
                     i
                        •
                      quidam ex Cant. 2.3. vide Perer. ad Genes.
                what ever fruit it were, that he tendred unto Eve. So they lost it: and their posteritie must recover it, ere they can enjoy it; they must win this Crowne againe, before they may weare it.
            Thus you see then that these things must be sought in regard of the hardnesse and difficulty, because otherwise they cannot be had.
                  Respect. 2.
            
            Now they must againe be sought in regard of the dignitie of them. Which worth and dignitie of them appeareth in the next Point.
            
            
               
               
                  Vses 2.But before we passe to that, the Vse of this in a word.
            
               
                  Vse 1. Confutation.
               And the First use hereof may be for Confutation, to controll the vaine conceits of those that thinke that these things wil come without seeking; 
                  Credunt dormientibus sibi haec cō
                     fectur
                        •
                      Deum. Ter. Adelph. 4.5. Non curāt quaerere, quae tamē desiderant invenire: cupiunt cō
                     sequi, non &amp; sequi. Bern. in Cant. 2. that hope to have them though they never once looke after them, or the meanes whereby they may be attained; that make account that heaven and happinesse will drop into their mouths, if they doe but gape when they lye a dying, and say, Lord have mercy upon me, or, Lord helpe me to Heaven. It were to little purpose for our Saviour to incite us here to seeke thus after them, if without such seeking they might bee had. No, 
                  Prov. 2.4. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Menand.
                
               If thou seeke for it, saith Salomon, as for silver, and search for it, as for treasure, &amp;c. And God, saith our Saviour, will have us 
                  Matth. 7.7. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Sophocl. Plut. de fortun.
                
               aske that we may have, and seeke that we may finde, and knocke that it may be opened unto us. And as he addeth there, that 
                  Matth. 7.8. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Idem. Nil tam difficile, quin quaerendo investigari possiet. Ter. Heaut. 4.2 
               Hee that seeketh findeth: so 
                  Illud desperandum est, posse nobis casu bonum tantum contingere. Sen. ep. 50. certaine it is, that he that seeketh not, is never like to finde ought.
            
               
                  Vse 2. Conviction.
               Another Vse hereof may be for Conviction, to convince many 
                  Nemo in sapientiam incidit. Nulli sapere casu obtigit. Sen. epist. 76. Et cui credere contigit? Bern. de Consid. lib. 3. not to have what they professe and pretend to have. For how many pretend title to, and claime interest in this Kingdome, that neuer tooke paines or labour about the compassing of it? How many professe themselves to be possessed of the Righteousnesse
               
here spoken of, that never travelled or laboured in the searching out of it, or in the seeking after it?
            He would be d
                  •
               emed a most vaine man, that would boast and beare men in hand that 
                  Quomodo Caius Caesar Gall
                        ••
                      Graecisque aliquot un
                        •
                      c
                        •
                     ndemnatis, Gallograeciam se subegisse g
                        •
                     oriabatur, cum pedem Italia non e
                        •
                     tulisset. Et Occanum ipsum deuicisse, cum legionibus signo dato imperasset, ut conchas per otium in litore l
                        •
                     ger
                        •
                     n
                        •
                     . Sueton. C
                        •
                     io. cap. 29. &amp; 46. Et Domitianus qui falsum à Germania triumphū egit, emptis per commercià, quorum habitus &amp; crines in captivorū sp
                        •
                     ciem formarentur. Tacit. Agric. Ac si quis de certaminibus gloriosè peractis gloriaretur, qui nec oleum quidem quo ungi solebant athletae, oculis unquam usurpasset, ut Theocrit. idyl. 4. he had beene at the East Indies, conquered a great part of the Country, and brought away much treasure and rich commodities from thence, who yet had never crossed the seas, or set foot once on ship-bord, or come neere the sea side. And no lesse vaine are they, that would have men beleeve them, that they haue made conquest of the Spirituall Canaan, and possessed themselues of much of the wealth and treasure of it; when as they never yet stirred once out of the mysticall Aegypt, never so much as enquired the way to it, much lesse ever travelled toward it. He would be deemed most ridiculous, that would professe 
                  Acsi eruditum se quis jactaret, 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , qui nec Aesopum unquam didi
                        •
                     isset: ut Aristoph. avib.
                to have rare skill in the Mathematickes, or some other abstruse Science, when he had never spent day or howre in the studie thereof. And no lesse ridiculous are they that will seeme to have gotten much skill in this spirituall 
                  Arte regnandi, siue imperandi, ut Liv. hist. 22. vel Arte Imperatoria▪ ut Cic. de Orat. l. 1. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Greg. Naz. Apolog.
                
               King-craft, (if I may so terme it▪) and yet never beate their heads, or busied their braines about it; never studied 
                  Euangelium Regni. Matth. 4.13. &amp; 24.14. 
               the Gospell of this Kingdome, the onely Booke out of which it may be learned. Yea in this regard is this Spirituall Treasure rather like learning than

               wealth; in that 
                  Pecunia veniet ultrò, honor afferetur, gratia ac dignitas fortasse ingerentur: virtus in te non incidet, ne levi quidem opera, aut parv
                        •
                      labore cognoscitur. Sen. ep. 76. worldly wealth and Honours may be had without labour or study by the donation of others, or by succession and descent; this, 
                  Philosophia non est res beneficiaria: non obvenit. Sen. epist. 90. not so; each one must seeke it for himselfe, and must seeke and labour in it himselfe, or else the seeking of others, and their endevour for him, will stand him in little stead.
            It is a pithie speech, indeed, that Bernard hath, and in his sense not unsound. Speaking of those words of the Prophet, 
                  Lament. 3.25. 
               The Lord is good to him that trusteth on him, and to the soule that seeketh him; 
               
                  Si tam bonus quaerenti, quid invenienti? (Quomodo idem in Cant. Si tā bonus sequentibus, quid consequentibus?) Sed in hoc mirum est, quòd nemo te quaerere valet nisi qui prius invenerit. Vis quaeri ut inveniaris: vis inveniri ut amplius quaeraris. Bern. de dilig. Deo, cap. 3. 
               If God be so good, saith he, to him that seeketh him, what will he be to him when he findeth him? But a strange matter it is; That no man can seeke God before he have found him; nor can a man sinne seeking of him, when he hath once found him. God will be sought, that he may be found of us; and he will be found, that he may further be sought of us. Men cannot seeke him, saith hee, untill they have found him: and certaine it is that they have not yet found him, that never sought him, or that doe not still constantly and 
                  Psal. 105.4. 
               continually seeke him.
            Yet for the better explaining of Bernards meaning in the words before recited, &amp; the assoiling of some scruple that thēce might arise, as also for the reconciling of some 
                  Luke 11.10. &amp; 13.24. speeches of our Saviour, that may seem the one to crosse the other: we must understand, that 
                  Esai. 65.1. there is never any seeking on our part, before some proffer on Gods part: for 
                  Potes quaeri &amp; inveniri: praeveniri non potes. Bern. de dilig. Deo, c. 3. Ad bonum assurgere perfectè non possumus, nisi nos spiritus &amp; praeveniendo excitet, &amp; subsequendo confortet. Greg. in Ezech. 10. Nolentem praevenit ut velit: volentem subsequitur, ne frustra velit, Aug. Enchir. cap. 32. 
               man can by no means

prevent Gods worke. Now to passe by those 
                  Rom. 1.20. &amp; 2.15. common lights and helpes of nature by God generally afforded unto all, of which the Apostle Paul to 
                  Act. 17.27. the Athenians, and 
                  Act. 14.17. the Lycaonians in the Acts; because 1 Cor. 1.21. &amp; 2.7, 8, 9. they never prove effectuall in this kinde to any purpose ordinarily in any: and to confine our selves to those aides that hee offereth and affordeth usually in his Church; which alone in ordinary course are effectuall to this end: There is as a twofold vocation; so a twofold diquisition: As 
                  Vocatio duplex; externa, interna: s
                        •
                     
                     ve generalis &amp; specialis: vel communis &amp; peculiaris▪ Vide Aug. de Corrept. &amp; Grat. c. 7. Drus Miscell. lib. 2. cap. 2. &amp; Calv. Institut. l. 3. c. 24. §. 7. a twofold vocation on Gods part; an externall vocation, in the offer of the meanes, which doth not alwaies take effect; of which our Saviour, 
                  Matth. 20.16. &amp; 22.14. 
               Many are called, but few chosen: and 
               
                  Quae &amp; vocati
                        •
                      secūdum propositū
                     ▪ Rom. 8.28. 2 Tim. 1.9. an internall vocation, in the blessing accompanying those meanes, which cannot bee without effect; of which the Apostle, 
                  Rom. 8.30. 
               Those that hee calleth, he justifieth; and those that hee justifieth, he glorifieth. So there is 
                  Disquisitio duplex.
                
               a twofold diquisition or seeking on our part; an outward seeking (if I may so tearme it) in the use of the meanes, the studie of them, and paines taking about them, which yet is not alwaies effectuall: For, 
                  Hosh. 5.6. 
               They shall goe to seeke the Lord with their sacrifices; but they shall not finde him, saith the Prophet: And 
                  Luk. 13.24. 
               Many shall seeke to enter, but shall not bee able, saith our Saviour. The other inward, 
               
                  Ier. 24.7. &amp; 30.21. &amp; 31.18, 19. 1 Ioh. 5.20. when those meanes by the gracious assistance of Gods Spirit, have wrought thoroughly upon the heart: of which the Psalmist, 
                  Psal. 119.2. 
               Blessed are they, that seeke him with their whole heart:
               
and God by the Prophet, 
                  Ier. 29.13, 14. 
               They shall seeke me, and finde me; because they shall seeke me with all their heart. And this is that seeking that Bernard speaketh of, which is ever effectuall; and of which our Saviour therefore, 
                  Matth. 7.7, 8. Luk
                        •
                     
                   11.9, 10. 
               Whosoever seeketh findeth. For none so seeke but such as by effectuall vocation are found of God before: none so seeke, but such as by effectuall conversion (the inseparable effect and fruit of such vocation) have 
                  Ierem. 24.7. &amp; 31.18. 
               returned unto God, and so found him in part alreadie. But as none are called ordinarily in the latter sort, but those that are called first in the former: so none seeke ordinarily in this latter sort, but those that have diligently 
                  Prov. 2.3, 4, 5. &amp; 4.19 10, 20. &amp; 8.33, 34. Io
                        •
                     . 5.39. Luke 10.39, 42. Act. 8.27, 28. &amp; 16.13, 14. &amp; 17.11, 12. sought first in the former: which seeking our Saviour therefore inciteth hereunto, and by which we may hope to attain to the latter, if we continue constant therein, through Gods blessing thereupon. But without it there is no hope ever to attaine to it, or to finde that, that in some sort may bee 
                  Iohn 7.34. Rom. 9.31, 32. sought and not found, but 
                  Psal. 119.155. cannot bee found unlesse it bee sought; and when it is once found, is so farre from causing men to give over their seeking, that it maketh them, 
                  Sirac. 24.23, 24. Propter saporis dulcedinem, qui gustatus magi
                        •
                      excitat appetitum, Bern. de Temp. Sic ergò quaeramus tanquam inventuri, &amp; sic inveniamus tanquā quae situri: quia Sirac. 18.6. Ibid. l. 9. c. 1. Videantur &amp; Ambros. epist. 11. Gregor. in Evang. hom. 36. Bern. de Dilig. Deo, c. 1. &amp; epist. 2. &amp; 341. &amp; de Divers. 38. Mā
                     ducant &amp; bibunt, quia inveniunt; &amp; quia esuriunt &amp; si
                     
                        •
                     iunt, adhuc quaerunt. Nam &amp; invenicudus quaeritur, &amp; quaerendus invenitur, qui &amp; quaeritur ut inveniatur dulcius, &amp; invenitur, ut qu
                        •
                      ratur avidiu
                        •
                     , Aug. de Trinit. l. 15. c. 2. encited by that sweetnesse that they finde in it in part found, 
                  Esai. 26.9. Psal. 119.10, 45. seeke more diligently now than ever before.
            Without 
                  Nugae d
                        •
                     ff
                        •
                     c
                        •
                     les. Turpe est difficiles habere nugaes: Et 
                        〈◊〉
                      est in
                        •
                     ptiarum, Martial▪ l▪
                   2. epist. 86. tristes ineptiae, Caecilius. imò ridiculae, Sen. epist. 113. Sophismata, quae nec ignoranti nocent, nec scientem juvant, Idem epist. 45. 
               seeking then, these things are

not to bee expected.
                  Question.
                But are they worth the seeking? may some man say. There are indeed some 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Scopas Thessal. Plu. de Avarit.
                
               toylsome toyes, hard to come by, but of no use or worth when a man hath them: like an Olive, or a Date stone, hard to cracke the one, and to cleave the other, but nothing or nothing worth ought, when it is crackt or clouen, within either: And the very wealth, yea and the 
                  Latrunculis ludimus. Jn supervacuis subtilitas teritur, Sen. epist. 106. 
               learning too of many consisteth much in such.
            But these are not so:
                  Answer.
                The things here propounded as they are 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . hard &amp; difficult, so they are singularly 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               excellent. And therefore as they must bee sought ere they can bee had in regard of their difficul
                     •
                  ie;
                  Respect. 2. so they may bee sought that they may be had, in regard of the dignitie, the worth, the excellencie of them; yea in regard of the use to, and the necessitie of them.
            For first, here is a Crowne, a Kingdome,
               
                  Member 2. Object. Branch 1. the highest pitch of ambitious mens aymes. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Eteocles apud E
                        •
                     rip. Phoenis. apud Plut. de Aud. Poet. &amp; 
                        •
                     anit. tu
                        •
                     d. Nam si violandum est jus, regnādi gratia Violandum est: alijs rebu
                        •
                      pi
                        •
                     tatem col
                        ••
                     , Cic. Offic. lib. 3. 
               If for any thing a man should breake his faith, it should be for a Crowne, for a Kingdome; saith one. And the Devill hoped, if by any meanes, by the proffer of 
                  Matth. 4.8. 
               a Kingdome, to draw our Saviour to his impious and devillish desires. If such reckoning then be made of 1 Cor. 9.25. 
               a corruptible Crowne, of 
                  Psal. 68.33. 
               an earthly Kingdome, 
               
                  Dan. 5.21. 
               the Kingdome of men; that which when it hath beene long a getting, may be lost and gone againe

the very next 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Eurip. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Idem Hecub.
                
               day, yea may bee overturned in an 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Demetrius Phalar. apud Plut. ad Apullo
                        •
                     . Longam morā dedit malis properantibus, qui diē dixit; hora momentum
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      t
                        •
                     mporis 
                        •
                     
                     vertendis imperijs suffecere, Sen. epist. 91. Simul parta ac sperata decora un
                        •
                     us horae fo
                        •
                     tuna 
                        •
                     vertere pot
                        •
                     st, Li
                        •
                     . hist. l. 30. V
                        •
                     ncendo didici magna momento obrui, Sen. Troad 2.2. 
               houre: what account should be made of an 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , 1 Cor. 9.25. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Iam. 1.12. 
               incorruptible Crowne, of a Crowne that cannot bee lost, of an heavenly Kingdome, the Kingdome of God; of 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                  ▪ 
                  Heb. 12.
                     •
                  8. 
               a Kingdome, saith the Apostle, that cannot be shaken, of 
                  
                     
                        •
                     sal. 45.6. 
               a Throne that standeth firme and immoveable forever?
            Secondly, here is Righteousnesse, 
               
                  Ephes. 4.24. a principall part of Gods Image, 
               
                  Gen. 1.27. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Greg. Naz. i
                        •
                      Matth. 19. Haec antecedit animalia; Deos sequitur, Sene
                        •
                     . epist. 76. wherein Man at fi
                  •
               st was made:
                  Branch 2. that whereby man excelleth the beasts;
                  Quic quid longa ser
                        ••
                     s, multis laboribus, mul
                        •
                     a numinis indulgentia stru
                        •
                     it, 
                        •
                     d 
                        〈◊〉
                      dies spargit &amp; d
                        •
                     ssipat, Senec. e
                        •
                     ist. 91. and that maketh him 1 Iohn 3.7. 1 Pet. 1.15, 16. 
               like God; yea without which man is not only no better, but farre worse than a beast; and whereby men doe as farre excell men, as men themselves doe beasts. For 
                  Ipsis best
                        •
                     is bestiali
                        •
                     r est hom
                        •
                      ration
                        •
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     , &amp; ratione non 
                        〈◊〉
                     , Bernard. in Cantic. 35. 
               a man endued with reason, without this righteousnesse, that is, without religion, is (not only as bad as, but) far worse than a b
                     •
                  ast. And 
                  Ratione homines jum
                        •
                     ntis, religione homines hominibus antistant. Vltra homines prove
                        •
                     it probitas sola, infra hominem detrudit improbitas, 
                        •
                     oct. Consol. lib. 4. Pros. 
                  
                     •
                  . 
               Religion maketh some men excell other some that want it, as much as reason maketh them excell brute beasts.
            
            It was the saying of an Heathen Man, that 
                  Nihil est virtute formosius, ni
                        ••
                     l pulchrius, 
                        〈…〉
                     , Cicer. de Nat. De
                        •
                     r. lib. 1. &amp; 2. &amp; de Amic. Quae si oculis cerneretur, mirabiles sui amores ex
                        •
                     i
                        •
                     ar
                        ••
                     , Idem O
                        •
                     fic. lib. 1. Omnes mortales in admirat
                        •
                     onem sui r
                        •
                     per
                        •
                     t. Senec. epist. 89. Nemo non amore ejus arderet, si vid
                        •
                     re illam contingeret, Ibid. 115. 
               Morall vertue was so beautifull, that if it could be seene with bodily eyes, it would make men to be

wondrously enamoured with it. And yet was that, saith Lactantius, but a bare 
                  Vmbra quaedam &amp; imago j
                        •
                     stitia, Lactant. Jnstitut. l. 5. c. 17. &amp; l. 6. c. 6. &amp; 
                        •
                     aber. in Rom. cap. 2. 
               shadow of the Righteousnesse here spoken of. But 
                  Sire ipsam prae
                     
                        •
                     l
                        •
                     r
                        •
                     ssimam omniū penitus videremus, quonam gaud
                        •
                     o cō
                     pleremur, quum 
                        •
                     ā
                     topere, ejus adambrata op
                        •
                     nione laetemur? Cic. de Fin. lib 5. if the shadow be so excellent, what is the substance? if the Picture be so beatifull; what is the Person it selfe, which the Picture commeth so far short of? 
                  Tanti Vitrum, quāti margaritum. Tertul. ad Martyr. Tanti vit
                        •
                     ū, quāti verum margari
                        •
                     ū? Hieron. ad Deme
                        •
                     r. ad Salvin. &amp; alibi.
                If they made such account of their glassie bugle, saith Ierome after Tertullian, how ought this rich and pretious Pearle of ours to be esteemed of? This to that is as 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Homer. Iliad. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     
                     ▪ V
                        •
                     lius argē
                     tum est auro. vi
                        •
                     tutibus aurū, Horat. lib. 1. epist. 1. 
               Gold to Brasse, saith Bernard; and a little of 
                  Melius est pallens aurum quam fulgens aurichal
                        •
                     ū. Bern. in Cant. 61. 
               the palest and coursest Gold is farre better than much of the finest and brightest Brasse.
            
            But let us consider them a little severally.
            In the First place then, here is
            
               A Kingdome propounded to all Christs followers anf favourites.
            
            
               Seeke Gods Kingdome, saith our Saviour.
            Concerning which,
                  Branch 1. it shall not be amisse to enquire;
                  Observ. 2.
               
                  1. What Kingdome this is;
                        Points 3.
                  
                  2. Wherein it consisteth;
                        Point 1.
                  
                  3. Why it is so termed.
               
            
            The Kingdome then here spoken of, is not so much the Kingdome of God 
                     •
                  ver us, as the Kingdome of God in us: not the Kingdome whereby 
                  Psalm. 
                  
                     •
                  03.19. Luke 19 27. he reigneth over us; (and yet it is no small priviledge and preeminence to be subject and 
                  Psal. 18. &amp; 36. Title. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , Man. Pal
                        •
                     ol. praecept. 7. Rom. 1.1. Phil. 1.1. Merit
                        •
                      Paul
                        •
                     s hoc titulo gloriatur, 2. Cor. 11.22. O praeclarum ministerium, quo non principatu gloriosius? Bern. de Consid. l. 2. 
               servant to so puissant a Soveraigne; if they were counted 1 King. 10.8. 
               happie that were in Salomons

service, then are they much more 
                  Psal. 84.4, 13. 
               blessed that dwell in Gods house and court, that have dependance upon him:) but the Kingdome whereby he reigneth in us, and wherein we reigne with him: 
                  Luke 12.32. 
               It is your Fathers will, saith our Saviour, to give you a Kingdome. And, 
                  Apoc. 1.6. &amp; 20.6. 
               Hee hath made us Kings and Priests, and we shall reigne with him 
               
                  Apoc. 22.5. 
               for ever. And, 
                  Apoc. 3.21. 
               To him that overcommeth I will give to sit on my Throne, as I overcame, and sit on my Fathers Throne.
            
            Now of this Kingdome there are two degrees.
            
            
               
                  Point 2. Degrees 2. Degree 1 Branch 1.There is first 
                  Regnum gratiae.
                
               a Kingdome of Grace; wherein 
                  Rom. 5.21. 
               we reigne here in grace by Christ, whereby wee haue power here;
            1. To quell, conquer, and over-come 
                  Humilis res est stultitia, abjecta, sordida, servi
                        •
                     is, multis affectibus et saevissimis subjecta. Hos tā graves Dominos, interdum alternis imperantes, interdum pariter, dimittit à te sapiē
                     tia, quae sola libertas est, Sen. ep. 37. Quē vicerim quaeris? non Persas, non extrema Medorū, &amp;c. sed avaritiam, sed ambitionem, sed metum mortis, qui victores gentiū vicit, Idem epist. 72. Nulla major est victoria, quam viti
                        •
                      
                     
                        ••
                     muisse. Innumerabiles sunt qui urbes, qui populos h
                        •
                     
                     bu
                        •
                     re in potestate; paucissimi, qui se. Quaest. Nat. l. 3. our naturall corruptions, our lusts and concupiscenses within us, our outragious passions, our unruly and inordinate affections, 2 Pet. 2.12. Iude 16. Non eunt, sed feruntur, Sen. ep. 23. Turpe est autem non ire, sed ferri, Idē ep. 37. wherewith worldly men are led captive, enslaved and enthralled, and which 
                  Rom. 6.17. 1 Cor. 12.2. Tit. 3.3. before our conversion bare sway, and ruled in and over us also. 
                  Sibi imperare maximum est imperium, Sen. ep. 113. Sivis tibi omnia subjicere, te subjice rationi. 
                        〈…〉
                      rexerit, Idem ep. 37. 
               It is a point of the highest command, saith the Heathen man, for a man to have command of himselfe. 
               
                  Regem non faciunt 
                        •
                     pes, Non vestis Tyriae color, Non 
                        〈…〉
                      r
                        •
                     giae, Non a
                        •
                     ro 
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        •
                     rabes. Rex 
                        •
                     st, qui 
                        〈◊〉
                      me
                     
                        •
                     us, Et diri mala pectoris: Qui tuto positus loco, Infra se videt omnia. Rex est qui metuit; rex est qui cupit nihil. Sen. Thyest. 2.2. Latius reg
                        •
                     es avi
                        •
                     um 
                        •
                     omando Spirit
                        •
                     m, quàm si Lybiam remotis Gadibus jungas, &amp; uter
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      Serviatuni, Horat. Carm. 2.2. Rectius enim i
                        •
                      appellabitur Rex quam Tarq
                        •••
                     ius, qui
                        •••
                      se nec suos regere potuit. Cic. de Finib. l. 3.—tum omnia jura tenebis, Cum poteris Rex esse tui, Claud. de 4. Coss. Hon.
                
               He is a King that dreads nought; hee is a

King that covets and desires nothing. And, 
                  Immane regnum est posse s
                        •
                     ne regno pati. Senec. Thyest. 3.1. 
               It is a wondrous great Kingdome for a man to be able to contemne a Crowne, to set light by a Kingdome, as 
                  Hebr. 11.24, 25, 26. 
               Moses did, that preferred afflictions with Gods people before it; to tread, not the Earth only, but the very 
                  Apoc. 12.1. 
               Moone too, and all sublunarie things, as 
                  Philip. 3.8. 
               drosse and Trash under his feet.
            2. To prevaile against,
                  Branch 2. and triumph over all the enemies and adversaries of our salvation without us, and all such outward evils as they are able to raise up against us. To which purpose it is that the Apostle having spoken before of persecutions the sword, f
                     •
                  mine▪ and nakednesse; 
               
                  Rom. 8.35, 36, 37. 
               In all these things, saith he, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Sicut Soph
                        ••
                     l. Elect. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               wee are more than Conquerors, (What is that? even Triumphers.) through him that hath loved us. For, 2 Cor. 2.14. 
               God maketh us alwaies to 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Theophyl. triumphat, i. tri
                        •
                     m
                     
                        •
                     hare facit Prunas.
                
               triumph through Christ. 
               
                  Crux Christo currus fuit triumphalis. Thom. Cartw. Harmon. Euang. in Luc. 13.32. &amp; Ioan. 12.32. Sic &amp; Col. 2.15. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Ignat. ep▪
                   5. Cum ultima hoste morte 
                        〈◊〉
                     , per trophaū crucis triumphavit, Tertull. ad. Marc. l. 4. 
               The very Crosse of Christ, saith one, was Christs Charet of Triumph. And the verie same is the Crosse even to this day to all Christians; it is their Charet, their Chaire of estate. 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Ig
                        ••
                     t. ep. 4. Duris ut ilex 
                        〈…〉
                      P
                        •
                     r damn
                        •
                     , per 
                        •
                     aede
                        •
                     , ab ipso Sumit opes animū
                     
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      ferro. Non hydra secto corpore firmior vinci d
                        •
                     lentem crevit in Hercui
                        ••
                     . Merces profundo: pulc
                        •
                     rior evenit. Luctere: magna pro
                        ••••
                      integrum Cum laude victorem, Horat. Carm. 4▪4. 
               He is a valiant Champion indeed, saith Ignatius, who though he be beaten, and receive many blowes, yet will not give over till he have vanquisht his adversarie. 
                  Apoc. 12.11. 
               They overcame him, saith the Holy Ghost, 
                  Apoc. 13.7. 
               that warred upon them, and overcame them, by the bloud of the L
                     •
                  m
                     •
                  e▪ 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   by the word of the Testimonie, and by not thinking much to lay

                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
downe their lives unto death; by setting light (as 
                  Act. 
                  
                     •
                  0.24. the Apostle of himselfe) by their lives. The Spirit of God may seeme to contradict himselfe when he saith in the one place, 
                  Apoc. 13.7. 
               He made warre upon the Saints and overcame them; and in the other againe, 
                  Apoc. 12 11. 
               They conquered and overcame him. But the one is spoken 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . according to humane conceit, the other 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . according to the truth of the thing. And certaine it is, that as Gods 
               
                  Tunc enim non ex malo uno, sed ex omn
                        •
                     bus simul &amp; s
                        •
                     m
                        •
                     l liberantur, Aug. in Psal. 34.17, 19. Ita liberantur, ut liberari amplius o
                        •
                     us non habeant, B
                        •
                     rn. in Psalm. 91.15, 16. 
               Children are never better delivered out of their troubles, than when they seeme not to be delivered at all, when they are delivered out of them by death. So 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Oecum. in 2 Cor. 2. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Chrysost. in Rom. hom. 15. they never more prevaile against, and triumph over their adversaries, than when those their adversaries outwardly seeme most to prevaile against, and to triumph over them.
            But because this their 
                  Ps
                        •
                     l. 45.13. 
               Majestie is most inward, and 1 Iohn 3.2. 
               the world cannot so well see it: there is secondly therefore 
                  Regnum gloriae.
                
               a Kingdome of Glorie, whereby those that 
                  Rom. 5.21. 
               reigne now in Grace by Christ, shall one day 
                  Rom. 5.17. 
               reigne in Glory with Christ. For, 
                  Coloss. 3.3, 4. 
               our life is now hidden with Christ in God; saith the Apostle: But when Christ, who is our Life shall appeare, then shall we also appeare in glory with him. And, 1 Iohn 3.2. 
               We shall at his appearing become like unt
                     •
                   
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  ,
               
                  Degree 2. 
               because we shall see him as he is. As 
                  Ephes. 2.6. 
               We are now glorified in him, so 2 Thess. 1.10. 
               hee shall then be glorified in us; what time we shall heare from him that blessed and joyful sound, 
                  Matth. 25.34. 
               Come and receive the Kingdome prepared for you from the beginning of the world.
            
            
               Now further this Kingdome is called the Kingdome of God;
                  Point 3. Reasons 4. Reason 1. Reason 2. Reason 3. Reason 4.
               
                  1. Because 
                        Matth. 20.23. he hath prepared it;
                  2. Because 
                        Luke 12.32. he conferreth and bestoweth it;
                  3. Because 
                        Apoc. 4.10. of and under him we hold it;
                  4. Because 
                        Apoc. 20.6. with him wee reigne in it; for from him we receive it, and together with him we reigne in it.
               
            
            Is it a Crowne and a Kingdome then, and such a Crowne and a Kingdome,
               
                  Vses 4. that our Saviour here maketh offer of?
            This serveth first, as to discover,
                  Vse 1. Reprehēsion.
                so to check and control the base-mindednesse of most men in the World: Who, as 
                  Num. 11.5, 6. the Israelites preferred the 
                  In cepe &amp; alliū impensa 1600. talenta in pyramidū una extruenda, refert Herodot. l. 2. 
               Leekes and Onions of Aegypt, before 
                  Psal. 78.25. 
               the bread of Angels, 
               
                  Iohn 6.31. the food that came downe from heaven; so preferre paltry Peables before these pretious 
                  Matth. 7.6. &amp; 13.45. 
               Perles; 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Habac. 2.6. 
               thick
                     •
                  clay, as the Prophet speaketh, before this 
                  Apoc. 3.18. 
               pure Gold; the worlds counterfeit coine, before this 
                  Luke 16.11, 
               true treasure; the base and slavish service of sinne and Satan, before the Crowne and the Kingdome that our Saviour here maketh offer of: that choose rather, with 
                  Gen. 49.14, 15. 
               Issakar, (dull asses indeed) to couch themselves quietly betweene two packes, and bowe their shoulders downe to beare any such (even unsufferable and unsupport
                  •
               bl
                  •
               ) burdens as 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ; Chrysost. in Matth. 38.1. Legatur Pers. Sat. 5. &amp; ad eundem Epictetum ex Arian. dissert. l. 3. c. 26. apud Casaub. qui eos multa facere contendunt qui cupiditatibus suis serviunt, quae si servus domini jussu faceret, de dura servitute sua multum quiritaret.
                the World is wont to impose on those that are slaves and drudges to it; than to rouse up

their spirits, that lye groveling on the ground, seeke to shake off the yoake, and free themselves from this thraldome, and strive to get command of him, that now keepeth them as captives: that 
                  Malunt servire Diabolo, quam regnare cum Christo: Cui servire regnare est, Bern. de Temp. 110. &amp; de bon. des
                        ••
                     .
                are content to serve the Divell rather, and their, nay his, brutish lusts, (
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Clem. Strom. l. 2 Nulla voluntariâ turpior est servitus, Sen. epist. 47. the baddest and basest service that can be,) than to reigne with Christ, or to serve him in a free and honourable service, whose 
                  Rom. 6.21. Fallitur egregio quisquis sub principe credit Servitium: nusquam lib
                        •
                     rtas gratior extat. Claudian. de Stilic. Philosophiae servias oportet, ut tibi contingat vera libertas. Qui se illi subjecit &amp; tradidit, statim circumagi
                        •
                     ur. Hoc enim ipsum Philoso
                        •
                     hiae s
                        •
                     rvire, libertas est, Senec. epist. 8. 
               service is true freedome, and 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Gregor. Nazianzen. de Pace 2. 
               to serve him is to reigne with him, who maketh all his servants Captaines, Commanders and 
               
                  Veruos quam Assur, Esai. 10.8. 
               Kings.
            
            Againe, it serveth to discover and convince many, not to be that indeed, which they professe themselves to be, not to be Christians indeed and truth, though they beare the name and title of such. For Christianitie is a Kingdome.
               
                  Vse 2. Conviction.
                It not freeth men only from the thraldome of Sinne and Satan; (
                  Iohn 8.31, 32, 36. Arbitrium voluntatis tunc est vere liberum, cum vitijs peccatisque non servit, Augustin. de Civitat. lib. 14. cap. 11. Sapientia sola libertas est, Senec. epist. 37. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Nisi sapiens nemo liber, Zeno apud Laert. Cic. Parad. 5. Non natura servum facit, sed insipientia: nec manumissio liberum, sed disciplina, Ambros. epist. 7. Solus sapiens liber est, Ibidem.
                
               they are free indeed that Christ maketh free;) but it maketh them Kings also to rule and sway over such as 
                  Ephesians 2.2, 3. before they were enthralled and enslaved unto. Whereas many millions of those that professe themselves to be Christians, remaine still Satans

vassals, 
               
                  Alius libidini servit, alius avaritiae, alius ambitioni, omnes timori. Dabo cō
                     sularē aniculae servi entē: dabo ancillulae divitē, Sen. ep. 47. Si metuis, si parva cupis, si duceris ira, Servitij patiere jugum; tolerabis iniquas, Interius leges -Claud. 4. Coss. Hō. Liber est qui servitutē effugit sui. haec est assidua servitus, &amp; in
                        •
                     luctabilis, &amp; per diē ac nocte aequaliter premens, sine intervallo, sine cōmeatu. Sibi servire gravissima servitus est, Sen. Nat. q. l. 3. Extr
                        •
                     ma est servitꝰ, cū animae vitijs d
                        •
                     ditae, rationis propriae possessione c
                        •
                     ciderint, Bo
                        ••
                     . Cōs.
                slaves some to their filthy lusts, some to their mucke and their money, some to their pride and ambition, some to their furious affection, some to one corruption, and some to another. Yea as one saith of Rome when she was in her Pride, that 
                  Victrix gentiū
                     ▪ captiva vitiorū. Aug. de Civ. l. 15. c. 4. 
               shee conquered other Countries abroad, but was vanquished with her owne Vices at home: and another of the Persian Kings, that 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plut. ad praesect indoct. 1 Esd 4 26, 29, 30, 31. E
                        •
                     ū sibi dominas, Ambr. ep. 7 captivarum suarū captivi. Ibid.
                they commanded the whole World, but their Wives or Concubines commanded them. And Cato of the Romans; 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Cato Censor. Plut. Apophth.
                
               All men, saith he, but we, rule their wives; We rule all mē; &amp; our wives rule us. And the Orator of Verres, that 
                  Iura omnia Populi Romani nutu at
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      arbit
                        •••
                      Chelid
                        •
                     nis meritriculae gubernari, Cic Verrin. 5. 
               he governed the Province, &amp; a base strumpet him. And Themistocles of himselfe, &amp; the Athenians, That 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Plut. in Apophth.
                
               the Athenians ruled all Greece, hee the Athenians, his Mother him, and his Sonne his mother: So many in this kinde, they are 2 Pet. 2.19. 
               Masters of others, and yet servants themselves; command some, but are againe commanded by others; 
                  Bonus etiamsi serviat, liber est: Malus, etiams
                        •
                      regnet, servus est: nec unius hominis, sed quod gravius est, tot dom norum, qu
                        •
                     t vitiorum, Aug. de Civit. Dei, l. 4 c. 3. Est sa
                        •
                     ie
                        •
                     t
                        •
                      &amp; s
                        •
                     rvire libertas: Stulto &amp; imperare servitus est: Et q
                        •
                     od p
                        •
                     jus 
                        •
                     st, cum paucioribus praesit▪ pluribus dominis &amp; gravioribus servit▪ Servit enim proprijs passionibus, servi
                        •
                      cupiditatibus suis, quarum dominatumnec nocte pote
                        ••
                      fugere nec d
                        •
                     e, Ambr. ep. 7, Vidit eos qui judiciorum D
                        •
                     minos se dici volebant, harū cupiditatū 
                     
                        •
                     sse servos. Cic. Ver. 3 Quos videssedere celso Solij culmine Reges, &amp;c. Detrahat siquis superbis Vana tegmina cultus, 
                        •
                     ā videbit in
                        •
                     us a
                        •
                     ctas Domi
                        •
                     os ferre 
                        •
                     atenas, Multos 
                        •
                     erre tyrannos, Bo
                        •
                     t. Co
                        •
                     sol. l 4. m
                        •
                     tr. 2. Refraenet pr
                        •
                     us libidin
                        •
                     s spernat volup
                        •
                     at
                        •
                     s, racundiā ten
                        •
                     at, coerceat avarit
                        •
                     ā, caetera
                        •
                      animi l
                        •
                     bes repella
                        •
                     . Tū 
                     
                        •
                     ncipia
                        •
                      al
                        •
                     j
                        •
                      imperare, 
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        •
                     pse imprubissimis Dominis dedecori a
                        •
                      turpitudi
                        ••
                     , parere desierit. Dum his qu
                        •
                      de obe
                        ••
                     e
                        •
                     , nō modo Rex, sed liber habendus omnino non erit. Cic. Parad. 5. Vide &amp; Horat. 
                        〈◊〉
                     . l. 2. Sat▪
                   7. have as many

               Lords as lusts, that beare rule and sway in them; For 2 Pet. 2.19. 
               by whom a man is overcome, his bond-slave he is, saith S. Peter: And, 
                  Rom. 6.16. 
               His servant hee is, whom he yeeldeth obedience unto; saith S. Paul: And, 
                  John 8.34. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Diogen. Laert. l. 6. Melior est autē ejus status qui famulatur homini, quam qui suae servit cupiditati, Aug. in Prosper. Sent. 164. 
               who so committeth sinne, is the servant of sinne, saith our Saviour. As long therefore as 
                  Iam. 4.1. —intus &amp; in j
                        •
                     c
                        •
                     re aegr
                        •
                     , Nascuntur domini, Pers. Sat. 5. Intra se dominos habet: intra seservitiū patitur intolerabile, Ambr. ep. 7. Levius autē est malum captivum esse corpore quam animo, Salviā. de Provid. l. 6. thou hast a Master, yea many Masters, within thee, thou art a slave to thy corruptions, 
                  Iam. 1.14. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Plat. leg. l. 1. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Antonin. vit. sua, l. 7. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Ibid. 12. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Ibid. l. 10. &amp; Chrysost. to. 8. Ser. 13. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Tu mihi qui imp
                        •
                     rita
                        •
                     , al
                        •
                     js servis miser, atque Duceris ut nervis alienis mobile lignum, Horat. ser. l. 2.7. they rule and sway thee as they list, they winde and turne thee whither way they will, like an artificiall motion that goeth with a screw, and stirreth as that writhes it; so long as thou reignest not over them, but they reigne in and over thee, and thou art ruled &amp; swayed by them, so long thou art no Christian, whatsoever thou mayest be counted or called; For Christianitie is a Kingdome; and 1 Cor. 7.22. 
               every Christian is not a Free-man only, but in this kinde even 
                  Apoc. 1.6. &amp; 5.10. 
               a King too.
            
            But are they so indeed? And are all Christians called to a Crowne,
               
                  Vse 3. Admonition.
                to a Kingdome? Then let them learne hence how charily and warily it behoveth Christian men to walke of all others.
            For first, 
                  Soli latere si licet, Regi licet. Sen. de Clem. l. 1. c. 8. Nam lux altissima fati Occuliū nihil esse sinit, Claud. de 4. Conss. Hon.
                
               The Sunne may goe unseene as soone as Kings may.
               
                  Reason 1. 
               
                  Qui in excelso aetatem agunt, eorum facta cuncti mortales novere, Salust. ad Caesar.
                They are in the eye of the world, and 
                  Omnium in ista conversi sunt oculi, Sen. vbi sup.
                all mens eyes are on them. And, 
                  Matth. 5.14. 
               You

are the light of the World, saith our Saviour, not to us Ministers alone, but to all Christians in generall. Yee are as 
                  Idem.
                
               a Citie seated on an hill, that cannot be hid.
            
            Againe,
                  Reason 2. the 
                  In maxima fortuna minima licentia, Salust. in Catil. Magna servitꝰ fortuna magna, Sen. ad Polyb. c. 26. Minimum debet lib
                        •
                     
                     re, cui nimium licet, Sen. Troad. Quanto plus liceat, tam libeat minus, Auson. 7. Sap.
                
               greatest states afford least libertie. 
               
                  Liberiora omnia sunt his quorum affectꝰ tegi possunt, Sen. ad Polyb. c. 25. Multa tibi non licent quae humillimis &amp; in angulo jacentibus licen
                        •
                     , Ibid. c. 26. Cui omnia licent, propter 
                        〈◊〉
                      ipsum multa non licent, Ibid. Quam multa tibi non licent, quae nobis tu
                        •
                      beneficio licent? Serv. ad Neron. de Clem. l. 1, c. 8. Many things may well beseeme meane men, that will in no wise become great ones. It stood not with Themistocles his state to stoope downe to take up of the spoiles, that the enemie had throwne from them in flight; but, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Plut. Themist. Servo quo melior, quo liberior sit avarus, In trivio fixum cum se demittit ob assem, Non video. Hor. ep. 16. l. 1. Hinc &amp; Pers. Sat. 5. In
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      luto fixū possis transcendere nummum.
                
               Take thou up of them, if thou wilt, saith hee to one of his followers; thou mayest well enough; for thou art not Themistocles; thou art not as I am: And many things may well beseeme a worldly man, as 
                  Mat. 6.32. to be greedie of the world, and to 
                  Phil. 3.19, 20. 
               minde earthly things, which will in no wise become a Christian.
            
            Besides that, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Dion. Chry. orat. 1. the greater and higher the person is that offendeth,
                  Reason 3. the more 
                  Indignitate peccans pecca
                        •
                      amplius, Iustin. in Authent. &amp; Hilar. Pp. apud Grat. c. 25. q. 1. c. 4. Majore Regum scelera taxantur modo, Sen. Herc. fur.
                hainous and 
                  Omne animi vitium tanto conspectius in se Crimen habet, quanto major qui peccat habetur, Iuvenal. Sat. 8. conspicuous is his offence. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Greg. Naz. in Matth. 19. In veste labes candida est insignior, Iuel. Apolog. Eccl. Ang.
                Any spot is soone spied upon white apparell; and the least staine doth evill upon a royall roabe. A small defect in a Christian is more, than a greater matter in a meere Worldling. And 
                  Ideò dete
                        •••
                     es sumus, quia meliores esse debemus, Salvian. de Provid. l. 4. therefore

               are such worse, saith Salvian, though they be no worse, than others, because they ought to bee better.
               
                  Vse 4. Exhortation.
               
            
            Lastly, is it no lesse matter than a Kingdome, that we are here invited unto? This may serve to incite us, if there be any mettle in us, to the diligent &amp; industrious seeking after it. 
                  Perp
                        •
                     ssi sunt exercitus in
                        •
                     piam rerum omnium, vixerunt herbarum radicibus, &amp; dictu foedis tulerunt famem. Haec omnia passi sunt pro regno (quo magis mir
                        •
                     ris) alieno, Sen. epist. 17. Ab mis
                        •
                     ris quid si peteretur crimine tanto Limes uter
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      poli? pugna est de paupere regno. Stat. Theb. l 1. Who would not put hard for it, to winne a Crowne, to gaine a Kingdom? Here is fit matter for our ambitious thoughts and desires to be working upon with warrant. For, as Augustine observeth, that there is a kinde of lawfull and religious 
                  Qui vetat te esse foeneratorem, idem jussit te esse foeneratorem, et dicitur tibi, Foenerare, Aug. in Psal. 36. 
               Vsury, that the Word of God alloweth; 
                  Prov. 17.19. 
               He that sheweth mercie to the poore, lendeth on Vsurie to the Lord; and it shall with large interest be repayed him. And there is a kinde of spirituall 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               Covetousnesse, that the Spirit of God approveth of; when men are 
                  Veri boni aviditas tuta est, Sen. ep. 23. 
               greedie of Grace, they can never have enough of it; 
                  Matth. 5.6. 
               Blessed are they that hunger and thirst after Righteousnesse. So there is a kinde of holy 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Rom. 15.20. 2 Cor. 5.9. 1 Thess. 4.11. 
               Ambition, that our Saviour Christ not alloweth only, but enciteth also, and exhorteth us hereunto. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 1 Cor. 12.31. 
               Affect, saith the Apostle, the best, the chiefest things. And, Let even a Kingdome at least, a Crowne, and no lesse, saith our Saviour, be your aime. It is enough for earthly Princes, their followers and favourites, if they can attaine to some Titles of inferiour Honour, to be Dukes and Marquesses, or the like. But if they begin once, 
                  Legatur Dio Cass. hist. lib. 57. with Seianus, to have an eie or aime at a Crowne, 
               
                  Nulla fides regni so
                        ••
                     j
                        •
                     , omnisque potestas, Impatiens consortis erit, Lucan. lib. 1. that will in no wise bee indured in them. But it is not

some 
                  Vsque ad regni dimid um. Ester 7.2. Marke 6.23. inferiour Honour, some petie place in a kingdome, but the Crowne and Kingdome it selfe, that our Saviour Christ here would have us shoot at, and seeke after. And who would not seeke after a kingdome, if he had any hope to attaine it? Wee see upon what uncertaine hopes ambitious persons in such cases lay 
                  Jmperia pr
                        •
                     tio quolibet cōstant b
                        •
                     
                     nè, Polyni
                        •
                     es apud Sen. Theb. 4. all at the stake, and hazard losse, not of living only, but of life. And certainely our Saviour would never encite us to seeke after it, if 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . it were not to be had. Yea he giveth us assurance, that if we seeke seriously, and so as we should, we shall finde it. For 
                  Luke 11.10. Solus Deus nunquam frustra quaeritur, etiam quum non invenitur, Bern▪ de Cons
                        •
                     d. l. 1. 
               Every one, saith he, that so seeketh, findeth: he is as sure to finde, as if he had found already. 2 Tim. 1.17. 
               One siphorus sought me diligently, saith the Apostle, and he found me: And so, 
                  Prov. 8.17. 
               I love them that love me, saith the Wisdome of God, that 
                  Apoc. 19 11. hath the disposing of this Crowne, 
               
                  Apoc. 2.26. &amp; 3.21. of this Kingdome; and all those that seeke me early, 
               1 Chron. 28.9. 
               shall be sure to finde mee. The Kingdome of this World, as the 
                  Aurum quaesiturus es, &amp; 
                        •
                     orte non inventurus: quisquis me quaerit, cum illo sum. August. in 1 Iohn 10. 
               Wealth of this World, may bee sought, and not found; this Kingdome we shall not misse of, if wee seeke it as we should. 
                  Amaturus es honorē, &amp; 
                        •
                     ortasse u
                        •
                      perventurus. Qui
                        •
                      me amavit, &amp; n
                        ••
                     s ad me pervenit? Ib.
                He that sincerely desireth it, hath in part attained it already.
            But a Crowne, a Kingdome? may some say.
                  Objection.
                
               
                  Imperare omnes volunt; parere nemo. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     
                     ▪ Greg. Naz. Apol.
                What man is there that will none of it? What need any man bee encited or exhorted to accept of it? 
                  Quis non perpetuò v
                        •
                     vere velit? Salvian▪ a
                        •
                      Eccles. Cath. l. 1. Nemo est qui beatꝰ esse nolit. Aug. de lib. Arb. l. 1. c. 14. Vit
                        ••
                      beatam omn
                        •
                      hominem mod
                        •
                     s omnibus vel
                        •
                     e quis dubitat? Id
                        •
                     m 
                        •
                     pist. 121. Who would not have heaven

and happinesse? Who would not reigne in heaven eternally with God and Christ? Vnlesse it be some wretched &amp; accursed Atheists, that thinke there is no such thing to be had.
            
               
                  Subjection.
               Yea but there is somewhat more than so in it. 
                  Matth. 19.28. Wee must begin to reigne here, if wee meane to reigne there. We must partake with Christ here in the 
                  Rom. 8.23. 
               first-fruits of Grace, if we desire hereafter to partake with him in 
                  Iohn 1.14, 16. 
               fulnesse of Glorie.
            
            
               Observ. 3▪
                  
               
               There is no accesse to this Kingdome, but by Righteousnesse only.
            
            
               
                  Branch 2.
               Seeke Gods Kingdome and his Righteousnesse, saith our Saviour Christ here. And, 
                  Rom. 5.21. 
               That Grace may reigne through Righteousnesse; saith the Apostle else-where.
            
               
                  Questions 3.Now concerning this Righteousnesse, three Questions would be discussed;

                  1. What is meant by Righteousnesse here;
                  2. Why it is called the Righteousnesse of God;
                  3. Why no part in this Kingdome can be had without it.
               
            
            
               
                  Question 1.There is therefore a twofold Righteousnesse; and every true Christian (it is the constant Doctrine of all our Divines; and 
                  Legantur quae Mortonus noster adducit ex scriptoribus Pontificijs, Apolog. Cath. par. 1. l. 1. c. 24. our Adversaries wittingly wrong us, when they charge us with the contrary) hath his peculiar share in either. There is 
                  Iust
                        •
                     tia imputata, Rom. 4.6. 
               a Righteousnesse imputed, and there is 
                  Iustitia impertita, Ephes. 5.9. 
               a Righteousnesse imparted; the one 
                  Ierem. 23.6. &amp; 33.16▪ 
                  Rom. 10.4. 2 Cor. 5.21. 
               inherent in Christ, and imputed to us; the other 1 Cor. 1.30. Ephes. 4.24. 
               imparted by Christ, and 
                  In nobis, non ex nobis, Aug. ep. 143. 
               inherent in us. For

that 
                  Esai. 61.1. spirituall Oyle that was powred upon Christ our Head, &amp; wherwith 
                  Psal. 45.7. 
               God anointed him aboue all his fellowes, when 
                  Iohn 3.34. 
               the Spirit was given him beyond measure, like 
                  Psal. 133.2. the Ointment that was powred upon Aarons head, is shed forth and diffused in some measure, more or lesse, unto every living member of his mysticall Body. 
               
                  Iohn 1.16. 
               Of his fulnesse have we received all, even grace for grace. 
               1 Cor. 6.11. The former is the Righteousnesse of Iustification; the latter is the Righteousnesse of Sanctification.
            
            Some understand here the former:
                  Answer.
                I rather the latter.
            1. Because the word is so taken every where else throughout this whole Sermon:
               
                  Reason 1. as where it is said; 
                  Matth. 5.6. 
               Blessed are they that hunger and thirst after righteousnesse: And, 
                  Matth. 5.10. 
               Blessed are they that suffer for righteousnesse sake: And, 
                  Matth. 5.
                     •
                  0. 
               Vnlesse your Righteousnesse goe beyond the Righteousnesse of the Scribes and the Pharisies, &amp;c. Which verie passage these words seeme to have reference unto.
            2. Because it is that Righteousnesse that doth properly, peculiarly,
                  Reason 2. and immediatly make us actually Kings, and putteth us in the actuall 2 Pet. 1.4. Mens regnum bona possidet, Sen. Thy. 2.2. Qui rectè faciet, nō qui dominatur, erit Rex. Auson. Monofyll.
                
               possession of this Kingdome: the former meriteth it, this entreth us into it: the former purchaseth it for us; this prepareth and fitteth us for it. 
                  Rom. 4.5, 6, 7, 8. Our justification acquiteth us of the guilt of sin: 
               
                  Rom. 8.1, 2. Our sanctification freeth us from the power of sinne, 
               
                  Rom· 6.8, 17, 14. enabling us to quell it, to subdue it, to prevaile against it, that ruled, conquered,

and kept us under before: and so causeth us 
                  Apoc. 20.6. to reigne here as spirituall Kings over it: yea 
                  Ezek. 36.25. Ephes. 5.26. it clenseth us also of the soile and filth of sinne, and so by eating our corruption out of us by degrees, it prepareth and fitteth us for that Kingdome to come, 1 Cor. 15.50. which flesh and bloud cannot enter, nor corruption inherit. But whether of the two be here meant, is not greatly materiall; since that 1 Cor. 6.11. &amp; 1.30. Rom. 8.29, 30. they never are severed the one from the other: And where the one therefore is expressed, there the other ever is implied.
            
               
                  Question 2. Answer. Generall.
               Now this Righteousnesse is here called the Righteousnesse of God;
            Generally, in opposition to 
                  Luke 18.9. that counterfeit Righteousnesse that the Scribes and Pharisies so much bragged of, and gloried so much in; and which our Saviour had discovered, taxed, and rejected before 
                  Chap. 5.20. in this Sermon.
            
            
               
                  Answer. Particular. Reason 1.More particularly, in divers respects:
            1. Because it is given of God. For, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Nullum bonum, quod non à summo bono, Aug. de divers. 3. 
               All good is of God. And, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , P
                        •
                     ndar. Olymp. 9. Nemo abs
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      numine aut est, aut fuit bonus. Bonus vir sine Deo non est, Sen. ep. 41. Nulla sine Deo 
                        〈…〉
                      est, Idem ep. 73. 
               No man ever was or is good without God. 
               
                  Iob. 3.27. 
               No man can have ought, saith S. Iohn the Baptist, unlesse it be given him from aboue. And, 
                  Iam. 1.17. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  · Marc. de L
                        •
                     g. Sp
                        ••
                     . p. 
                  
                     •
                  0. 
               Every good gift, saith S. Iames, is from aboue, and commeth downe from the Father of lights. As 
                  Matth. 19.17. 
               none is originally and essentially good but God: so no man is in any kinde or degree good without God. 
               
                  Nemo bon
                        ••
                     , qui non ex mal
                        •
                      bo
                        ••
                     s, Aug. in Prosper. Sent. 155. 
               There is no man good,
               
saith Augustine, but that of 
                     〈◊〉
                  , is by God made good. And, 
                  Qui n
                        •
                     minē bonum 
                        ••
                     venit, nemin
                        •
                     m salvat, nisi quē praevenit, Bern. de Grat. &amp; lib. Arb.
                
               He, saith Bernard, that 
               
                  Psal. 14.2, 3. 
               findeth no man good, saveth none but such as by preventing grace he maketh good.
            
            2. Because it is approved of by God▪
               
               
                  Reason 2. which that other of theirs is not. It is said of Zacharie and Elizabeth, that they were 
                  Luke 1.6. 
               just in Gods sight. Whereupon saith Ambrose, 
               
                  Multi hominibꝰ justi videntur, pauci Deo. Aliter enim hominibus &amp; aliter Deo. Hominibus sec. externam speciē &amp; fac
                        ••
                     m: Deo sec. internam veritatē &amp; virtutem, Ambr. in Luc.
                
               It is one thing to be just in mans sight, and another thing to be just in Gods sight, An outward shew and semblance, is enough for the one: but inward power and truth is required unto the other. And 
                  Luke 16.15. Mat. 23.27, 28. that that maketh a glorious shew in the eyes of man, is most abominable many times in the sight of God; 
               
                  Aurum hominibus, l
                        •
                     tū Deo. Greg. Mor. l. 34. c. 13. 
               Gold in mans eyes, durt in Gods sight; saith Gregorie.
            
            3. Because it is conformable to the Law of God; It maketh us 1 Ioh. 3.4, 6, 9, 10, 24. &amp; 5.2, 3. Rom. 7.25. 
               conformable to it in part here for the present,
                  Reason 3. and it will make us 
                  Eph
                        •
                     s. 5.27. 
               fully and perfectly conformable to it hereafter. Whereas that other of theirs doth nothing lesse. 
                  Tota vita infidelium peccatum est. Et nihil est bonum absque summo bono, Aug. in Sent. Prosper. 81. 
               The whole Life of such, saith Augustine, is nothing but sinne: and their best actions, no better than 
                  Splendida peccata: Et vitia potius quā virtutes, Idem de Civit. l. 19. c. 25. Sine Christo siquidem omnis virtus in vitio est, Hier. in Gal. 3. Incassum
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      quis laborat in acquisitione virtutum, si aliunde eas sperat, quam a Domino virtutum, Bern. in Cant. 22. Omne etenim probitatis opus, nisi semine verae Exoritu
                        •
                      fidei, peccatum est, inquereatum Vertitu
                        •
                     : &amp; sterilis cumulat sibi gloria poenam, Prosper. de Ingrat.
                
               glittering corruptions.
            
            4. Because it is and shal be rewarded of God. The Crowne expected is called 2 Tim. 4.8. 
               the Crowne of Righteousnesse. And, 
                  Rom. 2.7. 
               To those,
               
                  Reason 4. saith the Apostle, that by well-doing, and continuance therein,

seeke glory, and honour, and immortalitie, will God give eternall life in that day. And, 
                  Matth. 6.6. 
               Thy Father, saith our Saviour, that seeth thee in secret, will reward thee openly. Yea there is 
                  Mat. 25.34, 35, 40. Luke 14.9. no action so meane or slight proceeding from this, even to 
                  Matth. 10.42. Mark
                        •
                     
                   9.41. 
               the gift of a Cup of cold water, that shall passe unregarded, or unrewarded with God. Whereas that other Righteousnesse of theirs hath no reward promised it. 
                  Matth. 6.2. 
               Verily I say unto you, saith our Saviour, not barely, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               they have, but they 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Quod Theophylact
                        •
                     s observavit.
                
               have all, their reward: they have 
                  Matt. 23.5, 6▪ 7. all they desire, and all they deserve, and all that ever they are like to have: they may make their 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Quo mod
                        •
                      Paulus Phil. 4.18. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . De quo argutius Paulo D
                        •
                     naeus noster ad Chrysostomum Savilianum.
                
               acquittance; for such kinde and manner of discharge doth our Saviour there allude unto.
            But why may a man without this Righteousnesse have no part in Gods Kingdome?
               
                  Quest. 3.
            
            
               
                  Answer.
               For dive
                  ••
                
               
                  •
               auses and reasons;
            These among many others:
            
               
                  Reason 1.1. Because the Chiefe Commaunder in this Kingdome, is 
                  Hebr. 7.2. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   (ex Hebr. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                      Gen. 14.18.) 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Frustrâ ergò est autor Etymologici, qui 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , inquit, 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Imo 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                      ad quod Salem alludit, est 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , uti &amp; Apostolus, ibidem, Etymologico ducente alucinatus est &amp; Meurs. animadv. Miscell. lib. 1. cap. 11. 
               a King of Righteousnesse. The Scepter of this Kingdome is▪ 
               
                  Psalm. 45.6. 
               a Rod of Righteousnesse. The Throne of this Kingdome is 
                  Psalm. 9.5. &amp; 97.2. 
               a Seat of Righteousnesse: And the Kingdome it selfe is 
                  Rom. 14.17. 
               a Kingdome of Righteousnesse: And, 1 Cor. 6.8. 
               No unrighteous therefore can inherit this Kingdome; that hath nothing at all but Righteous in it. 
               
                  Esai. 60.21. 
               The people of it, saith the Prophet, are all Righteous.
            
            
               2. Because 
                  Rom. 5.17. Apoc. 20.6. none but those that have part here in the Kingdome of Grace,
               
                  Reason 2. may hereafter partake in the Kingdome of Glorie. But by Righteousnesse we become members of the Kingdom of Grace. 
               
                  Rom. 5.21. 
               That Grace, saith the Apostle, may reigne through Righteousnesse. None but such therefore have any part in the one; none but such shall ever have share in the other.
            3. Because this Righteousnesse is the Royall Roabe. 
               
                  Psal. 132.9. 
               Let thy Priests, saith the Psalmist,
               
                  Reason 3. (and the same Persons here are both 1 Pet. 2.9. Apoc. 1.6. &amp; 5.10. &amp; 20.6. 
               Kings and Priests) be cloathed with Righteousnesse. And, 
                  Isai. 61.10. 
               He hath clad me with the Robe of Righteousnesse. And, 
                  Apoc. 19.8. 
               To the Bride it was given to bee arayed in fine Silke: and 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               the fine Silke is the Righteousnesse of the Saints. As no man then might come into the Wedding-house 
               
                  Mat. 22.11, 12. without the Wedding-garment; so may no man enter into this Kingdome without this Royall Robe. 
               
                  Hebr. 12.14. 
               Without Holinesse, saith the Apostle, shall no man ever see God. And 
                  Psal. 132.9, 16. those alone that are cloathed with Righteousnesse here, shall bee cloathed everlastingly with Salvation hereafter.
            4. Because 
                  Apoc. 21.27. 
               No uncleane thing can come within the walls and compasse of this Kingdom:
               
                  Reason 4. nay, 
                  Esai. 35.8. 
               no uncleane person can set foot into the Way that leadeth to it. But this Righteousnesse, and this alone is that, that can truely and throughly clense, purge, and purifie us, and that not 
                  Psal. 24.3, 4. 1 Tim. 2.8. our hands onely, but our 
                  Matth. 5.8. Act. 15.9. 
               hearts too; as well the 
                  Rom. 7.22. 2 Cor. 4.16. 
               inward man, as the outward; as well 2 Cor. 7.1. Ephes. 4.23. the Spirit as the Flesh. Whereas that other Righteousnesse
               
               
                  Matth. 23.25. Luke 11.39. 
               clenseth the outside only, but leaveth the inside as foule still as ever it was. And therefore no marvell if our Saviour tell us, That 
                  Matth. 6.20. 
               unlesse our Righteousnesse exceed the Righteousnesse of the Scribes and the Pharisies, we shall never get into the Kingdome of God.
            
            
               
                  Vse 3. Vse 1. Information.
               First then, doe we desire to have part in this Kingdome?
            
            Are wee ambitious of a Crowne? and that such a Crowne, as is not 
                  Inest imperio cura maxima maximo, Salust. ad Caes. Seleucus Rex dicere solebat, si multi scirent, quātum 
                        •
                     it negotij tantū modo to
                        •
                      epistolas scrib
                        •
                     re ac legere, nec humi projectum diod
                        •
                     m
                        •
                      tollerent. Alphōsus Arag. Rex, As
                        •
                     norū cond
                        •
                     tionem esse pot
                        •
                     rē quam regum: siquidem illis dum pascuntur dominos parcere, regibus neminem. Rex alius accepto in manus diademate, O Pann
                        ••
                     , inquit, nobi
                        •
                     ē magis quam foelicē! quem siquis penitus cognoscat, quā multis periculis, sollicitudi
                        ••
                     bus ac miserijs fit re
                        •
                     ertus, ne humi quidem jacentem tollere dignetur, Erasm. in Apopht
                        •
                     . l. 6. &amp; 8. Lega
                        •
                     tur Dio Chrysost. de Rege Persarum, Orat. 4. Sen▪ Thy
                        •
                     st. 3.1, 3. &amp; Oedip
                        •
                     d. 1.1. &amp; Aga
                        •••
                     . l. 2. Et Petra
                        •
                     ch. Dialog. 79. &amp; 96. Scit
                        •
                      ita
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      Iocasta in Theb. 4. Ne metue; poenas &amp; quidem solvet graves: Regnabit; haec est poena.— environed with pricking Cares, as if it were 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Mark
                        •
                     
                   15.17. De qu
                        •
                      Meditationem Serenissimi Iacob
                        •
                      Regis nostri confidas sis.
                
               a Crowne of thornes or thistles, but such a one as may c
                     •
                  re and rid our heads of all carking care? as hereafter we shall see. Learne we here the way to it. The Way to this Crowne, to this Kingdome, is by Righteousnesse. Seeke yee, saith our Saviour, the Righteousnesse of God; and that will bring you to the Kingdome of God. For, 
                  Rom. 14.17. 
               The Kingdome of God is Righteousnesse. This Kingdome of God is not like the Kingdomes of this World: that are 
                  Scelere parte; s
                        ••
                     iere r
                        •
                     tenta: De quibus Sen. The
                        •
                     . 4.—regna cū scelere omnibus sunt exi
                        •
                     ijs graviora.— 
               gotten oft by wicked courses, and kept by the like: wherein 
                  Aud
                        •
                      aliquid brevibus G
                        •
                     aris &amp; carcere dignum, Si vis esse aliquid▪—Iuvenal. Sat. 1. men rise by unrighteousnesse, and wherein not 2 Pet. 3.13. 
               Righteousnesse, but —exe
                        •
                     t aulâ Qui volet esse pius— Virtus &amp; summa potesta
                        •
                      Non co
                        •
                     unt.— Lucant▪ 
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     
                     ▪ Phars. l. 8. — jura, pud
                        ••
                     que, Et conjugij sacrata fides 
                        〈◊〉
                      aula
                        •
                     
                     ▪ Fra
                        ••
                      sub
                        •
                     imi r
                        •
                     gnat in 
                        〈◊〉
                     , Sen. Agam. 
                  
                     •
                  .2.—sanctita
                        •
                     , pie
                        •••
                     . fides Privat
                        •
                      
                     
                        •
                     ono sunt, Sen. Thy. 1.2. Vt nemo doceat fraudis &amp; scel
                        •
                     rum vias, Regnum docebit.— Ibid. 
                  
                     •
                  .1.—quid jam non regi
                        •••
                      ans
                        ••
                     ? Aut quod 
                        〈◊〉
                      regni restat scel
                        ••
                     ? Silius bel. Pun. l. 16. 
               unrighteousnesse

oft reigneth. There is no way to rise in this Kingdome, there is no way to attaine to this Kingdome, but by Righteousnesse. 
               
                  Prov. 21.21. 
               He that followeth Righteousnesse and mercie, shall finde Righteousnesse, and Life, and Glory; saith Sal
                     •
                  mon. For it is the 
                  
                     •
                  ust, saith the Psalmist, that 
                  Psal. 11.5▪7. 
               God loveth and regardeth, that 
                  Psal. 5.12. 
               he gardeth &amp; protecteth, that 
                  Psal. 17.15. shall behold his face, that shall 
                  Psal. 140.13. 
               dwell ever in his house; and that 
                  Matth. 13.43. shall shine as the Sunne, saith ou
                  •
                Saviour, in the Kingdome of God their Father 
               
                  Dan. 12.3. 
               for ever and ever.
            
            Secondly,
                  Vse 2. Eviction.
                observe we hence how crosse and averse the corrupt heart of man is naturally to all goodnesse and godlinesse; that, though a Crowne, a Kingdome, an incorruptible Crowne, an everlasting Kingdome bee propounded to this Righteousnesse, and annexed unto it, yet will rather lose this Crowne, rather leave and forgoe this Kingdome, than condescend to accept of it upon such a condition; 
                  At 
                        •
                     aris ut vivat regnet
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      ben
                        •
                     ꝰ, Cog
                        •
                      posse 
                        •
                     egat▪ Horat. epist. 
                  
                     •
                  . 
               will not be constrai
                     •
                  ed to live happily, and to reigne everlastingly, unlesse he may doe so upon some other termes▪ will choose rather not to reigne, than to be righteous. If this Crowne indeed might be compassed by fraud and deceit, or by oppression and extortion; not a few would be sure to have a share in it, that are now never like to have any interest therein. Or if it might be held with loosenesse and lewdnesse of life, we should not need much Rhetoricke to perswade many to accept of it. It is 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Plut. ad 
                        〈◊〉
                     
                     ▪ indoct. 
                        〈…〉
                      potentiae suae magnitudinem metiuntur, Vell. hist. l. 2. Idque esse regni maximū pignus putant. Si quicquid alijs 
                        〈…〉
                     , Sen. 
                        •
                     gam. 2.2. 
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      qu
                        •••
                     ibet 
                        〈◊〉
                     , ill esse Regem esse, 
                        〈…〉
                      Hoc principat
                        •
                     s 
                        〈◊〉
                      putant, 
                        〈◊〉
                     . hist. 1. one maine end, for which many men desire

authoritie and greatnesse, that they may thereby gaine libertie to live and doe as they list; 
                  Sceptorū vis tota perit, si pēdere justa Incipit.—Lucā. l. 8. Vbicūque tantum honesta dominanti licent, Precario regnatur.— Atreus, Sen. Thyest. 1.2. and without which they esteeme power and authoritie nought worth. When 
                  Matth. 3.1, 2. 
               Iohn the Baptist preached the Gospell of this Kingdome, 
               
                  Marke 6.20. 
               Herode would willingly have had it, if hee might have held his Herodias, his Harlot with it. When 
                  Matth. 4.23. Marke 1.14. our Saviour Christ published it, 
                  Iohn 12.42, 43, &amp; 3 1. the Pharisies would faine have had it, if with their 
                  Matth. 23.6, 7. John 5.44. pride, 
                  Luke 16.14, covetousnesse, and 
                  Luke 12.1. hypocrisie, it might have beene had and held; or if such 
                  Matth. 5.20. Luke 18.9. a specious shew of Righteousnesse would have served the turne for it, as they dazled the eyes of the simpler sort with. But when this 
                  Matth. 5.20. &amp; 7.13. 
               Righteousnesse of God, this strictnesse of life, commeth to be propounded together with it, and to bee exacted of all those that will have any share in it; now 
                  Marke 6.17, 18. 
               Herode flieth off, and will none of it, 
                  Luke 7.30. the Pharisies keepe aloofe off, and reject it; &amp; every naturall mans perverse heart thinketh it held at too high a rate, if 
                  Mica 6.6, 7, 8. without change of his corrupt course of life it cannot be compassed.
            
               
                  Vse 3. Exclusion.
               Thirdly, this serveth to exclude many from it, that would yet seeme to have, yea and perswade themselves, that they haue a good share in it. They have no share in the former, because they have no part in the latter: They have no part in the Kingdome propounded by Christ, because no part in the Righteousnesse annexed unto it; because they remaine still as they were naturally, 1 Cor. 15.32, 33, 34. 2 Cor. 12.21. Tit. 1.10, 12, 15, 
                     •
                  6. unrenewed, unsanctified, unholy,

unrighteous, wholly impure and profane both in heart and in life; or if they have some shew of holinesse, it is 2 Tim. 3.2, 3, 4, 5. in outward semblance only, there is no inward substance or power of it. Such they are; and 
                  Psal. 58.3, 4, 5. &amp; 36.1, 2, 3. Ier. 9.2, 3, 5, 6. other they refuse to be. They like well of this Kingdome; but they cannot away with the Righteousnesse: 
               
                  Num. 23.10. They are desirous to reigne; but unwilling to bee righteous. 
               
                  Jmpius &amp; foelix sic simul esse cupit, Vt nolit pius esse, velit tamē esse beatus. De Macrin
                        •
                      nescio quis apud Iul. Capitolin.
                
               Happy they would be; but holy they wil not be. And yet they hope, they say, to doe as well as the best. A thing that 
                  Quod natura negat, nec ratio patitur, Ibid.
                neither Religion, nor natural Reason admitteth. For God hath lincked these two together with an indissoluble bond, 
                  Apoc. 20.6. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Bonus beatus omnis, et malus miser, Socrat. Plato. Greg. &amp; Cic. Tucs. l. 5. 
               Happinesse and Holinesse, Reigning and Righteousnesse; the one as the Crowne, the other as the Robe, which cannot be had or worne therefore the one without the other. And 
                  Matth. 19.6. 
               what God hath conjoyned, man, do he what he can, shall never be able to dis-joyne, and to sever. Whosoever refuseth 
                  Rom. 8.12, 13. Gal. 6.7, 8, 9. Vivite itaque benè, ne moriamini malè, August. de verb. Dom. 24. Id age ut bonam vitam habeas, &amp; quacunque occasione à vita exieris, ad requiem, ad beatitudine maeternam exibis: merces enim vitae bonae, 
                        •
                     terna est. Idem discipl. Christ. c. 2. to live as a Saint with Christ here on earth, shall never reigne as a Saint with him hereafter in heaven.
            
            Yea but, will some say,
                  Objection.
                though 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Plut. de Praefect. Ita, 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , Epicur. Stob. c. 16. Quod 
                        •
                     odiè non est, eras erit: sic vit
                        •
                      truditur, Petron. Satyr. Cras hoc fiet, idem cras fiet. Quid? quasi magnum Nempe diē d
                        •
                     nas. Sed cum lux altera venit: Iam cras 
                        •
                     esternum consumpsimus: ecce aliud cras Egerit hos annos, &amp; semper paulum erit ultra, Pers. Sat. 
                  
                     •
                  , Ita
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      pulchrè Chrysost. ad Pop. Ant. 19. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                we be not so for the present, yet intend we, and purpose one day to be such; we hope to be so ere wee

die, when wee lye a dying at least. As there is no wretched miser almost, no miserable worldling, no griping cormorant, no filthy leacher, no debauched hell-hound, unlesse he be 
                  Ierem. 2.25. 
               desperately bent to destroy his soule, and be wholly given up unto 
                  Rom. 1.28. 
               a reprobate sense, &amp; to 
                  Ephes. 4.19. 
               a senselesse estate, but will say, that he meaneth yet one day to doe otherwise; 
                  Ier. 8.5, 6. 
               he goeth far, they say, that never turneth; and he hopeth he shall have time enough so to do ere he die. But they must follow the world, or their own lusts first a while, and then they will take time at last to looke after these things.
            
               
                  Subjection. Member 3. Order.
               To meet with this slight that Satan is wont to suggest, therby to cheat men of their soules, our Saviour here admonisheth us to seeke Gods Kingdome and his Righteousnesse, not in the last, but 
                  Sive aliquid habes; ò jam▪ philosophare. Sive nihil, hoc prius q
                        •
                     aere quā quidquā, Sen. ep. 17 in the first place.
            
               Spirituall things as they must be sought, so they must be sought in the first place:
            
            
               
                  Observ. 4.
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Nigrinus apud Lucianū.
                They must bee sought instantly, without longer delay; 
                  Ab hoc incipiendum est. Nihil prius quam hoc parandū est. Quid tu differs &amp; post 
                        •
                     aetera paras? Sen. epist. 17. they must be sought first, 
               
                  Prou. 4.5, 7. 
               before and above all other things. Seeke ye first Gods Kingdome, and his Righteousnesse, saith our Saviour. And, 
                  Prov. 8.17. 
               He that seeketh me early, saith Gods Wisdome by Salomon, shall finde me.
            
            
               
                  Reasons 8.And great reason there is, why it should so be.
            
               
                  Reason 1.For first, 
                  Merito poscit studia majora pars melior, Euc
                        ••
                     r. ad Va
                        ••
                     r. Prior pars 
                        〈◊〉
                     . Vt qu
                        •
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      prior est, non 
                        •
                     it con
                        •
                     ideratione post
                        •
                     ri
                        •
                     r, Ibidem.
                
               The better part justly claimeth the

principall care, and to be provided for in the first place. Other things concerne our bodies; these our soule and its wel-fare. And as our Saviour saith, 
                  Matth. 6.
                     •
                  5. Luke 12.
                     ••
                  . 
               The Bodie is better than raiment: so 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Plut. cont. Epic. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , Idem de Tranq. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , Aristot. Polit. l. 7. c. 1. Nostri melior pars animꝰ est, Sen. quaest. Nat. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Greg. Naz. ad Cledon. 1. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Idem de Nupt. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , Post Euripid. Idē in I
                        ••
                     . 1. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Idem Apolog.
                
               the Soule is better than the Bodie. Besides that, The Soule may doe well without the Body; but the Bodie cannot doe well without the Soule. Our 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Chrys. tom. 8. ser. 17. Pr
                        •
                     
                     
                     
                        ••
                      animi bona, Iu
                     
                        •
                     en. Sat. 8. 
               first and principall care therefore should be for our soule, and those things that concerne it; and for these therefore in the first place, because they principally concerne it.
            Secondly, 
                  Aeterna momentaneis praef
                        •
                     ren
                        •••
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     .
                
               Things eternall should be preferred before things temporall. 
               2 Cor. 4.1
                     •
                  . 
               While we looke,
               
                  Reason 2. saith the Apostle, not on the things that are seene, but on the things that are not seene. For the things that are seene, are temporall; but the things that are not seene, are eternall. And, 
                  Iohn 6.27. 
               Labour, saith our Saviour, not for the meat that perisheth, but for 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Plut.
                
               the meat that endureth unto life eternall. But 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Euripid. M
                        ••
                     talium m
                        •
                     rtalis est foelicitas. Mortal
                        •
                      est omn
                        •
                      mortali
                        •
                     m▪ bonum. Metrodorus d
                        •
                      
                     
                        •
                     is loquit
                        •
                     r bo
                        ••
                      ad qu
                        •
                      concurritur, Sen. epist. 98. 
               all other things are temporall and transitorie; 
                  Certum est sempiter
                        ••
                     mque virtu
                        •
                      bon
                        ••
                     . Hoc unum contingit immortale mortalibus, Sen. epist. 
                  
                     ••
                  . 
               these only that our Saviour enciteth hereunto, are eternall. And what comparison then betweene the one and the other?
            Thirdly, 
                  Supe
                        ••
                     ac
                        ••
                      n
                        •
                     cessarijs pos
                        •
                     ponend
                        •
                      s
                        •
                     nt, Sen. epist. 49. &amp; 109. 
               Things necessarie ought to be preferred to the first place.
               
                  Reason 3. But these are the only necessary things. 
                  Vnicum nec
                        •
                     ssarium, Luke 10.42. 
               There is but one thing necessary; saith our Saviour to Martha. Which 
                  Psal. 27.4. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Chrysost. tom. 8. S
                        •
                     r. 17. 
               one thing
               
therefore only David desired; and Paul made his 
                  Phil. 3.12, 13. 
               maine aime, counting all but as drosse and trash unto it: to wit, this Kingdome, and the Righteousnesse of it. The old Proverb here holdeth, 
                  Aut Caesar, aut nullus, 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , Gregor. Naz. in Pentecost. Omnis homo aut est cum Christo regnaturus, aut cū diabolo cruciandus, Aug. de Temp. 85. 
               Either a King, or a Caitiffe. The greatest King in the world, if he misse of this Kingdome, is as miserable a wretch as may be.
            Fourthly, 
                  Indignum est dare Deo, quod dedignatur homo, Hier. in Malac. 1. Grat. Decret. Dist. 49., c. 3. 
               It is a most unworthy thing to deale so with God,
               
                  Reason 4. 
               as no man would endure to bee dealt with. We will serve God, forsooth: but when? when we are now good for nought. When we have served our selves of the world, and satisfied our owne lusts, are glutted with the one, and have surfetted of the other, and are unfit and unable any longer to follow either; —Postquam lapidosa cheragra Fregere articulos, veteris ramalia fagi, Pers. Sat. 5. Cum omnibus mēbris extorti &amp; fracti, ne in lectulo quidem queant nisi ab alijs moveri; uti de Domitio Tullo, Plin. epist. 18. lib. 8. when we are scarce able to turne our withered bodies, and wearied bones in our bed, then will wee offer and tender our service to God. 
                  Malac. 1.8. Non pudet te reliquias vitae tibi reservare, &amp; id solum tempus bonae menti destinare, quod in nullam rem conferri possit? Sen. de Brev. Vit. c. 4. 
               Offer it to thy Prince, saith the Prophet; and see if he will accept of it. Yea make proffer of thy selfe then, say I, to any meane man. And it is an unworthy usage of God, for a man to offer that unto God, that any man would thinke scorne of.
            
            Fiftly, 
                  Non omnis 
                        ••
                     as ad perdiscendum sat est. Plaut. Truc. 1.1. Nullum non tā magnis re
                        •
                     ꝰ tēpus a
                        •
                     gustū est, Sen. q. Nat. l. 3. Non cū vacaveris, philosophandum est: Omnia alia negligenda, ut huic assideamus, cui nullum tēpu
                        •
                      satis magnum est, etiamsi à pueritia us
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      ad longiss
                        ••
                     os humani aevi terminos vita protēditur, Idē ep. 72. 
               All mans life is little enough, were it never so long, as for the learning, so for the attaining of these things.
                  Reason 5. And 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ; Epicu
                        •
                     . Stob. c. 16. Nihil in diem, nihil in horam permittitur, Sen. ad Marc. c. 10. Nihil ne in totum quidem diem certum est, Idem ad Poly
                        •
                     . c. 29▪
                we have no suretie of any time, no not of an houre. 
                  Psal. 31.15. 
               My times,
               
saith David, are in thine hands. Our times are in Gods hands, who 
                  Qui promisit p
                        •
                     
                     nitenti veniam, nō promisit poenitendi horam. Qui poenitenti misericordiam promisit, peccanti crastinum non promisit. Aug de verb. Dom. 59. &amp; homil. 11. &amp; 13. &amp; in Sent. Prosp. 72. as he hath promised pardon, saith Augustine, upon our repentance, so hee hath not promised us, so much as an houre for repentance. And when 
                  Apoc. 2.21, 22. hee hath given men space, but they have no grace to turne, it is a just thing with him 
                  Apoc. 10.6, 7. to deny them further time for turning. 
               
                  Maximum benè vivendi impedimē
                     tum est expectatio, quae pendet ex cras
                        •
                     ino. Perdis hodiernum: quod in man
                        ••
                      alterius positum est disponis; quod in tua dimittis, Sen. de brevit. vit. c. 9. It is a fond thing therefore to let goe and lose the time that we have, in hope of, and building upon that that wee may never have; to let that goe that is in our owne hand, relying upon that that is in anothers hand.
                  Reason 6.
            
            Sixtly, 
                  Durus valdè, imò potius, quod molestius est, valdè mollis capitur, consuetudine mala &amp; diutina fractus, qui vitij
                        •
                      simul &amp; emarc
                        ••
                     t &amp; induruit, Sen. ep. 112. 
               The longer we defer it, the more unfit shall we finde our selves for it. 
               
                  Qui non est hodiè cras minus aptus erit, Ovid. Remed. l. 1. 
               He that is not fit for it to day, will be more unfit for it to morrow. 
               
                  Consuetudo peccandi tollit sensum peccati, Bern. de Cons. c. 4. 
               Continuance in sinning hardeneth in sinne, and breedeth a brawninesse in the Soule: while Nature, and Custome, 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Arist. Eth. Mag. l. 2. 
                     •
                  . 6. Cōsuetudo altera natura, Cic. Fin. l. 5. Ber. de Divers. 14. 
               a second Nature, concurring together, 
                  Ier. 13.23. Natura &amp; consuetudo robustissimam faciunt &amp; invictissimam cupiditatem, Aug. ad Simpl. l. 1. q. 1. Ex voluntate perversa facta est libido; &amp; dum servitur libidinū facta est consuetudo: &amp; dum consuetudini non resistitur, facta est necessitas. Idē Conf. l. 8. c. 5. Inveterata in nobis malorū omnium labe, aliter jā nō vitiosi esse nō possumꝰ, nisi ut omnino nō simꝰ, Salv. de Prov. l. 6. L
                        •
                     ngo quod usu in pejus us
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      induruit, multo facilius fregeris quā flexeris, Buch. Bapt.
                produce an irrecoverablenesse in evill.
            Seventhly, this Righteousnesse should bee sought in the first place,
                  Reason 7. because 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Arist. Eth. Nicō. l. 5. c. 1. &amp; Mag. l. 1. c. 34. et Eudem. l. 4. c. 1. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Plato de Rep. l. 4. Iustitia instar sanitatis est, sine qu
                        •
                      nihil quicquā juvat. Sine justitia nihil valet, Cic. Offic. l. 2. nihil potest esse laud
                        •
                     bile, Ib. l. 1. Domina siquidē est omniū et regina virtutū, Ibid. l. 3. 
               Nothing
               
whatsoever, though never so good, either is good, or can doe good without it. Yea the better and the more excellent any thing is, the worse it is, if it be not joyned with it.
            What is better than government? the verie 
                  Sin
                        •
                      imperio nec domus ulla, nec civitas, nec g
                        •
                     ns, nec hominū universum genus stare, nec rerum natura omnis, nec ips
                        •
                      mundu
                        •
                      potest, Cic. de leg. l. 3. Istud est vinculum, per quod Respub. co
                     
                        ••
                     ret: ille spiritus vitalis, quē tot millia trahunt: nihil ipsa per se futura nisi onus &amp; praeda, s
                        •
                      mens illa imperij 
                        •
                     ubtra
                        •
                     atur, Senec. de Clem. l. 1. c. 4. 
               Life of a State. Yet if the Scepter be not swaied aright; if it rule not according to justice and right; Regiment without righteousnesse degenerateth, and turneth into Tyrannie; it is but 
                  Iudex injustus latro cum privilegio est. Sicut medicus imperit
                        •
                     , homicida. Colum. lib. 1. Iudex locusta civitatis est malus, Scalig. A
                        •
                     e.
                
               Robberie with authoritie. For the maine 
                  Fruēdae justitiae causa reges constituti sunt, Cic. Offic. l. 2. Judex iniq
                        ••
                     s &amp; 
                        ••
                     trone p
                        •
                     jar est.
                
               end of government is for the execution and enjoyment of justice: and without it therefore government is no better than plaine 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Plut. ad praefect. ind
                        •
                     ct. 
                        •
                     emo
                        ••
                      justitia quid sunt Regna nisi magna latrocinia, Aug. de Civit. l. 4. c. 4. 
               robberie; yea it is in some respect 
                  Injusta reg
                        •
                     a justa latrocinia sunt.
                worse than it.
            What is 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Euripid.
                better than Law? the 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Arist. R
                        •
                     et. l. 1. c. 3. Pr
                        •
                     sunt enim Magistrati
                        •
                     us leges, ut populo Magistratus, Cic. de Leg. l. 3. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Demosth. apud S
                        ••
                     b.
                
               life of Government. But 
                  Leges iniqu
                        •
                      nec l
                        •
                     ges dice
                        •
                     d
                        •
                      su
                        ••
                     , Aug. de Civit. l. 19. c. 21. 
               injust Lawes are not worthy the Name of Lawes. 
               
                  Esai. 10.1. 
               Woe to those, saith the Prophet, that make unjust Lawes. Woe to those that make them; yea and w
                     •
                  
                to those also for whom they are made. For 
                  Legibus fundata civitas legi
                        •
                     us evertitur, Pli
                        •
                     . 
                        ••
                     neg.
                they are but a meanes to undoe those, for whose good they are pretended.
            
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Gregor. Naz. in Iul. 1. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Idem ad Cledon. 2. Pax opti
                        •
                     a rerum Qua
                        •
                      homini 
                        ••
                     visse datum. Pax una triumphi
                        •
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      p
                        •
                     ti
                        •
                     r.—S
                        •••
                     us bel. Pun. lib. 2. What is better than Peace, Vnitie, Agreement,
               
and Concord? 
               
                  Iudici
                        •
                     , l
                        •
                     gosque esse nō possunt pace sub
                        •
                     at
                        •
                     , Cic. Phil. 8. Without which those former also are of no use, of no force. The very Name of Peace is sweete;
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Greg. Nazi
                        ••
                     
                     ▪ de Pac
                        •
                     
                   3. Dulc
                        •
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      est pacis: res verô ipsa tū jucunda. tum salutaris, Cic. Philip. 2. &amp; 13. but the thing it selfe much sweeter. 
               
                  Psal. 133.1. 
               Behold, saith the Psalmist, 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Greg. Naz. de Eu
                        •
                     a
                        •
                     .
                
               how goodly and how pleasant a thing it is for brethren to dwell together in unitie▪
                
               
                  Psal. 
                  
                     •
                  33.2. It is for the pleasantnesse of it, like the pretious 
               
                  Levit. 8.12. 
               Ointment that was powred upon Aarons Head, that wet his Beard, and ran downe to the very 
                     •
                  kirts of his Garments. It is 
                  Pax 
                        〈◊〉
                      r
                        ••
                     
                     tis, tranquillitas a
                     
                        ••
                     ni, s
                        ••
                     plicitas cordis, vinculum amoris, consortium charitatis. Haec est quae sim
                        •••
                     ates tollit, bella compescit, ira
                        •
                      comprimit, discordes s
                        •
                     d
                        •
                     t, inimicos concordat, cunctis est placi
                        •
                     a, Aug. de ve
                        •
                     b. Dom. 57. delightfull not to those themselves alone, that are at unitie among themselves, but it sendeth forth a pleasing savour to their neighbors round about them: as on the other side, contentious persons are not troublesome to either other onely, but to all that dwell neare unto them. 
                  Quod in cantu 
                        〈◊〉
                     , i
                        •
                     civitate 
                        •
                     oncordia, arctiss
                        ••••
                      at
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      optimum 
                        〈…〉
                      Cic. de Repub. l. 2. Aug. de Civit. l. 2. c. 21. 
               Concord in societies, is as Harmonie in consorts, which being duly observed, maketh the Musicke delightfull; being not observed, by jarring maketh all harsh and unt
                  ••
               able, as well to the hearers, as to the fingers themselves. Again, for the profitablenesse and behovefulnesse of it, 
                  Psal. 133.3. 
               It is like the dew of Her
                     ••
                  n, and that that commeth downe upon the Hill of Sion. It is as a sweet 
                  Prov. 19.12. 
               dew, that maketh all things grow and thrive; as the contrarie spoileth and layeth all things waste, like the 
                  Ha
                        ••
                     . 1.9. 
               blast of some malignant aspect. 
                  Conc
                        ••
                     dia 
                        〈…〉
                      crescunt: discordia maximae dila
                        •
                     u
                        •
                     tur. Micypsae apud 
                        〈…〉
                     . 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , Eccles▪
                   4.1
                     •
                  . Gregor. Naz. ad Aegypt-adv
                        •
                     n.
                
               Concord and agreement addeth strength even to meane things; discord and disagreement bringeth the strongest to wracke. And no marvell: For

               
                  Nihil beatum nō favente numine. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , Eschyl. Theb.
                without the Blessing of God what can prosper; yea or subsist? But 
                  Psal. 133.3. 
               There, saith the Psalmist, hath God promised his Blessing, (to wit, 
                  Vers. 1. where Brethren agree together in one) and life for evermore. But 
                  Mat. 18.19, 20. Rom. 16.20. 
               the God of Peace will give 
               
                  Pacis Deus nisi pacē colentibus benedictionem nō dabit, Cyprian. Quid simultates amas, quod antori pacis placere non potest? Non potest concordiam habere cū Christo, qui discors esse voluerit cum Christiano, August. de verb. Dom. 57. 
               no blessing there, where Peace and Vnitie is not. So that there is nothing more delightfull, more behoovefull than Peace. In regard whereof, it is that the Apostle Paul so oft, and so instantly enciteth unto it. 
                  Ephes. 4▪1.—6. 
               I therefore Paul, the Lords Prisoner, beseech you, that you would walke worthy of the Calling whereunto you are called; with all humblenesse of minde, and meeknesse, with long suffering, supporting one another through Love; Endevouring to retaine the unitie of the Spirit in the 
               
                  Col. 3.14. 
               bond of Peace. There is 
               
                  Rom. 12.5. 1 Cor. 12.12, 27. 
               one Bodie, and 
               1 Cor. 12.13. 
               one Spirit, one Faith, one Hope, one Baptisme, 
               1 Cor. 8.6. 
               one Lord, one God and Father of all, aboue all, through all, and in you all. And againe, to passe by many other passages; 
                  Philip. 2.1, 2. 
               If therefore there be any consolation, if any comfort of Love, if any communion of Spirit, if any bowels and compassions; Fulfill yee my joy, that yee be 
               
                  Act. 4.32. Rom. 15.5, 6. 1 Cor. 1.10. Phil. 3.16. &amp; 4.2. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Aristoteles, Laert. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , Iocus in Catonem min. ipsius
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      hospitē, Plut. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , Gregor. Naz. in Basil.
                
               like minded, like affected, of one accord, and of one judgement. And so 
                  Phil. 2.3, 4. proceedeth he to dehort them from selfe-will, selfe-love, selfe-respect, and selfe-conceit, the very bane and pests of agreement and concord. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Chrysost. in 1 Cor. hom. 19. Hanc erg
                        •
                      qui accepit teneat; qui perdidit repetat; qui ami
                        •
                     it, exquirat, Aug. de verb. Dom. 57. This therefore should you strive and labour by all means to maintain among your selves, being (as 
                  Gen. 13.8. 
               Abraham
               
told Lot) brethren; and being 
                  Coloss. 3.15. 
               called and joyned together (as the Apostle speaketh) into one Bodie. But 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Greg. Naz. de Pace 1. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Chrysost. in Ioan. hom. 57 withall, you must have a care that this your Peace bee the Peace of God, that it be in God, and for God; that the maine aime of your agreement be the advancement of Gods Kingdome, and the maintenance of Right. For 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Greg. Naz. ibidem.
                if Peace be not joyned with Pietie, better no Peace than such Peace; 
                  Sine justitia pax nulla est, Cic. de Repub. l. 2. Aug. de Civit. l. 2. c. 21. if agreement be not joyned with justice and equitie, better no agreement at all than such. As it is 
                  Conciliabulum, sive Conventiculū, non Concilium.
                
               no Councell, but a Conventicle, wherein Truth is not aimed at: so it is 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Act. 23.13. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Chrys. in Matth. hom. 35. 
               no Societie, but a Conspiracie, wherein right is not regarded. When men are, as Simeon and Levi, 
               
                  Fratres in malo, Gen. 49.5. Pax mala est inter malos, ut quibus est una malitia, &amp; unus ad malefaciendum consensus, Autor oper. imperfect. in Matth. hom. 26. 
               Brethren in evill; when they combine themselves together to injure and wrong others; 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Chrysost. in Mat. 35. Pax cum bello sub Sylla de crudelitate certavit &amp; vicit. Aug. de Civit. l. 3. c. 28. such agreement and concord is worse than any discord or disagreement whatsoever. And 
                  Vt pernitiosum est, si unitas desit bonis: ita perniciosius est, si nō desit malis▪ Eripiuntur enim justa, dū dividuntur injusti. At verò contra bonos vehemēter praevalent, quādo in malo se cōcorditer tenent, Greg. Mor. l. 34. c. 3. Qui iniquos paci sociat, iniquitati vires administrat: quia bonos deterius deprimunt, cum unanimiter persequuntur, Idem Pastor. part. 3. c. 1. §. 24. the more strongly men in such case are united together, the worse they are, the more evill they may doe; yea the worse it is for themselves too. For the more they are united and conjoined either with other, the more are they dis-united and dis-joined from God.
            But to leave this Digression, though not altogether impertinent, which I was that morning admonished, that somewhat of this Argument was of course by the Doners desire required and expected. the present Occasion
               
in part required of me; and to returne to the maine Point that wee are principally to pursue.
            Therefore, lastly, are Gods Kingdome and his Righteousnesse first to be sought,
               
                  Reason 8. because
            
               The seeking thereof will be the most Compendious Course for the
Compassing of our owne Desires.
            
            For why do men neglect to looke after Gods Kingdome? 
               
                  Moratur me res familiaris. Sic illam disponere volo, ut sufficere mihi hoc agenti possit, ne aut paupertas mihi oneri sit, aut ego alicui. Quantū sat est, nō
                     dum habeo. Si ad illam summam pervener
                        •
                     , tunc me totum philosophiae dabo, Sen. epist. 17. Forsooth, because they must build their houses, they must feather their nestes first: they must get something that may bee a stay to them hereafter, that they may bee able to defend the world withall. To remove therefore this rubbe,
                  Member 4. Benefit.
                and to rid and ease men of this care, our Saviour here telleth them, that 
                  Quid in longum ipse te differs? expectabis ne foenoris quaestū, aut ex merce compēdium, aut tabulas beati senis, cum 
                        •
                     ieri possis statim dives? Repraesentat opes sapi
                        •
                     tia: quas cuicunque supervacuas fecit, dedit, Ibidem.
                upon the due seeking of Gods Kingdome and his Righteousnesse, or the Righteousnesse thereof, (for 
                  E
                        •
                     dem quod sensum attinet, rede
                        •
                     nt; etiamsi ad Deum, non ad Regnum referri Syntaxis Grammatica postulat. Atque hoc est quod Calvinus in hunc locum voluit. Quem iniquè igitur Maldonatus ta
                        •
                     at tanquam Graecarum literarum imperitum.
                all commeth to one effect) all these things that men so much desire and looke after, and take so much thought and care for, shall bee by God himselfe provided for them, supplied unto them, and cast in thereupon as an advantage thereunto.
            So that
            
               
                  Vi
                        •
                     tus omnia in se habet: Omnia adsunt bona, Quem penes est Virtus, Plaut. Amph. 2.5. Est tanti laborare, omnia bona semel occupature, Senec. epist. 76. 
               This one thing will bring all with it, it will helpe us to all things,
                  Observ. 5, that our heart can desire. 
                  Psal. 37.3, 4. 
               Trust in the Lord, saith the Psalmist, and doe

good, and thou shalt assuredly be 
                     •
                  ed. Delight thy selfe in the Lord, and he will give thee thine 
                     •
                  wne hearts desire. 
               
                  Psal. 84.11. 
               Hee will be 
               
                  Deus Sol et Sc
                        •
                     
                     tum, debit grati
                        ••
                      &amp; gloriam.
                
               thy Sunne and thy Shield; he will give thee grace and glory: and hee will deny thee no good thing, so long as thou leadest a godly life. As 1 King. 3.9—13. 2 Chron. 1.11, 12. when Salomon asked Wisedome, it pleased God so well, that he gave him Wealth and Honour together with it; so upon the seeking hereof, we shall not onely finde it, but we shall have all other good things cast in upon us together with it.
            Nor indeed can it be otherwise.
                  Reasons 4. Reason 1.
            
            For first, we shall have thereupon our right to all things restored us in Christ. 1 Cor. 3.22, 23. 
               All things, saith the Apostle, whether present, or future, this world or the next, all things, I say, are yours; and you Christs; and Christ Gods. As 
                  Hebr. 1.2. 
               Christ, so all Christians are 
                  Gal. 3.26. Rom. 8.17. 
               in Christ 
               
                  Apoc. 21.7. 
               Heires of all things. And for 
                  Aud
                        •
                     cter Deum roges, nihil illum de alieno rogaturus, Sen ep
                        •
                     st. 10. 
               God therefore to deny them ought, were to deny them of their owne.
            Secondly, they that thus doe,
                  Reason 2. are 
                  Iohn 1.12. Gal. 3.26. 2 Cor. 6.17, 18. 
               Gods Children in Christ; and 
                  Iohn 14.13. &amp; 16.23. 1 Iohn 5.14, 15. may have for the asking what they will at Gods hands. For, 
                  Matth. 7.11. 
               If you that are evill, saith our Saviour, use to give good things to your Children; how much more will your heavenly Father give you good things, if you aske him? 
               
                  Psal. 147.9. Mat. 6.26. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ; &amp;c. Epictet. Ari
                        ••
                     . Dissert. l. 3. c. 26. 
               He seedeth the fowles of the aire, and the beasts of the field: and hee that is carefull to provide for his hounds and his haukes, will hee suffer his Children to beg and starve, that must one day be his heires?
            
            
               
               
                  Reason 3.Thirdly, he hath prepared a Crowne, a Kingdome for them. 
                  Luke 12.32. 
               Feare not, little flocke, saith our Saviour; it is your Fathers will to bestow a Kingdome upon you. And, 
                  Qui dabit regnū, non dabit viaticū? Aug. de verb. Dom. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , Chrysostom. in Matth. 22. 
               will he deny them a Crum, that will give them a Crowne? Will hee deny them a bit of bread, or a cup of drinke, (1 Chron. 29.11, 12. all the wealth in the world is no more with him; he can as easily give the one as the other) that purposeth one day to make them Kings.
            
            
               
                  Reason 4.Yea lastly, he hath bestowed his owne, his only Sonne on them. 
                  Iohn 3.16. 
               He so loved them, that he gave his only begotten Sonne for them. And, 
                  Rom. 8.32. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Chrysost. in Rom. hom. 15. 
               He that spared not his owne Sonne, but gave him up to death for them, how can he but give them all things together with him? 
               
                  Qui misit unigenitum, immisit sp
                        •
                     
                     ritū, promisit vultum, quid tandem tibi negaturus est? Bern. de Temp. Nihil ei negaturꝰ creditur, quem ad esum vituli hortatur, Hieron. de Fil. Prodig.
                He that 1 Iohn 4.9, 10. 
               sent his Sonne to die for them, hath 
                  Galat. 4.6. 
               put his Spirit in them, and hath 
                  Matth. 5.8. 
               promised them the fruition of his blessed presence for ever; how can hee refuse to provide for them, and confer upon them whatsoever good thing they shall stand in need of, while they live here?
            
               
                  Vses 4. Vse 1. Admonition.
               Now this first serveth to admonish all Christian men, yea all men in generall, both what they should first and most, and what they should last and least care for. 
                  Optimum est curam principalem anima impendere. Eucher. ad Valer. Vt primas apud nos curas, quae prima habentur, obti
                     
                        ••
                     ant: summasque sibi sol
                        •
                     citudinis partes, qu
                        •
                      summa est, salus vendicet. Omnia vincat eo studio, quo praecedit omnia, Ibidem.
                Their first and principall care should be for the principall things, that is, for spirituall things, for Gods Kingdome and his Righteousnesse, for sanctification and true holinesse.

               
                  Quis extruendi, nisi cum fundamenta jeceris, locus est? Superaedificare caeteras utilitates destinanti salus fundamentum est. Caeterū quomodo quispiam sequentia addat, si nec prima possederit? Idē ibid.
                These are the things that most neerely concerne them; and without which they can have no benefit of ought else. And these are the things that God would have them most to looke after: As for other things, when we have so done, hee would have us leave the care of them wholly to him. 
                  Psal. 55.22. 
               Roll thy burden upon the Lord, saith the Psalmist, and he will maintaine thee. 
               1 Pet. 4.4. 
               Cast all your care upon him, saith S. Peter; for hee taketh care for you. And, 
                  Philip. 4.6. 
               Take you no thought for ought, saith S. Paul: but let al your wāts be made knowne unto God by prayer. He 
                  Matth. 6.32. 
               knoweth what is fit for you, and he will supplie you. What a deale of trouble, and distraction might wee free our selves of? How great quietnesse and sweet tranquillitie of minde might we procure to our selves, if we could doe thus?
            But alas how contrarily (and let that be the next Vse) are most men affected to that that God would here have?
                  Vse 2. Reprehēsion.
               
            
            God would have men take care for spirituall things,
                  Error 1. and leave the care of temporall things wholly to him. Whereas most men take a cleane contrarie course. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Chrysost. in Matth. 22. All the care they take is for temporall things, and as for spirituall things, they say, they will leave all to Gods mercie: They will take to themselves Gods part, and they will leave God their part. What he would doe himselfe, they will doe; and what he would have them doe, that they put off and referre wholly to him. Temporall things they will be sure to looke for, they will not trust God

with them: But for spirituall things if they will not be found without seeking, for their parts they are never like to be sought after.
            
               
                  Error. 2.Againe, Spirituall things God would have to be esteemed as the 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               principall, and to be set in the first place; and temporall things to bee reckoned of as 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Chrysost. in hunc locum.
                
               secondarie matters, as things accessorie unto them. Whereas worldly men generally take a direct contrary course. They 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Lucian. Terpsion.
                
               set the cart, as wee say, before the horse. They 
                  Si caro famula anima domina, non oportet posteriore loco nos dominam ponere, ac famulam iniquo jure praeferre, Eucher. ad Valer.
                make Sara tend on Hagar; the Mistresse wait on the hand-maid. 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Agatho apud Clem. S
                        •
                     rom. l. 5. Vel ut apud Athen. Dipnosoph. lib. 5. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Sic enim utrobique interstinguendum, ne suus sententiae lepidissimae lepos intereat. Vise Hadr. Iuni
                        •
                     m in Adag. Cen
                        •
                     
                     ▪
                   3. Adag. 79. They make the principall the accessorie, and the accessorie the Principall. Take most pains in that, that God would have them to take least in; and take least paines in that, that God would have them to take most in. First Gods Kingdome and his Righteousnesse, saith Christ, and then Riches or those other things, 
               
                  Vers. 
                  
                     〈…〉
                   
                  cives, cives, quaerenda pecunia primùm est. Virtus post nummos.— Horat. 
                        〈…〉
                      Lucri
                        •••
                     us est od
                        ••
                      ex re Qualibet.— Vade habeas quaerit ne
                        ••
                     o; sed oportet 
                        〈…〉
                     . Sat. 14. —facias rem, Si possis, rectè: si non, quocun
                        •
                      mo
                        ••
                      re
                        •
                     
                     ▪ Horat. ep. 1. 
                     〈…〉
                  ; cum omnia habu
                        •
                     ris, tunc &amp; sapientiam habere voles. Hoc 
                        •
                     rit ultimum vitae in
                     
                        •••
                     mentum, &amp;, ut ita dic
                        ••
                     , 
                        〈◊〉
                     , Sen. epist
                        •
                     
                   17. 
               meat, drinke, and apparell. But i 
               first Riches, saith the World, moneyes and meanes of maintenance, (for k these must be had howsoever) and l the Religion and Righteousnesse may a little, time enough, be looked after, when wee are once furnished of the former.
            Yea Gods Children themselves are oft-times too much faultie in this kinde: Too slacke and 
                  〈◊〉
                in seeking after the best things; and 
                  •
               ore careful thā they should be, for the things

of this life. Not so diligent in attending as they should be, with Mary, that 
                  Vnicum necessarium, Luke 10.42. 
               one thing, that is only necessarie, and without which no worldly thing can ought availe them; and on the other side, with Martha, 
               
                  Solliciti de multis, Luke 10.41. 
               troubled about many things, and those many times such as they might very well be without; much perplexed and distracted with care and thought about provisions for the bodie, for the backe and the belly, for meat, drinke and apparell; (that which our Saviour here 
                  Mat. 6.25, 28, 31. Luk. 1
                     •
                  .22, 29. had reproved in his followers before) as if either they wanted 
                  Matth. 6.26. 
               a Father to provide for them, or 
                  Matth. 6.32. Luke 12.30. their Father were ignorant of their wants. 
               
                  Perkins alicubi.
                If wee see a young man grow worldly, full of care and thought for the world; we are readie to say, Sure his Father is deceased, and his Friends gone; he hath lost those that should looke after him; he hath no bodie left to take care for him but himselfe; else 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Aristot. Rhetor. l. 2. c. 12. 
               he would never sure be so worldly, so full of care as he is. But our heavenly Father is not dead: (he 1 Tim. 6.17. Apoc. 15.7. 
               liveth for ever to doe for us:) nor doth or can 
                  Esay. 49.15. his care die for them, whom he hath once vouchsafed to undertake the care of. And it is a great wrong therefore, that Christian men offer to this their carefull and provident Father, when they are so full of care themselves.
            But doth no care at all then bec
                     •
                  me Christians▪
               
               
                  Question.
                may some man say. Or is all Care utterly condemned? Should Christian men be like those of 
                  Iudg 18.27. 
               Laish, a sort of carelesse people; to live looking after nothing, but 
                  Qui finxit alas papilioni, is curabit omnia. Luxurioso
                     
                        •••
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     . Sc
                        •
                     
                     lig. de Subtil.
                put off all to Gods

providence, and so let things goe at six and sevens, as we say?
            
               
                  Answer.
               Not so neither. We must wisely distinguish here, that we neither wheele into the whirle-pit of distrustfulnesse on the one hand, nor wrecke our selves against the rocke of retchlesnesse on the other. There is a two-fold care, yea or carefulnesse, if you will: there is 
                  Solicitudo diligē
                     tiae, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               a carefulnesse of diligence; and there is 
                  Solicitudo diffidentiae, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               a carefulnesse of diffidence: the one is approved and commended; the other is disallowed and condemned: we are 
                  Prov. 27.23. &amp; 22.29. Phil. 4.8, 9. 1 Tim. 5.4, 8. 
               enjoyned the one; wee are 
                  Philip. 4.6. 1 Tim. 6.8, 17. 
               inhibited the other; nor doth the one necessarily follow the other, or the expulsion of the one exclude also the other. Conceive it by a plaine and familiar instance. A Father placeth his Sonne in a Farme, furnisheth him with a stocke, biddeth him play the good husband; and further assureth him, to put him out of all feare, that, if things fall out otherwise than well, so that it bee not by his owne wilfull neglect or default, he will supplie him and set him up againe. The Sonne in such case, though he may well be the lesse distrustfull, yet ought not to be the lesse diligent, for this his Fathers kinde offer, and the assurance given him of such supplies. Nor ought Christian men therefore to bee the lesse carefull of 
                  Prov. 6.6, 7, 8. et 12.11. et 28.19. walking diligently and industriously in those places and callings whereunto God hath assigned them, or in following the affaires and doing the duties that doe thereunto appertaine. (They 2 Thess. 3.6, 11. 
               walke inordinately, saith the Apostle,

that 1 Thess. 4.11. 
               follow not their owne worke, and as well 2 Thess. 3.10. 
               earne, if they be able, as 2 Thess. 3.1
                     •
                  . 
               eat their owne bread;) because God hath graciously promised, and undertaken to provide for them. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Phil. 3.16. Walke they must each one carefully 1 Cor. 7.20, 24. within the compasse of his calling, and expect 
                  Deut. 28.8. Psal. 128.1, 2. 
               Gods blessing upon their labours and endevours. But for the issue and event of them, they must not be troubled and distracted about it; but 
                  Psalm. 37.5. 2 Sam. 10.12. leave that all to God, 
                  Hebr. 13.5, 6. assuring themselves that hee will not see them to want, howsoever things fall out, but will furnish them ever with what is fit.
            And so in the third place,
                  Vse 3. Prevention.
                this serveth to meet with a conceit that keepeth many from looking after the things of Gods Kingdome, because they feare that they shall want necessaries, if they shall so doe. For, to omit that true 
                  Fides famem non formidat, Hieron. ad Heliodor.
                
               Faith, as Ierome speaketh, feareth not Famine: and againe, that he is unworthie this Crowne, this Kingdome, that preferreth worldly trash before it, or 
                  Mat. 13.44, 45, 46. Luke 14.26, 33. that is not content 
                  Philip. 3.7, 8, 9. 
               willingly, yea and 
                  Hebr. 10.34. 
               gladly, 
               
                  Omnia relinquas, ut hoc habeas, Sen. epist. 76. to forgoe the one, for the attaining and compassing of the other: Such feare is wholly superfluous; it is a groundlesse feare: Since that God the Father by Iesus Christ his Son and 2 Cor. 1.20. 
               his Surety, hath here given thee assurance; that so long as thou seekest it as thou oughtest, 
                  At necessaria decrunt. Deesse non poterūt, Sen. ep. 17. thou shalt never want ought; all other things shall be from God himselfe supplied to thee with it. And 
                  Psal. 34.10. 
               the Lions themselves therefore, saith the Psalmist, (and the Lion is the 
                  Prov. 30.30, 31. Rex ferarum, Isid. Orig. l. 10. c. 2. 
               King of beasts,) shall hunger and starve; those that are

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
likeliest to be fed: But those that seeke the Lord shall want nothing that is good. Hee 
                  Psal. 78.24. Pluviam escatilē. Tertul. de Patient.
                will raine bread from heaven, and 
                  Psalm. 78.20. &amp; 114.8. Petram aquatilem, Ibid.
                set the flintstone abroach, and turne 
                  Psal. 107.35. 2 King. 3.17. Esai. 43.19, 20. the drie and waste wildernesse into rivers of water, before his shall pine and perish.
            Yea this rather should enduce, encite, and encourage us to seeke,
                  Vse 4. Encouragement.
                as the more carefully, so the more cheerefully after these things, considering that so gracious a promise is annexed thereunto 
                  Psal. 34.9. 
               Feare, that is, 
                  Sicut, 1 King. 17.32, 33. &amp; alibi.
                
               serve the Lord diligently, yee his Saints, saith the Psalmist: for there shall nothing bee wanting to them that feare him. 
               
                  Parare unde vivam volo. Simul &amp; parare disce— Sen. ep. 17. i. vis parare? Parandi rationem disce, Lips.
                Wouldest thou then bee cared for? Wouldest thou be provided for? Wouldest thou need to take no more thought or care for ought? Get thee into Christs Court; get thee a place in Gods Kingdome. Men thinke they shall be well, they shall be safe, they shall be made for ever, when they have got some place, so it be at least some gainfull one, about the King, or belonging to the Court: such an office could they compasse, they should never need more to feare wāt, or to take further care for the world. Yet we know and see that such places oft bring 
                  Desere palatia: nā Curia Curis, imò crucibus &amp; mortibus Semper est obnoxia. Petr. Bles. ep. 57.—dum excelsus steti, numquam pavere destiti.—Sen. Thyest. 3.1. 
               a world of cares with them, &amp; 
                  Pauc
                        •
                     s 
                        •
                     eavit aula, plures perdidit: Sed hos quo
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      ips
                        •
                     s, quos beavit, per didit.
                area means oft to bring men to want. But he that hath a share in this Kingdome of God, shall never indeed need to take further care for ought, shall never need indeed to feare any defect. 
                  Ierem. 17.7, 8. 
               Blessed is the man, saith the Prophet, that dependeth upon God: for he shall bee as a Tree planted by the water side, that

spreadeth her roote alongst the river, and doth not feele when the scorching heat commeth, but continueth ever greene, and taketh no thought for the yeere of drought, nor at any time ceaseth to have fruit on her. Forbeare not therefore the following hereof for feare of want; but follow these things rather if thou wouldest not feare want.
            In like manner for your Children, would you have them so provided for, that you should not need to take any further care for them in that kinde? Distrustfull care, I meane still, and of uncertaine event; for otherwise 2 Cor. 12.12. 
               Parents ought to be carefull to provide for their children; and 1 Tim. 5.8. 
               he is worse, I say not, than an Infidell, but 
                  Nahum. 2.13. Thren. 4.3. Ipsae fera savissimae f
                        •••
                     us su
                        ••••
                     vent, enutriunt▪ milvi pullis circumvolantes rapinis prospiciunt, Aug. de Civit. l. 19. c. 12. 
               than a brute beast, that doth otherwise. But would you so doe for them, that they may bee sure not to want? which otherwise, 
                  Eccles. 4.14. Amplae &amp; regiae 
                        •
                     pes, ubi ad malum dominum pervenerunt, momēto dissipātur, Sen. de Brev. vit. c. 1. Irus &amp; est subitò, quid modò Croesus erat. Ovid. Trist. 3.7. though you leave them never so much, they may doe. Doe the like for them, that you are exhorted here to doe for your selves. A poore man when he hath gotten his childe once into the Hospitall, how glad is he? he thinketh hee need take no more care for him, whether hee live or die, whether he leave him ought or no; (and yet he will do his best to get somewhat to leave him;) he knoweth there he shall not want. But get your Children, say I, not into Christs Hospitall, but into Gods Kingdome of Grace, and they shall then bee sure indeed never to want, you shall need to take no further thought for them. Let this be thy first care, and thy principall care, as for thy selfe, so for them, nor how to make them

               rich, but 
                  Genes. 18.19. Deut. 6.6. 1 Chron. 28.9. how to make them religious, how to worke the sincere 
                  Prov. 24.21. Ephes. 6.4. 
               feare of God, and 1 Tim. 4.6. 2 Tim. 1.5. &amp; 3.15. 
               faith of Christ into them. This when thou hast once effected, thou needest not bee troubled to thinke what will become of them, if thou beest taken away from them; or what thou shalt bee able, when thou diest, to doe for them: thou shalt leave them Gods blessing, if thou hast nothing else to leave them; (where Religion and Righteousnesse runneth on in a race, there 
                  Psal. 115.13, 14. 
               Gods blessing is also hereditarie with it:) and if thou leave them that, though thou leave them nought else, they shall be sure to doe well, they shall never want ought. For, 
                  Psal. 37.18, 19. 
               The Lord knoweth the daies of the upright, or the righteous; saith David: and their inheritance shall abide for ever. They shall not be confounded in the evill time: and in the daies of famine they shall have their fill. And hee confirmeth it further by his owne experience, both concerning them and their issue. 
                  Psal. 37.25, 26. 
               I have beene young, and am now old; yet 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Clem. Alex. Paedag. lib. 3. cap. 7. 
               never, either in my younger or elder times, have I seene any righteous man forsaken, or his seed driven to beg their bread. But though he be mercifull and readie to lend, (a meanes many times to lessen and impaire mens estates) yet his seed after him inheriteth the blessing.
            
            
               
                  Objection.
               Yea but we see even 
                  Hebr. 11.37. 
               godly men many times in want, may some say.
            I answer in a word. 
                  Psalm. 37.10. &amp; 64.11. 
               They never want what is good,
               
                  Solution.
                what is necessarie, what is 
                  Sicut contra de malis Chrysippus apud Plut. de commun. not. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Ai
                        •
                      sapientem nulla re indigere, &amp; tamen multis illi rebus opus esse: contra stulto nulla re 
                        •
                     pus est; nulla enim re scit uti, sed omnibus eget. Egere enim necessitatis est. Nihil autem sapienti necesse est quod non habet▪ Sen. epist. 9. 
               needfull and behoovefull for them to have. And whatsoever

is not good and fit for them, it is 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Di
                        •
                     gen. Laert. l. 6. 
               better for them to be without it, than with it; to want, than to have it. Doe we not see, I say not, the Sons of Kings, but even Kings and Princes themselves oft by the Physitians direction 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , Dion. Chrysost. Orat. 14. imprisoned in their owne Palaces, confined to, and cowpt up in their chambers, restrained of their wonted full and delicate fare, and held to hard meat, as we say, tied to a strict and spare diet; yea and glad too to observe it, because 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , ibid.
                it would otherwise be worse with them? No marvell then if the godly sometime in like manner, though Kings and 2 Cor. 6.10. 
               Lords of all things, are for their spirituall health and further good, restrained of some things that are not so fit for them at the present. Such want is no want, when a man rather 
                  Aliud enim non habere, aliud carere, Cic. Tuscul. l. 1. 
               is without, than wanteth that, which to be without then is for his good.
            
            To end where wee began; let us by any meanes take heed,
                  Conclusion.
                lest our immoderate care for the things of this life, expell and justle out our care for things belonging to a better life: 
                  Congruum nō est in honor
                        •
                      solicitudinis nostrae praestantioribus pej
                        •
                     ra subjicere, Eucher. ad Valer.
                Let that rather yeeld to this, and 
                  Philip. 4.4. this then wil discharge us of that: let our maine and principall care be for Gods Kingdome and his Righteousnesse, and for other things we may then boldly 1 Pet. 5.7. 
               cast our care upon God, who will be sure thereupon 
                  Psalm. 23.1. Luke 22.35. 
               sufficiently, yea 2 Cor. 9.8. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , &amp;c. Chrysost. in 
                        〈◊〉
                      l
                        •
                     cum.
                
               abundantly to furnish us with whatsoever 
                  Matth. 6.32. he shall see to be needfull and fit for us.
         
         
            
            
            A
Short Catechisme For the Simpler Sort.
            1 Q. Who made the whole World, and Man at the first?
            
            
               A. 
               
                  Genes. 1.1, 27. God, 
                  Eccles. 12.1. Rom. 11.36. Apoc. 4.11. the Creator of all things.
            2 Q. What is God?
            
            
               A. An 
                  Psalm. 90.2. &amp; 102.27. eternall, and 
                  Apoc. 1.8. Psalm. 115.3. &amp; 135.6. almightie 
                  John 4.24. Spirit, most 1 Tim. 1.17. Iude 23. wise, most 
                  Esai. 6.3. Apoc. 4.8. 1 Sam. 2.2. holy, most 
                  Psalm. 92.15. &amp; 145.17. just, and most 
                  Psal. 103.8.—19. &amp; 145.8. mercifull.
            3 Q. How many Gods are there?
            
            
               A. There is but 
                  Esai. 44.6, 8. 1 Cor. 8.5, 6. one God.
            4 Q. How many Persons are there in that one Deitie?
            
            
               A. There are 1 Io
                     ••
                  
                  ▪ 5.
                     •
                  . three Persons, 
                  Matth. 28.19. 2 Cor. 
                  
                     ••
                  .
                     ••
                  . the Father▪ the Sonne, and the holy Ghost.
            5 Q. Is each of these Persons God?
            
            
               A. Yea: 
                  Iob. 
                  
                     ••
                  .3. Ephes▪
                   
                  
                     •
                  
                  ▪3, 4. the Father is God, 
                  Iohn 1.1. Hebr. 1.
                     •
                  
                  ▪6, 8. Rom▪
                   9.5. the Sonne is God, and 
                  Act. 5.3, 4. the Holy Ghost is God.
            6 Q. Are they then three severall Gods?
            
            
               
               A. No: they are 1 Iohn 5.7. Matth. 3.16, 17. three distinct Persons, yet but 
                  Deut. 6.4. Iohn 10.30. 1 Iohn 5.7. one God.
            7 Q. Whereof did God create Man at first?
            
            
               A. 
               
                  Gen 2.7. &amp; 3.19 Eccles. 12.7. He made mans bodie of the mould of the earth; but his soule he created immediately of nothing.
            8 Q. In what estate did God then make Man?
            
            
               A. He made him 
                  Eccles. 7.31. pure and perfect, 
                  Gen. 1.26, 27. &amp; 9.5. in his owne Image, like himselfe.
            9 Q. Wherein was Man then like unto God?
            
            
               A. In that he was perfectly 
                  Colos. 3.10. wise, and perfectly 
                  Ephes. 4.24. good.
            10 Q. How came man then to be evil as now he is?
            
            
               A. 
               
                  Rom. 5.12, 18, 19. By disobeying God, in breaking his Commandement.
            11 Q. Wherein did Man breake the Commandement of God?
            
            
               A. 
               
                  Gen. 3.6. In eating of the fruit of one Tree, 
                  Gen. 2.17. which God had forbidden him.
            12 Q. Who perswaded him so to doe?
            
            
               A. 
               2 Cor. 11.3. Gen. 3.1, 4, 5. The Devill perswaded the Woman, and 
                  Gen. 3.6. the Woman her Husband.
            13 Q. What is the Devill?
            
            
               A. 
               
                  Matth. 4.1. The Devill is an 
                  Luk. 7.21. &amp; 8.2. evill Spirit, who being 2 Peter 2.4. Iude 6. damned for sinning against God, doth 1 Peter 5.8. Iohn 8.44. seeke to destroy others.
            14 Q. What became of Man after he had thus sinned against God?
            
            
               A. He became most 
                  Genes. 6.5. wicked, and most 
                  Iob 14.1. &amp; 5.6, 7. wretched.
            15 Q. In what regard wicked?
            
            
               A. In that 
                  Genes. 3.7. Ephes. 4.22.24. he lost Gods Image, and was 
                  Genes. 3.22. Deut. 32.4, 5. not

now like unto God as before, but 
                  Iohn 8.44. 1 Iohn 3.8. like the Devill.
            16 Q. In what regard wretched?
            
            
               A. In that 
                  Gen. 3.23. he lost Gods favour, &amp; 
                  Genes. 3.16, 17, 18, 19. Rom. 5.12, 16. brought upon himselfe Gods everlasting 
                  Galath. 3.10. curse and 
                  Rom. 2.8, 9. wrath.
            17 Q. In what state are we all then, since this fall of our first Parents?
            
            
               A. We are all also 
                  Ephes. 2.2, 3. by nature most 
                  Rom. 3.9—20. &amp; 5.12, 19. Titus 3.3. wicked, and most 
                  Rom. 3.23. &amp; 5.12, 15, 16, 17, 18. wretched.
            18 Q. When come we to be thus evill &amp; wicked?
            
            
               A. We are evill and wicked 
                  Gen. 8.21. Psal. 51.5. &amp; 58.3. Esai. 48.8. from our very breeding and our birth.
            19 Q. What doe wee for this our wickednesse deserve at Gods hands?
            
            
               A. 
               
                  Iohn 5.28, 29. Matth. 25.46. Eternall damnation 
                  Matth. 10.28. Apoc. 14.10▪ 12. &amp; 21.14, 15. both of soule and bodie in hell fire.
            20 Q. Are wee able any way to save our selves from this?
            
            
               A. No: 
                  Psal. 22.29. &amp; 49 7.8, 9. Rom. 5.6, &amp; 8.3. we are not able: for wee are by nature spiritually 
                  Ephes. 2.1. C
                        •
                     l. 2.13. dead in sin and naughtinesse.
            21 Q. Is there no meanes then to deliver us from eternall destruction?
            
            
               A. Yes: 
                  Rom. 7.24, 25. Act 4.12. wee may bee delivered 
                  Rom. 3.24, 25. &amp; 5.17—21. by Gods mercie in Iesus Christ.
            22 Q. Who is that Iesus Christ?
            
            
               A. Iesus Christ is 
                  Ioh. 10.30. &amp; 14.9, 10 Heb. 1.3. the second Person, 
                  Prov 30.4. &amp; 8.23, 24, 25. Matth. 16.16. the eternall Sonne of God.
            23 Q. What hath he done to save us?
            
            
               A. 
               
                  Esai. 
                  
                     •
                  3.4—12. Phil. 2.6, 7, 8. 1 Pet. 2.24. He suffred death upon the Crosse, 
                  Rom. 5.8, 9, 10. Galat. 1.4. &amp; 3.13. 1 Thess. 1.10. Hebr. 2.9, 14, 15. &amp; 9.12, 15. to

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
save us from death and destruction.
            24. Q. How could he die being the eternall Sonne of God?
            
            
               A. He was both 
                  Ier. 23.6. &amp; 33.16. Esai. 9.6. 1 Iohn 5.20. God and 
                  Ioh. 1.10. Gal. 4.4. 1 Tim. 2.5. Man; and 2 Cor. 13.4. 1 Pet. 3.18. died as he was Man; but 
                  Ioh. 2.19. &amp; 10.17, 18. raised himselfe again to life as he was God.
            25 Q. Shall all men then be saved by Christ?
            
            
               A. 
               
                  Luk. 13.23—28. Matt. 7.13, 14, 21, 22, 23. No. none shall be saved by Christ, but 
                  Marke 1.15. such as 
                  Luke 13.3, 5. &amp; 24.47. repent of their sinnes, and 
                  Marke 16.16. Joh. 3.14—18, 36. beleeve in him.
            26 Q. What is meant by repenting of Sinne?
            
            
               A. To repent of our sins is to be 
                  Act. 2.37. 2 Cor. 7.10. heartily sory for them, 
                  Psal. 97.10. Rom. 7.15, 20. &amp; 12.9. to hate and abhorre them, and to endevour carefully 
                  Prov. 28.13. Iohn 5.14. to shun &amp; avoid them.
            27 Q. What is meant by beleeving in Christ?
            
            
               A. 
               
                  Rom. 3.25, 28. &amp; 4.5. &amp; 9.32, 33. &amp; 10 4, 9, 11. To beleeve, or 
                  Psa. 2.12. &amp; 32.10. &amp; 37.22. to trust in Christ, is 
                  Esai. 50.10. Phil. 3.7, 8, 9. to rely wholly upon him for 
                  Heb. 1.2. &amp; 9.14, 26. 1 Ioh. 1.9. the pardon of our sinnes, and 
                  Rom. 5.9, 10. Hebr. 9.28. the safetie of our soules.
            28 Q. How come we thus to rely on him?
            
            
               A. By 
                  Rom. 1.16. &amp; 10.14, 17. the word of God, 
                  Rom. 3.21, 22. &amp; 10.5—8. Gal. 3.2. making knowne Gods mercy in this behalfe towards us in Christ Iesus.
            29 Q. What meanes are there to give us further assurance of the mercy of God towards us?
            
            
               A. The 
                  Mark. 1.4. &amp; 16.16. Act. 2.31. Luke 22.19; 20. Sacraments give us further assurance of Gods mercy revealed in the Word.
            30 Q. What is meant by the word Sacrament?
            
            
               A. Sacraments are as visible 
                  Gen. 17.10, 11, 23. Exod. 12.11, 13. Signes &amp; 
                  Rom. 4.11. Psal. 50.5. Ier. 34.18. Seales of Gods mercy towards us in Christ.
            31 Q. How many Sacraments are there now in use?
            
            
               
               A. There are 1 Cor. 12.13. two Sacraments; 
                  Marke 1.4. Matth. 28.19. Baptisme, and 1 Cor. 11.20, 23.26. the Lords Supper.
            32 Q. What is Baptisme?
            
            
               A. Baptisme is a Sacrament, wherein 
                  Hebr. 10.22. Ephes. 5.26. by washing of the Body is signified 1 Pet. 3.21. Rom. 6.2—9. the purging and clensing of the soule.
            33 Q. What is the outward Signe in Baptisme?
            
            
               A. The outward 
                  Iohn 1.26, 31. &amp; 3.23. Signe in Baptisme is water.
            34 Q. What is that a Signe of?
            
            
               A. Water in Baptisme is 
                  Matth. 3.11. Ioh. 1.33. &amp; 3.3▪ 5. a Signe of the Holy Ghost, 1 Cor. 6.11. Tit. 3.5. wherby we are inwardly renewed.
            35 Q. What is the Lords Supper?
            
            
               A. The Lords Supper is a Sacrament, wherein 1 Cor. 1.28. &amp; 10.21. Mat. 26.26, 27. by eating and drinking is represented 1 Cor. 10.16, 17. &amp; 12.13. our spirituall Communion with Christ.
            36 Q. What be the outward Signes in the Lords Supper?
            
            
               A. The outward Signes in the Lords Supper are 
                  Matth. 26.26. 1 Cor. 10.16, 17. &amp; 11.26, 27.28. Bread and 
                  Matth. 26.29. Marke 14.25. Wine.
            37 Q. What are they Signes of?
            
            
               A The 
                  Matth. 26.26. 1 Cor. 10.16. &amp; 11.27, 29. Bread signifieth Christs Bodie, and the 
                  Matth. 26.28. Luke 22.20. 1 Cor. 10.16. &amp; 11.27. Wine signifieth his Bloud.
            38 Q. What is meant by the breaking of the Bread, and the powring out of the Wine?
            
            
               A. The Bread is broken, and the Wine powred out, 
                  Mat. 26.26.2
                     •
                  . Luke 22.19.20. 1 Cor. 11.26. to represent 
                  Esai. 53.3, 4, 5, 10. Luk. 22.42—45. the cruell paines and torments, and 
                  Phil. 2.8. Esai. 53.12. Matth. 27.34—50. the bitter and bloudy death that Christ suffered for our sake.
            39 Q. To what end are we to come to the Lords Table?
            
            
               A. First, 
                  Luke 22.19. 1 Cor. 11.24, 25. to be put in minde of Christs death and passion:
            
               And secondly, 
                  Matth. 26.28. Luke 22.20. to be assured thereby of the forgivenesse of our sinnes.
            40 Q. How ought they to be affected that desire to repaire thither?
            
            
               A. First, they ought 
                  Ierem. 3.1, 13. Psal. 51.1, 2, 3. to see and know their sinnes;
            Secondly, 2 Cor. 7.10. Zech. 12.10. to be truly and sincerely sorie for them;
            Thirdly, 
                  Psal. 97.10. Prov. 8.13. to hate and abhorre them, as 
                  Esai 53.4, 5, 6. Rom. 4.23. 1 Pet. 1, 18, 19. the cause of Christs death,
            And lastly, 
                  Iohn. 5.14. Ier. 34.15, 16, 18, 20. 2 Pet. 2.20, 21, 22. Hebr. 6.4, 5, 6. &amp; 10.26—29. to resolve not to returne againe to the practise of them.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

