
   
      
         
            A booke of sundry draughtes principaly serving for glasiers: and not impertinent for plasterers, and gardiners: be sides sundry other professions. Whereunto is annexed the manner how to anniel in glas: and also the true forme of the fornace, and the secretes thereof.
            Gedde, Walter.
         
         
            
               1615
            
         
         Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01569
            STC 11695
            ESTC S102996
            99838755
            99838755
            3143
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01569)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3143)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 958:05)
         
         
            
               
                  A booke of sundry draughtes principaly serving for glasiers: and not impertinent for plasterers, and gardiners: be sides sundry other professions. Whereunto is annexed the manner how to anniel in glas: and also the true forme of the fornace, and the secretes thereof.
                  Gedde, Walter.
               
               [22], 103, [9] p., folded plate : chiefly ill. (woodcuts)  
               
                  Printed in Shoolane, at the signe of the Faulcon by Walter Dight,
                  London :
                  1615.
               
               
                  "Here beginneth the first part of square draughtes .." and "The manner, howe to anneile, or paint in glas" each has separate title page, the latter dated 1616; register is continuous.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Decoration and ornament --  Early works to 1800.
               Geometrical drawing --  Early works to 1800.
               Annealing of glass --  Early works to 1800.
               Glass construction --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-01
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-03
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-04
            Celeste NgSampled and proofread
         
            2007-04
            Celeste NgText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
               
               
                  A
BOOKE OF SVNDRY DRAVGHTES, Principaly ſerving for Glaſiers: And not Impertinent for Plaſterers, and Gardiners▪ be ſides ſundry other profeſſions.
                  
                     WHEREVNTO IS ANnexed the manner how to anniel in Glas: And alſo the true forme of the Fornace, and the ſecretes thereof.
                  
                  LONDON Printed in Shoolane, at the ſigne of the Faulcon by Walter Dight, 1615.
               
            
         
         
            
            
               
The Authour to the willing practiſers of glazeing, and anneiling in Glaſſe.
            
               AS the principall beautie, and countenaunce of Architecture, conſiſtes in outward ornament of lights, ſo the inward partes are ever oppoſite to the eies of the beholder, taking more delight in the beauty therof, being cūningly wrought, then in any other garniſhing within the ſame. To which purpoſe, is ſet downe in this, variety of draughts, ſome, ordinary and plaine, others, curious &amp; pleaſant, and although, it may ſeeme to thoſe that are expert in glazeing, that ſome of theſe draughts are needleſſe, being ſo plaine and in vſe, not deſeruing in this ſort to be publiſhed, yet notwithſtanding here I doe in friendly courteſie admoniſh, that it is moſt needefull, giuing choice to the builder, both for price, and draught of worke, which by no vnderſtanding can the Glazier ſo ſencibly demonſtrate his freat, as by ſhowing his examples of draught, for by ſuch ſhow, the builders ſhall vnderſtand, what to make choice off, for whoſe eaſe &amp; furtherance only, I haue publiſhed this practiſe of glazeing, knowing the expert maiſter is not vnfurniſhed of theſe vſuall draughts, though each workeman haue not all of them.
            And for the further benefit of the practiſer, there is herevnto annexed dyapring on each draught, either to be wrought or left, as it ſhall pleaſe the builder, moſt pleaſant to all that are willing to haue the ſame: Therefore haue it not in light regard▪ for the vſe thereof, will giue you great delight, and worthy to be practiſed, as a ſpeciall ornament to building, and will beautifie the Glaziers worke, be they neuer ſo expert.
            So by obſeruing the order and rules here ſet downe, the maiſter or workeman ſhall not only ſee a plaine way, to imitate and follow thoſe draughts, in glazeing and painting on glaſſe: but the ſimpleſt, and vnskild prentice, ſhall reape full and perfect vnderſtanding thereby: praying the Almighty, to bleſſe your labours in following the ſame.
            
               Wa: Gedde.
            
         
      
      
         
            
               
                  
                  
                     
                        THE MANNER TO DRAWE THE SQVARE.
                     
                     Directions how to make your Square.
                  Firſt then concerning the ſquare, which although it be cōmon to ſundry artificers, each one hauing his owne forme and deviſe, in drawing of it, ſome by deviſion of halfe circle, ſome by other rules: there is herefore ſet downe a more perfect and readier way for any worke in draught, and alſo if neede be, to try the ſquare rule thereby: for certainely, glaſſe worke of all others▪ requires moſt an exact ſquare, for the diſtance, of one haire out of ſquare, will deface the whole worke, and bring it out of all frame.
                  
                     The ordering of the ſquare.
                     To drawe this ſquare: Firſt you muſt drawe your line draught ſo long as your worke requireth, marking right theron with your compaſſe, three points of alike diſtance, next, devide your compaſſe larger, ſetting the one point on the figure 2. &amp; with the other drawe a quarter circle betwixt 4. and 5. after, remoue your compaſſe to the figure 3. and drawe a croſſe circle ouer betwixt 6. and 7. and whereſoever the iuſt middle of the croſſe appeareth, marke the ſame with the point of the compaſſe, as you may perceiue in the character, by the figure 8. laſtly, drawe a draught, betwixt the figure 1. and the croſſe point by the figure 8. and thou ſhalt find a perfect ſquare to conduct thee all thy draughts. As on the former ſide is ſhewed.
                  
               
               
                  
                  The deviſion of meaſures, in glaſſe draughts▪
                  
                  To make this more plaine to the practiſer, the ſquare draugh
                        •
                      for the moſt part paſſes on three ſeverall deviſions, the firſt, on a declining, or collaterall ſquare, others, on even ſquares, and the third, interlaced with both: This declining deviſion and ſetting this worke thereon, muſt begin after the forme you perceiue here on his deviſion, and may be extended, in any quantity you pleaſe: the perfect draught of this worke, and how it ſhall ſtande in glaſſe, you ſhall finde it in fol. 38. &amp; other draughts alſo agreeable to the ſame meaſure, in ſundry other places, as in fol: 16. 27. 47. and others.
                  It is alſo to be vnderſtood, that the ſhadowing, and darkning, ſet downe in all thoſe freats and draughts, demonſtrates the diapring, which is for the vſe of thoſe that deſire to haue their worke beautified with the ſame, and the plaine draught, is the convoy, and courſe of the lead, which dyapring, muſt only be in gray, or blew colour, as is largely ſet downe amongſt the rules of colour.
                  
                     
                     
                        Begin this at the figure 3.
                        
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  Of even ſquare deviſion.
                  There be a number of draughts, wrought by this even dire
                        ••
                      ſquare, which is moſt perfect of any; to ſet this worke right, ye muſt begin your firſt loſing, at the figure 4. and ſo runne out i
                        •
                      any quantity you will, as this deviſion will ſhew you: the perfect, and full draught hereof, as it muſt ſtand in glaſſe-worke, you ſhall finde in fol: 43. with ſundry other draughts of the ſame meaſure, as in fol: 40. and in other places.
                  
                     
                     
                        Begin at the figure 4.
                        
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  Of even croſſe deviſion.
                  This ſheweth a plaine draught with a double circle, and even over croſſe meaſure, beginniug his ſett at the figure 7. This whole perfect draught, as it is to be wrought in glaſſe, you ſhall finde in fol: 72. with ſundry other draughts alſo of the ſame deviſion, as in fol: 77. 78. 79. 80. 81. 82▪ and others.
                  
                     
                     
                        Begin at the figure 5.
                        
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  Of a declining croſſe draught.
                  This Interlaced double circle, with double declining croſſe deviſion, muſt begin his ſetting, at the figure 8. and his whole draught ſtandeth in fol: 86. and alſo others of the ſame deviſion, with double circle, as in fol: 83. 82. 80. 76. &amp; other places as may be perceiued.
                  
                     
                     
                        Begin at the figure 6.
                        
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  Of interlaced deviſion.
                  This interlaced deviſion, yeildeth very pleaſant draughts, exceeding cloſe, &amp; ſtrong: the ſetting of this worke on his deviſion, muſt begin at the figure 5. and from thence to follow out to the full quantity that your glaſſe-worke requireth: the principal draught hereof, you ſhall finde in fol: 47. with ſundry other of the ſame meaſure, as in fol: 12. 27. 32.
                  Some other ſquare draughts are here ſet downe of greater difficulty, but as they are ſomewhat more painefull in working, ſo are they more pleaſant, &amp; will make a delectable ſhow: which workes muſt haue his right deviſion, on the glaſſe table drawen with blacke, which will conduct the ſetting perfectly, making the moſt curious draught in this booke, eaſie, &amp; plaine to be wrought in glaſſe.
                  
                     
                     
                        Begin at the figure 7.
                        
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  Of compaſſe workes, or draughts.
                  Theſe draughts following, with their deviſion, are differing from the other: ſome there be of ſingle compaſſe draught, others double: ſome be ſquare, &amp; cōpas declīing croſſe draughts, and euen croſſe and withall interlaced.
                  Firſt then this ſingle circle of this deviſion, as you ſee here ſet downe, is a very fine draught in glaſſe-worke, &amp; the ſetting thereof, muſt begin at the figure 6. and the whole draught as it muſt ſhow in glaſſe-worke, you ſhall finde in fol: 74. and in ſundry other draughts of the like deviſion, as in fol: 87. very eaſie to be wrought, making exceeding pleaſant worke.
                  
                     
                     
                        Begin at the figure 8.
                        
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  Interlaced croſſe draught.
                  This as you perceiue is even croſſe and declining draught, intermixed, exceeding pleaſant in glaſſe-worke: hi
                        •
                      begīning of ſetting of your worke is at the figure 9. &amp; the principall whole draught is to be found in fol: 71. as alſo a great many moe of the ſame deviſion, in divers other places.
                  Other ſorts there be of theſe circle workes, of greater difficulty, but the deviſion thereof on thy glaſſe table, muſt be thy helpe to make it eaſy, as is before mētioned in the ſquare draughts
                  
                     
                     
                        Begin at the figure 9.
                        
                     
                  
               
            
         
         
            
               
                  
                  
                  
                     
                        HERE BEGINNETH The firſt part of ſquare draughtes Formed vppon direct, and collatterall lines: which fitly may be applied to ſundrie vſes.
                        And now newly publiſhed BY WALTER GIDDE.
                        
                        1615.
                     
                  
               
            
            
               
                  
                  
                     
                     
                        1.
                     
                     
                        
                        2.
                     
                     
                        
                        3
                     
                     
                        
                        4
                     
                     
                        
                        5
                     
                     
                        
                        6
                     
                     
                        
                        7
                     
                     
                        
                        8
                     
                     
                        
                        9
                     
                     
                        
                        10
                     
                     
                        
                        11
                     
                     
                        
                        12
                     
                     
                        
                        13
                     
                     
                        
                        14
                     
                     
                        
                        15
                     
                     
                        
                        16
                     
                     
                        
                        17
                     
                     
                        
                        18
                     
                     
                        
                        19
                     
                     
                        
                        20
                     
                     
                        
                        21
                     
                     
                        
                        22
                     
                     
                        
                        23
                     
                     
                        
                        24
                     
                     
                        
                        25
                     
                     
                        
                        26
                     
                     
                        
                        27
                     
                     
                        
                        28
                     
                     
                        
                        29
                     
                     
                        
                        30
                     
                     
                        
                        31
                     
                     
                        
                        32
                     
                     
                        
                        33
                     
                     
                        
                        34
                     
                     
                        
                        35
                     
                     
                        
                        36
                     
                     
                        
                        37
                     
                     
                        
                        38
                     
                     
                        
                        39
                     
                     
                        
                        40
                     
                     
                        
                     
                     
                        
                     
                     
                        
                        43
                     
                     
                        
                        44
                     
                     
                        
                        45
                     
                     
                        
                        46
                     
                     
                        
                        47
                     
                     
                        
                        48
                     
                     
                        
                        49
                     
                     
                        
                        50
                     
                     
                        
                        51
                     
                     
                        
                        52
                     
                     
                        
                        53
                     
                     
                        
                        54
                     
                     
                        
                        55
                     
                     
                        
                        56
                     
                     
                        
                        57
                     
                     
                        
                        58
                     
                     
                        
                        59
                     
                     
                        
                        60
                     
                     
                        
                        61
                     
                     
                        
                        62
                     
                     
                        
                        63
                     
                     
                        
                        64
                     
                     
                        
                        65
                     
                     
                        
                        66
                     
                  
               
            
         
         
            
               
                  
                  
                     
                        HEERE Foloweth Sundrie ſortes, of Circuler, or Compas Draughtes for Glazing: And will fitly ſerue for divers vſes.
                        
                        Newly Publiſhed by Walter Gidde▪
                           
                        
                     
                  
               
            
            
               
                  
                  
                     
                     
                        67
                     
                     
                        
                        68
                     
                     
                        
                        69
                     
                     
                        
                        70
                     
                     
                        
                        71
                     
                     
                        
                        72
                     
                     
                        
                        
                     
                     
                        
                     
                     
                        
                     
                     
                        
                     
                     
                        
                        
                           
73
                     
                     
                        
                        74
                     
                     
                        
                        75
                     
                     
                        
                        76
                     
                     
                        
                        77
                     
                     
                        
                        78
                     
                     
                        
                        79
                     
                     
                        
                        80
                     
                     
                        
                        81
                     
                     
                        
                        82
                     
                     
                        
                        83
                     
                     
                        
                        84
                     
                     
                        
                        85
                     
                     
                        
                        86
                     
                     
                        
                        87
                     
                     
                        
                        88
                     
                     
                        
                        89
                     
                     
                        
                        90
                     
                     
                        
                        91
                     
                     
                        
                        92
                     
                     
                        
                        93
                     
                     
                        
                        94
                     
                     
                        
                        95
                     
                     
                        
                        96
                     
                     
                        
                        97
                     
                     
                        
                        98
                     
                     
                        
                        99
                     
                     
                        
                        100
                     
                     
                        
                        101
                     
                     
                        
                        102
                     
                     
                        
                        103
                     
                  
               
            
         
         
            
               
                  
                  
                     
                     
                        THE MANNER, Howe to Anneile, or Paint in Glas: THE true receptes of the cullors, The ordering of the Furnace, and all the ſecretes there vnto belonging.
                        
                        1616
                     
                  
               
            
            
               
                  
                  
                     
THE TRVE FORME, OF THE Furnace, for the Anneiling in Glaſse, withall the Inſtruments belonging therevnto.
                  
                  
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  THE MANNER HOWE to erect the Fornace.
                  
                     TAKE free-ſtone, or Bricke, and proportion it fower foote ſquare, and three foote high and two foote and halfe in eache ſquare: And at either corner which is marked with the letter A. leaue an open hole, to let oute the ſmoake, when neede ſhall require: which holes you ſhall cover, with peeces of bricke-bats. And in the midle of the toppe of the Fornace, around hole made, fower inches over as ye ſee it markt with letter B. which hole you muſt alwayes keepe coverd with a turffe or Charcole, &amp; renew it ſo often as the fire doth conſume it away: And note that this hole doth ſerue to giue vent to the ſmoake, and to keepe in the heate: for this hole is right over the mouth of the Pan where the glaſse lieth.
                  This Pan, marked with the letter C. muſt be made of fine clay, fit to indure the fire and placed on an Iron trevet, in the middeſt of the Fornace, ſo that the fire may haue place to giue heat, both vnder and aboue the pan.
                  This Pan wherein the glas is put, muſt haue an open ſquare in the ſide, fiue inches high, and three inches broad, as you ſee marked with the letter D. and the like open place muſt be made in the ſide of the fornace, right oppoſite to the open ſquare in the ſide of the pan, where the peeces of glas do lie, called the proofe peces, which peeces, are to be taken in &amp; oute at your pleaſure, whereby you may knowe when your wrought glaſse is thorowly enameled, and of a faire coullour.
                  
                     
                     How you ought to prepare and put your Glas into the Furnace.
                     TAKE Chalke that is cleane, and beate it ſmall in a Morter, or elſe grind it well on a painters ſtone: then ſprinkle ſome of it in the bottom of the Pan, before the fire be put in the Furnace: then lay a plye, or laine of glaſse that is wrought thereō, thē ſift on more chalk and then laye another tyre, or laine of glaſse: So by beds of chalke &amp; glaſse, you may lay on as much prepared glas as the Pan will hold one rewe aboue another, but remēber that betwene every rewe of glaſse you do ſifte on chalke, that the wrought glaſs may not touch one another. Then take litle peeces of glaſse, and touche thē with the ſame coullour that your wrought glaſse is of, &amp; put them in at the paſſag, at the ſide of the Furnace, betwixt the beds of wrought glaſse, &amp; then begin to make a reaſonable fire vnder and aboute the Pan vntill you thinke, that the glaſse hath taken a faire coullour.
                     Now to knowe when your glas is perfectly ready; take a paire of tonges, and drawe oute one of thoſe little peeces of glaſſe, called the prooffe peece, and hold it betwext you and the light: if the cullor ſhowe faire, and ſtick faſt vppon the glaſſe, then you may be ſure that the worke vnder is well and perfectly anneiled, becauſe it hath had the greateſt ſtrength of the fire: But if you doubt that the cullours be not ſure, then rubbe with a rough ſtone or a knife, one of the proofe peeces, and then if the cullor come of, then you muſt let it continew longer in the fire, while you put the next peece to the proofe. Note further that the proofe hole in the ſide of the Furnace, marked with the letter D. muſt haue a ſtone that will abide the fire fitted to it, ſuch a one as you ſee marked with the letter F. which ſtone ſerveth to take of, and put on ſo often as you make triall of the proofe peeces.
                     Alſo yov muſt haue an earthen pot, ſuch as ye ſee marked with the letter E. wherein you muſt haue a readines ſome ſoft clay to faſten the ſtone againe, ſo often as you ſhall haue occaſion to remoue it? But the holes in the toppe of the furnace you muſt not ſtoppe with clay, but only with peeces of brick bats ſo that the ſmoake may haue vent oute.
                  
               
               
                  
                  THE RECEIPETS, FOR THE true making of Collours for Glaſse.
                  
                     To make a faire Blacke.
                     TAKE the Scales of Iron &amp; Copper, of each a like waight, &amp; put it in a cleane veſſell that will indure the fire, till they be red hotte, then take halfe as much Ieate, and ſtamp them into ſmal pouder, then mix them with Gumwater, &amp; grind them fine vpon a painters ſtone and ſo drawe with it vpon your glaſſe.
                  
                  
                     To make a Greene coullour.
                     TAKE Vertegreaſe, and grind it very well with Turpentine then put it in a cleane pot, and when you would vſe it warme it at the fire.
                  
                  
                     To make a faire red.
                     TAKE Sanguis draconis and beate it well in a Morter, &amp; after ſtraine it thorough a linning cloth, with a little Aquavitie, and ſo vſe it.
                  
                  
                     Carnation.
                     TAKE two oūces of Tyn-glas, and ſix ovnces of Ieat, half an ounce of gum, ten ounces of red Ocker, and grind them very well togeather, and ſo vſe it.
                  
                  
                     
                     Blew.
                     TAKE beades of blew glas, and beat them into poulder, in a braſen morter, and halfe as much of goldſmithes blew amaling that ſhines through, &amp; grind them together with gum-water, and ſo vſe it.
                  
                  
                     Yellow.
                     TAKE a quantitie of fine ſilver, and cut it in ſmale peeces, and put therto a little Antimonium beaten to poulder, and put them to-geather in a melting-pot, and ſet them on the fire well covered round about with hotte embers the ſpace of an hower, then take it from the fire, and poure it into the bottom of a cleane earthen veſſell that will abide the heate thereof: after it is cold beat it into fine poulder, and grind it on a Painters ſtone, and when it is well ground, take ſixe times as much Ocker as the Silver weighes, and ſeven times as much old earth that hath bin ſcraped off from enamaled worke: after that, let it be well ground, then put all this together in apot with gume-water, and ſtirre it well aboute and ſo vſe it.
                  
                  
                     To make a Grey couller.
                     TAKE Iron ſcales, alittle Criſtall, and ſum ſmale quantitie of Ieate, grind theſe well together vpon a painters ſtone, the more Ieate ye take, the ſadder the coullour will be, &amp;likewiſe the more chriſtall you put to it the lighter.
                  
                  
                     
                     To Diaper vppon glas.
                     TAKE Criſtall, beaten to poulder, and grind it well vppon a painters ſtone with Gumwater, and ſo vſe it: It will apeare a prettie light coullour, different from the glas: Keepe this coullour in a little Potte, and when you will vſe it, ſtirre it well aboute.
                  
                  
                     Another faire red Cullour.
                     TAKE a quātitie of red glaſse beades, and halfe as much of Goldſmithes red Enamaling, and prepare it as you did the blew coullour before.
                  
                  FINIS
                  
               
            
         
      
   

