
   
      
         
            The lavves and statutes of Geneua as well concerning ecclesiastical discipline, as ciuill regiment, with certeine proclamations duly executed, whereby Gods religion is most purelie mainteined, and their common wealth quietli gouerned: translated out of Frenche into Englishe by Robert Fills.
            Laws, etc.
            Geneva (Switzerland)
         
         
            
               1562
            
         
         Approx. 207 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 96 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01594
            STC 11725
            ESTC S103016
            99838775
            99838775
            3163
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01594)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3163)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 295:05)
         
         
            
               
                  The lavves and statutes of Geneua as well concerning ecclesiastical discipline, as ciuill regiment, with certeine proclamations duly executed, whereby Gods religion is most purelie mainteined, and their common wealth quietli gouerned: translated out of Frenche into Englishe by Robert Fills.
                  Laws, etc.
                  Geneva (Switzerland)
                  Fills, Robert, fl. 1562.
               
               [8], 85 [i.e. 87], [1] leaves   
               
                  By Rouland Hall [and Thomas Hacket], dwellyng in Gutter Lane, at the sygne of the halfe Egle and the Keye,
                  Printed at London :
                  1562.
               
               
                  Colophon reads: Printed at London by Rouland Hall and Thomas Hacket, the 16. of Aprill .. 1562.
                  Running title reads: The lawes of Geneua.
                  Variant: title has "concerning spirituall as ciuill".
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Church discipline --  Early works to 1800.
               Ecclesiastical law --  Switzerland --  Geneva --  Early works to 1800.
               Church and state --  Switzerland --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-12
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-06
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-06
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               THE
Lavves and Statutes
of Geneua, as well concerning eccleſiaſtical
Diſcipline, as ciuill regiment, with certeine
Proclamations duly executed, whereby Gods
religion is moſt purelie mainteined, and their
common wealth quietli gouerned: Tranſlated
out of Frenche into Engliſhe by
Robert Fills.
            
            Except the Lorde kepe the Citie, the keper
watcheth in vayne.
            PSAL. 127.
            AFTER DARKNES,
LIGHT.
            
               POST TENEBRAS LVX
            
            
               PRINTED AT LONdon
by Rouland Hall, dwellyng in Gutter
Lane, at the ſygne of the halfe Egle
and the Keye.
1562.
         
         
            
            
            To the right honorable,
the Lorde ROBERT DVDDELEY
Maiſter of the Queenes Maieſties
horſe, and knight of the noble order of the
Garter, Robert Fills wiſheth long lyfe,
with the encreaſe of godlye
honour.
            
               YOur good zeale (right
honorable lord) to the
aduaūcement of gods
glorye in this realme,
and the ſinguler gentilnes
and fauour that
you vſually ſhewe to the furtherers
thereof, hathe moued and encoraged
me to flie to ye protectiō of your name,
partlye to procure thereby ſome defence
and cōmendacion to this good
worke, which I haue tranſlated into
the Engliſhe tongue, and partly ſo
muche as in me lyeth, to do you that
honour whiche of righte I thinke to
to appertaine vnto you: that is to acknowledge
you by the dedication of
this worcke (as you are in deede to
your great praiſe &amp; renowne) a worthie
patrone of good &amp; godlye meanings.

But there is nothing ſo well
minded, or ſo godly deuiſed, but that
it may, &amp; cōmonly is, by euill taking
miſconſtrued, and by ſiniſter talking
depraued: ſuch is the nature and propertie
of the malicious and ſlaunderous
tongue, that being but a lytle
member, yet it is euer buſye and babeling,
neuer quiet, barking alwaies
byting ſomtime, fynding great matter
where none is, makynge of nothing
ſome thinge, of ſome thynge a
greate thinge, of a Mouſe a Mountaine,
of a Gnat an Olephant, of a
ſmale ſparke, enkindlynge a fyer of
much diſcorde and diſſencion. Therefore
albeit ye Greke Poet Ariſtophanes
truly ſayeth, that there is no remedie
againſt the byting of a Sichophant
or ſlaunderer: yet ſomewhat
to ſtoppe the rage of this running &amp;
ranging tongue, and to preuent and
cure as muche as maye be this peſtilent
poyſon, I haue not only thought
good to vſe the ſayde meane, of your
honorable name, but alſo to expreſſe
in thys my preface, bothe the purport
&amp; ſubſtaunce of the boke, and ye
               
minde &amp; meaning of my ſelfe ye tranſlatour,
yt if the malicious man wyll
carpe or cauil at either of them, your
honour and other that by your example,
ſhall iudge well of thinges well
entended, maye haue at hand a trew
apologie and defence. The booke conteineth
lawes and ſtatutes, without
which a common weale can no more
be ruled, then the body lyue without
the ſoule, or a great ſhippe in the boiſterous
ſea, bee gouerned without a
wiſe and ſkilfull lodeſman, and they
are ye ſtatutes of Geneua, a Citie coū
               ted
of all godly men ſingularly well
ordered, as well for good policie, as
alſo for the gouernemente of the
Churche in all eſtates, orders, and
vocations, where ſincere religion is
wonderfullye aduaunced, erroure
mightely beaten downe, vertue excedingly
maynteyned, vice ſeuerelye
repreſſed: ſuche is the execution of
thoſe lawes, ſuch ſtraight diſcipline
is practiſed, that not only groſſe crimes
are puniſhed, but common (faultes
as men take them) are narowlye
ſeene vnto, as blaſphemye, hereſye,

ſtraunge and peſtiferous doctrine,
fornication ſpirituall and corporall,
ſwearinge, ſclaunderinge and ſuche
lyke, ſo yt in dede that place maye be
a lantarne to manye other, bothe of
ſinceritie in iudgement, and of honeſtie
in conuerſation, as this booke
preſently doth witnes, &amp; the practiſe
and example doth much moore lyuely
declare. Now, the intent &amp; minde of ye
tranſlatour is faithfullye to communicate
to Engliſhe men, this treaſure
taken oute of the Frenche tongue,
(obteyning the copye oute of the regiſter
booke of the foreſayde Citie)
that thereby they may beholde as in
a glaſſe, a chriſtian reformation, and
employe them ſelues to the imitation
as farre forthe as they ſee beſt for
them, as ſhalbe moſt conuenient.
Hereby maye not bee gathered that
the Tranſlatour is a newe lawe maker,
or authour of any innouacion, or
that his induſtrie and diligence is in
any wyſe preiudiciall to the lawes of
this our realme, which are laudable,
good, and godlye: but as the knowledge
of all hiſtories is to all ſuche

as deſyre to heare, ſee, and knowe,
thynges profitable and pleaſaunte,
and neceſſarye, ſo beſyde the obſeruation
of the common lawes poſitiue,
the readynge of thys fruitefull
worcke, ſhall brynge to the priuate
man godlye inſtruction. If we haue
a pleaſure to reade Ioſephus, Xenophon,
Plutarche, Ariſtotle, Liuye,
and ſuche other, and wyſhe them to
bee tourned into knowen and familier
languages: that thereby we may
peruſe and vnderſtande the lawes,
faſhions and ordinaunces of the Iewes,
Grecians, Romaines, and others,
howe muche more ought men
to ſuffer and take in good parte this
facte of him that bringeth home to vs
out of a ſtrange and far coūtrey, and
forein tongue, a forme &amp; patrone, not
only of a wel inſtituted cōmon weale
but of a well reformed churche, not
for Heathen to gaſe on, but for Chriſtians
to folowe, not ſo much for delectation
as for edification. Whiche
fruite of my laboure, God graunte
maye tourne to hys glorye, and to
the encreace of good nourture and

diſcipline in Chriſtes ſcoole, that
trew repentaunce and amendment
of lyfe maye enſue, that by our workes
our heauenly father may be glorified,
and his people by the example
of our faith and mutuall charitie edified.
And further, this worke maye
ſerue for matter of anſwere to thoſe
that inueying agaynſte the lyues of
men of our profeſſion, do more falſely
ſpeake euill of vs, than they can
trewlye ſpeake well of theyr owne
faction. They charge vs with libertie
and licenciouſneſſe moſte vniuſtly,
reportinge that we departed oute
of this realme in the late tyme of baniſhement
of Goods churche, onelye
to this ende, to enioye more vnchaſtiſed
freedome of ſenſuall lyfe: But
when they ſhal beholde theſe lawes,
&amp; ſhal not bee able to proue, but yt the
ſame are as vertuouſly folowed, and
as ſeuerely executed in thoſe places
where we lyued, as in this boke they
be here expreſſed: which ſhal appeare
howe ſmall lycence is in oure reformed
churches left to ſynne, in compariſon
of the realmes drowned in their

ſuperſticion, where their truſte in
mans pardon hathe quenched the
feare of gods diſpleaſure, and where
horrible ſynnes are diſpenſable for
money, I truſte theſe ſlaunderours
ſhal haue their mouthes ſtopped, tyll
they bee able to ſhewe a common
weale of their owne, where ſo good
lawes both of ſincere religion and ciuill
iuſtice and honeſty, are ſo dewly
put in practiſe, ſo reuerentlye obeyd,
and ſo preciſelye kept, yea &amp; by thoſe
that willynglye for the loue of god,
and tender care of their owne ſaluation,
do forſake the landes of greater
libertie of lyfe, to thrall them ſelfes
to ſuch ſeueretie. For the maner of
tranſlating I ſhall beſeche your honour,
and all good readers to beare
with the plaine and ſimple rudeneſſe
thereof, and for myne excuſe to vnderſtonde,
that I conſidered theſe to
be lawes and rules of lyfe and religion,
in expreſſinge whereof, I had
rather be to curiouſly faithfull, then
any thinge neglygently or vntrulye
fine, I haue giuen it worde: for word
rather folowing ſomtime ye Frenche

praſe to muche, then at anye tyme
venturynge to preſume or take to
my ſelfe a iudgement that I attayned
the ſence of the worcke, yf I
ſhould ſwarue from the wordes. My
laboure I beſeche youre honoure to
accepte in good parte, as I wyll not
fayle to continewe in prayer to God
for the continuaunce and encreace
of your godlye zeale and
Chriſtian affection.
            
               Your honours moſte humble
to commaunde Robert
Fills.
            
         
         
            
            A table to finde the
principall pointes in this preſent booke.
            
               THE order of the offices inſtituted
by god for the gouernement
of his churche. fol. 1.
               To whō the inſtitutiō perteineth. 2.
               The forme of ye oth of ye miniſters. 3.
               The number, places, and tyme of the
ſermons. 6.
               The office of the preachers. 7.
               The office of the elders appointed by
the Seniorie in the conſiſtorie. 8.
               Of the deacons and their offices. 9.
               Of Sacramentes. 11.
               Of the Supper. 12.
               Of Mariages. 12. Of Buriyng. 13.
               Of the viſitation of the ſicke. 13.
               The orders which ought to be kepte
towardes lytle children. 14.
               Of the viſitation of ye priſoners. 15.
               The order towarde the aged. 15.
               The parſons whiche the officers or
Commiſſioners in cōſiſtorie ought to
admoniſhe. 16.
               The viſitation of ye miniſters in pariſhes
or villages perteynynge to the
citie of Geneua. 17.
               The maner of their viſitation. 18.
               
                  
Of the election of Seniours or lords
called Sendicques, and of the othe of
the lower counſell. 19.
               Of the election of ye ſmale coūſel. 21.
               The forme of their othe. 22.
               The election of the Treaſurer. 23.
               The election of the Secretaries. 23.
               The forme of their othe. 23.
               The counſell of ye two hundred. 24.
               The auditours of the accompts. 24.
               The forme of their othe. 24.
               The controler, the maiſter of the money,
&amp; the maiſter of the ordinaūce. 25
               Of the procurour generall. 25.
               The forme of his othe. 25.
               Of the Captaine generall. 26.
               Of perticulers. 26.
               Of Banderettes. 26.
               Of their Lieutenaunts. 26.
               Of Dizeners. 26.
               Of their othe. 26.
               Of ye geolyer &amp; forme of his oth. 27.
               Of the Saoultier. 27.
               Of the Haroldes. 27.
               Of the waiters. 28.
               Of the kepers of towers and the
Porters. 28.
               Of the Notaries. 28.
               
                  
The forme of their othe. 28.
               The office, charge, and authoritie of
the lordes Sendicques. 30.
               The office of the fyrſt in eſpecial. 31.
               The office of the thre other Sendicques,
that whiche two of them may
doe. 31.
               That whiche one of them alone may
doe. 32.
               Of matters criminalls 32.
               The office, charge, and dutye, of the
counſell. 33.
               For what cauſe thei ought to cal the
counſell. 35.
               The office of the Treaſurer. 35.
               The office of the Secretaries. 36.
               The office of the Captaines, Bande
retts, and Dizeners. 38.
               The Auditours of accompts. 39.
               The office of the Controler. 40.
               The office of the maiſter of the artillerie.
41.
               Of the office of the Procurour generall.
42.
               Of the office of the Saoultier. 44.
               Of the office of the Porters and kepers
of the towers. 45.
               The watches of the two ſteples. 46.
               
                  
The courte of the Senior lieutenant
and adiutors. 46.
               The forme of their othe. 48.
               The place of the Aſſiſtaunce. 48.
               Of the two Secretaries of the Lieutenauntes
courte. 48.
               The forme of their othe. 49.
               The office of the Lieutenaunte, and
the order of the courte. 49.
               Of ye penaltie of thē yt be abſent. 50.
               Of the ſummoning for appearaunce
in ciuill cauſes. 50.
               For default of appearaunce. 50.
               The ſummoning of ye witneſſes. 52.
               Of pleding. 52.
               Of the procedings and termes of delaye.
53.
               Of cauſes aboue a crowne. 53.
               In cauſes of exceptions. 54.
               Of termes appoynted to heare the
right. 55.
               Of the longeſt terme that the proceſſe
ought to endure. 55.
               Of the two Feries. 55.
               Of cauſes extraordinarie. 56
               Of relation of the Iudges in the proceding,
as in ſentence definitiue. 57.
               The cauſes excuſable. 57.
               
                  
The taxe of the reward of the Lieutenant
and his aſſiſtaunce. 57.
               The taxes for the Secretaries. 59.
               The taxes for the Sergeantes. 60.
               Howe the Lieutenaunt ought to gouerne
him ſelfe in matters of impriſonment.
60.
               The order which he ought to kepe in
proces criminall. 61.
               Of emolumentes and exactions of
ſeales, the vſaunce, &amp; gouernement,
and garde of the ſame. 62.
               The taxe &amp; emoluments which they
ought to take of the thre ſeales. 62.
               The ſeale to ſeale pupill goods. 66.
               Fyue proclamations conteynynge
moſt neceſſarie ordinaunces and ſtatutes.
67.
               The firſt proclamation. 67.
               The ſeconde proclamation. 69.
               The thirde proclamation. 74.
               The fourth proclamation. 76.
               The fyfte proclamation. 79.
               The valuation of their coyne. 87.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            Here folovveth the
ACTES AND STATVTES OF
the Citie of Geneua.
            
               IN the name of the moſt
mightie God, we Syndicques,
with the great and ſmale counſell of
Geneua, with oure people
aſſembled by the
ſoūde of trompett and the great bell,
folowing oure aūcient cuſtomes, hauing
conſidered yt it is a thinge worthy
of commendation aboue all other
that the doctrine of the holy goſpell
of oure lord god be conſerued well in
puritie, and ye chriſtian church mainteyned
accordingly, alſo that yougth
in tyme to come be well and faithfully
enſtructed, and ye hoſpitall ordered
in good eſtate for the ſuſtentacion of
the poore, the which cannot be excepte
there be eſtablished a certaine rule &amp;
manner to lyue, by the whiche euery
ſtate may vnderſtand the duety of his
office. For this cauſe it ſemed good
to vs that the ſpiritual gouernement
ſuch as god hath ſhewed vnto vs, and

inſtituted by his worde be brought in
to good forme, to haue place and to be
obſerued amonge vs, and we haue ordeyned
and eſtabliſhed to folowe and
kepe in oure towne and territorye, ye
eccleſiaſticall pollicy folowing, which
is taken oute of the goſpell of Ieſus
Chriſt.
            Firſt of all there are fower orders
of officers which oure lorde hath inſtytuted
for the gouernement of hys
churche, that is to ſaye paſtors, doctors,
elders, other wiſe named cōmiſſioners
for the Seniorie, and fourthly
Decons.
            If we will haue a churche well ordered,
and kept in ye purytie, we muſt
obſerue this forme of gouernement.
            As concerning paſtors whiche the
ſcripture nameth ſome times watche
men, and ſometyme miniſters, theyr
offices are to declare ye worde of god,
to teache, to admonyſhe, to exhorte,
to reproue as wel publikly as priuatly,
to miniſter Sacraments, &amp; to doe
brotherly correc
                  •
               yon with the elders
or Commiſſyoners.
            Nowe to the ende that nothinge be

done confuſedly in the churche, no mā
ought to thruſt him ſelfe into this office
withoute lawfull callyng: in the
which there are to be conſidered three
thinges, that is to ſaye, examinacion
whiche is principall, afterwarde, to
whom it apperteyneth to inſtitute ye
myniſters: thirdly, what Ceremonye
or maner of doinge is good to the induction
of them to their office.
            The examinacion conteyneth two
partes, the fyrſt is touching the doctrine,
that is to ſaye yf he which ſhalbe
appointed to the office haue good
knowledge in the holye ſcriptures,
and more if he be ſufficient and meete
to communicate it to ye people to their
edification.
            Alſo, to put away or eſchew all dangers,
that he whiche ſhalbe receyued
holde no euel opinions, it ſhalbe good
that he doe proteſt to receyue and reteyne
the doctryne approued in the
churche.
            To knowe if he be meete to teache,
they muſt procede by interrogatories
and to haue him treate of ſome parte
of the doctrine of oure lorde god.
            
               
The ſeconde parte is of lyfe: that is
to ſaye, if he haue good conditions, &amp;
if he haue alwaies gouerned him ſelfe
withoute reproche. The rule to procede
by is very well declared by S.
Paule, the whiche ought to be kept &amp;
obſerued.
            
               
                  ❧Here foloweth to whom it perteyneth to
inſtitute or appoint miniſters.
               IT ſhalbe good in this pointe to folowe
ye order of the auncient church
for as much as it is but a putting
in vſe of that whiche is declared vnto
vs in the ſcripture: that is, that the
miniſters firſt chuſe him which ought
to be put in office, geuing vnderſtanding
to the Seniorie, &amp; after preſent
him to the counſell, and if he be foūde
worthy, that the counſell receiue and
accepte him: and after hauing knowledge
of him (as they ſhal ſe expediēt)
geue him a teſtymony that he may be
brought forth, and finally preſented
to the people in the ſermon, to ye ende
he maye be receyued by the common
cōſent into ye companye of ye faithful.
               If he be founde vnworthye, and ſo
declared by lawfull proues, that then

they procede to a newe election and
choſe another.
               Concerning the maner of the induction,
bicauſe the ceremonies in times
paſt haue ben turned into manye ſuperſtitions
by reaſon of the infirmity
of the tyme, it ſhalbe neceſſarye that
one of the myniſters make declaration
and demonſtracion of the office, to
the which he is choſen, and after that
ye praiers be made for him, that ye lord
geue him grace well to diſcharge hys
offyce.
               When he ſhalbe choſen, it is neceſſarie
that he be ſworne before ye Seniorye
wyth ſuche an othe as ſhalbe
conuenient for a miniſter, as here foloweth.
            
            
               
                  ❧The maner and forme of the othe and
promyſe which the enangelicall myniſters
admitte and receyue in the cyttie
of Geneua, done before the Syndicques
and Counſell.
               
                  I Promyſe and ſweare that in ye miniſtery
to the which I am called, I
ſhall ſerue faythefully before God:
vſing his worde purely to edify thys
churche to the which I am bounde, &amp;

that I ſhall not abuſe his worde to
ſerue my carnall affectyon, to pleaſe
any man liuing, but that I ſhal vſe it
with a pure conſcience to ſerue to his
glorye and ye profit of hys people, to ye
which I am bounde.
               Alſo I promyſe and ſweare to kepe
the eccleſiaſticall ordinances which
are paſſed and ordayned by the ſmall
great, &amp; generall Counſells of this
Citie, as is geuen to me in charge,
to admonyſhe them which haue fayled,
to execute my dutie lawfully, not
geuing place to hatred, fauour vengeāe
cor other fleſhly deſire, &amp; in general
to doe yt which apperteyneth to a
good and faithfull miniſter.
               Thirdly I ſweare and promyſe to
kepe and maintayne the honour and
profyt of the Seniorye and the Citie,
to endeuoure my ſelfe wt all poſſybilitye
that the people be kept and conſerued
in good peace and vnity, vnder
the gouernemēt of the Seniorie, and
not to cōſent in any caſe to any thing
agaynſt the ſame, but to folowe my
ſayd vocation as wel in tyme of aduerſitie
as ī proſperity, be it peace, warre

peſtilence or other wiſe.
               Fynally I promiſe and ſwere to be
ſubiecte to the pollicye and Statutes
of this citye, myniſtring good example
of obedience to all other, yelding
my ſelfe for my part ſubiecte and obedient
to the lawes and magiſtrates
as much as my office doth beare, that
is to ſaye withoute preiudice to the
libertie which we ought to haue, and
teache according as god cōmaundeth
vs, and to doe all thinges whiche apperteine
to oure office. Alſo I promiſe
in ſuche ſorte to ſerue the Seniorye &amp;
the people, that I be therby ī no caſe
letted to render vnto god the ſeruice
which I owe to him in my vocatyon.
               Nowe euen as it is required dyligently
to examine the miniſters whē
they ſhalbe choſen, ſo it is neceſſarye
to haue good pollicye to holde &amp; kepe
them in their vocation: for the which
firſt it ſhalbe expedient that all the miniſters
gather them ſelues to gether
one certayne day in the weke, to conſerue
and kepe the puritye &amp; concorde
of doctrine, to haue conference of the
Scriptures, and that none exempte

them ſelues wtoute a lawfull excuſe:
yf anye be negligent, that he be admonniſhed.
               For thoſe which preache in the villadges
parteyning to the Seniorie, it
is neceſſarie that the myniſters of the
citie ſhal exhorte them to come as often
as maye be: and moreouer if they
be lacking one moneth together, the
ſame to be eſtemed to greate a negligence,
excepte it be by ſicknes or other
lawfull let.
               And if there happen to ſpring anye
difference in doctrine, ye miniſters ſhal
treate of it together to heare the matter.
After, yf that nede ſhall require,
they ſhal cal ye elders or cōmiſſioners
appointed by the Seniorie to helpe to
appeaſe the contention. Finallye, yf
they cannot come to anye amyable
concorde, by the obſtinacye of anye of
the partyes, let the cauſe be referred
to ye magiſtrates, to ſet order therin.
               For the auoiding of ſlaunderouſe
offences of lyuing, it ſhalbe nedefull
that there be a forme of correction vpon
the myniſters as ſhalbe declared
here after, to the which al they withoute

exception ſhall ſubmytte them
ſelues: which ſhalbe alſo the meanes
to cōſerue the miniſterie in reuerēce,
and that the worde of god be not by ye
euyll reporte of the myniſters diſhonored
or diſpiſed. For as correctiō is to
be done vpon him which hath fayled,
ſo it ſhall be nedefull to reproue the
ſlaunders and falſe reportes whyche
maye be iniuſtly made againſt Innocentes.
               But firſt it is to be noted yt there be
crimes which vtterly be intollerable
in a myniſter, and alſo there be vyces
which ſome what may be borne with
all, ſo that there be geuen brotherlye
admonicions.
               
                  The firſt be.
                  Hereſie.
                  Sciſme.
                  Rebellion againſt the eccleſiaſtylcal
order.
                  Manifeſt blaſphemye and puniſhable
by ciuile peine,
                  Simonie and al corruption of giftes.
                  Brybes to ocupie ye place of an other.
                  To forſake his churche withoute lawfull
cauſe and iuſt calling.
                  
                     
Falſehoode.
                  Periurie.
                  Whoredom.
                  Thefte.
                  Dronkennes.
                  Fighting worthye to be puniſhed by
the lawes.
                  Vſurye.
                  Plaies or Games forbidden by ye lawes
and which be offenſiue.
                  Dauncing and ſuch diſoluteneſſes.
                  Crimes importing euill infamie.
                  Crimes which deſerue in another to
be ſeperated from the churche.
               
               
                  The ſeconde.
                  Strange maner of handling the ſcriptures,
which may turne to offence.
                  Curioſitye to ſerch vaine queſtions.
                  Setting forth of any doctrine or maner
of doing not receued in ye churche.
                  Negligence in ſtuding, and principally
in reding the holy ſcriptures.
                  Negligence in reprouing their neighbours
vices to flatter them.
                  Negligence in doing all thinges belonging
to their office.
                  Scurrulitye.
                  Lieng.
                  Detraction.
                  
                     
Diſſolute in wordes,
                  Reprochefull wordes.
                  Raſhnes.
                  Euell deceites.
                  Auarice and to muche nygardnes.
                  Diſordinate angryneſſe.
                  Chiding and ſcoldinge.
                  Diſſollutneſſe vnſemely for a miniſter
both in apparell and geſture, and
other faſhions of lyuing.
               
               Concerning Crimes they ought in
no caſe to be borne with, if they be ciuyll
Crimes, that is to ſaye, yf they
oughte to be puniſhed by the lawes.
And if any of the myniſters doe faile,
then the Seniorye oughte to put to
their handes, and ouer and beſides the
ordinarie punyſhement with whiche
they be accuſtumed to puniſhe other
offēders, to take him, puniſhe him, &amp;
depoſe him, from his office.
               As touchinge other crimes of the
which the firſt inquiſicion perteineth
to the conſiſtorie eccleciaſticall, let the
commiſſioners or elders with ye miniſters
take hede therto: and if any be
conuicted let them make their reporte
to the counſell with their aduiſe and

Iudgement, ſo that ye laſt Iudgement
for the correction be alwaies reſerued
to the Seniorie.
               As concerning the offences whiche
ought to be corrected by ſimple admonicions,
let them therin procede according
to ye order of oure ſauiour chriſt,
ſo that the cauſe maie be ended in the
eccleſiaſticall Iudgement.
               To mainteine this diſcipline in his
eſtate, euery thre monethes let the miniſters
ſpecially enquiere yf there be
any thing to be talked of amōge them
ſelues, and remedye it accordinge to
reaſon.
            
            
               
                  ❧Of the number▪ place and, tyme of the
Sermons.
               VPon the Sondayes there ſhalbe
mornīg ſermons at the churches
of ſainct Peter and S. Gerueis,
alſo at y• houre accuſtumed, ſermons
throughe all the periſhes.
               At noone the catechiſme, that is to
ſay inſtructions for the ſmale childrē,
in thre churches, and at three of the
clocke lykewyſe Sermons in all the
churches.
               Vpon the weeke daies ouer and beſide

a ſermō ī euery periſhe, alſo ther
ſhalbe ſermons at ye heade churches
Mondaye, Wedinſdaye, and Fridaie
at fower of the clocke in the mornīg.
ſo that the ſermon maye be ended a
good ſpace before the ordinarie ſermō
be begon.
               If there be made any extraordinary
praier in tyme of neceſſitie, that the
order for the Sondaye be obſerued.
               To beare theſe and other burdens
of the miniſterie, it ſhalbe nedefull to
haue v. miniſters and iii. conductours
which ſhall alſo be miniſters, to ayde
and helpe according as nede ſhall require.
            
            
               
                  ❧Here foloweth the ſeconde order whiche
we call doctours.
               THe proper office of doctours is to
teache the faithefull with ſounde
doctrine, to the ende that the puritye
of ye goſpell be not corrupted by ignorance
or wicked opinions: neuertheles
according as thinges be dyſpoſed
in theſe dayes, we doe comprehende
them vnder this title, to be aides and
Inſtrumentes to conſerue ye doctrine
of god, ſo that the churche be not

deſolate for fault of paſtors and myniſters,
but to vſe a worde more intelligible,
we ſhall call them the order
of ſcholers.
               The next degree vnto the myniſters
and next conioyned to the gouernement
of the church, is reding of
diuinitie: which reding ſhalbe oute of
the newe or olde teſtament.
               But becauſe they cannot profytt in
ſuche leſſons excepte they be firſte inſtructed
in the tonges and humayne
ſcyences, alſo it is nedeful to raiſe vp
ſede for the time to come, to the ende
that the churche be not lefte deſtitute
to oure children, therfore it is nedful
to erecte A colledge to enſtructe children,
to prepare them aſwel to ye myniſterye
as to cyuill gouernement.
               For the firſt there muſt be a place
aſſigned aſwell for the lectures as for
the teaching of children and others
which will proffyt in learning, alſo
to haue a man learned and expert for
to dyſpoſe aſwell the houſe as the
lectours, which can him ſelfe teach &amp;
inſtructe others: and that there be vnder
his charge readers as wel ī tongs

as in Logicke yf it may be: alſo for
bachelars to teache yonge children, ye
which we wyll and ordaine to be don:
and that all thoſe which be there ſhal
be ſubiectes to the eccleſyaſtycall diſcipline,
as well as the miniſters.
               That there be no other ſchole in the
towne for children, but we will that
there be a ſchole a parte for mayden
children, as hath ben accuſtumed.
               That none ſhalbe receyued into
this office excepte he be approued by
the myniſters, and fyrſte let hym be
knowen to the Seniors, and then againe
be preſented to ye coūſell wyth
his wytneſſes, for feare of inconueniences.
And alwayes examinacions
oughte to be made before two of the
Seniors.
            
            
               Here foloweth the thirde order, whych
be elders otherwyſe called commiſſyoners
or deputes for the Seniors in the
conſiſtorie.
               THeir office is to take hede and to
watche of the demeanour and be
hauour of all and euery of ye people,
to admoniſhe louīgly thoſe which
they ſee fall or leade a diſſolute lyfe,

or yf it be nedeful to make ye reporte,
or to doe brotherly correctiō, and that
ſhalbe commonly done by ye company
that ſhalbe therto appointed.
               For the diſpoſytion and gouernement
of this church, it ſhalbe good to
chuſe two of the ſmale coūcel, fowre
of the councell of the three ſcore, and
ſyxe of the councell of the two hundred
men of honeſtie and of good life,
withoute reprofe, and voyde of all ſuſpection,
and aboue all hauing ye feare
of god, learning, and ſpirituall wyſedome:
and ſo they ought alwayes to
be choſen that there be of them in euery
quarter of the towne, that their
eyes maye be ouer all that is ordeined
or done.
               Likewiſe we haue determined that
the maner of the election be on thys
wiſe: that the ſmale councel ſhall deliberate
to name the moſt mete that cā
be founde, and the moſte ſufficient,
and ſo to doe, it is neceſſarye to call
the myniſters to communicate with
them, and after to preſēt them which
they haue named to the councel of the
two hundred: which approuing them

if they be founde worthy, a perticuler
othe to be made in forme folowing.
            
            
               The forme of the othe.
               I Promyſe and ſweare folowing
the charge that is geuen to me,
to hinder all Idolatries, blaſphemies,
diſſolutions and other thinges
againſt the honour of god and the reformacion
of the goſpel, and to admoniſhe
thoſe to whom it apperteineth
as occaſion ſhalbe geuen me.
               Item, when I ſhall knowe anye
thinges worthy to be brought before
the conſiſtorie, that I ſhal doe my duty
faithfully without fauour or hate,
onely to that ende that the towne be
maynteyned in good order and in the
feare of god.
               Item as touching all thinges concerning
the office to be diſcharged wt
a good conſcyence, to obſerue the ordynaunces
which be decreed by the
ſmale, great, and generall councell of
Geneua.
               IN the ende of the yere after they
haue choſen ye coūcel, theſe mē ſhal
be preſēted to ye Seniorie to knowe
if they be worthy to continue in their

office or to be chaūged for as much as
it is not expedient that they be chaū
                  ged
withoute a cauſe.
            
            
               
                  ❧The fourth order of the eccleſiaſticall
gouernement called deacons.
               THere hath ben alwayes two ſō
                  drye
kindes or ſortes of officers
in the auncient churche, ye one
were deputes to receyue, to delyuer,
and conſerue the goods of the poore,
as well dayly Almeſes, as poſſeſſions
Stipends, and penſions.
               The other to fede and ouerſee the
ſicke, and to miniſter the portion of ye
poore. The which cuſtume we doe obſerue
yet to this preſent, for we haue
procuratours and maiſters of the hoſpitall:
and to auoyde confuſion, one of
the procurators of the hoſpitall ſhalbe
receyuer of al the goods of ye ſame,
the which ſhal haue ſufficient wages
the better to execute his office.
               Alſo the number of the fower procuratours
ſhall continue as hath ben
ſayd. Wherof one to haue the charge
to the ende that the prouiſions maye
be the better made in tyme conuenyent.
               
                  
Alſo that thoſe which doe ſhewe any
charitie vpon the poore, be the more
aſſerteyned that the goods ſhalbe no
otherwyſe employed but according to
their intention: and if the reuenues
or gyftes be not ſuffycient and that
there happen any extraordinarie neceſſitie,
then the Seniorie ſhall determine
to furniſhe according as neceſſitie
ſhall requyre.
               Concerning the election of the procuratours
and maiſters of hoſpitalles,
it ſhalbe lyke ye order of the elders
or commiſſyoners in the conſiſtorye:
and in choſing them to folowe ye rule
of Saincte Paule touchinge deacons
in the fyrſt to Tymothie the thyrde
chapter, &amp; to Titus the fyrſt chapter.
               Touching the office and aucthoritie
of procuratours, we ſhall kepe ye
articles whiche be all redye by vs ordeyned
but ſpecially in things vrgent
&amp; where there ſhalbe daunger to differre
the tyme, but when there is no
great dyfficultie nor matters of great
charge, that then they be not conſtrained
to aſſemble daylye, but that one
or two may ordayne in the abſence of

the other that which ſhalbe reaſonable.
               Item it ſhalbe neceſſarye to take diligent
heede that the common hoſpitall
be well preſerued and meete to receyue
the ſicke, alſo for aged perſons
which cannot worke, men or womē,
for wydowes, children, orf
                     •
                  lyns, and
the poore, alwayes ye ſicke to be kepte
and ſeperated a part in a ſeuerall lodging
from the other.
               Item y• Almeſes for ye poore which
be dyſtributed throughoute ye towne,
ſhalbe brought to the hoſpitall according
as the procuratours ſhall determyne.
               Item that beſides the hoſpital it is
neceſſarye that ſtraungers and waye
faring men be relyeued, and holpē: &amp;
that therebe an hoſpitall aparte for
them as ſhalbe conuenient, and according
to the eſpecially order and rule of
charitye, and therefore we ordeyne &amp;
determine that there ſhalbe chambers
appointed to receyue ſuche as ſhalbe
directed thether by the procuratours,
and that ſuche ſhalbe receyued accordingly.
               
                  
Item aboue all this it be remembred,
that the famylies of the hoſpitallours
be honeſtly gouerned according
to the rule of gods worde, conſideryng
that they haue ye gouernaūce
of the houſe of god.
               Alſo that the miniſters and ye commiſſyoners
or elders wyth one of the
Sendiques ſhall of their parte be diligent
to enquire if in the aforeſayde
adminiſtracion for the poore, there be
anye lacke or neceſſitie, to the ende to
deſire and admoniſhe the Seniorie to
ſet order, &amp; ſo to doe that euery thre
monethes ſome of their cōpagnions
with the procuratours ſhall make
viſitacion in ye hoſpital to knowe if al
things be well ruled.
               It is neceſſarye both for the poore
of the hoſpital and other of the towne
whiche haue not wherwyth to helpe
them ſelues, that there be a Phiſiſion
and a ſurgian meete for ye ſame, mainteyned
by the wages of the towne,
yet neuertheles they maye practyſe
throughe the towne, and notwtstanding
to be bounde to haue care ouer ye
hoſpital, and to viſet other that haue

neede.
               Concerninge the peſtilence in the
hoſpitall, ye ſuche be ſeperated a part,
and principally if it happen that the
towne be ſcourged of god by any ſuch
rod. Moreouer to eſchue begging in ye
towne which is contrary to all good
pollicye, it is neceſſarye and alſo we
doe ordeine that the Seniori ſhall appoynte
certeyne of theyr officers at
theyr comminge oute of the churches
from the ſermons, to take away and
auoide from the place before the ſame
churches, thoſe that be loyterors or
thoſe that be diſſemblers &amp; obſtinate
beggers, and that they be brought before
one of the lordes Sendiques, and
lykewyſe at all other tymes that the
dyſenars be dyligent and take hede ye
this lawe for beggers be well obſerued
and kepte.They vſe but one ſuertye be it man or woman childe be ſide the father being preſent.
               
            
            
               
                  ❧Of ſacramentes.
               THat baptiſme be not myniſtered
but incontinent after the ſermon
and onely myniſtred by the miniſters
or coadiutours: and that they doe
regiſter the names of the children wt
their parents: and if their be founde

anye baſterde, the iuſtice to be aduertiſed
therof, and therin to procede according
to reaſon.
               Item that no ſtraunger be receiued
as godfather, but thoſe that be faithfull
people and of 
                     •
                  ure communion,
conſydering that others be not meete
to make promyſe vnto the churche to
inſtructe the infantes as it is requyred.
            
            
               Of the ſupper.
               FOr as muche as the ſupper hath
bene inſtituted by our Sauiour
Ieſus Chriſt to be frequented and
vſed and alſo it hath bene obſerued in
the primatiue chriſten churche, vntyl
ſuche time as the deuill turned al vpſyde
downe, ſetting vp ye Maſſe in ſted
therof whiche faulte ought to be corrected,
and alſo the rare celebratinge
therof we haue determyned and ordeined
yt it ſhalbe miniſtred fower times
in the yere that is to ſaye. At Chriſtmas,
Eaſter, Penticoſte, and the
firſt Sondaye in the monethe of September.
               Item that the myniſters diſtribute
the breade in good order wt reuerence

and that none other geue the cuppe
but onely the Commiſſioners or Deacons
with the myniſters: and for this
cauſe that there be no great number
of cuppes and veſſells.
               Item that the table be nere vnto ye
pulpytt, to the ende that the miniſter
maye more commodiouſly and playnly
declare the vſe therof nere vnto the
table.
               Item that it be not celebrated but
in the churche, excepte it be in greate
neceſſytie.
               Item that the Sondaye before the
celebracion of the ſayd ſupper, there
be declaration made, to the ende that
no chylde come before he haue made
profeſſion of his faythe, according as
ſhalbe declared in ye Catechiſme, and
alſo to exhorte all ſtraungers &amp; newe
commers, to come fyrſte and preſent
them ſelues vnto the churche, to be
inſtructed yf nede ſhalbe, and conſequently
that none approcheto his cō
                  dempnacion.the banes muſt be pronoū
                     ced 
                        〈◊〉
                      ſondaies ſolemnely.
               
            
            
               
                  ❧Of Mariage.
               AFter the declaration of the banes
accuſtomed, the Mariages to be

made when the party ſhall require it,
as well on the ſondaye as working
dayes, ſo that it be done at the beginning
of the ſermon.
               And as concerning the abſtynence
of the ſame, it ſhalbe good that onely
vpon the day of the celebration of the
ſupper, they abſteyne for the honour
of the ſame ſacrament.
               Item it ſhalbe good to bring in and
vſe eccleſiaſticall ſonges or pſalmes,
ye better to ſtirre ye people vnto praier
and praiſe god.
               Item firſt they ſhall teache their litle
children, and ſo in the proces of
time all the church may folowe.
               Touching debate in cauſes matrimonialls,
for that it is not onelye a
ſpirituall cauſe, but medled with the
ciuile order, the ſame to remayne to
the Seniorie: neuertheles we are determyned
to leaue to the conſiſtorye
the charge to heare the partyes, and
ſo to make reporte of ther aduyſe vnto
the counſell, therin to geue Iudgement,
ſo that good ordinances may be
from henceforthe made and folowed
accordingly.
            
            
               
               Of burying.
               ITem that they doe burie honeſtly
the deade in the place appointed.
And as concerning ye traine
or company, we leaue it to ye diſcreſſiō
of euery one.
               Item we haue moreouer ordeyned
and determyned that the porters appoynted
to bury, eſhalbe ſworne vnto
the Seniorye to put awaye all ſuperſticions
that are contrary to ye worde
of god, &amp; not beare them by nighte,
and alſo if anye be deade ſodeinly, to
make reporte therof, to the ende to auoide
al inconueniencyes which may
folowe therof.
               Item that after their death not to
beare them to theyr burying before
twelue howers, nor to kepe them aboue
fower and twenty howers.
            
            
               Of the viſitacyon of the ſicke.
               BEcause that many be negligent to
comforte them ſelues in god by his
worde when they be in extremity
of ſickenes, wherof it happeneth oftē
tymes that many dye without admonicion
or doctrine, the whiche at that
tyme is moſt nedefull of all times, for

this cauſe we haue ordeyned and determyned
that none ſhall tarye three
dayes in their bedde or 
                     •
                  icke, but that
it be made knowen to the myniſters,
and that euery one ſhalbe aduertiſed
to call ye myniſters, whenſoeuer they
wyl haue them at a cōuenient houer,
they not to with drawe them ſelues
frō their office in ye whiche they ſerue
in common to the churche: and to put
awaye all excuſes, we haue determined
that the ſame ſhalbe publiſhed, &amp;
moreouer to be geuen commaundement
by proclamacion yt the parents
frendes and kepers ſhal not tarie vntyll
the perſon be redye to yelde vp ye
ſpirite, for in ſuch extremitie the consolacion
ſerueth to ſmale purpoſe for
the moſt part.
            
            
               The order which ought to be kept for litell
children.
               THat all cytezens and inhabitauntes
ſhall bring or ſende their children
on the ſondaye at twelue of
the clocke, to the Cathechiſme, which
hath bene ſpoken of here before.
               Item there ſhalbe a certaine forme
or maner compoſed in the which they

ſhalbe inſtructed, and they ſhalbe demanded
and appoſed in the ſame doctryne
whyche they haue before learned,
to ſee if they haue wel vnderſtanded
and kept it.
               When a childe ſhalbe ſufficiently
inſtructed and haue paſſed his cathechiſme,
then he ſhall recite ſolempnely
the ſūme of that whyche is therin
conteyned, and alſo ſhall make as it
weare a confeſſion of his chriſtianity
in the preſence of the churche.
               Item before this be done, that no
childe be ſuffered to receyue the ſupper
of the lorde, and that the parents
be aduertyſed not to brynge them before
that time: for it is a thinge moſt
perelous as well for the chyldren as
the parents, to enter into it withoute
good and ſufficient inſtruction, for yt
which it is neceſſari to vſe this order.
               To ye ende that there be no defaute,
it is ordeined that the children which
goe to ſchole ſhall come to gether before
none, &amp; yt the maiſters doe bryng
them in good order in euery paryſhe.
               The others, that their parents doe
bringe or ſend them.
               
                  
And to the ende to auoyde all confuſyon,
they ſhall obſerue as much
as may be, the diſtinctiō of the pariſhes
in ye caſe as hath ben ſaid before
of ye ſacramēts.
               Item that thoſe whyche ſhalbe by
force conſtrayned to come, ſhalbe called
before the Seniors, elders, or cō
                  myſſioners,
and yf they wyll not be
perſuaded by good counſell, ye reporte
ſhalbe made to the Seniorye. Alſo to
take hede to ſuche whether they doe
their duety or not, and that the commyſſioners
haue an eye vnto them to
take order accordingly.
            
            
               Of the viſitacion of the priſoners.
               MOreouer we haue ordeyned a
certeyne day in the weeke, in
the whyche ſhalbe made certeyne
conſolacions to the priſoners,
for to admoniſhe and exhorte them: &amp;
that there be one of the Seniors of ye
counſell deputed to be there aſſiſtent,
to the ende there be no fraude committed,
and if there be anye appointed to
dye by the determynacion of the coū
                  ſell,
it ſhalbe neceſſarye to call ſome
certayne mynyſter to comforte the

perſon, as nede ſhall require, for whē
they tarye vntyll ſuche tyme as they
leade them to the death, they be often
tymes ſo occupied with horrour, that
they be not apte to receyue or vnderſtand
anye conſolacion, and this daye
is ordeined the ſatterday after diner.
            
            
               
                  ❧Of the order which ought to be kepte
towardes the growen perſons for to
obſerue good order in the churche.
               THe commiſſyoners aforeſayd ſhall
gather them ſelues together once
a weeke with the myniſters, whiche
ſhalbe on the thurſdaye, to ſee if there
be any diſorder in the churche, and to
talke together for the remedye therof
whē &amp; how as ſhalbe moſt couenient.
               Becauſe they haue no auctoritie
or Iuriſdiction to compell or to conſtrayne
anie, we haue aduiſed to geue
them one of oure offycers to call any
of thoſe perſons before theim vnto
whom they wyll geue admonycion.
If anye by contempte refuſe to appeare,
theyr offyce ſhalbe to aduertiſe
the counſell therof, to the ende to
geue order therin.
            
            
               
               
                  ❧Here foloweth the perſons whom the
elders or commyſſyoners oughte to
admonyſhe, and howe they oughte
to procede.
               IF there be anye whych teacheth
ſtraūge or falſe opinions agaynſt ye
doctrine receyued, that he be called
to conferre with them. And if he be cō
                  formable
they ſhall ſuffer hym to departe
withoute defame or ſlaunder, &amp;
if he be obſtinate, yet they ſhall admonyſhe
him certayne tymes vntill they
ſee that greter ſeueriite be nedefull:
and then to forbid him the communiō
letting it be knowen to ye magiſtrate.
               If anie be negligent in comming to
churche, ſo that there be perceyued in
him a notable contempte of the communion
of the faithful, or if ani ſhewe
hym ſelfe a contemner of the order
eccleſiaſticall, that they admoniſhe
him. And yf he render him ſelfe obedient,
yt they ſende him awaye gently.
But yf he doe perſeuer from euell
to worſe, after they haue aduertyſed
hym three tymes, that then they ſhal
ſeperate him from the churche and declare
him to the Seniorye.
               
                  
As concerning the lyues &amp; the correction
of their faultes whyche ſhall
happen, it is neceſſarye to procede accordinge
to the order whyche Chriſt
commaunded.
               That is to ſaye for ſecreate fautes
they ſhall reproue ſecreatly. Alſo that
none bring his neighbour before the
churche for to accuſe him of any faute
the which is not notoriouſe or ſlaunderouſe,
excepte he fynde hym ſtubborne
and contempteouſe.
               Moreouer thoſe yt be contempners
of particuler admonytyons of their
neyghbours, ſhalbe warned by the
churche, and if they wyll in no waies
come to reformaciō nor acknowledge
their faute when they ſhalbe conuinced,
that then they commaunde them
to abſteyne from the communion vntill
the time they be better diſpoſed.
               As concerning notorious and publicke
offences, the churche may in no
caſe wincke at thē or paſſe them ouer,
but if they be fautes whiche deſerue
onely admonityon, the office of the
Commyſſyoners or elders ſhalbe to
call them before them wc be culpable,

exhortinge them amiablie that they
may amende: and if they ſee amendement,
no further to moleſte them, but
if they perſeuer further in their euel,
againe to be admoniſhed: &amp; at length
if they profyte not, then to denounce
them as contempners of god, and ſo
to abſteyne from the communion vntyll
they ſee in them a change of lyfe.
               As concerning crimes whiche deſerue
not onelye declaracion and aduertiſemēt
by wordes but correction
with chaſtiſement: yf anye be faulen,
according as ye caſe ſhall require, they
ſhall denounce that he abſteyne from
the communion for a certayne tyme,
humbling him ſelfe before god, &amp; better
to knowe his faulte.
               If anye by contumacye or rebellion
wil preſume or preace in contrarie
to that is commaunded, and for bydden
him, the office of ye myniſter ſhalbe
to put him backe, for it is not lawfull
to receyue ſuch a one to the communion:
and neuertheles that it be ſo
moderated that there appeare no rigoure,
by the which any perſon ſhulde
be greued or offended, namely ſuche

corrections be but medicines to bring
the ſinners vnto god.
               Item that all this be done in ſuche
ſorte that the myniſters take not vpon
them anye Ciuil Iuriſdiction, and
that this conſiſtorie be in no caſe any
derogaciō to the auctoritie of the Seniorie,
nor to ordinarye Iuſtice: but yt
the Ciuill power continue in his full
efficacye, and namely where it ſhalbe
nede of puniſhement or compulciō of
the parties, but the miniſters wyth ye
conſiſtorie hauing hearde the parties
and declared with ſuche admonitiōs,
as ſhalbe nedeful, then to iudge therī
according to ye weightineſſe of ye caſe.
               Item that this pollicye be not onelie
for ye towne, but alſo for ye villages
perteyning to the Seniorie.
            
            
               
                  ❧Order for the viſitacion of the myniſters
and paryſhes parteyning to
Geneua
               FYrſt of all to conſerue vnitie &amp;
good pollicye eſpecially in doctrine
throughe the whole body
of the churche of Geneua, aſwel in the
towne as ye villages belonging therto,
the magiſtrates ſhall choſe two of

the councell, and likewiſe the miniſters
ſhall choſe two of the congregacion,
which ſhall haue the charge to
goe and enquire in euery pariſhe once
in the yere if ye miniſter haue ſet forth
anye newe doctrine repugnant to the
puritye of the goſpell.
               Secondlye they ſhall enquire if the
miniſter hath preached to edificacion,
or if he vſe anie ſlaunderouſe maner
of liuing, if he be not able to teache ye
people, or if he be obſcure, or vſe ſuperfluoꝰ
queſtions, or be ouer rigorouſe
in life and doctrine.
               Thirdly to exhorte the people to
haunte the ſermons diligentlye, to
heare them, and doe there after, and
lyue chriſtianly alſo to declare what
is the office of a miniſter, that he may
be inſtructed the better to ſerue.
               Fourthly to knowe if the miniſter
be dilligent both to preache and viſite
the ſicke, and to miniſter perticulerly
to thoſe which haue nede, and to ſtaye
that nothing be done cōtrarie to gods
glorye: alſo if he leade an honeſt lyfe
ſhewing it by his good example, if he
vſe anye dyſſolutneſſe or lyghtnes

either in him ſelf or in his houſholde,
if he be diſdainful or agree well with
his paryſhners.
            
            
               ¶The maner of the viſitacion.
               THat the miniſter beinge appointed
to thys offyce after he hath
preached and admoniſhed the people
as is aforeſaide, ſhall enquire of ye
wardes and procurators of ye paryſhe
both concerning the doctrine, and life
of the miniſter, and likewiſe concerning
his diligence and maner of teaching,
deſiring them in the name of
god not to ſuffer nor diſſemble anye
thinge which may hinder the honour
of god, the aduancement of his worde,
or the welth of the commons.
               Item according as he hath founde,
yt he make reporte to ye cōgregaciō, to
the ende that yf there be anye faute
which deſerueth no greater correction
then by wordes, he ſhalbe admoniſhed
according to the cuſtume.
               Item if he haue offended more greuouſly
then ought to be ſuffered, let
them procede according to the forme
of ye articls afore mēſioned, yt is to ſay,
the foreſaid fower deputes ſhal make

the reporte vnto the Seniorie, therin
to procede according to reaſon.
               Item viſitacion ſhall not importe
anye determinacion of cauſes or kind
of Iuriſdiction, but ſhalbe onely a remedie
to auoyde all offences. And aboue
all, ye miniſters ſhal not ſwarue
from their duety nor be corrupted.
               Item this ſhall in no caſe be anye
let to the courſe of Ciuill Iuſtice, nor
to exempt the miniſters from ye common
ſubiection: but yt they aunſwere
in cyuyll cauſes as others doe before
the ordynarye Iuſtyce. And alſo for
crimes not to ſpare them but to punyſhe
them when they haue offended
and in ſume, that their ſtate may cō
                  tynue
as it is at this preſent.
               This hath ben the order in the primitiue
church in ye time of ye Apoſtles,
and at thys daye is obſerued in the
churches well reformed, according to
the pure doctrine of the goſpell.
            
            
               
                  ❧Ordinances concerning election of offices
and officers, and firſt of the election
of the lordes Sendicques.
               EVery yere the tewſdaye before the
ſondaye after candlemas daye, the

counſell ſhalbe holden expreſſely to
choſe the Sendicques: and before they
begyn, the firſt Sendicque ſhal make
ſome good exhortacion, exhorting thē
to choſe men of good conſcience, regarding
ye honour of god, louīg equetie
and truth, and the profyte of the
towne, mē of a good life &amp; good name.
               Moreouer they ſhall make theyr
praiers vnto god,They begin with praier in al their election &amp; counſells. and after that euery
counſellour ſhalbe ſworne to choſe
thoſe which they ſhal thīke to be moſt
meete &amp; ſufficient in forme folowing.
            
            
               ¶The othe of the ſmale counſell.
               WE promiſe and ſwere before god
betwene the handes of the Seniory,
to choſe and name into the
office of Sendiques, thoſe which we
knowe to be meete and ſufficient, for
the maintenance of the honour of god
and the chriſtiā religiō, in this towne
to guide &amp; gouerne the people in good
order and pollicye, to conſerue the liberties
of the towne, and in choſinge
them we ſhall haue oure reſpecte to ye
publicke welth, and not to particuler
affectiōs, neither for fauour nor hate,
as god is oure wytnes of thys promyſe,

and ſhalbe Iudge therin yf we
doe the contrarye.
               After that done, euery one by order
ſhall name foure cittezens before the
Sendiques, and ye Secretaires ſhalbe
there preſent to wryte thoſe that
ſhalbe named.
               The frydaye folowinge they ſhall
holde the counſell of the two hūdred,
and after exhortaciō &amp; praier made,
the forme of their othe ſhalbe recyted
all preſently holding vp their hands.
               Alſo they ſhal declare eight of thoſe
whych haue bene named in the election
of the ſmale counſell, that is to
ſaye thoſe which had the moſt voices,
and vpon the ſame let them make the
election of eyghte, or of the number
which haue bene propoſed, or of other
if it ſhall ſeme good, nameli that they
be all citezens, in ſuche maner that ye
election of the ſmale counſell, be as an
aduertiſment withoute preiudice to
the libertie of the two hundred.
               The ſondaye folowing the generall
counſell ſhalbe aſſembled, &amp; there
they ſhall pronounce vnto the people
the election made by the two hundred

ſo that oute of eight which ſhalbe preſented
to the people, they ſhall choſe
foure, if ſo be yt they ſhal like thē: but
alwayes when it ſhall ſeme good vnto
them they ſhall haue lybertie to refuſe
as well all as any party.
               And yf it happen that oute of that
preſent nūber their ſhall not be foūde
foure whom the people ſhall like, that
is to ſaye by the moſte voices, yt then
they procede to a newe election, for
the number which hath bene refuſed:
firſt by the ſmale counſell, and afterwarde
by the two hundred, ſo that
none be receyued but ſuche as ſhalbe
approued by the people.
               Item this order ſhalbe obſerued to
take two to ye lower parte of ye towne
and two of the vpper.
               This election made and confyrmed
by the people, the foure newe elected
ſhall come into the towne houſe to
make their othe betwine the hands of
the foure aūcientes, &amp; ſo be put in poſſeſſion
of their office.
            
            
               ¶The forme of their othe.
               VVE promyſe and ſwere to acquite
vs faythefully in the duetye of

oure offyce, and fyrſte to maynteyne
and defende as muche as in vs lyeth
the lybertyes and ryghtes of the
towne, well and trulye to miniſter y•
which we ſhall haue in oure handes,
to execute good and right Iuſtice, rendring
to euery man that whiche ſhall
apperteine to him, ſuſteyning ye good
and punyſhinge the euill, wythoute
fauour or hate, moreouer we promiſe
to doe and obſerue that which is conteined
in the office of the counſellors,
god bearing vs witnes in al ye ſame to
punnyſhe vs yf we doe the contrarye.
               Touchinge the place for to knowe
who ſhalbe the firſt or ſecond, if thoſe
which they choſe haue bene before in
the office, let them ſee who hath ben
the fyrſte, and let hym goe before the
other, and ſo euery one conſequently
and after his order.
               If they haue taken anye whyche
haue not bene before in offyce, then
to ſee howe they were in the counſell
before the other, and accordynge to
their aūcienty they ſhalbe placed: by
the counſel, we vnderſtand as well y•
                  
threaſorers and ſecretaries as coū
                  ſellers,
and he which hath ended his
yere ſhall not be choſen vntyl he haue
reſted three yere.
               If it happen that anye of the Sendicques
die during his office, and that
there reſte yet foure monethe of hys
tyme, let there be another choſen as
ſone as maye be: but yf the tyme be
ſhorter, to let the yere paſſe withoute
ſubſtituting of any other.
            
            
               ¶The election of the petye or ſmale counſell.
               THe mondaie folowing, the fower
newe elected Sendiques with the
olde, and the threaſorer, ſhall aſſemble
together with the two hundred,
and after they haue made exhortacion
and praier, and the othe, they
ſhall recite the rowle of the yere paſt:
and whom they wil haue to continue
in their office: the other to be put of.
Neuertheles ye fower auncient Sendiques
ſhall continue withoute controuerſye,
excepte they haue committed
faultes worthy of reprehenſion in
the time of their gouernement.
               If that anye be put of by the moſte
voices, there ſhalbe no other put in

their places ſodenly, but the ſmale
counſell whyche ſhalbe choſen, ſhall
name in number double, yt is to ſay
two for one, to take which ſhall ſeme
good to thē, or to choſe by their iudgemēt,
as hath ben ſaid of ye Sēdicques.
               If it happen that anye counſellour
dye, there ſhall none ſuccede hym in
place vntyll the next yere, excepte it
be by peſtilence, or by other inconueniences,
yt ye nūber be ſo ſore diminiſhed
yt the coūſell ſhalbe vnfurniſhed.
               The election done, all ſhall come
and make their othe before they ſet
downe, principallye the newe elected
as the other hath done before.
            
            
               ¶The forme of their othe.
               VVE promiſe and ſweare faythfully
to applie and to doe all y• perteyneth
to oure office, and firſte
of al to doe oure diligence to conſerue
and maintayne the welth honour and
profite of the towne, and to come together
as often and as many tymes
as nede ſhalbe, to giue good and faithfull
counſell touchynge that whyche
ſhalbe required of vs.
               Item to aduertiſe thoſe to whom it
ſhall aperteine, of al yt we ſhal thinke

to be to the profyte of the towne.
               Item to kepe ſecret all that which
hath bene ſayd and determined in the
counſell, excepte it be a publike matter
which ought to be publiſhed.
               Item in no caſe to be preiudiciouſe
vnto the honour or profite of ye towne
for fauoure, or amytie, or hate, or any
other carnall conſyderacyon, whatſoeuer
it be.
               Item not to be moued with bribes
or anye ſuche practyſe whatſoeuer it
be, from Iuſtice, or rightly to doe our
duetie, but contrarily to breake &amp; let
with al oure power ſuch enterpriſes.
               Item not to take preſents or bribes
for fauour of anye, in that which concerneth
oure office, nor in generall,
all that maye be preſented vnto vs in
the reſpecte of oure eſtate, for to make
vs decline frō the fidelitie whiche we
owe to ye towne, &amp; the right which we
be bounde to render to all.
               Item in al cauſes yt which we ſhalbe
required of, to pronounce with all
right &amp; equitie that which ſhall ſeme
good vnto vs, wtoute fraud or hate to
ani of ye parties, &amp; aboue al to procure

that the chriſtian religion be puerlye
obſerued, and god honoured &amp; ſerued
as well in the towne as in y• teritoris
of the ſame, god being witnes vnto vs
in al theſe promiſes to be Iudge therin
if we doe the contrarie.
               Touching the appointement of all
their places, y• foure aūcient Sendicques
ſhalbe the firſt, and ſo orderly ye
other according to ye time y• they haue
bene counſellers, or in higher offices.
            
            
               The election of the Treaſorer.
               ITem from thre yere, to thre yere, he
ſhalbe choſen with the Sendicques
in like order and faſſion, moreouer
when he ſhalbe choſen that he make
like othe wt ye counſellers, adioyning
therto this promiſe: to miniſter faithfully
to the profyte of the towne, the
common monye which ſhalbe delyuered
into his handes, and in general to
procure for the common welth as his
owne proper, as wel in recouering as
in keping and diſtributing.
            
            
               ¶The election of the Secretaries.
               ITem their ſhalbe two Secreataries
the one ſuperior &amp; the other
inferior, whoſe office ſhalbe

for no prefixed terme, but euery yere
when the Sendicques ſhalbe elected,
the counſell ſhal conſider if it be good
that thei continue in their office. And
if it ſhall ſeme good vnto them vpon
good conſyderacion, to put them of, y•
then they place other in their ſteade,
referringe it alwayes to the Iudgement
of the two hundred, the whiche
maye doe as ſemeth good vnto them:
&amp; that there be ouerſeing or ſuruieng
euery yere ouer this office, to make election
whan nede ſhall require.
            
            
               The forme of their othe.
               WE promyſe and ſwere to put in
writing faithfully and diligently
al that ſhalbe nedeful as oure
office ſhal require, and alſo to trauail
that by oure defaulte or negligence
there come no damage neyther to the
towne nor to the people.
               Item not to reueale anye of ye Seacreates
of ye counſel, nor declare them
to any perſon excepte it be by ye ordynarie
cōmaundement of the counſell.
               Item to make expedicion in al that
ſhalbe committed to oure charge, as
well for the towne as for priuate parties,

and in generall to obſerue with
a good conſcience al y• apperteineth to
the duety of oure offices.
            
            
               ¶Of the counſell of the two hundred.
               ITem the ſmale counſell ſhal the
next day after ye election, peruſe
the roule of the yere paſt, to the
ende to choſe the counſell of thre ſcore
and conſequently the two hundred,
continuinge thoſe whiche they ſhall
thinke to be mete, putting of thoſe
which ſhall ſeme good to be put of,
placing other in their ſteade, to fulfill
the number: moreouer to commaunde
to ſwere or renewe their othe, y• forme
therof ſhalbe the ſame which they of
the ſmale councell doe make.
            
            
               ¶For the auditours of the accomptes.
               ITem that euery yere the pety coū
                  ſel
ſhal choſe foure, wherof one ſhalbe
one of the Sendicques for to cō
                  tynue
(if it ſhal ſeme good vnto them)
of thoſe whiche were the yere before,
or others: &amp; that done they ſhall make
their reporte to the counſell of ye two
hundred, the which haue ſuche lybertie
to ratifie them or put them of as
hath bene ſaide.
            
            
               
               ¶The forme of their othe.
               VVE promyſe and ſwere to doe in
oure office that which apperteineth
to good and faithful procurers
of the publyke welthe, and to
haue ſuch care therof as of oure owne
propre famylye.
               And principally in hearing the accomptes
which ſhalbe made vnto vs,
neither to ouer paſſe nor alowe anye
thinge, but that which ſemeth vnto
vs iuſt and reaſonable.
               Item to conſerue and kepe all the
rightes and priuileges of the towne
well and faithfully▪ bringing all into
good order as ſhalbe nedefull.
               Item if their be anye thinge amiſſe
or oute of the waie, to make good and
diligent inquiſiſion to brynge agayne
and recouer it.
               Item that all which ſhalbe perteyninge
to the towne be it rent, preſt,
fines, confiſcation, or other thinges
whatſoeuer they be, to make good &amp;
diligent inquiſition and purſute wt
                  oute
reſpecte of perſon.
               Finally to doe oure diligence that
nothinge periſhe or be alienated in

maner of wyſe by oure faulte negligence
or diſſymulacion.
            
            
               
                  ❧For the Controuler, the maiſter of the
monye, the keper of the towne houſe
called the Saoulter and the maiſter
of the ordinance.
               Item that euery three yere after the
counſel is choſen, the petie counſel
ſhall choſe theſe officers alwayes
vpō this condicion y• y• election ſhalbe
referred to the two hundred, to be ratified
by them: and yf they doe not approue
them, the petye counſell ſhall
choſe newe, neuertheles the olde may
continue if they ſhal ſee it good.
               Touching the forme of their othe
it ſhalbe ſufficient that it be general,
to procure the welthe and honour of ye
towne as muche as lyeth in their power,
and with all paine and diligence
wtout fraude or gile to exercyſe their
office, as wel towardes euery perticular
man as y• whole publicke ſtate.
            
            
               
                  ❧For the procurer generall.
               ITem that this ſhalbe a yerely office
for as muche as it ſhalbe lawefull
to continue him which hath ſerued

if it ſhall ſeme good, &amp; namely it ſhalbe
moſt expedient yf he be a mā meete
and one that ſerueth in his office diligently,
moreouer the maner of his
electyon ſhalbe lyke vnto the laſte
aboue ſayde.
               Item being choſen he ſhalbe ſworne
betwene the handes of the Seniorye
as foloweth.
            
            
               
                  ❧The forme of his othe.
               
                  I Promyſe and ſwere to maynteyne
and defende with all my power the
honour and profite of ye commons, &amp;
diligently to watche for the conſeruacion
of the rightes of the citie, as if
they were myne owne proper: and to
purſue thoſe to whom it ſhall apperteine,
&amp; likewiſe to recouer withoute
ſupporting y• one or greuing y• other.
               Item to haue an eye that no perticuler
perſon doe encroche vppon the
cōmunaltie, &amp; if ani happen ſo do doe,
to reueale him or purſue him according
as mine office importeth.
               Item to make no bargain couenaūt
or agrement in anye wyſe for to dyminyſhe
the profyte of the towne, nor
to receyue preſentes nor bribes, for to

diſſemble, nor to holde my peace whē
my dutie ſhalbe to ſpeake.
            
            
               
                  ❧For the captayne generall
               THis ſhalbe an office perpetual,
yet neuertheles there ſhalbe a
diligent vew had euery three
yere, to prouide for ye towne a newe,
yf he whyche is therin be faulen into
age, or longe ſickenes, or other wyſe
occupied that he cannot tende to hys
office: and the election to be by ye coū
                  ſell
and alſo approued by the two hū
                  dred
as is afore ſayde.
            
            
               ¶For the perticuler captaines.
               THis ſhalbe an office for terme of
lyfe, and in euery quarter of the
towne he ſhall choſe his perticuler
captaine in the preſence of the captayne
generall, and two of the counſell
deputed for the ſame, and after ye
election ſhallbe reported to the counſell,
whyche ſhall haue auctoritie is
ratifye hym.
            
            
               ¶For the banderettes.
               ITem ye banderettes general ſhalbe
elected as the captayne and in ſuche
ſorte. Touching the other banderettes

they ſhallbe choſen as the perticuler
captaynes, excepte in ſteade of
two counſellours it ſhalbe ſufficient
that the captayne of the quarter be
ther wyth their dizoners.
            
            
               ¶Of their lieutenantes.
               EVery one maye choſe him his lieutenant
ſo that it be by the conſent
of all their bandes in generall, excepte
in the time of daunger this ſhal
not be done withoute the knowledge
and expreſſe permyſſyon of y• coūſell.
            
            
               ¶Of the dizeners.
               ITem the petye counſell hathe full
power to choſe them, and to contynue
them ſo longe as they doe their
duetie, or other wyſe to diſpoſe them.
               All ſhalbe ſworne betwene y• hands
of the Sendicques in this forme, and
to renewe it in time of neceſſitye.
            
            
               ¶The forme of the othe.
               I Promyſe &amp; ſwere to endeuoure
my ſelfe faythefully for the defence
of the towne, &amp; in no caſe
to forſake it in the time of neceſſity.
               Item to be continually readie and
preſt to beare armes againſt the enemies,

whenſoeuer I ſhalbe appointed
by my ſuperiors.
               Item to maintaine and kepe peace
and tranquilitie amōge the burge
                     •
                  es
and habitantes of the towne: and to
ſtaye and let with al my power al ſedicion,
ſtrife, fighting, or chiding.
               Item to make no euell conſpiracie
or enterpriſe, but the contrarie, reſiſting
all thoſe which doe it, and to reueale
them to my ſuperiours.
               Item to ſtope all dyſſolucyons and
outrages, and in generall all whiche
ſhalbe contrarye to the order and pollicie
of the towne.
            
            
               
                  ❧For the geolyer or Souldan.
               THis offyce ſhalbe for no certeyne
tyme, neuertheles it ſhalbe ouerſeen
and vewed euery thre yere, to ſee
if he doe well his duetye: the election
ſhalbe by the counſell, the confirmacion
by ye two hūdred, as is aforeſaid.
            
            
               ¶The forme of the othe which they
vſe ſhalbe thus.
               
                  I Promiſe and ſweare to kepe faithfully
all that which ſhalbe committed
to me, and to render accompte
therof withoute fraude.
               
                  
Item to kepe euery priſoner commytted
to my charge chayned or at
large, as ſhalbe commaunded me.
               Item in ſuch caſes as ſhalbe forbidden
and not permitted that anye doe
ſpeake wt a priſoner, I ſhall take ſuch
diligent hede that none come at them
to talke with them.
               Item not to permit the priſoners
to vſe any bancketts, outrages, plaieng,
diſſollutneſſe, gamyng, or ſuche
other vnmete things.
               Item not to exacte or take aboue y•
which ſhalbe due according to ye taxe.
            
            
               ¶For the Saoultier.
               THis ſhalbe an office perpetual,he holdeth the bible open before the iudges at the time of Iudgement. if
he which be once choſen doe truly
diſcharge his office, neuertheles
he ſhalbe ouerſen euery thre yere,
to ſee if he be meete or conuenient to
contynue or be depoſed.
               Item this election ſhalbe made by
the petie counſell, and confirmed by y•
two hundred.
            
            
               ¶For the heroldes.
               THis ſhalbe an office likewiſe perpetuall
as of the Saoultier, the
one ſhalbe a horſe man, the other

a foote man, the election ſhalbe as is
aforeſayde.
            
            
               ¶The waiters or officers for the counſell,
and the lieutenant.
               THis ſhalbe an office perpetuall
excepte there happen anye notable
faulte, alſo the petie counſell
haue full power to make them or depoſe
them if nede ſhalbe.
               The number of the officers for the
Citie ſhalbe fourtene, and for the lieutenant
tower.
               Touching their othe it ſhalbe ſufficient
beſyde the othe of common burgeſes,
they ſhal promiſe to be diligent
aſſiſting at all times, readie to wayte
vpon the commaundement of ye Sendicques
and counſell, ſeruing them in
their offyce.
               Item to come incontinent whē they
ſhalbe commaunded, to execute all yt
ſhalbe geuen them in charge.
               Item to beare themſelues faithfully
in all that apperteineth to their office
withoute faulte or delaye, and to
kepe ſecreate all that ſhalbe done and
ſpoken in the counſell, and diligently

to watche and kepe well the towne
houſe, and all that is therin.
               Item to make faithefull reporte of
al meſſages or viſitacions which ſhal
be committed to them.
            
            
               ¶The gardes of the towers and the porters.
               ITem this office ſhalbe perpetual ſo
longe as they ſhall doe their duetie,
the counſel ſhall ouer ſee them, and
in theyr power to contynue or dyſpoſe
them.
               Item it ſhall not be nedefull to ſet
anye eſpeciall forme of othe, for it requireth
not but fidelitie and diligence
to kepe the place, in the whiche they
be conſtituted, which may be briefely
done by wordes.
            
            
               ¶For the notaires.
               THe power to make them or depose
them, ſhalbe in the petie coū
                  ſell,
neuertheles none ſhalbe receyued
withoute the reporte and witneſſe
of the notaires of ye towne, concerning
their ſufficiencie, wiſedome,
and learning.
            
            
               ¶The forme of their othe.
               
                  I Promyſe and ſweare to receyue no
acte nor Inſtrument which ſhalbe

to ye diſhonour or damage of y• towne,
or againſt the pollicie of the ſame.
               Item to couche faithefully and ſet
downe by writing al ſuch actes &amp; Inſtruments
as I ſhalbe required, withoute
addinge or dymyniſhing to the
puritie therof.
               Item to deliuer to euery one al ſuch
rightes as apperteine to him, &amp; ſhalbe
in my hands.
               Item not to Concele or kepe backe
anye inſtruement to the preiudice of
the one or fauour of the other, and alſo
not to delyuer into the handes of ye
partye contrarie, anye documents to
defraud him which I ought to helpe:
but to conſerue and kepe faithefully
all actes whiche ſhalbe committed to
my charge.
               Item to make expedicion to all mē
of that which may ſerue them according
to equitie and reaſon.
               The counſel haue ful power to ordeine
al theſe offices, to conſtitute &amp;
ſet in thoſe which they will.
               Nowe it is to be noted that to exerciſe
theſe offices aforeſayde, from the
petye counſell vnto the Sendicques,

and ſo downe ward vnto the Saoultier,
it is required yt he be a cittezen.
               Item to be the lieutenant or one of
the aſſiſtance.
               Item for al the Captaines &amp; banderettes
generall.
               Item the Controuller, Auditour
of the counſell, maiſter of the monye,
procurer generall maiſter of thartilery,
&amp; geoler, it ſhalbe required that
he be a citezen: for the reſt it is ſufficient
if he be a Burges.
               As concerning that which hath ben
ſayd of terme and ſpace of time, it is
to be vnderſtande in this ſorte, that if
it happen any faulte worthy to be puniſhed
by depoſicion it ſhall alwayes
be lawfull to depoſe the offender as
he hath deſerued.
               Moreouer the Burgeſes or citezens
which ſhall refuſe to take the dignity
of office or eſtate vnto the whiche he
ſhalbe called or ordeyned by the Seniorie,
and will in no caſe condiſſende
and agree to take it, that he ſhal then
be ſet to paye .xxv. Crownes for fine
for hys contumacye, and conſtrayned

to abſent the towne for a yere excepte
he haue a lawfull excuſe wel knowen
to the counſell.
            
            
               ¶The office charge and power of the
lordes Sendicques.
               THe foure Sendicques ſhalbe contynually
reſident in the towne,
during y• yere of their Sendicate,
not ſo muche as anye of them to departe
oute of the towne, to lodge oute
of ye towne, not for one night, excepte
he let it be knowen to ye others: &amp; that
none of them doe enterpriſe any farre
iourney, to be ſixe or eighte daies abſent,
wythoute the leaue of the
counſell.
               Item that euery daye they ſhal gather
thē ſelues to gether after dinner,
yt is to ſaye at one of y• clocke, to conſulte
vpon that whiche ſhalbe to doe,
and to put order their in, and alſo to
put thoſe thinges in execution which
hath been concluded by the counſell.
               Item vpon the ordinarie daies that
the counſel is holden, the Sendicques
ſhalbe the firſt in the towne houſe▪ as
wel to ſhewe good enſpāle vnto other
as to deliberate together of thoſe

things which they will doe.
               Item if anye thinge happen which
requireth the aſſemblie of the coūſel,
they ſhall gather them ſelues together
to doe thoſe thinges which ſhalbe
nedefull.
               Item in things which ſhal require
their preſence in dyuers places at one
tyme, they ſhal deuyde them ſelues in
ſuche ſorte as eche of them maye be
where it ſhalbe expedient.
               Item if it happen any publike noiſe
as fyre, tumulte, or other like, that ye
firſte Sendicque ſhall come incontynent
into the towne houſe, and ſhall
cōtinue there, waiting for the newes
which ſhalbe brought him, to y• ende
to aſſemble the counſell from hower
to hower if nede ſhalbe, or otherwyſe
to diſpoſe according as neceſſitie ſhal
require: and that the other thre ſhall
runne haſtely vnto the place where ye
dainger ſhalbe, and moreouer hauing
ſeen the thing, two ſhall diſſeuer, one
on the one ſyde of the towne and the
other on the other ſyde, to viſyte and
kepe the ſtreates, corners and ye gates
if nede ſhalbe, and the thirde ſhal continue

vpon the daūger, vntyll it ſhalbe
apeſed, or otherwiſe.
            
            
               ¶The office of the fyrſte and chiefe
Sendicques.
               THat euery daye when there ſhalbe
no counſell, he ſhall come into
the towne houſe that is to ſay at
the comming from the ſermō, to ſe if
there reſt anye concluſion of the coū
                  ſell
to execute, or heare thoſe plaintifes
which ſhall come.
               Item that he receyue the letters y•
ſhalbe addreſſed to the counſel, but he
ſhall not open them but in ye preſence
of one of his felowes, or at y• leſt two
coūſellers: but if it be a matter of haſt
he ſhall cal his other compagnions to
conſulte at the hower, or otherwyſe
to tarie vntyll they ſhalbe aſſembled:
and generally yt in al matters which
are worthye to haue conſultacion at
the hower he ſhall aſſemble hys compagnyons.
               Item on the dayes of ye counſell incontinent
after the ſermon, he ſhalbe
in ye towne houſe to heare thoſe which
ſhall require audience.
               Item at his cōmīg forth he ſhal make

aunſwere vpon thoſe thinges that be
hearde, and that ye ſame daye he ſhall
prouide to put in executiō that which
hath ben ordeined, if they be thinges
which may be executed ſo redilie.
               Item that he ſhal ſigne y• mariages
before they be pronoūced in ye church,
inquiring diligently yf the mariage
maye be made accordinge to the ordinaunces
of god.
               Item y• he ſhal haue y• towne ſeale
in his hāds, &amp; the charge for to ſeale.
               Item he ſhalbe preſident ouer ye ſecond
appellacions or ſupreame.
            
            
               ¶The office of the iii. other Sendicques.
               ITem the one ſhall ſet in the conſiſtorie,
the other in the chamber of accomptes,
and the thyrde ouer the
firſt appellacions.
               Item there ſhalbe one deputed or
appointed to vilet the priſoners once
a weeke, and this charge ſhalbe geuē
him in the beginning of the yere by y•
aduiſe of the counſell.
            
            
               ¶What ſome of them may doe.
               ITem two maye ſigne the commaū
                  dementes
ordinarie, to make paiementes
for the charges paſſed by

the counſell.
               Item to open y• letters y• be adreſſed
to the counſel as is ſaid.
            
            
               ¶That which one alone maye doe.
               ITem that whatſoeuer complainte
ſhal come, eche one of y• Sendicques
hath full power to cōmaunde thoſe
to whom it apperteneth to be examined,
and to examine them, and to impriſon
them if nede ſhalbe.
               Item that al diſſolutions, arroganſye,
inſolences, dronkennes, and ſuch
other lyke, euery one hath power to
impriſō ſuch, and after make reporte
to ye counſel, but he hath no power to
delyuer the priſonner before he hath
made reporte.
            
            
               ¶Of matters Criminalls.
               IF they take a Criminall or a malifactour,
that within xxiiii. howers
they ſhal commaūde the lieutenant
to make him aūſwere vpō thoſe pointes
of the which he ſhalbe accuſed.
               Afterward he ſhalbe committed to
the lieutenant, yf the caſe be that the
matter may be eaſly proued, or namelye
if he be alreadie proued, and that
there be no difficulty, as of murther,

thefte, or ſuche like, that incontinent
they ſhall doe iuſtice, and at the moſt
thei ſhal not kepe him aboue x. daies.
               Item yf it be a matter dyffycill to
proue as concerning the acte, or that
it require conſultacion concerning ye
ſentence, y• then a competent terme
ſhalbe geuen vnto the lieutenant to
bringe forth his witneſſes, according
to ye place where they be: neuertheles
he ſhall not haue aboue one monethe
to doe it at ye moſt, althoughe he ſeke
his witnes in other places.
               Item yf they be in the towne or
within two leagues, he ſhal haue but
fyftene daies.
               Item yf the criminall or malefactor
demaunde to be admytted to hys
Iuſtificacion, yt the coūſell ſhall haue
reſpecte if it be conueniēt &amp; according
to reaſon or not.
               Item if ye counſel ſhal perceiue y• he
ought to be admitted, they ſhall geue
him reſpit for .xxx. daies.
               Item the profe knowen and the examinations
&amp; defences hearde, in caſe
that they he admitted, ye Sendicques
ought to order the matter ſo that the

priſoner haue ſentence within .xii.
daies, at ye fartheſt, albeit yt the matter
require conſultacion, otherwyſe that
they doe it the firſt daie.
               Item the Sendicques ſhalbe iudges
of all criminall cauſes beinge accompanied
with the counſell, and eche of
the foure in his order ſhall pronounce
the ſentences, neuertheles if ther be
manye ſentences to be geuen in one
ſytting, there ſhalbe but one to pronounce
it, but if there be one or more
abſent, that thoſe which be the fyrſte
ſet after them in counſell y• they take
the place wt the ſtaf, e but yet thei ſhal
not pronounce the ſentence.
            
            
               
                  ❧The office, charge, and duetye, of
the counſell.
               ITem that iii. dayes in ye weeke
that is to ſay Monday Tueſday
and Fryday, e they ſhall come together
at the ſounde of the bell withoute
anye other calling: moreouer yf
it ſhall happen anye extraordynarye
matters, that they ſhal appeare at the
hower aſſigned by ye commaūdement
of ye Sendicques, by night or by daie.
               Item in the ordinarye dayes from

Eaſter, to Michelmas, they ſhall aſſemble
at ſeauen of the clocke. And
from Michelmas to Eaſter at eight of
the clocke which is at the ende of the

                     •
                  ermon: and he that appeareth not to
be aſſiſtant ſhall paie.
               Item in matters of greate importaunce
and which require ye preſence
of the whole coūſell, the Sendicques
ſhall commaunde to ſeke the counſell
by ye othe which they owe to ye towne,
but thys ſhal not be done but by good
diſcreacyon.
               Item whoſoeuer ſhalbe called vpon
his othe &amp; appeareth not, he ſhall
pay a fyne of fyue florence, excepte he
haue a lawful excuſe, for ye whiche he
ſhalbe ſworne if he wyll haue hys excuſe
receiued, &amp; moreouer y• he doe ſignifie
in his owne perſon or his wyfe.
               Item ye none ſhal depart before yt the
coūſel be ended wtoute aſking leaue.
               Item whoſoeuer ſhall depart withoute
the leaue of the counſell, and beinge
called agayne by the Saoultier,
at the commaundement of the fyrſte
Sendicque, yf he come not, he ſhall be
put to a fyne fyue Florens, and three

dayes impryſonment.
               Item after the praie
                     •
                   be made none
ſhal ſpeake but in his order,All their counſells beginne with praier and if many
ſpeake at once, the firſt Sendicque
ſhall impoſe Sylence, the ſylence impoſed
if their be any that ceaſeth not,
he ſhalbe put to a fine of v. ſhil.
               Item that euery one ſhall kepe his
place to auoide confuſion.
               Item y• noe man be ſo hardye to propoſe
any thīg of his own heade but he
ſhal reueale the ſame to the firſt Sendicque
before the counſell be ſet, that
the Sendicque may propoſe it, neuertheles
yf it ſeme good vnto hym, he
may commaunde the other to declare
it more at large the better to informe
the counſell.
               Item yf it happen that anye haue
aduertyſement after the counſeyll
be ſet, of anye thynge perteyninge to
the common welthe, that then beinge
entred into the houſe he ſhall aduertiſe
the firſt Sendicque a parte.
               Item that none ſhall reueale
that whyche is intreated of or decreed
in ſecreate in their counſeyll

vpon paine to be depoſed, and for euer
to be vnable for that eſtate: moreouer
according to the weighte of the caſe,
to be puniſhed by the aduyſe of ye coū
                  ſell
eyther by a fine of mouer or open
penāce, or els by corporall puniſhement,
but yf it appeare that he hath
done it to ſtoppe the courſe of Iuſtyce
it ſhalbe open penance, if it haue bene
to greue the common welth it ſhalbe
payne corporall.
               Item if any of them haue ought to
propoſe of his owne caſe he ſhal let it
be writen, or otherwyſe he ſhall tarye
vntyll they haue diſpatched the preſent
thinges.
               Item that none ſwere or curſe as to
name the deuyl wtin y• coūſell vpon ye
paine of v. ſhil. and if he contynue after
he hath ben corrected ſōdrie times
then to be depoſed.
               Item y• none ſhal blaſpheme god vp
on ye paine to crie god mercy ſolemynly,
that is wt a torche burning in hys
hand, and to be put in priſon, &amp; if he
doe it often tymes to be depoſed and
puniſhed more rigorouſly.
               Item y• none reproche or myſname

any other, nor to enter into any contenſſion
or chiding, or brauling, that
they ſpeake no contumelious wordes
or diſhoneſtie, but that eche one telling
his opinion ſhal ſpeake wt al modeſtye
withoute charging the other
or ſpeaking againſt their honour, vpon
the paine of v. ſhill. &amp; if he be accuſtumed
ſo to do, after certeyne admonicions,
and no amendemēt had, to be
depoſed from the counſel.
               Item if any doe charge another wt
a crime, he ſhalbe bounde to proue it
otherwyſe to crye him mercy: and to
be depoſed from ye counſel the reſt of ye
yere, and he whiche hath ben charged
ſhal haue his action.
               Item this order ſhalbe kept as wel
for ye coūſel of ſixtie as in general of ye
two hūdred, for ye auoiding of confuſion,
&amp; y• al thinges may be the better
obſerued, they ſhal rede yt which is paſſed
euery yere as wel in ye firſte coūſel
holdē after ye electiō, as alſo of ye two
hūdred, &amp; then al ſhal ſwere to kepe it.
               Item ye nothynge ſhalbe ſet forth amonge
ye two hundred before it hath
bene treated of by ye petye coūſel, neither

in the generall counſell before it
hath ben treated of before, as wel of ye
two hundred as of the petye counſel.
            
            
               
                  ❧For what cauſes the councellers ought
to retire them ſelues.
               ITem that euery one in hys owne
proper cauſe ſhall retyre hym ſelfe
before he be commaunded, and yf
he doe it not they ſhall compell hym
to doe it.
               Item in that whiche apperteyneth
to his, and not to his owne perſon, as
in ciuill cauſes, the father ſhall not be
preſent when the cauſe of hys ſonne
ſhalbe denounced, neither brother nor
vncle: moreouer if anye wil not retire
him ſelfe of his owne good wil, to be
admoniſhed by the counſell.
               Item in Criminall cauſes none ſhal
tarye in the affaires of his parent or
of his Cooſyn yſſued from his coſyn
germayne, but ſhalbe excluded.
               Item in all cauſes which ſhal ſeme
good to the counſell to exclude anye,
immediatly they ſhall depart.
            
            
               ¶The office of the threaſorer.
               THe threaſorer ſhalbe preſent eueri
day in ye counſell vpō paine aforeſaid,

and haue his voice as the other.
               Item that he ſhall kepe ſecreate y•
which ſhalbe ſayd or done in the coū
                  ſell,
vpon the ſame paine that is ſet
vpon the counſellers.
               Item to receiue all the commō money
as well of the ordinarye reuenue,
as the paynes of fines or other extraordinarye
ſommes.
               Item that he ſhall demaunde and
receiue in due time and alſo yelde accompte
of that which ſhalbe due, eyther
by fermers, perticuler receyuers,
or paines fines or reuenewes, as of al
ather things, ſo that the towne haue
no lacke by negligence.
               Item if he cannot be payde with a
good will, he ſhall conſtreyne the detters
by impriſonment withoute anye
further delaye.
               Item he ſhall delyuer no money to
anie perſon but by commaundement,
and hauing receiued commaundemēt
he ſhall not delaye the tyme, ſo that
there comme anye complaynte agaynſt
him.
               Item he ſhall render accomptes
euery ſyxte monethe in the chamber

of accomptes, &amp; not to dyfferre ye time
aboue ſixe wekes ouer his terme.
               Item in rendering of his accompts
he ſhall ſhewe howe he receyued it, wt
what modiaciō, Acte, or Ordinaunce,
or by what vertue he hath receiued it.
               Item concerning the things receyued
or paied, he ſhal ſhewe forthe the
commaundementes with ye quittances
vpon euery article.
               Item y• the accomptes may appeare
more cleare, he ſhall ſet them downe
in forme of a regiſter.
               When he ſhalbe depoſed frō his office
he ſhall render the accomptes wt
in thre monethes: and if he be founde
debitour, he ſhall render the remainder
within ſixe wekes, or otherwyſe
he ſhalbe kept in priſon vnto the laſt
ende of the paiment.
            
            
               
                  ❧The office of the Secreataries.
               ITem they both ſhalbe continually
in the counſell, excepte he
haue a lawefull excuſe: alſo they
ſhall kepe ſecreate that which ſhalbe
done in the counſell.
               Item they ſhall not make oute

or delyuer to anye perſon the copye
of any act which ought to be kept ſecreate,
nor to reueale anye thynge
without the knowledge of the Seniors:
he that doth the contrary ſhalbe
puniſhed as is aforeſayde.
               Item he ſhall haue two Regiſters,
the one for the publike affaires, or in
any poynte touching the comminaltie,
the other for perticuler men, whiche
appertayne not to the towne.
               Item, the fyrſte Secreatarye ſhall
wryte the fyrſte Regiſter of thoſe
thynges holden in the counſell, the
other ſhall haue that whiche appertayneth
to perticuler affayres.
               Not withſtandynge the one ſhall
wryte yf nede be, &amp; read the letters,
inſtrumentes and actes, that the other
ſhall make, to the end that there
be no delay.
               Item, that eche of them in his office
ſhall make diſpatche of the matters
whiche his Regiſter importeth,
neuertheleſſe, the fyrſte onelye ſhall
haue the charge to ſigne all thynges
when they ſhalbe preſent.
               Of the other part, when there ſhal

be publike matters to diſpatche of
great importaunce, as inſtructions,
and ſuch lyke, the firſt ſhall comunicate
with his companion, the one to
vſe the others counſell.
               But in the abſence of the one, the
other ſhall haue the whole charge, &amp;
the ſeconde ſhall doe the office of the
fyrſte.
               Item, there ſhalbe a Regiſter apart
for the letters miſſiues, and ſhal continue
in the Secretaries place or cloſet,
the whiche ſhalbe cōmon to them
both according to the neceſſitie.
               Item, a Regiſter aparte for cauſes
criminalls.
               Item, a Regiſter for cauſes of mariages.
               Item, a Regiſter wherin ſhalbe enrouled
the officers from the fyrſt day
of their office to the laſt.
               Item, another to kepe in order the
ſtatutes &amp; proclamatiōs, which ſhalbe
made accordīg to ye neceſſitie of time.
               Item, a Regiſter of the cōmaundements
 wt ſhalbe made for the diſburſing
of any monei, to ye ende y• the rendring
of the acomptes maye appeare

more cleare, and be better verified.
               Item, another Regiſter, wherein
ſhalbe drawen al the actes which import
the recoueryng of money for the
communaltie, as of fynes, and other
profittes.
               Item, that all informacions ſhall
be locked in a cheſte or cloſet, of the
whiche the firſt Secretarye ſhall
haue the kaye, and in his abſence the
ſeconde, of the which thei ſhal render
accompte: and that thei may be found
when nede ſhalbe, eche of them ſhall
haue a marke by number, and in another
coffer there ſhalbe an Inuentorie
marked, all the proces concluded &amp;
finiſhed, ſhalbe brought into another
place.
               Item, they ſhall make diligent diſpatche
aſwel for y• perticuler matters
as common, and that nothynge ſhall
be left vndone, thei both ſhall comme
together after dinner, at the ſame
houre that the Sindicques aſſemble,
alſo at ſixe of the clocke in the mornynge.
               Item, they ſhal diſtribute equallye
together all the profittes.
            
            
               
               ¶Of the office of Capitaines, Banderetts
and Dyzners.
               THE Capitaine generall ſhalbe
diligente and vigillant ouer all
the towne, he ſhall gather no aſſemblie
ſuſpecte, nor make any conuenticle,
whiche maye be a preparatiue
to ſedicion, tumulte, or mutinetie,
and the perticuler Captaynes,
Banderettes and Dizners, ſhall doe
the lyke, euerye one in his office and
quarter.
               Item, yf any ſuch lyke thyng happen,
or that there be beginninges of
trouble, the Captaine generall ſhall
take hede to it betymes and aduertiſe
the counſell.
               Item, if the perticuler Captaitnes
ſhall firſte perceyue it, they ſhall doe
the lyke, enformyng the Seniors, or
their Generall to make their reporte
as ſhall ſeme good to them.
               Item, thei ſhall watche euerye one
in his office that there be no diſorder
or inſolence, and that the Burgeſes
and Inhabitants gouerne them ſelues
honeſtlye in their houſholdes,
without noyſe, trouble, or brauling,

and if any do the contrary, they ſhall
admoniſhe him, and if that admoniſſion
profit not, they ſhall make their
reporte to the Captayne or Seniors.
               Item, if there happen any daunger
or inconuenience in the towne, they
ſhalbe alwayes readye for defence of
the ſame, when commaundement
ſhalbe geuen them.
               Neuertheles, it ſhal not be lawful to
the Capitaine or Banderet to aſſemble
men, or to arme any, without expreſſe
commaundement of the counſell,
except there happen ſome ſodein
aſſaulte without, in the whiche caſe
thei ſhal doe their office, whyle in the
meane tyme, the counſell maye prouyde
more largely.
               Item, to the ende that the towne
ſhal not be vnprouided, the Capitain
general ſhal not enterpriſe any farre
voyage, as to bee aboue eyght dayes
abſent without ſpeciall lycenſe.
               Item, that eche of them and eſpecially
the Dizners, ſhall be diligent
that the Proclamations and Ordinaunces
of the counſell, as well for
the reformation of the church, as for

the ciuile eſtate, that thei may be wel
obſerued: &amp; if any doe the contrarye,
they ſhal aduertiſe the Seniorie.
               Item that euery Dizener ſhal make
euery halfe yere a roule of all the burgeſes
and inhabitauntes within his
diznarie comprehended, with all the
houſholdes makyng fyre aparte, &amp; to
preſent the ſaid roule to the counſel.
               Item, that once a yere the captain
generall accōpanied wt the captaines
perticulers and Dizners, eche in his
quarter, ſhall make viſitation from
houſe to houſe, to know if the Burgeſes
and Inhabitauntes be furniſhed
with armour as it appertayneth for
the defence of the towne.
            
            
               ¶The Auditours of accomptes.
               ITEM, that three dayes in y• weke
that is to ſay Tewſday, Thurſday
and Saterdaye, they ſhall aſſemble
them ſelues together bothe mornyng
and euenyng, to doe that theyr
office requireth.
               Item, they ſhall put in writynge
all maner of Inſtrumentes, and obligacions
in order, and ſet thē downe
in Inuentorie, to the ende that nothing

be loſte but be founde eaſely.
               Item, they ſhall haue an officer conuenient
appoynted to ſeeke partyes
when nede ſhalbe.
               Item, that withoute exception of
perſon, they ſhall doe theyr dutie to
all men, to cauſe them to paye theyr
duetye.
               Item, when any refuſeth to paye,
or denieth the debt, or alledgeth anye
excuſe, which ſemeth to them inſufficient,
they ſhall make report thereof
to the counſell within eyghte dayes
folowinge.
               Item, if by fauoure or frendſhippe
they ſpare anye man, they ſhalbe punyſhed
vpon their wages, for that
whiche is paſte, and to be bounde for
the dette and charged therewith.
               Item, to declare that they do truely
diſcharge this office, euery .iii. monethes
thei ſhal preſent a roule of inuentorie
of dettes and obligations,
whiche they ſhall fynde, to cauſe the
partyes to appeare wyth diligence,
and thoſe wyth dilyueraunce of their
Regiſter to conferre with the ſame if
nede ſhall requier.
               
                  
Alſo concerning the profites of the
towne, they ſhall not concelethe perticulers
of their rightes, but when
the Regiſters of the town may ſerue,
they ſhall communicate wyth them
to make out copyes, when neede ſhal
requier.
               Item, they ſhall note all the rights
apperteyninge to the towne, as rentes,
reuenues, or cauſes, whiche bee
not paied, and after ſhal make report
to the counſell to the ende to ioyne
them to the ordinarye inuētorie, and
that vpon payne aforeſayde.
               Item thei ſhal reuiſite the comptes
of the Treaſurour incontinent after
thei ſhalbe preſented to them, &amp; cloſe
them vp without delay, but if thei do
not bring them in by the time appointed,
that to is ſaye at the ende of ſixe
monethes, they ſhall procure them,
and not ſuffer them to paſſe the time
appointed.
            
            
               ¶The office of the controuler.
               HE ſhal not paſſe one yere withoute
viſiting all the buyldings
apperteyning to y• towne, but
when he ſhalbe aduertiſed by the inhabitauntes

that there is neceſſitie of
reparaciō, that withoute longe delaie
of time he ſhall come vpon the place
to ſee what lacketh, and to ſet order
therin: but if it happen anye inconuenyence
by hys neglygence after he
hathe bene aduertyſed, that then he
ſhall aunſwere.
               Item in all buildinges where as is
no habitacion, as temples brydges, &amp;
other lyke, he ſhalbe dilygent to ouerſee
them wtout aduertiſemēt of other.
               Item he ſhall prouide and take order
that nothing periſhe or decaye for
faulte of reparacions.
               Item he ſhal haue a regiſter conuenient
to note all the daye workes of
maſſons, and carpenters, and that he
fayle not but to aſſygne the acquittance
of the threaſorer when he ſhalbe
therof certified.
               Item wherſoeuer there ſhalbe maſſons
carpenters or other workemen,
he ſhall not fayle to haue an eye to
them, to knowe yf they doe their duetye
faythefully.
            
            
               ¶The offyce of the mayſter of the
Artyllerye.
               
                  
HE ſhall kepe warely the keies
and not to deliuer them into y•
handes of anye other, nor put
anye in truſt withoute expreſſe commaundement
of the counſell, and yf
there happen anye defaulte, he ſhall
aunſwere therto.
               Item he ſhalbe diligent to kepe nete
and cleane and in good pointe the artillerie,
readie for to ſerue at y• hower
if nede ſhal require.
               Item he ſhalbe dilygent and take
hede in making cleane, that nothing
be put oute of order.
               Item, he ſhall take hede that there
be no diſceyte, for the whiche cauſe he
ſhalbe contynually preſent, and after
he ſhall reuiſyte and ſee that there be
no inconueniencie.
               Item, he ſhall neyther charge nor
diſcharge any peace but in neceſſitie,
excepte it be by expreſſe commaundement
from the Seniors, and that this
be obſerued in all the bulwarkes.
               Item he ſhall kepe the pouder well
lockyd, ſo that no inconuenience happen,
vpon paine to aunſwere it, yf it
be his faulte.
               
                  
Item whē nede ſhalbe to ſet abrode
the artillerie, his office is to do it by
the commaundement of ye Seniors.
            
            
               ¶For the proctour generall.
               HE ſhalbe aſſiſtant in ye courte of ye
lieutenant in ye time of pleading,
to knowe &amp; vnderſtande yf there
be anye cauſe or intereſt for ye towne,
and there after to forme his concluſions,
&amp; this to be done, audience ſhalbe
geuen him, and the lieutenant ſhal demaūde
if there be any thing to be ſaid
which ſemeth to be medled wt ye common
intereſt, before he end his cauſes.
               Item, in al cauſes which perteyne to
ye welth or profite of ye towne, &amp; to the
conſeruaciō of ye cōmen weale, he ſhal
inſtātly purſue it as a good proctor of
ye cōmon welth, &amp; namely in criminal
cauſes he ſhalbe ioined wt ye lieutenāt.
               Item, in ye faulte of parents &amp; frends
he ſhal ſolicite &amp; purſue to make gardens,
or ouerſeers for pupilles &amp; orfelings,
or to depoſe thoſe whiche be if
nede ſhall requyre.
               Item he ſhalbe a party to demaunde
&amp; call vpō all fines in the name of the
towne, of al thoſe wt offended: neuertheles
he ſhal receiue none, nor it ſhal

not be lawefull for him to make anye
pacte, or apointe anye man hys payement,
and thoſe whiche be condempned
in any payement he ſhall ſignifie
to the threſorer euery weke, that he
maye recouer it.
               Item he ſhal ſpare no maner of perſon
in ſuche caſes vpon paine to paye
the ſumme him ſelfe, neuertheles he
ſhall not moleſt anye man to brynge
hym before the Iuſtyce excepte he be
well furniſhed with proues.
               Item he ſhall take payne &amp; doe hys
diligence to knowe thoſe which holde
ought of the towne, as lands, poſſeſſiōs,
medowes, houſes, or whiche we
                  holdeth
anye thinge from the towne,
to aduertyſe the audytors of the accomptes
therin.
               Item when there ſhalbe anye buylding
in the towne he ſhal haue reſpect
that they enterpriſe not nor incroche
vpon the ſtrete, but he ſhall endeuer
him ſelfe to let it, vntil it be determined
by Iuſtice.
               Item yf anye houſe be ruynate or
faulen downe, ſo that the towne be
therby deformed, he ſhall purſue him

whyche oweth the place vntyll they
haue buylded or forſaken the ſame.
               Likewiſe if there be daūger of any
houſe to decaye or faulen in ruyne wt 
the common altie hath intereſt in, he
ſhall make pacte wyth the owner to
ſhore it or repaire it..
               Item, he ſhall ſuffer no houſe to be
ſhorde vpon the ſtrete to let the common
paſſage, excepte it be for a tyme
mete to repaire the ſame, but howſoeuer
it be it ſhall not paſſe eighte monethes,
but yf he be negligent and by
fauour of anye, diſſemble the time he
ſhalbe put to fyne.
               Item, he ſhall haue the ouerſighte
of the breade, which the bakers put to
ſale, whether it be of iuſt waight or
not, and this ſhal he doe euery weke.
And where he findeth defaulte, he ſhal
procede informe as foloweth, that is
to ſaye if he finde breade whiche hath
not his iuſt marke and waight according
to the pryce of ye corne, that was
the ſaterdaye before, he ſhall leuye v.
ſhil. for fine: of the which ye halfe ſhal
be geuen to the towne, and the threſorer
to receyue it, the other to ye ſayd

proctor: &amp; moreouer ye bread ſhalbe cōfiſcate
to the profyte of the hoſpital, &amp;
this for the fyrſt time.
               For the ſeconde time .xx. ſhil. for a
fine, and confiſcacion of the breade to
be applied as is aforeſaid.
               For the thirde tyme .lx. ſhill. for a
fyne, and confiſcacion of the bread as
is aforeſayde.
               For the fourth tyme tenne florence
to be diſtributed as is ſayde, and the
offe
                     •
                  der to be depriued of his occupacion,
and his ouen raced.
               Item, he ſhall make an Inuentorie
of all the mouables, confiſcacions, &amp;
goodes, where the Iuſtice hath layed
hande vpon, to the profyte of ye town
and make reporte to the counſell.
               Item, he ſhal take hede of ye houſes
apperteining to the towne ye none vſurpe
vpō them by any perticuler. Alſo
he ſhal let them to the profite of the
commonaltie, neuertheles he ſhal let
none: but by his aduertiſmēt, ye threaſorer
ſhal ſee if it be vnder .x florens, &amp;
for ye ſpace of one yere, or whether it be
longer terme, or higher price, y• he doe
according to ye cuſtome of the towne.
            
            
               
               ¶For the Saultier.
               HE ſhall haue the charge of the
town houſe, that vpon ye daies
of ye coūſel he ſhal open ye great
dore of ye counſel in ye morning: and
not ſhut it before ye coūſel be departed
               Likewiſe when the counſell ſhalbe
holden extraordinarely, or ye two hundred
aſſembled.
               Item, at ſuch time as ye firſt Sendicque
ſhalbe there to heare complaints
or diſpatche cauſes, or when the foure
ſhalbe gathered together after diner.
               Item, when the courte of the lieutenant
ſhalbe holden aboue where the
appellacions be, all that day longe he
ſhall not open but the littell doore.
               Vpon the eueninge he ſhall ſhut the
dores betimes, &amp; keepe it ſhut▪ all the
night: but before he locke it, he ſhall
ſearche &amp; vewe ye their be none within,
neuertheles whē any of ye Sendicques
come he ſhal opē to him, at what
hower of the night it be.
               Item, ye he ſhal kepe ye houſe nette &amp;
in good order, &amp; if there be any thing
to be repared incontinent he ſhall aduertyſe
the controuler.
               
                  
Item, he ſhall make a fyer betimes
in the morning to heate the hall, and
the chamber a certeyne tyme before ye
firſt Sendicque and the Secreataries
doe come.
               Item, he ſhall not fayle to be fyrſte
when the counſel ſhalbe holden for to
kepe the doore.
               Item, he ſhal kepe ſecreate al which
ſhalbe ſaid and done there within, vpon
the ſame payne whiche hath bene
ſaid of the counſellers.
               Item, he ſhall accompanye the Seniors
Sendicques in al acts of iuſtice.
               Item he ſhall accompanye the lieutenant
in the executyon of all Actes
Criminalles.
               Item, he ſhal preſent ye wine which
the Seniors ſhall ſende to the Imbaſſiadores,
or others.
               Item, he ſhal viſite the houſes ruinated
 wt thoſe that be ſworne whē it
ſhalbe requyred, and make reporte to
the counſell.
               Item, to lymyte and meaſure the
feldes, and poſſeſſyons, wyth in the
Fraunchiſes.
               Item he ſhal haue a cloſſet to locke

and ſhutt in the goodes which apperteyne
to the knowledge of the iuſtice,
tarying tyll the Inuentorie be made,
that is to ſaye when the towne ſhall
take anie intereſt, or when there be no
heyres, or when the heyres ſhall not
agree, or when it is requiſite that the
iuſtice ſeiſe any thing.
               Item, to take and kepe the notaries
cheſtes when anye of them doe die, to
conſerue the rightes which are paſſed
by their handes.
               Item, when any watche man dieth
or is depoſed he ſhall receiue agayne
his halberte and his harnes and other
ſecreate thinges which he hathe of ye
Seniorie, for to delyuer them to their
ſucceſſours.
               Item, when the watche ſhall take
anye by nighte in the ſtreates, they
ſhall bringe them to him, and he ſhall
take and kepe them vntyl ye next day.
               Item, if their be brought any thing
to him to be deliuered into his hands,
he ſhall receyue it and kepe it faythfully,
neuertheles he ſhall haue a regeſter
to write as well the priſoners
whyche be broughte hym as all other

things, and that he write it immediatly
in ye preſence of him which bringeth
it to him, and in the morning he
ſhall ſigne it by the Secreatarie.
            
            
               ¶The office of the porters, kepers of gate
                     •
                  
and gardes of the towers.
               ITEM, euerye porter ſhal ſhut
his gate at the ſound of the bel,
&amp; ſhal not open it before ye hower
appointed, be it morning or euening.
               Item if any deſyre to come in, after
the gate be ſhut he ſhall not open vnto
him withoute licence, excepte the
paſſage for ye poſtes, and yet they ſhal
not open vnto them excepte ye watche
be there preſent for feare of daunger.
               Item in ſpecial neceſſitie as in time
of peſtilence, the porter ſhall let oute
the ſicke or deade as he ſhal haue commaundement,
to open to him whiche
ſhalbe admytted for the purpoſe.
               Item that euery one ſhalbe diligēt
to kepe his keies, ſo that there happen
no inconueniences by his negligence,
but that he ſhall aunſwere it.
               Item none ſhall commyte anye other
in his place wtoute aſking leaue
of y• firſt Sendicque, or in his abſence

one of his companions.
               Item in the time of vproare▪ fier, or
ſuche accidentes, they ſhall abyde by
their gates, and not to depart thence
except he haue expreſſe cōmaūdemēt.
               Item, in ſuſpicious times the porter
with the gardes ſhall ſhutt ye gate
incontinent after the watch hath geuen
them a ſigne, ſuch as hath ben before
declared vnto them.
               Item, the gardes of y• towers ſhall
not faile but to lye eche of them in his
tower, and he ſhall not bring in anye
multytude of people wythoute leaue
or commaundement.
               Item in their abſence they ſhal put
none other in, except they haue liſēce.
               Item he that kepeth the bulwarke
of the market place ſhal haue the keie
of the cheyne of the lake, to ſhutte vp
the paſſage of the botes, and open it in
the morninge.
            
            
               ¶The watches of the two ſteples.
               ITEM, the watche men ſhalbe
nighte and daye in the ſteples,
of Sayncte Peter and Sayncte
Iarueis, and ſhalbe dilygent to eſpie
within and withoute.
               
                  
Item, if it happen anye fyer in the
towne, that he whiche is nereſt ſhall
crye with a loude voyce to the nexte
houſes withoute ſounding his bell.
               Item, in ſuſpecte tymes eche ſhall
haue a bell and a banner, and if he ſee
any great troupe of men he ſhal ſoūd
his bell and and put his banner that
waye that they be, to the ende that y•
porters may be vpō their gardes, and
if nede ſhalbe to ſhute the gates.
            
            
               ¶The courte of the lorde lieutenant and
Adiuters of ryghte, and the ſomnarye
of the Iuſtyce of Geneua. And fyrſte
the electyon of the Lieutenant and of
his fower Aſſyſtantes.
               THE teuſdaie before ye ſondaye
after S. Martyne, ye petye coū
                  ſell
ſhal aſſemble to make the
election of the Lieutenant &amp;: to haue
a good beginning, the firſt Sendicque
ſhall exhorte the company to pray vnto
god, that he wyll direct their waies
and hartes, o choſe mē of a good conſcience,
louing equitie, &amp; trueth, men
of prudence, and knowledge, to iudge
rightfully, and after the prayer made

they all ſhalbe ſworne in order, in
forme folowing.
               We promyſe and ſwere before god
to choſe &amp; name into this office thoſe
which we thinke to be meete and ſufficient
for the mayntenaunce of y• honour
of god in this towne, and to render
right to all withoute accepting of
perſon, and in choſing we ſhall haue
reſpecte vnto the common welth and
tonoe perticuler affection, neyther for
fauoure nor hate as god bearethe vs
witnes in this promyſe, therin to be
iudged if we doe the contrarie.
               After this eche ſhall name before ye
Sendicques, the Secreataries beyng
preſent, to wryte their voyces: ye Fridaye
folowinge in the counſell of the
two hundred after prayer made, ye declaration
and the othe, they ſhall propoſe
thoſe two which haue ben choſen
by the greateſt part, &amp; vpō that ye two
hundred ſhall procede in their electyō,
taking if it ſeme good to them one of
the two, or els another thirde, ſo that
the fyrſte electyon be as an aduertyſement
withoute preiudice to the libertie
of the ſeconde.
               
                  
The ſonday folowing, the general
counſell ſhalbe aſſembled, there they
ſhal pronounce to the people the election
made by ye two hūdred, to knowe
yf ye people be agreeable to haue him,
if the people accepte hym whyche is
choſen, then the election is fyrme, and
ſhall continue, but if they refuſe hym
they ſhal procede to a newe electyon,
firſt by the petie counſell, after by the
two hūdred, ſo that none be in the offyce
except he be cōfirmed &amp; approued
by the people or by the greateſt voice.
            
            
               ¶For the aſſiſtaunce
               TOVCHING the Aſſiſtaunce
two ſhall continue in their office
the ſeconde yere, ſo y• euery yere
they ſhall make but two newe in the
place of thoſe two which haue ſerued
two yere, neuertheles the laſt electiō
ſhalbe by the two hundred, withoute
comming to the people: and the ſame
daye the lieutenant wt his foure adiutors
(as well ye auncients which were
of ye yere paſt as ye newe elected) ſhall
come into ye towne houſe to be ſworne
before the Sendicques &amp; the councel,
and to be put in poſſeſſion.
            
            
               
               ¶The forme of their othe.
               VVE promiſe and ſwere to execute
oure offyce in the feare of god &amp;
with a pure conſcience, and rightly
to iudge &amp; pronounce thoſe things
which ſhal come before vs in all equitie
&amp; iuſtice, withoute exceptiō of perſon,
rendering right to eche one wtout
bearing fauour to thoſe whiche haue
an euyll cauſe.
               Item, not to receiue preſents, gifts
nor corruptiō to decline frō our duety
               Item, we all payne and dilygence to
make expedition of cauſes which ſhal
com before vs, to eaſe the parties frō
troubleſome charges.
               Item, not to burdeine any perſon wt 
any coſts and charges more then reaſon
will beare, and namely to folow
the taxe which is made vnto vs.
               Item, to be diligent to reproue &amp; correcte
al inſolences &amp; diſſolutneſſe contrarie
to good pollicy, &amp; to cauſe that
the ordinaunces of the towne maye
be well obſerued, as muche as lyeth
in vs, callynge god to wytnes therin,
to bee Iudged yf we doe contrary.
               
                  
Moreouer if it happen anye lieutenant
to dye before his yere, yf there
reſt yet foure monethes, they ſhal ſubſtitute
another in forme aforeſayde:
but yf he haue leſſe tyme, the moſte
auncyent of the Adiutors ſhall take
hys place.
            
            
               ¶The place of the Aſſiſtaunce.
               THE two auncients ſhall goe before
the other, but as well y• auncients
as the newe amonge themſelues,
ſhall goe according to their degre
and dignitye of office in ye which
they haue bene.
            
            
               
                  ❧For the two Secreataries of the
Lieutenauntes courte.
               THE petye counſell ſhall choſe
them, to preſent them to the two
hundred which haue authority to
ratifye the electiō or to make another
withoute prolonging the tyme: and
the office ſhalbe thre yere at the leaſt
excepte there happen death or a notable
fault, enot wythſtandynge in the
tearme of thre yere there ſhalbe made
a ſurueie, &amp; the office peruſed if they
ought to contynue therin: before they
ſhall enter into ye poſſeſſion they ſhall

make an othe before the counſell in
maner folowing.
            
            
               
                  ❧The othe of the Secretaries.
               WE promiſe and ſwere to receyue
no acte nor inſtrumente to the
dyſhonour or damage of the
towne, or againſt the polycye
of the ſame.
               Item, to couche faithfully by writyng
and to regiſter all ſuche actes
and inſtrumentes, as pertaine vnto
our office, and to conſerue that we
haue made, to diſtribute in tyme and
place, accordynge to the order of
Iuſtice.
               Item, not to reueale ought to any
party to the preiudice of another, or
ſtoppe the courſe of the right.
               Item, not to defraude any eyther of
Acte or inſtrument which may helpe
them or further them by reaſon.
               Item, to make expedicion of all
actes and copies, which we be bound
to delyuer, without delaying the one
to further the other.
               Item, not to eracte or take greater
wages than to vs is due by the order
of the taxe.
            
            
               
               ¶The office of the Lieutenaunt, and of
his Aſſiſtaunts, and the order of their
courte.
               THE Lieutenaūt &amp; his Aſſiſtantes
be bound to hold their court,
for to render right thre dayes in
the weke: ye is to ſaye Monday after
dinner, from twelue of the clocke tarying
till foure, lykewyſe Wedneſdaye
and Fryday.
               Moreouer, euery daye from eyghte
of the clocke vntill ten, the Lieutenaunt
or one of his Aſſiſtauntes one
after another, through oute, ſhalbe
reſident in the benche, to heare the
plaintyues, and ſette order amonge
them, vntyll they may do iuſtice: the
Saterday they ſhal do the lyke, both
in the morning and after dynner, becauſe
of the ſtraungers and multitude
which come to the market.
               Item, in matters of ſodaine prouiſion
the Lieutenaunt ſhall call the
adiutours, and aſſemble them extraordinarily,
accordynge to the neceſſitie
of the caſe, and that there be no
defaulte, the Lieutenaunte ſhall not
enterpryſe anye longe voyage, to be

abſent one courte day wythout leaue
of the counſell.
            
            
               ¶For the payne of thoſe that bee
abſent.
               HE that fayleth to be there in the
tyme aforeſayde, ſhalbe depriued
from ſuche profyttes as ſhal
fall or chaunce that daye, and if he
haue not a lawful excuſe, to pay two
ſhillings for amende, and if it be one
of the Aſſiſtauntes to paye double,
and the Secretarye ſhall note theyr
faultes faithfully, to render the role
to the receyuer of the fynes.
            
            
               ¶For the adiournement or ſummonning
for ciuill cauſes.
               WHO ſo euer wyll adiourne or
ſummon hys aduerſe partye,
maye doe it what daye he wyll,
yea at the preſente houre, and
this adiournement ſhalbe auaileable
as well by anye of his houſholde, or
hys wyfe, as of hym ſelfe: moreouer,
if he be abſent or ſicke, and haue any
other lawefull let, his wife or anye
of his, as his nieghbour, or his frend,

may appeare to the Aſſignation, and
excuſe him, but before the excuſe be
receyued, they ſhall be ſworne that
the excuſe is lawefull whyche they
alledge.
            
            
               ¶For defaultes.
               YF there bee no excuſe broughte
forth, and the action be ordinary,
for debte, or other cauſe, none reſerued,
as ſhalbe ſayd here after, and
if betwene two Burgeſes: the demaunder
ſhall make aſſignation
thryſe before he obteyne the default.
               If then he doe not appeare, &amp; there
be no excuſe broughte forthe, letters
ſhalbe geuen out to leauye vpon hys
goods, vnto the furniture of y• ſūme
whiche the cauſe amounteth: but yf
he do not delyuer gage into the hands
of the Sargeant, or if he haue not
ſufficiente in his houſe for to gage
the ſayde ſumme, then for defaulte of
goods they ſhal take his perſon, and
make hym priſoner, neuertheſſe in
caſe y• he ſuffer hys houſe to be ſearched
and thei take ſuch as thei finde,
they ſhall not take him out to putte
him in priſō, but if he abſent him ſelf

willingly, incontynent there ſhalbe
execution againſt him: but yf he haue
withſtande the officer, the Sargeant
ſhall bringe him the next daye before
the lieutenant there to paye all e
                     •
                  
                  epences,
aſſignations, letters, and execuſions
of the ſame, other wyſe he
ſhall procede, whatſoeuer matter to
the contrary notwithſtanding.
               But if the defendant after he hath
bene put backe againe, doe not appeare
to the firſte aſſignation, then
letters ſhall be graunted to the demaundaunt,
to adiorne him peaceablye,
to the whiche yf he obey not,
there ſhalbe graūted proceſſe againſt
him to take his bodie, and put hym
in priſon, to the ende of the pa
                     •
                  ment.
               If it be a ſtranger which aſſigneth
a Burgeſe, then to procede more ſpedily,
he ſhall demaunde yf it ſemeth
him good, and ſhall haue a iournement
frō the lieutenaunt: but if the
Burgeſe wyll not appeare vpon the
day in which he is aſſigned, then default
ſhalbe decreed againſt him, and
immediatlye letters of execution to
gage it in his goods, or to take hys

perſon for faulte of goods, but yf he
haue lawful excuſe, either by abſence
or by ſickenes, it muſt be declared in
the firſt aſſignation.
               Contrarywyſe if ye demaunder appeare
not, the defendour ſhal obteine
againſt him default, and ſhalbe freely
at lybertye from his aſſignation.
               Item, none ſhall be releued from
his faulte, excepte he come before the
courte be ryſen, ſo y• he come in tyme
to anſwere to his aſſignation, &amp; preſent
him ſelfe before the Iudge, and
that before he be ryſen, vnto the end
that this be no occaſion to prolonge
the cauſes: before they be vp, he ſhall
ſwere y• he doth it not to delaye or to
make fruſtrate his demaunder, but
that he is come as ſoone as he could.
               But in ſuche caſe yf the tyme wyll
ſerue, he ſhall be called agayne, neuertheleſſe
yf the demaunder be not
there preſent in hys owne perſonne
or Proctour for him, that thys callynge
ſhall not tourne to be preiudiciall
to put him to defaulte, but onelye
for a lette, that he ſhall not leuye
lettes of execution agaynſt hys partie:

moreouer, none ſhall be receyued
twyſe to pleade ſuch excuſe, but ſuch
a relyfe ſhalbe onely for one tyme.
            
            
               ¶For the adiornement of witneſſes.
               INcontinent after that the terme
for the probation ſhalbe geuen, the
partye which ought to bring furth
witneſſe, ſhall doe his diligence to
call them, that the examination may
be made in tyme and that the adiornement
be made with expreſſe denomination
that it is in caſe of witnes.
               If it happen, that he whiche they
demaunde for witnes, bee abſent or
ſicke, that his wyfe or one of his ſhal
come and excuſe hym wyth an othe,
as hath bene ſayde.
               If he appeare not, or there bee no
excuſe at the firſt aſſignation, he ſhal
be aſſigned the ſeconde tyme, and
yf yet he make defaulte, then letters
of compulſion ſhall bee graunted to
the partye, to conſtrayne hym to
comme before the tyme be expired, vp
on the payne of gage or impriſonment:
and if he ſuffer to bee gaged,

they ſhall take as muche of his goods
as the principall of the cauſe maye
amounte.
               But if he be ſicke, there ſhalbe deputed
one of the aſſiſtaunce, to goe
and examine him in his houſe, &amp; the
aduerſe partye ſhalbe called thyther
to ſee him ſworne, as if he were in
the courte.
            
            
               ¶For the pleding.
               ITEM, folowynge our auncient
cuſtome, the pleding ſhalbe holden
in the common language of the
countrey, and not in Latyne: but for
to auoyde all exceſſe of expences, as
prolonging and troubling of ye parties,
folowing our auncient cuſtome,
that all cauſes which amount not aboue
fyue Florence ſhall be diſpatched
wyth the greateſt expedicion
that maye be, withoute writynge,
but onely by wordes, as well the propoſitions,
and anſweres of the partyes,
as the proues and witneſſes.
               Item, to auoyde all vaine delayes
that in cauſes whiche exceade not aboue
ten Florence, the principal ſentence
that is geuen by the lieutenant

and his aſſiſtauntes ſhal ſtande
for the laſt, without appellation: but
for the other of hygher ſummes, it
ſhalbe lawfull to appeale, that is to
be vnderſtande onely for debte, &amp; not
for cauſe of rentes.
               Item, that all ſentences not paſſing
ten Florences, ſhalbe geuen by
mouth onely, and in general, all ſentēces
interlocutoris ſhalbe vnwrittē
but the Secretary to put them in his
regiſter.
            
            
               ¶For termes and delaies.
               TOVCHYNG the cauſes whiche
ought to be diſpatched without
wryting as is ſayd, that the
demaundant by him ſelfe, or by his
Proctor, ſhall make redilye at ye firſte
his trew demaunde, at the firſt aſſignatiō,
namely y• the aduerſe partie be
there to anſwere lyke wiſe, &amp; the defendour
ſhal anſwere redily &amp; directly, either
affirming or deniyng, proteſtīg
the cauſe if it be his owne proper act,
if it be the cauſe of another (for the
whiche neuertheles he is bounde) he
ſhall haue delaye for two dayes onely,
to giue informacion, yf the other

bee in the towne: but if he bee without,
he ſhall haue competent terme,
according to the place where he is.
               If it be nedeful to be proued, and ye
he will proue his intenſion by inſtrument
or by wrytyng, he ſhall bringe
it out incontinent, &amp; thus doinge he
ſhal not come without furniture: if it
be for witneſſes, he ſhall haue terme
cōpetent, hauing reſpect to the place
where they be.
            
            
               ¶Of cauſes exceding fyue Florence.
               TOVCHING other cauſes that
excede fyue Florence, if the demaunde
be certeyne, as a debt
proued by obligation, byll, or ſuch other
debt, where it is not nede to haue
a byll in wryting, the demaund ſhall
be made by worde, wt the profe of the
obligation, bill, or other inſtrument,
to ende the cauſe briefelye, in ſuche
forme as hath bene ſayde.
               If the cauſe be ſuch, that it requier
the demaunde to be put in wryting,
as when there be manye reaſons to
alledge, and that the deduction be
                     •
                  
                  
longe and difficill, than the demaunder
the firſte daye of his aſſignation
ſhall bringe furthe his demaunde by
wrytinge, and ſhall haue a copye of
the ſame readie to communicate wt 
his aduerſe partie, and ye to be done
at the coſtes of the demaunder according
to the taxe of charges.
               For to anſwere, the defender ſhall
not haue aboue eyght dayes reſpite,
and then to anſwere, denying or affirming
the declaration of the cauſe:
after ye defender hath anſwered, &amp; the
cauſe declared, yf the plaintyue wyl
ſet hys cauſe by articles, to come to
probation, as the day of his conteſtation,
he ſhall haue eyghte dayes to
doe the ſame, and then yf he haue
righte eyther by wrytinge or inſtrumente
for to ſerue hys purpoſe, he
ſhall bringe them furthe, and declare
them with his articles.
               Thys done, the Defender ſhall
haue eyghte dayes to anſwere vpon
the articles and no more.
               If the probation lye in wytnes, after
the Defender haue aunſwered,

the demaunder ſhall haue yet eyghte
dayes terme to bring furthe his witneſſes,
if thei be in the towne, if they
be withoute, he ſhall haue a competent
terme to bryng thē, or examine
them vpon the place, by the vertue
requiſitorie, ſo that eyghte dayes after
the terme geuen, the witneſſes
ſhalbe publiſhed, ſo that ordinarilye
they ſhall haue but fiftene dayes.
               This oughte ſo to be vnderſtand,
that after the beginning of y• terme,
ye ſayd party ſhal one certen day cauſe
his witneſſes to bee ſworne againſt
the daye of his publication excluſiuely,
neuertheleſſe callyng his aduerſe
partie as right and reaſon requireth.
               Item, in the daye of the publication
yf the parties pretend to propoſe
any obligation or ſedule to declare
their facte or righte, they ſhall haue
eyght dayes delay to do it.
            
            
               ¶In caſe of exception.
               IN caſe that the Defender in his
anſwere vſe exception, the whiche
requireth profe, as yf he alegeth
payment, or ſuche lyke
thynge, that the ſame terme ſhall be

geuen him, as hathe ben ſayd of the
Demaunder.
               Item, vpon the exceptions whiche
ſhalbe made, there ſhalbe one replication,
and it ſhall not be permittted
to ye defender to reioyn againſt him,
nor ye Plaintyue to ſurreioynder, neuertheleſſe,
it ſhalbe lawefull as the
matter ſhall require, to oppoſe diuers
exceptions in one cauſe, accordyng
to the diuerſitie of the proues,
or demaundes, ſo that one of the exceptions
let not another.
            
            
               ¶For termes to here the right.
               IN cauſes which mounte not aboue
fyue Florence the principall, and
all other which be eaſye, and nede
no longe conſultacion, as yf Iudgement
maye be geuen vpon an obligation
or other certayne proues: the
Lieutenant and his Aſſiſtaunts ſhal
not take aboue eyghte dayes terme
at the moſte.
               Item, in cauſes of greate importaunce,
whiche requireth further repecte,
and ſpeciallye require conſultation,

they ſhall take ſuch terme, as
they thinke by their iudgement to be
neceſſarye, neuertheleſſe ſo ſtanding
continuallye for briefnes, as muche
as in them is poſſible, ſo that for the
moſte higheſt terme, they ſhall not
paſſe aboue a moneth.
            
            
               
                  ❧For the longeſt tyme that proceſſe
ought to continue.
               THAT thys order ſhall ſerue to
diſpatche al proceſſes in the briefeſt
maner that maye bee, to auoyde
all prolongings and delayes,
ſo that in cauſes of great importance
the whiche ſhalbe broughte by wrytinges,
althoughe there be acception
of the partie Defender, a proces ſhal
not continue aboue foure monethes
and an halfe, but ſhalbe alwayes ended
and finiſhed in the ſayde terme,
namelye that they bee conſtrained to
ſeeke theyr wytneſſes oute of the
towne, for in ſuche caſe they muſte
ioyne to it ſuch tymes as is ordeined
to call them as hath bene ſayde, and
ſo the terme ſhalbe ſo manye dayes
prolonged.
            
            
               ¶Of the two Feries or vacations.
               
                  
THERE ſhalbe two Feries in the
yere, in the which the cauſes and
ſute ſhal ſeaſe: that is to ſay, in corne
harueſt and wyne harueſt, the which
ſhal dure eche one a moneth.
               For the beginning there is no certayne
tyme to continewe, but they
ſhall ordeyne it accordynge as the
yere and ſeaſon wyll beare, ſo in the
ende of the moneth of May, the Lieutenaunt
with his aſſiſtauntes, ſhall
conſulte when corne maye bee rype,
and there after the daye ſhall be appointed,
the whiche ſhalbe publiſhed
in the courte the weke before, and in
the wyne harueſt the like to be done.
               The reſte of the yere, there ſhalbe
no nother vacations to ſtoppe the
courſe of the audientes, except there
happen ſome neceſſitie extraordinarie
in the towne, for the whiche the
coūſel ſhal ordein according to reaſō.
               Moreouer, concerninge the examination
of the witneſſes, as hath bene
ſaid, thei may chaunge the dayes, as
the Sonday ought to be exempt, and
lykewiſe other actes iudiciall, as to
adiorne, to leuy goods, &amp; ſuche lyke.
               
                  
Now, alſo becauſe the feries maye
come often before one proces maye
be ended, as hath bene ſayd of times
and delayes in the terme, whyle the
cauſes ſhall duer, that is to be vnderſtande
by this exception, that the feries
ſhall not be compriſed in ye ſame
tyme of delay.
            
            
               ¶Of cauſes extraordinarie.
               TOVCHYNG cauſes, whyche
maye not ſuffer delaye, as matters
of prouiſion of fruites hanginge
or ſtanding on the grounde, &amp;
ſuche lyke, becauſe it is needefull to
prouyde more briefely, it ſhalbe ſayd
in the place and order of eche one.
            
            
               
                  ❧Of exception againſt Iudges in the
proceſſe &amp; ſentence difinitiue.
               THAT no Iudge ſhalbe holden
ſuſpecte excepte he be refuſed of
one of the parties, but in caſe the
partyes conſent both to haue hym, he
ſhall not refuſe to doe his office.
               Item, it ſhall not be lawefull to refuſe
wythout allegacion of the cauſe,
and to be knowen to the reſte of the
bench, and he that wyll refuſe ſhalbe
hearde vpon his reaſons.
            
            
               
               
                  ❧The cauſes to refuſe, be ſuche as
foloweth.
               THAT is to ſay to haue ben proctor
or counſeller or firſt Iudge in
the cauſe. Alſo parentage, as father
to ſonne, brother to brother, or
Vncle to neuew, or coſyn germayne,
likewiſe affiniti vnto ye degre of vncle
or neuew, and ſo to the contrarie.
               Item, when the cauſe toucheth him
which is refuſed, as if the proces were
touching marchandize, in the whiche
he was a peartener in, or yf he were
ſuertie or in any, caſe haue had to doe
in the ſame.
               Item, yf he beare manifeſt fauour
to the one partie, or hate to the other,
which maye be knowen or perceyued
by vehement preſumptyon, it ſhall
not bee nedefull to proue the ſame
thoroughlye.
            
            
               ¶Here foloweth the taxes of fees or ſtypendes,
in whiche it ſhall not be lawefull
to excede or paſſe.
               FYRST the lieutenant or aſſyſtantes
ſhall not exacte nor
take of the partyes aboue thys

which foloweth.
               
                  In the fyrſt audience when the demaūde
ſhalbe formed.Note that in ſhill▪ is a grote or 4. d. Engliſhe money or there about. i. ſhil.
                  ITEM, in the examinacions of
the witnes, briefly withoute ſettinge
downe in writing, where euery wytnes
ſhalbe examined. i. ſhil.
                  Item, if it ought to be written,
and yet briefly without articles, then
ſhal he take for euery witnes. ii. ſhil.
                  Item, yf it be by articles, that for
euery leafe of articles whiche ye proctor
ſhal preſēt, for eueri witnes. 3 ſhil.
                  Item, for the othe. iii. ſhil.
                  Item, yf the ſentence difinityue of
ye ſūme be leſſe then .5. florens. i. ſhil.
                  Item if it be a higher ſumme, &amp; yet
vnder a hundred florens. iii. ſhil.
                  Item, aboue a hundred, vnto fyue
hundred. vi. ſhil.
                  Item from fyue hundred florens, to
the higheſt ſūme.Note a ſtoren is xii. ſous. i. floren
                  Item they ſhall take nothynge in
ſhort proceſſes, where there is no productyon
of the caſe, and generally in
al proceſſes whiche requireth no conſultacion,
but in ſuche matters when
there nedeth conſultacyon, they ſhall

take no more then they diſbource, reſeruynge
nothynge to theyr owne
profyte.
                  Item, in commyſſyon where there
nedeth a longe informacion, the lieutenant
for hym ſelfe, &amp; for one offycer
which he ſhal contente, ſhall not take
aboue. iiii. florens
                  Item for the taxe of expences in
breife cauſes. i. ſhil.
                  Item in cauſes of greater importance.
ii. ſhil.
                  Item for euery decree made vpon ye
ſales, as vpon goodes of gardenſhips
or gouernaunces. iii. ſhil.
                  Item for a plaintife. i. ſhil.
                  Item all theſe profyttes ſhalbe deuided
amonge them, except any be depryued
by hys owne neglygence, as
hathe bene ſayde, they ſhall make
ſixe porſions whereof the lieutenante
ſhal take two, &amp; eche Aſſiſtante one.
                  Item yf there ought to be vew takē
of a place in proceſſes of heritage, or
other wyſe, if it be in the towne, that
thoſe that ſhalbe deputed for ye ſame,
eche one of them ſhal not take aboue.
ii. ſhil
                  
                     
Item yf it be wythoute the towne
in the feldes. v. ſhil.
                  Item for the eſtymacion or priſing
of goods if their be mouables whiche
moūte not aboue ten florens. ii. ſhil.
                  Item, from tenne vnto fyue and
twentye iiii. ſhil.
                  Item, frō .xxv. vnto fifty. vi. ſhil.
                  Item frō fifty to a hūdred. viii. ſhil.
                  Item, from a hundred to the vttermoſt.
i. floren.
                  Item if they be vnmouable whiche
ought to be cryed thre Saterdaies, he
ſhal not take aboue. vi. ſhil.
                  Item ye lieutenant or his Aſſiſtantes
which ſhalbe preſent at the makinge
of an Inuentorie, ſhal haue for
the firſt leafe. iii. ſhil.
                  Item,Note that a denier is the twelfe parte of a ſhil. for euery leafe beſide. 6. deniers
               
               Vpon thys condicyon that euerye
leafe ſhall conteyne fower and twentye
lynes, and that euery Item ſhall
conteyne or comprehende ye things of
one ſorte together.
            
            
               
                  ❧In cauſes criminalls.
               
                  THE Lieutenant for euery examination
which he ſhal make
before he ſhall bring forth the

malefactor, ſhal haue. iii. ſhil.
               
               Afterwardes the Iourney ſhalbe
taxed by the proctor, and leuied vpon
ye goodes confiſcate of the malefactor.
            
            
               ¶Here foloweth the taxe of the Secretaries.
               
                  IN euery audience they ſhall take of
ye plaintife for ye regiſter. iii. deniers
                  In commyſſyon for Ioureneies.
ii. Floren.
                  For to enregiſter the conſtitution
of the proctor. i. ſhil.
                  Item, for euerye percell of letters.
i. ſhilling
                  Item for bryefe examynacyon vpon
the wrytynge of eche wytneſſe.
iii. Deniers
                  Item, for examinacion by writing
and yet briefe and wtout articles, for
euery witnes. i. ſhil.
                  Item, for examynacyon vpon Articles
for euery leafe preſented by the
proctor. iiii. ſhil.
                  Item, for euery relacion of execuciō
of letters. vi. Deniers
                  Item for the Iourneyes taken oute
at the requeſte of anye partye, for
eche. vi. deniers
                  
                     
Item for euery leafe of copye, y• ſyde
conteining. xxv. lines. x. d.
                  Item for ſentence difinityue withoute
copye. iii. ſhil.
                  Item for copieing of the requeſt of
anye partie. v. ſhil.
                  Item for ye taxe of expenſes in ſhort
cauſes. i. ſhil.
                  Item in longe cauſes. iii. ſhil.
                  Item for inſtrumentes of tuteles &amp;
gardians. x. ſhil.
                  Item, for to Regyſter a playntyfe.
i. ſhil.
                  Item, to Regiſter a ſeiſoure or a
reſt. i. ſhil.
                  Item to regiſter Relaſions of damages
or other ſmale things. i. ſhil.
                  Item ye regiſter of ſubmiſſions which
be made in caſe of reſt. i. ſhil.
                  Item for all fyances made by iuſtyce.
i. ſhil.
                  Item for prayſing of mouables, the
deputie ſhall haue as muche as y• Aſſiſtante,
as well for the preſence as for
the inſtrument.
                  Item for vnmouables where there
is nede to leuie inſtrumēts of decre, if
the ſumme doe not excede a hundred

florens. x. ſhil.
                  Item, from a hundred florence vpwarde.
xx. ſhil.
                  Item for Inuentories, for the fyrſt
leafe as hath ben ſayd. iii. ſhil.
                  Item, for euery other leafe folowinge.
i. ſhil.
                  Item, for informacions, as wel vpon
the plantiues, as others, in cauſes
criminalls, for euery witnes. iii. ſhil.
                  Item for euery anſwere, in criminal
cauſes, vntyll the malefactor be dyſpatched.
iii. ſhil.
               
               Neuertheles they ſhall take nothīg
vntil ye ende, then if ye partie be foūde
culpable, or haue wherwith to ſatyſfie,
it ſhalbe diſbourſed.
               For other inſtrumentes, whiche be
alſo made by the notaryes, it ſhalbe
ſaide in the taxe common.
            
            
               ¶The taxe or fees of the Sergeantes.
               
                  ITEM for euery citacion, as well of
the partie as of ye witneſſes, if it be
in the towne. iii. d.
                  Item if it be withoute the towne wt
in the fraunchiſes. i. ſhil.
                  Item for a reſte of barrage and to
make the relacion. i. ſhil.
                  
                     
Item for execuſion of letters yf it be
in ſeaſure of vnmouable goods. 3. ſhil.
                  Item if it be to leuie mouables vnder
ten florens. i. ſhil.
                  Item if it be aboue. iii. ſhil.
                  Item, for takynge the areſt of a
mans bodye. iiii. ſhil.
                  Item, for prayſynge of mouable
goods, of euery floren. iii. d.
                  Item, for viſytacyon vpon anye
place. i. ſhil.
                  Item, to be aſſiſtant at any queſtion.
i. ſhil.
                  Item, to accompanie ye iuſtice to the
execuſion of a malefactor. ii. ſhil.
                  More ouer there is a common profyte
to be deuided amonge them, that
is to ſaye of euery difinityue ſentence
in briefe cauſes. iii. d.
                  Item, in thoſe of greater Importaunce.
vi. d.
               
            
            
               ¶Howe the lieutenant ought to gouerne
in matters of impriſonment.
               FOR the execuſion of hys letters &amp;
for default or contumaſye as hath
bene ſayde, he hathe aucthorytye
to impriſon.
               Item for the tranſgreſſion of cryes

or proclamations, in caſe that the offender
deſerue punniſhement, for the
lieutenaunt is the executour of proclamacions.
               Item at the requeſt of anye whiche
wilbe partye accuſer againſt another
he ſhall ſet him priſoner with him.
               Item in matters of crimes, be it
ſtrife, fighting or violence, if ye plaintife
come to him and the perſon whom
he complaineth of be ſuſpect of flieng,
excepte it be a man reſydent in the
towne hauing goodes and houſes, he
ſhal not laie hand vpon him before he
haue notified it to one of the Sendicques,
and hath had his permiſſion.
               Moreouer he hath no power to deliuer
or ſet at libertie a priſoner which
hath ben taken for other cauſes then
ciuill, and apperteyning to his tribunal,
but incontinent as he hath ſhut
vp any in caſe as hath bene ſaid, that
he notyfie it.
            
            
               ¶The order which ought to be holden in
proces criminalles.
               VVHEN he hath put in priſon any
man complayned on, or that the
Sendicques notifye to him that

they haue taken anye: that within
xxiiii. howers he ſhal examine them, &amp;
deliuer ye examinaciō to ye Sendicques
               If the offender be founde faulty, wt
                  oute
any dificultye, or that he render
him ſelfe ſo, y• there be ſufficient cauſe
againſt him, he ſhal make expedicion
of his proces.
               Item yf the fyrſte anſweres be not
founde ſufficient by the Sendicques,
he ſhall contynue his examinacions,
vntyll ſuche tyme as he maye render
vnto the Sendicques ſuch aunſwere,
as reaſon requireth: but howe ſo euer
it be, he ſhal not deferrre the time for
to render it aboue two daies.
               Neuertheles, this ſhall not be holden
for his laſt concluſion, but after y•
he hath rendred him ſelfe, and ſubmitted
hys cauſe vnto the proctor generall,
vnto ſuche tyme as ſentence be
geuen, and as ſhalbe founde in the deduction
of hys proceſſes, he ſhal make
vp and fyniſhe his concluſions.
               The ſentence pronounced to hym,
ſhalbe committed to the charge of the
executyoner, and he ſhal goe into the
place beynge accompanyed wyth the

Saultier and the ſergeants, and there
ſhall remaine til ye execuſion be done.
               Item for lacke of the Lieutenante,
whether he be abſent or ſicke, the firſt
Aſſyſtaunte ſhall take his parte, and
ſupplye all that ſhall apperteyne to
his office.
            
            
               ¶Ordinaunces vpon the emolumentes
and exactions of ſeales of Geneua,
thuſe, gouernement and keping of
the ſame.
               
                  ¶The keping of the Seales.
                  IT hath bene ordeined and determyned
that the lorde fyrſt Sendicque
(which euery yere accordinge
to the cuſtome ſhalbe elected)
ought and is bounde to haue the keping
and gouernemēt of thre ſeales,
and thoſe ſuerly to kepe, and with the
ſame to ſeale and vſe truely &amp; faithefullye
all thynges reaſonably as
foloweth.
               
               
                  ¶The vſe of the ſeales
¶And firſt of the common ſeale.
                  
                  ALL maner of Inſtrumentes wt
what name ſoeuer they be named,
being longe or ſhort receiued
in iudgement or without, al ſales
cōpactes, barganīgs, acquittances, releaſes,
Ratyfications, Bargaynes,
teſtamentes, Cauſes, Promyſes, Accordes,
Exchaunges, Confeſſyons,
Tutels, Curatels, Abridgementes,
Commyſſions, Ordinaunce paſte by
counſell, Mariages, Giftes, Atteſtacions
of proctors, profe of notaries,
Suppreme ſentences, executions vpon
the ſame, Sauegardes, Commaū
                     dementes
to leuye, Inſtrumentes,
Requiſitories, Burgeſes, Atteſtaſions,
liſence by writinges paſt by the
counſell, ſaufecondite, ordinaunces
for mariages.
               
               
                  ¶The ſeales of righte.
                  ALL patentes as the leuyinge of
poſſeſſions, citaciō, briefe, atteſtations,
cōmiſſions to examyne
the witneſſes, requiſitories, Contumacies,
preſice letters, ordinances of
ſentences, as wel interlocutories, as
difynityues, declared in the ordinarie
and bryefe courte of the Iuſtyce of

Geneua, Executoriables of the ſame
priſing or eſtimacion, in the ſayde ordinarie
courte, ſubmiſſions, letters
or ſentence for money, Appellacions,
or other like, al theſe ought to be ſealed
with the ſmale ſeale.
               
               
                  ¶For the Caſſhett or priuie ſeale.
                  ALL inſtructyons and charges
which ſhalbe geuen to Imbaſſadours,
namely that his charge is
not paſſed by generall counſell, that
then they ſhall vſe the great ſeale, al
letters miſſiue reſerued, that be afore
ſayd oughte to be ſealed with ye ſeale
called caſſhet, and they ſhall applye ye
to none other, excepte inſtructyons &amp;
miſſiues, as wel in fauour of the Seniorie
as for perticulers.
               
               
                  ¶The maner and taxe which oughte to
be leauied vpō the iii. ſeales reſpectiuely
of euery one of them.
                  
                     ¶Fyrſt for the great ſeale.
                     FOR ſales not exceding i. hundred
Florens. iii. ſhil.
                     Item, from one hundred to v C,
Florens .x. ſhil.
                     Item, from fyue hundred to a
thouſand, ſo that it doth not comprehend

ye iuſt ſūme of a thouſād .xx. ſhil.
                     Item from one thouſād florens, to a
number of thouſands for euery thouſande.
i. floren.
                  
                  
                     ¶Tranſactions.
                     ITEM for all tranſactions ſo ye inſtrument
be made in fauour of both
the parties, &amp; of the goods in which
both the parties haue right, namely
that the goodes doe not a mounte to
M. florens. v. ſhil.
                  
                  
                     ¶Quittaunces
                     FOR all quittaunces and ſummes
of money, and other thynges amoūting
to a C. florens. i. ſhil.
                     From a hundred to a thouſande
florens. v. ſhil.
                     From one thouſand vpward .x. ſhil.
                     For all quyttances in matters of
controuerſye or others. iii. ſhil.
                  
                  
                     ¶Releaſes.
                     FOR all reſignacions and releaſes
to be payd after the forme of ſales,
according to the ſūme of money.
                  
                  
                     ¶Ratifications.
                     FOR all Ratifications. iii. ſhil
                  
                  
                     ¶Bargeynes.
                     
                        
FOR al bargaines for time. iii. ſhil
                     For al bargeines perpetual. v. ſhil
                  
                  
                     ¶Teſtamentes.
                     FOR all teſtamentes amount inge
to v. C. florens. v. ſhil.
                     Item from fyue hundred, to a M.
Florence .x. ſhil.
                     Item, from one thouſande vpwarde.
v. Florens
                     Item, for all clauſes of teſtamentes
accordynge to the valuer and tare as
the ſumme amounteth, to be payd as
the Teſtament.
                  
                  
                     ¶Compromiſes.
                     ITEM, for all compromiſes. iii. ſhil
                  
                  
                     ¶Accordes.
                     ACCORDES pronounced and
broughte by wryttyng briefely.
iii. ſhil.
                  
                  
                     ¶Exchaunges.
                     FOR all exchaunges. v. ſhil.
                  
                  
                     ¶Confeſſing of bandes.
                     VVHEN any will ſeale a bonde or
obligation, for all ſuche obligacions
or bondes to ye ſumme of a
hūdred Florens, ſo that it doe not cō
                        prehende
the whole ſumme of the hū
                        dred
in paper or perchement. i. ſhil.
                     
                        
From a hundred to a thouſande.
.v ſhil.
                     Item, from a thouſande vpwarde.
x. ſhil.
                  
                  
                     ¶Gardenſhips of orphanes and other.
                     FOR al tutelles or gardyans ſhipes
x. ſhil.
                     for all Tutels gouernaūce. v. ſhil.
                  
                  
                     
                        ❧Abridgmentes.
                     FOR all abridgementes vnto the
ſūme of a hundred florens. iii. ſhil.
                     Item from a hundred to .v. C.
Florens. v. ſhil.
                     Item, from fyue hundred to a M.
Florens .x. ſhil.
                     Item, from a thouſand vpwardes.
v. florens
                     Item, thoſe whiche ſhalbe made
by the Seniorie vnto the ſumme of a
thouſande. v. ſhil.
                     Item, from a thouſande vpwarde.
x. ſhil.
                  
                  
                     ¶Commiſſion of recogniſaunces.
                     Item, for the ſeale of the ſayde commiſſions.
i. floren
                  
                  
                     ¶Ordinaunces of the counſell of matters
bothe ſmale and greate, the ſupreme
ſentence reſerued.
                     
                        
FOR all ordinaunces between partie
and partie. iii. ſhil.
                  
                  
                     ¶Ioyning of marriages.
                     FOR all inſtrumentes of marriages,
not compting of apparell, or
iewells, vnto C. Florences. 3. s.
                     Item, from. C. to. D. v. ſhil.
                     Item, from. D. to. M. xx. ſhil.
                     Item, from. M. Florence vpwarde,
v. Florence.
                     Item, donations to bee payde after
the forme of teſtamentes.
                     For all atteſtations of the probate
of Notaries. i. ſhil.
                  
                  
                     
                        ❧Commaundementes to leuye inſtrumentes
and other contractes.
                     ITtem, for ſuche commaundementes.
i. ſhil.
                     Item, for inſtrumentes leuyed by
commiſſion. ii. ſhil.
                     Item, for placettes vpon the requiſitories,
without the territorie. iii. s.
                     Item, for burgeoys. ii. ſhil.
                     Item, for ateſtation vpon the byrth
of cytezins. iii. ſhil.
                     Item, for licence paſſed by the counſell.
iii. ſhil.
                  
                  
                  
                     ¶Supreme ſentences in appellations.
                     FOR all ſupreme ſentences vnto
fyue hundred Florence .x. ſhill.
                     Item, from. D. to. M. xx. ſhil.
                     Item, from. M. vpward. v. Floren.
                     Item, for al executiōs of ye ſame. iii. s.
                     Item, for all protections, xx. ſhil.
                     Item, for all tranſſumptes in fauour
of priuate men. iii. ſhill.
                     Item, for ordinaunces in the cauſes
of marriages. iii. ſhil.
                  
                  
                     ¶Conſequentlye for the ſeale, called the
ſeale of iuſtice ordinarie.
                     ITEM, for all letters to leuye poſſeſſions
and citations for eche, two
ſhillinges.
                     Item, for euerye witneſſe in breife
ateſtations, named in the ſame for
the ſeale one ſhilling.
                     Item, for commiſſion to examine
the witneſſes, for eche. iii. ſhil.
                     Item, for all citacions with requiſitories, iii. ſhil.
                     Item, for all letters for contumacie,
i. ſhil.
                     Item, for all letters called preſice,
two ſhillinges.
                     
                        
Item, for all ordinaunces interlocutories
vpon the acceſſaries, three
ſhillinges.
                     Item, for all ſentences difinitiue
vnto fyue hundred florence, iii. ſhil.
                     Item, from. D. to. M. v. ſhil.
                     Item, from. M. vpwarde. v. floren.
                     Item, for al ſubmiſſions. iii. ſhil.
                     Item, for citations to appeare at
the firſt appellation, ii. ſhil.
                     Item, for ordinaunces vpon appellacions,
iii. ſhil.
                     Item, for ſentences vpon the ſame
appellations vnto. D. floren. v. ſhil.
                     Item, from. D. to. M. x. ſhil.
                     Item, from. M. vpward. xx. ſhil.
                  
                  
                     ¶For the Catchet or pryuye
Seale.
                     ITEM, for all letters myſſiues
graūted in the fauour of any particuler
ſtraunger, ii. ſhil.
                     Reſerued the Citezins and Burgeſes,
whiche ought to pay nothing.
                  
                  
                     ¶For the kepinge of the ſeale, to ſeale
the goodes of pupilles, or other things
at the inſtaunce of perticulers.
                     
                        
THE keping of the ſayd ſeale ſhal
apperteyne to the firſte Sendicque,
and when he ſhall happen
to ſeale any thing, the Saultier
ſhall come and demaunde the ſeale,
and alſo ſhal demaund of the Lieutenaunte,
one of his aſſiſtauntes, or a
Secretarie, to keepe hym companie,
and whether he hath fewe, or manye
he ſhall not take for the leſſer ſorte
aboue. iii. ſhil.
                     And yf the goodes be of greate importance.
vi. ſhil.
                  
               
            
            Finis.
         
         
            
            Poſt tenebras lux.
            
               ❧Here foloweth the Proclamations,
publiſhed by the ſounde of a trompet.
            
               
                  BE it knowen to you,
on ye partie of our moſt
redouted Seniour Sendicques,
and counſel of
this citie of Geneua.
               Where as here tofore
on the partie of oure moſte redoubted
Seniours and Superiours,
there hath bene made manye ſtatutes,
defences, commaundementes &amp;
cryes, publiſhed conformed and drawen
furth accordyng to the worde of
God and his holye lawes, and yet by
the inſtigation and craft of Sathan,
and the malice of many wicked people,
hauinge the ſame ſtatutes and
forme of holy and pure lyuing, haue
deſpiſed, contempned, mocked, and
ſet at noughte the Magiſtrates, the
Miniſters of the worde, and the holy
worde of God it ſelfe, ſo that the obſeruation
of the ſame lawes and commaundementes
bee reſtrayned, put

backe and hindered by certaine malignaunte
and wicked perſons, and
the right courſe of iuſtice letted and
hindered, ſo that many troubles and
greate offences be happened, ſo that
vice and ſynne ſo increaſe, that with
good right we can not loke but for ye
iudgemēt &amp; wrath of god for ſuch ingratitude.
Now, for as much as god
by his ſinguler grace, hath ſo holpen
in troubles, yt the principall authors
of ſuch iniquitie haue bene reuealed,
and putte by their purpoſes and intentes,
by the whiche they haue purpoſed
to doe hurte, for the which we
all ought to render moſt hartie thankes
to god, humbling our ſelues before
him, preuenting his deuyne vengeaunce,
in amendynge our lyues,
hauntynge the ſermons and preachinges
of his moſt holye worde, reuerencynge
the Iuſtices and Magiſtrates,
obeyinge Gods moſte ſacred
worde, lawes, and commaundementes.
Wherefore our moſt redoubted
Seniours willing from hence forthe
to employ all their power and induſtrie,
y• the honor of god may be mainteyned,

the iuſtice to haue his right
and true courſe. Now to all officers,
Iuſtices, Citezins, Burgeſes, inhabitauntes,
and ſubiectes, of what eſtate
or qualitie that they be, yonge
or olde, men or women, lordes, maiſters
or ſeruauntes, riche and poore,
doe charge and expreſſely commaund
from henceforth to haunt &amp; come diligently
to the ſermons of the worde
of God, according to the proclamations
heretofore made, to honoure
and feare the Iuſtice, and Magiſtrates,
to liue holily and peaceablye, to
be obedient according to their duties
to Magiſtrates, Fathers, Mothers,
Lordes and Maiſters, defending and
inhibiting all blaſphemie, diſpiſinge
of god, and his miniſters, diſhoneſt
wordes, vaine ſonges, dronckennes,
diſſollutions, erces, arrogancie, and
inſolencie, playes, or games, ydle
runnynge from houſe to houſe, cutte
or broydered hoſen, chydinge, diſſention,
fyghtynge or braulynge, iniuryng
of other, and all other thinges
not lawful &amp; contrary to y• holy word
of God, &amp; his cōmaundements, &amp; the

actes and proclamations heretofore
made, the whiche expreſſely we the
ſaide Seniours, will and commaund
to bee put in execution, and againſte
the offenders and repugners of the
ſame of what eſtate, maner, or condicion
ſo euer he be, to procede by puniſhment,
correction, and iuſtice, wt
                  out
ſauour, ayde, or ſupport, whatſoeuer
it be: to the ende that the honour
of God maye be mainteyned, &amp;
aduaunced, and his wrathe tourned
from vs, his iuſtice feared and reuerenced,
and generally to lyue as the
people of god ought to lyue, and that
the good policie and tranquillitie of
the common mighte be obſerued and
mainteyned, as far as god will geue
his grace, vpon peyne to incurre the
indignation of our moſte redoubted
Seniours Sendicques, and counſel,
as their affectuous deſire willeth, &amp;
intent emporteth, of the which euery
one ought to be aduertiſed.
               Made and paſſed in the counſell vnder
the common ſeale of the foreſayde
Seniours.
            
            
               
               ¶Publiſhed in Geneua by the ſound of
trompet after the accuſtomed maner,
decreed in the counſell, hopynge for
better god willing.
               LET it be knowen to you by the
commaundement of our redoubted
Seniours Sendicques, &amp; coū
                  ſell
of this citie, yt euery one ought, &amp;
is bound to come to heare the worde
of God, principallye vpon the Sondayes,
and the dayes of prayer, and
other dayes, when they maye haue
time and leyſure. Alſo that euery one
ought and is bounde, to gouerne and
guyde him ſelf after the ſame inſtructions,
vpon paine to be reprehended
by iuſtice.
               Item, that all men oughte and are
bounde, to ſende their children to the
Cathechiſme, for to bee inſtructed,
that is to ſay, thoſe which be of age,
and haue knowledge to lerne, vpon
pain to looſe when they ſhalbe found
lackyng. iii. ſhil.
               Item, that none ſhall be ſo hardye
to ſwere by the name of God, vpon
payne for the firſte tyme to kiſſe the
grounde: and for the ſeconde to kiſſe

the grounde, and thre ſhillinges: for
the thirde tyme thre ſcore ſhillings,
and three dayes in priſon with bread
and water: for the fourth tyme to be
depryued, and baniſhed the towne
for a yere and a daye.
               Item, that none ſhall blaſpheme
the name of god, vpon payne for the
firſt time to kiſſe the ground, &amp; foure
and twentie houres in priſon, wyth
breade and water, and. v. ſhil: for the
ſecond, to kiſſe the grounde and two
dayes in priſon with breade and water,
&amp; x. ſhil. For ye thirde tyme, to be
put in priſon thre dayes with breade
and water, and xxiii. ſhill, and otherwyſe
to bee puniſhed, and chaſtiſed
accordynge to the extremitie of the
facte.
               Item, that none ſhall renounce,
deſpyte,A vyle cuſtome amonge the Frenche nation. or maugre God, vpon payne
of amende honourable, wyth a torche
in hys hande, and in caſe that
anye doe rebell or repugne agaynſt
ſuche good ſtatutes and ordinaunces,
that he ſhall ouer and beſyde the
ſayde payne and punyſhement be put
in priſon thre dayes.
               
                  
Item, that none ſhal playe, or run
ydlye in the ſtreates, durynge the
tyme of the ſermons on Sondayes,
nor daies of praier, nor to open their
ſhoppes durynge the ſermon tyme,
vnder payne withoute anye fauour.
fyue ſhyllinges.
               Item, that none ſhall playe at any
maner of game, for golde, ſiluer, or
money, vnder payne of three dayes
impriſonment, and lx. ſhill.
               Item, that none ſhall make, nor
cauſe to be made or imprinted, neyther
to buye, nor ſel, cardes nor dyce,
or anye papiſticall thinges, concernynge
the arte of pryntynge, nor other
thynges, contrarye to the bolye
chriſtian reformation, vnder payne
of the loſſe of the marchaundiſe, and
thre ſcore ſhillings.
               Item, that none be hardy to committ
whoredome, or fornication, eyther
to be droken, to runne ydlye about,
looſing their tyme, nor runne
awaye from their maiſters, or from
their occupatiōs, but y• euery one ſhal
be occupied &amp; traueil in his vocation
according to his qualitie, vnder paine

to be puniſhed by iuſtice, accordinge
to their demerites, and made an example
to all others.
               Item, that none be ſo hardie in no
maner wiſe to practiſe or procuer ſecretly
or openlye, to aboliſhe, ſtoppe
or hinder, the preachinge and ſeruice
of god and of his holy goſpell, nor to
aduaunce ſet furth, or bring in anye
maner of papiſticall law or doctrine,
vnder paine to looſe his lyfe.
               Item, folowinge the ſame ſtatute
paſſed in the generall counſell, that
no maner of perſon dareth, or bee ſo
hardye, to moue, ſpeake, practiſe, or
procure, to ſolicite or vſe anye meane
what ſo euer it be, to alienate, tranſport
or chaūge in any maner of wiſe,
the Seniorie, and principalitie, and
ſtate of Geneua, otherwiſe then God
hath ordeyned it, and as it is at this
preſent, but that euery one according
to his power ought and is bounde to
mainteyne the libertie and fredome
of this citie, vpon payne to loſe bodie
and goods.
               Item, yf any do perceyue any maner
of conſpiracie, or practiſe, againſt

the ſayde principallitie, or againſte
the worde of God and his holye goſpell,
that he ought and is bounde, to
come incontinent to the Seniorie,
to reueale and declare it vnder the
payne aforeſayde.
               Item, that none ſay, or do, nor contract
or put in vre, anye thing without
the citie, which he dareth not do
nor ſpeake within the ſame, concerning
the worde of God, and his law,
and the reformation of his goſpell,
vpon payne to be puniſhed according
to his demerit.
               Item, that no man of what eſtate,
qualitie or condicion ſo euer he be,
dareth be ſo hardie to make, or cauſe
to be made, or to weare, hoſen or dooblettes
cut, iagged, embroydred, or
lyned with ſilke, vpon payne to forfeyte
.lx. ſhill.
               Item, that none bee ſo hardye to
miſname, or report euill of the princes
and magiſtrates, vpon payne to
be put in priſon, and chaſtiſed according
to equitie and iuſtice.
               Item, that none bee ſo hardye to
ſpeake euil, or miſname, or ſlaunder,

the miniſters of the worde of God vnder
the ſame payne.
               Item, that no maner of perſonne
of what eſtate qualitie or condicion
ſoeuer he be, ſhall not take or ioyne
vnto him anye ſuſpect perſon or of euyl
lyfe nor vacaboūds what ſoeuer
they be, but ſuch people that haue no
meane to lyue ſhall withdrawe them
ſelues within three dayes next folowing,
vpon paine to be chaſtiſed according
as the caſe requireth.
               Item, that none ſhall let any maner
of houſe or chamber to anye vnknowen
perſon, without lycence of
the Seniorie, and their captaine or
dyzener, vpon payne to forfeyte for
euery tyme, lx. ſhil.
               Item, that none bee ſo hardye to
walke by nighte in the towne after
nyne of the clocke, with out candell
lighte, and alſo a lawefull cauſe, except
thoſe whiche bee appoynted for
the watche, vpon payne to bee put in
priſon thre daies and to pay, lx. ſhil.
               Item, that euery one according to
his qualitie &amp; power ought to be furniſhed
wt armour &amp; weapon, &amp; to bee

obedient to his capitaine, lieutenant
and dizener and other officers appointed
for the affaires of the warres vnder
paine of thre traictes with a cord.
               Item, that none ſhall forſake 
                     〈◊〉
                  
citie, to ſerue anye foreyne prince in
his warres, withoute lycence of the
Seniorie, vpon payne of the indignation
of the ſayde Seniorie.
               Item, that none of what eſtate or
qualitie ſo euer he bee, dareth bee ſo
hardye to oppropriate to hym ſelfe
that whiche is common, vpon payne
to bee punyſhed according to the exigent
of the caſe.
               Item, that no ſtraunger ſhall ſell
any marchaundiſe, but vpon the thre
market dayes openly, and in the common
places, vpon the payne compriſed
in the texte of the fraunches.
               Item, that no maner of perſon
tranſport or cary out of the citie any
maner of buyllion, excepte he haue
fyrſte preſented it to the maiſter of
the mynte, vpon payne of loſſe of the
ſayde buyllion, and for euerye tyme
ſo doing, to forfeyte three ſcore ſhillynges.
               
                  
Item, that none ſhall bye nor contract
with anye of the citie, beinge
within the age of .xxv. yeres, without
the licence of his Tutour or Gardein
appointed for the ſame, vpon
paine to looſe the money delyuered,
and the contracte to be voide, and to
be reproued by iuſtice.
               Item, that no maner of perſons,
what ſo euer they be, ſhall ſinge any
vayne, filthye, or diſhoneſt ſonges,
neither daunce, or make maſkes,
mummeries, nor any diſguyſinge in
anye maner of wyſe, vpon payne to
bee put three dayes in priſon, with
bread and water onely, and for euetyme
.lx. ſhill.
               Item, that none bee ſo hardye, but
expreſſely defende generallye ye none
do outrage, iniurie or wronge, to another
in any maner of wyſe, nor alſo
to moue or raiſe vp, any rumour, chiding,
brauling, ſtryuing, queſtions,
or debate, in no maner of wiſe what
ſoeuer it be, vpon payne of .lx. ſhill.
and to be put in priſon &amp; puniſhed accordinge
to the demerit and exigent
of the caſe, by ye extremitie of iuſtice.
               
                  
Item that no cittezen burgeoys or
inhabitaūt of this citie of what eſtate
qualitie or condicion ſoeuer he be hauinge
houſe or houſholde reſydent in
this citie, dareth be ſo hardye to goe
from henceforth to eate, or drinke, in
anye tauerne,Note. Celler, ſhoppe, in anye
maner of wyſe: and alſo that no hoſts
nor Tauerners ſhall geue to eate, or
drinke, any of the aforeſayde citezens
burgeois or inhabitaūtes, vpon paine
for euery tyme thre ſcore ſhillinges,
payable as wel for ye hoſte as ye other.
               Item that euery notarie ſworne to
this citie ought and is boūde to cauſe
to be ſealed all and ſingnler publique
Inſtrumentes, which he ſhal receyue
accordinge to the ordynaunces of the
towne, and make expedicion to the
partyes vpon payne for euery tyme,
three ſcore ſhillings.
               Item y• none doe producte to helpe
him ſelfe with anye iudiciall acte, ordinaunce,
letters, patentes, nor publike
inſtrumentes, made and ſet forth
in this citie, excepte they be firſt ſealed
vpon paine of .lx. ſhil
               Item that al notaries be ſworne to

this citie ought and are bounde in receyuinge
the Inſtrumentes of anye
thinges recouered, dilygently to enquire
and knowe of the parties what
title, or by what meanes, they come
by thoſe goodes of which thoſe inſtruments
be made, and to reueale it, and
bring the deſignacions of all ſuch inſtrumentes,
which by them ſhalbe receiued
into the hādes of the Seniors,
committed for the chamber of accomptes
for this citie, euery thre monethes,
vpon payne for euerye tyme
.lx. ſhil.
               Item that euery one is bounde to
reueale vnto oure moſte redoubted
Seniors, all thoſe perſons, which they
ſhall perceaue or knowe, to be offenders
againſt theſe preſent ordinaunces
and proclamacyons, of oure moſt
redoubted Senyors, in all or in anye
maner of parte, vpon payne to be reproued
by the othe whyche they owe
to the towne.
               ¶Made and paſſed in the ordinarie
counſell of Geneua.
            
            
               
               WE let you to weete on the partie
of oure moſt redoubted Seniors
Sendicques, and counſel of this
Citie, for as much as here to fore manye
ſtatutes edictes and lawes hath
bene publiſhed, &amp; proclamacions made
and reiterated, to incyte and moue al
perſons the better to frequent the ſermons
and to praye vnto god in the
churches and commō aſſembling: neuertheles
ſeing that this hath not had
ſuch effecte, as hath bene deſyred, and
of the contrarye parte, that god doth
nowe geue vs ſuche warning and admonicions
as all men may ſee, therfore
let al people of what eſtate &amp; condicion
ſoeuer they be, haue a better reſpecte
to doe their duetie, then hath
ben here to fore, and from henceforth
not to diſpyſe the commaundement
which is geuen vnto them: yt is foraſmuch
as god by ye great troubles, ſeditions,
&amp; warres, which is nowe riſſē
all moſte ouer al, doth ſolicite, moue,
and ſtyrre vs, to retourne vnto hym,
and to humble oure ſelues before
hym, for as muche as the daungers
be not farre from vs, and on the

other parte the enemies of the goſpell
ſhewe them ſelues more vehement
and more enuenimed and cruell than
euer was ſene, to extermynate &amp; rote
oute the true and pure faithe, and religion
of Ieſus Chriſt.
               Therfore to the ende that all maye
be diligent to come to the preachings,
to frequente and haunte the prayers,
to cauſe their familie to come thereto
to be exhorted, to preuent ye ſcourges
of god, which be very nere vnto vs as
we maye ſee excepte he haue mercye
vpon vs, and that this may be contynued
vntyll ſuche tyme as we maye
perceiue that al doe obey with a good
affection vnfeynedlye, vpon payne to
be noted, punniſhed, and chaſticed, as
rebelles, contempners of god, and diſpyſers
of hys commaundements, and
the Seniorye.
               Item eſpecyally vpon the wedneſday,
which is ordeyned for the daye of
extraordinarie praier, that al workes
ſet aparte, as well the heades of houſholdes,
as theyr families, ſhall aſſemble
them ſelues to heare the worde of
god, and thoſe which haue houſholdes

ſhall ſo parte the howers y• they may
be al, eyther at the firſt or ſeconde ſermon,
there to call vpon god with one
accorde, that he wolde haue pitye vpon
vs, and take vs into his ſauegard,
and retourne from vs all thoſe daungers,
whiche other wiſe be nere vnto
vs, vnder the ſaid paine.
               Item generally that they praie vnto
god, and cauſe their famylies and
houſeholdes to praye with them, that
he will haue pitye of his churche, and
of thys common welthe, and that it
may pleaſe him to fortifye vs in theſe
daungerous times, and tourne away
from vs thoſe daungers of warres &amp;
troubles, which be prepared agaīſt vs.
               Item that al citezens, burgeois inhabitauntes,
and continuers here y•
be able to beare armure, oughte to be
ready furniſhed &amp; appointed throughly
with armor and weapon, according
to their power, preparing themſelues
to lyue and to die for the defence and
maintenaunce of the holy reformacion
and euangellicall doctrine, which
god hath geuē, and alſo for the libertie
of this common welth.
               
                  
Item that all ſhal be readye &amp; preſt
incontinent at the ſoūde of the great
bell, be it by daye or by nyghte to be
founde in his place and quarter, vnder
their Captaine and dizener, or other
wiſe when they ſhalbe commaunded
by the Seniorie, vnder ye paine of their
indignacion and diſpleaſure.
               Item, that al, as wel inhabitaūtes
as other that be paſſyngers, whyche
haue not made their othe before the
Seniorie, and haue not lycence to inhabyte
and continue in this citie, ſhal
retyre them ſelues and departe within
thre dayes vpon payne to be put in
priſon and chaſticed as rebelles.
               Item that frō henceforth no hoſtes
nor hoſteſſes, nor other of this Citye,
whatſoeuer they be, ſhall not receaue
vnto them anye ſtraunger or paſſanger,
nor to kepe him aboue two nights
in their houſes, nor procure them
lodging in anie other place, withoute
demaundinge leaue expreſſlye of the
Senyorye, vnder payne of three
dayes impirſonment and to paye thre
ſcore ſhyllynges for amendes.
               ¶Made and paſſed in the ordinary counſell
of Geneua.
            
            
               
                  
¶Another proclamacion.
               
                  BE it knowen vnto you
on the part of oure moſt
redoubted Seniors Sendycques,
and counſel of
thys Citye, that the aduertyſementes,
whiche
contynuallye be geuen by the preachyng
of the worde of god, oughte
well to ſuffyce and to contente al people,
as wel men as womē to vſe themſelues
in all modeſtye, honeſtye, and
temperaunce, and to walke chriſtenlye
in dedes, wordes, and geſture,
as the holye ſcripture teacheth vs: neuertheles
experience teacheth y• contrary,
that is to ſaye, many by exceſſe
whiche they doe commyte in meates,
drinkes, and apparell gyuing offence
to other, and ſmall apparaunce of any
good reformacion, for ſome there be
whych ſo doe ſeeke theyr owne pleaſure,
that it ſemeth they are determined
to preuerte the order of nature,
to ſatyſfye theyr owne pleaſure and
diſſolunes, muche excedynge the
ſuperfluytie of the panyms and infydelles,
whyche is intollerable

amonge Chriſtianes, for theſe cauſes
oure moſt redoubted Seniors hauing
here before preuented other exceſſes,
and vyces, by ſtatutes and proclamacions,
for ye reformacion, profite, and
welth, and the greater aduauncemēt
of this common welth, and principally
to the honour and glorye of god in
the ſame, and being ſtedfaſtly purpoſed
and with deliberation, to prouide
firmely and dilygently for the obſeruacyon
of the ſame, haue nowe once
againe, aduiſed to prouide for ye aforeſaid
exceſſe, to the ende that by repentaunce,
and amendement of lyfe, the
wrath of god comming vpō vs which
we worthilye haue prouoked, may be
forſeen and tourned from vs. In conſideracion
of their parte it is expreſly
forbidden and defended to all and
euery one of what eſtate qualitie and
condicion ſoeuer they be, yt they ſhall
not commyt anye exceſſe in meates,
or drinkes, be it at mariages, bankettes,
feaſtes, or other wyſe, whether
in apparell or clothing: but euery one
ought and is bounde in theſe caſes to
beare hym ſelfe modeſtly, and clothe

him ſelfe honeſtly, ſoberly, and ſimply
according to his eſtate, vpon paine of
three ſcore ſhillinges for euery tyme
when it ſhalbe knowen they doe the
contrarye, and moreouer thoſe that
doe perſeuer and continue obſtinate
and rebellyous agaynſt thys proclamacion,
to be chaſtyced accordinge to
their demerytt.
               Item, that no manner of perſon of
what eſtate qualitye or condicion ſoeuer
they be, men nor women, ſhall
weare any chaines of golde or ſiluer,
But thoſe wt haue bene accuſtomed
to weare them, ſhall put them of and
weare them no more after thys proclamacion,
vpon paine of three ſcore
ſhillings for euery time.
               Item that no women of what qualitie
or condicion ſoeuer ſhe be, ſhall
weare anye verdugales, golde vpon
her heade, coifes of golde, billimentes
or ſuche like, neither any maner of embroiderie
vpon her ſleues, or other apparel▪
vpon paine for euery time three
ſcore ſhillings.
               Item, that no maner of perſon of
what eſtate condicyon or qualitye ſo

euer they be, men or womē, ſhal weare
aboue two Ringes vpō their fingers,
ſauing that vpon the day of their mariage,
they maye weare more, And the
daye after likewiſe: vpon paine for euery
time thre ſcore ſhillinges.
               Item that no maner of perſon what
ſoeuer they be making brydales, bankettes,
or feaſtes, ſhal haue aboue thre
Coorſe or ſeruices to the ſaid feaſtes.
and to euery courſe or ſeruyce not aboue
fower diſhes and yet not exceſſyue,
vpō paine of thre ſcore ſhillings
for euery time, frute excepted.
               ¶Made and paſſed in the ordinarie counſell
of Geneua.
            
            
               
                  ❧Enſtructions to gouerne Chriſtian
houſeholdes, and principally Innes,
tauernes, and victuallinge houſes, in
Geneua.
               
                  WHAT ſo euer he be that
ſhall receaue people in
to his houſe, let him gouerne
him ſelfe pryncipally
accordinge to the
worde of god, and al other
perſons whiche ſhall reſorte to

him, he ſhall inſtructe them to liue holily
according to the ſame, and alſo to
enſtructe his houſholde in the feare of
god and his commaundementes, gouerning
al his affaires reaſonablie &amp;
keping his houſe in good order.
               Alſo that he lodge not wythin hys
inne by his knowledge any people of
of a wicked lyfe, as whoremongers,
herlottes, drounkerdes, murderers,
theues, ſorcerers, heretikes, nor ſuch
like, &amp; ſuffer not within hys preſence
the name of god to be blaſphemed, nor
vnreuerently to diſhonour god by naming
the deuil, nor yt the ſacred worde
of god be in no wiſe ſlaūdered or blaſphemed:
&amp; alſo not to be forgotten to
render graces and thankes to god before
meate and after. Alſo not to doe
in any caſe to others that thou wouldeſt
ſhoulde not be done to thee remē
                  bring
that thou muſt make accompte
to god for all thynges: alſo lodge thy
people well and ſafely, and call vpon
god wyth all thye compaygnye before
they goe to bed, and make their
prayers.
               Sel reaſonablie, &amp; compte faithfully,

diſcharging thy conſcience before god
ſuffer no wicked plaies, nor vnlawefull
games, but mainteine &amp; aduance
the honour of god, excerciſing ye reading
of his holye worde, kepe no exceſſe
in table, meates, and drynkes,
neyther vſe ouer late drynkinge, or
bancketing, walke vprightly in veritie,
and truth, in all thy affaires, folowing
Ieſus Chriſt and his holy
doctrine, thus doing the lord
ſhall ayde thee, and in the
tyme of nede ſhall not
faile thee.
            
         
         
            
            
               ❧Other proclamations publiſhed by the
ſounde of a trompet, the .xxviii. daye of
Februarye, and the .xxv. day of March,
the yere of our Lord God .M.D.LX.
            BE it knowen on the behalfe of our
moſt redoubted lords Sendicques
and counſell of this Citie, that euery
perſon, oughte and is bounde to
come to heare the worde of god,That is wednſday and fridaye. principally
vpon ſondaye and the dayes apointed
for prayer, and at other times
whē they may haue laiſour, and that
euery perſon ſhall gouerne and rule
them ſelues accordinge to the ſame
vpon payne to be reproued by iuſtice.On ſondais at after none
            
            Item that euery perſon ſhall ſende
their children and (ſuch as be of age)
to the cathechiſme there to be inſtructed
and taught vpō paine of thre ſhillinges
when they ſhalbe founde lackinge.
            Item, that all ſuche as come with
ye children to baptiſme, ſhalbe there aſſiſtant
and to heare the ſermon, vpon
payne of .lx. ſhil.
            Item, that no maner of perſon doe
plaie or run Idely aboute the ſtretes
during the time of the ſermon, vpon

the ſondayes, nor none to open their
ſhoppes vpon the ſondayes or dayes
of praier, during the ſermon time, vpon
payne of fyue ſhillinges withoute
anye pardon.
            
               ¶For children.
               Item it is commaūded to euery perſon
of what eſtate ſoeuer they be, to
fetche home their children, be it ſōnes
or daughters that they haue, or maye
haue in the papiſticall countrey: and
it is expreſly commaunded and defended
yt from henceforth they ſend none
thether, nor ſuffer any to goe thether
accordīg to the cōmaūdements heretofore
geuē in yt behalfe: vpō paine to
encur the indignaciō of oure aforeſaid
lords &amp; counſel.
            
            
               ¶For ſwering.
               Item that no maner perſon be ſo
hardie to ſwere by ye name of god, vnder
payne, the firſte tyme to kyſſe the
groūde, the ſecond to kiſſe ye groūd &amp;
to pay .3. ſhil: for ye third to pay lx. ſhil.
&amp; .3. daies in priſō wt breade &amp; water, &amp;
for ye fourthe to be banyſhed ye towne
for a yere &amp; a day, according to ye commaundementes
heretofore giuen in
that behalfe.
            
            
               For blaſpheming.
               Item y• no maner of perſon doe blaſpheme

ye name of god vpō payne, the
firſt time to kiſſe ye groūd &amp; 24. houres
in priſō wt bread &amp; water &amp; to pay fiue
ſhil: for ye ſecond time to kiſſe yt groūd
&amp; two daies in priſonmēt wt breade &amp;
water &amp; .10. ſhil: for yt third time to be
impriſonned .3. daies wt bread &amp; water
&amp; lx. ſhil: &amp; further to be pūiſhed &amp; chaſtiſed
accordīg as y• caſe requireth.
Item ye no maner of perſō doe renoūce
or diſpit god, vpō paine of a great fine
&amp; to ſtād wt a torch ī his hād, &amp; if any
doe reſiſt theſe ordinaūces, yt beſyde ye
ſame paine or forfeit to be impriſoned
and chaſtiſed accordinge as the caſe
requireth
            
            
               ¶For playing or gaming.
               Item yt no maner perſō do play at ani
maner game for money vpō payne of
lx. ſhil. &amp; .3. day impriſonment.
            
            
               ¶Againſt printing or making of cards &amp; dies.
               Item ye none do make or cauſe to be
made or printed either to bye or ſell
cards, dies or any other papiſtical thī
                  gs,
ye be imprinted cōtrary to the holy
chriſtiā reformaciō, vpon paine of lx.
ſhil. &amp; loſſe of the marchandiſe.
               
                  
Item that no maner of men ſhall
goe to the bathes or ſtoufes appointed
for women, and alſo women not to
goe to thoſe that be appointed for mē
vpon payne of .lx. ſhillings for whoſoeuer
ſhalbe ſo founde, and aſmuche
for ye maiſter of ye ſtoufe for ſuffrīg it.
               Item that no manner perſon doe
ſing anye vayne diſhoneſt or rebaudye
ſongs, neither to dance, nor make
maſques, or mommeries, or any diſguiſinges
in no maner or ſort whatſoeuer
it be, vpon paine to be put thre
dayes in priſon with breade and water
and .lx. ſhillynges for euery tyme
ſo offendyng.
            
            
               ¶For reuerent vſing of the magiſtrates
and miniſters.
               Item that no maner perſon doe miſname
or raylle vpon the prynces or
magiſtrates vpō payne of impriſonmente,
&amp; to be further chaſtiſied according
to the factes.
               Item, that no maner perſon doe miſname
or raylle vpon the mynyſter of
the worde of god vnder ye ſame paine.
               Item, that no maner of perſon of
what eſtate ſoeuer he be, ſhall in no

maner of wiſe procure nor practiſe ſecretly
or opēly to aboliſhe, let, or ſtop,
or cauſe to hinder ye worde and ſeruice
of god and his holy euangelly, neither
to aduance or bring ageine the papiſticall
lawe, vpon paine of death.
            
            
               ¶Againſt diſſolute and wicked behauiour.
               Item yt no maner of perſon be ſo hardy
to vſe whoring, drōkenes, or rūne
idely by ye ſtreats, or to ſpend his time
foliſhly, or to wtdraw them ſelues frō
their occupaciō or facultie, but y• euery
perſō ſhal trauaile &amp; be occupied in
his vocaciō, vpō paine to be pūiſhed by
iuſtice, accordīg as ye caſe requireth.
            
            
               ¶For the preſeruacion and liberty of the citie.
               Item that no maner perſon (accordinge
to the acte made by the whole
counſell) ſhall or dare be ſo hardye to
ſpeake, practiſe, moue, procure, or vſe
anye meanes whatſoeuer it be, touching
alienation, change or alteraciō
of ye ſeigniory or gouernement of the
ſtate of this Citie of Geneua, otherwiſe
then god of his goodnes hath ordeyned,
and is eſtabliſhed at this preſent,
but that euerye perſon doe hys
endeuour as he is boūd, to mainteine

the holy euangelycall reformacion, ye
liberties and Franchiſes of the citie,
vpon paine to loſſe body and goodes.
               Item yf any doe perceyue any maner
of practyſe or conſpiracie againſt
the principalite of this city, or againſt
the worde of god, and hys holy Goſgelly
that he is būnde to come and reuele
it incontinent vnto the lords of ye
councell, vpon the ſaid paine.
               Item that no maiſters of craftes, or
prentiſes, of what occupacion ſoeuer
they be, ſhalbe ſo hardye to gather or
make any vnlawfull aſſembly, neyther
to vſe from henceforth anye maner
of ordinances or ſtatutes heretofore
made amonge their companyes,
but that they ſhal firſt preſent &amp; ſhewe
them to the lordes Sendicques, to be
reformed by them according to their
diſcrecions, vpon paine to forfeyt for
euery tyme offēding .lx. ſhillings and
otherwyſe to be puniſhed as the caſe
ſhall require.
            
            
               For brauling and ſcolding.
               
               Item it is expreſly defended, &amp; forbidden,
to euery perſō perticuler, and
to all ingenerall, to braull, ſkolde,
miſname, ſlaunder, or ſturre vp anye
rumours or falſe tales, either to quarel,
or doe wronge to any perſon, vpon
payne of impriſonment and to be
further punniſhed accordynge as the
caſe requyrethe, wyth the extremitie
of Iuſtyce.
            
            
               ¶For tauarnes.
               Item that no citezen, burgeoiſe,
nor inhabitant of this Citye, of what
eſtate or qualitie ſoeuer he be, hauing
a houſeholde or reſidence in the ſame,
ſhall from henceforth eate nor drinke
in anye manner tauerne, ſeller, nor
cabyn whatſoeuer it be, nor any hoſts
hoſteſſes, nor tauerners ſhall geue to
eate or drynke to anye of the ſayde
Citeſyns, burgeoyſes or inhabitants
vpon payne of .lx. ſhillynges, for euery
of them, and for euery tyme to
be payd aſwell by the hoſtes as the
geeſtes, as is aforeſaid.
            
            
               ¶Againſt daunger of fier.
               
               Item, yt no maner perſon doe beare
any candell light, into anye ſtabyll,
barn, or grange, or anye place where
lieth wood, coale, or ſtrawe, where
is daunger of fyer, excepte it be with a
lantarn, vpon payne of .lx. ſhillinges
for euery tyme.
               Item that no maner perſon doe ſhute
of anye handgun, harquebouſhe, or
dag, within the walles of the citie
vpon the ſame payne.
            
            
               ¶For ſuſpicions and ſuppreſſing of ſuddein
tumultes.
               Item that all citezens, burgeoiſes,
and inhabitantes ſhall take diligent
hede aſwell by night as by day (euery
man for his owne parte) for al maner
of goers or commers, and in thys behalfe
euery one hath aucthorite, to examine
any ſuſpected perſō, and to diſcouer
and reuele them to the lords.
               Item that no perſon ſhall take to
them anye maner of perſon ſuſpected
of anye euell-conuerſacion, or vagabondes
whatſoeuer they be: but ſuch
as haue no meanes to liue, ſhal depart
within thre daies folowing.
               Item when nede ſhall require eyther

for fier, commociō, or other trouble
that euery man, ſhal incontinent
repaire to his quarter armed with his
armour and weapon, vnder the commō
officers appointed for that charge
by the lordes, vpon paine of ye indignacion
of the aforeſaid lordes.
               Item that no ſtraungers which haue
not geuen their othes to the lordes,
and be not inhabitantes in the towne
when ſuch caſe ſhall happen (from the
which god defend vs) ſhal not be foūd
in any place abrode in the towne, but
being abrode ſhall incontinent retire
into their lodging, vnder the cuſtody
of their hoſt, vpon payne being found
to be impriſoned, puniſhed &amp; chaſtiſed
corporally, and otherwiſe at the diſcrecion
of the aforeſayd lords.
            
            
               ¶Diuers other good ordinaunces to be
obſerued aſwell of inhabitauntes
as paſſingers.
               Item that all perſons aſwell inhabitantes
as paſſingers and ſtraūgers
which haue not geuen their othe to ye
lordes, nor haue licens to dwell and
kepe houſe in the towne, ſhall retyre
within three daies, &amp; depart ye towne

vpon paine of impriſonment and to be
chaſtiſyd as rebells.
               Item, that no citezen, burgeoiſe, or
inhabitant of this city, of what eſtate
ſoeuer he be, ſhall lodge nor take into
their houſes any ſtraungers whatſoeuer
they be, neither let them anie
houſe, excepte fyrſte they haue giuen
their othe to the lords and be receiued
inhabitāts, hauing to ſhewe ye letters
&amp; ſeales of our ſayd lordes, vpon paine
of .lx. ſhillings for euery tyme yt they
ſhalbe found lodging, or receyuing or
letting houſes to any, cōtrary to theſe
preſent proclamacions, and further to
be puniſhed and chaſtiſyd as the caſe
requyreth.
               Item yt no maner perſon ſhall kepe
any Inne, tauerne, or ſeller, neyther
to bake breade to ſell, except firſt they
be admitted by ye lords, with licence
to ſet vp a ſigne, vpon paine to be puniſhed
accordingly, and beīg receiued
they ſhal ſell oute their wine to euery
one for theyr money.
               Item that from henceforth no hoſte,
nor hoſteſſes, or any other of thys citie,
whatſoeuer they be, ſhall receyue

anye trauayler, or paſſanger, to kepe
hym lenger then two dayes, nother
procure them lodginge in anye other
place, withoute axing licence of the
lordes vpon payne of thre dayes priſonment,
and to pay a fyne of lx. ſhillinges
accordinge to the former proclamacions.
               Item it is commaunded to al hoſts
and hoſteſſes that euery day they ſhal
come, and reuele or declare to ye lordes
al ſuch geſtes as doe come into their
houſes, and declare their names and
ſurnames, and from whence they doe
come, and thys to be done the ſame
tyme they doe come, or incontynent
after.
               Item the ſaid hoſtes and hoſteſſes,
ſhall take all ſuche armours as their
geſtes haue, as ſhertes of Maill, gons
or piſtoletes, and to kepe them vntyl
they depart, and to bare them, but only
their ſwordes.
               Item, yf anye ſuche geſtes ſhewe
them ſelues obſtinate, that incontynent
the hoſte doe declare it to the
lordes, that they maye take order
therin accordingly.
               
                  
Item, that all hoſtes and hoſteſſes
ſhal aduertyſe their geſtes and expreſly
forbyd them, not to be oute of their
lodging, after ye trompet ſoūde to the
watch, or ringing of the bell (whiche
is at .ix. of the clocke) vpon paine of ye
indignacion of the aforeſaid lords.
               Item that no ſtraungers be founde
vpō the towne walles, eyther olde or
newe, neither vpon the rampares or
towne ditches, but ſhall walke on
their waye directly, and doe that they
haue to doe in the towne, vpon paine
aforeſayd, excepte in thoſe caſes the
ſayde ſtraunger be lycenſyd by vs the
lordes Sendicques.
               Item that all hoſtes &amp; others, ſhall
make their prayers to god and gyue
thankes before meate and after vpon
paine of .lx. ſhillings, &amp; for euery time
being foūde or prouid, and if ye hoſtes
or hoſteſſes be founde negligent and
not doyng it, to be puniſhed furder▪ as
the caſe requireth.
            
            
               ¶For ſtretes and common places.
               Item that no maner perſon ſhal encloſe
or appropriat to hym ſelfe any
parte of the common or ſtreate, vpon

payne to be puniſhed as the caſe requireth.
               Item, that whoſoeuer ſhall fynde
anie thinge that is loſt, not knowing
the owner therof, to bring it to ye common
cryer, appoynted by the lordes,
who ſhal bringe it incontinent to the
ſayde lordes, they to kepe it vntyll he
that oweth it ſhall haue knowledge
therof, and to render it againe, vpon
paine to be puniſhed as it foloweth.
               Item that none ſhall kepe within
the city nor limites of ye ſame, gootes,
Hogges, or Geſe, vpon paine of three
ſhillinges for euery tyme.
               Item that none ſhall bie any victualles
or marchandiſe in the ſtrete of ye
citie, nor folowe thoſe that bye them
to any ſuch entent, but ſhall bie them
in the accuſtomed market places, vpon
payne of fyue ſhillinges, and loſſe
of the things ſo bought.
               Item that no ſuch as doe bie victualles
to ſell againe within the Citye,
ſhall bie any victualies, before .xi. of
the clocke, nor in ani other place then
in ye common market places accuſtomed
for the ſame, vpon payne of fyue

ſhillinges, and loſſe of the thinges ſo
bought euery time.
               Item that no victuallers doe bring
into the towne, any maner of victuall,
and eſpecially cheſe, butter, &amp; fyſhe, yt
is not lawfull or good, neither to vnlode
the ſame, but in ye market places
appoynted for that purpoſe, vpon
paine of fyue ſhillynges and loſſe of
the goodes.
               Item that no perſon ſhall enter vp
on an others bargaine, nor come betwene
hym and the ſeller, to defeate
hym of hys bargayne, vpon payne of
fyue ſhillinges for euery time.
               Item that no baker, cooke, miller,
or anye that ſelleth againe, ſhall bye
nor cauſe to be bought anye corn, vntyll
it be .x. of the clocke, the priſe beinge
ſet by ye offycer, as the maner is,
vpō paine of fiue ſhil. for euery tyme.
               Item, that all corn that is to be
ſolde, which ſhalbe brought into thys
Citie, ſhalbe ſolde at the next market
place to the gate, that it commeth in
at, and ſhall not be caryed to anye other
market, nor ſold by the way, vpon
paine of lx. ſhillinges.
               
                  
Item, that vpon the corn markets,
the byer nor ſeller ſhal not be arreſt
                     •
                  d
for cyuyll matters, nor commytted
priſoner, from thence.
               Item, that no butcher ſhall ſel any
fleſhe, but vpon thoſe market places
appointed for the ſame, vpon paine of
lx. ſhillinges for euery time.
               Item that none doe brynge anye
infected or corrupted fleſhe vpō paine
of .lx. ſhillinges &amp; loſſe of the things.
               Item that no perſon doe ſell anye
fleſhe, before it be ſene and tared by ye
clark of the market, appointed by the
lordes after the accuſtomed maner,
vpon payne of .lx. ſhillinges and loſſe
of the fleſhe.
               Item the ſayde fleſhe to be ſold by
iuſt &amp; true weights vpon payne yt he
that ſhalbe founde wyth falſe weyghtes,
to pay .lx. ſhillinges, and to be
chaſtyced for deſceyt and falſhode.
               Item, that no butcher ſell the
heades of anye beaſte by wayghte,
nor yet by peice mele, but whollie
and by eſtymacyon, vpon the payne
aforeſayde.
               
                  
Item that no butcher doe dyſguyſe
hys fleſhe, of oxen, ſteres, kyne, ſhepe
or other beſts whatſoeuer they be, neither
to cut in peces the kyne to make
thē ſeme to be oxe beffe, or ſtiere beffe,
nor to conterfaite any maner of fleſhe
to make it ſeme other then it is, vpon
payne to beare a torche in his hād
thorowe the Citie with the ſayd pieces
vpon him, and to be depriuid from
the exercyſe of butchery for euer.
               Item that no butcher doe choke any
beſt to make the bloude to ſtaye in the
fleſhe, neither to ſell any bloude from
Maie to September.
               Item that euery perſon ſhall kepe
iuſt and true weightes and meaſures
vpon paine to be reproued and chaſtiſyd
for deceyt, according as the caſe
requireth, and to paie fyue ſhillinges
to him that reuealeth it.
               Item that no maner perſon ſhall
contract or bargaine with anie of the
towne which is vnder the age of .25.
yeres, wtoute licens of hys gouernor
apointed for him, vpon payne to loſe
the money delyuered, the bargaine to

be fruſtrate, and to be reproued
by Iuſtyce.
               Item that al commyſſaries hauing
charge, dizeners and other officers of
this citie ſhall diligently take hede to
the execucion and obſeruaciō of theſe
preſent proclamacions, euery one in
his quarter, wtoute fayll, vpon paine
to be puniſhed as the caſe requireth.
               Item that none doe enterpryſe to
doe, ſaye, nor contract anye thynges
oute of this Citye, that he dare not
doe or ſaye wythin the ſame, concerning
the lawe of god and reformacion
of the Goſpell, vpon payne to be
punnyſhed, accordynge as the faulte
requyreth.
               Item that euery perſon is bounde
to reueale to the Magiſtrates all ſuch
as they doe know to be offēders ī any
of theſe preſent ſtatuts either in part
or in the whole, vpon payne to be reproued
vpon the othe that they haue
made vnto the Citie.
               Item that no maner of perſon doe
contemne anye of theſe preſent ordinaunces
or ſtatutes of oure aforeſayd

lordes Sendicques, neyther doe abſent
themſelues, nor departe yt towne
but to appeare when they ſhalbe lawfully
called, eyther in their perſons,
or by ſome of thers, or their houſeholde,
vpon the loſſes and confiſcacion
of their goodes, and
further punnyſhement
whan they ſhalbe apprehended.
               FINIS.
            
         
      
      
         
            ¶For the knowledge of their coyne
or money.
            Note that the ſhilling named here in
this boke, is but a ſouce of their money,
whreof three make foure pence
of ours.
            A deniere is noted thus (d) ix. of them
make but a peny of oure money.
            A floren conteyneth .xii. ſouce which
make .xvi. d. of oure money.
            A Franke is .xxv. ſouce of theirs,
which amounteth to ii. ſhillings ix. d
farthing of our money
         
         
            
            Printed at London
by Rouland Hall
and Thomas Hacket,
the 16. of Aprill,
in the yere
of our lorde
1562.
         
      
   

