
   
      
         
            The decease of Lazarus Christ's friend A funerall sermon on Iohn. chap. 11. vers. 11. preached at the buriall of Mr. John Parker merchant and citizen of London. By Tho. Gataker B. of D. and rector of Rotherhith.
            Gataker, Thomas, 1574-1654.
         
         
            
               1640
            
         
         Approx. 142 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01531
            STC 11656
            ESTC R212839
            99835846
            99835846
            72
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01531)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 72)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1065:16)
         
         
            
               
                  The decease of Lazarus Christ's friend A funerall sermon on Iohn. chap. 11. vers. 11. preached at the buriall of Mr. John Parker merchant and citizen of London. By Tho. Gataker B. of D. and rector of Rotherhith.
                  Gataker, Thomas, 1574-1654.
               
               [8], 48 p.   
               
                  Printed by E[dward] G[riffin] for Edward Brewster, and Fulke Clyfton, and are to be sold at the Bible on Fleet-bridge, and on New-Fishstreet-Hill,
                  London :
                  1640.
               
               
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Parker, John, d. 1639 or 40 --  Early works to 1800.
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
               Funeral sermons --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2002-03
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2002-04
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2002-05
            TCP Staff (Oxford)Sampled and proofread
         
            2002-05
            Judith SiefringText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2002-06
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            THE DECEASE OF LAZARUS CHRIST'S Friend. A Funerall Sermon ON Iohn. Chap. 11. Vers. 11. Preached at the Buriall of Mr. JOHN PARKER Merchant and Citizen of LONDON.
            By THO. GATAKER B. of D. and Rector of Rotherhith.
            
            
               LONDON. Printed by E. G. for Edward Brewster, and Fulke Clyfton, and are to be sold at the Bible on Fleet-bridge, and on New-Fishstreet-Hill. 16
                  •
               0.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHT VERTVOVS and Religious Gentlewoman, Mrs. JOANE PARKER, the Relict of Master Iohn Parker lately deceased.
            
               HAving beene, with much importunity and renewed reqests, Qotidian
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  onviti
                     •
                   es flag
                     •
                  tatu
                     ••
                   Fa
                  
                     •
                  iu
                     •
                   Instit. pr
                     •
                  f.incessantly solicited, by divers, who either had themselvs heard, or from others heard of, what was delivered at the enterrement of your late wor
                  •
               hy Consort, and either had knowne him in his life time, or taken notice of his course of life then related, to make that more publick, that was then uttered, in the audience but of a few to speak of, and by reason of the lownesse and feeblenesse of my voice, of the fewer; I was at length overwrought (though having formerly no such purpose) to condescend thereunto: the rather hoping that his examplary course of life and

cariage, with the good effect and comfortable issue of it, might be a meanes, through Gods blessing working together therewith, to invite, incite, allure and winne others to the like. Experience teaching, that Vivi
                     •
                  ur exemplis. Nec tam imperio nobis opus est qam exemplo. Plin. Paneg. 
                     •
                  lus succendunt exempla. qàm praedicamenta. Gregor. Dialog. l. 1. prae
                     •
                  . &amp; qi praeceptis non accenduntur, exemplis saltem excitantur. Id. moral. l. 9. c. 43. Plerum
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ad exercenda bona opera, aliena nos utiliter exempla persuadent. Ib. l. 22. c. 7. &amp; grex, qi pastoris v
                     •
                  
                  c
                     •
                  m mor
                     •
                  s
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   seqitur, per exempla melius qam perverba graditur. Id. de Past. l. 2. c. 3. Facilius suadent exempla qam verb
                     •
                  . Ambr. in 1 Cor. 14
                mans nature is of it selfe more prone to walke by example then by rule; and to follow precedents rather then precepts. Those also having this advantage of these, that 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Arist. Probl. lib. 18. q. 3. Longum e
                     •
                  st iter per praecepta; breve &amp; essi ax, per exempla. Senec. Epist. 6. Insuevit 
                     •
                  a
                     •
                  er optimus hoc. me, u
                     •
                   fugerem, exemplis 
                     •
                  i
                     ••
                  orum q
                     •
                  
                  
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   notando, Formabat dictis puerum sic, sive j
                     •
                  bebat ut f
                     •
                  ce
                     •
                  em qid, sive vetab
                     ••
                  . Flac. Satyr. 4.
                they shew not only what things are enjoyned, and how things enjoyned may be done; but they Admonetur audi
                     ••
                  aetas omnis, fi
                     •
                  ri posse qod factum est
                     •
                   Cypr. ad Donat. Melius homin
                     •
                  s exemplis docentur; qae in primis hoc in se boni habent, qod approb
                     ••
                  t 
                     •
                  ieri posse qae praecipiunt. Plin. in Paneg. Sermo qidam vivu
                     •
                   &amp; efficax exemplum ope
                     •
                  is est, 
                     •
                  acilè pers
                     •
                   adens q
                     •
                  d intendimus, dum factibile probat esse qod suademus. Bern. de Resur. 2. Adjuvari se ex
                     •
                  m
                     •
                  lis exoptat humana in
                     •
                  irmitas, qo facilius ipsa etiam nunc faciat, qae alios secisse ante cognosca
                     ••
                   Salvian. contr. Avar lib. 3. Ex aliorum enim factis fieri posse credunt, qod fo
                     •
                  te dum putant fieri non posse, pigrescunt. August. Epist. 134.
                take away also that common counter-plea of impossibility, which against all exhortation and admonition is by the multitude usually objected; by shewing, that such things as are required of them, are no other then have beene done by 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Acts 14.15. Ia
                     •
                  es 5.17.
                men like themselves; and may therefore be done by others also, and

among others 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . M. An
                     •
                  on
                     •
                  n. l. 6. Sect. 19. Tes
                     •
                  es suos contra nos Dominus ins
                     •
                  a
                     •
                  r
                     •
                  t, eum bora qae f
                     •
                  cere ipsi negligimus. ad correptionem nostram, ab a
                     •
                  iis facta demonstrot: ut in recti tudini
                     •
                   appe
                     •
                  i
                     •
                  u nil sibi mens nostra di
                     •
                  si ile aes
                     •
                  imet, qod ante peragi ab aliis videt. Gr. Mor. l. 9. c. 43. Nescio qo modo amplius ad c
                     •
                  o
                     •
                  it
                     •
                  tē excitamur, per fidem, qâ cred. mus vixisse sic aliqē; &amp; spe
                     •
                   qa nos 
                     •
                  o
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ita posse v
                     •
                  vere, qi homines sumus, ex co qod aliqiho
                     •
                  ines ita vixerunt, mi
                     •
                  i. 
                     •
                  è desp
                     •
                  ramus. A
                     •
                  g. de Trinit. l. 8. c. 9.
                by themselves, if they will but as those before them have done, endeavour and enforce themselves thereunto. I remember a good saying of a Reverend Divine now with the Lord, that 
                  Mr. William Bradshaw in his Meditations on Christ. Tempt. MS.
                
               a good great man is a great Moat in the Devils Eye: for that the exampls of those that are in eminent places, as they are Matth. 5.14. Tu to totius medio telluris in o
                     ••
                  e Vivere cognoscas: cunc
                     •
                  is tua g
                     •
                  ntibus esse Fac
                     •
                  a palam: nec posse dari regalibus unqam secretum viti
                     •
                  . Nam lux al
                     •
                  issima fati occultum nihil esse s
                     •
                  nit, latebras
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   per omnes Intrat, &amp; abst
                     •
                  usos explo
                  
                     •
                  at fan are
                     ••
                  ssus. Cla
                     •
                  dian de Honor. Coss. 4. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Herodim. l. 4. Perluc
                     •
                  t omne regi
                     •
                  e vitium domus. Sen Agam. 2.1. Tibi nullum secret
                     •
                  m liberum est: in mult
                     •
                   l
                     •
                  ce fortuna 
                     •
                  e posuit. Idem ad Po
                     •
                  yb. c. 25. Nost
                     •
                  os motus 
                     •
                  auci sen
                     •
                  i
                     •
                  nt: 
                     •
                  ibi non magis qam so
                     •
                  ila
                     •
                  ere conti
                     •
                  gi
                     •
                  : multa circa te lux est: omnium in istam conv
                     •
                  rsi oculi sunt. Id
                     •
                  m de Clem. l. 1. c. 8. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Greg. Naz. in Patr. Qi m
                     •
                  gro imp
                     •
                  rio praed
                     ••
                  i in excelso aetatem agunt, corum facta cuncti mortales novere. Sal
                     •
                  st. ad Caesar Ad 
                     •
                  e oculos aures
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   tra
                     •
                  is: 
                     •
                  ua facta notamus. Pedo ad Liv. more eyed of others, so 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Basil. apud Anton. 
                     ••
                  l ss. l 2 c. 1. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Nicet. in Al
                     •
                  x. Comn. l. 2. c. 4. Vua principis censura est, ae
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   perpetua. ad hanc dirigimur, ad hanc convertimur. Flexibiles qamcun
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   in partem d
                     •
                  cimur a princ
                     •
                  p
                     •
                  : at
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ut ita d
                     ••
                  am, se
                     •
                  ac
                     •
                  s s
                     •
                  mus: huic enim cari, huic prob
                     •
                  ti 
                     •
                  ss
                     •
                   cupimus: q
                     •
                  d d
                     •
                  ssimiles 
                     •
                  rust
                     •
                   asperant. Plin. paneg. Rex veli
                     •
                   honesta, ne
                     •
                  o n
                     •
                  n 
                     •
                  adem v
                     •
                  l
                     •
                  t. Se
                     •
                  . Thyest 1.1. Nā totus componitur orbis Regis ad exemplū; nec sic inflect
                     •
                  re sensus Humanos edicta valent, qam vi
                     •
                  a regentu. Claud. ut sup. R
                     •
                  ctè facere princeps s
                     •
                  os sacie
                     •
                  do docet. V
                     •
                  lleius Hist l. 2. &amp; contra, Vitia principes non selū ipsi concipi
                     ••
                  , e
                     •
                  iam in civi
                     •
                  a
                     •
                  es infundun
                     •
                  ; plus
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   exemplo qam pecc
                     •
                  to n
                     •
                  cent. Cic. de leg. l. 3.
                they draw the more after them, either to good or to evill. And I may well adde, that a r
                     •
                  ligious rich man is likewise (witnesse blessed Iob 1.10.
                
               Job) a great Moat in the Devils Eye: not only because such an one, having his heart enlarged

answerably to his hand, may Iob 29.13, 15, 16. &amp; 31.16, 20.
                by his bounty and beneficence do a great deale the more good, and that Gal. 6.10.
                where the Devill least liketh: but because also in such it is made to appeare, that by honest courses and Prov. 10.22.
                Gods blessing upon them, men may attaine unto wealth, as well as by fraud, deceipt, extortion, oppression, and such indirect wayes, as Hab. 2.9, 12.
                most strive to raise and advance their estates by, and Varo, regustatum digito terebrare saelin
                     ••
                   Contentus per
                  
                     •
                  ges, si vivere cum Iove tendis. Pers. sat. 5. hoc est, qod Flac. l 2. Sat. 4. S
                     •
                  mp
                     •
                  r p
                     •
                  uper eri
                     •
                  . without which they think wealth cannot possibly be compassed. Yea, let me adde in the third place, that a religious industrious man (and yet I see not well, Ephes. 4.28. 1 Tim. 5.8.
                how they can be severed) is a great Moat in the Devils Eye. For that by his
                  •
                aven and wise practise such an one maketh it manifest, that a man may well serve God in a constant course, and yet follow also the duties of his speciall calling; and that there is therefore no such necessity, as many, on either side faulty, pretend, of neglect of the one, if the other be diligently attended; but that 
                  1 Cor. 7.20, 24. Vbi vo
                     •
                  atio duplex, in qâ, ad qam both of them may have their due time and place, without enterfering or justling out either of other, as the 
                  1 Thes. 4.11. 2 Thes. 3
                        •
                     7, 12.
                
               rules both of reason and Religion require. The common, yea, almost

generall abuse of the times, might well require me to adde, that a sober and temperate, as well as a religious (and yet Ephes 5.18. Rom. 13.13, 14
                        •
                     
                  
                what Religion can be, where excesse reigneth?) but yet, that a sober and temperate Merchant or Tradesman, may well be reckoned among those Moates, that disturbe the common adversaries eye: since that by such it appeares, that men may have ordinarily, in orderly manner, mutuall commerce, trade, and traffick either with other, without 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , ut Athen. dipnos. l. 11. Persa
                     •
                  um ritu, qibus 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . vid. Plut. Sympos. l. 7. c. 9.10.
                beating every bargaine they make over a Wine-pot, and concluding it with braines equally distempered on either side. In these therefore and divers other respects, I supposed the example of this our worthy friend and faithfull servant of Christ might be usefull to many: and was in that regard the rather induced to satisfie the desire of those, that so instantly pressed me in it. Which having once concluded on, I knew none fitter to addresse it to, then to your selfe; who had chiefe interest under God in him, G
                     •
                  n. 2.24. 1 Cor. 7.4.
                by Gods own ordinance, while he lived; and may with fairest title and plea lay best claime to the memory of him now deceased. To you

therefore, beloved in our common Saviour, I tender it to remaine by you; for my selfe, as a monument of mine entire a
                  •
               fection to him, who is now with the Lord, and to his surviving for him; for your selfe, as a memoriall of what a precious Iewell it pleased God sometime to possesse you of, and to grace you with: yet not thereby to renew your griefe for your temporary losse of him, (if it may be so tearmed, when he is but, as Philem. 15. Deside an
                     •
                  us 
                     •
                  s
                     •
                   tibi, q
                     •
                  si absens, n
                     •
                  n q
                     •
                  si 
                     〈◊〉
                  : u
                     •
                   illum expectare, n
                     •
                  n amisisse videa
                     •
                  is. H
                     •
                  er. de N
                     •
                  p. he saith of Onesimus, gone from you for a time, that you may after a while againe receive him and enjoy him for ever) joyned with his eternall and incomparable gaine; but 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Basil orat. 5. Ne doleas, qod talem amiseri
                     •
                  ; s
                     •
                  d gaudeas q
                     •
                  d t
                     •
                  lem habueris. Hi
                     •
                  ron. in Nepot. Non 
                     •
                  oeremus, qod ta
                     •
                  ē amisimus; sed gratias agimus, qod habuimus, imò habemus. Idem in Paul. Non contri
                     •
                  lor, qod accepisti; s
                     •
                  d ago g
                     •
                  a
                     •
                  tias, qod dedisti. Idem ad Iulian. E
                     •
                  si dolemus ablatum, non oblivis
                     •
                  imur tomen, qod datu
                     •
                   suit: gratias agimus, qod habere illum meruimus, qo carere in tantum non volumus, in qantum non expedit. Bern. in Ca
                     •
                  t. 26. &amp; de Humberto Ser. 110. Tulisti, q
                     •
                  niam tuus erat. Nec pro nobis, qibus ille sublatus est, murmurandum; magis gratias agendum, qod tam di
                     •
                   concessus est 
                     •
                  obis. to minde you of his goodnesse who bestowed him upon you, and of thankfulnesse to him for the continuance of such a favour so long unto you. So beseeching God abundantly to blesse you, and all yours and his, with all spirituall blessings and sweet comforts in Christ, I take leave, and rest
            
               Yours ever in all Christian office, THO. GATAKER.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            THE DECEASE OF LAZARVS CHRISTS Friend.
            
               John, Chap. 11. Vers. 11.
               Our Friend Lazarus sleepeth.
            
            
               THey are the words of our Saviour Christ, more covertly intimating that to his Disciples, which presently after hee telleth them in plaine tearmes; to wit,
                  Summe.
                
               Lazarus his decease. And they need no curious Analysis; for the sentence is but short; nor large explication; for there is nothing in them ambiguous, but what our Saviour himselfe in the words following explaineth.
            In them we may consider;
                  Branches 2.
               
                  1. The person spoken of:1. and
                  
                     
                     2.2. His present estate and condition.
               
            
            
               
                  Branch 1.The person spoken of is described;

                  
                     
                        Person. his 1. Name.
                     1. By his name; Lazarus, or 
                        Ita Tertullian de idolatr. c. 13. &amp; Prudent. hymn
                              •
                            de exeq. Vide Rigalt. ad Ter
                              •
                           .
                      
                     Eleazer. For 
                        Drus. ad voc. Hebr. N.T
                              •
                           
                        
                      all is one: and it 
                        •
                     ignifieth one whose aide God is.
                  
                  
                     2 Relation.
                     2. By his relation to Christ, and his Disciples. Our Friend.
                  
               
            
            
               
                  Branch 2. Condition.
                His present estate and condition is expressed in a Metaphore. He sleepeth. That is, as our Saviour himselfe by and by after expoundeth it, 
                  Verse 14. 
               He is deceased, he is dead.
            
            
               
                  Points 5.From the words thus opened, these Points of instruction offer themselves unto us.
            
               
                  1.1. That every faithfull one is one of Christs friends.
               
               
                  2.2. That every friend of Christ, is a friend of those also that are Christs.
               
               
                  3.3. That Christs friends dye as well as others.
               
               
                  4.4. That death, to such especially, is but as a s
                        ••
                     epe.
               
               
                  5.5. That this their friendship never faileth: it surceas
                        •
                     th not in death, but surviveth their decease.
               
            
            
               
                  Point 1.And of these in order, as God shall enable, and the streights of time permit.
            First then,
            
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Cl
                        •
                     m. pro
                        •
                     rep
                        •
                     . I
                        •
                     ter b
                        •
                     
                     
                     
                        ••
                     s viros &amp; Deum amiciti
                        •
                      est. S
                        •
                     nec. de provid. cap. 1. q
                        •
                     nqam negare h
                        •
                     c videatur Arist. Eth. magn. l. 2. c. 11 
               Every faithfull soule is a friend of Christ.
            
            Every true Christian is one of Christs Favourites. It is the usuall style of Abraham, 
               
                  
                     
                        •
                     om. 
                  
                     •
                  .11. the Father of the faithfull; Gods friend. 
               2 Chron. 
                  
                     •
                  0.7. 
               To Abraham thy friend: saith Iehoshaphat to God. And, 
                  Es
                        •
                     y 41
                     ••
                  . 
               ye

seed of Abraham my friend; saith God to his people. And, 
                  Iames 2.23. 
               Abraham, saith S. Iames, believed God; and he was called Gods friend. So here, of Lazarus, a Sonne of Abraham, Christs friend. Our friend Lazarus, saith our Saviour. And to his Disciples elsewhere in generall, 
                  Luc. 12.4. 
               I tell you, my friends. And, 
                  Iohn 15.14. 
               ye are my friends. 
               
                  Iohn 15.15. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Clem. S
                        •
                     rom. l. 2. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Ib. l. 7. Potest ergo &amp; servus esse &amp; amicus, qi servu
                        •
                      est bonus. Aug. in Ioan. 85. Qos amat, amicos habet, nonservos, amicus fit de magistro, neque enim amicos discipulos diceret, si non essent. Bern in Cant. 59. 
               No more servants, but friends.
            
            This will more cleerely appeare unto us,
                  Reason 1. if we shall consider, what the common nature of friendship or amity is.
            
               Friendship is defined, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Arist. Ethic. Nicom. l. 8. c. 2. &amp; l. 9 c. 5. Amor, sive benevolentia mutua, non la
                        •
                     ens.
                
               A mutuall love manifested: or, more largely, A mutuall love and affection betweene party and party, manifested by some means from either to other. And such is there betweene Christ and the faithfull.
            
            1.
                  Branch. 1. There is 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Aristot. Rhetor. l. 2. c. 4. Amicitia est voluntas erga aliquem rerum bonarum illius, ipsius causâ qem diligit, cum ipsius pari volun
                        •
                     ate. Cicer. de Invent. l 2. 
               a mutuall love and affection required unto friendship. And such there is betweene Christ and the faithfull. For 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               Christ loveth them; and they love him.
            
            He loveth them. 
                  Ephes. 5.28. 
               Christ loved his Church; saith the Apostle S. Paul. And 
                  Apoc. 1.5. 
               to him that loved us; saith S. Iohn: and they love him. 
                  Iohn 16.27. 
               My Father, saith he, loveth you, because you love me: and, 1 Iohn 4.19. 
               we love him, saith S. Iohn, because he hath loved us. And againe, 
                  Prov. 8.17. 
               I love them, saith he, that love me: and,

               
                  Iohn 14.21. 
               if any man love me, the Father will love him, and I will love him too. So that 
                  Benè igitur ratio accepti a
                        •
                     que expen
                        •
                     i inter nos conven
                        •
                     . Tu me amas, ego te amo: meritò id fieri ut
                        •
                     rq
                        •
                     e existimat. Plaut. Mostel. 1.3. there is no love lost betweene Christ and his. 
                  Ej
                        •
                     s amor nostrum &amp; praeparat &amp; remun
                        •
                     rat. Bern. de dilig. Deo. cap. 3. Et nostrum libenter, qem praecessit subseqitur. Idem. Epistol. 107. He loveth them first: and they love him, because he loveth them: and againe, he loveth them the rather, because they love him. Sweetly therefore Bernard; 
               
                  Nemo se di
                        ••
                     idat ama
                        •
                     i, qi j
                        •
                     m amat. Q
                        •
                     modo enim redamare pigebit, 
                        •
                     qi amavit necdum ama
                        •
                     tes? Bernard. Epist. 107. 
               Let no man, whose heart can truly testifie for him, that he loveth Christ, make any doubt but that Christ loveth him. For how can he choose but love thee, when thou lovest him, 
               1 Iohn 4.10. 
               who loved thee then, when thou loved'st not him?
            
            
               
                  Branch 2.2. Unto friendship is required, that this mutuall love and affection betweene party and party be manifested from either to other. And so is it also betweene Christ and the faithfull: the love and affection they beare either to other is by them mutually made manifest from either to other. 
                  Iohn 10.14. 
               I know mine, saith our Saviour, and am knowne of mine
               
                  •
                I know them, and they know me. I know their love to me. 
                  Iohn 21.15. 
               Lord, saith Saint Peter to our Saviour, thou knowest that I love thee. And 1 Iohn 4.16. they know my love to them. 
                  
                     •
                   
                  Gal. 2.20. 
               He loved me, saith the Apostle: and, we know, saith Saint Iohn, the love that God beareth to us. And, 
                  E
                        •
                     hes. 3.18, 19. 
               that with all the Saints, ye may know the love of Christ, saith S. Paul againe. Yea, he hath manifested his 
                  Iohn 15.13. Rom. 6.8. 
               matchlesse love to them, by what he hath done and endured for them: by

giving himselfe for them, 
                  Ga
                        •
                     . 2.20. 
               He loved me, saith the Apostle, and gave himselfe 
                     •
                  or me. And, 
                  Eph. 5.25. 
               Christ loved his Church, and gave himselfe for it: and making a bath of his own heart-blood, to bath their soules in, for the curing and healing of them. 
                  Ap
                        •
                     c. 1.5. 
               He loved us, saith S. Iohn, and washed us from our sinnes in his blood. Besides that, hee hath given them his Spirit, for this very end, to 
                  Rom. 5.5. 1 Iohn 4.13. 
               seale up his love to them, and 1 Cor. 2.12. to make them know what, out of his love to them, hee both hath done, and will further do for them. And they manifest and testifie their, though farre meaner, love to him, by their diligent observance of him, and dutifull obedience to him; by 
                  Iohn 14.15.21, 23. 
               keeping his Commandements, and 
                  Iohn 15.14. 
               doing whatsoever he enjoyneth them.
            
            Againe,
                  Reason 2. there is a solemne league of amity betweene Christ and the faithfull. Just such as that betweene Ionathan and David. For as they 1 S
                        •
                     m. 18.3, 4. Q
                        •
                     modo Glaucus &amp; Diomedes in amicitiae 
                        •
                     ospit
                        •
                     litatis
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      mutuae 
                        •
                     esseram, 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Homer. 
                        •
                     l. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . to confirme that league of amity mutually betweene them, changed apparell one with other: Ionathan took Davids raiment and put it on him selfe; he took his own garments and put them upon David; So our blessed Saviour Christ hath changed apparell with us (a 2 Cor 8.9. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . sorry change indeed to him selfe, though advantagious to us) hath taken and put on himselfe our garments, not 
                  Heb. 1.16. our nature alone, but even the sorry rags of it, 
                  Heb. 4.15. Rom. 1.3. our infirmities, by participation, and 
                  Esay 53.4, 5, 6. 2 Cor. 5.21. 1 Pet. 2.24. our iniquities also, by imputation, and he hath taken his owne raiment and put it upon us,

               1 Cor. 1.30. the rich roabe of his merits, and the royall roabes of his holinesse and righteousnesse; 
                  Rom. 3.24, 25. by imputation, unto justification, the one; and 
                  Iohn 1.16. by participation, for our sanctification, the other.
            
               
                  Reason 3.In a word, 
                  Heb. 3.14. he hath bestowed himselfe upon them; and 2 Cor. 8.5. they have given up themselves unto him. So that 
                  Cant. 2.16. he is not more his own now, then he is theirs: 1 Cor
                        •
                     
                   3.23. nor are they now more their own, then they are his. And what neerer or more intimate amity can there be then this?
            
               
                  Vse 1. for Information.
               Now the Vse hereof may first be for information, to informe us of the most high and honourable estate and condition, of every faithfull soule, of every true Christian: he is a friend of God, he is a favo
                     •
                  rite of Christ. It is noted as a speciall, yea a singular honour, in Zabud the Sonne of Nathan the Prophet, that 1 Kings 4.5. he was the Kings, to wit, King Solomons, friend. But behold 
                  Matth. 12.42. 
               a greater then Solomon here: and a greater honour therefore then King Solomons favour was able to afford. Every true hearted Christian, be he never so meane, be he never so contemptible in the eyes of the world, (for 1 Iohn 3.2. this dignity of theirs, worldly men cannot see, the world is not aware of) is, 
                  Iohn 15.15. not a servant only, (and yet were that honour enough; it is that the Apostle prefixeth before divers of his Epistles, as a matter of no small credit to him, 
                  Rom. 1.1. Philip. 1.1. Tit. 1.1. 
               Paul a servant of Iesus Christ) but a friend and favourite of him who is 
                  Apoc. 19.16. 
               King of Kings, and 
                  Matth. 28.18. 
               Lord of Heaven and Earth: then which what estate can be more high or more honourable?
            
               A second Vse may be for exhortation,
               
                  Vse 2. for Exhortation.
                to incite every one of us to labour to be of the number of those, whom this dignity, belongeth unto. 
                  Prov. 29.
                     •
                  6. 
               Many, yea 
                  Prov 19.6. 
               every one, saith Solomon, seeketh the face, 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                  
                     •
                   
                  Facies pro f
                        •
                     vore &amp; gratiâ Hebraeis passim. Num. 6.25. Psal. 4.6. &amp; 80.3, 7, 19. &amp; 105.4. that is, the favour, of the Prince, of the Ruler. And indeed what will not men do and indure, if there be any hope or possibility, as they conceive, of successe, to insinuate themselves into the favour of great ones? Creepe on all foure, as 1 Sam. 14.13. 
               Ionathan to get up the Rock, 
                  Obsequio gr
                        •
                     ssare, — &amp; leniter in sp
                        •
                     m Arrepe officiosus. Pers
                        •
                     a at
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      obdura: seu 
                        •
                     ubra canicula findat Infantes statuas, seu pingri tentus omaso Furius hyber
                        •
                     a
                        •
                      ca
                        •
                     â nive conspuit Alpes. Flac. Serm. l. 2. Sat. 5. debase themselves to the lowest and meanest services that may be, attend them with neglect of their own affaires and themselves. And why should a man then think any thing too much to do, too hard or harsh to endure, though it be to 
                  Matth. 16 24. Luke 9.23. the denying, forsaking, and abandoning of himselfe, (as 
                  Matth. 16.25. there is no way indeed but this to save himselfe) 
                  Phil. 3.8. for the indeering of Christ to himselfe, for the winding of himselfe into the favour and friendship of Christ. For alas, what is the greatest favour of the greatest Monarch in the World without this? or what is the greatest favour of the greatest on earth unto this?
            For first,
                  Difference 1. 
               Princes favours are fickle. A man may be in favour to day, and out of favour the next day: and so 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Qui summus bodiè cr
                        •
                     s futuru
                        •
                      nullu
                        •
                      est.
                aloft now, and as low as the lowest to morrow; yea, or sooner then so. 
                  Lubricu
                        •
                      est secundu
                        •
                      
                     
                        •
                     pud regem l
                        •
                     
                     cus.
               
               The second place in Court, said 
                  Plati
                        ••
                      in P
                        ••
                     . 2. 
               AEneas Sylvius sometime, is a slippery place. Yea, as it is 
                  Aul
                        •
                      cul
                        •
                     en lubricum. Senec. Thyest.
                
               slippery, so they that hold it, if they slip and fall (as 
                  Confragosa in fastigium dignitatis via est. Non in lubrico tantum illic statur, sed in praerup
                        •
                     o. Sen. Ep. 82. &amp; de tranq. c. 10. Quae excelsa videntur, praerupta sunt. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Plut. Symp. l. 2. c. 1. soone

they may) 
                  Psal
                        •
                     
                   73.15, 18. they come downe with a witnesse, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . N.Q. apud Stob. c. 105.— Ex alto magna ruina venit. Catale
                        ••
                     . Vi
                        •
                     gil. Et gravius summo culmi
                        •
                     e missar
                        •
                     unt. Maximin. Eleg. 1. they fall heavie; their downfall is very dismall and dreadfull. We have an example of it in 
                  Est
                        •
                     er. 5.11.12. and 7.9.10. 
               Haman: I cannot stand to relate it: you may when you will, reade it. Yea, I need not to relate it. For who is ignorant of it, that hath read, or heard read or told the story of Queene Esther? And this may befall those that are in favour with Princes, though they be never so faithfull unto them, never so carefull to please them. But Christs favour is not fickle: it is constant, it is permanent. 
                  Iohn 13.1. 
               Whom he loveth once, he loveth ever. Do thou 
                  Deut. 4.4. cleave close to him; and he will never leave thee: 
                  Apo
                        •
                     . 2.10. be thou faithfull to him; and 
                  Heb. 13.5. he will never forsake thee,
                  Psal. 89.32. he will never break his faith with thee.
            
               
                  Difference 2.Againe, Princes favours are no sure shelters. The greatest favourite may bee slaine in his Soveraignes eye, at his Soveraignes feet. Alas, 
                  Psal. 146.3, 4. how can they save them, when they cannot secure themselves? 
                  Dominus est vitae tuae
                        •
                      qisqis contempsit suam. Sen. Ep. 44. 
               Any one is Lord of their life, who sets light by his own life; unlesse the Lord be pleased to protect and afford them shelter against such. But Christs favour is a sure shelter. For 
                  Esay 63.1. he is able to save; 
                  Psalm. 68.20. to give issues against death; 
                  Ier. 1.19. to preserve his from death; to protect them so in death; that 
                  Iohn. 8.51. though they dye, yet they shall not dye; though 
                  Luke 21.16. they be slaine, yet there shall 
                  Luke 21.18. 
                     
                        •
                     t Acts 27.34. 1 Sam. 14.45. 
                     •
                   
                  Sam. 14
                     •
                  11. 1 Kings 1.52. 
               not an haires harme befall them; and to save them everlastingly after death. For 
                  Heb. 7.25. 
               he liveth for ever, to save perfectly all those that bee his.
            
               A third Vse may be for comfort,
               
                  Vse 3. for Consolation.
                
               consolation and encouragement, to every faithfull soule, to every true Christian. For hast thou Christ to friend? 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Eurip. O est. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . N.Q. apud Suidam. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Eurip. Herc. fur.
                Thou needest feare no evill; thou n
                  •
               edest dread no enemy. Thou mayest well rest upon him for matter of provision: thou mayest well relye upon him for matter of protection.
            
            1. For matter of provision. 
               
                  Philem. 17. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Fyth
                        •
                     g ap. Laert.
               
               
                  Branch 1. for Provision.
                
               For all is common among friends that are 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Euripid. Androm. Consortium rerum omnium inter nos facit amicitia, in commune vivitur. Sen. Ep. 48. Non, mebercule, 
                        •
                     am mea sunt, qae mea sunt, qam qae tua. Plin. l. 1. Ep. 4. No
                        •••
                      qod tuum est, meum est
                        •
                      omne meum est autem tuum. Plaut. Trin. 2.2. truly friends. And 1 Cor. 3.22, 23. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Clem. Protrept.
                if all things be Christs; then all things are thine, if thou be his; and shall not be denied thee, nor detained from thee, 
                  Psal. 34.10. &amp; 84.11. when thy necessity shall require them, and they may be for thy good. For well mayest thou reason here, as the Apostle of God; 
                  Rom. 8.32. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Chrys. in Rom. Hom. 15. 
               He that spared not his Sonne, but gave him up for us, how much more will he give us all things together with him? So of Christ; He that spared not himselfe, but hath given up him
                     •
                  elfe for me, hath bestowed himselfe upon me, hath not denied himselfe to me, how can he refuse to afford with all unto me, whatsoever shall be requisite, either for my support here, or for mine eternall welfare and salvation hereafter?
            
            2. For matter of protection.
               
                  Branch 2. for Protection.
                Hast thou Christ to friend? Thou mayest well reason, as the same Apostle doth in the same place, 
                  Rom. 8.31. 
               If God be with us; so, if Christ be with us, (for 
                  Rom. 9.5. 
               Christ also is God) who shall be against us? as, 
                  Si Deus co
                        ••
                     ra nos, qis pro nobis? Petr. Cellen. ep. 23. lib. 6. 
               if he be against thee,

who can be for thee? so, 
                  Qid tibi malipoteri
                        •
                      nocer
                        •
                     ? aut qid tibi boni poterit deesse, si 
                        •
                     lle te diligi
                        •
                     , qi de 
                        •
                     ihilo cuncta cr
                        •
                     avit? Bern. in Caen. Dom. Qid timendum, si adsit nobis, qi purtat omnia? Hebr. 1.3. Idem in Psal. 90 conc. 1. 
               if he be for thee, who can be against thee? And thou mayest therefore, having Christ to friend, say confidently with the Psalmist, 
                  Psal. 27.1 
               The Lord is my light, 
                     •
                  nd my salvation, whom should I feare? or of what should I be afraid? as long as he provideth for me, 
               
                  Psal. 23.1. Hebr. 13.6. 
               I shall be sure to want nothing: as long as he protecteth me, I need not to feare any thing. 
               
                  Psal. 23.3. 
               Though I walk, saith hee, through the vale of deadly shade, I will feare nothing, so long as thou art with me.
               
                  Vbi enim aut 
                        •
                     ecum male, aut sine 
                        〈◊〉
                      bene esse poterit
                        •
                      Bern. in advent. 1. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plut contr. Epicur.
                For where can a man be in safety without Christ? or where can he be but in safety with Christ?
            
            
               
                  Vse 4. for Caution.
               A fourth Vse may be for Caution, to disswade, yea, and deterre men
                  •
                from opposing or wronging any of the faithfull. 
               2 Sam. 18.12. How fearefull are men usually of offending a favourite? But all the faithfull are Christs favourites. 
               2 Cor. 11.28, 29. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Plut. de mul. amic.
                How chary are men of the credite, welfare, contentment, safety, and indemnity of their friend? even as chary as of their own; yea, or more. What is more usuall, then when we heare a friend traduced, or threatned, to say,
                  
                     •
                   
                  Rom. 16.4. 2 Cor. 7.3. &amp; 12.15. Phil. 2.17. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plato
                        •
                      in Symp. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Eurip. Iph. Taur. Dionysio caput Platoni 
                        •
                     bla
                        •
                     u
                        ••
                      
                     
                        •
                     i
                        •
                     i
                        •
                     ami, m
                        ••
                     n prius, inqit Xenoc. L
                        •
                     eri, l. 4. 
               speak what you please of me; but forbeare my friend: do what you will to me; but meddle not with my friend? And is not Christ think we, as chary, and as regardfull of those that be his? Yes undoubtedly. These are those, in behalfe of whom he giveth warning, and orieth, hands off; saying, 
                  Psal. 10
                     •
                  .15. 
               Touch not mine anointed ones. It is spoken

               1 Sam. 
                  
                     •
                  4.7. &amp; 26.9.11. of Kings, and that 2 Sam. 22.51. Psal. 18.50. &amp; 21.7.12. in a speciall manner, and 
                  Psal. 105.14. unto Kings there in their behalfe: as 
                  Ch
                        •
                     ysost. Theod. Euthymius, Aug. Prosp. Hugo Card, Lyran. in loc.
                the Ancients generally expound it. Doth thy conscience then tell thee; that such an one though never so poore a wretch, never so meane an abject, is a faithfull soule, a good Christian, one that sincerely feareth God, one that truly loveth Christ? 
                  Matth. 18 10. take heed how thou wrongest him. Thou shalt bee sure to heare of it againe at one time or other, if thou doest. He hath Christ to friend: he is one of Christs favourites, 
               
                  Zech. 2.8. Psal. 17.8. as deare unto him, as the very apple of his eye. 
               
                  Ier. 2.3. Matth. 18.6. Nor will he suffer any wrong offered in word or deed, unto any of his, to go unrighed, or unrevenged.
            A fifth use may be for triall and examination.
               
                  Vse 5. for Examination.
                Hereby then thou mayest try thy selfe, whether thou beest a friend of Christ, or no, and one that hath Christ to friend. (For 1 Iohn. 2.4. Frustra nobis in 
                        •
                     o plaudimus, cujus mandata non implemus. Hieron. ad Iovi
                        •
                     . l. 2. Ne
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      enim Christianus esse videtur, qi Christiani nominis opus non agit, cum nomen sine act
                        •
                      at
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      officio su
                        •
                      nihil sit. Salvia
                        •
                     . l. 4 c. 1 every professed Christian is not by and by 
                  Omne, amici, &amp; omnes inimici
                        •
                      omnes necessarii, &amp; omnes adversarii. Bern. in Cant. Ser. 33. 
               Christs friend. 
               
                  Phil. 3.18. Qi Christianos se dicunt &amp; Christo contradicunt. Aug. Ep. 171. Christiani in contum
                        •
                     liam &amp; opprobrium Christi. Salvian. l. 4. c. 11. There are some that so walk; and of professed Christians he speaketh; that they are enemies to Christs Crosse, and to Christ himselfe consequently) If thou beest a Lazarus; one that makest 
                  Psal. 70.5. 
               God, not the World thine aide, and thy stay. If thou beest an Abraham; or 
                  Luke. 19.9. 
               a childe at least of Abraham; one that 
                  Rom. 4.12. Gal. 4.12. Rom. 4.16. Eorum enim filli dicimur, qorum m
                        •
                     res imitamur. Orig. in Ezek. 16
                     •
                   
                  Vide Iuvenal. Sat. 8. 
               walkest in the steps of the faith of Abraham, 
               y who is the father of all the faithfull.
            
            But these things, you will say, are too generall.
               
                  Vse 6. for Admonition.
                We will descend therefore to some particular

notes in our ensuing discourse. And so passe we to the sixth and last Vse of this Point: which shall be for Admonition, to admonish us of the duties required of all those that professe or pretend to be in friendship and amity with Christ. 
               
                  Prov. 18.24. 
               He that hath a friend, saith Solomon, must carry himselfe friendly. If thou wilt therefore have a friend of Christ, thou must be Christs friend, (for friend and friend are Correlatives) thou must carry thy selfe as a friend unto Christ.
            
               
                  Duties 4.How is that? you will say.
            
               
                  Duty 1. Faithfulnesse.
               First, thou must be faithfull and loyall to Christ. For 
                  Prov. 20.6
                     •
                  
                
               faithfulnesse is especially required of friends, and regarded in friendship. 
               
                  Apoc. 2.10. 
               Be thou faithfull, saith he, unto death. Nor speaketh he of the faith that we 
                  Qam habe
                        •
                     us in Christum.
                
               repose and put in him, but of the faith that we 
                  Qam pr
                        •
                     sta
                        •
                     u
                        •
                      Christo.
                
               yeeld and performe unto him.
            
               
                  Notes 2.But when are we faithfull unto Christ?
            
               
                  Note 1.I answer. First, when we keep our heart and affections loyall and true to him, not suffering 
                  Iames 4.4. 1 Iohn 2.15, 16. this wicked world, or any sinfull lust (for these be the 2 Sam. 15 6. 
               Absoloms that filch our hearts from this our David) to sway in our soules; nor our affections to be so set upon any outward thing, even such as we may lawfully love, 
                  Matth. 10.37. 
               father or mother, husband or wife, childe, friend, or acquaintance, or ought else whatsoever, that it should either 1 Kings 11.1, 4. 
               withdraw our affection from Christ, or minish our love unto Christ, or 
                  Luke 14.26.33. that we should not be willing to relinquish it for Christ, if either 
                  Licet pa
                        •
                     vulus ex c
                        •
                     llo pe
                        •
                     d
                        •
                     at nepos, licet sparso crine &amp; 
                        •
                     usis v
                        •
                     stibus, ubera qibus 
                        •
                     e nutrierat, ma
                        ••
                     r ostendat, licet in limine pater jaceat, p
                        •
                     r calcatu
                        •
                      perge patrem: Siccis oculis ad vexillum crucis evola. S
                        •
                     lum
                        •
                      pietatis genus est, in hac re esse crudelem, Hier. ad Heli
                        •
                     d
                        •
                     r.
                it shall stand betweene Christ and us, or he shall be pleased to require it from us.
            
               Secondly,
                  Note 2. then are we faithfull to Christ, when we are affected as he is; when we love what he loveth, and hate what he hateth. For 
                  Idem 
                        •
                     elle &amp; nolle, 
                        •
                     a demum persecta am
                        •
                     ci
                        •
                     ia est. Salust. in C
                        •
                     til. Hieron. ad Demet. Ennod. l. 6. Ep. 24
                     •
                   
                  Sidon l. 5. Ep. 3. &amp; 9. Minut. Octav. Apul. de Philos. Ioseph. apud Cassi. an collat. 16. Ioan. Sari
                        •
                     b. polycra
                        •
                      l. 3. c. 4. P
                        •
                     t. Cluni. l. 4. Ep. 21. Fulb. Ep. 68 what is true friendship, but when men will and nill the same things? 
               
                  Psal. 97.10. 
               Ye that love the Lord, saith the Psalmist, hate that that is evill. Whereupon Augustine; 
                  Amas Deum? debes odisse qod odit. Aug ib.
                
               Doest thou love the Lord? thou must hate what he hateth. So art thou, or wouldest thou be Christs friend? thou must love what he loveth; and hate what he hateth. And what loveth he? 
                  Psal. 11.7. &amp; 45.7. He loveth piety, purity, mercy, charity, humility, sobriety, upright dealing, and the like. And on the other side, 
                  Prov. 6.16.19. &amp; 8.13. he hateth prophanenesse, uncleannesse, unmercifulnesse, uncharitablenesse, haughtinesse, drunkennesse, intemperance, falshood, unjust dealing, and the like. If then thou 
                  Zech. 8.19. Amos 5.15. 
               lovest, affectest, and labourest in the former, not so much because they conduce and are consentaneous to humane society, (for so one may do that is no friend to Christ or Christianity) as because Christ 
               1 Iohn 3.22. 
               liketh and loveth them, and they make thee 1 Iohn 3.3, 7. &amp; 4.17. Luke 6.35, 36. 
               like unto him: and 
                  Prov. 8.13. Amos 
                  
                     •
                  .15. Rom 12.9. 
               hatest the latter, not so much because they are contrary to civill society, as because Christ 
               
                  Zec
                        •
                     . 8.17. 
               hateth them, and they make unlike unto him, 
               
                  Colos. 1.10. whom thou desirest to please, and to approve thy selfe unto; yea, whom thou endeavourest 1 Cor. 11.1. Ephes. 5.1. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Marcus Imper. 
                        •
                     p. Iulian. in C
                        •
                     sar
                        •
                      
                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Iust. ad Diog
                        •
                      
                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Gr. Nys. de profes. Christ.
                to imitate, and strivest to be 
                  Rom. 8.29. Phil. 3.10. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Marcus Imp. l. 10. c. 8. like unto: knowing that 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plat. leg. l. 4. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plat. ib. l. 8. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Idem Lysid. qod &amp; Arist. Eth. l. 9. c. 3. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               likenesse

breedeth further liking and love: thou art then a true friend to Christ indeed. But on the other side, if thou canst not brook or abide, but hatest the former, which he loveth; and lovest and delightest in the latter, which he hateth and abhorreth; it is certaine, there is 
                  I
                        •
                     ter dispares 
                        •
                     nim mores non potest esse amicitia. Ambr. offic. lib. 3. c. 16. In taneâ morum discordia, qae potest esse concordia? 
                        •
                     ier. ad Nepot. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Plato Phadr. Clem. Strom. l. 5. &amp; Euseb. praep. l. 13. c. 13. 
               no friendship betweene Christ and thee, whatsoever thou maist professe or pretend to the contrary.
            
               
                  Duty 2. Observance.
               Secondly, if thou wilt shew thy selfe a friend to Christ, thou must diligently observe him. Friends, we see, are carefull to observe either other. Especially, if a meaner person have some great man to friend, how carefull and sedulous will he be to observe and attend upon such an one? And it is expected he should so do. So we finde in story, that it was the manner of those among the Romans that enjoyed the favour of any great ones, 
                  Mane salut
                        •
                     tum venio, tu diceris ante isse salutatum. Martia. l. 
                  
                     •
                  . Ep. 1
                     •
                  . Nec venit inanis rustici
                        ••
                      salutator. idem. l. 3. Ep. 
                  
                     •
                  8. Mercenari
                        ••
                      salu
                     
                        ••
                     tor circ
                        ••
                     volitat limi
                        ••
                      potenti. 
                        〈◊〉
                     , s
                        •••
                     um
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      regis s
                        •
                     i r
                        ••••
                     ribus a
                        •
                     gu
                        •
                     atur. Col
                        •••
                     l. p
                        ••••
                     at. l. 1. to repaire to them every morning, (that was 
                  Prima salutan
                        •
                     es at
                        •
                      altera 
                        〈…〉
                      art
                        •
                      l. 4. 
                     
                        •
                     p. 8. the first work they did, and 
                  
                     
                        〈…〉
                      c
                        ••
                     re
                        •
                     e, cu
                        •
                      pr
                        •
                     t
                        •
                     r li
                        ••
                     orem i
                        •
                     pell
                        •
                     t, &amp; ire pr
                        •
                     
                     
                     
                        ••
                     pite
                        •
                      
                     
                        •
                     ubeas
                        •
                      
                     
                        〈…〉
                      Ne prior 
                        〈…〉
                     
                   3. strived who should first do it) attend upon them so soone as they came forth, and tender themselves and their service unto them. In like manner, doest thou desire to maintaine friendship with Christ? thou must diligently and constantly attend upon him in his ordinances, in publick, in private: 
               
                  Psal. 2
                     •
                  .8. 
                     
                        •
                     
                   27.4
                     •
                   
                  &amp; 
                  
                     •
                  2.2. &amp; 84.2
                     •
                   
                  &amp; 
                  
                     •
                  22.
                     •••
                  
                
               repaire frequently to his house; attend at his threshold: (
                  Prov. 8.34. Psal. 84.4. he is a blessed

man that so doth) 
                  Col. 3.16. invite him oft to thine house: 
                  Luke 19.5. Iohn 14.23. he is not dainty of repaire to the meanest of his: 
                  Io
                        •
                     n 1.12. Luke 10.38, 39. he is willing to be entertained of us; and 
                  Prov. 8.31. delighteth in such invitements: especially take heed, how, when 
                  Apoc 3.20. 
               he knocks at the door of thine heart by the ministery of his Word or the motions of his Spirit, thou either refuse or neglect to open unto him. 
                  Ca
                        •
                     t 
                  
                     •
                  5.2.6. Such an oversight the Spouse committed, and she smarted for it, it cost her full deere. And 
                  Exclusit. red
                        •
                     
                     am? Ter. 
                        •
                     u
                        •
                     . 1.1 such unkindnesses oft make shrewd breaches betweene friends. Yea take heed of intermitting and letting fall thine usuall and wonted resorts. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . A
                        •
                     istot. Ethic l. 8. c. 5. 
               Intermission of entercourse breedeth strangenesse betweene friends And such intermission of spirituall entercourse; may, though not cut off all amity, yet breed no small strangenesse between Christ and thy soule.
            Thirdly,
                  Duty. 3. Obedience.
                our friendship with Christ must appeare, as by our diligent observance of him, so by our constant obedience to him. 
                  Iohn 14.15
                     •
                  21, 23, 24. Proba
                        •
                     io dilectionis ex
                        •
                     ibitio est operis, de dilectione conditoris m
                        •
                     ns &amp; vita reqiratur, nunqam o
                        •
                     iosus est amor Dei, operator si est; sin operari renuit, amor non est
                        •
                      Greg. in Evang. 10. &amp; Be
                        •
                     n. de temp. 106. &amp; can. Dom. q. 8. 
               If a man love me, saith our Saviour, hee will shew his love to mee by keeping my Commandements. And, 
                  Iohn 15.14. 
               you are then my friends, and manifest your selves so to be, when you do what I enjoyne you. Yea then indeed do we shew our selves, to esteeme Christ our friend, and carry our selves towards him as towards a friend, 1 Iohn. 5.3. Nil grave aut miserum est mihi, Qod re 
                        〈◊〉
                      voluisse: 
                        •
                     u tant in impera. Oedipus Antigonae in Thebaid. 
                  
                     •
                  . Minor huic est labor jussa exeqi, qam mihi j
                        •
                     bere: l
                        •
                     t
                        •
                     s imperia excipit. Senec. Herc. fur. 1.1. Facilia fiant cuncta charitati, 
                        •
                     uiuni Christi Sarcina levis est, qia ea una est Sarcina ipsa qae levis est, Dil
                        •
                     ctioni
                        •
                      
                     
                        〈…〉
                      poterit esse grave diligenti? Aut enim non diligit qis, &amp; ideo gravis est; aut di
                        ••
                     git, &amp; gravis esse non po
                        •
                     est. Aug. de nat. &amp; grat. cap. 69. when his Commandements seeme not

harsh and grievous unto us: when 
                  Ephes. 6.5, 7. 
               with heart and goodwill we serve the Lord Iesus, either in that we do for him, or for others at his request. That which a man doth lumpishly and heavily for a meere stranger, the same yet he doth readily and 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Liban. orat. 11. Non sunt onerosi labores amantium, sed delectant ipsi. Iulian. de viduit. c. 21. Nonsentiunt amanies, qod laborant. Sed tunc ab eis plus laboratur, q
                        •
                     ndo à labore qis
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      prohibetur. Aug. de Matth. 16.24. cheerefully for a friend. And that is it, that maketh 
                  Matth. 11.30. 
               Christs yoake seeme so easie, and his loade so light to his, that 
                  Non omnibus sunt onerosa tolerantibus, sed tolerare nolentibus, gravia vel levia facit animus tolerantis. Sicut nihil est tamleve, qod 
                        •
                     i grave non sit, qi invitus facit: sic 
                        •
                     ihil est tam grave, qod non ei, qi id libenter exeqitur, leve esse videatur. Salvian. de provid. l. 1. c. 2. Facit praeceptum liber, qi facit libens. Aug. de grat. Chr. l. 1. c. 13. seeme so unweldy and so unsupportable to others.
            
               
                  Duty 4. Patience.
               Lastly, it must appeare, as in matter of Obedience, so in matter of Patience; as in constant doing, so in patient enduring any thing whatsoever for him, even 
                  Luke 14.26, 33. to losse of liberty, limme, livelyhood, and life it selfe too. For what would not a man do or endure for a deere friend? Or what hath he not done and endured for us? Yea, appeare it must, not in patient only and quiet, but in willing and cheerefull enduring, undergoing and going through with, whatsoever we may be called to suffer and sustaine for his sake. 
                  Gen. 29.18. 
               Iacob, though hee served for Rachel some tearme of yeares, an 
                  Gen
                        •
                     
                   31.38.42. 
               hard s
                     •
                  rvice under an harsh Master; by day parcht with the heat, and by night nipt with the frost, yet he went cheerefully through with it, and 
                  Gen. 29.20. Amanti enim nihil difficile. Cicer. de orat. perfect. Qid grave n
                        •
                     n leviter tolerat, qi amat? Greg. in 1 Reg. 12. those many yeares seemed unto him but as a few dayes, because he loved her. So of the Apostles,

               Peter and Iohn, two of Christs faithfull friends, it is said, that when they had been in the Iewish Consistory, not rated and reviled, nor threatned only, but 
                  Act
                        •
                     
                   5.40. 
               beaten also, 
                  Ac
                        •
                     s 5.41. 
               they went away rejoycing, that they 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Oxymoron 
                        •
                     l
                        •
                     gantissimum. C
                        •
                     s
                        •
                     ub.
                
               were graced so much as to be disgraced for Christ. And, 
                  Rom. 5.3. 
               we, not rejoyce only, but even 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               glory, in our afflictions; saith S. Paul, another of Christs friends, and that in the name of the rest; 
                  Rom. 5.5. because the love of God 
               
                  Rom. 8.39. in Christ, and so 
                  Rom. 8.35. of Christ, is shed into our hearts by the Spirit that is 
               1 Cor. 2.12. 1 Iohn 3.24. 
               given unto us.
            
            In a word, what we do or endure for him, must come freely from us. 
                  Amor Affectus est, non contractu
                        •
                     . Ber
                        •
                     . de dilig. Deo. Amicitia non est vectigalis, sed liberalis: virtus enim, non qastus est. Amb. Offi. l. 3. c. 16 &amp; Cas
                        •
                     io. de amic. c. 2. Multum a beneficio distat negotiatio. Cleanth. Sen. de benef. l. 6. c. 13. 
               Friendship, as love the ground of it, is a free affection; not a trade or traffick for lucre and gaine. 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Arist. Ethic. l 8. c. 5. &amp; ibid. l. 9. c. 4. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Idem. Rhet. l. 2. c. 4. That is done by a man 
                  
                     •
                  reely, that is done for his friend; it is done as for 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Marc. Imp. l. 7. Sect. 13. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Ib. Sect. 32 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               himselfe: his friend 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Arist. Eth. l. 9. c. 4. Amicus alter ipse. Amb. desp. l 2. c. 7. being to him as himselfe. 
               
                  Benefi
                        •
                     iorum simplex est ratio, erogantur, non computantur. S
                        •
                     n. de benef
                        •
                      l. 1. c. 2. Interitura 
                        •
                     st rei 
                        •
                     a
                        •
                     tae dignitas, si beneficium me
                        •
                     cem facimus. lb. l. 3. c. 14
                     •
                   
                  Beneficium virtutis est; &amp; turpissimum id causâ ullius rei dare qam ut datum sit. Se intueri &amp; commodum suum, i
                        •
                     lud non est beneficium, sed soenus. Ibid. l. 4. c. 3. Non est beneficium qod in qastum mi
                        ••
                     i
                        •
                     ur, hoc dab
                        •
                     . hoc rec
                        •
                     piam, auctio est. Ib. c. 14. We must not stand to demand, or forecast with our selves, as those prophane ones in 
                  Iob 21.15. 
               Iob, What shall I get or gaine by what I do or endure? What shalt thou gaine by it? saist thou? It is gaine sufficient, and so art thou to esteeme it, that thou maist do Christ any service. A singular precedent have we of this freenesse of disposition in

that 
                  Acts 9.16. 
               choice vessell S. Paul: 
                  Phil. 1.20, 21. I care not what become of me, saith he, so that Christ be magnified in me, be it by life or by death. For all the gaine that I aime at both in li
                     •
                  e and death, is Christ: that is, to do service unto Christ, to bring glory unto him, as that D. Ayray in loc.
                
               Reverend Doctor of ours rightly expoundeth it. Yea as the Apostle, I may well say, expoundeth himselfe, where he telleth those of Ephesus at his taking leave of them, 
                  Act
                        •
                     
                   20.22, 23, 24. that he was going to Jerusalem bound thither by the Spirit, not knowing what might befall him when he should come thither: and howsoever from the Holy Ghost he was every where told, that bonds and afflictions there aboade him; yet did none of these things trouble him, nor was his life deere unto him, he regarded not what became of him, so he might joyfully finish his course, and discharge the work of his Ministery committed to him by Christ. That was all he de
                  •
               ired, and all that he aimed at, to do service to his Saviour, to finish cheerefully his task assigned him by him. And the like disposition who so can finde in himselfe, may assure himselfe that he is a true friend to Christ, and may build upon it, that he hath Christ to friend.
            
            And thus much for the first Point, that Every faithfull one is Christs friend.
            
            The second followeth, that Every friend of Christ,
               
                  Point 
                  
                     •
                  . 
               is a friend also to those that be his.
            
            
               Lazarus, saith our Saviour, not my friend, but our friend, mine and yours too: as well mine as yours, and yours as mine. And 1. Iohn 1.3. 
               the communion,

or society, saith S. Iohn, which you have with God and Christ, ye have also with us.
            
            And so it must needs be. For,
            1. 
                  Iohn 17.21. 
               All the faithfull are one,
               
                  Reason. 1. as in Christ, so with Christ. They are 
                  Ro
                        •
                     . 12.4, 5. 
               all members of one and the same Christs mysticall body; 1 Cor. 12.12. Caput &amp; corpus, unus est Christus. Aug. de Trinit. l. 4. c
                        •
                     
                   9. &amp; in Psal. 45. &amp; de verb. Dom. 49. &amp; 65. &amp; de temp. 40. Bern. Ep. 190. Beda in Ioan. 17. Omnes sancti &amp; fideles cum h
                        •
                     
                     mine Christo sunt unus Christus. Aug. de pec. mer. &amp; rem. l. 1. c. 31. the head and the whole body making up but one Christ. Nor can a man be a friend 
               
                  •
               o the head, that is an enemy to the heart or the hand, yea to the heele or the toe, to the lowest and meanest member of the body. 
                  Acts 9.4, 5. Non potest concordiam habere cum Christo, qi discordare voluerit cum Christiano. August. de verb. Dom. 57. Nor can he be in amity with Christ, who is at enmity with any member of that body, whereof Christ is the head.
            
            2. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . A
                        •
                     ist. Rhet. l. 2. c. 4. He that hath a friend must be a friend not to him alone,
                  Reason 2. but to his friends also. He therefore that is a friend to Christ, must be a friend also to them that are Christs friends; and such are all the faithfull; as hath formerly been shewed.
            The Vse whereof may be,
            First, to admonish u
                  •
                of our duty.
               
                  Vse 1. for Admonition.
                Do we professe our selves to be of the number of Christs friends? We must then be friends also to those that be his. We must shew our love to him by our friendly disposition and cariage towards them; and that,
            1. In affection.
               
                  Branch 1. Affection.
                We must have 
                  Rom. 12.16. Compatiamur affectu. Ambr. Offic. l. 3. c. 16. a sympathie, a fellow feeling, and fellow like affection with them. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Arist. Eth. l. 9. c. 4. &amp; Rhe
                        •
                     . l. 2. c. 4. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               Friends rejoyce in the good one of another,

               2 Cor. 2.3. as in their own; they 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               grieve for the evils one of another, as for their own: and 
                  Rom. 12.15. so must thou, yea so wilt thou, if thou beest a friend of Christ, 
               
                  Esay 66.10. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                
               rejoyce with his when they have occasion of joy, 2 Cor. 2.2. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Eurip. 
                        •
                     p
                        •
                     . Aul.
                
               weepe with them, when they have occasions of griefe. Yea so it is with the members, as of the naturall, so of this s
                     •
                  irituall body, 
               1 Cor. 12.26. 
               if any one be honoured, all rejoyce 
                     •••
                  h it; 
               2 Cor. 11.29. Heb. 10.34. &amp; 13.3. 
               if any one be afflicted, all sorrow and suffer with it. But how can we rejoyce in the good of our Christian brethren, when we 1 Cor. 13.3. 
               envie their welfare? How can we grieve with them in their griefe, when we our selves 
                  Rom. 14.15, 1 Cor. 6.8. 
               grieve them, or are 
                  Psal. 119.158. 2 Cor. 2.5. causes of griefe to them.
            
               
                  Branch 2. Action.
               2. In action: we must shew our love unto Christ by doing good unto them. 
                  Psal. 16.2. 
               O Lord, saith David, thou art my God, 
               
                  Acts 17.25. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Eurip. Herc. f
                        ••
                     . Clem. Strom. l. 5. Plut. de Stoic. Contradict. c. 37. Ipse est Deu
                        •
                      tuu
                        •
                     , qi 
                        •
                     o
                        •
                      eget bonis tuis. Aug. in Ps. 80. Nec ille collat
                        •
                      eget, nec nos ei qic
                     
                        •
                     am conferre poss
                        •
                     mus. Senec. de 
                        ••••
                     f. l. 4. 
                     
                        •
                     . 9. 
               thou hast no need of me; all my goodnesse, or well-doing, cannot reach unto thee. 
               
                  Ps. 16.3.
               But unto thy Saints that are here upon earth, to such as excell in grace and vertue, my desire and delight is to be doing good unto them. What I would, but cannot do unto thee, that for thee I do to them. So here, 
                  Acts 3.21. 
               Christ indeed himselfe is in Heaven; nor can ought we do reach to him, nor hath he need of it himselfe. But in his stead he commends unto us his poore limmes here on Earth. 
               
                  Mat. 26.11. 
               Me have you not alwayes with you; but my poor
                     •
                   members you have, and you may do them good when you will. 
               
                  Non eget miseriâ, sed eget misericordi
                        •
                     : non eget deitate pr
                        •
                     se; sedeget pietate pro suis. Salvian. cont. avar. l. 3. Yea though he wanteth not himselfe, yet he suffer
                  •
               th want in them. 
               
                  Mat. 25.35, 36, 42, 43. An non ege
                        •
                     , qi esurire, 
                        •
                     i sitire se qeritur
                        •
                      Salv. ib. 
                        〈◊〉
                     .
                
               I was, saith he, naked, and a thirst,

and a hungry, and sick, and restrained: and, 
                  Matth. 25.40, 45. 
               whatsoever is done to them, it is done to him, and whatsoever is denied unto them, it is denied unto him.
            
            And hereby therefore we may well try and examine our selves,
                  Vse 2. for Examination.
                whether we be indeed, as we professe, true friends unto Christ; if we shew our love to Christ, by 
                  Ga
                        •
                     . 6.10. 1 Iohn 3.17, 18. our beneficence and well doing to those that be Christs. Which if we faile in, we faile in truth of affection to him, whatsoever we may pretend. For as the Apostle reasoneth, 
                  Iohn 4.20. 
               How can he love God, whom he never saw, that loveth not his neighbour, whom he daily seeth? So, how can any man say he is a friend to Christ, whom he never conversed with, if he shew no friendship to such members of Christ, his Christian brethren, with whom hee daily converseth?
            Besides that,
                  Vse 3. for Consolation.
                it may be a comfort to every sincerely faithfull soule, that every true Christian is his friend; and he hath interest therefore both in the 1 Cor. 12.7, 25. 
               parts, and in the 
                  Rom. 1.9. Ephes. 1.16. Colos. 1.3. 2 Cor. 1.11. 
               prayers of all the faithfull, a great stay to a Christian soule, when it cannot satisfie it selfe with its own suits. Yea, that it hath a  stock going with them every where: though it have little of its own. But I hasten.
            The next Point is,
                  Point 3. that
            
               Christs friends dye as well as others. 
               
                  Iames 2.23. 
               Abraham Gods friend: and yet 
                  Iohn 8.52. Gen. 25.8. 
               Abraham is dead. 
               
                  Amos 3.7. Iohn 15.15. The Prophets Gods favourites: and yet 
                  Zech. 1.5. Iohn 8 52. 
               the Prophets are dead too. Lazarus Christs friend: and yet 
                  Vers. 14. 
               Lazarus is dead. The Apostles 
               
                  Luke 4.4
                     •
                  
                
               Christs friends: and yet 2 Tim. 4 6. 2 Pet. 1.14. 
               the Apostles are dead. Yea, 
                  Iohn 21.20. 
               the beloved Disciple,

Christs 
               
                  Iohn 13.23, 24. 
               chiefe favourite is dead. For 
                  Iohn 21.23. 
               Christ did not say, that he should not dye.
            
            And no marvell. For,

                  
                     
                        Reason 1.1. They are made 
                        
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Clē. Strom. l. 2. Iob 6.12. 
                           〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                        . Chrysost. de Compunct. 
                              〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                           . Greg. Naz. pro
                              •
                           aup.
                      of the same mould that others are: though they be possessed of pretious treasure, yet 2 Cor. 4.7. is it but an earthen vessell that the same is contained in.
                  
                     
                        Reason 2.2. They are subject to the like casualties that others are. For 
                        Eccle. 9.2. Cuivis po
                              •
                           est accidere, qod cuiqam potest. P. Syrus.
                      
                     all things here come alike unto all; to the good and the bad, the pure and the impure: to Christs friends, and Christs foes.
                  
                  
                     
                        Reason 3.3. They are by their naturall condition and constitution, as 
                     
                        Esay 40.6, 7. 1 Pet. 1.24, 25. 
                     the grasse; which though it be not cut downe, yet will wither of it selfe.
               
            
            
               
                  Objection.
               Yea, but as the Iewes reasoned, when they saw 
                  Ioh
                        •
                     
                   11.35. 
               Christ weepe at Lazarus his grave, 
               
                  Iohn 11.36. 
               Behold how he loved him: say some of them. And againe other some, 
                  Iohn 11.37. 
               Could not he that made the man borne blinde to see, have caused that this man should not have dyed? As if they had said, If he 
               
                  Iohn 11.5. 
               loved Lazarus so,
               
                  Solution.
                
               why did he suffer him to dye, whom he could have saved from death? So may some say, If the faithfull be Christs friends, why doth he suffer them to dye? when as 
               
                  Dan. 3.17. Iohn 21.22. 
               he might, if he pleased, deliver them from death?
            
            
               
                  Reason 1.I answer. 1. Because it is for their good. For they dye, 
               
                  Apoc. 14.13. 
               to rest from their labours; to be 
                  Rom. 6.7. Qod à malo liberat, qis non bonum pronunciabit? Tert. Scorp. c. 5. 
               rid of sin; to be 2 Cor. 5
                     •
                  4. Excutitur morte ve
                        •
                     ernus mortis. mors morte dissolvitur; vita a
                        •
                     fer
                        •
                     n
                        ••
                      confertur. Tert. ib. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . An
                        •••
                     han. Moriar? desi
                        •
                     a
                        •
                      m
                        •
                     ri posse. S
                        ••
                     . Ep. 24. 
               freed from death; to 2 Tim. 4.8. 
               
                  
                     •
                  eceive the reward
               
of their well doing; to 2 Cor. 5.8. 
               go to God; to 
                  Phil. 1.23. 
               be with Christ.
            
            2. It is according to their own desire that they so do.
                  Reason 2. Their desire with 
                  Luke 2.29. 
               Simeon is to 1 King. 19.10. be dismissed: they desire to be 2 Cor. 5.6. 
               eased of that burd
                     •
                  n, 
               
                  Rom. 7.24. 
               released from that body of death, that they beare here about them; 
                  Vide Methodii parabolam de caprifici radicibu
                        •
                      &amp; radicum fibris templi parietibus inna
                        •
                     is, q
                        •
                      nisi compag
                        •
                      dissolutâ eximi p
                        •
                     ni
                        •
                     us n
                        •
                     n possunt
                        •
                      apud Epip
                        •
                     an. in 
                        •
                     a
                        •
                     e
                        •
                     . 
                  
                     •
                  4. which cannot be done but by death; they desire to 
                  Psal. 120.5, 6. 
               leave this wicked and wretched world, and to 2 Cor. 5.8. 
               go to their own home, to their 
                  Iohn 14.2. 
               Fathers house, 
               2 Cor 5.1. to Heaven: they desire to depa
                     •
                  t hence, that they may 
               
                  Phil. 1.23. Iohn 14.3. 
               be with the Lord Iesus, and 
               1 Thes. 4.17. 
               abide with him for ever.
            
            3. It is for Gods glory that they dye;
                  Reason 3. and that they regard too as much as their own good. For 
                  Phil. 1.20. 
               Christ is magnified in them as well by their death, as by their life; as well by their pious and patient end and conclusion, as by their godly course of life and conversation. And a man may thereby as well glorifie God, though he dye in his bed, as if he dyed at a stake, or with 
                  Iohn 21.19. Saint Peter on the Crosse.
            
            4. They 
                  Iohn 8.51. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Callimach. Epig. 14. 
               dye not,
               
                  Reason 4. though they dye: death is no death to them: as they 
                  Prov. 14.32. 
               hope even in death; so they 
                  Iohn 11.26. 
               live even in death. 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Ch
                        •
                     ys. in Philip. Hom. 3. As others are 
                  Luke 9.60. 1 Tim. 5
                     •
                  6. 
               dead while they live; so they 
                  Luke 
                  
                     •
                  0.38. 
               live when they dye. As to the wordly their 
                  Per vitam ad moriem transitu
                        •
                      es
                        •
                     .
                
               life is but a passage unto death; So to the godly their 
                  Per mortem ad vitam reditus est. Am
                        •
                     r
                        •
                      de bon. mort.
                
               death is but an entrance into life: their 
                  Eccles. 7.1. 
               deaths-day is better to them then their birth-day: it is the 
                  Apoc. 21.4. 
               birth-day of their immortality, the 
                  AEternina
                        •
                     alu est. Senec. Epist. 102. 
               birth-day of their eternity.
            
            
               
               
                  Vse 1. for Admonition.
               Now it is so, that even the faithfull, though Chri
                     •
                  ts friends, yet are as well as others subject to death; are no more priviledged or exempt from it, then others are? This may then first serve to admonish us that have such friends, to make use of them while we have them, not to be like those fooles, of which Solomon; 
               
                  Prov. 17.16. 
               why is there a price in the 
                     •
                  ands of a foole to get wisdome with, when he hath no heart to make use of it? Nor like those, whom the Heathen man speaketh of, that 
                  Virtutem in co
                        •
                     lumē odimus: subla
                        •
                     ā ex oculis qaerimus invidi. Flac. carm. l. 3. od. 24. 
               cannot brook or abide such while they live, and yet lament for t
                     •
                  em, and wish them againe alive when they are dead: but 
                  Hab
                        ••
                     mus tanqam amissuri, tanqam recessuri, in ò recedentibus uta
                     
                        •
                     u
                        •
                     : tanqam extēplo abituros possideamus, Senec. ad Marc. c. 10. to make the best use we can of them for our spirituall good while we have them, not knowing how soone or suddenly they may be taken away from us.
            
               
                  Vse 2. for Consol
                        •
                     t
                        •
                     on, and Encouragement.
               Againe, it may serve as to encourage us against the feare of death, so to mitigate our griefe for the decease of such our friends; since that nothing therein shall betide us, or hath befallen them, but 
                  Psal. 49.
                     •
                  0. Esay
                        •
                     
                   57.1. what all Gods friends and Christs favourites have undergone before us, and doe daily undergoe. Nor would he suffer the same to befall those that are his intimatest friends, his best beloved, his dearest darlings, his neerest favourites, were there any 
                  Prov. 1.33. Nihil accidere bo
                     
                        ••
                      viro mali potest. Son. de provid. c. 2. evill in it, yea or were it not for their 
                  Rom. 8.28. Etiam pro ipsis est. Senec. ib. c. 3. good.
            
               
                  Point. 4.And so passe we to the next Point, to wit, that 
                  Sanctorum mors som
                        •••
                     . Hieron. in Matth. 25. 
               Death, to such especially, is but as a sleepe.
            
            So here, Our friend Lazarus 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . C
                        •
                     llimach. Epig. 14. 
               sleepeth, and 
                  Acts 7.60. 
               Steven, when he had so said, fell a sleepe: and, 
                  Acts 13.36. 
               David, when he had served his time, fell asleepe: and,

               1 Cor. 11.30. 
               for this cause some among you are sicke, and some sleepe: and, 1 Cor. 15.6. 
               whereof some are asleepe, and some yet survive.
            
            And indeed in divers respects is death to such as a sleepe.
            
            For 1.
                  Reason 1. 
               sleepe giveth 
                  Somnu
                        •
                      malorum domi
                        •
                     or, reqies animi: 
                        •
                     ars humanae melior vitae Senec. Herc. fur. Vtmors, sic somnus miseros foelicibus aeqa
                        •
                     . 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     , E
                        •
                     stath. ad 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Inde dictū, 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Aristot. Eth. l. 1. c. 13. 
               ease of paines and of troubles for the time: and so doth death to the faithfull: for 
                  Apoc. 14.13. 
               they rest from their labours, their troubles, their travels. But sleepe doth it only, as those 
                  Delinimenia, sive lenocinia morbi, non remedia. Sen. de beat. c. 17. &amp; Salvian. de provid. prafat.
                
               palliating medicines that empiricks usually give, that abate the paines for the present, but work no sound cure, so that the paine returneth after againe as fresh and fierce as before: whereas death with the faithfull worketh 
                  Iob 3.13, 18. Mors simulut veni
                        •
                     , dolores, no
                        •
                      a
                        ••
                     get, (non mitigat) sed aufert: ut remedium esse videatur, non poena. Ambr. de Cain &amp; Abel. l. 2. c. 10. Pro rememed
                        •
                     o data est, qasi finis malorum. Idem de fid. resur.
                
               a perfect cure of all evils either 
                  Esay 57.1, 2. corporall or 
                  Rom. 6.7. Reason 2. spirituall, so as they never feele them, or see them, or heare of them any more.
            2. Those that sleepe are 
                  Iohn 11.12. 
               not perished, are not dead; they are alive still: there is with them only a 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Arist. Ethic. lib. 1. cap. 13. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Sive, 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Idem de somn. cap. 1. &amp; 3. 
               suspension and an intermission of some naturall actions and of 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Aristot. Ethic. lib. 1. cap. 8. Hinc Heraclitus. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Plut. de superst. Anima in somno sic patitur, ut alibi agere videatur, dissimulatione praesentiae futuram absentiam ediscens. Tertul. de anim. cap. 43. all worldly imployments. 
               
                  Vers. 12. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Solet enim esse somnus aegrotantium, salutis i
                        •
                     dicium. August. in Ioan. 49. 
               Lord, if he sleepe, say they, he shall do well. In like manner,

               1 Cor. 15.18. Mors non est peremptoria, per qam non adimitur Vita. Ambr. de Cain &amp; Abel. 
                        •
                     . 10. those that sleepe in Christ, are not perished; though to the outward eye, to carnall sense they may so seeme. (
                  
                     
                        •
                     sai. 57.1. 
               The righteous, saith he, perisheth, and no man considereth it,) yet in truth it is not so: all 
                  Eccles. 9.6. Iob 14.21. Esay 63.16. 
               worldly imployments indeed are suspended and surceased with them, but they 
                  Esay 57.2. 
               rest in their beds, and they 
                  Luke 20.38. 
               live unto God.
            
            
               
                  Reason 3.3. Sleepe is but for a time; men are wont to 
                  Psal. 3.5. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Arist. de Somn. c. 1. 
               awake againe after a while; and 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Chrys. de stat. orat. 5. Stul
                        •
                     e qid est somnu
                        •
                     , gelid
                        •
                      nisi mortis imago? Lo
                        •
                     ga qi escendi tempora fata dabunt. Naso Amor. 2.9. 
               death is but a sleepe somewhat longer then ordinary. 
               
                  Iob 14.12. 
               Man, saith Iob, if he dye, shall not be awakened againe, untill 
               2 Pet. 3.10. 
               the Heavens be no more. But then 
                  Iohn 11.24. Vere dormit, qia de mor
                        •
                     e, velut de somno erat surrecturus. August. de temp. 104. he shall, at the worlds end, when he shall heare that voice of our Saviour, 
                  Esay 26.19. 
               Awake ye that sleepe in the dust of the earth, and 
                  Iohn 5.
                     •
                  8. 
               all hearing it shall arise.
            
            
               
                  Reason 4.4. Men usually rise from sleepe, 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Arist. de somn. c. 2. Hac reparat vires, membra
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      fessa levat. Naso Ep. 4. 
               refreshed with it, in better plight then they were when they layd them downe to rest. So shall the 1 Cor. 15.42.44 
               faithfull rise againe from death, in farre better plight then ever they were while they lived here. 
                  Psal. 17.15. 
               When I awake, saith David, I shall behold thy face, and shall be satisfied with thine image. For 1 Iohn 3.2. then shall we become perfectly like unto him, not 1 Iohn 3.3. in grace alone, but 
                  Colos. 3.4. in glory, too, when we shall see him as he is.
            
            
               
                  Vse 1. for Enco
                        •
                     ragement.
               Now is death then but as a sleepe to the faithfull? then first 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Chrys. de stat. orat. 5. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                  
                     •
                   
                  Ibid.
                why should any faithfull, any friend

of Christ feare death? It is a childish thing for a man to be afraid to put off his cloathes and go to bed; and what is death more then a stripping of us, that we may lay our selves down to rest? It is true indeed that in some diseases even sleepe it selfe is so 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plut. de sup. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Hom
                        •
                     r. Odys. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               restlesse and troublesome to the sick (it was 
                  Iob 7.14. 
               Iobs case sometime) and they are so ill after it, that they are 
                  Qomodo interest in ipsis, qi qotidiè dor
                        •
                     iunt &amp; exurgunt, qid qis
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      videat in somnis: alii sentiunt laeta somnia, alii torqentia, ita ut evigilans dormire timeat, ne ad ipsa iterum redeat: sic unusqis
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      hominum cum causâ su
                        •
                      dormit, cum causâ su
                        •
                      surgit. Aug. in Ioan. 49. 
               afraid and loath to sleepe: and so indeed 
                  Mors enim peccatori finis est naturae, non p
                        ••
                     ae. Ambr. in Luc. l. 7. c. 1
                     •
                  . it is, or may well be, in this case with the wicked. But it is not so with the godly: they may well say with the Prophet, 
                  Ierem, 31.26.
               I slept, and my sleepe was sweet unto me. The sleepe of death is no dreadfull, but 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Iliad. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                      Ibid. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                      &amp; 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                      dulcis qies mortis. Ambr. de bon. mort. c. 8. 
               a sweet sleepe unto them.
            Secondly,
                  Vse 2. for Comfort.
                is death as a sleepe, and such a sleepe, to the faithfull? 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Chrysost. de 
                        ••
                     at. orat. 5. there is no cause then to mourne and take on for such deceased. We reade of a people that 
                  De morib. gent. Autor. incertus. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Theod. de Chrysost. 
                        •
                     ra
                        •
                     . 3. used to houle and keepe an hideous coile every day at the setting of the Sunne, as if they feared he would never rise againe. Would wee not condemne such of extreame folly? or would we not deeme him little better then a mad man, that should stand weeping and wringing his hands over one that were falne asleepe, as supposing he would never awake againe? Yet the like doest thou, when thou doest so over the dead: since that they are but in a deepe sleep. 
               1 Cor 15 18. 
               They are fallen asleepe in Christ. And, 1 Thes. 4.13. Contrist
                        •
                     mur in nost
                        •
                     o
                        •
                     ū m
                        •
                     r
                        •
                     ibus, de necessi
                        •
                     a
                        ••
                      amittendi: s
                        •
                     d cons
                        •
                     lemur, de sper
                        •
                     cipiendi, ideo enim d
                        •
                     rmire dicuntur, 
                        •
                     t cum dormientes audimus, evig
                        •
                     la
                        •
                     u
                        •
                     os ne d
                        •
                     speremus. Aug. de Ve
                        •
                     b. Ap. 32. 
               I would not therefore,
               
saith the Apostle, that you should be grieved and sorrow for those that be 
               
                  D
                        •
                     rmientes appellavit, qi
                        •
                      resurrecturos praenunciavit. Aug. in Ioan. 49. 
               asleepe, as men that have no hope, as if you thought they would never awake againe. For 1 Thes 4.14. Manet ergo corum vita, qos manet resurrectio. Ambr. de obit. Valent.
                
               those that be asleepe in Christ, will God awake, and bring againe together with Christ.
            
            
               
                  Vse 3. for Confirmation
               Thirdly, this may helpe to strengthen 
               
                  Somnus mors dicitur, propter futuram resurrectionem, velu
                        •
                      evigil
                        •
                     tionem. August. Ep. 1 
                     •
                  0. c. 32. Id
                        •
                     o mortu
                        •
                     s consu
                        •
                     vit, Scriptura dicere do
                        •
                     mientes; qia ev
                        •
                     gilaturos, id est, resurrecturos vul
                        •
                      intelligi. Idem in Psalm. 87. Q
                        •
                     re enim dormientes dicantur nisi qia di
                        •
                      suo resuscitantur? Idem de verb. Dom. 23. Cum evigilav
                        •
                     ri
                        •
                      corpus, reddi
                        •
                     um officiis ejus, resu
                        •
                     r
                        •
                     ctionem tibi adfirmat. Ita per imaginem resu
                        •
                     rectionis fidem initiaris, spem meditaris, discis mori &amp; vivere. Tertullian. de anim. cap. 25. our faith in the assurance of the resurrection of the dead. Augustine speaking of those words of our Saviour, 
                  Mat
                        •
                     h. 9 24. 
               The Damosell is not dead, but sleepeth: 
               
                  Dormiebat: sed illi, qi poterat excitare
                        •
                      Aug. de verb. Dom. 44. 
               she sleepeth indeed, saith he; but to him who is able to awake her. So, 
                  Sor
                        •
                     ribus mortu
                        ••
                      erat; Domino d
                        •
                     r
                     
                        •
                     iebat, hominibus mortuus erat, qi eum suscitare non poterant: nam Dominus tan
                        •
                     â eum facilitate excitabat de Sepul
                        •
                     ro, qan
                        •
                     â tu non excitas dormientem d
                        •
                     lecto. A
                        •
                     gustin. in Io
                        •
                     n. 49. 
               Lazarus sleepeth here, but to Christ, who 
                  Iohn 11.43, 44. was able to awake him, and 
                  M
                        •
                     rtuos tanqam è somno suscitavit. Martial. Epist. 2. Sect. 1. to raise him up againe with a word. He sleepeth, saith he here: but I go to awake him. And indeed as easie a thing it is for Christ with a word to raise out of this sleepe, not 
                  Tardius qi
                        •
                      de som
                        •
                     o susci
                        •
                     a
                        •
                     ur, qam Lazarus de m
                        ••
                     te. August. de temp. 104. 
               Lazarus alone, but 
                  Iohn 5.28. Omnes pla
                        ••
                      ei, qi po
                        •
                     est exci
                        •
                     are, dormiunt. Nemo tam facilè excitat d
                        •
                     rmientes in lecto, qam Christus mor
                        •
                     uos in Sepulchro. August. de verb. Dom 44. all those, that shall be found deceased at the 1 Cor. 15.51. last day, as for any of us 1 Thes. 4.16. by making a noise to awake any one that lyeth fast asleepe.
            
            
               
                  Vse 4. for Admon
                        ••
                     ion.
               Lastly, is death as a sleep? We have that daily

then before our eyes that may minde us of death. 
               
                  Somnus mortis imago. Naso am
                        •
                     r. l. 3. cl. 9. Speculum mortis s
                        •
                     mnus &amp; exemplar. Tert
                        •
                      l. de anim. c. 24. Prop
                        •
                     nitur tibi corpus amicâ vi sopori
                        •
                      el. s
                        •
                     m, bla
                        •
                     dî qie
                        •
                     is prostratum, i
                        •
                     
                     mobile situ, qale ante vitam j
                        •
                     cuit, &amp; qale post mortem jacebit, ut tes
                        •
                     atio plasticae &amp; sepul
                        •
                     urae, exp
                        •••
                     ans anim
                        •
                     m qasi nond
                        •
                     m c
                        •
                     nlatam, &amp; qasi jam ereptam. Ibid. cap. 43. Our sleepe is a lively embleme of it: 
                  Qoties dormis &amp; vigilas, toties moreris &amp; resu
                        •
                     gis. Petr. Chrysolog. Ser. 59. 
               so oft, saith he, as thou layest thee downe to sleepe, and awakest againe from sleepe: so oft, in a similitude, as the Apostle 
                  Heb. 11.19. of Isaac, thou dyest, and risest againe from the dead. And well were it for us, could we take occasion thereby daily so to 
                  Deut. 32.29. 
               minde our end, that we might live 
                  Iob 14.14. in a continuall exp
                     •
                  ctation of it, and a continuall 
                  Psal. 90.12. 
               preparation for it.
            The last point is,
                  Point 5. that
            
               This friendship beweene Christ and the faithfull never faileth.
            
            It surceaseth not in death, but surviveth their decease.
            
            So here, 
                  Vers. 14. 
               Lazarus is dead, and yet, our friend still, saith Christ, and of Abraham, God, when he had beene many hundreds of yeares deceased, 
               
                  Esay 41.8. 
               Abraham my friend.
            
            And no marvell. For,
            1. Neither doth Christs love to them, nor theirs to him surcease, at their decease.
               
                  Reason 1. He ceaseth not then to love them still: for 
                  Iohn 13.1. 
               whom he loveth he loves for ever. Nor do they cease then to love him: nay they love him more then, then ever before, better then, then ever they did, or could do: they never did or could love him so well as then, when the grace of 1 Iohn 4.17, 1
                     •
                  . 
               love, as 1 Cor. 13.10
                     •
                  
                all other, comes to be perfected in them.
            
               
               
                  Reason 2.2. So far is it from this, that death should breed any enmity, or infringe that amity, that is between Christ and them, that it removeth utterly all the reliques and remainders of that, 
                  Colos. 1.21. that at first bred an enmity betweene God and them, and maketh some 
                  Esay 59.2. &amp; 57.17. &amp; 54.7, 8. 
               breaches betweene them now and then, while they live here, to wit, 
                  Rom. 7.24. &amp; 6.7. 
               sinne and corruption; which sanctification indeed eateth out here by degrees, but death utterly destroyeth.
            
               
                  Reason. 3.3. Christ and the faithfull, they part not in death. 
               
                  Ruth 1.17. 
               The Lord do so to me &amp; more too, saith Ruth to Naomi, if ought but death do part thee and me: and it is a solemne clause in our espousals, till death us 
               So should it be read, not, depart.
                
               do part. But it is more then so betweene this loving couple; betweene the faithfull soule and Christ. As David saith of Saul and Ionathan, 
               2 Sam. 1.23. 
               they are lovely and amiable either to other in their life, nor are they divided and sundred in death. 
               
                  Mark 6.16, 27. 
               The sword and death may sever the Christian mans head from his body, and his body from his soule: but neither 
               
                  Rom. 8
                     •
                  35. 
               sword nor 
               
                  Rom. 8.38, 39. 
               death can sever him either from his head Christ, or from the love of God in Christ.
            
            
               
                  Reason 4.4. Death bringeth 
               
                  Philip. 1.23. 
               Christ and the faithfull neerer together 
               2 Cor. 5.6. then ever: it bringeth them to a 2 Cor. 5.8. Apoc. 14.4. 1 Thes. 4.17. more entire &amp; immediate communion either with other, to 1 Cor. 15.28. 
               a fuller fruition either of other.
            
               
                  Vse 1. for Exhortation.
               First then would'st thou have a sure friend, a constant friend both to thee and thine, one that may stand by thee and stick to thee, when all other may forsake thee, yea of necessity must leave thee? Make Christ thy friend, and 
                  Gen. 28.15. Iosh. 1.5. Heb. 13.5. 
               he will never leave thee, though 2 Tim. 4.16, 17. all others do, when all others

shall. 
                  Ad limen carceris deduxerunt vo
                        •
                     . Tertul. ad Martyr. c. 2. 
               Your wordly friends, saith Tertullian, writing to the Martyrs in prison, tooke leave of you, and left you at the prison doore: but 
                  Vobisc
                        •
                     m carcerem intro
                        •
                     it. 
                        •
                     b. c. 1. 
               Christ your best f
                     •
                  iend went in with you. So thy wordly friends, yea all other thy friends will shake hands with thee and leave thee, if not before, yet at the 
                  Mundi buju
                        •
                      p
                        •
                     
                     
                     
                        •
                     tica mors. Peral
                        •
                     . Sum. de vit.
                
               posterne gate of this life, either at their death, or, at furthest, at thine: but if thou hast made Christ thy friend, he will never leave thee, he will for ever be thy friend, unto death, in death, and after death, unto all eternity.
            Yea, hast thou made Christ thy friend?
               
                  Vse 2. for Consolation.
                He will continue so 
                  Gen. 17.7. Exod. 20.6. Psal. 37.25, 26. &amp; 115.13, 14. not to thee only, but to thine also for thee. It troubleth men many times (and well may it, considering 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Eurip. Stob. c. 127. the untrustinesse and unfaithfull dealing of many professed friends) upon their sicke, and as it may fall out, their death-beds, to think whom they should intrust with their charge, their children, if God shall call them away. This may well ease in part the minde of the godly man in this case: Christ Iesus thy friend he will undertake the charge of them, he will be a trusty friend to thee as well when thou art gone, as while thou art here. 2 Sam. 9.1. 
               Who is there left, saith David, of Ionathans issue, that I may shew kindnesse unto for Ionath
                     •
                  ns sake? Nor could Davids love to his friend Ionathan surviving his decease, prevaile more with him, to move him to deale kindly with those that he left behinde him, then Christs love will with him towards those that have been, yea that are still, though deceased, his friends, to cause him to deale friendly

with those whom deceasing they leave here behinde them,
                  Vse 3. for Imitation.
                or at their decease commit unto his charge. It is the Argument that God useth to his people, to encourage them to depend upon him, not doubting of the continuance of his kindnesse to them, 
                  Esay 41.8. because they were the seed of Abraham his friend.
            
            And herein let us learne to imitate, our both Lord and friend, Iesus Christ. 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ; Eurip. Hecub.
                Let not our friendship to the faithfull deceased dye with them: 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ; Soph. Aj
                        •
                     c. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Stesichor. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Archilich.
                as the manner of the world, and worldly men is: but let us make it to appeare, that it lives and surviveth still with us; by 
                  Inimicitiae qo
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      suscipiende sunt propter amici innocentiam, cum restiteris vel responderis, qando amicus arguitur &amp; accusatur. Ambr. offic l. 3. c. 16.
               apologizing for them, and maintaining of their credit and good name, if need be; 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Eurip. Di
                        •
                     n Pr
                        •
                     s. orat. 37. by faithfull discharge of any trust reposed in us by them; and 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . D
                        •
                     mosth
                        •
                      Epist. 3. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Is
                        •
                     crat. ad D
                        •
                     m
                        •
                     n. Amicitia parentum rectè in liberos transferuntur, 
                        •
                     t charitas semel inita successorib
                        ••
                      e
                        •
                     rum haereditario jure proficiat. Symmach. l. 7. Ep. 87. Religiosa curae es
                        •
                     , qae amicorum liberis ex 
                        •
                     ibetur. Idem. l. 9. Ep. 31. Ad pos
                        •
                     er
                        •
                     s ami
                        •
                     o 
                        •
                     n cur
                        •
                     m tra
                        ••
                     fe
                        •
                     re debem
                        ••
                     ; ne fides cum hominibus interiisse vide
                     
                        •
                     tur. Id. l. 9. Ep. 45. by a ready performance of all friendly offices
               
                  •
                unto those they leave behinde them. Let us shew it then, I say, and 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Eurip. Ip
                        •
                     ig. Taur. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Me
                        •
                     nand.
                then most, when there may be 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Eurip. Herc. sur.
                most need of it, more it may be, then while they yet survived: that so it may be said of us, as 
                  Ruth
                        •
                     
                   2.20. she sometime of Boaz, that we cease not to shew kindnesse both to the living and to the dead; as 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . de Capan
                        •
                     o Eurip
                        •
                      Supplic. Caduca enim &amp; fragili
                        •
                      
                     
                        •
                     ffectio est, qae non &amp; amic
                        •
                     rum liberos amore propagato 
                        •
                     omplecti
                        •
                     ur. Symmach. l. 9. c. 31. 
               a true friend indeed will do.
            
               And so much for my Text,
               Testimony given to the Deceased. and the Points of Instruction observable out of it.
            Let me now crave your patience a little further, for the Application of it, and that that hath beene delivered out of it, to the present occasion.
            Of our deceased Christian Brother therefore, Mr. Iohn Parker, whose remaines are at this time to be laid up in 
                  Terra novissimè complex
                        •
                      gr
                        ••
                     i
                        •
                      j
                        •
                     m à reliqâ naturâ abdicatos tum maxime, ut mater, operiens, Plin. l. 2. c. 63. 
               the bosome of the Earth, as in 
               
                  Esay 57.2. Hi
                     •
                   disposicion in generall. 
               a bed of rest; I may well say, as in the words, so in the name of our Saviour, Ou
                     •
                   friend Lazarus sleepeth. For he was indeed a Lazarus, though not in name, yet in truth, one that made God his aide, his helpe, his strength, his stay. Nor was he lesse a friend to Christ, and to all that were Christs; to his Ministers, to his members; yea to all for Christ, with this aime, either to bring them on unto Christ, or to build them up in Christ.
            
            And he was indeed 
                  Eccles. 7.28. 
               a man of a thousand; yea such an one for a private man, 
               
                  Q
                        •
                     le
                        ••
                      vix repp
                        •
                     rit 
                        •
                     num Millibu
                        •
                      è multis. Aus
                        •
                     n. idyl. 16. as among many thousands, I suppose few to be found that might every way match him. For those things that are wont to be 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Greg. Naz. in Patrem.
                
               severally eminent in others, were in an 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Idem in Ba
                        •
                     il.
                
               eminency more then ordinary 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Id. ib.
                
               combined together in him.
            He was one of a sweet and sociable disposition;In Particular. of a meek and an humble spirit; just and upright in his dealings; faithfull in his trusts; firme and sure of his word; of a pittifull heart; of a bountifull hand; truly 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . De Pio Marc
                        ••
                      Imp. l. 6. Sect. 30. 
               religious, without superstition or ostentation;

zealo
                     •
                  s in 
                     •
                  n high degree, but with spirituall dis
                     •
                  retion; industrious in his Calling, (one that abhorred idlenesse) yet so as 
                  •
               is sedulity therein should not withdraw him from due attendance on better things; of a good understanding; a sound judgement; a tender conscience; a circumspect cariage; a strict course of life, yet without austerity or censoriousnesse: in a word, of a wise and prudent temper in all things.
            
            I remember a story in 
                  Plut. in Pr
                        •
                     c
                        •
                     pt. p
                        •
                     litic.
                
               Plutarch of an Artist at Athens, who being called among others to the undertaking of a piece of work for the publick, when one of his fellow-workmen had made a long speech, to shew them in what manner he would do it, if they would put it into his hands, he being a man of few words, but of good skill, said no more but this, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               As this man hath said it, so will I do it. To apply it to our purpose. We have spoken much
                  •
                of the duties that are required of all those that pro
                     •
                  esse friendship with Christ; their faithfulnesse to him, their ob
                     •
                  ervance of him; their obedience to him; their loving what he loveth, loving whom he loveth; and the like. Now of this our brother we may well and truly say, What we have said
                     •
                   he did: he made good all we have said in a methode, in a manner, in a measure more than ordinary. And for the making good of what I say, that which I shall deliver unto you, shall be the most of it, out of his own remembrances, (for he kept journals as well of his spirituall 
                     •
                  stat
                     •
                  
                and 
                  
                     •
                  mployments, as of his worldly reckonings and affaires) and the rest either from mine own knowledge, or the credible relation of those that conversed

versed most constantly and inwardly with him.
            When it pleased God to bring him first acquainted with Christ,
               His first Conversion. and to discover unto him the vanity of those courses that he had formerly taken; albeit he had a great measure of inward remorse, and was much humbled for the same, and he was now res
                     •
                  lved upon a new, and that a strict course of life; yet it troubled him not a little, that he could not shed teares, as he desired, for his sinnes, and his fore-passed excesses; that which made him somewhat doubtfull therefore of the sincerity of his then present repentance: nor did he leave earnestly begging of this grace and favour at Gods hands, untill it pleased God to vouchsafe it in great abundance unto him. In which te
                     •
                  res of his he professeth that he found more sound comfort, 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Eurip. Helen. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Greg. Naz. pro pauper. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     
                     
                        •
                      Chrysost. in Phil. Hom. 15. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Basil
                        •
                      Caes. Hom. 4. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Basil. Caes. Hom. 19. 
               more hearty joy, more true contentment, then all his former mirth and jolity, ever did, yea then all the mirth and merry company in the world (and he knew by experience to his griefe what such things meant) were able to afford unto any.
            
            Being now thus growne into some intimacy with Christ;Observa
                     •
                  ce of Christ by attendance on him in his Ordinances. that no strangenesse by neglect might accrew betweene him and Christ, he was carefull to maintaine it by a frequent and constant attendance upon him in his ordinances, both in private and in publick. For his ordinary addresses unto God in private:
               Ordinary. Private. he used prayer constantly, as 
                  Psal. 55.17. 
               David, and 
                  Dan. 6.10. 
               Dani
                     •
                  l, thrice a day; morning and

               evening with his fa
                     •
                  ily; and some other time of the day a part, either with his religious consort, if she were in the way, or in her absence, alone by himselfe. On the Lords-day his common course was, not as the manner of many. Yea the most, to lye longer in bed, and take their ease more on that day, then on others; but to get up early, that he might be an houre at least, if not more, sometime two, in private with God: after which he used to spend some time in prayer with his family: yet so, let me tell you, that the publick might not be drownd and swallowed up in the private;Publick. (for it was ever his saying, that the private must yeeld and give way to the publick) but that both he and his might be present in the congregation, as well at the publick prayers and service of the Church as at the preaching of the Word: after which publick performances also, his constant course was at his returne home to repeate with his family, and presse upon them, (which well he could doe) those things that had in publick been delivered unto them. And for the Week-dayes, once or twice at least, ordinarily he frequented the ministery of some of those of the best note about the City. And thus much of it I had from himselfe (the rest from those that conversed familiarly with him) when some halfe a yeare or thereabout before his decease, advising with me concerning some thoughts that he then had, of either abandoning, or abatement of his worldly employments, for the freer pursuit of spirituall things, which he most eagerly thirsted after, he related to me in particular

what liberty he had, notwithstanding his then present engagements by his trade and traffick, for the prosecution of the better part.
            This then was his ordinary course of addresses unto God, and attendances upon Christ. But besides these he had solemn days of humiliation upon speciall occasions:Extraordinary
                     •
                   Dayes of Humiliation. and no businesse of more then ordinary weight did he lightly undertake without some such imployment. It is said of Cornelius, 
               
                  Acts 10.4. 
               Thy prayers and thine almes, and 
                  Esay 58.6, 7. Qi vul
                        •
                      orati
                        •
                     nem suam i
                        •
                      coelum volare, fa iat ei duas al
                        •
                     s e
                        •
                     e
                        •
                     mosynam &amp; j
                        •
                     junium. Aug. de t
                        •
                     mp. 59. Erg
                        •
                      qi orat, j
                        •
                     j
                        •
                     ne
                        •
                     : qui jejunat, misereatu
                        •
                     : audiat petente
                        •
                     , qi petens opta
                        •
                      audir
                        •
                     : auditum Dei ape
                        •
                     i
                        •
                      sibi, qi su
                        •
                     m suppl
                        •
                     canti non cl
                        •
                     udit a
                        •
                     di
                     
                        •
                     um. Es
                        •
                     rien
                        •
                     em sentiat, qi vult Deum sentire qod es
                        •
                     
                     ri
                        •
                     : misereatur, qi misericordiam spera
                        •
                     : pi
                        •
                     tatem, qi qaerit, faciat: qi praestari sibi vult, praestet: improbus pe
                        •
                     itor est, qi qod a
                        •
                     iis negat, sibi postulat. Chrysolog. Serm. 43. these two constantly concurred, as with 
                  Acts 10.2. 
               Cornelius, so with him: for the day after ever abroad he went with the b
                     •
                  g, and no small summes in it, to distribute, where he supposed most need was, or deemed most good might be done: for neither did hee 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Isid. l. 1. Ep. 44. Collocare te vult Dous, q
                        •
                      habes, non projicare. Aug. de 10. Cho
                        •
                     d. cap. 12. Multi sunt, qi non d
                        •
                     nant, sed pro. jiciunt. Senec. Ep. 21. Beneficia nec in vulgus effundenda sunt: &amp; nullius rei, minin è beneficiorum, hon
                        •
                     sta largitio est. Senec. de benef. l. 1. c. 2. throw that he gave away, hand over head, but carried this, as 
                  
                     
                        •
                     sal. 112.5. other his actions, 
                  E
                        •
                     rat, siqis existima facilem rem esse donare, plurimum ista res habet difficultatis, si modo consilio tribu
                        ••
                     ur, non casu &amp; impetu spargitur: habebit sapiens sinum facilem, non persoratum; ex qo multa exeant, nihil excidat. Senec. de beat. 
                        •
                     it. cap. 24. with an advised discretion: without which liberality is 
                  Ambitio &amp; jactantia &amp; effu
                        •
                     io, &amp; qidvi
                        •
                      po
                        ••
                     us qam liberalitas existimanda est, cui ratio non constat. Pl
                        •
                     n. pan
                        •
                     g. B
                        •
                     n
                        •
                     fici
                        ••
                      si detrax. e
                        •
                     is judi
                        •
                     ium, de
                        •
                     iaunt esse beneficia, in aliud qodlibet incidunt nomen. Senec. de benef. lib. 1. cap. 2. nothing lesse then that it beareth the name of.
            Now as he had such times of solemne seeking to God;Gratulation. so he kept a due account of the successe of his

suits, and the returne of his addresses: and he had then accordingly, solemne dayes of gratulation and thanksgiving; on which the bag likewise with the greater summes walked, out of that stock and store, of which anon, that he had set a part for such purposes: that so the poor servants of God partaking with him in that wherewith God had blessed him, might blesse God for him, and together with him.
            
               Obedience.Thus much then for his due and diligent observance of Christ and attendance upon him. Now for matter of obedience; (
                  Prov. 15.8. &amp; 21.17. Esay 1.11.14. &amp; 66.3. Ier. 17.2
                     •
                  .23. Ezek. 20 39. without which all such observances are but loathsome, nor acceptable, but abominable in Gods eye) he was one that 
                  Colos. 1.10. 
               in all things endeavoured to approve himselfe unto God, desirous, as the Apostle speaketh, 
                  H
                        •
                     b. 13.18. 
               to keepe a good conscience in all things. And indeed he was a man of a very tender, yea of a scrupulous conscience, out of a feare to do ought, though unwittingly, that might be offensive unto God. To which purpose I can truly testifie of him that he made many a journey over of purpose unto me (that which also first occasioned mine acquaintance with him) to request resolution in such cases as seemed any whit ambiguous, 
               
                  Iuxt
                        •
                      illud R. Gamalielis in Dictis P
                        •
                     t
                        •
                     um, c. 1. Sect. 16. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  Ab
                        ••
                     ineas 
                        •
                     e à re dubiâ. Illud
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      c
                        •
                     utissimi cu
                     
                        •
                     us
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      praec
                        •
                     ptum, Qod dubites, 
                        •
                     e f
                        •
                     ce
                        •
                     is. Plin. l. 1. ep. 18. Siqidem benè praecipiunt, qi vetant 
                        •
                     icqam agere, qod dubites, aequm sit
                        •
                     n iniqum. Cicer. offic. l. 1. not daring to undertake them, till he knew what warrant there were for them, nor desiring to deale in them, unlesse he might see some good ground for what he did. In which kinde I know that he forbore diverse things, because they seemed doubtfull, which might in likelyhood have proved very advantagious unto him, and that few would have stuck at.
            
               Againe,Examination. because he knew well, that though a man be never so circumspect, yet 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . AEschyl. ap. St
                        •
                     b cap. 3. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  G
                        •
                     eg. Naz in Patr. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Idem in Basi
                        •
                     . Iames 3.2. N
                        ••
                      in uno sed in m
                        •
                     l
                        ••
                     s nec qosdam, sed omnes offendere dicit. Aug. Ep. 29. Non dixit, offenditis, sed offendimu
                        •
                     , inqi
                        •
                     : &amp;, in multis, praemisit; omnes subjunxit. Beda.
                
               in many things he may faile, either in doing that he should not do, or not doing that he should, or not doing it as he should; that he might not therefore runne far behind hand with God, he had his nightly exercise, as he tearmeth it, both in his remembrances, and (where he seriously commendeth it also to his) in his Will: 
                  Iuxta illud Pythagorae monitum. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . La
                        •
                     rt. in Pythag. Plut. d
                        •
                      superf
                        •••
                     . &amp; de Curios. Epictet. dissert. l. 4 c. 6. Non priu
                        •
                      in dulcem de
                        •
                     linat lumina somnum, Omnia q
                        •
                     m longi transege
                        •
                     it acta diei, Qo praetergressus? qid gestum in tempore? qid non? Cur isti facto de
                        •••
                      abfuit, aut ratio illi? Qod mihi p
                        •
                     aeteritum? cur haec sententia sedit, Qam m
                        •
                     liu
                        •
                      mutâss
                        •
                      fuit?
                        •
                      Qid volui, qod nolle bonum fuit? utile honesto, cur malu
                        •
                      
                     
                        •
                     ntetuli? —Sic dicta p
                        •
                     r 
                        •
                     mnia facta
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      Ingrediens, orto
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      à vespere c
                        •
                     ncta revolvens, Offensus pravis, dat palma
                        •
                      &amp; pramia rectis. Aus
                        •
                     n. idyl
                        •
                     
                   16. Idem de Catone Cicero de Senect. de Sext
                        •
                     o S
                        •
                     neca de irâ. l. 3. c 36. de s
                        •
                      idem ibid. de Christianis qibusdam Climacus Scalae grad. 4. Vide Chrys
                        ••
                     t. Tom. 8. orat. 10. wherein having withdrawne himselfe a part, he used to take a strict surveigh and account of his employments the day past: to the end that if he found ought therein amisse, he might humble himselfe for it, and by renewed repentance make up the breach; if he found nothing, he might yet, with 
                  Psal. 19.12. 
               David, crave pardon for his hidden transgressions, and blesse God for his direction and 
               1 Sam. 25.32, 33. 
               preservation so far forth. And yet beside this, he had his weekly, monethly, and yearely times of account, not for his worldly, but for his spirituall estate and condition, to 
                  Psal. 119.59
                     •
                  
                
               examine how therein it fared with him, and how he either thrived or paired in it.
            And thus much, as for his observance of Christ, so for his obedience unto Christ; his desire and endeavour

not to faile in any office required of him, and his care to finde out wherein he might faile, and to amend what he 
                  
                     •
                  ound amisse.
            
            But may some say, you told us ere while among other things, that those that are Christs friends must shew their love to Christ, in loving those that he loves, in being friendly, and doing good, unto those that are his.
            
            
               Beneficence.Why? this was one of the principall flowers, in that Garland of graces, wherewith it pleased God to crowne and adorne this our Brother. In other things he excelled others, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Eurip. apud Plut. in G
                        •
                     rg. &amp; Alcib. 2. &amp; Plut. Sympos. l. 1. c. 4. &amp; l. 2. c. 1. in this even himselfe. What faithfull minister of Christ did he not entirely 
               1 Thes. 5, 12, 13. 
               love, and affect? What faithfull member of Christ, though never so meane, did he not 
                  Psal. 15.4. 1 Pet. 2.17. 
               honour and respect? Neither was this his love and respect, 
               1 Iohn 3.18. 
               verball, or 
                  Iames 2.15, 16. 
               complementall, but active and reall, ready largely and liberally to manifest it selfe at all occasions, upon the least intimation and signification made to him, as my selfe at diverse times have had experience, and that even there 
                  Qod de Atheni
                     
                        •
                     us. Aristides. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . where no motion at all hath beene made to him for them, but he had come occa
                  •
               ionally to understand of their wants and necessities.
            At his first effectuall call, among other things he then resolved upon, this was one, to set apart every yeare a tenth of his gaine for the reliefe of the poore (and that besides his tithe to God.Tenth of yearly gaine for the Poore.) And will you know the reasons that induced him thereunto? you shall have them out of his own memorials, and most in his own words.
            
               
                  Reason. 1.First, to shew his love and his thankefulnesse unto

God; as 
                  Gen. 32.10. for raising him from a meane condition, having lesse then fifty pounds to begin withall at first, to that wealth that then he had; so more especially for 
                  Eph
                        •
                     s. 1.3, 4. his spirituall goodnesse to him, in electing him, redeeming him, reclaiming him, 
                  Psal. 103.1, 4. 
               remitting his sinnes, and receiving him to grace and favour in Christ.
            
            Secondly,
                  Reason 2. because he conceived, that this distribution of almes would be an excellent meanes of keeping him from being proud and high-minded, 
               1 Tim. 6.17. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Isidor. l. 3. 
                     
                        •
                     . 322. Ante omnia nihil est qod s
                        •
                     c generant divit
                        •
                     a, q
                        •
                     
                     mode superbiam: omne pom
                        •
                     m, granum, 
                        •
                     ructus, lignum 
                        •
                     abet vermem suum: liu
                        •
                      est vermis mali, ali
                        ••
                      py
                        •
                     i, alius fa
                        ••
                     , aliu
                        •
                      tri
                        •
                     ici: vermis divitiarum superbia. Aug. de verb. Dom. 5. &amp; homil. 15. Primus vermis divitiarum superbia. Idem de temp. 205. a vice that usually followeth wealth; for when in the exercise of this gift he should behold so many lamentable creatures, some blinde, some lame, some sore, some diseased, some hunger-starved, having death in their faces either through famine or other wayes, it would minister him occasion of these and the like thoughts. 
                  Sicut rusticus qidam ab aut
                        •
                     re Anonymo buf
                        •
                     ne conspecto lachrymas 
                        •
                     bertim fudisse refertur, h
                        •
                     c consideratione motus, potuisse eundem, qi hominem f
                        •
                     ceratipsum, 
                        •
                     usonem ejusmodi fecisse. Greg. Naz. pro pauper. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               Why am not I as this lamentable creature? Or why is not this lamentable creature as I am? 
               1 Cor. 4.7. 
               What makes the difference betweene me and him, but the mercy of God only more in this kinde to me then to him?
            
            Thirdly,
                  Reason 3. it would 2 Cor. 9.12, 13. 
               occasion many to blesse God, and to pierce the Heavens with their prayers, and indeed in giving to any his word was usually, 
                  Ha
                        •
                      est 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . ut Marc. Imp. l. 6. §. 7 
               Praise God: or when he sent to others, as to my selfe sometime, any summe to be distributed among poore people, his manner was to adde

in his lines accompanying it, will them to praise God for it.
            
            
               
                  Reason 4.Fourthly, he conceived he should be no small gainer by such gift. And shall I tell you from himselfe, what the gaine he meant, was? He considered, he saith, what 
               
                  Philem. 7. 
               comfort would accrue to such poore ones by his gift: and what a joy must it needs then be unto him, (yea and no small
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Gr
                        •
                     g. Naz. pro paup. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Idem ad cives su
                        •
                     s de prae
                        •
                     id. irâ.
                
               honour it is indeed, if it be rightly conceived) to be an instrument of such comfort to any member of Christ? I might well adde, and to 
               
                  Matth. 25.40. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Greg. Naz. pro paup
                        •
                     r. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Idem in tetrast. Christus accipit
                        •
                      qod de di
                        ••
                     i: ille accipit, qi unde dares dedit. Aug. de temp. 50. Ipse s
                        •
                      dicit accip
                        •
                     re, q
                        •
                     d pa
                        ••
                     tribus da
                        •
                     ur. Sibi colla
                        •
                     um praedicat, quod in pauperis ma
                        •
                     u ponitur. Idem hom. 47. Q
                        •
                     d in terrâ jacentibus porrigi
                        •
                     is, in coelo sedenti datis. Greg
                        •
                      in Evang. 40. 
               Christ in them. This therefore 1 Cor. 16.2. he constantly set apart: and out of this treasury it was, that upon the forenamed occasions he so liberally dispensed. That which being cast up, amounteth to many hundreds, a greater summe then for some considerations I think meet to expresse: and yet what beside he freely bestowed upon his kindred and allies, is deemed to amount to as great, yea a greater summe then it. Nor do I reckon what over &amp; above all this also went out of his poores purse, which he never carried out empty; that he might 
                  Gal. 6.9. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  
                     
                        •
                     lut. de S
                        ••
                     . 
                        ••
                     lit &amp; contr. C
                        •
                     lo
                        •
                     . Hoc est qod Marc. l. 12. Sect 29. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                  
                     •
                  
                
               ever be doing good; that which he much desired and most 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Marc. Imp. l. 7. Sect. 13 &amp; l. 6. Sect. 7. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                  
                     •
                   
                  Idem. l. 10. Se
                        •
                     t. 3
                     ••
                   
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Greg. Naz. in bapt. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     
                     
                        •
                      
                     
                        〈…〉
                      
                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Epicu
                        •
                     us ipse 
                        ••
                     ud Plut. de vit
                        •
                      Epic.
                delighted in, blessing and praising God, in his remembrances,

that had 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . M
                        ••
                     c. l. 1. Sect. 17. 
               given him ability and opportunity so to do: it being one branch also of his daily prayer, that as God increased him in wealth, so he would be pleased withall to encrease in him, wisdome, humility, and thankefulnesse, together with a constant and comfortable perseverance in that lovely grace of charity.
            
            Yea but, what got he, or gained he, may some of you say, by this his beneficence? or what was the fruit and effect of it?
            
            I answer. He esteemed it 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Ph
                        •
                     laris Ep. 17. &amp; Ep. 119. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . B
                        •
                     neficium dand
                        •
                      accepit, qi digno dedit. P. Syrus. Marc. l. 11. Sect. 4. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Idem lib. 9. Sect. 42. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ; Plut. de 
                        •
                     ffect. e
                        •
                     g. 
                        •
                     r. 4. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Aris
                        •
                     id Panat
                        •
                     . Ad ben
                        •
                     ficium no
                        •
                      adducit cogitatio avara, nec sordida, sed liberalis, cupiens dare, etiam cum dederit, &amp; augere novis ac recentibus vetera. Seneca de benef. lib. 4. cap. 14. 
               gaine enough to do any good: and 
                  Hebr. 13.16. 
               Gods acceptance of this his service to be recompence sufficient. But yet it pleased God abundantly to recompence this his beneficence unto him, both with outward and inward blessings.
            
            True it is indeed,Gods triall of him. that for some space of time, some three or foure yeares after that his resolution of setting a tenth apart for such purposes, he thrived not, he found no increase, nor came forward in the world, as formerly he had done. Yet was he not thereby discouraged, nor did he forbeare to be bountifull as opportunity was offered, and the necessity of poore people required it; but he gave still with cheerefulnesse and comfort out of love unto

God, (I give you his own words) freely leaving prosperity in temporall things to God his fathers good pleasure; and conceiving (so he saith) that God in wisdome and goodnesse prospered him not, thereby to try his sincerity to him, and his charity to others
                     •
                   yea and that 
               
                  
                     
                        ••
                     n. 2
                     •
                  .
                     •
                  2. 
                     
                        〈…〉
                     , id est, 
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        •
                     e f
                        ••
                     i: ign
                        •
                     tus enim 
                        •
                     ibi qis
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      est a
                        •
                     te interrogationē tentationis: latent
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      homi
                        •
                     em dilectionis &amp; 
                        •
                     idei sua vires, nisi exp
                        •
                     rimento divino eidem inno
                        •
                     escant. Aug. in Gen qaest. 57. &amp; in Deut. 13.3. q. 19. &amp; in Psal. 58. &amp; de Trinit. l. 1. c. 12. &amp; l. 3. c. 11. 
               he himselfe might thereby have experience of his love unto God, his faith, patience, and constancy; nor would he forgoe those evidences hereof, that thereby he gained, for ten thousand times ten thousand times more then they cost him. So that albeit he prospered not in his wordly estate, yet even then also he thrived much in his spirituall estate, and in the fruits and comforts of it.
            
               Blessing of him in his estate temporall.But from that time forward God abundantly advanced his estate. (You heare him againe speaking to you in his own language) so that he found experimentally those gracious promises of God true,
               
                  Psal. 112.9.
               
                  Prov. 19.17. (and he citeth the places) of his blessing of him that disperseth and dispenseth to the poore; of the repayment of that with interest,
               
                  Eccles. 11.1. 
               that is so lent to the Lord; of the finding againe after many dayes with increase the bread, or 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   
                  panem, id est, semen: ut Psal. 104.15. Iun.
                
               bread-corne, that is cast upon the face of the waters, or 
                  Secundum aqas in l
                        ••
                     is irriguis, ac proinde feracibus. Esay 32.20. Iun.
                on the land neare thereunto, though it seeme cast away for the present.
            But that, which is above all, and beyond all, it pleased God withall to afford him such evidences and assurances of his favour &amp; love towards him,
               Spirituall. 
               as who
                     •
                  oever would buy from him by offer of the whole world and all the soveraignty thereof, he professeth he would refuse a thousand such worlds in exchange for them. By meanes whereof, as he led 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Phil. 3.20. Qod Cypr l. 2. 
                     
                        •
                     p. 4. In ca
                        •
                     ne adhu
                        •
                      positis vi
                        •
                     a vivitur, non praes
                        •
                     ntis seculi, sed fu
                        •
                     uri.
                an heavenly course of life here on earth; so within his soule

in spirituall joyes and comforts 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Greg. Naz apolog. 
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Chrysost. de stat
                        •
                     is. 2. he had an heaven here out of heaven. And this cheerefull and comfortable estate and condition continued with him to the end.
            The nearenesse whereof as presaging before his departure into forraigne parts, whither his affaires drew him, he took a great deale of pains according to 
                  Esay 38.2. 
               Esaies advice to Ezechiah, in the se
                     •
                  ling of his estate, and in composing of his Will
                     •
                   Pliny the younger saith, it was a received opinion and common conceit in his times,Preparation for his End. that 
                  Testamenta 
                        •
                     ominum, specula morum. Plin. l. 8, 
                     
                        •
                     p. 18. 
               mens last Wils and Testaments, were as looking-glasses, in which a man might as cleerely descry and discerne the inward disposition of their minde, as he may see their bodily face in a glasse. And such indeed was the Will of this our deceased brother,His Will
                     •
                  
                all savouring of piety, all of charity, very lively resembling and representing his inward disposition. Few Wils, I suppose, so composed, come into the Office: full of spirituall, religious, holy, heavenly expressions; full of blessings of Gods name, and acknowledgements of his goodnesse, with incitement of others thereunto; full of works of mercy, bounty, and charity,
               In it, His charity. as if he were but then beginning that work, which the most put off till then. Besides large Legacies to not a few of his neare kindred and acquaintance, which I cast out of this account. To the poore Palatine exiles, fifty pounds: to the Towne of Leicester for the use of the poore Weavers and Knitters there, fifty pounds: for the reliefe of poore prisoners, one hundred pounds: for the taking up in the streets a certaine number of

               poore children, Boyes, and Girles, to be fitted for, sent out to, and placed in the forraine Plantations, three hundred pounds: among his poore servants, seventy pounds: among other poore, left to the discretion of his Executors, fifty pounds: to this poore man, and that poore Minister, as they came then in his minde, to the summe of forty and seven pounds; which in all amounteth to six hundred sixty and seven pounds.
            
            This for his charity, 
               
                  Apoc. 2.19. as fresh at last as at first, notwithstanding his charge, that is wont to coole charity with many, but did not so with him.
            
               
                  His Piety.
               Now for his piety, and his care of the continuance of it with those whom God had blessed him with or committed to his charge. It is report
                  •
               d of Plato, that when he had occasion to go abroad, he used to give in charge to those young men that lived with him, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plut. de Sanit. conserv.
                
               to spend their time during his absence, in some usefull imployments: and blessed Peter the Apostle was carefull to take such a course, that 2 Pet. 
                  
                     •
                  .13. 
               his Disciples might after his departure remember and beare in minde those things, that he had delivered to them while he lived. In like manner was it with this our brother. As he was alwayes carefull, (therein a true child of 
               
                  Gen. 18.19. 
               Abraham) to commend piety to his people, and to informe those of his family, as well servants as children, how to feare and serve God: so in speciall manner, at his departure beyond the seas, he assigned each of them, as their abilities and capacities were, what they should learne of the grounds of religion, and proofes thereof out of Scripture, against

his returne. And yet more specially for the better continuance of piety and godlinesse in those his child
                     •
                  en whom God had blessed him withall, and the i
                  •
               citing of them by his example and the fruit he had found in it, to a more constant and cheerefull practise thereof, he gave order in his will, to have all his spirituall journals, his meditations and remembrances, gathered together, digested and reduced into a methode, by some two godly Divines, unto whom also he hath assigned a very liberall consideration for their paines therein taken: and severall Copies thereof to be transcribed and made up for the use of each of his Children: that therein they might see him when he was gone, and 
                  
                     Qomodo de Pt
                           •
                        
                        l
                           •
                        m
                           ••
                        . Th
                           •••
                        r. idyl. 17.
                  —
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                     . Eurip. Helen.
                  
                treading in those steps that he had walked in before them, they might at length 
                  Heb. 13.7. arrive at that end, that he hath now attained to: which 
                  Qod Commod
                        •
                      Marci fili
                        •
                      Aristides; 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . the Lord in mercy grant they may. Thus both living and dying, yea as well dead as 
                  
                     •
                  live (though not dead indeed, but alive still, alive to God, yea alive to his too) he desired every way to doe good.
            What shall I need to adde ought concerning his end?
               His End. It is seldome seene, and 
               
                  Vix fi
                        •
                     ri p
                        •
                     test, ut benè moriatur, qi malè vixe
                        •
                     it.
                
               hardly, saith one, can it be, that one that hath lived ill, should make a good end. But 
                  Fieri non potest, ut malè moriatur, qi benè vixerit. A
                        •
                     g. 
                        •
                     om. de ver. &amp; f
                        •
                     ls
                        •
                     p
                        •
                     nit.
                
               it cannot be, that one that hath lived so well shou
                  •
               d make any other then a good end. Sure it was so with this our brother, by report of those that were eye-witnesses of it: full of pious expressions and sweet comforts to the last; and that, even after that speech failed him, but memory and understanding continued with him, by sign
                     •
                  s outwardly expressed, upon such passages recited, as he had before given order

to them about him to be read by him. Insomuch that we may well with good probability suppose, that God in his holy wisdome had so disposed it, that he should go ov
                  •
               r hence to make his end in that place, amids the enemies of Gods truth and grace, that those that are seduced by them, might see
                  •
                
               pregnant proofe of 
                  ••
               e power of piety, in the religious and comfortable end of one deceasing in that faith and profession, in which those seducers of them beare them in hand, that there is no safety or comfort to be had, either in life or in death.
            
            In a word to conclude all with the words of my Text; Our friend, and your friend; Christs friend, and the friend of all Christ his, sleepeth; his soule being entred into his Masters joy, his body to be laid up in its Chamber of rest; untill Christ come to awake him, and us altogether with him, to the et
                  ••
               nall blisse of both.Conclusion of all. Let us all make that use of wh
                  ••
                hath 
                  ••
               en delivered, that we be thereby encited to i
                     •
                  itate him in those good things that we have, either seene in him, or heard of him, that so through Gods goodnesse and his gracious ac
                  •
               eptance of our godly endeavours, we may both attaine and retaine those spirituall joyes and inward comforts that he found and felt, both in life and in death.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            Imprimatur, Iohannes 
                     〈◊〉
                  .
            
         
      
   

