
   
      
         
            Rodomontados. Or, Brauadoes and bragardismes. Collected out of the commentaries of the most dreadfull, terrible, and inuincible capitaine; Mattamores, Crocodillo, Raiabroquelos
            Rodomuntadas castellanas. English
            Gaultier, Jacques.
         
         
            
               1610
            
         
         Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01565
            STC 11691A
            ESTC S122512
            99857636
            99857636
            23401
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01565)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23401)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 888:1)
         
         
            
               
                  Rodomontados. Or, Brauadoes and bragardismes. Collected out of the commentaries of the most dreadfull, terrible, and inuincible capitaine; Mattamores, Crocodillo, Raiabroquelos
                  Rodomuntadas castellanas. English
                  Gaultier, Jacques.
               
               [38] p.   
               
                  Printed by W. Iaggard,
                  [London] :
                  1610.
               
               
                  A translation of a French version of: Gaultier, Jacques. Rodomuntadas castellanas.
                  A different translation from STC 11691.
                  Signatures: A-E⁴ (-A1).
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2007-01
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-01
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-04
            John LattaSampled and proofread
         
            2007-04
            John LattaText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            Rodomontados. OR, Brauadoes and Bragardiſmes.
            ¶ Collected out of the Commentaries of the moſt Dreadfull, Terrible, and Inuincible Capitaine; Mattamores, Crocodillo, Raiabroquelos.
            
            
               Arma virumque cano.
            
            Printed by W. Iaggard, 1610.
         
         
            
            
            
               To my Lord Vieillart, Councellor to the King, Treaſurer of France, and Generall of the Reuennues belonging to Soiſſons.
            
               My Lord,
            
            
               
                  I
                Stood a long while in doubt, whether I ſhould deliuer to publick view or no, this ſlender impreſsion, and vnder your fauor: becauſe the matter appeared to me too ſmall, in regarde of your great merit. But when I conſidered, that generous mindes doe alwaies receiue with gratefull acceptance, whatſoeuer is offered them in honeſt affection; I was excited to proceed on boldly. Wherefore, I preſent vnto your honour (with ſuch reſpect as becommeth mee) theſe pleaſant Caſtillian Rodomontados, or brauing boaſtes of an humorous Spaniard: wherein you you ſhall finde nothing elſe, but ſome harmeleſſe ieſts &amp; meriment, without iniury or wrong to any one offered. Specially not vnto Spaniards, whoſe name is no otherwiſe heere vſed or borrowed, then was that bragging Souldiour Thraſo by Terence: vnder which might be vnderſtood, an Engliſhman, Scottiſhman, Frenchman, or ſome man of any

other Nation. And indeed I am verily perſwaded, that many men in reading this Book, and falling into laughter: may happen to laugh and ſmile at themſelues, becauſe they may chance to finde their owne follies recorded, vnder the fable alluded to another.
            Well do I know, my Lord, that you are no ſuch cenſurer as Cato, nor yes ſo ſeuere as Ariſtarchus, but after you haue employed your ſpirites in great and graue affayres; you may finde ſome content in reading this trifle, as a pleaſing relaxation from former perturbances, as my ſelfe haue often made the like vſe of them.
            If the Bow ſtand alwaies bent, it wil at length become too ſlacke, and fit for no ſeruice when it is needed. After ſtormes and Tempeſts, the heauens do affoord vs faire weather; and ſuch as are ſtockt in Priſon, or chained to the Oare in a Galley, will ſometimes conſolate their afflictions, by the helpe of Songs, or pleaſant diſcourſes.
            Theſe Ieſts and Braggadochio mirthes, may ſerue in the like Nature to ſuch men, who, after they haue trauailed and ſpent their ſpirits in great and ſerious matters; deſire ſome other honeſt and ſportiue recreation. And if I may perceiue, that your wonted ſweet and gentle inclination, ſhall receiue this my poor vnworthy guift (which I offer you with my moſt humble ſeruice) with good lookes, and kinde acceptance; It wil excite me to more painefull labour heereafter, and to remaine for euer
            
               Your moſt humble Seruant,
Iacques Gaultier.
               
            
         
         
            
            To the Reader.
            
               SIr, vnderſtanding what curious deſire you haue to attaine vnto the lofty elegancy of the Spanish language: J haue dared as the moſt hardy and coragious, that I could heare off, ſince the worlde was a Worlde, to aduenture on this ſmal Summary of Spanish Rodomontados. And yet not without ſome dreade in my boldeſt reſolue, repreſenting vnto me this conceit, that effects are oftentimes more myraculous, and ſuller of Diuinity, then of common ſence or humanity.
            Neuertheleſſe, the inuincible courage that J haue had, and yet do containe for your eternall ſeruice, hath armed me at all pointes: not with Armor onely of Musket proofe, but thoſe ſillye and light Armes beſide, for the taſte of Codlings or ſodden Apples, to reſiſt againſt the threatnings of that Sun-ſhaddow, which neuer yet appeared in our France, without being many times ecclipſed, by the ſight and preſence of him, who lately raigned moſt happily ouer the true French.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            Rodomontados. OR, SPANISH Brauadoes, and Bragardiſmes.
            
               I.
               
                  WHen I came into the Worlde, Mars entered into my ſhoulders; Hercules into my right arme; Sampſon into my left; Atlas into my legges; Mercury into my head; Venus into myne eyes; Cupid into my countenance; Nero into my heart, and Iupiter into all my body. So that by the very aboundance of my power: when I walk I make the earth to tremble, heauen to look fearfull, the winds to ceaſe, the Sea to become calm, women great with childe to deliuer abortiues, men to flye amazedly heere and there. And men of greateſt valour, and higheſt courage, beholding

but my preſence, ſay all with one voyce, Libera nos Domine.
               
            
            
               II.
               I Sweare by my Sword (Villaine) if I can but ſee thee, I will giue thee ſuch a blowe with my Baſtinado, as by the verie ſtrength thereof, I will ſtrike thee ſixe foot down into the earth. And there ſhall remaine nothing of thee out of the ground, but onely thy right arme and thy heade, reſerued for this eſpeciall occaſion: to take off thy hat, and do me reuerence, as I ſhall paſſe or walk along by thee.
            
            
               III.
               ASſuredly when I conſider how highly Fortune hath indued me wt graces, I find that I want time to put all thoſe conſiderations in effectuall imployment. For firſt, ſhee hath heaped ſuch ſtrength vpon me, giuen me an immeaſurable maſſe of corage, &amp; builded ſuch a fabricke of extraordinary valor in me: that I am as a Colonie in France, a Baſtillion in Spaine, a Fortreſſe in Italy, a Caſtle in England, a Cittadell in Germany, a Tower in Poland, a rocke in Armenia, a wall in Denmarke, &amp; generally the hath adorned me aboue all ye
                  
men of this worlde. For I am of a moſt purified &amp; refined kinde of mettle, formed from the choyſeſt grace of the earths entrailes, and meerely engendered of Generoſitie.
            
            
               IIII.
               I Make a Vow to Iupiter, that I am as a Man without ſence, &amp; euen halfe deſperate, becauſe I cannot inſtantly meet with any man that is deſirous to entreat peace, or take truce with mee. Al my glorie therefore ſhall bee, to finde out ſome one, vpon whom I may diſcharge this choller, &amp; reuenge my ſpleene, ſince I cannot preuaile to deale with them that haue occaſioned this paſſion in me, by reaſon of their cowardly &amp; ſpeedy flight. For this is infallible, I can neuer expreſſe the height of my manhood, againſt pouerty in power, or ſillie reſiſtance.
            
            
               XIII.
               I Swear by the bones of the Sun, that it is not poſſible for me to reſtraine my right arme, from ſtriking one ſtroke with my Baſtinado, but it is death to the endurer: except the Sunne will ſtay his courſe in the firmament, and entreat me to be more mercifull.
            
            
               
               VI.
               I Am vndoubtedly perſwaded, that there is not any thing in the world, which is able to equall the horrible, dreadfull, and furious terribility of my courage. For what created creature is there in the world, but yeildeth me honor &amp; obeyſance? Such is my awefull and commaunding power, that I make the earth to tremble, the Skies to looke affrighted, the Plannets to ſtand at gaze, and the rudeſt windes to bee whiſt. The Sea ſhrinkes in her head, and dare not be ſeene, or ſtir: the Beaſts that haunt the higheſt Mountaines, and thoſe that liue among the leſſer hils, are glad to runne, and hide themſelues in their wombes, as in Dennes or caues: nay, that which is more, the Byrds which flye in the ayre, the Fiſhes that ſwim in the Sea, and men that are moſt valiant and couragious, at one very winke or turne of mine eye, they ſinke, and ſo I ſend them into their Graues or Sepulchres.
            
            
               VII.
               GO, run to my Cooke, commaund him from me, that forthwith he ſpit and lay downe to the fire, a dozen &amp; a halfe of my great Cannons

or Ordinance, aud to larde them with infinite Trunchions of Speares, Pikes, and Halberds, broken by mine owne arme, in ſo many ſeuerall fights, when none in the world (except my ſelfe) was able to depart thence conquerour. Bid him alſo to dreſſe ſome two or three Dozen of Muſkets, and make me a Sallet or two, of Petronilles or Piſtolles, ſtrewed about with Bullets, inſtead of Oliues and Capers. Then, let whoſoeuer dare, come ſuppe with mee: for theſe are the Vyands, whereon I am vſually accuſtomed to feede.
            
            
               VIII.
               I Am King of all the Paladines, the terrour of the World, the Flower of Nobility, among all the Rodomants, Rowlands, and Reynards; endued with infinite ſpeciall graces: Goodly, like an Angell: I haue the heart and courage of Lucifer: I am Seruant to the choyſeſt Ladyes of Beautie, and Prince or Soueraigne of the companie of Amaracoes.
               
            
            
               IX.
               VPon a certaine day, it was my hap to meete in Battaile the Queen of the Amazons, who

aduancing her arme, was in good hope to haue ſlaine me with her warlicke Sword. But I (neuer admitting the leaſt loſſe of time) at one blowe ſmote her downe to the ground, and then catching her by the haire, I threwe her with ſuch violent fury vp into the ayre, that ſhee neuer ſtayed, but went on ſo faxre as the fift heauen: where ſhe fell vpon Mars (who was playing at the Saunt with Venus) and ſhrewdly brake his heade. Venus being there at not a little affrighted, cryed out for helpe and ſuccour, and at her cry, al the Gods ranne immediately to her: where they were extraordinarily amazed, to ſee Mars lye along in ſuch gaſtlie manner. But Iupiter putting his heade out at the Windowe, and ſeeing mee laye ſuch ſtroakes ſtill on mine Enemies, my corage and choller holding on ſo furiouſly, that the Fyre ſparckled about the Field, as if it had beene another Mount Gibell or Aetna: hee forthwith ſayde to all the other Goddes: See that you ſtirre not, neither make any noiſe, for hee that hath alreadie ſlaine Mars; is able and ſufficient of himſelfe, to kill as many Goddes as remaine aliue, or dare vſe any reſiſtance againſt him.
            
            
               X.
               I Know not what kind of death I ſhoulde deuiſe or make choyſe of, for the punniſhment of two villaines, that eyed me this day in the ſtreet after

a baſe &amp; ſcuruie maner. I deſire to looke ouer mine Index or Repertory, where I haue ſet down with mine owne hand, ſeauen hundred, ſixty, and fiue ſeuerall kindes of ſlaughter, to ſee which of them may be by me beſt likt and allowed. For indeed, thoſe which now adaies I would cuſtomarily vſe, and haue as an extraordinary exerciſe in my hand: I could wiſh, that they might be blows without bloud, ſlaſhes of the ſword, yeilding no purple ſluces, but as if my weapons edge were Lead, or the reuerſes onely induſtrious▪ agile, and ſubtle. For my other kinde of fight, I finde and confeſſe it to be too dreadful and fatall: becauſe I neuer ſtab, but it is quite through, the very fall of my Sword makes an huge wide wound; my Eſtoccado is ouer dangerous, and the leaſt ſtroake mortall. Therefore I am oftentimes (in meere mercy) compelled to beſtowe ſome few blowes wt my Baſtinado; to the end, that I may giue reſt to my weapon, and let it reioyce a little in the Scabbarde.
            
            
               XI.
               LOoke to your ſelues, my Lordes, retire or withdraw a litle out of the way, vntil I haue put on my Cape or Cloake: becauſe the verie winde thereof, is ſufficient, to ſend you ſuddenlie aboue fiftie leagues hence, beyond the Pyrenean Mountaines.
            
            
               
               XII.
               IF my Sword could ſpeak, and tell what it daily doth, time were not able to alow it diſcourſe. Who coulde elſe, more people all the Churchyards in the world, then he hath done? who hath made richer Chirurgions euery where, then hee hath done? Who could, or can make the Armorers to haue more toyle and continuall trouble, then he hath done, and daily ſo endureth? What can cut through more armors of proofe, then it doth? Who more ſcoffes or ſcornes the Bucklers of Barcelona, or carues through the curious Helmets of Calataynd, then it doth? As for ye Caſks of Almazen, it cuts through as eaſily, as if they were all made of Muſke-Mellons.
            
            
               XIII.
               IT is now full twenty yeares, ſince this ſword hath bin my feeder and maintainer: For, thereby am I feared of men, and beloued of women.
            
            
               XIIII.
               
                  IT hath bin told me, that the great Turk commits many murders, and that he cuts off mens armes and legs. But by the life of my dead Fathers bones, if I go to him, that courage will bee cold, and quickely forſake him. For I ſhal no sooner appeare in his preſence, but he muſt preſently ſtrike himſelfe dead with his owne hand, for feare leaſt he ſhould fall into mine.
            
            
               XV.
               WIth one word only, I can penetrate and ſtrike downe to hell, and with my verie preſence, I am able to ſubdue the whole world, euen from the Eaſt vnto the Weſt, ſpoyling, defacing, and tearing all men &amp; other matters in pieces, that ſhal dare to oppoſe themſelues in my way. For it is vniuerſally knowne what I am: That my Bedſted is built with the ribs of Gyants; the Ticke or Bed it ſelfe, is ſtufte with the Monſtachios of the chiefe Commanders in the great Turkes Campe, and the Bolſters with the braines, which by verie boxes on the eares, I haue beaten out of his beſt Captaines heads. My Sheetes are wouen of the fayreſt lockes of the Amazones; my Couerings, of the Switzers beards, and my Curtaines of the ſoft downe of the Eye-Browes of the Hungarians and Germaines: The Walles of my lodging is conſtructed of diuers partes, not onely of Caſkes or Helmes, but of whole

of whole heads encloſed in them, carrying plumes and pendents of the Queene of England, who (being deade) I haue frighted in her Graue with my formidable Bilbo, for terrifieng mee in the terrible yeare of eighty eight. The Floore of my houſe (inſtead of Playſter of Paris) is artificially compounded of Ianiſſaries Teeth: The Tapiſtrie or Hangings, are Skinnes of Arabes and Sorcerers, flayed off with the verie poynt of my Dagger: And the Tyles or Slates which couer my Houſe, are the Nayles of Monarches and Kinges, whoſe bodies I haue long ſince (in deſpight both of them and their Corps du Guard) ſent in Slices of a foote long, into their Graues.
            
            
               XVI.
               SCorning (in mine Perſon) to drawe my dreaded Sworde, againſt a ſingle braue Engliſh Captayne: I gaue him ſuch a kicke with my foote, that he mounted, and ſmote his heade againſt the Sunne, with ſuch violent ſtrength, that it continued ecclipſed for the ſpace of fifteene dayes together. And then, within a while after, the Captayne went and fell vpon his knees before Iupiter, entreating him to pardon mee my Sinnes, in recompence of the good deede that I had done, that with a ſpurne of my foote,

I had placed him among the Starres, whereas (contrary-wiſe) I might haue caſt him downe into Hell, among the Wicked and Damned Soules.
            
            
               XVII.
               WIth one hayre of this Mouſtachio, which I careleſſely caſt away, I will make ſuch a wide ouverture or breach through thy Bodye, as all the Spaniſh Infanterie, and the French Caualaery, ſhall paſſe along eaſilie through, without any touch, eyther of the one ſide or other.
            
            
               XVIII.
               WHat matter were it, if Aſia, Europe, Affrica, the Pyrenian Mountaines, and the Alpes were all whelmed one vpon another: ſeauen Draggons, eight Elephants, tenne Tygers, two and twentie Lyons, and ſixtie fiue Bulles in fierce oppoſition? All theſe for mee to couquer and make peace-able, were a matter of nothing.
            
            
               
               XIX.
               MIſtreſſe of my heart, command me ſome ſeruice becomming my vocation; for I ſwear by the greateſt Tooth of Cerberus, to giue deſiance (for your ſake) to ten men together: and though there ſhould come twice as manie more, yet I ſtand reſolued, not to flye, but to reſiſt them all. Commaund me to kill one, two, three, foure, fifty or ſixty perſons, to hewe off legges, armes, noſes, or the faces of any whoſoeuer, as dare preſume to equall themſelues with you. For ſuch offices are eaſier to be by me performed, then at any time by you they can be commanded.
            
            
               XX.
               WIth this moſt re-doubted and terrifying Sword, I ruinate, I deſtroy, and ſet all thinges on fire: Ouer-throwing whole Armies, breaking downe citties, racing caſtels, leuelling Trenches, battering walles, and ſhaking in ſhiuers inexpugnable Fortreſſes. For, at my verye ſight or preſence, I make Iupiter to run and hide his heade; Mercury flyes like a Schoole-Boy; Cupid quakes and trembles; and Mars he ſtands in amaze, as if hee were tranſformed, rendering

ouer his tribute from Venus to me, becauſe ſhe affects me, as her much more amorous Seruant.
            
            
               XXI.
               IN what place ſoeuer I am, Death is alwayes with me, becauſe he gets more profit by me, thē if he were in the middeſt of the moſt furious and bloudieſt battailes in the whole world. Hee hath bin my continuall companion and follower, in conqueſt of ye kingdoms of the Grimeans, Diceans, Dinameans, Alopitians, Pitunians and Eſpinomeans. For to ſpeak nothing but the naked truth, without him. I had walked alone night &amp; day: becauſe I can find no other more familiar reſemblance to my ſelfe, or one that can be ſo pleaſing to me.
            
            
               XXII.
               I Finde in my ſelfe the Nature of the Baſiliſke, and (indeede) ſomething of greater power. For if he with his ſight can kill one after one, when I looke vppon men in my ſpleene and choller, I make them to fall downe by ten and ten, euen as if mine eyes were the Balles of your greateſt Artillerie.
            
            
               
               XXIII.
               I Am too olde to enduce any Trauaile, and yet but young to all valiant and aduenturous ſufferance: For from the time that I was in my Cradle, Venus made it her daily cuſtome, in ſtead of Milke to feede me with fire, and for fruite and ſweet meats, I ſwallowed leaden Bullets, and Balles of Braſſe.
            
            
               XXIIII.
               LIke as the Worlde is deuided into foure parts, whereof three are Aſia, Affrica, and Europe, and theſe three are circkled or round engirt with the Sea: Euen ſo is my heart deuided into three other parts, which doe containe three ſeuerall Natures, to wit; affable, terrible, and cruell. Now theſe three partes are rounde enuironed, yet not with Water, but vvith liuing flames of hot couſuming fire. And as this fyre (in Loues behalfe) is ſo ſweete, as much better for mee were it, if it were ſower or bitter, becauſe I cannot captiuate the poyſon which is in my heart, enen ſo in the ſame manner is my heart it ſelfe. And yet with three ſtroakes of this bright brandiſhed blade, the one deliuered ſlycing, the

ſecond reuerſing, and the thirde meerelie poynting: I could kill and ouer-quell all man-kinde, making Riuers of blood longer then Ganges, larger then Poe, and more terrible then Nylus. But let the Worlde bee thankefull for it, that at this inſtant I am become amorous, or falne in Loue, for in my former fierie and ouer-fierce humour: I vſed to kill dayly (at the leaſt) three or foure dozen of Men, Women, and Children. But now, in this more milde and temperate alteration, I vſe not to kill paſt a dozen in a day. And what doe you thinke may bee the reaſon thereof? Let me tell yee for an infallibletrueth, it is nothing elſe, but the meere loue or Cupidicall affection, wherewith I haue chaunged my furious humor, and proſtrated it in demure Deuotion, to the eternall ſeruice of my daintie and moſt Diuine Miſtris.
            
            
               XXV.
               MY Shoo-makec one Morning pulling on my ſhooes, I found one of them ſomewhat too ſtrait in the inſteppe, I gaue him ſuch a kicke with my foote againſt the ground, that the earth immediately opened, and he fell in as farre as Hell. Belzebub, Sathan, Pluto, and Barrabas, Lordes and Princes of thoſe Tenebrous

obſcurities, were thereat driuen all into no meane amazement. Great Cerberus cryed and howled moſt pittifully: Proſerpina rent and tore hir haire, ſhrieking and weeping verie bitterly, becauſe ſhe ſaw her dark kingdom receiue a glimpſe of light. The little Diabolotinos or leſſer Spirits, hidde themſelues in corners heere and there. Some leapt out of hell, and fled fearefully thence, &amp; ſince that time, many of them haue houered aloft in the Ayre, and others in nookes and crannies of the earth, tormenting diuers people, as in many places of the world it is daily noted.
            
            
               XXVI.
               WHat woman dare be ſo bold or audacious, as not to confeſſe her ſelfe moſt highly inamored of this ſtrong thigh, this puiſſant arme, this breaſt ful of al force and valour; this viſage, more goodly then that of Ganimede, or that of Dido, or the lookes of Abſolon? Let me but ſee that bluſhleſſe huſwife, and then bid her abide the fury of my indignation, if ſhe can or dare.
            
            
               XXVII.
               LAdie, you may (by good right) forſake the Name of Madame Beatrix, and entitle your

ſelfhence forward, Imperatrix or Empreſſe, Queen, Princeſſe, Marqueſſe, Counteſſe, Dame, and Damoſil: Seeing theſe two great Colombs or Pillers of Hercules, which do ſupport and ſuſtain the whole world, are ſoly obliged to your ſeruice. I could tel ye, that this Caſtillian body, is filled with the abounding courage of infinite Armies; that this breſt and this arme is ſtronger then the Tower of Babylon: Eſpecially, when it is aſſiſted by this redoubted Sworde, for the fires ſparkeling from it, do penetrate, &amp; ſurmount in bright ſplendour, the luminous beames of the Sun.
            
            
               XXVIII.
               IF mine infinite couragious valour, could poſſibly be bought with the price of Gold or Siluer, there needed no other trafficke either by Sea or Land, nor ſhoulde you heare any more ſpeech of Merchants or Merchandize, or of any man that would labour or addict himſelfe to followe ſuch a fruitleſſe vocation. Becauſe all men woulde procure to imploy their induſtry, to get the ſtrength but of one of mine armes, of a legge, of a finger, of my nailes pairing, of an haire frō mine eie-brow, or the very ſmalleſt from my head or beard, which onely might ſuffice to make them valiant, &amp; (then valour) what can be of greater price or eſtimation? But it is my ioy and comfort, that it cannot be compaſſed, and I am the rather therwith contented,

in regard of the peace and quiet of al thoſe Kings, Monarks, and Princes, that hold frendſhip with me▪
               
            
            
               XXIX.
               MY Maquerella, that old bawd Fortune gaue me her word, that I ſhould enioy the Lady, of whom I am ſo highly amorous. But if ſhe keepe not promiſe with mee, I ſweare by the hornes of Pluto, by the Beard of Mars, by ye lawes of Sampſon, and by the Alchoran of Mahomet, that I will take from her all her trickes, and bereaue her of her inconſtant and variable wheele. As for her body, with one Eſtoccado, I will hurle her to Valladolid, bruiſed and broken into ſo manie peeces or ſmall fragments, that ſhe ſhall no ſooner be falne downe there, but ſhe ſhall be ſquandered into duſt &amp; power, which I wil make vſe of, to caſt vpon thoſe letters, that by me ſhall bee daily ſent to my ſweet Miſtris.
            
            
               XXX.
               I Haue more augmented &amp; increaſed in the compaſſe of two poore daies only, the Stigian Kingdom of grim-faced Pluto, &amp; peopled his darke &amp; ſmoaky Hal with ſubiects, then either Rodomont,

Orlando, Reynard of Moutauban, Mandricard, or Radamanth, with all their powers could doo, and I haue dreadfully ſubiected, &amp; humbled vpon theyr knees, in a thouſand thouſand other places, harts that were dauntleſſe, moſt valiant, &amp; of vnmatchable courage. If you require any witneſſe or teſtimony heerof, ſend to all the inhabited Countries of the Eaſt, Weſt, North and South, and peruſing their Chronicles, do but note w
                     •
                  at you finde written in them all, of my vertue and valour.
            
            
               XXXI.
               THe great Turk is more affraid of my valiant reſolution, which this vnconquereable Arme hath dearly made known vnto him, then of ten armies or main battalions ioynd together. Becauſe I being one day in ye war of the Venetians, againſt the fore-named great Turk, I gaue ſuch a box on the eare to Abenhamet, great maiſter of his Camp, yt I ſmote his heade quite from his ſhoulders: &amp; preſently, with another ſpurn, I kickt it into Conſtantinople, where it deliuered the tidings of the foil and loſſe of all the army. But when the Graunde Signeur himſelfe, &amp; al the reſt there preſent wt him, beheld the head without a body, they fled foorthwith into their houſes, making their doores very faſt vpon them, &amp; continued in ſuch feare, as in 6. years after they durſt not peep abroad, through ye bread they ſtood in of me: til at length, I putting

on an humor of more milde temper, and falling into my woonted magnificence, gaue them free leaue to enioy their liberty, and to walk about the ſtreets, as in former times they had done.
            
            
               XXXII.
               WHen I walke along through the ſtreetes of the Citty, a thouſand Ladies preſent thēſelues before me. One puls me by the Cloake, another winkes with her eye at me, another prayes me to ſup with her, another offers me preſents, another kiſſes my hand, and bleſſeth the Mother that bare me, accounting her ſelfe to bee moſt happy if ſhe could compaſſe but one Nights lodging with me: To no other end, but onely to haue a childe ſprung from the race of ſo great and valiant a perſonage, as the world well knoweth me to be.
            
            
               XXXIII.
               IF the ſtrength of my members could bee imparted among diſordered perſons, and mutinous ſpirits; the world would be in an vprore, reuolt, and confuſion, and nothing elſe were to bee ſeene therein, but onely battailes and conqueſts. The bels would ring night and day, as deliuering the

interment of ſlaughtered bodies: Surgions could neuer come foorth of their houſes, for ſtitching vp ſlaſhes of ſwordes, healing Eſtoccadoes, ſetting in right ſhape broken armes and legges. Women would weepe for the death of their Huſbands, young children for the loſſe of theyr Fathers, and Maids for great wrong done to their Mayden-heads, hauing loſt their Louers, and in danger to die Ʋirgins.
            
            
               XXXIIII.
               IT is I onely that neuer felt feare, but haue menaced the Skies, the Ayre, Earth, and Water, yea Iupiter and Hel. I could wiſh to warre with all the Elements: for I fear no tempeſts, ſtorms, thunder or lightning. And I doubt not, but in very ſhort time, to make my ſelfe Lorde of the Sea, Earth, and Hell: I will do it, and I can do it, for my forces are ſufficient to performe it.
            
            
               XXXV.
               IF I come to thee, I will giue thee ſuch a ſpurne with my foot, that it ſhall raiſe and mount thee ſo high, as if thou wert prouided with ten Cart load of Bread, yet ſhouldſt thou ſtand more in fear of famiſhing, then of bruiſing or death, when thou falleſt downe againe.
            
            
               
               XXXVI.
               OH, how I ſmile to my ſelf, when I cal to mind the ignorance of the Gods, in deyfying Hercules, and giuing him a name of equall excellencie with them, calling him a God: onely becauſe hee kild the Hydra, took the Bull by the hornes, rent the Dragon in pieces, vanquiſhed the Lyon, ſurmounted the Centaure, and the wilde Beare: becauſe hee made the Harpies fearefully flye away, ſlew Cethes and Achelous, foyled Diomed King of Thrace, and ouercame Gereonea Qu. of the Amazons: fiinally, becauſe he erected Collombs or pillers in many places. In effect, al theſe things are nothing elſe but a meere fable, and actions of a young womaniſh ſpirit, being compared with my vnparaleld ſtrength, fortitude, and courage. For neither the puiſſance of Daryus, King of the Perſians, nor yet of that Alexander, entituled, ſtyled, or epittethized, the Great; nor the ſtrong Sampſon, nor mighty Hector the Troyan, nor the valiaunt Achilles, nor the mad and furious Rowland, ycleped (by ſome) Orlando Furioſo, nor the aduenturous Gridaſſo, nor the gallant Sacrapant, nor the terrible Mexican Mandricarde, nor the famous Rugiero, or French Roger, nor the horrible Agricano, or the robuſt Rodomont: No, not any one of them, or all aſſembled together, coulde or are able to equall my terrible, horrible, formidable,

fury-bond, and dreadfull force, if I pleaſe to let it appeare in my thundering humor.
            
            
               XXXVII.
               MIne arme quakes &amp; trembles, at that which I am determined to doe for my Lady &amp; Miſtris: For continually I ponder how and which way to compaſſe her contentment, and yet I neuer attaine vnto it. All the night long I dreame that I am performing deedes of Armes (for her ſake againſt tenne men, ſixe whereof, I ſlew outright, and of them which fled away, he that eſcaped with beſt ſafety and ſecurity, was gladde to leaue his left arme at my feete. But then (O you Sacred powers) how much more am I able to do in the day time, when I am awake, and at my martial exerciſe? Twenty men togither dare not touch the ſtring of my Shoo.
            
            
               XXXVIII.
               ONe day as I was playing at the Balloune, I ſmote it with ſuch force, that it flew vp into ye third heauen, where it mounted and leapt vp before the Goddes, who were then aſſembled in a verie ſerious Counſell. They looking earneſtly one vpon another, becam ſo confounded, yt they ſat

wide gaping, and had not the power to ſpeak one word, vntill at length their ſences being reſtored, they thought it neceſſary that Iupiter ſhoulde deſcend to earth, and falling on his knees before me, forſaking both his Crowne and Scepter, ſhould humbly offer himſelfe to my ſeruice, Venus to bee my Shee-ſeruant, Mars my Lacky, and Mercurie mine Apple-Squire.
            
            
               XXXIX.
               AS I was one day playing with the deſtinies, in the preſence of Time, Fortune, and Nature, vpon a difficult happening betweene vs, I was ſuddenly inforced to draw my ſword: Time, Fortune, and Nature, being deare friends to the Deſtinies, ſtept betweene vs to take vp the matter, and make peace. But I being a Spaniard, ſet my right foote formoſt, and gaue therewith ſuch a ſpurne to Time, that I caſt him betweene heauen and earth, and there hee hangs ſtill houering to this inſtant. Fortune, I ſliced hir in twain iuſt at her girdle, and threwe the one halfe of her there where the Sunne riſeth, and the other part where he takes vp his lodging. As for Nature, with my punto reuerſſo, I gaue her ſuch a deepe &amp; incurable wound, as neither Phyſitian, Chirurgion, Barber, nor Apothecary, coulde euer ſince vndertake to heale it, but euery month in the year that wound breakes forth a bleeding.
            
            
               
               XL.
               I Had vpon a time a quarrel with a French Gentleman, who with deſpightfull words, bad me draw my ſword: which I refuſed to do, becauſe I perceiued the French-man to looke pale, and to be of a very chil-cold complerion. Wherefore, in meere pitty to warme his blood, and ſet him in an heat, I ſuffered him to haue ſome fifty Eſtoccadoes at mee, and as many other violent blowes: yet could he not draw blood, or had the power to hurt me. But for my ſelfe, I knew my choller and courage to be ſuch, as with the very leaſt ſillip of my finger, I could haue beaten out his braines, and made him ſinke to hell.
            
            
               XLI.
               BEing deſirous, that Pluto ſhould pay mee ſuch ordinary tribute, as other Kings daily did and do: I tooke my iourny to hell, where I found Pluto walking at his pleaſure, accompanied with fiue hundred and forty fiue Millions, &amp; thirteene hundred ninety and ſix thouſand Legions of Deuils, that vſually attended vpon him. So ſoone as he beheld me a far off, comming towards him, he came directly to meet me and yeild himſelfe as

my priſoner. But I laid hand vpon my Sword, and Pluto perceiuing me to be offended, &amp; in choller, knowing (withall) that I was a Spaniard, fled backe into the deepeſt partes of hell, with all his traine frightfully following him, &amp; there made faſt the gates againſt me. But I being come thither for better obedience, marched on gallantly ſtep by ſtep, as thoſe of my nation are wont to do: and with a very ſneezing of my noſe, I made the gates flye open, and I entred. In a moment, I took there for my priſoners, great Sathan himſelfe, the Prince Pluto, and the faire Proſerpina; all whoſe hands I bounde faſt together with a hayre of my Mouſtachios or beard. Neuertheleſſe, beholding their inceſſant teares and lamentations, made with ſuch out-cries and wringing of hands: I vſed the mercy and magnificencie of a Spaniard, deliuered them out of their ſeruile bands▪ and ſo ſuffered them to enioy their former liberty.
            
            
               XLVII.
               I Wil kil this Villain, his Wife, his Children, his Seruants, his Dogs, his Cats, his Pullaine, his very Lice, Nits &amp; Fleas, or any liuing creature belonging to his houſe, which alſo I wil ruinyte from the top to the foundation: though Pluto himſelfe, and al the Deuils that are in hel, had ſolemnly vowed to ſaue them from my furie: And

what is my chiefeſt purpoſe heerein? Only to conſtitute ſuch a dread and terror of me, in the hearts of men, as no one (be he neuer ſo bold or couragious) ſhal at any time heereafter dare to offend me.
            
            
               XLIII.
               IT was my chance (one day) to bee walking abroad, ſomewhat necre to the Trenches which were made at Oaſtend; when ſuddenly a Bullet, being ſent from a piece of great Ordinance, fel into my mouth, ſhook two of my formoſt teeth, without any iniury or offence vnto mee. At the inſtant houre, I grew to be ſomwhat incenſed with choller, and the Bullet I took into my hand, &amp; caſting or returning it againſt the enemy, it happened to hit againſt a Tower in the wall, which immediately in an inſtant was driuen into ſmail duſt, and ſlew with the very fall thereof, about 1555. gallant Souldiors, who (by eſpeciall appointment) were placed there as a Corps du Guard, &amp; had the charge both of the Tower and wall.
            
            
               XLIIII.
               VPon a time, I would take a walke into Hell, where I found Pluto, Proſerpina, &amp; Death, all fitting at

a Table. They were in ſuch a fearefull aſtoniſhment, beholding me in their darkeſome dwelling, that I (wel knowing their weaknes of courage) without any further delay, leaping vp with a Caper after the French faſhion, with the verye crowne of my Hat or Beauer, broake the roofe of hell; and mounting forth at that breach, the meere noiſe of my departure thence, was ſuch, that it made the great Citty of Lisbone to tremble, and ouerturned 88
                     •
                  . houſes, in the ſtreet of Boaniſtre.
               
            
            
               XLV.
               BE not you offended, Miſtris and Ladie of my life, neither let it ſeeme diſpleaſing to you, that I am ſought after, and beloued by ſo many Brinceſſes &amp; Paragons; who but wrong themſelues therein, and meerely looſe their labor in vain. For I beare affection to no other, but only to your ſelf my ſweeteſt miſtris: becauſe you are indued with beauty farre beyond Diana, with good graces and behauiour, excelling Pallas, and with ſweet affability more ſupreme, then Venus. Al theſe three Soueraigne Goddeſſes equall not you, to whome I haue freely giuen my hart, &amp; properly choſen you as mine owne. Conſider then that I loue you, and forſake not me for any other, in regard that I am more then a Gentleman. Wherefore, if you marry with me, A ſweare by the faith of a Captaine, and by the life of the King my Father (for I neuer

heard him called by any other name) to beget yee the firſt night ſuch a regiment of Souldiours, as ſhall conquer all the world in a moment.
            
            
               XLVI.
               MY ſelfe, Hercules, Death, &amp; Loue, met all by chance on a day together, in a place which was appointed for Archery, and each of vs had his Bow and Arrowes there ready. Wee fell to this acord among our ſelues, that he who with his Arrow coulde make the greateſt ſlaughter or execution, ſhould beare away the ampleſt recompence of Honor. Hercules beganne firſt, and with his Arrow, he ſlew all the Panthers, Lyons Tigers, Beares, Wolues: al ſauage Beaſts, Deere, Elephants, Camels, and Buls. Next, Loue took his ſhaft, and drawing it to the head, he cauſed al the Gods, Gyants, Amazons, Men and Deuils; to fal and ſubmit themſelues vnder his amorous yoke (my ſelfe onely excepted, on whome Loue could not attaine to any power.) Death being reſolued to let looſe his Areow, he killed therewith all the creatures that were vpon the earth. Wherupon, I grew into ſome diſpleaſure againſt thē, &amp; beeing moued in a moity of choller, to be reuenged on them; I croſt mine Arrow in my Bow, determining to let it be my very laſt ſhoot, to auoyd all further quarrell and contention, but no ſooner flew mine Arrow from me (being let looſe indeed

with extraordinary ſpirit and courage) but in the very inſtant, I ſlew therewith, Hercules, Loue, and Death, and ſo remained the ſole Conqueror.
            
            
               XLVII.
               I Kiſſe the ſhoo-ſole of your Lady-ſhip, ſole Miſtris of my heart; Princeſſe of this breaſtes power, Dutcheſſe of this armes dexterity, Marqueſſe of my matchleſſe courage, Counteſſe of my valors capricious conceits, Queene of my forces Quinteſſence, and abſolute Gouerneſſe of me and my perſon.
               I am conſtrained to ſpit daily on the poynt of my ſword, for feare it ſhould paſſe fatally on any perſon in your preſence, or where your vertue may command my demonorance. This Epitaph is engrauen vpon his Tombe, whom I laſt ſlewe, for not being bare before you.
               
                  The Epitaph.
                  HEerelyeth Martino Alphonſo, Galeone, as dead as a Mouſe, who fearing to offend the only gallant man of the World, deſired to bee blowne away with his breath, becauſe his loue was out of date, and he durſt no longer liue in this world.
               
            
            
               
               XLVIII.
               
                  HE that dares but looke on mee,
                  From feare he neuer can be free;
                  Knowing my puiſſance of ſuch might,
                  That Death himſelfe, I kill out-right.
               
               
                  Alone I am, without compare,
                  To prooue my man-hoode, no man dare.
               
               
                  When I holde my Sword in hand,
                  Renowne and Honour I command:
                  From the Goddes is my deſcent,
                  And with them muſt my time be ſpent.
               
               
                  My Sword and Buckler dooth ſuffice,
                  Againſt a thouſand enemies:
                  They are as nothing in my ſight,
                  I make the Earth and Goddes affright.
                  What ere he be that dare reſiſt,
                  He dyes, then tarrie if he liſt.
               
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

