
   
      
         
            A declaration made by the Archbishop of Collen, vpon the deede of his mariage, sent to the states of his archbishoprike VVith the letter of Pope Gregorie the. 13 against the celebration of the same mariage, and the Bishops aunswer therevnto. According to the coppie imprinted at Collen. 1583.
            Gebhard, Truchsess von Waldburg, Archbishop and Elector of Cologne, 1547-1601.
         
         
            
               1583
            
         
         Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2004-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01567
            STC 11693
            ESTC S102953
            99838712
            99838712
            3100
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01567)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3100)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 295:03)
         
         
            
               
                  A declaration made by the Archbishop of Collen, vpon the deede of his mariage, sent to the states of his archbishoprike VVith the letter of Pope Gregorie the. 13 against the celebration of the same mariage, and the Bishops aunswer therevnto. According to the coppie imprinted at Collen. 1583.
                  Gebhard, Truchsess von Waldburg, Archbishop and Elector of Cologne, 1547-1601.
                  Deloney, Thomas, 1543?-1600.
                  Gregory XIII, Pope, 1502-1585.
               
               [40] p.   
               
                  Printed by Iohn VVoolfe,
                  London :
                  1583.
               
               
                  The Archbishop of Collen = Gebhard, Truchsess von Waldburg.
                  Translator's dedication signed: Thomas Deloney.
                  German original not traced.
                  Signatures: A-B C⁴.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Gebhard, --  Truchsess von Waldburg, Archbishop and Elector of Cologne, 1547-1601.
               Celibacy --  Catholic Church --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2004-03
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2004-03
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2004-07
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2004-07
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2004-10
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               
                  
                     ❧A declaration
made by the Archbishop
of Collen, vpon the
deede of his mariage, sent to
the States of his Archbishoprike.
                  VVith the letter of Pope
Gregorie the .13▪ against the celebration
of the same mariage,
and the Bishops aunswer
therevnto.
                  According to the coppie Imprinted
at Collen. 1583.
                  LONDON
Printed by Iohn VVoolfe.
1583.
               
            
         
         
            
            
            ¶To the right reuerend Father in God
Iohn, Bishoppe of London, Thomas Delone,
wisheth increase of grace, and continuall happinesse,
both of body and soule.
            
               
                  IT is not vnknowne to the
learned, nor of the wise forgotten,
(right reuerend Father) in what
miserable seruitude, intollerable
tormentes, heauines of heart, and
griefe of conscience, the godlie
hath from time to time continued vnder the tyranny
of superstitious Popes and Prelates of Rome, whose
intollerable pride is of the Lord detested, and of all
christian people abhorred, through whose hipocrisie
the world hath been so long deceaued &amp; many thousand
soules drawne frō the truth, to the abhominable
seruice of idolatry, forsaking the lawes and cōmaū
               dements
of God, to followe the vanities &amp; traditions
of men. Neuerthelesse, they are not ashamed most
impudently to challenge to themselues the name and
title of Catholiques and the seruants of Christ, &amp; yet
treadeth his word vnder feete, despising his holy ordinances
and institutions, and as it were in despite of
his glory, follow the works of their owne imaginations.
But after the world had of long time beene
blinded, by the notable dissimulation of this deceauing
church▪ the Lord of his mercy and loue, sending
the light of his holy worde, for the reliefe of his afflicted
flocke plainly discouered their hipocrisie, and
their filthines to all flesh. Wherby it is come to passe
that many worthy personages, lately liuing in darknes
and ignorance, is now turned to the trueth, with
most earnest repentance of their former life. And among
the rest, through the great mercy and grace of

God, this worthy Prince, &amp; bishop of Collen, Ghebbard,
whose hart being opened, and his eyes cleared,
hath most effectually showne the fruites of his vnfained
repentance, and hauing made declaration therof
throughout his dominions and iurisdictions, hath abolished
the abhominable masse, and in steed thereof
planted the euerlasting &amp; glorious Gospel of Christ,
to the great comfort of many grieued and wounded
cōsciences. Which when the Pope perceiued, &amp; knew
with great flattery and adulation, he sought to withdraw
him frō this most godly &amp; christian enterprise,
charging him with the othe he made to the church
Apostolique, &amp; with his duty towards God, which he
both by scripture, but specially by their owne lawes,
counsell, &amp; decrees, doth manifestly defend, &amp; by the
fame approue, that he hath done nothing against his
othe or duty in any respect: and the rather dooth he
reproue them by their owne aucthoritie, for as much
as the same is the greatest confutation that maye be
against them. And because the same was done by a
worthy person of noble race and parentage, and a bishop
by office &amp; calling, I thought none more meete
for the patron of such a specialty, thē your Lordship,
vnto whome I owe all duty &amp; reuerence, who for the
good will borne to your Lordshippe, hath dedicated
vnto you this simple translation, faithfully &amp; iustlie
done according to the coppy. Trusting you will accept
the same according to the worthines therof, and
be a defence against all that shall seeme to mislike of
the matter: and in so doing, you shall binde me for
euer at your cōmaund▪ vnto whome I wish continuall
prosperity in this present life, &amp; in the world to come
ioyes euerlasting.
            
               Your Lordships most humble at commaund,
Thomas Deloney.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶A Christian declaration
touching the Religion which the
right reuerend Prince, the Lord Ghebbard,
chosen, and confirmed Archbishop
of Collen, Elector of the Empire,
and Chancelor for the Prouince of
Italie, Duke of Westphalie and Enghern,
and proclaimed throughout
his dominions, the 17. daye
of Ianuarie. 1583.
            
               
                  WE Ghebbard, by the
grace of God elected,
and confirmed Archbishop
of Collen, Chancellor
for the prouince
of Italie, Elector of the
Empire, Duke of Westphalie, Enghern,
&amp;c. to ye Estates, Earles, Gentlemen,
Citizens, &amp; subiects, of our Archbishoprike
ingenerall, and to euerie
one particular, and to all other vnder
our obedience. Know you by this present,
all aboue named, and euerie of
you, as we neuer had nothing more in
minde, since it pleased God to call vs
to the estate &amp; office of this our Archbishoppe,

by a lawfull election (which
yet we also haue) then the safegard and
defence of this Archbishop sea and electorshippe,
committed vnto vs by God,
and likewise of Germanie, one part of
vs, principally in that which cōcerneth
the glorie of God: and hauing had most
humble supplications &amp; requests, made
vnto vs by some of the Estates and
Nobles of our dominions, ioyned with
earnest sute of the most noblest Estates
of this great and mightie Empire, to
haue the Gospell publiquely preached,
and the Sacramentes administred in
all places of our dominions: as it is ordained
and appointed by the word of
God. Following the articles, and confession
of Auspourg, and the christian
exposition thereof, according to the will
of God, which is that Iesus Christ his
sonne, should of vs be hearkened vnto,
and his commaundementes obserued
and kept: that all Princes and Magistrates
of this world; might open their
gates to the king of glory, that thereby
we may learne to knowe our duety in
the charge to vs committed, knowing

there is no excuse for vs, at the last day,
when Christ shall come in iudgement:
what time we must render account of
the charge and office wherein he hath
placed vs. For if by vs the way of saluation
should be stopt toward our subiectes,
being nothing ignorant thereof,
God which is a iust and seuere Iudge,
vnto whose will and commaundement
we are all bound to obey (&amp; that without
dissimulation) would not sée it vnreuenged.
            We for these causes, vnderstanding
the humble peticiōs of our sayd States
and subiectes, are determined no longer
to deferre the graunt of their iust
and rightfull request, hauing had the
aduise of our Lords and counsayle, and
after great deliberation we haue permitted,
to our aforesayd subiects, vnder
the dominion of our Archbishop sea, of
what state or condition soeuer, not only
the libertie of their conscience (alwayes
agréeing to the word of GOD)
but also assuraunce by this our present
ordinaunce, and by vertue therof, that
they shall not be grieued, molested, or

troubled in their personnes, dignities,
honors, or goods, by any gouernors, Iustices,
or other inferiour magistrates,
whatsoeuer. For the profession of their
faith, cōscience, &amp; rule of Religiō, being
according to Gods word &amp; the confessiō
of Auspurg. Graunting fréely to al prelats,
Earles, Lords, Cities, &amp; towns, wt
all other our commons &amp; subiects vnder
our Archbishop sea, &amp; Electorship, ful libertie
to vse publique preaching in all
parts of our dominion, &amp; to exercise the
administratiō of the holy Sacraments,
as it is ordained by the writings of the
Apostles &amp; Prophets, folowing ye Christian
exposition of Auspurg, &amp; notwithstāding
all impeachments of our Lieutenants
and Magistrates, or other persons
whatsoeuer: assuring for the same
(as it is the duty and office of a christian
Prince) of all and euerie vnder our
dominion and iurisdiction, to defende
and maintaine them through the helpe
and grace of GOD, being certainly
perswaded, that his almightie power
hath béene the onely direction of this
our christian enterprise, and that he

will defend his glory and holy worde,
against all the gates of hell.
            Moreouer we protest before the maiestie
of almightie God, which is the
searcher of the hearts and raines, that
we haue not taken in hand this godlie
and christian enterprise, moued by ambition
or desire of honour, or any other
thing to our particuler profit and commoditie:
but for the glorie of Christe
Iesus our onely sauiour and redéemer,
and the aduancement of his holy word,
and for the eternall felicitie and saluation
of our subiectes, which he hath giuen
vs in charge. Neither haue we
done it to rayse discord and discention
in the common wealth, but rather to
set and establish one christian order, in
the Churches and Schooles of this coū
               trey,
as it is thought conuenient, by the
counsayle and aduise of the principall
of our Estates: minding to take delyberation
and aduise vpon the reformation
of the Churches and Schooles of
our sayd Archbishop sea, &amp; Electorship,
at the first assembling of our States &amp;
Lordes, as soone as oportunitie shall

serue. Admonishing the while all
those vnder the óbedience of our foresayd
Elector, which shall be moued to
imbrace and follow the religiō established
at Auspourg, and the expositions
of the same, agéeing to the worde of
God, behauing themselues in all modesty,
as it becommeth all such as are
led by true christian zeale. Forbidding
them expresly, that they shall doo no
wrong nor iniury to any in déede, or in
wordes, to the ende that euerie one of
them maye liue quietly and peaceably
one with an other.
            And for the perticular safegarde of
our person, if it come to passe by the
will of God, that we should ioyne our
selues in mariage, to the end that none
might take occasion to blame vs, as doing
the same against our duety, séeking
thereby some perticular profite or commodity,
or that our intēt were, to leaue
to our heires some aduantage, to the
preiudice of our sayd Archbishop sea, or
Electorship, and to gratifie the same against
all reason or henestie. We protest
by this our publique writing, and

before the eternall &amp; euerliuing God,
that the same was neuer our purpose
or intent: that is to say, to drawe vnto
our heires, our sayd Archbishop sea, or
to bring them to any right of the same
succession, or for any other perticular
profite to their commoditie.
            And for this cause we will haue it openly
declared, by the publication, of
this our present ordinaunce, that whosoeuer
shall hereafter come, the election
ought to remaine at libertie, vnto
the consent of ye rest of our most noble
Electors (as heretofore it hath béene)
and after our decease, to be resigned
without force. And for this cause, all
and euerie of our subiectes and other
personnes vnder the obedience of our
Archbishop and Electorship, shall vnderstand,
that they are not held, or boūd
to owe any obedience, or in any respect
to reuerence, any man whatsoeuer (as
their true and rightfull Lord) tyll such
tune, as by the consent and councell of
our Electors, the Prince which shall
succéed, be lawfullie and righfullie chosen.
And that they shall not acknowledge,

or take for their Prince, any that
shall enterprise to take it in hād, without
the ordinarie and lawfull election
of our aforesayde Electors, and the expresse
declaration of him which shall
succéede, by their aucthoritie: as it hath
béene obserued by long and auncient
custome (notwithstanding any disposition
heretofore made by vs, or any other
preposed) against this our present
ordinaunce: but without regard therof,
we vtterly at this present, and for
the time to come, declare them of no
effect. Abrogated and abolished them
in the straitest manner and forme that
maye be, being ready at all times to
conferre, and take more deliberation
vpon the same, with our aforesayde Electors
and States of our prouince, making
them such confirmation and assuraunce
of this our present promise, in
such maner that no daunger, nor feare,
or other damageable enterprise maye
come or happen, for any such matter by
vs, or by our heires. Therefore, we
charge and commaund, all and euerie
of our Lordes, gouernors, magistrates,

Iudges, Treasurers, Receauers, Consulles,
Citizens, commons, and all in
generall, diligently, and straitly, to obserue
this our present commaund, that
euerie one may be maintained according
therevnto. And that they may
neither hurt, or doo iniurie to any, nor
they of any, be iniuried or molested, for
whosoeuer shall herein be found faultie,
shall incurre our indignation and
displeasure, and shall not escape most
grieuous punishment: for this is the
truth of our last charge and commaundement.
In witnesse whereof, we
haue published, and imprinted, and
sealed with our seale, this our present
declaration, causing it to be caried into
all partes and places of our dominions,
vnto such, as shall make it known
to all. Giuen at our Citie of Bonne,
the .16. daye of Ianuarie, in the yéere of
our Lord. 1583.
         
         
            
            ¶Pope Gregorie the 13. to our right
reuerend and beloued brother, Ghebbard
Archbishop of Collen, Prince, and
Elector of the Empire.
            
               RIght reuerend &amp; beloued
brother, the great &amp; woorthy
personage, procéeding
from the Noble house of
Truchces, your auncient &amp;
honorable progenitors, as well in auncient
time, as of fresher memorie, hath
left vs sufficient witnes of the worthines
thereof, and nobilitie of their blood:
whose affection and constancie, hath alwaies
béene manifestlie declared towardes
the catholique faith, but principallie,
by Cardinall Augustus, which
held the first seate hereof, vnder whose
discipline you haue béene most religiouslie
and holilie brought vp, as it was
cōuenient for ye holie Church of Rome,
in such manner as there was no small
hope conceaued of you, trusting that
you will shew your selfe a person worthy
so noble a race, by the like instruction:
from whence hath growne the fatherly
good will, which hitherto we

haue borne vnto you: which we haue
not onely since that time entertained,
but also in like manner augmented, by
the meanes of the good report of honorable
personages: which promised vnto
vs all things with you most excellēt
&amp; iust. After it came to passe, that you
were elected by the charter of Collen▪
               
to the dignitie &amp; Archbishop sea of this
church, and although that election was
disturbed by sundrie &amp; manifold difficulties,
in such sort that it was not onlie
stronglie withstoode, but in a maner
vanquished &amp; made vaine. Neuerthelesse,
we vsed such benignitie towards
you, that all impeachmentes reiected,
we approued and allowed the iudgement
and election, made by the same
charter for you. Increasing the force
and vertue of our Apostolique cōfirmation:
by reason whereof we are persuaded,
that there is none which ought
to beare greater reuerence to the holie
seate of Rome, nor that ought to be a
greater obseruer of the ecclesiasticall
discipline, then you, hoping that we
should haue had great helpe, through

your constancie &amp; fidelitie. But it doth
greatly displease vs, and merueilously
grieue vs, that our hope therein is not
onely weakned and made lesse, but also
vtterly lost. And further, we vnderstand
from day to day, by the letters of
many, and the report of diuerse, such
thinges of you, so vnworthy the dignitie
&amp; degrée wherein you are, that without
great shame, we are not able to expresse
it. And although verilie we haue
oftentimes refused to beléeue such vnworthy
reportes, yet the daylie clamor
hath constrained vs greatlie to doubte
thereof, being afraid of your fall, which
now we wil no lōger dissemble, wherfore
we doo admonishe you, that you
would haue a regard and a foresight to
your honour and saluation (while it is
time) and if possible you haue gone any
further, then reason required, spéedilie
withdraw your selfe, that those things
which heretofore hath béen declared of
you, may be proued false (which is our
onlie desire) &amp; that you will openly manifest
your mind &amp; ful intent, inwardlie
cōceiued in your hart: to ye end, that

your good name, princelie parentage, &amp;
the ecclesiasticall order, be not by your
means for euer stained, wt ignominius
reproch, by ye aduersaries of our honor.
            Againe, consider your duty towards
God, which hath raised you to the dignitie
and degrée of the sea Apostolique,
which you should cherish with singuler
affection and fauour, and for the same
it is that you ought to spend your blood
in all christian profession: For by how
much the more you are of hie calling,
and honourable estate, by so much the
more is your fault greater, then any others,
when you fall from any parte of
your duety. And by so much the more,
wil your fault be greater, as you were
of honour and dignitie, in the church of
God, and in great aucthoritie with the
Princes of the Empire. Consider then
what troubles and daūgers procéedeth
from such new remoouings of thinges,
and how héedfull the prudent and godlie
man ought to be, from hazarding
so lightly his honour, state, dignitie,
and his soule, whereof there hath béen
so many straunge and wonderfull examples

in our time, which may make
vs to be better aduised in our dealings,
but if we haue possible suffered somewhat
to much in former time, attribute
the same to our affection towards
you, and to the desire we haue had of
your honor and dignitie. Neither doo
we any thing doubt, but that this our
fatherly kindnes, shall be receaued of
you with that effect which it ought to
be, for many good reasons and iust causes:
and that you will not forgette to
shew due reuerence towardes this holy
seate, that we maye acknowledge
you, for our déere and beloued sonne,
as heretofore we haue done, which wil
be an occasion to vs greatly to reioyce:
and because we haue not thought it
sufficient to send our letters onely, we
haue sent our reuerend Brother, the
Archbishop of Treues, to take his iourney
towardes you, to conferre more at
large, of these our affaires, who shall
more cléerelye discouer vnto you our
will, counsayle, and intent, to whome
we are assured that you will giue both
faith and credite.
            
               Giuen at Rome,
                  
at saint Peters 
                  in the yéere of our Lord
1582. the 17. day of December,
                and in
the 11. yéere of our Pontificalitie.
Io. Baptista Canobius.
            
         
         
            To Pope Gregorie the .13. Ghebbard
Archbishop of Collon, Prince, and
Elector of the Empire, sendeth greeting.
            
               
                  I
                Haue vnderstood by your
letter, your fatherlie affection,
and worthinesse
of such a Prelate, but in
this principally, that you
will not lightlie giue place, to vntrue
tales, neither faith to the euill reports
spread abroad of my actions and déeds.
For if it were sufficient to accuse, who
should be in these corrupted dayes excused,
wherein the most godliest men,
are assailed with enuie 
                  •
                and what is
he that can defend himselfe against the
conspiracies of euil willers, I acknowledge
you as a good father, exhorting
me to perseuere in the faith, integrete
good discipline, and obedience vnto the
Chatholique, Apostolique, and true beléeuing
Church. Giuing me aduertisement

of the great and manifold daungers,
falling on those, which are desirous
of nouelties, which folowing their
disordinate lustes and affections, are
drawne from the company of the Apostolique
church. Wherefore my duty is
to accept of your charitable &amp; holie admonitions,
knowing that which is said
by Salomon, that he which refuseth discipline,
hath no regarde of his owne
soule: but he that harkeneth to correction,
shall obtaine knowledge. I must
néedes confesse, that I haue béene ouer
slacke and negligent in thinges appertaining
to the saluatiō of my soule, the
rest of my conscience, and the duetie I
owe to the glorie of God, and the dignitie
of the Church.
            But your letters hath serued me as a
spurre, pricking me forward, &amp; greatly
prouoking me, yt all dissimulation laid
aside, &amp; all superstition by me reiected,
I am minded openly to declare (euen
as you haue admonished me) yt which I
haue conceaued in my heart, &amp; considering
the faith I owe vnto GOD, that
hath called me to this his degrée, that

which I owe to the church Apostolique
to my countrey, &amp; the publique wealth
thereof, and also to my selfe, knowing
the saying of that great and holie man
Augustine to be true, and worthy to be
had in memory, that there is none that
doth more harme to the flocke of Christ
then such as coūterfetteth the lambe in
the roome and office of the ministerie,
the same is cited 83. distinction, the second
cannon. For as much then I am
come to the age, wherein I am able
without the aduice of others to gouern
my selfe, and by the onely will of our
Lord Iesus Christe, which hath vouchsaued
to call me to the great charge of
an Archbishop: and as it is a thing proper
to the nature of a christian man, to
inquire and followe after the trueth, I
am setled in the furtheraunce of this
good worke, without musing at all, on
any custome or humaine authority: finding
by the holie scriptures, and amōg
the ecclesiasticall histories, yt this which
we haue commaunded to be done, becōmeth
him which is the child of God:
and which is also required in the office

himself hath already established, yt is to
say, Iesus Christ, which is ye only way,
the trueth, and the life, in whose name,
as also with the Father and the holie
Ghost we are baptised: to whome appertaineth
ye catholique church, hauing
redéemed ye same by his precious blood.
Upon this foundation is the church sustained,
being also beautified and inriched
with most excellent tytles, which
he hath giuen by S. Paule in the first to
Timothy, the third chapter: calling her
the house of ye liuing God, the fortitude
&amp; strength of the trueth. Then the Romane
church which was in the time of
S. Paule, and certaine yéeres after, was
of great renoume and estimation, for
the faith they had in Iesus Christ, and
at that time taught through the whole
world: the which faith was her onelie
ornament, insomuch that the Priests &amp;
Elders of the same Romane Church,
plainly cōfessed, writing to S. Ciprian
in his 7. epistle of his 2. booke, in these
words, That letting the honor &amp; praise
decay, which S. Paule gaue to the Romanes,
was a great &amp; grieuous crime,

and yt it had béene lesse shame, neuer to
haue had those prayses spoke of, or preached
abroade, then after the publishing
thereof, to lose the honour of such high
commendations. Therfore as often as
it comes in question, to speake of the
pure, true, Apostolique, and vniuersall
church: reason requireth, and all wise
men giueth counsaile, that we ought to
discerne betwéene that, which is groū
               ded
vpon the head corner stone, Christ,
vpon the holy Gospell (the honour and
name wherof shal endure euerlastingly:)
and that which is ye bastard church,
going against the trueth▪ worshippeth
God in vaine, following after the commaūdements
&amp; traditions of men. And
therfore ye goldē rule of Tertullian, hath
euer pleased al good and vertuous men,
saying, that the first hath béen alwayes
the truth, &amp; that which came afterward
corrupted, and that is it which hindeth
mee to the othe which I haue made,
which othe dooth cōmaund, that I must
acknowledge the sayde Apostolique
church, which holdes the ancient beléefe
of the Romane church, agréeing to the

beléefe of Nice, and of Constantinople,
which dooth acknowledge and beléeue
one baptisme for remission of sinnes, by
ye blood of our Lord Iesus Christ: which
is our onely purgatorie that cleanseth
vs of all our sinnes, which receaueth
no other traditions then this only, that
are appointed by the Apostles, leauing
&amp; deliuering faithfully, that which they
receiued from our Lord Iesus Christ.
After whose example I am bounde by
my othe, to take the holy scriptures, interpreting
and vnderstāding the same,
not after the sence or interpretation of
any Bishop or Councell, whatsoeuer,
but after the vnderstanding and exposition
of the true, Apostolique, and holy
mother Church, that (I say) which hath
followed the steps of the holy Apostles.
Whervnto the auncient Fathers hath
from time to time consented, so that
without any blemish to the othe which
I haue made, I am addressed after this
rule, &amp; bound to this foūdation, neither
will I receyue or beléeue any thing,
which is not brought from the same,
wheresoeuer it was writtē, whether at

               Rome, or at Trent, being reasonable to
prefer these aunciēt things with new,
the truth with falsehood, &amp; the traditiōs
of the Apostles, with ye cōmaūdements
of men. For our lawes as it dooth euidently
appeare in the 15. distinctiō of ye
third canon: doth not alowe these auncient
and most renoumed Councelles
the like aucthority, as they do to the holie
Scriptures &amp; Apostles, which sayth
thus: The holy church of Rome, after
the writinges of the old and new Testament,
which we receiue for certaine
rules, doth not forbid but that we may
receiue the Councell of Nice, of Constantinople,
Ephesus, and of Chalcedonae.
Thus haue I hytherto shewed, what
was the band and foundation of yt othe
which I lent, vpō the which I protest,
that (by the grace of God) I will not
starte nor turne, from the true faith in
Iesus Christe, nor seperate my selfe
from the holy and Apostolique church,
to the which I do owe all reuerence, as
I wil doo all my life: in remembrance
of that which I did vowe in baptisme
to God, and promised to the Church.

For the rest, it is out of doubt betwéene
all good and learned men, that whatsoeuer
we haue promised or sworne, if it
be wrong &amp; contrarie to our first faith,
receyued in baptisme, that it bindeth
vs not at all, this (I saye) is to be seene
by the rule of the right cannon Lawe,
that is to say, that an oth taken against
good and godlie workes, bindeth not:
and following the right cannon, the
othes that are made against good déeds,
drawes vs vnto sinne. Wherevpon
the Maister of Sentences hath wiselie
sayd, in the 39. Distinction after Saint
Hierome, that an othe hath three proper
companiens, veritie, iudgement,
and iustice, and if any of these lacke, it
is not a true othe, but a false othe: But
Gratiā
                giueth these aduertisemēts vpō
the déede of an oth, Euil promises (saith
he) breakes faith, chaunge therfore the
the ordinaunce of euill and dishonest
thinges, and do not that, which thou
hast vnwiselie promised, for that promise
is against God, which is accomplished
with wickednesse.
            
            In the seuenth cannon of our lawe,

we haue a rule giuen, which we ought
straitlie to obserue, not onely for the regard
of othes, but in all the actions of
our life (that is to say) that if by the sutteltie
of our craftie enimie, we are falling
into any faulte, we must séeke to
escape it, by that meanes which we sée
is least hurtfull and daungerous: thus
you sée, that the olde and auncient Fathers
hath generally concluded, that all
vndiscrete and vnlawfull othes, ought
not to be obserued and kept: and that
it is more tollerable for to breake an
othe, then to perseuere in the sinne of
fornication. The same is also learned
by the aucthority of S. Augustine that if
faith be not obserued, to the intent to
returne to the right waye, it cannot be
called ye violating of faith, for as much
that the same is not true faith, which is
requisite to commit sinne. It is easie to
shew by many learned men, and also
by the holie scriptures, and by the auncient
Doctors, that partly the slacknes
and slouthfulnes: and partly by the couetousnes
and malice of many Popes,
sundrie things hath crept in ye Romane

church, as Platinus (though otherwise
greatly affectionated to ye Roman seat)
certifieth that those things do not agree
to the Apostolique &amp; catholique church,
but they are notably iniurious against
Iesus Christ, which is established for to
be the redéemer of peace, by the faith in
his blood, &amp; also most idolatrous, which
whosoeuer should followe of a trueth,
should sinne greeuouslie against God:
and yet as Arnobius sayeth in his seuenth
booke against the Gentiles, that▪
we ought to forgiue liberally and fréely,
though it were against the Church,
and against our owne conscience. For
these thinges then, I am not drawne
through any cause by you, (as many other
great &amp; woorthy personages hath
taken occasiō, to withdraw themselues)
not from the catholique church, but frō
the corruption &amp; abuses, which turneth
vpside downe the foundation thereof.
I wil not for this time enter into long
disputation, but I would rather come
to the crime, wherein I fell my selfe by
you most accused. I sée, I sée, or at the
least, I féele a certaine smell, that cannot

be lesse then a sinnefull thing, the
peine whereof, craueth the losse of my
life, or of my charge and dignitie: for
the which I am accused among you,
which maketh me most odious, &amp; maketh
the world to thinke, that I reiect
all discipline, all duety, and all honour,
but the shame thereof (falselie accusing
me) maketh your selues almoste to
blush. Which is, because I am purposed
to marie, which S. Paule neuerthelesse
affirmeth, to be honourable amōg
all men: and which is also sette in the
Romane church, among the number of
the Sacramentes. But whensoeuer I
am minded to accomplishe this thing,
what shall I doo, or enterprise against
the examples of the holy Apostles, and
their rules and decrees? What doo I
against the aduise of Clement, Alexandrian?
or against our owne Lawes, in
the .28. Distinction, the .11. and 12. Chapters,
where mention is made of the
wiues of Priests, and Deacons, being
aboundantly contained in the .17. cannon,
as it was decreed by the Councell
of Gangar, that, If any reiect a maried

Priest, being of opinion that he ought
not to offer, because he is maried, and
for that cause will not come to his seruice,
let him be accurst.
            
            Moreouer, those words spoken with
great grauitie by Paphuntius, in the
Councell of Nice, are cōmended in the
second parte of their decrée, which did
not feare to call mariage the second degree
of chastitie. Wherefore is it then
that the aucthoritie of Siricius or Pelagious,
should be of greater waight among
vs, then that of the Apostles? Of
generall Counselles? Of auncient Fathers
before mentioned? Or of GOD
himselfe? Which plainly pronounced,
that it was not good for man to be alone.
What follie, or what madnesse I
praye you is it then, to endure rather
adulterers, fornicators, and Sodomiticall
liuers, in the ministerie and church
of Christ, then those which hath true &amp;
lawfull wiues, following the cōmaundements
of God? From what spring,
or from whose mouth came the same
doctrine, which forbiddeth and condemneth
mariage? It appeareth by the eleuenth

chapter of Daniel, vers. 36. 37. and
the first of Timothy, the fowrth chapt.
ver. 1. 2. 3. Aeneus Silueus, in his discription
of Germany, witnesseth that the
holy bishoppe Vldricus, strongly withstoode
the lawes of Celebat, against the
Popes of his time, writing an Epistle
vnto Pope Nicholas, wherin he greatly
cōplained that the chiefest Prelates,
and Priests (namelie of Italy,) were so
much giuen to lust and lecherie, that
they would not abstaine from deflowring,
maid, wife, or any other, nor spare
theyr owne kindred, but commit sinne
against nature, with ye masquelin sort,
&amp; also with very brute beasts: and there
he declareth an historie worthy the noting,
that Pope Gregorie the first, being
he, that did first forbid ecclesiastical
persons to marie, sending afterwarde,
certaine fishers to fishe in a mote, hard
adioyning to a Nunrie, they founde
more then six thousand childrens heads
that had béene throwne therein, which
when Gregorie sawe, and perceyued
the wicked fruit of his Celebat, sorowing

to heare the same, he brake that decree,
alledging the sentence of S. Paul,
that, It is better to marie then to
burne: Adding also, that it is farre better
to suffer mariage, then to be the
cause of murder. The Abbot Vspergus
also in his Chronicle, maketh mention
of an epistle in the most renoumed coū
               cell
of the ecclesiasticall states at Bresse
Nore, made against Heldebrand, wherin
among other things, was a cōplaint
made, yt he deuorsed spyrituall persons
from theyr wiues, &amp; vnder this detestable
Pope, the Churches were in great
daunger, &amp; also he declared yt they were
not bound in any promise to the Pope,
for it is a greater thing to make a vow
to obey God, and the catholique church,
then to submitte our selues to the will
and pleasure of any Pope, whatsoeuer.
For these reasons, I that knoweth my
duetie towarde Iesus Christe, and his
Church, I am determined to take the
lawfull way and remedy, permitted to
all manner of men (without exception)
against euill and disordinate lustes, as

it becommeth a true bishop, and a man
of noble race to doo: to the ende, that I
may keepe my soule chaste, and arme
the same against all allurements of the
flesh. Therefore am I determined to
enter into mariage, not being mooued
by any light or disobedient minde: but
after long tryall made of my selfe, I
haue knowne that it is not good for me
to liue vnmaried. Which gifte is not
permitted to all, nor for euer, (that is
to say, to make so long a triall of themselues:)
I am resolued, following the
lawes of the church aboue mentioned,
to leaue that vndiscrete vow of the Celebat,
which is not in my power to performe,
estéeming that this is lawful for
me, for the auoiding of a greater euill,
and for the better obseruing &amp; accomplishing
the vowe of chastitie, which I
made vnto Iesus Christ: and in so dooing
I haue framed my selfe according
to the commaūdement of God, submitting
to his prouidence, and staying to
his protection, not caring what euill
men may iudge, nor for ye threatnings,

daungers, or any other thing whatsoeuer,
hauing in memorie that which
Theodorus hath written in his fourth
booke, the tenth chapter, of the auncient
Christians. Whiche dyd knowe no
greater griefe then the renouncing of
pietie: and although the tyrants went
about raging and running vpon them,
as stormes, or tempestes, yet could they
not be shaken or put backe from pietie
and godlines. Therefore, in all extremities,
I haue recourse to the iudgement
of those which hath right intelligence
and knowledge. Unto whome
I doo appeale and submit my selfe, after
the example of Iustinus Martyr, in
his Apolligie for the Christiās. In this
submission most rightfull and iust, that
by those which religiously feareth God
the trueth alone is reuerenced, and to
the same, all and euerie thing must be
agréeing.
            Nowe I addresse my selfe to you
Pope Gregorie, to the ende I may obtaine
of you this my purpose, (being
most chaste and according to the discipline

of the true and auncient Catholique
Church) some protection and defence.
Therefore I doo earnestlie pray
and beseech you, that of the same affection
which it hath pleased you to admonish
me, that you will take my part
in my most iust enterprise, remembring
that those which smothlie flatters
you, (a sort of bribe takers, which
dooth but lightlie and softlie touch the
moste daungerous woundes) bee not
those that dooth most honour, and reuerence
vnto you and the Church: but
well are they, which Plutarch speakes
of, in his Trentes of the difference betweene
the flatterer and the friend:
which boldlie and lyberallie speaketh,
admonishing, and rebuking, not according
to theyr owne appetie and desire.
What am I then that should speake or
brall against the Popes? if they take
all that they say out of the word, lawes
and commaundementes of God, and
out of the writings of the Apostles and
Prophetes, vppon which doctrine, the
Church and the Popes, ought to be

founded and builded; by GOD which
hath the sufferaintie ouer Kinges and
Popes. Oh that it were the good will
and pleasure of him, that I might see
the daye, that you would not take the
care to oppresse me, and all other men,
louers and followers of the doctrine
and life of the Apostles: but rather
that you should earnestlie vndertake
to cast farre away from you, so many
vanities, so many idolatries, simonies,
and sacrileges, and cut off these effeminates,
fornicators, and adulterers,
drunkardes, and idle personnes, which
our owne lawes dooth excommunicate,
to the ende that the Romane church,
might recouer her auncient dignitie,
and that peare and tranquilitie might
come againe, among all Christians.
that many grieued and wounded consciences
might finde rest and consolation.
Nowe as it is commonlie sayde,
that of a poore gardener, or a simple
man, something may be heard of reasonable
sence: so I hope that you will
not take this my small admonition, otherwise,

then with a fatherlie, religious,
and equitable hart: which is made
vnto you by one of your Brothers in
Iesus Christ, and an Almayn, which
could neuer dissemble, wherevppon,
I praye God to kéepe
you in his protection.
            FINIS.
         
      
   

