
   
      
         
            Ieroboams sonnes decease a funerall sermon on part of 1 Kings 14. 17. By Thomas Gataker B. of D. and pastor of Rotherhith.
            Gataker, Thomas, 1574-1654.
         
         
            
               1627
            
         
         Approx. 128 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01538
            STC 11663
            ESTC S102970
            99838729
            99838729
            3117
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01538)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3117)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1066:03)
         
         
            
               
                  Ieroboams sonnes decease a funerall sermon on part of 1 Kings 14. 17. By Thomas Gataker B. of D. and pastor of Rotherhith.
                  Gataker, Thomas, 1574-1654.
               
               [4], 44 p.   
               
                  Printed by Iohn Hauiland,
                  London :
                  1627.
               
               
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Funeral sermons.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-10
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-01
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-07
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2006-07
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            Ieroboams SONNES DECEASE: A FVNERALL SERMON ON PART OF 1 KINGS 14.17.
            BY Thomas Gataker B. of D. and Paſtor of Rotherhith.
            LONDON, Printed by IOHN HAVILAND. 1627.
         
         
            
            
            TO MY LOVING FRIENDS AND COSENS, Mr. NICOLAS CRISPE, And Mris. ANNE CRISPE his Wife.
            
               GOod Coſens, I know not well, what ſhould moue, either others to be ſo importunate with you, or you with me, for the making of this, preached at the late buriall of your little one, more publike. Somewhat (it ſeemeth) you heard therein handled, that you either had not at all before heard; or not deliuered (which is more likely) in that manner as then it was. And if it may bring any further light than hath formerly beene giuen, to the clearing either

of that point ſo eargerly oppoſed by the Pelagians, of ſinne, and the guilt thereof in Infants; or of that other doubt rather ſo much debated by many, concerning the iuſtice and equity of Gods proceedings in the puniſhing of Parents in poſterity; and may either in that regard, or any other way, be vſefull, either to your ſelues, or others, it is enough. Let it, howſoeuer, remaine as a pledge of my continued loue and affection to that Family, which ſince my firſt acquaintance with, and alliance to, I haue found ſo much comfort in, and receiued ſo much kindneſſe from; and vpon which deſiring God to continue, and multiply his graces and mercies, I take leaue, and reſt
            
               
                  Yours euer in the Lord Ieſus, Thomas Gataker.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            Ieroboams SONNES DECEASE.
            
               
                  
                     1 KING. 14.17.
                  
The Childe died.
            
            
               IT was foretold by Gods Prophet of this Childe, that it ſhould die. And the Prophet (you ſee) proued a true Prophet: For (ſaith my Text) the Childe died.
            
            Now howſoeuer a Childes death may ſeeme a matter of no great moment;Death of Children. yet the Death of Children, and more eſpecially the Death of this Childe, being duely conſidered,Of this Childe. Ieroboams. may well afford much matter of good vſe.
            
            The Childe was Ieroboams, a good Sonne of a bad Father, for his Parents ſinne by God ſmitten, before with ſickneſſe, and now with Death.
            
            The ſtorie briefly is this. Ieroboam,
               The Storie. 
               King of the 1 King. 11.31. &amp; 12.20. 
               Ten Tribes rent from Salomons houſe, had out of 1 King. 12.26, 27, 28. a wicked worldly policie, put downe Gods true

               worſhip within his Territorie, and ſet vp Idolatrie in the roome of it. For this the wrath of God being incenſed againſt him, the Lord ſmote with ſickneſſe 
               Abijas his Son, 1 King. 14.1. a childe he had, which (it ſeemeth) was right deere vnto him. Hereupon Verſ. 4. the Queene his mother, out of a motherly affection to her childe, deſirous to know what was like to become of it, Verſ. 2. with the aduice of her husband alſo, repaireth to one Ahias a Prophet of God, 
               1 King. 11.30, 31. &amp; 14.2. who had ſometime foretold her husband, being then but Salomons ſeruant, that he ſhould ſucceed his Soueraigne in part of his Soueraigntie. But becauſe ſhe thought ſhee ſhould be no welcome gueſt to him, Verſ. 2. ſhe diſguiſed her ſelfe that ſhe might not be knowne. Howbeit the Prophet vnderſtanding from God who ſhee was, told her, he had Verſ. 6. 
               heauie tidings from God for her: That her husbands houſe ſhould be vtterly deſtroyed; 
               Verſ. 10. 
               God would ſweepe it away, as a man ſweepeth away doung, till none of it be left. Verſ. 11. Thoſe of his ſtocke that died in the Citie, ſhould bee eaten with dogs, and thoſe that died in the field, ſhould bee deuoured by the fowles. 
               Verſ. 12, 13. This alone of all the reſt ſhould die in his bed, be laid in his graue, and mourning made for him, becauſe ſome good things were found in him, he had a good heart to God, as a childe might haue. And as the Prophet foretold her, ſo accordingly it fell out: For no ſooner was the Queene his mother returned, but Verſ. 17. euen as ſhee ſet foot vpon the threſhold of the Kings houſe, The childe died.
            
            
               Points.Now from this childes death thus conſidered, diuers points of Inſtruction readily offer themſelues vnto vs,

               
                  Some generall,
                     Generall.
                  
                  Some ſpeciall:
                     Speciall.
                  
               :
            I will pitch vpon two of either. The two Generall 
       points ſhall be;
       
                  
                     
                        Points Generall 2 the former, 
         that euen Children are tainted with ſinne;
                  
                  
                     
                        Points Generall 1 the latter,
         that Death is euer at our doores.
                  
               
               
                  Point Generall 2 For the former, that euen
       Children are tainted with Sinne, We hence deduce it, 
       in that 
                  Point Generall 1
       they are ſubiect to death. For Rom. 6.23. 
               Death is the wages of ſinne. And,
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  , ſtipendium: à re militari tranſlatum. Mortis ſtipendium: vitae donatiuum. Tertull. de reſurr. carn. 
               Rom. 8.10. 
               For ſinne it is that the body dies. And, Rom. 5.12. 
               Death came in by ſinne. And, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   Propterea quod. Ibid. Ita potius quam, In quo vti Vulg. &amp; Aug. de peccat. mer. &amp; rem. c. 10. &amp; ad epiſt. Pel. l. 4. c. 4. &amp; de verb. Ap. 7. &amp; 14. &amp; alibi. 
               Becauſe all haue ſinned, therefore all die. 
               Mors &amp; peccatum, vt acus &amp; filum. Sequatur neceſſe eſt poena peccatum. Aug. de praedeſt. &amp; grat. c. 3. 
               Sinne and Death, are as Needle and Threed; the one entring before, is a meanes to draw on the other, Intrare mors non poſſet, niſi intrante peccato. Aug. ibid. nor would the one follow, if the other went not before. Gen. 2.17. Before Sinne was, there was no death; Apoc. 21.4. 1 Cor. 15.26, 54. nor ſhall there be any, when ſinne ſhall be no more. It is apparant therefore, that euen Children are not free from ſinne, in that they are ſubiect vnto death.
            
            That which may alſo in few words be further confirmed vnto vs,

                  By their Birth;
                  By their new-birth.
                     Confirmation by Reaſons 2.
                  
               
            
            1. By their birth, or their off-ſpring. 
               In vtero damnati ante quam nati, quia de peccato &amp; in peccato procreati &amp; parti. Bern. de temp. 70. They come of ſinnefull perſons, of parents ſtained with 
                  Reaſon 1
               
               ſinne. And Iob 14.4. 
               who can draw a cleane thing out of tha that is vncleane? how can faire water come from a filthy ſpring? Yea euen the Children of faithfull and ſanctified parents; howſoeuer (for the comfort of thoſe that haue them taken hence in their nonage) they are by vertue of their parents copie, and Gods gratious entaile, 
               Fidei candidati, Tertull. de monogam. &amp; Hieron. ad Ocean. &amp; ad Paulin. quaeſt. 2. within the compaſſe of his couenant; it running in thoſe termes, Tibi &amp; ſemini tuo. Gen. 17.7, 10, 11. 
               I will bee thy God, and the God of thy ſeed; and Vobis &amp; liberis veſtris. Act. 2.39. 
               the promiſe therefore is made not to them onely, but to their Children too: and they are in that regard ſaid in ſome ſort to be Quomodo vaſa in tabernaculo ſancta dicuntur, quia ſacris vſibus deſtinata, cum vti
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ſancta eſſe non poſſint, niſi ea quae ſentiunt &amp; venerantur Deum. Hieron. ad Paulin. quaeſt. 2. 
               holy; (Rom. 11.18. 
               If the root bee holy, the ſprigs alſo be holy:) and Quomodo Gal. 2.15. non natura peccatores ex gentibus. Cartwr. Dum in Chriſto cenſentur, ex parentumfide. Morton. 
               cleane: (1 Cor. 7.14. 
               Els were your children vncleane; but now they bee cleane:) And there is good hope therefore of the Matth. 19.14. 
               ſaluation of ſuch; and much more comfort too, when they haue receiued alſo the ſeale of the ſame. Yet certaine it is, that euen the children of the faithfull alſo, (as Dauid, who confeſſeth as much by himſelfe, Pſal. 51.5. 
               Euen bred in iniquitie, and borne in ſinne;) are of themſelues as deepely tainted with this corruption as any. For that De mundatis naſcitur non mundatus, quia tales non facit generatio ſed regeneratio. A peccatis itaque nemo naſcendo, ſedomnes renaſcendo mundamur. Aug. de pecc. mer. &amp; rem. l. 3. c. 9. Cum ſit i
                     •…
                   progenie natorum generatio carnalis, in progenie renatorum regeneratio ſpiritualis, vis vt de baptiſato baptiſatus naſcatur, cum videas de circumciſo non naſci circumciſum? carnalis eſt certè iſta generatio, &amp; carnalis eſt circumciſio; &amp; tamen de circumciſo non naſcitur circumciſus: ſic ergò de baptiſato non poteſt naſci baptiſatus. Aug. de verb. Ap. 14. &amp; Albert. in Ioan. 3. Vide &amp; eund. de verb. Ap. 8. 
               procreation being but a naturall act, the parents thereby can paſſe no more to their iſſue, than what they had naturally themſelues. So Peccatum quod mundatur per baptiſmum manet in eis, quos genuerunt baptiſati, quomodo praeputium, quod per circumciſionem aufertur, manet in eis, quos genuerunt circumciſi. Aug. de pecc. mer. &amp; rem. l. 3. c. 8. the
Rom. 4.11. cum Col. 2.11, 12.
               
               circumciſed father bred an vncircumciſed ſonne: and 1 Cor. 15.37. Seritur ſolummodo granum ſine folliculi veſte, fundamento ſpica, numimento ariſtae, ſuperbia culmi: exurgit copia faeneratū, compagine aedificatum, ordine ſtructum, cultu munitum, vſque
                     •
                   quaque veſtitum. Tertull. de reſurr. carn. corne though it bee neuer ſo curiouſly ſeuered and clenſed, from the ſtraw by threſhing, from the chaffe by winnowing, 
               Pone granum purgatum; de grano purgato frumentum cum palea naſcitur, ſine qua ſeminatur. Aug. de verb. Ap. 14. Palea quae tanta diligentia opere humano ſeparatur, manet in fructu, qui de tritico purgato naſcitur. Idem de pec. mer. &amp; rem. l. 3. c. 8. Tranſmittere p
                     •
                  ſſunt ad poſteros, quod ipſi non habent, vt paleam frumentum, circumciſus praeputium, ſic fideles infidelitatem. Eſt in illis remiſſione mundatum, quod eſt in iſtis ſimili remiſſione, velat circumciſione, velut irituratione &amp; ventilatione mundandum. Ibid. c 9. yet commeth vp againe, if it be ſowne, with both, as before.
            2. By their new-birth. For Non ob aliud inſtiuta eſt regeneratio, niſi quia vitioſa eſt generatio. Aug. encbir. c. 46. Si ſanctificationaſcuntur de fidelibus fil
                     •
                  j, quid opus habent baptizari? Idem de pecc. mer. &amp; rom. l. 2. c. 26. Nemo renaſcatur in corpore Chriſti, niſi prius naſ
                     •
                  atur in corpore peccati: Ibid. l. 1. c. 29. 
               children ſhould not 
                  Reaſon 2 need either regeneration, or baptiſme, the Sacrament of it, were they not before, euen by their firſt breeding, defiled and polluted with ſinne. For 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Chryſ
                     •
                  ſt. in Tit. h
                     •
                  m. 3. nothing can ſpiritually pollute or defile, but it onely. Bernard ſpeaking of thoſe words of the Apoſtle, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Epheſ. 2.3. 
               We were by nature children of wrath, euen as well as the reſt. 
               Filij irae, non furoris. 
               We are, ſaith he, by nature, children of Gods wrath, but yet not children of Gods rage, that is, of his implacable wrath, as 2 Pet. 2.4. Iudae 6. the Deuills are, irrecouerably therefore damned. For, ſaith hee, Si non filius irae naſcerer, non opus eſſet renaſci: ſi filius furoris naſcerer, aui non contigiſſet, aut non proſuiſſet renaſci. Bern. in Cant. 69. 
               Were I not by nature a childe of wrath, I ſhould not need to be renewed; but were I a childe of Gods rage, or his implacable wrath, either ſhould I neuer haue beene renewed, or I ſhould neuer haue beene the better for being renewed.
            
            Both by the firſt and the ſecond breeding then it is apparent, that children are not free from ſinne.
            
            If any ſhall moue doubt here,Queſt. how children can

               haue ſinne, who neither are yet able to doe, ſpeake, wiſh, or thinke euill, yea that doe not ſo much as know what ſinne is.
            
               Anſwer generall 1.1. I might anſwer with Infantes qui negat peccatores, neget &amp; mortales. Peccatum autem vt cum paruulis naſcatur carnis oculis non videmus: ſed quod videmus paruulos mori, cogimur confiteri cum peccato naſci. Aug. de praedeſt. &amp; grat. cap. 3. 
               Auguſtine, that albeit wee could not conceiue how Infants ſhould haue ſinne; yet vnderſtanding out of Gods word, that Rom. 5.12. 
               death came in by ſinne, and that it is an effect and fruit of ſinne, wee muſt acknowledge that they are not free from the one, when we ſee them ſubiect to the other.
            
               Anſwer 2.But 2. I anſwer, that it may well be conceiued how euen children may haue ſinne, though not able yet to act it, or to vnderſtand at all what it is.
            
               
                  Inſtance 1 1. As the brood of Aſpes and Vipers, (for Pſal. 58.4. Eſa. 11.8. ſuch are we compared to) 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plut. de prouid. haue a poiſonfull nature, before euer they come to venome or to ſting any: or as the whelps of Lions, Wolues and Beares (for Eſa. 11.6, 7. ſuch alſo are we ſaid to be) Lupi catulus dum in luſtris deliteſcit caecus, rapinarum rudis &amp; ignarus, ingenium tamen rapax in ſe haber. Zuingl. adu. Calabapt. haue a rauenous diſpoſition in them naturally, before euer they come to bee able to prey, or to apprehend what prey is.
            
               
                  Inſtance 2 2. As wicked men Act. 28.3. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Dio Pruſ. orat. 74. Inſtrumenta illis explicandae nequitiae deſunt. Sic tutò ſerpens etiam peſtifera tractatur; dum riget frigore. Non deſunt tum illi venena, ſed torpent. Sen. ep. 42. 
               Pauls viper, that lay ſtiffe with cold, and for the preſent therefore might bee handled without harme, and yet was it no leſſe venomous all that while, than before. For is a bad man the leſſe euill,
               
when hee lieth faſt aſleepe? Or doth 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   Gyges apud Herodot. l. 1. Theano apud Laert. in Pytbag. &amp; Plut. de aud. &amp; de coniug. Mulier cum veſte deponit &amp; verecundiam. Hieron. adu. Iouin. l. 1. he lay aſide his wickedneſſe together with his weed.
            
            3. Take it by the contratie: as 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Epict
                     •
                  t. en
                     •
                  hir. c. 13. Stob. c. 7. Ita Ariſtot. de anima. l. 1. c. 4. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . a godly man is 
                  Inſtance 3 in the like caſes a good man ſtill, though his ſenſes be ſo locked vp for the time, and the vſe of vnderſtanding and reaſon ſo ſuſpended, that hee can neither minde nor tend any good thing for the preſent. For it is no naturall accident that can impaire ſpirituall grace in him; no corporall infirmitie or diſeaſe that can kill that incorruptible ſeed 
               1 Iob. 3.9. 
               of God once conceiued in the ſoule. And what ſhould hinder, but that as much may be in a young childe, as in a godly man ſo affected?
            4. To reaſon therefore from the ſtate and condition 
                  Inſtance 4 of children themſelues. They are capable of holineſſe, euen while they are ſuch. It is apparent in Iohn the Baptiſt, who was Luke 1.25. 
               filled with the Holy Ghoſt, euen from the wombe of his mother; and (as one of the ancients well ſaith) was In vtero priuſquam naſceretur renatus. Greg. mor. l. 3. c. 4. Quod tamen Aug. impoſſib
                     •
                  le cenſet. Nemo, inquit, ante renatus quam natus. Et, Renaſci nemo poteſt antequam ſit natus. Aug. ep. 57. &amp; de verb. Ap. 14. Verum regenitum ſi dixiſſet Greg. contradictionis ſpeciem omnem ſu
                     •
                  tuliſſet. 
               new-bred, yet vnborne. Yea ſo certaine it is of all young ones, that belong to Gods election, that they are Iob. 3.3, 7. 
               regenerate and ſanctified ere they goe hence: ſince that Apoc. 2
                     •
                  .27. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Clem. Alex. protrept. 
               no vnholy thing can enter into Heauen, 
               1 Cor. 15.50. 
               nor 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Iſid. Pel. l. 1. ep. 477. Corruptelae nomen non naturae. Tertull. de reſu
                     •
                  r. 
               fleſh and bloud inherite the kingdome of God. And if children may haue habituall holineſſe in them, though they be altogether vnable yet to doe ought that is good, yea though they know not ſo much as what it meanes; why may they not as well haue habituall 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   1 Pet. 1.13.
               
               naughtineſſe in them, albeit they be yet vnable vtterly to doe ought that is euill, or to In paruulis nec ſcientia eſt, nec conſcientia▪ &amp; eſt peccatum tamen originis. Aug. ad. Iul. l. 5. c. 1. 
               vnderſtand ſo much as what it is?
            This point then thus proued and cleered, the vſe of it it;
            
               
                  Vſe 1 1. To acquite God from all imputation and aſperſion of crueltie, or of iniquitie, if hee ſhould haue taken euerie one of vs, as ſoone as wee came into the world, and throwne vs headlong (as ſome wee need not doubt but hee doth) into hell. Wee brought that into the world with vs, for which hee might iuſtly haue ſo dealt with vs. Nor is this diſcrepant from our owne courſes in the like, kinde. Cant. 2.15. 
               Catch vs (ſaith he) the foxes, euen the young cubs too. Lupus, catulus licet, lupus eſt, &amp; à venatoribus captus iure confoditur. Zuingl. ad Vrban. Reg. &amp; Gualt. apolog. Wee deſtroy the verie breed of venomous creatures, when wee can come by them, as well as thoſe that they come of; wee kill the young whelps, if we light on them, as well as the old wolfe or the fox; not in regard of the hurt that they haue done, or are able yet to doe, but in regard of the harmefull diſpoſition that is naturally in them. And iuſt may it be with God to doe the like by vs, in regard of that Videram nondum diem; vteri
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   nondum ſolueram cluſi moras; Nox me occupauit, &amp; nouae luci abſtulit. Mors me anteceſſit, aliquis intra viſcera maternaletum praecocis fati tulit: Sed numquid &amp; peccauit? abſtruſum, abditum, Dubiumque an eſſem, ſceleris infandi reum Deus peregit. Senec. Theb. 
               euill diſpoſition that is Peccatum cum homine naſcitur. Olympius apud Aug. ad. Iul. l. 1. c. 3. 
               bred and borne with vs. For who can in equitie denie the Creatour that power ouer the creature, that the creature hath ouer its fellow-creature.
            
            
               
                  Vſe 2 2. To ſhew the reaſon why it is ſo difficult a matter to make a man good. 
               Wiſd. 13.1. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Menard. Man is euill by nature; he is bred and borne ſuch. And that (we ſay)

               that is bred in the bone, will not out of the fleſh. 
               Wiſd. 12.10. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   Ariſtot. ethic. l. 2. c. 1. Quae à natura ſunt, aliter ſe habere non poſſunt. Idem
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ethic. magn. l. 2. c. 6. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Hippocrat. de leg. med. Cuſtode &amp; cura natura potentior omni. Naturam expellas furca licet vſque recurret. Horat. epiſt. 10. l. 1. Thoſe things that are naturall cannot eaſily bee altred. You may tie or mouſle a wolfe, ſo that hee cannot prey or bite; or you may beat him ſo bound, till he bee not able to ſtirre; but 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Pindar. Olymp. 11. -natura recurret Ad mores fixa &amp; mutari neſcia. Horat. ſatyr. you ſhall neuer bee able to beat his woluiſh nature out of him. But ſinne it is naturall to vs, and cannot therefore bee remoued, but by a ſupernaturall power. As Nemo bonus, qui non ex malo bonus. Aug. in Proſp. ſint. 155. Ad neminem ante bona mens venit, quam mala: omnes praeoccupati ſumus. Sen. ep. 51. &amp; 76. 
               no man is good, but of bad made good; ſo no man can but 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Pindar. Olymp. 9. Bonus vir ſine Deo non eſt. Sen. ep. 41. Nulla fine Deo mens bona eſt. Idem ep. 73. by a diuine power of bad be made good. Sinne cannot be wrought out of vs by any meanes, but thoſe that God himſelfe hath ſanctified and ſet apart for that purpoſe, and by his gratious bleſsing accompanying the vſe of them.
            3. To admoniſh parents of their dutie concerning 
                  Vſe 3 their children; to begin as ſoone as they can with them, and as they are capable of ought, to vſe the good meanes by God himſelfe preſcribed for the working of this inbred naughtineſſe out of them. Be as carefull for your children in regard of their ſoules, as you are wont to be Vt corpora ad quoſdam membrerant flexus formari niſi tenera non poffunt: ſic animos quoque ad plaera
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   duriores robur ipſum facit. Quintil. inſti
                     •
                  . l. 1. c. 1. In cunctis fererebus citius aſſueſcit omne quod tenerum eſt. Pelag. ad Demetr. for their bodies. If ought grow awrie there, you are forward enough to be tampering about them, ſeeking helpe, and vſing meanes for them, while they age yet young, and their bones griſtly and Vt corpora ad quoſdam membrerant flexus formari niſi tenera non poffunt: ſic animos quoque ad plaera
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   duriores robur ipſum facit. Quintil. inſti
                     •
                  . l. 1. c. 1. In cunctis fererebus citius aſſueſcit omne quod tenerum eſt. Pelag. ad Demetr. 
               tender, before the Cerea flicti. Horat. art. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plut. paedag. -argilla qu
                     •
                  duis imitaberis 
                     〈◊〉
                  
                  ▪ Horat. 1. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . 2. 
               ioynts be knit, and the bones growne ſtiffe, that may make

it the more incurable. Oh be as wiſe and as prouident for them in regard of their ſoules. Since you are informed that they generally grow awrie by nature, vſe with all ſpeed; and all diligence, all good meanes to remoue this enormitie, and to ſet them right and ſtrait as ſoone as poſſibly may bee, before that nature and cuſtome (a 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Ariſtot. thet. l. 1. c. 11. Ʋidecund. ſ
                     •
                  p. ethic. magn. l. 
                     •
                  . c. 6. conſuetudo altera natura. Cic. fin. l. 5. 
               ſecond nature) concurring, make Ierem. 13.23. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Dinarch. adu. Ariſtogit. Dum feruitur libidini facta eſt conſuetudo; &amp; dum conſuetudini non reſiſtitur, facta eſt neceſſitas. Aug. confeſſ. l. 8. c. 5. Natura enim &amp; conſaetudo vobuſtiſſimam faciunt &amp; inuictiſſimam cupi ditatem. Idem ad Simplic. l. 1. q. 1. Inueterata in nobis malorum omnium labe, aliter iam non vitioſi eſſe non poſſumus, niſi vt omnino non ſimus. Saluian. de prouid. l. 6. Longo quod vſu in peius vſque induruit, Mult
                     •
                  facilius fregeris, quam flexeris. Bu
                     ••
                  an. Bapt. the cure at leaſt the more difficult, if not the euill irrecouerable.
            
            
               
                  Vſe 4 4. To admoniſh each one for himſelfe, to take heed how obſtinately he goe on in ſinne, how hee wilfully adde to this original corruption further actuall tranſgreſsion. 
               1 Pet. 4.4. 
               It is ſufficient (ſaith the Apoſtle) that we ſpent the former time of our ignorance in the luſts of the fleſh, &amp;c. So it was ſufficient, yea and more than ſufficient for vs, that wee brought into the world with vs that inbred naughtineſſe, for which God might iuſtly then haue deſtroyed vs. And if therefore Rom. 2.4. 
               concerning the 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               goodneſſe and long ſuffering of God, who hath hitherto borne with vs, and in much mercie forborne vs, wee ſhall ſtill wilfully runne on in the practice of ſinne, and ſo Deut. 20.19. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   Ariſtat. Ethic. l. 7. c. 2. Quod Galen. ſic extulit, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ; Quod malim, quam 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   cum Eraſm. chil. 2. cent. 1. adag. 8. Nam &amp; Ariſtot. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               adde drunkenneſſe to thirſt; we ſhall but 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Rom. 2.5. Sicut mittentes pecuniam in gazophylacium, quod vbi tam impletar confringitur, Stella in Luc. 
               treaſure vp wrath againſt the day of wrath, and make our iudgement at length the more intolerable.
            
               The other Generall point, that from the death of children we obſerue, is,Point 2. Generall. that

               Death is euer at our doores.
            
            
               Mors vbique nos expectat. Aug. de ſpir. &amp; anim. c. 51. Erras, ſi in nauigatione tantum exiſtimes, minimum eſſe qua à m
                     •
                  rte vita diducitur. In omni loco aequè tenue interuallum eſt. Non vbique ſe mors tam prope oſtendit; vbique tam prope eſt. Sen. ep. 49. Quod enim tempus morti exemptum eſt? A quo prope non eſt, parata omnibius locis, omnibus momentis? Idem ep. 30. Mors vbique praeſto eſt: occurrit vndique. Idem nat. quaeſt. l. 6. c. 2. It lieth in wait for vs not in our fields, or our ſtreets, or our ſhops, or our beds onely, but in our cradles to, in our ſwathing-bands, in the childe-bed, in the childe-birth. 
               Quomodo Sen. ep. 122. Nullum animal ſine metu mortis in vitam predit. None come into life, but by perill of death. Death is neere at hand with vs, Senibus mors in ianuis, adoleſcentibus in inſidijs eſt. Bern. de conuerſ. c. 14. Et ſub eodem pueritia fato eſt. Fuſcus Sen. ſuaſor. 2. not in our old age, or our decaying time onely, but in our mans eſtate alſo, in our riper yeeres, in our youth, in our childe-hood, in our infancie it ſelfe. How many are carried Ab vtero ad vrnam. Iob 10.19. &amp; 3.11. -protinus quoſdom editos N
                     •
                  x occupauit, &amp; nouae lucī abſtulit. Sen. Theb. In ipſo ſaepè lucis exordio mors naſcentem ſequitur. Hieron. ad Paul. Concord. from the wombe to the tombe, (as Iob ſpeaketh) from birth immediately to buriall? yea, how many die Eccleſ. 6.3. Pſal. 58.8. Iob. 3.16. -aliquis intra viſcera Materna letum praecocis fati tulit. Sen. Theb. Ita neceſſaria crudelitate in vtero trucidatur infans, matricida, ni moriturus. Tertull. de anim. in the wombe? how many periſh vnborne, before euer they come to light, ere they know what life meaneth, or Dubium an eſſem. Sen. Theb. wee know that they liue. That young goe as well as old, and children die as well as others, we haue as well a viſible as a vocall ſermon preaching it to vs at this preſent.
            That it is ſo therefore, it is of it ſelfe euident, and daily experience is a ſufficient proofe of it. The reaſon why it is ſo, is no leſſe apparent.
            For, to paſſe by that generall reaſon from the former point, that therefore Children alſo are ſubiect to death, becauſe they are not free from ſinne;Reaſon generall.
            
            1. There is no certaine ſtint, tearme, or leaſe of 
                  Reaſon 1 mans life. 
               Pſal. 31.15. Our times are in Gods hands. As for

our Leuit. 25.23 Deus ſolus proprietarius eſt: homines ad placitum coloni. St. Iun. vindic. l. 1. Aduenae naſcendo, incolae viuendo, quia migrare compelluntur moriendo. Aug. in Leuit. q. 91. 
               lands, ſo for our Vita da
                     •
                  a eſt vtenda, data eſt— Mutua, nec certo perſo
                     •
                  uenda die. Pedo ad Liu. 
               liues we are but Gods tenants at will. And he may turne our ſoules out of theſe 2 Cor. 5.1. mud-walled cotages of our bodies, when hee will. Prou. 20.27. The 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                
               breath of man (ſaith Salomon) is as 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  
                
               a candle of Gods lighting. And as wee doe with our lights, ſo doth God with our liues: we light candles, and put them out againe as we liſt: ſome wee doe out as ſoone as they beginne but to burne; ſome we let alone, till the wax or tallow be halfe waſted; ſome till weeke and wax all be ſpent. So doth God with vs; he ſetteth our Vita enim lucu vſura dicitur, Iob 3.20. Mers nocti fimilis perhibetur. Nobi
                     •
                   cum ſemel 
                     •
                  xcidi
                     •
                   breuis lux, Nox eſt perpetua vna dormienda. Catul. epigr. 5. 
               life vp as a light, and when he ſeeth good, hee doth it out againe, with ſome ſooner, with ſome later, but with each one when himſelfe will.
            
               
                  Reaſon 2 2. The bonds that tie ſoule and bodie together, are no ſtronger, if not rather more tender, in children, than in others of riper yeeres. Eſai. 40.6. 1 Pet. 1.24. 
               All fleſh is as graſſe. But children are as flowers, or bloſſomes, more tender vſually than any other part of the plant: The Eſai. 40.7, 8. Pſal. 103.15, 16. Iob 14.2. 
               flower ſooner fadeth, than the herbe it ſelfe doth: the bloſſome is ſooner blaſted and blowne away, that the fruit that followeth it, is wont to be, when it is once knit. Yea, to hold to our former reſemblance; a candle is ſooner and more eaſily blowne out againe, when it is but new lighted, than when it hath burnt awhile. And with leſſe difficultie is this light of life puft out in thoſe, whom it is but newly, and ſcarce thorowly yet, kindled in.
            The Vſe whereof may be,
            
               
                  Vſe 1 1. To diſcouer their folly, that preſume of long life, in regard of health and youth. They are but

               young yet, and therefore they may liue long and ſee many a good day. And they are healthie and ſtrong, and may therefore hold out as well as others, as long as any. Yea, but there is none of thoſe that thus ſay or thinke, ſo young, but they haue ſeene many younger goe; none ſo ſtrong, but that they may haue ſeene as ſtrong, if not ſtronger, goe than themſelues. Pſal. 90.4, 5, 6. Vno die totam hominis vitam concluſit. Philip. in Iob 1. Inſtar totius vitae dies eſt. Sen. Epiſt. 61. Vide Cic. Tuſcul. l. 1. cum Ephemero beſtiola hominem committentem. Mans life is as a day. And as we ſee that daies are not all of one length; there are Summer, and there are Winter dayes; ſome longer, ſome ſhorter; ſome of more, ſome of fewer houres: So is there no leſſe varietie in the length and ſize of mens liues, according to that time that God hath pleaſed to allot each. But herein againe there is great difference betweene this naturall day and the day of mans life; that Nihil intereſt inter diem &amp; ſeculū. Sen. ep. 100. Nihil enim habet longiſſimi temporis ſpatiū, quod non in vno die inuenis, lucem &amp; nocte, &amp; alternas mundi vices: plura, non alia facit iſta nox, alias contractior, alias productior, Idem ep. 12. the naturall day, be it neuer ſo ſhort, it hath a morning, a noone, an afternoone and an euening; whereas the day of our life may haue a morning, and no noone, or a noone and no after-noone. 
               Amos 8.9. 
               The Sunne (as the Prophet ſpeaketh in another ſenſe) may ſet with vs at noone day. We may be ſuddenly ſnatcht away Iob 15.33. &amp; 21.23. in the flower of our youth, in the prime of our age, in the height of our health, in the chiefe of our ſtrength. Yea, the Pſal. 129.6. Solſtitialis velut herba ſolet, Oftentatus raptuſque. ſimul. Auſon. profeſſ. Alluſit ad illud Plaut. Pſeud. 1.1. Quaſi ſolſtitialis herba paulisper fui; Repente exortus ſum, repentino occidi. Et ad illud Virg. Aen. 6. Oſtendent terris hunc tantum fata, nec vltra Eſſe ſinent. 
               Sunne may ſet with vs, ſo ſoone as it is vp; it may but peere out, and twinckle awhile with a twy-light, and in the twinckling of an eye inſtantly goe downe againe. It is a vaine thing therefore, for any in regard of youth, to preſume of long life, when as length of life no way dependeth vpon youth, and wee ſee young goe as well, yea as oft as old doe.
            
               
               
                  Vſe 2 2. Is it ſo that death is euer at our doores? Then it ſtandeth vs in hand to liue euer in expectation of it. Mors te vbique expectat: &amp; tu igitur, ſi ſapis, eam vbique expectabis. Aug. de ſpir. &amp; anim. c. 51. Bern. medit. c. 3. &amp; Ocul. moral. c. 7. Incertū eſt, quo te loco mors expectet: Ita
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   tu illam omni loco expecta. Sen. ep. 26. 
               Doth death (ſaith one) he euerie where in wait for thee? then thou alſo, if thou beeſt wiſe, wile be prepared alwaies for it. Say thou as bleſſed Iob ſaith, and doe as he (no doubt) alſo did; Iob 14.14. 
               All the daies (ſaith he) of mine appointed time here, I will wait till my change come, that is, till the time come of my deceaſe and departure hence. Nor let the young man thinke that this leſſon is for old men onely. No: Eccleſ. 12.1. 
               Remember thy Maker (ſaith Salomon) in the daies of thy youth. 
               Mors tam iuueni ante oculos debet eſſe quam ſeni. Non enim citamur ex cenſu. Sen. ep. 12. Eata ſeriem non ſeruant. Jbid. 62. It ſtandeth young men vpon as well as old, to prepare for death, becauſe youth as well as old age is ſubiect to death. And though there may be affirmatiue, yet there are no negatiue ſignes of it. Of doomes-day there are both; of thy deaths day but the one onely. Of the generall day of doome, there are ſignes both affirmatiue, ſuch Matth. 24.32, 33. Luk. 21.30, 31. as ſhew that it approacheth and draweth neere; and negatiue, ſuch as ſhew that it ſhall not be as yet, becauſe they muſt goe before it, and it ſhall not come therfore, before they be fulfilled, as 2 Theſſ. 2.3. was the reuelation of the man of ſinne, and is yet Rom. 11.25, 26, 31. 
               the Conuerſion of the Iewiſh Nation. But of the particular day of any mans death, howſoeuer there may be ſignes affirmatiue, ſuch as ſhew the neereneſſe of it, as old age, decay of nature, ſome diſeaſes, and the like; yet there is no negatiue ſignes of it ordinarily, (howſoeuer Luk. 2.26. 
               Simeon and Matth. 16.28. ſome others haue had ſome extraordinarily giuen them) ſuch as may ſhew that as yet it ſhall not be. A man cannot ſay, I am young, and therefore I ſhall not die yet; for Mixta ſenum ac inuenum denſantur funera, nullum ſaeuacaput Proſerpina fugit. Hor. carm. 1.28. he may

be taken away in his youth. A man cannot ſay, I am ſtrong, and therefore I ſhall not die yet: for with the ſudden ſtroake of an apoplexie may hee be ſtrucke downe Iob 21.23. in his chiefe ſtrength. A man cannot ſay, I am healthie, and therefore I ſhall not die yet: For Nunquid vt homo concidat res magni molimenti eſt? &amp;c. Sen. ad Marc. c. 11. Nihil tam exiguum eſt, quod nō in perniciē generis humani ſatis valeat. Idem qu. nat. l. 6. c. 2. there needs no long ſickneſſe, yea no ſickneſſe at all, to deliuer a man vp to death. As a man may die well before he be old, ſo may hee well die alſo, and yet neuer be ſicke. Since that death therefore lieth in wait for vs, as well in youth as in age, it behoueth young as well as old to be prepared for it.
            3. Are young children alſo ſubiect to death? Let thoſe whom God hath bleſſed with children then,
                  Vſe 3 hence bee admoniſhed, to apply themſelues betimes to worke good things into them; ſince that they know not how ſoone they may bee taken away from them. That if it ſhall pleaſe God to call for their children, while they are but young yet, away from them, they may with the more comfort part with them, when they may bee able to ſay of them, as it is ſaid Verſ. 13. of the childe ſpoken of in my Text, As young as they were, yet there were good things in them; ſome ſeeds and ſparks of grace began to appeare in them. Wee are wont to be troubled, when God taketh them away from vs, if we haue not beene ſo carefull as wee thinke wee ſhould haue beene, in ſomething concerning the health of their bodies: But we haue more cauſe to be troubled, when our hearts ſhall tell vs, that wee haue beene negligent and retchleſſe about them, in ſuch things as concerned the ſtate and welfare of their ſoules.
            
            4. Are our children thus ſubiect to death, and we 
                  Vſe 4
               
know not how ſoone they may bee taken away from vs? Then as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh in the like caſe, 1 Cor. 7.29. Noſtros ſic habere, ſic amare debemus, tanquam nihil nobis de perpetuitate, in ò nihil de diuturnitate i
                     •
                   ſorum promiſſum ſit. Sen. ad Marc. c. 10. 
               Let thoſe that haue children be as if they had them not. Not that Parents ſhould not loue and affect their children: they are Tit. 2.4. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . commanded ſo to doe: and they are worſe, I ſay not, than heathen, but than 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plut. de amor. prol. bruit beaſts, that doe otherwiſe: and it is well made a note therefore of men 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Rom. 1.28. 
               giuen vp to a reprobate minde, and caſt behinde euen the gouernment of nature, as well as the guidance of grace, to be 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Rom. 1.30. 
               deuoid of naturall affection. But that they ſhould not ſo ſet and faſten their affections vpon them, that they ſhould be vnwilling Tuliſti, quia tuus erat: gratias ago, quod dediſti; non obmurmuro, quoniam abſtuliſti. Bern. de temp. 110. to part from them, when God ſhall pleaſe to call for them, Ioſh. 24.3, 4. Pſal. 127.3. Abſtulit; ſed dedit. Sen. ep. 63. Non moeremus, quod talem amifimus; ſed gratias agimus, quod habuimus. Hieron. epitaph. Paul. from whom formerly they receiued them, and who hath therefore beſt right and title to them. So therfore muſt thou labour to haue thy children, and endeuour to ſtand ſo affected in regard of them, that if God ſhould call for thine Iſaak, thy darling from thee, (Gen. 22.1. 
               Take thine onely ſonne, ſaith he, Iſaak, thy Sonne that thou loueſt:) thou maiſt be willing to offer him to God with thine owne hands. If he call for one of many, as Anytus. he of Athens, when Alcibiades a young gallant came reuelling into his houſe, as hee ſate with ſome ſtrangers at ſupper, and tooke away the one halfe of his plate; and his gueſts ſtormed and tooke on at it; Viſe Plut. in Alcib. &amp; in Erotic. &amp; Athen. dipnoſop. lib. 12. he told them, he had dealt kindly that hee leſs them the other hal
                     •••
                  , that 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               he tooke not all, when all was his; ſo repine not thou, for that that is gone, but be thankfull to God, for thoſe that be left; he that taketh one, might as well, if he would, haue tooke all, and it is his mercie

if he leaue thee any. Yea; labour to bee like Iob, to be affected as he was. When God tooke not one of them, but Percuſſus ſubita orbitate filio
                     ••
                  m, vt quos ſigillatim ſuſceperat, ſimul perderet; tanquam eorum numeroſitas, non vnde foelicitas ernaretur, extiterit, ſed vnde calamitas augereti
                     ••
                  . Hugo Vict. de patient. c. 11. 
               all his children at once from him, Iob 1.21. 
               The Lord (ſaith he) hath giuen; and the Lord hath taken: Now bleſt bee his name. Hee parteth with them as one would doe with a nurſe childe, that the parents of it had ſent for home againe. And indeed (to ſpeake as the truth is) wee are but as foſter fathers and nurſing mothers to thoſe children that God bleſſeth vs here with; their true Matth. 23.9. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . lib. 3. 
               Father indeed is aboue in Heauen. So therefore ſhould we eſteeme of them, as of children by God put to nurſe to vs; whom therfore, when he ſhall ſee good to call for them home from vs, we ſhould be as willing to returne to him, as wee would a nurſe childe, though we loued it as our owne, to the parents of it, when they ſhould ſend for it; the rather, knowing that they ſhall be, and doe better with him, than they haue done, or can doe with vs.
            And thus much for the two generall points that from hence we obſerue:Points Speciall.
            
            Wee paſſe now to the ſpeciall: which ſhall bee theſe two, that

               The good goe oft before the bad,
               
and that,

               The good die oft-times for the bad.
               
            
            For the former,Point 1. Speciall howſoeuer we might hence obſerue, that

               The good goe as well as the bad.
Yet paſſing by that for the preſent, as hauing handled it on the like occaſion See, Abrahams Deceaſe on Geneſ. 25.8. elſewhere, the point that I purpoſe now to inſiſt on ſhall be this, that

               Point 2. Speciall.
               The good goe oft before the bad;
               That they die not onely as well as they, but they die oft euen before them. So the Prophet telleth vs, that Eſai. 57.1. 
               The righteous periſh, and good men are taken away: when the wicked meanewhile are left behinde ſtill. And the Pſalmiſt complaineth, that the godly were taken away ſo faſt, that there was ſcarce one good man left. 
               Pſal. 12.1. 
               Helpe Lord, (ſaith he) for there is not a godly man left, the faithfull are failed from among the children of men. But there is 1 Iob. 5.19. a world of wicked ones left ſtill. Pſal. 12.8. 
               The wicked (ſaith he) walke on euerie ſide. Here we ſee (to goe no further) Ieroboams good ſonne taken away, when his vngodly father,
               Reaſons 2. and his wicked brethren, with the reſt of that prophane and irreligious family ſtill remaine.
            
               Now this God thus diſpoſeth,
Sometime in iudgement, and
Sometime in mercie.
            
            
               
                  Reaſon 1 1. In iudgement ſometime. For 1 Pet. 4.17. 
               Iudgement beginneth at Gods houſe. 
               Ier. 25.17, 28, 29. The cup of Gods wrath is ſent firſt to Ieruſalem: ſhe beginneth to the reſt of it. 1 Cor. 11.30. The mortalitie at Corinth ſeized vpon the Beleeuers there for their abuſe of the Sacrament, ſ
                     ••
                  it ſome of them, and ſwepe away other ſome of them, when many an Infidell eſcaped, and went ſcot-free the whiles. Iohn 25.
                     •
                  . Planta ferax falcem patiturque petitque freqūentem, Cultoris 
                     〈◊〉
                   reciſa mamu. Dum rigid
                     •
                   r
                     •
                  bus inf
                     •
                  
                  lix intalla mucrone Permanet, hibernis eſca futura focis. Non pacitur impi
                     •
                  s, 
                     〈◊〉
                   farmentis 
                     〈◊〉
                   ad 
                     〈◊〉
                  : non 
                     〈…〉
                   ad proficiendem purgationem. Aug. ad Fauſt. l. 22. c. 21. The fruit tree is oft pared, and pruned, and trimmed
               ▪ while the brier ſtandeth by it vnſtirred and vntoucht, till it come at length to be f
                     •••
                  od at once for the fire. The ſtormie ſhower and raine lighteth firſt on the high bils, and 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   11.35. hauing waſhed them, then runneth downe to the vale, and there Zach. 9.1. 
               ſetleth with all the filth in the bottome.
            
            
               2. In mercie, (though in that iudgement alſo there 
                  Reaſon 2 be mercie; yea, it is not Habb. 2.3. 
               mixt onely with mercie, but euen the verie iudgement it ſelfe alſo is a mercie, becauſe 1 Cor. 11.32. it preuenteth a greater miſchiefe; but this in meere mercie without admixtion of wrath,) when (as the Prophet ſaith) Eſai. 57.1. 
               they are taken away from the euill to come. So was it foretold Ioſias that he ſhould be taken away, 2 King. 22.20. that hee might not ſee the euill that ſhould befall that place and his people. And ſo of this childe, that Verſ. 12-16. hee ſhould die before-hand, that he might not ſee and ſuffer in thoſe fearfull iudgements that ſhould betide his Fathers houſe and ſtocke after his deceaſe. God doth in this kinde, as wee would our ſelues in the like caſe, had wee children either at nurſe or at ſchoole in ſome place, where ſome trouble were like ſhortly to bee; and ſo dangerous being and abiding there for them: For example, had any of you had a childe at Breda, abiding there to learne the language, or for ſome other ſuch end, and ſhould haue heard that Spinola had an intent and purpoſe to come and ſit downe with all his forces, as he did alſo, before it; what courſe wouldeſt thou haue taken in this caſe; but in all haſte to ſend away for thy ſonne, and to cauſe him to come home to thee, where he might be in better ſafetie? 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ; Plut. ad Apollon. In like manner doth God with his that hee hath at nurſe or at ſchoole here, when trouble and danger is toward thoſe places where they make their abode, he calleth for them away, he taketh them home to himſelfe, where they are ſure to be ſafe, farre from touch or view of euill.
            
            Yea but,Queſtion. how doth God (may ſome ſay) then

make good Exod. 20.1
                     •
                  . Deut. 5.
                     ••
                  . Epheſ. 6.
                     ••
                  . his promiſe of long life, made to good and obedient children? ſuch as wee need not doubt but that this ſon of Ierobeams was; for where there is goodneſſe to God, there cannot but be a care of all good dutie and due reſpect to thoſe that are as Itaque mandatū hoc 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   appellat Philo de decalog. &amp; tabulae cam pri
                     •
                  r
                     •
                   dicat. in Gods roome, and whom Matth. 16.4. 
               God hath enioyned honour to be giuen vnto.
            To this I anſwer;
            
               
                  Anſwer 1 1. That long life is there promiſed ſo farre forth as it may bee a benefit and a bleſsing. Now howſoeuer it may be a bleſsing to liue long, to Pſal. 128.5, 6. 
               ſee Ieruſalem in proſperitie, and peace vpon Iſrael: yet to liue long, 
               1 Sam. 2.32. to ſee the enemie in the gates of our people, to ſee 
               Zech. 14.21. 
               the Canaanite in Gods houſe, 
               Pſal. 74.4. 
               Gods aduerſaries roaring in the middeſt of his Sanctuarie, and their enſignes in way of triumph ſet vp in his Temple: ſo to liue long, I ſay, might be no benefit at all, might bee a curſe rather than a bleſsing: becauſe Sic diu viuere, eſt diu torqueri. Aug. de temp. 113. 
               ſo to liue long, were but to liue long in miſerie, ſo to liue long, were rather 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plato apud Plut. de prouid. to bee long a dying, than to liue long: For how can a man bee ſaid truely Hincillud, Exigua pars eſt vitae, quàm nos viuimus. Caeterum omne ſpatium non vita ſed tempus eſt. Sen. de breu. vit. c. 2. Poteſt fieri, imò ſaepe fit, vt qui diu vixcrit, parum vixerit. Idem ep. 49. In longiſſima vita minimum eſt quod viuitur. Idem ep. 98. Quem ſaeuaden, peſtai a portu exceptum huc &amp; illuc tulit, 
                     〈…〉
                   in orbem egil, non ille multum 
                     •
                  auigau
                     •
                  , ſed mult
                     •
                  m 
                     〈◊〉
                   eſt, Idem de 
                     〈◊〉
                   8. Non illediu vixit, ſed diu fuit. Ibid. Ita de diſco
                     •
                  di con
                     •
                  ugio 
                     •
                  hemiſ
                     •
                   dē anima. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . to liue then, 
                  Anſwer 2 when he hath Gen. 27.46. Iob. 7.25. 
               no comfort of his life?
            
            2. God in ſuch caſes maketh his word good, in that in ſtead of a leſſe good, he giueth a better a greater. To vſe Chryſoſtomes compariſon: Chryſoſt. alicubi. ſed locus iam non fuccurrit. Thou commeſt to a Gold-ſmith or a Ieweller, that hath among other ſtones on his ſtall, a ſorrie Achate, and a rich Adamant; thou cheapeneſt, and bargaineſt with

him for the Achate, and in ſtead of the Achate hee deliuereth thee the Adamant; wouldeſt thou ſay, he did thee wrong? Or ſuppoſe thou commeſt to a great landed man, and dealeſt with him for ſome terme of yeeres in a farme; and when the deeds come to be drawne, he maketh ouer to thee the fee-ſimple of a manour. Euen ſo dealeth the Lord here. Pſal. 21.4. 
               The King (ſaith he) asked life of thee, and thou gaueſt him long life, euen for euer and euer. Hee promiſeth long life, and for that leaſe of life of ſome few yeeres continuance, he beſtoweth a perpetuitie; in ſtead of a miſerable long life here, hee giueth a bleſſed and incorruptible eternall life elſewhere. Hee maketh them payment (ſaith Chryſoſt. in Rom. hom. 7. 
               Chryſoſtome) in ſtead of 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               blacke moneyes in a ſtrange Countrey, in 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               good gold at home in their owne.
            Now the conſideration hereof may
            1. Teach and admoniſh vs, to ſuſpend our cenſures
               
                  Vſe 1 in regard of thoſe that are taken away from vs: and not to iuſtifie our ſelues in regard of thoſe that we ſuruiue in times of mortalitie, or that periſh at any time when wee eſcape. They may goe for the better, and we be reſerued for worſe matters, to ſee and ſuffer more miſerie which they are taken away from. Malac. 3.17. 
               Theſe ſhall be my 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   idquod in theſaur l
                     •
                   praecipuum &amp; primariū habetur. 
               iewels (ſaith God by Malachy) in the day that I doe this. God doth, as men in the like caſes. If their houſes be on fire, or in danger of fiering, their iewels and their treaſure is that that they haue moſt care of, and that in the firſt place therefore they will endeuour to remoue: ſo doth God with his, that are his iewels and his treaſure, (for ſo Exod. 19.
                     •
                  . Deut 7.6. &amp; 14.
                     •
                  . &amp; 26.18. he termeth them, and ſo he eſteemeth

them) when the fire of his wrath is ſeized, or ready to ſeize on the places they abide in, hee ſnatcheth them thence, and remoueth them to places of better ſecuritie. And what place more ſecure than Heauen, his owne houſe? Or where can they be ſafer than with himſelfe?
            
            
               
                  Vſe 2 2. It may comfort parents, in regard of their children that God taketh away from them, eſpecially hauing ſeene ſignes of grace and goodneſſe in them, ſuch as their tender age and few yeeres may afford: that it is no argument of Gods hatred, no nor of his anger alwayes, to be ſoone taken away. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Menand. Plut. ad Apollon. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Dion. Pruſ. orat. 28. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Ibid. 29. Dij coeleſ
                     •
                  es quibuſdam pi
                     •
                  ſſimis mortem, tanquam ſummis praemium perſoluerunt. Iulian. apud Ammian. l. 25. 
               They goe ſooneſt oft, whom he beſt loueth. Thoſe children that their parents moſt affect, though they put out from them vpon neceſſarie occaſions, yet they deſire as ſoone as may bee to haue home to them againe; eſpecially if they be not like to doe ſo well where they are, or if ſome ſickneſſe and mortalitie begin to reigne in thoſe parts. Nor may they doubt, being good children, but that the change ſhall be with them for the better: hee that hath Exod. 20.12. promiſed them long life, will make his word good to them with aduantage. They ſhall haue 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Chryſ. in Pſal. 114. 
               true life indeed for that, which in compariſon of it, is 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Eur
                     •
                  p. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Idem apud Plut. ad Apollon. Qualis eſt enim vita haec infulix, miſera, qua ſemper ad non eſſe, tendit. Chryſoſt. in. Pſalm. 143.2. not worthy the name of life; and for this tranſitarie and temporall, that euerlaſting and eternall. Beſides that, they know not what a mercie it may bee to them, that they are ſo ſoone taken, and what miſerie they might haue liued either to fee or to ſuffer. That which, as the times are, conſidering how the aduerſ
                     •…
                  rie getteth ground daily on Gods inheritance; and how the ſcourge hath runne ouer a great part

of Gods portion; and that we know not how ſoone it may paſſe ouer vnto vs to; may ſerue much to mitigate the griefe that parents are naturally affected with for the loſſe of their little ones; ſince that they know not 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plut. ad Apoll. O ignaros malorum ſuorū, quibus non mors vt optimum inuentum naturae laudatur? quae ſiue faelicitatem includit, ſiue calamitatem repellit, ſiue ſatiotatem aut laſſitudinem ſenis terminat, ſiue iuuenile aeuū, dum melio
                     •
                  a ſperantur, in flore de ducit, ſiue pueritiam ante duriores caſus reuccal, omnibus finis, multis remedium, quibuſdam votum, de nullis melius merita, quam de his, ad quos venit antequam inuocarctur. Senec. ad Marc. c. 20. Cogita quantum boni
                     •
                  pportuna mors habeat, quam multis diutius vixiſſe nocuerit. Ibid. what euils their children are taken away from, or what they themſelues may liue to ſee, which would be farre Matth. 24.19. heauier vnto them for ſuch hanging vpon them, than they would be for themſelues otherwiſe. Howſoeuer, they may aſſure themſelues, that their children gone to God, are In meliorem emittitur vitam, tranquillius tutiuſque inter diuina manſurus. Sen. ep. 71. 
               ſafer and better with him, than they either were, or euer could haue beene with themſelues here.
            And thus much for the former ſpeciall point, to wit, that

               The good goe oft before the bad.
            
            We paſſe now to the latter of them, which (as before you heard) is, that

               The good goe oft times for the bad.
               Point 2. ſpeciall.
And (if you pleaſe) yet a little more generally one way, though more ſpecially another; that 
                  Branch 1
               
               The Child ſuffers oft for the Fathers offence.
            
            Let them be, whether you will, either two diſtinct 
                  Branch 2 
               points, or two ſeuerall branches of one and the ſame point: ſince that both of them alike ariſe from my Text, and there is in it a pregnant example of either.
            For the former of them,Point 3. ſpeciall. that

               The good goe for the bad.
Wee haue a precedent of it in that good King Ieſus, 
               
                  
                     •
                   King. 23.25, 26, 27, 29. who was cut off, and his life ſhortned for the ſins of his people, and the remainder of Manaſſes his ſinnes rife ſtill among them: as alſo in this good Child taken away for the ſinnes of Ieroboam.
            
            Now the reaſon why the godly goe thus for the wicked, is
            
               
                  Reaſon 1 1. That they may not periſh with and among them, when ſome heauie iudgement is comming in vpon them. As Gen. 19.12, 13, 15, 16, 29. 2 Pet. 2.6, 7, 9. 
               God ſent his Angels to fetch Lot and his out of Sodome, when Sodome was to be deſtroyed with fire and brimſtone from Heauen, that they might not be 
                  〈◊〉
                vp with the inhabitants of it:Gen. 6.13. &amp; 7.1, 4. He cauſed Noa to goe into the Arke, as it were out of the world, when hee was determined to drowne the world with a generall deluge, that hee might not with the reſt miſcarry: So tooke hee here Ieroboams ſonne out of the way, 1 King. 14.
                     •
                  1. &amp; 15.29, 30. that hee might not be either eaten with dogs, or deuoured with the fowles, as the reſidue of that impious houſe and race were.
            
               
                  Reaſon 2 2. That they may not preſerue thoſe from periſhing, whom God is determined to deſtroy. It is ſaid of Moſes, that Pſal. 106.23. 
               he ſtood in the gap, to keepe out Gods wrath, from breaking in vpon his people, when God was minded to deſtroy them. And of Phineaz, that Pſal. 106.20, 30. when the plague had made a breach in vpon them, he was a meanes to ſtay it from further proceeding. God therefore when hee is reſ
                     •
                  lu
                     •
                  d, to proceed in iudgement againſt a people, hee taketh thoſe away from them, that may intercede for them, that by

their Gen. 18.31, 32. Ier. 5.1. Ezek. 14.14, 16, 20. 
               preſence or Ier. 7.16. &amp; 11.14. &amp; 15.1. 
               prayers, may ſtay his hand, as Moſes, (Exod. 32.10. Multum Moiſi permittit creator omnium; &amp; feriendi licentiam quarit à Moſe qui Moſeui fecit. Bern. de temp. 83. Sine me, ait, vt ille non ſineret, Tertull. ad. Marc. l. 2. 
               Let me alone, ſaith God to him, that I may deſtroy this people) and as Lot, (Gen. 19.21. 
               I can doe nothing, ſaith hee, as long as thou art here) that may turne away the ſtorme, as he did Gen. 19.20, 21. from Zoar, that had elſe as well as Gen. 19.24. Amos 4.11. 
               Sodome, Gomorrha, 
               Deut. 29.23. Hoſh. 11.8. 
               Adamah, &amp; Zeboim beene deſtroyed; that may ſtand in the gap, when it is breaking in, or make the breach vp againe, when it is broken in, and preſerue from periſhing either in whole or in part. God, hee doth, as men are wont to doe with thoſe they deſire to deſtroy. Hee that would ſet vpon a ſtrong man, (ſaith out Sauiour) will Matth. 12.29. Luke 11.22. 
               firſt, if he can, diſarme him. They that would conquer a countrey, if they can ſeize vpon their munition, will not faile to make themſelues firſt maſters of that; for they know then, they ſhall haue no power to reſiſt. Now the godly, they are the munition, the ſtrength of a ſtate; i. vis &amp; robur Iſraelis. Iun. in not. the chariots and horſe of Iſrael; ſaith 2 King. 2.12. 
               Elizaeus of Elias, and King 2 King. 13.14. 
               Ioas of Elizaeus. Theſe therefore God taketh away, and ſo diſarmeth a ſtate, when he is bent to deſtroy it, that ſo his wrath may finde no reſiſtance. And there bee but any one good in Ieroboams houſe, goe he muſt: Gods ſentence againſt it cannot be executed, till he be taken out of it.
            The Vſe whereof may be,
            1. To informe vs, what we may iuſtly feare and 
                  Vſe 1 
               expect, when God picketh out the good, and taketh many of them away. It is a ſigne ſome fearefull euill is towards, where he ſo doth. It is a preſage of warre towards, either with or in a countrey, when men on all hands, ſuch eſpecially as are acquainted

with ſtate-affaires, ſeeke to get home with all expedition, whatſoeuer goods or wares they haue in thoſe parts, and much more their friends and children, if they haue any reſiant there. And it is a forewarning of little good towards a place, where God doth the like with thoſe that be his deere ones, his darlings.
            
            Beſides that Somen ſanctum ſtatumen lerrae. Eſai. 6.13. 
               The holy ſeed (ſaith Eſay) vpholdeth the land. And, Iob. 22.30. 
               The innocent (ſaith Eliphaz) preſerueth the Iland: (as Ita Verſ. Geneu. poſt Dauid. Kimchi. ſome reade it:) or (as Ita Verſ. Regia poſt Leon. Iud. others) The Iland of the innocent ſhall hee deliuer: (that is, God will ſaue it for his ſake:) or (as others againe, whom I ſhould chuſe to goe with, no leſſe agreeably to our purpoſe:) Ita poſt R. Solomon. &amp; Menach. Elias in Thish. Mercer. &amp; Iun. 
               He ſhall ſaue him, that is not guiltleſſe himſelfe; and euen ſuch ſhall be deliuered for the puritie of thy hands: that is, ſome one good man, ſuch as Ezek. 14.14, 16. 
               Iob was, may be a meanes to ſaue and deliuer a whole citie of men, otherwiſe guilty and readie for their ſin to be deſtroyed. But to returne againe to that of Eſai: there ſeemes Viſe Iun. &amp; Piſcat. verſ. &amp; annot. an alluſion in it to 1 Chron. 26.16, 18. 1 King. 10.5. 2 Chron. 9.11. 
               a banke or a cauſey mentioned in the ſtorie, that went from the Kings houſe to the Temple, &amp; was borne vp with trees planted on either ſide of it. Which trees (ſaith the Prophet) as they kept vp the cauſey, ſo the holy and godly in a land ſupport and hold vp the ſtate. And as thoſe trees, if they were remoued, the banke or cauſey would ſoone come downe: ſo that holy ſeed, if it be once taken away, that whole land or ſtate is likely to come ſhortly after to ruine. As it was a ſigne therefore, that Sampſon meant to bring downe the houſe vpon the heads of the Philiſtines, when Iudg. 16.26, 29, 30. he pulled downe the pillars that bare vp the

               roofe of it. So it is a ſhrewd ſigne, that God is about to ruine a ſtate, when he plucketh away thoſe that are the ſhores and the props of it. As it is an argument of deſtruction towards, when Eſai. 3.2, 3. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Pauſan. in Lacon. he taketh away the mightie, the man of warre, the Iudge and the Prophet, the prudent and the ancient, the Captaine or Commander, the honourable and the Counſellor, the cunning Artificer, and the eloquent Orator: So it is no leſſe, (if not much more) an argument of the like, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plaut. apud Strigel. in 2 Reg. 23. when he taketh away the good and godly, the righteous and religious. Since the one are the temporall, the other the ſpirituall ſtaies of a ſtate: the one ſupport it againſt the power and policie of man, the other protect 
                  Vſe 2 it againſt the wrath and iudgements of God.
            
            2. This conſidered, may teach vs, what cauſe we haue to pray earneſtly for the life and continuance of good and godly men among vs: and how iuſt cauſe of griefe and ſorrow is giuen vs, when it ſeemeth good to God to take any ſuch from vs. There goeth a prop or ſhore of our ſtate away, when any ſuch goeth. How would we be grieued, if we ſhould haue newes brought of ſome one of the Kings ſhips loſt or caſt away at ſea? and that not without cauſe: for our ſhipping is the ſtrength of our ſtate; they are (as we terme them) our 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Oraculum Athenienſibus datū; quod ita interpretatus eſt Themiſtocles. Herodot. l. 7. Plut. in Themiſt. Aelian. l. 12. c. 43. Galen. exhort. ad art Clem. Strom. l. 5. Euſeb. praepar. l. 5. c. 24. Suid. 
               woodden wals. And no leſſe cauſe haue we to mourne, when we loſe a good man; (ſuch an one eſpecially as is in eminent place with vs,) ſince that ſuch are indeed, (as he ſaid ſometime of his warlike Lycurgus interrogatus cur muris vrbem non cinxiſſet, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   Plut. apophth. Vide eund. ſympoſ. l. 2. c. 5. &amp; Epictet. apud Stob. c. 5. Sed &amp; Ageſilaus quaerenti 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . ciues armatos oſt
                     •
                  ndens, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   quod &amp; idem de inuenibus Spartanis Antalcidas: adiecitque, 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plut. ibid. Vide Plaut. Perſ. 4.4. 
               citizens)

the beſt wals and bulwarks of our ſtate.
            
            
               Point 4. ſpeciall.But leaue wee this, and paſſe on to the laſt Branch, which is, that

               Children ſuffer oft for their Parents:
               That Children, I ſay, as well good as bad, ſuffer ofttimes at Gods hand for their Parents offences: God puniſheth the one ofttimes in the other. So puniſhed he Exod. 4.22, 23. &amp; 13.29. 
               Pharao by the death of his firſt-borne, for his obſtinate refuſall to diſmiſſe his people. So he puniſhed 2 Sam. 12.14. 
               Dauid, by the deceaſe of the childe begotten in adulterie, for that enormious act of his. And ſo Ieroboam here 1 King. 13.33. &amp; 14.1, 17. for his idolatrie, by the loſſe of a ſonne, that no doubt to him was verie deere. Yea, it is that that God threatneth, as well Exod. 20.5. Deut. 5.9. in the ſanction of the ſecond precept, as oft alſo Exod. 34.7. Num. 14.18. Ier. 32.18. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Eurip. apud Plut. de prouid. elſewhere, that he will viſit, that is, puniſh the iniquitie of parents vpon their poſteritie, and that not vnto one or two alone, but euen to three or foure deſcents. So not Gen. 9.22, 24, 25. 
               Canaan onely was curſed for his Father Chams offence; and Ioſh 7.1, 24, 25. all Achans family deſtroyed for his fault; but 2 King. 5.27. 
               the leproſie of Naaman for Giezies falſhood ſtucke by him and his poſteritie ſo long as any of them laſted.
            The reaſon of this courſe that God taketh ofttimes in puniſhing of the tranſgreſsions of parents by paines inflicted vpon their children is,
            
               
                  Reaſon 1 1. Becauſe Children are Liberi inter, parentum ſuorum bona numerantur. Alibuſ. dicaeolog. l. 1. c. 30. Sunt res parentum, &amp; in eis etiam parentes puniuntur. Tho. ſum. p. 2
                     •
                  .2
                     •
                  . q. 108. a. 4. ad. 3. 
               part of their parents poſſeſsions. It is reported of a Perſian Emperour, Artaxerxes the Long-handed, that 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plut. apophth. &amp; Artaxerx. Hinc Dio Pruſ. orat. 37. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . for ſuch faults of his Nobles and Chieftaines, as their haire had wont

to bee pulled, their head-tire or turbants ſhould bee openly ſo vſed, and for ſuch offences as their bodies had wont to be beaten, their robes ſhould publikely be ſcourged; which was deemed to them no ſmall diſgrace. And in like manner (ſaith Theodoret, ſpeaking of the plague of leproſie in mens houſes and garments) doth God deale with men: 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Theodoret. in Leuit. quaeſt. 18. when they offend themſelues, God puniſheth them not in their perſons alwayes, but ofttimes in their poſſeſsions, in their goods and chattels, in their worldly eſtate. And if in their poſſeſsions, no maruell if in their children to, being part of their poſſeſsions, as is euident by the commiſsion giuen and granted to Satan, concerning power ouer Iobs poſſeſsions, 
               Iob 1.12, 18. which comprehended his children as well as his chattels, as appeareth by the execution of it.
            2. Yea, children are not part onely of their parents 
                     Reaſon 2 poſſeſsions, but they are Filij membra parentum eſſe videntur. Saluian. de prouid. l. 3. Parſqūe tui latitat corpore clauſa meo. Ouid. epiſt. 2. ex Phyllidis perſona. Liberi ſunt quaſi vna perſona cum patre. Alihuſ. l. 1. c. 30. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plut. de prouid. 
               part (in ſome ſort) of the parents themſelues; or Tanquam membra vnius corporis. Aug. in loſ. q. 8. &amp; Iun. in Ioſh. 7. of one and the ſame bodie at leaſt with them. As 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Iuſtin. nom. orthodox. quaeſt. 137. the Subiects and the Soueraigne make ioyntly one body politicke, and 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Ibid. the loſſe of the ſubiects therefore is a puniſhment to the Soueraigne: and God doth ſometime puniſh the Soueraigne ſo (witneſſe 2 Sam. 24.10, 15. 
               Dauid) in the ſubiect. So the Father and the whole family make both as one body; and euill befalling any of them is a puniſhment to him, eſpecially befalling one ſo neere as a childe: (Matth. 15.22. 
               Haue mercie on mee, Lord; ſaith the mother: My

daughter is diſtracted: 
               Ad ſeipſam petit adiutorium, quia in filia ſua, velut in perſona propria 
                     •
                  orquebatur. Simon, Caſſ. in euang. l. 5. c. 24. Filia malum ſuum reputat. Petr. Richard in Euang. her daughters paines were a puniſhment to her:) and God doth oft puniſh the father or maſter ſo (witneſſe Gen. 20.7, 18. 
               Abimelech) in his family, and thoſe that be of it. He doth 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plut. de prouid. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Ibid. as the Phyſitian that openeth a veine in the arme, or (it may be) in the foot either, for ſome diſeaſe in the head. For ſo he let Pharao bloud in the right arme, when Exod. 12.29. hee ſmote his firſt borne for his fault: ſo he let 2 Sam. 24.15. 
               Dauid bloud in the feet, that is, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Iuſtin. 
                     •
                  rthod. q. 137. in his ſubiects, (for they are the Prou. 14.28. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Chryſoſt. de ſtatuis, hom. 11. 1 Cor. 12.21. 
               feet that the Soueraigne ſtandeth vpon) for his offence.
            
            
               Obiection.But how, may ſome ſay, doth this ſtand with Gods iuſtice to puniſh one for another. Or how can threatning to puniſh ſinne ſo in poſteritie, ſtand with that which God himſelfe enacteth elſewhere, that Deut. 24.16. 
               the childe ſhall not ſuffer for his fathers offence; or with his anſwer to the people, that had gotten vp a bad prouerb, 
               Ier. 31.29. Ezek. 18.2. 
               The fathers haue eaten ſowre grapes, and the childrens teeth are ſet on edge: thereby meaning that Patres peccant, &amp; filij vapulant. Chald. 
               Their fathers had ſinned, and they ſuffered: that, Ier. 31.30. Ezek. 18.4. 
               the ſoule that ſinneth ſhould it ſelfe die the death, and Ezek. 18.20. 
               not one ſuffer for another.
            
            This queſtion hath not a little troubled many, both old and new Writers: and that place in the Law, hath verie much puzzled many, yea, the moſt of the Ancients,
               Euaſions 3. beſide others; which in that regard  they haue laboured,
            Some of them to diuert by allegoricall interpretations;
            
               Some to auoid by ouer-violent &amp; forced expoſitions; 
            
            Some to ſalue by ſtrange and needleſſe ſhifts.
               
            
            Some of thē (I ſay) expound the words allegorically; 
                  Euaſion 1
            
            Either Peccatores diaboli fi
                     •
                  ij, vnus ex 
                     •••
                  ero per ordinem perſuaſionis generatis hi iu carne pofiti p
                     ••
                  i
                     •
                  ntur, ne in aeternum pereant: pater autem diabolus non in hoc ſeculo corripitur, vt in aeternum damnetur. Origen. in Exod. hom. 8. of Satan, and his ſonnes, all wicked ones; 
                  Expoſition 1 whom 1 Cor. 11.32. 
               God puniſheth here that they may not be damned with him hereafter, Iude 6. reſeruing the Deuill their Father to the laſt day of doome:
            
            Or Quidam ad animam humanam reſerunt. Patrem primum vi
                     •
                  iorum incentiuum; filiu
                     •…
                  , vbi peccatum cogitatio concepit; nepoſē, vbi 
                     •
                  ecc. opere perpetratur; pronepotē, vbi in peccato quis gloriatur. Primos ac ſecundos ſtimulos Deum non punire: actumtertium ac quarſum vindicare. Hieron. in Ezech. 18. of degrees of ſin in the ſoule, making the firſt 
                     Expoſition 2 motions of ſin the Father; the conſent to ſin the ſon; the act of it the grand childe; and obſtinacy or glorying in it the great grand-childe: that God ſpareth men oft for the firſt and ſecond, but Iam. 1.14, 15. 
               ſtriketh home when ſinne is come to her height in the two laſt.
            
            But to frame allegories thus without need or ground, is but Commentatoris officium eſt, non quid ipſe velit, ſod quid ſentide ille quem interpretatur, exponere. Hieron. apolog. 1. de Ioum. Nihil quaerendum in verbis niſi loquentium voluntas: cui demonſtrandae inuigi
                     •
                  are d
                     •
                  bent omnes veridici narratores &amp; 
                     •
                  narra
                     •
                  o
                     •
                  es. Aug. de conſenſ. Euang. l. 2. c. 46. Litera enim ſuauiter excutionda eſt, non captiuorum m
                     •
                  re acerbe torquenda, donec reſtituat quod non accepit. Ioan. Sarub. metalog. l. 3. c. 1. to wrong the Text;Exception. to peruert the purpoſe of Gods ſpirit, and to make God himſelfe ſpeak that, that he neuer therein meant, nor intended.
            
            Others take the words literally; but expound them either nothing agreeably, or euen directly contrary
               
                  Euaſion 2 to the intent of Gods ſpirit in them.
            Some not of puniſhing ſinnes vpon ſuch deſcents, but 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Theodoret. in Exod. q. 40. Non eſt argumentum truculentiae tantis per iram tenere, ſed ſignum miſericordiae poenam differre peccati. Hieron. in Ezec. 18. Idem
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   Thom. ſum. p. 
                     •
                  a. 2ae. q. 108. a. 4. ad 1. Miſericordiae potius quam ſeueritatis, quod couſque differt. &amp; Ale
                     •
                  ſ. p. 3. q. 41. m. 4 a. 1. non inaequalitate iudicij, vt alij peccent, alij puniantur: ſed magnitudine clementiae, dum poenitentem expectat. &amp;c. of deferring and putting off the puniſhment of 
                  Expoſition 3
               
ſinne to ſuch a deſcent, as a matter not of wrath and iudgement, but of mercy rather and patience: which ſome of them alſo in particular apply to the Iewiſh people; either 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   Aegypto exeuntes in eremo ceciderūt. Theodoret. in Exo. q. 4
                     •
                   Gen. 15.16. Exod. 12.41. &amp; 13.18. in the firſt generation puniſhed, after their departure out of Egypt, for all their idolatries during that whole time committed;Ab Abr. ad Dauid ae
                     •••
                   1
                     •
                  . a Dauid ad tranſportationem Babylon. 2
                     •
                  
                  ▪ Conceſsion. 
                     •
                   tranſport. ad Chriſtum 3. inde ad 
                     〈◊〉
                   ſecull 4. ae
                     ••
                  
                  
                  
                     •
                  e 
                     •
                  . captiua fuit gens Iudaica, in 4. eradicata. Aug. ad Adi
                     •
                  ant. c. 7. or elſe (as ſome other) captiued in the third, and deſtroyed in the fourth age of the world.
            
            
               Conceſsion.Now howſoeuer it be true indeed, that God in mercy ſometime deferreth iudgement from the Fathers daies to the Sons, as he did in 1 King. 21.29. 
               Ahab. yea and in Ieroboam too; for his ſtocke was not ſo deſtroyed as was 1 King. 14.10. 
               threatned, till 1 King. 15.29. after his deceaſe: yea hee deferreth it, as with Iam. 1.15. Apoc. 2.
                     ••
                  .2
                     •
                  . particular peſons, ſo with Gen. 15.16. Matth. 23.32.38. 1 Theſſ. 2.15, 16. whole peoples and ſtates for many deſcents, till their ſinnes be come to a certaine height. Yet the oppoſition there Exod. 20.6. Deut. 5.10. &amp; 7.9. Ier. 3
                     •
                  .18. of mercie to be ſhewed to thouſands on the other ſide,Exception. that is, both to them and theirs, ſheweth that the place cannot be ſo expounded.
            
            Others vnderſtand it of originall ſinne onely, 
                  Expoſition 4 which deduced from Adam, is, and hath beene from time to time for many deſcents puniſhed in his poſteritie with death; and In vtraque ſententia diſſ
                     •
                  milis ſenſus, P
                     •
                  cantum quippe originale quia à parentibus trahimus, niſi per gratiam bapt. ſolu
                     •
                  mur, etiam parentū peccata p
                     •
                  rtamus, quia vnum adhuc cum illis ſumus. Reddit ergò peccata parentū in filios, dum pro culpa parentis ex originali peccato anima polluitur prolis: Et nurſus nou reddit, &amp;c. quia cum ab orig. pecc. per bapt. liberamur, iam non parentum culpas, ſed qua
                     •
                   ipſi committimus, habemus. Greg. mor. l. 15. c. 21. which as the Parents fault the child ſtandeth charged withall,Pſal. 115.13, 14. till by the new birth it be diſſolued;Deut. 24. de natis, Exod. 20. de nandum natis, propter peccatum originale quod ab Adam trabitur, &amp; cuim
                     •
                  rs temp
                     •
                  ralis redditur, Aug. in Deut. q. 42. or at leaſt vntill it come to haue iniquitie of it owne.
            But this will as euill hold as the former: For,
            
               1. Neither is any one ordinarily puniſhed for 
                  Exception 1 
               anothers originall ſinne, but for Eſt enim inherens quiddam proprium ac pecullaro tulque vittam originale, non imputatio mera peccati anemi, vti delir
                     •
                  nt Pig
                     ••••
                   controu. 1. &amp; Catharin de pec. orig. c. 6. Vide Alex. Ales p. 2. q. 122. m. 2. a. 1. 
               his owne:
            
            2. Nor will the Parum enim ſolidum, quod Aug. vbi ſup. Per numarum ſeplenarium (qui 3. &amp; 4. conſtat) vntuerſ
                     •
                  m intelligi. 
               ſtinting of deſcents to three or foure on the one ſide, oppoſed to that Exod. 20.6. Deut. 7.9. large extent
               
                  Exception 2 of mercie on the other ſide, admit this expoſition:
            
            3. Nor is there difference in this kinde between 
                  Exception 3 either good and bad, or the poſteritie of either; both alike tainted with originall ſinne, and both alike liable to temporall death:
            
            4. Nor doth it ſtand with the drift and ſcope of the place, Exod. 
                     •
                  0.4, 5. to deterre from idolatrie an actuall 
                     Exception 4 tranſgreſsion for feare of puniſhments vpon poſteritie:
            
            5. Nor are euen the regenerate freed from ſuſtaining ſuch puniſhments for their parents offences; 
                  Exception 5
            
            6. Or the growne and great ones any more 
                  Exception 6 than infants, howſoeuer hauing actuall ſinnes indeed alſo otherwiſe of their owne.
            But the ſenſe and meaning of the place is ſo plaine and euident, that by no meanes it can be auoided; and a verie pregnant proofe it is of the preſent point, that children ſuffer oft for their fathers faults.
            
            Nor need we haue recourſe here for the acquiting
               
                  Euaſion 3 of Gods iuſtice, or the reconciling of his doomes, to thoſe ſhifts and ſalues, that ſome other haue here vſed: as to ſay,
            1. That it was 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Theodoret. in Exod. q. 40. 
               threatned indeed, but neuer executed:
               
                  Expoſition 5 for that God oft in ſuch caſes is better than his word: 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Ibid. hee threatneth to terrifie, but intendeth not what he threatneth: yea, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Ibid. that it were impious to take it as intended ſo, as the threatning ſeemeth to import.
            
            
               
               
                  Exception 1 For 1. neither are Non ſunt van
                     •
                   mina, dominicae. Polan. in Mal. 1. 
               Gods threatnings in vaine; as Siimpune, vacat Ve. Tertull. ad Marc. l. 2. they ſhould be, ſhould they neuer take effect; ſince that Matth. 5.18. Ego iam 
                     •
                  lim mihi perſuaſi in ſacri preti
                     •
                  ſique eloquij textu nec modicam vacare particulam. Bern. in. cant. 72. 
               no iot or tittle of his word is ſuch:
            
               
                  Exception 2 2. Neither want wee examples, many a one, of the execution hereof; as hath formerly beene ſhewed:
            
               
                  Exception 3 3. Nor, albeit Eſai. 38.1, 5. Ion. 3.4, 10. Ierem. 18.7, 8. 
               God in mercie ſometime reuoke his ſentences, doth he euer threaten ought that hee may not iuſtly inflict.
            
            
               
                  Exception 4 4. Nor is it impious to ſay, that God intendeth ought that hee threatneth: impious rather it may ſeeme to be, to ſay that it is impious to auow it.
            Or 2. that it was for a time onely enacted, 
               Patram delicta ex fili
                     •
                  s exigit: duritia populi talia remedia, vt velpoſterit 
                     〈◊〉
                   ſuis proſpiclentes legi diuina obedirent. Tertull. ad Marc. l. 2. to 
                  Expoſition 6 tame that ſtiffe-necked people by feare of hauing their poſteritie puniſhed, but was Futurum vt poſt duritiam populi duritia legit edomitam, iuſtitia iam nou genus, ſed perſonas iudicaret. Ibid. afterward reuerſed, when they were amended. As if that in Ezech. 18.4. 
               Ezechiel were a reuocation of the former.
            For 1. neither are the ſanctions of the Law Morall, 
               
                  Exception 1 of leſſe continuance than the Law it ſelfe, Pſal. 119.89. Matth. 5.17, 18. Luk. 16.17. which laſteth for euer.
            
            
               
                  Exception 2 2. Nor was it Gods purpoſe there to reuoke or alter ought of his former courſes, 
               Ezech. 18.25. the equitie whereof he there auowes; and Ierem. 32.18. this among the reſt is auerred, by another Prophet of the ſame time, to haue beene euen then Gods wonted practice.
            
            
               
                  Expoſition 7 Or 3. that this concerneth Ambae eiuſdem voces: prior per Moſem ad Iudaeos. Optat. ad Donat. l. 7. the Iewes onely, who Praeuidens parum dictures prae magnitudine culpae. Ibid. beyond that Matth. 27.25. they wiſhed themſelues, ſhould be puniſhed for Chriſts death, not in their

               children alone, but in their childrens children too for many deſcents; but concerneth not Chriſtians, 
               Altera ad Chriſtianos pertinet. Ibid. Vide de boc &amp; Aug. ad Iulian. l. 6. c. 12. of whom that other ſhould be meant in Ezechiel.
            
            For 1. both the former is more generall.
            
            2. Nor is there difference in Gods dealings betweene 
                  Exception 1 
               Iew and Chriſtian in this kinde.
                  Exception 2
            
            3. Not to adde that euen the faithfull themſelues 
                  Exception 3 ſometime haue ſo ſuffered.
               
                  Exception 4
            
            4. Nor doth either this or the former any way aſſoile the doubt or vntie the knot, concerning the iuſtifiableneſſe or equitie of the point or practice queſtioned, but reſtraine onely the execution of it to ſome people or perſons.
            
            Or 4. that therefore God may iuſtly puniſh children
               
                  Expoſition 8 for their fathers offences, becauſe Parentum peccatis paruulos obligari, non improbabiliter dicitur. Aug. Enchir. c. 46. Parentū peccata modo quodam ſunt aliena, modo quodam &amp; noſtra 
                     •
                  aliena quippe proprietate ſunt actionis, &amp; noſtra ſunt contagione propaginis. Idem ad Iul. l. 6. c. 4. Viſe Le
                     ••
                  . 
                     •
                  . Pp. ep. 86. &amp; Greg. mor. l. 15. c. 22. they ſtand guiltie of the ſame in Gods ſight: which guilt yet Quouſqua implicetur proles ſtatuere non audet Aug. Enchir. c. 47. how farre it goeth, they dare not determine.
            For 1. this is a conceit that Vide I
                     •
                  om. ſum. p. 1 a. 2 ae. q. 81. a. 2. &amp; Alex. Ales, p. 2. q. 122. m. 2. a. 1. hath no ground at all 
                  Exception 1 in Gods word: which if it be admitted, that of the Heathen man of Damnoſa quid non imminuit dies? Aetas parentum peior auis tulit Nos nequiores, mox daturos Progeniem vitioſiorem. Horat. carm. 3.6. the world growing worſe and worſe, would be true, not onely as he meant of it, of the practice of ſinne, but much more in regard of the guilt of ſinne more and more multiplied in each ſeuerall deſcent.
            
            2. Nor will Sed &amp; ſi benedictio patrum ſemini quoque corum deſtinabatur ſine vllo adhuc merito eius, cur non &amp; rentus patrum in fillos quoque redundaret? vt per totum genus &amp; gratia decurreret &amp; offenſa. Tertull. ad Marc. l. 2. 
               Gods bleſsing of poſteritie for the anceſtors well-doing, (a worke of meere grace and free 
                     Exception 2 fauour onely) proue a ſpeciall guilt of an anceſtours particular miſdeeds to adhere to any of his iſſue.
               
A King may well 2 
                     •
                  am. 9.5. Pa
                  
                     •
                   inſtr
                     ••
                  m qui 
                     •
                  spa
                     •
                   apud to bená acta ſeruantur. Cuius 
                     〈…〉
                   fides innotuerit, h
                     •
                  reditatis iure, quod autori debueris, 
                     〈…〉
                   refundis. Hacten
                     ••
                   de maiorum obſe
                  
                     •••
                  is fructum, &amp; tamen de ſuppli
                     •
                  ijs exceſſum non 
                     〈◊〉
                  , &amp;c. E
                     •••
                  d. Panegyr. 
               reward a man for ſeruice, done him by his Father. Yet it followeth not thence, that he may therefore in like manner either 2 King. 14.6. 
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     ••••
                  ldem damni p
                     •
                  r 
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     •
                  ffici p
                     •••
                  ſt filius: quate
                     •••
                   bo
                     ••
                  m eius à parenti
                     •
                   bono depe
                     •
                  idet: ſica
                     •
                   in 
                     〈…〉
                  , filius amittit hareditatem pro peccato parentis. Them. p. 2 a. 2 a. q. 108.
                     •
                  
                  ▪ 
                  
                     〈…〉
                   2. 
                     〈◊〉
                   Cic. ad Brut. ep. 13. Nec vere me fugit, quam fit acerbum, Parentum ſcelera fiſiorum 
                     〈…〉
                   ſed hoc praeclare legibus comparatum eſt (de bona p
                     ••••
                  candis) vt 
                     ••••
                  lias libero 
                     〈◊〉
                   parentes 
                     〈◊〉
                  . radderet, At non 
                     〈◊〉
                   flage
                     ••
                  . 
                     〈…〉
                   multo minus gl
                     ••
                  ij. 
               condemne him or execute him for his Fathers offence.
            
            
               
                  Expoſition 9 Or 5. that this ſentence is neuer put in execution, but De eis qui in paternis verſaniur malis. Quis enim 
                     〈◊〉
                   &amp; mali filium 
                     〈…〉
                   execretur? quō. bonum &amp; boni filium duplici quis honore honor andum tenſeat. Aug. 
                     〈◊〉
                   vet. &amp; nou. Teſt. quaeſt. 14. Non hoc fit, niſicum fuerit 
                     〈…〉
                  . Aug. poſt coll
                     •
                  t. c. 7. Muta
                     ••
                  r, ſi parentum facto non ſapientur. 
                     •
                  2. 
                     •
                   is quippè non reddicatur peccata parentum, qui non imitantur mores illorum. Quemod modum autem bonorum 
                     〈◊〉
                   fac
                     ••
                  , vt eliam propria peccata 
                     〈…〉
                   facit, vt non 
                     〈◊〉
                   ſuo ſed etiant corum, 
                     〈…〉
                  . Pſal. 10
                     •
                  . Non 
                     〈…〉
                   parentes fuerunt peccat
                     •••
                  s, ſed quis ipſi peccatorum amidatores. Hibr
                     ••
                   in Ezech. 18. Cum pr
                     •
                  
                  nectiores ex parentum culpa ferinutur, ill
                     •
                  rum poenas luunt, quorum opera ſecuti ſunt. Greg. mor. l. 15. c. 21. Non niſi ſit culpae particeps. Them. ſum. 1 a. 2 a. q. 81. a. 1. &amp; Alex. Ales p. 2. q. 122. m. 1. where the children tread in their Fathers ſteps, and doe in impietie or iniquitie imitate their bad Parents: For that when they ceaſe to follow their bad Parents baſe practice
                     •
                  , they De
                     ••
                  nit eſſe filius iniquorum, qui non imitatur mores illorum. Aug. in Pſal. 108. Eorum 
                     •
                  uim 
                     〈◊〉
                  , quorum mores imitamur. Origen. in Ezech. bom. then ceaſe to bee their Sonnes. And that therefore is there mention made of the third and fourth deſcent onely, becauſe that Quia
                     •
                  ſque ad 3. &amp; 4. prog
                     •
                  
                  
                  
                     •
                  , eam quam imitentur filij, parentum vitam poſſunt videre, 
                     •
                  ſque adeos vltio extenditur, qui viderunt quod male ſequerentur. Greg. Ibid. 
               parents may liue ſo long, and their euill examples conſequently be ſeene of their iſſue.
            
            
               
                  Exception 1 For 1. the verie example that wee haue here in hand, of a good Sonne ſmitt
                     •
                  n for his bad Fathers offence, doth directly proue the contrarie.
            
               
                  Exception 2 2. Nor ſeemeth it ſtinted to the third and fourth deſcent, ſo much, becauſe Parents may liue ſo long

to giue euill examples to their iſſue, as becauſe they may liue ſo long to ſee Gods iudgements on it.
                  Expoſition 10
            
            Or laſtly, that it is then onely executed, 
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plato de leg. l. 9. Quod idem cum iſto facit, Euſeb. praepara
                     •
                  . Euang. l. 2. c. 39. when impietie runneth on ſo from deſcent to deſcent, as hereditarie, that the whole race it ſelfe ſeemeth Quomodo milites Maximini percuſſores, Ex peſſimo genere ne catulum quidem eſſe relinquendum. Iul. Capitol. worthy to be vtterly rooted and raced out.
            For beſides the former exceptions,
               Exception. which here alſo hold; the examples ſome of them before produced doe euidently euince the contrarie.
            Thus you ſee how about the Solution of this Queſtion many haue beaten their braines, and thoſe men of great note, and yet haue giuen no good or iuſt ſatisfaction therein.
            For the vntying therefore of this knot, rather ſnarled more and entangled, than by them vnknit, and the reconciling of thoſe ſeeming differences betweene the texts of Scripture before mentioned, let me intreat a while your beſt attention to that that ſhall be deliuered, that I may not be in ought therein miſtaken.
            Firſt therefore let it be conſidered,Solution. that Heb. 9.26. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Archin. Clam. Strom l. 6. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Eurip. Alceſt. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Antho
                     ••
                  g. Debemur m
                     ••
                  ti. H
                     •
                  rat. art. 
               all men (Father and Sonne, as well the one as the other)
                  Conſiderati∣on 1 
               owe a death vnto God; Natura dabitum Deut repetit quomodo &amp; quando vidi: homo tum dema
                     •
                   r
                     •
                  petit, cum ī
                  
                     •
                  bet naturae Deus. Iuſ
                     •
                  . in Ioſ. 7. which hee may iuſtly require whenſoeuer, and whereſoeuer, on what occaſion, and by what meanes ſoeuer he will. Joſua 7.24. Deus hoc ipſe mandauit, non iudex, cui illud praeceptum eſt. Deut. 14.16. Aug. in Ioſ. q. 8. God therefore for the ſinne of Achan, might command his whole houſhold, and his children among the reſt, (though not Neque enim liquet, quod Iun. laboraſſe faminam contagione conſcientiae. 
               priuie to, or guiltie of that offence of his) to be put to death, and ſo puniſh him in them as

well as in his owne perſon, becauſe they ought all of them a death to him, which on that occaſion he might require. But 2 King. 14.6. 2 Chron. 25.4. Homine iudice nemo niſi ex eulpa propria poenas debet luere. Aug. in Ioſ. q. 8. 
               Amazias may not put to death the ſonnes of thoſe traytors that ſlew the King his Father; according to that Deut. 24.16. Reatus patris non obeſt liberis. Althuſ. dicaealog. l. 1. c. 30. Filius pattis aniquitalem ferre non debet. Petr. Fons leg. ſelect. Sancimus ibi eſſe poenam, vbi &amp; noxia eſt. Propinquos, natos, familiates procul à calumnia ſub
                     ••
                  oue
                     •
                  ꝰ quos reosſceleris ſocietas non facit. Peccata ſuos teneant autores. Nec vlterius progrediatur metꝰ 
                     〈◊〉
                   re
                     •
                  
                  atur delictū. Arcad. Theodoſ. &amp; Honor. Cod. l. 9. tit. 47. leg. 22. Crimen vel poena paterna nullam maculam filio nifligere poteſt. Nam
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   vnuſquiſ
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   ex ſuo admiſſo forti ſubijcitur, nec 
                     〈◊〉
                   criminis ſucceſſor conſtituitur. 
                     〈◊〉
                  . Digeſt. l. 48.1.19. l. 26. Et 
                     •
                  rat. d
                     ••
                  r. c. 1. q. 4. c. 
                     •
                  . 
               Law which God had enacted betweene man and man to be obſerued: becauſe they were no way obnoxious to him, neither did they by any Law or Statute humane or diuine owe a death vnto him otherwiſe.
            Yea the iuſtice and equitie of Gods dealing in this kinde may bee further cleered euen by ſuch courſes as men alſo may lawfully take: For ſuppoſe we ſome great Noble-mans only ſonne and ſole heire condemned to die, for ſome rape or robberie by him committed. Howbeit his Soueraigne conſidering that the young man is one of good parts otherwiſe, and may hereafter doe his King and Countrey good ſeruice, though he were ouertaken in that act; as alſo out of pitie to his Fathers houſe, loth to ſee an ancient family vtterly extinguiſhed in him; and beſides, hauing earneſt ſuit made in his behalfe by diners neere about him is inclining, yea &amp; purpoſed to grant him his pardon. But in the interim, while the matter hangeth yet in ſuſpence, it commeth to be diſcouered, that the Noble-man his Father hath his hand in ſome foule treaſon, hath entred into conſpiracie either with ſome forraine 
                  〈◊〉
                or ſome domeſticall traitour againſt the perſon of his Prince. Now hereupon his Soueraigne, altring his minde and purpoſe concerning his Sonne, cauſeth him inſtantly to bee brought out and executed in the ſight of his Father, whom after alſo hee diſpoſeth

of according to his deſert. In which caſe the Sonne (you ſee) is puniſhed for his Fathers offence, but for which hee might haue eſcaped: and the Father is puniſhed in the Sonne; his Sonnes death (no doubt) being no leſſe puniſhment to him than his owne: and yet is there no wrong or iniuſtice done either to Father or Sonne, becauſe both had deſerued death, and death was therefore due to either.
            And herein erred thoſe wicked Iewes, that charged God with iniuſtice, that they complained that their Fathers had done amiſſe, and that Quomodo de Roman is Hor. carm. 3.6. Delicta maiorū immeritus lu
                     •
                  s, Romane, donec templa refeceris Aedeſque labentes Deorū, &amp;c. they (themſelues being no way faultie) ſuffered onely for their Fathers faults. Whereas indeed, vile wretches, Ezek. 20.30, 31. Ierem. 7.26. &amp; 16.12. they were euerie whit as bad, or worſe rather than they, and Ierem. 3.25. bare the burden of their owne iniquities.
            
            Secondly, let it be conſidered, that God layeth 
                  Conſideration 2 no temporall iudgement at any time vpon any, but hee is able to turne the ſame Rom. 8.28. Sicut nihil eſt, quod malis non noceat. Quibꝰ peſtifera fiunt, quae profutura eſſent, ſi alijs darentur. Sen. de benef. l. 5. c. 12. Ita. nihil eſt quod non bonis prodeſſe poſſit. Idem de prou. c. 3. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Xenoph. apud Plut. de mimic. to the good of the partie vpon whom it is inflicted. And that he doth ſo, as here alſo hee did, when hee layeth any outward euill on a godly perſon for the ſinne of ſome wicked one, and ſo puniſheth (as he doth oft alſo) the bad in the good.
            
            For the better cleering of this, wee may well make vſe of that diſtinction ſo riſe in the Schooles, that Panalia aliquando habent ratronem maledicti, ali
                     •
                   habent rationers medicinae. Vide poſt Aug. in Ioſ. qu. 8. Thom. ſum. p. 1 a 2 ae. q. 87. a. 7, 8. &amp; p. 2 a. 2 ae. q. 108. a. 4. Simplic. in Epictet. enchirid. c. 13. &amp; Senet de prouid. c. 3. Hinc diſtinctio illa poenae, in nocentem, &amp; conferentem; ſiue in ſuffocantem &amp; promouen
                     •
                  em: item in poenam vindictae, &amp; poenam cautelae: ſiue in condemnantem, &amp; corrigentem: apud Alenſ. p. 1. q. 39. m. 
                     ••
                  . 4. § 1. ſ. 6. &amp; p. 2. q. 115. m. 3. ſ. 1. &amp; q. 122. m. 1. ſ. 1. &amp; p. 3. q. 41. m. 4. a. 1. theſe outward temporall euills, or penall ſufferings are in the nature,

                  
                     
Sometime of a curſe.
                  
                  Sometime of a cure.
                  
               
            
            
               Courſes 4.And accordingly there is a foure-fold courſe of Gods dealings in theſe caſes.
            
               
                  Courſe 1 For ſometime God puniſheth a bad Father in a bad Sonne; and then it is not a croſſe onely, but a curſe to both. So God puniſhed (wee may iuſtly deeme) Exod. 12.29. 
               Pharao in his firſt-borne.
            
            
               
                  Courſe 2 Sometime hee puniſheth a good Father in a good Sonne; and then it is, though a croſſe, yet a cure to both. So puniſhed he 2 Sam. 12.14, 15, 18. 
               Dauid (i
                  •…
               e may well iudge) in his young childe.
            
            
               
                  Courſe 3 Sometime hee puniſheth a good Father in a bad Sonne; and then it is a cure to the Father, and a curſe to the Sonne: So puniſhed he the ſame. 2 Sam. 12.10, 11. &amp; 18.9, 15, 33. 
               Dauid in his ſonne Abſolom.
            
            
               
                  Courſe 4 Sometime hee puniſheth a bad Father in a good Sonne; and then it is a curſe to the Father, and a cure to the Sonne. So puniſhed hee 1 King. 14.1, 3, 12, 17. 
               Ieroboam in his ſonne here mentioned. And that which was no doubt a great and grieuous croſſe and plague to his Father, yet proued through Gods goodneſſe in mercie wiſely ſo diſpoſing it, no leſſe Verſ. 13, 18. a benefit and bleſsing to the childe.
            
               Recapitulation.Thus then I hope that by this time you ſee, how God without any the leaſt blemiſh to his iuſtice, may by death take away the Sonne for his Fathers 
                     Branch 1 offence.
               Branches 4.
            
            
               
                  Branch 2 Why man may not ordinarily doe therein as God doth: and yet that in ſome caſes men doe alſo, and may well doe the ſame.
            
               
                  Branch 3 That the wicked Iewes had no iuſt cauſe to

charge▪ God with iniuſtice for his dealings with them, albeit that he ſhould ſo haue done.
            And how God can turne to the good of a good child,
               
                  Branch 4 the euill that he ſuffers for his bad Fathers default; though to his vngodly Parent the ſame be a fearefull iudgement, and not a croſſe only, but a curſe too.
            Now a word or two of vſe, and ſo an end.
            And firſt it may admoniſh Parents to be the 
                  Vſe 1 more carefull to ſhun ſinne, if not for their owne Vt vel poſieritatibus conſul
                     •
                  ntes diuinae leg
                     •
                  ob
                     •
                  dirent. Tertull. ad Marc. l. 2., for their childrens ſake yet: becauſe their ſinnes may bring iudgements vpon their children alſo, euen as well as vpon themſelues. There is no Parent, if he be not wholly ſtript of naturall affection, but deſires the welfare of his child. Yea, Quis non magis filiorum ſalutem quam ſuam curet? Tertull. Ibid. Ita Leo Homericus Il. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 135. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  ; Auiſque apud e
                     •
                  nd. Il. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 324. 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plut. de amor. prol. Catulorū amor in venabula impingit faeras Sen. ep. 74. 
               Parents are vſually wont to be more charie of their childrens welfare than of their own. Art thou deſirous then of thy childrens well-doing? Doe not wilfully that that may any way impeach it. And nothing may ſooner doe it than thy ſinne. As thine obedience and vpright carriage of thy ſelfe in Gods ſight may procure Deut. 4.40. &amp; 5.29. &amp; 7.8, 9, 13. &amp; 28.4. a bleſsing euen to thy poſterity: ſo thy ſinne and tranſgreſsion may bring Deut. 28.18, 32, 41. Ier. 5.17. 
               euill alſo vpon it. What a griefe would it be to any of vs that haue children, if in playing with one of them wee ſhould let it fall vnwittingly, whereby the childe ſhould get a knocke, that it ſhould lie long ſicke, and at length die of? Take heed then how to ſatisfie ſome wanton luſt or deſire of thine, thou doe wilfully that that may prouoke God to wrath, &amp; cauſe him to lay the like on thy childe, as thou ſeeſt that in the like caſes ſometime he hath done. Yea, conſider with thy ſelfe, if ſhortly after ſome ſuch wilfull

running out of thine, and giuing way to thine vnreſtrained corruption, ſome ſuch thing ſhould befall thy childe, and 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   (ex Eurip. Oreſt. Clem. Str
                     •
                  m. l. 7.) 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plut. de tranquill. thy guilty conſcience ſhall then (as it may iuſtly) ſuggeſt vnto thee, This may well be the hand of God vpon my childe for mine exceſſe, or my ſinne; 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Plut. de ſanit. what griefe and anguiſh of heart muſt it needs procure to thee, and poſſeſſe thy ſoule withall, when thou ſhalt euer and anon bee thinking, and ſaying within thy ſelfe, 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . 
               All this torment doth this poore infant endure for my ſake, for my ſinne. We cry out oft of witches, when our children are ſtrangely taken, and ſay ſuch a one hath bewitched them, when we are the witches our ſelues; and, as hee ſaith of the 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Baſil. Caſ. de ebrietat. 
               wine, that men take aboue meaſure, it is our ſinne that hath bewitched them. Nor let Gods children thinke themſelues priuileged in this kinde more than others. 2 Sam. 12.10, 11, 14, 15, 18. &amp; 13.1, 14, 28, 29. &amp; 16.22. &amp; 18.9, 15, 33. 1 King. 1.5, 9. 
               Dauid (you heard) was ſo puniſhed, as well as Ieroboam, howſoeuer God turned it to his good; and that not in one onely, but 2 Sam. 12.10, 11, 14, 15, 18. &amp; 13.1, 14, 28, 29. &amp; 16.22. &amp; 18.9, 15, 33. 1 King. 1.5, 9. in diuers of his. And if other of Gods children ſhall in like manner grow wanton, and preſuming on Gods goodneſſe, ſhall take liberty to themſelues, to walke loofely, and run riot; God may iuſtly by the like iudgements call them home againe, and reclaime them, which may be alſo for their good.
            
            
               
                  Vſe 2 To conclude, it may teach Parents what vſe to make of Gods hand vpon their children. That they take occaſion thereby to looke home to themſelues, examine their hearts, view and ſur
                     •
                  ey their liues, make inquiry what corruption of theirs either ſwaying (without controll) in the one, or

breaking out by way giuen to it in the other, might giue God iuſt occaſion to lay that croſſe vpon them: and in more ſpeciall manner, (becauſe 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . Sapient. 11.13. In quibus peccamus, in eiſdem plectimur. In Hellogabali conſcios ſaeuitum vario genere mortis, quum alios vitalibus exemptos n
                     •
                  carent, alios ab ima parte perfodederent, vt mors eſſet vitae conſentiens. Lamprid. 
               God oft puniſheth vs in thoſe things that we offend in; as he puniſhed Dauid in his children, for his ouer-much 2 Sam. 18.33. &amp; 19.4, 5, 6. 1 King. 1.6. Ʋerum ac ſeuerum illud Pi
                     •
                   2. Pp. Hoſtem in ſe nutrire, qui nimis filio ignoſcit. Platin. 
               indulgence towards them) wherein we haue beene faulty about them, and defectiue in our duty toward them, either in fond affection, or neglect of inſtruction and correction, or the like. Now, where is there almoſt any that thinke in ſuch caſes on this? We are troubled to thinke, when our children are euill, that we haue let them go too thin clad, and ſo they haue caught cold: But wee thinke not how careleſſe we haue beene of cloathing (not their bodies, but) their ſoules. We are troubled when they are gone, to thinke that we omitted this or that meanes of helpe for them. But we are not troubled to thinke, that we neglected the beſt meanes with them, and thoſe that concerned not their temporall but their eternall good. Or wee are not troubled for this, that we brake not off, or humbled our ſelues for ſome ſinne, which repented of might haue kept them ſtill with vs. Neither yet doe I, or dare I affirme generally, that this is alwaies the cauſe why God croſſeth men in their children: He may doe, and doth it alſo (no doubt) many times, for the Ad examen. 
               triall and Ad exercitium. Exercitiaſunt nobis iſta, non funera. Cypr. de mortal. Vide Alex. Ales p. 1. q. 39. m. 3. a. 4. § 1. ſ. 6. 
               exerciſe of his gifts and graces in them, their patience, obedience, confidence in God, and the like, and for other ends to himſelfe beſt knowne, as to make way for ſome other worke of his. It was not for any ſpeciall ſinne of Iob, that Iob 1.18, 19. his children were all at once ſo deſtroyed,
               
though it were a: grieuous croſſe vnto him. It was Iohn 5.3. Vnde Alex. Ales p. 3. q. 5. 
                     〈…〉
                   dupli
                  
                     •••
                   
                  
                     〈…〉
                   ad 
                     〈…〉
                  , ad 
                     〈…〉
                  . not for any ſpeciall ſinne of his Parents (our Sauiour himſelfe faith it) that that poore beggar in the Goſpell was borne blinde. Howbeit, ſince that we learne out of Gods word, that God doth frequently inflict ſuch euills vpon, children for the tranſgreſsions of their Parents, yea, and he hath threatned alſo ſo to doe: it ſtandeth vs vpon, and it is one of the beſt vſes that we can make, as of thoſe croſſes that God layeth on vs in our goods and chattels, and our worldly eſtates; ſo, much more of thoſe that in our children (who are much neerer than thoſe to vs) doe befall vs, that we take occaſion thereby 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   3.39, 40. to ſife and ſearch out our wayes, and to humble our ſelues in, the ſight of God for our ſinnes. Had Iereboam ſo done, peraduenture hee might haue ſaued his ſonnes life, he had at leaſt preuented other iudgements more fearefull, that for want thereof after befell him and his. And wee by ſo doing, may either remoue Gods hand lying heauy on our children, and on vs alſo in them, or at leaſt we may haue the croſſe ſo qualified and ſanctified, that it ſhall turne to the good both of vs and ours.
            
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

