
   
      
         
            The first set of madrigals and mottets of 5. parts apt for viols and voyces. Newly composed by Orlando Gibbons, Batcheler of Musicke, and organist of his Maiesties honourable chappell in ordinarie.
            Madrigals and mottets
            Gibbons, Orlando, 1583-1625.
         
         
            
               1612
            
         
         Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2006-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01689
            STC 11826
            ESTC S103065
            99838824
            99838824
            3213
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01689)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3213)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1067:02)
         
         
            
               
                  The first set of madrigals and mottets of 5. parts apt for viols and voyces. Newly composed by Orlando Gibbons, Batcheler of Musicke, and organist of his Maiesties honourable chappell in ordinarie.
                  Madrigals and mottets
                  Gibbons, Orlando, 1583-1625.
               
               [120] p. : music  
               
                  Printed by Thomas Snodham, the assigne of W. Barley,
                  London :
                  1612.
               
               
                  Five partbooks. At head of title, part 1: "Cantus."; part 2: "Altus."; part 3: "Tenor."; part 4: "Bassus."; part 5: "Quintus.".
                  Signatures: A-C⁴; A-C⁴; A-C⁴; A-C⁴; A-C⁴.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Madrigals, English --  Early works to 1800.
               Motets --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-09
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-10
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2005-11
            Andrew KusterSampled and proofread
         
            2005-11
            Andrew KusterText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-01
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
               
                  
                  
                     
CANTVS.
                  THE FIRST SET OF MADRIGALS AND MOTTETS of 5. Parts: apt for Viols and Voyces.
                  
                     NEWLY COMPOSED by Orlando Gibbons, Batcheler of Muſicke, and Organiſt of his Maieſties Honourable Chappell in Ordinarie.
                  
                  
                     LONDON: Printed by THOMAS SNODHAM, the Aſſigne of W. Barley. 1612.
               
               
                  
                  
                     
                        CERVA CHARISSIMA ET GRATISSIMVS HINNVLVS PRO
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  TO THE RIGHT VVORthy, my much Honoured friend, Syr Chriſtopher Hatton, Knight of the Honourable Order of the Bath.
                  
                     SYR:
                  
                  
                     
                        IT is proportion that beautifies euery thing, this whole Vniuerſe conſiſts of it, and Muſicke is meaſured by it, which I haue endeauoured to obſerue in the compoſition of theſe few Ayres, but cannot in their Dedication: for when I compare your many fauours with my demerits, your curious Eare with theſe harſh Notes, there appeares ſo plaine a diſproportion betweene them, that I am afraid, leaſt in offring to your Patronage Songs in ſome tune, my action heerein ſhould be out of all tune; yet haue I made bould to honour them with your Name, that the world may take notice, rather of my want of abilitie, then good-will to be gratefull. By which little outward demonſtration, you may eaſily gueſſe at the greatneſſe of my inward affection, as skilfull Geometricians doe obſerue the true ſtature of the whole body by ſight of the foote onely. Experience tels vs that Songs of this Nature are vſually eſteemed as they are well or ill performed, which excellent grace I am ſure your vnequalled loue vnto Muſicke will not ſuffer them to want, that the Author (whom you no leſſe loue) may be free from diſgrace. They were most of them compoſed in your owne houſe, and doe therefore properly belong vnto you, as Lord of the Soile; the language they ſpeake you prouided them, I onely furniſhed them with Tongues to vtter the ſame: they are like young Schollers newly entred, that at firſt ſing very fearefully, it requires your Patience therefore to beare with their imperfections: they were taught to ſing onely to delight you, and if you ſhall take any pleaſure in them, they haue their end, and I my wiſh, a full recompence for my paſſed labours, and a greater encouragement to preſent you with ſome future things more worthy your Patronage; till which opportunity, I reſt
                  
                  
                     Yours euer to command
Orlando Gibbons.
                  
               
               
                  
                  THE TABLE.
                  
                     THe ſiluer Swanne, who liuing had no note. I
                     O that the learned Poets of our time. II
                     I waigh not Fortunes frowne nor ſmile. 1 Part. III
                     I tremble not at noyſe of warre. 2 Part. IIII
                     I ſee Ambition neuer pleaſde. 3 Part. V
                     I faine not friendſhip where I hate. 4 Part. VI
                     How art thou thrald, O poore deſpiſed creature? 1 Part. VII
                     Farewell all Ioyes. 2 Part. VIII
                     Daintie fine Bird which art incaged there. IX
                     Faire Ladies that to Loue captiued are. 1 Part. X
                     Mongſt thouſands good. 2 Part. XI
                     Now each flowry bancke of May. XII
                     
                        Lais now old, that erſt attempting Laſſe. XIII
                     Faire is the Roſe. yet fades with heate or colde. XIIII
                     What is our Life? XV
                     Ah deere Hart, why doe you riſe? XVI
                     Nay, let mee weepe. 1 Part. XVII
                     Nere let the Sunne with his deceiuing light. 2 Part. XVIII
                     Yet if that age had froſted ore his head. 3 Part. XIX
                     Truſt not too much faire youth vnto thy feature. XX
                  
                  FINIS.
               
            
            
               
                  
                  Of 5. Voc.
                  CANTVS.
                  Orlando Gibbons.
                  
                     I.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        THe ſiluer Swanne, who liuing had no Note, When 
                           〈♫〉
                         death approacht vnlockt her ſilent throat, Leaning her 
                           〈♫〉
                         breaſt againſt the reedie ſhore, Thus ſung her firſt and laſt, and ſung no more, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Farewell all ioyes, O death come cloſe mine eyes, More Geeſe then Swannes now 
                           〈♫〉
                         liue, more fooles then wiſe.
                  
                  
                     
                     II.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        O That the learned Poets of this time, this time, O, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         learned Poets of this time, this time, of this 
                           〈♫〉
                         time, of this time, Who in a Loue-ſicke line ſo well can ſpeake, Who, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Who in a Loue-ſicke line ſo well can ſpeake, Would not conſume 
                           〈♫〉
                         good Wit, conſume good wit in hatefull rime, good, &amp;c. good, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         But with deepe care ſome better ſubiect finde, ſome, &amp;c. For 
                           〈♫〉
                         if their Muſicke pleaſe in earthly things, in, &amp;c. For, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         earthly things, pleaſe in earthly, earthly things, How would it ſound if ſtrung with 
                           〈♫〉
                         heauenly ſtrings? How would it ſound, if ſtrung with heauenly ſtrings? heauenly ſtrings?
                  
                  
                     
                     III.
                     1 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        I Waigh not, I waigh not Fortunes frowne nor ſmile, 
                           〈♫〉
                         nor ſmile, I waigh not Fortunes frowne nor ſmile, I 
                           〈♫〉
                         ioy not much in earthly ioyes, I ioy not much in earthly ioyes, in earthly ioyes, I 
                           〈♫〉
                         in earthly ioyes, I ſeeke not ſtate, I reake not ſtile, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I ſeeke not ſtate, I reake not ſtile, not ſtile, I am not fond of 
                           〈♫〉
                         Fancies toyes, I, &amp;c. I reſt ſo pleas'd with what I haue, 
                           〈♫〉
                         I wiſh no more, no more I craue. I, &amp;c. I wiſh no 
                           〈♫〉
                         more, no more I craue. I, &amp;c.
                  
                  
                     
                     IIII.
                     2 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        I Tremble not at noyſe of warre, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I tremble not at noyſe of 
                           〈♫〉
                         warre, I, &amp;c. I quake not at the Thunders cracke, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I quake not at the Thunders cracke, I ſhrinke not at a 
                           〈♫〉
                         blazing ſtarre, I, &amp;c. I ſhrinke not at a blazing ſtarre, I ſound 
                           〈♫〉
                         not at the newes of wrack, of wracke, I feare no loſſe, I 
                           〈♫〉
                         hope no gaine, I hope no gaine, no gaine, I feare no 
                           〈♫〉
                         loſſe, I hope no gaine, I en-uy none, I none diſdaine, I none diſdaine, I 
                           〈♫〉
                         enuie none, I none diſdaine, I enuy none, I none diſdaine.
                  
                  
                     
                     V.
                     3 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        I See Ambition neuer pleaſde, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I, &amp;c. I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I ſee ſome Tantals ſtarue in ſtore. I, &amp;c. I ſee Golds 
                           〈♫〉
                         dropſie ſeldome eaſd, ſeldome eaſd, I, &amp;c. Golds dropſie ſeldome 
                           〈♫〉
                         caſd, I ſee each Midas gape for more, I, &amp;c. each Midas gape for 
                           〈♫〉
                         more, I, &amp;c. I ſee each Midas gape for more, I neither want, 
                           〈♫〉
                         nor yet abound, I, &amp;c. nor, &amp;c. a-bound, Inough's a 
                           〈♫〉
                         feaſt, a feaſt, Inoughs a feaſt, content is crownd, is crownd, Inoughs a feaſt, 
                           〈♫〉
                         content is crownd. Inoughs a feaſt, content is crownd. Inoughs, &amp;c.
                  
                  
                     
                     VI.
                     4 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        I Faine not friendſhip where I hate, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I fawne not on the great for grace, I priſe, I praiſe a meane eſtate, a 
                           〈♫〉
                         meane eſtate, Ne yet too loftie, nor too baſe, Ne, &amp;c. Ne, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         too loftie, nor too baſe, This this is all my choiſe, my cheere, my choiſe, my 
                           〈♫〉
                         cheere, This, this is all my choiſe, my cheere, my choiſe, my cheere, A minde content 
                           〈♫〉
                         and conſcience cleere, and conſcience cleere, A, &amp;c. This, 
                           〈♫〉
                         this is all my choiſe, my cheere, This, &amp;c. This, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         A minde content and conſcience cleere, and conſcience 
                           〈♫〉
                         cleere, A minde content and conſcience cleere, A, &amp;c. and, &amp;c.
                  
                  
                     
                     VII.
                     1 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        HOw art thou thral'd, how art thou thralde, O poore diſpiſed 
                           〈♫〉
                         creature? How art thou thralde, O poore diſ-pi-ſed 
                           〈♫〉
                         creature? Sith by creation, Sith by creation, Nature made thee free, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Nature, &amp;c. O traiterous eyes, O, &amp;c. to gaze ſo on her 
                           〈♫〉
                         feature, to gaze ſo on her feature, ſo on her feature, That quits with 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſcorne thy deere loſt libertie. that, &amp;c. thy deere loſt 
                           〈♫〉
                         liber-tie.
                  
                  
                     
                     VIII.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        FArewell all ioyes, Farewell all ioyes, Farewell all ioyes, 
                           〈♫〉
                         all ioyes, O Hell, O Hell, O Hell, Now 
                           〈♫〉
                         reſtleſſe cares my pillow, Sweet Mirtle ſhades, farewell, farewell, Now 
                           〈♫〉
                         come, now come ſad Cipreſſe and forlorne, and forlorne, Loues willow, She ſmiles, 
                           〈♫〉
                         She ſmiles, ſhe laughs, ſhe ioyes at my tormenting, at my tormenting, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Toſt on Deſpaires blacke billow, Toſt on Deſpaires blacke billow, Toſt on Diſpaires 
                           〈♫〉
                         blacke billow, blacke billow, O let me dye lamenting. O let mee 
                           〈♫〉
                         dye lamenting, lamenting. la- menting.
                  
                  
                     
                     IX.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        DAintie fine Bird, that art incaged there, Alas, how 
                           〈♫〉
                         like thine and my for- tunes are? Alas, how 
                           〈♫〉
                         like thine and my fortunes are? Both priſoners be, And both ſinging thus, 
                           〈♫〉
                         and both ſinging thus, and both ſinging thus, Striue to pleaſe her that hath impriſoned 
                           〈♫〉
                         vs, Onely thus we differ thou and I, and I, Thou liu'ſt ſinging, but I ſing and 
                           〈♫〉
                         dye, Thou liu'ſt ſinging, but I ſing and dye, I ſing and dye. and dye.
                  
                  
                     
                     X.
                     1 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        FAire Ladies that to Loue capti- ued are, Faire Ladies 
                           〈♫〉
                         that to Loue captiued are, Faire, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         And chaſt deſires doe nouriſh in your minde, And, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         doe nouriſh in your minde, Let not her fault your ſweet affections marr, Let not 
                           〈♫〉
                         her fault, her fault, Let, &amp;c. your ſweet affections marr, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Ne blot the bountie of all Woman- kinde. Womankinde. Ne, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Ne blot the bounty of all Woman-kinde. the bountie 
                           〈♫〉
                         of all Woman-kinde.
                  
                  
                     
                     XI.
                     2 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        MOngſt thouſands good, one wanton Dame to finde, one 
                           〈♫〉
                         wanton, wanton Dame to finde, Amongſt the Roſes 
                           〈♫〉
                         grow ſome wicked, wicked weedes, Amongſt the Roſes grow ſome wicked, wicked 
                           〈♫〉
                         weedes, Amongſt, &amp;c. Amongſt, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſome wicked weedes, For this was not to loue but luſt inclinde, but luſt inclinde, 
                           〈♫〉
                         For loue doth alwayes bring forth, For, &amp;c. bring forth, ij. 
                           〈♫〉
                         bounte- ous deedes, doth alwayes bring forth bounteous deedes. And 
                           〈♫〉
                         in each gentle hart deſire of Honour breeds, And, &amp;c. deſire 
                           〈♫〉
                         of Honour breeds. And in each gentle heart deſire of Honour breeds.
                  
                  
                     
                     XII.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        NOw each flowry bancke of May, Wooes the ſtreames that 
                           〈♫〉
                         glides away, Wooes the ſtreames that glides a- way, a- way, Mountaines 
                           〈♫〉
                         fan'd by a ſweet gale, a ſweet gale, Loues the humble, the humble looking Dale, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Loues the humble looking dale, Windes the loued leaues doe kiſſe, windes, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Each thing taſteth of loues bliſſe, Each, &amp;c. Onely 
                           〈♫〉
                         I thought bleſt I be, by deſtinie, Onely I though bleſt I be, to be lou'd by deſteny. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Loue confeſt by her ſweet breath, Whoſe loue is life, whoſe hate is death. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Whoſe, &amp;c. is death, whoſe loue is life, whoſe, &amp;c. whoſe hate is 
                           〈♫〉
                         death, whoſe, &amp;c. Whoſe deere loue is life, whoſe hate is death.
                  
                  
                     
                     XIII.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           LAis now old, that erſt at- tempting laſſe, that 
                           〈♫〉
                         erſt at- tempting laſſe, that, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         To Goddeſſe 
                           Ʋenus conſecrates her Glaſſe, her Glaſſe, For 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſhe her ſelfe hath now no vſe of one, hath now no vſe of one, No dimpled, no 
                           〈♫〉
                         dimpled cheekes hath ſhe to gaze vpon, to gaze vpon, She 
                           〈♫〉
                         cannot ſee, ij. her ſpring-time damaſke grace, not ſee her 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſpring-time damaſke grace, Nor dare ſhe looke vpon, looke vpon her Winter 
                           〈♫〉
                         face. Nor dare ſhe lookevp- on, Nor dare ſhe looke vpon her Winter face.
                  
                  
                     
                     XIIII.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        WHat is our life? our life? a play of paſsion, ij. What is 
                           〈♫〉
                         our life? our life? a play of paſ-ſion, Our mirth the muſicke of di-ui- ſion, of di-ui-ſion, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Our mothers wombes the tyring houſes be, Where we are dreſt for this 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſhort Comedy, Heauen the Iudicious ſharpe ſpectator is, That ſits and markes ſtill 
                           〈♫〉
                         who doth act amiſſe, that, &amp;c. Our graues, ij. that hide vs 
                           〈♫〉
                         from the ſearching Sun, Are like drawne curtaynes when the play is done, When the 
                           〈♫〉
                         play is done, the play is done, Are like drawne curtaines when the play is done, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Thus march we playing, thus, &amp;c. Thus march wee playing to our lateſt 
                           〈♫〉
                         reſt, Thus march wee playing, Thus march wee playing to our
                  
                  
                     
                     XV.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        AH deere hart, why doe you riſe? The light that 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſhines comes from your eyes, your eyes, The, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         from your eyes, The day breakes not, it is my heart, To thinke that 
                           〈♫〉
                         you and I muſt part, To, &amp;c. O ſtay, or elſe my ioyes will dye, 
                           〈♫〉
                         And periſh in their infancie. And, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         la- teſt reſt, thus, &amp;c. Onely we 
                           〈♫〉
                         dye, we dye in earneſt, that's no ieſt, we dye in earneſt, that's no Ieſt.
                  
                  
                     
                     XVI.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        FAire is the Roſe, yet fades with heate or colde, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Faire, &amp;c. Sweet are the 
                           〈♫〉
                         Violets, yet ſoone grow olde, Sweet, &amp;c. yet ſoone grow old 
                           〈♫〉
                         The Lillie's white, yet in one day tis done, White is the Snow yet melts againſt 
                           〈♫〉
                         the Sunne, yet melts againſt the Sunne, againſt the Sunne, So white, ſo 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſweet, ſo ſweet was my faire Miſtris face, yet altred quite in one ſhort houres 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſpace, in one ſhort houres ſpace. So ſhort liu'd beautie a vaine gloſſe doth borrow, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Breathing delight to day, ij. delight to day, 
                           〈♫〉
                         but none to morrow, breathing delight to day, but none to morrow.
                  
                  
                     
                     XVII.
                     1. Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        NAy let mee weepe, though others teares be ſpent, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Though all eyes dryed be, let mine be wet, Vnto thy 
                           〈♫〉
                         graue ile pay this yeerely rent, vnto &amp;c Ile pay this 
                           〈♫〉
                         yeerely rent, Thy liueleſſe Coarſe demands of mee this debt, I owe more 
                           〈♫〉
                         teares then euer Coarſe did craue, then euer Coarſe did craue, Ile pay more 
                           〈♫〉
                         teares then ere was payd to graue. Ile, &amp;c. then ere was 
                           〈♫〉
                         payd to graue. then ere was payd to graue.
                  
                  
                     
                     XVIII.
                     2. Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        NEre let the Sunne with his deceiuing light, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Seeke to make glad theſe watry eyes of mine, theſe, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         My ſorrow ſutes with melancholy night, I ioy in dole, in 
                           〈♫〉
                         languiſhment I pine, I, &amp;c. My friend is 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſet, he was my Sunne, My deereſt friend is ſet, hee was my Sunne, he was my 
                           〈♫〉
                         Sunne, With whom my mirth, my ioy, and all is done. with, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         with whom my mirth, my ioy and all is done, my mirth, my 
                           〈♫〉
                         ioy, and all is done.
                  
                  
                     
                     XIX.
                     3. Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        YEt if that age had froſted ore his head, had froſted 
                           〈♫〉
                         ore his head, yet, &amp;c. Or 
                           〈♫〉
                         if his face had furrow'd beene, Or if his face had furrowed beene with yeeres, 
                           〈♫〉
                         I would not thus bemone that hee is dead, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         bemone that hee is dead, I might haue beene more niggard of my 
                           〈♫〉
                         teares, I might haue beene more niggard of my teares, But O the Sunne new 
                           〈♫〉
                         roſe is gone to bed, And Lillies in their ſpring-time hang their head. is 
                           〈♫〉
                         gone to bed, But, &amp;c. And Lillies in their 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſpring-time hang their head.
                  
                  
                     
                     XX.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        TRuſt not too much faire youth vnto thy feature, truſt &amp;c▪ 
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         vn- to thy feature, Truſt, &amp;c. Truſt, &amp;c. faire youth vnto thy 
                           〈♫〉
                         feature, truſt, &amp;c. vn- to thy feature, Be not enamored, be &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Be not enamored of thy bluſhing, bluſhing hew, Be 
                           〈…〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         whilſt thou art a goodly creature, thou, &amp;c. 
                           〈…〉
                         &amp;c. 
                           〈…〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         whilſt thou art a goodly creature, be, &amp;c. 
                           〈…〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         fade that▪ in thy garden grew, the, &amp;c. Sweet Viol
                           〈…〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         in their ſpring, their ſpring, gathered in their ſpring, in their ſpring, ſweet Violet
                           •
                         
                        
                           〈◊〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         gathered, are &amp;c. White Primit fals withouten pittying, White, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         fals withouten pittying▪ White Primit fals, i
                           •…
                         withouten pittying▪
                     
                  
                  FINIS.
               
            
         
         
            
               
                  
                  ALTVS.
                  THE FIRST SET OF MADRIGALS AND MOTTETS of 5. Parts: apt for Viols and Voyces.
                  
                     NEWLY COMPOSED by Orlando Gibbons, Batcheler of Muſicke, and Organiſt of his Maieſties Honourable Chappell in Ordinarie.
                  
                  
                     LONDON: Printed by THOMAS SNODHAM, the Aſſigne of W. Barley. 1612.
               
               
                  
                  
                     
                        CERVA CHARISSIMA ET GRATISSIMVS HINNVLVS PRO
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  TO THE RIGHT VVORthy, my much Honoured friend, Syr Chriſtopher Hatton, Knight of the Honourable Order of the Bath.
                  
                     SYR:
                  
                  
                     IT is proportion that beautifies euery thing, this whole Vniuerſe conſiſts of it, and Muſicke is meaſured by it, which I haue endeauoured to obſerue in the compoſition of theſe few Ayres, but cannot in their Dedication: for when I compare your many fauours with my demerits, your curious Eare with theſe harſh Notes, there appeares ſo plaine a diſproportion betweene them, that I am afraid, leaſt in offring to your Patronage Songs in ſome tune, my action heerein ſhould be out of all tune; yet haue I made bould to honour them with your Name, that the world may take notice, rather of my want of abilitie, then good-will to be gratefull. By which little outward demonſtration, you may eaſily gueſſe at the greatneſſe of my inward affection, as skilfull Geometricians doe obſerue the true ſtature of the whole body by ſight of the foote onely. Experience tels vs that Songs of this Nature are vſually eſteemed as they are well or ill performed, which excellent grace I am ſure your vnequalled loue vnto Muſicke will not ſuffer them to want, that the Author (whom you no leſſe loue) may be free from diſgrace. They were most of them compoſed in your owne houſe, and doe therefore properly belong vnto you, as Lord of the Soile; the language they ſpeake you prouided them, I onely furniſhed them with Tongues to vtter the ſame: they are like young Schollers newly entred, that at firſt ſing very fearefully, it requires your Patience therefore to beare with their imperfections: they were taught to ſing onely to delight you, and if you ſhall take any pleaſure in them, they haue their end, and I my wiſh, a full recompence for my paſſed labours, and a greater encouragement to preſent you with ſome future things more worthy your Patronage: till which opportunity, I reſt
                  
                     Yours euer to command
Orlando Gibbons.
                  
               
               
                  
                  THE TABLE.
                  
                     THe ſiluer Swanne, who liuing had no note. I
                     O that the learned Poets of our time. II
                     I waigh not Fortunes frowne nor ſmile. 1 Part. III
                     I tremble not at noyſe of warre. 2 Part. IIII
                     I ſee Ambition neuer pleaſde. 3 Part. V
                     I faine not friendſhip where I hate. 4 Part. VI
                     How art thou thrald, O poore deſpiſed creature? 1 Part. VII
                     Farewell all Ioyes. 2 Part. VIII
                     Daintie fine Bird which art incaged there. IX
                     Faire Ladies that to Loue captiued are. 1 Part. X
                     Mongſt thouſands good. 2 Part. XI
                     Now each flowry bancke of May. XII
                     
                        Lais now old, that erſt attempting Laſſe. XIII
                     Faire is the Roſe. yet fades with heate or colde. XIIII
                     What is our Life? XV
                     Ah deere Hart, why doe you riſe? XVI
                     Nay, let mee weepe. 1 Part. XVII
                     Nere let the Sunne with his deceiuing light. 2 Part. XVIII
                     Yet if that age had froſted ore his head. 3 Part. XIX
                     Truſt not too much faire youth vnto thy feature. XX
                  
                  FINIS.
               
            
            
               
                  
                  Of 5. Voc.
                  ALTVS.
                  Orlando Gibbons.
                  
                     I.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        THe ſiluer Swanne, who liuing had no Note, When 
                           〈♫〉
                         death approacht vnlockt her ſilent throat, Leaning her 
                           〈♫〉
                         breaſt againſt the reedie ſhore, Thus ſung her firſt and laſt, and 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſung no more, Farewell all ioyes, O death come cloſe mine eyes, 
                           〈♫〉
                         More Geeſe then Swannes now liue, more fooles then wiſe.
                  
                  
                     
                     II.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        O That the learned Poets, O that the learned 
                           〈♫〉
                         Poets of this time, O that the learned Poets of this time, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Who in a Loue-ſicke line, Who in a Loue-ſicke line ſo well can ſpeake, Who 
                           〈♫〉
                         &amp;c. Would not conſume, Would not conſume go
                           ••
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         Wit in hatefull rime, But with deepe care ſome better ſubiect finde, ſome, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         For if their Muſicke pleaſe in earthly things, their Muſicke pleaſe in earthly 
                           〈♫〉
                         things, For, &amp;c. For if their Muſicke pleaſe in earthly 
                           〈♫〉
                         things, in earthly things, How would it ſound if ſtrung with heauenly, heaunely 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſtrings? How would it ſound, if ſtrung with heauenly ſtrings?
                  
                  
                     
                     III.
                     1 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        I Waigh not Fortunes frowne nor ſmile, nor Fortunes 
                           〈♫〉
                         frowne nor ſmile, I, &amp;c. I waigh not Fortunes 
                           〈♫〉
                         frowne, I waigh not Fortunes frowne nor ſmile, I ioy not much in earthly ioyes, not 
                           〈♫〉
                         &amp;c. I ioy not much, not much in earthly ioyes, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I ſeeke not ſtate, I reake not ſtile, I reake not ſtile, I ſeeke not 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſtate, I reake not ſtile, I am not fond of Fancies toyes, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I am not fond of fancies toyes, I reſt ſo pleas'd with what I haue, I wiſh no 
                           〈♫〉
                         more, no more I craue. I, &amp;c. I wiſh no more, I 
                           〈♫〉
                         wiſh no more, no more I craue.
                  
                  
                     
                     IIII.
                     2 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        I Tremble not at noyſe of warre, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I tremble not at noyſe of warre, 
                           〈♫〉
                         not at the noiſe of warre, I quake not at the Thunders cracke, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I ſhrinke not at a blazing ſtarre, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I ſhrinke not at a blazing ſtarre, I ſound not at the newes of wracke, I feare 
                           〈♫〉
                         no loſſe, no loſſe, I hope no gaine, I feare no loſſe, I 
                           〈♫〉
                         hope no gaine, I, &amp;c. I enuy none, I none diſdaine, 
                           〈♫〉
                         I none diſdaine, I enuie none, I none diſ- daine. I enuy none, I 
                           〈♫〉
                         none diſdaine.
                  
                  
                     
                     V.
                     3 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        I See Ambition neuer pleaſde, I, &amp;c. I 
                           〈♫〉
                         &amp;c. Ambition neuer pleaſd, I, &amp;c. I ſee ſome Tantals 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſtarue in ſtore. I, &amp;c. ſome Tantals ſtarue in ſtore, I ſee Golds-dropſie 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſeldome eaſd, ſel- dome eaſd, I, &amp;c. ſeldome eaſd, I ſee each 
                           〈♫〉
                         Midas gape for more, I, &amp;c. I, &amp;c. I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I neither want, nor yet abound, abound, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         nor yet abound, Inough's a feaſt, content is crownd, inoughs, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Inoughs a feaſt, Inoughs a feaſt, content is crownd, Inoughs a feaſt, content 
                           〈♫〉
                         is crownd. Inough's, content is crownd.
                  
                  
                     
                     VI.
                     4 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        I Faine not friendſhip where I hate, not, &amp;c. I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         not, &amp;c. I fawne not on the great for grace, I priſe, I praiſe, I praiſe a 
                           〈♫〉
                         meane e- ſtate, I, &amp;c. a meane eſtate, Ne yet too loftie, nor too 
                           〈♫〉
                         baſe, Ne, &amp;c. nor too baſe, neither too loftie, nor too baſe, This 
                           〈♫〉
                         this is all my choice, my cheere, my cheere, This, &amp;c. A minde content and 
                           〈♫〉
                         conſcience cleere, A, &amp;c. a conſcience cleere, A, &amp;c. a 
                           〈♫〉
                         conſcience cleere, A, &amp;c. This, this is all my choiſe, my cheere, my 
                           〈♫〉
                         choice, my cheere, This, &amp;c. my cheere, This, &amp;c. A 
                           〈♫〉
                         minde content and conſcience cleere, A, &amp;c, and conſcience cleere, a 
                           〈♫〉
                         minde content and conſcience cleere, and, &amp;c. A, &amp;c.
                  
                  
                     
                     VII.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        HOw art thou thral'd O poore diſpiſed creature? 
                           〈♫〉
                         O poore diſpi- ſed creature, Sith by creation, Nature 
                           〈♫〉
                         made thee free, Sith by cre-a-ti- on, Sith, &amp;c. creation, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Nature made thee free, made thee free, ij. thee free, O traiterous eyes 
                           〈♫〉
                         to gaze, to gaze ſo on her fea- ture, to gaze ſo on her fea- ture, to, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         That quits with ſcorne thy deere loſt li-bertie, that, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         loſt libertie. loſt libertie.
                  
                  
                     
                     VIII.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        FArewell all ioyes, all ioyes, Farewell all ioyes, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Farewell, Farewell all ioyes, O Hell, O Hell, Now 
                           〈♫〉
                         reſtleſſe cares my pillow, Sweet Mirtle ſhades, farewell, Now come ſad Cipreſſe, now 
                           〈♫〉
                         come ſad Cipreſſe, She ſmiles, ſhe laughs, ſhe ioyes, She ſmiles, ſhe laughs, ſhe 
                           〈♫〉
                         ioyes at my tor- menting, Breake then poore hart, breake then poore 
                           〈♫〉
                         hart, poore hart, poore hart, breake then poore hart, breake then poore hart, poore 
                           〈♫〉
                         heart, Toſt on Deſpaires, toſt on Deſpaires blacke billow, O let mee dye lamenting, 
                           〈♫〉
                         O let me dye lamenting. lamenting. O, &amp;c.
                  
                  
                     
                     IX.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        DAintie fine Bird, ij. that art in- caged there, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Alaſſe, alaſſe, how like thine and my for- tunes 
                           〈♫〉
                         are? Alaſſe, how like thine and my fortunes are? Both priſoners be, And both 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſinging thus, and both ſinging thus, and, &amp;c. both ſinging thus, Onely thus we 
                           〈♫〉
                         differ thou and I, and I, Thou liu'ſt ſinging, but I ſing and dye. Thou, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I ſing and dye.
                  
                  
                     
                     X.
                     1 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        FAire Ladies that to Loue captiued are, Faire Ladies 
                           〈♫〉
                         that to Loue captiued are, captiued are. Faire 
                           〈♫〉
                         &amp;c. And chaſt de- ſires doe nouriſh in your minde, in your 
                           〈♫〉
                         minde, Let not her fault, Let, &amp;c. your ſweet affections marr, affections marr, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Let not her fault, her fault, your ſweet affections marr, your ſweet affections 
                           〈♫〉
                         marr, your, &amp;c. the bountie of all Woman-kinde. Ne blot the bountie 
                           〈♫〉
                         of all Woman-kinde, Ne, &amp;c. Ne blot the bounty of 
                           〈♫〉
                         all Woman-kinde. all Woman-kinde.
                  
                  
                     
                     XI.
                     2 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        MOngſt thouſands good, one wanton Dame to finde, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Mongſt thouſands good, one wanton Dame to finde, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Amongſt the Roſes grow, Amongſt, &amp;c. ſome wicked weedes, wic- 
                           〈♫〉
                         ked weedes, Amongſt, &amp;c. Amongſt, &amp;c. ſome wicked weedes, ſome 
                           〈♫〉
                         &amp;c. Was not to loſſe but luſt in- clinde, For loue doth al- wayes bring forth 
                           〈♫〉
                         bounteous deedes, For, &amp;c. And in each gentle hart deſire of 
                           〈♫〉
                         Honour breeds, And in each gentle heart deſire, deſire of Honour breeds. And 
                           〈♫〉
                         in each gentle heart deſire of Honour breeds.
                  
                  
                     
                     XII.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        NOw each flowry bancke of May, Now, &amp;c. Now, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Wooes the ſtreames that glides a-way, wooes, &amp;c. the ſtreames that glides away, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Wooes the ſtreames that glides a-way, the, &amp;c. Wooes, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Mountaines fan'd by a ſweet gale, a ſweet gale, Loues the humble Dale, the humble 
                           〈♫〉
                         looking dale, Loues the humble looking dale, the, &amp;c. Windes the loued 
                           〈♫〉
                         leaues doe kiſſe, windes, &amp;c. doe kiſſe, Each thing taſteth of loues blis, of, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         loues bliſſe, Onely I though bleſt I be, to be lou'd by deſteny, Loue confeſt by 
                           〈♫〉
                         her ſweet breath, by, &amp;c. Whoſe loue is life, whoſe hate is death. ij. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Whoſe, &amp;c. whoſe loue is life, whoſe hate is death, whoſe, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Whoſe loue is life, ij. whoſe hate is death. whoſe hate is death.
                  
                  
                     
                     XIII.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           LAis now old, that crſt at-tempting 
                           〈♫〉
                         laſſe, that, &amp;c. To Goddeſſe 
                           Ʋenus 
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         conſecrates her Glaſſe, For ſhe her ſelfe hath now no vſe, no vſe of one, no, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         No dimpled cheekes hath ſhe to gaze vpon, no, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         no, &amp;c. She cannot ſee her ſpring-time damaſke 
                           〈♫〉
                         grace, damaſke grace, her, &amp;c. Nor dare ſhe looke vpon her 
                           〈♫〉
                         Winter face. Nor, &amp;c. vpon her Winter face. vpon her 
                           〈♫〉
                         Winter face. Nor dare ſhe looke vpon her Winter face.
                  
                  
                     
                     XIIII.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        WHat is our life? a play of paſsion, of paſ-ſi-on. What, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Our mirth the muſicke, the muſicke of di-ui-ſi-on, Our, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Our, &amp;c. Our mothers wombes, our, &amp;c. the 
                           〈♫〉
                         tyring, the tyring houſes be, Where we are dreſt, are dreſt for this ſhort Comedy. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Heauen the Iudicious ſharpe ſpectator, ſpectator is, That ſits and markes, that 
                           〈♫〉
                         &amp;c. ſtill who doth act amiſſe, that ſits and markes, markes ſtill who doth act amiſſe, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Our graues that hide vs from the ſearching Sunne, Are like drawne curtaynes 
                           〈♫〉
                         when the play is done, when, &amp;c. When the play is done, is done, Are, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         the play is done, Thus march we playing, thus, &amp;c.
                  
                  
                     
                     XV.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        AH deere hart, why doe you riſe? Deare hart, why doe 
                           〈♫〉
                         you riſe? The light that ſhines comes from your eyes, 
                           〈♫〉
                         The, &amp;c. from your eyes, The day breakes not it is my hart, To thinke that 
                           〈♫〉
                         you and I muſt part, that &amp;c. O ſtay, or elſe my ioyes will dye, or elſe my 
                           〈♫〉
                         ioyes will dye, And periſh in their infan-cie. And periſh in their infancie. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Thus march we playing, Thus, &amp;c. Thus march we 
                           〈♫〉
                         playing to our lateſt reſt, thus, &amp;c. thus, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Onely we dye in earneſt, that's no ieſt. we, &amp;c.
                  
                  
                     
                     XVI.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         FAire is the Roſe, yet fades with heate or colde, faire, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Sweet are the Violets, yet ſoone grow olde, yet ſoone grow old, yet, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         the Violets, yet ſoone grow old, Sweet, &amp;c. Sweet, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Sweet, &amp;c. The Lillie's white yet in one day tis done, the, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         White is the Snow yet melts againſt the Sunne, white, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         againſt the Sunne, So white, ſo ſweet was my faire Miſtris face, my faire Miſtris face 
                           〈♫〉
                         yet altred quite in one ſhort houre, in one houres ſpace. So ſhort liued 
                           〈♫〉
                         beau-tie, ſo ſhortliued beautie a vaine gloſſe doth borrow, a vaine 
                           〈♫〉
                         gloſſe doth bor-row, Breathing delight to day, but none ſo morrow, breathing, &amp; 
                           〈♫〉
                         delight to day, delight to day, to day, breathing, &amp;c.
                  
                  
                     
                     XVII.
                     1. Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        NAy let mee weepe, though others teares be ſpent, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Nay let me weepe, Nay, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Though all eyes dryed be, let mine be wet, Though, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Vnto thy graue ile pay this yeerely rent, vnto &amp;c. vnto, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Thy liueleſſe Coarſe demands of me this debt, this debt, 
                           〈♫〉
                         I owe more teares then euer Coarſe did craue, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I, &amp;c. I, &amp;c. Ile 
                           〈♫〉
                         pay more teares then ere was payd to graue. then ere was payd to graue. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Ile pay more teares, then ere was payd to graue.
                  
                  
                     
                     XVIII.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        NEre let the Sunne with his deceiuing light, will 
                           〈♫〉
                         &amp;c. Seeke to make glad theſe watry eyes of 
                           〈♫〉
                         mine, theſe, &amp;c. My ſorrow ſutes with melancholy night, my, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I ioy in dole, in languiſhment I pine, I pine, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I pine, I ioy, &amp;c. I ioy in dole in languiſhment 
                           〈♫〉
                         I pine, I, &amp;c. My deereſt friend is ſet, he was my 
                           〈♫〉
                         Sunne, My, &amp;c. he was my Sunne, My, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         With whom my ioy, and all is done. with whom my mirth, my ioy, and all is done, 
                           〈♫〉
                         With, &amp;c. With whom my mirth, my ioy, and all is done.
                  
                  
                     
                     XIX.
                     3. Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        YEt if that age had froſted ore his head, yet, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Or if his face had furrow'd beene with 
                           〈♫〉
                         yeeres, Or if his face, his face had furrowed ben with yeeres, Or, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Or, &amp;c. I would not ſo bemone, I would not 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſo bemone that he is dead, he is dead, I, &amp;c. I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I might haue ben more niggard of my teares, I, &amp;c. of my teares, 
                           〈♫〉
                         But O the Sunne new roſe is gone to bed, the, &amp;c. And Lillies in their 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſpring time hang their head. And, &amp;c. But, &amp;c. but, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         And Lillies in their ſpring-time, in their ſpringtime hang their head.
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                     
                     XX.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        TRuſt not too much, too much faire youth, Truſt not too much 
                           〈◊〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         youth vnto thy feature, Truſt, &amp;c. vnto thy feature, Be not enamored, 
                           〈♫〉
                         be &amp;c. enamored of thy bluſhing hew, Be not enamored of thy bluſhing 
                           〈♫〉
                         hew, Thou art a goodly creature, Be gameſome whilſt thou art a goodly creature, 
                           〈♫〉
                         a goodly creature, thou, &amp;c. be, &amp;c. Be gameſome 
                           〈♫〉
                         whilſt thou art a goodly, goodly creature, The flowers will fade that in thy garden grew the 
                           〈♫〉
                         in thy garden grew, that, &amp;c. Sweet Vi- olets are gathered in their ſpring 
                           〈♫〉
                         time, are gathered in their ſpring, ſweet, &amp;c. are gathered in their 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſpring, their ſpring, White Primit fals withouten pit- tying, White, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         White Primit fals withouten pittying, withouten pittying.
                  
                  FINIS.
               
            
         
         
            
               
                  
                  QVINTVS.
                  THE FIRST SET OF MADRIGALS AND MOTTETS of 5. Parts: apt for Viols and Voyces.
                  
                     NEWLY COMPOSED by Orlando Gibbons, Batcheler of Muſicke, and Organiſt of his Maieſties Honourable Chappell in Ordinarie.
                  
                  
                     LONDON: Printed by THOMAS SNODHAM, the Aſſigne of W. Barley. 1612.
               
               
                  
                  
                     
                        CERVA CHARISSIMA ET GRATISSIMVS HINNVLVS PRO
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  TO THE RIGHT VVORthy, my much Honoured friend, Syr Chriſtopher Hatton, Knight of the Honourable Order of the Bath.
                  
                     SYR:
                  
                  
                     IT is proportion that beautifies euery thing, this whole Vniuerſe conſiſts of it, and Muſicke is meaſured by it, which I haue endeauoured to obſerue in the compoſition of theſe few Ayres, but cannot in their Dedication: for when I compare your many fauours with my demerits, your curious Eare with theſe harſh Notes, there appeares ſo plaine a diſproportion betweene them, that I am afraid, leaſt in offring to your Patronage Songs in ſome tune, my action heerein ſhould be out of all tune; yet haue I made bould to honour them with your Name, that the world may take notice, rather of my want of abilitie, then good-will to be gratefull. By which little outward demonſtration, you may eaſily gueſſe at the greatneſſe of my inward affection, as skilfull Geometricians doe obſerue the true ſtature of the whole body by ſight of the foote onely. Experience tels vs that Songs of this Nature are vſually eſteemed as they are well or ill performed, which excellent grace I am ſure your vnequalled loue vnto Muſicke will not ſuffer them to want, that the Author (whom you no leſſe loue) may be free from diſgrace. They were most of them compoſed in your owne houſe, and doe therefore properly belong vnto you, as Lord of the Soile; the language they ſpeake you prouided them, I onely furniſhed them with Tongues to vtter the ſame: they are like young Schollers newly entred, that at firſt ſing very fearefully, it requires your Patience therefore to beare with their imperfections: they were taught to ſing onely to delight you, and if you ſhall take any pleaſure in them, they haue their end, and I my wiſh, a full recompence for my paſſed labours, and a greater encouragement to preſent you with ſome future things more worthy your Patronage: till which opportunity, I reſt
                  
                     Yours euer to command
Orlando Gibbons.
                  
               
               
                  
                  THE TABLE.
                  
                     THe ſiluer Swanne, who liuing had no note. I
                     O that the learned Poets of our time. II
                     I waigh not Fortunes frowne nor ſmile. 1 Part. III
                     I tremble not at noyſe of warre. 2 Part. IIII
                     I ſee Ambition neuer pleaſde. 3 Part. V
                     I faine not friendſhip where I hate. 4 Part. VI
                     How art thou thrald, O poore deſpiſed creature? 1 Part. VII
                     Farewell all Ioyes. 2 Part. VIII
                     Daintie fine Bird which art incaged there. IX
                     Faire Ladies that to Loue captiued are. 1 Part. X
                     Mongſt thouſands good. 2 Part. XI
                     Now each flowry bancke of May. XII
                     
                        Lais now old, that erſt attempting Laſſe. XIII
                     Faire is the Roſe. yet fades with heate or colde. XIIII
                     What is our Life? XV
                     Ah deere Hart, why doe you riſe? XVI
                     Nay, let mee weepe. 1 Part. XVII
                     Nere let the Sunne with his deceiuing light. 2 Part. XVIII
                     Yet if that age had froſted ore his head. 3 Part. XIX
                     Truſt not too much faire youth vnto thy feature. XX
                  
                  FINIS.
               
            
            
               
                  
                  Of 5. Voc.
                  QVINTVS.
                  Orlando Gibbons.
                  
                     I.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        THe ſiluer Swanne, who liuing had no 
                           〈♫〉
                         Note, When death approacht vnlockt her ſilent 
                           〈♫〉
                         throat, Leaning her breaſt a- gainſt the ree- die ſhore, Thus 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſung his firſt and laſt, and ſung no more, no more, Farewell all ioyes, O 
                           〈♫〉
                         death come cloſe mine eyes, More Geeſe then Swannes now liue, more 
                           〈♫〉
                         fooles then wiſe, then wiſe.
                  
                  
                     
                     II.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        O That the learned Poets of this time, this time, 
                           〈♫〉
                         O, &amp;c. O, &amp;c. the learned Poets 
                           〈♫〉
                         of this time, Who in a Loue-ſicke line ſo well can ſpeake, Who, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         who, &amp;c. ſo well can ſpeake, Who, &amp;c. Would not 
                           〈♫〉
                         conſume good Wit in hatefull rime, conſume, &amp;c. good, &amp;c. in 
                           〈♫〉
                         hatefull rime, But with deepe care ſome better ſubiect finde, But, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         For if their Muſicke pleaſe, For, &amp;c. in earthly things, 
                           〈♫〉
                         For, &amp;c. in earthly things, in earthly things, how 
                           〈♫〉
                         would it ſound if ſtrung with heauenly ſtrings? how, &amp;c.
                  
                  
                     
                     III.
                     1 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        I Waigh not Fortunes frowne nor ſmile, I 
                           〈♫〉
                         waigh not Fortunes frowne, nor ſmile, I ioy not much in 
                           〈♫〉
                         earthly ioyes, in earthly ioyes, I, &amp;c. in earthly ioyes, I 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſeeke not ſtate, I reake not ſtile, not ſtate, I reake not ſtile, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I am not fond of Fancies toyes, I, &amp;c. of fancies 
                           〈♫〉
                         toyes, I reſt ſo pleas'd with what I haue, I wiſh no more, no more I craue. I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I wiſh no more, no more I craue. I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         no more I craue.
                  
                  
                     
                     IIII.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        I Tremble not at noyſe of warre, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         not at the noyſe of warre, I quake not at the Thunders crake, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I ſhrinke not at a blazing ſtarre, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I ſhrinke not at a blazing ſtarre, I ſound not at the noyſe of warre, 
                           〈♫〉
                         I feare no loſſe, I hope no gaine, no gaine, I feare no loſſe, no 
                           〈♫〉
                         loſſe, I feare no loſſe, I hope no gaine, I enuy 
                           〈♫〉
                         none, I none diſdaine, I, &amp;c. I enuie none, I none diſdaine, diſdaine. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I, &amp;c. I enuy none, I none diſdaine.
                  
                  
                     
                     V.
                     3 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        I See Ambition neuer pleaſde, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I ſee Ambition neuer pleaſd, neuer pleaſd, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I ſee ſome Tantals ſtarue in ſtore. I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I ſee ſome Tantals, I, &amp;c. ſtarue in ſtore, I ſee Golds dropſie 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſeldome eaſd Golds dropſie ſeldome eaſd, I ſee each Midas gape for more, each 
                           〈♫〉
                         &amp;c. I, &amp;c. I ſee each Midas gape for more, I neither want, 
                           〈♫〉
                         nor yet abound, I, &amp;c. Inough's a feaſt, content is crownd, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Inoughs, &amp;c. content is crownd. Inoughs, &amp;c. content is crownd, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Inoughs a feaſt, content is crownd. content is crownd, Inoughs, &amp;c.
                  
                  
                     
                     VI.
                     4 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        I Faine not friendſhip where I hate, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I, &amp;c. I, &amp;c. I fawne not on the great for grace, I 
                           〈♫〉
                         priſe, I praiſe a meane eſtate, I, &amp;c. Ne yet too loftie, nor too 
                           〈♫〉
                         baſe, nor too baſe, Ne, &amp;c. Ne, &amp;c. nor too baſe, This this is 
                           〈♫〉
                         all my choiſe, my cheere, This, &amp;c. this, &amp;c. A 
                           〈♫〉
                         minde content and conſcience cleere, and, &amp;c. A, &amp;c. A, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         and conſcience cleere, This, this is all my choiſe, my cheere, This, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         my choiſe, my cheere, This, &amp;c. my, &amp;c. A 
                           〈♫〉
                         minde content and conſcience cleere, and conſcience cleere, A, &amp;c.
                  
                  
                     
                     VII.
                     1 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        HOw art thou thral'd, O poore diſpi- ſed creature? 
                           〈♫〉
                         How art thou thralde, O poore diſpiſed creature? Sith 
                           〈♫〉
                         by crea-tion, Sith by crea- tion, crea- tion, Sith, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Nature made thee free, Nature, &amp;c. made thee free, O traiterous eyes, 
                           〈♫〉
                         to gaze ſo on her feature, to gaze ſo on her fea- ture, 
                           〈♫〉
                         That quits with ſcorne thy deere loſt libertie, thy deere loſt libertie. thy deere 
                           〈♫〉
                         loſt liber- tie.
                  
                  
                     
                     VIII.
                     2 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        FArewell all ioyes, Farewell all ioyes, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Farewell all ioyes, O Hell, O Hell, Now reſtleſſe 
                           〈♫〉
                         cares my pil- low, Sweet Mirtle ſhades, Sweet Mirtle ſhades, farewell, 
                           〈♫〉
                         and forlorne, and forlorne, and forlorne, Loues willow, She ſmiles, ſhe laughs, ſhe 
                           〈♫〉
                         ioyes at my tormen- ting, at my tormenting, Toſt 
                           〈♫〉
                         on Diſpaires blacke billow, Toſt on Deſpaires, Diſpaires blacke billow, 
                           〈♫〉
                         blacke billow, O let me dye lamenting. lamenting. O let mee dye lamenting. 
                           〈♫〉
                         lamenting.
                  
                  
                     
                     IX.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        DAintie fine Bird, fine Bird, that art incaged there, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Alas, how like thine and my fortunes are? Alas, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Both priſoners be, And both ſing- ing thus, both ſinging thus, Striue to 
                           〈♫〉
                         pleaſe her, to pleaſe her that hath impriſoned vs, Onely thus we differ thou 
                           〈♫〉
                         and I, wee differ, Thou liu'ſt ſinging, but I ſing and dye. I ſing and dye, 
                           〈♫〉
                         but I ſing and dye. I ſing and dye.
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                     
                     X.
                     1 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        FAire Ladies that to Loue capti-ued 
                           〈♫〉
                         are, Faire Ladies that to Loue captiued are, And chaſt deſires 
                           〈♫〉
                         doe nouriſh in your minde, in your minde, your minde, Let not 
                           〈♫〉
                         her fault, her fault, your ſweet affections marr, Let, &amp;c. Let 
                           〈♫〉
                         &amp;c. Ne blot the bountie of all Wo-man-kinde. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Ne, &amp;c. all Womankinde. Ne blot the bounty of all 
                           〈♫〉
                         Womankinde. the bountie of all Woman-kinde. of all Womankinde.
                  
                  
                     
                     XI.
                     2 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        MOngſt thouſands good, one wanton Dame to finde, to 
                           〈♫〉
                         finde, one wanton Dame to finde, one, &amp;c, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Amongſt the Roſes grow ſome wicked weedes, ſome wicked weedes, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Amongſt the Roſes grow, Amongſt, &amp;c. ſome wicked weedes, ſome, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſome, &amp;c. For this was not to loue but luſt inclinde, but luſt in-clinde, inclinde, 
                           〈♫〉
                         For loue doth alwayes bring forth bounteous deedes, For loue doth alwayes, 
                           〈♫〉
                         doth alwayes bring forth bounteous deedes, And in each gentle hart deſire of Honour 
                           〈♫〉
                         Honour breeds, And in each gentle heart deſire of Honour breeds. And, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Honour breeds. de-ſire, deſire of Honour breedes.
                  
                  
                     
                     XII.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        NOw each flowry bancke of May, each, &amp;c. Wooes the 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſtreames that glides a-way, Wooes the ſtreames that glides a-way, wooes, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Mountaines fan'd by a ſweet gale, by a ſweet gale, Mountaines, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Loues the humble looking Dale, Loues the humble looking dale, the, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         the loued leaues doe kiſſe, windes the loued leaues doe kiſſe, doe kiſſe, Each thing 
                           〈♫〉
                         taſteth of loues bliſſe, taſteth of loues bliſſe, One-ly I though bleſt I be, to be 
                           〈♫〉
                         lou'd by deſtinie, by deſtinie, to &amp;c. Loue confeſt by her ſweet breath, Whoſe 
                           〈♫〉
                         loue is life, whoſe hate is death▪ whoſe hate is death, whoſe loue is life, whoſe hate is death, 
                           〈♫〉
                         whoſe, &amp;c. whoſe hate is death, Whoſe loue is life, whoſe hate is death▪ whoſe, &amp;c.
                  
                  
                     
                     XIII.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           LAis now old, that erſt at-tempting laſſe, that erſt attempting 
                           〈♫〉
                         laſſe, To Goddeſſe Ve-nus conſe-crates her 
                           〈♫〉
                         Glaſſe, conſecrates her Glaſſe, For ſhe her ſelfe hath now no vſe of 
                           〈♫〉
                         one, hath now no vſe of one, No dimpled cheekes hath ſhe to gaze, 
                           〈♫〉
                         to gaze vp-on, No dimpled cheekes hath ſhee to gaze vpon, 
                           〈♫〉
                         to gaze vpon, She cannot ſee her ſpring-time damaſke grace, damaſke grace, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Nor dare ſhe looke vpon her Winter face. Nor, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         looke vpon her Winter face. Nor, &amp;c. vpon 
                           〈♫〉
                         her Winter face.
                  
                  
                     
                     XIIII.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        WHat is our life? a play of paſ- ſion, a play of paſsion, What is 
                           〈♫〉
                         our life? What, &amp;c. what, &amp;c. Our mirth the muſicke of 
                           〈♫〉
                         di- ui-ſion, Our, &amp;c. Our mothers wombes the tyring houſes be, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Heauen the Iu-dicious ſharpe ſpectator is, Heauen, &amp;c. That 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſits and markes ſtill who doth act amiſſe, that, &amp;c. ſtill who doth act 
                           〈♫〉
                         a- miſſe, Our graues that hide vs from the ſearching Sunne, that, &amp;c. Are 
                           〈♫〉
                         like drawne curtaynes when the play is done, Are, &amp;c. Are, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Thus march we playing, thus, &amp;c. Thus march 
                           〈♫〉
                         we playing to our lateſt reſt, our lateſt reſt, thus, &amp;c.
                  
                  
                     
                     XV.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        AH deere hart, why doe you riſe? why doe you 
                           〈♫〉
                         riſe? doe you riſe? The light that ſhines comes from your 
                           〈♫〉
                         eyes, The, &amp;c. The, &amp;c. comes from your eyes, 
                           〈♫〉
                         The day breakes not, it is my heart, my heart, To thinke that 
                           〈♫〉
                         you and I muſt part, O ſtay, or elſe my ioyes will dye, 
                           〈♫〉
                         And periſh in their infancie. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Thus march we playing to our lateſt reſt, Onely we dye in earneſt, that's 
                           〈♫〉
                         no ieſt. in earneſt, that's no Ieſt.
                  
                  
                     
                     XVI.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        FAire is the Roſe, yet fades with heate or colde, or colde, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Faire, &amp;c. Sweet are the Violets, yet ſoone 
                           〈♫〉
                         grow olde, yet ſoone grow olde, Sweet, &amp;c. yet ſoone grow 
                           〈♫〉
                         olde. The Lillie's white, the &amp;c. yet in one day tis done, it is done, White is the 
                           〈♫〉
                         Snow yet melts againſt the Sunne, So white, ſo ſweet, is my faire Miſtris face, yet altred 
                           〈♫〉
                         quite in one ſhort houres ſpace, yet, &amp;c. So ſhort liu'd beautie 
                           〈♫〉
                         a vaine gloſſe doth borrow, doth borrow, So, &amp;c. Breathing 
                           〈♫〉
                         delight to day, ij. but none to morrow, breathing, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         breathng, &amp;c. de- light to day, delight to day, breathing, &amp;c.
                  
                  
                     
                     XVII.
                     1. Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        NAy let me weepe, though others teares be ſpent, though 
                           〈♫〉
                         others teares be ſpent, Though all eyes dryed be, let mine 
                           〈♫〉
                         be wet, be wet, Let mine, let mine be wet, Vnto thy graue ile pay this 
                           〈♫〉
                         yeerely rent, vnto &amp;c. this yeerely rent, I owe 
                           〈♫〉
                         more teares then euer Coarſe did craue, then, &amp;c. I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         then e- uer Coarſe did craue, Coarſe did craue, Ile pay 
                           〈♫〉
                         more teares then ere was payd to graue▪ then, &amp;c. Ile, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         then ere was payd to graue.
                  
                  
                     
                     XVIII.
                     2. Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        NEre let the Sunne with his deceiuing light, Nere &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Seeke to make glad 
                           〈♫〉
                         theſe watry eyes of mine, My ſorrow ſutes with melancholy night, with, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I ioy in dole, in languiſhment I pine, I ioy in dole; 
                           〈♫〉
                         I, &amp;c. I pine, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         My deereſt friend is gone, My deereſt friend is gone, he was my Sunne, 
                           〈♫〉
                         My, &amp;c. With whom my mirth, my ioy, and 
                           〈♫〉
                         all is done. My mirth, my ioy and all is done, with, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         with whom my mirth, my ioy, and all is done.
                  
                  
                     
                     XIX.
                     3. Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        YEt If age had froſted ore his head, had, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Or if his face had furrow'd beene with 
                           〈♫〉
                         yeeres, Or, &amp;c. Or if his face, his face, had 
                           〈♫〉
                         furrow- ed beene with yeeres, I would not ſo bemone that hee is dead, 
                           〈♫〉
                         I, &amp;c. hee is dead, that hee is dead, I would haue ben more 
                           〈♫〉
                         niggard of my teares, More niggard of my teares, But O the Sunne new roſe is 
                           〈♫〉
                         gone to bed, to bed, And Lillies in their ſpring-time, in their ſpring-time hang their 
                           〈♫〉
                         head. And, &amp;c. hang their head. But O the Sunne new roſe 
                           〈♫〉
                         is gone to bed, to bed, And Lillies in their ſpring-time hang their head.
                  
                  
                     
                     XX.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        TRuſt not too much faire youth, faire youth vnto thy feature, truſt &amp; 
                           〈♫〉
                         Truſt not too much faire youth vn- to thy feature, truſt 
                           〈♫〉
                         not &amp;c. Be not enamored, be &amp;c. be, &amp;c. be 
                           〈♫〉
                         not ena- mored of thy bluſhing hew, thy bluſhing hew, of &amp;c. Be 
                           〈♫〉
                         gameſome whilſt thou art a goodly creature, whilſt, &amp;c. be, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         a goodly creature, The flowers will fade that in thy garden grew, 
                           〈♫〉
                         that, &amp;c. Sweet Violets are gathered in their ſpring, are, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         in their ſpring, are gathered in their ſpring, Sweet, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         gathered in their ſpring, White Primit fals withouten pittying, Wh
                           •••
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         &amp;c. White Primit fals withouten pittying. White, &amp;c.
                  
                  FINIS.
               
            
         
         
            
               
                  
                  TENOR.
                  THE FIRST SET OF MADRIGALS AND MOTTETS of 5. Parts: apt for Viols and Voyces.
                  
                     NEWLY COMPOSED by Orlando Gibbons, Batcheler of Muſicke, and Organiſt of his Maieſties Honourable Chappell in Ordinarie.
                  
                  
                     LONDON: Printed by THOMAS SNODHAM, the Aſſigne of W. Barley. 1612.
               
               
                  
                  
                     
                        CERVA CHARISSIMA ET GRATISSIMVS HINNVLVS PRO
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  TO THE RIGHT VVORthy, my much Honoured friend, Syr Chriſtopher Hatton, Knight of the Honourable Order of the Bath.
                  
                     SYR:
                  
                  
                     IT is proportion that beautifies euery thing, this whole Vniuerſe conſiſts of it, and Muſicke is meaſured by it, which I haue endeauoured to obſerue in the compoſition of theſe few Ayres, but cannot in their Dedication: for when I compare your many fauours with my demerits, your curious Eare with theſe harſh Notes, there appeares ſo plaine a diſproportion betweene them, that I am afraid, leaſt in offring to your Patronage Songs in ſome tune, my action heerein ſhould be out of all tune; yet haue I made bould to honour them with your Name, that the world may take notice, rather of my want of abilitie, then good-will to be gratefull. By which little outward demonſtration, you may eaſily gueſſe at the greatneſſe of my inward affection, as skilfull Geometricians doe obſerue the true ſtature of the whole body by ſight of the foote onely. Experience tels vs that Songs of this Nature are vſ
                        ••
                     lly eſteemed as they are well or ill performed, which excellent grace I am ſure your vnequalled loue vnto Muſicke will not ſuffer them to want, that the Author (whom you no leſſe loue) may be free from diſgrace. They were most of them compoſed in your owne houſe, and doe therefore properly belong vnto you, as Lord of the Soile; the language they ſpeake you prouided them, I onely furniſhed them with Tongues to vtter the ſame: they are like young Schollers newly entred, that at firſt ſing very fearefully, it requires your Patience therefore to beare with their imperfections: they were taught to ſing onely to delight you, and if you ſhall take any pleaſure in them, they haue their end, and I my wiſh, a full recompence for my paſſed labours, and a greater encouragement to preſent you with ſome future things more worthy your Patronage: till which opportunity, I reſt
                  
                     Yours euer to command
Orlando Gibbons.
                  
               
               
                  
                  THE TABLE.
                  
                     THe ſiluer Swanne, who liuing had no note. I
                     O that the learned Poets of our time. II
                     I waigh not Fortunes frowne nor ſmile. 1 Part. III
                     I tremble not at noyſe of warre. 2 Part. IIII
                     I ſee Ambition neuer pleaſde. 3 Part. V
                     I faine not friendſhip where I hate. 4 Part. VI
                     How art thou thrald, O poore deſpiſed creature? 1 Part. VII
                     Farewell all Ioyes. 2 Part. VIII
                     Daintie fine Bird which art incaged there IX
                     Faire Ladies that to Loue captiued are. 1 Part. X
                     Mongſt thouſands good. 2 Part. XI
                     Now each flowry bancke of May. XII
                     
                        Lais now old, that erſt attempting Laſſe. XIII
                     Faire is the Roſe. yet fades with heate or colde. XIIII
                     What is our Life? XV
                     Ah deere Hart, why doe you riſe? XVI
                     Nay, let mee weepe. 1 Part. XVII
                     Nere let the Sunne with his deceiuing light. 2 Part. XVIII
                     Yet if that age had froſted ore his head. 3 Part. XIX
                     Truſt not too much faire youth vnto thy feature. XX
                  
                  FINIS.
               
            
            
               
                  
                  Of 5. Voc.
                  TENOR.
                  Orlando Gibbons.
                  
                     I.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        THe ſiluer Swanne, who liuing had no 
                           〈♫〉
                         Note, When death approacht vnlockt her ſilent throat, againſt 
                           〈♫〉
                         the ree- die ſhore, Thus ſung her firſt and laſt, and ſung no more, and ſung 
                           〈♫〉
                         no more, Farewell all ioyes, O death come cloſe mine eyes, More Geeſe then 
                           〈♫〉
                         Swannes now liue, more fooles then wiſe.
                  
                  
                     
                     II.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        O That the learned Poets of this time, the, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         the learned Poets of this time, O, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Who in a Loue-ſicke line ſo well can ſpeake Who 
                           〈♫〉
                         &amp;c. Would not conſume good Wit in hatefull 
                           〈♫〉
                         rime, Would, &amp;c. good, &amp;c. good wit in hatefull rime, in hatefull 
                           〈♫〉
                         rime, But with deepe care ſome better ſubiect finde, but, &amp;c. For 
                           〈♫〉
                         if their Muſicke pleaſe in earthly things, in earthly things, in, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         For, &amp;c. in earthly things, How would it ſound if 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſtrung with heauenly ſtrings? if, &amp;c. if ſtrung with heauenly ſtrings?
                  
                  
                     
                     III.
                     1 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        I Waigh not Fortunes frowne nor ſmile, not. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Fortunes frowne nor ſmile, I, &amp;c. not Fortunes 
                           〈♫〉
                         frowne nor ſmile, I ioy not much in earthly ioyes, earthly ioyes, I ioy not much, not 
                           〈♫〉
                         much in earthly ioyes, I, &amp;c. I ſeeke not ſtate, I reake not 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſtile, I, &amp;c. not ſtile, I ſeeke not ſtate, I reake not ſtile, I 
                           〈♫〉
                         an not fond of Fancies toyes, of fancies toyes, I, &amp;c. fancies 
                           〈♫〉
                         toyes, I reſt ſo pleas'd with what I haue, I wiſh no more, no more I craue. I 
                           〈♫〉
                         wiſh no more, no more I craue. I, &amp;c. I wiſh no more, no 
                           〈♫〉
                         more I craue.
                  
                  
                     
                     IIII.
                     2 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        I Tremble not at noyſe of warre, at noiſe of 
                           〈♫〉
                         warre, at noyſe of warre, I, &amp;c. of 
                           〈♫〉
                         warre, I quake not at the Thunders cracke, not, &amp;c. I ſhrinke not 
                           〈♫〉
                         at a blazing, blazing ſtarre, not, &amp;c. I ſhrinke not at a blazing 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſtarre, I found not at the newes of wracke, of wracke, I feare no loſſe, I hope no 
                           〈♫〉
                         gaine, I feare no loſſe, I hope no gaine, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I enuy none, I none diſdaine, I enuie none, I none diſdaine, I enuy 
                           〈♫〉
                         none, I none diſdaine.
                  
                  
                     
                     V.
                     3 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        I See Ambition neuer, neuer pleaſde, I ſee Ambition neuer pleaſd, neuer pleaſd, I, &amp;c. Ambition neuer pleaſde, I ſee ſome Tantals ſtarue in ſtore. I, &amp;c. ſome 
                           〈♫〉
                         Tara's ſtarue in ſtore, I ſee Golds-dropſie ſeldome eaſd, I, &amp;c. I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſeldome eaſd, I ſee each Midas gape for more, I, &amp;c. I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I, &amp;c. each Midas gape for more, I neither want, nor yet abound I &amp;c. nor yet abound, Inough's a feaſt, content is crownd, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Inoughs a feaſt, content is crownd, content is crownd. inoughs, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         inough's, &amp;c. content is crownd. is crownd.
                  
                  
                     
                     VI.
                     4 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        IFaine not friendſhip where I hate, I, &amp;c. I 
                           〈♫〉
                         &amp;c. not friendſhip where I hate, I fawne not on the great, not on the great 
                           〈♫〉
                         for grace, I priſe, I praiſe a meane e- ſtate, I, &amp;c. a meane eſtate, Ne 
                           〈♫〉
                         yet too loftie, nor too baſe, too baſe, Neyet too loftie, nor too baſe, nor too baſe, Ne, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         too baſe, This, this is all my choice, my cheere, my cheere, This, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         This is all my choice, my cheere, A minde content and conſcience cleere, A, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         A, &amp;c. A, &amp;c. and conſcience cleere, This, 
                           〈♫〉
                         this is all my choiſe, my cheere, is, &amp;c. This, &amp;c. my cheere, This 
                           〈♫〉
                         &amp;c. This is all my choiſe, my cheere, A minde content and conſcience 
                           〈♫〉
                         cleere, A, &amp;c, A, &amp;c. A, &amp;c. and, &amp;c.
                  
                  
                     
                     VII.
                     1 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        HOw art thou thral'd O poore diſpiſed creature? 
                           〈♫〉
                         How, &amp;c. Sith by creation, 
                           〈♫〉
                         creation, Sith by crea-tion, Sith, &amp;c. cre-ation, Nature made thee 
                           〈♫〉
                         free, ij. Nature made thee free, thee free, O traiterous eyes. O &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         to gaze ſo on her feature, to gaze, to gaze ſo on, ſo on her feature, 
                           〈♫〉
                         to, &amp;c. That quits with ſcorne thy deere loſt li-bertie. 
                           〈♫〉
                         thy deere loſt libertie. thy deere loſt libertie.
                  
                  
                     
                     VIII.
                     2 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        FArewell all ioyes, Farewell all ioyes, Farewell all 
                           〈♫〉
                         ioyes, all ioyes, O Hell, O Hell, O Hell, Now reſt-leſſe 
                           〈♫〉
                         cares my pillow, now, &amp;c. Sweet Mirtle ſhades, ij. farewell, farewell, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Now come ſad Cipreſſe, ſad Cipreſſe, And forlorne, And forlorne, forlorne lones willow, 
                           〈♫〉
                         She ſmiles, ſhe laughs, ſhe ioyes at my tormenting, at, &amp;c. Breake 
                           〈♫〉
                         then poore hart, breake then poore hart, poore hart, breake then poore hart, breake 
                           〈♫〉
                         then poore hart, breake, &amp;c. Deſpaires blacke billow, Toſt 
                           〈♫〉
                         on Deſpaires blacke billow, O let me dye lamenting. O let me dye lamenting. lamenting. 
                           〈♫〉
                         ij.
                  
                  
                     
                     IX.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        DAintie fine Bird, that art incaged there, Alaſſe, alaſſe, 
                           〈♫〉
                         how like thine and my fortunes are? Alaſſe, how like 
                           〈♫〉
                         thine and my fortunes are? Both priſoners be, Both, &amp;c. And both ſinging 
                           〈♫〉
                         thus, and, &amp;c. Striue to pleaſe her that hath impriſoned vs, Onely thus we differ, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Onely thus we differ thou and I, Thou liu'ſt ſinging, but I ſing and dye. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I ſing and dye. Thou, &amp;c.
                  
                  
                     
                     X.
                     1 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        FAire Ladies that to Loue captiued are, captiued 
                           〈♫〉
                         are. Faire Ladies that to Loue captiued are, And 
                           〈♫〉
                         chaſt deſires doe nouriſh, And chaſt deſires doe nouriſh in your minde, Let not her 
                           〈♫〉
                         fault your ſweet affections marr, Let not her fault, Let, &amp;c. your ſweet af-fections 
                           〈♫〉
                         m arr, Let, &amp;c. your ſweet affections marr, Ne blot the 
                           〈♫〉
                         bountie of all Woman-kinde, of all Woman-kinde. Ne blot the bountie of all 
                           〈♫〉
                         Wo- man-kinde. the bounty of all Woman-kinde.
                  
                  
                     
                     XI.
                     2 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        MOngſt thouſands good, Mongſt thouſands, thouſands 
                           〈♫〉
                         good one wanton, wanton Dame to finde, Mongſt thouſands 
                           〈♫〉
                         good, one wanton Dame to finde, Amongſt the Roſes grow ſome wicked weedes, Amongſt, 
                           〈♫〉
                         &amp;c. ſome wicked weedes, Amongſt, &amp;c. Amongſt, &amp;c. ſomewicked 
                           〈♫〉
                         weedes, A, &amp;c. ſome, &amp;c. For this was not to loue but luſt in- clinde, 
                           〈♫〉
                         For loue doth alwayes bring, doth alwayes bring forth bounteous deedes, For, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         bring forth bounteous deedes, doth, &amp;c. And in each gentle 
                           〈♫〉
                         hart deſire of Honour breedes, And, &amp;c. And, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Each gentle heart deſire of Honour breeds.
                  
                  
                     
                     XII.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        NOw each flowry bancke of May, Now, &amp;c. Wooes the 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſtreames that glides away, woos, &amp;c. Wooes the ſtreames that glides a- way, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Wooes, &amp;c. Mountaines fan'd by a ſweet gale, ſweet gale, Loues the humble looking 
                           〈♫〉
                         Dale, Loues, &amp;c. the humble looking dale, Windes the loued leaues doe kiſſe, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Windes the loued leaues doe kiſſe, doe kiſſe, Windes, &amp;c. Each thing taſteth 
                           〈♫〉
                         of loues bliſſe, of loues bliſſe, One- ly I though bleſt I be, to be lou'd by deſteny, by 
                           〈♫〉
                         deſtinie, Loue confeſt by her ſweet breath, Whoſe loue is life, whoſe hate is death. ij. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Whoſe, &amp;c. is death, whoſe, &amp;c. Whoſe loue is life, is life, whoſe 
                           〈♫〉
                         hate is death. whoſe, &amp;c. Whoſe loue is liſe, whoſe hate is death.
                  
                  
                     
                     XIII.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           LAis now old, that erſt attempting laſſe, that 
                           〈♫〉
                         erſt at- tempting laſſe, that, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         To Goddeſſe 
                           Ʋenus conſecrates her Glaſſe, For ſhee her ſelfe hath now no 
                           〈♫〉
                         vſe of one, hath now no vſe of one, hath, &amp;c. No dimpled cheekes hath 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſhe to gaze vp- on, to gaze vp- on, no, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         She cannot ſee her ſpring-time damaſke grace, She, &amp;c. ſhe 
                           〈♫〉
                         cannot ſee, ij. her ſpring-time damaſke grace, ſhe, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Nor dare ſhe looke vpon her Winter face. Nor, &amp;c. Nor dare ſhe looke vpon 
                           〈♫〉
                         her Winter face. Nor, &amp;c. Nor, &amp;c.
                  
                  
                     
                     XIIII.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        WHat is our life? a play of paſsion, a play of paſsion, What, 
                           〈♫〉
                         &amp;c. What, &amp;c. Our mirth the 
                           〈♫〉
                         muſicke of diuiſion, Our, &amp;c. Our mo- thers wombes, our, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         the tyring houſes be, Where we are dreſt for this ſhort Comedy, ſhort Comedy, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Spectator is that ſits and markes, That ſits and markes ſtill who doth act amiſſe, 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſtill who doth act amiſſe, that, &amp;c. Our graues that hide 
                           〈♫〉
                         vs from the ſearching Sunne, from the ſearching Sunne, the ſearching Sunne, Are like 
                           〈♫〉
                         drawne curtaynes, drawne curtaynes when the play is done, the play is 
                           〈♫〉
                         done, Are like drawne curtaynes when the play is done, Thus march we
                  
                  
                     
                     XV.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        AH deere hart, why doe you riſe? deare hart, why doe you 
                           〈♫〉
                         riſe? you riſe? The light that ſhines comes from your eyes, 
                           〈♫〉
                         your eyes, The, &amp;c. your eyes, The day breakes not it is my hart, To 
                           〈♫〉
                         thinke that you and I muſt part, that &amp;c. O ſtay, or elſe my ioyes will dye, And 
                           〈♫〉
                         periſh in their infancie. O ſtay, or elſe my ioyes will dye, And periſh in their infan- cie. 
                           〈♫〉
                         playing, Thus march we playing, Thus, &amp;c. Thus march we 
                           〈♫〉
                         playing to our lateſt reſt, thus, &amp;c. thus, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         thus, &amp;c. Onely we dye, we dye in earneſt, that's no ieſt.
                  
                  
                     
                     XVI.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        FAire is the Roſe, yet fades with heate or colde, Sweet are the 
                           〈♫〉
                         Violets, Sweet are the Violets, yet ſoone grow old, Sweet, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         The Lillie's white, yet in one day tis done, the Lillie's 
                           〈♫〉
                         white, yet in one day tis done, the, &amp;c. tis done, yet, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         So white, ſo ſweet was my faire Miſtris face, yet altred quite in 
                           〈♫〉
                         one ſhort houres ſpace, in one ſhort houres ſpace. So ſhort liu'd beautie a vaine 
                           〈♫〉
                         gloſſe doth borrow, a, &amp;c. Breathing delight, delight to 
                           〈♫〉
                         day, breathing, &amp;c. but none to morrow, breathing, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         but none to morrow, breathing, &amp;c. but none to morrow.
                  
                  
                     
                     XVII.
                     1. Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        NAy let me weepe, though others teares be ſpent, though 
                           〈♫〉
                         &amp;c. weepe, though others teares be ſpent, Though 
                           〈♫〉
                         all eyes dryed, dryed be, though, &amp;c. let mine be wet, Vnto thy graue ile 
                           〈♫〉
                         pay this yeerely rent, vnto &amp;c. this yeerely rent, vnto, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Thy liueleſſe Coarſe demands of me this debt, demands of mee 
                           〈♫〉
                         this debt, I owe more teares then euer Coarſe did craue, more, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Ile pay more teares then ere was payd to graue, Ile, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Ile pay more teares, then ere was payd to graue. Ile, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Ile pay more teares then ere was payd to graue.
                  
                  
                     
                     XVIII.
                     2. Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        NEre let the Sunne with his deceiuing light, Nere, &amp;
                           •
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         Seeke to make glad 
                           〈♫〉
                         theſe watry eyes of mine, of mine, My ſorrow ſutes with melancholy night, My ſorrow 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſutes, my, &amp;c. with melancholy night, I ioy in dole, in dole, in languiſhment, 
                           〈♫〉
                         I pine, in languiſh. ment I pine, I pine, I ioy in dole in languiſhment 
                           〈♫〉
                         I pine, I, &amp;c. I pine, in, &amp;c. My 
                           〈♫〉
                         deereſt friend is ſet, he was my Sun, he was my Sun, My, &amp;c. My, 
                           〈♫〉
                         &amp;c. my Sun, he, &amp;c. With whom my mirth, my ioy, and all is don
                           〈◊〉
                         
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         my mirth, my ioy, &amp; all is done, with, &amp;c. my ioy, and all is done.
                  
                  
                     
                     XIX.
                     3. Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        YEt if that age had froſted ore his head, had, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         yet, &amp;c. his face had furrowed 
                           〈♫〉
                         beene, Or if his face had furrow'd ben with yeeres, his face had furrow'd ben with 
                           〈♫〉
                         yeeres, not ſo bemone, I would not ſo bemone that he is dead, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I, &amp;c. is dead, I might haue beene more niggard of my 
                           〈♫〉
                         teares, of my teares, I, &amp;c. more niggard of my teares, But O the 
                           〈♫〉
                         Sunne new roſe is gone to bed, is gone to bed, And Lillies in their ſpringtime, in 
                           〈♫〉
                         their ſpring-time hang their head. hang their head, But, &amp;c. the, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         And Lillies in their ſpringtime, hang their head▪ hang their head
                  
                  
                     
                     XX.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        TRuſt not too much faite youth vnto thy fea-ture, Truſt, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Truſt, &amp;c. Truſt, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Be not enamored, be &amp;c. of thy bluſhing hew, enamored of thy 
                           〈♫〉
                         bluſhing hew, Be gameſome whilſt thou art a goodly creature, be▪ &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         be, &amp;c. be, &amp;c. Thou art a goodly crea- 
                           〈♫〉
                         ture, Be gameſome whilſt thou art a goodly creature, in thy garden grew, Sweet 
                           〈♫〉
                         Vi-olets are gathered in their ſpring, are, &amp;c. ſweet, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         White Primit fals withouten pittying, White, &amp;c. White 
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           〈…〉
                        , White Primit fals withouten pittying, withouten pittie pittying.
                  
                  FINIS.
               
            
         
         
            
               
                  
                  BASSVS.
                  THE FIRST SET OF MADRIGALS AND MOTTETS of 5. Parts: apt for Viols and Voyces.
                  
                     NEWLY COMPOSED by Orlando Gibbons, Batcheler of Muſicke, and Organiſt of his Maieſties Honourable Chappell in Ordinarie.
                  
                  
                     LONDON: Printed by THOMAS SNODHAM, the Aſſigne of W. Barley. 1612.
               
               
                  
                  
                     
                        CERVA CHARISSIMA ET GRATISSIMVS HINNVLVS PRO
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  TO THE RIGHT VVORthy, my much Honoured friend, Syr Chriſtopher Hatton, Knight of the Honourable Order of the Bath.
                  
                     SYR:
                  
                  
                     IT is proportion that beautifies euery thing, this whole Vniuerſe conſiſts of it, and Muſicke is meaſured by it, which I haue endeauoured to obſerue in the compoſition of theſe few Ayres, but cannot in their Dedication: for when I compare your many fauours with my demerits, your curious Eare with theſe harſh Notes, there appeares ſo plaine a diſproportion betweene them, that I am afraid, leaſt in offring to your Patronage Songs in ſome tune, my action heerein ſhould be out of all tune; yet haue I made bould to honour them with your Name, that the world may take notice, rather of my want of abilitie, then good will to be gratefull. By which little outward demonſtration, you may eaſily gueſſe at the greatneſſe of my inward affection, as skilfull Geometricians doe obſerue the true ſtature of the whole body by ſight of the foote onely. Experience tels vs that Songs of this Nature are vſually eſteemed as they are well or ill performed, which excellent grace I am ſure your vnequalled loue vnto Muſicke will not ſuffer them to want, that the Author (whom you no leſſe loue) may be free from diſgrace. They were most of them compoſed in your owne houſe, and doe therefore properly belong vnto you, as Lord of the Soile; the language they ſpeake you prouided them, I onely furniſhed them with Tongues to vtter the ſame: they are like young Schollers newly entred, that at firſt ſing very fearefully, it requires your Patience therefore to beare with their imperfections: they were taught to ſing onely to delight you, and if you ſhall take any pleaſure in them, they haue their end, and I my wiſh, a full recompence for my paſſed labours, and a greater encouragement to preſent you with ſome future things more worthy your Patronage: till which opportunity, I reſt
                  
                     Yours euer to command
Orlando Gibbons.
                  
               
               
                  
                  THE TABLE.
                  
                     THe ſiluer Swanne, who liuing had no note. I
                     TO that the learned Poets of our time. II
                     I waigh not Fortunes frowne nor ſmile. 1 Part. III
                     I tremble not at noyſe of warre. 2 Part. IIII
                     I ſee Ambition neuer pleaſde. 3 Part. V
                     I faine not friendſhip where I hate. 4 Part. VI
                     How art thou thrald, O poore deſpiſed creature? 1 Part. VII
                     Farewell all Ioyes. 2 Part. VIII
                     Daintie fine Bird which art incaged there. IX
                     Faire Ladies that to Loue captiued are. 1 Part. X
                     Mongſt thouſands good. 2 Part. XI
                     Now each flowry bancke of May. XII
                     
                        Luis now old, that erſt attempting Laſſe. XIII
                     Faire is the Roſe. yet fades with heate or colde. XIIII
                     What is our Life? XV
                     Ah deere Hart, why doe you riſe? XVI
                     Nay, let mee weepe. 1 Part. XVII
                     Nere let the Sunne with his deceiuing light. 2 Part. XVIII
                     Yet if that age had froſted ore his head. 3 Part. XIX
                     Truſt not too much faire youth vnto thy feature. XX
                  
                  FINIS.
               
            
            
               
                  
                  Of 5. Voc.
                  BASSVS.
                  Orlando Gibbons.
                  
                     I.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        THe ſiluer Swanne, who liuing had no Note, When 
                           〈♫〉
                         death approacht vnlockt her ſilent, ſilent throat, Leaning her 
                           〈♫〉
                         breaſt againſt the reedie ſhore, Thus ſung her firſt and laſt, and ſung no 
                           〈♫〉
                         more, Farewell all ioyes, O death come cloſe mine eyes, More Geeſe then 
                           〈♫〉
                         Swannes now liue, more fooles then wiſe.
                  
                  
                     
                     II.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        O That the learned Poets of this time, the, 
                           〈♫〉
                         &amp;c. O that the learned Poets 
                           〈♫〉
                         of this time, of this time, Who in a Loue ſicke line, Who, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſo well, ſo well can ſpeake, Would not conſume good Wit in 
                           〈♫〉
                         hatefull rime, good, &amp;c. But with deepe 
                           〈◊〉
                         ſome better ſubiect 
                           〈♫〉
                         finde, ſome, &amp;c. For if their Muſicke pleaſe in earthly things, for 
                           〈♫〉
                         &amp;c. in earthly things, For, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         How would it ſound if ſtrung with heauenly ſtrings? with heauenly ſtrings? 
                           〈♫〉
                         it ſtrung with heauenly ſtrings?
                  
                  
                     
                     III.
                     1 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        I Waigh not Fortunes frowne nor ſmile, frowne 
                           〈♫〉
                         nor ſmile, I ioy not much in earthly ioyes, I▪ &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I ioy not much in earthly ioyes, in earthly ioyes, I 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſeeke not ſtate, I reake not ſtile, I ſeeke not ſtate, I reake not ſtile, I 
                           〈♫〉
                         am not fond of Fancies toyes, I, &amp;c. not fond of fancies toyes, I 
                           〈♫〉
                         reſt ſo pleas'd with what I haue, I wiſh no more, no more I craue. I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         no more I craue. I wiſh no more, no more I craue.
                  
                  
                     
                     IIII.
                     2 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        I Tremble not at noyſe of watre, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I quake not at the Thunders cracke, the 
                           〈♫〉
                         Thunders cracke, I ſhrinke not at a blazing ſtarre, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I ſhrinke not at a blazing ſtarre, a blazing ſtarre, I ſound not at 
                           〈♫〉
                         the newes of wrack, of wrack, I feare no loſſe, I hope no 
                           〈♫〉
                         gaine, no gaine, I feare no loſſe, no loſſe, I hope no 
                           〈♫〉
                         gaine, no gaine, I en- uy none, I none diſdaine, I enuie none, I none diſdaine, 
                           〈♫〉
                         I, &amp;c. I none diſdaine. diſdaine.
                  
                  
                     
                     V.
                     3 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        I See Ambition neuer pleaſde, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I ſee Ambition neuer 
                           〈♫〉
                         pleaſde, I ſee ſome Tantals ſtarue in ſtore. I, &amp;c. I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         I ſee ſome Tantals ſtarue in ſtore, in ſtore. I ſee Golds-dropſie ſeldome 
                           〈♫〉
                         eaſd, I, &amp;c. ſeldome eaſd, I ſee each Midas gape for more, I 
                           〈♫〉
                         &amp;c. I, &amp;c. I, &amp;c. gape for more, I neither 
                           〈♫〉
                         want, nor yet abound, I, &amp;c. nor yet abound, Inough's a feaſt, content 
                           〈♫〉
                         is crownd, inoughs, &amp;c. inough's, &amp;c. content is crownd. 
                           〈♫〉
                         inoughs, &amp;c. inoughs, &amp;c. Inough's a feaſt, content is crownd.
                  
                  
                     
                     VI.
                     4 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        I Faine not friendſhip where I hate, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         where I hate, I fawne not on the great for grace, 
                           〈♫〉
                         I priſe, I priſe a meane e- ſtate, I, &amp;c. Neyet too 
                           〈♫〉
                         loftie, nor too baſe, Ne, &amp;c. too loftie, nor too baſe, This, this is all my 
                           〈♫〉
                         choice, my cheere, my cheere, This, this is all my choice, my cheere, my choice, my 
                           〈♫〉
                         cheere, A minde content and Conſcience cleere, A, &amp;c. A minde content, 
                           〈♫〉
                         content, and conſcience cleere, This, this is all my choiſe, my cheere, my 
                           〈♫〉
                         cheere, This, &amp;c. my choiſe, my cheere, A minde content and conſcience 
                           〈♫〉
                         cleere, A, &amp;c. A minde content, content, and conſcience cleere.
                  
                  
                     
                     VII.
                     1 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        HOw art thou thral'd O poore diſpiſed creature? 
                           〈♫〉
                         Sith by creation, creation, Sith by cre- a- tion, Sith, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Nature made thee free, ij. Nature made thee free, thee 
                           〈♫〉
                         free▪ O traiterous eyes to gaze ſo on her feature, ſo on her feature, to, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         to, &amp;c. her feature, That quits with ſcorne, That, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         That quits with ſcorne thy deere loſt libertie▪ thy deere loſt libertie.
                  
                  
                     
                     VIII.
                     2 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        FArewell all ioyes, Farewell, Farewell all ioyes, 
                           〈♫〉
                         O Hell, O Hell, Now reſtleſſe cares my pillow, 
                           〈♫〉
                         my pillow, Sweet Mirtle ſhades farewell, Now come ſad Cipreſſe, ſad Cipreſſe, 
                           〈♫〉
                         She ſmiles, ſhe laughs, ſhe ioyes at my tormenting, at my tormenting, Breake 
                           〈♫〉
                         then poore hart, poore hart, poore hart, breake then poore hart, breake, &amp;c. breake 
                           〈♫〉
                         then poore hart, breake, &amp;c. poore hart, Toſt on Deſpaires blacke billow, Toſt 
                           〈♫〉
                         on Deſpaires, Deſpaires blacke billow, O let me dye lamenting, lamenting▪ O let me 
                           〈♫〉
                         dye lamenting.
                  
                  
                     
                     IX.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        DAintie: Alaſſe, how like thine and my fortunes are? Alaſſe, 
                           〈♫〉
                         how like thine and my fortunes are? Both priſoners 
                           〈♫〉
                         be▪ And both ſinging thus, Striue to pleaſe her that hath impriſoned vs, impriſoned 
                           〈♫〉
                         vs, Onely thus we differ thou and I, Onely thus we differ thou and I, Thou liu'ſt 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſinging, but I ſing and dye.
                  
                  
                     
                     X.
                     1 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        FAire Ladies that to Loue, to Loue captiued 
                           〈♫〉
                         are, And chaſt deſires doe nouriſh in your minde, And 
                           〈♫〉
                         &amp;c. your minde, Let not her fault, her fault your ſweet affections 
                           〈♫〉
                         marr, Let, &amp;c. your ſweet affections marr, your, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Ne blot the bountie of all Woman-kinde, Ne, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         the bounty of all Woman-kinde. all Woman-kinde. Ne, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Ne blot the bountie of all Woman-kinde.
                  
                  
                     
                     XI.
                     2. Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        MOngſt thouſands good, Mongſt thouſands good, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Mongſt thouſands good, one wanton, wanton Dame to 
                           〈♫〉
                         finde, Amongſt the Roſes grow ſome wicked weedes, Amongſt, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Amongſt, &amp;c. ſome wicked weeds, ſome, &amp;c. For this was not to 
                           〈♫〉
                         loue but luſt inclinde, inclinde, but luſt inclinde, For loue doth alwayes bring forth 
                           〈♫〉
                         bounteous deeds, For Loue doth alwayes bring forth bounteous deeds, For, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Deſire of Honour breeds, And in each gentle heart deſire of 
                           〈♫〉
                         Honour breeds. And, &amp;c. deſire of Honour breeds.
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                     
                     XII.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        NOw each flowry bancke, Now each flowry bancke of 
                           〈♫〉
                         May, Wooes the ſtreames that glides a- way, that glides away, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Wooes the ſtreames that glides a- way, that, &amp;c. Mountaines fan'd by a 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſweet gale, Mountaines fan'd by a ſweet gale, a ſweet gale, Loues the humble looking 
                           〈♫〉
                         Dale, Windes the lo- ued leaues doe kiſſe, Windes the loued leaues doe kiſſe, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Each thing taſteth of loues bliſſe, Loue confeſt by her ſweet breath, Whoſe loue 
                           〈♫〉
                         is life, whoſe hate is death. Whoſe, &amp;c. is death, Whoſe loue is 
                           〈♫〉
                         life, whoſe hate is death.
                  
                  
                     
                     XIII.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        
                           LAis now old, Lais now old, that crſt attempting 
                           〈♫〉
                         laſſe, For ſhee her ſelfe, her ſelfe, for ſhee her 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſelfe hath now no vſe of one, her ſelfe hath now no vſe of one, No 
                           〈♫〉
                         dimpled cheekes hath ſhe to gaze vpon, no, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         She cannot ſee her ſpring-time damaſke grace, She cannot ſee, not ſee her 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſpring-time damaſke grace, her, &amp;c. Nor dare ſhe looke vpon 
                           〈♫〉
                         her Winter face. vpon her Winter face. Nor dare ſhe looke vpon her Winter, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Winter face. vp-on her Winter face.
                  
                  
                     
                     XIIII.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        WHat is our life? a play of paſsion, What is our life? our 
                           〈♫〉
                         life? a play of paſsion, Our mirth the muſicke of di- uiſion, of diuiſion, Our, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Our mothers wombes the tyring houſes be, Where 
                           〈♫〉
                         we are dreſt, are dreſt for this ſhort Comedy, Heauen the Iu-dicious ſharpe ſpectator 
                           〈♫〉
                         is, That ſits and markes who doth amiſſe, That ſits and markes ſtill who doth 
                           〈♫〉
                         act amiſſe, ſtill who doth act amiſſe, Our graues that hide, that hide vs from the 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſearching Sunne, Are like drawne curtaynes, when the play is done, when, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Thus march we playing, to our lateſt reſt, Thus, &amp;c. our 
                           〈♫〉
                         lateſt reſt, Thus march we play- ing, thus, &amp;c. Onely
                  
                  
                     
                     XV.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        AH deere hart. The light that ſhines comes from your eyes, 
                           〈♫〉
                         The light that ſhines comes from your eyes, comes 
                           〈♫〉
                         from your eyes, your eyes, The day breakes not it is my hart, To thinke that 
                           〈♫〉
                         you and I muſt part, to, &amp;c. to, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         O ſtay, or elſe my ioyes will dye, And periſh in their infancie. And 
                           〈♫〉
                         &amp;c. And, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         we dye in earneſt, that's no ieſt. no ieſt.
                  
                  
                     
                     XVI.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        FAire is the Roſe, yet fades with heate or cold, with heate 
                           〈♫〉
                         or colde, Sweet are the Violets, yet ſoone grow old, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Sweet, &amp;c. The Lillie's white, yet in one day tis done, yet in one 
                           〈♫〉
                         day tis done, White is the Snow yet melts againſt the Sunne, yet melts againſt the Sun, 
                           〈♫〉
                         So white, ſo ſweet was my faire Miſtris face, yet altred quite in one ſhort houres 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſpace, So ſhort liu'd-beautie a vaine gloſſe doth borrow, ſo, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         a vaine gloſſe doth borrow, Breathing delight, delight to day, 
                           〈♫〉
                         breathing delight to day, brea, &amp;c. delight to day, but none to morrow, 
                           〈♫〉
                         breathing, &amp;c. delight to day, but none to morrow, but none to morrow.
                  
                  
                     
                     XVII.
                     1. Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        NAy let me weepe, though others teares be ſpent, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Nay, &amp;c. be ſpent, Though 
                           〈♫〉
                         all eyes dryed be, let mine be wet, let mine be wet, be wet, Vnto thy 
                           〈♫〉
                         graue ile pay this yeerely rent, Ile pay this yeerely rent, Thy liueleſſe 
                           〈♫〉
                         Coarſe demands, thy liueleſſe Coarſe demands of mee this debt, I owe 
                           〈♫〉
                         more teares then euer Coarſe did craue, then euer Coarſe did craue, Ile 
                           〈♫〉
                         pay more teares then ere was payd to graue. was payd to graue. Ile pay more 
                           〈♫〉
                         teares, then ere was payd to graue. then ere was payd to graue. Then ere was 
                           〈♫〉
                         payd to graue.
                  
                  
                     
                     XVIII.
                     2 Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        NEre let the Sunne with his deceiuing light, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Seeke to make glad theſe wa- try eyes of 
                           〈♫〉
                         mine, theſe, &amp;c. My ſorrow ſutes with melancholy night, My, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         with melan- choly night, I ioy in dole, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         in languiſhment I pine, I ioy in dole, in languiſhment I pine, I, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         My deereſt friend is ſet, hee was my Sunne, 
                           〈♫〉
                         My, &amp;c. My deereſt friend is ſet, hee was my Sunne, 
                           〈♫〉
                         With whom my mirth, my ioy, and all is done. With whom my mirth, my 
                           〈♫〉
                         ioy, and all is done. my ioy, and all is done.
                  
                  
                     
                     XIX.
                     3. Part.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        YEt if that age had froſted ore his head, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Or if his face had furrowed beene, Or, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Or if his face had furrowed beene with yeeres, I 
                           〈♫〉
                         would not ſo bemone that hee is dead, I might haue beene more niggard 
                           〈♫〉
                         of my teares, I, &amp;c. of my teares, But 
                           〈♫〉
                         O the Sunne now roſe is gone to bed, And Lillies in their 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſpring-time, hang their head. the Sunne new roſe, But O the Sunne new roſe is 
                           〈♫〉
                         gone to bed, is gone to bed, And Lillies in their ſpring-time hang their head.
                  
                  
                     
                     XX.
                     
                        
                           〈♫〉
                         
                        TRuſt not too much faire youth vnto thy feature, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Truſt not too much, too much faire youth, Truſt not too 
                           〈♫〉
                         much vnto thy feature, Truſt, &amp;c. Be not en-amored, be &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         of thy bluſhing hew, of, &amp;c. Be gameſome whilſt thou art: a goodly, creture, 
                           〈♫〉
                         Thou art a goodly creature, Thou, &amp;c. be, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         thou art a goodly creature, be, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         Sweet Vio-lets are gathered in their ſpring, their ſpring, in, &amp;c. 
                           〈♫〉
                         ſweet, &amp;c. their ſpring, their ſpring, 
                           〈♫〉
                         White Primit fals with-outen pittying, White Primit fals withouten pittying.
                  
                  FINIS.
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
               
            
         
      
   

