
   
      
         
            Christiana-Polemica, or A preparatiue to warre Shewing the lawfull vse thereof. The iust causes that may moue thereunto. The necessitie of preparation for it. The duties of those that wage it. Together with diuers instructions concerning it. A sermon preached at Wooll-Church in London, before the captaines and gentlemen that exercise in the artillerie-garden vpon occasion of their solemne and generall meeting. Aprill 14. 1618. By Abraham Gibson, Bachelour of Diuinity, and then preacher to the temples.
            Gibson, Abraham, b. 1586 or 7.
         
         
            
               1619
            
         
         Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01690
            STC 11828
            ESTC S118766
            99853973
            99853973
            19378
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01690)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19378)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1067:04)
         
         
            
               
                  Christiana-Polemica, or A preparatiue to warre Shewing the lawfull vse thereof. The iust causes that may moue thereunto. The necessitie of preparation for it. The duties of those that wage it. Together with diuers instructions concerning it. A sermon preached at Wooll-Church in London, before the captaines and gentlemen that exercise in the artillerie-garden vpon occasion of their solemne and generall meeting. Aprill 14. 1618. By Abraham Gibson, Bachelour of Diuinity, and then preacher to the temples.
                  Gibson, Abraham, b. 1586 or 7.
               
               [12], 32 p.   
               
                  Printed by Edw. Griffin for Iacob Bloome, at the signe of the Grey-hound in Pauls-Church-yard,
                  London :
                  1619.
               
               
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  17th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-02
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-02
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-03
            Pip WillcoxSampled and proofread
         
            2007-03
            Pip WillcoxText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            Christiana-Polemica,
OR
A PREPARATIVE
TO WARRE.
Shewing
The lawfull vſe thereof.
The iuſt cauſes that may moue thereunto.
The neceſſitie of Preparation for it.
The duties of thoſe that wage it.
Together with
Diuers inſtructions concerning it.
            A Sermon
Preached at Wooll-Church in London,
before the Captaines and Gentlemen that
exerciſe in the Artillerie-Garden vpon occaſion
of their ſolemne and generall
meeting. Aprill 14. 1618.
            BY
Abraham Gibſon, Bachelour of Diuinity, and
then Preacher to the Temples.
               Aug. Epiſt. 205. ad Bonif.
               Pacem habere debet voluntas, bellum neceſſitas.
            
            LONDON,
Printed by Edw. Griffin for Iacob Bloome,
at the ſigne of the Grey-hound in
Pauls-Church-yard. 1619.
         
         
            
            
            To the right honourable
FRANCIS Lord VERVLAM
Lord Chauncellor of England
his very ſingular good LORD:
A. G. wiſheth all happines and
felicitie, externall, internall,
eternall.
            
               Right honourable,
            
            
               AS is the nature
of warre, ſo is
the ſtate of this dedication.
No warre is
held lawfull, which

hath not a ſpeciall reference
to peace. And
this diſcourſe of warre
hath nothing in it
cōmendable, but that
it is deuoted to your
Lordſhip, the State
oracle of Counſell, and
Preſeruer of peace.
In which caſe I haue
beene more bold to
make you the Patron
of my endeauours, becauſe
you haue deigned
already to be the

               Protectour of my perſon.
Not knowing to
whom more fitly I
might nuncupate a
Sermon of GOD
and GIDEON
(the two Supporters of
euery Souldiers armes,
the ground vpon which
euery field is to bee
pitcht) then to
him who repreſenteth
both mediately the
perſon of GOD, and
immediately the perſon

of GIDEON.
I humbly therefore
beſeech your Honour
to accept it candidly
according to the modell
of the Offerer,
not the magnitude of
the Receiuer, whoſe
Patronage I ſhall account
the beſt title
to it, and the comelieſt
couer your countenance,
and the only
cum priuilegio your
approbation. VVhich

whileſt your Honour
ſhall vouchſafe,
I in the meane time
ſhall not ceaſe to enlarge
this little ſchedule
by greater volumes
of continuall
Praiers for your
Lordſhippes welfare,
that the LORD
would pleaſe to bee
your Keeper on earth,
and ſeale you among
the number
of them that haue

the marke of the
Lambe in heauen.
            
               Your Honours moſt
deuoted Chaplaine,
ABRAH: GIBSON.
            
         
         
            
            TO THE WORTHY
and well-deſeruing Citizens
of LONDON, that practiſe
Armes in the
Artillery Garden.
            
               GENTLEMEN,
            
            
               THis ſhort Sermon
heretofore preached
before you, finding
better acceptance
then either it merited
or I expected, I was importuned
by diuers of you to commit it
to the Preſſe. Which though I
withſtood ſtiffly at the firſt, yet now
at length vpon theſe late rumours
of warres I haue with an vnwilling
willingneſſe yeelded to your

ſuit, not doubting but it will haue
the ſame effect of encouragement
in others when they reade it, as it
had in many of you when you heard
it. For this is one aduantage which
writing hath aboue preaching,
that the benefit thereof is more diffuſiue,
extending the fruit of that
doctrine to a whole kingdome,
which when preached was impaled
in the breaſts of a priuate auditorie;
and ſo doth more conforme vs
in this particular to the Apoſtles
times, that though our charge be
ſpeciall, yet our labours may be
vniuerſall. And this is my onely
aime at this preſent, the furtherance
of the publike good, by a diſcourſe
ſmall in it ſelfe as a drop of
water or a ſparke of fire, yet ſuch
as by Gods bleſsing may grow to a
pleaſant fountaine to ſatisfie the
ſoules of the thirſtie, and increaſe
to a pillar of fire to enlighten thoſe

that ſit in darkneſſe: water, to
coole the courages of our Countrey
hotſpurs that will fight in no cauſe
but a bad; and fire to enflame the
hearts of all truſtie ſubiects that
they doe fight in no cauſe but a
good, to wit (as Tullie ſaid, aut
pro fide, aut pro ſalute) for the
peace of Sion, or proſperitie of Ieruſalem;
for the quiet of the
Church, or defenſe of the Common
wealth. Ye ſee how theſe
times make good our bleſſed Sauiours
prediction, that wee ſhould
heare of warres and rumours of
warres:
               Matth. 24. 6. I pray God wee may onely
heare the rumour of them, and not
feele the ſmart. Howſoeuer, let vs
not be troubled or feare, ſeeing we
haue both a gratious God to fight
for vs, and a princely Gideon to
leade vs. Let euery man gird his
ſword vpon his thigh faſt fixing
his heart vpon God, and his eyes
               
vpon Gideon, our hope in the
name of the Lord, and our praiers
for the ſafetie of our King, beſeeching
God who is the King of
Kings, that after a full reigne on
earth, he would tranſlate him to
the kingdome of kingdomes in heauen.
Amen.
            
               Yours in all Chriſtian
duties and ſeruices,
A. G.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            Christiana-Polemica
OR
A PREPARATIVE
to Warre.
            
               IVDG. 7. 18.
               For the Lord, and for Gideon.
            
            
               THe lawfull vſe of
Warre amongſt
Chriſtians (howſoeuer
the Anabaptiſts
denie it,
thus ſowing the
ſeedes of diſcord
vnder a pretence of peace, and ſtirring

vp warre in the Church, whilſt
they would exclude it out of the
Common-wealth) though it had no
Politicall reaſons to backe it, yet
wanteth it not arguments both Phyſicall
and Theologicall, fetcht both
from the light of Nature which dictates
ſo much, and from the authoritie
of Scripture, which warrants
and allowes ſo much.
            For Nature.
               The neceſſary vſe of warre appeareth, Indeed created Nature
abhorreth nothing more then
diſcord and diſſention.
               1. By nature. According to
her prime perfection there had
beene no iarres, either in a mans ſelfe,
or with other things.
            
            Not in a mans ſelfe; the Elements
and Humours had lien at peace in
our bodies, the Iraſeible and Epithumeticall
faculties had bowed at the
becke of reaſon in our ſoules: Nor
with other things; the creatures had
all beene ſubiect to mans dominon,
there had beene no litigious Pronounes
(no Meum and Tuum) to ſet
vs by the eares together.The originall of warre is from originall ſinne. So then
the originall of diſcord is from originall

ſinne; warre it is a branch of that
accurſed tree: had there beene no
fall of man, ſure no falling out amongſt
men; our nakedneſſe as it had needed
no garments to couer it, ſo nor
no weapons to defend it. And therefore
for corrupted Nature, warre is a
neceſſary concomitant of her condition.
It muſt needs be that ſtrifes
ſhould ariſe amongſt men, and by
conſequence warres to decide thoſe
ſtrifes, when law and equitie cannot
take place. That as it was with the
tongues at the confuſion;Geneſ. 11. 7. they had
an ill beginning, but an vſefull propagation:
So is it with warre in this ſtate
of corruption. It is 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , a
neceſſary euill, adeò nec cum illo nec ſine
illo, we can liue neither with it, nor
without it. Becauſe it is the deſtroier
of nature in indiuiduo, but the defender
of it in catholico: the daughter of
iuſtice as well as peace,
               Gen. 29. 17. though Leah
like it haue a harder fauour and a
more wateriſh eye,
               Gen. 25 25. more red and
rough-handed with Eſau. That howſoeuer
naturally (Simile generat ſimile)

like begetteth like, yet Politically
wee ſee eftſoones one contrary to
beget another, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               .
Warre, it is as the ſiſter, ſo the parent
of peace, and yet what ſo oppoſed
to peace as warre? a good end of a
bad medium, and an happie daughter
of a diſaſtrous mother. Repugnant
indeed to the foecunditie of nature as
an enemie to her numeroſitie, but
conſonant to the preſcript of nature,
as a preſeruer of her proprietie; the
cauſa ſine qua non, and finall arbitratour
of all generall important controuerſies.
            Thus for Nature.
               2. By Scripture. Now for Scripture,
we haue God himſelfe commanding
it,Ioel 3. 9. 
               Ioel 3. 9. the Angell of the
Lord curſing the neglect of it,Iudg. 5. 23. 
               Iudg.
5. 23.Quibꝰ propriū ſtipendium ſufficere debere praecepit, militare vtique non prohibuit. Auguſt. epiſt. 5. ad Marcellinum. 
               Iohn Baptiſt directing ſoulders
in it,Luk. 3. 14. as a lawfull calling, Luk. 3. 14.
And laſtly the examples of Gods
Saints practiſing it, as Abraham, Moſes,
Ioſhua, and ſo many others, that
the time would be too ſhort to recount
them, and withall to tell of
Barak, and of Sampſon, of Iephthah
               
alſo and of Dauid: wee need goe no
further then Gideon here in the Text,
whom God elected by the miniſterie
of an Angell to deſtroy the Hoſt of
Midian, confirming his courage by
diuerſitie of ſignes, and directing his
courſe by a moſt famous ſtratageme,
               Gideons warre accompanied with ſtratagems.
whereof there are fiue moſt notable
parts.
            
               Firſt,
               1. In reducing the 32000. to 300. verſe 6. 
               that hee ſhould reduce the
two and thirty thouſand to three hundred,
(Trecenti, ſed viri, ſed Lacones)
Who ſo is fearfull and afraid, let him
returne, verſe 3. And this we reade
to be the policie of Epaminondas,
when he ſaw many of his Armie
faint-hearted, he cauſed to be proclaimed,

                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               : Whoſoeuer
would faine be gone, let him
ſtraight be packing. Likewiſe of Iphicrates,
who to rid his Armie of
whiteliuered Souldiers, he made the
Crier proclaime,
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               : If any man haue left his
heart behinde him, let him returne.
Laſtly of Chabrias, who commanded
his Souldiers 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               :

if they were not well
at eaſe, to put off their armour.
            Secondly,In taking the aduantage of be night. that he ſhould take the
aduantage of the night, verſe 9. for as
Aurora Muſis, ſo Nox Martis amica:
any ſtratageme will take beſt in
the night, which is the fitteſt time to
plot, and the beſt curtaine to conceale:
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , ſaith the Greeke prouerbe.
            
               In giuing eue
                  
                     •
                  y man a lampe.Thirdly, that he ſhould giue them
euery man a Lampe, verſe 16. And
this policie likewiſe Iphicrates that
excellent Captaine vſed againſt the
Barbarians: he made his horſemen
euery one to take ardentem facem,
a burning lampe in their hands, at
the vnaccuſtomed ſight whereof
the Barbarians horſes fled backe
And the like tricke it was that Hannibal
put vpon Fabius Maximus.
            
            
               4. In putting a Trumpet into euery mans hand.Fourthly, euery man with his
Trumpet in his hand, as it is in the
ſame verſe. And this proiect Mnaſippidas
is ſaid to haue vſed, when hauing
but a ſmall company of Souldiers,
he made his light horſemen

in the darke ride about the enemies,
euery one with a Trumpet in his
hand, the ſound whereof bred in
the enemies a ſuppoſall of a huge
multitude.
            
               5. In the vſe this watchword For the Lord &amp; for GideonFiftly and laſtly, that hee ſhould
vſe this famous watchword in my text,
For the Lord and for Gideon. You
know what was wrote in Conſtantines
Enſigne, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , in this
ſigne ſhall yee ouercome. And Attalus
when he fought with the French had
this poeſie, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , the Kings
victorie. And here in my Text you
haue both theſe included: both in
whom we ſhould ouercome, that is,
the Lord, in hoc ſigno vinces; and vnder
whom we ſhould ouercome, and
that is Gideon; 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ): both
from whom victorie commeth, and
for whom it is got, God and the King,
For the Lord and for Gideon.
            
            So that you ſee the text it is Theandricall;
               The contents of the Text.
it hath as it were two natures;
it conſiſteth as it were of God
and Man,
               God and the King. 
               Deus &amp; Rex: He that is
God eſſentially, and hee that is called

God metaphorically,Pſal. 82. 6. God and his
Viceroy, the Lord and Gideon.
            Which if you examine by Analyſis,
               The two wayes for a Warriour to walke in.
it ſets downe, firſt the two wayes
which euery Souldier muſt walke in
vnto the battell:1. Via ſacra. 
               via ſacra, the Eccleſiaſticall
way, hee muſt fight for
God and holy Church:
               
                  
                     •
                  . Via regia. 
               via regia, the
Politicall way, he muſt fight for the
King and his Countrey.
               The perſons vpon whom the ſuc
                  
                     •
                  eſſe of warres dependeth. Secondly the
Perſons vpon whom the ſucceſſe of
warres depends, God and Gideon:
God as Captaine, Gideon as Lieutenant:
God as the Efficient, Gideon as the inſtrument,
and ſo we may learne hereby
to giue God what belongeth vnto
God,
               Matth. 22. 21. 
               and to giue Caeſar what belongeth
vnto Caeſar: thus harmonically ioyning
together religion and policie,
Church and Common-wealth, God
and the King. For the Lord and for
Gideon.
            
            There are ſome tranſlations that
reade it, the ſword of the Lord and of
Gideon: but becauſe the particle
Sword is not in the originall, I rather
follow thoſe which reade it thus,

               For the Lord and for Gideon.
            
            
               Two things to be handled.In the words obſerue two things.
Firſt the parts of the diſtribution;
both for God and for Gideon. Secondly
the order of the parts. Firſt
for God, and then for Gideon. 
               1. The parts o
                     •
                   the distributio
                     •
                  
               Firſt
of the firſt, the parts of the diſtribution,
where the firſt clauſe is, For the
Lord.
            
            That warre is not warrantable,
               The firſt clau
                     ••
                   
                  For the Lord
               
which is not grounded on a iuſt
cauſe. For as it is not the death but
the cauſe that maketh a Martyr, non
ſimpliciter mori, ſed pro Chriſto mori:
ſo it is not the fight,
               It is not the figh
                     •
                   but the cauſe that maketh a Souldier. but the cauſe
that maketh a Souldier, non ſimpliciter
pugnare, ſed pro Domino pugnare.
If a warre be begunne without cauſe,
it ſhall end without comfort: for God
is an impartiall ſpectator of all theſe
actions,Auguſt. de c
                     ••
                   Dei li. 17. ca. 1 
               &amp; partem quam inſpicit iuſtam,
ibi dat palmam, ſaith Auguſtine.
So then a Souldier may not
fight, as a Sophiſter may dispute, in
vtramque partem, pro &amp; contra, his
limits are not ſo large as thoſe of the
Logicians, de omni themate: Nay he

is abſolutely confined to aequum &amp;
iuſtum, licitum &amp; honeſtum: it is equitis
that maketh a good cauſe, and
a good cauſe that maketh a good
Souldier.
            
            Now what better cauſe can there
be,
                  
                     •
                  o better cauſe 
                     ••
                  en the cauſe of 
                     ••
                  rd. then that which concerneth the
Lord, who himſelfe is prima cauſa,
the firſt mouer, and ſole doner of
whatſoeuer we haue?
                  
                     ••
                  m. 11. 36. For of him, and
through him, and for him are all things.
Let vs therefore returne the honour
of all to him. Of our ſelues we haue
nothing, we are not ſo much as our
owne men; our eyes, andPſal. 12 4. 
               tongues,
and armes, and legges, they are not
our owne; we haue no true title either
to body or ſoule. Wherefore let
vs glorifie God both in our bodies and
ſoules,
               Cor. 6. 20. 
               for they are Gods. There is no
peace you know to the peace of God,
nor no warre to that which is for
God. Hence (bella Iudaeorum, bella
Dei) the warres of the Iewes were
called the warres of God, vel quia
pro ipſo, vel quia ab ipſo: either be
cauſe God fought for them, or becauſe

               they fought for God.
               God is euery w
                     ••••
                   the cauſe of warre. For God,
he hath the relation of euery cauſalitie
in this kinde peculiar and proper
to him.1. The efficien
                     •
                   cauſe. He is the efficient cauſe
thereof, By mee Kings raigne, and
Princes beare rule:Prou 8. 15. the great Centurion,
that ſaith to euery creature,Matth. 8. 9.
               Goe and he goeth, Come and he commeth,
Fight and he fighteth. He is
the formall and exemplary cauſe
thereof:2. The formall cauſe. 
               Hee teacheth my hands to
warre and my fingers to fight,
               Pſal. 144. 1. ſaith
Dauid,
               Pſal. 18. 39. 
               He girdeth mee with ſtrength
vnto the battell, and ſubdueth mine
enemies vnder me. He is the instrumentall
cauſe:
               3. The inſtrumentall cauſe. 
               my rocke, and my Fortreſſe,
ſaith Dauid in another place,Pſal. 18. 1.
my ſhield and ſtrong tower, and a
buckler to all them that truſt in him.
And therfore it ſtandeth with good
reaſon,4. The finall cauſe. that he ſhould be the finall
cauſe too,Prou. 18. 10. 
               in whoſe name all battels
muſt be begunne,Pſal. 115. 1. and to whoſe glory
they muſt be deuoted.
            And hence it was that the Iewes
neuer went out to warre, vnleſſe they
firſt offered ſacrifice: and wee in our

               Baptiſme doe take Sacramentum militare,
               
                  
                     •
                   Baptiſme wee 
                     ••
                  ceiue our preſſe
                  
                     •
                  oney to become 
                     •
                  hriſts ſouldiers.
an earneſt penny, or preſſemoney,
to become Chriſts Souldiers.
And to this end we weare his colours,
and are attired in his liuerie, with a
ſolemnevow to fight for him, and
that not onely in the ſpirituall warfare,
where we put on the armour of
God, but euen in the corporeall alſo,
where we put on armour for God
            
            Not that God ſtandeth in need of
any helpe of man:
               Not that God 
                     •
                  eedeth it. he requireth no
Champion, hee can vindicate his
owne cauſe without vs, nay againſt
vs, but becauſe the law of ſubordination
and retaliation doth exact ſo
much.
                  
                     •
                  ut our dutie re
                  
                     •
                  uireth it. Wee are his vaſſals vnder
him,Mal. 1. 6. to whom we owne ſuit and ſeruice;
we are children begotten and
created by him, to whom wee owe
feare and reuerence: and therefore
muſt thinke our ſelues obliged in a
double bond to defend his cauſe, who
doth himſelfe pleade ours; to die in
his quarrell,
               Acts 17. 28. by whoſe prouidence wee
liue: whoſe gracious goodneſſe it is
to turne that to a bleſſing,
               Rom. 8. 28. which at

firſt was a curſe;
               Gen. 2. 17. ſo ſweetning death
which is a puniſhment, as to cauſe vs
to die for his name; ſo ſweetning
life which is a warfare,
               Iob. 7. 1. as to cauſe vs
to fight for his ſake. In which quarrell
though a man die in warre,
               Luk. 1. 29. yet
doth he alſo depart in peace: in conflict
with men, but in peace with God,
becauſe he putteth on as a militarie
habite, ſo a peaceable minde. Good
Chriſtians go to warre (ſaith Bernard)
both meekely and couragiouſly:Veri profe
                     ••
                   Iſraelitae pro
                     ••
                  cedunt ad be
                     ••
                   pacific &amp;c.
               &amp; agnis mitiores, &amp; Leonibus
fortiores: innocent as Doues becauſe
they imitate Chriſt,
               Ber. ſer. ad m
                     •
                   Tem. cap. 4. and bold as Lyons
becauſe they fight for Chriſt.
            
            And to this end the Chriſtians in
their enſignes,
               For this cauſe t
                     ••
                   Chriſtians bea
                     ••
                   the Croſſe in their enſignes. they beare the Croſſe
to ſhew they fight in Chriſts behalfe.
And hitherto allude all your
auncient orders of Knighthood, as
Knights Hoſpitallers and Templers:
Knights of S. Iohn of Ieruſalem, and
S. Iames of Compoſtella; and Knights
of the holy Ghoſt, which Henrie the
third of Fraunce inſtituted: whoſe
enſigne was the Doue in the midſt of

a Croſſe; intimating that they were
not to fight, but either in Gods cauſe
implied by the Croſſe, or in a iuſt
and innocent cauſe ſignified by the
Doue.
            
            The Pope,
               The cruelty and 
                     •
                  mpiety of the Pope of Rome. he would faine be accounted
Maſter of this order. For
as though he were elected Gods immediate
Vicegerent aboue Caeſar, and
Gideon, and all Princes: hee taketh
vpon him to inſtitute warres at his
pleaſure; againſt Infidells and thoſe
whom he calleth Heretikes, or whoſoeuer
dare but mutter at his vſurped
authority.
               
                  
                     •
                  mulata ſan
                  
                     •
                  itas. And this hee calleth
by the name of a Croyſadoe or holy
warre, the marke whereof is a red
ſcarfe, which the Souldiers weare in
their Troupes. Such a warre Pope
Innocent decreed againſt the Valdenſes;
and Pope Martin the fourth againſt
Peter King of Arragon. And
it is a miſerable thing to conſider
how many hundred thouſands of
men haue bin cōſumed throughout
all Chriſtendome by thoſe voyages
into the holy Land at the Popes appointment.

The zeale of this iourney
hath eaten vp Chriſtians and enlarged
the Popes territory, who tooke
this opportunitie to ſend Emperors
and Kings afarre of, that hee might
wrong them at home without controule.
What?This is not to fight for Chriſt. Is this to fight for
Chriſt? to ſpill the bloud of Chriſtians
as it were in a humour for his
owne gaine? Is this to be called a
holy warre?
               Neither can it be called a holy Warre. Sure, as improperly as
he a holy Byſhop, or that a holy action,
whereby he hath diuers times giuen
away the Kingdomes of England,
Fraunce, Sicily, Naples, and the reſt
to thoſe that could get them: or Paleſtine
the holy Land, which is rather
to be accounted an accurſed Land
(as the Iewes were ſometime Gods
people, but now are an accurſed people)
a Land of it ſelfe not worth
the recouery were it not for the reſcue
of ſome Chriſtians there in
thraldome, and for the expelling
the Turke out of the Chriſtian confines.
Yea and all ſuch proiects as
theſe, they were neuer deriued from

               heauen but hatched in hell. This is
not to be Gods Vicar but Sathans
Liefetenant: not Succeſſour to Peter,
but Predeceſſour to damnation.
This is to fight againſt God
and man, againſt the Lord and againſt
Gideon, not to crie with the
people here, For the Lord and for
Gideon.
               Chriſtians muſt not warre without a calling from God.
            
            But for vs (Beloued) let vs bee
ſure as in all our actions, ſo eſpecially
in warre caſes to take God along
with vs. For as there is no
Captaine to be compared to the guidance
of his Spirit, no policy to his
prouidence, no aides nor allies to his
aſſiſtance, ſo on the contrary no
ſword woundes ſo deepe as his deſertion,
no Foe like his frowne,
               Rom. 8. 32. no
danger like his diſpleaſure. As if hee
be with thee no man can be properly
againſt thee becauſe all things worke
together for the beſt of thoſe that are
his:Rom. 8. 28. So if he be not with thee all men
may be ſaid to be againſt thee, becauſe
all creatures bow at his becke,Eſai. 10. 5.
and become as roddes of his indignation

to take vengeance on thoſe
that doe euill.
            You know how in the old Teſtament
they ſtill asked counſell of the
Lord,
               Iudg. 20. 27. before they went vp to fight
againſt any people:2. Sam. 5. 19. and the Heathen
themſelues vſed in like manner to
aske aduice at their Oracles: ſo let vs
be ſure that we haue the Lords call
and the Lords allowance. Otherwiſe
we ſhall haue the ſame ſucceſſe that
the Iſraelites had, when they fought
againſt the Amalakites contrarie to
the Lords will.Numb. 14. 45▪
                
               Numb. 14.
            Wherefore as Barak ſaid to Deborah
Iudg. 4 8.Iudg. 4. 8. If thou wilt go with
mee, then I will go; but if thou wilt
not go with me, then I will not go;
ſo muſt we to God. Let his cauſe awaken
vs, let his preſence prepare vs,
let his glory prouoke vs, let his Spirit
poſſeſſe vs, let his name go before
vs, and then no enemie can annoy
vs. Stand wee for the Lord, and the
Lord will ſtand for vs. If wee fight
with Gideon for the Lord, the Lord
will fight with vs for Gideon. Which

is the ſecond part of the firſt generall
braunch.The ſecond clauſe. For Gideon. As they crie for the Lord,
ſo alſo for Gideon.
            
            
               Gideon is added for further incouragement
to them,Added for incouragement to them, and terrour to the enemie. and further terrour
to their enemies. For we daily
read how that the very name of
ſome valiant Captaines, Caeſar, Alexander,
and the like haue daunted
the enemies without ſtriking a
blow. That as it is ſaid of the ſwords
of Hazaell,
               
                  
                     •
                   King. 19. 17. 
               Iehu, and Eliſha, 1. King.
19. 17. Him that eſcapeth the ſword
of Hazaell ſhall Iehu ſlay: and him,
that eſcapeth from the ſword of Iehu
ſhall Eliſha ſlay: So here of God and
Gideon, He that will not be affrighted
at the name of God, why yet that
man ſhall tremble at the name of
Gideon, though he but Gods Liefetenant.
            Now Gideon hath a twofold conſideration.
Firſt, Gideon a meane
man. Secondly, Gideon a ſingle
man.
            Firſt,Gideon a 
                     •
                  eane man. 
               Gideon a meane man, his Family
by his owne confeſſion was

               poore,
               Iudg. 6. 15. 
               in Manaſſeh, and he the leaſt in
his fathers houſe as it is in the former
chapter.
            He was not trained vp in feates
of armes,
               Not trained vp in armes. or facts of chiualrie; more
skilfull in tilling the ground then
pitching a feild; in handling a flaile
then toſſing a pike: yet when God
had made him their Prince, appointed
him their Captaine, preſently
they follow his direction, and forgetting
all ſiniſter reſpects they crie
out,Pſalm. 115. 1. 
               for Gideon, for Gideon, Non nobis
Domine, non nobis, ſed nomini tuo, &amp;
ſeruo tuo: not for our ſelues, our
wiues, our children, or our eſtates,
but for Gideon.
            
            A good Captaine is aequipollent
to the whole Armie.
               A good Captaine is aequipollent to the whole armie▪
                
               Plus in Duce
repones quam in exercitu, ſaith Probus
of Epaminondas. Me verò Ducem
tuum pro quot nauibus aeſtimas, ſaith
Demetrius in Plutarch: Whence it
was ſaid, better haue an armie of
Stagges and a Lyon Captaine, then
an Armie of Lyons and a Stagge the
Leader. The hazard of all ſtandeth

in the hazard of the Prince,
               In vnius ſalute ſalus omnium: in Imperatore vniuerſorum periculum. or Captaine.
And therefore neglecting
both themſelues and the meaneſſe
of his beginning; they crie for Gideon
for Gideon.
            
            To teach vs,The weakneſſe of the meanes not to be regarded when wee haue Gods warrant. when we haue Gods
warrant not to regard the weakeneſſe
of the meanes, the weakneſſe of God
being ſtronger then men,
               1 Cor. 1. 25. 26. 1. Cor. 1. for
though Gideon was not a trained
Souldier, yet the Angell of the Lord
calleth him a valiant man becauſe
the Lord was with him. The Lord
is with thee thou valiant man.
               Iudg. 6. 12. 
               Iudg.
6. 12. As Chriſt cured, ſo God ſaueth
without meanes, nay againſt
meanes. Howſoeuer therefore the
inſtrument ſeeme weake which God
ſetteth ouer vs, yet wee muſt not
intertaine diſtruſt and diffidence, but
ioyne the reſpect of our Gouernours
with our repoſe in God. For the Lord
and for Gideon.
               2. Gideon a ſingle-man.
            
            Secondly for Gideon a ſingle man,
and this confirmeth that Polemicall
rule,Better in wa
                     •
                  re to haue one Generall then many. In bello magis expedit Principatus
Monarchicus quam Ariſtocraticus;

better in warre to haue one Generall
then many; one ſingular then
many good. 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ,
many Captaines loſt the
Citie. Whence the Romanes in time
of warre did alwaies chuſe them a
Dictator, which was aboue their
Conſuls:
               Malo vnum Zopyrū, quam centum Babilonios capere. and Scipio in Iuſtine, I had
rather (ſaith he) take one Zopyrus
then a hundred Babilonians. A dangerous
thing to haue Corriuals in
warre, as well as in loue-matters, becauſe
that enuie and emulation will
nouriſh diſcord and faction. But I

                  •
               reſſe not this point, becauſe it is
more Polemicall then Theologicall,
               
                  ••
               tter to bee diſcourſed in Gideons
               
                  •
               ent, then in Moſes chaire.
            Onely for our inſtruction you

                  •
               ee,Note 1. the people content with the Captaine whom God ſet ouer them. the people here are content
with the Captaine, whom God ſet
ouer them, they labour not to ſet vp

                  •
               ny Anti-captaine. They diſpute

                  •
               ot his inexperience or inſufficien
               
                  •
               ie,
as did Nabal to Dauid,
               1 Sam. 25. 10. 1. Sam.
25. Who is Dauid, or who is the ſonne

                     •
                  f Ieſſe? what portion haue wee in Gideon,

                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
or what inheritance in the ſonne
of Ioaſh? but in a holy ſubmiſſion
whatſoeuer he commaunded them,
that they put in practiſe, for the Lord
and for Gideon.
               Where God is honoured, there Gideon will be obeyed. For certainly where
God is honoured there Gideon will be
obeied: where the feare of God is,
there will be reuerence of the Magiſtrate.
There is no Parentheſis betwixt
God and Caeſar in Chriſts
ſpeech: no medium twixt the Lord
and Gideon in the people crie. For
the Lord and for Gideon.
            
            And from theſe two perſons
iointly ariſeth a neceſſarie condition
requiſite to euery warre;
               It is requiſite that euery warre be grounded either on religion to God, or loyaltie to the Magiſtrate vnder God. namely,
that the cauſe be iuſt groundes
either on religion to God or loyaltie
to our Prince. For it is religion that
maketh a man truely valiant; the
righteous are bold as a Lyon.
               Prou. 28. 1. If they
liue, they know by whom they ſtand.
If they die, they know for whoſe
ſake they fall. Hence it is that Thomas requireth three things in the
vndertaking of any warre,Th: Aqu: 2. 2 2ae qu. 40. Art. 1. 
               Authoritas
Principis, cauſa inſta, intentio recto
               
a lawfull commiſſion, a iuſt occaſion,
an vpright intention. Otherwiſe to
wage warre, where a man is not fully
perſwaded of the iuſtneſſe of his
cauſe, be it iuſt or vniuſt, he ſinnes
mortallie, ſaith the Schoole.
            
            Then what ſhall we thinke of all
your Duelliſts,
               Againſt Duelliſts, whoſe combates haue no iuſt ground or warrant. who being priuate
perſons vpon euery triuiall occaſion
will be pointing field: The taking of
the wall, or giuing of a diſgracefull
word is quarrell iuſt enough: as
though either of their honours were
of more worth then both their
ſoules. Such men certainely know
not what it is to liue, and care not
how they die. If there were any feare
of God, or reuerence of man, any
reſpect of life or death, they would
neuer giue themſelues ouer to this
higheſt pitch of madneſſe.
               It is hard to determine in this kinde of quarrells, who eſcapes beſt, whether the partie killing, or party killed. In which
it is hard for a man to determine
who ſcapes beſt, he that killeth or he
that is killed. For a man is preſſed
with an vnanſwerable Dilemma on
both ſides. If he be killed, he hazardeth
with his body his ſoule, becauſe

hee dieth in paſſion and diſtemper.
If he kill hee hazardeth
with his ſoule his body, becauſe hee
fighteth both againſt God and againſt
Gideon. Againſt God, whoſe
image he extinguiſheth, and againſt
Gideon,
               Gen. 4. 10. whoſe law he contemneth.
And therefore both the wrath of
God followes him,Leuit. 24. 17. and the ſword of
Gideon ouertakes him: hee muſt anſwere
it both to the Lord and to Gideon.
And ſo much for the firſt
thing, the parts of the diſtribution,
both for the Lord and for Gideon.
               2. The order of the parts.
            
            Now a word or two of the ſecond
thing, the order of the parts. Firſt
for God and then for Gideon.
               Firſt for God and then for Gideon. And
becauſe for God therefore for Gideon,
becauſe Gideons authoritie is
from God. So then, for the Lord and
for Gideon, that is, ſimply and abſolutely
for God: ſubordinately and
dependantly for Gideon: primarily
for God, and ſecondanlie for Gideon.
            
            A good leſſon for all Souldiers
and militarie men:A threefold caution to Souldiers. to direct them

both in the beginning, continuance,
and end of their battels.
            For the beginning wee muſt firſt
looke to the cauſe of God.
               1 Giue not Gideons cauſe the predominancie before the cauſe o
                     •
                   God. Giue him
the vpper hand: giue his quarrell
the preheminence. Yet is not a ſubiect
alwaies to diſpute whether the cauſe
be iuſt if his Prince commaund, becauſe
he is a Miniſter of the law, not
a Iudge:
               Aug. lib. 21. contra Manichaeos. 
               Belli ſuſceptio penes Principem,
executio penes Militem, ſaith
Auguſtine.
            
            For the continuance of our fight
we muſt take heed of relying more
vpon Gideon then vpon God.
               2. Relie not mor
                     •
                   vpon Gideon then vpon God. Take
heed of truſting to the arme of fleſh
before the outſtretched arme of
God.
               Pſal. 118. 8. 
               It is better to truſt in the Lord,
then to put confidence in Princes, ſaith
the Princely Prophet.
            And laſtly in the end of the fight,3. Aſcribe not more to Gideon then to God.
take we heede of aſcribing more honour
to Gideon then to God. For Gideons
power is from God.
               Rom. 13. 1. 
               Omne
regnum ſub regno eſt.
               Pſal. 82. 1. 
               God is King among
the Gods, Reges in ipſos imperium
eſt Iovis. For euery King is the

Miniſter of God:
               Rom. 13. 4. 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ,
and though they be Gods
with men,Pſal. 82. 6. 7. yet they are but men with
God,
               Reuel. 19. 16. who is Rex regum &amp; Dominus
dominantium, King of kings, and Lord
of lords, Reuel. 19.
            Hence it was that King Henry the
fifth of England,
               The royall and religious diſpoſition of KING Henrie the fifth. that good and valiant
Prince, after his conqueſt in
France would not ſuffer his Helmet,
which was full of blowes and dintes
to bee brought ouer into England
with him, nor to be welcomed home
with any ſongs of the ſucceſſe, but
would haue all the glory aſcribed to
God. Becauſe the key of victorie
God keepeth in his owne power:Pſal. 144. 10. It
commeth neither from the eaſt, nor
from the weſt,
               Pſal. 75. 7. nor from the north,
nor from the ſouth. Vnleſſe God
hold vp his hand, Gideon cannot
preuaile. Not the people without
Gideon, nor Gideon without God. For
the Lord,
               Application of the Text to the Gentlemen aſſembled. 
               and for Gideon.
            
            And now (beloued brethren)
that I haue ripened my diſcourſe and
brought it as it were to a head in it

ſelfe, I come in a word to ſhew you,
how it fitteth and ſuiteth this preſent
ſolemnitie. And therefore for
you Generous Gentlemen and Heroicke
ſpirits, that haue an exemplarie
Campe in your companie, and a
Colledge of Souldiers in your ſocietie:
it will ſerue both as a warrant for
your profeſſion, and an acquittance
againſt all diſcouragement, in that
ye know aſſuredly, in whoſe name,
for what end, to whoſe ſeruice, you
haue dedicated your ſelues and all
your endeuours.Exhortation.
            
            What though ſome goe about to
ſlander your ſocietie,
               To contemne a ſlanders raiſed againſt them. and diſcountenance
your vndertakings, ſpeaking
euill of all becauſe ſome few miſcarrie?
It will be your glory to contemne
the cauill,Prou. 20. 3. and forgiue the wrong, remembring
that he will neuer endure
a blow, who cannot concoct a word:
he is not likely to ouercome an enemie,
who cannot vanquiſh himſelfe:
he is vnfit to fight for equitie, that
hath not learned to paſſe by an iniurie.
But if there be any ſuch diſordered
               
perſons crept in among you,
who are lead with the ſpirit not of
fortitude, but faction; not of conſcience,
but of inſolence; not of zeale,
but ambition; (milites non tam emerti,
quàm malè meriti) expell them
your liſts,
               
                  
                     •
                  o expell all fa
                  
                     •
                  tious ſpirits frō 
                  
                     •
                  mong them. let them not march vnder
your colours,
               
                  
                     •
                   Theſſ. 3. 6. that ſo you may ſtop
the mouthes of your oppoſers, and
open the hearts of men in place
and gouernment to aduance your
intendments, both with countenance
and maintenance, if neede ſo
require.
            In which dutie if they ſhall be
backward, wee may well account
them as baſe and ignoble Caitiffes,
neither good ſeruants of God, nor
truſtie ſubiects of our King, ſeeing
neither in conſcience to the one, nor
allegeance to the other, they will
giue due reſpect, nor lend aſſiſtance
to you, who by your continuall
practiſe (both for Gods ſake and for
Gideons ſake) doe preſerue intemerate
that honourable forme of militarie
diſcipline, which in times of

peace vſeth to grow obſolete and out
of vſe.
            Howſoeuer,To goe on with an vndaunted ſpirit in that honourable exerciſe. goe ye on happily in
your courſes, your memory ſhall ſuruiue
in a ſecond age, and your names
ſhall be had in euerlaſting remembrance,
thoſe that are yet vnborne
ſhall bleſſe you, and bleſſe God for
you. Yet withall be informed that
this your daily exerciſe is but a medium
to a further end, a preparation
to a greater performance. You doe
but now ſpend your paines and your
purſes:
               To prepare for worſe, and harder times. time may require your perſons.
You now vſe rather (fulgentibus
armis quàm fortibus) weapons
defenſiue then offenſiue, and fight gloriouſly
without an enemie: Time
may make triall of your courage in
hotter skirmiſhes, and more bloodie
oppoſition.
            Indeed for the preſent it may be
ſaid of vs,1. King 4. 25. as of Iſrael and Iuda,
1. Kings 4. euery man dwelleth ſafely
vnder his owne vine, and vnder his
owne figtree, there is no leading into
captiuitie,Pſal. 144 14. 
               no complaining in our

ſtreets,
               Pſal. 122. 7. but peace within our walles,
and proſperitie within our palaces.
And long may it bee continued
to vs, to the glory of God, and
quiet of our Nation.
               Wee cannot promiſe to our ſelues perpetuall peace. But wee cannot
promiſe to our ſelues any perpetuitie
of this felicitie; the hideouſneſſe
of our ſinnes may giue
vs good cauſe to expect a change.
Therefore it is your parts to reſerue
your ſelues chiefly for worſe
times, whenſoeuer God ſhall ſend
them; leſt you bee thought like
thoſe doubtfull companions, whom
Diogenes is ſaid to affect in Laertius,
               
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . &amp;c.
that would ſtill bee about
to marry, and yet did not marry;
and that would ſtill be about to
rule, and yet did not rule. (I may
adde) 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               ,
that would ſtill be about to
fight, and yet did not fight.
            Wherefore I ſay no more but as
Saul to Dauid,
               1. Sam. 18. 17. 1. Sam. 18. Be valiant
for your King, and fight the Lords battels:
And as Ioab to the people,1. Sam. 10. 12.
2. Sam. 10. Be of good courage and

play the men for the people and for the
cities of your God.
            
            In the meane time all true Subiects
will pray to the God of peace to
gird you with ſtrength vnto the battell,
               Pſal. 18. 39.
               to teach your hands to warre and
your fingers to fight,
               Pſal. 144. 1. that ſo being
well appointed,Epheſ. 6. 11. both with the ſpirituall
armour of a Chriſtian, and the
corporeall armour of a Souldier (intus
fide,
               Bern. ſer. ad mil. tem. cap. 4. 
               foris ferro muniti) you may be
able both to defend your ſelues againſt
the ſiege of Sathan, and your
Country againſt all forraine inuaſions,
and I doubt not but all true-hearted
Subiects will ſay Amen.
            
            Wherefore wee humbly beſeech
thee O Lord God of Hoſts,
               Pſal. 80. 14. 
               looke downe
from heauen, and behold and viſit this
vine, and the vineyard which thy right
hand hath planted amongſt vs. Let
not the Bore out of the wood deſtroy it,
nor the wilde Beaſts of the field eat it
vp, but forgiue the crying ſinnes of
the ſame, remoue thy iudgements that
hang ouer vs,Luk. 19. 42. and teach vs to know
the things which belong vnto our peace.
               
And becauſe there is none other
that fighteth for vs but only thou O
God, pleade our cauſe (O Lord) with
them that ſtriue with vs; and fight
againſt them that fight againſt vs. And
thou that art a man of warre, whoſe
name is Ichonah,
               
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                oh teach our hands
to warre and out fingers to fight,
               
                  
                     •
                  ſal. 144. 
                     •
                  . that
the Heathen may neuer come into
thine inheritance,
               
                  
                     •
                  ſal. 79. 1. and make this our
Ieruſalem an heape of ſtones, but that
thou maiſt ſtill bleſſe vs with peace
within our walles and proſperitie within
our palaces,
               
                  
                     •
                  ſal. 122. 7. while the Sunne and the
Moone endureth. Theſe things we
begge at thy hands in the name of
thy beloued Sonne and our bleſſed
Sauiour, to whom with thee and the
holy Spirit be aſcribed all praiſe,
honour, and glory, now
and for euermore.
Amen.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

