
   
      
         
            A premonition for euery disposition published for the profit of all if it be well applied / by Charles Gybbon.
            Gibbon, Charles, fl. 1589-1604.
         
         
            
               1588
            
         
         Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01681
            STC 11819.5
            ESTC S3028
            29701171
            ocm 29701171
            28088
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01681)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28088)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1861:50)
         
         
            
               
                  A premonition for euery disposition published for the profit of all if it be well applied / by Charles Gybbon.
                  Gibbon, Charles, fl. 1589-1604.
               
               1 sheet ([1] p.).   
               
                  Printed by I.C. for Thomas Gubbin,
                  At London :
                  Anno Dom. 1588.
               
               
                  Reproduction of original in the Society of Antiquaries.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Bible --  Use.
               Christian life.
               Broadsides --  London (England) --  16th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-10
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-01
            Emma (Leeson) HuberSampled and proofread
         
            2008-01
            Emma (Leeson) HuberText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
               ❧A premonition for euery diſpoſition:
Publiſhed for the profit of all if it be well applied.
By Charles Gybbon.
            
               ❧ TO THE READER
            Art thou 
                  Jnſolent, or ignorant of thy eſtate,
                  Jnticed, or enclined to euill,
                  Jntangled, or ouercome of euill.
                beholde 
                  Thy apparant miſerie.
                  Gods pronounced iudgment.
                  Gods promiſed mercie.
                And it may 
                  Humble thee in preſuming.
                  Terrifie thee in attempting.
                  Comfort thee in diſpayring.
               
            
            
               A Mappe of mans miſerie.
               
                  I know mine owne wickednes, and my ſinne
is euer before me.
                  
                     Pſal. 51. 3.
               
               
                  
                     WHat is man, whereto ſerueth he? 
                     Ecclus, 18, 6
                  
                  
                     He is like a thing of naught. 
                     Pſalme, 144, 4
                  
                  
                     He is made of the duſt of the ground. 
                     Gene, 2, 7,
                  
                  
                     He is ſhapen in wickednes and conceiued in ſinne.
                     Pſalm, 51, 5,
                  
                  
                     He is by nature the Childe of wrathe. 
                     Ephe, 2, 3,
                  
                  
                     He is by his owne knowledge but a beaſt. 
                     Iere, 51, 7,
                  
                  
                     He cannot of himſelfe thinke a good thought. 
                     2, Cor, 3,
                  
                  
                     The earth was curſed for his ſinne. 
                     Gene, 3, 17,
                  
                  
                     Dum creatures are deſtroyed for his cauſe. 
                     Zeph. 1. 3
                  
                  
                     It repented the Lord that he had made man. 
                     Gene, 6, 6,
                  
                  
                     He is borne vnto trauaill as the ſparks flie vpwarde.
                     Iob. 5, verſe 7,
                  
                  
                     His dayes are ſorrowes and his trauaile greefe.
                     Eccles, 2, 23,
                  
                  
                     His glory is but dunge and wormes. 
                     1, Mala, 2, 62
                  
                  
                     His helpe is but vaine. 
                     Pſalm, 60, 11,
                  
                  
                     His time is like the ſhaddowe vpon the earth.
                     1, Chro, 29, 15,
                  
                  
                     His life is but a ſpanne long. 
                     Pſal. 39, 6,
                  
                  
                     When he hath doone his beſt he is but an vnprofitable
Seruaunt. 
                     Luke, 17, 10,
                  
               
            
            
               A Mirror of Gods iustice.
               
                  If thou ô Lorde ſtraightly markeſt iniquities
who ſhalbe ſaued.
                  
                     Pſal. 130. 3.
               
               
                  
                     IT is a feareful thing to fall into ye hands of God. 
                     Heb. 10,
                  
                  
                     As his mercy is great ſo is his puniſhmēt. 
                     Ecclus, 16, 12
                  
                  
                     He is a great God mighty and terrible. 
                     Deu, 10, 17,
                  
                  
                     He is a God of reuenge. 
                     Deut, 32, 35
                  
                  
                     He is able to caſt both body and ſoule into hell. 
                     Math, 10
                  
                  
                     If a man ſinne againſt the Lord who ſhall pleade for him.
                     1, Sam, 2, 25,
                  
                  
                     Vengeance belongeth vnto me, I will recompence (ſayth
the Lorde) 
                     Deut. 32, 35,
                  
                  
                     Euery mā ſhal haue reward according to his work. 
                     Ap. 22
                  
                  
                     The reward of ſinne is death. 
                     Rom, 6, 23
                  
                  
                     He that committeth ſinne is of the deuill. 
                     1, Ioh, 3, 8
                  
                  
                     The face of the Lord is againſt ſuch as doo euill.
                     1, Pet, 3, 12,
                  
                  
                     There ſhalbe no end of plagues to the euil man. 
                     Pro, 24, 20
                  
                  
                     He ſpared not the Angels that had ſinned, but caſt them in
to vtter darknes. 
                     2, Pet, 2, 4,
                  
                  
                     He deſtroyed Kings for all they be as Gods vpon the
earth. 
                     Acts, 12, 23,
                  
                  
                     He puniſhed rich men for all they had the welth of thys
worlde. 
                     Luke, 16, 23,
                  
                  
                     For with him is no reſpect of perſons. 
                     Act, 10, 34,
                  
               
            
            
               A mention of his mercie.
               
                  According to the multitude of thy mercies put
away mine iniquities.
                  
                     Pſal. 51. 1.
               
               
                  
                     IT is better to fall into the handes of God then of men, (for his mercies are great.)
                     2, Sam, 24, 14
                  
                  
                     As his greatnes is ſo is his mercie. 
                     Ecclus, 2, 21,
                  
                  
                     He is a gratious God and a mercifull. 
                     Micha, 4, 2
                  
                  
                     He is a God of patience and conſolation. 
                     Rom, 15, 5
                  
                  
                     He is rich in mercie. 
                     Ephe, 2, 4,
                  
                  
                     His mercy is aboue all his works. 
                     Pſalm, 145, 9,
                  
                  
                     He is ready to forgiue. 
                     Eſay, 55, 7,
                  
                  
                     Before they cry I will heare, and whilſt they are yet thinking
what to ſpeake I wil anſwer (ſaith ye lord) 
                     Eſa, 65, 25
                  
                  
                     He taketh no pleſure in the death of ſinners. 
                     Ezech, 18, 32
                  
                  
                     He maketh as though hee ſawe not the ſinnes of men, becauſe
they ſhould amende. 
                     Wyſd, 11, 20
                  
                  
                     He ſent his own ſon to cal ſinners to repentance. 
                     Mat, 9, 13
                  
                  
                     Though ſin aboundeth, grace ſuperaboundeth. 
                     Rom, 5, 15
                  
                  
                     He pardoned Dauid for all he had commiteed both whoredome
and murther. 
                     2, Sam, 12, 13
                  
                  
                     He receiued the prodigall ſon into fauor againe. 
                     Luk, 15, 22
                  
                  
                     He receiued the theefe into Paradiſe for all hee was a moſt
haynous malefactor. 
                     Luke. 23. 43
                  
                  
                     For at what time a ſinner doth hartily repent him, ye Lorde
hath promiſed to forgiue him. 
                     Ezech. 18. 21. 22.
                  
               
            
            
               Our life we leade Gods lawes to learne, with will to do the ſame:
               We read to know, and know to liue, and liue to prayſe Gods name.
            
            
               
                  ❧A caueat for Rich-men:
Be rich in Faith.
               ¶To the ende you may vſe and beſtowe your goods to your owne
good, and his glory that gaue them, conſider of theſe ſentences
pronounced againſt ſuch as abuſe
them. And
               Amongſt others, reade
                     Eſay, chap. 5. verſe. 8.
                     Amos, chap. 8. verſe. 4.
                     Iames. chap. 5. verſe. 1.
                    
                  Like Sheepe they lye in
graue, Death deuoureth
them. 
                  Pſalm. 49. 14.
               
               
                  ¶Speciall cauſes to dehort you from ſuch greedines in gathering,
and griplenes in keeping your goods.
                  1. The deſire of money is the roote of all euill. 
                     1. Tim. 6. 10.
                  
                  2. A mans life ſtandeth not in his goods though he haue aboundance. 
                     Luk. 12. 15
                  
                  3. When he dieth he ſhall carrie nothing awaie with him. 
                     Pſalm. 49. 14. 17
                  
                  4. His goods will not auaile him in the day of wrath. 
                     Prou. 11. 4.
                  
               
               
                  ¶Hauing goods, you ought to giue and doo good with
them, partlie to this ende.
                  1. For the glorie of GOD. Honour GOD with thy riches. 
                     Prouerbs. 3. 9.
                  
                  2. For good example to others. Let your light ſo ſhine before men that they may ſée your good works. Math. 5. 16.
                  
                  3. For a ſigne of the ſinceritie of your proſeſſion.
                  A good Trée bringeth forth good fruite. Math. 7. 18. Iames. 2. 18.
                  
               
               If you would knowe
to whom you ſhoulde
giue, reade 
                     Iob, chap. 31. verſe, 16.
                     Eſay, chap. 58. verſe, 7,
                     Luke, chap. 14. verſe, 13.
                  
                  Zacheus gaue the one
halfe of his goods to ye poore.
Luke. 19. verſe 8.
               
               Why you ought to
giue to the poore. 
                     Becauſe God hath commaunded ye ſhould giue. Deu. 15. 10.
                     
                     Giue to the poore for commaundement ſake. Ecclus. 29. 9.
                     
                     Becauſe hee hath made them as his inſtruments to trye
your harts &amp; charitie, as appeareth. Deu. 15. 11. Mat. 26. 11
                     
                  
               
               Howe you ought to
beſtowe your beneuolence.
It muſt be doone 
                     Simply.
                     Chéerfully.
                     Liberally.
                  
                  
                     For GOD loueth no vaine oſtentation.
Math. 6. 2.
                     
                     For he loueth a chéerful giuer. Ecclꝰ. 35. 10
                     
                     For it is a plague to a rich man to want
a liberall hart. Eccles. 6. 1. 2. &amp;c.
                     
                  
               
               
                  ¶What good inſueth in giuing to the poore.
                  1. He that giueth to thē lendeth to ye lord. Pro. 19. 17. and ſhal not lack. Pro. 20. 27
                  
                  2. He layeth vp a good ſtore for himſelfe againſt the day of neceſſity. Tob, 4, 9.
                  
                  3. He ſhall haue great reward in heauen. Math. 25. 40.
                  
               
               
                  ¶What hurt followeth by with-holding from ſuch.
                  1. He that hideth his eyes from them ſhall haue manie curſes. Pro. 28. 27.
                  
                  2. If they curſe thée in ye bitternes of their ſoule their praier ſhalbe heard. Ecclꝰ. 4
                  
                  3. He that ſtoppeth his eare at their cry, ſhall cry and not be heard. Pro. 21. 13.
                  
                  4. He that ſheweth no mercy, ſhall haue mercileſſe condemnation. Iam. 2. 13.
                  
               
               
                  ¶Therfore do good whilſt ye may, remembring this ſaying.
                  
                     What ſhall it aduantage a man to winne the whole world, and afterward looſe his owne ſoule. 
                     Luke. 9. 25.
                  
               
            
            
               
                  ❧A comfort for Poore-men:
Be poore in Spyrite.
               ¶To the ende thou maiſt beare thy poouerty more patientlie,
enter into this conſideration.
               
                  1. Haſt thou not a houſe
to hold thy head in. Our Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe had not wheron to reſt
his head. Math. 8. 20.
                  
                  2. Haſt thou little
foode or rayment. Paule ſuffered hunger &amp; cold, &amp; yet (ſaith he) I haue learned
in whatſoeuer ſtate I am in, therwith to be cōtent. Phil. 4.
                  
                  3. Haſt thou any
thing at all. Solomon ſaith, better is a little with the feare of GOD, then
great treaſure and trouble therewith. Prou. 15. 16.
                  
                  4. Haſt thou nothing
at all. Dauid ſaith, he that ſeeketh the Lord ſhall lack no manner of
thing that is good. 
                        Pſalm. 34. 10.
                  
                  5. Haſt thou a fewe croſſes
and cares in this worlde. We muſt by many enter the kingdome of heauen.
Acts. 14. 22.
                  
                  6. Haſt thou many miſeries
&amp; afflictions. All that wee ſuffer héere are not counted woorthy the
glory of the life to come. Rom. 8. 18.
                  
               
               Thy pouerty
may be laide
vpon thée 
                     For trial of thy faith &amp; patience,
                     For thyne amendement.
                  As it
was vppon 
                     Iob. Iob. 1.
                     
                     The prodigall ſon.
                  
               
               
                  ¶Seeing pouertie and riches come of God, vſe theſe
three things in thy extremitie.
                  1. Prayer. Not to diſpayre of
Gods prouidence. For he is faithful, &amp; wil lay no more vpon thée
thē he will make thee able to beare. 1. Cor. 10. 13.
                  
                  2. Patience. to take thy croſſe
thankfully. For it is an eaſie thing in his ſight, ſuddainlye to
make a poore man rich. Ecclus. 11. 21.
                  
                  3. Labor. to get thy liuing
if it be poſſible. For better it were to die thē beg. Ecclꝰ. 40. 28 and it is
a bleſſed thing to giue rather then receiue. Act. 20. 35.
                  
               
               
                  ¶If thou dooſt conſider what inconueniences and euils be incident,
and come oftentimes with proſperitie and riches, thou wouldeſt
be better contented with thy poore eſtate.
                  
                     Dauid ſayde in his proſperitie hée ſhould not be mooued. Pſalm. 30. 6.
                  
                  Riches
often
times 
                        Withdraw vs frō wel dooing.
                        Mooue vs to ſecuritie.
                        Be the meanes of our miſerie.
                      as appeare
by the parble
of 
                        The yong man. Mar. 10.
                        
                        The rich man. Luk. 12.
                        
                        Diues and Lazarus.
                     
                  
                  Héerof it is ſaid. A rich man ſhall hardly enter the kingdom of heauen. Mat. 19. 23.
                  
               
               
                  ¶Therefore comfort thy ſelfe with theſe conſolations, remembring
this ſaying:
                  
                     Godlines is great riches if a man be content with that he hath.
                      1. Tim. 6. 6.
                  
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
               AT LONDON
Printed by I. C. for Thomas Gubbin. Anno. Dom. 1588.
            
         
      
   

