
   
      
         
            The order of equalitie Contriued and diuulged as a generall directorie for common sessements. Seruing for the indifferent defraying, taxing, and rating of common impositions and charges, lyable to citties, townes, or villages, that they may be done in some equall and proportionable order, for the benefit of the common-wealth. Very necessarie for all persons, to whome the execution and apprehension of this businesse appertaine.
            Gibbon, Charles, fl. 1589-1604.
         
         
            
               1604
            
         
         Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01679
            STC 11817
            ESTC S116511
            99851727
            99851727
            17018
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01679)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17018)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1306:12)
         
         
            
               
                  The order of equalitie Contriued and diuulged as a generall directorie for common sessements. Seruing for the indifferent defraying, taxing, and rating of common impositions and charges, lyable to citties, townes, or villages, that they may be done in some equall and proportionable order, for the benefit of the common-wealth. Very necessarie for all persons, to whome the execution and apprehension of this businesse appertaine.
                  Gibbon, Charles, fl. 1589-1604.
               
               [6], 32 p.   
               
                  Printed by Iohn Legat, printer to the Vniversitie of Cambridge, 1604. And are to be sold at the signe of the Crowne in Pauls Churchyard [London] by Simon Waterson,
                  [Cambridge] :
                  [1604]
               
               
                  Place of publication from STC.
                  "To the Reader" signed: C. Gibbon.
                  Identified as STC 11817a on UMI microfilm.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Taxation --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-01
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-01
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-08
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-08
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE ORDER
OF EQƲALITIE.
Contriued and diuulged as a generall
Directorie for common Seſſements.
Seruing for the indifferent defraying, taxing,
and rating of common Impoſitions and charges, lyable to
Citties, Townes, or Villages, that they may be done in
ſome equall and proportionable Order, for
the benefit of the common-wealth.
Very neceſſarie for all perſons, to whome the
execution and apprehenſion of this buſineſſe
appertaine.
1. CORINTH. 14. 40.
               Let all things be done honeſtly and by order.
               
                  HINC . LVCEM . ET . POCVLA .  SACRA
                  ALMA MATER CANTA BRIGIA
                
            
            PRINTED BY IOHN LEGAT, PRINTER TO
the Vniverſitie of Cambridge, 1604.
And are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Crowne in Pauls Churchyard
by Simon Waterſon.
            
         
         
            
            
            TO ALL IVDICIALL
and indifferent Readers.
            
               IT was no meruaile that the heathen man Xenophon
willed euerie one aequalitatem colere, to honour equalitie,
ſeeing it ſerueth ſo much to the commending
of a ciuill life, to the managing of common affaires,
to the conſeruing of popular vnitie, which is
ſo excellent in compariſon, ſo generall in comprehenſion,
ſo neceſſarie in all actions, that no Common wealth can doe well
without it: yet ſuch is the error of this age, that more are readie to
confeſſe then to expreſſe this equalitie in any of their actions.
            There is no common weale can flouriſh without impoſition of charges:
for they are as neceſſarie, ſaith Plato, as arteries or ſinewes to
the bodie, but inequalitie in the ſeſſing and rating of theſe charges is
but an enemie to a Commonwealth: for they are as ill as prickes or
thornes to the bodie, euerie one is willing to beare charge reſpectiuely
to his portion, but who can indure to be ſurcharged in no equall proportion
to others? there is a fit inſtance in one Aemilius appliable to
this purpoſe; who beeing complained of vnto Tyberius Caeſar for vnequall
taxations he impoſed vpon the people, T. Caeſar returned this
anſwer, Se tondere velle ſuas oues non deglubere, that he would
haue him to ſheare his ſheepe, but not to flea them. Bruſon: this ſaying
is worthy to be obſerued of all ſeſſors, to deale indifferently without
extremitie, and equally without partialitie in common wealth caſes:
ſeeing vnequall rates vnder the title of vnrighteouſneſſe is ſaid to be
abhomination, as well as vniuſt weights and meaſures, Deut. 25. 16.
            As ſinne is aggrauated by circumſtances, ſo is that iniquitie of inequalitie:
for to deale vnequally in priuate callings, is not tollerable,
but to vſe inequalitie in publike caſes is farre more deteſtable, becauſe
the iniurie is more generall, as the Schoolemen ſay, quanto iniquitas
in plures extenditur tanto grauius peccat, the ſinne is the
greater the more it is extended and diſperſed: and therefore ſuch as
are taken therein tardie, ipſo facto, in the deede doing, or, as the Civilians
tearme it, in flagr
                     •
                  nti crimine, in the apparent fault, are to
be puniſhed exempli cauſa, if it were but for example ſake, that i
                  •
               
might reſtraine the reſt, according to the old Canon, Vt vnius poena
               
               metus fit multorum, That the puniſhment of one might be a terror
to many; and to this ende S. Paul ſaith, Them that ſinne rebuke
openly, that the reſt alſo may feare, 1. Tim. 4. 20. for amongſt
many ſinners ſome muſt be made examples.
            There is no man doubtes but that inequalitie hath ſome intercourſe
and continuall current in common ſeſſments, ſome that cannot
ſee into it, ſuffer it, others that are fauoured in it, wincke at it,
thoſe that are wronged in it, murmure at it, howſoeuer it be, they
muſt with patience take this pill of Virgill omnis fortuna ſuperanda
ferendo, learne to ſuffer that they cannot remedie. For this
cauſe hauing ſome obiectes of inequalities offered to my eyes, I could
not forbeare my pen without impietie, conſidering that mellifluous
Father ſaith, eſt conſentire ſilere cum arguere poſſis, to be ſecret
where one may ſay ſomething is a ſinne in conſent, and to conceale
veritie eſt aurum ſepelire is no better then to burie gould, as Enagrius
ſaith.
            I ſpleane no mans perſon but his vnequall proceedings, I inuey not
againſt common impoſitions and charges, but againſt vnequall proportion
in the taxing, I ayme not at any one man; becauſe I ſpeaks
generally to all, and it is a principle in all artes, He that ſpeakes generallie
ſpeakes to none▪ when Dauid heard the generall report of
the parable; the delinquent (ſaith he) ſhall die the death; he litle
thought it concerned himſelfe, vntill Nathan told him he was the
man. When Iudah heard the common clamor againſt Thamar; let
her be burnt, ſaith he, he did not ſuſpect himſelfe to be criminall, vntill
Thamar ſhewed him his ring, his cloke and his ſtaffe. Gen. 38. ſo
by theſe examples we may perceiue, that generall ſpeeches can detect
none vnleſſe he be named, though they may touch any if they be tainted
with guilt.
            Such as be galled may take reformation by this and conceale it:
for I cannot ſaie he is the man; ſuch as be not guiltie may take information
by this, to continue ſo; for it is rare to ſee ſuch a man, notwithſtanding
it is pittie that ſo common an euill as inequalitie which
by cuſtome is made no ſinne▪ ſhould be teſt vp and downe from one to an
other like a tennys ball, and paſſe without any check or reproofe: the
fowles of the aire will bewray. Eccles. 10. 20. the ſtones in the wall
will crie out. Haba. 2. 11. nay the very dumb beaſt will ſpeake rather
then ſinne ſhould paſſe vnreprooued. 2. Pet. 2. 16.
            The greateſt workes are ſometime wrought by the weakeſt inſtruments,

as Goliah was ſlaine by à litle ſtone with á ſlinge, when no
cumbatant durſt incounter with him, and as the Elephant is ſaid to
be afrighted at the grunting of à pigge, ſo men may ſometime be terrified
and reclamed by mere trifles, and made true penitentes by the
daſh of à penne, as Peter was ſtroke with ſorrowe at the crowing of
the cocke.
            I deſire nothing but that my penne may be as à pricke to the hartes
of the guiltie to ſee their faults, and that my praier may be as à
meane to haue their hartes opēed with Lydia to amend their faults:
ſo God ſhall be much glorified by their conuerſion, the Agents more
eſteemed by their actions, and the Author well ſatisfied for his
paines.
            C. Gibbon.
         
         
            
            THE CONTENTS OR
cheife heads handled in this Treatiſe, as the ſame are
diſtributed into 12. Chapters.
            
               1 Of the ſignification and ſundrie acceptions of the word Equalitie.
               2 Of the excellencie of equalitie.
               3 Of the generalitie of equalitie.
               4 Of the neceſſitie of equalitie.
               5 What equalitie is, as it extendeth to common impoſitions and
charges.
               6 What charge ſignifieth, that they muſt be neceſſarie, with deſcription
of ſuch neceſſarie charges.
               7 What is meant by impoſition of charge, and wherein they differ
from voluntarie charges.
               8 Of equall proportion, how it is to be taken, properly, comparatiuely,
and reſpectiuely, and that euerie one is to be rated properly
in ſome equalitie to his abilitie, according to nationall
cuſtomes.
               9 That euery one is to be taxed comparatiuely in ſome equall proportion
agreeable to generall taxations.
               10 That euery one is to be charged reſpectiuely, according to the
qualitie of the ſeſſement, whether it be lands or goods.
               11 The probable cauſes and coniectures why men are ſo vnequally
rated in common impoſitions and charges repugnant to generall
proportions.
               12 What perſons are lyable and ought to be taxed towards common
impoſitions and charges.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            THE ORDER OF
Equalitie.
            
               CHAP. 1.
               Of the Signification and ſundrie Acceptions of the word
Equalitie.
               
                  EQVALL is not vnfitly deriued of
aequus right or iuſt, to ſignifie that there
can be no equitie without equalitie, in
this ſenſe it is taken in the ſcripture, doe
that which is iuſt and equall Colloſ. 4. 1.
which wordes are but voces cōuertibiles:
for the copulatiue (and) doth ſhew that
they accord in ſenſe though they differ
in ſound, and that like relatiues one cannot be well without an
other.
               To be equall, doth import aſmuch as to be euen, it is ſo accepted
in Gen. 44. 18. where Iudah perceiuing the dignitie &amp;
deportment of his brother Ioſeph, ſaid by way of inſinuation to
him, thou art euen as Pharaoh, intending thereby that he was equall
in authoritie to him, as it is well quoted in the marginall
note thereupon.
               It is common amongſt the Latines as they terme it euphoniae
gratia for the better ſound to contract two wordes into one,
as for equall qualitie, to ſaie aequalitas, and for equall abilitie to
ſaie aequabilitas, which wordes although they be confounded in
our common ſpeech and are taken promiſcuè one for an other,
yet they ſomewhat diſſent in ſignification.
               Equalitie is ſo called of aequali qualitate of equall qualitie;
becauſe it hath ſpeciall reference to qualities and conditions,
and therefore the word is taken ſometime for vnitie, ſometime
for paritie or likenes.
               Equalitie is taken for vnitie, when many are of one mutuall
conſent, they are ſaid to be Monanthropos, one man, as it was
ſaid of the Iſraelites in Iudg. 20. 10. they were knit together as
one man, &amp; ſo in affections, when many are of mutuall mindes

they are ſaid to be vnaenimi, knit together in one minde as the
Apoſtle phraiſeth it. 1. Cor. 1. 10. according to that which is
ſaid of the beleeuing companie in the Acts. 4. 32. they were
of one heart and of one ſoule.
               
               Equalitie is ſometime taken for à paritie or likenes: when
the Apoſtle would haue vs to be equally affected, he willeth
vs to be like minded one to another. Rom. 15. 5. &amp; not to beare
the proud mind of the inſulting Phariſe to ſaie, I am not like
others, or the ambitious mind of Pompey to admit none to
be his equall, but as we are taught to make our ſelues equall to
them of the lower ſort, Rom. 12. 16. (not in titles and degrees
as ſome vrge equalitie, or in poſſeſſions or goodes as many
pretend community where God hath put à difference) but in
lowlines of mind, as one commentes vpon that place, by imitating
him which ſaith, learne of me I am meeke and lowly: Math.
11. 29.
               Equabilitie is ſo called of aequali habilitate, of equall abilitie;
becauſe it doth moſt properly extend to Abilities by the naturall
etymologie of the word.
               What Ability &amp; Non-abilitie is in our common lawes, I will
omit, but in the ſcriptures it is moſt commonly takē for à temporall
ſtate of liuing, to ſignifie that as there ought to be an vnity
in profeſſion, an vnanimitie in affection, a ſympathy in affliction,
ſo there ought to be an equalitie in outward affaires,
that where mē are of equabilitie or equall value in abilitie, they
ſhould be equiualent in all good actions; both by the preſcript
rule of God. Let euery one miniſter according to his abilitie. 1.
Pet 4. 11. and by preſident in the godly, we according to our
abilities doe. Neh. 5. 8.
               Thus in ſome tranſparent ſort I haue giuen ſome light and
introduction to the matter: for by the ſundry acceptions of
the word you may ſee that to be euen, all one, equall, &amp; like, are
but ſynonomies or wordes of like ſenſe and ſignification, and
by the deriuation of the word you may perceiue the ſignification
of the ſubiect: for as in the beginning Adam gaue names agreeable
to the nature of euery creature, ſo in the firſt inuention
of wordes Etymologicians gaue denomination according to the
ſignificatiō of euery word, which might be deriued from ſome
language by exquiſite linguiſtes, although now where we want

reaſon to deriue a word, we are inforced to call it primitiue.
               For as much as this is no probleme or diſputable queſtion
to controuert, before I enter into the definition and diuiſion of
this ſubiect, I will firſt (omitting the order of diſputants) illuſtrate
and ſet forth the excellencie, generalitie, and neceſſitie
thereof, that it may appeare to be a fit argument for this age, as
an inſtigation to mooue euery one to make more care and conſcience
of equalitie in all their actions.
            
            
               Chap. 2.
               Of the Excellencie of Equalitie.
               TO beginne with him, who gaue beginning to all, and yet
is without beginning himſelfe, if we enter into that metaphyſicall
and diuine miſterie of the Deitie, there appeares to be
an apparent vnion of equalitie: for though there be a trinitie in
perſōs, there is an vnitie and equalitie in godhead, although the
father is ſaid to be greater, Ioh. 14. 28. then the ſonne, as he was
man.
               In the firſt creation of man, he was a kind of Microcoſme or
little world, not becauſe he is circular or ſphericall, as the Philoſophers
hold, but for that there was ſome likeneſſe and ſimilitude
of the Creator reſplendent in the creature, for it is ſaid,
Let vs make man to our owne image and likeneſſe: behold (ſaith god)
the man is become as one of vs, Gen. 3. 22. Yet none muſt hereby
thinke himſelfe equall to God as Tyrus did, Ezech. 28. 6. leaſt
he become a beaſt, as Nabuchadnezzar was: for God can indure
no equall vpon earth, To whome will you compare or make
me equall? ſaith God, Iſaiah, 46. 5.
               In the Redemption of mankind, he which was deified and
equall with God, did vouchſafe to be homified, by aſſuming
vpon him, the very fleſh and forme of man, by participating
with man in eating, drinking, ſleeping, talking, walking, beeing
paſſible as man, in hungring, thirſting, watching, weeping; in a
word, he was equall to man in all things ſauing ſinne, as Ioſeph
was to Pharaoh, ſauing the ſcepter.
               In the dignifying of man, God did not onely impart to him
his owne image in puritie of minde, and impoſe humane ſhape

in habite of his perſon, but he doeth further grace and adorne
him with his owne equall titles, by tearming of him a God, eſt
animata imago Dei, as one ſaith, he is the liuely image of God:
for as Lactantius ſaith, though he be but a man before God,
yet he is a God amongeſt men: it was this that made the Egyptians
affirme that man was a terreſtriall God; but yet leaſt he
ſhould haue too ſublimious a conceit of his ſingularitie, it is not
amiſſe to remember what the Cynicall perſon ſaid to Alexander,
though he were a God vpon earth, yet he was but a God
of earth; and as the Phoenix beeing bred of aſhes doth burne to
aſhes, ſo he beeing made of earth muſt yeild to earth.
               In the Diſſolution of man, god doeth ſtill grace him with
his ſmall glorie: for if he dieth well, he will deuide his glorie to
him: Haman thought it was the greateſt honour to man in
this life, to haue the kings royall apparrell put vpon him; to
ride vpon his owne horſe, and to haue his crowne ſet vpon his
head, Eſter, 6. 8. then howe great glorie is it to man in the life to
come, to be made like him that is moſt glorious? 1. Ioh. 3. 2. to
ſit vpon the throne with him that ſhall iudge vs? Apoc. 3. 21. &amp;
to be partaker both of a crowne and a kingdome?
               In the taking of Eue from Adam there is ſhewed a coequalitie
betweene man and woman; for they were equall euery
way vntill the ſinne made man her ſuperiour, and therefore
ſubiection was one part of her puniſhment, as may appeare in
Gen. 3. 16.
               In the eſtates of men although they be different in reſpect
of proſperitie and pouertie, yet God hath ſhewed therein an
excellent patterne of parilitie: for if he had made all rich, one
would not care for another▪ if all poore, one could not helpe
another; ſo that rich and poore haue neede one of another, 2.
Cor. 8. 14.
               In the Regiment of a common wealth, God hath ordained
equalitie amongſt many vnequalls: for if all were Rulers, then
it were monſtrous, for one head is enough for one bodie, as
one ſunne is ſufficient for the whole world. If there were no
ruler, then were it confuſed, as it is ſaid of the Iſraelites when
they were without a King, euery man did that which was good
in his owne eies, Iudg. 17. 6. for in extremities it is better to haue
a tyrant (as the heathen man ſaith) then no ruler: and therefore

for one to Rule and the reſt to obey is the onely ſquare of equalitie.
               What ſhould I ſpeake more of equalitie? ſeeing it is of ſuch
excellencie that the very Ethnickes did honour equalitie, becauſe
it doeth combine the good with the good, ſaith Xenophon,
and doth conſerue cities in tranquilitie, ſaith Ariſtotle,
2. polit. whereas inequalitie is ſaid to be ſeditionis ſeminarium,
the verie ſeed of ſedition, as Plutarke tearms it. To end all with
this epiphonema, ſeeing equalitie is deitatis Idea, the expreſſe
Idea of the indiuiſible Deitie in heauen, and vnitatis cauſa, the
inſtrumentall cauſe of vniuerſall vnitie vpon earth, what is of
greater excellencie then equalitie?
            
            
               Chap. 3.
               Of the Generalitie of Equalitie.
               IN the olde lawe Lex talionis was ordained to no other ende,
but that an euill action might haue an equall puniſhment, as
an eie for an eie, a tooth for a tooth, life for life; the validitie of
which lawe is in ſome caſes yet recent amongſt vs: for by our
poſitiue lawe, he that of malice prepenſed taketh away another
mans life, looſeth his owne life.
               It is commonly ſeene in this life that where the parents care
not howe they gather their goods togither with the rake, the
children care not howe they caſt them abroad with the forke,
ſo that olde ſaying is iuſtly verified, goods euill gotten are euill
ſpent. Hemingius reports a thing of his owne experience, of
one that was capax, rapax, and tenax in getting of his goods by
oppreſſion, he afterward left them to his children, who plaid
the prodigal ſonnes, and went vp and downe a begging: ſo true
it is, ex male quaeſitis non gaudet tertius haeres, that the third heire
ſhall neuer come to inioy them▪ Such therefore as by extorting
and griping make a gaine, ſhould doe well to remember non
male lucreris, mala lucra aequalia damna, that their euill lucre will
haue equall loſſe, ſometime or other.
               It is a generall note in the ſcriptures, that malum culpae and
malum poenae haue commonly concourſe togither in ſome equall
proportion betweene the malefactor and the miſdeede,

according to that olde verſe, Qualia vir faciet tali quoque fine
peribit, that which a man practiſeth to others, he ſhall periſh by
himſelfe; whereof there are many examples in the ſcriptures.
Pharaoh cauſed the children to be caſt into the riuer, he himſelfe
was ouercome in the red ſea. Haman made a gallowes to
hang Mordecai, he himſelfe was hanged on the ſame gallowes:
the Rulers cauſed Daniel to be caſt into the denne of Lyons,
they themſelues were deuoured with the Lyons. Adoni-bezek
did cut of the thumbs and the feete of ſeauentie Kings, he himſelfe
had his thumbes and feete cut off by others, Iudg. 1. 6. The
prodigall ſonne becauſe he liued in filthineſſe like a ſwine, he
did afterward eate huskes with the ſwine.
               It is the iudgment of the Almightie in the life to come, to inflict
equall puniſhment according to the qualitie of the delinquent,
and that may be probably collected out of Eſay, 26. 17.
where it is ſaid, Iudgement will I lay to the Rule, and righteouſnes
to the Ballance. By the Rule is vnderſtood the euen meaſure
that ſhall be betweene the partie and the puniſhment: and by
the Ballance is ſignified, the equal weight that ſhall be betweene
the torment and the ſinner, according to that ſaying
in the Apocalyps, 18. 7. For as much as ſhee (meaning the Babylonian
whore) hath glorified her ſelfe, and liued in pleaſure,
ſo much giue her torment and ſorrowe. We read that Diues
becauſe he would not giue Lazarus a crumme of bread to
quench his hunger vpon earth, he himſelfe could not haue a
droppe of water to coole his tongue in hell.
               To come to a more generall and vniuerſall inſtance of equalitie,
though Pompey would ſuffer none to be his ſuperior
amongeſt men, though Tyrus affirmed that he was a God, Ezech.
28. 2. though Nabuchadnezzar exalted himſelfe aboue
God, though Kings are as gods vpon earth; yet howeſoeuer
men differ in humors and affections, or in degrees or dignities
in this world, if they come to this memento, to conſider in man,
that his creation is of earth, his diſſolution is to earth, his reſurrection
is from earth; may not euery one ſay, he is conceiued
in ſinne with Dauid? he is a miſerable ſinner with the
Publican? he is the greateſt ſinner with Paul? 1. Tim. 1. 15. Is
not God father to vs all by faith? Sauiour to vs all by grace? then
what doth this intimate vnto vs all, but a generall Equalitie in

ſtate and condition.
               When we ſhall all be arraigned before that great Iudge of
that high Star-chamber in heauen, when the tares muſt be taken
from the wheat, and the goates ſeperated from the ſheepe,
and this generall Eccho ſhall ſound in the eares of al Ite, Ʋenite,
what other difference ſhall be there then this? ſuch as haue
wrought in the vineyard ſhall haue all one price, and ſuch as
haue no oyle in their lampes ſhall haue all one puniſhment,
that is ſuch as haue done well ſhall be coheires in heauen, and
ſuch as haue done ill ſhall be copartners in hell, whether
they be Emperous, kinges, keyſers, beggers, without exception
of any: for God will deale equally without reſpect of perſons.
               The generality of equality is ſo copious that they are not to
be contained in a nut ſhell like Homers Iliades, but they would
rather require a large Tome then a ſhort Tractat: I will therefore
refer you to the particulers in the next chapter for further
illuſtration hereof.
            
            
               Chap. 4.
               Of the Neceſſitie of
Equalite.
               IN naturall cauſes, by the opinion of Naturaliſts, if all partes &amp;
members of the bodie be not proportionable and equall,
there cannot be that perfect Symmetry which is required in
nature, and therefore ſuch as be of goodly partes and lyneamentes
of body doe carrie a king of encomion in the ſcriptures:
it is ſaid of Saul, that he was a goodly yong man, 1. Sam. 9. 2.
and of Dauid, that he was a comlie perſon 1. Sam. 16. 18,
and of Chriſt, that he was of a meane compoſition and
ſtature, as Publius Lentulus reporteth: the poet giueth a reaſon
hereof, gratior eſt pulchro veniens è corpore virtus, thoſe
gifts are more gracious that proceede from a comly perſon:
for oftentimes a deformed bodie doth argue a deformed mind,
and therefore Ariſtotle in his booke of gouernmēt would haue
cōly mē called to office &amp; not miſhapē &amp; deformed; for which
cauſe ſuch as had a blēiſh might not ēter the order of preiſthood

by the old lawe. And by the ciuill lawe this compoſition and
habitude of bodie is ſo eſtimable, that it alloweth the ſonne an
action of the cauſe againſt him that ſhall deface the portract of
his father.
               In the conſtitution and ſtate of mans bodie good proportion
and equalitie of humors and qualities cauſeth health, and
therefore health is defined by the philoſphers to be nothing els
but a well proportioned vnion of many humors together: for
where one qualitie and humor doth exceede another, they are
the very ſymptoms of ſome naturall defect by iudgment of
phyſitions.
               In Aeconomicall matters if that cōiugiall bond betweene man
and woman be not equall, the coniunction is inconuenient: if
parties diſſent in religion, then will follow prophanes of life: as
Salomon was drawne to Idolatrie by marrying of ſtrange women:
and therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, be not vnequally yoked,
2. Cor. 6. 14.
               If they differ in lynage, then there will be vpbrayding by
birth: it was this that made Dauid ſay, ſeeme
                        •
                      it a light thing to
marry a kings daughter, ſeeing I am a poore man and of ſmall reputation.
1. Sam. 18. 23, therefore Plutarke ſaith, marry a wife of
thine owne degree.
               If they diſagree in conditions and manners, then will be nothing
but contentions and malice: hereof one ſaith there is ill
agreement in that houſe in qua gallina eantat, gallus tacet: where
the hen doth crowe, and the cocke holds his peace, alluding to
that ſaying in the prouerbs. 27. a continuall dropping in the day
of rayne and a contentious woman are alike.
               
               If they vary much in yeares then their braynes will be buſied
with ielouſie and they ſhall be conſtrained to exclame with
Terence O me miſerum duxi vxorem that he was miſerable by
marrying a wife: for age and youth are as repugnant in qualitie
as froſt &amp; fyre.
               So that from hence euery one may learne to make equall election
in nuptials, &amp; to indeuour to match with a meete wife,
as God made Adam a meete helper: for as bordes if they be
not euen ioyned can neuer hold: ſo men and women if they be
not equally ioyned can neuer agree, and therefore remember
that poeticall verſe of Ouid Siqua voles aptè nubere, nube pari, if

thou willt fitly marrie, marrie thy equall.
               In Families where there is no equality vſed by maſters to ſeruants,
there is meere tyranny: hereof it is ſaid, giue to your ſeruants
that which is iuſt and equall. Col. 4. 1. that is aequabilitatem
legis analogicè as Ariſtotle termeth it: it is not ſo to be interpreted
that maſters ſhould make themſelues equall to their ſeruants
in condition and degree, but ſub hoc nomine, as Marlorat noteth,
is vnderſtood the humanity, clemency, and gentle intreating
maſters ought, to vſe, without too much rigor: Leu. 25. 43. for
albeit they are maſters amongeſt men, yet they are but ſeruants
before God, who ſeeth the dooings of all, becauſe he is cheife
maſter of all: and earthly maſters can in nothing more liuelie
repreſent their heauenly maſter, then in ſhewing of mercy.
               In politicall cauſes, in all contractes, if there be not ſome
analogie and equall proportion in the price betweene the venditor
and the emptor, it is no better then oppreſſion, therefore
Abraham when he ſhould purchaſe the field of Ephron gaue
him the value of it; Gen. 23. 13. and Melancthō ſaith ex naturali
aequalitate nemo locupletetur cum alterius iniuria, euen frō natural
equalitie or iuſtice there is no reaſon why one man ſhould inrich
himſelfe by hindering of an other: Mel. in lib. definit. appellat.
               
               In partition of poſſeſſions there is meere iniury without equality,
and therefore the ordinance of lottes were vſed to that
end in cauſes ciuill and diuiſorie: and it was this that made the
copartener come to Chriſt to haue him deuide the inheritance
betweene the two brethren, for no other end, but that the partition
might be equall: as Bullinger obſerueth in his Decades: or
ad iuſtam patrimonij diuiſionem for a iuſt diuiſion, as Aretius interpreteth
that place in Luke. 12. 13.
               In buying and ſelling, if the weights and meaſures be not iuſt
and equall, it is abhominable before God Deut; 25. &amp; puniſhable
by the lawes of men: for as Chytraeus ſaith aequalitas precij
&amp; mercis ſeruanda eſt equalitie muſt be vſed aſwell in the price
as the ware, leaſt it be ſaid of ſuch as the prophet reporteth; there
is like buyer and like ſellar▪
                   Eſa. 24. 2.
               In Military affaires, where the aduerſaries be not equall, the
conflict is dangerous: when Ioſhua ſent thirty thouſand men

to incounter with the Citizens of Ai, the Citie was ſoone ſacked,
becauſe the enemies were not equall.
               In Duell, where combatantes be not equall, the inconuenience
is great: what was Dauid to deale with Goliah, if God had
not aſſiſted him? ne Hercules cōtra duos: he muſt be a ſtrong man
that is able to withſtand two.
               In Spirituall warfare, where the enemies exceede, how doe
they inſult ouer the ſpirit? in what caſe was Iob, when he ſaith, he
was aſſaulted with whole armies of ſorrowes? Iob. 10. 17.
               In Muſick, where there is no equall proportion of ſoundes
there can be no perfect ſymphonie.
               In Arithmeticke, without the vſe of equall nombers there can
be no exact computation.
               In Architecture, where there is no equall proportion in the
worke, it can be no exquiſite building.
               Doe we not ſee by experience, that in 
                     Ʋegetatiue creatures,
where trees are vnequally planted in the orchyard, they neuer
proſper well? that in Senſitiue creatures, where oxen are vnequally
yoked in the plough, they neuer draw well? that in Senſeles
creatures, where ſtones are vnequally laid in maſonrie, they
neuer couch well? then much leſſe among rationall creatures
can there be any concordance without the vſe of equalitie.
To conclude, let this ſuffice, that all lawes, all creatures in their
kind, yea all artes and ſciences for the moſt part are ordained
and doe aime at this ende, to reduce thinges to a generall vniformitie
and equalitie.
            
            
               Chap. 5.
               What equalitie is.
               IF I ſhould diſcourſe of Equalitie according to the curious
definitions and diuiſions of philoſophers, as they controuert
their aequaliae and inaequalia in logicall manner, it were tedious
and friuolous; ſeeing my purpoſe is ſummarily to intreat only
of that equalitie which tendeth to the taxing and rating of common
impoſitions &amp; charges lyable to Cities. Townes, Villages:
&amp;c. becauſe this may conuict the conſcience of ſuch as vſe no
equalitie at all in theſe actions.
               
                  
Equalitie (thus conſidered) is nothing els but a Neceſſarie
Charge impoſed in ſome equall proportion vpon euery one reſpectiuely.
               In this definition or rather deſcription we may obſerue 4.
things concurring in the words.
               
                  
                     1. The Charge
                     2. The Impoſition
                     3. The Proportion
                     4. The Collection
                  
that
it be

                     Neceſſary
                     Lawfull
                     Equall
                     Generall
                  
muſt
haue
reference
to

                     the Cauſe
                     Authoritie.
                     Abilities.
                     Perſons.
                  
               
            
            
               Chap. 6.
               1. What Charge ſignifieth. 2. howe Charges ought
to be neceſſarie. 3. What Charge is
neceſſarie.
               CHarge may be ſaid to be a departing from ſomething to
the benefit or vſe of others from the dominion of the owener;
and this may be done either as the Lawyers ſay, in pecunijs
numeratis, in ready money; or as the Schoolemen ſay, pecunia
menſurabile, of that which may be valued for money.
               This Charge is according to the occaſion ſaid to be impenſae
mitior aut acerbior, leſſer or greater: it is called a charge of onus
which commeth of ones an aſſe, to ſignifie that heauie burdens
are fit for the aſſe, but neceſſarie burdens are fit for men: and
therefore heauie burdens are condemned in the ſcriptures.
You lay heauie burdens, Matth. 23. 4.
               As there is a logicall neceſſitie in the precepts of Art▪ a phyſicall
neceſſitie in the order of nature, ſo there is a politicall neceſſitie
in disburſing of charges; to worke vpon the Sabboth if
it be neceſſarie it is tollerable, to giue almes where it is neceſſarie,
it is charitable; and ſo to pay charges if they be neceſſarie, it
is profitable, which the heathen man obſerueth when he ſaid, emas
non quod opus eſt, ſed quod neceſſe, Seneca, lib. 14. Epiſt. 34. he
would haue vs to lay out money, not for all things we need, but
for thoſe which are moſt needefull and neceſſarie.
               Charges ought to be neceſſarie for theſe reaſons: It is farre
more difficult, capere quàm fundere, to get goods, then to giue
them away, as the Philoſopher ſaith, and therefore it is no leſſe

diſcretion quā querere partae tueri, after they be once gotten, to
be carefull in the diſpoſing of them, as the Poet ſaith: ſo true is
it that Tacitus ſaith, Many knowe howe to diſpend, but not to
diſpoſe. Tacit. lib. 1. hiſt.
               The wiſeman ſaith, the Riches of the godly are pretious, Prou.
12. 17. and therefore as we will not vſe a pearle like a pebble, ſo
we muſt regard howe we impart our riches, ſeeing they are
ſo pretious, euen as Naboth was loath to depart with his patrimonie,
&amp; we muſt not abuſe them with the prodigall ſonne,
but vſe them as Gods bleſſings in all neceſſarie occaſions.
               When the generall Auditor of the whole world ſhall take a
computation of all his ſtewards howe they haue beſtowed his
goods (for the gold is mine ſaith he, Hag. 2. 9.) this will be a lawfull
diſcharge for ſuch as impoſe and pay charges, to plead they
were neceſſarie, and that may be inferred from that ſaying in
Math. 25. 40. For as much as ye haue done theſe things, come and
enter, &amp;c.
               
               Thoſe charges are ſaid to be neceſſarie which concerne a
common wealth: In the charge of a common wealth, reſpect
muſt be had vnto the Prince, the Countrie, the Poore, &amp;c.
               The Prince is called Princeps quaſi Principalis; becauſe he is
the principall perſon amongeſt the people, as the head is the
principall part of the bodie: nowe as the head in ſome naturall
ſort prouideth for the bodie, ſo ought the ſubiects in a reciprocall
ſort to prouide for their prince: for he that is Princeps
ought to be particeps boni; for this cauſe we are commanded to
giue to Caeſar that which is Caeſars, aliud eſt ſceptrum, aliud eſt
plectrum; it was this made king Seleucus ſay, he that knew what
a diademe were would not take it from the ground to ſet vpon
his head: for a crowne is accompanied with many cares and
combrances, Dauid had leſſe trouble with his ſheephooke, thē
his ſcepter, and therefore euery Prince in this caſe may ſay to
his ſubiects as Moſes did, Howe can I alone beare your combrances
and your charge? Deut. 1. 12. for which cauſe he was the firſt
that ordained Magiſtrates vnder him to extenuate his troubles:
and the firſt that inuented Tributes amongeſt the Iſraelites to
ſupport his charge, as Polidor: Virgil reporteth.
               It was firſt called Tribute à Tribu, becauſe it was impoſed
vpon all the Tribes of Iſrael, to ſignifie that all men ought to

contribute to their Prince, according to that ſaying in Rom.
13. 5. Giue tribute to whome tribute belongeth, and therefore Subſidies
and ſuch like charges are neceſſarily graunted by the
Commons, quaſi ſubſidium, as a helpe to vphold their Prince,
which euery one ought to beare, becauſe he is partaker of the
benefit commeth by it. Bullinger Decad. 6, praecept.
               One demanding of Diogenes what countrie man he was,
ſaid, he was Ciuis mundi, a citizen of the world: Paul ſaid he was
no citizen but a ſoiourner in the world; yet commonly we account
that our Countrie where we haue our birth, bringing
vp, and abode, and therefore it is called our Nation à natu, becauſe
it is as it were natale ſolum, our natiue countrie: but more
properly it is called our countrie à patriae, which is deriued of
pater, to ſignifie that in both kinds our Countrie is the father
and the mother of vs all. And this ſhould make vs regard our
natiue countrie, as our naturall parents. Hence it is that Pythagoras
beeing asked howe he ſhould demeane himſelfe to his
countrie; he anſwered, vt ergamatrem, as to my mother. And
Phocion ſaid that he would haue a ſonne tam patriae quam patri,
euery way as loyall and dutifull to his countrie as his father:
the examples are infinit of ſuch as haue loſt their liues for their
countrie, it was euer deemed ſo honourable a ſeruice, pro patria
magnum decus eſt profundere vitam, ſaith Homer. Nowe ſuch
charges as are for the defence of our countrie, as charges of
chiualrie or ſuch like, are neceſſarie: for we ſhould not inioy
our liues, wiues, or liuings without them. Hereof that mellifluous
Father ſaith, Sumptus pro militia honorabilis eſt, the charge
for warres is honourable.
               The Poore man is called Pauper, as one ſaith, quaſi parum
potens, putans, aut imperans, becauſe he poſſeſſeth, thinketh, or
commandeth little, yet pouertie is the ſubiect to prouoke mercie,
when riches are but obiects to procure enuie: therefore one
ſaith, Viuitur paruo bene, a man liues beſt of a little, if he can be
content with his lotte; according to the verſe, Qui placidè ſortē
ferre ſcit, ille ſapit.
               
               To be poore by Grace, diuinum eſt, it is heauenly, which
Chriſt noteth in the Goſpel after Matthew, 19. 29. for this
voluntarie pouertie is a kinde of Martyrdome, as S. Bernard
ſaith.
               
                  
To be poore by Nature humanum eſt, it is incident to mankind,
for all the Apoſtles, yea Chriſt himſelfe was ſo: and therfore
Seneca ſaith, Quemcum
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      miſerum vides hominem ſcias,
Whome thou ſeeſt to be miſerable, thou maieſt knowe he is a
man.
               To be poore by Follie belluinum eſt, it is bruitiſh, as appeares
by the prodigall ſonne; howeſoeuer men come to pouertie, we
are not to diſpute, but to diſpence, becauſe ciuill humanitie (as
Lactantius ſaith) bindes vs to doe good to a man, becauſe he is a
man, Lact. lib. 6. cap. 11. and as the moone ſheweth her light
ſhee receiueth from the ſunne, ſo ſhould men ſhewe their liberalitie
of that they receiue from God: but ſeeing all creatures
in their kinde are compaſſionate one to another, and all lawes
in commiſeration prouide for the releife of the poore; I ſhall
not neede to vrge the neceſſitie of this charge by multiplicitie
of arguments.
               There be diuers other neceſſarie charges which for breuity
I forbeare, but all the reſt may be reduced and comprehended
vnder theſe heads: for if the Prince be our father, the Countrie
our mother, and the poore our brethren, we ought to ſupply
their deficiencie in ſuch ſort as may deſigne our natures, and
ſerue their neceſſities.
            
            
               Chap. 7.
               1. What is meant by Impoſition of Charge.
2. Howe Charges impoſed differ
from others.
               THere are many Charges neceſſarie which are called Voluntarie,
becauſe euery one as he hath any naturall ſympathie
or inſtigation to good, doth depart with all of benevolence
or willingly, according to his free diſpoſition, but becauſe the
great Schooleman ſaith, Volenti non fit iniuria, there is no wrōg
done to the willing; it were impertinent to ſpeake prolixly of
theſe charges, the rather, becauſe this Charge is more properly
ſaid to be exhibitio, then Impoſitio, a gift of good will, then a
charge againſt will, which being left to a mans own liberty, cā
                  not
be ſaid to be done of neceſſity, but willingly. Philemon. 14.
               
                  
There be other charges called Compulſatorie, becauſe they
are impoſed by the Magiſtrate of euery Citie, Towne, village,
&amp;c. which charg differeth from the former, for that is done of
beneuolence, this is to be paid volens nolens, whether a man wil
or nill, hereof it is called an Impoſition quafi in populum impoſitum
becauſe it is impoſed vpon the people by order of mandatum,
praecept, commaundement, warrant, or otherwiſe; charges
thus impoſed are to be paid auctoritatis cauſa thogh there were
no neceſſity to vrge it, as D. Chytraeus ſaith, for we are taught
to obey the magiſtrate; and he that doth thus pay it non peccat,
qui iniuriam patitur doth not offend. I remember a prety ſaying
of Saint Auguſtine Da quod iubes &amp; iube quod velis, ſeeing
theſe doe aſwell impart as impoſe charge, the common ſort
muſt by ſuppoſition deeme theſe charges to be neceſſary.
               D. P. Martir reporteth in his cōmentary vpon the Romans
that magiſtrats had wont to be called patres cōſcripti appointed
fathers, and ſo in many places in the ſcriptures they are phraſed
by the name of fathers, to no other end but that their denomination
might giue them information velle bonum non diuellere
to helpe and not hinder, but to ſhew themſelues as louing to
the people euen as fathers are to their children, hereof Xenophon
ſaith bonus magiſtratus nihil a bono patre differt; a good
magiſtrate doth litle differ from a good father; which if they
doe, then will they not impoſe any impertinent charge, but that
which is inſtant for the neceſſitie, conuenient for the perſons,
and expedient for the place, conſidering there is a father in
heauen which ouerſeeth and obſerueth the actions of all the
fathers vpon earth.
            
            
               Chap. 8.
               1. Of Equall proportion. 2. howe many waies
it is to be taken. 3. that euery one
is to be taxed in ſome
equality to his
ability.
               Equall proportion is to be taken 3. waies; properly,
comparatiuely, reſpectiuely. Properly it is that charge

which is impoſed vpon any according to his owne abilitie:
comparatiuely is that charge laid vpon one which agreeth in
ſome equall proportion to the generall taxation of others.
Reſpectiuely is that charge which is exacted of any ſortable to
the quality of the Seſſment in landes or goods.
               That portion which is proper to a mans owner eſtate ought
to be taxed in ſome meaſure equall to his eſtate according to
the common courſe and cuſtome of the country, and this is called
a proportion properly, the reaſons followe.
               You ſhall reade that in caſes of redemption the Prieſts were
to proportion the prices according to the eſtate of the perſons,
as appeares in Leuit. 27. 8. where it is written. If he be poorer
then thou haſt eſteemed him, then ſhall he preſent himſelfe
vnto the priest, and the prieſt ſhall value him according to his
ability, nowe the prieſt he is called preſbiter quaſi praebens alijs iter
of ſhewing others the way, and therefore his action ought to
giue example to others in all charges to make an equall taxation
in ſome proportion to the abilitie of the perſon.
               It is noted in the people of Hieruſalem that in a generall charge
for the common good they did not preſſe themſelues beyond
their powers: for (ſay they) we according to our Abilities haue
done it. Neh. 5. 8. which is a good preſident to be obſerued of
all ſeſſors to rate men according to their abilities.
               In diſpencing to the poore, men are willed to miniſter but
according to their Abilities. 1. Pet. 4. 11. ſo, it ought to be in
al other charges: men are not to be vrged beyond their abilities:
for in giuing away and in paying away there is no difference in
the worke but in the will: for there is a departing from ſomething
in both, ſauing one is a free cōmmutatiō, the other is a kind
of coaction.
               If the ſaddle be not ſet right on the horſe-backe it will
wring him, if the ballance be not equall in weight, it will wrong
one, ſo if a man be not taxed equally to his portion it will iniury
him, and that is againſt the word which ſaith, thou ſhalt not
doe thy neighbour wrong Leuit. 19. 13.
               Men vſe to lade the Camell when he lieth downe as he may
riſe vp with his burden, he that will haue his beaſt to hold out
in trauell muſt not ouerburden him: the like courſe muſt be
taken with men, ſo to taxe them as they may continue in vndergoing

charges, and not to make impoſitions become oppreſſions.
To this purpoſe Bruſon reporteth a matter of one Aemylius
a ruler in Egipt, who beeing complained of to Tiberius
Caeſar by the people for oppreſſing them with paiments, he
wrote to Aemylius ſe tondere velle ſuas oues non deglubere, that
he would haue him to ſheare his ſheepe but not to flea them,
meaning thereby that he would haue men aſſeſſed indifferently
and not ſurcharged extreamely.
               In all Taxations euery man ſhould remember this golden
rule To doe as he would be done to, that is to taxe others as he
would be taxed himſelfe by others, nowe as the ſtring ouerſtraind
in the lute will neuer ſound well, or cloth too much
ſtretched on the tayntors will neuer weare well; ſo if he himſelfe
be taxed aboue his ſtate he will neuer take it well: then
conſider what Seleucus the Emperor ſaid, which Gualter obſerueth
to that ende quod tibi non vis fieri alteri ne feceris that
thou wilt not haue done to thy ſelfe doe not to others: but as
in martiall diuiſions the Quartermaſter ſets out euery one his
ſhare according to his place and degree, ſo in politicall impoſitions
the Seſſor ſhould taxe and ſet euery one his rate according
to his ſtate and portion.
            
            
               Chap. 9.
               That euery man is to be taxed equallie in
ſome comparatiue and proportionale
ſort agreeable to the generall
traxation of others.
               
                  THe graſhopper is a burden to one, Eccles. 12. 5. when a
bull was but a burden to Milo: a myte is aſmuch to the
widowe, as a talent was to Alexander, and therefore ſeeing the
abilities of men are not equall, it is not ment hereby that al men
ſhould be equall in taxation, which are vnequall in eſtate, but
that euery one may haue as indifferent valuation as another by
comparing their portions together: for as the heathen man
ſaith he is an euill man cui non ſatis est id quod caeteris eſt ſatis to
whome that is not enough to one that is enough to others: if
Eſau could ſay I haue enough when he ſhould take, men muſt

not vrge more then enough when they doe taxe. Gen. 33. 9.
               Where one buyeth cloth he wil looke to haue as good meaſure
as the other, where one buyeth Iron he will looke to haue
as good weight as an other: where one buyeth ware he lookes to
haue as good a penny-worth as an other: and therefore why
ſhould not one man that is taxed in charges looke to be aſwell
vſed as an other? and if there be required ſuch proportion in
giuing that one muſt not be greiued when an other is eaſed, as
Paul ſaith, the ſame reaſon may ſtand in the proportion of taxing,
that one muſt not be racked when another is remitted, but
that there muſt be equality in both. 2. Cor. 8. 13.
               If there were a ſuruey of generall ſeſſements, in ſome places
it will appeare that there is inaequalium Catalogus a catalogue of
confuſed inequalities: you ſhall find that Beniamin ſhall haue
fiue times more to his meſſe; Gen. 43. 34. when Lazarus ſhall
haue hardly a crum, Naboth with his vyneyard ſhall be aſmuch
as Naball with all his reuenues, and as in India there
are antes as big as maſtiues, and miſe as hie as Camells, as
Pomponiue Mela reportes, ſo in England you ſhall find poore-men
aſmuch as rich-men, and meane men aſmuch as gentlemen.
               All rates for the moſt part are either par, Suppar, or Impar,
that is the leſſer part are like one an other, the greater part are
ſomewhat like others, but the moſt part are nothing like others:
are not many worth ſixe hundreth poundes taxed at xx.
in terris, when an other not worth an hundred is as much, and
an other of equall value is VI. in bonist is there not ſome worth
ſixe thouſand poundes, ſet at IIII. p. when an other vnder a
thouſand is rated at VIII. p. and another that may diſpend
three thouſand is but VIII. p. and yet able to buy or countermaine
Twenty three pound men? what ſhould I dilate theſe
endles inequalities, as Protogenes knew Apelles by the
draught of one line, and Hercules proportion was perceiued
by the ſize of his foote, ſo you may iudge the generall by theſe
particulars, ſeeing it is no more ſeen then the monſtrous heads
were of Hydra, the deformed body was of Eſope, or the infamous
marke was of Cayne.
               Plato reſembleth mans life to a chaunce at dyce, and ſo may
our ſeſſmentes, therefore it is growne to a prouerbe that mē are

charged as the dice chance, deuce ace cannot, ſiſe ſinke will not,
but quater trey he muſt pay: this is no matter of noueltie, but
antiquitie; for it is obſerued in that generall charge about Ieruſalem
in Nehem. 2. The poore were vnable and could doe nothing,
for vltra poſſe, non eſt eſſe, and we can haue no more of a
catte but her skinne; the beſt ſort were vnwilling and would do
nothing: ſo it is noted, The great men would not put their neckes
to it, Nehem. 3. 5. but the middle ſort they bare moſt of the
burden, and ſo it is in moſt of theſe rates: as the ſunne mooueth
ſloweſt when it is higheſt in the zodiacke, ſo men are euer
ſlackeſt that are higheſt in eſtate: and as the lighter ballance euer
mounteth hieſt, ſo the meaner ſort are commonly taxed
heauieſt.
               This Inequalitie is meere iniquitie in the agents that impoſe
it, and manifeſt iniurie to the patient that pay it, and therefore
it is condemned by the example of God himſelfe, and by the
lawes of God and man.
               Inequalitie is condemned by the example of God himſelfe;
for God is equall, and he deales equally with euery man, to the
ende one man ſhould deale equally by another: vt ſementem feceris
it a metes: for ſuch meaſure as we mete ſhall be met to vs.
               Inequalitie is by inference condemned by the word of god,
in this ſort if falſe weights and meaſures which are vnequall &amp;
vniuſt are ſaid to be abhominable, theſe vnequall rates of charges
cannot be tollerable: for in both there is but a defrauding
of a due: and therefore it is condemned as well as the other.
Deut. 25. 16.
               Where many of equall ſtate are vnequally taxed, it argueth
partialitie, becauſe there is reſpect of perſons, tribuere aqualibus
inaequalia &amp; inaequalibus aequalia eſt perſonarum acceptio: for as D.
Chytraeus vpon the Commandements ſaith, To giue to equall
perſons vnequall things, and to vnequall perſons equall things
is reſpect of perſons, which is a ſinne generally condemned in
the lawe of God.
               Inequalitie is condemned by poſitiue and nationall lawes, if
you haue recourſe to the Statute made in Anno 43. of our late
ſoueraigne Lady of famous memorie, Queene Elizabeth, there
is a clauſe concerning the Seſſement of ſubſidy inſerted in theſe
words, The ſaid Commiſſioners to whome it ſhall appertaine, ſhall
                  
Indifferently ſet, taxe, and ſeſſe themſelues, and the ſaid Aſſeſſors.
This is ſpoken demonſtratiuely to ſhewe that indifferencie &amp;
not inequalitie ſhould be vſed in all Seſſements to all perſons:
for indifference eſt quaſi non differens, that is, there ought to be
no difference in theſe dealings, in regard of perſons, but that euery
one ſhould haue a proportionable penniworth according
to his portion as well as another.
               What ſhould I ſpeake more of Inequalitie? doe we not ſee
that as Cockes cannot fight well that are vnequally matched, ſo
men can neuer agree wel that are vnequally charged▪ for wheras
Equalitie is the cauſe of loue, and is therefore called vnitatis
nutrix, the nource of vnitie; this Inequality is nothing els but
the cauſe of diſcontent, and is therefore called ſeditionis altrix,
the nource of ſedition: for as wheeles going vpon vnequall
ground will make a rumbling, ſo men preſſed with vnequall
rates will make a murmuring, as appeares by the labourers in
the Vineyard: for if they did murmure in receiuing of money,
becauſe their wages was equall when their worke was vnequal;
what will they doe in departing from money where their eſtates
are equall, if they be vnequally taxed?
            
            
               Chap. 10.
               That euery one is to be charged reſpectiuely according
to the Qualitie of the Seſſement, whether it
be in lands or goods.
               AS euery one ought to be taxed properly according to his
owne eſtate, comparatiuely according to generall taxations,
ſo he muſt be vſed reſpectiuely according to the qualitie of the
Seſſement, whether it be in terris or bonis, or els it is no better
then inequalitie.
               If a leuie be made for a common charge in money, and the
direction or warrant be generall to collect ſixe pence in the
pound as well of lands as goods without difference, this is
meere iniurie; becauſe that proportion is not obſerued which
aimeth at equalitie. For the Statute it ſelfe concerning Seſſement
of ſubſidies doth make a diaphora or diſtinction therein;
for landes bee at foure ſhillings, and goods at two ſhillings

and eight pence the pound: and therefore to make lands
and goods all at one rate in other charges is repugnant to the
equalitie and equitie of the lawe; aequalitas quam Magiſtratus
ſtatuit ſeruanda, which as Hemingius ſaith, ought to be obſerued:
but yet this is made but a ſuperficiall and light matter in
many places, amongeſt ſuch (no doubt) as are more forward to
impoſe then to pay charges, which that learned man D. Chytraeus
noted in his time, and therefore he left this ſentence to all
Seſſors, Quae alijs praecipis ipſe facere primus videare, That which
thou doeſt command others to doe, ſee that thou thy ſelfe firſt
doeſt it: for that common wealth muſt needs doe well, where
precepts and preſidents goe togither, as Plato ſaith.
               The rate of the Subſidie is, or ought to be, aequabilitatis Normam,
the very rule of equalitie to deriue and direct all other
charges by: for this cauſe many reſpect not altogether the proportion
obſerued in the Subſidie: but becauſe in moſt places,
eſpecially in cities or great townes, collections are made commonly
by the rate of the ſubſidie, ſuch as are therein vnequally
taxed, are made ſubiect to infinit inequalities and iniuries in
all other charges.
               In common charges to ſee one that is ſet at twentie ſhillings,
to pay foure pence, when another of his value paieth two ſhillings
by the rate of the ſubſidie; to ſee one that may diſpend in
annuall reuenews two hundred pounds, taxed at two ſhillings,
when another that hath not the tythe of his liuing, laid as much
by the rate of the ſubſidie; what greater inequalitie and iniury
can there be, that theſe which diſdaine to conſort with the loweſt
in caſes of countenance, ſhould be linked with the loweſt in
matters of charge? ſo the old prouerbe is ſtill approoued, The
weakeſt muſt to the wall. For as wormes breed ſooneſt in the
ſofteſt wood, ſo wrongs are ſooneſt offered to the weakeſt perſon.
               Theſe Inequalities are ſo apparent that in moſt places when
a Charge is impoſed, the better ſort with the Conſtables of the
towne aſſemble together, about the equall taxation and collection
of it: if it be in Hundreds they deuide themſelues into
Villages: if in great towns, they deuide themſelues into Wards,
and ſo taxe men not according to the rates in the Subſidie, but
in ſome meaſure according to their abilities agreeable to the

generall proportion of others, which muſt needs be a very indifferent
and diſcreet courſe for the conſeruation of the people
in much vnitie, where there is ſo great circumſpection to equalitie:
and ſithence it is plebeiae &amp; publica expenſa, the commō
charge of the vulgar ſort, it is great reaſon they ſhould proportion
their owne rates, ſo the charge which is impoſed be diſcharged,
as Bullinger deliuereth in his Decades.
            
            
               Chap. 11.
               The probable cauſes and coniectures why men are ſo
vnequally taxed in common Impoſitions and
charges, repugnant to generall
proportions.
               THeſe vnequall proportions are committed by the Seſſors,
either of negligence for want of dutie, or of indiſcretion
for want of iudgement, or of ignorance by way of Apologie,
or of wilfulneſſe by way of affection.
               Theſe inequalities are committed of Negligence for want
of dutie: for there are ſome which rate men vpon rumors and
reports; nowe as it is a maxim amongeſt Philoſophers in vniverſalibus
verſatur dolus, ſo it is a principle of experience in the
world, that generall relations are but common fallations. I will
not ſay but that ſometime vox vulgatis veritatis eſt, the vulgar
voice may be verified: but yet as the Phiſition in ſome caſes
ſaith, that 
                     Ʋrina eſt fallax; ſo in theſe caſes I would haue men
thinke that fama eſt mendax, rumor is but a flatuous eccho of
idle tongues: and therefore Thales Mileſius beeing demanded
howe much trueth did differ from rumors? ſo much (ſaid he)
as the eies are diſtant from the eares, noting thereby that men
ought to be oculer and not auriculer agents, if they wil know
the trueth: for many are blazond to be perſons of great liuing,
which when they come to be founded, it appeares but a falſe
allarum, and thus are many hindred by heare-ſay.
               It was well ſaid of one melius eſt, it is farre better to fall
into the hands of the iudge, then into the mouthes of the
common people: for hee will not ſentence any without

examination &amp; proofe, when the other will cenſure euery one
by rumors and reportes.
               If you looke into all our ſtatutes concerning the ſeſment of
ſubſidies and taxes, there is a prouiſion made for the appointing
of certaine perſons with the Conſtables of euery Towne
to be ſeſſors of their neighbours, and this is done to preuent
iniury by reportes that the ſeſſors ſhould by their owne perſonall
inquiery take inteeligence of euery mans eſtate, &amp; not rely
vpon relations of others, and therefore this may be one cauſe
why many are wronged by inequality if the ſeſſors neglect
their duties in the order of equality.
               Theſe inequalities are committed of Indiſcretion for want o
Iudgement: for as Seneca ſaith quidam homines duplo plus vident
quàm alij; ſome men can ſee twice aſmuch as others, &amp; there
be ſome as wiſe as Choraebus that would vndertake to tell the
waues of the ſea, and yet he could not nomber aboue fiue,
thereof came the prouerbe ſtultior Choraebo. And this is ſometime
the ouerſight of the ſeſſors, they can prie into mens eſtates
what they haue to liue on, but they neuer expend their charge
which is to liue of them, and ſo they ayme at men in theſe matters
as the blind man doth at the crowe.
               The marchant recounteth his charges and detriments before
he can reſolue what he gaynes by his ware, the vintner defrayeth
the loſſe of leckage before he can ſet downe what he
ſaues by his wine, the husbandman reſpecteth the charge of
fowing and reaping before he can ſee what he getts by his harueſt,
&amp; ſoe ſeſſors ought to looke into the charge of a mans familie
before they can well tell howe to charge him by his ability:
for as it is noted in Summa Angelica, lucrum non dicitur niſi
deductis expenſis, it is not properly called gaine vntill expences be
deducted, ſo it is to be obſerued in the eſtates of men, vnleſſe
there be conſideration of their charge, there can be no information
of their eſtate.
               It is reported by hiſtorians, that in Florence he that was father
of fiue children was exempted from all impoſitions; Amongeſt
the Lacedemonians, he that was father of three children
was freed from watches, he that was father of foure children,
was releaſed ab omni onere, of all charges, Amongeſt the
Womans he that was father of three children was neuer inforced

to any ambaſſage, if he were father to fiue children, he was
freed from common charges, but if he were father of thirteene
children, he might challenge immunity from all charge, as Vlpian
ſaith.
               I note theſe examples to this end, not that any ſhould be priuiledged
from charges which are able to pay, but that in common
taxations there ſhould be ſome regard of euery mans eſtate
by his charge, and to haue the more fauour in reſpect of
his family: as for inſtance where one is worth a thouſand pounds
and hath none but his wife and himſelfe to prouide for, and being
a Man yet liueth not like a man but feedeth like Diogenes
with a roote, and goeth like Lazarus with a ragge, ſuch a miſer
as this (if he be compared with another of equall portiō which
hath ſeauen or eight children &amp; maintaines his charge in ſome
ciuill &amp; credible ſort) is to be called to quadruple charge more
then the other, or elſe in all reaſon it can be no equality but iniury.
               Theſe inequalities are commonly excuſed by way of Apologie
deduced from the example of the labourers in the Vyneyard,
who beeing male-content becauſe they had equall pay
for vnequall paines, the maſter reprooued them and ſaid, Is thy
eye euill becauſe mine is good? Vnder this pretext many doe apologize
inequalitie.
               When any complaine and pleade for equall eaſe of charge
aſwell as others, what is that to you (ſay they) doe you enuy an
others good ſeeing you are taxed but according to your worth,
are you any way wronged? Maledicta gloſſa quae corrumpit textum
as one ſaith; it is a curſed gloſſe that mars the text, and this
is nothing but a retrouerting of the text for a mans owne turne
as the deuill did wreſt the ſcriptures to ſupply his purpoſe: for
firſt it is not fit to mixe ſpirituall and temporall matters in one
ſence, no more then it was allowed in the ould lawe to weare
lynſey wolſey both in one garment: ſecondly, it was lawfull for
the maſter of the vyneyarde to diſpoſe his owne goodes at his
pleaſure, but it is not lawfull for a ſeſſor to vſe reipublice bonis at
his pleaſure: and although the maſter did them no iniury, becauſe
he compounded for equall ſalarie, yet theſe are offered
wrong which are vſed without equalitie according to generall
proportions, as in the 9. chapter appeareth very pregnantly.
               
                  
Theſe inequalities are for the moſt part lead by ſwaie of affection,
either in loue or hatred, fauour or diſpleaſure: for in
theſe caſes, as one ſaith, voluntas &amp; amicum &amp; inimicum fait, it is
the will that doth make equality and inequalitie: for if men
were all beloued a like then ſhould they be charged alike reſpecting
their portions, but whether they be loued or hated in
theſe generall actions of inequalitie, the Poets wordes prooue
true, Sic volo, ſic iubeo, ſtat pro ratione voluntas, the will beareth
the greateſt ſway amongeſt ſeſſors, who are as skilfull in ſubſtraction
and Addition as the beſt Arithmetitians, and they
can as cloſely vent their willes vnder a viſor, as Thamar did
her vice vnder a vaile, for this Cymmerian darknes cannot indure
the ſunne no more then owles can the light: yet as the
Steward when he had a ſiniſter pretence could readily cōceiue
and ſay, I knowe what to doe. Luke. 16: ſo theſe men are not to
ſeeke of a ſecret conueyance when they intend what to doe as
by the ſequele you may obſerue: for as Paul. ſaid of the Epheſians,
ſo doe I of theſe ſeſſors, it is ſhame to ſpeake of the things are
done oft them in ſecret, Eph. 5. 1.
               Such as haue eaſe vpon Fauour or Affection are for the moſt
part ſpared in theſe reſpectes.
               It is my kinſman (ſaith one) I muſt vſe him kindly in regard
of aliance, affinitas eſt quaſi immunitas: for one ſaith, affinity is a
kind of immunity.
               It is my friend (ſaith another) I muſt gratify him becauſe of
his good remembrances, munus amicos parit: for giftes will beget
frendes. It is my cuſtomer (ſaith another) I will eaſe him
becauſe I take his money. Quid non perunia poteſt? for what will
not mony doe?
               It is my man (ſaith another) I will ſpare him in reſpect of his
ſeruice, eſt vir palliatus: for a cloake is good for the raine.
               It is my tenant (ſaith another) I muſt forbeare him becauſe I
am his Landlord: for he had need of an eaſy rate that payes an
hard rent.
               This may well be ſaid to be a Fauour: for ſuch as are thus
ſet at a lowe rate in the ſubſidy, are the leſſe ſubiect to priuie
ſeales, to millitarie munition, to multiplicine of charges, &amp; therfore
amongeſt the Scithians he was accounted the happieſt
man that had the beſt freindes as Lucian reporteth thereof:

came the prouerbe, vbi amici ibi opes, where there are frendes
there are riches; yet this is called a Fauour but abuſiuely as
Chriſt was called ſinne: for that cannot be deemed gratious
which occaſioneth a double diſgrace both in the ſeſſor and the
receptor.
               That may be ſaid of the ſeſſor which Nehemiah ſaid of ſuch
perſons, that which you doe is not good; Neh. 5. 9. for according
to the prouerbe, you doe but cut large thonges of other
mens leather, ſuch as theſe which can frankely effuſe an other
mans goodes as the waſtfull ſteward did, Math. 16. for their
owne pleaſures, if they were to doe good with their owne
goodes they would be as neere as Naball was, loath to part frō
a penny; if you will afforde a fauour where you affect, you
ſhould doe well to effect it with your owne: for theſe are
Reipublicae Bona and therefore this dooing is not worth gramercie,
ſeeing it is rather to be deemed a fault then a fauour.
               Thoſe which are thus taxed with Fauour it is but an ecclips
to their credites by expoſing themſelues to all opprobrie: for
fleſh and bloude cannot brooke to ſee ſuch as haue wealth and
poſſeſſions like Diues, that looke to be called Rabbi with obſequious
congies, and to haue the higheſt places with the
proud Phariſies, that ſuch as theſe ſhould pay no more thē the
Publican, towards publike charges, and ſuch as theſe are no
better then Impoſtors to their prince: for he that is rated moſt
according to his portion is a better ſubiect to his prince then
ſuch an one as exceedes him in common ſeſſements and yet is
taxed far vnder his ſubſtance, as the myte of the poore wydowe
was farre better to the treaſurie then the offerings of the
rich.
               As thoſe which are taxed with fauour, it is perceiued by a
kinde of ſubſtraction in taking ſomewhat from aſſeſſements
without equality, ſo ſuch as are rated vpon diſpleaſure, as the
ſtone is ſaid to growe per additamentum by a kind of adding to,
ſo that will appeare by a kinde of Addition or putting to more
with in equality, which may be apparantly diſcerned vpon theſe
or ſuch like occaſions.
               He hath ſet vp his trade (ſaith one) in the towne to hinder
me, I will nowe helpe him forward in this, figulus figulum odit:
                  
for it is a common thing to ſee howe one mechanicke will maligne
another.
               He would not giue (ſaith another) to ſuch a voluntary charge
when he was mooued; I will nowe meete with him in this: for
he which is in office can doe much ex officio, vnder colour of
his office, if he feareth not confuſion of face.
               He would not doe me ſuch a pleaſure (ſaith another) when I
had occaſion to vſe him, I will now remember him in this: I
haue a way (ſaith Ieſabell) when ſhee could not haue her wil another
way.
               He hath done me much iniurie (ſaith another) by ſuites and
ſpeeches; I will now ſomewhat requite him in this: for priuate
grudges are eaſily protected vnder publike buſineſſe.
               He is very thriftie in the world (ſaith another) I will nowe
crop his living a little in this, as the Egyptians did oppreſſe the
Iſraelites with burdens, becauſe they did multiply and increaſe.
               This may well be ſaid to be a Diſpleaſure: for vnius compendiū
alterius diſpendium, that which the other of Fauour doth prevent,
this of Diſpleaſure muſt vndergoe, in extremities Symon
muſt needs beare the croſſe.
               It is too odious in this age to ſee howe ſuch as dare not play
the lyon, will play the Foxe, and when they can no way quite
themſelues in their owne matters, they will cloake it ſub officio,
vnder their office, or pretence of ſome legall or regall buſines;
and becauſe this ſhall not ſeeme to be a paradoxe, I referre you
to ſcripturall inſtances for proofe.
               When the Rulers had a ſpite againſt Daniel becauſe he was
ſeconded by the king, they could no way tell howe to be reuē
                  ged,
but by ſoliciting the king to make a decree, that by colour
thereof, they might worke their wills vpon good Daniel.
               When Haman did malice Mordecai becauſe he would not
mooue his hatte, he durſt not openly be reuenged of him, but
by ſuggeſting the king to write letters, that vnder pretext therof,
he might haue his mind of good Mordecai.
               It is ſo generall a note in the nature of man, that ſuch as haue
their minds cauterized with malice, care not with what weapons
they fight, ſo they may haue their wils.
               
                  
Theſe kinde of Seſſors ſhould conſider this ſaying, poſſe &amp;
nolle nobile, it is the part of a wiſeman ſometime to ſequeſter his
will from his power, and in ſome caſes not to doe, what he might
doe, is held for a true type of nobilitie; this were a good courſe
to kirbe in men of theſe conditions, that in their taxations they
deale not as their wils and affections carrie them, but as Cicero
ſaith, quid lex &amp; religio cogat, what lawe and religion compell
them, and to doe what is meete to be done, and not that which
they may doe: for who knowes not what a man in office may
doe pretextu officij by colour of his office, where there is no care
or conſcience in the execution of it?
               The Philoſopher ſaith, iniquus eſt qui inuidet aut fauet, that he
is a wicked perſon that doeth enuie or fauour eſpecially in
publique caſes where there ought to be ſome proportion in equalitie
without reſpect of partialitie: therefore Seſſors ſhould
doe wel to obſerue what a great reproch it is to be reputed partiall,
it is to their names farre worſe them a myte to the cheeſe, or
a moath to the cloth; and who would be branded for bad dealing,
either with the blacke cole as a marke of infamie to the
world, or by caſting of the blacke ſtone (in ſigne of ignominie)
into the water, as it had woont to be an auncient cuſtome amongeſt
the heathens, to excuſe or accuſe men by caſting of
white and blacke ſtones into the water, which Ouid reporteth,
Mos erat antiquis, niueis, atriſ
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      lapillis, his damnare rees, illis abſoluere
culpa. Metamorph. lib. 15.
               Such Seſſors which ſeeke to reuenge their priuate wrongs
or wils vnder publicke buſineſſe, ſhould feare by following the
former preſidents, leaſt they incurre the like puniſhments.
               If your Statutes puniſh thoſe which vſe falſe weights &amp; meaſures
to deceiue others, God wil not ſpare thoſe which vſe falſe
and vnequall rates to iniure others, and if Iurors are bound by
oath to preſent ſuch as vſe falſe weights, all men are bound by
allegeance to diſcouer ſuch as make falſe rates: for by the ciuill
lawe, peccata nocentium expedit eſſe nota, it is deemed a ſinne to
conceale any ſiniſter dealings.
            
            
               
               Chap. 12.
               What perſons are liable and ought to be taxed towards
common Impoſitions and
Charges.
               ALL perſons of abilitie as well ſubſidie men as others cohabiting
within any citie, towne, village, &amp;c. are to be taxed
towards common impoſitions and charges.
               Charges are ſaid to be a burden, and we are taught to beare
one anothers burden: for a burden beeing borne by many,
though it be heauie, it will ſeeme light, according to the olde
ſaying, many hands make light worke.
               It is noted amongeſt ſwine, that one hogge will ſuccour an
other that is baited, then amongeſt Chriſtians one man ought
to helpe another that is burdened.
               It is the nature of dogges in fighting, not to reſcue, but to
fall vpon him that is beaten: men doe not differ from dogges,
if they will not releiue him that is vnder a burden, and if a good
man will be mercifull to his beaſt, he is worſe then a beaſt that
will not be mercifull to his brother.
               It is reported of that godly gouernour Nehemiah, howe in
a common wealth cauſe, to animate others, he made himſelfe
the firſt example; Euen I (ſaith he) doe it, Nehem. 5. 10. the magiſtrate
is called Magiſtratus, either of magis &amp; ſtratus, becauſe
he is of more dignitie and authoritie then others; or of magis &amp;
ſtatus, becauſe he is of greater ſtate and abilitie then others: and
therefore ſuch as be Magiſtrates will rather addere then adimere,
that is, they will be as readie to conioyne as to inioyne any
charge; for the office cannot priuiledge any from expence, but
as the Poet ſaith, Si quaratur honos non fugiatur onus, if any will
get honour by his office, he muſt not eſchewe the burden: and
ſuch as are readie to command and will not commute with others,
eſt onus non honos, as one ſaith, it is chargeable but not honourable:
for as Peter ſaid to Chriſt, Maſter pittie thy ſelfe, ſo it
will be reported of theſe, they are of Peters minde, they will pittie
themſelues though they oppreſſe others, but by reaſon of
authoritie they will not put their neckes to it, as it was ſaid of
the great men of Ieruſalem, Nehem. 3. 5. nay they will not put

ſo much as their finger to it, as it was noted in the Scribes and
Phariſes, Math. 23. 4.
               It is obſerued in the Preiſts &amp; Leuites that in theſe common
charges they were preſidents to the common people: for they
are firſt placed to commend their forwardnes as you may read
in Neh. 3. 1. which is a good memento to all miniſters of the
word: for a miniſter is ſo called à miniſtrando of miniſtring, to
ſhew that there is required as well exhibition with the hand, as
exhortation with the tongue, which S. Gregorie noteth when
he ſaith qui alios ad bene operandum excitat ad bene agendum ſeipſum
ligat: he that exciteth others to welldooing doth bind
himſelfe to the like, otherwiſe as Cato ſaith, turpe eſt doctori it is
a ſhameful thing to the teacher if his deedes reprooue his doctrine,
as it was in the Preiſt and Leuit who could ſhew others
the way, &amp; yet themſelues did ſhun the way when they ſhould
compaſſionate the wounded man.
               Thus when the magiſtrate doth prodeſſe aſwell as praeſſe and
the miniſter dare as well as fari, it muſt needes be a great incouragement
to the common ſort to followe: for ſimilitude and
example doe mooue much, faith Cicero, &amp; S. Auſtine ſaith that
examples are as ſermons to the vulgar people, and therefore as
many horſes which trauell together goe more willingly in the
way, ſo many men participating together, pay the more cherefully
their charges.
               There be ſome which vnder colour of office doe challenge
a kind of immunity from common charges: for it is a common
practiſe of Conſtables in ſome places in reſpect of their paines
to ſaue their purſes.
               In taking of paynes they doe but their office, the very word
officium doth ſignify duty, to teach ſuch as are in office to doe
their duties, which cannot be without paines.
               This duty and paines is required by the lawes of god &amp; mā.
               The word of God commandeth euery one that is in office
to be diligent therein, hereof it is written, let him that hath an
office waite of it, Rom. 12. 7. and therefore it is obſerued in
ſuch officers as feare God that they would performe their duties
with al ſedulitie euen for conſcience ſake without commodity,
they deemed it ſo odible to ſaue by their office. Neh. 5. 15.
               The lawes of men doe not only compell Conſtables to be

diligent &amp; attendant in the execution of their office, as appeares
in the Statutes made in the 33. Hen. 8. cap. 10. 37. Hen. 8.
cap. 8. and in diuers others, but there is inflicted puniſhments
vpon Conſtables for negligence in their office, in ſome caſes,
with the loſſe of fiue poundes, 14. Eliz. 5. in other caſes with
the loſſe of twenty poundes. 23. Hen. 6. cap. 14, yea and in
ſome caſes with the loſſe of all their goods. 11. Hen. 4. cap. 12.
ſo that paines is vrged as a thing penall.
               If we ſhould reaſon a pari by comparing the Conſtables
paines with others that are in office, if you conſider the office
of ouerſeers for the poore, they take triple paines to the conſtables
and neglect their owne priuate buſines for a publique benefit,
and yet they are contributors as well as others, and ſhall
Conſtables be paid for their paines? de ſimilibus ſimile debet eſſe
iudicium, I can ſee no reaſon for it in equity or equality.
               If we ſhould reſpect the loſſe of their time, why? in dooing
of their duties they doe redeeme the time, when in their idle
paſtimes and ſportes they doe but miſpend the time, and ſeeing
as Plato ſaith, Naſcimur pro patria, how can they better improue
their time then for the common good of their country, whereunto
we ought to dedicate our paines, purſes, and perſons if
occaſion conſtraineth?
               In Citties and in great townes where there are many Conſtables,
their paines are the leſſer, but their ſauings are the greater.
In a leuie of twenty poundes, if Conſtables may be ſuffered
to reſerue their owne payments, how ſoone may they ſaue
aboue thirty ſhillings according to ordinary rates, which is vnreaſonable?
conſidering it far exceedeth princely allowance: for
the Conſtable or other officer in ſubcoliecting of the ſubſidy
hath but two pence in the pound allowed him, and ſhall the
Conſtables ſaue aboue eighteene pence in the pound for the
collection of all other common charges? nominatim aliquos referre
poſſum: I feare there be too too many, I will not maligne
them, but God amend them.
               If you ſearch all the statutes you ſhall not find (vnleſſe it be
in the ſubcollection of the ſubſidy) that conſtables are to make
a profit of their paines: for then it were rather an occupation
then an office; and therefore this kind of ſauing is not to be ſuffered
in a common welth: for it is condemned in the ſcriptures

by an argument drawen à maiori ad minue from the greater to
the leſſer in this ſort; ſuch as were couetous were not to be called
to office by the word of god Exod, 18. 21. but theſe which
ſaue their owne charges vnder coulour of their office are couetous,
ergo &amp;c.
               This vnderhand ſauing may by circumſtance be cōdemned
by our poſitiue lawes, in this manner. Sauing is ſecret kind of
getting, he that ſecretly getteth by ſiniſter meanes is no better
then a theefe, and therefore if he be deemed a felon by our
lawes which taketh aboue fiue ſhillings from a priuat perſon
what ſhall we terme theſe that defraud the Common-welth of
ſo much mony in a publique charge? It makes me remember
that pretie alluſion of M. Cato ſitting to this purpoſe, fures tenues
the leſſer theeues (ſaith he) are reſtrained with ſhackells &amp;
linckes of iron about their legges, but the greater theeues, doe
geſtare in colo Catenas aureas, iett vp and downe with chaines
of gould about their neckes, and coſtly induments vpon their
bodie. I pray god theſe kind of ſauers be not ſuch, if they be
they are no better then caterpillers to a common-welth.
               There be others that plead a priuiledge from common
charges; becauſe they are out of the Subſidy booke; if they
be of any competent ability, this is rather a reaſon of ſome emphaſis
to make them capable of other charges: for ſeeing they
neither pay ſubſidy, or finde armor as others doe which are in
the ſubſidy, they may the better contribute to other charges.
               Who knowes not that many are ſpared out of the ſubſidie
for many reſpectes and yet they are (or ought to be) lyable
to the charge of puruey for the prince, prouiſion for the
poore, impoſitions of a towne? the widowe gaue her myte, aswell
as others that gaue more, he liueth like a hogge that doth
no good while he liueth, nay as Seneca ſaith, Non viuit qui nemini
viuit he liueth not at all, that liueth for none but himſelfe.
               He that will haue the roſe muſt away aſwell with the pricke
as the ſauour, the philoſopher could ſay qui ſentit commodum
debet ſentire onus, he that receiueth profit muſt not refuſe expence:
for ſuch as cohabit together to reape a benefit, muſt be
coadiutors together for eaſe of a burdē, otherwiſe they deſerue
not the name of a neighbour, but are fit to be ſecluded frō humane
ſocietie.
               FINIS.
               
            
         
      
   

