
   
      
         
            Englands vvay to vvin vvealth, and to employ ships and marriners: or, A plaine description of what great profite, it will bring vnto the common-wealth of England, by the erecting, building, and aduenturing of busses, to sea, a fishing With a true relation of the inestimable wealth that is yearely taken out of his Maiesties seas, by the Hollanders, by their great numbers of busses, pinkes, and line-boates: and also a discourse of the sea-coast townes of England, and the most fit and commodious places, and harbours that wee haue for busses, and of the small number of our fishermen, and also the true valuation, and whole charge, of building, and furnishing, to sea, busses, and pinks, after the Holland manner. By Tobias Gentleman, fisherman and marriner.
            Gentleman, Tobias.
         
         
            
               1614
            
         
         Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01617
            STC 11745
            ESTC S103037
            99838796
            99838796
            3185
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01617)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3185)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 838:03)
         
         
            
               
                  Englands vvay to vvin vvealth, and to employ ships and marriners: or, A plaine description of what great profite, it will bring vnto the common-wealth of England, by the erecting, building, and aduenturing of busses, to sea, a fishing With a true relation of the inestimable wealth that is yearely taken out of his Maiesties seas, by the Hollanders, by their great numbers of busses, pinkes, and line-boates: and also a discourse of the sea-coast townes of England, and the most fit and commodious places, and harbours that wee haue for busses, and of the small number of our fishermen, and also the true valuation, and whole charge, of building, and furnishing, to sea, busses, and pinks, after the Holland manner. By Tobias Gentleman, fisherman and marriner.
                  Gentleman, Tobias.
                  United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal. Proceedings. 1613?-07-19.
               
               [6], 46, [4] p.   
               
                  Printed [by Nicholas Okes] for Nathaniel Butter,
                  London :
                  1614.
               
               
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  "The States proclamation, translated out of Dutch", dated The Hague, 19 July [1613?], [4] p. at end.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Fisheries --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2002-09
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2002-10
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2002-11
            Jennifer KietzmanSampled and proofread
         
            2002-11
            Jennifer KietzmanText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2002-12
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            Englands VVAY TO VVIN Wealth, and to employ Ships and Marriners:
OR, A plaine description what great profite, it will bring vnto the Common-wealth of England, by the Erecting, Building, and aduenturing of Busses, to Sea, a fishing.
            With a true Relation of the inestimable wealth that is yearely taken out of his Maiesties Seas, by the Hollanders, by their great numbers of Busses, Pinkes, and Line-boates:
AND ALSO
A discourse of the Sea-coast Townes of England, and the most fit and commodious places, and Harbours that wee haue for Busses, and of the small number of our Fishermen, and also the true valuation, and whole charge, of Building, and Furnishing, to Sea, Busses, and Pinks, after the Holland manner.
            By Tobias Gentleman, Fisherman and Marriner.
            
               LONDON Printed for Nathaniel Butter. 1614.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE RIGHT NOBLE, LEARNED, AND TRVELY HONORABLE, HENRY, Lord HOWARD, Earle of Northhampton, Baron of Marnhill, Constable of the Castle of Douer, Lord Warden, Chancellour and Admirall of the Cinque Ports, Lord Priuy Seale, Knight of the most Noble Order of the 
                  •
               arter, and one of his Maiesties most Honourable Priuy Councell.
            RIGHT HONOVRABLE,
            
               SEeing that by Nature our Country challengeth a greater interest in vs, then our Parents, Friends, or Children can, and that we ought for preseruation thereof, oppose our liues vnto the greatest dangers: It is

the part of euery Natiue to endeauor something to the aduancement and profite thereof, and not to affect 
                  •
               t, for that wee possesse in it, but to loue it for it selfe, as being the common Mother and Nourisher of vs all. For mine owne part, albeit my short fadome can compasse no such great designe as I desire, yet from a willing minde (as hee that offerd his hands full of water to great Artaxerxes) I am bold to present this project of my honest and 
                  〈◊◊〉
               ; beseeching your L. whose 
                  〈◊◊〉
                truely enobled you, to take the 
                  〈◊◊〉
                your protection: And prefer it to the 
                  〈◊〉
                of our most Royall Soueraigne, recommending the good effecting thereof to his gracious fauor and 
                  •
               rtherance. Doubtlesse: your 
                  •
               tions and endeauours hauing

all bene full of virtue and goodnesse, are not the least preuailing motiues whereby his Maiesty hath so endeered you vnto him. In this then you shall not thinke your selfe disparaged, the matter being both honest and commendable, and in true valew of as great substance, as the offer of Sebastian Cabota, to King Henry the seuenth, for the discouery of the West Indies.
            
               Humbly at your Lordships commandement,
Tobias Gentleman.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            ENGLANDS WAY TO WIN WEALTH, AND TO IM
               ploy Ships and Marriners▪
               
            
            
            
               NOble Brittaines, for as much as it hath pleased the Almighty God to make vs a happy Nation, by blessing and enriching this Noble Kingdome with the sweete

dew of his heauenly word, truely and plentifully Preached amongst vs; and also in cytuating our Country in a most 
                  〈◊〉
                Clymate, &amp; stored with many rich &amp; 
                  〈◊〉
                Treasures for our 
                  〈◊〉
               , which also yeeldeth in aboundance all things necessary, 
                  •
               o that wee doe not onely excel other Nations in strength &amp; courage, but also a
                  •
                other Kingdomes 
                  〈◊◊〉
                are by our English 
                  〈◊◊〉
                &amp; cherished. It seemeth 
                  〈◊〉
                the 
                  〈◊〉
                of 
                  •
               ur gracious God, hath 
                  〈◊〉
                vs 
                  〈◊◊〉
                gemme vnto himse
                  •
                
               
                  〈◊◊◊〉
                Country with the plenteous 
                  〈◊◊〉
                &amp; 
                  〈◊〉
                of vs frō the whole Continent 
                  〈◊〉
                the rest of the inferiour world, by our rich and commodious Element of water, which in due seasons yeeldeth to vs in aboundance. For altho
                  •
               gh o
                  •
               r Champion Soile, by the 
                  〈◊〉
                of the Husbandman, be plentifull vnto vs: yet doth these watry Regions and Dominions yeeld yearely, great variety of all kind of most whole
                  •
               ome and 
                  〈◊〉
                fishes: so that it may seeme 
                  〈◊〉
                and 
                  •
               
               table, and hard to determine, 
                  〈◊〉
                of his Maiesties Dominions of the Land or Seas, bee richest. My selfe being the most 
                  〈◊〉
                of

all, in that I am no Sholler, but borne a Fishermans sonne by the Sea-side, and spending my youthfull time at Sea about 
                  •
               isher affaires, whereby now I am more skilfull in Nets, Lines, and Hookes, then in Rethoricke, Logicke, or learned bookes: yet in those fewe which I haue read, besides the instinct of nature, which maketh me to know that euery one should endeuour himselfe the best he is able to be beneficiall &amp; profitable to the Kingdome &amp; Common-wealth wherein hee is borne, which was a forceable motiue to incite me to thinke of this present discourse, the penning whereof was thus occasioned.
            It was my fortune, some two yeares past, to bee sent for into the company of one Maister Iohn Ke
                     •
                  mar, who is a man very well deseruing of his Country, and hee knowing me to haue experience in Fisher affaires, demanded of me the charge both of Busses and Line-boates, after the Hollanders fashion, and shewed vnto mee some few notes that hee had gathered and gotten from other men of my trade, which hee seemed greatly to esteeme of: for that himselfe was altogether vnexperimented in such businesse,

and further, I deliuered to him certaine principall notes which hee seemed greatly to esteeme; for that hee said that hee did mind to shew them vnto the right Honourable Counsell, whereupon I entred into the cogitation of writing this true relation out of my owne experience and knowledge, touching the Inestimable summes of money taken yearely for fish and herrings out of his Maiesties Seas by strangers, whereby they haue not onely maintained their warres many yeares against the Spaniard, both by Land &amp; Sea, he being one of the great Monarkes of the world, and at length, they haue not onely wearied him in the wars, and brought him to good termes &amp; reasonable composition; but also it is most apparant not withstanding the huge charge of their warres so long continued, which would haue made any other Nation poore and beggarly, they to the contrary are growne exceeding rich and strong in fortified Townes and beautifull Buildings, in pl
                  •
               ty of money and gold, in trade and trafficke with all other Nations, and haue so increased and multiplied their shipping and Marriners, that all other Nations and Countries in the world doe

admire them.
            Moreouer, whereas one Hauen in one of their Townes did in former times containe their ships and shipping with infinite cost, now they haue cut out two Hauens more to a Towne, and at this present, are all three Hauens scarce sufficient with roome enough to containe their Ships and shipping, and by reason of their industrious Fisher-trade, not one of their people are idle, nor none seene to begge amongst them, except they bee some of our owne English Nation.
            And what their chiefest tr
                  •
               de is, or their principall gold-mine, is well knowne to all Merchants that haue vsed those parts, and to my selfe and all Fishermen; namely that his Ma
                  •
               ies Seas is their chie
                  •
               st, principall, and onely rich Treasury, whereby they 
                  〈◊〉
                so long time maintained their warres, and haue so greatly prospered, and enriched themselues.
            If that their little Countrey of the vnited Prouinces can doe this, as it is most manifest before our eyes they do, then what may we his Maiesties Subiects doe, if this trade of fishing

were once erected among vs, wee hauing in our 
                  〈◊〉
                Coun
                  •
               ies sufficient store of all necessaries to 
                  〈◊〉
                the 
                  〈◊◊〉
               . For the Hollanders haue nothing growing in their owne land for that bu
                  •
               esse, but they are compelled to 
                  〈◊◊〉
                their wood▪ tymber, and planke, wherwith they build, &amp; make all their Ships of, out of diuers Countries, and their iron out of other 
                  〈◊〉
               
               ▪ their 
                  〈◊〉
                &amp; Cordig
                  •
                out of the 
                  〈◊◊〉
               
               ▪ their Hoopes and Barrellboords out of Norway &amp; Sprucia, their breadcorne out of Poland, &amp; East parts, their Mault, 
                  〈◊〉
                and 
                  〈◊〉
                d
                  •
               inke from England, &amp; also all their fish 
                  〈◊◊〉
                we
                  •
               lth out of his Maiesties S
                  •
               s.
            The which they doe transport vnto the foresaid 
                  〈◊〉
               , &amp; 
                  〈◊〉
                for the 
                  〈◊〉
                of 
                  〈◊〉
                and 
                  〈◊〉
               , the 
                  〈◊〉
                commodities, whereby their Ships and Marriners are set on worke, and continually multiplied, and into their countries is plentifull store of money and gold daily brought, onely for the sailes of fish and herrings.
            And their Countrey being, as it were, a small plot of ground in comparison of great

Brittaine, for two of his Maiesties Counties, Suffolke and Norfolke, do equall, if not exceed, in spaciousness▪ all their Prouinces, &amp; yet it is mani
                  •
               t, that for shipping and 
                  〈◊〉
                
               
                  •
               ring men, all England, Scotland, France and 
                  〈◊〉
               , 
                  •
               or quantity of shipping and Fisher men cannot make so great a number.
            Howsoeuer this may 
                  〈◊◊〉
                vnto many that doe not know it; yet doe I assure my selfe, that a great number besides my selfe know I 
                  〈◊〉
                nothing 
                  〈◊◊〉
                the 
                  〈◊〉
               .
            Wherefore seeing the great 
                  〈◊◊◊〉
                busines by the Busses, 
                  〈◊〉
               , or 
                  •
               
               ships, by 
                  〈◊〉
                of this profitable 
                  〈◊◊〉
                trade, which will bring plen
                  •
                
               
                  〈◊◊〉
                
               
                  •
               
               iesties 
                  〈◊〉
               , and be 
                  〈◊〉
                the 
                  〈◊〉
                good of the Common-wealth, in setting of many thousands of poore people on wor
                  •
               , 
                  〈◊〉
                now 
                  〈◊〉
                not how to 
                  〈◊〉
               , and 
                  〈◊◊〉
                the increasing of shippes and 
                  〈◊〉
               -men, which shall bee imployed about the taking of fish &amp; 
                  〈◊〉
                out of his 
                  〈◊〉
                own 
                  〈◊〉
               , as also 
                  •
               or the imploying of ships, and 
                  〈◊〉
                of M
                  •
               riners, for the 
                  〈◊〉
                o
                  •
                
               
                  〈◊〉
                Kingdome ag
                  •
               inst all 
                  〈◊◊〉
               , and

for the enriching of Merchants with transportation of Fish and Herrings into other Countries; and also for the bringing in of gold, and money, which now is growne but scarce, by reason that the Dutch and Hollanders haue so long time beene suffered to carry away our money and best gold for fish and Herrings, taken out of his Maiesties owne streames, which his Maiesties owne Subiects do want (and still are like to doe) if that they bee not forbidden for bringing vs of Fish and Herrings: And this worthy Common-wealthes businesse of Busses fostered and furthered by his Maiesties Honorable Councell, and the Worshipfull and wealthy subiects, by putting too of their helping Aduentures now at the first: for that those that bee now the Fisher-men, of themselues, be not able to beginne.
            Those poore Boates and sorry Nets that our 
                  •
               ishermen of England now haue, are all their chiefest wealthes, but were their ability better, they would soone be imploying themselues: for that it is certaine that all the Fisher-men of England do reioyce now at the very name and newes of building of Busses, with a most ioyfull

applaud, praying to God to further it for: what great profite and pleasure it will b
                  •
               ing they doe well vnderstand, and I will hereafter declare.
            First, I shall not neede to proue that it is lawfull for vs that bee his Maiesties owne Subiects to take with all dilligence the blessings that Almighty God doe yeerely send vnto vs at their due times and seasons, and which doe offer themselues freely and aboundantly to vs, in our owne Seas and nigh our owne sho
                  •
               s.
            S
                  •
               ondly, to proue that it is feacible for vs: for what can bee more plaine then that we see daily done before our eyes by the Hollanders, that haue nothing that they vse growing in their owne Land, but are constrained to fetch all out of other Countries; whereas we haue all things that shall bee vsed about that businesse growing at home in our owne Land, Pitch and Tarre onely excepted.
            Thirdly, to proue it will bee profitable, no man need 
                  •
               o doubt, for that we 
                  〈◊〉
                the Hollanders haue long 
                  〈◊〉
                their warres, and are neuerthelesse growne exceeding 
                  •
               ich, which are

things to be admited, in so much that themselues do call it, their Chiefest Trade, and principall Gold-mine, whereby many thousands of their people of Trades and Occupations, bee set on worke, well maintained, and do prosper. These be the Hollanders owne words in a Dutch Proclamation, and translated into English, and the coppy of that Proclamation is her
                  •
                annexed vnto the end of my booke.
            And shall wee neglect so great blessings: O slothfull England and carelesse Countrimen, Looke but on these fellowes 
                  〈◊◊〉
                call the plumpe Hollanders, be hold their dilligence in fishing, and our owne carelesse negligence.
            In the midst of the month of May doth the Industrious Hollanders beginne to make ready their Bu
                  •
               es and Fisher fleetes, and by the first of their Iune, are they yeerly ready, and s
                  •
               ne to saile out of the 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  , the 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  , and the Vly, a thousand 
                  〈◊〉
                together for to catch 
                  〈◊〉
                in the North seas.
            Sixe hundred of these Fisher-ships, and more, bee great Bu
                  •
               s some sixe score Tunnes, most of them 
                  〈◊〉
                a hundredth Tunnes and the rest three score and fifty Tunnes, the biggest of

them hauing foure and twenty men, some twenty men, and some eighteene and sixteene men a peece, so that their cannot bee in this Fleete of people no lesse then twenty thousand Sailors.
            These hauing with them bread, butter, and Holland-cheese, for their prouision, do daily ly get their other diet out of his Maiesties Seas, besides the lading of this Fleete three times a p
                  •
               ce, commonly before S. Andrew with Herrings, which being sold by them, but at the rate of ten pound the Last, Fl
                  •
               te vnto much more then the summe of one million of pounds Sterling onely by this Fleete of Busses yearely: no King vpon the earth did yet euer see such a Fleete of his owne Subiects at any time, and yet this Fleete is there, and then, yearely to bee seene: A most worthy sight it were, if they were my owne Country-men, yet haue I taken pleasure in being amongst them, to behold the neatnesse of their ships and Fisher-men, how euery man knoweth his owneplace, and all labouring merily together, whereby the poorest sort of themselues, their wiues, and children be well maintained, &amp; no want seene amongst thē.
            
               And thus North-west and by North hence along they steere, then being the very heart of Summer, and the very yoalke of all the yeare, sayiing vntill they do come vnto the Ile ofShotland is the greatest Ile of all the Orcades, &amp; lyeth in the heighth of 60. degrees of Northerly latitude. Shotland, which is his Maiesties Dominions, and with these gallant Fleete of Busses, there haue bene seene twenty, thirty, and forty ships of warre to waft and gaurd them from being pillaged and taken by their enemies, and Dun
               
                  •
                kars: but now the warres be ended, they do saue that great charge, for they haue not now aboue foure or sixe to looke vnto them for being spoyled by Rouers and Pirates.
            Now if that it happen that they haue so good a winde to be at Shotland before the 14. day of their Iune as most commonly they haue, then do they put all into Shotland, nigh Swinbornehead, into a Sownd called Braceies Sownd, and there they frolicke it on Land, vntill that they haue sucked out all the marrow of the Mault, and good Scotsh-ale, which is the best liquor that the Iland doth affoord: but the 14. day of Iune being once come, then away all of them go, for that is the first day, by their owne Law, before which time they must not lay a Net, for

vntill then the Herrings be not in season, nor fit to be taken to be salted.
            From this place, being nigh two hundred leagues from Yermouth, do they now first begin to fish, &amp; they do neuer leaue the Skoales of Herrings, but come along amongst them, following the Herrings as they do come, fiue hundred miles in length, and lading their ships twice or thrice, before they come to Yermouth, with the principall and best Herrings, and sending them away by the Marchant ships that cō
               meth vnto them, that bringeth them victuals, barrels, and more salt, and Nets if that they do need any, the which Ships that buyeth their herrings, they do call Herring-yagers, and these Yagers carry them &amp; 
                  •
               ell them in the East Countries, some to Reuell, and to Rie, and some so far as the Narue, and Russey, Stockhollume in Sweathen, Quinsbrough, Danske and Eluinge, and all Poland, Sprucia, and Pomerland, Letto, Burnt-hollume, Stateen, Lubicke and Youtland, and Denmarke.
            
            Returning Hemp, Flax, Cordige, Cables, and Iron, Corne, Sope-ashes, Wax, Weinskot, Clapholt, Pitch, Tarre, Mastes, and Spruce-deales, &amp; Hoopes, and Barrel-boords, &amp; plenty of siluer

and gold onely for their procedue of Herrings.
            Now besides this great Fleete of the Busses the Hollanders haue a huge number more of smaller Burthen onely for to take Herrings also, and these be of the Burthen, from fifty Tunnes vnto thirty Tunnes, and twenty tunnes; the greatest of them hauing twelue men a peece, and the smallest eight and nine men a peece, and these are Vessels of diuers fashions, and not like vnto the Busses, yet go they onely for Herrings in the season, and they bee called some of them, Sword-pinks, Flat-bottomes, Holland-toads, Crabskuits, and Yeuers, and all these, or the most part doe goe to Shot-land, but these haue no Yagers come vnto them but they go themselues home when they be laden, or else vnto the best Market: There haue bene seene and numbred of Busses, and these, in braces sound, and going out to Sea, and at Sea in sight, at one time, two thousand Sailes besides them that were at Sea without sight, which could not be numbred.
            It is Bartholmew-tide yearely before that they be come from Shotland, with the Herrings so

high as Yermouth, and all those Herrings that they doe catch in Yermouth Seas 
                  •
               rom Bartholmew-tide vntill S. Andrew the worst that be the roope-sicke Herrings that will not serue to make barreld Herrings by their owne Law, they must not bring home into Holland, wherefore they doe sell them for ready money, or gold, vnto the Yermouth-men, that be no Fisher-men but Merchants and Ingrosers of great quantities of Herrings, if that by any meanes they can get them, so that the Hollanders be very welcome guests vnto the Yermothian Herring-buyers, and the Hollanders doe call them their Hostes, and they doe yearely carry away from Yermouth many a thousand pound, as it is wel known but; these Hollanders with their ladings of the best, which they make their best brand herrings to serue for Lenton store, they send some for Burdeaux, some for R
                     •
                  
                  chell, Nantes, Morliax, and S. Mallaus, Cane in Normandy, Roan, Paris, Ameance, and all Pickardy, and Callice, and they doe returne from these places, Wines, Salt, Fethers, Rossin, Woad, Normandy Canuise, and Dowlas cloth, and money, and French Crownes, but out of all the Arch-dukes

Countries they returne nothing from thence but ready mony, in my owne knowledge, and their ready payment was all double Iacobuses, English twenty shilling peeces. I haue seene more there in one day: then euer I did in London at any time, for at Ostend, Newport, and Dunkirke, where and when the Holland pinks commeth in, there daily the Merchants, that be but women, but not such women as the fishwiues of Billinsgare, for these Netherland women do lade away many waggons with fresh fish daily, some for Bridges, and some for Brussels, Iper, Dixmew, and Rissels, and at Sasse, by Gant. I haue seene these women Merchants haue had their Apornes full of nothing but English Iacobuses, to make all their payment of, and such heapes and budget-fuls in the counting-houses of the fish-brokers, which made me much to wonder how they should come by them; andI haue seen
                     •
                   a small Haddocke sold there for two 
                     •
                  hillings sixe pence: and a Turbut for a Iacobus. also I know that Capons are not so deerely sold by the Poulters in Gratious Streete in London, as fresh fish is sold by the Hollanders, in all those Romaine Catholicke, and Papisticall Countries.
            And whereas I haue made but a true relation

of their Fleetes of Busses, and onely the Herring-fishermen that be on his Maiesties Seas from Iune vntill Nouember, I will here also set downe the fishermen that all the yeare long, in the seasons, do fish for Cod and Linges continually, going and returning laden with barreld fish.
            And these be Pinks and Wel-boats of the burthen of fourty Tunnes, and the smallest thirty Tunnes, and these haue some twelue men a peece, one with another, and their is of this sort of fisher-boates, beginning at Vlushing, Camefere, Surwick-sea, the Mase, the Tessell, &amp; the Fly, and the other sandy Ilands, about fiue hundred or sixe hundred Saile, which all the yeare long are fishing for Cod, whereof they do make their barreld fish, which they do transport in Summer into the East parts, but in Winter all France is serued by them, and all the Archdukes Countries before spoken of, both of barreld fish, and fresh fish, which they of purpose do keepe aliue in their boates in Wells; and to vs heere in England for loue of our strong Beare, they bring vs barreld fish in Winter, and carry away our money and gold euery day

in great quantities.
            Besides all these Pinks and Wel boats, the Hollanders haue continually in the season, an other Fleete of Fisher-man, at the North-east head of Shotland which be of an other quality, and there is more then two hundred of these, and these be called Fly-boats, and these do ride at ankor all the season at Shotland, in the fishing grounds, and they haue small boats within them which be like vnto Cobles, the which they do put out to lay &amp; hale their lines &amp; hookes, whereby they do take great store of Lings, the which they do not barrell, but splet them and salt them in the Ships Bulke, and these they fell commonly for foure and fiue pounds the hundreth, and these go by the name of Holland-lings, but they are taken out of his M
                  •
               iesties Seas, and were Shotland lings before they tooke them there, and for these Lings they do carry away aboundance of Englands best money daily.
            Now hauing declared according vnto truth, the numbers of their Fishermen of Holland, for 
                  〈◊〉
                vpon his Maiesties Seas, and also of their Pinks, and Wel-boates, and their

courses for taking, and venting and selling of their barreld fish, and fresh-fish and also of their Flie-boates at the North-east head of Shotland, for Shotland-lings: I thinke it now best, truely to shew the true number of our English Fishermen, and how they do imploy themselues all the yeare long, first beginning at Colchester nigh the mouth of the Theames and so proceed Northward.
            I can scarce affoord these men of that water the name of Fishermen, for that their chiefest trade is dreggin of Oisters; yet haue they in the Summer some eight or ten boates in the North-seas for Cods, which if that they happen to spend all their salt, and to speed well, they may get some twenty pound in a Summer cleere: but heere by the way, I will make knowne a great abuse that is offered to the Common-wealth, and especially to all the herring fishermen of England, onely by those men of Colchester water.
            For these men from S. Andrew vntill Candlemas, &amp; some times longer, do set forth stale-boates, amongst the sands, in the Theames mouth, for to take sprats, with great stale-nets, with a

great poake, and they standing in the Swinn
                  •
                or the Kings channell on the backe of the Gunfleate, they do there take in steed of sprats, infinite thousands of yong Herrings, smaller then Sprats, and not good to be eaten, for one Sprat is better worth then twenty of those Bleakes, or yong Herrings, but because they do fill the Bushell at Billingsgate where they do sell them for Sprats, the which, if that they were let liue, would all be at Midsummer a Fat Summer full He
                  •
               ring, and a pecke is sometime there sold for 2. pence which number of herrings at Midsummer, would make a barrell of Summerherrings, worth 20. or 30. shillings.
            If that rhey could take the Sprats it were good, for they be good victuals for the Citty, but for euery Cart-load or Bushell of Sprats, they take a hundred Cart-loads, or Bushels of these yong herrings, which be the very spawnes of the Skoales of the herrings that commeth from Shotland euery Summer, and when as they come into Yermouth Seas yearely about S. Luke, and sometimes before, if that it do blow a hard Easterly wind, do alwaies at that season become Roope-sicke and do

spawne and become Shotten betwixt Wintertonnesse, and O
                     •
                  fordnesse, and those frey of that spawne, those yong little creatures, by the wisedome of the great Creator, seeketh into the shoare, and shallow places, there to be norished, and also into the Theames mouth into the sweetest waters; for that the water nigh the shoare, and in the Theames mouth is not so brine salt, as it is farther of into the deepe water, where these Bleakes yearely seeking to be nourished, they be alway at that season taken and destroyed: but if that these men will needs vse their stale-boates and nets, let them go where the good Sprats be, they must then stand at Orfordnesse, and in Donwich-bay, where there be cellent sprats, and for the good of all the Herring-fishermen of England, I wish that they might be prohibited to sell that which is not wholesome to be eaten, which is as much as to sell hemlocks for perseneps.
            The next to Colchester, is Harwich water, a royall harbour, and a propper Towne, fit for the vse of Busses, no place in all Holland comparable, for their is both land and strand and dry beach enough for foure hundreth

Saile, but the chiefest Trade of the Inhabitants of this place, is with Caruiles for New-castle coales, but they haue three or foure Ships yearely that they do send to Isle-land for Cod and Lings, from March vntill September, and some yeares they get, and some times loose, but if that they had but once the trade of Busses, this would soone be a fine place. but those Caruiles and Ships which they now haue be all their chiefest wealth.
            Sixe miles vp Harwich water stands Ipswich, which is a gallant Towne, and rich; this Towne is such a place for the Busses, as in all England and Holland I know no place so conuenient: first it is the best place in all England for the building of Busses, both for the plenty of Timber and Planke, and excellent workemen for making of Ships, there is more there, then there is in sixe of the best Townes in all England: Secondly, it is a principall place for good Huswiues, for spinning of yarne, for the making of pouldauice, for there is the best that is made: which Towne with the vse of making of Twine, will soone be the best place of all England for to prouide Nets for the Busses.
            
               It is also a most conuenient place for the wintering of the Busses, for that all the shoares of that Riuer is altgether oose and soft ground, fit for them to lye on in winter.
            Also the lpswich men be the chiefest MarchantThis Towne is a most fit and conuenient place to make a staple towne for corne, for all England, for the returne and saile of the 
                     〈◊〉
                   herring from 
                     〈◊〉
                  , and Poland. Aduenturers of all England for all the East-lands, for the Suffolke cloathes: and they haue their Factors lying all the yeare long in all those places where the Hollanders do vent their Herrings, and where the best price and saile is continually. And although that yet there bee no fisher-men, yet haue they store of Sea-faring men, and for Maisters for the Busses they may haue enow from Yermouth and Sowld and the Sea coast Townes downe their Riuer, from Nacton, and Chimton, Holbroke, Shotly, and Cowlnes, they may get men that will soone be good fishermen with but a little vse, for vnderstand thus much, that there is a kind of emulation in Holland betweene the Fishermen that goeth to Sea in Pinks and Line-boats, Winter and Summer, and those Fishermen that goeth in the Busses, for they in the Pinkes make a skorne of them in the Busses, &amp; do call them Koe-milkens, or Cow-milkers, for in deed the most part of

them be men of occupations in winter, or else Country-men, and do milke the Cowes themselues, and make all the Holland Cheese, when they be at home.
            This place is also most conuenient for the erecting of Salt-pans, for the making of Salt vpon salt, for that the Harbour is so good that at all times Ships may come vnto them with Salt from Mayo, or Spanish salt to make the brine or pickell, and also the Caruiles from New-castle with coales, for the boyling of it at the cheapest rates at any time, may come thither. To the North-east of this place, three or foure leagues is Orford-hauen, and the Townes of Orford and Alborough especially, be many good Fishermen, and there is belonging to those Townes some forty or fifty North sea boates, that yeerely goeth to Sea, hauing seuen men a peece, and ten or twelue Island Barkes, which sometimes get something, and sometime little or nothing; if that these mens wealth were in Busses and Nets, and had but once the trade, they would put downe the Hollander, for they be great plyers of any voiage that they do vndertake.
            
               About three leagues to the Northward is Sowld-hauen, and in the Townes of Sowld, donwich,
               
                  Donwich in ancient times, ha
                     •
                  h bene the seate of the Kings of the East Angles, but now all ruined. and Walderswicke be a very good breed of Fishermen, and there is belonging vnto those three Townes, of North-sea Boates some 20. Saile, and of Island Barkes some fifty Saile, which yearely they send for God and Lings to Island: This Towne of Sowld, of a Sea coastMy father liued in 
                     〈◊〉
                   Towne 
                     〈◊〉
                   hee was 
                     〈◊◊〉
                   of age, and gaue these Composition Lings seuenty yeeres, 
                     〈◊〉
                   foHre 
                     〈◊〉
                  , viz K. 
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     , Q. Mary, Q. 
                     
                        •
                     
                     lizabeth, and vntill the 
                     〈◊〉
                   yeare of the raigne of our most 
                     〈◊〉
                   Soueraigne, which 
                     〈◊〉
                   to much more then one thousand pound, f
                     •
                  r one man of that Towne. Towne, is the most beneficiall vnto his Maiesty of all the Townes in England, by reason all their trade is vnto Island for Lings, and his Maiesties Seriant Cater hath yearely gratis, out of euery Ship and Barke, one hundreth of the choysest and fairest Lings, which be worth more then ten pound the hundred, and they call them Composition fish: But these men of this place, are greatly hindred, and in a manner vndone, by reason of their Hauen is so bad, and in a manner often stopped vp with Beach and Chingle-stone, that the winde and the 
                  •
               ide and the Sea do beate thether, so that many time, in the season, when they be ready to go to Sea, they can not get out when time is to go to Sea, neither can they get in when they returne from Sea, but oftentimes do 
                  〈◊〉
                away

their goods and themselues: This Hauen if that it had but a South peire built of Timber, would be a far better H
                  •
               uen then Yermouth Ha
                  •
               n, with one quarter of the cost that hath bene bestowed on Yermouth Hauen, they be now suiters vnto his Maiestie, God grant they may speed, for it is pittifull the trouble and damage, that all the men of these three Townes do daily sustaine by their naughty Harbour.
            To the North-ward of Sowld-hauen, three leagues is Kirkley and Layestof decayed Townes, they haue sixe or seuen North-sea Boates, but them of Layestof make benefite yearely of buying of Herrings of the Hollanders, for likewise these Hollanders be Hosted with the Layestof men, as they be with the Yermothians.
            To the North-ward 2. leagues is the Towne of great Yermouth, very beautifully builded,In all his Maiesties Kingdomes not any Towne comparable vnto it for braue buildings. vpon a very pleasant and sandy plaine of three mile in length, this Towne is a place of great resort of all the Herring fishermen of England, for thether do resortall the Fishermen of the Cinque Ports, and all the rest of the West Countrimen of England, as far as Burport and

L
                  •
               ne in Dorcetshire, and those Herrings that they do take they do not barrell, because their Boates be but small things, but they sell all vnto the Yermouth herring-buyers for ready mony, and also the Fishermen of the North-countries beyond Scarborough and Robin-hoods bay and some as far as the Bishopricke of Durham do thether resort yearely, in poore little Boates called fiue men Cobbles, &amp; all the Herrings that they do take they do sell fresh vnto the Yermouth-men to make red Herrings. Also to Yermouth doth daily come in to the Hauen, vp to the Key, all or the most part of the great Fleet of Hollanders, which before I made relation of, that go in the Swoard-pinks, Holland-toads, Crabskuits, Walnut-shels, and great and small Yeuers, 100. and 200. Saile at one time together, and all their Herings that they do bring in, they do sell them all for readdy mony to the Yermouth men: And also the French men of Pickardy 
               And Norman
                        •
                     y.
                some hundred Saile of them at a time do come thither, and all, the herrings they catch they sell fresh vnto these herring-mongers of Yermouth for ready gold; so that it amonnteth vnto a great sum of mony, that the Hollanders &amp; Frenchmē do cary away,

from Yermouth, yearely, into Holland and France, which mony doth neuer come againe into England: This Towne is very well gouerned by wise and ciuell Magistrates, and good orders carefully obserued for the mainetenance of their Hauen and Corporation, and this Towne, by reason of the cituation, and the frech Riuers that belongeth to it: one vp to the Citty of Norwich, and another that runneth far vp into Suffolke, a butter and cheese country, about B
                     •
                  nga and Betkels; and a third that runneth far vp into 
                  •
               legg, a Corne Country, by reason whereof this Towne of Yermouth is alwaies well serued with all kind of prouision at all times plentifully, at good and cheape rates, whereby they of the Towne do relieue the strangers, and also do benefite themselues: To this Towne belongeth some twenty Island Barkes, which yearely they do send for Cods and Lings, and some hundreth and fifty Saile of North-sea boates, they make a shift to liue, but if that they had the vse of Busses, and also barreld fish, they would excell all England and Holland, for they be the onely fishermen for North-seas, and also the best for the handling

of their fish that be in all this land.
            The Herring buyer of Yermouth doth pro
               
                  •
               ite more then doth the Fishermen of Yermouth, by reason of the resort of the Hollanders, for that they are suffered to sell all their roope-sicke Herrings at Yermouth, to the Merchants there, and also the barreld fish that the Flemmings do bring in Winter to London,
                  
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     , 
                        〈◊〉
                     
                     ▪
                   and 
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     .
                do also gale them, but for that our Fishermen may, if they please, make barreld fish themselues, and therefore I will not mone them.
            The Merchant herring-buyer of Yermouth that hath a stocke of his owne, so long as heeYermouth Hauen is the onely refuge, in 
                     〈◊◊〉
                   whether, for all the Fishermen of the Cinque ports, and all other that 
                     〈◊◊◊◊◊〉
                  , and it is 
                     〈◊◊◊〉
                   timper, against the violence of the 
                     〈◊〉
                   sea▪ It is now in great danger to come to ruine, if they haue not help in time. can make his gaines so certaine with buying of Roope-sicke herrings of the Hollanders, will neuer lay out his mony to build or set forth Busses, and the Fisher-men be now so poore, by reason that they onely do beare the whole charge of that costly Hauen; the Merchant herring-buyers being not at any charge thereof, but all that great cost commeth out of the Fishermens labours, for the maintenance of that wodden Hauen, which amounteth to some fiue hundred pound a yeare, and some yeares more: so that though they be willing, yet there

ability will not suffer them to do it, 
                  •
               either can they forbeare their mony for to aduenture their 
                  •
               gs into the East Countries where the best sailes alwaies be.
            To the North▪wards of Yermonth eight leagues, are the Townes of Blakney and Wels, good Harbours and 
                  〈◊〉
                for Busses, and they haue good store of fishermen, and these townes haue some twenty Saile of Barkes, that they do ye
                  •
               ely send vnto Island; but these Townes be greatly deca
                  •
               ed, to that they haue bene in the times passed, the which places, if that they had but 20. Busses belonging to them, would soone grow rich Townes in short time.
            Then is there Lin a propper gallant Towne▪ for Sea-faring men, and for men for Island; this is a rich Towne, and they haue some twenty Saile of Island ships, that they yearely send for Cods and Lings, and I am in hope to see them fall to the vse of Busses as soone as any men.
            To the Northward is Boston, a propper Towne, and like vnto Holland soyle for low grounds and sands comming in, but yet there is but few Fishermen, but it is a most fit place

for Busses, if that they had but once the taste of them they would soone finde good liking.
            Next to 
                  〈◊〉
                some 20. leagues to the Northward, is the great riuer of Humber, wherein there is Hull, a very proper Towne of Saylors and Shipping, but there be but few fishermen but it is a most conuenient place for to aduenture Busses.
            There is also Grimsbey, Paul, and Pat
                  •
               ington: in all these places now there is great store of poore and idle people, that know not how to liue, and the most of all these places be decayed, and the best of them all grow worse and worse, which with the vse of Busses would soone grow rich Merchant-townes as is in Holland, for 
                  〈◊〉
                these places would be transported out of the East-lands all manner of commodities, for the vse of Busses, and houses, and worke-yards erected for Coopers, and Rope-makers, &amp; great numbers of Ne
                  •
               akers, and with the recourse of the Ships that shall bring salt and other commodities, &amp; ships that shall lade away their Herrings and Fish, these places will soone become populous, and mony stirring plentifull in these places returned

for the procedue of fish and Herrings which places now bee exceeding poore and beggarly.
            In all these fisher Townes that I haue before named, as Colchester, Harwith, Orford, Alborough, Donwich, wa
                     •
                  derswicke, Sowld, Yermouth, Blackney, Wels, Lin, Boston, and Hul: These be all the chiefest Townes, and all that vseth the North-seas in Summer and all these Townes it is well knowne be 
                  •
               inated.
            In all these Townes I know to be o—o Island Barkes, and o—o North-sea Boates, and all these Fishermen hauing o—o men a peece, amounteth to the summe of o—o. But admit that there is in all the West Country of England of Fisher-boats, tag and rag, that bringeth home all fresh fish, which seldome or neuer vseth any salt: say that they haue o—o men a peece, which make the summe of o—o in all England; but in all these I haue not reckonedI 
                     〈◊〉
                   pardon, for that I omit the particular numbers and 
                     〈◊〉
                   summe, which I could heere 
                     〈◊〉
                   downe, if I were commanded. the Fishermen, Mackrel-catchers, nor the Cobble-men of the North-country, which hauing o—o men a peece, commeth to so 
                  •
               ny men in all England.
            But so many in all England, and I haue truely

shewed before, that the Hollander hath in one Fleete of Busses twenty thousand Fishermen, besides all them that goeth in the Sword pinks, Flat▪ bottomes, Carbl kuits, Walnut-shels, and great Yeuers, wherein there is not lesse then 12000. more, and all these are onely for to catch Herrings in the North seas.
            Besides all them that goeth in the Flye-boates, for Shotland Lings, and the Pinks for barreld fish, and Trammell Boates, which commeth vnto 5000. more.
            So that it is most true, that as they haue the summe of o—o Fishermen more then their is in all this Land: and by reason of there Busses, and Pinks, and Fishermen that set their Merchant Ships on worke, as that they haue 
                  〈◊〉
                Fishermen more then we haue, so haue they o—o and o—o ships &amp; Marriners more then we.
            Now in our summe of o—o Fishermen, let vs see what vent haue we for our fish into other Countries, and what commodites and coine is brought into this Kingdome, and what Ships are set on worke by them, whereby Marriners are bred, or imployed, not one: It's pittifull.
            
               For when our Fishermen commeth home, the first voyage 
                  •
               rom the North-seas, they goe either to London, Ipswich, Yermouth, Lin, Hull, or Scarbrough, and there they do sell at good 
                  •
               ates, the first voyage, but the second voyage, because that they which be now the Fishermen haue not yet the right vse of making of barreld fish wherewith they might serue France, as doth the Hollanders, they be now constrained to sell in England, for that it is staple fish, and not being barreld the French will not buy it.
            But if that our Fishermen had but once the vse of Pinks and Line-boats, and barreld fish, then they might serue France as well as the Hollanders, which by this new trade of Busses being once erected, and Pinks, and Line-boats, after the Holland manner, there will be Fishermen 
                  •
               now to manage the Pinks for barreld fish, from Nouember vnto the beginning of May, onely the most part of those men that shallbe maintained by the Busses, for that when the Busses do leaue worke, in the Winter their men shall haue employment, by the Pinks, for barreld fish, which men, now, do little or nothing,

for this last Winter at Yermouth, there was three hundreth Idle men that could get nothing to do, liuing very poore for lacke of imployment, which most gladly would haue gone to sea in Pinks, if there had bene any for them to go in.
            And whereas I before said, that there was not one Ship set on work by our Fishermen, there may be obiected against me this.
            That there doth euery yeare commonly lade at Yermouth 4. or 5. London Ships for the Streights, which is sometimes true, &amp; the YermouthNo more English, but two small Shippes, this yeare lad
                     •
                  d there. men themselues do yearely send 2. or 3. Ships to Bourdeaux, and 2. or 3. Boates laden with herrings to Roan, or to Nance, or S. Mallaus, whereby there is returned, Salt, Wines, Normandy Canuice, whereby the King hath some custome, but there is no mony returned into England for these Herrings, which cost the Yermothians ready gold before that they had them of the Hollanders, and Frenchmen, to lade these Ships, and therefore I may boldly say not one.
            And this last yeare, now, the Hollanders themselues haue also gotten that trade, for there

did lade twelue Sailes of Holland Ships withNote heere how the Hollanders employ themselues and th
                     •
                  r Ships, fi
                     •
                  st in taking of the 
                     〈◊〉
                   quick, and yet are not content but catch them againe 
                     〈◊〉
                   they bee dead, and doe 
                     〈◊〉
                   both their ships and Marriners on worke, and English ships 
                     〈◊〉
                   vp a rotting. red herrings at Yermo
                  •
               , for 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  , Ligorne, Genoa, and Marsellis, and 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  , most of them being laden by the English Merchants, so that if this be suffered, the English owners of Ships shall haue but small imployment for theirs.
            Now to shew truely, what the whole charge of a Busse will be, with all her furniture, as Masts, Sailes, Ankors, 
                  〈◊〉
               , and with all her Fishers implements, and 
                  〈◊〉
               , at the first prouided all new, is a great charge, she being betweene 30. or 40. Last, will 
                  〈◊〉
                some fiue hundred pound.
            By the Grace of God the Ship or Busse will continue twenty yeare with small cost and reparations, but the yearely slite and weare of her tackell, and war-ropes, and Ne
                  •
               s will cost some eighty pounds.
            And the whole charge for the keeping of her at Sea for the whole Summer, or three voiages, for the filling of a hundred Last of Caske, or Barrels.
            
               
               
                  
                     100. Last of Barrels—72.
                     A huudreth Last ofIf any will know. all the perticulars of weyes of Salt, or barrels of Beere, or 
                              •
                           
                           dreths of Biskets, I will willingly resolue them, but here is all the whole charge, and with the most. Barrels, filled and sold at 10. pounds the Last commeth to one thousand pound.
                  
                  
                     For salt 4. months—88.
                      
                  
                  
                     Beere 4. moneths—42.
                      
                  
                  
                     For bread 4. months—21.
                      
                  
                  
                     Baken and Butter—18.
                      
                  
                  
                     For pease 4. months—03.
                      
                  
                  
                     For billet 4. months—03.
                     Herrings 1000. li.
                  
                  
                     For mens wages 4. M. 88.
                     The whole charge 335.
                  
                  
                     ———
                     ———
                  
                  
                     335.
                     gotten. 0665.
                  
               
            
            Heere plainly appeareth that there is gottenAnd I haue rated the herrings but at 10. pound the Last, which is with the least, for they bee commonlysoid by the Hollanders at Danske, for 15. and 20. pounds the Last. 665. pounds 
                  〈◊〉
                one Summer, whereout if that you do deduct one hundreth pounds for the weare of the Ship, and the reparations of her Nets against the next Summer, yet still there is 565. pounds remaining for cleare gaines, by one Busse, in one yeare.
            The Hollanders do make the profite of their Busses so certaine, that they do lay out their owne childrens mony, giuen them by their deceased friends in aduenturing in the Busses, and also there is in Holland a Treasury for Orphants, opened and layd out in aduenturing in the Busses.
            The Hollanders do make both a profitable,

and a pleasant Trade of this Summer fishing, for there was one of them, that hauing a gallant great new Busse of his owne, and he hauing a daughter married vnto one which was his Mate in the Bu
                  •
               e, and the owner that was Maister of this Busse did take his wife with him aboord, and his Mate his wife, and so they did set saile for the North▪seas, with the two women with them, the mother and the daughter, where hauing a faire wind, and being fishing in the North-seas, they had soone filled their Busse with herrings, and a Herring Yager commeth vnto them, and brings them gold and fresh supplies, and copeth with them, and taketh in their herrings for ready monyReady 
                     〈◊〉
                   or Tallyes, which are as bils of exchange to bee paid at first sight. and deliuereth them more barrels and salt, and away goeth the Yager for the first Market into Sprucia, and still is the Busse fishing at sea, &amp; soone after againe, was full laden, and boone home, but then another Yager commeth vnto him as did the former, &amp; deliuering them more prouision of barrels and Salt, and ready mony and bid them fare-well, and still lyeth at Sea with the mother and daughter so long and not very long, before they had againe all their

Barrels full, and then they sailed home into▪ Holland, with the two women, and the Busse laden with Herrings, and a thousand pounds of ready mony.
            If that any man 
                  •
               hould make any question of the truth of this, it will be v
                  •
               ry credibly approued by diuerse of good credite that be now in the Citty of London.
            Now to shew the charge of a pinke of eighteene or tweene Last, the Pinke being builded new, and all things new vnto her, will not cost two hundred and sixty pounds, with all her Lines, Hookes, and all her Fisher appurrenances.
            
               
                  
                     And 15. Last of Barrels will cost——
                     10.
                  
                  
                     Fiue weyes of salt vpon salt——
                     15.
                  
                  
                     For Beere and Caske———
                     07.
                  
                  
                     For bread—————
                     03.
                  
                  
                     For butter—————
                     01.
                  
                  
                     For the Petty tally————
                     01.
                  
                  
                     For mens wages for 2 mo. M. &amp; all toge:▪
                     
                     20.
                  
                  
                      
                     ———
                  
                  
                      
                     57.
                  
               
            
            Fifteene last of barreld fish at 14. pound, and 8. shillings the Last, which is but 24. shillings

the barrell amounteth vnto two hundreth and sixteene pounds, whereout if that you do deduct fifty and seuen pounds, for the charge of setting her to sea, their is still resting one hundreth fifty and eight pounds cleere gaines, by one Pinke, with fifteene Last of fish for two months.
            Wherefore, seeing the profite so plainely, and by the grace of God so certaine, both by the Busses and Line-boates, whereby the Hollanders haue so long gained by, Let all Noble Worshipsull, and wealthy Subiects, put too their aduenturing and helping hands, for the speedy lanching, and floating forward of this great good Common-wealth businesse, for the strengthening of his Maiesties Dominions, with two principall pillars, which is, with plenty of coine brought in for fish, and herrings from other Nations, and also for the increasing of Marriners against all forraigne Inuasions, and also for the bettering of Trades and Occupations, and setting of thousands of poore and idle people on worke, which now know not how to liue, which by this Trade of the Busses shall be imployed, as daily we see is done before

our eyes by the Hollanders. And as alwaies it hath bene seene, that those that be now the Fishermen of England, haue bene alwaies found to be sufficient to serue his Maiesties ships in former time, when their haue bene employment, which fellowes, by this new trade of building, and setting forth Busses will be greatly multiplyed and encreased in this Land; which fellowes, as we see the Hollanders, being well-fed in Fisher affaires, and strong and lustier then the Sailors that vse the long Southerne voyages, that sometimes are greatly surfeited, and hunger-pined▪ But these couragious, yong, lusty, fed-strong yonkers, that shall qe bred in the Busses, when his Maiesty shall haue haue occasion for their seruice in warre, against the enemy, will be fellowes for the nonce, and will shew themselues right English, and will put more strength to an Iron Crow, at a peece of great Ordinance in trauersing of a Cannon, or Culuering, with the direction of the experimented Maister Gunner, then two or three of the fore-named surfeited Sailors, and in distresse of winde growne sea, and fowle Winters weather, for flying forward

to their labour, for pulling in a tops
                  •
               ile, or a spret saile, or shaking of a bonnet in a dark night, for wet and cold can not make them shrinke nor staine, that the North-seas, and the Busses, and Pinks haue dy
                  •
               d in graine, for such purposes.
            And whosoeuer shall go to Sea, for Captaine to command in Marshall affaires, or take charge for Maister in trade of Merchandize, (as in times past I haue done both) will make choice of these fellowes, for I haue seene their resolution, in the face of their enemy, whenIt is not vnknowne, that this last yeare there was a generall presse along the Coast of England, frō 
                  Hull in Yorkeshire vnto S. Michaels Mo
                     •
                  nt in Corne-wall, onely for Sailors, to furnish but 7. Shippes, for the wafting ouer of the Count Pallatine, and his most Noble Princes, but 28. leagues. they haue b
                  •••
                
               l
                     •
                  g
                     ••
                  menta, and frolicke, and as forward as about their ordinary labours, or businesse.
            And when his Maiesty shall haue occasion and imployment for the furnishing of his Nauy there will be no want of Maisters, Pilots, Commanders, and sufficient directors of a course, and keeping of Computation, but now there is a pittifull want of sufficient good men. to do the offices and labours before spoken of, all which, these men of the Busses and Pinks, will worthily supply.
            And to the Art of Sayling they may happily

               
                  〈◊〉
               , for 
                  〈◊〉
                it hath beene com
               
                  •
                seene, that those men, that haue beene brought vp, in their youth, in Fishery, haue des
                  •
               ued as well as any in the land for artificiall Sayling; for at this time is practised all the proiections of Circular and Mathematicall skales and Arithmeticall sayling, by diuers of the yong men of the Sea-coast Townes, euen as commonly amongst them as amongst the Themse
                  •
               .
            Besides all the Hollanders before spoken of, the Frenchmen of Pickardy haue also a hundred Saile of Fishermen, onely for Herrings,Some of these be 3. and 4. score Tunnes the burthen. on his Maiesties Seas euery yeare, in the Summer season, and they bee almost like vnto the Busses, but they haue not any Yagers that commeth vnto them, but they do lade themselues, and returne home twice euery yeare, and finde great profite by their making but of two voyages euery Summer season.
            And it is much to bee lamented, that wee hauing such a plentifull Countrey, and such 
                  〈◊〉
                of able and idle people, that not one of his Maiesties Subiects, are there to

be se
                  •
               ne all the whole Summer, to fish, or toThe Hollanders do yearely take so many, as they do make more th
                     •
                  n two millions of pound Sterling. take one Herring: But onely the North-sea boats of the Sea-coast Townes, that goeth to take Cods, they do take so many as they do need to baite their hookes and no more.And wee his Maiesties Subiects doe take no more then doe. baite our hookes.
            
            We are daily skorned by these Hollands, for being so negligent of our profite, and carelesse of our fishing, and they do daily floute vs that be the poore Fishermen of England, to our faces at Sea, calling to vs and saying, Ya English, ya zall, or cud scoue dragien, which in English is this: Yon English, we will make you glad for to weare our old shoes.
            And likewise the French-men they say we are apish, for that we do still imitate them in all needlesse and fantasticall iagges and fashions, as it is most true indeed, for that they haue no fashion amongst them in apparell, nor Lace, Points, Gloues, Hilts, nor Garters, euen from the spangled Shoe-lachet, vnto the spangled Hat, and Hat-band, be it neuer so idle, and costly, but after that we do once get it, it is far bettered by our Nation.
            Wherefore, seeing that we can excell all other Nations, wastfully, to spend mony, let

Vs, in one thing, learne of other Nations, to get thousands out of his Maiesties Sea, and to make a generall profite 
                  〈◊〉
                the benefites that Al mighty God do
                  •
               h yearely send vnto vs, in far more greater aboundance then the fruite of our trees, which although they be more chargeable in the gathering together, yet is the profite far more greater, vnto this Kingdome, and Common wealth of all his Maiesties Subiects, increasing the wealth of the aduenturers; as also for the enriching of Merchants, and maintaining of Trades Occupations, and employing of Ships, and encreasing of Marriners, which now do but little or nothing: as also for the setting of poore and idle people on worke, which now know not how to liue, and to teach many a tall fellow to know the propper names of the ropes, in a ship, and to hale the 
                  〈◊〉
               
               The 
                     〈◊◊〉
                  : The Sea 
                     〈◊〉
                   the Gallowes refuse none. that now for lacke of employment many such, by the inconuenience of idle liuing, are compelled to end their daies, with a rope by an vntimely death, which by the employment of the Busses might be well a
                  •
               oyded, and they in time become right honest feruiceable and trusty Subi
                  •
               cts.
            
               Here since my booke came to the 
                  〈◊〉
               , I haue bene credibly certified, by 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                  . 
                     
                        〈◊◊〉
                     , M. 
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      To
                        •
                     , 
                  
                     •
                  nd 
                     〈◊〉
                   others of the Company of Fishmongers. men of good worth (being 
                  〈◊〉
               ) that since Christmas last, vnto this day, there hath bene paid to the Hollanders, here in London, onely for b
                  •
               rreld fish, and Holland Lings, the summe of twelue thousand pound.
            And 
                  〈◊〉
                of all, if that there be any of the Worshipfull Aduenturers, that would haue any di
                  •
                for the building of these Busses, or Fisherships, because I know that the Ship
               
                  •
                of England, be not yet skilfull in this matter, wherefore if that any shall bee pleased 
                  〈◊◊〉
                to me, I will bee willing to giue them directions, and pl
                  •
               ine proiections, and G
                  •
               icall demonstrations for the right building of them, both for length, bredth, and depth, and also for their mould vnder water, and also for the 
                  〈◊〉
                of their roomes, and the laying of their g
                  •
               ,And for prouiding of their Cordige, and Nets, after the most 
                     •
                  est &amp; cheapest rates. according to the Hollanders fashion, any man shall heare of me at M. 
                  
                     〈◊◊〉
                  , a Stationers Shop at Saint 
                  〈◊〉
                g
                  •
                in P
                  •
                Charch-yard: Farewell this 
                  〈◊〉
               . of February.
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            The States Proclamation, Translated out of Dutch.
            
               The 
                  •
               ates 
                  〈◊〉
                of the United Pro
                  •
                of the low 
                  〈◊◊〉
                all those that shall see 
                  〈◊◊〉
                these presents 
                  〈◊〉
               , 
                  〈◊〉
                let to 
                  〈◊〉
                that 
                  〈◊〉
                it is 
                  •
               ell 
                  〈◊〉
               , that the great 
                  •
               
               ing, and 
                  〈◊〉
                of he
                  •
               gs is the chiefest Trade, and 
                  〈◊〉
               -mine of these United 
                  〈◊◊〉
                many thousands of 
                  〈◊〉
               
               ▪ 
               
                  〈◊〉
               , 
                  〈◊〉
               , Trades and 
                  〈◊〉
               , are 
                  〈◊◊〉
                worke, well maintained, and 
                  〈◊〉
               ; e
                  •
               ally the Sailing and 
                  〈◊〉
               , as 
                  〈◊〉
                
               
                  •
               thin, as without these 
                  〈◊〉
               , is 
                  〈◊◊〉
                great esteemation: Moreouer 
                  〈◊◊〉
                of 
                  •
               ey, with the increase of the 
                  〈◊〉
                
               
                  •
               yes, 
                  •
               
               stomes, and 
                  〈◊〉
                of these Countries are augmented thereby 
                  〈◊◊〉
               , and for asmuch as there is 
                  〈◊◊◊〉
                to 
                  〈◊◊〉
                good Orders conseruing the 
                  〈◊〉
               , 
                  〈◊〉
               , and

beneficial vttering of the said 
                  〈◊〉
               , to the end to preserue and maintaine the 
                  〈◊◊〉
                Trade, in the United Prouinces; which Trade, by 
                  〈◊〉
                encounters, of some that seeke their owne ga
                  •
               , is enuied, in respect of the great good it bringeth to the United 
                  〈◊〉
               : and 
                  •
               e are informed that a new deuise is put in practise to the pr
                  •
                of the Trade, to transpor
                  •
                out of the United Countries, into other Countries, Staues for herring-barrels 
                  〈◊◊〉
               , and ha
                  •
                
               
                  •
               ing barrels, put into other Ba
                  •
               els, and Nets: to crosse the good Orders and Pollicy here intended to them of these 
                  〈◊〉
               , for the catching, salting, and selling the 
                  •
               ings, dressed in other Contries, after the order of these Countries, whereby this chiefe Trade should be decaied here, and the 
                  •
               habitants of these Countries damnified, if that we make not pro
                  •
               on, in time against such practises, therefore 
                  •
               ee, after Nature Iudgement, and Deliberation haue Forbidden and Interdicted, and by these Presents do forbid and interdict, all, and 
                  〈◊〉
                one, as well Home-borne and Inhabitants, as strangers frequenting these parts, to take vp any herring-barrels, or halfe ones prepared, or any kinde of Nets▪ in any Ship, Towne or Hauen, of the vnited Prouinces, to be sent into other Countries, or Places, vpon paine of confiscation of the same, and the Ship also wherein they shall be found, besides a penalty

of 
                  〈◊〉
               . of Netherlandish 
                  〈◊〉
                Royals, for the 
                  〈◊〉
                time, and for the second time aboue 
                  〈◊〉
                of 
                  〈◊〉
                &amp; 
                  〈◊〉
               , &amp; 400. of the 
                  〈◊◊〉
                of 
                  〈◊〉
               , and for the third time, 
                  〈◊◊〉
                of 
                  〈◊〉
                and goods, and 600. of the said 
                  〈◊〉
                of 
                  〈◊〉
               , &amp; corporal 
                  〈◊◊◊◊〉
               , and penalties, shall be 
                  〈◊◊〉
                third 
                  〈◊〉
                to the 
                  〈◊〉
                of the 
                  〈◊〉
               , 
                  〈◊〉
                third part to the poore, and one third part of the 
                  〈◊〉
               , where the 
                  〈◊◊〉
                shall be demanded: and not onely they shall 
                  〈◊〉
                this penalty, which after shall be taken with the deed, but they also, that within one yeare after the deed shall bee con
                  •
               ted, and that 
                  〈◊〉
                may pretend ignorance, and that this order may be in all places duely obserued, and the offendors punished according to Justice, Wee will and require, our deere and welbeloued Estates, Gouernours, Deputies of the councell, and the Estates of the 
                  〈◊〉
                Prouinces of Gilderland, and the county of Satfill 
               
                  〈◊〉
                
               Ho
                     •
                  , 
                     〈◊〉
                   Freesland, Zeland, Vtricts, F
                     •
                  d, 
                     〈◊〉
                  , the Towne of Groyning, and the 
                  〈◊〉
                places, and to all Justices and Officers, that they cause to bee published in all places, and 
                  〈◊〉
               , where the vsuall Proclamation and Publication is made; 
                  〈◊〉
                do charge also the chancellors, and Prouinciall co
                  •
               cell, and the counsell of the Admiralty, the Aduo
                  •
               , and the 
                  〈◊〉
                generall, and all other Officers. Judges,

and Justices of these vnited Prouinces, and to all generall colonies Admirals and Uice-admirals, captaines, Officers, and commanders, to performe, and cause to be performed, this Order and commandement; and to proceed, and cause to be proceeded against the Offendors, without grace fauour, dissimulation, or composition: because we haue found it necessary, for the good, and benefite, of the said United Prouinces, dated in Hage this 19. of July.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

