
   
      
         
            The invasions of Germanie with all the civill, and bloody warres therin, since the first beginning of them in anno 1618 and continued to this present yeare 1638 : wherein are described the severall battles, encounters, conflicts, and assaults, of cities, townes, and castles ... with a new and exact map of Germany ... : together with the progresse of every army, marked with severall markes or lines, with the pictures of the chiefe commanders on both sides / faithfully collected out of good and credible originalls by a Gentleman well deserving that hath suffered much in those warres.
            Gentleman well deserving that hath suffered much in those warres.
         
         
            
               1638
            
         
         Approx. 125 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01653
            STC 11791
            ESTC S244
            22150912
            ocm 22150912
            21828
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01653)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21828)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1204:1 or 1747:17a)
         
         
            
               
                  The invasions of Germanie with all the civill, and bloody warres therin, since the first beginning of them in anno 1618 and continued to this present yeare 1638 : wherein are described the severall battles, encounters, conflicts, and assaults, of cities, townes, and castles ... with a new and exact map of Germany ... : together with the progresse of every army, marked with severall markes or lines, with the pictures of the chiefe commanders on both sides / faithfully collected out of good and credible originalls by a Gentleman well deserving that hath suffered much in those warres.
                  Gentleman well deserving that hath suffered much in those warres.
               
               [125] p. : map, ports.  
               
                  Printed by I.Norton for I. Rothwell, and are to bee sold at the Sunne in Pauls Church-yard,
                  London :
                  1638.
               
               
                  Signatures: A4 B-E8 F4 2F8 G-H8.
                  Bound with: The warnings of Germany (STC 3759), A true and brief relation of the bloudy battell (STC 1907), The lamentations of Germany (STC 24761) and Lacrymæ Germaniæ.
                  Reproductions of originals in the Newberry Library and Harvard University Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Campaigns --  Germany.
               Germany --  History --  1618-1648.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-01
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-03
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2009-01
            Judith SiefringSampled and proofread
         
            2009-01
            Judith SiefringText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2009-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
               
               
THE INVASIONS OF GERMANIE. With all the Civill, and bloody Warres therein, ſince the firſt beginning of them in Anno. 1618. and continued to this preſent yeare 1638. Wherein are deſcribed the ſeverall Battles, Encounters, Conflicts, and Aſſaults, of Cities, Townes, and Caſtles, at ſeverall times, and in ſeverall places, with a new and exact Map of Germany, wherein the Cities, and Townes are figured with the ſame figures which are expreſſed over the heads of the patticulars in the booke, ſo that the Reader may behold at one view the places, time, yeere, and event of every Battle, Skirmiſh, and Aſſault. Together with the Progreſſe of every Army, marked with ſeverall markes or lines, with the Pictures of the chiefe Commanders on both ſides. Faithfully collected out of good, and credible Originalls.
            
               By a Gentleman well deſerving that hath ſuffered much in thoſe warres.
            
            
               LONDON, Printed by I. Norton, for I. Rothwell, and are to bee ſold at the Sunne in Pauls Church-yard. 1638.
         
         
            
            
            To the Reader.
            THe Civill Warres of this (ſometime) flouriſhing Country might be rather deſired to be buried in ſilence, then bee recalled and perpetuated to memory, 
                  •
               ut that the Lord will have his great 
                     •
                  orkes to be had in remembrance, that 
                  ••
               hers might ſee, and feare him that doth 
                     •
                  hat ever he pleaſeth in Heaven, and 
                     〈◊〉
                   Earth. How great the miſery of Ger
                  
                     •
                  any hath beene, no tongue can expreſſe, 
                  〈◊〉
                heart can beleeve, except thoſe that have 
                  •
               ene, and felt the bitterneſſe of it, they have 
                  
                     •
                  runken the wine of Aſtoniſhment, 
               
                  •
               hough they would not beleeve their miſery 
                  〈◊〉
                have beene ſo neere, nor ſo dreadfull, who 
                  •
               or theſe last twenty yeares have beene mi
               
                  ••
               rably destroyed, that I may ſay of it, as the 
                  •
               rophet Eſay ſaith of Ieruſalem: Your
               
               Country is deſolate, your Cities burnt with fire, your land ſtrangers devoure in your preſence. Shee is now left ſo poore, that ſhe can call nothing her owne, ſhe that relieved others is now in need of others reliefe. She that of late was as a Princeſſe among the Nations, with her ſumptuous Palaces, is now with the Daughter of Zion, as a Cottage in a Vine-yard, or as a deſert Wilderneſſe.
            
            We all this while continue as the Vineyard of the Lord, fenced about by his providence, and ſheltred under his protection, wee onely heare what others feele. God ſtrikes ſome that others might take warning. Goe to my place which was in Shiloh, where I ſet my Name at firſt, and ſee what I did to it, ſaith the Lord. Eſay. 7. 12. We are admired (by all the world) for our peace, it will be our wiſdome to labour to be as famous for Piety, peace ſhould bee the Nurſe of Piety, if we improve this our proſperity

to Gods Glory, it may be a lengthning of our tranquillity.
            If you ſhall meete with any harſh phraſe, 
                  〈◊〉
                unuſuall expreſsion in the inſuing Treatiſe, you will be eaſily inclined to a charitable construction, when you ſhall conſider that he is a German borne. A Gentleman ſometimes of good worth in his own Country, able to deliver himſelfe elegantly in his owne Language, in Latine, or in thoſe other Languages in which he hath been longer exerciſed, than in our Engliſh tongue. You ſhall find it worthy your reading, wherein you ſhall ſuddenly behold the state of the wars, the ſeverall Battles, Encounters, Conflicts, and Aſſaults of Cities, Townes, and Castles, with a new, and exact Map, with figures both on Map, and Book, referring you to each other, wherin you may perceive the time, the yeere, and day, with the ſucceſſe, and event of every Battle, Skirmiſh, and Aſſault, extracted out of the beſt German Hiſtories. Read, and conſider. Vale.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            
            
               
                  Henry Duvall Count of Dampier Lieutenant, Generall to Bucquoy.
                   Who Came into Bohemia with an Army of 6000 men 24 Iuny 1618. fought against Count of Thurn Mansfeld. Duke Anholt Generalls of ye Bohemians Forces: was 
                        •
                     hot and afterwards his head cut of by the Hungarians of Bethlehem Gabors. Garriſon in the aſsault of Preſpur
                        •
                     . 8 Oct: 1620
               
               THE INVASIONS OF GERMANIE.
            
            With all the civill, and bloody Warres, ſince the firſt bebeginning of Anno 1618. to this preſent yeare 1638.
            
               (1)
                
                  COunt of Dampier Liutenant Generall for the Emperour Mathias, with an Army of ſix thouſand men, maketh the firſt invaſion into the Kingdome of Bohemia, beſieged and aſſaulted the Towne of Pilgram, wherein three companies of the Bohemians were put to the ſword, and the reſt taken priſoners. This Pilgram was the firſt Towne, which by the Imperiall Forces was aſſaulted, the fift of September. Anno 1618.
            
            
               
               (2)
                The Imperiall Generall, Count Bucquoy with his Army comming into Bohemia, fought the firſt battle with the Bohemian forces, conſiſting of 14000. horſe and foote, under the leading of Count Mathias, of Thurn, before Budweis, the 12. of October. Anno. 1618. The Bohemian forces ſtood not long conſidering upon the matter, but fell with ſuch fury upon the Imperialiſts, that they utterly diſperſed them; killing an exceeding great number, and ſome 300. priſoners were taken.
            
            
               (3)
                The 11. of November, Anno. 1618. Count Ernſt of Mansfeld comming into Bohemia, he firſt preſents himſelfe with his, and the Bohemians Army, before the Citie of Pilſen. Summons being given the ſecond time, and denied; Mansfeld brings forward his approaches. Some ſallies, and rencounters there paſſed: for all which Mansfeld gat up a very large battery &amp; mounted ſome pieces of good Ordnance upon it. A vaſt breach and a ſaultable he made, and commands it to be ſtormed. The Imperiall Garriſon, with the Citizens therein maintained it very ſtoutly, and beate off the Aſlaylants many times from their walls. But Mansfeld ſo overlayes the defendants with numbers, that he by maine force enters the City.
            
            
               (4)
                
                  September the 4. Anno 1619. The Imperiall Generall Bucquoy falls upon the Towne Biſcka, in

                  Bohemia, wherein all that were found in Armes, are put to the ſword. Immediately after this Bucquoy lighting upon a great party of the Bohemian Forces, not farre from th
                     •
                  s Towne, takes away three Cornets of them, and more then 1500 utterly defeated.
            
            
               (5)
                
                  Bethlehem Gabor, Duke of Tranſilvania, ſending an Army of 12000. horſe and foot, under the command of Redei Ferentz, to aide the Bohemians, who joyned with them, and making an Army both together of 26000. brave men. All theſe being drawn up into battalia, before the Imperialiſts Campe, at the Donaw-bridge by the Imperiall reſidence, and City of Wien. The Bohemians being deſirous to tempt Generall Bucquoy out of his Campe into faire Campagnia. The 25. of October. Anno. 1619. fell there out a ſore battle on the further ſide of the ſame bridge; wherein on the Bohemians ſide were ſlaine ſome 1000. men; On the Imperiall ſide above 4500. and a great many of common ſouldiers wounded, which were brought with waines into the Hoſpitalls of Wien. Generall Bucquoy himſelfe wounded, but not mortally.
            
            
               (6)
                At Egenburg in Bohemia, a great Battle was fought under the conduct of Duke Christian of Anhalt, then Generall of the Bohemian Army, againſt the Imperiall Generalls Bucquoy, and Dampier, wherein the Imperialiſts were beaten, with the loſſe of 2000. common ſouldiers, and divers officers. On the Bohemians ſide were alſo ſlaine, 1800. the 10.

of March, Anno. 1620.
            
            
               (7)
                The 26 of Auguſt. Anno. 1620. Marqueſſe Ambroſius Spinola, with an Army of 25000. Foot, and Horſe, came into Germany, marching with his Army towards the Proteſtants Leaguer, before Oppenheim in the Palatinate; from thence removed to Creutzenach, which he beſieged. The Palatin Garriſon, out of all hopes of being relieved, parlies, and yields, the 31. of August. he tooke Altzheim. Then with 12000. men encompaſſed the Towne of Oppenheim againe. The Towne unprovided for ſiege, was rendred alſo unto Spinola, the 6. of September. Anno. 1620.
               
                  
                  
                     Marquis Ambroſius Spinola Generall. over ye Spaniſhe Army in the Netherlandes. 
                     Was ſent by the King of Spaine with 25000 men into the Palatinat the 26. of August. A
                           ••
                         620 fought against Marquis of Durlach. Mansfeld. and Duke of Brunſwick, takes in poſseſsion the most part of ye Lower Palatinat dyes in Italy in the niew fort of Serivia. the 15 of Sept: A
                           ••
                         630.
                  
               
            
            
               
               
               (8)
                The Elector of Saxonie, with 12000. of Horſe, and Foote did aſſault the Towne of Bautzen, wherein eight Companies of the Bohemians were in Garriſon. The Saxons fell to myning, and ſhooting of Granadoes into the Towne; attempting to ſcale the walls, are by a Sally many times beaten off. But the Saxons with 12. peeces of Canon, fired and ſpoiled at laſt this goodly Citie; againſt which they made in the ſpace of two dayes 3931. ſhot, and alſo taketh it. The Towne is almoſt wholly turned to Cinders. 1136. houſes. 9. goodly Churches, and two Hoſpitalls are burnt, the 25. of September. Anno. 1620.
            
            
               (9)
                Count of Dampier being very deſirous to ſurprize the Hungariſh Garriſon under Bethlehem Gabor in Presburg, goes thitherward with 6000. of Horſe, and Foote, takes and fires the fort in the Suburbs, neere the River Donaw. Five hundred Souldiers thereupon were commanded to ſtorme the Caſtle, &amp; with a Petard to enter it. But the Garriſon perceiving this, iſſues out of the Caſtle, and a great number of the Aſſaylants cut in peeces. Count Dampier himſelfe was ſhot, and afterwards his head was cut offby the Hungarians. Octob. the 8. An. 1620.
            
            
               (10)
                Upon the 7. of November, Anno. 1620. a great, bloody, and ſore battle was fought before Prage; in which the Duke of Bavaria, and the Imperialiſts

under Generall Bucquoy, and Tilly, did overthrow the Bohemians, and Proteſtants Army; all Canons, and Ordnance were here taken, 9000. men of the Bohemian Forces ſlaine, 6000. upon the place of battle, and the reſt, in the reſt of purſuing. Priſoners were taken, the young Duke Chriſtian of Anhait, the young Count of Thurn, Count of Styrumb, divers Officers and Captaines, and of common ſouldiers 500. On the Bavarian, and Imperialiſts-ſide, ſlaine ſome 250. and ſome brave Cavaliers, and Chiefe Commanders, as the Generall Quarter-Maſter Caretti, Colonell Megaw, Captaine Proſing, and Dompre, with 4. Wallons Captaines more. 
                     •
                  he Proteſtants Army before the beginning of this battle is ſaid to have been full 30000. men, and of the Imperialiſts, and Bavarians. 50000.
            
            
               (11)
                
                  Iuly the 10. Anno. 1621. The Imperiall General Bucquoy preſents himſelfe in full Battalia before Ne
                        •
                     heuſel, wherein Bethlehem Gabor had a ſtrong Garriſon, and demands it to be rendred, The ſummons being denyed, the Towne is ſurrounded by his Army. The Garriſon falling out ſlaying there 900. Imperialiſts, and bringing ſome 100. away priſoners. Some dayes after, the Garriſon ſallies out againe, where Generall Bucquoy himſelfe, with divers Commanders was ſlaine, and Prince Torquato de Comitibus, and ſome Officers taken priſoners, and ſo the Imperialiſts were faine to levy their owne ſiege.
            
            
               
               (12)
                
                  Iuly the 8. and 11. Anno. 1621. Divers Troopes of the Bavarian Generall Lieutenant Tillys Army, made a ſhow of themſelves before Count Mansfelds Quarters, neere Frawenberg in Bohemia who ſending out ſome troops againſt them, drave them to retreat, and cut in pieces 300. of them. The next day the Imperialiſts came on with greater forces, the Mansfeldiſh well aware of their comming, theſe feigning to flee, draw on the Imperialiſts into an ambuſh, where many of them were ſlaine, and amongſt them the Bavarian Colonell Baur, with divers Captains and Ritt-maſters. In theſe divers rencounters of the Bavarians, ſlaine more then 1600. on the Mansfeldiſh ſide ſome 500.
            
            
               (13)
                
                  September the 19. Anno 1621. Don Cordua, Spaniſh Vice-Generall, with his whole Army, and divers peeces of Ordnance, comming to beſiege the Town of Franckendall in the Palatinat, wherein was a Garriſon of ſome 12. Companies under the command of Colonell Witgenſtein; who ſallies out with his Souldiers many times upon the Spaniſh, defeats, and diſperſes many of them. But Count Mansfeld comming with an Army of 16000. men to relieve the Towne, the Spaniſh were forced to give over, &amp; to leave ſome Ordnance behind them. On the Spaniſh ſide were ſlaine and wounded in all this time of the ſiege, from the 19. of September, till the 14. of October, no leſſe then 3000. men. 9. Citizens, and 100 of the Garriſon were alſo ſlaine.
            
            
               
               (14)
                
                  Bethlehem Gabor by this time falling with an great Army upon Tirna a Towne in Moravia, wherein was an Imperiall, Garriſon of 7. Companies; this being a wonderfull well provided place, makes great countenance of reſiſtance, in ſo much that Bethlehem Gabor in the third aſſault loſt above 700 of his men before it. But at laſt parlies, and yeelds Anno. 1621.
            
            
               
               (15)
                In the beginning of Aprill Anno. 1622. Count Ernſt of Mansfeld advancing with his Army into Alſatia beſieged the ſtrong Towne Zabern; and 12. dayes, and nights together he battered it. All which time the Imperiall Governour Count of Salm, with his Garriſon, and the Citizens helpe, defended the Towne, and put of one or two aſſaults very manfully. Mansfeld fell very furiouſly on againe, and was againe repulſed with loſſe of 300. of his men, with divers Officers, and Commanders.
            
            
               (16)
                
                  Aprill the 5. Anno. 1622. Generall Tilly ſummons the Towne Neckergemund three Engliſh miles from Heidelberg, the Garriſon doing ſome reſiſtance, whereupon the Imperialiſts with aſſault, the Towne ſurpriſed, putting to the ſword both the Garriſon, and Inhabitants with women, and children. The ſecond day after this Maſſacre, Tilly falls upon 20. Cornets of the Mansfeldiſh Horſ-men, defeates, and kills 200. of them.
            
            
               (17)
                The 14. of Aprill Anno. 1622. Count of Mansfeld comming to revenge in full Battalia againſt Tilly at Mingelheim neere Wiſeloch in the Palatinat, cut in peeces 2000. of his Horſ-men, and followed ſo hard upon his reere, that the wayes ſide by the River Rhein towards Germerſheim were ſtrewed with the dead bodies of his Army: takes

13. Cornets, and 4. Enſignes 4. peeces of Ordnanc
                     •
                   and many priſoners, amongſt them 2. Colonells 1. Sergeant Major, divers Rittmaſters, Captaines and Lieutenants on the Mansfelders ſide ſlaine not above 100.
            
            
               (18)
                After this Generall Count of Mansfeld encompaſſes the Towne Ladenburg in the Palatinat; to which he the next morning gives ſummons by a Trumpet. The Imperiall Governor giving a deniall anſwer. Mansfeld brings forward his approches: one part being blowne open with a petard, is intred by the Mansfeldiſh, put to the ſword the reſiſtance, and takes 8. Enſignes. Anno. 1622.
            
            
               (19)
                The 26. of Aprill Anno. 1622. At Wimpffen Generall Tilly, and Don Cordua fought a bloody battell againſt the Marquis of Durlach, which battell began from the morning till 8. a Clock in the night. The Marquis with his Cavallary having charged the Imperialiſts, and Spaniſh, at ſeverall times, was with ſuch reſolution anſwered, that after five or ſix charges bet wixt them, his whole Army was defeated, all Ordnances, and baggage, 7. Enſignes, and 11. Cornets taken; 5000. ſlaine upon the place of Battle on both ſides; amongſt which Magnus Duke of Wirtemberg, and one Duke of Saxon Weimar. 800. Common Souldiers, beſides Captaines, Rittmaſters, and Lieutenants, both of Horſe, and Foote were taken priſoners.
               
                  
                  
                     Ferdinand Cordua Vice-Generall of the Spanish Army.
                      Left by Spinola in the Palatinat 1621 Beſieged Franckendall and many other places, was beaten of the ſame Siege with loſſe of 3000. men by Mansfeld: ſought against him and Branſwick in the Battel before Hochst. 1622 the 9. of Iuny. and in ye Encounte
                           •
                         vpon, the Borders of Brabant the 26. of August 1622.
                  
               
            
            
               
               
               (20)
                Whereas Duke Chriſtian of Brunſwick had taken the Towne, and Caſtle Hochts; Iune the 9th. Anno. 1622. ſetled his quarter in the ſame place. But long he ſtayed not. For Generall Tilly with Don. Cordua with 22000. of Foote, and 140. Cornets of Horſe, marching againſt him, a great conflict fell out, which continued 6. houres. But the Imperialiſts more in number overthrew, and diſperſed the others, which fleeing to the Bridge ſo throunged, and wedged in one another, that a great number thruſt into the River Main; wherein more were drowned, then killed in the battell. Duke Chriſtian with 5. Cornets of Horſe through the River did eſcape. Of great Commanders on the Dukes ſide were not many ſlaine, except the Count of Lowenſtein, which was drownd. Colonell Lieutenant Kochler, and Francking with 5. or 6. Captaines more were taken priſoners.
            
            
               (21)
                In the end of July, Anno. 1623. Duke Chriſtian of Brunſwick charged ſome Imperialiſts under the leading of the Duke of Saxon Lawenburg, within few leagues from Pleſſe in the Dukedome of Brunſwick. 1000. Imperialiſts Horſe-men he cut in peeces, the reſt fled, leaving 7. Cornets together, with one Rittmaſter, and ſome priſoners and 140. Waggons of Ammunition, and Baggage behind them.
            
            
               (22)
                Upon the 7. of Auguſt. Anno. 1623. A ſore battell was fought at Statlo in W
                        •
                     stphaly, wherein

Generall Tilly prevailed againſt Duke Christian of Brunſwick, and defeated his whole Army. 4000 of Duke Chriſtians Army were ſlaine, and ſo many, and more taken priſoners; all baggage, and Ammunition. 11. demi-Canons, and 4. Leſſer peeces of Ordnances beſides 70. Enſignes, and 9. Comets taken. Priſoners of account were, Duke William of Saxon weimar; the Count of Iſenburg Generall of the Artillery, John Philips Rhinegrau, a Count of Witgenſtein, and another Count of Slick, beſides divers Colonels, Captaines, and other officers. Duke Chriſtian, and the Count of Thurn, who was hardly wounded, and with the moſt of his Horſe-men fled by night unto Breford. On Tilly ſide ſlaine 3. Rittmaſters, and one Captaine, and ſome 100. of common Souldiers.
               
                  
                  
                     Christian Duke of Brunſwick. &amp; Biſhop of Halberſtad 
                     Came first into vpper Germany with 1500 Horſemen ye 18 Nov: 1621. fought ſeverall Battels with Tilly &amp; Don Cordua was overthrowen. lost his left Arme in a Battel upon ye borders of Bmb the 26. Aug: 1622. d
                           •
                        ed of a ſeaver at Groningen 6 May. 1626.
                  
               
            
            
               
               
               (23)
                
                  Octoher the 4. Anno. 1625. 3000. Imperiall Horſe-men, and 3000. of Foote, falling upon the King of Dennemarcks, and Duke Chriſtian of Brunſrick's Troopes, neere the City of Hannover, in the lower Saxony, where above 500. of them were ſlaine, and all the reſt utterly rooted. 5. Cornets tooke the Imperiall Partie, and many Priſoners alſo. Duke Frederick of Anhold was ſhot dead upon the place, in the beginning of the Conflict. And ſo dyed Colonell Obentraut, and that of the wound received in the Battle few houres after, in the Imperiall Leaguer.
            
            
               (42)
                
                  Aprill the 21. Anno. 1626. Count Mansfeld comes with his Army before the ſtrong Sconce by Deſſaw-bridge, in which the Imperiall Generall Altringer then commanded. Againſt this Mansfeld caſts up three Batteries: from whence he night, and day thunders upon the Imperialiſts. Duke of 
                     
                        •
                     riedland comming to ſuccour them, skirmiſhes with the Mansfelders, and utterly defeates the Horſemen, and foure Regiments of Foote: 3000. of the Mansfelders were ſlaine upon the place; amongſt them three Colonels. Kniphouſen was taken priſoner with other Officers, and 30, Enſignes, and 7. peeces of Ordnance. The Imperialiſts loſt ſome 1000. men likewiſe.
               
                  
                  
                     Ernst Count of Mansfeld
                      Came into Bohemia the 20 of Aug: 1618 was first Generall of ye 
                        
                           〈◊〉
                         and Commander of 4000 Horſemen: tooke. Pilſena Towne in Bohemia by aſsault fought against Tilly. Cordua and Spinola had a particular Army by himſelfe in the Pelatinat. Alſatia Sileſia and Hungaria: died at Racon betwixt Sara and Spalato in his yourny from Conſtantinopel towards Venice the 10: of Novemb: 1626
                  
               
            
            
               
               (25)
                
                  May the 27. Anno. 1626. Generall Tilly with his Army, ſetting him downe at the ſiege of Mun
                     
                        •
                     en, in the Dukedome of Brunſwick, which hee moſt fiercely aſſaults. The Daniſh Garriſon, under Colonell Claut, ſallies out of the Towne, and doth valiantly reſiſt them. Tilly reſolves upon a generall aſſault, by force breaking into the Towne, hee takes it; maſſacring and putting to the Sword 25000. Citizens, and Souldiers, with women, and children in it.
            
            
               (26)
                
                  Iuly the 29. Anno 1626. Generall Tilly, with the Count of Furſtenberg, Generall of the Ordnance, comming with 20. Cornets of Horſe, and 1500 of Foote, to the reliefe of the Fort Calenberg, which was by the Daniſh Army beſieged. But Tilly encountring with them, put them to a retreat, and defeates them utterly; tooke 21. Cornets, and Enſignes, and many priſoners, with ſlaughter of 500. Common Souldiers, 6. Rittmaſters, and other Officers, and Colonell Frytags of the Daniſh Army.
            
            
               (27)
                The 25. of Auguſt. Anno. 1626. At Luttor, few leagues from Wolffenbuttel, in the Dukedome of Brunſwick, the Imperiall Generall Tilly obtained a great Victory againſt the King of Dennemarck, and there ſlew, and tooke priſonersſome 4000. men of Foot, with. 60. Enſignes, and 6. Cornets. There was 
                     •
                  laine beſides on the Kings ſide, upon the place of

Battle, the valiant Colonell Fuchs, who commanded, as Sergeant Major, Colonell Nyab, Colonel
                     •
                   
                  Pentz; the Daniſh Generall Commiſſary Powiſ
                        •
                     
                   and the Landgrave Philip of Heſſen. Priſoners 
                     ••
                   account were taken, Colonell Lindſtaw, Colonel
                     •
                   
                  Franking, Courville, Rantzaw, and divers other Officers. On Tillies ſide ſome 3. or 400. were ſlaine.
            
            
               (28)
                The Auſtrian Boores, ſome 20000. ſtrong, did beſiege, and aſſault the Imperiall Towne of Lintz but were beaten off with loſſe of 800. men. Afte
                     •
                   this they fall upon ſome Imperialiſts Forces, unde
                     •
                   the leading of Duke Adolph, of Holstein, which they utterly defeat, the reſt were glad to runne away. This to revenge comes Pappenheim, with 6000. men upon them, and overthrowes them. 3000. he cut in peeces, and put the reſt to flight, the 4. of Novemb. anno. 1626.
            
            
               (29)
                The Towne of Northeim in the Dukedome of Brunſwick for a long time being blockd up by the Imperialiſts. The Imperiall Generall Sergeant Major, Count of Furstenberg reſolves to take it by a generall Aſſault; whereupon the Imperialiſts fall furiouſly on at ſeverall times, but by the Daniſh Garriſon, and Citizens, were againe as bravely repulſed, with loſſe of 6. Captaines, 8. Ancients, and ſome 100. Common Souldiers. 9. Captaines, with divers Officers, and 500. Souldiers were wounded, and hurt. The Garriſon being out of all hopes of reliefe at laſt parlies, and yeelds, the 5. of Iune, anno. 1627.
            
            
               
               (30)
                Betwixt Bredenborg and Itzeho in Holstein, the 
                     •
                  mperiall Commander, Count of Slick, fought a Battle againſt the Marquis of Durlach, where the Marquis loſt the Field. The Imperialiſts tooke 42. Enſignes, and 32. peeces of Ordnance from him, with a ſlaughter of many 1000. men, whereupon the 
                     •
                  mperialiſts ſurpriſed the Fort Bredenborg, putting 
                     •
                  o the ſword all that was found in Armes, in Octob. Anno. 1627.
            
            
               (31)
                Count of Slick having notice that 12. Daniſh Companies under the conduct of Colonell Calen
                     
                        •
                     ach, 4. of Conrad Nell, and 6. under Colonell Holck with 200. Horſemen, of Colonell Bauditzen were 
                     •
                  nquartered about Froy-borg in Jutland, hee with all 
                     •
                  is forces overtakes them. 300. Muskettiers, and Dragooners were cut in peeces, 3000. of the Daniſh Horſemen, ſticking in Moriſh places, were alſo taken priſoners by the Imperialieſts, the 17. of October. Anno. 1627.
            
            
               (32)
                Duke of Fridland ſending the Imperiall Colonell Pechman with 7000. Horſe-men, &amp; Dragoners to purſue the Daniſh, and Weinmariſh Army about Fridberg in Sileſia, where began a great fight betwixt thē; 
                     •
                  ll the Daniſh Troopes were ruinated, the reſt put 
                     •
                  o fight, 10. Companies of them were taken priſoners, and afterwards conſtrained to turne unto the 
                     •
                  mperialiſts, Colonell Pechman was ſlaine in the firſt encounter.
            
            
               
               (33)
                The firſt of Iune, anno. 1630. Guſtavus Adolphus, King of Sweden, with ſome 12000. (for ſo many brought he out of Sweden with him, his Fleete was about ſome hundred and thirty Shippes of all ſorts) landed firſt at that Dorp, or Village, in the Iſle of Vſedome, called Pennemund. The Kings Army conſiſting of eleven Regiments of Swediſh, Scottiſh, and High-Dutchmen, was entrenched before day-light. The Enemies Confuſion in this Iſle, which the King tooke, at his comming, and aſſaulting, was ſo great, that three hundred of them periſhed by the ſword, or in the water.
               
                  
                  
                     Gustavus Adolphus king of Sweden,
                      Came into Germany and landed first in the Jle of Vsedom, with an Army of 12000 men the. 1. of July Ao: 1630. obtained many glorious victory Conquered in two yeares &amp; 4 Moneths two third parts of Germany, was ſhot thorow y• Body &amp; ſlaine in y• Battel of Lutzen y• 6. No: Ao: 1632.
                  
               
            
            
               
               
               (34)
                The King of Sweden ſendeth that Colonell, and his men, who had layne in Garriſon in Stetin, which Towne was rendred to the King the 26. of July. Anno. 1630. to the Towne of Stargard. This Colonell came by night upon the Towne, and having given advertiſment unto theſe Burgers within, they ſecretly opening a Port unto him, give him preſent entrance. He thus got in preſently, cutts in peeces the Corps du-guard, which had the watch upon the Market-place. This done, he without ſtay goes towards another Port, which he preſently aſſaulted, killing 350. Souldiers, which he found within them.
            
            
               (35)
                The King of Sweden paſſing beyond Stetin, and towards Straleſund againe, he ſet's him downe before Wolgaſt, the Towne he by fine force tooke in. In the heat of the aſſault, the Garriſon, and chiefe Citizens retyre themſelves into the Caſtle. This the King aſſeiges. Torquati Conti the Emperours Generall in thoſe parts, came with 3. Regiments towards the reliefe of it, but was beaten, and loſt 12. Enſignes, and 3. Cornets in the skirmiſh. The Garriſon conſiſting of 600. Souldiers thus defeated of her ſuccours parlies. In this ſiege the King loſt 120. men. This was done in the end of Auguſt. Anno. 1630.
            
            
               (36)
                The Imperiall Garriſon, under the cammand of

the cruell Colonell Gotze, having plundered, and forſaken the Towne Paſewalck, and carried the chiefe men away, take it againe, from the Swedes, which being 140. ſtrong, had entred the forſaken Towne, September, the 7. and after moſt valiant reſiſtance: beate, kill, and drive out the Swediſh; fall to tortu
                     •
                  ing of the Towneſ-men for their money; raviſh Women, and Girles even in the open Streets, and Church-yards; yea Women in child-Bed; kill and abuſe the men, fire the Houſes, and the People, in them; thruſt Straw into Cellars where children are hidden, and then ſet fire to it, burne the Churches; maſſacre the Miniſters; and at length burne downe the whole Towne. Thus their rapes and ravages continue till the 11th or 12th of September. Anno. 1630.
            
            
               (37)
                After which the ſame Imperialiſts goe to 
                     Ʋckermund, a Towne hard by, this they fall upon, and take; uſe as before, keepe the gates ſhut, and ſo burne the people in the Towne. Anno. 1630.
            
            
               (38)
                
                  October the 5th. Anno. 1630. Certaine troopes of Crabats making a brave before the trenches at Stetin, drive away the Cattell thereby feeding. In reſcue of them there 
                     •
                  ally out 1000. Swedens. The Swedes overlayd by numbers, looſe ſome 300. brave men, 2. Captaines of Horſe, and one Sergeant Major in the Skirmiſh; the reſt being glad to get out with their lives.
            
            
               
               (39)
                A pretty kinde of Battell betweene the Swedes, and Imperialiſts, happened upon the 11th. of Nouember. Anno. 1630. In the miſt before Colbergen. In which, what with thoſe that were ſlaine by the Enemy, and what they had killed themſelves at their owne miſtake, were 500. men loſt. But the Emperours whole Forces both Foote, and Horſe were defeated: their Cannon, all their Baggage and 4. Cornets taken from them.
            
            
               (40)
                
                  December the 23. Anno. 1630. The King of Sweden with 12. Regiments of Foote, and 85-Troopes of Horſe in perſon, drawes downe towards the Towne of Griffenhagen, naturally a very ſtrong place in Pom
                        •
                     ren; in which lay an Imperiall Garriſon of ſome 3000. Men; and Don Capua a Spaniard their Governour. A fayre, and large breach being made, 10. 15. or 20. Peeces of Canons continually going off together, the Swedens twice attempt to enter, and are twice moſt valiantly repulſed. But 2500. Men (for no more were now left) being unable to hold out againſt 20000. The Towne is at the third aſſault taken. The Governour received a ſhot in his thigh, whereof in priſon he afterwards dyed: many chiefe Commanders and 100. Common Souldiers were alſo taken. 200. were ſlaine, ſome fled, the reſt flinging away their Armes craved quarter, and had it.
            
            
               
               (41)
                About the middeſt of September, Anno. 1630. The Imperialiſts of Garze, which Towne they leaving afterwards emptie unto the King of Sweden, did looſe more then 1000. Men in a bloody fight, with the Kings Forces.
            
            
               (42)
                At the ſelfe ſame time the Swediſh Commander Bauditzen fell upon the Imperialiſts Garriſon of Piritz a Towne betwixt Griffenhagen, and Connixberg in which were ſome 1400. Men thoſe he defeates, and ſo was that Towne taken.
            
            
               (43)
                In the beginning of Octocter. Anno. 1630. Duke of Friedland ſent a ſtrong convoy of 4000. Men to open the paſſages, and to thruſt ſome men, and victuals into the City of Roſtock, which was block't up by the King of Sweden. There the Swedens grapling withall, ſhrewdly defeated, and kill the moſt of them: utterly fruſtrating their deſigne. About the beginning of December, ſome 7. Cornets of Horſe iſſue out of the ſame Towne, to goe a boote-haling: theſe the Swediſh purſue. In the skirmiſh were 200. Imperialiſts ſlaine upon the place 280. taken priſoners; and ſome 400. Horſe brought away: ſcarcely 20. Sound men recovering into Roſtock againe: which afterwards yeelded to the King, and their Lord the Duke of Mecklenburg.
               
            
            
               
               (44)
                
                  February, the 14. Anno. 1631. The King of Sweden with an Army of 16000. Horſe, and Foote ſet's downe to the ſiege of Dammin a very ſtrong Towne; after a hideous Battery was the Caſtle firſt taken of all by aſſault; the 15th. day, he thunders upon that againe, beates downe the workes, and makes ſo vaſt a breach in the walls, that the Imperiall Govemour the Duke of Savelly finding the place not to be tenable againſt ſuch thunder, and reſolutions, parlyes, and yeelds. the King loſt about 200. men in this ſiege.
            
            
               (45)
                At this time Generall Tilly with an Army of 22000. Men, and 26. peeces of Ordnance beſieging Feldsberg a Caſtle neere unto New Brandenburg, which was kept by the Swediſh, by aſſault he tooke in, putting all to the Sword in it.
            
            
               (46)
                Thence hee did goe to New Brandenburg, which was taken by the King of Sweden with Compoſition, which Tilly ſtreightlie beſieged, and moſt fircely aſſaulted. There are his men ſoundly knock't downe many a time, by the Swedens Sallyes out of the Towne, and by others from the Army by Dammin. Tilly thus enraged with the loſſe of his men, after a large Breach in the Walls made with his Ordnance, he breaking into the Towne,

he takes it, kills all that hee finds in Armes: except the Governer Kniphouſen; foure Captaines, ſome Lieutenants, and Ancients with about 60. common Souldiers: all which hee ſends priſoners away. This was done the 9th. of March, Anno. 1631.
            
            
               (47)
                Neere Munchenberg 600 Swhediſh Horſe falling on the ſudden upon 700. Crabats, of which the moſt part they kill, and 100. they take, their Colonell hardly eſcaping into Franckford Anno. 1631.
            
            
               (48)
                The King of Sweden Vantcurryers going toward the ſiege of Franckford, ſurpriſe Zednick kill 300. Crabats obtaine 3. Cornets, and 460. Horſe, with a great booty beſides, Anno. 1631.
            
            
               (49)
                The King of Sweden with an Army of ſome 18000. men advancing towards Franckford upon the Oder the 3. of Aprill, Anno. 1631 which he tooke by great, and bloudy aſſault of the Imperialiſts. Count Schomberg who commanded in chiefe within the Towne (with full 7000. men in Garriſon) Tieffenbach, and Monte Cuculi eſcaped into Sileſia. The Souldiers, and fleeing Imperialiſts ſo throng'd, and wedged in one another upon the Oder Bridge, which was cluſtred full with carriages, that many were ſtifled, and many thruſt into the River Oder. Lieutenant Generall Herberſtein was ſlaine; ſo were Heidum, Walſtein,
                  
and Iour, all Colonels, with 500. other Captaines, and Officers: and 2000. Souldiers at the leaſt dead upon the place: beſides thoſe that were drowned; and others found in Cellars, Chambers, and elſewhere, as many more perchance. Generall Major Sparre, Colonell Waldaw, Colonell Meves, Buttler, Count Sebaudi all Colonels, and 2. others, together with 800. common Souldiers being ſent priſoners unto the King. Enſignes were there 23. with 8. Cornets preſented unto the King. There were 300. Swedes ſlaine, and 100. hurt. To increaſe the miſery of the Citizens, there fell a fire at night, which burnt downe 17. faire Houſes.
            
            
               (50)
                Some Swediſh over-confident of their valour, and fortune would needs ſet upon certaine Troopes of Imperialiſts, which they heard were then abroad betwixt Landsbergen, &amp; Schiffelbein. But the Swedes are well beaten, 300. of them loſt, and 3. Cornets. Upon the 15. of Aprill Anno. 1631. The King of Sweden having fully finiſht his workes. before the ſtrong Towne of Landsbergen, falls ſtrongly upon the Enemies Out-works, and takes them; and 300. Souldiers in them. The Garriſon, ſome 4500. in all, over which was Count Cratz Governour, whoſe ſonne the young Colonell, in falling out, by a Musket bullet was killed demands conditions. About this ſiege firſt, and laſt, the King loſt 600. Men.
            
            
               
               (51)
                In this time the Imperialiſts attempted the recovery of Croſſen in Sileſia, a great Towne upon the Oder, which the Swedes had taken before upon agreement: but the Swediſh Garriſon being aſſiſted by there Fellowes out of Franckford, and Landsbergen, kill ſome 200. of them upon the place, driving the reſt into Great Glogaw.
               
            
            
               (52)
                
                  June the 13. Anno. 1631. 
                     •
                  00. Imperialiſts in Werben were taken ſleepers, killd, rowted, or impriſoned; their Leiutenant Colonell, their cheife Quarter-matter, and their Towne ſurpriſed by the Kings of Swedens Generall Baiudtzen.
               
            
            
               (53)
                Upon the laſt of June, Anno. 1631. The Swediſh Colonell Duwaldt ſent out from the King with 2000. Horſe, and 2000. Dragoners, who paſſing through the River Elue at a ſhallow paſſage, (as Bauditzen had done before in ſurpriſing Werben) falls upon the City of Tangermnnd; where both Towne, and Caſtle being taken, the moſt of the Garriſon ſlaine in the reſiſtancie.
            
            
               (54)
                The King of Swedens Generall John Bannier falls upon Havelberg, 110. Imperialiſts he put to the Sword, 440. taken priſoners, and the Towne alſo, the 9th. of July. Anno. 1631.
               
                  
                  July the 17. Anno. 1631. A great defeat was given to the Imperialiſts from the King of Sweden Colonell Callenbach, and the Rhinegrave at Tanger; where 4. Regiments of Horſe they utterly defeated. 1500. were ſlaine. Colonell Bernſteins which was their leader killed, Colonell Holck, and Coronino fled, ſome 28. or 29. Cornets taken, beſides thoſe that were burnt.
            
            
               (56)
                Whereas Generall Tilly the City of Magdenburg for a long time beſieged, Count Pappenheim then Generall Field Marſhall, the 10. of May, Anno. 1631. by a Generall aſſault enterd, and the Imperialiſts fall to killing. The valiant Falckenburg chiefe commander was ſlaine. the Marquis of Brandenburg Adminiſtrator hurt, and taken Whileſt all thus goes to wrack, a mighty fire breakes out, the whole City was in 12. houres ſpace wholly turned to cinders, excepting 139. houſes. Sixe goodly Churches were burnt. 20000. people at leaſt were here killd, burned, and ſmothered. 6000. being obſerved to be drowned in the Elue. Tillyes Wallons, and Crabats would give Quarter to few, ſo that all were killed.
            
            
               (57)
                Upon the 7. of September Anno. 1631. about a mile from Leipſig a ſore Battell was fought betwixt the King of Sweden, and Generall Tilly. Tillies Army was ſome 44000 brave men. The Kings troupes were ſome 18000. and the Duke of Saxony, together with the Elector of Brandenburg ſome 22000. in which great, and bloudy Battell the King prevailed againſt

                  Tilly. There were 9000. of the Imperialiſts ſlain
                     •
                   upon the place of Battell: and a great number beſides in the chace, the ſame night, and the dayes, following. The King loſt ſome 1200. Men in the whole fight, and the Duke of Saxonie not full 2000. Of the chiefe Commanders on the Kings ſide theſe were ſlaine, Baron Teufel, Callenbach, Hall, Aldergast all Colonels, with divers Captaines, Lieutenants. On the Duke of Saxonies ſide theſe. Colonell Bintauf, Starſhedel, Sergeant Major Holberſdorff, and Lamminger, both Lieutenant Colonells, and ſome more: whereof ſome died the ſame day, and ſome the next. Of Tilly ſide ſlaine theſe following, the Generall of the Ordnance Count of Schomberg: Erfft Serjant Major Generall: Baumgarten, Planckhard, Colonels; Colonell Leutenant, and Baron of Grota, Caratelle Leutenant Colonell: together with diverſe other Italian Colonels, beſides Captaines of Horſe, and Foote. Tilly himſelfe wounded, and fled into Hall.
               
               
                  
                  
                     9 John Tscherclaes Count of Tilly first Lieutenant Generall of the Duke of Bavaria
                      Came into Auſtria with 6000. of Horſe and foot the. 10. Juny. Ao: 1620 was victorious in ye Battel before Prage fought againſt ye Marq: of Durlach. Mansfeld. Branſwick. and King of Dennemarck and overthrow. them. his wholy Army defeated by ye King of Sweden in ye Battel of Leipzig and Lech. dyed. at Jngolſtad of the wound receved in the Conflict at Lech the 20 of Aprill. Ao: 1632
                  
               
            
            
               
               
               (58)
                
                  October the 8. Anno 1631. the King of Sweden tooke by a generall aſſault that ſtrong, and (by the Enemy ſuppoſed) impregnable Caſtle of Wurtzburg, being therein an Imperiall Garriſon of 1500 fighting men. All that reſiſted ſuffred. The Governour Keller, a Captaine of a Troope of Horſe, ſaved his owne life by begging it at the Kings feete: all the defendants being ſlaine, and taken priſoners. The Caſtle for one houre was permitted to the pillage: where an unvaluable booty was obtained by the Souldiers. Some 200. of the Swediſh loſt their lives upon the ſervice. Troy it ſelfe was not better provided for its ten yeares ſiege, for victualls, money, and Ammunition, then this goodly, rich, ſtrong, and pleaſant Fort of Wurtſburg was.
            
            
               (59)
                The Towne Werthhaim was kept by the Italian Colon. Piccolomini. He now iſſuing out of the town, and making the beſt reſiſtance that he could, had all his men that eſcaped not by fight, eyther ſlaine upon the place, or carried away priſoners. October the 15. Generall Tilly having a minde to be revenged of the loſſe of Piccolominies men, and the towne, ſends ſome 3000. Horſe, and Foote to make an enterpriſe upon that place againe. The King of Sweden ſends ſome of his men againſt Tilly. Tilly falling into the Swediſh Ambuſcado whence he gate not out, but with the loſſe of 2700. men 800. Horſe, 14. Enſignes, and Cornets, and all their Armes, and Baggage.
            
            
               (60)
                About October the 21. Anno. 1631. Generall Tilly ſends out 3. Regiments more to oppoſe the Swediſh at Rotenburg an Imperial towne neere the head of the

River Tauber; but theſe three whole Regiments were either routed, or ſlaughtered by the Kings Troopes.
            
            
               (61)
                
                  December the 8, Anno. 1631. the King of Sweden tooke by aſſault the Caſtle of Oppenheim, where 200. Spaniſh of Don Cordua's Army were cut downe, and 8. Colours taken.
            
            
               (62)
                Not long after this, Rhinegrave Otto Ludwick upon his march towards Franckendall, chances upon, a Partee of 9. Troopes of Don Philip de Silva' 
                        ••
                     
                   Horſe (who was then Generall of all the Spaniſh in the Palatinate, and in the Biſhopricks of Mentz and Triers) that were going out a bootie haling, whom, after a long fight, hee rowtes, and overthrowes, taking 5. Cornets away, from them Anno. 1631.
            
            
               (63)
                Upon the New-yeares day at night, anno. 1632. was the ſtrong Towne, and Fort of Manheim, yea the ſtrongeſt of all the Palatinate, by a pretty ſtratagem ſurpriſed by Duke Bernhard of Saxon Weimar. Being believed, and admitted as a friend into the Towne, hee preſently cut in pieces the next Court of Guard, kills 300. of the Garriſon: layes hold upon Maravelli the Governour, and his Lieutenant Colonell; giving Quarter to none, but to the Germanes.
               
            
            
               
               (64)
                About the 8. of Ianuary, Anno. 1632. After the Towne of Wiſmar had yeelded to the Swediſh Generall Todt, and the Imperiall Garriſon under Colonell Gram, marching out with almoſt 3000. men, upon occaſion of a quarrell by the way, whom the Swediſh Colonell Lohauſen falling aboard with, kills 300. upon the place, and ſo terrifies 2000. more, that to ſave their lives they became Souldiers to the King of Sweden. And Gram himſelfe taken priſoner.
            
            
               (65)
                
                  Ianuary the 20. anno. 1632. the Swediſh Generall Rhingrave falls upon Kirch-berg, in the Hunts-ruck, and takes it in by aſſault; wherein 147. Italians, and Burgundians were put to the Sword, and 100. Germans taken priſoners.
            
            
               (66)
                About this time the Rhingrave ſets upon 2. Regiments of Spaniards, not farre from Kaſtel: whereof, one he utterly overthrew, forcing the other to retire into the faſtneſſe of a wood. Here were 8. Colours obtained, and afterwards preſented unto the King of Sweden, at Mentz. But the Spaniards reſolving not to put it up ſo, ſuddenly paſſe over 1800. Horſe, and diſpoſing one Foot Regiment in cloſe Ambuſh. The Rhinegrave hoping of the former fortune, though hee had but 600. Horſe in all with him, loſt in the cloze of the Buſineſſe ſome 300. men.
            
            
               
               (67)
                
                  Ianuary the 22. Anno. 1632. The Towne and Caſtle Crutzenach, wherein 600. Germans, and Spaniards were in Garriſon, taken in by great aſſault from the King of Sweden; a breach firſt wa
                     •
                   made of the Kings Canon, thorow which the Towne was entred: the Caſtle being night and day beſieged, at laſt yeelds upon hard conditions. There were loſt on the Kings ſide, 3. Captaines, and of common Souldiers, 250.
            
            
               (68)
                In the beginning of February, Anno. 1632. Generall Field-Marſhall Pappenheim, having gott
                     ••
                   notice, how that the Swediſh Colonell Cag, wa
                     •
                   with three new, and weake Regiments, Dragooners, of about 1500. men, lodged neere unto Hoxter, and Corvey, he falling into their Quarters, cut in peeces the moſt of them.
            
            
               (69)
                Before the middle of February, Anno. 1632. Landgrave Wilhelm of Heſſen repriſed Warburg, whereinto Pappenheim had newly thruſt a Garriſon of 900. men. The Towne he tooke by ſtorme; and all that reſiſted, dyed for it.
            
            
               (70)
                About this time Duke William of Saxon Weimar, and Generall Bannier do ſtorme, and enter by forc
                     •
                   the Towne of Gottingen, wherein the Imperiall Colonell Carthaus commanded with a Garriſo
                     •
                  
                  
of 900. men. Carthaus with his Officers flinging downe their Armes, are taken priſoners, and the houſes plundered.
            
            
               (71)
                
                  February the 28th. Anno. 1632. Guſtavus Horne, Swediſh Field-Marſhall, cut in peeces two Regiments of Generall Tillies Horſe, obtaines 2. Cornets, the reſt together with the baggage being all burnd within a mile of Bamberg. But Guſtavus Horne likewiſe in forſaking Bamberg, loſt 500. priſoners. Henry William, Count of Solms wounded, whereof he dyed in March following at Sweinfurt.
               
            
            
               (72)
                
                  Guſtavus Horne in recovering Mergentheim firſt of all defeated 800. new-come Imperialiſts, who had thought to have thruſt themſelves into the Towne. The Garriſon after this being roundly beſieged, and for two or three dayes battered, came to a compoſition the 16. of December Anno. 1631.
            
            
               (73)
                Whereas the King of Sweden beſieged the Citie Donawerth, wherein were ſome 1200. Foote. 500. Horſe, and 500. of the Bavarian trained Bands, and Rodulph Maximilian, Duke of Saxon Lawenburg being their Governour, perceiving that they were neither able to reſiſt the King, nor to ſtay the expectation of reliefe; thought a little before breake of day to have, under favour of the darkeneſſe, marcht out of the Towne over the Bridge, towards Bavaria, this deſigne of theirs was hindred by Colonell Hebron: that though Saxon Lawenburg, and ſome few with him got ſafely over, yet

the reſt that would have followed, betwixt 3. and 400. of them being cut downe, and 400. taken priſoners, the 27. of March, Anno. 1632. Donawerth being thus taken, the Kings Troopes falling upon 400. Imperiall Souldiers, in a Caſtle not farre from Donawerth, kill 200. of them in the Caſtle, and the reſt were taken priſoners.
            
            
               (74)
                The 5 of Aprill. Anno. 1632. A great confict happened at Lech, the King of Sweden paſſing the ſame River Lech, and Generall Tilly ſtreightly oppoſing him not to come over, the Generall Altringer of the Bavarians Army with the ſhot of a Fieldpeece was ſpoyled, and carried off in the Duke of Bavarians owne Coach: and Tilly alſo received a Musket-ſhot, which proved a mortall wound unto him. The Duke of Bavaria himſelfe and the whole Army fled by great diſorder, ſome 1000. men of the Bavarians Army were here ſlaine, with many great Commanders, and under Officers.
            
            
               (75)
                In the end of April, Anno. 1632. Pappenheim being come with an Army of 10000. Horſe, and Foote, in the City of Stade falls upon 4. Com
                     •
                  anies of the Swediſh Colonell Monroes, and a Swediſh Regiment of Generall Major Leſlyes, cuts them off, takes 19 Colours, and ſome of the Captaines, and Officers priſoners.
               
                  
                  
                     10. Godtfrid Henry Count of Pappenheim.
                      Sent from the Emperour the 10. of Octob. Ao: 1626 with 6000. against the rebellious Boores into Austria Afterwards was made Field-Marſhall to Generall Tilly over the Jmperiall &amp; Bauaria
                           •
                         Army. was ſtrucken with a bollet of a Falconet in the Battel of Lutzen ye 6 of No: A•: 1632
                  
               
            
            
               
               
               (76)
                In the beginning of Iune an. 1632. the Imperiall Generall Cratz, with 2000. Foote, and Baron of Cronenburg with his Regiment of Horſe, together with 2. Regiments of Crabats, beſieged and takes the Imperiall City of Weiſſenburg: the Swediſh Garriſon, conſiſting of 8. Companies of Foot, and 2. of Horſe, refuſing to turne to the Imperiall party, had all their throats cut. The Towne plundered, the chiefe Citizens, and Miniſters were carried away priſoners, the Gates of the City burnt downe to the ground.
            
            
               (77)
                Duke Bernhard of Saxon Weimar in the purſuite, of the Imperiall Army under Oſſa, lights upon one of his braveſt Regiments, conſiſting of 2000. men, and conducted by Hannibal, Count of Hohen-ems: all which hee had utterly rowted and defeated; tooke the Count, with 400. priſoners, and 8. Enſignes. This defeate happned about Iſne. an. 1632.
            
            
               (78)
                Sir Patrick Ruthven then Swediſh Governour in the City of 
                     Ʋlm, falling upon ſome 1000. Boores ſtirred up by their Land-lords againſt the Swedes, killed 400. of them about Kempten. Others of them beingbuſie at Zipperiden, where almoſt 800. were cut in peeces, 300. more of them in an other place were affrighted, and diſarmed by the Swedes, Anno. 1632.
            
            
               (79)
                The Imperialiſts falling upon 5. troops of the Elector

of Saxonies Horſe, then lying at Rakonick in Bohemia, where the Saxons were ſurpriſed, and knockt downe, ſcarce 120. of them eſcaping with their lives, and loſſe of two Cornets. Anno. 1632.
            
            
               (80)
                The Saxons Forces, under the leading of Baron Hoffkirck, defeated 900. Crabats, and take 11. Cornets from them, about Prage. Three Enſignes of the Imperialiſts, that had before cut off 5. Companies of Saxons at Rakonick; were almoſt every man of them cut in peeces, by the Saxons againe, before the Gates of Prage. Anno. 1632.
            
            
               (81)
                
                  Iuly the 30. Anno 1632. Colonell Sparr was ſent out from Generall Walſtein, in his encamping before Norimberg, with 8. Cornets of Horſe, and 20. Troopes of Crabats, and 500. Muskettiers to cut off the Swediſh Colonell Dubatel in his retreat from Freyenſtat. But the King of Sweden with his Dragooners falling upon the Walſteiners, rowted, and defeated them. Sparre himſelfe, with his Lieutenant Colonell Tertskie taken priſoner, together with 4. Captaines, divers Officers, and above 100. Common Souldiers, 3. Cornets were then obtained, and 2. Enſignes. 600 of the Walſteiners were ſlaine upon the place; and divers more drowned in the River, and Mooriſh places. On the Kings ſide were not many ſlaine; but amongſt them was Colonell Ries. This was done about Burghtan.
               
               
                  
                  
                     11. Albrecht Walstein Duke of Friedland. Generall of the Jmperiall Army 
                     Came first against the Mansfeldiſhe &amp; Weinmariſhe Forces into Sileſia out of Hungary the. 16 Apr: Ao: 1626. pravailed against ye King of Dennemarck: was quitted of his Generallſhip Ao: 1630. &amp; againe recalled to it Ao: 1632. Lost the Battel before Lutz••
                        ▪ was killed wth: a Partiſan from Cap: Debrox at 
                           •
                        gra. Feb: 25 Ao: 1634.
                  
               
            
            
               
               
               (82)
                
                  July, the 20. Anno. 1632. Landgrave Wilhelm of Heſſen with a partee of 500. Horſe, &amp; as many Muskettiers lighting upon 3. Companies of Imperialiſts, killed 100. of them, tooke 2. Cornets, and 500. priſoners. 150. of the Imperialiſts more ſlaine the ſame time about Sweinfurt.
               
            
            
               (83)
                
                  June, the 23. Anno. 1632. Duke Bernhard of Saxon Weimar came before the Port of Ehingen; thoſe hee breakes with a petard; he puts 200. Imperialiſts therein to the Sword, who had before ſurpriſed the Swediſh Officers in the ſame place.
            
            
               (84)
                By this time Duke Bernhard ſurpriſed the Towne of Fueſſen, opening the Gates by Petards, and Scaladoes; wherein▪ 1500. men of the Imperiall Generall Altringers old Regiments were in Garriſon: 300. of which being in the heate of ſlaughter were cut off; the reſt flung downe their Armes, and were taken priſoners.
            
            
               (85)
                Upon the 24th. of Auguſt. Anno. 1632. a bloody conflict fell out betwixt the King of Sweden, and the Imperiall Army before Norimberg, where on the Kings ſide were ſlaine. The Count of Erpach who dyed of his wounds: Generall Major Boetius Lieutenant Colonell Scepter, Rittmaſter Maurice of Malsburg with Rittmaſter Crailsheim all men of account.

Divers other Captaines, Lieutenants, Enſignes, and other inferiour Officers there loſt their lives, with 800. common Souldiers, wounded on the Kings likewiſe the Count of Eberſtein, Castel, &amp; Thurn all Colonels, together with divers other Captaines ſide, Rittmaſters, and other Officers, of common Souldiers there were ſome 1500. wounded. On the Imperiall and Walſteiners ſide ſlaine 1000. of common Souldiers of acount were ſlaine the Lord Fugger, Colonell Aldobrandino, Colonell Don Maria de Caraffa. Some dayes after this Battell, the King going out upon a party falles upon ſome Walsteiners, 250. of them he cut in peeces, divers priſoners they left behind them.
            
            
               (86)
                In the end of Auguſt. Anno. 1632. The King of Sweden in his removing from Norimberg cutts the throats of 350. Crabats by Rain, and tooke 7. Enſigns from them.
            
            
               (87)
                About this time 14. Haſſian Troopes of Horſe ſent to relieve the Towne Volckmarſen were diſcovered, and ſurpriſed by the Pappenheimers, of theſe were 200. ſlaine, and as many priſoners, with the loſſe of 9. Enſignes, and all their Baggage. The Towne was yeelded preſently upon it to Pappenheim.
               
            
            
               (88)
                
                  September the 20. Anno. 1632. Generall Pappenheim purſuing the Swediſh Generall Ba
                        •
                     diſſin and Skiermiſhing with him 20. Engliſh miles together, did very much ſpoile upon the Swediſh, and

cut of all the ſicke, and tyred men, that could not faſt follow: There being ſlaine on both parties. 
                     ••
                  e 1000. men. This was about Hebenhuſen.
               
            
            
               (89)
                
                  Auguſt the 17. Anno. 1632. A great fight was 
                     ••
                  tweene the Swediſh, and Imperialieſts before 
                     
                        •
                     einaw, where the Imperiall Leager then was un
                  
                     ••
                  r Don Balthaſar di Marradas with ſome 12000 
                     •
                  ong. The Swediſh Colonell, and the Saxons Field
                  
                     •
                  arſhall Arnheim falling upon the Imperialiſts 
                     •
                  orſe quarters, they after a charge or two tooke the 
                     •
                  wte upon it: running towards Sweinitz, and 
                     
                        ••
                     eſlaw; ſome 4000. of their Foote having thruſt 
                     ••
                  emſelves into the Fort of Steinaw. In theirs en
                  
                     ••
                  unter were ſlaine above 2000. Imperialiſts. The 
                     
                        •
                     wediſh hereupon recovered the Paſſe, and Fort of 
                     
                        ••
                     einaw. Upon Auguſt the 31. the Imperiall Ge
                  
                     ••
                  rall Sergeant Major Schaffgotzki was alſo over
                  
                     ••
                  rown by Arnheim betwixt the Od
                        •
                     r, &amp; Namstaw; 
                  
                     •
                  here 1200. Imperialiſts loſt their lives, the reſt 
                     •
                  ed, and their Colonell Eckſtad with many Of
                  
                     ••
                  cers taken.
               
                  
                  
                     12 Don Balthaſar di Marradas
                      Sent from the Emperour with. 2 Rigiments of Spaniards ye 
                        
                           ••
                         Jul: 1620 into Bohemia afterwards left Chiefe Commander in 
                           〈◊〉
                         parts by Walstein. fled out Prage at ye Saxons com̄ing. 1 of Nov: 1632. recovered &amp; loſt againe ſome places in Bohemia: defeat
                           •
                         at Steinaw and before Breslaw by Arnheim 1653.
                  
               
            
            
               
               (90)
                Upon the 6. of Nouember Anno. 1632. hap
                  
                     •
                  ned the long, cruell, bloudy, and bravely fought 
                     •
                  ttell of Lutzen, which in continuall exerciſe one place or other had laſted from 9 in the 
                     •
                  orning untill night, in which the Swedes by the 
                     •
                  lour of Duke Bernhard Saxon Weimar, and 
                     •
                  enerall Major Kniphouſen did overthrow, and put flight the Imperiall Army, and their Generaliſſi
                  
                     •
                  o Duke of Friedland. 9000. men were ſlaine upon 
                     •
                  e place; and many a brave man dyed of the an
                  
                     ••
                  iſh of his wounds miſerably. Of great Comman
                  
                     •
                  ers ſlaine on the Kings ſide; Firſt, the King of 
                     
                        •
                     wedens Majeſty himſelfe, whoſe death is never e
                  
                     •
                  ough to be lamented. Next to the King was 
                     
                        •
                     rave Neeles, Duke Ernſt of Anhalt, Count of 
                     
                        •
                     hurn, Colonell Wildenstein, Colonell Winckel, 
                  
                     •
                  ergeant Major Generall Iſler, and Colonell Gerſ
                     
                        •
                     rff, with divers Lieutenants Colonells, Majors, 
                     •
                  ittmaſters, and Captaines. On the Imperiall ſide; 
                     •
                  e Abbot of Fulda; the Count of Pappenheim 
                  
                     •
                  ield Marſhall: Count Berthold Wallenſtein: Ser
                  
                     •
                  eant Major Generall Breuner, Lo. Weſtrumb, Lan, 
                        •
                     omargo, Witzleb, and Foves all Colonels: together with Taxheim, Lampert, and Cammerhoff Lieute
                  
                     •
                  ant Colonels; beſides Majors, Captaines of Horſe, 
                     •
                  nd Foote, and other Officers.
            
            
               (91)
                
                  Gustavus Horn Swediſh Field Marſhall, and the Rhinegrave Otto Ludowick obtained a noble Victory before Wiſeloch the 16. of Auguſt. Anno. 1632. defeated a thouſand Horſe-men of

the very flower of the Imperiall Army, led by C
                     •
                  
                  lonell Vitzthumb, and Montbaillion, where Col
                     •
                  
                  nell Montbaillion was ſhot dead, and ſo his I
                     •
                  
                  tenant Colonell fell at the ſame time by hi
                     •
                   Divers Rittmaſters were there diſmounted, and 
                     •
                  
                  bove 400. of the common Souldiers ſlaine.
            
            
               (92)
                
                  October the 15th. 1632. the Swediſh General Rhinegrave falling upon the Imperiall Army u
                     •
                  
                  der Count of Salm, who with 4000. Boores. 200▪ Souldiers, and 600. Horſe intend to relieue Be
                        •
                     
                     feld, which was by Guſtavus Horn beſieged, ki
                     ••
                   600. of them, and takes about 150. priſoners wher
                     •
                   upon the reſt retyred unto Molſheim.
               
            
            
               (93)
                Upon the 30. of October Anno. 1632. wa
                     •
                   the ſtrong Towne, and Fort Benfeld delivered to Guſtavus Horn, who from the 12. of September untill the 30. of October, had ſtreightly beſieged, and many times aſſaulted. The Imperial Governour having done, and ſuffered as much a
                     •
                   might be expected from a man in his place, had loſt above 400. in all this time of his men, marching out with 400. Foot, and 220, Horſemen.
            
            
               (94)
                The 16. of November. 1632. whereas 12. Cornets of the Briſachers Horſe, were reſolved to affront Gustavns Hornes Quarter, and to attempt the relieving of Colmar, Rhinegrave Otto Ludwick, with

3. Regiments flyes in upon the necks of them, kills, takes, and diſperſes them, ſcarce 100. of them recovering with ſafety unto Briſach, 7. Enſignes hee tooke from them, and that he might purſue the victory, falls likewiſe upon the Imperialiſts at Witte
                     
                        •
                     en hard by Enſiſheim, where 300. hee knockt downe upon the place, and amongſt them 2. Barons of Reiffenberg, Lieutenant Colonell Roben, a Sergeant Major. 6. Horſe Captaines, with divers Cornets and under Officers. Colonell Aſcanio their chiefe commander being eſcaped with 3 Cornets of Horſe, the remainder of 1200.
            
            
               (95)
                The 8. of December, Anno. 1632. the Swediſh Colonell Zillhart of Gustavus Horne's Army, and Lieutenant Colonell Remthinger with a reaſonable partee ſteale ſuddenly upon Endingen, where the Imperiall Colonell Croneck with 5. Troopes of Horſe was enquartered, who was himſelfe in the very beginning of the fight ſhot dead upon the place, above 100. of his men ſlaine, and all the reſt diſperſed, and the Towne of Endingen taken.
            
            
               (96)
                The 9. of January, Anno. 1633. the Vantcurriers of Guſtavus Horn Army falling upon 200. Bauarian Dragooners not farre from Memmingen, kill the moſt of them, whereupon Gustavus Horn with his whole Army aduanced towards the Bavarian, and Imperiall Army under Duke of Feria skirmiſh with them, and defeate 2. Regiment of Horſe, where the chiefeſt Officers were ſlaine, 6,

Cornets taken, and the reſt priſoners.
            
            
               (97)
                
                  January, the 28. Anno. 1633. the Swediſh Colonell Canofsky having gotten intelligence of 1700▪ Imperiall Horſe, and 1500. Muskettiers comming upon him to ſurpriſe him, and his forces, preſently gathered his men together, falls with fury upon the Imperialiſts, and diſperſed them, forced the reſt to runne away into Fryburg, tooke 400. priſoners, and killing 400 of them.
            
            
               (98)
                In the end of January, Anno. 1633. 4000. Imperialiſts tooke by force that Fort of Oppelen. But the Saxon Colonell Sneider falling upon them, cut in peeces 300. of them, and put the reſt unto a diſorderly retreate. Not long after this Skirmiſh, the Swediſh, and Saxon Forces comming againe upon the Imperialiſts at Strelen, where they were beaten off, with ſlaugther of ſome 500 men.
            
            
               (99)
                The 24th. of March. Anno. 1633. After Duke Bernhard of Saxon Weimar had taken the Towne Herrieden, Dan, and Ohrenbaw by aſſault, the Imperiall Generall John de Werth with 40. troupes of Horſe comming to reliefe, and to beate of the Swediſh, Duke Bernhard falls upon them, killed more then 400. of the Imperialiſts, the reſt eſcaping with loſſe of 2. Cornets, and ſome priſoners.
            
            
               
               (100)
                In the middle of Aprill, Anno 1633. The Swediſh Colonell Dubatel with 5. Troopes of Horſe falling into the Quarters of 3. Troop
                     •
                  s of Crabats, at Wonſidel, hee cut in peeces the moſt of them, takes 3. Enſignes, and their Colonell, with ſome Officers priſoners. Few dayes after Dubatel light upon 1600. other Crabats, that ſcoured up and downe the country, cut the throates of the moſt of them, carrying away their 8. Enſignes.
            
            
               (101)
                The 25. of Aprill, anno. 1633. Duke George of Luneborg, Swediſh General, having beſieged Hamelen▪
                   upon the River Weſer; 30. Cornets of Horſe, and 12. Enſignes of Foote, under command of the Imperiall Generall Bonninghuſen, and the Biſhop of Oſenbrug came to the reliefe of this Towne, whereupon Duke Luneborg ſent the Lieutenant Generall Melander with ſome Regiments of Horſe and Foote againſt them, who encountring with the Imperialiſts at Angeren, neere the City of Lemgow, killing, and deſtroying them utterly. There were ſlaine upon the place of this Battle almoſt the halfe part of this Imperiall Army, and amongſt them Colonell Haxthuſen, Colonell Dunbert, Colonell Aſchenburg, with divers Captaines and Officers, and 9. Enſignes were taken.
            
            
               (102)
                
                  Iune the 4. Anno. 1633. The Swediſh under the leading of Colonell Deloni fell upon 1600. Imperialiſts

and Bavarians before the City of Memmingen, where the Imperialiſts were defeated, and Knockt downe, few of them eſcaping with their lives into Memmingen.
               
            
            
               (103)
                About this time, the Swediſh Field-Marſhall Guſtavus Horne having taken with compoſition the ſtrong Fort of Pappenheim, the Imperiall Generall Altringer ſends 1500. Crabats to attempt the Swediſh; but the Swediſh being ready to entertaine them, kill 300. of them, and drive the reſt to a ſhamefull retreate.
               
                  
                  
                     13 Guſtavus Horn Swediſh Generall Field Marſhall,
                      Came into Germany with ye king of Sweden 1630 was first ſent with a Army towards Sileſia. then afterwards Generall of a particular Army by himſelfe in Franconia Alſatia &amp; Swabenland, where he much prevailed against the Coeſarca
                           ••
                         &amp; Bavarian Forces was taken priſoner by ye k: of Hung: in ye Battel of Norlingen. 27 Aug: 1634
                  
               
            
            
               
               
               (104)
                Upon the 28th. of June. Anno. 1633. A bloody Battell was fought at Oldendorp, where the Imperlaliſts, who had gathered a new Army under the leading of Generall Merode, and Count of Cronsfeld, comming the ſecond time to the reliefe of Hamelen, by the manhood of the Swediſh Generals, as Duke of Luneborg, Generall Melander, and Kniphouſen, they were overthrowne, and 5000. of them ſlaine upon the place; amongſt them the Imperiall Colonell, Quad, Weſtphall, and Dincklag, Generall Merode, who dyed few houres after, beſides Captaines, Rittmaſters, Lieutenants, and other Officers, whoſe dead, and naked bodies were not knowne. Priſoners were taken Sergeant Major Marſ
                        •
                     seler, Colonell Weſterhold, and divers Officers more, beſides 2500. Common Souldiers. 13. great peeces of Ordnance, and 70. Cornets, and Enſignes, alſo taken. On the Swediſh, and Haſſians ſide ſome 200. loſt their lives. Hereupon the Towne of Hamelem was rendred to the Swediſh Conquerors.
            
            
               (105)
                At Pfaffenhoven, in Alſatia upon the 31. of June. Anno. 1633. Prince Palatin Chriſtian of Berckenfeld Generall of a Swediſh Army, by himſelfe, obtained a great Victory againſt the Duke of Lorrlayne, in which Battell the Lorrlaynes Army was wholy ruinated, and defeated; leaving all

their Ordnance, and Baggage behind them with the loſſe of 1000. men; the Swediſh Garriſon in Pfaffenhoven likewiſe in the heate of this encounter fell out, cutting of, and diſperſing 500. of the Lorraynes Muskettiers. Of the Swediſh were ſlaine the Generall of the Ordnance Schulthes, and Baron of Ruppa; of common Souldiers ſlaine, and hurt ſome 208.
            
            
               (106)
                In the midle of October 1633. the Imperiall Generall Bonninghuſen falling at night upon the Swediſh, under Field Marſhall Kniphouſen neere Paterborn cut off a great many, tooke 200. priſoners, and 5. Enſignes of them.
            
            
               (107)
                
                  November the 4th. Anno. 1633. Guſtavus Ho
                        ••
                      Swediſh Field Marſhall comming with his Army upon 3. ſtrong Regiments of Imperialiſts, and Bavarians under the conduct of the Count Bray Colonell Luirs, and Konig of Generall Altringers Army, he gives them a ſhrowd defeat, put to the Sword 400. of them, and many carried away priſoners, amongſt them Count of Bray, and divers Officers more. This Skirmiſh happened at Oberndorff neere Balingen.
               
            
            
               
               (108)
                In the end of the Month November Anno. 1633. the Swediſh Generall Rhinegraves Horſe Regiment falling upon ſome troupes of the Imperiall Generall Altringer about Mindelheim, where after a ſharpe conflict neere 1000. Imperialiſts were cut off, and Altringer himſelfe had beene almoſt ſurpriſed.
            
            
               (109)
                About this time the Swediſh Colonell Kanoffsky had a good fortune upon that Pleſkowiſh Regiment of Crabats, which he utterly routed at Wangen; their Liutenant Colonell he tooke priſoner beſides ſome other Officers, the reſt being put to the Sword. A little after this the Swediſh Generall Major Roſtein runiated alſo three Regiments of Imperialiſts, about Kempten whereof many were cut in peeces, and the reſt put to flight. Anno. 1633.
            
            
               (110)
                At this time the Swediſh Generall Rhinegrave tooke in many places in the upper Alſatia, and amongſt others aſlaulted the Towne Rufach, in which hee tooke Priſoners the old Earle of Lichtenstein, together with many other Officers, and above 500. common Souldiers, which

gave up their names to the Rhinegrave, but the Boores were all put to the Sword, within a weeke or 10. dayes ſpace, there were a full 1000. Imperialiſts cut off in ſeverall places thereabouts. Anno. 1633.
            
            
               
               (111)
                In the end of December Anno 1633. the Swediſh Colonell Cracaw falls upon ſome Imperiall troopes of Colonell Bucheim, going towards Huimolſt neere Landsbergen, where he ſorely ruinated them, kills 400. takes 9. Enſignes, one Cornet and many priſoners.
            
            
               (112)
                
                  December the 29. Anno 1633. Landgrave William of Heſſen, and the Swediſh Field-Marſhall Kniphouſen tooke in by a generall aſſault, the Towne of Saltzkoten, and whereas the Citizens thereof had dealt very treacherouſly with the Swedes, the Town was ſet on fire, by heaving and ſhooting of Granadoes in two ſeverall places, which burnt ſo fiercely, that the whole Towne quite conſumed unto aſhes; few of the Citizens and Garriſon could eſcape away, but the moſt of them were put to the ſword. The Imperiall Governour was alſo taken priſoner.
               
                  
                  
                     William Landgrave of Heſſen the first Protestant Prince▪ in Germany
                      Which made an union with ye king of Sweden and 1631. did goe privately over vnto ye kings Campe at Werben and returned with 3. Regiments of Horſe and. 1. of Foot. for his aſſistance. Brought an Army of 12000. men to yoine with kings Forces at Franckford ye 20. Nov: 1631. tooke many Cities and Castles in Ringkow Westphaly. &amp; Lower Saxony. died of a burning Feaver in Eastfriesland. 1637
                  
               
            
            
               
               (113)
                Upon the 29 of January Anno 1634. the Swediſh Colonell Kirkhofer of Duke Bernhard Saxon Weymars Army, had the fortune to light upon the Imperiall and Bavarian Generall, John de Werths Regiment, conſiſting of 11. Companies, all which hee wholly routed and diſperſed, ſome priſoners he took and brought into Deckendorff. At the ſame time the Sergeant Major of the Sa
                        •
                     tleriſh Regiment, brought back three of John de Werths Ritmaſters. 3. Lieftenants. 2. Cornets. and above 80. priſoners. In both theſe conflicts were full 300. Imperialiſts ſlaine, the Bavarian Colonell Swartz taken priſoner. Not long after two Swediſh Colonells, Roſa and Karpffen, light upon Colonell Corpus with his Regiment of Crabats, whom falling upon unawares, they put them to flight, kill 300. and take 200 priſoners.
            
            
               (114)
                
                  February the third Anno 1634. Landgrave Iohn of Heſſen, and the Swediſh Lieftenant Colonell Ramell and Colonell Sperreuter with 700. Horſe, fall out of Weiſſenburg upon the Imperialiſts, with whom they began a hard skirmiſh, 300. Dragooners and Muskettiers they cut in peeces, and tooke 800. priſoners. Amongſt which were Colonell Snetter and Haſlanger. The reſt of the Imperialiſts fled, leaving foure Enſignes, with foure Ancients, one Rittmaſter, and one Lieftenant.
            
            
               
               (115)
                The tenth of March An. 1634. the Swediſh Colonell Plato ſent from Duke Bernhard Saxon Weimar unto Mundelheim, to ſurround the Crabats Regiment of Budiani in it, tooke the Town by aſſault, and put ſome 200. that lay in it, to the Sword; their Leiftenant Colonell hee tooke priſoner, together with many Officers.
            
            
               (116)
                About this time, Rhinegrave Otto Ludowick Swediſh Generall did obtaine a great victory againſt the Lorraynes and Imperialiſts, under command of Count Salm, and Marqueſſe of Baſſompier Generall of the Lorrayne Forces who with 7000. ſtrong ſet upon him, that was little above 2000. betwixt the Town of Senan, and the Dorpe of Ochſenfeld, whereof the Lorraynes and Imperialiſts were ſlaine 2000. upon the place. Colonell Philip was ſhot. Count of Salm, Governour at Zabern, Marquiſſe of Baſſompier with Colonell Mercy, and 600. common Souldiers were taken priſoners. The Duke of Lorrayne retired himſelfe into Dan.
               
            
            
               (117)
                The 29 of May Anno 1634. 700. Imperialiſts Horſemen, and other commanded Forces, together with 700. of Foot, under the leading of Colonell Wolckenſtein, came before the towne of Wangen, thinking to ſurpriſe it unawares, and in haſte they aſſaulted it with great fury: on the other ſide the Commander Colonell Kanosfky with his Swediſh

Garriſon did as bravely, and reſolutely ſtand to their defences; ſo that after ſome time of reſiſtance the Imperialiſts retired; The Swedes iſſuing out upon them, purſued them till they came to Ravenſpurg, where Canofſky conſtrained them to fight, and put above 500. of them to the Sword, and brought 400. priſoners with him into Wangen.
               
            
            
               (118)
                Whereas the loſſe of the Citie of Regenſpurg ſo much diſcontented the Imperial Party, that the Caeſarian Army augmented with 2000. Hungarians, &amp; the Bavarian Forces under the Generall Altringer, marched thitherward to regaine it the 17. of May Anno 1634. But Duke Bernhard of Saxon Weimar ſudden comming, was ſo terrible to the Enemy, that they preſently retired towards the upper Palatinate. The Swedes purſuing them, and overtaking the Reare, cut of 300 Crabats, amongſt which was their Commander Pleſkowits ſlaine, and tooke 400. priſoners. On the Swediſh ſide was Generall Major Courville ſhot through the body, whereof he died immediately. But the Bavarians joyning with the Imperiall Army under the King of Hungary, both which together conſiſting of 30000. Foot, and 15000. Horſe, applying themſelves to the fiege, intending to make an aſſault upon the Citie, when they could make a ſufficient breach by battery. Hereupon May the 26. with an 100. peeces of Ordnance begin to batter it. Preſently after, they made an aſſault, but were repulſed with the loſſe of 500. men, by the Swediſh Garriſon out of the Citie, taking priſoner of the

Imperiall Colonell Breuner, divers other Officers, yea the Swedes they ſurpriſe many Crabats in ſeverall places, which were put to the Sword with their commander Budiani; that alſo in this firſt aſſault of the Imperialiſts 3000. loſt their lives. July the 10. was the laſt aſſault upon the Citie on all ſides, wherein 4000. Imperialiſts, likewiſe miſerably from the Swediſh were cut in peeces. But whereas the Garriſon and Citizens had for a long time, behaved themſelves ſtoutly in defence of the Citie, even to the admiration of the Imperialiſts, who had before it, by their owne relation, 8000. ſlaine upon the place, 6000. others who had runneaway, made 15000. Canons ſhot upon the Town, caſt above 2000. Granadoes into it, and 465 Sallies endured from within, the Citie is at laſt ſurrendred upon honourable conditions.
               
                  
                  
                     Ferdinand the third king of Hungarie and Bohemia proclaimed king of the Romanes the 11. Dec: 1636 at Ratisbone.
                      Which Citie he for along time beſieged, most fierceli aſsaulted, and at last tooke from the Swedens vpon honourable Conditions the 16 July. 1634. Fought a bloody Battel with Duke Beruhard of Saxon Wemar▪ &amp; Gustavus Horn Generalls of ye Swedish Army. before ye Citie of Nordlingen and obtained the Victory against them the. 27. Aug: 1634,
                  
               
            
            
               
               
               (119)
                
                  May the 12. Anno 1634. Duke Georg of Luneborg Swediſh Generall, having received certaine intelligence, that the Imperialiſts, and Leaguiſh Forces conſiſting of ſome 3000. men, had an intent to releefe the Towne of Hildeſheim, which he ſtill beſieged; he ſends 1330. Horſes in all of his, under Colonell King towards the Enemy, where began, not farre from the Towne Bevern, a ſharp conflict betwixt them; at laſt the Swediſh were victorious, the oppoſite parties were put to a Suddaine flight, with great loſſe and ſlaughter. The Proteſtant Forces purſuing them ſo furiouſly, that they were head long tumbled into the river of Weſer; the way of Bevern was ſtrowed and ſcattered full of dead carcaſſes, there were very few that eſcaped, and the moſt of them were afterwards found and ſlaine. Priſoners were taken ſome 300. amongſt which was one Colonell Lievetenant. one Colonell the Earle of Eſſenfeld, and an Earle of Wangenburg.
               
            
            
               (120)
                The Imperial Commander Bonninghuſen was with Generall Geleen beſieging the Towne of Coesfeld, to which they gave two fierce aſſaults the 17. and 19. of May. Anno 1634. at which aſſaults, they were bravely received, and repulſed with great loſſe, and whileſt they lay at the ſiege, the Swediſh and Heſſiſh Troupes came ſuddenly in the neck of them, and after a furious encounter for the ſpace of foure houres doubtfull, the moſt part of their Foot Forces were diſperſed, and a great many of them

ſlaine: and purſuing the Horſemen betwixt Ham and Lunen, 500. of them were ſlaine; with the reſt of the Horſemen Bonninghuſen and Geleen retired to Lunen, which the Swediſh after the third aſſault had it alſo ſurrendred: 4000. Souldiers which were therein are come over to the Swedes.
               
            
            
               (121)
                About this time Generall Lieftenant Melander of the Haſſian Army, marching againſt the Army of the Catholique Leaguers in Weſtphalia, overtooke their Foot forces, and put 1500. of them to the Sword; the reſt under the command of Generall Bonninghuſen and Geleen, fled in a confuſed order into Hamme, wherein he left a Garriſon under his Colonell Lieftenant Veglen; which Towne the Swediſh went to aſſault, there the Petards were imployed and took ſuch effect, that though the Souldiers defended themſelves ſtoutly from the walls, yet the Citie was taken the 27. of May. Anno 1634. to the great confuſion and moſt totall ruine of the Leaguiſh Catholick Army; and more than the fourth part of the fame Armie was put to the Sword.
            
            
               (122)
                After this the Swediſh Army being brought before the Citie of Munſter, the Swediſh Generall Duke of Luneborg without delay ſummoneth the Citie, to be ſurrendred unto him: but they giving an deniall anſwer, the Swediſh did continue the ſiege. A party of ſome 1000. ſtrong ſallyed out of the Citie, to fetch proviſion in it, in their returne were met by ſome Haſſians, and Swedens in the

Army, who put 800, of them to the ſword, and and tooke from them all the proviſion. An. 1634.
               
                  
                     George Duke of Lunenborg Chiefe Commander of Fridlands Army before Stral-Sundt: 1626
                      Came to the king of Sweden and maide Generall in Lower Saxony with 5000. men Swediſh Forces. 1. May 1631 beſieged and tooke many places obtained 2 glorious Victoria against the Jmperialists the 28. Juny 1633 at Oldendorp the other before Hildesheim. 5. of July. 1634.
                  
               
            
            
               
               
               (123)
                Upon the third of May. Anno. 1634. Generall Fieldmarſhall Arnheim of the Saxons Army obtained a memorable battle, and brave ſucceſſefull victory againſt the Imperialiſts at Lignitz: where the onſet and firſt ſhocke of the Battell was very hot and fury, continuing with great obſtinacy and bloody oppoſition, the ſpace of five houres: the Saxons Canons being three times loſt to the Imperialiſts, and three times with much occiſion recovered againe from them by the Saxons: the Imperiall Curaſſiers and the Crabats did ſhew much valour, and reſolution for the moſt part of the Battell, till in the end the victory inclined to the Saxons ſide. The Imperialiſts fleeing towards Lignitz were purſued and cut in peeces, by the Saxons with an exceeding great ſlaughter, above 4000. Imperialiſts were ſlaine upon the place; amongſt whom were Colonell Bigots, two Generall Majors, the Lieftenant Colonell of Winſen Regiment, foure other Officers and Commanders, and 1400. taken priſoners. Colonell Troſt was dangerouſly wounded, and ſo was Coloredo the Generall himſelfe, and Colonell Winſe. Colonell Goſlitz was taken priſoner, moſt of the Captaines of the Foot Forces were ſlaine. Of the Saxons party ſlaine about 400. whereof 2. Ritmaſters, 5. Cornets, and foure Ancients, and 200. hurt: 36. Enſignes. nine peeces of Ordnance. 27. Cornets won in the field, and two others more in purſuing of the Enemy.
            
            
               
               (124)
                The 6. of May. A. 1634. The Imperiall Commander Goltz comming with 5000. men to beſiege Oppelen, began to aſſault it in 5. ſeverall places at once. But the Saxon Garriſon under Command of Colonell Sneider, did their beſt to keep the Imperialiſts out. That 140. of them lay dead in the ditch neere the breach, three or foure one over another, and neere the other workes lay ſcattered here and there, a great many carcaſes, in ſo much that above 400. were found dead upon the place, and more then were ſlaine, were hurt and wounded. The Commander Goltz was ſlaine, the Lieftenant Colonell Sieghoſe was ſhot in the ſhoulder. foure Captaines with ſome Lieftenants and Ancients loſt their lives, leaving their Ordnance alone upon the Batteries, and ranne away.
            
            
               (125)
                The fift of Aprill Anno 1634. The Army of the Catholique League, after ſome reſiſtance, having taken the Towne of Hoxter by aſſault, the Imperialiſts made their victory exceeding bloody: ſparing neither armed or unarmed, man, woman, or child, putting all to the Sword, and what the Sword could not ſpoile, they cauſed the fire to conſume, and the dead corpes they caſt into the river Weſer: yea did moſt inhumanely and butcherly murther and hew in peeces, without reſpect either of age, ſex, or condition: the Heſſiſh Generall Lieftenant Melander hearing of the cruelty of the Imperialiſts, ſending 1200. Horſemen before

his Army againſt them, put above 500. to the Sword, and tooke 4. Companies of them priſoners.
            
            
               (126)
                
                  Iune the ſeventh Anno 1634. Betwixt Landshut and Pfaffenhoven in Bavaria, Guſtavus Horn having the purſuit of the Bavarian Generall Iohn de Werth, cut in peeces 900. of the Bavarians, and Iohn de Werth himſelfe hardly eſcaped.
            
            
               (127)
                
                  Iune the 14. Anno. 1634. Generall Field Marſhall Horn did repriſe and take by aſſault the Towne Aicha, put the moſt of the Towneſmen and Souldiers to the ſword, hanged the perfidious Commander, who contrary to the agreement and his promiſe, had repoſſeſt himſelfe of the place, from which hee had ſo lately been ejected, before one of the gates, and burned the Towne to the ground.
            
            
               (128)
                
                  Iuly the 12. Anno 1634. Duke Bernhard of Saxon Weimar and Guſtavus Horn taking Landshut in Bavaria by aſſault, fired the Caſtle and Suburbs, pillaged the Citie, and put as many as they found in Armes to the Sword. Hither was Altringer the Bavarian Field Marſhall ſent with ſome troups to ſuccour it, a man knowne to the world, for a prudent and valiant Souldier, but he in a battell being ſlaine, with a ſhot through the head, his Army was routed.
            
            
               
               (129)
                Upon the 26. and 27. of Auguſt Anno 1634. the great, ſore, and bloody Battell was fought before Norlingen, in which the King of Hungary together with the Bavarians and Spaniſh Army, under Cardinall Jnfant of Spaine, prevailed againſt the two Swediſh Generalls Duke Bernhard of Saxon Weimar, and Guſtavus Horn, ſo that the Swediſh Army being overlayed, and oppreſſed with multitude of the Imperialiſts, Spaniſh and Bavarian Forces, was forced to give ground, and ſo were beaten and diſordered, that many of the old and beſt Infant
                     •
                  ria were ſlaine, and divers of the beſt Commanders killed, hurt, or taken priſoners: amongſt others the valiant Guſtavus Horn, who himſelfe, together with the Fieldmarſhall Cratz, the Generall Major Roſtein, the Generall Major Schafelitzki, Colonell Hume, Lieftenant Colonell Stuart and Forbes, and other high and under Officers were taken priſoners. The young Marqueſſe Friderick of Anſpach, the Lord Zerotin, Colonell, Sneidewind, which commanded as Generall Major, Colonell Wettberger, Colonell Grun, Colonell Lieftenant Willibart, Sergeant Major King, and ſeven Scots Captaines, beſides Lieftenants, Enſignes, and other Officers were ſlaine upon the place of Battell. Generall Lieftenant Hoffkirchen, and many of other Officers and Commanders were wounded and hurt: what and how many of common Souldiers on both ſides were ſlaine, man had no certainty of it. After this bloody Encounter was ended, the Citie of Norlingen,
                  
being yeilded to the King of Hungary.
               
               
                  
                     17 Ferdnand. Cardinall Jnfant of Spaine
                      Joyned with the Jmperiall Campe at Norlingen 22 Aug: 1634. wth: 12000 Jtalian &amp; Spainiſh forces in witch fight he gayned much glory &amp; is Gouerner of Brabant. etc:
                  
               
            
            
               
               
               (130)
                The Imperiall Army came from thence, beſore the Imperiall Citie of Hailbrun, and troubled the ſame with no Ordnance, but only with Granadoes, in ſuch manner, that at once, there were ſet on fire, and burnt to the ground, above 140. houſes. A Swediſh Lieftenant Colonell Senger of Smidbergers Regiment, commanding in the Towne, being ſlaine in a ſally, and the Towne taken, in the end of Auguſt. Anno 1634.
            
            
               (131)
                Whereas July the fift Anno 1634. The Imperialiſts under command, of the Colonells Waldeck and Schelhammer, who brought together above 400. Horſe and Foot to Neuſtat, did the ſecond attempt to reliefe Hildeſheim, were by the Proteſtants Army, under the Swediſh Generall Commiſſary Anderſon, and Generall Lieftenant 
                     Ʋſler defeated; within one houre they fled in a diſordered confuſion, and the reſt of the Army, within a ſhort ſpace was ſo utterly routed, that of 2500. Horſe, ſcarce 250. returne to Neuſtat; their Foot Forces, being at the firſt 1500. were almoſt ſlaine upon the place. About 1000. priſoners were taken, amongſt which were two Lieftenants Colonells, two Majors, ſeven Ritmaſters, three Captaines, 11. Lieftenants 9. Cornets, and 13. Standards. The Citie of Hildeſheim whereupon, when they within ſaw themſelves deprived of all ſuccour, Iuly the 17. was delivered to the Swedes.
               
            
            
               
               (132)
                After the Battell at Lignitz, the Saxons Armie under Lieftenant Generall Arnheim, marched towards Olaw, wherein the Imperiall Governour Roſtick, being advertiſed of the Saxons comming, burnt the whole Towne to the ground, and betooke himſelfe into the Caſtle: from thence the Saxons did goe to Oels, wherein the Imperiall Governour Don Johan de Languiall yeilded, to the mercy of the Saxons, and was taken priſoner, with his 300. Souldiers; likewiſe in the purſuit of the Imperialiſts from Namſlaw, tooke more than 100. priſoners of them, in the moneth of May Anno 1634.
            
            
               (133)
                Upon the 29. of Iune 1634. the Swediſh Generall Bannier, entered into a ſet Battell with 15000. Imperialiſts, under the conduct of their Generall Coloredo, and got a noble victory, neere the Citie of Griffenberg in Sileſia, where the Imperialiſts loſt ſome 4000. men, ſlaine upon the place, and many Officers of account, were taken priſoners: 30. Cornets. 70. Enſignes, and 38. peeces of Ordnance were gotten by the Swedes, by this puiſſant Army.
            
            
               (134)
                
                  Iuly the fourth Anno 1634. The Saxons Army, though not with ſtrong oppoſition tooke Sittaw in Sileſia by aſſault; which iſſue of the aſſault was bloody on both ſides; the Saxon Colonell Lieftenant Wanger was ſlaine, by a bullet of foure pound weight, with 50. common Souldiers, and

the Maſter of the Horſe, to the Duke Saxon Lawenburg, received a mortall wound: whereof hee died few houres after. On the Imperiall ſide within was ſlaine the chiefe Commander, Lieftenant Colonell Fuchs, two Captaines, and 60. Souldiers, the reſt were taken priſoners, with 12. Enſignes, and two ſtandards of the Enemy. The Citie being plundered by the Souldiers in the furie.
            
            
               (135)
                About this time, the Saxon Commander Donner, who was guarded with ſome 400. Horſe, lighted upon the young Maximilian of Wallenſtein, of the Imperiall Army, who held his Randevouz neere Glatz in Sileſia, routed his troops, carried away 300. priſoners, and amongſt them two Captaines.
            
            
               (136)
                As the Saxon Colonell Daube tooke the Citie of Elnbogen, upon the river Eger, he by a ſtratageme, though it was both well fortified, and well manned, and had but one way of comming to it, quickly entered, and put the Imperiall Garriſon therein to the Sword. July the 15. Anno 1634.
            
            
               (137)
                At this time, the Saxon Generall Lieftenant Arnheim, and the Swediſh Generall Bannier being ſate downe before the Citie of Prage, with their Army, they played upon the Citie, with their Canons, for the ſpace of three dayes, and were replayed unto from thence in the like kind, with

great loſſe on both ſides. 900. men of the Saxons, and Swedes there being ſlaine, of the Imperiall Garriſon within conſiſting of 14000. men, under the Command of Coloredo, and Don Balthaſar, two expert and valiant Souldiers, which neither omitted the fortification of the Citie againſt aſſaults, nor ſhunned the danger of fight, loſt their lives ſome 600. after this the Swedes and Saxons marching off.
            
            
               (138)
                The 25. of Auguſt Anno 1634. Generall Bannier comming with his Army, before the Towne of Satz, diſtant from Egra three German miles, upon the Borders of Bohemia, the Imperialiſts within ſtanding out after his ſummons, tooke it by force, putting all to the ſword in it.
               
                  
                  
                     19 Iohn Bannier Generall of the Infantery
                      Came into Germany with the king of Sweden 1630. employed afterwards from ye king with a strong Army towards Tyrole Bavaria Lower Saxony and Sil
                           •
                        ſia: did admirable good ſervice in ye Battel o
                           •
                         Leipzig 1631. is yet still Generall &amp; Chiefe Commander of all ye Swediſh Army in Pomerland and upon thoſe borders, where he lately ye. 3. Oct: 1636. obtained a memorable Victory against ye Imp: &amp; Saxons Forces at Wi
                           •
                        stock
                  
               
            
            
               
               
               (139)
                The Swediſh and Saxons Armies joyntly marching forward in Bohemia, did obtaine a bloody victory on the Enemies ſide, in taking by aſſault the Towne of Limpurg; wherein did lie foure Companies of Imperiall Dragooners, and three of Foot; the Souldiers aſſiſted with the Citizens, and Boores, and women, threw burning pitch and ſcalding water upon the Proteſtants Army, made what reſiſtance they were able, but their unadviſed Action, and deſperate obſtinacy, provoked the invaders to anger, which was not pacified, but with the death of above 2000. perſons in that Citie. The principall Commander in the midſt of the ſlaughter with 150. Souldiers retired into the Caſtle, craved quarter, but was likewiſe put to the Sword with all thoſe, that were with him. After this cruell victory, ſome Imperiall ſuccouts were comming to releefe this place, but thoſe the Swedes encountered alſo, ſlew a great many, tooke the Waggons and carriages, and forced the reſt to a confuſed flight Auguſt. the 6. Anno 1634.
            
            
               (140)
                
                  Auguſt the 12. 1641. Generall Bannier advancing with his Army towards Brundeiſ, where hee firſt got the bridge from the Imperialiſts, and broke it downe, then cut in peeces 300. Crabats, which were hindered in their flight, and laſtly tooke the Citie.
               
                  〈2 pages missing〉
               
            
            
               
               (144)
                The fourth of January 1635. The Imperiall Commander Bamberger, who had formerly commanded in Vdenheim, for the elector of Tryer as the Swedes tooke it the yeare before, uſing the benefit of the froſt, tooke it forcibly againe, from the French, and Germaine Souldiers, that till then held it, by an aſſault. Six Companies, the moſt of them in heat of bloud, were put to the Sword therein: the Governour himſelfe was taken priſoner.
               
                  
                  
                     18 Piccolomini a great Commander first of Walſteins Army after Pappenheim was mortally wounded in the bloody Battel of Lutzen.
                      Advanced with his owne and ye Cauallery which Pappeheini had ſeconded ye Jmperiall Army with extremitie of reſolution, was twice or thrice ſhot: &amp; whereas his Regiment was that wch: first Charged when ye King of Swē: was ſlaine Walstein, reunrded him as much as was better, then 100000 pounds Sterlings. 1632 Com̄anded afterwards ye principàll part of ye  k: of Hun
                           •
                         Army, was ſent to aſsist ye  Spaniſh Cardinall Ao: 1637
                  
               
            
            
               
               
               (145)
                
                  January the 17. Anno 1634. Count Lodowick of Naſſaw Dillenburg tooke the ſtrong Fort Braunfels, three Engliſh miles from the Citie of Mentz, to the terrour of the Imperialiſts, 1400. of whom being quartered thereabout, by aſſault, having maſtered the out-workes, fell upon the head watch, whom he put to the Sword, applied his petards to the gates one, he fired the reſt of the gates and ſo entred, one Lieftenant, two Captaines, three Lieftenants, one Cornet, three Ancients, and many under Officers, and 156. common Souldiers were taken priſoners, beſides the loſſe of many, who were ſlanie.
            
            
               (146)
                
                  February the 28. Anno 1635. A ſharp Gonflict fell out betwixt the Imperialiſts, and the French, together with Duke Bernhard of Saxon Weimar troupes, before the Citie of Speyer, in which the French and Swediſh prevailed againſt the Imperialiſts, that rhey retired towards the Fort of the ſame Citie, 800. of them being partly ſlaine in the Battaile, and in part taken priſoners by Duke Bernhard. After this Duke Bernhard fell upon the gates of the Suburbs, though it was guarded with 400. men, 300. of theſe were put to the Sword, and the reſt ſaved by the mercy of the Conquerour. On the Aſſailants ſide, were ſlaine about ſixtie men, and about that number wounded. They of qualitie were theſe, a French Baron, Commander of the Regiment of

                  Normandy. one Lieftenant, one Enſigne, and Captaine more of the French Army. Of the Enemies were ſlaine 600. After this bloody Encounter the Imperiall Garriſon in Speyer, being no
                     •
                   brought to 500. Foot, and 300. Horſe, 900 others being ſlaine in this ſhort time of the ſiege and many taken priſoners, yeelded upon diſcretion. Meternick the late Commander and Hartemberg Commander of the military men, and Gotz the Colonell, who was dangerouſly wounded, with 80. Officers became priſoners, to the Swediſh and French Generalls. This Citie of Speyer, was firſt taken by Mansfeld, then retaken by Tilly, lately recovered by the King of Sweden, repoſeſſed by John de Werth, conquered againe by the French in this ſiege, and afterwards taken in againe by Gallas.
               
            
            
               (147)
                The 21. of March, Anno 1635. The Earle of Eberſtein, Generall Major of the Haſſian Army, ſurpriſed and defeated 1200. Crabats, and obtained a noble conqueſt neere Hirchsfeld in Haſſia. Jllo Lieftenant Colonell, who was commander of theſe Crabats, himſelfe being ſhot through the head, moſt of his Souldiers &amp; Officers were ſlaine, and the reſt, which eſcaped with their lives, made priſoners, whom with their baggage, and 500. goodly Horſes the Count of Eberſtein, Governour of the ſame Citie, brought into Caſſell.
               
            
            
               (148)
                The ſtrong and goodly Citie of 
                     Ʋlm being already

blockt up in the end of February, Anno 1635. by the Imperiall Generall Gallas, expected every day to be beſieged. In the beginning of March. Anno 1635. ſix Companies of their Garriſon ſallying out of the Citie, fell upon 300. Crabats, which were lodged in a neighbour village, ſlue them every man, and tooke their Colonell alive and brought him into the Citie: alſo in the end of Aprill, a Swediſh Colonell, who had eſcaped out of priſon from the Imperialiſts, aſſiſted with the maine body of the Garriſon, having in one Sally utterly rooted three whole Imperiall Regiments.
            
            
               (149)
                The ſeventh of Iune. Anno 1635. The Imperiall Generall Lieftenant Hatzfeld, for Gallas being advanced into the lower Palatinat, beſieged the towne Keiſerſlautern, battered it with his Canon, made breaches in the wall, aſſaulted it valiantly ſeverall times, and was in the end beaten off, with the loſſe of 1500. men, by the valiant Swediſh Colonell Schombeck Commander in the ſame Towne. But the Imperialiſts fell violently againe upon the Citie, the 7. of June, carried by their number and deſperate manner, and in the fury, in revenge of their Enemies, 3000. of whom were loſt in this ſiege, put not to the ſword, thoſe only, whom they found in armes, but old men alſo, women, children, and little Infants, without any condition or diſtinction. Only the Colonell Schombeck, of all the Swediſh Regiment ſhrewdly wounded, became a priſoner to Hatzfeld, and ſome Citizens ſaved themſelves by much

intreaty, and promiſe of a large beneficence.
            
            
               (150)
                
                  July the 19. Anno 1635. Duke Bernhard of Saxon Weimar, and the French Cardinall de Ʋalette, who were in all about 18000. Foot, and 10000. Horſe well diſciplined, fell upon the Reare of the Imperiall Generall Gallas, and cut of ſome 1600. of his Foot, and above 1000. Horſemen, neere Lanſtell.
               
            
            
               (151)
                The Caeſarian Field Marſhall Goetz, marching with his Army towards Heſſenland, ſummoned Zoeſt, a ſmall Citie upon the River Lippe, which refuſing to yeeld, was by his Army beſieged, and allmoſt burnt to the ground, by the Granadoes caſt out of the Campe the 9. of September. Anno 1635.
            
            
               (152)
                About the middle of October. Anno 1636. A bloody and ſore Battell, was fought at Witſtock, in which the Swediſh Generall Iohn Bannier got a glorious victory, againſt the Elector of Saxonie, and the Imperialiſts, where was a hard and long doubtfull Combat. Of the Imperiall chiefe Commanders were ſlaine; the two Generall Majors Wilſdorp, and Goltz, and Marazini himſelfe deadly wounded, and five Colonells ſlaine, whereof threee are particulariſed by name, Wilzberger; young Hatzfeld and Kunigell
                  
beſides Rittmaſters, Captaines, and divers Officers, and by 7000. of common Souldiers ſlaine upon the place of Battell, and many others more, which fell by the Sword, of the Swedes in the proſecution, ſix whole Regiments as Coloredoes, Wendenſales, Walſteins, Goltz, Eracts, and Pappenheimes, being totally ruined. Priſoners were taken 1500. amongſt which were 170. Officers, and 146. women of quality, wives to the Caeſarian, and Saxon Colonells, and their Officers. 143. Cornets and Enſignes. 14. peeces of Ordnance, and 8000. Wagons were left to the Conquerors. On the Swedes ſide were ſlaine 1000. and upwards, amongſt were of account the two Colonells, Berghawer, and Conigham, foure Lieftenants Colonells, and ſundry Ritmaſters, Captaines, and under Officers. Colonell Cracaw, Linſe, and Gun were wounded.
            
            
               (153)
                The Fourth of November Anno 1636. The Swediſh Army under Generall Bannier, fell upon 300. Saxons Horſemen; the avantguard of ſeven Regiments, under the Saxon Generall Major Dehne, neere the Fort of Mansfelt whom the Swediſh environed round about, put the greater part to the Sword, and tooke the reſt both Officers, and common Souldiers priſoners.
            
            
               (154)
                About this time the Swediſh Generall Bannier receiving intelligence, of two Imperiall Regiments

enquartered not farre from Helmſtat, routed them totally, and cut in peeces the moſt part of them.
            
            
               (155)
                
                  November the 15. Anno 1636. The Count of Eberſtein, Generall Major to the Landgrave of Heſſen, hearing of the Imperialiſts march, and how the Swedes purſuit after them, made all the haſte he could to ſtop their journey, falling upon the Reere-guard, commanded by Generall Goetz neere Rotenburg, upon the river Fulda, where being compaſſed in behinde and before, by the Swedes and Haſſians, foure of his beſt Regiments, were cut in peeces, and alſo defeated. three peeces of Canon. 13. Enſignes, 300. Horſe being taken; 800. Imperialiſts more were alſo not farre from this place, from the Haſſian Commander Gunterot ſlaine and taken.
            
            
               (156)
                
                  December the 16. Anno 1636. The Imperiall Commander Geleen being upon his march, with foure Regiments towards Weſtphalia, to unite his Army to Goetz and Hatzfeld the two Imperiall Generall Majors, was encountred by the Swediſh Generall Major Stalhanſe about Ma
                        •
                     ningen, who ſlew 700. of them upon the place, tooke neere as many priſoners, and amongſt the reſt, the two Colonells, Manteuffell and Ramſdorff, gained three peeces of Ordnance, and purſued the reſt almoſt to Wurtzburg, Generall

                  Geleen and the Count of Furſtenberg ſaved themſelves with much difficultie.
            
            
               (157)
                In the beginning of Ianuary Anno 1637. the Swediſh Generall Major Stallhanſe, who having paſſed the river Sala, cut off the bridge behinde him, in three ſeverall Skirmiſhes with the Imperiall Commander Hatzfeld, who led the Avantguard of ten Regiments, ruinated foure of them utterly not without much loſſe of his owne partie. After this the Haſſian troupes, after a a ſharp conflict with the Imperiall Count Budiani, and his Crabats, cut in peeces 300. of them, himſelfe was forced to flight, and carried with them 26. p
                     •
                  riſoners, all or moſt of them of note, and eminent Commanders in the Army. In another place the Haſſians falling upon foure Companies Caeſarians, which lay in a ſmall Citie, put them all to the Sword, and returned home with 150. Horſe and other good bootie, and baggage, of which they had ſpoyled the Imperialiſts.
            
            
               (158)
                A bloody timefell out betwixt the Imperiall Generalls, and Banniers Forces, March the 23. Anno 1637. The Swedes advancing with ſix full Regiments, burned the Citie and Caſtle of Stralen to the ground, and ſurpriſed one of the Caeſarian Quarters neere Wurtzen, carried away 300. Wagons laden with baggage: the Caeſarians burning hereupon many faire townes to the ground,

that 44. ſeverall fires within two Leagues compaſſe, might at once been diſcovered to the eye. Colonell Slang being ſent by Bannier with 1500. Horſe towards Leiſnick, and Eylenburg, in his returne at Wurzen, defeated two Imperiall Regiments, carried away their baggage, ſlewe 600. upon the place, takes many priſoners, amongſt which were two Ritmaſters, five Lieftenants, and many other Officers. Generall Bannier in the abſence of Colonell Slang, purpoſely to bring a generall terrour upon the Armie of the Imperialiſts, falling upon 2000. Imperiall Horſe, whom he defeated and routed utterly. This victory incited him to proceed further, and appearing in Battell arry before the Enemies Campe, another ſharpfightfell out, where the Swedes encountered with three Imperiall Regiments, charged them ſo furiouſly, that abovt 300. of them were ſlaine, and ſo many drowned in the river.
            
            
               (159)
                The Bavarian Generall John de Werth with the ſtren
                     •
                  gt of his army, which conſiſting 4300. Horſes, and as many Foot, foure ſeverall times did aſſault Duke Bernhard Saxon Weimar, neere Enſiſheim, but was ſtill repulſed with loſſe of above 1000. in ſeverall conflicts. 500. dead corpes being found dead up
                     •
                  n the place, and all the Officers of one whole Regiment ſlaine, and ſo Duke Bernhard with the loſſe o
                     •
                   130. of his men, got a happy victory. After this Battell was ended, Duke Bernhard with the Rhinegrave, took by aſſault the Towne Enſiſheim, and ſlue as many

as they found in Armes. The Officers were made priſoners, and the reſt came to ſerve under Duke Bernhards Colours.
            
            
               (160)
                
                  June the 5. Anno 1637. The Imperiall Generall John de Werth with his owne forces, and 24. Cornets of Crabats, commanded by Jſolani, going to relief Kentzingen, was beaten and defeated by Duke Bernhard of Saxon Weimar, who ſlue and routed 500. of his Foot, and three ſqu
                     •
                  
                  drons of his Cavallery, with the loſſe of 100. of his owne.
            
            
               (161)
                
                  Iune the 6. Anno 1637. Generall Bannier lighting upon ſome certaine Companies of the Saxons Commander in the Towne of Meiſſen, owne Foot Regiment encloſed them with his Army, and put them all to the Sword, not leaving one to carry newes of his fellowes misfortune. This done, by a ſtratageme he preſently ſurpriſed the Towne, who came alſo in with his Cavallery, made himſelfe Maſter of the Citie, putting alſo to the Sword, ſome few only excepted, which ſaved themſelues in the Caſtle with the Governour Meurer.
               
            
            
               (162)
                
                  June the 15. Anno 1637. The Imperiall Gommander Mercy in behalfe of Charles Duke of Lorrain with 13. Regiments of Horſe and foure of Foot, to hinder Duke Bernhard with his Army, from paſſing the river Soane. Duke Bernhard having

notice of the Lorraines deſigne, put his men into Battalia, towards the River, where after a great Encounter Duke Beruhard got the victory neere Sangre upon the borders of Lorraine. All the three Germain Regiments of the Imperialiſts, 50. perſons excepted, were ſlaine, or brought into captivity 500. dead corpes of them being found upon the place, and 900. taken priſoners. 3000. Horſes gained by this victory. Priſoners of note were theſe, the Count of Reux Colonell, two Lieftenants Colonells. ten Captaines of Horſe, 9. Lieftenants, 14. Cornets, 13 Quarter-Maſters, 37. Corporalls. 13. Trumpets. 426. common Souldiers, and 400. Dragooners. But 16. Enſignes gained by the victory, were ſent to the King of France. This defeat was ſeconded by another; Mercy having rallyed up his broken Army with 2000. Horſe, was againe defeated by the Rhinegrave, who ſlew 400. of them upon the place, put the reſt to flight, and purſued them to Veſon.
               
               
                  
                  
                     Bernhard Duke of Saxon Wemar first Generall▪ of a 1000 Horſe &amp; Foot of the king of Sweden Army about the Bodenſee Danuby &amp; in Bauaria. 1632
                      Then was left with halfe of the Kings Army in Franconia by his great Valour &amp; manhood obtained victory in ye Battel of Lutzen: halfe the Swediſh Army was cōmitted to him after ye Kings of Sweden death is now Generall for ye King of France and ye confederate Princes in Lorrain Alſatia &amp; about ye Rhine. where in this preſent yeare ye 3 of March. 1638, got aglorious Victory against ye Imperialist before ye Towne of Rhinfelden.
                  
               
            
            
               
               
               (163)
                
                  Auguſt the firſt, Anno 1637. the Swediſh Colonell Wrangell, being advertiſed that in new Brandenburg, lay ten companies of Imperiall Dragooners, making in all about 700. Horſe, under the command of their Colonell Debroll, and 300. other Horſe commanded by Winſen, drew out 800. of the moſt valiant in the Army at Anclam, marched directly againſt them, ſurpriſed and ſlue the major part of them, tooke 300. priſoners, with three Lieftenant Colonells, two Ritmaſters, and three Captaines, with two Cornets, gained in the Battaile.
            
            
               (164)
                
                  Auguſt the ſecond Anno 1637. Slang the Swediſh Colonell was attended with the like good Fortune falling upon two Brandenburgiſh Regiments, under the conduct of Colonell Dobitz, 
                  
                     •
                  eere Shiffelbein, hee ſurpriſed them ſodainly, defeated them totally, and put them all to the Sword, except 200. whom he made Captives.
            
            
               (165)
                About the midſt of Auguſt, Anno 1637. the Imperiall Generall Gallas falling upon the Caſtle of 
                     Ʋckermund, where the young Lieftenant Colonell Wrangell lay, tooke it by aſſault, and put the Swedes to the Sword.
            
            
               
               (166)
                The third of March new ſtile, Anno 1638. Duke Bernhard of Saxon Weima got a glorious victory before Rheinfelden, where he the Imperiall Army under Command Generall Iohn de Werth twice intirely defeated, having ſlaine in the firſt ski
                     •
                  miſh, about the paſſe of Bicken 400. and 600. taken priſoners, with 10. Cornets of the Enemy; and in the ſecond Combat betwixt the ſame Citie, Rheinfelden, and Lauffenberg, 1200. more cut in peeces upon the place of Battel, and 2500. were taken priſoners, the moſt of them Officers, and men of qualitie, as Generall Iohn de Werth himſelfe, together with the Italian Duke of Savelly, Generall Lieftenant Enckenford, Generall Major Sperreuter, beſides 17. Colonells and Lieftenants Colonells, 106. Rittmaſters, Captaines and Ancients, with 110. Cornets and Enſignes. On Duke Bernhards fide ſlaine not above 500. in the Battell, but amongſt them Lieftenent Generall Iohn Philip Rhinegrave, and ſome other Officers.
            
            
               (167)
                Upon the fourth of March. Anno 1638. The Imperiall Generall Klitzingen with 200. Horſe and Foot, ſurpriſed and tooke in by aſſault the ſtrong Towne and Fort Gartz in Pomeren, wherein all that he found in Armes of the Swediſh
                  
garriſon, were put to the Sword, taking priſoner in it Generall Major Trumund, two Lieftenant Colonells, eleven Captaines with 12. Enſignes.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            ERRATA.
            NVmb. 19. lin
                     •
                  
                11. for no both, read on both. by numb▪ 20. in the mar. for 2627. r. 1623. numb. 22. l. 1. fo
                  •
                Auguſt, r. Auguſt. numb. 22. l. 12. for Stick r. Slick. afte
                  •
                the numb. 23. for numb. 42. r. 24. numb. 32. l. 6. for figh
                  •
                
               r. flight. numb. 52. l. 5. for Baiudtzen, r. Bauditz
                     ••
                  
                numb. 53. for reſiſtancie, r. reſiſtance. after numb. 54. r. 55. which is left out. numb. 72. l. 6. for 1631. 
                  •
                1632. numb. 114. l. 3. for and r. unto. numb. 122. 
                  •
                9. dele. and. numb. 129. l. 31. for Nortingen r. No
                     •
                  linge
                     •
                  
                numb. 143. l. 4. for was, r. were. by numb. 144 an
                  •
                145. in the m. for 1634. r. 1635. Vlt. pag. for 1635. r. 1638.
            Here is alſo a more large Relation of th
                  •
                Batttell lately fought for Rhinefelden betwixt Iohn de Werth, and Duke Bernhar
                     •
                   Saxon Weimar, and with more circumſtances, as is mentioned. Numb. 166.
            
               
               
                  21 John de werth a Bauarian Commander tooke in the Citie of Anspach, and was rewarded with the honr. of the Marquisat there of by the K: of Hungary
                   Made an inuaſion in Francomaye 10 Au: 1634 afteryebattel of Norlingen being Joyned withye Duke of Loraine, tooke in many places in the vper Al
                        •
                     atia, had a Fortunate attempt againstye French in Picardi 1636, did goe with Picolom
                        •
                     nito Luxinberg, returned with his Army into A
                        •
                     
                     satia, 1637▪ where hee had many Incounters withye Rhine graue and Saxon Weimar, who took
                        •
                      him 
                        〈◊〉
                      Battel before Rhin
                        ••
                     ld 31 1638
               
            
         
      
   

