
   
      
         
            A vvomans vvoorth, defended against all the men in the world Proouing them to be more perfect, excellent, and absolute in all vertuous actions, then any man of what qualitie soeuer. Written by one that hath heard much, seene much, but knowes a great deale more.
            Paradoxe apologique, où il est fidellement démonstré que la femme est beaucoup plus parfaite que l'homme en toute action de vertu. English
            Pontaymeri, Alexandre de, d. 1618.
         
         
            
               1599
            
         
         Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01694
            STC 11831
            ESTC S105731
            99841457
            99841457
            6042
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01694)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6042)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 244:03)
         
         
            
               
                  A vvomans vvoorth, defended against all the men in the world Proouing them to be more perfect, excellent, and absolute in all vertuous actions, then any man of what qualitie soeuer. Written by one that hath heard much, seene much, but knowes a great deale more.
                  Paradoxe apologique, où il est fidellement démonstré que la femme est beaucoup plus parfaite que l'homme en toute action de vertu. English
                  Pontaymeri, Alexandre de, d. 1618.
                  Munday, Anthony, 1553-1633, attributed name.
                  Gibson, Anthony.
               
               [12], 70 leaves   
               
                  By Iohn Wolfe, and are to be solde at his shop in Popes head Alley, neere the Exchange,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  1599.
               
               
                  A translation of: Pontaymeri, Alexandre de.  Paradoxe apologétique, où il est fidellement démonstré que la femme est beaucoup plus parfaite que l'homme en toute action de vertu.
                  Possibly translated by Anthony Munday, whose motto "Patere aut abstine" appears on the title page.
                  Editor's dedications signed: Anthony Gibson.
                  "An other defence of womens vertues, written by an honorable personage, of great reckoning in Fraunce", leaves 62-70.
                  Running title reads: The defence of womens vertues.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Women --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2005-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-04
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-04
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2007-04
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A WOMANS Woorth, defended againſt all the men in the world.
            Proouing them to be more perfect, excellent and abſolute in all vertuous actions, then any man of what qualitie ſoeuer.
            Written by one that hath heard much, ſeene much, but knowes a great deale more.
            Patere aut abſtine.
            Imprinted at London by Iohn Wolfe, and are to be ſolde at his ſhop in Popes head Alley, neere the Exchange. 1599.
         
         
            
            
            To the Right Honorable Lady, Elizabeth, Counteſſe of South-hampton.
            
               TRuely honor'd Lady, and by me (for many your great fauours) to bee euer (more) then honoured: As ſome teſtimony of my dutifull remembrance, to anſwere by humble thankfulneſſe, what all other meanes vtterly diſ-able me of, ſome part of ſuch your eſpeciall open handed graces receiued; I offer you a tranſlated Apologie of womens faire vertues, written in French by a Lord of great reckoning, giuen by him to a

very honorable Dutcheſſe: ſince, tranſlated by a fellow and friend of myne now abſent, who gaue me truſt to ſee it ſhould not wander in the world vnregarded, or depriued of that beatitude which makes bookes reſpected, whereto animated beſide by diuers my good friends: I haue (noble Lady) the rather thus preſumed. If eyther then for the ſubiect, my ſelfe, or my friendes ſake, it may ſeeme any way pleaſing to you: the French Lord neuer thought his labour halfe ſo graced, as I will continually confeſſe our fortunes honored.
            
               Your Honours euer obliged. ANTHONY GIBSON.
               
            
         
         
            
            To the Right Honourable the Counteſſe of South-hampton.
            THe loue (most honor'd Lady) that I owe
            To your high vertues, cannot be confin'd
            In words or phraſes: nor can paper ſhowe
            The obiect-leſſe endeuours of my mind.
            How then ſhall any (though the purest ſpirit,
            That ſucks the ſeau'n-fold flower of art) expreſſe
            The genuine glories of your Angell-merit,
            Which ſhine the more, in that you make them leſſe?
            Now could I wiſh, I had a plenteous braine▪
            
            That thence (as from Inuentions clearest floud)
            Thoſe formes might flow, compoſd in a rich vaine:
            That crowne your nobleſſe, and enrich your bloud.
            Thē would my zeale breake forth like mornings fier
            That now lyes ſpent in ſparkes of my defier.
         
         
            
            
            To the worthy Ladyes, and vertuous Maydes of Honor, to her royal Maieſty: Miſtreſſe Anne Ruſſell, Miſtreſſe Margaret Ratcliffe, Miſtreſſe Mary Fitten and the reſt, &amp;c.
            
               VErtuous Ladies, and Right Honorable Maides, attending on the only vertuous Ladye and Maide in the world: the duteous affection I beare yee, and the vnualuable reſpected graces receiued from you ſeuerally,

is the onlie aduocate muſt plead for my preſent boldneſſe; what he can ſay for mee, is but returne of humble thankefulneſſe; what hee expectes from you, is but excuſe from preſumption and fauourable acceptaunce: both which meeting in no miſinterpreted cōſtruction, you shal remaine for euer honored, &amp; I in my ſute right fully ſatiſfied.
            A friend &amp; fellow ſeruant with me to her Maieſty hauing left in truſt with me this litle treatiſe, being a Paradoxe

Apologicall of womens vertues, written in French by an honorable perſon, and Dedicated by him to a worthy Dutcheſſe: knowing my friendes intent to ſute with mine, that on you (rather then any other) the ſame should be beſtowed, as only true Ideas of vertue, and glories of your ſexe: In his abſence, (though yet in his harts meaning I know) I offer both his good will and mine thus ioyntly together.
            If you giue it but good lookes, it is all I deſire, but

if it may gayne your very leaſt good word, his labour and my loue are moſt highly anſwered. In which hope (as to hope otherwiſe from ſo true ſpirits, were well worthy reproofe:) I humbly commit this tranſlation to your fauourable peruſing, and my very vttermoſt trauailes to beat your commaunding.
            
               Yours euer moſt deuoted. ANTHONY GIBSON.
            
         
         
            
            To the Honorable Miſtreſſe Anne Ruſſell.
            LAdy to whom my true deuoted loue,
            Hath been engadgd, in more then wit can pay,
            Which to diſcharge, the more I ſtill haue ſtroue,
            The more in deepe arrearedge euery day.
            So much from me, vnto your ſelfe is due,
            That all my thoughts, vnto the debt must runne,
            Yet is there more remaining vnto you,
            And as theſe croſd, ſo others are begun.
            Deareſt of deareſt: take in thankefull part,
            This ſacrifice, which may my will approoue:
            Vppon the Aulter of a faithfull heart,
            Conſumed in the flames of zeale and loue.
            True honourable Virgin, euer liue,
            In all that arte, that time, that fame can giue.
         
         
            
            
            To the Honourable Miſtreſſe Margaret Ratcliffe.
            TO you (deare Nimph) whoſe wit, and forme, enflames
            A world of ſpirits, with wonder of your graces,
            That (in their ſtrength) purſew no higher ames,
            Then how to giue your bounties ſoueraigne places.
            I heere am bolde, to make extent of will,
            Though not of power. Pardon my firſt eſſay:
            
            I goe by night, now to the Muſes hill:
            But I may liue, to drinke there, at Mid-day.
            O then: my ſoule ſhall flow through my cleare vaines,
            And (taking light from your bright vertues ſpheare)
            Pay richer duties, in farre-ſweeter ſtraines,
            Tun'd to your worth, and ſet to euery eare.
            Had I a Spencers ſpirit, a Daniels powers:
            Th'extracted quinteſſence were only yours.
         
         
            
            
            To the Honorable Miſtreſſe Fitten.
            
            THis teſtimonie of my true hearts zeale,
            Faire, and (for euer honord) vertuous maide:
            To your kinde fauour humbly dooth appeale,
            That in conſtruction nothing be miſ-ſaide.
            Thoſe fierie ſpirits of high temperd wit,
            That drinke the dewe of heauen continually:
            They could haue graced you with termes more fit,
            Then can my lowlie, poore, weake ingenie.
            Let not my loue (yet) ſlightly paſſe reſpect,
            Deuoted onely to your excellence:
            Winke woorthy Virgin at my lines defect,
            Let will extenuate what ere offence.
            It is no bountie that is giuen from ſtore,
            Who giues his hart, what gift can he giue more?
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            
            To all the Honorable Ladies, and Gentlewomen of England.
            
               LAdies (and moſt perfecte Ideas of all vertues,) I haue ſo many times admired your rare perfections, brought from the Theater of the very beſt aſſemblies thorow Europe: that hauing combated with mine owne naturall affections, which till then had no matter of maruaile offered them; of neceſſity now muſt needes (by right confeſſe) that you are the onely wonders of time and eternity. And that I am not miſſe-led heerein, Mercurius Triſmegiſtus ſtands foorth in your cauſe, and thus defends yee againſt all your enemies.
            
               
               A ſoule encloſed within a body, purely celeſtiall, where the notes of whatſoeuer diſanulling, are not to be diſcerned, becauſe their period can alter no part of a true nature: For no way are her ordinary functions weakned, but onely in ſtrengthning the vertue of the minde. So that ſhe is no way to bee diſſolued, but may well chaunge into a forme more conuenable, and agreeing with the quality of her Demon.
            
            Ladies, you are ſuch as Sappho deſcribes ye to be.
            
               With child of Honor, rich in all good grace,
               Splendant in vertue, which them both ſurpaſſe,
               A piercing eye, and carried with ſuch ſtate:
               As the worlds Torch may light it ſelfe thereat.
               Euen as Apollo from Auroraes lookes,
               Gildes all this goodly rounde, &amp; darkeſt nookes.
            
            And to giue you certaine aſſurance, that ſuch is mine opinion, I haue roughly hewen out this diſcourſe, extracted from the vertues of your ſexe:

to the end, that by the hiſtories of many women, euery man whatſoeuer may perfectly perceyue, that the gifts and graces of women are infinite, and where they can alleadge any doubt in the religion of your deſertes: being heerein reſolued, you may remaine ſo much the more admired.
            I might call it a Paradoxe, becauſe ſome men (vainely tranſported) no doubt will tearme it ſo: Notwithſtanding, I holde it for a truth, and will defend it againſt all ſortes of men, let them be of what mettall ſoeuer; being fully perſwaded, that if I had no other argument for proofe of my ſayings, then the very meere ſubiect of your choyſe perfections: I ſhould finiſh my deſſeignes with no meane honour, and make them perfecte beyonde all other humaine enterpriſes.
            Receiue then this gadge of mine humble duty, or rather of the vertue of your owne deſeruings: and I ſhall

binde all my hability to a further imployment, eyther of enlarging this, or any thing elſe wherein I may doe you ſeruice.
            
               Yours in all duety, Anonimus.
               
            
         
         
            
            To the Reader.
            
               FReind, or foe, I care not whether, I offer thee this Treatiſe of truth, which may ſtand more in doubt of enuy, then cenſure: Notwithſtanding I will take all in good part from thee, euen till thou haſt run thy mallice out of breath: yet this ſhall bee the honour of my paines, that thou canſt not rancke me among common ſpirits, for I haue borowed nothing of any, who haue writ on this ſubiect; well deſeruing to be ſung in a higher key, then my diſabled voice either hath, or can reach vnto.
            
               Yet this is a comfort to mee, that though as ſcant fledge it flyes thus from me, ſome royall Birde may protect her from greedie Cormorantes, and defend it vnder the ſhaddowe of her wings: for I will alwayes buy the abatement of mine owne honor, with the riche price of womens true glorie.
         
         
            
            From what Authours this little labour receiued his originall.
            
               Aelianus.
               Aeſchilus.
               Aeſchines.
               Anaxagoras.
               Anacreon.
               Alcmeon.
               Anacharſis.
               Antimachus.
               Appolonius.
               Ariſtotle.
               Ariſtophanes.
               S. Auguſtine.
               Archimedes.
               Auerroes.
               Auicen.
               Biblia ſacra.
               S. Bernard.
               Bandello.
               Boccace.
               Du Bartas.
               Boiſteau de Launay.
               Cornelius Tacitus.
               Clearchus.
               Cicero.
               Cteſias.
               Diogenes Laertius.
               Demoſthenes.
               Dioniſius Mileſianus.
               Ennius.
               Empedocles.
               Fredericke d'Aſte.
               Galen.
               Guicchiardine.
               Herodotus.
               Heſiodus.
               Hippocrates.
               Homer.
               Hortenſius.
               Iſocrates.
               Ithiobaldus of Corfue.
               Licras.
               
                  Linus.
               Lycoſthenes.
               Manethon.
               Martiall.
               Mercurius Triſmegiſtus.
               Menander.
               Memnon Epheſ.
               Muſaeus.
               Nicholas de Nicholai.
               Origen.
               Orpheus.
               Ouid.
               Papinian.
               Plato.
               Pindarus.
               Plutarch.
               Pithagoras.
               Plinie.
               Poſsidonius.
               Propertius.
               Raſis Arab.
               Socrates.
               Steſichorus.
               Sapho.
               Saluſt.
               Sanazar Neap.
               Timaeus Scicillianus.
               Thales.
               Torquato Taſso.
               Theophraſtus.
               
                  Ʋigo.
               
                  Ʋirgillius.
               Xenophon.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            
            A Womans woorth, defended againſt all the men in the worlde.
            
               AS (according to Anaxagoras) the body of Nature is heauen, and the influence thereof her ſoule: euen ſo, the body of a woman is the heauen of humane perfections, and her ſoule the treaſurie of celeſtiall and diuine vertues. That it muſt needes be ſo, the auncient Philoſophers, as well morall as naturall, the ſpeculatiue Aſtronomers, Poets, the interpreters of holye things, and maiſters of the beſt approoued manners, chimerique Painters, and namely 
                  •
               he profeſſours of diuinitie, doo conſent and maint
                  •
               ine: that the faireſt ſciences, the ra
                  •
               eſt 
                  •••
               
               tues,

the inimitable graces, ought to be repreſented in the forme and figure of women, as it may be ſeene in Heſiodus, who ſpeaketh thus.
            
               Faire Vertues face, with beautie honored,
               Lookes like a field in Aprill diapred.
               Or as the difference of enammeld flowers,
               Which natures daughter forth in plētie powers.
            
            In like maner, the formall vnderſtanding of things that are, or may be, is ſignified to vs by the feminine vertue, wherof Raſis Arabe thus diſcourſeth.
            As Eleborus, of one and the ſelfe ſame ſubſtance brings foorth diuers effects for the heads diſeaſes: Euen ſo a woman qualifies diuers manner of tempeſts, which wandring through a mans braines, do weaken his ſtronger powers, vntill this lawfull and naturall medicine be therto applyed. Timaeus the Scicillian reporteth, that the Lions of Lybia looſe their force and furie, if they haue neuer ſo little ſight of a maidens eyes. And Bandello witneſſeth to

vs in his hiſtories, that a Lord of Scandia, being by nature dull and blockiſh; at the very firſt ſight and regarde of a Lady of Vicenſa, became diſcreetlie wiſe and well gouerned. Reaſon it ſelfe (according to Homer) is figured to vs by the perſon of Minerua, who flew out armed from the braines of Iupiter: and Bacchus, that is the angrie facultie, beeing painted in the forme of a man, had no other birthe then from his thigh. Wherupon, Ariſtophanes the comicall Poet of the Athenians, thought good to ſet downe this deſcription.
            
               Vertue in man dooth not abide,
               She's waſht away with furies tyde.
               But in faire women kinde ſhe reſts,
               For mildenes harbours in their breſts.
               And did not women make men wiſe:
               How many harmes would them ſurprize?
            
            
               Ariſtotle, that profound Occean of Philoſophie, and ſecond author of Nature, acknowledged ſo much of womens merits: that he ſacrificed (as it had bin to the gods) a million of times

to his beautifull Hermia, according to the report of Origen, and this which the Siracuſane Poet ſayeth:

                  No greater loue did Ariſtotle beare
                  To Thebane Hermia his ſoules ſoueraigneſſe:
                  But farre beyond that loue (if more there were)
                  Holde I to Tyna my faire Sheepheardeſſe.
               
            
            Diuine Plato, of whom Saint Auguſtine that Eagle of the Doctors, deliuereth a moſt ſinguler teſtimonie: ſo highlye commended the vertues of Archaneſſa, as he not onely ſerued her like a ſlaue, but compoſed diuers himnes in praiſe of her, comparing her qualities to be celeſtiall and ſupernaturall, as Diogenes Laertius truely recordeth. What ſhall I ſay of Socrates, the ornament of men, the ground of Oracles, glorie of the Greekes, ſplendoure of the Athenians, and flood of diuine pluralities? did he not deſire to make all poſterities know, that man is ſomwhat leſſe then a woman? yea, and that in ſound earneſt, whē to the great

ſcandale of beleeuing them of his own kind, in contempt of the critique Philoſophers, ouerthrowe of the preſumptuous, debaſing the Athenians, and contrary to the opinion of all the Greekes: he preferred one onely Aſpaſia (as Clearchus reciteth) before a million of men, for her knowledge in all kinde of learning, and deepe skill, not onely in thoſe things that beſt might ſerue, but enriching beſide all humaine ſocietie.
            The meruaile of Cos, Hippocrates hath taught vs, that the moſt perfect bodyes are thoſe, which haue leſſe heate then moiſture. Whereupon, the great ſonne of kings, Prince of Arabia, three times together reprooued Galen, who held, that heate is cheefeſt in the building of all things, as maintaining, that moyſture is onely fomented and ſeaſoned by the heate. Diuine Homer likewiſe inſtructs vs, that the eſtate of all things is drawne from the Occean, and that it is the cheefeſt of the elements:

wherein the Cittizen of Millet Thales dooth ſecond him, and likewiſe Pindarus in this Ode.
            
               The Sea aboue all elements,
               Hath the cheefeſt ornaments.
               Euen as golde dooth luſtre bright,
               Like to a ſacred flame in ſight,
               And ſhines more faire then all mettalls,
               Diſperſed in the mineralles.
            
            Now as women are much more moyſte then men, ſo in like manner may we diſcerne in them, that frenzies and furiouſnes is not ſo familiar with them as men: in regarde they will neuer runne madde for loue, or any other worldly deſire. Whereas men from time to time, make themſelues as in a publique Theater, the ſubiect of very tragicall follies, ſuch as the like can ſcant be imagined, yet cuſtomablie vſed in aſſemblie of their friends, agreeing with the oppinion of the Poet Antimachus.
            
            
               
               The Cadmeane cittie brought foorth crueltie,
               Thoſe Germaine twins pale Death and Enuie▪
               
               Which more inhumaine then an angrie Beare,
               Depriuing life, leaues yet a world of feare.
            
            I will begin by ſtate affaires to approoue, alleadging thereto ſufficient witneſſes, that the vertue feminine hath bin of greater efficacie then men, not onely in this ſubiect but any other whatſoeuer, eſpecially the matter heer alleaged: for it conſiſteth much more of debating caſes, and the facultie imaginatiue, which indeed are the happieſt functions of the ſoule, then any other deſſeignes that we can deale withall. And ſo dooth Xenophon teſtifie, that the partie which is apte for the managing of publique occaſions, whereon many welfares conſiſt, euen infinite as it were: is endued with ſome perticuler gift of nature, or bleſſed from the heauens beyond many other. All the great Monarchies were inſtituted by the councell of women. Sbithea Siſter to Nimrod, enſtructed him

in the courſe of gouernement, according as Manethon reporteth. Preſigithes a Sheepheardeſſe did the like to Cyrus. Dydo firſt founded the common wealth of Carthage. Semiramis reſerued the Empire to her Sonne, albeit hee was thereof vncapable: and Fauna brought together the people of Italie diſperſed heere and there, before ſhe went to Caſsino in Caſsina, for agreeing of the one with the other; as it is recorded in certaine fragments of the Poet Ennius.
            
            
               
                  Fauna the Goddeſſe Veſtaes woman preeſt,
               Firſt taught the Latines ciuill gouernement:
               And whē in fields they wandred where they liſt,
               She brought them into Citties regiment.
            
            
               Tomyris Queene of the Scithians; appointing to them the lawes of Anacharſis the Philoſopher: aſſured them to be more holy and better then thoſe of the Athenians. She reſtored her Empire, being halfe bruſed by the Souldiours of Ariartſanes the Captaine,

and the death of her own Sonne, who ſuffered himſelfe to be fondly ſurprized, and afterward cruelly ſlaine: notwithſtanding, ſhe valiantly triumphed ouer Cyrus, the vniuerſall Monarche of the Eaſt.
            
               Pentheſilea knowing that it would be hard to ſquander the Greekes in Helleſpont, by reaſon of their multitude, beeing well neere numberleſſe: attended them on the frontiers of Miſia, and there ouerthrew Hippoclus, conducter of the back bandes of all the Grecian people. Hippolita diſſipated the troupes of great Theſeus, diſmounting himſelfe in the fight, yet afterward (on meere grace) made him her husband.
            The Siracuſan women were cauſe of their Citties preſeruation, beeing before abandoned by their huſbands, whence aroſe the prouerbe of Venus armed, as Menander deſcribeth in one of his Comedies.
            
               
               Let none himſelfe ſo much abuſe,
               As offer to take Syracuſe
                  ▪
               
               For women haue it in reſpect,
               And Venus dooth them ſafe protect.
               Good were it then the God of warre,
               Should lend to her his Cemiter.
            
            
               Cyrus vanquiſhed by the common flight of his Souldiours, and his owne proper faulte: thus deliuered the victorie to his enemie by this only exhortation, that they but came to fight with women. The Romaines ſurprized by the Sabines, and other people neere neighbours to them: were warrented from death and vtter deſtruction of their Cittie, by the meanes of women, who knew how to quenche the anger iuſtly enflamed in their fathers againſt their husbands. Paryſatis, daughter to Cyrus, and mother to Artaxerxes, was ſo well enſtructed in the ſtate affayres: as ſhee made Aſia tryumphe of the Greekes liberty, compaſſing by her gouernement the loſſe of all the allyed common weale, and

ſtealing by her gifts, the moſt liberall courages of her Empires enemies, which was (in ſhew) ruled by her ſon, but in verye deede maintained by her ſelfe. The mother of Coriolanus ſaued the citty of Rome, euen from the cradle to her glorious height, vſing ſo manie great maximes of and for the ſtate, to her ſonne being then the citties enemie: as all the Xenophons, Tacituſſes, Machiauels, yea, whatſoeuer Councellers to the Princes of Europe, may iuſtly learne example by thoſe noble reſolutions, and admit them amongſt the very cheefeſt deſſeignes. Cloelia gaue freedome to ſixe ſcore young men of her Cittie, by admiration of her fayre enterpriſe couragiouſly effected: which made Ennius the Poet thus write thereof.

                  What vertue male may with thy woorth cōtend,
                  Can men h
                        •
                     pe any way to doe as much
                  By their beſt meanes? Alas, tis to no end,
                  In like affaires their haps were never ſuch.
               
               
And elſewhere.
            
               Young Romaines feeble are your mindes,
               Your glorie of the leaſt eſteeme:
               When Cloelia paſſage for you findes,
               And muſt with honor you redeeme.
            
            
               Rhea knew ſo well to temper the prodigious crueltie and tyrannie of Saturne, who not onely would diſinherit her ſonnes, but deuoure them, to aſſwage his more then brutiſh hunger: that as Orpheus rehearſeth in his Songs.
            
               
                  Iupiter from blame had not been free,
               If Rheas prudence had not been of might:
               To ſheeld him from the ſpightfull iealoſie.
               Her tyrant husband vſde both day and night.
            
            
               Veſta deliuered the Hetrurians from the beſiegings of Alſichoris. Medea made victorious Iaſon conquer the golden Iſles, and defended the Argonautes from ſtraunge ambuſcadoes, which were preparde for them in the Iſle of Colchos. A
                     •
                  alanta knew how

to enfranchiſe the Curetes, from their ordinarie tributes to the Princes of Achaia, euen till the day ſhe triumphed ouer them in the race.
            
               Debora, Iudith and Heſter, wrought meruailes for conſeruation of their people, euen to the enterpriſe of ſo high actions, as the iſſue of them could not be apprehended, their beginnings were ſo dreadfull, their effects beyond compariſon, and their vertue bounded within no equalitie, to the confuſion of men, amazement of the Gods, and perpetuall memorie of the feminine ſexe.
            Thus much for ſtate affaires, although this is not the hundreth part of that I could produce to maintaine this ſubiect, which might be handled by Angels, and ſufficient for my ſences to ſtand and woonder at. Yet haue I heere made no mention of the Amazones in generall, nor of the Cipriotes, nor of the Sydonians, and many other ſundry countries, who both in

common &amp; perticuler, haue gotten ſo much glory by armies of womē: as mē durſt hope no otherwiſe, but in the meere fables they haue written of thē
               ſelues, boaſting of victories gottē ouer their equalles, and one while againſt Lions, then Beares, and ſome Tygers, with other of like ſtrength and violence, wherein women haue done as much, or rather more then they.
            They were wont to tryumph ouer Ladyes reputation, making vauntes of ſome thinges wherein their merites were vnequall, finding their courage to be eyther to feeble, or not anſwerable: whereupon diuine Sapho complained in this ſort.
            
               Diuers there be haue heard men ſay▪
               
               That ouer women they beare ſway,
               Making their tryumph of our hearts,
               As vanquiſhed by their deſerts.
               All which is nothing but a dreame,
               And folly out of courſe extreame.
            
            I haue knowne diuers, who but admitted to the ſight of a Ladies ſleeue, preſently haue made theyr vauntes of

her maidenheades victory, when (God knows) they durſt not intreate ſo much fauour as a kiſſe.
            Conſtancy followeth ſo neere to the vertuous exerciſe of ſtare affaires, and occaſions of war, as being the organe of fayreſt deſſeignes, and only perfection of moſt commendable ſtrength: that as I might heere (on mens behalf) preſent to your ſight the ſame ſeuerally in Sceuola, Regulus, Marius, Cato Vtican, Scipio Affricanus, and Paulus Aemillius among the Romaines; ſo like wiſe for the Grecianes, Antigonas, ſurnamed the wiſe Anaxagoras, Socrates, Xantippa, Anaxarcus, Ariſtides, &amp; Phocion: like wiſe out of holy Scripture, Eliazer, Tobias, the Machabees, all which are but as vaſſailes &amp; meane ſeruants, in reſpect of the iuſt and lawfull conſtancy of women: who in this as all thinges elſe worthy to be commended, haue ſo farre out-gone the courage of men, as the Sunnes glorious bryghtneſſe excelleth all the

candles of the night: I call them iuſt, becauſe I ſhall neuer be perſwaded, but that ſuch as haue beene enforced to the abandoning of ouermuch ſadneſſe, and thence haue made choiſe of voluntarie deaths, more for obedience to reaſon then diſpaire: well deſerued to bee called conſtant or magnanimous, conſidering that no defect of courage, or feare of great puniſhment any iote diſmayed them, but rather (to ſpeake more properlie) gladly ſubiected them to this funerall reſolution.
            
               Soclaris, daughter to Cibaris Gouernour of Athens, firſt Prince of Morea, ſometimes called Peloponneſus, after the conqueſt of Combly, was deliuered into the hands of Selim, to vſe at his pleaſure, according to the barbarous cuſtome of his predeceſſours, who were more vniuſt in their victories, then the vanquiſhed miſerable in their ouerthrow: and hauing her at his diſpoſing, hee commaunded the Bathe to bee prepared, which is the

critique ſignall of the Eaſterne luxuries. The young Princeſſe, who to the Cataſtrophe of this Greekiſh tragedie, would giue beginning to a new Hiſtorie, drawne rather from the deſpoyle of her owne life, then delight to looſe her inuiolable chaſtitie; ſpake in this manner to the Prince of the Eaſt.
            MY Lord, vntill this very inſtant I was perſwaded, that the wrath of God, iuſtly diſperſed among our familie, would ſerue it ſelfe with matters familiar, and ordinarie to afflict vs withall, as beeing doubtleſſe guiltie of ſome farre greater puniſhment, then euer wee felt vnder your victorious hand: and beeing caried away with theſe ſweete oppinions, I drew my comfort from mine owne proper ill, as onely hoping of remedie in your grac
                  •
                and fauour. But at this preſent, your Maieſtie being rapte with what furie I knowe not, wherein royall

vertue is not to bee diſcerned: I cannot beleeue, that heauen hath limitted your thoughts to ſuch an abhominable courſe, or rather a moſt prodigious violence, the beginning whereof I beholde, by the ende of my life, trayned through mine owne default, alongſt the torrent of ſolaſciuious an enterpriſe. Then ſhewing him a little needle: See heere (quoth ſhee) what armes are prepared as guardians of my virginity, behold the innocent organe of ſuch vengeance, as I meane to take on my offending eyes, that wounded you ſo againſt the will of my ſoule, which from my mouth pronounceth ſentence of death againſt them, and you ſhall ſee execution immediatly performed.
            The great Monarch, toucht to the quicke with extraordinary compaſſion, made a ſodaine change of his loue to a perpetuall admiration, and his ouer fond commaund tooke ending with a moſte maieſticall reſpect, returning

theſe or the like words to the Princeſſe.
            MAdame, if Kings could as wel tryumph ouer loues paſſions, as they can cheriſh mercy▪ and giue pardon to the faulty, euen againſt the firſt obiect of theyr owne vnruly motions, which figure in theyr courage a tempeſtious ſea of vengeance, yet notwithſtanding, becomes calme by a naturall inclynation of imbracing mildeneſſe: rather then purſuing the ouer-ſwift current of choller:) I ſhould haue ſomewhat to complaine of to you, for grafting the trophees of my deſires, on the firme rock of your chaſte deſſeignes, which teach me the ſcience of good life in ſo holy a Schoole.
            It followes therefore, that I muſte confeſſe the deſtinies to be vniuſt, for ſhewing that freedome to the body, wherewith the ſoule no way can bee forced.
            
               Accuſe loue then, who armed himſelfe for you here in my houſe, where your beauties priſoners are become Princeſſes of my heart, entyrely enthralled: And neuer conceiue, that I am onely he, that deſires the fruite of his victory, on a ſubiect of ſuch merite, the enioying whereof is more to be coueted, then aduerſe Fortune is to be credited.
            Conſidering, that in proſecution of my good haps, vntill this preſent, I haue beene alwayes armed with reaſon, not enterpriſing any thing to diſaduantage of the vanquiſhed, otherwiſe then the ſecuritye of mine owne eſtate did teach me. The proofes whereof remaine euident to be ſeene, in that I haue not made your countries miſhaps greater, then the inconſtancy of Fortune yeelded vnto: where I haue ſet downe my reſt, giuing lymits to my iuſt ambition, which elſe had extended it ſelfe ouer the common libertye of Greece, if ſeruitude

were not called an exchange of ſtate▪ rather happening by the prouidence of heauen, who would haue but one ſole Monarch in the vniuerſall world, for generall adminiſtration of his iuſtice, rather then any vnſatiable deſire in my ſelfe of Soueraignety, which containes mine actions where they are only appropriate.
            But if I haue treſpaſſed, in requeſting that of you, which my Kingdoms lawes cannot deny me, neyther may bee tearmed as an offence, but only that your will doth ſo holde and eſteeme it: then cuſtome is more to be blamed then I am, for ſhe inuites me to take poſſeſſion, of that which freely is reckoned mine owne.
            Therefore Lady, that you may ſee I wil not deſerue a Tyrants name, eſpecially in the ſimple practiſe of victory, wherein vſuallye more rygour is expected, then in the gouernment of a peaceable eſtate: I will compell mine vnlawfull paſſions, to yeelde

vnto your iuſter deſires, entreating you to reſt thus contented, that in repentaunce for offending you, I doo wronge to the nature of mine owne power, diſarming my heart of that prerogatiue, which the very meaneſt men moſte couet in theyr ſpeciall Fortunes, namely, to tryumph in commaunding of their owne.
            Demaund of mee thoſe ſelfe ſame thynges, which you could not hope for in your former condition: and I will ſatiſfie them with as much willingneſſe, as there is worth and deſert in your Princelye conſtancye. Such ende had the great Turkes loue, if the name of great bee worthye enough to dignifie his vertues, which in greatneſſe did exceede hys Empyre.
            The hiſtory of Tenora, taken priſoner in the Citty of Modon, and enfranchiſed for her conſtancy, beſt knowen to Baſcha Ariaden, who gladly would haue marryed her: might

heere bee auouched to the great ſcandale of men, and perpetuall honour of the female ſexe: but in regard of the l
                  •
               ngth, let me referre yee to I
                  
                     •••
                  obaldus of Corfue, a moſt ſound and faythfull expreſſer thereof.
            The height of courage in three Spaniardes, who offered theyr chaſte breſtes to their miſerable father▪ conſtrayned to graunt them ſo vnpleaſing an execution, for ſhielding them from the ſhamefull ſeruitude prepared for them: is of ſuch efficacy, as men (for preſeruation of theyr renowne) had neuer the heart to endure ſo extreame a remedy. For reading of which excellent diſcourſe, I muſt leaue yee to Nicholas de Nicholai, hys voyage of Conſtantinople, in the hiſtorye of the ſeidge of Trypoly.
            
            I haue very much wherewith to enlarge my labour, as the maruaylous conſtancy of Ioan the Pucel, whoſe life the Engliſhmen had gladly ſaued, if

ſhe would ſimply haue ſaid, that ſhee was holpen by charmes, extraordinarie meanes, and ſupernaturall power in execution of her perillous enterpriſes: but ſhe preferred her honor before life, yeelding her conſcience to tormenters, and her tormenters to leaſings, as louing rather to ſuffer a bodilie hell, then making helliſh the freedome of her owne courage, in a purpoſe not beſeeming the greatneſſe of her deeds, nor the true oppinion iuſtlie conceiued of her behauiour, the principall organs of her valour, which made Fraunce more famous then euer it had beene before, yea, more then at this daye it hath attainde vnto: For though ſhee bee now troubled with ſome foure or fiue Spaniards in her liuer vaine; yet ſhe then drew a million of Engliſhmen out of her entrailes.
            I will not goe ſeeke out an Arbecha on Danubie, nor Gertrude on the Rheine, nor Flotenſa on Tanais, ſeeing the hiſtories of the North haue no

other honor, then onely of the ſubiect drawen from their conſtancies. Leſſe cauſe ſhal I haue to produce Polixena, whoſe death made the life of the Grecians infamous, and theyr victory inſolent, euen the vtter ouerthrow of all their renowne. The conſtancy of Antigone, deſcribed by Antimachus and Euripides, is of ſuch merite, as all men together cannot boaſt of any thing to come neere it: her piety is of ſuch commendation, as the moſt religious of our Aheiſtical age haue iuſt cauſe to complaine, that chriſtianity as yet neuer conceiued the like. The conſtant patience of Griſilda, written by Frederick of Aſt the Pied-monteſe, is vneuitable, and almoſt exceeding beleefe, in our weake ſoules ſo little inured to ſufferancy. That of Virginia, Portia and Sophonisba, the ornament of Affricke &amp; terror of Roome, is ſo great, as ſhee could endure more, then arte is able to deſcribe. Oh cowardly men, what ſhal become of ye? or rather, what are you

among ſo many gallant women, that haue abid the violent aſſaults of death, euen of death vndeſerued, and much leſſe expected? you are no way firme, but in lookes: conſtant, but in words: dreadleſſe, but in ſecurity: without corruptiō, but in feare to be made knowen to others. Better is it for you goe learne to ſpin, thē to prefer your ſelues before women: as your graund Hercules came capable of that occupation, by the enſtruction of his Miſtreſſe Dianeira. Sampſon was glad to reele hy his Dalila: Achilles ſowed by his Briſis: king Demetrius did the like by his Latmia. Heſiodus acknowledged this imperfection in men of his time, ſaying.
            
               You that are Natures infamy,
               And to your ſexe doe iniury.
               Shewing your ſelues imperfect men,
               By actions not beſeeming men.
               One ſits, and by his Miſtreſſe ſowes,
               Another, like a Goddeſſe goes.
               Other, miſsled by iealouſie,
               Muſt weare his garments to his knee,
               Yet all makes vaunts of Fortunes bliſſe,
               When ſhe moſt wretched to them is.
            
            
               My paper is vnworthy to beare my p
                  •
               n, in 
                  •
               eſcribing my immaginations, 
                  〈◊〉
                the high merit of holy Virgins, what contempt and diſdaine they made of the moſt barbarous cruelties, that could be inuented by the enemies of the Chriſtian faith, for defence wherof, they haue bin deliuered ouer to the feareful rage of perſecuters, who haue beene more weary of tormenting them, then they (any iot diſmaided) at the ſeuerall ſorts of violence inflicted on their bodies; by nature ſoft and tender, and more worthy to be admired, then ſo bloodyly murdred. Like matter could neuer men ſet downe of themſelues, albeit themſelues were Authours of the legends: for theyr martirologe containes ſo few of them (making compariſon with that of women) as the very wiſeſt tearme theyrs but a meere vanity, diſpearſed among the veritie of the Saintes ſufferings. The Church it ſelfe is reſembled to a woman without ſpot or blemiſh,

ſuch as Salomon deſcribes the Princeſſe of Aegypt, a figure of the Church. In the new Teſtament yee may note the three Maries, and the Chananean, who were ſo conſtant in their holy reſolutions, as the bleſſed ſpirit (being ſpeaker of the ſacred hiſtory) hath left them a ſpectacle to all poſterities. The mother of the ſeauen Martires, wherof deſcription is made in the Machabees, deliuered ſuch witneſſe of her truely tearmd celeſtiall confidence, as that onely acte might beautifie the hiſtory of vertuous women, more then men can gleane glory, from the conſtant reſolution of Abraham, Moyſes or Iob: all which deſerue not the tytle of conſtant, becauſe a little detection did in ſome ſort touch them.
            As firſt to begin with Abraham for a leaſing, who ſaid that his wife was his Siſter, only for a little feare of death, much more ſuſpected, then any way prepared. Next for diſtruſt, as whē 
               Moyſes ſaid to the Lord: Howe may it

be, that I ſhould preſent my ſelfe before Pharoah, ſeeing J can hardly abſtaine from ſtammering? Js it poſſible that I ſhould deliuer this meſſage? Then for murmuring, as Job, who ſtood expoſtulating with the eternall. Which minde neuer came neere the Virgin of Virgins, for ſhe ſaid: I am the ſeruant of the Lord, be it vnto mee according to his word. Abraham, Moiſes and Iob, were but weake in reſolution, if one ſhould compare them with that vertuous woman, mother to theſe 7. Martires who ſuffered as many paines, as ſhe ſaw diuerſity of torments applied, to ruinate and ouerthrow the conſtancy of her Sons: yea, ſhe did ſollace her ſelfe in ſuch ſort among the rigours of theyr martirdome, with ſuch behauiour and ſpeeches in contempt of death, and aſſurance of better condition in the life ſucceeding; as they all were euen ſorry they could dye but once. In ſooth I muſt needs ſay, that the very greateſt matter among mē, neither is or can be,

but the remainder &amp; ouerplus of this one womans glory, who practiſed the ſame in her ſelf, which ſhe had taught to her Sons: for ſhe dyed ſo conſtantly, that Antiochus (the very abhomination of Kings) became enraged (as it were) to ſee a ſimple woman mocke him and all his angry threatnings, no way able to enforce her from the ſeruice of God, after which ſhe ſighed &amp; longed, euen to the lateſt office of her vitall powers. The daughter of Jeptah ſhal giue end to this diſcourſe, becauſe ſhe concluded the raſh vow of her Father with ſuch reſolution, as the ſacrafice of her own life: for which, I had rather cōmit ye to read the hiſtory in the Iudges, for better ſight of her death, then drowne my paper in iuſt teares, which freſh reuiued pitty of ſo ancient a maruel, would forcibly compel to fal from mine eies, ſo to conceale by weeping, what I could not ſet downe in writing, Thus much remēbred for womens cōſtancy, which makes me ſtand

in doubt, whether I ſhould erect the ſame on any other collom or no, then their own greatnes &amp; deſerts, as more needing imitation, then any witnes, &amp; therfore more requiring to be followed, then can be by words witneſſed effectually: For mē (malitiouſly iealous of womens honor) haue buried (as much as in them lay) the moſt commendable deeds of ſuch, to whom themſelues were no otherwiſe then Apes, nay worſe imitators, if worſe may bee. He that (of Poets) hath beſt writtē amōgſt the Greciās, is Homere, yet not ſo much for his learning, as for ye ſubiect, where he makes men &amp; the Gods cōbate together, thoſe are his Jlliades, a worke in ſooth praiſe worthy for his time, &amp; not for any other conſideratiō. Yet the Athenians made thē be publikly burned, by reaſō of the impiety wherwith they are furniſhed, euē as it were a ſhop of Atheiſme, irreligiō, &amp; imodeſty, making the Gods to be vanquiſhed by mē, &amp; eſtabliſhing a contempt of royalty, duty

and obeyſance, in the perſon of Achillis (a meere brothell hunter) who preferred a brutiſh kinde of affection, before the loue of his Countrey, and his owne peculiar hate before the general welfare of his followers. Hee makes a dog of Agamemnon; a kitching fellow of Patrocles; a mad man of Hector; a bawde of Jris; a drunkerd of Vulcane; a Cony-catcher of Mercury; a Lacky of Appollo; a rauiſher of Neptune; a paltry companion of Mars; a witch of Minerua; a Woolfe of Venus; a Megera of Iuno, a dreame of a man, and himſelf a contemner of the Gods, as Licras ſpeaketh in this manner.
            
               Curious Antiquity,
               Made Homere a deitie,
               For his booke, a meere fable,
               Againſt the Gods abhominable,
               Where all men that were vicious,
               Haue praiſe before the vertuous.
            
            Among Latine Poets, we may ſpeak of Virgill: in the Hierarchie of Philoſophers,

who but Ariſtotle? among Phiſitions, Hippocrates: amongſt the auncient diuines, Mercurius Triſmegiſtus: in our latter times, S. Auguſtine: of Aſtronomers, Anaxagoras: of Mathematicians, Archimedes: of Ciuillians, Papinian: all which had (euen then liuing) two, nay three or foure women in their owne Artes, to whome I will ſend them ſeuerally to ſchoole, for apprehenſion of the chiefeſt principles in their ſciences. Homere was taught by Clorinda the Samian, in the Citty of Argos, and to her hath bin attributed that ſo famous worke of the Illiads: &amp; would ye but compare his Odiſſeaes therwith, you ſhould finde ſuch a large difference in one ſtile, ſo much rebated in the diſcourſe of Vliſſes: as you wold be conſtrained to confeſſe, that eyther the firſt is none of his, or els hee made neither the one nor other. Faire Sapho holpe him at a need, for changing the armes of Glaucus and Diomede, where it euidently appeares that hee dealt

ſcarce honeſtly: as alſo in his compariſon of Aiax to an Aſſe, where he plaid the grinder too apparantly. She likwiſe corrected the works of Pindarus, as ye ſhal find it ſet downe in Plutarch. Carmenta was ſo learned in poeſie, as ſhe ſurpaſſed al the men of her time, &amp; had indeed ſuch a general name, as not any to this day did euer attaine the like, no ordinary matter among our mē Poets whoſoeuer: And ſhe enſtructed Pithagoras himſelfe (true Prince of the very beſt Philoſophy among the Pagans.) Ariſtotle ſearching the cauſes, whence the ebbing &amp; flowing of the ſea ſhuld proceed: had his reſolutiō from Soſtrata the Lesbian, by a ſimilitude taken from womens infirmity, as alſo from ſweate: Nor did he drowne himſelfe, (as ſome bawling curres wold make vs beleeue) in the Ocean ſea, wherinto he ſhould head-long caſt himſelfe. Hippocrates learned the curing of the Hemeroides, of Dorothea Abderita, as it was found written in Epheſus, in the

Temple of Diana, as alſo the other at Eleuſina. Mercurius Triſmegiſtus is not only the firſt or chiefeſt, of the celebrate &amp; moſt commendable Diuines of antiquity: but (I dare ſay) of al men, bee it that wee ſpeake of Salomon, or were it poſſible to find a wiſer; his life did truely anſwere his doctrine, and his doctrine is both the ſchoole of vertue, and ſtudy of true piety.
            Yet notwithſtanding, hee is not to be extolled beyond the Sibilles, all which propheſied of the true Meſſias the Son of God ſo euidently, as there is not a text in the olde Teſtament, more expreſſe then their propheticall writings were. Wherein, it pleaſed the holy Ghoſt to ſerue himſelfe by them, for confuſion of the Pagane incredulity, and to giue theſe deuoute women, as theyr Iudges, being faithfull Trumpets of the comming of Chriſt Ieſus, as alſo of his death and reſurrection.
            I may equal Marcella the virgin with

S. Auguſtine, as well for her excellent writings, full of all erudition, as for her ſanctity: ſhe only being the cauſe of the Hungars cōuerſſion. Which good hap did neuer befal S. Auguſtine, who long time held very heretical opinions &amp; far from the vniuerſal beliefe: where contrariwiſe this woman, neuer had her thoughts toucht with any other conſideration, then the community of Chriſtians in the primatiue Church, which being ſnarled at in her time, &amp; not as then knowen in the Northerne parts: ſhe reduced from old ruines, &amp; made it fauored in the moſt barbarous ſpirits: yea, they that were leaſt capable of vnderſtanding in Europe. The roots of her piety ſtretched thēſelues ſo far as Albania, euen to the Citty of Raguſa, held then in ſubiection by Cyarſin the Sclanonian: whom ſhee not onely made a chriſtian, but cōpanion likwiſe of her deuout ēterpriſes, &amp; that in ſuch ſort, as he came with a maine army ſo far as Danuby, &amp; there aduāced

the glorious ſtandard of the euangelical truth. I could ſay, that Frenchmen had not been Chriſtians, but by the eſpeciall vertue of Clotilda, whom God ordained to inſpire the heart of Clouis, onely made a Chriſtian by her charitable admonitions and faithfull enſtructions: who▪ by the loſſe of many battailes, could not elſe be ſo reſolued. When ſhall it be ſayd, that men haue been ſo ſoudious in like number of ſoueraigne exerciſes and ſanctitie? that our God (the iuſt electer of pureſt ſoules, for communicating of his very deareſt perfections) hath made more redound to his glorye vnder the perſons of women, then euer it pleaſed him to doo the like by men.
            
               Anaxagoras was as ignorant in the reaſon of the Seas ebbing and flowing, as Ariſtotle, vntill he had ſome enſtruction therein, by Dyoris the wyfe of one Barquerot of Pyrea: ſhe ſhewed him the originall of the Iſles engirting neere to the firme land, where

the borrowing waues ſeemed to enlarge their waye by ſome violent meanes.
            He learned the cauſes of coniunction of the great Planets, and their times, of a woman Gardiner of Smirna: by whome likewiſe hee came acquainted with the deepeſt ſecrets of the Meteores. Archimedes was mocked by Tyanea the Syracuſaine, for hauing rudely ſaid, that all bodyes were ſuperficiall: which ſhe ſhewed to bee falſe, by the Atomies and coullers in the ayre. Lachis of Athens, daughter to Megeſteus, ordained lawes to the people of Attica, which were ſo venerable and commodious: as the Romaines receiued them naturally for their own limitting them vnto twelue tables, wherein there was contayned more iuſtice and pietie, then in all the volumes of Papinian.
            
            I was too blaine (in this ſerious purpoſe) to forget Oratours, ſuch as were Demoſthenes, Aeſchines, Jſocrates,
               
and manye other amonge the Grecians; Cicero, Hortenſius, Marke Anthonie, &amp;c. of the Romaines.
            Moſt true is it, that this my forgetfulnes had been infinitely aduantageable for men, who likewiſe heerein are not exempt from theyr naturall imperfection, beeing ouer much weake in eloquence to women.
            
               Demoſthenes, of whome it is written, that if the Goddes would ſpeake Greeke in Orations, they could no waye amend the ſweete elocution of this Oratour: yet was hee ſo confounded, hearing Lais diſcourſe of men and womens perticuler affections, as hee cryed out; that the Athenians did but ſtammer in theyr Schooles, and women at Corinthe ſpake Oratours-like in theyr familiar conferences.
            To confirme this, Nature teacheth vs, that women are or may be moſt eloquent, conſidering the organes and

inſtruments of theyr voyce is more mylde and gentle, then thoſe in men, whoſe pronunciation is very rough, ſharpe and coorſely ſhapte, by reaſon of the aboundance of choller, which (with their woords) driues foorth ſo much vehemencie of ſpirit, as they are well neere choakt therewith, or breake their winde in vttering of their ſpeeche: yet wee muſt confeſſe, that melancholly men are ſofter in words, then the ſwarthie and ſanguine, ſuch ſeuerall qualities remaine in men.
            The nature of a woman being enclined to ſadneſſe, diſcouers wiſedom, makes her prudent and apprehenſiue: whereas men are commonly raſhe and vnrulye, becauſe diuers appetites tranſport them, to many friuolous and fleeting conſiderations, which mightie faulte you ſhall finde fewe women, or none at all infected with. In lyke manner, your high and ſoueraigne Courtes, are nothing elſe but filled with mens continuall tumults, whence

enſue iniurious offences to theyr betters: and that in matters of ſo meane reckoning, as womens modeſtie are aſhamed thereof, and theyr height of ſpirit holdes it in moſt deepe diſdaine.
            Oh moſt happye ſexe, if it were lawfull for me to ſpeake, as Plato did, who thanked the Gods for making him a man, and not a beaſt: ſo could I haue wiſhed, that I had beene created a woman, hauing attayned to ſuch knowledge of feminine perfections, which is in euery reſpect accompliſhed, beyond all that can be tearmed perfect in humaine defects.
            But returne wee to our Oratours, leauing the Aſſe, eares and all, to them that perſwade themſelues to be more eloquent then women: from whome the ſweete Nightingale firſt learned her notes, as Pyes, Crowes and Rauens tooke theyrs from men, into which ſhapes they haue likewiſe been tranſformed, as the onely beſt forme the Greeke and Latine Poets could

giue them. You ſhall many times read, that the Gods haue made complaint to Jupiter, eyther of men, or their bad conditions, and could neuer gaine accompliſhment of theyr deſires; ſo groſſe and abſurde were they in theyr Orations, in regarde of the Goddeſſes, who were neuer ſent backe but fully ſatiſfied, euen in thoſe things which humaine iuſtice made a conſcience of graunting; ſo much well-ſpeaking women haue preuayled, aboue the vnſauorie barking of rude men. Which wiſe Pithagoras well perceiuing, forbad his Schollers to ſpeake, to keepe vnſeene the great defect in nature, which is much more in men then women▪ 
               Cornelia the mother of Gracchus, was ſo eloquent, as the Romaines erected her an Altar, and ſacrificed to her in the Temple of Pitho, which Pitho was the Goddeſſe of eloquence, and ſurpaſſed both Gods and men in that vertue. Mercurie thus complained, as ſaith one of the Greekes.
            
               
               Alas, what helps it me to be,
               Ambaſſadour to Ioue
               
               My father, and each day to ſee,
               the roundneſſe from aboue:
               Of earth, and heauen all conuayd
               within my wings faire flight:
               When as my Godhead it miſſayed,
               and robbed of his right?
               Sweete ſpeaking Pytho calleth me
               abortiue, baſely borne:
               Becauſe my ſpeech is harſh to hers,
               and held as common ſcorne.
               A Goddeſſe I confeſſe ſhee is,
               yet may ſhe not like me,
               Sit at that boord of higheſt bliſſe,
               where but twelue Gods may be.
               All which the heauens doo controule,
               and one of them am I:
               Yet thus ſhe ſingeth from her ſoule,
               my endleſſe obloquie.
            
            I ſhall neuer haue doone with this endleſſe piece of worke, which by infinite pluralities doo offer themſelues, for iuſtifying of the feminine eloquence, the vſe whereof would God I might borrowe a while, as nothing more appropriate to this theame, for what elſe can make it ſo perfect

as it deſerues? but onely the diuine eloquence of thoſe celeſtiall creatures, and therefore had neede to be addorned with the excellencie of their nature, which of it ſelfe is ſo ſinguler, as nothing can be more. Oh might I be inſpired but with the leaſt of thoſe perfections, which as the bodies ſhaddowe wayteth duely vppon women, an accident inſeperable from the firſt ſubſtance of theyr heauen borne eſſence, that ſtandeth exempt from bad thinking, much leſſe blunt ſpeaking: then ſhould this diſcourſe appeare in more excellent manner, witneſſe that which the Greeke makes Calipſo ſpeak to 
                  Ʋliſſes.
            
            
               Twas not of me thou learndſt ſuch bitter breath
               Againſt ſtout Aiax, who did ſeeke to ſcape
               Thy iniurie, by prompt and preſent death,
               Or to reuenge him on thy Cowards ſhape.
               Nor, to the Ithacanes (vnapt, to lead,)
               Learndst thou of thy too faint harted flight,
               When as on heapes Sarpedon dung downe dead
               The Argines which their veſſels had in ſight,
               My words with infamie did nere take truce,
               
                  Or my faire ſoule endure baſe feares abuſe,
               Nor hadſt thou there that day beheld my land,
               Which on all ſides the Sea dooth counterband.
            
            If Painting were not reckoned among mechanicall Artes, I would approoue women to merit the very beſt trophee thereof: But as Nature euermore delighteth to create thoſe things which to her ſelfe are moſt pleaſing and conformable, and makes herſelfe exerciſe in thoſe matters, that doo deſcribe her cheefeſt perfections; ſo may I ſay of women, who ſhould too much wrong themſelues by taking pleaſure in painting, conſidering it is a matter impoſſible for them, to make ſuch a rare repreſentation, as their iuſt beauties doe require, becomming much leſſe by Painting, then the diuine graces wherewith they are moſt richlye accompanyed, builded onely vppon inimitable liniaments of theyr behauiour, the very onely models of the angels beauties, which were neuer

fourmed but by the abſolute 
                  〈…〉
               .
            Great Apoſtles, in his ordinarie painting of the Gods, very well knew how to figure Iupiter, Mars, Mercurie or Saturne: but when he went about to ſet downe the fourme of 
                  Ʋenus; hee found his skill to be of ſuch woonderous weakeneſſe, as hee was compeld to leaue his labour imperfect, teſtifying to all poſterities, that his arte altered it ſelfe into ignoraunce, when hee went about to ſet downe the ſingularitie of women; among whom, Loue it ſelfe ſought to be looked on, as in a publique Theater, where her maieſtie receiued much more luſter, then in any other ſubiect poſſible to be heard of or choſen. And this was the reaſon that kinde Leander thus ſpake to Hero.
            
            
               
                  Hero my most deare Princeſſe,
               Loue her ſelfe liues in thine eyes:
               The Graces, and their youthfulneſſe,
               Abide in thee as in the skies.
               Who is it can thy ſhape depainte,
               
                  Or who can iustly 
                     〈…〉
                  
               
               Exce
                     ••
                   
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
               
               
                  
                     〈1 line〉
                  
               
               
                  
                     〈1 line〉
                  
               
               
                  
                     〈1 line〉
                  
               
               
                  
                     〈1 line〉
                  
               
               
                  
                     〈1 line〉
                  
               
            
            
               Vulcane, as 
                  〈◊〉
                
               
                  •
               eaded as hee was, yet could hee vſe theſe woords to Venus.
            
            
               The thunder well I wot to make,
               And ſtout Aegides menacer:
               The tempeſt that all earth dooth ſhake,
               And through the ayre is wanderer.
               Battailes faire figures I can frame,
               All formall combates I can plot:
               The height of walles, and whence they came,
               Nor haue! Soldiours heate forg
                     •
                  t.
               But ſhould I offer to ſet downe,
               Thy beauties woorth and ſoueraigntie:
               Then heauen it ſelfe on me would frowne,
               For paſsing my capacitie.
            
            As for Muſique, among women it is ſo familiare, as their very voyce is naturally a hermonie. Aelianus recounteth, that there was a woman

Muſitian in Roome ſo excellent, as euery one imagined ſhee holpe her ſelfe by Magique: ſo rarely could ſhe rauiſh by the eare the mindes of them that heard her; yea, it grewe to ſuch effect, as many frantique people were thereby recouered from theyr furye. Moſt certaine is it, that Philliada the Tiriane inuented the Lute, whence roſe the prouerbe: The Harpe of Idumea, and the Lute ef Phoenicia, and the teſtimonie heereof is drawne from others, by the Lord of Bartas.

                  The cunning Tirianes, who on barke of trees,
                  Did first ſet downe the voices hermonies.
               
And a Grecian, thus.

                  Inuentreſſe was Philliada,
                  
                  Of Lutes in faire Phoenicia.
                  
                  She first gaue ſpirit and quick life
                  To dead dull wood, and made ſo rife
                  The ſeuerall ſweetes of Hermonie,
                  By her rare wit and induſtrie.
               
            
            
               When Alexander the great had conquered the kingdome of Darius, he found ſo skilfull a woman Muſitian in the cittie of Suſa, as could accomodate the varieties of her voice, to the ſeuerall noates of all kinde of birdes, and that with ſuch exceeding dexteritie, as they which ſawe her not, could make no difference from the verye thing it ſelfe. Great Caeſar likewiſe was woont to ſaye, that mens tunes were learnde from the Birdes chattering on trees: but the voice of women came from the Gods themſelues. The Syrens, ſo much deſcribed by the Grecians, had ſongs ſo wonderfull ſweete and mellodious: as they could out-eare the windes, and rob all mouthes of their naturall offices. The Greekes returning from the warres of Troye, reſted themſelues a long while in the Iſles where they inhabited, little caring for returne home into their owne country, by being rapt, or rather charmed with ſuch an hermonious delight.
            
               Perhaps ſome one will ſay vnto me, that the Tritons are verye excellent Muſitians, but he muſt withall confeſſe, that they neuer had like powet and vertue as the Syrens haue, of whom they learned their very deepeſt knowledge, albeit their Muſique ſtretche no further then the ſound of a Trumpet. Which Miſenus the Trompetter to Aeneas well perceiuing, prouoked them to ſound, to trie whether he could goe beyond them or no: marie he loſt his life therefore, if this narration be of any certaintie.
            
               But whilst his Trompet he did ſound,
               with glorie indiſcreetes
               Vpon the marble of the waues,
               the Tritons notes to meete.
               They iealous to be ſo defyed,
               in their owne pleaſing arte:
               In anger threw him in the waues,
               and ſo his life did parte.
            
            
               
               Iſtrina, the mother to Ariphita king of Scithia, was of ſuch eſtimation in Muſique: as the Poets haue feygned, that the Seas would neuer be calme, but when this Lady ſtood exchanging her ſweete Zephires with the Northerne guskes, which blew very bitterly vpon them continually. The Aſtronomers do holde, that Venus is the patroneſſe of Muſique, and that the influence of her Planet, brings moſt ſpeciall felicitie to ſuch as deale in that facultie.
            Let vs admit, that Theſpion the prieſt of the Gymnoſophiſts, Zoroaſtes of the Perſians, Hermes of the Aegiptians, Buda of the Chaldeans, Abbares of the Scithians, and Zalmoſis of the Thracians, excelled no leſſe in Muſique, then in pietie and knowledge of ſacred matters: yet notwithſtanding, they were but ſimple admirers of fayre Clora, daughter to God Anubis, who could charme the Crocadils of Nylus, as alſo them of hot Cyrena,

by the benefit of her voice reputed incomparable, which Lycoſthenes reports ſuch wonders of, as they ſeeme to mooue more aſtoniſhment then beleefe. Enough hath been ſaide concerning ſciences, and the glory which women haue gotten thereby, ouer-far beyond men: it remaines for me now to ſpeake of the morall vertues, which ſerue perticulerly to the guiding of life and ſanctitie. In which courſe (me thinkes) Temperance deſerues to haue the firſt place, as beeing that, which according to Hyppocrates and Galen, is the deareſt freend and fauourite of Nature. Euripides was not ignorant thereof, when he ſayd.
            
               Temperaunce makes men to liue,
               And beſide dooth freedome giue,
               From death, who ſooneſt dooth them ſmite,
               With a deceiuing appetite,
            
            The Greeke and Latine hiſtories are growne groſſe with millions of examples, which witneſſe the rare ſobrietie

of women, and exceſſe of men in all things whatſoeuer, according as it is ſayd in Exodus: Men roſe vp to playe, after they had long time wallowed in drunkenneſſe. Homer hath deſcribed this inſolence vnto vs, in the perſons of Penelopes Courtiers, who continued blameleſſe, notwithſtanding all theyr great immodeſtie. Hence is it, why Dioclea could not endure the laſciuious behauiour and diſhoneſtie of the Tyrant Phalaris, and therefore threw her ſelfe downe from a windowe, of which fall ſhee dyed verye ſoone after, ſpeaking theſe verſes of Menander.
            
            
               She that is in the grace of heauens happineſſe,
               Liueth not long in this worldes wretchedneſſe.
            
            And when an Epicure ſayd to her, that there was no other lyfe after this ſhould bee finiſhed, ſhee aunſwered him out of Pindarus in this ſorte.
            
               
               When as the night lockes vp the day,
               Yet heauen bideth at one ſtay.
               Our ſoules are then in thoſe faire fields,
               That daintie coullerd Roſes yeelds,
               Couerd with Trees perfumde and pure,
               And balmes that haue the richest cure.
               Vpon whoſe braunches fruites of golde,
               Doo hang most glorious to beholde.
               There, diuers walke deliciouſlie,
               Some ride on horſſes cheerefully.
               Others to muſiques hermonie,
               Of inſtruments make mellodie.
               There is a thouſand thouſand flowers,
               Of different ſmell to ſent the powers.
               There a many Altars fume,
               With Mirrhe and other ſweete perfume.
               And there is ſeene a ſhining fire,
               In this rare place which ſoules deſire.
            
            She likewiſe rehearſed this ſentence of Euripides.
            
            
               That which by name we doe entitle life,
               Is in effect but a continuall ſtrife.
            
            Indeed I well remember, that men haue beene famous for ſome rare qualities; as inuenting the ſundrie idle

playes at Dice and Cardes, with other ſuch like exerciſes beſide: Wherevpon, Saint Bernard ſhaping his courſe to the young men of his time, ſayde. You follow idleneſſe, to ſhun idleneſſe: you apply your ſelues to play, euen vntill yee fall into Deaths daunger. Iob in like manner cryed out againſt men, that they conſumed their dayes in vaine delights, and ſo in the end were diſpoſſeſſed of theyr liues. Good old Sara, hauing care of a holye conſcience, diſcourſed in this ſorte with the Eternall: I haue not frequented to theſe players, neither had acceſſe to vaine perſons. Well then, we may ſay, that men are artezanes and continuall labourers, in things altogether apperteining to follie, as in ſuperfluous tempering of meates, or in delicacies, the onely companion of inconſtancie, the goade to luxurie and birthe of death, and from whence he receiueth his onlie conception.
            Oh vile gourmandiſe, the onelye

peſtilence to humane kinde, by good reaſon oughteſt thou to liue amongſt men, who naturally are enemyes to theyr owne ſelues. Thou art he which troubleſt the braine, impeacheſt reaſon, prophaneſt chaſte eares, miſordereſt the behauiour of them thou poſſeſſeſt, thou beggereſt them that inherit thee, thou layeſt ambuſcadoes for chaſte thoughts, thou loadeſt the ſpirits with laſciuiouſnes; thou art hee that didſt murder our firſt father, and ſo brought an vniuerſall death vppon all mankinde, thou ſouldeſt Eſaues birthright; thou maſſacredſt the people in the deferr: in breefe, thou art the only inſtrument, wherwith are erected all circumuentions that worke violence to our ſoules, and eſpecially in the perſons of men, the ordinarie miniſters of thy pernicious practiſes.
            We read enough concerning intemperance, of Heliogabalus, of Caracalla, Caligula, Lucullus, Phaon, Xerxes, Ariſtippus, Myle of Crotona, and of Philoxenus,
               
who intreated Jupiter to grant him the neck of a Crane, to taſte with more leyſure the ſweetneſſe of his delicate viands: likewiſe of Candaules of Lidia, of Hermagoras, of Alexander, Darius, Marke Anthonie, with many other among the Pagans. Wee read beſide in holy Scripture, of Holophernes the enemie to God, a moſt diſſolute man, of Dauid in ſome ſort, of Ammon his ſonne, the Beniamites, the olde accuſers of Suſanna, the Gomorrhiſts and Sodomits: but of intemperate women, you ſhall verye hardly finde any that can be ſpoken of. 
                  Ʋeſta was ſo ſober in her life, that the Painters figured Faſting by her, as Exerciſe by Diana, Maieſtie by Iuno, and Prudence by Minerua. I will referre to your owne iudgement, that (ſeeing theſe vertues could be no way better ſignified, for in mē they would haue appeared moſt monſtrous) if womens natures muſt not needs be celeſtial, yea euen in their ordinary and cuſtomarie functions.
            
               Search thorow all Germanie, which is the empire of all drunkenneſſe and ſeruitude of the ſober: yee ſhall not finde one woman, but ſhe is not onely free from being taxed with that beaſtlineſſe, but likewiſe if ſhee haue once ouer drunke; it is ſufficient for her euer after. Where contrariwiſe the men, they hardly reſpect any other exerciſe, then toſſing &amp; emptying of the pottes, which is more ſhamefull to the vnſatiable, then the Wine they diſgorge can be to them healthfull. But perhaps you will ſay vnto me, it is not ſeemely for a woman to drinke much, and therefore that folly may be tollerated in men. Let me returne yee this anſwere, euill dooing is no more permitted to men then women, the rather in this reſpect; becauſe men make vaunts of beeing their ſuperiours, and that womens primacie conſiſteth not in commanding▪ but in obeying. Alas, this excellence is not in the degree, but in ſuch behauiour as makes them

woorthy therof: yet they will approue that good in themſelues, which they thinke bad and condemne in women, as if vice and vertue were limitted by their deſſeignes, and as though by their maner of life and demeanor, they were no way ſubiect eyther to one or other. Wherin they declare, how much they diſſent from nature, who neuer ordayned to the ſubiect where ſhe appointed moouing, but what was apt &amp; conuenient for it, or elſe ſuch reſt as ſhuld not be vnprofitable, like a faithfull Oeconomie of graces, and mother of all Hierarchie. Nay more, theſe prophane men would binde the feminine ſexe to ſuch laws as themſelues are not able to obſerue, lawes drawne from their own iealoſie, their ſuſpition, their weaknes, their auarice, their depraued conſciēce, their pride, thinking it good to prohibite others, ſuch things as thē
               ſelues could neuer effect: wherin they haue regarde to their owne perticuler imperfection▪ &amp; not the law of nature:

who meaſures the conſtrainte of her will; her will by the inclination; her inclination by that which is moſt proper; and the moſt propper by that which is moſt common, and moſt neceſſarie for the conſeruation of her kinde.
            Let vs now ſpeake of Liberalitie, which is as worthy noting in her own ſubiect, as anye other vertue in the worlde beſide, ſo royall and ſeemely is ſhee in all faire mindes whatſoeuer. More familiar is ſhee with women, then men, for they are naturally full of pittie, mercie and diuineſt charitie. They vſe continually to viſite Hoſpitalles, Priſons, and other places of wants, to giue aſſiſtance to the miſeries of men, who fill the ayre with their wretched lamentations: yea, thoſe places that commonly haue beene infected with theyr bad ſauour, women haue not ſpared to make theyr vſuall acceſſe vnto. Mauſolus monument, builded by a Woman in

remembrance of her husband, is a matter of ſuch eſpeciall eſtimation, as the very richeſt Sepultures of Kinges doe thence deriue their names, as from the fountaine of all honour and excellence.
            
               Sarteſhkia wife to Arphaxed, gaue inſtruction for building the proude and incomparable walles of Elchatana, as you may at large read in Memnon of Epheſus. Pariſatis Queene of Perſia, cauſed all the Monarches of Aſia to be buried in pure golde, and inſtituted a ſacrafice to Cyrus, the expence whereof amounted yeerely to a thouſand Affricke tallentes, according to the report of Dioniſius Mileſianus.
            
            
               Olympias, mother to Alexander, employed ſeauen hundred thouſand crownes, in erecting an Alter to Iupiter Hammon, vpon the coaſt of Accium. Cleopatra redeemed fiue thouſand Romaines, for two millions of golde and thirty crownes, which ſhee

                  〈2 pages missing〉
               
               
in a perpetuall Aprill of theyr tyme.
            
               Diana gaue chaſtity, diligence, and honeſt care of houſholde affayres. So that but for the liberality of theſe before named: the Gods had had no Altars, and men had bin depriued of all vnderſtanding.
            
               Iuno placed Hercules among the Gods number: Pallas Vliſſes, Ʋenus Aeneas, Thetis Achilles, Diana Hippolitus, Veſta Romulus, Iſis Pompilius, Calipſo was ſo liberall, notwithſtanding the ingratitude of Vliſſes: as ſhe would haue made him immortall, which he refuſed, through a baſe deſire, of ſeeing once againe the chymneys ſmoke of Ithaca or Caſſina, which cauſed Sapho to cry out in this ſort.
            
               Men through fooliſh malice led,
               Eſteeme baſe vice in vertues ſteed,
               And doe conceipt iniquity,
               In their raſh braines a Diety.
               To women they obliged be,
               For ſhielding them from infamy,
               
                  Becauſe they make them gracious,
               And change their Fortunes ominous,
               By perfection of their kinde,
               To beſt good haps that they can finde.
            
            
               Plato in like manner affirmeth, that womens ſociety hath made ciuill the moſte outragious condition of mens liues: yea, ſuch as naturally haue been barbarous, and enemies to their owne kinde: as Caine was to his brother Abell: one of Noahs ſonnes to his owne Father: Abſolom to Dauid, and many others beſide in the Holy Scripture.
            Amongſt the prophane they haue ſo exceeded, as there is not nowe ſo many women liuing, as we can number men reclaymed, onely by the diſcreete counſell of theyr company, and brought into the perfect path of wiſedome: ſo eſpecially it pleaſed Heauen to beſtow theſe graces, vpon this ſexe ſo diuine and bountifull in all vertues: as my vttermoſt praiſes comes farre too ſhort of theyr exceeding merits.
            
               
               Empedocles, that great ſearcher and friend to nature, was wont to ſay: that woman was her meere renewed Image, and her very leaſt conſideration in the ſubiect of thinges naturall, extended it ſelfe much more neere to truth, then the deepeſt ſearch or curioſitie of man could reach vnto. The Aegiptian Hieroglificques figured the Heauens by a woman, hauing her eyes couered, and laden with many mountaines on her backe: meaning heereby, that thoſe diuine creatures ſaw all thinges, euen they which were to come, as them preſent, and withall, ſupported the miſdeedes of men with a forgetfull remiſſion; ſignifyed by the burdens ſo farre from theyr regard, as al mens defects whatſoeuer, were caſt behinde theyr backes.
            It nowe remaines for mee to ſhewe, howe Hiſtoryes doe abound with examples of men prodigiouſly

rich, as Dauid himſelfe witneſſeth in this verſe: Men are ſo vnſatiable, as they thinke themſelues poore, euen when they poſſeſſe riches in greateſt aboundance.
            
            Holy writ lets vs ſee in this apparell, the wealthy Naball: whoſe extreame auarice was approoued by the ſecond King of Iſraell, euen with the perrill of his life almoſt.
            It ſhewes vs Achab likewiſe, taking away the goodes of Naboth: And in the newe Teſtament, we may look vpon Simon Magus.
            
            In prophane ſtories, wee behold Midas, Croeſus, Septimilius, Dioniſius, Chriſophilus, Tantalus, Lycaon.
            
            
               Jugurth cryed out (as Saluſt recordeth) that the Empire of Rome beeing to bee ſolde: Fortune too much iniured him; in letting him knowe it, and not admytting him the meanes to compaſſe the wonderfull riches which belonged to

the Primates of the Romain common wealth.
            
               Virgill, and (before him) Appolonius and Cteſias, depainted to vs Polimneſtor of Thrace, a man ſo carried away with auarice, as he violated al the rights of hoſpitality, and wickedly murdered Polidore, ſon to King Priam his neighbour.
            I might haue a world of worke, if I ſhould heere ſet downe the Geraudes of Thylos, who ſolde theyr Siſter to the Lappyans: Joſephs bretheren, who offended in like ſort: the King of Perſia, that cauſed the tombe of Cyrus to be opened, within which this inſcription was to be read.
            
               Thou man inſatiate, couetous,
               Cruell, vnkinde and barbarous,
               This Tombe by thee had not been ope,
               But that thy couetous extreame,
               Heere to haue found a Diademe,
               Gaue thy thoughts that greedy ſcope.
               Thy comming I right well did know,
               For heauen did the ſame fore-ſhew,
               And thy fruitleſſe hope beſide:
               
                  Heere get'ſt thou nothing for thy paine,
               But this poore carkaſſe fraile and vaine,
               To ſpeedy death thy preſent guide.
            
            I haue made mention ſufficient of womens liberality, as alſo the auaritious nature of men: it is now high time, that by humility (wherewith they are much more endued then men theyr aduerſaries:) I ſhould cleuate them them ſo high, as the heauens may bee diſcerned vnder them, and that they ſerue to addorne heauen as vertues, or rather, that all vertues are (as it were) their ſeruants,
            
               Triſmegiſtus the Prince of auncient Theologie, names humility to be the guide of the ſoule, and onely regent of all our actions.
            It is ſhe that moderates violence, and yet is violent vpon immodeſty, compelling it to an abatement of ſuch heate, as many times makes itſelfe too much acquainted with men, which very quickly carries them from a perſwaſiue

kinde of pride, to incredible forgetfulnes of themſelues.
            The holy Bible offers the examples of Sara, Heſter; and beyond all other, the new Teſtament (which is the perfection of witneſſe to the Prophets) deliuers vs the humility of the Saint aboue all Saintes, the bleſſed Virgin Marie, ſo humble both in apparaunce and effect, as it pleaſed God to make choyſe of her, for the birth of his onely Sonne our Lord Chriſt Ieſus.
            Contrariwiſe, yee cannot but read of the ambition of Caine, of Nimrod, Cirus, Abſolon, Haman, Rehoboam, and many others beſides.
            In hiſtories likewiſe ye ſhall finde the preſumption of Alexander, naming himſelfe the Sonne of Iupiter: of Pirrhus the Epirote: of Menecrates, who called himſelfe a God: of Caliphanes, Xerxes, Romulus, Caligula, Caeſar, Senecion, Patricius, and Marke Anthonie.
            
            
               Amongſt our moderne men, of Borgi
                  
                     •
                  , Leo, Boniface, Caraffa, Baldwin the impoſture, and ſo many more beſide: as I my ſelfe ſhould ſeeme ambitious of a very vaine matter, if I would make recitall of them; producing withall, what is ſaid of Hanniball, of Nicanor, of Salmoneus, of the Aloides, Prometheus: Icarus, Tiphon, Phaeton, the Giants in generall, and in breefe, a whole bedrole of the like: but eſpecially ſuch as S
                     •
                  eſichorus ſpeakes of in his Odes.

                  Mad men who in their proper praiſe,
                  Will crowne themſelues with laurell bayes,
                  While other ſeeke effectually,
                  Into the bottom of the graue.
                  For that whereby they honor haue,
                  And thereby liue in memory.
               
And Muſaeus in his ſongs.
            
               Thoſe that were of Lesbos Iſle,
               Gaue themſelues an honourd ſtile.
               Which was indeed but villiany,
               Like to an aged Rauens noate,
               
                  Into ſome withred Elme being got,
               To tell the world her hermony,
               The Sea they doe reſemble well,
               Which ſinckes as if it were to hell.
               Though to the cloudes it oft ariſe,
               Or like the Sea-man, that would breake,
               A huge rocke with his Oares too weake,
               When fond conceite thus dimmes his eyes.
            
            Where can be read a matter more inſupportable, then the inſolence of Caine, who anſwered his Lord and creator: Haſt thou giuen Abell my brother to my cuſtody; or am I to yeelde account of him?
            
            Contrariwiſe, where can be heard of a more humble creature, then the Cananite, who hauing not offended at all, held her ſelfe not onely faulty in the fact of her religion: but comparing her ſelfe to the bruite beaſtes, combated againſt the rigour of Ieſus Diſciples, and that with ſuch mighty modeſty, as had not the holy Scripture expreſſely reported it, it would haue exceeded beleefe: yea, all

hiſtories els in the world beſide. Mary Magdaleins humility cannot be equalled in compariſon, by the very humbleſt ſubmiſſion of men ingenerall or perticuler, wyping our Sauiours feete with the hayre of her head, being as then but ſcantly knowen vnto her.
            But if yee will commend the inſolence of a man, it is to be noted at that very inſtant, when one cryed out: What loſſe commits this Woman at this preſent? Such odours might haue been ſold at a very good rate, and afterward beſtowed vpon the poore.
            But let vs leaue diuine authorityes, and looke into hiſtories, Hippolita the Amazone was ſo humble and lowly to Theſeus, that he hauing receiued a hurt with the Bulles horne of Praxila on his right ſhoulder: ſhe vſed often times to lick the wound with her tongue; whereas euen Chiron the Centaure grewe offended.
            
               
               This is not thy chiefeſt glory,
               Nor thy Fortunes faireſt ſtory,
               Oh Theſeus, to haue conquered,
               The mighty Bull of Praxila,
               Whoſe wounding thee that very day,
               Might full well haue done thee dead,
               But to haue faire Hippolita,
               
               So worthy noting euery way,
               In thy houſe to waite on thee,
               And deſtinies to grace her ſo,
               When elſe thy life thou muſt forgoe,
               Then ſhe to giue thee remedy.
            
            As goodneſſe, honeſty and vertue, are onely principall among the perfections of the minde, ſo in that only ſubiecte woulde I conclude heere my diſcourſe: but that I cannot well doe it, vnleſſe thereby I giue men to vnderſtand, that whatſoeuer goodneſſe abideth in them, is only but borrowed, and the very maine goodneſſe of the whole world conſiſteth in women, who (to ſpeake no more then truth) are as a ſoule to the whole vniuerſſe, and the eſpeciall procurers of all celeſtiall bleſſings.
            
               The Romaines amongſt all their conqueſtes, made an intermingling of ſtrange Goddes, and cauſed Altars to be erected vnto them, yet notwithſtanding, in the deſpoyle of ſo many nations, they could neuer get any one God that bare the tytle of good, ſo rare was this qualitye amongſt them which were figured in the ſhapes of men. And yet in the very cradle of their Empire, they had a Goddeſſe of goodnes, named Veſta, ſo highly eternized for her deſerts, as at one time ſhe was honored with ſeauen hundred crowns of pure golde, and neuer could men haue the credite to enter her Temple▪ 
               Ennius the Poet renowneth her in this manner.
            
               
                  Veſta (good Goddeſſe) is ſole guardiane,
               Of our great Capitole, and people Romaine,
               All other Gods are feeble in their might,
               But ſhe and Pallas, who giues wiſedomes ſight.
            
            The goodneſſe of Juno is noted of euery one, and farre to exceede the mallice of Iupiter, for though ſhee

had good cauſe to procure his ouerthrowe, for being ſo long time tyed by the heeles to one Mil-ſtone, agaynſt all lawes of equity and reaſon: yet did ſhe not forbeare to diſcouer to him, the ſecret traines laide for him by the other Gods, who were growen weary of his tyranie and oppreſſion; which made the Greeke thus to ſpeake of her.
            
               
                  Iuno, the goodnes ouer rare,
               Made thee too kinde and debounaire,
               To thy vngratefull husband ſtill,
               When faſtned to his clog too long,
               He vext the Gods, and did thee wrong,
               Yet didſt thou alwaies ſhield his ill.
            
            The goodneſſe of Sirua of Corinthe, was exceſſiue, if exceſſe be to be found in ſuch a vertue, for being forſaken by her husband, a man beyond all meaſure diſſolute, &amp; wiſely learning how he ſpent his time: to wit, in the ſtewes which was the moſte infamous in all Greece, where hee had vtterly waſted

and conſumed himſelfe: She yet appointed him an annuall penſion, that hauing wherewithall to diffray his charges, he might in time learne to leaue that wicked kinde of life.
            
               Plutarch makes mention of a Courtezane ſo kinde and affable, that ſhee gaue a golden Crowne of maruailous valew, the very ſum of all her riches conſiſting therein: to a young man, who had refuſed her for another, to whome he gaue the very ſame crown, with the will and conſent of her, who had bin his before firſt Miſtreſſe &amp; louer. Oh worthy courtezane, the hiſtory doth thee wronge in giuing thee that name, for by this one deed thou haſt rayſed ſo many vertuous opinions of thee, and ſet downe ſuch a memory of thy woorth: as they that ſhall defame thee, will be but infamous, thoſe that accuſe thee, but ſnarling detractours, and he that refuſed thee, well worthy the name of a wretch and vnthankfull.
            
               Who can but maruaile at the goodneſſe of Proſerpine, ſhe hauing beene ſtolne from the Theater of men: yea, from her mothers lap, the terreſtriall Paradiſe of her contentment, and hurried into a place of darkeneſſe, horrour and diſpayre, by a Tyrant, more couetous of her beauty, then matrymoniall coniunction: did neuertheleſſe make Jupiters intent knowen to Pluto, to the heauens great ſcandale, and perpetuall prayſe of the nether regions, where ſhe was confined, to preuent a ſecond ſubuerſſion of the world, which would haue enſued vpon her rape againe, as witneſſeth that which Pluto himſelfe ſaid.
            
               Ere the loud thunder make me let her goe,
               Ile burne the heauens, ſo doth her beauty moue,
               Deare care to keep a Iewell gotten ſo,
               Deſpight my brothers force, ſhe is my loue,
               And ſooner ſhall the Sunnes bright golden torch,
               Be ſaffrond in theſe dim and nether nookes,
               
                  Ire ſhe be carried foorth of Plutoes portch,
               That giues me life and eſſence by her lookes.
            
            
               Empedocles, Ariſtotle and Plinie haue affirmed, that the beſt kinde of beaſtes are thoſe which moſte vſe to weepe: if it be ſo, there is nothing more facile in a woman then teares, nay, it is a thing ſo naturally giuen vnto them, as I haue noted many Ladyes, not to looſe one iotte of their perfection thereby, but rather to increaſe it much more by theyr teares, as eſpecially proceeding from a ſpring or ſourſe of grace; howe ſtrange then is the ſauage nature of men, who neuer weepe but onely through chollor? But Al
                     •
                  meon yeeldes the reaſon therof, in this manner.
            
               A woman being of her ſelfe more apprehenſiue then man, cannot eaſily alter from her firſt conception, which makes her ſooner to weepe then a man, who takes lōger time in ſeeking remedy for his grief.
            
            
               
               But this is moſt certaine, teares only proceed from an exceeding good nature, and all thoſe beaſtes (moſt capable of enſtruction) are ſubiect thereto.
            
            Lyons, Beares and Tygers neuer weepe, ſaith Auerroes, becauſe rage is ſo familier with them, as they cannot bee taught to ſhunne theyr owne harmes. But horſes and Elephantes vſe to weepe, as ſome men doe, not ſo much for their natural humiditie, as a certayne feeling of inward ſadnes, for the Hart (altogether hot) weepes oftentimes, being purſued and taynted: and after this manner is the weeping of men: but beyond all, the woman is ſubiect to teares, eſpecially ſhe, in whome moſte ſweetneſſe and tendernes is found. It ſeemes the Comick Menander knew ſomewhat in this caſe, when he ſaid.
            
               For women do weep, for harmes may them befal,
               Mean while their barbarous husbands ſit &amp; ioy
               Neuer fore thinking on their illes at all,
               
                  When deſperate hazard of moſt ſharp annoy,
               With hurly burly through the Citty flies,
               Deſpoilde and widdowed of her liberties,
               This fooliſh courage women doe deſpiſe,
               And by their teares expreſſe themſelues more wiſe.
            
            
               Andromache the wife of Hector, was endued with ſuch goodnes, as her ſeruantes were in her houſe as in a Temple: yea, ſhee tooke care and paines for managing her husbandes horſes, he himſelfe neuer hauing ſo much courage, as ſhe had vertues. I may referre thee for further proofe heereof, to Homere where the Lackies of Paris tearmes her a Pithagorician for this cauſe.
            It is ſtrange to heare how ſome bawle againſt this text, for they talke of Metempſichoſis, which we call tranſauimation, the paſſage of ſoules from one body to another: and then will not ſticke withall to ſweare, that the Authour heereby meaneth ſome deceipt: but heerein they reſemble little chyldren, who imagine belles to

ſound all that they ſing.
            
               Iulia Cenſorina hauing heard, that ſentence of death was pronounced againſt her husband, diſguiſed him ſo ſodainely, as the Iaylor imagined him to be her, ſo ſhe remained priſoner in his habite, while he eſcaped with ſafety of life.
            They threatned her with torments to reueale where he was: but ſhe replyed, neuer make ſpare of mee, for I haue done no more then a woman ought to doe.
            There is no true hiſtorian, that euer did ſet downe like example of a man. I knowe very well that ſome will obiecte vnto mee, howe Diuine Orpheus deſcended into hell, there to demaund his fayre wife of Pluto: but if hee did ſo, it was more becauſe hee coulde not liue without her, then for any eſpeciall goodneſſe remaining in himſelfe, conſidering hee was a perpetuall enemy to women.
            
               Likewiſe hee behaued himſelfe ſo ill, if Aeſchilus ſay true.
            
               As he encurd the high diſgrace,
               Of all the beauteous dames of Thrace▪
               
               And being thus diſhonoured,
               Loſt firſt his harpe and then his head▪
               
            
            I would not aduiſe men to ſhed any teares for him, becauſe happily they haue too few for themſelues. The generall hiſtorie of nations tells vs, that an infinite number of good women vowed themſelues to their husbands graues, as not deſiring any longer life after them.
            Wiſe Salomon, hath figured forth a good woman to vs, and though ſhe come ſhort of many eſpeciall qualities due to ſuch perfection: yet hath hee deſcribed in her more excellent matters, then can bee in a man, whom he eſteemeth not capable of any praiſe. For ſaith he: A good woman is an ineſtimable treaſure.
            
            
               In this Song of Songs, he ſings nothing els then of the vertuous woman.
            
               Plato held, that ſhee is no leſſe to bee deſired in a familye, then a iuſt Magiſtrate in a common wealth: this made them paynt 
                  Ʋenus ſtanding on a Tortuſe, to ſhew, that a woman ought neceſſarilye to keepe at home. Poſsidonius nameth a woman, the eye of neceſſity, meaning thereby, that her fore-ſight being as a Sun of grace, a houſe is waſte and deſolate without her beames, and men can neuer clearely ſee into their houſhold affayres, but onely by the warie eye of theyr wiues.
            There is ſuch ſuperaboundaunce of goodneſſe in women, as wee may grieue to ſee them deceiued by the bolde mallice of men, who make no reckoning at all of theyr treaſons and treacheries: for, while they weep like Crocadiles, they will ſweare by Heauen and Earth, that theyr

affections are loyall, their words faithfull, their behaui
                  ••
                
               
                  〈…〉
                yet for all this, in 
                  〈…〉
               , they are 
                  〈…〉
                the Hiena, 
               
                  〈…〉
                
               
                  ••
               en vipers▪ more inconſtant men the Polipe fiſh, more 
                  〈◊〉
                men Tigers, and leſſe worthie loue then Hornets. Ariſtophanes ſhall take my part, although he was an Athenian, to wit, gadding minded and vncertaine, lyke many other of his companions.
            
               To ſeduce faire women kinde,
               Pretending loyaltie of minde,
               And yet not loue but for a while:
               Or elſe for baſe deſire of gaine,
               A greefe that many may complaine,
               When plaine apparance ſhewes the guyle▪
               
               It is a most vnwoorthy parte,
               Farre different from the high deſert▪
               
               That to women dooth belong,
               Who being debounaire and milde,
               Neuer thinke men to be ſo vilde
               As to requite them with ſuch wrong.
            
            If yee will haue ſome of this good

ſtuffe out of mens ſtorehouſe, looke then on deteſtable and vngratefull Theſeus, on Paris the lyer and periurde wretch, on inconſtant Hercules, and diſloyall Iaſon, who all moſt falſelye deceiued their friends, after they had triumphed by their meanes and credit, I will not ſay on their honors: for theſe men (none woorſe that euer were) could not any way wound the happie and laudable reputation, of theſe their faire foſterers and deareſt friends, which made them (indeed) more enemyes to themſelues, then they could be to the renowne of theſe Ladyes, whoſe vertues may perhaps bee toucht with ſome ſlaunder, but their innocent natures ſtand free from iniurie, and their good cariage from all baſe ſuſpition. Yet let vs conſider heerewithall, that a woman can haue no greater enemy then a man, who is like vnto a rauenous Lyon, continuallye ſeeking to deuoure new ſpoyle. Oh ſexe abhominable, thou art too

much affected to thy ſelfe, to knowe rightly indeede howe to vſe women kinde, eſpecially in theſe dayes, wherein, as ſaith the Italian Poet.
            
               Th'abortiues of this cittie in a flame,
               Do at their countries woes but make a game.
            
            And an other:

                  A Coridon, a Coridon gapes after gaine,
                  And nothing pleaſeth him but womens paine.
               
            
            Not many moneths ſince, a Gaſcoigne Gentleman became amorous of a young and vertuous maiden, and raiſde vp ſuch a ſcandale to mens reputation, who ſpare not to fault in the lyke offence: as enforceth mee to ſet downe the hiſtorie, not ſo much to make them the more infamous, as to make knowne the iuſt vengeance, which this honeſt Virgin tooke on the ingratitude of her feygned and diſſembling friend.
            
               He, after a million of purſuites, fild full of ſeruices, complaines, teares and promiſes, yet not able to compaſſe his vnlawfull deſires: forgot him ſelfe ſo farre, as to publiſh abroade with no ſillie proteſtations, that hee was not meanely intereſted into the Maidens beſt fauours. She hauing no other ſupporte for her innocencie, then the true witneſſe of her ſoule, vnattainted and free from ſo vile an infamie; raiſde vp her ſpirits with ſuch rightfull diſdaine, againſt the vniuſt rauiſher of her reputation, as ſhe ſpared not to kill him in the middeſt of a verye honourable aſſembly, where ſhe waited long for the effecting of ſuch a woorthy enterpriſe, which (vnder correction of better iudgement) in my minde deſerued rather pardon and recompence, then any ill reproche, ſcandale or puniſhment. For

                  Pacience importun'de dooth conuert to hate,
                  And who ſo quitteth not an offered blame:
                  Waites but a ſecond blemiſh of his name.
               
            
            
               Neuertheleſſe, in the Parlement at Burdeaux, ſhee was condemned to looſe her head, men did ſo earneſtlye purſue the cauſe. But after their rigour became ſomewhat more moderate, ſhee was confyned vnto perpetuall priſon, wherout I would very willinglie deliuer her, if I could conuert my ſelfe into a ſhower of golde, as ſometime did the Sonne of Saturne.
            
            
               If Loue deny to open me the gate,
               By other meanes I will get in thereat:
               Her guardians crueltie I meane to bend,
               Euen by thoſe beautious lookes which her defend
               That way to make them mylde and debonaire.
               No more to fright me from ſo ſweete a faire.
               Then on the houſe Ile raine a ſhower of golde,
               To glut their eyes, while Loue makes mee more bolde.
            
            When Juno would haue borrowed a fauour of Aeolus, ſhee eſteemed no recompence woorthy of ſuch grace, but the offer of one of her Nimphes: where to the God ſo well lent his eare, as he effected that, which before hee would by no means yeeld to promiſe.

                  〈2 pages missing〉
               
               
will not admit thee to mollifie theyr furies, witneſſe that which Linus ſaith.
            
               Men of their furie would be much aſhamde,
               And their behauiour mightily be blamde,
               Did they but ſee the wood Nimphes golden life,
               So ſweete, ſo pleaſing, and ſo voide of ſtrife.
            
            
               Pharaohs daughter had more goodneſſe in her, then all the Egiptians beſide could be ſtoard with malice, ſhee was more kinde and affable, then her father was rigorous, let mee not ſaye cruell: for that great Captaine and lawe deliuerer Moyſes, did ſhee ſaue from ſhipwrack, yea the gulfe of death, auouching him for her owne ſonne in a time moſt dangerous, ſo that it may (vnder reuerence) be ſaid, it pleaſed God to make her doo him ſeruice, as well as Moyſes in ſuch a neede, and all for the deliuerance of his people.
            
               Heredotus the father of hiſtories, (be it ſpoake in no diſpraiſe to Plutarch,) makes rehearſall of a Spartane woman, who let ſcape a priſoner from her

houſe, that had in earneſt ſmitten her: and becauſe her husband ſhould not kill him for it, ſhe ſaued his life, by ſending him to Thebes. Yee ſhall hardlie finde the like qualitie in men, by nature addicted to crueltie, and more enclined to offend their friends, then pardon any that haue doone them iniurie.
            
               Homer maketh mention of Pallas, who quallified the rage of the fierie God of warre, that but for her would haue made a generall deſtruction, when he vnderſtood the death of his ſonne. The fugitiue Aeneas, might long enough haue wanted humaine ſuccour, yea, lyfe and all had vtterlye miſcaryed: if (as a helpe vnexpected) hee had not happened to the good Queene Dydo, where he found a bleſſed hauen after ſo many miſhaps, and much better was entertained then his baſe trecherie deſerued. Thraſilla ſaued Phorybus, who ſcaled her houſe to rob her treaſurie, and as the neighbours

would haue ſlaine him, ſhe ſaid: Let him alone, he is but a foole, and hath doone no harme but to my windowe nayles. Herſilia ſeeing Melanthus in the Temple at Delphos, and that hee would haue ſtolne a Crowne thence, which Perſeus had cauſed there to bee ſacred: excuſed him to the Preeſtes, who had likewiſe perceiued him, telling them, that he was a Goldſmith of Athens, and her husbands hoſte, who came not thither with any ill intent, but onlye had a curious deſire after workemanſhipe, which ſhe allwayes had knowne him addicted vnto. All the frenche had miſcaried at the Scicilian Veſpres, except ſuch as ſaued themſelues in Sperlinga: but that they were aduertiſed by a Nurſſe, who ſerued the Podeſta of the Ile, whereon was written:

                  
                     Sperlinga only ſhall not burne,
                  Elſe all the Iſle to hauocke turne.
               
            
            And elſe where.
            
               
               A pittying Nurſe did many French preſerue,
               That in Sperlinga ſundry monthes did ſerue.
            
            When the Thebanes recouered their libertie from them of Sparta, and that the tirannie of Charondas was vtterly extinguiſhed: the women of Thebes preuayled ſo well with the two Captaines Pelopidas and Epaminondas, iuſtly diſpleaſed againſt them of Lacedemon; as there were but very few put to the ſwoord, albeit they had beene ſo iniuriouſlye handled, as the remembraunce thereof could not but bee irkeſome to them, and bloudy reuenge no more then lawfull. When Prometheus ſtole the fire from heauen, and Jupiter bound him to the mount Caucaſus, where a vulture glutted her ſelfe continually on his entrayles: the Goddeſſe Iris rayned downe a ſhower of Nectar on this ouer-hardy mans breſt, till Hercules at length became his deliuerer by Iunos
               
appointment, who grew into pittie of his hard extremitie, notwithſtanding at one inſtant he had committed two mightie offences: the one by his great ingratitude to Jupiter, the other by his execrable theft, according to that which Aeſchilus ſaith.
            
               None more ingracefull then Prometheus was,
               Who from the high and vaulty houſe of heauen:
               Stole holy fire, and thence away would paſſe,
               Hauing had gentle entertainement giuen,
               By all the greatest Gods in ſeemely ſorte,
               Yea, Iupiter receiu'd him in his Courte.
            
            
               Theoderita, the wife to John Paleologus, ſeeing that her husband would needes haue fiue ſlaues hanged for a ſmall offence, and that ſhee durſt not beg theyr liues, becauſe he was ſo furious: gaue a ſumme of money to a Countie their keeper, who fled awaye with them, and were afterward neuer heard of. On the daye of Saint Bartholmew (when the French ſhew themſelues the moſt barbarous that can be

imagined) there was a good and hardie woman, neere to whom a man had withdrawne himſelfe, as if it had been to a ſanctuarie of aſſurance, from the rage of thoſe bruite beaſts who forciblie followed him: ſhe caught a dizeuier by the coller, and would not let him goe, albeit ſhee were halde and puld by the garments, vntill ſhe iudged the man purſued to bee in ſound ſafetie, as indeed by her means it came ſo to paſſe. If ſuch a notable deede might not too much diſpleaſe the conditions of men, eſpeciallye the French executioners of their owne fellow Cittizens: I would bring ſuch a rancke (among them that I could name) as ſtrange hiſtories ſhould haue cauſe to complaine, that their ſubiects giue them not leaue once to rehearſe matter ſo memorable.
            
               Sophronia returning from Church, and ſeeing two young men come led as priſoners, laden with garments which they had ſtolne from her houſe,

when ſhee was tolde by the officers, they had robde her of all, and left iuſt nothing, ſhee anſwered: That what they had doone, was by her own conſent, and they tooke theſe things but as a pledge of a certaine ſumme of money, which in her neceſſitie ſhe had borrowed of them, and ſo they had no other puniſhment then feare onely.
            Hee that would take vppon him to number the ſtarres, ſhould not finde himſelfe ſo confounded by their infinitie in his ſight: as I am dazeled with multiplicitie of matter, deliuered only vppon this ſubiect, which going beyond admiration, aſtoniſheth my ſences, rauiſheth my ſpirits, wearies my hand, and by wearineſſe diſpoſſeſſeth mee of all hope, to get out of this boundleſſe Oceane: but that the verie goodneſſe it ſelfe of this matter I handle, ſupplyes my defects, as contented with a little in ſo vnable a perſon.
            I haue ſaide ſufficient, concerning

the happy qualities of women, which (to ſpeake truely) triumpheth ouer men in all cheefe glory of perfections, that can be affoorded by heauen and nature, who ordinarily makes her ſelfe more admired in the feminine ſexe, then any ſubiect elſe whatſoeuer: neuertheleſſe, me thinkes I am iuſtly to condemne my ſelfe in all I haue done, becauſe it hath not caried the weightie ſtile it deſerueth; much more then am I to be affraide, if I ſhould dare to make entrance among theyr diuine graces, the celeſtiall forme of theyr Angelicall beauties, with what ſpirit I ſhould proceed in ſo high an employment.
            
               Apelles that skilfull and abſolute Painter, when hee ſhould figure the graces of 
                  Ʋenus, found him ſelfe to bee in ſuch a ſtraunge confuſion, as hee was compelled to crye out: That hee was the onely enemie to his fame and credit, that did ſet him about ſuch a difficult matter. I referre

it to your iudgements, ſeeing Thimantes could not portraite Agamemnons teares, for the ſacrifiſing of his onely daughter: whether it be poſſible or no, to deſcribe the moſt ſweet attractions of a young Lady, who in one inſtant can cauſe both life and death, not onely in men of homely mettall, but euen the very reſoluteſt perſon in the worlde, you may beholde (without any arte to helpe) a hayrie tufte, daintily floating vppon a front largely extended, where two eyes (or rather two Sunnes) make reſplendaunce with ſuch a temperate fire: as our ſences forget their condition, our ſpirits their iudgment, our hearts their freedome, and our ſoules all conceit, as caryed away with intire conſideration of ſo many meruailes. Neapolitane Sanazar aptlie diſcourſeth thereon.
            
               Beautie to the Lillie like,
               Pleaſeth with her daintie white:
               Plaited into radiant curlles,
               Which about ſweete liking hurlles▪
               
               By ſo rare and pleaſing couller,
               
                  Raiſing vp a ſecond honor,
               Beautie like the waters fall,
               Running with a gentle braule.
               In a chanell ſiluer hewde,
               All the hearbes enammeled,
               As it dooth her treſſes ſpred,
               By the ſtanders by are viewd.
               It is louely, like the Roſe,
               That in mornings dooth vncloſe,
               When faire heauen hath diſtilde,
               On Auroraes cradle bed,
               Which the Gangian worſhipped,
               Her pearled drops through the f
                     •
                  eld.
            
            I can hardly thinke, that men ſhould bee ſo miſgouerned, as to preſume to haue any grace aboue that of women▪ ſeeing at all times by this fayre ornament of nature (which I dare call the cheefeſt gift of heauen) there hath beene ſuch woonders wrought thereby: as Tyrants haue beene made to forget theyr rigour; Iudges haue altered their ſettled determinations; ſterne people haue been pacified, and the very wiſeſt circumuented, as by a verye neceſſarie tranſportance of the minde.
            
               By this gracious endowment, fayre Heſter gaue concluſion to the Kings of Perſiaes cuſtome, conſtrayning Ahaſuerus to offer her his royall rod, as well when hee ſeemed to be moſt mooued with choller, as in the time of more pleaſing acceptance. By this means Juno, as Homer recordeth, knew how to lull a ſleepe her husband, for the Grecians aduantage, and ruine of the Troyans. Prince Menelaus iuſtly offended with Helen his wife, perceiued her accompanyed with ſo many graces, when ſhee came into his preſence with Diophoebus: as he durſt do nothing againſt ſo rare a beautie, but became euen then to be more amourous, then he was before on the day of his nuptials. The graces of Cleopatra, comming for tryall before Marke Anthonie: the Iudge himſelfe became ſollicitour.
            
               Auguſtus intending to deſtroy Alexandria; was put from his purpoſe by the very ſight of Therinda, beeing but

the daughter to a poore Shipmaiſter. Aelianus rehearſeth, that on the Sea coaſtes of Liguria, certaine marine monſters haue beene ſeene, bearing ſome ſhewe of humaine ſhape: that would ſtand gazing on the countrye damoſels, as they went for water to the neighbouring Fountaines. Lycoſthenes, and after him Boiſteau de Launay, declareth, that a Triton was ſo rauiſhed with the graces of a countrye mayde, as hee forſooke the Sea, and followed ſo farre after her, that hee was taken by the Village-dwellers, wherevpon hee dyed afterwarde with ſorrowe.
            That part of the bodye, where this gracious iewell receiueth moſt ſplendoure, is in the eye, the cheefe and principall piece of Natures woorkemanſhip.
            In lyke manner dooth Ariſtotle call it, the onely ornament of the bodye: it is the meſſenger of the Soule; and alſo it is the Paynter

of our affections, and the faithfull ſpeaker of all our deſires. Hence is it, that the eye of a woman is naturally ſo ſweete: that if all the ſalte in Pequay or Bronage might touch but one of the lids, it would immediatly conuert into the pureſt Suger. Homer and Pindarus had ſuch ſound knowledge of the eyes excellence, as for one word they ſtroue to giue diuers epithites, and by one body, to make conſideration of all womens perfections, ſo to be diſcerned as in a mirrour of Chriſtall.
            
               Alexander the Great, ſo well apprehended the eyes of the Emperour of Periſiaes daughters his enemie, as afterward hee would not ſo much as looke on them, fearing to looſe his liberty in the moſt happy priſon of the world: whervpon he marryed one of them, to the end that this legittimate alliance, might keepe him within the boundes of perpetuall modeſtie and charitie.
            
               
               Mahomet the ſecond, drewe ſuch admiration from the eye of an Armenian woman ſlaue, as (in fauour of her) he cauſed him to bee hanged vp that had taken her: which made her to complaine of his crueltie, albeit he requeſted not any thing preiudiciall to her honour. Selim, who was the very rudeſt enemie to Chriſtendome, hauing ſeene a young Damoſell in the kingdome of Boſleua named Iſina, became in ſuch ſort attached: as he ſwore neuer to take any reſt, till he had conquered the whole prouince, where a creature ſo rare and precious firſt receiued life. Neuer did he kiſſe but her eyes onely, and afterward married her to Horruccio Barbaroſſa, the father to the kings of Argire.
            
            But how now? may not I ſeeme fooliſh and indiſcreet (or rather vnwoorthye of any fauour) in preſuming to diſcourſe of things ſo little agreeing with my conceits, as that I dare bee ſeene in the glorious Theatre of ſo

faire reſplendance? Oh pardon me, fayre eyes, for I imagined, that the refexion of ſo many graces as flowe from you, as from the ſource of glory and Maieſtie; would giue ſuch ornament to my woords, as elſe could not chooſe but want, and ſuch lyfe to my lines, as might make them immortall. It ſeemes that Martiall was of my minde.
            
               Your eyes, the Well-ſprings of faire light,
               That chaſeth hence the ſable night:
               Begetteth brightneſſe perfectlie,
               Where none (till then) had memorie.
            
            
               
                  Ʋigo hath written in his practiſe of medicine, that the eyes of a dead mayden are of ſuch vertue, againſt charmes and enchauntments, as if one but laye the apple of the eye vnder a Candleſtick of Braſſe; immediatlie all viſions and apparitions ſhall vaniſh away and not be ſeene. Many diſeaſes haue beene cured, by the very behoulding of Women that came to viſite the

parties. When the ayre and Sunne is obſcured from the Tartares, as it is a caſe that often befalles them: they teare foorth the eyes of ſome woman ſlaue, thereby to ouercome the firſt charme of darkeneſſe, &amp; ſo to haue the Sunne ſeene againe in theyr Horizon. It is very true, that they neuer vſe this but on great neceſſities, as when they ſeeke after gaine, or when they haue loſt ſome battaile: and thence forwarde is that ſlaue made free, and maintained at the charges of the common purſſe.
            The Perſians ſo mightily feared the graces hid in theyr womens eyes, as when any Lady or other ſhould come before their Iudges; they would turne their backes, and not looke vpon them.
            When Philocus was reproched by Demetrius, for his ouermuch follie in loouing Latmia; he anſwered him▪ If thou thy ſelfe hadſt but once behelde her eyes, thou wouldſt chide me, and

ſay, I loue her not ſufficiently. For this cauſe, the Italians will neuer ſuffer theyr wiues to go with their faces vncouered: ſo much they ſtand in feare, leaſt others ſhould loue them better then they themſelues doe. Wherfore, euen as the braine is the ſeate of the ſoule, and the throne of loue is placed in a womans eye: ſo may we call it the bright burning beacon, or rather the perfect load-ſtarre, to direct the way, in the Sea of our inconſtant hearts and cogitations. By this windowe did Mars become amorous of Venus, according to the teſtimonie of Ouid.
            
            
               
                  Mars ſaw her, and by ſight increaſt ſuch fire,
               As afterward gaue light to gaine deſire.
            
            Why then heereby I may conclude, that euen as the Sunne hath more light in his vnitie, then all the ſtarres in number haue together: ſo the very eye of a woman containes more

graces in it, then is to bee found or imagined. (I ſpeake vpon ſound knowledge) in all mens perfections which (to write vprightly) could neither bee gracious, curteous or ciuill, but onely by the ſociety of women. In this caſe I may likewiſe ſay, that as the Opall repreſents the colour of all precious ſtones: ſo a womans face, is the true liuely figure of all graces celeſtiall and humaine, and that God endued it only with perfections aboue all other creatures.
            The goodly heauens might not compare with the ornament and graces of a woman, if nature had not made thē of longer continuance: but by her death ſhe doth ſo much the more enrich their beauty▪ encreaſing their fairneſſe, in no meane meaſure, and yet to our vnſpeakeable loſſe. It is now high time I ſhould ſpeake of beauty, the faithfull companion of all thoſe graces which I place formoſt in the hyerarchy of things that ſeeme to be, or

are corporall, albeit the minde haue the greater part thereof.
            Bodily beauty is a continued proportion of the partes with their whole in perfect ſubſtance: This is the common definition of beauty, which only reſpectes the nature of the thing, and not the accidents. Plato holdes, that beauty is an Idea of perfection, which we attrybute to the ſubiect that beſt liketh vs.
            And hereupon, being demaunded what was the verie faireſt thing in the world: he anſwered, Loue. Now it is moſt certaine, that this Loue is a Woman; for as nothing can burne but the fire, or that which is of fiery nature: ſo can wee loue nothing but a woman, I meane in this Theater of humaine affaires, except we will build vp againe the walles of Sodom. Oh would to God it pleaſed him, that ſome two or three, who make a practiſe of ſuch a horrible ſin, yea, euen to the great ſcandale of Fraunce, had bin

but imployed in this buſines, (which eſpecially I vndertooke on ſo grieuous an occaſion:) the kingdome could not then but bee much more flouriſhing, and the wrath of God in leſſe meaſure follow vs. Well be it ſo then, that beauty onely appertaineth to a woman, according as Anacreon teſtifieth.
            
               Nature on Bulles did hornes beſtow,
               And tallents to the Birdes ſhe gaue,
               Hoofes to the horſe, and well we know
               Swiftnes to Hares their liues to ſaue.
               Fiſhes ſhe made glide through the ſtreame▪
               
               Teeth to the Lyon was her gift:
               But as for man, his hap extreame,
               Was to be witleſſe, voide of thrift.
               When woman came, then did ſhe ioy,
               And gaue ſuch beauty to her face:
               As worlds of hearts it ſhould deſtroy,
               And no power elſe haue greater grace▪
               
            
            Yet am not I of the vulgares opinion, who ſubiect beauty to ſome certaine rules, which cannot ſupport the faire in any ſubiect, without dooing iniurye to a Myllion of beautyes,

rare and extraordinary, who neuertheleſſe, haue manytimes none of thoſe curious notes of antiquity: for a little woman may be faire: a low forehead may be ſo too: a black hayrde woman, a mouth ſomewhat large, and other ſuch like parts, leſſe to be wondered at then Apelles Venus, in whome it was ſayd nothing to bee wanting. For

                  Beauty beſt we learne to know,
                  By lookes not ouer ſwift nor ſlow:
                  And when behauiour doth agree,
                  The body ſtraight, well ſhapt to ſee.
               
            
            But tell me, will not you iudge the woman to bee moſte fayre, that writte to her Louer in thys manner?
            
               My Loue, I am a little blacke,
               But ſay that I were much more blacke.
               Mine eyes browne, my face like browne,
               Admit my necke and breſts more browne,
               My haire and skin all black to be,
               Sauing my teeth of Iuory:
               Inuironed with a curroll fence,
               Which breaths more ſweet then frankinſence
               
                  That might delight both Gods and men,
               Much more thy ſelfe, what ſaist thou then?
               Muſt I for this my louely browne,
               Haue my Loue on me to frowne?
               Are not mine eyes as piercing ſtill,
               And able Marble hearts to kill?
               Or can my Loue be ere the leſſe,
               My minde being made of gentleneſſe?
               Why night is duskie, ſable blacke,
               Yet no beauti
                     •
                  us starres doe locke:
               When the Moone with ſiluer light,
               Gallops through the thicke fac'd night.
               
                  Venus doth loue nights browneſt howers,
               The darkeſt nookes are her ſafe bowers,
               Thickets and Forreſtes moſt obſcure.
               Yea, where no haunt hath been in vre,
               Thither doth ſhe moſt repayre,
               Sooner then to a garden faire.
               There may be ſeene the liuely ſparke,
               Thats beſt diſcerned in the darke:
               The ball that in a bright blacke eye,
               Shines like a Meteor in the skie.
               There browne and faire are both as one,
               When two ſweet ſoules are ſo alone:
               Tell me then (Loue) in ſuch a night,
               Wouldſt thou not thinke the browneſt white?
            
            In truth, it is not lawfull for any vpright iudgement to perſwade it ſelfe, that beauty hath any perticuler

colour, a proportion definite, or a grace imaginary: for nature (the ſoueraigne worke-miſtreſſe of all beauties, hath made an Ethiopian or Moore perfectly blacke, to be as faire as the whiteſt in our Europe. And the reaſon is, as Auicen affirmeth, becauſe ſhe would haue no monſter in nature, but the very thing that her ſelf ſhould abhor: for to ſee a dogge with ſixe feete, a calfe with two heades, a man of two natures, or a woman with two ſplenes: this is no monſtrouſnes, but rather an excellence of the firſt heate, whych would build vp many thinges in that moode, but often times ſets downe her reſt vpon one, and yet at ſome other time falles to plurality.
            Monſters then are framed of thinges diſſemblable to theyr kinde, and ſometimes in the imagination, or a depraued appetite, which euer more is contrary to nature. Empedocles ſaith thus thereof.
            
               
               The monſter takes originall,
               From ſeede of quite contrary kinde▪
               
               To that it ſhould agree withall,
               When it planting firſt did finde.
            
            I may well-ſay, with a million of our elders, that there is ſixe and thirty ſeuerall beauties in one woman, and hardly any one in a man: for he is the true anotomy of natures imperfection, yea, the very Image of her weakneſſe, as a woman may iuſtly tearme her ſelfe, the perfecte mirrour of her vertues: whereof Plutarch was not ignorant when he ſaid.
            
               If nature wiſh her ſelfe to ſee,
               A woman then her glaſſe may be.
            
            
               Propertius was of the ſame opinion.
            
               Is women not a miracle?
               Her voice a perfect oracle?
               Nay, is ſhe not a deity,
               By beauty of ſuch maieſty?
            
            
               Men being naturally compoſed of all corruption take no delight but in deſſimulation. The reaſon is, becauſe Loue and Venus withdrawing once from mens aſſembly, knowing the mallice which dayly frequented them: left them euen ſo to their fraudulent complexions, and gaue them the gift to be ſinguler in deceiuing. The report of Anacreon teſtifies as much.

                  Beholde the Dolphins how they play,
                  And on their ſiluer finnes conuey:
                  Loue and Venus naked both,
                  To ſhield them from the great vntroth
                  Of men moſt flattering and vntrue,
                  Let ſtill deceite falſe hearts purſue.
               
Although a woman were indued with any other perfection, then being beautifull, or admit ſhe had but this ornament only: yet that alone may exalt her aboue all men, who neither are faire, well fauoured or good, nor indeed (to ſpeake the truth) can they any way be capable of apprehending

theſe qualities, they are in ſuch plenty beſtowed vpon women. The holy ſcripture holds womanhood in ſuch account; as it teacheth vs, that nothing can ſooner put ſadneſſe from afflicted mindes, then the ſight of a good woman: euen as one ſhould ſay, for a celeſtiall remedy, becauſe a husband can indeede haue greater comfort in his cares, The Prophet Dauid, euen in the coldeſt winter of his age, hoped for ſuch conſolation by beautie, as he made choiſe thereof, and age indeed can haue no better coraſiue.
            
               Timeus, Sticillianus rehearſeth a maruailous hiſtorie, of a Shepheardeſſe of Affrica, who in the daies chiefeſt heate, caſting off her garmentes, that ſhee might bath in the riuer well ſhadowed from the Sunne: a Lyon comming that way, for the ſpace of three houres ſtood gazing vpon her, and ſeemed as ſurprized with exceeding contentment.
            The poore Virgin was in wonderfull

feare, and durſt not come to her cloathes, leaſt the Lyon ſhould deuour her: but growing to better courage in the end, hearing the noyſe of certaine Cammell driuers not farre off: betooke her ſelfe to flight, naked as ſhe was, not taking ſo much as her ſmocke with her; which the Lyon getting vp in his teeth, folowed withal, and laid it mildely at her feet, fetching afterward all her other garments, and then as making a ſigne of obeyſance, left her and returned among the woodes, to her no little ioy, finding ſuch ſeruice in ſo vnaccuſtomed a louer. Admetus wife was of ſuch admirable beauty, as the Swannes of Meander would leaue the riuer to follow her, and pearch many times vpon her ſhoulders. A matter very ſtrange, the like neuer hapning to any man whatſoeuer: as alſo the inconuenience of her death, onely for deliueraunce of her husband, hath more note of honour; piety and meritte, then all

the men in the world can brag of any vertue, in thoſe thinges which moſte may make for their aduantage. For ſhee ſacrificed her ſelfe willingly, to redeeme her hasbandes life, which leſſened euery day by mortall langour of an vlcer, that poured foorth more loathſome and filthy ſtench, then Augeus ſtable (clenſed by Hercules) could compare withall. All which notwithſtanding, he no ſooner ſlept, but ſhee ſuckt foorth the venome, paying the ranſome for him, who could not elſe liue, but by loſſe of her life.
            
               Cambles the Prince of Sardys, being one day drunke, would needes kill his houſholde ſeruants, and proceeding ſo farre in this rude determination, as hee had compaſſed the iſſue of his mercileſſe rage, eyther by fire, ſwoord, or ſome other meanes.
            But beautifull Soclea, being ſo faire as any woman poſſible could bee,

preſented her ſelfe before him, and ſweetly taking him by the hand, made him on a ſodaine become ſo tractable, and not onely he deſiſted from further aſſayling them, but forgot likewiſe that hee had beene in any ſuch fury, ſubmitting himſelf mildely and gently to her, both being thus recouered of his drunkennes and fury.
            Womens beauty then is aboue all elſe moſt maruellous: It is the excellencie of the Diuine workemanſhip, or rather the chiefeſt thing of his heauenly labour: It is the modell, not onely of thinges that beautifie the world, but the very eſpeciall of all formes: It is the table of rhe celeſtiall powers: the gadge of natures alliance with the world, and the onelie mirrour of perfect Ideaes: briefly, it is that which I cannot worthily enough admire, and therefore am the more vnable to deſcribe.
            The man that will enter but into conſideration thereof, ſhall in that one

book read all perfections whatſoeuer, and cenſuring of them by this little, or rather no part thereof at all: will vnfainedly confeſſe, that the body of a woman is a true Temple, and her ſoule the very image of God, or figure of his bleſſing.
            He will ſay, himſelfe is made but of ſlime and dung, whereas woman was formed of a matter otherwiſe prepared, finiſhed in a happy and wel ordered ſubſtance, with all qualities beſeeming a moſt perfect creation. Hee will like wiſe confeſſe, that woman was giuen him for his eternall good, and the houſe is not bleſſed where ſhe wanteth.
            By her is this huge maſſe ſubſiſted, cōmon weales made immortal, citties peopled, Realmes ſtrengthened, Kings aſſured, and ſubiects maintained. By her it is, that we liue againe in our children, poſterity haue knowledge of vs, and our memory is continued. It is by her, that we remember our houſes,

and reſpect our families. By her wee learne to growe heedfull, ſhe makes vs quick and ready, ſhe ripens our lawfull actions, and drawes vs from the world to liue in her company: as in a ſchoole of pietie, modeſtie, and iuſt apprehenſion of following accidents, wherein (elſe) we ſhould but little differ from bruite beaſts. It was ſhee that had her birthe in the terreſtriall Paradiſe, and not man. Laſt of all, ſhe is our meanes of comfort to God the Father, the cauſe of his bleſſings to vs in this life, and by her we are made ſure of all happineſſe in the life to come.
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            An other defence of womens vertues, written by an Honorable perſonage, of great reckoning in Fraunce, and therefore thought meete to be ioyned with the former diſcourſe.
            
               That a VVomans excellence is much greater then a mans.
            
            
               MAny things brought foorth by Nature, are oft times made but ſlender account of, through want of diligent knowledge, as alſo ſearche into the excellencie of them: which being a matter vulgare and common, caryeth the leſſe price and eſtimation with euery one.
            
               Omitting other circumſtances, whoſe number might grow well neer infinite, I find the rare and vnualuable vertues of women too much neglected, and their worth not lookt into as their merites iuſtly challenge: but though ſome (through ouermuch familiarity) haue bin bolder with them then beſeemed: yet let me thus farre ſtand in their defence, that whoſoeuer) with vnpartiall iudgement) will but ſee into their excellencies, ſhall finde them to be of no meane eſteem, but will giue them more right then hitherto they haue done.
            And me thinkes, their detractours ſayings are not receiueable, alleadging a bed role of faultes found in their ſexe; which yet (by their owne confeſſion) are not ſo marke-able as thoſe in men: for admitte they haue ſome fewe, and thoſe but pritty little ones, let men but lay their handes on theyr harts, ranſacke their muddy thoughts, and continuall bad cogitations, they

ſhall perceiue, that womens ſingularityes both in minde and body, do far out go whatſoeuer perfections in men; whom yet I will graunt to go beyond women in frailty. And to reſolue yee herein, I take my firſt proofe from the womans firſt forming, who was not made of any vncleane, loathſome or baſe matter, as the body of man was: but euen of his purity and moſt refined part, as may appeare by her face, repreſenting a very ſweet and gracious complexion, without any ougly haires diſfiguring, which ſufficiently declares her to be the only piece of worke, extracted from the fountaine of al excelling beauty.
            Beſide, the exquiſite proportion of ſweet feminine bodies, is much more rare compoſed then thoſe of men are, by iudgement of the very beſt mayſters in depth of skill: not making deniall of any one part, but that all doe aboundantly expreſſe the true celeſtiall meaſures.
            
               What ſhall I ſay of their ſinguler ſpirit, which ordinarily ſhewes it ſelfe moſt conſtant in aduerſitie, moſt gratious and fauourable in felicitie, and farre beyond all abilitie remaining in men? How often times (if the auncient and moderne hiſtories are of any trueth) haue they beene the cauſe of exceeding victories? How manye times haue they couragiouſly reſiſted againſt the troopes and feeble ſquadrons of mens vertues, whome they haue not only ouerthrowen, and broken their diſſeignes, but likewiſe compelled moſt ſhamfully to flight? Where is he that can produce the Captaine of any nation, who in valour, proweſſe and councell, might be equalled with the victorious Volſcian Queene Camilla, or the magnanimous Pentheſilea? what dilligence or ſagacitie ſo admirable, can yee produce to compare with that of Semiramis? was euer any vertue ſpoken of, to bee noted in truer ſhape, then in Zenobia, Ʋalaſca, and

many other famous Ladyes of elder times, ſo royally flouriſhing in all excellencies and perfections whatſoeuer? Name but one that ſurmounted them (or to ſpeake more properly) that was not (indeede) greatly inferiour to them in fidelitie and conſtancie.
            For mine owne parte, I haue turned ouer and ouer the leaues of Hiſtories, as well of my natiue, as of moſt languages beſide, and I haue obſerued them with the greateſt care I could: yet finde I not in them any examples of more weightie and illuſtrate vertues, then thoſe which by Ladyes haue been taught at all times. How many of them (to maintaine theyr intire faith &amp; feruent loue) haue oppoſed thēſelues againſt a thouſand dangers of wars: and neuer were their frends or eſteemed thruſt into exile, but (with infinit greefes) they haue gladly changed both name and habit, onely through pure affection borne to their husbands, beloued by thē more dearly

then life, &amp; more honored then ought els could be by them.
            As for humanity and curteſie, yee ſhall not finde any man equal to them. Ye are not able to comprehend the number of noble Dames, who for releefe of hoſpitals, ayde of poore beggers, building of Churches, founding of Chappels, and redemption of pryſoners, haue employed and conſumed al their temporal goods, preferring the honour of God and care of Chriſtians, before baſe loue to ſuch corruptible traſh. Yea, they haue done this with ſuch affection and zeale, as (let men take it how they will) I neuer heard of any man, how noble or valiant ſoeuer hee was: that euer did but halfe ſo much, as a woman hath bin knowen in his time to haue done, being more renowned and honored therfore, then he with all his beſt attemptes could compaſſe.
            What thinke yee of the noble womans minde, that deigned to receiue

al the Romaine hoaſt in her own land: with ſo great and bountifull liberality beſide, as the memory thereof continues to this preſent day? Why ſhould we forget the noble and kinde diſpoſition of Phryne, who offered to build againe the whole compaſſe of Thebes walles? without demaunding any other recompence of the Cittizens, but onely to ſhew her ſo much fauour, as her name (for memories ſake) might be engrauen on the building: thinke what manner of Citty Thebes was, that contained an hundred ſeuerall gates in the circuite thereof.
            I let a number paſſe my pen, whoſe memory and fame are of ſuch ample record, as there are none of ſo meane knowledge but doe very well remember.
            As good Tabitha, whoſe charitye was reputed ſo great and memorable, that for the preſent reliefe of poore afflicted Widdowes, ſuccour of Orphanes and needy ſoules, ſhe ſcantly

left to ſerue her owne weake neceſſitie.
            Such charitie was neuer heard of in any man, and therefore the more worthye to liue for euer. The like hath beene doone by diuers other women, ſufficientlye to bee knowne by obſerued writings, which are ordinarilye read in manye places of the world.
            But to anſwere certaine greeuous obiections, which womens aduerſaries haue falſely alleadged, as hoping that way to ouerthrowe womens honour; albeit thoſe points (as I haue alreadie approoued) makes nothing at all againſt their excellence, which farre ſurmounteth all the ſlaunders inuented againſt them: Neuertheleſſe, to ſhewe I am not vnprouided of an anſwer, I will euidentlie make it knowne, that the frailties againſt Women affirmed, are much more great and notorious in men then women, which prooues them ſo much

the rather ſuperiour, then any waye ſubiect or inferiour to men.
            One ſayth, that for money (which is a vile and ſeruile thing) they ſomtimes part with that, which they ought to eſteeme dearer then their proper liues. Nowe let vs regarde, whether this promptitude be cauſed by the ſweetneſſe of their noble blood and affection: or rather the kinde gentleneſſe of their hearts, which makes them yeelde ſo eaſily to the intreats of their fauourites. But goe we a little further on, and then we ſhall finde, that this faulte ought rather to be imputed to the troubleſome opportunities of men, theyr laſciuious eye-glaunces, theyr ambuſhes, threats and deceipts, which daily (without any care of conſcience) they practiſe and procure againſt ſo noble a ſex. As for my ſelfe, I neuer heard or knew, that any woman voluntarily gaue her ſelfe to a man, without his traynes and craftie ſollicitings vſed before.
            
               But I haue euermore well noted, in ſuch as laboured moſt to detect them, firſt, a ſhew of long ſeruice, vrged on with feigned and diſſembled teares, intermingled with a million of counterfeit ſighes, beſide infinite ingenious tromperies, which men haue at commaund to attend vppon them.
            Moreouer, I haue ſometimes obſerued, that when by all theſe meanes they could not attaine their purpoſe: they haue ſought by violence to compaſſe it, furthering their attempts by hatefull treaſons, or the preſent villanie of ſome ſubtill ſeruant, whome ſuch maiſters are woonte to recompence very largely, for ſuch an honeſt and ſeruiceable peice of worke.
            See to what kindes of excellencie, the mindes of men are dayly addicted, and yet they will be Lordes and controullers ouer women, when baſeſt infamie dooth thus commaund ouer themſelues. Truely, the conceipts of

women are farre otherwiſe, and (if it be true that Ariſtotle ſaith) that the parties compoſed of moſt noble and delicate fleſh, are of a higher and better ſpirite then the other: then none are ſo ſimple to doubt, but the fleſh of women is much more ſoft and tender, then mens: do wee not likewiſe beholde by experience, that in all ingenious inuentions, their ſpirits doe exceede the greateſt eminence of mens?
            Looke in the catalogue of inuenters of things, if they haue not beene the inuentreſſes of many excellent and incomparable woorkes: eſpecially of good letters, which at this day make men ſeeme ſo rare and excellent. Why then this ſerues to ſhew yee, that euen as men are borne of them; ſo likewiſe are the ſciences which we call humaine. For proofe heereof, the vertuous Lady Carmenta firſt of all inuented them, by meanes whereof it happened, that the skilfull Leontia,
               
confuted and woone (by reaſon in diſputation) the victorie ouer learned Theophraſtus. Sappho inuented the verſes, which (after her name) are called Sapphicks; and had great contention with many excellent Poets in her time, confuting all of them in the end, as the lyke (not without ſinguler praiſe) did faire Corinna.
            
            If wee would ſpeake of our time, where is the Italian Poet ſo hardie, and ſo ſure in his compoſition, as to compare with the Ladye Marqueſſe of Peſcara, or 
                  Ʋeronica of Gambara, or gentle Armilla Angoſciole? In Spaine and Germanie yee ſhall finde whole Legions, that kept Schooles of all Sciences, eſpeciallye of good language, and pureſt writing, excelling the very skilfulleſt men in thoſe countries.
            How many is there in the Courte of Fraunce, whom the learnedſt in the land (I ſay not in diuinitie) but in humaine ſciences, dare not deale withall

or contradict? And as for them in Citties, we may remember the ſweete Gentlewoman Eliſena, Morella, Robertet the Bayli
                  •
               eſſe of Touraine, young fayre Moyfa
                     •
                  ct, beſide infinite others whom I leaue, able to inſtruct a right good ſecretary, how skilfull ſoeuer he be, to couche in writing any caſe of inuention, be it eyther in rime or proſe. As for recluſe women, moſt certain is it, that neither Valeria Proba, nor Paula, nor Euſtochium, who liued in the time of S. Hierom, excelled them that now are at this preſent daye. For breuities ſake I am conſtrained to let them paſſe, becauſe their ſingularitie ſhall the more commend them, by ſuch workes as ſhall make them liue perpetually renowmed: yet therein they begge not applauſe as men baſelie doo, who will not be a little offended, if men reporte not of them to the vttermoſt.
            I could wade very long in this diſcourſe, &amp; run far to aſſemble by breefe

recitall, diuers noble and ingenious women more: were it not, that euen as Heſiodus and Plutarch, haue largely written their vertues of elder time: ſo for our moderne dames, Maiſter Iohn Boccace and others haue honeſtly diſcharged their conſciences, ſo that no further proofe neede to be produced in this place.
            If yee will vrge me to confirme this caſe, by extraordinarie priuiledges graunted to women: I neede goe no further then the old Teſtament, where God commaunded Abraham, that he ſhould doo what his good wife Sara willed him. Moreouer we finde, that our Sauiour (after his holy reſurrection) did firſt of all appeare to women, Mereurius Triſmegiſtus, who (of men) woorthily may be tearmed excellent, knowing the merueilous perfections and vertues of women; left written in his bookes, that the man who had not a wife ought eſpecially to be auoyded, conſidering, that from the woman (as

from a moſt aboundant fountayne,) flowed all gifts of bountie and goodneſſe: and the houſes where no women were, ought to bee eſteemed as vaſt Deſerts, or vntilled lands.
            Where is true pollicie, if not in a houſholde? where is perfect honeſtie, if not where women are? Saint Paul, in his Epiſtle to the Hebrews, when he would produce the example of peoples faithfulneſſe, to bee kept and obſerued betweene each other: did hee not alledge that of Rahab? But becauſe it is a common matter in the moſt part of men, to obiect againſt women, that they are of weake courage, and ſo conſequently, very niggardly and couetous: I would demaund of them, were not women in auncient time called Dames, becauſe of their readineſſe and franckneſſe in giuing? I haue not ſo many hayres on my head, as I haue knowne honeſt women, not onely prompt to giue moſt courteous and amiable preſents; but withall, to offer

ſuch a zealous heart and affection, as witneſſed they could neuer bee ſufficientlie requited againe: yet doone without expecting publique glorye and applauſe, as men doo, who are ambitious and couetous of vayne reportes.
            Seeing women then haue ſhowne themſelues ſo vertuous and excellent, it may bee thought a matter not without great reaſon, that the vertuous Grecians retayned Womens names among them, and not mens: as well knowing by theyr firſt detracters, that Women were ſinguler freendes to honour and vertue.
            I could (to this effect) alleadge infinite other reaſons and examples, for confirmation of Womens excellencie: but becauſe I haue referred yee to Hiſtories, I will giue ende to this well imployed labour. Yet let mee firſt intreate yee, to make reuerend regarde of that you ſhall finde in

approoued good Authours: which if yee doo, the height and dignitie of women will be ſo ingrauen in your mindes, as no malignitie whatſoeuer can preuayle againſt them, and your ſelues will truly confeſſe, that the moſt I can deuiſe to write, can neuer reache to the leaſt part of theyr eſpeciall deſeruing vertues, and moſt excellent graces wherewith they are decked and adorned.
            And this I can aſſure yee beſide, that the moſt parte of excellent and vertuous men, haue attributed all tytles of honour to Women, daylye becomming theyr ſeruantes in hart, yea, euen humble in proſtration (as it were) to adore them, as if in ſome ſorte they tooke parte with the higheſt diuinitie.
            Then let vs not fayle hencefoorth to looue them hartilye, by example of our wiſe and diſcreete elders, yeelding our ſelues voluntarily

as ſubiect to them: neuer regarding venemous ſpightfull tongues, that haue not ſpared to ſpeake their vttermoſt againſt them.
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            Imprinted at London by Iohn Wolfe, and are to be ſolde at his ſhop in Popes head Alley, neere vnto the Exchange.
            1599.
            
         
      
   

