
   
      
         
            An easie entrance into the principall points of Christian religion verie short and plaine for the simpler sorte, and may soone be learned of them, if they haue any care (as all ought to haue) of their saluation. By I.G.
            Gibson, John, fl. 1579-1599.
         
         
            
               1579
            
         
         Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01695
            STC 11832
            ESTC S114026
            99849254
            99849254
            14392
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01695)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14392)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 709:09)
         
         
            
               
                  An easie entrance into the principall points of Christian religion verie short and plaine for the simpler sorte, and may soone be learned of them, if they haue any care (as all ought to haue) of their saluation. By I.G.
                  Gibson, John, fl. 1579-1599.
               
               [24] p.   
               
                  [By H. Middleton] for William Norton,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  1579.
               
               
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Not the same text as STC 20585.3: R., O.  An easie entrance into the chiefe poynts of christian religion.
                  Signatures: A B⁴.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-07
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-08
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-05
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2008-05
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            ¶ AN EASIE ENTRANCE INTO the principall points of Chriſtian Re
                     ••••…
                   verie ſhort and plaine for the 
                  〈◊〉
                
               
                  •••
               te, and may ſoone be lea
                  〈…〉
               , if they haue any care 
                  〈◊…〉
                
               
                  ••…
               ght to haue) 
                  〈◊…〉
                
               
                  ••…
               uuation▪
            
            By I. G.
            
               Hebr. 5. 12.
            When as concerning the time ye ought to bee teachers, yet haue ye neede againe that we teach you what are the firſt principles of the word of God▪ and are become ſuch as haue neede of milke, and not of ſtrong meate.
            
               Iohn. 3. 12.
            If when I tell you earthly thinges, ye beleeue not, how ſhould ye beleeue, if I ſhall tell you of heauenly thinges?
            ¶ IMPRINTED AT London for William Norton.
            1579.
         
         
            
            
               
            
         
         
            
            To the Reader.
            
               I HAVE endeuoured (gentle Reader) to ſet downe the principall pointes of Chriſtian Religion, in as plaine ſorte as I coulde poſſible: for their ſakes eſpecially, whoſe capacities are ſmall, and memories vnable to cō
               taine much. If I haue attained that whiche I attempted (that is to ſay, their profite) I haue my deſire: If otherwiſe▪ then although my worke deſerue no
                  •
                prayſe (which if it did, were due onely to God) yet my will deſireth pardon, whiche I doe not doubt to obteine at thy handes, ſeeing I ſeeke nothing but thy aduauntage. The excuſes that are dayly made for ignorance, while one layeth the fault in his want of time, an other in his ſimplicitie, and want of capacitie, and others in want of memorie, &amp;c. did much moue me to trie what I coulde doe, to doe them good: although I am not ignorant, that others alſo haue gone about the ſame. But ſuch is the dulneſſe of our dayes, and ſo hard is it to be both ſhort and yet playne,

in ſo great matters, that it is well, if eyther their or my labour, or all that we all can doe, may bring men forwarde in the faith. If wee miſſe this, yet becauſe wee meane it, he that is not vncharitably ſuſpicious, will not thinke the labour ſuperfluous. If this come to the hands of ſuch, as are already paſt ſuch A. B. Cees▪ let it not offend them, that children are ledde, though they beeing men can goe alone. And let them leaue this, eyther to children in yeares or in knowledge: whiche muſt of neceſſitie be trained vp in this, or ſuch ſhort and plaine ſorte, if they will profit, as I pray God they may, and wee all euerie day increaſe in knowledge, and growe in the grace of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, who euer preſerue you, &amp; to whome be prayſe in the Church through all generations for euer.
            
               *⁎*
            
            AMEN.
         
      
      
         
            
            The Lawe.
            Miniſter. Pariſhioner.
            
               WHat Religion doe you profeſſe?
            
               P
               The Religion of a trueRom. 10. 1
                        •
                     . Mat. 10. 32. Act 11. 20. Chriſtian.
            
            
               M.
               Wherein conſiſteth chiefly the Religion of a true Chriſtian?
            
            
               P.
               In the true vnderſtanding and profitableAct. 2. 41 42. vſe of the ten commaundements: the Articles of faith: the Sacramentes: and prayer.
            
            
               M.
               Rehearſe firſt the ten cōmandemēts.Deut 4 13. Exod. 20. Deut. 5.
               
            
            
               P.
               The ſame which God ſpake, &amp;c.
            
            
               M.
               What doeth God chiefly require in theſe commaundements?
            
            
               P.
               That I ſhould loue him with all myMa. 22. 37. 39. heart, with al my ſoule, and with all my ſtrength: and that I ſhoulde loue my neighbour as my ſelfe.
            
            
               M.
               Howe is God loued?
            
            
               P.
               By obeying perfectly thoſe commandementes,1. Iohn. 2. 5. which teach our dutie towards him.
            
            
               M
               How many are they.Exod. 34. 1. Deu. 10. 1. 2. Exo
                        •
                     . 
                        •
                     0. 3. Ma
                        •
                     
                     ▪ 
                     
                        •
                     . 10. Deut. 10. 12. &amp; 
                        •
                     0. &amp;. 6. 13.
               
            
            
               P.
               Foure in the firſt table.
            
            
               M.
               What dutie teacheth the firſt▪
               
            
            
               P.
               That I ſhould alwayes worſhippe,

feare and loue this true and liuing GodPſal. 50. 13. 14. and. 23. Deut. 6. 4. and 14. aboue all things, truſt in him only, pray and giue thankes to him alone. And neuer by theſe meanes to worſhip or ſerue any creature in his preſence.
            
            
               M.
               The ſecond. Exod. 20. 4. 5. 6.
               
            
            
               P.
               That I ſhould not imagine him toDeut. 4. 15. 16. 17. 18. 19. Leui. 26. 1. Exo. 34. 14. Eſa. 42. 8. Aba. 2. 19. 20. Io. 4. 23. 24. be like any thing that I ſée or knowe in the whole worlde, nor worſhip him in, or vnder anye image, or likeneſſe of anye thing, but in ſpirite and trueth, as hée hath commaunded.
            
            
               M.
               The thirde. Exod. 20. 7.
               
            
            
               P.
               That I ſhould not abuſe his nameLeuit. 24. 16. and 19. 12. Mat. 5. 34. Heb. 6 16. Exod. 22. 10. Iac. 5. 12. Deut. 28. 58. any kinde of way, much leſſe by falſe or vaine othes, but beeing lawfully called to an othe, then to ſweare truely by him onely, and at no time by any creature, and to vſe his name alwayes to his honour and glory.
            
            
               M.
               The fourth. Exod. 20. 8. 9. 10. 11.
               
            
            
               P.
               That I, and all mine, ceaſe from alLeuit. 26. 2. bodilie labour, and wéekely trauayle, and come to Church to heare the wordeAct. 20. 7. of God, and receiue the Sacramentes, and pray together with the whole Congregation:Deut. 5. 14. Ex. 23. 12. and that my familie and all my cattell may by the ſame reſte bée refreſhed.
            
            
               
               M.
               And howe ſhall we loue our neighbour?
            
            
               P.
               By kéeping perfectly thoſe commaundementes,Rom. 13. 8. 9. 10. which conteyne our du
                  
                     •
                  ie to him.
            
            
               M.
               Which are they?
            
            
               P.
               The other ſixe in the ſecond table.Exod. 32. 15.
               
            
            
               M.
               What meaneth the fift, beeing theExod. 20. 12. firſt of the ſame?
            
            
               P.
               That I ſhoulde loue, reuerence, obey,Mar. 7. 10. Ephe. 6. 1. 2. Gal. 6. 6. 1. Theſ. 5. 12. Rom. 13. 1. Exod. 21. 17. and. 22. 28. and helpe my natural parentes, and all my ſuperiours, and gouernours of the Church and common wealth, and at no time reſiſte or diſpiſe their authoritie.
            
            
               M.
               The ſixt, Thou ſhalt do no murther?Exo. 20. 13. 1. Iohn. 3. 15. mat. 5. 21. 22. 1. Iohn. 3. 16.
               
            
            
               P
               That I ſhoulde not kill, nor hate in my hearte, nor reuyle any with my tongue, but helpe, ſaue, and kéepe their liues as much as I am able.
            
            
               M.
               The ſeuenth, Thou ſhalt not commitExod. 20. 14. adulterie?
            
            
               P.
               That I ſhould not commit the déedeMat. 5. 27. 28. 1. Theſ. 4. 3. 1. Cor. 7. 2. Ephe. 5. 3. 4. in bodie, nor luſt after it with any in my heart, but vſe all meanes to kéep and declare my ſelfe ſober and chaſt.Exod. 20. 15.
               
            
            
               M.
               The eight, Thou ſhalt not ſteale?
            
            
               
               P.
               That I ſhould not take away theLeuit. 19. 13. 1. Theſ. 4. 6. De. 25. 13. 14 Luke. 12. 15. Ephe. 4. 28. 1 Iohn. 3. 17. 1. Tim. 6. 7. 8. goods of any other by deceite or violence, nor in my heart deſire the ſame: but reſtore to euery man his, to giue to them which néede, &amp; to be content with mine owne.
            
            
               M.
               The ninth, Thou ſhalt beare no falſe witneſſe againſt thy neighbour? Exodus. 20. 15.
            
            
               P.
               That I ſhould not hurt any withExod. 23. 1. Iac. 4. 11. Leuit. 19▪ 16. 1. Cor. 13. 5. Leuit. 19. 17. Mat. 18. 15. Ephe. 4. 29. my tongue by falſe witneſſe, backbitings, ſlaunders or flattering, nor without cauſe ſuſpect euill of any: but vſe my tongue to further and profite them in whatſoeuer I am able.
            
            
               M.
               The tenth. Thou ſhalt not couet? Exodus. 20. 16.
            
            
               P.
               That there ſhould not be in me anyMar. 7. 21. 22 Rom. 7. 7. Iac. 1. 14. Pſal. 11. 7. motions or deſires to any ſinne, but that I ſhoulde be without all ſinne, and holy in my whole ſoule and bodie.
            
            
               M.
               Are you able then thus to kéepe theſe commaundementes?
            
            
               P.
               No verelie.Rom. 8. 3.
               
            
            
               M.
               Where is the faulte?
            
            
               P.
               In my corrupt nature, which is enimieRom. 8. 7. to all righteouſnes.
            
            
               M.
               Who corrupted your nature?
            
            
               
               P.
               Adam, by his trangreſſion, fo
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                  odRom. 5. 12. Gen. 1. 26. Eccle. 7. 31. created it good.
            
            
               M.
               Séeing then we cannot chooſe, but breake them, what is the puniſhment of1. Io. 3. 4. our ſinne and tranſgreſſion.
            
            
               P.
               The curſe of God vpon bodie andDeut. 28. 15. ſoule, to euerlaſting death.
            
            
               M.
               If we kéepe ſome, will he not beare with vs for the reſt?
            
            
               P.
               No: but accurſeth vs, if we continueDeut. 27. 26. not in all things in them to do them.
            
            
               M.
               Is he not then mercifull?
            
            
               P.
               Yes: but this Lawe is the rule ofExod. 34. 6. Leuit. 18. 5. Rom. 2. 13. his iuſtice, and teacheth vs what we are bound to do, and not what he will forgiue.
            
            
               M.
               What is the vſe of this knowledge?
            
            
               P.
               To teache me that in my ſelfe I amRom. 4, 15. Gal. 3. 10. 2. Cor. 3. 7. Rom. 6. 23. Mat. 6. 33. &amp; 16. 26. always the childe of wrath, accurſed and condempned to euerlaſting death.
            
            
               M.
               Howe then ſhall we be ſaued?
            
            
               P.
               By faith: Luke 7. 50. Roman. 1. 16. and 3. 28. and 10. 9. Galat. 2. 16. Epheſ. 2. 8. Mar. 10. 16.
            
            
               M.
               What is faith?
            
            
               P.
               A certeine knowledge and full aſſuranceIo. 17. 3. Heb. 11. 1. in the principall pointes of ſaluation▪
                  
I called the Goſpell.
            
            
               M.
               Which are theſe chéefe pointes of ſaluation?
            
            
               P.
               The articles of faith, which is the ſecoond thing, in the true vnderſtanding and vſe whereof conſiſteth chriſtian religion.
            
            
               M.
               Rehearſe them.
                     
                        •
                     . Pet. 3. 15.
               
            
            
               P.
               I beléeue in God the father almightie, maker of heauen and earth, &amp;c.
            
            
               M.
               Wherfore ſay you, I beléeue, &amp; not we beléeue, ſéeing this doctrine of ſaluatiō belongeth to others aſwel as to you?
            
            
               P.
               Becauſe my faith doeth apply it toGal. 2. 20. Abac. 2. Heb. 11. 6. my ſelfe, and maketh it effectuall to ſaluation to my ſelfe onely.
            
            
               M.
               Wherefore beléeue you in God?Eſa. 43. 11 Ephe. 2. 4. 2. Tim. 1. 9. Tit. 1. 3.
               
            
            
               P.
               Becauſe my whole ſaluation commeth from him alone.
            
            
               M.
               What is God?
            
            
               P.
               A ſpirituall ſubſtance, infinite, andIo. 4. 24. Eſai. 66 1. Io. 17. 3. 
                        •
                     . Cor. 8. 5. 6. incomprehenſible.
            
            
               M.
               Is there but one God onely to beléeue in?
            
            
               P.
               No: but this one God is thrée perſons.
            
            
               M.
               Which are they?
            
            
               P.
               The Father, the Sonne, &amp; the holieMat. 28. 19.
                  
Ghoſte, which do together worke whatheuerLuk. 3. 22. Tit. 3. 4. 5. 6. belongeth to my ſaluation.
            
            
               M.
               Wherefore beléeue you in God the Father?
            
            
               P.
               Becauſe he hath ſo loued me, that heIoh. 3. 16. 
                  
                     •
                  ath giuen his onely begotten ſonne to 
                     •
                  aue me.
            
            
               M.
               What profiteth it you, that he is 
                     •
                  lmightie?
            
            
               P.
               That being my father, his powerGen. 15. 1. and 17. 1. Mat, 10. 29. 30. 31. 2. Tim. 1. 12. which nothing can reſiſt) ſhal alwayes watch ouer me.
            
            
               M.
               What ſignifieth, Maker of heauen and earth?
            
            
               P.
               That he will alwayes prouide ſufficientLuk. 12. 22. 23 and 30. Pſal. 37. 25. Heb. 13. 5. 6. foode and rayment for my bodie, and the nouriſhment of my life in this worlde.
            
            
               M.
               From whence haue you this truſt that he is your father, and that he will do all this for you?
            
            
               P.
               Through my belefe in Ieſus ChriſtIo. 14. 6. Ephe. 2. 18. 1. Pe. 1. 20 21. Rom. 8. 32. his Sonne, whome he hath giuen to mée, &amp; with him will giue mée all things elſe.
            
            
               M.
               Why is he called Ieſus?
            
            
               P.
               Becauſe God hath appointed himMat. 1. 1. 21 Act. 4. 12. onely to ſaue mée from my ſinnes.
            
            
               
               M.
               And why is he called Chriſt?Ioh. 1. 41 Dan. 9. 24. Pſal. 45. 7. Act. 3. 22. 23. Heb. 10. 14. Heb. 1. 1. Mat. 21. 5. Luke. 1. 32. 33 Ihon. 18. 36.
               
            
            
               P.
               To ſignifie that he is annoynted 
                     〈◊〉
                   God, to be my only teacher in the mean
                     •…
                   of my ſaluation: my onely Prieſt, to reconcile mée to his father: my onely ſpirituall King, to gouerne and rule me by his worde and holie Spirite.
            
            
               M.
               What manner of perſon is Ieſus Chriſt, which doth all this for you?
            
            
               P.
               Both God and man.Rom. 1. 3. 4. Phil. 2. 6. 7.
               
            
            
               M.
               Which wordes teach you that he is God?
            
            
               P.
               Theſe, His onely ſonne our Lord.Rom. 8. 3. Iohn. 10. 36.
               
            
            
               M.
               Whoſe Sonne do you meane he is?
            
            
               P.
               The ſonne of God the Father.Mat. 17. 5. Heb. 1. 5.
               
            
            
               M.
               Why call ye him his onely ſonne, ſéeing men and Angelles are called his ſonnes alſo?
            
            
               P.
               Becauſe he is begotten of his veriePſal. 82 6. Rom. 8. 14. Iob. 1. 6. Iohn 1 14. Heb. 1. 3. ſubſtance, and is true &amp; verie God with his Father.
            
            
               M.
               When was he begotten of his Father?
            
            
               P.
               He hath béene begotten euer, euenPro. 8. 22. Iohn. 1. 1. 2 as the Father hath béene euer, without beginning, or elſe he were not God.
            
            
               M.
               And which wordes teache thatGal. 4. 4.
                  
was made man?
            
            
               P.
               Theſe: which was conceiued by theMat. 1. 18. Luk. 1. 27. 
                  
                     〈…〉
                  lie Ghoſt, borne of the vingin Marie.
            
            
               M.
               Why was he conceiued by the ho
                  
                     〈…〉
                   Ghoſt?
            
            
               P.
               That he might be moſt holie &amp; iuſtLuke. 1. 35. Actes. 22. 14. Heb. 7. 26. without all ſinne.
            
            
               M.
               Why was he borne of the Virgine 
                     •
                  arie?
            
            
               P.
               That he might be a true man likeHeb. 2. 11. 16 
                  
                     •
                  nto vs in all things, ſinne excepted.
            
            
               M.
               Wherefore was he man?
            
            
               P.
               To ſtande in our roume, and to ſufferHeb. 2. 14. 15 Gal. 4. 4. 5. 1. Tim. 2. 6. in bodie and ſoule, that curſe which 
                     〈…〉
                   due to our ſinnes.
            
            
               M.
               Which wordes teach this?
            
            
               P.
               Suffered vnder Pontius Pilate,Luke. 23. 1. Iohn. 19. 33 Mark 15. 40. was crucified, dead, and buried, he deſcended into hell.
            
            
               M.
               What do theſe former words ſignifie?
            
            
               P.
               That he was condemned of PontiusMat. 27. 24. &amp; 25 26. Luke. 23. 33. Phi. 2. 8. Pilat, to the accurſed death of the croſſe, which he ſuffered in bodie.
            
            
               M.
               And what ſignifieth, Deſcended into hell?
            
            
               P.
               It is added, to ſhewe that he humbledPhil. 2. 8. him ſelfe, and went vnder the

wrath of God euen in the ſame curſ
                     •
                  
                  Gal. 3. 13 Eſ. 53. 10. Mat. 26. 39. Lu. 22. 44. Mat. 27. 46. death which he ſuffered in body: A
                     •
                   that he felt the anguiſhe and horrour 
                     •
                   ye ſame wrath of God in his ſoule which cauſed him to ſweat droppes of bloud and to cry, my God, my God, why ha
                     •
                   thou forſaken me?
            
            
               M.
               This curſe and wrath of God the
                     •
                   you meane is the hell that he was in before he died: and that he was in it bot
                     •
                   in body and ſoule.
            
            
               P
               Yea verily: for the ſcripture teachet
                     •
                  
                  Io. 19. 30. no other ſuffering in any other place fo
                     •
                   our deliuerance from the ſame.
            
            
               M.
               And howe doth this profit you?
            
            
               P.
               Becauſe I beléeue that this which
                     •
                  
                  1. Pet. 2. 24. Gal. 3. 13. he thus ſuffered in his bodie and ſoule, was for my ſinnes, ſo that he hath redéemed me from the ſame for euer.
            
            
               M.
               You ſaid before that he is God alſo, did this his Godhead ſuffer any thing?
            
            
               P.
               No: For God cannot ſuffer.
            
            
               M.
               Wherefore then was he God?
            
            
               P.
               That he might ouercome death, and2. Cor. 13. 4. get the victorie, which beeing man onely,1. Pet. 3. 18. he coulde not haue done.
            
            
               M.
               Which words contein this victory?
            
            
               P.
               Theſe following, The third day he
                  Luc. 24 40.
                  
                  roſe againe, &amp;c.
                  Act. 2 32.
               
            
            
               M.
               Did the ſame body riſe againe?
            
            
               P.
               Yea, and is aſcended into heauen,Ioh. 20. 27 Luk 24. 51. Mar. 16. 
                        •
                     9. 
                  
                     •
                  nd is there God and man in the glorie 
                     •
                  f his father.
            
            
               M.
               Did he aſcende by and by after hée 
                     •…
                  oſe againe?
            
            
               P.
               No: but walked fourtie days on theAct. 1. 3. 
                  
                     •
                  arth, and ſhewed him ſelfe to his diſciples, to confirme them in the truth of his reſurrection.
            
            
               M.
               What doeth this profite you?
            
            
               P.
               I beléeue that he now hath giuen toRom. 4. 25. Ephe. 4. 7. 8 1. Cor. 1. 30 
                  
                     •…
                  ne his holineſſe of nature, &amp; the righteouſneſſe of his whole life, to ſanctifie, and 
                     •
                  uſtifie me alwayes before God.
            
            
               M.
               What meaneth his ſitting at theHeb. 1. 3. &amp; 12. 2 1. Pet. 3. 22. Mat. 28. 18. Ephe. 1. 22. 1. Cor. 15. 25. r
                     •
                  ight hand of God the father almightie?
            
            
               P.
               That his father hath giuen him all power in heauen and earth, to gouerne and defend his Church, &amp; to confound all the enimies of the ſame.
            
            
               M.
               What elſe doth he now in heauen for vs?
            
            
               P.
               He maketh continual interceſſion toRom. 8. 
                        •
                     4. Heb. 7. 25. Io. 14. 13. 14 his father, ſo that I beléeue whatſoeuer I aſk in his name, I ſhal ſurely receiue.
            
            
               M.
               what remayneth to be done of him?
            
            
               
               P.
               From thence ſhall he come to iudg
                     •
                  
                  Actes. 1. 11. 2. Tim. 4. 1. the quicke and the dead.
            
            
               M.
               Who are they?
            
            
               P.
               All that are departed this life befor
                     •
                  
                  1. Cor. 15. 51. 1. Theſ. 4. 15. his comming, and all which ſhall be her
                     •
                   aliue at his comming.
            
            
               M.
               What is your cōfidence in that dayAct. 3. 19. &amp; 17. 30. 31. 1. Cor. 1. 8. Iude. 24. Mat. 25. 34. whereof we ought to haue chief regard?
            
            
               P.
               That by this faith in him, I ſhall ſtand blameleſſe, and that he wll giue me the inheritance of the kingdome of heauen, which he hath purchaſed for me.
            
            
               M.
               Why beléeue you in ye holie Ghoſt?
            
            
               P.
               Becauſe he doth worke this faith &amp;Ephe 1. 13. 14 2. Cor. 1. 22. Rom. 8. 16. aſſurance of this my ſaluation by Chriſt in my heart.
            
            
               M.
               Howe ſhall it bee knowne that he hath wrought this faith in your heart?
            
            
               P.
               By his inſeparable worke of regeneration,Tit. 3. 5. Io. 3. 5. 6. or newe birth in my nature.
            
            
               M.
               What is that?
            
            
               P.
               To ſanctifie me daily, by killing ſin2. Theſ. 2. 13. 1. Theſ. 4. 3. 1. Pet. 1, 2. in me, and by quickening me to newnes of life.
            
            
               M.
               What is the Catholike Church?
            
            
               P.
               All, of all nations which haue, doe, &amp;1. Cor. 1 2. Act. 2. 47. and 13. 48. &amp;. 15. 8 9. ſhall thus beléeue in Ieſus Chriſt for ſaluation.
            
            
               
               M.
               What is the cōmunion of Saints?
            
            
               P.
               That all theſe in what parte of theEphe 4. 12. 13. 1. Cor. 1. 9. 1. Ihon. 1. 3. Ioh. 17. 17. 19 
                  
                     •
                  arth ſo euer they liue, are gathered in
                  
                     •
                  o the fellowſhip of Chriſte, and are par
                  
                     •
                  akers in commune of all his benefites where by they are made Saints.
            
            
               M.
               What is the remiſſion of ſinnes?
            
            
               P.
               That all their ſinnes are ſo fullyEphe. 1. 7. Col. 1. 14. 1. Io. 2. 12. 
                  
                     •
                  uniſhed in Chriſte, that they are free
                  
                     •
                  y forgiuen &amp; remitted to them for euer.
            
            
               M.
               And what is the reſurrection of the body, and life euerlaſting?
            
            
               P.
               That all their bodyes ſhall be raiſedIo. 6. 54. Rom. 8. 11. 1. Cor. 15. 41. 43. 44. Phil. 3. 22. vp againe at the laſt day, and be ioyned to their ſoules, to liue with Ieſus Chriſt for euer in true glory.
            
            
               M.
               What doeth the beléefe of all theſe thinges profite you?
            
            
               P.
               I beléeue that nowe being called2. Cor. 15. 5. Act. 26. 18. Rom. 8. 30. from ignorance to this faith and aſſurāce in Ieſus Chriſt with them, I do, and ſhal enioy all theſe benefites alſo with them for euer.
            
            
               M.
               Thus you haue gone briefly thorough the Law, &amp; the doctrine of Faith, what is next, the true vnderſtanding wherof belongeth to a true Chriſtian?
            
            
               P.
               The Sacraments.
            
            
               
               M.
               What is a Sacrament?Rom. 4. 11. Gal. 3. 27. 1. Cor. 11. 26.
               
            
            
               P.
               An outwarde ſigne and ſure ſeale to ſtrengthen my faith in Chriſt, and al his benefites by my outwarde ſenſes: and a badge of my profeſſion before men.
            
            
               M.
               Howe many are there in Chriſt his Church to this vſe?Ephe. 5. 26. Titus. 3. 5. 1. Pet. 3. 21. 1. Cor. 11. 20. &amp; 23. 24. 25.
               
            
            
               P.
               Two.
            
            
               M.
               Which are they?
            
            
               P
               Baptiſme, and the Lordes ſupper.
            
            
               M.
               What is the outwarde ſigne &amp; ſure ſeale of Baptiſme?
            
            
               P.
               Water.Iohn. 3. 23. Actes. 8. 36. 38
               
            
            
               M.
               Howe doth it ſtrengthen your faith in Chriſt, and all his benefites by your ſenſes?
            
            
               P.
               That▪ as I ſée and knowe water wherewith I haue bene baptized, doeth waſhe and make cleane thinges that are foule: ſo as certainly Chriſte doeth giue himſelf to me, that his blood may alwaisActes. 2. 38. &amp; 22. 16. waſh and cleanſe me from al my ſinnes.
            
            
               M.
               And what is the outwarde ſigne &amp; ſure ſeale of the Lordes ſupper?
            
            
               P.
               Bread and wine.1. Cor. 11, 13 24. 25.
               
            
            
               M.
               And howe do they ſtrengthen your faith in Chriſt by your ſenſes?
            
            
               P.
               That as I know bread and wine to

be a full &amp; perfecte nouriſhment of my1. Cor. 10. 16 
                  
                     ••
                  die: and as I ſée the ſame giuen vnto 
                     •
                  e in the communion by the Miniſter:Mat. 26. 26. 27. Ioh. 36. 54. 35 
                  
                     •
                  nd I take, and eate, and drinke ye ſame: 
                     •
                  o as certainely Chriſt giueth to me his 
                     •
                  ody and bloud to be the full and perfect 
                     •
                  oode of my ſoule to eternall life.
            
            
               M.
               From whence haue they this force, 
                     •
                  o ſeale and confirme the trueth of theſe 
                     •
                  hinges in your heart?
            
            
               P.
               From the inſtitution of Chriſt, whoLuk. 22. 19. 20 Matth. 28. 19. 
                  
                     •
                  s trueth it ſelfe, and can not deceiue.
            
            
               M.
               By what meanes is this brought 
                     •
                  o paſſe, ſeeing Chriſtes body is now in 
                     •
                  eauen, and there muſt continue till hisAct. 3. 21. 
                  
                     •
                  omming againe?
            
            
               P.
               By the ſecrete power of the holyIo. 6. 63. 56. Ghoſt, which by faith maketh mee one with Chriſt: and Chriſt with me.
            
            
               M.
               Séeing Chriſte (which you haueRom. 3. 4. 2. Tim. 2. 13. 
                  
                     •
                  aide before) cannot deceiue, offereth himſelf, and al his benefits thus certain
                  
                     •
                  y, by them, Are al that come vnto them, partakers of the ſame?
            
            
               P.
               No: for the vnfaithfull, ignorante,1. Cor. 10. 4. Heb. 11. 6. and vnrepentant, by their vnworthyneſſe, depriue themſelues of them, and receiue onely the outward ſignes, to their1. Cor. 11. 28 &amp;. 29.
                  
owne condemnation.
            
            
               M.
               What elſe remaineth to be vnderſtoode and vſed of a true Chriſtian?
            
            
               P.
               Prayer.Rom. 12. 12. Col. 4. 2. 1. Peter. 4. 7. 1. Tim. 2. 8. Luke. 11. 9. &amp; 13. Iac. 1. 5.
               
            
            
               M.
               What is ye vſe of prayer vnto you?
            
            
               P.
               Séeing God is now become my father, through Chriſt his ſonne, I 
                     ••
                  e and haue recourſe to him by the ſame, for all thinges néedefull, both for my body and ſoule.
            
            
               M.
               Howe ought we to pray?
            
            
               P.
               Euen as our Lorde Ieſus ChriſteLuke. 11. 1. 2. himſelfe hath taught vs.
            
            
               M.
               Reherſe the ſame as you haue learned it.
            
            
               P.
               Our father which art in heauen, &amp;c.Luke. 11. 7. Matth. 6. 9.
               
            
            
               M.
               May we pray with no other words then theſe?
            
            
               P.
               Yes: but this is the rule wherby al our prayers muſt be ſquared, if we ſhallIac. 4. 3. 1. Io. 5. 14. pray aright, &amp; obtein any thing by them.
            
            
               M.
               And doe you pray ſo ofte as you vſe theſe wordes?
            
            
               P.
               No: for if I do not vnderſtand whatMath. 15. 7. 8. thinges I pray for, and deſire earneſtlie1. Cor. 14. 15 in my hart, whatſoeuer I aſke with my tongue, I babble rather then pray.Matt. 6. 7.
               
            
            
               M.
               What things doth this rule of praier

chiefly conteine?
            
            
               P.
               Firſt I learne by it, how to bee prepared to prayer: ſecondly, what thinges to pray for.
            
            
               M.
               In which wordes learne ye how to be prepared to prayer?
            
            
               P.
               In theſe: Our father which art in heauen.
            
            
               M.
               What learn you by this word Our?
               
            
            
               P.
               That I ought to be in loue, &amp; to prayIac. 5. 16. for others as well as for my ſelfe.
            
            
               M.
               What in this word Father?
            
            
               P.
               That I muſt pray with this faithIac. 1. 6. Rom. 
                        •
                     . 15. Gal. 4. 6. Ephe. 3. 11. and ſure truſt in his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, wrought in my heart by the holy Ghoſt, whereby onely I, and all the faithfull, haue this 
                     •
                  ol
                     •
                  neſſe to call him father.
            
            
               M.
               What in theſe: Which art in heauē?
               
            
            
               P.
               That he is ready and able to performe,Pſal. 145. 18. Phil. 4. 5. 6. 1 Peter. 5. 7. Iohn. 17. 1. Pſal. 25. 1. whatſoeuer I aſke: And that my mind muſt be remoued from all earthly and wandring thoughtes, and preſent it ſelfe before him in heauen.
            
            
               M.
               What followeth next?
            
            
               P.
               The petitions for the thinges conteyned1. Iho
                        •
                     . 5. 15. in the ſame.
            
            
               M.
               How many are they?
            
            
               P.
               Sixe.
            
            
               
               M.
               What thinges are they for?
            
            
               P.
               Thrée for thoſe things which chieflyIo. 7. 18. 17. 1 1. Cor. 10. 31. concerne Gods glorie: And thrée for all thinges néedfull for our ſelues.
            
            
               M.
               Shew them bréefly, which concern Gods glorie.
            
            
               P.
               The firſt, that his name may be reuerenced,Pſal. 72. 19. 1. King. 8. 43. Act. 4. 29. 30 Iohn 16. 8. Luke. 18. 7. 8, Reue. 6. 10 &amp; 22. 20. feared, and by all meanes glorified amongſt vs. The ſecond, that hee may raigne daily more and more in our hearts, by his word and ſpirit: and in his good time finiſh and make perfect ye ſame his kingdome, by his laſt comming. The third, that we may yéeld our ſelues wholyHeb. 13. 20. Rom. 12. 1. 2. to his will in all thinges, and ſtriue to go forward in ye ſame, til we méet in perfect obediēce with his angels in heauen.
            
            
               M.
               And what thinges are the other thrée for, which concerne our ſelues?
            
            
               P.
               The firſt Giue vs this day our daily bread, for all thinges for our bodies in this life.
            
            
               M.
               What are they?
            
            
               P.
               Sufficient foode &amp; rayment, health,1. Tim. 6. 8. Pſal. 107. Rom. 15. 30. &amp; other proſperity, according to his will, and as he knoweth to be beſt for vs. And that he would bleſſe all thinges that we
                     
                        •
                     . Cor. 9. 10. vſe &amp; take in hande for the maintenance

of our life.Luk. 11. 4.
               
            
            
               M.
               What thinges aſke you in the other two?
            
            
               P.
               All thinges néedefull for our ſoules 
                     •
                  or the life to come.
            
            
               M.
               What are they?
            
            
               P.
               Firſt that our fayth may increaſeLuke 17. 
                        •
                     . 2. Pet. 3. 1
                        •
                     . Pſal. 32. 5. and grow more &amp; more in Ieſus Chriſt, 
                     •
                  hat we may alwayes féele in our con
                  
                     •
                  iences, the remiſſion and frée forgiue
                  
                     •
                  eſſe of our ſinnes.
            
            
               M.
               Why doth Chriſt adde, As we forgiue them their treſpaſſes?
               
            
            
               P.
               Becauſe we ſhoulde neuer preſumeMar. 6. 14. 1
                        •
                     
                     ▪
                   
                  
                     •
                  o aſke forgiuenes of God, except we can 
                     •
                  réely forgiue others whiche haue anie 
                     •
                  ay offended vs.
            
            
               M.
               What is ye laſt for: And lead vs not?
               
            
            
               P.
               That GOD woulde not giue vs o
                  
                     ••
                  erIude. 24. Rom. 8. 13. Gal. 5. 16. 17. Ia. 4. 7. 1. Pe. 5. 8. 9. 1. Theſ. 5. 23. to our owne luſtes, and the temptations of Satan, but ſtrengthen vs with his holie ſpirit alwaies to ſtriue againſt them: &amp; that he would preſerue and kepe vs from all their euill.
            
            
               M.
               Where haue you learned theſe principall pointes of Chriſtian religion?Pſal 19. 7. 
                        •
                     . 119. 
                        •
                     . &amp; 105 Eſa. 8. 10. Iohn. 5. 
                        ••
                     .
               
            
            
               P.
               Out of the word of God.
            
            
               M.
               By what meanes?
            
            
               
               P.
               By hearing i
                     •
                   preach
                     ••
                  , 
                     〈…〉
                  
                  Rom. 10. 14. 1. Cor. 1. 
                        ••
                     . Actes. 17. 
                        ••
                     . 
                  
                     ••
                  ſe exercizing myſelf
                     •
                   in the ſame.
            
            
               M.
               Wil this knowlege thē 
                  
                     〈…〉
                   you
            
            
               P.
               No: but I muſt increaſe 
                     〈…〉
                   goHeb. 
                        ••
                     2. 
                        •
                     
                     ▪ 
                     
                        •
                     e
                        •
                     . 2. 2. 
                        •
                     . Ti. 3. 14 15. Mat. 24. 13. forward by the ſame exerciſe of ye 
                  
                     〈…〉
                  or of GOD, to my liues end, if I make at 
                     ••
                  mpt of my ſaluation.
            
            
               M.
               God graunt you ſo to doe.1. Cor. 1. 8. 9. Phil. 1. 6.
               
            
            
               P.
               Amen.
            
            
               
            
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

