
   
      
         
            A vvork vvorth the reading VVherein is contayned, fiue profitable and pithy questions, very expedient, aswell for parents to perceiue howe to bestowe their children in marriage, and to dispose their goods at their death: as for all other persons to receiue great profit by the rest of the matters herein expressed. Newly published by Charles Gibbon.
            Work worth the reading
            Gibbon, Charles, fl. 1589-1604.
         
         
            
               1591
            
         
         Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01685
            STC 11821
            ESTC S101910
            99837713
            99837713
            2053
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01685)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2053)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 296:03)
         
         
            
               
                  A vvork vvorth the reading VVherein is contayned, fiue profitable and pithy questions, very expedient, aswell for parents to perceiue howe to bestowe their children in marriage, and to dispose their goods at their death: as for all other persons to receiue great profit by the rest of the matters herein expressed. Newly published by Charles Gibbon.
                  Work worth the reading
                  Gibbon, Charles, fl. 1589-1604.
               
               [8], 60 p.   
               
                  Imprinted by Thomas Orwin: and are to be solde by Henry Kyrkham, dwelling at the little north doore of S. Pauls Church, at the signe of the Blacke Boy,
                  London :
                  1591.
               
               
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Conduct of life --  Early works to 1900.
               Parent and child --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-01
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-01
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-04
            Celeste NgSampled and proofread
         
            2007-04
            Celeste NgText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A
VVork vvorth the
Reading.
            VVherein is contayned, fiue profitable
and pithy Questions, very expedient,
aſwell for Parents to perceiue
howe to beſtowe their Children in
marriage, and to diſpoſe their
goods at their death: as for all
other Perſons to receiue
great profit by the reſt
of the matters herein
expreſſed.
            Newly publiſhed by Charles Gibbon.
            
            The wiſdome of a man commeth by vſing well his vacant
time, and he that ceaſeth from his owne matters
and labour, may come by wiſdome.
            Eccleſ. 38. 24.
            LONDON
Imprinted by Thomas Orwin: and
are to be ſolde by Henry Kyrkham, dwelling
at the little North doore of S.
Pauls Church, at the ſigne of
the Blacke Boy.
1591.
         
         
            
            
            To the Right Worſhipfull, Sir
Nicholas Bacon Knight: long life in
proſperitie, with endles ioye by
Mortalitie.
            
               
                  IAakob could not beare the
vnkindenes of Laban, but
departed from him: Dauid
could not ſuffer the diſcurteſie
of Hanun, but attempted
warre. The Heathen Man
made a Lawe to puniſh vnthankful
perſons with death:
And Salomon ſaith, Hee that rewardeth euill for
good, euill ſhall neuer depart from his houſe. Theſe
examples and ſayings (right Worſhipfull) although
they be manifest in many to practiſe, they be impertinent
in this place to repeate; for I feare no ingratitude
for my goodwill, though I merit diſpleaſure
for my preſumption. But where the Vnicorne drinketh
all infection is driuen away, where the Beare
breatheth no other beastes will feede, where lenitie
harboreth no miſliking can happen. It was boldlie
done of Sinaetaes to offer Cyrus a handfull of water,
or of the Perſian to giue Artaxerxes the like;
they being beggers by abilitie, thoſe being Kinges
by calling, and the preſents farre vnfit for Princes.
Yet their willingnes in accepting, did bewray the
worthines of their calling: for as the tree is known

by the frute, the golde by the touch, the bell by the
ſound: euen ſo is a mans birth by his beneuolence, his
honour by his humilitie, his calling by his curteſie, and
indeede true Gentillitie ſhould obſerue one thing by
the Lark, which although he mounts neuer ſo high in
the ayre, yet hee buildeth his neſt very lowe on the
earth. I preſume with theſe poore men to offer a
booke no better worth than their water, and I hope
by the curteſie of theſe kings your worſhip will accept
of it as it is, meaſuring the matter by the mulberie,
which will euer bee red though it bee not ripe, but if
the tree be full of bloſſomes and beare not, we commonly
impute the fault to the rygorous weather, and
not to the roote, and if my booke carry a great ſhew
without ſubſtāce, I truſt your VVorſhip wil attribute
the defect to my ignorance and not to my beneuolence:
for hee that diggeth in the coale-pit woulde
worke in minerall if he might, and he that bloweth
the fire would faſhion the iuell if he could, the twigg
muſt haue much time to grow ere it be great, and I
more libertie to practiſe, ere I be perfect: All men
write not according to their learning, but their
leaſure, Apelles drew the picture of Venus in the
beginning very rude, by continuance very rare, ſo
he that at the firſt by his attempts appeares ſimple, at
length may proue ſingular, Demoſthenes did mend
his ſtammering with much ſtriuing against the hil,
and ſo ſhall I my learning with more labour in ſtudy,
yet he that carrieth morter though he be no maſon,
is not to be blamed becauſe he furthereth the building;
neither is he that ſhewes his diligence, though
he cannot doe well, to be reprehended, becauſe of his

good diſpoſitiō: we miſlike not the Taylor, ſo he can
mend where he maketh a fault in the garment, neither
ought any to diſcourage that Author, ſo he may
correct, where he comitteth an eſcape in his writing,
conſidering what difference there is betweene cutting
with the hand, and conceiuing with the head:
But I hope your VVorſhip (in whome the pure word
of GOD is planted) will carrie Moecenas minde, to
further and fauour aſwell the forward as the famous
writers, and then ſhall my Treatiſe, though it bee
ſimple haue good ſucceſse: it ſufficeth me although it
be but barbarous, that it hath beene allowed by my
betters, or whatſoeuer it be, ſo it be well accepted of
your VVorſhip, I craue no other rewarde, than your
patronage of this enterpriſe though it be ſimple, and
your pardon for my good will if I offend. Thus being
loth to trouble your worſhip with many
words, referring the ouerſight hereof to
your graue cenſure, humbly ſubmitting
my ſelfe to your curteſie, I
commit the tuition of your
W. to the Almighty.
            
               Your VVorſhips to commaund,
CHARLES GIBBON.
            
         
         
            
            To the indifferent Reader.
            
               I Was in a doubt after I had finiſhed
this treatiſe, whether I
ſhould publiſh it, or pull it a
peeces, I thought it too baſe
to bee read, and better worth
than to rende, but ſeeing I
haue beſtowed ſome paines in
the pēning, I meane to hazard
my hap in the printing, hee
ſhall write well that can ſatiſfie all, and he as bad that can
pleaſe none, if Chriſt could not content al, being a God,
it is no maruaile wee miſlike many, being but men; In
times paſt they did not care how plaine a thing were, ſo
it were profitable, and now we force not how bad it be, ſo
it be pleaſant, it is this that maketh ſo many writers imploy
their time more wantonly than wiſelie, becauſe
they ſee a vaine trifle is more accepted thā a diuine treatiſe.
If it bee ſo, that thoſe bookes which are moſt light
are beſt liked, and thoſe men that employ their learning
to leuitie, are moſt laudable, then the tenor will but impaire
the title of my booke: for it will not be worth the
reading: but (good Reader) thou muſt obſerue in writing,
the manner of it according to the matter, wee muſt
not paynt the Scriptures with ſuperfluous ſpeaches, as
men doo their owne fictions after their fancies: for the
maieſtie of the word requireth modeſty in the wrter,
this is not vnlike that gem Chalazias, which will be cold
though it be caſt in the fire or the Chorall, which is beſt
without colouring, thoſe be like water which is apt to any
coulour as it hath courſe, or the Camelion which

wil change it ſelf into any hewe it beholds, but this I am
ſure, there is none can afford ſo fruitefull a phraſe as the
Bible, though they practiſe neuer ſo fine tearmes in
their bookes; I ſpeak this not to that end I would gloſe
to get credit by my words, or to diſgrace thoſe that deſerue
it by their workes, but to ſhew what difference
there is betweene a pleaſant ſtory (which wee may handle
according to our humors) and a graue diſcourſe
(which muſt be penned according to the platforme.)
Well ſeeing my former attempts haue found ſuch fauour,
my care ſhall bee the leſſe for the latter, for this I
knowe, that the enuious will ſpite, bee a thing neuer ſo
ſpeciall, the flatterer will ſooth, be it neuer ſo ſimple, the
idle will inuay, be they neuer ſo ignorant, and there are
ſome will finde fault, be they neuer ſo fooliſh; (were not
he a wiſe man could ſtop al their mouthes?) but my meaning
is not to ſatiſfie ſuch readers which bee rude, but
reaſonable, not the curious but the curteous, the one
will excuſe and couer a fault with diſcretion, the
other will but carpe and cauill without
cauſe: ſo farwell. Bury S. Edmond
in Suffolke.
            
            
               Yours
Charles Gibbon.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            Whether the Election of the Parents
is to be preferred before the affection
of their Children in Marriage.
            The Speakers are

                  Philogus.
                  Tychicus.
               
Two louers of Learning.
            
               Philogus
               THere is an olde verſe which retaines
his olde vertue being as credible for
antiquitie as trueth,
               It is this;

                     When Adam dig'd and Eue ſpan
                     who was then a Gentleman?
                     Then came a rich churle and gathered good,
                     and ſo came in the gentle bloud.
                  
Wherein appeares that the ground of gentillity began
with goods: for (as the wiſeman ſaith) haue not
all men one entrance into life and a like going out. Sap. 7.
6. are we not equall by creation, heires by adoption,
brothers by profeſsion, and yet it is a ſtrange thing
to ſee what preciſenes of Petigrees, and difference
of blouds there is amongſt vs, the dayes haue been,
that Kings would beſtowe their daughters vppon
plaine men, and yet thought it no diſparagement of
bloud, as Saul, who beſtowed his daughter Michol
1. Sam. 18. 27. vpon Dauid being but a ſimple ſhepheard;
that Lords would haue matched their ſonnes
with meane mens daughters, and yet account it no

blemiſh to their birth, as Sechem the ſonne of Hemor,
who ioyned with Dinah, the daughter of Iaakob,
he was a Lords ſonne that ruled a whole Countrie,
Gen. 34. 1, 2. ſhe, a plaine mans daughter that
dwelt in tents, Gen. 25. 27. The time was when
rich men would haue taken poore women to their
wiues, and yet neuer made any reſpect of their portions,
as Boaz did Ruth, he was a man of great authoritie
and riches. Ruth 2. 1. as ſome thinke iudge of
Iſrael Iudg. 12. 8. ſhe, a poore woman, that glened vpon
his land for her liuing. But now it is no match
amongſt vs, where the parties be not anſwerable in
birth, and agreeable in abilities, where indeede the
beſt gentilitie conſiſt in pietie, and the moſt wealth
in contentment.
               I thought good to vſe this preamble for this purpoſe.
There is olde Cleanthes an auncient Gentlemā,
who is adorned aſwell with the affluencie of fortune,
for great poſſeſsiōs, as with the excellencie of
Nature, for good properties; he hath amongſt many
children but one daughter (yet a ſiſter to euery
ſonne,) this mayde is very deſirous to marrie, and
hath made her choyce of ſuch a one, as is both of a
goodly compoſition of bodie, and of a godly diſpoſition
of minde. Yet as hee is proper and well diſpoſed,
ſo he is very poore, inſomuch as her father by
reaſon of the baſenes of his linage, and barenes of
his liuing, will not allow of her liking, but hath appoynted
her another, which both by parentage and
portion may counteruaile her calling and his contentment,
yet nothing anſwerable to his daughters
deſire, becauſe for his yeares hee may rather bee her

father than her husband, which as he cannot be the
firſt, ſo he is ſo farre from the latter that ſhe will rather
be martyred than married to him, now in this
caſe whether is the affection of the childe to be preferred
before the election of the father.
            
            
               Tichi.
               You produce your preamble (as it ſeemeth)
to impugne and reprooue ſuch as (vpon circumſtances
of parentage and poſſeſsions) will permit
or prohibit marriage, and therefore before I anſwere
your propoſition, I will ſay ſomewhat to
your proteſtatiō. You bring an olde verſe to proue
that gentilitie began with goods. Indeede goods in
theſe dayes adde a grace to many, yet gentry hath
not his beginning all of one ground. Some haue
been baſe borne, yet came to great eſtimation, not
by their poſſeſsions, but by their valiant exploytes,
as Iphtah, being ſonne of a harlot: Iudg. 11. 1. became
Iudge of Iſrael. Iudg. 12. 7. Others haue been poore,
and yet came to great promotion, not for their
wealth, but their wiſdome; as Ioſeph who being an
abiect of his brethren, Gen. 37. 4. became fellow to
king Pharaoh, and was made gouernour ouer all
Aegipt Gen. 41. 40. and in theſe dayes amongſt vs,
many come to preferment, not for their liuing, but
learning, not by progeny but prowes, not by deſert,
but diſcent: notwithſtāding I affirme your ſayings
that as touching the bare birth, a king hath no better
beginning than a beggar, or in reſpect of the ordinary
ende, the Prince hath no priueledge aboue the
poore; for as both proceede from a woman, ſo both
ſhall feede the wormes; yet that followeth not although
all be made of one mettall, none ſhould bee

more excellent in maieſtie, or albeit none be noble
by nature, any ſhould not be renowmed by calling:
for as many differ in degrees of dignity, ſo according
to their title and authoritie they are to be preferred,
and what renowne the predeceſſor dooth purchaſe
by his life, it diſcendeth by ſucceſsion to his poſteritie
after him. You proceed further &amp; ſay, that kings
would beſtow their children vpon plaine men, and
for proofe you bring in Sauls daughter and Dauid?
this example nothing auaileth: for Dauid had her,
not by interceſsion, but vpon condition, if hee had
not ſlaine Goliah he had gone without her, 1. Sam. 17.
25. Yet are you aduiſed of Dauids anſwer after hee
ſhould haue her, What am I (ſaith he) and what is my
life, or the familie of my father in Iſrael, that I ſhould be
ſonne in Lawe to the King. 1. Sam. 18. 18. Herein hee
doth ſhewe his vnworthines to match with ſuch a
mans daughter (I meane for petigree, not for piety)
&amp; this argueth that in thoſe daies they had a ſpeciall
reſpect of parentage? And Lords (ſay you) would
match with meane mens childrē, &amp; for this you infer
Shechem and Dinah; you muſt note, although he
were a Lords ſonne he plaid a leaud part to deflower
her, &amp; therefore no doubt it was the filthines of the
fact that forced him to marrie her. Yea &amp; rich men
(ſay you) would take poore women to their wiues,
as Boaz did Ruth, ſtill you ſtriue againſt the ſtreame,
for Boaz was hir kinſeman, &amp; therefore was to take
her by the title of affynity according to Gods law as
it was commanded. If bretheren dwel together, &amp; one
of them die &amp; haue no ſonne, (as ſhe had not) the wife of
the dead ſhall not marrie to a ſtranger, but his kinſeman
                  
                  ſhall goe in to her and take her to wife, and doe the kinſmans
office to her. Deut. 25. 5, 6, 7. So that your preamble
is impertinent: for where parties be matched
equally according to their birth and abilities there
is euer beſt agreement. Nowe to your queſtion:
Whether the election of the father is to bee preferred before
the affection of the childe. This is as eaſie to anſwere
as to aske: The ten commandements teach
children to honour and ſubmit themſelues to their
parents, therfore if they cōtract &amp; couple cōtrary to
their contentatiō, they rather rebell thā obay them.
            
            
               Phi.
               It is true indede but you know the common
by word, It is the eye of the maiſter, that fatteth the
horſe, and the loue of the mayd that maketh the liking,
ſhee that matcheth her ſelfe after anothers
mind, is like him that fitteth his foote by anothers
laſt: one is oftē wroong with his ſhooes in the wearing,
the other oftē vexed with her husband after
wedding, either let vs linck to our owne liking or
elſe better vnborne, than liuing.
            
            
               Tich.
               Your talke tendeth only to ſenſuall circumſtances
altogether prepoſterous frō the propoſition:
for the word of God hath giuen parents great prerogatiue
ouer their children, euen in this matter
concerning Marriage; inſomuch as no contract
(much leſſe any coniunction) can bee lawful vnleſſe
the parents allow it, according as it is written. If a
woman vowe a vowe vnto the Lorde and binde her ſelfe
by a bonde being in her Fathers houſe in the time of
her youth, and her Father heare her vow &amp; bond wherwith
ſhe hath bound her ſelfe, and her Father holde his
peace concerning her, then all her vowes ſhall stand, and
                  
                  euerie bond wherewith ſhe hath bound hir ſelfe ſhall ſtand.
But if her father diſallowe her the ſame daye that he heareth
all her vowes and bonds wherewith ſhe hath bound
her ſelfe, they ſhall not be of value, and the Lord will forgiue
her: becauſe her father diſſalowed her. Nomb. 30. 4▪
5, 6.Hereof it is that where the maide was taken away
and abuſed, albeit ſhee was afterward married
to the man that did it, yet hee was to pay a peece of
money to her father, becauſe he had not his preconſent,
as it is written, If a man intice a maide that is not
betroathed and lie with her, he ſhall endowe her and take
her to his wife, If her father refuſe to giue her to him, hee
ſhall pay mony according to the Dowry of Virgins. Exod.
22. 16, 17. It is more fullie confirmed in Deuter. 22.
28, 29. If a man finde a maide that is not betroathed, and
take her and lye with her and they bee found, Then the
man that lay with her, ſhall giue vnto the maides father
fiftie Shekels of ſiluer, and ſhe ſhall be his wife, becauſe hee
hath humbled her, he cannot put her away all his life, yea
Saint Paul himſelfe dooth approoue the ſuperioritie
of Parents in this reſpect, for (ſaith he) If any man
thinke that it is vncomely for his Virgine, if ſhe paſſe the
flower of her age, and neede ſo require let him doo what
he will, he ſinneth not: let them be married, 1. Cor. 7. 36.
And hereto agreeth the ſame ſaying of the wiſe
man, Marrie thy daughter, and ſo thou ſhalt performe
a waightie worke. Eccleſ. 30. I coulde amplifie the
matter very much, but theſe are ſufficient to reſolue
you, that children cannot match without their Parents
conſent.
            
            
               Phi.
               Alas, you doo not conſider the innumerable
inconueniences that bee incident to thoſe parties

which bee brought together more for lucre than
loue, more for goods than good will, more by conſtraint
than conſent, nay more than that, you doe little
way the inequalitie of yeares, the contrarietie of
natures betweene age and youth, is there no difference
betweene the withered Beech and the floriſhing
Bay tree, no oppoſition betweene froſt and
flowers, or is it poſsible that oxen vnequally yoked
ſhould draw well together? if you would conferr al
theſe circumſtances together with the accidents
you ſhal find that ſuch an husband, is an hell to a tender
Virgine, and that ſuch a marriage, is the beginning
of al miſerie, and no doubt he that beſtows his
daughter no better, ſhall abridge her griefe, by following
her to the graue. So that I conclude, ſeeing
marriage is of great moment, not for a moneth
but a whole life time, there is no reaſon, but hee
or ſhee that entreth into that bond, ſhould make
their owne bargaine: becauſe it is they that muſt abide
by it.
            
            
               Tich.
               You ſtill continue your carnall poſitions, to
confirme your craſed opinion, as though the preſcript
rule of Gods book, where to be impugned by
the naturall reaſon of mans brayne. If a man may
giue his goods to whome hee will, hee may as well
beſtow his Children where hee thinketh beſt, for
Children are the goods of the Parēts? So it ſeemeth
by that which God himſelfe ſaide to Sathan, when
he earneſtly deſired to deale with Iob, All that hee
hath (ſaith the Lord) be in thy handes. Iob. 1. 12. If you
looke into the olde law, you ſhall finde that Parents
might ſell their Children to ſupplie their neceſsity,

as appeare in Exod. 21. 7. If a man ſell his daughter to
be a ſeruant &amp;c. Laban did little better than make a
benefit of his daughters before he beſtowed them:
For by Iaacobs ſeruitude it appeareth he made a ſale
of them, and ſo they could ſay themſelues afterward.
Gen. 31. 15. Therefore if Parents had this
great priuiledge then (which is almoſt importable)
why ſhould they bee barred of this benefite now,
not in ſelling but in beſtowing them (which is ſo
reaſonable) you alleadge it is good reaſon they
ſhould make their own bargaine, becauſe they muſt
abide it; as though parents would ſeeke the preiudice
of their owne children, but what libertie of liking
had Leah to Iaakob, who inſtead of her ſiſter
Rahel was brought to his bed, Gen. 29. 23. This argueth
that parents would diſpoſe their children at
their pleaſure.
            
            
               Phi.
               I perceiue by your ſpeech you ſo much preferre
the parents, that you altogether enioyne their
children to an inconuenience; that is, not to match
to their own liking but as their parents liſt, as thogh
they ought not to ſhew aſwell a fatherly affection,
as they looke for filiall obedience.
            
            
               Tich.
               You miſtake both the matter and my meaning,
for albeit parents ought to yeeld their conſent
to their childrens choyce, yet they haue no power
to prouoke them to marry, if neceſſitie vrgeth not,
hereof ſayth Paul. He that ſtandeth firme in his heart
that he hath no neede, but hath power ouer his owne will,
and hath ſo decreed in his heart that hee will keepe his
Virgin he doth well. 1. Cor. 7. 37. neither may they depriue
them of that remedie if they cannot liue continent,

                  for it is better to marry than burne. ibid. verſ 9
nay more then that, the parents muſt preſently prouide
for them as a duetie enioyned to them, which
the ſame Apoſtle prooueth in theſe wordes, Let
them be married 1. Cor. 7. 36. neither may they inforce
thē to any match, if their children miſlike; we
haue example thereof in Rebecca, for when the ſeruant
(who ſhould haue her) whome Abraham ſent
was requeſted that ſhe might remaine ten dayes before
their departure, his expedition was ſuch that
he had rather goe away without her, than tarry to
take her: whervpon her parents called her, to aske
her conſent, and to know whether ſhee would goe
with that man or no, her anſwer was, ſhee would:
Gen. 24. 27. &amp;c. this argueth that parents muſt not
vſe any coaction, where their children haue no
diſpoſition to the partie.
            
            
               Phi.
               Yet all this is to no purpoſe to the queſtion
I propoſe, for the maid neither meaneth to liue ſingle
as a Virgin, yet ſhe cannot bee ſuffered to match
to her minde, as ſhe would doe: nowe in this caſe
whether may the peruerſitie of the parents hinder
the choyce of the childe?
            
            
               Tich.
               It is needeleſſe to adde a double anſwere
to a ſingle queſtion, or to demaund a reaſon where
there is no doubt, your word peruerſitie, is ſo termed
of the wilfull, but it is taken for prudencie amongſt
the wiſe; for they know that it is the propertie
of parents, not to deale frowardly but fatherly
with their children, and to beſtow them not as
they deſire, without diſcreſion; but as is moſt expedient;
with circumſpection: but admit, that Parents

be ſometime peruerſe, ſhall children bee pernicious,
or (as wee commonly ſay) driue out one
nayle with another? God forbid, they muſt win thē
by peticion, not prouocation; by obedience, not obſtinacie.
The parents ioy depend vpon their children,
and therefore their euill placing, turne to
their diſpleaſure, did not Eſau by taking wiues, cō
                  trary
to his fathers will, procure his ſorrowe, inſomuch
as his mother ſayd, It ſhould not auaile her to
liue if his Brother Iaacob did beſtow himſelfe ſo, Gen. 27.
46. let then the example of Eſau dehort the diſobedient
which care more to pleaſe their fancies,
than their fathers, and let Iaacob be an imitation to
the dutifull, which preferre their fathers precept,
before their own pleaſure: and to reſolue you more
fully I will ſhew ſome apparrant examples that ſhall
approoue the ſubmiſsiō of children to their parents
in this reſpect; Sechem, the ſonne of a Lorde hauing
deflowred Dinah, although (by reaſon of the
filthynes of the fact) it was more time for him
to marry the mayde, than to motion the matter,
yet before hee woulde marry hee craued his fathers
good will, as appeareth in the text for it is
there ſaid, He ſaid to his father Hamer, get me this
mayde to wife, Gen. 34. 1, &amp;c. If the conſent of Parents
was obſerued as a principle amongſt the very
Infidels, how much more ought wee to bee carefull
of it that be Chriſtians▪ 
                  Sampſon was Iudge of
Iſrael, and a ſtrong and valiant man, yet falling in
loue with Dalilah hee did not ſatisfie his luſt without
his fathers liking: for he ſayde to his Father,

                  Giue mee her to wife. Iudg. 14. 2. Ruth was content
to bee ruled by Naomi her mother in lawe, yea
euen in this matter concerning her marriage. Ruth.
3. 5. then how much more ought we to ſubmit our
conſents to our naturall parents? Many ſuch examples
I could inſert, but theſe may ſatisfie a ſenſible
man in a reaſonable matter.
            
            
               Phi.
               I haue permitted your ſperch hitherto, not
becauſe I could not preuent your Apologie, but
that I was deſirous to learne what you could alleadge;
and now I plainely ſee, that a fearce ſtreame
hath no ſtay, if it be not ſtopped in time, nor your
arguments an ende, if they be not intercepted; to
the matter, I confeſſe that children are commaunded
to obey their Parents, yet I affirme they muſt
not in many things approoue their proceedings, for
their limites are preſcribed, They muſt obey them in
the Lord: for this is right, (ſaith Paul) Epheſ. 6. 1. if parents
wil prouoke their children to marry with Infidels
they may not: for they haue no warrāt by the
word of God. 2. Cor. 6. 14.
            
            
               Tich.
               Yet the ſame Apoſtle ſaith, The vnbeleeuing
husband is ſanctified by the beleeuing wife, and the vnbeleeuing
wife is ſanctified by the husband. 1. Cor. 7. 14.
What ſay you to this?
            
            
               Philog.
               I thought by taking your riſe ſo raſhly
you woulde leape ſhorte: for there are three things
to bee obſerned which you ouerſlipped in thoſe
words, the cauſe that prouoked him: 1. the perſons
he reſpected; 2. the end he aymed at; 3. the cauſe that
prouoked him was to anſwere an obiectiō againſt
ſuch as thought that the godly ſhoulde bee defiled

by the ſocietie of the wicked, which he contrarieth
in the ſame chapt. verſ. 14. the perſons he reſpected,
were ſuch as were ſo already contracted, to preuēt
thoſe that vnder that pretence might take occaſion
purpoſely to ſeperate thēſelues, which we may gather
by the 15. verſe. the ende he chiefly aymeth at,
was to premoniſh the vnmarried not to match in
that manner as apeareth in the 2. Cor. 6. 14. 15. Bee not
(ſaith he) vnequally yoaked with Infidels: then hee
ſheweth a reaſon, for what fellowſhip hath righteouſneſſe
with vnrighteouſnes, &amp; what communion hath light
with darkneſſe, and what concord hath Chriſt with Belial,
or what parte hath the beleeuer with the Infidel? So
hauing aunſwered your obiection, I will iterate
where you interrupted me: As children may not
intercommon with Infidels, ſo their parents may
not vrge them to match with Idolators, or ſuch like
becauſe it is prohibyted.
            
            
               Tich.
               And yet it is nothing reſpected in theſe
dayes, for in mariages amongſt vs, we make no regarde
of godlines, but goods, of righteouſnes, but
riches, how well, but how welthy, they be made: be
he Atheiſt, be he Papiſt, be he Newter, we reſpect
not the man, but his money, not his life, but his liuing,
not his profeſsion, but his promotion; and
therefore I ſee no reaſon, but that they may deale
with Idolators. The Iſraelites a choſen people of
God did intercouenant with the Gentiles which
were great Idolators. Iudg. 3. 6. Salomon that prudent
king tooke the daughter of king Pharaoh. 1. King. 3.
1. &amp; Dauid that holy mā, matched with the daughter
of king Saul, yet Pharaoh and Saul were groſſe Idolaters.
            
            
               
               Phi.
               I ſee you ſtriue to wring water out of the
pomice, or elſe you would neuer waſte the time
with ſuch wordes, doth it follow becauſe moſt in
marriage haue regarde of goods, that I by their example
ſhould impaire Gods glory, why wee are
taught, not to follow a multitude in euill. Did the
Iſraelites intercouenant with the Gentiles? why
they did contrary to the commaundement of God:
Deut. 7. 3. Yet the Lord did not let them paſſe vnpuniſhed.
Iudg. 3. 8. Did Salomon marrie an Idolatrous
wife? why he was drawen to Idolatrie by them, &amp;
what followed; he incurred the wrath of God for
his wickedneſſe. 1. King. 11. 14. As for that act of
Dauid it cannot animate vs, ſeeing the example of
diuers may deterre vs, neither is it expedient for any
to preſume of Gods power, without his will.
Now hauing anſwered your digreſſion, I will proceede
where I left, I ſay ſtill, that the glory of God
not the motions of men, his praiſe not their practiſes
are to be preferred in euerie thing, as in this matter
concerning marriage; we ought indeede to obay
our earthly parents, yet we muſt not diſhonour
one eternall father, for we are taught by the Apoſtle
Peter to obay God more than man. Act. 5. 29. Wee
ought to loue our worldly parents, yet we muſt not
offēd our heauēly father: for, He that loueth father &amp;
mother more thā me is not worthy of me, (ſaith Chriſt)
Mat. 10. 37. we ought to feare our natural parents,
that haue gouernment of our bodies, yet wee muſt
be more afraide of our celeſtiall Father, which preſerues
both bodie and ſoule, and is able to caſt them
into hell fire Mat. 10. 28. whereupon I ground my

argument, that if Parents will profer and impoſe
vpon their children ſuch a match as tendeth more
to profite, than pietie, more to content their greedy
deſire for lucre, thā their childrens godly choice
for loue, as this man hath doon to his daughter, neyther
they nor this mayde ought to depend on their
Parents in this poynt: what greater occaſion of
incontinencie can be giuen, than to match a young
and luſty maid againſt her owne minde, with an infirme
and decrepite perſon to ſatisfie an others pleaſure?
what a croſſe contract would this be? and ſhall
not the maide (who hath made a fit choyce to her
owne minde) marry, vnleſſe ſhe take ſuch an old mā,
againſt her minde? what ſay you, ſhal the ſeuerity of
of her Father abridge her liberty, or depriue her of
the lawfull remedy? Nay more than that, ſhall the
maide increaſe in ſin for want of her deſire, becauſe
her father wil not yeeld his conſent, vnleſſe it bee to
her diſliking? I ſay no. The Apoſtle telleth vs, It is
better to marrie than burne, and yet ſhe ſhall keepe her
within the bounds of obedience, becauſe ſhe doth it
not of purpoſe in cōtempt of her parents, but in regarde
of Gods glory to auoyd the occaſion of euill.
            
            
               Tich.
               Indeede I muſt needes cōfeſſe that to match
a young maide with an olde man, it is miſerable:
nay then that which is more admirable, ſome man
that hath liued ſingle aboue ſixtie yeares, will (vpon
a little fleſhly fancie) needes to the world; yet he wil
ſooner angle for a frogge than a fiſh; I meane, he wil
ſooner catch a light miniō, thā couple with a graue
matron, and as the worlde doth wonder at him for
his wantonnes, in making ſuch a match, ſo his kindred

which did hope to haue good of him, are deceiued
by this meanes: for he will ſo much reſpect
the trifling tricks of his Coſſet, that he wil not care
to caſt off the tried loue of his kindred, whom of a
lōg time he hath put in hope of ſome great promotion
by his death (which no doubt by their duety
&amp; diligence they haue deſerued) and at laſt doth recompence
them with this deluſion, by his life to
giue all to his young wife, fie vpon fleſh that rageth
ſo furiouſly, &amp; of men that haue no more modeſty,
&amp; of age that yeelds no better grauitie (for the grace
of man conſiſts not in proportiō, but properties; nor
the glory of age in gray haires, but in grauitie. The
dayes haue bin that men would not haue their poſſesſions
go out of the name, Ruth 4. 5. but theſe accompt
more of their filthy pleaſure, thā their poſteritie;
Moſes made a law in Iſrael, that he that had no
iſſue, ſhould giue his inheritance to ſuch as were of
his conſanguinitie, for faile of ſuch, to ſome of his
affinitie: Nombr. 27. 8. &amp;c. but theſe doe more regarde
their greedy luſt, than a godly law. Wee
ſhall reade in the olde Teſtament that they might
not ſell any parcell of their poſſeſsions from their
Kindred: Ruth▪
                   4. Then with what conſcience may
theſe giue all away from them? Good GOD
what a ſtraunge thing is this, that thoſe which
goe holding downe their heads as though they
woulde droppe into their graues, ſhoulde bee caſting
vp their eyes a doting after girles, when it
were more meeter for them to make a couenāt with
death, than a contract with a damſel: but it ſeemeth
ſuch haue liued longer for their yeares, than their

vertues, that neither the decrepitie of their age,
nor the imbecilitie of their bodies, can bridle their
concupiſence, but they muſt further their infirmities
by their owne follies; the young fleſh of Abiſhah
(ſay they) did foſter Dauid in his age, this giueth
a great light to their leuitie, as though Dauid would
make his deathbed, a place of beaſtlynes, when the
text ſaith He knew her not. 1. King. 1. 4. and to couer
their dotage, they will carry this cloake for an excuſe,
It is better to marry than burne (as though rottē
wood could take fire ſo faſt), It is lawfull for them
to marry I confeſſe, yet not expediēt to match with
moathers, the original of ſuch a marriage is grounded
vpon no goodnes; for he taketh her vpō a burning
vnbridled luſt, ſhe him vpon a leaud deſire of
liuing, the ſight of ſuch nuptials are ridiculous, for
who ſees them that in deriſion will not ſay, the old
horſe hath got him a yoūg fillie, the ſucces of ſuch
a cōtract is ſorrowfull: for there is no greater rage
than the ielouſie of man (ſaith Salomon) Pro. 6. 34. it
is as cruel as death Cant. 8. 6. and who can bee more
ielous thā an olde man ouer his yoūg wife: the end
of ſuch a vniting is but euill, for imbecilitie and debilitie
is a meane to cauſe his wiues inconſtancie.
Then what reaſon ſhould moue the olde man to
make ſuch a match, or what maid well diſpoſed
will match with ſuch a man, my reaſon is: It is not
ſufficient for vs to doe well, but therwith to auoyd
the occaſion of euill, although ſhee bee of an honeſt
conuerſation, yet the taking of ſuch an olde huddle,
will giue occaſion to the worlde to iudge the
worſt.
            
         
         
            
            VVhether the Father may lawfully
diſinherit his first borne.
            
               PHilogus.
               Children (no doubt) are a great bliſſing
of God, &amp; happy are thoſe that haue them
to increaſe his kingdome. What ioye conceiued
Elizabeth vvhen ſhe found herſelf to be cō
                  ceaued
with childe, Luk. 1. 15? for barrennes was a
great reproach among the Iewes. How ioyful was
Hannah when ſhe had a childe? for ſhe was but vpbraided
afore for her barrennes. 1. Sam. 1. 5. What
made the daughter of Iphtah deſire two moneths
to goe to the mountaines to bewaile her virginitie
before ſhe died? was it not her barrennes? for it was
counted as a ſhame in Iſrael to die without children.
Iudg. 11. 38. The Grecian women accompted
their age, from that day they were Brides, and not
from the day of their birth; for then (ſay they) we
enter the world, when wee haue children to take
charge of. When Rahel had for a time left child-bearing,
ſhe was content to ſuffer her maide Bilhah
to beare vpon her knees, to couer her vnfruitfulnes
as though it came from her, Gen. 30. 3. for barrennes
was counted as a curſe, becauſe fruitfulnes came of
Gods bleſsing, who ſaid, Increaſe and multiplie:
barrennes is a ſigne of diſobedience, for the Lord
hath promiſed to thoſe that feare him, There ſhall
none cast their frute, or be barren. Exod. 23. 26. It
is ſaid, the Lord ſhut vp euery wombe of the houſe
of Abimelech, and why? for a puniſhment of ſinne,
becauſe of Sarah, Gen 20. 18. The barren woman
enioyes not the promiſe, which God made to them

that were maried, to haue iſſue, but principally ſhee
is depriued of that promiſe that God made to Abraham,
that he would increaſe his ſeede. Therfore
let no man lightly eſteeme of children, as many do,
which accompt them rather a charge, than a bliſſing,
a trouble, than a benefit: for, as they bee arguments
of the loue of God, as may appeare in Hannah,
whoſe praier the Lord remembred, 1. Sam. 1.
19. ſo they be meanes to increaſe mutuall loue betweene
man and wife; for after Leah had borne a
ſonne, ſhe was perſwaded her husband would loue
her and keepe her companie, Gen. 29. 32. 34. Notwithſtanding,
as godly children are a great gift of
God, ſo the wicked are a great griefe to the parēts;
one a renowne, the other a reproach to them. Now
manie will ſay, A good tree bringeth foorth good
frute, &amp; ſo condemne the parents, by their childrēs
impietie: but let no man iudge raſhly, for it falleth
out ſometime by men, as in other matters: there are
few trees that beare frute, but haue ſome windfalls;
few gardens that bring forth flowrs, but haue ſome
weeds; few men that haue iſſue, but ſome proue euill.
Noah had Cham aſwell as Sem, Abraham, Iſmael
aſwell as Iſaac, Dauid Abſolom aſwell as Salomō:
yet Noah, Abraham, &amp; Dauid were the children
of God. But I will omit this matter, and manifeſt
my meaning by an example.
               There is one that dwelleth by me, that is verie
wealthie, who hath but three ſonnes to impart his
liuing to, he hath beſtowed great coſt vpon the eldeſt
to preferre him by learning, yet (preſuming of
his patrimonie, as manie rich heires doo in theſe

daies) he is either fooliſh, or vnfortunate, for hee
yeelds in ſteed of wiſedome, wantonnes, for learning
lewdnes, and for obediencie obſtinacie; yea, he
had better haue bin put to Cart than to Cambridge,
ſo he might haue reaped more profite, and haue eaſed
his fathers purſe: but his other two ſonnes hee
hath brought vp with litle coſt, &amp; yet they increaſe
his poſſeſsions by their paines; now this man at his
death doth diſinherite his eldeſt ſonne, that procured
his griefe, and bequeath it to the two yonger
that augmented his gaine. Now in this caſe I demaund
whether he may lawfully diſinherite his eldeſt
ſonne, yea or no.
            
            
               Tych.
               I doo not thinke that the prauitie of his
demeanor, can barre him of the priuiledge of his
dignitie: for the firſt borne were euer moſt to bee
preferred, according as it is written; If a man haue
two wiues, one loued &amp; another hated, &amp; they haue
borne him childrē, both the loued &amp; alſo the hated:
if the first borne be the ſon of the hated, then when
the time commeth that he appointeth his ſons to be
heires of that which he hath, he may not make the ſon
of the beloued firſt born, before the ſon of the hated,
which is the firſt borne, but he shall acknowledge the
ſon of the hated for the first borne, &amp; giue him double
portiō of al that he hath, for he is the first of his
ſtrength, &amp; to him belongeth, &amp;c. Deu 21. 15, 16, 17
            
            
               Phil.
               What dignitie hath the firſt borne aboue
the reſt of his brethren, ſeeing they are al ingendred
in one womb, &amp; proceed al frō one woman, beſide
that law you repeate was litle reſpected: for Abrahā
                  
had children of the hated, before the loued, Gen. 18.
                  
                  4. of his concubines, before his wiues, Gen. 22. 24.
and yet it is ſaid of him, he gaue all his goods to Iſaac,
whom he had by Sarah his wife. Gen. 25. 5.
               
            
            
               Tych.
               If the elder were not to be dignified aboue
his brethren, what mooued the Lord to ſay to Cayne,
that his brother Abels deſire ſhuld be ſubiect
to him, and that he ſhould rule ouer him. Gen. 4. 7?
Yea, what cauſed Iaacob to ſay to Reuben his eldeſt
ſonne, thou art my might and the beginning of my
ſtrength, the excellencie of dignitie, and the excellencie
of power. Gen. 49. 3?
            
            
               Phil.
               But is it not lawfull for a man to giue his
poſſeſsions to whom he pleaſe?
            
            
               Tych.
               Not in all caſes: for it is neither naturall
nor agreeable to Gods word, for a man to giue his
inheritance to a meere ſtranger, hauing both children
and kindred, as it appeareth in the olde Lawe,
where it is written, If a man die &amp; haue no ſonne,
then ye ſhall turne his inheritance to his daughter,
and if he haue no daughter, ye ſhall giue his inheritance
vnto his brethren, &amp; if he haue no brethren,
ye shal giue his inheritāce vnto his fathers brethrē,
&amp; if his father haue no brethren, ye shal giue his inheritaunce
vnto his next kinſeman of his familie,
and hee shall poſſeſſe it. Nombers. 27. 8. &amp;c.
What was Naboths anſwere to King Ahab when
he demaunded to buy his vineyard, The Lord keepe
me (ſaith he) from giuing the inheritance of my father
vnto thee. 1. King. 21. 3. it was this that made
the King not onely to kill him, but (to extinguiſh all
iſſue of inheritance) his ſonnes likewiſe 2. King. 9.
26. Naomi came out of her Countrie of Moab, to

ſell a little parcell of ground at Bethlehem, not becauſe
there was not anie would buy it, but becauſe
ſhe was firſt to profer it to her kindred. Ruth. 4. 3. If
Naomi might not ſell her owne to none but ſuch
as were of her alliance, much more wee ought not
to giue away our owne, from our children and
kinſmen.
            
            
               Phil.
               Indeed, as touching inheritance I hold with
you, yet all be not inheritors by diſcent, but manie
doo purchaſe by the pennie, and gather their goods
by their paines, &amp; therefore what reaſon is there, a
man ſhould not diſpoſe of that at his owne pleaſure?
            
            
               Tych.
               You ſay verie wel, but as there is no cauſe
to conſtraine anie, to giue againſt his will, ſo there
is no conſcience to abridge one of that benefite, he
ſhould enioy by right, A man ſhall doo verie wel to
giue ſeueral portions as he ſeeth cauſe, yet he ought
to reſpect the ſuperioritie of his eldeſt ſon, that he
make him not equall with his brethren, but as he is
better by prioritie of birth, ſo to prefer him by ſufficiencie
of liuing, which as it is moſt charitable by
the courſe of nature, ſo it is beſt tollerable with the
courſe of ſcripture: for it is written in the behalfe
of the firſt borne, Thou shalt giue him double portiō
of all that thou hast. Deu 21. 17. meaning as much as
to two of the others, Iehoshaphat King of Iuda had
manie children, to whome (the text ſaith) hee gaue
great giftes of ſiluer and of golde, and of precious
things with ſtrong Cities in Iuda, but the greateſt
thing of all which was his kingdome, he gaue to
Iehoram: and why? it is there ſaid, becauſe he was
                  
                  the eldeſt. 2. Chro. 21. 3. ſo that the prerogatiue of the
elder, is to be preferred aboue his brethren.
            
            
               Phil.
               Is a man ſo bound to exalt his his eldēſt ſon
of dutie, that he may not prefer others before him,
of deſert? May not the yonger haue preferment by
beneuolence, though the elder hath preheminence
by birth? I ſee no cauſe to the contrarie, becauſe I
haue examples to cōfirme it. Iehoiakim was the eldeſt
ſon of Ioſiah that good king. 1. Chron. 3. 15. yet
Iehoahaz his yonger brother was preferred to the
dignitie royal before him, 2. Kin. 23. 30. Eſau was
the eldeſt ſon of Iſaac, yet Iaacob his yonger brother
got the bleſsing before him: ſo that it is a matter,
not of coactiō but election to prefer the eldeſt.
            
            
               Tych.
               I know not what you may vrge by argument,
but I am ſure your proofes are altogether repugnant,
which vpon examination of your examples
will appeare. For Iehoahaz although he were
preferred to the regall regiment a time before his
brother, it was by the choyce of the people, and not
by conſent of his father, yet he was depoſed from
the place within 3. moneths, and Iehoiakim his eldeſt
brother inſtalled in his ſteade, according to
right. 2. Kin. 23. 30. 34. As for Eſau, there wer three
cauſes, that might lawfully depriue him of his dignitie;
one was his owne greedines in ſelling of his
birthright to his brother Iaacob. Gen. 25. 33. Another
was, his brothers diſsimulation which he practiſed
with his father to get the bliſsing from him.
Gen 27. 19. The third was, the neceſsitie of Gods
prophecie to come to paſſe, that the elder might
ſerue the yonger. Gen. 25. 23. So that all theſe examples

do rather prolong the time to no ende, than approue
your propoſition to be true.
            
            
               Phil.
               Becauſe you both conuince me of the time
for tediouſnes, and of my ſpeeches for prolixitie, I
will cut off manie curious termes, and come briefly
to the matter, and according to my firſt motion
let me common with you in this manner; Is the eldeſt
moſt diſſolute and inclined to euill, and are the
yonger more diligent and forward to thriue? hath
the father beſtowed a great portion of the other to
prefer him by learning, and brought vp theſe hardlie
to take paines for his liuing? is all his coſt caſt away
vpon the other, and haue theſe yet receiued no
profit for their paines? then what reaſon is there,
to tie golde to the girdle of him that is graceles, and
leaue a browne cruſt for them to chew that are wel
giuen? What wiſedome to beſtow abundance on
him that will waſt it, and to leaue ſuch to thriue
with a penie, that will proſper? Are men ſo bound
to prefer the elder of cuſtome, that they will iniure
the yonger without conſcience? No, no, A wiſeman
will alter cuſtome after diſcretion, and diſpoſe
his wealth according to wiſedome, hee will not
leaue his riches to him that is riotous, for hee
knowes full well, that a broken veſſell will holde
no water, that wealth in his fingers, is like waxe aganſt
the fire, one will conſume with much heating,
the other with much handling: hee conſequently
conſidereth, that the leaud lauiſhing of his
liuing after his death, vvill bee an argument to others,
they vvere euill gotten by him ſelfe in his
life, hee vvill therefore make him his heyre, not

which is firſt borne, but beſt inclined, not the eldeſt,
but the excellenteſt, he will (I ſay) giue moſt of
his goods to ſuch a one, as by his owne life, he ſhall
haue foreſight of his forwardnes to liue, and not to
ſuch a one, as hath no regard to be reformed in his
life; yea, hee will make him the better that is moſt
obedient and dutifull to doo him good, this is the
courſe Chriſtians ought to take, and for this they
haue warrant by the word of God, and thus it may
be prooued; Goods are the gift of God, and he hath
appointed vs, not to doo as we liſt with them, like
Lords, but to diſpoſe them well, as his Stewards, &amp;
therefore wee ought to haue a great regard of this,
to beſtowe them on ſuch, where he that gaue them
may be glorified, according to the Apoſtles teaching,
VVhatſouer ye doe (ſaith he) do all to the praiſe
and glorie of God. 1. Cor. 10. 31. If one ſhould giue
his goods to his eldeſt Sonne, that taketh his felicitie
in venurie, voluptuouſnes, or ſuch like, I
would ſuppoſe the gift would be ſo far from Gods
glorie, that it would rather be a meane to maintaine
than reclaime him from ſin: and ſhall he not make
another his heire, which is more worthie, becauſe
he is elder and moſt wayward? Why? Iaacob
was a verie godly man, and had two ſonnes Reuben
&amp; Iudah, Reuben vvas his eldeſt ſonne, yet he gaue
his kingdome to Iudah, Gene. 49. 4. What made
him diſpoſſeſſe his firſt borne of his priuiledge and
Kingly honour? Nothing but his improbitie; for
he vvas giuen ſo much to beaſtlines, that he did not
let to defile his fathers bed; and therefore it is lavvfull
for anie man, vppon ſuch leaude occaſions, to

take the like courſe.
            
            
               Tich.
               If parents ſhould alter their diſpoſition vpon
euery ſmal diſpleaſure, then they may make a Wil
euery weeke, and yet neuer a wiſe one in the ende.
A wiſe man, hath reaſon, to whome he giueth, and
therefore is reſolute when he giueth, he will be angry,
and yet ſinne not, that is he will not ready in
his rage, to diminiſh his gift for euery grudge, but
mitigate his wrath with wiſedome, hee may well
put vp ſome diſpleaſures, that hath receiued manie
pleaſures, if one offence ſhall make a man froward,
the remembrance of many forepaſſed benefits, may
purchaſe his beneuolence. I ſpeake this to this end,
there is many a good man that hath vngodly children,
yea and ſometimes they are moſt euill, that are
eldeſt▪ but yet it were pittie they ſhould be depriued
of their dignity. Ioſiah did not ſo much beate down
Idolatrie, as his eldeſt ſonne after him did ſet it vp,
yet he poſſeſſed his fathers kingdome. 2. King. 23. 32
Iehoſhaphat aboliſhed al ſuperſtition as his father did
afore, but his eldeſt ſonne after him did erect it,
yet he came to his fathers kingdome, 1. Chro. 21. 6.
and therefore God forbid the elder ſon ſhould haue
iniurie for euery light occaſion: for he runneth far
that neuer turneth, and though it be long, it is better
late than neuer.
            
            
               Phi.
               I perceiue a great ſound may come from an
emptie Caske, much pith from a peece of weake
elder, and a great flame of a little bundle of bryers,
but I will leaue the cenſuring of it to your ſelfe: if
I ſhoulde reaſon with a ſcholler, I could forbeare
him, becauſe he is my better, or with one that is ignorant

I would ſuffer him, becauſe he is ſimple, but
the wilfull I cannot permit, becauſe they are peeuiſh:
your examples (I denie not) are ſingular, but
your application is ſo ſingle that it woulde make a
man ſtretch his lipps like a peece of leather, to heare
ſuch a reaſon proceede from one that profeſſeth
learning. I ſpeake of ſuch as haue preſent experiēce
of their childrens impietie, by their life, and you of
thoſe that haue come to future filthines after their
parents departure. Iaacob in his time ſaw his ſonnes
vntowardnes, but neither Ioſiah or Iehoſhaphat did
theirs, in their dayes: then how can theſe arguments
agree, yet to mend the matter you ſay they runne
farre that neuer turne, as though that were a reaſon
worthy of recorde? why is not hee that giueth
them grace to repent, as able to giue them goods
to inrich them, either inferre that which is effectuall
to the purpoſe, or elſe referre your ſelfe to cō
                  mon
ſenſe in iudgemēt, if neither, then let vs deſiſt.
            
         
         
            VVhether a reaſonable allowance may be
taken for lending of monie.
            
               PHilogus
               Becauſe I will not prolong the time
with any impertinent proteſtation, I will begin
briefly with another queſtion: So it is, there is
a neighbor of mine that is of great reporte for riches,
who hath cōuerted his poſſeſſions into a peece
of monie, and by reaſon of his age being not able
to labour, he letteth his monie to get his liuing, there
reſorts of al ſortes to borrow of him, to the poore he
lendeth only for loue, to the rich for loane, now my
deſire is to knowe whether hee may lawfully take

Vſury of the rich yea or no?
            
            
               Tich.
               If wee diſpiſe the droane that liueth by the
honie, &amp; the caterpiller that conſume the fruit, ſhall
we ſupporte him that ſucketh the lucre of our labours?
neither doe I thinke that Vſury may bee admitted
or excuſed in regarde of our external eſtates,
or any ſuch ſiniſter circumſtances, for it is both generally
and flattly forbidden, Thou ſhalt not giue to
Vſurie to thy brother, as Vſurie of monie, Vſurie of meat,
Vſurie of any thing that is put to Vſurie. Deut. 23. 19.
            
            
               Phi.
               Yet you omit that you ſhuld remember, for it
followeth further in that place you produce, Vnto a
ſtranger thou maiſt lend vpon Vſurie, Verſ. 20. wherby
it appeareth Vſury was then permitted, &amp; yet there
was ſome difference to whome it was done.
            
            
               Tich.
               It was not reſtrained frō ſtrangers, rather for
the hardnes of their harts at that time, than becauſe
the thing it ſelfe was tollerable, but God forbid we
ſhould by that liberty practiſe it as lawfull, for you
muſt note, it might be offered to none but ſtrangers
(ſuch as were addicted to Idolatrie &amp; enemies to
religion) but to their brethrē (which were inclined
to the true ſeruice of God) it might not, therfore amongſt
vs which be Chriſtians (being all brethren
by profeſſion) it may not.
            
            
               Ph.
               You are greatly deceiued herein for it appeareth
by the yeare of freedom, that not only one neighbor
but one brother, haue takē Vſury of an other, theſe
are the words: At the terme of ſeuē years thou ſhalt make
a freedome, &amp; this is the maner of the freedom, euery creditor
ſhall quite the loane of his hand which he hath lent to his
neighbour, he ſhal not aske it againe of his neighbor nor of his
                  
                  brother, for the yeare of the Lords freedome is proclaymed,
Deut. 15. 1. 2. So that I can ſee no cauſe but
that the rich may lawfully paye vſury, and ſo much
the rather becauſe that yeare of priuiledge was in
reſpect of the poore, but as for the rich creditor he
had no eaſe by that order but might be conſtrayned
to pay, for ſo it appeareth by the wordes, that which
thou haſt of thy brother thy hand ſhall remit, Saue when
there ſhall be no poore with thee. Deut. 15. 3. 4. yea, and
there bee diuers places of proofe in the ſcripture
whereby one may gather that Vſury is prohibited
in reſpect of the poore and not of the rich as apeares
in Exod. 22. 25. where it is written, If thou lend monie
to my people, that is to the poore with thee (he ſaith not
to the rich with thee) thou ſhalt not bee as an Vſurer
vnto him, ye ſhall not oppreſſe him with Vſury: and
for further confirmation, I referre you to Leuit. 25
37. 38. where the matter in effect diſſents not from
this. Theſe be the wordes, If thy brother bee impoueriſhed
and fallen in deacay with thee, thou ſhalt relieue
him &amp;c. thou ſhalt take no Vſury of him nor vantage,
&amp;c. what can be more properly and emphatically
ſpoken in reſpect of the poore than this without any
regard of the rich: for indeed you pretermit two
things you ought to expend: the firſt is the abilitie
of the borrower, the next is, the cauſe that induceth
him to borrow, his abilitie is ſufficient, the cauſe is
ſuperfluous: ſufficient, becauſe it rather exceedeth
thā is equall with the liuing of the lender: ſuperfluous,
becauſe it rather proceedeth of ſome couetous
forecaſt, for commoditie than vpon any vrgent vſe
of neceſſitie, and therefore what deede of charitte

is it to lend ſuch a one as needes not, Luk. 14. 12. or if
hee borrow, what reaſon is it the lender ſhould not
be partaker of his profite.
            
            
               Tich.
               Your ſayings are very ſenſuall, and be rather
meanes to animate many, than reſtraine any
from euill, wherein you take a confuſed courſe to
maintaine ſuch a monſtrous ſinne as Vſurie is,
for the next way to quench fire is not to powre on
oyle, or to driue away the dropſie to followe drinking,
neither is it the beſt courſe to abādon Vſurie by
excuſing it: if the Apoſtle would haue vs to abſtaine
frō al appearance of euil, 1. Theſ. 5. 22. how horrible
is it to become approouers of euill? I perceiue that
the drift of your long diſcourſe is to no other ende
but to proue that Vſurie may be taken of the rich;
yet I cannot finde it lawfull for them to giue it,
the Prophet Iheremie confesſing his integritie amongſt
the wicked (which did curſe him without
cauſe) to cleare himſelfe altogether of the blotte of
Vſurie ſaith in theſe wordes: I haue neither lent on
Vſurie, nor men haue lent mee on Vſurie. Iherem. 15. 10.
ſhewing thereby that it is a ſinne aſwell to giue, as
to take intereſt.
            
            
               Phi.
               I perceiue he that deales with knottie wood
muſt not want an yron wedge, and yet I ſee no reaſon
why that ſingle proteſtation of Iheremie which
you obiect, ſhould confound the double confirmation
of Moſes which I alleadge: Notwithſtanding I
confeſſe that ſame ſaying of Iheremie is ſingular, as
hee placed it, although it be but ſimple as you apply
it; for if you vnderſtand it ſimplie by the verball
ſenſe, then you ſhew your ſelfe ſo ſimple that you

bee voyde of all ſenſe; for I neuer read of any
godly Prophet that did euer let or take monie to Vſury,
neither was it like that he whoſe calling was
ſo excellent by inſpiration, would haue his life to
ſauour of ſuch corruptiō: &amp; what though the Prophet
doth by a Simile make a mention of Vſury to
ſome intricrate end, doth it follow that the naming
of it ſhal make the thing to be nocent, without exception?
Therfore no doubt you are greatly deceiued
herein, for thoſe wordes (I haue neither lent, or
men lent me to Vſury) are vſed of the prophet for two
principall endes: The firſt is by Synecdoche pars pro
toto (to ſet forth the ſimplicitie of his calling) ſhewing
that he was as well cleare of that, as of all other
worldly matters and meanes which might either
bee impediments to his profeſsion, or giue any occaſion
of curſing: the next is by a Metaphore drawn
from an act of the accidents (to note the peruerſitie
of the people) who exclaymed againſt him
as bitterly (and yet without cauſe) euen as the
poore doo when they are grieuouſly oppreſſed by
the Vſurer, which outcries are ſometime ſaide to
be ſo pitiful that they pierce the skies. Eſa. 5. 9. now
becauſe here may riſe ſome ambiguity in this latter
aſſertion, I will proue it ſufficiently by reaſon, for
your better reſolution, It ſeemeth by all ſenſe and
reaſon that the original of theſe outcries ſhuld proceede
from the poore, firſt becauſe they of all others
haue moſt occaſion to borrow, and whether
ſhould they repayre but to the rich? next, becauſe
when they are oppreſſed (by reaſon of want)
they can not vſe thoſe remedies the rich may,

and it is this that makes them to exclaime againſt
them. Yea to conclude theſe exclamatiōs can neuer
be conſtrued to come from the rich: for they will
ſooner crucifie than curſe the poore, becauſe (as Salomon
ſaith) he maketh his goods his ſtrong Citie
Pro. 10. 15. beſides that the ſame wiſe man ſaith in
another place, his friends are many. Pro. 14. 20. ſo
what by the helpe of his riches one way, and the
furtherance of his friends another way, he will vſe
his remedie by reuengement not by exclamation.
            
            
               Tich.
               Your diſcourſe is ſo long that I may iuſtly
cut ſhort your logitiā cauils, with a laconian quib
&amp; yet your matter is more tedious to remēber, thā
troubleſome to anſwere, but becauſe I haue other
proofes apliable for this purpoſe, I will ouerpaſſe ye
                  
I could impugne, &amp; infer that you cānot refel. That
famous Citie of Ieruſalē
                   being deſtroyed, the Lord
by the mouth of his Prophet ſhewing the cauſe that
prouoked him therto (amongſt many other iniquities)
noteth this for oee, Thou haſt taken vſury &amp; increaſe,
&amp; hast defrauded thy neighbour. Ezek. 22. 12. no
doubt this ſaying was ſet downe for 3. cauſes, 1. to
ſhew vs that it was a horrible ſin, and that in meaſure
amongſt the reſt it procured parte of the puniſhment;
ſecondly that we might by this example
ſhun it; thirdly that it was not one but many ſinnes
that cauſed the deſtruction of that Citie.
            
            
               Phi.
               I cānot denie but that Vſurie was much vſed
in that citie, yet I cā ſee no cauſe therby that ſhould
make me to yeeld to your argumēt: for the Lord in
that place meaneth not the intereſt that one richmā
taketh of an other, but the vſurie that the rich tooke

of the poore by oppreſſion, &amp; that we may perceiue
apparantly in the 5. of Nehemiah, where the rich,
had gotten from the poore all their landes, houſes
vinyardes, corne, &amp; what they had into their hands
verſe 11. Inſomuch, as the exclamation of the poore
of that Cittie, was very pitifull againſt the rich,
vntill ſuch time as the ſame Prophet did make a
mitigation thereof: So that the intruſiō of your laſt
poſition is nothing to the purpoſe; becauſe our
talke tendeth onely for the taking of intereſt of the
rich.
            
            
               Tich.
               You ſtill inuert my proofes at your owne
pleaſure, but yet I ground not my opinion, vpon
your perſwaſion, for I cannot ſee but that Vſury is
very contemptible. The Prophet Dauid declaring
who ſhould dwell in the Tabernacle of God, he nameth
him to be one in the number that hath not giuē
forth vpon Vſury. Pſal. 15. (this is ſpoken generally
without exception of perſons and that is cleane oppoſite
to your opinion) ſo conſequently wee may
gather, that he that doth contrary ſhallbe excluded
according to the alluſion of the Prophet Ezekiel, He
that hath giuen foorth vpon Vſury or taken intereſt ſhall
not liue. Ezek. 18. 13.
            
            
               Phi.
               I perceiue your principal proofes conſiſt in
your laſt poſitions, which I haue no doubt to refute
as well as the reſt. The Euangeliſt Luke recordeth a
ſaying that ſhould be vſed by our Sauiour Chriſt,
which is this: It is a bleſſed thing to giue rather than
to receiue. Act. 20. 25. Now if you ſhould demand
how I could proue theſe wordes by any other part
of the Scripture, my anſwere ſhould bee, I knowe

not (for the like literall forme, is not to bee found)
but if you ſhould aske, why I beleeue thoſe bare
words to be true? thē I would anſwere, the effect of
them may be gathered (though not orderly, yet ſufficiently)
by the words of our Sauior Chriſt in manie
other places in the ſcriptures. Euen ſo, touching
your authorities &amp; places you produce, I perſwade
my ſelfe they are altogether pronounced agaynſt
ſuch as oppreſſe the poore: if you ſhould aske mee
how I could proue it? I might anſwere, I knowe
not: for there is no one ſpeciall place of proofe for
it. But if you ſhould demaund, what reaſon ſhould
inforce me to ſay ſo? then I would make this aunſwere,
If you confer all places of the Scripture together,
tending or pertaining to this purpoſe concerning
Vſurie, it will appeare that euerie part hath
a ſpeciall reſpect to this ende, to ſupport and profite
the poore, and to repreſſe the rich from oppreſsing
them: whereof as I haue ſhewen you ſome examples
of it before, ſo for your further confirmation,
I referre you to Eſa. 5. 8. Amos. 8. 4. others at your
owne leaſure you may looke out.
            
            
               Tych.
               As no man doubteth, but that the word of
God is of ſufficiencie of it ſelf without circūſtance,
yet there is reaſon to make a doubt of your bare
ſurmiſe without authoritie, ſeeing we all knowe it
is a courſe wooll will take no colour, &amp; a bare matter
that will beare no argument. Salomon that wiſe
man, doth note the ſinne of Vſurie by this ſentence,
He that increaſeth his riches by vſurie and intereſt,
gathereth them for him that will be mercifull to the
poore. Prou. 28. 8. the Lorde will not onely abridge

his daies (for the wicked ſhalbe ſoone cut off) but
alſo thoſe goods he hath gathered ſo vngodly together
(how hardly ſoeuer he had them) ſhall bee taken
from him, and left to ſuch a one as ſhall better
beſtowe them. I pray you, doo but conſider into
what an intollerable extremitie the people were
brought in the time of Nehemiah by burdens of vſurie
and exactions, inſomuch, as if the ſame Prophet
had not ſpeedely ſought a remedie, there had
followed great confuſion vpon it. Nehem. 5. And
no doubt, if good lawes had not been prouided to
repreſſe it amongſt vs, it would haue cauſed ere this
day, as great calamitie in England, as it did then in
Iheruſalem. So that you may plead what you pleaſe
euerie way to excuſe Vſurie, but I ſee no reaſon anie
way to admit it.
            
            
               Phil.
               Hee that wants wood, will rather burne
turfe, than be without a fire; &amp; he that lacks matter,
wil rather multiplie words, thā ceaſe frō reaſoning:
who would thinke you ſhoulde giue ouer ſo many
good arguments, to relie vpon this laſt allegation of
Salomon, when indeed his intent is cleane contrary
to your interpretation; for hee meaneth thoſe that
gather their goods by intereſt of the poore, and not
of the rich, yea, and (that which is more malignant)
thoſe that ſpare the rich, &amp; pinch the poore: which
may be gathered in another place in his Prouerbes,
Hee that oppreſſeth the poore to increaſe himſelfe,
and giueth vnto the rich, shall ſurelie come to pouertie.
Prouer. 22. 16. As for that matter of Nehemiah,
I meruaile you implie it ſo impertinentlie,
hauing prooued before that it pertaineth to the oppreſsion

of the poore: and that may more euidently
appeare vnto you by the Prophets owne proteſtation,
who (the better to beate downe Vſurie,
and to mooue the rich to remorſe) perſwadeth
them by his example to be good to the poore: For
(ſaith he) euen I and my brethren and my ſeruants
doo lend them money and corne: I pray you let vs
leaue of this burden. Nehe. 5. 10. As for your laſt aſſertion,
touching our Lawes againſt Vſurie, certes
they are verie well prouided: for albeit they reſtraine
the vnreaſonable loane for lettage, yet they
admit ſome competent allowaunce for lending: (I
mean not of the poore but the rich) otherwiſe, mē
may want ſometime of a ſodaine, but they may be
bolde to borrowe at leaſure. So that all your obiections,
be rather needleſſe for prolixity, than neceſſarie
for probabilitie.
            
            
               Tych.
               I remember there is a common ſaying,
that hee that is once wet, cares not how deepe hee
wade; ſo it ſeemeth, that you hauing ouerſhot your
ſelfe in your ſayings, care not how you maintayne
them by ſhiftes, our S. Chriſt hath giuen vs a newe
commandement (not to lend for lone as the Iewes
did in their daies) but (ſaith he) Lend looking for
nothing againe. Luk. 6. 35. what ſay you to this?
            
            
               Phil.
               I ſay, it were beſt to intercept you with
ſome other ſentence, that might barre the borrower
from all the benefit; could you be content to lend
a ſumme of money to your friend at his inſtance,
and take this peece of ſcripture for paiment at your
day? I thinke not. Our S. Chriſt doth not onely wil
vs to lēd looking for nothing againe, but alſo in the

ſame chapter, of him that taketh away thy goods, ask
them not againe, Luk. 6. 30. yet his meaning is not
by theſe words to maintaine wrong; for if wee bee
forbidden to couet our neighbours goods, much
more we may not violently take them awaye: neyther
doth he meane by lēding looking for nothing
againe, that a man ſhould looſe al when he lendeth;
for he willeth vs to do, euē as we wold be done to;
then what is he will lend to looſe all, albeit he could
be content to borrowe and brooke all? Beſides, to
detaine a mans dutie, it is a great argument of impietie,
and that may appeare by the Prophet Dauids
ſaying; For (ſaith he) the wicked borroweth, &amp; paieth
not againe, Pſal. 37. 21. Therefore you muſt not
conſter the Scriptures by the literall but the myſticall
ſenſe, as hauing regard to the time when, &amp; to
the end wherefore it is ſpoken: and conſequentlie
you may perceiue that all your poſitions, are diſcrepant
from your opinion. Now hauing attended &amp;
anſwered all your obiections with patience: you
haue reaſon to heare a little what I can alleadge
for proofe: for indeede, it is the part of a cunning
Chirurgian, not onelie to purge the wound from
corruption, but to applie a plaiſter to cure it. But to
the matter; The new Teſtament may be a teſtimonie
with me: for all other particular ſinnes (as couetouſnes,
extortion, and ſuch like) are expreſſed &amp;
ſet downe, but as for vſurie there is no mention
made of it, ſauing in one place, where it appeareth
by the words of our Sauiour Chriſt, that vſurie is
rather admitted than adempted, (whē he reproued
the ſloathfull ſeruant, that vnder idle excuſes made

no profite of his talent) Thou oughtst (ſaith he) to
haue put my money to the exchangers, and then at
my comming should I haue receiued mine own with
vauntage. Mat. 25. 27.
            
            
               Tych.
               If the Surgeon you ſpeake of coulde no
better cure by his arte, than you cōuert me by theſe
arguments, he ſhould rather procure a putrifaction
than a purgation; for there is neither ſenſe nor ſequele
in your aſſertion: becauſe vſurie is not expreſſely
named in the newe Teſtament, you will
conclude ex conſequenti that Vſurie is no ſinne.
What a paradoxe is this? is not the affection the
cauſe of the action, the intent, the procurer of the
attempt: why then, it is impoſsible but that vſurie
ſhould be comprehended &amp; condemned with couetouſnes;
for where there is no auaricious deſire,
men will lend for loue without lucre: and ſeeing
couetouſnes is the roote of all euill, it is no maruell,
though Vſurie be a branch of it. Thou oughtest to
haue put my mony to the Exchangers ſaith our Sauiour
Chriſt) ergo (ſay you) Vſurie is tollerated.
What a parabolicall proofe is this? are we now to
learne the purport of a parable, when indeede it is
not to be beleeued ſimplie but ſignificantlie, not according
to the circumſtance of the matter, but the
ſubſtance of the ſenſe, and the doctrine, that may be
deduced from it, thus your ſimple handling of your
two laſt propoſitions, may be wray the looſenes of
all the reſt of your allegations.
            
            
               Phil.
               I haue read that the Tigreſſe milke the
more it is ſalted, the leſſe it is ſeaſoned, that the Cipreſſe
tree the more it is watred, the more it withereth,

ſo it fareth with you: for my reaſons the more
forcible the les effectuall they be to perſwade you,
whether I ſhould impute it to your ignoraunce, or
obſtinacie, I knowe not: but no doubt to erre, and
excuſe it is a greater argument of wilfulneſſe than
wiſedome; you ſay Vſurie is included within couetouſnes,
for where there is no greedie deſire, men
will lend for loue onely, by this reaſon, hee that letteth
his land ſhalbe reſtrained of his rent, for if his
deſire were not couetous, he might aſwel take God
amercie as money, what a concluſion were this, you
would haue men, liue by the aire like the Elephant,
when you abridge them of their lawfull courſe to
increaſe. You proceede further and ſay my proofe
is parabolicall? I confeſſe it, yet it followeth not it
ſhould be improbable? The husbandman that ſoweth
the ſeeede (albeit he referreth the bliſsing to
God) yet he hath great regard of the ground; and
ſhall wee that read a parable (although wee reſpect
chieflie the ende and effect of it) neglect the matter
that doth manifeſt the ſame? Is it poſsible that
the myſterie beeing ſerious and ſingular, that the
matter ſhould be light and ſiniſter? Would GOD
bewraye his heauenly Wiſedome, by ſimilitudes
without ſenſe, or not worth our obſeruation? I denie
it: for his diuine prouidence diſpoſeth althings
to a good purpoſe. The end of the parable of Diues
and Lazarus, is to terrifie vs frō hardning our harts
againſt the poore, yet there is ſomewhat elſe to bee
obſerued in the matter of that parable: for I beleeue
that after death euerie one ſhall goe immediately either
to heauen or hell, as there be manifolde proues

in the ſcripture, ſo I haue a manifeſt exāple of this
euen of Diues and Lazarus. The like I may ſay by
the other parable, although the efficient end therein
was to reproue the ſlothful ſeruāt, becauſe he made
no vſe of Gods benefits; yet we may perceiue that
the matter beſides doth not only import but aproue
that it is better to imploy our treaſure to ſome profit
by exchaunge, than to hide it in the earth to no
ende by excuſe; for Gods gifts are abuſed if they be
not vſed. Therefore let vs not ſo lightlie eſteeme of
parables, knowing to what ende our S. Chriſt vſed
them, that the people by ſeeing might ſee &amp; not perceiue,
and by hearing might heare &amp; not vnderſtād
thē. Mat. 13. 13. Now, if we ſhall both hear &amp; ſee thē
&amp; yet (by reaſon of our curious conſtructions) neither
vnderſtand or perceiue thē, ſhal not thoſe parables,
nay that people procure our greter cōdēnatiō?
            
            
               Tych.
               Although in worldly matters (for lucre
ſake) wee deale rather ſubtilly than ſimplie, yet in
matters of Religion, wee muſt not wreſt the word
of God to our wills, by cunning without conſcience;
for that is the diuine rule of all humane reaſon.
It is an eaſie matter by follie to make a peece of
good timber to ſerue for burning as for building; as
many places of the ſcripture by cauilling, aſſoon to
bolſter as to bridle ſin. But what of that? If mē (euē
in matters of no momēt) are ſo circūſpect that they
wil not put that to burn that is meete to build with,
how much more ought wee (in a cauſe of conſcience)
to be carefull, wee applie not that to ſupport
which is meete to ſuppres ſin? If all I haue ſaid will
not ſerue to ſatisfie you, yet in this reſpect Vſurie

is not to bee permitted, becauſe the Apoſtle Paule
teacheth vs to shun things of euill report. Therfore,
ſeeing there is nothing more odious and opprobrious
amongeſt vs than Vſurie (to auoide the verie
occaſion of euill) it muſt not bee practiſed but expelled.
            
            
               Phil.
               Either you delight to vrge argument to
no ende, or els you are ouerweened with the ſufficiencie
of your owne wit; then I ſhall ſooner beat
the truth into your head with a hammer, than remooue
your determination with reaſon, for There
is more hope of a foole (ſaith Salomon) than of him
that ſtandeth in his owne conceipt, and yet of both
the foole is more to be borne with: for he erreth of
ignorance, the other of malice. It ſeemeth you are
put to great penury, by your laſt poſitiō, for therby
we may aſwel ſhun that which of it ſelf is abſolutely
good, as that which cōmonly by occaſion is euil,
and this was the iniquitie of Ionah, who being willed
by the Lord to goe preach at Niniue, hee went
another way, (yet the word of God is excellent and
worthy to be preached, &amp; the cōmandement giuen
him expediēt to be performed) what was the cauſe
of his contempt? nothing els but for feare he ſhuld
be euill ſpoken of. Ionah. 4. 1, 2. &amp;c. Thus he did omit
that which was good and meete to be done, for
feare of the euill might follow of it. But admit the
Apoſtle perſwadeth vs to ſhunne ſuch things as be
ſiniſter and of euill report: yet thoſe wordes condemne
not vſurie, as it may be vſed; for if you note
the originall of that report, it will appeare that it is
the extremitie of the rich that vrge the poore to cry

out vpon them, and hereof conſequently riſeth this
euill reporte. Nehe. 5. verſ. 6. 9. ſo that this poſition is
prepoſterous, for our conference concerneth the
rich, and not the poore.
            
            
               Tich.
               Yet there remayneth one thing that commeth
fitly to my remembrance for this purpoſe, our
firſt father Adam after his creatiō was put into the
garden, to dreſſe and keepe it, and after his fall, hee
was enioyned to get his liuing, In the ſweat of his
face: whereby I gather that all Chriſtians ought to
liue in ſome good vocation; nowe the Vſurer hath
none, therefore for want of a calling he muſt needs
be condemned.
            
            
               Phi.
               What a ſimple Silogiſme is this? the Gentleman
that letteth his lande, will haue a reaſonable
rent to liue by, the marchant that ſelleth his ware
wil take a reaſonable gain to ſaue by, yea al mē that
haue any dealings will haue ſome deuiſe to get by:
and ſhall he that hath monie be only barred of that
benefite, as though it were not as tollerable to vſe
the lawfull meanes to profite by monie, as in any other
matter?
            
            
               Tich.
               I grant ſo too, but in Vſury nothing is to be
taken of couenant but of curteſie.
            
            
               Phi.
               What a ridiculous reaſon is this? You will
allow al other men to be circumſpect in bargaining
for their owne benefite, but binde him that letteth
his monie to the beneuolence of others; thoſe may
worke ſurely for their owne profite, this ſimply at
other mens pleaſures; when indeede it is no wiſedome
for a man that lends to tie his libertie at anothers
election, nor conſcience in him that borroweth,

to receiue a benefit without amends? But I pray
let me demaund one queſtion of you? We haue hitherto
contended about Vſury, but what call you
Vſurie?
            
            
               Tich.
               We terme that Vſury which is taken ouer
and beſides the principall that is lent.
            
            
               Phi.
               If it be Vſurie to take any thing more than
the principall, who is not a Vſurer? The Gentlemē
will require, the husbandmen will rayſe, the tradeſmen
will rate, in ſelling of their land, corne, &amp; ware
a proportionall price according to the time of payment:
now if Vſurie be after your definition, theſe
aſwell as the Vſurer doe ſin, though they deale not
in like ſorte: for Vſurie extendeth not onely to monie,
but alſo to meat, or any thing that is put forth.
Deut. 23. 19. What a proper expoſition is this, that
men may take no allowance to liue by without offence.
It ſeemeth you would haue them ſpend all
they haue firſt, and then to ſee what they can gather
without a beginning he that doth in this forte prouide
for his family, is no better than an Infidell by
his folly. And therefore it is no maruaile, you haue
vſed ſo long a circumſtāce without ſenſe, ſeing you
are ignorant of the foundation you defend: for Vſury
is not the reaſonable, but the vnreaſonable, taking
of any ouerplus aboue the principal; which the
Prophet in reſpect of the poore calleth a burthen,
Neh. 5. 7. 10. So according to my former conference
I fully conclude, that although Vſury is prohibited
to be taken of the poore, I ſee no reaſon it ſhould be
remitted of the rich.
            
         
         
            
            VVhether the Rich or the Poore are to
be accompted moſt bleſſed.
            
               PHilogus
               I might moue a queſtion concerning
the ſtate of men, whether the rich or the poore
are to be coūted moſt bleſſed? for riches are the
gift of God and therefore I would think him moſt
happie, vpon whome, God moſt aboundantly beſtoweth
his benefites.
            
            
               Tich.
               If wee conſider of men by their externall
eſtates then it is hard to iudge who is moſt bleſſed:
for in that reſpect as Salomon ſaith all things come alike
to all, and the ſame condition is to the iuſt and the
wicked. Eccleſ. 9. 1. Lot had aboundance of wealth,
ſo had Diues, one was iuſt and ſaued, the other wicked
and damned, Lazarus had leſſe than both, yet
his ioye was equall with the beſt: ſo that your antecedent
is doubtfull, and your concluſion indirect▪
becauſe pouertie aſwell as proſperitie is Gods gift,
Pro. 14. 31. and therfore ſeeing the greateſt gift is not
goods but grace, the poore being partaker thereof,
may be more bleſſed than the rich.
            
            
               Phi.
               Yet this is no reaſon to diſanul my argumēt,
for as God giueth goods, ſo hee can giue grace, and
both thoſe bleſſings meeting, muſt needs make that
man more bleſſed thā him that hath but the benfite
of one, for though golde be good, yet being beautified
with pearle it is more precious according as a
learned diuine ſayd. Iuncta wirtus fortior.
               
            
            
               Tic.
               There is no man will denie but that goods of
themſelues are ſingular good, yet moſt will ſaye,

that ſuch are ſeldome ſeene that can well vſe them,
beſides ther be ſome ſpeciall reaſons, why the poore
by all preſumptions ſhould be preferred before the
rich into heauen; riches make men high minded.
Nabucadnez-zers heart was lifted vp, and why? (the
text ſayth) becauſe of his riches. Ezeki. 28. 5. Riches
makes vs forget God: Dauid ſaid he ſhould not be
mooued, when ſaide hee ſo? it appeareth by his
owne ſpeech, in his proſperitie. Pſalm. 30▪ 6. Riches
withdrawe vs from well doing: The ruler was
very heauy when he heard he could not poſſeſſe eternall
life, vnleſſe hee parted from his liuing: and
why? for the Euangeliſt ſaith, hee was merueilous
rich. Luke. 18. 23. Riches makes men bolde to doe
euill, whereas pouertie bridleth the poore from
many euills. Prouerbs 10. 15. To be briefe richmen
haue ſo many temporall conſolations, that they
little regarde any ſpirituall conſiderations: Therefore
as he that is emptie ſhall with more eaſe enter
in at a ſtraight gate, than he which beareth a great
burden; ſo the poore (who haue none of theſe
impediments) ſhall with more facilitie obtaine eternall
felicitie, than the rich (who by reaſon of
their aboundance) ſhall goe to heauen as a Camell
through a needles eye.
            
            
               Phi.
               Your long proteſtation is more prepoſterous
than pertinēt, for as no man doubteth but that proſperity
with godly gouernment is good▪ ſo none can
denie but that pouertie with the feare of God is cō
                  mēdable.
Pro. 15. 16. Yet as you ſay, ſuch are ſeldom
ſeene, that can wel vſe welth, ſo I may alleage ſuch
are rare to finde that can poſſeſſe pouerty patiently.

Riches (ſay you) make men high minded; and yet
the deuill hath other deuiſes to drawe poore men
to pride he hath many engines to work euill with,
and can allure men to one ſinne after many ſortes,
as wealth may inflate the rich man, ſo knowledge
may puffe vp the poore man, and ſometime hee
that wants both, is prowde in his owne conceipt:
riches makes vs forget God (ſay you), ſo doth pouertie,
for this cauſe the wiſeman deſired to be kept
from it, leaſte he fell to ſtealing and ſo forget the name
of GOD. Pro. 30. 9. As the rich man hath many temporall
conſolations, and the leſſe regardeth any ſpirituall
meditations; ſo the poore man hath ſo many
temporall miſeries, that it makes him often diſpaire
of Gods mercies. Therefore as there is no difference
of danger to eſcape Scylla, and to ruſh vpon
Caribdis, ſo there is no equalitie of euill to ſinne either
by exceſſe or by extremitie.
            
            
               Tich.
               It appeareth by many places of the Scripture
that the poore are moſt preferred, and more to bee
regarded than the rich, for although in this world,
the mightie ouermaiſter them, yet in the world to
come God hath choſen ſuch to confoūd the mightie:
1. Cor. 3. 27. albeit here they are diſpiſed and are
of no reputation, yet the Apoſtle ſaith, God hath
choſen them to bring to naught things that are: 1.
Cor. 3. 28. Againe our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith Bleſſed be
ye poore, for yours is the kingdom of God. Lu. 6. 20 now
on the contrary he ſaith to the rich▪ 
                  Woe be to you for
you haue receiued your conſolation. Lu. 6. 24. The Apoſtle
Iames ſaith God hath choſen the poore in this life
to be heires of eternall life Iacob. 2. 5. but hee willeth

the richmen to weepe and howle for the miſeries
ſhall come vpon them. Iacob. 5. 1.
            
            
               Phi.
               I maruaile you prolong the time with ſuch
friuolus poſitions, as though God had ſo peculiarly
choſen the poore, that hee hath vtterly excluded
the rich, as for thoſe exclamations that are threatned
againſt the rich, it is not againſt ſuch as vſe their
riches well, but wickedly; and the like I may ſay,
as for thoſe bleſſings that are vſed to the poore, it
is not ment by ſuch as are poore in eſtate and haue
little to liue on, but by ſuch as are poore in ſpirite,
and renounce their owne righteouſnes. Eſai. 6. 2.
for if the poore man doth contemne his croſſe, hee
ſhall be puniſhed aſwell as the rich man that abuſeth
his benefite.
            
            
               Tich.
               I perceiue you and I ſhall varie in argument:
for you drawe your ſpeech, by imagination what
a richman ſhould be, and I decipher them by contemplation,
what they commonly be, if it were
poſsible to finde ſuch a one as you ſet foorth, then
your propoſition could no way be imperfect.
            
            
               Phi.
               I haue read in the ſcriptures that Iob was a
very rich man, and yet he vſed his goods verie godly
as may appeare by his proteſtation made in his
extremitie concerning his integritie. Iob. 31. 16. Zacheus
was a rich man, yet he vſed his wealth verie
well, he gaue one halfe to the poore, and proffered
reſtitution foure folde to ſuch as hee had offended:
infinite are the examples I coulde recite, but two
ſhall be as good as twenty to reſolue you.
            
            
               Tich.
               What doth the view of the vertuous examples
of others auaile vs▪ ſeeing we haue no practiſe

of their proceedings amongſt vs, you ſhould do
well to ſhew where any of theſe benefactors are.
            
            
               Phi.
               It is not neceſſary to note any by name,
yet this I can ſay, there bee ſome that are good to
the poore at their doores, a few that will help their
friendes in diſtreſſe, otherwiſe as I doo not loue to
looke into the dealings of many, ſo I can ſay little
of the diſpoſitions of moſt.
            
            
               Tich.
               They ſay that one ſwallow is no argument
of ſummer, nor the Aethiopians white teeth cannot
make his face faire, neither may the forwardnes of
a few, be a generall preſumption for all that be rich,
It were hard if amongſt many bloſſomes all ſhould
proue blaſts, or amongſt many rich men, all ſhuld be
miſers, but yet if you marke the maner of ſuch
as doo good, you ſhall finde they either doo it
grudgingly or glorionſly, and that was the fault of
the Phariſies, one doth a pleaſure and but ſeldome,
and yet he muſt ſpeake of it very often, hee cannot
be content to doe good before God who can make
reſtitutiō, but he muſt haue it known to the world,
that laugh at his vaine oſtentation to giue, it is
good; the deede is charitable to him that hath need,
but not acceptable to God, becauſe he ſinneth if he
doth it not ſimplie: and ſurely hee that braggeth or
vpbraydeth where he hath done good, deſerueth no
better amendes than his owne mouth. Other
there be that be wealthy, that wil hardly parte from
a pennie by their life, but giue great promiſes of
much after death, and yet I think if they could carie
it with thē, they would hardly leaue it behinde.
It is a wonderfull thing that ſuch men as almoſt

haue no heires to inherite, no cauſe to be couetous,
no reaſon to hold faſt, ſhould ſhewe themſelues ſo
wretched to the world, that they will crucifie theyr
owne carkaſſe for want of coſt, and ſooner die than
depart with ought to doo another pleaſure. Alas,
what poſsibilitie of preferment is to be expected of
ſuch a perſon, that will yeeld no likelihood of liberalitie
by his life? Beſides, doo they thinke, one can
feede vpon faire wordes, or proſper by bare promiſes?
Why, he may goe long barefoote that tarries
for dead-mens ſhooes, and yet when he hath them,
they wil not be worth the wearing: for I haue knowen
ſuch, as haue promiſed goldē hils by their life,
that haue performed but durtie daies at their death:
It is but a fetch of fraudulencie, yea oftentimes the
cauſe of farther incōuenience, to bring one in hope
of hauing a thing, and then to delude him at the laſt
with nothing. Theſe ſhould doo well to remēber
the Wiſemans words, to doo good before they die.
For it is far better they ſhould ſend their workes afore
them, than they ſhould follow after them, &amp; it
is a greater worke of charitie for them to doo good
by their life freely, than to doo it after their death
forcibly. Wel, to be briefe, let this ſuffice, where
there is one that doth good with his goods, there
are a hundred that doo hurt with them.
            
            
               Phil.
               If I ſhould make as long a deſcription of
the poore, as you haue made a vayne inuection againſt
the rich, you might iuſtly ſay, I vſe more
words than wit, both becauſe your circumſtance
of ſpeech, is nothing to the ſubſtaunce of the matter,
as alſo, becauſe if both their cuills were weyed

together in an equall ballance, although they differ
in exterior eſtate in regard of liuing, I feare me they
would not be inferior in interior deſerts in reſpect
of their liues: for as you ſay of the rich, ſo amōgſt
the poore for the moſt part there be manie that bee
leaudly addicted. But becauſe it is a needleſſe diſcourſe
to diſcouer them, I will omit that, and to
the matter; The good man (ſaith Salomon) shall
giue inheritaunce vnto his Childrens Children.
Prouerbs. 13. 22. then it ſeemeth, ſuch as haue nothing
to giue, are vngodly. But the Prophet Dauid
doth make it more manifeſt: for (ſaith he) I neuer
ſaw the righteous forſakē, nor his ſeed begging bread
Pſa. 37. 25. If we conſter this by the contrarie, what
ſhould I ſay, is not pouertie an argumēt of impietie?
            
            
               Tych.
               It is a perillous thing to giue any peremptorie
iudgement of the poore, conſidering what the
Pſalmograph ſaith, Bleſſed are they that iudge wiſelie
of ſuch. What though Salomon ſaith, The good
man shall giue inheritance, &amp;c? Yet that is no conſequent
to condemne the poore, that haue nothing
to part with? For the Scripture ſaith, God hath choſen
ſuch. I am. 2. 5. Beſides that, the Prophets, nay the
Apostles, yea Christ himſelfe was but poore, &amp; had
no worldly poſſeſsions to diſpoſe; yet we muſt not
ſay they were impious: therefore that poſition was
ill put in, and your latter to as little purpoſe. For
though Dauid in his dayes neuer ſawe the righteous
beg their bread: yet ſince, we haue ſeene in the
Scripture an example to the contrarie, for Lazarus
lay begging at the rich mans gate, and yet his ſoule
did reſt in Abrahams boſome.
            
            
               
               Phil.
               You muſt conſider there are diuerſitie of
pouerties: Dauid was a King, and yet in regard of a
richer, he counted himſelfe but poore; for ſaith hee
(to his ſonne Salomon) According to my pouertie
haue I prepared for the houſe of the Lord. 1. Chr. 22.
14. Now, I ſpeake not in reſpect of a competent liuing,
for it was that, the Wiſeman moſt deſired;
neither of him that hath but a little to liue on, for
with the feare of God, it is better than great treaſure
and trouble with it. Prou. 15. 16. but of ſuch as cannot
ſupport themſelues, but by the beneuolence of
others, as the beggar doth.
            
            
               Tych.
               Why, hath not God ordeined ſuch as inſtruments
to trie the hearts of the rich? and ſhal we
ſo badlie accompt of beggars?
            
            
               Phil.
               Yet the workman is more woorthie than
the inſtrument, if he can vſe it well: and why? becauſe
the Apoſtle ſaith, it is a bleſſed thing to giue,
rather than receiue. Act. 20. 35.
               
            
            
               Tych.
               If the poore man bee content with his
wallet, ſhall we condemne him for want, ſeeing we
are taught that Godlines is great riches, if a man be
content with that he hath. 1. Tim 6. 6.
               
            
            
               Phil.
               Yet our Sauiour Chriſt commaunded his
Apoſtles, to vſe neither ſtaffe nor wallet. Matth. 10.
nor to goe from doore to doore: for as the Wiſeman
ſaith, It were better to die than beg. Eccle. 40.
28. It was this that made Paul labor with his owne
hands, rather than he would be chargeable to anie.
            
            
               Tych.
               The cauſe of the rich-mans happines cō
                  ſiſts
party in the poore, as appears by Salomons ſaying,
He that hath mercie on the poore is bleſſed. Pro.
                  
14. 21. therefore the poore are moſt to be preferred:
for if the cauſe be adempted, the effect muſt needes
diminiſh.
            
            
               Phil.
               This argument is not worth any thing: for
though I did admit your antecedent, it wold make
againſt your ſelf, if I ſhuld reaſon with you by waie
of compariſon, in this ſort; If he be bleſſed that beſtoweth
on the poore, what is he that hath nothing
to giue them? if the concluſion be made by the contrarie,
what ſay you to this? yet betweene your argument
and this, there is neither barrell better herring;
as for your conſequent, it is vainly intruded:
for if the poore can effect the bleſſednes of the rich,
the cauſe can neuer faile, conſidering that our Sauiour
Chriſt ſaith, ye shal haue the poore alwaies with
you. Mat. 26. 11. Therefore in this you doo but reſemble
the Spaniell, that forſakes the Partridge to
baite after birds, when you defend the matter by caſting
ſuch bolts; it is better to lay the finger on the
mouth, thā to ſpeak without modeſtie: but becauſe
it is a follie to ſtriue to go ouer a ſtile when the gap
lieth open, I will leaue off ſuch tearmes as I might
well returne, for the imperfection of your poſitions,
and produce ſuch matter as is meete to applie,
for the proofe of my propoſition. You knowe the
queſtion, I were loath to be much about it, leſt you
ſhould thinke I would begge it. I affirme that the
Rich man (although it bee rare) that diſpoſeth of
his goods like a good Steward, is more bleſſed
than the poore that haue not any thing to giue.
All men will graunt this, becauſe it hath been proued
euen by the Apoſtles ſpeech in my former defence.

                  Act 20. 35. Againe, this is another reaſon;
ſuch kinde of pouertie is to be counted as a croſſe,
and for this cauſe, the Wiſeman deſired to be kept
from it, Prouerb. 30. 9. And this was one of the puniſhments
that fell vppon Iob. Salomon willeth vs
not to loue ſleepe? and why? leaſt (ſaith he) thou
come vnto pouertie. Therefore, if it were not a puniſhment,
he would not premoniſh vs to preuent it
Prouerb. 20. 13. Yea, and in the ſame Chapter by
this hee dooth adde a double puniſhment to the
ſloathfull perſon: for hee telleth him, becauſe hee
will not worke in Winter, he ſhall begge in Summer,
but haue nothing. verſe. 4. So that I maye
conclude, the rich man is more bleſſed than the
poore in this reſpect, becauſe God giueth him the
benefite of a double bliſsing, one in this World
with aboundance, another (if he vſe them well) in
the world to come more ſuperabundant.
            
         
         
            VVhether there be degrees of glorie in
heauen, or difference of paines
in hell.
            
               PHilogus.
               There is a Queſtion much debated
vpon, but not decided? which although it bee
not a principle in Religion to be obſerued, yet
it is an argument of ambiguitie, not to be ouerſlipped.
I haue heard, that in heauen all be not equall in
excellencie, but (as ſome ſay) there be degrees of
glorie euen amongſt the Angels.
            
            
               Tych.
               If you can as readily approoue by reaſon
as you doo ſhewe me by report ſuch a matter, then

I ſhould be the rather induced to beleeue ſuch a miſterie.
            
            
               Phil.
               You knowe the Prophet Daniel ſaith, The
godlie shall shine as ſtarres in heauen, Daniel. 12. 3.
Now the Apoſtle Paule ſaith, that one ſtarre differeth
from another in glorie 1. Cor. 15. 41. Hereof it
is they ſay, the Saints ſhall doo ſo.
            
            
               Tychichus
               The Apoſtle hath ſuch a ſaying, yet
this is nothing pertinent to your propoſition, becauſe
hee ſpeaketh it in another ſenſe. For in that
place (ſpeaking of the reſurrection) he doth not only
reproue the Epicure that preferreth the pleaſures
of this life, but he proueth by way of compariſon,
that although our bodies bee in ſome ſort glorious
vpon earth, yet they ſhall be much more glorious in
heauen, and this he deſcribeth by the difference of
ſtarres: but that there ſhould be degrees of glorie, it
can no way bee gathered thereby. For that appeareth
plainly in the ſame chapter verſ. 48. where the
words extend rather to equalitie, As is the heauenly
(ſaith he) ſuch are they alſo that are heauenly. Againe
it is ſaid of our Sauiour Chriſt, that the iust
shall shine as the Sunne, Mat. 13. 43. Now, the
light of the Sunne exceedeth the light of the ſtars,
yet that were no conſequent that the iuſt ſhould ſo
farre exceede the godly in glorie, for both are but
Saints, and neither could haue been ſaued, if theyr
ſinnes had not been couered in Chriſt Ieſus: but
theſe ſimilitudes doo ſhewe vs, that although the
puritie of the godlie be obſcured in this world by
the prauitie of the wicked, as the ſunne and ſtarres
be often ouercaſt by reaſon of the clowdes; yet in

the world to come, whē both are ſeperated by thē
                  ſelues,
then the better ſhall haue his perfect appearance,
and ſhine like ſtarres, yea like the Sunne (whē
they are not ſhadowed) to the great glorie of themſelues,
and the vtter griefe of the vngodly.
            
            
               Phil
               My meaning is not to refell your reaſons,
but to recite ſuch as I haue heard: and amongſt others,
this they alledge, that in the palace of an earthly
Prince, there be manie ſeuerall roomes, &amp; in the
houſe of our heauenly King there be manie dwelling
places, ſo ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt Iohn. 14. 2.
Now as there is neuer a roome in an earthlie Pallace,
but hath his ſeuerall Office, and euerie Office
doth ſomewhat differ in dignitie from another, ſo
ſay they, there be manie manſions in heauen, and euerie
one according to the worthineſſe of his placing,
is preferred to the greater glorie.
            
            
               Tych.
               As though hee which is the omnipotent
Creator would take a patterne by the proceedings
of his Creatures, when wee reade that thoſe things
which are highly eſteemed amongst men are but abhomination
in his ſight. Our Sauiour Chriſt vſed
that ſpeach to his diſciples for their conſolation becauſe
he perceiued they were much troubled to
thinke of his departure, as though when hee were
gone, he would either vtterlie forget them, or goe
to ſuch a place, that there ſhould be no ſpace for thē
to be where hee was: therefore our Sauiour Chriſt,
to comfort them in theſe croſſe cogitations, dooth
nothing elſe but by theſe manie dwelling places,
amplifie and ſet foorth the largenes of his heauenlye
houſe to aſſure them they (as the faithfull)

ſhould be where he was: for although the gate bee
verie ſtraight to enter, heauen is wide enough for
thoſe that ſhall inherite it. This I take to be the true
meaning of our Sauiour Chriſt: for albeit hee maketh
mention of manie māſions, we muſt not think
there bee anie diſtinct dwellings in heauen, (much
leſſe any degrees of glorie) for it is written, the godly
ſhall all meete in one place in Gods preſence, and
miniſter a like ſeruice to his Maieſtie. Apocalipſe
cap. 7. ver. 15.
               
            
            
               Philogus
               To prooue there is difference of glorie
in Heauen, they proceede further and ſay; The
Apostles ſhall bee more glorious than the reſt:
becauſe they ſhall ſit vpon twelue Thrones, and
iudge the twelue Tribes of Iſrael. Matthew. ca.
19. verſ. 28.
               
            
            
               Tychicus
               I remember our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith
in another place to his Diſciples, that they ſhall
eate and drinke at his Table in his Kingdome,
Luke. 22. 30. yet I doo not thinke ſo. And in the
ſelfe ſame place, hee ſaith, They ſhall all ſit on
ſeates, and iudge the twelue Tribes of Iſrael;
yet I doo not take it ſo. For thoſe Similitudes
and ſayings, import nothing elſe but their aſſuraunce
to bee partakers of his glorie. My reaſon
for the firſt, is this, In heauen is neither eating
nor drinking, becauſe wee ſhall reade, that there
wee ſhall neither hunger nor thirſt anie more. Apocalips.
7. 16. Eſay. 49. 10. My reaſon for the latter
is this, The Apoſtles ſhall not iudge vs, becauſe
they, we, and all, ſhall bee iudged by Chriſt Ieſus.
Symbolum.
               
            
            
               
               Phi.
               They reſt not ſo but referre themſelues to a
ſaying of ſaint Paul to approue ſome difference of
dignitie in the Saints, becauſe he ſaith that they ſhal
iudge the world. 1. Cor. 6. 2.
               
            
            
               Tich.
               This aſſertion is anſwered by my former,
yet for your better reſolution I will explaine it by a
temporall conſtitution: you knowe that when a
priſoner (being a hainous malefactor) hath his accuſation
laid open apparantly to all that be preſent
(although the chiefe office of giuing ſentence belongeth
to the Iudge) yet all the reſt that bee there
may eaſily iudge what puniſhment that priſoner deſerues,
euen ſo in this reſpect the Saints may be ſaid
to iudge the world when our ſinnes and liues are
laid open manifeſtly in the preſence of ſo many
millions of Angels and Saints (albeit it appertaineth
properly to Chriſt to iudge vs) yet it is an eaſie matter
for them to iudge what we are, and in this ſenſe
it may very well be ſaid, we ſhall ſtand helples before
ſo many Iudges as haue excelled vs in good
workes; for the ſight of ſuch as are innocent is ſufficient
to iudge thoſe that haue iniuried them, yea,
it will ſtrike ſuch a horror into their hearts that
their very thoughts (as the Apoſtle ſaith) wil accuſe
or excuſe them Rom. 2 15. 16. at that day.
            
            
               Phi
               Yet they leaue not here but aleadge this for
a further probation of the matter, they ſay that as
we haue on earth Biſhops, ſo there are which differ
from them in dignitie, which are intituled Archbiſhops,
ſo in heauen there are Angels of great glory,
and yet there are Archangels which are of greater
glory.
            
            
               
               Tych.
               This concluſion is nothing forcible, becauſe
your compariſon is fallible, for although manie
be preferred more than others to higher dignitie
in this world, yet their inferiors may bee equall
to them in excellēcie, (cōſidering how theſe earthly
preferments come to men oftentimes aſmuch for
their reuenewes, as their vertues): now we knowe
with God is no reſpect of perſons, neither doth he
regard the promotion of a man by his title, but the
puritie of his life by his workes: and therfore, albeit
it pleaſeth God (of his good pleaſure) to call vs by
ſundrie names, as Archangels, Angels, Saints, Citizens,
Iust, Righteous, Children, Heires, Sonnes, and
ſuch like, it is no conſequent anie ſhoulde differ in
glorie from another; for what greater glorie can anie
haue more, than to be like him that is most glorious?
1. Iohn. 3. 2. and to ſit vpon the Throne with
him that ſhall iudge vs? Apoc. 3. 21. Yet this is ſpoken
generally to all the faithfull.
            
            
               Phil.
               I haue read that ſome of the Prophets as
Eſay, was cut in peeces with a ſawe of wood, Ieremie
was ſtoaned to death, Amos thruſt into the
temples of the head with a great nayle: others, as
the Apoſtle ſaith, were tried by mockings, ſcourgings,
&amp;c. Hebr. 11. 36, 37. yea in our times, manie
haue ſuffered as Martyrs for the teſtimonie of the
truth. And ſhall not theſe which haue indured ſuch
extreame torments in this world farre aboue theyr
brethren, poſſeſſe ſome greater glorie in heauen
than they?
            
            
               Tych.
               If you had ſaid poſſeſſe ſome greater ioy
in heauen, then it might haue bred a queſtion: for,

if in this world (where all our pleaſures are but purgatories)
when one that is poore doth attaine riches,
which are but momētany, if he taketh more ioy
by remembrance of his miſerie paſt, than hee that
was neuer pinched with penurie, then no doubt, in
the world to come (where the leaſt pleaſure is vnſpeakable)
it cannot be, but that he, which hath bin
moſt afflicted here, ſhall conceiue and receiue farre
more exceeding ioy, than he which hath been touched
with leſſe tribulation, &amp; yet the ioyes of heauen,
are fitlie compared to veſſells filled with licour
of all quantities, for euerie man ſhall haue his full
meaſure there. Againe, it pleaſeth God to afflict all
whom he loueth, &amp; yet he doth it not in like manner
and meaſure to all. For as his giftes and graces
are not of like excellencie in euerie one, ſo his afflictions
are not of like equalitie to all; yet that argueth
not anie ſhould exceede others in glorie in heauen,
ſo they indure that croſſe with patience, which
God doth lay vpon them on earth. There bee two
ſpeciall reaſons, that make much againſt you in this
matter: one is this. All the afflictions a man maye
ſuffer cannot ſaue him, becauſe when he hath done
his beſt, he is but an vnprofitable ſeruant ſayth our
Sauiour Chriſt. Luk. 1
                        •
                     . 10. Another reaſon is this,
no man maye hope to haue greater glorie than his
brother: becauſe they themſelues (for all their ſuffrings)
are not worthy the glory of the life to come.
Rom. 8. 18. Therefore, let euerie one reioyce (as Peter
perſwadeth vs) inaſmuch as he is counted worthie
to be partaker of Chriſts ſufferings: for, as by
faith the thiefe was ſaued vpon the gallowes at the

laſt gaſpe, euen ſo all men are ſaued by that meanes
when they haue perpetrated aſmuch as is poſsible.
The Similitude of our Sauiour Chriſt is ſufficient
to ſatisfie you in this behalfe; it is concerning the
houſholder that hired laborers into his vineyard at
all howres in the day: he that came early &amp; wroght
in the heate of the day, had no greater reward than
thoſe which were idle and wrought but an hower▪
ſeeing the hyre is indifferent to all, none ſhall haue
glorie greater than another.
            
            
               Phil.
               Yet to proue the matter more apparantly,
they drawe a reaſon by the contrarie, and ſay, that
ſeeing there is difference of paines in hell amongſt
the wicked, it muſt needes followe there muſt bee
difference of degrees in heauen amōgſt the Angels;
for there is inequalitie aſwell of good as of euill.
            
            
               Tych.
               Although your antecedent can neuer approoue
your conſequent, yet I would bee glad to
knowe ſuch places as may prooue thoſe difference
of paines in hell?
            
            
               Phil.
               Our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith, he that knowes
not his maſters will, and yet doth it not, ſhalbe beaten
with ſome ſtripes; but he that knoweth it and
doth the contrary ſhalbe beaten with many ſtripes,
this they alleadge for one. The ſame our Sauiour
ſpeking of the hypocrits in another place, ſaith, that
they ſhal receiue the greater damnation. This ſaying
is inuiolable (which they likewiſe produce. Alſo
our Sauior Chriſt, (ſpeaking of Chorazin &amp; Bethſaida,
he telleth thē that it ſhalbe eaſier for Tyrus &amp;
Sydon than they at the day of iudgement, Luke. 10.
13, 14. This is another notable obiection of theirs.
            
            
               
               Tych.
               I muſt needs confeſſe that it ſtandeth with
great reaſon, where God moſt abundantly beſtoweth
his benefites, there the abuſe and ingratitude deſerue
to be moſt puniſhed, yet (that there ſhould be
degrees of glorie in heauen becauſe there are difference
of paines in hell) it is againſt all reaſon: for
the ſinnes which drawe vs to hel are manie, and differ
one from another, but the mean wherby we be
drawen to heauen, is but one, and indifferent to all:
if euerie ſinne deſerueth death, it ſhoulde appeare,
the more grieuous ſinne ſhuld haue the greater dā
                  nation,
but ſeeing no merit can deſerue heauen, the
meanes are not manie can effect our ſaluation, but
onely faith in Chriſt Ieſus.
            
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

