
   
      
         
            The ofspring of the house of Ottomanno and officers pertaining to the greate Turkes court. Whereunto is added Bartholomeus Georgieuiz Epitome, of the customes rytes, ceremonies, and religion of the Turkes: with the miserbale affliction of those Christians, whiche liue vnder their captiuitie and bondage. In the ende also is adioyned the maner hovv Mustapha, oldest sonne of Soltan Soliman, twelfth Emperour of the Turkes, was murthered by his father, in the yere of our Lorde 1553. al Englished by Hugh Goughe.
            Georgijević, Bartolomej, d. ca. 1566.
         
         
            
               1569
            
         
         Approx. 174 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 93 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01618
            STC 11746
            ESTC S108633
            99844290
            99844290
            9087
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01618)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9087)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 544:10)
         
         
            
               
                  The ofspring of the house of Ottomanno and officers pertaining to the greate Turkes court. Whereunto is added Bartholomeus Georgieuiz Epitome, of the customes rytes, ceremonies, and religion of the Turkes: with the miserbale affliction of those Christians, whiche liue vnder their captiuitie and bondage. In the ende also is adioyned the maner hovv Mustapha, oldest sonne of Soltan Soliman, twelfth Emperour of the Turkes, was murthered by his father, in the yere of our Lorde 1553. al Englished by Hugh Goughe.
                  Georgijević, Bartolomej, d. ca. 1566.
                  Gough, Hugh, fl. 1569.
               
               [184] p.   
               
                  In Fletestreate, neare vnto saint Dunstones church by Thomas Marshe,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  [1569?]
               
               
                  A translation, by Hugh Gough, from the original Latin by Bartolomej Georgijević.
                  Publication date conjectured by STC.
                  "The Turkishe rites and ceremonies" and "The horrible acte, and wicked offence of Soltan Soliman Emperour of the Turkes, in murtheringe his eldest sonne Mustapha, the yeare of our Lorde. 1553" have caption titles.
                  Signatures: A-L m4(M4 is a blank).
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Prisoners of war --  Early works to 1800.
               Turkey --  History --  1453-1683.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-01
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-01
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-04
            John LattaSampled and proofread
         
            2007-04
            John LattaText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            ¶ The ofſpring of the houſe of Ottomanno, and officers pertaining to the greate Turkes Court.
            
               Whereunto is added Bartholomeus Georgieuiz Epitome,
                of the cuſtomes Rytes, Ceremonies, and Religion of the Turkes: with the miſerable affliction of thoſe Chrſtians, whiche liue vnder their captiuitie and bondage.
            
               In the ende alſo is adioyned the maner hovv Muſtapha, eldeſt ſonne of Soltan Soliman, twelfth Emperour of the Turkes, was murthered by his father, in the yere of our Lorde 1553. all Engliſhed by Hugh Goughe. (⸫)
            
               Imprinted at London in Fleteſtreate, neare vnto ſaint Dunſtones church by Thomas Marſhe.
               
            
         
         
            
            
            ❀ To the right worſhippeful knight, Sir Thomas Greſsam. Hugh Goughe vviſheth all godly honour, with Neſtors yeres, and Galens healthe.
               
            
            BEyng not manye Monethes ſence, by ſome fortunate chaūce (right vvorſhippeful) in the hearing of certaine graue communicatiō, debated by mē, both diſcrete, learned, and not altogether vnvvorſhippefull: it vvas at that preſent my luckye happe to heare of ſuche vvell diſpoſed perſons as of late daies, and before our time, had bene benefactours to Englād their natiue coūtrey. Amonge the vvhiche, ſome of a Zealous minde, had beſtovved their ſage coūcel and politike deuiſes, for defence of the ſame, other of a fauorable affection, geuen their labour, to the hauinge in readines of ſuche

neceſſary inſtrumentes, as bothe in time of peace, might ceaſe our doutfull mindes, frō carefulnes therof, and in the perilous ſeaſons of vvarre, defende vs from our daylye imminent aduerſaries: the reſte, beinge not many in number, hadde either, of a godlye and voluntarie vvil, vvholy (vvich chaunced more ſeldome) applied their riches, or many ioyning together, laid out their treaſures, to the erectinge of ſuche noble buildinges, as might be for a publike commoditye vnto the inhabitantes of this vvorthy Ile of Britaine. All vvhoſe deedes for an euerlaſting memoriall of them, and of ther vvell ſpent daies, haue moſt vvorthely deſerued to be engrauen in tables of braſſe. But fevve, yea alas to fevve, haue floriſhed, in vvhom all theſe commendable qualities haue▪reygned, as both to be beneficiall to their countrye, by ſage councell, procuring of ſafegarde for protection of the ſame, and beſtovving of their ſubſtance, to the building of ſuch famous and magnificent vvorkes,

as might ſerue for common vtilitie vnto all men. And by the diſcretion of thoſe men,, that be learned and vviſe, if euer anye ſubiecte hath enioyed thē, they attribute it vnto yow. For what is he, vvhiche is ignorāt of the policies, and trauels, that your vvorſhippe haue vſed and ſuſteined, for to gette ſafegard, and requiſite furniture to the realm. Beſydes the infinite riches geuē to the buildinge of that princely vvoorke, commonly called the Burſe, vvhich already declareth, and in Lōdon is openly to be ſēne. vvhat commodity generaly, it vvill bringe to the Citiſens therof. Theſe noble exploi
               
                  •
               es (as in dede they ar not a litle by all men praiſed) can not, but be highely commended. To vvhat end ſhuld I reherſe, or make mention of the great diuerſity, which men accōpt to be betwene it and the huge towre of Babilō, or outragious buildings in Egipt named Pyramides: or of the exceding difference, wherby it excelleth the intricate Laberinthes,

and monſtruous pillers, erected in diuers partes of the world: c
                  •
               ſidering that it is vnknovven vnto fevve, that theſe vvere either builded for a vaine oſtentation, or friuolous memorial, vvith out any profitable vſe, or of enuye, becauſe the founderers of the ſame, vvoulde not leaue ouer muche ſtore of worldly treaſures vnto their ſucceſſours. I neade not alſo to make rehearſal of your curteſy, gētilnes, frendſhip, and liberalitie tovvardes al men, yea and (vvhich deſeruethe no ſmall commendation) tovvardes the vnknovven, and ſtrangers, as diuers other, and I alſo of late dayes, haue ſufficiently proued. In conſideration vvherof, leſt I might ſeeme, eyther vnmindfull of ſuche benefites, as vndeſeruidlye, I haue receiued at your frendly handes, or be thought vnthankefull, by not endeuoring, (according to my pore habilities) partly to recompenſ
                  •
                your fauorable gentilnes declared tovvarde
                  •
                me: I counted it good to preſent your vvorſhyppe, vvith ſome ſuche treatice, as both
                  •
               
               
myght declare me mindfull of your ſo vnſpeakeable benefites, and vvype cleane avvaye from you, the opinion of deteſtable ingratitude, vvhiche othervviſe your vvorſhippe might moſt iuſtely haue conceyued of me. And in ſo muche as vvithin theſe thre hundred yeares, to the great domage, and vtter decay almoſt of Chriſtes infallible religion, the great Turkes povver, and Empire hath ſpredde it ſelfe ſo farre, that at this inſtant, ar ſubiecte to his cruell tyrannye, aboue foure and thirtye moſte famous nations vvhiche in times paſte haue bene chriſtened, yea and vvithin theſe foureſcore yeares, as one Hiltenius by propheſyinge hathe foretolde vs, he ſhall haue dominion both in Italie and Germanie: ponderinge vvith my ſelfe this pitifull eſtate, and lamentable ruyne of Chriſtianitye, I imagined that it did not ſo become me, as by dvvtie I vvas bounde, in gratifying your vvorſhippe, to reveale and make manifeſte vnto my countrey men, the nature, diſpoſition,

cuſtomes, rites, and faithe of thoſe circunſiſed Infidelles, vvith the horrible rackinge, painefull tormenting, and vnnaturall abuſing, of our faithefull brethren the innocent Chriſtians, moſt miſerably oppreſſed vvith the heauye youke of their vnmeaſurable taxes, tributes, and continuall bondage: that they by conſidering of the daungers, hanginge vniuerſally ouer our heades, may learne hence fourth to amende their ſinfull liues, and cal inceſſantlye vnto god for ſoccour againſt that mortall aduerſarye, bothe to the vndoubted veritie of Chriſtes holye goſpell, to our countrye, liues and ſoules.
            VVerefore accordinge to my ſimple ſkill and knovvleage I haue trāſlated into our vulgar ſpeche, this little booke, that herein, the vnaquainted vvith the latine toungue, may learne reade and ſee the ſūme of their belefe, the vnſtable, vveake, and foliſh foundations of their fained religion, vvhich in token of my bounden dvvtie, I offer &amp; dedicate vnto your vvorſhippe: deſiring moſt

humblye that you vvill accept it in good parte, and ſo accept it, as to voucheſafe to protecte and defende the ſame, vvith the title of your vvorthy name. This if you do, and receiue it ſo fauorablely, as other thinges of late dayes you haue done, you ſhall encorage me, hereafter for ſo frendlye takinge of theſe rude lines, to attempte and geue the onſette, both vpon bookes of greater volume, and matters of more vveight and ſubſtance. In the meanne tyme I vvill not ceaſe daily to call vppon God, that he of his infinite goodnes, vvill encreaſe this louing affection tovvardes your countrye, endvvynge you vvith perfecte healthe, vvith all godlye honour, and after thys vvaueringe lyfe, to aduaunce youre worſhip aboue the ſkyes, ther to remaine in perpetual bliſſednes, vvorld vvithout end.
            
               Your vvorſnippes moſt
bounden Hugh Goughe.
            
         
         
            
            ☞ Bartholomeus Georgieuiz the author wiſhethe vnto the godly and Chriſtian reader perfecte felicitie
            
               THe ciuill diſcention, deadly diſcorde and contentious warres of our Princes, moſt chriſtiā reader, haue procured me thys, that (beinge ſpoiled of all my goodes, bound with cheines, ledde to be ſolde as a beaſt, throughe townes, villages, ſtretes, and the moſte daungerous and ſlippery places of Thrace and the leſſer Aſia), ſeuen times I haue ben ſold vnto moſt peineful and manifolde kindes of huſbandry: and there conſtrained vnder the turkiſh ruſtical whippe and ſharpe ordinances, in hungar and

thirſt, in colde and nakednes, lying a brode out of houſe, to kepe horſes, and fede flockes of ſheepe and 
                  •
               eardes, to learne the arte of warrefare, and exerciſe tylling of ground, From whence taking flight, and lyuinge by the maſt of Okes, by wilde herbes, and ther bitter rootes ſprinkeled with a litle ſalte, and wandring in deſertes, beholdinge the north pole as my guide, I haue bene enuironed with moſte rauenous wilde beaſtes, I haue moreouer, on plankes of timber, bound together with a corde, endeuored to paſse ouer the ſea Helleſponte: but beinge taken at length, brought back againe vnto my maſter, bound hand and foote, caſt proſtrat on the earthe, and greuoſly beaten with roddes, I was after caſt of vnto the vnmercifull regraters of mankinde, and

ſlaughterous boutchers to be ſolde: ſo that toſsed with the fluddes of aduerſitie by the ſpace of thirtene yeares, I haue bene forced to ſuffer and ſuſteine manye miſeries, afflictions, calamities and perſecutions, throughe ye loue that I bare vnto oure holye and catholyke faith, But when I could not eſcape by that more nere way, which is throughe Thrace ſuche tirannye, greuous bondage, and cruell affliction of the Infidelles, flying by an other way, whyche is to wit, towardes the pole Antartike, throught the moſt daungerous places, and deſartes of Caramania and Siria.
            
               Throughe ſoudrie perilles on the lande
               And daungers ſtraung bi ſeas and ſande.
            
            At length I came into the holy lande, vnto the Fryars of Saincte Frances, by Ieruſalem, dwelling in the mounte

Sion. From whence after the courſe of 
                  •
               ne yere, raiſed (by goddes prouidence) 
                  •
               s it were from the dead, taken out of the mouth and iawes of that rauenous and inſatiable dragon, and deliuered from his rackinges and tormentes, I came vnto my brethren the chriſtians 
                  •
               as an vndouted meſsanger of their pu
               
                  •
               niſhementes, that they may do worthy 
                  •
               penance for ther errors and offences, leſt thei com into that place of tormēts and affliction: that they may vnderſtande alſo in what hatred thei ought to be, whiche hinder from that moſte holy and longe deſired expedition the chriſtian ſworde, in time to come, to be the reuenger of our miſeries, foreſhewed ſo many yeres ſence, as well by the propheticall mouthe of trewe beleuers as infidelles, and predeſtinated to deſtroye

and vterly ſubuert that kingedome of Sathan, when therfore after my pergerinatiō throuh the holi land and viſitinge of certayne places in the w
                  •
               ſte partes, I had briefly noted the tragidyes of theyr crueltye, and certayne other thynges whych by remayninge in the court and warrefare of of the Turkiſh emperour, I had learned, eyther by daily conuerſation long vſe, and experience, or ſuche as I had hearde the learned and wiſer ſorte of the ſame, to rearde and rexearſe, or (in time paſt mencioned and readen) vnderſtode to be queſtioned by their ſageſt coūcellours, and committed thē to memory: all, in fewe wordes and faithefully written, at ſondry places and diuers times, by peece meale, I had publiſhed, after with publiſhing, when by

certayne learned and well diſpoſed men, I had found them made commō, diſperſed into diuers languages, and perceyued that they woulde be profitable, expediente, and after a ſorte neceſsarie vnto the readers, I gathered the whole into this one bondell, and nowe brought &amp; reduced it vnto a more compendious order. I offer them, moſte gentile and Chriſtian reder, of thee to be redden. Thou therfore by the example of oure ſauiour Chriſt (which preferred the litle gifte offred by a poore widoiſhe woman, before the riche preſentes of ſo many Princes) voucheſafe to take and accepte in good parte this ſimple gifte of a poore afflicted Pilgrime. ❀
         
      
      
         
            
            
            ❀ The Originall beginning of the Turkishe Empyre and Lineall Race of theyr Emperours, vvyth the trade and Ordinaunces of theyr warres
            
               THat the Turkes are lineally deſcended frō the Barbarous Nation of the Scithians, not onely all the auncyente Hyſtoryographers do witneſſe, but alſo ther maners, face, countenāces, pryde, raſhenes, wonderfull audacity, &amp; finallye al their trade and order in fightyng doth it moſte euidently declarē. They ſixe hundred yeres ſence, entring into the leſſer Aſia, which now hath to name Natholia, committed ther infinite ſpoilinges, and robberies, vntill by litle and litle they had brought ſubiect to their empire inheritances, caſtels, and cyties, and oppreſſed the inhabitantes

of Aſia the leſſer, whiche hadde not bene accuſtomed to fightinge, and warres. Neyther at that time had the Turkes any certaine Prince or Kynge, but, rouing abrode by flockes, ouerrane, brought vnder their ſubiectiō, and cruellye raygned ouer the noble countreye of al the leſſer Aſia. But afterwarde when thre hundred thouſande footmen and an hundred thouſand horſmen of the Chriſtians had aſſembled and gathered together vnto the moſte renowmed Duke Gottfridus Bilioneus, and paſſed ouer the Sea to poſſeſſe and inhabite the holye lande, where was the ſepulcher of our redemer Ieſus Chriſte: the Turkes alſo flocking together, created one Soliman ther Captaine, &amp; ſo made warre agaynſt the Chriſtians. But after a cruell and blouddye battell, they were by the ſayde Chriſtians vanquiſhed and put to flight. From this time foreward we reade not that the Turkes had any Prince, vntill

the yeare after Chriſtes incarnation a thouſand and thre hundred, about which ſeaſon at lenght Ottomannus began to wexe famous, and being of great powr
                  •
                and ſtrenght, was created firſt Emperour of the Turkes, from whom al the reſt, as the table enſewing ſhall plainely declare, conſequently tooke ther beginninge.
            
               
               A brefe reherſall of al the Emperours of Turkeye
               
               
                  Otthomannus,
                  
                     OTthomannus firſte Emperour of the Turkes, whiche was of the turkiſhe nation as it wer the grandfather, &amp; from whom all the other Princes of Turkey do take their name, was fortunate, victorious, and a very cruell tyrant. He raigned eight and twentye yeares, and dyed in the yeare of our Lorde, a thouſande, thre hundred, twenty and eight.
               
               
                  Oreanus,
                  
                     OReanes ſecōd Emperour of the Turkes, was ſubtil &amp; wittye, he inuented ſondrye ſortes of inſtrumentes and Enginnes of warre, and gouerned the Empire two &amp; twentie yeares.
               
               
                  Amurathes,
                  
                     AMurathes the ſonne of Oreanes and

third Emperour of the Turkes, beynge a young man, was diſceiful, circumſpect and vigilant. In the yeare of Chriſte a thouſande thre hundred thre ſcore and thre he poſſeſſed by force of armes Adrianopolis, and raygned thre and twentye yeares.
               
               
                  Baiazetus,
                  
                     BAiazetus the firſt of that name &amp; forth Emperour of ye Turkes, was victorious, but a famous and cruell tyrant. He brought in ſubiection to his Empire almoſt all Grece, and was at lenghte vanquiſhed by the moſt mighty Tamberlane.
                  
               
               
                  Cyriskelebes,
                  
                     CYriskelebes the ſōne of Baiazetus, and fifte Emperour of the Turkes, came vnto the Empire beynge a very younge man. He fought a battel with Sigiſmundus Emperour of Rome, whiche at that preſent was king of Hungarye, ouercam

and put him to flight in the felde called Salumbetus. He dyed beinge yet of youthely yeares, &amp; rained about ſixe yeares.
               
               
                  Moiſes,
                  
                     MOiſes was ſixt Emperour of ye Turkes. After yt he had ſlaine Oreanes his brothers ſōne, he obteined ye turkiſh Empire, but not lōg gouerned the ſame. For he was alſo murthered by Mahometus brother vnto Oreanes ſlaine of him before, which after the death of Moiſes brought vnder his ſubiection the Empire of Turkey.
               
               
                  Mahometus,
                  
                     MAhometus the firſt of that name, &amp; ſeuenth Emperour of Turks was notable throughe his cruelty. He weakened in many battells the ſtrenght of the Walachians, &amp; oppreſſed them. He raigned fouretene yeares, and dyed in the yeare from Chriſtes incarnation a thouſande foure hundred and nintene.
               
               
                  
                  Amurathes,
                  
                     AMurathes the ſeconde of this name, &amp; eight Emperour of the Turkes was full of guile and cruel. He firſt inuented, and eſtabliſhed the order of Ianitzaries, of whome it ſhalbe ſpoken hereafter. He raigned yeares thirty one, and died in the yeare of chriſtian health, a thouſand four hundred and fiftye.
               
               
                  Mahometus.
                  
                     MAhometus of that name the ſecond, ninth Emperour of ye Turkes, was bolde, of great audacitye ſtubborne, and raſh. He toke Conſtantinople in the yere from Chriſtes incarnation, a thouſande four hundred fifty and thre, the nine and twenty day of may, and was Emperour thirty and two yeares.
               
               
                  Baiazetus.
                  
                     BAiazetus called the ſecond of that name, tenth Emperour of ye Turkes, by

force of warre ſubdewed all Moldauia, and brought it in ſubiection to his Empire. Beſides that he fought many, gret, and perilous battels, at the whiche he was preſent in his owne perſon among his ſouldiers. He raigned thirty and one yeares.
               
               
                  Selimus,
                  
                     SElimus eleuenth Emperour of ye Turkes was marueilous cruel. He poiſoned his Father, and by that meanes obteined the turkiſhe Empire, in the yeare of our Lorde God a thouſande fiue hundred and twelue. Afterwarde when he had ſubdewed the great Sultan, he ſacked the moſt populons citye Alkairum, and raigned but eight yeares, at what tyme he was iuſtly puniſhed for his crueltye.
               
               
                  Solymannus,
                  
                     SOlymannus the ſonne of Selimus and twelueth Emperour of the Turkes, whiche reigned in our time, but now is

ſaide to be dead, was for our ſinnes and offences fortunate and victorious. By him wer ſubdewed ye Grecian city Alba, with Rhodes. And after that he had vanquiſhed kyng Ludouicus, he adioyned alſo to his Empire, Buda, Strigonium, Alba Regalis, and many other cityes of Hungarye. He alſo in the yeare of our Lorde a thouſand fiuehundred twentye and nyne beſeged Vienna, wher from by helpe of the ſone of God, whom he hathe as his enemye, he was driuen away.
               
            
            
               
               In what maner the Turkes do vſe to make vvarres.
               
               
                  AFter that the Turkes had vanquiſhed the ſtrenght &amp; powre of the Macedonians, thei kept and imitated ther traininge vp of ſouldiers, warrelike diſcipline, and maner in gouerning, althoughe in euery particuler point they agre not. Wherfore ther harneis being coates of maile, they ar accuſtomed to fight with ſpere, ſhilde, and ſwordes croked in the backe lyke our woode kniues, and often times proue conquerours. It is moſt certain that the Ianitzaries do nothing at all differ from the moſt picked ſouldiers of Macedonia, by whoſe martiall prowes Alexander the great, vanquiſhed the inhabitantes of the Eaſterne partes, and brought thē in ſubiection to his Empire. They bring vp, exerciſe, and inſtructe them euen frō
                  
their infancye in fighting and the warres. Not one amonge them doth knowe either his parentes, or kniſefolke. They ar (to ſaye the truth) the children of chriſtians, rauiſhed and taken awaye at ſondrye robberies, and ſpoiling conqueſtes, whiche beyng brought into the orcharde of the turkiſhe Prince, they practiſe and traine vp in warrelike feates and exerciſes, wherby in time to come, they may be haue and defend thē ſelues more mā
                  fully in the forefront of their battelles. If any of them chaunce to dye, or to bée ſlaine in the felde, eyther at the aſſaute of any citie ſtrong caſtell, or other mightye places of defence, incontinent they ordaine and ſubſtitute in ther places, certaine of thoſe ſo exactly exerciſed and inſtructed yong menne, and by that meanes fil vp the member. By reaſon wher of the bande of Ianitzaries, whiche is is it were the fortreſſe and harte of all the powre and ſtrength of the Turkes, doth

alwaies confinew vndeminiſhed. They haue not equal ſtipendes, but euery one hath a penſion: according to his propre manlines and puiſant dedes atchiued.
               And this is the onelye cauſe why they proue ſo deſperate prompt and ready to attempt all kynde of valiant actes and aduentures, as of late yeares wée haue of them bene taught and certifyed, not withe out oure greate grefe, domage, and diſcommodytie. For euen ſithens the time of Amurathes the ſecond, which firſt conſtituted the Ianitzaries, and diſpoſed them in this order, we neuer reade that they loſte the vniuerſall and hole ſtrenght of any generall armye, but by experience haue rather knowen them, to be the victours and conquerours.
               The Turkes do mainteine &amp; kepe with ſuche iuſtice and ſeueritie the diſcipline of war, the lawes and cuſtomes in battell, that in this behalfe they maye ſeme farre to paſſe ye 
                  Gretiās &amp; Romains. Ther

neuer chaunceth amonge them, eyther diuiſions, mutual ſlaughters, ſeditions, or treaſon. For they ar fourthe with beheaded, being but for a trifeling offence conuicted. The turkiſh ſouldiers in many reſpectes do ſurmount the warriours of other nations. Firſt of all they readily obeye, with out grudging or diſdaine, their Prince &amp; Captaines, which is not obſerued among vs. Secōdly al thoughe they be enforced with moſte vrgent neceſſitie, yet they neuer take flight, but rather aſſaile and fight more deſperatly. For they fully beleue that by celeſtiall prouidēce it is determined at what time, and after what ſorte euerye mane ſhall ende his lyfe and dye, and therfore they thinke that no miſfortune may chaunce vnto them before the prefixed houre.
               Finally in as muche as they ar endurable &amp; moſt patiēt, a lōg ſpace of time they can ſuſteine thē ſelues with out bred or wine, with only water and rice.
               
                  
                  ❀ The Officers perteinning to the greate Turkes Courte and vvarres, vvith the diſpoſition of the ſame, and diuerſities of his ſouldiers.
                  
                     Viſier Baſsae,
                     
                        VIſier Baſsae are Councellours to the turkiſhe Emperour: For with theſe he accuſtometh to deliberate &amp; conſulte of all his buſines and affaires. They ar in number foure, and are choſen by the Emperour him ſelfe, of the multitude of thoſe, whiche haue forſaken Chriſt, and of Chriſtians ar bée come Turkes, yea ther haue bene founde to proue of them more worſe then the Turkes thē ſelues Their authorytye and powre is of great eſtimation, and they are of marueilous riches and ſubſtance.
                  
                  
                     Lesker Kadie
                     
                        LEsker Kadie are ye chefe Judges, whiche determine, &amp; diſcide, be they neuer

ſo many, all contentions, and controuerſies of warre. The one hath his ſeat in in Romania, the other in Natolia. Theire office is to declare the lawe, ſit in iudgement, and the cauſes of as manye as ar brought before them, to decyde accordyng to the lawes of Mahomet. Unto theſe do apeale and reſort all the other inferiour Judges named alſo Kadie, and in their powre it lyeth to geue iudgement of any controuerſie, be it neuer of ſo great weight.
                  
                  
                     Beglerbeg,
                     
                        BEglerbeg he hath the ſoueraintye of al other Captaines, &amp; is chefe Prince of warrefare, or one that ſupplieth ye chefe Princes rome. Ther ar two Beglerbegs, and they haue the dominion ouer them that ar named Szantſakbegler. The one hath his abode in Natōlia at Cutheia a citye of Galatia, the other in Romania in a citie of the Ruſcians, whiche of them is

called Sophia.
                     
                  
                  
                     Tepthedar
                     
                        Tepthedar in their lāguage doth ſignify a boke, in the which reckoninges and accoūptes ar writen. Wherof they haue their name Tepthedar. They ar ye Queſtours, or Treaſourers. The one in Ramania, the other in Natolia do receyue an accounte of the yearly profites, and reuenewes, throughe out the whole turkiſhe Empire, and of all rentes and expenſes. They ar of great authoritye an eſtimation in the courtes of Princes.
                  
                  
                     Iereys,
                     
                        Iereys is Prince of the battels fought vpon the ſea, and warres about the ſea coaſtes, whiche alwaies is choſeu out of the nomber of them wyche are named Szantſakbegler, or Liuetenantes whyche gouerne Calliopolis. He hath the charge of thre hundred ſhippes, all whiche are gouerned by ſailes.
                  
                  
                     
                     Moderie,
                     
                        Moderis are menne learned in the conſtitutions, decres, and ordinaunces of Mahomet, wiſe, and of meruelous experience, and therfore they are all generallye called by this name.
                  
                  
                     Muthi,
                     
                        Muthi are lawiers, of the whiche one is elected to be as principall Doctor of the lawe, whoſe apointmente or deciding it is not lawefull for any manne to retracte or call againe. If any obſcure &amp; darke places are founde in the lawes, theſe are conſulted concernynge the interpretation therof.
                  
                  
                     Iaziti.
                     
                        Iaziti are diuers ſcribes in the courtes of turkiſhe Princes, howbeit they vſe ſondrye languages and letters. For in Turkeye they ſpeake and writte withe their propre ſpech and letters. In Grece

and Italye with the tounge and letters of the Grecians. But in Pannonia and Moldauia are accuſtomed in writing the language and letters of the Raſcians. The Turkes do call all the ſcribes by one name Iaziti.
                     
                  
                  
                     Spahioglani.
                     
                        Spahi in their 
                           •
                        ong betokeneth noble, and Oglan doth ſignifye a younge man or ſonne, wherof they haue to name Spahioglani, and they are the principall borſemene in the turkiſhe armye, brought vp in the Emperours Orchard, and are called his ſonnes. Out of ye band of theſe are choſen ſuch as they call Szantſakbegler, after that his Legates or Embaſſadours. The ful number of thē is a thouſande▪ beinge apparaled with gorgeous and riche ornamentes, they ride by the Emperours right ſyde. Euery one of thē hath ſeuē or eight ſouldiers vnder him.
                  
                  
                     Soluphthari
                     
                        
                        Soluphthari, theſe are hrought vp together with the Spahioglans, and are equivalent vnto them in powre and dignity. Their number alſo is a thouſand, being cladde in moſte fine and ſumptuous robes thei go by the Emperours lefte ſide.
                  
                  
                     Capiti.
                     
                        Capi in the turkiſhe language dothe ſignifie a Gate, of the which their name deriued is Capici. They are the kepers or porters of the Princes Gates, whiche are maruelouſly eſtemed, and aduaunced to highe dignities. They are elected out of the bande of Ianitzaries. The number of them is fourhundred.
                  
                  
                     Vlufagi.
                     
                        Vlufagi are a thouſande horſemene ſo called, choſen from the troupe of Ianitzaries, or pycked ſouldiers of the Baſsaens, whiche haue made manifeſt by ſome famous or notable acte their fidelytye and manlye prowes. They kepe the thirde

ranke after the Emperour of Turkye.
                  
                  
                     Caripiti.
                     
                        Caripiti, theſe alſo are horſemene, in number a thouſande. And euen as their horſes are quicke and ſwifte, ſo are they alſo endewed with wonderfull audacity and ſwiftenes. Thei vſe and arme them ſelues with bow, arrowes, ſhilde, 
                           •
                        ere, and croked ſwordes, and haue ſtipendes verye large.
                  
                  
                     Solakhi.
                     
                        Solakhi, are the principall and beſt apointed ſouldiers. Theſe alſo are choſen frome the bande of Ianitzaries, whyche ar marueilous ſkilful in ſhewing with arrowes, and are practiſed and accuſtomed, aboue all the reſt, in ſhewtinge thē of moſt ſtreight vnto ye prefixed marke. Their number is ſeuen hundred, whoſe offyce is to enuiron and ſafegarde the Emperour with their arrowes nocked.
                  
                  
                     Ianitzaraga.
                     
                        
                        Ianitzaraga. By this name is called the Chefteine of the Ianitzaries, which hath vnder him Peticapteines, of whom certeine haue the gouernmēte ouer a thouſande, other of fiue hundred. Ther are beſydes theſe Centurions, and captaines ouer tenne. Vnder whoſe dominion do the reſt of the Ianitzaries lead a moſte quiet lyfe.
                  
                  
                     Ianitzari,
                     
                        Ianitzari are footmen in nūber twelue thouſande, moſt valiant, of marueilous practiſe, &amp; ſtronge ſouldiers, vnto whoſe fidelity the turkiſhe Emperour is wont thefelye to credite and committe hym ſelfe. They vſe long Gunnes, out of the whyche they ſhowte fourthe pellettes with great ſwiftnes, &amp; ſtrike the marke or thinge whervnto they ſend the ſame.
                  
                  
                     Beſlie,
                     
                        Beſlie, are alſo ſouldiers moſt famous and exerciſed, whiche haue declared notable

actes of their ſtrenght. Euery one of them receiueth the ſtipendes of fiue ſouldiers, and are almoſt in nūber fourhundred.
                  
                  
                     Mutapharak
                     
                        Mutapharak, are the ſonnes of greate Princes, miniſters or ſeruantes of the Emperour, they enioye aboundant lybertye, and ſuſteine no trauels, ſauinge that they ſtande before the turkiſh Emperour, obſerue, waite vpon, and accumpanye him.
                  
                  
                     Czauſi.
                     
                        Czauſi, theſe do cary clubbes in their handes, they order and diſpoſe the hoſte. They goe alſo before the Prince in the armye, and make him waye, as hereafter it ſhalbe declared againe. Ther are of them thrée hundred. Whoſe help and aide, the turkiſhe Emperour is alſo accuſtomed to vſe in Ambaſſadges.
                  
                  
                     Gimlie,
                     
                        
                        Gimlie. Theſe ſouldiers are formeſſangers, which haue horſes moſt ſwifte, and when neceſſitye requireth, can ryde and diſpatche a great ſpace of grounde in one night. They are couered with coates of maile, and fight with ſhild ſpe
                        
                           •
                        es and croked ſwordes.
                  
                  
                     Alcantzi,
                     
                        Alcantzi be horſemen of the loweſt eſtate or degre, they are cruell waſters and ſpoilers, whiche, in as much as they goe to warre, onely for their priuate cō
                        modities ſake (for no ſpoiles or booty is wonte to be exacted at their hādes) they waſte and conſume euerye thinge with fyre and ſworde. The multitude of them is great, for they excead the number of thirty thouſande.
                  
                  
                     Mekther
                     
                        Mekther, are miniſters of the turkiſhe Prince, whiche are ordeined to purge, make cleane, and decke vp the houſes of

the Emperour of Turkeye. Theſe haue the charge of al the hanginges of tapeſtrye and arras. They kepe the tentes of the turkiſhe Emperour, when he goeth vnto any warre.
                  
                  
                     Aſappi,
                     
                        Aſappi are footemene verye ſkilefull in ſhowetinge of arrowes, ſent from the cities of Turkeye, the help the turkiſhe Emperour in time of warre Euery one of them, for the ſtipende of one moneth, dothe receiue thrée turkyſhe peace of goulde.
                  
               
            
         
         
            
            ❀ The Turkishe rites and ceremonies. The forme of the turkiſhe temple, of the reſort therunto, and order in praiinges.
            THey haue temples of a competēt largenes, and ſumptuous, called in their language Meſchit, in the which I ſaue at all no images or pictures, ſauinge theſe woordes writen in the Arabian tounge: La Illah Illellah. Mehemmet, Ireſul, Allab, Taure Bir Pegambir Hath: which is as much to ſaye as, their is no god but one, and Mehemmet his prophet, one receatour, and the reſt of his Prophets equall. Or theſe Fila Galib Illelah, whiche thuſe maye be engliſhed, their is none ſo ſtronge as God. After that their is to be ſene a gret multitude of Lāpes burning with oyle, all the temple whitlimed, the pauement

couered with mattes, and bewtiſyed frō aboue with hangings of tapiſtre worke. Not farre from the temple, their is a toure or turret of exceading height, whiche their preſt aſcēdinge before the time of prayer repeatethe theſe wordes thriſe, with a loude voyce, his eares ſtopped with his fingers: Allah Hechber whych doth ſignifye, their is one trewe God. Whoſe voyce beyng hearde, bothe the noble and baſer ſorte of mene reſort vnto the church, they are ſo geuen, and addicted vnto deuotion. Then the forenamed preſte comming downe doth praye with them, and ſo is he bounde to doe fiue times within the ſpace of a daye and night, by his office. But as manye as come vnto the prayer Church, ought firſt to waſhe their handes, féete, and pryuy partes: after ye thriſe they ſprincle water vpon their beades, rehearſinge theſe wordes: Elhemdu Lillahi, wiche is, glorie be to my God. Laſte of all their

ſhoes put of, called Patſmagh, and lefte before the dore of the temple, they enter in: ſome with bare feet, other hauinge cleane ſhowes named Meſth, with the which they tread not one the bare earth. The turkiſhe women neuer kepe cumpanye, and ſitte with the menne, but a part in a place altogether ſeparete from their ſighte and hearinge: and they ſeldome frequente the temple, but at the time Bairam of Eaſter, and nowe and then on the Frydaies, which in their lā
               guage is named Gſumaagun, they praye from the nynthe houre of the night vnto the twelueth of the ſame, which is myddenighte: and in the time of their praier, they marueilouſlye beate and torment their bodyes with continuall mouynge and exclamations, in ſuche wiſe that often times deſtitute of ſtrenght and remembrance, they fal flatte one the earth and if any of them from that time foreward ſhal féele her ſelfe to be with child,

ſhe affirme the to haue cōceyued by vertue of the holye ghoſte. And when they are deliuered, the children borne of them are called Nefes Oglu, wich is Soules, or children of the holye ghoſte. So was it declared vnto me by theyr waitinge maides: for I neuer ſawe it, neither is it permitted that any man ſhoulde be preſent at that ſpectacle. But at the prayers of the men I haue bene oftē times with my maiſter, whoſe maner and cuſtome is ſuche. While their prayer endureth, they put not of their bonettes (wyche in their toūg are named Tſalma) but touch them with the toppes of their fingers, as thoughe they were about to lifte thē vp, they knele on their knées and kyſſe often the earthe. A heinous déed among theim it is accounted that a Chriſtian ſhould be permitted to their prayers: for they beleue (as it is reported among thē) their churches to be defiled by ſuche vncleanely perſons. For the Chriſtians accuſtome

not thoſe often frequented waſ
               
                  •
               hinges, acordinge to their cuſtome. Ther the preſte goeth vp vnto the pul
               
                  •
               itte, and preachethe about the ſpace of 
                  •
               wo howers: his Sermon being finiſhed 
                  •
               wo boyes ſupply ye roome, with ſinging pronounce their praiers. Which alſo en
               
                  •
               ed, the preſte beginneth with all the people in a lowe voyce to ſinge (ſhakyng his head from one ſyde to an other) no other but theſe wordes, La Illah Illelah, whoſe meaning is, ther is but one god, and ſo the ſpace almoſt of halfe an houre 
                  •
               he ſhaketh him ſelfe, and ſoundethe the prayers with his voyce. But 
                  ••
               ch kynde of prayers and ceremonies, as ſinginge and Sermons are not vſed euerye daye, ſauynge in the time of Lente, and on a feſtiuall daye, as Thurſdaye, from the ninthe houre of the night vnto the twelueth. And of ſome Frydaye is moſt religiouſly obſerued.
            
               
               Of the Turkes Lent, vvhen They kepe it and hovve their Eaſter is obſerued.
               ALent they haue alſo, in their propre language called Orutz, wherin euerye yeare they faſt the ſpace of one Monethe and a weke, but not alwayes one, and the ſame, for if this yeare they faſte Januarye, the next folowing they abſteyne in Februarye, goinge in order, ſo that in the courſe of twelue yeares, thei faſte a yeare, and the twelue wekes are offredde vnto God in ſtéede of a Tenth. In the time of their faſting, they taſt all the daye of no kynde of meate, no not ſo muche as of bredde or water. But after the ſight of a ſtarre, it is lawfull for thē the féede on all ſortes of meates, excepting ſtranguled, and the fleſh of Swine. Stranguled meate of thē is called Murdar, whiche doth ſignifie a deade, or vncleane carcas, and the ſwine Domutes. The Lent finiſhed they celebreate the

feaſt of Eaſter, in their mother ſpeache 
                     •…
                  ned Bairam, with marueilous ſolemytie, by the ſpace of thre dayes, anoyn
                  
                     •
                  nge the nayles of their handes &amp; féete 
                     •
                  ith a certaine oyntment by thē named 
                     •
                  hna, whiche cauſethe their nayles to 
                     •
                  liſter: they ſteigne with the ſame oynt
                  
                     •
                  ente alſo, the tayles and féete of their 
                     •
                  ouſes: thys colour ſticketh very faſte, 
                     •
                  nd cane not eaſely be wéeped or waſ
                  
                     •
                  ed awaye: wherfore excepte new nay
                  
                     •
                  s encreaſe out of the rootes, they all
                  
                     •
                  ayes apeare gliſtringe, but from the 
                     •
                  andes with often and continewal waſhyng it maye he weipte out. The women not only infecte their nailes, but alſo their handes and féete with the ſame Oyntemente.
            
            
               ❀ The maner of the turkiſne circumciſion, after vvhat ſort it is done, and of their names.
               THey vſe Circunciſion called in theyr propre ſpech Tſuneth, not on ye eighte

daye, accordynge to the cuſtome of th
                     •
                   Jewes, but after the childes birth whe he is in the age of ſeuen or eyghte yeares, then ſkilefull in ſpeaking their language: and that ceremonye is obſerued amonge them at that time, for the wordes of confeſſyon, whiche are required before the circumciſion (the Thumbe of his hande called Larmath, lifted vp) and they are thoſe to witte, that before we haue mentioned to bée written in their temples. And the childe is not brought vnto the chuch, but circumciſed at home in his parentes houſe, At this ſolemnity haue I ben often preſent, which is done after this maner. Firſt of all their frindes are called together to a bankete, for whom of dayntye diſhes, ther are ſufficient prepared, of all kyndes of fleſhe, ſuche as they may lawfully féede on, and here and ther, (as among the richer ſort) is ſlaine an Oxe, in the which (flean, &amp; his boweles taken out), they encloaſe a

ſheepe, in the ſhepe a henne, and in the henne an egge, all whiche holye together are roſted in honour of that daye.
               After that at the time of their banketing and feaſt, the childe is brought fourth to bée circumciſed, then the Phiſition or Surgion ſeruinge for that purpoſe, openeth the mitte of his yarde, and taketh the ſkinne folded in a crampe wire, ſōne after whereby to rydde the childe from feare, he ſayeth that ye circunciſion ſhalbe deferred vntill the nexte daye, and ſo departeth, not longe betwine, fayninge as thoughe ſome thynge were omitted or forgotten, whiche neceſarye appertaineth to the accōpliſhinge of that acte, vpō a ſodaine he cutteth of peace of that ſkinne, whiche couereth the heade of the childes yarde, putting vpon the wound a litle ſalte and ſofte ſilke thenſe fourth he ſhalbe called Muſulman, which is circumciſed, and they haue no names geuē them on the daye of circumciſion, but at

their very birthe, when firſte they are brought into light and this worlde, whiche are theſe, and firſte of kynges as Suleiman, interpreted Solomon Sultan Stelim, whiche is a Prince of peace Murath Begh, a deſyred ruler: Muſtapha &amp; ſuche like. Of captaines as Pirin, Haradon, Hader, Ebrahim. And the names of lordes of the meaner condition are Spahalar, Sauſlar, Eminler, Behram, Memmi Mehē
                     met, Alli, Ahmat, Tcielebi, Paiazith, Chatſun, Hutſcref. Vnto all the reſte, Mutſa, Ionutz, Sthender, Perhat, Ferro. Their captiues and bondemene, for the greater parte are called Seremeth, which name ſignifyeth a bolde and ſpedye ſeruante. From that time forewarde the feaſt continewing by the ſpace of three dayes, the circumciſed childe is brought with a moſte ſolemne triumphe vnto a Bathe. And in retourning home, he is leade by the gueſtes and banketters, which offer giftes vnto him before prouided:

ſome ſilke garmentes, ſome ſiluer cuppes, other mony or horſes. The womē alſo preſent him with ſhirtes, naptkinnes, and other ſuche like. Euerye of the feaſters geueth acording to his pleaſure, habilytye, or riches. The women are not at all circumciſed, but confeſſing only the fornamed wordes, are counted Mulſuman But if any amonge the chriſtians of his voluntarye will, graunting him ſelfe to bée a Mehemmetiſte, dothe ſuffer circumciſion whiche not ſeldome chaūceth by reaſon of the moſt greuous yoke and burthen of tribute, he is caried throughe all the ſtreates &amp; highe wayes of the cytye, with great honour and ioye of all the people, playing vpon timbrelles: vnto him alſo are geuen certain giftes, after that he is made frée frō paying any tribute, in their mother tounge called Haracs. And throughe gredines of this lucre and aduantage, manye of the Grecians, whiche they call Vlumlar, and

Albanians, that are named Arnautla haue bene circumciſed. If anye manne forced by vyolence, as one whiche hath ſtroken a Mulſuman, miſuſed him with reproche, or blaſphemed Mehemmet wiche I ſawe chaunce vnto a certaine Biſhoppe of the Grecian religion) be circumciſed, ther is no thing geuen vnto him, albeit he ſhalbe diſcharged from paying any tribute, as the reſte Mulſulmanlar, whiche is of the circumciſed are.
            
            
               ¶ Of the turkiſhe Preſtes by vvhome they are elected, and hovv thei liue.
               THe preſtes, which in their ſpeche are called Taliſmanlar▪
                   do very litle or no thinge at all differ from the laye people, neither from the chefe miniſters of their ceremonies (which amonge vs are. Biſſhoppes) and no depe learnynge is to be required in them, it is ſufficiente if they are of abilytye too reade the Alkaron and Muſſaphus. But they that canne interprete them accordynge to the texte, are

counted profundely learned: becauſe thei were not deliuered by Mehemmet in the vulgare turkiſhe toung, but in the Arabian language, for they counte it a heinous matter if beynge interpreted they ſhould be writen in their mother ſpeche. Theſe preſtes are elected by the people, but receyue a ſtipende for their labour of the kinge: they haue wiues and their apparell is lyke vnto ſeculer menne. If the ſtipende be not ſufficiente for them to lyue, throughe the multitude of their children, they vſe ſome handye crafte, and handle ſome ſuche occupation, as maye be thought worthye a frée manne, they become ſchole maſters and writte bookes, I ſaue verely no printers among them, but they dreſſe their paper verye finelye. The reſt doo vſe other meanes for aduantage and games, as the occupatiōs of Showemakers, Tailers, and ſuche lyke.
            
            
               
               ¶ The feſtes of the turkiſhe Munkes and maner of ther liuinge.
               THer are not wantinge amonge them Munkes called Deruiſlar, of diuers ſortes verely, but chefely of thrée orders. The firſt order is of thoſe, which hauing no one thinge propre, goo as it were naked, ſauing their pryuye partes are couered with ſhepes ſkinnes, and likwiſe in the time of extreme coldnes, they vſe the ſame ſkinnes to couer their backes: but their ſydes, handes, féete, and head, they couer at all with no garmente. Requeſting almes as wel of the chriſtians as Turkes, they deſyre it Alahiſi, which dothe ſignifye for gooddes ſake. Theſe Munkes deuourynge the herbe called Maſ
                        •
                     ath, are driuen into a madnes, in ſo muche that they wounde them ſelues, and draw a launce from one ſide of their breaſt ouerth wart vnto the other, after, that alongeſt their armes, without ſhewinge fourthe any token of grefe: and

remoue not the kindlede drye ſtickes of trées layed vpon their head, breaſt, and hands, vntil they be reſolued in to aſſes. I ſawe an other ſecte whiche forebidden carnal copulation with women, goe, the fore parte of their yarde, or the ſecrete parte it ſelfe perced throughe, and therin encloaſed an iron ringe of the weight of thrée poundes to obſerue chaſtitye.
               The third order ſeldome goeth abroad, but doth remaine day and nyght in temples, hauing litle cabines in the corners of thoſe churches, with out ſhowes, garmentes, and bare headed, hauinge nothyng about them, exceptyng one ſhirte. faſtinge the ſpace of manye dayes, and prayinge, that God woulde reueale vnto them the eſtate of thynges to come, withe whom the turkiſhe, beyng about, and entendynge to ſtirre or make warre accuſtometh to conſulte.
            
            
               
               ¶ Of the marueillous reūerence vvhich the Turkes exhibite vnto the traditions of Mehemmet.
               THe Turkes attribute ſuch reuerence vnto the traditions &amp; decrées of Mahomet, yt not only god they blaſpheme note (which chaunceth often among vs) yea if they but finde, a ſcroll, in what facion ſoeuer it be writen, lyinge on the earth, taking it vp, and often times kiſſed, they encloaſe the ſame, throuſte into ſome chenke of the wal: for it is counted a ſynne, that the letters, wherwithe the name of God, and lawes of Mahomet are writen, ſhoulde be trode vnder their féete. And therefore no manne dare to ſell an Alkaron, or anye other of their writinges vnto a chriſtian, or mane of ſome other faith and religion, leſt being neglected and caſt awaye, they ſhould be troden vnder their féete, or touched with vncleane handes, if otherwiſe they are be headed. Wherefore in this reſpecte,

they can not verely but be preferred and eſtemed before vs.
            
            
               ❀ Of the Scholes for bothe kindes, and in vvhat artes they inſtructe their youthe.
               THey haue places apointed to trade in good letters their youthes of bothe kindes, called in their toung Ochumachgirleri, and teachers for the ſame whiche are named Hogſialar, howbeit ſeparatly they are inſtructed, as the male children by men, and young girles by women, in Aſtronomye, Philoſophye, and the arte of Poetrye. Durynge the time of their learnyng, ſpeaking in a ſhr
                     •
                  l voyce, they moue their bodyes from one ſyde to the other. They haue no ſkill in artifyciall Muſicke, but faine certaine vearſes by preſcribed rules, whiche are in this maner. Euerye vearſe ought too comprehende a leuen ſyllables. Wherefore it pleaſed me for an example to ſubſcribe theſe fewe.
            
            
               
               
                  ❧ Vearſes called of them Bethler.
               
                  Birechen bes on eiledum derdumi
                  Iarà dandam iſtemiſcem iardumi
                  Terch eiledum Zachmanumi gardumi
                  Ne ileim ieniemezum glunglumi
               
               They ar amorous vearſes, of a goddeſſe called in their language Aſsih, whyche is goddeſſe of loue, whoſe interpretation worde by worde is ſuche:

                     Birechen, bes on, eiledum, derdumi:
                  
                  
                     Of on, fifty, I haue mad, in my tribulatiō
                     
                  
                  
                     Iara dadam, iſtemiſcem, iardumi:
                  
                  
                     Of my creatour, I haue required, ſuccour
                  
                  
                     Terch eiledum, Zachmanumi, gardumi:
                  
                  
                     I haue neglected, of my countrey, the viſitation.
                  
                  
                     Ne, ileim, ieniemezum, glunglumi.
                  
                  
                     What, ſhall I do? I can not ſubdew, my minde.
                  
               
            
            
               ☞ Hovve they contracte matrimonye, of their dovvries, and occaſion of deuorſe.
               
                  THer matrimonye called in their toūg Eulenmech, is done in this maner. They ioyne to gether in mariage with out any betrowething
                     •
                   made, they take their wiues without dowrye, and for the moſt parte are conſtrained to bye them, contrarye to that aunciente cuſtome, which in time paſt was vſed among the Romaines, wher the ſonne in law was wounte to be bought, and not the ſōnes wife. The ſpouſe hath no comelye deckynge or furniture about her body, whiche the bridegrome is not compelled to raūſome and by of his wyues parentes. Leude and vnſemelye behauiour or baraines cauſeth a diuorſe betwine them. Their Judge hathe certificate, and decydeth ſuche matters. Mariage is alſo permitted vnto them withe their bonde ſeruantes, but the children borne are counted in ſeruitude and boundage.
            
            
               ❀ Of their Pilgrimmes, and to vvhat places they goe in Pilgrimage.
               
                  PIlgrimes in their language called Hagfilar, do viſite the places by them counted ſacred and holye, whiche are Mecha, Medinus, (as our men Jeruſalē) wher they affirme that Machomet dyed, but no leſſe throughe hope of gaine, then for religion or deuotions ſake. Ther after the ſ
                     •
                  ght of a Shoe called Tſaroth, which gilted only, hangeth downe from the roofe or vaulte of the temple, and certaine moſte ſubtile nettes, named Chumas, bought, they departe with greate aduantage into their countrye. And in their retourne, ſome for deuotions ſake dothe carye water throughe the ſtreates, and offer the ſame ſrelye vnto the thyrſty, ſuche as they méete, other attende their propre buſines. And if anye, by what meanes ſo euer it be, happe to dye in the iorney, allthoughe they come not to Metha, yet are they accounted amonge the nomber of Pilgrimes.
               
                  ❀ The fooliſhe fayle vvriten by Mahomet in his Alkaron, and of the beaſt named El Barahil
               MAchomet write the in this Alkaron of two Angelles called Aroth and Maroth, whome he affirmethe to haue 
                     •
                  ene ſente by God into the earthe, that 
                     •
                  hey ſhoulde miniſter iuſtice and equitie 
                     •
                  nto menne, and were commaunded too 
                     •
                  rinke no wyne, neyther adioyne them ſelues in cōpanye with women, or ſhew 
                     •
                  nto any body the waye whiche leadeth to the place of perpetual bliſſednes, whi
                  
                     •
                  he tranſgreſſynge the commandement of God, becam drūke, deceiued by a woman, defyled them ſelues, and declared 
                     •
                  nto her the waye whyche to heauen bringeth, whome whē God ſawe comminge towardes heauen: he aſked the Angelles ſtandyng by him, who it was that endewed with ſuche a ſhape, would come into heauen. When the Angelles hadde affirmed that it was throughe the

folie of Aroth &amp; Maroth, God commaunded that the woman ſhoulde bée turned inta a Starre, but bidde them caſte the Angelles cheyned together into a burninge pitte foreuer ther to bée tormented. He maketh mention likewyſe of a beaſt named El barahil capable of the ſpeache of manne, whyche beaſte caried Machomet into heauen, wher he confeſſed to haue ſene great Angelles, hauing many heades, and thoſe heades to haue diuers and manifolde tōges. Theſe trulye ar rather toyes to mocke Apes withal, and vnworthy to be ſpoken by ſuche a prophet as they counte Machomet to be. But peraduenture well tipled with wine, he thought to haue dreamed in his dreames of ſuch miracles, or rather prodigious foliſhenes. Therfore in as much as he was not aſhamed to declare ſuche trifles, by mouth, but alſo to write them in his Alkaron, he ought deſeruedly not to be called a Prophet, but a falſe deceyuer, and malicious ſeducer frō the truth.
            
            
               
               ☞ Of the miracles vvrought at Mecha by Machomet, and of ſuche as they report him ther dailie to doe.
               I Doute, and am vncertaine whether they ought to be called miracles, or miraculous trifles, thoſe I meane which are writen in their boke named Mehemmedinum▪
                   For they ſtedefaſtlye affirme and throughely perſwade them ſelues, that, when Mecha ſhoulde bée builded, God throughe the prayers of Machomet gaue commaundement vnto the Hilles, that euery one ſhould bringe ſtones, for the erectynge and building vp of Mecha: and when all the hilles had brought the tenth of his ſtones, wherby Mecha was builded and finiſhed, a certaine hill named Araphatdagh beyng more ſlacke, by reaſon of his comming frō farre coaſtes, then ye reſt, whē he ſaw Mecha throughlye builded, and perceiued that they neaded not hys ſtones, began bytterlye too wepe. Whom whē Machomet had ſene

murning, and vnderſtode the cauſe of his lamentation, ſayde, lette not thy corage fainte the, and bée not ſorowefull, but laye downe ther (apointinge to the place with his finger) thy tenthe: &amp; whoſoeuer ſhall not praye vpon that ſtone, his pilgremage ſhalbe vnprofitable and vnthankefull. Then Machomet ſtroke the ſtone with his foote, &amp; brought water ther from, not good to be dronken of, and called it by name Abzemzemſui, which is water of purification, wherof al their Pilgrimes are accuſtomed to cary home with them in veſſelles: and when one chaunceth to die, the clothes wherin the dead carcas ſhalbe wrapped are ſprincled with that water, in remiſſyon of all his ſinnes and offences.
               They ſaye alſo that no man can come vnto Mecha, but his comminge is foreknowen by Machomet, which afterward to the kepers (&amp; they are all Eunuches) by hym is reuealed: but if that Hagij,
                  
whiche ſignifyeth Pilgrime, bée a thefe, a wicked perſone, chriſtian, or manne of oher ſuche like religion, the forenamed kepars doe prohibite him entrance into Mecha. But in deed his dead corps, as ſome affirme, lyethe not ther, but the ſhape of an image printed by the perſon of Machomet in a wall of the temple, whome they kyſſe, and ſo retourne vnto their habitation. Thoſe Infideles haue ſuche vaine lyes perſwaded vnto thē by Machomet, and a gret number mo to be laughed at, which here I am aſhamed to alleage. Howbeit I would that the gentyle reader, ſhoulde enquere of ſome Turke, whether ſuche thinges are ſo in déede, and then he ſhall bol
                     •
                  lye affirms that the Author hath ſpoken mere veretye and truthe.
            
            
               ❀ Of their almes houſes, and vvhat meate is geuen vnto the pore.
               THey haue hoſpitalles or almes houſes, called Imareth, builded by the teſtamentes

of their kinges, in whyche places meate or foode is geuen vnto the poore and Pilgrimmes, but diuerſly at ſondrye places. Ther are whyche geue Rice named Pirrincts Tſocbà, with fleſh: at an other place, Bolghdaias, whyche is made of wheat, in ſteade of potage, they adde bread alſo of a reaſonable quantitye: the drincke whyche they diſtribute is water. But place is graunted vnto none ther to remaine alnyght, or ſlepe, for ther is a publike Charuatſaur
                        •
                     e, wher frelye they are receiued to hoſpitalytye, howbeit ther be aſſigned vnto them no beddes, but they ſlepe vnder the couering of a houſe eyther in heye or ſtrawe.
            
            
               ❀ The maner of their ſacryfice, for vvhat cauſe they do it, and hovv the beaſtes offred are vſed and diſtributed.
               THey offer beaſtes in ſacrifice, but for the moſte parte before vowed, called Chorban as well in the turkyſhe as arabiane

language: In the time of anye diſeaſe or perill, they promiſe (euery mane acording to his habilitie) in certaine places to ſacrifice eyther a Shepe or Oxe: after that the vowed offringe is not burned, like vnto a beaſt killed and layed on the aulter, as the cuſtome was amōg the Jewes, but after that the beaſt is ſlaine, the ſkinne, head, féete, and fourthe parte of the fleſh are geuen vnto the preſt, an other part to poore people, and the thirde vnto their neigheboures. The killers of the ſacrifice doe make readye the other fragmentes for thē ſelues and their compaynons to féede one. Neyther are they bound to performe the vow, if they haue not bene deliuered from the poſſeſſed diſeaſe or peril. For all thinges with them are done condytionallye I will geue if thou wilte graunt. The lyke woorſhyppinge of God is obſerued amonge the Gretians, Armenians, and other realmes in Aſia imitating yet ye chriſtian religiō.
            
            
               
               ¶ VVhat is aſſigned to be done by the Teſtamentes of the Turkes, as vvell of menne as vvomen.
               IF any of the circumciſed dying entendeth to make a teſtament, ſuche legacies for the moſt part are apointed, (their neigheboures and frendes called together) eyther to fetche ſpringes of water, and bringe them before ſome Hoſpitall, temple, or drye place, that is frequented be menne Haritſi, moued with a godlye zeale, &amp; Gſianitſi, for their ſoules health. Other bequethe their goodes to make captiues and bound menne frée. But the women (as thys kynde aboue all other is moſte ſuperſtitious) geue monye vnto ſouldyers, for to kill a certaine number of chriſtians. They make account, that by ſo doynge, it will greatlye profite the health of their ſoules. The kynges apoint temples and hoſpitalles to be builded, and other of the nobility when their lotte is to dye.
            
            
               
               ¶ Their ceremonies about the dead, and maner of interrement.
               IF a circunciſed manne dyeth amonge them, the men take care to make ready the dead corps: if any of the female kind, the women. They waſhe cleane the coarſe, and wrappe in freſh and néet lyuen, after that the ſame is caried vnto ſome place without the cytye, for it is a heynous crime to burye in the temples.
               The taper bearers &amp; monkes with light goe before, the preſtes folowe after, ſyngynge by all the waye, vntill they come vnto the place of interrement. But if the diſceaſed perſon were poore and nedye, money gathered together is accuſtomed to be geuen vnto the religious people for their labour and trauell.
            
            
               ¶ The building of ther ſepulture called Tulbe, and of the ſacrifices done to the dead.
               VPon the kynges ſepulcher is builded a temple, for their kinges are buryed

in Cities: the tumbe of riche and poore mene, is about the height of an auter, ſo that beaſtes can not leape vpon, and defile the ſame. They often reſort thither in wepinge and murnynge: and certaine infernall ſacrifices layde on the monumente, as bread, fleſhe, chéeſe, Egges, milke, and the banket continewinge by the ſpace of nyne dayes, accordynge to the Ethnicke cuſtome, it is al deuoured, for the diſceaſed ſoules ſake, eyther by Piſmares and the birdes of heauen, or poore people. For they affirme that it is lyke acceptable vnto God, that almes ſhoulde be offred to the brute beaſtes hauinge néede therof, as vnto menne, ſins that it is geuen for ye loue of God. I haue ſenne many, whiche geuing the valewe in monye of one litle birde before kepte incloaſed, haue caſt of the ſame to flye awaye: other to throwe bread into the riuer for fiſhes, through the loue of God: addinge that they for ſuche mercifulnes

towardes the neadye, ſhoulde receiue an abundante rewarde at goddes handes.
            
            
               ¶ Of the Turkiſhe vvarrefare: and firſt of the king, and a part of his officers.
               THey haue all one kynge, and in their lāguage he that now raigneth, of thē is called Huncher Othmanlardan Sahitſultan Suleiman, which by interpretation is, Salomon is emperour &amp; Prince of Turkeye, of the Othomans deſcended, whiche now hathe his firſt begotten ſone of the age of thrée and twenty yeares, or their about named Muſtapha, in crueltye and tyrannye, paſſyng his prediceſſors, often lying in waite for his father, if he might by any meanes kille or cauſe him to bée ſlaine, throughe gredie affection, and deſire to beare rule. But in what ſorte, he was murthered by his Father it ſhalbe declared in the ende of this booke. The kynge hath vnder him two chefe goue
                     •
                  
                  nours, or liuetenantes, ouer Europe and Aſia, named Tſangiach Begler, vnto the

whiche are ſubiecte inferiour preſidentes called Timargilar, whoſe heſtes doe certaine ordinarye ſouldyers obeye, but if they be founde lingringe and ſlacke, when they be called for expedition vnto war, are puniſhed with hāging. Baſſalar, whiche they interpret heades, are manye in number, they for councell do alwayes accompanye the kinge. Sulihtarlar alſo, whyche are the garde of hys bodye, are wont continewally to folowe immediatlye after his backe, together with hys Capugtſibegler chamberlaines, Iazitgtſibegler chauncellours, Eminler exactours of tribute, whyche is to witte, of children and money, Spahalar lyght harneyſed horſemen, a great route, Vlachlaris poſtes▪ or purſiuantes, with other ſuch like alwayes folowing the courte.
            
            
               ¶ The eſtate of the Turkes peeres or nobilitie, and of the poſſeſsione.
               NOt one of the nobles, doth poſſeſſe anye prouince or cytye by ryght

title of inheritāce, which after his death, he maye leaue vnto his children, heires or ſucceſſours, with out conſente of the kynge. But if a Prince or gouernour coueteth to haue certaine poſſeſſions, it is graunted vnto him vpon this condition. They enter in bargaine concernyng the Prince and reuenewes of thoſe poſſeſſions. The Turke doth know, how many ſouldiers may yearely be mainteined by the profits of that prouince, then ye Liuetenante is bounde to haue allwayes in readines for him, that band of ſouldiers, at all callinges, otherwiſe he léeſeth his head: and no thing may excuſe him from going vnto warre, but onely ſicknes. And if at anye time, it ſhall pleaſe the Turke to depriue him of that benefyte, it is in his frée will and choyſe: But if he be not depriued, it is his propre poſſeſſiō vntill death. After whoſe interremente, if the heyres of the diſceaſed, will obſerue and kéepe the ſame couenant, they

are permitted to enioye it, if not, it is aſſigned vnto others. If ſome time any of theſe péeres or noble doth talke with the kyng, he faſteneth his eyes on ye ground, not daring to beholde hys countenance.
            
            
               ¶ Of the Baſſans, vvhom vve may cal councellours, chancellours or rather Secretaries.
               ALl the Baſſans, for the greater part are made 
                     •
                  nuches (as it was declared vnto me, when I was bonde manne of a certain ruler in Conſtantinople and are in greater eſtimatiō with the Turke then all the reſt of his nobles, excepting the Sangiackes, and almoſt as manye as are aduaunced vnto that dignitie, are the rauiſhed children of chriſtians. Not one among them, albeit he hathe a daughter of the Turke to wyfe (as one Chruſtā a Baſſan had) is indowed eyther with caſtell cytye are towne, which he may chalenge by inheritance: but if he be aduaū
                  ced vnto any honorable authoritie, he enioyethe

the ſame vntill his deathe, or as longe as it ſhall pleaſe the Turke.
            
            
               ☞ The obediēce vvhich the Turkes are cōſtrained to attribute vnto their king and of his meſsaengers or poaſtes.
               NOt one, eyther of the Jenitſaries, or nobles, hath leaue, or maye bée permitted to walke in the cytye, armed, or girded withe a ſworde: excepte it bée, whē the Turke goeth out of his palaic
                     •
                  , eyther to pray, or hūte. The gouernours and officers of the cytie do beare in their handes coogelles, whiche if they fynde any brawlyng, or doinge iniurye, and offence one to an other, they puniſhe them with the aforenamed coogelles. And not one ſpeakinge to an officer, dare to looke him in the face, but fallynge flatte to the earthe, and kiſſyng his féete, he ſpekethe vnto him his eyes faſtened on the groūd. And when the kynge ſendeth Poaſtes with letters vnto the gouernours of any hys Prouinces, whoſe horſes, as ſonne

as they are weried with iourneyng, or tyred with ſwifte, and contine wall galopinge, the poaſt is licenſed, to take from them their horſes, what ſoeuer they bée whiche méete him in the waye, but if in traueling he méeteth with none, then he turneth towardes the cytyes or townes, Cadiam, whyche is to ſaye, the iudge he goeth vnto, whiche, excepte he prouide him an horſe, is hanged before the gate of his oune houſe, and for this cauſe, horſes are nowriſhed by fewe, but for the greater part Aſſes. And when that meſſanger, or poaſt ſhall come to thoſe, vnto whome he was ſent, the kynges letters receyued with greate humilytie, kyſſed, and his comaundementes with all ſpede poſſible executed, he is ſent awaie. Then is no Prince whych dare gaine ſay him, no one Prouince or cytye (as it often chaunceth amonge vs) that rebellethe, and finallye not one whyche dothe not feare hym.
            
            
               
               ☞ By vvhat meanes the Turkes powre is alvvaies found, and hovve it maye be deminiſhed.
               THe turkiſhe Emperour equallye diſtributeth all his prouinces, vnto the péeres of his realme, but on this condition, that continuallye, as well in the time of peace, as warre, a bande of ſouldyers may be mainteyned by the yearely profites of that prouince: his powre is not at al deminiſhed, the ſouldyers being ſlaine, excepte he léeſe alſo the prouince. As for an example, if the Emperour of Turkeye hath now fowre hundred bandes of ſouldyers, of the whyche a hundred is ſuſteined by the reuenewes of Hungarye, then if Hungarye ſhoulde be loſte, he léeſeth alſo the hundred bandes of ſouldiers: but if he forgoe no prouince, and léeſe all the ſouldyers mainteyned therby, he léeſeth nothyng: becauſe that to ſuccede in their places, (yea if he wold deſire a greater number,) they may eaſelye

be founde: like as amonge vs eccleſiaſticall liuinges, and other vacant offices, may quicklye finde a poſſeſſor.
            
            
               
                  ❧ The ſtate of the Chazilarious.
               THe ſouldiers called Chazilar, are ſtronge, and marueilouſlye practiſed in warrelike affaires, whyche at the firſt bickering, do breake their ſpeares vpon the aduerſaries, vſyng no kinde of weapons, ſauyng ſhéelde, ſpeare and gleues, accordynge to oure countrymen, with a helmet, and coate of maile: but their ſperes beyng broken, they manfullye fyght with drawen gleaues, defendynge them ſelues with ſheildes, alwais endeuoring to miſchefe the handes or heades of their enemyes, and lyinge in wayte with all their force to deſtroye them. It is counted among them no prayſe, but an ignominyes, to ſtryke the enemye or horſe with the point of their ſwoorde. Theſe men put all their lyfe and ſafegarde vnder moderation of the goddeſſe Fortune,

called in their mother ſpeche Haſsup, or Ctſutara, of whom the moſt common prouerbe amonge them all is this, Iazilan Gelur Baſsina, whyche in the Englyſhe tounge after this maner maye bée interpreted, Iazilan, the writynge, Baſsina, on the heade. Gelur, ſhall take effecte: their meanyng is that, what ſo euer the Goddeſſe Fortune, at the daye of Natiuitye, hathe writen on euerye mans heade, to auoyde it, it is impoſſible althoughe he lurketh in an in vincible caſtell. Their worthy déedes and exploites are writen by Hiſtoriographers in vearſe, and reherſed by all ſortes of men, that the reſte wt ſuch lyke boldnes (encoraged through deſyre of honour and prayſe) may valiūtlye, and with out feare aſſaile their enemies. But for euery noble victorie atchiued by them, their ſtipendes are doubled, and therfore al the fornamed horſe men, ought to folowe &amp; accompanie the kyng, furniſhed with theſe kynds of weapens,

that is to witte, Jauelinges or ſpeares, gleaues, dartes, and iron clubbes, ſome haue tergates, other haue none, and they alwayes receiue wages, as well on the time of peace as warre.
            
            
               ❀ Hovv manie orders ther be of the turkiſhe footemene.
               THe firſt order of footemene, is of the Solachlaries, which are archers, they vſe bowes, arrowes, gleaues, and differ by their heade garment from the Ienitzaries. The ſecond order is of the Ienitzaries, they alſo haue wepons lyke vnto the Solachlaries, howbeit, for bowe and arowes they vſe hargabuſheares &amp; poleaxes. All theſe gathered from amonge the chriſtians, leadynge their liues their vnder tribute, taken awaye by force, circumciſed, and brought vp in a certayne place called Tſarai, doe fight moſte coragiouſly againſt the chriſtians, and haue ſtipendes litle enoughe to liue by: that is to ſaye, ſome fowre, fiue, or ſixe peces of

monye called Ahtſe, of the whiche thrée ſcore do make vp a Crowne: and theſe vpon paine of lyfe may not ryde, excepte they be ſicke. Ther are many alſo found to be made Ienitſaries of the Turkiſhe children. The third order of footemene is of the Azaplares, of whome, the warre being ended, ye wages alſo do ceaſe, and they are all the children of Turkes.
               They vſe a longe ſpeare, gleaue, &amp; haue red heade coueringes, or of ſome other colour, made of cloth, with fowre angles, corner wiſe, called Tachia, and differ frō the Ianitſaries, and Solachtaries, by their garmentes, and armour: in the time of battell they throuſt throughe the horſes of their enemyes. Ther is beſides theſe an other order of footemene, from wallachia, of the Grecian religion, named Voinichlar, whych haue no other ſtipend of the Turke, then that they are frée frō payinge any tribute and Tenthes. The men of this order are bound, at their proprecoſtes

and charges, to féede the idle horſes of the Turkiſh kinge, to take iare of them, and brynge them fourthe in the time of warre.
            
            
               ¶ Of the great Turkes tentes, and pauilions of his nobles, and ſouldiers, with the order of their iorneyinge in the time of vvarre.
               WHen the Emperour of Turkie, forſaking Conſtantinople, ſetteth forewarde vnto anye warre, he taketh with him two tentes, called Satorlar, that one this day, may be pitched at the next place of taryinge, when the daye folowing, he purpoſeth to be receyued. The greatnes of his tabernacle is ſuche, that vnto the beholders a farre of, it maye be thought a cytye: next therevnto doe the Princes pitche their pauilions, and encompaſſe round the kynges tabernacle: after theſe the horſemen, wherof euery one ſingulerly, or thrée enioye a tente. The footemen alſo haue vnto them peculier tabernacles,

for it is decréed by ordinance of warre, that no mane ſhall lye abrode out of houſe, or couering. Certaine laborers do make way for the Armie to paſſe, placing heapes of ſtones, or piles of woode, on euery ſyde, as tokens of the waye, in ſomuch that in the darke, they can ſcarſe ſtraye out of the waye. They begine to ſette forewarde about middenight, and continew marching vntill noone tide of the next daye. In the time of their iorneyinge, the kinge is caried, ſittinge in the middeſte, betwne two Baſſans talkynge with him, before whom do iorney certaine ſouldiers of the 
                     •
                  enitſarye order, on horſes, caryinge burning torches, and this is done in a very obſcure and darke night. Then the Tſanlar, whyche are captaines or diſpoſers of ye Army, hauinge iron clubbes, ſharpened and ky
                     •
                  e on euery ſyde, do driue men awaye from the kinges ſighte, by the diſtance of ſtones caſte, or ſhootynge of an arowe,

where Sulihtarlar, the multitude of the garde doth goe, amonge whom are the wagons or chariottes laden with loue boyes, ſeruyng for the Turkes vſe and his péeres. Then the forenamed captaines or diſpoſers of the armye, iorney eyther before them, or come after, with infinite bandes of horſemen, footemen, and ſouldiers of diuers orders, ſome hauing wages, other for gaine, and lukces ſake: men only, for they bringe no womē with them.
            
            
               ❀ The driuing of their beaſtes, order in the campe, in vvhat ſort they lodge, and vvith vvhat foode they lyue.
               AFter theſe ſuccedeth a multitude of Camelles, Mules, and horſe (ſumetimes they bring Elephantes with thē alſo, called in their language Phil) carying victalles, tentes, with other ſuche thinges neceſſary for the Campe. And when the Turkes tabernacle is pitched, euery thing is their ſetled, and placed in order,

as it were in a cytie: ther are places for Shoemakers, Bakers and Butchers: ſome ſéeke and prouide for all ſortes of fleſhe, but if freſhe meate can not be gotten, then they drawe fourthe ſuche foode as is caried by their beaſtes, that is to witte, bredde twiſe baken, fleſhe dried in the ſmoke, named Pastarmar, cheſe, and milke congealed to curdes. They ar moſt pacient of hunger, thirſt, and colde. Very ſeldome they herboure, or lodge in cities, but in the feldes vnder tentes, not farre from heye cockes and riuers, hauinge a greater regarde vnto their beaſtes, then of them ſelues, contēted with a light and baſe meat, as congealed milke tempered with water, and bread put therin, eyther newe, or twiſe baken, both maiſters and ſeruantes. Ther is ſuche ſylence obſerued amonge them in the nyght ſeaſon, that they neglecte their captiues flyinge awaye, for feare leſte if a noyſe, or clamour ſhoulde be ſtirred, they ſhould ſuffer

the puniſhment ordeined for ye breche of Sylence: but at what time they goe to reſte, and when they ryſe from their beddes, to walke abrode, they crye all with a loude voice theſe wordes, repeatynge them thriſe Allah, Allah, Allah, whyche doth ſignifie. O god, O god, O god.
            
            
               ☞ VVhat ſeuere iuſtice is exerciſed in the time of vvarre.
               SUche ſeueritie is vſed to the breakers of decrées, and ther ordinances in war that no ſouldier dare to take any thynge vniuſtelye, if otherwiſe he ſhould be puniſhed with out compaſſion: For ther ar elected among them, certaine ordinarye kepers, or defendours of ſuch neceſſaries, as ar brought in the wayes, towards the campe, by children of eight or tenne yeares olde, which bring to be ſolde, bredde, egges, frute, corne, with other ſuch like. The forenamed officers ar alſo bound to defende the Orchardes of frutes, ſytuate by the wayes ſydes, in ſo much that they

them ſelues dare not to take one apple, or other ſuch lyke thing, with out licence of the poſſeſſed, for if it happen otherwiſe they alſo ſhalbe puniſhed by léeſing ther heades. When I was in an armye of the Turke, at an expeditiō or voiage againſt the Perſians, I ſaue a Eſpahye together with his horſe and ſeruant beheaded, becauſe his horſe breakyng louſe, had entredan other mans fielde.
            
            
               ❀ Of the triumphe to be celebrated for the Turkes victorie, vvher he is allvvayes reſident, and vvherefore he maketh vvarre ſo often againſte the chriſtians.
               WHen it is ſignifyed, or relation made of the Turkes victorye, the cytyes breke fourth into all kinde of ioyefulnes. By night about the firſt kindeling of the candell, they begin this triūphant mirth, torches, linkes, and tapers of waxe, are euery wher diſplayed, the houſe &amp; wayes whereby the turkyſhe emperour muſte

paſſe are adorned with tapeſtry workes clothe of Arras, and hanginges of ſilke. But the moſt ſolemne pompe is done at Conſtantinople, wher he is alwayes reſident, if no warres be ſtirringe betwene him and other countries. Howbeit by the lawes, he hym ſelfe is bounde, after euery thrée yeares, to take a voiage into the chriſtian realmes, eyther for amplifyinge or defence of his kyngedome and dominion.
            
            
               Of their hunting.
               THer is no nation, vnder the ſunne, that ſo muche deliteth in hunting as the Turkes. For in purſuing wilde beaſtes, thei runne throughe on ther horſes, daungerous, ſharpe, and rockye places, takyng diuers kyndes of beaſtes, and if the dead beaſt hath bene choked by dogges, neyther they them ſelues do féede vpon the fleſhe therof, neyther the chriſtians inhabiting thoſe coſtes. But if by chaunce they kill a boare, him they geue

vnto the chriſtians of thoſe partes, for the circumciſed are forebidden to eate of Swines fleſhe.
            
            
               ¶ Of huſbandrie, and craftes men, vnto whom the tenthes do perteine, of the bath, and ceremonies about the ſame.
               THe Huſbandemen doe til the feildes by their ſeruantes, and paie the tenth therof vnto their Emperour. The laborours ſuſteine them ſelues with handye craftes, but they whiche lyue ſluggiſhlye, and in idelnes, do pine awaye withe hunger. Merchandiſe is practiſed alſo very diligently amonge them. They trauell into Aſia the leſſe, whiche nowe is called Natolia, Arabia and Egipte, they diſcloaſe them ſelues, euen amonge the Venetians. In euery of their cytyes ther are Bathes, in the whiche accordynge to their accuſtomed vſe, they waſhe them ſelues twyſe or thryſe. If they voyde vrine, their priuey member is waſhed, if they vnlode the burthen of nature, their

                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
                     〈1 page duplicate〉
                  
                  
                  
fundament is made cleane with water: the lyke is done by the women, both kindes are waited vpon, as the men by ther ſeruantes, and the women by their waitinge maydes, caryinge after them veſſelles full of water. And when they goe fourth to waſhe, the women do anointe them ſelues, with a certaine kynde of Oyntement, whyche after the ſpace of halfe an houre, doth cauſe the heares to fall of, the men them ſelues doe ſhaue ther priuye partes, and in no wyſe they ſuffer the heares to growe, but ridde thē ſelues therof, as wel the men as the women, in euery moneth twiſe or thriſe: but chefly when they frequent the temples, otherwyſe (as defillers of the ſacred and holy place) thei ſhould be conſumed with fire. Ther are amonge them alſo diuers ſortes of craftes men as bowchers, ſhoemakers, tailers, goldſmithes, ſiluerſmithes, and of al other kinds of metall, likwiſe printers, and maſons, but not of ſo

ſubtile and excellent wittes, as certaine ther ar amonge vs.
            
            
               ¶ The iuſtice and equitie vſed amonge Citizens.
               ALl the chriſtians, and lykewyſe the Turkes, haue one iudge choſen frō among the circumciſed, whiche is bound to miniſter the law, and iuſtice equallye vnto all eſtates of men. If any man cō
                  mitte murther, he ſhall ſuffer deathe for the ſame. If he ſteale, or take any thinge by force, he ſhalbe therfore hanged. As it chaunced vnto a certaine Janitſary, that had dronken vp the milke of a woman, carying it to be ſolde in the market, not payinge the price therof, whiche, accuſed before the iudge, whē he had denined the facte, being hanged vp by the héeles, and bounde harde about the middle with a corde, incontinent he vomitted vp the milke, and fourthe with by iudgemente condemned to hanging. This happened, I beyng preſent, at Damaſcus, when I

iorneyed from Armenia towardes Jeruſalem. If any temple commit adultrye, the man is caſte into priſon, and after certaine monethes redemed for monye, but the adulterous womanne is caryed throughe the ſtreates and highe wayes, on an Aſſe, ſcourged with whippes naked, and hauyng the intralles of an Oxe hāged about her necke, is ſtoned to death
            
            
               ☞ The tilling of their grounde, of the graine, Vines, and other frutes, vvhiche grovve in thoſe countries.
               AS well the Chriſtians, as circunciſed Turkes, do till the feldes, mainteine paſtures, and plante vines, hauing corne or graine like vnto this of our coū
                  trye, as wheat, Millet or Hirſe, barlye, Oates, fine wheat, beanes, and al kindes of pulſe: forthermore Rice in great plentye, flaxe, and ſilke cotten, more then in our countries. Both the ſortes of menne aforenamed haue alſo in poſſeſſyon vineardes, vſinge diuerſly the frutes therof.
               
                  The Chriſtians make wine, but the Turkes a kinde of honye called in their language Pecmez, thei vſe, and order certaine reaſons in ſuche ſorte, that as well to the eye, as in taſte, they all wayes ſeme freſhe and new, and are by them named Vzum Turſsi. They haue frutes ther in gret abundance. At their propre ſeaſons, the Orchardes, gardens, and feldes, are repleniſhed, and laden with Pompones, Melons and cucumbers. Ther are nuttes, apples, peares, pome granates, almoundes, cheſt nuttes, figges, cheries, plummes, and other of lyke ſorte, for a ſmall price to be bought, but not in euerye nation. For ther are places, as heare and ther in Cappadocia and Armenia the leſſe, where (throughe extreme cold) not one of theſe ar to be had, or may be gottē.
            
            
               ¶ The ſtate of their Shepardes, vvhat heardes of beaſtes they fede, and of the tribute vvhich is required of the Chriſtians.
               
                  THer are Shepardes among the Turkes called Sobaenlar, which leade ther liues contineweally in deſartes, &amp; chang places for freſhe paſture almoſte euerye moneth, hauyng at all no houſes or poſſeſſyons, exceptyng tentes, and droues of beaſtes. They féede Camelles, Mules, Horſes, Oren, Shepe, Goates, and make chéeſe, butter, and ſhere Shéepe, wherof they make a kinde of garment, or clokes called Ghepenech, and tapeſtrie workinges, which ar ſolde, to bye corne for foode vnto their familie. The fornamed Shepardes generally, do yearly pay vnto the turkiſh Emperour, tyethes, of ye encreaſe of al their beaſtes. The Chriſtians alſo, liuinge vnder tribute, ar conſtrained to paie tēthes, which in quantitie is to wit, of euerye male beaſte, one crowne, and whiche is moſte cruell, they take awaye from them by force all their ſonnes hauinge no wiues, makyng ſearche therfore in ther houſes, euery fifte yeare.
            
            
               
               ❀ The forme of building ther houſes.
               THeir is no great magnificence beſtowed vpon ther houſes, the greater 
                     •
                  art of them builded of bricke worke, and 
                     •
                  her bricke is made after two ſortes, eyther they are baked in a kéele, or dryed by heat of the Sunne. The rowſes of ther houſes ioyne together wedgewiſe, as do the buildinges of our countrye, and this is obſerued throughe out al Europe, but in Natolia the coueringes or roufes, are plain, in faſhion of a flowre, without any ridge: cundites they haue, and water pipes, that ſende downe the rayne water vnto them, whiche is conueied throughe rouled pipes.
            
            
               
                  ❧ The faſhion of ther garmentes, vvherof they are made, and in vvhat ſorte.
               THeir aparaill made of the ſubſtance of wooll, flare, and ſilke, is riche and magnificent enoughe, the garment called Chauton, they vſe gardeo, plaites, and

hangyng downe euen vnto ye ſhoe hēme our bréeches they abhorre, obiectinge thē opprobriouſly vnto vs, as thynges to be aſhamed at. Their ſhertes named Gumlech, and Naptkins ar dyed with a violet colour, ther head is builded vp with an heape of cloth, in maner of a turret, and gathered together at the toppe, not much vnlike the faſhion of a ſtéeple, and ſuche a couering for their head is called in ther tonge Tulbent, or Salma. The wiues of riche men goe with their faces couered, and neuer open their countenaunces vnto any other ſauing their huſbandes, neither at any time frequent the market, or common aſſemblies. The ſhoes named Babucs, or Cſiſme, as well of the women as men, haue thicke ſooles, that they may vſe them the longer ſpace.
            
            
               ¶ Of their meates, and foode.
               THey vſe bread moſt holeſome, called Echmech, both white, &amp; browne, euen as the men of our countries doe, but thei

ſcater or mingle with the dooghe a certaine kinde of ſéede named Suſsam, after that it is baked, which geuethe a delectable ſwitnes vnto the eaters, that bread is not vſed amonge the Chriſtians, ſauinge at certaine places, here and their in Spaigne, as in the kingdome of Granata, and about Ciuill. In their foode is beſtowed great conninge, and diuers ſortes of ſauces, their ordinarye meat is ſo muche thickened with rice▪ that the partes therof maye be drawen a ſonder with their handes. Marueilous is the abſtinence amonge them from fiſhe. They eate all ſortes of fleſhe, exceptynge of Swine. Their are amonge them no tauerns, or publike Innes, to entertaine ſtrangers, as with vs, howebeit in the ſtretes are ſold diuers kindes of meate, requiſite for ſuſtenance, with other thinges neceſſarye to liue by.
            
            
               ¶ The diuerſities of their drinke.
               
                  THrée ſortes of drynke they haue: the firſte is made of Suger, of them named Secher, or honye alayed with water, this drinke hathe to name Tſerbeth. The ſeconde is of reaſons (the kerneles firſte drawen forth) boyled in water, after that is added water of Roſes, with a quantitye of pure honye, that drynke hath his denomination Hoſsaph, and is ſold euery wher in Turkye, it is ſwete, and cauſeth the bealy to ſwell. The thirde is of that kinde of hony named Pechmes, whiche is made of newe wine ſodden, vntill the third parte be boyled awaye, this drinke in taſte, and to the ſight repreſenteth the lykenes of honye, it is alayed with water, and geuen to be dronken of their ſeruantes.
            
            
               ¶ The maner of the turkiſhe tables, and hovv they ſit at meate.
               WHen the time of refreſhyng is cōme, they put vnder them mattes, called Hactſer, after that they ſpred, abrode tapeſtrye

clothes, or Cuiſhens. Some, ſitte downe vpon the bare ground. Their table hauing to name Tſophra is made of leather, it is ſprede abrode and drawen together in forme of a purſe. They ſitte not downe acordynge to our cuſtome, or after the maner of the auncient fathers, as leanyng to their Elbowes, but their legges lyinge one ouer the other, croſſewiſe, muche like vnto Tailers, Grace or thanke geuinge vnto God is ſaid, before they taſt of any meate. They eate ſpedelye and with great ſilence, in which ſpace their wiues are kept in ſom ſecret place The menne ſeruantes, after the age of twelue yeares, ar not permitted to enter the houſe wher women be: but yoūge boyes, within the age of twelue yeares, comming in, and goinge fourth, do bring them thinges neceſſarie, whyche ſeparated farre of, haue their habitation in an other houſe. The bounde women haue not ſo muche lybertye, as to ſtep without

the dores, except it be with the Turkes wiues when they enter the bathes to waſhe, or goe ſome other where, with out the cytye, as into Orchardes, vineardes, and Gardens, for recreations ſake (whiche often times they are wount to doe) but labour harde, continewally lurkynge in ther houſes, neyther are they permitted to talke, or be conuerſant with the men ſeruantes, as in his propre place, whiche is in the treatiſe next folowing, of the afflictions of captiues, the readers eaſely ſhall vnderſtande.
            
            
               
               ❀ The ſalutation of the Turkes, Perſians, and Arabians, is ſuche.
               Sellam aliech Tſultanum,
               
                  Peace be vnto the O Prince.
               
               Sellam aliech Baba.
               
                  Peace be vnto the O Father.
               
               Sellam aliech Ana,
               
                  Peace be vnto the O Mother.
               
               And ſo the reſte in order yow maye ſalute according to the worthines of their perſons.
            
            
               Ther aunſwere.
               Rahmatullah Sellam alechmi,
               
                  Our mercifull God geue peace to yow alſo,
               
               Rahmatullah aliech, tſeudigum,
               
                  Our mercifull God geue vnto yow, my frende,
               
               Berechyat.
               
                  his bleſſyng.
               
               
                  ¶ A Dialogue conteininge queſtions, and aunſvveres of a Turke vvith a chriſtian, and firſte the Turke in this maner ſpeaketh vnto the Chriſtian.
                  
                     Handa gidertſan bre Giaur?
                  
                  Whether goeſt thou O Chriſtian?
                  
                     The Chriſtian.
                     
                        Tſultanū giderum ſtambola.
                     
                     O Prince I goe towardes Conſtantinople,
                  
                  
                     
                     The Turke.
                     
                        Ne iſsum Vac bu meinleketten?
                     
                     What buſines haſt thou in theſe countries?
                  
                  
                     The Chriſtian.
                     
                        Ederum bezrgenlik Affendi
                     
                     I excerciſe marchaundiſe maiſter.
                     Or
                     
                        Maſlahatom var anadolda.
                     
                     My buſines is into Aſia.
                     
                  
                  
                     The Turke.
                     
                        Ne habar ſcizum gilerden?
                     
                     What newes is ther ſpoken of in your partes?
                  
                  
                     The Chriſtian.
                     
                        Hits neſte bilmelom tſaa dimege.
                     
                     I knowe not what newes you deſire to vnderſtande, that I might declare it vnto you.
                  
                  
                     The Turke.
                     
                        Gioldaſsum varmi tſenumle?
                     
                     Haue you anye companion?
                  
                  
                     The Chriſtian.
                     
                        Ioch, ilanuz gheldum.
                     
                     No, but alone I came.
                  
                  
                     The Turke.
                     
                        Gelutmiſun benumle?
                     
                     Dothe it pleaſe you to come with me?
                  
                  
                     The Chriſtian.
                     
                        Irachmider tſenum iataghom?
                     
                     Is your lodgeynge farre of?
                  
                  
                     
                     The Turke.
                     
                        Iachender, gueſtereim tſaa bundan,
                     
                     It is hard by, I will ſhew it you from hence.
                  
                  
                     The Chriſtian.
                     
                        Gel ghuſteriuere, tſeuertſon Allaha.
                     
                     Come and ſhewe, if you loue God.
                  
                  
                     The Turke.
                     
                        Kalch iochari tur honda.
                     
                     Lifte thy ſelfe vp, ſtande here.
                  
                  
                     The Chriſtian.
                     I knowe not in what parte it is.
                     
                        Bilmezum hanghi daraſtan der.
                     
                  
                  
                     The Turke.
                     
                        Tſag eline bacha ghun doghtuſine.
                     
                     At the right hand looke towardes the eaſt.
                  
                  
                     The Chriſtian.
                     
                        Bir buch eun atſarhibi, gurunur, ōmider?
                     
                     One hyghe houſe as it were a Caſtell apeareth, is that it?
                  
                  
                     The Turke.
                     
                        Gerſkſou oder iaken deghilmi?
                     
                     It is euen hit, it is the ſame, is it not hard by?
                     
                        The farevvell.
                     
                  
                  
                     The Chriſtian.
                     
                        Tſamarlodach tſeni Alaha.
                     
                     I committe you vnto God.
                     
                        
                        Ben gitmezom oraa.
                     
                     I will not goe that waye.
                  
                  
                     The Turke.
                     
                        Bre neden korkartſon? nitie gelmetſon?
                     
                     Oh whom do you feare? why come you not?
                  
                  
                     The Chriſtian.
                     
                        Benūiolum deghelder oraa.
                     
                     My iorneye is not that waye.
                  
                  
                     The Turke.
                     
                        Vargeth tſagloga, eier ghelmeſon.
                     
                     Depart with good Luke, if you will not come.
                  
                  
                     The Chriſtian.
                     
                        Gegſien hair altſon.
                     
                     A proſperous nyght chaunſe vnto you.
                  
                  
                     The Turke.
                     
                        Aghbate hair oltſon.
                     
                     And vnto you a more happy night.
                     
                        Ben kurtoldom tſoch ſuccor Allaha.
                     
                     I am deliuered, highe praiſe be vnto God.
                  
                  Theſe fewe wordes of the turkyſhe lāguage, I haue here added for the, moſt gentill reader, not of neceſſitie, but for delectations ſake: that thou maiſt vnderſtand, how groſſe and barbarous they be▪ The euer liuing God graunt, that they

may haue more néede of our ſpeche, then we of thers.
                  Farevvell.
               
            
            
               The lamentable affliction, as vvell of the captiue Chriſtiās, as of them vvhich liue vnder the moſt greuous youke of Tribute.
               ❀ In vvhat ſort the Chriſtians, taken in warre by the Turkes are handeled.
               THe turkiſhe Emperour entending to take any voige, againſt the Chriſtiās, amonge other hys honorable marchantes a grat number or rablement, of vnnaturall Regraters of manne kynd, and ſlaughterous bouchers, ſitting on Cameles, doth allwayes accumpanye him: theſe for hope of bondemen, doe bringe with thē cheines of a merueilous lēght, in the whiche maye fiftye, or thrée ſcore eaſely be bound on a rowe. So many as

the enemies ſworde hathe not muthered and cōſumed, they by of the ſpoilers and botye ſekers, whiche is permitted vnto them, on this condition, that they pay the tenth of their captiues vnto the Emperour, the reſte it is lawfull for them to kéepe, eyther for their propre vſe, or to be ſolde: and amonge them ther is no merchandiſe ſo frutefull, profitable, or more vſed and accuſtomed, as in time paſte it was among the Romanes which called gods merchādiſe, bought with no faute, and in the whiche no conuincement by lawe ought to be feared.
            
            
               ¶ In vvhat maner the Emperour ordereth, and dipoſeth his captiues.
               THe aged ſorte, and youthe of bothe kindes, which befel and happened vnto him vnder the name of tēthes, he this diſpoſeth, that the wel ſtroken in yeares, may be ſold to applye huſbandrye, howbeit they ar very ſeldome taken, for it is arare thinge, that they ſhould be ſpared,

whome age of many yeares hath made ſcarſe ſaleable. The young men, and virgins, they kéepe incloſed in a certaine place named in their lāguage Sarai, that ther they maye be inſtructed in profitable artes and ſciences, wherby in time to come, they may vſe them the more commodiouſly, but firſte it is attempted, that, the chriſtian faith and religion being denied, they may be circunciſed. And nowe hauyng receiued the firſt inſtructions of their ceremonies and the proportion and lineamentes of their bodyes, diligentlye marked by Phiſiognomye, they ar acording to euery ones diſpoſition &amp; towardnes, apointed, either to learne the lawes of their country, or, (if a greater force of body, apeareth in them, then ſharpnes of witte,) vnto warrefare: and they haue geuen for their daily pention, two or thre Ahcſe peces of mony, that they call Aſpres, thrée ſcore of the whiche do make a crowne: they thinke it to be ſufficient for

their foode, and aparaill, vntill they be able to fight in a battell. In this maner, they are inſtructed in the rudimentes of warrefare. Firſte for the tendernes of their ſtrenght, they haue a weke bowe aſſigned vnto them, but in continuance of time, the force of their bodye, and ſkilfulnes in ſhowtinge beinge encreaſed, a tougher and more ſtrong bowe is aſſigned, thus it ſtill augmenteth vntill they ar fit for the warre. A moſt ſeuere maiſter, at night wil be preſent among them, to examine, and haue an accounte of ther daily exerciſe, and as often as they haue 
                     •
                  rred from the marke, ſo manye tymes ſhall they be beaten with roddes. Theſe are aſcribed to the order of Solacrarors, whiche are Archers. Certaine other ar brought vp, for that they may be elected amonge the Ienitſaries: theſe alſo haue their ouerſears, which conſtraine them to a daily kynde of combating, their contendyng is with clubbes. But the reſte

(Oh enuious acte) in whome a greate
                     •
                   grace of bewtie apeareth, ar ſo mangled, that no manlines is to be ſene in all ther bodyes, with no ſmall daunger of léeſing their liues: but if they eſcape, yet from thence fourth ſaftye and ſauegard maye they not obtaine, vntill they are made pertakers of their vnnatural luſt and lecherye, or, their comly bewtye wearynge away, ar made Eunuches, to ſerue matrones, and dames, eyther appointed to kéepe horſes and Mules, or aſſigned to be drudges in their kitchens.
            
            
               ¶ Hovv they deale vvith virgins, and other vvomen.
               SVche as are endewed with excellent bewtye, they chuſe to be Concubines, the meaner ſorte are geuen to ryche Dames and matrones, for wayting mades, to vſe them about their neceſſarye buſines, amonge the whiche, certaine ar ſuch vncleanlye offices, that with honeſtye they may not be named: for the maydes

ar compelled to folow them, with a veſſell of water, when they goe fourth to lay downe the burthen of nature, and purge their inferiour partes. The reſte are ſtreightlye kept to labors fitte for women, as imbrotheringe, and weuing. It is lawful for none of them all, eyther to perſiſte in the Chriſtian religion, or cō
                  ceiue anye hope of fredome, as longe as they liue.
            
            
               ☞ In vvhat ſort, the other Turkes doe Vſe their captiues.
               HEre before wée haue ſhewed, what the turkiſhe Emperour accuſtometh to doe, and nowe ſhalbe declared, what is done by theſe priuate perſons. When any new captiues by them ar receiued, firſt they endeuour by all kinde of thretninges, faire promiſes, and flatteringes, that the late obtained bondmen, maye be circunciſed: whych when it is done, he is handled ſume what more gentellye, but all hope of returning into his country is

cleane cutte of: for burning is ordeined 
                     •
                  s a puniſhement vnto the flyers away, Thoſe whiche ar counted moſt conſtant, and leſſe fugitiue, ar taken by their ma
                  
                     •
                  ters, to ſerue them as pages in the armye, and then at lenght fréedom is purchaſed, whē, being vnprofitable through his age, he is rather reiected by his maſter, then dimiſed, or when his maiſter being in daunger of death at the warres, doth bequeth him fredome. They ar ſuffred to marrie, but their children ar diſpoſed accordynge to the arbitrement, and pleaſure of their maiſter, whiche thinge cauſeth the wyſer ſorte to abhorre matrimonye. But ſuche as refuſe circumciſion, ar moſte cruelly tormented: what miſeries haue I ther ſuſteyned by the ſpace of thirten yeres? Verely I am not able to expreſſe in any wordes, what calamity and grefe is in that kynde of life.
            
            
               ¶ After vvhat maner, they vvhich ar vnſkilefull of manual ſciences, ar vſed.
               
                  MOſt miſerable is the eſtate of them which haue not learned the manual
                     •
                   craftes, for they onely amonge them are had in honour &amp; regarde, wherfore when the learned ſort, preſtes, and noble men, whyche haue leade all their lyfe in idelnes, come into their handes, they ar coū
                  ted in a more greuous caſe then of al the reſt. For the regrater neuer entendeth to beſtow any coſt on them, as ſcarſe ſaleable: they trauell bare legged, with vncouered heades, and often times naked in the greateſt part of their body: for their firſt garmentes worne out, ther ſhalbe no newe apparell beſtowed vpon them, they ar lead and drawen throughe cold, ſnowe, rockes, ſtones, ſummer and winter, and haue no prefixed ende of miſerye vntil they dye, or chaunce vpon ſome folyſhe maiſter, whiche byeth ſuch vnprofitable merchandiſe, this is their pitifull eſtate, and dolefull miſfortune. Finallye not one among them is ſo happy of what

age, condition, ſcience or bewtye ſo euer he be of, that, falling ſicke by reaſon of iorneyinge, the regrater will leaue hym at ſome place to be loked vnto. Firſte he forceth him to go with ſtripes, if that can not preuaile, he is placed on a beaſt, vpō the which if he cane not ſitte vpright, he is bounde to the beaſt, his fore part, and face lokinge to the grounde, lyke vnto a fardell or packe: and beyng about to dye, firſt ſpoyled of his garmentes, they caſte him into the next diche, or pitte, there to be deuoured by dogges, and vultours.
            
            
               ❀ Hovv the nevv taken captiues are handeled in iorneyinge,
               NOt only in the iorney, they bynde ther captiues in perpetual cheines but alſo adde manacles to their handes: the diſtance of a paſſe is betwine euerye of them, leſt one ſhould tread vnder féete the other: whiche they doe for this occation, becauſe they would not beſtoned, of the bondemen, to deathe. For in as much

as euery Regrater leadeth with hym a great multitude, ſo that often times they haue fiue hundred men lincked in Iron
                     •
                  , they feare the force of ſo great a number if they ſhould haue their handes at libertye, and frée to caſte with all. But when the night is come, they late their féet alſo with giues, and laye them vp right to al domages of the aire. The ſtate of women is more gentill, they whiche are of competent ſtrenght, go on their féete, the weker ſorte ar caried vpon beaſtes, but ſuche as are ſo féeble, that they cane not abide the rockyng of the beaſt are placed to be borne in panniars lyke Géeſe. The nyght is vnto them more ſadde and ſorowfull, for eyther they are incloſed in mightie ſenced places, or enforced to ſuffer the beaſtly luſt, and vncleane lecherie of thoſe mankynd regraters. And a moſt lamentable howlynge and wepynge is heard throughe the darke of youthelye wightes of both kindes ſuſteining violence,

neyther maye the age of ſixe or ſeuen yeares defende the miſerable wretches from ſuche filthines, the malitious nation is ſo fearce and feruent, bothe againſt and beſide all courſe of nature in libidinous lecherye.
            
            
               ☞ After vvhat faſhion the captiue Chriſtians are lead, and brought fourthe to be ſolde.
               WHen the daye begynneth too were bright, they are brought fourthe into the market to be ſolde, lyke drones or flockes of ſhepe and Goates. The merchantes aſſemble together, the price is ſette: if the captiue liketh them, his garmētes taken of, he is ſhewed openly before the eyes of his mayſter to come, all his membres are vewed, they ar felte, and euery part ſearched, whether anye hurt or domage hauing bene taken, lieth in the limmes and ioyntes. If he likethe them not, againe he is retorned vnto the regrater, ſo many times that to ſuffer, as

any man entending to by ſhall come and drawe neare: if he contenteth their mindes, and they agre vpon a price, he is leaden awaye to moſte painefull bondage, eyther to bée made a ploughe manne or ſheparde, that in the weane time I may omitte more laborous trauels. For there are amonge them vnſpeakeable examples of miſerye, I haue ſene menne verye often coupled together in a youke to drawe the ploughe. The bonde women, are moſte ſtreitly kept to perpetuall labours, ſeparate from the ſight of menne, and they are not permitted ſo muche as to talke with their felowe ſeruantes. If any man hath bene taken by them, with his wife and children, the noble and rich men will bye him very gladdely, and he is made ouerſear of their farmes, eyther to take the charge of tillinge their lande, dreſſyng of their vineyards, or maintainyng paſtures. The children of theſe are in bondage. If they perſeuer and continewe

in the chriſtian faithe, a certaine time of bondage is aſſigned vnto them, whiche beynge paſſed, they enioye their auncient fredome: howbeit their childrē, except they be redemed, remaine in ſeruitude, according to the pleaſure of their maiſter, eyther to abyde in the ſame places, or ſom other wher to be tranſferred: there is no lande geuen by inheritance, for the which they ſerue a certaine ſpace of time. If after their obtained libertye, they long to retorne into their countrye, letters patentes are deliuered vnto them for ſafe conducte. But vnto ſuch as haue abiured and foreſworne our religion, neyther is ther any determinate time of bondage, neyther lawe to be chalenged cōcerning retorne into their natiue lāde, all hope of Fredome onely dependeth at their maiſters frée will and pleaſure, and albeit that fredome be obtained, yet paye they tyethes, as the reſt of the Turkes doe, but are frée from other burthens,

were with the Chriſtians ar oppreſſede.
            
            
               ❀ The ſtate of thoſe captaines vvhich they make Shepardes.
               PEinefull is the lyfe of huſbandmen, yet more greuous it is with thē which are bought to take the charge of Shepardes, they muſt leade their liues in deſertes, and remaine continually both day and night abrode in the open ayre: only their maiſter with his wife, dwelleth in the tente, and beſides the painefull trauell in defendyng and kepyng their ſtockes, they ar cōſtrained at leaſurable houres to make garmentes, &amp; tapeſtrye workinges. Euerye moneth they change paſtures, conueying them ſelues from one hill to an other. They which are of a nature more gentil and tractable, ar w
                     •
                  nte to gene a ſmall ſtipend vnto their ſeruantes, ſuche as we reade to haue bene meaſured amonge the Romaines, and that is counted their propre goodes, whiche is kept for aſſiſtance in the waye, yf

after obtained Fredome they purpoſe to retorne into their countrye, or vnto other thynges neceſſarye for maintenance of their lyfe. But this chaunceth not euery wher, for it is a miſerable enticement in to bondage, wherby they reſtreine them from their intente of departure. But vnto them whiche haue denyed Chriſte: becauſe they ar ſure that they will not take flight, no ſuche fauour is ſhewen.
            
            
               ¶ The flight of bonde menne out of Europe.
               FLight is more eaſye for them to take whiche paſſe their dayes in Europe, then vnto ſuche as are ſold ouer into the regions beyond the ſeas: for by them no daungerous places ar to be paſſed but riuers, whiche eaſely they maye ſwimme throughe, the greateſt perill is in goinge ouer the ſea Helleſponte. Theſe whiche purpoſe to flie awaye, are wont to endeuour it in the time of harueſte, for that the more commodiouſly they maye hide

them ſelues in the corne, and haue ſuſtenance therof, they continewe their flight in the night ſeaſon, and lurke in the daye time, either in wooddes, mariſhes or among the corne, and had rather to be deuoured by wolues and other beaſtes, thē backe to be drawen againe to their olde maiſters.
            
            
               
                  ❧ Of their flight out of Aſia the Leſſer.
               THey whiche ſeke meanes to flye out of Aſia, doe take their iorneye towardes the ſea Helleſpont, betwine Call
                        •
                     polis, and ye turrettes ſumtime called Seſton and Abidon but nowe in theſe our days Bagas Aſar, whych maye be interpreted, a caſtell of the ſtreightes of the ſea, wher the ſea is moſt narrowe. Thei cary with them an Axe and cordes, both to cutte downe trées, and binde them together, therof to make them boates for paſſage ouer the ſea, bearinge no other thynge with them, ſauing ſalte: by nyght they

enter the boate. If the windes and good fortune be fauorable, they rowe ouer in thrée or foure houres, if otherwyſe, eyther they periſh in the waters, or are driuen backe agayne to the ſea bankes of Aſia▪
                   Hauinge eſcaped the ſeas, they approche the hilles, and fixinge allwayes their eyes vppon the Pole, and Bootes, they directe their iorneye into the northe part: In the time of hūger they ſuſtaine them ſelues with Acornes, and herbes ſprinckeled with ſalte. If a companye reſorte &amp; aſſēble together to take flight, they inuade by nyght the Shepardes, whiche beyng ſlaine, they carye awaye with them what meate and foode ſoeuer ther they finde, howebeit often times they periſh them ſelues, receiuing death of the Shepardes, or taken by them, and deliuered to their old maſters, ar brought again vnder their accuſtomed thraldome and bondage. But a greater nomber the daungers deſtroye, thenne doe eſcape in

ſafty, for either they ar drowned by ſhipwracke, deuoured with ye téethe of wilde beaſtes, ſlaine by their enemies ſworde, or finally famiſhed for defecte of nowriſhemēt, when by flyinge thei haue wandered a longe ſpace.
            
            
               ¶ Of the puniſhement ordained for fugitiues.
               MAnifolde ar the puniſhemēts apointed for flyars awaye: ſome hanged vp by the héeles ar moſt greuouſly ſcourged, but of ſuch as haue committed murther, the féete ar launced with kniues into manye furrowes, and ſo miſerablely mangled they ſprinkle them with ſalte, throughe the bodyes of other is thruſte a great forke, that hath an iron toppe, which a longe ſpace both daye and night they beare and ſuſteine.
            
            
               ¶ The fauorable affection of Grecians and Armenians tovvardes fugitiues.
               PUniſhement by death and forfaiture of all their goodes is ordained for thē,

ye fauer or further the flight of fugitiues. Notwythſtandyng the Armenians and Gretians doe not ceaſe daily to hide the Chriſtian captiues in their houſes, and bringe them diffigured with their apparell vnto the ſhippes of the Venetians, or other Chriſtians, and geue prouiſion requiſite for their iourneye, with all other thinges neceſſarye, neyther by them are ther omitted any tokens of godlye loue, For they affirme to haue receyued lyke fauour at our handes, at what time they come to Rome and Compoſtella.
               
            
            
               ❀ Of the inchauntementes Vſed by the Turkes againſt Fugitiues.
               THey haue a certain kind of inchauntmente, wherby they bringe thē backe ma
                     •
                  ger their teth. The name of the ſeruant writen in a ſcroll of paper is hanged vp in his lodging or cabinne, after that they coniure his heade with horrible wordes and incantatiōs: which dōne by poore of the deuil it commeth to paſſe,

that the ſeruaunte flyinge ſhal thinke to chaunce, in his iorneye, amonge Lions or Dragons, either the ſea and fluddes to breake oute againſte him, or all th
                     •
                  
                  ges to ſeme blacke by reaſon of darkenes, and driuen backe with this terrible ſightes, he retorneth vnto his maiſter.
            
            
               ¶ Hovve the memorie of Chriſt by litle and litle vvereth to obliuion in the Prouinces ſumetime of Chriſtian religion.
               THere are certaine yet remayninge aliue, whyche haue in remembrance the conqueringe of Conſtantinople, and the kyngdones of Gretia, Albania, VValachia, and Seruia, whiche the Turkes do nowe call Boſnam, reduced and brought into Prouinces, they verelye ſticke moſt firmelye vnto Chriſte, but the younger ſorte can not remember it, and in ſhort ſpace it will come to paſſe, that the obliuion of Chriſtianitye ſhall repleniſhe all thoſe countries: The like will happen in

                  Croatia, Ilungarie, &amp; Sclauonie, which are 
                     •
                  ate additions and augmentinges of the Turkiſhe empire.
            
            
               ☞ In vvhat ſort the conquerour aafe
                     •
                   any victorie behaue them ſelues, and hovve by them are vſed the Spirituatie.
               WHen the Turke hath ſubdued any
                     •
                   prouince, al the goodes therunto appertayning as wel moueable as not moueable, are graunted and geuen for a bootye. He noteth out by the grounde all the nobility, but chieflye the princes iſſue. And in that at this preſēt is fauoured by them the ſonne of kynge Ihon, they do it not to none other ende, then if Hungarie ſhould be taken frō them, they may place him therin, newe miſchiefes to attempt, but whē of Hungarie they ſhal haue ſure and ſafe poſſeſſion, no doubt but they wil ridde hym out of this life. For the Turkes to obtaine a kingdome do fauor neither their owne bloud nor kinſfolke, no

not their propre brethren. If they murther not the ſpirituall men, at leaſt wiſe▪ ſpoiled of al their riches and promotiōs▪ thei caſt them of to be laughed at, and to get their liuinge by begging. They take oute of the Churches all the belles, organes, and other muſical inſtrumentes, yea the temples them ſelues profaned &amp; defiled, they cōſecrate to their Mahomet: the naked and baſe chapelles are lette ſtande for the Chriſtians, wher they ſay their ſeruice not openlye, but with great ſilence, and couertly: whiche when they are fallen to the grounde by meanes of earthequakes, conſumed with fyrye flames, or rotten throughe longſtanding, it is not lawfull for them to réedifye without the paiment of a greatſome of mony. Sermons and preaching of the Goſpel is plainelye forbidden, neyther is it lawfull for thē to aſſēble vnto any Chriſtian cōmon wealth, beare wepōs about with them, be cladde with like apparrail

vnto the Turkes, daunce, or ſette fourth pleaſant ſightes of a ioyefull lyfe▪ If any iniurie be done towardes the, or Chriſt, by opprobrious wordes, thou muſt holde thy peace, and pacientlye ſuffer it. But contraryewyſe, if thou ſpeake anye vnworthye or diſdainefull thynge of their religion, thou ſhalt be enforced to circū
                  
                  
                     •
                  iſion, if then alſo thou mutter againſte Mahomet, fire and burnyng ſhall conſume the to aſſhes. And if a horſeman of ye Chriſtians paſſe by a Muſulman, whiche is one entrede in the turkiſh religion it is neceſſaryly required that he deſcend from his horſe, and worſhippe the other ſitting, with a lowly countenance, and bēding his body, which except it be done, he is beaten downe from his horſe with clubbes.
            
            
               ¶ The eſtate of preſtes and munkes liuinges vnder tribute of the Turkes.
               PKeſtes and mūkes with the Turkes are of all other in vileſte eſtate,

they ar reputed as cōmitters of ſacrilege &amp; accurſed both by god &amp; man, neither do they receiue any ſtipēds of ye church. Upō Feſtiuall they haue caſte vnto theym 
                     •
                   y certaine women, a ſmall quantitye of bredde, no thinge is diſtributed amonge them vppon otherdayes. They lyue by purueyinge of wodde: for the cuſtome is that they he we downe trees in the woddes, wherwith their aſſes beynge laden, they wander wyth that marchaundyſe through out al the ſtreates, proclayming wodde to be ſolde.
            
            
               ¶ Of the vnmerciful tributes exacted at the Chriſtians handes.
               THe Chriſtians do pay the fourthe of all their increaſe, and this fourthe is not only gathered of the profites of their landes, fieldes and flockes, but alſo the manual artificers do geue the fourthe of all their gaines. Ther is beſides this an ther burthen of payment, by the which

ſo many as ar in one familie, do exhibite euery one a duccate. If their parentes be not able to diſcarge it, they are conſtrained to ſell their children into bondage. Some other linked in cheines do wander doore by dore to begge money for diſchargement therof, but if neyther then they ar of abilitie to paye, they are condemned to perpetuall impriſonement. And nowe when they haue performed all dew
                     •
                  ies, yet is it alwayes lawful for the Turke to haue the frée election of the beſt of his ſonnes, whiche, circumciſed, and conueied awaye out of his parrentes ſight, is trained vp for the warres, neyther ſhall he euer retorne againe to his parentes, and firſt becauſe a childe will quicklye commit Chriſt to obliuiō, ſoone after alſo his parentes and alyes, ſo that if they ſhould be conuerſant with him, he can not diſcerne, or iudge one of his kinſefolke. No manne is able to expreſſe 
                     ••
                   wordes, with what bitter teares,

ſorowefull ſighes, and pitifull ſobbinges that violente ſeparation is done. The Father ſéethe his ſonne, whom he hathe inſtructed and brought vp in the true worſhippinge of Chriſte, to be drawen by force vnto the warrefare of Sathan, that he maye fight againſt Chriſte: the ſoone is rauiſhed from his parentes perpetually to liue amonge ſtraungers and Aliantes, vtterly to forſake that whiche by bloud is dearely beloued, grateful throughe aquaintāce, and frendly by familiarity: from thenſe foreward to come amonge the number of them, whom the Grecians are wont to call Apatoras and Ametoras. And albeit that this greatlye degenerate frō the trew Chriſtian faith, yet a great number of them do cary vnder their armepittes, as a moſt ſure preſeruatiue againſt euill happes, the Goſpell of ſaint Ihon, (whiche is to witte. In the beginning. &amp;c.) throughely written vnto the ende, bothe in the Grecian and

                  Arabian language, whiche intentinelye and with feruent deſire expect and lōge for the Chriſtians ſworde (of whom the turkiſhe prophet dothe ſpeake, as it ſhalbe declared in ye treatice next folowing) to reuenge and deliuer the Chriſtians from their vnſpeakeable afflictions and painefull perſecutions. Whiche in that it hathe not vntill this daye made haſte, and ben lifted vp againſt them, who ſoeuer they be that ar the hinderers therof, and to what purpoſe they do it, it forceth not, but they ſeme trewlye to haue deſerued moſte vnworthely of the Chriſtian religion. For nowe (Oh ſoroweful miſchaunce, our brother George of Varadinum being diſceaſed) how quickely haue we loſt the gouernement of the Temeſuans? let hence fourthe Hungarie lament, and Tranſyluania be ſorowefull, Pollonia alſo ought to bée circumpecte, with Lutē Ruſsia, Pruſsia, Moſchouie, Dacia, Denmerke, Gutlad, Norvvaie, and Sueuelande
                  
Lotte the lyke be ſayde of Auſtriche, Morauie, Siletia, Boeme, Saxonie, Germanie. England, Scotteland. Spaigne, and France. Let Rome, Venice with all Italie loke no better to ſpede. God graunt that theſe thinges maye attaine vnto a more happye end then I ſuppoſe they will.
            
            
               A ſalutinge dialogue in the Sclauone tounge.
               
                  Bogh pomozi goſpodaru
               
               God helpe you my patrone.
               
                  The Aunſwere.
                  
                     Dobro doſsao priiateliu.
                  
                  In good time you come my frende.
               
               
                  The Queſtion.
                  
                     Ieli ouay praui put u kaliplie?
                  
                  Is not this the ſtreyght waye into Callipolis.
               
               
                  The Aunſwere.
                  
                     Ni brate, Zabludioſsi daleko.
                  
                  No brother, you haue erred greatlye,
               
               
                  
                  The Queſtion.
                  
                     Od Zemlie koieſsi kazuimi.
                  
                  Of what Countrie ar you? tell me.
               
               
                  The Aunſwere.
                  
                     Od Vlaſke Zemlieſsam, od benetak▪
                     
                  
                  Of the Italiās region I am, from venice.
               
               
                  The Queſtion.
                  
                     Vkaſi mi praui puth takoti boga.
                  
                  Shewe me the ſtreight waye, for goddes ſake,
               
               
                  The Aunſwere.
                  
                     Hodi ſsamnon, neboiſse niſtar
                  
                  Come with me, neyther feare you▪ any thynge.
               
               
                  The Queſtion.
                  
                     Ieda koie glaſse imas, Kazuimi.
                  
                  If any newes you haue, declare it vnto me.
               
               
                  The Aunſwere.
                  
                     Ne takomi vice dafnam prouidablih ti.
                  
                  No by my faith If I knew any I would ſhewe it you.
               
               
                  The Farewell, and geuinge of thankes.
                  
                     Oſtai Zbogom brate, onie grad
                  
                  Staye in goddes name brother, that is ye citye.
                  
                     
                     K amogres
                  
                  whether you goe.
               
               
                  The Aunſwere.
                  
                     Poi Zbogon, i bogh te zdrano no
                           •
                        sio.
                  
                  Depart in goddes name, &amp; god the in ſafty keepe.
                  
                     Hallu ti imam i dobrati nots bila.
                  
                  Thankes vnto you I geue, and a haypy nyght haue you.
               
            
            
               ❀ The Lordes praier in the Sclauone toungue.
               
               
                  Naſs otſse ki yeſsi na nebeſsi. Our Father whiche arte in heauen. Ssuhtiſse tuoie ime. Kralyeuſstuo Holowed be thy name. They kyngdome. pridi, tuoia olia budi na zemlij kako come, they will be done in earthe as it is na nebu. Dai na
                        •
                     ga danaſs naſsega in heauen. Geue vnto vs this daye our ſsagdaniga kruha, iodpuſciainā naſse dughe daillye bredde, and forgeue vs oure debtes. kako mi odpuſcianao naſsiiw duſuikon, i as we doe forgeue our depters. and nepeliai nats u napaſt, da izbaui leade not vs into temptation, but deliuer nate od nepriazni, Amen. vs from euill.
               Amen.
            
            
               
               The Salutation of the Angell.
               
                  ZDrano Mario puna miloſti, goſpidin Haile Marie full of grace, the Lorde is ſtobum, blaſena ti meuſenami, with the, bleſſed art thou amonge women, i blaſen tſad tuoye vtrobe and bleſſed is the frute of thy wombe Ieſus Kriſtus, Amen. Jeſus Chriſte,
               Amen.
            
         
         
            ❀ The Author vnto the Chriſtian reader.
            I Thought it good, moſt fauorable reader, heare to recite certaine woordes of Scaluone ſpeche, yt thou mighteſt knowe by howe muche the Sclauone tonge, differeth from the Perſian language, whiche is vſed by the Turkes. Ʋnderſtand therfore that it is lawfull for all men, ſkilefull in that tounge, ſafelye to paſſe into Croatia Dalmatia, Ruſsia VValachia, Seruia, Boeme, &amp; Poole althoughe throughe diſtance of the prouinces, they differ not alitle in certaine wordes, and pronunciation,

as the Italians frō the Spaigniar: des, and Germans from the Flemminges. Farther let not this be vnknowen to the, that the Ruſsians and inhabitantes of Seruia do vſe one lāguage in their deuine ſeruice. For they haue foure and thirty letters, not muche vnlike thoſe of the Grecians▪
                And likewiſe the Croatians, but their letters differ verye muche from the other in forme▪ howbeit in number and pronunciation thei ar like. And therfore it is impoſſible for vs, with Engliſh letters to vtter the trew pronunciation of their words. The Turkes conuerſant in their kings courte, and confines of Scla
                  •
               
               
               
                  •
               ony do vſe the ſame language.
            Farevvell.
         
         
            
            
               ❧ 
               The horrible acte, and wicked offence of Soltan Solimam Emperour of the Turkes, in murtheringe his eldeſt ſonne Muſtapha, the yeare of our Lorde. 1553.
            
               I Haue thought it a thinge conuenient, and neceſſarye for me purpoſing to make manifeſt by writing vnto the world ſo miſchenous a déede, for the more full and perfecte demonſtration therof, a litle to retire, and firſte of all brefelye to tu
                  •
               che the originall cauſe, &amp; beginning of that vnnaturall acte. It is therfore to be vnderſtanded, ye 
               Soliman had begotten thys Muſtapha on a certaine bondewoman, vnto whom euen from his childehoode he aſſygned the prouince of Amaſia. Whether, after the contine wance of certaine monethes, he iorneyed, his mother him accūpanying, at what time, through his floriſhinge in youthelye yeares and

vertue, he was thoughte, in ye opinion, &amp; iudgement of al men, by ſome heauenly prouidence, to be geuen and ſente vnto their countrye. This younge man being departed with his mother, the kynge in proceſſe of tyme what rauyſhed aboue meaſure with the be wtie of an other his cōcubines named Roſa: by whom he had foure menne children, and one woman. The finite had to name Machomet, and vnto him was geuen the prouince of Caramania. The ſeconde Baiaſith, whyche helde the country of Magneſia. The third Selimus, vnto whome Machomet beynge dead, was aſſigned the prouince of Caramania. The fourth was ſirnamed Iangir of the bunches, wher with he was both deformed before, &amp; behinde in his backe, notwithſtāding of a ſharpe prudent and politike will. But the virgine was maried to one Rustanus a paſchan. He after the ſlaughter of Hybrachimus obteined the dignitye of a Viſier, whiche we may

cal one of the chiefe councellers. But abuſing that office with ye auerice in him naturally engraffed, he eyther renewed or cleane changed all the cuſtomes and orders, deminiſhed the yearly ſtipendes of the ſouldiers, whiche they call Janiſcharies, enhaunſed the reuenews of the Captaines (paide by them vnto the Emperour) whiche are named Sangiackes, encreaſed ſub
                  •
               idies and tributes vppon the prouinces, and no leſſe added a meaſure to the inordinate expenſes of ye kinges houſe, applyinge his office to none other ende, then that he might heape vp for him ſelfe infinite treaſures, by his colored and di
                  •
               ceitfull pillage, by the whiche meanes, beinge eſtemed as a diligēt and profitable ſeruitour, he eaſely allured the kings fauour vnto him ſelfe: litle regardynge in the meane time, that he was enuied and hated of all other men. Duryng whiche ſpace, Roſa, of whome we haue mencioned before, perceyuinge

her ſelfe to be fauored and beloued of the kynge aboue the reſt of his concubines, vnder a colour of religion minded to declare vnto ye 
               Muchti, that in déed ſhe was ſtirred of a godly deſire and affectiō, and throughely purpoſed to build a temple, and erecte an hoſpitall, to receiue pilgrimes in the honour of the highe God, and his prophet Machomet, yet that ſhée had determined, not to attempte it with out his councell and aduiſe. wherfore ſhe demaunded of him whether ſuche workes wolde be acceptable vnto God, and anye thinge auaile for the health of her ſoule▪ To whiche demaundes the Muchti aunſwered, that the déedes woulde be vnto god moſte gratefull, and althoughe not muche profitable for the ſafegarde of her ſoule, yet that they woulde bée a greate 
                  •
               urtherance vnto the kings ſoule, vnder whoſe dominion, &amp; at whoſe commaundement were all her goodes, riches, and alſo (for ſhée was a bondewoman) her

lyfe. With this aunſwere, the woman ſemed, euery day one more thē an other, to be ſadde, ſorowfull, and diſquieted in her minde, and ſo much that in the ſpace of many daies ſhe coulde not bée comforted. Of whiche anguiſhe &amp; pēſiuenes, the kinge beyng certifyed, begane to ſolace her moſt curteouſelye, affirminge that hée in ſhoorte ſpace woulde finde a remedye, whereby at lenght ſhée ſhoulde enioy the long wiſhed end of her deſire, Wherfore incontinēt he made her frée, and thervpon confirmed his déed by ſuch writinges (as amonge them it was accuſtomed to bée done) that from thence fourth ſhe ſhoulde neuer be bounde vnto him againe. After obteining of this deſired and louing fauour, Roſa with a great quantitie of treaſure, departed to finiſhe the woorke before mencioned. Duringe which time the kyng (as aboue it is ſpecified) baited, and as it were drowned, paſſinge all moderation, in an vnbrideled

deſyre and luſt of Roſa, commaunded by a meſſanger that ſhe ſhould come vnto him. But the craftye and deſceitfull woman, from whome no guile was hidden, ſubtillye willed the meſſanger, that he ſhoulde admoniſhed his Lorde of honeſtye, and obſeruinge the lawes: and that ſhée acknowleged her ſelfe no lenger to be bonde, but a fre woman, albeit in the meane ſeaſon not to denye, hys kingely maieſtye, at his arbiterment to haue the apointing and diſpoſition both of her life and death: but concerning carnall copulation, that of all other thinges it coulde not be done, with out the committinge of a moſte greuous ſinne and offence. And leaſt perhappes he myght thinke it to be a fable forged, and fained by her, that ſhe was contented, and wold repoſe her ſelfe in all thinges to the iudgement of the Muchti. This repulſe ſo ſtirred vp the inflamed hart of the kyng, that, all delaye ſet aparte, he commaunded

the Muchti to be ſent for vnto hym, and geuing him frée leaue to aunſwere, aſked, whether with out breakynge and violation of the lawes, he might carnallye ioyne with a bonde woman by hym made frée? wherunto the Muchti auneſwered, that it was not lawfull, except he had firſt contracted lawful matrimony with her. But this difficultie ſo augmented the kinges affectiō, that blinded beyounde all meaſure with ſenſuall appetite, he conſented in wedlocke too the frée woman. Wherfore the mariage robes, and other neceſſary prouiſion made ready, acordyng to their cuſtome, he ſente her fiue thouſand Soltane ducates, vnder the name of a gift for their mariage, not with out the great admiration of all men, eſpecially becauſe it was contrary to the vſage and cuſtome of the houſe of Ottomanno. For, to auoyde equalitie in the Empire, they neuer marye anye honeſt and lawfull wiues, but in their places,

to ſatiffye their pleaſures, and libidinous luſtes (whervnto in moſte vile &amp; and filthy maner, they are ſubiecte, as boue all other nations) they haue rauiſhed virgines frome all partes of the worlde, bewtifull and in fauour the moſt excellent, whom princeſſe like, and honorablelye, they nouriſhe in the kinges palaice (whiche of thē is called Sarai) bring them vp to ſerue for al vſes and commodities, and inſtructe them in honeſt, and ciuill maners, with whome the kynges by courſe, as their pleaſure ſhalbe, are wount to accompanyé. But if by chaūce any amonge them beyng begotten with childe of the king, ſhall afterward bring foorth and be deliuered, then ſhe aboue all the reſte is reuerenced and honored, and for a great dignitie and reputation, is therfore called Soltana. Thoſe women after the birth of their childrē ar maried to great Lordes, paſchans, and Sangiaches. But to retorne vnto our purpoſe of to

this bonde woman latelye made frée ſo highelye aduaunced by the benefite of Fortune, yt ſhe myght well be thought the chefeſt of all the women of Aſia, and accompanyed with ſuche ſucceſſe of felicitie, wherby ſhe might ſatiſfie all her ambitious endeuours and deſires: this only thinge remained, that meanes and occaſion might be founde, wherby Soliman beynge dead, the ſucceſſion of the Empire, myght be tranſlated vnto her only poſteritie which purpoſe, the gentilmāly to wardnes of Muſtapha ſo much hindered, a younge mane of a noble corage, and paſſynge witte, no leſſe excelling in his coragious hart, thē in ſtrenght by reaſon of ye multitude of his ſouldiers, whiche alſo throughe his magnanimity and fortitude was in wounderfull eſtimation with the ſouldyers, and for hys graue wiſdome and vpright iuſtice, marueilouſly fauored of the people. All whiche commendable qualities in him, the

crafty woman well conſidering, and priuely with Ruſtanus conſultinge of that matter, for ſhe knewe (as by the inſtinct of reaſon it is moſt probable) that Ruſtanus woulde rather deſire his kinſeman, and brother of his wife, to be aduaunced and ſetled in the Empire, then Muſtapha with whom ſhe knewe for a certaintye, that he was in moſt mortall hatred, and chefely becauſe ther had fallen betwyne them great variance and ſtrife. For from the beginning, whiles he went aboute to deminiſhe the pentions of others (as before we haue partly touched) he endeuored alſo, but in vaine, to detract a part of the ſtipend and reuenewes of Muſtapha: wherby ſhe ſone coniectured, that ſo noble and ſtout a hart, if he ſhoulde bée aduaunced vnto the eſtate of the Empire, woulde not eaſelye burye in obliuion, ſo vnderſerued an iniurye, in ſo muche ye 
               Muſtapha raigning, he thought by meanes of his forepaſſed lyfe, that not

onely, he ſhoulde fall in danger of his office and dignitie, but alſo of his heade. All whiche lykelihodes to chaunce the malicious woman pondering in her peſtilent minde, endeuored to kindle in the kynges thought no ſmall ſuſpitions of Muſtapha, which were that he inflamed with deſire to beare rule, hauinge his cō
               fidence in the fauour and beneuolence of all menne towardes him, and ſwellynge throughe the great armye of ſouldiers (of the whiche he hathe great plentye and abundance) lefte no other thinge to bée looked for at hys handes, then that ſhortlye he woulde affecte the Empire, and craftelye lye in waite to murther his Father. And whereby the better to conceale and clooke this matter, ſhée fitelye prouided all thinges to be attempted by Ruſtanus, whiche continually hadde the charge of weightie affaires about ye king neither were ther anye craftye meanes priuy vnto him, whiche he applied not

for the deſtruction and accuſemēt of the young men. For vnto as many as were ſente for adminiſtration and gouerment of the prouince of Siria, he priuely tolde, as thoughe Muſtapha was had in ſuſpicien by his father, geuinge in charge to euery of them that they ſhoulde haue a diligent eye vnto the eſtate of Muſtapha, and with out faile to certifie him by writinge of all ſuche matters as they bothe ſawe &amp; heard concerning his behauiour: craftely affirming, that the more odyous thinges, were writen by them of Muſtapha, ſo muche the more they ſhoulde be in fauour and accepted of the kyng. Frō that day forewarde Ruſtanus beynge often certifyed by them, of the princelye excellency, wiſdome, fortitude, magnanimitye, beneuolence, and liberalytye of Muſtapha towardes all men, wherewith he hadde marueilouſlye purchaſed vnto him the fauour of the multitude, and no leſſe of the moſte feruent deſire, with the

whiche all menne, for the moſt parte, ſemed to bée kindled, about election of him vnto the Empire: all thys notwithſtanding, he not onely firſt dared to ſowe the ſéede of ſo miſcheuous a conſpiracie, but alſo thoſe letters deliuered vnto the vngratious woman, he lefte the reſte to bée proſecuted by her peſtiferous head. But Roſa ſeyng good opportunitie offred, for accomplyſhinge of her deteſtable intent, thought neuer to leane of corrupting the kynges minde with effeminate allurementes, and Flatteringes (as ſhe knew the wayes, few lyke vnto her) ſo that, if at any tyme mention ſhoulde be made of Muſtapha, ſhe woulde take a fitte occation of the time to oppen the letters.
            And in déede ſhée was not deceiued of her expectation, for a conueniente ſeaſon beyng awaited, ſhe admoniſhed the king not with out teares (as vnto women in fained matters they are at no time wantinge) of the perill and daunger wherevnto

he was ſubiecte, rehearſing among other obiections, howe Selimus the kinges parent, had before at one time, by ſuche lyke meanes depriued his Father bothe of his kingdome and lyfe: wherefore ſhe earneſtlye entreated him by example of other to take diligent care for him ſelfe. But theſe argumentes of ſuſpicion, at the firſte ſight, ſemed not in euery behalfe ſo probable vnto the king, whereby it came to paſſe, that by thoſe aſſayes, the curſed woman litle profited. Whyche perceiuynge in her enuiouſe harte, after tracte of certaine monethes, ſhe directed her malitious thoughtes vn▪to other diſceites, ſekynge opportunitye by all mannes poſſible, to diſtroye the younge manne wyth poiſon. Neyther were ther wantinge bloudſheders, and moſt deteſtable menne, prompt and ready to accompliſhe vilanouſlye all heynous actes, leaſt by celeſtiall prouidenc
                  •
                ſhée might haue applyed her ſelfe to ſ
                  •
               
               
horrible a dede. wherfore he firſt touched not the venimed robes, ſent vnto him, by this woman, vnder the name of hys Father, vntill an other hadde bene clad with the ſame: by whiche prouident wiſdome, he preuented the vndeſerned miſchefes of his vnnaturall ſtepmother, and openlye, in the ſight of all menne made manifeſte the poiſon. Howbeit the adulterous harlot yet ceaſed not to imagine againſte him freſhe and newe wiles, for ſhe wēt about (beyng boldened throughe the amourous drynkes, with the whiche by the héelpe of a bewtifull woman, a Juiſhe enchauntriſſe, ſhée hadde ſo allured the kinges minde, that euerye daye riche preſentes, and the ſucceſſe of diuers requeſtes, wer vnto her daily, more and more promiſed by the kynge) to get her ſelfe ſuche beneuolence and familiarytie, as neuer any béefore hadde obteined in the princely palaice of Ottomāno: for ſhée deſired, that by courſe her children

might he conuerſant in the royall houſes of their Father, whyche was becauſe by their continewall preſence, and daily faire flatteringes, thei might more and more entice vnto them his Fatherlye loue, and if throughe ſome fortunat chaunce, Muſtapha ſhoulde alſo come, ſhée might gette a more conuenient occation to oppreſſe him: if not, to expecte the time to kill hym by meſſangers.
            But Muſtapha in déede not comminge (for the kynges ſonnes haue not accuſtomed, their father not wittinge of hit, to depart out of the prouinces aſſigned vnto them, and repaire to Conſtantinople, except their father beyng dead, they come accompanied with a great number of ſouldiers, to take poſſeſſion of the Empire) ſhe hadde ſoone in redines an other miſchefe. For the requeſt whyche was deſired, beynge obteyned, ſhée brought to paſſe, that not onlye in the cytye, but in the prouinces alſo her children folowed

the kynge their Father yea Giangis difformed with bunches accompained his father remaining in the cāpe. But the forged inuention of this wicked ſteppe mother ſtandynge in doubte the ſpace of certaine yeares, fortune at lēght minding to fauer thoſe curſed iutentes of the woman, brought ſuſpicious letters from the Paſchan (for euery of the kings ſonnes is wount to haue with hym one Paſchan, whiche is ſuche a one, as occupieth the rome of him, that geueth aunſwere vnto the people concernynge the lawe, and miniſtreth councell about warrelyke affaires, with a teacher by whom he is trained vp in good letters, and princelye behauiour) whyche was conſtituted ouerſear of the regiment of Muſtapha, and gouernynge of the prouince of Amaſia: in the whych was conteined, a mariage to be in handeling betwine Muſtapha and a daughter of the kynge of Perſia, and that he therfore referred

the matter vnto the ſacred gate, becauſe that if anye miſfortune ſhoulde chaunce therof, he might be counted frée from al ſuſpition. Theſe letters brought vnto Ruſtanus, he thought that at lenght he ſhoulde bringe the long hoped ruine, and deſtruction of Muſtapha to a deſired ende. And makynge no longer delaye, with ſpede he declared al the whole matter to Roſa, and ſoone after bothe conueyinge them ſelues into the palaice, they reuealed the ſtate therof before the kinge. In the whyche cauſe, whereby to drowne the kynges minde, yet ſtaggeringe, and full of doubtes, in their ambiguouſe ſuſpicious, they applied all their wilye diſceites, ſayinge: that Muſtapha, as an ambitions perſon, to bée kindled, and ſette on fire, with a furious rage of the minde, contrarye to all heauenly and humaine lawes, throughe deſire of obteinynge ſoo noble an Empire: to conſpire alſo againſt his fathers death: and

wherby a greater confidence myght bée geuen to their crafty imaginations, they put the kinge in remembrance of the aliance contracted by Muſtapha with the perſians, moſt auncient and deadly enemies to the of ſpringe of Ottomanno, and therefore he ought narowely to ſée vnto hym ſelfe, leſt, to perſian ſtrenght ioyned to the Sangiaches and Ianiſcharies, whoſe fauoux Muſtapha longe ſence had wonne by his liberalitie, in ſhort ſpace, he ſhoulde bereue his father both of lyfe and kingedome with theſe and ſuch like accuſations, they brought the troubled minde of the olde manne to ſuche paſſe, that he fullye purpoſed to prouide for ſafegarde of his owne eſtate, by death of his ſonne, after this maner. In the yeare of our lorde God a thouſande fiue hundred fiftye and twoe, he cauſed with all diligence and celerytie, throughe out, for the moſte parte, all his prouinces, to bée proclaimed, the Perſians, departed out

of their coaſtes, to haue inuaded Siria wt a great Oſte of armed men, ouerthrowē cityes, lead awaye the people captiue, and, no mane reſiſtyng them, ſpoiled all the countrye with fire and ſwoorde, whiche ſo bolde an enterpriſſe, and deſperat acte to repell, that he was conſtrained, to ſende thither Ruſtanus with an, army. Certaine bandes of ſouldiers therefore beynge gathered together, he priuelye committed thē to Ruſtanus, that as ſecretlye as it might be, and without all tumulte, he ſhoulde laye handes or Muſtapha, and bringe him bounde vnto Conſtantinople, but if he coulde not commodiouſlye bringe it to paſſe, that then by one meanes or other, he ſhoulde cauſe him to be murthered. This vnnaturall and beaſtelye commaundement of a father being receiued, Ruſtanus guarded wt a mightye Oſte of ſouldiers, marchethe towarde Ciria. Whither, when he was come, Muſtapha certified of his ariual,

all lingrirg ſet a part, iorneyed towardes Siria, accompained with ſeuen thouſand of the moſt valiant and beſt apointed ſouldiers throughe out all Turkeye. Wherof Ruſtanus hauing intelligence, and ſeyng that he could not, according to his intēt, accompliſh the wicked cōmaū
               dement, of his moſt cruell &amp; vnkinde father, with out longer tarying begane to flye, and, retiring made haſt with his army to Conſtantinople again, &amp; with ſuch ſpede, that he dared not to ſée the duſte, rayſed in the aire by the horſemene of Muſtapha, muche léeſſe too abyde hys commynge. Beynge retorned therfore wythe hys companye of ſouldiers, he perſwaded all menne, to haue founde the prouince quiet and in ſafegarde. But at lenght opened vnto the kynge in ſecret the cauſe of hys retorne: addynge that he had ſenne by moſte manifeſt ſignes and coniectures, the mindes of all the whole armye, to be meruellouſlye enclined to

the fauour of Muſtapha and yt he thought it not good, in ſo daungerous a buſines to attempt the matter by open warre: for whiche cauſe he referred the decydynge therof vnto the wiſdome of hys maieſtye This relation encreaſed newe and no ſmall ſuſpicion in hys vncurteouſe and bloudſhedynge father, and in no pointe degenerating from the engraffed crueltye of his aunceſtours, from whiche too deliuer him ſelfe, in his wicked thought he throughely determined, wherefore in the yeare next folowyng, he commaunded a mightye oſte to be gathered to gether, ſignifying that the Perſians hadde inuaded Siria with a more huger armye then before: and that he forced for a publike ſafegard, hadde determined thither to leade the Oſte in his propre perſon, and reſiſte the intētes of their enemies. The ſouldiers therfore gathered to gether all moſt at a beckning, and neceſſarye prouiſion generally ordeined for the

warre, commaundement beynge geuen to ſette forwarde, after fewe dayes the bloud ſuckyng father dothe folowe hys armye. Whiche when he was ariued in Siria, fourthe with charged Muſtapha, to repaire vnto him at Alepes (for ther he had pitched his tētes. But in the meane ſpace Solimam was not ſo able to conceale, by outwarde aparance, (althoughe diligent regarde was applied thervnto) the deteſtable and deadlye hatred, which in his harte he had conceiued towardes his ſonne, but that it came to the euident perſeuerance of the Paſchans, and other men of greater dignitye about him.
            Throughe the whych one Acmat a paſcha ſecretly warned Muſtapha by a meſſenger, that he ſhoulde haue a more carefull regarde vnto his lyfe and ſaflye.
            And in deede Muſtapha thought it not vnworthy to be marueled at, ye hys Father with out any probable reaſon, ſhold thither reſort with ſo great an armye of

ſouldiers, howbeit truſtynge to his innocencye extremely vexed with anguiſh and perturbation of minde, he fully purpoſed to ſatiffye and obeye, (althoughe with no ſmall perill of his lyfe) hys fathers cōmaundementes. For he thought it to be more honeſt and laudable, by obeyinge his father to incurre death, then by liuynge to fall into the crime of diſobedience. But weyinge, in this ſo great ſorowe and heauines, many cogitations in his minde, at lenght conſtantlye and with out tremblinge, he demaunded of his teacher, whome (as before wée haue mencioned) he had alwayes with hym, in his courte, whether on empire of the whole worlde, or a bliſſed lyfe, were rather to be wiſhed for by a man? vnto whō the doctor frely aunſwered, that ye Empire of this worlde, vnto a man throughlye conſiderynge it, doth brynge no felicitye, but vnder a vaine and colored apearence of the trewe goodnes, for then

that, their is nothynge more vnſtable, and leſſe aſſured: in as muche as it is wont to brynge with it ſelfe, méere ſorowe, perplexitye of minde, tribulation, ſuſpicions, manſlaughter, feare▪ vngodlines, vniuſte dealinges, ruine, captiuitye, ſpoilinge, with diuers other kindes of miſchefe, neuer too bée wiſhed by ſuch a one, as is deſirons to attayne vnto the trewe bliſſednes, by the whyche doutles a happye lyfe ſhoulde bée loſte and not wonne, but vnto whome bée geuen, depelye to weye and conſider the vnſtabilitye and ſhortnes of this our fragile eſtate, whyche the common ſorte eſtemeth to be the trewe felicite, and ſtriue againſte the vanityes of this worlde, and imbrace honeſtye, that no doubte for them, ther was a place aſſygned and prepared in heauen by the highe God, wher they 
                  •
               ſhoulde geue the fruition of perpetuall ioye, and a bleſſed lyfe. With thys aunſwere of the Doctor, the young

mans minde beynge marueilouſly troubled, as it were after a ſorte, by a preſagement of hys deathe, it is throughelye purpoſed, he ſayde, and abidyng no long communication, incontinent directed his iorneye towardes hys bloude thirſtynge Father, and not farre from hym, pitched his tentes in the plaine felde. But this ſoo haſtye commynge of Muſtapha, kyn
                  •
               led a greater ſuſpicion in hys wicked Father, and in the meane time Ruſtanus ceaſed not, in that behalfe to augment and encreaſe thys ſuſpicion with hys moſte leude lyes, and diſſemblynge deuiſes, for geuynge a ſygne, he encoraged the Janiſcharies, and other the chefeſt ſouldiers of the armye, to goe fourth and mete Muſtapha. And farther prolonging ſette a ſyde, euerye one moſte ſpede
                  •
               ye executed hys commandementes, prouided and furniſhed hym ſelfe for the iorneye. After that the moſte diſceitfull villaine ſhewinge fourthe (as he knewe

exceadyngelye to faine) a diſdainefulnes in hys countenance, conueyed ſtreyght waye hym ſelfe into the kynges tente, moſte impudentlye affirming
                  •
               , that all the principall ſouldiers, for the moſte parte, were departed of their owne accorde, and without any biddinge, to receyue and méete Muſtapha. Whyche beynge heard, the kynge, throughe vexations of hys minde, beganne too were pale, and goynge out of hys tente, ſoone perſwaded him ſelfe, that the woordes were trewe whyche had bene ſpoken by Ruſtanus. And there wanted not vnto Muſtapha prodigious viſions of his vnfortunate chaunce to com. For the thirde daye béefore he ſhoulde make ready him ſelfe for the iourneye, ſlepyng about the twye light of the daye, he ſemed to haue ſeene Machomet appareled with gliſteringe robes, takyng him by the hande, to bringe him vnto a certaine place moſte delectable, graniſhed with exquiſite and

gorgiouſe palaices, and enuironed with a moſt pleaſant garden, whiche pointing to euerye thynge with his finger, ſpake to hym in this maner: ſayinge, here perpetually do reſt as many as in the world, haue leaden a godlye and vpryght lyfe, with ſuche as haue bene mainteiners of the lawes and rightuouſnes, and equitie and reprouers of ſynne and vices. After that turnyng his face on the other ſyde, to haue beholden two brode and moſte ſwifte riuers, whereof the one to ſéethe with water more blacke then any pitche, and great number to bée drowned therin, the reſte to appeare aboue the water, cryinge for mercye with a moſt horrible voice: and in this place, he ſayd, are tormēted ſuch as malitiouſly haue wrought iniquitie, remaininge vnder the waueringenes of hys fickle life. And the greateſt parte of them he affirmed to be Emperours, kynge, princes, and other ſuche great potentates of the worlde. Whiche

being finiſhed, Muſtapha broken out of his ſlepe &amp; viſion, commaunded the Doctor to be ſent for, &amp; opened vnto him the whole courſe of his dreame. But he muſing ther vpō a long ſpace, (for the ſuperſticious Machometiſts do attribute very much vnto ye doting to yes of dreames) repleniſhed with ſorow &amp; penſifenes, in the &amp; aunſwered, that the viſion was to be feared, as one whych foreſhwed vnto hym great perill of hys lyfe. Wherfore he councelled hym to haue eſpeciall regarde of his healthe and dignitye. But Muſtapha, as he was endewed withe magnanimitye and fortitude, hauynge no reſpecte to hys awneſwere, ſtow
                  •
               lye replied, ſayinge, ſhal I ſuffer my ſelfe to bee made a fearde, and vanquiſhed, with friuolous and childiſhe feare? whi rather doe I not make haſt with a conſtant and vnwauering corage, to go towardes my Father, and ſo much the bolder, becauſe I knowe moſte certainelye, that I haue

alwayes ſo duelye reuerenced (as it béecommed me) his maieſtye, that hée vnwillinge thervnto, I neuer turned mine eyes towardes his roiall ſeate, muche leſſe my féete, but leaſt of all mynded to affecte the Empire: except the eſpeciall fauour of the highe God, had called hym awaye vnto a better lyfe, and not then alſo withou
                  •
               e the frée and publike election of the whole Oſte, that at length, with out all ſlaughter, bludſheding, and crueltye, I might raigne after a godlye ſorte iuſtelye, and kéepe inuiolated the Frendeſhippe of my brethren. For I haue purpoſed with my ſelfe, and rather choſen, ſins that my Fathers will and pleaſure dothe ſo require, by dwe obedience to ende my lyfe, then raignyng manye yeares, to be reputed of all men, but chiefely by mine aduerſaries, as a rebell. This communication finiſhed, Muſtapha apparaleth hym ſelfe in whit robes, putteth certaine letters in his boſome,

whyche the Turkes mindinge to goe any where, ar wont alwayes to carye with them, (for in ſuperſticious ceremonies they dote verye muche,) and ſo ſette forwarde towardes his Fathers campe, and (as we haue ſayde (pitched Pauilyons: this at length accompained with certaine of hys truſtye frendes, he directed hys iorneye to the tente of hys wicked Father, mindinge with great reuerence (as the cuſtomes amonge them required) to kyſſe his parentes handes.
            But when he came to the firſt entrance therof, remembryng him ſelfe to be girded with a dagger, he entred not in before he hadde layed downe the ſame, becauſe he woulde not be ſéene to come armed in his fathers preſence, and to remoue far from him all ſuſpicion. Being entred the iuner partes of the t
                  •
               nte, he was receiued ioyfullye enoughe &amp; with ſuche reuerence as ought to bée required, by the Evnuches of his Father.

But ſeing but one ſeate prepared wherin he alone ſhould ſitte▪ repleniſhed with care, he ſtede ſtill a good ſpace muſinge with him ſelfe, and at lenght demaunded where the Kynge was. When the ſtanders by hadde aunſwered, that he ſhoulde incontinent behold him, he ſawe frome the other ſyde ſeuen dumbe men to come towardes him, (whom the Emperour of Turkye is accoſtomed to haue about him, as partakers of his ſecretes, and redye wickedlye to accompliſhe all kyndes of murther, and heynous actes) wherwith beyng ſtroken with feare and terror, beholde my deathe, he ſayde, and riſynge, contented to flye awaye, but in vaine, for apprehended by the Evnuches and kepers, he was drawen by force vnto the appointed place of hys vnhappye chaunce, and with out anye longer delaye, the dumbe men quickly bounde the ſtringe of a bowe aboute his necke, the miſerable younge man ſtruggeling, and

humbly deſiringe that he might bée permitted to ſpeake but two onely woordes vnto his father, whiche beaſtlye and vnnaturall manquellour, that, from an other ſide of the tente behelde that lamē
               table ſight, rebuked them with a thundrynge crewell voice, ſaying: what not yet at lenght, will you execute my commaundementes? and kil this traiter whiche by the ſpace of tenne yeares hath not ſuffred me to take one quiet nights reſt? whoſe ſo ſharpe, fearce, and imperious wordes beyng hearde, the Evnuches by helpe of the dumbe men, threwe the miſerable wretche to the grounde, and the ſtringe bounde about his necke, drawen from eyther his ſides, they ſtrangled the moſt vnhappye ſone, by commaundemēt of his vnkynde Father. This horrible &amp; pitifull murther in ſuch ſorte diſpatched, ſone after by aſſignemēt of the king, was taken the Paſchan of the prouince of A maſia, and beheaded in the kynges preſence,

whyche accomplyſhed, he ſent for the bunched Giangir, ignorant of ſuche happes as were befallen, and ieſtinge as thoughe he hadde done a thinge worthy prayſe and commendation, he bidde hym to go and receiue his brother Muſtapha. Then Giangir with a ioyfull and merye hart made haſte, thinkyng to haue mette wyth his brother. But when he came vnto the place, and vnhappye ſtrangled brother, and beheld him yinge one the earthe, it is impoſſible to bée declared, with what griping gryfes he was pricked at the harte. And ſcarſe was he yet come thyther, whē hys malitious father, ſente after hym meſſangers, whyche in his name, ſhoulde offer vnto him all the treaſure of Muſtapha, his horſes, tentes, ſeruantes, robes, ornamentes, and beſides that the prouince of Amaſia. But Giangir repleniſhed with extreme ſorow and penſifenes, for the pitifull deathe of hys deareſt beloued brother, powrynge

out plentye of teares, ſpake in thys maner: Out vppon the, O defeſtable and wicked dogge: Otraiter, I wil not name the Father, thou thy ſelfe nowe enioye the treaſures, horſes, ornamentes, &amp; prouince of Muſtapha. Coulde ther any ſuch thinge take place, in that fearce vngodly and miſcheuous minde of thyne, as too murther ſo noble, warlyke, and ſonne of ſuche a towardes, whoſe lyke the houſe of Ottomanno hadde neuer vntill thys daye, neyther ſhall in time to come, and that withe out all reſpecte of humanytye or ryght of bloudde? I will beware therfore, leaſt heereafter, thou triumphe in lyke maner, bragge ſoo vnſhamefaſtlye ouer me poore bunched miſer. Hauinge in this ſorte tragicallye lamented, and takyng in hande his dagger, wherwith hée was girded, he thruſte it throughe his inwarde boweles, and ſo ſodainlye gaue vp the ghouſte. Whiche déede whē it cam vnto the Emperours hering,

a hard matter it was to ſpeake, what vexations griped him at the hart. Howbeit ſo great anguiſhe and ſorowe ouercame not his couetous minde, for incontinent he commaunded all the riche treaſures of Muſtapha to be brought into hys tentes. But the ſouldiers thinkynge that all his ſubſtance was graunted and geuen for a praye, made earneſt ſpede with prompt and readye mindes to performe the kynges hoſtes. Durynge which time the ſouldiers of Muſtapha remaining in the campe, ignorante of that whyche had befallen to their Lorde and gouernour, ſeynge ſo great a bande of ſouldiers, to come ruſhe on, with out al order of war, wherby to repell &amp; driue of their tumultuous inſolence, came armed agaynſte them, and ſoo manfullye brake theyr force, not with out ſlaughter of a great number on their ſyde. As ſoone as ye rumor of this tragedye was brought vnto the kyngs ſouldiers, perceiuing the hurlye

burlye more and more to kyndle and encreaſe, determined to helpe their companions: and ſo at lenght proclamation made vnto armour, a blouddye cumbate was fought on bothe ſydes, in ſo muche that in ſhort ſpace wer ſlaine aboue two thouſande men, and manye other wounded: and the tragedye had gone farther, if one Achmat a Paſchan, a manne moſte graue, and for his vertuous exploites, of no ſmall reputation amonge the ſouldiers, had driuē backe the Janiſcharies, and apeaſed their rage, turnynge hym ſelfe alſo towardes the ſouldiers of Muſtapha, and mitigated with gentill wordes and exhortations their ſtirred mindes, ſaynge: what will you nowe deare brethren and louyng frendes, degenerating frō that wiſdom throughe the whiche, in ſo many ages you haue bene praiſed and highelye commended, go againſt and withſtande the commaundementes of the great Soltan our Emperour? I

can not (as God ſhoulde loue me) maruell enoughe, what hath ſoo inflamed your harts, whom I hethervnto haue alowed as moſtvaliant &amp; renowmed ſouldiers, as in this ciuill conflicte, to ſtr
                  •
               tche fourth theſe wepons againſte your owne fellowes, whiche with ſuche proſperours ſucceſſe, and good fortune, you haue vſed vpon the enemies of the houſe of Ottomanna, and to repreſent ſuche a ſpectakle vnto your aduerſaries, yt they, by whoſe ryght hande they lament them ſelues, vanquiſhed, ſhoulde now reioyſe for their mutual deſtruction and ſlaughter. Therfore my ſonnes haue diligent regarde, for your magnanimities ſake, leſt by this your raſhe inſolency, you leſe that wiſdome and fortitude, wherby vnto this daye aboue all other men you haue bene extolled, and reſerue theſe wéepons, which to much you haue exerciſed agaynſt your owne ſelues, for your enemies, when a better occatien, and more

prayſe woorthy ſhalbe miniſtred. With this and ſuche lyke ſainges, Achmat the Paſchan aſwaged the kyndled corages of the ſouldiers, ſo that they ſuffred all thinges peaceablely to bée caried out of the tentes of Muſtapha vnto the kynge. But when the death of Muſtapha came to the Janiſcharies &amp; eares of the whole Hoſte, a freſhe ſedition began amonge them. Euerye one cried vnto armour agayne, and makyng a terrible noyſe, by reaſon of their teares and wepinges, as they were this in a ragyng and furious minde, came violentlye ruſhynge withe great tumulte and drawen ſwordes, into the kinges tente. But this renewed conſpiracye, broug
                  •
               t ſuche tremblynge into the kynges minde, that deſtitute of all councell, he woulde haue taken flight, with no ſmall daunger of his head. How beit beynge helde by his ſeruantes, and takynge occation of neceſſyty, he purpoſed to attempt the thyng, whiche in ſaftye,

he neuer thought to haue done, and entringe out of the doores, ſpake in thys ſort (but with a pale countenance) vnto the ſoudiers: what rumor, noyſe, rufling, and inſolencye is this, wherwith ſo raſſhelye you haue diſquieted my minde? What doe this furious, inflamed, and irefull viſages ſignifie? Wil you not cal to remēbrance that I am he which hathe the powre to rule &amp; gouerne you? Haue you determined to blotte your warrlyke prowes, and the martiall feates of your aunceſtours, by ſhedynge the bloudde of your kynge and Emperour? Vnto the kynge ſpeaking in this maner, ſtoutlye aunſwered the ſouldiers: that they in dede confeſſed him to be the ſame, whom manye yeares ſence they hadde elected, but in that they hadde by their coragious mankynes conquered him ſo large an Empire, and defended the ſame, for thys occation to be done, becauſe he ſhoulde raygne vprightlye, miniſter iuſtice, and

not without regarde to laye hys handes one euery iuſte perſon, and wickedlye too embrwe him ſelfe in the bloud of Innocentes. And that in defence of an vpright quarell, they were come armed, and prouoked to reuenge the deathe of giltles Muſtapha, neyther the kyng to haue any reſonable cauſe, whereby to bée ſtirred with diſpleaſure againſt them. Their deſire therfore was, that, wherby to purge them ſelues openly of the crime of traiters, of the whiche they were falſely accuſed by ye aduerſaries of Muſtapha, the accuſer ſhould come fourthe in the middeſt, &amp; that they woulde not laye downe their armour, beefore he had perſonallye apeared in iudgemente, and beginne his accuſation, as the lawe required, vppon paine of lyke puniſhement. Duringe the time that theſe thinges ſhould he donne, the horrour of that heynou
                  •
                acte, prouoked them all to wepyng, in ſo much that the kynge ſemed to repent hym of that

cruell, deteſtable, and beaſtlye killing of his ſōue. Then the kinge promiſed vnto the ſouldiers, with gentill woordes, the ſucceſſe of their demaundes, and endeuored, as muche as he coulde, to pacifye their inflamed minds. But in the mean time the ſouldiers, leſt the kynge ſhould craftelye haue eſcaped, and diſapointed them of his promiſes, and the expectatiō of ſuche thinges as they had requeſted, remained all of ſette purpoſe, with diligent care to kepe the watche and warde, After that the kyng cleane depriued Ruſtanus of all his dignities, toke from him the kynges ringe, wherof he hadde bene keper, and deliuered it to Achmat the paſchan. But Ruſtanus brokē with feare and trembling, ſeynge hym ſelfe ſcarſe voyde of daunger in hys owne tentes, fludde priuely vnto the pauilious of Achmat the paſchan, and conſulted with him what were beſt to be done in ſoo doutfull and perilous a buſines, whiche aunſwered,

that therin he ſhould vſe the aduiſe of the kynge, and obeye what ſo euer by him ſhould be commaunded. Theſe wordes greatly contented the mynde of Ruſtanus, and makyng no long delay, aſked councell of the kyng concernyng all hys minde, by meſſangers, his truſty and familiar frendes. But aunſwere being geuen, that, al lingring ſet a part, he ſhould abſent him ſelfe, moſt ſpedely from the kinges ſight and pauilions: he replied, that it coulde not conueniently be done, with out money &amp; pauilions, vnto whom the king againe aunſwered, that neither time, place, or longer delay to take commodious opportunitie, by anye meanes ſhoulde be graunted▪ Then Ruſtanus at length, with out longer taryinge, giltye enoughe vnto him ſelfe, of his miſceuous committed dedes, accōpained with eight of his moſt faithfull frendes directed his iorney towardes Conſtantinople, and with ſpedy pace (as feare is accuſtomed

to miniſter wynges) in the ende came thyther, and there with Roſa, and manye other confederates vnto that conſpiracye, expecteth the euente of his fortune, not with out great iepardye of leſinge his head. The rumor went that Soliman alſo, giltye vnto him ſelfe of ſo outragious a murther, was pricked with a ſuperſticious repentance, to goe vnto Mecha, and takyng his iorney, beyng cō
               pelled by the Perſian powre, from théſe to ſpede him ſelfe vnto Ieruſalem, ther to offer ſacrifice (called in ye language Corban) for his diſceaſed ſon. And this much (once to make an ende) came to my remembrance, to declare, or rather geue admoniſhement of Muſtapha, yt he was, for his warrelyke prowes, and prompt minde to ſhedde chriſtian bloud, ſo fauored of all menne, that they maye thynke neuer anye to haue ſprongen out of the linage of Ottomanno, whyche woulde haue promiſed ſo muche concerning enlargemēt

of their empire, ſo that among them of diſpared maters is ryſen thys prouerbe Gietti Soltan Muſtapha, wherby they would ſignifie, that of their firſt purpoſed intent their labour to be loſt, or in vaine. We oughht therfore to reioyce one with eche other, for the deathe of ſo fearce, cruell and deadly an enemye, and thinke, that it came not to paſſe with out the prouidence of God, whyche in that behalfe was minded to prouide for our ſaftye and ſauegarde. Finallye, lette vs once at length, take diligent care for our ſelues, that we maye abſteine from ciuil warres and diſſentions, thynkynge, that we ought to goe againſte (euery manne addynge his helpinge hande) this common enemy, not only of our natiue countrye and liues, but alſo vnto our ſoules. Whyche if we doe, it ſhall not bée harde to driue from vs this mortall aduerſarye vnto the name of chriſtianitie, if otherwyſe, it wilbe daungerous, leaſte, (wee

beyng occupied about hatefull conſpiracies amonge our ſelues) endeuour to inuade, waſt, and ſpoile with his tyrannye that part of Europe that yet remaine the vnto vs vnperiſhed, whyche the almightye and omnipotent God forbidde, and reduce ds vnto concorde and vnitie for his ſonne IESVS Chriſtes ſake our Sauiour and redemer
            AMEN.
         
      
      
         
            
               ❧ Imprinted at London in Fleteſtrete, nere to S. Dunſtons Churche by Thomas Marſhe▪
                ❀
            
         
      
   

