
   
      
         
            The epistle of Gildas, the most ancient British author who flourished in the yeere of our Lord, 546. And who by his great erudition, sanctitie, and wisedome, acquired the name of sapiens. Faithfully translated out of the originall Latine.
            Liber querulus de excidio Britanniae. English
            Gildas, 516?-570?
         
         
            
               1638
            
         
         Approx. 294 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 229 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2006-06 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01759
            STC 11895
            ESTC S103163
            99838920
            99838920
            3311
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01759)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3311)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1139:02)
         
         
            
               
                  The epistle of Gildas, the most ancient British author who flourished in the yeere of our Lord, 546. And who by his great erudition, sanctitie, and wisedome, acquired the name of sapiens. Faithfully translated out of the originall Latine.
                  Liber querulus de excidio Britanniae. English
                  Gildas, 516?-570?
                  Abingdon, Thomas.
                  Marshall, William, fl. 1617-1650, engraver.
               
               [134], 327 [i.e. 325] p. : port.  
               
                  Printed by T. Cotes, for William Cooke and are to be sold at his shop neere Furnivalls-Inne gate in Holborne,
                  London :
                  1638.
               
               
                  Translation by Thomas Abington of: Liber querulus de excidio Britanniae.
                  P. 325 misnumbered 327.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
                  The portrait is engraved and signed: Will: Marshall. sculp.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Great Britain --  History --  To 440 --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2003-03
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2005-12
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-03
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2006-03
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-04
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
               
                  Vera effigies Gildae qui ob insignem Prudentiam, Morum
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      Severitatem Cognominatus est Sapiens Floruit anno reparationis humanae DXXXXVI
                  Will: Marshall-sculp:
                  portrait of Gildas
               
            
         
         
            
            THE EPISTLE of GILDAS, The most Ancient BRITISH Author: Who flourished in the yeere of our Lord, 546. And who by his great Erudition, Sanctitie, and Wisedome, acquired the name of Sapiens.
            
            Faithfully Translated out of the Originall Latine.
            
            
               LONDON, Printed by T. Cotes, for William Cooke and are to be sold at his shop neere Furnivalls-Inne gate in Holborne. 1638.
         
         
            
            
               Imprimatur,
            
            
               Tho. Wykes▪ R. P. Episc. Lond. Capell. domest.
            
         
         
            
            Of Gildas and the Translation.
            
               THE age of bookes shows the strength of their composition; Weake or abortive births, perishing in the infancy, scarce numbred among the workes of Time. This Author lived neere the so memorable desolation of this Island, when the Saxons, under the conduct of Hengist and Horsus, forc't the natives to

cold and inaccessible mountaines, and conquered the Country so farre, that they left it not the empty honour of the former name.
            The causes of their ruine, he passionately, but faithfully, attributes to the misgovernment of evill govern'd Princes, ignorance of a licentious Clergy, and an universall laps of the people into impiety. Against these as a zealous Citizen of the world, and a most particular, but sad lover of his Country; this Reverend Father inveighes, and profitably

instructs the present, by correcting the enormities of the age hee lived 
                  •
               n. The Translation was made neere the first entrance of the Scottish line upon the Throne of England. To the continuance 
                  •
               f which the Preface con
               
                  •
               urres with most zealous 
                  •
               ishes. In rendring this 
                  ••
               to English, much faith 
                  ••
               th beene observed; by 
                  •
               hich you may discover, the 
                  •
               uthor still the same▪ 
               
                  ••
               ough in his apparell fashi
               
                  ••
               ed to the time. In peru
               
                  ••
               ng whom, the Reader

shall finde, that impiety is the great destroyer of Empires; and that kingdome that remaynes most emmaculate from sinne, stands safest from ruine.
         
         
            
            TO THE INHABITANTS OF THE Island of great BRITAINE, Vnitie and Felicity.
            
            
               IF all men are generally so much addicted unto the monuments of forepassed ages, and every Country particularly

unto the antiquities of the Land wherein they inhabit, which is the reason that this our owne Island so much delighteth in beholding the ruines of Verolamium, the renowned Towne of the Romans, the huge and wonderfull stones on Salisburies plaine, the remembrance of the Britanes, Thonge Castle the first seate of the Saxons, the trenches and Fortresses of the Danes, and the Abbey of Battaile the

trophey of the Normanes, that I may omit the quoines of the old. Emperours, the tombs of conquering Kings, with the Armes, swords and Launces of famous men, being all held in estimation, of purpose to reward with continuall commendation the worthy actions of deceased persons, and to leave us examples to imitate their right Noble enterprises: How much more are wee then bound with affectionate

eyes to behold this ancient Author Gildas, who doth not onely present unto our view the lively Image of this Land, how in glory of beautifull Citties, in pollished order of good husbandry, &amp; in industrious trafficke of merchandise, shee shined above a thousand yeeres agoe (at which time some ignorant men suppose she was onely overgrowne with a wildernesse, and overwhelmed

with Barbarisme) but also that she did as then bring forth unto the world learning, wisdome and true religious vertue, which above all these are most highly to bee honoured. And although some fresh water souldiers (who never saw the large Sea of ancient writers) may imagine every shallow brooke of our late pamphleters, to bee the very Ocean of learning, yet when overpassing our

mechanical Chroniclers I looke into Malmsbury and Hungtington, and others such as these, yea and above them into venerable Bede and Gildas, me seemeth that traveiling over the barren Alpes I descend downe into pleasant and fruitfull Italy, or sayling beyond the rude Ethiopians and Indians, I arrive on the coasts of the incomparable Country of China. But falling on this treasure of antiquitie (Gildas
               
I meane) I found my selfe instantly so devoted unto him, that what for mine owne recreation, and what to deceive the tediousnesse of my lingring imprisonment: and lastly, that they who are not able, for want of the tongue to purchase the knowledge of him in his owne naturall Latine, should not remaine altogether destitute of so great riches, I painted him out though unskilfully,

yet howsoever in our English language: In wch attempt, I found two especiall difficulties, the one he was in many places (through the negligence of them in whose hands he rested) so over-eaten with the rust of time, that I could scarcely discerne his lively Portrature, the other his sentences were so long and obscure, that they would be harsh and disliking to the reader, yet love overcomming all, and

pleasure drawing mee forward, I adventured as touching the first, to ayme at this Image, &amp; give a guesse where I could not determine the certainety, and for the last to set himselfe (as neere as I could) according to his proper fashion, knowing it to be as undecent to turne his grave speeches into idle words, and his long periods into short sentences, as to picture a sad man with a pleasant looke,

and to draw the counterfet of a reverent Iudge not in his robes but in some light attire: Wherefore I must intreate for the obscuritie the readers attention, for the tediousnesse his patience, and for mine owne enterprise his pardon.
            
               The cause why Gildas alledgeth almost only the Scriptures.One silly writer unskilfully noteth how Gildas (leaving all authorities of men) followeth only the Scriptures, little considering that he intending

to reproove the depraved lives of Princes and Prelates, could finde no Patrons so worthy and able to protect him, as the volumes of the holy Prophets, who bent all their powers to batter downe the enormous offences of Governours; as for the Church having not long before (by the conclusion of the primitive persecution) overcome her most grievous enemies, and instantly

afterwards incountring with her unnaturall rebells, the horrible Arians and others, she could hardly yet finde a time to suppresse these abuses, and for the Doctors who were some of them but lately dead, and others as yet unborne, the later were not extant, and the former had not by continuance of time received their strength and glory; for if I may compare small things unto great

Authors are like coates of Armes, which by antiquitie purchase commendations.
                  Gildas citeth Scriptures not after the vulgar Translation.
            
            Another matter not onely cavilled at by the former carper, but observed also by Pollidor Virgill is, that in most of the citations of the holy Scripture, he very farre differeth from the vulgar translation; a thing not much to bee merveiled at, for it is not unknowne unto the learned, how in old time there were many

Translations of the Bible, for extinguishing of which dangerous varietie, and establishing of Gods Word in one perfect uniformitie, Saint Ierome at the commandement of Pope Damasus, Translated the Old Testament out of the Hebrew, and also the New Testament out of the Greeke, whereof Gildas could not be ignorant, sithence he flourished about one hund
                  •
               ed

yeeres afterwards, and was a man of great knowledge and wisedome; but in respect this Island had beene long corrupted with Heretickes, and now oppressed with Infidels, it is likely that the Church in Britaine (by reason of the tumults of such rebellious and outragious enemies) wanting her due preeminence, could not as yet display the banner of this reformed Bible, but marched under the

Ensigne of some other Translation which our Authour speaking generally to the whole Land) hath for conformitie unto the common fashion (as it seemeth) vouchsafed here to use, being especially as apt as any other to reprove the disorders of the Iland, and no way patronizing either the Arians or Pellagians (the most deadly cankers as then of the Christian Commonwealth) or any other

heresie, that hath ever since lifted up her viperous head against the Church of God.
            Another thing very much to bee lamented and merveiled at is,The reasons why Britaine was at this time so defiled with vices. that not onely the temporall Princes, but also the Spirituall Rulers (whose lives should be a light unto the rest, and salt to preserve the soules of men from corruption) had at this time many of them so degenerated from all goodnes, as not only it

provoked the justice of God to dispossesse them of their Country and give it to their deadly foes the Saxons, but also made Pollidor Virgill suppose that Britaine did never after the persecution of Dioclesian perfectly returne unto the unity of the Catholicke Church againe; an opinion by Gildasses owne words refelled, for he sheweth how after the stormy winter (as hee calleth, it of this persecution,

succeeded the flourishing spring of true Christian and Catholicke religion; but the Author himselfe declareth some notorious causes of the ruine of as well Civill as Ecclesiasticall discipline, and the first was heresies, for upon this fruitfull seede of the Gospell, came the Arians, and scattered the darnell of their detestable doctrine, yea (as he saith) all other damnable Sectaries breathed out

upon the Land, their venemous poyson, and not onely this, but also from the very bowels of Britaine was borne that accursed wretch Pellagius, and shortly after the death of Gildas were the Britaines overwhelmed with the darkesome cloud of the Quartodecimani (who varied frō the Church of God in celebrating the feast of Easter, these truely were the mothes that did eate the garment of the governmēt

of the realme. Another was bloudy warre (the depraver of Civill discipline, and the Author of disorder, that for many yeeres built here his Fortresse, who as hee commandeth for the time all Spirituall and nationall Lawes to silence, so hee corrupteth the manners of all Countries through which hee marcheth; by the power of warre were Infidels planted in the Land, who as they were professed

foes of the faith of God, so were their lives defiled with all offences; and these also in all likelihood infected the Britaines with the plague of their vices. After the warres were ended, and Britaines together with the Saxons (like Sheepe and Goates) continued in one fold, altogether for a while the scourge of misery (which chastised the Christian Britanes) terrified them from transgressing the

Commandements of God, yet plentifull peace (the Nurse of sensuality) so lulled them afterwards asleepe in her lap with a seeming but deceitfull security, that hereupon sprung the last cause of their confusion (to wit) exceeding wickednesse sprouting out from the roote of abundant wealth: For according unto Moses; Incrassatus est dilectus, &amp; recalcitravit; incrassatus, impinguatus, dilatatus dereliquit

Deum factorem suum, &amp;c. and even as the Children of Israel did sit them downe to eate and drinke, and then arose to play, untill the fury of our Lord was pawred out upon them; so the Britaines growing fat in worldly pleasures, and foule in hidious sinnes, continued on in their earthly contentments, untill the sword of the Saxons (which was scarcely as yet put in the sheath againe) was by

the sufferance of God drawne out afresh to deprive them of their pleasant Country. But although mine Author Gildas discovereth the defects of Princes and Prelates, yet let no man thinke that any Subjects can for the deadly sinnes of their Superiours, either deprive or disobey them, since neither David did for his adultery with Bersabee, and murther of his faithfull servant Vrias, lose his royalty,

nor yet the Authority of the chaire of Moses, was any whit diminished, although Scribes and Pharisees for a time possessed the same, but that the Leapers who were clensed were sent to the Priests (although unworthy of their Primacy) and Caiphas himselfe (albeit he was the persecutor of Christ Iesus) prophesied, because he was high Priest of that yeere; all which I professe against the Heretickes

who have perversely maintained the contrary. Neither yet let any man falsly imagine, that the Land was wholly as then drowned in iniquities, for (as Gildas doth in 2 places apparantly manifest) there were diverse at that very time, whose vertues he doth most highly commend and reverence.
            Now before I doe harbour in the Haven of my desired end, I must of necessitie passe

by three rockes of exceeding danger, the invectives (I meane) of Gildas, against some sorts of people most happily combined under his Majesties government, the first the Britanes, the most auncient inhabitantes of this Island, the other the Irish together with the Scottish, and Pictes who next possessed part of the Land, and last the Saxons and English who have very long enjoyed the most

large and fruitfull portion of the Country. The Britaines not onely by the pen of Sir Iohn Price (a learned Knight and writer of theirs) suspect Gildas for a Libeller, but doe hardly also sustaine other Authors, who alleadge also out of him any thing that may seeme disgracefull to the Nation, unto whom truely as I have ever borne all due respect and tender affection, so doe I most

humbly crave their pardon in a word or two without offence, to defend their wise and worthy Countreymen whom I may well compare unto a father who (correcting his childe) telleth him onely of his faults and imperfections, or unto the Prophets who in old time reproving the Israelites did lay nothing before their eyes but their sinnes and offences, or to the man in the Gospell who

labouring to make his vine bring forth the desired fruit; dresseth the roote with unsavory dung. He doth not declare as now (O renowned Britaines) how yee releived your friends the Galles against the invincible Legions of Caesar, how valiently yee defended your Land against his conquering army, how one King of a little corner of your Island (Silures or South-Wales I meane) maintained

warre against the whole power of Rome and the world, and afterwards onely by misfortune falling into the hands of his honorable enemies, was by them held in equall estimation for worthinesse, with Perses the successour of Alexander
               ▪ but for valour with Alexander the great himselfe, he nameth not your victorious Vortimer, nor yet your invincible Arthur who in twelve foughten fields overthrew

your cruell enemies the Saxons, he leaveth those discourses to his Chronicle which Henry of Huntinton in the actions of Arthur citeth, hee revealeth now onely your reproaches, but why? because hee would reforme your abuses; hee chasticeth your vices, because hee would cherish your vertues; he aggravateth your offences ut sugeret mel de petra oleumque de

saxo durissimo, that hee may strike the fire of grace out of flinty hearts, and bring the oyle of Charity out of stony minds; he saith the Romanes did conquor yee, not so much with Armes as with the threates of their countenances, but telleth not how before that yee encountred (as most true it is) with their puissant power, and what was it (alas) for the naked to resist the armed, for them

who were altogether unskilfull in the order of fight to joyne in battell with the best practised souldiers, and one little Island to contend with the whole world? Yee fell with the generall calamity of the earth, into the subjection of the Romaine Empire. But afterwards (they say) ye were unfaithfull because yee killed them who were left in authoritie over yee: And who can tell what occasion

they offered yee to execute that slaughter upon them: wee see the cruelty that commonly all Conquerous exercise on their subjects; experience teacheth that all almost are tyrannous, and few or none moderate; yee wrought the like stratagem as the Cecilians did, afterwards on the Frenchmen; why are yee so soulely condemned as unfaithfull, but because it succeeded unhappily?

For ye were upon this occasion troden under the feete of your enemies; it is a Proverbe that never Rebell prevaileth against his Prince, and what is the reason? but this, if hee prevaileth hee is no Rebell, but usurpeth rather the title of a reformer of the Commonwealth, I doubt not but King Iohn and Henry the fourth, if they had not obtained the royall garland, had beene

registred for rebellious traytors, although now they are ranked among the famous Princes: so actions are measured not according to the intents, but after the events. But hereupon ensued your misery and reproach, ye were againe overcome (as he saith) without resistance, and therefore not accounted valiant! and did not the Iewes (who were truely as couragious a Nation as ever was on the

earth) open the gates of Ierusalem to Alexander, because they could notwithstand him? did not the Persians (those conquerours of the world) flye the face of the Macedonians? and the Persians and mighty Macedonians
               ▪ submit themselves to the Romaines? did not those nations who for war-like glory excelled all others, runne away as sheepe before these Italian Lyons? and why

should we then accuse the Britaines, (who were in respect a small handfull and never knew the Art of war) if they resisted not the Romanes who had three parts of the world at their commandment, and were the most expert souldiers that ever marched on the earth? The Britaines upon this became captives! and what Nation was not in subjection to the Romaines who held the earth as a slave in bondage

and ruled her Kings as if they were but servants? These things (noble Britaines) Gildas somewhat bitterly recounteth, but why? that he may with the knife of correction, pruine avvay your superfluous and dead branches and leaves of vaine glory and other vices. But although he swayeth throughout his vvorke in great austeritie, yet can he not so conceale the fire of his fatherly affection,

but that it flameth ou
                  •
                very often to your singular commendation. Yee were at the first termed unfaithfull, upon what occasion I have declared; but afterwards hee showeth your faith in the highest degree, in profession (I meane) of the Christian religion, in suffering terrible persecution, in obtaining most glorious martyrdome: your flight is objected as reprochfull vnto ye, but when?

before yee had the knowledge of warfare, but after ye had atchieved the art thereof, hee writeth how under the cōduction of Maximus, ye overthrew, though unjustly, yet most valiantly two Emperours of the world: but the lively blood of Britaine being extended into forraigne Nations, and there extenuated, and lastly, by misfortune extinguished, the entrailes and heart of the Island began at home

to grow weake and cold, which made her body so long oppressed with the invading diseases of the Scottish, Pictes, and Irish, and lastly, almost killed with the deadly plague of the Saxons: and did not the like befall unto the Romanes themselves who having wasted their strength in overcomming and keeping other Countries in obedience, became in the same sort weakned at home, and so fell in

               
                  •
               he end to be a prey, 
                  •
               nd spoile unto o
               
                  •
               hers? All this is but 
                  •
               he course and chance of fortune, or rather the high pleasure of God, to teach us that in this world there is nothing permanent. And againe our Authour not contayning himselfe, breaketh out into a singular report of your vallor, when (in the reproofe of Maglocune) hee saith that your Souldiers were so couragious, as their countenances in

battle were not unlike the terrible lookes of young Lions. But that I may passe to the rest, and so conclude this point, he doth so highly extoll the Country, Castles, and Cities of Britaine, as truely I am out of doubt the Island hath never since that time flourished in the like glory as then it did: and who so thinketh mee deceived, let him but looke into the histories of the Romans, where he shall reade of

               
                  •
               he Emperors, that did 
                  •
               n this land of Britaine 
               
                  •
               ontinue or finish their 
                  •
               ives, where among 
                  •
               he rest hee shineth in most eminent Majesty, who shutting up the temple of hellish ido
               
                  •
               atry, did first set open the gates of the Catholike Church, and of her peaceable God, Iesus, I meane that Constantine, vvho being borne in Britaine, &amp; of a Britaine Saintly Mother, tooke on him the Emperiall dignity, in this very

Island, vvhere so many governors of the vvorld vvould never have made their royall residence, had not the Country beene both fruitfull and civill, but barren and barbarous as the Romanes at their first entrance supposed the same to be. Lastly, he manifestly declareth that the land vvas as then also furnished vvith learning, because (vvriting generally an epistle unto the Country) he useth the Latine

tongue, which as it had beene a great folly in him to doe, if the same had not beene universally understood, so doe I verily thinke if the like worke in Latine were at this time presented unto the realme, it would little profit without an Interpreter.
            The next sort somewhat bitterly taxed by Gildas,
               The excuse of the invective of Gildas against the Scottish and Irish. are the Scottish, Pictes, and Irish, who are reproved as bloudy and barbarous: but

when? before ever they received the light and heate of civility, which from the Sunne of the Romane Empire did spread throughout all Countries, and undoubtedly made a singular preparation to the Almighty Grace of the holy Ghost, that afterwards replenished the whole world; but after they had accepted discipline, and were reduced into better order, and cheefely above all had imbraced Christian

and Catholike religion, then behold what these Benjamins proved, who by the British Iacob (Gildas I meane) are termed Lupi 
                     •
                   rapaces ravenous Wolves? see if that was not truely fulfilled in them which was rightly prophesied of that worthy Benjamin S. Paul, which is Mane rapit vespere dividit escas, in the morning or at the first they gained their booties by spoyling, but in the evening or at the

last they distributed their foode or baites; what foode? but to satisfie the hungry soules of men: what baites? but to catch such fish as might serve for the festivall table of our Saviour: Looke into Wales and Cornewall, and see how many Townes beare yet the names of Irish Saints, who harboured there, not as before to punish the Britaines with death, but to draw them to the rewards

of eternall life! Peruse the histories of the Countries beyond Humber, you shall read how the Pictes, and inhabitants of Scotland, who sometimes broke downe the Northerne fortifications, and invaded the Land, did afterwards beate down the Bulwarke of hell, delivered the soules which sinne did withhold in bondage, and made them the blessed captives of Christ, men undoubtedly of rare

holinesse, and unspotted conversation, had they not beene a little blemished with an erronious opinion, about the celebration of Easter, which as venerable Bede signifieth continued the longer among them, because inhabiting in a farre removed region of the world, they had not heard of the Cannons of the Church which commanded the contrary. Moreover as our Saviour did feede them bodily,

whom before he refreshed spiritually, so did they of Scotland, not onely with the bread of life, releeve their neighbours, but also received the Britaines (when they were expulsed out of their Country by the Saxons) into their bosome, and suffered them quietly to inhabit by them in Cumberland; and with like charitable affection entertained also the Saxons with their Prince Edgar, when they fled

from the countenance of the victorius Norman, William the Conqueror. And as touching their old barbarous misbehaviour (which Gildas here mentioneth) we have no more reason to upbraide the Scottish therewith, then to cast in the teethes of the refined Italians, what their Country was before Saturne did first instruct them in civility, being a time so overgrowne with rudnesse

as the Poets doe thereupon wittily descant, that men of that age were borne out of the trunckes of trees. For in processe of time by carefull diligence commeth the correction and amendment of Countries, and by carelesse negligence falleth the corruption and destruction of Nations.
            The last are the Saxons and English,
               The excuse of his seveare censuring of the English.
                called by him a people odious to God and man, to

God, because they were Idolatrous Infidels, to man, because they murthered and oppressed the Christian Britaines, and although he enlargeth himselfe in the dispraise of the Nation, let no man neverthelesse suppose that he uttereth this of any malice as stung with the dreadfull miseries with the which they vexed his Country: For who knoweth not that the English were in his age enemies

of Christ, religion, and the Land: But according to Esay, In the dennes wherein dragons did formerly dwell, greene reedes and rushes did afterwards grow; and after the sentence of Hosea; Where it was sayd ye were no people of mine, there shall the same persons bee named the sonnes of the living God. Yea the Lyons, the Liberds, the Beares, and the Wolves shall (as the Prophet writeth) quietly lodge and live with Oxen,

Sheepe, Kiddes, and Calves, and a little child (no doubt the Sonne of the Virgin) shall governe them all. For if ever the wilde Olive were changed into the rightfull Olive of our Lord, or if ever tree brought forth the true fruits of goodnesse, then were both these undoubtedly verified in the Saxons: For although they came but lately into the Vineyard, yet having entred, they laboured diligently,

and undertaking the race of a Christian life, they ranne most swiftly, and gained the garland victoriously; and who so thinketh I exceede in their commendation, let him but cast his eyes round about this Realme, and hee shall see the Churches and Monuments of religion (some fevv onely excepted) altogether founded by them; and that vve may leave the dead buildings, and

come to the lively stones of the heavenly Ierusalem; how are the Provinces, shires, and Parishes of the Land severally adorned with mighty number of English Saints, and if we may measure by the Governours, what the people were (since unto the examples of their Rulers, the subjects are commonly conformable) let us but consider the royall offspring of the Saxons, and we shall finde that

never in any land so many Princes left their worldly estates to embrace Christian poverty, and draw in the Yoake of our Saviour, and never so many of Kingly blood were canonised in the heavenly Register, as in this our Country; what shall I say more, In omnem terram exivit sonus eorum, their renowne is spread over the whole world, and their glory fixed above the firmament; in so much as

               William of Malmsbury deriving the Pedegree of holy Edward the Confessour, sheweth a descent, not onely of Kings but also of Saints so as to the Church then among us those Words of Esay may be fitly applyed, Reges servient tibi: and againe, Mamilla regum lactaberis, Kings shall doe service unto thee, and with the teates of Princes thou shalt be nourished. Let us leave the heavens and returne to the

earth, was the glory of the Saxons, which now mounted in blessed vertues aboue the Skie, bounded here below, onely in the Cloystures of Monasteries? No, but as the shaddow followeth the body, so likewise ensued all commodities requisite in a well ordered regiment, and first as touching learning (which manureth the mindes of men, and maketh them in due season bring forth their timely

fruites) they foun
                  •
               ded both the Vniversi
                  •
               ties of Oxford and Cam
                     •
                  bridge: For the ancien
                  •
                lawes, the most excel
                  •
               lent helme which steared the state, the bridle which restrayned distempered wils, and the very soule of the body of the Commonwealth, they were by them chiefely framed: and did their prayse onely consist in matters of pietie and peace? and was not their warlike glory equall to

their civill government? not so truely: but as a well compacted body hath bones and sinewes sutable to the head, so was their powerfull strength answerable to their other vertues, and not-onely of singular proofe at home; but also obtained a most high commendation abroad in forraigne Countries: All which heroicall actions they accomplished in lesse than five hundred yeeres notwithstanding

they were during the same time almost continually either invaded by strangers, or molested by unquiet neighbours.
            And thus have I somewhat inlarged my selfe in declaring the undoubted worthinesse of these three Nations, because I shall be enforced in this my translation to discover their ancient imperfections; neither have I used this commendation as sugar; Whereby

these distastfull pills may bee the better swallowed, but of purpose to shut up their mouths who otherwise might perhaps despightfully upbraide them with these old offences; which truely they have no more reason to doe, than those irreligious tongues who (audaciously talking of the blessed Apostles) call Saint Peter the denyer of his Master, Saint Paul the Persecutor,

Saint Matthew the Publican, for if wee should be esteemed as we have beene, what were we other than the children of wrath; but by the grace of God we are as we are, and I beseech Christ his grace may not be voyd in us.
            
               How the Kings Majestie is descended of the blood royall of these three Nations.And now verily it is with great applause to be received, that it hath pleased God to make the royall lines of these three severall people to meete in the

Center of his Majesties person: For of the first I meane the Britaines) he is come by his last and best knowne descent out of our Country, to wit the daughter of Henry the seventh, whose Grandfather Owen Theoder was of their Princely blood: For the second, as cleere as the Sunne, hee is by due originall lawfull King of Scotland: and for the third, it is knowne to those who have any experience

in antiquities, tha
                  •
                
               Margaret (from whom all the Kings of Scot
                     •
                  land have these fiv
                  •
                hundred yeeres issued) was the onely true in heritrice unto her great Vncle Edward the Confessour, and her Grandfather Edmund Ironside; and in one word to all the Saintly Saxon Kings of England, so as a lineall right hath from that time hitherto remained in Scotland, although William the conquering

               Norman did by the sword (as especiall descider of kingdomes) not onely obtaine the actuall possession of the Realme, but also ever since leave the same unto his posteritie. And yet moreover that none of the Norman race may in his Majesties enjoying of the Kingdome, finde themselves agrieved, God in his wisedome also disposeth (as to the whole realme it is most apparent) that he

likewise rightly deriveth his title from the off-spring of the Conquerour. Yea and that the Danish too (if any now remaine who were planted here by their puissant Lords) may have no cause to repine, behold the Queene his Majesties Wife and their Sonne our Prince, or exceeding hope, are come of the Danish, among whom that renowned Canatus was sometimes King of this Land, in

whom it is hard to determine whether, his devotion to God, his great conquests, or his generall clemeney deserved high
                  •
               st commendation: In all which is to be considered hovv God of his goodnesse hath in one man conjoyned these mighty houses, vvhich were not onely for descent and Country sometimes so diverse, but also in deadly hatred so far disagreeing, and in bloody wars so

violent and contentious, not unlike the frame of a perfect body, which is contrived of the foure contrary and repugnant elements; and also that those people which since the confusion of Babylon were ever severall, should as loving brethren be now united in his Majesties Kingdome, even as the Rivers which arising from contrary regions of North and South doe notwithstanding

fall into one maine Sea, and are made in the end one mighty water;How the Saxons and Britaines are united in this Realme. For as you shall perceive in this ensuing treatise, the Britaines and Saxons were not onely sundry Nations, but also in discord most dissenting: to number the battailes that were fought betweene them, were an endlesse labour, they confronted either others many hundred yeeres in continuall hatred, three Languages

were most different, their lawes &amp; customes divers; the Britaines distressed and dispossessed of their noble, fertile, and Native soyle, and driven by the power of their adversaries to live poorely in the barren mountaines of Cambria or Wales, the English invaders raigned and disposed freely of all the rest of the Land, untill it pleased the God of peace to make an end of all controversies.

The English in time having overcome them received the Britaine into the body of their Common-wealth and kingdome, they never excepted at the diversitie that had beene betweene their lawes and ours, they saw how in this very realme the Normanes had agreed before under one selfe-same rule and regiment with the Kentish Saxons, notwithstanding their legall customes were of another fashion:

For as by skilfull Musitians is made of sundry instruments one delightfull consort, and as by Lapidaries of diverse coloured stones, one most rich Iewell, and as of the Starres (which vary in severall motions) proceedeth the perfect harmony of the heavens: So of these sundry Countries, and customes of Britaines, Saxons, Danes, and Normans, is now framed one most excellent

Commonwealth: Neither yet was it objected that the Britaines having beene long starved with oppressing povertie, would greedily raven on the English riches and Possessions, for they were then neerer the time of Christ, and so more perfectly instructed with his Charity, who received the needy and sometimes prodigall child, to bee partaker with his wealthy elder brother, who rewarded

him that entred into his worke at the latter end of the day, with as large hire as the other, who laboured from the morning, who accepted into his favour as well the Gentiles as the Iewes. And what insued hereupon? hath any English-man beene hereby deprived of his profit? No surely; but although there have reigned 5 Kings and Queenes successively descended of the Britaine Nation, although

wee have had Generalls, Councellours, Iudges, and Magistrates of that Country, there was never as yet any Welchman (as we call him) boulstred out by their authority to afflict the English with any injuries. The cōmodities that flowed from this blessed union were many: first the charitie betweene both Nations, a thing most acceptable in the sight of God; the enlarging of the kingdome

with the addition of so worthy a people; the enriching of the same by making the marches and borders of the Country (which heretofore lay waste by reason of the warre) now subject to industrious husbandry: the incorporating of that Land as a limbe now of England, which was not onely sometimes a continuall adversary, but also ever ready to entertaine and assist any forraigne invasion:

the fortifying of the power of the realme with the forces of those vvho deteined them before vvith discord at home from augmenting their dominion abroad: the finishing of the unspeakeable charges of vvarre and expenses in maintaining garrisons on the fronteyres: the stincking of all spoyle and stuffe; and the ending of the effusion of Christian blood.
            
            And novv if it bee easier to imitate a former example, than bee the beginner of any action; vvhy then doe not the English and Scottish seeing this vvith farre more readinesse conjoyne in one? If discorde hath heretofore raigned betweene them, the like hath also raged betweene the Saxons and Britaines; if the Lawes of the one are diverse from us, the Lawes of the other have beene

as different, if the discommodities of warre with the Britaines have beene so great and grievous, no lesse have also beene those with the Scottish; if the commodities of peace betweene the Britaines and us, are so great and gracious, why should not the same be also in like sort betweene us and the Scottish? the English and Britaines were in language most unlike, the English and Scottish are of one

tongue; and if the names of persons and places doe not much deceive us, the Southerne people of Scotland are either descended of the Saxons, or at the least very much intermingled with the English blood, besides that, it is to be supposed that many of them are issued from the Britaines, since their confiners in Cumberland (which was a part sometimes of Scotland) have heretofore beene

               Cambro or Welch Britaines: For Nations by Neighbourhood passe one into another, even as wee perceive by neerenesse of property the purest of the water to become ayre, and the finest of the ayre to change into fire; the English might also have justly conceived a jealousie against the Britaines in admitting them into the communitie of the kingdome, least (as the Lawyers say) they should have accounted

themselves in their remitter, and upon this occasion have claimed their ancient possession of the Land whereof in fore passed ages they were (as they thought) wrongfully deprived; which can no way be objected against the realme of Scotland who (saving the most righteous title of our Soveraigne Lord to the Crowne) can make no lawfull challenge of her forefathers inheritance, but

commeth as a Princely Virgin with the royall portion of a Kingdome, to bee joyned in marriage with her husband England; the banes betweene England and Wales were bid with many a terrible battaile, and the match was made with blood shed; but the union of England and Scotland was begun in loving wedlocke, and established in lawfull descending issue; Since it hath therefore pleased

God to graft them both in one stocke, let no man seeke to rent them into two sundry trees, or rather breake them a sunder, since he hath formed them into one body, let none labour to dissever the members of the same; since hee hath created them into one little world, and encompassed it about with one mighty sea, and now after thousands of yeeres reduced into one entire regiment,

let none presume to cut in two that webbe which God hath weaued in one, or separate what hee hath joyned, or spurne against his providence.
            It is no new thing to see the greatnesse of Kingdomes encrease by the union of Countries;How other Kingdomes have increased by Vnions. for to omit the Assirians, Persians, and Macedonians, who not onely flourished in the former and more unknowne ages of the world, but also for the

situation of the regions are farre distant from us, and to consider a little of the Romanes and other more familiar and adjoyning Nations who have in latter dayes growne to the height of their renowne, did not those Iron legges of Daniels statue, the Cittie I meane that swayed over the universall world, gather her first arising strength, by receiving divers Territories (which shee subdued)

into the corporation of her commonwealth? did not the French by combining sundry Dukedomes and Earledomes together (of which some to our cost and losse we have good cause to remember) become the most ample and fruitfull Kingdome of all Christendome? was not Spaine within these few hundred yeeres distracted in severall pettie Dominions, the beames of whose glory

by intermariages conjoyning in one are growne, doe not onely shine through many parts of Europe, but also to the East and West Indians? The Dutchy of Burgundy the garden of Christendome, was not sometimes divided in the small principalities of Flanders, Henault, Holland, and the rest, all which are now by uniting of houses gathered into one Coronet of exceeding beauty? But let us

leave travailing abroad and returne home into our owne Country; were not the Saxons and English severed in seven smal kingdomes, and afterwards by conquest brought into one whole Monarchie? Were not the Britaines or Welch divided in three sundry regiments, and hath not the force of the English fornace melted all their crownes into one mighty streame of gold, and like the rod

of Moses devoured all the rods of the Magicians: and if we but enter into the histories either of our owne Iland or otherwise of these forraigne Nations, shal we not every where easily finde, that as by divided Kingdomes there came nothing but discord, poverty, and debasements, so from united powers groweth tranquility, plenty, and magnificence: we see the water of a great poole

conserveth it selfe, which if it were separated in small plashes would be quickely either dryed up with the sunne, or soked downe in the earth, and it is well noted by Saint Gregory, writing upon Saint Luke, that at the comming of our Saviour, the Commonwealth of Rome was in her perfection, because shee was conteined under the government of one Emperour, and how the

Kingdome of the Iewes ranne then to confusion, in regard it was distributed into sundry Seignories, grounding his reason on those words of Christ, with which I will end this point, Omne regnum in se divisum desolabitur, Every Kingdome divided in it selfe shall fall to desolation.
            Shew not therefore your selves (as the Poet saith) so farre removed from the Sunne (which is the authour of wisedome)

that ye should seeke with envie to hinder the raysing of that frame which God hath so charitably builded, but rather as the same Poet in the person of Dido uttereth, that a Trojan and Tirian, shall by her with equall affection bee respected, so let us all with one voyce, pronounce that English and Scottish shall by us now with love alike be entertained. Neither yet if the matter it selfe can

be concluded, let there bee any difference about the name of this Kingdome:How united nations have beene called by one generall name. for as it hath beene usuall to unite Nations, so hath it beene as common to call united Nations by one name; Although Greece had in times past beene divided into many Commonwealths and Principalities, yet being all subjected afterwards under the dominion of one, the former names vanished away,

and the whole was renowned by the name of the Empire of Greece, the like was of Italy, whose severall governments being gathered into one were all intituled by one name; the Aquitanes, Celtes, and Belgickes were in former ages comprised under the name of Galles, and having beene afterwards severed in sundry Provinces, are now almost all conjoyned in one entire famous

Kingdome, which after the name of the most puissant part thereof is termed France; our Ancestors not many yeeres since did familiarly know Castil, Arragon, and others, which are all now universally converted into one mighty name of Spaine; so were the West Saxons, Mercians, Norfolcians, Northumbers, and the rest of the Saxon Soveraignties, changed by our Monarch Egbert
               
into the potent and glorious name of England: and Scottland doth in like sort not onely comprehend the Scots but also the Hebrides and others;How conveniently the name of Britaine agreeth to the Kingdome of the whole Island. If therefore this hath beene so greatly practised, let us not refuse to follow so many worthy presidents, especially since it is not required at our hands that we should assume a newfound name, but the most ancient name of the whole Island,

the most famous name by which it hath beene knowne to all the mighty Emperours of Rome, and blazed throughout the world, the most learned name as the bookes of the Latines, and all other tongues and languages doe largely witnesse, and lastly the most generall name of all the inhabitants, for what are the English, Scottish, and Welch, but three parts of the whole large and most beautifull

Island of Britaine? And surely as it were absurd in familiar speech of London to tearme it after the names of the particular Wards or companies of the City, and not according to the entire Corporation, or to call any Shire of the Realme, after the Hundreds or divisions of the same, and not according to the well knowne title of the whole Country, so is it as farre against all

reason that our little world of Britaine being now included in one Kingdome, should be dis
                  •
               evered in names that would but ever rubbe up the remembrance of former injuries, and be Nurses of dissention, which his Majestie not unlike that ancient Romulus seeketh providently to abolish, and making a skilfull mixture of the English, Scottish, and Welch, laboureth now to severe them all into three distinct

orders, of the Nobility, Gentry, and Cominalty, of his entire Realme of great Britaine, vvhich being of three sundry people framed into one happy Soveraigntie, I beseech the Almighty Trinity, to bring to a most perfect Vnitie.
            Thus have I vvithThe Conclusion. more good vvill than good skill presumed upon the mention of these three people to leape rashly into the matter of the union,

vvherein although I may bee condemned for vvant of discretion, yet no man shall ever accuse mee for lacke of indifferencie.
         
      
      
         
            
            Here beginneth the Prologue of Gildas, surnamed the Wise, as touching the overthrow of Britaine, with his lamentation upon the same: being a sharpe reprehension of the Princes and people of the Land.
            
               WHatsoever I shall throughout this Epistle of mine, rather by way of lamentation than declamation prosecute with mine unworthy, but wellwishing pen; let no man suppose I declare

the same with any affectation of d
                  •
               spising others, or vainely esteeming my selfe better than all the rest, (being alasse the man, who with weeping complaints bewayleth the common losse of all goodnesse, and the increasing heape of mischiefes)▪ but rather communicating my sorrow on the discommodities and mis
                  •
               ries of my Country; and on the contraryside my comfort on the reformation of the same. Because it is not now my determination somuch to report the dangers of the bloody battailes of most valiant souldiers, as the perils of slothfull men. In silence have I (I con
                  •
               fesse) with exceeding greefe of my heart (as God the searcher of all secrets is my witnesse)

passed and overslipped full tenne yeeres space or more, mine unskilfullnesse, together with my vile basenesse ever (as at this instant) curbing me that I should not presume to write any so little an admonition. I did notwithstanding reade how the admirable Lawgiver for the misdoubting of one onely word never entred into the desired land.
                  Moses Num. 20.12.
                
               
                  Levit. 10.1.
               How the sonnes of the Priest for offering with other fire than was commanded, by a sudden death perished; how the people that broke the word of God, being 
                  Num. 14.28.
                six hundred thousands, yea, and they most deare to him, (
                  Exod. 14.22.
                as whose smoothest way, was the sands of the deepe red sea, whose meate 
                  Exod. 16.14.
                the heavenly bread,

whose 
                  Exod. 17.6.
                drinke, the new water passing out of the Rocke, 
                  Exod. 17.11.
                whose invincible army, but onely the stretching up of hand
                  •
               ,) all these (two upright men excepted) to have dyed through 
                  Num. 21.6.
                serpents, 
                  Num. 14.45.
                sword, and 
                  Deut. 1.45.
                fire, here and there along the desarts of Arabia; yea, after the entrance of the unknowne 
                  Num. 11.1.
                gate (as it were) of Iordan, and their 
                  Iosu. 3.16.
                adverse Cities wals, by the onely sound of trumpets through the commandement of God ouerthrowne,
                  Ios. 6.20.
                one silly cloake,
                  Ios. 21.24
                and a little gold presumptuously taken of the accursed spoile, to have beene the slaughter of many men; how the breaking of the league made with the 
                  2 Sam. 21.1.
                
               Gibionites (yea though the same were through subtilty

extorted) was also to some their destruction. I have read the complaining cryes of the holy Prophets poured out for the sinnes of men, and especially those of Ieremie, with his fourefold Ieremies foure Lamentations written with the order of the Hebrew Alphabet.
                Alphabet, lamenting the ruine of his Citie. I saw moreover in this our time (as he in former bewailed) 
                  Thren. 1.1.
                
               The widow City now sit alone, sometimes replenished with people. The Lady of nations, the Prince of Provinces, (to wit the Church) to be made tributary; 
               
                  Thren. 4.1.
                
               The gold obscured the most excellent colour (which is the beauty of the word of God) changed.
               
                  Thren. 4.2.
                
               The sonnes of Sion, (that is of our holy mother the Church) sometimes famous and clothed

in the purest gold, to have embraced dung; And that which to him as a principall man to me also (though an abject yet howsoever) encreased this mountaine of sorrow, whilest beforehand hee lamented them, living as yet so famous in their flowing prosperity that he said, 
                  Thren. 4.7.
                
               Her Nazarens were whiter than snow, redder than the ancient Ivory, fairer than the Saphire. Beholding in the old Testament, these and many others as certaine looking glasses of our life, I turned me also to the new, and there the shadow now ceasing, and the light more clearely shining, more plainely did I reade, what before perchance was obscure unto me; I did reade (I

say) that our Lord hath said, 
                  Math. 15.24.
                
               I came not but to the lost sheepe of the house o
                     •
                   Israel; and yet on the other side, 
                  Mat. 8.12.
                
               But the children of this kingdome shall bee cast into outward darknesse, there shall bee weeping and gnashing of teeth. And againe, 
                  Mat. 15.26.
                
               It is not good to take the bread of the children, and cast it unto dogs. And also, 
                  Mat. 23.13.
                
               Woe be unto you Scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites. I heard, 
                  Mat. 8.11.
                
               Many shall come from the East and the West, and sit with Abraham, Isaac, and Iacob, in the kingdome of heauen: And on the contrary part, 
                  Mat. 7.23.
                
               And then shal I say unto them, Depart from me yee workers of iniquity. I have read, 
                  Luc. 23.29.
                
               Blessed

are the barren, and the teats that have not given sucke; And in contrary position, 
                  Mat. 25.10.
                
               They who were ready entred with him to the mariage, afterwards came also the other Virgins, saying, Lord, Lord, open unto us, to whom it was answered; I know yee not. I did truely heare, 
                  Mat. 16.16.
                
               Who so shall beleeve, and be baptised, shall be saved, but who shall not beleeve, shall bee damned. I did reade from the penne of the Apostle,
                  Rom. 11.17.
                that the branch of the wilde Olive was graffed on the good Olive, but notwithstanding should be cut off from the community of the roote of his fruitfull fatnesse, if hee carry not himselfe in feare, but rashly entred into

high secrets. I knew the mercy of our Lord, but dreaded his judgements. I praised his grace, but trembled, that every man shall receive according to his workes. Seeing the sheep of one folde, unlike in fashion, worthily I commended the most blessed Peter for his full confession of Christ, and condemned most miserable Iudas for his thirsting covetousnes. I praysed Stephen for his glorious crowne of martyrdome, but reproved Nicholas as miserable in respect of the shamefull marke of his uncleane heresie. I did assuredly reade, 
                  Act. 4.32.
                
               They had all things in common: but likewise, 
                  Act. 5.9.
                
               Why have yee conspired to tempt the spirit of God. I did on the other side behold

to how great a security men of our age were growne, as if there rested no cause at all of feare. Wherefore considering with some, whatsoever compunction of heart, full often in my amazed minde these things, and very many other, which because of briefenesse I have determined to omit. If (quoth I) our Lord hath not spared his people so peculiarly chosen out of all Nations, his royall race, and his solely Country, (to whom hee said, 
                  Exod. 4.22.
                
               My first begotten Israel,) If not her Priests, Prophets, Kings, throughout the revolution of so many Ages, if not his servant and Apostle, and members of his primitive Church, when they wandred from the right way: what will

he then doe against such deformity of this of our present time, on the which, besides the unspeakable and monstrous sinnes that it hath in common with all the wicked of the world, have also fallen, that naturall quality (as it were) and irrecoverable and inevitable burden of folly and inconstrncy? What? (I speake to my selfe) hast thou (oh wretch) so great a care cast upon thee (as though thou wert some eminent and most high Doctor) that thou shouldest withstand the b
                  •
               llowes of so violent a streame, and keepe the charge committed into thy hands, against this race of invetrate vices, which throughout the space of so many yeeres, have without interruption

beene spread and continued? Hold therefore thy peace, for otherwise thou wilt bid the foote see, and the hand speake. Behold and plainely confesse. Britaine hath rulers, she hath watchmen. Why dost thou goe about thus trifling to mutter? Shee hath (I say) shee hath if not more, not lesse then a just number, but because overpressed with so great a weight they bend under their burthens, they have not left them a time of breathing, My sences therefore as debtors joyned in one obligation with these and such like objections yea rather more biting mutually forebusted themselues, they (as I have said) no small time (having read there is a time of speaking, and a time of holding

ones peace) as it were in a cumbersome narrow passage of feare,Eccles. 3.7.
                with wrastling strived, the Creditor notwithstanding at the last prevailed and gained the victory, saying, If thou art not of that audacity that (among the prosetical creatures, who in regard of the gift of reason, have the next roome to the Angelicall messengers) thou dost not feare to bee marked with the comely note of golden liberty, refuse not yet at least the affection of the understanding Asse,
                  The history of Baalam and his Asse.
                to that d
                  •
               y dumbe, but then inspired with the Spirit of God, denying to carry the mitred Magician who went to accurse the people of God,Num. 22.23.
                and dashing in the streights of the vineyards his loosned foote, albeit shee

therefore did feele his most cruell blowes, to whom although unthankfull and furiously 
                  •
               in the meane time beating against all right and reason her innocent sides, she did as it were with a finger shew the heavenly Angell threatning with a naked sword, and crossing his course, whom he blinded with dull folly, did not behold. Wherefore in the zeale of the house of our Lord and of his holy law, be it that I am constrained either by the accounts of mine owne con
               
                  ••
               its, or the religious prayers of my brethren, I doe now satisfie the debt long challenged at my hands, worthlesse truely, yet faithfull (as I suppose) and friendly to all renouned Souldiers of Christs band, but grievous

and in supportable to foolish Apostataes; of whom the first, (unlesse I am deceived) will with teares perchance that flow from the charity of God, receive the same, and the last with sorrow, but such as is outwrested from the indignation and pusillanimity of an attainted conscience. But before the performance of my promise, I will (God willing) in few words endeavor to discourse, 1. Of our Countries situation. 2. Of her disobedience. 3. Subjection. 4. And rebellion. 5. Of her second subjection, and dreadfull slavery. 6. Of her Religion. 7. Persecution. 8. Holy Martyrs. 9. And divers heresies. 10. Of her Tyrants. 11. Of two her wastfull adverse

Nations. 12. Of her defence. 13. And also of her spoile. 14. Of the second revenge taken on her enemies. 15. then of her third confusion. 16. Of her famine. 17. Of the Letters writen to Agitius. 18. Of her victory. 19. Of her villanies. 20. Of the suddaine rumour of her approaching enemies. 21. Of the faminous plague. 22. Of her Counsell. 23. Of a foe farre more cruell then the first. 24. Of the overthrow of the Cities. 25. Of the remnants of our Countrimen. 26. And of the last victory obtained by our Nation▪ which was through the goodnesse of God bestowed on us in our time.
         
         
            
            THE EPISTLE of GILDAS:
            
               THE Iland ofOf the situation of the Iland. 
               Britaine placed in the ballance of the divine poising hand (as they call it) which weigheth the whole world, almost the uttermost bound of this earth towards the South and West; extending it selfe from the South West,
               
out towards the North Pole, eight hundred miles in length, and containing two hundred in bredth, besides the farre outstretched Forelands of sundry Promontaries, embraced by the embowed bosomes of the Ocean Sea; with whose most spacious, and on every side (saving only the Southerne streights, by which we saile to Gallebelgicke) unpassable enclosure (as I may call it) shee is strongly defended; enriched with the mouths of 2. noble Floods, Thames and Severne, as it were two armes (by which outlandish commodities have in times past beene transported into the same) besides other Rivers of lesser account,

strengthned with eight and twenty Cities, and some other Castles, not meanely fenced with Fortresses of Wals, embattelled Towers, Gates, &amp; buildings (whose roofes being raised aloft with threatning hugenesse, were mightily in their aspiring toppes compacted) adorned with her large spreading fields, pleasant seated hils, even framed for good husbandry, which overmastereth the ground, and mountaines most convenient for the changeable Pastures of cattell, (whose flowers of sundry collours, troden by the feete of men, imprint no unseemely picture on the same) as a spouse of choice, decked

with divers jewels; watered with cleere Fountaines, and sundry Brookes, beating on the snow white sands together with silver streames sliding forth with soft sounding noise, and leaving a pledge of sweet savours on their bordering bankes, and lakes gushing out abundantly in cold running Rivers.
            
               Of her disobedience.Secondly, this Land with a stiffe proud necke, and stubborne minde from the time since shee was first inhabited, hath ungratefully rebelled sometimes against God, other whiles against her owne Countrymen, and at other seasons also against outlandish Kings and their Subjects. For what matter of fowler

deformity, or what greater injustice can in the attempts of men, either be, or ever be committed, then to deny God of that awful feare, honest Countrymen of that charity, and those who are placed in higher authority (without impeachment of faith) of that honour due unto them, to breake alleageance to divine and humane reason, and casting away all dread of Heaven and Earth, to be ruled by their owne inventions and sensualities? Omitting therfore those ancient errours common to all nations of the earth, with the which before the comming of Christ in our flesh, all mankinde was entangled and

bound, nor yet recounting up the monstrous Idols of our Country, surpassing almost in number the very devilish devises themselves of Egypt, (of the which we behold as yet some, both within and without the wals of their forsaken Temples, with deformed portratures, and terrible countenances after the accustomed manner, now mouldring away) neither yet crying out, namely one after another on the mountaines themselves, or hils, or floods, damnable sometimes, as to the which divine honour, by the people then blinded was yeelded, though now truely profitable to the use of mankinde: and letting

passe in silence those old outworne ages of our detestable Tyrants, who in other far remooved regions were infamous (in so much as Porphyrie that outragious easterling dogge, who barked against the Church, hath in the stile of his madnesse and vanity also added this; That Britaine is a fruitfull Province of Tyrants.) I will onely endeavour to set forth to the world those miseries, which in the time of the Romane Emperours she suffered, and likewise heaped on the heads of others, as well her Countrymen, as Strangers, and not farther neverthelesse then I am well able to declare, neither yet so much out of the

Chronicles of our Country, or the monuments of our owne Authors (for why these truely if any such there have beene, are either now devoured with the fires of our foes, or being transported into forraigne Nations by the meanes of our banished Countrymen, are quite vanished away) as by the relation of outlandish writers which broken off with many interruptions doth not sufficiently appeare.
            
               Of the subjection of the Iland.Thirdly, for when the Rulers of Rome, had obtained the Empire of the world, and now having brought under their governement, all their next neighbours, Nations and Ilands)

had towards the East confirmed with the power of their encreasing renown, the first peace of the Par
                     •
                  hians who confine on the Indians) which being finished warres thenceased through out almost the whole earth, the fury in a sort of this flame towards the West, could no
                  •
                with the blewish billows of the cold Ocean Seas be suppressed or extinguished; but passing over without resistance drew our Iland to the lawes of obedience, and subdued absolutely to their command, the weake but unstable people not like other nations so much with sword, fire, and warlike engines, as with threats, or amazing their mindes with

the superficious frownes of their countenances, so deeply were their hearts inwardly dismayed.
            
               Of her Rebellion▪
               Fourthly, after whose returne unto Rome, which for want of pay (as they said) was present suspecting nothing lesse then rebellion, the subtil Queene Voadit
                        ••
                     
                   slew with the power of her Countrymen the Britanes threescore and ten or fourescore thousand Romanes.
                
               Lioness murthred the Rulers, who were left behinde of purpose more fully to show; or rather to confirme the enterprises of the Romane Empire. Which being so done, when the report thereof was declared unto the Senate, and they with a speedy army made all haste to be revenged on the crafty foxes cubbs (as they called them) there appeared no warlike

Navy on the Seas prepared valiantly to encounter for our Country, nor yet a square mustered army, neither the right wing of the battaile, nor other order of fight to withstand on the shore but backes in place of sheilds were turned to the pursuing foes, neckes subjected to the conquering swords, cold feare invading all their limbs, and supplyant hands stretched out▪ wom
                  •
               n-like▪ to be bound; so that it was bruted farre and neere, as a proverbe and scornefull reproach, that Britaine were Neither forward in warre, nor stable in peace. neither valiant in warre, nor faithfull in peace.
            Fifthly;Of the second subjection of the Nation. many therefore of the rebellious being

slaine, and some of the inthralled for baser workes (least the Land should be wholly brought to desolation) left alive, they sailed from our Country (void of wine and oyle) towards Italy, leaving behinde them some of their Governors, as scourges over our Countrymens shoulders, &amp; yokes on their neckes, who should engrave, as it were, on the very ground the name of their subjection to Rome, and chastice not so much with warlike weapons, as with reprochfull punishments the subtill people, and if occasion so required, should fashion them (as they say) to weare their naked swords by their sides, so

that now it was not reputed as Britania but Romania, and what soever Brasse, Silver, and Gold it could possesse, was stamped with the Image of Caesar.
            
            Sixthly,Of her Rebellion. in the meane while, Christ the true Son of God, spreading forth not onely from this temporall firmament, but also from the Castell and Court of Heaven, (which exceedeth all times) throughout the whole world, his most glorious light, especially (as we know) in the Raigne of Tiberius Caesar, (whereas in regard that the Emperour) against the will of the Senate threatned death to the disturbers of the professors thereof, Religion was most

largely without any hinderance dispersed of his infinite mercy, did first cast on this Iland, starving with frozen cold, and in a farre remote climate from the visible Sunne, his gladsome beames, to wit, his most holy Lawes.
            
               Of the PersecutionSeaventhly, which although they were received of the inhabitans, but with lukewarme mindes, remained notwithstanding fully in the soules of some, and in others lesse, untill the nine yeares persecution of the Tyrant Dioclesian, in which the Churches throughout the whole world were overthrowne to the ground, all holy Scriptures (that could be found) burned in

the streetes, the chosen Priests of the flocke of our Lord, together with the innocent Sheepe murthered, to the end that not the least remembrance, truely of Christian Religion (if possibly it might be) should in any place of the Provinces be left. How foule the flights were then, how great the slaughters, what torments of sundry deaths, what ruines of Apostataes, what shining Crownes of glorious Martyrs, what furious madnesse of the persecutors, and on the contrary, what singular patience of the Saints of God, the Ecclesiasticall History declareth: so as the whole Church, in mighty thronging

troopes (leaving behind them all worldly darkenes) hastened with speede to the pleasant Pallaces of Heaven as to their proper seats.
            
               Of the holy Martyrs of Britaine.
               Eightly, God therefore whose will is, that all men should be saved, and who calleth no lesse sinners then such as repute themselves just, magnified his mercy with us, who as wee conjecture of his gracious aforenamed goodnesse, that Britaine should not be altogether overwhelmed with the black cloud of this dark some night, lightned unto us in this time of persecution the most cleare lamps of his Holy Martyrs, the tombes of whose bodies

and places of passion (were wee not for our most manifold offences through the lamentable interruption of the barbarous, deprived of them) would even now inkindle in the mindes of the beholders no small fire of the divine charity. I meane S. Alban.
                St. Alban of Verolamium and Aaron, and Iulius of 
                  Carlile upon Vske in Monmouthshire.
                
               Carlile with others of both Sexes persisting in many places with most singular magnanimity in the battle of Christ. Of whom the first, after he had for charities sake, concealed a Confessor, pursued by the persecutors, and even now ready to be taken, by hiding him in his house, and then by changing garments with

him, and lastly, in the apparell of his fore-recited brother, had willingly offered himselfe to the ensuing danger (imitating also in this Christ, who gave his blood for his Sheepe) so pleasing was he found in the sight of God, and betweene his sacred confession and Martyrdome so exceedingly glorified with miracles even in the very eies of the wicked, who with fantasticall outrage presented the ensignes of the authority of Rome, as entring in the fervour of his Prayers, together with a thousand others dry sooted, the Channell of the noble River of Thames, he made a passage through the waters that hung in the meane

time as broken mountaines on the one side, &amp; the other. 
                  Iosh 3.17 not unlike to that dryed &amp; unworne way of the Israelites when the Arke of the Testament remained long on the sands in the midst of the River of Iordan, and by the sight of so miraculous a matter, he changed his first designed executioner, from a Wolfe to a Lambe. Yea &amp; made him together with himselfe most earnestly to thirst, and constantly to atchieve the triumphant victory of Martyrdome. Others also were with such sundry torments tortured, and with such unspeakeable tearing of their limbes rent in peeces, as without delay the glorious conquerours

fixed the tropheys of their Martyrdome, in the famous gates (as it were) of Ierusalem. For they who remained alive, did hide themselves in woods, in desarts and in secretdens, expecting when God the rightfull ruler of all things would pronounce upon their tormentors his severe judgements, and grant themselves the safety of their lives. Tenne yeares therefore of the above named tempestuous hurlewinde being not yet fully ended, and these wicked decrees by the deaths of their blooddy beginners now withering away, al the Souldiers of Christ with joyfull eyes, doe after this long Winters night, behold

the milde season and faire light as it were of the Heavenly sky. They reedifie their Churches battered downe to the ground, they found, builde, and finish the Temples of holy Martyrs, and display farre and neere in a sort their conquering banners, they celebrate holy dayes, and sacrifice with pure hearts and mouthes, yea all the children of the Church being now most lovingly embraced and tenderly nourished in the bosome (as you may call it) of their mother doe exceedingly rejoyce.Of the divers heresies.
            
            Ninthly, for this sweete consort of the members of Christ their head remain
                  •
               d inviolable, untill the Arrian
               
treason like an horrible serpent, vomitting out upon us his outlandish poysons, brought to mortall discord brethren who dwelt in one, and so all cruell beasts together, making as it were a passage over the Ocean Sea, and spitting the damnable venome of every heresie from their abhominable mouthes, fastened their deadly wounding teeth on our Country, which is ever desirous to heare novelty, and never truely continueth in any certainety.
            
               Of the Tyrants.Tenthly, moreover also at the length, new springs of Tyrants encreasing, and even now growing up into a very wildernesse of wickednesse, our Iland which

bore as yet the Romane name, but farre degenerated from the manners and lawes of the same, yea rather which did cast away the first roote of her most bitter planting, furnished out unto the Galles 
               The Tyranny of Maximus.
                
               Maximus (not lawfully invested, but Tyrannically usurping, and advanced by mutinous souldiers) with mighty bands of men to guard him, and ensignes of the Emperiall Majesty, (which never yet did any way become him) who rather first which crafty subtilty then any valour, tying and combining together all neere adjoyning Shires and Provinces against the estate of Rom
                     •
                  , as the nettles of

his perjury and falshood for the atchieving of his wicked government, stretching out one of his wings to Spaine and the other to Italy, and seating at Trire the Throne of his most unjust Empire, rebelled against his Lords with so great outrage, as he expelled two most lawfull Emperors, the one out of Rome, the other out of his most Religious life; and without delay encouraged with such fatall attempts, lost at the City of Aquilege his accursed head, who before in a sort had throwne to the dust the Crowned heads of the whole worlds Kingdome.Of two wastfull Nations.
            
            XI. After this Britaine
               
being now dispoyled of all armed Souldiers, of warlike companies, of (though outragious yet) Rulers, and of her brave and valorous youth, (who marching along with the afore recited Tyrant, never returned to their home againe) and now absolutely ignorant of all practise of warre, was astonished, and lamentably groaned, as trampled many yeares under the feete of especially two very fierce outlandish Nations, the Scots from the South, and the Pyctes from the North.
            
            XII. Vpon whose invasions,Of the defence of the Iland. and most terrible oppressions, she sent Ambassadors furnished with Letters to Rome, humbly beseeching

with pittious prayers an hoast of Souldiers to redresse her wrongs, and vowing with the whole power of her minde her everlasting subjection to the Romane Empyre, so as these her foes might be once chased further away. In whose behalfe (all forepassed injuries being cleane forgotten) a Legion strongly provided for the warre, was forthwith mustered: which being Shipped and so transported over the Ocean into our Country, and incountring hand to hand, with our grievous foes, and slaying an huge number of them, drave them all out of the British bounds, and with so blooddy a fight delivered

their friends and subjects from that imminent thraldome. Whom they commanded to builde acrosse over the Iland, from Sea to Sea a wall, which being manned with garrisons of Souldiers, might be a terror to suppresse the enemy, and a safe-guard to defend their friends. But this being without any director made by the people, and unreasonable rout, not so much of stone, as of turfe, prooved to little purpose.
            XIII.Of the other spoile of the Country. The army was no sooner with great triumph &amp; rejoycing returned home but their accustomed foes not unlike devouring Wolves, that ravening with extreame hunger, and greedy

jawes, leape over the fold, in the Shepheards absence, being furthered and furnished with the wings of Oares, and the strength of Rowers, and Sailes filled with too prosperous winds, breake downe all bounds, commit all murthers, and as men who reape the now ripe corne, so tread they under foote, and overrunne them all.
            
               Of the second revenge taken of the enemy.XIV. And now againe they send supplyant complayning Embassadors with rented garments (as they say) and heads overspread with ashes, humbly beseeching assistance from the state of Rome, &amp; shrowding themselves like fearefull chickens under the most

trusty wings of their Parents, that their miserable country might not be altogether made desolate, nor yet the Romane name (which now was onely left with idle sound of words to fill the empty eare) basely vanish away, as consumed with the reproachfull despights of forraigne Nations, whereupon the Romanes being mooved (as much as mans nature possibly might be) with the declaration of this so lamentable a tragedy, advancing forward (as Eagles in their flight) withall speede their troopes of Horse by Land, and Marriners mustred on the Sea, doe sease on the shoulders of their foes, first

with the unexpected, and then the terrible tallons of their swords, and slaughtering, overthrow them as thicke as leaves, that withered Autumn hurleth down. And as the streame that powreth out from the Mountaines, and encreaseth with sundry brookes, that rise of tempestuous raines, which in her roaring fall, surmounteth now all channels, and outragiously fometh with her furrowed backe and vehement boyling fountaine, and leaping (as they say) to the very clouds with her dashing waters (through whose divers circuling wheeles the appels of our eyes, though often refreshed with our

twinckling eie-lids are notwithstanding dazled) even with one billow, beareth downe all resisting powers, so our rightworthy assisting friends most speedily chased the troopes of our foes (if any could so escape their hands) beyond the Seas, because beyond the same Seas, they did yeare by yeare in great abundance greedily transport their praises, no man daring withstand them. The Romanes therefore declaring unto our Country, that they could not endure to be so often troubled with such tedious journeyes, nor yet to weary out the Ensignes of Rome, together with such and so great an army, both

by land and Sea, on these wandring wasters; and perswading them rather by exercise of warfare, and couragious fighting, with their whole powers of themselves to defend their lands, goods, wives, children, and (which are dearer then all these) their liberties and lives, and not in any case to yeeld unto Nations no way more valiant then themselves (if by sloath and idle cowardlinesse they were not weakened) their disarmed hands to be manacled in bands, but rather to shew them the same hands armed with Targets, Swords, and Speares, and manfully prepared to make slaughter of their foes, doe

together with the poore miserable inhabitants by the common charge of all and private helps of many, (because they supposed it would be some advantage to the people, now left to themselves) build a wall as the first, though not weake as the first, by levell, directly from Sea to Sea, along the Cities, which for dread of their 
                  •
               oes, were there by chance situate, give manfull admonitions to the feareful people, leave them the art to make armour, and teach them the order of warfare. And moreover on the Southerne shore of the Ocean, where their Shippes lay in Harbour (because the landing of the barbarous savage

sort, was there most to be feared) they doe in divers and distant convenient places erect watchtowers, to ken over the Seas, and now as never to returne againe, give them their last farewell.
            
               Of the third wastfull spoile of the Land.XV. They were notwithstanding no sooner gone home, but as the brownish bands of wormes and eamots, which in the hieghth of Sommer, and encreasing heate, doe swarming breake out of their most straight and darkesome dens, the dreadfull routes of Scots and Pictes, partly dissenting in manners, but consenting in one and the selfe same greedy thirst of shedding blood,

and shadowing rather their terrible faces, with shagging glibes, then hiding the secrets and shame of their bodies with comely garments, doe runne in throngs and mustring troopes, a land out of their Ships, wherein they were transported over their Scithian vale,
               The Sea betweene England and Ireland called Scyth
                        •
                     ca vallis.
                and being assuredly informed, as touching the departure of our assisting friends, and their absolute denyall of ever returning againe, even now more boldly then at any time before they invade, and bereave the inhabitants of all the Northerne and uttermost bounds of the land, to the very wall it selfe. For the withstanding of whose forces was

placed on the fortresse a sloathfull garrison, backeward to fight, unfit to encounter, an unprofitable dismayed company, which day and night in amazement wasted away; in the meane while ceaseth not the hooked weapons of the naked enemies, with the which our miserable Countrymen were pulled from the wal, and dashed downe to the ground. And yet truely they who lost their lives in this slaughter, reaped through the torment of their untimely death, this commodity, that by their suddaine ends they eschewed the sight of those lamentable and imminent plagues and punishments which fell

upon their brethren and deere children. What need many words? They left the Cities, they left the high wall, againe they flye, and are againe dispersed in farre more desperate sort then before; and now the enemy pursueth afresh, and afresh he hastneth, and heapeth slaughters on slaughters, more cruelly then ever, and as Lambs by butchers, so our pittifull Countrymen are by their foes hewed in peeces, insomuch as their habitation was like a wildernesse of salvage beasts.
            XVI. For even theyOf the famine. themselves did not withhold their hands from ravening on their owne miserable

Countrymen, yea for a little sustenance of a small deale of food, and so overthrowes from the enemy were enereased with civill sedition, and the reason was because through these such sundry wastefull spoyles, the whole Country was utterly disfurnished of all manner of provision of victuals, that onely excepted which they gat by hunting.
            
               Of the Letters to Aeitius.
               XVII. Wherefore againe the ruthfull remnants of us direct unto Agitius (a man of power, in the state of Rome) their Letters indited to this purpose. The lamentation of the Britanes unto Agitius thrice Consul, and a little after in

this sort complaining. The Barbarous beate us to the Seas, the Seas drive us back on the Barbarous, between these two dreadfull kindes of death, we are either slain or drowned; but neverthelesse they obtaine no manner of aide. In the meane while a cruell and most notorious famine oppressed the strugling and discomforted people, which enforced many of them without delay, for the gayning but of a little meate to refresh their lives, to yeeld▪ their neckes to the yokes of their terrible spoyling foes, although others would never be constrayned thereunto, but rather from of the mountaines and from out

the dens and defert wooddy forests made continuall resistance.
            
               Of the victory obtained by the Britaines.
               XVIII. And then first of all they overthrew their foes, who now for many yeares had wasted their Country, yet not trusting in the strength of man, but in the power of God, according to that of Philo. It is necessary to have divine assistanc
                     •
                  , when humane forces faile. A while ceased the attempts of our enemies, but yet not ceased the wickednesse of our Countrymen, our foes left our people, but our people left not their iniquities.
            
               Of their offences.XIX. For it hath beene still a custome with our Country (as still al
                  •
               s it remaineth)

that she hath been weake to represse the power of their enemies, but strong to raise civil broiles, and beare the burthens of offences; feeble (I say) to execute the lawes of peace and truth, but able enough to sin, falsifie, and deceive. The impudent Irish wasters departed home, as they who not long after determined to returne againe, and then first the Pictes seated themselves (where afterwards they continued) in the furthest part of the Iland, breaking every while forth in spoyling and defacing our Country. Wherefore in such truces as these, the cruell sore of famine (which the desolate people

sustained) was now cleare healed, another farre more poysonous secretly arising. For no sooner did the enemy desist from spoyling the Country, but the Iland abounded with so great plenty of all things, as no forepassed age could ever remember the like, wherewith all kind of licenciousnesse in like sort encreased. Yea truely it increased with a mighty off-spring; so that very aptly to the same time might be applyed the saying which is; To be short, such fornication is heard of,
               1 Cor. 3.1. 
               as among the Gentiles there is not the like. Neither yet this vice alone, but all others that to humane frailty doe accustomably befall,

and chiefly (that which now also overthroweth in her the whole estate of goodnesse) hatred of truth with her maintainers, and the love of falshood with the framers thereof, the acceptance of sin for sanctity, the worshipping of wickednesse for benignity, the desire of darkenesse for the Sunneshining, the embracing of Sathan for an Angell of light. Kings were annointed, not as God appointed, but such as in cruelty excelled others; and within a while after were they by their Electours without due examination of their deserts murthered, other more blooddy Tyrants being in their places

advanced, if any one of them were of a milder disposition, or seemed to draw any whit nearer to the truth, on him as the subverter of Britaine were all mens hatred and vengeance with out respect throwne, and at an equall rate was valued all that displeased and pleased God, if that which displeased bore not the higher price. So as rightly to our Country might be spoken those words of the Prophet, which to that people of old were denounced. 
                  Esai. 1.5. 
               Children without a law, have ye left God and provoked to anger the holy One of Israel, to what end shall ye be as yet strooken, adding iniquity? every head is languishing, and

every heart is grieving, from the sole of the foote even to the very crowne of the head, there is no soundnesse in him. And so they managed all matters, that were contrary to their salvation, as if the true Physition of all things could Minister no medicine to the enfeebled wound: And thus dealt not only the Lay people, but the very flocke of our Lord, and the Pastors thereof, who ought to give all the Commons good example; very many as it were washed in wine did carelessely waste themselves in drunkennesse, and were moreover attainted with the swelling of pride, the contention of anger, the griping talo
                  •
                of envy, and

the indifferent estimation of good and evill; so that apparently (as now also it fareth) there seemed to be powred out 
                  Psa. 106 
               Contempt on the Princes, who caused them to wander astray, and not in the way.
            
            
               Of the suddaine newes of the enemy.XX. God in the meane while being willing to cleanse his family, and with the onely report of tribulation to amend them who were infected with so great a pestilence of mischiefes; the winged flight of no uncertaine fame, peirced the listning eares of all men, concerning the instant approach of their inveterate enemies, even now resolved to make a spoile of all, and to possesse after their

accustomed manner, the whole Country from the one end to the other. Yet did our Countrymen neverthelesse reape small commodi
                  •
               y hereby, but like to bransicke beasts, most wilfully taking (as they say) in the teeth the bit of reason, they left the safe, though straight way, and ranne mainely to the open passage of sundry vices, that leade headlong to deadly destruction.
            XXI. While therefore (as Salomon saith) The stubborne Servant is not with words amended,Of the faminous Plague. the foole is scourged and feeleth it not. For a pestilent sicknesse did mortally infect the unwise people, which (without any

stroake of the sword) did in short time devoure so great a multitude of them, as the living were unneathable to bury; but neither with this were their sinnes corrected, that the same of Esay the Prophet might be also in them fulfilled, saying▪ 
               And God hath called to Lamentation,
               
                  Isai. 22.12. 
               to baldnesse, and to the girdle of sackecloth, and behold they rejoyce to kill calves, and to slaughter Rams, to eate and drinke, and to say, Let us eate, and let us drinke, for to morrow wee shall dye. For why the houre drew on a pace, wherein all their iniquities as those sometimes of the Amorrheians should be fully accomplished.
            
            XXII. For a CounsellOf the Counsell. was called to determine what were the best or safest way to repulse and represse such deadly and often invasions and spoylings made by the aforesaid Nations.
            XXIII. When all the Counsell,Of an enemy far more cruell then the first. together with the proud Tyrant, were blinded in finding out this defence, nay, offence, and utter destruction of our Country, that those most fierce and detestable people named the Saxons, a Nation odious both to God and man, should be sent for into the Iland (as wolves into a fold of Sheepe) to beate down the Northerne powers; then which nothing

ever befell to this our Country more pernicious and miserable. O most palpable darkenesse of their sences! O desperate and blockish dulnesse of their mindes! whom they dreaded in their absence, more then death it selfe, were now freely and willingly invited to inhabit with them under the roofe (as I may call it) of one selfe same house, by the foolish Princes (as it is said) of Taneos giving undiscreete Counsell to their King Pharaoh. And then an huge litter of whelpes ramping out of the denne of the barb
                  •
               
               rous 
                  Saxony.
                
               Lionesse, in three Ciuls (according to their tongue, but (after ours) in

three long Shippes or Gallies, with prosperous sailes, fortunes and prophesies, through which by a certain Southsayer among them was foretold, that they should three hundred yeare possesse the Country wherunto they directed their course, and spend an hundred and fifty of the same (to wit) the one halfe in often spoyling of the Realme, and landing first in the Easterne part of the Iland, fixed there, by the unhappy Tyrants commandement, their cruell clawes, as it were to fight for our Country, but more truely to overthrow the same. After whom the aforesaid 
                  Saxony.
                Dam, (finding her first beginnings

had so good successe) sendeth also forth a new and greater supply of her ravening race, which being shipped over, joyne themselves with the former bastardly bands. Hereupon the bud of iniquity, the roote of bitternesse, and the plant of poyson, answerable truely to our demirits sprung out from this our native soyle in fierce armes and branches. The Barbarous therefore being invited and admitted into our Iland, demaund and obtain allowance of victuals to be granted them as Souldiers and such as would undertake mighty dangers (as they pretended) for their good hosts, and entertainers

which being a long time largely bestowed. stopped (as they say) the dogges mouth. Yet afterwards notwithstanding they cavill that they had not sufficient victuals and habitations appointed them, forging thereupon, quarrels of set purpose, and if they found not greater abundance of bounty, they protest they would breake the league, and sacke the whole Iland, and without delay they make good their threats with following effects.
            XXIIII. For the fire of just revenge,Of the overthrow of the Cities. being in regard of our former offences now inkindled, was increased and continued from

sea to sea, as fed by the hand of the sacrilegious Easterlings, which spoyling and consuming al neere adjoyning Cities and Countries, when it was once inflamed, ceased not till burning almost the whole Westerne face of the Iland, it dipped histerrible red scorching tongue into the Ocean Sea. Wherefore in these assaults, not unlike those which the Assyrians sometimes attempted against Iudah, the same was also Historically performed in us, which the Prophet lamenting said; 
                  Psal. 73.7 
               They have burned with fire thy Sanctuary, they have pollat d in earth, the Tabernacle of thy name. And againe, 
                  Psal. 78.1 
               O God the

Gentiles have come into thine inheritance, they have defiled thy holy Temple. In so much as all the townes with the often beatings of the Rammes, and all the Townes-men, Pastours, Priests, and People, with naked swords that glittred on all sides, and crackling flames were together whirled to the ground; lamentable and dreadfull to behold, there lay the toppes of lofty Towres now tumbled downe, the stones of high wals, the holy Altars, and rented peeces of carcaces covered with distilling &amp; congealed purple blood, confusedly in the midst of the streetes heaped in one, as if they were to be crushed

together in a certaine horrible winepresse: and now besides the ruines of houses, there remained no grave at all for the dead, but the bellies of beasts and birds; be it spoken with reverence to the sacred soules (if many yet were to be found) which at that time by the blessed Angels were assumpted to the high Heavens; for that vine which was sometimes so good, had as then so degenerated into bitternes, that (according unto the Prophet) like as when the winemakers or harvest men have done, there was hardly a grape or eare of corne to be seene.Of the remnant of the Britaines.
               
            
            XXV. Some therefore

of the miserable remnants being taken in the mountaines, were in heapes murthered; others constrained by famine, came and yeelded themselves to be eternall slaves to their foes, if they were not instantly neverthelesse slaine, which truely was the greatest favour that could be offered them: some others passed over beyond the Seas, singing or rather sighing with wonderfull lamentation under the shadowes of their sailes, in place of the Marriners sound, this heavy sentence; 
                  Psal. 43.12. 
               Thou hast given us as Sheepe to be slaughtered, and among the Gentiles hast thou dispersed us. Others committing the safegard of

their lives, in continuall doubtfull dread, to the mounting hils, to the fortresses of deepe downefals, to most thicke wooddy forrests, and to the Rockes of the Seas, remained (albeit with trembling hearts) yet still in their Country. But in the meane while, an opportunity happening, when as these most cruell robbers were returned home, the poore remnants of our Nation (to whom do flock from divers places round about our most miserable Countrymen as fast as Bees to their hives, for feare of an insueing storme) being strengthened by God, and with all their hearts calling upon him, and lading (as

they say) the Heavens with innumerable vowes, that they might not be now brought to utter distruction take armes under the conduction of Ambrose the Aurelian a modest man (who of all the Romane Nation was then alone in the confusion of so great a tempestuous season by chance left alive, his parents who for their honour were adorned with purple, being slain in the same broyles, although his progeny in these our dayes do foulely degenerate from the worthinesse of their Ancestors) and provoke to battaile their cruell Conquerors, and so by the goodnesse of our Lord obtaine the victory.
            
            
               Of the last victory granted by God to the Britaines.
               XXVI. After this sometimes our Countrymen, sometimes the Enemy won the field, to the end our Lord might in this Land try after his accustomed manner these his now Israelites, whether they loved him or not, untill the yeare of the siege of the mountaine of Bath, and of the last almost though not the least slaughter of our villanous foes, which was (as I am sure) forty foure yeares and one moneth after the landing of the Saxons, and also the time of my Nativity. And yet neither to this day truely are the Cities of our Country as before inhabited, but being forsaken and overthrowne doe hitherto

lye desolate, our forraigne warres ceasing, but civill remaining. For as well the remembrance of so desperate a distruction of the Iland, as also that of the unexpected recovery of the same remained in the minds of them, who were eye witnesses of the wonderfull events of both, and in regard thereof, Kings, publicke Magistrates, and private persons, with Priests and Clergy men, did all and every of them live orderly according to their severall vocations. But when these departed out of this world, and a new off-spring succeeded, that was ignorant of this troublesome time, and had onely experience

of the present prosperity, all the lawes of truth and justice were so shaken and turned upside downe, that I will not say one step, but not so much truely as one little memory of these vertues hardly rested to be seene in the fore-recited orders of men, a few, yea a very few excepted, who in respect of the losse of so great a multitude, which rusheth daily head-long downe to hell, are accounted so small a number, that our reverent mother the Church doth in a sort scarce behold them reposing in her bosome, whom shee doth onely accept for her true children; whose worthy lives being admirable

to all men, and of God beloved (by the sacred prayers of whom, as by certaine pillars and most profitable supporters, our infirmity is sustained up, that it may not utterly fall downe to the ground) I would have no one suppose I goe once about to reprove, if any way enforced by the encreasing heapes of offences I shall more liberally, yea more lamentably not so much declare as bewaile the wickednesse of those who are become servants not onely to their bellies, but also to the devill rather then to Christ, who is our blessed God, world without end.
            
            For why shall their Countrymen conceale, what forraigne Nations round about doe as now not onely know, but also cast in their teethes? Britaine hath Kings but Tyrants, shee hath Iudges but wicked, often spoyling and confounding, but the Innocent; defending and protecting but the faulty and Felons; having very many wives, but queanes and adulteresses, sundry times swearing but forswearing, vowing and almost instantly falsifying the same, making warres, but civill and unjust, mightily pursuing robbers abroad truely in the Country, and yet not only loving but also rewarding such

theeves as are with them at their tables; giving almes bountifully, but on the contrary side heaping upmountaines of mischiefes miserably, sitting in the throne of Iustice, but seldome seeking out the rules of rightfull judgement, disdaining the honest and humble, but extolling (as much as in them lyeth) unto the very starres, the blooddy, the proud, the monstrous murtherers, the combined and adulterous enemies if so (as they say) they may prevaile, of God himselfe, who together with their very names are to be razed absolutely out of the earth; having many fettered in their goales, but lading

them with chaines, whom they rather beate downe by deceits, then punish for any due desarts; making solemne oathes on the Altars, and presently afterwards despising the same Altars, as if they were but durty stones. The reprooving of Constantine
                Of which so horrible a crime, Constantine the Tyrannicall whelpe of the uncleane Lyonesse of Dannonier is not guiltlesse. This selfe same yeare after the taking of a dreadfull oath (whereby he bound himselfe first before God, and by a solemne sworne protestation, then calling all the quires of Saints, and Mother of God to witnesse, that hee would not contrive

any deceipts against his Country-men) he did neverthelesse in the reverent bosomes of two mothers, the Church, and the carnall Parent, under the habit of the Saintly Abbot Amphibalus,
               
                  Amphibol
                        •
                     s.
                amiddest the very holy sacred Altars (as I have sayd) in stead of teeth with his abhominable sword and lavelin, wound and rent the most tender sides of two royall 
                  
                     I thinke this shou'd be rather thus.
                  
                  Youths, and cruelly the entrailes of two nurselings. Fo
                           •
                         it appeareth to be two severall slaughter; the first of two young men, the last of two nurse children, according to our Chro
                           •
                        icles;
                  
                children, or cruelly the entrailes of two such nurselings, whose armes no way defended with armour (which no man almost as then more stoutly, than these poore babes used) but stretched against the day of Iudgement, to God

and the Altar, did hang up (O Christ) at the gates of thy City, the venerable ensignes of their patience and faith: yea so he did it as the purple cloakes (as it were) of congealed blood, did touch the seate of the heavenly sacrifice, neither did he commit this truely after any precedent commendable actions: For many yeeres before was he overcome with the often and interchangeable stenches of adulteries, having thrust away his lawfull wife against the commandement of Christ, and also the Doctor of the Gentiles, saying, 
                  Mat. 19 6. Marke 10 9 
               What God hath joyned, let not man separate; and againe, 
                  Eph. 5.28 Colos. 3.19. 
               Husbands love your wives,
               
For why he had planted in the ground of his heart (an unfruitfull soyle for any good seede) a certaine most bitter set of incredulity and folly, taken at the first from the Vine of Sodome, which being watred with his vulgar and domesticall impieties, as poyso
                  ••
               nous kinds of showres, an
                  •
                afterwards to the offence of God more audaciously springing up, hath brought forth into the world the sinne of horrible murder and sacriledge; and not as yet discharged of the entangling netts of his former offences, he encreaseth his new wickednesse with old villanies. Goe too now, I reproove thee as present,

whom I know as yet to be in this life extant; why standest thou astonished, O thou butcher of thine owne soule? why dost thou wilfully inkindle against thy selfe the eternall fires of hell: Why dost thou in place of enemies, desperately stabbe thy self with thine owne swords, with thine owne javelins? What cannot those same poysonous cuppes of offences yet satisfie thy stomack? Looke backe (I beseech thee) and come to Christ, (for why thou labourest, and art pressed even downe to the earth with this huge burthen) and he himselfe, as he sayd will give thee rest. Come to

him who wisheth not 
                  Esa. 52.2. 
               The death of a sinner, but that hee should be rather converted and live. Vnlose (according to the Prophet) the bands of thy necke,
               
                  Ezech. 33.11. 
               O thou sonne of Sion. Returne (I pray thee) although from the farre remote regions of sinnes,
                  Luc. 15.13. unto the most pyous Father who for his sonne that will despise the filthy foode of swine, and feare the death of cruell famine, and so come backe to him againe, hath with great joy accustomed to kill his fated Calfe, and bring forth for this erronio
                  •
               s wanderer, the first stole and royall ring, and then talking as it were a taste of the heavenly hope thou shalt perceive. 
                  Psa. 33.9. 
               How sweete

our Lord is. For if thou dost contemn
                  •
                these, be thou assured, thou art almost instantly to be for ever tossed and tormented in the inevitable and darke floods of endlesse fires. What dost thou also thou Lions whelp (as the Prophet saith) Aurelius Conanus?The reproving of Aurelius Conanus.
                Art not thou as the former (if not farre more foulely) to thy utter destruction, swallowed up in the filthinesse of horrible murders, fornications and adulteries, as in certaine over-whelming flouds of the sea? Hast not thou by hating, as a deadly serpent, the peace of thy Country, and thirsting unjustly after civill warres, and often frequent spoyles,

shut up the gates of heavenly peace and repose against thine owne soule? Being now left alone as a withering tree in the middest of a field, remember (I beseech thee) the vaine and idle phancies of thy Parents, and brethren, together with the untimely death that befell them in the prime of their youth; and shalt thou for thy religious deserts, be reserved to live some hundreds of yeares, or to attaine to the age of Methusalem, being now bereft almost of all succeeding posterity? No surely, but unlesse (as the Psalmist saith) thou shalt bee more speedily converted unto our Lord, that King

will shortly 
                  Psal. 7.13. 
               Brandish his sword against thee, who by his Prophet saith 
                  Deut. 32.39. 
               I will kill, and I will cause to live, I will strike, and I will heale, and he is not who can deliver out of my hand. Bee thou therefore 
                  Esa. 52.2. 
               shaken out of thy filthy dust, and withall thy heart converted to him, who hath created thee, that 
                  Psal. 2.12. 
               When his wrath shall shortly burne out, thou mayest be blessed in hoping on him. But if otherwise, eternall paines will be heaped up for thee, where thou shalt be ever tormented and never consumed in the cruell jawes of Hell.The reproving of Vortiper.
                Thou also who like to the sundry coloured Parde art divers in manners and diverse in mischeifes,

whose head now weareth hoare, who art seated in a Throne full of deceipts, and from the botome even to the very top deflowred with sundry detestable murders and adulteries, a naughty sonne of a good King, as another Manasses sprung from Ezechias, Vortiper thou Tyrant of the Demetians why dost thou astonished stearve away? What! doe not such violent gulfes of sinnes (which thou dost swallow up as most pleasant wine, if thou thy selfe art not rather swallowed up by them) is yet satisfie thee, especially since the end of thy life dayly now also approacheth? Why dost thou

heavily clogge thy miserable soule with a lustfull sinne of all others the foulest, by putting away thine owne wife, and after her honourable death, with a certaine irrecoverable burden of thine impudent daughter? Wast not (I beseech thee) the residew of thy life in offending God, because as yet an 2 Cor. 6.2. 
               acceptable time and day of Salvation shineth on the faces of the repentant, wherein thou mayest worke well, that thy 
                  Math. 24.20. 
               Flight may not be made in the Winter, or Sabbath. 
               
                  Psal. 33.15. 
               Turne away (according to the Psalmist) from evill, and doe good, seeke forth blessed peace and follow the same, because the eyes of our Lord
               
will bee cast upon thee, when thou dost righteousnsse, and his eares will bee then open unto thy prayers, and he will not destroy thy memory out of the land of the living, thou shalt cry and he will heare thee, and out of thy tribulations deliver thee, for Christ doth never despise 
                  Psal. 50.19. 
               an heart that is contrite and humbled with his feare. Otherwise 
                  Esay 66.24. 
               the worme of thy torture shall not dye, and the fire of thy burning be never extinguished.
               
                  Marc. 9.44. And why art thou tumbled in the old filth of thy naughtinesse,The reprooving of Cuneglasse.
                yea since the very first spring of thy tender youth, thou Beare, thou rider and ruler of many, and guider of the chariot

which is the Beares bearour, thou contemner of God, and depressour of his lot Cuneglasse, and by interpretation in Latine a yellow or golden butcher? why dost thou raise so great a warre as well against men as also against God himselfe, against men yea thy Country-men with thine especiall powers, against God with thine infinite offences? Why besides other thine innumerable ruines having throwne out of doores thine owne wife, dost thou with the lustfull love, or rather blockish dulnesse of thy minde, against the Apostles expresse prohibition,
                  Galat. 1.21. denouncing that no adulterers can

be partakers of the Kingdome of heaven, esteeme (according to the Poet) as the exceeding dainties of the celestiall nimphes, her detestable sister, who had vowed unto God the everlasting continency of her widdowhood? Why dost thou provoke with thine often injuries the lamentations and sighes of Saints, by thy meanes corporally afflicted, which will in time to come like a terrible Lionesse, breake thy bones in peeces? 
                  Psal. 36.8 
               Desist (I beseech thee (as the Prophet saith) from wrath, and leave of thy deadly, and (that which will be) thy selfe tormenting fury, which thou breathest out against heaven

and earth which is against God and his flocke: make them rather with altered mindes to pray for thee, who possesse a power of binding over this. world, when in this world they binde the guilty, and of loosing when they loose the penitent. 
                  Tim. 6.17. 
               Be not (as the Apostle saith) proudly wise, nor hope thou in the uncertainty of riches, but in God who giveth thee many things abundantly, and by the amendment of thy manners purchase unto thy selfe a good foundation for hereafter, and obtaine a 
                     •
                  rue, and truely everlasting life, and not a transitory one Otherwise thou shalt know and see yea in this very world,

how bad and bitter a thing it is for thee to leave thy Lord God, and not have his feare before thine eyes, and in the next, how thou shalt be burned in the foule incompassing flames of endlesse fire, nor yet by any manner of meanes ever dye. For why the soules of the sinfull are as well eternall in perpetuall fire, as the soules of the just in perpetuall joy and gladnesse.
            And likewise O Dragon of the Island,The reproofe of M
                        •
                     glocune.
                O depriver of many Tyrants, as well from their kingdomes as also from their lives, and among the fore-recited the last in my writing, but the first in thine owne mischiefe,

exceeding many in power, and also in malice, more liberall in giving, more licentious in sinning, boystrous in armes, but stronger in working thine owne foules destruction, Maglocune, to what end art thou (as one 
                  Ier. 23.9. 
               Soken in the wine pressed out of the Sodomiticall grape) foolishly moyled in that so ugly old deformity of thine offences? Why dost thou wilfully heape in bands upon thy kingly shoulders, such huge weights of sinnes, not unlike (as I may say) unto the unsupportable burdens of great mountaines? Why dost thou not shew thy selfe unto the King of all kings (who hath made thee

as well in kingdome as also in stature of body higher than almost all the Dukes of Britaine besides) better likewise in vertues than the rest; but on the contrary side for thy sinnes much worser? The certaine affirmation of which sinnes, do thou a while with an indifferent eare, heare and listen unto, wherein I will not touch any whitte thy domesticall and higher offences (if yet any of them are light) but onely report those open ones which are spread farre and broade in the knowledge of all men. Didst not thou in the very first entrance of thy youth, most terribly oppresse through sword,

speare, and fire, the King thine uncle together with his most couragious bands of Souldiers, whose countenances in battell were not much unlike unto young Lions? Little esteeming those words of the Prophet that say; 
                  Psal. 54.24. 
               Men of blood and deceite shall not accomplish the middle part of their daies: and were not the sequell of thy sinnes such as insued) yet what revenge shouldest thou expect at the hands of the just Iudge for this onely offence; He also saying by his Prophet: 
                  Esa. 33.1 
               Woe be to thee who spoylest, and shalt not thou thy selfe be spoiled? and thou who killest, shall not thy selfe be killed? and when thou shalt make an end of thy

spoyling, then shall thy selfe ruinate.
            
            But when the conceit of this usurping raigne had succeeded according to thine owne hearts wishes, didst not thou being taken with a desire of returning to the right way, day and night as then (perhaps through the deepe remorse of thy sinnefull conscience) chaw first of all, the cudde of thy many meditations about the service of God, and the observance of the rules of Monkes, and afterwards make it knowne to the whole world, and for ever vow thy selfe before Almighty God, and in the sight of Angels and men (breaking as it was thought

those most large nets, wherein fat buls of thy sort are wont to be headlong intangled, and overcomming all temptations of thirst of Kingdomes, Gold, and Silver, and which is greatest that of thine owne will) and wert professed a Monk without any thought (as thy selfe didst say) of violating the same, and didst not thou being now become of a crow a dove, like the same bird, when shee sheareth swiftly with her singing wings the empty aire, and avoideth with her often winding turnes, the fell talons of the ravenous hawke, safely recover thy selfe to the cels, and reposes of Saints, as thy most

trusty refuge? Oh how great a joy should it have beene to our Mother the Church, if the enemy of all mankind had not lamentably pulled thee in a sort out of her bosome! Oh how ample fewell of Heavenly hope, would have been inkindled in the hearts of desperate sinners, hadst thou remained in thy blessed estate! Oh what, and how great rewards in the Kingdome of Christ would have beene laid up for thy soule against the day of judgement, if that crasty wolfe had not caught thee, who of a wolfe, was now become a Lambe (not much against thine owne will) out of the fold of our Lord, and

made thee of a Lambe, a wolfe like to himselfe, againe? Oh how great a joy would the conservation of thy salvation have beene to God the holy Father of all Saints, had not the devill the miserable father of all castawaies, as an Eagle of monstrous wings and claws carryed thee captive away against all right and reason, to the unhappy roote of his children? And to be short, as great gladnes and sweetnesse, did thy conversion to righteousnesse minister to heaven and earth, as now thy detestable returne, after the manner of a sicke mastive unto the horrible vomit againe, breedeth griefe and lamentation:

which being done; 
                  Rom. 6.13. 
               The members are now become the armours of iniquity for sinne and the devill, which in right sence should have beene busily imployed, as the armours of justice for God: for now with thy listening eares are not heard the praises of God sweetly sounded forth by the pleasant voices of Christs Souldiers, nor the Organs of ecclesiasticall melody, but thine owne praises (which are nothing) rung out after the fashion of Bacchus giddy rout, by the mouthes of thy villanous followers fulfilled with lies, and also with foming malice, to the utter overthrow of every one of their neighbours, so

as the vessell sometimes prepared for the service of God, is now turned to a vessell of durt, and what was once reputed worthy of Heavenly honour, is now worthily cast into the bottomelesse pit of hell. Neither yet is thy sensuall mind (which is overcome by the excesse of folly) any whit abated or debarred of his course with committing so great sinnes, but hot and prone (like a young colt that coveteth every pleasant pasture) runneth▪ headlong forward, with irrecoverable fury, through the large fields of offences, in heaping new wickednesse on the head of the old. For the former marriage of thy

first wife (although after thy violated vow of Religion, she were not lawfully thine) yet being sometimes thine, was now despised, another, the wife of a man then living, and hee no stranger, but thine own brothers sonne, being in her place beloved. Vpon which occasion that stiffe necke of thine (being already laden with many burthens of sinnes) is now moreover with two monstrous murthers, the one of thy aforesaid Nevew, the other of her who sometimes was thy marryed wife (as with the outragious extremity of thy sacriledge) from low to lower, and from bad to worser,

bowed, bended, and depressed downe. Afterwards also didst thou accept her, (by whose deceit and suggestion such mighty matter of offences was undergone) publickely, and (as the flattring tongues of thy parasites with faigned, but not faithfull words pronounce) lawfully as a widdow, but (as we) say most wickedly to be thine owne in wedlocke. And therefore what holy man is there, whose bowels being mooved with the narration of such an history, would not presently break out into weeping and lamentations? What Priest (whose heart lyeth open unto God) would not instantly upon the hearing of

this, with marveilous mourning cry out that saying of the Prophet: 
                  Ier. 9.1. 
               Who shall give water to my head, and to mine eyes a fountaine of teares, and I will day and night bewaile those of my people, who are slaughtered. For why full little (alas) hast thou with thine eares once heard that reprehension of the Prophet speaking in this wise: 
                  Eccle. 4 1.11. 
               Woe be unto yee (O wicked men) who have left the Law of the most holy God, and if ye shall be borne, your portion shall be to malediction, and if ye die, into malediction shall be your portion, al things that are from the earth, to the earth shall bee converted againe, so shall the wicked from malediction passe to perdition:

(but ever supposed) if they returne not unto our Lord, receiving especially this admonition: 
                  Eccle. 21.1. 
               Sonne thou hast offended, adde no farther offence thereunto, but withall, doe thou pray for the forgivenesse of the former. And againe, 
                  Eccle. 5.8 
               Forslow not to be converted unto our Lord, neither yet doe thou put of the same from day to day, for his wrath doth come suddenly. Because as the Scripture saith: 
                  Pro. 29.12 
               When the King heareth the unjust word,
               
                  Pro. 29.4 
               all under his dominion become wicked. And, The just King (according to the Prophet) raiseth up his Region. But warnings truely are not wanting to thee, since thou hast for thine instructor the

most eloquent Master, of almost all Britaine. Take heed therefore, lest that which Solomon noteth, befalleth not to thee, which is: 
                  Eccle. 22.8. 
               Even as he who stirreth up a sleeping man out of his heavy sleepe, so is that person who declareth wisdom unto a foole, for in the end of his speech will he say. What hast thou first spoken? Wash thine heart (as it is written) from malice (Oh Ierusalem) that thou maist be saved. Despise not (I beseech thee) the unspeakeable mercy of God, calling by his Prophet, the wicked in this sort from their offences 
                  Iere. 18.7 
               I will on the suddvine speake to the Nation, and to the Kingdome, that I may roote out,

and dispearse, and destroy and overthrow. As for the sinner hee doth in this wise exhort him vehemently to pennance. And if the same people shall do pennance from their offence, I will also doe pennance upon the evil which I have said that I would doe against them. And againe, 
                  Ier. 18.8. 
               Who will give them such an heart, as they may heare me, and keepe my Commandements, and that it may be well with them all the daies of their lives, And also in the 
                  Deut. 32.28. 
               Canticle of Deuteronomy, A people without counsell and prudence, I wish they would be wise, and understand, and foresee the last of all, how one pursueth a thousand and two put to flight ten

thousands. And againe, our Lord in the Gospell. 
                  Mat. 11.28 
               Come unto me all yee who doe labour and are burthened, and I will make ye rest. Take up my yoake upon you, and learne of me, because I am meeke and humble of heart, and yee shall finde repose in your soules. For if thou dost hearken to these admonitions, but with deafe eares, if thou contemnest the Prophets, if thou despisest Christ, and (although most base we are) makest no account of us, so long as with sincere pietie and puritie of minde, we observe the same of the Prophet, that we may not bee found, 
                  Esa. 56.10 
               Dumbe dogges, not able to barke (howsoever I for

mine own particular am not of that singular fortitude, in the spirit and vertue of our Lord as to declare 
                  Esa. 58.1. 
               To the house of Iacob their sins and the house of Israel their offences) and so long as wee shall remember that of Salomon.
               
                  Pro. 24.24. 
               Who so termeth the wicked to be just, shall be accursed among the people, and odious to nations, for they who reproove shall have better hopes.
               
                  Eccle. 24.27 And againe, Respect not with reverence thy neighbour in his ruine, nor spare thou to speake in time of Salvation. And as long also as wee forget not this,
                  Pr
                        •
                     . 24.11. 
               Withdraw them away by force, who are led to death, and forbeare not to redeeme them who are murthered;

because as the same Prophet saith 
                  Pro. 11.4 
               Riches shall not profit in the day of wrath, but justice delivereth from death. And 
                  Pro. 11.31. 1 Pet. 4.18. 
               If the just truely be hardly saved, where shall the wicked, and sinner appeare? If thou scornest us and all these, the darkesome flood of hell shall without all doubt eternally drowne thee in that deadly whirlepoole, and those most terrible fiery streames that shall ever torment and never consume thee, and then shall the palpable knowledge of these paines, and sorrow for sinnes bee altogether to late and unprofitable unto him, who as now in this acceptable time and day of Salvation

deferreth his conversion unto the righteous way of of life. And here truely if not before was this so dolefull and lamentable an history of the miseries of our time, to have received a conclusion, that our mouth might no further discourse of the workes of men; But that we may not be esteemed fearefull or overwearied, whereby we might the lesse carefully avoyde that saying of Esay, which is, 
                  Esa. 5.20. 
               Woe be unto them who call good evill, and evill good, placing darkenesse for light, and light for darkenesse, bitter for sweete, and sweete for bitter,
               
                  Mat. 13.13. 
               who seeing see not and hearing heare not, whose he
                     •
                  rts are overshadowed

with a certaine thicke and blacke cloud of vices! We will breefely set downe, what and how great threatnings are denounced (against these five aforesayd lascivious horses, the franticke followers of Pharaoh, through whom his army is wilfully urged forward to their utter destruction in the red sea, and also against such others) by the sacred Oracles, with whose holy testimonies (as with a faire roofe) the frame of this our little worke, may be most assuredly covered, that it be not subject to the showres of the envious, which otherwise would be mainely powred thereupon. Let therefore the holy Prophets

(who have beene unto mortall men the mouth in a sort) of God, and the Organ of the holy Ghost, forbidding evils, and favouring goodnesse) answere for us as well now as in that before, against the stubborne and proud Princes of this our age, that they may not say we menace them with such threates, and so great terrors, onely of our owne invention, and overbusie talking rashnesse. For to no wise man is it doubtfull how farre more grievous the sinnes of this our time are, than those of the first age, the Apostle saying Any one transgressing the law,
               
                  Heb. 10.28. 
               being convicted by two or three witnesses, shall

dye, how much worser punishments thinke ye then that hee deserveth, who shall trample under his foote the Sonne of God? And he first of all appeareth before us, Samuel (by the Commandement of God) the stablisher of a lawfull kingdome, dedicated to God before his birth, undoubtedly knowne by admirable signes, to bee a true Prophet unto all the people, from Dan even to Bersheba, out of whose mouth the Holy Ghost thundreth to all the Potentates of the world, by denouncing unto Saul the first king of the Hebrews, onely because he did not accomplish some matters commanded him from our

Lord in this sort.1 Sam. 13.13. 
               Thou hast done foolishly, neither yet hast thou kept the Commandements of our Lord thy God, that he hath given thee in charge; which if thou hadst not commited, even now had our Lord prepared thy raigne over Israel for ever, but thy kingdome shall no farther arise. And what did hee commit adultery, or any abhominable murder like to the offences of this time? No truely, but broake in part a Commandement, because as well one of ours noteth; The question is not of the quality of the sinne, but of the violating of the precept. Also when he endeavored to answere (as hee thought) the objections

and after the fashion of men wisely to make defences for his offences on this wise; Yea I have heard the voyce of our Lord,
               1 Sam. 15.20 
               and walked in the way through the which hee hath sent me: with this reprehension was he corrected by him: What will our Lord have burnt offerings or oblations,
               1 Sam. 15.22 
               and not rather that the voyce of our Lord should be obeyed? Obedience is truely better than oblations, and to hearken unto him, better than to offer the fat of Rammes. Because as the sinne of Southsaying, so is it to resist, and as the offence of Idolatry not to obey; in regard therefore thou hast cast away the Word of our Lord, hee hath also cast thee away that

thou be not King. And a little after.1. Sam. 15.28. 
               Our Lord hath this day rent the Kingdome of Israel from thee, and delivered it up to thy neighbour, a man better than thy selfe. The triumpher of Israel truely will not spare, and will not be bowed with repentance, neither yet is hee a man that he may 
               
                  be penitent
                
               doe pennance, (supposed ever) upon the hard stony hearts of the wicked: Wherein it is to bee noted how he saith, that to be disobedient unto God is the sinne of Idolatry. Let not therefore our wicked transgressors (while they doe not openly sacrifice to the gods of the Gentiles) flatter themselves that they are not Idolaters, so long

as they treade like swine the most precious pearles of Christ under their feete. But although this one example as an invincible affirmation might abundantly suffice to correct the wicked: Yet, that in the mouthes of many witnesses all the offences of Britaine may bee approved, let us passe to the rest. What chanced to David for numbring his people, the Prophet Gad speaking unto him in this sort? Thus saith our Lord. The choise of three is offered thee,
               2 Sam. 24.12. 
               Elect to thee one of these which thou wilt, that I may execute it upon thee. Either shall there befall thee a famine for seaven yeares, or three monethes shalt thou

flye thine enemies and they pursue thee, or certainely there shall be three dayes Pestilence in thy land. For being brought into great streights upon this condition, and willing rather to fall into the hands of God who is mercifull, than into those of men, he was humbled with the slaughter of LXX thousand of his subjects, and unlesse with the affection of an Apostolike charity, he had desired to dye himselfe for his Country-men, that the Plague might not further consume them,2 Sam. 24.17. by saying, I am the same person that have offēd
                     •
                  d I the sheepheard have dealt unjustly: these who are sheepe what have they sinned? Let

thy hand (I beseech thee) be turned against mee, and against the house of my Father. He should have purged the unadvised pride of his heart with his owne death. For what doth the Scripture afterwards declare of his Sonne.1 Reg. 11.6. 
               And Solomon wrought what was not pleasing before our Lord, and he did not supply in his place, that hee might as his Father follow our Lord. And our Lord said unto him; Because thou hast thus behaved thy selfe,
               1 Reg. 11.11. 
               and not observed my covenant and precepts, which I have commanded thee, breaking it asunder; I will divide thy Kingdome, and give the same unto thy Servant. Heare now likewise

what fell upon the two sacrilegious Kings of Israel, (even such as ours are) Ieroboam, and Baasa, unto whom the sentence and doome of our Lord, is by the Prophet in this sort directed: For what cause have I exalted thee a Prince over Israel, 
               1 Reg. 14.7. 
               in regard they have provoked me in their vanities. 
               1 Reg. 16.2, 3, 4. 
               Behold I will stirre up after Baasha and after his house, and I will give over his house as the house of Ieroboam the Sonne of Nebat. whoso of his blood shall dye in the City, the dogges shall eate him, and the dead carkasse of his in the field, shall the foules of the aire devoure. What doth hee also threaten unto that wicked King

of Israel, a fellow souldier of the former band (by whose collusion and his wives deceit, innocent Naboth, was for his Fathers Vineyard oppressed) talking by the holy mouth of that Elias, yea the selfesame mouth that was instructed with the fiery speech of our Lord. Thou hast killed,
               1 Reg▪
                   21.19. 
               moreover likewise thou hast possessed, and after these thou wilt adde yet more. Thus saith our Lord, in this very place, wherein the dogges have licked the blood of Naboth, they shall lick up thy blood also. Which that it fell out afterwards in that very sort we have certaine experience. But least perchance (according as it

befell unto the aforesaid Achab) The lying spirit which pronounceth vaine things,1 Reg. 22.22. 
               in the mouthes of your Prophets may seduce ye, harken ye to the speeches of the Prophet Michaias.
               1 Reg. 22.23. 
               Behold God hath suffered the spirit of lying to poss
                     •
                  sse the mouths of all thy Prophets that doe here remaine, and our Lord hath pronounced evil against thee. For even now it is certaine there are some Doctors replenished with a contrary spirit, preaching and affirming rather naughty pleasure then truth: whose words are softer then oyle,
               
                  Psa. 54.22 Iere. 6.14. &amp;. 8.11. 
               and the selfe same are darts, who say, peace, peace and there shall be no peace to them, who persevere in

sinnes, as the Prophet in another place, on this wise speaketh. It is not for the wicked to rejoyce saith our Lord.
               
                  Esa
                        •
                     
                   48.22 &amp; 57.21. 
               Azarias also the sonne of Obed, did speake unto Asa, who returned from the slaughter of the Army of ten hundred thousand Ethiopians,
               2 Para
                        •
                     . 15.2. saying, Our Lord is with yee, while ye remaine with him, and if yee will seeke him out, he will be found by ye, and if ye will leave him, he will forsake ye. For if Iehoshaphat but yeelding assistance unto a wicked King, was thus reproved by the Prophet Iehu, the sonne of Anany, saying.2 Paral. 19.2. 
               If thou givest aid to a sinner, or lovest them whom our Lord doth hate,

the wrath of God doth therefore hang over thee, what shall become of them, who are fettered in the proper snares of their owne offences? whose sinnes but not whose soulēs, we must of necessity hate, if wee will fight in the Army of our Lord,
                  Psal. 96.10 the Psalmist saying, Hate ye evill, who love our Lord. What was said to the sonne of the afore rēcited Iosaphat, named Ioram, that most horrible murtherer (who being himselfe a bastard, slew his noble brethren, that hee might possesse the throne in their place) by the Prophet Elias, the wagon and wagoner of Israel?
               2 Paral. 21 21. 
               Thus speaketh (quoth he) the Lord God of

thy Father David. Because thou hast not walked in the way of thy Father Iosaphat, and in the waies of Asa the King of Iudah, but hast made thy passage through the wayes of the Kings of Israel, and in unsensiblenesse according to the behaviour of the house of Achab, and hast moreover killed thy brethren, the sonnes of Iosaphat, men farre better then thy selfe; behold our Lord shall strike thee and thy children with a mighty plague.
               2 Paral. 21.25. And a little afterwards. And thou shalt be marveilous sicke, of a disease of thy belly, until the entrailes of thy belly shal together with the malady it selfe from day to day passe forth away from thee? And listen also what

the Prophet Zachary the sonne of Ioiades menaced to Ioas the King of Israel, leaving our Lord even as ye now do, who arising, spoke in this manner to the People; Thus saith our Lord,
               2 Paral. 24.20. 
               why doe ye transgresse the Commandements of our Lord and doe not prosper? Because ye have left our Lord, he will also leave you. What shall I mention of Esay, the first and chiefe of the Prophets, who beginneth the proeme and enterance of his Prophesie, or rather vision, saying in this sort; Heare O yee Heavens,
               
                  Esa. 1.2. 
               and O thou earth conceive in thine eares, because our Lord hath spoken, I have nourished children, and exalted them, but they

themselves have despised me. The Oxe hath knowne his owner, and the Asse the manger of his Master, but Israel hath not knowne me, and my people hath not understood. 
               From this place forward all the sentences of Esay are omitted in another Booke. Esa. 1.8. And after a few words, framing threatnings answerable to so great a folly, he saith: The Daughter of Sion shall be uterly left as a shelter in the Vineyard, and as a hovell in the Cowcumber Garden, and a City that is sacked. And especial-conventing and accusing the Princes,
                  Esa. 1.10. he saith, Heare the word of our Lord (O yee Princes of Sodome,) perceive ye the Law of our Lord, O yee people of Gomorrah. Where truely it is to be noted, that unjust Kings are tearmed

the Princes of Sodome, for our Lord forbidding sacrifices and gifts to be offered unto him by such where we with greedy covetousnesse receive those offerings which in all Nations are displeasing unto God, and to our owne destruction suffer them not to be bestowed on the poore and needy speaketh to them who laden with abundance of riches, are likewise given to the filth of offences on this wise.
                  Esa. 1.13. 
               Offer not any more your sacrifice in vaine, your incense is abomination unto me. And againe he denounceth.
                  Esa. 1.15. 
               And when yee shall stretch out your hands, I will turne away mine eyes from ye, and when ye shall multiply

your prayers, I will not heare. And hee declareth wherfore he doth this, saying; Your hands are full of blood. And likewise showing how he may be appeased, he saith,
                  Esa. 1.16. 
               Be ye washed, be ye cleane, take away the evill of your thoughts from mine eyes, leave of to deale perversly, learne to doe well, seeke for the judgement, succour the oppressed, doe justice to the pupill or Orphan. And then assuming as it were the part of a reconciling appeaser, he adding saith,
                  Esa. 1.18. 
               If your sinnes shall be as scarlet, they shall be made white as Snow: &amp; if they shal be as red as the little worme, they shall be as white as wooll. If ye shall be willing and will heare me, ye

shall feede on the good things of the Land, but if ye wil not, and shall provoke mee unto wrath, the sword shall devoure ye. Receive ye, heare the true and publike avoucher witnessing without any falshood or flattery, the reward of your good and evill▪ not like the soothing humble lippes of your Parasites whispering poysons into your eares. And also directing his sentence against ravenous judges, he saith thus.
                  Esa. 1.23. 
               Thy Princes are unfaithfull, companions of theeves, all love gifts, hunt after rewards, they doe no justice to the Orphan, the widowes cause entreth not unto them. For this saith our Lord God of hosts, the strong one

of Israel. Alas, I will take consolation upon my foes, and be revenged upon mine enemies, and the hainous sinners shall be broken to powder and offenders together with them and all who have left our Lord, shall be consumed. And afterwards,
                  Esa. 2.11. 
               The eyes of the lofty man shall bee brought low, and the heighth of men hath bowed downe. And againe,
                  Esa. 3.11. 
               Woe be to the wicked, evill be fall him, for he shall be rewarded according to his handy workes. And a little after, Woe be unto ye who arise earely to follow drunkennesse,
               
                  Esa. 5.11. 
               and to drinke even to the very evening, that ye may vapouring fume with Wine. The Harpe, and the Lyra, and the Taber, and the Pipe,

and Wine are in your banquets, and the worke of our Lord ye respect not, neither yet consider ye the workes of his hands. Therefore is my people led captive away, because they have not had knowledge, and their Nobles have perished with famine, and their multitude hath withered away with thirst. Therefore hath hell enlarged and dilated his spirit, and without measure opened his mouth, and his strong ones, and his people, and his lofty and glorious ones, shal descend down unto him. And afterwards, Woe be unto ye who are mighty for the drinking of wine,
               
                  Esa. 5.22. 
               and strong men for the procuring of drunkennesse, who justifie the wicked for rewards,

and deprive the just man of his justice. For this cause even as the tongue of the fire devoureth the stubbell, and as the heate of the flame burneth up, so shall their roote be as the ashes, and their branch shall rise up us the dust. For they have cast away the law of our Lord of hosts, and despised the speech of the holy one of Israel. In all these the fury of our Lord is not turned away, but as yet his hand is stretched out. And somewhat after debating of the day of judgement and the unspeakeable feare of offendors, he saith. Howle ye out,
               
                  Esa. 13.6. 
               because the day of our Lord is neere at hand (if then neere, what shall it now be thought to be) in regard

destruction shall proceed from God. For this shall all hands be dissolved, and every mans heart shall wither away, and be bruised, small tortures and dolours shall hold them, as a woman in labour so shall they be grieved, every man shall at his neighbour stand astonished, burned faces shall be their countenances. Behold, the day of our Lord shal come, cruell and full of indignation, and of wrath, and fury, to turne the earth into a desert, and breake her sinners in small peeces from off her, because the starres of Heaven and the brightnesse of them, shall not unfold their light, the Sunne in his rising shall bee covered over with darknes, and the Moone

shall not shine in her season, and I will visite upon the evils of the world, and against the wicked their owne iniquity, and I will make the pride of the unfaithfull to cease, and the arrogancy of the strong, I will bring full low. And againe, Behold, our Lord will disperse the earth,
               
                  Esa. 24 1. 
               &amp; he will strip her naked, and afflict her face, and scatter her inhabitants, and as the people, so shall be the Priest, and as the slave so shal be his Lord as the handmaid so shall be her Lady, as the purchaser so shall be the seller, as the usurer, so shall be he that borroweth, as he who demandeth, so shall be he that oweth. With dispersing shall the earth be scattered,

and with sacking shall she be spoyled. For our Lord hath spoken this word. The earth hath bewailed, and hath fleeted away, the world hath run to nothing, she is weakned by her inhabitants, because they have transgressed lawes, changed right, brought to ruine the eternall truce. For this shall malediction devour the earth. And afterwards, They shall lament all of them who doe in heart rejoyce,
               
                  Esa. 24.7. 
               the delight of the timbrells hath ceased, the sound of the glad
                     •
                  some shall be silent, the sweetnesse of the Harpe shall be hushed, they shall not with singing drinke their wine, bitter shall the potion be to the drinkers thereof. The Cittie of vanitie is wasted, every

house is shut up, no man entring in; an outcry shall be in the streetes upon wine, all gladnesse is forsaken, the joy of the land is transferred, solitarinesse is left in the town, and calamitie shall oppresse the gates, because these things shall be in the middest of the land, and in the middest of the people. And somewhat afterwards,
                  Esa. 24.
                     •
                  6. 
               Swarving from the truth, have they wandred out of the right way, with the stragling of transgressors have they gone astray. Feare and intrapping falls, and a snare upon thee who art the inhabitant of the earth. And it shall come to passe: Who so shall flye from the voyce of the feare, shall tumble downe into the intrapping pit, and

who so shall deliver himselfe out of the downefall, shall bee caught in the intangling snare: because the flood-gates from aloft shall be opened, and the foundations of the earth shall be shaken. With bruising shall the earth be broken, with commotion shall she be moved, with tossing shall she be tottred like to a drunken man, and she shall be taken away as if shee were a pavilion of one nights pitching, and her iniquitie shall hang heavie upon her, and she shall fall done, and shall not attempt to rise againe. And it shall be, that our Lord in the same day shall visit on the warfare of heaven in the high place, and on the Kings of the earth,

who are upon the earth, and they shall be gathered together in the bundle of one burthen into the Lake, and shall there be shut up in prison, and after many dayes shall they be visited. And the Moone shall blush, and the Sunne be confounded, when our Lord of hosts shall raigne in mount Sion and in Ierusalem, and be glorified in the sight of his Seniors. And after a while, yeelding a reason why hee threatneth in that sort, he saith thus, Behold the hand of our Lord is not shortned that he cannot save,
               
                  Esay. 59.1. 
               neither yet is his eare made heavy that he may not heare. But your iniquities have divided betweene ye and your God, a
                     •
                  d your offences have hid his

face from yee, that he might not heare. For your hands are defiled with blood, and your fingers with iniquitie: Your lippes have spoken lying, and your tongue uttereth iniquity. There is not who calleth on justice, neither is there he who judgeth truely, but they trust in nothing, and speake vanities, and have conceived greefe, and brought forth iniquity. And a little after;
                  Esa. 59.6. 
               Their workes are unprofitable, and the worke of iniquity in their hands, their feete runne into evill, and make haste that they may shed the innocent blood; their thoughts are unprofitable thoughts, spoyle and confusion are in their wayes, and the way of peace they have

not knowne, and in their steps there is no judgement, their pathes are made crooked unto them, every one who treadeth in them is ignorant of peace; in this respect is judgment removed farre off from yee, and justice taketh no hold of yee.
               
                  Esa. 59.14. And after a few words; And judgement hath been turned back, and justice hath stoode a farre off, because truth hath fallen down in the streets, &amp; equitie could not enter in, and truth is turned to oblivion, and who so hath departed from evill, hath layne open to spoyle. And our Lord hath seene, and it was not pleasing in his eyes, because there is not judgement. And thus farre may it suffice among

many, to recite a few sentences out of the Prophet Esay.
            
            Now truely doe ye a while with diligent eares hearken unto him (who was foreknowne before he was formed in the belly, sanctified before hee came forth of the wombe, and appointed a Prophet in all Nations) Ieremiah I meane, what he hath pronounced of foolish people and cruell Kings, beginning moderatly his Prophesie in this manner.
            
               And the Word of God was spoken unto me saying;
               
                  Ierem. 2.2. 
               Goe and cry in the eares of Ierusalem, and thou shalt pronounce. Heare the Word of our Lord thou house of Iacob,

and all ye kindreds of the house of Israel; Thus saith our Lord; What iniquity have your fathers found in me, who have beene farre removed from me, and walked after vanitie, and are become vaine, and have not sayd, Where is he who made us ascend out of the Land of Egypt? 
               In another booke this first sentence of Ieremy is onely mentioned, and the rest all omitted. Ierem. 2.20. And after a few words; From the beginning of thine Age thou hast broken my yoake, violated my bands, and sayd, I will not serve, I have planted thee my chosen vine, all true seede. How art thou therefore converted into naughtinesse O strange Vine? If thou shalt wash thee with Niter, and multiply unto thee the hearbe Borith, thou art spotted in

my sight with thine iniquity, saith our Lord. And afterwards; Why will yee contend with me in judgement?
               
                  Ier. 2.29. 
               Ye have all forsaken me saith our Lord, in vaine have I corrected your children, they have not received discipline. Heare ye the Word of our Lord. Am I made a solitarinesse unto Israel, or a lateward Land? why therefore hath my people sayd, we have departed, we will come no more unto thee? What doth the Virgin forget her ornament, or the Spouse her gorget? my people truely hath forgotten mee innumerable dayes. 
               
                  Ier. 4.22. 
               Because my people are foolish, they have not knowne me, they are unwise and mad children. They are wise to doe

evill, but to doe well they have beene ignorant. Then the Prophet speaketh in his owne person saying; O Lord thine eyes doe respect faith, thou hast stroken them, and they have not sorrowed, thou hast broken them, and they have refused to receive discipline, they have made their faces harder than the rocke, and will not returne. And also our Lord:
                  Ier. 5.20. 
               Declare ye this same to the house of Iacob, and make it to bee heard in Iuda, saying: Heare ye foolish people who have no heart, who having eyes see not, and eares heare not. Ye will therefore not dread me saith our Lord, and yee will not conceive griefe from my countenance, who have

placed the sand the bound of the sea, an eternall commandement which she shall not breake, and her waves shall be moved, and they cannot, and her sourges shall swell, and yet not passe the same. But to this people is framed an incredulous and an exasperating heart, they have retired and gone their wayes, and not in their heart sayd, Let us feare our Lord God. And againe; Because there are found among my people wicked ones, framing wiles to intangell as if they were foulers,
               
                  Ier. 5.26. 
               setting snares and ginnes to catch men; As a net that is full of birds, so are their houses fullfilled with deceites. Therefore are they magnified and enriched, they

are become grosse and fat, and have neglected my speeches most vildly, the orphans cause they have not sentenced, and the justice of the poore they have not adjudged. What shall I not visit over these saith our Lord? or shall not my soule be revenged upon such a nation? But God forbid, that ever shold befall unto you, which followeth, Thou shalt speake all these words unto them,
               
                  Ier. 7.27. 
               and they shall not heare thee, and thou shalt call them, and they shall not answer thee, and thou shalt say unto them; This is the Nation that hath not heard the voice of their Lord God, nor yet received discipline, faith hath perished, and been taken away from out

their mouth. And after some few speeches, Whoso falleth doth he not arise againe,
               
                  Iere. 8.4. 
               and who so is turned away, shall he not returne againe? why therefore is this people in Ierusalem, with a contentious aversion alienated? they have apprehended lying, and they will not come backe againe. I have beene attentive, and harkened diligently, no man speaketh what is good. There is none who doth pennance for his sinne, saying, What have I done? All are turned unto their owne course, like a horse passing with violence into battle. The Kite in the sky hath knowne her time, the Turtle and Swallow and Storke have kept the season of their comming, but my people

hath not known the judgement of God. And the Prophet being strucken into feare, with so wonderfull a blindnesse, and unspeakeable drunkennesse of the Sacrilegious, and lamenting them who did not lament themselves (even according to the present behaviour of these our unfortunate Tyrants) he beseecheth of our Lord, that an augmentation of teares might be granted him, speaking in this manner;
                  Ie
                        •
                     e. 8.21. 
               I am contrite upon the contrition of the daughter of my people, astonishment hath possessed me: is there no gumme in Galaad, or is there no Physition there? Why therefore is not the wound of the daughter of my people

healed? Who shall give water unto my head, and to mine eyes a fountaine of teares, and I will day and night bewaile the slaughtered of my people? who will grant me in the wildernes the Inne of passengers, and I will utterly leave my people, and depart from them, because they are all of them adulterers, a roote of offenders &amp; they have bent their tong as the bow of lying, and not of truth, they are comforted in the earth, because they have passed from evil into evill, &amp; not known me saith our Lord. And againe:
                  Iere. 9.13. 
               And our Lord hath said, Because they have forsaken my law, which I have given them, and not heard my voice, nor walked thereafter, and have wandred away

after the wickednesse of their owne heart, in that respect our Lord of hostes the God of Israel, saith these words, Behold I will feede this people with wormewood, &amp; give them to drinke the water of gall. And a little after (speaking in the person of God) See therefore thou doe not pray for this people,
               
                  Iere. 11.14 
               nor assume thou for them praise and prayer, because I will not heare in the time of their outcry unto me, and of their affliction. What then shall now our miserable Governours doe, these few who found out the narrow way and left the large, were from God forbiden to powre out their prayers for such as persevered in their evils, &amp; so highly provoked

his wrath, against whom on the contrary side when they returned with all their hearts unto God (his divine Majesty being unwilling that the soule of man should perish, but calling backe the castaway that he should not utterly be destroyed) the same Prophets could not procure the Heavenly revenge, because not Ionas, when hee desired the like most earnestly against the Ninevites, could obtaine it. But in the meane while omitting our owne words, let us rather heare what the propheticall trumpet soundeth in our eares speaking thus:
                  Iere. 13.22 
               If thou shalt say in thy heart, why have these evils befalne? For the multitude

of thine iniquities. If the Ethiopian can change his skin, or the Parde his sundry spots, ye may doe also well when ye have learned evill (supposed ever) because ye will not. And afterwards:
                  Iere. 14.10 
               These words doth our Lord say to this people, who have loved to move their feete, and have not rested, and not pleased our Lord; now shall he remember their iniquities, and visit their offences, and our Lord said unto me, Pray thou not for this people to worke their good, when they shall fast, I will not heare their prayers: 
                     •
                  nd if they offer burnt sacrifices and oblations, I will not 
                     •
                  eceive them. And againe, And our Lord said unto me;
               
                  Iere. 15.1. 
               
                  
                     •
                  f Moses and Samuel shall

stand before me, my soule is not bent to this people, cast them out away from my face, and let them depart. And after a few words: Who shall have pitty on thee Ierusalem,
               
                  Iere. 15.5. 
               or who shall be sorrowfull for thee, or who shall goe to pray for thy peace? Thou hast left me (saith our Lord) and gone away backeward, and I will stretch forth my hand over thee, and kill thee. And somewhat after:
                  Iere. 18.11 
               Thus saith our Lord, Behold I doe imagine a thought against you, let every man returne from his evill course, and direct ye streight your waies and endeavours, Who said, we despaire, we will goe after our owne thoughts, and every one of us doe the naughtinesse of

his evill heart. Thus therefore saith our Lord. Aske the Gentiles, who hath heard such horrible matters, which the Virgin Israel hath too often committed? Shall there faile from the rocke of the field, the snow of Libanus? or can the waters be drawne dry that gush out colde and flowing? because my people hath forgotten me. And somewhat also after this, propounding unto them an election, he speaking saith, Thus saith our Lord,
               
                  Iere. 22.3. 
               Doe ye judgement and justice, and deliver him who by power is oppressed out of the hand of the malicious accuser; and for the stranger, and orphan, and widdow, doe not provoke their sorrow, neither yet

worke ye unjustly the griefe of others, nor shed ye out the innocent blood. For if indeed ye shall accomplish this word, there shall enter in through the gates of this house, Kings of the linage of David, sitting upon his throne. But if ye will not harken unto these words, by my selfe I have sworne (saith our Lord) that this house shall be turned into a desart. And againe,
                  Iere. 22.24 (for he spoke of a wicked King) I live (saith our Lord) if so be that Iechonias shall be a Ring on my right hand, I will plucke him thence away, and give him over into the hands of them who seeke his life. Moreover holy Abraham cryeth out saying:
                  Abac. 2.12 
               Woe be unto them who build a City in

blood, and prepare a towne in iniquities, saying: Are not these things from our Almighty Lord? and many people have failed in fire, and many Nations have beene diminished. And thus complaining, hee beginneth his prophesie:
                  Abac. 1.2. 
               How long (O Lord) shall I call, and thou wilt not heare? shall I cry out unto thee, to what end hast thou given mee labours and griefes, to behold misery and impiety? And on the other side;
                  Abac. 1.3. 
               And judgement was sat upon, and the Iudge hath taken in regard hereof, the Law is rent in peeces, and 
                     •
                  udgement is not brought fully to his conclusion, because 
                     •
                  he wicked through power 
                     •
                  readeth the just underfoote.

In this respect hath passed forth perverse judgement. And marke yee also what blessed Osee the Prophet speaketh of Princes saying:
                  Osee 8.1. 
               For that they have transgressed my covenant, and ordained against my Law, and exclaimed out. Wee have knowne thee, because thou art against Israel, they have persecuted good, as if it were evill, 
               
                  Osee 8 4. 
               They have raigned to themselves and not by mee, they have held a Principality, neither yet have they acknowledged me. And heare ye likewise the holy Prophet Amos, in this sort threatning:
                  Amos 2 4. 
               In three hainous offences of the sons of Iudah, and in foure I will not convert them, for that they have

cast away the Law of our Lord, and not kept his Commandements, but their vanities have seduced them. And I will send fire upon Iudah, and it shall eate the foundations of Ierusalem. 
               
                  Amos 2.6. 
               Thus saith our Lord; In three grievous sinnes of Israel, and in foure I will not convert them, for that they have sold the just for money, and the poore man for shooes, which they tread upon the dust of the earth, and with buffets they did beate the heads of the poore, and have eschewed the way of the humble. And after a few words: Seeke our Lord and ye shall live,
               
                  Amos 5.6. 
               that the house of Ioseph may not shine as fire, and the flame devoure it, and he shall not be, that can extinguish

it. 
               
                  Amo. 5.10 
               The house of Israel hath hated him who rebuketh in the gates, and abhorred the upright word. Which Amos being forbidden that he should not prophesie in Israel, without any fawning flattery, answering saith: I was not a Prophet, nor yet the sonne of a Prophet,
               
                  Amos 7.14 
               but a Goate herd, I was plucking Sicamores, and our Lord tooke me from my herd, and our Lord said unto me, Goe thy way and prophesie against my people of Israel, and now heare thou the Word of our Lord (For hee directed his speech unto the King) Thou sayest, doe not Prophesie against Israel, and thou shalt not assemble troopes against the house of Iacob. For which

cause our Lord saith thus, Thy wife in the City shall play the harlot, and thy sonnes and daughters shall dye by the sword, and thy ground be measured by the cord, and thou in a polluted land shalt end thy life, but for Israel, shee shall be led from his owne Country a captive. And afterwards:
                  Amos 8.4. 
               Heare therefore these words, ye who doe outragiously afflict the poore, and practise your mighty power against the needy of the earth, who say, When shall the moneth passe over that we may purchase, and the Sabbaths that wee may open the treasuries. And within a few words after:
                  Amos 8.7. 
               Our Lord doth sweare against the pride of Iacob, if he shall neglecting

forget your actions, and if in these the earth shall not be disturbed, and every inhabitant thereof fall to lamentation, and the finall end as a flood ascend, and I will turn your festivall dayes into wailing, and cast on the loynes of every one hairecloth, and on the head of every man baldnesse, and make him as the mourning of one over his beloved, and those who are with him, as the day of sorrow.
               
                  Amos 9.10. And againe: In the sword shall die all the sinners of my people, who say, Evils shall not approch, nor yet shall light upon us. And listen ye likewise, what holy Micheas the Prophet hath spoken saying:
                  Mich. 6.10. 
               Hearken ye Tribes. And what shall adorne

the City? shall not fire? and the house of the wicked hoording up unjust treasures, and with injury unrighteousnesse. If the wrongfull dealer shall be justified in the ballance, &amp; deceitful weights in the scales, by which they have heaped up their riches in ungodlinesse. And hearken also what threates the famous Prophet Sophonias thundereth out together:
                  Sopho. 1.14. 
               Neere draweth on (saith he) the great day of our Lord, neere it is at hand, and very swiftly approcheth. The voice of the day of our Lord is appointed to be bitter and mighty, that day, a day of wrath, a day of tribulation and necessity, a day of clouds and mist, a day of the trumpet and

outcry, a day of misery and extermination, a day of darknesse and dimnesse, upon the strong Cities, and high corners. And I will bring men to tribulation, and they shall goe as if they were blinde, because they have offended our Lord, and I will powre out their blood as dust, and their flesh as the dung of Oxen, and their silver and gold shall not be able to deliver them in the day of the wrath of our Lord. And in the fire of his zeale shall the whole earth be consumed, when the Lord shall accomplish his absolute end, and bring solitarinesse upon all the inhabitants of the earth. Come together and be joyned in one, thou Nation without Discipline, before ye

be made as the fading flowre, before the wrath of our Lord falleth upon ye. And give eare also unto that which the Prophet Aggeus speaketh on this wise:
                  Aggei. 2.22 
               Thus saith our Lord, I will once moove the Heaven, &amp; Earth, &amp; Sea, and dry land, and I wil drive away the Thrones of Kings, and roote out the powre of the Kings of the Gentiles, and I will chase away the chariots of those who mount upon them. Now also behold ye what Zacharias the sonne of Addo, that chosen Prophet said, beginning his prophesie on this manner: Returne ye to me,
               
                  Zach. 1.3. 
               and I will returne unto ye, (saith our Lord) and be not like your Fathers, to whom the former

Prophets have imputed saying, Thus saith our Almighty Lord, Turne away from your waies, and they have not marked whereby they might obediently heare me. And afterwards: And the Angell asked me,
               
                  Zach. 5.2. 
               what dost thou see? and I said, I see a flying sythe, which containeth in length twenty cubits. The malediction which hath proceeded upon the face of the whole earth: because every one of her theeves shall be punished even to the very death, and I will throw him away saith our Almighty Lord, &amp; he shall enter into the house of fury, and into the house of swearing falshood in my name.
               
                  Malac. 4.1. Holy Malachy the Prophet also saith, Behold

the day of our Lord shal come inflamed as a furnace, and all proud men, and all workers of iniquity shall be as stubble, and the approching day of our Lord of hostes shall set them on fire, which shall not leave a roote nor a bud of them. And hearken ye also what holy Iob debateth of the beginning and end of the ungodly,
                  Iob 21.7. saying: For what purpose doe the wicked live, and have dishonestly worne even to old age, and their issue hath beene according to their owne desire, and their sonnes before their faces, and their houses are fruitfull, and no feare nor yet the scourge of our Lord is upon them. Their Cow hath not beene abortive, their great with young, hath

brought forth her young ones and not missed, but remaineth as an eternall breede: and their children rejoyce, and taking the Psaltery and Harpe, have finished their dayes in felicity, and fallen peaceable a sleepe downe into hell. Doth God therefore not behold the workes of the wicked? Not so truely;
                  Iob 21.17. 
               But the candle of the ungodly shall be extinguished, 
                     ••
                  d destruction shall fall upon them, and dolors as of one in childbirth, shall with hold them from wrath; and they shall be as chaffe before the wind, and as the dust which the whirlewind hath carryed away. Let all goodnes faile his children, let his eyes behold his owne

slaughter, nor yet by our Lord let him be redeemed. And a little after he saith of the same men;
                  Iob 24.2. 
               Who have ravenously taken the flocke with the shepheard, and driven away the beast of the Orphans and engaged the Oxe of the Widdow, and deceiving, have declined from the way of necessity. They have reaped other mens fields before the time, the poore have laboured in the Vineards of the mighty without hyre and meate, they have made many to sleepe naked without garments of the covering of their life they have bereaved them. And somewhat afterwards, when hee had throughly understood their workes, he delivered them over to

darkenesse. Let therefore his portion be accursed from the earth,
               
                  Iob 24.18. 
               let his plantings bring forth witherings; let him for this be rewarded according to his dealings: 
               
                  Iob 24.20. 
               Let every wicked man like the unsound wood be broken in peeces. For arising in his wrath hath he overthrown the impotent. Wherefore truely 
               
                  Iob 24.22 
               shall he have no trust of his life, when he shall beginne to grow diseased, let him not hope for health, but fall into languishing. For his pride hath beene the hurt of many, and he is become decayed and rotten, as the mallowes in the scorching heate, or as the yeare of corne when it falleth off from his stubble. And afterwards; If his children

shall be many, they shall be turned to the slaughter,
               
                  Iob 27.14. 
               and if he gather together silver as if it were earth, and likewise purifie his gold as if it were durt, all these same shall the just obtaine. Heare yee moreover what blessed Esdras that Library of the Law, threatneth in his discourse on this wise.4 Esd. 15.22. 
               Thus saith our Lord God; My right hand shall not be sparing upon sinners, neither shall the sword cease over them who spill the innocent blood on the earth. Fire shall proceede from out my wrath, and devoure the foundations of the earth, and sinners as if they were inflamed straw. Woe be unto them who offend, and observe not my Commandements,

saith our Lord, I will not forbeare them. Depart away ye Apostatizing children, and doe not pollute my sanctuarie. God doth know who doe offend against him, and he will therefore deliver them over to death and to slaughter. For now have many evils passed over the round compasse of the earth.
               4 Esd. 16.3. 
               A sword of fire is sent out against yee, and who is he that shall restraine it? shall any man repulse a Lyon that hungereth in the wood? or shall any one quench out the fire when the straw is burning? our Lord God will send out evills, and who is he that shall represse them? and fire will passe forth from out his wrath, and who shall extinguish

it? it shall brandishing shine, and who will not feare it? it shall thunder, and who will not shake with dread? God will threaten all, and who will not be terrified? before his face shall the earth tremble, and the foundations of the sea fleet from the depth. And marke ye also what Ezechiel the renowned Prophet, and admirable beholder of the foure Evangelicall creatures, speaketh of wicked offendors, unto whom pittifully lamenting before hand, the scourge that hung over Israel, our Lord doth say,
                  Ezek. 9.9. 
               Too farre hath the iniquity of the house of Israel and Iudah prevailed, because the earth is fully filled with iniquity and uncleannesse.
               
               
                  Ezeck. 5.8. &amp; 11. 
               Behold I am, mine eyes shall not spare, nor yet will I take pitty. And afterwards,
                  Ezeck. 7.23 
               Because the earth is replenished with people, and the City fraughted with iniquity, I will also turne away the force of their power, and their holy things shall be polluted, prayer shall approach and sue for peace, and it shall not be obtained. And somewhat after; The Word of our Lord (quoth he) was spoken unto me saying;
               
                  Ezeck. 14.12 
               Thou sonne of man, the land that shall so farre sinne against me as transgressing it shall commit an offence, I will streatch forth my hand upon her, and breake in peeces her foundation of bread, and send upon her famine, and take away

mankind and cattle from her; and if these three men, Noah, Daniel, and Iob bee in the midst of her, they shall not deliver her, but they in their justice shall be saved, saith our Lord. If so be that also I shall bring 
                     〈◊〉
                   evill beasts upon the land and punish her, she likewise shall be turned to destruction, and there shall not be one who shall have free passage from the face of the beasts, and admit these three men are in the midest of her, I live (saith our Lord) if their sonnes and daughters shall be preserved, but they alone shall be saved, and as for the land it shall fall to confusion.
               
                  Ezeck. 18.20 And againe; The sonne shall not receive the unrighteousnesse

of the Father, neither yet the Father the sonnes unrighteousnesse. The justice of the just shall be upon himselfe. And the unjust man, if he turneth him away from all the iniquities which he hath done, and keepeth all my Commandements, and doth justice and abundance of mercy, hee shall live in life and shall not dye. All his sinnes, whatsoever he hath committed, shall have no further being; he shall live the life in his owne justice which hee hath performed. Doe I with my will voluntarily wish the death of the unrighteous (saith our Lord) ra
                     •
                  her than he should returne from his evill way and live? But when the just shall turne

himselfe away from his justice, and doe iniquity, according to all the iniquities which the unrighteous hath committed, all the just actions (which hee hath done) shall remaine no further in memory. In his offence wherein he hath fallen, and in his sinnes in which hee hath transgressed, he shall dye. And within some words afterwards:
                  Ezech. 29.23. 
               And all nations shall understand, that the house of Israel are led captive away for their offences, because they have forsaken me. And I have turned my face from them, and yeelded them over into the hands of their enemies, and all have perished by the sword; according unto their

uncleane sinnes, and after their iniquities have I dealt with them, and turned my face away from them. This which I have spoken may suffice concerning the threates of the holy Prophets: onely I have thought it necessary to intermingell in this little worke of mine, as well as the former menaces, a few words also borrowed out of the wisdome of Salomon, which declares unto Kings matter of exhortation or instructiō, that they may not say I am willing to lade the shoulders of men, with heavie and insupportable burthens of words, but not so much as once with mine owne finger (which is with

speech of consolation) to moove the same. Let us therefore heare what the Prophet hath spoken to rule us.
                  Sap. 1.1. 
               Love justice (saith he) yee that judge the earth. This onely testimony (if it were with a full and perfect heart observed) would abundantly suffice to reforme the governours of our Country. For if they had loved Iustice, they would also love God, who is in a sort the fountaine and originall of all justice. Serve our Lord in goodnesse,
               
                  Sap. 1.1. 
               and seeke him in simplicity of heart. Alas who shall live (as one before us hath sayd) to see these things performed by our Countrymen, yea if perhaps they

may be any where accomplished▪
               
                  Sap. 1.2. 
               Because he is found of those who doe not tempt him, he appeareth truely to them who have faith in him. For these men without respect doe tempt God, whose Commandements with stubburne despight they contemne, neither yet doe they keepe to him their faith, unto whose Oracles be they pleasing, or somewhat severe, they turne their backes and not their faces.
                  Sap. 1.3. 
               For perverse thoughts doe separate from God, and this in the Tyrants of our time very plainely appeareth. But why doth our meannesse intermeddle in this so manifest a determination? Let therefore him

who is onely true (as wee have sayd) speake for us, the holy Ghost I meane, of whom it is now pronounced;
                  Sap. 1.2. 
               The holy Ghost verily will avoyde the counterfetting of discipline. And againe.
                  Sap. 1.5. 
               Because the spirit of God hath filled the globe of the earth. And afterwards, (shewing with an evident judgement the end of the evill and righteous) hee saith,
                  Sap. 5.15. 
               How is the hope of the wicked as the doune that is puffed away with the wind, and as the smoake that with the blast is dispersed, and as the slender froth that with a storme is scattered, and as the memory of a guest who is a passenger

of one day. But the just shall live for ever, and with God remaineth their reward, and their cogitation is with the highest. Therefore shall they receive the kingdome of glory, and the crowne of beauty from the hand of our Lord. Because with his right hand he will protect them, and with his holy arme defend them. For very farre unlike in quality are the just and ungodly, as our Lord verily hath spoken saying,1 Sam. 2 30. 
               Them who honour me I will honour, and who so despise me shall be of no estimation. But let us passe over to the rest, Hearken (saith he) all yee Kings and understand ye,
               
                  Sap. 6 2. 
               learne ye Iudges of the bounds of the earth, listen with your eares

who conteine multitudes in awe, and please your selves in the troopes of nations. Because power is given unto yee from God, and puissance from the highest, who will examine your actions, and sift your thoughts. For that when ye were ministers of his kingdome, ye have not judged uprightly, nor kept the law of Iustice, nor yet walked according to his will. It shall dreadfully and suddenly appeare unto yee, that a most severe judgement shall be given on them who governe. For to the meaner is mercy granted, but the mighty shall mightily sustaine torments. For he shall have no respect of persons, who is the ruler of all, nor yet shall he reverence

the greatnesse of any one, because he himselfe hath made both small and great, and care alike he hath of all: but for the stronger is at hand a stronger affliction. Vnto yee therefore (O Kings) are these my speeches, that yee may learne wisdome, and not fall away from her. For who so observe what things are just, shall be justified, and who so learne what things are holy, shall be sanctified. Hitherto have we discoursed no lesse by the Oracles of the Prophets, than by our owne speeches with the Kings of our Country, being willing they should know what the Prophet hath spoken saying,
                  Ezeck. 21.2. 
               As from the face of a Serpent, so flye thou sinnes:

If thou shalt aproach unto them, the teeth of a Lyon will catch thee, their teeth are such as kill the soules of men.
               
                  Eccles. 17.18. And againe, How mighty is the mercy of our Lord. and his forgivenesse to such as convert themselves unto him. And if wee have not in us that Apostolicall zeale,
                  Rom. 9.3. that wee may say, I did verily desire to he amathematised by Christ for my brethren, Notwithstanding we may from the bottome of our hearts speake that Propheticall saying; Alas that a soule perisheth. And againe, 
                  Thren. 3.40. 
               Let us search out our wayes, and seeke and returne unto our Lord: Let us lift our hearts together with our bands to God in heaven,
               
And also that of the Apostle, 
                  Phil. 1.8. 
               We covet that every one of yee should bee in the bowels of Christ. And how willingly truely, as one tossed on the waves of the sea, and now arrived in a desired haven; would I in this place make an end (blushing shame forbidding me further to proceede) did I not behold such and so great mountaines of malice advanced against God by Bishops or other Priests, or clearkes, yea some of our owne order, whom as witnesses my selfe must of necessity first of all stone (accordi
                  •
               g unto the Law) with the hard blowes of words (least I should be otherwise reproved of partiality towards

persons) and then afterwards the people (if as yet they keepe their decrees) must pursue with their whole powers the same execution upon them, not to their corporall death but to the death of their vices and their eternall life with God. Yet (as before I have sayd) I doe crave pardon of them, whose lives I doe not onely prayse, but also preferre before all earthly treasure, and of the which (if it may be) yet before my death I desire and thirst to be a partaker: and so having both my sides defended with the double shields of Saints, and by those meanes invincibly strengthned to sustaine

all that arise against me, arming moreover my head in place of an helmet with the helpe of our Lord, and being most assuredly protected with the sundry assistances of the Prophets, I will boldly proceede notwithstanding the stones of worldly rioters flye never so fast about me.
            IT is very aptly said, that sinne creepeth on as a Cancker, for no man in a moment becommeth absolutely evill, but even like the Sea that making his entry first at a little hole, and afterwards enlarging his passage, in the end breaketh downe the bancke, and overwhelmeth the whole

land; so vice hath her progresses in depraved mindes; the lamentable example whereof, we may in the history of Britaine apparantly behold. Our Authour hath already declared the infection of Heresie, the corruption of infidelity, the disorders of warre, and the dissolution of manners, that distempered the body of the Iland, he laid open the sores of the temporall governors to the end that medicines might have beene the better applyed for their remedies, and here now he beginneth to discover the grievous imperfections of the Clergy, which are truely so much the worse, by how much their lives ought

to be more vertuous and exemplar; and yet would I have you to know, that these were defects not of Religion but of life, such as those offences of the Priests, Scribes, and Pharisees, so often in the word of God recited, whose sins (although too foulely they soiled their owne soules) yet could they never staine the immaculate Church of God, committed unto their charge: Neither yet did Gildas as another Elias complaine that there was not one left but himselfe alone who worthily served God, since in sundry places he sheweth how many were yet here in this land whose holy lives deserved most

high commendation, even as our Lord spake to the same Elias saying. There remained seven thousand in Israel, who never bowed their knees to Baal. But suppose Britaine had beene wholly drowned in the deepe Seas of offences, yet did Italy, Greece, and Gall. with many other mighty Provinces of the Christian world, flourish at the selfe same time, both in vertuous Life, and true Religion, not unlike the Kingdome of Iudah, which in that season, when Elias so complained of Israel, did notwithstanding openly maintaine the true worshipping of God; but this insueing Treatise telleth us that in the field of

our Lord, there sprung up Cockell, and in his barne of purest Corne, there was found chaffe, and among his wisest Virgins, foolish ones, all which in this world cannot be separated, but remaine untill the day of judgement, to be severally divided; thus doth he set before our eyes the beginning and proceeding of the wickednesse of Britaine, whose blessed soule possessed with a true zeale to God, departed to receive a Crowne of eternall glory, before the conclusion of this tragedy of sinne, for (as ye shall reade in venerable Bede) presently after the decease of Gildas, they fell to open errors, and then to

disobedience of the Church in withstanding the authority of Saint Augustine, the first Arch-bishop of Canterbury, although within a while afterwards, it pleased God of his singular mercy to recall them backe into his Catholike fold againe: Neither let any man imagine I have Translated this worke to disclose the faults of Pastors, and Superiours; For I had rather with Sem and Iaphet conceale, then with Cham reveale the imperfections of spirituall Fathers. But having Englished the former part of Gildas, I did also (because I would not leave the worke maimed, and unperfect) adventure upon this latter, wherein

I would wish the Readers to consider that if this flame of sinne did scorch the Cedars of Libanus, no doubt but it may burne the lesser silly shrubs, if it infected (I say) the spiritualty, it may assuredly (unlesse wee be ware) consume us of the Laity.
            
               BRitaine hath Priests, but some shee hath that are unwise; very many that Minister, but many of them impudent; Clearkes shee hath, but certaine of them deceitfull raveners; Pastors (as they are called) but rather wolves prepared for the slaughter of Soules, (for why they provide not for the common peoples commodity,

but covet rather the gluttony of their owne bellies) possessing the houses of the Church, but obtaining them for filthy lucres sake; instructing the Laity, but shewing withall most vilde examples, vices, and evill manners; seldome sacrificing, and seldome with cleane hearts, standing at the Altars; not correcting the Cominalty for their offences, while they commit the same sins themselves; despising the Commandements of Christ, and being carefull with their whole hearts to fulfill their owne lustful desires, some of them usurping with uncleane feet the seate of the Apostle Peter; but for the demerit

of their covetousnesse falling downe into the pestilent chaire of the traitor Iudas; detracting often, and seldome speaking truely; hating verity as an open enemy, and favouring falsehoods, as their most beloved brethren; looking on the just, the poore, the impotent, with sterne countenances, as if they were detested Serpents, and reverencing the sinne 
                  •
               ull rich men without any respect of shame, as if they were heavenly Angels, Preaching with their outward lips that almes are to be disbursed upon the needy, but of themselves not bestowing one halfepenny, concealing the horrible sinnes of the people,

and amplifying injuries offered unto themselves, as if they were done against our Saviour Christ; expel
               
                  •
               ing out of their houses 
                  •
               heir religious mother perhaps, or sisters, and fami
               
                  •
               iarly entertaining with indecency strange women, as 
                  •
               f it were for some more se
               
                  •
               ret office, or rather, to 
                  •
               peake truely, though fond
               
                  •
               y, (and yet not fondly to 
                  •
               ne, but to such as commit 
                  •
               hese matters) debasing 
                  •
               hemselves unto such bad 
                  •
               reatures; and after all these 
                  •
               eeking rather ambitiously 
                  •
               or ecclesiasticall dignities, 
                  •
               hen for the Kingdome of Heaven; and defending af
               
                  •
               er a tyrannicall fashion 
                  •
               heir atchieved preferments,

nor ever labouring with lawfull manners, to adorne the same; negligent and dull to listen to the precepts of the holy Saints (if ever they did so much as once heare that which full often they ought to heare) but diligent and attentive to the playes and foolish fables of secular men, as i
                  •
                they were the very waye
                  •
                to life, which indeede are but the passages to death▪ being hoarse, after the fashion of Bulls, with the abundance of fatnesse, and miserably prompt to all unlawfull actions; bearin
                  •
                their countenances arro
                  •
               gantly a loft, and having ne
                  •
               verthelesse their inwar
                  •
                sences, with tormenting an
                  •
               
               
gnawing consciences, depressed downe to the bottome, or rather to bottomelesse hell, with the gaining of one penny glad, and with the losse of the like valew sad, floathfull and dumbe in the Apostolicall decrees (be it for ignorance or ra
               
                  •
               her the burden of their offences) and stopping also 
                  •
               he mouthes of the learned, but singularly experienced 
                  •
               n the decitfull shifts of worldly affaires; and ma
               
                  •
               y of this sort and wicked conversation, violently in
               
                  •
               ruding themselves into the 
                  •
               referments of the Church, 
                  •
               ea rather buying the same 
                  ••
                an high rate, then being my way drawne thereunto, 
                  •
               nd moreover as unworthy

wretches, wallowing (after the fashion of swine) in their old and unhappy puddell of intollerable wickednesse, after they have attained unto the seate of Priesthood or episcopall dignity, (who neither have been installed or resident on the same) for usurping onely the name of Priesthood, they have not received the orders or apostolicall preeminence, bu
                  •
                how can they who are no
                  •
                as yet fully instructed in faith, nor have done pennance for their sinnes, be any way supposed meet
                  •
                and convenient to ascend unto any ecclesiasticall degree (that I may not speak
                  •
                of the highest) which non
                  •
                but holy and perfect men

and followers of the Apostles, and (to use the words of the Doctor of the Gentiles) persons free from reprehension, can lawfully and without the foule offence of sacriledge undertake. For what is so wicked and so sinnefull as after the example of Simon Magus,
               
                  Act. 8.18. (yea although with other faults, he were not before hand defiled) for any man with earthly price to purchase the office of a Bishop or Priest, that onely with holinesse and righteous life is lawfully compassed? but herein they doe more wilfully, and desperately erre in that they buy their deceitfull and unprofitable ecclesiasticall degrees,

not of the Apostles or their successours, but of tyrannicall Princes, and their father the devill; yea rather they raise this as a certaine roofe and covering of all offences, over the frame of their former serious life, that being protected under the shaddow thereof, no man should lightly hereafter lay to their charge their old or new wickednesses, and hereupon they build their desires of covetousnesse and gluttony, because being now the rulers of many they may more freely make havocke at their pleasures. For if truely any such offer of purchasing ecclesiasticall promotion
                  •
               
               
were made by these impudent sinners, (I will not say with Saint Peter) but to any holy Priest, or godly King, they would doubtlesse receive the same answere which their Father Simon Magus had from the mouth of the Apostle Peter, saying:
                  Act. 8, 20. 
               Thy money be with thee unto thy perdition. But (alas) perhaps they that order and advance these ambitious aspirers (yea they who rather throw them under foote, and for a blessing give them a cursing, whilst of sinners, they make them not penitents (which were more consonant to reason) but sacrilegious and desperate offendors, and in a sort install Iudas, that traytor to

his Master, in the chaire of Peter, and Nicolas the author of that foule heresie in the seate of Saint Stephen the Martyr) it may be did by the same meanes at the first obtaine their Priesthood themselves, &amp; therefore doe not greatly dislike in their children, but rather respect the same race, that they their fathers did before hand assuredly runne. And also if finding resistance, in obtayning their Diocesses at home, and some, who severely renounce this chaffering of Church-livings, they cannot there attaine unto such a pretious pearle, then it doth not so much loathe as delight them, (after they

have carefully sent their messengers before hand) to crosse the Seas, and travaile over most large Countries, that so in the end, yea although with the saile of their whole substance, they may winne and compasse such a pompe, and such an incomparable glory, or to speake more truely, such a durty and base deceit, and illusion. And afterwards with great show and magnificall ostentation, or rather madnesse, returning backe to their owne native soile, they grow from stoutnesse to statelinesse, and being wonted to levell their lookes to the toppes of the mountaines, they now lift up their drowsie eyes

streight into the aire, yea to the very highest clouds, and as Novatus that foule hog, and persecutor of our Lords precious jewel, dealt sometimes at Rome, so do these intrude themselves againe into their owne Country, as Creatures of a new mould, yea rather as devillish instruments, being even ready in this state and fashion to stretch out violently their hands (not so worthy of the reverent Altars, as the revenging flames of hell) upon Christs most holy Sacrifices. What doe ye therefore (O unhappy people) expect from such belly beasts (as the Apostle calleth them?
                  Tit. 1.12.) Shall your manners be amended by these,

who doe not onely not apply their mindes to any goodnesse, but (according to the upbraiding of the Prophet) also labour to deale wickedly?
               
                  Iere. 9.5. Shall ye be illuminated with such eyes as are onely with greedinesse cast on those things that leade headlong to vices (which is to say) to the gates of hell? Nay truely, if according to the saying of our Saviour,
                  Mat. 7.16. ye flie not these mostravenous wolves like those of Arabia,
               
                  Gen. 19.20 or avoide them as Lot, who ranne most speedily from the fiery showre of Sodome up to the mountaines, then being blinde and led by the blinde,
                  Mat. 15.14 ye will both together tumble downe into the

infernall ditch. But some man perchance will objecting say, that all Bishops, or all Priests, (according to our former exception,) are not so wickedly given, because they are not defiled with the infamy of Scisme, pride, or uncleane life, which neither wee our selves will deny, but albeit wee know them to bee chaste, and vertuous, yet will wee briefely answere.
            What did it profit the High Priest Hely,
               1 Sam. 2.11. that he alone did not violate the Commandements of our Lord,Examples of the Old Testament. in taking flesh with forkes out of the pots,1 Sam. 4.11. before the fat was offred unto God, while he was punished

with the same revenge of death wherewith his sonnes were? what one (I beseech yee) of them whose manners wee have before sufficiently declared hath like Abell upon theAbell. Gen. 4.8. malicious emulation of the more acceptable sacrifice (which with the heavenly fire ascended up into the skies) beene martyred? since they feare the reproach even of a seely ordinary word, which of them hath hated the councell of the malicious,
               
                  Psa. 25.59. 
               and not sate with the ungodly, so that of him as a Prophet, this may be verified which was sayd of Enoch;
               Enoch. Genes. 5.24 
               Enoch walked with God and was not to be found in the vanity (forsooth) of the

whole world, as then leaving our Lord and beginginning to halte downe right after Idolatry? which of them like Noah in the time of the Deluge,Noah. Genes. 7 7. hath not admitted into the Arke of Salvation (which is the now present Church) any adversary unto God, that it may be most apparent that none but innocents or singular penitents, ought to remaine in the house of our Lord? Who is he that offering sacrifice like Melchisedeck,
               Melchisedeck. hath onely blessed the conquerours, and them who delivering in the number of three hundred (which was in the Sacrament 
                  Gen. 14.18.of the Trinitie) the just man have overthrowne

the deadly armies of the five Kings, together with their vanquishing troopes, and not coveted the goods of others?Abraham. Which of them hath like Abraham at the Commandement of God freely offered his owne sonne on the Altar to bee slaine,
                  Genes. 22.1. that hee might accomplish a precept of Christ,
                  Math. 5.29. agreeable to this saying, thy right eye if it scandalizeth ought,
                  Ier. 48.10. to bee pulled out, and another of the Prophet, that he is accursed who withholdeth his sword from shedding blood?Ioseph. Who is he that as a Ioseph hath rooted out of his heart the remembrance of an offered injury?
                  Gen. 50.15. Who is he that as a Moses speaking

with our Lord in the Mountaine,Moses. Exod. 19.16. and not thereupon terrified with the sounding trumpets, hath in a figurative sence presented unto the incredulous the two tables, and his horned face which they could not endure to see, but tremble to behold? Which of them, praying for the offences of the people, did from the very botome of his heart cry out, like unto him saying:
                  Exod. 32 3. 
               O Lord this people hath committed a grievous sinne, which if thou wilt forgive them, forgive it; otherwise blot me guilty out of thy booke? Who inflamed with the admirable zeale of God hath couragiously risen for the revenge of fornication,Phin
                     •
                  es. Num. 25.7.
               
curing without delay by the present medecine of pennance, the affection of filthy lust, left the fire of the wrath of God should otherwise consume the people, as Phinees the Priest did,
                  Ps. 105.31. that by this meane justice for ever might be reputed unto him? Who verily of them hath in a morall understanding imitated Iesus Nave either forIesus Nave. the utter rooting forth (even to the slaughter of the last and least of all)
                  Ios. 24.11. the seaven Nations out of the land of promise, or for the establishing of spirituall Israel in their places? Which of them hath shewed unto the people of God their finall bounds beyond Iordan
               
(that it may be knowne what to every tribe is convenient) in such sort as the aforenamed Phinees and Iesus have wisely divided the land?Phinees and Iesus. Who is he that to overthrow the innumerable thousands of Gentiles, adversaries to the chosen people of God, hath as another Iephte,
               Iephte. for a sacrifice of a votive placation or appeasing,
                  Iud. 11.29.34. slaine his onely daughter (which is to be understood his owne proper will) immitating also therein the Apostle, saying, (Not seeking what is profitable to me,
               1 Cor. 10.33. 
               but to many, that they may be saved) which daughter of his, met the conquerours with drummes and daunces (to wit carnall

desires?) Which of them that he might disorder, put to flight, and overthrow the campes of the proud Gentiles,Gedeon. by the number of three hundred (being as before we have sayd,
                  Iud. 7.6.16. &amp; 20. the mystery of the blessed Trinity) and with his men holding in their hands, those noble sounding trumpets (which are Propheticall and Apostolicall sences, according as our Lord sayd to the Prophet, Exalt thy voyce as a trumpet,
               
                  Esay 58.1. and the Psalmist of the Apostles;
                  Psal. 18.5. 
               Their sound hath passed throughout the whole earth) and bearing also those famous flagons shining in the night season, with that most glittring fiery light (which are

to be interpreted the bodies of Saints adjoyned to good workes, and burning with the flame of the holy Ghost, yea having as the Apostle writeth,2 Cor. 4.7. 
               This treasure in earthen vessels) hath after the hewing downe of the Idolatrous grave (which is morrally meant, duske and darke desire) marched on like Gedeon,
               
                  Iud. 6.25. with an assured faith in the evident signe of the fleece, which to the Iewes was voyde of the heavenly moysture, but to the Gentiles made wet with the dew of the holy Ghost?
                  Iud. 6 36. Who is hee that (earnestly wishing to dye to this world, and live to Christ) hath as another Sampson.
               Sampson utterly extingui
                  •
               shed

such innumerable luxurious banquetters of the Gentiles,
                  Phil. 1.23. while they praysed their gods (which is meant while the sences of men extolled these earthly riches,
                  Iud. 16.30. according to the Apostle speaking thus;
                  Iud. 16.23, 24. 
               And covetousnesse which is the service of Idols) shaking with the power of both his armes the two pillars (which are to bee understood,
                  Coloss. 3.5. the naughty pleasures of the soule and body) by the which the house of all worldly wickednesse is in a sort compacted,
                  Iud. 16.30. and underpropped?Samuel. Who like Samuel that with prayers and the burnt sacrifice of a sucking lambe,1 Sam. 7.9. drave away the feare of the Philistians,
               
raised unexpected thunderclaps,1 Sam. 12.17 and showring clouds, established without flattery a King,1 Sam. 10.1 &amp; 17. deposed him when he displeased God, and annointed another his better in his place and Kingdome,1 Sam. 13.14 &amp; 15.18. &amp; 16.13. when he shall give to the people his last farewell, shall constantly appeare in this sort saying,1 Sam. 12.3. 
               Behold I am ready, speake ye before our Lord and his annointed, whether ever I tooke away the Oxe or Asse of any man. If I have falsely accused any one, if I have oppressed any body, if I have received a bribe from the hands of any? Vnto whom it was answered by the people; Thou hast not wrongfully charged us, neither yet oppressed, nor taken

any thing from the hands of any? Which of them like the famous Prophet Elias,
               Elias. who consumed with heavenly fire the hundred proud men, and conserved the fifty that humbled themselves;2 Reg. 1.9.11. &amp; 13. and afterwards denounced without fawning dissimulation, unto the unjust King (that sought not the Counsell of God by his Prophets, but of the Idoll Accaron) his imminent death, hath utterly overthrowne all the Prophets of Baal (which are interpreted worldly senses ever bent (as we have already sayd)1 Reg. 18.40. to envie and avarice) with the lightning sword (which is the Word of God?) and as the same

               Elias moved with the zeale of God,1 Reg. 17.1 after the taking away of the ayrie showres from the Land of the wicked, who were now shut up with famine in a strong prison, as it were of penury for three yeeres and sixe moneths, being himselfe ready to dye for thirst in the desert, hath complaining sayd,1 Reg. 19▪10. 
               They have murthered (O Lord) thy Prophets and undermined thine Altars, and I alone am left, and they seeke my life? Which of them like Haeliseus
               Haeliseus. hath punished his deerely beloved disciple if not with an everlasting Leprosie,2 Reg. 5.23 27. yet at least by abandoning him, who was extraordinarily burthened with the weight of

worldly coveting, those gifts which his Master before (although very earnestly entreated thereunto) dispised to receive?2 Reg. 6.15 &amp; 17. and which of these among us hath like him revealed unto his servant (who was troubled with despaire of life, and on a suddaine trembled at the warlike army of the enemies that besieged the City wherein hee was) through the fervency of his prayers, powred out unto God those spirituall visions, so as hee might behold a mountaine replenished with an heavenly assisting army, of warlike chariots &amp; horsemen, who shined with fiery countenances, and also beleeve that he was stronger

to save, then foes to offend? And which of them as the afore-recited Helizeus with the touch of his body, being dead truly to the world, but living unto God,2 Reg. 4.34 shall raise up another course perishing and carried out with a contrary funerall of death undoubtedly to God, but of life to vices, so as instantly revived, hee may yeeld humble thankes unto Christ for his unexpected recovery from the hellish torments of all mortall offences? which of them hath his lips purified and made cleane with the fiery coale carryed by the tongues of the Cherubin,
               Esaias. Esa. 6.6.7. from off the Altar (that his sinnes may be quite wiped away with

the humility of confession) as it is written of Esay,
               2 Reg 19.1. by whose effectuall prayers adjoyned with the ayde of
                  Esa. 37.1. the godly King Ezechias an hundred fourescore and five thousands of the Assirians Army through the stroake of one Angell without the least print of any appearing wound, were overthrowne and slaine? which of them like blessed Ieremy
               Ieremy. for accomplishing the Commandements of God, for denouncing the threates thundred out from heaven, and for preaching the truth even to such as would not heare the same,
                  Ier. 1.17. hath suffered loathsome stinking prisons as momentary deaths? And to be breef

what one of them (as the Doctor of the Gentils said) hath endured like the holy Prophets to wander in mountaines,
                  Iere. 20. in dennes, and caves of the earth, to bee stoned,
                  Heb. 11.38. to be sawed in sunder, and attempted with all kindes of death, for the name of our Lord? But why doe wee dwell in examples of the old Testament as if there were none in the new? Let therefore them (who suppose they doe without any labour at all, under the naked pretence of the onely name of Priesthood, enter this streight and narrow passage of Christian Religion) hearken unto us while we recite and gather in one a few

as the highest and cheefest flowers out of the large and pleasant meddow of the Saintly souldiers of the New Testament;Examples of the New Testament. which of ye (who rather sleepe than lawfully sit in the chaire of Priesthood) being cast out of the councell of the wicked,
                  Act. 11.50. hath after the stripes of sundry rods,
                  Act. 16.23. as the holy Apostles given from the bottome of his heart,
                  Act. 5.41. thanks to the blessed Trinitie that he was found worthy to suffer disgrace for Christs true Deitie? What one for the undoubted testimony of God, having his braines dashed out with the Fullers 
                  •
               lubbe;
                  Act. 12.2. hath as Iames the first, a Bishop of the New Testament, suffered corporall

death? Which of yee like Iames the brother of Iohn was by the unjust Prince beheaded? Who like the first Deacon and Martyr of the Gospell (having but this onely accusation,
                  Act: 7.57. that he saw God, whom the wicked miscreants could not behold) was by the ungodly hands stoned to death? What one of ye, like the worthy keeper of the keyes of the heavenly Kingdome, being nayled to the crosse with his feete upward, in regard of the reverence of Christ,S. Peter. whom no lesse in his death than in his life, he endeavored to honour, hath so breathed out his last gaspe? Which of yee for the confession

of the true word of Christ, hath like the vessell of election, and chosen Doctor of the Gentiles, after suffering the chaines of imprisonment,S. Paul. sustayning of Shipwracke, after the terrible scourges of whips, the continuall dangers of Seas, of theeves, of Gentiles, of Iewes, and of false apostles, after the labours of famine, of fasting, &amp;c. after his incessant care had over all the Churches, after his exceeding trouble, for such as scandalized, after his infirmity for the weake, after his admirable peregrination over almost the whole world in Preaching the Gospel of Christ, through the stroke of the sword lost his head?

which of yee, as the holy Martyr Ignatius,
               S. Ignatius. Bishop of the City of Antioch, hath after his miraculous actions in Christ, for testimony of him beene broken in peeces by the jawes of Lyons, as hee was sometimes at Rome? whose words (being now led to his passion) when yee shall heare (if ever your countenances were overcome with blushing) ye will not, onely in comparison of him esteeme your selves no Priests, but not truely so much as the meanest Christians; for in the Epistle which hee sent to the Church of Rome, he writeth thus: From Syria even unto Rome, I fight with beasts,

at Land and Sea, being bound and chained unto tenne Leopards, the Souldiers (I meane) appointed for my custody, who for our benefits bestowed upon them become more cruell but I by their wickednesse am the better instructed, neither yet am I in this justified; Oh when shall come those beasts the causers of my Salvation (which are for me prepared)? when shall they be let out loose at me? when shall it be lawfull for my carkas to enjoy them? whom I doe most earnestly wish to be eagerly inraged against me, and truely 
                     •
                   will incite them to devoure me, moreover, I will humbly pray, least perchance they should dread to touch my body (as in some others they

have heretofore done) yea also if they doubtfully stagger. I will offer violence, I will enforce my selfe upon them. Pardon mee (I beseech ye) I know what is commodious for me, even now I beginne to be the Disciple of Christ; let all envy, be it either of humane affection or else of spirituall wickednesse surcease, that I may diserne to obtaine Christ Iesus, let fires, let crosses, let cruelty of beasts, let breaking of bones, and renting of limbes, with all the paines of the whole body, and all the torments devised by the art of the devill, be altogether powred out on mee alone, so that I may merit to attaine unto Christ Iesus. Why do ye behold these things with

the sleepy eyes of your soules? why do ye hearken unto them with the deafe eares of your sences? Shake off (I beseech yee) the darkesome and blacke mist of the slothfulnesse of your hearts, that so ye may see the glorious light of truth and humility. A Christian and he not meane, but a perfect one, a Priest not base, but one of the highest, a Martyr not ordinary, but one of the chiefest, saith: Now I begin 
                     •
                  o be the Disciple of Christ. And ye like the same Lucifer, who was throwne downe out of Heaven, are puffed up with words not with power, and after a sort doe chaw under the tooth, and make pretence

in your actions, even as the Authour of this your wickednesse hath expressed saying,
                  Esa. 14 13. 
               I will mount up into the Heavens, and be like unto the highest: And againe, I have digged and drunk water,
               
                  Esa. 37.25. 
               and dryed up with the steppes of my feete all the rivers of the bankes. Where more rightly yee should have imitated him and harkened unto his words (who is doubtlesse the most true example of all goodnesse and humility) saying by his Prophet,
                  Psal. 21.7. 
               I am verily a worm and not a man, the reproch of men, and the outcast of the people. Oh unspeakeable matter! that he called himselfe the reproach of men, when as he washed quite away

the reproaches of the whole world. And againe in the Gospel, I of my selfe am not able to doe any thing.
               
                  Ioh. 5.30. When as he being coeternall with the Father, coequall with the Holy Ghost, and consubstantiall unto both, Created not by the helpe of another, but by his owne Almighty power, the Heaven and Earth, with all their inestimable Ornaments, and ye neverthelesse have arrogantly lifted aloft your voyces, notwithstanding the Prophet saith,
                  Eccle. 10.9 
               Why doth earth and ashes swell in prid
                     •
                  . But that I may returne unto the purpose. which of yee (I say) like the famous Bishop of the Church of Smerna Policarpus,
               St. Policarpus.
               
that witnesse of Christ, hath courteously entertained as guests at his table, those who violently drew him out to be burned, and being for the charity which he did beare unto Christ) brought to the stake sayd, He who gave me grace to endure the torment of the fire, will likewise graunt mee without fastning of nayles to suffer constantly the flames. And now overpassing in this my discourse mighty armies of Saints, I will as yet touch but one, for examples sake,S. Basill. 
               Basil, I meane the Bishop of Caesaria, who when hee was thus by the unrighteous Prince threatned, that (unlesse he would on the next morrow be as

the rest, defiled in the durty dunghill of the Arrian heresie) he was absolutely to be put to death, answered (as it is reported) I truely will be to morrow the same as to day, and for thee, I wish thou wouldest not change thy determination. And againe, O would I had some worthy reward to bestow on him that would speedily discharge Basil from the bands of this breathing bellowes. What one of ye to daunt the menaces of Tyrants, doth inviolably keepe the rule of the Apostolicall speech, which in all times and ages when some ever hath beene observed by al holy Priests to suppresse the suggestion of men, when they sought

to draw them headlong to naughtinesse, saying in this manner, It behoveth rather to obey God then men.
               
                  Act. 5.29. Wherfore after our accustomed manner making our refuge unto the mercy of our Lord, and to the sentences of his holy Prophets, that they on our behalfe may now levell the darts of their Oracles at unperfect Pastors (as before at Tyrants) so as thereby receiving compunction they may be cured, let us behold what manner of threates, our Lord doth by his Prophets utter, against slothfull and dishonest Priests, and such as doe not as well by examples as words, rightly instruct the people. For even

               Hely the Priest in Silo, for that hee did not severely proceed (with a zeale worthy of God) in punishing his sonnes, when they contemned our Lord, but (as a man overswayed with a fatherly affection) too mildly and remisly admonished them, was sentenced with this judgement by the Prophet speaking unto him:1 Sam. 2.28 
               Thus saith our Lord, I have manifestly shewed my selfe unto the house of thy Father, when they were the servants of Pharaohin Egypt, and have chosen the house of thy Father out of all the Tribes of Israel, for a Priesthood unto me. And a little after,1 Sam. 2.29. 
               Why hast thou looked upon mine incense, and upon my sacrifice, with a dishonest

eye? and hast honored thy children more then mee, that thou mightst blesse them from the beginning in all sacrifices in my presence? And now so saith our Lord: Because who so honour me I will honour them againe: and who so make no account of me shall be brought to nothing. Behold the dayes shall come and I will destroy thy Name, and the seed
                     •
                   of the house of thy Father. And let this be to thee the signe, which shall fall upon thy two sonnes Ophnee and Phinees, in one day shall they both dye by the sword of men. If thus therefore they shall suffer paines, who correct them that are subjected under their charge, with onely words,

and not with condigne punishment, what shall become of those who by offending exhort ye, and draw others unto wickednesse? It is apparant also what befell unto the true Prophet, who was sent from Iudah to prophesie in Bethel and forbidden not once to taste any meate in that place, after the signe which he foretold, was fulfilled, and after hee had restored the wicked King, his withered hand againe, being deceived by another Prophet, (as he was tearmed) and so made to take but a little bread and water, his host speaking in this sort unto him,1 Reg. 13.21. 
               Thus saith our Lord God; Because thou hast beene

disobedient to the mouth of our Lord, and not observed the precept which thy Lord God hath commanded, and hast returned, and eaten bread and drunke water in this place, in which I have charged thee that thou shouldest neither eate bread nor drinke water, thy body shall not be buried in the Sepulcher of thy forefathers. And so (saith the Scripture) it came to passe, that after he had eaten bread and drunke water, he made ready his Asse, and departed, and a Lion found him in the way and slew him. Heare yee also the holy Prophet Esay,
               
                  Esa. 3.11. how he speaketh of Priests on this wise. Woe be unto the ungodly, evill befall him; for the reward

of his hands shall light upon him. Her owne exactors have spoyled my people, and women have borne sway over her. O my people who tear me thee blessed, they themselves deceive thee, and destroy the way of thy footesteps. Our Lord standeth to judge, and standeth to judge the people. Our Lord will come unto judgement with the elders of the people and her Princes. Ye have consumed my Vine, the spoile of the poore is in your house. Why doe ye breake in peeces my people, and grinde the faces of the poore, saith our Lord God of Hosts? And also;
                  Esa. 10.1. 
               Woe be unto them who compose ungodly lawes, and writing have written injustice, that they may oppresse

the poore in judgement, and worke violence unto the cause of the lowly of my people, that widdowes, may be their prey, and they make s
                     ••
                  ile of the Orphans, what will ye doe in the day of visitation and calamity approching afarre of? And afterwards, But these also in regard of wine have beene ignorant,
               
                  Esa. 28.7. 
               and in respect of drunkennesse have wandered astray, the Priests have not understood, because of drunkennesse, and have beene swallowed up in wine, they have erred in drunkennesse they have not knowne him who seeth, they have beene ignorant of judgement. For all tables are filled with the vomit of their uncleannesse, in so much as there is not any

free place to be found. Heare therefore the Word of our Lord (O ye men ye deceivers) who beare authority over my people that 
                     〈◊〉
                   in Ierusalem.
               
                  Esa. 28.14. 
               For ye have sayd, we have entred into a truce with death, and with hell we have made a covenant. The overflowing scourge when it shall passe forth shall not fall upon us, because we have placed falshood for our hope, and by lying we have beene defended. And somewhat after, And haile shall overthrow the hope of lying,
               
                  Esay. 28.17. 
               together with the defence. Waters shall overflow, and your truce with death shall be destroyed, and your covenant with hell shall not continue, when the overflowing scourge shall passe forth,

yee shall also be troden under foote, whensoever it shall passe along thorough yee, it shall sweepe ye away withall. And againe, And 
                     〈◊〉
                   Lord hath sayd:
               
                  Esay 29.13 
               Because this people aproacheth with their mouth, and with their lippes glorifie me, but their heart is farre removed from me, behold therefore I will cause this people to admire with a great and amazed wonder. For wisedome shall decay and fall away, from her wisemen, and the understanding of her sages shall be concealed. Woe be unto yee that are profound in heart, to conceale counsell from our Lord, whose workes are in darkenesse, and they say who seeth us? And who hath knowne us? for this thought

of yours is perverse. And somewhat afterwards. Thus saith our Lord: Heaven is my seate, and the earth the foote stoole of my feete.
               
                  Esay 66.1. 
               What is this house that ye will erect unto me, and what place shall be found of my resting repose? all these things hath my hand made, and these universally have beene all created saith our Lord, on whom truely shall I cast mine eye, but on the humble poore man, and the contrite in spirit, and him that dreadeth my speeches? he that sacrificeth an Oxe, is as he that killeth a man; he that slaughtereth a beast for sacrifice is like him who beateth out the braines of of a dogge; he that offereth an oblation is as he that offereth

up the blood of an hogge; he that is mindfull of frankincense, is as he that honoureth an Idoll: Of all these things have th
                     •
                  y made choice in their wayes, and in their abominations hath their soule beene delighted. Listen ye also what Ieremy that Virgin and Prophet speaketh unto the unwise Pastors in this sort; Thus saith our Lord:
               
                  Iere. 2.5. 
               What iniquity have your fathers found in me, because they have removed themselves farre off from me, and walked after vanitie, and are become vaine? And somewhat after;
                  Ier. 2.7. 
               And entring in; ye have defiled my Land, and made mine inheritance abomination. The Priests have not sayd,

Where is our Lord? and the Rulers of the Law, have not knowne mee, and the Pastours have dealt treacherously against me. Wherefore I will as yet contend in judgement with you, saith our Lord, and debate the matter with your children. And a little afterwards,
                  Iere. 5.30. 
               Astonishment and wonders have beene wrought in the land. Prophets did Preach lying, and Priests did applaud with their hands, and my people have loved such matters.
               
                  Iere. 6.10. 
               What therefore shall be done in her last and finall ends? To whom shall I speake and make protestation that he may heare me? behold their cares are uncircumcised, and they cannot heare. Behold the word of our

Lord is uttered unto them for their reproach, and they receive it not: because I will stretch out my hand upon the inhabitants of the earth, saith our Lord. For why from the lesser even unto the greater, all study avarice, and from the Prophet even unto the Priest, all worke deceit, and they cured the contrition of the daughter of my people, with ignomy, saying, Peace, Peace, and peace there shall not be. Confounded they are, who have wrought abomination: but rather they are not with a confusion confounded, and have not understood how to be ashamed. Wherefore they shall fall among those who are ruinating, in the time of their visitation shall

they rush headlong downe together, saith our Lord. And againe, All these Princes of the declining sort, walking fraudulently,
               
                  Iere. 6.18. 
               being brasse and iron, are universally corrupted, the blowing bellowes hath failed in the fire, the Fi
                  
                     •
                  er of mettals, in vaine hath melted, their malicious acts assuredly are not consumed, 
                     •
                  all them refuse and repro
                  
                     •
                  ate silver, because our Lord 
                     •
                  ath throwne them away. And after a few words, I 
                     •
                  m,
               
                  Iere. 7.11. 
               I am, I have scene saith 
                     •
                  ur Lord. Goe your wayes to 
                     •
                  y place in Shilo, where my 
                     •
                  ame hath inhabited from 
                     •
                  he beginning, and behold 
                     •
                  hat I have done thereunto 
                     〈◊〉
                   the malice of my people of 
                     •
                  srael. And now because ye

have wrought all these works saith our Lord; and I have spoken unto yee, arising in the morning, and talking, and yet ye have not heard me, and have called yee, and yet yee have not answered. I will so deale towards this house, wherein my name is now called upon, and wherein ye have confidence: and to this place which I have given unto y
                     •
                  e, and to your fathers, as I have done to Shilo, and I will cast yee away from my coun
                     •
                  enance. And againe,
                  Iere. 10.20. 
               My children have departed from me, and have no abiding, and there is not he who any more pitcheth my tent, and advanceth my Pavillion: because the Pastors have dealt fondl
                     •
                   and not sought out our Lord.

Wherefore they have not understood, and their flocke hath beene dispersed. And within some words after,
                  Iere. 11.15 
               What is the matter that my beloved hath in my houses committed many offences? shall the holy flesh take away thy malitiousnesse from thee, wherein thou hast gloried? our Lord hath tearmed thy noone a plentifull, faire, fruitfull, goodly olive, at the voyce of the speech a mighty fire hath beene inflamed in her, and her Orchards have beene quite consumed▪ therewith. And againe, Come ye to me,
               
                  Iere. 12.9. 
               and be ye gathered together all ye beasts of the earth, make ye haste to devoure. Many Pastours have throwne downe my vine, they have trampled

my part under foote, they have given over my portion which was well worthy to be desired into a desart of solitarinesse. And againe he speaketh: Thus saith our Lord unto this people,
               
                  Iere. 14.10 
               which have loved to moove their feete, and not rested, nor yet pleased our Lord; now shall he remember their iniquities and visite their offences. Prophets say unto them, ye shall not see the sword, and there shall no famine be among ye, but our Lord shall give true peace unto ye in this place. And our Lord hath said unto me, The Prophets doe falsly foretell in my name, I have not sent them, neither yet laid my Commandement on them, they prophesie unto ye a lying vision,

and divination together with deceitfulnesse, and the seducement of their owne hearts. And therefore thus saith our Lord: in sword and famine shall those Prophets be consumed: and the people to whom they have prophesied shall by meanes of the famine and sword be cast out in the waies of Ierusalem, and there shall be none to bury them. And moreover;
                  Iere. 23.1. 
               W
                     •
                  e be to the 
                     •
                  astours who des
                     •
                  roy and rent in peeces the floc
                     •
                  e of my pasture, saith our Lord. Thus therefore saith our Lord God of Israel unto the Pastours who guide my people, ye have dispersed my flocke, and cast them forth, and not visited them: Behold I will visite upon ye the malice of your endeavours,

saith our Lord. For the Prophet and the Priest are both defiled, and in my house have I found their evill, saith our Lord, and therefore shall their way be as a slippery place in the darke, for they shall be thrust forward, and fall downe together therein, for I will bring evils upon them, the yeare of their visitation, saith our Lord. And in the Prophets of Samaria, I have seene foolishnesse, and they did prophesie in Baal, and deceived my people of Israel, and in the Prophets of Ierusalem, have I seene the like resemblance, adultery, and the way of lying, and they have comforted the hands of the vildest offendors, that every man may

not be converted from his malice: they have beene all made to me as Sodome, and the inhabitants thereof as those of Gomorrha. Thus therefore saith our Lord to the Prophets; Behold, I will give them wormewood for their food, and gall for their drinke. For there hath passed from the Prophet of Ierusalem pollution over the whole earth. Thus saith our Lord of hosts; listen not unto the words of Prophets, who prophesie unto ye, and deceive ye, for they speake the vision of their owne heart, and not from the mouth of our Lord. For they say unto these who doe blaspheme me, our Lord hath spoken, peace shall be unto ye; and to all that walke

in the wickednesse of their owne hearts, they have said, Evil shal not fall upon them. For who was present in the counsell of our Lord, and hath seene and heard his speech, who hath considered of his word, and hearkened thereunto? Behold, the whirlewinde of the indignation of our Lord passeth out, and a tempest breaking forth, shall fall upon the heads of the wicked, the fury of our Lord shall not returne, untill the time that he worketh and untill he fulfilleth the cogitation of his heart. In the last daies of all shal ye understand his counsell. And little also do
                  •
                ye conceive and put in execution, that which the holy Prophet Ioel hath likewise

spoken in admonishment of sloathfull Priests, and Lamentation of the Peoples dammage for their iniquities,
                  Ioel 1.6. saying: Awake ye who are drunke, from your wine, and weepe and bewaile ye all, who have drunke wine even to drunkennesse, because joy and delight are taken away from your mouthes. Mourne yee Priests, who serve the Altar, because the fields have beene made miserable. Let the earth mourne, because corne hath become miserable, and wine beene dryed up, oyle diminished, and husbandmen withered away. Lament ye possessions, in regard of Wheate and Barly, because the vintage hath perished out of the

field, the vine withered up, the figges diminished: the pomegranates, and palme, and apple, and all trees of the field are withered away, in respect that the children of men have confounded their joy. All which things are spiritually to be understood by you, that your soules may not wither away with so pestilent a famine, for want of the word of God. And againe, Weepe out yee Priests,
               
                  Ioel 2.17. 
               who serve our Lord, saying; Spare O Lord thy People, and give not over thine inheritance unto reproch, and let not Natio
                     •
                  s hold dominion over them, that Gentiles may not say, Where is their God? And yet ye yeeld not your eares

unto these sayings, but admit of all matters by which the indignation of the fury of God is more vehemently inflamed. With diligence also attend ye what holy O see the Prophet hath spoken unto Priests of your▪ behavior.
                  Osec 5 1. 
               Heare these words (O yee Priests) and let the house of Israel, together with the Kings house marke them; fast
                     •
                  n ye them in your eares, for that unto ye appertaineth judgement, because yee are made an intangling snare to the espying watch, and as a piched n
                     •
                  t more and worse then the toyle which the followers of hunting have framed. To ye also, may this kinde of alienation from our Lord, be meant by the

Prophet Amos saying, I have hated and rejected your festivall daies,
               
                  Amos 5.21 
               and I will not receive the savour in your solemne assemblies, because albeit ye offer our burnt sacrifices and hosts, I will not accept them, and I will not cast mine eye on the vowes of your declaration. Take away from me the sound of your songs, and the Psalme of your Organs I will not heare. For why the famine of the Evangelicall meate consuming, in your abundance of victuals, the very bowels of your soules, rageth violently within ye, according as the aforesaid Prophet hath foretold,
                  Amos 8.11. saying: Behold the daies shal come▪ saith our Lord, and I will send out

a famine upon the earth, not the famine of bread, nor the thirst of water, but a famine in hearing the word of God, and waters shall be mooved from sea even to sea, and they shal run over from the North even unto the East, seeking out the word of our Lord, and yet shall not find it. Let holy Micheas also pierce your eares, who not unlike a certaine heavenly trumpet soundeth shrilly forth against the deceitfull Princes of the People, saying: Hearken now yee Princes of the house of Iacob,
               
                  Miche. 3.1. 
               is it not for yee to know judgement, who hate goodnesse, and seeke after mischiefes, who plucke their skinnes from off men, and their flesh from their

bones? Even as they have eaten the flesh of my people, and fl
                     •
                  yed of their skins from them, broken their bones to peeces, and hewed them small as meate to the pot, they shall cry to God, and he will not heare them, and in that season turne his face away from them, even as they before have wickedly behaved themselves in their inventions. Thus speaketh our Lord of the Prophets who seduce my people, who bite with their teethes, and preach against them peace, and if a man giveth nothing to stoppe their mouthes, they raise and sanctifie a war upon him. Night shall therefore be unto yee in place of a vision, and d
                     •
                  rkenesse unto ye in l
                     •
                  we of divination,

and the sunne shall set upon your Prophets, and the day shall waxe darke upon them, and seeing droames they shall be confounded, and the diviners shall be derided, and they shall speake ill against all men, because there shall not be any one that will heare them, but that I myselfe shall doe mine uttermost &amp; strongest endeavour in the spirit of our Lord, in judgement and in power, that I may declare unto the house of Iacob their impieties, and to Israel their offences. Hearken therefore unto these words ye Captaines of the house of Iacob, and ye remnants of the house of Israel, who abhorre judgment, and overthrow all righteousnesse, who build up

Sion in blood and Ierusalem in iniquities: her rulers did judge for rewards, and her Priests answered for hire, a
                     •
                  d her Prophets did for money divine, and rested on our Lord, saying: And is not our Lord within us? evils shall not fall upon us. For your cause therefore shall Sion be ploughed up as a field, and Ierusalem as a watch cabbin of a garden, and the mountaine of the house as a place of a wooddy wildernesse. And after some words ensuing,
                  Mich. 7.1. 
               Woe is me for that I am become as 
                     •
                  e that gathereth stubble in the harvest, and a cluster of grapes in the Vintage, when the principle branch is not left to be eaten. Woe is me, that a soule hath

perished through earthly actions, the reverence of sinners ariseth even reverencing from the earth, and hee appeareth not that among men correcteth. All contend injudgement for blood, and every one with tribulation afflicteth his neighbour, for mischiefe hee prepareth his hands. Listen ye likewise how the famous Prophet Sophonias debated also in times past, with your fellow banqueters (for hee spake of Ierusalem, which is spiritually to be understood the Church or the soule) saying:
                  Sopho. 3.1. 
               O the Citty that was beautifull and set at liberty, the confident Dove hath not obediently hearkened to the voyce, nor yet entertained

discipline, she hath not trusted in our Lord, and to her God she hath not approached. And he sheweth the reason why,
                  Soph. 3.3. 
               Her Princes have beene like unto roaring Lyons, her Iudges as Wolves of Arabia did not leave towards the morning, her Prophets carrying the spirit of a contemptuous despising man; her Priests did prophane what w
                     •
                  s holy, and dealt wickedly in the law, but our Lord is upright in the middest of his people, and no unjust morning will he make, in the morning will he give his judgement. But heare ye also blessed Zachery the Prophet, in the Word of God, admonishing yee: For thus saith our Almighty Lord,
               
                  Zach. 7 9. 
               Iudge ye righteous judgement

and worke yee every one towards his brother mercy and pitty, and hurt yee not thorough your power the Widdoow, or Orphan, or stranger, or poore man, and let not any man remember in his heart the malice of his brother; and they have beene stubborne not to observe these, and have yeelded their backes to foolishnesse, and made heavie their eares that they might not hearken, and framed their hearts to be not perswasible that they might not listen to my law and words, which our Almighty Lord hath sent in his spirit, through the hands of his former Prophets, and mighty wrath hath beene raised by our Almighty Lord. And

againe, Because they who have spoken,
               
                  Zach. 10.1. 
               have spoken molestations, and diviners have uttered false visions and deceitfull dreames, and given vaine consolations; in respect hereof they are made dry as sheepe, and are afflicted because no health was to bee found; my wrath is heaped upon the Shepheards, and upon the Lambes will I visite. And within a few words after, The voyce of lamenting Pastors, because their greatnesse is become miserable.
               
                  Zach. 11.3. 
               The voyce of roaring Lyons, because the fall of Iordan is become miserable: Thus saith our Almighty Lord; who have possessed have murthered, and yet hath it not repented them, and who have

sold them, have sayd; Our Lord is blessed and we have beene enriched and their Pastors have suffered nothing concerning them. For which I will now beare no sparing hand over the inhabitants of the earth, saith our Lord. Heare ye moreover what the holy Prophet Malachy denounceth unto yee, saying,
                  Mala. 1.6. 
               Yee Priests who despise my name, and have sayd: Wherein doe we despise thy name? in offering on mine Altar polluted bread: and yee have sayd, Wherein have we polluted it? In that ye have sayd: The table of our Lord is as nothing, and have despised such things as have beene placed thereupon; because if yee bring what is

blind for an offering, is it not evill? If ye set and apply what is lame or languishing, is it not evill? Offer therefore the same unto thy governour, if he will receive it, if he will accept of thy person, saith our Almighty Lord. And now doe ye humbly pray before the countenance of your God, and earnestly beseech him (for in your hands have these things beene committed) if happily he will accept of your persons. And againe, And out of your ravenous theft ye have brought in the lame and languishing,
               
                  Mal. 1.13. 
               and brought it in as an offering. Shall I receive the same at your hands, saith our Lord? Accursed is the deceitfull man who hath in his

flocke one of the male kinde, and yet making his vow offereth the feeble unto our Lord, because I am a mighty King, saith our Lord of hosts, and my name is terrible among the Gentiles. And now unto yee appertaineth this Commandement, O yee Priests, if yee will not heare, and resolve in your hearts to yeeld glory unto my name, saith our Lord of hosts, I will send upon ye poverty, and accurse your blessings, because ye have not setled these things on your hearts. Behold I will extend out an arme upon yee, and disperse upon your countenances the dunge of your solemnities. But that ye may in the meane time, with a more thirsting desire prepare

your Organs and instruments of mischiefe, to be converted into goodnesse, hearken yee (if there remaineth as yet any so little inward listening in your hearts) what he speaketh of a holy Priest saying; My covenant of life and peace was with him (for historically he did speake of Levi and Moses) I gave feare unto him,
               
                  Mala. 2.5. 
               and he was timerous of me, he dreaded before the countenance of my name, the law of truth was in his mouth, and iniquitie was not found in his lippes, he walked with me in peace and equity, and turned many away from unrighteousnesse. For the lippes of the Priest shall keepe knowledge, and

from out his mouth they shall require the law, because hee is the angell of our Lord of hosts. And now againe hee changeth his stile, and desisteth not to rebuke and reprove the unrighteous, saying;
                  Mal. 2.8. 
               Ye have departed from the way, and scandalized many in the law, and made voyde my covenant with Levi, saith our Lord of hosts. In regard whereof I have also given ye over as contemptible and abject among my people, according as 
                     •
                  ee have not observed my 
                     •
                  ayes, and accepted counte
                  
                     •
                  ance of men in the law. What is there not one father of us all? What hath not one god created us? Why therefore doth every one despise his

brother? And againe, Behold our Lord of hosts will come,
               
                  Mal. 3.2. 
               and who can conceive of the day of his comming, and who shall endure to stand to behold him? For he shall passe forth as a burning fire, and as the fullers hearbe, and shall sit melting and trying silver, and he shall purge the sonnes of Levi, and clense them as gold and as silver. And somewhat afterwards,
                  Mal. 3.13. 
               Your words have growne strong against me, saith our Lord, and ye have spoken thus. He is vaine who serveth God, and what profit because we have kept his Commandements, and walked sorrowfull before our Lord of hosts. We shall therefore now call the arrogant blessed, for

because they are erected and builded up, while they worke iniquity, they have tempted God, and are made safe. But heare ye also what Ezechiel the Prophet hath spoken, saying:
                  Ezec. 7.26. 
               Woe upon woe shall come, and messenger upon messenger shall be, and the vision shall be sought for of the Prophet, and the law shall perish from the Priests, and counsell from the Elders. And againe: Thus saith our Lord;
               
                  Ezec. 13.8. 
               In respect that your speeches are lying, and your divinations vaine. For this cause, Behold, I my selfe unto ye saith our Lord; I will stretch out my hand on your Prophets, who see lies, and them who speak vaine things, in the discipline of my people

they shall not be, and in the Scripture, of the house of Israel, they shall not be written, and into the land of Israel they shall not enter, and yee shal know that I am the Lord, because they have seduced my people, saying, The peace of our Lord, and there is not the peace of our Lord. Here have they built the wall; and they annointed it, and it shall fall, And within some words afterwards;
                  Ezec. 13.18 
               Woe be unto these who fashion pillowes, apt for every elbow of the hand, and make veiles upon every head of all ages to the subversion of soules, and the soules of my people are subverted, and they possesse their soules, and contaminated me unto my people for a handfull of barley, and a

peece of bread to the slaughter of the soules, whom it behooved not to dye, and to the delivery of the soules, that were not convenient to live, while ye talke unto my people that listeneth after vaine speeches. And afterwards: Say thou sonne of man,
               
                  Ezec. 22.4. 
               thou art earth which is not watered with raine, neither yet hath raine fallen upon thee in the day of wrath, in which thy Princes were in the middest of thee as roring Lions, ravening on their preyes, devouring soules in their potent might, and receiving rewards, and thy widd
                     •
                  wes were multiplyed in the midst of thee, and her Priests have despised my law, and defiled my holy things. Betweene holy

and polluted, they did not distinguish, and divided not equally betweene the uncleane and cleane, and from my Sabbaths they veiled their eies, and in the midst of them they defiled.
               
                  Eze. 22 30. And againe, And I sought among them a man of upright conversation, and one who should altogether stand before my face, to prevent the times that might fal upon the earth, that I should not in the end utterly destroy it, and I found him not. And I powred out upon it, the whole designement of my minde, in the fire of my wrath for the consuming of them: I repaid their waies on their heads, saith our Lord. And somewhat after:
                  Eze 33.1. 
               And the word of our Lord was spoken

unto me saying: O Sonne of man, speake to the children of my people, and thou shalt say unto them: The land whereupon I shall bring my sword, and the people of the land shall take some one man among them, and ordaine him to be a watchman over them, and hee shall espie the sword comming upon the land, and sound with his trumpet, and signifie unto the people, who so truely shall then heare the sound of the trumpet, and yet hearing shall not beware: and the sword shal come and catch him, his blood shall light upon his owne head, because when hee heard the sound of the trumpet, hee was not watchfull, his blood shall be upon him, and this man, for

that hee hath preserved his owne soule, hath delivered himselfe. But the watchman if he shall see the sword comming, and not give notice with his trumpet, and the people shall not beware; and the sword comming shall take away a soule from among them, both the soule it selfe is caught a captive for her iniquities, and I will also require her blood at the hand of the watchman. And thou O son of man, I have appointed thee a watchman over the house of Israel, and if thou shalt heare the word from out my mouth, when I shall say to a sinner, Thou shalt die the death, and yet wilt not speake whereby the wicked may returne from his way: both the

unjust himselfe shall die in his iniquity, and truely I will require his blood also at thy hands. But if thou shalt forewarne the wicked of his way, that he may avoide the same, and he neverthelesse will not withdraw himselfe from his course, this man shall die in his impiety, and thou hast preserved thine owne soule. And so let these few among a multitude of Propheticall testimonies suffice, by which the pride or sloath of our stubborne Priests may be repelled, to the end they may not suppose that we doe rather of our owne invention, then by the authority of the Lawes, and Saints denounce such threats against them. And

now let us also behold what the trumpet of the Gospell, sounding to the whole world, speaketh likewise to disordered Priests; for as wee have often said, this our discourse tendeth not to treate of them, who obtaine lawfully the Apostolicall seate, and such as rightly and skilfully understand how to dispose their spirituall foode (in time convenient) unto their fellow servants (if yet at this time there remaine any great number of these in this our Country) but wee onely talke of ignorant and unexpert Shepherds, who leave their flock, &amp; feed on vaine matters, for learned and good Pastours are free

from these vanities. And therefore it is an evident token that hee is not a lawfull Pastour, yea not an ordinary Christian, who rejecteth and denyeth these sayings, which are not so much ours (who of our selves are very little worth) as the decrees of the old and New Testament; even as one of ours right well doth say, We do exceedingly desire that the enemies of the Church should also, without any manner of truce, be our adversaries: and that the friends and defendours thereof, should not onely be accounted our confederates, but also our fathers and governours. For let every one with true examination, call

his owne conscience unto account, and so shall he easily finde, whether according unto righteous reason hee possesseth his Priestly chaire or no. Let us see (I say) what the Saviour and Creator of the world hath spoken. Ye are (saith hee the salt of the earth,
               
                  Math. 5.13 
               if that the salt vanisheth away, wherein shall it be salted? it prevaileth to no purpose any farther, but that it be cast out of the doores, and trampled under the feete of men. This only testimony might abundantly suffice to confute all such as are impudent, but that it may be yet by the Words of Christ, more evidently prooved, with what huge intollerable

bands of offences, these false priests, intangle and oppresse themselves, some other sayings are also to be adjoyned; For it followeth: Ye are the light of the world.
               
                  Math. 5.14 
               A C
                     •
                  ty placed on a mountaine cannot be hid, neither yet doe they light a candle, and put it under a bushell, but upon a candlesticke, that it may shine unto all who are in the house. What Preist therefore of this fashion and time, who is so poss
                  •
               ssed with the blindenesse of ignorance, doth as the light of a most cleere burning candle, shine with the lampe of learning and good workes, in any house, to all that sit in the darkesome night? What one is so accounted a safe

publike and apparant refuge, to all the children universally of the Church, that he may be to his countrimen a most defensible and strong City, situated on the top of an high mountaine? Moreover, which one of them can accomplish one day together, this that followeth:
                  Mat. 5.16. 
               Let your light so shine before men, that they may see your good workes, and glorifie your Father who is in Heaven: Since rather a certain most obscure cloud of theirs, and the blacke night of offences, do in that sort hang over the whole I
                  •
               land, that they turne all almost away from the righteous course, and make them to wander astray

through unpassable and cumbersome paths of wickednesse, and so their heavenly Father is not onely by their workes not magnified, but also by the same intollerably blasphemed. And truely I gladly would in some historicall or morrall sense how so ever, willingly interpret (as farre forth as our meanenesse could afford) these testimonies of Holy Scripture, which are either already cited, or hereafter to be intermixed in this Epistle, but for feare least this our little worke, should be unmeasurably tedious unto those who despise, loathe, and disdaine, not so much our speeches as Gods sayings, I

have already alledged, and meane hereafter to affirme these sentences plainely without any circumstance. And to proceed, within a few words after:
                  Mat. 5.19. 
               For who shall breake one of the least of these Commandements, and so instruct men, shall be called the least in the Kingdome of Heaven.
               
                  Mat. 7.1. And againe, Iudge ye not that ye may not be adjudged: for in what judgement ye shall judge, ye shall be judged. And which one (I pray you) of your Company will regard this same that followeth;
                  Mat. 7.3. 
               But why dost thou see (saith he) the mote in the eye of thy brother, and considerest not the beame in thine owne eye? or how dost thou say to thy brother, suffer

me, I will cast the mote out of thine eye, and behold the beame remaineth still in thine owne eye? Or this insueing: Doe ye not give what is holy to dogges,
               
                  Mat. 7.6. 
               neither yet shall yee cast your pearles before swine, least perchance they tread them under their feete, and 
                     •
                  urning against ye breake ye asunder, which hath most often befallen unto ye. And admonishing the People, that they should not by deceitfull Doctors (such as ye) be seduced hee saith: Keepe your selves carefully from false prophets,
               
                  Mat. 7.15. 
               who come unto yee in the clothing of sheepe, but inwardly are ravenous wolves: by their fruite shall ye know them. Do men gather grapes of thornes,

or figs of thistles? So every good tree beareth good fruite, and the evill, evill. And somewhat afterward: Not every one who saith unto me,
               
                  Mat. 7.21. 
               Lord, Lord, shall enter into the Kingdome of Heaven, but who so doth the will of my father that is in Heaven, he shall enter into the Kingdome of Heaven. And what shall then become of yee, who (as the Prophet hath said) beleeve God onely with your lippes, and not adhere to him with your hearts. And how doe ye fulfill that which followeth;
                  Mat. 10.16 
               Behold I send yee forth as sheepe among the midst of the wolves. Who doe cleane contrariwise, proceede as wolves against a flocke of sheepe;

or the other ensueing sentence; Be ye wise as serpents and simple as doves,
               
                  Mat. 10.16 since ye are onely wise to bite others, with your deadly mouthes, and not to defend (with the objection and adventure of your whole body) your head, which is Christ, whom with all the endeavours of your evill actions, yee treade under foote; neither yet have ye the simplicity of doves, but the resemblance rather of the blacke Crow, which taking her flight out of the Arke, (which is the Church of God) and finding the carren of earthly pleasures, did never with a pure heart returne back thither againe. But let us looke on the rest.

               Feare ye not (saith he) them who kill the body,
               
                  Mat. 10.28 
               but are not able to slay the soule, but feare ye him, who can overthrow both soule and body into hell fire. Receive in your minds which of these ye have performed? And what one of yee is not wounded in the very deepe secrets of his heart, with this testimony following, which our Saviour uttereth unto his Apostles, of evill prelats, saying,
                  Mat. 15.14. 
               Doe ye suffer them, the blinde are leaders of the blinde, but if the blinde be a guide to the blinde, both shall fall into the ditch. But the people doubtlesse whom yee have governed, or rather beguiled, have just occasion to listen hereunto.

Marke ye also the words of our Lord speaking unto his Apostles and to the people, which words likewise (as I heare) yee your selves are not ashamed to pronounce full often in publicke:
                  Mat. 23.2. 
               Vpon the chaire of Moses have Scribes and Pharisees sate, observe ye therefore and accomplish, all whatsoever they shall speake unto ye; but doe ye not according unto their workes. For they doe but speake, and they of themselves doe nothing. It is truely unto Priests a dangerous and superfluous doctrine, which is overclouded with sinfull actions. Woe be unto ye Hypocrites,
               
                  Mat. 23 13. 
               who shut up the Kingdome of Heaven before men, your selves truely enter

not in, neither yet doe yee suffer those that are entring to passe in. For yee shall with horrible paines bee tormented, not onely in respect of the great offences of your wickednesse, which ye doe heape up for punishment in the world to come, but also in regard of those who dayly perish through your bad example, whose blood in the day of judgement shall be required at your hands.
            Yeeld ye in like sort diligent attention unto the misery, which the Parable setteth before your eyes that is spoken of the servant, who saith, 
                  Mat. 24.48. 
               in his heart, my Lord maketh delay

in his comming, and upon this occasion perchance, hath begunne to strike his fellow servants, eating and quaffing with drunkards. The Lord of the same servant therefore (saith hee) will come on a day when hee doth not expect him, and in an houre whereof hee is ignorant, and will divide him (from holy Priests undoutedly) and will place his portion with hypocrites (with them certainely who under the pretence of Priesthood doe shadow much iniquity) affirming that there shall bee weeping and gnashing of teeth; Which sorrow in this present life, neither for the daily ruines of the children of our holy

Mother the Church, nor yet for the desire of the Kingdome of Heaven, they have often sustained. But let us see what Paul, the true Schollar of Christ, and Master of the Gentiles (who is a mirrour of every ecclesiasticall Doctor,1 Cor. 11.1. 
               Even as I (saith he) am the Disciple of Christ) speaketh about a worke of such importance in his first Epistle on this wise: Because when they have knowne God,
               
                  Rom. 1.25. 
               they have not magnified him as God, or given thankes unto him; but vanished in their owne cogitations, and their fool
                     •
                  sh heart is blinded, affirming themselves to be wise, they are made fooles. Although this seemeth to be spoken

unto the Gentiles; looke into it notwithstanding, because it may conveniently be applyed unto the Priests and people of this age. And after a few words; Who have changed (saith he) the truth of God into lying,
               
                  Rom. 1.25. 
               and have reverenced and served the creature rather than the Creator who is blessed for ever: therefore hath God given them over unto the passions of ignominy. And againe,
                  Rom. 1.28. 
               And even as they have not approved themselves to have God in their knowledge, so God hath yeelded them up unto a reprobate sence, that they may doe such things as are not convenient, being replenished with all iniquitie, malice, uncleannesse of life, fornication,

covetousnesse, naughtinesse, full of envie, murther, (of the soules truely of the people) contention, deceipt, wickednesse, backbiters detracters, hatefull to God, spitefull, proud, puffed up, devisers of mischiefes, disobedient to their Parents, senselesse, disordered, without mercy, without affection, who when they had knowne the justice of God, understood not that they who commit such things, are worthy of death. And now what one of the aforecited sort hath indeede beene voyde of all these? And if he were, yet perhaps hee may be caught in the sense of the ensuing sentence, wherein hee saith; Not onely who doe these

things, but also who consent unto the doers,
               
                  Rom. 1.31. to wit, that none of them truely are free from this wickednesse. And afterwards; But thou according to thy hardinesse,
               
                  Rom. 2.5. 
               and impenitent heart, dost lay up for thy selfe wrath, against the day of wrath, and revelation of the just judgement of God, who will yeeld unto every one according unto his workes. And againe, For there is no acceptation of persons with God.
               
                  Rom. 2.11. 
               For whosoever have offended without the Law, shall also without the law perish: whosoever have offended in the Law, shall by the Law be judged. For not the hearers of the Law, shall with God be accounted just, but the dooers

of the law shall be justified. How severe a sentence shall they therfore sustaine, who not onely leave undone, what they ought to accomplish, and forbeare not what they are forbidden, but also flie as an hideous snake, the very hearing of the word of God, though lightly sounding in their eares. But let us passe over to that which followeth to this effect:
                  Rom. 6.1. 
               What shall wee therefore say, shall we continue still in our sinne, that grace may abound? God forbid, for we who are dead in sinne, how shall wee againe live in the same? And somewhat afterwards,
                  Rom. 8.35 
               Who shall separate us (saith hee) from the charity of Christ? tribulation,

or distresse, or persecution, or famine, or nakednesse, or danger, or the sword? What one (I pray you) of all you, shall with such an affection be possessed in the inward secret of his heart, since ye doe not only labor for atchieving of piety, but also indure many things for the working of impiety, and offending of Christ? Or who hath respected this that followeth:
                  Rom. 13.
                     •
                  2 
               The night hath passed, and the day appreached. Let us therefore cast of the workes of darkenesse, and put on the armour of light, even as in the day, let us honestly walke, not in banqueting, and drunkennes, not in couches, and wantonnesse, not in contention, and

emulation, but put ye on our Lord Iesus Christ, and make no care to bestow your flesh in concupiscences. And againe, in the first Epistle to the Corinthians, hee saith: As a wise workemaster have I laid the foundation,
               1 Cor. 3.10. 
               another buildeth thereupon, but let every man consider how he buildeth thereon. For no man can lay any other foundation besides that which is Christ Iesus. But if any man buildeth upon this, gold, and silver, pretious stones, hay, wood, stubble, every ones worke shall be manifests; for the day of our Lord shall declare the same, because it shall be revealed in fire, and the fire shall prove what every mans work is. If any mans worke shall

remaine, all by the fire shall be adjudged. Who so shall build thereupon, shall receive reward. If any mans worke shall burne, he shall suffer detriment. Know ye not that ye are the temple of God, and that the Spirit of God inhabiteth in ye? but if any man violate the Temple of God, God will destroy him. And againe,1 Cor. 3.18. 
               If any man seemeth among yee to be wise in this world, let him be made a foole that he may become wise. For the wisedome of this world, is foolishnesse with God. And within some words afterwards: Your glorying is not good.
               1 Cor. 5.6. 
               Know ye not, that a little leaven corrupteth the whole masse? Purge ye therefore the old leaven, that ye

may be a new sprinkling. How shall the old leaven, (which is sinne) be purged away, that from day to day with your uttermost endeavours is encreased. And yet againe.1. Cor. 5.9. 
               I have written unto ye in mine Epistle, that ye be not intermingled with fornicators, not truely the fornicators of this world, or the avaritious, ravenous, or idolatrous, otherwise ye ought to depart out of this world. But now have I written unto ye, that ye be not intermingled, if any one is named a brother, and be a fornicator, or avaritious, or an idolator, or a slaunderer, or a drunkard, or ravenous, with such an one, ye should not so much as eate. But a felon condemneth not

his fellow theefe for stealing, or other open robbery, whom he rather liketh, defendeth, and loveth, as a companion of his offence. Also in his second Epistle unto the Corinthians; Having therefore (saith he) this administration,
               2 Cor. 4.2. 
               according to that we have obtained mercy, let us not faile, but let us cast away the secrets of shame, not walking in subtilty, nor yet corrupting the word of God, (that is by evil example and flattery.) And in that which followeth, he doth thus discourse of wicked Doctors, saying: For such false apostles are deceitful workemen,
               2 Cor. 11.13 
               transfiguring themselves into the Apostles of Christ. And no wonder. For Sathan

himselfe transfigureth him into an Angel of light. It is not much therefore if his ministers are transfigured as ministers of justice, whose end will be according unto their workes. Listen yee likewise what hee speaketh unto the Ephesians? and consider if ye find not your consciences attainted as culpable of this that followeth? where he denounceth thus;
                  Ephes. 4.17 
               I say and testifie this in our Lord, that ye doe not as now walke like the Gentiles in the vanity of their owne sence, having their understanding obscured with darkenesse, alienated from the way of God, through ignorance, which remaineth in them in regard of the blindnesse

of their heart, who despairing, have yeelded themselves over to uncleannesse of life, for the working of all filthinesse and avarice. And which of ye hath willingly fulfilled this that next ensueth;
                  Ephes. 5.17 
               Therefore be ye not made unwise, but understanding what is the will of God, and be ye not drunke with wine, wherein there is riotousnesse, but bee yee fulfilled with the holy Ghost. Or that which he saith to the Thessalonians.
               1 Thess. 2.5 
               For neither have wee beene with ye at any time in the speech of flattery, as your selves doe know; neither upon occasion of avarice, neither seeking to be glorified by men, neither by ye, nor any others, when as wee might be honoured

as other Apostles of Christ. But wee have beene made as little ones in the midst of ye, or even as the nurse cherisheth her small tender children, so desiring yee, we would very gladly deliver unto yee, not onely the Gospel, but also our very lives. If in all things yee retained this affection of the Apostle, then might ye be likewise assured, that ye lawfully possessed his chaire. Or how have ye observed this that followeth: Yee know (saith hee) what precepts I have delivered unto yee.
               1 Thess. 4.2 
               This is the will of our Lord, your sanctification, that ye abstaine your selves from fornication, and that every one of ye know to possesse his owne vessell, in

honour and sanctification, not in the passion of desire, like to the Gentiles who are ignorant of God, and that none of you doe encroach upon or circumvent his brother in his businesse, because our Lord is the revenger of all these. For God hath not called us into uncleannesse; but unto sanctification. Therefore who despiseth these, doth not despise man, but God. What one also among you hath advisedly and warily kept this that insueth: Mortifie therefore your members which are upon the earth,
               
                  Colos. 5.3. 
               fornication, uncleannesse of life, lust, and evill concupiscence, for the which the wrath of God hath come upon the children of disfidence. Ye perceive therefore

upon what offences the wrath of God doth chiefely arise, in which respect do ye likewise heare what the same holy Apostle with a Propheticall spirit, foretelleth of you, and such as your selves, writing plainely in this sort to Timothy; For know you this,
               2 Tim. 3.1 
               that in the last daies there shall be dangerous times at hand. For men shall be selfelovers, covetous, puffed up, proud, blasphemous, disobedient to their parents, ungratefull, wicked, without affection, incontinent, unmeeke, without benignity, betrayers, froward, lofty▪ rather lovers of sensuall pleasures, then of God, having truely a show of piety, but renouncing the vertue

thereof, and avoide thou these men. Even as the Prophet saith; I have hated the congregation of the malitious,
               
                  Psal. 25.5. 
               and with the wicked I will not sit. And a little after, he uttereth that (which in our age we behold to encrease) saying: Ever learning, and never attaining unto the knowledge of truth:2 Tim. 3.7 
               For even as Iannes and Mambres resisted Moses, so doe these also withstand the truth: men corrupted in minde, reprobate against faith, but they shall prosper no further; for their folly shall be manifest unto all, as theirs likewise was. And evidently doth he also declare how Priests in their office ought to behave themselves, writing thus

to Titus, Shew thy selfe an example of good workes,
               
                  Tit. 2.7. 
               in learning, in integrity, in gravity, having thy word sound without offence, that he who standeth on the adverse part, may be afraid, having 
                     •
                  o evill to speake of us. And moreover hee saith unto Timothy; Labour thou as a good Souldier of Christ Iesus,
               2 Tim. 2.3. 
               no man fighting in Gods quarrell intangleth himselfe in worldly businesses, that he may please him unto whom hee hath approoved himselfe, for who so striveth in the lists for the mastery, receiveth not the crowne, unlesse he hath lawfully cont
                     •
                  nded. This is undoubtedly his exhortation given to the good. Other matter also which the same

Epistles contain, is a threatning advertisement unto the wicked (such as your selves, in the judgment of al understanding persons, appeare to be.) If any one (saith he) teacheth otherwise,
               1 Tim. 6.3. 
               and doth not peaceably assent to the sound sayings of our Lord Iesus Christ, and that doctrine which is according unto piety, he is proud, having no knowledge, but languishing about questions, and contentions of words, out of the which doe springing arise, envies, debates blasphemies, evill suspicions, conflicts of men corrupted in minde, who are deprived of truth, esteeming commodity to be piety. But why in using these testimonies, here and there dispersed,

are we any longer (as it were) tossed up and down in the silly boate of our simple understanding, on the waves of sundry interpretations? We have now therefore at the length thought it necessary, to have recourse even unto those lessons, which are worthily gathered out of almost all Texts of holy Scriptures, to the end they should not onely be rehearsed, but also be assenting and assisting unto the benediction, where with the hands of Priests, and others of inferiour sacred orders, are first consecrated, and that therby they may continually be warned never by degenerating from their Priestly dignity,

to digresse from the Commandements, which are faithfully contained in the same; so as it may be plaine and apparant unto all, that everlasting torments are reserved for them, that they are not Priests, or the servants of God, who doe not with their uttermost power follow and fulfill these instructions and precepts. Wherefore let us hearken what the Prince of the Apostles, Saint Peter, hath signified about this so weighty a matter saying: Blessed be God,
               1 Pet. 1.3. 
               and the Father of our Lord Iesus Christ, who through his mercy hath regenerated us into the hope of eternall life, by the resurrection of our Lord Iesus Christ

from the dead, into an inheritance wch can never corrupt, never wither, neither be defiled, conserved in heaven for yee, who are kept in the vertue of God; Why then doe ye fondly violate such an inheritance, which is not as an earthly one, transitory, but immortall and eternall? And somewhat afterwards; For which cause be ye girded in the loynes of your minde,
               1 Pet. 1.13. 
               sober, perfectly hoping in that grace which is offered ye in the revelation of Iesus Christ: Examine ye now the depths of your hearts, whether yee be sober and doe perfectly conserve the grace of Priesthood, which shall bee duely discussed and decided in the Revelation

of our Lord. And againe he saith,1 Pet. 1.4. 
               As children of the benediction, not configuring your selves to those former desires of your ignorance, but according unto him who hath called yee holy, be ye also holy in all conversation. For which cause it is written; Be ye holy because I am holy. Which one of ye (I pray) hath with the burning desire of the-whole minde, so pursued sanctitie, that he hath earnestly hastened, as much as in him lay, to fulfill the same? But let us behold what in the second lesson of the same Apostle is conteined,1 Pet. 1.22. 
               My deerest (saith he) sancti
                     •
                  ie your soules for the obedience of faith through the

spirit in charitie, in brotherhood, loving one another out of a true heart perpetually, as borne againe not of corruptible seede, but of incorruptible, through the Word of God, living and remaining for ever. These are truely the Commandements of the Apostle; and read in the day of your ordination, to the end ye should inviolably observe the same, but they are not fulfilled by ye in discretion and judgement, nay not so much as duely considered or understood. And afterwards, Laying therefore aside all malice,
               1 Pet. 2.1. 
               &amp; al deceipt, &amp; dissemblings, and envie, and detractions, as infants now newly borne, reasonable and without guile

covet ye milke, that ye may thereby grow to salvation, because our Lord is sweet. Recount yee also in your mindes, if these sayings which have sounded in your deafe eares, have not often likewise bin troden by ye underfoote; And againe, Ye truely are the chosen linage,
               2 Pet. 2.9. 
               the royall Priesthood, the holy nation, the people for adoption, that ye may declare his vertues, who hath called yee out of darkenesse into that his so mervoilous light. But truely by yee are not onely the vertues of God not declared and made more glorious but also through your wicked examples are they (by such as have not perfect beleefe) despised. Ye have

perchance at the same time likewise heard, what is read in the lesson of the Acts, on this wise; Peter arising in the middest of the Disciples sayd;
               
                  Act. 1.15. 
               Yee men my brethren, it is expedient the Scripture be fulfilled, which the holy Ghost hath by the mouth of David foretold of Iudas. And a little after, This man hath therefore purchased afield,
               
                  Act. 1.18. 
               of the reward of iniquitie. This have yee heard with a carelesse or rather blockish heart, as though the reading thereof had nothing at all apperteined unto your selves. What one of yee (I pray yee) doth not seeke the fielde of the reward of iniquitie? For Iudas robbed and pilled the

purse, and yee spoyle and waste the sacred gifts and treasures of the Church, together with the soules of her children. Hee went to the Iewes to make a Market of God, ye passe to the Tyrants, and their father the Devill that ye may despise Christ. He did set to sale the Saviour of the world for thirty pence, and yee even for one poore half-penny; what neede many words? The example of Matthias is apparently layd before yee for your confusion, who was chosen into his place, not by his owne proper will, but by the election of the holy Apostles, or rather the judgement of Christ, wherat

ye being blinded, doe not perceive how farre yee run astray from his merits, while yee fall wilfully and headlong, into the manners and affection of Iudas the traytor. It is therefore manifest that he who wittingly from his heart, tearmeth ye Priests, is not himselfe truely a worthy Christian. And now I will assuredly speake what I thinke: This reprehension might have beene framed after a milder fashion, but what availeth it to touch onely with the hand, or dresse with a gentle oyntment, that wound which with impostumation or stinking corruption, groweth now in it selfe so horrible, as it requireth the

searing iron, or the ordinary helpe of the fire, if happily by any meanes it may bee recured, the diseased in the meane while not seeking a medicine, and the Physitian much erring from a rightfull remedy? O yee enemies of God, and not Priests; O yee traders of wickednesse and not Bishops, O yee betrayers and not successours of the holy Apostles, O ye adversaries and not servants of Christ! Yee have certainely heard at the least, the sound of the words, which are in the second lesson taken out of the Apostle Saint Paul, although ye have no way observed the admonitions and vertue of them, but even as statues

(that doe neither see nor heare) stood that day at the Altar, while both then and continualy since he hath thundred in your eares saying; Brethren it is a faithfull speech,
               1 Tim. 3.1. 
               and worthy of all acceptance. Hee called it faithfull and worthy, but ye have despised it, as unfaithfull and unworthy. If any man coveteth a Bishopricke,
               1 Tim. 3.1. 
               he de
                     •
                  ireth a goodworke. Ye doe mightily covet a Bishopricke in respect of avarice, but not upon occasion of spirituall commoditie, and for the good worke which is convenient for the place; ye want it. It behoveth therefore such an one,
               1 Tim. 
                  
                     •
                  .2. 
               to be voyde of all cause of reprehension. At this saying

we have more neede to shed teares than utter words; for it is as much as if the Apostle had sayd, He ought to be of all others most free from occasion of rebuke.1 Tim. 3.2. 
               The husband of one wife, which is lkewise so contemned among us, as if that word had never proceeded from him;1 Tim. 3.2. 
               Sober, Wise, Yea which of ye hath once desired to have these vertues ingrafted in him, Vsing hospitality. For this, if perchance it hath beene found among ye,
                  Ibidem.
                yet being neverthelesse rather done to purchase the favour of the people, then to accomplish the Commandement, it is of none availe, our Lord and Saviour saying

thus; Verely I say unto yee, they have received their reward.
               
                  Mat. 6.2. Moreover, A man adorned,
               1 Tim. 3.2. 
               not given to wine; no fighter; but modest; not contentius, not covetous: O lamentable change! O horrible contempt of the heavenly Commandements! And doe ye not continually use the force of your words and actions, for the overthrowing or rather overwhelming of these, for whose defence and confirmation (if neede had required) yee ought to have suffered paines, yea and to have lost your very lives. But let us see what followeth; Well governing (saith he) his house,
               
                  Ibidem.
                
               having his children

subjected with all chastity. Imperfect therefore is the chastity of the Parents, if the children be not also indued with the same. But how shall it be, where neither the father, nor yet the sonne as depraved by the example of his evill parent, is found to be chaste?1 Tim. 3.5. 
               But if any one knoweth not how to rule over his owne house, how shall hee imploy his care over the Church of God? These are the words, that with apparant effects, shold be made good and approoved.1 Tim. 3.8. 
               Deacons in like manner, that they should be chast, not double tongued, not overgiven much to wine, not followers of filthy gaine, having the mystery of faith in

a pure conscience, and let these also be first approoved, and so let them administer, having no offence. And now trembling truely to make any longer stay on these matters, I can for a conclusion affirme one thing certainely, which is; that all these are changed into contrary actions, in so much that Clarkes, (which not without griefe of heart, I doe here confesse) are shamelesse and deceitfull in their speeches, given to drinking, covetous of filthy commodity, having faith (or to say more truely) unfaithfulnesse in an unpure conscience, ministring not upon probation of their good workes, but upon foreknowledge of

their evill actions, and being thus defiled with innumerable offences, they are notwithstanding admitted unto the holy function, ye have likewise heard on the same day (wherin ye should with farre more right and reason have beene drawne to prison or punishment, then preferred unto Priesthood) when our Lord demanded whom his Disciples supposed him to be, how Peter answered; Thou art Christ,
               
                  Mat. 16.16 
               the Sonne of the living God, and our Lord in respect of such his confession, said unto him: Blessed art thou Simon Ba
                     •
                  jonas,
               
                  Mat. 16.17. 
               because flesh and blood hath not revealed unto thee, but my Father who is in Heaven. Peter
               
therefore instructed by God the Father, doth rightly confesse Christ; but ye being taught by the devill your father, doe with your lewd actions, wickedly deny our Saviour. It is said to the true Priest, Thou art Peter,
               
                  Mat. 16.18 
               and upon this rocke will I build my Church: But ye are resembled unto the foolish man,
               
                  Mat. 7.26. 
               who hath builded his house upon the sand. And verily it is to be noted, that God joyneth not in workemanship with the unwise, when they build their house upon the deceitfull uncertainty of the sands, according unto that saying: They have made Kings unto themselves▪ and not by me. Semblably that (which followeth)

soundeth in like sort,
                  Mat. 16.17 speaking thus: And the Gates of hell (whereby the infernall sins are to be understood) shall not prevaile. But of your fraile and deadly frame, marke what is pronounced? The floods came,
               
                  Mat. 7.25. 
               and the winds blew, &amp; have mainely dashed upon that house and it sell, and great was the ruine thereof. To Peter and his successors our Lord doth say: And I will give unto thee the Keyes of the Kingdome of Heaven:
                  Ma
                        •
                     
                     ▪t 16.18 But unto ye; I know yee not, depart from me ye workers of iniquity, that being separated with the goates of the left hand, ye may together with them, go into eternall fire. It is also promised unto

every good Priest;
                  Mat. 16.18. He speakes not of the power and jurisdiction but of the decency and 
                     •
                  itnes 
                     •
                  ince no Priest but may absolve another though in sinne himself, neither can he excummunicate himselfe. Prov. 5.22. 
               What soever thou shalt loose upon earth, shall be likewise loosed in heaven: and whatsoever thou shalt binde upon earth, shall be in like sort bound in Heaven. But how shall ye loose any thing, that it may be loosed also in Heaven, since your selves for your sins are severed from Heaven, and hampred in the bands of your owne hainous offences, As Solomon saith: With the cords of his sins, every one is tyed? And with what reason shall ye binde any thing on this earth, that above this world may be likewise bound, unlesse it be your only selves, who intangled in your iniquities, are so detained on

this earth, as ye cannot ascend into Heaven, but without your conversion unto our Lord in this life, will fall downe into the miserable prison of hell? Neither yet let any Priest flatter himselfe upon the knowledge of the particular cleannenesse of his owne body, since their soules (over whom he hath government) shall in the day of Iudgement be required at his hands as the murtherer of them, if any through his ignorance, 
                  •
               loth, or fawning adulation have perished, because the stroke of death is not lesse terrible, that is given by a good man then which is inflicted by an evill person: Otherwise

would the Apostle never have said that which he left unto his successors, as a fatherly Legacy; I am cleare and cleane from the blood of all:
               
                  Act. 20.26. 
               for I have not forborne to declare unto ye al the counsell of God. Being therefore mightily drunken with the use and custome of sinnes, and extreamely overwhelmed with the waves, (as it were) of encreasing offences, seek ye now forthwith the uttermost endeavours of your mindes, (after this your shipwrake) that one borde of pennance, which is onely left, whereby ye may escape and swimme to the land of the living, that from yee may be turned away the wrath of our Lord,

who saith: I will not the death of a sinner:
               
                  Ezec. 33.11 
               but that he may bee converted and live. And the same Almighty God, of all consolation and mercy preserve his few good Pastors from all evill, and (the common enemy being overcome) make them free inhabitants of the heavenly City of Ierusalem, which is the congregation of all Saints, grant this, O Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghost, to whom be honor and glory, world without end, Amen.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

