
   
      
         
            A neaste of vvaspes latelie found out and discouered in the Law-Countreys, yealding as sweete hony as some of our English bees
            Goddard, William, fl. 1615.
         
         
            
               1615
            
         
         Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01794
            STC 11929
            ESTC S123090
            24145368
            ocm 24145368
            27248
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01794)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27248)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1817:12)
         
         
            
               
                  A neaste of vvaspes latelie found out and discouered in the Law-Countreys, yealding as sweete hony as some of our English bees
                  Goddard, William, fl. 1615.
               
               [58] p.   
               
                  Printed in the Low-Countreyes,
                  At Dort :
                  1615.
               
               
                  In verse.
                  "To the reader" signed: Will. Goddard.
                  Signatures: A⁴(-A1) B-G⁴ H².
                  Imperfect: signature H2 lacking.
                  Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Epigrams, English.
            
         
      
      
         
            2003-10
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-11
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-12
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2003-12
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2004-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A NEASTE OF VVASPES LATELIE FOVND out and discouered in the Lawcountreys, yealding as sweete hony as some of our English bees.
            
            
               AT DORT▪
                Printed in the Low-countreyes. 1615.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE Reader.
            
               GIve roome hoe; giue roome to my actiue penn
               Oh giue hir roome; sheel laie about hir then.
               Mistake hir not; she plaies noe fencers parte,
               Shee plaies the Popes; sheel make the whole world smarte.
            
            
               Will. Goddard.
            
         
         
            
            THE COMMISSION.
            
               A Broade my Waspes, in to the world goe flie
               make knowne your natures to all men you spie
               Searche eu'ry creeke; goe flie you round aboute
               let noe wretche rest vntil y'aue found him out,
               And hauinge found him, styng him: None forbeare
               but stinge em all, for all growne wicked are,
               My Loue excepte, at which, if some repine
               saie thinges you muste not touche that are devine
            
         
      
      
         
            
            AN EPIGRAM TO my Epigrams.
            
               1
               
                  MVsicke strike-vp, some livelie quick Iigg plaie
               Hange tunes that runne on malencollie kaie.
               Skippe nowe my verse: light Epigrams come skipp.
               Like doe on lawne, come light and nimblie tripp
               Like Catt with mouse come sporte you swiftlie faste
               But see like catt you pinche and nipp at laste.
            
            
               
               2
               My sences standes amaz'd, my hands doe tremble
               To think to what I should my loue resemble,
               Compare hir to the rose; hir cryimson die
               Is farr more pure; hir white excells the Ivorie,
               Vnto hir skynn rug'd is the smoothest Iett
               The softest downe to it is counterfett
               With in hir faces circute there are plac'd,
               Two heaunlie sonns, by whom the world is grac'd,
               Whose golden beames from-of hir lippes exhales,
               That hunnye dewe which Poets Nectar calls
               Soe faire is shee, soe sweete, smooth, soft, soe cleere
               As on this Earthe naught like hir maie appeare,
               Oh what a Matchles Mistresse haue I caught
               That iustlie cann compare hir vnto naught
            
            
               3
               Some men Ill censures Had-land; calls him Asse
               Idle Goose. Vppon him most men passe
               
                  But not so much for selling of his townes
               As vainelie spending and consuming's crownes
               For that a foole hee's held. Nowe I'me of mind,
               A wiser man a man shall hardlie find
               Who hath a crowne; I but one crowne enioies
               Must haue a thowsand cares. Cares Crownes annoies
               
                  Then Hadland's wise, the other Coxcombes are,
               
               
                  For whoo'd keepe crownes since one Crowns full of care.
               
            
            
               4
               For making, speede, pace, and firie spright
               The braue proude Couser should the court delight
               His gentle gesture, milde-sterne-statelie grace
               Maie gett him loue (I graunt) in eury place
               That hee's respected I nere wonder why
               It is at Th' Asse; at Asses wonder I
               Noe worthe's in th'asse, yet daubd' hee is in gold
               And trickt-vp trymmer then proude Iennetts bold
               
                  At which I musd aud wondred, vntill when
               
               
                  I found th' Asse deare and neare to most great men.
               
            
            
               
               5
               Had I commaund at Court I would casseere
               Both all the porters and doore-keepers there
               They let too manie beggars in. Tis seene
               Ev'n in the presence there some beggars beene
               
                  Amend it Porters; tis noe seemlie thing
               
               
                  To haue to manie beggars nere the Kinge.
               
            
            
               6
               At Court a Beggar to a Porter came
               Ope doore quoth hee, I am one cripled lame
               The porter annsweres sirrah gett you gone
               This is the Court, of Beggars here coms none
               
                  Then lett mee in quoth hee and make noe doubt
               
               
                  Twill scarce a courte be shut your beggars out.
               
            
            
               
               7
               A chattring Ape mett with a gruntling hogg
               Hogg quoth the Ape beware the may stife dogg
               Oh Ape quoth th'hogg, hard, oh hards my case
               For I doe meete with Doggs in eurye place
               Dost soe replies the Ape? What wilt thou giue
               And I will teache thee howe shalt feareles live
               Forsake thy stie and to the lyons Court
               From thy base contrye howse doe thou resort
               Noe Dogg soe hardie is as once to dare
               Presume to make his bold appearaunce there
               For the braue lyons nature will not brooke
               Vppon a churlish surlie Curr to looke
               Beasts of my nature like his nature beste
               His frownes wee turne to smiles with some sleight iest
               To see vs leape, skipp, make an antik face▪
               
               
                  first wonn vs apes in to the lyons grace
               
                  And therefore hogg I do wish thee take my shape
               
               
                  the lyon fauours well the toying ape▪
                  
               
            
            
               8
               Clownus would court it, nowe his countrye seate
               Hee halfe doth loathe, in cloathes hee groweth neate
               Dust here mee Clowne for that life thart vnfitt
               Thy want's a braine; whose there must want noe witt
               Hee that would court-it, in the Court would thrive
               Must sympathize in nature with these five
               In youth hee must bee Ape and Monkey both
               The Ape to Imytate what others doth
               And like the Monkey hee in lust must burne:
               Must stand readye; prick-on at eurye turne
               The Foxes nature hee in age must haue:
               Must plott. None riseth like your deepe-sculd knaue
               Like more beastes yet hee must be: doe you heare?
               He must turne Asse; great mēs greate loads must beare
               must be an OX: must hugg who gives the horne
               Tis noe disgrace for favours no we thare worne
               
                  
                  Clowne, bee still a Clowne, whood chaunge maulie shape
               
               
                  To be an ox, fox, monkey, Asse or Ape?
               
            
            
               9
               A Foole t'a wiseman came, Wiseman quoth hee
               Ive beene with Fortune who hath blessed mee
               My sonne sayde Fortune, thus I blesse thy birthe
               Thou shalt euioye the happy'st life on earthe
               Thou shalt haue Wealth ease, mirth: thou shalt liue free
               Live where thou wilt shalt neuer envy'd bee
               Nor shall Mistrust attend thee. Crosse the seas:
               for sake the Court; I doe child what you please
               Yet it shall like: it shall give noe distaste
               Thy deedes thy mother Fortune will haue graste
               with that about shee turnd hir, groping-out
               To find hir wheel; which found, she turnd about
               Allotting mee all pleasures on the earthe
               You, life envide: Mistruste poysning your mirth
               
                  Come Wiseman then; come marcht in rank with mee
               
               
                  The daungers lesse, yet honourd more you see
               
            
            
               
               10
               A godlie Father of the romishe sect
               A privie and ahogstie would erect
               Workman saide hee looke on this logg of wood
               For those two purposes me thinkes 'tis good
               The workman seeing tw'ould not serue the turne
               Cry'd sir▪ this is not good enoughe to burne
               Howe not to burne the zealous father cries?
               Noe not to burne the Carpenter replies:
               It is such rotten stuff t'wil not bewrought
               It is soe knottie ruf tis good for naught
               Come come the papiste cries thou wantest witt
               Ile haue a god made ant; Ile kneele to it
               To it Ile praie: foe will I guild-it ore
               As all that see't shal't for a god adore.
               What will not make a privie, godes will make
               For that vse, of the rottenst thinges wee take
               
                  Therefore to make my privie finde some good
               
               
                  And Ile wake godes of this my rotten wood.
               
            
            
               
               11
               Before his Holines three sutors came
               The firste was one giv'n all to whore and game
               The second vnto drinke was givn-ore soe
               As sober to his bedde he'ed neuer goe
               The third a murthrer was giv'n all toth stabb
               These comming to that babalonian drabb
               (after greate revrence to his sacred knee)
               They humblye craue that they might pardond be
               Your sinns are greate his holines doth crie
               Wee doe confesse it father they replie
               But as our sinns are greate our meanes is greate
               Father quoth they with anngells wee haue mett
               Which anngells told vs that yov lou'd em soe
               As anie thinge for theire sweete sakes youd doe
               Therefore, for what w'aue done, wee mercie craue
               For those good Anngells sakes letts perdon haue
               
                  Pleades Angells for you quoth the Pope? naie then
               
               
                  I must for give. Anngells haue powre o're men.
               
            
            
               
               12
               Ide haue a plaie could I but to my mind
               Good actors gett; but thats'not now to find
               For (oh) thare dead; this age afordeth none,
               Good actors all longe since are dead and gone
               For beggars parte a Courtyer I would haue
               A Courtyers parte your scoller act-would braue
               You souldyer should your scoller act. But yit
               To plaie the king lie parte hee is more fitt
               Nowe for the foole I haue an exlent one
               Oh for that parte giue mee your merchancts sonne
               To act the whore; tutt thats a common parte
               Eache girle of twelue yeares old can do'ot with arte
               But oh the Diuell! I am graueld nowe
               To finde a Divell out I knowe not howe
               And with out one my plaie shall nere comeforth
               For with out Divells, plaies are nothing worth
               
                  Mas I haue thought of one for gold heel come
               
               
                  An exlent actor is the Pope of Roome,
               
            
            
               13
               Fryer quoth the Divelles thou standst my freind
               Im'e caste awaie; my daies are at an end
               
                  Nowe god defend the fryer saithe; for then
               Wee fryars should bee left fatherles poore men
               As for my frendshipp, doubt mee of noe evill
               Faithfull fryers nere falfe-are to the divell
               Therefore make knowne your case; be bold, reveale
               Our order can your secretts best conceale
               Then knowe it fryer, in loue, in loue I am
               To thee for counsell in that case I came
               A Nunn I loue, without I haue'a Nunn
               Tell all the world the Divell is vndone
               
                  Loue you a Nunn? a Nunn ist you desire
               
               
                  Take my shape on you; Nunns deneys noe fryer.
               
            
            
               14
               At hells wide gates a souldyer once did stand
               His reason was to veiwe th'infernall band
               But as hee lea'nd to see eache troope passe by
               Hee taken-was and doubted for some spie
               What makst thou here? what art the divell cryes?
               A Martialliste; a souldyer hee replies
               The multitude of Monkes and fryers there
               At name of souldyer, thus cry'de-out with feare
               Oh divell, if thou dost loue vs convaie
               That souldyer hence: withs passe pack him awaie
               
                  In quiet else wee nothing here shall doe
               Theil vse our gods, our holie sisters too
               And therefore out with him, tis fowle abuse
               Yf anie but oue selues doe those things vse
               This is the Cloister we allotted are
               Therefore from vs all souldyers out debarr
               Children the Divell cry'd yf it bee soe
               That hee's a souldyer: hath naught with mee to doe
               Nor I with him. God did ordaine theire birth
               Not hell to trouble, but to vex the earthe
               My charge lies heere: their'es on the earthe: both hath
               A charge to shewe men our greate Maisters wrath
               Souldyers, mens bodies are to fall vppon
               I, on the soule, to see sharpe tortures done
               Who for theire paines in heaun aboue must dwell
               And I for mine, belowe in this darke hell
               And therefore out hee shall, too's heaun Ile send him
               Which yf hee likes not else where lett himmend him
               
                  Soe out from hell the souldyer straight was throwne
               
               
                  Since when in hell a souldyer nere was knowne.
               
            
            
               15
               I praie tell mee my fortune sir: I am
               A Beggar wench; to you for that I cam
               
                  A beggar wench the Fortune-teller cryes?
               Indeed' I am the beggar-wench replies
               Then knowe it wench quoth hee thy Fortunes good
               And these three babes shal springe from thy base bloud
               Two bratts one beggar shall begett of thee
               Both of them Kinghts and both shall Courtyers bee
               Naie yet an other sonn thou shalt emoye
               A Iugler shall begett of thee a boie
               This shall a lawyer bee, and shall in tyme
               With's Iugliug tricks vp to high turretts clime
               Thou hearst thy Fortune wench: be gone quoth hee
               It Ioies mee much, I thank you for't quoth shee
               Yet ere I doe departe praie lett mee craue
               Yf these bee all the sonns I'me like to haue
               For trulie sir my mynd doth give me yit
               I shall haue one son more; who shall in wirt
               And valour th'rest as farr surpasse
               As steedes in couradge doe the sillie Asse
               My mind doth giue me sir I shall bring forth
               A sprightfull souldyer one of matchles worth
               
                  A souldyer whore quothe hee? out baggadg base
               
               
                  A souldyer cannot spring from beggars race.
               
            
            
               16
               Plorus your wise let tenn—in one night
               One of those tenn you knowes the Parsons right
               
                  Why pay't him then; thou knowst a barlie strawe
               Will make a parish parson goe to lawe
               
                  Paye him his—oh pry thee lett him ha'te
               
               
                  Lesse thinges then—will stirr them to debate,
               
            
            
               17
               Tis saide that Idelnes doth mischeefe breed
               And soe it doth; that sayings true indeed
               Then Parish parsons you are nowe a daies
               The onelie men that doe deserue best praise
               For lawyers would growe Idle, did not you
               Stirr your parish to sett them taskes to doe
               A blessed worke; a deed well worthy noate
               A thing befitting best, men of your coate
               
                  I doe applande the deede; and lawyers shall
               
               
                  Stand bare to you, shall you theire maisters call.
               
            
            
               18
               Benefio, benefis, benefit
               Ide conster thus yf I should English it
               I doe well; so's englisht benefio
               Benefis, a benefize to buy ho
               
                  For though I'ue neither learning nor goodwitt
               
               
                  Yet buy a benefice Ile benefitt.
               
            
            
               
               19
               Oh Deate th'art wrongd! abused in our land
               Thy office Deathe is wrested out thy hand
               Vnto thy office Death it doth belonge
               T'vnloose that sacred knott god tyed soe stronge
               
                  God did ordaine thee Deathe, and onelye thee
               
               
                  T'vnloose that knot, bu't nowe more Deathes there bee.
               
            
            
               20
               A Iudge t'a surgeon came, surgeon quoth hee
               My arme is sore, what ist soe payneth mee?
               The surgeon looking on it, sir hee cryes
               Oh much corruption in your arme there lies
               
                  A poore man by, cryes surgeou vnderstand
               
               
                  T'is not in's arme, corrupted is his hand.
               
            
            
               21
               A Bedrid man before a Iudge was brought
               The Iudge biddes stand-vp sirrah as you ought
               Oh sir, nor goe, nor sitt, nor stand can I
               I am your freind praie give me leaue to lie
               
                  Art thou my freind quoth hee? then lie thy fill
               
               
                  a Iudg gives all his freindes leaue to lie still.
               
            
            
               
               22
               Were I to choose a Captaine, I would than
               Not choose your courtyer or a youth full man
               Noel would choose a Iudge; one grym and graue
               To make a Captaine such a man Id'e haue
               
                  Giue mee that man whose frowning browe is deathe
               
               
                  I such a one as cann kill men with breathe.
               
            
            
               23
               Younge Lawyers Cubs (spruse studentes termd by some)
               To you as humble sutor I doe come
               My sute is this you'l send mee from yovr Inns
               Some of you old slye-pated foxes skynns
               Weel make drumms heades of them: in doinge soe
               I knowe by th'eares our foes and we shal goe
               
                  Praie send vs some; wee all will thank you then;
               
               
                  I knowe theire skynns to braules will stirr-vp men.
               
            
            
               24
               Clarke quoth the Coun sellor I must ride downe
               What shall I doe, ther'es not one horse in towne?
               Why sir replies the Clarke, that is noe lack
               In steed of horse bestride some Clyentes back
               
                  Although an Asse vn seemelie is in showe
               Yet hee treades sure, and whipp him on, heel goe
               
                  Bestride a Clyent sir, hee shall not tire
               
               
                  Il'e spurr him on, vnto your owne desire.
               
            
            
               25
               A Woman to a Lawyer came, sir quoth shee
               Beseeche your doe a fauour vnto mee
               What wouldst thou haue the man a lawe replies?
               O sir your helping hand the good wife cryes
               For god sake sir quoth shee let me entreate
               Youl make my husbandes smale thing very great
               
                  The saie of nothing lawyers can great matters make
               
               
                  Therefore I praie sir this thing vndertake.
               
            
            
               26
               A Chauncery Clyent hauing spent his summs
               Vnto a vsring broker sneaking comes
               Broker saide hee t'is told me by a freind
               That you vppon a sute good gold will lend
               I haue a sute, faire, stronge, but verye deare
               One that I've worne almost this twentie yeare
               Which yet is freshe as when I firste did weare-it
               
                  T'will weare-out me'till I've noe strengh to beare it.
               A sute soe lastinge stronge thother replies?
               Ile deale for it: where is it sir hee cries?
               Why in the Chauncrye replies the clowne
               There carelely my sutes throwne vp and downe
               And therefore praie sir ridd me oft: The saie
               Men of your trade soone ridd mens sutes awaie
               
                  The Broker scornfullie from him goes forth
               
               
                  And tells him those old sutes are little worth.
               
            
            
               27
               An old bald-pated graue graie-bearded sire
               Stole to a wench to quench his lustes desire
               shee askt him what profession hee might bee
               I am a Civell lawyer girle quoth hee
               A Civell lawyer sir? you make mee muse
               Your talkes too broade for cyvell men to vse
               
                  Yf Civell lawyers are such bawdy men
               
               
                  Oh what (quoth shee) are other lawyers then?
               
            
            
               28
               Take leases ho. You that haue hansome wiues
               Good husbandes plaie, take leases for theire lives
               For If your wives but faire and hansom bee
               
                  Phisitians will warrant em for yee
               If they but feele theire pulse, then doubt noe lives
               Il'e warrant you theile warrannt then your wiues
               
                  By arte to women they cann put in life
               
               
                  He'es sure to gett that letts them warrants' wife.
               
            
            
               29
               Three sortes of Folkes there are which haue a trick
               Gold out of men and womens tailes to pick
               Your Panda'rs one, the second of these three
               Is one which nightlie scoures things priuylee
               
                  Ide name the third and last sorte of these men
               
               
                  But all Phisitians I should anger then.
               
            
            
               30
               Lye thus (the Fencer cryes,) thus must you guard
               Thus must you slipp, thus poynte, thus passe, thus ward
               And yf youd kill him sir, this trick learne then
               With this same trick you maie kill manie men
               A Doctor standing by, cryes Fencing Foole
               Both you and hee, to mee, maie come to schoole
               
                  Thou dost' but prate: my deedes shall showe my skill
               
               
                  Where thou hurtst one, a hundred I do kill.
               
            
            
               
               31
               If warrs should cease &amp; tyme of peace should growe
               I would Phisitian turne: that course Id'e goe
               Soe might I keepe my handes in vre; and still
               Some one or other eu'rye daie might kill
               
                  Oh Ide growe subtill, I would learne the trick
               
               
                  To make a sick man sound, a sound man sick.
               
            
            
               32
               Are you returnd my waspes? I cannot see
               Howe manie men soe soone should stinged bee
               This world is spacious wide: tis roundlie large
               Soe soone then howe could you my charge discharge
               
                  
                  Therefore abroade againe; aboute goe seeke
               
               
                  I loue to see men arie, t'heare women shreeke▪
                  
               
            
            
               33
               Tis saide of roringe boies ther'es manie theeues
               (Hees in the truthe I thinke which soe beleeues)
               Yet I doe think more witches are of them
               Then are of anie other sortes of men
               
                  My reason's this (I feare I shall bee bangd)
               
               
                  Cause alwaies ther'es as manie burnd as hangd▪
                  
               
            
            
               34
               Hee that hath wealth tis fitt that hee should haue
               A lock on's trunck, his gold and wealth to saue
               But he in whose pate there remaines noe witt
               Me thinkes a lock on his pate is vnfitt
               
                  Then Rorers why doe you weare such huge locks▪
                  
               
               
                  Your heades are poore. Of with them with a pox.
               
            
            
               35
               Hath hee in question beene for pursing crymes?
               Scap te sargants handes, the hangmans twentie tymes
               
                  Hath hee on whores consumd his landes and stock?
               Beene brought to bedd, deliv'red of the pock?
               Lost'es haire from's heade? loste th'ead of you know what?
               Yf he those scapes haue had, and hath loste that
               
                  Oh praie then let him passe: lett him enioye
               
               
                  This famous title; yon's a Roringe boie.
            
            
               36
               Wouldst thou turne Rorer boye? wouldst growe in fashon
               Learne this garbe then, shalt gaine faire reputation
               Tobacco take; run in each mercers score
               Visit plaies, be seene to court thy whore
               Laughe at learning; call preachers sheepishe men
               schollers asses: stick not nowe and then
               To censure deedes of Kinges. Naie gainst gods deytie
               Be bold to belche forth broadest blasphemie
               Must keepe a cattalogue: must haue the name
               Of eurye merchannts wife which is of fame
               Must slannder all; the fairest dames muste staine
               Must saie with conntesses, with queenes thast laine
               Muste bee noe coward: thy selfe must proudlie carye
               Muste mouthe-it stoutelie in eache ordynarye
               Where, yf but of thy losses thy tongue walke
               
                  Muste of noe lesse a losse then hundreds talke
               Must learne to lie; muste learne thy lie to face
               And lastelie howe to sweare God dam the: with a grace
               
                  Learne these younge boie, great man thou shalt be then.
               
               
                  Who doe these Ill thinges well must needes bee men.
               
            
            
               37
               Furious Hott-spurr, a reason pry thee yeild
               Why thou soe fighst; why thou goste soe in feild
               Ist' after bloude thy drye soule soe doth thriste?
               Remember Cayn howe god that murthrer curste
               But tell me Hott-spurr, wherein doste thou gaine
               When thou in feilde thy euemye haste slaine?
               Thy venter's muche: Ift' bee but to gett bloude
               Then tell mee (being gott) wherefore ist good?
               Thou canst not canst? I tell thee thou vaine goose
               Thou hazardst bodie howe thy soule to loose
               This bloud once spilte doth not like bodies die
               But that reviues and vp to th'eauns doth fllie
               Where to the lord it pointes out that black deed
               Crying-out for vengeanc, vengeance lord with speed
               
                  Foole sheathe thy sworde; avoide fond privat braules
               
               
                  Our blades should sleepe vntill our countrie calles.
               
            
            
               
               38
               Gooden-dagh Butter-boxe: I vnderstand
               Thou dost in-habitt in the Netherland
               I pry thee Smeere-chopps doth not he which buyes
               A thing cald wife there, paie for hir excise?
               Who buyes an ox, a cowe, or such like beaste
               Paies for hir hornes, hide, flleshe, excise at leaste
               Hee knowes not when shees bought: beside the Boore
               He must betall the gelt to twentie more
               
                  I pry thee Butter-boxe make mee so wise
               
               
                  As knowe, yf men maie wiue, not paie excise.
               
            
            
               39
               Dutchmen should paie (yf they did paie theire due)
               A taxe for eu'rye chymney old and newe
               Then honest Dutchmen, praye nowe lett me axe
               Why for your womens tayles you paie noe taxe?
               Yf those are chymneys where folkes fyers make?
               Then your wiues tailes for chymneys I doe take
               
                  For there are Fiers, Fyers there they dailie keepe:
               
               
                  And therefore paie your dues; those chymneys sweepe.
               
            
            
               
               40
               Demaund you why or'e stoues Dutch-women sitts?
               Oh strange! praie why doe you putt meate on spitts?
               Ist' not to roste the same? nere wonder then:
               For soe they sitt to roste meate for theire men
               
                  Althoughe theire men all daie on hodgepodge eate
               
               
                  Yet in the night they cloye them with roaste meate.
               
            
            
               41
               Water they saie will not wild-fyer quench
               Then wild-fire in thy stoue thou bearst dutch-wench
               For yf by water it would quenched bee
               Then out il would; soe waterd tis by thee
               
                  But why it wil not out, I nowe doe knowe
               
               
                  Thy bellowes wench; they alwaies puff and blowe.
               
            
            
               42
               In Holland, Zealand, all the Netherlandes
               Younge men with maides (allnight) walk handes in handes
               In darkest night, to walk, they moste delight
               
                  For doinge which, some doe applaude theire sight
               
                  They neede not do't; they see as other men
               
               
                  For when tis darke they goe by feeling then.
               
            
            
               43
               A Huntsman and his Dogg did latelie come
               To the lowe countreys from theire English home
               Oh Dogg quoth hee (I speakt' with griefe of harte)
               Wee one from tother shalbe for'cd to parte
               I shall not able-bee to give thee meate
               Nowe bones and paringes I my selfe must eate
               Why sir (replies the Dogg?) I hope not soe
               I cann and will your maisters pleasure showe
               
                  Pleasure quoth hee? If thou wilt them delight
               
               
                  Thou must showe proffit Dogg, or learn to fight.
               
            
            
               44
               A messenger from the'auns was latelie sent
               T'envite poorè tradesmen vnto merryment
               Bruers, Taylors, and cookes (amongst the reste)
               Envited' were vnto that solenm feaste
               But they being verye busie annswerd thus
               Oh messenger saide they excuse thou vs
               Our leasure will not serue vs there to goe
               The Divell here on earth employes vs soe
               
                  My Country'es French the Taylor cryes: and I
               Must liue there-in else Frenchmen straight will die
               As th'ynglishe nation doe theire bellies cramm
               Soe wee our backs: To them a nurse I am
               I'me Englishe quoth the Cooke: my Nation lookes
               For naught but meate, good stomacks and good cookes
               Therefore should I to heaun; my Country men
               Could not devise howe they should surfett then
               I'me Dutch the Bruer cryes, and should I clyme
               Aboue the cloudes before prefixed tyme
               Our nations soules beneathe hells pitt would sincke
               For dead theire hartes growe when they want good drinke
               
                  Therefore tell God the Divell staies vs here
               
               
                  To keepe our nations from ascending there.
               
            
            
               45
               When Foxe-furr walkes, he treades the formalst pace
               When Foxe-furr talkes, hee talkes with grauest grace
               Hee licks not's lipps, nor pickes his fingers endes
               But to formality eache motion tendes
               In all thinges Foxe-furs formall; I, his nose
               At all times with formallitie hee blowes
               At meate (at mouthe) hee formallie breakes winde
               From meate as formallie hee breakes behind
               
                  Oh since graue Foxe-furr cann saie I and noe
               
               
                  
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      a sheere-towne Mayor maie passe I trow.
               
            
            
               
               46
               Aske Crafte the Merchante whether hee doth walke;
               Why to th'exchaunge quoth hee t'exchaunge some talke
               Askes' ietting wife; his lisping prettie bride
               To what greene banck that golden snake doth slide
               Shee lispes-out, to my garden trulie sir:
               
               But wott you what t'is thither draweth hir?
               Oh sir, thats hir exchaunge: shee walketh there
               Tex'change hir bodie, in the open aire
               
                  Hir prentize there, his maisters factor proues
               
               
                  And choppes such wares as merchantes wiues best loues;
               
            
            
               47
               You Sailors, yf you'l wealthy-growe, and thrive,
               Steere suche a course as you maie fairelie wiue
               Gett you but bewtious wiues, and you shall see
               Againste your comming home thei'le loaded bee
               
                  I, costom-free your merchanntes loade em will
               
               
                  And with best wares your wiues ware-howsen fill.
               
            
            
               48
               While Sea-horse gallopps ouer gulfes and sandes
               Entending to discouer vnknowne landes
               At home hee leaues his marchannt with his wife
               Who sailes with hir yet nere adventers life
               Nowe on a ruffe waues back his friggot daunceth
               Anon t'a vaultie hollowe downe it channceth
               Nowe is shee toste; anon turnd o're and ouer:
               Vnder nowe; a non shee manlie doth recouer
               &amp; thus on lande strannge straightes hee seekes to find
               Runing his course soe longe as good's his winde
               
                  In hir hee rows; but all's discou'ries 
                        〈◊〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     〈1 line〉
                  
               
            
            
               
               49
               Ther'es three thinges makes me think that cittie wiues
               Are least infected with these papiste liues
               The firste is this; they keepe noe hollidaies
               For then they are most occupyde men saies
               The second is, to see them croste t'is rare
               For Townsmens wiues but sisdom crossed are
               The third is this (this often hath beene tryde)
               Fastinge, and prayers they cannot well abide
               
                  Ill Nunns they'd make, for who of late did see
               
               
                  A London girll that did vowe chastetee?
               
            
            
               50
               A souldyer, Lawyer, and a Cytizen
               In thicke-wide Forreste (once these wandring men)
               Had loste them selues, but Fortune did provide
               For eache of these a beaste to bee his guide
               Vnto the souldyer (with a mild-maiestick grace)
               A princelie Lyon gentlye bent his pace
               Vnto the Lawyer did the subtill Foxe
               Two to the Townsman went, the Ass the Oxe
               Eache telling in theire languadge, howe that they
               Would t'eache of them a guider bee in's waie
               The firste the Lyon thankes; thother the oxe
               The Townsman thankes and followes th'Asse &amp; thoxe
               
                  But most in gratefull hee (in humane borne)
               
               
                  Robbes the mild asse ofs' witt, and th'oxe ofs' horne.
               
            
            
               51
               I'st not a braue life hoe to serue a Lorde?
               Its naught but trusse his pointes and waite ats'borde
               A man shalbee assu'rd enoughe to eate
               Yf hee catche bones which hath enough of meate
               
                  The life hath ease; a man neede ueuer stirr
               
               
                  Lesse whens Lorde—t'aske, doe you call mee sir.
            
            
               
               52
               Had I a thousand girles noe care I'de take
               For those my girles, portions to scrape or rake.
               I'de make em chamber maides; or else they should
               Bee wayting gentlewomen If I could
               
                  Were they not then card'-for? then yf they will
               
               
                  Vnder theire lordes they maie bee getting still.
               
            
            
               53
               Ist not straunge that Townsmen daielie eates
               Fatt uenison as oft as other meates?
               Noe, tis not straunge; for theire sweete wiues may haue
               As manie warrants as thei'le euer craue
               Pure soules! if they but lispe-out praye my Lord
               
               
                  Giue me a warrant; tha'ue it at firste worde
               
                  Lordes are kinde to giue; and a Cittie dame
               
               
                  To begg a warrant neuer holdes it shame
               
            
            
               54
               Nowe good sir Iohn (the beggar cryes) I praie
               Bestowe your worshipps almes on mee to daie
               Releeue my wantes quoth hee; I am your brother
               Wee borne-are one to helpe and ayde an other
               
                  My brother quoth Sr. Iohn? poore wretched wight!
               Why thou mistakest me, I am a knight
               
                  I know't quoth hee; but harke you kinde sir Iohn
               
               
                  Ther'es manie a knight kinn to the beggar man.
               
            
            
               55
               Late did I take a knight on Beggar wench
               Hee was on fire; twas shee the flame must quench
               The Beggar-wenche I askt yf shee did like
               Better with knightes, then with poore beggars strike
               
                  Faithe sir quoth shee yf I shall speake but right
               
               
                  I finde as one, the Beggar and the knight.
               
            
            
               56
               Nowe god bee with old Chuff; avouch't I cann
               That graie side-coated swadd dyed a good man
               Yet dailie heed' bee drunck: naie this is more
               The riche old churle for eache daie kept a whore
               Yet not-withstanding I doe tell noe lie
               In saying Chuff did a right goodman die
               
                  Praie speake; maie not the knight his sonn bee glad,
               
               
                  In that for father hee a good-man had.
               
            
            
               
               57
               Praie wronge not Late-coynd; giue the man his right
               Hee's made a gentleman although noe knight
               Hath hee not bought a kinghts old cloathes? why than
               
                  Late-coynd I hope is made gentleman
               For nowe tis cloathes the gentleman doth make
               Men from gaie cloathes theire pedigrees doe take
               
                  But wott you what's the armes to such mens howse
               
               
                  Why this, hands chasinge of a rampant Lowse.
            
            
               58
               What shall wee thinke nowe of the Iack-dawes state?
               Is not that Fowle becom a Potentate?
               The Eagles howse of stickes and strawes are built
               Free from vaine pompe; not burnist ore with guilt
               But Dawes haue built em howses wondrous faire
               With proude pyramides t'out-braue the aire
               
                  Blame not the Dawe to leaue base, strawes to peck:
               
               
                  You sec whose' nowe the Iacke-dawes archyrect.
               
            
            
               59
               Why laughe you at Iack-dawes? I cannot see
               But that Iacke-dawe's both wise and honest bee
               
                  Honest in this: howskeeping they vphold;
               They keepe good howses as in daies of old.
               And herein wise: Greate men greate howses make
               But Iackdawes straight possession of them take
               Thare wise and honeste, and to outward showe
               They are devoute; to Church they dailie goe
               
                  Longe maie they live. For Iack-dawes I will praie;
               
               
                  Were Iackdawes dead, howskeeping would decaie.
               
            
            
               60
               Dost heare mee Iacke-dawe? thou doste saucie growe:
               Gett better manners; learne thy selfe to knowe,
               Howe dar'st thou Iett-it to the Eagles courte?
               Thou art too bold; why there doth none resort
               But birdes of noblest partes. There doth fall
               The soring Faulcon which soe praies on all
               The Peacock with his riche embrodred plumes
               Spreades there his taile; high place he there asumes
               The Nitingall singes there, and nowe and than
               There falls a turtle Doue, a milke-white Swan
               A waie thou foolishe dawe, seeke not t'aspire
               Keepe thou thy countrye howse; perke-vp noe hire
               Or yf thou needes must change, seeke-out the Gull
               
                  
                  Cuckoe; woodcock; eache Cittie of them's full
               
                  Exchaunge with them: Cittie Cuckoes loue
               
               
                  To flie a breade: eache summer they remoue.
               
            
            
               61
               England, of Oxen, sheepe, horse, thou haste thy parte
               Likewise, with hartes, hindes, buckes; enritcht thou art
               Plentie of these thou haste: but I doe muse
               Noe more wild-bores with in thy boundes doe vse
               If Bores of hogges doe come, thou shouldst haue store
               Noe land of truer hogs had euer more
               
                  Search courte, or country; woodes or Fenny boggs
               
               
                  Alls' one, all places nowe yeildes gruntling hoggs.
               
            
            
               62
               Sir quoth a Clowne, your father (as wee saie)
               Was a good man; yet neuer went soe gaie
               His cloathes were such as howsewiues fingers spinn
               I neuer sawe him strutt it in sattyn
               Hee deed good deedes. Twas seld seene from his doore
               A man came vnreleivd' that liv'd but poore
               The Chymneys of his howse were alwaies swept
               They allwaies smoakt: that she'wd what howse hee kept
               
                  What talkst thou of his actes (younge Make-waste cries?)
               Nowe good deedes with the good deed-doer dies
               
                  Talk of my acts; I can orethrowe the oake
               
               
                  And make my nostrylls like his chymneys smoake.
               
            
            
               63
               
                  Prate-well hath courted me; hath wood my witt
               Told me for plaies it was exceeding fitt
               Would haue mee beate my braines t'instruct &amp; teache
               
                  Parrottes and Mag-pies howe on stage to preache
               Goe Epigram goe annswere thas fond woer'
               Tell him I will not: bidd him sue noe more
               Soe tell him I will teache noe cranes to stalke
               Nor clipp these Mag-pies tongues to make em talke
               
                  I am noe beareward; for doe what I can
               
               
                  I cannot make an ape to Imitate a man.
               
            
            
               64
               Goe to your plaie-howse you shall actors haue
               Your baude, your gull, your whore, your pandar knaue
               Goe to your bawdie howse, y'aue actors too
               As bawdes, and whores, and gulls: pandars also.
               Besides, in eyther howse (yf you enquire)
               
                  A place there is for men themselues to tire
               
                  Since th' are soe like, to choose ther'es not a pinn
               
               
                  Whether bawdye-howse or plaie-howse you goe in.
               
            
            
               65
               But speake I praie, who ist would gess or skann
               
                  Fantasmus to be borne a Englishe man?
               Hees hatted spanyard-like and bearded to
               Ruft Itallyon-like; pae'd like them also
               His hose and doubletts' Frenche; his bootes and shoes
               Are fashond pole in heeles, but French in toes
               
                  Oh hees compleate! what shall I descant an?
               
               
                  A compleate Foole: noe compleate Englishe man.
               
            
            
               66
               Were I a captaine and might choose my men
               Flattrers and Parrasits I would choose then
               Valyant they bee; they neuer feare the shott
               Tha're forwardst still when seruice is most hott
               They feare noe shot. Yet such men Flattrers bee
               As still yf anie scapes, they scape shott-free
               
               
                  Mistake mee not; misconster not this shott
               
               
                  Th' are shott-free, when, service in Tavern's hott.
               
            
            
               
               67
               A honest Baker latelie did espie
               A Scivner preachinge on the pillorie
               Scrivner hee saide, bequeathe thy eares to mee
               Though I can heare, yet I want eares quoth hee
               
                  Take them the serivner cryes to doe thee good
               
               
                  Oft Bakers eares or'e serivners heades haue stood.
               
            
            
               68
               Were I a gallant and could maintaine men
               Id'e haue bald-pated laddes t'attend mee then
               For men whose pates are bare and bald at topps
               Are exlent fitt to keepe Tobacco shoppes
               Two thinges vppon a bald crowne on maie doe
               That's cutt Tobacco, and well drye-it too
               
                  Theire braines are hott: theere sculls as thinn as shell
               
               
                  Lay't on the bald-place it will drye it well.
               
            
            
               69
               Souldyer (quoth a Iugler) wilt learne of mee?
               Ile' teache thee tricks; such, thou didst neuer see
               The souldyer sighes, shakes head, and annsweres thus
               
                  
                  A Las, too manye trickes are showne to vs
               Tricks on poore souldyers eu'rye Captaine putts:
               Slyghts to drawe gold from-out our shrunck-vp gutts
               
                  Tis they haue tricks, and therefore Iugling Foole
               
               
                  Yf thou't learne tricks, to them goe thou to schoole.
               
            
            
               70
               Captaine (a Seargant cryes), a souldyers dead
               What shall bee done? shall hee bee buried?
               Howe buryed man? thou dost thy office trymm
               Firste lett mee make the moste I can of him
               Aliue I made the moste of that poore man
               I'le nowe as much make of him as I can
               If his haire, fleshe, skynn is nothing worthe
               Then rypp-out's harte; his verye harte pull forth
               
                  Sell it in Spaine: Folkes of those forraine partes
               
               
                  Will giv'es good gold for our poore souldyers hartes.
               
            
            
               71
               A Scotche and Englishe-man made theire request
               Vnto the godes that they in heaun might rest
               Wee will admytt you both the Godds did crie:
               But Scotchman, vnto thee conditionallie.
               
                  Th'agreement's this; yf here wee thee estate
               Thou must not bee to bold, nor full of prate
               
                  Naie, more conditions yet; Thou must not lie
               
               
                  Nor sooth vs vp. Wee Goddes hate flatterie.
            
            
               72
               
                  Why howe nowe Waspes, are you returnd agen?
               
               
                  I knowe vnstung remaines a world of men
               
               
                  And therefore once more out; make th' other flight
               
               
                  Where yf you find noe men, on women light
               
               
                  Turne taile to them; but mark you what I tell
               
               
                  Sting them not much, too much theire flesh will swell.
               
            
            
               73
               My mistress is not light, yet shynes shee light
               Hir bewties beames appeares in darkest night
               
                  If in the darke shees light, you must confess
               A Dyamond shee is, or little less
               
                  Oh shees a Diamond; in Darke shees light
               
               
                  A tutchstone too, and tries yf thinges are right.
               
            
            
               74
               To gild the heauns, in daie, the golden sunn
               Through the cleere skie his course doth proudlie runn
               The silv'rye Moone (with thowsands spanglie lights)
               Doth likewise brnish-ore the gloomie nightes
               But th'Earth (our sullen damm) to sett hir forth
               Noe taper had vntill my mistresse birth
               
                  But since hir birth th' Earth maie with th'eauns compare
               
               
                  For to hir Lightnes they but darknes are.
               
            
            
               75
               Awaie with sicklye wenches (whitelye fac'd)
               And those whose heades with amber lockes are grac'd
               Those puling creatures are vnfit for men
               They crye tha're sick when wee haue neede of them
               Wouldst chuse-out one vnto a man most true?
               Chuse then out one of cleere deepe-sanguy'nd hue
               With black-browne haire: in whose sweete face is sett
               
                  Two sparkling lampes; yet black as blackest iett
               With dympled chynn, with lipps pure rubby-redd
               This wench a liue shalt find with in thy bedd
               I, actiue, nimble: hah; hir stirring spright
               Hates sluggishe sleepe. Loues motion all the night
               
                  Chuse suche a one; I chuse soe for my parte
               
               
                  Such, men should loue; such loue men with theire harte.
               
            
            
               66
               Oh What a bodie hath my ladie there?
               Shees straungelie stronge! what burthens shee doth beare!
               Late did a dunghill Carr vppon hir fall
               Vnder which shee laie; neuer hurt at all
               
                  Oh who but shee could liue, being soe brusht?
               
               
                  T'is wondrous strannge hir honours noe more crusht.
               
            
            
               67
               Some Ladies in noe coatch or croatche will ride
               Vnles tha're dawbd with gold, such shewes their pride▪
               
               Welfare my Ladye Constance▪
                   heaunlie starr!
               She leaues hir coatch-of to ride with a Carr
               
                  I with a dunghill Carr nowe doth shee ride
               
               
                  Oh would all Ladies were soe free from pride.
               
            
            
               
               78
               
                  Poetus with fine sonnets painteth forth
               This and that fowle ladies, bewties worth
               Hee shewes smale witt thereby; and for his paines
               (By my consent) hee neuer shall reape gaines
               
                  Why what neede Poetts painte them? oh sweet elues!
               
               
                  Why ladyes painte theire bewties best themselues.
               
            
            
               79
               When I to Court did come, I musd▪ to see
               The Lordes soe braue. It halfe amazed mee
               I did expect the most had mourners beene
               All widowers I thought I should haue seene
               
                  I did in deed: This reason fort had I
               
               
                  Cause eurye daie theire Ladies there doe die.
            
            
               80
               My Ladies teeth are alwaies extreame white
               Yet fewe knowes howe they come in that faire plight
               Shee rubbes em not with ranck tobacco ashes
               Nor with pure water, white hir fanges shee washes
               Nor ist with water as is stild from rose
               Noe hirs distild is from hir owne sweete nose.
               
                  For as the tubb receaues each dropp from spout
               
               
                  Soe doth hir mouth from hir still-dropping snoute.
               
            
            
               
               81
               When Maddam Minsitt at hir table sitts
               Shee seemes to straine to swallowe downe small bitts
               If shee but cram a larkes thighe downe hir bellie
               Shee Streakes, cryes shees soe full, shee burst-shall wellie
               Praie aske hir Foole (shee being out a sight)
               What greate bitts then must serue hir appetite
               
                  Bitts then indeed, Indeed then in hir bellie
               
               
                  Bitts of a pound hir foole doth putt-in wellie.
               
            
            
               82
               Maide quoth my Ladye (as in bedd shee lies)
               Make mee a Caudle' gainst such time I rise
               Dy Doctour saith it will doe me noe harme
               To put some thing into my bellie warme
               The maide lowe-cursey makes, and cries, forsooth
               It shall bee done; soe ambling forth shee gooth
               
                  But shee scarce gone, hir back not turned wellie
               
               
                  But th'vsher putts warme caudles in hir bellie.
               
            
            
               83
               Boye, bring my horse quoth Shift; but doe not tarye
               This meale I meane to saue an ordynarie
               
                  To daie my ladie Shift-of Ile goe see
               Who will I hope to dynner envite mee:
               Ile bring your horse his boye replies; But sir
               You'l loose your labour yf you visitt hir
               Hir Cooke for dynner nothing ready makes
               Till dinners paste shee alwaies phisick takes
               
                  Shee'l not bee seene; hir chamber shee keepes then
               
               
                  To eate, and feed, and feed, and eate agen.
               
            
            
               84
               Why should Ladye my wedd? this maradg knott
               Is knitt too faste: till deathe it looseth not
               And what are husbandes good for? faith d'yee heare
               For nothing after firste or second yeare
               Therefore my ladyes wise: with out controule
               (To please hir bodie) shee maie damm hir soule▪
               
               An vsher shee maie haue nowe to hir mind
               Nowe vnto what hir Ladishipps enclind
               shee nowe maie haue; hir page to come at call
               A wanton monkey else to sport with all
               Him maie shee stroake, laie in hir lapp, make fatt
               Doe anie thing with him; yet what a that
               Nowe maie shee ride, walke, daunce, kisse, laughe, lie downe
               What maie shee not doe nowe? noe threatring frowne
               
                  Noe austeere looke, noe angry bended browe
               Apales hir cheekes. Shees free, lives fearles nowe
               
                  My Ladyes wise; there is noe mary'd wife
               
               
                  Such pleasure takes as shee in single life.
               
            
            
               85▪
               
               My ladyes verdingall is wondrous wide
               But what a that? shee wear'st not soe for pride
               Indeed shee doth not sir. yet yf you'd knowe
               Why'boute hir bumm soe hudge a hoope doth goe
               Ile tell it you. Praie sweet sir vnderstand
               Shee for a maide doth goe, as yet vn mand
               By vertue of hir vardingall, shee (wellye)
               Doth make poore men beleeue shee hath noe bellie
               
                  A rare trick tis: Greate wastes twill make seeme small
               
               
                  And bellies barrell-bigg, seeme naught at all.
               
            
            
               86
               My ladye learnes hir little page to skipp
               I lie Infaith for tis my Ladies whipp
               But why think you my Ladye takes such paines
               To borrowe from Nedds britch such crimson staines
               Oh Nedd did see lie at my Ladies back
               
                  My Ladyes Freind, of which did Edward clack
               
                  Who can excuse the boie? waggs sworne toth smock
               
               
                  should from their tongues such secrett secretts lock.
               
            
            
               87
               A Cannon-shaken souldyer lame-lie legd'
               Late of a braue Court ladie boldlie begd
               Madam (the souldyer cried) praie give releife
               Vnto a man dismembred full of greife
               
                  Wantst members knaue quoth shee? oh hang thee then
               
               
                  Wee ladies nere releiue dismembred men.
               
            
            
               88
               If you were wise then would you nere ask why
               My Ladyes womans tayle soe oft doth crie
               Alas hir vardingales' a doore soe wide
               As it letts more winde in then t'can abide
               
                  And thats the cause (Indeed I doe not lie)
               
               
                  Which makes my Ladies womans taile soe crie.
               
            
            
               89
               Page (quoth my Ladie) goe shitt the doore. The wind
               Whispers to lowde: a Tyrant tis I find
               
                  And therefore shitt boye shit; shitt-too the doore
               Tis good lett badd guests out, but in noe more.
               T'vnhappie wagg (fraught with a knauish witt)
               Cryes, Maddam, tis not my office doores to shitt
               
                  Praie bidd your gentlewoman doo't: hir face
               
               
                  Doth looke as yf shee would shit eurie place.
               
            
            
               90
               By wans wise pollicie it hath beene found
               That beastes (though nere soe strōge) are alwaies bound
               The hudge greate Elaphaunt, the Maystiff Curr
               By men are bound; both made they dare not sturr
               The princelie lyon by man's speciall witt
               Is forcd with mildnes in his denn to sit
               But womens nere chain'd tongues (beastes smale to th'eye)
               Mans moste engenious witt could neuer tie
               
                  Oh men I nere shall hold you trulie wise
               
               
                  Vntill to hold them engynns you devise.
               
            
            
               91
               Thinges that are bitter, bittr'er then gall
               Phisitians holdeth to bee phisicall
               Then womens tonges mee thinkes to powder beaten
               
                  Must needes bee soe, yf as a potion eaten
               Nothing more bittir is. Therefore I muse
               Why they in physick womens tongues nere vse
               
                  Faithe prove them Doctors: vse them in a pill:
               
               
                  Thinges oft helpe sick men which doe sound men kill.
               
            
            
               92
               A Revr'end Iudg sitting to rite mens wronges
               Cōmaundmēt gaue that all should hold theire tongues
               At which as dumb a while the Audyence satt
               Vntill a woman with hir taile gann chatt
               Why who talkes there (the rev'rend father cries?)
               All hold theire tongues (graue Iudge) the men replies
               Onelie a woman troubled here with wind
               Vnto hir self (wee thinke) doth breake hir mind
               
                  Indeed quoth hee to much it is to doe
               
               
                  T'make women hold theire tailes and their tongues too.
               
            
            
               93
               Naie trulie husband, praie nowe husband cease
               Perswasions cannot moue and therefore peace
               Haue not I saide I will not? shewing why
               A leadging this stronge reason too, For I
               
               
                  
                  Mee thinkes such reasons might' perswade a man
               
               
                  When wee saie Will not, rockes moues sooner than.
               
            
            
               94
               In Bedd a younge man with his old wife laie
               Oh wife quoth hee Iv'e lett a thing to daie
               By which I feare I am a looser much
               His wife replies, youthes bargaines still are suche
               
               Soe turning from him (angrie at hir harte)
               Shee vn-awares letts-out a thundring—
               Oh wife quoth hee noe looser I am nowe
               A marles greate sauer I am made by you
               
                  Younge men that old wiues haue neede neuer sell
               
               
                  Because old wiues (quoth hee) letts things soe well,
               
            
            
               95
               A proper man which late had loste that Iointe
               Which men ymprysons with a cod peece pointe
               Vnto a widowe came; widowe quoth hee
               My wealthe is greate; speake, wilt thou marrie me?
               Aboute my howse, faire goodlie pastures haue I
               My feildes are large; by which much money saue I
               Cowes haue I store; and though men should not prize
               
                  Theire owne true worthes; yet all men hold mee wise
               Nor witt nor wealth I want your loue to merritt
               I am noe waie defective but in spiritt
               
                  Ist spright you want? want you a spright quoth shee?
               
               
                  Know't▪ were you lord of th' Earthe you gett and mee.
               
            
            
               96
               Wouldst learne to woe? a Fawkner learne to bee
               Wild hawkes by watching are made tame you see:
               Soe must thou watch thy wench; what though she'es wild?
               Yet watch hir well shalt rule hir as a child
               
                  I, caste hir of; yet hold thou vp thy lure
               
               
                  Then stoope shee will: I, downe shee will be sure.
               
            
            
               97
               Lisba hath manlie partes; you shall not find
               A wenche on th'Earthe that beares a manliere mind
               A wrasler she'es; she'el trye a fall with anie
               A Fencer she'es; shath channgd a thrust with manie
               An Archer she'es; shee laies-well to a marke
               Drawes home a shaft; nockt right too in the darke
               
                  S'hath yet more partes; in parte a souldyers shee
               
               
                  sheel fight, whore, drinke, vntill shee cannot see.
               
            
            
               
               98
               When rich mens wiues are dead (to couer them)
               They vse t'haue marble stones laide over them
               Since t'is an anncyent custome I much muse
               Why Harts-head thou dost not that custom vse
               Thy wife was tall, fayre, wittie: such a one
               As in hir life would not haue lackt a stone
               Therefore Hartes-head, t'eternize hir good name
               Laie ore hir one, write this vppon the same
               
                  Here lies one dead vnder this marble stone
               
               
                  Which when shee liv'd laye vnder more then one.
               
               Vppon hir stone write this: yet dost thou heare
               At name of stone sheel rise againe I feare.
            
            
               99
               
                  Smale-witt loues a woman▪ oh wonder straunge!
               But wherefore think you? world tis time you channge
               Tis tyme; tis high time that you were renewd
               When men think women virtuoustie endewd
               Aske him why hee loues hir, vp go'es eyes
               For virtue, For hir virtue sir he cries
               
               It is hir virtue onelie (sir saith hee)
               That hath soe sence-charmd and soe rauisht mee
               
                  Women virtuous? oh straunge vnheard of Iest▪
               
               World World; thy latter age it seemes proues best
               Fond' Smale witt nowe gives not his loue hot chace
               As others doe, onelie for flesh and case
               But for hir virtue; tis for hir virtues sake
               That makes young Smale-witt that chace vndertake
               
                  Nowe god be'es speed; praie god the youth maie wynn hir
               
               
                  But's chaunce is rare yf hee findes virtue in hir.
               
            
         
         
            Conclusion.
            
               100
               Clere-eyd bright Titan allwaies blusheth redd
               When he beetakes him to his Thetis bedd
               The youth full livelie god in glowing flame
               Sitts and lies downe as yf surprisd with shame
               
                  But man, oh shameles man! t'is cause hee spies
               
               
                  In's daie-runn course, thy daie-done villanies.
               
            
            
               101
               My Epigrams make their encrease as men
               As Fathers getteth sonns, soe sonns getts sonns agen
            
            
         
      
   

