
   
      
         
            A breve cronycle of the Bysshope of Romes blessynge and of his prelates beneficiall and charitable rewardes. from the tyme of Kynge Heralde vnto this daye.
            Gybson, Thomas, d. 1562.
         
         
            
               1548
            
         
         Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01706
            STC 11842A
            ESTC S103090
            99838847
            99838847
            3236
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01706)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3236)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 49:12)
         
         
            
               
                  A breve cronycle of the Bysshope of Romes blessynge and of his prelates beneficiall and charitable rewardes. from the tyme of Kynge Heralde vnto this daye.
                  Gybson, Thomas, d. 1562.
               
               [16] p.   
               
                  By [R. Wyer for] Iohn Daye, dwellyng in Sepulchres parish at the signe of the Resurrection a lytle aboue Holbourne Conduite. Cum priuilegio regali, ad imprimendum solum,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  [1548?]
               
               
                  By Thomas Gybson.
                  In verse.
                  Actual printer's name supplied and publication date conjectured by STC.
                  Signatures: A.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2008-01
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-02
            John PasSampled and proofread
         
            2008-02
            John PasText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A breue Cronycle of the Byſſhope of Romes bleſſynge, and of his Prelates beneficiall and charitable rewardes, from the tyme of Kynge Heralde vnto this daye.
            ¶Imprinted at London by Iohn Daye, dwellyng in Sepulchres pariſh at the ſigne of the Reſurrection a lytle aboue Holbourne Conduite.
            ¶Cumpriuilegio Regali, Ad imprimendum ſolum.
         
         
            
            ¶ The preface.
            WHo lyſt to loke aboute
            May ī Cronicles ſoon fīde out
            what ſedes the Popyſſhe route
            In England hath ſowen
            Becauſe the tyme is ſhorte
            I ſhall bryuely reporte,
            And wryte in dewe ſorte
            Therin what I haue knowen.
         
      
      
         
            
               
               ¶Kynge Herolde.
               IN the tyme of Herolde the Kynge
               Robert of cāterbury had his banyſhinge
               Ye may be ſure for no good lyuynge
               That euer man harde ſaye
               To Wyllyam Conqueror the byſhop went
               To whom Alexander a banner ſent
               Of clene remyſſion theyr wycked entent
               Was Englande to dekaye.
            
            
               ¶William conqueror.
               THe abbeys of Englande great &amp; ſtoute
               This kynge cauſed to be ſerched oute
               The money there founde all rounde aboute
               Was brought to the kynges treaſure
               The byſhop of canterbury with many mo
               And dyuers abbottes were depryued alſo
               And were made quōdams ye may well know
               For no good demenure.
            
            
               ¶William the ſeconde.
               WIth william ye .ii. what ſtryfe dyd make
               Byſhop Ancelme &amp; howe ſtoute a crake
               
                  Made Rafe of checheſter for the trybutꝭ ſake
               For women that prieſtes dyd paye
               This kynge in poſeſſion had certayne
               The byſhoprycke of cāterbury &amp; dyd retayne
               Wynton and Sarum in his full mayne
               Tyll the houre of his death.
               The abbays he ſolde or to farme dyd lette
               The ſtyffe necked prelates he vnder kepte
               And with theyr popery he euer mette
               So longe as he had brethe.
            
            
               ¶Henry the fyrſte.
               ALrelme alſo dyd lykewyſe crake
               With Henry the fyrſt &amp; out dyd ſhake
               Moche diſobediens, and woulde not forſake
               To withſtande the kynges wyll.
            
            
               ¶Stephyn.
               By a falſe othe lyghtly taken
               Of wyllm̄ of cāterbury ſtephen was not forſaken
               Kynge of Englande, but ſhortly ſhaken
               Or his mynde he could fulfyll.
            
            
               ¶Henry the ſeconde.
               
                  THat poyſon prelate Thomas becked
               A ſaynt by name, but wt treaſon decked
               And with popery all to ſpecked
               To his later ende,
               Proude and ſtoberne in all aſſayes
               with ye neuer, but euer with nayes
               His prynce to withſtande thus he alwayes
               His mynde dyd fully bende.
            
            
               ¶Rycharde the fyrſte.
               TO the holy lande archbyſhop baldwyne
               Of canterbury went full fyne
               The kynge taryed not longe behyne
               But thether alſo went
               And not without the pryuie councell
               Of the byſhoppes yf I dare it tell
               That they myght rule and beare the bell
               Was theyr full entent,
               Tharche byſhoppe of yorke alas alas
               Was the kyngꝭ brother who endly dyd pas
               His lyfe of byſhoppes as the maner was
               Nowe it is not ſo.
               All the chaleſes gyuen were
               
                  To raunſome the kynge beyng priſonere
               With Themperoure more than a yere
               Fro thens or he myght go.
            
            
               ¶Kynge Iohn̄.
               WHat myſery alſo a longe tyme was
               In kyng Iohn̄ tyme, by that wycked as
               Stephen Leigton of Canterbury alas, alas
               That euer he was borne.
            
            
               ¶Henry the thyrde.
               IN the fyrſte yere of this kyng
               The ſayd Stephen dyd in bryng
               The Legate Pandulphe with his bleſſyng
               The kynge an othe to take
               whiche was theyr churche for to defende
               But ſuche rebellions againſt hym dyd bende
               That euer after to his lyfes ende
               Peace he coulde not make.
            
            
               ¶Edwarde the fyrſte.
               THe biſhop of ſaint Andrewes ī ſcotlād
               with ye biſhop of baſtō made a gret bād
               
                  Of dyuers lordes and toke in hand
               Agaynſt this kynge to fyght
               As periured rebelles the byſhoppes were ſent
               By the kynge to the fyfte Innocent
               The lordes were heddyd and in peaces rent
               As traytors ſhulde be dyght.
            
            
               ¶Edwarde the ſeconde.
               SUche ſtryfe and rebellione
               Had Edwarde the ſecone
               With his lordes eche one
               Tyll his latter daye
               That yf his prelacy
               With theyr priuie popery
               Had not ſtonde therby
               His lordes had made no fray.
            
            
               ¶Edwarde the thyrde.
               IN this kynges tyme the .vi. Innocent
               Gaue in Englande benefyce and prebēt
               Vntyll this kynge ſent contrary cōmaūdmēt
               To his byſhoppes all
               This kynge forbadde that Peter pens
               
                  Shulde to Rome be gathered from hens
               His mynde was and whole pretens
               To gouerne great and ſmale.
            
            
               ¶Richarde the ſeconde.
               A Rūdell of cāterbury in this kyngꝭ tyme
               And the erle of darby for no ſmale crime
               Banyſhed were who after dyd clyme
               And the kynge was ouer throwen.
            
            
               ¶Henry the fourth.
               THen was the Erle crowned kynge
               Henry the .iiii. this is no leſynge
               Of whom the byſhops had the rulynge
               After theyr owne mynde.
            
            
               ¶Henry the fyfte.
               HEnry the fyfte they dyd not let go
               Out of theyr rulīge, they wel dyd know
               That yf they dyd a mortuall fo
               No doubt they ſhulde hym fynde
               This kynge went aboute to take awaye
               
                  Theyr temporalties, but nyght and daye
               His mynde to turne they dyd aſſaye
               With money to conquere fraunce
               So in to fraunce the kynge dyd go
               Where in ſhort tyme he ſubdued ſo
               Townes and Caſtelles he dyd ouer thro
               To Fraunce a bytter chaunce.
            
            
               ¶Henry the .vi.
               IN Henrys dayes the .vi. this is no naye
               The good duke of glocet was caſt away
               By the byſhop of wyncheſter yt prelate gaye
               In ſtryfe dyſdayne and pryde
               A cardynall this prelate was made
               Who ſhortely after to Fraunce yade
               Betwene both kynges a peace to be hadde
               And there he dyd abyde
               With the romyſhe legate to haue his fyll
               Of the popyſhe power was all his wyll
               But of peace he made no ſkyll
               And that dyd well appere
               For euer after to Englande fell
               Muche miſery, the deuyll of hell
               
                  Rewarde ſuche prelates that ſo doth ſell
               The truth both farre and nere.
            
            
               ¶Edwarde the .iiii.
               THis kyng wold had gottē fraūce agayn
               But the prelatꝭ the rat dyd ſore diſdayn
               And from that purpoſe dyd hym refrayne
               Whiche cauſed bate and ſtryfe
               Who lyſt the Cronicles for to rede
               Shallſe to death howe many dyd blede
               And howe the prelates helped at nede
               With ſwerdeſpere or knyfe.
            
            
               ¶Rycharde the thirde.
               THis kynges tyme was ſo ſhorte
               That with hym to haue theyr ſporte
               The Popyſhe prelates had no comforte
               So feable was thyr myght.
            
            
               ¶Henry the .vii.
               THe Deane of Paules with ye prouinciall
               Of the blacke fryers &amp; other great &amp; ſmal
               And ye Pryor of Langley by treaſon dyd fall
               
                  For lacke of godly ſyght
               The Cardynall Morton &amp; fox of wyncheſter
               By theyr ſubtyle councell conſydred togyther
               Cauſed Bolen to beſeged with fyre and ſpere
               And many was there ſtroyed.
            
            
               ¶Henry the .viij.
               LIke cautell vſed Cardynall Wolſey
               By cauſyng the ſcottes to ronne and flye
               To the Englyſhe pale but them quickeley
               The Norden men anoyed
               And what craftye prākes ye prelatꝭ dyd playe
               To turne the kynges mynde cleue awaye
               When on the petycottes he wolde thē paye
               Accordyng to theyr deſerte.
               Moche therof I nede not wryte
               Theyr Popyſhe Iuggelynge is in ſyght
               And howe agaynſt the ſtreame they fyght
               Which cauſeth them to ſmerte
               In this kynges tyme ye do well know
               Howe great an enmye and mortall fo
               The Popyſhe prelates hath bene alſo
               Agaynſt Gods worde ſo pure
               For whiche wordes onely ſake
               
                  Many an hert full often to quake
               Ryght piteouſly they dyd make
               And for that thynge I you enſure
               To the whiche with legge, fote, and toe
               They ceaſe not a pace nowe to goe
               Full mekely crouchyng and full lowe
               Gladly agreyng there to
               As the kynge in earth ſupreame
               Heade of the Churche of this realme
               Onely to be oure Ioyfull beame
               We muſt obey and knowe
               And all ſuche that in autoritie
               His grace hath aſſigned to be
               We muſt obey in eche degre
               Orelles we get damnacion
               Vnto oure ſelfes, this is no ly
               The power is gods mynyſter to vs truly
               Yf we do euyll he reuengeth frely
               And all for oure ſaluacion
               The pardons alſo for purgatory
               With the deteſtable ſynne of buggary
               And all kynde of Idolatry
               Gods worde hath put to flyght
               
                  And muche popery I tell you playne
               That ranckely dyd priuely raigne
               As nowe is knowen abrode certayne
               Gods worde hath brought to lyght
               Many thynges mo were hydden
               And by the papyſtes ouer ſtrydden
               Whiche abrode be nowe ſpredden
               Dayly before your eye,
               wherat ſome whyne full ſore
               But ſpeſially that theyr popyſhe lore
               whom they had ſo longe in ſtore
               Awaye nowe do flye
               Had not the poore ſely ſoulles
               So often brought forth to powlles
               Spred abrode the popyſhe rolles
               Of theyr olde faſſyon
               The ſhameles popyſhe clargye
               wolde ſtyll haue bene hardye
               And nothynge at all tardye
               In theyr habomynacyon
               This is no lye that I you tell
               Full cruell were they and full fell
               Agaynſt them that of the Goſpell dyd ſmell
               And forſoke theyr fuſty popery
               
                  They knowe now ye lawe they know ye payne
               They can no longer clocke nor fayne
               And yf they do I tell you certayne
               Theyr rewarde is playne ropery
               Hereof I nede not moche to ſaye
               Many aſſayde the game and knewe ye playe
               It were beſt they turne theyr mynde awaye
               And ſtryfe not agaynſt the ryght
               Yf theyr lordly power myght ones abate
               Then wolde they quyckely open the gate
               Of true doctryne whiche of late
               Kynge Harry hath brought to lyght
               God ſaue kynge Edwardes noble grace
               And ſende his hyghnes tyme and ſpace
               To contynewe forth his fathers trace
               With force ſtrenght and myght
               And ſende euyll chaunce and croked happes
               To all ſuche Popyſhe forked cappes
               That gaue ſo many curſed flappes
               For Gods bleſſed worde
               So hath he done it is certayne
               They haue not wone I tell you playne
               And neuer ſhall tyll they haue agayne
               The Pope to be theyr Lorde.
               
                  ¶God for bydde.
               ¶Thus endeth this breue Cronycle.
            
         
      
   

