
   
      
         
            A short treatise against the Donatists of England, whome we call Brownists Wherein, by the answeres vnto certayne writings of theyrs, diuers of their heresies are noted, with sundry fantasticall opinions. By George Giffard, Minister of Gods holy Word in Maldon.
            Gifford, George, d. 1620.
         
         
            
               1590
            
         
         Approx. 278 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 62 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01736
            STC 11869
            ESTC S114289
            99849515
            99849515
            14667
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01736)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14667)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 925:16)
         
         
            
               
                  A short treatise against the Donatists of England, whome we call Brownists Wherein, by the answeres vnto certayne writings of theyrs, diuers of their heresies are noted, with sundry fantasticall opinions. By George Giffard, Minister of Gods holy Word in Maldon.
                  Gifford, George, d. 1620.
               
               [12], 110, [2] p.   
               
                  Printed [by J. Windet] for Toby Cooke, dwelling at the Tygers head in Paules Churchyard,
                  At London :
                  1590.
               
               
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  Running title reads: An ansvver to the Brovvnists.
                  Last leaf blank.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Brownists --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-07
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-08
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-04
            John PasSampled and proofread
         
            2008-04
            John PasText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A SHORT TREATISE againſt the Donatiſts of England, whome we call Browniſts.
            
            Wherein, by the Anſweres vnto certayne Writings of theyrs, diuers of their hereſies are noted, with ſundry fantaſticall opinions.
            By George Giffard, Miniſter of Gods holy Word in Maldon.
            
            
               NON SOLO PANE VIVET HOMO: Luke 4
               Verbum Dei manet in aeternum:
            
            AT LONDON Printed for Toby Cooke, dwelling at the Tygers head in Paules Churchyard. 1590.
         
         
            
            
            To the right Honourable, Sir VVilliam Cecill, Knight of the Garter, Baron of Burghley, Lorde high Treaſurer of England, and Chancelor of the Vniuerſitie of Cambridge, Grace and peace.
            
               I Am (right Honourable) to excuſe my ſelfe in two thinges: the one, that I take vpon me to write againſt the Browniſts, ſeeing there be ſo many great learned mē in our land, which doo refraine: the other, that I doo offer ſo ſlender a peece of woorke vnto your Honour. Touching the former, the truth is, I haue beene vnwares drawne vnto it, not purpoſing any ſuch matter. For more then two yeares paſt, there were brought vnto me certaine articles which the Browniſts doo call, A breefe ſum of their profeſſion, with diuers arguments againſt read prayer. They were brought vnto me by a Scholemaiſter in Eſſex, who of a godly minde▪ did deſire mee to write my iudgement of the ſame, which when I refuſed, hee vrged me with this, that diuerſe of the people about them were troubled, and did hang in ſuſpenſe, and for their ſakes he did require it, I did graunt his requeſt, and when they had my writings, they were carried to the cheefe men of that ſect. Not long after, I receiued large replies, where I perceiued that which before I did not ſo much as dreame of, namely, that they had made chalenge, and looked to be encountred by the learnedeſt in the land. They take it greeuouſly, and reprehend me, as hauing intercepted this buſineſſe, and taken it from the hands of the learned. Heerevpon I ſtayed long, purpoſing to giue them but ſhorte anſwer to their chiefe matters. But when I ſawe that aduantage was taken, as if I had receiued matters vnanſwerable,

and that Browniſme did begin to ſpred in manye places of the land: I thought it not amiſſe, ſeeing the burthen thus to haue light vpon me, though I be not able to deale ſo ſufficiently as ſuch a matter requireth: yet to publiſh to the world ſome of their hereſies, and frantike opinions, which are to be gathered from their writings. I haue not ſet downe the whole diſcourſe of wordes, which hath paſſed betweene them and me, for it would be ſomewhat tedious. But if any ſhall thinke I haue paſſed any reaſons of theirs vnanſwered, or wreſted their words from the true ſence, to gather hereſies: let them ſhew any particular, and I wil be able to cleere my ſelfe. And let men conſider, whether the Browniſme can be ſupported by any pillers, but thoſe hereſies which I haue noted. I meddle not with the controuerſies of our Church, but deale by way of admiſsion. I neuer receyued the names of any ſubſcribed to the writings I receiued, and for that cauſe I do name none. And now for the other point, why I preſume to offer it vnto your honour. God hath giuen your honour to be an auncient graue Counſellor, and which many yeares haue borne, and ſtill doo beare, a great part of the waight of this our common-wealth, vnder her right excellent Maieſtie: and for that cauſe I iudge it meete your Honor ſhould ſee ſuch things as any way touch the generall eſtate. I truſt therefore, that although it be not for the ſlenderneſſe worthy to be offred to ſo honorable a perſon, yet it ſhall be accepted in ſome ſort. And touching your Honor, as I do not doubt of it but it ſhal be, ſo I wiſh &amp; pray to God, that you may be one of thoſe of whome it is written, Pſal. 92. The righteous ſhall flouriſh like a palme tree, and ſhall growe like a Cedar in Lebanon. Being planted in the houſe of the Lord, they ſhall flouriſh in the Courtes of our God, they ſhall ſtill bring forth fruite in their age: they ſhall be fat and flouriſhing: to declare that the Lorde my rock is righteous, and that there is none iniquitie in him.
            
               Your Honors in all duty to commaund,
George Gyffard.
            
         
         
            
            The Preface to the gentle Reader.
            
            
               IT is a thing of great wonder, to behold how God preſerueth his Church from drowning and deſtruction in theſe greeuous times. The Deuill is ſo full of wrath, knowing his time is but ſhort, Reuel. 12. v. 12. that he raiſeth vp ſuch tempeſts &amp; whi
                  •
               le windes, with ſuch lightning and thunders, with ſuch outragious ſurges and waues, as if heauen and earth ſhould bee mixed together. His cheefe Vaſſals, the tyrants and Heretikes, doo wonderfully beſtirre them, to effect his curſſed deſires. By the one ſort hee dooth breath out terror, and as it were ſpit fire. By the other he ſpueth vp deadlye poiſon, and caſteth his poiſoned dartes. He is ſo ſubtill, that he tranſformeth himſelfe into the likeneſſe of an Angell of light, and his Miniſters come in faire cloakes▪ For behold all ſortes of Heretikes and Schiſmatikes, and yee ſhall ſee fewe of them come in the Deuils liuerie. The Papiſts ſhrowde themſelues vnder the name and title of the Catholike Church. Theſe cry out, the fathers, the fathers, the auncient Fathers. Theſe proclaime vs and all Churches, which haue forſaken their fellowſhip, and imbraced the Goſpell, to be Schiſmatikes and Heretiks. Theſe affirme, that we haue no word of God, no Sacraments, nor Miniſtrie, becauſe we be cut off from them. Theſe preuaile mightelie among the blind ſuperſtitious people, who greedely drinke vp all the poiſon &amp; abhominations, which the Deuill hath ſpued vp into that faire golden cuppe in which they offer them, Reuel. 17. which is, that they be Catholikes. There is riſen vp among vs a blinde ſect, oppoſite to theſe, which is ſo furious, that it commeth like a raging tempeſt from a contrary coaſt, ſo that our ſhip is toſſed betweene contrary waues. For theſe cry alowd, that our aſſemblies be Romiſh, idolatrous; antichriſtian Synagogs. That we worſhip the beaſt, receiue his marke, and ſtand vnder his yoake. And finally, that we haue no Miniſtery, no word of God nor Sacraments. Theſe pretend ſuch feruencie of zeale againſt all falſe worſhip, ſuperſtition, and Idolatrie, and ſuch loue to the diſcipline of Chriſt, and crie ſo lowd, that a man would thinke he heard the voice of Elias, of Haggeus, and of that third Angel, Reu. 14. Downe with the Preeſts of Baal, come out from among them, worſhip not the beaſt, ariſe, ariſe, &amp; build the Temple and altar of the Lord. With this counterfet voice the Deuill ſeduceth many, and troubleth all ſuch as are weake, and yet haue zeale againſt falſe worſhip, trembling for feare of pollution: with this ſect onely haue I now to deale. Firſt therfore touching their name, we terme them Browniſts, as being the Diſciples &amp; Scholers of Browne. There be indeed new maſters ſprong vp, which ſeeke to carrie awaye the name, and I haue heard diuers ſay, they go beyond Browne. But whoſoeuer ſhal reade his books

and peruſe all their writings, ſhall well ſee, that he deſerueth to haue the honour, if any be, and to be called the Captaine and maiſter of them all. They haue all their furniture from him: they do but open his packe, and diſplaye his wares. They haue not a ſharpe arrowe, which is not drawne out of his quiuer.
            Then next, touching the queſtion betweene them and me, let the reader conſider, it is not about the controuerſie in our Church, as whether there be imperfections, corruptions, and faults, in our worſhip, miniſterie, and church gouernment, nor how many, great or ſmall. But whether there be ſuch heynous enormities, as deſtroy the verye life and being of a true Church, and make an vtter diuorſe from Chriſt. I will lay it open more plaine by a compariſon which the Scripture vſeth. The Church is like a man, in whom there be many parts and members. Rom. 12. If all the parts or members of the body haue their iuſt proportion, be whole and ſound, and ſet in their due order, the ſoule and life departed, he is no longer a man, to ſpeake properly, but the dead carcaſſe of a man. But now if he be ſicke and diſeaſed, ſo that all partes are feeble, or if he be deformed with ſores and maimes, wanting hand, foote, eye, noſe, or ſuch like, yet is he ſtill a man, ſo long as the ſoule and life remaine in him. All men doo know this to be true, yea euen the ſimpleſt make no doubt or controuerſie about it. Let vs ſee therefore whether it be a fitte compariſon with the Church, and whether it be ſo in it of neceſſitie, and as manifeſt by the doctrine of the holy ſcriptures, as this other is vnto our bodily ſenſes.
            To finde this, we muſt firſt conſider, whether there be no true Church of GOD, but that which is perfect in this worlde? Wee knowe that there are none but Heretikes, yea ranke abhominable heretikes, which obſtinately deny this cleere doctrine of the holy Scriptures, namely, that euen the moſt faithfull, and the moſt godly, are not perfect while they liue vpon the earth. We know but in part. 1. Cor. 13. In many things we ſinne all. Iam. 3. v. 2. And who vnderſtandeth his errors, or who can tell how oft he offendeth? Pſal 19. The perfecteſt members of the Church doo erre, doo ſinne, are maimed, are weake, are ſpotted and deformed many wayes. Nowe, whereas all the members be in this caſe, needes muſt the whole body which is compoſed of them be in the ſame eſtate. Then we may not looke for a Church in this world, which is not ſpotted, deformed, maymed, and weake, in ſome reſpects.
            But the queſtion muſt bee, how farre it may bee deformed and maimed, and yet remaine aliue, and ſo a true Church of God. Let all the partes bee ioyned together: let there be all ſortes of officers and offices, yet if the life, and as it were the ſoule of the Church be wanting, it is but a dead carcaſſe. Contrarywiſe, let there be ſome members wanting, ſome maimed, all parts deformed and weake, yet is it a true Church of God, ſo long as the ſoule and life dooth remaine in it. And what is the ſoule and life of the Church? Ieſus Chriſt apprehended by faith. I liue now, ſaith Saint Paul, but not any longer I, but Chriſt liueth in me, Galath. 2. ver. 20. All the members of the

Church are incorporate, and graffed into Chriſt by faith, and doo growe in him, and through the operation of his ſpirite receiue the iuice and ſappe of life from him, Iohn. 15. Whoſoeuer beleeueth in the Sonne of God, ſhall be ſaued, though he be full of errors, full of infirmities, and deformities, both in body and ſoule, labouring to be purged.
            But if a man, or an aſſembly do hold that which ouerthroweth the faith in Chriſt, they are gone, there is no life remaining. As the Papacie holdeth many things aright touching Chriſt; but it holdeth ſundry things contrary, which ouerthrow the very foundation of the faith, and ſo the Papacie it ſelfe is not Gods true Church.
            Thus haue I laide open the queſtion, betweene mee and the Browniſts: wherein then are the Maiſters and Capitaines of Browniſme deceiued? And what is it, in which they ſeeke victorie and glory? They knowe there is no ſinne, no error, no corruption, nor no abuſe, but that if all the learnedeſt in the worlde would take vpon them to cleere and to defend the ſame, they ſhall not be able. Then they are deſirous of victorie, of triumphe and glorye▪ ouer all both wiſe and learned. Heere therefore they entrench themſelues, they make their Bulwarkes, plant their ordinance, ſet themſelues in arraye, and ſound the Trumpet of defiance againſt all. They preſume, none ſhall euer be able to driue them out of their holde. And indeed, he that condemneth an error, and goeth no further, can neuer be vanquiſhed. But heerein they are deceiued, that out of this Forte they will batter downe the Church. For theyr ordinance is ouer weake for that: they ſtoppe in powder in great plenty, for they laye on toong enough, and ſo make terrible thundering crakes. But the Bullets which come foorth, and which ſhould doo the deed, are nothing but hereticall, erronious, and fantaſticall opinions, and ſo all vaniſheth into ſmoake. They muſt therefore at the laſt, leaue their holde, and take them to their heeles, for Gods Church will not be battered downe by any aſſaults of Schiſmatikes.
            Some will thinke hardly, that I terme them Schiſmatikes, ſeeing they be men that are accounted zealous▪ and ſtand for good things. But the truth is, they be not onely a Schiſme, yea a vile Schiſme, rending themſelues from the Church of England, and condemning by their aſſertions, the whole viſible Church in the worlde, euen as the Donatiſts did of olde time: but alſo they maintaine hereſies, and ſome that touche the very foundation of faith and Chriſtian religion: they be vtter violaters of eccleſiaſticall diſcipline, they abridge the power of the ciuill Magiſtrate, beſide ſundry fantaſticall opinions. For when as the life of the church conſiſteth in the apprehenſson of Chriſt through faith, it muſt needs be an hereſie, to conclude as they doo, a nullitie, &amp; a quite ouerthrow of the ſame, from errors &amp; faults which are not fundamentall. Faith and regeneration being vnperfect, in all that liue vpon the earth, it is heriticall, to ſay, that is no Church of God, which holding the ſounde doctrine, hath ſinnes and great abuſes in it.
            The ſtableneſſe of Gods couenant towarde the Church, being founded onely vpon his free grace, it is deteſtable impietie, to hang it vpon the works

of men, as the Browniſts do, when they affyrme, that where there is any open ſinnes ſuffered in an aſſemblie, the couenant is diſanulled with them all. And if men conſider well, they ſhall finde that the whole Browniſme reſteth vppon the hereſie of perfection and Anabaptiſticall freedome. For from hence, that it is written, Ieruſalem from aboue is the mother of vs all, and is free with her children. They boaſt of ſuch freedome, as that touching outwarde orders, the Prince and Church hath no power to impoſe any thing by Lawes and Conſtitutions. Which is one thing wherein they do not onely abridge the power of the Chriſtian Magiſtrates, denying them the authoritie to reforme the Church, and to compell their ſubiects to the true worſhip, ſpoyling the Church of that comfortable ayd: but alſo condemne all reformed Churches which haue orders and preſcript formes of prayers impoſed, which theſe Browniſts tearme Idolatrie, a tradition bringing Chriſtian libertie into bondage, and therefore a thing moſt deteſtable. Moreouer, they hold ſuch a perfect freedome from all ſpirituall bondage of ſinne, that they affyrme S. Paule neuer conſented to wicked thoughts after he was regenerate. But in an other place they affyrme, that all men be Idolaters, and can keepe no one Commaundement: where they are both contrary to themſelues, vttering that which ouerthroweth the whole Browniſme▪
                and alſo ſpeake groſely. For albeit there is no man perfect in any Commaundement, yet the holy Scriptures do not call them Idolaters nor adulterers. They boldly gayne ſay the holy Ghoſt, by affirming that the Pſalmes were not to be ſung vnto God. And touching the diſcipline, which is the thing they moſt glorie of, as if they ſuffered for it: let all men know for certaintie, that they be not only ignorant what it is, but alſo do in their practiſe breake and ouerthrow the very pith and ſubſtance thereof in the chiefe rules. For they take vpon them to abandon and caſt foorth whole aſſemblyes which profeſſe the Goſpell, and haue their eſtimation and dignitie among all godly Churches, without obſeruing the rule giuen by our Sauiour Chriſt, Math. 18. They intrude themſelues without calling, beeing meere priuate men, to the erecting and eſtabliſhing of a publike gouernment, forgetting that which is written, I haue not ſent them, and yet they runne. They cut off alſo the power of the Church in a great part of the diſcipline, as namely, in ordeyning conſtitutions in things that are variable. Finally touching this poynt, I may ſay boldly, the Diuell can no way almoſt more diſgrace Eccleſiaſticall gouernment then he doth by them, for it is the Sterne of Chriſtes Ship, and requireth men of the greateſt wiſedome, learning, experience, and ſobrietie that may be, for to guide it. Now when the common Artificer, the Apprentiſe and the Bruer intrude themſelues, and they will guide the ſame, being ignorant, raſh, and headie, what worldlie wiſe man will not take it, that diſcipline her ſelfe is but a bedlem? Who will aduenture himſelfe in that Ship, where preſumptuous ignorance, and bold frenſie doth ſit at the Helme? Shall that Ship eſcape the rockes? If it would pleaſe God to giue Browne the grace to repent, and to ſpeake the truth, he could beſt declare this thing. For when he had with certayne other, drawne

ſome both men and women ouer the Seas, and there ſpread his Sayles, how ſoone did his ſilly Boate daſh vppon the rocke, and was clouen in two or three peeces? Let not men be deceyued with euery vayne ſhewe, for vndoubtedly, he that obſerueth ſhall finde, that the end of Browniſme, is infinite Schiſmes, Hereſies, Atheiſme, and Barbariſme. For what other fruites can followe of the diſgracing and condemning the liberall Artes, of bringing the miniſterie of Gods Word, by which the religion and godlines that is in men, hath been 
                  •
               rought into vtter contempt? What can followe from immoderate outragious raſh furie, wrath, and bitter zeale, and vainglorious contention, which are earthly, ſenſuall, and diueliſh? If men could ſtay themſelues but a while, and ſee whether the ſame things ſpring not foorth, which came from the Donatiſts and Anabaptiſts, it were well. For it is to be wondred at, that any which profeſſe the Goſpell, ſhould be ſeduced and called away not only from the Miniſters of the Church of England that haue taught them, but from all the moſt worthy men and Churches vnder heauen, and that by the voyce of the Deuill in ſuch furious blinde Schiſmatikes. In deede there be two ſpeciall cauſes of it: the one, that ſundry men receyue not the holy Word of God in humilitie, with feare and trembling, with conſcience to practiſe, but are puffed vp, and ſwell with opinion of their knowledge, as ſoone as they can vtter a fewe words: and growe vnto vayne iangling, yea, vnto bitter zeale, and contention, in ſtead of being quiet (as S. Paule willeth) and medling with their own buſines, 1. Theſ. 3. and alſo in ſtead of following after righteouſnes, faith and loue, 2. Timoth. 3.
            He that ſeemeth moſt zealous in religion, and refraineth not his toong, hath but bitterneſſe in ſteed of heauenly zeale. For wheras, in ſteed of gentleneſſe, meekeneſſe, patience, mercie, and loue, yee finde wrath, fierceneſſe, intemperat rage, vncharitable condemning and ſlaundering, know for certainty, that the true zeale is not there. The other cauſe of mens ſeducing, is that in this corrupt age there be many ſtumbling blockes, and greeuous offences: where indeed, it is the part and duty of euery true Chriſtian man, beſide the taking heede to his owne wayes, moſt inſtantly to offer vp praiers and ſupplications to God, to intreate him to ſhew mercie and compaſſion vpon vs, by increaſing all heauenly graces and giftes of his holy ſpirit in our moſt noble Queene, and in all Gouernours, both ciuill and eccleſiaſticall, that there may be feruent zeale to purge the houſe of God, and to take away the cauſes of contention, that we may not alwaies ſeeke to deuoure one an other, but that vnity and concord may floriſh, holding this withall, that it is alſo euery mans dutie that will feare God, to giue him hearty thanks for the ineſtimable treaſures and bleſſings which he hath beſtowed vpon vs, by meanes of the happy raigne of our gratious Soueraigne: and to take heed of that malignant ſpirite of Browniſme, which would carry vs to this wicked opinion, that ſhe bearing the Sworde of God, hath doone no more for vs then an Heathen Prince might doo. For if we haue no word of God, no miniſtery, no Sacraments nor viſible Church, but all idolatrous and antichriſtian,

what hath ſhe done, what honor can ſhe haue for defence of the Goſpell? This is no ſmall diſhonour and iniurie to a Chriſtian Prince, thus to diminiſh the loue of the ſubiects. The Lord giue them repentance, and grace, to ceaſe from ſuch impietie; and let all men with modeſtie, reuerence, and ſubiection, and not with reproch and contempt, ſeeke the redreſſe of abuſes at their hands which be in Authoritie: and not aduenture like Corah, Dathan, and Abiram, to intrude themſelues without calling and warrant from God. They cryed out, are not all the Lords people holy? and therefore Moſes and Aaron yee take too much vppon yee. The Browniſt proclaymeth, that all the Lords people are free, and therefore freely to deale, and not to haue any thing impoſed by any. Be not deceyued, but knowe for certaintie, that they be full and rancke Donatiſts and Anabaptiſts in part. I knowe it is complayned of, that there be ſo many and ſo diuers Sectes and Hereſies dayly ſpringing vp where the Goſpell is preached, for it ſeemeth a foule diſgrace both to the Goſpell it ſelfe, and to the Preachers. There are, ſay ſome, at the leaſt fifty ſeuerall ſectes. Behold, ſay others, how the people are lead without ground, and haue no ſtay but are caryed without ende from one thing to another. What is the cauſe? is not the preaching? is there any thing deliuered which is certayne? are not the fruites of theyr Sermons, factions, and Schiſmes? Theſe ſpeeches do ſo abaſh and trouble ſome, that they are driuen backe, and retyre into flat Poperie, as into a ſafe hauen, which yet in truth is the gulfe of all Schiſmes and abhominable hereſies Others are ſo much diſpleaſed, that they become Atheiſts, and care not much for any Religion, though of both they doo rather fauour the Poperie. A third ſort there be which did runne, and now ſtand ſtill and wonder: they knowe not whether they were beſt to goe backe or forward. Their loue and zeale is decayed, and readie vtterly to be quenched. It is wonderfull that there ſhould be ſuch blindnes in men, and want of wiſedome to conſider rightly of all cauſes and effects. The Scriptures are cleere that light is come into the world, and men loue darkneſſe more then light, becauſe their works be euill. And what followeth heerevpon, becauſe they receyue not the loue of the truth, that they might be ſaued: God doth ſend them ſtrong deluſion to beleeue lyes, that they may be damned, 2. Theſſ. 2. It is the heauie iudgement of God vppon the wicked world, that Satan is let looſe to ſeduce and leade into error. Men are worthie of ſuch a plague, and it doth come vppon them to the full: for they be not able now to diſcerne the truth, but do reproch and blaſpheme it, ſeeking the diſgrace of ſuch as do bring it. Moreouer, the Scriptures do ſhewe, that God hath an other purpoſe in ſending ſtrong deluſion, and the efficacie of error, and that is touching his elect, for they be clogged with the fleſhe, ſlowe and dull to ſearch out the truth: they be readie to leane to their owne wiſedome, and ſeeke not vnto God. When Schiſmes and Hereſies ariſe, it doth awaken them, cauſeth them to ſearch more diligently, yea, to ſeeke vnto God, and to depend wholly vppon him for light and inſtruction. It cauſeth them to feare and tremble in humilitie, and to make precious account of

the truth when they haue once found it: ſeeing the Deuill laboureth ſo mightely to depriue them of it by quenching the light. I heare (ſayth S. Paule) that there be Schiſmes among ye, and I do in part beleeue it: for there muſt be Hereſies, that ſuch as are approued, may be made manifeſt, 1. Cor. 11. When we ſee it come to paſſe, that through the malice and craft of the Deuill and his inſtruments ſuch confuſion doth ouerſpread all, let vs not loue the Goſpell the worſe, let vs not blaſpheme it, but knowe it ſtandeth vs vpon to be more carefull. The bleſſed Apoſtles themſelues had to encounter with Heretikes and falſe Apoſtles, and full cunningly did Satan winde in himſelfe in their dayes. When they were taken away, what troups of Heretikes did he ſend foorth? what blaſphemies and deteſtable furies did he vtter and ſpread by them? how were all the auncient Doctors and holy Fathers in the Churches ſet on worke to confute them, and to defend the true Chriſtian people from infection? Why then ſhould we nowe be daunted? or why ſhould it be any reproch to the holy Doctrine now more then of old, that the Diuell, where any light is ſhewed, doth followe it by and by at the heeles, to worke diſgrace? Let the miniſters of Gods Word looke diligently to theyr flockes, and teach them the wholeſome pure Doctrine, and the way of Sanctification. Let true zeale ſpring afreſh, which nowe ſuffreth great contempt, becauſe there is a mad bedlem riſen vp, which nameth her ſelfe by her name. There be diuers which cry out againſt zeale very naughtely, when it is moſt certayne no man can haue ouermuch godly zeale, eſpecially in theſe dayes, wherein, who almoſt hath any hote loue for the glorie of God, and the ſaluation of his people? If Chriſt ſhould ſpeake, what other ſentence can we looke for, but that which he vttered of the Church of Laodicea, Reuel. 3. Thou art neyther hote nor cold. But let vs come to the matter in hand.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            A breefe ſum of the profeſsion of the Browniſts.
            
            _1 WE ſeeke aboue all things the peace and protection of the moſt high, and the kingdome of Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.
            2 We ſeeke and fully purpoſe to worſhip God aright, as he hath commaunded in his holy worde.
            3 We ſeeke the fellowſhip and communion of his faithfull and obedient ſeruants, and together with them to enter couenant with the Lord. And by the direction of his holy ſpirite to proceed to a godly, free, and right choiſe of miniſters and other officers by him ordained to the ſeruice of his Church.
            4 We ſeeke to eſtabliſh and obey the ordinances and lawes of our Sauiour Chriſt, left by his laſt will and teſtament to the gouerning and guiding of his Church, without altering, changing, innouating, wreſting, or leauing out any of them, that the Lord ſhall giuevs ſight of.
            5 We purpoſe by the aſſiſtance of the Holyghoſt in this faith and order to leade our liues. And for this faith and order to leaue our liues, if ſuch be the good will and pleaſure of our heauenly Father: to whom be all glory and praiſe for euer. Amen.
            6 And now that our forſaking and vtter abandoning theſe diſordered aſſemblies, as they generally ſtand in England, may not ſeeme ſtrange or offenſiue to any man, that will iudge, or be iudged by the worde of God: we alledge &amp; affirme them hainouſlye faultie, and wilfullye obſtinate in theſe foure principall tranſgreſſions.
         
         
            
            
               1 They worſhip the true God after a falſe manner, their worſhip being made of the inuention of man, euen of that man of ſinne, erronious, and impoſed vpon them.
               
               2 Then for that the prophane vngodly multitude without the exception of any one perſon, are with them receiued into, and reteined in the boſome and body of their Church, &amp;c.
               
               3 Then for that they haue a falſe and Antichriſtian miniſtery impoſed vpon them, retained with them, and maintained by them.
               
               4 Then for that their Churches are ruled by, and remaine in ſubiection vnto an Antichriſtian and vngodly gouernment, cleane contrary to the inſtitution of our Sauiour Chriſt.
               
            
            
               
                  G. G. 1 IN my former anſwer vnto theſe your articles which ye call A breefe ſum of your profeſſion, I kept the ſame order in which they ſtand. But now I begin firſt with your heauy accuſation of the foure heinous tranſgreſſions for which ye condemne and abandon all the aſſemblies as they generally ſtande in England: and come after vnto thoſe former articles, which conteine your aſſociation, wherein ye conioyne your ſelues, and enter into couenant with God (as ye ſay) to ſet vp all the ordinances of Chriſt, for I take this to bee the fitteſt order. Your ſyxt article which now muſt be firſt, being expreſſed in theſe words. And now that our forſaking and vtter abandoning theſe diſordered aſſemblies, as they generally ſtand in England, may not ſeeme ſtrange or offenſiue to anye man, that will iudge or be iudged by the word of God: we alledge and affirme them heinouſlie faultie, and wilfullie obſtinate in theſe foure principall tranſgreſſions. To this I anſwered: That Elias did ſée outward idolatrie practiſed, and ſaw none

which did miſlike, and therefore complained of all. It was an error, but whereas Gods word is imbraced, and multitudes abhorre Idolatrie, and labour with ſorrowfull teares to bee purged from their ſinnes, it is an intollerable pride and preſumption of men, to ſet themſelues in Gods iudgement ſeat, and to condemne all of wilfull obſtinacie. Let it be ſhewed where euer any, led by Gods ſpirit haue dealt in this ſort, and eſpecially in charging them moſt falſlie, as ſhall appeare.
            
         
         
            The Browniſts.
            
               HEre you verye vehemently charge vs with vntollerable pride, preſumption, and intruſion into Gods iudgment ſeate, to be voide of Gods ſpirite, to charge and condemne you moſt falſely, as you ſay ſhall appeare. How iuſtly you charge vs with theſe crimes, or diſcharge your ſelfe, and your aſſemblies of theſe preſent tranſgeſſions vpon the ſcanne of your anſweres ſhall appeare▪ &amp;c.
            
            
               
                  G. G. All ſuch as take vpon them to iudge and condemne whole aſſemblies, that profeſſe the Goſpell, and that with ſlanderous accuſations, as▪ you do, may right well be charged with intollerable pride, preſumption, and intruſion into Gods iudgement ſeate, ſéeing the Scriptures do cleerely warrant it. For he that iudgeth one man to be no true Chriſtian, which holdeth the place of a brother, and laboureth to pleaſe God, profeſſing the faith ſoundly in all fundamentall points, either for ſome errors in iudgement, or frailties committed in life, proudlye aduanceth himſelfe into Gods office, who alone ſearcheth the heart, and trieth the raines of the children of men. What ſhall we ſay then of thoſe which condemne whole multitudes, amongſt whom there be many vnſpotted with groſe errors and offenſes? But the ground of your dooing is from hence, that ſuch as commit principall tranſgreſſions, and be wilfullye obſtinate in the ſame, the word of God dooth condemne them. And then yée ſay, that the aſſemblies in England be heinouſly faulty, and wilfully obſtinate in foure principall tranſgreſſions. Ye boldly alledge and affirme, but ye make proofe neither

of the tranſgreſſions, nor of the wilfull obſtinacie. Touching the tranſgreſſions, what meane ye by principall? If yée vnderſtand great faults and groſſe errors, and holde withall that there is no faith nor regeneration among thoſe which erre groſely, &amp; commit great faults, ye maintaine hereſie, which is conuinced by infinit places and examples of the Scriptures. The beſt that euer were, did know but in part. 1. Cor. 13. The godlieſt were regenerate but in part. Rom. 7. Of the ſtrongeſt it was ſaid, who can tell his errors, Pſal. 19. and in manye things we ſinne all, Iam. 3. If Noah, Abraham, Lot, Dauid, Solomon, Samſon▪
                   and other holy men, greatly repleniſhed with the holy Ghoſt and with faithe, did ſometime fall into great ſinnes: howe many will be the errors, the diuiſions, the frailties, and offenſes among the multitude in the church, where, with the ſtronger, and ſuch as haue the greater knowledge and godlineſſe, there are heaped vp together multitudes of weake, and ſuch as be carnall, and but babes in Chriſt, beſides hipocrites, and counterſait brethren? If by principall tranſgreſſions, ye meane onely ſuch as be fundamentall, then ye doo moſt falſely accuſe the Church of England, which holdeth not any hereſie or blaſphemie againſt any one ground or principle of the holy Chriſtian faith. Yée muſt then either mainteine this hereſie, which is, that where the true faith is, there can breake foorth no great faults, errors, and abuſes: or this abſurd manner of ſpéech which afterward yée vſe, that all errors and deformities in religion, be hereſies, blaſphemies, and abhominations, or els confeſſe that with intollerable pride preſumption, and intruſion into Gods iudgement ſeate, yée haue taken vpon yée to iudge and condemne whole aſſemblies, which profeſſe the faith of Chriſt ſincerely in all fundamentall points, among whom there be many particular perſons which ſtudy earneſtly to pleaſe God, mourning for their owne ſinnes, and are like iuſt Lot, 2. Pet. 
                        •
                     . vexed and tormented to behold the wickedneſſe of others? And now touching wilfull obſtinacie, how will yée prooue that to be in all the aſſemblies, and in all members of the aſſemblies of England? If ye ſay there be apparant tranſgreſſions in which they continue,

and therefore they be wilfully obſtinate, and ſo to be vtterly abandoned. I anſwer, that your concluſion doth not follow, becauſe the continuance in all ſorts of errors and offenſes, in ſuch as profeſſe the faith, doth not warrant men vtterly to caſt them out as Heathen: but where after admonition and conuiction, the cenſure of the Church is deſpiſed. The rule of diſcipline giuen by our Sauiour Chriſt, maketh this verye cléere. If thy brother ſinne againſt thée, tell him of it betwéene him and thée alone▪ If he heare thée, thou haſt wunne thy brother: if he heare thée not, take one or two with thee, that by the mouth of two or thrée witneſſes, euery word may be confirmed: If he heare not them, tell it to the Church: if he heare not the Church, let him be as an Heathen or as a Publican. Math. 18. We ſée that priuate members may not vtterly abandon and caſt foorth any one brother, that is one which profeſſeth the true faith, and for his profeſſion hath the place and dignitie of a Chriſtian: nor iudge him ſo wilfully obſtinate, that he muſt be accounted as an Heathen, vntill the Church haue ſo iudged and caſt him foorth. The ſame orderly courſe and rule of diſcipline is to be obſerued, in admoniſhing, accuſing, conuincing, condemning, and vtter abandoning any particuler aſſembly, which hath the dignity of a Chriſtian church, and doth offend ſo gréeuouſly, and ſhew ſuch obſtinacie, that it deſerueth ſo heauy a cenſure. In a particular Church there be errors and ſinnes, I will not ſaye in many, but in all, in as much as euery one hath his blindneſſe and corruption, erreth and ſinneth continuallye one waye or other. From hence it commeth, that of neceſſitie there be alwaies in the Church diuerſities of opinions, diſcord, diuiſion, and diſſention, with many corruptions and abuſes. For if it be moſt manifeſt, that the learnedeſt and godlieſt that liueth, doth carrie with him his errors, defects, and corruptions: what ſhal we looke for where the multitude is of learned, vnlearned, ſtrong and weake, altogether, how innumerable will the frailties and corruptions now among all be: wherevpon it followeth, that the vniuerſall Church cannot rightly cut off and vtterly abandon anye particular aſſemblies, vnleſſe it be for errors &amp; abuſes which

ouerthrow the faith, &amp; deſtroy true Chriſtianity. The precept of S. Paul, in that whervnto we are come, let vs procéed by one rule, to be like minded, Phi. 3. is héer to take place. I will now procéed more particularly. The church of England, euen as it generally ſtandeth in the publike aſſemblies, among al godly Churches which know the faith which ſhe dooth openly profeſſe and maintaine, hath the place &amp; dignity of a ſiſter: They all giue vnto her the right hand of fellowſhip, acknowledging her for a mother in Iſrael, in as much as ſhe hath not béene barren, but hath brought foorth many deare children to God, and not a few of them crowned with martyrdome. Behold then the inordinate dealing, and arrogant preſumption of you Browniſts. Yea behold euen the top of your pride, againſt God and man, which profeſſing to ſet vp diſcipline, and glorying that you ſuffer for it, do breake and vtterly aboliſh the rules thereof giuen by Chriſt, by your vtter forſaking and abandoning all the aſſemblies in England: for let it bee confeſſed, that the errors, the ſinnes, the imperfections, the ſpots, and deformities of our Church be many, ſo that ſhe is not in her generall eſtate, ſo faire as the faireſt of her ſiſters: yet hath ſhe héeretofore had, and now hath, many noble children, richlye adorned with heauenly iewels, and pretious gifts of learning knowledge, faith, and godlineſſe. And howſoeuer the Papiſts one way, and the Browniſts another way, do aggrauate her crimes with peſtilent ſlaunders, yet ſhall they neuer prooue, that either in doctrine or manners ſhe is guilty of any fundamentall crime, which ſeparateth from Chriſt, and deſtroyeth the life and being of a true Church: yet you Browniſts, not obſeruing the rule giuen by Chriſt, doo vtterly abandon and caſt foorth from their dignitie, all our aſſemblies in England. For ye haue condemned al of wilful obſtinacy, euē to particular members: &amp; who hath giuen you this authoritie to thruſt them out of Gods familie, which the whole vniuerſall Church cannot rightly doo? Who could euer imagine, that vnder the pretence of ſetting vp diſcipline, the diuell ſhould breath ſuch pride into rotten fleſh, as vtterly to ouerthrow the whole ſubſtance of it: for whereas all the Churches of Chriſt in theſe

parts of the world, doo know the eſtate of our Church, and be able to diſcerne the gréeuouſneſſe of our errors: yet doo they all acknowledge and reuerence our aſſemblies as holye ſiſters. And you Browniſts, men voide of knowledge and diſcretion, without authoritie, without any calling or warrant, euen vpon a frantike brauerie, and without obſeruing any rule giuen by Chriſt Ieſus, take vpon ye moſt preſumptuouſly contrary to the iudgement of the Churches, to caſt foorth and vtterly to abandon the ſame. What Pope hath dealt more proudly in violating the diſcipline? If there were but this one thing againſt you, it were ſufficient to declare your curſed dealing, but your furies are many, firſt in your ſlaunderous accuſations, which now we come vnto.
            
         
         
            The firſt principall crime obiected by the Browniſts.
            
            
               
                  Tranſgreſ. 1 
               The Browniſts. 
               THey worſhip the true God after a falſe manner: their 
               worſhip being made of the inuention of man, euen of the man of ſinne, erronious, &amp; impoſed vpon them.
            
            
               To this I did anſwer, that our worſhip is the imbracing of the holy Bible: by the doctrine thereof, we ſéeke to beléeue in God, to call vpon him, and to doo all good workes, &amp;c.
            
         
         
            
               The Brow. 
               The firſt tranſgreſſion we charge your aſſemblies with, is 
               that you worſhip God after a falſe manner, your worſhip being made of the inuention of man, euen of the man of ſinne, erronious, and impoſed vpon you. You anſwer, your worſhip is the imbracing of the holy Bible. Thus begging the queſtion, you neither prooue your worſhip by the Bible, nor anſwer one of the foure apparant reaſons, which we bring in our article, where it is falſe and contrary to the Bible, &amp;c.
            
            
               
                  G. G. To the intent that mine anſwer and your accuſation may ſtand the cléerer to be ſéene into, and the better to be iudged of, I draw your words into a ſyllogiſme thus.
               
                  Whatſoeuer aſſemblies worſhip the true God after a

falſe manner, their worſhip being made of the inuention of man, euen of the man of ſinne, &amp;c. the ſame are not the true Churches of God.
                  But the aſſemblies as they generally ſtand in England, doo worſhip the true God after a falſe manner, their worſhip being made of the inuention of man, &amp;c.
                  Therefore the aſſemblies in England be not the true churches of God.
               
               I did not, nor doo not deny the firſt part of this argument, the propoſition, ſo that we vnderſtand by falſe maner of worſhip, and the ſame made of the inuention of man, ſuch a falſe manner as dooth ouerthrow the very ground and foundation of faith, and make an vtter ſeperation from the Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Such as the worſhip is in popery, where they teach and doo many things contrary to the principles of faith, placing holineſſe and the worſhip of God in their owne inuentions, and ſéeking remiſſion of ſinnes, and the merite of eternall life, in euery beggerly ſuperſticious obſeruation and ceremony. But if by falſe manner of worſhip, yée vnderſtand euery error, fault &amp; corruption, in matters of religion, which though they be euill and to be condemned, yet ouerthrow not the faith nor the very eſſence of Gods true worſhip, but be in circumſtances, or in parts that may be maimed, and yet the life remaine: then I deny the propoſition as moſt erronious, falſe, and hereticall For king Dauid with the princes, the Préeſts, the Leuites, and people, erred, and that groſly, contrary to the expreſſe law of God, Numb. 7. verſ. 9. when they carried the Arke vpon a Cart: yet were they euen then the true Church of God. It was a great offence, that in the dayes of ſome good Kings of Iuda, the people ſacrificed in the high places, but only to the Lord▪ 
                  2. Kings. 11. &amp;. 14. 15. They ſhould by Gods appointment haue doone it at Ieruſalem onely: yet were they neuertheleſſe Gods people. The Paſſouer was a principall part of Gods worſhip, but they kept it not ſo preciſely according to the law, of a long time, as they did in the 18. yeare of Ioſias. 2. King. 23. 2. Chron. 35. The Preachers at Corinth did very euill in building Timber, Straw, and Hay, vpon the foundation: and ſo did the people which ſorted themſelues

as it were by ſeuerall companies to follow them. But yet becauſe they held Chriſt the foundation in the true doctrine, S. Paul ſaith, their workes ſhould burne, they ſhould ſuffer loſſe, neuertheleſſe they themſelues ſhould be ſaued as it were by fier. 1. Cor. 3.
               
               Now to come vnto the ſecond part of your argument, the aſſumption, which is, that the Church of England dooth worſhip the true God after a falſe manner, their worſhip being made of, &amp;c. I did deny that, by affirming that the worſhip of our Church, is the imbracing the holy Bible, by the doctrine thereof, &amp;c▪ Ye ſay, I beg the queſtion, and prooue not our worſhip by the Bible. And I ſay (if yée call it begging) you beg the queſtion, &amp; would haue that graunted vnto yée as true, which is moſt falſe. For excepting imperfections, wants, ſpots, blemiſhes, &amp; faults, which deſtroy not the true worſhip of God, our Church dooth worſhip the Lord aright, without hereſie, blaſphemy, or idolatry. The doctrine of our Church is publiſhed: if yée can take exception againſt any point, to be hereſie or blaſphemie, bring it foorth that it may be tried by the Bible. Then next yée complaine further, that I do not anſwer one of thoſe 4. apparant reaſons which yée bring, why it is falſe and contrary to the Bible. Well then they may now be conſidered. Thus yée haue noted them with figures ouer the head, our worſhip being made of the 1 inuention of man, euen of the 2 man of ſinne, 3 erronious, and 4 impoſed vpon vs. I know not for what cauſe they ſhould be called apparant, vnleſſe by a farre fetched trope of Metonymie, becauſe they manifeſt and make apparant your vanitie, and Anabaptiſticall error. For the firſt thrée be no more but one bare affirmation of that principall tranſgreſſion which yée charge vs withall. For all falſe worſhip is mans inuention, whether it be the inuention of the man of ſinne, or of any other man, it is all one before God, who reſpecteth not perſons, but the wickedneſſe of the ſinne. Alſo to be mans inuention in Gods worſhip, and to be erronious is all one. For whatſoeuer man inuenteth in Gods worſhip, is erronious: and whatſoeuer in the ſame is erronious, hath béene inuented by man. So that the thrée firſt are

all one bare affirmation, and the very ſame with your article. Your Anabaptiſticall error is in the fourth: for yée challenge ſuch a fréedome to the Church, as that nothing may be impoſed vpon the flockes, no not any thing that the Church gouernours ſhall decrée by the word, which dooth ouerthrow the diſcipline in a great part. Then yée procéed and ſay, for further manifeſtation of our worſhip in particular, let the booke of Common prayer be examined by the word of God: which yée terme a great pregnant idoll full of errors, blaſphemies, and abhominations. If the booke ſtand to be tried by Gods word, there is no doubt, but as all things done by men, euen the beſt, it ſhall be found vnperfect. He that will haue it to be no true worſhip of God, in which there be errors and ſpots, holdeth the hereſie of perfection, which is very foule and deteſtable: for it is as farre beyond our power, to bee perfect in Gods worſhip, as to performe perfect obedience in the ſecond table of the lawe. And touching the booke of Common prayer, let the reader conſider, it is not the queſtion betwéene vs, whether there be faults in it, great faults, or how many: but whether it be a great pregnant idol, full of hereſies, blaſphemies, and abhominations? I confeſſe that all men ought with vtter deteſtation, to ſhunne our worſhip, if it be ſuch as you accuſe it. But indéed your accuſation is falſe, your ſlaunders are foule and impudent. This ſhall appeare by following your words as they be ſet downe, where yée name thoſe blaſphemous abhominations, which yée charge the booke withall, in their ſeueral rankes▪ Yée aſke vs where we find in the new Teſtament our Romiſh faſts, our Ember daies, Saints éeues, and Lent. I am indéed out of all doubt, and moſt aſſured, that if a man read ouer, not onely the new Teſtament, but alſo both old and new, from the very beginning to the end, he ſhall neuer finde any allowance of Romiſh faſts. I ſay likewiſe of the Booke of Common prayer, that there be no Romiſh faſts in it: and that yée doo moſt iniuriouſly ſlaunder and belie vs in matching our Church in this point with the blaſphemous ſynagog of Rome. For that Antichriſtian Church, de rogating in all things from the Croſſe of Chriſt, hath vpon certaine daies, and at certaine times,

times, appointed an abſtinence from meates, placing therein the worſhip of God, remiſſion of ſinnes, and the merite of eternall life. The Church of England dooth vtterly condemne this as the doctrine of Diuels, 1. Timoth. 4 pronouncing them enimies to the croſſe of Chriſt, which maintaine meritorious faſting. We teach that the kingdome of God is not meat and drinke, but righteouſnes and peace, and ioy in the Holy-ghoſt. Rom. 14. And that there is no holineſſe in eating or not eating, but an abſtinence whereby we may humble our ſelues, and be more feruent in prayer. The politike lawes of this land, which appoint that vpon certaine daies men ſhall not eat fleſh, doo it in reſpect of the common-wealth, as to maintaine Nauigation ſo much the better, by incouraging men to fiſh, and for the ſpare of the bréed of yoong cattle: appointing moreouer a penaltie for ſuch as ſhall take the daies to be obſerued as meritorious Romiſh faſts. Therefore let all men héere at the firſt conſider, how ſophiſtically yée doo argue: that the Church of England dooth abſteine from fleſh vpon ember dayes, Saints Eues, and in Lent: therefore the Church of England dooth maintaine and obſerue Romiſh faſts. Thus dooth one cracke of your great ordinance, vaniſh onely into ſmoake. Then yée ſay, your idol feaſts, your Alhallowes, Candlemas, ſeuerall Lady dayes, Saints dayes, and dedicating Churches vnto Saints. Héere alſo yée thunder out terror, as if the Church of England did worſhip idols, and celebrate feaſts in the honour of falſe gods: and yet all is but a ſtarke lie, and a wicked ſlander. And I would wiſh all men to obſerue the boldneſſe and eloquence which yée haue in this vaine. For whereas the ſynagog of Antichriſt, denying the onelye mediation of our bleſſed Lord Ieſus, did ſet vp the Saints as mediators, did praye vnto them, worſhip them, celebrate holy dayes in their honour, and dedicate churches vnto them: the Church of England for theſe and ſuch like abhominations, hath ſeparate her ſelfe from them, teaching by the holye Scriptures, that there is one God, and one mediator betwéene1. Timoth. God and man, the man Ieſus Chriſt. That the ſame only true God is to be worſhipped alone, and called vppon

through the only mediation of his beloued Sonne, in whome
                     
                        〈…〉
                     ath. 4. 
                        〈…〉
                     al. 51. 
                        〈…〉
                     ath. 3. he is well pleaſed. That Saincts are not to be worſhipped, neyther the bleſſed Virgin, nor any other, nor no dayes to be celebrated in their honour, nor Churches dedicated vnto thē: how bitterly then do you ſclaunder? Ye will reply, that the Saincts dayes be kept in our Church: yea but ye muſt ſhewe that they be kept in their honour, which ye ſhall not be able to doo, ſéeing the contrary is manifeſt, the Statute expreſſing that our Church doth call thē Holydayes, not for the Saincts ſakes, but for the holy exerciſes vſed vpon them in publike aſſemblyes. Diuers Churches alſo among vs are called by the names of thoſe Saincts which they were dedicated vnto, but to ſay that we do therefore dedicate Churches vnto them, is very ridiculous. In the City Athens there was a place of Iudgement which bare the name of Mars, S. Luke calleth
                     
                        〈…〉
                     s. 17. it by the ſame name, doth he therefore dedicate it alſo vnto that heathen God of battaile? When we call S. Peters Church, or Paules Churchyard, it is but to diſtinguiſh them by the names by which they are commonly knowne and called. Then follow our Comminations, Rogations, Purifications. Touching Comminations, they be a part of the Canonicall Scripture which is to be read in the Church. Rogations, I take to be the compaſſing in of the limits and bounds of Pariſhes, which is commaunded only to auoide contention and ſtrife that might growe, and there is nothing in the booke of Common Prayer touching theſe, that euer I could finde. Purifications are annexed, only to make vp your riming figure: for neither the booke, nor the doctrine of the Church of England, doth ſpeake of any Purification, but only in the bloud of the Lambe. There is a Thankſgiuing preſcribed for Women after Childbirth, but neyther for Iewiſh Purification, or Popiſh Superſtition, &amp; therefore not in ſuch ſort to be condemned. After comes in our Tithes▪ Offerings, Mortuaries. For the Tithes and Mortuaries, I do not finde them once named in the booke, the Offrings in déede are. But ye will ſay that is no great matter, ſéeing they be in our Church. That is true, but yet they are but for maintenance of the

Miniſterie, &amp; not as a matter tyed of neceſſitie vnto a Prieſthoode, as in the time of the Lawe: and if they were, the error could not be fundamentall. In the next place are brought in, our manner of viſiting the ſicke, and howſling them with the Sacrament, our Abſolution, blaſphemous Dirges, and Funerall Sermons ouer and for the dead. There is preſcribed a manner of viſiting the ſicke, and ſo is there in the leiturgies of ſome other Churches that profeſſe the Goſpell, but where haue ye ſéene it practiſed, or the practiſe vrged by thoſe that haue the gouernment of our Church, at their hands which are able and diligent Paſtors? Whereby your iniurious dealing may appeare, in charging all the aſſemblies as they generally ſtand in England with matters which the greater part do not practiſe, nor yet are required. For if the ſicke man be by the Miniſter of the word inſtructed, exhorted, comforted, and ſtrengthened in faith and repentance, yea euery way prepared to depart ioyfully in the Lord, it is that which the booke aimeth at, neither is there any more required, although he vſe no preſcript forme ſet downe. By your phraſe of howſling with the Sacrament, ye would make the ſimple beleeue, that the Popiſh Howſling is retained among vs. This is but a falſe kind of packing, ſeeing our Church vtterly condemneth all the wicked blaſphemous corrupt doctrine of the Papiſts touching the Lords Supper: and alſo denyeth that a man is of neceſſitie to receiue this Sacrament at his death. If yes replie, that howſoeuer we teach, yet the booke implyeth a neceſſitie, which appeareth by that it doth appoint a priuate Communion. I anſwer, that euen the booke doth denie it to be a matter of neceſſitie, and doth appoint it but to relieue the trouble which might ariſe in weake conſciences through the want thereof, for theſe be the words of the booke: The Curates ſhall diligently from time to time, but ſpecially in the Plague time, exhort their Pariſhioners to the often receiuing in the Church, of the holy Communion of the bodie and bloud of our Sauiour Chriſt, which if they doo they ſhall haue no cauſe in their ſuddaine viſitation, to be diſquieted for lacke of the ſame. And if any ſicke perſon that would receiue this

Sacrament, hath any impediment that he can not, the Booke willeth the Miniſter to inſtruct him, that if he do truly repent him of his ſinnes, and ſtedfaſtly beléeue that Ieſus Chriſt hath ſuffered death vppon the Croſſe for him, and ſhead his bloud for his redemption, earneſtly remembring the benefites he hath thereby, and giuing him hartie thanks therefore, he doth eate and drincke the Bodie and Bloud of our Sauiour Chriſt profitably to his ſoules health, although he do not receiue the Sacrament with his mouth. How maliciouſly then do you charge the aſſemblies in England with howſling the ſicke with the Sacrament, when all the learned, faithfull, diligent Paſtors do, as the booke requireth, exhort thoſe that be of their flockes to the often receiuing of this holy Sacrament in the publike aſſemblie, as the due place for publike ſeales, and the people by inſtruction being growen ſo ſtrong, that they do not in their ſickneſſe require it, and ſo in the moſt Congregations which are well taught, the thing is not practiſe
                     •
                  ? The Sinagog of Antichriſt deuiſed a purgatorie which is blaſphemous againſt the bloud of Chriſt. They had indéed their Dirges, euen blaſphemous prayers for the dead. That Purgatorie do we vtterly deny as a wicked inuention, we condemne prayer for the dead, and therfore, where ye tearme thoſe prayers which are read at burials blaſphemous Dirges ouer and for the dead, yee are more then impudent in lying. Funerall Sermons I finde not inioyned by the booke, nor commaunded by any Lawe. Ye adde further, our corrupt manner of adminiſtring the Sacraments, the Font, the Croſſe in Baptiſme, Baptiſme by women, Goſſippings, the blaſphemous Collects that we vſe vnto this Sacrament, Byſhopings, with all the hereticall Collects of the Booke, which, as ye ſay, is a wearines vnto ye to repeate, though not to vs both to tollerate and defend. When ye ſhewe ſome reaſon, why the Font is an abhomination, I ſhall knowe what to ſay. Touching the Croſſe, it muſt needes be confeſſed that it was blaſphemouſly and horribly abuſed in Poperie, they aſcribing vnto it power to driue out and expell Deuils, and worſhipping it with deuine honour. In my iudgement alſo,

the holy Church of God, within ſhort time after the bleſſed Apoſtles, and the reuerend godly Paſtors, did offend, in taking ouermuch libertie to ordeine Ceremonies Symbolicall, as that and ſuch like, yet no doubt very reuerend godly learned men, led by the example of thoſe holy Fathers of olde, haue iudged it lawfull for the Church to ordeine ſuch Ceremonies. Touching the Baptiſme by women, it is condemned both by the chéefe gouernours in our Church▪ and others, and is not practiſed vnleſſe it be among the popiſh and ſuperſticious ignorant ſort. By Goſſyppings, I ſuppoſe yée meane the witneſſes at baptiſme, a thing vſed in the beſt reformed churches, and thought to be expedient: ſo that yée doo not heerein condemne the Church of England, but all Churches▪ Biſhoping of children is little practiſed, for vnleſſe the people require it by offering their children few Biſhops doo vrge them thervnto, onely this excepted, that they be taught and inſtructed in the Catechiſme. The blaſphemous collects which we vſe in the Sacrament, and all the hereticall collects of the booke, doo trouble yée very ſore, and weary yée to repeat. But if it pleaſed God, I would ye were as weary of lying and ſlaundering, as ye ſhould be in ſéeking in all the collects of the booke, if yée were bound to ſéeke and to finde, I will not ſay ſome faultes, ſéeing all things framed by the beſt men, may haue imperfections and faults: but ſome blaſphemies or hereſies. If yée haue any regard at all what ye ſay, gather your wits together, conſider what is blaſphemie, and what is hereſie, and then note the collect where it is, and what it is▪ There ſhall neuer any man be able to prooue, that the Church of England dooth tollerate, much leſſe defend, either blaſphemie or hereſie. Yet you, as if your words were true as the Goſpell, clap your wings, and crowe, ſaying, but this candle may not be lighted, leaſt the people ſhould ſée into the abhominabl
                     •
                   ingredients, which you their Antichriſtian miniſters doo giue them, or rather ſell them, in the whore of Babilons cuppe. All this is but your foule toong, which is no way ſo eloquent, as in rowling out ſlaunderous accuſation of blaſphemies, hereſies, and abhominations, with ſuch like. Moreouer, whereas the caſe ſtandeth

thus in the church of England: that there is controuerſie about the Booke: and that one part dooth approoue all things in the ſame as good and alowable, or at leaſt as tollerable, the other condemne certaine things as corruptions, and ſuch as néede reformation. I would know how ye could abandon all the aſſemblyes? to this ye make a double anſwer, firſt, that vſing a part, they do homage to the whole. This is a fooliſh anſwer, void of all reaſon, for can we not praiſe the good things in a man, but we ſhall allowe his faultes and imperfections? Your ſecond anſwer is this: Neither can the cunningeſt of ye all make the beſt part of it other then a péece of Swines fleſh, an abhomination to the Lord. Who could imagin that ſuch a frenſie might take hold of any, that in mad furie they ſhould not ſpare after a ſort to ſtrike at God, and to blaſpheme that which is moſt holy? for ye knowe right well▪ that there is in the booke of Common Prayer, much of the ſacred Canonicall Scripture, there is the Lords prayer, the tenne Commaundements, with many other partes and ſentences, there be the articles of the Chriſtian faith, are all theſe become Swines fleſh an abhomination to the Lorde? Let not ſimple men wonder that ye are bold to proclaime all the Miniſters of the Goſpell within this land, to be the marked ſeruants of Antichriſt, when ye dare preſume to ſet your ſtincking brand of pitch vpon the moſt holy things of God. Ye will héere cry out of iniurie, and ſay that ye eſtéeme all thoſe parcels of the ſacred Canonicall Scriptures, in thē
                  ſelues to be holy and pure. What is it then which turneth them into Swines fleſh, and maketh them an abhomination to the Lord? is it becauſe they be bound together, and make one booke with the hereticall Collects? then take you héede, leaſt being in priſon, and fettred with heretikes, ye be turned alſo into Heretikes. If ye ſay, it is our abuſe which turneth ſo holy things into Swines fleſh, I aunſwere, that the abuſe of holy things is abhominable, but the things themſelues remaine vndefiled: and ye muſt remember that we deale touching the partes of the booke, but abuſe is no part thereof. When ye ſay the beſt part thereof is no other then a péece of

Swines fleſh, it can not be tranſferred from the partes vnto the abuſes. If it were graunted vnto ye, which yet is to be denied as moſt fantaſticall, that all read prayer offred vp vnto God as a ſacrifice, is Idolatrie: neuertheleſſe your ſaying is wicked and blaſphemous, ſeeing that the reading is not any part of the booke, neither doth it peruert or defile the things themſelues which are read. Thus your firſt accuſation, that we worſhip the true God after a falſe manner, is with falſe ſclaunder, and furious outrage of ſpéech, crying out of Idolatrie, blaſphemies, and abhominations, when as ye can ſhewe no one ground of the holy Religion and worſhip of God, which is not holden ſound and entire among vs, only ye rippe vp corruptions and ſpots in Ceremonies, orders, and circumſtances, which touch not the foundation, but are ſuch as men may erre in, and yet be Gods déere children, and true woorſhippers.
            
         
         
            
               The Brow▪
               
               
                  
                     Iohn. 4. 23. 24.
                  God is a Spirit, and muſt be worſhipped in ſpirit and truth.
               
            
            
               The reaſons why wee diſalow of read prayer, in ſtead of ſpirituall prayers, that though they may be read for meditation, as any other mens writs, yet is it Idolatry to offer vp to God ſuch manner of ſacrifices eyther priuately, or in publique aſſemblyes.
            
            1 No apocripha muſt be brought into the publique aſſemblyes, for there only the liuely voyce of Gods owne graces, of the word, and the ſpirit, muſt be heard in the publique aſſemblyes. And more lawfull is it to vſe Homelyes, then reade prayers vnto God.
            2 To do any thing in the worſhip of God without the teſtimonie of his word, is ſinne: but there is no ground in the Scripture for ſuch manner of praying, as hauing no witneſſe of the word, whether God be pleaſed with them, or no.
            3 Admitte that it were a thing indifferent, as we call it, for the forme of prayer, which is but a mockery, to call reading in ſtead of ſpirituall calling on God, to be but altering the forme, or chaunging the manner, whereas in deede it is

changing the worke of the Spirit into an Image, or Idoll. Yet is it a bondage, and breaking of that libertie, which Chriſt hath purchaſed for vs, and therefore moſt deteſtable.
            4 Becauſe true prayer muſt be of faith and knowledge vttered with the hart, and liuely voyce vnto God, I am perſwaded it is preſumptuous ignorance to bring a booke to ſpeake for vs ſuch things, as we could not otherwiſe vtter in Gods ſight.
            5 To worſhip the true God after another manner then he hath taught, is Idolatry: but he hath commaunded vs to come vnto him being heauy loden, with contrite hearts, yea to cry out vnto him in the griefe of our ſoule, yea and as S. Paule ſayth, The Spirit helpeth our infirmities with groning and ſighing that can not be expreſſed, and how dare we then being a dead tree vnto God, to ſtand reading of the ſame in ſtead of faithfull petitions, quenching the Spirit.
            6 We muſt ſtriue in prayer with continuing, with feruency, without wauering, which we can not doo vppon a booke.
            7 We muſt call vppon God in prayer at all times, as the neceſsities of the time requireth, not making a babling of many things, whereof we haue not any preſent neceſsitie: but ſtinted ſeruice cannot be ſo applyed, ſo it is but a babling of vaine repetitions.
            8 All the deuiſes of Antichriſt, though it were otherwiſe lawfull, not being neceſſary, ought to be abhorred of true Chriſtians, eſpecially ſuch reliques as maintaine ſuperſtition, but to reade other mens bookes to God in ſtead of true prayers, and ſtinted ſeruice, were deuiſed by Antichriſt, and maintaine ſuperſtition, and an Idoll Miniſterie: therefore ought to be diſallowed.
            The prayers and worſhip of ſuch Miniſters and people as ſtand vnder a falſe gouerment, are not acceptable, nor haue any promiſe in Gods ſight, not only becauſe they aske amiſſe, but becauſe they keepe not his commaundements.
            
               
               
                  G. G. 
                  Read prayer is one chiefe thing for which yee condemne 
                  our worſhip as Idolatrous and moſt deteſtable, and for that cauſe to be annexed vnto this firſt accuſation.
               
               
                  
                     God is a Spirit, and muſt be worſhipped in ſpirit and in truth.
                  
                  
                     The Brow. 
                     THE Scripture doth moſt briefely and pithily ſeuer all 
                     fantaſticall deuiſes of man, from the pure and ſincere worſhip of God, preſcribed in his Word. For ſeeing all fleſh is graſſe, and the wiſedome thereof fooliſhnes with God, it muſt needes follow, that mē earthly minded ſhould pleaſe themſelues in ſuch pretended religion, as agreeth nothing with the diuine nature of God. It is needfull then in the worſhip of God, that we thus alwayes conſider with our ſelues, we haue to do with God himſelfe, and not with men, who is ſo farre differing from vs, that thoſe things which are moſt eaſy, and pleaſing vnto vs, is a weariſomnes and abhominable ſacrifice in his ſight: and although God dwelleth in the heauens in his diuinitie incomprehenſible, yet haue we a perfect rule, whereby we know what is agreeing to his will, namely, his written word, for that we may be heere taught 1. That all hipocriſy in ſuch things as hee hath commaunded, be carefully auoyded. 2. That wee attempt not to do any thing in his worſhip, whereof we haue not ſpeciall warrant from his word, of which ſort we take all manner of ſtinted prayers offered vp as a worſhipping of God, diſagreeing from the nature of God (which ſeeth in ſecret) and ſo agreeth with our fleſhly nature, that we can not pray as we ought, &amp; ſo we ſeeke to help our ſelues with ſuch a broken ſtaffe, wearying our ſelues with our owne deuiſes, without any promiſe to receyue bleſsing thereby. And therefore where you affirme, that a man may pray in ſpirit and truth, with ſighes, and grones, proceeding from faith, when prayer is read, that is not true, for if their ſighes came from faith, it would miniſter matter and prayer without a booke, yea no doubt, a troubled mind is the penne of a readie writer; and to worſhip God in ſpirit, is, when the inward faith of the heart bringeth forth true inuocation, and it is
                     
                     then in truth, when ſimply it agreeth with Gods word. But you would teach men in ſtead of powring forth their harts, to help themſelues vpon a booke, yea, to fetch their cauſe of ſorrowing &amp; ſighing from an other mans writing, euen in the time of their begging at Gods hand. We graunt, that prayers conceaued without faith, ar not acceptable, yet may the ſame be called ſpirituall, becauſe it is the gift of the Spirit, though not ſanctified in him that ſo hipocritically mocketh with God. But what maketh this to our queſtion of ſtinted read prayers in Gods worſhip? But ſay you, to make read prayers only to ſerue for meditation, is falſe doctrine, wherein, me thinke you offer great iniurie, for we affyrmed that it had ſuch vſe as other of mēs writings haue. But it ſeemeth you make little cōſcience to ſlander vs, and heere you fall into an error your ſelfe, affirming, and going about to proue, that reading of prayers is not for meditation at all: the proofe you bring, is, that Chriſt ſaid not to his diſciples, whē ye meditate, ſay thus, Our Father, but when you pray, ſay thus▪ 
                        &amp;c. Where, beſide that you make no difference between your owne Liturgies, &amp; the holy word of God, which is not of any priuate interpretation: Beſides this I ſay you ſeeme to proue, that the Lords prayer, &amp; all other prayers in the Canonicall Scripture ſerue not at all for meditation. Well, you haue hereby made the matter apparant, that read prayers vpon a booke are as acceptable, as faithfull prayers conceiued by the ſpirit, &amp; vttered with vnderſtanding. You ſay that prayers read or conceiued, being void of faith, is but vaine babling: we ſay the ſame, but what of this forſooth? you cannot ſee by what cenſure it can be called Idolatry. If falſe worſhip cannot be called Idolatry, let the firſt and ſecond Commaundements be witneſſes, ſo that it is not our pennes, but the penne of Gods own finger that hath iudged all deuiſes of man, &amp; hipocriticall worſhip of Idolatry. And although all the breaches of the firſt Table were not Idolatry, yet you know that to worſhip our own deuiſes, is Idolatry. Is not prayer a ſpeciall part of the firſt Commaundement, and our Sauiour Chriſt comprehendeth all the foure firſt Commandements in this, that we loue God aboue all:
                     
                     the tranſferring of any part whereof from God, muſt needs be idolatry. But ſay you, if we do thus &amp; hold withall, that no idolator can be ſaued, thē ſurely are all loſt, &amp;c. This is countrey diuinity, if the Salt haue loſt his ſauour, what ſhould be ſeſoned therwith, we hold that no idolator cā be ſaued without true repentance, &amp; renouncing their ſinne ſo far as God ſhall ſhew it thē, yea &amp; craue with Dauid for pardon for their hidden &amp; ſecret ſins. And doo you thinke any man liuing is void of idolatry, either inwardly or outwardly, ſo long as we liue, or that we can keep any one cōmandement in perfection? The Lord therfore giue vs repentance: for in ſome things we ſin all. Methinks this ſhould not be, M. Giffords language to be ſo ignorant in the principles of religion, &amp; if you haue waighed our arguments no better then your preface, it ſhall be greeuous to me to make any aunſwer.
                  
               
               To condemne and ouerthrow read prayer, yée bring, as the ground or foundation of all your matter, this ſentence▪ 
                  God is a ſpirit, and to be worſhipped in ſpirit. Iohn. 5. This ſcripture indéed is cléere and ſtrong, to cut downe all carnall worſhip as diſagréeing from the nature of God. And if any doo maintaine, that the very bodily action of reading prayer, is the worſhip of God, it may fitly be alledged againſt them. But to apply it in that manner which you doo againſt red praier, is friuolous, vnleſſe (as I ſay) yée could prooue, that a man cannot pray by the ſpirit of God, with ſighes and grones procéeding from faith, when the praier is read vpō the booke, or vttered after a preſcript forme. To this you reply with diuers arguments. The firſt is, that if the ſighes and grones were of faith, it would miniſter matter of praier without a booke. This reaſon by a connection is drawne from, and dependeth wholy vpon the force and effect of faith, to miniſter matter of prayer. It is to be framed thus. If the prayer with ſighes and grones were of faith, it would miniſter matter without a booke: but the matter of their prayer, with ſighes and grones, is not miniſtred without a booke, therefore it is not of faith. to make this argument ſtrong and ſufficient from the connection of faith, and the liuely efficacie thereof to vtter prayer, yée

muſt adde two things, the one, that faith is perfect vnto this efficacie, to miniſter matter of praier, and néedeth no helpe. The other, that the effect and power of faith, to miniſter matter of prayer, cannot ſtand nor be ioyned with any outward helpes. Vnleſſe I ſay yée adde theſe two, with the cupling together faith and the effect, which are both of them hereticall, there can be no neceſſarie conſequence. To make it yet more manifeſt, let it be drawne into an other forme of ſyllogyſme▪ thus. That which hath power and efficacie of it ſelfe to miniſter matter of prayer▪ néede not any outward helpe, nor cannot touching the vtterance of matter in prayer, ſtand with any outward helpe: But faith hath force and efficacie in it ſelfe to miniſter matter of prayer: Therefore faith néeds not the helpe of a booke, nor cannot ſtand with any outward helpe, touching the vtterance of matter in prayer: And ſo conſequently, the ſighes and grones in prayer red, cannot be of faith. This conſequence ſhall neuer be brought in, vnleſſe yée frame your argument after that ſort. So that both theſe fantaſticall errors be included in your ſpéech, the one, that faith touching the efficacie to miniſter matter of praier is ſo abſolutely perfect, that it néedeth no outward helpe, the other, that it cannot touching prayer ſtand with any outward helpe. I doo acknowledge that there be no ſighes nor grones, nor any praiers that can be regarded of God, but ſuch as come from faith. I doo alſo hold, that faith is not in any, without ſome efficacie and power to vtter ſome matter of praier. But now we muſt conſider the degrées thereof: for doubtleſſe if there were in men a perfection of knowledge, of faith, and of quickneſſe, there ſhould néed no outward helpe: but the beſt come farre ſhort of that. Such as approche néereſt there vnto, néed ſo much the leſſe any outward helpe. But the moſt are ignorant, weake, ſhort of memory, dull and ſlow, and néed all helpes to ſtirre them vp, and to direct them, euen as children, that are to be ſtayed vp and led by the hand. Praier indéed is a ſpirituall worke, procéeding from faith, which is a ſpirituall gift, but yet it doth ſtand with outward meanes and helpes. The Holy-ghoſt alone dooth worke faith in man, but yet it commeth by hearing, Rom. 10,
                  
Faith bringeth foorth prayer, but we muſt conſider, that as the ſame faith commeth by hearing, and is grounded vpon the word, ſo is it cheriſhed, ſupported, increaſed, continued, and quickened in efficacie, and made more forcible vnto euery good worke by thoſe helps of outward meanes. For further confirmation ye adde, yea no doubt, a troubled minde is the penne of a ready writer. Let it ſtand in forme of ſyllogiſme thus. That which is the pen of a ready writer, néedeth not the helpe of a booke. But a troubled minde is the pen of a ready writer: therefore it néedeth not the helpe of a Booke. The propoſition is true, if by the pen of a ready writer yée vnderſtand an abſolute perfection of knowledge, chéerefulneſſe, direction, memorie and vtterance. But that was not in Moſes, Daniel, Paul, or any other. Therefore héere againe yée runne vpon the rocke of an hereticall opinion of perfection. Your aſſumption, where yée ſay: no doubt, a troubled minde is the pen of a ready writer, is vtterly falſe, and your bold affirmation without ſcripture is not enough, ſéeing there be many ſo perplexed and confuſed in the trouble of their minde, and oppreſſed with ignorance, that they cannot pray, nor know not what to vtter: which, when they haue inſtruction and conſolation miniſtred vnto them by ſome godly man, or if that chéefe help faile, by reading vpon a booke, poure foorth teares and ſupplications.
               Your next reaſon is in many words, which yet I will repeate. To worſhip God (ſay you) in ſpirite, is when the inward faith of the heart bringeth foorth true inuocation: and it is then in truth, when it ſimply agreeth with Gods word. But you would teach men in ſteed of powring foorth theyr hearts, to helpe themſelues vpon a booke, yea to fetch the cauſe of their ſighing and ſorrowing from an other mans writing, euen in the time of their begging at Gods hand. I will alſo drawe it into a ſyllogiſme, to the end it may the better be iudged of. None worſhip God in ſpirite, but they which from the inward faith of the heart bring foorth true inuocation, that is, ſuch as ſimply agréeth with the word of God. But all ſuch as read vpon the booke the prayer which they pray,

fetch the cauſe of their ſorrowing from an other mans writing in the time that they pray, and doo not from the inward faith of the heart, bring foorth true inuocation. Therfore none that reade their praier vpon the booke, doo worſhip God in ſpirit. The propoſition I aſſent vnto as ſound and good: for it is no true inuocation except it agrée with Gods word. It is not to worſhip in ſpirit, vnleſſe it procéed from faith out of the heart. But your aſſumption, which is, that all that reade the praier which they pray, doo not from the inward faith of the heart, bring foorth true inuocation, I cannot allowe, ſéeing yée bring nothing for proofe thereof, but that which is moſt friuolous. For whereas yée ſay in the firſt part of your confirmation, that we would haue men in ſtéed of powring foorth theyr hearts, to helpe themſelues vpon a booke, yée ſpeake vntruly and fooliſhly. For we wiſh men to vſe the helpe of a booke that they may the better poure forth their hearts to God. Being ſuch as are not otherwiſe throughly able.
               The next part of your confirmation, is euen to as great purpoſe, when yée ſay, We would haue men fetch the cauſe of their ſighing and ſorrowing, from an other mans writing, euen in the time of their begging at Gods hand. For how fondly doo yée make that to be the cauſe, which dooth but manifeſt the cauſe? for the cauſe of all ſighing and ſorrowing, is the ſinne and miſerie which is within vs: which we may the better behold and expreſſe by inſtruction. I haue gréeuous ſinne, and wrath belonging therevnto, which I doo partlye know, and can make ſome moane therein, and praye: I come into the publike aſſembly, where I heare the miniſter preach the word, which dooth more fully laye open and diſplay my ſinne and miſery: I am héereby driuen into déeper ſighing and ſorrowing, with vehement praier in my heart vnto God: ſhall it be ſaide, that I doo now fetch the cauſe of my ſorrowing from an other mans ſpéech in the time of my begging at Gods hands? If not, then why ſhould I be ſaid to fetch the cauſe from the booke, which alſo dooth inſtruct me? the like may be ſaid, when the congregation dooth pray with their paſtor: they fetch not the cauſe of their ſighing from him: but are ſtirred vp by him. Your next words ſtand thus. The reaſons

why we diſalow of read prayers, in ſteed of ſpiritual prayers, that though they may be read for meditation, as any other mens writs▪ yet is it Idolatrie, to offer vp to God ſuch manner of ſacrifices, either priuately, or in the publike aſſemblies. Yée are very angrie, that I termed your reaſons, by which yée oppoſe read praier vnto ſpirituall praier, ſpirituall fantaſies. But take you héed that they grow not to be worſe. Yée are alſo gréeued, that I call them your ſtuffe, but how good ſtuffe it is, let the pure word try. I ſaid it is falſe doctrine to make read prayer ſerue only for meditation. My proofe was this, that Chriſt ſaith not, when ye meditate, but when ye pray, ſay thus, Our Father which art in heauen: and héere ye fling about as if ye had Béez. For firſt ye exclaime that I make ſmal conſcience to ſclaunder ye, becauſe I ſaid ye make read prayer ſerue only for meditation, which is falſe doctrine. Meditation (as I take it) comprehendeth all that is done in ſtudying and muſing when one readeth, the praying is another. If ye can ſhew a third vſe when one readeth prayer, I will confeſſe an error, otherwiſe, though ye haue not expreſſed the word only, yet ye haue in effect vttered ſo much, when ye ſay read prayer is not to be prayed. Secondly, ye charge me to deny that read prayer ſerueth for meditation at all, which is in deede falſe doctrine: becauſe I ſaid Chriſt ſaith not when ye meditate, but when ye pray ſay thus, Our Father which art &amp;c. Do I not ſay truly that Chriſt ſaith not when ye meditate, but when yée pray, ſay thus, Our Father which art &amp;c. How can you then but like Spiders ſucke that poyſon from thence? Thirdly, ye accuſe me, that I make no difference betwéene our owne Leiturgies and the Canonicall Scripture, which is a moſt friuolous cauill, ſéeing our queſtion is about reading of prayer, whether it be Canonicall Scripture, or framed from thence according to the rules of godly prayer. Thus haue ye anſwered nothing at all vnto that commaundement which I alleaged giuen by our Sauiour, to vſe that preſcript forme of prayer, but only by ſhift and cauill. Then ye goe about to proue that euery ſinne againſt the firſt Table of the Lawe is Idolatry, but with no ſhewe of reaſon. And heere ye ſcoffe becauſe I ſayd, if euery ſinne that is againſt the firſt Table

be Idolatry, who ſhall be ſaued? and ye demaund who is frée from Idolatry? an abſurd ſpéech: for the Scripture doth not call the godly either murtherers, théeues, idolaters, or ſuch like. I thought we had not reaſoned about the reliques of ſin which remaine in the beſt ſo long as they liue héere, but of ſuch groſſe idolatry as a Church is to be condemned and forſaken which is defiled therewith. But ſéeing ye confeſſe that all men be idolaters, that is, touching the remnants of ſinne, it muſt néedes followe that there is no Church frée from all ſpottes, for if all the partes and members be defyled, the whole can not be cleane. This doth ouerthrowe all the arguments which yée bring to condemne the Church of England, which haue no force vnleſſe yée will maintaine a perfection: for if a Church and euery member in it can not but of neceſſitie be ſpotted and defyled with ſome remnants of idolatrie, euen by your owne confeſſion: then can ye not reaſon thus, this is a fault, it is idolatrie, therefore this or that aſſemblie which is ſpotted is no true Church, but to be forſaken. But ye muſt ſtand to prooue that the idolatrie is ſo groſſe, that it deſtroyeth the faith, ouerthroweth Gods true worſhip, and ſo deſtroyeth the verie life &amp; béeing of a Church. Thus much about your preface, now follow your argumēts.
               No apocrypha is to be brought into the publike aſſemblyes.
                     
                        ••
                     gum. 1. All read prayer is apocrypha. Therefore no read prayer is to be brought into the publike aſſemblyes.
               In my firſt anſwere I did deale only with the aſſumption or ſecond part of this Argument, affirming that I could not ſée how it can be proued, and ſhewing ſundry abſurdities that would follow; as namely, that a prayer of the Canonicall Scripture being read when one prayeth, ſhould become apocrypha, &amp;c. But you replyed that thoſe abſurdities grow from my miſtaking your words, and I ſawe it was ſo, for our queſtion being about the reading of prayer, and not about the matter it ſelfe, I tooke it, that although yee hold the Lords prayer, and other prayers in the holy Scripture to be Canonicall in themſelues, yet being read to become apocrypha, becauſe ye ſay all read prayer is apocrypha, and did not expreſſe it with this reſtraint, all read prayer framed by men, is apocrypha.

I muſt now take the Argument as you ſay your meaning is, and deale with both the parts thereof. Firſt then touching the propoſition, no apocrypha is to be brought into the publike aſſemblies, what can be more falſe? Apocrypha is oppoſed vnto Canonicall, if nothing may be brought into the Church but the Canonicall Scriptures, then the Sermons and prayers of the paſtors and teachers are to be baniſhed. I knowe your meaning is not at all to exclude theſe, although your words (taking apocrypha as it is in vſe among vs) do in déede ſhut them foorth, and not only them, but any paraphraſe vpon the Scripture, as the Pſalmes in Metre▪ Now to your aſſumption, which ſaith, all read prayer is apocrypha: firſt, it is falſe touching the Pſalmes and the Lords prayer, which be Canonicall when they be prayed. Then further, I ſée no fitneſſe in applying the name apocrypha vnto our ſpéech to God, though it be vſed for that which is not his vndoubted word to vs. For by what name oppoſite to apocrypha, will ye call thoſe prayers which ye do allow? ye will not call them Canonicall, this Argument therfore is falſe and friuolous.
               
                  
                     Argum. 2. We muſt do nothing in the worſhip of God without warrant of his word. Read prayers haue no warrant of his word: Therfore read prayers are not to be vſed in the worſhip of God.
               To this I anſwer at the firſt, that it is great audacitie to affirme, that there is no warrant of the word for read prayer, whē there be ſundry teſtimonies to warrant the ſame, vnleſſe ye will make a difference betwéene that which a man readeth vpon the booke, &amp; that which he hath learned out of the booke. Further I ſaid, I do not remember that euer I haue read in the holy Scriptures, that God commandeth the prayer ſhall be read vpon the booke: for he commendeth this diligēce in all his people, that they ſhould throughly learne to vnderſtand, not only the matters, but alſo the ſentences and phraſes, which his ſpirit taught his holy Prophets and ſeruants to vtter in their prayers, and that this is the reaſon why there be ſo many prayers preſcribed in the booke

of the Pſalmes, and in other bookes of the Scriptures: that whatſoeuer thing befall a man, wherein he is in the feruent affection of his heart to pray vnto the Lord, if he haue in memorie the ſpéeches which holy men in ſuch diſtreſſe vttered, it is a great help vnto him, if not, he may help his memory with a booke. To this you reply, that touching the vſe of ſentences and phraſes of ſcripture, you could eaſily conſent, but that ye perceiue I would not agrée with ye in certaine points, the firſt, that this is required only at the hands of Gods children, with promiſe to be heard and accepted. I wonder with what eyes ye can ſée that I would not agrée with ye in this thing, I put ye out of doubt, I hold aſſuredly, that none haue promiſe to be heard and accepted but Gods children, though they vſe neuer ſo much the ſentences of Scripture in their prayers. The firſt hinderance of your conſent is remoued. The ſecond is, that ye ſée I would not agrée with ye, that the ſame ſpirit doth now teach Gods childrē to pray, which taught the Prophets &amp; holy men in other ages. I profeſſe vnto ye, that I hold it a wicked opinion, to deny that the ſame ſpirit doth nowe teach Gods children to pray, which taught the Prophets, &amp;c. and ſo the ſecond let is remoued. In déede héere you and I diſſent, that I hold, that as our faith is wrought by the word of God, ſo is it nouriſhed and quickned vnto prayer, and euery good work by the ſame, and that the holy Ghoſt hath not only taught matters by the Prophets &amp; Apoſtles, but alſo ſpéeches and phraſes ſit for to vtter ye ſame. And you hold that becauſe the ſame ſpirit now teacheth to pray, which taught the Prophets &amp; Apoſtles that either we may not, or we néede not vſe their▪ ſpéeches. The third ſtop remaineth, which is, that I take it, God ſhould be delighted with words and ſentences. You greatly miſtake it and do but cauill: for I ſhewed my minde, not that God would regard words &amp; ſentences, but we ſhould be holpen and comforted by them. Thus the third and laſt hinderance is alſo remoued, and now you may conſent that in our prayers we may vſe the preſcript formes, ſentences, and phraſes of the word of God. To my next wordes, where I ſayd, the reaſon why there be ſo many prayers

preſcribed in the booke of the Pſalmes, is: that whatſoeuer diſtreſſe befall a man, &amp;c. you reply: yée thinke I halt greatly, that our queſtion being about Idolatrous leiturgies, I ſéeke to ſhrowd my ſelfe vnder the vſe of Canonicall ſcripture. Indéed this would be a learned queſtion, whether idolatrous leiturgies be idolatrie? or whether it be not idolatry to pray an idolatrous praier? who would looke for ſo childiſh a ſhift? you know our queſtion is about the reading of a praier when one prayeth? And if it be not idolatry to vſe the praiers of the ſcriptures, euen in their preſcript forme, then all read praier offred to God as a ſacrifice, is not idolatrie. I reaſon thus: it is not idolatry to pray the Lords praier, or any other preſcript forme deliuered in the Canonicall ſcriptures: therefore it is no idolatry to vſe a preſcript forme of praier, which is framed after the rules of true praier: as to aſke of God alone, through the onely mediation of his ſonne, and for no matters, but ſuch as he hath promiſed to giue: Yée ſay it is not true doctrine, that thoſe Pſalmes and Scriptures were written that we ſhould vſe in our praiers the words there ſet downe. Your reaſon is becauſe there be other vſes. I doo confeſſe there be other vſes, but that might yet be a ſpeciall reaſon, why there be ſo many praiers preſcribed. Then yée ſay yée do not diſalow the ſpeaking, according to the word of God, but that we might not affect ſo much the phraſes of ſpéech, as the true féeling of our wants, He that hath not the féeling of his wants in praier, but affecteth phraſes, is but an hypocrite. But ye are in a vaine opinion, if ye thinke the vſe of the phraſes and ſentences of ſcripture, being fitly applied, is any hinderance either to the féeling or opening our wants, becauſe where ſkill or memorie faileth I would haue them vſe the helpe of a booke. I am, you feare, papiſtically affected vnto words and ſentences. I haue already ſhewed, that this is not to affect the words and ſentences, but the inſtruction, the ſupport and quickning which our faith receiueth by thoſe words &amp; ſentences. And this doctrine is not as you charge it, diſagréeing from the counſell of the Holy ghoſt, which willeth vs to continue in praier, to ſtriue in praier, nor contrarie to Dauid, which ſaid, O my ſoule, &amp;c▪
                   nor to

                  Paul, who teacheth that the ſpirit helpeth our infirmities, and maketh requeſt for vs. But your doctrine, which ſaith, we muſt continue in prayer, therfore we may not vſe ſuch helps: the ſpirit dooth helpe our infirmities, and maketh requeſt for vs, therefore we may not be holpen by the praiers, or by the words of the holy ſcripture, is phantaſticall, for the Holy ghoſt doth helpe our infirmities, and teach vs to pray, by the written word. You thinke it were hypocriticall worſhipping of God, to take helpe by a booke, when we know not what to aſke. If a man know not what to aſke, he ſhall be able to vnderſtand little by the booke. But a man may know what he ſhould aſke, and yet not ſo well able to expreſſe the ſame without helpe, both for memory and feruencie. Stinted praiers (yée ſay) are as Cuſhions for idle papiſts, hypocrites, and Atheiſts. I graunt that ſuch people doo abuſe all the beſt things, ſhall the godly therefore be debarred from the vſe? I doo teach, that whether a man of himſelfe pray without a booke, or vpon a booke, if he pray not in ſpirit with faith, he dooth but offer the ſacrifice of fooles, his praier is abhominable. Therfore it is but your lauiſh ſpéech, when ye ſay I giue libertie to the lame ſacrifices: on the contrary, if a man pray in faith vpon a booke, or without a booke, it is true praier, and ſuch as God heareth. God will haue no ſtrange fire put vpon his Altar, ſay you. I graunt it is ſo: but praiers framed by the rules of ſcripture, and offered vp in faith, are not ſtrange fire. Yée wiſh all men to take héed of this craftie doctrine, and I wiſh all men not to be to haſtie in receiuing new phantaſticall opinions▪ Your anſwer vnto thoſe two Pſalmes, which I noted, were giuen as a preſcript forme of praier to be vſed of the Church, and the forme of bleſſing preſcribed to the Préeſts to bleſſe the people withall, Num. 6▪
                   is more then friuolous. For touching the firſt, which is 92▪ appointed for the Sabaoth, yée graunt it was at their méeting to magnifie the praiſes of God, &amp; many other Pſalmes. But yée demaund, what this maketh for ſtinted leiturgies, papiſticall and erronious, impoſed, &amp;c. I ſay, it maketh nothing at all for that which is papiſticall and erronious. But it prooueth that all read praier is not idolatrie, and

that it is no ſtinting of the ſpirit, to vſe a preſcript forme of praier. Theſe fantaſies of yours are firſt confuted thereby. Then next I argue thus. If I may vſe a whole praier of the ſcripture, and no idolatrie, then a praier that is compoſed by the rules of the ſcriptures may be vſed, and no idolatrie. You deny, that the argument drawne from the vſe of the Pſalmes dooth follow, becauſe praiers compoſed by men, are not equall to the Canonicall ſcripture: and ſo ſhut out all praiers, if yée marke well what yée ſay, that are framed by the Preacher, For let them be holy and good, yet yée may not ſet them as equall with the Canonicall ſcriptures. Againe yée deny the argument, by affirming, that ſinging of Pſalmes was no part of praier, but onely for inſtruction and meditation: ye take vpon ye to prooue this a little after, and when I come to that, ye ſhall haue anſwer. The Pſalm. 102. ye ſay was not a praier of the Church, becauſe it is ſaid, O Lord heare my prayer, and not, O Lord heare our prayer: a poore ſhift, when vſually the church ſpeaketh of her ſelfe in the ſingular number. Touching the bleſſing: ye ſay, that forme of words was not to tie them to vſe thoſe words, but after that manner, which is manifeſtly falſe.
               Touching the orders of ſingers appointed by Dauid, I alledged it to no ſuch end, as you ſéeme to drawe it vnto. But that in ſinging the Pſalmes, they did read them vpon the booke. Héer now ye do not onely deny, that ſinging of pſalmes was any part of praier, but alſo ye will prooue it by the teſtimony of S. Paul to the Epheſians, and to the Collofs. where he exhorteth thē to ſpeake vnto themſelues in pſalmes &amp; hymnes and ſpirituall ſongs. It is a foule audacitie, contrary to the manifeſt word of truth, to affirme that the Pſalmes were not ſunge to God, ſéeing that not onely the ſpeeches be directed in a multitude of places vnto him: but alſo the Holy-ghoſt doth call vpon men in this wiſe. Sing vnto God, ſing a new ſong vnto him, ſing praiſes vnto the Lorde. But beſide this you go further, for in both places by you cited, ye leaue out the latter part of the ſentence, which is, that they ſhould ſing vnto the Lorde with grace in their hearts. Let the reader peruſe

the places, and iudge what kinde of tricke this is. It is moſt cléere, that they did reade the Pſalmes vpon the booke when they did ſing them. It is alſo out of controuerſie, that they did ſing them to the Lord, vnleſſe we will deny the flat word of the Holy-ghoſt, and alſo affirme, that albeit the ſpéech be directed to God, yet they did not in ſinging ſpeake vnto him. It cannot be denied, but that many of the Pſalmes be full of petitions. Alſo praiſe is a part of prayer, and a ſpirituall ſacrifice: this was offered vp to God, in reading vpon the booke, for it is ſaide. Sing praiſes to the Lorde: therefore I conclude, that read prayer hath warrant by the word, and the reading dooth not make it idolatrie, or contrarie to ſpirituall praier. Héere yée complaine againe▪ that this argument dooth not follow, becauſe praiers compoſed by men, are not to be matched with the Canonicall ſcriptures. I haue anſwered this poore ſtale ſhift already▪ that the praiers compoſed by men are no further lawfull, then they be framed by the rules of Gods word for prayer.
               Thus haue I not, as you charge me, laid aſide the queſtion to make new queſtions: but haue diſprooued that your olde queſtion, by ſhewing, that reading the praier which is godly, dooth not make it contrary vnto ſpirituall praier, nor idolatry.
               
                  
                     Argu. 3. We may not in the worſhip of God, receiue any tradition which dooth bring our liberty into bondage. Read Prayer vpon commaundement in the aſſemblies, is a tradition that dooth bring our libertye into bondage. Therefore read prayer, &amp;c.
               To the aſſumption of this argument, I anſwered at the firſt which I particularly rehearſed, how can yée then with any ſhew of truth, ſay my words import a deniall of the Antecedents, aſſumption and all. My words are theſe: The third argument ſaith, that the forme of praier is a bondage and breaking our libertie with, &amp;c. The prooues which I bring do onely ouerthrow the aſſumption, for I did and doo acknowledge the propoſition, which you ſay my words import a deniall of. I would wiſh yée to vſe more ſimplicitie, I ſay it is vngodlye and néere vnto blaſphemy, to affirme that preſcript

forme of prayer, is a tradition, bringing our libertie into bondage, and a changing the worke of the ſpirit into an idoll. My reaſon was and is, that the Lord by Moyſes preſcribed a forme of bleſſing which the Préeſts ſhould vſe Nomb. 6. The Prophets, as in the Pſalmes, preſcribed many formes of prayſes and prayers, to be vſed of the Church. Our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt preſcribed a forme, and ſayd, when yée pray ſay Our Father, &amp;c. If the verie reading, or vſing the preſcript forme commaunded, were a bondage, breaking Chriſtian libertie, or a changing the worke of the Spirit into an idoll, then the Lord God, Moyſes, the Prophets, and our Sauiour Chriſt, are charged with a great fault. Your reply is with ſome roughneſſe of ſpéech, which I omitte, becauſe it is but your faſhion. But for proofe, that read prayer is mans inuention, and thruſt vpon the Church by conſtraint, ye ſay England knoweth by wofull experience. There hath béene I graunt in the Church of England variance about ſome matters to be read, which are commaunded in the Leiturgie, but not about the commaunding a preſcript forme of prayer to be vſed: for therein our Church doth agrée with all godly Churches, that a preſcript forme of publike prayers is conuenient, yea, the reformed Churches haue and do practiſe the ſame.
               Héere therefore I would wiſhe the Reader to obſerue, that you Browniſts, doe not only condemne the Church of England, but all the reformed Churches whatſoeuer, and can be none other but méere Donatiſts. For héere in this your third argument ye affirme, that preſcript forme of prayer commaunded, is the changing the worke of the ſpirit into an idoll, a tradition breaking Chriſtian libertie, and therefore moſt deteſtable. In your fift Argument, ye ſay, it is a dead letter which doth quench the ſpirit. But all reformed Churches doo by commaundement receyue and vſe preſcript forme of prayers. Conſider then what ſentence yee haue giuen againſt all the viſible Churches of our time, and of former ages, for it will come to paſſe, that as the Donatiſts tooke themſelues to be the only true Church in earth, ſo muſt

you Browniſts of neceſſitie, if your ſpéeches be weighed, ſéeing all Churches haue and doo things which you affirme to be moſt deteſtable idolatry: but let the matter come into queſtion to be debated among the Churches, and you will be found Anabaptiſts for imagining ſuch a Chriſtian libertie and fréedome in the Church, that nothing is to be receyued which is impoſed by commaundement. Then ye ſay, that it breaketh our libertie, S. Paul proueth moſt plainely to the Galathians and Coloſsians. I pray ye then that we may ſée ſuch plaine proofe, which as yet none but your ſelues can eſpy: note the ſentences that will prooue the matter. You take it, there is no warrant to ſet foorth any preſcript forme of prayer, becauſe Chriſt hath preſcribed a forme. Ye thinke I might more ſafely reaſon thus, Chriſt hath preſcribed a forme of prayer, therefore neyther Pope, Byſhop, or Prelate, ought to impoſe any other vpon Gods children, vntill they can ſhewe ſome warrant from Gods word ſo to do. I am fully of your minde, that none ought to impoſe any other forme, vntill they can ſhewe warrant from Gods word. But nowe marke how the Argument will followe: Moyſes, the Prophets, and our Lord Ieſus gaue preſcript formes of prayer and prayſing God, to be vſed by the Church: therefore the reading of a preſcript forme of prayer when one prayeth or offreth vp the ſacrifice of prayſe to God, doth not change the worke of the Spirit into an idoll, nor is not a breaking Chriſtian libertie, nor idolatrie, for the holie Scripture is farre from appointing any idolatrous thing. Then I reaſon further, that if the Prophets and our Sauiour gaue preſcript formes to be vſed, the Church may take order to ſée them vſed. And from hence it doth followe, that the Church may impoſe preſcript forme of godlie prayers, which are framed aright.
               If any thinke this a ſtrange conſequence, let them conſider that the Lords prayer in generall conteyneth in it matter touching the ſubſtance and ſumme of all prayers which haue béene made, or are to be made aright. The Pſalmes, and other prayers in the Scriptures, doo expreſſe particulars,

with ſundrie ſentences, and phraſes, moſt fitte to expreſſe the ſame.
               Nowe the Church hath power and authoritie, not onely to expound theſe prayers, but alſo to applye them vnto euerie ſeuerall vſe and neceſſitye. This I adde withall, that the Church hath no authoritye to bring in any one thing in prayer, which is not conteyned in thoſe prayers of Gods word: but when the prayers be compoſed and framed of nothing but the doctrine of the Scriptures, and after the rules of true prayer, nothing is brought in which God hath not commaunded. Lay aſide therefore all your ſhiftes touching Apocrypha, mens writings, and inequalitie with Canonicall Scriptures, and bring your Arguments againſt the preſcript forme and the reading, to prooue that they make a prayer holie in it ſelfe, to become abhominable, and contrarie vnto ſpirituall prayer.
               That yee ſay, our Sauiour neuer vſed the words of the Lords prayer, when he prayed, neyther commaunded his Diſciples to ſay ouer theſe words, neyther doo we reade that the Apoſtles did euer vſe, or enforced others to vſe certayne words, &amp;c. ye ſpeake vntruly, for the Diſciples deſired him to teach them to pray as Iohn taught his diſciples to pray, and he commaundeth, when yée pray, ſay thus: Our Father which art in heauen, hallowed be thy name &amp;c. Luke 11. and S. Mathew an Apoſtle, with S. Luke the Euangeliſt, hath deliuered the ſame to the whole Church, if we reade not any where that they did vſe the Lords prayer, or commaunded others to vſe it? Will ye reaſon thus, we do not reade that the Apoſtles, or the Church in their time, did baptize Infants, therefore Infants were not baptized? or will ye reaſon thus, we neuer read that the Apoſtles did pray eyther before or after they preached, therefore they did not? your argument is the very ſame with theſe two former, yet from hence ye will néeds conclude, yt we will impoſe vpon whole Churches certaine words, euen our own words, ſtinting the ſpirit of God.
               I haue alreadie ſhewed, that the Church hath not authoritie to bring any forme of prayer into the aſſemblies, but

ſuch as is agréeable to the rules appointed for prayer by the word of God. And where ye call it a ſtinting of the Spirit, I aunſwere, that the Spirit of God is not ſtinted, but ſome men are furthered by preſcript formes, their infirmities requiring ſuch an eye, as I haue ſhewed before.
               
                  
                     Argum. 4. Becauſe true prayer muſt be of faith, vttered with heart and liuely voyce, it is preſumptuous ignorance to bring a booke to ſpeake for vs, &amp;c.
               
                  
                     Argum. 5. 
                  To worſhip the true God after an other manner then he hath taught, is Idolatrie.
                  
                     But he hath commaunded vs to come vnto him heauie laden with contrite hearts, &amp;c.
                  
                  
                     How dare we then bring a dead letter vnto God, to ſtand reading of the ſame in ſtead of faithfull petitions, quenching the ſpirit?
                  
               
               
                  
                     Argum. 6. 
                  We muſt ſtriue in prayer with continuance, &amp;c. therefore 
                  not vpon a booke.
               
               Theſe thrée I ioyned together as hauing no waight. Ye ſay I anſwere by playne contradiction, without Scripture, or proofe. In déede you quote Scripture to prooue thoſe things which are not doubted of, as, that true prayer muſt be of faith, vttered with hart: that to worſhip God after an other manner then he hath taught, is idolatrie: that we muſt ſtriue in prayer with continuance. But what ſcripture do ye bring to prooue that it is preſumptuous ignorance to vſe the help of a booke, that thoſe which reade vpon a booke come not with faith and contrite hearts, &amp;c. but ſtand reading a dead letter which quencheth the Spirit, and that a booke is no helpe for continuance in prayer, what Scripture I ſay, bring yee to prooue any of theſe? is not my bare denyall as good as your bare affirmation, and in this farre better that I haue before proued the vſe of reading by ye word of God. Dauid (ſay you) would prayſe the Lord with hart and doyce, therefore not vpon a booke. S. Paule would pray with the ſpirit, and with vnderſtanding, therefore not vpon a booke. Dauid and Paule had not ſo much néed of the booke as other men. But whē they will other to ſing prayſes to God, as in Pſalmes, &amp; Himnes,

and ſpirituall ſongs, did they not ſend them to the booke, or to the preſcript formes, wherein others might praiſe God together with them, although they binde not men alwaies to the booke. Then yée adde a reaſon, why praier read, cannot be true praier: which is, that in reading we fetch the matter from the booke which mooueth the heart. In true praier we fetch the matter from the heart, which cauſeth the mouth to ſpeake: as, I beléeued, and therefore I ſpake. This is a moſt ridiculous vanitie, for tell me this, when we bring foorth in true praier, matter from the heart which cauſeth the mouth to ſpeake, hath not the heart béene firſt mooued with the word of faith? why may not the heart be mooued againe with hearing or reading the word, and ſo vtter true praier? the heart is mooued when one heareth the praier of the miniſter, and preſently ſendeth forth praiers together with him. Do ye imagine that the heart cannot both be mooued and pray at the ſame inſtant? Is it not poſſible for one to pray in ſinging a Pſalme?
               
                  
                     Argu. 7. 
                  We muſt pray as neceſſitie requireth. But ſtinted praiers cannot bee as neceſſitie requireth. Therefore ſtinted prayers, &amp;c.
               
               To this I anſwered, approouing the propoſition, and in the aſſumption I did diſtinguiſh of matters to be praied for, as that there be things neceſſarie to be praied for at all times, and of all men: of theſe a preſcript forme may be vſed at all méetings of the Church. There be matters not at all times néedfull to be praied for: touching theſe, there can be no preſcript forme to be vſed continually, yea ſome things fall out ſo rare, that it were hard: for, as it is a fault to omit that which néedeth continually and of all men to be praied for: ſo is it a groſe babling to pray for things whereof there is no néed. And if yée obſerue the preſcript praiers of all Churches, yée ſhall find the regard of theſe two things, that nothing neceſſary be omitted, yt no praier be for ſuch things as fall out ſildome, but they are limited to the time. And further, that which falleth out beſide the preſcript formes, the miniſters of the word are to ſupply. And in the Church of England, the Preachers are not limitted touching the matters of their praiers. But if I

meane by the things which be neceſſary to be prayed for at all times, the Sacraments or any ſuch thinges as Chriſt hath ſet foorth in his word, wee ſhould thinke our Sauiour Chriſt, you ſay, to haue forgotten himſelfe, that when he did commaund them to preach and baptize, that he did not preſcribe ſome forme of wordes for their praiers, before their doctrine and Sacraments.
               To this I aunſwer, I doo not holde that for the adminiſtration of the worde and Sacramentes, it is of neceſſitie there ſhould bee a forme of praier preſcribed: for the Miniſter may conceiue the prayers at the adminiſtration of the Sacraments, as well as at the preaching of the worde. But preſcript forme, is for conueniencie. Neither am I of the minde, that one preciſe forme is of neceſſitie. Therefore yée reaſon verye fondlye, in ſaying wee might thinke our Sauiour forgat himſelfe, that he did not preſcribe a forme of wordes for their prayers, before their doctrine and Sacramentes. Your nexte wordes, that then I muſt further ſaye, that all things neceſſarye in the worſhip of GOD, are not conteined in the Canonicall Scriptures, and ſo euerye waye vpholde the Papiſts, are euen as farre wide. For all things neceſſarye and conuenient in Gods worſhippe bee conteined in the Canonicall Scriptures. But are you ignorant of this, that there be many thinges conteyned in the Scriptures, which are not in particular expreſſed, but to bee gathered from the generall groundes and rules of doctrine. What if one ſhould obiect vnto yée, there is no commaundement nor example of the Apoſtles in the ſcriptures, for anye prayer to bee made at the Preaching of the worde, and adminiſtration of Sacraments. Therefore it is not conteined in the Scriptures, that there ſhould bee anye, and ſo a thing not neceſſarye. Would yée not flie to this, that although it bee not expreſſed by anye commaundement, that there ſhould bee ſuch prayers, yet is it to bee gathered out of the doctrine conteined in the Scriptures? How groſſe are yée then, in ſaying that this dooth vpholde the Papiſts?
               
                  But yée ſaye, it were well I ſet downe what it is, that may bee fitte at all times, and for all perſons to craue? I maruaile anye ſhould be ſo babling, as to propound ſuch a matter, making doubt. For can yée be ignorant, that going through the whole Lords praier, and opening the particulars▪ there is no one petition, but almoſt all branches of it are neceſſary to bee craued at all publike méetings and of all perſons.
               When will there bee a time, and an aſſemblie, in which it ſhall not bee fitte for all to make ſupplication, that the name of the Lorde may bee ſanctified: that they may receiue the giftes and graces of the Holy-ghoſt, to imbrace the true light of the Goſpell, to increaſe in knowlege, faith, and repentance: to praye for Princes, for the whole Church, and for the ouerthrowe of Chriſtes enimies? to haue grace to obey, and to walke worthy of the Goſpell. To craue all benefites for our neceſſary ſuſtentation, and the pardon of our ſinnes, with deliuerance from the deuill. They bee all conteined in the Lordes praier, but wee as children néede to haue them particularly expreſſed, in that manner which may beſt helpe and guide vs.
               And touching praiers at the Sacraments, they may verye well be the ſame, ſéeing the thinges doo euer remaine the ſame which we are then to craue. Vnleſſe yée will maintaine, that there bee thinges in adminiſtration of Sacraments, at ſometime to be prayed for, and not at other. Then ſo farre as preſcript forme of prayer dooth fullye and fitlye expreſſe our néede, it is no babling, and ſo this your argument dooth not condemne it.
               
                  Read prayers were deuiſed by Antichriſt, and maintaine ſuperſtition and an idol miniſterie. Therefore read praiers are not tollerable, &amp;c.
               
               Antichriſt deuiſed manye blaſphemous wicked prayers. But to ſay that the reading or following a preſcript forme of praier was his deuice, is moſt falſe: for there were leiturgies in the Church of olde, before Antichriſt was ſet in his throne. And moreouer, the preſcript formes deliuered in

the ſcriptures to be vſed, and which were vſed and practiſed by the Church, ſhewe that the thing is allowed by God. Yée ſay, I haue confeſſed, that I neuer read in the ſcriptures any warrant to reade praiers vnto God: and then it muſt néedes follow that it is antichriſtian. I ſay, you know that yée doo falſifie my ſpéech. For I ſaid and haue prooued, that it is great audacitie to affirme, that there is no warrant in Gods word for preſcript forme of praier. But I doo not remember that euer I read in the ſcriptures, that God dooth commaund a man to reade the praier vpon the booke. My reaſon is rendered, that God dooth commend ſuch diligence in all his ſeruants, as to haue in memorie, &amp;c. Will ye gather thus, it is not expreſſely commaunded, therefore there is no warrant? it is not expreſly commaunded that euer I read, that the Miniſter ſhal make praier before and after his ſermon. Will yée charge me héerevpon, that I ſay there is no warrant for it in the word? There would ſundrye inconueniences growe for want of preſcript forme of publike praiers. I did onely mention this, that euery frantike ſpirit, of which ſort there may bee ſome in the Miniſtrie, will not onely be vnlike themſelues, but vary from others. You reply, that the Papiſts haue not ſo weake reaſons for their idolatrous leiturgies, rubrikes, and Canons. It appeareth by all your arguments, how méete men yée are to iudge of the waight and ſufficiencie of reaſons, alledged by the Papiſts or others. Ye ſay, if it be but in phraſes of ſpéech, that they differ, it is no ſufficient cauſe to ordaine leiturgies. I graunt that is true: then yée ſay, if it be in doctrine or conuerſation, the cenſures of the Church are to helpe that. I confeſſe that the cenſures of the Church are to redreſſe ſuch things. But your reaſon yet hath two defaults. The one, that ye deuide differing in adminiſtration of Sacraments and publike praiers, but into two members, difference of phraſes, and difference of doctrine. When as there be ſundry other differences, as in order and ceremonies, which the Church is to haue regard of, and not to leaue arbitrary. Your experience in theſe matters, is not ſo great as your boldneſſe. The other fault is, that becauſe the cenſures of the church ſhould redreſſe

defaultes, therefore there néedeth no preſcribed order. It is a world to ſée, how many men talke of the Cenſures and gouernment of the Church, which knowe not what it meaneth.
               The Church hath this power, to ordeine according to the word of God, and to appoynt ſuch Orders in matters of circumſtance about publike prayer, preaching of the word, and adminiſtring of the Sacraments, as ſhall moſt fitlie ſerue for edification. And then theſe Orders béeing eſtabliſhed by publike Authoritie, the Diſcipline and Cenſures of the Church are to driue men to the obſeruation of the ſame. Who is able to imagin the innumerable diuiſions and offences which would ariſe in the practiſe of your Anabaptiſticall fréedome, in which, yee denye the Church to haue power to ordeyne and to impoſe any orders? I would the Miniſterie of England were better then it is. If by tearming it a franticke Miniſterie, you meant but to ſpeake againſt vnlearned and vngodlie men, you ſhould haue leaue for me: but you comprehend all the learnedeſt and godly, whiche you could not bée bolde to doo, vnleſſe yee were taken with a frenſie, ſéeing there bée many whome yée are neuer lyke in any meaſure of giftes and graces, eyther for knowledge, or Godlyneſſe, to approch néere vnto. Well, now yée fall to your ſober reaſoning agayne. Paule commaunded the Coloſsians to admoniſhe Archippus, you would haue a Leiturgie for your Miniſters, not onely to tell them what they ſhould doo to men, but alſo to God himſelfe: this is your laſt reaſon, and hauing before ſpent your ſtrength, it is as a weake childe of your olde age. If yee had no better, I would neuer haue ſet this laſt. For I meruayle, vnleſſe yee did it to mocke, to what ende yee ſhoulde bring it in. Archippus was to bée admoniſhed by the Coloſsians, the Paſtors are to bée admoniſhed by theyr flockes, therefore there ought to bée no preſcript forme of publike prayer. Or is your meaning, that the Leiturgies goe too farre in telling the Miniſters what they ſhall

ſay, not only to men, but to God himſelfe. Then I aunſwere, that the Coloſsians were to admoniſh Archippus, to looke to his whole dutie. Set Archippus aſide, for he doth not ſtrengthen, but weaken your argument, and take theſe words only, which ſéeme to carrie a great abſurditie, namely, that the Miniſter ſhould be told by a Leiturgie what he is to ſpeake both to God and men. I aunſwere, that the Leiturgie is not to teach Miniſters, which otherwiſe can not tell what to ſay: it is not to maintaine an idoll Miniſterie. But to auoyd thoſe inconueniences which I haue before mentioned, and ſuch lyke, you may ſée in the reformed Churches, they haue Leiturgies, and yet all theyr Miniſters are able, and knowe what to ſpeake, both to God and men. I propounded this queſtion, that if read prayers, and impoſed Leiturgies bée Idolatrie, where ſhall wée fynde a viſible Churche? You aunſwere, that in this poynt they might erre of ignorance, and yet be the true Church. This is ſome fauour yet: the Church came nowe vnto yee in a lucky houre, but yee may continue thus gratious, leaſt the poore Churches of England craue the like at your hande. Haue yee not ſet downe, that to reade a prayer vppon the booke, is to woorſhip hym with a woorſhip diſagréeing from his nature? haue yee not ſayd, it is the deuiſe of Antichriſt, a dead letter, quenching the Spirit, ſtinting the Spirit, not of Faith, Idolatrie, a changing the worke of the Spirit, into an Idoll, a tradition and bondage, breaking our libertie which Chriſt hath purchaſed for vs, and therefore a thing moſt deteſtable? Doo yee not denye that to bée the Church of Chriſt which hath any thing impoſed? and yet yee ſaye touching Leiturgies impoſed vppon all Churches, they might erre in this poynt, of ignorance, and yet bée a true Church. Your ſpéeches doo condemne all the viſible Churches in the worlde, wherein, yée bée rancke Donatiſts. But you woulde hide this, and make ſhewe as though yée condemned only the Churches of England. But if read prayers and impoſed Leiturgies bée ſuch as you affyrme in thoſe

ſpéeches which I haue mentioned, how could ignorance excuſe them? And why may not the Church of Englande bée excuſed by ignorance? let the Reader héere obſerue the pride of ignorant blinde Sciſmatikes, which imagine they knowe more, then all the Churches of God in the earth. You take it that I vſe the Popiſh Argument of vniuerſalitie and Antiquitie, and ſo wonder what I will ſay againſt the Papiſts traditions, ſéeing I fight with their weapons agaynſt the truth. Nay, if yée could ſée your owne blindneſſe, it would make ye meruaile in déede.
               I reaſon thus: It is manifeſt by the word of God, that there ſhould bée a true viſible Church in earth: but if impoſed Leiturgies be ſuch as you make them, that could not bée ſo, there could bée no true Church, in as much as all Churches that are and that haue béene for many hundred yeares, haue had impoſed Leiturgies.
               The Papiſts doo drawe theyr Arguments of Antiquitie and Vniuerſalitie not from the Scriptures, as you may ſée this reaſon that I alleadge is, but againſt the Scriptures. And nowe how truly yée conclude touching this queſtion of read Prayer, and preſcript forme of Leiturgies, let the Reader iudge: and whether the Scriptures that I haue brought, doo not ouerthrowe your fantaſticall and Anabaptiſticall errors.
               There were ioyned with theſe Arguments againſt read Prayer, two other: the firſt is this. The Prayers of ſuch Miniſters and people as ſtand vnder a falſe Gouernment, are not acceptable, not onely becauſe they aſke amiſſe, but becauſe they breake Gods commaundement. The other is, The Prayers of ſuch as bée ſubiect to Antichriſt, are abhominable. Thoſe Miniſters which haue no power with theyr people to receyue in, and to caſt out, hauing come in by the windowe, are Antichriſtian, and ſubiect to Antichriſt, therefore the prayers of &amp;c.
               Theſe doo concerne the third and fourth accuſation, and therefore the Aunſwere is included in the Aunſwere to

them. Yet I tooke exception againſt the firſt, that the Church may be holden by force from executing Gods commaundement touching externall Gouernment, and yet be the true Church of God. And for example, I alleadged the Church that was held captiue in Babylon.
               You according to your vſuall manner, extend this to a wilfull violating of Gods commaundement. And further, you deale in that which yée demaund, as if all your accuſations againſt the Churche of Englande were true, touching Idolatrous worſhip. You ſhould aunſwere directly, whether they be not the Church of God which are by force, being willing, kept backe from executing Church Gouernment? You take your ſelues to be the true Church, and yet yée are reſtrayned from ſetting vp thoſe Orders which yée profeſſe ye would. I would knowe whether this bée not ſome bondage. If yée ſay yet this is not to be ſubiect to any falſe gouernment. To prooue that the Church may of ignorance and frailtie bée in ſome bondage of a falſe gouernment, and yet bée the true Church, I indeuored to ſhewe, that Ieruſalem from aboue is not in this world ſo fullie poſſeſſed of her fréedome, but that ſhée, and euerie one of her children, bée in ſome ſpirituall bondage. For proofe, I alleadged that Saint Paule ſayeth, He ſawe in his members a lawe, rebelling againſt the lawe of his minde, and leading him captiue to the lawe of ſinne Rom. 7.
               
               You cry out and ſay, yée will thinke me a carnall Libertine, if I recant not this doctrine. What Atheiſt (ſay you) would thus haue defended his groſſe ſinne? I doo not meruayle that yée are moued ſo ſore at this doctrine, for if it bée prooued that the true Church, and euerie member of the ſame, is tyed in ſome ſpirituall bondage in this world, it breaketh the mayne piller of Browniſme, which they erect out of this ſentence, Ieruſalem from aboue is free with her children, and ſo their whole frame commeth downe: this maketh you ſo haſtely to thruſt vnder a rotten proppe, euen as it came to hand. Ye ſay, that Saint Paule neuer continued captiue vnto

ſinne after regeneration, neither gaue place vnto euill thoughts: no more doo any of you. S. Paul ſaith, that the law in his members did lead him captiue to the lawe of ſinne. He ſaith I do the euil which I hate. I my ſelfe in my minde ſerue the law of God, and in my fleſh the lawe of ſinne. Was not Dauid regenerate, and yet gaue place to euill thoughts, ſo farre as to commit adultrie and murther. If the regeneration and fréedome of Browniſts from all ſpirituall bondage be ſuch, that they giue not place vnto euill thoughts, they ſhall neuer haue any great company, vnleſſe it be of ranke hypocrites, of ſuch indéed there may be ſtoare. Ye looke that I ſhould recant. But I ſay, either you or S. Paul muſt recant: for that which you ſay, is flat contrary and oppoſite to that which hee ſaith. Looke well to it, for I tell ye, he is too conſtant to recant. If it pleaſe God to beſtow his grace, you may. Ye ſay, what Atheiſt would thus haue defended his groſſe ſinne? And I ſay, what Heretike could more bouldly ſpeake flat contrary to the bleſſed Apoſtle, and to the manifeſt doctrine of the Scriptures deliuered euery where, then you doe? it may be ye ſtand chéefely vpon the words of our Sauiour, which yée alledge: that no man can ſerue two maiſters. If the regenerate be held captiue in any part vnto ſinne, they ſerue two maiſters. This needeth to be opened.
               We are moſt ſure that Saint Paul in that hée ſaith, dooth not differ from our Sauiour Chriſt, and yet in ſhewe hee ſéemeth to ſpeake quite contrary. For where the one ſaith: No man can ſerue two Maiſters. The other ſaith: I my ſelfe in my minde ſerue the lawe of God, and in my fleſh the lawe of ſinne. How ſhall this bee reconciled? is there no waye but to fall vpon the rockes of Browniſme, and to imagine that the regenerate are ſo fréed, that they be in no captiuitie vnto ſinne, nor giue place vnto euill thoughtes? Yes verelye: The regenerate doo fall into ſinne, not onelye in thoughts but in déedes: not onelye of ignorance, but euen againſt theyr knowledge, as Dauid, Peter, and manye other in the holye Scriptures.
               
                  And therefore they may be ſaid to ſerue ſinne in the fleſh, that is in the corruption yet remaining in them, not extinguiſhed by the law of the minde, that is the grace and worke of regeneration▪ Yet the doubt remaineth, for all is but one man, ſo farre as he is regenerate, and ſo farre as he is corrupt: and therefore when in the fleſh he dooth ſerue the law of ſinne, the whole man may be ſaid to ſerue the lawe of ſinne. S. Paul dooth deny that, and ſaith: I doo the euill that I hate, I conſent to the lawe of God that it is good, I delight in the law of God concerning the inner man, it is no longer I that ſinne, but the ſinne that dwelleth in me. We ſée then the ſame man ſinneth, and in ſome reſpect is ſaide to be in captiuitie, and to ſerue ſinne, and in an other reſpect he is accounted with God, not to ſerue ſinne, ſéeing he is by tyrannous forcing drawne to doo that which he hateth. How ſtandeth the fréedome then of Ieruſalem, and her Children? I ſay, her perfect fréedome with all her children is in the remiſſion of ſinnes. Touching that ſhe hath in this world, it may thus be compared. As if a man lye bound in chaines, ſo that he cannot ſtirre any member, and after his chaines be looſed he can riſe and walke: but yet his chaines hang vpon him, and are a burthen, hee cannot caſt them off. For by nature we are ſo faſt chained, that we haue no moouing at all in vs, being dead in ſinne. But through the worke of regeneration we are borne, we are raiſed, our bands and chaines are looſed and broken: we can riſe, we can ſtand, we can walke, though faintlye, our chaines, euen a lumpe of corruption in the fleſh, preſſing vs downe ſo ſore. Then I conclude, that ſeeing the Church in this life is in ſome bondage to ſinne, and yet the true Church. And ſéeing there may be the true viſible Church vnder ſome yoake of outward bondage: let the Church of England haue that fauour which other churches haue had, and not bee ſo rigorouſlye condemned. Thus much touching the firſt accuſation▪ together with your arguments againſt read prayer.
            
         
         
            
            The ſecond tranſgreſsion.
            
               The Brow. 
               2 THat the prophane multitudes without exception of 
               any one perſon, &amp;c.
            
            
               The ſecond fault is, that all the prophane multitudes, without exception of any one perſon, are admitted and retained in the boſome of the Church. Manye Churches in England want godly Paſtours, and there all are admitted. It may be, he that admitteth is the worſt in the company. But there be many greater and ſmaller congregations, where the Paſtour doth keepe backe ſome for ignorance, &amp;c.
            
            
               Heere you confeſſe, that very many Churches in England want godly Paſtours, and that there all are admitted, and that he that admitteth them is the worſte of the company. Thus you make the moſt Chuches in England in a very bad eſtate, and ſo farre foorth you affirme your article. But yet you know ſome Churches, &amp;c.
            
            
               I did confeſſe, and doo ſtill with gréefe, that in very manyeG. G. aſſemblies in England, all are admitted to the Table of the Lord, which offer themſelues, euen the moſt prophane and groſſe ſinners. I ſhewed alſo, the reaſon of this gréeuous offence, namely that the miniſters which ſhould repell ſuch open offenders, are many times the worſt, or at leaſt negligent in that behalfe. And moreouer, that the Church of England dooth neither approoue ſuch admiſſion of prophane men to the Sacrament, nor yet ſuffer it in practiſe wholy. For touching practiſe, there be many congregations in the land, where ſundrie for ignorance, and open wickedneſſe, are by the miniſters kept backe, and not ſuffered to communicate, vntill they ſhew repentance. And for not approouing ſuch admiſſion, I ſaid, the booke of Common prayer dooth preſcribe and commaund the repelling of notorious wicked offendours: and alſo that ſome are excommunicated iuſtly, &amp; not admitted to publike praier. This was the firſt part of mine anſwer: wherein I prooue your accuſation falſe. The other is, that the godly are not polluted

by the companye of the wicked, which are ſuffered to communicate with them in Gods worſhip, and the thing not in their power to redreſſe. And for example I alledged the Church of the Iewes. By which I prooue, that if your accuſation were true, yet it deſtroyeth not the Church. Now let vs examine how you ouerthrowe this by your replye. Yée aſke whether there were no more prophane in the pariſh beſides thoſe twenty or thirty which are repelled? And whether thoſe other prophane were not admitted? I anſwer, If there were, yet the repelling of twenty or thirty in a flock, dooth ſhew that you accuſe falſely, when yée ſay, all the prophane, without exception of any one perſon, are reteined in the body and boſome of our Church: But to prooue your article at once, as yée ſay, by a more direct courſe, yée bring an argument. And yée demand if I know anye in all the realme of England vnbaptized. Is not Baptiſme (ſay you) a Sacrament belonging to the Church, by which all the faithfull and their ſéed doo enter into it? Wherevpon yée argue thus? All being baptized, it followeth that all are receiued into the body of your Church. Now being once receiued in, they can no way be caſt out but by excommunication. And it is manifeſt, that the Parſon and all his pariſh, hath not the powre which Chriſt hath left vnto his Church, to excommunicate any offender, be he neuer ſo obſtinate or notorious, &amp;c. This being the onely reaſon by which ye ſtand to prooue the truth of your accuſation, I muſt beſtow the more paines about it. Thus it muſt be ſet in forme. Where all are receiued in by Baptiſme, and no power to caſt foorth any by excommunication, there all the prophane multitudes are without exception of any one perſon, receiued into, &amp; reteined in the boſome and body of the Church: But in the Church of England all are receiued in by Baptiſme, and there is no power to caſt foorth any by excommunication: Therefore in England, all the prophane multitudes, without exception of any one perſon, are receiued into, and reteined in the boſome and body of the Church. In your propoſition there are to be excepted ſuch as are repelled from the Sacrament, who are in ſome ſort, for the time, remooued out of the boſome of the

Church. And alſo ſuch Papiſts, Heretikes, and Sciſmatikes, as depart out of themſelues. It is further alſo to be conſidered in it, that all the baptized, continuing outwardly obedient, they cannot be iuſtly called the prophane multitudes. Your preſumption, in which ye charge the Church of England with a principall tranſgreſſion, for receiuing in all by Baptiſme, and hauing no power to caſt foorth any by Excommunication, is with foule error and falſehood.
               Touching the Baptiſme of Infants, this appeareth to be your iudgement, that the children of prophane men which remayne in the Church, and profeſſe the faith of Chriſt, belong not to the couenant, and therefore ought not to be Baptiſed. No doubt the Church doth offend, when open notorious ſinners are not Excommunicate, and brought to repentance, or at the leaſt to ſuch a ſhewe of repentance, as that men can not further iudge them but as Brethren. It is alſo an offence, where ſuch not being caſt foorth, their children are receyued vnto Baptiſme, and that without care to ſée them brought vp and inſtructed in the Chriſtian Religion, and to leade a Godly life agréeable to the ſame. But to ſay, that the children of prophane men, taking prophane men as you doo, which profeſſe Chriſtianitie, and remayne in the Church, are not to be Baptiſed, is a very wicked iniurie to Gods people, and contrarie to the manifeſt doctrine of the holie Scriptures, and can not without Hereſie be mayntayned.
               Firſt, touching prophane people, it is certayne that all Heathen Heretikes, all Sciſmatikes, open contemners of the holie Religion, and all obſtinate wicked men whiche deſpiſe the cenſure of the Church, that hath paſſed vppon them, may be called prophane. But you Browniſts go further, and condemne them all as Infidels and prophane, which profeſſe the faith of Chriſt, becauſe notwithſtanding they doo it in ſome weakenes and infirmities: which is a wicked preſumption, and intruſion into Gods ſeate, and in which (as I haue ſhewed before) yée breake the rule of diſcipline giuen by our Sauiour Chriſt, by which, no brother, that is,

none which profeſſeth the true faith, is for his ſinnes and impenitencie to be iudged as heathen, vntill he haue deſpiſed the admonition of the Church, and ſo be caſt foorth. You take vppon yée to plucke vp all the Darnell: yée are commaunded the contrarie▪ leaſt yée plucke vp the Wheate Math. 13. You dare, and that in moſt ſauage and deſperate manner, rend and teare vp the weake plants: yée doo it vnto whole aſſemblyes, in which there be many that vnfaynedly ſorrow and mourne for their ſinnes, and ſtudie to pleaſe God: all that feare the Lord, may tremble at this your intollerable wickednes. But now to procéede. Ye will not allowe the children of prophane men the Sacrament of Baptiſme. And what is your reaſon? they bée not the ſéede of the faithfull. In déede in this yée ſay true, that none are in theyr infancie to be admitted to this Sacrament, but the ſéede of the faithfull: but when yée take it that the children whoſe next parents are hypocrites, or wicked and prophane perſons, which yet remayne in the Church, and profeſſe Chriſt, be not the ſéede of the faithfull at all, and in any reſpect, and ſo within the couenant, and to be baptized, yée are farre wide: for let it be that their next parents before haue béene hypocrites and vnfaithfull, yet may they bée the ſéede of the faithfull: for their intereſt in Gods couenant doth (as béeing the ſeede of the faithfull) not depend vppon theyr next parents, but vppon the auncient Chriſtians theyr fore-fathers: for when he ſayth, I will be thy God, and the God of thy ſeede, the promiſe is made to a thouſand generations, Exod. 20. It is ſayd, that Leuy payd Tithes vnto Melchiſedech becauſe he was in the loynes of Abraham, when he met Melchiſedech, and gaue Tythes, Hebrewes 7. ver. 9. 10. Abraham begat Iſaake, Iſaake begat Iaakob, and Iaakob begate Leuie, and yet of Leuie it is ſayd, that he was in the loynes of Abraham: yea, it muſt néedes be confeſſed, that all the whole Nation of the Iewes were in the loynes of Abraham. Our Sauiour Chriſt according to the fleſhe, was in the loynes of Abraham. For this cauſe, Saint Peter calleth all the Iewes the children of the Prophets,

and of the couenant Acts. 3. ver. 25. So doth S. Paule Rom. 9. and in that reſpect, they be all called holie, Rom. 11. If the firſt fruites be holie, ſo is the lumpe: if the roote be holie, ſo are the boughes. Abraham, Iſaak, and Iaakob, are the firſt fruites, and the roote: all the Iſraelites the lumpe, and the boughes: but were they all faithfull, no nor yet the greater part? for Eſayas cryeth, that if the number of the children of Iſraell were as the ſand of the ſea, yet but a remnant ſhould be ſaued, Eſay. 10. How often doth the Lorde complayne euery where of the greeuous infidelitie and rebellion in the greateſt part of that Nation? Why then are they called holie, and the holie people, being many of them reprobates? Is it not becauſe they be Abrahams ſeede, and were in the Church by outward profeſſion, adding this withall, that the elect of God, euen the right holie ſeede, were in theyr loynes: for Gods choſen did not ſpring only from the ſanctifyed, but alſo from other, who touching the outward profeſſion, and touching the holy ſeede which was in theyr loynes, were eſteemed as members in the Church, and were all of them, euen the whole nation, called the holy people. It is not diſalowed, that in the times of idolatrie openly maintained, their children were circumciſed. Nay further, the Lord calleth the children of thoſe wicked idolaters, his children, Thou haſt (ſayth he by Ezechiel) taken thy ſonnes and thy daughters which thou broughteſt foorth vnto me, and ſacrificed vnto them, to be conſumed. Thou haſt ſlayne my ſonnes, and giuen them, by cauſing them to paſſe through to them, Ezech. 16. ver. 21. Theſe Idolaters did offer their children to Deuils, euen to the Idols of Canaan, and ſhead innocent bloud, euen the bloud of their ſonnes and daughters, when they cauſed them to paſſe through the fire, Pſal. 106. If the promiſe to Abraham and his ſéede had not béen ſo effectual, as that the holy choſen ſéede was in the loyns of theſe Idolaters, how could they be ſaid to bring foorth Sonnes &amp; Daughters to the Lord? How could it be ſayd, thou haſt ſlayn my ſonnes? or how could they rightly haue béen circumciſed? If ye ſay, theſe Idolaters ſhould not haue remained

in the Church, but if not by the Ciuill power put to death, yet by the cenſure of the Church caſt foorth. Yea, but there was ſo generall a declining, that neyther of theſe was performed: and ſo they remayned ſtyll in the Church, and brought foorth children vnto God, euen ſuch as the couenant made with Abraham did belong vnto, they were in his loines, they were his ſéede, and not cut off by the wickednes of theyr next parents. If yée obiect that the Iewes nowe at this day are the ſeede of Abraham, and by that reaſon ſhould be ſtill the viſible Church▪ I aunſwere, that although there be Gods elect among them, whome eyther he taketh away in their infancie, or elſe calleth them to knowe Chriſt when they come to mans eſtate: yet the Iewes can not now be called the viſible Church, nor the Church, in as much as they haue reiected hym in whome the Couenant was ratifyed, euen the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and therefore he ſayde vnto them, the Vineyard ſhall be taken from thoſe Huſbandmen, and let foorth vnto other. And then expounding himſelfe, he ſayth, the Kingdome of God ſhall be taken from yee, and giuen to a nation, that will bring foorth the fruite thereof. The Vineyard was not taken from thoſe naughtie Huſbandmen that killed the ſeruants of the Lord of the Vineyard which came for fruites, euen the Prophets, vntill they had killed the ſonne and heire himſelfe. Now the naturall braunches are broken off, and the wilde oliues, euen the Gentiles, are graffed in, Rom. 11. They are nowe the children of Abraham, and heyres of the promiſe, as it is ſayd, I haue made thée a father of many Nations. And in thy ſéede all Nations of the earth ſhall be bleſſed. Our fore-fathers, many of them declyned in the Apoſtaſie, and worſhipped Idols: but as the Idolatrous Iewes, ſo they remayned ſtill in the Church, and brought foorth children to God, that is, ſuch as were within the Couenant, to be accounted the holie ſéede, and ſo of right were to haue the ſeale of the couenant ſet vpon them, euen Baptiſme. We can not ſay therefore that the Couenant was diſanulled, and that the Churche vtterlie fayled, no not euen in the moſt horrible confuſion

of popery, but Antichriſt did ſit in the temple of God, 2. Theſ. 2 Thoſe idolaters were in the Church, and the heirs of promiſe in their loines, for we and all the Churches are ſprung out of them, ſealed with the ſigne of the Couenant, as of right belonging vnto vs from our holye aunceſtors. But you Browniſts as Catabaptiſts, denie that we haue the ſigne of the Couenant: for yee ſay we haue no Sacraments. If we bee not within the Couenant from our anceſtours, what are you? who hath béene ſent from God to call yée vnto a Couenant, which yée were not within before? Who hath giuen yée the ſigne of the Couenant? or haue yee receiued a couenant without a ſigne? How will you indure this terrible voice of Almightie God: yée haue rooted vppe and caſt foorth my ſonnes and my daughters? For if it were ſaid to idolators, yée haue ſlaine my ſonnes? how much more vnto you, which in a moſt proud furie, with intollerable boldneſſe and crueltie, roote vp and caſt foorth the infants of whole aſſemblies, which haue renounced idolatry, and profeſſe the Goſpell, becauſe yée doo account them prophane? Let it be, they are many of them nothing ſuch as they ought to be, but ſinners, and ſuch as ſhould by the Cenſures of the Church bee brought into better order, yet profeſſing Chriſt, and remaining in the Church, their infants are not by their vngodlineſſe caſt foorth of the Couenant. I conclude therefore, that the Church of England, or at the leaſt many of the teachers and guides doo offend, in not executing the diſcipline vpon vngodly men, to bring them to repentance▪ but in receiuing their children to be baptized, they doo not offend, ſo they ſée them taught in the faith, and to liue a godlye life, as our Church hath eſtabliſhed, yea in refuſing them the infants ſhould receiue great iniurie.
               But to make this matter yet more cléere, the queſtion is to be anſwered, whether the Church of Rome be the Church of Chriſt. For the Browniſts doo hold, that our aunceſtors were not the Church of Chriſt in the time of poperie, and that we now are confuſed multitudes, not rightlye entered into couenant with God, to become a Church, ſéeing wee were not of Gods true Church before, neither orderly entered into couenant.

Indéed if we were not within the couenant before from our aunceſtors, nor entered orderly to become a Church, the matter would ſéeme ſtrong againſt vs. Let it therefore be examined. I know this is the vſuall ſpéech of the learnedeſt Deuines, the church of God is in the Papacie, but the Papacie is not the church. And it may be, the ſenſe will differ little or nothing, but I take it a fitter ſpéech to ſaye, the Papacie is in the church, then to ſay, the church is in the papacie. For Antichriſt dooth ſit in the Temple of God: his lawes, his worſhip, and all his abhominations, were brought into the church. All the men which receiued his marke, and worſhipped him, were in the church, yea euen the whole Apoſtaſie was in the churche. The church was before, and that commeth after, and entreth into or ariſeth in it. Then to the queſtion, if by the church of Rome we vnderſtand the Pope, his lawes, his worſhip which hath béene deuiſed by himſelfe, his adherents, and all that worſhip him or receiue his Marke. I anſwer, that this is that which may properly be called the church of Rome, which is, the papacie, the apoſtaſie, and ſeduced to damnation, and not the church of Chriſt, otherwiſe then thus, that the Pope, the Cardinals, and all that worſhip the Beaſt, be falſe Chriſtians by profeſſion, bred in the Church, and continuing in it, their ſéede not excluded from the couenant. But if by the Church of Rome, we vnderſtand all thoſe companies of people, ouer whome the tyrannie of the Pope hath heeretofore extended it ſelfe, or dooth at this day: or thoſe things which were giuen by Chriſt, which remaine in the ſame. I ſay, this is not the church of Rome, but the Church of God. Firſt, if we reſpect the holye doctrine of God, in all thoſe points which were and are kept ſound among them, and the holye Sacrament of Baptiſme. Then ſecondly, if we conſider the kingdoms and people themſelues, all did not fall from Chriſt, but many held the foundation, the moſt of them lying ſcattered and hid in the deſolations and ruines. Thirdly, if we regard that the infants not only of theſe faithfull, but euen of the wicked Apoſtates which worſhipped the beaſt, were ſtill within the couenant as the holy ſéed: we ſhall ſee that the papacie was, and is, in the

Church, which is the Temple of God, and not the ſynagog of Rome. The Church of Rome then is not the true Church of God: but the Church of Rome is the Apoſtaſie in the church. Let vs come then more particularly. The church of England in the time of poperie was a member of the vniuerſall church, and had not the being of a church of Chriſt from Rome, nor tooke not her beginning of being a Church, by ſeperating hir ſelfe from that Romiſh ſynagog: but hauing her ſpirites reuiued, and her eyes opened by the light of the heauenly word, did caſt foorth that tyrannie of Antichriſt, with his abhominable idolatrie, hereſies, and falſe worſhip: and ſought to bring all her children vnto the right faith, and true ſeruice of God: And ſo is a purer and more faithfull church then before. Idolatrie was openly ſet vp in the church of Iſrael, at ſundrye times. It did not, as I haue ſhewed, diſanull the couenant of God with them, nor debarre their children from the holy ſigne of circumciſion, but all the Iewes are called the children of the couenant. Then let the Browniſt ſhew ſome reaſon, why it ſhould bee otherwiſe in this caſe with our churches, then it was with the church of Iſrael.
               Thus much for the one part of your aſſumption, wherein ye blame the church of England, for receiuing in all by baptiſme. Now touching the other part of it, in which ye affirme that there is no power to caſt foorth any by excommunication, yée ſpeake very falſely. For the church of England hath ſome power to excommunicate. But you reaſon thus: the perſon and all his pariſh hath not the power to excommunicate anye one offendor, therefore the church of England hath not powre to excommunicate. Is it poſſible, if a man would ſtudy to reaſon abſurdlie, that he ſhould excell yée? Will yee argue thus: euery ſeuerall part by it ſelfe hath not power to excommunicate: therefore the whole together hath not the power? It is not méete indéed, that the Parſon and his pariſh ſhould haue the power to excommunicate, vnleſſe it bee ſuch a Pariſh as hath the Conſiſtorie of Paſtors, Teachers, and Gouernours. It ſéemeth yée haue great ſkill in the diſcipline of Chriſt.
               
                  The ſeuerall flockes about Geneua without the Citie haue euery one a Paſtor, and two Elders: but yet they haue not the power to excommunicate, but that is referred to the Conſiſiorie which is within the Citie, Maiſter Beza, Epiſt. 20. Will yée ſay thoſe ſeuerall flockes cannot be the Churches of Chriſt, vnleſſe their paſtors and they together haue power to excommunicate? They are members of that church which hath power to excommunicate. But yée will ſay, that the excommunication of the Commiſſarie is no excommunication, and therfore our pariſhes be no members of a church, which hath power to excommunicate.
               The like yée will ſay of the excommunication by the Biſhop himſelfe, and by the Archdeacon. I aunſwer, that if it ſhould bée graunted ye, that their excommunication dooth not binde in heauen, yet it is of force to remooue, and dooth remooue from the ſocietye of our aſſemblies, which prooueth your accuſation falſe, becauſe we reaſon about this outward remoouing. But what if the Biſhop, together with ſundry other Miniſters of the Goſpell, doo excommunicate duely an obſtinate wicked man, is he not excommunicate before God? If there be an heretike conuinced, and found obſtinate, and the Biſhops and Miniſters of the Church of England aſſembled, or ſome competent number of them, as in the conuocation, or ſuch ſynod do duely excommunicate him, is it no excommunication? Will yée reaſon after this ſort, that becauſe euery Miniſter with his flocke ſeuerally, hath not the power to excommunicate, therefore the Miniſters of the Church of England are vtterly without this power? You confeſſe that it is the Church of Chriſt which hath this power, though it fault much by negligence in executing the ſame. I would all Browniſts could conſider, what it is to excommunicate, or to cut, not onely particular perſons, but whole aſſemblies from Chriſt, it would abate their horrible preſumption.
               Then for the ſuſpenſion from the Sacrament, by which the vnworthy, either for ignorance, or open wicked life, are ſeperated from the néere fellowſhip of the Church, I ſaid yée might demaund by what right the miniſter dooth it? Yée ſay,

that indéede would be knowne, adding moreouer, that if it be in the nature of Excommunication, it were no ſmall preſumption in the Miniſter to arrogate ſuch abſolute authoritie to himſelfe. I hold it ſomewhat in the nature of Excommunication, in ſuch, as haue béene before admitted, but yet not to be compared as any thing néere ſo great as Excommunication: and neuertheleſſe, I déeme it no preſumption for the Miniſter, to repell the vnworthy from the Sacrament. He is to take héede to himſelfe, that he giue not holie things to dogs. He is to beware of that which may giue publike offence, and bring the holie myſteries into contempt. It is in déede no ſmall matter to debarre from the Sacrament. The Miniſter therefore may eaſily offende in this caſe diuers wayes: as namely, if he be carried with euill will for priuate reſpects toward any, and ſo aggrauate their offences, and make that heynous which is not: or if he doo not make the matter apparant ſo much as he can, that the flocke may ſée there is iuſt cauſe to repell them, and no iniurie offered, the crimes for which they are remoued being notorious.
               Now becauſe I ſayd, the booke of common Prayer doth warrant this, héere yée ſet vp your briſtles, and firſt it may not be let paſſe, but noted, that euen the beſt of our Churches ſtand vnder this Idoll by our owne confeſſion. This is a ſpeciall note, and well marked. Why, did ye not knowe that we vſe the booke in publike prayer, and adminiſtration of Sacraments? Then yee aſke if the booke be Chriſts newe Teſtament, that we muſt fetch our warrant and direction from that Idoll? I might aſke you a queſtion, whether ye be in your wits? for doo we diſpute héere, whether a Miniſter is warranted in conſcience before God to repell any from the Sacrament? I thought that you Browniſts whiche take vppon yee to iudge, and vtterly to abandon and caſt foorth whole aſſemblyes which profeſſe the Goſpell, and which are eſtéemed of the godly Churches as Siſters, had made no doubt, but that by Gods word the Miniſter is warranted to repell a notorious wicked man from the Sacrament. But I

ſuppoſed yee would obiect, that by the eſtabliſhed order and gouernment of our Church, all power to keepe the Sacraments from wicked prophanation, is taken away from the Miniſters, and for this I alleadged the booke. Let the Reader now iudge, how fitlie yee clap your wings and crowe, ſaying: In déede it is a fit Porteſſe for ſuch Prieſts, and the ſuſpenſion ye vaunt of, a fit toole for ſuch workemen, euen the inſtruments of that fooliſh Shepheard. If the iudgement of God (you ſay) were not vppon our right eye, we might ſée how our Lords the Byſhops doo dreſſe vs, and perceyue how this weapon that they allowe vs, wanteth both edge and poynt &amp;c.
               You ſpeake, as if the Byſhops did take vppon them, and we ſubmitte our ſelues vnto them, as Lords ouer our faith and conſciences, and as though we were at theyr allotting, when as in déede they bée but miniſters to ſée thoſe orders kept which bée alreadie eſtabliſhed, and haue not authoritie to take from any Miniſter that power which the booke doth giue him: much leſſe can one word of maiſter Commiſſaries mouth heale the greateſt wound (as you ſay) we can make with it. Yee ſay, not one in the Pariſh ſetteth a flye by it. Yee ſpeake ſo confidentlie, and with ſuch ſhewe of honeſtie, that I ſhould beléeue yee in theſe things, if I had not for ſundrie yeares tryed and ſéene your words falſe by experience. I ſayd, ſuch as be iuſtly Excommunicate, as ſome are, be not admitted to the publike prayer. Héere yee bid ſée how God inſnareth me in mine owne words, and how hard a bad cauſe is to defend. What is the ſnare which I am héere caught in? Forſooth I doo héere openly iuſtifie Excommunication by the Commiſſarie, becauſe we haue no other power or meanes, and our Church wardens doo ſtand ſworne to that Court. But how ſhall I get out of your ſnare? I muſt be fayne to breake it, if it be not looſe of it ſelfe. What if when I ſay ſome are Excommunicate iuſtly, I haue reſpect, not to thoſe which Excommunicate, but to the deſert of them that be Excommunicated. Againe, it is vntrue that ye ſay, our

Church hath no power, but the Commiſſaries Court (as I haue alreadie ſhewed.) Touching your next ſpéech, wherein yee charge vs, that we thincke to heale, or at the leaſt, to couer enormities with theſe two drie withered figge leaues, the one, that we can not remedie the matter, the other, that priuate men are not to reforme: the aunſwere ſhall be more fitte, when wée come to ſhewe what priuate men may doo.
               Now let vs come to the other part of mine Anſwer which denyed the conſequence, though your accuſation were true, which is this: Wicked prophane men are receyued in, and retayned in the boſome and bodie of their Church, therefore the Couenant is diſanulled with them, and they are no longer Gods people, but a falſe Antichriſtian ſynagog. To diſprooue this, I did alleadge, that there were but a fewe true worſhippers that frequented the Temple among multitudes of prophane and vngodly men. To which ye reply, that comparing our Church to the Temple of God, and ſtill begging the queſtion, I frame my Arguments as though our people were faithfull, and our prayers holie. I pray yee what is the queſtion which I begge? This ſay you, is the queſtion, whether the aſſemblyes in England be the true Church of God? and then yee woulde beare the Reader in hand, that I reaſon in ſuch ſort as I would firſt haue this graunted, that it is a true Church of faithfull people, and holie worſhip. You ſhould haue done well to haue ſhewed how I frame my Arguments from the Queſtion graunted. But the truth is, yee can ſhewe no colour héere of any ſuch thing.
               Nowe may I charge you, and that iuſtly, which I wyll alſo make apparant to all which will not ſhut theyr eyes, that in ſtead of anſwering, yee doo not onely cauill, but moſt ſottiſhly with a blinde ſhift. For our queſtion heere is this, the Church of England doth receyue in and retayne in her boſome the prophane multitude, therfore the Church of England is not the true Church. To diſproue this, I reaſon thus,

the Church of Iſrael retayned the multitude of wicked ones in her boſome, for there were but fewe true worſhippers frequented the Temple among multitudes of prophane vngodly men. Therefore this fault doth not deſtroy the béeing of a true Church, neyther is the worſhip and prayers of the faithfull polluted by the company of the wicked which worſhip together with them, eſpecially when they can not remedie the matter. To ouerthrowe this Argument, you muſt of neceſſitie prooue one of theſe two things, eyther that the Church of Iſraell did not retayne the prophane multitude in her boſome, and ſo the good and the bad worſhipped together: or elſe that they were not Gods Church when this was ſuffered, but all that came ſo together fell from God. You ſhift from this, and ſpeake of Idolatrous times, in which it is moſt certayne that the godly did not mixe themſelues with the wicked in idolatrous worſhip. We doo not argue whether the godly did ioyne with the wicked in idolatrous worſhip, for it is moſt cléere they might not, nor did not. But whether the wicked were ſuffered, and did ioyne with the godly in the true worſhip? and whether they were polluted by communicating with them, and that ſo gréeuouſly, as to diſanull the Couenant? let the Scriptures be iudge in both theſe. If I ſhould ſtand to recite all the teſtimonies, and all the complaints which are made by the Prophets againſt the multitudes of wicked which worſhipped together with the godly at ſundrie times, it would be long, ſome fewe may ſuffice in a matter ſo euident. He that readeth the bookes of Moyſes touching the ſtate of the Church for the ſpace of fortie yeares in the wilderneſſe, what ſhall he finde in the moſt but multitudes of prophane rebels, againſt whome, the Lord ſware, that they ſhould not ſée his reſt, whoſe carcaſſes alſo he ouerthrewe in the deſert, and yet they were not caſt out of the aſſemblie, nor ſeparated from the reſt ſo long as they liued, nor their ſeede reiected? If yee will ſee an epitome of their rebellions for that ſpace, and for the time of the Iudges, looke vppon the 106. Pſalme.
               
                  Afterward, when the Kings of Iuda raigned euen vntill the captiuitie, what gréeuous complaints are made againſt them? A great part which came to worſhip in the Temple, were as Sodom and Gomorrah, Ieſay. 1. &amp; 3. Being the Lords Vineyard, they brought foorth ſtinking grapes. Ieſa. 5. Hauing committed thefts, adulteries, periuries, and other abhominable ſinnes, they came together with the godly to worſhip in the Temple, in ſo much that the Lord demaundeth, if they tooke his houſe to be a Denne of théeues, Ierem. 7. The Préeſts themſelues were not frée from this horrible pollution, for it is written, they are all dumbe Dogges that cannot barke, they loue to ſléepe, they are gréedy, and giuen to Wine, Ieſay. 56. The Prophets propheſie lies, the Préeſts exerciſe dominion by their hand, the people loue to haue it ſo. Ierem. 5. ver. 31. The Préeſts conſpire together, they are like a roring Lion, they deuide the pray, they doo violence to the law, prophane the holy things, and put not difference betwéene the holy and prophane. Ezech. 22.
               
               What horrible things are theſe, by which the wrath of the Lord was kindled? But were they not ſtill the daughter of Sion? Reade for this the Lamentations of Ieremie. After they were returned from the captiuitie, the print of the rod being yet in their ſkrinne, they were not fréed from ſuch pollution▪ for Malachi accuſeth both Préeſts and people, and that heinouſly. They mixed themſelues by Mariage with the Heathen, and prophaned the Sabbaoth by kéeping market vpon it. Eſra. 9. Nehe. 13. From the time that God raiſed them vp no mo Prophets, vntill the comming of our Sauiour Chriſt, their ſtate grew woorſe and worſe, not onely by Sects, but alſo, that the Préeſts prophaned the Temple, Iohn. 2. Math. 21. The Teachers which ſat in Moyſes chaire, did expound the law corruptly in ſundry points, they mixed their leuen, they were hypocrites, blinde guides, couetous, and ambitious. Matth. 5. and 15. and 16. and. 23. Theſe reſiſted Chriſt, and would excommunicate thoſe that ſhould confeſſe him. Iohn. 9. And yet the godly did not onely worſhip together with them in the Temple, but alſo our Sauiour dooth will they ſhould

heare them teach. Math. 23. If they had béene polluted by worſhipping together with them, he would haue commaunded to ſeparate themſelues. This were enough to ſhew the groſſe hereſie of the Browniſts in this point: but yet I will adde ſomewhat of the Churches founded by the Apoſtles. In the Church of Corinth, Saint Paul reprooueth many things. There were factions and ſchiſmes among them. The Preachers did ſet foorth the Goſpell with humane wiſdome. The Paſtors and Gouernours did not execute the diſcipline, but ſuffered the inceſtuous perſon. They ſtraue one with an other in the law before Heathen Iudges. They feaſted in the idol Temples, at the feaſts which were kept in honor of the idols, and ſo were partakers of the cup of Deuils. They prophaned the holye Supper of the Lorde, they abuſed ſpirituall gifts. There were among them which denied the reſurrection of the dead.
               A Browniſt will héere replye, that this Church did repent being reprehended by Saint Paul, as he witneſſeth of them, 2. Cor. 7. I aunſwer that they were Gods true Church before they repented, 1. Cor. 1. and alſo that they did not all ſhew repentance, as that ſecond Epiſtle which he wrote vnto them dooth declare, and eſpecially, theſe wordes: I feare, leaſt when I come, I ſhall not finde yee ſuch as I would, and I ſhall bee found ſuch as you would not: leaſt there bee ſtrife, emulations, wrath, contentions, backbitings, whiſperings, rumors, tumults: leaſt when I come againe, my God abaſe me among yee, and I ſhall bewaile many of thoſe which haue ſinned before, and not repented for their vncleaneſſe, fornication, and wantonneſſe which they haue committed, 2. Corin. 12▪ verſ. 20. 21.
               
               The ſeauen Churches of Aſia, Reuel. 1. were not in euery reſpect commended: for in ſome of them the Nicholaitans were ſuffered, and they that taught the doctrine of Balaam, and a wicked woman, which made her ſelfe a Prophetiſſe, was ſuffered to teach and to ſeduce the ſeruants of God. One Church neither hote nor colde. Another had but a fewe in it which had not polluted themſelues, Reuel. 2. and 3. Yet are

theſe named the Churches. I conclude therefore, that the not ſeperating of ſome wicked ones out of the Churche, although it be euill, yet is not ſuch an euill as deſtroyeth the Church, and that the godly are not polluted by the wicked, which come together with them vnto the publike exerciſes of the holy religion.
               Thus haue I prooued your article, or your accuſation, partly hereticall, and partly falſe. I haue alſo made manifeſt, that if yée did accuſe rightly, yet the conſequence is to be diſalowed as hereticall, in as much as we ſée, that very often it hath come to paſſe, that heapes of vngodly men haue worſhipped together with the godly, and they not polluted by them. It may be ſome will thinke hardly that I account it hereticall, that the Browniſt concludeth after this ſorte, they haue open ſinners, and men prophane in life, which doo worſhip together with them, as members of their Church, therefore the couenant is diſanulled with them all. I will therefore prooue that I haue ſaid by ſtrong arguments: the firſt ſhall be this. Whoſoeuer maintaineth, that where any groſſe ſinnes breake forth and appeare, there is not any true faith in the parties which offend, he doth contrary to the expreſſe word of God, maintaine flat hereſie: for we are taught euery where, that regeneration which conſiſteth in putting of the old man, and putting on the new, is by degrées wrought in Gods elect. Whervpon the holy Ghoſt compareth the ſpirituall birth with the naturall. A man is borne a poore weake babe, not able to go alone, or yet to ſtand vpright: hee is nouriſhed and fed with milke, and ſo in continuance, dooth growe vp by degrées vnto mans eſtate. We are borne againe, not of mortall but of immortall ſeed, euen the word of God which indureth foreuer, 1. Pet. 1. wherefore he willeth, that laying aſide all maliciouſnes, deceipt, hypocriſie, and ſuch like, we couet the ſincere milke of the word, that we may grow thereby, 1. Pet. 2. ver. 1. &amp; 2. The regenerate are in many places exhorted to put off, and to mortifie euill and vncleane luſts, &amp; to forſake their wicked ſins, Rom. 12. Epheſ. 4. Coloſ. 3. Iam. 1. And if in many things we ſinne all, Iam. 4. Yea euē ſuch as are grown vp in Chriſt to mans eſtate.

How many, ſhall we then ſuppoſe, are the falles of poore new borne Babes? if Dauid, Solomon, Samſon, and many other, repleniſhed with great grace, did fall gréeuouſly, how ſhall we looke that other ſhall be frée? Let the Church of Corinth be for an example in this point, euen the teachers and people together, vnto whom S. Paul writeth thus: I could not ſpeake vnto yee brethren, as vnto ſpirituall men, but as vnto carnall men, as vnto babes in Chriſt. I gaue yee milke to drinke and not meate, for yee could not beare it, neither can yee now: for yee are yet carnall: for when as there are among yee emulation, contention, and diſcords, are yee not carnall and walke as men? when one ſaith, I am of Paul, an other I am of Apollo, are yee not carnall? 1. Cor. 3. ver. 1. 2. 3. 4. Is not the matter as cléere as the Sunne, that he calleth them carnal, burthened with the fleſh, and in that reſpect prophane, as their open ſinnes did declare, and yet babes in Chriſt, regenerate through faith, and the déere children of God? It is ſaid of our Sauiour, Hee will not breake the bruſed reed, nor quench the ſmoaking Flax Math. 12. ver. 20. Saint Paul following the ſteps of his Maiſter, in care, in loue, in mercie, and compaſſion, toward the poore weake babes in Chriſt, behaued himſelfe in the Churches, as a nurſſe vnto hir little infants. 1. Theſſ. 2. ver. 8. But the fierce Browniſts doo maintaine contrary to this manifeſt doctrine of the Scriptures: that where corrupt manners breake foorth in thoſe that profeſſe the Goſpell, they be not onely vtterly voide of faith which offend, but alſo, that all they which worſhip together with them, though neuer ſo much gréeued at their ſinnes, are fallen from the couenant moſt cruelly by this meanes, thruſting downe all the weake, and caſting foorth all poore babes. I may ſay the ſtrong together with them: therefore the Browniſts doo maintaine hereſye. Euery faithfull man is to follow the example of bleſſed Paul, in that which he dooth teſtifie of himſelfe, how he forgat the things which were behinde, and preſſed forward toward the things which were before, euen towards perfection, Phil. 3. ver. 14. But yet it followeth in the ſame place, neuertheleſſe, in that vnto which we are come, let vs procéed by one

rule, to be like affected. Shall the ſtrong, when all are to take the iourney together, runne away, and leaue the babes and the féeble behinde them? nay, rather let them leade them by the hand, carie them in theyr armes, and vpon their ſhoulders. Let the Browniſts alone, who, as if they were ayrie ſpirits, diſburthened of all lumpe of the fleſh, mount vp aloft, and leaue poore heauie loden ſinners crawling vppon the earth. The other argument by which I prooue them to maintaine Hereſie in this their ſecond accuſation, is this, Whoſoeuer maketh the ſtableneſſe of Gods couenant towards his people, and with his Church, to depend vppon the works of men, he mayntayneth flat Hereſie: for albeit the words of the Couenant be theſe, I will be your God, and you ſhall be my people, which implyeth a true ſanctification required to glorifie God, and to be thankfull, yet the Couenant is wholly and altogether of mercie, yea euen of the riches of his frée grace, who hath promiſed and ſworne vnto vs to declare the ſtableneſſe of his counſell, that we might haue ſtrong conſolation, Hebrewes 6. verſ. 17. We are ſaued by grace, and not by works, Tit. 3. As the Couenant was made vnto Dauid in ſome particular, ſo was it to Abraham and his ſéede in generall. Then thus it is written: I will make him my firſt borne, higher then the Kings of the earth. I will keepe my mercy for him for euer, and my couenant with him ſhall be ſtable. I will ſet his ſeed for euer, and his throne as the daies of heauen. If his children ſhall forſake my lawe, and not walke in my iudgements. If they ſhall prophane my Statutes, and not obſerue my commaundements: I will viſite their defection with the rod, &amp; their iniquitie with plagues. But I will not diſanull my mercy towards him, nor falſifie my faith. I wil not prophane my couenāt, nor alter the thing which is gone out of my lips. I haue once ſworne by my holines, I wil not lie vnto Dauid, Pſal. 89. v. 28. If the couenant made with Abraham and his ſéede, did not ſtand after the ſame ſort ſtabliſhed vppon the frée promiſe of grace, and vppon the oath of God, how could it be ſaid after all the defections and rebellions of the Churche of Iſraell reckoned

vp, and after hée had chaſtiſed them, that hée remembred his couenant with them, and he repented through the multitude of his compaſſions, if it be ſayd, they repented, and ſo returned agayne into couenant with him, and obteyned mercie. I anſwere, they repent not but by his mercie and grace which he beſtowed vpon them, becauſe they were within his couenant. Now the Browniſts in affirming that by open groſſe ſinne committed by any, if they remayne ſtill in the Church, the couenant is not only diſanulled to them, but vnto all that doo communicate with them, and ſo make the ſtableneſſe of Gods couenant, not to depend vpon mercie and frée grace promiſed and bound with an oth, but vppon our works, yea, and in a more tickle eſtate, euen vppon the woorkes of other whome we muſt iudge. Therefore the Browniſts mayntayne verie wicked hereſie, when they crye out, that thoſe aſſemblyes where any open ſinners are not caſt foorth, they be no longer the true Church of God, but the Couenant is diſanulled with them all that doo ioyne together in that ſocietie. I might héere make an ende touching this ſecond principall tranſgreſſion, but that there bée certayne particular reaſons, by which they ſtand to mayntayne theyr opinion. Firſt, to this effect many doo ſpeake. If there be wicked men ſuffered to come to the Table of the Lord, the Miniſter and Eccleſiaſticall Gouernours doo commit ſo grieuous a ſinne, that they can not but be vtterly voyde of the true feare of God. Then, he which is a wicked man, can not be a Miniſter of Chriſt, and béeing no Miniſter of Chriſt, there is no Sacrament of Chriſt deliuered, how then ſhall a man communicate with that aſſemblie? I haue ſhewed before, that there be great ſinnes and great neglect of dutie oftentimes where there is the true faith in weakeneſſe, and ſo they ſinne damnablie, which take vppon them to iudge them no Chriſtians. The faithfull in Corinth were blinded in theyr owne faults, and verie ſecurely did the Paſtors and Gouernours ſuffer the inceſtuous perſon to continue among them. And whereas they ſay, that if the Miniſter

be vngodly, he can be no Miniſter of Chriſt, it is falſe: for the man touching his owne perſon may be a reprobate, and yet touching his miniſterie, a Miniſter of Chriſt. Iudas was a Miniſter of Chriſt, and baptized, Iohn. 4. ver. 2. they were as truly and effectually baptized by him, as by Peter, and yet in himſelfe a Deuill, Iohn. 6. verſ. 70. The two Sonnes of Ely were horrible wicked men, 1. Sam. 2. ver. 12. 22. and yet they are called not only Prieſts, but Prieſts of the Lord, 1. Sam. 1. verſ. 3. Ely himſelfe did offend, and was ſharply puniſhed, that being not only their Father, but alſo high Prieſt and Iudge, he did not put them from the dignitie of the Office, but did honour them with the ſame, not regarding Gods honour, 1. Sam. 2. verſ. 29. The Scribes and Phariſies who were not all of the Sonnes of Leuy, for Saint Paule was a Phariſie, and the Sonne of a Phariſie, but yet of the Tribe of Beniamin, were Miniſters of the Church, for Chriſt ſayth, They ſate in Moyſes Chayre, and willed men to heare them, notwithſtanding, they were blinde guides, hypocrites, prowde, couetous, ambitious, and verie reprobates, Matth. 23. Then, next they alleadge, that a little leauen doth leauen the whole lumpe, 1. Cor. 5. Therefore where one open notorious Sinner is admitted to be a member of the Church, all are leauened and polluted, all doo fall from God. I aunſwere, that Saint Paule rebuketh the Corinthes, that they were puffed vp, and did glorie when they ſhould haue ſorrowed: for as many as had the power of the Diſcipline in theyr hands, and did neglect, were partakers of his ſinne, and not only they, but of priuate members, all that did not mourne and lament to ſée ſuch a foule matter wincked at. As the Lord himſelfe doth cléere all thoſe which mourned for the abhominations of Ieruſalem, Ezechiel. 9. ſo were they frée and not leauened, which did mourne at Corinth for ſuch abuſes. Moreouer, it is verie falſe to ſay, that whole Church was leauened, or polluted with the ſinne of that wicked man, therefore they were not the Church of God. For béeing giltie not only in that fault,

but in many other, hée giueth them the honour of Gods Church, writing to the Church of God which is at Corinth, 1. Corinth. 1. Then are obiected the words and commaundement of the Lord by Saint Paule: If any that is called a brother be a fornicator, or couetouſe, or an Idolater, or a rayler, or a drunckard, or an extortioner, with ſuch ſee that yee eate not, 1. Cor. 5. Some hold, that this commaundement is giuen only againſt the eating with an open ſinner at the Lords Table, ſéeing we may eate common bread with ſuch as be verie wicked. Others doo argue thus: If it be not lawfull to eate common bread with a wicked man, how much more vnlawfull ſhall it be to eate with him that holie bread of the Lords Table? as the Anabaptiſts lighting vpon theſe words of our Sauiour Chriſt, but I ſay vnto ye, Sweare not at all, Matth. 5. do gather, that it is vtterlie vnlawfull in any reſpect or at any time to take an oath, and erre, in not conſidering the circumſtances whereby the words vttered in generall, are to be reſtrayned vnto the particular abuſe, and raſh ſwearing. Euen ſo the Browniſts, taking the words as they ſtand, and not waying the circumſtances, doo mayntayne abſurdities. They drawe theyr Argument of compariſon from things in which the ſinne or pollution is not: for the ſinne is not in the eating of the common bread, neyther in eating the bread of the Lord with the wicked, but in circumſtances. For I may eate bread with open ſinners, and offend thereby, and I may eate bread with notorious wicked men, and not offend therein, yea, I may grieuouſly ſinne, in refuſing to eate with them. I will expreſſe how. If there be open groſſe offenders, and my familiaritie with them, or my eating with them, can not be, but I ſhall eyther be partaker of their ſinne, or countenance and harden them in the ſame, I offend, if I doo not ſhunne their companie. If any brother in the Church be conuict of foule ſinne, found obſtinate▪ and ſo Excommunicate▪ euery member of the Church euen by the commaundement of God, is to haue no fellowſhip with him, that he may be aſhamed,

                  2. Theſ. 3. v. 14. But yet we are willed in the ſame place, not to account him as an enimie, but to admoniſh him as a Brother. For if men ſhould now in familiaritie, receiue him to their table, or go to his table, it would harden him in his obſtinacie, and bring the cenſure and power of the Church into contempt. This is that S. Paul dealeth about. The wife of this man, his children, and ſeruants may eate with him, or anye other, where it cannot be eſchewed, for then it dooth not countenance him. Now if I be in a ſhip vpon the ſea, among a company of vild wicked men, or in a priſon, or in an armie, and can haue no meate, vnleſſe I eate with them, if I refuſe, I famiſh my ſelfe to death, and ſo offend gréeuouſlie. We ſée then it is not the very eating with them that dooth defile, but the circumſtances. Euen ſo is it at the Lordes table, where wicked men be admitted. For ſuch as doo admit them, hauing power to repell, do offend in eating there with them, becauſe they countenance them in their ſinne. But nowe a priuate member which is gréeued at this, and dooth what lyeth in him to haue it redreſſed, dooth not offend, nor is not polluted by eating with them. But as he, that among the wicked in the ſhip, in the priſon, or in the Campe, doth offend in refuſing his bodely ſuſtenance: ſo ſhall he, if he refuſe that heauenly foode of his ſoule, for all the wicked cannot corrupt the ſame vnto him.
               This man hath no fellowſhip with the vnfrutefull works of darkeneſſe. This man dooth obey the Commaundement, come out from among them, ſeparate your ſelues, and touch no vncleane thing, &amp;c. For he toucheth not their ſinne, but the holy things of God: for the ſeperation from the wicked, cannot be alwaies in body. Where there is idolatrie practiſed, and the faith and true worſhip ouerthrowne, we muſt depart both in minde and bodye: but from wicked men in the Church, we cannot depart in bodye, vnleſſe we will alſo depart from Chriſt.
               If it were otherwiſe, how ſhould the faithfull, without pollution, worſhip as they did in the Temple, among ſo many prophane men? and how ſhould thoſe few at Sardi, Reuel. 3
                  
haue kept their garments vnpolluted, among that heape of vngodly men? Now let the reader iudge, whether I haue in a frantike manner, as you accuſe me, blaſphemed the name of Chriſt, by comparing yée vnto Anabaptiſts, and Donatiſts, in this your condemning and forſaking the Church for the euil men which be in it. I would to God both you and others could conſider that which is written of King Saul, when as the holy Ghoſt ſaith, he was zealous for the Children of Iſrael and Iuda, 2 Samuel. 21. and would roote out the Gybeonites. Did not the Lorde declare by the thrée yeares famine, and by cauſing ſome of the houſe of Saul to be hanged, how curſſed his cruell zeale was, which yet hee had ſome colour of from the lawe, which willed them to roote out the Heathen? The cruell zeale of Browniſts, which ſéemeth to bee for the Church, is more without excuſe, when they will néedes roote vp the naturall plants, as now they may be called, yea euen the whole aſſemblies, both old and yoong.
            
         
         
            The third accuſation.
            
               The Brow. 
               FOr that they haue a falſe Antichriſtian Miniſterie impoſed 
               vpon them, &amp;c.
            
            
               The third fault is an Antichriſtian miniſterie impoſed andG. G. maintained. Héere is no reaſon rendred, why it is a falſe and Antichriſtian miniſtery which is impoſed. If yée be Prophets raiſed vp of God, then wee muſt beléeue that which you ſay: but they did not lie in any matter, but euery man may ſée that you haue in the former article lyed, wee may not therefore giue, &amp;c.
            
         
         
            
               The Brow. 
               Heere you ſay is no reaſon rendered by vs, why it is a falſe 
               and Antichriſtian miniſtery which is impoſed. But if you had better weighed theſe two former tranſgreſſions, wherewith we charge you, or duly conſidered of this, or of your owne anſwer, before you had put penne to paper, you might haue gained this labour you haue taken, and ſhame you
               
               are like to ſuffer by theſe your friuolous and indirect anſweres, &amp;c.
            
            
               What reaſons yée haue brought in your two former accuſations,G. G. or in this third, to prooue the Miniſterie of England Antichriſtian, let all wiſe men iudge. Indéed if we will admit falſe accuſations, and hereticall opinions, for reaſons, then haue yée ſaid ſomewhat, for in them yée are prompt and plentifull. The ſhame yée ſpeake of, that I am like to ſuſtaine by mine aunſwers, I doo not feare at all. It appeareth plainely by your words, it dooth not pleaſe yée, that yée are not encountred in diſputation by ſome famous learned men, ſo deſirous yée are of that glory. But is it méete, or is there any reaſon, that preſumptuous, bold, and raſh ignorance, ſhould not be incountred but with great learning: Sophiſters, nay poore artificers and Huſbandmen, are the eueneſt matches to diſpute with yée? If I had counſelled with my learned brethren, yée ſay, they would haue counſelled me not to write. You haue put on the Lions ſkinne, and ſo imagine, that all the learned doo tremble at yée, and the truth is, they haue eſpied your long eares: (But rather to haue vſed my diſcretion in the Pulpit, as they doo, where wee may ſaye what wee luſt without controulement, for they conſider an euill matter is to bee raked in,) &amp;c. If I did not know the contrary, yée are ſo confident in your ſpéeches, that I ſhould almoſt beléeue yée. But now that I know, as ſure as anye thing may be knowne, that you doo impudently ſlaunder and belie the learned, who though they diſdaine to deale with mad frenſie, yet they like well, in reſpect of the poore people which are ready to be ſeduced, that your matters ſhould be aunſwered, how will yee perſwade me, or others, that yée are not without care what yée ſpeake? And if there be any ſparke of modeſtie leaft in yée, I will not ſay, make ſome due proofe, but euen a colourable ſhew, that the learned of this land, if I had conferred with them, would haue giuen that counſell vnto me▪ which you affirme, and for that cauſe which you mention. Now come your reaſons, you are perſwaded by the worde of God, that a true miniſter of

Chriſt, cannot be a miniſter of idolatrous and falſe worſhip. Yee are rightly perſwaded, and I am fully of your minde in this point. But where yée ſay ye haue prooued our worſhip to be ſuch, therein yée faile, for ye haue falſely accuſed, but not prooued. Then yee were alſo perſwaded by the word of God, that a true Paſtor cannot ſtand an heard to the Lords Goates and Swine, bleſſing them with the bleſſing of the faithfull, and deliuering to them the holy things of God, as the Sacraments, &amp;c. I haue ſhewed alſo in that your ſecond accuſation, how preſumptuouſly and heretically yée haue dealt, in iudging Chriſtian men to be Heathen and Swine. In this third accuſation, your reaſon is in the word impoſed. That miniſterie which is impoſed vpon the flockes, is Antichriſtian, becauſe they be not fréely choſen by the Lords faithfull people, &amp;c. But the Miniſtrie of the Church of England is impoſed, &amp;c. I take exception againſt both the propoſition and aſſumption of this argument. For the propoſition, albeit the impoſing of a miniſter vpon the flocke, may carry an iniurie to the Church depriued of hir priuiledge and right: yet it dooth not followe, that the ſame miniſter or his miniſtery is Antichriſtian. Our Sauiour in the place ye alledge, Iohn. 10. ſpeaketh onely of Heretikes and falſe Prophets, which clime ouer into the ſhéepefold, he ſpeaketh not of any which lead the ſhéepe to the doore, that is to Chriſt, whether their calling to the office haue béene ſuch in all reſpects, or not as it ought to be. Secondly, if by frée choiſe of the faithfull, you meane that in the chooſing of a Paſtor, the people or priuate members of the flocke are to giue their voices, or elſe the miniſter is impoſed and Antichriſtian: then doo yée condemne all the Miniſters of France, of Geneua, and other Churches. For they are not choſen by the voices of the people, neither doe they hold that way the moſt conuenient, for the people to declare their conſent, but rather theyr ſilence, as yée may ſée in diuerſe Epiſtles of Maiſter Beza, and namely in the laſt. But when a flocke is deſtitute of a Paſtor, their choiſe is after this ſort: The Prebyterie or Senate of Paſtors and Teachers, doo examine and make triall, and chooſe him whome they ſhall finde euery way qualified for ſo

worthy a function. The matter being made knowne to as many as may be, and eſpecially to that flocke ouer which he is to be ſet, that if any can alleadge iuſt cauſe why he is vnworthy of ſuch an office, they be heard, otherwiſe after a due kind he is ordeyned and put into poſſeſſion of his Miniſterie. Then touching your aſſumption, the Miniſters of the Church of England (as ye ſay) be impoſed: If ye vnderſtand by impoſed, that they be all thruſt vppon the flockes againſt theyr will and liking, or that the flockes haue no power to take exception, yee ſpeake vntruly. For there be many flockes in England, which haue thoſe Paſtors and Miniſters of the Goſpell whome they haue deſired to haue, and made choyſe of, I meane by ſuite, both to the Patrones, and to the parties whome they deſire to haue: and if any of the people can ſhew iuſt cauſe againſt the partie which is to be ordeined, the Byſhop may not admit him. There follow now many boaſting words, with which yee march in tryumph, it is pitie to put them out of their array. You require one reaſon at the leaſt to confirme our Miniſterie: I confeſſe it is a reaſonable requeſt, but firſt, I muſt anſwere that which ye bring for to ouerthrowe it. To proue our Miniſterie not to be of Chriſt, but to haue his negatiue: Yée ſay, yée finde not in his Teſtament the names we carry, the offices we beare, the manner of our entrance and adminiſtration, our ſupport and maintenance. Touching our names, we are called Miniſters of the Goſpell, Paſtors, and Teachers, which be the Tytles giuen in Gods word. The names of Parſons and Vicars, are not to make any diſtinction of the Miniſterie, but of the ſtate of maintenance annexed vnto the ſame. The Offices we beare, are to teach and inſtruct our flockes by the wholeſome word of God, to adminiſter the Sacraments, and to make publike prayers. And I am ſure, theſe are preſcribed in Chriſtes Teſtament, and if your eye were not malignant, yee might eſpy them there. Our entrance is not by intruſion, but by calling, and that in many, by the deſire of the flockes, as I haue ſhewed before: and for the manner of our adminiſtration, it hath béen dealt in at large in the firſt accuſation. Our ſupport

by Tythes and ſuch like, is not mayntayned as a matter of neceſſitie, but as the moſt conuenient. The word of God hath giuen the generall rule, that the Miniſter of the word is to be liberally mayntayned: the manner touching circumſtances, is to be ordered for moſt conueniencie by the Church, and power of the Chriſtian Magiſtrate. For many things are lawfull, and in the power of the Church to ordeyne, which are not particularly named in Gods word, but conteyned in generall rules. Your next words are farre ſharper, and cut more déepely, yea, euen ſo déepely, that wo bée vnto vs all, if you haue not the venemous toong of liers and falſe accuſers. Yée vſe a gradation to ſet foorth our pedigrée, for we are (yée ſay) the children of the Byſhops: The Byſhops are the creatures of the Pope: The Pope is the eldeſt ſonne of Satan, and his vicar generall in earth. Now, as yée haue ſet vs héere vnder a verie honorable parentage, ſo doo yée ſhewe vs great kindneſſe, in ſetting vs foorth not to be degenerate, but to beare the image, the marke, the power and life of the Pope: and together with him, to growe, liue, raigne, ſtand, and fall, as the branches with the trée. Héere is the verie bottome of your gall, héere is your poyſoned ſting thruſt as déepe as is poſſible. But let your words be examined: and by the ſtepps that you aſcend, I will deſcend. The higheſt is the Deuill, the father of lyes: Next vnto him, the Pope his eldeſt ſonne, and vicar generall in earth. In déede I am reſolutely perſwaded, that the Pope is the Beaſt, vnto whome the Dragon gaue his power, his Throne, and great authoritie, Reuel. 13. of whome it is ſayd in the ſame place, that all the world wondred and followed the Beaſt. They worſhipped the Dragon which gaue power to the Beaſt, and they woorſhipped the Beaſt, ſaying: Who is like to the Beaſt, who is able to warre with him? This no doubt is that man of ſinne, who hath exalted himſelfe aboue all that is called God, or that hath imperiall maieſtie, ſitting in the Temple of God, and boaſting himſelfe as God: whoſe comming ſhould be by the effectuall working of Satan, with all lying ſignes and wonders, 2. Theſſ. 2. He hath ſet vp the verie

worſhip of Deuils, with all abhominable Idolatrie, and blaſphemous hereſies and lyes. He hath not only vſurped and challenged a ciuill power and Lordſhip ouer Kings, but alſo a ſpirituall Dominion ouer the conſciences and faith of man, to make Lawes at his pleaſure contrarie to Gods word, to binde the ſame: this is the vicar generall of the Deuill. Then to come to the next ſteppe, where there is no queſtion nor doubt neyther to be made, but that all Popiſh Byſhops be the creatures and children of the Pope, in as much as they haue their calling, and conſecration, and power deriued from him; in as much as they ſweare obedience vnto him, to mayntayne his dignitie, his tyrannie, his doctrine, and his lawes: and in as much as they challenge together with him a Lordſhip and tyrannie ouer the conſcience. But the Byſhops of the Church of England haue not their calling, conſecration, or power frō the Pope, but frō our Church, which hath forſaken the Church of Rome, as the Sinagog of Satan. The Byſhops of England acknowledge no ſubiection to the Pope, but by an oath renounce his vſurped power &amp; tyranny. The Biſhops of Engl. are not ordeined to maintain or defend ye religion &amp; lawes of Antichriſt, but quite contrary, they promiſe and profeſſe to aduance the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; by the liuely word, to cut downe all idolatrie, hereſies, and popiſh abhominations. Finally, the Biſhops of Engl. do not vſurp a Lordſhip ouer the faith &amp; conſciences of men; for the power which they haue peculiar in the Church, is only in the adminiſtration of externall gouernment. It is therfore with manifeſt &amp; wicked ſclander, that ye tearme the Biſh. of Engl. Antichriſtian, the creatures of the Pope, and ſuch as haue his power &amp; life in thē, yea ſuch, as whoſoeuer is ordeined by thē, hath his miniſtry frō Antichriſt, and from the Deuill. There is controuerſy about the ſtate &amp; gouernmēt by Biſhops, whether ye Church of Engl. hath not erred in cōmitting into their hands the execution of diſcipline, which is the matter to be handled in your fourth accuſation: but to gather from hence a pedegrée from the Pope, is verie fooliſhe. Let vs come then to the loweſt ſtep, which is in the miniſters.

We haue laboured in ſtudie of holie things, to be fitte for the Miniſterie, and ſo furniſhed and inſtructed to the Kingdome of Heauen, as to be lyke Houſeholders that bring out of theyr Treaſures things new and old. We deſire to call men that wander in ignorance and ſinne, vnto the light, and ſo to build the Church of Chriſt. We know, no man is to be Iudge of his owne ſufficiencie, nor to intrude himſelfe into publike office, but to be tryed and ordeyned by the Church which hath that power committed into her hands from Chriſt. The ſupreme Magiſtrate, and Church of England haue committed this truſt vnto the Byſhops, iudging it the quieteſt and ſafeſt way. We are preſented vnto them to be examined and tryed, to be ordeyned and put into poſſeſſion of our Miniſterie by them, and from them to receyue the power to execute the ſame, not as theirs, but the Churches, which hath put it into their hands. It is the ordinance of God, and not the deuice of Antichriſt, that Paſtors and Teachers ſhall be tryed and ordeyned by Elders, Paſtors, and Gouernours, and ſet ouer his people. We receyue only this Ordinance, and ſuch as haue any vnderſtanding may ſée, that the queſtion can not be whether the power it ſelfe bée from Antichriſt, but whether there be not error and defects in adminiſtring the ſame, to the hurt and dammage of the Church? Now further, hauing receyued this authoritie, we Preach the holie Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, and by the pure doctrine of the ſame, we conuince and ouerthrowe Idolatrie, ſuperſtition, and Hereſies. We correct and reprooue all manner of vices, informe and exhort vnto true Godlines. In performing theſe things, we drawe men out of Poperie, by letting them vnderſtand, that the worſhip of Poperie, is the verie worſhip of Deuils, and that the Pope is Antichriſt.
               This Romane Antichriſt and his adherents doo féele, that the miniſterie of the Goſpell in England doth deſtroy hys kingdome, and therfore ſtirred vp by the Deuil they rage, and by all diueliſh meanes, ſéeke to deſtroy our noble Quéene and Countrie. Except therefore you Browniſts had euen let looſe all the raynes of your toong, and after a ſhameleſſe manner

to lie and ſlaunder, how could ye pronounce, that the miniſtery of England is Antichriſtian, and of the Deuill? or that it is in the life and power of the beaſt, to liue, to raigne, to ſtand, to fall together with him, as the branches with the trée? In the next place, yée haue whet &amp; filed your cankered toong, to vtter verye vile reproche, againſt the nurſeries of all good learning and holy religion within this land, the two Vniuerſities. I know not how idlely, and in what heathen vanitie yée ſpent your time there your ſelues: but this I dare avow, and make the challenge, and let triall be made, I will beare the ſhame for euer if it be not found true: that there be many in the Vniuerſities, and not aboue the degrée of Bachelour of Arts, vnto whome the principall Maiſters of Browniſme are inferior: if wee reſpect either the Liberall Artes, or the knowledge of toongs, as of Hebrew, Gréeke, and Latine, or a ſound iudgement in Diuinitie. If this can be attained in fewe yeares, with more then Moonkiſh idleneſſe, the Browniſts may in ſome thing be beléeued. Some do abuſe the liberall Arts: but to condemne Logike, Rhethorike, and the reſt as vaine and curious, as you doo, is a very beaſtly error. Saint Luke, from whom yée draw your phraſe of ſpéech, Act. 19. dooth not ſpeake of theſe, but of Magicall ſcience. I doo not maruaile, that blind Schiſmatikes doo ſo bitterly iuueigh againſt learning, ſéeing it is their bane. For they ſéeke victorie, triumphe, and glorye ouer all the learnedeſt, and if there were no learning to diſcouer and to lay open their nakedneſſe and ſhame, they would much preuaile, and be had in greater reputation. Thus do the Browniſts labour to bring in ſauage barbariſme. But yet héere, vp goeth your ſaile againe, and yée haue winde at will, and neuer ſo much ſea roome, as when with bitter ſlaunders and reproches yée rowle away. Ye wrappe vp altogether for the offences of ſome. Yée reckon vp certaine things of circumſtance, and in themſelues indifferent and yet vpon your credit we muſt take them to be odious enormities. Ye are vp with perfidi, tyrannie, and the ſtatutes of Omry. Your frenſie is great, I did aduiſe, that men would ſuſpend their iudgement, and enquire of the Churches touching the Miniſterie of England.

Againſt this yée crie out, and aſke, if it be the beſt counſell I can giue them? I anſwer, it is the beſt, being that which God hath ordeined. Haue yée not read, that the Préeſts lippes ſhall kéepe knowledge, men ſhall enquire at his mouth, for he is the Angell of the Lord of Hoſtes? By this it is cléere, that whenſoeuer Heretikes and Schiſmatikes doo raiſe doubts, it is Gods will that the people ſhall enquire for reſolution out of the word, at their mouthes whome he hath raiſed vp, and ſet as the greateſt lights in his Church. Yet ſée how ſottiſhly you cauill againſt this. Yée take it I would haue them doo things which they doubt off, and my wordes are but to haue them ſuſpend their iudgement, vntill they enquire, and not to be too raſh in following the call of blinde, preſumptuous, and hereticall ſchiſmatikes. Then yée ſay, I ſend them ouer the ſea we wotte not whether, &amp;c. They make doubt of vs, we are the men whoſe Miniſtery is in queſtion, we ſend them therefore vnto thoſe of whome they can haue no doubt, and that is to the worthy inſtruments and ſeruants of God, the Paſtors of other Churches. I do no not ſend them ouer the Seas, for there be diuerſe godly Churches of ſtrangers within the land, as the French, the Dutch, the Italian: there be the churches of Scotland, and no ſea to paſſe, nor diuerſitie of language ſo great as to hinder: we haue alſo the writings of all the worthieſt. Yée ſay I ſend them vnto the word of man: which is falſe, for I doo ſend them vnto the learned paſtors, to be reſolued by the word of God. Theſe haue the calling vnto this office from God, and his bleſſing vpon thoſe which ſéeke it with humility and reuerence. It is not to vſe old popiſh worne arguments, but yours is the courſe of all arrogant proud heretikes &amp; ſchiſmatikes, which couet to draw the people to depend vpon them, that they may haue fame, &amp; to forſake their Paſtors, which take it gréeuouſly, that they ſhould ſéeke reſolutiō any where but at their hand. Whether ſhall we iudge the godly learned miniſters of the Churches aboue named, which haue their calling from God, or the vnlearned &amp; raſh Browniſts, intruding themſelues without calling, and run before they be ſent, fitteſt to enquire at for reſolution? It were a pretie thing, to heare the Harlots

in the ſtewes, euen in good earneſt to boaſt and glory of their chaſtitie. Who is more fierce and outragious, more vncharitable in condemning, then yée Browniſts? And yet ye bragge of ſuch patience and charitie, as cannot be ouercome. Then yée turne your ſelues to thoſe poore ſoules as yée terme thē, whom we, like miſerable Phyſicians ſéeke to cure: and your Counſell you giue them. I doo allow it, for it is the ſame in effect, if you could ſée, that I gaue them before. I would to God the people did follow it: we ſhould not then haue one Browniſt, The Deuill counterfaiting Chriſts voice, in hereticall ſchiſmatikes, ſhould not be able to allure and call away the ſhéepe from their ſhéepeheards. Now remaineth the laſt point onely, that I ſhew ſome reaſon to prooue our Miniſtery to be of Chriſt.
               The miniſtery of the Goſpell, which bringeth the worde of faith and reconciliation betwéene God and the worlde, is the true miniſterie of Chriſt, for the Deuil and Antichriſt ordeine no ſuch miniſterie. Nowe the miniſterie of the Church of England, doth bring no word nor doctrine, but the ſacred ſcriptures. It preacheth faith in God through Chriſt, and the doctrine of repentance, deliuering the holy ſacraments, as ſeales to confirme the ſame. Let all the ſchiſmatikes in the world barke againſt it, and ſay we haue no word nor Sacraments: yet this is the holy word: God ſo loued the world, that hee gaue his onely begotten ſonne, that whoſoeuer beleeueth in him ſhould not periſh, but haue life euerlaſting. It may be ſayde, that many miniſters in England, doo not, nor cannot preach the Goſpell, how then is their miniſtery the miniſtery of reconciliation? Héere note, that as we muſt diſtinguiſh betwéene the miniſtery and the man himſelfe which is the miniſter: for the man may be of the Deuill, and yet his miniſtery of God: ſo muſt we alſo diſtinguiſh betwéene the function it ſelfe, and the execution of the ſame. For when one is called to bee a miniſter of the Goſpell, which is able, and dooth not preach, the defect is not in the function, but in his negligence about the execution. Likewiſe when the office or function is layd vpō him that cannot preach, the function it ſelfe is entyre,

the defect is in the execution thereof, through his diſabilitie. I ſay therfore, that the Miniſterie of England is the Miniſterie of the Goſpell, though ſome doo not, and ſome cannot Preach. Then further, ſuch as haue the calling and ordination of the Church, haue the Miniſterie of Chriſt: for it is giuen to the Church, to haue power to call and ordeine Miniſters. Now if the Church doo falt and breake, either by error or negligence, in ſome rules which are to be obſerued about this calling and ordinatiō, yet the power is not diſanulled, nor the function deſtroyed, vnleſſe we will hold, that where there is tranſgreſſion either of ignorance, or otherwiſe, the whole is ouerthrowne: and ſo conclude, that there is no praier nor worſhip of God, nor any true ſeruice doone vnto him vnder heauen, becauſe all is with errors and faults.
               In England the Miniſters haue their calling and ordination by the Church of God. For that people which hath forſaken hereſies, and falſe worſhip, and imbraced the doctrine of the Goſpell, hath in it the true Church, which hath the power. And the Miniſters intrude not themſelues, but haue the power giuen them by the hands of the Biſhops, who doo it not by their owne authoritie, nor by any authoritie from Antichriſt, but as committed to their truſt by publike authoritie. Moreouer, that is the Miniſterie of God, which is to bring men to the faith, and to build vp the body of Chriſt. The Miniſterie of England is to none other end. For the whole drift, the whole ſcope, and burthen laid vpon them, is to féede with wholſome doctrine, and to guide in the waye of godlineſſe, the ſhéepe of Chriſt, walking before them in godlye conuerſation. The Browniſt will not take himſelfe héere conuinced, but will ſay, theſe cauſes are but pretended, and are not in truth. I will therefore now reaſon from the effect, together with that which is properly adioyned to the Miniſterie of Chriſt. That Miniſterie, with the execution whereof there is ioyned the effectuall grace, power, bleſſing, and operation of the Holy-ghoſt, to the true conuerſion of mens ſoules, is not a Miniſterie of the Deuill, nor of Antichtiſt, nor commeth not in the life and power of the beaſt, but is indeed the true Miniſterie of Chriſt.

I thinke the Browniſts will not be ſo beaſtly as to affyrme that the grace and operation of the holy Ghoſt to the conuerſion of mens ſoules, is ioyned to that, and worketh by that which is of the Deuill, and commeth in the life and power of Antichriſt. Then it remayneth only, to ſhewe that there hath béene and is this grace and worke in the execution of our function. If the Browniſts will deny that euer they felt that maieſtie and power in the preaching, which can not be in the words of man, but only in that word which is ſharper then any two edged ſword, and pierceth ſo déepe, as to be a diſcerner of the thoughts and ſecret intents. Or if they will denie that euer they haue béene driuen by it vnto hatred, ſorrowe, and remorſe for ſinne, and rayſed vp with comfort and hope of forgiueneſſe, and with the promiſes of eternall glorie: Yet vnto many other which by it are conuerted vnto the Lord in déede, which vnto feare and trembling doo féele the power and ſwéetneſſe of the liuely word, it may be ſayd, as S. Paule ſpeaketh to the Corinths: for when his aduerſaries did denie him to be an Apoſtle, the Corinths by his Miniſterie were begotten in Chriſt: wherevpon he ſayth, If I be not an Apoſtle vnto others, yet am I vnto you, for you are the ſeale of mine Apoſtleſhip in the Lord▪ 
                  1. Cor. 9. ver. 2. Euen ſo, if the Miniſtery of Englād, be not the Miniſtery of Chriſt vnto others, yet you can not doubt of it: your faith, your repentance, your ioy in the Lord, are the ſeale of it. You can not but ſée and knowe, that they be vile blaſphemous wretches, which beare ye in hand, that it is not the word of God, nor the grace of his ſpirit which worketh in ye, but the power of the Deuill, and the ſpirit of Antichriſt. You knowe it is the direct way which the Deuill taketh by his miniſters to bring in flat Atheiſme, to diſgrace and throwe downe the credite of the miniſterie. But doth it not make againſt the Miniſterie of England, that many of the Browniſts confeſſe they haue béene greatly moued at ſometimes with the power of the preaching, and at the adminiſtration of the Sacraments? for may it not bée ſayd héerevpon, that it is but a deceyuable ſhewe of grace and power, for if it had béene in truth, it would haue continued?

I anſwer, it is ſufficient to proue the Miniſterie, and that the power of the holy Ghoſt goeth with it, when men haue bin ſo moued, although they do not continue, ſéeing the reprobate do féele the power, and taſte the ſwéetnes of the word for a time, Hebr. 6. He that hath therefore felt the power of God in his ſoule by the preaching of the word, and now doth not, the falt is in himſelfe. If the Brow. do further reply, that they be not true Chriſtians which yet are moued by the preaching, the motions are deceiptfull. Then I wil frō that which they confeſſe, ſhew that ſuch people are truly faithfull. For they confeſſe, that they were bleſſed and holy Martyrs that ſuffred in the dayes of Quéene Mary: and I ſay they were conuerted by the ſame miniſterie which we haue now. They had but the ſame motions at the preaching of Latimer, Howper, Taylor, Bradford, and others, which our people haue nowe. If the people at this day then féele the ſame effect in their ſoules at the preaching and Sacraments, touching faith, repentance, and reſolution to dye with ioy for the teſtimonie of the Lord if he ſhall require it, let the Browniſts, and all other wicked Sciſmatikes barke that we haue no Miniſterie, we haue no Word, we haue no Sacraments, nor true Church, yet the godly wiſe ſhall be able to diſcerne the voyce of Chriſt from the voyce of the Deuill, and perceyue that the power of our Miniſterie is not of the Deuill, but of the holy Ghoſt, whom they haue moſt wickedly reproched.
            
         
         
            The fourth tranſgreſsion.
            
               The Brow. 
               THen, for that their Churches are ruled by and remayne 
               in ſubiection, &amp;c.
            
            
               The fourth fault is, in the ſubiection to an AntichriſtianG. G. gouernment. If it were admitted that there is ſome yoake of Antichriſtian gouernmēt, vnder which, the poore Church may grone, as it is her lot to be oppreſſed with outward bondage, to be made to kéepe the Vineyard which is not her owne, to be beaten of the watchmen, to haue her vayle taken from her: is ſhe therefore no longer the Spouſe of Chriſt?
            
         
         
            
            
               The Brow. 
               But oh how farre are you from this? which wincke 
               with your eyes, ſtoppe your eares, and harden your hearts, which can not endure ſo much as to heare of your fearefull eſtate, which you ſee not, no nor ſuffer your ſores which you ſee to bee touched, but ſeeke rather to cloake and hyde them both from God and man, yea, to mitigate, tollerate, and iuſtifye them. Seeke you not heere to mitigate that heauie apparant Antichriſtian yoake your Churches ſtand vnder (whereof heeretofore you haue complayned in Parliaments) tearming it ſome yoake, beeing now peraduenture through long cuſtome growne lighter vnto you and more eaſye, then Chriſts yoake, at the leaſt, then Chriſts croſſe, &amp;c.
            
            
               To this fourth accuſation, my anſwere was very ſhort:G. G. for I did only propound this queſtion, whether it be no longer the Spouſe of Chriſt which is oppreſſed, and doth groane vnder ſome yoake of Antichriſtian gouernment? and ſhewed my iudgement, that it is the lot of the Church to be oppreſſed with outward bondage, alleaging for proofe ſome what out of the Song of Solomon. At this ye are ſtriken with ſuch wonderment, that as men caried almoſt beſide your ſelues, you begin with a vehement exclamation: and thrée things there are in my ſpéech which haue caſt ye into this agonie: the firſt, that (as you ſay) our Churches ſtand vnder an apparant heauie yoke of Antichriſt, and I ſpeake of the true Church oppreſſed with ſome yoke of Antichriſtian gouernment: the ſecond, that I ſay it is the lot of the Church to be oppreſſed with outward bondage. This ye tearme a blaſphemous error, becauſe as ye ſay, bondage is the badge of Antichriſt, the marke of the Beaſt, whereby his ſouldiers are diſcerned frō the ſouldiers of Chriſt, &amp;c. The third, that I falſifie &amp; peruert the places of Scripture which I alleadge to prooue that Gods Church may be oppreſſed with ſome outward bondage: where you will redéeme the places from ſuch violence and corruption, and giue ſuch a glimſe, that ſimple men of vnderſtanding ſhall diſcouer and ſearch out the falſe dealing of ſuch watchmen, and the greateſt clarke of vs all ſhal be taught héereafter how

to abuſe the ſcripture for a cloake to couer our ſinnes. O what valiant fellowes you be, who ſhall be able to ſtand in your hands? the greateſt clarks in this land are but babes to ſuch mighty gyants: how ſhall I do then? I muſt now defend my ſelf in theſe particulars aboue named. I will let the queſtion about the heauy apparant yoake of Antichriſt alone, vnto the laſt place, vnder which ye falſely charge our Church to ſtand, and deale with that firſt which I ſet downe. Where the firſt queſtion is, whether the true ſpouſe of Chriſt may be vnder ſome yoake of Antichriſtian gouernment. The ſecond, whether it be her lot to be oppreſſed with outward bondage. The third, whether thoſe places by me alleadged be rightly applyed to proue the ſame. I will not deale ſeuerally in theſe, but in all together, becauſe they be all but one in effect. Now to ſpeake preciſely and ſtrictly, the yoke of Antichriſt is only ſpirituall &amp; inward, where the faith &amp; conſcience are burthened, and be in ſubiection, to receiue his lawes and worſhip. This can not be borne, without falling from the fréedome we haue in Chriſt. But in a longer ſenſe, we call it Antichriſtian, whē the paſtors of the Church, or any of them, do vſurp more then they ought, in external gouernment, or tyrannouſly abuſe the power committed into their hands. This is that which I called ſome Antichriſtian yoke. Now the very point of the queſtion is, whether the true ſpouſe of Chriſt hath euer béen oppreſſed in this by any of her gouernours, as her lot in ſome outward bondage? I hold that ſhe hath, and for proofe, I alleaged thoſe ſayings out of the Song, againſt which you take exception, as places wreſted, which ſhall be conſidered, after other teſtimonies ſhewed. Then I demaund of ye firſt, whether it was not the ſpouſe of Chriſt, whom the Lord calleth Iſraell, his ſhéepe and his flocke? The paſtors of Iſraell did not only ſcatter theſe, but ruled ouer them, and exerciſed dominion by violence &amp; tyranny, Ezech. 34. v. 4. What ſay ye to this, the Prophets propheſie lies, the Prieſts exerciſe dominiō by their hand, &amp; my people loue to haue it ſo, Ier. 5. v. 31. Was there no true Church vnder this ruling of ye prieſts? Paſhur a chief prieſt in the temple, ſtroke Ieremy the Prophet, &amp;

put him in the ſtockes, Ierem. 20. ver. 1. will yée affirme that there was no true Church then? Come to the time in which our Sauiour liued vpon the earth: for as yet the kingdome of God was not taken away from them, which is threatned, Matth. 22: but the high Préeſt, with the other Préeſts, with the Phariſies and Elders of the people, had the Eccleſiaſticall power, which they tyrannouſly abuſed, and by it oppreſſed the faithfull, as appeareth in diuerſe places of the Goſpell, and namely in Iohn. 7. ver. 13. and Iohn. 9. ver. 22. Diotrephes ambitiouſly abuſed the power of gouernment, when he withſtood S. Iohn, as he teſtifieth in his third Epiſtle written vnto Gaius. I wrote (ſaith he) vnto the Church, but Diotrephes, who loueth to haue preheminence among them, receiueth vs not. Therefore if I come, I will declare his deeds, railing at vs with malitions words: and not content therewith, neither he himſelfe receiueth not the brethren, and them that would he forbiddeth, &amp; caſteth them out of the church. ver. 9. 10. Dooth S. Iohn tell the Chriſtians, that this tyrannous oppreſſion by Diotrephes, did make them to be no longer Chriſtes Church, which remained vnder him? Did he will them to ſeperate themſelues, and not to obey him any longer in any thing? Our Sauiour ſaith, the time will come, that they ſhall excommunicate yée. Iohn. 16. ver. 2. Antichriſt himſelfe ſitting in the Temple of God, ſeduced the reprobate, but could not deſtroy the Church, which yet he did gréeuouſly oppreſſe, and kéepe in ſome bondage. Whereby it appeareth, that Solomon ſpeaketh of that which ſhould fall out often, and be euen as it were the lot of the Church, to be iniuried, oppreſſed, and kept in ſome outward bondage, euen by thoſe, at whoſe hands ſhe ſhould finde moſt comfort, holding the places of Paſtors and Gouernours: as we haue ſéene in the Church of Iſraell before our Sauiour came, at the time he liued, and alſo in the Church vnder the Goſpell.
               You bring in diuerſe ſcriptures, which prooue, as you imagine, that an outward oppreſſion of the Church in externall gouernment, dooth make an vtter deuorſe betwixt her and Chriſt: but he that conſidereth thoſe things which I haue before

noted, and the ſundry oppreſſions of the Church, by her Paſtors, ſhall eaſily perceiue that Anabaptiſticall fréedome which yée glory of. For howſoeuer the Church with her Children are frée with God, and receiue no yoake vpon their faith and conſcience: yet in outward things they may be oppreſſed. You could abide well enough that phraſe of ſpéech oppreſſed, but to ſay, the Church of Chriſt may be in anye bondage, yée terme a blaſphemous error. Becauſe bondage yée ſay, is the badge of Antichriſt, the marke of the Beaſt, &amp;c. Take héede of the ſaying that is written, 2. Pet. 2. ver. 19. That the ſeducers promiſe libertie, and are themſelues the bend ſeruants of corruption. For you imagine and glorye of ſuch a full and perfect libertie, as that yée account it a blaſphemous error, to ſay the Church may be oppreſſed with outward bondage. It is ſtrange that there ſhould be ſuch a bolde ſpirite in rotten fleſh, as flatly to contrary the ſpirit of God. For the Lord ſayd to Abraham: Thy ſeede ſhall bee in bondage, and they ſhall oppreſſe them. But the nation whom they ſhall ſerue, will I Iudge, Geneſ. 15. He ſaith, he brought them out of the houſe of bondage, or of bond men, Exodus 20. Will ye affirme that the Church was not oppreſſed with outward bondage in Egypt? will ye deny that they were led captiue, and held in outward bondage in Babilon? cannot this word bondage, which the holy Ghoſt vſeth, be allowed of yée? muſt bondage of neceſſity be the badge and marke of Antichriſt? when the Lord threatneth by his Prophets, that his people ſhould go into captiuity, and that there ſhould be a yoake of bondage layd vpon them, dooth he giue them ouer to weare the badge of Antichriſt? or ſo to be ſeruants vnto men, that they could not alſo be his ſeruants? Indéed the Anabaptiſts do holde, that wee cannot be ſeruants vnto men in any outward bondage, &amp; yet be the ſeruants of Chriſt, grounding their hereſie vpō the places which you alledge. If all maner of bondage be the marke of the beaſt, and the badge of Antichriſt, and a looſing of Chriſtian liberty, as you and the Anabaptiſts would haue it: then how could S. Paul ſay, Art thou a bond man, care not: thou art the Lords free man, 1. Cor. 7? Let no man ſuppoſe that I charge ye ouer hardly, with this groſſe point of Anabaptiſtrie, becauſe our

queſtion is about Church gouernment, and I ſpeake of ciuill bondage: for ye ſpeake generally of outward bondage, and denie that it can be the lot of the Church, or of any member therof. The worde bondage, though it▪ be outward, cannot in anye ſenſe be allowed by you, to agrée with your fréedom. Now for the places in the ſong, My mothers ſonnes were angrye with me, they ſet me to keepe the Vines, mine owne Vine I haue not kept. In this place the Church willeth: firſt yt they ſhould not looke ſcornefully vpon her, becauſe ſhe is ſomwhat blacke. Then ſhe ſheweth, that it is not her natiue colour, but ſhe is ſunne burnt: the ſunne (ſaith ſhe) hath looked vpon me. There followeth the occaſion, that her mothers ſonnes were angrye with her, ſet her to kéepe the Vines. Who theſe be whome ſhe calleth her mothers ſonnes, is the greateſt difficultie to finde. Tremellius (whoſe interpretation in that point ye follow) doth expound it of originall ſinne, &amp; the luſts which ſhe hath frō the wombe: other take it, &amp; more fitly, of falſe brethrē, which boaſt thēſelues to be true worſhipers, &amp; children of the church, which ſhe calleth her mothers ſonnes, becauſe they deſcended frō the ancient mother church, &amp; were the degenerate children of holy forefathers, for I take it ſomwhat hard to cal ſins or concupiſcences her mothers ſons. But take it whether way ye wil, either of original ſin &amp; concupiſcences, or of degenerate children, among whom there were many, euen of the Paſtors &amp; gouernors, yet ye cannot auoid, but yt there is a violence, an oppreſſion▪ &amp; ſome bondage: for ſhe ſaith, they ſet her to kéep the vineyards. Howſoeuer you would ſlily inſinuate, that it were but negligence, &amp; that when ſhe repenteth, ſhe is ſo cléered, that ſhe is in no bondage vnto ſinne at all. But when ye haue cauilled what ye can, it ſtandeth cléere by the ſcriptures, yt the Church in her perfecteſt repentance, euen with all her children, is held in ſome ſpirituall bondage vnto ſin, but yet ſhe is not obſtinat I grant, for ſhe hateth the euil ſhe doth, &amp; laboureth againſt it. I doe not gather from this, that the Church either did or may, kéepe Antichriſts Vine, as you demaund, what a bolde falſifiyng of the place this is? But I ſaye: what a bolde impudencie is this in you, ſo to falſifie my wordes? For I alledge it, to prooue, that the Church is ſubiect to bee oppreſſed

                  
                     〈1 page missing〉
                  bable ſo much of Antichriſt and his yoake. Then let hym prooue that euery error, abuſe, and great fault in diſcipline, doth ouerturne it, and make it become Antichriſtian, yea, Antichriſts yoake, ſo farre as to make it no Church which is ſubiect to ſuch oppreſſion. It is moſt cléere that a Church may erre in ſundrie poynts of Doctrine, and not be Antichriſtian, but the true Spouſe of Chriſt. And an error in Doctrine, if it be foule, doth approch néerer towards the ouerthrowe of faith, then an error or an abuſe in externall gouernment.
               Moreouer, if the execution of diſcipline by Byſhops be the yoake of Antichriſt, and if all the Churches which doo ſtande vnder the ſame, doo worſhip the Beaſt and be no Chriſtians, it muſt néedes followe, that ſuch as did euer execute this power, were Antichriſts, and no children of God at that time, or before they repented. But this is falſe euen by your owne confeſſion, which acknowledge, that thoſe woorthie ſeruants of God which ſometime executed that power, and after ſuffered death for the Goſpell in the dayes of Quéene Mary, were bleſſed Martyrs. I conclude therefore, that the Browniſts can not but with hereſies, and moſt heinous iniurie, and inordinate dealing, condemne a Church as quite diuorced and ſeparated from Chriſt, for ſuch imperfections and corruptions in Gods worſhip, as be not fundamentall, nor deſtroy the ſubſtance: for that wicked men come with the godly to the publike exerciſes of religion: for ſome wants in calling, and ordeyning Miniſters, and in Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline.
            
         
         
            
               Article 1.
               
                  The Brow. 
                  We ſeeke aboue all things the peace and protection of 
                  the moſt high, and the kingdome of Chriſt our Lord.
               
               
                  G. G. The firſt Article is that which all true Chriſtians doo ſéeke indéede. But the kingdome of Chriſt, or the kingdome of God (as Chriſt ſayth) is within men: it conſiſteth in righteouſneſſe and peace and ioy of the holy Ghoſt. For the preſeruation

of this, Chriſt hath ordeyned a Church gouernment. They ſinne againſt God, which doo not couet, and according to theyr calling, labour to haue ſo great a helpe. But to tranſport the name of Chriſts kingdome, which is chiefely Spirituall in the heart, vnto this, which is but a part, and as though the kingdome of God could not be in any, vnleſſe they haue this (ſo they doo not wilfully deſpiſe it) I ſay is falſe, and the contrary to be proued by the Scriptures.
               
                  The Brow. 
                  Our Article beeing by you confeſſed to be the bounden 
                  dutie of all true Chriſtians, wee ſee not with what equitie you can in this manner cauill at our words, or with what conſcience you can miſconſtrue and conſtrayne them as you doo, ſeeking thereby to retract by ſleight, what you can not gayneſay in truth, and taking occaſion to contende about wordes, namely, the kingdome of Chriſt, you make it only inward, and vſe Chriſt like one of the Phiſitions Planetarie Signes, aſsigning to him in hypocriſie your heart and ſoule to rule, whileſt in the meane whyle you yeeld your bodyes and whole aſſemblyes to the obedience and rule of Antichriſt, making no conſcience to obey his lawes openly, and to tranſgreſſe Chriſtes, thinking belike Chriſts kingdome ſo inward and ſpirituall, as that he requireth no bodily nor outwarde obedience, or becauſe it conſiſteth in righteouſnes and peace and ioy of the holy Ghoſt, that there may be peace without righteouſnes, or ioy without peace or inward righteouſnes, where is ſuch outward diſobedience, and wilfull tranſgreſsion, &amp;c.
               
               
                  G. G. I did confeſſe, and doo ſtill acknowledge, that this fyrſt Article is that which all true Chriſtians ſhould ſéeke. I hold, that Chriſtes Kingdome is chiefely inwarde and Spirituall, and that the diſcipline is but a part thereof: your ſelues haue repeated my words, and yet charge me, that I make Chriſtes Kingdome only inwarde, aſſigning the Soule to

him, and the body to Antichriſt to be ruled. I can not but wonder at your boldneſſe in lying. You ſay, that to diſcuſſe how farre euery Chriſtians calling and duty extendeth héerein, were to diſmiſſe all mine anſwers, and to plucke away the mantle of ſhame wherewith we couer our nakedneſſe, negligence, and abhominations. I meruaile why ye doo not then diſcuſſe it: for we hold, that no man is to labour beyond his calling to reforme any thing amiſſe in the Church: and when it ſhall be declared vnto what bounds and limits the calling of priuate men is reſtrayned, I am ſure there will be no mantle nor ragge to couer the preſumptuous dealing of Browniſts, which intrude themſelues without calling. Yée let this thing paſſe therefore, and will only aſke two queſtions. The firſt is, whether any which haue their calling of Antichriſt, be his marked Miniſters and waged ſeruants, can truly and vprightly couet and labour for Chriſts ſincere gouernment; which is his whippe wherewith he ſcourgeth out all théeues, intruders, and idle bellies out of his houſe? The other queſtion is, whether to remayne wittingly and ſeruilely in the bondage and yoake of Antichriſt xxix. yeares, be to labour for the gouernment of Chriſt faithfully in our callings? Ye muſt graunt me ſome time to anſwer to theſe two queſtions, and that ſhalbe when you anſwer theſe two which I propound. The firſt is, whether ignorant, hereticall, and raſh Sciſmatikes be méete and competent Iudges to condemne all the learned Miniſters in a Kingdome? The other is, whether falſe and lying accuſations be to ſtand for due proofe? Ye ſéeme to graunt, that the Kingdome of God may be in the ſcattered faithfull which yet haue not the diſcipline: I did not charge ye with the contrarie, but only ſhewed how I did allowe the Article. Yet remember what ye doo hold in this place.
            
            
               Article 2.
               
                  The Brow. 
                  We ſeeke and purpoſe to worſhip God aright according 
                  as he hath commaunded in his word.
               
               
                  G. G. This ſecond Article ought all men that will pleaſe God to approoue.
               
               
                  The Brow. 
                  This article ſay you, ought all that will pleaſe God to approoue. 
                  How then ſeeke you to pleaſe God? which continue in idolatrie, and are a miniſter thereof, which prophecie in Baal, and plead for Baal? or how approoue you it, when yee condemne vs of ſchiſme and hereſie, becauſe we forſake your falſe and Antichriſtian worſhip, and ſeeke to worſhip Chriſt according to his word?
               
               
                  G. G. When yée haue prooued that our worſhip is Idolatrie, and that we propheſie in Baal and for Baal, let men take yée to be no ſchiſmatikes nor heretikes. But ſuch as boaſt that they ſéeke to worſhip God according to his word, and yet arrogantlye breake ſundrye ſpeciall rules thereof, cannot but in their vaine boſting be liers, as S. Iames ſaith, againſt the truth.
            
            
               Article 3.
               
                  The Brow. 
                  We ſeeke the fellowſhip and communion of his faithfull 
                  and obedient ſeruants. And together with them, to enter couenant with the Lord, and by direction of his ſpirite to proceed to a godly free right choiſe of Miniſters, &amp;c.
               
               
                  G. G. The third Article, if it be taken in this ſence, that ye do ſet vp a ſocietie ſeperated from all other within this land, which make publike profeſſion: then I ſée not, when yée haue gone by your ſelues, and ſet vp your officers, howe you will cléere your ſelues from Donatiſme. If theirs were a damnable fact which God did accurſſe, then take héed to yours. For if it can be ſhewed, that their hereſies are not holden by you, I will change my minde.
               
                  The Brow. 
                  The words of our article being, that we ſeeke the fellowſhip 
                  and communion of Chriſts faithfull and obedient ſeruants, &amp;c. cleere vs of all ſchiſme and hereſie, ſo farre forth: ſo that if you would conuince vs of theſe crimes, it had been expedient you had firſt prooued your aſſemblies as they generally ſtand, by the euidence of Gods word, to be true churches
                  
                  of Chriſt, rightly entered and keeping couenant with the Lorde, continuing in the order and obedience of his word, &amp;c. and that we prepoſterouſly departed from yee, &amp; vncharitably haue forſaken your fellowſhip. But aſſoone as you ſhal ſhew vs ſuch a church amongſts you, by the grace of God we will ſhew, how free we are from ſchiſme. As likewiſe when ye ſhall lay open our error vnto vs, how farre we will be from hereſie. In the meane time we will not ceaſe to pray vnto God for ye, that he will not lay theſe ſinnes vnto your charge, which in your ignorant zeale you commit, but in mercie ſhew ye, the fearefull eſtate ye ſtand in, and giue ye a heart, vnfeinedly to repent, &amp; ſpeedely to turne vnto him.
               
               
                  C. G. Your owne bare words, whatſoeuer yée profeſſe by them, cannot be ſufficient to cléere yée from ſchiſme and hereſie. I haue ſhewed, that our Churches are from auncient diſcent within the couenant, and that by ſuch euidence of Gods word, as no heretike or ſchiſmatike ſhall be able to ouerthrowe. I haue alſo ſhewed, that the ſtableneſſe of Gods couenant with the Church, is founded vpon the frée promiſe of his mercie, which though we haue ſinned with our fathers, and doone wickedly, ſo that there hath béen great apoſtaſie in the Church, yet he remembreth his couenant towards vs. I haue alſo ſhewed how prepoſterouſly ye haue departed, arrogating that power to Iudge whole aſſemblies, which dooth belong to the Churches of Chriſt, and without any orderly procéeding, according to the rule of the Goſpell. And moreouer, that yee haue moſt vncharitably and falſely accuſed our Churches. We cannot ſhew ye a church, nor any one member of a church ſo perfect, but that there be many defects and faults. A true church being ſhewed among vs, though yee repent, yet can yee not be frée from ſchiſme, which is already committed. And touching your hereticall opinions, and groſſe errors, time will declare how well ye will performe this promiſe, not to become heretikes. I know I am in the right way, albeit I am ſo farre from running, that I doo ſcarſe créepe, I deſire the praiers of all the faithfull, that I may procéed in it. But the praier which you

promiſe to make for me, is much fitter for your ſelues.
            
            
               Article 4.
               
                  The Brow. 
                  We ſeeke to eſtabliſh and obey the ordinances and lawes 
                  of Chriſt, left by his laſt will and teſtament, to the gouerning of his Church, &amp;c.
               
               
                  G. G. The fourth article, ought all godly men to practiſe, ſo farre forth as the limits of their calling doo extend. But let it bee ſhewed, that euer priuate men did take vpon them to reforme when things were amiſſe in the Church, or that any of the Prophets did will them to take the matter in hand, or ſhewe your warrant that ye be not priuate men.
               
                  The Brow. 
                  This Article you firſt allowe, and after reſtraine it, to wee wot not what limits of calling. But if ye graunt it to be the dutie of euery true Chriſtian, to ſeeke to eſtabliſh and obey the ordinances and lawes of Chriſt, left in his Teſtament, to the gouerning of his Church, without any altering, &amp;c. It is as much as we indeauour or purpoſe. Otherwiſe we allow not that which the law of God condemneth, either intruſion without lawfull calling, either tranſgreſſion in calling, or preſumption aboue calling. Our purpoſe is not to meddle with the reformation of the ſtate, otherwiſe then by our praiers vnto God, and by refraining from all things that be contrary to Gods lawes, &amp;c.
               
               
                  G. G. You ſay that I firſt allowe this article, and then after reſtraine it to ye wot not what limits of calling. How is this true, when I make the reſtraint euen in the firſt ſentence? for I allowe it no further then the limites of euery mans calling doo extend. It is no maruaile that ye ſay, ye wot not to what limites of calling I reſtraine it. For if yée did regarde to kéepe within the bounds of calling, yée would not thruſt forward priuate men, to doo that which GOD hath not called them vnto. But yée plead for your ſelues, that ye do not indeuor or purpoſe any thing, beyond the limits of priuate calling.

Ye allow not, as ye ſay, that which the law of God condemneth, which ye expreſſe in theſe words: either intruſion without lawfull calling, either tranſgreſſion in calling, or preſumption aboue calling. If yée could ſée it, you doo héere, as it were, put the halter about your owne neckes, and about the necks of all Browniſts: for yee ſtande to this, that the lawe of God condemneth intruſion, without lawfull calling, and preſumption aboue calling, and I wiſhe no ſharper weapon to fight againſt ye withall. But you thinke ye are well enough yet for all this, for ye do not purpoſe to meddle with reformation of the ſtate, but by praier to God, and refraining from euery thing that is contrary to Gods law: And this is commaunded all men that will ſaue their ſoules: All are willed to come out of Babilon. Héere is a poore ſhift: haue yée no other way to plucke of the halter, which yee put about your owne necke then this? I graunt it is the dutie of all men, aſwell priuate as other, to obey Gods voice, which calleth them out of Babylon, and to ſeperate themſelues from falſe worſhip I adde further, that euen in the true Church, it is the dutie of euery priuate man, in all humble and peaceable manner, to kéepe himſelfe vnpolluted, from thoſe corruptions and abuſes that créep in. But doo you procéed no further then thus? Haue ye not profeſſed in the third article, that ye will procéed vnto a godly frée choiſe of Miniſters and other officers? Doo ye not in this profeſſe, that yée ſeeke to eſtabliſh the lawes of Chriſt, to the gouerning of his Church? Is this no more, but to obey the voice of God, calling vs out of Babylon? Ye go beyond the common ſaying, Giue ſome an inch, and they will take an ell. For God hath not called nor ſent yee to performe ſuch a worke. I haue before layd open your foule ſlaunders, wherewith yée accuſe vs, that our worſhip is idolatrous, and Antichriſtian. But admit the Church of England were Babilon, and the ſynagog of Antichriſt, and that yée haue but obeyed the voice of God, in ſeparating your ſelues, which is a worke of priuate men: Yet who hath giuen ye the power &amp; authoritie to chooſe and ordeine Miniſters, to ſet vp and eſtabliſh publike gouernment? I would know this of ye, whether it be a leſſe worke to

repaire a decayed place of a building, or to build the whole frame? whether it be leſſe to ſwéepe the houſe, or to ſet it vp? It is the leſſe to repaire, and the leſſe to ſwéepe, all men will graunt. Then I reaſon thus, priuate men haue not authoritie, nor ought not to take vpon them ſo much as to cleanſe Gods houſe from abuſes, or to repaire the ruynes thereof: how much leſſe ought they to take vpon them to ſet vp the whole frame? You meane not to medle with reformation of the ſtate, but ye will erect a ſtate and gouernment: for is not the power of the Church both publike and great? Ye will not daube the walles of Antichriſt, nor build Iericho: no in déede ye are ouerprowd to be dawbers or to repaire: ye will erect the Altar, and build the Temple in Ieruſalem, ſuch worthy men muſt haue a new building of their owne. Thus may all men ſée, that ye confeſſe, the lawe of God condemneth intruſion without lawfull calling, and preſumption aboue calling, and yet ye take vppon ye being priuate, and thruſt forward other priuate men vnto the chiefe publike worke vnder the heauens: but more of this in the next Article.
            
            
               Article 5.
               
                  The Brow. 
                  We purpoſe by the aſsiſtance of the holy Ghoſt, in this 
                  faith and order to leade our liues: and for this faith and order to leaue our liues, if ſuch be the good will of our heauenly Father, &amp;c.
               
               
                  G. G. If men haue the truth, it is good to ſtand vnto it to the death, rather then to deny it, as our Church in the ſame eſtate it is now in, yéelded many bleſſed conſtant Martyrs. But if a man haue not the truth, it is great obſtinacie to die for it, as ſundrie Anabaptiſts, and other Heretikes haue ſhewed by theyr dying. Euery true Chriſtian will rather die, then denie the diſcipline which Chriſt hath left: but you muſt ſhewe that God commaundeth priuate men to ſet it vp.
               
                  The Brow. 
                  The word of God and your owne mouth hauing approued 
                  our deſires in theſe Articles, we can not be moued with
                  
                  Satans old temptation, to doubt of the Lords vndoubted truth, or call his commaundements into queſtion, with if it be the truth, &amp;c. Neyther can we be remoued with that old Popiſh reaſon ye bring of certayne bleſſed Martyrs that dyed in this eſtate your Church is now in. This is not to approoue the ſtate of your Church by Chriſtes Teſtament: which vntil you do, though all the men in the world ſhould both dye in it and for it, yet could they not iuſtifie that God condemneth, &amp;c.
               
               
                  G. G. How the word of God and my mouth approoueth your moſt wicked intruſion without calling, let euery wiſe man iudge.
               Yee call it an old Popiſh reaſon that I bring of certayne bleſſed Martyrs which dyed in the ſtate our Church is nowe in. If you had no more frenſie in yée then my reaſon hath Poperie, it were much better for yée. Let vs ſée howe you or any Browniſt is able to anſwere it. That Churche which is of the Deuill, and hath not the truth, but is Antichriſtian, can not bring foorth and nouriſh vp children to God: But the Church of England in the eſtate it is now in, brought foorth and nouriſhed vp children to God, ſéeing it yéelded many bleſſed and conſtant Martyrs: Therefore the Church of England in the eſtate it is in, hath the truth, and is not a falſe and Antichriſtian Church. When you haue ſhewed that a falſe Church can bring foorth and nouriſh vp true children to God, yée may well ſaye that this is not to prooue our Church by Chriſtes Teſtament. If yee can not prooue that, ceaſſe to cauill. Yée denye them not to be bleſſed Martyrs, but yee ſay, that they dyed not in our Church, nor for our Church. Ye ſpeake confidentlie: but in the confirmation of your ſpéech, yée ſhewe your ſelues moſt fooliſhe. For yée ſay, they dyed not in our Church, béeing through Gods great mercie depriued and diſgraded by theyr enemies. All the Martyrs were depriued by theyr enemyes of theyr liues, they could not depriue them of theyr faith, nor of the

truth which they had learned before from the mouthes of Gods Miniſters in our Church. What were they all diſgraded of? doo yée take it they were all members of the Synagog of Antichriſt, or ſtoode for any dignities or priuiledges in that fellowſhip, vntyll theyr enemyes thruſt them foorth? Then yée ſay, they dyed not for it, but for the truth of Chriſt. How will you ſeparate things as contrarye, which doo ſtand well together? they dyed both for the truth of Chriſt, and for our Church: they conſtantly gaue teſtimonie to the truth, and were content to indure any torments to confyrme theyr Bréethren in the ſame, and therein may be ſayd to dye for the Church. I doo not meane that euery thing which they allowed, muſt néedes be good, for they had theyr errors and imperfections. Neyther doo I reaſon after this ſorte, as though the Martyrs ſhould dye for euery order and obſeruation of our Church, they dyed for the ſubſtance of that faith and woorſhip which our Church mayntayneth. And (as I ſayd before) you muſt prooue they were not begotten to God by our Church, or elſe confeſſe our Church to bée the Spouſe of Chriſt. Doubtleſſe, if our Church did not bring them foorth, and nurſſe them vp to God, they were deceyued, and departed out of the worlde ſuch babes, that they tooke a wrong woman for theyr Mother, for they tooke our Church to be theyr Mother. But you haue another Anſwere, and that is, that thoſe Martyrs neuer reſiſted the truth béeing ſhewed them, nor neuer yéelded vnto any yoake or corruption which God gaue them ſight of, contrarie to theyr conſciences, as yée ſay we doo in theſe dayes. Then the difference will fall out betwéene them and vs, that they offended of ignorance, and ſtoode vnder Antichriſtes yoake, yea, ſome of them muſt be Antichriſt himſelfe, in as much as they were Byſhops, and yet Gods true Church. For, yée ſay, they were faithfull in that little light, and wée offende of knowledge, and therefore can not be the true Church.
               Your confeſſing them faithful in that little light, &amp; ſo Gods

Church vnder the ſame gouernment we be, which ye tearme Antichriſts yoake, doth quite ouerthrowe all Browniſme, make what difference ye can betweene them and vs in truth, yet ſhall it appeare, that of neceſſitie graunt them to be the Church, ye muſt confeſſe ours. If ignorance excuſed them, ignorance ſhould excuſe many among vs, ſéeing there be multitudes in the land profeſſing the Goſpell that are perſwaded we haue the truth, and be in the right way both in doctrine and gouernment. And againe, ye are much deceiued, if ye ſuppoſe that euery Chriſtian man now hath ſo great vnderſtanding, as the chiefe of them had that ſuffered death in the dayes of Quéene Mary. Would ye haue men beléeue, that Browne himſelfe, and thoſe Browniſts, which take themſelues his equals, haue greater light then eyther Ridley, Cranmer, Howper, Bradford, Philpot, Taylor, and other had? when the learnedeſt in theſe dayes are not aſhamed of thoſe woorthie men, but acknowledge them as excellent Diuines? How abſurd a thing is it, that ignorant blinde Schiſmatikes, full of fantaſticall and hereticall opinions, ſhould boaſt of theyr great light in compariſon of theirs? Now we come to the laſt poynt of all, and one of the greateſt. I ſayd, ye muſt ſhewe that God commaundeth priuate men to ſet vp diſcipline. As it ſtandeth ye greatly vpon, ſo ye doo apply all your force héerevnto: and in verie déede looke to it, for if ye be weake in this, and can not ſhewe good warrant, all men will ſée that your preſump ion againſt the holie ordinance of God, is moſt vile and damnable: let vs ſée then how this queſtion will be concluded. Firſt, ye ſay, God in his lawe commaundeth euery one to ſéeke the place where he putteth his name. Chriſt in the Goſpell commaundeth to ſéeke the kingdome of God, and to take his yoake vppon them, &amp;c. I aunſwere, that if a man from theſe places ſhoulde conclude, therefore priuate men are commaunded to preach the word, and to adminiſter the Sacraments, it were ridiculous: and yet ye may, as well as to ſay, that therefore they are to reforme, to eſtabliſhe, or to ſet vp the diſcipline.

Your next reaſon is drawne from the nature of diſcipline, in that it is perpetuall. Indéed the ſubſtance, and eſſentiall forme of diſcipline are perpetuall: and there be circumſtances in it which are variable. And thus a man may reaſon: there is a diſcipline giuen by Chriſt, which is not variable: therefore the authoritie neglecting it dooth offend, and the Church hath wrong, where it is not eſtabliſhed: but to ſay, that therefore méere priuate men are to eſtabliſh it, is without anye good warrant. For when any thing is doone that ought not, or anye thing let paſſe, which ought to bee doone in the Church and common-wealth, and ſo a perpetuall commaundement of God broken: it is no warrant for priuate men to take the matter in hand, and to redreſſe. But you ſay, the Church cannot be gouerned by any other lawes or gouernement. I am of this minde, that there can be no viſible eſtabliſhed Churches, but where there are ſome rules of Chriſtes diſcipline obſerued. As if there be no Paſtors or Teachers, no flockes, no calling nor order for Preaching the word, and adminiſtring the Sacraments. But to ſay there is defect or want in ſome parts of diſcipline, or it is in ſome things corrupted, therefore it is no Church that is gouerned thereby, is very hereticall. Séeing the Goſpel preached, and imbraced with true and liuely faith, giueth the being to a church. Yea but true faith, ſaith the Browniſt, cannot be without obedience. I graunt it cannot be the Church of God, if it be wholy diſobedient, or in matters which concerne the grounds of faith and holy doctrine. I ſaye moreouer, that one part of this obedience is, that priuate men kéepe themſelues within the limits of their calling, and doe nothing but that which Gods worde dooth warrant them to deale in. Neither ought the Church to be without this diſcipline, ſaye you. I aſſent, that ſo farre as it is perpetuall, the Church cannot want any part, or haue it corrupted, but with iniurie and damage.
               But your meaning extendeth further, as appeareth by your words. For God (ſay you) holdeth them all in the ſtate of enimies, which haue not his ſonne to raigne ouer them▪ And your

marginall note is. If they haue not his Scepter of grace, they ſhall haue his Iron mace. Indéed, if a man could not haue Chriſt to raigne ouer him, nor be in the ſtate of grace, vnleſſe the diſcipline be erected, that he may be gouerned thereby, all priuate men ſhould be warranted by neceſſitie, to ſet it vp and to eſtabliſh it, if they could no where finde it already erected, where to ioyne themſelues: but haue yée not before againſt this hereſie confeſſed the truth in your reply vpon the firſt article, by affirming Chriſtes kingdome to extend vnto all ſuch as by true faith apprehend and confeſſe him, howſoeuer they be ſcattered, or whereſoeuer diſperſed, vpon the face of the earth? If yee had not confeſſed, yée muſt néedes be driuen thereto. For yée take it, that Browniſts are Gods Churche, And yet yée haue not eſtabliſhed the Diſcipline. If ye replye, that yée indeuour, and are letted by force, which dooth excuſe yée before God. I anſwer, that the fetters and chaines, can no faſter binde the handes and féete of Browniſts, then the handes of priuate men are bound with the bandes of conſcience, and the feare of God, from preſuming to take vpon them publike authoritie.
               And let vs ſée where that commaundement ye ſpeake of is giuen vnto priuate men, as namely, that they are willed to come together, with promiſe of direction and protection, and authority, not onely to eſtabliſh Chriſtes lawes and ordinances among them, but faithfully to gouerne his houſe: yée doo boldly and preſumptuouſly affirme, and can ſhew no one place of Scripture for it. Yée ſay, this aſſemblie, before they be planted and eſtabliſhed in this order, conſiſteth hetherto but of particular priuate perſons, none as yet being called to office or function? Who then hath called them together? Or being all priuate, dooth their comming together make them not to be priuate? or is not the action of many priuate men aſſembled, as priuate as of one ſeuerallye by himſelfe? Did the aſſembly of Corah &amp; his companions any thing helpe the matter? Yee will chooſe Paſtors and Elders? who ſhall ordeine them? Doo yee euer reade of anye ordeined, but by

Apoſtles, Prophets, Euangeliſts, Paſtors, Teachers, and Gouernours? Was not the power deriued at the firſt, from the extraordinarie Miniſters to the Ordinarie? If all the Browniſts in the land ſhould come together, and chooſe a Miniſter, and ordeine him, ſhould it make him anye more a Miniſter indéede before God, then if all the Apprentiſes in London taking vpon them to chooſe a Lorde Maior of the Citie, and to miniſter an othe vnto him ſhould make him a Lord Mayor? The Quéens Maieſtie hath granted no ſuch authority in the Common-wealth, to the Apprentiſes: no more hath the Lord God in the Church, vnto the Browniſts. And as it is in the higher matter, ſo is their wicked preſumption more deteſtable. But ye procéed and ſay: therefore we may well conclude, that God commaundeth his faithfull Seruants, being as yet priuate men, together to build his Church, &amp;c. Yée may euen as well conclude, as in the reſt of all your hereticall concluſions. Is it not wofull, that men ſhould be drawne into moſt damnable wayes, by ſuch blinde ſeducers, which bring not ſo much as a ſhew or colour of warrant out of Gods word, to ſet them a worke in that whereof they chéefely glorye, as namely that they will eſtabliſh Chriſtes lawes and ordinances, without altering, changing, &amp;c? But ye alledge the examples of the Primitiue Churches (for your patterns, and warrant) which ſued not to the Courtes and parlements, nor waited vpon Princes pleaſures, &amp;c. What can bee ſpoken more groſſely? The holy Apoſtles were ſent by our Sauiour into al the world, furniſhed with authoritie and commiſſion to ſet vp his kingdome. The Paſtors and Gouernours ordeined by them, receiue the power, not onely for themſelues, but alſo to conuey ouer vnto others, What maketh this for priuate men? Doubtleſſe ye haue no patterne in the Scriptures which you follow, but of Corah, Dathan, and Abyram with their company, who cried; Are not all the Lordes people holye: euen as you Browniſts, with the Anabaptiſts crye out: Are not all the Lordes people frée? Yee hane no commiſſion from GOD, it is the Deuill that hath thruſt yee forwarde,

and will yée in ſuch vile and wretched manner, pretend the examples of the Primitiue Churches? But your reaſon dependeth much vpon this, that the Primitiue Churches ſtayed not the pleaſures of Princes. If this were granted, that princes are not to be ſtayed for, yet dooth it not follow there vpon, that priuate men are to eſtabliſh Church gouernement: but there muſt bee ſome to doo it, which are called and furniſhed with authority from God.
               Yet the queſtion dooth remaine touching Princes, whether they be to be ſtayed for? Browne maketh many arguments to prooue, that they are not to be ſtayed for, nor yet haue to do by publike power to eſtabliſh religion? which opinion of his, is with ſuch abridging the ſacred power of Princes, and with ſuch horrible iniurie to the Church, contrarye to the manifeſt worde of God: that if there were nothing elſe, it is enough to make him an odious and deteſtable heretike, vntill he ſhew repentance. You follow him héere, and alledge ſome reaſons which are to be conſidered. But firſt the queſtion which is generall, muſt be reſtrained vnto the ſpeciall. We muſt diſtinguiſh: for there be Heathen and Idolatrous Kings, and there be Chriſtian Princes. Thoſe are againſt Chriſt, and theſe are for Chriſt.
               When the holye Apoſtles were ſent foorth to Preach the Goſpell in the whole world, the Kings were all Heathen, and bent their power againſt them. To what end ſhould they, hauing commiſſion from Chriſt, to eſtabliſh diſcipline, ſue vnto the Courts and Parliaments of ſuch Princes, or attend their pleaſure? The caſe is all one, where the kings profeſſe Chriſt in name, and be idolaters. As in France, the Miniſters whom God hath raiſed vp, and ſent to publiſh the Goſpell in former yeares, attended not the pleaſure of thoſe their idolatrous Kings, for the ſetting vp of diſcipline: for they might aſwell, at their inhibition, haue ceaſed from preaching. But where there is a Chriſtian Prince, the ſacred power of the ſword is with Chriſt and for his Church, and héere the caſe is cleane changed. For this Magiſtrate, King, or Quéene, ſitting vpon

the royall Throne, and holding the Scepter, is the chiefs and principall member of the Church. This Magiſtrate béeing Gods miniſter, and bearing the Sword to take vengeance vppon all euill dooers, Rom. 13. and to mayntayne peace with all godlineſſe and honeſtie, Timoth. 2. hath the charge and burthen not only to prouide for the bodyes of the Subiects, and theyr outward ciuill eſtate, but alſo by good ciuill Lawes, to procure the eſtabliſhing of Gods true Religion and worſhip among them, for the comfort of theyr Soules: for how ſhall he puniſh all euill, and mayntayne all Godlyneſſe by the Sword, but by eſtabliſhing Chriſtes holie Religion? Therefore this Magiſtrate is to aſſemble all the learned, the wiſe, the graue and experienced, that he may conueniently, and to haue it diſcuſſed by the Word of God, which is the true and pure Doctrine, and which be the rules and orders that Chriſt hath giuen for the gouernment &amp; preſeruation of his Church. Then are Lawes to bée made (for Kings can not rule but by Lawes) to deſtroy and aboliſh all falſe Religion, Superſtition, Idolatrie, and Hereſies; and to compell all ſtates and degrées of perſons within the Kingdome, to receyue the holie doctrine and rules of Chriſt, and to walke in the ſame. This dyd the Kings of Iuda, as the holie Scriptures doo playnely declare.
               Nowe if this Chriſtian Prince doo erre in ſome matters of Doctrine, or touching the rules of diſcipline, yet holding and mayntayning all the fundamentall poynts of the Chriſtian faith, ſo that there be abuſes and corruptions in the Churche, euerie priuate godlie man is to kéepe a good conſcience, not breaking the vnitie and peace of the faithfull, but not to take publike authoritie to reforme. Then yée demaund, If they ſhould tarrie Princes leyſures, where were the perſecution wee ſpeake of? Héere ye vtter a moſt beaſtlie ſpéeche. Saint Paule willeth to make earneſt prayers and ſupplications for Princes, that wee may liue in

peace with all godlineſſe, 1. Timoth. 2. Whereby it appeareth, that the defence of the Chriſtian Magiſtrate is a ſingular bleſſing vnto the Church. And you take it, the Croſſe of Chriſt is aboliſhed, vnleſſe the Magiſtrate be prouoked, and doo perſecute. The faithfull doo beare the Croſſe of reproches and afflictions vnder the moſt Godly Kings, who yet in dutie are vppon knowledge to redreſſe it. Do yée thincke the Godly did not beare the Croſſe vnder King Dauid, who was not frée himſelfe? Or would yée haue no peace by Chriſtian Kings? If your meaning be not ſuch, why doo yée vtter ſo wicked ſpéech?
               Then yée ſay, we make Chriſt attend vpon Princes.
               I anſwere, that Chriſt hath ordinarie Miniſters, if theſe be ſlacke, when he will haue hys woorke doone, he can and hath rayſed vp extraordinarie workemen. If his Kingdome lye waite, doth that warrant priuate men to ſteppe foorth, and to reforme or eſtabliſhe? Or ſhall Chriſt bée brought to ſtoupe vnto Princes, if euerie Schiſmatike intrude not himſelfe to runne when GOD hath not ſente him?
               There be certayne Anſwers which go vnder the name of Henry Barowe, where béeing demaunded whether the Quéene may make Lawes for the Church which are not contrarie to the Word of God? The Anſwere is this, I thincke no Prince, neyther the whole world, nor the Church it ſelfe, can make any Lawes for the Church, other then Chriſt hath left in his Word.
               This ſéemeth vnto ſimple men a verie ſound Anſwere, drawne from two firme principles, the one, that there is but one Law-giuer, which is God: the other, that he hath by Ieſus Chriſt giuen full and perfect Lawes for hys Church. The deceypt lyeth hid in this, that men doo not conſider there be generall lawes or rules giuen by Chriſt for matters of circumſtance, that bée indifferent and variable in the particulars, and ſo to be altered and aboliſhed, as

the peace and edification of the Churche ſhall requyre. And therefore, that Princes with the Church are to ordeine and to eſtabliſh ſuch orders by thoſe generall rules, as may afterward for iuſt cauſe be altered. Wherefore it is manifeſt, that the anſwer of Barow, dooth cut off a great part of the Diſcipline, and ſhorten the power of the Prince. And moreouer, it is not conſidered, that the Prince, being to puniſhe all euill by the doctrine of Sainte Paul, and to maintaine all godlineſſe, cannot doo it but by lawes, and ſo is to eſtabliſhe by lawes the whole Chriſtian religion.
               Where, vpon this Anabaptiſticall anſwere of Barow (I thinke it the dutie of euerye Chriſtian, and principally of the Prince, to enquire out, and to reuew the lawes of GOD, and ſtirre vppe all the Subiects, vnto more diligent and carefull kéeping of the ſame) goeth alſo verye currant among manye. Whereas indéede, it denieth a great parte of that power which GOD hath giuen to Princes.
               For ſhall not the Chriſtian Magiſtrate, driue the negligent to heare the worde Preached? ſhall hee not puniſh the wicked deſpiſers, blaſphemers, Heretikes, Schiſmatikes, Idolators, and ſuch like? And howe can this bee doone, but by lawes made and eſtabliſhed? Yet Browne the roote of this hereſie, who hath by his writings ſeduced the reſt, dooth make verye great ſhewe in this matter.
               
                  The kingdome of Chriſte is ſpirituall, and not ſet vp by the arme of fleſh and blood, but by the Holy-ghoſt. The Subiects of Chriſte come willinglye of theyr owne accorde, and not by compulſion. None of all the godlye Kinges, durſt compell any to the worſhip of God. And that all the Kings of Iuda, which did reforme religion, did it by a ſpirituall power, as being figures of Chriſt. Indéed the kingdome of God is ſpirituall: all the power of Kings in the

world, cannot conuert one ſoule vnto Chriſte: that is doone by the Holy-ghoſte, through the liuelye worde of faithe. Neuertheleſſe, the ciuill power is an outwarde meane to driue men to heare the Goſpell preached, and to obey the diſcipline. Chriſtes ſubiects are franke and willing, ſo farre as his holye ſpirite and word haue wrought, and haue power in them to ſubdue, and bring vnder euery high thing, which exalteth it ſelfe againſt God: but before men bee conuerted, compulſion, euen with penalties, is a meane to bring them to that, whereby this regeneration is wrought: &amp; after conuerſion to God, there remaineth ſtill a great lumpe of corruption, which is to be kept in and bridled with ſome force. I will make the matter cléere, by the chaſtiſment which the Scripture willeth Parents to vſe to their children. A father hath a ſonne which is diſſolute and proud, whom he cannot reclaime by anye inſtruction or exhortation. He correcteth him with ſtripes, and forceth him to heare the word of God diligentlye being preached. It pleaſeth God ſo to bleſſe this indeuour of the Father, that his Sonne is conuerted, and dooth become a right godlye man. Shall we ſaye he is none of Chriſtes ſubiects, becauſe at the firſt he came not willingly? The King is the Father of all his Subiects, and by fatherly correction laboureth to bring them to goodneſſe.
               And where Browne ſaith, that none of the Kings of Iuda, durſt compell their Subiects to the worſhip of God: it is moſt falſe. For beſide the puniſhment of death, mentioned in the dayes of Aſa. It is ſaid ſtatlye, that Ioſias compelled them to worſhip the Lorde God of their Fathers, 2. Chron. 34. The Hebrew worde is Iagnabed, which is, he bound them, or made them ſerue. And finallye, where Browne faith, the Kings of Iuda did reforme religion by a ſpirituall power, as figures of Chriſt, it is abſurd and falſe. Firſt ſéeing they did that which Chriſt himſelfe did not: for hee neuer reformed the ſtate of religion.
               Had they a ſpirituall power, to reforme and to eſtabliſh

religion, becauſe they were figures, and ſo did breake downe and roote out falſe worſhip: and Chriſt himſelfe, who then ſhould haue had all the power, did not meddle that way? Was not the high Préeſt as worthy to bee depoſed, as he whome Solomon did depoſe? Were there not horrible abuſes▪ among the Préeſtes, the Scribes and Phariſies, which hee did but Preach againſt? Againe, will Browne be ſo fooliſh as to imagine, that the kings of Iuda ſet bodily penalties by a ſpirituall power? It is as cléere as may bee, that they reformed by that ciuill Kinglye power, which God gaue them.
               
                  Cyrus the King of Perſia, who made the Decrée for the building of the Temple in Ieruſalem, Ezra. 1. was no figure of Chriſt.
               
                  Iehu King of Iſrael, who deſtroyed the Temple, the Idols, and the Prieſtes of Baal, 2. Kings. 10. was no figure of Chriſt. I conclude therefore, that the wickedneſſe of Browne, and of Browniſts, is great in thys poynt, when they in thys manner abridge the power of Princes, ſpoyle the Churche of her comfortable ayde and protection, and thruſt forward priuate men, to take vppon them that which God hath not called them vnto.
               And I doo intreate all Godly Chriſtians, and warne them in the name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that they looke to theſe holie rules of Gods Word. Firſt, with all humilitie, modeſtie, ſubiection, and lowlineſſe of mynde, to kéepe themſelues within the boundes and limits of theyr calling, ſtudying to be quiet, and to doo theyr owne buſineſſe, 1. Theſſ. 4. verſ. 11.
               
               Then, that they turne not the holie Religion of GOD, or the profeſſion thereof, into queſtions, bitter diſputations, wrath, contentions, and vayne-glorious boaſting: but that in practiſe they followe after Righteouſneſſe, Faith, Loue, and Peace, with thoſe that call vppon the Lord out of a pure heart, 2. Timoth. 2. verſ. 22. Finally, not in rigour and

preſumption to iudge, to condemne, and to treaddowne. But with mercie, with pittye, and compaſſion, to ſupporte the weake, Gal. 6. This is the plaine, ſtraight paued, and holye waye of GOD: and whoſoeuer maketh account of ſaluation, let them take héede they bee not drawne out of it into crooked by wayes, and into myrie flowes, by preſumptuous Heretikes, and Schiſmatikes.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            Faultes eſcaped.
            
               Page 18. line 16. for being a dead trée, reade bring a dead letter.
               
               Page 25. line 13. for Béez, reade Bréez.
               
               Page 72. line 35. for prebyterie, reade presbyterie.
               Page 75. line 5. for man, reade men.
               
               Page 86. line 11. for bend, reade bond.
               
            
         
         
            AT LONDON Printed by Iohn VVindet, for Toby Cooke, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Paules Churchyard, at the ſigne of the Tygers head. 1590.
            
            
            
         
      
   

