
   
      
         
            The Hollander A comedy written 1635. The author Henry Glapthorne. And now printed as it was then acted at the Cock-pit in Drury lane, by their Majesties Servants, with good allowance. And at the court before both their Majesties.
            Glapthorne, Henry.
         
         
            
               1640
            
         
         Approx. 154 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01773
            STC 11909
            ESTC S103204
            99838961
            99838961
            3354
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01773)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3354)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 925:19)
         
         
            
               
                  The Hollander A comedy written 1635. The author Henry Glapthorne. And now printed as it was then acted at the Cock-pit in Drury lane, by their Majesties Servants, with good allowance. And at the court before both their Majesties.
                  Glapthorne, Henry.
               
               [72] p.   
               
                  Printed by I. Okes, for A. Wilson, and are to be sold at her shop at Grayes-Inne Gate in Holborne,
                  London :
                  1640.
               
               
                  Partly in verse.
                  Signatures: A-I⁴.
                  The first leaf is blank.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2003-04
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-05
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-06
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2003-06
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-08
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE
HOLLANDER.
            A Comedy written 1635.
            The Author
HENRY GLAPTHORNE.
            And now Printed as it was then Acted
at the Cock-pit in Drury lane, by
their Majesties Servants,
with good allowance.
            And at the Court before both their
Majesties.
            
               LONDON:
Printed by I. Okes, for A. Wilson, and
are to be sold at her shop at Grayes-Inne
Gate in Holborne. 1640.
         
         
            
            The Persons in the Play.
            
               
                  Artlesse, a Doctor of Physicke.
               
                  Vrinal, his man.
               
                  Mixum, his Apothecary.
               
                  Freewit, a yong Gentleman, and a Sutor to
               the Lady Know-worth.
               
               Sir Martin Yellow, a jealous Knight.
               
                  Popingay, his Nephew.
               
                  Fortresse, a Knight of the Twibill.
               
                  Sconce, a Gallant nuturaliz'd Dutchman.
               Captayne Picke.
               Lady Yellow.
               
               Mistrisse Know-worth, her fister.
               Mistresse Mixum.
               
               
                  Dalinea, the Doctors daughter.
               
                  Lovering, a Chamber-maid disguised.
            
            The Scene London.
         
         
            
            To the great hope of growing
noblenesse, my Honourable
friend, Sir Thomas Fisher,
Knight, &amp;c.
            
               Sir,
            
            
               THe knowledge of your stil
increasing virtue has begot
in all men love, in me
admiration, and desires to
serve it: as cunning Painters
expresse more significant Art in
modell, then extended figures, I have
made election of this little of spring
of my braine, to show you the largest
skill of my many indearments to you;
and as an Ambassadour from the rest
of my faculties, to informe you how
much devotion the whole province

of my Soule payes to your worth and
goodnes. Had I bin endow'd with
such blessings, (noble young man) I
should have presented you a welmand
Hawke, or an excellent Cour
                     •
                  er, gifts
(because more agreeable to your Disposition)
more fit to have bin tendred
you: But I am confident you know
that a Booke (as it is my best inheritance)
is the most magnificent sacrifice
my zeale can offer: this Play
therefore accept, best Sir, from him
who is nothing more ambitious then
of the title of 
            
               your true servant and
honourer,
Hen. Glapthorne,
            
         
      
      
         
            
            The Hollander.
            
               Actus primus. Scena prima.
               Doctor and his Wife.
               
                  Doctor.
                  
                     HOw doe these new Guests like us?
               
               
                  Mrs.
                  Very well:
                  That fortnight they've beene here, I have observ'd
                  From them not the least relish of distaste;
                  The Lady and her sister are so good
                  Themselves, their innocence cannot mistrust
                  Ill in another, specially in us,
                  Who doe assume that formall gravity
                  Might dash prying eyes: But is the sister
                  Cur'd of her Ague perfectly?
               
               
                  Doct.
                  The Spring
                  Does not produce an Ague but for Physicke,
                  
                     
She's cur'd, and onely does expect her sister,
                  The Lady Yellow, otherwise I feare
                  We should not have her company.
               
               
                  Mris.
                  Green-Sicknesse take her,
                  I thought it had beene that, and then my Art
                  Would have beene requisite. I should have found
                  Some lusty youth that would have given her physicke,
                  More powerfull to expell that lasie humour
                  Than all your Cordialls: Heaven, I can but thinke
                  How in this seven yeares, since we came to towne,
                  The Tide is turnd with us: when thou wert an Inne-
                  Keeping Apothecary in the Country,
                  The furniture of our shop was Gally-pots,
                  Fild with Conserve of Roses, empty Boxes,
                  And Aqua vitae glasses: and now thou art
                  My most admir'd Doctor, walk'st in Sattin,
                  And in plush, my heart.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Applaud my wit that has effected it.
               
               
                  Mris.
                  You will grant I hope
                  An equall share to me? Was it not I
                  That first advis'd you to set up a Schoole
                  For Female vaulters, and within pretence
                  Of giving Physicke, give them an over-plus
                  To their disease. How much this has conduc'd
                  To our advancement, forgetfulnesse it selfe
                  Cannot deny.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Nor will I, my deare associate, I have now
                  Atchiev'd a wealth sufficient to procure
                  My selfe a license, though the murmuring Doctors
                  That doe not bite-backe it, though they watch
                  All opportunities that may undoe
                  My estimation: we must therefore arme
                  Our selves with circumspective care: be sure
                  Those vertuous gentle women, who are now
                  Domesticke guests, have no cause to suspect
                  A misdemeanour here, nor that, our daughter,
                  
                     
A virgine could as morning ayre or Ice.
                  So timerous of society, that shee seemes
                  Neglectfull of mankind, be expos'd to every common eye,
                  Frequents our house, we must be politicke, wise, or our state,
                  Will soone embrace a ruine.
               
               Enter Vrinall.
               
                  Vrin.
                  Are you the Doctor Artlesse pray sir?
               
               
                  Doct.
                  My name is Artlesse
                  
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Sir, I am sent from Mr. Mixum, your Apothecary, to
give attendance on you.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Your name is Vrinall, I take it?
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  you take my name by the right end sir, my father was a
brother of master Mixum's function: marry my mother told me
a Doctor got me, for professions sake I hope you'l use me kindly.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Doubt not good Vrinall, if thou beest not crack'd canst
thou hold water.
               
               
                  Mist.
                  Well, that is, bee secret, insooth husband, the young
man will be very good at a dead lift, to serve our patients turnes,
he has a promising countenance.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  A good subsidy face mistris, but master Mixum has certified
me, that hither come Ladies and gentlewomen, City
wives and country wives, and the better sort of saylors wives:
Nay wives of all sorts, but Oyster wives, some to have the falling
sicknesse cur'd, others the inflammation of the blood, the
Consumption of the body and lungs; if I doe not to any man or
woman administer a glister, vomit, potion, Iulip, Cordiall, or
what physicke your worship shall thinke fit, with dexterity, say
I am no sound Vrinall, and beat me to pieces.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  I believe thee, but did Tom Mixum give you nought in
charge to say to me?
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  O yes sir, hee had mee tell you hee had a fat Goose in the
pens, only for your pulling: a yunker of a thousand pound per
annum.
                  
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Sayst so, what is he; knowest thou?
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  I saw him sir, he was a propenman: but I thinke has
not much more wit then my selfe, he seemes of a good 
                        •
                     ane disposition,
and may I believe, be led by the nose as quietly as the
tamest Beare in the garden: he has not wit enough to be a knave,

nor manhood enough to be an honest man: this is my 
                        〈◊〉
                     
of him sir, when you see him you'l understand him better.
               
               Enter 
                     〈◊〉
                  , Sir Martine Yellow 
                     〈◊〉
                   his 
                     〈◊〉
                  
               
               
                  Pop.
                  With licences, is not this 
                        〈◊〉
                      a receiptacle
                  For sinners?
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Now you are in't perhaps it is, what meane you?
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Pish, seeme not to obscure, is it not in plaine termes, a
house of ease.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  There is one in the garden sir.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Where one may do his businesse with 
                        〈◊〉
                      fear of Marshall,
                  Constable, or any one of that most awfull tribe.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Surely this gentleman comes to take a purge, hee talkes
so eleanely.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Shall I have answer sir? I come as hot from sea, as a
                  Hollander from herring fishing, I have an appetite,
                  The most insatiate citizen who frequents
                  Your mansion cannot tame; had she beene fed
                  With amber possets, eaten sparrowes egges, or her accustom'd
                  Bevendy, been the juice of Clare or Sparagus.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  What abuse may this be?
                  Perhaps your most officious pander 
                        〈◊〉
                     
                  
                  That for a shilling will betray his sister
                  to prostitution; did mistake, be gone, or I shall
                  Fetch a gentleman will whip your hot blood out of you.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Shall I 
                        •
                     unne for the Bead les mistris?
               
               
                  Mist.
                  No goe to the next Justice for a warrant, and make haste,
be sure Ile have the knave smoak'd for abusing my house.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  This must not fright me, doe you not keepe a pimping
                  Roaring varle
                        •
                      noted as much as pig, have you not constant
                  She 
                        ••
                     uldiers in your citadell, none such,
                  Had Hollands Leager, Lambeth Marsh is held
                  A Nunry to your Colledge.
               
               
                  Virn.
                  And the three Scuirrels in the towne; I warrant a very
                  Sanctuary to it.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Come here's gold, be not so bashful, Mistris pray receive it,
                  I know you are open handed.
               
               
                  
                  Mist. Art.
                  Now I desie thee for a Rascall
                        •
                      
                     Vrinall why run you
not to the Justice, his man would have taken your money ere
this time.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Yet least I should mistake you, though I am by all
                  Truth confident this is the house: pray resolve me;
                  Has the Lady Yellow a chamber here?
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Yes sir, she lies in the yellow chamber, and has done this
two months.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  I did believe it.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Nay you may believe mee if you will: I know neither
Lady Yellow, nor yellow chamber, I have not beene here above
halfe an houre.
               
               
                  Doct. Tom Mixum,
                  Sure sent this fellow hither, he's so unmannerly,
silence Vrinall, what if that Lady have a chamber here sir?
               
               
                  Sir Mart.
                  Now he comes to the purpose.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Nay speake directly suppositions: include a doubtfull
sence, if she have not, I shall repent the error of my language
and crave your mercy.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Impudence I thinke, beyond my own rests in this youth,
                  I must finde out his meaning; tis perchance some one
                  Sent from her jealous husband, whom she told me,
                  In discontent was travel'd prithee wife goe in, and tell the
                  Lady Yellow, here is one wishes the knowledge of her.
               
               
                  Mrs. Art.
                  Hang him young whisling, he know a Lady, pity of
his life first.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Doe as I bid you: Vrinall attend your mistris in.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Yes, I will attend her in and in too, to do her any service.
               
               Exeunt Vrinall, and Mistris.
               
                  Doct.
                  Sir, the uneivill language you have given me,
                  Might justly stirre a passionate man to rage;
                  But it no morestirs me then the light wind,
                  If you've relation to the Lady Yellow:
                  
                  She's one who
                        •
                     e vertues merit that respect,
                  Twould be a staine to manners not to use the meanest of her
                  Friends with due regard: pray sir what is she to you?
               
               
                  Pop.
                  As any woman else is for my money, onely I must confesse,
I have an itch, a tickling thought to her before the rest of
common prostitutes: I know she'l lodge in none but vitious

houses, which inforces me thinke yours is so.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Tis a misconceit, I me sorry for her sake (whom I esteem
                  So chast, the pure untainted Doves may envy
                  Her unstain'd whitenesse) should be cast upon
                  My innocent house, expect Ile send her to you, shee'l shape you 
                        •
                     
                  
                  Just answer, would she were as they suspect her.
                  Ex. Doct.
               
               
                  Sir Mar.
                  This Doctor is dishonest, speakes untruth,
                  My jealousie is just, that any man
                  Should so undoe his reason; in beliefe
                  Of womens goodnesse, as on their loose soules,
                  To venture his creation; nay transforme
                  His essence by them: for a cuckold is
                  Na
                        •
                     ures huge prodigy, the very abstract
                  Of all, that is wonderfull: contempt and shame, are accidents as
                  Proper to his brow, as baire and whitenesse.
               
               Enter Lady Yellow.
               
                  Pop.
                  Is this she sir?
               
               
                  Sir Mar.
                  I nephew that's the monster.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  If Africke did produce no other monsters, there would
                  Be more cuckold in it then Lyons, but to my businesse,
                  Madam the old tradition of this house invites your
                  Knowl
                        •
                     dge to conceive for what I sent to speake with you.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  As yet indeed it does not.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Truely it does, I hope I shall obtaine
                  The virgine glories of this daies encounter,
                  Come shalls kisse, and then retire into your chamber.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  My chamber, sure your manners lies in your berd, what
doe you take me for?
               
               
                  Pop.
                  An excellent creature▪ one whose meanest smile
                  Would tempt a votary earnest at his prayers,
                  Before the image of his tutelar Saint; to vary his
                  Fix'd brow: yet I must tell you, you are a factress
                        •
                      of the
                  Divells, one who fell damnation pleasingly as Asps
                  Infuse their itching venum: a standing poole,
                  On whose salt wombe the too lascivious sun
                  Begets of Frogs and Toads a numerous off-spring.
                  Compar'd with you is empty of corruption.
               
               
                  
                  Lady.
                  
                     
                        ••
                     so have at him, a strange complement to win a Lady,
                  Sir by your first discou
                        ••
                     e I had imagin'd
                  You came to spend part of this cheerefull morne
                  In amorous dalliance with me, I am apt
                  For entertainement of it, as a bride
                  Long time contracted to some exquisite man
                  
                     Is on her wedding night, but your quicke change,
                  (Did not my glasse assure me) no great blemish
                  Dwels in my cheekes, would urge me to mistrust
                  An imperfection in them: they are my owne sir,
                  I doe not weare (though its common among Ladies)
                  My face ith day-time only, and at night
                  Put off the painted visor, this haire believe it,
                  Was never shop-ware, you may venture on me, let but your
                  Creature keepe the doore, my chamber is empty for you.
               
               
                  Sir. Mar.
                  Impudent strumper.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Ga
                        •
                      y
                        •
                     u be a woman, &amp; utter this, the hot desire of quailes,
                  To yours is modest appetite, you carry
                  A stone about you, not to warme your blood
                  Oppress'd with chilly cold, but to enflame it
                  Beyond all sensuall heat, which you would extinguish,
                  (Had you a soule about you) with your teares,
                  Or weepe with the continuance that tall Pines
                  Diffuse their gummy drops in summer, and
                  Faster then trembling Isicles, or snow, at their own dissolution.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  This is stranger yet sir, I see you come to convert mee
                  Prompted with a zeale would choake ten precisians earnest in
                  Their hot house of convention, alasse poore youth thy want
                  Of practice in the sweet delights of love,
                  Undoes thy judgement, can there be a joy
                  Equall to this to have a sprightfull Lady,
                  Whose every lineament speakes captivity
                  To the beholder, claspe with the same strictnesse
                  That curling billows doe embrace a wracke,
                  Her lovers necke, kisse close, and soft, as mosse
                  Does some oregrowne Oake; but I see tis vaine,
                  To prate to thee whose ignorance may plead
                  Excuse for thy fond here
                        •
                     ie; goe depart,
                  
                     
Turne Eunuch and reserve thy voyee, perhaps 
                        •
                      will purchase thee
                  A petty Cannons place in some blinde chantry.
               
               Enter Doctor and Dalince.
               
                  Doct.
                  Ile cut off their discourse, if 
                        〈◊〉
                      be right ile have my
benefit out of her: Dalinea attend her Ladyship, Madam I feare
you take cold here, your Sister, Mistris Know
                           •
                         worth expects you
too within; Gentlewoman you cannot complaine you have been
us'd uncivilly; pray now depart, tis time.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  They may returne to the wise man my husband, from
whom I'm sure they come, and tell him my disposition, ha, ha, ha.
               
               Exeunt Lady, and Dalin
                     •
                  a.
               
                  Sir Mart.
                  Flames rise on flames successively, the spheare
                  Has no such fire as I doe 
                        •
                     arbour here.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  What divine creature should the other be, well master
                  Doctor, we shall be even with you.
                  Exe. Sir Mart. Pop.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  
                     I, doe your pleasure sir, the small Riveret
                  Does in its cold waves, seeme to drench the sun
                  (When liks a riotous drunkard) his hot rayes
                  Suckes up the pea
                        •
                     ly waters, if this Lady
                  We are in her brest, the burning spots of lust,
                  They shall encrease, and like the Starres, light her soule
                  To th' firmament of pleasure. The businesse sirrha?
               
               Enter Vrinall and Sconce.
               
                  Vrin.
                  The businesse sirha, he's gotten into th' Lordly phrase
                  Already, Sir the gentleman I speake off?
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Is this he? would you have ought with me sir?
               
               
                  Scon.
                  
                     Amon Deui, this is the Doctor: Foutra I would faine
speake to him, Sir I should bee happy to initiate my knowledge
in your acquaintance Master Mixum an Apothecary, at whose
shop I use to eate Eringo Roots, did recommend me to you.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Honest Tom Mixum, you are welcome; what's your designe
with me?
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Fame does divulge you to be a man experienc'd in the
Arts.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Of cousenage and lying excellently.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Which does concerne our bodily health.
               
               
                  
                  Doct.
                  And you perhaps Iabor of some disease,
                  And come to seeke for remedy, I can
                  As Gallen or Hipocrates, read a lecture,
                  On maladies, their causes and effects,
                  Tell by the countenance of a man, the ill oppresses him,
                  You by that 
                        
                           〈…〉
                        
                      altitude of your horoscope,
                  Should be subject to Calentures.
                  
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Neen up mine 
                        •
                     eale min here: ick neet, infection vanish
I never was subject to disease, but the gentile itch which I obtaind
in the Low Countries.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  I was in hot service certainely.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  With licence sir, let me desire your character, I long to
know you, Symptomes of worth declare you in my opinion
noble.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  
                     I shall explaine my selfe by land shape a far off, my father
was a Dutch man.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Which makes him looke so like a smoak'd westphalia
ham, or dry Dutch pudding.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  And one in the conspiracy with Barnevet, at whose
hanging he fled ore hither.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  And the gentle noose had knit up him, and a hundred of
his country men, 
                        •
                     our land would not be pestred so with butterboxes.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Thinking to have purchas'd a monopoly for Tobacco:
but that the Vintners tooke in snuffe, and inform'd the gallants,
who had like to smoak'd him for't.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  An admirable project.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Afterwards he undertooke to have drayn'd the Fens, and
there was drown'd, and at the ducking time at Crowland
drawne up in a net for a widgin.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Pray sir what tribe was he of?
               
               
                  Scon.
                  He was no Jew Sir, yet he would take pawnes, and their
forfeits too, and has left me such as you see, I am a proper man: a
trifling patrimony, a thousand pounds perannum.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  I admire no man begs him for a foole, and gets it from
him.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  May I request your name?
               
               
                  Sco.
                  My name is Sconce sir, Master Ier
                           •
                        my Sconce, I am a gentleman
of a good family, and can derive my pedigree from

                     Duke Alvas time, my ancestors kept the inquisition out of Amsterdam.
                  
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  And brought all Sects in thither.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  And tooke their surname from Kickin pot, the strongest
Sconce in the Netherlands.
                  
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  An excellent derivation for a Dutch-man, Kickin-pot.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  I had a good strong cosen taken in by th' enemy, last
summer, Skinks Sconce Mr. Doctor, my cozen german once remov'd
by a stratagem of hay boats a fire on them.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  That should have beene before they came there Master
Sconce.
                  
               
               
                  Scon.
                  But tis thought our nation had recover'd it ere this,
but that the villanous Dunkerkers at sea met with the Herrinbusses
and made stocke-fish of them.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  They beat them soundly then it seemes.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Have you no brothers Mr. Sconce?
                  
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Not any that I know of, as I am gentleman, nor was there
any of my name till of late, that gallants have begot me namesakes
in every Taverne.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  But the businesse you have with me is unrelated yet, and
I have haste, pray what may it concerne?
               
               
                  Scon.
                  A household matter Mr. Doctor; I would be loath to be
accounted troublesome, I should be none of your vulgar guests
though: Mixum has inform'd me you have faire lodgings in your
house, convenient for ease and pleasure, might I be so much engag'd
to your goodnesse, as to affoord me a hansome one for my
mony, it should be an end earement conspicuously trenching upon
my gratitude, and render me your oblig'd servant ever lastingly.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  As long as his money lasts, that is
               
               
                  Doct.
                  If that be all, for Tom Mixums sake, were chambers
scar
                        ••
                     r, you should not be denyed. Vrinall bring the gentleman
into the dining roome, Ile goe acquaint my wife with it.
               
               
                  Scon,
                  
                     Vrinall, art thou stil'd Vrinall?
                  
               
               Exit Doct.
               
                  Vrin.
                  It is my right and title to be term'd so.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Come hither my sweet Rascall, canst keepe councell,
there's gold for thee, thou shalt have a new case sirrha, wilt thou
be true to me?
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  I will steale nothing from you Mr. Sconce.
                  
               
               
                  
                  Scon.
                  Thou lookst not like a man of theft, I mean in a designe.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Tis not to convey gold over, in hollow anchors, to pay
your Countrimen souldiers; if it be, Ile heare no more of it.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Pish, not that neither. Mixum thou knowst him, dost
not?
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Twas he preferd me hither.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  I did imagin't; my fine Vrinall reports thy Mr. to have
the rarest salve.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  The weapon salve I warrant.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Which would, if I were desperately hurt, cure mee
without a Surgeons helpe.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  So I have heard indeed.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Now Vrinall, it is our Countrie Custome onely to Stick
or Snee. But couldst thou but procure this pretious salve, I
would confront the glistering steele, out-face the sharpest
weapon.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  My Master is very cautious in parting with it.
               
               Enter Freewit.
               
                  Free.
                  Save you gentlemen, belong you to this house?
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  No sir, this house belongs to us.
               
               
                  Free.
                  Mistris Know-worth, the Lady Yellowes sister, she is not
stirring?
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Tis a lye sir, she is.
               
               
                  Free.
                  Your wit is very scurvy Sir: if you serve a Creature here
to carry messages; pray deliver one to her.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  I may chuse whether I will or no though.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Nay, and he shall chuse sir.
               
               
                  Free.
                  Prethee good friend let him; ile doe't my selfe.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Nay, that you shall not neither: what stand I here for?
But sir, 'tis not the fashion of this liberall age, to imploy a man
of merit in a message without consideration: your Lawyers Clark
will not acquaint his Master with a Clyents cause, untill his fist
be soundly greas'd: Why may not I then use the priviledge of
my office? Sir, wee Doctors men take aurum palpabile for Restorative:
you are not unfurnished sir.
               
               
                  Free.
                  O thou wouldst have money; there's for thee, prethee
Intreat her presence.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Instantly, instantly, noble sir, Mr. Sconce pray bear this

worthy gentleman company.
                  Exit Vri
                        •
                     all.
               
               
                  Free.
                  Why should she lodge here? all similitude
                  Explaines this house for vicious, and this Doctor
                  For an impostor: Though she have 
                        •
                     bin sicke,
                  She might have found to remedy her disease,
                  Another, and more fam'd Physician
                  Than this: She stayes perhaps to beare
                  Her sister company. Whatsoere's the cause,
                  Who dare deprave her innocence, or cast
                  A thought of blemish on her vertues? Light
                  Diffus'd through aire (although some thicke-brow'd fogge,
                  Or sickly vapour doe invade ayres sweetnesse)
                  Suffers no loath'd corruption. Thomes may gore
                  With envious pricking, the discoloured leaves
                  Of the chaste wood-binde, but can never blast
                  Their unstain'd freshnesse.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Now in the name of madnesse what 
                        〈◊〉
                      this man? Sir
are you jealous of your wife before you have her?
               
               
                  Free.
                  What if I be sir.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  She may chance Cuckold you after you have her for it.
               
               
                  Free.
                  Good Go
                        ••
                     combe hold thy pratling.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Coxcombe? how Coxcombe to a naturallis'd Dutchman?
Death sir, shall I blow you downe with my Can; or
shew you Twibill.
               
               
                  Free.
                  How Sir?
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Nay, bee not angry man, I meant no harme, tis but a
complement all salutation, I purchas'd of the Mr. of the Order
oth' valiant Knights of the Twibill.
               
               
                  Free.
                  A new Order of Knight-hood, that may I know the institution.
               
               Enter Mistris Know-worth, Martha, as Mr. Lovering leads her.
               
                  Know.
                  Servant welcome: Lovering intreat
                  That gentleman to withdraw with Mr. Doctors man.
               
               
                  Love.
                  Sir, my Mistris begs your absence.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Beggars are no chusers my friend: she shall
                  Undergoe no contradiction: but Madam, tis the fashion
                  Vrin.
                  
                     
As I tak't, to salute at meeting, and kisse at parting.
                  Kisses her.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  You had best kisse her double Mr. Sconce.
                  
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Lady, serviture vostre &amp; a vous assi Monsieur tresnoble.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  He lookes like a squirrill indeed: this way sir.
               
               Exeunt Lovring, Sconce, Vrinall.
               
                  Free.
                  I hope you grow to perfect health,
                  The Native beauty that once sild your cheeks,
                  Like to the budding Rose puts forth agen,
                  After cold winters violence: and your lips
                  On whose soft touch, had it bin possible,
                  Death would have dy'd himselfe, begin to shew
                  Like untouch'd Cherries, pale with Morning dew,
                  Which once shak't off, the purple fruit aspires
                  With amorous blushes to intice the small
                  Linnet and wanton Sparrow from their Layes,
                  To doate on its pure tincture, till they eate
                  What they admir'd.
               
               
                  Know.
                  —O you are pleasant servant; did you know
                  How neare I am to death, and for your sake,
                  Your humour soone would alter.
               
               
                  Free.
                  Truely, faire one,
                  It is a sweetnesse in you, I could wish
                  Were temper'd with lesse passion: (Your much care
                  Of my unworthy selfe;) tis but a fortnight,
                  Since last my eyes enricht their needy sight,
                  By the reflection of these starres, and had
                  The least ill seas'd me, you had bin the first
                  Whose eares would have receiv'd it; harmes are aptest
                  To be reported where they are least welcome.
               
               
                  Know.
                  They are indeed, and one of yours is come
                  To kill my knowledge; such a one, as had
                  You worne a common heart, no strong disease
                  Could have dispatched sooner.
               
               
                  Free.
                  —I feele
                  No inclination in my faculties
                  Tending to sicknesse: I have never yet
                  By nightly sursets forc'd my youthfull blood
                        •
                     
                  
                  To a distemper.
               
               
                  
                  Know.
                  Would your youthfull blood
                  Has ne're forc'd you one. Perfidious man,
                  Had I atchiev'd the patience of a Saint
                  (Seclude my love to thee) I should in rage
                  Title thee worthlesse: nay, a name above
                  That hatefull appellation: did you never
                  Injure a Creature of your mothers one Martha?
                  
               
               
                  Free.
                  Ha: how meane you Lady?
               
               
                  Know.
                  In the blacke act of Sinne, when you design'd
                  Her honour, as a carcasse to the Grave,
                  Whereever since your deed of ill was acted,
                  'T has slept lost and forgotten.
               
               
                  Free.
                  By just truth.
               
               
                  Know.
                  Invoke your falsehood, if you dare etect
                  On the blacke number of your heed lesse oathes
                  A monument to perjury. White truth,
                  Flies from the ranckorous poyson of your breath,
                  As from a stifling dampe. Can you deny
                  Without a blush what I have urg'd?
               
               
                  Free.
                  My resolution staggers a tall Oake,
                  Whose weighty top has discompos'd his roots)
                  When whirlewinds doe assault it, fits unmov'd,
                  Ballanc'd with me, to recollect the strength
                  Of impudence, and deeply contradict
                  Her mightiest affirmation, were to wage
                  A feeble warre with truth. Say I did Mistris;
                  Twas ere a thought reciprocall enjoynd me
                  A serious duty to you and your mercy,
                  In which you doe approach as neare heavens goodnesse,
                  As heaven does blest eternity, wil pardon that wit lesse error in me.
               
               
                  Know.
                  Truth I shall n
                        •
                     t: the harmlesse Mirtle first shall live in frosts,
                  And the pale Couslips flourish, ere warme showres
                  With quickning moysture raises them to tell
                  The e
                        •
                     rly Violets they are not alone
                  The Springs prime Virgins: my peculiar wrong
                  I freely pardon: but if you respect
                  Your conscience, seeke that injur'd woman, and
                  Restore by sacred marriage the sad losse
                  
                     
Of her deprived fame. Doe it Free-wit, heaven
                  Will smile at thy integrity; my teares
                  Shall strive to wash your crime away.
                  Ex. Mrs. Know.
               
               
                  Free.
                  She weeps: so choice flowers, when extracting fire,
                  Inforces their lost leaves to a mild warmnesse,
                  Doe through the Lymbecke temperately distill
                  Their odoriferous teares. But tis most just
                  To lose a chaste love, when distain'd with lust.
                  Exit.
               
               Explicit Actus primus.
            
            
               Actus secundus. Scena prima.
               Sconce, Vrinall; with a boxe of weapon salve.
               
                  Scon.
                  BUt are you certaine Vrinall this oyntment is Orthodoxall;
may I without errour in my faith believe this
same the weapon salve Authenticall?
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Yes, and infallibly the creame of weapon salves, the
simples which doe concurre to th' composition of it, speake it
most sublime stuffe; tis the rich Antido
                        •
                     e that scorns the steele,
and bids the Iron be in peace with men, or rust: Aurelius Bombastus,
Paracelsus, was the first inventer of this admirable Unguent.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  He was my Countryman, and held an Errant Conjurer.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  The Devill he was as soone: an excellent Naturallist, &amp;
that was all upon my knowledge, Mr. Sconce; and tis thought
my Mr. comes very neare him in the secrets concerning bodies
Physicall, as Herbes, Roots, Plants vegetable and radicall, out
of whose quintessence, mixt with some hidden causes, he does extract
this famous weapon salve, of which you now are Mr.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  There's a Welch Doctor ith' City reported skilfull in
compounding it.
               
               
                  
                  Vrin.
                  He? a meere Digon a whee▪ his salve, why it is Casebaby
to my Masters: I dare be sworne tis nothing but Methegling
boyld to jelly, the blades of Leeks, mixt with a Welch
Goats blood; then stampt, and straind through a peece of British
Freese, or one of the old laps of Merlins Jerkin.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Probable Vrinall. That Welch Doctor I doe not like: I
did attempt him for the weapon salve, and like a Turke hee answer'd
me, that Hollanders were Iewes.
                  
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  They are a rebellious nation that's certaine.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  And that the salve was onely made for Christians; there
is a City Captaine too; I know not how you stile him.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Not Iohn a Stiles, the Knight of the post is it?
               
               
                  Scon.
                  No, no, a very honest gentleman; but he's
                        •
                     , reported to
have atchiev'd the salve in Lapland among the witches, and to
be very liberall in imparting it to his friends, an Aldermans
daughter Vrinall may, and they say a witty gentlewoman.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Is't possible Mr. Sconce? they have few sonnes of that
condition.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Had a desperate hole made in her by a gentleman,
with his But-shaft, as in her Country garden he was shooting at
Penny pricke; was, when none else could doe it, eur'd by this
Captaine.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  By this light a trifle, a meere trifle, the very scraping of
our Galley-pots performes more monstrous wonders: there
was a Puritane Mr. Sconce, who, cause he saw a Surplisse in the
Church, would needs hang himselfe in the Bell-ropes.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Why did not the Sexton ring him by the eares for it?
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Him my Mr. seeing, did for experience sake anoynt the
noose wherein his necke had bin, and it recovered him.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Is't possible he should so easily escape a hanging! but
on good Vrinall.
                  
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Nay sir Ile tell you a greater miracle: You heard of the
great training last Summer master Sconce?
                  
               
               
                  Scon.
                  O when the whol: City went in Armes to take in Islington;
marry I heard the Ale-wives curse the report of their
Muskets, it made their Pies and Custards quake ith'Oven, and
so come out dow-back't, whìch almost broke the poore Harlots.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  I then Mr. Sconce there was at least three-score blown

up with a basket of powder, thirty of their lives my Master
sav'd.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Rarer, and rarer yet: But how good Vrinall?
                  
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  He dress'd the smoake of the powder as it flew up Sir,
and it heald them perfectly.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  O that any body would blow me up, to see how I
could eure my selfe. Still on good Vrinall.
                  
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Nay theré, are thousands of this kinde: but now I
thinke on it since, it did commit a villanous mischiefe.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Could it ever doe a mischiefe Vrinall?
                  
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Yes, yes, it has done a most notorious one, sufficient to
exauctorate its power, and almost annihilate the vertu of it.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  What was't good Vrinall?
                  
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  I could e'ne weepe to tell yousir: tis suppos'd twill never
recover the favour of gentlemen and City wits, they are
quite out of conoeite with it.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  But why should they be so Vrinall?
                  
               
               
                  Vrin,
                  I scaree dare answer Sir, for feare you hate it likewise,
                  Twas such another mischiefe.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Prethee what? nay on my gentility Vrinall.
                  
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Why sir, it cur'd two Serjeants, and their yeomen.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  How? two Serjeants.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Who otherwise had drunke Mace-Ale with the Devill.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  A Capitall crime that same, to cure two Serjeants.
               
               Enter Doctor, his wife: Mixum, his wife.
               
                  Doct.
                  
                     Tom Mixum I thanke thee for the man
                  Thou setst me; tis a most serviceable knave;
                  
                     I've set him to pull you bird of Paradice, you parcell Dutch:
thou sentst him hither too.
               
               
                  Mix.
                  I knew he was for your purpose, Mr. Doctor: this is
the gentleman I told you had one thousand pound per annum, and
would be a match for Mr. Doctors daughter.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  There was a touch for him indeed Vrinall.
                  
               
               
                  Doct.
                  It will, indeed, now I consider on't, I had rather shee
should marry a wealthy gull, than a witty Beggar: Wife and
Mr. Mixum, will you discourse a little with the gentleman,

sound his intent and pronenesse to a match, and as you finde him
use him; Mr. Sconce I should be glad to wait on you, did not urgent
affaires withdraw me.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Mr. Doctor I saw you not before: I am sorry sir, you
will be gone so soone, I should have chang'd some sillables
with you.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Another time sweet Mr. Sconce.
                  
               
               Tom Mixum, Vrinall, Exeunt with Doctor.
               
                  Mrs. Mix.
                  A very good fortune Mrs Arilesse for your daughter,
and not to be neglected: shall I speak to him, or will you
for sooth?
               
               
                  Mrs. Art.
                  Perhaps hee'l speake to us: see kind gentleman.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Lady, my manners does command mee leave you: you
would perchance be private by your selves, or peradventure Vrinall
were more behoofefull for your company: then I adiew
Vfroes.
               
               
                  Mrs. Mix.
                  Pray stay sir, we have some businesse with you,
(let me alone to trye him Mrs. Artlesse) besides wee had rather
be private with a gentleman, then by our selves: they say you
Dutch-men are the kindest men, and love a woman heartily, you
kisse so finely too.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  You shall feel that presently [kisses
her] there was a touch for you: Nay Mrs. Artlesse you shall not
blame my manners, I have a lip, a piece for you [kisses her] and
there was a touch for you Lady.
               
               
                  Mrs. Mix.
                  So please you sir, I have another touch for you too,
[kisses him] Must trie his disposition Mrs. Artlesse.
                  
               
               
                  Scon.
                  A very strong touch that same; she will beleaguer me I
thinke, and her Cannon shot will bee kisses, they almost
blow mee over. Surely the Minikin is enamoured on me.
               
               
                  Mrr. Art.
                  Motion it to him Mrs. Mixum.
                  
               
               
                  Mrs. Mix.
                  Pray give me leave to feele his minde first, Mistris
Artlesse: Tis pitty sir, you are so long unmarried; you are an
exceeding handsome Gentleman.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Yes, yes, I know that well enough, I might serve
for a gentleman Usher, were my legges small enough: there
are Ladies would consume halfe the revenews of their Lords,
on such a man of Chine and pith as I am.
               
               
                  
                  Mist. Mix.
                  Fie master Sconce, thinke not of Ladies sir, they
are so imperious, a man must serve them as they doe command,
at every turne and toy comes in their head; they'l puffe and fret
else, like their taffata peticoats withoften brushing up; I will
protest to you, you had better set you minde upon some honest
country Gentlewoman, or Citizens daughter, Master Doctor has
a handsome girle (though I say it before her mothers face) only
she wants the audacity, which a man would put into her; would
you were married to her: Sir, she may doe worse, I dare assure
you.
               
               
                  Mist. Art.
                  Yes indeed may you master Sconce, have you not
seene her yet? tis a pretty puling baggage, so it is, marry ere I
would make her a Lady, shee should be a new Exchage wench,
your Citizens wives they are the goodest creatures, live the finest
lives.
               
               
                  Mist. Mix.
                  Very right, mistris Artlesse, good soules, did you
but know sir, what tender hearts they have, how kind they will
be to a gentleman that comes to deale for their commodities,
they will use him and it were their owne husbands.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Ile lay my life this musk-melon has a minde to use mee
so: I care not much to give her a touch, or so, she's of the right
sise, but Mistris Artlesse should I have your good will, if I could
love your daughter.
               
               
                  Mist. Art.
                  Certainely sir, were you of English blood, I should
like you better.
               
               
                  Mist. Mix.
                  Fie Mistris Artlesse, when I was a maid, I had a
desire to be a kinne to all nations: I have tried some English
men, and they are like my husband, meere meacocks verily:
and cannot lawfully beget a childe once in seaven yeares.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  A touch, by this light, that's the reason there are so many
bastards in the city.
               
               
                  Mi. Mix.
                  Your Spaniard as a neighbour of mine, told me who
had liv'd among, is too hasty, he will not give a woman time to
say her prayers after she is bed: your French is with a woman
as with an enemy, soone beaten off, but mistris Artlesse, if you
will marry your daughter to the most compleat man, let him be
Dutch: they are the rarest men at multiplication, they will doe
it so readily.
               
               
                  
                  Seon.
                  They be indeed very good Arithmeticians.
               
               Enter Lady Yellow, Mistris knoworth.
               
                  Mist. Art.
                  Here comes the Ladies: Mistris Mixum we'l depart,
they must not know our conference.
                  Exe. Mrs. Art.
               
               
                  Mist. Mix.
                  A diew kinde master Sconce.
                  
               
               Mrs. Mixum.
               
                  Scon.
                  Adiew min vroen, I have a pestilent mind to this talking
harlotry, I will to her, but if I should obtain the Neapolitan beneach,
a creeke ith'backe, or so, from her, 'twould be but a sourvy
touch, that for me, I should be forc'd to swim ith tub for it, or
be hang'd by the armes, and smoak'd like a bloat herring, I had
forgot my pretious salve, should I be serv'd so, 'twere but dressing
the weapon that hurt mee (which I can have at any time)
and be sound agen, ha other donsella's: Madams, they are creatures
of Plush, and Sattin, Ile accost them.
               
               
                  Know.
                  This is the gentleman I told you of, I wonder what
his quality may be, our Landlord the Doctor is a much fam'd
man, and surely very honest.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  It shall be so, my English is not compleate enough
                  To hold discourse with Ladies of regard, my naturall
                  Dutch too is a Clownish speech, and only fit to court
                  A leagurer in: no your French shall doe it, and thanke
                  My memory, I am perfest in it, tis your most
                  Accomplish'd language, there's scarce a gallant but does woe
                  His mistris in the moode, but if they should
                  Not understand me: well I will experce
                  Me it.
               
               Sconce cringes to the Ladies.
               
                  Lady.
                  He meanes to speake surely in cringes.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Madametres puissant en lecommand. de touts ceurs de cest
monde, ie que sui semond &amp; invite en tant de lieux que ie ne scay

                        •
                     u aller pour abrir mon sayn: a vn bewtie digne de mon acceptance.
               
               
                  Lady
                  Heyday, what's this, how should he know
                  Who can speake French.
               
               
                  Know.
                  He supposes it, prithee answer him sister.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Suiuant vostre treschier virtue, Ie sui si liberal
                  Que ie abadonnerenie &amp; renounce a tout mis biens
                  Demon vid mon Engin mon alayne mon sang &amp; mon
                  
                     
Pensir (pour ie ne saurioye, que dire) proueior mon
                  Ceur mon affection tout a vostre plaiseur.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  Aproche's ie ne vou's morderay pas.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Si ié ne vous fay tratement t'el que
                  A vons appartient, ie espere que vostre
                  Noblez te contera de mon bon intention.
               
               Enter Sir Martine, Popingay, and Vrinall.
               
                  Vrin.
                  There is the Lady you enquire for.
               
               
                  Sir Mart.
                  Thanke thee my friend, there's for
                  Thy paines, depart.
                  Nephew stand cleare, observe.
               
               Exit Vrinall.
               
                  Scon.
                  Sily'a chose en mon petit povoir en quoy ie vous puisse
                  Servir &amp; aider commandes moy librement.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  Vous Este fort &amp; liberal de suparoll monsieur.
               
               
                  Sir Mar.
                  At it so close, so now he wrings her hand,
                  And she smiles on him: and her sister laughs
                  At the lascivious posture, that I could
                  Command a flash of lightning, or usurpe
                  A minute the prerogative of death
                  That I might force a ruine on them, suddaine
                  As water falls from mountaines, yet so wretched,
                  They might despaire and damne themselves, what say they?
               
               
                  Pop.
                  They speake French, I understand them not.
               
               Scon. kisses the Lady.
               
                  Mart.
                  O that's the ages bawd to lustfull contracts,
                  Hell seise them, may their lips, like twins
                  In mischiefe grow together, that their foule breath
                  May have no vent, least like some poisonous fogge,
                  It doe infect the aire.
               
               Kisses her hand.
               
                  Scon.
                  Per dona mi Madam apre's le's leures le maine.
               
               
                  Sir Mart.
                  Againe, why strait,
                  If I stand still, they'l to the very act,
                  
                     I shall behold my selfe transform'd to beast,
                  And like an innocent lambe, when the keene knife's
                  Prepar'd to slit his wesand never bleat
                  But in calme silence perish; villaine divell
                  Hadst thou as many lives as thou hast sins.
                  
                     
This should invade them all with the swift rage
                  Of fire or whirlewinds.
               
               Runs at Sconce, hurts him in the arme, Sconce disarmes him.
               
                  Lady.
                  Heavens blesse yee
                  Innocent gentleman: sister my husband.
               
               
                  Know.
                  I feare he has mischiev'd him.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  You thinke you have hurt me wonderfully I warrant.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Good sir be more your selfe.
               
               Laughs.
               
                  Scon.
                  Give me thy hand, tis but a touch ith arme man, thou art
a valiant fellow, I warrant thee a right twibiller, run a tilt at
a man before his weapon is drawne, your, Lady would not have
don't I me sure, but tis no matter, thou hast done me a curtesie,
or otherwise I should not take't so patiently, (I shall by this
meanes experience my precious weapon salve) hold, thou wilt
fight no more, there's a twibill for thee, thy sword Ile keepe till
wee next meet, Ladies beso los doights de vostre blanch mains, adiew
comrade remember I am beholding to thee.
                  Ex. Sconce.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  He's gone, but has left his hanger behinde him.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  Sister prithee speak to him, he has put me in such a fright,
                  I cannot.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Sir be not so extreamly passionate,
                  Discourse your grievance mildely, heare her answer,
                  Then censure justly of her.
               
               
                  Knor.
                  Brot
                        •
                     er 
                        •
                      admire
                  A person of your breeding should transgresse,
                  Civility so highly, to at empt
                  Upon a gentleman, who to my knowledge
                  Injur'd you no way.
               
               
                  Sir Mart.
                  He is your champion, and you his Ladies.
               
               
                  Know.
                  How sir?
               
               
                  Sir Mart.
                  His prostiutes I might have said O creature,
                  Who art so bad, the present age will question
                  The truth of history, which do's but mention
                  A vertuous woman; with what impudence
                  Canst thou behold me, and a shivering cold,
                  Strong as the hand of winter, casts on brookes
                  Not freese thy spirits up, congeale thy blood.
                  To an ere'lasting le
                        •
                     hargy. The starres
                  
                     
Like straglers, wander by successive course,
                  To various seats yet constantly revisit
                  The place they mov'd from: the Phaenix whose sweetnesse
                  Becomes her sepulcher, ascends agen
                  Vested in younger feathers from her pile
                  Of spicy ashes, but mans honor lost
                  Is irrecoverable the force of fate cannot revive it.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  Sir tis past my thoughts,
                  What should incense you to this jealous rage
                  'Gainst me your loyall wife, when no one blemish
                  Lyes on my soule that can give testimony
                  Unto my conscience that I have not ever
                  Truely and chastely lov'd you.
               
               
                  Sir Mart.
                  Yes just so the greene
                  Willow and shady Poplar love the brooke,
                  Upon whose bankes they're planted, yet infect
                  By frequent dropping of their witherd boughes,
                  Its wholesome waters; that thou shouldst be faire
                  And on the white leaves of thy face beare writ
                  The character of foulenesse, swallow up
                  In thy abysse of sin, thy native purenesse,
                  As the high seas that doe with flattering curles
                  Intice the spotlesse streames to mixe their waves
                  With the insatiate billowes, that intombe the innocent rivers.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  O me unfortunate woman.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Good uncle speake more kindly to her, alasse she weepes.
               
               
                  Sir Mar.
                  I see it nephew,
                  So violent raine weepes or the purple heads
                  Of smiling Violets, till its brakish drops
                  Insmuate among the tender leaves,
                  And with its waight oppresse them: these are teares,
                  Such as distill from henbane full of poison,
                  And craft as she they come from: tell me woman,
                  Who hast not shame enough left in thy cheekes
                  To cause a blush, darst thou usurpe the name
                  Of good or vertuous, when these eares can witnesse
                  Thou didst sollicit yesterday this youth,
                  To fate the ravenous heate of thy desire,
                  
                     
With all the eloquence well worded lust
                  Could borrow to adorne its painted fow lenesse.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  Was it you indeed? I'm glad I know't deare sir,
                  Had I the chastest temper, that fraile flesh
                  Could ever boast of, your strange usage of me,
                  Would undermine it: to forsake my bed,
                  Before my blood scarce relish'd the delights
                  Attending on young nuptialls, so that I
                  Expect no anger from you, if I seeke
                  That from the charity of other men,
                  Which your neglect (though you in duty owe it)
                  Will not allow me.
               
               
                  Know.
                  Well said sister.
               
               
                  Sir. Mar.
                  Life sheel tell me straight
                  She will retaine before my face some slave,
                  Some strong back'd monster to performe her hot
                  Desires with able activenesse, the slow
                  Motion of snayles that carry on their heads
                  Their shelly habitations to the pace
                  Of my dull rage, is swift as erring flames,
                  Which had it not been leaden wing'd; as sleepe,
                  Ere this had seis'd the monster.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  Ha, ha, ha, the man is sure distracted, ha, ha, ha,
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Heyday, here's laughing and crying both with a winde,
                  As boyes doe, a juglar's but an asse to a right woman.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  Good sir will you walke? the gentleman hee's in a terrible
sweat, should he stand still, he may chance catch an Ague.
               
               
                  Know.
                  A Cardus posset were very soveraigne for him, I perceive
his fit is comming.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  How doe you husband, sweet heart, what not speake? I
thought your jealousie ere this had driven you into France, but
now I see you feare to bee sea-sicke, you have found mee out it
seemes; I hope ere long you will provide Gossips for the child
I goe with, marke you ducke.
               
               
                  Sir Mar.
                  If I stay, my rage
                  Will hurry me to mischiefe, better leave her
                  To certaine ruine, then betray my selfe
                  To danger of it, when strong tides meete tides
                  
                     
In a contracted chanell, they theirforce,
                  Resigne to th' wearing of the troubled waves
                  A frothier livery, then when Oceans
                  Encounter with full liberty, the windes
                  Imprisond in the Cavernes of the earth,
                  Breake out in hideous earthquakes, passions so
                  Encrease by opposition of all scornes,
                  Tis most opprobrious to be arm'd with hornes.
                  Ex. Sir. Mar.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  He leaves you here sir as his spie, do's he not?
                  Pray wait upon your master, I suppose he is so.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Pardon me Madam, he is my uncle.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  Which of his sisters sonnes are you?
               
               
                  Pop.
                  The Lady Popingaies.
                  
               
               
                  Lady.
                  My cosen Harry Popingay; I cry your mercy sir: your
good mother knowes, and grieves Ime sure, to see her brother
wrong me as he does: should I tell her how you dealt with mee
too, she would chide you soundly.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Your goodnesse Madam will forgive it on my submission
and sorrow for it.
               
               
                  Know.
                  Weel beg it for you sir.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  Sister he has it, were it possible
                  To worke a reclamation on this man,
                  From his fond jealousie, I would not wish
                  A change to be an Empresse.
               
               Enter Dalinea.
               
                  Dal.
                  Madam, my mother does entreat your Ladyships company
in your chamber, Mrs. Mixum has brought the conserves
my father did appoint her.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Tis the same face, or else some Angel does
                  Assume this shape to mocke mortality,
                  With the true forme of beauty.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  Nephew pray see us oftner, and use all meanes to gaine
your distracted uncle from his frensie, sister shall's walke; Dalinea
be it your care to see my Nephew forth.
                  Exe. Lady and Knoworth.
               
               
                  Dal.
                  I shall Madam.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Life, she speakes too
                  A tempting language, such was our first mothers voyce,
                  While she was innocent, most perfect woman.
               
               
                  Dal.
                  Would you have ought with me sir?
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Yes bright vertue.
               
               
                  
                  Dal.
                  That title relishes flattery for ought you know: I may be
vicio us.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Goodnesse deludes it selfe then,
                  I cannot flatter Lady, you mistake me:
                  What I shall speake, comes from an innocence
                  Yet undefild by falshood.
               
               
                  Dal.
                  Speake quickely, if it concerne me, otherwise I must
                  Entreat a licence to depart.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  You cannot affoord example of such cruelty
                  To following Lovers, to deprive my sight so soone
                  Of yours, for whose least view, the darke Cimmerian, blinded
                  With continuall sleepe, would rowse his heavy eyelids.
               
               
                  Dal.
                  Nay, and you begin to run a complementout of breath,
                  You' l drive me hence indeed: (believe me sir) had I not lik'd
                  You well, my modesty would scarce have suffered the least
                  Enterchange of words (but since it has done) pray be briefe,
                  What tends your conference to?
               
               
                  Pop.
                  I love you Lady
                  With the religious fancy, that one Saint
                  Affects another; such a heate as mine
                  Was that, with which the first who ere knew love,
                  Had their soules warm'd (essentiall) not as now
                  The common garbe is to adore a lip,
                  Or any other lineament, but for
                  The abstract of perfection, which do's glory
                  In being deriv'd from one so good as you are,
                  Am I become your captive.
               
               
                  Dal.
                  This to me, sounds as the empty whistling of the ayre
                  Does in some hollow vault, unspotted truth
                  Informes my ignorance, there's not a person
                  In all the multitude of men loves chastly.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Be so charitable
                  As to believe I can, who never yet
                  Knew flame was vicious, my desires retaine
                  Their maiden purity, no other object
                  Did ere attract my soules unblinded eyes, but your faire selfe.
               
               
                  Dal.
                  Then I believe you sir,
                  No man will be so worthlesse to dissemble
                  
                     
With me, who cannot thinke but all the world
                  Intends the same reality that I doe:
                  Yet tis an errour, which perswasion scarce
                  Shall free me from: that every woman ought
                  To love a man with that indifferent heate
                  She fancies other women, without sence
                  Of difference twixt the Sexes.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Soule of sweetnesse,
                  How equally an Angels intellect
                  Informes her sacred Reason: to love chastly,
                  Could not have bin defin'd with juster strictnesse,
                  Had we produc'd the constancy of Swans,
                  Or never changing Turtles, as our patternes,
                  (T'had but describ'd chaste love) the Palme that prospers,
                  (Not but by's fellow) and the Vine that weaves
                  Of her owne leaves a thinne, yet glorious mantle
                  For her naked lover. Doe but embleme what
                  Her truth has utt'red: but resolve me faire one,
                  Could you affect so?
               
               
                  Dalin.
                  If that were all
                  Requisite to love, I could; but there's obedience
                  A Nuptiall wreath brings with it, which I feare
                  My frailty would scarce keepe, and to become
                  Perfidious to a vow were such a sinne
                  As I should quake to thinke of.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  You alledge
                  Vaine difficulties: I perceive your looks
                  Would be propitious to me, did your will,
                  Asham'd perhaps to suffer suddaine conquest,
                  Not play the Tyrant with them, and call backe
                  The crimson Nectar from your well-form'd cheeke
                  To guard your heart from yielding: come, let's kisse,
                  The modest heate proceeding from my lips
                  Will thaw your soule to softnesse.
               
               
                  Dal.
                  Away, we may not;
                  If true—chaste love had rested in discourse,
                  I could have beene its votary, but a thought
                  Of any thing beyond it, is to me
                  
                     
Dangerous as sicknesse: farewell sir.
                  Ex. Dal.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Sure some white Cherubim,
                  Comming to teach the irreligious earth
                  The ancient truth; in its swift flight to heaven,
                  Pronounc'd that happy farewell to the soules
                  Its musicke had converted, I've not lost
                  In my first tryall, like some ventrous man,
                  Who findes the Indies, though he get small wealth,
                  Yet he sets forth agen, in hopes at last
                  To lade his winged vessell: Ile returne.
                  That fire's not out, which does in Ashes burne.
                  Exit.
               
               Explicit Actus secund
                     •
                  s.
            
            
               Actus Tertius, Scena Prima.
               Sconce solus, dressing his weapon.
               
                  Scon.
                  SO, now it workes: the operation I believe is not on
the suddaine, and my wound rancles as fast as if hee
had runne his Rapier through a Head of Garlicke, or wash'd it
in Aqua fortis; and this weapon salve, so much extold byth' Twiball
Knights, commended by Mixum, deified by Vrinall, and
adored by my believing selfe, procures no more miraculous effect,
than if it were unguentum album. Well, I am confident
yet, there's no defect ith' 
                        
                           ••
                        guent; my blood, my blood is sure
anathemated; carries some curs'd impediment about it, that
disannuls the vertue and incomparable force of the divine s
                        •
                     lve.
This Dutch blood of mine, guilty of Bacon grease, and potted
Butter—Sof, who are these? my Cozen Fortresse, Generall
of the Twiball Knights; and his assistant Pirke, with Mr. Mixum;
twere a detriment to valour to complaine before them.
               
               
                  
Enter Mixum, Fortresse, and Pirke.
               
                  Mix.
                  Yonder's your Cosen talking to himselfe: pray Gentlemen
draw neare. Mr. Sconce I brought these friends to visit you.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Thanks good Mr. Mixum, Cosen Fortresse, and my
Diminutive Captaine Pirke; give your hands, you are welcome,
very welcome.
               
               
                  For.
                  Health to the Weather-cocke of my Kin, the noble Signeur
I
                           •
                        emias Sconce.
                  
               
               
                  Pirke.
                  Propitious, and auspicious be thy starres, man of renowne
and merit: ha thy arme in sling my Palmerin: Confusion
Captaine Fortresse, he weares a wound about him.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  No, no, a touch, a meere touch, a Flea-bite, Captain Pirke.
                  
               
               
                  Mix.
                  Is't not recover'd by the salve Mr. Sconce?
                  
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Yes, as good as whole; the weapon salve will remedy
it.
               
               
                  Fort.
                  Yes, past all chance it will: twill mundifie and purge
your body Cosen: I use to combate three of four at once, every
spring, purposely to be let blood a little: it does me good all the
yeare after.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  I am very glad of it. But tell me Cosen Fortresse, how
fares it with the residue of the blades, the valiant Twiball
Knights, the famous brethren, doe they walke in Coat gelt, or
all a mode in Dunkirke Cloaks?
               
               
                  Mix.
                  Those fashioned Cloaks I never heard of before: I mervaile
my Tayler gets not a patterne of them; Pray sir, what is a
Dunkirke Cloake?
               
               
                  Pirke.
                  Not know a Dunkirk upper garment, a leag
                        •
                     er Cloak;
behold my I
                           •
                        , this Cane, this staffe of office; this wee stile the
Millitarie Caster.
               
               
                  Mix.
                  Twill hardly keepe a shoure of raine out that.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Are they confin'd to Chamber still, for want of Boots,
or Linnen? I love to heare of their prosperities.
               
               
                  Fort.
                  Why Cosen they are well, but in the accustom'd garbe,
the frugall brimme, and petty feather: they expect most carefully
thy admittance into our Order.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  'Tshall be don
                        •
                      after my wedding Cosen▪ I have got,

dost heare, sirrah Pirke a girle of mettall, the Doctors daughter
Bully, Fortresse. Flesh of Milke and Roses Blade.
               
               
                  For.
                  But Cosen, tis necessary, you inrole your selfe into the
Family before you wed: our order, like the Knights of Malta,
does admit no persons espoused: but with this difference, if
they receive the Order Batchellours, they may then marry and
yet retaine the title.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Say you so Cosen?
               
               
                  For.
                  Certaine truth my Io: we met npon our grand Exchange
last night, our place of trade and consultation, and there concluded
some decrees, necessary for supporting our Commonwealth.
               
               
                  Pir.
                  How perdition Captaine? how durst you meet without
me? or conceite that decree valuable, which the voyce of Captaine
Pirke has not assented to. Refuse me sir, the brethren of
the Blades shall me their bold confrontment: vengeance doe
you take mee for a boy, or some Pigwiggin? consult without
me?
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Patience, good Captaine Pirke, I would faine heare
them.
               
               
                  Pirk.
                  He reads his necke-verse, reads them in my presence:
Death rob me of the priviledge of my place and dignity Captaine,
confound you, I could shew you Twibill for it.
               
               
                  Mix.
                  What does this Tom Thumbe meane troe?
               
               
                  For.
                  Why sirrah Dandiprat, you might have given attendance.
               
               
                  Pirke.
                  What without a summons, you can send Iacke Shirke
your Beadle; to congregate the meaner branches of the Brotherhood,
not a Picke-pocket I warrant you, but had notice of it:
and must I be forgotten? by my man-hood tis base.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  You have given the Captaine too bold a touch Senior
Pirke; thou art just like the Mouse to the Elephant, borne to
vexe him 
                        〈◊〉
                      p
                        •
                     ethee for my sake let him read them.
               
               
                  Birke.
                  Your sake prevailes, or otherwise—
               
               
                  For.
                  Attend then Cosen Sconce; our Orders Ile assure you are
such, as the most envious Justice, nor their Goose-quill Clarks,
that smell at new Bridewell, and Finsbury shall not exclaime
on. Imprimis, it is generally decreed.
               
               
                  Pirk.
                  How, generally without me? Fire of Styx this is insufferable.
               
               
                  
                  Scon.
                  Good Captaine Pirke, on cosen Fortresse.
                  
               
               
                  Fort.
                  That no knight of the Twibill; as Whiskin or allye
gentleman shall presume to lead or convey any of the sisters of
the order, viz. Striker, Cockatrice, or Gynimeg through the
watch after twelve, unlesse he see them asleepe, or be in see with
the Constable, under the penalty of being sent to the house of
Correction.
               
               
                  Pirk.
                  Renounce me sir, this order Ile not signe to, it savors of
cowardise, feare to convey a sister through the watch, tis against
Our noble institution
               
               
                  Fort.
                  Next it is enacted, that none of the groomes of our wardrobe
shall offer to deprive any man of cloake, coate, or hat,
unlesse it be in the darke, as they feare to answer it at the next
assises, and be burn'd in the hand for it.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Twould be a hot touch for them cosen Fortresse.
                  
               
               
                  Fort.
                  Next it is decreed, that the receivers of our rents and
customes, to wit divers Rookes, and Saint Nicholas Clearkes
shall certainely use no more slights to get more then they can
clearely come off with, under penalty of being carried up Holborne
in a cart, and at Tiburne executed, which may tend to the
dissolution of our whole fraternity.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  But have you concluded nothing for the sisters, I long to
heare them?
               
               
                  Fort.
                  O yes cosen, we have confinde them to a certaine price, a
stipend reasonable, so that they shall not need to dive into
pockets.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  They will doe that if you would hang them cosen.
               
               
                  Pirk.
                  I doe disclaime that order, Captaine Fortresse. your
wisedome should have well considerd at wha
                        •
                      charge they are,
for coach or hand litter, specially those of the gentile garbe,
next their ushers must be maintaind, paint payd for, cloaths, provided
and the matron satisfied, these things considerd, could you
bee so cruell as to confine them to a price by valour sir, I am asham'd
on't.
               
               
                  Fort.
                  Tis mended by the next order, they are prescrib'd from
wearing Plush and Sattin, unlesse in peticoats.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  You will not have them like the Jewes at Rome weare
party coloured garments, to be knowne from Christians?
               
               
                  
                  Fort.
                  By no meanes sir, we would have every one take notice
of them, but Marshalls men, Beadles, and Constables, and
therefore have ordain'd that they shall weare Beaver Hats,
Poak'd Russes, Grogram Gownes, or at the best wrought Taffata,
Foxe Skinne Musses, Moehaire peticoates, Bodkins and Croscloaths
edg'd with gold lace.
               
               
                  Mix.
                  This is the habit of our Rotterdamians.
               
               
                  Fort.
                  The only shape to hide a striker in: ever while you
                  Live, your city is most secure from officers, and most
                  Notorious to gentlemen, they will take up your city ware at
                  Any rate. Besides while they 
                        •
                     lanted it in plush,
                  'Twas an abuse to gentlewomen and Ladies, we have er'd in
                  Questioning them for females of our tribe, and had our pates
                  Broake for it.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  But Cosen is this edict generally confirm'd by all the society
of the Twibillers Knights and Ladies.
               
               
                  Fort.
                  Tis universall cosen, only for Captaine Pirkes name, wee
left a blanke, there's the decree sir, read it if you please.
               
               
                  Pirk.
                  Twas the safest course to leave a blanke for me, or I had
                  Blank'd your whole decree! I had by magnanimity.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  
                     Im
                           •
                        rimis, I Captaine Furibundo Fortresse.
               
               
                  Mix.
                  A fearefull name that same.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Knight great master of the order of Twibill: Lord of no
                  Cloke, Viscount Ratan, cane and one spur.
               
               
                  Mix.
                  You are but an ill cocke of the game it seemes.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Count Freese, gray Felt, and mony-lacke, Duke of Turnbull,
Bloomesbury, and Rotten Row, Lord paramont of all
Garden-Alleyes, Gun Ally, and Rosemary Lane.
               
               
                  Mix.
                  He has more titles then the great Turk
                        •
                      Proceed sir.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Chief commander of all Twibills, dangerfeild and whiskins,
who will quarell in Tavernes with a man, and not fight
in the field with a mouse. And of the residue of the fraternities
of husses, diverse dammes and decoyes, sole sultan and grand signeur,
have to the premisses set my mighty hand, together with
hands of our trusty and our couragious assistants (this blanke's
for you Captaine Pike) Holafernes Make-shift, Rosiran Knockdowne,
and twenty six more of our principall companions of the
order.
               
               
                  
                  Fort.
                  Nay there are others too, bu
                        •
                     y not their appellations
in oblivion, they merit memory.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  To which at our command also are subsign'd our most illustrious
and remarkable sisters (they are slit nos'd perhaps)
(there was a touch for them cosen Fortresse) Donna Iesabella,
Garreta, mother of the maids of Lambeth Marsh, with her conspicuous
consort, at the three skipping Conies in the towne.
(a touch that) you meane the three Squirrels, you are cunning
cosen Fortresse, together with our most industrious servant Pythagoras
Pigge.
               
               
                  Pirk.
                  I gave him that name from his transmigration into cast
suites, who has put his petie toes to it, and finally the woman
that sings ballads, has her name trunled at the taile of it.
               
               
                  Mix.
                  I mervaile master Doctor has not set his hand to this.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Seald with the seale at armes of our order, viz. Three
Rooks volant in a field sanguine, two broken jugs the supporters,
and a Twibill for the erest, and given the second day of this present
month, at our mansion royall, or place of meeting in the
long gravield walkes in our usuall fields.
               
               Enter Doctor, Vrinall, Freewit, Sir Martine.
               
                  Sir Mar.
                  Well Master Doctor you'l remember me,
                  And have an eye unto my nephew, I trust
                  Her with you. Farewell sir.
                  Exit Sir Mart.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Doubt it not good sir Martime.
                  
               
               
                  Fort.
                  Captaine Pirke pray retire unto the brothers of our
                  Society: entreat them to prepare againe tomorrow, for
                  My cosen Sconces enseasement.
               
               
                  Pi
                        •
                     k.
                  Upon compulsion sir, I should refuse, marry on faire entreaty
I doe flye, good and high fates looke on you.
                  Ex. Pirk.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Sonne Sconce (I'm bold to call you so) how do's your
at me?
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Indifferent sir, but yet I have not found
                  That rare effect ith' weapon salve you spoake of,
                  
                     Vrinall I feare since it cur'd the two serjeants and their
                  Yeomen, the vertue has beene much extenuated.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Twas your ill dressing the weapon: give me your sword

sonne, this is of the right salve the welsh Doctor makes, this
shall save my credit. (Annoints the weapon.) Now Vrinall take
this weapon, lap it warme in linnen cloaths, and locke it in my
sonne, your anguish sonne will soone be mitigated.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  I have a touch of it already sir.
               
               
                  Fre.
                  I have seene experience of this weapon salve, and by its
most mysterious working knowne some men hurt, past the helpe
of surgery recover'd.
               
               
                  Mix.
                  Marke you that master Sconce, the gentleman may be believ'd.
               
               
                  Free.
                  Yet I cannot
                  With my laborious industry invent
                  A reason why it should doe this, and therefore
                  Transcending naturall causes, I conclude
                  The use unlawfull.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  He is unlawfully begotten sir, dares tearme it so, there
was a touch for him cosen Fortresse; I cald him sonne of a
whore, and he would take no notice of it.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  But pray sir, why should it be unlawfull?
               
               
                  Free.
                  Cause Conscience and religion disallow
                  In the recovery of our impair'd healths,
                  The assistance of a medicine made by charmes,
                  Or subtle spells of witchcraft.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  his mother was a witch, saies this maide, so there was
another touch for him cosen Fortresse, son of a witch, but he understands
not that neither.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Conceive you this to be compounded so?
               
               
                  Free.
                  Ile prove it master Doctor.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  The proofe of a pudding is the eating, in your teeth sir,
a pudding in his teeth: you know what I meane cosen Fortresse,
another touch for him, but al's one, he has wit in's anger, and wil
not understand me.
               
               
                  Fort.
                  If he durst blunder for it Cosen Sconce.
                  
               
               
                  Free.
                  Yet to avoide a tedious argument,
                  Since our contention's only for discourse,
                  And to instruct my knowledge, pray tell me,
                  A 
                        〈◊〉
                      you not tha this same salve will cure
                  At any distance (as if the person hurt
                  
                     
Should be at Yorke) the weapon, dres'd at London,
                  On which his blood is.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  All this is granted 'twill.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Nay we'l grant you more sir (that it will not) and yet
prove it, and you shall prove your selfe a (so you shall.) There
had been another touch for him cosen Fortresse, but I fear'd hee
would have understood me now, ere you shall prove it.
               
               
                  Fort.
                  Silence cosen Sconce, let's heare the whif
                        •
                     ter if he cannot
verifie his words, sink me my Jo, he shall taste arme of dangerfield.
               
               
                  Free.
                  Out of your words sir Ile prove it Diabolicall, no cause
                  Naturall; begets the most contemn'd effect,
                  Without a passage through the meanes, the fire
                  cannot produce another fire untill
                  it be apply'd to subject apt to take
                  Its flaming forme, nor can a naturall cause,
                  Worke at incompetent space: how then can this
                  Neither consign'd to th' matter upon which
                  Its operation is to cause effect;
                  Nay at so farre a distance, worke so great
                  And admirable a cure beyond the reach
                  And law of nature; yet by you maintain'd,
                  A naturall lawfull agent, what dull sence can credit it.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Very authenticke this, well if the divell have tane the
paines to be my surgion, my arme I feare will be possest, I feele
an evill spirit in it already.
               
               
                  Fort.
                  Respect the Doctors answer.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Sir, you speake reason, I must confesse, but every cause
                  Workes not the same way; 'we distinguish thus:
                  Some by a Physicall and reall touch
                  Produce: So Carvers hewing the rough Marble,
                  Frame a well polish'd statue: but there is
                  A virtuall contact too: which other causes
                  Imploy in acting their more rare effects,
                  So the bright Sun does in the solid earth,
                  By the infusive vertue of his raies,
                  Convert the for did substance of the mold
                  To Mines of mettall, and the piercing ayre
                  
                     
By cold reflexion so ingenders Ice;
                  And yet you cannot say the chilly hand
                  Of ayre, or quickning fingers of the Sunne,
                  Really touch the water or the earth.
                  The Load-stone so by operative force,
                  Causes the Iron which has felt his touch,
                  To attract another Iron; nay, the Needle
                  Of the ship guiding compasse, to respect
                  The cold Pole Articke; just so the salve workes,
                  Certaine hidden causes convay its powerfull
                  Vertue to the wound from the annointed
                  Weapon, and reduce it to welcome soundnesse.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  The salve is legitimate agen, Cosen Fortresse, O rare
Doctor
               
               
                  Mix.
                  Nay, you shall heare him tickle the gentlemen I warrant
you.
               
               
                  Free.
                  This, Mr. Doctor, is
                  A weake evasion, and your purities
                  Have small affinity; the glorious Sunne
                  As tis a generall instrument of heaven,
                  In all its great productions, and the Ayre
                  An Elementall agent, naturally
                  Ingender Mettalls in the earth, and Ice
                  On the selfe 
                        〈◊〉
                      waters: The Load-stone
                  As tis a simple body, may afford
                  That vertue to the steele by secret power
                  Of all-commanding nature. But that this,
                  This weapon 
                        ••
                     lve, a compound, should affect
                  More than the purest bodies can, by wayes
                  More wonderfull than they doe, as apply'd
                  Unto a sword a body voyd of life,
                  Yet it must give life, or at least preserve it.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Pish, he talkes like an Apothecary to the Doctor.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  You mistake, it does not,
                  Tis the blood sticking to the sword atchieves
                  The cure: there is a reall simpathy
                  Twixt it, and that which has the juyce of life,
                  Moystens the body wounded.
               
               
                  
                  Fort.
                  Rare Parac
                           •
                        lsian, thy Annalls shall be cut in Brasse by
                  Pen of steele.
               
               
                  Free.
                  You may as well
                  Report a reall simpathy betweene
                  The nimble soule in its swift 
                        •
                     light to heaven▪
                  
                  And the cold carkasse it has lately left,
                  As a loath'd habitation: blood, when like
                  The sap of Trees, which weepes upon the Axe
                  Whose cruell edge does from the aged Trunke
                  Dissever the green Branches from the Veines,
                  Ravish'd, forgoes his Native heate, and has
                  No more relation to the rest, than some
                  Desertlesse servant, whom his Lord casts off,
                  Has to his vertuous fellowes.
               
               Enter Mistris Know-worth.
               
                  Know.
                  Mr. Free-wit return'd agen, and in discourse
                  With Mr. Doctor: Ile not disturbe your conference.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  So please your Ladyship we had even done.
                  I am glad she's come to rescue me.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  There was a touch for him Cosen Fortresse, victus, victa,
victum, he lookes like a Schoole-boy vanquish'd at capping verses:
harke you sir, repent your errour, and in time you may bee
sav'd; you see the vertue of the salve the Doctor had dress'd his
Speaking weapon with it. It hurt you, and it has cured you Beware
you fall not into a relapse: there was another touch for
him Cosen
               
               
                  Fortresse.
                  Doctor give your hand (father I should
have said) some fam'd Historian, some Gallo-Belgicus shal Chronicle
thee and thy salve, there was a touch for him Cosen Fortresse.
Come you shall see my Mistris.
               
               Exeunt Sconce, Fortresse, Mixum, and Doctor.
               
                  Know.
                  Mr. Freewit have you yet found the injur'd
                  Woman out, I motioned at last parting?
               
               
                  Free.
                  Truely Mistris, had she bin worthy the seeking, your
                  Command should not have beene protracted, but
                  'Twere a staine to my owne honour to be inquisitive
                  After a prostitute, and a blot to your
                  Discretion, should nice judgements know you enjoyn'd me
                  So manifest a folly.
               
               
                  
                  Know.
                  'Twas a greater to be the authour of her shame,
                  Whom now you slight so infinitely.
               
               
                  Free.
                  Could I slight her more,
                  'Twere a due justice which I owe my selfe,
                  (In hazarding the forfeit of your love)
                  Undone by her, but your most serious thoughts
                  Will sure convert your soule from the intent
                  Of my most certaine ruine, which your last
                  Discourse perhaps, for triall of my faith,
                  Seem'd to invert upon me.
               
               
                  Know.
                  You mistake; needlesse are second trialls, when a first
                  Proves you perfidious; doubtlesse you confirm'd▪
                  
                  Your love to her, with the same sad protests
                  You've done to me (yet left her) for her sake,
                  And in revenge of womans innocence, martyr'd by you,
                  I here to heaven pronounce a sure disjunction
                  Of our loves and vowes for ever.
               
               
                  Free.
                  O reserve that breath,
                  Which ought like sacred incense to be spent
                  Onely on heaven, or in delivering notes
                  May charme the world to peace, when raging warres
                  Or Earth quakes have affrighted it. Confirm't
                  On no such use, horrid and ominous,
                  As if it threatned thunder to the earth,
                  Or would infect the genius of the ayre
                  With Mists contagious (as if compos'd
                  Of Viper steame) O had you were wont
                  To be so good, that vertue would have sigh'd
                  (At the unwelcome spectacle) if you
                  Had appeard woman in a passion,
                  (Though of the slightest consequence) O do not
                  Renounce that Saint-like temper, it will be
                  A change hereafter burthenous to your soule,
                  As sinne to one, who all his life time blest
                  With peace of Conscience, at his dying minute,
                  Falls into mortall enmity with heaven,
                  And perishes eternally.
               
               
                  Know.
                  These words
                  
                     
Have not the effectuall Oratory you first had,
                  When I was confident, as day of light,
                  Your youth had beene as destitute of vice
                  As of deformity. So a sweet streame,
                  Whose bubling harmony allur'd the Birds
                  To court its moving musicke, when it mixes
                  With impure waters, with the noyse affrights
                  The eares, before delighted in it.
               
               
                  Free.
                  This is too severe a Justice, and extends
                  To cruelty, had some intemperate rage
                  Purpled my hand in murther (though the guilt
                  Would have beene written in a larger Text
                  In Conscience blacke booke; yet the punishment
                  Had not bin halfe so hideous. I should for that
                  Have suffered but a temporary paine
                  At worst; and my truely repentant soule
                  Perhaps have had free entrance to the place
                  consign'd to penitents, when now, like so me
                  Manacled Captive, or diseased wretch,
                  On whom each minute does beget a death:
                  I like a slow fire by my owne soft flames,
                  VVith Tortoyse speed extinguish.
               
               
                  Know.
                  Sir, your words are superficiall, as a shadow which
                  The morning Sunne produces and blacke night
                  Renders forgotten: and no more excite
                  Beliefe in me: that what you utter's truth,
                  Then Mand rakes groanes doe a conceite of death
                  In persons resolute▪ while I have yet
                  A specious memory left, that once my heart
                  Tendred you dearly; I would counsell you
                  First to indeavour to finde out that maid,
                  (If that succeed not) not to thinke on me,
                  As one affianc'd to you by a neerer interest then other women
                  Are that never had conversation with you.
               
               
                  Free.
                  Had a frost, sharpe as a tedious winters Northerne blasts,
                  Congeal'd your mercy, my unfained teares
                  Should with moyst warmth dissolve it, mistris you
                  Approach so neare the attributes of heaven,
                  
                     
That had you liv'd ith' superstitious age,
                  More pretious gums had fum'd upon your altars,
                  Then on all female deities. O forgive me,
                  A rigorous tyrants breath will scarce pronounce
                  For one and the first crime, so strict a sentence:
                  You shall not goe yet if you will recall it,
                  Lovers will blesse your piety, and sub scribe to your
                  Superlative goodnesse.
               
               
                  Know.
                  Pray desist, affoord me liberty to retire, I cannot alter
my resolution.
               
               
                  Free.
                  Yet reclaime it; some divells spleene has lately fraught
                  Your brest, and banish'd thence milde de pitty, (bostrous winds,
                  Force so the gentle and untroubled seas,
                  To swallow up some ships, its naturall calmenesse
                  Would have transported safely with their wealth
                  To their desired harbors) were my thoughts,
                  Not fix'd with that religion upon you
                  That are my prayers (when I repent) on heaven,
                  I should not thus transcend the lawes and strength
                  Of manhood, and like some distressed babe
                  Left by its parent to the desolate woodes,
                  Or ayres cold charity, so long implore
                  A new and holier union twixt our soules,
                  Then ere had link'd them which when you have tied,
                  Time shall depend like summer on your brow,
                  And your whole life be one continued youth,
                  (Such were the springs in paradise) and when
                  You passe to be a sharer in heavens blisse,
                  Virgins and innocent lovers spotlesse teares,
                  Hardned to pearle by the strong heat of sighes
                  Shall be your monument.
               
               
                  Know.
                  
                     I shall relent spight of my setled will, if be continue
                  These moving supplications: Sir because
                  You shall not blame my cruelty, or judge
                  Tis for regard of any thing but my honour,
                  I doe forsake you, if ere to morrow night
                  You finde that woman, get her to renounce
                  Freely her title to you, 
                        •
                      agen
                  
                     
On 
                        〈◊〉
                      of your future loyalty
                  Will stand the triall of your wavering faith,
                  Perhaps be yours agen: you have
                  Receiv'd my utmost meaning,
                  Exit Kno
                        •
                     .
               
               
                  Free.
                  How I adore
                  This constancy of worth in her, though
                  It make against myselfe, well I must to my taske,
                  That labour's richest that most paines doth ask.
               
               Explicit Actus tertius.
            
            
               Actus Quartus, Scena prima.
               Enter Doctor and Lady Yellow.
               
                  Doct.
                  TIS a strange humour Madam, and condemnes
                  Your judgement of much indiscretion,
                  Did I not know it lawfull; nay no way
                  But that for the recovery of your health,
                  I should not urge it thus, you are lately falne
                  Into a desperate melancholy, and your blood
                  Can no way purge so well as by
                  Performance of what I have declar'd.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  Truth sir I weigh not at so high a rate, my life
                  That to prolong it to an irke some age,
                  I should destroy my honour, neither doe I
                  Finde any such strange sickenesse raining on me
                  As you have urg'd; pray as you love me sir,
                  Unlesse you meane to drive me from
                  The house, repeate this argument no more.
               
               Enter Sir Martine and Vrinall.
               
                  Vrin.
                  Why looke you sir, my master has
                  Perswaded her as much as lay in him, and
                  
                     
He has a tounge able to cosen the divell: but twill not doe,
                  She is too honest believe it, for your nephew Sir Martine, shee
                  His kept her chamber ever since she came,
                  None but my selfe has seene her.
               
               
                  Sir Mar.
                  It shall be so, the holy law of heaven
                  Made us one individuall; the strickt league
                  'Iwixt man and wife, ought to confine both soules
                  To a most constant union, injur'd woman.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  My husband and on the suddaine, speake you to me sir.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  His mouth opend Ime sure, sir the Dutch Gentleman.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  O my sonne Sconce, come hither Vrinall.
                  
               
               
                  Lady.
                  This acknowledgement cannot
                  Be serious from him, good Sir Martine
                  
                  Has your wilde fancy not impos'd enough,
                  Temptations on my fraylty that you come after
                  So many strange indignities, againe to delude me.
               
               
                  Sir Mar.
                  Tis misery of customary sinners when they meane
                  A reall truth, then their precedent ills,
                  Deprive it credit, Madam not that night,
                  That sacred night which spred its starry wings,
                  (Like Curtaines shadowing the Altar) ore
                  Our Hymeneall couch, could witnesse more
                  Sincerity of indissolving love'twixt us,
                  Then does this minute, if your soule,
                  (Which is so passive it may justly challenge
                  A Martyrs temper) can dispense with pas'd
                  Absurd distastes, and like a Saint for humane
                  Condition is too vengefull freely pardon
                  What I amisse have acted.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  As you are my husband sir, and consequently my head.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  How many Lad
                        •
                     ies in towne are of that minde.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  And ought to be the guider of my youth,
                  I will not stand on that nice terme of honour,
                  With you whom duty ties me to observe
                  With more then superficiall care, t'injoyne
                  A penance for your folly; the light smoake
                  Findes not a surer buriall in the a yre
                  (To whose embraces with ambitious haste.
                  
                     
On azure wings it soar'd) then has your guilt,
                  In this forgiving bosome, this pure kisse seales the agreement.
               
               
                  Sir Mar.
                  She offred first too, and me thought she kis'd
                  As she would eate my lips, the ravenous touch
                  Sir Mar.
starts.
                  Of her hot flesh has seard me up like grasse
                  In summer time, and her fowle breath like blasts
                  Of Southerne windes, has quickned my dead fire
                  Of jealousie, nay rais'd it to a greater
                  Heat then my former.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  What ayle you sir on the suddaine?
               
               
                  Sir Mar.
                  Viper, toad, out of my presence, ere my just wak'd
                  Rage, get to its height, whence like a Falcon towring
                  At full pitch ore the trembling fowle, it will sease on thee.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Madam tis best to leave him, I feare he's absolutly franticke;
Vrinall looke to him, least he act some violence on himselfe,
please your Ladiship withdraw.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  Soft patience guard my heart: wheres no offence,
one safely may rely on innocence.
                  Exit Lady and Doctor.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Why sir Martine, how doe you sir? not speak? now by my
life, hee lookes like a staggerell newly come to his Hornes,
flings his head just in that manner they do not touch the seeling,
yet Sir Martine: in time they may be three and foure at top, and
serve to hang hats and cloakes on in the best knights hall in
towne.
               
               
                  Sir Mar.
                  
                     O Vrinall.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  O Vrinall, what a pittifull noate was there, that very
sound has almost crack'd me to pieces: Sir Martine, good Sir
Martine what ayles you? or rather what ayles your wife, that
you hum and haw so after kissing her▪ her breath is savory, I dare
bee sworne shee has neither eaten Onions nor drunke Aquavitae.
               
               
                  Sir Mar.
                  O no, she is like a too ripe, so extreamely sweet,
                  Shee poisons like the hony which small Bees
                  Sucke from the Aconite, the Panther so
                  Breaths odors pretious as the Sarmaticke gums
                  Of Easterne groves, but the delicious sent not taken in at
                  Distance choakes the sense with the too muskie savor.
               
               
                  
                  Vrin.
                  You should have kis'd her as the Court fashion is, upon
the cheeke, but pray 
                        •
                     ir, why are you so jealous: yet cannot prove
your Lady has a trick with her toe, or turnes oftner then an honest
woman (if shee do) had not you better like an old Stag, cast
the cognisance of your order into the hedge, then like a wanton
Pricket, runne f
                        •
                     ll Butte at every one you meet, as who should
say; take notice of my horns. I am ashamed of it so I am.
               
               
                  S. Mar.
                  Do'st not believe I am? a hideous cuckold.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  And must you needs cry Cuckow therefore. There are
knights in towne who know their Ladies to be Hens oth'game,
and 
                        •
                     ive by tredding, yet like mettle Cockes they never hang the
Gills for't, they are sure faire Gamesters use to pay the boxe well:
especially at In, and In, (the Innes of Court Butlers would have
had but a bad Christmas of it else) and what care they, so they
can purchase plush, though their wives pay ith' hole for it.
               
               
                  Sir Mar.
                  Can there be such monsters?
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Monsters, they are men Sir Martine, such as you are;
only they are velvet browd a little: but heare me Sir, if a man
would venture faire offer to give a certaine knowledge of your
wifes honesty.
               
               
                  Sir Mar.
                  Doe that, and be my genius Vrinall.
                  
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  You would have an evill Angell of me, Ile tell you sir,
my master intends privately this night to wed his daughter to
the Dutch younker S
                           •
                        once, the house will be atquiet, and your
Lady left alone in her chamber, her sister Mistris Knoworth, being
to goe to Church with them.
               
               
                  Sir Mar.
                  What of this?
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Soft and faire Sir Martine, I will ith' evening steale you
into the Ladies chamber when she's in bed, come to her, and in
the darke, (thats the only time to deale with a woman) (and as
another man) trie what you can doe with her: if she consent
(the worst) you doe but cuckold your selfe, if hold out, being a
woman alone, in bed, and in the dark having a man standing by
her, you may then conclude her an honest wife, and your jealousie
foolish, as your vexation needlesse, you thinke I have no wit
now I warrant.
               
               
                  Sir Mar.
                  According as my soule could wish.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Why law you then, who's the fooole now? Sir Martine
                     
come in the evening, I will not faile you.
               
               
                  Sir Mar.
                  Nor I hopes of triall, fare you well,
                  A jealous man has in his heart his hell.
                  Ex. Sir Ma
                        •
                     .
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  well knight, if I doe not fit your jealous head, let me bee
sung in ballads for an erranter coxcombe then your selfe.
               
               Enter Mistris Artlesse, Mistris Mixum, and Dalinea.
               
                  Mist. Art.
                  Well said mi
                        •
                     x, you will not have him: but you had
best consider and doe as I and your father would have you: or
you shall trudge for it, you shall be his wife.
               
               
                  Mist. Mix.
                  Nay in sadnesse Mistris Dal. you are too blame, the
gentleman is an honest gentleman, I and a kinde man I warrant
him to a woman; your mother and I have made triall of him,
and finde him of a very good disposition, come chicke you shall
have him.
               
               
                  Mrs. Art.
                  Nay let her chuse and bee hangd, proud baggage
who will refuse a gentleman of my owne chusing, but Ile send
him to you and see if thou darst deny him, for thy life, come
Mistris Mixum.
                  
               
               Exeunt Mistris Artlesse and Mistris Mixum.
               
                  Dal.
                  Was ever innocent virgin thus betrayd
                  By cruelty of parents, who for wealth
                  Have sold my youth to slavery, the cold
                  Ashes of injurd maids surround my heart,
                  Or some divine dew, stead of blood replenish
                  My swelling veins, circle my thought with Ice,
                  Thou power of chastity, that like the fresh
                  Primrose uncropt, by any hand, I may
                  Returne my selfe as pure and white
                  To earth, as when I came from't.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  How doe you Mistris Dal. alasse poore gentlewoman,
would they have thee coverd with a Frisland horse, a Dutch Stallion:
now shame upon their soules that wish it, he's neighing
here already.
               
               Enter Sconce.
               
                  Scon.
                  
                     Vrinall, my cosen Fortresse and the rest oth' Knights will
be here presently; pray you prepare the musicke and the wine,

I would not faile in the most diminute ceremony.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Of a most absolute coxcombe, I shall provide them sir.
                  Exit Vrinall.
               
               
                  Dal.
                  Now begins my horror, the fatall Bell should it proclaime
my death, were spheare-like musicke to his night-crowes
voyce; yet I must heare it and retaine my sense, continue subject
to a da
                        •
                     ly noyse from the ill boding monster.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Lady or Madamosell, Vfroe or Seniora, what you please,
or in what language to be entituled the Mistris of my thoughts,
the complemental garbe is customary, and though I have learn'd
by conversation with the Twibill Knights to kisse my hand, believe
me I had rather bestow my lips on yours; our naturall Dutch
contracting is the best, without deceit or shadow, there we only
goe to th' taverne and be ungue browd, then drunke together.
Ther's all our ceremony, and tis lawfull marriage too.
               
               
                  Dal.
                  Would you would sir, better consider with your selfe and
ma
                        •
                     ch where your own customes are observ'd, my feare my quality
will never suite the liking of your Dutch manners.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Manners Lady, you mistake I've none at all; ere we will
disagree about manners, Ile be as clownish as an Upland Bore,
foutra, tell a Dutch man of manners?
               
               
                  Dal.
                  Yet sir have so much charity.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  We detest that worse then the former, tis Papisticall, and
was with that religion banish'd our reform'd Common-wealth:
but to our businesse, pretty soule, I shall give thee touch mon and
get a burger of thee.
               
               
                  Dal.
                  Gentle sir, there ought to be in manhood a divine
                  Pitty, believe me as I tender truth,
                  I cannot set the smallest of my thoughts
                  On your ill welcome love, therefore I beseech you
                  Not to proceed in my unfortunate match
                  Which will be fatall to us both, for goodnesse
                  Have so much mercy on me.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  An excellent touch that, as if there could be mercy in a
Dutch-man, and to a woman? if there had beene any, the Nuns
at Tilmont had not beene us'd so horribly last summer: why
should you say you cannot love me
                        •
                     tis a false touch I me certaine
of it, I shall know anone, till when receive your lips in pledge

that no such words shall issue forth of them, adiew Lady,
anone we must to the old touch of Matrimony.
                  Ex. Sco.
               
               
                  Dal
                  The hand of death
                  Shall give me first a bride to some darke grave,
                  Where I will mixe with wormes before the Priest
                  Knit so unjust an union, the kinde grasse
                  Will sure be greene still on my Sepulchre, and spotlesse
                  Virgins annually dance a fairy ring about it.
               
               Enter Vrinall and Popingay in disguised clothes.
               
                  Vrin.
                  Now if you doe not catch a Roach in her troubled waters,
I shall conclude you a gudgion: speake to her; a woman has ever
a hole open to receive a mans tale, believe it you shall have
my assistance, and if I doe not second you confidently, may my
tongue be cramped, my wit breech'd; and the machina of my invention
ruind perpetually.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Fairest creature.
               
               
                  Dal.
                  Had you said wretched'st, Mistris you had given me
                  My proper attribute.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Can there be on earth,
                  A savagenesse so great as will conspire
                  To afflict so rich a goodnesse? yet by your eyes
                  Adorn'd by those cleare pearles which doe transforme
                  Even sorrow to a lovelinesse beyond
                  Indifferent beauty, I conceive some fiend
                  Rested in humane shape (for man would never
                  Have dar'd so vile a sacrilege) in hope
                  By your pure teares, t'extinguish his owne flames
                  Caus'd this distemper in you.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Pish you are long to speed, be
                  Short and quick, that pleases Ladies.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  I had a younger brother, though not fully blest
                  In your sweet knowledge, yet once his tounge
                  Was his hearts bold embassador, and deliver'd
                  A true narration of his zealous love,
                  Which is in him so permanent, that when
                  his eares receive a notice that your faith
                  
                     
Is plighted to another, twill be 
                        •
                     uice
                  Of balefull hemlo
                        •
                     ke to his braine, convert it
                  Either to suddaine madnesse or a sleep, cold and erelasting.
               
               
                  Dol.
                  I remember once a nephew of Sir Martines did sollicit
                  That which he term'd my love, but I conceiv'd
                  His meaning rather was to cause discourse,
                  Then that his strict intention had resolved
                  His promises performance.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Did I not tell you she would come about?
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Trust me Lady, the solitary Nightingale who sings
                  To her lost honour a harmonious ditty,
                  Loves not the thorne so dearely, to whose pricks
                  She sets her featherd bosome, as I me sure
                  My brother tenders you, the gawdy light
                  May sooner be obscur'd by wandring smoake:
                  Nay the eternall essence of the soule
                  Become corporeall and revisite earth,
                  After its flight to paradise, ere he
                  Descend to variation of his love, could you affect him.
               
               
                  Dal.
                  Had your brother been
                  Of the same disposition and soft sweetnesse
                  That I perceive in you (though this be our
                  First enterview) there could not have beene molded
                  (Had I beene borne to entertaine loves heat)
                  A man that would so fitly sympathize
                  With my condition, nor whom I should fancy
                  With more intire perfection.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Strike home, and sure the iron's hot already,
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Behold him Lady,
                  Whose every motion does as from the spheare,
                  Receive a lively influence from your lookes;
                  The modest silence of the temperate Even,
                  When zephire softly murmures to the flowers
                  A wholesome farewell undisturb'd by stormes,
                  May sooner rest in one continued night,
                  Then can my soule in quiet without just
                  Assurance of your love, which if you grant,
                  Times native Belman, the shield Organd Cocke
                  
                     
Shall cease to carrol
                        •
                      
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      to the morne,
                  The 
                        •
                     arely Larke that whispers to the Sun
                  A constant Augury of a beauteous day,
                  Shall lose his light plumes in the che
                        •
                     kerd Clouds,
                  Ere I my resolute chastity▪ nor can you
                  Invent evasions to declare my suite,
                  Since on its grant relyes the only hopes
                  Of your redemp
                        •
                     ion from the barbarous armes,
                  Of him you were espous'd to.
               
               
                  Dal.
                  This surprize,
                  And your strong vowes would batter a resolve,
                  Downe in a brest that could be flexible
                  To easy love, but since I cannot frame
                  My conscience to a warrantable zeale
                  Toward any man, Ile rather fixe my hate
                  (For that must of necessity accrue
                  To him that weds me) on a person worthy
                  Contempt, then on your selfe, whose wor
                        ••
                      do's challenge
                  A noble and reciprocall regard
                  For your affection, blessings on ye sir, thinke not amisse of me.
                  Exit Dalinea.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Now the curse of a tedious virginity light on ye, you
will not be tupped by a Dutch Ram, a Hausen Kender, a West-fally
Bore-pig, now the iniquity of a swagbellied Hollands
Burgers get thee with childe of a dropsie, if thou marriest him,
why how now Master Popingay, stroken with a Plannet? tis a female
Star, as changeable as the Moone, goe to your chamber, I
heare company approaching, this Dutch Butter-Firkin shall bee
melted to grease ere he shall have her, trust to it.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Passion on passion fall when hopes are spent,
                  The best of comforts is a forc'd content.
                  Exit.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  So here comes my blades, now plot but hit,
                  And Vrinall shall be stil'd the Lord of wit.
                  Exit.
               
               Enter Sconce, Fortresse, and Knights.
               
                  Scon.
                  Cosen Fortresse welcome, welcome Captaine Pirke, valiant
brothers, nay gentlemen, then your accoutrements be of

the vulgar cut, be not daunted, tis hereditary to Low Country
souldiers to weare off reckonings, the time shall come the little
worme shall weave, and silken tribute pay to men of service,
give me your hands gentlemen, I shall be one of you anone, but
Cosen F
                           •
                        rtresse, what bashfull youth is that that dares not thrust
his nose out of his coate, for feare the winde should blow it
to his face, ha?
               
               
                  Fort.
                  Tis flat enough already, this my Jo, nay show thy Phisnomy,
h'is our quondam trusty attendant, but now Knight of the
Twibill, Pithagoras Pig.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Is this the famous off-spring of great hog? we should be
kindred certainely, my Ancestors were Bores, give me thy foref
                        •
                     ot
sirrha, and tell me coz, why dost not wander into a new
skin? this begins to crackle vilely.
               
               
                  Pirk.
                  O tis forwant of basting sir.
               
               
                  For
                        •
                     .
                  No my Jo, hee casts his skin but once a yeare, like the
poore snake: well, he has done our Order speciall service; but
coz, where are the preparations the vancarriors coz, to the solemnity
of your insta
                        •
                     m
                        •
                     nt? renounce me, if you vilifie the institution
by disregard of properties, this hand shall never crosse the
Twibill ore thy head, nor give thee thy avant chevalier, while
thou art mortall my Jo, I say I shall not.
               
               
                  Pirk.
                  No matter sir Sconce, by the head of valor, my selfe shall
dub thee.
               
               
                  Fort.
                  Who you King Twadle? Mushrome you dub him?
               
               
                  Pirk.
                  Yes, I Gog, Magog, I dub him Garantua.
                  
               
               Ent. Vrin.
               
                  Scon
                  Nay good cosen Fortresse, Captaine Pirke, this Vrinall I
could e'ne fill him to the brim with curses, but here's my agent;
come where are the musitioners Vrinall?
                  
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  They will bee loud enough by and by, I warrant
you.
               
               
                  Fort.
                  This is legitimate blood of the Spanish grape my Jo.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Lusty sacke credit me coz, twill give the touch, Vrinall
make fast the doore, and leave us, and give us notice if any body
approach.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  What haste this gull makes to cheat himselfe in private,
must the musicke enter?
                  Exit Vrin.
               
               
                  Fort.
                  No by no meanes, weel call to them through the doore,
varlet avoide.
                  
                     
Now coz, to beginne our ceremony; first, drinke to me.
               
               
                  Scon:
                  I like it well when it begins with drinks, tis a signe
twill end merrily; this cup is abominable to little, one can
scarce wet his whistle out of it, it shall be this goblet, a vostre
grace, coz Fortresse.
                  
               
               
                  Fort.
                  Sir Pithagoras we doe create you skinker, it shall goe
round my blades, you shall dible in liquor of account; here brother
Make-shift.
                  
               
               
                  Make,
                  Gramercies Captaine.
               
               
                  Pirk.
                  Choake you sir, learne manners, offer to drinke before
betters, tis an affront to seniority, destroy me if I can suffer this,
no forsake me Captaine I cannot.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  There was a touch for you brother Makeshift, but good
little Pirke be patient.
               
               
                  Mak.
                  This Preface is very Cannonical my Io, nay, I shal learn
the phrases instantly.
               
               
                  Pig.
                  Have you all had it brothers?
               
               
                  Pig.
                  All but my selfe Sir Holofernes.
                  
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Who my coz Pig, off sup off thy wash my Jo, at worst
thou canst but be swine-drunke; but coz, shall we dispatch? I long
to be instald.
               
               
                  Fort.
                  I now we'l to't, come hither Captaine, sing the hymne
preparatory to Knight-hood, but wet your pipes first, Ganimed,
they'l squeake the better.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  An admirable touch this, what's next troe?
               
               Song.
               
                  Fort
                  Now coz Sconce, our Order does constraine us to a frisk, a
dance about you, as the Fairies tred about their great King Oberon.
                  
               
               
                  Pirk.
                  But can this musicke play the Twibill dance, none else
will satisfie.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Musicke you must play the Twibill dance he sayes, dance
so while.
               
               
                  Dance.
                  They dance, the wine shall tread a sink apace into my
belly, you have lost one of your best heels cosen.
               
               
                  Fort.
                  No me Jo, twas off before the ceremony is halfe accomplish'd,
you are our wardrope keeper, brother Knock
                           •
                        downe have
you brought the vestments of our Order?
               
               
                  Knocke.
                  Fuse Captaine not I.
               
               
                  Pirk.
                  Rot me sir, you would be made to fetch them.
               
               
                  For.
                  How, not our robes of honor the ensignes of our cheval
                        •
                     y?
               
               
                  Knock.
                  Sinke me, sir you know they are in tribulation.
               
               
                  
                  For.
                  Hell take the Broker: we must perforce imploy one of
our owne suits.
               
               
                  Knock
                  Take my Buffe Jerkin Captaine.
               
               
                  Make.
                  Death keepe it on, you'll shew your dirty shirt.
               
               
                  Pirke.
                  Found you sir, you lye: I fathome in your guts, hee has
none on.
               
               
                  Make.
                  How, sonne of foule Adultery, the lye?
               
               
                  For.
                  What doe you blunder, whi
                        ••
                     lers Pigge, are you grunting
too: shall I whet my Twibill on your bones mips of debility?
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Nay, Cosen, Gentlemen rather than you shall fall out,
Ile be content to bee dub'd in my own cloathes: nay pray you
Gentlemen.
               
               
                  For.
                  Tis against order, and we must observe ceremony.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  O by all meanes Coz.
               
               
                  For.
                  First then receive this cap of maintenance.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Cap of Maintenance doe you call it? I will maintaine
when this old Cap was new, 'twas a Dutch felt, but now tis
nine degrees below a straw Hat; I doe not like this touch: but
Coz I shall have my Bever agen I hope?
               
               
                  Fort.
                  How? suspitious my Io: Brother Knockdowne disroab
his necke of this old linnen, savours of a winding-sheet: this is
Decimo Sexto, feares no rumpling: Now Cosen Sconce, you must
discusse your doublet.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  That will be damn'd instantly; pray heaven my skinne
scape.
               
               
                  For.
                  Here sir, receive this Military Cassocke, 't has seene
service.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  'Thas been shot through both the Elbowes; this Military
Cassocke has I feare, some Military hangbyes: this Twibill
Knight-hood is but a lousie Order, would I had he're medled
with it.
               
               
                  Fort.
                  Now you appeare something above an Embrio: Makeshift
helpe to untrusse his breeches.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  I shall be whipt instantly: But Cozen Fortresse, is there
no redemption for my Breeches?
               
               
                  Pirke.
                  Sume me Captaine, tis not requisite he should put off his
Breeches.
               
               
                  
                  Scon
                  Thankes good Captaine Pirke, twas a friendly touch that
               
               
                  Pir.
                  May not his transitory money serve to excuse his breeches?
               
               
                  Fort.
                  To him it may.
               
               
                  Pir.
                  A Twibill Knight ought to regard no money, but the glistring
steele.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Well, since it must be so, there take my money.
               
               
                  Knock.
                  Paw sir, you lose the priviledge of the Order, if you
respect your money.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Now doe I looke like—as if I were new come from
the Lottery: or what say you Sir Holofernes, to the Picture of
the Prodigal in the painted Cloath? Sure I have now perform'd
all the Ceremonies; if not, I me sure I have nothing else left
to performe withall.
               
               
                  Fort.
                  So, now kneele downe, while thus I thee create: Ieremia
                           •
                        
Sconce, Knight of the order of Twibill. Now avaunt
Chevaleire.
               
               
                  Omn.
                  Health to our worthy Brother, Ieremi
                           ••
                         Sconce, Knight
of the Twibill.
               
               
                  Fort.
                  But brothers, there is Sacke yet to be drunke, in Celebration
of this Knight-hood,
               
               
                  Scon.
                  I like this drinking heartily; there's some goodnesse in't:
will you beginne, my Captaine Generall; Ile call you so now.
               
               
                  Fort.
                  
                     Pythagoras, fill his Bowle up. Capt. Pirk this Cornucopia
To my Leiftenant Generalls health: Ile call you so now.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  A place of Marke and Charge that.
               
               
                  Pirke.
                  Man of valour, respect this Cup to the health of our Leift,
Generall.
               
               
                  M
                        •
                     rk.
                  A vous brother Knockdowne.
                  
               
               
                  Knock.
                  Here Sir Barrabas.
                  
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Altogether gentlemen, a health Musitians,
sound.
Gentlemen all tres humblement serviture vostre: I ha done you
right.
               
               
                  Fort.
                  Expect me Io; heart of my father, you must for consummation
of your installment, drinke a cup a piece to each of us.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Twas my intention Generall: to you all in generall,
helpe Pith. let it be be two Captaine, tis pitty to put so many
worthy men in a pint pot.
               
               
                  Perk.
                  Soule of my valour, y'are ship'd sir, you must drinke five
together.
               
               
                  
                  Scon.
                  Y'are wanton Captaine, a wag upon my Knight-hood,
you meane to measure the profundity of my belly, twill bee a
hard taske to doe it to a Dutch-man—looke you Captaine.
               
               
                  Fort.
                  Thou shalt be my Bacchus Io, he drinkes as if hee had
eaten Pickle Herring.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  This Cup was as deepe as Fleet-street Conduit. Sound
me my Io, I ha' made a new River in my Belly, and my Guts are
the Pipes: Tother cup good wreckling, vertue shall be vertue
still, so long as I can stand Captaine.
               
               
                  Fort.
                  That will not be long I hope.
               
               Enter Vrin.
               
                  Scon.
                  This Coller spoyles my drinking, or else this Sack has
horse-flesh in't, it rides upon my stomacke. O Vrinall, Ime a
Knight of the Twibill honest Vrinall.
                  
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Take heede you'll crush me sir to pieces. Gentlemen
yonder are the Constables at the doore to apprehend Captaine
Fortresse.
                  
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Some more sacke sirrah, I shall be married anon.
               
               
                  For.
                  That's I, tis for the linnen brothers: Hell my Io, how
shall I scape them?
               
               
                  Scon.
                  More Sacke sirrah, the tother touch sweet Pig, the tother
touch.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  There is no way but one sir, they have beset the house;
my Master is perswading them. Follow mee, Ile by a backe
way set you safely out with your company.
               
               
                  For.
                  Noble Vrinall: come Blades here's purchase for us.
               
               Exit Vrinall cum Kn
                     •
                  ghts.
               
                  Scor.
                  This is but foure Cups captaine Cosen Pigge. Skinke
my parting Cup, and then I me gone: ha! where be you Gentlemen,
I am not blinde, or play you at Boe-peep? they are gone,
this is a pretty touch, my touch my Io, with my money and
Cloathes, a pretier touch still, let me see, they have left some
Sacke behind them, there's my comfort yet.
                  E
                        •
                     t. Poping.
and Lovring in
womans cloa
                        •
                     hs.
                  Who's this? my wife that must bee.
                  Come hither wife, thou seest the worst of me
                  I am but drunke: Kisse me Borankee: never feare, I will not
spoyle thy gorget. Hark in thy eare my Io, shall I have a gentle
touch? twill doe no harme, wee are to be marryed anon thou
know'st; I shall get wise children on thee.
               
               
                  
                  Lo
                        •
                     .
                  What wouldst thou ravish me libidinous Swine? Strive, and thou dyest.
               
               strikes up his heeles.
               
                  Scon.
                  Twas an unkinde touch that, my Io, you might have
falne under me, 't had beene the fitter place for a woman, (pray
helpe me up agen.
               
               
                  Lov.
                  Yes, to thy death, if thou deny t' performe what I enjoyne
thee.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  How, kill a knight of the Twibill, and in the Ensignes
of his owne Order, ere it shall be said to the disgrace of Knight-hood,
that any of the fraternity was kild by a woman, Ile doe
any thing: Lead on, Ile follow you.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Thus they must strive▪
                  
                  Who in loves subtle Merchandise will thrive.
               
               Exeunt.
               Explicit Actus quartus.
            
            
               Actus Quintus, Scena prima.
               Enter Doctor, Vrinall, Mrit, Artlesse, and Mris. Mixum.
               
                  Doct.
                  THis stealth was unexpected, tis almost
                  Beyond beliefe, my daughter should thus change
                  Her perverse humour, and embrace his love
                  Which when I motion'd to her, the darke shade
                  Seem'd not a greater enemy to blest light
                  Than she appeard to it: and that she should
                  Cosen my hopes, and without me her mother,
                  Or any friend resigne her will to his,
                  And strike the match up, puzzles my best faith,
                  Though I rejoyce at it.
               
               
                  
                     
                        •
                     rin.
                  You have reasons sir to doe so, your daughter had more
wit then you expected, tis the quality of maids, to deny what
they desire: had you but seene how nimbly shee trod over the
threshold; you would have sworne she had beene mad of the
match: I stood and heard him aske her: shall wee goe to the

Church 
                        〈…〉
                      not too late 
                        〈…〉
                      
                     
                        •
                     oo
late to doe well replied she agen: (though it were at midnight)
and then the Dutch you 
                        〈◊〉
                      tooke her up into a (what doe you
call it) 
                        〈◊〉
                      (and heaven speed) away they went, marry to
what Church, he's gone I know not, only I heard him sweare he
would not 
                        〈◊〉
                      at Pencridge.
               
               
                  Mrs. Art.
                  And why not; tis an ancient Church, and all old
things must not be cast away▪ there has beene many an honest
couple given to the lawfull bed there, so there has.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  No matter for that, he protested he would be marryd in a
Taverne ere that pencridge, there's no drinke nere it; but at the
Pinder of Wakefield, and thats abomi
                        •
                     able, and he has vowd to
season their bargaine with a cup of Sacke ere they returne.
               
               
                  Mist. Art.
                  Hee will not bee drunke on's wedding night I
hope; my daughter would have a sweet bed-fellow of him, if he
should.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  There is another loving couple gone with them too
for company, who will be man and wife if the Priest say Amen
to it.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  who are they of our knowledge?
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  O yes sir, tis Master Lovering, the attendant to Master
Know
                           •
                        rth, and Sir 
                        
                           〈◊〉
                        
                      Niece that came but yesterday.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Is't possible? twas some 
                        •
                     lie policy of her Uncles to
bring her hither, Master Lovering knew her before it seemes.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Too well I feare sir, they would not have marryd in such
post haste else.
               
               
                  Mrs. Mix.
                  Well Master Doctor, I hope my gloves shall bee
better then the ordinary, I had no small hand in this match, you
know.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Tis nine a clocke at least: twill not belong ere they returne,
wife pray goe in and see all things in readinesse for their
lodgings.
               
               
                  Mist. Art.
                  They will have more stomacks to their beds then
to their suppers.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  To morrow we'l celebrate their nuptiall feast: Vrinall
be you carefull of the doores▪ let none come in but our owne
company.
               
               
                  
                  Vrin.
                  Ile locke them up, and keepe the keyes my selfe sir, Mrs.
Mixum your husband is with them, and in his absence I would
desire a word with you.
               
               
                  Mrs. Mix.
                  
                     I love to talke with any man in my husbands absence;
sweet Vrinall I will fulfill your pleasure, will you goe
Mistris?
                  Ex. Vrin. Mrs. Art. &amp; Mrs. Mix.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  So now have at her.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Have I not plotted finely? has my braine
                  not won the lawrell garland the fa
                        ••
                     d breath
                  That wafts the honor of deserving wits
                  Among the humorous multitude (as 
                        〈◊〉
                     
                  
                  As it speakes conquering triumphs) shall proelaime
                  My politicke merit, who have raised my selfe
                  From worse then no name in the judging world,
                  To an indifferent wealth, which though
                        •
                      ve g
                        •
                     t
                  By wayes sinister, such as erre from truth:
                  Nay might incurre a punishment no eyes
                  Has ere discern'd them, but with wonder how
                  I should atchieve such fortune, now compleat
                  In this alliance.
               
               Enter Lady Yellow and Knoworth.
               
                  Lady.
                  Sister, let's to our chambers and to bed,
                  That time approaches.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Your good Ladiship (I hope) will honour me so much
                  As for an houre to dispense with rest▪
                  
                  And see my bride in bed.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  Your bride good Master Doctor, who should that be?
                  I understand you not.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  My daughter Ladies, that to me
                  And all the house seem'd so averse from marriage,
                  Is this night stolne forth with younker Sconce,
                  
                  And is by this time wedded to him.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  Beyond wonder, well sir,
                  We'l have her bride garters, it shall goe
                  Hard else, sister could you have thought it?
               
               
                  Doct.
                  You may both credit it, instantly they will returne, and
                  Then Ile wait upon you.
                  Exit Doctor.
               
               
                  
                  Lady.
                  I pitty the p
                        •
                     ore girle,
                  That she should be so suddaine in her choyce,
                  Enthrall her soule ith' manacles of fate,
                  (For such are nuptiall bonds) 
                        〈◊〉
                      sister
                  Inforces me to 
                        〈◊〉
                      her 
                        〈◊〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  Know
                        •
                     
                  
                  How equally we two
                        •
                     
                  
                  Divide true, sorrow sympathi
                        •
                     e in griefe,
                  As in our blood and nature: sister you
                  When your affectionate fancy 
                        •
                     ix'd your heart
                  Upon your husbands love, had no suspition
                  Of his unmanly jealousie, and I
                  When I c
                        •
                     nfin'd my love to Free 
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      breast▪
                  
                  Judg'd him as void of falshood, as the spring
                  When it has rested in green tobes the Earth is
                  Of bare nakednesse, but we are both
                  Deceiv'd by our cred
                        •
                     lity▪
                  
               
               
                  Lady.
                  For you, discretion may 
                        〈◊〉
                      you from the care
                  Of his affection, you are free (as light)
                  (Which in the darkest night retaines some splendor)
                  From the obedient slavery, due to marriage;
                  But I no burne-markd captive is engag'd
                  With more officious 
                        •
                     eale to serve his Lord,
                  Then I my husband, I must either perish
                  Like the chaste ice, when from a Christ all Rocke,
                  It feeles a sad conversion into fowle
                  Corrupted waters, by his jealous flames;
                  Or breake those ties whose dissolution
                  Would betray my innocent vertue to a ruine,
                  Sure and eternall.
               
               
                  Know▪
                  
                  But yet counsell me,
                  I love this man so that if honour would
                  Dispense with his offence, I should forgive him,
                  And take him to my bosome
               
               
                  Lady.
                  Alasse you cannot,
                  What noble soule (though halse starv'd) would be fed with
                  Base reversions, conscience too forbids.
                  Enter Vrin.
                  The supplantation of another, sister strive to forget him
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Mrs. there is a gentleman without, this knockt for entrance
as if he had beene a Constable, his businesse is with you,
and his name Free
                           •
                        it; I told him you were in bed 
                        •
                     nd he swore
he would come to you through the doore, shall I admit him?
               
               
                  
                  Know.
                  This is his last night, his businesse carryes weight, pray
let him in. Be now propitious Love: is any with him?
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  There is enough of him, unlesse he made lesse noise. Ile
send him to you.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  Sister, now give him his latest answer, and resolve
                  Upon some choise more happy: here he comes.
               
               Enter Freewit:
               
                  Know.
                  How, as a Bridegroome?
                  Deckt with the Ensignes of young Nuptialls,
                  A wreath of Flowers, and Bayes, and yet me thinkes
                  His hand displayes a Willow: what should this Embleme?
                  Master Freewit we scarce expected you thus late.
               
               
                  Free.
                  You'll please to afford my manners an indulgent pardon,
                  For pressing to your presence thus: but tis
                  Perhaps our extremest enterview, and so
                  May challenge the prerogative of excuse,
                  For the audacious errour.
               
               
                  Know.
                  Would I could, with as much safety to my honour, grant
Remission to your other fault.
               
               
                  Free.
                  My thanks, are humble debtors to you for it, Mistris,
                  The nimble minutes have with crafty theft,
                  Stolne time away, reduc'd your limited houre
                  To an unwelcome period: I have sought
                  With the same diligence good men seeke heaven,
                  What you injoyn'd me, but the raine that falls
                  In Summer time upon the parched dust,
                  May easier be restor'd to the moyst Clouds,
                  Then she to my discovery. Wherefore since
                  Her losse is certaine, and the losse of you
                  Depends on her, to satisfie your soule
                  That I have man about me, I am come
                  With the same confidence your scorne has taught me,
                  To tell you, I as lightly prize your love,
                  As you have valued mine
                        •
                      nor can you blame me, since 'twas your owne desire.
               
               
                  Know.
                  Credit me I
                        •
                     me very glad on't: but pray tell me sir,
                  Why yo
                        •
                      come thus adorned with Nuptiall wreathes
                  Into my presence? is't to invite me to your wedding, or expression
                  Of your contempt, I have not merited so harsh an usage.
               
               
                  Free.
                  Neither: This branch of forsaken Willow I resigne
                  To your owne wearing, that when after times
                  
                     
Shall know our 
                        ••
                     tuall parting; 't may report,
                  That we were both forsaken, though we sever
                  With the unwillingnesse that flourishing 
                        •
                     rees,
                  Divest themselves of greenenesse, yet no blemish
                  Of harsh unkindnesse shall defile our thoughts:
                  We'll part faire, though for ever.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  This gentleman seems so noble, I repent that I advis'd her from him.
               
               
                  Free.
                  This Laurell wreath, that circles
                  My uncaptiv'd brow, I doe justly challenge,
                  Since I have conquerd the greatest enemy,
                  Mankind can combate (passion) yet the dew
                  (That on the red lips of the blushing Rose
                  Bestowes a weeping kisse) leaves not so sadly
                  The amorous flower, that curles its purple leaves,
                  To hide it from the Suns enforcing Rayes,
                  As doe my thoughts your memory, which did once
                  Preserve it as inviolable, as heaven
                  Does the bright soules of innocents.
               
               
                  Kno.
                  You might
                  Have had so much humanity, as to have kept
                  Your purpose to your selfe: though your loose sinne
                  Constraines my honour to renounce your love,
                  I would not have my eares 
                        〈◊〉
                      with this
                  Relation of your contempt, for so
                  Trust me I take it Freewit.
                  
               
               
                  Free.
                  Why, good Madam? can you condemne my too officious truth,
                  Of a conceite of falshood, when the spring
                  Of my Revolt, derives its head from yours.
                  You for a triviall, and scarce knowne offence,
                  Could without scruple banish me your heart,
                  When Angels should, for a desertlesse kisse
                  From an impure lip, have renounc'd their blisse,
                  Ere the most urgent reason of suspect,
                  Should upon me have practis'd a contempt
                  Of you: Had not your breath e
                        •
                     pos'd a mist
                  Of infidelity before the eyes
                  Of my cleare seeing soule, and left it blinde
                  As the blacke Mole, that like a Pioner digs
                  A winding Labyrinth through the earth to finde
                  A passage to the comfortable light,
                  He never has fruition of.
               
               
                  
                  Lady.
                  But sir, suppose my sister did it for a proofe,
                  Of your affection, and now should reclaime
                  The harsh prescription she impos'd, you would not
                  Continue in this temper.
               
               
                  Free.
                  Madam ever. The Cedars juyce, whose bitter poyson gives
                  The most strong body unavoyded death,
                  Preserves the Carcasse by its dying force,
                  Voyd of corruption: so has dealt her love
                  With me; its reclamation strucke me dead,
                  And since my Exequies has kept my heart
                  From entertaining a corrupt regard
                  Of future slavery,
               
               Enter Doct. Vrin. Mris. Artlesse.
               
                  Vrin.
                  They are entred, sir, I heard Mr. Mix. say as I let them in,
that they were marryed.
               
               Enter Mixum with a Tore
                     •
                  , Popingaies in Sconce his cloaths, leading
Dalinea: Lovering leading Sconce a
                     •
                  tir
                     •
                  d in Poping. womans cloaths.
               
                  Mix.
                  Nay, come an end gentlemen and your wives, Mr. Doctor wil
not be angry though I have usurp'd his office, and beene the father to
his daughter.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  You are not a cunning baggager you would
none forsooth when I propos'd it to you; but when the fit came on
you, you could then runne madding, and never let the Sexton ring
the Bell to give us notice: had it beene any one but Mr. Sconce, you
should have fought a portion; but since to him, we pardon it: take her
sonne, heavens give thee joy of her.
               
               
                  Vri.
                  You would scarce say so, knew you as much as I doe.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  We thanke you sir, and rest your dutifull children.
               
               
                  Lad.
                  Ha
                        •
                      my Nephew Popingay!
                  
               
               
                  Doct.
                  
                     Mr. Popingaies. Sir 
                        
                           〈◊〉
                        
                      Nephew! I am abus'd, undone,
my daughter's cousend Vrinall, a 
                        〈◊〉
                      put on mee, Mr. Popingay to
wed my daughter.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  
                     
                        •
                      was with her owne consent Sir, and
she my wife by your free gift.
               
               
                  Mrs. Art.
                  Your wife, your whore she is as soone, she is Master
Sconces wife, and that you shall finde, so you shall, let me come to
the baggage husband, 
                        〈…〉
                      her eyes out.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      he sh
                        •
                     ll injoy her, Ile spend the best part of my wealth
he shall not have a penny portion with her, depart my house I charge
you
                        •
                      
                     vrinall call in my neighbours, ere 
                        〈◊〉
                      he us'd thus▪
                  
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  
                     
                        〈…〉
                      I know you and your wayes.
               
               
                  
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  Vrin.
                  Goe to, be patient, then give this gentleman your daughter;
nay be friends, and love him too, or all shall out.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Thou wilt not betray me villaine?
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  But I shall discover you and your practises, nay to the Justice,
                  This gentleman is the same Sir Martin brought hither as his Niece.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Plots upon plots against me.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  But the great one is still behinde: if you will be friends
quickly with them, so; if not, your impostures all come out.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Is it even so? well since I am ore-reach'd.
                  Better sit downe in peace, than with disgrace:
                  Mr. Popingay consideration of your just desert,
                  Now his perswasion has suppress'd my heat,
                  Enjoyns me to forgive your loving theft▪
                  
                  Accept my daughter with as good a heart
                  As she is mine: come hither wife, say you so too?
               
               
                  Mr
                        •
                     s. Art.
                  Nay, since you say it, it must be so.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Humbly I thanke you: such another gift,
                  Should Nature offer all her pretious store,
                  Could not be given Mortality: but truely sir▪
                  
                  I had much adoe to winne her.
               
               
                  Dal.
                  You have me now;
                  But I professe untill we came to be
                  Conjoyn'd ith' Church, I tooke you for Mr. 
                        
                           〈◊〉
                        , but now rejoyce
                  
                     I was deceived so, I shall study to love you
                        •
                     
                  
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Now you name, where is Mr. Sconce?
                  
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Tis my cue now. O father I me here they have given mee a
touch, a very scurvy touch, I am a brother of the Twibills, and I am
married too, but I need not feare being a Cuckold.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  Mris. you know the Gent.
               
               
                  Know.
                  My servant Lovering married to Mr. Sconce!
                  
                  You'll get brave boyes I doubt not.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  
                     I and wenches too; come hither, we will be man and wife,
that's certaine, nay and lie together, so we will, you shall behave
your self well enough like a woman: but that you have a 
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        ••
                     pediment
for-bearing Children: but give me thy hand, shal's be drunk
together?
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  He is scatoe sober yet I thinke.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  
                     
                        •
                     e tell you father, ere I▪
                      went to the Church I had gotten a
touch in the 'Crowne, the Twibil Knigh
                        ••
                      
                     
                        〈…〉
                      my 
                        〈◊〉
                     
had made me'drunke, and got my 
                        〈…〉
                      by these

                     I know not: But ha, let me see, this should be my suite, tis it, by valour
it is: doe you heare good man Foxe, how crept you into this
Lyons case?
               
               
                  Pop.
                  What meanes this new married man?
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Do you jeare me, with a touch of that? harke you husband,
Though I be your wife, you shall not hinder me from claiming my
owne Breeches. Mistris a word with you too you put a gentle touch
upon me did you not? But I shall know you hereafter, Ile say no
more, and touch you boldly for it.
               
               
                  Lov.
                  Y'are very merrily dispos'd Sir: had it not beene to have
done Sir Martines Nephew, I should not have beene fool'd so.
Ile trie his temper though.
               
               
                  Know.
                  No matter Lovring thou art a Gent.
                  And since I am resolv'd from Master Freewit,
                  
                  That heele not have me now, (though I were willing)
                  To toote the least remembrance of him
                  Out of my breast, by this my happyer choyse,
                  Ile marry thee.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  But let him marry you though if he dare, ile sue the Statute
of Bigamy upon him, he shall be hang'd for being double marryed.
               
               
                  Free.
                  In this one act
                  She onely appeares woman, all her Saint,
                  Speake her a Saint. I did not thinke her heart
                  Could have resum'd (though than rejected me)
                  A baser choyse, Sir you've good Fortune: Mris
                  
                     I will not wish you ill successe in your
                  So suddaine Love: but it was eruell in you
                  To give away your soule, (as in despight)
                  In my loath'd presence: yet to shew how much
                  
                     I prize your satisfaction, I resign
                        •
                     
                  
                  My interest in you to him, and thus freely
                  Bestow him on you: will you have him Lady
                        •
                     
                  
               
               Pulls of Loverings Periwigs, he is discovered to be Marth
                     •
                  .
               
                  Lady.
                  Heaven blesse me sister, this is the same maid
                  Whom Master Freewit is reported to have
                  Got with Child: this is strange
                        •
                     
                  
               
               
                  Free.
                  Nay, be not amazed Mistris it is she:
                  You had best call her to a strict account
                  How long tis since I lay with her.
                  
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     Freewit, what meanes this mad delusion?
               
               
                  
                  Scon.
                  My wife turn'd a woman indeed: this is a touch indeed, I
had best be
                        •
                      gone, for feare she challenge me.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  O stay your patience good Mr. Sconce.
                  
               
               
                  Free.
                  Now let heaven, and all that can be titled good beneath
                  Divinity, conjoyne to frame a piece
                  Of vertue great as this; yet be deficient
                  In the atchievement▪ for some c
                        •••
                     ing Artist
                  To draw her in this posture (to be plac'd
                  (In Alablaster, white as her owne figure)
                  Or some greene meade or flowry valley, where
                  Posterity of Virgins yearely might
                  Offer a teare to the blest memory
                  Of perfect feminine goodnesse. Let me dye,
                  Gazing on you and I shall flye to heaven
                  Through your bright eyes.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Sir, what meanes this extasie?
               
               
                  Free.
                  Ile tell you, and Mrs trust each word▪
                  
                  As the just accent of Oraculous truth:
                  Knowing your and e
                        •
                     t love to me, I feard
                  It might embrace a change, and therefore shap'd this woman
                        •
                     
                  
                  In the habit of a man got her unknowne to you,
                  Prefer'd to serve you: (which she could not have bin without
                  Discovery, in her owne shape) not too'
                        ••
                     -looke your life.
                  Or watch your actions, but to raise report
                  That I had bin false: so to trye if that
                  Would stagger your resolve, which I have found
                        •
                     
                  
                  So noble, that the happinesse of Fates,
                  Can give no more addition to my blisse.
                  Madam beg you my pardon.
               
               
                  Know.
                  O sir you have it, and I my best of wishes, but why did you
                  Employ a woman thus dis
                        ••
                     is'd suppose
                  She had beene got with childe you must
                  Have beene the father of it.
               
               
                  Free.
                  I knew she was too honest, and beside,
                  I put her to the acting of't because
                  She being the accuser of me for her selfe
                  Might without the least seruple of 
                        〈◊〉
                     
                  
                  Free me from her owne calumny, nay here's another,
                  Can witnesse this for truth.
               
               
                  Know
                  How Vrinall Master: Doctor's man turnd to 
                        〈◊〉
                      Mr.

                     Freewits man, and Marthies brother?
               
               
                  Vrin
                        •
                     
                  
                  So it appeares by
the story Mrs. I am glad sir you put my sister in this disgu
                        •
                     se, she has
got a good husband by the shift, take your wife sir, she is no worse
a woman then my owne sister.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  But let me see and feele you better, it is no periwigge this
but are you my husband, a woman; wife?
               
               
                  Liv.
                  I your wife am sir.
               
               
                  Sc
                        •
                     n.
                  Master Doctor you wish me well I know, I have married
here I know not whom, you have excellent salves and unguents sir.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  They are at your service all.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Thanke you good
Mr. Doctor, have you never a one that will eat off the wen of manhood,
make all whole before that will eunuchise a man, I would

                        •
                     aine be a Her maphrolite, or a woman to escape this match, I do not
like it
               
               Enter Mrs. Mi
                     ••
                  um.
               
                  Mris. Mix.
                  Help gentlemen, help Mr. Doctor, yonder is a man
would ravish me whether I would or no, nay kild me, I thinke he
has puld out the longest naked weapon, O there he is.
               
               Ent. S. Mar. drawne.
               
                  S. Mar.
                  She shall not scape me were she
                  Fenc'd with fire, strumpet thou diest.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Who's this, Sir M
                           ••
                        tin, what doe you meane sir?
               
               
                  Mris.
                  I, this is he Thomas doe you see what a terrible thing hee
has got? was that sit to use to a woman? I was but laid in the next
roome, to sleepe, and he would have done something to mee so hee
would had not I beene the honester woman.
               
               
                  Lady.
                  Is't so Sir Martine? I have now just cause
                  To suspect your loyalty, and that your fond
                  Jealousie proceeds out of intemperate lust,
                  Could I not serve, but underneath my nose
                  You must be rioting upon another?
               
               
                  Sir Mart.
                  Shame and confusion sease me.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  You may see Sir what comes of your jealousie, but feare not
Sir, your wife will pard on it, there's no harme done.
               
               
                  Mrs. Mix.
                  But there might have beene, had not my honesty been
the greater.
               
               
                  Lady,
                  Well Sir martine, though you have injurd
                  Me most infinitly, I doe re
                        ••
                     t all if you will protest
                  Nere to be jealous more.
               
               
                  S. Mar.
                  Amasement and my shame hinders my utterance,
                  Let me breath in sighes my true repentance,
                  And henceforth
                  That jealousie in man if't be injust
                  Is ill, nay worse then in a womans lust.
               
               
                  
                  Know.
                  But pray you brother, who brought you hither?
                  We shall tejoyce to have you at out wedding,
                  And see this reconcilement.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  
                     I Madam, I; under pretence to have attempted his wife, but I
sent him in to Mrs. Mixum, who I knew would fit his turne.
               
               
                  Mrs. Mix.
                  And so I could have f
                        ••
                     ed him as well as another woman.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Brother Vrinall you are a 
                        ••
                     ave, brother Vrinall, and
have showd all a 
                        •••
                     ehing touch.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  No sir I sav'd you from being cozend, my sister shall have
some portion, here's a hundred pieces in this pu
                        ••
                     e.
               
               
                  Scon.
                  Sinke me my 
                        •
                     o, my owne purse.
               
               
                  Vrin.
                  It, is indeed Sir, I got it from your 'Twibill brothers, and
this your watch too, and your cloths which Mr. Popingay weares, by
locking them into a roome, and threatning punishment, if
                        •
                      they denied,
the blades shall now resume freedome▪ this key will let them
out, come forth gentlemen, he
                        •
                     e is your brother Master Sconce.
                  
               
               Enter the 
                     〈◊〉
                   Knights.
               
                  Scon.
                  Captaine generall, give thy hand bully, Captaine Pirke, my
cosen Pig, and all of you; though you would have cheated me tis
no matter, you shall dance at my wedding, and be drunke too, my
Joe, you shall.
               
               
                  Pirk.
                  Confusion rot the bones of Vrinall perdition shall slay him;
               
               
                  Free.
                  Madam I hope we shall keepeour nuptiall feast with Master
Doctor.
               
               
                  Know.
                  As you dispose it sir, I have resign'd my will to yours.
               
               
                  Pop.
                  Unckle I hope you'l pardon me, that I deceiv'd your expectation
in watching my Aunt, she is too ver
                        ••
                     ous: father your blessing,
and then we are happy.
               
               
                  Doct.
                  Take it.
                  Thus all are pleas'd I hope: what this night cannot
                  (For celebration of these feasts) performe,
                  To morrow shall, and from this 
                        〈◊〉
                      I
                  Renoun
                        •
                     e all waies sinister to get 
                        〈◊〉
                     
                  
                  Things that ith' p
                        •
                     riod prosperously
                        •
                      succeed,
                  Though cros'd before, are acted well indeed.
               
               FINIS.
               
            
         
      
   

