
   
      
         
            A treatise concerning the trinitie of persons in vnitie of the deitie Written to Thomas Mannering an Anabaptist, who denyed that Iesus is very God of very God: but man onely, yet endued with the infinite power of God.
            Gill, Alexander, 1565-1635.
         
         
            
               1601
            
         
         Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01747
            STC 11879
            ESTC S118376
            99853583
            99853583
            18973
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01747)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18973)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1100:09)
         
         
            
               
                  A treatise concerning the trinitie of persons in vnitie of the deitie Written to Thomas Mannering an Anabaptist, who denyed that Iesus is very God of very God: but man onely, yet endued with the infinite power of God.
                  Gill, Alexander, 1565-1635.
               
               [6], 74 p.   
               
                  By Simon Stafford, dwelling on Adling hill neere Carter-lane,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  1601.
               
               
                  Signed at end: Alecsander Gil.
                  The Bodleian copy has date in imprint changed by pen to read 1603.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Jesus Christ --  Divinity --  Early works to 1800.
               Trinity --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-07
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-07
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-09
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-09
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               A
TREATISE
concerning the Trinitie
of Perſons in Vnitie
of the Deitie.
            
               Written to Thomas Mannering
an Anabaptiſt, who
denyed that Ieſus is very
God of very God: but man
onely, yet endued with the
infinite power of God.
(⸪)
            Imprinted at London by
Simon Stafford, dwelling
on Adling hill neere
Carter-lane.
160
                  •
               .
         
         
            
            
            TO MY VERY LOuing
and deare friend Maſter
Thomas White, a Citizen
of Briſtow.
            
               WHile I was at Norwich, in
the yeere 1597. I writ
this Treatiſe vpon ſuch
occaſiō as appears therein,
and deliuered it vnto
that Heretike, that by himſelfe, if
God would, he might conſider and be
perſwaded Since which time I haue
kept it by me: and though ſome of my
priuate friends deſired copies; yet allowing
that wiſdome of Solon, who
would make no law againſt Patricide,
leaſt the mention of the fact might

giue occaſion to commit it: and withall
conſidering that it is too ſ
                  •
               mple and
poore for the publike view; I haue hitherto
refuſed to make it common.
Yet now perceiuing a preſent neceſsitie,
becauſe that ſ 
                  •
               me of late haue
wandered in this labyrinth: &amp; withall
remembring, that of any weakling
ſhall hereafter entertaine this
opinion, he may, before he be wholy
poſſeſſed therewith, find the abſurditie
of it and be reformed▪ that many
a nouice in Chriſtianitie, who
therefore doubts of the trueneſſe of
his Religion, becauſe he findes no familiar
reaſon to perſwade, but onely
the racke of authorities to 
                  〈◊〉
               
him to acknowledge it; may perhaps
be hereby ſatisfied and find comfort:
and that they who are already ſtrong,
may by this ouerplus, triumph in the
goodneſſe of God, who requires them
to beleeue no more, then they may by
that vnderſtanding, which he hath giuen

them, be perſwaded of: I haue for
their ſakes, who may reape benefite
thereby, ſet at nought all other Cenſurers,
not guilty vnto my ſelfe of any
offence which I can commit in making
it publike. Such as it is, accept
(good maſter White) as a parcell of
that aſſertion, which may hereafter
follow, of euery article of our Chriſtian
faith; if God ſhall vouchſafe
me vnderſtanding, leaſure, and maintenance
thereto. I therefore offer it
vnto you, both becauſe I know you
are diligent in reading bookes of good
argument; and becauſe I haue none
other meanes, whereby to ſhew my
ſelfe thankefull for your manifold
kindneſſes and your loue. At London,
this 20. of April. 1601.
            
               Your louing and aſſured
friend,
A. G.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            THE TREATISE.
            
               THough many things
diſcouraged mee to
write vnto you of
this Argument in
ſuch ſort as I intend;
conſidering that neither your daily
reading of the Scripture, neither
the perſwaſion of learned Diuines
can moue you to accord vnto
the trueth; though by manifeſt
teſtimonie of Scripture they conuince
your hereſie: and moſt of all,
that God hath left you to beleeue
that lying ſpirit of Antichriſt, who
denyeth that Ieſus is that Chriſt: Yet
neuertheleſſe, hauing ſome hope

that God of his goodnes will at laſt
pull you as a brand out of the fire,
and quench you with the dew of
his grace, that you may grow in
the knowledge of his Sonne; I wil
as briefly as I can, lay down ſome
few reaſons of that faith, which euery
one that will be ſaued muſt
hold. Whereby if I perſwade you
nothing, yet ſhall I obtayne thus
much; that you, who neither beleeued
his word, nor yet opened
your eyes to ſee the light of reaſonable
vnderſtanding, ſhall at laſt
confeſſe, that his word and iudgements
are holy and true. But before
I come to the point, let mee
firſt perſwade you, that although
the knowledge of the holy Trinity
be one of the moſt high myſteries
which can be knowne or
beleeued, and that it is the onely
work of ye 
               holy Ghoſt to work this
faith and knowledge in the heart
of man, yet neuertheles, God hath

not left vs deſtitute of meanes,
whereby to come to this faith and
knowledge; but hath alſo with his
word, giuē vs a reaſonable ſoule &amp;
vnderſtanding, whereby to grow
in the knowledge of himſelf &amp; his
will. For whē 
               Adam was created,
he had giuen vnto him all perfite
knowledge meete for him. Now
God, who created the world for no
other purpoſe, thē the manifeſtation
of his owne glory, might not
leaue that creature without vnderſtanding
of the Godhead, who being
by nature &amp; creatiō the moſt
excellent in this world, was made
for that purpoſe eſpecially aboue
al other, to ſet forth his prayſe and
to call on him. Now how could he
do this, if he knew him not? But (I
think that) ſeeing it is ſaid, that mā
was created in the Image of God, you
wil not deny yt man before his fal,
had much more perfit vnderſtanding
of ye 
               Godhead, thē it is poſsible

for him to haue, till he come to
know euen as he is knowen, but that
by him (you may ſay) this knowledge
was loſt: not loſt, but corrupted
onely, euen as mans will.
For then it ſhould follow that wee
were inferiour to bruit beaſts, who
haue in thē a ſenſible knowledge
meete for that ende whereto they
were created. Furthermore, it is
not poſsible that mans ſin ſhould
fruſtrate the ende which God intended
in his creation, but it is manifeſt,
that man was created to
know and honour the creator. Againe,
ſeeing in Chriſt al things conſiſt,
hee being ordained of the Father
before all worldes, in whom
the world ſhould be both created
and reſtored; it is plaine that this
light of our vnderſtanding both
proceedeth from him, and is reſtored
in him, as it is ſaid, Ioh. 1. He is
that light which lightneth euery man

that commeth into the world, not
onely his choſen with knowledge
of his ſauing trueth, but euen generally
euery man with reaſonable
vnderſtanding, whereby wee
may know whatſoeuer is to be known
of God: &amp; how? euen by the works
of God, as it is plainely concluded,
Rom. 1. 19, 20. Therefore are they
not to bee heard, who hold any
thing without the compaſſe of
Faith, which is without the compaſſe
of Knowledge. For Faith ought
ſo to be grounded on Knowledge,
as Hope is grounded vpon Faith. So
that as Faith, Heb. 11. 1. is ſayd to
be 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               , an euiction or proofe of
things hoped for, though they bee not
ſeene▪
                ſo may I ſay that Knowledge
is the proofe of things which are
beleeued. For Faith is nothing els
but the Concluſion of a particular
Syllogiſme, drawen from the concluſion
of an vniuerſall, which the

knowledge of God had cōcluded,
as it is manifeſt, Iam. 2. 19. &amp; Heb.
11. 3. By conference of which
two places it appeareth, that this
knowledge, of which I ſpeake, this
Hiſtoricall Faith, as to beleeue
that there is one God which made
all things of nought, is onely ſuch
a knowledge, as the deuils &amp; wicked
men haue: but to beleeue, and
haue confidence in this God, is that
particular concluſion, &amp; that faith
which cauſeth vs to haue hope in
his promiſes. Therefore ſaid Chriſt,
Haue fayth in God: that is, ſtriue to
know God, that knowing, you may
haue faith, and beleeue in him.
And wee ſee that in theſe things,
where a bare faith without knowledge
might ſeeme to be moſt required,
becauſe as a man would
thinke, there were no reaſon to be
giuen of them, namely, concerning
the maintenance of this life,

and the reſurrection to the life to
come; both Chriſt and his Apoſtles
vſe no other reaſons, but ſuch as euery
reaſonable man may eaſily
be perſwaded by, though authorities
of Scripture were not wanting
to both purpoſes, as it is manifeſt,
Mat. 6. and 1. Cor 15. yea Paul
at Athens, or whereſoeuer he perſwaded
the worſhip of the true
God among the Gentiles, hee perſwaded
not by authority of Scripture,
which amongſt thē had bene
very weake; but by ſuch argumēts
as they knew to be ſufficient euē in
thēſelues. If theſe things were not
ſo; how thē could the Gentiles which
knew not the Scriptures, he without
excuſe for their ignorance of God?
Therefore I conclude, that there is
nothing which is beleeued, but it
may alſo be knowen. Now knowledge
(we know) is ingendred by
ſuch principles as haue truth in thē,

the which is euident of it ſelfe. So
that by plaine and reaſonable vnderſtanding,
a man may knowe
whatſoeuer he beleeueth. You wil
ſay, To what purpoſe then ſerue
the Scriptures? I anſwere: That
God, infinite in goodneſſe, hath together
with this vnderſtanding
&amp; light of Nature, giuen vs withall
his word, as a greater light whereby
our leſſer lights might become
more ſhining: That he hath giuen
vnto vs not only an inward word,
to wit, our natural vnderſtanding;
but alſo an outward worde, as a
moſt illuſtrious Commētary, both
of declaration and amplification of
that text; whereby we may the better
vnderſtand, whatſoeuer wee
ought to vnderſtand without it.
But how thē commeth it to paſſe,
that all men haue not Faith? And
how is Faith ſayd to bee the gift of
God? The firſt is anſwered, Rom. 1

21. and Ephe. 4. 18 For hardnes of
their heart, who when they knew God,
did not glorifie him as they ought:
therefore their imaginations▪ became
vaine, &amp; their fooliſh heart was ful of
darkenes. And for this cauſe is Faith
alſo ſayd to bee the gift of God.
Firſt, in reſpect of that knowledge
whence it doeth proceede, which
knowledge is his gift. Secondly,
becauſe it is the onely worke of
God, to make that knowledge to
become fruitful, by laying it ſo vnto
mans heart, that the hardneſſe
thereof may bee remoued, that
when wee know God to bee good
and iuſt, we alſo beleeue and worſhip
him as we ought. Thirdly and
moſt eſpecially, becauſe that God
oftentimes pardoning the ignorance
which men haue of himſelfe
and the creature, doth ſo illumine
the heart with 
                  〈◊〉
                
               holy Spirit,
that it is ſuddenly 
                  〈◊〉
                without

any previant knowledge, to
faith and obedience. The trueth
whereof neuertheles doth not any
whit impugne that which I ſay,
That God hath giuen vnto euery man
ſo much vnderſtanding as to know
what he ought to beleeue, and to bee
ſatisfied for the reaſons of his Fayth,
if he could open his eyes to ſee in the
middeſt of what wonderous light hee
were placed. This point is manifeſt
both by many Scripture-authorities,
and by many reaſons which I
omit. But taking this as either
granted, or ſufficiently prooued,
that God hath giuen vs light of vnderſtanding,
whereby to yeeld a reaſon of
the Hope that is in vs; a reaſon I ſay
euen of euery article of our Faith:
let vs with holy reuerence come
vnto the thing in queſtion, and ſee
what reaſon wee haue for our defence.
I will therefore a while forbeare
to vſe the authoritie of holy

Scripture; not that I eſteeme the
waight or euidence of any reaſon
comparable thereto: but onely
perceiuing by that talke I had with
you, that you had read the Scripture,
as one of thoſe whom Peter
noteth, 2. Epiſt. 3. 16. Not intending
to wrangle about your wreſted
interpretations; I wil firſt propone
the euidence of reaſonable
proofe: and afterwards bring in
the aſſent of holy Scripture, that
you may perceiue in what wondrous
cleare light you ſtriue to be
blinde. And becauſe I know not
what your opinion is concerning
God, (for he that denieth the Godhead
of Chriſt, may as well denie the
Godhead abſolutely:) that beeing
one ſteppe toward the queſtion, I
will proceed orderly, and giue you
alſo a reaſon of our faith, concerning
that matter: taking this onely
as granted, which is rife in euery

mans knowledge, that both the
termes of Contradiction, cannot
bee affirmed of the ſame Subiect:
that is, that one and the ſame thing
cannot be both affirmed and denied,
of the ſame Subiect, at one time,
and in the ſame reſpect.
            But firſt, by the Name of God,
know that I meane an Eternall Being,
infinite in goodneſſe, in power, in
wiſedome, in glory, in vertue, and onely
worthie of endleſſe loue and honour.
My reaſon is thus. If there be not
a Being which had no beginning,
then of neceſsitie, that which was
firſt exiſtent or begunne, muſt be a
beginning vnto it ſelfe, by cauſing
of it ſelfe to be, when it was not.
But this is impoſsible, that any
thing ſhould bee a cauſe, and not
bee: for ſo ſhould it both bee and
not be; therefore there is an eternall
Being, which is the beginning,
middle and ende of all things, and

himſelfe without beginning, and
this eternall Beeing wee call God.
My reaſon is plaine to bee vnderſtood;
and remember what I haue
ſaid, that I may goe on.
            Whatſoeuer is without beginning,
is alſo without ending; becauſe
it hath no Superiour which
might bring it to nothing: therefore
God is eternall. Againe, whatſoeuer
comes to nothing, is corrupted
by his contrary; but nothing can
be oppoſite to God, therefore hee is
Eternall. Or elſe I might thus
reaſon.
            Being and Not Being are ſuch
contraries, as one of them cannot
ſpring out of another: for euery
thing, for the preſeruations ſake of
it ſelfe, doth repreſſe and corrupt
the contrary. Seing then that there
is Beeing, which could not poſsibly
raiſe it ſelfe out of Not Being, it followes
that Being had a primacy or

prioritie before Not Beeing: and
therefore of neceſsitie muſt be eternall;
for otherwiſe there was a
time, wherein it might be ſaid, that
Being is Not Being, &amp; ſo Not Being
ſhould haue been firſt, and contradictories
might haue ſtood together:
but both theſe are impoſsible,
therefore there is an eternall
Being; and this eternall Being,
wee call God. Furthermore wee
know, that the greateſt excellencie
or perfection of euery thing, is
in the proximitie or approch thereof
vnto the firſt cauſe. But euery
thing is more excellent in the Being
thereof, then in the Not Being:
therefore Beeing was before Not
Being; and for that cauſe Eternall.
Now Eternitie is an Infinite Continuance:
therefore whatſoeuer is Eternall,
muſt of neceſsitie be Infinite:
and this Infinite Being, we call
God. Moreouer, whatſoeuer hath

Infinite continuance, hath Infinite
Power to continue infinitely; and
this omnipotent or endleſſe Power
we call God.
            
            I might reaſon likewiſe of his
Goodnes, of his Wiſedome, Trueth,
Glory, &amp;c. but one ſhall ſerue in
ſtead of the reſt, and I will take his
Wiſedome for my example, and
proue vnto you, that likewiſe to be
Infinite, and that not onely in exiſtence,
but in action alſo. And
firſt that hee is wiſe; God is moſt
worthy to be ſuch as he is: but if he
were not wiſe, he were not worthy
to bee God: ergo hee is wiſe. Now
marke how theſe depende one on
another. In God is Wiſedome,
which by reaſon of his Infinitie, is
alſo infinite: and by his Eternitie, is
alſo eternal: ſo that there is no time,
wherein it may be ſaid, that this infinite
Wiſdom is not infinitely exerciſed,
for then were it not eternally

infinite. Therefore his wiſedome
is infinite, not in exiſtence
onely, but alſo in action.
            Againe, the wiſedome of God
is ſuch, as hath no defect or imbecillitie
therein. But if it were not
Infinite both in action and in exiſtence,
a man might find defect
therein, and imagine a more Infinite
wiſedome then that is, but
this is impoſsible. So might I conclude
of all the other Dignities of
God, but I haſte to the purpoſe, and
I thinke that you will not vnwillingly
graunt what I haue ſaid, but
vnderſtand the reſt. All the Dignities
of God beeing actuated or
brought into working, require of
neceſsitie an Infinite Obiect,
whereon they worke, becauſe they
thēſelues are Infinite: but nothing
can be Infinite, but God alone, therfore
it followeth that theſe Dignities
are obiected or exerciſed in

               God alone. And this is that Eternal
Sonne, begottē before the worlds,
in whome the Father reſteth: or as
the Prophet ſpeaketh, His beloued,
in whome his ſoule delighteth; which
cannot be applyed to any creature,
without which, God is happy in him
ſelfe: therefore ſaith the Apoſtle,
that in him dwelleth the Godhead bodily.
How is that? not in his manly
body eternally; for his humane body
tooke beginning of the fleſh of
the Virgin, when the fulnes of time
came, but yet bodily, that is, as eſſentially,
or ſubſtantially, as the body
of a man is ſubſtantiall to the
man. For euery Dignity of God being
infinite in action (as was proued)
muſt of neceſsitie produce
ſuch as it ſelfe is. As for example;
the Wiſdome of God or his Infinite
Vnderſtanding, muſt haue an Infinite
intelligible or vnderſtandable
obiect, which is produced

thereby, by an infinite vnderſtanding.
So that ye muſt know of neceſsitie,
and marke three Termes,
as I will a while call them: the
Terme from whence: the Terme
whereto, or wherein: and the
middle Terme betweene them. I
will for your capacitie, which I
know not to bee much exerciſed in
theſe matters, make a compariſon
meet for your vnderſtanding.
            When the minde or vnderſtanding
of a man conceiueth any vnderſtandable
obiect, then is (you
know) firſt the vnderſtanding in
the minde it ſelfe, ſecondly the obiect
vnderſtood, and thirdly, the
diſcourſe or vnderſtanding, whereby
that obiect is apprehended.
            Now giue me leaue to tell you,
what differences you muſt make,
betweene the vnderſtanding of
God, and the vnderſtanding of
man in this compariſon.
            
               
Firſt, the minde of man beeing
finite, the vnderſtanding is not able
to view al that which can be vnderſtood
thereby at one time, or with
one action of vnderſtanding, but
muſt conceiue of one thing after another:
whereas the vnderſtanding
and wiſedome of God is ſuch, as at
one ſight ſeeth himſelfe, and euery
thing els, paſt, preſent, and to come;
and this not once onely, but euen
continually, becauſe it is eternally
infinite.
            Secondly, the intendement of
man worketh nothing in the thing
conceiued, to make it either to be,
if it be a meere conceit, or to be other
then it is, if it be exiſtent: but
the vnderſtanding of God, is by
reaſon of his power ſo actiue, as that
it cauſeth that wherein it is exerciſed,
both to be, and that according
to his maner of apprehenſion or
vnderſtanding of it: which vnderſtanding

is by his Infinitie ſo infinite,
and by his Eternitie ſo continuall,
as that of neceſsitie there
muſt bee a ſubſiſtence or a perſon,
wherein it muſt be exerciſed, which
muſt alſo be Infinite and Eternall.
And this is that glorious Sonne of
God, who is thus begotten or produced
eternally, both before the
world was, euen as hee is now, and
ſhall not ceaſe to be produced after
the world ſhall ceaſe eternally.
            Thus you ſee two of the termes
ſpoken of: from whence, &amp; wherein:
now you muſt know the middle
terme betweene them. The terme
whence, is the Wiſedome intelligent,
God the Father. The terme
wherein, is the Wiſedome intelligible,
God the Sonne. The middle
terme is, ipſum intelligere, which in
my Compariſon I called, The diſcomſe
it ſelfe, which alſo in this muſt
needs bee Infinite. For an Infinite

intelligible, cannot bee conceiued
of an Infinite intelligent, but by an
Infinite intelligere; and this is that
Holy Ghoſt, which as you may eaſily
vnderſtand, muſt of neceſsitie proceede
from both the Father and the
Sonne, and be alſo infinite and eternall,
and therefore God. Now becauſe
they are all Infinite, and of
Infinite, eſſentially there can
bee but one: therefore are theſe
three in Eſſence or Being, one, but in
Subſiſtence or cleare diſtinction of
Perſons, three.
            Vnderſtande my compariſon
which I made: I will yet cleare the
matter further for your conceyuing.
            If you take in a myrrour, the
light of the Sunne, and reflect it
directly thereon againe, in the
Sunne it is one, in the glaſſe another,
and yet the reflection
of the beames, is alſo a

third, but for all this, there is but
one nature and worde of light,
which comprehends al three: ſo is it
in this Tri-Vnitie of which I ſpeake.
My leiſure ſerues me not to dilate
theſe things, but I hope you are
able to vnderſtand what I ſay,
therefore I will proceed. It is ſaid,
that Powers are knowne by their
actions, and actions are limitted by
their obiects. I know the meaning
of it, and it is not vnfitte in this
place. But to my reaſon: The Power
of God is infinite, and by his infinite
wiſedome hee knoweth it to
be infinite: but God could not know
that his Power were infinite, vnleſſe
he were able thereby to bring
forth an infinite action; and euery
infinite action muſt of neceſsitie be
exerciſed in an infinite ſubiect.
(For whatſoeuer is receiued, is receiued
according to the capacitie of
the receiuer:) therefore there is an

infinite ſubiect, wherein the power
of God is exerciſed: that is the
Sonne of whom I ſpeake. And here
againe behold the Tri-Vnitie; an infinite
power the Father; an infinite
action the Holy Ghoſt; an infinite ſubiect
the glorious Sonne; all three one
infinite Being. Returne to your
compariſon.
            As the vnderſtanding of man
could no way know his owne power,
but by his actions, neither can
there be any actions of vnderſtanding,
where there is nothing to be
vnderſtood, no more is it poſsible
to bee in the Deitie. Now vnderſtand
that, as I haue reaſoned from
the Wiſedome and Power of God: ſo
might I reaſon from all his other
Dignities: ſo that for one reaſon
which I haue brought. I might
haue brought you fiftie. But I ſhew
you the way, if you be guided by
the Spirit of Trueth, how you may

ſtrengthen your ſelfe in the way
of Trueth: therefore I wil goe on,
and ſhew you yet more plainely by
more familiar reaſons.
            An Infinite power is not more
weake then a finite: but euery finite
creature which we can caſt our
eies vnto, doth by nature produce
his like, as much as in it is; as a man
begetteth a man; trees bring forth
ſeed, whereof their like in nature
may ſpring, and in likewiſe euery
other thing. Therefore the Infinite
Power of God begetteth his
like alſo, which is the Sonne, the image
of the inuiſible God, the firſt begotten
of euery creature, Col. 1. 15.
But none can bee like vnto God in
his Being, who is not very God:
therefore Chriſt the onely begotten of
the Father is alſo very God.
            
            Maruel not, that I make this argument
from the creature to the
Creator; for in this very point of

the Power &amp; Godhead, the Holy ghoſt
himſelfe teacheth me to reaſon of
the inuiſible things of God▪ by the things
viſible, Rom. 1. 20. And hereby alſo
learne to helpe your ignorance,
and put away your wonder, how
God ſhould bee one, and yet three.
See you not how the vnderſtanding?
the Sun-light alſo, is one in
nature, and yet three in euident
and cleare diſtinction? though in ſo
baſe and imperfect order, as that
which is aboue all perfection, is
poſsible to be aboue it.
            And further, ſee you not in euerie
thing a bodie, a ſpirite and a
life, which is the knot betweene
them?
            Or rather, ſee you not how the
very bodily compoſition is both
one, and three? one body which is
vnited of three bodies? that is,
earth, water, and ayre, or oyle,
which yet again in the root of their

nature are but one. For oyle is but
a due mixture of water and earth,
meanely fixt, and meanely volatil;
and earth is but fixed water; ſo that
water which is but one, is the root
of the three: as it is manifeſt,
Geneſis 1. and 2. Pet. 3. 5. They
which vnderſtand the rules of Pyronomy,
know what I ſay; and if
you vnderſtand me wel, you would
confeſſe, that not onely this inſtance
which I haue brought, of
earth, water and ayre; but euen the
whole frame of Nature did proclaime
the Trinitie in the Vnitie. You
would, I ſay, confeſſe, that whatſoeuer
may be knowne of God, is manifeſted
in the creature. If I ſhould
here tell you, how the Heauen, the
Earth, &amp; the Deepe, Gen. 1. might
be vnderſtood myſtically, and the
Analogie betweene the Creator and
the creature therein: and then tell
you, what Let the earth bring forth

liuing ſoule, might meane, and compare
it with that place, That which
was made in him was life; and then
particularly for man, The Lord God
alſo made the man of the duſt of the
earth, and tell you, that it was ſo neceſſary,
becauſe that Chriſt is Terra

                     •••
                  enti
                     ••…
                  : and inforce an argument
to proue the Tri-Vnitie, by
that treble repetition of the man
made in the image of God; comparing
it with that place, 1. Cor. 11. 3.
and 7. If I ſhould then tell you,
that it was neceſſarie that the Sonne
of God muſt become fleſh, as well
that the infinite Iuſtice of God might
be actuated in him, which could not
bee actuated in him beeing onely
GOD: as for many other reaſons,
both from the Iuſtice, and Mercie,
and Wiſedome of GOD, though
to a well ſighted vnderſtanding I
might ſeeme to haue layd a precious
foundation of Philoſophie diuine

and natural: yet to you I might
rather ſeeme perhaps to haue proponed
Cabaliſticall dreames, then
any ſound argument to the thing in
queſtion.
            Yet this will I tell you, and
holde it for good Diuinitie: that
the mayne drift and ſcope of the
whole Scripture, is to ſhew the Creation
of all things in Chriſt, through
him and for him: and the reſtoring
of the whole creature in man by him:
That in al things he might haue the preeminence,
Col. 1. Neyther doth this
any whit derogate from the honour
of the Father.
            For firſt, It hath pleaſed the Father,
that in him ſhould all fulneſſe
dwell: and beſides, it is an honour
aboue all honours vnto the Father,
to be the Father of ſo glorious a
Sonne.
            
            Therefore is this world and all the
things therein, created to the Image

of Chriſt, to expreſſe his glory, euen
as he is the expreſſed Image and glory of
the Father. And here is the worlds
Eternitie, which had in Chriſt an eternall
Being; according to that
his Name, Eſay. 9. 6. The Father of
Eternitie.
            
            Here are thoſe ſeparate Ideas,
about which Plato and Ariſtotle
could neuer agree, and which neyther
both of them, nor many of
their followers did perfectly vnderſtand:
not that they might not by
the frame of nature, and the wiſedome
which GOD had giuen to
man, be vnderſtood.
            For is not this world as a booke
wherein wee may reade and vnderſtand
by the created trueths, what is
the Trueth which is increated? but
all true knowledge is the gift of
GOD.
            Therefore wreſt not that place,
Coloſſ. 2. 8. againſt the Chriſtian

ſearch after the knowledge of Nature,
whereby aboue all other humane
knowledges a man is brought
to know GOD, and to honour
him as he ought: but rather be ſory,
that your knowledge of Nature
is no more. For that will I tell you,
to teach you to know your ſelfe,
that there is nothing in the creature,
which may be knowne, (and
all may bee knowne that is in the
creature) but man ought to know
it, and to glorifie the Creator thereby.
And this great labour hath GOD
giuen to men, that knowing how
ſhort they are of that they ought
to be, they might bee humbled thereby,
Pſal. 1. 11. Eccles. 1. 13. And
why ought this to ſeeme ſtrange?
doth not God require that perfectiō
at mans hand wherein he did create
him? and was he not created with
perfect diſcourſe to know the creature,
that hee might therein behold

the Creator, and ſo glorifie his wondrous
Power and goodneſſe? But this
queſtion would draw mee from the
queſtion in hand: &amp; therefore I wil
briefly adde one reaſon more: and
becauſe my leiſure is little, I will be
as ſhort as I can: but I pray you lend
mee your eare; for it is hard in
Engliſh, an inartificiall language,
to expreſſe my mind: but becauſe
you told me, you could a little Latine,
I will be bold here and there,
to vſe a word: my reaſon is thus.
The whole and perfect nature of a
Principle or Beginning is in God,
who is alone the beginner of all
things. Now a Principle is of three
ſortes, whereof euery one is ſo
clearely diſtinct from another, as
that one cannot poſsibly be that other:
therefore in the Vnitie of the
Deitie there is alſo ſuch cleare diſtinction
into a Trinitie, as that one
diſtinct cannot poſsibly be that other,

from which hee is diſtinguiſhed,
yet in the Vnitie of eſſence they
are all one. The differences of a
Beginning ſtand thus; It is either
Principium principians, non principiatum;
that is, a beginning, which is
a Beginner vnto another; yet hath
not his beginning from another,
leſt there ſhould be a proceſſe into
Infinitie a parte ante: this is God the
Father, to whom it is peculiar to beget
the Sonne, yet is himſelfe neyther
made▪ nor created, nor begotten
of any other.
            Secondly, there is Principium
principiatum principians; to witte,
a Beginning which hath his beginning
of another, and is alſo a
beginning to another, leſt there
ſhould be any defect or imbecillitie
in the Beginning: and this is the
Euerlaſting Sonne, very God of very
God, begotten of the ſubſtance of
his Father alone before thē worlds,

neither made nor created.
            Thirdly, there is Principium principiatum
non principians; that is, a Beginning,
which is alſo begun, but
is not a beginner vnto another: leſt
there ſhould be a proceſſe into Infinitie
a parte poſt: and this is the
Holy Ghoſt, who proceedeth from
the very ſubſtance and Being of the
Father and the Sonne, and is with
them one GOD coeternall and
coequall. But you will ſay, Is not
the Holy Ghoſt a Beginner vnto any
other? how is he then the Authour
of our conſolation? and how is hee
ſaid to leade vs into all trueth, &amp;c?
Vnderſtand what I meane: Hee is
not a Beginner vnto any other of
the ſame Infinite Eſſence or Being
with himſelfe. For the beginnings
which I ſpake of before, are in ye Eſſence
of God alone now our ſpiritual
conſolation, whereof the Holy Ghoſt
is ſaid to be the Beginner, is but an

or effluence from that
Being, which he himſelfe is; as the
light of the Sunne doth illuminate
euery bright body expoſed to his
light, and yet imparteth not his being
thereto. You will againe obiect,
that Eternitie hath no beginning
nor ending: how then can
Chriſt be both eternall and begun?
and how againe can he be equall to
the Father, whereas hee beeing begotten
of the Father, the Father hath
a prioritie before him? I anſwere,
that this beginning is none other,
then that production or begetting,
which I before declared, to haue
been heretofore none other, then
it is now and ſhall be eternally: as
the Sunne hath brought forth light
ſince his creation, and ſhall ſtill
bring forth light till the worlds diſſolution.
For this action of GOD,
whereby hee begetteth his Sonne, is
not a tranſeant action, to cauſe a

paſsion in the ſubiect, and a repaſsion
in the agent, for in ſuch the
ſubiect of neceſsitie ſhould haue
been exiſtent before the action; but
this action is immanent, and therefore
of neceſsitie of the ſame nature
with the agent; which agent
becauſe it is eternall, therefore the
production is alſo eternal, and conſequently
the product, and ſo of neceſsitie
very GOD. But you muſt
euer remember what difference I
made betweene the action of God,
infinite in power, &amp; therefore able
to actuate the obiect; and the immanent
actions of our minde. Now
for the Prioritie or Poſterioritie,
you may obiect. I graunt there is
Prioritie among the perſons of the
Godhead; but of what kinde? not
of Being; for their Eſſence is one,
and therein is none afore or after
another, neither is any one of the
Trinitie more or leſſe God then another:

not of time; for they are all
one Eternitie: not of dignitie, for
they are all one Infinitie: and the
Sonne himſelfe being very God, thinketh
it no robberie to bee equall with
God.
            
            But yet there is Prioritie, and that
of order onely; for the Father is in
order before the Sonne, becauſe the
Sonne is begotten of the Father: and
the Sonne likewiſe is before the Holy
Ghoſt, becauſe the Holy Ghoſt is the
mutuall loue betweene the Father
and the Sonne: and ſo proceeding
from them both.
            I will make a compariſon vnmeet
for the matter of which I ſpeake; for
to whom ſhall wee aſsimulate the
Higheſt? but yet meete to helpe your
vnderſtanding. When a man doth
dreame and imagine things which
are not, there is, you know, the phantaſie,
the phantaſme or thing imagined
or dreamed, and the phanſying

or working of the phantaſie about
that obiect. Now theſe three are all
of one nature, and are one after another
onely in order, and not in
time.
            For the particular phantaſie
of ſuch an obiect, is before the obiect,
and makes it to haue an intentionall
being; then the obiect being,
the diſcourſe of the phantaſie followeth
in order, which neuertheleſſe was
in time as ſoone as it, obſeruing euer
the cautions that are to bee obſerued.
            Thus haue I very briefly ſhowne
not many reaſons, but rather how
that many reaſons may bee ſhowen
for this Chriſtian aſſertion: yet haue
I ſhowen ynough to perſwade any
reaſonable man, to yeelde meekely
vnto the trueth of that doctrine,
which is ſo euident both in the
booke of GOD, and in euerie
faithfull and true Chriſtian mans

confeſsion, and according to that
diſcourſe which is euident to euery
mans vnderſtanding. Now giue me
leaue to ſpeake a little to thoſe arguments
which haue throwen the
moſt learned of the Iewes head-long
to the feet of Chriſt, to make
thē acknowledge that the Meſsiab
muſt be both God and man. I will not
herein doe any thing contrary to
that, which in the beginning I proteſted,
that is, not to compel you by
authoritie of Scripture, but to intreate
you by reaſonable perſwaſion,
to encline your eare to the
trueth. But becauſe I may not
without iniurie to the cauſe, leaue
altogether out ſuch manifeſt
proofe, and without iniurie alſo to
your ſelfe, who might thinke that
I went about to ſophiſticate a true
ſeeming vntrueth, which would not
abide the touch: I will onely intend
my finger to ſome very few, of many

thouſandes of axiomes of the
Scripture for this purpoſe, &amp; leaue
you to make the concluſion by your
ſelfe, hoping that the Iewes example
may prouoke you to follow
them, ſo farre forth as they haue followed
the trueth. Exod. 13. 21, it
is ſaid, The Lord went before thē, &amp;c.
Chap. 14. 19. The Angel of God,
which went before them, remoued:
where Chriſt the Angell of the Couenant,
is called The Lord Iehouah.
Againe, Exod. 15. 3. The Lorde is a
man of warre, his name is Iehouah:
therefore Chriſt is God and man:
who by his conflict vpon the croſſe,
triumphed ouer Death and Hell, as
it is written in the Goſpell, the booke
of the warres of the Lord. Againe,
Eſay. 9. 6. Vnto vs a childe is borne,
there is his Manhood: and vnto vs a
Sonne is given, and they ſhall call his
name, The mightie God. And Eſay 35.
verſ. 4. Your God will come and ſaue

you. Ierem. 23. 5. &amp;c. I will rayſe vp
vnto Dauid a righteous branch and a
King ſhal raigne▪ and this is the Name
whereby they ſhall call him, The Lord
our righteouſneſſe. And Ierem. 33.
verſ. 16. Iudah shall be ſaued, and be
that shall ſaue her, is the Lorde our
righteouſneſſe. Where the name vſed,
is that great Name 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               Iehouah,
which is neuer giuen to any
creature. Zach. 9. 9. proues him
God and man. What ſhall I cyte
vnto you that of the ſecond Pſlam?
Thou art my Sonne, this day haue I begotten
thee: which place with many
more, is brought in the Epiſtle to the
Hebrewes, to this purpoſe, which
is your queſtion.
            Theſe authorities the Thalmadiſts,
who ſticke onely to the killing
letter and apparant ſenſe of the
law, hold ſufficient to put this matter
out of doubt.
            Now, if leauing this outward ſenſe

of the Scripture, we ſhould deſire
to know what is the quickning ſpirit
thereof, and ſhould ranſacke
the treaſuries of the Cabaliſts, remembring
that place of our Sauiour,
Matth. 5. 18. One iod, or tittle
of the Law shall not paſſe, till all bee
fulfilled; and ſhould examine the
queſtion by the letters and pricks
of the Scripture, wee ſhould more
eaſily find an entrance, then an end
thereto. Yet for a taſte take only ye
               
firſt 3. words of the Law, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
               breshith, bará, elohim: which
may not vnfitly be thus turned: In
the beginning, they the mighty God created.
And of that againe, take the
firſt 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               bresbith, and ſee what
it may ſignifie by that part of the
Cabala which they call Notariacon,

                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               b. the firſt letter of ben, ſignifieth
the Sonne: 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               r. the firſt of ruach, ſignifies
the Holy Ghoſt: 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               n a. the beginning
of av. is ye Father: 
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   s. the firſt of

Sabbath importeth reſt: 
                  ••…
                the beginning
of the ineffable name of
God 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                and not there onely, but
euen of it ſelfe it imports the Deitie.
For we conſider of things not obuious
to our ſenſes and vnderſtanding,
as if they were not: and therefore
this leaſt of all the letters, neereſt
vnto nothing, doth ſignifie
GOD. 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . th. the firſt of Ta. or
Thom. is conſtrued a Cloſet or a
Depth. Which conſtruction if you
put together, according to the rules
of that excellent Grammar of Diuinitie,
with reference to that which
followes, may import thus much.
The Word, the Spirit, and the Father,
reſting eternally in the Cloſet, or
vnconceiueable abyſſe, or as Paul
calls it, the inacceſsible light of the
infinite Deitie, manifeſted their almighty
power in creating the heauē
and the earth. Neither is it without
a great myſterie that the Son is here

put in the firſt place: for In the beginning
was the word: becauſe the
chiefe honour both of the Creation,
and reſtauration of the world is
giuen vnto Chriſt, as the Apoſtle
doth comment vpon this text, Coloſſ.
1. And in another place, In him
is all the treaſure both of the wiſedome
and knowledge of God. As Pſal. 104.
verſ. 24. In wiſedome haſt thou made
them all. For in Chriſt were al things
together one infinite wiſedome, till
in the Creation he made them ſeuerall,
according to their diſtinct
Ideas. Therefore ſaith the Apoſtle,
He ſuſtayneth euery thing by his powerfull
word: that is, the Sonne: and
elſewhere, In him (Chriſt) wee liue
and moue (after the Creation) and
haue our Being (before the Creation.)
And for this cauſe doth Iohn begin
the law of mercie and grace, in the
very ſame words wherewith Moſes
began the law of Iuſtice and condemnation:

               In the beginning. For
we know nothing of God, neyther
of iuſtice, nor of mercie, &amp;c. but
onely by Chriſt; as he ſaith, No man
knoweth the Father, but the Son, and
he to whom the Sonne wil reueile him.
And in another place, No man commeth
to the Father, but by me. Now,
the Holy Ghoſt is put in the ſecond
place, becauſe hee is the mutuall
loue of the Father and the Sonne,
and as I may ſay, the inſtrument of
their actions, both in manent, and
tranſeunt.
            Go forward now, if you will, to
the next word, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               bará; you ſee, it
affords the ſame argument for the
Tri-Vnitie, by the three letters before
explained, and the number
which is the ſingular.
            Thinke not this a fancie, neither
reproch the diuine Cabala, as the
ignorant Sophiſters vſe to doe, not
knowing how aboue all other

knowledges, it doth aduance a
mans meditation on high.
            And to the preſent purpoſe, they
which know any thing in the holy
language, know that this ſentence
can no way agree in Grammatical
conſtruction, vnleſſe the ſingular
verb 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               bará, be thus made plurall,
that it may haue concordance with
the plurall 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               Elohim.
            
            You will aske, why theſe letters,

                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                  . b. r. a. 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . a. are twice put, ſeeing
in this preciſeneſſe, no ſuch ſuperfluitie
ſhould haue needed.
            I tell you, that it is not done, but
to intimate vnto vs a moſt high
myſterie.
            For in the firſt place it imports
that Eternall and Infinite Being of
the Father, the Sonne, and the Holy
Ghoſt, which they had before the
worlds in their endleſſe glorie &amp; felicitie,
in that ſilence of the Deitie, in
that ſuper-ſupreme Entity which is

vnto the Godhead, perfect aboue perfection,
without any reſpect vnto
the creature, it imports that Infinitie,
that Eternitie, that Power, that
Wiſedome, which is aboue all
things, and giues vnto it ſelfe, to be
ſuch as it is: that Nothing, as the diuine
Areopagite ſeemes to ſpeake,
which is before and aboue al things,
that may be ſpoken or thought,
without any reſpect of any emanation,
or effluence whatſoeuer. And
therefore followes that letter of reſt

                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                that of vnitie, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . and that of perfection.

                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . Now in the ſecond place,
it ſignifies the Deitie, as exerciſed in
the creature: and therefore followes
that Epithyte Elohim, which ſhewes
that emanation of Power or
Strength; and is ſometimes giuen
vnto the creatures, Angels, and
men. It were an endleſſe thing, to
ſpeake that of theſe myſteries, which
may be ſpoken, neither can I; For

               the Law of the Lord is perfect, and man
is full of weakeneſſe. I haue ſaid ſo
much as I thinke meete concerning
the Tri-Vnitie.
            
            Now a word to that point, that
Chriſt is GOD: which although it
appeare ſufficiently in the Tri-Vnity
before proued, by this anagogicall
doctrine: yet to that ſecond perſon
in particular, is that which followeth.
Eſay 7. 14, it is ſaid of Chriſt,
that his name ſhould bee called Immanuel;
but in the hiſtorie of the
Goſpell, in Matthew and Luke, both
before his Conception, and at his
Circumciſion, he is called Ieſus. It
is therefore meete that you know,
how Ieſus is Immanuel or God with
vs. The writing of the Name of
IESVS is thus 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               Ihſuh,
though according to the rules of the
pronunciation of that tongue, Ieſu,
and according to the ancient abbreuiation
following the Hebrue orthography

IHTS. In which Name
you ſee, are al the letters of the greateſt
ineffable Name of God, 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               Iehouah;
with ye
                interpoſition of that
letter of reſt 
                  
                     〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                   s. for then was God reconciled
to the world; then was euerlaſting
righteouſneſſe brought
in, when the Word became fleſh.
            This is that glorious Name, of
which God ſpake by the Prophet,
Behold, I will make my Name new in
the earth. For you ſee how of 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               
is made, 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                that is, IESVS.
            
            This is that Name, which is
meet for the Sonne of GOD alone,
and cannot bee giuen to any creature,
becauſe it is a Name of the
DEITIE, as it is Hebr. 1. It
is that Name, which is aboue all
names: in which the Angels and
the righteous ſoules triumph; at
which the powers of Hell are agaſt
and tremble; to which the whole
creature yeeldeth meek obedience.
            
               
               This is that Name, of which our
Lord ſpake, Father, I haue manifeſted
thy Name vnto men, the Father

                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               the Sonne 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               .
            For ſo long as the myſterie of
the Incarnation of God was hidde, ſo
long that Name remained vnſoundable:
but when the Word became
fleſh, and dwelt amongſt
men, ſo that the myſterie was reueiled;
then the Name, which was
before not to be pronounced, was
lawfully pronounceable. That as
the Word of life was to bee ſeene with
eyes, and handled with handes; ſo
that glorious Name might alſo be
beaten betweene our lippes and
teeth; and this by the interpoſition
of that letter of reſt. The Iewes
knowing this reaſon of this great
myſterie, &amp; moued with the reuerence
thereof, durſt neuer pronounce
that Name 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                but in
ſtead thereof, Adonai or Elohim.
            
            
               
Let it not trouble you, that Iudah
the ſonne of Iacob was called by ſuch
a name, as had theſe foure letters
therein, with the addition of 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               d,
thus 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               Iehudah: but rather
wonder and learne, how by theſe ſacramentes
the children of GOD
before the Incarnation, exerciſed
their faith, ſaluted the promiſes afarre
off, and ſaw that our Lord ſhould enter
into our earthly tabernacle, by
the doore of Iudahs fleſh; for ſo
much the letter 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               Daleth importeth.
To which myſterie the heauenly
Poet alluding, triumphed with that
double ioy, Pſal. 24. Lift vp your
heads yee gates, and be ye lift vp yee euerlaſting
doores, &amp;c. foreſeeing the
deſcenſion of GOD the Sonne, by
the gate of our fleſh, and the aſcenſion
of our fleſh by Chriſt, into the
heauenly places: both which he celebrated
by that repetition. Compare
with this place, Gen. 39. 35.

and 49. 8. 9. 10. 11. 12. and Reuelat.
5. 5. and other places as you ſhal
reade, and vnderſtand them: and
with all conſider, how the ancient
Fathers haue prided themſelues with
the ſeuerall letters of this Name, to
keepe in remembrance by their
owne names, a thing neuer to bee
forgotten, The Incarnation of our
Lord. As Abram aſſumed h. 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                and
was called Abraham. Oſhea tooke
i. and was called Ioſhua, as you
know. Neyther againe let it trouble
you, that ſome do write this name
thus 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . ISV, becauſe (ſay they)
the letter 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               s. turned vpward 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                is as
much as the double he 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                omitted.
I know no reaſon for this, but many
authorities againſt it, as you may
know by that which is and ſhall be
ſaid, though I let paſſe a very great
number. Now conſider the name
in euery letter, and ſee what cloudes
of witneſſes there are, that Chriſt is

               God and man: and learne by the
Name it ſelfe, how Chriſt is the Character
or ingraued Image of the perſon
or ſubſiſtence of the Father, Hebrewes
1. 13.
            
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                
               i. Is the Crowne or Diademe
of the ineffable Name of
GOD, and ſignifies the Godhead.
            
            
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . u. Pretends the Tree of life:
for it is a thing much noted among
the learned of the Hebrue tongue,
that this letter is neuer put radically
in any naturall Hebrue word, either
in the beginning or end thereof,
but is as the Tree of life, in the
middeſt of the Paradiſe of God.
            The double letter h. 
               
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . ſignifieth,
that Chriſt, concerning his Deitie,
is eſſentially vnited to the Humanitie;
and concerning his Humanitie,
vnited alſo eſſentially to
the Deitie; and that by the Holy
Ghoſt. For 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . h. is a ſpirit or

breath: therefore is Chriſt in himſelfe,
or in reſpect of his Deitie, the
ſuperiour Wiſedome of the Father,
and the Sonne of GOD, not made,
but begotten. Prou. 8. 22. In the
creature, or with reſpect of his Humanitie,
the inferiour wiſedome of
GOD; not begotten, but made,
and created, Ecclus. 24. 11. 12.
            Now the letter 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . s. hath many
things therein to bee conſidered.
            For you may not thinke, that it
was taken by chaunce into this
Name; but for the Notory, and for
the Geometrie.
            
            For the Notory, I haue obſerued
that the Theologians, both of the
old and new Teſtament, haue celebrated
thereby; firſt, the reſt or
dwelling of the Godhead in him, as
Eſay. 42. verſ. 1. and 
                  •
               o. 1. verſ. 33.
Then the reſt, or 
                  •
               ie all beeing
of the world in Chriſt before the

creation: and the reſtoring of the
world by his ſuffering: wherein the
iuſtice of God reſted, or came to a period,
as Eſay. 53. 11. He ſhall ſee the
trauell of his ſoule, and be ſatisfied.
Laſtly, that great Iubile or Sabbath of
Sabbaths in the world to come, when
all the creature ſhall reſt from corruption.
Secondly, they learned
thereby, the euerlaſting Anointing
of Chriſt to bee our King, our Prieſt
and our Prophet. For 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                is the head
of 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                which is to anoint. Hitherto
belongs that of the 45. Pſal. Thou
art anointed with the oyle of gladneſſe
aboue thy fellowes. And in particular;
I have found Dauid (or my beloued)
ſeruant, with my holy oyle haue
I anointed him: that for his Kingdome.
Dan. 9. 24, ſpeakes of his
Prieſthood: To finiſh the wickedneſſe,
to ſeale vp the ſinnes, &amp;c. and to ancint
the moſt Holy. Eſay. 61. of his
Prophecie; Therefore hath the Lord anointed

mee, hee hath ſent mee to
preach, &amp;c. For this cauſe was there
no Anointing in the old Teſtament,
but typicall, as a ſhadow of the good
things that were to come; ſo that
when He came, all theſe anoyntings
ceaſed; both of the Leuiticall
Prieſthood, for Thou art a Prieſt for
euer. Heb. 7: and of the Kingdome;
for Hee ſhall raigne ouer the houſe of
Iacob for euer: Luk. 1. 33. And for
his Prophecie he ſaith, Whatſoeuer I
haue heard of my Father, I haue made
knowen vnto you. The whole ſcope of
the new Teſtament is to this effect.
            Now the Geometrie hath alſo many
myſteries: firſt, it is one ſemicircle
with three branches; the myſterie
of the Trinitie in the Vnitie: all whoſe
dignities of Vertue and Power, &amp;c.
are coequall in all, and in euery perſon,
intirely, and indiuiſibly; and
therefore in our Lord alſo: according
to that ſaying of the Angell, The

holy Ghoſt ſhall come vpon thee, and
the power of the moſt High ſhall euerſhadow
thee; therefore alſo that holy
thing which ſhall be borne of thee, ſhall
be called the SONNE of GOD.
            
            Shall I tell you what Lectures
the Diuines haue made vpon the
text of this letter: Z
                  •
               ch. 11. 13, did
reade herein that goodly price, at
which the wicked Iewes did value
him. For 
                  •
               . i. in the Hebrue Arithmeticke
is tenne; ſo the three
tennes in the triple Crowne of this
letter, are the thirtie pieces of ſiluer,
which the traytour tooke to betray
that precious blood, which was too
deare a raunſome for the whole
world.
            And one in another place ſaid;
They haue ſold the Iuſt for ſiluer.
            
            Conſider the letter and euerie
part thereof. 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                This inferiour
ſemicircle is the creature, the earthly
Paradiſe, in the middeſt of which

is the Tree of life. And that thus the
letter vau
                     •
                  
                is one part, and ſignifies
in that tongue, a nayle, if you will,
that nayle, that pierced his tender
handes and his beauteous feete, to
which if you adde the iod reuerſed,
            you may well perceiue the figure
of the whole Croſſe, that Tree of life,
which bare that heauenly fruite;
that ſpirituall food, whereof Adam
and his faithfull children, which ouercome,
may cate and liue for euer.
Reuel. 2. 7.
            Thus you may ſee, how the
Word became fleſh, and dwelt among
vs. You may ſee that riddle of the
Angel to Eſdras, 2. Booke, chap. 5.
verſ. 37. expounded: The image of
that Word, from which, and whereto,
the bookes of both the Teſtaments
do found.
            You may ſee what confidence
wee may haue in that promiſe
of Chriſt, who in the dayes of his

fleſh ſaid, Whatſoeuer you ſhall aske
the Father in my name, hee will giue is
you, Ioh. 16. 23 But after his Aſcenſion,
the myracles that are to bee
done in that Name, are more ſtupē
               dious,
Mark. 16. 17. And againe,
He that beleeueth in me, greater workes
then theſe ſhal he do, for I goe to the Father.
Beholde the myſterie of it,
cauſe it to aſcend, and deſcribe that
circle, whoſe center is euery where,
whoſe circumference is no where. 
                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               .
Now are the ſuperior and inferior
conduit-pipes ſoudered together,
(as the Hebrues ſpeake) now the
higher influences, the Spirit and
Graces of God are not giuen by meaſure:
and the refluences ſo great, as
that Whoſoeuer beleeueth, out of his
bellie ſhall ariſe fountaine: of liuing
water, ſpringing vp vnto eternall life.
O glorious Name! O ſacred Myſterie!
by which you may wel perceiue,
that there is greater Vnitie betweene

the Deitie and the Humanitie, then
by any wordes of Contiguitie, or
Continuitie, may bee expreſſed.
You may well perceiue, how according
to that place of the 89.
Pſalme, He the firſt borne; or as Iohn
ſaith, Chap. 1. The onely begotten of
the Father, is made higher then the
Kings of the earth. Here is our righteouſneſſe,
our ſanctification, and
redemption complete: here is our adoption
and reward: our conſolation,
our life, and religion: our reuerence,
and our feare: yet our ioy and boldneſſe:
all in all: The preſence of God. I
may not ſay what experience hath
taught mee, by this magnificent
and admirable Name; neyther am
I able to giue due honour thereunto.
My thoughts are ſwallowed vp,
when I conſider the other great
myſteries which this one letter
doth import: the myſterie of the
triple world; the myſterie of mercy

and of Iuſtice; of Election, and
Reprobation; of that great Iubile,
or Sabbath of Sabbaths, when that
which is aboue, ſhal again deſcend,
to reſtore the creature from corruption
and change, into that nimietie
or exceſſe of Goodnes, wherein
it was created. But theſe things
are therefore here to bee omitted,
becauſe the diſcourſe thereof were
long, and becauſe they are rather
conſequents, then premiſes to the
queſtion. To tell you at once, &amp; to
make an end of this argument: The
whole Nation of the learned Iewes
confeſſe, that the Meſsiha ſhould
bee called by this great Name:

                  〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
               . To which purpoſe, there
are, beſides theſe which haue been
brought, many places of Scripture,
which in the Hebrue veritie are
moſt direct, though by our tranſlations
they might ſeeme ſomewhat
harſh. They hold, I ſay, that Hee

muſt be both God and Man: and in
a word, there is nothing which wee
Chriſtians doe affirme concerning
our Lord, but the euidence of Scripture
doth compell them to confeſſe
it. Onely they differ in this, from
vs; whether This Ieſus be that Chriſt
that ſhould come into the worlde;
though this alſo be a thing not queſtionable,
as you may learne of Daniel
9. verſ. 24. 25. 26. &amp; 2. Eſd. 7.
verſ. 28. 29.
            Although the common errour
and expectation of the Iewes, was
of a terreſtriall Monarchy; yet the
beſt learned of them agree, that
the Kingdome of Chriſt is not of this
world. For they remember that
place in the Teſtament of Iacob:
The Scepter ſhal not depart from Iuda,
till Shiloh come. By which it followes,
that whē 
               Meſsiha ſhal come,
there ſhould bee no more ſhew
of an earthly kingdome. That of

Zach. 9. 9. is as direct, Ieruſalem, behold,
thy king commeth vnto thee poore.
They remember alſo that in the
21. Pſalme, I am a worme and no
man, a ſhame of men and the contempt
of the people. And that alſo of Eſay.
53. Hee hath neyther forme nor
beautie: when we ſee him, there ſhall
be no forme that we should deſire him.
He is deſpiſed &amp; reiected of men, &amp;c.
Reade the whole Chapter and the
Pſalme, compare them with the hiſtories
of his Paſsion, and behold
Him on the Croſſe, in the horror of
his anguiſh, &amp; extreme perplexitie.
            But you will ſay, what is this Iudaiſme
in the letters of his Name,
for argument to proue that hee is
God? Is it more then if wee ſhould
write the name of Chriſt with the
laſt letter thereof capitall, Chris T;
becauſe it may repreſent the croſſe?
or els the two laſt letters ſo enterlaced,
that they may haue reference

to the ſerpent in the wildernes, becauſe
that was alſo a figure of
CHRI
                  'S' superimposed on 'T'
               ? Though I had here
to anſwere for the Cabala of euery
of the 72 languages of the Confuſion,
yet I ſay only thus: If after all
this that I haue ſaid, you will ſtill be
contentious, I haue no ſuch cuſtome,
but I am well content, that
either thus, or by any other means,
a Christian man ſhould hold that
in perpetuall memorie, which is his
Ioy, his Victorie, his Crowne, his
Happines in this world, and in the
world to come.
            Were it to any purpoſe to make
you know, what the ancient Philoſophers,
who knew not the Scriptures,
haue thought of this matter?
all ſpeaking this one thing, which
the light that GOD hath giuen to
mankind, did make them know, although
they concealed their intendiment
by diuers names. Yet

               Hermes called him plainely the
Sonne of GOD. Zoroaſter, the Vnderſtanding
of his Father. Pythagoras,
Wiſedome; as Paul and Salomon,
euery where, and particularly, Prouerb.
8. and in the booke of that
title.
            
               Parmenides named him The
Sphere of Vnderſtanding. Orpheus
termed him Pallas, to the ſame
effect as the other, if you know the
fable: and yet hee ſpeakes more
plainely to the Trinitie, in his
Hymnes of the Night, of the Heauen,
and of the Ayre. Platoes ſeparate
Ideas meane nothing elſe: and
in fumme, as many of the Philoſophers,
as were worth any thing,
were not ignorant of this thing.
But I feare, theſe authorities are
with you of little worth: yet haue
I brought them, that you may ſee
how wee are furniſhed with all
kinde of proofes, and how you

doe contemne all maner of teſtimony.
            If this which I haue ſaid, perſwade
you to looke better to the
foundation of your faith, it is ſufficient:
if it perſwade you nothing,
then haue I done contrary to the
Commandement, which forbiddeth
to caſt pearles before ſwine.
But yet I hope, that God will not
ſuffer you to bee ledde any longer
by that Spirit of Antichriſt, againſt
which S. Iohn doth ſo often warne
vs. For I doe you to witte, that this
your hereſie is no new thing, but euen
as ancient as the Apoſtles
time. For, the reaſon of Iohns writing
of his Goſpell, was, to proue
the Godhead of Christ, againſt the
Heretikes that denied it in his
owne time. And truely, I maruell
that you, who haue receyued
this Hereſie from the rotten

bones of Arrius, ſhould not prouide
for your ſafetie as he did. He denied
the authoritie of S. Iohns writings
to be authenticall. And why? becauſe
this earth-bred Gyant, which
would pul Christ, out of the throne
of his Deitie, ſhould with his lightening
be ſuddenly burnt. Beleeue
you the Scripture? Is Iohns authoritie
ſufficient? then the caſe is plaine.
We are in him that is true, in his Sonne
Ieſus Christ, who is very God, and eternall
life. 1. Ioh. 5. 20. Can you
now confer this Scripture with that
place, I haue ſaid ye are Gods, and
not be aſhamed? I and the Father are
one. The Iewes vnderſtood, that
hee herein profeſſed himſelfe to be
very GOD: and are you his enemie
more then they? Read Ioh. 10.
verſ. 30. and 33. and 34. and you
may vnderſtand the meaning of
both places. The diuels acknowledged
him to be GOD of Infinite

power: I know thee who thou art, euen
that Holy one of God: And wil not
you cōfeſſe as much as the diuels? But
this is more then I thought to ſay, only
you may ſee hereby, that we ſpeake
no other thing then Christ himſelfe,
euen in his enemies vnderſtanding,
ſaid. Now if you could ſee a little the
folly of your owne opinion; that were
inough to cauſe you to put on a better
mind. I wil touch it as lightning doth
touch the ground: for if you be willing
to be reformed, there is no doubt, but
you may propound it to the learned
Diuines, and be fully ſatisfied. You
ſay Christ is onely man, but yet indued
with the infinite Power of GOD. Here
firſt you doe iniurie to the Higheſt, to
make the Power of God to bee accidentall
vnto him: whereas hee is purus
actus, abſolute perfection, and without
ſhadow of change: his Beeing is
moſt ſimple and pure, not capable of
accidents. Then his Being is ſuch, as

no addition can be made thereto, to
make it more thē it is: therfore it is neceſſary,
that he be euer actually whatſoeuer
he may be. Beſides, His Being
is infinitely diſtant from Not Being;
therfore his Power is inſeparable. Again,
if there come any thing to God as
an accident, it muſt come vnto him frō
himſelfe, or els frō another: not frō another,
for he is impaſsible, or ſuch as
cānot ſuffer violence: not frō himſelfe;
for all ſuch accidents do proceed a potentia,
that is, frō the imbecillity, or imperfection
of the ſubiect: but his Being
is moſt ſimple, &amp; infinitely perfect. Again,
all accidents do riſe frō 
               ye
                matter,
forme or compoſition of ye
                ſubiect. In
him is neither matter, forme, nor compoſition.
Now all things we ſee in this
world, do conſiſt, ex actu &amp; potentiâ, of
Perfection from God, &amp; imperfection
frō thēſelues: for of thēſelues they are
non entia, abſolutely nothing. Yea, euen
the very Angels, and the ſoule it
ſelfe, are partakers of this compoſitiō:

(for nothing is purus actus, but God alone)
therefore are they ſubiect to accidents;
yet they which come neereſt
to perfection, are moſt free from accidents;
as that which is meere perfection,
hath no accidents at al. Know
then, that all the dignities of God are in
him eſſentially one God. For the Goodnes
of God, his Power, his Wiſedome, his
glory, &amp;c. beeing all infinite, do of neceſsity
concur in the nature of Infinity.
Whence it followeth, that whatſoeuer
is in him, is eſſentially himſelfe:
therefore the power of God is not accidentall,
or ſuch as may be imparted to
a man. The learned Hebrues according
to this do hold, that Euſoph or Infinitie,
is not to bee numbred among
the other attributes of God: becauſe it
is that abſtract Vnity, wherinto they
all eſſentially concurre, &amp; from which
they al eſſentially proceed. And hēce
by the way take another ſtrong argument
to the former queſtion: for
if GOD bee eſſentially a Father,
               
then the terme correlatiue a Sonne,
muſt bee in the Godhead alſo, and that
eſſentially. But now againe ſee another
folly in your ſuppoſition. The
worke of our redemption is a worke
of infinite goodneſſe, mercie, power,
wiſedome and glory; therefore it followeth,
that Christ the worker, had
infinite mercie, power, wiſedome, &amp;c.
            Now I demaund; had Christ this
infinite goodneſſe and power, ſo giuen to
him of God, that the Father himſelfe
had in the meane time none? This
you dare not ſay, for that were to ſay,
that GOD did ceaſe to bee GOD;
which cannot ſtand with his Eternitie.
            Now if GOD the Father had, notwithſtanding
this abſolute infinite
Power of Christ, of which he ſpake,
All power is giuen vnto me, both in heauen
and in earth: then it followeth that
either there were two infinities of Power;
or elſe that theſe two which had
this infinite Power, were all one Infinite.

The firſt is againſt the nature
of Infinitie: or that is abſolutely infinite,
which ſo comprehendeth all
things, as that it leaueth nothing without
it ſelfe, and yet is not comprehended
of any other. Beſides, if you
would ſay, that the Father and the
Sonne had each of them ſeuerall indiuiſible
infinite Powers; it muſt follow,
that neither of their Powers were
abſolutely infinite: becauſe each of
them had not the infinite Power of the
other: And beſides, that both theſe
infinite Powers muſt bee conioyned
with infinite weakeneſſe, becauſe they
muſt be mutually ſubiected to the infinite
Power one of the other. but both
theſe things are impoſsible. So you
ſee, that two Infinities can by no
meanes ſtand together: therefore it
followeth, that theſe two, to wit, the
Father and the Sonne, are in Being one,
and that of infinite Power; and this is
that which I ſtriue for: which, as you

ſee, I haue concluded by your owne
aſſertion.
            The time would faile mee, to lay
before your eyes the manifold vntrueths,
which would inſue of your
poſition which ſauoureth neyther of
witte, iudgement, nor learning: And
therefore I ſee, how they which haue
once departed from the trueth, muſt
of neceſsitie runne into infinite abſurdities.
Therefore looke backe,
and be aſhamed of ſuch new-fangled
toyes, as you do dayly imagine, which
in trueth doe argue the great inconſtancie
and vanitie of your minde,
and withall, ſuch palpable blindneſſe
of vnderſtanding, as the darkneſſe of
Egypt. For tell mee without ſelfe-liking,
what ſound iudgement doth
this argue, to be driuen about with euery
wind of doctrine? a Proteſtant,
a Browniſt, an Anabaptiſt, an Antichriſt.
What bringing vp? what gift
of learning and knowledge haue

you, that you ſhould preſume to oppoſe
your ſentence, againſt the faith
and doctrine of all the Christian
Churches in the world? Bluſh, and
learne with meekeneſſe the trueth of that
Word, which is able to ſaue your ſoule.
You may ſee by your owne miſerable
experience, what it is to forſake the
Vnitie of Faith, and the Communion
of the Saints, who imbrace the
trueth of Gods word, and haue manifeſt
tokens that they are the true
Church, to wit, The word of God truely
taught, and the Sacraments duely adminiſtered.
What if there want perfection?
The Church militant muſt euer
confeſſe; I am louely, yet blacke▪
                For it
is impoſsible that any Church ſhould
be without imperfectiō, ſo long as the
world ſtandeth: but at the end it ſhall
bee preſented without ſpotte or wrinkle.
Therfore remēber from whence you are
fallen, &amp; repēt, &amp; do the works of righteouſnes,
leſt Christ, whō you ſo deſpite,

               come againſt you ſhortly. The worke of
Christianitie is not in fooliſh queſtions,
and diſputing about needleſſe
ſubtilties, but in doing the workes of
trueth and righteouſneſſe. Pray and
endeuour your ſelfe thereto. And
till ſuch time as GOD for his Christs
ſake, vouchſafe to haue mercie on
you, the enemie of his SONNE,
and giue you grace to repent of this
great wickedneſſe, I am neither your
friend, nor yet your foe.
            Alecſander Gil.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

