
   
      
         
            Wit in a constable A comedy written 1639. The author Henry Glapthorne. And now printed as it was lately acted at the Cock-pit in Drury lane, by their Majesties Servants, with good allowance.
            Glapthorne, Henry.
         
         
            
               1640
            
         
         Approx. 136 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01779
            STC 11914
            ESTC S103219
            99838976
            99838976
            3369
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01779)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3369)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 926:01)
         
         
            
               
                  Wit in a constable A comedy written 1639. The author Henry Glapthorne. And now printed as it was lately acted at the Cock-pit in Drury lane, by their Majesties Servants, with good allowance.
                  Glapthorne, Henry.
               
               [68] p.   
               
                  By Io. Okes, for F[rancis] C[onstable] and are to be sold at his shops in Kings-street at the signe of the Goat, and in Westminster Hall,
                  London :
                  1640.
               
               
                  In verse.
                  Publisher's name from STC.
                  Signatures: A-H⁴ I² .
                  The first leaf is blank.
                  Reproduction of the original in the New York Public Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2003-04
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-05
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-06
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2003-06
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-08
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            WIT IN A Constable.
            A Comedy written 1639.
            The Author HENRY GLAPTHORNE.
            And now Printed as it was lately Acted at the Cock-pit in Drury lane, by their Majesties Servants, with good allowance.
            
               LONDON: Printed by Io. Okes, for F. C. and are to be sold at his shops in Kings-street at the signe of the Goat, and in Westminster Hall. 1640.
         
         
            
            
            To the Right Honourable his singular good Lord THOMAS LORD WENTWORTH.
            
               My LORD!
            
            
               SO many are the noble attributes inherent to your Heroicke Nature, that 'tis difficult to distinguish whither they be divers, or one intire virtue, but impossible to define which ought to be accounted the Superlative in so perfect a Harmony: to ascribe to one more then to another, were to derogate

from the justice of either. I cannot therefore proclaime 'twas any particular, but your generall Goodnesse which has imboldn'd me to intrude this Poem on the Patronage of your Name, as honourable in vertue as in Greatnesse: nor shall I tender any excuse for the presumption, since I am assured your Lordship cannot conceive an anger from the true devotion of
            
               
                  Your humblest honourer, Hen: Glapthorne.
            
         
         
            
            The PROLOGUE.
            
            YOu need not feare me Gentlemen, although
            I come thus arm'd; tis but to let you know
            I am in office; in my owne defence,
            And to secure me from the violence,
            Which might from you (who now my Iudges sit)
            Be off'red to this Trophee of my wit:
            And cause I know that you will obay
            Authority, I doe charge you, like the Play:
            Thinke who I am, how often I may catch
            You at ill houres in Tavernes, or ith' Watch;
            In Fraies sometimes; nay sometimes (not to trench
            Too much upon you) with a pretty wench.
            All this is possible, and Gentlemen,
            Consider how my rage will use you then,
            If you should now, as sure tis worth your feare,
            Be in the censure of my wit seuere,
            Vext I' me implacable; and though the Tribe
            Of Constables doe us't, Ile take no bribe
            To let you passe: These sturdy knaves will take
            Not the least mercy on you for my sake:
            Nor will the Iustice free you: (to your smart)
            You'le find, he and his Clarke will take my part.
            I can but gently warne you to prevent
            A danger, nay a certaine punishment,
            Should you dislike: for if the Play doe fall
            Vnder your votes, Ile apprehend you all.
         
         
            EPILOGUE.
            ARe you resolv'd yet Gentlemen? I am
            In earnest haste of Towne-affaires, and came
            To know your minds: how's that? there's one I spye
            That will dislike, to th' Counter instantly
            With him; intreat
                  •
                Sir, shall not prevaile,
            Nor shall you thi
                  •
               ke to come out upon baile.
            For in this case (believe it) I'de not spare
            (Though the sword were borne before him) my Lord Major;
            Nor should the Court of Aldermen reprieve
            For such a f
                  •
               ct, my good friend Master Shreive.
            If so severe to them then, who by vow,
            Are my owne bretheren? what will become of you?
            I have consider'd; and will now commit
            To your free votes the Cen
                  •
               ures of my wit.
            For though their dulnesse (whom I've threatned) may
            Dislike (you'ave wit) and will allow the play.
         
         
            
            The Persons in the Play.
            
               Thorow good, a young Gentleman, sutor to Clare.
               Valentine his friend, a sutor to Grace.
               Knowell their friend.
               
               
                  Sir Timothy Shallowit, a Country Knight.
               
               
                  Sir Geffery Hold-fast, a Knight of Epping.
               Jeremy Hold-fast, his Sonne.
               
               
                  Alderman Covet.
               Busie, a Linnen Draper, the Constable.
               
               Tristram, servant to Jeremy Hold-fast.
               Formal, servant to Alderman Covet.
               
                  A Parson.
               
               
                  Foure watch-men.
               
               Clare, neece to Alderman Covet.
               Grace, his Daughter.
               
               Maudlin, servant to Clare.
               Nel, daughters to Busie.
               
                  Fidlers boy, Drawer, Attendants.
               
            
            The Scene London.
         
      
      
         
            
            VVit in a Constable.
            
               Actus primus, Scena prima.
               Enter Holdfast, Tristram.
               
               
                  Holdfast.
                  
                     DID you ere we departed from the Colledge
                  Orelooke my library?
               
               
                  Trist.
                  Yes sir, I spent two dayes in sorting Poets from Historians,
                  As many nights in placing the divines
                  On their owne chayres, I meane their shelves, and then
                  In separating Philosophers from those people
                  That kill men with a license: your Physitians
                  Cost me a whole dayes labour, and I finde sir,
                  Although you tell me learning is immortall,
                  The paper and the parchment, tis contayn'd in,
                  Savors of much mortality.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  I hope my bookes are all in health.
               
               
                  Trict.
                  In the same case the Mothes have left them, who have eaten more
                  Authenticke learning then would richly furnish
                  A hundred country pedants; yet the wormes
                  Are not one letter wiser.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  I have beene idle
                  Since I came up from Cambridge, goe to my stationer
                  And bid him send me Swarez Metaphysickes,
                  
                     
                     Tolet de anima is new forth,
                  So are Granadus commentaries on
                  Primui
                        •
                      se
                        •
                     undae Thomae Aquinatis,
                  Get me the Lyricke Poets. And —
               
               
                  Trist.
                  
                     I admire
                  How he retaines these Au
                        •
                     hors names, of which
                  He understands no sillable, 'twere better
                  
                     I bought the Authenticke Legend of Sir Bevis,
                  
                  Some six new Ballads and the famous Poems
                  Writ by the learned waterman.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  
                     Iohn Taylor, get me his nonsense.
               
               
                  Trist.
                  You meane all his workes sir.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  And a hundred of Bookers new Almanacks.
               
               
                  Trist.
                  And the divell to boot,
                  Your fathers bookes in which he keeps th accounts
                  Of all his coyne will scarce yield crowns to afford
                  Your fancy volums: why you have already
                  Enough to furnish a new Vatican,
                  A hundred country pedants can read dictats
                  To their young pupills out of Setons logicke,
                  Or Golius Ethicks, and make them arrive,
                  Proficients learn'd enough in one bare twelmonth
                  To instruct the parish they were borne in: you
                  Out of an itch to this same foolish learning
                  Bestow more money yearely upon bookes:
                  Then would for convert sisters build an almes-ho
                        •
                     se.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  You will displease my patience Tristram.
                  
               
               
                  Trist.
                  I speake truth: if you shud want, your learning scarce would make you
                  Capable of being town Cleark, or at best,
                  To be a famous Tyrant unto boyes,
                  And weare out birch upon them: or perchance
                  you may arrive to be the City Poet,
                  And f
                        •
                     nd the little moysture of your braine
                  To grace a Lord Maiors festivall with showes,
                  Alluding to his trade, or to the company
                  Of which he's free, these are the best preferments
                  That can attend your learning.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  
                     I say Tristram, the spirit of my learning stirs me up
                  
                     To give thee due correction.
               
               
                  Trist.
                  Would you study? as does young Thorowgood your noble Cosen,
                  Not bookes, but men which are true living volums:
                  You would like him, be held rich ith' esteeme
                  Of all the illustrious wits that decke the city
                  When the extent of your admirers is
                  Confinde to fresh men: and such youths as only
                  Know how to frame a syllogisme in Darij,
                  
                  And make the ignorant believe by Logicke
                  The Moones made of a Holland Cheese: and the man in't.
                  A swagbellied Dutch Burger
Intras Thorowgood.
                  
               
               
                  Thoro.
                  Cosen Holdfast, a good day attend
                  Thy learned piamater: prithee tell me
                  How doe the Cabalists and antient Rabbins
                  
                  And thou agree? will they be sociable,
                  And drinke their mornings draught of Helicon
                  With thee: have they instructed you to prove yet
                  That the world runs on wheeles? or that the sea
                  May be drunke off by a shole of Whales? such things
                  You know there are in nature.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  O far stranger.
               
               
                  Thoro.
                  Peace you booke-worme,
                  Fit only to devour more paper then
                  A thousand grand tobacco men or a legion
                  Of boyes in pellets to their elderne gunnes.
                  Dost thinke to live this life still? you're not now
                  Amongst your eues at Cambridge, but in London,
                  Come up to see your mistris beautious Clare,
                  The glory of the city: goe and court her,
                  As does become a gentleman of carriage,
                  Without your Tropes and figures Inkehorne termes,
                  Fit only for a Mountebanke or Pedant,
                  Or all your Physickes Metaphysickes and Meteors,
                  (Tomes larger farre and more repleate with lies,
                  Then Surius, Gallo-Belgcus, or the welsh
                  Bard Geffrey Monmouth) sh
                        •
                     l be straight-way made
                  Pitifull Martyrs.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  Why cosen I had thought.
               
               
                  
                  Thoro.
                  Thy selfe an errant ideot, that's the fittest
                  Thought for thy braine more dull then a fat Burgers,
                  Or reverend countrey justices, whose wit
                  Lies in his spruce clearkes standish, thou wert begot
                  Surely ith' wane oth' Moone, when natures tooles
                  Were at lame Vulcans forge a sharpening, thou art so lumpish.
               
               
                  Trist.
                  He has already spoyld
                  His eyes with prying on Geneva prints,
                  And small dutch Characters: his watching makes him
                  Looke like a grand-child of old Errapaters,
                  
                  Some leane Astronomer, who to get ten shillings,
                  For that's a large price for an Almanacke,
                  Has wasted himselfe to the bignesse of his Iaccobs staffe,
                  Which is so limber, 't cannot stand to take height of Venus rising.
               
               
                  Thoro.
                  He sayes truth: besides your study has attain'd already,
                  Learning enough to informe your minde the knowledge
                  Of arts fit for a gentleman, wert not better
                  For you my sprightfull senior to advance
                  Your bever with a hatband of the last
                  Edition in the Court, among the noblest
                  Youthes of our nation, then to walke like Faustus,
                  
                  Or some high German conjurer, in a cap
                  Fit for a Coster-monger, to weare your purle
                  Or cut worke, band then this small 
                        ••
                     ip of linning
                  That's proper only for T
                           •
                        om Thum: or some of queen Mabs gentlemen-ushers.
               
               
                  Trist.
                  This Cassocke were a pretty garment for a fortuneteller.
               
               
                  Thoro
                  And this cloake of tinder comely for a ballad-seller,
                  Life sir, you are borne here to an ample fortune,
                  Your father absent knowes not how you've altered
                  Your disposition: I must reclayme it,
                  Thou shalt with me and court the beauteous Clare
                  
                  Reserv'd for thee, a purpose ith' meane time,
                  Our chiefe companions, shall be wits more pure,
                  Then your quicke sophisters, or 
                        •
                     lie logicians,
                  Wee'l talke of the bright beauties of the age,
                  Girles whose each looke deserves to be a theme
                  For all the nimble poets, two dayes practise
                  
                     In our brave arts will teach thee to forget
                  Philosophy as fruitlesse and abjure
                  All other Ethicks, but what's usd mongst us, as most erronious▪
                  
               
               
                  Hold.
                  Well You shall perswade me, Ile be an errant asse, or any thing
                  For thy sake coz, but shall we have such wenches
                  As are at Cambridge, hansome as peg Larkin.
               
               
                  Thoro.
                  O farre before her, cosen thou shalt read
                  
                     Are
                           •
                        ius Politicks; and Ov
                           •
                        ds Art,
                  Shall be new read, thee and wee will refine
                  Thy Academicke wit with bowles of wine.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  
                     Tristram shall toth' Colledge and sell my bookes immediately.
               
               
                  Thoro.
                  Speake like the son of Phoebus and my cosen.
               
               
                  Trist.
                  My studious master.
               
               
                  Thoro.
                  Sell thy Dictionary.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  Ile not keepe a prayer booke.
               
               
                  Thoro.
                  They are out of fashion.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  Nor a Calender, to looke the age oth' Moone in, Trist. be sure
                  You burne G
                           •
                        eens groats worth of wit; I scorne to keepe
                  The name of wit about me.
               
               
                  Trist.
                  Tis confest sir, but for the numerous Rhemes of paper, which
                  Are pil'd up in your study, give them mee,
                  I have a brother in law ith' towne's a cooke,
                  Ile give them him to put under his bake meates.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  Take them: I will not leave a pen within my lodging,
                  
                     I will forget to write, or set my hand to any thing.
               
               
                  Thoro.
                  Unlesse 't be to a bond.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  Ile goe put this blest designe in execution,
                  Cosen anon ile meet you at your chamber.
               
               
                  Thoro.
                  What in that reverend shape? the gentlemen
                  That I converse with, will believe thee some Itinerant
                  Scholler, have thee whipt by th' statute.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  
                     I would be loath, now I am past a fresh man to bee had into the buttries.
               
               
                  Thoro.
                  Still them termes? study to forget them, Ile send my
                  Man to you with a new suite of mine I never wore yet,
                  Be sure to put it on right, you mere Schollers
                  Know no degree of garment above Serge,
                  Or Satanisco: tie your band-strings neatly
                  And doe not eat the buttons off, put not
                  
                     Your Cuffs both on one hand; twill tax your judgement
                  Of new inventing fashions when accoustred,
                  Come to my chamber, and Ile furnish you
                  With language fit to accost your mistris.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  Rare, I've got more learning from him in halfe an houre,
                  Then in a whole lifes practise out of bookes.
                  Follow me Tristram, farewell deare cosen.
Ex. Hold. Trist.
                  
               
               
                  Thoro.
                  How I could laugh now, were my spleen large enough: a
                  Hundred such lame stupid Ideots were enough, if marry'd,
                  To precise Burgers daughters to replenish
                  The city with a race of fooles, and root
                  The stocke of knaves quite out of it, he loves books:
                  Not that he has a scruple more of learning
                  Then will suffice him to say grace, but like
                  Some piteous cowards, who are oft thought valiant
                  For keeping store of weapons in their chambers,
                  He loves to be esteem'd a doctor by
                  His volumnes: but I shall fit his schollership: whose these?
                  Alderman Covets, Formall, byth' proportion:
Ent. Formal and Clare.
                  
                  That rib of mans flesh should be Clare, dost heare
                  My honest Cadis garters: who for care
                  And close attendance on thy charge deserves
                  To be grand porter to the great Turkes Seraglia: how hight that vayl'd damsell?
               
               
                  Form.
                  She has been at Brit
                        •
                     ins burse a buying pins &amp; needle
                  To worke a night-cap for my master sir.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  Pox upon him, is not her name Clare, niece to Alderman Covets
                  
               
               
                  For.
                  Her father was a country Squire of large revenew and her mother.
               
               
                  Thoro.
                  I shall be forc'd to heare him blaze her pedigree,
                  Ide beat him, but that clubs and paring shovells oth' city
                  Would be so busie abou
                        •
                      my eares: they'd spoyle
                  My hearing two months after Gentle Lady
                  Pardon my error if I doe mistake, are not you mistris Clare?
               
               
                  Clar.
                  
                     Formall at last, would have resolv'd you, and I held my
                  Peace of purpose, cause I knew his slow discovery would vex
                  Your nimble patience
               
               
                  Tho.
                  You are a Gipsie, but does thy unkles hu
                        •
                     our hold of wedding
                  His daughter to sir Timothy.
                  
               
               
                  
                  Clar.
                  Yes, or to young monsieur Holdfast whom he sayes is
                  Learned enough to make Cheap-side a Colledge,
                  And all the City a new Academy, but have you
                  
                     Thorowgood perform'd what I advis'd you to?
               
               
                  Thoro.
                  Yes, my girle: good Formall use thy motion to convay
                  Thy ears a little farther off, there's mony
                  To buy thee a new payre of garters: Clare
                  
                  Thou shalt no more behold me in the garbe
                  And noble ornament I us'd to weare, my fashion shall be altred.
               
               
                  Clar.
                  To the schoolars,
                  Young Holdfasts likenesse.
               
               
                  Thoro.
                  O by all meanes girle▪ thou shalt behold this comely hat transform'd
                  To frugall brim, and steeple crowne, this band
                  Of faire extent chang'd to a moderne cut,
                  Narrower then a precisians: all this gay
                  And gawdy silke I will convert to Serge
                  Of limber length: like some spruce student (newly
                  Exalted for saying grace well, to be fellow
                  Oth' Colledge he had studied) I will
                  Salute thy reverent Uncles spectacles,
                  And without feare of his gold chaine, ile woe thee
                  In metaphores and tropes Scholastick till
                  The doting Senator with a liberall hand give
                  Thee his dainty darling to become my spouse inseparable.
               
               
                  Clar.
                  This suites well with my directions.
               
               
                  Thoro.
                  True girle true, farewell Clare,
                  
                  
                     I kisse thy white hand: Sir resume your charge,
                  
                     I've done my errand: let not your old Sir Amiar
                     ▪
                  
                  Know of this conference, if you doe, that twist
                  Of spinners thred, on which your life depends
Exe. Clare. &amp; Formall.
                  
                  Shall be shorne off like a horse mane. Farewell.
               
               
                  Form.
                  Mans life indeed is but a thred, good day sir.
Ent. Valentine &amp; Sir Timothy.
                  
               
               
                  Thor.
                  Attend your charge friend, Valentine, Sir Timothy.
                  
                  You'r well incountred, may I inquire the affaire
                  Which happily has brought you up toth' City?
               
               
                  Thoro.
                  May I know it? is't not to purchase a Monopoly
                  For Salt and Herrings? for state businesse,
                  Unlesse it be to see the great new ship,
                  
                     Or Lincolns Inne fields built: I'me sure you none here.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Very right sir.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  But for thee: my noble man of merit, thou art welcome,
                  Weel be as kind to one another boy,
                  And witty as brisque poets in their wine,
                  Weel court the blacke browd beauties of the time,
                  And have by them the height of our desires: with ease accomplished
               
               
                  
                     V
                           •
                        l.
                  
                  Noble Thorowgood,
                  
                  Did I not owne you by the name of friend,
                  Already these indearments would ingage me to beg that title.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Very right, and me too.
                  
                     I know you for the most Egregious'knight
                  In all the country.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  You sir, you've reason,
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Very right▪ I am indeed esteem'd so.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  One that live on Onions and Corne-sallets.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Right agen,
                  Sure he can conjure, I had one to my breakefast.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  Nay no Herald
                  Can better blase your pedigree. I've heard
                  Your father my most worthy knight, was one
                  That died a knave to leave you so.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Passing right still.
               
               
                  
                     Tho
                           •
                        .
                  
                  And pray right witty, and right honor'd sir,
                  What may your businesse seeme to be ith' city.
                  Are you come up to learne new fashions?
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Exceeding right agen.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  To change this ancient garment to a new one
                  Of a more spruce edition.
               
               
                  Val.
                  Yes, but before,
                  For I am privie unto all's intentions,
                  He means to see and court his mistris.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  Who's that? my doughty Impe of spur and sword,
                  Some faire Dulcina de Tob
                           •
                        so.
                  
               
               
                  Val.
                  No, tis Grace, daughter to Alderman Covet.
                  
               
               
                  Thor.
                  I doe commend thee my deare Don, and will
                  Be thy assistant, goe and see thy horse drest,
                  And then approach my chamber.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Very right, I kisse your fingers end.
Ex. Timothy.
                  
               
               
                  
                  Thor.
                  Doe you, Valentine, know
                  The Lady he intends to Court.
               
               
                  Val.
                  Onely by report,
                  Which speakes her most accomplish'd.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  Oh she'll make
                  An excellent Asse of him: she has a wit
                  More sharpe and piercing than a Waspes sting, she speaks
                  All fire; each word is able to burne up
                  A thousand such poore Mushromes: had her mother
                  Not beene held honest, I should have believ'd
                  She'd bin some Courtiers By-blow, or that some
                  Quicke Poet got her.
               
               
                  Val.
                  How's her feature?
               
               
                  Thor.
                  Rare, past expression, singular, her eyes
                  The very sphears of love, her cheeks his throne,
                  Her lips his paradise, and then her minde
                  Js farre more excellent than her shape.
               
               
                  Val.
                  You give her a brave Character; is't possible
                  To have a sight of her?
               
               
                  Tho.
                  Yes, by my means, scarce otherwise wilt thou have her▪
                  
                  Speake but a syllable, 't shall be perform'd
                  As sure as if Don Hymen, in his robes
                  Had ratifi'd the contract.
               
               
                  Val.
                  You are merry sir.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  When didst thou know me otherwise: yet now
                  In sober sadnesse friend, couldst thou affect
                  A woman, as there's few of them worth loving,
                  Thou canst not make a nobler choise: Ile bring thee
                  On to the skirmish, but if thou retreat,
                  Beat backe by th' hot Artillery of her wit,
                  Which will play fast upon thee: maist thou live
                  To be enamour'd on some stale Hay, or Matron
                  Of fourescore, that may congeale thee to a frost
                  Sooner than forty winters: or be wed
                  To an insatiat Chamber-maid.
               
               
                  Val.
                  Defend me
                  From thy last curse; feare not my valour.
               
               
                  
                  Thor.
                  This foole shall serve both her and us for sport:
                  Lets to our taske; and if our project hit,
                  Ile sweare all fortune is compris'd in wit.
Exeunt.
                  
               
               Explicit Actus primus.
            
            
               Actus secundus. Scena prima.
               Covet, Clara, Maudlin.
               
                  Cov.
                  YOu will provoke me.
               
               
                  Clar.
                  No matter:
                  Although you be my uncle, and so nature
                  Binds me to observe you, ile not be oblig'd
                  To what the phlegmaticke humour of your age
                  Strives to enforce upon me: I was borne
                  Free, an inheritresse to an ample fortune,
                  Of which you doe pervert the use, and trust me,
                  Ile be no longer tame and suffer it.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Suffer what? you're us'd
                  Too well: if you complaine of this, I shall
                  Study to be more harsh.
               
               
                  Clar.
                  Doe; you shall not, as you had wont,
                  Thinke to attire me in blacke Grogram,
                  Daub'd o're with Sattin lace, as if I were
                  Daughter, and heire apparent to a Tayler,
                  Who from the holiday Gownes of sixe neat fish-wives
                  Had stole the remnants made the thrifty garment.
                  Nor shal you sir (as tis a frequent custome,
                  Cause you're a worthy Alderman of a Ward.)
                  Feed me with Custard, and perpetuall White-broth,
                  Sent from the Lord Majors, or the Shriefes feast,
                  
                     And here preserv'd ten dayes, (as twere in pickle)
                  Till a new dinner from the common hall
                  Supply the large defect.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  You'll leave this language?
               
               
                  Clar.
                  Leave to use me so then:
                  Y'ave made my selfe, your daughter, and my woman,
                  Sup with a penyworth of Lettice, under
                  Pretence 'twould make us sleep well: your full morsells
                  (Had not the vertue of Clay wall, and Oatmeale
                  Preserv'd my maid) ere this she'd bin shrunk up
                  Toth' bignesse of a Squirrill.
               
               
                  Maud.
                  Any Dwarfe
                  might without stretching his small fingers, have
                  Spand me about the waste.
               
               
                  Clar.
                  Nor shall you,
                  (As sure tis your intention) marry me
                  To th' quondam fore-man of your shop, (exalted
                  To be your Cash-keeper) a limber fellow,
                  Fit onely for deare Nan, his schoole-fellow,
                  A Grocers daughter, borne in Bread-street, with
                  Whom he has used to goe to Pimblico,
                  
                  And spend ten groats in Cakes and Christian Ale,
                  And by the way has courted her with fragments,
                  Stoln from the learned Legends of Knights Errants,
                  Or from the glory of her fathers trade,
                  The Knight o'the Burning Pestle.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Sure the Devill
                  Has entred her ith' likenesse of an Eele,
                  Her tongue's so slippery: Minion—
               
               
                  Clar.
                  Ile not be frighted
                  As are your Prentises, with Little ease,
                  Or shewing them the Beadle. In plain termes,
                  I doe not meane to incorporate with a Salter,
                  Or any of those thriving trades, to have
                  My shooes lickt o're each saturday night
                  Byth' under prentise; they shine so brightly
                  With soot and kitching-stuffe, that I next morning
                  May spare my glasse, and dresse my head by their
                  
                     Greasie reflection: yet let me tell you,
                  I must be marry'd instantly a virgin:
                  Of my full age, setting aside all nicenesse
                  May justly claime a husband.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Have but patience, ile wed thee to a Knight.
               
               
                  Clare.
                  What is hee, one oth' Post sir, or some such
                  As was in the old famous Ballad mention'd:
                  He that has forty pounds per annum, by
                  Which Charter I should be undutifull,
                  And take the wall of my ag'd Grandame: No,
                  Ile have a Courtly gentleman, whose wit
                  Shall equall his estate, and that so large,
                  As't shall afford me a sufficient joyncture.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  This Knight shall do't, or if you like not him,
                  What say you to Sir Geffery Holdfast's sonne,
                  The famous Schollar?
               
               
                  Clare.
                  If he be a Parson;
                  And I his wife, I sure shall make my friends
                  Lucky to horse-flesh: No, I will have one
                  That shall maintaine my Coach, and foure faire horses:
                  Not such thin jades, nor such a crazy Chariot,
                  As i've seene us'd by Citizens to convey
                  Their wives with leisure to their Country houses,
                  (For feare the late Plum-pudding they had eaten
                  Fryed to their Breakfast, should with too much jogging
                  Broyle on their queasie stomacks) One that shall
                  Maintaine me a Sedan, and two strong varlets,
                  That so I may not need the Common men Mules,
                  With their wood-Litters, with nineteene at end of them,
                  The usuall shelters, which the Gallants carry
                  Their wenches to their Chambers in: In briefe,
                  If you can find me any where a husband
                  That I can like, I will allow your choyse;
                  If not, ile take my owne; so good day to you.
                  Pray meditate upon it.
Ex. Clare, Maud:
                  
               
               
                  Cov.
                  This is the maddest wench: would I were rid of her,
                  She vexes me more than her Portion's worth;
                  But if she stoope not to my Country Knight,
                  
                     Sir Timothy Shallow-wit, or to young Holdfast,
                  
                  (Whom I had rather marry to my daughter)
                  She shall ha grasing.
               
               Enter Formall.
               
                  For.
                  Sir, there are a brace of gentlemen without,
                  Desire admittance to you.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Let them enter.
               
               
                  For.
                  I shall denote your pleasure.
Ex. For.
                  
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Some young heires,
                  To borrow money upon Morgages.
               
               Enter Holdfast, Brave, Tristram.
               
                  Hol.
                  I shall observe my Cosens rule, nere fear me.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Save you sir.
               
               
                  Hol.
                  You do not think me damn'd sir, you bestow
                  That salutation on me.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Good sir no.
                  Whom would you speake with here?
               
               
                  Hol.
                  Sir, my discourse
                  Poynts at one Alderman Covet.
                  
               
               
                  Cov.
                  I am the party.
               
               
                  Hol.
                  Good Mr. Covet, I covet your acquaintance:
                  I understand you have a daughter is
                  Of most unknowne perfections.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  She is as heaven ma
                        •
                     e her.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  She goes naked then,
                  The Tailer has no hand in her; may I see her?
               
               
                  Cov.
                  I must desire your name first.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  My name is Holdfast.
                  
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Sonne to sir Geff. Holdfast.
                  
               
               
                  Hold.
                  His proper sonne and heire, and I am come
                  To see your Daughter and your Neece.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Came you from Cambridge lately.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  I come from Cambridge:
                  What do you see in these my looks, should make you
                  Judge me such a Coxecombe.
               
               
                  
                  Cov.
                  Your father writ me word, his son that should
                  Come up to see my Daughter and my Neece,
                  Was a rare schollar, wholly given to's bookes.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  My father was an arrant asse for's labour,
                  I ne're read book in all my life, except
                  The Counter scuffle, or the mer
                        •
                     y Gossips,
                  Raynard the Foxe, Tom Thumbe, or Gargantua,
                  And those i've quite forgotten: I a schollar!
                  He lyes in's throat that told you so.
               
               
                  Trist.
                  On my Conscience
                  You may believe him: he scarce ere saw booke,
                  Vnlesse the Chronicle in an iron Chaine,
                  In's fathers Hall: for learning sir, except
                  What's in a Horse, a Hawke, or hownd, he knowes not
                  How to expound your meaning.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  I mar'le sir Geff. knowing my aversion
                  From any of these courses, should bring up
                  His sonne to all of them: nay, write me word,
                  Knowing my love to learning, he had him
                  A schollar purposely: pray sir resolve me,
                  Are you sir Gefferies sonne?
               
               
                  Hold.
                  I am a Bastard else.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Sir Gefferies sonne of Eppinge?
                  
               
               
                  Hold.
                  Yes, of Eppinge,
                  
                  One that will venture five hundred pounds upon his horse,
                  Soone as the proudest hee that lives in London,
                  
                  Ile play my Crop-eare 'gainst my Lord Majors Steed,
                  And all his furniture: I doe intend
                  To scoure Hide Parke this summer.
               
               
                  Trist.
                  didst give him
                  His Oates this morning? Shall I see your daughter.
                  Did he drink's water hastily? Your Neece
                  I'de be acquainted with.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Sir, you must pardon me, you're not the man
                  I tooke you for.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  You did not take me for an Asse I hope.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  O by no meanes, but they cannot be seene
                  Conveniently this morning: another time,
                  At your best leasure, I shall not deny you.
                  
                     Please you walke in, and taste our Beere?
               
               
                  Hold.
                  I know 'tis but oth' sixes; and I hate
                  Liquor of that complexion: pray commend me
                  To both my sweet-hearts. Tristram come lets backe,
                  And, as my Cosen sayes, drinke lusty sacke.
               
               Exeunt Holdfast and Tristram.
               
                  Cov.
                  There's some deceite in this, perhaps some gallant,
                  Knowing my purpose with Sir Geffery Holdfast,
                  
                  Has tane his name upon him: ile dispatch
                  A messenger straight to him: whom have we here?
               
               Enter Thoroug▪ and Formall.
               
                  Form.
                  Sir, that's the Alderman my Master.
               
               
                  Thor:
                  Is this the venerable Man, to whom
                  This goodly Mansion is impropriate:
                  I should negotiate with his reverence
                  About authentick businesse.
               
               
                  Cov:
                  This rather
                  Should be sir Geff. sonne, his words and habit
                  Speake him most learned. I'me the person, pray
                  Let me be bold to crave your name.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  My appellation or pronomen, as
                  (It is tearm'd by the Latins) is hight Ieremie,
                  
                  But my Cognomen, as the English gather,
                  Is called Holdfast.
                  
               
               
                  Cov.
                  This is he certainely; are you, I pray
                  Sir Gefferies sonne of Eppinge?
                  
               
               
                  Thor.
                  The Nominalls, the Thomists, all the sects
                  Of old and moderne Schoole-men, doe oblige me,
                  To pay to that Sir Geffery fillial duty.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  I'me glad to heare it, tother was some varlet,
                  I shall finde out and punish: Sir, y'are welcome;
                  I gesse your businesse; tis about a match,
                  Or with my Neece, or Daughter: which you like,
                  Shall be at your dispose: if not, your businesse.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  My businesse is of procreation, or as
                  The Civill Lawyers learnedly doe paraphrase,
                  
                     Is of concomitance, Cohabitation,
                  Or what you please to terme it.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  How am I blest, that this rare schollar shall
                  Be match'd into my family? Within there;
                  Neece, Daughter, both come hither.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  One at once sir,
                  Twill satisfie; the Canon does prohibit
                  Us Polygamy.
               
               Enter Clara, Gray.
               
                  Cov.
                  Sir, this is my onely daughter, this my neece,
                  Pray know them better.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  Faire types, nay Orbs of beauty, J salute you,
                  Each in his proper altitude.
               
               
                  Graie.
                  Heyday, this is some Fortune-teller.
               
               
                  Clare.
                  Tis Thorowgood, you must not seeme to know him.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Daughter and Neece, this is a gentleman,
                  My care has pick'd out, as a most fit husband
                  For one of you; which he can soonest fancy,
                  Heare him but speake, and he will put you downe
                  Ten Universities, and Jnnes of Court,
                  Jn twentie sillables. Good Mr. Holdfast
                  
                  Speake learnedly to th'wenches; though J say't,
                  They have both good capacities.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  Most rubicund, stelliferous splendant Ladyes,
                  The ocular faculties, by which the beames
                  Of love are darted into every soule,
                  Or humane essence, have into my breast
                  Convey'd this Ladies lustre: and J can
                  Admire no other object; therefore beauty
                  Your pardon, if J onely doe addresse
                  In termes Scholasticke, and in Metaphors
                  My phrase to her.
               
               
                  Graie.
                  J shall not
                  Envy my Cosens happinesse.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  Y'are full of Candor;
                  Jf you will love me Lady▪ ile approach your eares,
                  Not in a garbe Domesticke, or termes vulgar,
                  
                     But hourely change my language, court you now,
                  In the Chaldean, or Arabicke tongues,
                  Expound the Talmud to you, and the Rabbines,
                  
                  Then read the Dialect of the Alanits,
                  
                  Or Ezion Gebor, which the people use
                  Five leagues beyond the Sun-rising, in stead
                  Of pages to attend you, I will bring
                  Sects of Philosophers and queint Logicians,
                  Weel Procreat by learned art, and I
                  
                  Will generate new broods of Schollers on you,
                  Which shall defend opinions far more various
                  Then all the Sectaries of Amsterdam
                  Have ever vented.
               
               
                  Covet.
                  Learned, learned young man,
                  How happy am I in thee?
               
               
                  Thor.
                  Doe but love,
                  Ile call the Muses from the sacred hill
                  To Enucleat your beauty: I my selfe
                  (After in loftier numbers I have sung
                  Your fam'd Encomiums) will convert to poet,
                  And for your sake Ile write the city annals,
                  In famous meter which shall far surpasse
                  Sir Guy of Warwickes history: or Iohn Stows upon
                  The custard with the foure and twenty Nooks
                  At my Lord Majors feast.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  How am I ravisht!
               
               
                  Thor.
                  Whose brave show hereafter
                  Shall be no more set forth with stalking pageants,
                  Nor children ride for angels nor lowd actors
                  Pronounce bold speeches, I will teach his Henehboyes
                  Serjeants and trumpeters to act and save
                  The city all that charges: Nay Ile make a new
                  Found engin; which without fire shall keepe his
                  Whitebroath warm til his return from Westminster
                  Nor shall the Aldermens daughters, who have
                  Dreamt at least six nights before of guilded
                  Marchpane, forfeit their serious longing: Ile have
                  Horses with their Saint Georges on them, that shall gallop
                  Into their handkerchers.
               
               
                  
                  Clar.
                  You promise wonders.
               
               
                  Covet.
                  Hold your tongue, hees able
                  To performe more by's learning.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  The crosse
                  And standerd in Cheapeside I will convert
                  To Hercules pillars: and the little conduit
                  That weepes in lamentation for the Church,
                  Remov'd that did leane on, it shall be still
                  Like the great tun at Heidleberge sild with wine,
                  And alwayes running, that the prentises
                  Shall not on Sundayes need to frequent Tauerns,
                  And forfeit their indentures.
               
               
                  Covet.
                  Still more miraculous.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  The great conduit
                  Shall be a magezin of sacke, and Smithfield
                  A Romish Cirque or Grecian Hippodrom,
                  My Lord Maiors gennet shall not die without
                  An Elegy, nor any cittizen breake,
                  But have a dolefull ditty writ upon him.
               
               
                  Val.
                  Save you gentlemen.
               
               
                  Covet.
                  Noble sir Timothy, and your friend both
                  Welcome, this is my neice, &amp; that my daughter, pray
                  Be pleas'd to know them, Sir honor me to walke,
                  I'de have some private conference with you,
                  The house sir Timothy is at your command.
               
               
                  Grace.
                  Cosen what would these gentlemen?
               
               
                  Clare.
                  Truth I know not,
                  Ile venture my discretion to his nose there,
                  And that appeares a rich one, they are two
                  Country Ideots whom thy father would
                  Put upon us for husbands.
               
               
                  Grace.
                  Very likely,
                  Pray gentlemen your businesse.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Speak for me Valentine.
                  
               
               
                  Val.
                  Ladies wee'r come to see you, fame does give
                  You the attribute of faire and witty.
               
               
                  Clare.
                  Yet our wits you see sir will not serve to keepe
                  Fooles from our company.
               
               
                  
                  Tim.
                  Very right yfaith.
               
               
                  Val.
                  That tartnesse
                  Becomes you prettily, and might serve to fright
                  Young linnen-drapers or some millaner
                  That does with gloves and bracelets stolne from's
                  Master court you, a haberdasher would have shak'd
                  His blocke-head (as if he had beene trying a Dutch
                  Felt out) and with a shrug departed, but we are
                  Gentlemen Ladies, and no city foremen
                  That never dare be ventrous on a beauty,
                  Unlesse when wenches take them up at playes
                  To intice them at the next licentious Taverne
                  To spend a supper on them, we are creatures
                  Deserve you at your best a
                        •
                     d noblest value,
                  And so expect you'l use us.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Very right, this is
                  A countrey gentleman my neighbor I,
                  A trusty and coragious country knight.
               
               
                  Clare.
                  
                     I doe believe you sir, your face does tel me,
                  You'r one that feed on bacon and bagpudding,
                  Your nose by its complexion does betray
                  Your frequent drinking country Ale with lant in't,
                  Have you no hobnayls in your boots, driven in
                  To save the precious leather from the stones
                  That pave the streets of London.
               
               
                  Grace.
                  Is not sir your
                  Cloake new turn'd, the aged three pil'd velvet
                  Was not your grandams peticote this jerkin
                  Made by your grandsire at his first translation
                  From Clowne to Gentleman, and since reserv'd
                  An heire long to the family, and this sword
                  The parish weapon?
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Very right agen.
               
               
                  Clare.
                  Now for you sir.
                  Who of two fooles doe yet appeare the wisest,
                  Can your ingenious noddle thinke that we
                  Bred in the various pleasures of the city,
                  Would for your sake turne beasts and grase ith' country,
                  
                     We cannot milke, make wholsome cheese, nor butter,
                  And sell it at next market and lay up
                  Out of the precious Income as much coyne
                  In thred bare groates, mill-sixpences, and pence,
                  As will suffice to finde the house in Candles
                  And Sope a twelve month after.
               
               
                  Grace.
                  Nor can wee
                  Spin our owne smockes out of the flax which growes
                  Behind your Dovehouse, no. nor card the wooll
                  Must make us peticoates things (to say truth)
                  Not worth the taking up.
               
               
                  Val.
                  They've Magicke in their tounges
                  They have so daunted me, I thinke I shall
                  Turne foole and get me▪ 'hem without reply.
               
               
                  Clare.
                  All the company,
                  We can injoy there is each day to walke
                  To the next farmers wife, whose whole discourse
                  Is what price Barly beares, or how her husband
                  Sould his last yoake of Oxen: other meetings
                  We cannot have, except it be at Churchales,
                  When the sweet bag-pipe does draw forth the
                  Damsells to frisquo about the May poles, o
                        •
                      at
                  Weddings, where the best cheare is, wholsome
                  Stewd broth made of legs of porke and 
                        〈◊〉
                     
                     ▪
                  
               
               
                  Grace.
                  Yes, at Christnings, where the good
                  Wives, stead of burnt Wine and Comfets,
                  Drinke healths to th' memory of all christian soules
                  In Ale, scarce three houres old: eat cakes more tough
                  Then glew or farthing gingerbread: then talke
                  Of the last Blasing Starre, or some new monster:
                  Then drinke, and cry heaven blesse us from the Spaniard,
                  While the learn'd Vicars wife expounds the Ballad
                  Of'twas a Ladies daughter in Paris properly,
                  And so breakes up the wise assembly.
               
               
                  Val.
                  And you
                  That are the precious paragons of the City,
                  Who scorne these harmelesse sports: can have your meetings
                  At Islington, and Green Goose faire, and si
                        •
                     
                  
                  
                     A zealous glasse of Wine till the parch'd floore
                  Be moistned with your virgin dew, then prattle
                  How that you dream
                        •
                      last night that Iohn the Mercer,
                  Or Tom the Drapers man at London-stone
                  Was in your bed, and what sweet work he made there.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Very right, and kis'd you oftner
                  Then ere the good man did his Cow, and hug'd you
                  As the Divell hug'd the Witch, that's right now▪
                  
               
               
                  Val.
                  When you'r married
                  (For that you will be, or else run away
                  With Costermongers, Mountebankes, or Taylors)
                  Your husbands are more subject to you then
                  Their bondmen are, whom by profuse expense
                  You breake beyond redemption from the Indies▪ the
                  Straights, or Barbary, see them lodged in Ludgate,
                  And then turne pricking semsters, till that trade
                  Fayling, you take your selves (as to the last refuge)
                  To the old occupation; till the Marshall
                  Carry you to Bridewell, of which you'r free,
                  Even by your fathers charters that have beene
                  Sometimes the masters of it, there Ile leave you,
                  So farewell wildcats.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Very right as I am a gentleman.
               
               
                  Grace.
                  I like his 
                        〈…〉
                      
                     Clar
                           •
                        , 
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
                  Or none shall be my husband.
Enter Thorowgood.
                  
               
               
                  Thor.
                  helpe me to laugh good wenches, I haue tal
                        •
                     'd
                  Thy Unkle Clare into so free an humour,
                  That hees resolv'd straight to take forth the licence,
                  And marry us ith' morning.
               
               
                  Clare.
                  What od fellow's this?
                  Know you him Cosen Grace.
                  
               
               
                  Thor.
                  Prethee good wit noe more, we've overcome
                  All forraigne enemies, and tis unfit
                  To war among our selves.
               
               
                  Grace.
                  This is the pedant
                  My father brought to mocke us, good thine stuffe,
                  Get thee home to thy parish,
                  And instruct
                  
                     Thy people wholesome Doctrine, for us,
                  We have no zeale to learne.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  Life they'l perswade me out of my selfe,
                  
                     Clare, Grace, know you not me, not Thorowgood.
                  
               
               
                  Amb.
                  
                     Thorowgood, pray put your trickes on some body,
                  More easie to be wrought on, Thorowgood, Ha, ha, ha.
Exe.
                  
               
               
                  Thor.
                  What should these wenches meane, the 
                        •
                     ive and sheares
                  Cannot resolve this mystery; they know me
                  Better then I can know my selfe: 'twas she
                  Advis'd me to this habit to deceive
                  Her uncles prying eyes, and why then
                  Should they abuse me thus? the rest were made
                  But fooles in Quarto, but I finde my selfe
                  An asse in Folio: Ile away, and if
                  I quit them not with an abuse as fine,
                  Ile say there is no quickning spirit in wine.
Exit.
                  
               
               Explicit Actus Secundus.
            
            
               Actus Tertius, Scena prima.
               Enter Thorowgood, Valentine Knowell.
               
                  Know.
                  ARE they so witty sayst thou?
               
               
                  Val.
                  You'd best try
                  The acutenesse of their intellects.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  You may endeavor
                  With the large talent of your masculine wit
                  To exceed their female sharpnesse you shall finde,
                  Though you firme and stiffe in your defence,
                  These city lasses able to take downe
                  Your most couragious fury: pray endeavour't.
               
               
                  Know.
                  That gentleman, were to usurpe your presence,
                  I finde no inclination, yet I thanke you,
                  
                     To rest a foole upon record as you doe.
               
               
                  Val.
                  How's that, my impe of understanding?
               
               
                  Know.
                  By being so egregiously abus'd
                  By two poore City infants, things that never
                  Have heard wit nam'd, unlesse 'twas when their father
                  Has cal'd his Formall foreman witty varlet,
                  For cheating hansomely, had they been some
                  Illustrious dames, the glory of Cheape-side,
                  Stars of the City, that are daily haunted
                  By this great Lord that courtly kisse their gossips,
                  It had beene possible their conversation
                  Might have instild into them so much language
                  And wit sufficient to withstand the assaults
                  Of some young Innes acourtman.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  Yes, who never
                  Had mooted in the hall or seen the revels
                  Kept in the house at Christmas.
               
               
                  Know.
                  Some such gamster might have
                  Come oft with credit, though hee'd ventur'd
                  His whole estate of wit on them and lost it,
                  But you the rookes oth' age to be ored one
                  At your owne game by city girles.
               
               
                  Val.
                  Thou art an asse,
                  A very coxcomb, there are girles ith' City
                  Able to oredoe at their owne game a hundred
                  Such feeble fellows as thy selfe, but Thorowgood,
                  
                  Leaving this infidell to his mis-beliefe,
                  Are you resolved that I shall undertake
                  The new designe we plotted?
               
               
                  Thor.
                  With what speed
                  Can be convenient, sir Timothy
                  
                  Shall be our instrument.
               
               
                  Know.
                  If there be wit in't,
                  Honour me to assist you.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  A revenge
                  Upon these peevish wenches, one of them
                  Loves me intirely, nay has vow'd me a marriage,
                  And did advise me to assume this shape,
                  
                     To cheat her uncle.
               
               
                  Val.
                  And for the other,
                  By many a shrowd cast of her eye upon me,
                  I doe suspect for all her queint dissembling,
                  She's taken with my good parts.
Enter Maudline.
                  
               
               
                  Thor.
                  Thy face I must confesse,
                  Is full of choyce allurements, see there maid,
                  How fares it with your witty mistris,
                  My gallant type of beauty, is the stomach,
                  Come down, I'm sure you are furnish'd
                  With some excuse or lamentable epistle,
                  To reconcile me to them.
               
               
                  Maud.
                  Sir I am
                  As ignorant of the interpretation of your words,
                  As of your person.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  Shee not know me neither?
               
               
                  Maud.
                  But if there be one Valentine among you,
                  A well accomplish'd gentleman.
               
               
                  Val.
                  That's I, thats I.
               
               
                  Maud.
                  Then sir,
                  I would require your privacy some minutes.
               
               
                  Val.
                  Weel be as private as thou wilt, my girle,
                  Your patience gentlewoman.
               
               
                  Know.
                  I wonder Thorowgood what businesse
                  She can have with him.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  Heel declare it.
                  See they are parting.
               
               
                  Val.
                  Tel them Ile advise ont.
               
               
                  Maud.
                  You will be speedy.
Exit Maudline.
                  
               
               
                  Val.
                  Yes, 
                        •
                     es, nere doubt my haste, say I me their servant.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  The businesse Valentine.
                  
               
               
                  Val.
                  Dost not thou know it,
                  Euen by instinct?
               
               
                  Know.
                  We cannot prophecy.
               
               
                  Val.
                  Thou art a foole then,
                  Does not the harmony of my good parts
                  Speake me the conqueror of all beauties Thorowgood.
                  
                  The wenches are on fire for me.
               
               
                  
                  Tho.
                  Their bloods
                  Are alwayes 
                        〈◊〉
                      ith' Dogdayes: but good Valentine
                  
                  Be serious, did their maid bring newes of love
                  From either of them?
               
               
                  Val.
                  From both, from both, now wert for the statute,
                  That Bigamy my tender conscience
                  Would not much be oppress'd to have two wives,
                  But one of them thy Pinnace, thou shalt man her:
                  But J delay too long, I must goe meete them;
                  I long to be a kissing, pray heaven their breath
                  Smell not of Marmalade, 'twill turne my stomacke.
               
               
                  Tho.
                  You'll practice our designe I hope.
               
               
                  Val.
                  Methodically: farewell boyes.
Ex. Val.
                  
               
               
                  Tho.
                  Pray be you Sir Timothy, know his entrance:
                  Tis such another mad-cap my Scene is.
               
               Enter Holdfast.
               
                  Hold.
                  Nay, come forward Land lord Spoild else.
Trist. Bus.
                  
                  Tis my Cosen
                        •
                      lodgings, pray be bold in't,
                  As is my Chamber. Cosen this is a Constable.
               
               
                  Tho.
                  He comes not with a warrant.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  No, Ile warrant you, I
                  Brought him Sir to see you; he's a wit,
                  A very wit, or as the modernes terme it,
                  A sparke, a meere sparke, such a one as I am▪
                  
                  Since I left off those idle toyes cald books,
                  He'll take Tobacco too, and with a grace
                  Spit ith' rub'd chamber, though his testy wife,
                  Crye fie upon him: he's a very sparke,
                  and worthy your acquaintance.
               
               
                  Tris.
                  Come forward sir, you stand as if you'd cosen'd
                  One of them with bad linnen; pray advance,
                  My Master is your Leader.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  Save you gentlemen.
               
               
                  Tho.
                  Y'are very welcome Sir, my Cosen speakes you
                  A Citizen of ranke.
               
               
                  Know.
                  That you beare office
                  Of honour in your parish.
               
               
                  Tho.
                  That y'are witty,
                  
                     Or as he sayes a sparke.
               
               
                  Know.
                  Nay, a good fellow.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  Tis granted gentlemen,
                  This is my Character, I am by trade
                  A Linnen Draper.
               
               
                  Tho.
                  Would trust me
                  For forty ells of Holland?
               
               
                  Bus.
                  Ha, how's that sir?
                  I have more wit I thanke you: cause you seeme
                  A Gentleman of quality, I care not
                  To venture as much Cambricke as shall make
                  Your Crush a gorget, but 
                        •
                     o farther, sir,
                  There is no wit in't: how's that Mr. Holdfast?
               
               
                  Hold.
                  You are a sparke still Landlord.
               
               
                  Know.
                  Ile sweare in this he's witty.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  Tis my humour,
                  My wit has halfe and one me long ere this;
                  But for my wit Ide be
                        ••
                     ie an Alderman,
                  And twirld a pondrou
                        •
                      chaine upon the bench,
                  With as much grace as can the formalst of them:
                  
                     I should have fin'd for Sheriffe, but all Guild Hall
                  Hearing I was a wit, cry'd out upon him,
                  Twill breed an alteration in the Senate,
                  To have a wit amongst them. How's that sir?
               
               
                  Know.
                  And so you mist preferment▪
                  
               
               
                  Tho.
                  And continue
                  Ith' state of wisedome still; an humble Constable?
               
               
                  Hold.
                  Yes, and an honest one, i
                        •
                     e say that for him,
                  He ne're stop'd wench in's watch.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  How's that? I scorne it,
                  
                     I've stopt a hundred in my time: how's that sir?
                  You relish wit I see.
               
               
                  Know.
                  Tis so acute,
                  No pallat but most taste it; shall's to th' Taverne?
                  Y'are for a cup I hope?
               
               
                  Bus.
                  For now sir,
                  It is my frequent use, when I have set
                  My watch, to view the Taverne, drinke a quart,
                  
                     And then backe to my businesse, and there wit in't.
               
               
                  Tho.
                  Tis granted sir: Come gentlemen, an 
                        •
                     oure
                  Is ou
                        •
                      extent of time: good Mr. Constable
                  It shall be yours. Cosen J have some businesse
                  Concernes your knowledge, as we passe along
                  J shall informe you.
Exeunt.
                  
               
               Enter Valentine, Grace, Clare, Maudlin.
               
                  Val.
                  You see I me come
                  Vpon your summons.
               
               
                  Clar.
                  Sure you mistake,
                  There's none here is so fond of you to court
                  Your cheap and vulgar presence.
               
               
                  Val.
                  Here's a Letter
                  Speaks other language, you might cloath your discourse
                  In the same phrase, or I shall laugh your folly
                  Into a milder temper, and then leave you.
               
               
                  Clar.
                  You'r very confident.
               
               
                  Val.
                  No, you're too coy,
                  I me now ith' humour to be tempted to
                  Love any of you: take me while the fit
                  Is on me, for ime sure twill not endure
                  Longer than does a wealthy widdowes griefe
                  For a loa
                        •
                     h'd husband. Speak, ha you a mind to me?
                  Speake quickly, or for ever more hereafter
                  Be sure to hold your peace, and that's a taske
                  Farre worse then death to any of your sexe.
               
               
                  Clar.
                  Her blushes does betray her, wer't to me,
                  He should finde other usage. Sir my Cosen,
                  
                     I know not how transported by her love,
                  Above her reason, has enthrald her heart
                  To your dispose. I hope sir you'r so much
                  A Gentleman, you will make civill use
                  Of her affection; twill be worth your care sir.
                  Besides the rich endearements of her youth,
                  She's Mistris of a fortune that may challeng
                        •
                     
                  
                  A noble retribution for her love.
                  
                     Weele not disturbe your conference.
Ex. Clar. Maud.
                  
               
               
                  Grace.
                  Cosen, cosen, you will not leave me thus?
                  
                     I pray let me goe sir.
               
               
                  Val.
                  Thus farre into my armes girle, that's the place
                  Thou oughtst to rest in: you expect I warrant
                  That I should court you now, and with an armie
                  Of oathes, stuft with as many sinicall falsehoods,
                  Protest I love you: by this light I know not,
                  Tis folly to dissemble, whether or no
                  
                     I can affect thee; yet thou seemst to weare
                  That pretty harmlesse innocence in thy lookes,
                  It wins my credulous thoughts to believe
                  Thou maist be vertuous.
               
               
                  Grace.
                  Sir, I hope my owne
                  Too forward zeale, in tendring you my love,
                  Will not in your good thoughts beget an ill
                  Opinion of my modesty.
               
               
                  Val.
                  Never fear
                        •
                     t:
                  That freenesse more engages my just faith
                  To embrace thy affection. I have seene some Ladyes,
                  Coy as a Voteresse below their suiters,
                  Yet with a tough-backt groome, have knowne them sin
                  With most libidinous appetite in private;
                  But J'me as fearelesse girle, that ought amisse
                  Can staine thy soule, as thou wert confident
                  In setling thy most constant choise upon
                  A stranger; yet I must desire the reason
                  Why you did love me: for my owne good parts,
                  Certaine they're not so attractive as to conquer
                  A beautie at first sight▪
                  
               
               
                  Grace.
                  Since I have
                  Disclos'd my affection to you, (although love
                  Oft times admits no reason) ile endeavour
                  To satisfie your question: the first cause
                  Moov'd me to love you, was my father.
               
               
                  Val.
                  Hang thy father
                  In's owne gold chaine: but such another word,
                  And never hope to have me; dost thou thinke
                  
                     Ile be beholding to an eight ith' hundred,
                  To such an empty caske as is thy father,
                  (Who soon did get his wealth by the old proverbe▪
                  
                  Of fooles have fortune) for a wife; but that
                  I have some mercy in me to believe
                  Thou maist be virtuous; I would not match
                  With any of my squeamish Ants of London,
                  
                  For all the wealth ith' Chamber.
               
               
                  Grace.
                  Sir, you ask'd,
                  A question of me, and will not permit
                  Me give a civill answer; as I said,
                  My father—
               
               
                  Val.
                  Father agen, farewell, my eares doe blister
                  At the harsh sound: would thou hadst beene a Bastard,
                  So thou hadst no title to his blood:
                  Another father, like a whirlewind, blowes me
                  Hence from thy sight for ever.
               
               
                  Gra.
                  Pray heare me.
                  Intends to match me to Sir Timothy
                  
                  
                     Shallow-wit, a creature onely fit for scorne;
                  Which to prevent, and taken with the fulnesse
                  Of your true worth, I rather chuse to cast
                  My reputation on your noble pitty,
                  Than stand the desperate hazard of my ruine.
               
               
                  Val.
                  She loves me by this light, this is no tricke.
                  Now to my Thorowgoods project: th'art a good wench,
                  A harmlesse wench, and I believe a sound one,
                  And I will have thee; give me thy hand: yet stay,
                  Ere I doe cast my selfe away upon thee,
                  You here shall promise Mistris, to become
                  A most obedient wife, and not according
                  To th' ancient tricke inherent to the City,
                  Raile till you be my Master.
               
               
                  Grace.
                  Never feare me.
               
               
                  Val.
                  Nor shall you, when you're at my house ith' Country
                  Be niggardly, or spoyle a dinner for
                  Want of the tother ounce of Sugar, nor
                  Repine to see me merry with my friends,
                  
                     Or curse my brothers, when they so journe with me▪
                  
                  Nor starve my servants when I am from home.
                  I must be dr
                        ••
                     k
                        •
                      sometimes 
                        •
                     oo, then you must not
                  Whine and cry out, were I 
                        •
                      maid agen,
                  Ide never marry any that does take
                  This wicked Herbe Tobacco. Those injunctions,
                  And some few hundreds mo
                        ••
                      of the same nature,
                  Seald and deliver'd to me by your promise,
                  I may be wonne to wed thee, nay to bed thee,
                  And get a race of such Heroicke children,
                  As shall intice posterity to conceive
                  Some good came from Cheapside. Your lip shall seale this.
               
               
                  Grace.
                  You see your strength
                        •
                      upon me.
               
               
                  Val.
                  Tis my good girle:
                  Thy father, armed with the trained bands o'th City,
                  Shall never pull thee from me▪ to confirme thee
                  How much I love, ile disclose a plot
                  I had to gaine thy affection.
               
               
                  Grace.
                  Tis some good one,
                  Pray let me heare it.
               
               
                  Val.
                  You see my youth and feature will admit
                  A womans Character; if I were cloath'd
                  But in the habit, should I not appeare
                  A bouncing Mary Ambr
                           •••
                        
                     
                     ▪
                  
               
               
                  Grace.
                  Some such creature▪ but to your project.
               
               
                  Val.
                  I have prepar'd mee
                  A handsome female-shape, my man without
                  Has them under his 
                        〈◊〉
                     ; and I perswaded
                  Sir Timothy, in hope that would court thee
                  I his behalfe, to have presented me
                  Here for his Neece; you marke me.
               
               
                  Grace.
                  Very well; but now
                  This the designe is uselesse.
               
               
                  Val.
                  By no meanes;
                  It must be pu
                        •
                      in action; come goe in,
                  And helpe to dresse me: Sir Timothy expects
                  To meete me in that shape here: and besides
                  In that disguise, secure I can at any time
                  
                     Steale out with you, and marry you.
               
               
                  Gra.
                  Your reason
                  Shall governe my obedience.
               
               
                  Val.
                  Come let's in then.
               
               Enter Timothy, Covet, Formall.
               
                  Tim.
                  Tis very right that sir, but yet methinkes
                  A wholsome song, sung to a fine new tune,
                  Should not be much amisse: my boy here has one,
                  And Ide be very loath, although I cannot
                  Sing, as they say, my selfe, that she should heare
                  What those, I can keep, can doe; is not this right now?
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Your pleasure shall prevaile, though to say truth,
                  Sonne Shallow-wit, for sonne I still shall call you,
                  I never lik'd a Song, unlesse the Ballad
                  Oth' famous London Prentice, or the building
                  Of Britaines Burse: for Musicke, lesse the Virginalls,
                  I never car'd for any. Does but cloy
                  The eares, but never fills the purse sonne.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Very right indeed; tis too light
                  For such a purpose.
               
               
                  Form.
                  With your leave sir,
                  Musicke is most delightfull, and young Mistris
                  
                     Grace, and her Cosen surely will receive it
                  With thankfull Equipage.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Honest Formall,
                  
                  Th'art in the right still; come exalt thy voyce
                  My little Impe of gut and haire: My Mistris
                  Shall know there's something in me.
                  How doe you
Sings.
                  
                  Like it?
               
               
                  Form.
                  Tis very odoriferous.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  I shall beginne
                  To love it better then I have done; tis a good boy,
                  A very pretty boy, and ile reward thee.
                  There's a threepence for thee.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Very right.
                  
                     Father you are too bountifull.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  He shall take it,
                  Indeed he shall; tis manners to receive
                  Mony from your betters boy: but here's my Neece.
               
               Enter Clare.
               
                  Tim.
                  Very right, I had almost forgotten, pray where's mine?
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Why, have you a Neece Sir Timothy?
                  
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Yes, yes, I've two or three, but one I sent
                  Hither, to view my Mistris in a Coach
                  An houre agoe at least.
                  Sure she is come.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  
                     Clare did you see the gentlewoman?
               
               
                  Clar.
                  None such came hither yet Sir.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  That's not right though,
                  A poxe upon her for her paines.
               
               Enter Maudlin.
               
                  Maud.
                  Mrs. your Cosen does desire some conference with you.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Maudlin,
                  Did there a Gentlewoman arrive here lately,
                  To see my daughter?
               
               
                  Maud.
                  There is one within,
                  In busie conference with her.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Very right that, he's pleading for me now.
                  Faire Damsell that's my Neece; pray tell her▪ here's
                  A Knight, a simple Uncle of hers, or so, desires her
                  Company. But here she comes, my Mistris with her; Neece
                  Tis well done, ile give thee the tother thousand to increase
                  Thy portion for't: Mistris, and how, and how do y
                        ••
                      like my
                  Neece, a plaine Country girle, or so.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  A very handsome woman, I could love her,
                  Did I but know her portion. Mistris welcome.
                  Whats in that house is yours?
               
               
                  Grace.
                  Sir Timothy,
                  
                  You have much grac'd me by the sweet acquaintance
                  Of this good gentlewoman. Pray Cosen know her;
                  She's worthy your endearment.
               
               
                  Clare.
                  
                     I shall be proud
                  To doe you service.
               
               
                  
                  Val.
                  
                     I most fortunate
                  To be esteem'd your creature.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Very right
                  Shees a poore niece of mine, yet she can speake you
                  May perceive or see.
               
               Enter Thorowgood, Holdfast, Tristram, Knowell.
               
                  Cla.
                  Life Thorowgood with young
                  
                     Holdfast, pray heaven my folly
                  Has not undone me.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  You'l please to pardon
                  Our rude intention sir, we have some businesse.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Please you declare't.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  This gentleman and my selfe,
                  Come to informe you that this sparke my Cosen,
                  Is sonne and heire to sir Geffrey Holdfast,
                  
                  And since I heare you have dispos'd your daughter
                  To that good knight, I in his fathers name,
                  Desire your niece should be his wife.
               
               
                  Cla.
                  Pray Sir speake
                  In your owne cause he needs no advocate.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  I've beene abus'd,
                  In this Sir Geffreys son the scholler?
               
               
                  Thor.
                  The very same sir.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  I am the sparke sir.
               
               
                  Know.
                  
                     Valentine, ith' name
puls off his periwig.
                  
                  Of madnesse: man why in this shape?
               
               
                  Thor.
                  
                     Valentine, Ha, ha, ha.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Very right, my niece is Valentine.
                  
               
               
                  Thor.
                  And how ist bully, hast not found these girles
                  Of a hot appetite, how often ha?
               
               
                  Val.
                  Has my Land-lady
                  Provided me a cullis, life my backe
                  Does needs a swathband.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  What meanes this gentleman?
               
               
                  Thor.
                  Nothing sir,
                  But to informe you what strange things your neice,
                  
                     And daughter and, nay never blush he has
                  Perform'd it better then your uncles foreman.
                  I know he has.
               
               
                  Covet.
                  
                     Timothy this abu
                        •
                     e must not be thus put up,
                  Did not you say I was your Neice.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Very right, but it was Valentine.
                  
               
               
                  Know.
                  He has beene here all night 
                        〈◊〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  Grace.
                  Cosen we are basely betray'd.
               
               
                  Cla.
                  Take courage.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  Doe you thinke sir, my Cosen shall mixe with such
                  Stale ware that keepe their gamsters in their chambers.
               
               
                  Know.
                  Or this knight have Valentines reversions?
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Very right, I scorne it.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  Keepe them. they I serve to set up some twise
                  Broken Merchant, or undone Linnen-draper, come away
                  
                     Valentine, thou hast made a brave discovery. Farewell,
                  My witty virgines, you are pay
                        •
                      now.
Exeunt.
                  
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Ile be reveng'd for this, and if it cost me
                  Halfe my estate Formall send post, for sir Geffrey,
                  
                  The whole towne shall know of this abuse▪
                  
                  Ile make you fast enough.
               
               Explicit Actus terpius.
            
            
               Actus Quartus, Scena prima.
               Grace, Clare, Busie, Luce.
               
                  Busie.
                  THey are both sparkes, that's certaine, 
                        ••
                     ere
                  I take them in my watch, Ile make them stoope
                  Under my staffe of office, Mistris Clare,
                  
                  Though I'me a Citizen, and by my charter,
                  Am not allowed much wit, as being free
                  Oth Linnen-drapers, and a man in office,
                  
                     Yet if my counsell, if you please to follow it,
                  Doe not revenge you on these sawcy mad caps,
                  May taking up of Holland at deare rates,
                  Be quite abjur'd by courtiers: and I canvas'd
                  Out of authority, how's that now?
               
               
                  Clare.
                  Master Busie,
                  
                  You seeme of sage discretion: and to say
                  Truth, I conceive you have the stocke of wit
                  Belonging to the city in your custody,
                  You are the chamber of London, where that treasure
                  Is hoarded up, and I doe hope you can
                  Be true and secret.
               
               
                  Busie.
                  How's that Lady?
                  
                     I were unworthy else to thrive by linnen,
                  Could I not keepe smocke secrets for your uncle,
                  Your father mistris Grace, I care not for him,
                  Although he be right worshipful and an Alderman,
                  As I may say to you he has no 
                        〈◊〉
                     
                  
                  Wit then the rest oth' bench: what lies in's thumbe-ring,
                  Yet I doe love you deerely for the kindnesse
                  Shown to my girle here, and because you have
                  Some flashes in your braines: and since you have
                  Opend the case to me, ere we proceed
                  To sentence, tell me seriously doe not you two
                  Love Valentine, and Freewit?
               
               
                  Grace.
                  For my owne part,
                  And I dare say as much too for my cosen,
                  Their memories are as distant from our hearts,
                  As civill honesty from theirs.
               
               
                  Clare.
                  And though
                  I well could like that Freewit for a husband,
                  Yet in mere spight because he shal not have me,
                  Ile wed the next mans offered me.
               
               
                  Busie.
                  How's that?
                  I would my wife were dead; two comely lasses,
                  Such as sometimes I light on in my watch,
                  would make fit wives for such rude sparks, and t'shal
                  Goe hard but I will for your sakes sweete beauties,
                  
                     Number a brace of such sound 
                        •
                     u
                        •
                     tell to them,
                  If you'l give way to it.
               
               
                  Cla.
                  And crowne thee for
                  The king of witty Constables use our names,
                  Or any thing to draw them forward, that
                  Wee may in triumph laugh at their disgrace,
                  And weel procure a pattent, to continue
                  Thy office to thee, during life: and after
                  To hire some ingenious poet that shall keepe
                  Thy fame alive in a brave Epitaph
                  Grav'd on thy marble.
               
               Enter Covet, Sir Geffrey Holdfast, Sir Timothy, young Holdfast.
               
                  Geff
                  What varlet should that be trow?
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Truth I know not,
                  Nor can conjecture, yet I 
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
                  Him to be truely yours, because attird
                  Ith' habit and the phrase of a right Scholler,
                  And for your sonne, pardon me master Holdfast,
                  
                  I tooke you for some lewd audacious varlet,
                  That had usurpt that title.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  I imagine
                  It was some bastard of my fathers, gotten
                  In youth upon his Taylors wife or Landresse,
                  He has good store of them, but master Alderman
                  You now conceive I me son and heire apparent
                  Unto the Holdfasts, whosoever got me,
                  That's not much matter.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  How's that, anon before I set my watch,
                  Ile visit you agen: meanetime, pray give my
                  Daughter Luce leave to come home, her sister
                  Poore wretched, is troubled with a paine ith'
                  Bottome oth' body, pricks even to her very heart,
                  And I would have Luce goe toth' Pothecaries,
                  And get some Besar stone, they say 'twill cure her.
                  Farewell good Ladies, you'l be sure to come Luce.
                     Ex. Busie.
                  
               
               
                  
                  Geff.
                  Are these the maidens, I promise you master
                  Alderman the'r virgins of good feature, and I shall
                  Be well apaid if my sonne match to either,
                  Which lik'st thou best boy?
               
               
                  Hold.
                  Both of them good father,
                  Be not so troublesome, but let me take
                  A view of them: Sir Timothy which doe you
                  Like best of these two Ladies?
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Which doe you
                  Like best good Mr. Holdfast.
                  
               
               
                  Hold.
                  Yours shall be
                  The choyce noble Sir Timothy.
                  
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Yours indeed,
                  Magnanimous Mr. Holdfast.
                  
               
               
                  Hold.
                  On my gentility yours.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Yours on my knighthood.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Good sir Timothy,
                  
                  No striving, they are free for you▪ and for
                  The staine those idle gallants put upon them,
                  Twas on my credit gentlemen to keepe
                  All other suitors off, in hope by that meanes
                  To obtaine them for themselves.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Tis very likely
                  That Valentine's a wagge.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Daughter and neice,
                  This hopefull gentleman, and this good knight are
                  By my care provided for your husbands, pray use
                  Them as befits their worth, and take it
                  As a fatherly admonition; either resolve
                  To marry these or none.
               
               
                  Cla.
                  Tis a hard choyce sir,
                  Yet rather then our maiden-heads shall starve,
                  Weel feed on this course fare, young wenches uncle,
                  Are like young hungry Hawkes: they'l stoope at
                  Jack-daws, when they can meet with no better prey,
                  Draw neerer thou doughty knight, and thou good
                  Squire oth' damsells, Uncle these youthes are bashfull in the
                  Presence of you two their grave Elders: your grim beards,
                  
                     And azure notes able are to fright
                  Their precise love to silence.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Shees ith' right,
                  Ime scuh a fearefull foole I cannot speake,
                  If any body looke on me.
               
               
                  Geff.
                  Let's withdraw,
                  Now plye thy businesse boy.
               
               
                  Clare.
                  So now the game
Exe. Sir Geffery and Covet.
                  
                  Will begin presently: I pray you tell me
                  Which of you is the valiant Rosicleer,
                  Dares breake his Launce on me.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Marry that would I
                  
                  If I durst be so bold, mine is a stiffe one,
                  And will pricke sorely.
               
               
                  Clare.
                  A fooles bable ist not?
                  But come in briefe toth' purpose: is it you
                  Sir knight of the ill favored face,
                  That would have me for your Dulcina?
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Very right,
                  You know my minde as well it seemes as if
                  You'r in my belly.
               
               
                  Grace.
                  So then you are sped:
                  This gentleman's my comely spouse that must be,
                  Twere fitting Cosen Clare ert be a bargaine,
                  They know on what conditions they doe cast
                  Themselves away upon us.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  Twas discreetly
                  Thought on, I would doe nothing rashly.
               
               
                  Clare.
                  Marke then
                  You men that will transforme your selves to
                  Monsters, wretches that will become so miserable,
                  You'l hang your selves: &amp; think it a faire rid dance,
                  Marke what youl come to, if you be so mad,
                  So desperate mad to wed us, you must first,
                  Resolve like patient gulls to have your no
                        •
                     es
                  Twingd if ours'chance to itch: your eares like asses
                  When they grow lasie cropt, least they oreheare
                  Our chamber secrets, for our recreation,
                  
                     And least with too much ease we should grow resty,
                  Weel beat you daily: while you like tame Spanells,
                  Shall fawne and licke our shooe-strings.
               
               
                  Grace.
                  Nor expect,
                  To get a good word from us in a twelve month,
                  Hourely revilings and perpetuall noyses
                  Shall be as favours taken that we would
                  Vouchsafe to spend in such regardlesse trifles,
                  Wee'l be as proud as ere our mothers were,
                  When she was Lady Majoresse, and you humble,
                  As her trim hench-boyes: whatsoever servants
                  You kept before, although they were your grandsires,
                  You shall turne off and limmit your attendants,
                  As tis the city fashion to a woman
                  Butler, that shall not dare without our license,
                  To let you have a penny pot of sacke
                  To give a frugall entertainment, to
                  Your visiting friends.
               
               
                  Clare.
                  If you have a brother,
                  Kinseman, or friend, that does in pitty grieve at
                  The tyranny you live in, him it shall be felony
                  To converse with, we in tissue and plush will
                  Brave it while you walke in fustian, weel
                  When we please have our faire coach and horses
                  To carry us up to London to aske counsell of
                  Our mothers and our gossips how to abuse you.
                  You shall be still obedient, we commanding,
                  And if a Lord or courtly gentleman,
                  Whom we stile servant, out of love sometimes
                  Gives us a visit, you shall not repine:
                  If we forsake your bed to goe to his.
               
               
                  Gra.
                  And if you chance, as fooles will oft be
                  Peeping to spye us coup
                        •
                     ing, with respective silence,
                  You shall depart, not daring to bedew
                  Your eyes with tears for grief that you are cuckolds,
                  Nor to exalt your honors above your neighbours,
                  But big with joy triumph that you have wives
                  That are in so much credit, as to have
                  
                     Persons of quality, take the paines to get your
                  Heires to your large revenewes.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Very right,
                  Tis not the fashion now adayes for knights
                  To get their owne sons, tis sufficient for us
                  If we can leave them lands, no matter who
                  Was their true fathers.
               
               
                  Cla.
                  Say sir Timothy
                  
                  If upon these conditions you can like
                  The match is perfect: but faith take my counsell,
                  Make not your selves meere raskalls: the reproach
                  To boyes and schollers, subjects fit for ballads,
                  Not worthy M Ps name to them, good Sir Timothy
                  
                  Have pitty on your selfe, and marry rather
                  In your owne tribe, some damsell that can churne,
                  Make Cheese and Apple pies with Currants in them,
                  And Mr. Holdfast twere farre better for you to
                  Match with some grave doctors impe at Cambridge
                  Or else as twas your use when you'r a student,
                  Lye with your bed maker.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Very right,
                  Yet I doe know all this is but in jest,
                  To make us love you better.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  True sir Timothy;
                  Speake as it were to let us understand
                  By an Irony as we the learned call it,
                  How well they meane to use us: therefore in
                  My judgement it were requisit with all speed,
                  While there in this good humour
                  To strike the match up.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Very right, we are
                  No Jackdawes to be fright with these Scar-crowes,
                  Mistris your hand, and if you'l have me so,
                  If not so likewise: but you will repent it,
                  You'l scarcely meet two that will offer fairer
                  Then we have done.
               
               
                  Cla.
                  But doe you meane performance,
                  Truely of these conditions.
               
               
                  
                  Hold.
                  As sincerely
                  As ere we meane to eate.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Or drinke good Ale
                  At mother Huffs a mornings.
               
               
                  Grace.
                  You'll confesse this
                  Before the Priest and witnesses.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  Before
                  The Congregation, or at a Commencement
                  Before the University.
               
               
                  Clar.
                  That you'll be
                  Honest contented Cuckolds, beare your heads
                  As peaceably, and with as much obedience,
                  As the tam'st beast ith' City.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  On my Knight-hood.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  On my gentility.
               
               
                  Clar.
                  Why then strike hands on't;
                  Since you will needs undoe your selves, 'twere folly
                  To indeavour to redeeme you: but this night
                  We will be marry'd, and in private,
                  Not yours nor our friends being acquainted with it.
                  Weele meet you any where, procure the license,
                  And weele be ready; so farewell: to night,
                  Or not at all lets heare from you.
               
               Exeunt Clara, Grace.
               
                  Hold.
                  And feele us too ere morning, 'tshal goe hard else.
                  Sir Timothy, was not this wisely carryed:
                  To let them have their sayings? but we will not
                  Be such starke fooles to doe what we have promis'd;
                  When they're ours once, we may rule them easily
                  At our owne pleasures.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Very right; and use them
                  At our owne pleasures: But see here's your Mr.
                  And Mr. Constable your Landlord.
               
               Enter Grimes, Busie.
               
                  Hold.
                  Landlord, welcome
                  On my Gentility, to my house that must be.
                  Thou thoughtst, because I did weare Lokram shirts
                  Ide no wit: but harke thee, I have got
                  
                     The wench of Gold: Sir Timothy, and I
                  Have strucke the stroake old boy: to night's the night,
                  Thou shalt know more of it ere twelve of Cl
                        •••
                     e,
                  And then believe me: Grimes goe you to th'office;
                  There's mony, fetch a Licence.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  There's more money,
                  Bring me a Licence too; sure as we woo'd
                  Weele wed together,
               
               
                  Busie.
                  How's this? Gentlemen
                  I shall have gloves I hope.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  And favours too,
                  Thy daughter Nell shall have my Bride gatters,
                  And thy fore-man my poynts: But hones
                        •
                      Landlord,
                  I know th' art excellent at a device,
                  This matter must be private, not my father,
                  Nor Mr. Alderman must be acquainted,
                  Till all is finished: Could thy wit but helpe us
                  To plot this finely: Clare and Grace will meet us,
                  At any place where weele appoynt.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  How's that?
                  Ile set you presently ith' way; my house
                  Shall be your randevous: soone after ten.
                  The houre of meeting: there Ile have prepar'd
                  For the two Ladyes a Sedan: that shall
                  Carry them thence unseene through the watch
                  At Ludgate, where I exercise my office,
                  Into white-Friers, there shall a little Levite
                  Meet you, and give you to the lawfull bed.
                  With much celerity: give me your mony, &amp; ile take out the licence.
                  How's that now?
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Very right.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  Meane time my daughter Lu
                           •
                        e shall give them notice
                  How all's contriv'd, they'll be willing,
                  When they shall know the managing's committed
                  To my discretion; but about your businesse;
                  It will grow late oth' suddaine.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  Come Sir Timothy.
                     Ex. Hold. Tim. Grimes.
                  
               
               
                  Bus.
                  So, so, as I would have it: if I doe not
                  Doe something to exalt the fame of Constables,
                  
                     May I be hang'd upon my staffe of Office.
                  Ha! Valentine and Freewit with my daughter?
                  They must not see me.
Exit.
                  
               
               Enter Valentine, Free-wit, Luce.
               
                  Luce.
                  Tis certaine Mr. Freewit they are contracted,
                  And this night to be marryed: I am sorry
                  You should be thus supplanted, by two such
                  Dull witlesse ideots: but they are so bent on't,
                  That when I speake in your behalfes, my Mistris
Ent. Clar. Grace.
                  
                  Stopt my mouth with a blow oth' lips: see here
                  They are themselves; if you doe any good,
                  It must be now or never.
Ex. Luce.
                  
               
               
                  Clar. Grace.
                  Ha, ha, ha.
               
               
                  Free.
                  What doe the Monkyes laugh at?
               
               
                  Clar.
                  To behold
                  Two such trim gallants as your selves, like Asses,
                  Shaking your empty Noddles ore the Oates
                  You faine would eate, but must not lick your lips at.
                  You thought to have wonne us by your wit, where lyes it?
                  In your gay cloaths; perhaps so, if you can
                  Out-sweare the faithfull Tayler, that's unpaid yet.
                  Or cheat your Sempstresse. Troth make safe retreat
                  Into the Suburbs, there you may finde cast wenches,
                  Who will in pitty have you: and for dowry,
                  Bring you an ampler stocke of hot diseases,
                  Than you are already furnish'd with. We Orphans
                  Oth' City have more charity to our selves,
                  Than to wed
                        •
                     Surgeons boxes.
               
               
                  Grace.
                  When our portions
                  Shall be consum'd in Pothecaries Bills,
                  Or giving Doctors fees; or at best use,
                  Serve but to purchase Sacke; or be as tribute
                  Paid toth' three Kings; or piously bestowed
                  Upon Ierusalem.
                  
               
               
                  Free.
                  No, you'd best reserve them,
                  Till th
                        •
                     se you wed be beg'd for fooles; and then
                  
                     They will be seas'd to better use. You think now
                  You have broake our gulls with anger that you have
                  Resolv'd on other husbands: who would have you?
                  But two such ideots, fit to be the styles
                  To the vast pride and lust lurkes in your blood,
                  Derivative from the City: for our selves,
                  Why should you have a thought we could descend
                  So much from gentries honour, to mixe with you?
                  Tis true, you appeare handsome, but you paint
                  Worse then a Bawd, or waiting-woman, in love
                  With the spruce Chaplaine.
               
               
                  Val.
                  For your haire let's see
                  Your eye-browes badge: oh tis not your owne;
                  Be modest and confesse it: tis a Peruke,
                  I saw it at the French-mans in the Strand,
                  The other day: and though you hold your head up,
                  It is suppos'd it growes too neare your shoulders,
                  And you weare iron bodyes, to keep downe
                  And rectifie the crooked paths that are
                  In this same hill your body.
               
               
                  Free.
                  Nay, besides
                  Y'are infinitely lascivious, tis reported
                  Y'ave kild the reverend Alderman at least,
                  Ten Prentises, besides foure journy-men.
                  With too much labour: That you will be drunke
                  Our selves can testifie: and with these imperfections
                  This inexhausted Magazin of vices,
                  Could you imagine we would have you? no.
                  Heaven give you joy, with your well-chosen spouses:
                  May they be patient Cuckolds, that's all the harme
                  Weele wish them: the more fooles, more fit for husbands
                  To such hot wild cats.
               
               
                  Clare.
                  Well Mr. Free-wit,
                  
                  
                     I thought how ever we, in mirth, or madnesse,
                  Could have transgrest civility, that you
                  Would not have made such a severe construction
                  Of our intentions: how i've lov'd you, heavens
                  Can beare me righteous witnesse; but mans faith
weeps.
                  
                  
                     Is 
                        •
                     ickle as his shadow, never seene,
                  But when the Sunne shines.
               
               
                  Grace.
                  And that you, whom I
                  Even at the first view lov'd, and fixt my heart on:
                  Should not alone contemne me, but with these
                  Abuses wound my fame, torments my soule
                  Beyond the strength of patience, heaven forgive you.
               
               
                  Free.
                  They are our owne, deare Valentine: our owne as surely,
                  As if the officious Priest had put the Ring
                  Upon their pretty fingers; why you need not
                  Take words with such unkindnesse Clare yourselves
                  Being the occasion.
               
               
                  Clar.
                  Such discourtesies
                  From friends; nay, such beloved friends as you were,
                  Wounds deeply Mr. Freewit.
                  
               
               
                  Free.
                  Prethee Clara
                  
                  No more remonstrances of this unkindnesse,
                  Drye thy faire eyes, or I shall else grow childish,
                  And weep for company: poore heart i'me sorry
                  Th'art thus distemper'd; prethee sweet forgive me;
                  We will be friends, and instantly steale hence,
                  And end all difference in a happy marriage.
               
               
                  Clar.
                  Ha, ha, ha: hold the mans head, heel swowne
                  I feare oth' suddaine: marry you; goe boast
                  How you've abus'd us, and doe not forget
                  This part oth' story, twill much grace the action,
                  That you were foold agen into beliefe
                  That we could love you: ha, ha, ha.
Ex. Clare, Grace.
                  
               
               
                  
                     V
                           •
                        l.
                  
                  We have made our selves fine fooles, a poxe upon them:
                  I knew their teares could not be serious:
                  They onely fell from their left eye, as wealthy
                  Young widowes weep for their old husbands, Freewit
                  
                  They're lost, past all recovery.
               
               
                  Free.
                  Who can helpe it;
                  There are more wives ith' Kingdome; yet Ime vext
                  That two such gulls should carry them: lets goe seeke
                  Sir Timothy and my Cozen Holdfast out,
                  And geld them, then proclaime them to be Eunuchs.
                  
                     That course may spoile their marriage.
Enter Busie.
                  
               
               
                  Bus.
                  I have o're-heard them all, and it 
                        •
                     onduces.
                  Much to my purpose: now, or never Busie
                  
                  Shew thy selfe a true sparke, that Constables
                  Hereafter may be thought to have some wit▪
                  
                  More than is in their staffe. Good day to you gallants,
                  I have some businesse with you.
               
               
                  Val.
                  Your name is Busie?
                  
               
               
                  Bus.
                  The same body,
                  Your friend, although a Constable▪ there were two Ladyes
                  Went lately from you.
               
               
                  Free.
                  What of that?
               
               
                  Bus.
                  They told me, as I am of their councell, that they lov'd you.
                  And though some words of cou
                        •
                     se had past between you,
                  As oft does among friends: you know the Proverbe put lately
                  In a Ballad, where I learnd it, that amantiumirae amoris redinteg
                           •
                        atio est: yet that was but in jest, and in all haste,
                  Wished me to assure you, that if you would speedily
                  Take out the Licences this very night, twixt nine and ten, at my
                  House they would meet you, and joyne with you in Matrimony.
               
               
                  Free.
                  Is this truth?
               
               
                  Bus.
                  How's that? upon the faith sir of a man in office,
                  You may believe me: for a P
                        •
                     iest, leave that
                  To my care gentlemen, ile have one ready
                  Privately in White-Friers, the house anon
                  
                     I will enforme you, and what way to take
                  To misse pursuit, if any should endeavour
                  Your apprehension.
               
               
                  Val.
                  How may we deserve this kindnes from you?
               
               
                  Bus.
                  When tis done, then thanke me; meane time make haste, and get the licences.
Ex. Free. Val.
                  
                  
                     I will pursue the rest, and if I fit not some body,
                  Ent. Luce.
                  Let me be held as other of my fellowes are, Asses in office.
                  
                     Luce thou art come as aptly as I could wish: be sure at nine of
                  Clock to be at home, and if you can bring with you two of the gentlewomens gownes, question not why?
                  But on my blessing doe it; if this hit,
                  Time shall report some Constables have wit.
Ex.
                  
               
               Explicit Actus Quartus.
            
            
               
               Actus Quintus, Scena prima.
               The Watch.
               
                  1 Watch.
                  
                  IT is a cold night neighbour,
                  And tis likely we shall have frost,
                  That will make Sea-coales deare: heaven helpe poore people.
                  Is no newes stirring neighbour?
               
               
                  
                     Men. 2 Wat.
                  
                  Yes, to day
                  
                     I heard such newes, heaven blesse us, as would make
                  A mans heart quake in's belly; strange, and true,
                  It came up in a Carret Boat from Sandwich
                  Last tide; an Oister wife, a good old Woman,
                  Heard it at Billingsgate, and told my wife on it,
               
               
                  3 Watch.
                  
                  What is it? pray lets heare it.
               
               
                  
                     Men. 2 Wat.
                  
                  Marry, that twixt Deale
                  
                  And Dover, one fishing for Flounders, drew
                  A Spaniards body up, slaine ith' late sea-fight,
                  And searching him for monie, found ith' sets
                  Of his great Ruste the — I shall think on't presently,
                  Tis a hard word—the Inquisition.
               
               
                  1 Wat.
                  
                  O monstrous, what's that?
                  
                     I have not heard of such a Beast before.
               
               
                  
                     Men. 3 Wat.
                  
                  You've heard nothing then:
                  It is a Monster very like the Man-drake
                  Was shewen at Temple Barre.
               
               
                  2 Wat.
                  
                  You have heard nothing neither:
                  The Monster's no such Monster: neighbor Mandivell
                  
                  You are a zealous brother, a Translator,
                  Tis such a Monster as will swallow thee,
                  And all the Brethren at Amsterdam,
                  
                  
                     And in new England at a morsell: verilies,
                  Your yeas, and nayes will not appease its stomacke,
                  Twill sup them up as easily as a Tayler
                  Would doe sixe hot loaves in a morning fasting,
                  And yet dine after.
               
               Enter Busie and Parson.
               
                  Bus.
                  There is the Licence sir for Mr. Holdfast,
                  
                  And wise Sir Timothy; you have instructions
                  How things ought to be carryed: when I have
                  Dispos'd my Watch, I will be there my selfe;
                  Meane time good Sir be carefull.
               
               
                  Pars.
                  Doubt me not,
                  Good Mr. Constable; tis not the first time
                  I have espoused couples of as much worship,
                  Behinde the Brickhills: when tis done, tis done,
                  And surely consummate.
               
               Ex. Parson.
               
                  Bus.
                  Well said neighbours,
                  Y'are chatting wisely o're your Bils and Lanthorns,
                  As becomes Watch-men of discretion: pray you
                  Let's have no wit amongst you; no discourse
                  O'the Common-wealth; I need not neighbours give you
                  Your charge to night: onely for fashion sake.
                  Draw neare and be attentive.
               
               
                  3 Men.
                  
                  I have edified
                  More by your charge I promise you, than by
                  Many a mornings exercise.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  First, then,
                  You shall be sure to keep the peace; that is,
                  If any quarrell, be ith' streets, sit still, and keepe
                  Your rusty Bills from blood-shed; and as't began
                  So let it end: onely your zeales may wish
                  The Devill part them.
               
               
                  1 Wat.
                  
                  Forward Mr. Constable.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  Next, if a thiefe chance to passe through your watch,
                  Let him depart in peace; for should you stay him,
                  To purchase his redemption he'le impart
                  Some of his stolne goods, and you're apt to take them,
                  Which makes you accessary to his theft,
                  
                     And so fit food for T
                        ••
                     urne.
               
               
                  Men.
                  Good advise,
                  I promise you, if we have grace to follow it.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  Next if a drunkard of a man disguisd,
                  Desire to passe the gate, by all means open't,
                  You'l run your selves intoth' premunire,
                  For your authority stretches but to men,
                  And they are beasts by statute.
               
               
                  1 Wat.
                  
                  Such as we are,
                  Horn'd beasts he means.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  How's that; you carry lanthornes,
                  Thou hast wit, and Ile reward't, there's foure tokens
                  To buy the cheese: next for the female creatures,
                  Which the severer officers ith' suburbs
                  Terme girles, or wenches, let them passe without
                  Examining where they been: or taking from them
                  A single token: lasse good soules, they get
                  Their mony hard, with labours of their bodies,
                  And to exact on those were even extortion
                  Beyond a brokers.
               
               
                  Men.
                  Yet they doe't
                  Without the City, I have heard a brewer,
                  Being one yeare in office, got as much from those
                  Good soules as bought him a new mash-fat,
                  And mended all his coolers.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  How's that? we are bidden
                  Not to take ill examples, for your selves you have
                  Free leave for th' good oth' common wealth to
                  Sleepe after eleven: meane time you may play at
                  Tray trip, or cockall for blacke puddings,
                  So now your charge is finish'd.
               
               Enter Sir Timothy, Grimes, Holdfast, with a Sedan.
               
                  1 Wat.
                  
                  Stand, who goes there?
               
               
                  Men.
                  Come before Mr. Constable.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  Tis I Landlord,
                  
                     There's sixteenpence to buy thy watch some 
                        〈◊〉
                     .
                  Prithee tie up their tongues.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  And there's four 
                        〈◊〉
                     
                  
                  To purchase tosts to it.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  How's that, pray stay 
                        〈…〉
                     ,
                  You'r sober men and fit 
                        〈…〉
                     :
                  Whither goes all this carriage? 
                        〈…〉
                     ,
                  These are the cunningst wodden bawnly houses,
                  Were ere invented, and these blew coate men 
                        〈◊〉
                     ,
                  The most authenticke pimps: set downe and open
                  Your chaire of sinne you 
                        〈◊〉
                     
                  
               
               
                  Hold.
                  Why good Landlord,
                  You will spoyle all, doe you not know your tenent,
                  Not Ieremy Holdfast?
               
               
                  Bus.
                  How's that? not my father
                  Upon a watch, Ile lay my life they've stolne
                  Some city orph
                        ••
                     e, they'r so loath to have
                  Their load discover'd.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  There's ten shillings▪ Landlord
                  To buy thee sack: although it be thy office,
                  And thou art sworne to't, for a friend tis lawfull
                  To breake an oath: I will forsweare my selfe
                  A hundred times to doe thee good.
               
               
                  Exeunt Holdfast, Timothy, Grimes, 
                        ••
                     d Seda
                        ••
                     
                  
               
               
                  Bus.
                  Iam
                  Appeas'd, march on: looke you remember my
                  Instructions: so this money was well gotten,
                  And 'tshall as merrily be spent, you need no
                  More, club your halfe pence sparkes to purchase Ale,
                  You've an exchequer: ha
                        •
                      another chariot,
Int.
                  
                  This same should be some Lady from a labor,
                  Her waiters smell of groning cheese: goodnight
                  Gentlemen, pay the Porter, what ist twelve pence▪
                  
                  Share it amongst you.
               
               
                  Men.
                  Mr. Constable
                  Tis very late, a fire and a browne tost now,
                  With some of mother Trundles Ale, I promise you
                  Would comfort much the inwards.
               
               
                  
                  Bus.
                  How's that hang it,
                  It is hereticall: Sack's the Orthodoxall
                  Liquor: and now I thinke ont, you two, and Mendwell
                  
                  Shall with me to th' Saint Johns head: there is
                  A cup of pure Canary, and wee have it,
                  Twill breake your heads, your owne bills,
                  And weare your Lanthornes in your noses bullies:
                  My masters, you that stay behinde observe
                  My charge with strictnesse, and if any businesse
                  Be of importance, call me.
               
               
                  Exit cum C
                        •••
                     ri
                        •
                     .
               
               
                  1 Wat.
                  
                  Now my masters,
                  Shall I expound a motion to you, shall wee
                  Share, and share like this mony?
               
               
                  4 Wat.
                  
                  With all our hearts▪ 
                     Omnes
                     ▪
                  
               
               
                  1 Wat.
                  
                  Lets see what comes it to a peece▪ there's eleven groats,
                  And we are five of us, that is — that is, let me see seven pence a piece.
                  No, no, I lye, tis eight pence, and six pence over.
               
               
                  4 Wat.
                  
                  Right, right, this it is to be booke-learn'd,
                  He's a good Arimetician: but stay neighbours,
                  Here comes more company: come before the Constable.
               
               Enter Covet, Sir Geffery, Formall with a Linke.
               
                  Cov.
                  This is the government the city keepes,
                  How doe you lik't Sir Geffery?
               
               
                  Geff.
                  Very well,
                  I doe not thinke all Christendome affoords
                  The like for formall discipline.
               
               
                  1 Wat.
                  
                  Leave your pratin
                        •
                     ,
                  And come before the Constable, though he be not
                  Here himselfe, theres those that can examine you?
               
               
                  Cov.
                  You doe well masters to keepe diligent watch,
                  Theres many varlets at these houres commit
                  Disorders in the City: Wheres the constable?
               
               
                  1 Wat.
                  
                  Good master Alderman, I cry your worship mercy,
                  Because your worship wanted your worshipfull horse.
                  We did not know you: Mr. Constable
                  
                     And please your worship is but at next doore
                  Drinking a pint of sacke
               
               
                  Cov.
                  How at a Taverne?
               
               
                  1 Wat.
                  
                  At the Saint Johns head▪
                  
                  And please your worship, where if your worship please,
                  You may have excellent s
                        •
                     cke, and please your worship.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  This is the fowlst enormity I ever
                  Heard on ith' city, that a Constable,
                  Who ought to see good orders kep
                        •
                     , should be
                  At these unlawfull houres, breeding disorder▪
                  
                  And in an open Taverne. Good Sir Geffery
                  
                  Beare me but company, Ile make the knave
                  A faire example to all men in office, how they
                  Come nere a bush: watchmen looke well
                  To the charge committed to you: for your Constable,
                  Ile make him kisse the counter, light on Formall.
                  
               
               Exit Covet, cum caeteris.
               
                  1 Wat.
                  
                  A shrewd man this, if ere he live to be
                  Lord Majors, ha mercy upon us; neighbours surely
                  Tis very late, and I was up till twelve
                  Last night a mending my wives bodies, shall we
                  Each to his bulke and take a nod?
               
               
                  Omnes.
                  Agreed, agreed.

                        Ex
                              •
                           . Watch.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Busie, M
                        •
                     ndwell, watchmen 
                        〈◊〉
                      in a Taverne.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  Set downe your trusty Bills my sparkes, and let us
                  Watch ore a cup of Sacke, here tis will make you
                  Each one an Alderman: a bigger glasse boy,
                  I doe not love these thimbles, they are fit
                  For none but precise Taylors, that doe sip,
                  In zeale, and sweare cuds nigs over their wine,
                  To cheat their customers: so this is something.
                  A score or two of these my sparkes, will set
                  Our braines a floate, and then weel talke as wisely,
                  As all the common Counsell, how's that now?
               
               
                  Men.
                  Mr. Constable
                  
                     Y'are in the right I promise you: I feele
                  My selfe already growing from a watchman
                  Into a head-borow.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  How's that? thou shalt be
                  A Constable within this halfe houre Mendwell,
                  
                  Carry thy staffe with the red Crosse and Dagger
                  In as much state, as the best gold smith,
                  That ere bore office in Cheap-side; here's to thee,
                  Hang care and Cosenage; let mercers use it
                  In the darke shops: I am a Linnen Draper,
                  Love wit and Sacke, and am resolv'd to thrive by't,
                  When they shall break like bottles: Here lets 
                        ••
                     nvas
                  This quart, and then will bumbaste off another,
                  And drinke a health to Holland, and the mad boyes
                  That traile the puissant Pike there: how's that; doe you peepe?
               
               Enter Fidlers Boy.
               
                  Boy.
                  Please you hear a good song Gentlemen?
               
               
                  Bus.
                  These squeakers, doe claime more
                  Priviledge in a Taverne,
                  Then a man in office; into every roome
                  They thrust their frisled heads; and Ide bin at it
                  With some distressed Damsell, that I had taken
                  Late in my watch, thus Ide bin serv'd: ile have
                  An Edict made against them at Guild Hall,
                  
                  Next sitting certainely.
               
               
                  Boy.
                  A very new song and please your worships gentlemen.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  There you lye boy;
                  I doubt it is some lamentable stuffe,
                  Oth' Swine-fac'd ge
                        ••
                     lewoman, and that youle grunt out
                  Worse than a parish Boare when he makes love
                  Unto the Vicars sow; her story's stale boy,
                  'T has beene already in two playes.
               
               
                  Boy.
                  An't please your worships,
                  My song is of a Constable.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  How's that? a Constable,
                  Tis not my selfe; I hope ime not exalted
                  Into a ballad: Dare you sirrah abuse
                  Officers in your Madrigalls; you deserve,
                  
                     And so does he that made 
                        〈◊〉
                     , to be whipt for't.
               
               
                  Boy.
                  Pray heare it sir: tis no such matter on my credit.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  How's that? Well, on thy credit I will heare it.
                  Callin your company; welcome my Master
                        •
                     :
                  Ent. Musicians.
                  Here: wet your 
                        〈◊〉
                      first, then thund
                        ••
                      forth
                  Some lofty Sonnets in the praise of Constables;
                  And never feare the whipping-post hereafter.
               
               
                  
                     
                        
                           Constables 2 Song.
                           
                              SIng and rejoyce, the day is gone.
                              And the wholsome night appeares.
                              In which the Constable on Throne
                              Of trusty bench, does with his Pe
                                    •
                                 res
                              The comely watch; men 
                                    〈◊〉
                                  of health,
                              Sleep for the good oth' Common-wealth.
                           
                           
                              Tis his office to doe so,
                              Being bound to keep the peace.
                              And in quiet sleep all know
                              Mortall jarre
                                    •
                                 , and lewd brawles cease:
                              A Constable may then for's health,
                              Sleep for the good oth' Common-wealth.
                           
                           
                              Vnlesse with Nobler thoughts inspir'd,
                              To the Taverne here sort,
                              Where with Sacke his Sences fir'd,
                              He raignes as fairy King in Court;
                              Drinking many a lusty health,
                              Then sleepes for th' good oth' Common-wealth.
                           
                           
                              With a comely girle, whom late
                              He had taken in his watch,
                              Oft he steales out of the gate
                              Her at the old sport to watch,
                              Though it may impaire his health,
                              He sleeps with her for th' good oth' Common-wealth.
                           
                           
                              
                              Who then can Constables deny
                              To be persons brave and witty,
                              Since they onely are the eye,
                              The Glory, the delight 
                                    •
                                 th' City,
                              That with staffe, and 
                                    〈◊〉
                                  light
                              Are like blacke Pluto Princes of the night.
                           
                        
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     
                        〈◊〉
                     .
                  An excellent Ditty I promise you.
               
               
                  Busie.
                  Well done boy.
                  There's twelve pence for you Knaves, and tell the Poet
                  That made it, if heele come to me, ile give him
                  A quart of Sacke to whet his Muse.
Ent. Drawer.
                  
               
               
                  Draw.
                  Sir, below there's one enquires for you, and I suppose him
                  To be at least an Alderman.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  And if he be
                  The Major and his horse, let them come up.
                  Flinch Squeakers into another roome: Good Mr. Alderman
                  Tis strange you are abroad so late, wil't please you
Ent. Cov. Sir Geff. Formall.
                  
                  To taste a cup a Sack, twill warme your stomacke
                  After your walking.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  No Sirrah, ile not be
                  Partaker of your riot: this the watch
                  You keep good Mr. Constable? introth
                  The City's much beholding to your care,
                  And they shall understand it, in a Taverne
                  A fit place for an Officer: but ile send you
                  To one fitter for you to the Counter.
                  Lay hands I charge you, beare him hence,
                  Ile have you all laid fast else.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  How's that? I hope youle let us
                  Drinke off our sacke first: twere farre better sir,
                  In my poore judgment, that you sate down in peace,
                  As does befit your gravity, and drinke
                  A friendly cup or two: then for the first
                  Offence to send your neighbour to the Counter:
                  Pray sir be not so fierce; a glasse, or two
                  Will mollifie your hard heart.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Will you not stirre knaves?
                  
                     Where is the Master of the house? ile make
                  This Busie an example.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  Pray doe not sir:
                  Perhaps y'are bashfull sir, and will not dr
                        •
                     nke,
                  Cause you want coyn
                        •
                      to pay: ile lend you some;
                  Or if you scorne to borrow, you may dip
                  Your chaine; a good pawne never shames the master.
                  Pray sit downe sir; we just now had Musicke,
                  Ile call them in agen.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Within, the master of the house, ile have
                  These knaves indicted for this bold contempt,
                  And whipt about the City.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  You may see sir,
                  My Watch-men know their duty, they'll obey
                  None but the Constable, and ile experience,
                  If they'le know me for one: My masters, take
                  This Alderman and his company I charge you,
                  And carry them straight to th' Counter, ile secure you
                  'Gainst all the harme that followes.
               
               Seise on the Alderman and Sir Geffery.
               
                  Men.
                  Come, come, come along sir.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Dare you doe this sirrah?
               
               
                  Bus.
                  Yes, and answer't too sir.
                  Y'ave met a Constable that has the wit,
                  To know the power of's office: neighbour Mendwel,
                  
                  Because they'le take him for a Rat ith' Counter,
                  And Ide be loath to have his reverend b
                        ••
                     rd
                  Be twitch'd off for his Garnish, to my house
                  Convey him, and that comely Knight, and bid
                  My maid shew them a Chamber; ile deale kindlier
                  With you, then you'd have done with me: there watch them
                  Till I come home: how's that now?
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Sirrah, sirrah, ile make you smoak for this.
               
               
                  Mend.
                  Come, we lose time sir.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  Let him have
                  A good fire pray you. So, all works as't had bin
                  Molded afore in waxe: boy there's your reckoning.
                  Now to my sparkes, Ive done that will be talkt on ith' City,
                  And registred, a Constable was witty.
               
               
                  
                  Freewit, Thorowgood, Valentine, Luce, Clare.
               
               
                  Clar.
                  You thinke you have us sure now. This same Busie
                  
                  Is a meere cheating Rascall.
               
               
                  Thor.
                  Come, your rage
                  Is uselesse now: he has done better for you,
                  Than I by th' circumstance perceive you had
                  Intended for your selves: what would you've done
                  With two such March-pane husbands? I believe,
                  For all you set a good face on the matter,
                  Twas your owne plot.
               
               
                  Clar.
                  Ours? then may we dye Virgins,
                  And these same trusty youths, now cald our husbands,
                  Be suddainly transform'd to Eunuchs; we
                  Had thought young Holdfast, and Sir Timothy
                  
                  Had bin the Squires had usher'd us, and them
                  We had resolv'd to couple with.
               
               
                  Free.
                  Sweete Clare
                  
                  No more of this; for all your queint dissembling.
                  
                     I know you love us, better than to part
                  For a slight quarrell; now we're man and wife,
                  And we will love you, if you'll be obedient,
                  And get such Boyes upon you, as shall people
                  Cheap side with wit five generations after us.
               
               
                  Val.
                  Feare not thy fathers frownes: sweet Grace I have
                  An Aldermans heire a joyncture.
               
               Enter Busie.
               
                  Bus.
                  Blesse you my hearts of gold, and give you joy.
                  Frowne not good Mistris Clare, I knew your minde
                  And so fulfild it.
               
               
                  Free.
                  Constable, ile have
                  Thy Annalls writ, in a farre larger volume,
                  Than Speed or Hollingshed.
                  
               
               
                  Clar.
                  Well Mr. Busie,
                  
                  Y'ave serv'd us sweetly.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  How's that? I hope your husbands
                  Anon will serve you sweetlier: faith I thought
                  There was no wit in't, that you two should cast
                  
                     Your selves away on two such gulls, your portions.
                  Deserv'd more noble husband
                        •
                     : therefore finely
                  After you were gone downe, to take your Chariot,
                  Instead of them, when ith' meane while my daughters
                  Held in discou
                        •
                     se, I sent these, now your husbands▪
                  
                  To exercise their office: Now you are marryed.
                  I shall have Gloves I hope?
               
               
                  Clar.
                  Yes, and such favours
                  As thou shalt weare in triumph: but what have you
                  Done with our other sweet-hearts?
               
               
                  Bus.
                  How's that? matcht them
                  To two will hold them play: Come will you 
                        •
                     ravaile
                  Your father Mistris Grace is at my house,
                  Thither you shall, and if he will be angry,
                  Let him be pleas'd agen
                        •
                      Advance my sparkes▪
                  
                  Ile be your valiant 
                        〈…〉
                     
                     Exeunt.
                  
               
               Sir Geffery, Covet, Formall, Watchmen.
               
                  Geff.
                  Storme not so Mr. Alderman, the man
                  Has done no more beleev't, than what his office
                  Will beare him out in.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Ile spend a thousand
                  Pound, but Ile be reveng'd: a sawcy rascall
                  In my owne Ward to serve me thus?
               
               Enter Timothy, Holdfast, Grimes, Luce, Nell.
               
                  Hold.
                  Nay, come forward Ladyes,
                  Although your father sweet-heart, be in our search,
                  Be not abash'd, come forward, though you kept
                  Your tongues in peace, ere since our going forth,
                  And nere spake word, unlesse before the Parson
                  When we committed Matrimony, yet now
                  Pull of
                        •
                      your Maskes and Vailes, and shew your faces,
                  Be not asham'd of them.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Who's here? Sir Timothy and your sonne, Ile lay
                  My life on't they have struck a marriage up
                  Without our knowledge.
               
               
                  Geff.
                  Very likely Ieremy.
                  
               
               
                  
                  Hold.
                  No more words sir, tis done, I and sir Timothy
                  
                  we hit the white: Good father Covet be not
                  
                     
                        •
                     ungry mood now I have wed your daughter,
                  And he your Neece, weele use them kindly: pray you
                  Bid give us joy; your daughter is so fearefull,
                  She dares not aske you blessing.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  This qualifies all anger, I forgive them.
               
               
                  Luce.
                  Forgive us sir? you doe not heare us aske it,
                  Not need we your remission.
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Ha! who are these! Sir Geffery we are cheated
                  Abhominably, cheated by this Constable,
                  This rascall Busie, these are his daughters.
               
               
                  Luce.
                  Nor are we asham'd
                  To owne him for our father, that has provided
                  Us two such wealthy husbands.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  
                     Nell, I did not thinke you would have serv'd me thus
                  Unkindly, gentle Nell.
                  
               
               
                  Nel.
                  Unkindly sir, in what? to make you master
                  Of all I have. Ile use you kindly trust me;
                  When you come drunke a nights home, in the morning
                  Ile make you amber Caudles.
               
               
                  Hold.
                  Saist thou so;
                  Give me thy hand: Father pray be not angry,
                  My Wife's my wife, and so I will maintaine her
                  Gainst all the world. Sir Timothy, your spouse
                  Is not to be contemn'd, she's a good girle.
                  And therefore pray regard her.
               
               
                  Tim.
                  Very like; for your sake
                  I will doe much: Although I find my selfe
                  Made a starke Asse. Come hither Luce
                  
               
               Enter Clare, Grace, Thorougood, Freewit, Valentine, Busie.
               
                  Grace.
                  Your pardon Sir, and blessing.
               
               
                  Clar.
                  We have done sir
                  What cannot be undone, now if you will
                  Be foolish now, and vexe your selves, you may
                  Be laught at for your labour; they're our husbands,
                  And we no cause now to repent our choyce,
                  Nor you Sir to repine at.
               
               
                  Free.
                  Our duties
                  
                     And after carriage, shall deserve your love,
                  Nor our fortunes Sir so m
                        •
                     ane, but may
                  Merit their portions
               
               
                  Cov.
                  Well▪ you shall not
                  Report me cruell; you have my consent,
                  And blessing with it; neighbour Busie, Ile
                  Be friend
                        •
                      with you, and at my intreaty
                  Sir Geffery shall be reconcil'd.
               
               
                  Bus.
                  How's that?
                  Give me thy 
                        〈◊〉
                      good brother Knight, my daughters
                  Shall not come without portions; they shall have
                  Each one a Bolt of Holland
                     ▪ that's enough.
                  Sonne Knight give me thine too; and sonne Holdfast
                  
                  Weele be as merry boyes, and drinke old Sacke
                  In plenteous glasses, till we all grow witty,
                  A
                        •
                      humorous Poets▪ to your beds, the're ready,
                  Your wedding dinner shall be mine, weele dance.
                  And have the Song oth' Constable; March faire,
                  And get each one a chopping boy by Morning;
                  I and my Watchmen here will drinke your healths,
                  Though we doe lose our owne by it.
               
               
                  Free.
                  Mr. Busie,
                  
                  Wee're all beholding to you, and 'tis fit,
                  We should confesse this Constable had wit.
               
            
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

