
   
      
         
            The xliiij. sermon of M. Giulio of Milane, touchyng the Lordes supper
            [Giulio, da Milano].
         
         
            
               1559
            
         
         Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01765
            STC 11901
            ESTC S118377
            99853584
            99853584
            18974
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01765)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18974)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1100:12)
         
         
            
               
                  The xliiij. sermon of M. Giulio of Milane, touchyng the Lordes supper
                  [Giulio, da Milano].
               
               [64] p.   
               
                  By Rycharde Iugge, printer to the Quenes Maiestie,
                  [Imprinted at London :
                  [1559?]]
               
               
                  Imprint from colophon; publication date suggested by STC.
                  Signatures: A-D.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Sermons, English --  16th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-09
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-10
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-10
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               
                  
                     ❧ The xliiii. Sermon of M. Gialio of Milane, touchyng the Lordes ſupper.
                  Dedicated to the worſhypfull myſtres Anne Carowe.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            The .xliiii. Sermon of Maſter Giulio of Milane, touchyng the Lordes Supper.
            
               SAthan in all tymes hath deuiſed, howe he might by ſubtiltie defyle and deface with al kind of ſuperſtition the Lordes ſupper. In the time of Saint Paul God did ſmite and ſharpely puniſhe the Churche of the Corinthians, becauſe they dyd euyll vſe this Sacrament. In our tymes (becauſe we wyll not recoūt the errours of all worldes) be brought in, ſundry kyndes of ſuperſticious hipocriſies, about the vſage of this Supper. All

whiche I wyll not nowe name in perticuler, for ſpendynge of tyme. I wyll onely intreate of that which is of moſt force, that we may learne after what ſorte we ought to preſent our ſelues to this holy table. Some wryters moued by theſe wordes of S. Paule: He that cateth vnworthelye of this breade and this wyne, cateth his owne iudgement: they haue takē in hand to declare how a man may worthely vſe this Sacrament. And after much debating, they haue thus reſolued them ſelues: that a mā hath than worthely eaten this bread, whē he is in the ſtate of grace. And paſſing on a little further, they haue expounded &amp; ſaid, that a man is than in ſtate of grace, when he is purged and clenſed of all mortall and veniall ſinnes. In this ſort they reſolue

them ſelues, becauſe their ſtudye is to vnderſtande after what ſort ſynnes be purged, &amp; howe a man may come into the ſtate of grace. The writers of theſe dayes be of diuers iudgementes touchyng this matter. Some ſay that through contricion, confeſſion, and ſatiſfaction of workes, a man is purged from all ſinne, and doth deſerue the ſtate of grace. But when a mā doth diligently ſearch what is this meritorious worke of this great goodnes, thei do very yll agree vpon the matter. For ſome ſay that this ſatiſfactorye worke is faſtyng, accompanyed with teares and prayer. Other adde this and ſay that our praiers muſt be done with ſackcloth and other chaſtiſementes of the fleſhe. Others do ſaye, that not

only theſe workes be neceſſarye to deſerue the ſtate of grace: but alſo there muſte be almoſe, the whiche doth clenſe a man from ſinne.
            The furder we be ſeperated frō the pure time of the Apoſtles, ſo much greater is the nomber of ſatiſfactions, and the thyng is ſo augmented, that mens conſciences be brought into feare, error, and deſperation, and in them ſelues ſo confounded, that they knowe not where to fynde the beginning. Wherfore a man is neuer certayne to do theſe ſatiſfactory workes ſo perfectlye that he may deſerue to be in the ſtate of grace: No more there is no conſcience of anye lyuynge man, be he neuer ſo holye, that cā aſſure himſelf to be without ſinne, yf he ſhall beholde his

merite, and the dignitie of his own workes. Let vs then leaue of ſuch encomberaunce of conſcience: and for the eatyng of the Lordes ſupper, let vs folow the facion that was vſed by the Apoſtles. Paule doeth not bring our mindes to this deſperation and doubtfulneſſe, when he doth exhorte the Churche of the Corinthians to vſe worthelye this Supper: But this he ſaith, that than do we worthely vſe this ſacrament, when we do acknowlege our ſelues to be vnworthye, and laye open our ſinnes before Ieſus Chriſt, that he through his mercye woulde make vs worthye. That we ſhoulde alſo diſpayre of our ſelues, &amp; all our workes: for that we myght receaue comforte in hym, that we ſhuld humble our

ſelues, that in Chriſt we myght be exalted: that we ſhoulde acknowledge our ſelues ſinners, that in Chriſte Ieſu we myght be iuſtified: therfore we mai not thynke to come to this Sacramēt boyde of ſinne, nether that wee be worthye to deſerue ſo great a benefit. But let vs thus thinke, that we being poore, do go to a liberall geuer: that beyng ſicke, we go to a gentle phiſitian: And beyng ſinners, doo runne to our ſauiour. Thus the dignitie wherof Paul ſpeaketh that is in this Supper, is perfourmed by fayth, at thoſe tymes when we beleue that all the merites of Chriſt be oures: And that we behaue our ſelues in loue towards our neygbours as this daye ſhalbe declared.
            This error that I haue nowe

ſpoken of, is one of the moſt notable errours yt is in the church conſerning ye vſage of the lordes Supper. The ſeconde error is this, the which hath ben and is continuallye preached, that vnder breade and wine is conteyned the body &amp; bloud of Chriſte Ieſu. Theſe preachers &amp; ſcoolemaſters of mens conſciences, do only occupy them ſelues to perſwade two thynges to the people.
            The firſt, that in this ſacramēt is the body and bloud of Chriſt. The other, that all Chriſtians ought with great deſyre to receaue this Sacrament, becauſe thei do receiue the body &amp; bloud of Ieſu Chriſt. And theſe reuerend fathers ſay, that men may ſearch no further, becauſe that all matters of faith ought to be

beleued ſimplye. But to what ende a man ought to vſe this Sacrament, and what commoditie a Chriſtian getteth by it: theſe our reuerēde fathers haue not ſo muche as touched one worde, to comfort ſuche conſciences as be in trouble. Theſe fathers do not conſider that this theyr fayth may be in the deuyl, and in all his members. It is no hard thing to perſwade this theyr article to the people. For yf thei beleue that Ieſus Chriſt is ryſen from death, that by a miracle he entred, the gate beyng ſhut, into the houſe where the Apoſtles were gathered together, without any hurt to his body: alſo if they beleue manye other miracles that was done of the Lord whyle he lyued here vpon earth: By the ſame reaſon

it is an eaſy mater to perſwade the Chriſtian people, yt in bread and wine there is the body and bloud of Ieſu Chriſt. This this were a ſmall matter whervpon to ſtay: but we muſt ſearch ſomthing further. Theſe ſpirituall maſters thynke to haue done theyr offyce, whenſoeuer they haue perſwaded this to the people: that in the ſacrament is the bodye of Ieſu Chriſte, and that they be bounde to receaue it.
            We be come nowe to this paſſe: lette a man aſke a Chriſtian yf he wyll communicate, he wylī aunſwere yea. And if you aſke him wherfore he wyll do ſo, he aunſwereth, becauſe the Churche hath ſo ordeyned. But yf we ſhoulde conſyder the matter ſomthyng more deepelye, and ſearche for what pourpoſe and

to what end this was ordeined: he wyll aunſwer, to receaue the body and bloud of Chriſt Ieſu. And they thynke to knowe enough, whē they can after this ſort geue accompt of theyr conſcience. But as I haue already ſayde, yf this thing be no otherwayes conſidered, this fayth is nothing: becauſe euery naughtye perſon can haue this faith. And he that can geue no better accompte of his fayth, then is commenly done nowe a dayes, lette hym take heede to receaue this ſacrament. To admit vnto the ſupper thoſe perſōs thus euyll enſtructed: is as a manne ſhould admit a brute beaſt to an holy banquet, to the great ignominie of Ieſu Chriſte, and confuſion of the church, It is then erpedient that the Chriſtian be

otherwaies inſtructed, and that he knowe what thing this Sacrament is, and for what ende the Lorde hath ordeyned it, for what cauſe alſo the church doth vſe it: what profite the faithful do receaue by it: and manye other thinges which be neceſſary to vnderſtande, as this daye is made manifeſt. I ſay the miniſter ought to vſe in this Sacrament the ſelfe ſame meanes, as is vſed in baptiſme, whē a child is baptiſed, or yet any other perſon growen in yeres. The whiche partie when he goeth to be baptiſed, it is not ſufficient to deſire to be vnited to the church &amp; that he beleueth ſuerlye that this waſhyng is baptiſme, and that this ſacrament is ordeined of God: No nor it is no ſufficient cauſe that the partie doeth

deſyre to be baptiſed, becauſe this belief may be both in good and euyll. But the principall point that the miniſter doth deſire to know of him that is baptiſed, is this: Whether he doth forſake the deuyll with all his works, and that he that is baptiſed do confeſſe ſo to do openly. That done, the miniſter doth aſke yf he beleue in the father, in the ſonne, and in the holye ghoſt. In which demaunde the mynyſter doth ſearche out the fayth of him that receaueth the Sacrament: of which faith, the Church muſt be aſſured. Therefore it is nedeful that euery one that is baptiſed, ſhuld know to geue accompte of theyr fayth in the face of the congregation. Howe muche more then oughte this to be done in the Sacrament

of the Lordes ſupper, the which is only miniſtred to ſuch as be of ſufficient yeres, &amp; that be able to vnderſtande the word preached.
            Therfore when any man ſhal firſt communicate, it is erpedient to heare his confeſſion vppon this article. For by that confeſſion the Churche maye iudge yf ſuche a perſon bee a fitte veſſell to receaue ſuche a Sacramente: that by this meanes there maye bee a difference of Iudas and other brutyſſhe creatures. There is then to be wyſſhed ſome other fayth, muche dyfferynge from this of the Hypocrytes, the whiche thynke they haue done enough, whē they haue perfourmed that worke, becauſe it is ſo

ordeyned. Were it not a great folly yf one of rype yeres ſhould be baptiſed, and yf he were aſked wherfore art thou baptiſed could make no other aunſwere but that he is baptyſed becauſe it is ſo ordeyned. And hauynge no other ſtaye wherevnto the Chriſtian fayth ſhould ſtaye vppon: ſhould not ſuch one be almoſt iudged and taken for a diſſimuled Chriſtian? Seing than ye Sacramentes be witneſſes of our fayth: it is needefull that they whiche wyll preſent them ſelues to this table, be well inſtructed to geue accomptes of theyr fayth. Therfore it is conuement that ſuche ſhoulde be eramined of the miniſter of the Churche.
            Firſt the miniſter doth aſke the Chriſtiā what is this ſacramēt?

The faithful doth anſwere, that this ſacrament is an aſſuraunce and gage, left of Ieſu Chriſte in his church, for that none ſhould doubt, but that his body is dead for vs, &amp; that hys bloud is ſhed for the remiſſion of our ſinnes. Then the miniſter ſhal aſke him what he intendeth to do, when he doth preſent him ſelfe to this ſupper. The faithfull doth aunſwere, I do beleue to receaue al the merites of Ieſus Chriſt, and to receaue them in ſuche ſorte, that they bee no more Chriſtes, but that they bee myne, in no leſſe force then yf I with my owne proper bodye had merited the kingdome of heauen. Then the miniſter doth thys aſke and ſay: what aſſuraunce haſt thou to aſſure thy ſelfe after this ſort of the workes of thy Lorde? The

faythfull doth aunſwere, I do thys aſſure my ſelfe vppon the wordes that Ieſu Chryſt ſpake in his laſt ſupper, when he ſaid, take and eate, this is my body, thys is the cuppe of the newe Teſtamente in my bloud, the whiche ſhalbe ſhed for you. Agayne the miniſter doth aſke, after what maner doeſt thou thynke to eate thys bodye, and drinke this bloud? The faithful doth aunſwere: I do beleue to eate it ſpiritually, in ſuche ſort as the goſpell vnder the ſignes of bread and wyne doth offer, &amp; my fayth doth receaue. The miniſter doth aſke, wherefore doeſt thou not thynke to eate the carnal body of Chriſt? The faithful doth aunſwere, becauſe it is the ſpirite that geueth me life, &amp; the fleſhe profiteth nothynge. For this cauſe ſayeth the Chriſtian,

am I come hyther vnto the company of the faythfull for to receaue this ſacrament, becauſe I beleue that the bodye of my Lorde is dead for me, &amp; that hys bloud is ſhed for my redemptiō: therfore my fayth is confirmed &amp; comforted by this ſacrament. The miniſter doth demaunde, what profit &amp; commoditie receueth thy ſoule of thys holy ſupper? The faithful doth anſwere, the commoditie that I receaue therby, is ye I am made a membre of Chriſte, who is the head of the Churche: And I do tranſfourme my ſelfe into my neighbour, ſo ye I become one ſoule, one hart, &amp; one wil wt him. With theſe &amp; other lyke inſtructions, ought the Chriſtian people to be inſtructed, when they doe fyrſt preſent them ſelues to thys holye ſupper. Thys Sacramente

is a witneſſe of our fayth, and alſo an open confeſſion of the ſame: For when we do frequent it, we do declare the death of the Lord. The miniſter of the churh ought to admyt none to thys ſupper, who were not very well inſtructed, and alſo openly had made confeſſion of theſe thynges: And whē thys faith is not, all thinges be decayed and of no force. Let vs now then conſider what difference is betwixt the fyrſt fayth &amp; this ſeconde. Thou beleueſt by thy fyrſt fayth, that in this ſacrament is the bodye and bloud of Ieſu Chriſt.
            What profit haſt thou by this beliefe? The deuil and any wicked perſon may haue this faith, and yet for all that ſhall not be ſaued. Thou beleueſt that to vſe this ſacramēt, is a good worke.

The deuyll beleueth alſo &amp; knoweth that it is a good woorke: ſo ye this common faith maketh man no better then the deuyll, or any other naughtie perſon: Therfore it is requiſite to haue ſome other fayth. But ſo ſone as the true &amp; lyuely fayth ſpringeth in our hartes, and ſpeaketh to our conſcience, it ſayeth: Ah from henceforth be mery, ſeinge Chriſt is wholy thine in all reſpectes, becauſe that in this ſupper thou doeſt receaue all hys merites, he hath ſupped vp in his bloud all thy ſinnes. Confeſſe therefore from henceforth openly in thys Sacrament, the death of thy Lord, becauſe he is preſent in all thy doinges.
            This ſeconde fayth farre paſſeth the fyrſt, the which maketh thee no better then the Deuyll,

no nor than any hipocrite. But this ſecond chriſtian faith, doth geue vnto thee, al that treaſure encloſed, and promyſed in theſe wordes of Ieſu Chriſte: Take &amp; eate this is my body. Therefore it is nedefull that the miniſter of the Church be wel aduiſed in geuinge thys ſacrament to any body, yf he haue not before vnderſtande his faith. And by that confeſſion which the Chriſtian hath made in ye church, to iudge that he is worthye to eate thys ſupper, and to be made one bodi with Ieſus Chriſt. This confeſſion is to be had of neceſſitie, becauſe that ſacramētes be ordained for this ende, that they may be witneſſes, &amp; alſo an open confeſſion of our faith. It is expedient that we liue after ſuche ſort in thys mortall lyfe, yt we helpe our neyghbour, &amp; that we ſhuld ſhew our faith, the which is hid

in our hartes, openly by ſome outwarde token to the Church. That is bi baptiſme, &amp; with the ſupper of the lorde. The goſpell muſt bee confeſſed openly wt our mouth, and for this cauſe alſo is this ſacrament ordayned, that al the worlde maye knowe that we be Chriſtians: he that vſeth not the ſacrament of this ſort, doth greuouſly offend hys lord. What ſhall profit thee this fyrſt faith of the hipocrites, when in paſſing ouer of this worlde, the deuilles ſhal tempt thee? if thou ſhalt ſaye I beleue that I haue receaued the body of Chryſt, becauſe it is ſo ordayned: In lyke ſort wil the deuil ſay. And I beleue alſo that thou haſte receaued it. This faith will nothinge profit thee, nor yet eaſe thee of thy troubles. But if thou be inſtructed in the true fayth: thou ſhalt aunſwere the deuill &amp; ſay.

Ah Satan thou tyraunt, what power haſte thou in me? I am armed in thys ſacrament with the merites of Ieſu Chriſt, who is made mine and I am become his: what canſt thou do againſt me? I do not eſteme thee, vſe thy force, I do not feare it: my lorde is greater then thou. With thys fayth ought euery one to be armed, not only to paſſe ouer this lyfe, but alſo in all parylles whiles we ſhall here lyue. After thys ſort it becommeth a Chriſtian to be inſtructed, yf this ſacrament ſhould profit him. For yf thou haſt not thys fayth, although thou hadeſt al the Prieſtes of the worlde aboute thee with the Sacrament in theyr handes, it ſhould profit thee nothinge. We reade in the boke of the Kynges, that the people of

Iſraell fyghting with the Philiſtines, were ouerthrowen, put to flyght, and diſperſed. After thys ouerthrowe, the Elders of the people of Iſraell, gathered them ſelues together and ſayde to them: for thys cauſe are the Philiſtines lordes and conquerours in this warre, becauſe the arke of the couenaunte is not 1. Reg. 11 with vs. It was then ordayned that the arke ſhould be brought into the army, of whiche when it came, al the people were glad. The Iewes cryed with greate ioye, thinkinge therby to haue made affrayde the Philiſtines, triumphinge of victoritie, not yet gotten. The people of Iſrael being proude for the preſence of the arke of the Lord, they beganne battell a freſhe with the Philiſtines, but with great loſſe

and more ſhame, they were put to flight &amp; ouerthrowen. Howe came this to paſſe, that ye Iewes were thus ſubdued &amp; euyll handeled? The arke of the lorde was preſent, in which they had ſuch confidence, that they thought God to bee preſent, and that he had there a peculier habitation. Of thys they had no leſſe confidence, then hath the hipocrites of this ſacrament. Why dyd not God helpe the Iewes: becauſe the Hebrues were voide of faith, thought by the preſence of the arke, to haue god to be fauourable. The very ſelfe ſame thinge doth come to paſſe in our times, to ſuch as truſt in the outward worke of this ſacramēt, and be not inſtructed with ye true faith where with a chriſtian ought to be endued. Therefore the deuill hath more power of ſuche, after thei haue receaued ye ſacrament,

then euer he had before. Let vs then leaue of this illuſion, and beleue, that that Chriſtian whiche is partaker of Ieſu Chriſte by faith, doth become of the ſelf ſame ſubſtaunce with his lord. This is that coniunction of the church wt Chriſt, whereof Paule ſpake ſaying: that we ſhould encreaſe Ephe. 11 by all meanes in Chryſt, who is the head, whervnto the body faſtened &amp; ioyned by euery kind of coniuction, according to ye power &amp; meſure of euery part, cauſeth the body to encreaſe in edifiyng it ſelf by charitie. Our bodies be mēbres of Ieſu chriſt, and the habitation of the holye ghoſt. Theſe benifites be geuen vnto vs, becauſe our lord is ioyned vnto vs both in ſpirite &amp; in bodi. This coniunction that we haue wt Ieſu Chryſt, can not be declared, wt greater prayſe then Paul did, when he ſaid, that our

fleſhe is the fleſhe of Chriſt, and Ephe. v. our bones the bones of him. In no leſſe force thē was the bones and fleſhe of Eua formed of Adam.
            Seinge we haue nowe made manyfeſte the inſtruction that ought to be kept when a Chriſtian will vſe thys ſacrament or ſupper: It is nowe nedefull to declare what fruite and commoditie we haue of this ſupper. I ſaye thys ſupper doth brynge forth two fruites to a Chriſtian. The fyrſt is, that we become after a ſort the brethren of Ieſu Chryſt, and that we be the ſelfe ſame ſubſtaunce with him. The ſecond fruite is, that we be trāſfourmed after a ſort with oure neighbour, that we become one harte, and one ſoule with hym. And after this ſort al the whole

Churche is vnited with Ieſus Chryſt and in it ſelf. Theſe two fruites be deſcribed of Saynct Paule who ſayth: The cuppe of bleſſynge whiche we bleſſe, is it not the cōmunion of the bloud of Chriſt? The bread whiche we breake, is it not the communion of the bodi of Chriſt? Becauſe that many be one bread and one body, therefore all we be partakers of one bread, whenſoeuer we do eate of thys bread, that wytneſſeth that thys meate is common to all beleuers. And ſeyng that in this ſacrament al thinges be common: let vs receaue together that, the whiche Chryſte hath wrought for vs. Thys is that commoditie of whiche I haue ſo often ſpoken. If the chriſtian haue fayth, and beleue that the body and bloud

of the lorde be hys, he hath then Ieſu Chriſt in him with all hys benifites. Thenceforth the hart is meri, reioyſeth &amp; triumpheth, truſtyng to be ſaued, not by his owne goodnes, but by the innocent bloud of Ieſu Chriſt. This is to be trāſfourmed into chriſt, and to be his body &amp; bloud: for that he taketh vpon him al our miſeries, all oure vnhappynes, &amp; al our miſhappes. Theſe two thinges be ioyned together, and agree in one, that is the goodnes of Chriſt and our ſinne, that we ſhould be of the ſame health and ſtrength, if we be one ſoule with Ieſu Chriſt: what thynge ſhuld we deſire more then that. Theſe and ſuch other like thinges, ought to bee preached and taught the people, when they fall a reaſonynge of thys ſacrament,

for that end, that the chriſtians may vnderſtande to geue accompt to the Church of theyr ſayth. But ypocriſie hath nowe ſuche power and force, that the Chriſtians be onely geuen to ceremonyes, the whiche be more ſuperſticious then godly. They vſe this ſacrament only becauſe it is ſo ordayned: becauſe they thynke to receaue the bodye of Ieſu Chriſt: there thei ſtay. And leauyng the true vſe of thys ſacrament, they haue framed of their owne heades, many other commodities without the warantiſe of the worde of god. The fyrſte commoditie is thys, yf a man heare maſſe, all day he can haue no harme: If thou haſte loſte any thynge, or yf thou bee robbed, cauſe maſſe to be ſayde, and thou ſhalte fynde thy

thinges, and that ſhalbe reſtored that was robbed. If thou wyll fynde grace in maryage, or bee healed of any dyſeaſe, or yf thou wouldeſte haue a proſperous iourney, or delyuered from any peryll, cauſe maſſe to be ſayd of ſuche or ſuche a Sainct, vnto whom the wyſedome of man hath grauen theyr peculyer office. Theſe be not the commodities of this ſupper. For it is not intituled that a manne ſhoulde therby obtayne proſperitie, honour, ryches, and other worldly goodes: but it is principally ordayned for a remembraunce of the lordes death, that we ſhould be vnited to him, neuer to be ſeperated. There is alſo an other cauſe, wherfore this ſacrament is ordayned, and that is: that it ſhould be in ſtede of an erhortation

to ſtirre vs vp to loue and vnitie with our neighbour. For this cauſe doth the Lord participate his bodye to vs, that he may be wholy vnited to vs, and we ioyned together with hym. And being al ioyned in one miſticall bodye, we ſhoulde be the members one of another. This ſociete which we ought to haue together, is figured bi the bread and wine whiche be offered in this ſupper. The bread is made of many cornes, the whiche be after a ſorte made one and mingled together, ſo that the one can not be ſeperated from the other. Euen ſo we Chryſtians ought to be vnited together wt 
               
                  ••
               ch charite, that one could not be ſeperated frō another. This vnitie was deſcribed of Saint Paule as I haue ſayde before:

who ſayde that all thoſe which were partakers of this holye breade, be one body. The Chriſtian than ſhall reape a greate profite by this Sacrament, yf he ſhall be tranſfourmed into his neyghbour, and doth preferre the wealth, honour, and profite of his neyghbour before his owne. Out of this greate charitie ſpryngeth theſe good thoughtes in vs, which can not offende, which can not deſpyſe, nor by any meanes tormēt our neyghbour. And by that meanes is not Ieſu Chriſt offended, neither torne, nor yet rente in peeces. Therfore we can not be ſeperated from our neyghbour, but we be alſo ſeperated from Ieſu Chriſte: we can not loue our brother, if we loue him not in Ieſu Chriſte. We ought to

haue the ſelfe ſame care of our neyghbour, as we haue of our ſelues. We be one the membre of another, and we be altogether the bodye of Ieſu Chriſte, who is the head. Lyke as there is no one part in our carnal body that is hurt, but that all the reſt of the members feele ſmart by the ſame: Euen ſo ought we to haue compaſſion one vpon another, when he is in trouble, and ſuffereth any ſorowe: and our neyghbours buſines ought no leſſe to be oures, then our owne. This is to be mery with them that be mery, &amp; to ſorowe with them that ſorowe, and to be diſpoſed with the ſelfe ſame mynde one towardes another. Theſe two frutes be at large ſet forth of S. Auguſtin, who ſaid: The faithfull do nowe knowe

this to be the bodi of Chriſt, not to deſpiſe to be ye body of Chriſt. They become the body of Chriſt yf they wyll lyue by the ſpirite of Chriſt: of the ſpirite of Chriſt lyueth nothyng but the body of Chriſt. Vnderſtande this brethren that I haue ſpokē. Thou art a man and haſt a ſpirit and a body: thy ſpirite is inuiſible, thy body viſible. Tell me what lyueth? liueth the ſpirite by the bodye, or the bodye through the ſpirite? The bodye to conclude lyueth by the ſpirite. Wylt thou ti
                  〈◊…〉
                by the ſpirit of Chriſt, become Chriſtes body. Tell me, liueth my body by the vertue of thy ſpirite? my body liueth by his owne ſpirite, and thy body by the vertue of thy owne ſpirite. The bodye of Chryſte can not lyue but by the ſpirite of

Chriſt. Therfore Saint Paule makynge manifeſt this breade, ſayde: we be one bread and one bodye. O Sacrament of Godlyneſſe, O ſigne of vnitie, O knot of charitie. What oration either of Demoſthenes, or yet of Marcus Cicero, or of any other famous wryter, coulde ſtirre vp or moue more vehementlye to the loue of our neighbour, than this ſacrament moueth? What prouocation can be more lyuely and ſenſible then this? Let all the Oratoures of the worlde come forth and perſwade vs to the loue of oure neyghboure with theyr polyſhed Orations: Let them vſe all the coloures of Khethoricke and all theyr connyng, they ſhall neuer brynge ſuche a perſwaſion as this ſacrament doth preache.
            
               
The wyſe men of the worlde perſwade vs to loue our neighbour, becauſe we be of the ſelfe ſame ſubſtaunc
                  •
                tha
                  •
                we ſhuld lyue together ciuilly and without diſorder: But this Sacrament doth erhorte vs vnto charitie, becauſe that Ieſu Chriſte is tranſfourmed in vs, that we ſhould lyue by his ſpirite, and beyng thus ioyned together to our headde Ieſu Chryſte, one ſhoulde be the members of another. Out of this fountayne ſpryngeth all theſe erhortations of Paule, which do erhort, that we ſhoulde loue together in ſuche ſorte as Chriſt hath loued vs, who hath geuen his lyfe in a ſwete ſacrifice for our ſaluation. This is to bee clothed with Chryſte, to be inflamed with the loue of thy neighbour,

to be continually charged Ephe. v Roma. 
                     •
                   Gala. v. with charitie, euer deſierous to ſerue thi brother. O how much hath the Chriſtian profyted in this ſacrament, yf he be moued &amp; ſtirred with a wyl to ſerue his neyghbour. Not without cauſe than dyd S. Auguſtine name this Supper a Sacrament of Godlyneſſe, a ſigne of vnitie, and the bonde of charitie. For as this Sacrament is a ſpirituall meate, and ſwete to thoſe that be incorporate with Ieſu Chriſte, and with their neyghbour: Euen ſo of the contrary, it is a mortal poyſō to thē whiche put not their whole truſt in Ieſu Chriſte, &amp; be ſeperated frō their neighbour. The naturall meat whē in findeth a body full of naughtye humours, turneth to poiſon, corrupteth &amp; hurteth:

Euen ſo doeth the ſpirituall meate yf it fynde the ſoule vnfaythfull, it dryueth it to vtter ouerthrowes, becauſe that to an vnfaythfull manne, euerythyng is vnfaythfull and damnable.
            Therfore ſayth Paule: he that 1. Cor. xi. eateth and drynketh vnworthelye, is worthy blame, and is alſo a betrayer of the Lorde: ſuch one as this doth eate and drynk his owne iudgment, not iudgeyng the body of the Lorde. By which place I vnderſtande that it is all one, not to iudge the bodye of the Lorde- and to eate it vnworthelye. Wherefore they which lacke faith, &amp; be voyde of charitie, without all religion, and lyke hogges caſte in them ſelues to this Supper: ſuch as theſe make no difference of the

Lordes Supper. Therefore ſeyng they beleue not, that that body is theyr lyfe, whenſoeuer they do preſent them ſelues in the Church to receaue this Sacrament: they do blaſpheme, &amp; do greate iniurye to the body of Chriſt, they ſpoyle it of all dignitie, and receauyng it after this ſorte, they be falſe betrayers of theyr Lord. Euen ſo theſe that be in diſcorde with theyr neyghbours, the whiche do ſo hate them that they can not abyde the ſyght of them, whan they do come together in company to celebrate the holy ſupper, and to ſhewe that they be knytte together with theyr brother in the bande of charitie: ſuch do blaſpheme God, deuide the miſtical bodi of Ieſu Chriſt, and teare in ſunder the holye

Churche by peece and peece, Therefore worthely are they to be blamed, &amp; be betrayers of the body of Chryſt. I ſay not onely that they bee betrayers of the Churche, whiche is the miſtical bodye of Chryſte: But I ſaye they be betraiers of theyr Lord, no leſſe then Iudas and the Iewes whiche crucified hym. Eatyng after thys ſort, vnworthely, thei do receaue their own damynation, for vſynge thys Sacrament without fayth as the hypocrites do, they do confeſſe that with theyr mouth, whiche they beleue not in their harte. And to be preſent at thys table, is no other thinge but an abiuration whiche is done in euery falſe religion. It is a confeſſion that we beleue to bee ſaued onely by the death of Ieſu

Chryſte. The hypocrite then doth condemne hym ſelfe, doth pronounce ſentence in hys owne condemnation, and prouoketh the anger of GOD vppon hys owne head. When a man doth not putte hys whole confydence in Chriſt, he can not loue hys neyghbour with that Chriſtian loue wherewith thys Sacrament doth bynde hym. Then a wycked perſon is cutte of from his neyghbours, and ſo he hath no parte at all in the Churche, nor yet maye vſe thys Sacrament, but faynedly. For when he outwardelye ſheweth hym ſelfe at this holy Table, he confeſſeth to be tranſfourmed into hys neyghbour, neuertheleſſe in hys harte, he is replenyſhed with hatred. For this cauſe 1. Cor. x1.
               
Paule willed that a man ſhould 
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   xi. make triall of himſelf, before he dyd eate of thys bread, &amp; drynke of this cuppe. The whiche wordes I do vnderſtande after thys ſorte: that euerye one ought it theyr proper conſcience, and with ſtedfaſt fayth, beleue that Ieſus Chriſt onely is theyr redemer, and the ſatiſfier for all theyr ſinnes. Alſo they ought to declare the death of Chriſt, that is, with tong openly to confeſſe that, the whiche he beleueth in hys hart. Thys is to confeſſe Chriſt alone to be our Sauiour in daungers, troubles and all perſecutiōs of Antichriſt. When a Chriſtian hath taſted of thys fayth and confeſſion, it is neceſſary before he receaue thys Sacrament, that he conſider in his owne conſcience, whether he be

redy to geue hym ſelfe wholy to the ſeruyce and benefyt of hys neighbour as Chriſt hath done, who is made the ſeruaunt of the whole Churche: whether he be alſo deſyrous to helpe to defende and to gouerne his neighbour, becauſe he is of the fleſhe of his owne body. Thys is that preparation the which he ought to haue, that myndeth to eate the ſupper of the Lorde. This is that examination wherof Paul ſpeaketh that he ought to make that wyll eate of thys breade, and drinke of this cuppe. He that hath not this fayth and this charitie, lette him not goo to this ſupper of the Lorde: becauſe yf that anye ſuche who is voyde of faith and charitie, doth preſent hym ſelfe to thys table, he is worthi of more blame, and

becometh a betrayer of the body of Chryſt. Let vs nowe conſider what difference there is bet wixt this fyrſt and common fayth of the hypocrites, and of thys ſeconde Chriſtian faith. This firſt fayth wylleth that we ſhoulde eate this ſupper, becauſe it is ſo ordayned, and becauſe the body of Chryſte is receaued. But becauſe the wicked and reprobate, and the Dyuell may haue thys fayth: therefore the hipocrite doth not eate worthely the ſupper of the Lorde. Let vs then leaue of thys 
                  ••••…
               on hipocriſie, and beynge 
                  •
               rmed with fayth and charitie▪ 
               
                  •…
               et vs eate thys bread, and drynke thys cup together with the other faythful, chaunginge our ſelues into our neyghbours by charitie, beinge repleniſhed with all humilitie,

of whiche we haue at this preſent a rare example of oure maſter Chriſt, which is written by S. Iohn after this ſort. Before Iohn. xiii the feaſt dai of the paſſouer, Ieſus vnderſtandynge that his houre was come that he muſte depart out of this life to hys father: hauynge loued hys that were in the world, for euer and euer he loued thē. When ſupper was done and the deuil had moued ye hart of Iudas of Symon Iſcarioth which betraied hym: Ieſus knowing that his father had geuen into hys handes all thinges, and that he came from GOD, and that he muſt go to God: he ryſe from ſupper, put of his garmentes, tooke a towell, girde himſelfe: after that, put water into a baſen, and beganne to waſhe the feete of hys

Diſciples, and to wype them with the to well where with he was gyrt. The Euangelyſt dott deſcribe the cauſe wherfore the father ſent Ieſu Chriſt into the worlde, that by the meanes o
                  •
                the croſſe, he muſte retourne to hys father. Our merites then nor our good workes, bee not o
                  •
                ſuche pleaſauntneſſe that the
                  •
                haue cauſed the ſonne of god to deſcende into the earth. But th
                  •
                great earneſt loue that he bar
                  •…
                hath moued the heauenlye father to geue 
                  〈◊…〉
                hys benifites in hys beloued C
                  •••
               d.
            In this is made manyfeſt th
                  •
                
               i. Ioh. iiii. loue of God toward vs: In tha
                  •
                he ſen
                  •
                
               
                  〈◊〉
                only begotten ſonne i
                  •
                
               
                  〈◊…〉
                
               
                  ••
               rlde, that we ſhould ly
                  ••…
                
               
                  〈◊…〉
                him. In this doth ap
                  ••…
                
               
                  •
               ys loue, not that we lo
                  ••
                
               
                  〈◊〉
               , but that he loued vs▪
               
and ſent his ſonne a propiciation for our ſynnes. The ſonne hath folowed the loue of the father: therefore ſuch as were at the firſt beloued, they were dere and fauoured for euer and euer. Our Lorde fayleth not in his loue, albeit his Diſciples ran away &amp; denyed hym. For al this he departed not frō one iote of his good wyl, ye all men myght knowe that God is true, &amp; man is but a lyer. It is a ſmall mencion Roma. i
                     •
                  
                that Iohn maketh of this ſupper, becauſe it was already throughli deſcribed of the other Euangeliſtes. Now had the deuyll moued the harte of Iudas Iſcarioth that betrayed hym. And Ieſus vnderſtandyng ye his father had layd this burden vppon his ſhoulders, te l
                  •
               ue al beleuers by the meanes of the

croſſe: he therfore gaue into his handes the euerlaſtynge good thinges, that is, lyfe, righteouſneſſe, remiſſiō of ſinnes, he alth, redemption, iudgement, and reſurrection. All theſe good thinges were geuen into the handes of Chriſte, becauſe he hath purchaſed them, &amp; hath gotten the by the croſſe. This is the wyl of my father that hath ſente me, that I ſhoulde not loſe one of thoſe that he hath geuen me: that euerye one that ſeeth the ſonne, &amp; beleueth in him, maye haue lyfe euerlaſtynge. When Chriſt ſhoulde be exalted aboue the heauens, he would firſt hū
               ble him ſelf in waſhyng his diſciples feete, geuing this for an example, that firſt in this mortall life we ought to be humble, if in the other lyfe we wyll be

glorious with Ieſu Chriſte. I praye and beſech you brethren, that euery one of you conſider with deepe conſideration, this fact of humilitie of our Lord, to the ende that we ſhoulde know that he came to this extreme baſeneſſe to eralt vs. What maner of perſōs were they (O maſter) whoſe feete thou waſhed? it was theyrs who betrayed thee, denyed thee, forſoke thee in thy daunger, fled away when thou ſtodeſt in moſte nede of them.
            Wherfore we ought to conſider in this waſhynge of feete, the marueylous humilitie of oure maſter, and the feruent loue he bare towardes his enemies. It was the maner in thoſe dayes, to waſhe ſtraungers feete when they were bydden to any mans houſe: therfore the Lorde rebuked

the Phariſey which waſhed not his feete. Paule would not receaue a wydow to the ſeruice of the Churche, yf firſt ſhe were not knowen to be humble and of a godly lyfe. And the Apoſtle myndyng to declare this humilitie, ſayde: It is erpedient that 
                  
                     •
                  imo. v. a wydowe ſhoulde haue w
                  •••
               ed the feete of Saintes. For if any do hūble them ſelues after this ſorte, as to be content with ſo meane an office as to waſhe the feete of Saintes, &amp; to ſerue ſuch as haue ſores and infirmities: this is an euidente ſigne of a loue that is vnfayned. He came vnto Peter, &amp; Peter ſayd: Lorde ſhalt thou waſhe my feet, Ieſus aunſwered and ſaid: What I do thou knoweſte not, but thou ſhalt know hereafter. The wordes of Peter beyng conſidered

as they be in apparent, do declare great modeſtie, whiche in the worlde is worthy of prayſe. Yt is a ſigne of ciuilitie not to ſuffer without great nede to be ſerued of a mans better. But Chriſt in this that he dyd, hadde occaſiō, wherfore he willed that Peter ſhould beare that ſeruice, although it were baſe. Therfore ſayd Chriſte, thou ſhalte knowe hereafter Peter why I do this. At this aunſwere ought Peter to haue ſubmitted hym ſelfe, &amp; ſuffered his feete to be waſhed, &amp; to haue declared a ciuill wiſedome. Therfore it may be ſayd, that in Peter doth appeare the ſuperſtitious hypocriſie of our carnall nature. Peter made a conſcience, and feared to declare ſo ſmal reuerence to his maſter, to ſuffer him to waſhe his feete.

But after forgettyng all religion, treadyng vnderfeet both the loue and reuerence to his deare maſter, with an othe forſoke hym when he ought to haue cō
               feſſed hym. Chryſt hath ſaide: he that wyll not confeſſe me before men I wyll not confeſſe him in ath. 10. the preſence of my father. Peter made ſmal accompt of the commaūdement of God, denyed his maſter, makyng lytle conſcience to ſwere falſely, with 
                  •••
               te ſhame and ignominie to Ieſu Chriſt: yet he after made a conſcience, and thought it ſinne to ſuffer his maſter to waſſhe his feete. Thus doth our naturall hipocriſie: it reuerenceth Chriſt and wyll honour hym where is no nede: And agaynſt his commaūdement he wyll after make ſmall accompt of that true religion,

wherwith god wyl be ſerued and worſhipped. Our reaſō knoweth not the cauſe of Gods workes, nor yet can not knowe them if the ſpirite of the Lorde do not make manifeſt theſe ſecretes. Therfore Peter not knowyng but as man, ſtroue with his maſter, and ſayd, thou ſhalt neuer waſſhe my feete. Peter doth not only declare hym ſelfe co
                  ••••…
               tious, but yf we conſider th
                  •
                
               
                  •…
               nſwere, we ſhall fynde Peter a great blaſphemer. The maſter had ſayde before to his diſciples, that it was not without cauſe that he waſſhed theyr feete. Therfore Peter being obſtinate, &amp; reſiſting that he ſhuld not waſhe his feete at all, ſhewed him ſelfe to be wiſer then his maſter. And the aūſwere of Peter hath this vnderſtandynge.

Albeit thou art my maſter, yet for all that thou ſhalte pardon me: for in this doyng thou declareu thy ſelfe to haue ſmal experience touching wordly thinges. I know by experience it is not decent the ſeruaunt woulde be ſerued of his maſter: ſo that thy fact maſter doth gayneſaye the polytyke order of the world. And this that I do is done politikely. In Peter is declared a zele of the honour of God: but this deuotion was not groūded in the word of God. Lette vs ſee what aunſwere the wiſdome of God doth make to Peter. If I ſhall not waſſhe thy feete, thou ſhalt haue no parte with me.
            Chriſt contendeth not with Peter, for that he ſhuld not be wilfull and wyſe in his owne conceite. What ſhall we ſaye to the

aunſwere of our Lord? ah is it ſo great a matter to waſhe feet? was not Iudas feete waſſhed? yet he had no part with Chriſt: it is verye true his feete were waſhed, but not after that ſorte as Chriſt doth heare declare in this Goſpell.
            The aunſwere of Chriſt is this. Peter hath not wel vnderſtand my office, nor yet vnderſtandeth not home nedeful my ſeruyce is to all the whole worlde. O thou fantaſtical man, why doeſt thou beleue yt I am a Meſſias, a carnall king, a monarche of all the worlde, to whom all nations ſhould be ſubiect, thou thinkeſt to ſerue this Meſſias, but Peter thou arte deceaued. For if I do not fyrſt ſerue thee, thou ſhalte neuer ſerue me: yf I do not fyrſt ſaue thee, thou ſhalt neuer come to be ſaued, if I do not fyrſt ſhed

my bloud for thee, yf I do not firſt waſh thy ſinnes, thou ſhalt neuer be ſaued, nor yet haue ani porcion with me. Theſe wordes of Ieſu Chriſt, yf I waſhe not thy fete, thou ſhalt haue no portion with me: Albeit they bee few, and appeare ſimply, yet for al that, if we cōſider them depely, we ſhall fynde that they deſtroy all falſe and cloked religion. Although there bee many amongeſt the Iewes, which lyue honeſtly, yet for all that they be not ſaued in the bloud of chriſt, nor yet haue they no part with him. The Turkes albeit they ſay they ſerue god aboue, &amp; glory that they haue the true religion, and ſhewe with outwarde ceremonies, a cloked holynes: yet they obtayne not remiſſion of their ſinnes, becauſe they be not waſhed in ye bloud of Chriſt.

Our hipocrites although they doe manye good workes, yet becauſe they thynke to be waſhed in theyr owne merites, and not in the bloud of Chriſt: Therfore ſuch hipocrites haue no portion with Chriſt at al. But let vs returne to Peter who ſaid: O lord not only my fete, but my hands and head alſo. At the firſt Peter was very obſtinate, and would not ſuffer hys maſter to waſhe his fete, but now he would haue him to doe more then was fyrſt commaunded. The ſelfe ſame thinge we ſe nowe to be done in many, who when they perceaue the ſeueritie of the law, and the bonde which we are bounde in, they do as Peter dyd, they wyll not only obſerue the commaundement of god, but they finde of theyr owne workes beſydes the worde of God. Therefore they

thinke to merite remiſſion of ſin nes. partly by the merite of Ieſu Chriſt, and partly by the merite of their owne worke. Such be lyke Peter, for they wyll not only do that that god commaū
               deth, but thei wil of their owne heades finde out other merites, wherby to deſerue lyfe euerlaſtynge. Peter not walkyng in the kinges high way, Ieſus ſaid vn to hym: he that is waſhed, hath no nede to waſhe any parte, but his fete, and than he is al clene. Our maſter reproued the vnſkil fulnes of Peter by the common cuſtome of theſe dayes. For ſuch as be waſhed in a bathe, when thei go forth, they ſet their feete vpon the ground: And nede not after to waſhe anye thynge but theyr feete. When any was bydden to feaſt to the Iewes, it was onely nedeful to waſhe the fete,

becauſe they vſed to eate vppon beddes: As nowe emongeſt vs, when any is biddē to feaſt, it is only nedeful to waſh theyr handes, for all elles is cleane. But Chriſt by this matter wyl in
                  ••
               r a matter of more importan̄ce, &amp; not only 
                  •
               epr
                  •
               hend the inciuilitie of Peter. All they whiche by fayth be made cleane &amp; pure, all ſuch be al wholy clenſed in Ieſu Chryſt, becauſe ye fayth hath aſſured thē of the purenes &amp; holynes of Ieſu Chriſt. There is no damnation to thoſe that be engraffed in Ieſu Chryſt: with all this therfore is iuſtified the ſinner, &amp; yet hath he his feete myered, the which continually haue nede to be clenſed.
            The feete be the carnal deſires and the remanentes of the olde man, the which ought continually to be chaſtened and mortified.

The Chriſtian in Chryſte is wholy cleane: but in him ſelf he hys filthy, foule, &amp; ful of carnal deſires. And although he is not therfore condemned, yet he hath ſinnes, the which were nedeful to bee waſhed awaye: whyleſt therefore we lyue in this myery lyfe, we haue nede to haue oure feete waſhed. That is, to walke in the ſpirite, &amp; not in the fleſhe, becauſe a Chriſtian oughte to ſerue with his mynde the lawe of god, therfore ought he to take good hede not to ſerue the lawe of ſinne. When our maſter had waſhed hys Diſciples feete, he toke agayne his garmentes, ſat him down, and ſaid vnto them: you call me maſter and lorde, ſo ſay you well, for ſo I am. If I then beinge lorde &amp; maſter haue waſhed your fete, you ought alſo to waſhe one anothers feete,

becauſe I haue geuē you an example, that as I haue done euē ſo do ye. The lord hath now declared ye cauſe that moued hym to take in hand ſo meane an enterpriſe in the world. The Apoſtles did thinke that Ieſus chriſt ought to be the worldly meſſias that was loked for of ye Iewes, that ſhoulde be a kinge and monarche of the whole world. Our Lorde had often preached vnto them, that hys kyngdome was ſpirituall and not terreſtriall, &amp; that they ſhould not ſet their felicitie beneth in the earth. For to confirme therfore the trueth of this his prechyng, he did this baſe and meane offyce to waſhe his diſciples feete. And our lord deferred this fact vntill his laſt ſupper, for that hys doctryne ſhould be more freſhe in memorie in our mindes, being done at

a tyme moſte worthy of remembraunce, I haue geuen you an example that you ſhoulde do as you haue ſeene me to doe: you thynke that I am come into this world to enioye an earthly kyngdome, you receaue youre ſelues. Therefore caſte of from you al felicitie that the worlde can promyſe you, take example by me that am made your ſeruaunt. Thus followe my pathe and foteſteppes, be ſeruauntes of all men, but be faythfull. This onely ſayeth Paule is required in the miniſters of the goſpel, that they be faythfull in their doctryne: none then ſhall glory in man, we ſhal onely glory in Ieſu Chryſt who is ye true fode of our ſoules. To whom be honour, power and glory for euer and euer.
            Amen
         
      
      
         
            ¶ Imprinted at London by Rycharde Iugge, Printer to the Queues Maieſtie.
            
         
      
   

