
   
      
         
            A satirycall dialogue or a sharplye-invectiue conference, betweene Allexander the great, and that truelye woman-hater Diogynes
            Goddard, William, fl. 1615.
         
         
            
               1616
            
         
         Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01795
            STC 11930
            ESTC S105741
            99841467
            99841467
            6052
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01795)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6052)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 958:16)
         
         
            
               
                  A satirycall dialogue or a sharplye-invectiue conference, betweene Allexander the great, and that truelye woman-hater Diogynes
                  Goddard, William, fl. 1615.
                  Alexander, the Great, 356-323 B.C.
                  Diogenes, d. ca. 323 B.C.
               
               [48] p.   
               
                  By George Waters] for all such gentlewomen as are not altogeather idle nor yet well. ocupyed,
                  Imprinted in the Lowcountryes [i.e. Dordrecht :
                  [1616?]
               
               
                  Dedication signed: Willyam Goddard.
                  In verse.
                  "A morrall satire, intituled the Owles araygnement", F2r-end.
                  Printer's name supplied and publication date conjectured by STC.
                  Signatures: A-F⁴.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Women --  Controversial literature.
               Marriage --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2003-10
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-10
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-11
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2003-11
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-12
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            SATIRYCALL
DIALOGVE
OR A SHARplye-invectiue
conference, betweene
Allexander the great, and
that truelye woman-hater Diogynes.
            
            Imprinted in the Lowcountryes for all
such gentlewomen as are not altogeather
Idle nor yet well,
OCVPYED.
            
         
         
            
            
            bewteous: to the all-Illustrious, and
most puissaunt creatures of the Earth, VVOEMEN:
Willyam Goddard, sole desirer of th'yncrease of your
bewtyes, and chiefe adorer of your goddes-like vertues,
(with al reuerence to your Angelicall sex,) commendes to
your protection this harsh vnlearned
DIALOGVE.
            
               STarrs of this earthlie heaun, you whose essence
            Composd was of mans purest quyntessence,
            To you (to virtuous you) I dedicate
            This snaggy sprigg, hew'd from a crabby pat
                  •
               
            
            Wherein (Celestiali bewties) you shall see,
            Howe old Diogynes extolleth yee.
            We men, doe loue to see our selues vp-raisd
            And Iocond are, o heare our own selues praisd
            
               But (oh you springes of Wisdome) I doe find
            
            That is a thing most hatefull to your kind.
            Yet old D
                     •
                  ogynes did see your worth,
            Such worth hee sawe, as needes heed paint it forth.
            Accept his loue; for all the Cynnicks deedes
            Out of true zeale vnto your sex proceedes
            With rev'rent zeale, as high as th'azurd skyes
            Your virtuous deedes, the old man magnifies.
            Contrary wise, he with a bitter penn
            Invectivelie, doth write against bad men
            Comaunding them, that what soe e're they doe,
            They alwaies should example take by you.
            Badd are these men, such is their perverse kind
            They burne all bookes, wherein theire faults they find
            And therefore (earthlie aungells) my desire
            Is you'l protect this, from consuming fire.
            
               The euer-faythfull honourer
of your celestyall Sex
Willyam Goddard.
               
            
         
         
            
            To the senceles Censurer.
            
               RAsh Reader▪ read my booke, and when tis read
            Disdaynefullie through 't o're thy muddy head
            Thy condemnations peale a both sides ringe:
            Rash men are priviledgd t'saie anie thing
            And therefore (hare-braine) reade, criemewe dislike:
            My spleene swells not when fooles with bables strike.
            Pack hence precision: cry'st it is obsceane?
            Diue deeper shallowe pate: knowe what I meane
            Knowe what I meane? alas! what hope haue I?
            Since carpers mindes haue but a poreblynd eye
            Yet to prevent thy censures thus much knowe
            Whollye this booke was made, follie to showe
            And he which laies ope tymes abuse, and vice
            Are sildome blam'd of men Indicious wise:
            At which I ay'md; and therefore duncepate hence
            Or looke for lashes for thy rude offence.
            
               William G.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            A SATIRYCALL DIALOGVE
OR A SHARPLYE-INVECTVIE
CONFERENCE
Betweene
ALLEXANDER THE GREATE▪
and that
Trulye woman-hater Diogynes.
            
               Allexander.
               
                  WHy howe nowe Cy
                     •
                  nick, what dust doe a daies
That thou in tubb art coop't-vp thus alwaies?
            
            
               Diogynes.
               What doe I doe? not daunce from howse to howse
               To bibb in wynes sweete Iuice, eache dambd 
                     •
                  orrowse
               Nor doe I gallop it from place to place
               To veiwe each faire bewitching painted face
               Nor studdye howe, this populous world to wynn
               My studdy's howe, to beate and conquer synn
               I studdye not wherewith my gutts to cramm
               On what soe ere I feede, well pleasd I am.
               To mee's all one the fyn'st and grossest meate
               So't wholesome be, I nere eare what I eate.
               With in my selfes a world, and it is true
               I howrlie fight, all that world to subdue
               And these fell-fighters bee the enymies,
               That rebell-like, againste me dailie rise
               Vaine Pryde (my cheifest foe) the leading hath
               Of these feirce-foes: loathd, drunkenues and Wrath
               
               With Averice, Sloathe, Gluttonie, and Lust,
               
               
                  
Encounter hottlie eu
                     •
                  ie daie I must
               To beate downe these, I daylie doe devise:
               To this end, I vse strentgh and pollicies:
               I studdy not, nor trouble I my witt
               Howe I by flatt'ry should be fauouritt
               Vnto greate Allexander. I would refuse
               To be that monarchs selfe, If I might chuse.
            
            
               Allexander.
               THou wouldst not; wouldst?
            
            
               Diogynes.
               I would by Ioue I vowe
            
            
               Allexander.
               ALas (poore sillie snake) why what art thou?
            
            
               Diogynes.
               WHat thou art not: I am an honest man
               And then (I hope) the more vnlike thee than.
               I am noe Courtyer I, for once by chaunce
               I with an other mans faire wife did daunce
               Yet Icie-vayned I (vnsett a fire)
               Did freeze moste coldlie, in loues hott desire:
               I did indeed: but doe you heare me hoe?
               Was e're hott-blouded Courtyer frozen soe?
               I am noe Lawyer I, for once there was
               A poore man praide me vndertake his case
               Quoth he, praie vndertakt and you shall haue your fee
               Though you sitt dumb, and nothing speake for me.
               But I refusd it I: yet harke you hoe
               What Lawyer ere refusd, and tempted soe?
               I am noe younger-brother, brauelie sprighted
               For once a vsring golden Asse (be nighted)
               Quite laden, with his full stu
                     •
                  t treasure baggs;
               By me that dreaming drudge, all feareles laggs
               Yet honest I (vntempted with this sight)
               Though emptie mavd, at this baite would not bi
                     •
                  e
               Hence capring Courtyer ask you who I am?
               Goe, gett you hence, s
                     •
                  udd quick from whence you came.
            
            
               
               Allexander.
               CYnnick you are to sharpe did you but knowe me
               I am assurd more reu'rence you would showe me.
            
            
               Diogynes.
               HOwe? I showe reverence? noe, vnderstand
               That Allexander getts none at my hand.
            
            
               Allexander.
               IN faithe Diogynes thou haste not beene,
               In all thy life, where anie thing th'ast seene.
               Yf thoudst but trauayle and some fashions see,
               Thoudst aunswere none, as nowe thou aunswerst me.
            
            
               Diogynes.
               HAue I not trauayld? ha? yes yes I trowe,
               (Spruce fellowe) thou haste neuer trauaild soe.
               Where I haue bene, theres fewe harh euer beene
               But yet men saie noe wonders I haue seene,
               Why once I sawe, a rit
                     •
                  h-left heire to weepe,
               When's old dadd tooke his euerlasting sleepe.
               Once did I see a bewteous maide (tis straunge!)
               Liue twentie yeares, yet not that title chaunge
               Once did I see a wife in mourninge weede
               Shedd teares ouer hir husbands course indeed
               I once did see a Cytizens faire wife
               Liue at the Courte, he leading else wher'es life
               And hee (ins witt) noe wiser then an asse
               Yet was hee brow'd, more smothe then smothest glasse
               Once did I see a King giues foes the foile
               And gaue his souldyers leaue, to take the spoile
               And lastlie once I was in such a Court
               Where 'bout the King, noe flattrers did resort
               Where I haue beene, oh furelie none haue beene,
               Then why saie you, noe wonders I haue seene?
            
            
               
               Allexander.
               WHy faith Diogynes me thinkes these are,
               No
                     •
                   things (as thou wouldst make em) wondrous rare
               The like in eu'rie place and realme I see
               Th'
                     •
                  re comon, man, they ordynarie be.
            
            
               Diogynes.
               THose ordynarie thinges? I fayth sir noe;
               These thinges, are th' ordynarie thinges, I trowe
               To see faire bewtious ladies nowe a daies
               Refuse to take at once both pricke, and praise
               Of both the ile not accept, for still those men
               Which gives the one, shall tother haue agenn.
               The other thinges? why! those are wondrous rare
               These 
                     •
                  e the thinges that ordynarie are
               
                  
                     •
                  o see howe Lords shake-of their serving men
               And howe their ladies take them on agen
               Holding emin (vnto their Lords vnknowne)
               To ride in private, with them vp and downe
               T'see m
                     •
                  rcers 
                     •
                  ookes fild-vp with courtyers names.
               To see your min
                     •
                  yng bewteous cyttie dames
               Haue alwaies some one gallant of the court,
               (As knisman to them) to theire howse resort.
               To see, a plaine kind man loue none soe much
               As he which giues his pate the cuckolds tutch
               These; these are ordynarie man: also
               This things is as much ordynarie too
               To see your riteh old country squires to wedd
               Their chamber maides vnto theire servaunts bedd
               But firste themselues to take the maydenhead
               Then place them in some cottage nere at hand
               To haue theire service, readie at comaund.
               Thou saydst the first were ordynarie thinges:
               Awaie awaie: why man to see on Kinges
               Howe Daunger plaine, cloathd smoothly-smiling Daunger
                        •
                     
                  
               
               Wayteth on them, attending like noe straunger
               But like some smyling, countenanced freind
               Onelie to giue too's Prince, his fatall end:
               
                  
Thoult say perhaps, this is noe common thing
               But thoud'st vn say't againe wert thou a King
               What thinges are common, and not common be,
               Thy shallowe reatch, cannot conceaue I see.
            
            
               Allexander.
               NAie fie Diogynes infaith thou art,
               In thy conclusions still a dram, to tart
               I pray thee lett me soe prevaile with thee
               As ride to Allexanders court with mee
               Twill mend thee much, and I will vndertake,
               The King shall byd thee welcome for my sake.
            
            
               Diogynes.
               VNto my Tubb, lett Allexander come
               I'me in a Pallace, when I'me in this home
               Let those that list, vnto thy King resort,
               Tis not my list: what should I doe at's court?
            
            
               Allexander.
               AS others doe; in spending of smal
                     •
                   pelfe,
               Thou maiste in tyme to honour raise thy selfe.
            
            
               Diogynes.
               
                  I cannot fawne, my tongue too rustie is;
                  I bashfull am; I'm nothing boldlie rude
                  I rather chuse Court delecates to misse
                  Then with a brazen face my selfe ty'ntrude:
                  In tubb (coop't-vp) I will liue euer mude
                  And euer liue vppon sowre garden woortes
                  Er'e Ile' a flattr'er be, and followe cortes
               
               
                  I cannot turne my tongue to praise and laude
                  A soone-lamb'd prick-eard proud-feerce fi
                        •
                     y steed
                  I cannot Fyndalls full deepe mouth applaude
                  Nor swaere the greate-mans grew hound hath best speed
                  
                     
When hee doth plaie the slowe-slugg cur
                        •
                      indeed
                  Though some cann doo't, yet such is my sowre kind
                  I neuer could, though't gall's his sweld pust mind
               
               
                  I cannot tell the greate foole hee is wise,
                  Nor t
                        •
                     ll fowle ladies, they are wondrous faire
                  I ne're applaude aboue heauns-spangled skies
                  The curld-worne tresses, of dead-borrowd haire
                  Like Northern blaste I breathe my crittick aire:
                  I am noe Mimyck ape, I loathe and hate,
                  Each light-braind, giddy-head to Imy tate
               
               
                  I cannot brooke, to suck the livings bloud
                  Of these old Vsrer's ritch-left prodigalls
                  I nourish not with such sweete-bitter food:
                  I hate to rise by other mens downe falls
                  I knowe tis Ill though other think tis good
                  Though some doe think such papp all sweete to be
                  Yet I doe not; it poyson proues to mee.
                  To make short worke, I neuer loud' vaine sportes
                  And therefore I'me vnfitt for Prynces Courtes?
               
            
            
               Allexander.
               
                  DIogynes, thou art deceyued quite
               In vanities Kinges take the least delight
               Ile vndertake none shall respected bee
               (Yf thou wilt followe him) better then thee
               Come to the Court, and then in seeing him
               Thou also maiste, take veiwe of ladies trymm
               Mee thinkes, hee is too dull and sadd of spright
               That in a bewteous dame takes noe delight.
               Why hee that's mary'd is in heaun all night.
            
            
               Diogynes.
               THere lett him bee, for I had rather dwell
               A thousand tymes, a single man in hell
               I am assurd that ther'es noe Divell cann
               (Like to a wife) torment a mary'd man.
               
                  
Il'e none of them, I'me euer worse a yeare
               When once I doe, a womans tongue but heare
               It galls my gutts when I a woman see
               Ile not once come, where such straunge creatures be
               Come hold your tongue, and prate no more to me
            
            
               Allexander.
               NAie good Diogynes bee not soe quick
               I hope yet 'ere I die, see thee loue sick
            
            
               Diogynes.
               LOue-sicke? why I doe loue these women soe
               As I'me soe fonde, I knowe not what to doe
               Such is my loue vnto the femall Kind
               As were I Empr'our of thyn fernall lake
               But women, none with me should fauour synd
               One man into my Kingdome I d'e not take
               Ide' send my servaunts our, to scarch and see
               To bring all women in the world to mee.
            
            
               Allexander.
               BYth masse Diogynes thou loust em well
               Wert thou the King and gouernour of hell
               Thou wouldst I see advaunce the women kind
               There is noe want of will hadst to thy mind
               Wert thou (I see) the prince of that faire place
               Women, (onelie) with thee should be in grace
               I see thoudst very carles be of men
               I see thoudst women haue, t'attend thee then.
            
            
               Diogynes.
               I that I would, and this they should be bold
               Ide carefull be they should not freeze with cold
            
            
               Allexander.
               I fayth Diogynes I doubt th'ast euer
               Beene privatelie a vild laciuious liuer
               
                  
Or neuer haste beene yet (I greatelie feare)
               Where anie one faire vertuou
                     •
                   creature weare.
            
            
               Diogynes.
               NOr nere will looke to be: I am too wise
               To thinke that vertue cann remaine in vice
            
            
               Allexander.
               WErt thou at Court, thou'dst alter then thy mind
               When women thou didst see, soe wondrous kind
               Forsake this Tubb, t'is solliterie Ill
               And howe to court faire ladies, learne the skyll.
            
            
               Diogynes.
               
                  NOwe, by the lustfull fire, hott boiling vaines▪
                  
                  Of that same wanton greate god Iupiter
                  I am vn skild in these speech-pleasing straines
                  To courte a wenche when I come vnto hir
                  I'me then an all-mute dumb and surlie sir
                  I cannot lispe, nor cann I courtlike saie,
                  When I doe women woe, I runn my waie.
               
               
                  I cannot singe, nor cann I turne my tongue
                  To chaunte a Syren-charming quau'ring dittye
                  When I these bewties chaunce to come amonge
                  My lead-sade-sable lookes must moue their pittie
                  All what is in me then, is all vnwittie
                  I want these warbling noates to wynn their loues
                  Nor cann I pricksong sett, which better moues
               
               
                  I cannot musick it, nor finger fyne
                  A sweete-cleare-throated, care-charme instrument
                  I'me not posseste with such sweet parts devyne
                  Whereby to cause, faire bewties merryment
                  T'ynchaunt theire eares nothing cann I invent
                  And well knowe I, that women take delight
                  In these same instruments, both daie and night
               
               
                  
                  I cannot daunce, no
                        •
                      with my sprawling heeles
                  Cann I the ny'mble cutt-heele caper kick
                  My sullen bloud an other humor feeles
                  To woe a wench, I want the wanton trick
                  I am a milksopp then, I then am sick
                  Againe, strenghes moysture in may vaines is skant,
                  Which women after dauncing must not want.
                  And therefore pry thee fellowe lett me reste
                  Of all these worldly Courts, my Tubb's the best.
               
            
            
               Allexander.
               DIogines, my meaning is mistooke
               I would not, that your Tubb be quite forsooke
               But for your recreation nowe and then
               Youd' goe too th' Court, from court t' your tubb agen.
               Mistake me not, it will for your good tend
               A wiseman alwaies lysten will too's freind.
            
            
               Diogynes.
               NAie would you would these complementes forbeare
               For Courtyers freindshipps, I did neuer care
               Ye
                     •
                   should I chuse a freind, a Courtyer than
               I would make 
                     •
                  hoise-of, fore another man:
               By this example I will plainelie proue
               That like to courtyers, none doe truelie loue
               Like to apparrell they doe loue theire freind
               To what (like that) doe they theire loues extend:
               Like cloathes they loue theire freindes: why that is true
               Iust like em, cause they nere loue cloathes but newe:
               Pack hence, for such loue should I find of you.
            
            
               Allexander.
               NAie fye Diogynes you cann (yf list)
               Forbeare to plaie this crabb-sowre satirist
               I pry thee Cynnick broach thy milder braine
               And let thy wordes runn in a sweeter vaine
               In others natures too too much you markst,
               
                  
Against theire faultes too rusty 
                     •
                  ond you barkst
               I doe dislike it I, I pry thee cease
               Thoud'st gaine more loue, yf thou didst hold thy peace:
               Turne courtyer man, come, be thou pollitick wise
               He best wynns loue, that best cann sooth-vp vice.
            
            
               Diogynes.
               THen Ile' wynn hate: nor King nor Clowne Ile' spare
               Yf they with vices vennym poysned are
               Yf with Prides swellinge tympany I fynd
               Theire hartes are once puft-vp; Ile speake my mind.
               Let's pate be crownd, with hundred thowsand crownes
               Lett cruell deathe, succeed his wrathfull frownes
               Yet (yf in him) loathd filthie synns I see
               Hee shall not (in them) sooth'd-vp-be, by mee
               I cannot soothe; I am not that waies wi
                     •
                  e:
               Who liveth not in vertue, dies in vice.
            
            
               Allexander.
               THou sayst well Cynnick, for I hold this race
               Of oyld-tongu'd flattrers, to be dangerous base
               The cankerd rust, doth not the Iron frett
               Soe faste as these, doe in good natures eate
               The statelie oake a longer tyme would liue
               Yf to the Ivie, he noe truste did giue
               But as the Ivie', 'boute the oake entwyndes
               To worke his fall; so't fares with flattrers mindes.
               But whether in discourse, shall our tongues walke?
               I came not here, of court affaires to talke
               I came to see, thy manner kind of life
               And t'aske thee, why thou getst thee not a wife.
               Faith gett thee one, I would not lie alone
               Yf all the world could but afford mee one.
            
            
               Diogynes.
               
                  A wife? why for my life I cannot see
                  Howe man, with woman, euer should agree
                  
                     
When men goe backward, and goe downe the wynd
                  It frettes, cuttes, galles, and greiveth sore the mind
                  When women backward growe▪ and downeward goe
                  Theire spleenes, with laughter tickles then I trowe:
                  Since theire two natures, are soe contrarie
                  I muse howe tweene them, cann be sympathie
                  A wife? oh fellowe tha'rt a younge man yet
                  Ther'es much sowre sawce, belonges to that sweete bitt:
                  Who would be troubled with the yawling noyse
                  Of a harsh-whewling young childes whympring voice
                  Againe, to see em fligger, smile, and plaie
                  Doth make mee greiue as much an other waie
                  When they doe simper, I doe sighe; for then
                  I mynd the miseries, theyl see (ere men.)
                  Twould cutt my heart to heare a babe crye dadd
                  Oh giue me meate: when tis not to be hadd
                  He that doth wiue, for pleasures sole intent
                  Tis tenn to one, but soone he will repent.
                  Who would be bound to scrape, pinch, carke, and care
                  For brattes, (perhapps) that gott by others ate?
                  Not I: Ile' none of this thing, cald a wife
                  Let him take one, that's wearie of his life
                  For hee that alwaies will supplies' wiues lack
                  Must vnto Nature goe, for a steele back.
                  A wife? Ile ha noe wife: such sprights will frowne
                  Vnles they (er'e a non) are coinurd' downe:
                  Againe my little Tubb is too too small
                  To hold my wife, my selfe, and whom shee'le call
                  It must not be a smale howse that cann hold
                  A silent man, ioynd with a shrill-tongud schold
                  Nowe will hir gossipps come; then praie nowe where
                  Is roome for them to chatt, and make good cheere?
                  And nowe hir old-acquainted freind will come
                  (Perhapps to see hir, when I'me from my home)
                  Then where's my galleree, for them to walk?
                  Or anie place for old freindes secrett talk?
                  Some what perhapps theyd' doe, I should not see:
                  Where haue I chambers then for them to bee?
                  Not in my Tubb my Tubb 
                        •
                     ath nor the scope
                  For hir to gossip't, with hir mates I hope.
                  
                     
Yet though I haue 
                        〈◊〉
                      wife (with ho
                        ••
                      de
                        •
                     ire)
                  My harte is flamd: burnt am I with loues fire
                  A loue I haue to whom I will be true
                  Obserue hir partes, I will discribe them you
                  My loues pure white hath ne're sustaind a spot
                  She's wise, 
                        •
                     ood, rich, faire, chaste, what is shee not?
               
               
                  Hlr eyes1, grace2, speach3; hath1 fir'd, amaz'd2, rauisht3,
                  My harte1, sence2, thoughts3; with loue1, wonder2, delight3,
                  But fyr'd1, 'mazd2, sence-rest3; I sought1, prayde2, and wisht3,
                  To quenche1, cure2, and heale3; loue1, sence2, and eyes3-dymd sight
                  Thus eyes1, grace2, speache3; hath fyr'd1, amazd2, sence-charmd3
                  
                  My thoughts1, sence2, witts3, with loue1, with feare2, vnarmd3
                  
               
               
                  Oh my loue's fairelie white without a spott
                  Such is hir hue noe staine hir hue can blott
                  
                     Virtue's that Dame in hir sweete grace I sitt
                  'Tis shee loues me, she'es womans oppositt,
                  Could I one headles lymb les corp les see
                  To such a one would I betrothed be
                  For had shee nere a head; noe tongue sheed haue:
                  Nor corps; then Ide not d
                        •
                     ead the lechrous knaue:
                  Nor lymb; then should I neuer quiv'ring stand
                  Fearing my eares remembraunce of hir hand
                  Of rope or hangman I was nere afrayde
                  At noe sight quake I but at wife or maide.
               
            
            
               Allexander.
               OH harsh-sowre, crabby Cyn
                     •
                  ick, still I see
               To gentle creatures thou wilt stubborne be
               If with a girle thast neuer slept a night
               Thy soule hath neuer tasted sweete delight.
               Such is the femall sex, while wife or maide
               As of them, too much good, cannot be saide
               Methinkes the skipping bloud (a Virgins grace)
               
                  
Which tripps lavaltoes in each maydens face
               When mens fowle tongues, o're-flowes with ribaldery
               Should make thee loue maides, for theire modestie.
            
            
               Diogynes.
               MAydens modest? what is this modestie?
               
                  
                     •
                  f t'is in them, it is a vice saie I
               Vertue in women is as cold as Ice:
               Nothinge is warme in them vnlest be vice.
               Thou art a dunce, thou haste noe reatche I see
               Why Maydes at all tymes cann faine modestee.
               Theil' blush as oft while they liue single liues
               As they will weepe, when they be mary'd wiues:
               If twas my liste, I could a thowsand name
               That would (yf men talke Ill) blush at the same
               Y
                     •
                  t thy themselues, their tongues shall nimblie walke
               Whole nights togeather, all in too-broad talk.
            
            
               Allexander.
               THou wrongst em soore: I doe not think it I
               That maydens tongues, will tripp Immodestlie.
            
            
               Diogynes.
               THou doost not, doost? I prithee think soe still:
               I think thy witt is like a womans will
               But what thou dost not think, I trulie knowe:
               What I haue saide of maydes men shall find 
                     •
                  oe
               I fellowe, fellowe, till theire by thems
                     •
                  lu
                     •
                  s
               Maydes in talke are modest bashfull elues
               But beinge from the companie of men
               The lawes of modestie is broken then.
               Twas not longe since I stood to maydens neere
               But Lord! thou't ne re beleeue what I did heare
               For onelie that same wench esteemd' was well
               Which could the ribauldst dreame, relate and tell:
               I could relate all what they did relate
               But that my tongues, disvs'd to such like prate
               'Tis vild obscene; speake younge man wilt you hav't?
            
            
               
               Allexander.
               COme, out with't Cynnick, I knowe thy delight
               
                  
                     •
                  s, all in all to worke faire woomen spight.
            
            
               
                  
                     
                        DIOGINES RELATES
the three wanton Sisters wanton
dreames.
                        
                           Diogynes.
                           O Yet the fyer, once three maydens satt
                           
                              
                                 •
                              nknowne to them, I ouer heard theire chatt
                           Eache with hir tuckt-vp cloathes, in pleasing plight
                           (Pleasing I meane vnto fond y
                                 •
                              unge mens sight)
                           Satt ore the fyer, soe, as one might see,
                           From sl
                                 •
                              nder foote, to round white nimble knee
                           As thus they satt, I'me sure thou doest thinke what
                           (When maydes with maydens bee) wilbe theire chatt
                           Girles (quoth the eldest sister) what shall's doe?
                           Smal'es my desire, vnto my bedd to goe
                           Fo
                                 •
                               yet, I never in my couche could fynd
                           A sportiue mate to please my mayden mind
                           Alas, alas, what pleasure and delight
                           Takes one mayde with an other in the night?
                           But smale god knowes it, for my owne part I
                           Ne're tooke anie with whom Ie're did lie.
                           For loue, noe revells in that bedd doth keepe
                           Where one girle, by an others side doth sleepe.
                           
                              
                                 •
                              or trulye (sisters) there is none that can
                           Giue maydes delight in bedd, but a young man
                           And but in dreame (the more vnhappie I)
                           I ne're with such a beddfellowe could lie
                           But yet in dreame (oh matchles sweete delightes!)
                           Iv'e lyne, and lyne, with one whole wynters nightes
                           The greater greife (you'l saie) 'twas to my mind
                           When I did wake, and my selfe single fynd.
                           Oh girles it was! but sisters I doe see,
                           
                              
It is with eu'rye mayde as 'tis with mee.
                           Such are our dreames, as wee doe laugh in sleepe
                           But when wee wake againe, oh then wee weepe.
                           But what shalls' doe? wee'l not soe soone to b
                                 •
                              dd
                           Letts rather tell, howe ne're wee haue beene spedd.
                           Our merry'st dreames come le
                                 •
                              t vs nowe relate
                           Girles gott with girles, their mindes maie freelie prate
                           What though w'are maides? here are noe men to heare vs
                           Freelie wee vse to chatt, when th'are not nerevs
                           W'are by our selues: what ere we talke, is well
                           Come letts drawe lotts, which first hir dreame shall tell.
                           At which the youngest, blushing like a rose
                           Being assignd by lott, firste to disclose
                           Begynns to tell howe to hir soules delight
                           Hir sences ravisht' were, the other night.
                        
                        
                           THE YOVNGEST
Sisters dreame.
                           QOth shee, on bedds softe downe downe did I lie
                           And s
                                 •
                              ugd doowne close, to haue sleepe close eache eye
                           But ere twould bee, I entred in a muse
                           (I such a muse as all wee maydens vse)
                           I mus'd (me thought) yf there were sweeter blisse
                           For maydes, then't lie with men, to clipp and kisse
                           Me thought, I thought (this thought fetcht out a groane)
                           It was a hell to lie, all night alone.
                           At which I sight, and turning me I wept
                           Desiring, what I knowe not, till I slept
                           In which my sleepe (oh fancies sweete delight?)
                           Appeard a youth (Pheobus was much lesse bright)
                           Gold were his lockes, firye sparkles were his eyne
                           His browes, cheekes, and chynn were as louelie fyne
                           I'ns shirte was hee, a shirt soe fyne I wynn
                           As one might see, what was tweene shirt and skynn
                           His snowe-white armes, in-laide with azurd vaine
                           (Mixed with crimson dye) one might see plaine
                           His full-broade manlie some-what-downye cheste
                           Dale-like indented tweene two mounting brestes;
                           
                           On which two prettie fr
                                 •
                              iteles teatlinges grewe:
                           Not milkie sweete, sweete onelie for the ve
                                 •
                              we.
                           I saw's soft slender waste; and sisters well nie
                           I fawe what grewe beneathe his plump-round bellie:
                           All what I sawe (sweete w
                                 •
                              nches) I would tell ye
                           But that sweete loue coniures me (heres' the spight)
                           Not to discribe, mans sweetly-sportiue spright:
                           Oh sweet's the dreame, which yeeldeth such delight!
                           But come girles come; (fye whether doe I roame?)
                           Me thinkes bu
                                 •
                               coldlie I tooth purpose come:
                           To me he came, and kiste me too; when I
                           Me thought did faine, I did a sleeping lie
                           Me thought, I lett him kisse and kisse agenn
                           And 
                                 •
                              ouche me too (maydes maie be toucht by men.)
                           I sisters, faythe (me thinkes) that maide's vnwise
                           That will in private, to hir l
                                 •
                              ue be nice
                           Two faythfull lovers cannot synn I weene
                           Soe what they doe, by others is not seene.
                           Nowe would the wagg, be stroaking of my face
                           And nowe my pappes, anon another place
                           Delighting of himselfe, sisters you can
                           (Better then I) tell what best likes a man
                           But fayth-la girles, I cannot chuse but smile
                           I laie, as yf I soundlie slept the while
                           Permitting him to please the appetite
                           Of his too too-fond, youth-last-burning sight
                           Fayning, I soundest slept, whe
                                 •
                               hee did steale
                           To vnhill that which maides should cheifst conceale
                           But, when as hee'd haue come into my bedd
                           The feare I had to loose my maydenhead
                           Awaked me: Quoth thother sisters, what?
                           I hope we maydens least of al
                                 •
                              feare that
                           Beleeue me (quoth the elder girle) should I
                           With my sweete-hart, on my wedding-night lie
                           And find him drowsie dull, like heauie lead
                           Hunting but coldli
                                 •
                               for a maydenhead:
                           Twould kill my tender hart: twould murder mee
                           The blushing morne I nere should liue to see
                           Oh I should fill the roome with groanes: in morne
                           With lookes deiected I should seeme forlorne.
                           
                              
But when you wakt (quoth she) cha
                                 •
                              t you not then
                           Oh noe! in that case maides nere chafe with men
                           Though wee seeme angry, at there boldest partes
                           Yet seldome comes, our anger from our hartes
                           For in loues sporte (this is our sexes wyle)
                           We'el seeme to frowne when most of all we smile
                           Yet sisters faith (quoth shee) me thought I wept
                           When I did wake, cause I noe longerslept
                           For trath-la girles such pleasure in't tooke I
                           As in like dreame, twould nere greiue me to die
                           Had I a world, Id'e givt to learne the skyll
                           Howe I should sleepe and dreame soe at my will
                           Had I that arte, that matchles pleasing slyght
                           Fewe daies Id'e haue, eache daie Id'e turne to night:
                           Lye downe I would, lulling my selfe a sleepe,
                           Bidding my soule delightfull revells keepe:
                           Sild would I wake, but alwaies by my will
                           Ide sleepe, and dreame, and be embracing still.
                           Nowe second sister wake, I praie (quoth shee)
                           And in your laste nightes dreame come second me.
                        
                        
                           THE SECOND SIsters
dreame.
                           THe second sister some what modest bold
                           Reply'd; my dreame partlie by you is told
                           Before you slept, me thought, I heard you saie
                           You in sweete musinge, did a longe tyme laie
                           You mu
                                 •
                              ing sigh'd, and sigh'd till sleepe did steale
                           Vppon your mayden eyes, their lidds to seale
                           At length you slept and dreamt you sawe your loue
                           (A dreame indeed, which much vs maydes doe moue)
                           You kiste with him but when he'ed with you lie
                           That made you w
                                 •
                              ke, and out the bedd to flie
                           But soe (me thought) sweet sister did not I
                           For I (me thought) did think it was noesym
                           To lett a youth betweene my sheetes leape in
                           But yet for fashions sake oft thus I de crye
                           
                              
Praye gett you 
                                 •
                              ence, seeke some where els to lye
                           Yet this repulse should still soe faintlie come
                           As it should feircer whett him on for roome
                           For coldlie, to denie loues sweete delight
                           Spurrs to a gallop, thefeirce appetite.
                           And sisters well you knowe, we maydes doe hold
                           Those youngmen weake which hunt loues chase but cold
                           What is it to crye, fye, or praye nowe hence?
                           
                           Why to a resolute mynde, that kinde of fence
                           Too open lies: oh! men are desprate foes
                           Vppon advantage, theile come in, and close,
                           Ide ne're crye, fye awaie, nor vtter this
                           But I would closly hugg to him and kisse.
                           Begone, sur
                                 •
                              ease, y'are rude, forbeare I praie
                           Of tymes such wordes, I've gone aboute to saie
                           But er'e those cruell wordes, could haue their birth
                           Tha'ue smoth'erd bynn, and all has turnd to mirth
                           Wagges well knowe howe, to quench our angers flame
                           Sweete kisses, at first kindling, dampe the same
                           For (sisters) Loue, his schollers this doth teache
                           Wee ioyne should lippes, to seale our lipp's from speach
                           And soe it fard with vs; speachles we laie
                           Giving to pleasures sweetned streame free waie
                           Soe longe (me thought) we dally'd in the bedd
                           As allmost I had lost my maydenhead
                           But (girles) I curse Dreames false deluding guile
                           As I was loosing it, I wakt the while
                           Oh girles! oh girles! who knowes what I did misse,
                           For I awakt, in midst of sweetest blisse
                           If euer mayde, toucht Nectar with hir lipp
                           Then I (in dreame) of that sweete iuyce did sipp
                           But oh I wakt! oh then (awakt) my spight
                           For being 'wakt, a sleepe fell all delight
                           Nowe eldest sister you must wake (quoth shee)
                           Your turne's to tell, the next dreame after me
                           And reason to the eldest sister sayde
                           Else let on me, some for feyture be laide
                           But, I must tell 
                                 •
                              e dreames you haue told twice
                           Vnles I should, some fayned dreame devise
                           Were here more then fiue hundred maydes: yet each
                           
                           Of vs, should in one text and lesson preache
                           For all we maydes doe dreame alike a nights
                           Then to our eyes appeareth pleasing sigh
                                 •
                              s
                           And then a smack we taste of loues delights,
                           Oh that Dame Nature, would but heare my sute
                           Then should our mayden bodies, beare noe fruite.
                           Or would it were noe scandall to our liues
                           To haue our pappes giue sucke, er'e marryed wiues:
                           Yf with that pleasing graunt, we maydes were blest
                           Then soner would we yeild to loues requeste
                           For a my fayth girles were it not for feare
                           To be with childe, Id'e ne're denie my Deare
                           
                           Oh then these false dreames fond deluding sightes
                           Weed ne're care for: we'ed taste loues tr'ust delights
                           More then tenn thowsand tymes, Ive thought to pyne
                           This mallenchollie sullen corpes of myne
                           For sild (alas) we maydes can taste sweet loue
                           But our owne bellies, doe the tell-tales proue
                           With 
                                 •
                              ullen puft-vp pride alowde they reade;
                           Proclayming publikelye our private deed
                           Happie are wiues, for they are nere afrayde
                           Of that which terryfyeth moste a maide,
                           They maie haue boyes and girles, and boies agen:
                           They maie with husbandes lie, and other men;
                           Yet nothing noted; but alas poore we
                           Sild dare doe ought, but what the world maie see,
                           Eache thinge, it selfe againste vs doth oppose
                           All thinges are blabbes, our secrets to disclose
                           For sild we reape loues pleasure in the night
                           But envious daie (to'ur shames) bringes it to light
                           Shewing too plaine, at what game we haue beene
                           Making our sweetlie stolen pleasures seene.
                           Oh were it not for dreames, I wonder I
                           Howe we in bedd a nights could brooke to lie
                           But come, lett these things passe; eyther of you
                           Your dreames haue told: my dreame beginneth nowe
                        
                        
                           
                           THE ELDEST SIsters
dreame.
                           OH (sisters) knowe you, to my ravisht sight
                           My loue with's amber locks appeard laste night
                           Bold boie boldlie hee came as feard of naught,
                           Shewing in what schoole hee his skill was taught
                           Scar
                                 •
                              e speaking ought at all 
                                 •
                              f ought twas this
                           Where's my Gerle? smothring that too with a kisse
                           Nor with this kissing spent hee all the night
                           
                              
                                 •
                              utt (girles) our pastime yeelded more delight
                           I dreamt it did doe soe, for you must knowe
                           I did but onelie dreame, it did doe soe:
                           To loues embracementes, wee (me thought) fell then
                           But loues sweete game is coldlie chaste by men.
                           Yet our sex, workes loues labor, eu'rye daie
                           With mindes, as willing, as men goe to plaie
                           I girles I girles, I speakt in heate of bloude
                           Men too toosoone are ty'rd, with doying good
                           But oh deare girlis (such is our sexes kind)
                           One man maie please vs all, except our mind
                           For yf one man content one woman cann
                           Then, why should it not be this youthfull man?
                           His vaines were full, soe stronge a backhee had
                           As Herculis to him was but a ladd
                           Yf youth and strength 'tis, quencheth womans fire
                           Then 'twas in him, as much as Ide desire
                           But 'tis not Oceans of that liquid stuff
                           Which lyes in youthfulst men that is enough
                           To quench the mindes outragious frying flame;
                           For that once ty'nd age onely dampes the same
                           Manie a woman 'till shee hath tr'yd twoo
                           Distasteth all, hir firste sweetehart doth doe
                           From whence praie comss that Luste, that s
                                 •
                              wre-sweet smart?
                           Oh th' ead of that same springes, a divelish harte.
                           But whether from my text am I uowe fled
                           My dreame was this, I loste my maydenhead
                           
                              
To that let me retourne: oh tis delight
                           Vnto vs maides, to think but on that night.
                           Him t'weene my armes one while I did infold
                           Another while, he me, 'tweene his would hold.
                           Entwindinge leggs (me thought) with me he laie
                           While I, withs curledl
                                 •
                              cks, did sporte and plaie
                           Soe longe plaide we as sisters-well I wisse
                           Our sportes extended further then to kisse
                           Soe longe I kiste, soe longe on's looks I fedd
                           As sure in dreame I loste my maydenhead▪
                           
                           But (sisters) was it in my pow're to choose
                           Then such a losse Id'e eu'ry mynute loose
                           For when we maydes doe lose our mayden treasure
                           Oh by that losse we wynn a world of pleasure
                           Fayth Girles, Maydes cannot think what sweet delight
                           Two louers take which warr in loues feirce fight:
                           To them loath som's the daie, ouer the night
                           But nowe I sighe, nowe doe I greiue to thinke
                           That, that night my eye-lides did euer wynke
                           For when I wakt (oh dreames! oh dreames y'are theeues
                           And mist my loue, Iudge then (girles) of my greeues
                           Oh had I had tenn worldes I would haue than
                           Gev'n all those worldes (sweete girles) for half
                                 •
                               a man
                           Men stuffs their chestes as full as they can hold
                           With cramb'd-trust bagges of aungell-winged gold:
                           But what to doe? for sooth to by this land:
                           Oh would I had that dust of Tagus strand
                           Ide not buy land or howses with it I
                           For other merchandize Ide make it flie:
                           Had I such laden truncks this Ide doe than
                           For enry night ith' yeare Ide buy a man
                           For, sisters, I maie speake to you my mind
                           When I awakt, and lookt my loue to find
                           Feeling for's neck to claspe that neck of his
                           For's ruddy lipp, hoping that lipp to kisse
                           For's wanton legg, for myne with that t'yntwind
                           And sisters for—oh girles you knowe my mind
                           When for these louelie thinges I searcht to see
                           
                              
Du
                                 •
                               could not find, where those sweet things might be
                           With bitter passion, I burst out and cryd
                           Wishinge, with in my mothers womhe Id'e dy'd
                           Oh sisters! oh sweete sisters, then did I
                           Wishe, fatall Death attache me instauntlie.
                           Nowe did I stare aboute; nowe did I call
                           But when noe aunswere I could heare at all
                           Vp in my smock I rose and searcht each place
                           (Oh girles extreames our sex in loues sweete case)
                           Groping behind eache trunck, feeling vnder bedd
                           Me thought for him which had my maydenhead
                           And oft Ide crye sweete wagg, thy selfe disclose▪
                           
                           For Iv'e another maydenhead to loose
                           But when noe answere I could heare, oh then
                           Weeping, I sigh'd and went to bedd agen
                           Wher'e one while tumbling that waie; other this:
                           Nowe should I sighe; nowe my poore pillowe kiss
                                 •
                              
                           
                           Entwinding it betweene my armes embrace
                           Ide hug g't as yf my deare duck were in place
                           Fayning (in that my frying passions flame)
                           I hottlie chaste loues sweetst delightfull game
                           But when I found my sence deluded soe
                           My passions heate, to coldnes then did growe
                           For myssing him I grewe more cold then stone;
                           Oh't paynes my heart to telt; come lett's be gone.
                           Soe vp they rose, but er'e they went I rusht
                           From where I stood, at which the wantons blusht.
                           Nowe sir I hope you see what modest chatt
                           Young maydes will haue when by themselues theire gott.
                           
                              Graues swallowe them: were all dead I'de be gladd
                           The best of wiues, or maides, are worse then badd.
                        
                     
                  
               
            
            
               Allexander.
               COme, come Diogenes, although those three
               In private mirthe exceeded modestie
               Yet you doe Ill t'accuse soe gennerall;
               Cause one is badd therefore must they be all?
               In soe concludinge, very Ill you doe
               Noe man soe gen'rallie, concludes but you▪
               
            
            
               
               Diogynes.
               ANd by your leaue sir Il'e conclude soe still
               Where one of them is good tenn thowsand's Ill
               What I haue saide, I will re-saie agen
               Wer't not for them, oh blessed were we men
               Into vs men, they eate as rust and moathes
               Eates into Iron, and the fynest cloathes
               Thou seest this riv'led hollowe-eyd face of mine
               Thoudst little thinke it has beene dect-vp fyne,
               And tricklie trym'd-vp in a womans guise
               Onelie to dive into their knaueries
               But dust thou heare (I speake it to their praise)
               I haue a mary'd wife beene in my daies
               At least wise like one, for th'e
                     •
                  le yet confesse
               They once tooke old Diogines for noe lesse:
               Noe butned dublett, on my back I bo
                     •
                  e
               A gowne downe to my heeles (wif-like) I wore
               And such attire, this head of myne did beare
               As mary'd wiues in those daies vsd to weare
               Then to my chynn, noe briflye haires were knowne
               Nay'thad not entertayned anie downe
               But twas soe soft, soe slee
                     •
                  , as each man sayd
               When I past by, there goes a wife o
                     •
                   maide:
               My curled locks, hang in a careles guize
               With which the wynd did plaie in wanton wise
               Like to a wanton, I was trymlie drest
               But why I was soe, there consists the iest.
            
            
               Allexander.
               WHy wast thou soe? I pry thee Cynnick tell:
               Till thou haste told it, I shall nere be well.
            
            
               Diogines.
               WHy then be Ill: in sooth 'tis not my liste
               To make thee laughe: for I'me a Satyrist:
               
                  
Againe thy companie, I doe brooke soe Ill
               As I would haue thee gone, had I my will
            
            
               Allexander.
               WHy tel't mee then, and instantlie shalt see
               I will departe, and gett me hence from thee.
            
            
               Diogynes.
               ON that condition I will telt: why knowe
               This was the cause I went disguised soe
               The Dames of Athens merrye wenches be
               And vnto meetings giv'n-are much you see
               To gossip't with them, I did long time longe
               To heare the verdict of eache womans tongue
               For well knewe I when wiues are gott with wiues
               There's tryalls to be heard, of husbands liues
               False accusations, cruell Iudgments then,
               (Vnmercy fullie) passe vppon poore men
               To heare all which (tooth hazard of my life)
               I tooke on mee, the habitt of a wife:
               And well I womand it when I did walk
               But when at table, I were sett to talk
               Then did my tongue betraye me; for I trowe
               It prou'd a Iade in pace; t'was dull and slowe:
               I mumping satt: I could not for my life
               Make my tongue gallopp, like a marry'd wife
               Twas cause I lackt theire arte to spur it vp
               Euer anan with a full sugerd' cupp.
               Yet wiud I it the best that I could doe
               And nowe and then raild on my husband too:
               But marke mee nowe; nowe to my tale I goe.
            
            
               
                  
                     
                        The Cynnycks discription of the manner
of womens gossypping.
                        AS at our meate we satt twas hard to knowe
                        Whether our teeth or tongues, did fastest goe.
                        
                           
At tables vpper end in cheifest place
                        Satt maddam, Will, in reeling drunken case
                        Light in atire shee was, shees womens god
                        They hir true subiects be: but she'es mans rodd
                        Nothing by Will, at anie tyme is saide
                        But is by wiues, and widdowes still obayd.
                     
                     
                        VVills Oration.
                        SVbiectes quoth maddam Will I here am sett
                        Not alltogeather, to se howe you eate
                        Nor came I whollie to participate,
                        With this your freelie-spoken merrye prate
                        But chieflie why amongst you nowe I come
                        Is to knowe howe eache wife, fares in hir home
                        Howe by hir husband shee is dailie vsd
                        Whether she'es well-entreated, or abusd,
                        Therefore yf anie of you suffer greife
                        Know't I am Will, and will yeild you releife
                        Be bold to speake, I am the wiues delight
                        And euer was, and wilbe th'usbandes spight
                        Il'e sut as Iudge vppon these wicked men
                        Doe you accuse, and Il'e guie s
                              •
                           ntence then.
                     
                     
                        The old vviues complaynt againste
hir younge husband.
                        AT which old Crona with hir redd-bleare eys
                        From of the stoole she satt did straytewayes rise
                        And out aloude, to Will, for iustice cryes.
                        Quothe she, mysou'raygne Queene 'tis not with tongue
                        I able am t'expres my dayelie wronge.
                        Three husbandes haue I had; two old in truth
                        But they the cropping had, of my greene youth
                        In lewe of whith (to thin'k on't nowe I'me sadd)
                        They left me all the goodes and gold they had.
                        With Cattell sto'rd-was all my pasture growndes
                        
                           
With fyne woold bleating sheepe 
                              〈…〉
                            downes
                        Crambd'was my barnes, my cheste with in't did hold
                        Manie a Princes picture in puere gold
                        and while they liv'd, that thing was wondrous skant
                        That Crona euer did speake-for and want:
                        Then in wealthes pleasures I did swymm and floate
                        But out alas that e're old fooles should doate
                        For since theire deathes (oh Queene I speakt' with ruth?)
                        Fond-foolish I sett my loue on a youth
                        Making him maister and possessor quite
                        (In hope heed' doe to mee all true loues right)
                        Of all the golden goodes I were possest
                        And left-with by theire soules, which nowe doe res
                              •
                           e
                        But (aye me Caytif) neuer wretched I
                        Vntill this tyme knewe, what was miserie
                        Oh nowe I fynd, this is the sweeter life
                        To be an old mans nurse, then a youths wife
                        For' s loue I wedded him, but he aboue
                        Doth onelie knowe, who doth enioie his loue
                        My bedd hee loathes; hee neuer giues me kis
                        But hee cries, wife, reward my leue for this
                        For yf younge men old wiues one kis affordes
                        Tis for the loue th'aue, to theire golden hordes,
                        Without I buy his loue, heel lye all night
                        In sullen wise, and discontented plight
                        Not once soe much as turning vnto me
                        Vnles a golden lure, his eyes doth see.
                        And nowe greats goddes Will, for loues intent
                        Soe longe I bribd him haue, as all is spent
                        And I am cast-of, wherefore lett me craue
                        That gainst him, publick sentence I maie haue
                        At which same periodd, all the wittles route
                        In hir behalfe vnto dame Will cryd' out.
                     
                     
                        Dame VVills Sentence.
                        SVbiect quoth Will, well has thy fluent tongue
                        Exprest with passion thy too greate a wronge
                        
                           
The sentence I pronounce against that wight
                        Is this; thou shalt torment him daie and night
                        With that same poysned instrument of thyne
                        I meane thy tongue: then shalt-thou se, in fyne
                        Howe despratelye, to hang himselfe he'ele gadd
                        Or els, howe soone he will proue braint-sick madd
                        My seutence is at noe tyme thou shalt rest,
                        But with thy tongue torment him still thy beste.
                        Infeilde, in bedd, at borde, in eache place still
                        Ide haue thee stying him with thy bitterst skill
                        Call him vp start, base scumm, the worst of worst;
                        Ask him who made him, and who raisd him firste?
                        Tell him, e're thou mettst with him hee did lacke
                        Shoes for's feete, hose for's leggs, and cloathes for's back
                        Such peales at all tymes ring thou in his eare
                        It is my sentence; doo't, and doe not feare
                        To doe that hest, awaie did Crona trudge
                        Praising dame Will, for a moste vpright Iudge.
                     
                     
                        The younge vvifes complaint against
hir ieolous headed old
husband.
                        THat wrinckle-faced drudge, noe sooner gone
                        But in hir place straight flept-vp such a one
                        As matchles was in bewties pleasing grace;
                        One, who exceld, loues mother in the face
                        Men call hir Youtha: oh-greate queene quoth shee
                        Since woemens wronges thou rightst', then right thou mee
                        My couetous parents (not to Natures kinde)
                        Vnto an old man matcht me, 'gainste my minde
                        Fortie such men, vnable are to quenche
                        The firye flames tyn'd in a lustfull wenche.
                        When burning Luste with's violent scortching fire
                        Hath sing'd my harte with passions feirce desire
                        Then in Loues chase I hunt, for in Loues game
                        Remayneth that which quencheth Lusts hott flame.
                        
                           
But, tweene an old mans armes what's there to quench?
                        Still flares the flames, ty'nd in a youthfull wench.
                        Yet yf that shiu'ring coldnes heate allaies;
                        Then that in old men, shall we find alwaies
                        As we are extreame hott, soe still are they
                        Extreame in that same cold extremytee
                        But loues feirce fire with fire must quenched be;
                        'Ells still the more it burnes: so't fares with me.
                        For 'las, when lust hath heate me, I cann find
                        His cold embrace, nòe quencher of my mind
                        My parents might haue matcht me to one dead,
                        As well as to a sapples old mans bedd:
                        I cann smale diffrence make: for men one old
                        Like dead men laye: oh th'are corruptly cold.
                        Rug'd-wrinckled is his face: his head in showe
                        Seemes like a hillock, hild with milk white snowe
                        His humors heauier, then sadd massie lead
                        His leggs like Isicles doe warme my bedd
                        Noe signe of heate, is in this aged fire
                        'Les in his nose, but that resembles fire.
                        What shall I saie, ther'es none, that doth him see
                        But saies the picture of cold winte'rs he
                        Yet I (oh moste vnequall matche!) alas
                        Enforste to wedd, with this cold dotard was
                        With whom (greate Queene) I such a life doe leade
                        As I eache mynute, wishe my selfe were dead.
                        Soe hath his aged disabillitie
                        Possessed him, with this feende Ieolosie
                        As I cann noe waies, goe from sight ofs' eyes
                        But straitewaies after me, he sendes his spies
                        Nor cann I talke with anie, but in's head
                        A riseth some conceipte, Il'e wrong his bedd.
                        Let but atrech'rous doore in night once creake
                        Then straight he doubtes, ther'es some with me would speake
                        Confrence with neerest knin, heel not allowe,
                        Fearing we plott, to breake our weddlock vowe
                        Which god he knowes (greate Queene) my spottles mind
                        That waies as yet, hath neuer beene inclynd
                        
                           
Smyle I, or weepe I, all is one; for hee
                        Of wha't soe e're I doe, will ieolous bee
                        If I doe smyle, then sayes he straight Iv'e had
                        Sport with my loue; tis that, makes me soe gladd
                        If I am sadd; then doth hee saie hee knowes
                        The spring from whence my mallanchollie flowes
                        Vp braydinge me, I'me onelie sadd for this
                        Because my loue, of his sett how're did misse
                        Such is a grislie old mans, faire wiues' state
                        As ieolous-headed he will deeme she'el hav't
                        Though ouer hir hee setts a thousand spies,
                        And eu'rye spie, an Argus is, for's eyes:
                        Therefore, since (causles) he doth wrong me soe
                        Teache me revenge against this loathed foe.
                        Giue sentence (Queene) what shall bee done by me
                        Againste him in revenge ofs' ieolosee.
                     
                     
                        Dame VVills sentence in the young
wifes behalf against hir old
husband.
                        
                           YOutha quoth maddam Will, with greate reguard
                        Haue I, this thy sadd information heard
                        And doe bewaile the same; but Ile' haue thee
                        Plague thy old husband, for his Ieolosee.
                        Yet Ieolous-headed men noe plagves doe neede
                        For in themselues, sufficient plagues doe breede
                        For looke in what place, Iealosie doth dwell
                        There are the tormentes, of an earthlie hell.
                        Yet since for naught, he doubts soe faire a dame
                        Thus shalt thou sting and torture him, forth' same.
                        In secrett wise, Ile haue: hee staine his bedd,
                        And graft faire guilded hornes, on's silverd head
                        Such glorious spriggs soe well in noe place growes
                        As in the riv'led furrowes of an old mans browes.
                        Thou art a woman, therefore canst not want
                        At all tymes skill, such setts and grafts, to plant
                        
                           
My sentence is thou shalt him soe beguild
                        As make him thinke his father to that child
                        Which thou thyselfe knowst not who it bego
                              •
                           t
                        Togather goodes for whom, shall th'old drudgi trott
                        Not sparing night nor daie, till's life be done
                        Howe to scrape wealth, to giue anothers sonn
                        And cause thy parents, forste thee to his bedd
                        Thus will I haue thy parents punnished.
                        Thou shalt, vnto theire skarlet blushing shame,
                        Bespott them with the spotts, of thy staind name
                        Soyling thy wedding sheetes, faire I'vry white
                        With fowle black spotts, of salt lusts loathd delight
                        Bewteous youtha my sentence nowe is done
                        See that on them the'res execution.
                     
                     
                        The gossipping vviues complaint
against hir riche churlishe
husband.
                        THis sentence giv'n, the whole route
                              •
                           gann to rise
                        But pert-quicke-tongued Gossippa (whose eyes
                        Contaynd of brymishe teares a cristall fluude)
                        Starts-vpp, and praies Dame Will, to hir be good.
                        Of all thy louing subiectes I (quoth shee)
                        Haue euer yet beene found faythfulst to thee
                        And therefore my good Queene, let me acquainte
                        Thy gentle eares with one petition plainte.
                        Two thinges I loue; two vsuall thinges they are
                        The firste, newe-fashiond cloathes, I loue to weare
                        Newe tires, newe ruffes; I, and newe gesture too:
                        In all newe fashions, I doe loue to goe:
                        The second thing I loue, is this I weene
                        To ride aboute to haue those newe cloathes seene
                        At eu'rye gossipping I am at still
                        And euer wilbe, maie I haue my will
                        For at ons owne howse, praie, who ist' cannsee
                        Howe fyne in newe found, fash'ond tires wee bee?
                        
                           
Vnles our husbandes; faithe; but verye fewe
                        And whoo'd goe gaie, to please a husbands veiwe?
                        Alas we wiues doe take but smale delight
                        Yf none (besides our husbandes) se'es that sight.
                        It ioyes our heartes, to heare an other man
                        P
                              •
                           aise this or that attire, that wee weare on
                        Wee iocond are, and thinke ourselues much graste
                        Yf we heare one saie, faire wenche, faithe in waste
                        
                        This straight-girt gowne, becomes you passing well
                        From other Taylors, yours doe beare the bell:
                        Oh hee that well cann actt-out such sweete partes
                        Throwes-vp the sure which wynns our verye hartes
                        When we are stubborn'st, then let men with skill
                        Rubb'es well with th'oyle of praise and bend we will
                        That smoothe-fyne supple oyle doth soften vs foe
                        As what ist then we will not yeild vnto?
                        Meetinges and brauerye were my delight:
                        Those were the two: but (greate queene) he'res the spight
                        Without greate store of wealth, be dailie gainde
                        Of all delightes, those are the worste maintaind
                        And therefore I did alwaies plott in mind
                        Howe a wealthie, riche husband, out to find
                        And one I've gott: but such a churle is hee
                        As scarce a penny will bestowe on mee
                        And that shall neuer come, but (fore, I ha'te)
                        The miserable clowne, will scratch his pate
                        Alwayes demaundinge what with't, I will doe
                        
                           And then comes out, her'es such a stir with you.
                        A man had better tidd-be of his life
                        Then clog'd with such a fydling foolish wife
                        Such are his tauntes, when I demaund him ought
                        As what I gett from him is dearelie bought.
                        I cannot grosslie feede, for I in sooth
                        Haue a tender mawe, and a daintie tooth
                        These beeues and muttons, are but homelie fare
                        My appetite doth thirste-for what's most rare:
                        Had I vnto my mind, then I would eate
                        Still of the fynest pallat-pleasing meate
                        
                           
But fye on h
                              •
                           gges! oh! there is none liues, liues
                        Soe straunglie hatefull as these rich churles wives
                        For yf I cannot gnawe, a hard drye cruste
                        Manie a daie, faste-out the tyme I muste.
                        Iuste like to Tantalus it fares with mee
                        For what I hunger-for I alwaies see.
                        All what against him I d'e to saie, Ive saide
                        Nowe queene I doe ymplore thy counsells ayde.
                        I cannot gossipp it nor cann goe trymm
                        Cause I want arte, to worke coine out from him.
                        Tatling Gossippa here-at holdes hir tongue
                        With praying maddam Will to right hir wronge.
                        Silence beinge made, thus dame Will replies.
                     
                     
                        VVills sentence vppon the
rich churle
                        SVbiect quoth shee I've heard thy Iniuries
                        And yf they all hee true which I did heare
                        Then are they too too much for thee to beare
                        For to vs women these thinges are moste Ill
                        T'abate our prides, and to restraine our will
                        If hee bee riche; his harnes are full of graine
                        Where hee one bushell sells, sell thou still twaine
                        His swyne, sheepe, geese, henns, ducks, doe thou convaie
                        I, sell his very shirtes but goe thou gaie,
                        Of all men, hee vnworthy'st is of life
                        That will not laste of all mistruste his wife.
                        A nightes, faile not but pick the churles stuft purse
                        Yf hee doth sware, I hope thy tongue cann curse
                        But yf his barnes, purse, yarde, and all doe fayle
                        Then to th'old vse put thou thy nimble tayle
                        Lett that worke for thee; for by that same waie
                        Ther'es manie a woman makes hir selfe gaie
                        That waie thou maiste the supple sattins ware
                        That waie thou maiste feede on thee dainty'st fare
                        Yf noe waie else thou canste make thy selfe trymm
                        Then that waie, tis my will, thou punnish him
                        
                           
Whoo'd sweate and toyle for this same golden treasure
                        When one maie gett it, with the sweetest pleasure
                        Thou knowst my minde; Gossippa, doe it then:
                        Fare wenches cannot want, while there are men.
                     
                  
               
            
            Diogynes makes himself
knowne.
            AT th'end of which same sentence, all arose
            Where at my selfe to them I did disclose
            But er'e I did it, I did gett to'oth dore
            For had they caught me, they'd haue vsd me sore:
            To hold me, eu'rye woman out did crie
            But being out theire reache awaie rann I:
            Gladd that Id'e seene and heard theire knauerye
            Nowe sir, Ive iustlie told, for what intent
            I like a woman amongst women went
            Yf you on theire behalfes haue ought to saie
            Sait'e some where else, or gett you hence awaie
            
               Allexander.
               TO what thast' saide, smale creditt I cann giue
               For I shall neuer made-be to beleeue
               That creatures halfe devine for glorious bewtie
               Should soe respectles be to man in dutie.
               Thinges eu'rye waie soe perfect faire in showe
               In virtues fullie perfect, are I knowe.
            
            
               Diogynes.
               THou knowst it; doost? awaie, thou art an else
               What canst thou knowe, that knowest not thy selfe
               The golden-skaled snake's, a louelie thinge
               Had not that glorious worme, a poysned stinge
               Of maides and wiues noe barrell better bee
               Would God made none, but what were spoke of mee.
            
            
               
               Allexander.
               WHy prithee speake; howe manie wouldst haue then?
            
            
               Diogines.
               FOr one halfe girle, tenn hundred thowsand men.
            
            
               Allexander.
               NOwe fie vppon thee 
                     •
                  ynnick, why dost bite
               And sett soe pure a thing, as woman light?
               I am a shamd' of thee; doe what I can,
               I cannot think, thou art a perfect man
               I doe beleeue that thou at noe tyme haste
               That manlie heare, which causeth man to waste
               Thou art noe man; for we'rt a man. I'me sure
               A womans companie thou couldst endure.
               But saie, thou wert en forst vppon thy life
               To take thee to some one to be thy wife
               What kinde of woman-creature wouldst thou chuse
               Yf it were soe thou mighst' it not refuse.
            
            
               Diogynes.
               BY hanginge, Ide chuse rather end my life
               Then Id'e a woman haue, to be my wife
               But were it soe, that one I needes must haue
               And that I had noe waie, my selfe to saue
               Then all the world Ide' seeke, but I would fynd
               A woman for my wife, dumb, deafe, and blinde
               Besides; yf I could possiblie prevaile
               Ide seeke the world for one, without a taile
               Most men in bodie wasted are by wiues
               But such I' me sure, would proue restoritiues.
            
            
               
               Allexander.
               FIe man; why what in women doost thou see
               That they soe much, distastefull are to thee.
            
            
               Diogynes.
               NOe more then thou maiste see, yf th'art not blind
               Why moste of them hudge gyantes are for minde
               
                  Pride keepes hir faire in eache faire wantons face
               And Luste keepes in theire 
                     〈…〉
                   markett place
               Revengefull Wrath theire furious tongues doth swaie.
               From labor, drowsie Sloath their handes doth staie
               In syns sweete-poysned Iuyce drunken theile be
               And Envie others, drunken soe to see
               What see I not in them? they are the Inns
               Wherein doth lodge those monstrous murdring synns.
            
            
               Allexander.
               FIe Cynnick, thou doste blowe too bitter aire
               On tender blossoms, which are sweetlie faire.
            
            
               Diogynes.
               YF shee be faire, and a sharpe-witted one
               And honeste too; a Phenix she'es alone.
               Who hath tenn Herculesses strengths in's loines
               And with a faire sharpe-witted wanton Ioyns
               Shall be assurd the horne, on's browe to fynd:
               Whoo'l quench a wantons luste must quench the mind;
               Th'are proude; eache wench would bee an Allexander
               
               And by hir will, ouer a world commaunder.
               But yf not proude, nor lustfullie inclind
               Then eyther foole, or scold, of hir shalt fynd.
               Eyther of them, mans patience soe would alter
               As they would make him straight make vse ath halter,
               They are all naught, I cannot brooke em I
               
                  
                  
                     •
                  ould I were Dea
                        •
                     e, then women all should die
            
            
               Allexander.
               NAie fie Cynnick thou railst too gennerall
               Thou muste not for some fewe condemn em all,
               Thou talkst, as yf thou wert noe womans sonn
               I would th'adst trauaild, but as I haue done:
               Although th' Athenians givn are to theire will
               And liue a life displeasinge (hatefull ill)
               Yet since my travaile, (whe
                     ••
                   I haue beene)
               Aboundance vertuous 
                     〈◊〉
                   I haue seene.
            
            
               Diogynes.
               OH ya'r a trauaylier; praie are you soe?
               Where you haue beene, black swanns you haue seene too
               Good trauayler the hearinge I will giue you
               But you shall giue me leaue not to beleeue you
               Women are naughte: Il'e talk noe more with thee
               And therefore naught, because women they bee.
            
            
               Allexander.
               OH straung! yf Allexander heard but thee
               For womens sakes (I'me sure) thou'dst punnisht be.
            
            
               Diogynes.
               GOe telt' him goe; I doe as little care
               For him as thee; let both doe what you dare.
               Tell me of him? I feare him not a flie:
               I dread not might: Diogynes am I:
               Hees but a man; Il'e ne're fa
                     •
                  ne for mans grace
               What I haue saide, Il'e boldlie saye too's face
               And wer't, he were as badd as women bee
               Id'e bite the monnark to his face, shouldst see.
            
            
               
               Allexander.
               HE knowes thou wouldst in that I knowe the 
                     〈◊〉
                  
               
               For I am hee: for this cause here I came
               To heare thy wittie bluntnes, and to see
               Whether thy sayings and thy deedes agree,
               Come Cynnick burne this tubb and followe me
               And vnto noble titles, Il
                     •
                  raise thee.
            
            
               Diogynes.
               THou wilt: but I will not: none can raise me;
               I'me in my tubb as greate a Kinge as th
                     •
                  e.
               Who holdes the world and it's vaine trash for flight
               He truelie conquers it, giue him his right:
               And soe doe I: therefore hudge Allexander
               
               I hold my selfe (ath twaine) the greatst commaunder
               I will not begg to rule and governe landes
               Onelie thy absence, Ile begg at thy handes.
               I prethee pack thee hence and gett thee gone
               The companie still is best, where is but one.
               Goe seeke thee out an other world to wynn
               And putt the women of this world therein
               But let that world be farr enough; and then
               Learning and virtue will encrease with men
               Naught else I haue to begg, graunt but this suite
               Then henceforth euer, shall my tongue rest mute.
            
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            YOu choyceste creatures, (you which god did take
            From-out mans selfmans comforter to make)
            Discomfort not your selues nor be dismayd
            At what a dogged Cynnick here hath sayde
            What though sowre-churlishe-he (too currish blynde)
            Hath barkt too broadlye gainste your gentle kind
            Yet little doth such clouds keepe from our sights
            Your shynninge virtues; this worldes splendanntst lights
            Happlye his gally ve
                  •
               aym'd speech proceeds
            As grounded byself-doyinge divelishe deedes.
            Dead is the dogg, I hope and for your sex
            The spirritts doth his spirritt hottlye vex.
            Excuse my worke, it paintes the Cynnick forth
            And to the wise it nothinge staines your worth.
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            A MORRALL SATIRE,
Intituled the Owles araygnement.
            
               
                  WHen fowles could talke with reason like to men
               This accydent amongst em happend then:
               Before the Prince of fowles the Owle was brought
               To aunswere why she did things lawles naught:
               Her adversaries were the batt the thrush
               
               With others moe: who night' lie in the bush
               Shee ey her scard with skreeking fearefull cryes
               Or sodeynlie (ere wake) did them surprize:
               Wherefore they apprehending hir did craue
               That they against hir might iuste Iustice haue.
               Greate Prince quoth they to death put thou this Owle
               She is a vildlie living wicked fowle:
               Vnfitt to liue: all daie shee sleepes; a nightes
               Smale birds shee kills; the best and greatst she frights
               Breaking our quiet sleepe with the fell noyse
               Of manlike lure and yauling-whooping voice
               And therefore sou'raigne Prince wee all doe craue
               Since shee deserveth death, death she maie haue.
               The Eagle sternlie mild putt them a side
               Commaunding silens thus the Eagle cryd
               Come forward Owle and free thy hart from feare
               Speake freelie bird true iustice I doe here
               Before my sword of iustice Death doth strike
               Th' accuser, and th' accusd I heare alike
               Bribes nor affection maks my cleare eys blind
               And therefore freelie feareles speak thy mind
               When th'owle did heare this mild speach of hir Lord
               Couradg shee tooke in gesture and in word
               Chearing hir selfe, shee thus tooth Eagle cryes
               Impartiall iustice comes from Maiesties
               
                  
And since your highnes doth thus daine to heare
               My cause your selfe; my cause I little feare
               For what need I quoth shee dread anie thing
               Being my cause is heard before my King.
               Let murdrers quake when, Iustice shakes hir rodd
               The Iust nere feares the Iudgment of Iust god
               Noe more will I since freelie plead I must
               (In guiltles cause) before a King soe iust
               Two accusations are against me 
                     •
                  ayde
               To be a murdrer is the first I'me sayde
               The second is that I in sylent night
               With manlike voice smale birds and fowles afright
               Greate Prince I both confes; but firste Ile showe
               The cause and reason which makes me skreek soe
               A nightes I hollowing whoop and wondring crye
               But gratious Prince this is the reason why
            
            
               In eache place I doe see proude Babells built
               With cloude-braving turretts daubd-o're with gu
                     ••
                  t
               With in those Babells I doe peepe to spie
               The princelie presence of your maiestie
               But when in steed of you (on bedd of strawe)
               I see that tatling bird, the Iack-adawe
               With admiration then awaie I flie
               Then lo ho ho then wo ho ho crye I.
               
            
            
               Sometimes I daringlie presume to peepe
               With in your Court when all your courtyers sleepe
               Where when I see the prating parratt grac'd
               And birdes of better worth for him displac'd
               Or when I see the plumy peacocks pride
               To striue to lie by's sou'raigne Princes side
               And se the valiant Cock with swaines to liue
               That sight much wonder to my eyes doth giue
               With admiration then awaie I flie
               Then lo ho ho then wo ho ho crie I
               
            
            
               Sometimes I flie ore Neptunes glassie soile
               To veiwe the slipps of our set-girt-in Ile
               
                  
But 
                     〈…〉
                   they hee
               Howe like they are tooth winter-shaken tree
               And howe from them all braue sea birds are fledd
               Then like a malecontent I hang downe head
               With admiration then awaie I flie
               Then lo ho ho then wo ho ho crie I
               
            
            
               Sometimes ore sto'nd-paud Citties I take flight
               Where to my night-cleard eyes admired sight
               I see the Cuccoe build in house his neaste
               Which ere was wont to be Silvanus gueste:
               Baselie brooking each cock-sparrowes rivalrye
               Suffrings mate for trash to bath in brothelry
               A nights such sights presented to my eye
               Makes me with wonder wo ho ho to cry.
               
            
            
               This is the cause greate Prince why in the night
               I wonder soe: nowe where they doe indight
               Me for a murtherer: your grace shall find
               I'me leaste of all your-nobles soe inclind;
               Guitles I plead; or yf I guiltie be
               With me must die your whole nobility
               Your Hawkes (dread souraigne Prince) doe dailie kill
               And dailie doe devoure eate-vp and spill
               Your honest subiects yet theres noe a aint
               Laies hold of them `gainst them the'res noe complaine
               Greate-peares nere to Princes should not doe soe
               By their stepps we track which waie Kings doe goe
               As Phebes light from Phebus doth proceed
               Soe doth a great Lords act froms Princes deed
               Yf Kings encloud with vice their Virtues sunn
               That selfe thick-foggye course their peeres will runn
               If I doe murther, they doe murther too
               What waie I goe, that waie your hauks must goe
               Else gratious Prince your lawe giues waye and place
               To such as are, or are not in your grace.
               Else greate ones open maie your m
                     •••
                  yes doore
               Sucking the fatt from men but meanlie poore
               Iniustly wronging poore-poore vnderlings
               
                  
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
               
               Far fowler acts within themselues they 
                     ••
                  rrish
               And consciensles the 
                     〈…〉
                   things cherrish
               But soe it should not be my souraigne King
               For from a Kingdoms lawes cleere christ all spring
               Alike all streames should runn: I eu'ry where
               That should spoute water vncorruptlie cleare
               Let it doe soe my Prince: let poore mans cryme
               Be iudgd like theires: w' are made of self-like slime
               All kings are earthlie gods; therefore should Kings
               In an impartiall ballance weigh all thinges
               The iustest iudge doth soe; and soe should your
               Like that corruptles iudg in all pointes doe.
               I freelie speake; the cause I speake soe free
               Is' cause at first great Prince you licensd mee.
               I haue accusd, but not excusd; for still
               My faults not lessond for an others ill
               Therefore my Prince to this my pleadings tend
               You'l quitt my fault, and Ile my fault amend.
               The Prince well listning to th' appeaching Owle
               Turnes to the hawkes, on whom with wrathfull scowl
               He fixt his eyes. Quoth he, speake is it true
               My nobles which this owle reports of you?
               In guiltles bloud haue you embrud your hands?
               T'is monstrous vilde! why your the propps of land
                     •
                  
               
               The steres men to your Prince: by you hees lede
               By whom but you should he be counselled?
               Your heades should conduicts be: cleare cristall springs
               From which should powre al wholsom virtuous things
               From your braines fountaines such pure streames should flowe
               As by that moysture things should florishing growe,
               Wherefore enact I lawes with your consent?
               I thinke to punish vice was our intente
               Will you 
                     〈◊〉
                   are parte makers of the lawe
               Be breakers of it first? How then in awe
               Shall I my sub
                     ••
                  cts haue? why when they se
               You drownd 
                     〈◊〉
                   haue they 'le deeme the like of me
               Disgracefullie then this they will report
               
                  
Howe theirs an extreame famin grown at court;
               Of virtuous men theres such a famin grown
               As scarcelie one about the Court is knowne
               By you shall I growe to loathd infamie
               And iudgd the nurse of fowle-fell tyranny
               And therfore nobles yf your free and cleare
               From these dambd haynos crimes, makt now appeare,
            
            
               Silence being made, the guiltie nobles
               Seing themselues to growe to dangrous trobles
               Thus (despratly) replies: oh King quoth they
               I hope vnto our murthers youl giue waie
               Yf we make spoile and other birds vndoe
               We take thexsample souraign Prince from you
               We nerest Princes Imitate them still
               We be the emblems of your good or Ill
               Yf you slaie, we slaie; yf you saue, we saue
               All Kings about them manie shadowes haue:
               For this our fau
                     •
                   we seeke not make excuse
               Cause from your selfe sprang firste this faults abuse
               And therefore King yf you'l haue subiects awe
               You must not onelie make but keep your lawe.
            
            
               This peremptory aunswere so incenst
               His maiestie as twene them wars com
                     ••
                  st
               But while as they were soe at Civill strife
               The Owle that malefactour saues hir life
               She being loose awaie from keeper scudds
               Lusking from sight all daie in thickest woods
               But eu'ry night about the outlawe flies
               Ioying hir escape; wo ho ho the cryes.
               
            
            FINIS.
            
               W. G.
            
         
      
   

