
   
      
         
            The new starre of the north, shining vpon the victorious King of Suueden
            Gill, Alexander, 1597-1642.
         
         
            
               1631
            
         
         Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01744
            STC 11879.2
            ESTC S122602
            24498611
            ocm 24498611
            27739
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01744)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27739)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1852:15)
         
         
            
               
                  The new starre of the north, shining vpon the victorious King of Suueden
                  Gill, Alexander, 1597-1642.
               
               [2], 50 p., [1] leaf of plates : port.  
               
                  Printed by Augustine Matheuues for Robert Milbourne,  and are to be sold at the signe of the Greyhound in Pauls Church-yard,
                  London :
                  1631.
               
               
                  Attributed to Alexander Gill by STC (2nd ed.) and NUC pre-1956 imprints.
                  Signatures: A⁴(-A1,2) B-G⁴.
                  Includes portrait of Gustavus II Adolphus.
                  Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
                  Includes bibliographical references.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Gustaf --  II Adolf, --  King of Sweden, 1594-1632.
               Sweden --  Kings and rulers.
               Sweden --  History --  Gustavus II Adolphus, 1611-1632.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-07
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-07
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-10
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2007-10
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               
                  GUSTAVUS ADOLPHVS KING OF THE SWEDS, GOTHS, &amp; VANDALS, GREAT PRINCE OF FINLAND &amp; etc.
                  Behold the beames of this bright Northen ſtarr
Enflam'd by Mars, but sweetned more by Ioue.
He hands, and Lands subdues by dint of warr▪
But farr more hearts by goodnes win̄ing love.
By both before he came, he overcame.
Owing of Victory as swift, as Fame.
Etiam juriusquam venj, vicj
               
            
            MD ſculpsit, Sold by R Mylbourne at the Greyhound in Paules Church yard
         
         
            
            THE NEVV
STARRE
OF THE
NORTH,
SHINING VPON
the Victorious King of
SVVEDEN.
            LONDON,
Printed by AVGVSTINE MATHEVVES for
ROBERT MILBOVRNE, and are to be
ſold at the Signe of the Greyhound
in Pauls Church-yard.
1631.
         
      
      
         
            
            
            THE NEW STARRE
OF THE NORTH,
            Shining vpon the Victorious
King of Sweden.
            
               IN the yeere one thouſand
fiue hundred ſeuentie
two, there appeared
in the heauens
a new ſtrange Light,
exceeding in the apparant
bigneſſe thereof all the fixed
Starres, and ſhewing forth a bright and
Maieſticall luſtre, which was beheld,
not onely in the night time, but alſo by
ſome at Noone day, and became at that
time the gaze of the world, and taske

of all the Aſtronomers of Europe: many
of them in divers Countreyes publiſhing
their Obſervations and Opinions
concerning the nature of this Star,
and future events fore-ſignified thereby:
but none comparably with the
moſt famous Aſtronomer of our time,
called Tycho Brahe, a Nobleman of Denmarke:
who, by the advantage of his
large and curiousBy a ſtrange inſtinct of providence were thoſe admirable Inſtrumēts made and erected by Tycho a little before the appearing of this Starre, as if either the ſtar had ſtayed for his tooles, or he had foreſeene the birth of that ſtarre. Inſtruments, and vnceſſant
paines in Aſtronomicall Obſervations,
more exactly then any other ſetteth
downe the true Place, Forme, Motion,
and Height of this wondrous heauenly
Lampe. Whereunto hee addeth
alſo his Iudgement what euents it portendeth,
like to befall in the yeeres neere
following the ſaid Apparition. Accordingly
hee treateth of the ſayd Starre in
aboue 500 pages of his Booke called
by the name of Astronomica Progymnaſmata,
which Booke in the yeere 1593
was honoured by the Atteſtation of
King Iames our late Soueraigne of bleſſed
memory, in manner following.
            
               
                  
                     
                        
                        James by the grace of God
King of Scots, to the Noble
Tycho Brahe, Lord of
Knudſtrup, the chiefe Aſtronomer
of this age.
                        
                           WHereas Wee haue
vnderſtood as wel by
your letters written
to Vs, as alſo by Our
ſeruantSir Peter Young ſometime Tutor to King Iames in his minoritie. 
                           Young,
that you intend to publiſh thoſe
Workes of yours, which with invincible
paines, and manifold watchings
haue been compoſed by you,
namely, thoſe your excellent Astronomicall
Exerciſes, ſtiled by you,
Aſtronomica Progymnaſmata:
Towards the publiſhing whereof you
haue made ſuite vnto Vs, that Wee

would vouchſafe thereunto our
Commendation to be written by vs
in Ʋerſe, as alſo our Royall Priuiledge
to the Impreſsion of them.
We haue thought fit to affoard both
thoſe fauours to your ſingular good
Deſerts, and admirable Learning:
whereof wee are not now to take notice
by other mens report, or by the
only view of your Writings, hauing
in preſence with our owne eyes and
eares been made ſpectator and hearer,
in that veryThis houſe is ſcituated in the Iland called Huenna in Denmark &amp; is furniſhed with exquiſite Inſtruments and Engines for Aſtronomie, which King Iames did behold in his voyage into Denmark, whē hee went thither to bring home his Queene Anne.
                            Houſe or Tower
erected and dedicated by you vnto
Vrania the Heauenly Muſe,
where We receiued ſuch content by
that goodly ſpectacle, &amp; by the learned
conference which you had with
vs, that it is hard to determine whether
be greater, the delight, or the

admiration wherewith we now call
the ſame to remembrance, &amp;c.
                     
                  
               
            
            Then followeth the Tenour of the
Kings Priuiledge, that none for the
ſpace of thirtie yeeres, within the Dominions
of Scotland, preſume to Print
the ſaid Workes, without the conſent
of the ſaid Tycho, or his heyres.
            This Letter of Priuiledge is dated
from his Maieſties Court in Halyroodhouſe,
that laſt of Iuly, 1593, in the ſixe
and twentieth yeere of his Raigne
            Then the Latine Verſes, with this
Title.
            The commendation of Tycho
Brahe his Aſtronomicall Treatiſes by
Iames the 6. King of Scots.
            In which verſes, after the deſcription
of the artificiall modell of the motion
of the Planets, &amp; fixed Starres repreſented
in thoſe incomparable engines erected
in that houſe by Tycho Brahe, followeth

alſo the intent of Aſtrologicall
prediction in theſe words.
            
               Vt miti, aut torvo aſpectu longe ante
futura
               Praemonſtrant, Regniſ
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   Tonans quae fata
volutet
               Tychonis pandunt operae. Lege, diſce:
videbis
               Mira: domi Mundum invenies, Caelumque
libello. &amp;c.
               
                  Iacobus Rex F. manuque propria
ſcripſit.
               Great Tycho's labours alſo doe foreſhow
               Events, which ſhall befall on earth
below,
               And by diſaſterous, or faire aſpects
               What deſtinyes on Kingdomes God
directs.
               Reade heere, and learne. If you for
wonders looke,
               Loe heere the world at hand, the heavens
by booke.
            
            Made by King Iames, and written with
his owne hand.
            
               
               Tycho in this his booke after generall
obſervations of the motions of the heavens,
treateth at large of this much
admired newe Starr, (whereupon
that whole Treatiſe is intitled De nova
Stella anni 1572.) giving the deſcription
of the forme, place, motion, and
durance thereof, and demonſtrating
out of his owne and other Aſtronomers
experimentall obſervations, that
it was not ſeated in the aire, but aboue
in the throne of the higheſt Heavens,
being fixed in the very chaire of Caſsiopeia
(a figure of Starres ſo called) he
very certainly concludeth that it could
not poſsibly be any Comet ſuppoſed to
ariſe out of the vapours of the Earth
elevated into the vpper Region of the
ayre (according to the vulgar errour of
ſome Philoſophers) but that it was a
true and proper Starr, made of heavenly
matter, being none of the originall

firſt borne lights made by the hand
of God in the Creation (which poſſeſſe
an indefeiſible freehold of their
ſtation to the worlds end) but a kinde
of adopted childe of the heavens, admitted
onely for a Termer in that habitation,
which he poſſeſſed about ſixteene
Moneths.
            This Starre, as it was ſcituated in
that part of the heavens, which is called
via lactea (the milke white way)
ſo it is not vnprobably ſuppoſed by Tycho
to haue beene compoſed of the matter
of that part of the heavens. Wherein
Tycho avoweth that he beholdeth
ſince the vaniſhing of that Starre a kind
of vacuity or diverſity of colour in that
very place where the Starre ſtood, as
ſhewing the conſumption and abſence
of ſo much white ethereall matter as
was vſed to the compoſure of that Star.
            By ſome it was deemed to be the
very ſame Starre, which appeared vnto
the Sages of the Eaſt at the birth of our
Saviour, and thereupon coniectured to

be the neerefore-runner of the ſecond
comming of Chriſt, as that was the
attendant of his firſt comming. Accordingly
(as Tycho in this booke recordeth)
Vir admodum celebris, &amp; de literis
tam ſacris, quam philoſophicis praeclare meritus,
de hac ſtella eleganti Epigrammate ſic
luſit. Theodore Beza a man famous in
this age for his great abilities in learning
both of Humanity and Divinity,
made an elegant Epigram, which thus
endeth.
            
               Et, qui naſcenti praeluxit, nunciat idem
               Ecce redux reducem rurſus adeſſe Deum.
               Hinc igitur felix ô turba applaude piorum
               Tu vero Herodes ſanguinolente time.
               That lampe, which at our Saviours
birth did burne,
               By this returning light ſhewes
Chriſts returne.
               O therefore now reioyce ye ſonnes
of God:
               But bloody Herod tremble at this
rodde.
            
            
               
As then Tycho, ſo much more we
now may ſay that Maſter Beza heerein
did not ſo much intend Hiſtoricall certainty,
as morall application in this his
pious Poeticall rapture. And therefore
well may we take vp his concluſion, as
applyable to the event of Gods mercies
to his Church, and iudgements againſt
the enemies thereof.
            Our learned and noble Tycho Brahe
in the concluſion of this his worke ſetting
downe his Aſtrologicall iudgment
profeſſeth the ſame to bee but coniecturall,
aſcribing vnto God onely the certaine
foreknowledge of all ſuch events
vpon earth, as are cauſed or intimated
by extraordinary apparitions of Comets
or new Starres in the Heavens. And in
the leading motiues to his opinion
heerein he proceedeth not boldly like a
raſh heatheniſh Starre-gazer, but modeſtly,
warily and in generall.
            Firſt, he layth this ground, moſt probable
in it ſelfe, that, if there be any certaine
portending inclination in ſuch

rare and admirable apparitions, ſurely
moſt in the moſt rare and extraordinary.
But none like this (ſayth Tycho) was
ever teſtified by any monument of antiquity
to haue bin ſeene in the world,
except that which Pliny avoweth to
haue beene ſeene and obſerved by
Hipparchus, who lived toward the
end of the Grecian Monarchy about
120. yeares before the birth of our
Saviour.
            Now if, by interpretation of event,
&amp; conſent of the learned, that new ſtarr
then appearing 
                  •
               id foreſhew the declining
of the Greeke Monarchy &amp; the riſe &amp;
ſtrength of the Roman Empire, why may
not this new Star being of the like kind,
foreſhow alſo rariſsimos, ingentes, at
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  
improviſ
                     •
                  s 
                     •
                  ffectus, ſtrange, great, and
vnexpected effects to come in the neare
ſucceeding times in the eſtate of Kingdomes
or Common-weales Which
what they will be in particular nulli
mortalium ſatis perspectum iudico.
               Pag. 802. I thinke
no mortall man is of counſayle.
            
               
Then ſtepping forwarder to the nearer
view of the kind of effects to come,
he gathereth out of the Ioviall luſtre of
it ending in a more fiery and Martiall
glaring redneſſe that it promiſeth proſperous
ſucceſſe,Ibidem. but intermingled with
violence and trouble: as alſo by the
place of it in the Aequinoctiall Colure (vbi
ſacrorum indicatio) that ſome great alterations
are like to befall in matter of
Religion,Pag. 803. 
               ſo that thoſe deviſes, which by outward
ſhew and Phariſaicall hypocriſie haue
long time bewitched ignorant people, ſhall
come to their full poynt and end.
            
            And becauſe the Star fixed neere the
Colure, yet poſſeſſed the firſt degree of Aries
being the place of the Spring when
the day getteth advantage of the night,
therby is portended ſome new light which
ſhall abate and vanquiſh former darkneſſe.
               Ibid.
            
            Theſe generals leade but a little way
vnleſſe ſome direction follow of quando
and vbi by the maine index of this Dyall
pointing vnto time and place.
            
            As for the time,Quando. hee proiecteth firſt

by the direction of the Poles of the
world,Pag. 804. 
               Si ex Aſtrologicis temporum menſurationibus
prima initia quando aliquatenus
huius Stellae ſignificata pullulabunt coniectare
licebit ex directione Coniunctionis
maximae (cui Stella haec Prodromus) &amp;c.
If we take leaue by Aſtrological calculation
of time, to make coniecture concerning
the firſt beginning of that which
is portended, we gueſſe it will be in the
bud about nine yeeres after the great
Coniunction following ſhortly after the
appearing of this Star. And ſo in Computation
with the place of the new Star,
this deſigned time wil fall out at the accompliſhment
of the third Septenary of
yeeres, (viz. the 21. yeere after the
firſt appearing of the Star) being the
yeere 1592. But if one and twentie
yeeres complete, (which Tycho ſeemeth
to intend) bee added, the time will
reach rather to the yeare of our Lord,
1593.
            The ſecond way of this Calculation
of the time,Pag. 805. is by the Direction of the Zodiaque,
               
from the place of that Great
Coniunction by the Longitude of the new
Starr vnto the ſeuenth Degree of Taurus,
which Coniunction happeneth
neere the ende of the ſeuenth Septenary,
48 yeeres after the firſt appearing of
the New Starr, viz about the yeare,
1620. About that time, ſaith
Tycho, in all probabilitie will inure
the vigour and operation of this
new Starr, Annis praeſertim aliquot ſequentibus,
eſpecially ſome yeares after
that time, poſt, viz. completum a nato
Chriſto annum. 1632. aut circiter, namely
after the yeare of Chriſt 1632. or thereabouts.
            As for the deſigning of the place
where the influence of this Starr ſhall
worke,Vbi. firſt in generall it muſt needs
concerne the Northerne part of the
World on this ſide of the Aequator, becauſe
the Starr appeared and dwelt in
this Hemiſphere: and conſequently
muſt be held to haue moſt operation
where it was moſt verticall; that is on

thoſe parts where the Star was moſt direct
over the head, and ſent forth the
beames of his influence moſt perpendicular.
Not that mutations muſt needs
happen in thoſe places onely, or neceſſarily
in thoſe very places, but (as may
well be noted out of the words of Tycho)
prae caeteris aliquid ominis thoſe parts
are ominous aboue the reſt:Pag. 808. inſomuch
as INDE mutationum tantarum occaſio
at
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   author expectanda: from thence are to
be expected the occaſion and author
of ſo great alterations. Which much
conduceth to the interpretation hereafter
following.
            Now becauſe the fixed ſeat of the new
Star was in diſtance from the Aequator
Northward about 62. degrees, that
tract of the earth which lieth in the
Northen latitude of 62. is to be taken
as principally intended: which in our
part of the knowne world rangeth along
from the Weſt through Norvegia,
Swedia, Finlandia, Livonia, Moſcovia, and
Tartaria. In all which Countries thoſe

parcells which lye vnder the forenamed
latitude, had once every day that
new Starre in their Zenith, that is iuſt
over the head. But in this Diurnall
motion how and vpon what poynt
of this circle to fixe the dint of the influence,
Hic labor, hoc opus eſt. There lies
the buſineſſe.
            Learned Tycho guided his Contemplation
by the very firſt New Moone
after the firſt appearing of the Starr:
which New Moone fell vpon the fifteenth
of Nouember, ſeauen houres thirteene
minutes ⅔ in the afternoone, accounting
the time by the Meridian of
Tycho's Iland: at which inſtant the new
Starr was in the Meridian of 53 Degrees
from the Weſt, and ſo became in
that inſtant verticall and higheſt to that
place of the earth, which lyeth in the
longitude of 53, and latitude of 62:
being ſituated in reſpect of the Citie of
London twentie Degrees more Eaſterly,
and about ten Degrees more Northerly.
            
               
So now, in regard of the ayme of this
eiaculation of prediction, the parallell
of 62 may be called the Butt, &amp; the Meridian
of 53, (where it cutteth that parallell)
the white, or marke deſigned.
For the finding whereof, and touching
it with the finger of Evidence, we need
no other guidance, then

                  Cogimur è tabula pictos ediſcere Mundos.
                  Of all the world the ſeuerall parts
by name,
                  Wee cannot chuſe but learne by
tabled frame.
               
            
            View we therefore our moſt approued
and current Mapps, whether Vniverſall,
or Nationall and particular,
wherin the ſeverall Countries are Geographically
diſtinguiſhed by the regular
lines of latitude (which is the ſituation
from South to North) and of longitude
(being the reſpect vnto Weſt and
Eaſt) and therein ſhall we find, that the
very place of this forenamed poſture is
either a part of Finicus Sinus, the Bay or
Gulfe of Finland, or ſome border of

the Land and Townes ſeated vpon that
Gulfe.
            If we take counſell of Gerad Mercator
in his Atlas Major either by viewing his
Mapps or reading the numbers deſigned
in his Alphabeticall tables, he affordeth
vs at leaſt 4 degrees to ſpare,
whereby the verge of Finland is extended
Eaſtward in the parallele of 62.
beyond the Meridian of 53. as evidently
appeareth by the ſituation of Kinaveb
Egrepe, Iegaborg, and other Townes
neere bordering. Some other Mapps
draw thoſe parts a little more to the
Weſt: which is not to be accompted
ſtrange, when as in many parts of the
world (eſpecially thoſe that are leſſe frequented
by travellers, or leſſe furniſhed
with inhabitant Aſtronomers) the true
longitude is not ſo certainely knowne,
as the latitude. And therefore a ſmall
diverſity of this kind occurring in variouſe
Mapps is not much to be ſtood
vpon.
            True it is that our Tycho expreſſeth

that deſigned concurrence of longitude
and latitude, as lighting vpon Illam
Moſcoviae plagam, qua cum Boreali &amp; ortum
ſimul respiciente Finlandiae parte coniu
                     •
                  gitur:
That coaſt of Muſcovy, which
bordereth vpon the Northerly and
Eaſterly part of Finland. Whether ledd
thereto by the compoſure of Mapps in
his time, pulling Moſcouy more Weſt:
or thinking that huge continent of
Moſcovy and other Eaſtern parts more
fit for the title of Magna ſeptentrionis
domus, The great houſe of the North
hereafter mentioned in Sybills prophecy:
or laſtly (which is moſt likely) for
that divers diſtaſts and quarrells happening
between his Soveraigne the King
of Denmark,
               
                  Tycho once was faine to hide his head for bringing too nere home a praediction, which afterward proved true. &amp; the neighbouring King
of Sweden, it had bin over open to envy
and iealouſies to haue deuoted in direct
termes any part of the Dominions of
the Sw
                     •
                  de for the ſeminary of great and
violent alterations: and ſo he choſe rather
to expreſſe the place by the phraſe
of Ruſsia bordering vpon Finland, then

of Finland bordering vpon Ruſsia.
            
            Sutable heereunto is that his modeſt
or cautelouſe demurre, wherewith the
events of this ſigne are by his penn tenderly
tacked vpon the deſigned place,
with ſubmiſsion to other mens iudgements,
in theſe words. An igitur HINC
tantarum turbarum &amp; mutationum,
               Pag. 810. 
               quae per
hoc inſolens oſtentum innuebantur, primae occaſiones
pullulabunt, at
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   poſt-modum in alias
Mundi Plagas late magna &amp; diuturna vi
diſſeminabuntur, aliis expendendum decidendum
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  
relinquo. I leaue it to be weighed
and determined by other mens iudgments,
whether or no the firſt occaſions
of thoſe great turmoyles &amp; alterations
implyed by this extraordinary wonderous
Starr, ſhall budd foorth out of
this place deſigned by me, and ſhortly
after be ſhed abroad thence into other
Regions of the world farr and wide,
with great and durable forces. Thus
Tycho Brahe.
            
            It is a true ſaying, that in predictions
(eſpecially humane, and coniecturall)

event, and experience is the beſt Comment.
If therefore about a place and
time thus decyphered there now appeare
evidence of vnexpected immutations,
being the ſtreames iſſuing from a
fountaine lately breaking forth and getting
more ſtrength with full Tide of
proſperous ſucceſſe, why may not we
acknowledg herein Gods extraordinary
handy-work as performed in the event,
ſo alſo fore-deſcribed in the heavenly
Characters of ſuch miraculous ſignes?
            If Eclipſes of the two great lights,
and coniunction of Planets vnder ſome
portions of fixed ſtar, haue at any time,
or may portend events vpon earth,
much more may new Starrs moulded
by the hand of God in the higheſt heavens
challenge the like propheticall language.
Thoſe Eclipſes and coniunctions
are meerly naturall, and haue their
certaine revolution, and concurrence,
which many yeares before their apparition
may be infallably ſet downe by
the obſervation of Gods ordinary

Power in the motion of the creature:
but this admirable Sarr in the eſſence,
and place thereof ſheweth the finger
of God, reaching higher then to the
ſupport of Naturall agents: and therefore
much more probably may be preſumed
to be an obiect, not onely of
the eye by beauty and luſtre, but alſo
of the vnderſtanding, in being a meſſenger
of Divine future operation.
            In the times now mentioned by
the learned Tycho, and in and about
the places, whereupon he eſpecially
fixeth the influence of this new Herald
of Heaven, we can finde no other
fit ſubiect of application then
the new riſen Starr radiant in virtue
and goodneſſe, ſparkeling with the
beames of Martiall Valour, the proſperous
and admired Guſtavus Adolphus
King of Sweden, who by his
manifold and ſudden Conqueſts is
now made the ſpectacle of the Chriſtian
World, beheld and ſpoken of
with no leſſe admiration, then that

new Starr of the North, which ſeemeth
to be his fore-runner.
            As for the time, the three termes of revolution
intēded by Tycho, viz. the yeares
1593. 1620. 1632. or therabouts may decipher
him, the firſt (well neare) his Birth,
the ſecond his Ingreſſe, the third his Progreſſe
in ſucceſſefull Conqueſts.
            Then likewiſe the place pointed at
by the Heavens, or rather appointed by
the God of heaven to be the Seminary
or Neſt, which ſhall ſend forth the Author
of great alterations is found to be
the Countrey of Finland, a part of his
Dominions belonging to the Kingdom
of Sweden, and recited in his Title, Great
Prince of Finland
            
            Seeing that time and place ſo conveniently
concurr with incomparable
ſucceſſe in his Victories, (wherein he
deporteth himſelfe ſo admirably, that it
is hard to ſay, whether be greater his
Valour in ſubduing, or his Iuſtice in the
vndertaking, and well vſing his Victories
to the reliefe of the oppreſſed we

ſhall not need here to deſcribe the particulars
of his Atchiuements blowne abroad
by the Trumpet of publique
Fame, and ecchoed vnto vs by the
weekly tell-tale Corantoes Such cleare
beames of Vertue and Glory Envy it
ſelfe can neither out-face nor ſuppreſſe.
            Yet to ſet vnder one view ſome part
of that, which otherwiſe may diſperſedly
be gathered by certaine Information,
we will take leaue to ſhadow out
ſome few lineaments of his worth and
happineſſe.
            
               Guſtavus Ericus King of Sweden (the
firſt crowned Proteſtant of our Age)
was his Grandfather: to whom that
Kingdome oweth their liberty from
the yoake of the Danes: whoſe ſonne
Charles likewiſe freed them from the
preſſures of the Polacks. This Charles
marryed the daughter of Adolph Duke
of Holſtein, and by her begate this Guſtavus
Adolphus, borne at Stockholm the
laſt of November 1594, ſtilo vet. Who
thus by two deſcents is in blood and generous

diſpoſition qualified to be a Reſtorer
of Liberties.
            About the ſeuenteenth yeare of his
age, Anno 1611, he was by his Father
Charles made Colonell of a Troope of
Horſe in the Warrs againſt Denmarke.
            
            When hee had ſetled Peace in his
owne Countrey, by compoſing of differences
and quarrells riſen betweene
him and the King of Denmark, about
the yeare 1614, vpon refuſall made
vnto him of re-imburſment of l
                  •
               rge
ſummes of money layd out by the State
and Subiects of his Kingdome, and lent
to the Emp
                  •
               rour of Muſcovy, he vndertooke
vpon that iuſt quarrell to make
an Inroad vpon the adiacent Dominions
of that potent Emperour, and taking
his March from Finland with proſperous
ſucceſſe he in a ſhort time conquered
the mighty Province of Ingria,
or Ingerland: and among the reſt hee
took the famous ſtrong 
                  •
               ort of Kexholm,
and ſhortly after by the med
                  ••
               tion
of King Iames our late Soveraigne concluded

a Peace betweene himſelfe and
the Emperour of Muſcovy vpon very
good and honourable Conditions:
whereby he not onely held that Country
which hee had ſeized on, but alſo
received of the Moſcovite a great ſumme
of money for his expence in that warr.
So that now hee is poſſeſſed of ſome
part of that vaſt Continent of Moſcovia,
whitherward our Tycho Brahe (as before
is noted) would ſeeme to extend
more Eaſterly the poynt deſigned by
this Calculation.
            And conſequently if (ſuppoſing, but
not graunting) we ſhould ſtretch the
foreinſtanced longitude of 53▪ into this
border of Muſcovy, then may we thus
vnderſtand theſe words of Tycho, inde
initia mutationum, thence or from that
place ſhall iſſue out the beginnings of
alterations, namely, that other alterations
ſhall be produced in other places
and regions, but by him, who ſhall very
there in Ruſsia make the Commencement
of his exploits and Conqueſts.

For that footing and ground gayned
there may well be accompted the firſt
ſtepp to his greatneſſe,In this conſtruction Finland may be the place a quo whence, and Ruſsia the place both in quo and a quo where, and whence great alterations may be ſayd to have their cruption. and foundation
of his other conqueſts, not onely in order
of time, but alſo in the inhabling
him and fleſhing his hardy Finlanders
for further vndertakings.
            About the beginning of the yeare
1618. he entred Livonia againſt the
Polonian, and proceeded in that invaſion
ſo proſperouſly by ſeverall conqueſts,
in divers places, that by the yeare
1624. that whole countrey was made
ſubiect vnto him.
            About the yeare 1626. he entred
Pruſsia, and ſurpriſed the Fort of Pelavia,
at once making himſelfe Maſter of
all the trade of the rich Cities of Coningsberg
and Elbing:
               The Finlanders and other Sweds are his tougheſt helps, being beſt able to endure the cold and hardſhip of Winter-warfare. which enterpriſe he vndertook
with his owne natiue Sweds &amp;
Finlanders (who in that employment did
not exceed the number of 9000. men)
but with ſo wonderfull ſucceſſe, that
this achieuement may rightly be counted
the riſe and growth of his greatnes.
            
               
With this ſmall force he marched towards
Elbing, and whileſt the Burgers of
that Towne were treating a neutrality
with his Counſell in the Tents, he, with
ſome few Musketers attending him,
boldly entred the city, which with feare
and amazement admitted him vpon the
onely command of his word, and confident
Maieſty of his countenance: the
walls thereof being at that inſtant laden
with armed men well appoynted for
defence againſt him, who then beholding
his entrance durſt not diſcharge a
bullet, or make any other reſiſtance againſt
him.
            This City he made his Magazin for
the warr, and departing thence he took
the great Caſtle of Mariburg, being the
ſeat of the Teutonique Order of Knighthood.
Where not having eight thouſand
foot he entrenched himſelfe, fighting
in the face of forty thouſand Polonians,
and ten thouſand Imperialls: and ſo
tyred and wore out the great army of
the enemy, that they not onely by the

mediation of our dread Soueraign King
Charles, in the yere 1629, ſubmitted vnto
his conditions of Peace very honorable
on his part, but alſo yeelded vnto him a
great part of that Territory of Pruſsia.
            
            The Emperour hauing thus made
war againſt him in Pruſsia, and oppreſſed
the King of Denmark, the Duke of
Pomerania, &amp; Mechlenburg, and the King
of Swedes enemies being likely to make
themſelues Maſter of the Baltique Sea,
not only to his ruine, but alſo to the endangering
of Denmark, and endammaging
of Great Britaine and Holland, the
King of Swedens ſubiects being vniuſtly
ſpoiled of their goods, and forbid comming
on the German ſhore to trade, the
Towne of Stralſond hauing formerly
grieuouſly complained vnto him of the
wrongs and danger wherewith they
were encompaſſed; vpon theſe and other
neceſſary cauſes (as by his publiſhed
Manifeſto may appeare) he entred Germany
in the yeare 1630, and took from
the invading Imperials the Iſle of Rugia,
               
a place of great importance, which ſerveth
him for a ſafe ſtation for his ſhipping.
And then winning a ſtrong Fort
on the maine land (on purpoſe by the
oppreſſors of the liberties of Germany
then built againſt him,) himſelf landed
at Stralſond in Iune, 1630.
            In December following he took the
Townes of Griffenhagen, and the Fort of
Gartz in the face of the enemies Army,
and following the Victory chaſed the
Army of Walenſteine Duke of Frieland,
which having poſſeſſed the Citty of
Franckford on the Oder, and Lantz-bergh,
he took the one by aſſault in the open
day, when it had 6000 old Souldiers
in Garriſon, and the King not aboue ſeven
thouſand to attempt it.
            From thence marching without delay
the very next day to Lantzbergh with
two thouſand foot and a thouſand
horſe he tooke that ſtrong paſſe by
compoſition yielding to him vpon the
onely motiue of his reputation, out of
which Marched foure thouſand foot,

with ſhame and aſtoniſhment beholding
ſo ſmall a number, to whom they
had yielded themſelues.
            In this preſent yeare 1631. the defeat
given by him (ioyning with the
Duke of Saxony) in open field and
pitched Campe, may bee called the
downe weight of his valour, caſting on
his ſide the ballance of predominant
ſucceſſe: which was atchieved vpon the
ſeuenth of September laſt neere Lipſich
in Saxony, in a field called Godſacre, being
the ſelfe ſame plot of ground wherin
the Emperour Charles 5. tooke Frederick
Duke of Saxony, and Philip Lantgraue
of Heſſen priſoners in battell, deveſting
thereupon the Duke of Sax. of
his Duchy and Electorat; which is
now by revolution of Time repayed
by this Defeat vpon the very ſame
place.
            
               Tillies Army conſiſting of 44000
fighting men, the King of Swedens and
the Duke of Saxonies Army in all of
38000. In which battell the Duke of

               Holſtein leading the left wing of Tillyes
Army, gaue the onſet vpon the Kings
Army, and was taken priſoner within
ſhort time; the Duke of Sax. being hotly
charged by Tilly, left him elbowroom
in the field together with three of the
Saxon Regiments that ſtood to it. And
ſo the King hauing now not aboue
18000 fighting men, ſet couragiouſly
vpon Tilly, putting him to flight, entred
vpon his Ordnance, Wagons, and Tents
as they ſtood furniſhed with meat vpon
the Tables prepared by them, who
now had no liſt to returne to that Supper,
but rather left it to thoſe for whom
God had provided it.
            The flying enemy was ſhrowded by
the black mantle of the night, ſo that the
conquering King could not further purſue
his Victory till the next morning,
when drawing out a thouſand horſe he
in perſon followed them eight Dutch
myles, cutting off 1000 of the foot, and
taking priſoners 3000 more.
            The loſſe on Tyllies part is eſteemed

at 18000, whereof ſlaine 8000, and
taken priſoners 10000. The loſſe on
the other part not aboue 1200 men as
by the more ſtrange &amp; truer Computation
is avowed. The Kings Motto or
Word was Deus nobiſcum, God on our
ſide. Tillies Word, Sancta Maria, Saint
Marie.
            
            I think more foreboading coniecture
might haue been made out of the vnequall
counterpoiſe between theſe two
tutelary Patrons or protectors, then out
of the auſpicious flying of a great troop
of birds in that field, by ſome obſerved
vpon that very morning, inſtantly before
the Armies ſet vp their reſt in the
place, namely overflying the place of
Tillyes army, and lighting in the place of
the King of Swedens army.
            The ancient Latines called that auguſtum,
which was bonis avibus geſtum,
acheived according to the foreſignification
made by the lucky and proſperous
flying of birds, and in that ſence may
this victory be called auguſta, though

               contra ipſum Auguſtum in his principall
commander of his forces defeated, and
ruined.
            Some haue obſerued the ſymbolizing
and eaſy tranſmutation between the
names Auguſtus and Guſtavus, inferring
thence that whereby his friends would
heap vpon him more glory, and perhaps
his enemies more envy. But thoſe that
looke vp higher to reade Characters
written in the Heauens, and guilded
with the beames of new Stars, will not
ſo low, and vpon ſo light ground, as
Anagrams are, lay the foundation of predictions:
and therfore neither will we
inſiſt vpon that menacing ſentence,
Te debellabit averſus DEVS, denoting
the SVED.
            
            And becauſe the late coniunction and
aſſociation between him and the Duke
of Saxony, hath bin &amp; is a ſtrong means
of the late further growth of his ſtrēgth
and progreſs in Victories, it is here to be
obſerued and accounted no ſmall part
of the fore-ſpoken alterations, that the

ſaid Duke, (formerly being a kind of
dormant Neutral, &amp; therby giving way
to the encroachments of the enemy) is
now awaked, &amp; not only ſeeth the danger
whereunto the Liberties of Germany
were caſt, but alſo reacheth forth his helping
hand and ingageth his ſtrength toward
the recovery of the ancient &amp; iuſt
Liberties, therin commenting by action
vpon the Prognoſticall ſpeculations writtē
about ſixty yeares agoe by Paulus Grebnerus,
a man of the ſame Aſtronomicall
profeſsion with our Tycho Brah
                     •
                  ; but
what authoritie or reputation his writings
deſerue, I leaue to the iudgment of
others Penes authorem esto fides
            
            This Grebner wrote a l
                  •
               rge book of
predictions which he is ſaid to have given
to Queen Elizabeth, our late Soveraigne
of bleſſed memory. The originall
wherof written by the hand of the
Author, was by the worthy and Reuerend
Doctor Nevil giuen and put into
the Library of 
                  
                     •
                  rinitie Colledge in Cambridge,
whereof hee was Maſter, and a

               moſt generous and edifying Benefactor
vnto it. In the 261 page of that Book
he thus, Bohemia Tumultus et bellicoſos
ſtrepitus magna cum defectione ſuorum ſentit.
Tempore ill Caeſar Electoris Saxoniae
naſo Hiſpanica, fraudulenta, doloſa, blanda,
inſidioſa imponit conſpicilla, quorum naturā
tandem ipſe pern
                  •
               ſcit, proprio
                  
                     
                  
                  que
                edocetur experimento,
quod haec Auſtriaca conſpicilla poppyſmata
et phalerata verba ſceleratae et proditoriae
ſint practicae: quibus ſi vltra fidem
habere duceret, ſeipſum, conjugem, natos, &amp;
vniverſos Chriſtianiſmi confederatos in pernicioſum
praecipita et exitium.
            What revolt of Bohemia may here be
intended, let others make conſtruction:
but ſure this preſent Duke of Saxony
being now himſelfe a grand agent both
in oppoſing Tilly, and alſo ſince that in
vnyoaking the chiefe City Prague, with
other Townes in Bohemia, demonſtrateth
that he hath recovered the right vſe
of his eyes, by caſting away thoſe falſe
Spectacles, which were put vpon his
noſe by ſome cunning hand.
            
               
Out of this Grebner diverſe other parcells
haue bin tranſcribed and much enquired
after, as applyable to theſe times
and to the mutations preſent or probably
expected in Germany and other countreys.
But I forbeare inſerting them, becauſe
they conteine confuſed and ambiguous
matter, and may happily ſeeme
as well to poynt at other times,Greb. Pag. 173. as this,
in which S
                     •
                  ecus feliciſimo ſucceſſu claſſe
&amp; ſuo populo terra mari
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   in hoſtem vtetur,
The Swed ſhall with moſt happy ſucceſſe
employ his Navy and people by ſea
and land againſt the enemy. Yet verily
the attribute of feliciſsimus ſucceſſus may
by this Guſtavus, for the vnmatchable
proſperity of his attempts, be challenged
as a proper Character, in which neither
any other Swed, nor man for many ages
can pretend partnerſhip with him,
much leſſe eminency aboue him.
            Whileſt theſe things are vnder the
pen, the further proceſſe of his victories
comes to our eares, and, among the reſt,
his entring of Franc
                     •
                  ford vpon the Mein
               
being the chiefeſt Mart-town of Europe,
and the ſeat of the Crowne of the Emperor.
Which Towne he rather won
by loue, and reſpect to his honour, then
ſubdued by force; The gates whereof
willingly opening to admit him, he
made entrance thereinto the ſeventeeth
of November, Through which Towne
he paſſed with all his army in aray; but
with ſo good order and diſcipline,
without violence or wrong to any of
the inhabitants, that it ſeemed rather a
pomp of a natiue King, then an enforcement
by a foreiner.
            Of this, and the like his ſeiſures, or
entries into the many other yeilding cities
and townes it may be ſaid, that he
ſpeaketh by action, what formerly was
vttered by the pen of one of his predeceſſors,
Theoderick King of the Gothes (&amp;
ſharer in Roman Empire with Iuſtinian)
He in one of his Reſcripts, or letters
Miſſiue thus,Vide Aurel. Caſsiodorum variarum lib. 3. Ep. 43. 
               Aliorum forte Regum
praelia captarum civitatum aut praedas appetunt,
aut ruinas: nobis propoſitum eſt (Deo
iuvante) ſic vincere, vt ſubiecti ſe doleant noſtrum

dominium tardius acquiſiſſe Warrs
vndertaken by other Kings for the moſt
part tend to the deſtruction, or ſackage
of thoſe cities, whereof they get the maſtery:
but our purpoſe is, by Gods aſsiſtance,
to conquer in that manner, that
the ſubdued may think themſelues ill apayed,
that they did no ſooner caſt
themſelues into our hands.
            Add we hereunto, for concluſion of
this preſent application, the happy protection
which hath accompanied him
in the midds of extreame dangers,
which argueth that the hand of Gods
providence hath both appointed &amp; ſafe
conducted him to become an inſtrument
of great mutatiōs in melius for the
bettering the eſtate of ſome parts of
Chriſtendome.
            Warfare is to all militant men a perpetuall
contexture of the netts of danger,
but moſt to Princes vndertaking in perſon:
With this enemy hath this King
often grappled.
            Firſt in the ru
                  •
               iments of his proweſſe,
and budd of his ſtrength, when he was

but ſeventeene yeares old, in the warrs
between his father and the King of
Denmarke he was hard put to it, fighting
vpon the yce, when he very hardly eſcaped
drowning: and being then put to
the worſe, hath made good that obſervation
of an ancient warrier, that none
can be a good leader in the warrs that
hath not ſometime bin well beaten by
the enemy. This hanſ
                  •
               ll therefore may
well be accounted the apprentiſage of
hardſhip to him.
            Some of the Indian people diſtinguiſh
their Noble from the Vulgar by raced
marks and figures imprinted in the
skin; Surely more proper markes of
nobleneſſe in warriours are the ſcarrs
of wounds caſually inſcribed on the
body.
            
               Nam
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  
                  Sidonius Apollinaris Carm 23. in corpore fortium virorum
               Laus eſt amplior amplior cicatrix.
               The ſumme of honor in the Warrs
               Is ſcor'd by characters of Scarrs.
            
            The badge of this acquired honour
this King beareth in his Royall limbs,
peirced with ſhot more then once: ſuch

rude meſſengers frō the enemy hauing
dared to make forcible entry in his
belly, and ſhoulder, where they yet continue
their lodging, and haue the honor
to enter with him into many a ſurpriſed
or yeilding City and Caſtle, like the dull
bittle, that mounted high by cleaving to
the Eagles wing. Theſe vneaſie gueſts
cannot by their gravity ſlack his Martial
motion, but rather by the ſenſe of them
add a ſpur to his valour, and more force
to the bullets, which he ſendeth back in
requitall.
            In his warrs in Pruſsia at Darſaw he
was ſurpriſed by ſome that iſſued out
from an ambuſcado, and ſo twice within
a few houres fell into the hand of the
enemy: and was again as often reſcued
by his owne, partly valor, partly ingenious
and nimble ſleight, as alſo by the caſual
approach &amp; aſsiſtance of one of his
ſouldiers, by whom, for concealment of
his perſon, he was in the action called
Brother. And this ſouldier preſently after
being himſelfe taken by the enemy, was

by the Kings owne hand mutually reſcued:
who thereupon by the reſcuing
King was ſaluted in theſe friendly
words, Quit brother, now you and I are euen.
            
            Of which accid
                  •
               nt may be made this
typical conſtruction, that he is ordeined
to relieue thoſe that defend and aſsiſt
him: and that his abiding the adventure
of captiuity, tendeth to the redeeming
of others out of bondage.
            Moreouer, in this or ſome other conflict
audacious danger aſpired ſo high, as
to ſtrike at his head: but miſsing the
ayme it hit his Hat: which being ſtricken
off it came into the hand of the enemy,
and being knowne, was afterward
ſent to Vienna the chiefe City in Auſtria,
and receiued there with ioy and congratulation,
as a Trophey of victory againſt
him, and pledge of fu
                  •
               ure getting
the head that wore it.
            
               Quo nunc Turnus ovat ſpolio, gaudet
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   potitus.
               When Turnus gat young Pallas in his power,Virg. Aeneid. 10.
               
               He from him hent the b
                     •…
                  ſſed belt he wore.
               And thus poſſeſſe of that hoſtile ſpoile
               In triumph beareth it about a while.
               
               But what followeth hereupon?
               Turno tempus erit &amp;c.
               The time wil come, when he ſhal curſe the day
               Wherein he tooke and bare that ſpoile away.
            
            That Hat is like to be purchaſed at a
dearer rate, then ſome Kings have ſold
their Crownes.
            
               Ille oculis postquam ſaevi monumenta doloris
               Exuviaſ
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                  
                  Aeneid. 12. ad finem. hauſit, ſurijs accenſus, &amp; ira
               Terribilis, Tune hinc ſpolijs indute meorum
               Eripiare mihi?
               
                  Aeneas, when he ſpyed that well knowen Belt,
               Revived griefe, and anger inly felt:
               And flaming with revenge, Shalt thou (quoth he
               Clad with my friends aray eſcape from me?
            
            The bloud of heroical Aeneas boyled
at the triumphant poſſeſsion of a piece
of furniture ſurpriſed from, not himſelfe,
but his friend; not living, but ſlain;
How much more may a generous victorious
Spirit reſolute by ſtrong hand
and Martiall inroad to recover that vpper
couerture of his owne head?
            It hath bin reported that thence it is
tranſported into Italy, and beſtowed on
the wooden Lady of Loretto, for whoſe
weare it is as fit, as the Gowne bequeathed
to her by that Father of Critiques, of

whom it is fitly ſaid, that
            
               Criticus virilem Virgini togam legans
               In morte fecit Lipſius ſoloeciſmum.
               A dying Latiniſt of great renowne
               Vnto the Virgin Mary gave his Gowne.
               And was not this falſe Latine ſo to joyne
               With Female gender that caſe Maſculine?
            
            But now leaving this digreſsion concerning
his Hat, and returning to the
Crowned head that wore it, we referr
to the contemplation of iudicious men,
whether a man thus armed with protection
for eſcape of many more capitall
hazards, then here are, or can be, recited,
admired vnto aſtoniſhment for his
great &amp; ſuddē Victories beloved for his
virtues both Chriſtian, Morall, &amp; Military,
iuſtly ſtiled the releever of the wronged,
and reſtorer of oppreſſed Princes &amp; Liberties,
concurring ſo neere in time and
place with this fore-deſcribed Celeſtiall
calculation, be not to be accounted that
Stellae filius, &amp; aureus Coeli partus, the
child of that priviledged Starr, and the
golden iſſue of Heaven, glittering with
the beames of high attempts &amp; matchleſſe
Honour.
            
               
Do not theſe preſent alterations make
way to a fuller accompliſhment in the
time now by computation approaching,
namely the yeare 1632. and the
yeares inſtantly following after the
ſame? wherein may be made good not
only the generall predictions of our
Aſtronomer, but alſo in particular (among
other redreſſes befitting this
Conquerors greatneſſe, and goodneſſe)
the reſtitution of ſome other deveſted
and deiected Princes to their natiue
dignity, and vndoubted inheritance.
            But (may ſome ſay) do all the hopes
or feares of the future ſucceſſe of theſe
great alterations depend vpon the
weak ſtring of ſuch Apparitions, whoſe
activity in ſuch events perhaps is either
none at all, or vtterly vnſearchable by
the witt of man? And if ſearchable,
why not rather fetched from ſome later
Comets or pretending Starrs, which
ſince this haue appeared within our
Horizon?
            
            
               Reſpon. 1.Not meerely on ſuch farfetched and

coniecturall premiſes relyeth the expectation
of the conſequents betyding theſe
times. For if, abſtracting all coniectures
from aboue, and ſuppoſing there were
no ſuch fore-ſignifications, wee confine
our thoughts onely to the conſideration
of neere by-paſſed, and now preſent events,
and thereby in the balance of humane
probability weight out the expectation
of the future, we ſhall need none
other bond of aſſurance then the pledge
of Gods providence, wheron we are to
rely: and whereunto all forenamed
coniectures are but acceſſory and ſupernumerary.
            
                As for the operation, or portending
ſignification of ſuperior lights, (whatſoever
doubt may be made of the ordinary
lamps of heaven, and the aſpects
reſulting out of their regular motions)
it cannot be denyed but that extraordinary
wonderous viſibles may haue, and
haue had their attendant ſignifications.Ioel 2. 30.
In which ſence it is no impiety literally
to interpret thoſe words I will ſhew wonders

in the heauens and in the earth, partly
of that flaming ſword-like Comet, that
appeared, as a forewarner of the deſtruction
of Ieruſalem. Sutably hereto why
may not ſome ſignificant power bee
graunted to this high heauenly, more
then ordinary, ſpectacle? Why not
thence modeſt, and ſober collection, and
probable inference be made? The principles
whereof, and manner of deduction
from them are not here ſuppreſſed,
but, according to our authors proceſſe,
layed out fairely aboue board: To
which way of inference the Chriſtian
Reader may affoard what parcell of credit
hee ſhall thinke fit to meat out by
the rule of piety, and liberty of opinion.
Valeat vt valere poterit. Let it float as farr
as this water will beare it.
            Laſtly concerning other later Comets,
or appearing ſtarrs, it may truely
be avowed, that among them all none
was ſo remarkeable for height, bignes,
and luſtre, all concurring, as this the elder
brother and Captaine of them: in

compariſon whereto they may be content
to be called, as puiſnees, and afterlings,
ſo alſo minorum gentium, petits of a
lower forme.
            Diverſe of them were obſerued by
our Tycho in his life time, and ſurnamed
by him rather Comets, then ſtarrs. But
this eſpecially he iudged to be foreſpoken
of by one of the Sibylls in that prediction,Sibylla Tiburtina.
which in the yeare 1520. was
found vnder ground in Suitzerland engraven
in a marble ſtone in very ancient
latine characters,Vide Cornel. Gemmam de divinis characteriſmis. in this manner
of Orthography Orietour ſydous in Europa
ſoupra Yberos ad magnam ſeptentrionis domum:
colus radii orbem terrarum ex impreviſo
illouſtrabunt: &amp;c. A ſtarr ſhall ariſe
in Europe over the Iberi at the great
houſe of the North: whoſe beames
ſhal ſuddenly (or vnexpectedly) enlighten
the whole world.
            In regard of the heauens the ſeat of
this admirable ſtarr (whereof wee
haue treated) is evidently domus Septentrionis,
being in Caſsiopeia, not aboue

eighteene degrees diſtant from the
North-pole: to which neerneſſe none
of the later did approach: and in reſpect
of the ſubiect place in the earth,
correſpondent thereto, that tract, wherof
formerly we haue diſcourſed, is by as
good right magna domus Septentrionis, the
great houſe of the North.
            It befits not (nor is it eaſie) to determine
who are theſe Iberi, and accordingly
how ſupra may be diverſly conſtrued,
nor what is meant by the other
words of Sibyll, Eodem fere tempore, hoc
demorſo ſydere, coaevum quoddam eious loumen
longe ardentioribous Mavortis ignibus
exardeſcens Antipodum finibus occludet
Imperium. But vndoubtedly in this
Sibylline prediction muſt be intended
(as the following parts ſhew) not ſo
much (or not onely) portentum coeleſte, a
bright viſible in the heaven, as Stella
Moralis a radiant, admirable, potent
atcheiver on the earth. Which who,
what, when, or where he is, or ſhalbe is
certainely knowne onely

               Stellarum domino, ſtellifici
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   Deo.
            
            to him that framed this new great light
in the heavens, and ordained the
ſame vnto ends beſt knowne
to his heavenly
Wiſedome.
            Praſe him all ye Starrs,Pſal. 148. 3.
and Light.
         
      
      
         
            Theodahadus Rex.
            
               COgnoſcite arma noſtra pro ſalute veſtrâ
deſtinata,
               
                  Caſsiodorus Variarum. lib. 13. ep. 18. 
               vt, qui vos tentaverint appetere,
divino auxilio manus eis Gothorum-debeat
obviare. Bee it knowne to you,
that our Army is ordeined for your
ſafety: So that whoſoever ſhall bee ſo
bold as to ſet vpon you, ſhall finde that
the warrlike troopes of the Goths are
preſt and ready by Gods helpe to encounter
them.
            FINIS.
         
      
   

