
   
      
         
            A fruitful sermon preached at Occham in the county of Rutland, the second of Nouember, 1583 by Thomas Gybson.
            Gybson, Thomas, fl. 1583.
         
         
            
               1584
            
         
         Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2009-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01703
            STC 11840.5
            ESTC S2130
            23063224
            ocm 23063224
            26165
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01703)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26165)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1796:8)
         
         
            
               
                  A fruitful sermon preached at Occham in the county of Rutland, the second of Nouember, 1583 by Thomas Gybson.
                  Gybson, Thomas, fl. 1583.
               
               [76] p.   
               
                  Printed by Robert Walde-graue dwelling without Temple-Barre,
                  At London :
                  1584.
               
               
                  "God is my defender."
                  Signatures: [A]-D⁸ E⁶.
                  Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 1st, IX, 16 --  Sermons.
               Sermons, English --  16th century.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-11
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2008-01
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2008-02
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2008-02
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
               ❧ A FRVITful Sermon, preached at Occham, in the County of Rutland, the Second of Nouember. 1583.
            By Thomas Gybſon.
            
            
               PROVERB. 29.8. ¶ VVhere there is no Viſion, the people decay.
            GOD IS MY DEFENDER
            
               GOD IS MY DEFENDER
            
            AT LONDON; Printed by Robert Walde-graue dwelling without Temple-Barre. 1584.
            
         
         
            
            
            ¶ TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE Lorde, FRAƲNCES, Earle of BEDFORD, and one of her Maieſties moſt honourable priuy Counſell Knight of the Noble order of the Garter: VVith the Right Honourarable, Syr VVALTER MILDEMAY Knight, Chancelour of the Queenes Maieſties Court of Exchequer, and one of her Highnes moſt honourable priuy Counſell, Grace, Mercy, and peace be multiplied from God our Heauenly Father, &amp; from our Lord &amp; Sauiour Ieſus Chriſte.
            
               THE bleſſed &amp; holy Euangeliſt Saint Luke, (Right Honorable) penning and publiſhing the Heauenlye ſtory and bleſſed Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, doth alſo dedicate the ſame to one Theophilus, a Noble and famous man, of ſingular credit and authority. The reaſon and

cauſe that mooued him thereto, is becauſe in thoſe times, the pureneſſe of the Goſpell was hindred, and perſecuted, whereby many erroures began to be ſpreade and allowed: and therefore in great Wiſdom it pleaſed the holy Ghoſt, not onely to write a faithfull, ſure, and perfect ſtory: but alſo to offer and preſent the cuſtodie and defence of the ſame, to one of Religion and Povver. The verye ſame cauſe, partly hath mooued me at this time, to bee ſo bolde as to offer and Dedicate this poore and ſimple teſtimony of my trauaile to your Honoures. For although I doe confeſſe, vvee liue vnder a Gracious Prince (whome the Lorde long continue to his glory, to the ſhame and confuſion of his enemies, and to the dayly profit of his Church) although (I ſay) we liue in ſo peaceable, happy, and gracious a time, vnder the flowriſhing ſtate of the Goſpell; yet truely the deareſt Children of God, and the ſincerity of Religion, is ſubiect to bitter Perſecution. Theſe wordes at

the firſt may ſeeme verye greeuous, hard and haynous, and yet they are moſt certaine and true. The holy Apoſtle S. Paul, writing to the Galatians, 4.29. ſpeaketh on this maner: As he that was borne after the Fleſh, perſecuted him that was borne after the Spirite; euen ſo is it nowe: hee ſpeaketh of Iſmael and Iſaac, and yet we do not reade in the ſcripture of any perſecution betweene them, neither did Iſmael perſecute his Brother Iſaac, with hande or ſworde, but that which is worſe, proudly &amp; arrogantly, he raiſed him ſelfe againſt him, mocking him, and as it were, treading vnder feete the promiſe of God. And this dealing by the apoſtle is cálled a perſecution, &amp; in deede there is not any perſecution more greeuous to the Children of God then this. Nowe who doth not dayly ſee, that the beſt Chriſtians, and the purenes of Religion are greatly perſecuted, by Papiſts, Atheiſts, and Hipocrites, as Iſaac was by his Brother Iſmael, And of all matters of religion, I thinke there is ſcarſe any in

theſe dayes more generally hated of ſuch kind of men, then that, which is moſt altogether, &amp; almoſt only hand led in this ſimple Sermō. For theſe &amp; ſuch like men, many of them can bee content with a common ordinarye profesſion, to heare Mattins and Euenſong, and ſometimes a Sermon, by ſuch men as they like of, but that there ſhould be any continuall courſe of the pure preaching of the worde of God, they can in no caſe allowe or like of. This I ſay, is hated, reiected and perſecuted ſo farre as may be, of the greater ſorte, and therefore not without cauſe haue I attēpted to dedicate this my labor, to your honors as ſpecial Patrons, &amp; defendors of the Lords cauſe, &amp; tried Friends and Fauorers of God &amp; his trueth. But yet this attempt may ſeem very raiſh and needles: For who am I, that I ſhould take vppon mee to ſet foorth and to publiſh any thing. The vnworthieſt I confeſſe of many hundreths, and the vnableſt of manye thouſands, and yet ſeeing many things more ſimple, leſſe

needefull and profitable, are not only ſuffered, but alowed to come abroad: I am not altogether diſcouraged, neither hath any mā iuſt cauſe to accuſe mee in this my ſimple enterpriſe. I know theſe be daies of knowledge &amp; learning, there bee greate ſtore of famous and learned diuines in our land (whom I beſeech the Lorde to bleſſe, that they may asſiſt their weake brethren, in the defence of this, and ſuch good cauſes,) and yet the two mites of the pore widow caſt into the treaſury, amongeſt the great giftes of the wealthy, are not to be refuſed. I know your Honours be daily hearers of famous and learned men, both in your houſes and abroad, you are acquainted with the ſermons of profound &amp; deepe diuines, and ſuch as are mighty in the ſcriptures: notwithſtanding hauing in my ſelf ſufficient trial &amp; experience of your honors moſt curteous humble, &amp; fauorable dealing towards me, and alſo of ſome liking of my ſimple &amp; my poore trauelles in preaching heretofore. I am not aſhamed

or afrayd after ſuch triall and proofe, to offer this ſo ſmall and ſimple a thing vnto your Honours. The great necesſity of the matter I deale withall, the care of Gods glory, the zeal of his houſe, the benefit that his church may haue by it, hath eſpecially mooued me that it ſhould be publiſhed &amp; come abroad. Let not therefore hypocrites bee too raſh in iudging, the Lorde the ſearcher of the hearts and reynes knoweth my purpoſe and affection, in preaching and publiſhing this matter. The cauſe that hath moued me to preſent it to your Honors, rather then to other, is the lōg proof and acquayntance of your honourable courteſies, and friendlye good will towards me, which for my part, I am neuer able to requite, for the which I thinke my ſelfe as long as breath is in me, moſte bound and indebted to your Honours. And here I offer this poore fruite of my trauaile, as ſome Teſtimony of good will and thankfulnes. And whereas wee are wont commonly to offer and preſent

to our deareſt Friendes, ſome giftes, as tokens of good will, or elſe of ſpecial duety. Amongſt many great and precious preſentes, vvhich are no doubt giuen and preſented to your honours; I alſo offer this ſimple mite, and yet I hope more pleaſant and acceptable to the receiuers, then thouſands of gold or ſiluer, or any earthly thing whatſoeuer. And in deede, can there be any matter more ſweete and pleaſaunt, to the cheefe Patrons and Defenders of the Godly Preachers, and the word of God, then to heare of the necesſity, profite, and excellency of preaching: which things, are ſet foorth plainly &amp; largely in this little Sermon. For howſoeuer many mē hate and abhorre this matter, and can in no caſe diſgeſt it: yet your honours zeale, courage, liking, goodwill and countenaunce, to this and other good cauſes is cōmonly known and ſpreade abroad. A further reaſon why I publiſhe this Sermon, is becauſe there is ſome matter in it, for the which I haue beene in the country where I dwell, oopenly

ſlaundered and euill ſpoken off, and therefore to cleare my ſelfe from ſuch falſe reports, to ſatisfie my friends which are readie to anſwer in my cauſe, to let the enemies knowe, I haue ſpoken nothing whereof I am aſhamed, but dare put it to the witneſſing and teſtimonie of the Chriſtian reader: and alſo to reſolue more fully, the weaker ſort, in ſuch things as at the firſt ſeeme ſtrange and abſurd: for theſe and ſuch like cauſes, I ſay, I am content and willing that this my trauell come to light: although the whole or moſt part of this Sermon is vnſauory &amp; vnpleaſaunt to the greater ſort, and ſpecially to the ignorant people, to the hypocrit, to the idol or dumb miniſter: yet this is that, which chiefly miſliketh and grieueth them; becauſe, both in the place where I preched this Sermon, and alſo elſewhere, I ſayd and affirmed, that the miniſter which preacheth not, and hath not thoſe gyftes which the Lorde requireth in his Miniſters, that ſuch a one is no Miniſter, approoued of GOD,

neyther hath anye right and authoritie from the Lorde, to myniſter his Sacramentes; which matter, howe ſtraunge and abſurde ſoeuer it ſeeme to ignoraunt and carnall men: yet I hope it is heere ſufficiently confirmed by authoritye and examples of the holy Scripture. I coulde alleadge further, the allowaunce and iudgement of moſt famous and pure Diuines, and ſuch as are gennerally receyued and allowed of all true Chriſtians. Maſter IOHN CALVIN, about the latter ende of his Catechiſme, which is allowed by her Maieſties authoritie, ſayth in playne wordes, that the miniſtration of the Sacraments belongeth to them, who haue the charge to preache openly in the Church. For the preaching of Gods worde, and the miniſtration of the Sacraments, be things ioyntly belonging to one kind of office: theſe be his very words which are as plaine as may be. M: Rodolphus Gualter in his 118. Homely vpon Mark, ſpeaking of the inſtitution of the Lordes ſupper,

and of the right order in miniſtring that ſacrament, amongſt other things ſayth on this manner. Peccant qui coenam abſ
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   verbi predicatione peragunt, adeó
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   illam huic praeferunt, quaſi vel ad dei cultum, vel ad ſalutem plus conferat, quam verbum, cum tamen huius maiorem quam ſacramentorum rationem habuerunt Chriſtus &amp; Apostoli. They ſinne againſt the inſtitution of Chriſte, which doe miniſter the ſupper without preaching of the word, and ſo preferre the Sacrament before preaching: as though that auayled more to ſaluation and ſeruice of God, then the worde preached; whereas notwithſtanding, both Chriſte and the Apoſtles eſteemed more the preaching of the Worde, then the Sacrament: theſe are his wordes. I might alleadge many other teſtimonies for this cauſe, not onely from the moſt worthy, Godly, and learned diuines, both old and new of other Nations: But alſo from famous Martyrs and Byſhops in this oure Lande, in their ſermons and writings, publiſhed and priuileged by authority.

I hope then ther is no cauſe why this doctrin ſhold not receiue a fauorable intertainment &amp; allowance, as of your honors, ſo of al faithful Chriſtians, hauing ſuch warrant from ſo pure and learned men, and from the teſtimony of the holy word. VVhat ſoeuer I ſpake in deliuering and vttering this ſermon, I haue here ſet it down (ſo nere as I could remember) both in forme and matter. To conclude, I moſte heartily deſire in the Lord, the Chriſtiā reader, &amp; eſpecially your honors, to accept this my pore trauell. I am bold to ioyn you both in one, not only becauſe the Lord hath ioined you together in the bonde of friendſhip, &amp; in a care of my good eſtate: but alſo that which is greateſt of all, in a zeale of Gods glory &amp; furtherance of his religion. Now the very God of peace, ſanctify you through out: and I pray God that your whol ſpirits and ſouls, and bodyes, may be kept blameleſſe vnto the comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Amen.
            
               Your Honours in the Lord; THOMAS GYBSON.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            Hearken with feare and reuerence to the worde of the Lorde, written by the holy Apoſtle Saint Paule, in his firſt epiſtle to the Corinthians.
            
               
                  
                     Chap. 9. verſe 16.
                  
                  Woe be to me, if I preach not the Gospell.
               
            
            
               OVR Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, in the 17. chapter of the bleſſed Euangeliſt Luke, amongſt manye other excellent things, vttereth and propoundeth this parable, Who is it of you, that hauing a ſeruaunt plowing or feeding cattell,Luk. 17.7.8.
                        •
                     . would ſay vnto him by and by when he were come from the field. Goe and ſit downe at table, &amp;c. And afterwardes in the tenth verſe applieth it on this maner. So like wiſe ye, when ye haue done all thoſe thinges which are commaunded you, ſay, we are vnprofitable ſeruauants: we haue done that which

was our duetie to doe. The holy Apoſtle and ſeruant of Chriſt in this place, auoucheth and confeſſeth in him ſelfe, the ſaying of his Maſter to be moſte true. For although amongſt many good workes, there is not a more excellent or better work, then the preaching of the word of God (which was done moſt purely, effectually, and diligently by the Apoſtle) yet he is ſo farre from accounting it meritorious, that he ſayth, a neceſſitie is layd vpon him, that duety bindeth him to do it. In the former verſes from the beginning of this Chapter. S. Paule ſheweth, and that with diligence and large copie of wordes, that beeing amongſt the Corrinthians, he was content to giue place to his owne right, to forbeare that which he might lawfully doe, to take no maintenaunce at all from them, leaſt he ſhould giue occaſion of cauilling to the falſe Apoſtles: as though he vnder the pretence of the calling of an Apoſtle, ſhould ſeeme to ſeeke his owne gaine and lucre. Amongſt other thinges he

hath ſayde, and that in the former verſe: It were better for me to dye then that any man ſhould make my reioycing in vaine. The which wordes may ſeeme to proceed and flow from an ambitious and vaineglorious ſpirite. And therefore it might be ſayde, What now Paule? What needes all this? Thou art wont to glory in Chriſt alone, and doſt thou now glory in thine owne doinges? To ſuch a queſtion or obiection the Apoſtle aunſweareth qualifiyng his former ſpeach, as if he ſhould ſay: Although it be an excellent worke to preach the Goſpel, and that freely, yet take not my wordes 
                  •
               o, as though I repoſe any merite of ſaluation in this worke, for I am called to it, and bound to it, by duety and commaundement from my maſter Chriſt. And if I doe it not I prouoke and procure the anger of God, and the ſentence of his curſe and condemnation on me.
            
               Woe bee to me if I preach not the Goſpell: Of theſe words, being but a part of the verſe, I haue taken vpon me to

ſpeake at this time. From whence I meane by Gods grace to ſpeake of theſe three pointes. Firſt I will gather ſome deſcription of preaching, that you may know what it is. Secondly, I meane to prooue the neceſſitie of preaching, and that euery Miniſter is bound to preach.
            Thirdly, I will ſhewe what they ought to preach. The firſt point as in many other places, ſo here it is named, but not fully ſet downe what it is, but in other places we may eaſily gather what it is. The ſecond is here named and prooued. For Saint Paule being a Miniſter, and ſaying, 
                  Ʋ
                  Ʋoe bee vnto mee, if I preach not the gospell, doth plainely affirme as much. The third is here ſet downe moſt plainly, the matter that we muſt preach of, namely the Goſpell.
            As touching the firſt, let vs ſee how the ſcripture ſpeaketh of it, as it is particularly and ſpecially applyed to the publique office of the Miniſter, otherwiſe I knowe this worde preaching to haue a further and more general

ſignification: But I ſpeake of it, as Chriſt and the Apoſtles doe, applying it to the Miniſters. Saint Paul ſayth,1. Cor. 14.3. 
               He that prophecieth ſpeaketh vnto men to edifiyng,2. Tim. 4.2. to exhortation, and to comfort. The ſame Apoſtle charging Timothie &amp; in him euery miniſter, to preach the word, addeth immediatly,Ioh. 21.15. 
               Improoue, rebuke, exhort with all long ſuffering and doctrine.
               1. Pet. 5.2. The bleſſed Apoſtle Peter, as he receiued of his Maſter a charge to feed his flocke, ſo he exhorteth al other to do the ſame.
            The holy Euangeliſt Luke ſayth that Chriſt taught or preached in Nazareth. He firſt reade,Luk. 4.16. then ſhut the booke, afterwarde he expounded that ſcripture which he read, and ſo applyed it to the hearers. By theſe and ſuch like places we may gather, that preaching properly as we ſpeake of it, is an expoſition and application of the ſcriptures, by the liuely voyce of the miniſter, to the edifiyng of the people: whereby it may eaſily appeare that reading is not preaching, nor yet ſufficient in a miniſter approued of God.

               Saint Paul wil haue him apt to teach.
            
               1. Tim. 3.2.The Prophet Malachy affirmeth, that the Prieſtes lips muſt preſerue knowledge.Mal
                     •
                  . 2.7. Chriſt after reading ſhut the booke and expounded, and yet ſome are not aſhamed to count ſimple reading ſufficient, ſaying, it will ſerue the turne, and there may be as much good done by it, as by preaching. As for reading, wee ſpeake not againſte it wee diſalowe it not, but account it a holye, lawfull, neceſſarye, and profitable meane, whereby greate good and benefite is wrought to the Church of God: but yet, it doth not follow yt it is ſufficient in a miniſter, yt it will ſerue ſimply of it ſelf in the publique congregation. The Lorde hath ſet downe another order, and requireth greater things at the handes of his ſpeciall ſeruaunts. But this matter ſhal appear more plain in the words following. For my purpoſe in this part is, only to ſhew you by ſome circumſtances and diſcriptions what preaching is, and that reading is not preaching, or at leaſt that kinde of

preaching, which the Lord requireth in his miniſters, as may appeare by comparing them together, and by vſing ſome apt ſimilitudes for the explanation of this matter. The ſmell or ſight of meat doth good to the hungry man, but it will not feede him, except he taſte of it: ſo by reading men may haue ſome ſmell of Religion, but they ſhall neuer throughly taſte of it, without preaching,Eph. 4.11. and therefore it is called a feeding, as we hearde before and Preachers are counted Paſtors and feeders. Again, meate that is rawe and fat, maye bee called good, but it is not to bee eaten before it bee made readye and dreſſed: ſo are the Scriptures reade good, holy and pure, but not ſufficient foode for the people, without preaching. Againe, bare reading is as thogh one ſhould caſt a whole loafe, before them which want ſtrength to cut it,2. Tim. 2.15. Preaching is a cutting and diuiding of the breade of life, that euery one may haue his ſeueral portion. Again, bare reading without preaching is

euen as the huſbandman ſhould caſt whole ſtrikes and buſhels of Corne, on his Land together on heapes, not ſcattering of it.Mat. 13. Preaching is a ſpreading and a ſowing of the ſeed. Again. bare reading is as though the Fiſher ſhould ſhuffle his nets on heapes, not opening them: Preaching is a wiſe opening, laying and handling of the Net.
            Bare reading is as one ſhould offer good treaſures, and yet ſuche as were hid, ſhut vp &amp; faſt locked, &amp; could not becōe by: preching is an opening of the Treaſures, to the ioy of Gods Children. Reading is like to fire couered with Aſhes, which doth ſmally profite them that ſtand by it. Preaching is an opening and diſcouering of the fire. Let vs conſider one example amongſt many, for the further explaning of this matter.Act. 8.27. The Chamberlaine that Noble Treaſurer of Aethiopia, going to Hieruſalem, to worſhip God as he went, reade the ſcriptures, if reading wold haue ſerued his turn, Philip needed not to haue come to

him, but he vnderſtoode not before be had a guide, hee was not conuerted, neyther had he ſayth ſufficient to ſaluation, before hee hearde the preaching of the Worde, which in deede is that eſpeciall, effectuall, bleſſed and excellent ordinarye meane of fayth, as it appeareth more plainly and fully in the next part of our text.
            Which beeing rightly waighed, confirmeth the greate neceſſitye of preaching, and prooueth that euery Miniſter ought to preach. Woe bee to me, if I preach not the Gospell. And why ſo? becauſe I am called to it, becauſe I am a Miniſter, becauſe the Lorde requireth it of me. Although Saint Paule and the other Apoſtles had priuiledges and prerogatiues, which we haue not, although we haue not fullye ſo large a commiſſion, as hee and they had: Although they did many thinges, which we neither may, nor can doe: yet as touching the office of preaching, it appertaineth as well to vs as to them. And for the further

proofe of this matter I will rehearſe ſome argumentes, which before I haue vſed in this place, adding diuers others to them.
            
               1 It is the commandemēt of Chriſt and the holy Apoſtles, therefore neceſſary. Chriſt ſayd to his Apoſtles, Goe preach the Gospell.
               Mar. 16.15. The which cō
               mandement, in this behalfe belongeth to all the miniſters of God. Saint Paule ſtraightly chargeth the miniſters of Epheſus. Take heed vnto your ſelues, and to all the flocke, whereof the holy Ghoſt hath made you ouerſeers, to feede the Church of God, which he hath purchaſed with his own bloud.
                And moſt weightily of al, he requireth it in the place already alleadged, he leaueth it not as a thing indifferent, that may be done, or vndone, but ſpeaketh with a wonderful and mighty proteſtation, he ioyneth the Scripture and preaching togeather. For hauing before in the former Chapiter, ſet foorth the great profit of the ſcriptures, ſtraight waye hee neceſſarilye addeth this forecible exhortation.2. Tim. 4.1. 
               I charge thee

therefore before God, and before the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which ſhall iudge the quicke and the deade at his appearing, and in his kingdome, preach the worde, be instant, in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, improoue, rebuke, exhort.
            
            
               2 It is an argument &amp; token of the loue the Miniſter oweth vnto Chriſt and to the people, as it appeareth Ioh. 21.15. where Ieſus Chriſt ſayth to Peter after his reſurrection.Iohn. 21.15.16.17. 
               Simon ſonne of Iona, loueſt thou me more then theſe? He ſayde vnto him, yea Lorde, thou knoweſt that I loue thee: he ſayde to him, feed my Lambes. He ſaid vnto him the ſecond time. Simon the ſonne of Iona, loueſt thou me? He ſayde vnto him, yea Lorde, thou knoweſt that I loue thee: he ſayd vnto him feed my ſheepe. Chriſt ſaid to him the third time. Simon the ſonne of Iona, loueſt thou me? Peter was ſory becauſe he ſayd to him the third time, loueſt thou me, &amp; ſaid vnto him, Lord thou knoweſt all thinges: thou knoweſt that I loue thee. Ieſus ſayd vnto him: feed my ſheepe. Whereby it is euident, that thoſe which feed not, loue not Chriſt: Séeing

then that feeding or preaching is ſo plaine a token of the loue that the miniſter oweth to Chriſt, it is moſte neceſſarily required if any do preach and yet not vpon this loue, they haue their condemnation.
            
               3 The Church of God is begunne and grounded, by the preaching of the word:Rom. 10.17. and therfore neceſſary. Paule ſayth, Faith commeth by the worde preached.
            
            
               1. Cor. 3.6.Againe, he counteth his preaching amongſt the Corrinthians, a planting of them in faith and religion. S. Peter ſayth,1. Pet. 1.23. 
               We are borne a new, not of mortall ſeede, but of immortall, by the word of God, who liueth and indureth for euer. And preſētly addeth. This is the word which is preached among you,
            
            
               1. Cor. 3.1. Heb. 5 12. &amp; 6.1.
               4 By preaching, the church of God is not onely begun, but alſo amplified, buildes and enlarged. It wil not onely make vs babes in Chriſte, but ſtrong and ſpirituall men. It hath not onely milke for the weake, but ſtrong meate for them, that are of age. By it we are brought not onely

to the beginning of Chriſte, and firſte rudimentes of Chriſtian religion, but alſo we are ledde forwarde vnto perfection. The holy Apoſtle affyrmeth this, when as hee ſayth, that Ieſus gaue ſome to be Apostles, and Prophetes, and ſome Euangelistes, and ſome Pastoures and Teachers, for the gathering of Sayntes, for the worke of the Ministery, and for the edification of the bodye of Christe vnto a perfect man, and vnto the meaſure of the age of the fulneſſe of Christe.
            
            
               5 The Church of God begun and brought to that perfection which can be in earth, is alſo ſtayed, ſtrengthened, vpholden and preſerued, by the preaching of the worde, againſt ſinne and errour. And therefore for theſe cauſes alſo, the preaching of the word is moſt neceſſary, yea and that daylye and continually, becauſe ſome are weake and haue need of daily ſtrengthening, ſome fall into errours, and ſome into greeuous Sinnes, from the which they are to bee drawen

out by the effectuall preaching of the worde. This doth the holy Apoſtle confirme, whereas he ſayth, that The whole Scripture is profitable to teach,
               2. Tim. 3.16. 
               to improoue, to correct, and to instruct in righteouſneſſe, that the man of God may be abſolute, beeing made perfect vnto all good workes.
            
            
               6 Againe, to the pure preaching of the word, the Lorde hath promiſed a bleſſing, the miniſter ſhal be bleſſed, the people alſo bleſſed through it. They that be wiſe ſayth Daniell,
               Dani. 12.3. 
               ſhall ſhine as the brightneſſe of the firmament: And they that tourne many vnto righteouſneſſe ſhall ſhine as the ſtarres for euer and euer.
               Mat. 24.45.46.47. 
               The wiſe and faithfull Steward, that giueth meate to the houſholde in due ſeaſon, when his maiſter commeth he ſhall be bleſſed, and made partaker of exceeding ioy and glory.
               1. Tim. 4.16. 
               Take heed ſayth the Apoſtle to thy ſelfe, and to learning: continue therin, for in doing this, thou ſhalt both ſaue thy ſelfe and them that heare thee. God ſo bleſſed the preaching of his Seruaunt Ionas,
               Ionas. 3.4. that through it the Niniuites beléeued God, humbled them

ſelues, and forſooke their former wicked wayes.Act. 2.41. At one preaching of Peter there were wonne to the Lorde about thre thouſande ſoules. Thus doth the Lorde bleſſe his owne order, the miniſter by pure and faithfull preaching, diſchargeth his owne ſoule, obtayneth peace in conſcience, and ſo is bleſſed in this life, but ſhall be farre more bleſſed in the life to come, when hee hath finiſhed his courſe, he ſhall receiue an incorruptible crown of glory. The people alſo by this means are many ways bleſſed, they receiue knowledge, faith,Act. 2
                     •
                  .18. &amp; ſaluation: their eies are opened, they are turned frō darknes to light, &amp; frō ye power of ſatan vnto God All theſe great and notable bleſſings, doe enſue the preaching of the worde, and therefore required moſt neceſſarilie in euery miniſter.
            
               7 On the other ſide, without this, both the miniſter and the people are accurſed, the bloud of the people ſhal be required at his handes, becauſe he hath not as a faithfull watchman,Ezec. 3.17
               
forewarned them of daunger, and yet they ſhall die in their owne ſinnes.
            The Lord complaineth by his Prophet Hoſea ſaying,Hoſea. 4.6. 
               My people are deſtroyed for lacke of knowledge, becauſe thou haſte refuſed knowledge, I will alſo refuſe thee, that thou ſhalt be no Prieſt to me.
               Mat. 5.13. To this agreeth our Sauiour Chriſt, If the ſalt haue loſt his ſaltnes, it is good for nothing, but to be caſt out, and to be troden vnder foot of men. And if theſe Miniſters which ſometimes haue had Salte in them, zeale, and knowledge to ſeaſon the people, and by negligence and careleſnes, decay and looſe it
            If theſe I ſaye be worthy to be caſt out, howe miſerable and curſed are they which neuer had nor yet haue any Salt in them. It muſte needes be fulfilled of them which our Sauiour ſpeaketh in an other place, They be blinde leaders of the blinde, and if the blinde lead the blind,
               Mat. 15.14. 
               both ſhall fall into the ditch, (that is) both the ignoraunt Miniſter and the ignoraunt

people ſhall periſhe. And in another place it is ſayde,Mat. 25.30. 
               Caſt that vnprofitable Seruaunt into vtter darkeneſſe, there ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth. And here it is ſayde, Woe be to me if I preach not the Gospell.
            
            Seeing then that euery way there hangeth ſo manye greeuous curſes, both vppon the miniſter and people, where the worde is not preached, it is moſt requyſite and neceſſarie, that euery miniſter looke to this, euen as hee will eſcape the fearefull and heauie curſſe of God.
            
               8 Moreouer the chiefe ende and vſe why the ſcriptures were written, doth requyre preaching.Rom. 15.4. 1. Cor. 14. They are lefte for our comforte, inſtruction, and edifying. But we are moſt comforted, inſtructed, and edifyed, if they bee opened and applyed to vs, and therefore moſte neceſſarie that they be ſo vſed.
            
               9 Alſo the Corruption and dulneſſe of our nature requyreth the ſame, we are dull, ignoraunt, and careleſſe. We pleaſe our ſelues in

our owne ſinnes, the Deuill goeth about continually to deuour vs, and therefore we haue need to haue continuall preaching of the word.1. Cor. 2, 14. The naturall man perceiueth not the thinges that are of Gods ſpirit. Dauid,
               2. Sam. 12. after he had ſinned, continued in his ſinne, vntill the Prophet reprooued him for it, yea and woulde not take it to him ſelfe, although Nathan ſpake a very plaine parable, till it was particularly applyed to him. Seeing then there is in our nature ſuch corruption, ſuch blindneſſe, ſuch ſlouthfulneſſe, and alſo forgetfulnes: what can be more neceſſary for the curing of theſe ſo great diſeaſes, then the continuall and dayly preaching of the word:
            Beſides all this, it hath beene an vſuall order in the church of God vnder the lawe, by Chriſt and the Apoſtles, not onely to reade, but alſo to expound and apply the Scriptures, and therefore the ſame order is to be obſerued of vs.Nehe. 8.8. It is ſayd of the Leuites that they red in the booke of the

law of God diſtinctly and gaue the ſence, and cauſed them to vnderſtande the reading. Chriſt as we haue heard already cō
               tinually preached and commaunded the ſame to his Apoſtles, who as they obeyed in them ſelues their Maiſters commaundement, ſo they required it as a continuall and vſuall rule to be obſerued for euer of al the Miniſters of God in his church.
            And moſt ſpecially the Apoſtle in thoſe Epiſtles which he wrote vnto Timothie and Titus very largely &amp; effectually vrgeth this matter. I referre you alſo vnto the 14. Chapter of his firſt Epiſtle to the Corinthians: wherein ſo highly he commendeth the gift of Propheſieing,1. Cor. 1
                     •
                  
                Interpretation or preaching, that he preferreth it before all other giftes, and accounteth it ſo neceſſarie, that he would haue it continually obſerued in the Church of God.
            Againe Chriſt commaundeth vs, and wee doe daylie praie for the enlarging of his Kingdome, whereas he hath taught vs to ſay thy kingdome come: Now, the ſinguler and excellēt meanes to eſtabliſh the kingdome of Ieſus Chriſt is, by the pure and effectual preaching of the word,

and therefore he ſaieth in an other place, Pray to the Lorde of the Harueſt,
               Math. 9.38. 
               to ſend forth Labourers into the Harueſt. And how cā they pray with any ſafe cōſcience, for the enlarging and eſtabliſhing of the kingdome of Chriſt, which by their ignorance and careleſneſſe, do altogether hinder it. Furthermore, all and euery one of the names whiche are giuen by the holie Ghoſt to the miniſters, in ye word of God, doe neceſſarily require at their handes Preaching: They are called the light of the worlde, the ſalt of the earth. They are called Paſtors and Sheepheards. They are called Huſbandmen, Guides, Stewards and Meſſengers, beſides many other excellent titles giuen to them. Now how can they bee called Lightes, whiche haue no light in them, which either are in ignoraunce and darkneſſe themſelues, or els hide their cādle vnder a Buſhel? How can they bee called the Salt of the earth, which cannot or will not ſeaſon the vnfauorie and ſinfull people, with the heauenly &amp; wholeſome doctrine of eternall life: How can they be called Paſtors and teachers, which do not feed or haue no foode

at all to giue to the flocke? How can they be called the Lords Huſbandmen, which haue no ſkill at all in tilling his ground, and ſowing his ſeede? How can they bee called Guides vnto other, whiche either know not the way themſelues, or els will not vouchſafe to open and declare it to other: How can they be called Stewards, which haue no care of the houſhold, which either cannot or will not feede them? And how can they bee called the Lordes Meſſengers, whiche are not able to doe their meſſage, or haue no care at all to doe it.
            If the Miniſter bee a light to the people, of neceſſitie he muſt needes goe and ſhine before them in knowledge and doctrine. If he bee the Salt, he muſt needes ſeaſon. If he be a Paſtor or Sheepheard, he muſt needes feed. If he be a Huſbandman, he muſt needes haue a care of the Lordes Huſbandrie. If he be a Guide, he muſt needes ſhewe the waye. If he bee a Stewarde, he muſt prouide for the houſholde. If he bee a Meſſenger, he muſt bee willing and able to do his meſſage: Naie I ſaie more, it ſtandes for the Lordes glorie and credite to haue ſuche Paſtors, and

ſuch Huſbandmen, ſuch Stewardes and Meſſengers, as haue wiſedome &amp; knowledge. The poore people of the Countrie will not hire him to be a Sheepheard to their Sheepe, whom they know to be ignorant and careleſſe, and ſhall the Lorde chooſe ſuch to gouerne &amp; guide his flock? The Gentleman and the Yeman wil not hire any to be ouerſeers of their Huſbandrie, except they knowe them to haue ſufficient diſcretion and experience: and wil he thinke ye bee content with ſimple, fooliſh, and reckleſſe ouerſeers of his ſo dere and precious a Huſbandrie? The Noble man for his honors ſake, wil ſeeke to haue ſuch a one to be the Steward of his houſe, as is truſtie, wiſe, &amp; of ſufficient to guide and gouerne a whole houſholde, and ſhall the Lorde be leſſe carefull of his honour? ſhall he bee content with vnwiſe and vnfaithfull Stewardes? The Prince will haue a ſpeciall care to ſende ſuch to be his meſſengers and Ambaſſadors, as be moſt wiſe and faithfull, and are able diſcreetly and cunningly to doe their meſſage, and ſhall the Lordes meſſengers bee without knowledge? What can be more to the diſcredite

and diſhonour of his holy name? This argument I amplifie the more, becauſe it is very plaine &amp; effectuall. Mark I beſeech you wel, all theſe and other names giuen to vs in the holie Scripture, doe require of euery miniſter of God that he preach the worde, as we haue a rare to aunſwere to our names, and a care of the glorie and credite of our God: euen ſo let vs be carefull in doing this ſo neceſſarie a duetie. What ſhall I ſaie more, the end and purpoſe of our calling and Miniſtrie requireth at our handes Preaching. The Lorde hath ordained Paſtors and Teachers for the gathering together of his Saincts, and to the edification of the bodie of Chriſt: Seeing then we are called to this ende, ſeing we are ordained to this purpoſe, there is no remedie, we that are the Miniſters of God, muſt needes of neceſſitie preach his worde. For a further proofe and concluſion of this matter, I call you to recorde, I appeale to your owne conſciences, which are now wonne to the Lord, which haue ſome meaſure of knowledge, which are called out of darkneſſe to light, from ignoraunce to knowledge:

ye that ſometime haue been content with reading Miniſters, and quarter Sermons, but now hunger and thirſt for the worde preached. I call you I ſaie, as witneſſes in this cauſe, what comfort you feele, what profite, what power in the effectuall preaching of ye word? How careleſſe, how prophane, how ignorant, how leaude you were before, notwithſtanding the daylie and the ordinarie Readinges whiche diligently you had? What hath wrought in you that meaſure of faith, that heauenly knowledge whiche you now haue? What is it, that hath wrought in you ſuche a ſorrowe of your former life, ſuche a griefe and hatred of ſinne and ſuperſtition, both in your ſelues and others, ſuche an earneſt zeale of the worde, ſuch a conſcience and a care to reforme your ſelues and your houſholdes. What (I ſaie) hath wrought theſe thinges in you? How came you by them? What is it that hath ſo altered your mindes, deedes and affections: Let your conſcience be witneſſe to me in this matter: I am ſure you wil approue that which I haue ſpoken, and acknowledge the profite, the power and neceſſitie

of the worde preached.
            All and euery one of theſe arguments doe proue and confirme as I thinke, that euery Miniſter neceſſarilye ought to preach, and otherwiſe, that he is no Miniſter approued of God. All and euery one of theſe, or moſt of them doe quite ouerthrow and condemne, all dumbe, idle and careleſſe Miniſters whatſoeuer. One day they ſhall knowe what accounte he maketh of the ſoules of his people, for ſeeyng the worde of the Lord, in ſo many places, requireth in a Miniſter preachyng, yea, diligent and carefull preaching, in what a miſerable and damnable ſtate doe theſe men ſtand? The Apoſtle ſaieth woe be to me if I preach not the Goſpell. Well, it maie bee whatſoeuer I haue yet ſpoken will be graunted. It is neceſſarie that euery Miniſter preache: but what ſhall all thoſe be condemned which haue not ſuch full meaſure of knowledge as other haue, whiche be not accounted and allowed for publique Prachers, God forbid? I know theſe difference in giftes, there was ſo amongſt the Apoſtles, but they all ſuficiently preached. Amongſt vs and ſuche others

as vſe this place, and ſuch like places, there is differēce, euery one of vs haue not the like meaſure, but for my parte I ſpeake as I thinke, our meaſure is ſmall inough, yet the Lorde be thanked for that we haue, and giue vs grace to vſe it to his glorie and the benefite of his Church, in my ſelf I profeſſe and graunt very ſmall and weake meaſure, inſufficiencie and lacke of gifts, and the Lord the ſearcher of the harts knoweth, that the conſideration of this hath and doeth make me to feare and trimble often tymes, to ſigh and lament that ſo great a charge, and ſo waightie a burthen is layed vpon me, ſo ſimple and weake a wretch.
            To you that haue any meaſure of thoſe gifts which the Lord requireth in his Miniſters, to you (I ſay) quenche not the ſpirite, vſe the meanes to increaſe your meaſure, if you be painefull, carefull, watchfull, and faithfull in your miniſtrie with a holy and pure affection, the Lorde will bleſſe you.Act. 18.26. 
               To him that hath ſhall be giuen, we cannot at the firſt come to perfection. Appollos a learned Docter, feruente in the ſpirite, and mightie in the ſcriptures,

yet was he ignorant in ſome things, and receiued inſtructions from Aquila and Priſcilla. Some haue more then others,Math. 25.14. ſome haue tenne talentes, ſome fiue, and ſome but one, yet alwaies remember, and let it neuer ſlippe out of your minds, that the ſlothfull and vnprofitable ſeruaunt ſhalbe caſt into vtter darkenes, there ſhall bee weepying and gnaſhyng of teeth. Againſt ſuche I ſpeake whiche in deede neuer had any one talente, or any giftes of Miniſters, or hauyng any do either abuſe them, or at leaſt doe not put them forth to any profitable vſe. Conſider a little the ſtate of our miniſtrie. There bee ſome amongſt vs ſacrificeing and maſ
                  •
               ing Prieſtes full of manifeſt ſuperſtition and hypocriſie, and in truth enemies to Chriſts religion. Others there be altogether ignorant, vnlearned, very idoles, they can doe what? Euen iuſt nothyng. Others there be which may haue ſome ground of learnyng, but in deede they vtter very little, neither is the people better by them. Some are idle, ſome careleſſe, ſome altogether leude and profaine, ſome ioyne liuing to liuing, and take more vpon them,

then they can diſcharge although it may be they ſpeake in one place, yet are they du
                  ••…
               e in an other. All theſe and ſuch like are worthte of blame, to be openly ſpoken againſt becauſe they open offence. All theſe ſtand dayly in a miſerable and damnable ſtate without repentance. But my cheif drifte at this tyme in this parte of my text, is to proue as you haue hard, that euery Miniſter approued of God muſt preache, that is, he muſt teede the people, he muſt cut the worde of God, he muſt improue, rebuke, exhort, he muſt not ſimply or barely reade, or heare the people ſaie ſome Catachiſme, but he is to be able in ſome ſufficiēt meaſure to open and interpret the holy Scripture, and applie them, and I hope that this is alreadie proued: onely I exhort you to accompt the Lord wiſeſt to reſt in his holy decrees, and allowe his owne order as beſt. Let vs not take vppon vs to appointe him what he ſhould do. Seing he hath ſet downe preaching, as the moſt excellent, and ordinary meanes to ſaluation, let not vs ſay that reading will ſerue the turne: ſeing that he requireth that his Miniſters bee apt to

teach, let vs not coumpt them his Miniſters which neuer taught, nor euer had any aptneſſe in them. If he maie bee counted a lawfull Miniſter and Teacher that onely readeth the ordinarie Seruice, and ſometime heareth a fewe children to ſaie a Catechiſme without booke, as it is ſet downe before him, then maie the Clarke alſo of the Towne be coumpted a Miniſter, and teacher: then may euery Huſbandman, Seruing man, nay euery boye or childe that can doe aſmuch, be ſo counted. Let not ſome ſaie for defence of ignorant Miniſters, that if they do that, which they can doe, it will ſerue the turne: for in the building of an houſe, as there be ſome Maiſter builders which bring timber and ſtone, ſo other there be, which bring morter and fillinges, and ſerue to neceſſarie vſe, but let vs remember that euery Miniſter in his charge, is or ought to bee a builder, yea a Maiſter builder, and if the chief builder bring nothing but fillinges, how ſhal the Lords building in that place goe forwarde? The Apoſtle in that place whiche hath been already twiſe alledged,Ephe. 4. ſaieth That the Lorde hath ordained the

Minister for the gathering together of his Saincts, and for the edification of the bodie of Chriſt, till wee all meete together in the vnitie of faith and knowledge of the Sonne of GOD, vnto a perfect man, and vnto the meaſure of the age of the fulneſſe of Chriſt. Oh theſe be no ſmall things, theſe are no trifles, this is no vile, ſimple, and drudgerie woorke, no ſmall meaſure, but very great, weightie, high, and moſt excellent. The holy Ghoſt in an other place ſaieth, Leauing the doctrine of the beginning of Chriſt,
               
                  
                     •
                  eb. 6.
                     •
                  . 
               let vs be led forwarde vnto perfection, not laying againe the foundation of repentance from dead workes, and of faith toward GOD, of the doctrine of Baptiſme and laying on of handes, and of the reſurrectiō from the dead, and of eternal iudgement. Marke I beſeech you theſe words. There be many people, yea &amp; Miniſters alſo that are ignoraunt of the firſt rudimentes of Chriſt, that of repentaunce, of Baptiſme, of the reſurrection, of eternall iudgement, are able to ſaie nothing to any purpoſe: but yet let it bee ſo that ſome can doe this, they can teach as they ſaie in ſome meaſure: their an Catechiſe, and ay

the groundes of Religion, yet this will not ſerue the turne, there muſt bee building after the foundation, there muſt be a leading forward to perfection. The Lord in building the material Tabernacle, did chooſe men of ſinguler wiſedome, and vnderſtanding, and will he be content, with euery drudge and bungler in the building and erecting of his ſpirituall Tabernacle: But herein chiefly haue ſome gathered offence and grief, becauſe I haue ſaid in this place before, and alſo other where, that ſuche Miniſters haue no right to adminiſter the Sacramentes.
            This ſeemeth a ſtraunge and hard doctrine, yea, ſome are not aſhamed to count it erronious and hereticall, if I would ſtande vpō the authoritie of men, I could alledge for the confirmation of the very wordes whiche I haue ſpoken, the iudgement of thoſe which by common conſent of all true Chriſtians are receiued and allowed, as the beſt, moſt learned and moſt pure Diuines that euer were ſince the time of the Apoſtles, but this I hope ſhal not neede: for if of neceſſitie euery Miniſter ought to preache, or if all the former

argumentes wil ſerue to proue this, then alſo that other doctrine, how ſtraunge and obſurde ſoeuer ſome count it, I muſt I ſaie needes neceſſarily and conſequently followe, none ought of right to deale with the Lordes Sacramentes but his Miniſters. Chriſt requireth of him that Baptiſeth, that he teach: ſaiing, Go teach and Baptiſe:
               Math. 28.19. No Teacher, no Baptiſer, that which God hath ioyned together, let no man put aſunder.
                  
                     •
                  . Cor. 11.26. Sainct Paule ſpeaking of the Lordes Supper: As often ſaieth he, as ye ſhall eate this breade, and drinke this cupp, ye ſhew the Lordes death till he come. If the people at the receiuing of the Sacrament, ought to haue an effectuall and thankfull remembraunce of the death of Chriſt, it muſt needes follow that the Miniſter is bound, ſufficiently to inſtruct them in the ſame. If any will ſay that this done by the dumbe Miniſter in reading the wordes of the inſtitution, he preacheth, he ſheweth and publiſheth Ieſus Chriſt crucified, ſo may I ſay that he or any other doth the ſame, and that more effectually, if they doe but ſaie their beleefe openly before the Congregation,

but we ſpeake of a ſingular, of an effectuall, of an excellent and liuely ſhewing of his death, which is by preaching. The Apoſtle ſpeaking to the Galatians ſaieth,Gala. 3.
                     •
                  . 
               That Ieſus Chriſt was deſcribed in their ſight, and among them crucified. His meaning is that Chriſte was ſo liuely preached to them, as his liuely Image was ſet before their eyes, or els had been crucified amongſt them. This is the power of preaching, this is the duetie of the Miniſter, plainly and effectually to diſcribe and ſet forth the merite of Chriſt his Paſſion, ſo that it maie bee ſeen as it were before the eyes.
            The firſt Miniſter of Baptiſme Iohn the Baptiſt was a Preacher,Math. 
                     •
                  . he ioyned Preaching and Baptiſme together, and in no dou
                  •
               t the Lorde would leaue to his Churche an example and patterne, and a forme of the right miniſtration of the Sacramentes.Mark. 1.
                     •
                  . Chriſt although there were ſundrie cauſes why he would not Baptiſe, yet he miniſtred the Supper to his Apoſtles,Math. 16.
                     ••
                  . but Chriſt was a Preacher, yea he preached then of his death before

that firſt miniſtration and inſtitution of that Sacrament, leauing vs an example to doe the like.
            
               Act. 2.38. Act. 8.12.38. Act. 10.34. Act. 20.7.The Apoſtles miniſtred the Sacramentes but they all preached, yea, the Euangeliſt Luke in the ſtorie of the Actes, ſetteth Preaching alwaies before the miniſtration of the Sacramentes. Iohn the Baptiſt, Chriſt, the Apoſtles and Primatiue Church are the beſt examples that I knowe, and beſt worthie to bee followed.
            Conſider further I beſeeche you, the greate inconueniences which followe in theſe places where the worde is not preached, the people are ſtill in ignorance and blindneſſe, and kept ſtill in their olde and Popiſhe errors, receiued from their forefathers, they know not the vſe of the Sacramentes, or to what ende they ſerue, they holde ſtill their Papiſticall tranſubſtantiation: ſome ſaie, they receiue their maker: other ſaie, they neuer heard what a Sacrament meant: ſome ſaie they doe it in a good intent, and yet they knowe not their owne intent: other ſay thei hope that they receiue it as others doe: fewe make any conſcience with knowledge,

feare and reuerence to prepare themſelues. The greateſt cauſe of this, is lack of Preaching, and in deede how can their greate ignoraunce be taken awaie, how can their olde ſuperſticious errors bee effectually confuted, but by the continuall and pure preaching of the worde? And is it not then moſt fitt and conuenient, when the Sacrament is to be miniſtred: but we are ſo farre from hauing any vſuall preaching before the Sacrament, that be many thouſandes whiche neuer heard any preaching at al of the Sacramentes in al their life, they haue liued theſe 25. yeares in a Chriſtian land vnder the Goſpel, and yet they haue profited no further: and if they ſhould liue ſtill dubble and triple the ſame yeares, they ſhould bee neuer a whit the better, except they had better Miniſters, Woe be to me if I preach not the Goſpell. Learne one thing further before I goe to the next parte of my Text, if there depende a woe ouer the Miniſter if he preache not the ſame, woe is alſo againſt the people if they heare not, and obey not the worde preached: Woe Chorazin:
               Math. 11.2
                     •
                  . 
               woe

                  Bethſaida,
                woe Capernaum, wo to theſe Countries, Citties, Townes and People, which neglect and contemne the word preached, it ſhall be eaſier for the lande of Sodome and Gomorrha in the daie of Iudgement, then for ſuche a people. The ſame God, the ſame worde whiche requireth preaching of the Miniſter, requireth alſo hearing and obedience of the people. He that is of God heareth Gods word,
               Ihon 8.4
                     •
                  . 
               and therefore doe ye not heare it becauſe ye are not of GOD.
               Ihon. 10.27. 
               My Sheepe (ſaieth Chriſt) heare my voyce. And to the true Miniſter it is ſaid,Luke. 10.16. 
               He that heareth you heareth me, and he that diſpiſeth you, diſpiſeth me, and he that diſpiſeth me diſpiſeth him that ſent me.
               Ihon. 13.20. And againe, Verely verely I ſaie vnto you, if I ſend any, he that receiueth him receiueth me.
               Heb. 2. 
               Wherefore we ought diligently to giue heede to the things which we haue heard, leaſt at any time we ſhould let them ſlippe. For if the worde ſpoken by Angels was ſtedfaſt, and euery tranſgreſſion and diſobedience receiued a iuſt recompence of rewarde, how ſhall we eſcape, if we neglect ſo greate ſa
                     ••…
                  ation, which at the firſt began

to be preached by the Lord, and afterward was confirmed vnto vs by them that heard him, GOD bearing witneſſe thereto, both with ſignes and wonders, and with diuers miracles, and giftes of the holy Ghoſt, according to his owne will? Woe then vnto all Papiſtes, Infidells, Atheiſtes, Hypocrites, ignorant and carnall men, for none of theſe in truth doe make account of the Goſpell.
            And now let vs come to the third parte of our Text,The third parte. wherein is ſett downe what euery Miniſter ought to preache, namely the Goſpell. They are not bounde to deliuer the Counſelles of men, the Traditions of the Fathers, the Statutes of earthly Princes, or the authoritie of mort
                  •
               ll men: but as they are the ſeruauntes of Ieſus Chriſt, Prince of all Princes,Ierem. 1. ſo are they bounde onely to preache his Goſpell.Ezec. 3. The true Prophetes neuer ſpeake of them ſelues to the people, but as they receiued warning from the Lorde. They had no authoritie to ſpeake their owne words, nor the words of any mortal man. The Apoſtles might not teach their own

doctrine,Math. 28.20. but onely that whiche they had receiued from their Maiſter, who enioyneth them to teache all thinges what ſoeuer he had commaunded them: Goe (ſaieth he) and preache the Goſpell.
               Marc 16. The holy Apoſtle writing to the Corinthians,
               1. Cor. 11.23. auoucheth that he receiued of the Lorde, that which he deliuered to them,1. Cor. 15.3. whereby wee maie ſee all theſe Teachers confuted, which ſtande vpon the authoritie of men, whiche adde or diminiſhe any thing from the Scriptures, whiche ioyne their owne fantaſies and the traditions of men, with the holy pure and perfect worde of God: Woe be to thoſe ſonnes of vanities for in deede they preache not the Goſpell, they preache not Chriſt but themſelues. They deface and weaken the authoritie of the holy Scriptures:Pſalm. 19. 
               The lawe of GOD is a perfect lawe conuerting ſoules.
               
                  
                     •
                  . Tim. 3. 
               The Scripture is able to make the man of God abſolute and perfect to all good workes. The Lord ſaith by his Prophet: He that hath a dreame,
               Ierem. 23.28. 
               let him tell a dreame, and he that hath my word, let him ſpeake my word faithfully: and what is the chaffe to the

wheate, ſaith the Lorde? Is not my worde euen like a fire, ſaieth the Lorde, and like a hammer that breaketh the ſtone? Our Sauiour in the Goſpel ſpeaketh againſt ſuch teachers: ſaying,Math 15.
                     •
                  . 
               In vaine they worſhippe me, teaching the doctrine and preceptes of men. Let vs remēber that which is ſpoken in the laſt Chapter of the Reuelation.Reue. 22.18. 
               I proteſt vnto euery man that heareth the propheſie of this booke, if any man add vnto theſe thinges, God ſhall add vnto him the plagues, that are written in this booke. And if any man ſhall diminiſhe of the wordes of this propheſie, God ſhall take awaie his parte out of the booke of life, and out of the holy Cittie, and from theſe thinges which are written in this booke. Woe be to them which preache and yet preach not the Goſpell. But that we may know the better howe the Goſpell ſhould bee preached, let vs conſider a little what it is, and what it containeth. The Euangeliſtes call it the Goſpell of the Kingdome.Rom. 13.16. Sainct Paule accoumpteth it that whiche was promiſed before by the Prophetes in the holie Scriptures concerning

Ieſus Chriſte our Lorde: And in the ſame Chapter he ſaieth,2. Cor. 5.18. 
               It is the power of GOD vnto ſaluation to euery one that beleeueth. And in an other place he calleth it the worde and miniſtrie of Reconciliation.Reue. 1.2. Sainct Iohn calleth it the teſtimonie of Ieſus Chriſt. From theſe and ſuche like places maie bee eaſily gathered a full definition of the Goſpell, whiche I leaue to your godly conſideration: Onely this I adde, that vnder the voyce of the Goſpell, is comprehended the whole hiſtorie of Ieſus Chriſt in the fl
                  •
               ſhe, and alſo the fruite and vſe of the ſame Hiſtorie.Luke. 24.46. As touchyng the firſt, namely the hiſtorie of Chriſte, it is ſommarily comprehended vnder his Paſſion and Reſurrection: the vſe and ende of all is, that wee ſhould haue repentaunce and remiſſion of ſinnes in his name, and this doeth Chriſte himſelfe witneſſe, when as he laied to his Apoſtles after his Reſurrection: Thus it is written and thus it behooued Chriſt to ſuffer, and to riſe againe from the dead the third daie, and that repentance and remiſſion of ſinnes ſhould bee

preached in his name among all Nations. To this agreeth the holy Apoſtle Saint Peter,
               Act. 5.30. when as he ſaieth with other the Apoſtles, to the Counſel and chief Prieſtes. The God of our Fathers hath raiſed vp Ieſus, whom ye ſlue, and hanged on a tree. Him hath God lift vp with his right hande, to bee a Prince and a Sauiour, to giue repentaunce vnto Iſraell, and forgiueneſſe of ſinnes. By this wee maie ſee how the Goſpell muſt bee preached, the people muſt bee taught what Chriſte hath done for them. The whole Storie of his Incarnation, Conception, Birth, Sufferinges, Reſurrection and Aſſention, theſe thinges I ſaie muſt bee often tymes and effectually preached to the people, as they are ſet downe by the holy Euangeliſtes and Apoſtles: But yet this is not enough to ſhewe what Chriſt hath done, to rehearſe the Storie of his Incarnation, but alſo the Miniſter muſt bee carefull to preache the vſe, the ende and fruite of the ſame Storie: whiche is, that the people maie repent, bee tourned vnfainedly vnto God, and ſo by faith made

pertakers of remiſſion of ſinnes through Ieſus Chriſte. Repentaunce is a true tournyng to GOD, a chaungyng of the outwarde and inwarde man, a dying to ſinne, a liuing to righteouſneſſe, and a mendement of the whole life: which this doctrine wee muſt beginne, this we muſt firſt of all and chiefly vrge: This is that doctrine chiefly and moſt of all preached by the holy Prophetes:Ierem. 4.1. Ezec. 18.1. This is the common and vſuall voyce, O Iſraell returne to the Lorde.
               Hoſe. 14 1. Math 3.2. Math. 4.17. 
               Iohn the Baptiſt the Meſſenger, and alſo Ieſus Chriſte his Maiſter, they crye both of them: Repent for the kingdome of Heauen is at hande. The Apoſtles alſo euery where exhorte men to repentaunce to amendement of life,Rom. 3.2. to mortification and regeneration. This is an vſuall doctrine in all their Epiſtles. Now,Rom. 7.7. they can neuer truly repent which knowe not the greatneſſe of their ſinnes and the puniſhment due to them. And how ſhall they knowe this, except their ſinnes bee reproued and laied open by preaching the lawe of GOD, for by the lawe commeth the knowledge of ſinne:

ſo that the doctrine of the lawe muſt not bee ſeperated from the preaching of the Goſpell, for it is a Schoolemaiſter to bring vs to Chriſt. This then is neceſſarily required of euery Miniſter, freely and boldly to reprooue ſinne in all ſtates and degrees whatſoeuer. This is it that the Lorde ſaieth to his Prophete.Iſai. 58.
                     •
                  . 
               Crye aloude, ſpare not, lift vp thy voyce like a Trumpet, and ſhew my people their tranſgreſſions, and to the houſe of Iacob their ſinnes. Our Sauiour Chriſt accounteth it as an office &amp; duetie of the holy Ghoſt,Ihon. 16.8. to reproue the worlde of ſinne. And in deede there is no doctrine more neceſſarie for this age, wherein wee liue, although fewe can away it, but crie out againſt ſuch as preache it. And as in other places, ſo in this place heretofore I haue had proofe in this matter. For vpon iuſt occaſion noting the certaintie of Gods iugements and condemnation of the wicked, I finde then that the impenitent and ſuche as continue in their ſinnes could not bee ſaued, God could not forgiue them, here vpon ſome haue ſayd and

doe ſay ſtill of mee, that I preached, that God could not forgiue ſinnes. I ſayde, and I ſay agayne, the Lorde is as true in his iuſtice, as in his mercie. Chriſt ſaieth, except ye amend, ye ſhall all periſh: and againe, he that beleeueth not is damned. Saint Paul ſayth, no whoremonger, nor adulterer, no vnrighteous or vncleane perſone ſhall inherite the kingdome of Heauen. This is aſmuche as I ſaied, and in effect all that I ſaide, woe bee to me if I preache not the Goſpell.
            Now Repentaunce is a parte of the Goſpell, and that wee maie repent, it is needfull to knowe our ſinnes, and as the ſinnes of all men muſt bee reproued, and the iudgementes of GOD threatened againſt them, ſo eſpecially the ſinnes of publique perſones as Magiſtrates and Miniſters: And if this in no caſe will bee borne, but he that doth it, is ſtraight way blamed, alas, what ſhall wee doe? If wee ſpeake againſt the people, they are greeued, they ſaie we deale hardly with them, but looke not to our ſelues or to the higher powers. If wee deale againſt

Gentlemen and greate men, wee are hated, euill ſpoken of and abuſed: If wee ſpeake againſt the ignoraunt and careleſſe Miniſters, they are alſo offended, and ſaye wee lacke diſcretion, charitie and modeſtie. Thus daungerous a thing it is to preache the Goſpell, yea euen amongſt them that glorie in the Goſpell, ſo that as our ſtate ſtandeth it mate bee ſaied cleane contrarie to the ſaying of the Apoſtle in this place: Woe to them that preache the Goſpell: and happie are they which preache not the Goſpell, and they are coumpted wiſeſt whiche either holde their peace, or els meddle not with this parte of the Goſpell. But the faithfull Miniſter how ſoeuer he ſeeme to be diſcouraged by ſuche wicked and vnthankfull dealinges of the worlde, yet he is to comforte himſelf in the Lorde, and to feare GOD more then men: It is farre better to diſcharge our dueties faithfully with a good conſcience, although wee procure diſpleaſure of men, then by leauing our duetie vndone, or by doyng the Lordes worke negligently

and vnfaithfully to procure the diſpleaſure and heauie curſe of God.
            The holie Apoſtle hath ſpoken it, woe bee to me it I preache not the Goſpell: And to aunſwere them ſomewhat which blame vs for dealing ſo hardly and openly againſt the ſinnes of the Miniſters. Is it not a parte of diſcretion to reproue their ſinnes whiche doe moſt hurte, and are the cauſes of many other ſinnes: this is that diſcretion whiche was vſed by the holy Prophetes euery where: They crie out againſt the negligence of the Prieſtes, againſt their ignoraunce, careleſneſſe, and leude conuerſation. Amongſt many and infinite places, I referre you that one place in the Prophet Malachie, who dealeth ſo hardly and particularly with the Prieſts, as though all ſinne had been in them. No doubt there were many ſinnes amongſt the people, and yet in all his Propheſie, he ſeemeth to deale ſpecially almoſt onely againſt the Prieſtes, being in deede the cauſes and the authors of the ſinnes of the people: yea, and theſe were ſuche Prieſtes, as were ordeined

of GOD, as were the ſucceſſors of Aaron, and the tipes of Ieſus Chriſte, and yet are ſo ſharply and publiquely reproued by the Prophet. This diſcretion was vſed by Chriſt himſelf.Math. 28.
                     •
                  3. How often times together doeth he pronounce woe againſt the Scribes and Phariſes, calling them Hypocrites, fooles, blind guides, Serpentes, and generation of Uypers: yea, how often times doeth he moſt ſharply and openly rebuke his owne Apoſtles.Marc. 
                     •
                  .
                     •
                  7. 
               Perceiue ye not yet (ſaieth he) neither vnderſtand, haue you your hartes yet hardened? haue you eyes and ſee not, haue ye eares and heare not, and doe ye not remember? Are not theſe my bretheren very hard wordes, and ſuche wordes as are vſed in the Scriptures againſt the very reprobate, and yet the Lorde Ieſus vſeth them againſt his owne Apoſtles.Marc. 16.14. In an other place he reproueth them for their vnbeleefe and hardneſſe of harte. How ſharply doeth the Apoſtle deale in all his Epiſtles againſt falſe Apoſtles: Naye, did he not repoue openly to his face,Gala. 2.
                     ••
                  . 
               Peter the Apoſtle, and his fellowe miniſter,

becauſe he went not the right waie to the truthe of the Goſpell? So that it is not onely lawfull, but alſo neceſſarie, that the ſinnes of all ſtates, and ſpecially of the greateſt, and of the Miniſters bee ſharply and openly reprooued. The holy Apoſtle ſaieth, Them that ſinne openly, rebuke openly, that the reſt alſo maie feare. But are not the ſinnes of our Miniſters open? Is not their ignoraunce apparant? Is not their idleneſſe and careleſneſſe knowne? Doeth not the common ſorte of people ſee it? And are not ſome of them faine to ſeeke for inſtruction in other places? Dooe not many complaine of the liues of the Miniſters? Dooe they not ſaye commonly of them, they ſpeake well and dooe euill? They bee as couetous as others, they haue neuer enough, doe not the people ſee this and a greate deale more? Are not theſe open offenders? Doeth not duetie, diſcretion and charitie binde the Preacher, if he will faithfully preache the Goſpell, to reproue them ſeuerally whiche giue cauſe of ſuche offences? The Apoſtle vſeth

this modeſtie againſt himſelf, Woe be to me if I preach not the Goſpell: which woe ſignifieth no light, ſmall or eaſie matter, but greeuous curſe of GOD in this life, and that fearefull condemnation in the life to come. Can they bee too ſharpely reprooued, or can any ſpeeches bee too harde for them, whiche are ignoraunt and careleſſe in ſo greate a light of the Goſpell, after ſo long profeſſion, whiche ſhoulde bee guides to others, whiche haue ſo many excellent meanes, ſo greate helpes of knowledge, offered to them by the Lorde, in theſe dayes whiche we liue in? Can they bee too muche or to often ſpoken againſt, which are ignoraunt, and will bee ignoraunt, whiche miſtike thoſe that reprooue them, whiche hate all that are not like themſelues, whiche ſeeke to deface the painefull Miniſter, yea, &amp; ſtande in defence of their owne wickedneſſe? Is not this to binde ſinne together with Cart-ropes? Sinne not twiſe, ſaieth the wiſe man, for one ſinne ſhall not be vnpuniſhed, &amp; therefore

take heede in tyme and amende, or els you periſh: Say what you will thinke what you will, the Lorde is my witneſſe I ſpeake the truthe. I knowe I might bee better thought of to paſſe euer ſuche matters, but woe bee to mee if I preache not the Goſpell. But it may bee yet that ſome will ſaye although this bee true that you haue ſpoken, yet all truthe is not to bee ſpoken at all times, in all places, and to all perſones. The Miniſter muſt cut the word of GOD aright: like a wiſe Steward, he muſt giue meate in due ſeaſon. To theſe men I aunſwer, that no neceſſarie truthe is to bee hidden from the Churche of GOD. And to ſpeake more fully and directly to the purpoſe, as touchyng this matter of the neceſſitie of preachyng, of the miſerable eſtate of them that be with out it, and of ſuche Miniſters as preathe not, this matter I ſay in my conſcience, with wiſdome and diſcretion may be ſpoken priuately or openly, where ſoeuer, when ſo euer, and before whom ſoeuer, there is no

place, but it hath need of this doctrin, no time but it requireth it, no perſons that it is not meet for. It is moſt fit and conuenient, moſt profitable and neceſſarye for all ſtates and degrees of men, high and low, rich and poore, ſtrong and weake, learned and vnlearned, Princes, Nobles, Biſhops, Preachers, dumbe Miniſters and people, all haue need of this doctrine. They which haue knowledge, haue need of it, that they may know what they haue beene, that they maye ſee what they are, &amp;c be thankfull to God. The ignorant ſort haue need of this doctrine, that they may feel their miſerable eſtate, and ſo ſeek for help and remedy. Princes, Nobles and gentlemen, haue neede of this doctrine, and it is fit and neceſſary to be preached before them, that knowing the neceſſity and worthines of preaching, they may be more carefull and liberall to maintaine it, and with better conſcience beſtow their liuinges. The learned Biſhops haue neede of this doctrine, it is chiefly to be vrged before

them, and they are continually to remember it, leaſt they lay hands raſhly on any man, and ſo be partakers of other mens ſins. The wiſe and Godly Preachers haue neede of this doctrine, that they may be comforted and ſtirred vp to greater zeal and trauail: ignorant miniſters haue need of this doctrine, that they may ſee the damnable ſtate they ſtande in, and ſo either amende if it will be, or els giue thēſelues to ſome other calling, more fit and profitable for them. Let this doctrine be ſtayed: Let men be perſwaded, as they are of them ſelues that they are in good ſtate without the word preached, that bare reading wil ſerue the tourne, the people waxe careleſſe, and make no account of preaching. For they thinke they are wel inough, and beſt of al without it, the people of God ſhal lack their ſtrēgthening, their growing in faith and knowledge, Princes and Gentlemen wil make no account (as they do but little alreadie) how, or on whom they beſtow their liuinges. The preachers

ſhal be nothing ſet by, the Idol miniſters encouraged: ye famous vniuerſities decated &amp; ouerthrown: &amp; in a word yt concealing, hindring, &amp; withſtāding this doctrine, is the next way to caſt down al religion &amp; learning: to bring princes, nobles, rich &amp; poore, miniſters &amp; people, to hipocriſie and Atheiſme. The lord therfore open ye mouthes of his faithful miniſters, to ye dayly vrging of this ſo neceſſary a doctrine, yt the prince may be ſtrengthened, the Nobles ſtirred vp, all good miniſters encouraged, the poore people inſtructed, ignoraunce &amp; idolatry defaced, religion and knowledge of God, may flowe thorow the whol land, that at ye length, al ignorāt &amp; careles miniſters may be aſhamed, &amp; euery congregatiō may haue a faithful, ſeuerall, &amp; a reſident Paſtor. Thus we haue ſeene at large, yt whoſoeuer wil preach yt Goſpel faithfully and profitably, he muſt firſt of all, &amp; chiefly, vrge the doctrine of repentaunce, which men can neuer haue, before they know their ſins by the law of God, and therefore the ſins

of all men muſte be throughly and ſharply reprooued, and chiefly the ſins of them which do moſt hurt, and giue greateſt occaſion of offence: as the ſin of the magiſtrate and the miniſter. Now indeed to repentance, ther muſt be ioyned alſo the doctrine of remiſſion of ſinnes through Chriſt. But this belongeth onely to them that repent, that are humbled and caſt down, that feele in their conſcience the torment of ſinne and condemnation, to ſuch belongeth remiſſion of ſinnes, to ſuch it is to be offered and preached, but it doth not appertaine to ignorant and ſenceleſſe men, to hipocrites, infidels, Atheiſtes, Iuſticiaries, prophane and carnall men, theſe haue nothing to do with the doctrine of remiſſion of ſins.
            And becauſe this age is altogether ſecure and careleſſe, ful of iniquitie, of ignorance, diſobedience, vnthankfulneſſe, and contempt of the worde, it is vnworthie of the doctrine of mercie, and remiſſion of ſinnes, ſo much the more vnworthy, as the benefites of God in ſo great meaſure, and ſo long

a time haue beene receiued without any profit at all, ſo that in many ther is nothing ſtil, but ignorance and Idolatry, in others leſſe zeal and religion, leſſe godlineſſe of life then was in them many yeares agoe: and are theſe men worthy of mercy? Is remiſſion of ſins to be preached and offered to them, nay the former doctrin of repentaunce, of the lawe of reproouing ſinne, of denouncing the iudgements of God againſt all ſtates and degrees. This part of the Goſpell, I ſay is moſt fit and needful for ſuch an age. And woe be to vs, if we preach not the Gospell.
            
            Conſider alſo, I beſech you here before we goe to an ende, the excellency and worthineſſe of the preaching of the goſpel. It is ſmal accounted of in the worlde, it is thought a vile and a ſimple office, it is contemned and diſpiſed of the moſt part: But if theſe mē knew the ſweet and excellent things contained and offered in the Goſpell, which is the matter of preaching, they woulde alſo know the worthineſſe of

this ſo high a calling, &amp; that the excellēcy therof may more clearly appeare, let vs adde ſome further proofe of this matter. And firſt remember, that this calling of the miniſtery &amp; preaching of ye word, is no deuiſe of any mortall man, but the ordinance of the liuing God.2. Peter. 1. It was he ye ordayned Moſes &amp; the prophetes. The propheſy came not in the old time by the will of man, but holy men of God ſpake as they were mooued by the holy Ghoste.
               Mark. 3.13. The Lorde Ieſus himſelf, called, appointed, &amp; ſent foorth into ye world his Apoſtles to preach ye goſpell:Acts 20. It is the holy ghoſt, which ordaineth faythfull ouerſeers to feede the Church of God.Ephe. 4. It is Chriſte alſo at this day, which appointeth paſtors and teachers, for the gathering together of his ſaints. It muſt needes be a worthy and an honourable calling, which hath ſo worthy authors, euen God him ſelf, his ſonne Chriſt Ieſus, &amp; the holy ghoſt: yea, and not only ſo, but as worthy haue exerciſed &amp; practiſed this calling. The firſt preacher yt euer was in the world was God him

ſelfe, he preached to Adam in paradiſe that comfortable Goſpel, the ſeed of ye woman, ſhall deſtroy the Serpentes head. After that he ſtirred vp Noe, &amp; Lot, Moſes and the prophetes, men of ſingular credite and authoritie. Nay what ſhal I ſpeake of Dauid and Solomon, of the which, the one was a moſt victorious prince, and the other moſt wealthy, &amp; yet they haue gotten more glory and credits, by their doctrines and inſtructions, then by all their riches and triumphes. Theſe are gone and they are gone, but their good coū
               ſel, their prouerbes, their Pſalmes, &amp; Preachings, remaine and abide for euer for their euerlaſting memory, to the glory of God, and dayly profite of his church. The firſt miniſter &amp; preacher of the new Teſtament, was Iohn the Baptiſt, of whom Chriſt our Sauiour ſaith,Mark. 2. there was not a greater Prophet amongſt womens children. Nay Chriſt himſelfe was alſo a preacher of the goſpel, &amp; witneſſeth that he came into the world euen to that purpoſe. After him ye Apoſtles alſo were

ſent into the world, euen to this end. Seing then that God him ſelfe, &amp; his ſonne Chriſte Ieſus, haue vouchſafed to preach the word, ſeeing ſo famous men as the Prophetes and Apoſtles were ordayned to this purpoſe, it muſt needes followe that the office of preaching is moſte famous, worthy and excellent. The worthineſſe alſo of our calling moſt euidently appeareth in the worthineſſe and price of the things committed vnto vs, which is the people of God, the Churche of Chriſt, his dear ſpouſe, the very price of his bloude: It ſo great thinges bee committed to vs. If the Lorde put vs in truſt with ſo deare and precious thinges, our calling muſt néedes bee worthy and notable. Remember the notable effect and fruite of this calling, the winning of ſoules, the conuerſion and ſaluation of the faithful.1. Cor. 1. It pleaſed God by the fooliſhneſſe of preaching to ſaue them that beleeue. And further, the worthy matter of preaching, is both here and other where ſet downe, namely the goſpell,

the word of reconciliation, the worde of grace, the good newes and glad tidinges of ſaluation, the teſtimony of Ieſus Chriſt, repentance and remiſſion of ſinnes. O that al men woulde conſider this, that the glory of Gods miniſtery might appeare. If Princes noble men, and Patrons, would remember this, they would haue more care &amp; conſcience in beſtowing their liuinges, and in defending the good miniſter. Pharaoh,
               Gen. 47.23. king of Egipt in the time of famine, had ſuch a care to prouide for his idolatrous prieſts, yt hee would not ſuffer thē to ſel their land, but gaue thē a ſufficient ordinary to liue vpō. This example of an idolater in prouiding for idolatrous prieſtes ſhal condemn many chriſtian gentlemē, which haue a great deal leſſe care for true &amp; Chriſtian miniſters, which are ſo farre from adding any thing of their owne to their maintainaunce, yt rather daily by deceite or violence, they take that from the Miniſter, which long agoe was giuen by others. Let the papiſt, the Atheiſt and

hipocrite remember and conſider the worthy calling of the miniſter, that laying aſide all contempt, ſkoffing, diſdaine and railing, they mighte in heart, reuerence and honor the Lords ordinance, &amp; let al people remember this that they may chearfully yeelde honor obedience, reuerence and maintainance to the faithful miniſter, remember that his calling is of the Lorde, that he hath to deal with your ſoules, that his purpoſe is to win you to the Lord, that he preacheth no leſſe a thing then the holy goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt. Now theſe things righty conſidered, is he not worthy to be obeied and maintained.Rom. 10. 
               Howe beautifull are the feete of them, that bring the glad tidinges of peace: And reade al which is gone before in the chapter, that you may know that hee which preacheth the goſpel, by right and equity ought to liue of the Goſpel. Let al good Miniſters remember this for their comfort, and inſtruction, that howſoeuer the world thinke of them, they haue a worthye and highe calling,

and let thē not faint, but make their miniſtery fully known, and end their courſe with ioy: and let al ignoraunt and careleſſe miniſters, eſpeciallye remember this doctrine, that ſo they may either amend, or elſe come to ſhame &amp; confuſion. If the Lord be the authour of the miniſtery, the ſoules of the people are committed to vs: If the effect of our calling be to ſaue the ſoules of the people: if wee haue to deal with the goſpell of Chriſte: If ſo famous &amp; notable men haue alwayes beene in this calling, what a man ought ye miniſter to be? what care? what conſcience? what knowledge? what zeale &amp; holy conuerſation is required at his handes? You may ſee &amp; witneſſe with me, I ſpeake nothing to the defacing and diſcredite of the miniſter of God, but rather to his great credite and glory: his calling is moſt worthy and honourable, hee is worthy of double honour, he is to bee obeied &amp; ſufficiently maintained, hee is the ſteward of the Lords houſe, and the meſſenger of the Lorde of hoſtes.

But as the faythfull miniſter is to haue his credit and commendation, ſo the ignorant and careleſſe ſort, as we haue ſufficiently already prooued, are to be caſt down &amp; defaced, becauſe by their ignoraunce, idlenes and lewde conuerſation, they greatly diſhonour the Lord, and deface his glory, I conclude and end with the holy Apoſtle: I beſeech you brethren, that you know them which labor among you, &amp; are ouer you in the Lord, and admoniſh you, that you haue them in ſingular loue for their worke ſake. By the which place, we ſee that ſuch as labor not, admoniſh not, and work not (ſuch I ſay) are not worthy of any loue or honor, but rather to be thruſt out and banniſhed, as vnprofitable mēbers out of ye Church of God. The which ye Lord of the harueſt, graunt for his tender mercies, in Ieſus Chriſte. Amen.
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

