
   
      
         
            The ladies priviledge As it was acted with good allowance at the Cock-pit in Drury-lane, and before their Majesties at White-Hall twice. By their Maiesties Servants. The author Henry Glapthorne.
            Glapthorne, Henry.
         
         
            
               1640
            
         
         Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01775
            STC 11910
            ESTC S103220
            99838977
            99838977
            3370
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01775)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3370)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 925:20)
         
         
            
               
                  The ladies priviledge As it was acted with good allowance at the Cock-pit in Drury-lane, and before their Majesties at White-Hall twice. By their Maiesties Servants. The author Henry Glapthorne.
                  Glapthorne, Henry.
               
               [68] p.   
               
                  By I. Okes, for Francis Constable, and are to be sold at his shops in Kings-street, at the signe of the Goat, and in Westminster-hall,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  1640.
               
               
                  In verse.
                  Signatures: A-H⁴ J² .
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2003-04
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-05
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-06
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2003-06
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-08
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE LADIES Priviledge.
            As it was Acted with good allowance at the Cock-pit in Drury-lane, And before their Majesties at White-Hall twice.
            
               By their MAIESTIES Servants.
            
            The AUTHOR Henry Glapthorne.
            
            Militat omnis amans, et habet sua castra Cupido.
            Imprinted at London by I. Okes, for Francis Constable, and are to be sold at his shops in Kings-street, at the signe of the Goat, and in Westminster-hall. 1640.
         
         
            
            
            To the true Example of Heroicke Vertue, and Favourer of Arts, Sir FREDERICK CORNWALLIS.
            SIR:
            
               YOu are so well acquainted with the Iustice of Nobility, that your owne Fame is your owne History: you are writ in that Sir. Nor need I study to expresse it in a larger Character, since it is texted already in a Volume, time (which is Edaxrerum) cannot exterminate. Thinke not, worthiest Sir, this can in me be flattery; your worth admits none: nor dare I sell my selfe to such a slavery, as to beginne my

service to You with that unmanly prostitution: You have alwayes affoorded me such transcendent favours, that I should descend to ingratitude, should not I study a retribution: which though I cannot reach at, accept Sir, I beseech you, this Essay of gratitude from
            
               
                  Your most obliged honourer, Hen: Glapthorne.
            
         
         
            
            The Persons.
            
               Trivulei, Duke of Genoa.
               Doria, Admirall of Genoa.
               Vitelli, his Friend.
               
               Adorni his Lieutenant.
               
               Bonivet, a Kinsman to Trivulci.
               Lactantio, a Genoese Lord.
               
               Sabelli, Page to Doria.
               Frangipan, nephew to Corimba
               Senators, Officers of State.
               
                  
                     
                        Chrisea,
                        Neeces to Trivulci.
                        
                     
                     
                        Eurione,
                     
                  
               
               Corimba, a Court Matron.
               
               Priest, Executioner, Virgins, Attendants,
            
            The Scene Genoa.
         
         
            
            
               The Prologue.
            
               
                  TIs worth my Feares, to see within this place
               Wits most accomplish'd Senate; tis a grace
               Transcending our desert, tho not our feare,
               Least what our Author writes should not appeare
               Fit for this Iudging presence; all the wayes
               He knowes that lead to the true throne of Playes
               Are rough uneasie pathes, such as to tread
               Would fright an active able Muse; strike dead
               A weake and timerous travailer: for some
               Will gine the play a pitious Martyrdome
               Ere it hath life; yet have t'excite that flame,
               Only distrust in the new Authors name.
               Others for shortnesse force the Author run,
               And end his Play before his Plot be done.
               Some in an humorous squemishnesse will say,
               They only come to heare, not see the Play,
               Others to see it only, there have beene,
               And are good store, that come but to be seene:
               Not see nor heare the Play: How shall we then
               Please the so various appetites of men.
               It starts our Authors confidence, who by me
               Tels you thus much t'excuse the Comedy.
               You shall not here be feasted with the sight
               Of anticke showes; but Actions, such as might
               And have beene reall, and in such a phrase,
               As men should speake in: Ladies if you praise,
               At least allow his language and his plot,
               Your owne just Priviledge, his Muse hath got
               So full a wreath, that spight of Envies frowne
               Shall in his Brow sit as a lasting Crowne.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            The Ladies Priviledge.
            
               Act. 1. Scena. 1.
               
                  
                     Enter Bonivet, Lactantio, and Vitelli.
               
               
                  Bonivet.
                  
                     IS the newes certayne he is arriv'd?
               
               
                  Vit.
                  The Duke
                  Had sure intelligence, that the whole Fleet
                  Anchor'd last night without the Bay: and now
                  For confirmation of it, the thick breath
                  Of his saluting Cannon hangs in Clouds
                  Over the Cittadell, and the glad noyse
                  Of the applauding people, gratulate
                  His entrance to the River.
               
               
                  Bon.
                  The day rose
                  So cheerefully, as if it meant to gild
                  With unaccustom'd light, his sayles swolne big
                  As pregnant mother with the pleasing ayre
                  Of victory.
               
               
                  Lac.
                  The rumour of the Fleet
                  Has fild all Italy with wonder, how
                  So small a number should in open fight
                  Defeat the Turkish Navy; and conclude
                  The Generals skill and valour, the mayne cause
                  Of the atchievement.
               
               
                  Vit.
                  Hee has return'd as large
                  
                     
Assurance of his worth, as when his force
                  Back'd with successive fortune which attends
                  His mighty resolution, over-threw
                  The power of Uenice in a fight; which changed
                  The Sea into a flame, and tooke me in't
                  His fortunate Captive.
               
               
                  Bon.
                  Sir, tis noble in you
                  To acknowledge that as good, which might have bin
                  Your eminent ruine; stately buildings so
                  Rise out of ancient structures which the rage
                  Of eating time, or anger of the windes
                  Had totter'd from the ground works: you may prove
                  As fairely happy in the Generals love,
                  As in the honour which your name or Country
                  Confer'd on your desert.
               
               
                  Vit.
                  You speake the scope
                  Of my intention, a perfect friend
                  Includes both honour, Country, Family,
                  And all that's deare and holy: such a friend
                  As is my Doria, to whose spacious merit
                  Succession shall pay volumes, who was man
                  Ere in the smooth field of his face, rough age
                  Displayd his hairy Ensigne; who has puld
                  Bright honours wreath from her triumphant front
                  In battailes when the trembling Sea being calme
                  Did croud and thrust its waves into a storme
                  To part the dreadfull fury.
               
               
                  Lac.
                  The report
                  Of his Land services do stand on termes
                  Of Competition with the multitude
                  Of his Sea Victories.
               
               
                  Vit.
                  Yet must subscribe
                  To his Navall triumphs: though the Land
                  Has seene him Conquerour, when the bodies flayne
                  Buried the ground they dy'd on, which did shake
                  To view it selfe entomb'd by them, for whom
                  It was ordain'd a Sepulchre, the Drums
                  Were to his eares delightfull as the Lute:
                  
                     
Pikes moving then in Forrest, seem'd as groves
                  Of lofty Cedars stird by sportive winds,
                  And when warres Quiresters, the whistling Fife,
                  And surly Trumpet sung an army dirge,
                  That fatall musicke wraps his sprightfull sence,
                  Like joviall Hymnes at Nuptialls.
               
               
                  Bon.
                  You cannot exceed
                  His praises duty, since his worth containes
                  Ent. Frangipan.
                  Honours most severall attributes.
               
               
                  Lac.
                  Signior Frangipan,
                  
                  What riding post on foot, whither in such haste?
               
               
                  Fran.
                  Very well met gentlemen, I scarce have breath
                  To utter a wise word yet.
               
               
                  Lac.
                  We doe believe you Signior, and are in doubt
                  When you'll have leasure for't.
               
               
                  Fran.
                  Heare you the newes,
                  The General's arriv'd: farewell, he will not land
                  Till I have had the maiden-head of his hand.
                  Exit.
               
               
                  Bon.
                  Tis such another Parrat, he relates
                  Things by tradition, as dogs barke: his newes
                  Still marches in the reare, yet he relates it
                  As confidently, as if each tale he tells,
                  Ent. Doria, Adorni, &amp; Sabelli.
                  As to be straight inserted as an eight
                  To the seven former wonders—But here comes one
                  Will cut off the Fooles Character: renowned Generall
                  Doe us the gratious honour to permit us
                  Salute the hand has sav'd our Country.
               
               
                  Do.
                  Noblest friends,
                  I am more victorious in your earely loves,
                  Than in the Turkish Conquest; though I remaine
                  A Captive to your kindnesse, my Vitelli,
                  
                  The solid earth, or a continued Rocke,
                  May by some strange eruptions of the wind,
                  Be rent, and so divided; but true friends
                  Are adjuncts most inseparable: I have
                  Still worne thee here Vitelli, as a Jewell
                  Fit for no other Cabinet: gentlemen
                  Your welcome hands me thinks we should embrace,
                  
                     
So as ships grapple in hot fight, nor part,
                  Till our affectionate fury has discharg'd
                  Vollies of joyfull courtesie.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  This is fitter ceremony for them
                  Then to embrace an enemy, who will not part
                  On termes so easie; these gentlemen know better
                  To cut a Caper, than a Cable, or board a Pinck in the Burdells, than a Pinace at sea: I marvaile my Lord should know such Milk-sops.
               
               
                  Vit.
                  My Lord,
                  You come t'instruct us Courtship, as y'ave taught
                  Your foes to feare your valour: you appeare
                  As if this were your Nuptiall day, on which
                  You were to wed bright triumph; but you can
                  As well Court peace in silkes, as raging warre
                  In burnish'd steele, and touch the ravishing strings
                  With as much cunning industry as if
                  
                     Mars could like Orpheus strike the trembling Harp▪
                  
                  Signior Adorni welcome home, I hope
                  Y'ave made a richer prize, then when my ship
                  Struck to your mercy.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  Yes, we are very like
                  To make good prize indeed, when all the profit
                  Goes to the State and heavy-headed Burgers,
                  That lye and snort at home, and eate what we
                  Sweat bloody drops for.
               
               
                  Do.
                  Honest Adorni,
                  
                  His bluntnesse must excuse him gentlemen▪
                  
                  How harsh and rough soe're he seemes, his honour
                  Will quickly vary, when I have bin tyr'd
                  With toyle of warre; the observations which
                  His travailes have afforded him of men,
                  Countries, and manners, lively set forth
                  Flourish. Enter Trivulci, Chrisea, Eurione, Corimba.
                  By his expressive action, has begot
                  Mirth in my drowsie soule: when y'are acquainted
                  With his conceit of carriage; you'll not affect
                  A jovialler Companion,—See the Duke
               
               
                  Tri.
                  My noble warriour,
                  Peace now lookes lovely on us, since we enjoy
                  
                     
The author of't in safety: rise my Doria,
                  
                  Let me embrace those youthfull limbes which cloath
                  Warre in loves livery: thy honour'd father,
                  When he return'd laden with Turkish spoyles,
                  As trophies of his valour from the slaughter
                  Of Haly Bassa at Lepanto, where
                  The Christian name was hazzarded, arriv'd not
                  More welcome to the State; beleeve me youth,
                  Hadst thou a mother living, to be proud
                  Of thy Nativity, unlesse she wept
                  For joy to see thee, could no way expresse
                  A more affectionate gladnesse: Chrisea,
                  
                  
                     Eurione welcome him home, who cannot
                  Receive an equall grace to the just value
                  Of his deservings.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  Your grace prepares us for that,
                  We did intend to offer.
               
               
                  Corin.
                  Yes truely did wee sir, this Generall is ill-bred, I warrant him, to slight a gentlewoman of my demeanor.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  My gracious Lord,
                  To tender thanks, where tis a debt, not duty,
                  Befits an equall; subjects ought to offer,
                  With the sincere devotion that our Priests
                  Doe prayers to Heaven, their hearts as sacrifices
                  To their deserving Princes, whose sole favours
                  Doe as the quickning lustre of the Sunne
                  Cherish inferiour spirits: yours have bin
                  Showr'd downe on me as elementall dew
                  On the parcht earth, which drinks it up, and cannot
                  Give heaven a retribution, yet my duty
                  Shall speak my willing thankfulnesse, and while
                  These armes can weild victorious steele, no danger
                  Shal fright me from that service which I owe
                  My Prince and Country: since men are not borne
                  For themselves onely; but their life's a debt
                  To th' Common-wealth that bred 'hem.
               
               
                  Tri.
                  Gentle warriour,
                  Thy fathers spirit swells thy soule, I reade it▪
                  
                  
                     
In thy submissive loyalty; lets in,
                  Tis just that those who caus'd the warres to cease,
                  Flour. Ex. praeter Corim. and Eurione.
                  Should have the early fruits of their owne peace,
               
               
                  Euri. and Corimba.
                  Have you imploy'd a serious diligence yet
                  In giving Lord Vitelli secret notice
                  Of my affection to him?
               
               
                  Corim.
                  Truely Madam,
                  And as I hope to have a husband yet
                  Ere I be fifty, I have beene so ta'ne up
                  About my new device, I scarce have leisure
                  To say my prayers sincerely: Ladybird
                  You looke not sprightly, ravishing, onely this fear
                  Was not well cut, nor well laid on, it wanted
                  A little of my learned art: Vitelli
                  
                  Doubt him not Madam, he shall love you so:
                  Tis pretty neat now; I would not have a Lady
                  That weares a 
                        〈◊〉
                      about her, have the least
                  Pimple in her countenance discompos'd▪ it does
                  Disgallant a whole beauty.
               
               
                  Eur.
                  But Corimba▪
                     
                  
                  What's this to me, thou maist as well tell tales
                  Of love to one departing life, these toyes
                  Relish with me as bitter pills with children,
                  Wilt thou effect my businesse?
               
               
                  Cor.
                  I confesse
                  I have beene very fortunate in bringing
                  Couples together, though I neare could couple
                  My selfe with any, your Ladyship could not
                  Have chose a better agent.
                  Enter Frangipan.
               
               
                  Fran.
                  Save you sweet Lady, save you, Aunt I have
                  Lost all my morning exercise at tennis
                  In seeking you, and yet was still in hazzard▪
                  
                  Whether I should meet you; I must request a little
                  Helpe from your Art good Aunt, a patch, or two,
                  
                     
To make me appeare more lovely; for my glase
                  Tells me I have a very scurvy face
                  Without some ornament.
               
               
                  Cori.
                  Tis a good innocent face, be not asham'd on't;
                  Ile cut out one instantly; nay I never
                  Goe unprovided of materialls let me see,
                  What forme is best for thee; that somthing timerous
                  A heart stuck neatly on thy face, will excite
                  Thy heart to more audacity, good Madam
                  Dost not become him prettily? Cosen be sure
                  You doe commend this fashion to all gentlemen,
                  Wert but as common among them as Ladyes,
                  My wit would be eternally made famous
                  For the invention.
               
               
                  Fran.
                  Wilt please you to dispatch Ant, i'me in hast,
                  I've a whole staple of newes to vent.
               
               
                  Corin.
                  Of what troe?
                  I would have my kind red more ridiculous
                  To th'world than I am; Cosen all your newes
                  Is stale; invent me rather some choice story,
                  How true or false no matter, and declare it
                  For newes, twill please farre better, and endeare
                  Your judgement i'th' relation—
                  Enter Doria, Chrisea, Sabelli.
               
               
                  Fran.
                  Noble Generall y'are happily encountred:
                  Have you seen my Aunt yet Signior; here she is, I have
                  Newes to informe you worth your knowledge.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Keep them
                  Good Signior till some other time: Eurione
                  
                  We must implore your absence, we'd be private.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Why we have beene trusted
                  With as good secrets: please your Lordship
                  Accept this Crescent, you see my Cosen
                  
                     Is in the fashion; let me lay it on,
                  Insooth your face is, for a souldiers,
                  Too smooth, and polite; this device will shew
                  
                     
As't had a skar upon it, which is an honour
                  To faces Military.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Good Madam gravity,
                  Keep your devices for your Chamber Lords,
                  That dance to Ladies shadowes; pray be gone,
                  We need not your society—Sabelli
                  
                  Exeunt.
                  Put to the doore, and then be gone—Chrisea
                  
                  Exit.
                  The modest Turtles which
                  In view of other more lascivious Birds
                  Exchange their innocent loves in timerous sighes,
                  Do when alone most prittily convert
                  Their chirps to billing; and with feather'd armes
                  Encompasse mutually their gawdy neckes.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  You would inferre that we
                  Should in their imitation spend this time
                  Intended for a conference which concernes us
                  Neerer then Complement.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Why my Chrisea,
                  
                  We may entwine as freely, since our loves
                  Are not at age yet to conceive a sinne,
                  Thine being new borne, and mine too young to speake
                  A lawlesse passion, for my services
                  Pay me with pricelesse treasure of a kisse,
                  While from the balmy fountaynes of thy lips
                  Distils a moisture precious as the Dew,
                  The amorous bounty of the morne
                  Casts on the Roses cheeke: what wary distance
                  Do you observe? speake, and enrich my eares
                  With accents more harmonious then the Larks
                  When she sings Hymns to Harvest.
               
               
                  Chri
                  Sure my Lord
                  Y'ave studied Complement; I thought the warre
                  Had taught men resolution, and not language.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Oh you instruct me justly, I should rather
                  Have tane the modest Priviledge of your lip,
                  And then endeavor'd to repay the grace
                  With my extreamest eloquence.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  You mistake me.
               
               
                  
                     
Dor.
                  Remit my ignorance, and let me read
                  The mystery of thy language in thy lookes,
                  In which are lively Characters of love
                  Writ in the polish'd tablets of thy cheekes:
                  Which seeme to vary colours, like the Clouds
                  When they presage a storme; and those bright eyes
                  Dart unaccustom'd beames, which shine as anger
                  Flash'd from their fiery motion.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  You misconster
                  The intention of my lookes, I am not angry
                  Though much distemper'd.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  At what, by whom?
                  Lives there a creature so extreamly bad
                  Dares dis-compose your patience? speake, reveale
                  The monster to me; were he fenc'd with flames,
                  Or lock'd in Bulwarkes of congested yee:
                  And all the feinds stood Centinels to guard
                  The passage, I would force it to his heart,
                  Through which the mounting violence of my rage
                  Should peirce like lightning.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  I beleeve
                  That in some triviall quarrell to redeeme
                  My fame, should scandall touch it, you would fight
                  Perhaps to shew your valour: But I have
                  A taske to enjoyne me, which my feares possesse me,
                  You dare not venture to accept.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  By truth
                  You wrong my faith and courage to suspect me
                  Of so extreame a Cowardize: have I stood the heat
                  Of Battailes till upon the mountainous piles
                  Of slaughter'd Carcasses, the soules which left em
                  Seem'd to ascend to Heaven: that your suspition
                  Should taint my honour with this base revolt?
                  This is not noble in you.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  Doe not rage,
                  When you shall heare it, you will then confesse
                  Your confident errour.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  My loyalty will not
                  
                     
Permit that strong rebellion in my breast,
                  To doubt the meanest falsehood in a word
                  Her voyce can utter, which should charme the world
                  To a beliefe, some Cherubim has left
                  Its roome in heaven, to carroll to the earth
                  Celestiall Anthems, and I now beginne
                  To question my owne frailty; but by all
                  Which we call good or holy, be't your will
                  
                     I should invade inevitable death,
                  
                     In its most ugly horrour, my obedience
                  Shall like a carelesse Pilot cast this bark
                  On that pale rocke of ruine.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  Will you sweare this?
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Yes, invent
                  A forme of oath so binding, that no Law
                  Or power can dispense with: and ile seal
                  With my best blood: pray Madam tell me what
                  The imposition is you judge so easily,
                  Will stagger my just truth, that I may flye
                  On Loves light wings to act it.
               
               
                  Chr.
                  Heare it then, and doe not,
                  As you respect your oath, or love, request
                  The cause of what I shall command.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Still Suspitions:
                  My honour be my witnesse, which no action
                  Shall violate, I will not.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  Enough, that vow
                  Cannot but be materiall, receive it,
                  
                     I must no longer love you.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  That's no command: what did you say Chrisea?
                  
               
               
                  Chr.
                  
                     I must no longer love you, and command you,
                  Leave your affection to me.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Y'are very pleasant Lady.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  You'll finde me very serious: nay more,
                  
                     I love another, and I doe enjoyne you,
                  Since tis a man you may o're-rule, to assist me
                  In my obtaining him, without whose love
                  I'me resolute to perish.
               
               
                  
                     
Dor.
                  Sure I dreame,
                  Or some strange suddaine death has chang'd his frame
                  To immortality; for were I flesh
                  And should heare this, certaine my violent rage
                  Would pull me to some desperate act beyond
                  The reach of fury; these are words would infect
                  Rose-colour'd patience; Cleere and lovely front
                  With loathsome leprosie, change flames to teares
                  And with unusuall harshnesse of the sound
                  Deafen the genius of the world.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  Where's now
                  The strength of soule you boasted, does the noyse
                  Of the death speaking Cannon, not affright
                  Your setled resolution, and the voyce
                  Of a weak woman shake your youthfull blood
                  Into an ague: since you so ill beare this
                  When you shall heare the man, whose love has stolne
                  Your interest, you will rage more than unlimited fire
                  In populous Cities.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Sure tis she who speakes:
                  I doe enjoy yet sound untainted sence,
                  Each faculty does with a peacefull harmony retaine
                  Its proper Organ; yet she did rehearse
                  She must no longer love me: oh that word transformes
                  The soule of quiet into rage,
                  Above distracted madnes: madam tell me,
                  What place is this? for you have led me
                  Into a subtle Labyrinth, where I never
                  Shall have fruition of my former freedome,
                  But like an humble anchorite, that digs
                  With his owne nayles his grave, must live confin'd
                  To the sad maze for ever.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  Sir you cannot
                  By most submissive and continued prayers
                  Reclaime my affection, which stands fixt as Fate
                  Vpon your friend Vitelli.
                  
               
               
                  Dor.
                  My friend Vitelli?
                  
               
               
                  Chri.
                  Sir, I not use
                  
                     
To jest my life away: Vitelli is
                  The person, to obtaine whose pretious love
                  I doe conjure you by all tyes of honour
                  To imploy your utmost diligence.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Can I bee
                  So tame o'th' suddaine? has the feeble spirit
                  Of some degenerate Coward frighted hence
                  My resolution, which has given a Law
                  To fate it selfe, that I must now become
                  The stale to my owne ruine: oh Chrisea,
                  
                  Who wert so good that vertue would have sigh'd
                  At the unwelcome spectacle, had you
                  Appeard but woman in a passion,
                  Though of the slightest consequence: oh doe not
                  Abjure that Saint-like temper, it will be
                  A change hereafter, burdenous to your soule:
                  A sinne to one, who all his life-time blest
                  With peace of conscience, at his dying minute
                  Falls into mortall enmity with heaven,
                  And perishes eternally.
               
               
                  Chr.
                  My will guides my determination, and you must
                  In honour act your promise.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Yes, I will,
                  Since you can urge it tho, but two
                  Things pretious to me, and one cruell word
                  Robs me of both; my friend and her, Chrisea
                  
                  I have not left another sigh to move,
                  Nor teare to beg your pitty.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  They are but vaine,
                  You may as easily thinke to kisse the starres,
                  'Cause they shine on you, as recall my vowes,
                  Which I will urge no further; but wish you
                  Regard your honour: But farewell, I must
                  Be cruell e're, to my owne love unjust.
                  Ex.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  She's gone; what vapour, which the flattering Sunne
                  Attracts to heaven, as to create a starre,
                  And throw it a fading meteor to the earth,
                  Has falne like me: I am not yet growne ripe
                  
                     
For perfect sorrow, but as a bubling brooke,
                  That sports and curles within its flowry Bankes,
                  Till the vast sea devoure it, onely falling
                  Into theabysse of mischiefe; passions surround
                  My intellectuall powers, only my heart,
                  Liketo a rocky Island does advance
                  Above the fo my violence of the flood,
                  Its unmov'd head: love be my carefull guide,
                  Who sailes 'gainst danger both of wind and tide.
                  Ex.
               
            
            
               Actus Secundus.
               
                  Enter Bonivet, Lactantio, and Adorni.
               
               
                  Bon.
                  THanks good Adorni, we are much endeer'd
                  To your relation; this rich corsick wine
                  Erected our dull spirits, and you shall
                  Command our service in as high and jocund
                  A Nature.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  Sir, although I am
                  One that affects not the nice phrase of Court,
                  Having bin nurs'd in warre, yet I can frame
                  My selfe to imitation of what honour
                  Shall there, or any where appeare to be.
                  Worthy my laughter.
               
               
                  Bon.
                  You have explain'd your knowledge, we who breath
                  Onely the aire of Genoa, and ne're tasted
                  Forraigne behaviour, covet nothing more
                  Than certaine knowledge of it, as 'tis proper to
                  Complexions intellectuall to delight.
                  In novelties; your Spaniard as you say,
                  Is of a staid, serious, and haughty garbe:
                  
                     
Acts all his words with shrugs and gestures, kisses
                  His hand away in kindnesse, is of dyet
                  Sparing, will pick his teeth as formally
                  After an Orenge, or a clove of Garlicke,
                  which is his ordinary morsell, as he'd fed
                  On Partridges or Pheasant.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  'Tis his grace
                  After his dinner Sir, and to confirme
                  Their most officious gravity, a Castilian
                  
                  Was for some crime in Paris to be whipt
                  In triumph through the streetes, and being admonished
                  To be more swift of foote, so a voyd
                  The dreadfull lash the sooner, in scorne answer'd,
                  He rather would be flead alive, than breake
                  A Title of his gravity.
               
               
                  La.
                  Much good
                  Doe it his patient shoulders: but Adorni,
                  
                  What thinke you of the French?
                  
               
               
                  Ador.
                  Very ayry people, who participate
                  More fire than earth; yet generally good,
                  And nobly disposition'd, something inclining
                  Ent. Corim.
                  To over-weening fancy—This Lady
                  Tells my remembrance of a Comick scene,
                  I once saw in their Theatre.
               
               
                  Bon.
                  Adde it to
                  Your former courtesies, and expresse it.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  Your entreaty
                  Is a command, if this grave Lady please,
                  To act the Lady I must court.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Why doe you thinke
                  I cannot play the woman? I have plaid a womans part
                  About twenty, twenty yeares agoe in a Court Masque,
                  And tho I say't as well as some o' them, &amp; have bin courted too,
                  But it is truth, I have a foolish quality as many more women are guilty of besides my selfe, I alwayes love them best, which slight me most, and scorne those that doe court mee: look you Signior, if't be a lovers part you are to act:
                  Take a black spot or two, I can furnish you.
                  
                     
'Twill make your face more amorous, and appeare
                  More gracious in your Mistris eyes.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  Stand faire Lady.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Tis your part to stand faire sir: doubt not my carriage—
                  O most rare man: sincerely, I shall love the French
                  
                  The better while I live for this.
                  Ador Acts furiously.
                  Nay pray sir; gentlemen entreat the man
                  To pacifie his wrath, tell him Ile love him,
                  Rather than see him rage thus.
               
               
                  Bon.
                  He would have just reason to be mad indeed then, but now
                  The Mood is alter'd.
                  Ador. acts ut antea.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Excellently ravishing: this is of force
                  To make the hardest hearted Lady love him:
                  Can I intreat him but to teach my Cosen
                  Some of his French, he will for ever be engallanted—
                  Enter Eurione, and Frangipan,
               
               
                  Bon.
                  Beautious Cosen,
                  Y'ave mist the quaintest sport; honest Adorni
                  
                  You would endeare this Lady to you, would you
                  Please to react it.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  Nay, if you make me common once, farewell,
                  I am not for your company.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Pray sir a word or two; here is a gentleman,
                  Nay Nephew, though I say't a toward young man,
                  Vouchsafe him your acquaintance.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  Will he fight, is he souldier?
               
               
                  Cor.
                  No truely sir, nor shall hee bee:
                  I would be loath to have my onely Cosen
                  Heated about the heart with lead; he's dull
                  Enough already: Frangipan come hither,
                  This gentleman will for my sake teach thee French.
                  
               
               
                  Ador.
                  For your sake reverent Madam I shall do't:
                  Sir please you walke, we will conferre on rudiments.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Come with him Coz: Sir, and you have occasion
                  To use me in a pleasure, stands within
                  The ability of my performance, pray command,
                  
                     
You shall not be deny'd.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  Come Signiors, will you walke?
                  Ex.
               
               
                  Eur.
                  Cosen Bonivet,
                  
                  I should be glad, after some minutes, to
                  Enjoy your Company.
               
               
                  Bon.
                  I shall attend your Ladyship.
               
               
                  Eur.
                  
                     Corimba what answer from Vitelli? do I live?
                  Or in the killing rigour of his scorne
                  Must I dye wretched.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Sincerely Madam,
                  You are too timorous of your owne deserts,
                  Or else you durst not doubt, that he, or any
                  You being so neat your selfe, and drest as neatly
                  As any Lady in the Court, should hazzard
                  The reputation of his wit, by slighting
                  Such an accomplish'd beauty.
               
               
                  Eur.
                  You talke,
                  And play the cunning flatterer, to excuse
                  Your negligence; but know affections fire
                  Once kindled by desire, and blowne by thought
                  Into a heat, expires a thousand sighes,
                  Which as loves smoak, like incense flyes to heaven,
                  While the light fire with nimble wings doe soare
                  To its owne spheare, true lovers hearts who cherish
                  The flame, till they to ashes burne, and perish.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Why Ladybird, are you so passionate, the gentleman
                  Is a kind gentleman, has all that may
                  Set forth a man; for when I told him how
                  Like a hurt Deare you wounded were with love,
                  Life how he leapt for joy, as if the selfe
                  Same arrow which struck you, had glanc'd on him,
                  And as a token of his love, hee sent you
                  A bleeding heart in a Cornelion, which
                  Beshrew me, most unfortunately I lost.
                  Enter Chrisea.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  
                     Cornuba see
                  If Generall Doria be within—Eurione
                  
                  Ex. Cor.
                  
                     
I have beene seeking thee, how dost thou sister?
                  I must demand a question that concernes
                  The safety of your fame.
               
               
                  Eur.
                  I rest
                  Secure in mine owne innocence, and no malice
                  Can forge an accusation which can blemish
                  My meanest thought with scandall.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  I beleeve, but know Eurione I am enform'd
                  You doe affect Vitelli, and conjure you
                  By the deare memory of our mother, tell me
                  If the report be certaine.
               
               
                  Eur.
                  Should I deny't,
                  My love would muster thousand blushes up
                  To invade my guilty Cheeks, I must confesse
                  I love him so, as modesty and truth
                  Afford me warrant.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  Tis ill done, and childishly so easily to impart
                  The treasure of your liberty, to keeping
                  Of a neglected stranger.
               
               
                  Eur.
                  His owne worth
                  Deserves as noble knowledge here, as many
                  Who borrow titular glory from the dust
                  Of their forgotten Ancestours.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  You defend him
                  Like a brave Championesse, as if you meant,
                  T'ingage your dearest pawne of life and honour
                  In his protection.
               
               
                  Eur.
                  Say I did, the even'st,
                  Though most strict justice would allow as lawfull
                  My honourable purpose.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  Fie, you are lead on too wildly by your fancy sister,
                  It ill befits the greatnesse of your blood
                  To seeke to mixe its pure streame with a poore
                  Regardlesse River.
               
               
                  Eur.
                  He appeares to me
                  Broad in his owne dimensions as the sea,
                  Cleare as a brooke, whose Christall lips salute
                  Onely the freshest medowes: such a Creature
                  
                     
That were some cunning painter to expresse
                  An Angell cloath'd in humane shape, he might
                  From his derive a patterne.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  But suppose my fancy
                  Should over-sway my judgement, to affect
                  
                     Vitelli; sure your manners would allow me,
                  By willing resignation of your choyce,
                  The priviledge of my birth-right.
               
               
                  Eur.
                  Would you urge
                  A claime so justly mine, because you view'd
                  The light two yeares before me: no Chrisea.
                  
                  Love's an unlimited passion, that admits
                  No Ceremonious difference: this prerogative
                  Should Queenes endevour, their unvalued Dowries
                  Are not of worth to purchase: and tho here
                  As it befits me, I observe the distance
                  Due to your birth; yet in loves sacred Court,
                  My place is high as yours, and there we may
                  Walke hand in hand together.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  Doe not flatter
                  Your fancy with this vaine conceite: Vitelli
                  
                  Must be no more yours; Know I have enjoyn'd
                  The Generall Doria to engage his friend,
                  To imbrace my proffer'd love to him.
               
               
                  Eur.
                  You strive,
                  Because you thinke my young and timerous flame
                  Unapt t'incounter brave Vitellis heat;
                  As cunning Nurses doe with froward Babes,
                  Fright them into an appetite: but say
                  All this were reall, thinke you Doria would
                  So easily be perswaded to renownce
                  His proper interest, and inthrall his friend
                  To an unwilling slavery?
               
               
                  Chri.
                  By truth he has impawn'd his honour to endeavor
                  What I have utter'd, gentle Girle consider
                  Loves unresisted violence, and beleeve
                  I would not have a rivall to usurpe
                  A corner in the Kingdome of that heart
                  
                     
Of which i'me soveraigne, so farewell deere soule,
                  Consider out.
                  Exit.
               
               
                  Eur.
                  Consider out, why this is such an act,
                  Done by a cruell sister, as shall taint
                  That holy name with such a blacke reproach
                  That should a thousand pious Virgins weepe,
                  Rivers of teares, their most immaculate drops
                  Would not wash white her scandall haplesse girle,
                  That in loves tempests wert but lately tost;
                  And now recoverd in a calme art lost,—
                  Enter Lactantis.
               
               
                  Lact.
                  Madam the Duke intreats your instant company.
               
               
                  Eur.
                  
                     I shall attend his pleasure, good Lactantio.
                  
                  If you can meet my Cosen Bonivet,
                  
                  Desire him visite me.
                  Exit.
                  Enter Doria.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Noble Lactantio,
                  
                  Y'are happily encounterd, I expected
                  My friend Vitelli here, this is his houre,
                  
                     I wonder he is tardie.
               
               
                  Lact.
                  Your Lordship prevents the time with speed, or else Vitelli
                  
                  Has some impediment by businesse, sir.
                  Enter Uitelli.
                  Y'are opportunely welcome to deliver
                  Your owne excuse, I was about to stretch
                  My invention for you.
               
               
                  Uit.
                  Noble friend, your enemy had you ingagd your faith
                  To any personall meeting could expect you,
                  But at the minute, reason may dispense
                  Twixt us with such a nicety.
               
               
                  Lact.
                  Now your friends
                  Arriv'd, I must beg licence to depart,
                  I have some vrgent businesse.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Good Lactantio your time's your owne.
               
               
                  Lact.
                  I kisse your Lordships hand.
                  Exit.
               
               
                  Vit.
                  Friend now wee're alone, I safely may
                  Speake my conjecture, I have read your lookes,
                  And in their pensive Characters finde secret,
                  Strange signes of sadnesse.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  
                     I am sad indeed,
                  When my remembrance tells me I have only
                  
                     
Verball assurance of your friendship.
               
               
                  Vit.
                  Try me by any attempt, whose danger does surpasse
                  The common path of daring, beet to snatch,
                  A firy boult when it from heaven comes wrap'd
                  
                     In sheetes of lightning to afford true proofe
                  Of my affection, and with eager haste,
                  Such as inspires a husband to enjoy
                  His spouses virgine purity, ile runne
                  To the atchievement.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  These are but protests; such as be got by ceremony, proceed
                  Not from intensive zeale, yet ile experience
                  The truth of your affection by a triall
                  Of such a noble and effective weight,
                  Which if you bravely doe support, you'l stand
                  As some tall Pyramid or Columne for
                  Your owne memoriall to tell after-times
                  The power and strength of friendship.
               
               
                  Uit.
                  Pray nam't, and 'twere a burden would orepresse the earth,
                  Ile be the able Atlas to sustaine
                  Heaven on my willing shoulders.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  There is a Lady in whose each eye sits fire, &amp; on her cheek
                  Victorious beauty captive to her smiles
                  Dances in lovely triumph, one who emblemes
                  The glory of mortality in each looke,
                  Contracts the orbe of lusture to a glance,
                  Brandishes beames, whose purity dispence,
                  Light more immaculate then the gorgeous east,
                  Weares when the prostrate Indian does adore
                  Its rising brightnesse, yet this wonder doates
                  On you with such inevitable fervor
                  That I in pitty of her sufferings come
                  T'intreate you love her.
               
               
                  Vit.
                  Whom my Lord?
               
               
                  Dor.
                  You cannot appeare so strangely stupid not to acknowledge
                  Creations miracle, when I point out 
                  Her very figure you as well may seeme,
                  When the bleake North does with congealing blasts
                  Binde up the crisling streames in chaines of Ise,
                  
                     
Not to know Winter, ignorant of her
                  Who had she liv'd when superstitious mists
                  Shaded the world, more groves of gammes had fam'd,
                  T'her Divinest beauty, then to all
                  The race of idle deities: tis Chrisea,
                  
                  The faire Chrisea loves you.
               
               
                  Uit.
                  The faire Chrisea, your Lordship's merry.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Doe you slight
                  What I deliver'd with that unfain'd zeale,
                  That penitents doe their prayers, I say, Chrisea,
                  
                  A name whose every accent sweetlier sounds,
                  Then quires of Syrens sence bereaving notes,
                  
                     Chrisea loves you infinitely above
                  Expressive termes; the Orators shoud strive
                  To paint her masculine fancy, and i'me bound
                  To pay this homage to her best content,
                  As to conjure you, by all sacred ties
                  Of honour, amity, and what else may serve
                  To inforce the indeerement with your noblest love
                  To gratifie her fancy.
               
               
                  Vit.
                  No perswasion
                  Can make me thinke this serious, good my Lord,
                  Doe not you love Chrisea?
                  
               
               
                  Dor.
                  More then a babe does the kind Nurse that feedes it with her blood,
                  More then I doe my quiet, or the joyes 
                  Of ought but blest eternity; Uitelli,
                  
                  No other argument can more convince,
                  Suspition should it doubt my love: but this
                  That to procure her peace, I have confinde
                  The greatnesse of my passion, and give up
                  To thy dispose, a Iewell which the earth
                  And sea should both unlade their hidden wealth,
                  Should not have purchas'd from me.
               
               
                  Vit.
                  These are arts to pusle my conceits, my Lord
                  I'me no such punie in the Craft of love,
                  That I want braine to finde this drift, which is
                  As obvious to me as your eyes: now you
                  Are home return'd victorious, big with praise,
                  Laden with titles that sit heavier on you
                  
                     
Then your steele Corslet in hot fight coniemne,
                  Affinity with me, to whom y'ave heard
                  the faire Eurione has resign'd her heart,
                  And by this circumvention should I court
                  At your entreates her sister might pretend
                  A righteous cause, for an unjust revolt,
                  For were it otherwise,, your temper could not
                  Brooke your Chriseas change without a start
                  Into a sudden fury.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  This language I understand not, by my honour friend,
                  This ireration may disperse your doubt,
                  
                     I doe agen conjure you by all right
                  Friendship can challenge in you to affect
                  
                     Chrisea nobly; shall I have your answer?
               
               
                  Vit.
                  Nay then my Lord, since you are serious, freely I resume
                  The priviledge of my liberty; this body
                  I doe confesse your captive, and t'has sufferd
                  an honourable thraldome, but my minde
                  Remaines unbounded as the ayre or fire,
                  Are from their spheares, Eurione has wone
                  By the subduing valor of her lookes,
                  That in a field of fancy, not of blood,
                  And ere another shall usurpe her right,
                  In the defence ile dye her willing martyr.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  
                     I judg'd what serious value
                  your boasted friendship would retaineith test,
                  Draw your bright weapon, know that I doe hate
                  Basenesse as much as cowardice: and since
                  You slight a Lady for whose pricelesse love
                  Kings might resigne their Crownes, and humbly fall
                  Like bare foot pilgrimes prostrate at the shrine
                  Of such a beauty, sure if in this sword,
                  Death has a residence your life shall finde it,
                  And not survive to boast the cruell triumph of her refusall.
               
               
                  Vit.
                  Sir your sword cannot excite a trembling in my blood,
                  The glistring splend our cherishes my sight,
                  Like polish'd Chrystall, henceforth name of friend
                  Be no more known betwixt us then a dreame.
                  
                     
Thus I expire it, I may now regaine
                  My honour forfeited in the Generall cause
                  By this particular Combate.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Should my fate yield me the conquest, yet his death would not
                  Beget Chriseas quiet, but augment
                  Her griefe and hate against me: stay, forbeare,
                  I feele a palsie in my veines, and cannot
                  Manage this little instrument of death,
                  My sinewes put on infancy agen
                  And have no vigor in them, oh Vitelli,
                  
                  I am so full of passion, I have scarce
                  Roome left to vent a sigh, a mine of lead
                  Hangs on my heart, and with its weight has crack'd
                  The feeble courage.
               
               
                  Vit.
                  Noble soule, his griefe
                  Workes more compunction in me, than his sword
                  Did suddaine anger; could I grant what you
                  Request, no brand-markt slave should fulfill
                  Sooner his Masters most severe command,
                  Than I would yours; but this abrogates all lawes
                  Of friendships duty: ify'ave vowd this act,
                  You may as safely disanull the Oath,
                  As should you in some desperate fury sweare
                  To be your fathers murtherer.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Bid me first renounce
                  My allegeance to my honour, sell my faith
                  I owe my Native Country: my Vitelli
                  
                  I feele an humour in my braine, which strives
                  For passage at mine eyes, wilt see me weepe?
                  Consider friend, denying my request
                  Thou dost undoe a Lady, who may claime
                  The priviledge of all hearts: depriv'st the world
                  Of such a jemme, that should old nature strive
                  To frame her second, it would quite ex haust
                  Her glorious treasury, then in her ruine:
                  My life and honour's forfeited, think this,
                  And were thy heart obdurate as a rocke
                  Of Adamant, this thought joyn'd with my teares
                  
                     
Would sooner than the blood of Goats dissolve it
                  To gentle softnesse.
               
               
                  Vit.
                  Your eyes are moving advocates, they speake
                  Such an o're-flowing Language, that my love
                  Then in its owne cause a most partiall Judge,
                  Allowes my mercy freedome to pronounce
                  Sentence on your side: you have prevail'd,
                  Ile serve Chrisea, as her pleasure shall
                  Dispose my will and fortune.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  I beginne to feele my spirits quicken, and my blood
                  Receive its noble temper; deare Vitelli,
                  
                  Thy noblenesse does prompt thee to an act
                  Shall write thy friendship higher in the lists
                  Of sacred amity, than mothers loves.
                  Goe to my best Chrisea, she expects
                  To know by thee the truth of my successe,
                  Tell her I am more happy in her blisse,
                  Than if I had enjoy'd her constant love:
                  So leave me love, I may perhaps transgresse
                  Man-hood agen, and shouldst thou see me weepe
                  Twice, thou wouldst judge my former flood of teares
                  A feigned passion.
               
               
                  Vit.
                  Your Genius guard you; thus I apply
                  Balme to his wounds, while I doe bleeding dye.
                  Ex.
                  Enter Bonivet.
               
               
                  Bon.
                  Noble Generall, I come to gratulate the happy choyse
                  Y'ave made in faire Chrisea; she's a Lady,
                  That though she were a stranger to my blood,
                  My judgement would allow as rich a vertue
                  As ever glorifi'd the sexe.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  'Twould be a sacrilegious errour not to admit
                  Your Character for truth, but in our loves
                  A thousand hidden causes doe produce
                  Alternate changes, my returne has setled
                  My thoughts on new resolves, and I must suite
                  My affections to them.
               
               
                  
                     
Bon.
                  How? perhaps because
                  You are return'd triumphant with your bayes,
                  Growing upon your brow, you doe reject
                  The love before you su'd for, tis not noble
                  So to abase a Lady, whose bright fame,
                  Although untainted as a Christall rocke,
                  Must passe a popular censure, if you, who
                  Did with such earnestnesse pretend her match
                  Should on the suddaine scorne it.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  I'me not bound
                  To give you reasons why; but know my mind,
                  Which your contesting cannot alter's fixt
                  On what I have related.
               
               
                  Bon.
                  I must then tell you
                  You doe defame the opinion of that worth
                  The world does credit in you: this affront,
                  Should all her other friends sit idle gazers
                  On her disgrace, should stirre me to attempt
                  An ample satisfaction from your heart,
                  Though you had multitudes of greater glories
                  Heap'd on your head, or were defenc'd with legions
                  To affright me from the adventure.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Sir, your courage is juster than your quarrell, doe you think
                  
                     I weare a sword onely for ornament;
                  And though our yeares declare us equalls, yet
                  My education was i'th' trade of warre.
                  Tis my profession to infranchise soules
                  From prisons of their flesh, and would be loath
                  Cause you have interest in Chriseas blood,
                  Your passion should betray you to the fury
                  Of my incensed wrath.
               
               
                  Bon.
                  All discourse is tedious to me, sure the world's abus'd
                  With report of your valour, men who commit
                  Affronts they dare not answer, use excuse
                  
                     In moderation of them, I expected
                  
                     I should have met an adversary of you,
                  Of temper hot as lightning, and as bold
                  As Lyons vext with hunger, and I finde you
                  
                     
A tame dege nerate Coward:
               
               
                  Dor.
                  All respect of love and pitty hence:
                  sight.
                  Beare up, my steele
                  Has prickt your breast; I would not have you dye
                  
                     Chriseas Martyr.
               
               
                  Bon.
                  I've puld untimely ruine on mee, I'me hurt,
                  I feare to mortall danger: Noble Generall,
                  See me conducted to Lactantios house,
                  There I shall get a Surgeon.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Noble young man,
                  Muster thy strongest spirits up: I am one
                  Of Fortunes pastimes; yesterday return'd,
                  Advanc'd to heaven by the peoples breath,
                  To day hurl'd downe into the abysse of death.
                  Ex.
               
            
            
               Actus Tertius.
               
                  Enter Chrisea, and Corimba.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  CAme none yet from the Generall?
               
               
                  Cor.
                  No insooth Madam; I protest your sister
                  If she continue in these suddaine fits,
                  Will so undoe her face, that all my art
                  Can never rectifi't; shee weepes, as if
                  She might as easily be supply'd with eyes
                  As with new dressings, ile be sworne, I tooke
                  As hearty paines to cut a handsome heart;
                  And though I say't it was a pretty one
                  As e're was made of Taffaty, to grace her Check,
                  And never trust me if I lye to you,
                  Her teares has wash'd her heart away.
               
               
                  Chr.
                  Th'art still
                  
                     
In these impertinent discourses: what's the cause
                  My sister is so prodigall of her griefe,
                  To let thee see her vent it?
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Why Madam, I have seene a Lady weepe,
                  Besides your sister, and have wept my selfe too,
                  I never shall forget the time; I could
                  Een cry agen to thinke on't; twas at the death
                  Of your fine little Iewell: never Lady
                  Nurst such a dainty puppy, but hee's gone,
                  And farewell he; I will not give a rush
                  For any woman cannot use her eyes
                  With as much liberty as her tongue, these fooles,
                  These loving Ideots men for three forc'd drops
                  Will mollifie like wax, and be made apt
                  For any impression.
                  Enter Vitelli.
               
               
                  Chr.
                  
                     Vitelli you are wellcome, I suppose
                  Your businesse has been urgent, we expected
                  Your presence sooner, howsoever now
                  Tis grateful hither.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  My young Lady shall
                  Have notice of's arrivall, perhaps his sight
                  Will cheere her drooping spirits.
                  Ex.
               
               
                  Vit.
                  Madam, my friend
                  The Generall, does by me tender his best
                  and truest service to you, he has sent me
                  Prompt, to fulfill the nicest poynt of duty
                  Your pleasure casts upon me.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  Sir, the Generall is so just in his proceeding, I must ever
                  Esteeme him truely Noble, though I should
                  Banish him my affection.
               
               
                  Vit.
                  I could wish
                  The sweetnesse of your vertue would vouchsafe
                  To lay a reclamation of your love:
                  Had you but seene with what ambitious haste,
                  With what extreame perswasions he endeavour'd
                  
                     
The satisfaction of your will, you could not.
                  Fancy a change from one so worthy.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  No? not to enjoy your selfe?
               
               
                  Vit.
                  Me Madam;
                  No equall eye can parallell my poore
                  Regardlesse merit, with the glorious worth
                  Which does as farre transcend mine in desert,
                  As't does in eminence of fortune.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  Sir your modesty
                  Extenuates your owne worthinesse, to bestow
                  A large addition on your friends, my judgement
                  Has ballanc'd both, and has concluded which
                  Ought to be held most noble, I doe honour
                  True constancy in men, pray tell me sir,
                  For it concernes me neerely, did you ever.
                  Fervently love my sister?
               
               
                  Vit.
                  To include,
                  (All strength of humane zeale) as Doria does adore
                  Your excellent beauty, with a heat
                  Holy as soules in deonest fancy
                  Their sainted fellowes.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  And can you extinguish
                  So great a flame so easily, can entreates,
                  So soone subdue your temper? if your truth
                  Be of this wavering quality, how shall I
                  Receive assurance of it?
               
               
                  Vit.
                  The vow
                  I made, my friend secures it, thinke not Madam
                  That both my parents with perswasive prayers,
                  Could have enforc'd me violate my faith
                  To faire Eurione, but when my friend,
                  My honor'd friend to whom I owe my life,
                  As tenant to his, bounty did in teares,
                  A souldiers teares whose every drop prevailes.
                  More then a captive princesse, plead the losse.
                  Of his owne life, my gratitude did vanquish
                  Passion, and forc'd me tear even from my soule
                  
                     Euriones affection.
               
               
                  
                     
Chri.
                  You are just
                  In your determination.
                  Enter Eurione.
               
               
                  Vit.
                  Blesse me friendship,
                  And with thy white wings overshade my heart,
                  Or here descends a Saint will dispossesse thee
                  Of the accustom'd shrine, a barke enclos'd,
                  Twixt two encountring tides is not more tost
                  Then I twixt striving passions, while a friend,
                  I cannot be a lover.
               
               
                  Eur.
                  
                     Uitelli am I in your opinion lost? my sister
                  Relates so sad a wonder, that if truth,
                  I am undone for ever.
               
               
                  Vit.
                  Harke she speakes too,
                  A tempting language; such was our first mothers voyce,
                  While she was innocent, deeere Ladies would
                  I could divide my selfe, for being one,
                  I cannot on the Theater of my minde,
                  Act both a friend and lover, that two names
                  Of so intire affinity should occasion
                  So manifest a dissension, in a soule
                  That would be true, yet is inforc'd, though loath,
                  To forfeit one, or to be false to both.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  My expectation did not
                  Sage this softnesse in you, I had thought
                  You had come furnish'd with a full resolve
                  To act your friends request.
               
               
                  Vit.
                  Yet I must needs
                  Speake in a cause so moving; Madam thinke
                  How much more noble tis in you to save,
                  Then to destroy; behold three bleeding hearts
                  Imploring pitty from you, mine, your sisters,
                  And your adorer Dorias, which one word
                  Of yours would ransome from approaching death,
                  Oh be not sparing of that breath, 'twill sound
                  In the just eares of heaven more sweet then prayers
                  Offerd by Cloyster'd virgins, of resume
                  Your native charity, and fulfill my suite,
                  And in requitall of that sacred grant.
                  
                     
Time shall depend like summer on your brow,
                  And your whole life be one continued youth.
                  Such were the springs in Paradise, and when
                  You passe to be a sharer in heavens blisse,
                  Virgins and innocent lovers spotlesse teares,
                  Hardned to pearle by the stronge heare of finger,
                  Shall be your monument.
               
               
                  Chr.
                  This whole discourse
                  Should you inlarge it to a volumne, cannot
                  Alter my meanest thought, I only wish you
                  As you are noble to respect your honour;
                  That's all my answer.
                  Exit.
               
               
                  Eur.
                  But doe you meane
                  
                     Uitelli, to performe what Doria has enjoyn'd you.
               
               
                  Uit.
                  
                     I shall melt
                  Into a willing pitty, if the flame
                  Of friendship did not with its effectuall heat,
                  Dry up loves moysturer deere Madam he
                  That has commanded me this deathfull taske,
                  Claimes such a lawfull Interest in my life,
                  That spight of my affection, I must-yield
                  To his resistlesse will: yet I will love you
                  So far as honour gives me warrant, and
                  Wish you the best of women, the best joyes
                  Happinesse can impart to you, farewell,
                  'Tis a befitting gratitude to give
                  That life a being; by whose guift I live.
                  Exit.
               
               
                  Eur.
                  sorrowes flow high; griefe unto griefe succeed,
                  Wounds are more dangerous which doe inward bleed.
                  Exit.
                  Enter Adorni, and Frangipan.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  Come let not this dishearten you, your French
                  Is a thing easily gotten, and when you have it,
                  As hard to shake it off, runnes in your blood,
                  As 't were your mother language, but there is
                  An observation farre more necessary
                  T'improve your judgement, still let your discourse
                  
                     
Concerne the forraigne businesse, and be sure
                  To applaud out-landish fashions, and take off from
                  What is native, as if you shall heare
                  Any commend the Genoa garbe, or state
                  Answer in France, in Naples, or in Spaine,
                  
                  No Matter where, so it be farre enough.
                  From hence, they are more politicke, more witty;
                  Every way more deserving, this will speake
                  Infinitely judicious, when to praise
                  Our owne domesticke manners, is as if
                  A man should praise himselfe, and be accounted
                  A selfe conceited gul for't.
               
               
                  Fran.
                  Very good, this is a rule Ile put in practice I,
                  Thanks to my inclination can speake ill
                  Of my owne father signior.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  Signior; still, you betray your igorance, why signior,
                  Mounsiuer has a farre more airy and harmonious sound,
                  There's musicke in the letters, still polish your phrase
                  With particles of language, which till I've taught you
                  Perfectly answer with a shrug or nod,
                  Or any forraigne gesture, such a silence
                  Will be esteem'd for gravity, and become you better
                  Then volubility of speech does some
                  Whose tongues are gentlemen ushers to their wits,
                  Still going before it, and when you doe speake,
                  Let it not be, as now you doe of newes
                  Abroach ten daies before, and quite drunke of;
                  But what affaires are acted then in France,
                  
                  What in the English Court; and still remember
                  T'extoll 'hem infinitely, and if any answer
                  Comparatively with our owne a serious laughter,
                  Will not become you ill, to shew how much
                  You slight their error.
               
               
                  Fran.
                  Better still, I like this slighting humour infinitely, but how
                  If they should talke of our Italian dames, 
                  I'me bound to be their Champion, for I've heard
                  Strangers report, and I hold their opinion,
                  Our Curtezans excell all other Nations.
               
               
                  
                     
Ador.
                  That shew'd those strangers judgements, and confirm'd
                  What I would have you understand in England,
                  
                  Where publicke houses are prohibited:
                  There are the bravest Lasses, there some Donsella
                  
                  That was the last night yours, shall for two Ducats
                  To morrow be a Saylers: when there
                  Your Citizens wives, girles fresh as ayre, and wholsome
                  As pretious Candy wives will meet their Gamsters,
                  At a convenient Taverne, rob their husbands
                  Without a scruple, and supply their friends,
                  While the good innocent Cuckolds pay a price
                  For their owne horning.
               
               
                  Fran.
                  Excellent, excellent
                  
                     Genoa, I doe defie thy costive girles,
                  Ile henceforth love these English sparkes of gold:
                  Would I were there: it should goe hard but I
                  Would graft on their Aldermens Coxecombs.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  Th'are grafted fast already sir, besides
                  They ne're get Children, but their Hench boyes on
                  Their Sergeants wives, after some City feast,
                  When the provoking spirit of White broath, and
                  Custard enflames their blood: what Genoa Burgesse
                  Da res be so boldly courag'd: Ile tell you,
                  And marke how base and fordid it appeares
                  To have our Cellers stuff'd with Corsike Wines:
                  Yet for this foolish sinne cald Temperance,
                  Tantalize, and nere taste it, while your Dutch,
                  Your noble-spirited German will carrouse
                  A score of Goblets to provoke this stomacke
                  To's bread and Butter; doe nothing but by discreete
                  Counsell of drinke, not match his daughter to
                  A man he sees not drunke first, scarce say's prayers
                  Till he be full of liquor, which enflames
                  The minde to generous actions.
               
               
                  Fran.
                  Commend 'hem, and will be glad to imitate.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  Your English
                  Deserves as large applause, who to say truth,
                  Out-drinks the Dutch, as is the common proverb,
                  
                     
The Dutch-man drinks his buttons off, the English
                  Doublet and all away, then marke their carriage:
                  If two fall out and strike, and be by company
                  Parted; though one weares in his face the badge
                  Of his dishonour, which excites him to
                  As brave revenge, not daunts him: for he'll straight
                  Call out his enemy to a single Duell,
                  Scorning his life; concerning the Lands lawes,
                  Which doe forbid those combats, and ne're part
                  Till one be slaine, and the survivour sure
                  As death to hang for't.
               
               
                  Fran.
                  Excellent, I love a man that cares not for hanging.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  Then to their further glory, which takes off
                  All the disgrace of halter, they are sure
                  Ere they be scarce cold, to be Chronicled
                  In excellent new Ballads, which being sung
                  Ith' streets 'mong boyes and girles, Colliers, and Carmen,
                  Are bought as great memorialls of their fames,
                  Which to perpetuate, they are commonly stuck up
                  With as great triumph in the tipling houses,
                  As they were scutchions.
               
               
                  Fran.
                  Better: yet I'de give
                  A hundred Ducats to be chronicled
                  In such a historicall Canto: who composes them?
               
               
                  Ador.
                  They have their speciall Poets for that purpos
                  Such as still drinke small Beere, and so are apt
                  To spit out lamentable stuffe: then for their cloathes
                  They hate a cut domesticke, but imitate
                  The French precisely gallants, weare their long
                  Parisian Breeches, with five poynts at knees,
                  Whose tagges concurring with their harmonious spurres
                  Afford rare musicke; then have they Doublets
                  So short ith' waste, they seeme as 'twere begot
                  Vpon their Doublets by their Cloakes, which to save stuffe
                  Are but a yeares growth longer than their skirts;
                  And all this magazine of device is furnish'd
                  By your French Tayler: what Country man is yours?
               
               
                  Fran.
                  A Genoese.
                  
               
               
                  
                     
Ador.
                  Fie, change him Monsieur,
                  You have heard a Spanish Count's
                  Lately arriv'd, without any advice, hou'd you salute him?
               
               
                  Fran.
                  Thus sir, after our Italian fashion.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  That's too vulgar;
                  You must accost him thus with a state face,
                  As if your beard had beene turn'd up that morning
                  By advice of all the Barbers in the City,
                  As you had drest you in a Looking-glasse,
                  Proper to none but the Dukes privy Counsellors:
                  Pronounce your Besolos manas with a grace,
                  As if you were the sonne and heire, apparant
                  To th'Adelantado of Castile.
                  
                  Enter Lactantio.
               
               
                  Lact.
                  
                     Adorni, this is no time for mirth,
                  Your noble General has slain Lord Bonivet,
                  
                  And for the act is a prisoner.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  Dares the state bereave him of his liberty,
                  Without whose most unwearied valour,
                  It had beene betray'd to slavery?
               
               
                  Lac.
                  You know Lord Bonivets alliance to the Duke.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  Allyance, death a thousand Bonivets,
                  
                  And Dukes and States, weigh not
                  A scruple poys'd with his full worth.
               
               
                  Lac.
                  He's to be tryed ith'morning without noyse,
                  For feare of mutiny, and tis suppos'd
                  That if some virgin Lady doe not claime
                  Her priviledge, and begge his life, he'll suffer.
               
               
                  Fran.
                  If the maid that begges must be above fifteene,
                  Tis shrewdly doubted where she'll be found.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  All our virgins ought, if they have vertue, to contend
                  For such a glory; but if all be squeamish,
                  May all the daughters of our best Burgers runne
                  Away with souldiers, and become Sutlers wives.
               
               
                  Fran.
                  Or else when they have a masculine itch upon 'hem,
                  And would taste man, may they be wed to Eunuchs.
               
               
                  
                     
Lact.
                  else be forc'd to keepe their maiden-heads
                  Till they be musty and not marchantable
                  To younger brothers with additions of wealthy portions.
               
               
                  Fran.
                  May they when they would strive to mend their faces to allure a suitor, want paint and blacke-patches to stoppe the Crannies of their Cheekes; may their Pomatum bee mixt with Hogs-grease, that they may be abominable even in the nose of Iewes: may the green-sicknesse raigne in their bloods, and may they be debar'd of oate meale, and clay-wall, and fall to Ratsbauc.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  May their parents turne most precise precisians,
                  And forbid em the sight of playes, or they may never
                  Dance unlesse be to a bag-pipe or a Crowd.
               
               
                  Fran.
                  May they want silkes for gownes, and if they seeke
                  Supply from Naples, let them insteed, be furnish'd
                  With their Disease; may Millaners breake and Feather-men,
                  May my Aunt dye suddenly, and bury with her
                  All her devises; may there be no Earth
                  Found to make looking-glasses, that they come to use of
                  Kitchen-wenches, dresse their heads by the reflexion of a
                  Paile of water, or in a pewter chamber vessell.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  
                     Lactantio, let's go wayte the Generall
                  In prison, 'twould be base should we neglect him in
                  His extremity.
                  Exeunt.
                  
                     Enter Doria, and Sabelli.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Is it confirm'd hee's dead?
               
               
                  Sab.
                  The generall voyce
                  Divulges so ith'City; and the Duke
                  Has sent an order which commands you forth
                  I'th morning to your tryall: my deare Lord
                  I hope the service you have done the State
                  Abroad, will here at home secure your life
                  From the Lawes violent Rigour.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Yes poore boy,
                  If thou mightst be thy masters judge Sabelli,
                  
                  
                     I am at the period of my fate, and would not
                  Have thee a sad spectator of my fall
                  At home, whom thou so oft hast waited on
                  
                     
Abroad in triumph, therefore gentle heart,
                  Returne home to thy mother, and survive
                  To serve a happier master.
               
               
                  Sab.
                  My noble Lord
                  Have I so often followed you, when death
                  Attended on each step, when every hurt
                  That scar'd your noble body, I have wish'd
                  Imprinted on my flesh, and with my teares,
                  Even drown'd the purple deluge of your wounds,
                  That as my truth and loyalties reward,
                  I must be turn'd a way unkindly, when
                  My last and just est service might declare
                  My zeale to you my master; Oh sir,
                  You more afflict my innocence with these words,
                  Then if sad truth had brought me the report
                  Of my owne mothers sunerall, and should you
                  Enforce me leave you, the succeeding care,
                  And labour of my life should be consum'd
                  In a perpetuall weeping.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Good Sabelli
                  
                  Cease this afflicting language, lest I grow as
                  Childish as thy selfe, and burst into teares
                  To beare thee company.
               
               
                  Sab.
                  Besides my Lord,
                  When your blest soule does on immortall wings
                  Arrive at heaven who shall attend it there, the
                  Saints and Angels will esteeme themselves
                  Worthy to be your fellowes, while my poore
                  And humble Ghost would reckon it a blisse
                  To waite on you, as carefully as when
                  We liv'd on earth together, deere my Lord,
                  Let me dy with you, death and I have beene
                  Play-fellowes these many yeares, he'l only bring me
                  To rest as pleasing to my sence as sleepe
                  After a tedious watching.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  This kinde passion shakes my
                  Most masculine temper; heere Sabelli
                  
                  Accept this Gold, these Iewells, as the lest
                  
                     
Gift of thy perishing Lord, thou shalt accept 'em;
                  If the law doe not passe upon my life,
                  Ile send for thee agen, I prethee leave me,
                  I would be private, and thy presence does
                  Disturbe my serious thoughts.
               
               
                  Sab.
                  Nay then tis time for
                  Me thewretched'st soule on earth to take
                  My lasting farewell of you; all the joyes
                  Of blest eternity in stead of my
                  Desertlesse service; waite upon your life;
                  You ne're shall view your boy agen, for sure if your
                  Light be extinguish'd, my weake flame
                  Cannot continue burning; give me licence
                  To kisse your honour'd hand, and to let fall
                  A parting drop or two: and now farewell
                  For ever noble Lord; that greefe appeares most true,
                  That's writ in blood as well as teares.
                  Exit.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Poore boy; I have not yet deserv'd so ill
                  But my untimely fate excites some pitty.
                  Enter Adorni, Lactantio, and Frangipan.
                  
                     Adorni thou art come to see the last
                  And greatest of thy Generalls actions,
                  Which like a cunning and well mannag'd scene,
                  not till the period will disclose the plot
                  Or my lifes Tragedy.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  Your life my Lord;
                  Death dare not venture to invade it, and
                  The state as soone will call the enemy
                  Into their City, as pretend the least
                  Danger to their supporting Columne, which
                  Should it but shake, it might dismantle their
                  Best Bulwarkes, burne their Navy, and surrender
                  Themselves to present slavery.
               
               
                  Lact.
                  The Duke,
                  Though he did hold his kinsman deere, will value
                  The publique good before his private ruine.
               
               
                  Fran.
                  Let the Duke doe his worst, and all the state
                  Stand on Pontilios, I can fetch a Lady
                  Of excellent quality shall beg your Lordship,
                  
                     
Ile make her doo't.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  Nay, should all fayle you sir,
                  Should the States angers, and the Dukes partiall-sentence,
                  The peoples malice bandy to surprize
                  The treasure of your life; know you have friends
                  Would fixe the heads of halfe the Towne upon
                  Their Lances poynts, ere your least drop of blood
                  Should be diminished.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Gentlemen, I thank you
                  All your loves; but know the shape of Death
                  Is not ougly to me, but if justice
                  Contract me to the monster, I shall court it
                  As 'twere some beauteous Bride; and think the Axe
                  That like the Priest, unites me to a Spouse
                  That will not play the woman and revolt.
                  Come Gentle-men let's in, brave soules doe hate,
                  To be dejected by the force of Fate.
                  Exeunt.
               
            
            
               Actus Quartus.
               
                  Enter Chrisa, Enrione, Vitelli.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  I Am very sorry that his Fate has cast
                  Such a disastrous chance upon his Life:
                  But his desert will blunt the edge of justice,
                  And mitigate the severity, which would
                  Question the safety of his Life.
               
               
                  Vit.
                  'Tis in your mercy
                  To dash the Lawes proceedings, gracious Madam,
                  The Priviledge that our Country gives your Sexe,
                  Can hope for no imployment, that will rayse
                  A greater Trophee to your fame, then this
                  To ransome him, whose constancy and truth
                  Exceeds all boast of Stories.
               
               
                  Enr.
                  You'l redeeme
                  The opinion of your piety, which scandall,
                  Should you omit this just and righteous taske,
                  Would blast with blackest infamy.
               
               
                  
                     
Chri.
                  You plead in your owne cause, not his, t' does not beseem
                  My modesty to interpose my selfe
                  In that which nought concernes me.
               
               
                  Uit.
                  Is his life
                  Of such a triviall value in your thouglits,
                  That you esteem't not worthy your intreats,
                  To sav't from killing, ruine, sacred love,
                  Thou miracle of Mature, and delight
                  Of all who know humanity with some
                  Religious arrow pierce her flinty breast,
                  Some pious shaft, on whose subduing point
                  Pitty and amorous softnesse gently sit,
                  Reduce this straying Schismaticke to the first
                  Vnspotted purenesse of her constant faith,
                  And we will pay a thousand clouds of sighes,
                  As incense to thy Altars.
               
               
                  Eur.
                  Offer up
                  Miriads of virgin vowes and with our teares
                  Extinguish all irregular flames that taint
                  Thy holy fries.
               
               
                  Uit.
                  Oh Madam
                  What heart so barbarous, does not at loves smiles
                  Put off the native fiercenesse, beasts with beasts,
                  Observe his lawes; the Lyons whose big breath
                  Affrights the trembling people of the woods,
                  Were his hoarse accents to be understood,
                  They would appeare to be affections groves.
                  The Nightingale that on lascivious wings
                  Flies from the poplar to the trembling Beech,
                  And on each bough chaunts melancholy notes,
                  Had hea humane utterance, would proclaime
                  Those pensive straines, the musicke of his love;
                  And can yee be lesse sensible of a power,
                  That is so great, then creatures bard the use
                  Of sacred reason, and discourse?
               
               
                  Chri.
                  This is to seeke to pacifie the sea
                  With teares; Vitelli you mistake, your friend
                  Values not at so deere a rate his life,
                  
                     
As to receive a being tributary
                  To my unask'd entreats, besides I should
                  Envy the states prerogative, whose mercy
                  Is in remitting his unwilling fault,
                  But a becomming thankfulnesse, and should
                  Be censur'd, as too partiall to my owne
                  Affection should I strive to be his wife,
                  Whose hand is purpled with the innocent blood
                  Of my late murdered kinsman.
               
               
                  Eur.
                  This concernes
                  As neerely me as you, but by just truth,
                  Though I'me ingag'd by my particular choyce
                  To my Vitelli, were I sure the Generall
                  Would not contemne my offer, and so blast
                  My future fame, I would disclaime all eyes
                  Of former fancy; and implore his safety.
               
               
                  Vit.
                  This is a sweetnesse
                  Which I cold wish you, what has begot
                  This strange desertion of your faith, true love,
                  Being once receiv'd into the soule converts
                  Into its very essence, does become
                  The same eternall substance, can you then
                  Teare from the tender Cabinet of your brest
                  Your very heart? this cruelty exceeds
                  The depth of tyranny, but est assur'd,
                  If Doria suffer by your proud contempt,
                  I'me freed then from my promise, and will sooner
                  Warme an empoysoning Scorpion in my armes,
                  Then yeeld my meanest thought to you who are
                  By evident circumstance, though not by fact,
                  My friend the Generalls murdresse.
               
               
                  Chri
                  This Vitelli
                  
                  Is not a meanes to winne me to your friend,
                  But more avert me from him, it inflames
                  My minde with holier fire to Court your love;
                  There is an evident beauty in your soule,
                  Equall to truest honor, I will cherish
                  This bravery in you, if your masculine fancy
                  
                     
Engages you thus constant, to a friend,
                  You'l be a loyall husband, fare you well,
                  Be still thus noble, and be happy.
                  Exit.
               
               
                  Eur.
                  My sister
                  Has lost all sence of pitty; deere Vitelli,
                  
                  There is no wretchednesse oppressing earth
                  Equall to ours, love thus the Tyrant playes,
                  Afflicting innocence by unusuall waies.
                  Exeunt.
                  Enter Doria as a prisoner, Lactantio, Adorni, to them Trivulci, Senators, Officers, and Attendants.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  Tis like your selfe my noble Lord, but see
                  The Duke approaching, let your soule expect
                  An equall hearing.
               
               
                  Offic.
                  Beare backe, roome for the Duke and Senate, what
                  Cuckold's that would have his Coxcombe broake? beare backe there.
               
               
                  Triv.
                  Cite in the prisoner.
               
               
                  Offic.
                  Hee's here my Lord.
               
               
                  Tri.
                  I'me sorry that
                  You for whose head the gratitude of the state
                  Decreed triumphant bayes should be enforc'd
                  To stand here a delinquent, but the law
                  Must as a streight and uncorrupted streame
                  Enjoy its usuall freedome, my Lords,
                  We are not met here to arraigne a prisoner,
                  Whose guilt does speake his sentence, but a person
                  Not only most unblemish'd in his fame,
                  But one to whom our country owes its life:
                  Who with his dearest blood has balm'd the wounds
                  Which michiefes giant-off-springs, raysing warre,
                  Cut in the bosome of the common-wealth.
               
               
                  Sen.
                  We all confesse his worth.
               
               
                  Tri.
                  Yet this brave youth,
                  This patron of our liberty, all his honours,
                  His blood and titles, his defensive bayes
                  
                     
(That would have guarded his victorious front
                  From blasts of lightning) laid aside, is come
                  To tender satisfaction to the lawes,
                  He has offended, and since judgement is
                  The immediate act of Justice, it must passe
                  To save impartiall censure on his life,
                  As on the wretched'st malefactors; for
                  His former merits cannot take away
                  His present fault; for who ere is guilty
                  Vndoes the priviledge of his desert and blood;
                  For if great men offending passe unpunish'd,
                  The common people who doe use to sinne,
                  By their example fearelesse, will runne on
                  Into licencious wickednesse.
               
               
                  Sen.
                  Your grace delivers
                  The intension of the state, no oracle
                  Could have explain'd the meaning of our lawes
                  With more integrity.
               
               
                  Tri.
                  Yet my good Lords,
                  I speake not this, that my particular vengeance,
                  Because slew he my kinsman, has the least
                  Ayme at his life, which I would strive to cherish
                  As my owne health, or as the Cities peace,
                  For Magistrates ought to behold their crimes,
                  Not the committers, as the Poets faine
                  Of wise Tyresias, to want eyes, and only
                  Have seeing understanding, for a judge
                  Is guilty of the fault he does not punish,
                  And if rewards and triumphs doe adorne
                  Deserts tis just that shame and punishments
                  Should wait on vices, and how much more worthy
                  The person is that acts them, so farre sharper
                  Should be the penalty inflicted on him.
               
               
                  Sen.
                  And when the law
                  Vses its utmost rigor, tis the crime,
                  And not the man it sentences.
               
               
                  Tri.
                  In briefe We must
                  Decline his merit, and forget
                  
                     
Our gratitude, and since his hand is dipt
                  In civill blood, his life must expiat what
                  His arme unfortunately committed.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  My Lords,
                  The services which I have done the state,
                  Were but my naturall duty, I atchieved 'em
                  To gaine me fame and glory, and you safety, and
                  Should esteeme them Traytors to honour, if their intercession
                  Be a protection for my crimes, I meane not
                  To plead to save a dis-respected life,
                  Cause I feare death, a sea incompass'd rocke
                  Is not lesse timerous of the assaulting waves,
                  Then I of the grimme monster, but there is
                  A fame surviving which I would be loath,
                  Should tell posterity I tamely yeelded
                  My head to th' Axe, and dyed because my spirit
                  Durst not desire to live to quit this scandall,
                  I hope what I can urge in my defence
                  Shall have indifferent hearing.
               
               
                  Tri.
                  Speake freely.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Know then my intention
                  Is not by excuse to extenuate my fact,
                  Which I confesse most horrid, and woud I pay
                  A thousand showers of sorrow, could this hand
                  Reedifie that goodly from of flesh
                  Which it demolisht, but my pricelesse fame,
                  In whose deere cause I slew him, will to justice
                  Boldly proclaime, I did no more then what
                  The truth I owe my reputation tells me,
                  Was right in poynt of honor.
               
               
                  Tri.
                  But the law
                  Does disallow it as unjust, and that
                  Must be your judge, and not that idle breath
                  Which you abusively terme honor.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Your lawes cannot without partiality pronounce
                  Iudgement against me, for they doo acquit
                  That man of guilt that to defend his life
                  Is forc'd to slay his enemy; my act
                  
                     
Carries the same condition, since my fame,
                  Whose safety urg'd me to kill him, is my life,
                  My immortall life, as farre transcending this
                  As the soule does the body, for the sword,
                  Returnes that to its primitive matter dust,
                  And there it rests forgotten, but a wound
                  Strucke upon reputation, leaves a brand,
                  So selfe diffusive is dishonors guilt,
                  Even to posterity, and does revive
                  After t'has sufferd martyrdome.
               
               
                  Sen.
                  Yet this
                  Cannot excuse your fact, for civill reason
                  Allowes a reparation for the losse
                  Of fame, but gives no man a lawfull licence
                  To snatch the priviledge from the hands of justice,
                  Which would dispose it equally.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  This strictnesse destroyes all
                  Right of manhood, since a coward
                  May fearefully relying on this sufferage
                  Of Law affront even valors selfe, consider
                  That the most cunning Pilot cannot steere mans
                  Brittle vessell 'twixt these dangerous Rocks
                  Of law and honor safely, sayle by this,
                  And on that suffer ship wracke, for suppose
                  I had with patience borne this scandalous name
                  Of a degenerate coward, I not only had
                  Nip'd the budding valor of my youth,
                  As with a killing frost, but left a shame inherent
                  To our family, disgrac'd
                  My noble fathers memory, defam'd
                  Nay cowarded my Ancestors, whose dust,
                  Would 'a broke through the Marbles, to revenge
                  To me this fatall infamy.
               
               
                  Ador
                  Well urg'd, and resolutely.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Nay more, your selves
                  That hate the deed being done; would have detested
                  The doer worse had it not beene perform'd
                  Withdrawne my chardge ith' army; as from one
                  
                     
Protested for a coward, I might then
                  Have abjur'd the trade of warre, in which I have beene nurs'd,
                  Yet for preserving this unvalued jemme
                  Of pretious honour that hangs on my soule,
                  Like a well polish'd Iewell in the care,
                  Of the exactest beauty, must I suffer
                  The lawes sterne rigor.
               
               
                  Tri.
                  Sir I should refute
                  With circumstance your wrong opinion, but in briefe,
                  Religious conscience, utterly disclaimes
                  An act so barbarous to take mans life,
                  Is to destroy Heavens Image, and if those
                  Are held as Traytors, and the law inflicts
                  Severest tortures on them, who deface
                  The stamps of Princes in their coyne, can they appeare,
                  As guiltlesse whose rude hands disgrace
                  The great Creators Image, and commit
                  Treason 'gainst awfull nature; Oh my Lord
                  Collect your serious temper, and put off
                  The over weening fantasies of youth,
                  Consider what a vaine deluding breath
                  Is reputation, if compar'd with life.
                  Thinke that an idle, or detracting word
                  May by a faire submission (which our lawes
                  Of honor doe require it will enforce)
                  Be wash'd away, but the red guilt of blood
                  Sticks as a blacke infection to the soule,
                  That like an Aethiop cannot be wash'd white,
                  A shout within. Enter Corimba and Frangipan.
                  Thinke upon this, and know I must with griefe
                  pronounce your fatall sentence.—
               
               
                  Fran.
                  Doe you heare Generall, Ile tell you newes, you were in
                  Ieopardy to have had your little weason slit; but I pronounce
                  The happy word, be safe; his peece of beauty,
                  By my perswasions does intend to take
                  The edge of law off, and become your wife,
                  True and inseparable.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  With reverence to this presence, my good Lords,
                  Know that I come not urg'd by heate of youth.
               
               
                  
                     
Fran.
                  Tis true Ile beare her witnesse.
               
               
                  Cor
                  Or any wanton or unchast desire
                  To beg this gentleman for my husband, neither
                  To raise my selfe a fortune by the match,
                  But mov'd in charity, and provok'd in minde,
                  With pitty to behold a man so proper,
                  Brought to an end untimely, by a death
                  So scandalous to honour as the Axe,
                  I come to crave our priviledge, and desire him
                  For my most lawfull husband.
               
               
                  Tri.
                  Gentle mayd
                  Your piety does prompt you to an act
                  That shall engage your country to erect
                  A statue to your memory, though I could not
                  Dispence with justice, yet since there's a meanes
                  Without the lawes infringement, to preserve him,
                  
                     I doe rejoyce as much as if my sonne
                  Had scap'd apparant danger: goe on and prosper
                  In your designe.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Doe you thinke because I pleaded
                  For my honours life,
                  I doate so much upon this idle breath,
                  As to preserv't with infamy, dispose
                  This womanish priviledge to submissive slaves,
                  Know that I hate a being that depends
                  Upon anothers bounty more then death,
                  At which my soule does, like an Eagle stretch its
                  Silver wines, and ore the monsters head
                  Will make flight at heaven; pray sit proceed
                  To judgement suddenly, delay begets
                  More tortors in me then your sentence.
               
               
                  Gor.
                  What doe you meane sir, pray let me understand you Better, looke upon me, I am no woman to be slighted.
               
               
                  Fra.
                  She's not asham'd to shew her face, marry her Uncle, that I may call you so.
               
               
                  Sen.
                  To wed this figure, is a farre greater punishment then Death.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  Nere stand on tearmes, but marry her, and free your

selfe, and trust to me, you shall not want a mistresse has better colours in her face.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Corimba,
                  I'me much engag'd to your officious haste,
                  And pay you many thankes, conceive not that
                  I doe contemne your person or dislike
                  The meannesse of your match, for were your beauty
                  Created for a miracle, and adon'd
                  With the addition of a fortune ampler,
                  Then that perfection, I should crave a licence
                  To tell your modesty I am prepar'd
                  Rather for death then Nuptialls, and no strength
                  Of prayers and beauty, shall have power to tempt me
                  From my fixt resolution.
               
               
                  Tri.
                  This is madnesse not courage Doria.
                  
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Sir I must tell you, you know not how to use a woman rightly,
                  Perhaps tis bashfulnesse, take courage sir,
                  I have reserv'd my deere virginity
                  This fifty yeares for such a pious purpose,
                  And should you slight me now, I should forswear
                  Good purposes hereafter: gentlemen perswade him,
                  Sure he cannot chuse but melt
                  At your entreaties.
               
               
                  Tri
                  Will you then pull your ruine on; that seeks
                  Recorders. Enter Uitelli, and Sabelli, as a Lady. Virgins.
                  Thus easily to flye from you; Iustice calls
                  On me to give your sentence—new interruptions
                  It is the voyce of musicke, and presages
                  An Omen as harmonious as its notes,
                  Approach faire troops of Virgins, here's subject,
                  Fit for your maiden pity.
               
               
                  Cor.
                  Tis time for mee to take my farewell, these may bee beauties, perhaps my Lady may bee one, adiew sir; you may be offer'd worse.
                  Ex. Cor, and Fran.
               
               
                  Sab.
                  My honour'd Lord,
                  The charity I owe my native country,
                  That in the ruine of this brave young man,
                  Would suffer infinitly, has forc'd us strive
                  With earely zeale first to presentour duties
                  
                     
For his redemption, 'mong ten thousand Virgins
                  That would attempt it, and my true affection
                  Has wonne this favour from my fellowes, that
                  To me they yield their interest, which I claime
                  As my desir'd prerogative.
               
               
                  Tre.
                  Tis an act the State will thanke you for; unvaile your selfe,
                  That we may know to whom we owe our gratitude,
                  A most excelling beauty, such an eye
                  Would tempt religious coldnesse to a flame,
                  Thaw Ages chilly frost, at such a cheeke
                  The Spring might take a patterne to create,
                  A most accomplish'd freshnesse; in her looks,
                  Are modest signes of innocence, such as Saints
                  Weare in their liveliest counterfeits: Doria, here
                  A Lady begs you, whom if you refuse,
                  The times would blacke you with the hatefull title
                  Of your owne wilfull murther; take her to you
                  And live a fortunate husband.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Noble maid, my misery is so extreame a sinne,
                  It cannot meet your bounty without breach
                  Of vowes; which should I violate, would pull
                  Eternall torments on me; keep your beauty
                  For one whose soule, free as the ayre he breaths,
                  Can yield a mutuall fancy to your flame,
                  And not destroy his honour, for your goodnesse
                  Since my expir'd date, cannot yield you thanks
                  Worthy the bound lesse merit of your love,
                  If there can be a gratitude after death
                  Express'd by prayers, my soule in heaven shall pay it
                  To your kind charity.
               
               
                  Sab.
                  Oh my Lord,
                  I did expect this answer, my poore worth
                  Cannot deserve your value; yet there is
                  A constant purity in my thoughts, that intend you
                  So much of Blisse, that had your safety no
                  Dependance on my suit, it would be deem'd
                  Most cruell to contemne me, I have lov'd you
                  These many yeares; wish'd you as many glories
                  
                     
As I have number'd dayes, have vow'd I never
                  Will marry any man, but your blest selfe my Lord,
                  Should you neglect the justnesse of my request,
                  Besides the danger waiting on your life,
                  A thousand Virgins, whose unspotted prayers
                  Like hosts of guardian Angels, would have borne
                  You on their wings to heaven, will for my sake
                  Convert their zeale to curses, and in teares
                  Of anguish drowne your memory.
               
               
                  Vit.
                  Why friend, this is
                  Such an o're-weening passion, as does question
                  The soundnesse of your judgement, fills the world
                  With a conceit you dye; because your feares
                  Dare not accept of life: Besides your Mistris,
                  To whom you would so strictly keepe your faith,
                  Does so much scorne your constancy, that no
                  Entreats could move her pitty undertake
                  This honourable imployment.
               
               
                  Tri.
                  Doe it with speedy diligence.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Her causelesse frailty
                  Shall more confirme my truth:
                  My Noble Lord pronounce
                  My happy sentence, 'twill be welcome to me
                  Enter Priest &amp; Executioner.
                  As charming harmony, and swell my brest
                  With more than humane pleasure.
               
               
                  Tri
                  Are you come? approach,
                  Behold this Executioner, and this Priest,
                  This is to wed you to destruction, that
                  To this rich Mine of purity: your choyse
                  May accept either: if you fixe on this,
                  Besides your owne redemption, you enjoy
                  A Lady, who may clayme as many hearts
                  As she has vertuous thoughts; but leane to that,
                  Your Spring returnes unpittyed, to the rude
                  Armes of perpetuall winter, that will freeze you
                  To a ne're melting isicle, be suddaine,
                  And wise in your election.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Tis but vaine: a Saint may sooner be o're-come to sell
                  His native Piety: come thou grim man,
                  
                     
Thou art to me more lovely then the face of perfect
                  Beauty: Do thy office, it will free me
                  From these perplexities.
               
               
                  Sab.
                  Well my Lord,
                  Since I'me unworthy to enjoy in life
                  Your faire society, my soule shall hast
                  To waite on you to death, there is no blisse
                  Without your presence, since you will not have
                  Mercy on your owne life, by your example
                  Ile be as harsh to mine, Ile goe
                  Before you to the other world,
                  And be your lov'd Ghosts Harbenger.
               
               
                  Tri.
                  Hold, hold the Lady—
               
               
                  Sab.
                  Let no hand presume to seize me,
                  For the meanest touch that shall
                  Endeavour to prevent my will
                  Shall urge my speedier ruine: Good my Lord,
                  Shall I have answer? I would fayne be going
                  On my long journy.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  I'me confounded
                  In my imagination, I must yield,
                  You have enforc'd a benefit upon me, I
                  Can hardly thank you for, yet I will try
                  To love you as my wife; that I were lost
                  In Clouds of black forgetfulnesse.
               
               
                  Tri.
                  My Lord,
                  Your pardon's seal'd as soone as by the Priest
                  You are conjoyn'd in marriage:
                  Ile not leave you
                  Till't be solemniz'd, Hymen light thy Pine,
                  Deaths tapers fade at the cleare flame of thine.
                  Exeunt.
               
               The end of the fourth Act.
            
            
               
               Actus Quintus.
               
                  Enter Trivulci, Doria, Sabelli, Adorni, Priest and Uirgins.
               
               
                  Tri.
                  IS the Priest prepar'd
                  For his Hymne after Nuptialls, and the virgins
                  Ready to gratulate the Bride, and Bridegroome
                  With the appoynted dance?
               
               
                  Ador.
                  The Priest I thinke
                  Has the song perfect, but it is a question
                  Among the wisest, whether in the City
                  There be seven Virgins to be found to furnish
                  Recorders.
                  The dance as't should be; but you must accept them
                  With all their faults; this musicke speaks their enterance.
                  Enter Virgins.
               
               
                  Song.
                  TRiumph appeare, Hymen invites
                  Thee to wait upon this feast,
                  Mixe thy joyes with his delights,
                  'Tis the Generall is chiefe guest.
                  Bid the Drumme not leave to teach,
                  The Souldiers fainting heart to beate,
                  Nor warres loud musicke Canon cease,
                  Breasts with deathfull fire to heate.
                  
                     
Thy waving Ensignes in the aire display,
                  The Generall lives, tis triumphes Holyday;
                  Come bright vertues that reside
                  In heaven, as in your proper spheare,
                  Though all contain'd in the faire bride,
                  Chastity doe thou first appear,
                  With Temperance and innocent grace,
                  Rose-colourd Modesty and truth,
                  Dance harmlesse measures in this place,
                  With health, and a perpetuall youth:
                  And all your Virgin Trophies bring away,
                  To grace these Nuptialls, Triumphs Holyday.
               
               
                  A Dance.
               
               
                  Tri.
                  You have our hearty thanks, and we shal study
                  To give you faire requitall; come my Lord
                  Erect your drowsie spirits, let your soule,
                  Dance ayry measures in your jocund breast;
                  This is a day on which each Bridegroome ought
                  To weare no earth about him; ayre and fire
                  Are Hymens proper elements, your mirth
                  Ought to infuse into your frolicke guests,
                  An humour apt for revelling and sport:
                  Your disposition is more dull, than if
                  You were to be chiefe mout'ner at a Coarse:
                  For shame shake off this sadnesse.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  It becomes you to say truth scurvily, I doe not like it,
                  You looke as if y'ad lost some victorie,
                  Of which your hope had an assurance: Shall I tell your Lordship
                  A very pleasant story?
                  Enter Vitelli.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  It must be, if it be delightfull to me, a discourse
                  Of some quicke meanes to free me from this cruell
                  Oppressive weight of flesh, which does entombe
                  My martyr'd soule, that like to sulphury fire
                  Hid in a Mountains entrayles, strives to burst
                  The prison, and flye upwards; it must needs
                  
                     
Be a sad wedding, when the Bridegroome weares
                  His Nuptiall livery on his eyes in teares.
               
               
                  Vit.
                  Friend, this is
                  A passion too effeminate for a heart
                  Endu'd with manly courage; things past helpe
                  Should be past thought, your sadnesse casts a Cloud
                  Upon the lustre of this Ladyes looks,
                  You make her dimme the brightnesse of her eyes
                  With unbecomming teares, if you continue
                  This strange distraction.
               
               
                  Sab.
                  Alas my Lord,
                  Let me participate your cause of sorrow,
                  And be a willing partner in your griefe,
                  Which like a violent Current that o're-flowes
                  The neighbouring fields and medowes in its rage,
                  Into two streames divided, smoothly runnes,
                  Kissing with calme lips the imprisoning banks,
                  Would, though too mighty for you, when my soule
                  Should vent a part of it, be milde, and passe
                  Away without disturbance of your peace,
                  Which to procure I would even burst my heart
                  With sighes devoted to your quiet, and
                  Become a loving fountaine by my teares
                  I shed without intermission.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Gentle Lady,
                  I am at such an enmity with fate,
                  Makes me incapable of ought but griefe,
                  But I shall study to declare how much
                  Enter Eurione, Chrisea, Corim. Lact. &amp; Bon.
                  I am indebted to your care—good heaven
                  Send downe some Angell to protect my heart,
                  Or my religion will scarce stay my hand,
                  For acting wilfull violence on my life,
                  I have suckt poyson from her eyes, that will
                  Like to juyce of Hemlocke drowne my soule
                  In a forgetfull Lethargy, or oppresse
                  My temperate faculties with madnesse.
               
               
                  Tri.
                  Cosen y'are welcome, know this vertuous Lady
                  
                     
Who has redeem'd the Generall.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  Sir, ime come to gratulate your beauteous bride, and wish you joyes immortall.
               
               
                  Sab.
                  I hope Madam, my innocence has gi'n you no offence,
                  That you refuse me, being a stranger to you,
                  The Ceremonious wishes, which pertaine
                  To new made Brides, and onely doe conferre them
                  Vpon my Lord.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  Your happinesse already,
                  Is so superlative, I cannot thinke
                  A new addition to it, you enjoy
                  The very summe of fortune in your match,
                  To such a noble and illustrious husband.
                  I no longer can hold my passion in,
                  These walls of flesh are not of
                  Strength sufficient to contayne
                  My big swolne heart: My Lords behold a creature
                  So infinitely wretched, I deserve not
                  The meanest shew of pitty, who have, like
                  A silly merchant, trifled away a jemme,
                  The darling of the quarry, lost a love
                  By my too foolish nicenesse, to regaine
                  Whose forfeiture I would lay downe my life:
                  But he is gone for ever, and I left
                  A pittious spectacle for the reproach
                  And scorne of wiser women.
               
               
                  Eur.
                  Is this possible?
                  Was all her passion to Vitelli seign'd?
                  My hopes recover life agen.
               
               
                  Tri.
                  Why Chrisea,
                  
                  Whence springs this passionate fury?
               
               
                  Chri.
                  Oh my Lord,
                  When you shall heare it, you will sigh for me,
                  And shed a charitable teare, at thought
                  Of my unkinde disaster: sir my Justice
                  Cannot accuse your constancy, which stood
                  In the first tryall of your love, as fast
                  
                     
And spotlesse as an Alablaster rocke,
                  That had it but persisted in that height
                  Of honourable loyalty, your glory
                  Had been advanc'd to heaven, as the fix't starre,
                  To guid all lovers through the rough
                  Seas of affection.
               
               
                  Uit.
                  This taxation
                  Cannot be just from you, who did enforce
                  The sad revolt upon him.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  
                     Is there in heaven no friendly
                  Boult left that will strike this frame into
                  The center, and set free a wretch
                  (So overgrowne with misery) from life,
                  That death would be a comfort above health,
                  Or any worldly blessing, may time blot my name out
                  Of his Booke, that such a Prodigy
                  May not affright succession, nor sticke
                  Like an orespreading Leprosie upon
                  The beautious face of manhood.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  Oh my Lord, each griefe of which
                  Y'are sensible, is mine, and not your
                  Torment, every sigh you breath is an
                  Afflicting motion, expir'd by my vext
                  Spirit, and if you could weepe, each drop
                  Would be my blood, who am the spring
                  Of the whole flood of sorrow; oh forgive
                  The too exceeding honor of my love, I would
                  Have had you for your perfect truth so glorious;
                  Your loyalty should not for
                  Preservation of your fame, have needed
                  To adopt a statue for its heire, or builded a
                  Monumentall pyramid, but love
                  Is ofttimes loves undoing.
               
               
                  Tri.
                  This is such
                  A cunning la byrin of,
                  Sorrow, that no clew
                  Can lead them out of.
               
               
                  
                     
Dor.
                  It would be
                  A great affront to misery, should there live
                  A person halfe so wretched to out-dare
                  The strength of my affliction, me thinkes
                  
                     I me like some aged mountaine that has stood
                  In the seas watry bosome, thousand shocks
                  Of threatning tempests, yet by th' flattering waves,
                  That cling and curle about his stony limbes,
                  Is undermind and ruind, I have scap'd
                  Warres, killing, dangers, and by peacefull love,
                  Suffer a strange subversion, Oh Chrisea,
                  
                  While I have reason left that can distinguish
                  Things with a coole and undistracted sence,
                  Let's argue mildly the unhappy cause
                  Of our undoings.
               
               
                  Eur.
                  Truely sister,
                  'Twas a suspicious rashnesse, I could wish
                  You never had attempted.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  My Lord,
                  Humane condition alwaies censures things
                  By their event, my aimes have had successe
                  So strangely haplesse, that will blast the truth
                  Of their intentions purity, I never
                  Harbor'd the least suspicion of your faith,
                  Which I did strive to perfect, by the test,
                  As richest gold refind, and purg'd
                  From drosse of other baser metals, and besides
                  The triall of your constancy, I meant
                  To sound Vitellies depth; upon whose love
                  My sister doted, so that I was loath
                  To see her cast the treasure of her heart
                  Upon a stranger, of whose constancy
                  She had too small assurance.
               
               
                  Tri.
                  Gentle Cosen,
                  Your good intents encounter'd bad successe,
                  But I ad mire, since you must needs have notice
                  Of his disaster, that the law would passe
                  
                     
Upon his life, you did not to prevent
                  All other virgin intercessors haste
                  To pay the early tribute of your love.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  My wretched fate
                  With a too quicke prevention has orethrowne
                  The justnesse of my purpose,
                  
                     I relyed so much upon his noblenesse, I thought
                  The ugly horror of a thousand deaths
                  Could not have mov'd his temper, and besides,
                  Knowing his mighty courage, I permitted
                  The law proceed upon him, that hereafter
                  He might be sure no merit can appeare
                  Offended justice, otherwise I could
                  Easily have stop'd this mischiefe.
                  Enter Bonivet.
               
               
                  Tri.
                  How Chrisea? I understand you not.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  Lady, to quit all scruple that I doe not wish
                  Yours and your Lords succeeding happinesse, Ile offer
                  Something as an oblation that shall ad de
                  Peace to your nuptiall garland (see my Lord)
                  My Cosen Bonivet lives.
               
               
                  Tri.
                  Lives? Lactantio did not you informe us
                  That he was dead, and you had caus'd his body
                  To be prepar'd for funerall? which occasioned
                  The Generalls suddaine tryall, because our custome
                  Does not permit the corpes to be entomb'd,
                  Before the murderer have his sentence, sir you shall know
                  What tis to mocke the state thus.
               
               
                  Lact.
                  Good my Lord
                  Heare but my just excuse, I am so much the faire
                  
                     Chriseas beauty's by such ties
                  Oblig'd to serve her, that I choose to hazzard
                  The anger of the state ere her displeasure,
                  And doe submit me to your gracious censure.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  I must confirm't,
                  Sir it was I who caus'd him to conceale
                  My Cosen Bonivet, for the causes which
                  I did declare before, and now my selfe
                  
                     
Having receiv'd a satisfying proofe
                  Of his affection, came resolv'd to cleare
                  These misty errors, but my cruell fate
                  Has like a suddaine storme which has beate downe
                  A goodly field of standing Corne even ripe
                  For the laborious sickle, crush'd my hopes
                  In one sad minute into nothing.
               
               
                  Sab.
                  My Lord I owe
                  Such an obedient duty to your peace,
                  That though my heart does wish to waite on yours
                  For ever; since I see betwixt this Lady
                  And you such firme apparences of love,
                  If the law please to allow it, I resigne
                  My interest to her and be fortunate
                  To see you two live happy.
               
               
                  Vit.
                  Since the marriage
                  Has not arriv'd to consummating act,
                  I doe beleeve this may be done.
               
               
                  Tri.
                  Doe not delude
                  Your favour with vaine hopes, the law cannot
                  Dispense with the strict Cannon, tis impossible
                  You should be separated.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  This happinesse
                  Was too extreamely good to be confirm'd
                  To such a wretch as I am: I am like
                  One that did dreame of a huge masse of wealth,
                  And catching at it, grasp'd the fleeting ayre,
                  And waking grieves at the delusion.
               
               
                  Sab.
                  Sir resume your antient quiet, the formall
                  Love shall not oppose your peace, Ile disanull
                  The marriage easily, and most noble Lord
                  Pardon your humble servant.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Sure this is
                  Some apparition to confirme my faith,
                  Speake, art thou my Sabelli.
                  
               
               
                  Vit.
                  Yes tis he, fate would not suffer two such
                  Noble soules to be so disunited, gentle boy,
                  
                     
Thy duty to thy Master will continue,
                  Thy name in story, as the great example
                  Of loyalty in servants.
               
               
                  Sab.
                  'Twas the zeale I ought in duty to my Mrs. life,
                  Hath put me on the attempt, which if he pardon,
                  I'me fully satisfied.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  My joyes does with a suddain extasie oppresse
                  My fraile mortality, and I should sinke,
                  Wert not for my supporters, my Sabelli,
                  
                  Thou hast restor'd two lovers to their blisse,
                  Whose gratitude shall pay to thy desert
                  The tribute of their hearts: Deare Madam, now
                  I hope your scrupulous doubts will remaine free
                  From any new suspition.
               
               
                  Chri.
                  Since I have scap'd the danger past, beleeve ile avoyd
                  The like hereafter; my Lord please you confirme
                  My choyse; and let my sister be dispos'd
                  To good Vitelli, he deserves her.
               
               
                  Tri.
                  Your wishes are fulfild, Cosen Bonivet welcome to life
                  Agen; you and the Generall must be friends.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  Your goodnesse will pardon my misfortune?
               
               
                  Bon.
                  And desire to be esteem'd your servant.
                  Enter Frangipan.
               
               
                  Fran.
                  With your leave gentlemen: Madam I have such newes to tell you, as will tickle your understanding, to beleeve the Generall is married; and more, Signior Doria, Lord Bonivet lives; That's lucky newes for you.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  He's here, good Signior Frangipan.
                  
               
               
                  Fran.
                  My newes has ever the worst lucke; I must resolve to leave it off.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  But sir J have somesuddaine newes to tell you:
                  The thousand Ducats you contracted to pay me,
                  When you could understand the French as perfectly
                  As my selfe; by all these Lords indifferent judgement is
                  Due on this very minute.
               
               
                  Fran.
                  This is newes indeed; you do not mean to make a gul of me, a figo for a thousand Ducats: as J am a gentleman I know not French for any thing, not for an Asse: good your grace let mee not be abus'd.
               
               
                  
                     
Cor.
                  'Twas I my Lord who made the bargaine with him,
                  The mony is not due untill my Cozen
                  Have French as perfect as himselfe.
               
               
                  Dor.
                  He has, ile beare him witnesse; for Adorni Speakes not one true French word.
               
               
                  Fran.
                  How not one true French Word?
               
               
                  Ador.
                  No not a word, you must disburse.
               
               
                  Fran.
                  Tutor, ile tell you newes,
                  You made a foole of mee,
                  I could abuse him horribly,
                  If I durst for feare of beating.
               
               
                  Ador.
                  My Lord
                  If he will undertake warres,
                  Ile quit my bargayne.
               
               
                  Fran.
                  Ile pay it trible first, the name of warre Has brought an age on me.
               
               
                  Tri.
                  You two agree that: Cozens I rejoyce
                  To see this happy period of your loves.
                  Let's backe unto the Temple, that the Priest
                  May by his sacred power unite your hearts.
                  Lead to the Temple.
                  Exeunt.
               
            
         
         
            
            The Epilogue.
            
               Frangipan.
               GEntlemen, Ile tell you Newes, the Play is done,
               And he that writ it betwixt hope and Feare
               Stands pensive in the Tyring-house to heare
               Your Censures of his Play: Good Gentlemen
               Let it be kind, or otherwise his Pen
               Will write but dully, for he needs must lacke
               If you disprayse't the quickning Spirit of Sacke
               To inflame his Genius, which you'le ever find
               Devoted to you, if your Votes be kind.
            
            FINIS.
         
      
   

