
   
      
         
            A true relation of the faction begun at VVisbich by Fa. Edmonds, alias VVeston, a Iesuite, 1595. and continued since by Fa. Walley, alias Garnet, the prouincall of the Iesuits in England, and by Fa. Parsons in Rome, with their adherents: against vs the secular priests their bretheren and fellow prisoners, that disliked of nouelties, and thought it dishonourable to the auncient ecclesiasticall discipline of the Catholike Church, that secular priests should be gouerned by Iesuits.
            Bagshaw, Christopher, d. 1625?
         
         
            
               1601
            
         
         Approx. 197 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01748
            STC 1188
            ESTC S100519
            99836356
            99836356
            621
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01748)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 621)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 169:11)
         
         
            
               
                  A true relation of the faction begun at VVisbich by Fa. Edmonds, alias VVeston, a Iesuite, 1595. and continued since by Fa. Walley, alias Garnet, the prouincall of the Iesuits in England, and by Fa. Parsons in Rome, with their adherents: against vs the secular priests their bretheren and fellow prisoners, that disliked of nouelties, and thought it dishonourable to the auncient ecclesiasticall discipline of the Catholike Church, that secular priests should be gouerned by Iesuits.
                  Bagshaw, Christopher, d. 1625?
                  Watson, William, 1559?-1603.
               
               [8], 90, [2] p.   
               
                  Newly imprinted [by Felix Kingston],
                  [London] :
                  1601.
               
               
                  By Christopher Bagshaw.
                  Also attributed to William Watson.
                  Printer's name from STC. "Almost certainly printed in England with the consent of Bishop Bancroft, but made to appear like a foreign printed book for purposes of deception"--Folger Library catalogue.
                  The last leaf is blank.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Weston, William, 1550-1615 --  Early works to 1800.
               Jesuits --  England, (Controversial literature)
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-03
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-03
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-03
            Ali JakobsonSampled and proofread
         
            2007-03
            Ali JakobsonText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A True relation of the faction begun at VViſbich, by Fa. Edmonds, alias VVeston, a Ieſuite, 1595. and continued ſince by Fa. Walley, alias Garnet, the Prouinciall of the Ieſuits in England, and by Fa. Parſons in Rome, with their adherents:
            
               Againſt vs the Secular Prieſts their brethren and fellow Priſoners, that diſliked of nouel
               ties, and thought it diſhonourable to the auncient Eccleſiaſticall Diſcipline of the Catholicke Church, that Secular Prieſts ſhould be gouerned by Ieſuits.
            Newly Imprinted.
            1601.
         
         
            
            
            To the true Catholick Reader.
            
               IN ſuch bookes as ſome of our brethren haue bin lately constrayned to ſet out for your ſatisfaction: there is often mention made of the contention at Wisbich begun 1595. Of this contention, there haue gone many reports: and as yet the truth thereof hath not bin ſo fully publiſhed, as it is conuenient: the indirect courſe of our new aduerſaries conſidered. Such as are infected with our Engliſh Ieſuitiſme, do aſcribe all the blame in that behalfe vnto vs, that are ſecular Priests: in that we could not be brought to alter our old orders for the aduauncement of Fa. Weſton a Ieſuite to become our Gouernor or Agent; as his faction tearmed him. To make this matter therefore as cleare as the ſunne, and that no indiſcreete Catholike may be ignorant of the truth herein, if he will not wilfully ſhut his eyes, or ſtop his eares, as our Archprieſt would haue them: we haue thought it our duties to deliuer vnto you from point to point (as in the ſight of God) the beginning and proceeding of thoſe garboyles then amongst vs. And at this time, we are the rather moued ſo to do: becauſe it hath pleaſed Maiſter Blackwell our ſayd Arch-prieſt, very lately to ſend to his twelue Aſſistants to be diuulged a certaine Cenſure, or (we know not what to tearme it) a ſheet of paper, fraught neither with wit, honeſt dealing, diſcretion, or learning: but in effect with as many ſhifts and lyes almoſt as lines, in derogation not only of ſome of the ſaid bookes ſet out by our brethren, tearming the ſame (as if either he himſelfe, or ſome of his commaunders the Ieſuites had made them) to be ſeditious bookes: but likewiſe taketh vpon him, to touch the ſaid contention, not in many words, but with much follie and great vntruth. We will be bold by way of Preface, a little to touch them.
            Theſe are his words. The firſt point (ſayth he, meaning the diuiſion at Wisbich) was a thing long ſince ended with great edification, and by the meanes principally of thoſe

which are moſt condemned. It toucheth the greater and better part of that company. It nothing concerneth our authoritie: it being more auncient, and hauing orders taken at the attonement by their owne conſent. It is well knowne at Rome by whoſe meanes they were diſanulled. Neither is it more vnfitting for thoſe which liued in one houſe to inſtitute rules for ſuch as voluntarily demaunded and accepted them then to procure a ſodality abroade. Thus farre our Arch-prieſt: and it is all he writeth to his aſſistants of this matter: which we the rather note to ſhew the extremity of his pride, in ſuppoſing by ſuch an anſwere to the ſayd bookes concerning that diuiſion to wipe away thoſe imputations &amp; matters, wherwith both Fa. Garnet, &amp; Fa. Weſton, &amp; he himſelfe in ſome ſort are charged. That which here he ſayth either touching our contention at Wisbich, or any thing whereof he hath written to his ſayd aſſistants againſt the ſayd bookes, is fully anſwered in print by one of our brethren, a true Catholick Prieſt: We hartily pray you to procure the booke, and then iudge of our Arch-prieſt as you finde him. In the meane while and becauſe this our treatiſe may come to your hands before the other, although the hiſtory following doth ſufficiently confute his words by vs now cited: yet will we giue you ſome little tryall of our new Gouernors wiſedome and ſinceritie, by that which here he writeth.
            The firſt point (ſayth he) was a thing long ſince ended. And what then maiſter Blackwell? will you reaſon thus? It was long ſince ended: ergo, maiſter Garnet and maiſter Weſton, the firebrands of that garboile with their factious adherents are not to be blamed as our brethren haue writ of them in their ſayd booke? But we beſeech you ſir vpon your ſmall credit tell vs, is that contention long ſince ended? Nay rather (ſpeake man) is it ended as yet? It was in effect: whether it were meete, and according to the auncient eccleſiasticall Diſcipline, that a Ieſuite ſhould haue the commaundement ouer ſecular Prieſts. And is this point

yet decided? There was we confeſſe (as we thought) an end made amongſt vs 1596. by maiſter Muſh, and maiſter Dudley, and that with edification: but it fell out farre otherwiſe. The edification you make mention of was nothing ſutable to that edification, whereof the Apostle ſpeaketh: but was much more agreeable to the building of Babell that tower of confuſion. For whileſt we of the vnitie were quiet, and ſuppoſed all had bin well: maister Garnet, and his ſubiect maiſter Weſton, were ſo moued, that they had bin diſappointed of their ſayd gouernment amongst vs, as like prowde Nymrods and boisterous hunters they caſt about how to bring vs vnder them by an other ſtratageme, ȧs by the historie it will appeare.
            When he alſo further ſayth, that the end he mentioneth was made by the meanes principally of thoſe which are moſt condemned: he meaneth maiſter Garnet and maiſter Weſton to be thoſe principall perſons; or elſe his ſpeech is ſenſeleſſe: and then alſo he writeth moſt falſely. For true it is, that the end which we ſuppoſed had bin made, was compaſſed by maister Muſh and maister Dudley full ſore againſt the harts and good likings of the ſayd two Ieſuites. Mary if he meane ſuch an end of the ſayd contention as they two propounded to themſelues, which was but an interim to a further miſchiefe, ſuch an end, as then they respected and ſought after, and do now perſwade themſelues to haue found it (whileſt maister Garnet ruleth the roaſt) then indeede Fa. Garnet and Fa. Weſton may truly be ſayd to haue bin the especiall contriuers of it: otherwiſe it proceedeth from incredible boldnes to pretend them to be authors of any good peace, who breathe forth nothing but diſſenſion and cruelty.
            And where he ſayth (as we ſuppoſe) that maister Garnet and maister Weſton, are two men now moſt condemned: it is true that they are indeed condemned for their Machiuilian practiſes againſt their brethren: being (vnder pretence of their Fatherhoods) ſo puft vp with pride and arrogancic, as it is ſcarſe probable to relate. But yet ſome

exception may iuſtly be taken to his words, in that he ſayth, they are moſt condemned. For in good ſooth, we thinke his maisterſhip as farre too blame as either of them, or more: in that being a ſecular Prieſt, he doth ſo tyrannize ouer his owne brethren by calling, and hath not the wit to ſee, how he is abuſed and made a puppie to daunce after their pipe, and to execute what they do commaund him.
            But it followeth for ſooth: that the ſaid diuiſion toucheth the greater and better part of that company. Alack alack, doth it ſo? It toucheth indeede the greater part: and that very neerely: for it ſhewed them for the time to be very factious: ſuch as ſecretly banded, and combined themſelues with a Ieſuite againſt their fellow priſoners and brethren. And therefore in that hee ſayth thoſe conspiring companions were the better part, he ſpeaketh like himſelfe very vntruly, as we in our indgements do esteeme of honeſt men. Mary in his ſenſe, and according to the common ſaying, the veryer knaues, the better luck: they may well be reckoned the better part: becauſe none are iudged vertuous or of any estimation that oppoſe themſelues againſt the Ieſuites, or refuſe to worſhip their Ieſuiticall Idoll our Arch-prieſt. And yet we will be content to let them go for once as he would haue them: ſo he ioyne thoſe words with the other that follow: and to this effect. The ſayd contention toucheth the better part, and therefore it concerneth neither himſelfe, nor any of his louing aſſistants, nor their impregnable authoritie. But in good ſooth maister Blackwell, ſpeake truly man: doth not that contention in ſome ſort touch your high authoritie? Was it not the ground of it? If we had yeelded to Fa. Weſtons agencie, had you bin euer aduaunced as you are? Did not our garboyles beget your greatnes? If maister Weſton had preuailed with vs, maiſter Garnet would haue wiped your noſe for dealing like a yong prince abroade-as you do. And therefore indeed in a right good ſenſe, wee are your good maisters, and ſo you ought to esteeme vs. But if we ſhould deale more ſeriouſly

with you, and vrge you to ſet downe, wherein the ſaid great part was, or is the better: what durſt you ſay, if you haue any ſparke of the feare of God before your eyes? Are they better learned? for ſhame you will not ſay it. Are their liues more ſincere? I hope you will charge vs with no diſhonestie: or if you dare, we defye you: being in our liues we truſt blameles before men, and euery way as honeſt as your ſelfe at the leaſt.
            As touching the orders you ſpeake of; they were yeelded vnto (it is true) by our conſent, and that moſt willinglie: but as for maister Weſton, it ſo ſtroke him to the hart to yeeld vnto them, as he fell downe preſently before the company into a ſwoune: ſuch was his pride, and ſo vnwilling he was to be ouer-ruled for the time. And whereas our Archprieſt ſaith: that it is well knowne at Rome by whoſe means the ſaid orders were diſanulled: we are glad to heare it, and haue taken ſome little paines in this treatiſe, to make it alſo as well knowne here in England. If his meaning be that we of the Vnity did firſt diſanull them, he ſayth vntruly, and they in Rome are falſely informed. No, no, thoſe orders croſſed too much the Ieſuites deſeignements to haue any long continuance, where they had any factious creatures to infringe them.
            But that which followeth, is worthie ſome especiall conſideration. Neither was it more vnfitting (ſayth maister Blackwell) for thoſe which liued in one houſe to institute rules, for ſuch, as voluntarily demaunded and accepted them, then to procure a ſodality abroade. In good faith we are ſory, that we are compelled to diſcloſe this fellowes falſ
                  •
               
               hood, and how much he is ſunne-burnt with Ieſuitiſme. It is a world to ſee how artificially he doth ſmooth ouer in thi
                  •
                place diuers falſe, and ſome very abſurd points. And firſ
                  •
                conſider we pray you: whether it was as fit for Priests i
                  •
                priſon to chooſe a Ieſuite to rule them, as for other Priests abroade, to deſire to haue a Biſhop to gouerne them: and whether ſuiteth better with the auncient diſcipline of the

Catholick Church for ſecular Priests to ſue to the Prouinciall of the Ieſuites to haue a Ieſuite for their head: or for others to ſue to his holynes to aſſigne them a Biſhop. But let this paſſe: and proceede we to the reſt: and when you heare the truth in a word, then conſider the mans ſinceritie. It will appeare vnto you by the history following, that Fa. Weſton had bin laboring for a ſuperioritie ouer his brethren for the ſpace of ſeauen yeeres. To that purpoſe he had inſinuated himſelfe by hypocriſie, and vnequall distribution of money into the fauors of the yonger ſort, ſuch as were either themſelues Ieſuites, or elſe inclining thereunto. The Rules he ſpeaketh of, were of Fa. Weſtons owne making. And all this was done ſecretly, the grauer ſort of the company being neuer acquainted with it. When they had contriued their buſines, as you haue heard: they pretend themſelues to be more holy, then the reſt of vs whom they miſliked: and that therefore, in respect of the ſinnes that raigned amongſt vs; they would no more either eate or drinke with vs, but would haue their diet by themſelues. And in concluſion, they ſeuered themſelues from vs, and dealt as you ſhall perceiue in this treatiſe at large; more like Donatiſts, then Catholick Priests. And all this inquitie doth this Ieſuiticall Arch-prieſt couer in the ſayd words, ſo Clarkly masked with good tearmes, without any regard either of conſcience, or common honesty, but to abuſe the world, for the better vpholding of his owne credit: which being gotten by falſhood, is ſtill yet ſo mainteined. But we keepe you too long from the ſtory it ſelfe: and therefore referring you for this matter to the ſayd printed diſcourſe, in anſwere both of it, and many other points, we commit you by our prayers to Almighty God, who open your eyes and harts, that you may truly diſcerne betweene wolues and true pastors of your ſoules, and accordingly to imbrace them, as heretofore you haue done, and we hope will do hereafter.
         
      
      
         
            
            A true relation of the faction begun at VViſbich.
            
            
               IN the yeare 1579. M. Saunders was diſpatched from Rome to Ireland: and not long after the Pope ſent other forces thither. About the ſame time alſo, the King of Spayne intending to aſſayle Portugall, vpon the death of King Henry the late Cardinall, prepared an Army and a Nauy (as it was pretended) for England. And to countenance the ſame, he procured by Cardinall Alexandrino his meanes, the renouation of the Bull publiſhed by Pius quintus againſt her Maieſtie: and printing of them to the number of 1500. at the leaſt, he was content they ſhould be ſpread abroad. Not long after Father Parſons, and two other Ieſuites his ſubiects, Father Campion and Father Cotham, came into England with ſuch a noyſe, as mooued great expectation in ſome, and diligent caution to be had of their proceedings by others. Theſe things hapning thus together: her Maieſtie and the State (as fearing the worſt) diſpoſed of the affayres in the Realme accordingly: and thought it conuenient to carry a hand more hardly vpon the Catholicks. So as in the yeare 1580. Doctor Watſon Biſhop of Lincolne, Doctor Fecknam Abbot of Weſtminſter, Doctor Young, maiſter Metham, Doctor Oxenbridge, and maiſter Bluet, were ſent to remayne as priſoners in the Caſtle of Wiſbich, where they liued in great vnitie and brotherly kindnes: euery man intermedling only with

his owne affayres and priuate meditations. They were all in commons with the keeper: and for their recreation, had a Garden there to walke in, and to ſolace themſelues as they thought good. Such money as was ſent to any particular man he had himſelfe the diſpoſition of it as he thought it conuement, that which came for the common vſe, was by all their conſents deliuered ſtill to mayſter Bluet, who diuided the ſame to euery man alike. There was then no affectation of ſuperiority, but euery man yeelded of his owne accord that duty and precedencie which to euery one was due, the keeper hauing the commaundement ouer them all. Afterwards within about three yeares, eight or nine Gentlemen were likewiſe ſent to remayne there as priſoners, vpon certayne ſpeeches that the Duke of Guiſe had ſome intendment againſt England, whereby the number of the priſoners increaſed, without any diſturbance at all to the foreſayde vnity. Theſe Gentlemen liued at their owne charges, and as moſt dutifull children demeaned themſelues towards their fellow priſoners, and ſpirituall fathers. If at any time ſome little indiſcretion hapned in any, a word (eſpecially of his ghoſtly father) was more then ſufficient to reforme it: or if vpon ſuch like an occaſion Biſhop Watſon were mooued to reprooue this or that, his anſwere was, What? are we not fellow priſoners? Are we not at the commaundement of an other? Shall Iadde affliction to one that is afflicted? Are we men who profeſſe our ſelues to be examples to others in ſuffering for our conſciences, and ſhall we not be thought then able without controllers to gouerne our ſelues? Be content: I will not take vpon me to reprooue my fellow priſoners. And indeed this was the courſe that euery man held: ſo as by ſubmitting themſelues one to an other, euery man had a commaunding power one ouer an other, ſuch was the moſt

chriſtian and brotherly affection amongſt them. In this ſort they liued till all were either dead or gone, but maiſter Metham and maiſter Bluet, which was for the ſpace of about ſixe or ſeauen yeares.
            Afterwards (vpon new attempts by Babington and his aſſociates againſt her Maieſtie, and by reaſon of the rumours of the King of Spaines preparations) aboue thirtie prieſts that were priſoners elſewhere, were in the yeare 1587 (as we remember) ſent likewiſe to Wiſbich. In which number was maiſter Edmonds, alias Weſton, a Ieſuite: a man, who after Heywoods departure out of England, was ſent hither by Parſons from Paris to bee his ſubſtitute, or Prouinciall: Vpon whoſe apprehenſion maiſter Walley, alias Garnet, by order from Fa. Parſons, did ſuccede him in that office. This company had ſcarſely conſorted themſelues with maiſter Metham and maiſter Bluet by the ſpace of a weeke, but Fa. Weston (hauing in him the reliques of his late prouincialitie) began to caſt about how he might aduance himſelfe aboue his brethren. To which effect, entring amongſt his beſt acquaintance into a great commendation of diſcipline, he offred to their conſiderations a very ſimple man one maiſter Dryland (a Seminary prieſt, and his ghoſtly father) for a fit perſon, to take vpon him the direction and ouerſight of the whole companie: adding, that if they thought that there were any thing in him (the ſayd Weſton) worthy the reckening of, he would imploy the ſame at their commaundement to the aſſiſting and directing of him the ſayd Dryland for the full ſupplying of any defects in him. This motion finding little ſucceſſe, it being very abſurd to make choyſe of a head, that muſt borrow his diſcretion and directions of an other (as at this day our Arch-prieſt Blackwell doth of Fa. Garnet the Ieſuite) he the ſayd Weſton gaue it ouer for about three weekes. And then he began againe

(though in a more generall ſort) to inſiſt very grauely vpon his ſayd pretended diſcipline: ayming with all his skill at his owne particular preferment: for thus the caſe ſtood. Maiſter Bluet (being a man that had bin chiefely imployed in the affaires of that houſe) was iunior to maiſter Metham: and he the ſayd maiſter Metham (hauing more lately entred into the ſociety of the Ieſuits then maiſter Weſton) was thereby (notwithſtanding that otherwiſe he was farre his auncient) yet his inferior according to the rules of that calling. Now one of theſe three (if there ſhould haue bin a gouernour choſen) being ſuppoſed to be the fitteſt amongſt all the reſt for ſuch a place: maiſter Weston geſſed, that in that choyſe they would haue omitted maiſter Bluet in reſpect of maiſter Metham; and him the ſayd maiſter Metham in regard of himſelfe, and that ſo they ſhould haue bin driuen to haue choſen him the ſayd Weston. But it fell out otherwiſe: for in their conſultation it was thought that maiſter Bluet, by reaſon of his long experience in that houſe, and of his acquaintance in that towne, together with the generall knowledge had of him with all Catholicks in England, in reſpect of his long dealings with the common money, could in no ſort be omitted: So as they concluded, that if they muſt be driuen to haue any ſuch gouernment ouer them, it was moſt expedient to chooſe them all three. Whereupon maiſter Weſton perceiuing that he could not get the whole regiment to himſelfe, gaue that attempt ouer: vnder pretence, that he being a Ieſuite, was forbidden by the rules of his order, and others his ſuperiors, to meddle in matters of gouernment.
            But it is here to be obſerued: that the Ieſuites long before this time, hauing gotten the regiment of the Engliſh Seminary at Rome: our countriemen of that order no ſooner came into England, but preſently (as

the ſequele declared) they began to lay their plots how they might bring the ſecular prieſts heads vnder their girdles. For notwithſtanding their ſaid rule (of not intermedling with gouernment) mentioned by Fa. Weston, they haue ſo many wayes to qualify it, as indeed it is but a mask to couer their ſleights with, till opportunitie doth ſerue them. Whereof Fa. Weſton hauing ſufficient intelligence and skill, did not from time to time (almoſt by the ſpace of ſeauen yeares) omit to put the ſame in practiſe. He laboured, as cunningly as he could, to creepe into the fauour of the yonger ſort. When ſtrangers came, it ſhould eſcape him narrowly, but he would be the firſt that ſhould bid them welcome: and no friendſhip could be held with him, except he might make the collation at ſuch times vſuall. In which collations he would ſeldome omit to inſiſt vpon the commendation of order and diſcipline: which being things in themſelues of great worth, he was ſtill therein to them that vnderſtood him not very plauſible. Being a man as impatient as ſome of his fellowes, and of as haughty a ſpirit as any man can be: it was wonderfull to conſider, what humblenes and ſimplicitie he would pretend. His ſighs and zeale ſeemed to be extra ordinary: as though the perfection of true mortification had bin the only thing he aymed at. Marry, with all this hypocriſie he deceiued none, but ſuch as did not looke more narrowly into his proceedings: a righter Phariſee cannot eaſily be found. In the middeſt of his humilitie nothing troubled him more, then that maiſter Doct. Bagſhaw (being a Doctor of Diuinitie) ſhould haue place before him at the table: inſomuch as the better to content him, we were driuen to place him at the tables end with him. The Ieſuites abroad hauing gotten the greateſt part of cōtribution for priſoners into their hands, much was ſent to be diſtributed, by this good father:

wherewith (through his vnequall diſtribution of it) he laboured nothing more, then how he might draw, and binde men vnto him, to make his ſide and faction ſtrong inough againſt the time, he had occaſion to vſe them. Theſe &amp; many other ſuch his vnder-hand practiſes being well diſcerned by maiſter Metham and others, he the ſayd maiſter Metham was very much mooued, and did greatly lament the ſame. This maiſter Metham was a vertuous learned Prieſt, who when he was priſoner in the Tower vowed to become a Ieſuite; as admiring that calling, becauſe he was not acquainted with their courſes: but afterwards at his being in Wiſbich, he found by wofull experience that all was not gold that gliſtered. Sundry times he hath ſayd to ſome of our company, not without teares in his eyes, Keepe this fellow downe aſmuch as you can, meaning Fa. Weston: by labouring to be popular, he becōmeth the ringleader of all mutinies in the houſe, which in time will breede faction againſt you. This houſe will come to vtter ſhame through his folly. I pray God that I dye before it commeth to paſſe, for I do foreſee ſuch a miſchiefe. Thus maiſter Metham.
            
            Cardinall Alane, when the Ieſuites firſt came into England, told ſundry of his friends, that certainely they (the ſaid Ieſuites) would rayſe great garboyles in this countrey, by ſeeking to diſgrace ſecular prieſts, and to aduance themſelues aboue them. He had great experience of the ambition which raigned in many of that ſocietie, and therefore indeuoured (as he might conueniently) to repreſſe that humor in our Engliſh Ieſuites, which kept them within ſome reaſonable compaſſe whileſt he liued. But afterwards they heard no ſooner of his death, and ſhortly after of the death of Doctor Lewys Biſhop of Caſſane (of whome they ſtood in ſome feare, ſuſpecting he ſhould haue bin made Cardinall in the others place) but their inſolencie

burſt foorth as a flame that had bin long ſuppreſſed. They depraued both thoſe worthy perſons now dead very ſlaunderouſly, charging the Cardinall to haue bin but a ſimple man, and of no great worth; and the Biſhop to haue bin a factious perſon in Rome: and all this (forſooth) becauſe ſometimes they both had croſſed ſundry of their lewd attempts. Fa. Weston at Wiſbich (as a man who had long trauailed with his imaginary diſcipline) hearing of theſe mens deaths, and being as he thought, backed ſufficiently by his confederates, began to bring forth the fruits thereof. He lifted vp his coūtenance, as if a new ſpirit had bin put into him, and tooke vpon him to controll, and finde fault with this and that: (as the comming into the Hall of a Hobby-horſe in Chriſtmas) affirming that he would no longer tolerate theſe and thoſe ſo groſſe abuſes, but would haue them reformed. At this his pride and vanitie ſome of vs greatly maruayled, but the reaſon thereof (which we then knew not) was this. We were then priſoners in the houſe to the number of 34. whereof by his foreſayd practiſes he had allured vnto him 19. who by his direction had choſen him to be their head, and giuen him the name of their Agent. Whereupon this grand ſenior thus promoted, withdrew himſelfe to his chamber by the ſpace of a fortnight, of purpoſe (as we afterwards perceiued) to rowze himſelfe, and to deuiſe ſome ſuch new orders and lawes, as he thought moſt conuenient for the gouernment of his ſubiects, which being reſolued vpon by him, he did dedicate them vpon Candlemas day to the bleſſed Virgin, as himſelfe afterwards confeſſed. You muſt vnderſtand, that he did not proceede thus farre, without Fa. Garnets priuity and conſent. Howbeit, his ſayd ſubiects being ignorant thereof, they poore fooles muſt needs write a letter to his fatherhood, to craue his approbation of their ſayd election.

Beſides, Fa. Weston had to practiſed vnder hand with ſome of his ſayd 19. ſubiects, as this his new preferment muſt be obtruded vpon him, whether he would forſooth or not. And accordingly the ſayd letter was framed: ſignifying to maiſter Garnet, that he the ſayd maiſter Weston was as a man taken with the palſey of the mind, and would in no wiſe accept of their election, except that he by his commaunding authoritie, would bid him riſe vp and walke before them in the way of the righteous.
            With this letter they ſent alſo the ſayd lawes or rules, being in number 22. where of ſome of them were ridiculous, and ſome of them very ſcandalous. Theſe things (as we coniecture, for the diſtinct times were kept cloſe from vs) being ſent to Fa. Garnet; the new Agent after he had withdrawne himſelfe from the reſt of the company by the ſpace of a fortnight, directed maiſter Southworth a Prieſt, and our fellowpriſoner vnto maiſter Bluet, to ſignifie vnto him, that Fa. Weston deſired him to allot to him, and to his company being 19. the high table in the Hall: and that leauing the ordinary Kitchin to them, he the ſayd maiſter Bluet, with the reſt (but twelue in number) would be content to prouide themſelues of another. What meane you by this meſſage, quoth maiſter Bluet? Cannot the Hall and Kitchin ſerue vs all now, as heretofore they haue done? No, ſayth maiſter Southworth, we are determined (20. of vs) to draw our ſelues into a more ſtrict order of life: and haue therefore reſolued to keepe commons together amongſt our ſelues, thereby the better to auoyd ſuch ſinnes, as whoredome, drunkennes, and dieing, the ſame being too ordinarie with ſome in this houſe. What, quoth maiſter Bluet: hath Fa. Weston ſent you vnto me with this meſſage? and he anſwering, yea: He the ſayd maiſter Bluet went to Fa. Weston, who iuſtified the ſayd meſſage:

ſauing that he qualified the mentioning of the ſayd crimes with humme and hah: ſaying at the laſt (as though butter would not haue melted in his mouth) indeed we reuerence you, and maiſter Doct. Bagſhaw: but amongſt the reſt, there are ſome enormities, which we would be glad to auoyd: and do therefore purpoſe to impoſe vpon our ſelues a more ſtrict order, leauing you and others, to follow ſuch courſes, as you ſhall thinke good. With this his anſwere, maiſter Bluet being ſomewhat moued: Haue you kept your chamber (ſayth he) all this while, for this? Shall we haue a new Donatus amongſt vs, to reuiue againe that peſtilent ſchiſme? Can you name any in the houſe, worſe then your ſelues? Well, well: I pray you leaue this courſe: it is naught. Be content to eate and drinke with vs ſtill: for, aſſure your ſelfe, we will neuer yeeld, that you ſhould haue any ſeuerall roomes graunted vnto you; thereby to ſeuer your ſelues from vs. And ſo after many other ſpeeches, for that time they parted.
            When maiſter Bluet had imparted vnto vs the ſayd meſſage, and his ſayd diſcourſe with Fa. Weston, it did very much grieue vs all, as foreſeeing what publick ſcandale it would grow vnto: and therefore diuers of vs dealt with them particularly, that they would deſiſt from that their purpoſe, and be content that we might liue together ſtill, like priſoners, and louing brethren, as we haue done before. But all was in vaine: they inlarged their calumniation and ſlauders of vs, and began to ſpread the ſame abroad to our great diſcredits: and would in no wiſe be ſtayed from the courſe they had begun. Howbeit, we hindered as long as we could their publick ſeparation from vs, by keeping our old places, ſome of vs, at euery table: ſo as they could not chooſe, except they would haue forborne their dinners and ſuppers, but that they muſt needs ſit amongſt vs. Whereupon Fa. Weston ſent the

ſayd Southworth to our keeper, with the like meſſage in effect to the former, concerning their intent (for the auoyding of ſinne) to keepe commons by themſelues, apart from the reſt: and therefore to intreate him, that they might haue a roome aſſigned them, to make a Kitchin of, and ſome other places meete and conuenient for them; offering him ſome large conſideration for his good will therein. But he conſulting with ſome of the grauer ſort, diſliked their attempt: and reiecting their ſuite, commaunded them to continue in peace and quietnes, as the State had appointed, and as he found them, at his firſt comming to be their keeper: vnleſſe they could ſhew vnto him againſt the reſt, ſome capitall crimes which might warrant him to graunt their ſeparation: for (ſayd he) I am a Iuſtice of peace, qualifyed to take notice of ſuch crimes. To whom maiſter Southworth anſwered: that in this caſe, the Queene could not make him a competent iudge: and that the crymes were ſuch and ſo great, as in conſcience they could not keepe company with vs. Why (ſayd maiſter Medlye) what crymes are thoſe ſo horrible, that the Queenes authority cannot reach to take knowledge of? Maiſter Bluet can tell you (ſayth maiſter Southworth) for I haue ſignifyed them vnto him. Very well quoth maiſter Bluet: I ſee the old prouerb verified now in you: An Engliſh man Italionate, is a Diuell incarnate. If you told me the cauſes why Weston and you do attempt to make this ſchiſme and diuiſion in the houſe, why may not your ſlaundering toong vtter the ſame to maiſter Medlye our keeper? Muſt I be your Bedle to proclayme your lyes? But maiſter Medly, this Italionated company on hath this craft in his budget: if I ſhould now relate vnto you what he hath told me of this matter, then would he being meerely Ieſuited, deny it, and ſo turne the blame vpon me, that I telling it you publickly, do

ſlaunder the houſe, and not he, nor his fellowes, that told it but ſecretly. Vpon this, and ſuch like communication, maiſter Medlye fell to the commendation of the quiet behauior of thoſe priſoners, which were firſt ſent to Wiſbich: ſaying, that it was nothing, but the turbulent ſpirits, and humour of youth, that wanting due wiſdome, diſcretion, and grauitie, thruſt them into theſe noueltyes.
            Much iangling they kept both at this time and afterwards for ſeuerall roomes: but fayling of their deſire therein, they grew to a great diſlike with the keeper: and to be reuenged vpon him, procured in ſhort time two Prieſts to eſcape from him out of priſon, which they knew would grieue him much. Beſides, the ordinary Chappell belonging to the Biſhop of Ely, lying fitly by them, they aduentured of themſelues to dedicate the ſame to Bacchus for their Buttery: and entertayning an other Brewer (one Palmer) laid ſuch Beere in it as they thought meete. It is not almoſt credible what brablings were about theſe matters: and with what malice and impietie they did alſo proſecute vs, by ſeeking to blemiſh our good names, as though they had quite forgot that we were Catholick Prieſts, and their fellow priſoners. The common enemy could not haue vſed vs much more deſpitefully.
            By this time Fa. Garnet hauing peruſed the ſayd rules and letter, returned his approbation of them in a generall letter to that company, and alluding to a point mentioned in their letter to him, commaunded his ſubiect Fa. Weston as an hypocriticall paralytick, to take vp his bed and walke: that is, he gaue him leaue to accept of the Agency, impoſed forſooth by them vpon him: but vnder-hand ſent to Fa. Weston himſelfe a priuate letter; wherein he admoniſhed him in any ſort ſo to take vpon him that his new Prelacy, as both his the layd fathers name for auoyding of enuy might

be concealed: and that it might ſeeme to proceede wholy, from the importunity of thoſe that had choſen him. All theſe particulars were at this time vnknowne vnto vs: they played faſt and looſe in corners (as you ſee) buying and ſelling of vs (as honeſt men as themſelues) at their pleaſures.
            Whileſt they were thus in this garboyle with vs, animated therein by Fa. Garnet: it hapned that maiſter Dolman (a graue Prieſt) came to Wiſbich, with ſome contribution for the whole company: who perceiuing and lamēting what a breach he found of our auncient vnity, did endeuor for the ſpace almoſt of a weeke, to haue reduced vs thereunto againe, being earneſtly deſired by vs all ſo to do. At this his being there, maiſter Southworth drew him with importunitie into his chamber, and did ſhew vnto him their foreſayd letter, and rules, which they had ſent to Fa. Garnet, entring into a long diſcourſe with him, concerning their purpoſe, to ſeparate themſelues from vs. Whereunto maiſter Dolman aunſwering, that in ſo doing, they would aſſuredly be the occaſion of great ſcandale: he replyed, that their company were reſolute to go through with it.
            We had heard before of the ſayd letter and rules ſent to Fa. Garnet: but (as we then told M. Dolman) we could neuer come to the ſight of them: and therefore we deſired him to be a meanes, that we might haue the peruſing of them. Whereunto he did very willingly yeeld; as thinking our motion therein very reaſonable: and thereupon going to maiſter Southworth, he ſo preuayled with him, as that he the ſayd maiſter Dolman brought them vnto vs: which when we had read, we were much perplexed, finding our credits to be greatly touched by them. Howbeit, maiſter Doctor Bagſhaw, in a very mild and charitable ſort, did then deſire maiſter Dolman, that by his mediation he might

haue conference with Fa. VVeston: promiſing, that he would be a meanes, that this controuerſie ſhould be ended to his honor &amp; credit, and to a further increaſe of amity and charity, then euer there had bin for a long time amongſt vs. Maiſter Dolman being a glad man to heare ſo much from him, dealt with Fa. VVeston accordingly: whome he found ſo ſtiffe, as he could by no meanes perſwade him to admit of that godly offer: notwithſtanding it was made vnto him thrice; and ſo oft preſſed by him the ſayd Dolman. Whereby maiſter Dolman gathered, that Fa. VVeston had receiued ſome commaundement from maiſter Garnet, to take vpon him his ſayd Agency: and for the better contenting of Doctor Bagſhaw and his friends (being ſomewhat moued, that maiſter VVeston had ſo oft refuſed conference) told them ſo much: adding, that he thought maiſter VVeston his ſayd refuſall to be thereupon grounded: it being vnlawfull for him to reiect, or call into queſtion that, which his Prouinciall had impoſed vpon him. But afterwards he the ſayd maiſter Dolman imparting to maiſter VVeston what he had ſayd to Doctor Bagſhaw and his friends, maiſter VVeſton flatly denyed that he had receyued from maiſter Garnet any ſuch approbation or commaundement, either by letter, or otherwiſe. With which his aunſwere, maiſter Dolman acquainting vs, we did the more maruaile why he diſdayned the ſayd offer of conference. Howbeit, ſeeing their courſes, we ſayd that we would not impeach any order, which they thēſelues thought meete to liue vnder: only we deſired to liue in commons together with them, that the world might not take notice of any ſuch ſchiſme amongſt vs: but this was reiected. Whereupon maiſter Dolman demaunded of Fa. VVeſton whether they meant to keepe any more ſtrict or large dyet by themſelues, then the reſt? who anſwered, that they did not. Why then (quoth he)

haue you taken another Brewer? Maiſter Weſton aunſwered: it was, for that he brewed better Beere then the other. Vpon occaſion of theſe ſpeeches betwixt them, maiſter Dolman told him, that by reaſon of the choyſe of the ſayd new Bruer, the Towneſmen began to talke at large of their great breach in the Caſtle: and further ſayd, that ſome ſcandale was already growne, by appointing the ſaid Chappell for their Buttery. To which laſt point maiſter Weston replying, aunſwered: that he thought (as the caſe ſtood now in England) they might vſe things heere as they found them: which words of his gaue maiſter Dolman occaſion to ſhew the contrary, both out of S. Thomas, and out of Nauarre, in his Commentaries De ſpolijs. It were too long to ſet downe what then paſſed amongſt vs, at this time of maiſter Dolmans being with vs: but he perceiued ſuch oppoſition to his godly motions, as that he deſired to haue ſome ioyned with him: and that he might then depart, and returne with his Colleague, named by them one Doctor Bauin, a fortnight after Eaſter. Hereunto we all willingly yeelded: and ſo after ſixe dayes trauayle amongſt vs, he bade vs farewell. But conſider now a Ieſuiticall trick that hapned. As maiſter Dolman was going to horſeback, maiſter Southworth met him in the Porters lodge, and told him with great vehemencie of ſpirit, that Fa. Weston had greatly abuſed both him the ſayd maiſter Dolman, and the whole company: in that he had receiued a fortnight before a letter from Fa. Garnet in approbation of their choyſe to haue him for their Agent: and had kept the ſame in his hands ſo long, without making his company acquainted with it: which he tearmed to be double dealing, as indeed it was in them both. But maiſter Southworth pretending his great diſcontentment in that reſpect, perſwaded maiſter Dolman to returne back to maiſter Weston, and then hearing the

ſayd letter read, and perceiuing that it was ambiguouſly written, ſo as the time did not ſerue him to enter into any diſcourſe of it (hauing a great iourney that night) he departed, without making any of vs acquainted with the ſayd letter: much meruailing (as ſince he hath confeſſed) to finde ſo groſſe a falſhood in maiſter Weston.
            
            In the meane time that we were in expectation of maiſter Dolmans returne with his Colleague, it was a world to heare the people, that before had honored and admired vs, ſo long as we kept vnity and integrity, how they changed their opinions of vs, eſpecially of the Ieſuites, tearming them in all ordinary aſſemblies, prowde, ambitious, and vndicatiue perſons: perturbers of ſtates, countries, and commonwealths. What would theſe men do (ſay they) if they had all in their hands: that being in a Gaole, dare take vpon them to rayſe vp ſuch tumults and garboyles? Certaine good men relating theſe things to maiſter Weston, deſired him humbly vpon their knees, to conſider what ſcandale he gaue to the world, and how God and his truth were much blaſphemed by this diſſention: but he, with great contempt and irriſion aunſwered, that he waighed not any mans iudgement: let them alone (ſayth he) caeci ſunt &amp; duces caecorum: if it be a ſcandall, it is ſcandalum per accidens, which I care not for: this matter is gone further then may be controlled by man: you ſhall ſee it with hands and ſeales confirmed, ere it be long. With this fathers obſtinacy many were diſcontented: and maiſter Bluet did thereupon thinke it conuenient to write to maiſter Perpoint, and to deſire him (hauing bin a priſoner before at Wiſbich) to moue maiſter Weston by his letter to ſome better quietnes. But the ſayd maiſter Perpoint being now altogether Ieſuited (which maiſter Bluet knew not of) ſhewed his letter to Fa. Garnet, who taking

it in euill part, writ himſelfe thereof to Fa. Weſton, aduiſing him, that ſeeing maiſter Bluet had begun to write abroad of the affayres in that place, they ſhould not now ſpare either him or any of the reſt, to requite them with the like. So as thereupon maiſter VVeston ſtirred vp a young Prieſt very well learned, to write a bitter, rayling, and an vnghoſtly letter to a Gentleman in London (a lay brother of that ſociety) againſt Doctor Bagſhaw and maiſter Bluet: to the intent that the ſayd lay brother (being well eſteemed amongſt all the chiefeſt Catholicks) ſhould blaze and ſpread the ſame abroad, to their exceeding diſcredits. But Doctor Farbeck being about that time in London, and knew very well the affayres then at VViſbich: vpon the ſight of this letter by a Noble man, dealt very roundly with the ſayd lay Ieſuite, for the indignity and vnchriſtian dealing offered to thoſe two perſons ſecretly behinde their backs, where they could not defend their innocencie. He did at that time after a ſort, ſatisfye the Gentleman ſo farre forth, as the ſpirit of that generation will be qualified in ſuch a matter: and beſides ſo informed the Nobleman of ſuch things as he knew, as that he was pleaſed with ſome diſdaine to teare the letter in pieces. But the poore Prieſt that was vrged againſt his conſcience to write it, being admoniſhed thereof, fell out of his wits, and threatned to kill thoſe that ſet him on worke: whereby they were driuen to intreate their keeper to ſhut him vp in a cloſe chamber, where he remayned a tweluemoneth, and confeſſing willingly, that for abuſing his penne againſt innocents, he was thus tormented: he asked the ſayd parties forgiuenes. You haue heard peraduenture of a Machiuilian maxime: detrahe audacter, aliquid adhaerebit: and here you haue ſeene the practiſe of it.
            Maiſter Doleman (as you haue heard before) being departed from vs, hath reported vpon occaſion, how

carefully he imployed himſelfe on our behalfe. I met (ſayth he) with a deere friend to you all: a man well knowne to be excellently well learned in both lawes, and for his vertuous wiſdome and other ſingular good parts in him well beloued, and greatly eſteemed of all that know him. I meane Doctor Windam: vnto whom, I opened plainly and ſincerely the whole matter, and craued it earneſtly at his hands, that he would take ſome paynes therein, and for the loue he bare the generall cauſe, the eſpeciall affection he had to your company, which I know is as great as he can giue and you deſire, and for the old acquaintance and loue, that was between vs beyond the ſeas, he would aduiſe and inſtruct me what to deliuer vnto you. How much he lamented this controuerſie amongſt you, I am not able to expreſſe. After three dayes aduiſement, he told me, for any that liued together as you do (preſuppoſing he vnderſtood your ſtate very well) to diuide themſelues from the boord, from the reſt of the company (things ſo ſtanding as they do now) though their purpoſe were right good, was both againſt charitie and pollicie. Whereupon hearing his great miſlike, I made ſome haſtie returne, and let Fa. Weston, with ſome of his company, vnderſtand his reſolution, with mine owne therein. Thus farre maiſter Dolman. This his returne was within tenne dayes after his departure, and before the time limited to him and his Colleague to deale in our cauſes. Vpon which his ſayd ſpeeches and communication with Fa. Weston concerning Doctor Windams opinion: Would God (ſayd maiſter Weston) with moſt earneſt affection (as it ſeemed) that you maiſter Dolman were as well able to perſwade the reſt, as you haue done me. For mine own part, I mind to giue ouer and meddle no further, but to commend the cauſe wholy to God: aſſuring you, if I could do the leaſt of this houſe good for his

ſoules health, by laying my head vnder his feete, I would moſt willingly do it. I pray you talke with ſome of our company, and ſee whether you can perſwade them. And thus farre this diſſembling Ieſuite (by maiſter Dolmans report) very well putting Father Garnets aduiſe in practiſe, ſo to enter into his courſe of gouernment, as that it might be thought to be impoſed vpon him in effect againſt his will. But how found maiſter Dolman this Agents ſubiects? Fa. Weston could haue told him, like a crafty company on, if he had liſt to haue ſaued the poore old mans labour. For he no ſooner moued them to reunite themſelues, but they ſtartled thereat, and ſayd, they were ſtill reſolute to proceede in the courſe which they had vndertaken: and would heare nothing to the contrary.
            At this time (as we remember) of maiſter Dolmans being at Wiſbich, maiſter Bluet entred into ſpeech with maiſter Weston in his the ſayd maiſter Dolmans preſence, concerning both their deſire of ſeuerall commons, and alſo their rules and lawes before mentioned: and ſayd vnto him: that it ſeemed very ſtrange that he ſhould perſiſt as he did, in defence of theſe his proceedings. To whom maiſter VVestons ghoſtly father aunſwered: that as he, and Doctor Bagſhaw, had caryed away the glory and fame of all that was heretofore lawdably done in that Caſtle: ſo from hence-forth Fa. VVeſton would indure it no longer, but would haue the ſame aſcribed to himſelfe, and to the Ieſuites. Fa. VVeston halfe aſhamed of this ſo plaine a confeſſion, tooke vpon him to mend it: ſaying, that their intent of ſeparation was, rather to auoyd ſuch ſinnes as were in the houſe, as whoredome, dronkennes, and dicing, then for any ſuch cauſe, as the party before had mentioned. And being further vrged to ſpeake plainly, whether he knew himſelfe of any ſuch ſinnes to be in the houſe, he aunſwered, that he ſpake not in particular,

but in generall of them. Whereunto maiſter Bluet replying, affirmed, that in ſaying as he did, and charging no man in particular, he inuolued the whole houſe as guiltie of thoſe ſinnes, and was a detractor thereby in the higheſt degree. He alſo the ſayd maiſter Bluet proceeded further in effect, as followeth. If there be ſuch enormious ſinnes amongſt vs, haue we not ghoſtly fathers to reforme them? or can you name any that herein hath bin refractarious? Is not the ſacrament of healthfull penance a ſufficient remedie for men in our caſes, to keepe vs from ſuch enormities? If the meanes appointed by Chriſt, haue not ſufficient force to remedie theſe euils: what extraordinary grace or power can we expect from your ſuppoſed authoritye and lawes to effect the ſame? Againe, if ſuch ſinnes were in the houſe: either ſome particular men were guilty of them, or all: if ſome, why are they not denounced, that the reſt may know, as well thoſe that committed them, as thoſe that fauour or defend them in ſuch their turpitudes? And whereas we are priſoners heere againſt our wils, and therefore cannot chooſe but of neceſſity muſt dayly conuerſe and be together, by order and commaundement of the State, and condition of the priſon: how dare you (except you will incroach vpon her Maieſties authority) thus violently attempt to ſeparate her ſubiects, promulgate lawes, execute puniſhments, and make your ſelfe in effect to haue as full power as the Pope hath himſelfe? In that you ſeeme without his authority to make a new order of Religion, or I know not what, with bands, lawes, rules, and puniſhments, except your power be more then we can dreame of: you incurre thereby the ſentence of excommunication: and by the lawes of this Realme, it is well knowne, that omnis coitio in the kingdome not preſcribed by her Highneſſe, is ſubiect to a very heauy cenſure. When Iames and Iohn priuatly

               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
               
                  〈1 page duplicate〉
               
               
and therefore vnlawfully ſought by inediation of their mother, the right hand and the left: the reſt of the Apoſtles did worthily diſlike that attempt: but when Peter and theſe two were called vp to Mount Tabor to behold Chriſt in his Maieſtie; all the reſt tooke it in good part, and neuer grudged, becauſe they were called thither by lawfull authority. Beſides▪ if you and your pretended ſubiects will keepe no company with vs, becauſe of our ſinnes (as you pretend) be your ſurmiſes true or falſe: yet (as you proceede) you ioyne therein with the Donatists; who becauſe they would not defile themſelues (pure creatures) with other mens ſinnes, departed from the Church, and periſhed in their foule ſchiſme and hereſie. In the proceeding of this diſcourſe there were ſundry interruptions: but the ſumme was, that maiſter VVeston did little regard it: notwithſtanding his pretence of yeelding mentioned before, if his companie would be thereunto perſwaded.
            When maiſter Dolman was to depart, he moued maiſter VVeston and others, that foraſmuch as he had acquainted them already both with Doct. VVindams opinion and his owne, concerning the intent of his company for diuiding themſelues in Commons from their brethren: he might with their good fauours be releaſed of his promiſe of cōming againe after Eaſter. But they would in no ſort yeeld thereunto: but deſired him in any wiſe, as he loued them, to keepe the time appointed. Which made ſome of vs to meruaile, knowing now by maiſter Dolman, that Fa. Garnet had approued maiſter Westons Agency: although neither then nor ſince we could euer obteine a copy of his letter to that effect. Howbeit afterwards we perceiued his drift herein: which was to make tryall, if by any poſſible meanes he could winne of the ſayd Arbitrators; to determine that ſome other order, then formerly

had bin vſed in that place, was neceſſary to be appointed. For then preſently by way of a conſequent depending vpon Fa. Garnets authority, he would haue obtruded vpon vs his owne Agency: or at the leaſt haue gotten ſome aduantage againſt vs, to haue depraued vs to thoſe, who would not conſider, that the admitting of maiſter Weston for our head, we had thereby ſubmitted our ſelues to Garnet, and ſhould ſo haue become meere ſubiects to the Ieſuites.
            At the time appointed our two Arbitrators, Doctor Bauyn and maiſter Dolman comming to Wiſbich: we found him the ſayd Bauyn much more ſtiffely lyned with Ieſuitiſme, then euer we could haue ſuſpected. He being in maiſter Bluets chamber, and demaunding the cauſe why they were ſent for: aunſwere was made, that their preſence was deſired for the examining and deciding a fact of great ſcandale and deformitie: yea a flat ſchiſme (as we thought) begun, and proſecuted in priſon by Fa. Weſton: and to reduce vs againe to our auncient vnity. To this Doctor Bauyn ſayd, that he would do his beſt indeuour, to ſet quietnes amongſt vs: and further told vs; that he had with diſdaine read Father Westons lawes and platforme, and was fully reſolued to caſheere them, whatſomeuer came ofit: but yet (quoth he) you muſt haue ſome order and forme of gouernment amongſt you. It was aunſwered him; that we had deſired their company, but to iudge, whether the breach they had made, was lawfull or no: iudge that firſt (quoth we) and then we will friendly conferre, what is meete to be done hereafter. We are in priſon, and ſometimes cloſe priſoners, not in caſe to ſpeake one with an other: and perhaps muſt be, as heretofore we were at the Keepers dyet: what ſhall we then trouble our ſelues, with rules, orders, or common wealthes? Are not the Canons of Councels, the lawes of the Church, and

the ſacrament of penance ſufficient for Prieſts, that are in priſon for the Catholick faith? Did the Biſhop of Lincolne when he liued here, trouble himſelfe with any ſuch matters: or hath this yonker amongſt vs, a Ieſuite, more wit, grace, experience, and authority, then he had, being the Popes Legate ouer all England? To admit theſe his new lawes and penall ſtatutes, were to confeſſe in effect, that we had liued inordinatly, vntill this Ieſuiticall youth came to reforme vs. No, no, they ſhall haue no ſuch aduantage againſt vs: it is the But, they ayme at, to make the ſimpler ſort of Catholicks beleeue, that we ſecular Prieſts are no body, nor able to do any thing of our ſelues, except the Ieſuites may haue the commaundement ouer vs, to direct and commaund vs, as they thinke good.
            After ſuch communication had in maiſter Bluets chamber, maiſter Dolman and he went to maiſter Weſton, and his adherents, to know wherein they would commaund their ſeruice. But maiſter Weston after the new faſhion, deſired them firſt to fall downe and pray with him: which done, he aroſe; and framing his countenance as though he would haue wept, ſayd vnto them thus in effect. Your comming hither maketh vs glad, and heauy: glad, if that you will aſſiſt vs in that we haue begun; and ſo we will giue you prayſe and benediction: but if you will croſſe our deſignements, and condemne our indeuors, you ſhall giue vs very great cauſe of ſorrow. Aduiſe therefore your ſelues very well what you do: for the matters are of great importance, which we put into your hands. Then Doctor Bauyn (to pay maiſter Weston with his owne coyne) pretended to be ſo mooued with his words, as if he likewiſe could ſcarſely haue refrayned from teares: which maiſter Dolman and we obſeruing, we doubted to finde him but an halting Arbitrator. Beſides it ſeemed, that they were halfe vnwilling, to

commit their former deſignements to theſe mens arbitrement: had it not bin for feare, that elſe the world would haue condemned them: and therefore they laboured them in ſecret, with all their might and maine to approoue their enterpriſes. Whileſt we were in conſultation (ſayeth maiſter Dolman) good Lord, how were we dealt with vnder-hand, to allow wholy of their doings, and to reprooue the others. Many iarres hapned in theſe conferences. One of them that ſtood for the vnity, told the Arbitrators that a brother of the ſeparation, threatned him, and all the reſt that ſtood againſt maiſter Weston, that if they would not ſubmit themſelues vnder the Ieſuites obedience, and liue vnder their ſtatutes and lawes, they ſhould ſtarue, and not haue a morſell of bread to put in their mouthes.
            
            When Doctor Bauyn and maiſter Dolman grew to the conſideration of Fa. Westons rules, and other his deſignements, he the ſayd Doctor Bauyn did vtterly reiect them. Marry withall he made mention of a certaine draught and forme of diſcipline, which was more beneficiall to the Ieſuites, then their owne: and ſuch a one (as he himſelfe hath confeſſed) the Ieſuites abroad had agreed vnto. In this platforme, eight (beſides maiſter Weston) were to haue bin choſen out of the brethren of the ſeparation, and two of the vnited to make vp tenne: which tenne ſhould haue gouerned all the reſt; maiſter Weston being appointed euer for their mouth. So that as before in his owne common wealth called the Agenage, he was maiſter Agent: ſo in this other of Doct. Bauyns (tearmed the tenne men, and the mouth) this our deuout Ieſuite was to haue bin called in proper ſpeech, maiſter mouth. In communication about this new platforme of Doctor Bauyns, there grew ſome heate betwixt him, Doctor Bagſhaw, and maiſter Bluet: both of them with great earneſtnes, and very forcible arguments impugning

the ſame, which Doctor Bauyn tooke in euill part, but was afterwards wel inough appeaſed. Then after a day or two our ſaid Arbitrators (hauing taken great paines this way and that way) agreed together vpon a forme of pacification, to be offered vnto vs all: the principall effect whereof was: that we ſhould reconcile our ſelues generally one to an other, remitting freely and wholy each to other, all pretended or ſuppoſed iniuries paſt, vttering the ſame in order by ſome ſhort word or ſpeech, without any rehearſall, debating, or reaſoning of any matters paſt, and without any condition, or exception for the time to come. This pacification being firſt ſhewed to Doctor Bagſhaw, and maiſter Bluet, they did moſt ioyfully receiue it: and deſired the Arbitrators very inſtantly, that for Gods ſake, they would go forward with it. Afterwards they went to Fa. Weston, and maiſter Southworth, and deliuering them the copy of it, they ſeemed very willing to accept the ſame: ſo as an hower the next day after dinner was appointed for the mutuall recōciliation of all the company, according to the effect of the pacification before mentioned. Againſt which time maiſter Dolman being in the Gallery ready to go into the Hall to dinner, Fa. VVeston drew him aſide to a window, and vſed theſe words vnto him: I truſt (maiſter Dolman) this reconciliation ſhall not preiudice our determination, of diuiſion of Commons: to whom maiſter Dolman aunſwered, that all their breach was about that matter: and that therefore, he and his fellow could in no ſort like thereof, nor permit the ſame. Then ſayth maiſter VVeston very ſharply, you do vs great wrong. I meane you no wrong, quoth maiſter Dolman, but all the good I can wiſh or deuiſe: yes mary do you (ſayth he) and ſo you would confeſſe, if you ſaw but our extract: which conteyneth three ſheetes of paper of the enormious crymes, that we

haue to charge them withall. But I pray you (ſayth he) let vs intreate maiſter Doctor Bauyn, and you to ſtay this reconciliation, vntill to morrow: for we haue certaine Articles to ſhew you firſt, that cannot ſo ſoone be made ready. Vnto this motion the Arbitrators condeſcended, hoping it would haue turned vnto the beſt: but it fell out quite contrary. For they found that nothing would content them, except they would agree vnto the ſeparation of Commons.
            The Articles exhibited concerning vs, together with our Articles which we were conſtrayned thereby to offer to our ſaid Arbitrators, we haue thought good here to ſet downe. Firſt theirs (which are rather indeed Interrogatories to examine the Arbitrators, then matters that do much touch vs) and then our owne: which we offer to all men, to be cenſured, as they ſhall think good.
            1 Whether (ſay they to the Arbitrators) will you ſtay the time to examine thoſe Articles, which any may be accuſed of?
            2 Whether you thinke it ſecure for vs, that liue and meete together many times in the day (not hauing the meanes to auoyd each other) to haue thoſe things propoſed, and examined, and whether you can compaſſe our quiet?
            3 That whoſoeuer doth come to declare any matter, ſhall ſubmit themſelues to you, as to their Ordinary, to declare without all equiuocation, or lying, any thing, whereof you thinke neceſſary to the manifeſtation of the verity.
            4 That you do take the promiſe of euery one that is called before you, to behaue themſelues with modeſtie and good tearmes.
            5 This ſuppoſed: we are all for our parts contented, that they obiect, what they can againſt vs.
            6 We require alſo, that they ſhall giue their conſent,

that they are all contented, to heare what may be layd out againſt them.
            7 Euery thing being heard: that you pronounce ſentence againſt thoſe, that you ſhall finde culpable.
            When our ſayd Arbitrators had peruſed theſe Interrogatories, no maruaile though they troubled thē, being ſo contrary to their expectation: and deuiſed of purpoſe to breake off all hope of reconciliation by their meanes: and ſuch likewiſe, as by Ieſuiticall ſhifts might haue bin prolonged, if they had liſt, for we know not how many yeares. With theſe Articles we were no ſooner acquainted: but preſently we ſet down theſe fower in ſome ſort to aunfwere them.
            1 We require that ſufficient ſatisfaction may be made for the ſlaunder and diffamation of vs by their breach and letter: if ſufficient cauſes cannot be proued for their ſo doing.
            2 We require that euery accuſation be ſet downe in writing vnder the accuſers hands, ſub poena talionis, if it be not proued.
            3 We will aunſwere in all things according to the order in the Canon law: ſuppoſing theſe men to be our lawfull Iudges.
            4 We will ſuſteine any cenſure, with this condition, that being cenſured by theſe men, we may be ſecured thereby from all other cenſures concerning that matter.
            When theſe our Articles were deliuered to Fa. Weſton, and he with ſome others had peruſed them: they began firſt (ſayth maiſter Dolman) to take exceptions againſt the fourth Article: and in the end againſt them all, plainely ſhewing indeed, that they liked nothing, but their owne deſignements, being reſolued to proceed in them: let it fall how it ſhould either back or edge, as the common prouerb is. Whereas we (by the teſtimony of the ſayd maiſter Dolman) profeſſed our ſelues very deſirous of reconciliation:

and offred our readynes to aunſwere any matters, that might be obiected againſt vs: proteſting that we would only indeuor to maintaine our owne credits, without any recrimination at all.
            
               But the truth is, that our ſayd Arbitrators ſaw ſo many inconueniences that would haue followed, if they had entred into this courſe, as they by no meanes would be drawne vnto it: but ſtill inſiſted to haue lapped vp all diſcontentments in their ſayd generall reconciliation. Whereunto we for our parts, were all of vs well inclined: inſomuch as maiſter Dolman himſelfe proteſteth, that he he will euer charge maister Weſton and his company, to haue bin the cauſes that the ſaid goodworke ſo greatly vrged by him and Doctor Bauyn, was not effected by them. For (ſayth he the ſayd maiſter Dolman) all our motions were irkeſome vnto them: and two or three, one after another came vnto me: and told me, that except I would remoue my opinion touching the breach of commons, they wiſhed me to be gone. Whereupon he writ a letter to our whole company, and concluded thus. As before God I ſpeake it in conſcience, I am throughly perſwaded: you, that ſhall vnder pretence of ſubmitting your ſelues vnder a head, and to liue vnder an order, diuide your ſelues from the reſt, ſhall do a thing ſinfull. This is my minde: this is my cenſure. And ſo the good old man departed from vs.
            
            After his departure, notwithſtanding that Doctor Bauyn, to our owne knowledge was very reſolute againſt our diuiding of Commons; as maiſter Dolman and diuers others can alſo witnes: yet we know not, how afterwards it came to paſſe (through their Ieſuiticall practiſes with him) but (as we haue heard) within two dayes he turned his tippet, and incouraging them to take their owne courſe, went his way like a charitable Prieſt, and neuer bade vs farewell. We would be loth to do him iniurie, if this matter hath bin

miſreported vnto vs: but this we do affirme, that ſince that time his credit hath ſo increaſed amongſt the Ieſuites, as now he is become one of their Archprieſts aſſiſtants: and that within a day or two after his departure from Wiſbich, maiſter Weston and his company, entred into an actuall and publick ſchiſme: they refuſed either to eate or drinke with vs: they left the Hall altogether: they made the Chappell their Buttery, maiſter Brampstons lodging their Kitchin, and their Agents chamber their Refectory.
            Whileſt Fa. Weston and his conſorts were talking, as you haue heard before, of certain great matters which they had againſt vs, why they could not keepe company with vs any longer: he the ſayd good father, to ſhew what good ſtuffe they had in ſtore, called one Garret forth, and perſwadeth him to vnfold to the Arbitrators his owne confeſſion, that vnto Weston his ghoſtly father, he had made a yeare and a halfe before. This demy-Ieſuite, although the thing ſeemed moſt abſurd and irreligious, obeyeth willingly to vnfold to the Commiſſioners, either what he had vttered in his confeſſion of one of his fellowes, or at the leaſt, what he had deuiſed between him and maiſter Agent. Well: propter bonum ſocietatis, he commeth moſt ſadly (as if he had bin compelled) and telleth thē that he is moſt vnwilling to vnfold that which turneth to the diffamation of a Prieſt: but yet for diſciplines ſake, which was ſeene decayed in the houſe, and for the obedience which he ought vnto his ghoſtly father, he will informe them of that, which may giue thē light to proceede, as they thought good. Marry he will not haue it knowne, but vnto themſelues in ſecret. This proteſtation made, he ſayth, that one of maiſter Medlye his men, an heretick told him, how that a Prieſt (and named him) was in the greene chamber (which was the keepers lodging) talking with Mary maiſter Medlyes
               
may de: and that the Porter (who was in loue with her) was by maiſter Southworth willed to go vp to the greene chamber, for that there was ſuch a Prieſt talking with Mary: who in all haſt went vp, and finding the Prieſt not in the chamber with Mary, he looked into the Study within the chamber, and found him there with an engliſh booke in his hand, whereat he was offended. Now (ſayth maiſter Weston) you ſee matter ſufficiēt for to leade you to giue ſentence with vs. Indeed (ſayth Doctor Bauyn) this is a matter that moueth me to be willing to giue my iudgement: what thinke you maiſter Dolman? The Romanes being Pagans (quoth M. Dolman) would not condemne S. Paul vpon the requeſt, and accuſations of the Iewes, before they heard Paul defend himſelf in a publick place: and ſhall we here cōdemne a Prieſt, and in him, 12. more, vnheard, vnexamined, and no place of defence left them? Maiſter Ba. I will not do it: but I will heare what the Prieſt can ſay for himſelfe. I do not thinke (quoth Bau.) that we can doe ſo: for this matter is vttered to vs in ſecret, not to be opened againe. How then, ſhal we pronounce an externall ſentence (quoth maiſter Dolman) as we are externall iudges, and condemne theſe 13. but it muſt be knowne? Well, well, this is very ſtrange: and ſo that matter was daſht.
            If maiſter Agent and Doct. Bauyn had proceeded with the reſt of their ſuppoſed enormious crimes againſt vs (ſo many as filled vp three ſheetes of paper) and that M. Dolman would haue bin aduiſed by thē: you ſee what a prety courſe of iuſtice would haue bin held in theſe aſſiſes. What all thoſe ſeuerall accuſatiōs were, we could neuer haue the fauour to be informed: either by M. Agent or his aſſiſtants. You may ſuppoſe they were not great, in that we had been receyued with great applauſe, as companyons with them of their holy order: if we would but haue yeelded to

Fa. Ed. Weſtons Agenage, thereby admitting a kinde of Fryer to be the head of ſecular Prieſts: as rare a deuiſe, as lightly hath hapned. But to returne where we left. A ſeparation is made, and maiſter Agent is in his ruffe, ſitting in a corner with his obedient ſubiects. If we ſhould haue tearmed him Vſher of their new Hall, which was his owne chamber, and maiſter Brampston in the like reſpect, their chiefe maiſter Cooke, hauing good oportunitie, though he had lyen in his bed, to haue ruled the roaſt: the phraſes had not bin very improper. Howbeit, ſuch manner of conceits were then farre from vs: our hearts being very greatly repleniſhed with griefe, to ſee ſo many of our brethren Catholicke Prieſts, and impriſoned for the ſame cauſe with vs, ſo irreligiouſly to ſeparate themſelues from vs. Beſides: we were otherwiſe ſet on worke by them, in laboring to defend our ſelues from their diueliſh practiſes in ſlaundering of vs: as though we had bin the men, that had made the faction, and not they: whereas it was moſt apparant to thoſe that would not ſhut their eyes, that we ſwarued not one iot from that courſe which had bin held both by vs, and our very honorable &amp; reuerend predeceſſors in that priſon: as mē that deteſted ſuch childiſh innouatiōs. Furthermore, our ſayd griefe was greatly increaſed, in that we were daily aduertiſed from our friends abroad, how many Catholicks in euery corner (otherwiſe very graue and zealous) began to fauour this new deuiſe: being poſſeſſed with a conceit, that we (formerly reputed their deere and louing fathers) were become on the ſodaine, without any change at all in vs, perſons of great licentiouſnes; ſuch as could neither indure any good order nor holeſome diſcipline. Lord (thought we) whither do theſe things tend: or what will be come of the moſt auncient and Catholick Romane Religion; if the old and conſtant profeſſors thereof do begin to

delight in change and innouations? And here by the way, we would gladly haue it obſerued, that as well in all the aforeſaid garboyles, as in the reſt that follow hereafter: we that ſtoode for vnitie, haue alwaies been in effect meerely paſſiue, ſtanding ſtill vpon our defence: our aduerſaries (for ſo our brethren did make themſelues) practiſing their beſt actiuitie to hurt and wound'vs.
            For to keepe their hands and tongues in vre, this Gentlemā our ſaid new Agent was no ſooner inueſted in his Ieſuiticall authoritie, but preſently he ſendeth abroad certaine reaſons (fiue in number) to his friends, leaſt he ſhould (forſooth) haue been miſtaken in his ſaid publike ſeparation from vs. In which pretended reaſons, many points being childiſh, and many falſe, we hold them not fit to be here inſerted: only we haue mentioned them, becauſe they driue vs againe to our Apologie, by incountring them with fiue others, which we will alſo pretermit: the fact it ſelfe attempted by the Agent and his confederats being ſo abſurd, and ſchiſmatically handled, as whoſoeuer doth well know it, his owne reaſon and iudgement (if he haue any) are ſufficient to condemne it.
            You haue heard at large before of our troubles, which Doctor Ba. and maiſter Dolman would gladly (wee are perſwaded) at the firſt, haue compounded, but as the matter fell out, their paines therein, did not only, not end them, but through maiſter Agents Ieſuiticall skill in ſhifting and falſe gloſing, were the beginning of other new garboyles. For he hauing gotten into his hands certaine writings and letters of Doct. Bauyns, did pretend and giue it out amongſt his friends, that he and his adherents had been very willing to haue entred into any good pacification, had we not been ſo obſtinate as no reaſon would content vs. He ſhewed ſome Prieſts of the ſaid Doctors letters,

wherein (as it ſhould ſeeme) he affirmed, that their ſeparation was in effect, no ſeparation. Beſides, it was giuen out, that we vtterly refuſed to haue the crimes obiected againſt vs, ſifted by the arbitrators and looked into. Againe, they ſaid, that we hauing giuen the ſaid Commiſſioners full authoritie to decide all matters betwixt vs, did for feare, or becauſe we would be ſtill wilfull in our diſorderly courſes, reuoke the ſame: ſo as thereby nothing could bee effected. Alſo they quarrelled with vs concerning our yeelding to haue receiued ſuch new lawes, as the Arbitrators ſhould thinke good to impoſe vpon vs. All which particulars, with many more ſuch like, being moſt falſly layd to our charges, they went from hand to hand, farre and neere, and were receiued by ſuch Catholicks, as began to be infected with Ieſuitiſme, as if they had been true: thereby taking occaſion to depraue vs exceedingly. Inſomuch as the good old Father maiſter Dolman was driuen to write diuers letters, for the cleering of the ſaid falſe accuſations, and was ſo earneſt in them, as theſe and diuers others ſuch like ſentences fell ſometimes from his pen: Detrahere, aut detrahentem audire quid horum ſit damnabilus non facile dixerim: it is hard to ſay, whether is the greater ſinne to be a ſlaunderer, or giue eare vnto him: ſub Christi ſpecie daemon inique lates? thou art diſguiſed (Sathan) in the habite of Chriſt? O ſecula nostra, hoc phariſaiſmo pleniſſima! our times are pestered with phariſaicall hypocriſie!
            
            
               By theſe and ſuch like courſes which this Ieſuitical faction did thus practiſe againſt vs, the Catholickes abroad were greatlie diſtracted: ſome leaned to vs, but more inclined to them: it being the fatall calamitie of our Nation to be too much addicted to faction and nouelties. They of the new guiſe, ſent vs word that in oppoſing our ſelues againſt the Ieſuits, wee laboured but in vaine, and loſt thereby our reputation: that

order being of ſuch excellencie, as it might not be withſtood. An other writ vnto vs a long diſcourſe, dated the 26. of Iune 1595, how vnwilling the Ieſuits are to take vpon them anie ſuperioritie: that Father Westons Agencie was not worthie to be tearmed by the name of ſuperiority, becauſe it was not praeeſſe ſed prodeſſe: that Cardinall Allen a little before had willed ſundrie Priestes that came for England, to acknowledge the Ieſuits for ſuch men, as had beene their ſuperiours and maisters: and that therefore, they ſhould make no difference but keepe peace with them, and goe vnto them for their aduiſe and direction. And afterward in the ſame letter, the Catholickes (ſaith he) are ſo wholie affected to the ſociety, &amp; haue them in ſuch estimation, that whoſoeuer ſhall ſhew himſelfe to fauour anie part against them, or not ſo throughlie to affect them, yea though he be one of our owne coate (meaning a Prieſt) hee ſhall be leſſe gratefull and welcome to them. And a third: in his letter dated in Auguſt 1595. the ſame yeere, writeth thus vnto vs: I can aſſure you, that in the generall opinion of the beſt ſort of Catholickes, the tide is againſt you; and if you loue me, contend not with Father Weston. This and much ſuch like ſtuffe wee receiued from the fancifull. But on the other ſide, they that plodded in the old ſteps of antiquitie, and had a great diſguſt of nouelties, did now and then write vnto vs, after another ſort: Sometimes they ſignified vnto vs with great indignation, the abuſes offered vnto vs, how our fellow priſoners of the faction did write in ſuch manner againſt vs, and they were in horrour to thinke of it: and how alſo the gallants abroad (being at libertie) did inſult vpon our miſeries, treading vs vnder their feet, as though no ſecular Prieſt were worthie to be named the ſame day, that mention is made of a holie Ieſuit. And ſome of great fame ſaid vnto others, that Father Westons ſeparation from vs, was ſo odious, as they thought it expedient in their opinions, that ſeeing

they deuided themſelues from our table, wee ſhould deuide our ſelues from their prayers. An other moued vs to this effect: that ſeeing the old ſigillum Salomonis, and our Sauiours direction failed, wee would inuent ſome new pentacle to binde theſe furious ſpirits (meaning the Ieſuiticall faction) which will do much hurt, if God be not mercifull, and men prouident. An other alſo in one mans perſon deſcribeth vnto vs, the right qualities of our Engliſh Ieſuits, as wee our ſelues haue found by experience, and the world in the end ſhall trie them. The man he writeth of, is now one of the aſſiſtants to the Archprelate: and theſe are his words: he is the Ieſuits Curſitor, alwaies in motion for them, either for gathering of monie, or for harkening after newes. If he can learne of any legacy giuen to your houſe, he ſeeketh by all the meanes he may, to conuert it from you to their vſes, ſo (as I verilie thinke) there is not of a Prieſt a greater enemie to your companie then he is. Notwithstanding if he talke with anie, yea, that he likes not, he will moſt palpablie flatter him; but behinde his backe hee will moſt monstrouſlie detract him. Let him be told againe of it in ſuch ſound manner, as with no face he may denie it; then hee looketh a while vp to the heauens, and after anſwereth: hee remembreth no ſuch matter. Neuertheles for humilities ſake, he will ſay he will render what ſatisfaction you will: and ſo with that geſture, and this hypocriſie, hee will ſhuffle ouer all matters, be they neuer ſo foule, that he ſhall be charged with. O Lord graunt him better grace. And ſome there haue bin, who haue by their letters, bin ſo farre from diſliking of our proceedings at that time: as in Iulie 1595. they moued vs earneſtlie to continue, as wee had begun, and in no wiſe to giue place to faction, and nouelties: adding that they had not talked with any, that were either of learning or iudgement, which did not greatlie condemne father Weston for his vnquietnes: deeming him either to be growne into great melancholines, or els vnto too much ſimplicitie. We
               
               ſpare to trouble you with more to this effect; our purpoſe onlie being in this point to let you ſee the diuiſion in the Church: procured by this breach amongſt vs then at Wiſbich. Whereof a godlie father writing thus generallie vnto vs al, ſaith: if through the continuance of your diſſentions and diſcord, you will ſo greatly terrifie vs, as we ſhall think: our holie anchor drayling a floote: our viſible Church to be hid vnder a buſhell: our forme (through the great good conceit wee abroad had of you) of heauen, to be now a figure of hell: looke then hereafter for ſmal commiſeration &amp; pitty, when too late you ſhall lament your incurable woe, which by giuing the full reynes to your paſſions, you haue indrenched and implunged your ſelues into.
            But howſoeuer at this time, many Catholicks were growne to be of Father Westons faction: yet it ſeemeth that ſome of themſelues, who beſt knew the impietie of it, &amp; what a dangerous ſcandall it gaue to the Catholicke cauſe, began to draw backe, as repenting verie much that euer the ſaid Agenage was attempted. For if M. Perpoint the lay Ieſuit, be an honeſt man, and his report to M. Dolman true, made in Iulie 1595. M. Garnet himſelfe vpon occaſion ſaid: that he was neuer willing with the breach or diuiſion of commons: which being made plaine to him the ſaid M. Perpoint to be as falſe as God is true, his owne letters teſtifiyng the contrarie, he the ſaid M. Perpoint anſwered, that he was well aſſured of it, that M. Garnet did now vtterlie miſlike it. Whether this laſt cauſe was true or no, it doth not much concerne vs, becauſe no man is able to bind vpon any Ieſuits word, they haue ſo manie ſhifts, and ſo little conſcience in ſpeaking truelie, except it be one of themſelues to another. Otherwiſe their manner is, to frame their ſpeeches, according to their companie: alwaies applying themſelues to the times and occaſions, as they fall out: if their diſſeignements proue wel,

they take the contriuing ofthem to themſelues: if not, there is none will more condemne them: vtterlie renouncing them, as hauing neuer liked them, or conſented vnto them. Some further experience hereof, you ſhall finde in the proceſſe following concerning this good Prouinciall.
            You haue heard before in ſome ſort, how we were vſed by the aforeſaid faction amongſt vs at home, and by their adherents abroad in deprauing vs, and ſlaundering vs, farre beyond the limits of all Chriſtianitie. They charged vs to be ſtraglers, backbiters, liuers vpon rapine, extortioners, impugners of order, men of confuſion, violent perſons, deteyners of other mens goods, and with we know not how manie other impieties: whereof our conſciences beare vs witneſſe, wee were as cleare and free as the beſt Ieſuit in Chriſtendome. Neither durſt the diuell himſelfe haue bin ſo impudent (as we ſuppoſe) to haue fraught their hearts with theſe conceits of vs, or framed their tongues to haue vttered them, had hee not firſt inueagled them with this moſt odious opinion: That detractiō in generall (ſo that a ſingular perſon be not named) is no offence. Vpon which ground, they ranne a great while, not daring to touch vs with any particularities till at the laſt in plaine termes, they laid theft in effect to ſome of our charges. Now theſe and ſuch other like reports, flying farre and neere againſt vs, as though we had bin not Catholike Prieſts, but diuels incarnate, it pleaſed God to moue the diſcreeter ſort of Catholickes in the North, to ſend vnto vs about a quarter of a yeere (after the aforeſaid ſeparation of commons) two learned Prieſts, M. Muſh, and M. Dudley, to ſee and vnderſtand how matters went with vs, and whether wee were ſuch men, as the reports (made by our aduerſaries) went of vs. Theſe two, both of them very diſcreete and zealous perſons, men of great traueile

and paines in their vocations, and of eſpeciall eſtimation in the parts of their abode, for their great wiſedome, learning, and ſinceritie, comming vnto vs, and finding ſuch garboyles amongſt vs: they ſo demeaned themſelues, as on all ſides, we were content to impart our griefes vnto them, and to be aduiſed by them. Whereupon, after the debating of manie things, hauing conſidered with themſelues, what courſe it were beſt to hold, for the repayring of the rent that was amongſt vs (ſo ſcandalous and offenſiue to all true Catholickes) they drew twelue articles, wherof one was, that wee ſhould all ioyne againe in commons in the common Hall: and the reſt did containe ſuch other orders, as they thought meete for quietneſſe to be obſerued by the whole companie. Which articles, they firſt offered to M. Weston and his fauourers to be peruſed, allowed, and ſubſcribed by them: but they albeit they ſhewed then no diſlike of them, yet they intreated M. Muſh and M. Dudley to carrie the ſame, firſt vnto M. D. Bagſhaw and M. Bluet (hoping as the euent declared) that they would preſentlie haue reiected them, as they had done before D. Bauyns ten men and the mouth: whereby hee himſelfe, and his adherents might haue more iuſt colour likewiſe to diſclame them. But contrarie to his expectation, wee of the vnitie, hauing well conſidered them, did preſentlie without any further delay, ſubſcribe vnto them verie willinglie and readilie. Whereat maiſter Agent and his ſubiects were much amazed: and in fine it pleaſed the good Father vtterlie in effect to reiect them: ſaying, that hee and his, had certaine rules of their owne approued vnto them, which they muſt follow, &amp; minded not now to alter or change them, for theſe which they offered or any ſuch like. Hereupon maiſter Muſh and maiſter Dudley (ſuppoſing they ſhould not be able to doe any good amongſt vs) left vs: and tooke

their iournie towards London, of purpoſe to conferre with the Catholickes there, about theſe matters and ſcandals amongſt vs. At their comming to the Citie, they found the laytie generally, &amp; likewiſe manie of the Cleargie, exceeding ſtiffely bent to iuſtifie maiſter Weston, with all his proceedings, and to condemne vs, eſpeciallie D. Bagſhaw, and maiſter Bluet, as men of no worth, vnrulie, diſordered, and diſobedient perſons, not to be fauoured or reſpected by any. Beſides, ſuch a preiudicial opinion, they perceiued to haue poſſeſſed mens hearts, through their admiration of Ieſuitiſme, as if the Catholicke faith had neuer beene trulie preached, nor any good order rightlie eſtabliſhed, or practiſed, by vs poore ſecular Prieſts, or any of our predeceſſors: before theſe yonkers thruſt thēſelues, with high lookes and great bragges into our labours, and that it might be ſufficient for vs, if we might haue but ſome curateſhippes to ſay Maſſe, and ſo much fauour as to attend vpon them, to know their maiſterſhippes pleaſures what they would commaund vs. Theſe two godlie Prieſts, ſeeing the violence of this ſtreame, offered at the firſt but little reſiſtance: but as though they had inclined to the imputations againſt D. Bagſhaw and maiſter Bluet, drew forth their ſaid articles before mentioned: and hauing read them in the hearing of ſome principall Catholickes, addicted as you haue heard, deſired their iudgements of them: who (thinking they had beene maiſter Westons rules) did anſwere verie readilie, that they were reaſonable, diſcreet and godlie: ſuch as no honeſt Prieſt would, or could refuſe to admit &amp; allow of. And theſe be the articles (quoth maiſter Muſh) that D. Bagſhaw and the reſt of the vnited companie haue very willinglie ſubſcribed vnto: but haue beene verie peremptorilie reiected by Father Weston and the ninteene his adherents: whereby you ſee, that matters goe not at Wiſbich,
               
as (I well perceiue) you haue beene informed. Here they that were ſo readie to condemne vs, began to bluſh, and hold downe their heads, being willing to heare and know, what before (like proper iudges condemning Catholicke Prieſtes vnheard vpon an imagined opinion that the Ieſuits could not doe amiſſe) they would not indure to heare mentioned. So as after true knowledge, taken of the eſtate and diſpoſition of both ſides, and remēbring what letters Father Weston &amp; his adherents had ſent abroad againſt D. Bagſhaw and maiſter Bluet, and the reſt of the thirteene vnited to the effect, that no Catholicks ſhould ſend them any reliefe, or countenance them, that therby through want, they might be compelled to yeeld to the regiment impoſed vpon them by Father Garnet: they repented them of ſome courſes, which formerly they had held againſt vs: and deſired verie inſtantlie theſe two learned Prieſts to goe back againe to Wiſbich, and to ſpare no paines, vntill they had brought vs all to peace &amp; concord, giuing them great thanks, praiſe, and benediction, for that which they had done alreadie. Whereunto they anſwered, that they could be well content, to ſpend if it were their liues to bring that to paſſe; but at Wiſbich, they thought they could doe no good, except they could firſt perſwade him to order, who had been the authour and contriuer of thoſe nouelties (which had procured ſuch garboyles there) and that was (as they were informed) Father Garnet the Prouinciall of the Ieſuits. If we can (ſayd they) bring him to argue with vs touching that action, we doubt not, but that we ſhall preuaile with him: and then our trouble is in effect at an end before we begin: Eius eſt ſoluere, cuius eſt ligare; his letters to maister Weston &amp; his fauourers, were the cauſe of their ſeparation, and a word from him, will be ſufficient to reunite them. Now (as God would haue it) it ſo fell out, that according to their deſire, they met with maiſter Garnet,
               
who at their firſt incounter, ſeemed to be inexorable, affirming that he ſaw no reaſon why the Ieſuits might not gouerne, and haue as well the preheminence ouer all the ſecular prieſts in England, as they had at Rome, ouer the Engliſh Seminarie. With which proude anſwere they were ſomewhat ſharpened, and entred more roundlIe into farther communication with him: no whit fearing to tell him what they thought, aſwell of his ſaid wordes vnto them, as of other the Ieſuits proceedings in matters of ſtate, ſucceſſion of the Crowne, and ſuch like (hauing latelie peruſed maiſter Parſons booke of titles:) and alſo what account the ſecular Prieſts haue had with all true Catholickes, before his ſocietie was borne, and muſt ſtill haue of neceſſitie, except God in his ſecret iudgement, doe purpoſe ſome greater ouerthrow to the Catholicke faith, then they relying vpon his mercie, did any wayes expect. Manie words paſſed betwixt them, and ſome in ſuch heat, as he threatned to be euen with them for their good wils to the Ieſuits: but in the end hee was content to yeeld vnto them, and bidding them farewell, did write his letters to maiſter Weston, D. Bagſhaw and ſome others, of his pleaſure and purpoſe, that the ſaid Agencie ſhould be committed to their further conſideration, to be either retained, or diſanulled, as they ſhould thinke meete: very hartilie deſiring them ſo to compound all matters amongſt themſelues, as that hereafter they might liue in quietnes.
            
               Amongſt many fayre floriſhes, vſed by him to maiſter Doctor Bagſhaw, he writeth thus: Edmundum meū tibi ſocium &amp; adiutorem adhibeo. In this buſines, I aſſigne vnto you, as your company on and aſſistant, my beloued maiſter Edmonds. And againe: hiſce ego literis eum vehementer moneo &amp;c. by theſe my letters to you, I do earneſtly admoniſh him (maiſter Edmonds) alias Weston, and alſo

in the name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and in the vertue of his obedience, commaund him, that he apply his minde ſeriouſly to the propounding and establiſhing of ſome rules, whereby an honeſt and firme friendſhip may grow and continue amongst you. And in an other of his letters to a friend of his in Wiſbich at that time, he ſayth after this ſort: I do determine, that if an agreement be not now made, to write to the 20. that Fa. Edmonds may liue priualty as the reſt, all or ſome by courſe performing that which was laid vpon him. What he writ to Fa. Weston we know not: but craftily inough, we are aſſured by his practiſes towards vs ſince: being as meere a Ieſuite, as if he had bin ſpit out of Fa. Parſons mouth.
            
            The aforeſayd two godly Prieſts, hauing wrought with maiſter Garnet as you haue heard, returned to Wiſbich, where notwithſtanding the ſayd letters, they found Fa. Weston exceeding loth to lay downe the ſcepter of his Agencie, caſting out ſome words, as though he had not bin bound in that caſe to the obedience of his Prouinciall. Howbeit maiſter Muſh, and maiſter Dudley ſo vrged him before all the company, that ſundry of his owne adherents, perceiuing how the matter went, began to draw back from him, and ſayd, they would haue peace with their brethren, and diuide themſelues no longer from them. Whereupon (quoth maiſter Weſton) very pitifully: Ha, my maiſters, will you for ſake me thus? I would neuer haue left you, but ſith it is ſo, I am content to giue ouer: and thus ſpeaking, corruit inter manus diſcipulorū, he fell downe as if he had bin in a ſwoune, and much ado there was in recouering him. This entrance towards our vnity being made, then many things came in courſe to be debated, and particularly the report of theft publiſhed abroade by them of the Agenage: viz. that maiſter Bluet and maiſter Potter had riotouſly deteyned from them ſo much Pewter, and other furniture, as amounted

to the value of 17. pound, and that they could haue no iuſtice for the recouering of it. And firſt for the better triall thereof, Fa. Weston, maiſter Bluet, and maiſter Potter, were required by the ſayd two Prieſts, that they would cauſe all the Pewter, and other kitchin furniture which they had in their hands, ſeuerally to be brought forth: which was done by them all accordingly. Then maiſter Muſh and maiſter Dudley, ſent for a Pewterer, and willed him to view all the ſayd Pewter, and kitchin furniture, and to tell them truly, what he iudged it to be worth: which vpon due conſideration, and view had of it by the ſayd party, he affirmed it to be all ſcarce worth foure pound. Well then (ſayd maiſter Muſh) yeſterday, you maiſter mine (naming the partie) exclaimed that we had not the courage to ſay with Saint Iohn Baptiſt, non licet tibi habere, but now we aunſwere, that although we are not comparable to Saint Iohn Baptiſt, yet as Prieſts muſt tell you playnely: non licet, it is not lawfull for you to infame and belye your fellow-priſoners, as we find you haue dealt with M. Bluet, and M. Potter. For we ſaw your letters abroade, wherein you charged them two, to with-hold from you 17. pound value in Pewter and kitchin furniture: and now we ſee, that all that both you and they haue, is ſcarce worth 4. pound. And therefore we ſay againe with Saint Iohn Baptiſt: non licet. You ought not ſo to haue belyed them, but are bound in conſcience to aske them forgiuenes: and with your ſecond letters to reuoke this ſlaunder that you haue ſo rayſed againſt them: which if you ſhall refuſe to do, we muſt be glad to do it for you. Now it is to be obſerued, that when maiſter Weston and his adherents diuided themſelues from vs, and made maiſter Brampstons chamber their kitchin, they found an oportunity to go into the common kitchin, and tooke from thence ſuch Pewter and

other furniture, as had bin prouided, and euer before vſed for the company in the common Hall; and afterwards thought it a kinde of theft, that any was deteyned from them, but that they might haue had all.
            Theſe matters and others likewiſe, theſe two good Prieſts hauing compounded amongſt vs, they fell to the draught of new Articles, increaſing the ſaid 12. after much diſcuſſing of them on all ſides to the number of 19. Whereunto we all ſubſcribed in the yere 1595. the 6. of Nouember; and ſo after our long diſſenſions, a generall peace was concluded to our great contentment, we dare be bold to ſay it; and maiſter Weston and his friends returned vnto vs againe, and tooke their commons with vs in the common Hall, as before their breach made they were accuſtomed. Now we being all of vs thus reunited, not long after it pleaſed maiſter Garnet to write an other letter to maiſter Doctor Bagſhaw, dated the 17. of Nouember 1595. Wherein it is very ſtrange to conſider, what ioy he pretendeth in that behalfe, whereas indeed, we are able to affirme it vpon our owne knowledges, that the ouerthrow of maiſter Westons agencie went to his heart: we meane vexed him, and angred him exceedingly. But heare the diueliſh Politician how he transformeth himſelfe into an angell of light. When the bleſſed ſoules in heauen (ſayth he) did ſing with one conſent, Glory be to God on high, you at Wiſbich preached, and restored comfort and in earth peace to men of good will: then no doubt the princes went before, the ſingers followed after, and in the middeſt were the damſels playing on their tymbrels. Alſo he telleth vs, that as there is a coelestiall Hierarchy in Heauen, ſo we had then an other at Wiſbich, which all England did reuerence: which the Queene of Saba admired: and which many from the vttermoſt borders of the earth came to ſee and behold: adding, that thoſe men were bleſſed together with our ſeruants that ſtood in our preſence,
               
               that heard our wiſedome, and beheld our mutuall loue. Hereunto alſo, it may pleaſe you, that we adde ſome other words of his written to maiſter Doctor Bagſhaw two yeres before, after himſelfe had bin with vs at Wiſbich in the yeare 1593. concerning his iudgement of our whole company at that time: I aſſure you (ſayth he) that the being with you hath wrought ſuch effect in the barts of all that were with me (being indeed three or four Gentlemen, whom we afterwards tearmed his Deacons, and Subdeacons) that they neuer ſaw place or perſons which more delighted them: and for mine owne part, I tell you very ſincerely, that it was the greateſt comfort to be amongst you, which I had theſe whole ſeauen yeeres. Testis enim mihi eſt Deus, quomodo cupiam omnes vos in viſceribus Ieſu Christi: Which ſentence of S. Paule being read that very day in the Epistle in the Church, when I came firſt vnto you, with other many moſt comfortable ſentences, I was both not a little recreated, with a conſcience of an vnfeyned loue towards euery one of you, and moued to thanke God almighty, Super communicatione vestra in Euangelio Christi à prima die vſque nunc: conſiderans quia qui caepit in vobis opus bonum, perficiet, ſicut eſt mihi iuſtum ſentire de omnibus vobis: And (that which contented me moſt of all) comforted with an aſſured hope, that you are they, who in your ſingular charities will haue me dayly in corde &amp; in vinculis vestris, &amp; in defenſione &amp; confirmatione Euangelij ſocium gaudij veſtri. Hitherto maiſter Garnet then: and now againe in the letter before mentioned he profeſſeth: that being at that time with vs, he thought himſelfe all that while to haue felt the ioyes of Heauen. Now we referre our ſelues and our cauſe to your conſiderations, to iudge as God ſhall mooue you: If he the ſayd Garnet did thinke then truly of vs, and writ ſincerely as he thought, what cauſe had his ſubiect maiſter Weston before the yere 1593. or afterwards, we continuing as before we were, to moyle and

make a faction amongſt vs for the ſetting vp of his Agency, as though we had bin not ſuch men, as maiſter Garnet ſayth he found vs, but as Fa. Weston to colour his ambition reputed vs, that is, perſons of all diſorder, licentionſnes, and confuſion. And againe if maiſter Garnet at his being with vs three or foure dayes, did thinke himſelfe all that while in Heauen: what a hell did he afterwards finde in his conſcience, when he had bin the chiefe cauſe that Father Weſton and his adherents did ſeparate themſelues from vs. Moreouer if the ſayd letter congratulatorie for our vniting proceeded from maiſter Garnets hart: and that thereby we were indeed in his opinion ſo charitable, ſo wiſe, and ſo admirable perſons: how iuſtly may all Catholicks, that tooke part with the ſayd ſeparators from vs, and factious againſt vs, blame and condemne themſelues, in that we continuing our former courſes without alteration, either in our conuerſation, or in our regiment (if it may ſo be tearmed) from the time that maiſter Garnet was with vs, vnto the very inſtant of our ſayd reconciliation: the ioyning againe of maiſter VVeston and his adherents vnto vs, is now reckoned by him the ſayd maiſter Garnet to be a matter ſo glorious both to God and men, as he hath deſcribed it. But we will proceede.
            The aforeſayd Agencie being thus ouerthrowne, and a peace concluded amongſt vs, we for our parts, were repleniſhed with great ioy: but you are farre deceiued, as we our ſelues were, if you thinke as we then thought: that either maiſter Garnet, maiſter VVeſton, or their Ieſuiticall crue, did take this ſo great a foyle in good part: we afterwards perceiued to our griefe, that maiſter Weston would neuer haue yeelded to haue ioyned in commons with vs againe, except maiſter Muſh, and maiſter Dudley vnder-hand had conſented vnto them, that if afterwards he and his

company ſhould thinke it conuenient to ſeparate themſelues againe from vs, they ſhould haue theſe, and thoſe roomes, ſuch a table in the Hall, ſuch a place for their Kitchin, and ſuch other roomes, as they held conuenient for them: all which they ſet downe particularlie vnder their hands, and left the ſame ſealed vp with them: which God knoweth, wee neuer dreamed of. Beſides, maiſter VVeston did not long ſit at the vpper Table with vs, and below maiſter Bluet, and Doctor Bagſhaw, where his due place was, but that he deſired, and had it eaſily graunted vnto him, that he might leaue his ſaid place, and ſit in ſome other as he thought good Whereupon as diſdaining to ſit where he did before, he bound himſelfe afterwards to no certaine place, but ſate (you muſt thinke) for humilities ſake, now here, now there, as he liſt. Moreouer notwithſtanding our ſayd reunion, ſuch abroade as had depraued vs poore Prieſts, and charged vs as you haue heard: did continue (to ſhew their conſtancie in their former good wils towards vs) iuſtifying in their common aſſemblies, what before they had reported of vs. Maiſter Dolman who dealt like a very honeſt man, to haue compounded all ſtrifes amongſt vs, as is before expreſſed, was likewiſe very ſharply galled by them, becauſe he deemed their ſayd ſeparation from vs to be a ſinne, and that he had before greatly blamed them for making the Chappell at VViſbich their Buttery. Which particulars being reprochfully caſt into his teeth, he maynteyned his former aſſertions: adding, that by their ſayd prophaning that Chappell, they were ſcandalous, ſacrilegious, irregular, and excommunicated perſons. Whereof maiſter Garnet hauing notice, he deſired maiſter Doctor Bagſhaw, by his letter to pacifie and ſtay maiſter Dolman, from theſe or any ſuch like ſpeeches, which might tend to the renewing of the memorie of our former breach. Which maiſter Doctor Bagſhaw
               
vndertooke, putting him the ſayd Fa. Garnet, notwithſtanding in minde how vilely he the ſayd maister Dolman had bin dealt with, by ſuch as he the ſayd Garnet had great intereſt in: in that firſt Fa. Parſons had ſet out the booke of Titles in maister Dolmans name, which (notwithstanding that he detested the contents of it) might haue brought him into great danger: and ſecondly, for that one (a ieſuite) vnder his commaund, had very cunningly thruſt him out of a place, where of long time he had found great entertaynement, and ſo wrought, as foure pound yerely haue ſince bin deteyned from him, which was giuen vnto him, as a legacy by will. Againe: within ſome quarter of a yere, after our ſayd eſtabliſhed concord, great hartburning grew, and many ſlaunderous ſpeeches were caſt abroade againſt ſome of vs by maiſter Weston and his old friends, concerning a prieſt and priſoner with vs, his eſcape 
                  ••
               om Wiſbich: who being aduiſed ſo to do by ſome of that crue, and with Fa. VVestons priuitie, 
                  •
               is taking againe was aſcribed by them to maiſter Doctor Bagſhaw and ſome others: which gaue not only them occaſion, but many of their friends abroad to write and rayle againſt vs exceedingly. Not long after, viz. in September, maiſter Archer a Ieſuite (that liued with vs in priſon) gaue an other occaſion of very great garboyles by affirming that the ſtewes in Rome were there cum approbatione (teſtified vnder the hands of Doctor Norden, maiſter Buckley, maiſter Meredith, and Doctor Bagſhaw:) that the ſtewes were as lawfull in Rome, as any Citizen there: (teſtified vnder the hands of Doctor Norden, maiſter Buckley, and maiſter Meredith:) that the ſtewes were in Rome, as lawfully as any Magiſtrate in that Citie: (teſtified vnder the hands of Doctor Norden, and Doctor Bagſhaw:) that the ſtewes were in Rome as lawfully as the Pope himſelfe, or any order of religious men (teſtified vnder the hand of Doctor Norden, and Doctor Bagſhaw:) and

that they were moſt neceſſarie (teſtified vnder the hands of Doctor Norden, maiſter Buckley, and Doctor Bagſhaw.) Which very lewde aſſertions, comming to Fa. Westons eares, and vnderſtanding how they were impugned by maiſter D. Norden, he the ſayd M. Weſton, did take vpon him by a fond and falſe diſtinction to defend them. Whereupon maiſter Doctor Bagſhaw being drawne into that oppoſition, diuers long treatiſes paſſed betwixt him, and Fa. Weston: he the ſayd maiſter Doctor Bagſhaw impugning thoſe lewde poſitions, and maiſter VVeston with all his ſhifts and skill laboring to defend them. About theſe points, there grew ſuch parts-taking and hatred, as that the ſayd orders eſtabliſhed amongſt vs by maiſter Muſh and maiſter Dudley, (in that they croſſed theſe and ſuch like demeanors) were in the latter end of the yeare 1596. vtterly caſhierd and reiected. So as notwithſtanding we kept commons ſtill in the Hall together: we liued (God knoweth) there with great diſquietnes: many of our old friends abroad being ſo farre drawne to Ieſuitiſme, as that they blamed vs, and tooke part with them in defence of theſe ſo abhominable abſurdities.
            And now it may pleaſe you to leaue vs in our ſayd troubles and diſcontentments, and to be aduertiſed of the beginning of a more bitter tragedie. Whileſt after our ſaid peace we were lulled aſleepe for a time in VViſbich, by maiſter Garnets inchaunting letter of congratulation, and exerciſed with the vniuſt afflictions of our brethren, as before we haue touched: he the ſayd maiſter Garnet with his complices beſtirred themſelues, and that ſecretly, ſo as then we did not ſuſpect, or looke for any further plots to be in contriuing againſt vs. We will be bold to acquaint you with one of their notable ſtratagemes, which argueth more wit and foreſight, then playne dealing or honeſtie.

It appeareth that by the Ieſuites practiſes here amongſt vs, in diſgracing and abuſing the ſecular prieſts very ſhamefully, there was ſome rumor thereof in Rome, to the great impeachment of the Ieſuites credits there, being then as turbulent in that Citie in their dealing with our Engliſh Seminary, as they had bin, and were ſtill firebrands amongſt vs. For the better incountering of which rumor, it being thought inconuenient, that any of their owne calling by commending themſelues, ſhould take vpon them that office, a ſecular prieſt was found out, a man of a quicker penne, then either of wiſedome or ſinceritie: who being well acquainted with all the iarres and quarrels betwixt vs, and the Ieſuites; and hauing written himſelfe a letter vnto vs, as preſuming to aduiſe men of farre greater experience then himſelfe, concerning our troubles about the ſayd Agencie: this man (we ſay) did ſo harden his forehead, or in his ſimplicitie was ſo ſeduced, as contrary to his owne conſcience he writ the tenth of Ianuary 1596. to Card. Caietan
                     •
                  , Protector of the Engliſh Seminary, in the behalfe of the Ieſuites, a moſt falſe and impudent letter. Wherein amongſt many other things, he aſſureth the Cardinall, that of his owne knowledge, for twenty yeeres, there had not bin any diſſenſion betwixt the ſecular prieſts and the Ieſuites: and that the reports made againſt theſe good Fathers, concerning their ambition, were ſo farre from the truth, as that indeed the Ieſuites were in all places moſt notable examples to the ſecular prieſts of ſingular humilitie, gentlenes, patience, pietie, and charitie. The letter it ſelfe with ſome obſeruations vpon it, you ſhall finde amongſt other things to this ſtory annexed. With this cunning trick of theſe good Fathers, we were not then acquainted: it was well handled of them, that they had got ſo falſe a brother frō amongſt our ſelues to fit their deſeignements

ſo aptly, that is ſo lewdly, according to their deſire.
            After that maiſter Weston had begun his ſaid Agencie, as hath been before mentioned, our brethren abroad of the grauer and wiſer ſort, began to foreſee: that if the ſame did continue, maiſter Garnet would ſhortly after, as well by M. Weſtons example in Wiſbich, as alſo by the example of the Ieſuits gouernment of the Seminarie at Rome, challenge, and take vnto himſelfe, ere it were long, the Prelacie and gouernment ouer all the Prieſts in England. For the preuenting whereof, as alſo there being many Catholicke Prieſts in England, and many wants, as of authoritie of confirmation for the full accompliſhing of the effects of Baptiſme, and of holy oyle, being of ſo neceſſarie imployment, they thought it conuenient to deuiſe certaine orders, for a general aſſociation, amongſt all ſecular Prieſts: and in the end concluded to referre the eſtate of our Church here, together with their reaſons and moſt humble ſupplication to the Popes Holines, that it might ſtand with his good pleaſure (if he thought it conuenient) to graunt vnto them that they might haue ſome Biſhop or ſuffragane here: as he had yeelded heretofore to our brethren in Ireland. In theſe conſultations, one maſter Standiſh a Prieſt was a great intermedler, no man being therein more forward then himſelfe: but finding in the end ſo many fitter men in all reſpects then himſelfe for any imployment or extraordinarie preferment in that companie: he ſhortly after ſhifted his ſayles, &amp; going to the Ieſuits, did acquaint them with the whole courſe that the ſecular Prieſts had taken, and intended to proceede in. Whereof they (the Ieſuits) hauing full notice (as we geſſe by the euent) ſent into Spayne, to admoniſh Father Parſons of all the premiſſes, aſwell concerning maiſter VVestons ſaid Agencie, and the ouerthrowe of it, as of the enterpriſe, which our brethren the ſecular

Prieſts here had in hand: and likewiſe to impart vnto him, an other courſe deuiſed by them, &amp; to be better managed and brought to paſſe by his great policie, wiſedome and credit. What anſwere Father Parſons returned vnto them, wee can but alſo geſſe. But we thinke wee may coniecture it, by that which followed, viz. that he would thinke of the matter, and that they ſhould ſend one to meet him at Rome with further inſtructions, for his better proceeding to the accompliſhment of their deſires. Now you haue heard before, what a way they had made alreadie for themſelues, and for the repayring of their credit in Rome, by maiſter Blackwell his falſe letter mentioned, very well knowing, that if any meanes might be had to aduance their credits, and ſet them aloft, it muſt come from thence, and therefore laid that machiuilian ground for Father Parſous their only hope to work vpon afterwardes: which as you ſee fell out, as they could haue wiſhed at that time.
            Alſo the ſaid Father Parſons (then as wee ſuppoſe) or ſhortlie after, hauing taken notice what our brethrē the ſecular Prieſts were in hand with in England, did ſend to ſome of the beſt account amongſt them, and likewiſe to ſome others that in any ſort, they ſhould not proceed in that courſe: aſſuring them that it would be very offenſiue to his holines, becauſe of this knowledge, the very ſame in effect, hauing heretofore beene offered to his conſideration, hee did vtterlie reiect the ſame as inconuenient in all reſpects as things ſtood for England. Beſides to our further abuſe, and to keep vs occupied with our own concits, that wee might not ſomuch as ſuſpect any thing of theirs: wee in our plaine dealing acquainted them with our whole drift, and purpoſe. Whereunto for a time, they craftilie applauded: as hoping ſhortlie, by their former courſes to haue it daſht: but afterward

perceiuing that their owne purpoſes could not ſo ſoone be compaſſed: (as wiſe men in their generation fearing the worſt) thē they mightilie oppoſed themſelues, and depraued ours. And then maiſter Blackwell himſelfe amongſt others could write a diſcourſing letter with very much earneſtnes and rhetoricall arguments againſt ſo ambitious a cogitation, as once to thinke of any one mans Soueraignty ouer all his brethren, during the times of our perſecution.
            Howbeit wee continuing reſolute in our former purpoſe, but proſecuting the ſame with great dulnes, maiſter Garnet and his fellowers, diſpatched the ſaide maiſter Standiſh, our falſe brother to Rome in the latter end of the yeere 1596. there to expect Father Parſons comming. We will here leaue this honeſt man about his buſines in that Citie, and put you in mind, that after Cardinall Allens death, the ſtudents in the Engliſh Colledge there, felt no leſſe oppreſſion by the Ieſuits their tyranizing gouernours, then wee did at home: becauſe we withſtood their deſeignements in aſpiring to the like ſoueraigntie ouer vs here. It may be that hereafter ſome of our brethren, will ſet out thoſe tragedies at large, which indured long, and will appeare to all men of indifferencie to haue beene verie intolerable. In the meane while you ſhall vnderſtand that two or three, being of likelihood more grieued then the reſt, or hauing a greater ſenſe of our calamities, both at home and abroad, then manie others: did write a treatiſe of the Ieſuits dealing, &amp; naming it a memoriall, dedicated the ſame in Latine to his holines in the yeere 1597. about which time Father Parſons being come to Rome, was in the middeſt of all his machiuilian plots, and vnder pretence of compounding the ſtirres in that Seminarie, firſt ſo dealt, as in verie ſhort time by couſoning the Rector, he got that place for himſelfe, and now enioyeth it.
            
               
The imputations laid vpon the Ieſuits in the ſaide memoriall (the effect whereof you ſhall finde at the end of this hiſtorie) were ſo verie ſharpe, and touched their freehold ſo neerely, as no meruaile if Father Garnet beſtirred his ſtumps to ſalue their credits by all the meanes and wayes he could deuiſe. And therefore he held it beſt to write his letter to all the ſecular Prieſts: wherin after certaine flouriſhes, how much they were beloued and honoured by him and all his brethren of the ſocietie, he intreateth very earneſtlie their teſtimonies in their behalfe, againſt thoſe reports made of the Ieſuits in the ſaid memoriall. And that hee might obtaine a faire ſhew of many hands, hee was content to play ſmall game before hee would ſit out (as our Engliſh prouerb ſaith:) and therfore he commendeth to them ſuch a triple anſwere, as he thought would fit the moſt. Although (ſaith he) we are not ſo well known to many of you, as you all peraduenture will pronounce the whole contents of the ſaid treatiſe to be falſe: yet one of theſe three anſwers may ſit all your turnes. Some may ſay all is falſe: other that they themſelues haue nothing to accuſe the Ieſuits with, and doe not therefore beleeue the ſaid reports to be true: and the reſt may affirme without any ſcruple, that for their parts, they neuer dreamed of the ſaid memoriall, nor doe in any ſort approue the ſame. And the better to perſwade them thus to anſwere, he ſweareth by more then his little honeſty, that there is not a true word in it. There is a ſaying amongſt ſuch lawyers as are of experience, that they ſeldome fall out to be the honeſteſt men, who aredriuen ſo oft to ſeeke teſtimonials for the approuing of their good behauior. But that is no matter with them, and peraduenture, that conceit here holdeth not at Rome, ſo as maiſter Garnet did content himſelfe with his owne courſe, and made ſuch haſte therin, as before Auguſt the ſame yeere, the teſtimonial he got, was with Fa. Parſons in the Engliſh

Seminary. And here we cannot omit one thing, which indeede made vs a little merry in the middeſt of our ſorrow, how good Fa. Parſons was troubled with one mans ſubſcription to the ſayd teſtimoniall. For thus he writeth: as he pretendeth from Naples, primo Augusti 1598. to the ſayd party. After I ſaw a particular testimony of your owne hand in latine, concerning the memoriall giuen vp againſt the ſocietie, I could haue bin content you had not written it: but either haue ſubſcribed ſimpliciter, as many other auncient and graue Prieſts did to the cunning letter, as it was written (being very modeſt and moſt true) or that you had ſayd nothing at all: as well you might haue omitted: the memoriall being writ and ſent from Plaunders, whileſt you were yet in Italy: and ſo that it was done, and exhibited, Te neque conſentiente, neque conſcio (for thoſe are only the words of testimony that you giue) was not needefull: the thing being euident of it ſelfe, and your particular writing ſo bare a thing vnder the common letter, was to detract from all the letter before: and for the matter it ſelfe (which was moſt abhominable, falſe, and ſlaunderous,) you leaue it indifferent to be beleeued, or not beleeued &amp;c. Were it not that you might hereby perceiue what packing, and practiſing is amongſt theſe fellowes for the maintenance of their owne credit: and how ſwift they are in the expeditions they take in hand: we would haue made no mention hereof, becauſe thereby our owne dulnes may iuſtly be condemned, who all this while had not ſent our meſſengers to Rome, for the information of his holynes, as touching our eſtates here, and the common deſire of vs ſecular Prieſts, for a Biſhop as before is mentioned. In which ſlow proceeding, we will leaue our brethren for a time, and returne to maiſter Standiſh attending vpon Fa. Parſons in Rome.
            
            After this good Father had gotten the Rectorſhip of the Engliſh Seminary, it then pleaſed his Worſhip

to proceede with the cauſe commended vnto him by his ſubiects in England, Fa. Garnet and the reſt. We doubt not, but that in the meane time he had conferred with his friends, and was reſolued of the plot he meant to effect: the execution whereof was in manner as followeth. Standiſh that honeſt man muſt haue acceſſe to the Popes holynes, accompanyed with two runnagates, both of them Prieſts, Doctor Haddock, and maiſter Martin Array. Theſe muſt take vpon them, and ſo they did, that they were men deputed from the ſecular Prieſts in England, moſt humbly to intreate his Holynes that he would be pleaſed by his moſt preheminent Authority, to appoynt a ſuperior ouer the Church of England. And the rather to perſwade him thereunto, they affirmed like very lying wretches, that there was ſuch great diſſenſion betwixt the ſecular prieſts and the laytie, as great inconueniences would certainely inſue, except one were placed amongſt them, that by his authority might reforme and reconcile them. Now it is too well knowne, that the ſtrife which was heere, reſted betwixt vs and the Ieſuites; no one lay Catholick (for ought we know) being at enmity with any other ſecular Prieſts, then with ſome few of vs, that were at Wiſbich, and one or two more abroad that tooke our parts: and the diſlike that ſuch lay perſons had of vs, was procured by the falſe practiſe of the Ieſuites: we our ſelues, otherwiſe hauing neuer offended them, nor interteyned any quarrell with them, God is our iudge. His Holynes hearing and marking well their ſuite, demaunded of them, in expreſſe tearmes, if that which they had ſayd vnto him, proceeded from the deſire and conſent of his louing Prieſts in England, affirming that otherwiſe he would in no ſort giue any eare vnto them. Where-unto maiſter Sandiſh, very well inſtructed before by Father Parſons, and ſufficiently aſſiſted by the ſayd

two lying Prieſts, anſwered, that what he had preſumed to deliuer to his Holynes, he had done it moſt aſſuredly by their conſent. If Ananias was iuſtly charged with lying to the holy Ghoſt, in telling Saint Peter an vntruth, being repleniſhed with that holy ſpirit, we ſee no cauſe, why we may not ſo charge this diſhoneſt company on with all his aſſiſtants (Fa. Parſons and the reſt) in that they Iyed ſo apparantly to Saint Peters ſucceſſor the Popes Holynes, who we doubt not, but that he is likewiſe indued with the ſpirit of God in ſuch plentifull ſort, as the excellency of his high calling doth require. For it is well knowne, and may be proued moſt euidently, (if any dare be ſo ſhameleſſe as to deny it) that if you except Fa. Garnet, and ſome one or two of his adherents, the reſt of the Prieſts in England generally were altogether ignorant of that deuiſe. Inſomuch as the ſayd Standiſh after his returne into England, being asked by certaine Prieſts, how he durſt preſume ſo impudently to abuſe his Holynes with ſo intolerable an vntruth, he excuſed himſelfe in this ſort, viz. that when he ſayd, he had the conſent of the ſecular Prieſts in England to make that motion, his anſwere therein was made by him Cautè, that is, ſubtilly, or by equiuocation, meaning to himſelfe, viz. as he ſuppoſed, or preſumed; which words he kept in his minde and vttered not. By which vngodly ſhift, the tyranny wherewith now we are oppreſſed, was hatched.
            By this ſo falſe and Ieſuiticall a ſleight, the Popes Holynes being abuſed as you haue heard, committed that matter (ſo propounded vnto him) to the further conſideration of Cardinall Caietane, protector of the Engliſh Seminary, and to Cardinall Burgheſius, which was the very plot that Fa. Parſons before had layd: the ſayd Cardinall protector, being one, with whom he the ſayd Parſons had eſpeciall familiaritie and friendſhip; and by reaſon of his protectorſhip ouerruled the

other Cardinall as he thought good: ſo as they two being appointed for this ſeruice, Parſons deſeignement was in effect thereby accompliſhed. Well it had hapned to vs, if his Holynes had bin at that time indued with that worthie gift of the holy Ghoſt, tearmed diſcretio ſpirituum: that when he made this deputation to the Cardinall, he might haue ſayd to the aforeſayd falſe wretches: why haue you lyed to the holy Ghoſt, that thereby, either ſome extraordinary calamitie might haue fallen vpon them, or his Holynes haue taken ſome other courſe for the inflicting vpon them ſuch puniſhment as they deſerued. But the matter paſſed as you haue heard: and Parſons muſt contriue it as he thinketh it conuenient, which he did in ſort as followeth. One muſt gouerne all the Prieſts in England, but Parſons durſt not name a Ieſuite for that purpoſe: that had bin too groſſe dealing, he muſt then be a ſecular Prieſt, there was no remedie. And who ſhould that be, but maiſter Blackwell, who was knowne to be a chiefe paraſite of the Ieſuites, and would be ſure, if he might haue this authoritie by them, neuer to do any thing, that might in any ſort diſpleaſe them. Whereupon Blackwell is named for the Arch-prieſt of England: aſſiſtants are appointed to wayt vpon him: a letter with the Cardinals conſent is framed by Father Parſons, dated the ſeauenth of March 1598. rules are made, and one in effect you may be ſure, that maiſter Arch-prieſt and his aſſiſtants ſhall do nothing in any matter of importance, without the Ieſuites conſents. All things thus diſpatched, maiſter Standiſh (as wee thinke) is ſent back with this ſtuffe into England; and euen when our two meſſengers were ready at the laſt to go towards Rome, he arriueth: maiſter Blackwell receiueth his authoritie, and publiſheth the ſame for

want of a Cryer by his owne letters: requiring all Prieſts to ſubſcribe vnto it.
            Hereof when ſundry of vs had notice, we conferred together as we could: and finding that the Cardinals directions were not warranted, by any Breue from his Holynes: we feared ſome falſe packing by Father Parſons. Alſo ſome of our brethren talking with maiſter Blackwell, about the Cardinals conſtitutions, tooke him directly with a manifeſt forgery, in pretending certaine to haue come from the Cardinall which he was driuen to confeſſe, were of his owne making. Beſides we conſidered, that if the Pope were made acquainted with the ſayd Cardinals deſignements; what he did, or allowed therein, was vpon falſe ſuggeſtion, (for as then wee did not certainely know, how Standiſh had played the Ieſuite by Parſons aduiſe as is before expreſſed. Againe, wee perceiued by the Cardinals inſtructions, that maiſter Blackwell was made no better in deede then an Arch-prieſt of cloutes, being limited to do nothing, but as it ſhould pleaſe maiſter Garnet. And it could not ſinke into our heads, that his Holynes being throughly acquainted with theſe plots, would euer haue bin drawne to haue yeelded, that his Clergie of England ſhould be ouertopt, and controuled by the new vpſtart Ieſuites. We alſo did eaſily ſee into what danger this ſubordination would bring vs, being left in effect to Father Parſons directions. For theſe, and ſundry other conſiderations, we deſired that we might not be vrged to ſubſcribe to the ſayd authoritie, vntill wee might either ſee the Popes Breue to ratifie it, or haue time to know his Holynes further pleaſure: when we ſhould haue informed him the truth in theſe matters. Vpon our ſtay herein, (which ſeemed to vs ſo reaſonable,) it is ſcarſe credible, how we were ſlaundered

and abuſed: inſomuch as through ſuch and many other iniuries offred by the Arch-prieſt and Ieſuites vnto vs, we were compelled to appeale to his Holynes. But we were ſtill too ſlow and dull in our proceedings, and indeede wanted money, and other fit oportunities to make ſuch quick diſpatch as we deſired. Whereupon Father Garnet, and maiſter Blackwell abounding in all things, and perceiuing our intent, they preſently diſpatched their curſitors into euery part of the Realme, to get hands to certaine letters (drawne either by them, or by their direction) of thankeſgiuing to the Pope, and Protector, for their ſingular care ouer the Church heere, in appointing vnto them ſo excellent a forme of gouernment: with much more to this purpoſe. And ſuch a courſe was taken with our poore brethren, who many of them had neuer heard of this matter before, as partly through ignorance in ſome, through threatning and feare in others, and by faire promiſes to many; a number of hands were gotten to the ſayd letters. This exployt thus effected, they ſent the ſayd letters with all ſpeede to Rome, and procured by their meſſengers as they went, other letters, from ſundry perſons beyond the ſeas to their friends in that City to depraue our enterpriſe as much as poſſibly they could, affirming that what our meſſengers, when they came thither, ſhould propound againſt the ſubordination in England, did proceede only from a few that were factious, and that it would be very diſhonorable to his Holynes former proceedings, if they ſhould finde any fauour or countenance there.
            With theſe aforeſaid Machiuilian practiſes, wee were not then acquainted, but as honeſt and plaine dealing men; when our ſaid meſſengers, maiſter Biſhop and maiſter Charnock, two learned Prieſtes, were

readie to goe to Rome to proſecute our cauſes there: we acquainted our Archprieſt therewith and deſired, (if ſo it might ſtand with his pleaſure) to ſende ſome thither alſo, that might be furniſhed to anſwere for him, if we ſhould be thought to informe amiſſe. This motion of ours, was ſo greatlie diſdained by his maiſterſhip, as wee thinke the higheſt Cardinall in Chriſtendome, could not with greater contempt haue reiected ye meaneſt Prieſt his ſute yt liueth. And relying vpon Father Parſons, and his other ſaid plots, hee preſumed to tell vs plainelie (to the great preiudice of iuſtice in the Court of Rome) that if we ſent any thither, they ſhould not be heard, but finde that entertainement, which they little expected. Howbeit wee neuer imagined, nor could in deed thinke, either of thoſe meſſages which they had ſent before, or of that which followed: but rather ſuppoſed he had vſed ſuch ſpeeches vnto vs of purpoſe to ſtay vs from proceeding in our former determination. And therefore we diſpatch them hence, who being gone, our Archprieſt chafeth: the Prouinciall his good maiſter, clappes him on the backe and egges him forward: the reſt of the Ieſuits whet their tongues and prepare their pens to ſpeake and write what they can falſelie deuiſe againſt vs to make vs odious: ſo as preſentlie, we are become a by-word in their mouthes, &amp; are nothing with them but Rebels, Apostataes, and what they liſt to report of vs. One Lister a Ieſuit writeth a booke to proue vs al ſchiſmatikes, who had appealed to Rome, and both maiſter Blackwell and Father Garnet ſubſcribed vnto it. In this booke, beſides the tearmes before expreſſed, we are ſaid to haue fallen from the Church, and the ſpouſe of Chriſt: to haue troden vnder our feete our obedience due to the higheſt biſhop: to haue loſt our faculties, whereby we ought to haue wonne ſoules vnto Chriſt: to haue made
               
               our ſelues irregular: to haue incurred the ſentence of excommunication: to haue giuen a ſcandall to all goodmen: to be in all mens mouthes as infamous perſons: to be as publicanes and ſinners, and to be nothing better then ſoothſayers and Idolaters.
            
            Wee haue now brought this ſtory to the ſetting out againſt vs of the ſayd treatiſe of ſchiſme: and for the reſt do referre you for a larger diſcourſe to the bookes lately printed and publiſhed by ſome of our brethren. Therein you ſhall finde that by Father Parſons practiſes, our ſayd meſſengers no ſooner came to Rome, but within ſixe or ſeauen dayes they were caſt into priſon, and could neuer be ſuffred to come to the Pope. Whileſt they were in priſon, his Holynes Breue is procured for the confirmation of maiſter Blackwels authoritie. Afterwards the poore men are ſet at libertie, but kept aſunder, and baniſhed into diuers Prouinces, not to repayre into England, vntill they ſhould haue leaue from Rome. The ſayd Breue commeth hither: wee being informed thereof, ſubmit our ſelues to our Arch-prieſt: ſhewing our ſelues to be farre from ſchiſmaticks; and ſuch was our deſire of peace, as we were well content to remit all the former ſlaunders imputed moſt falſely vnto vs.
            Beſides, for the auoyding of further contention, we deſired our Arch-prieſt, (whome now we reuerenced as we were bound in dutie) to take ſuch order, as that hereafter there might not be ſo much as once mention made of the ſayd pretended ſchiſme. Whereunto he yeelded very willingly, and made a Decree to that effect: promiſing to be a meanes that our ſayd two brethren might be releaſed of their baniſhment. His dealing with vs in this kinde ſort did very much comfort vs, becauſe we being men, who ſtill had bin afflicted, any thing ſeemed a great

benefit to vs. But ſhortly after we well perceiued, that our former appellation and ſending to Rome with our refuſall in the meane time to bow vnto him, did ſtick in his ſtomack. For whether prouoked by the malitious Ieſuites, or ſtirred vp by his owne pride, and rancor to be reuenged vpon vs, now that we had ſubmitted ourſelues vnto his gouernment, he renewed the remembrance of the old ſore, contrary to his ſayd decree, and that vnder the pretence of a letter that ſhould come vnto him from Rome, from two Ieſuites, Tichborne, and Warford: wherein he ſayd, it was expreſtely ſet downe, that we were iudged in Rome to be ſchiſmaticks before the obteyning of the ſayd Breue, in that we did not ſubſcribe to his authoritie, when the Cardinals firſt letters were intimated vnto vs. And vpon this falſe ground (except theſe two Ieſuites and ſome one or two more of that crue had ſo iudged vs) he writ his letters abroade to that effect, as well what forſooth he had receiued from Rome, (concealing the names of the ſayd two Machiuilian Ieſuites) as alſo that he would receiue none to his fauour or abſolue them, which would not acknowledge that they had ſinned, and giuen a great ſcandale by their ſayd prolonging to acknowledge his authoritie. When we heard hereof, it grieued vs much to ſee the weakenes of our new Gouernour: but more in that we perceiued what new troubles and diſſenſions would thereby inſue. We did write therefore both to him and to his aſſiſtants, that they would be pleaſed, the old controuerſie amongſt vs might lye buryed ſtill in the graue of obliuion, and not to be againe now renewed. But they ſhut their eares to our humble ſuites, and reiect vs with contumelious and reprochfull words, for preſuming ſo raſhlie (forſooth) to intermeddle with any thing that they had reſolued

of. Notwithſtanding becauſe they were our brethren, and many of them before that time ſome of our inferiors; we aduentured once againe to intreate this fauour at their hands, that two or three of the beſt learned amongſt them, might be appointed to conferre of this matter with as many of vs: that ſo the controuerſie might be compounded, before it brake out any further. How this was taken at our hands, it is ſcarcely credible: they tearmed our ſupplication a tumultuous expoſtulation, being fraught (as they ſayd) with the forgetfulnes of our duties, and with the ſpirit of pride and preſumption. And hereupon euen now, that we were become his ſubiects, after we had vnderſtanding of the Popes Breue, and looked to haue bin greatly cheriſhed and defended from iniuries by the ſtrength of his ſoueraigne authoritie, we are againe as ſharply proſecuted with imputations of ſchiſme and rebellion as we were before, which cauſed vs to propound the queſtion in controuerſie amongſt vs, to the famous Vniuerſitie of Paris: hauing offered to them before, but in vayne, if it pleaſed them to ioyne with vs therein. That worthie company after due conſideration, determined the matter on our ſide. Whereof the Arch-prieſt being informed, addreſſeth out his owne edict, and condemneth therein their ſayd iudgement: inflicteth great cenſures vpon thoſe Prieſts that ſhould at any time maynteine that determination: and ſpareth not likewiſe to mulct the laytie (ouer whom for ought we know he hath no authoritie at all) as many as ſhould incline to the imbracing and fauoring of it.
            When we ſaw this our Arch-prieſt with his aſſiſtants thus peremptorilie bent by ſtrong hand to oppreſſe vs: and without either conſcience, or conſideration of morall honeſtie to ſpreade abroade againe to our

diſcredits their former calumniations, and very groſſe and palpable ſlaunders: we thought it our beſt courſe if it were but to heape coales vpon their heads, to commend vnto them this conſideration: whether it might not ſtand with their good liking to ſend two Prieſts to be choſen by them, with two others of ours to Rome to know his Holynes opinion and direction in this cauſe ſo hotely impugned by them: the ſame being the aſſured rule for the ending and finall determination of it: adding, that if we were condemned for ſchiſinaticks, for delaying our obedience, as is before expreſſed, till we knew his Holynes pleaſure, we would moſt willingly ſubiect our ſelues to the heauieſt cenſures that might be impoſed vpon vs: and if cleared, the leaſt ſatisfaction that they would thinke good to award vs, ſhould fully pleaſe and content vs. But this our laſt ſuite was more diſdained (if it were poſſible) then either of the former: and ſo farre the Arch-prieſt was from yeelding vnto vs herein, or to affoord vs otherwiſe the leaſt ſhadow of his fauour, as he caſt abroade his decrees, that our ſayd deferring to receiue his authoritie before the Breue came, was ſchiſme, and prohibiteth any vnder grieuous paynes, either by word or writing to affirme the contrary. Whereupon we were compelled, as hauing no other refuge at all, to appeale againe to the infallible ſeate of the holy Apoſtle Saint Peter: thinking with our ſelues that thereby (at the leaſt till the cauſe were decided) our aduerſaries would haue forborne the proſecution of their malice againſt vs. But the humor they are poſſeſſed with, being altogether Ieſuiticall, that is violent and implacable, they ceaſed not but ſtill continued, contrary to all courſe of law &amp; iuſtice, euery day more and more to wound and oppreſſe vs. Our ſayd appellation ſubſcribed with the

hands of 30. Prieſts, men of good deſert and reputation, they tearme an infamous libell, and preſently vpon the ſight thereof, de facto, do ſuſpend and depriue tenne of them from their faculties: eight of them being priſoners at Wiſbich, and two others, both of them perſons of extraordinary note and worth. There hath bin of long time an old ſaying in England: that ſet a begger on horſeback, and he will ride a gallop: our ſaid new gouernors ſitting in their thrones, and ſcorning that any ſhould refuſe to worſhip them, can finde no limits for the ſtay of their fury, but ſtill runne on from one miſchiefe to an other. For, our cauſe thus depending, they forbid all the lay Catholicks to keepe vs company, to relieue vs, or to ſuffer vs to execute any ſpirituall function with them: affirming, that whoſoeuer ſhall be preſent at one of our Maſſes, or aſſiſt vs therein, doth commit a great ſinne: and that to receiue the ſacraments at our hands, is loco medicaminis, to receiue a deadly poyſon. None may confeſſe their ſinnes vnto vs, and none may heare vs preach, (at the leaſt of thoſe which are to too many) that yeeld themſelues to the direction and pleaſure of ſuch abſurd commaunders, and wicked condemners of their brethren, notwithſtanding we be exempted from ſuch their prohibitions by our appellation, and do therefore ſtill mioy the full libertie of our Prieſthood. The courſe they hold againſt vs, or at the leaſt their ſtomack, may appeere vnto you, by that which a Ieſuite hath written concerning vs, to one of his friends: Deteſt (ſayth he) my deere mother the curſed crue of the diſobedient to lawfull authoritie: if you know any, either of our coate, or of the lay ſort, that be tainted with this pestilent poyſon, eſchue his company, as you would auoyd one that hath a plague-ſore running vpon him, aſſuring your ſelfe, that if ſuch rebelliow perſons do not ſubmit their necks to the yoke of their ſuperiors,
               
               that vnleſſe God ſhew them ſome extraordinary fanour (which in ſuch caſes he vſually denyeth to ſuch malitious Rebels) their reuolt and Apostaſie from the Catholicke vnitie, will be the iuſt reward of their obstinacie and malapert oppoſition againſt their ordinary. God be mercifull vnto vs poore men: ſome of vs are priſoners, and are daily in the Magiſtrates hands to be cut off, and finiſh our miſeries at their pleaſures; and on the other ſide, where we ſhould finde comfort, we are dealt with, as you ſee: and all is either becauſe we are readie to offer our liues for the Catholick faith, or refuſe, till we may be heard by the Popes Holynes▪ to acknowledge our ſelues to be Rebels, Schiſmaticks, contemners of the See Apoſtolick, Ethnicks, Publicanes, Idolaters, Apoſtataes, and what not? becauſe we did not at the firſt ſubſcribe to our Archbiſhops authoritie, but appealed as you haue heard. Which acculations, we truſt no man liuing by learning or arguments ſhall be able to prooue againſt vs: and in the meane time, God is our witnes, how free we are in foro conſcientiae, from any of theſe wicked imputations. In the aforeſayd proceſſe with theſe our aduerſaries, ſome of our brethren haue bin as carefull to defend vs from ſchiſme by writing, as they haue bin buſie to accuſe vs: and amongſt ſundry of our diſcourſes to that eff
                  •
               ct, two haue bin lately publiſhed in print, which we deſire you would procure: and hauing duly peruſed them, then thinke and iudge of vs as you ſhall finde cauſe. Now for our concluſion, if any Ieſuitical humoriſt, ſhall blame or ſeeke to diſcredit vs, becauſe in the premiſſes of this Narration we haue forborne to vſe any ſharp ſpeeches againſt our common enemyes, we thinke it conuenient for the preuenting of their malitious collections, to yeeld vnto you our reaſons thereof. Firſt, the ſtory gaue vs no occaſion ſo to do. Secondly, we reteyne ſtill the opinion which we haue ſignified to his Holynes,

that the Ieſuiticall perſecution begun againſt vs, is much more grieuous vnto vs, then that which we are ſubiect vnto from the State. Thirdly, we haue found by experience, that the rayling courſe which the Ieſuiticall crue haue taken and vſed in many of their treatiſes againſt her Maieſtie: and the proceedings by the lawes of the Realme: hath done the Catholick cauſe exceeding much hurt. Fourthly, as our caſe ſtandeth, and for ought we ſee, if the pretended holy Fathers may haue their willes, we ſhall be driuen to relye more vpon her Highnes fauour for our temporall reliefe, that we periſh not with famine, before we be cut off by her lawes, then vpon all the world beſides. And laſtly, howſoeuer we diſſent from the State in the profeſſion of our Religion: yet we are her Maieſties borne ſubiects, and vaſſals, and ought not for any cauſe, as we are perſwaded, to withdraw in that reſpect, our duties, loue, and allegiance from her Highnes, or our natiue Countrie: much leſſe to ſlaunder, or ſecke the cruell ouerthrow of both, as our trayterous aduerſaries of the ſocietie, not indeede of Ieſus, but of the Diuell, and their adherents haue done. And thus praying to God with all our hearts, to heape vpon her Maieſtie all temporall and heauenly bleſſings, and vpon our ſtate ſufficient wiſedome and prouidence, for the good continuance of it: and vpon our Countrie all proſperitie and happines, and vpon the Church a dayly increaſe of zeale for the propagation and maintenance of the Catholick faith, and vppon our Ieſuiticall aduerſaries ſuch riches of his mercie, as ſeeing the height of their owne pride, and the excremities of their proceedings, they may become humble in their owne eyes, and deſiſt from their very prowde Machiuilian and cruell deſeignements: and vpon all Catholicks ſufficient grace to take heed of thoſe that are the authors of ſchiſme and contention:

delighting in nothing, but in factions and nouelties: and vpon our ſelues conſtancie to continue in his obedience, and patience, to be able to indure whatſoeuer calamities ſhall happen vnto vs for our profeſſion of the truth, and the diſcharge of our conſciences: we take our leaues, and do heere end for this time.
            The memoriall mentioned Page 52. is hard to be got: few or none of vs that are ſecular Prieſts could euer come vnto the ſight of it. Certaine abſtracts of it are common. We haue ſeene two: whereof one hath annexed vnto it certaine obſeruations of the Ieſuites cariage of themſelues in Rome: and both are as followeth.
            
               An abstract of the memoriall ſent by certaine Engliſhmen out of the Low-countryes, to the Popes holines Clement the eight, againſt the Ieſuites labouring in the Engliſh Vineyard, September 1597.
               
               The inſcription of the memoriall.
               A briefe declaration of the miſerable ſtate of Catholicks in England.
               
               After the Preface, it followeth in theſe words.
               THe Ieſuites that are in England, deſirous either to bring vnder bondage, or vtterly to beare downe the Cleargie of the Church of England, haue dared to attempt it by a wonderfull ſtratagem. Firſt, their will is, that in euery Catholicks houſe, (and ſuch houſes are in ſteed of the Church) either they themſelues may be the Paſtors, or others deputed by them in their roomes. And if happilie there be any, that do de
                     •
                  y the faculties graunted by them; or will not take notice that ſuch aſſemblies, or companies of Catholicks depend

on them; or will not obediently (as it were at a beck) execute thoſe things, that they haue commaunded; ſuch ſhall be cenſured either as Apoſtataes, or Hereticks, or taynted at leaſt with ſome infection of hereſie. So holie, ſo godly, ſo religious would they ſeeme to be; as nothing is holie, that they haue not ſanctified; no doctrine Catholick, and ſound, that commeth not from them; no diſpenſation auailable, that is not graunted by them: and which is worſe, they haue beaten into the heads of the moſt, that the Maſſe is not rightly, and orderly celebrated of any, but a Ieſuite.
               When any of the Cleargie graunteth a diſpenſation in any caſe; by and by there is doubt made of his power and authority; ſome queſtion ariſeth of his life, and conuerſation; as if his Prieſthood, and calling were not certaine, or aſſured. It is not inough for the Cleargie to liue a godly, and an holie life, vnleſſe withall they will acknowledge the leſuites to be their ſuperiors; thus ſome man ſhall be tormented, another ſome turmoyled, a third ſome troubled: for who ſo gathereth not for and with them only, he ſhall be iudged altogether to ſcatter. And that they may the better ſet this their deuiſe abroeh, they cauſe to be made knowne to all men the faculties graunted vnto them by his holynes the Biſhop of Rome; and they giue it out, that the moſt vnlearned Ieſuite doth farre excell the moſt learned ſecular Prieſt, both in faculties, and priuiledges. And it is noyſed about, as it were by the common cryer that they haue power from his holynes to graunt to all, and euery one, all and ſingular their faculties; inſomuch as it ſhall not be lawfull and ſafe for any to vſe their priniledges though graunted them many yeres before frō his holynes, but with the leaue, and conſent of theſe Fathers of the ſocietie. And when they do giue out their faculties, they do not beſtow

them on learned, godly, or holy men; but on vnlearned, vngodly, and irreligious; nay ſeditious perſons, ſuch as follow their humor, ſtoupe at their beck, and ſtand bound euer after vnto them.
               Further they endeuor, that by all meanes poſſible, both thoſe almes which are giuen for the reliefe of them that are in priſon, or any other poore afflicted whatſoeuer; as alſo whatſoeuer is paid in caſes of diſpenſation, may come to their hands. Heretofore (when Prieſts had the collection of theſe almes) priſons were therewith maintayned; the want in Colledges was ſupplyed; the baniſhed Catholicks (whoſe goodes were forciblie taken from them by Hereticks) were yerely ſuccoured: but now, what is done with them we know not. Priſons and Colledges are depriued of them; the baniſhed haue them not; the Prieſts ſee them not: but there are hired herewith ſeditious perſons; deuiſers of fables, ſlaunderers of their brethren, and skorners of the Saincts are herewith enriched; theſe, and ſuch as theſe, receiue large ſtipends of their labours.
               And yet ſo great a maſſe of monies cannot be conſumed, with ſo ſmall charges, and expences, but that the Fathers alſo beſtow much vpon themſelues. For they go indeed in great gallantrie; no Ieſuite goeth but to viſit any one, or trauelleth from one place to another, but he is richly apparrelled, he is attended on with a great trayne of ſeruants, as if he were a Baron, or an Earle; which is not neceſſary, but playnely ridiculous and abſurd. The ſecular Prieſts themſelues do go alſo Gentlemen-like becauſe of danger; but not arayed in that ſumptuous manner, nor guarded with ſo many attendants, as the Ieſuites. They wrangle, and reproue the Prieſts garments, and ſpendings; whereas the expences of one Ieſuite were able to mayntayne twentie Prieſts plentifully, and richly. Neither by

this meanes alſo could ſo great a quantitie of almes be waſted, but that (as the report goes) much treaſure is conueyed beyond the Seas, but to what purpoſe, we know not, vnleſſe it be beſtowed vpon their bodie, their corporation, or ſocietie.
               Beſides they deſire (as ſome conceiue) that England ſhould be conuerted of none but Ieſuites only. For they will admit no fellow-laborers: and they vſe the ſame meanes they heretofore vſed in Colledges, to diſſwade many for the order of their calling, counſelling them by all meanes to enter into their ſocietie; and this they dayly attempt by flatterie, by gifts, and rewards, &amp; ſometimes by threatnings. They neuer ſend one ſcholler out of England to the Colledge at Doway to ſtudie there, but hinder what they may them that are going thither. They care not for that Colledge, becauſe they cannot draw it into their ſocietie: nay they haue laboured by all meanes vtterly to diſſolue it.
               Moreouer, they challenge vnto themſelues a ſpirituall Monarchie ouer all England, as it may appeare by a certain contention in the priſon at Wiſbich, in which there were, and are in hold for the profeſſion of their faith 32. Prieſts, dayly looking for their death. Theſe liuing a long time a godly, and an holy life, did eate altogether, ſtudied altogether, vſed euery day to preach, to diſpute, to intreate of caſes of conſcience, to expound the ſcriptures; and exerciſed the ſame ſtudies, as they were wont to practiſe in the Vniuerſities: all were of one minde; all of one heart; all as brethren; one bearing with another. The towne of Wiſbich loued them; all the land praiſed them; the hereticks admired them; the keepers of the priſons greatly affected them: ſo that they inioyed euery day more and more libertie. Their maintenance came to them from all places yea the very Miniſters (though hereticks) very often helped to reheue them. Many

yeeres liued they in this godly, holy, and deuout kind of life, vntill a Ieſuite, one Edmunds by name (inſpired we know not with what ſpirit) gaue to ſome occaſion to doubt of the well imploying of the almes receiued. This foundation laid, he ſo inſinuated himſelfe with faire demeanour and falſe deuiſes into the hearts of many, as that he deuided the Prieſts into two parts, whereof the one part drew to him, the other ſtood againſt him.
               They vſe alſo to fawne vpon men of noble birth, eſpecially if they be rich, and mueigle them by all faire meanes to ſell all that they haue, and enter into their Societie. Women alſo are induced by them to become Nunnes, and to leaue ſuch goods as they haue, to them. Which thing many that are godly-wiſe allow not. For ſuch rich Laitie (all circumſtances conſidered) are able to further more the eſtabliſhing of the faith in England, then the Ieſuites conſider of. For ſuch as they, might giue maintenance to Prieſts; enrich the priſons of Catholicks with their gifts; help the afflicted: they may more freely, and with leſſe danger ſpeak of the Catholick religion, and faith; more commonly argue and diſcourſe with hereticks. But the Ieſuites conſider not, that theſe, and ſuch other things may be done, and would be done by them without any difficultie. But in this manner do they make merchandiſe of the conuerſion of England; thus do they diſpoſe of the laſt wils of the ſick; thus loue they to intermeddle with the mariages of many, with their temporall goods, and indeed with all things: Alwayes taking that courſe with all men, that ſomething happen to their ſhare, hauing minde indeed of nothing, but their owne gaine. They skorne to come to any one, but where they may be daintily, and coſtly entertayned: they looke not after the cottages of the poore, nor miniſter their help to them, be there neuer ſo much need.
               
                  
Moreouer, they are ſo delighted with equiuocation, or a ſubtile and diſſembling kind of ſpeech, as that to the ſcandall of others they are not aſhamed to defend it in their publick writings. There were read before the Iudges on the bench in open Court, and in the hearing of all the people the letters of a certain Ieſuite named Southwell, wherein equiuocations were moſt abſurdly defended, which gaue cauſe of laughter to the hereticks, and occaſion of ſcandall to the Catholicks. They take pleaſure alſo to ſcatter rumors, and to ſuggeſt certaine nouelties in the eares of Catholicks, yea to forge and inuent things that are not, inſomuch as they are commonly held now a dayes great lyars; and it is come to that paſſe, that though they ſweare, men will not beleeue them.
               All Vniuerſitie men, and ſuch as haue taken any degree in ſchooles (and ſuch in our countrey are moſt regarded) they hate moſt, deſpiſe, contemne, and reproch. It is a common report in England, that had it not bin for the pride, and ambition of the Ieſuites, there had eare this bin graunted ſome toleration in Religion.
               To conclude, omitting all other things (which are very many) I wil only rehearſe one, which I haue heard of many; that it is come to this paſſe now, that the Catholicks ſtand in more feare of the Ieſuites, then of the hereticks. For the hereticks (ſay they) can but chaſten the bodie only; but the Ieſuites wound both their bodies, and their good name. They do not indeed directly cauſe Prieſts to be apprehended, but indirectly. That is, hauing ſpread ſome reports of them, whereby their good name is taken away, ſo as they ſtand ſuſpected either of hereſie, or of ſome other heynous offence, no Catholick entertayneth them, and ſo conſequently, they are driuen to pouertie, how can they eſcape the hands of the hereticks? And albeit they lye

in priſon, and bonds, and are many wayes tormented, if they be not crowned with the glory of martyrdome, they ſhal neuer be purged from that former ſuſpition, but ſhall be accounted euery day more and more, as hereticks.
            
            
               Certayne chiefe points of accuſations, wherewith many Engliſh men haue iuſtly charged the Ieſuites vnto the Pope, and diuers Cardinals: taken out of the Memoriall and other letters: ſome of them dated at Rome 8. of Nouember 1597.
               
               Touching the Ieſuites in England.
               
               THe Fathers of the Societie do diſſent among themſelues, Fa. Henrie the ſuperior, and Fa. Edmonds, in the Priſon at Wiſbich, and there 26. Articles of their diſſenſion.
               If any Prieſt haue a conuenient place of reſidencie, the Ieſuits will not ceaſe vntill they haue caſt him out, and that by wicked meanes, by defaming him, and bringing him into ſuſpition.
               That the Ieſuites are the firebrands of all ſoditions.
               That the Ieſuites by right or wrong ſeeke ſimply and abſolutely the Monarchie of all England.
               
               They are enemies to all ſecular Prieſts.
               They are the cauſes of all the diſcord in the Engliſh Nation.
               They are called of the ſchiſmaticks horſe-leaches, or bloud-ſuckers.
               That Fa. Parſons, and Sir Fra. Inglefeild Knight, deuiſed the complot to ſet the Cardinals Aldobrandinus, Caietane, and the Biſhop of Caſſana together by the cares: and to fall foule one vpon an other.
               
                  N. wrote to Cardinall Allen, that Fa. Holt ſtoode guiltie, and might be accuſed by him of ſuch infamous matters, as he durſt not make mētion of in his letters.
               
                  
That Fa. Holt did not only intend, but would indeede giue wretched England in Conqueſt to himſelfe and his fauorites.
               That Fa. Holt and his companions had gathered ſuch an infinite maſſe of money from the Catholicks in England, for diſpenſations, or vnder the colour of expending it to their vſes, as many credibly affirmed it to exceede the ſumme of 50000. pounds engliſh, which make two hundreth millions of Italian Scutes.
               That the Ieſuites haue driuen certaine excellent men to deſperation, inforcing them to leaue England, and to enter into ſome religious order, or to take ſome other miſerable courſe.
               That the Ieſuites in England by certayne cunning ſleights, hauing gotten into their hands all authoritie, good eſtimation, and all the ſtock or treaſure of money, do what they liſt at home and abroade. They thruſt out, and let in, hire, and buy, intercept letters, and maintayne factions as they pleaſe them ſelues.
               That Fa. Holt in Belgia, and Parſons in Spayne, haue continued theſe nine whole yeres, to the great gricfe of the Nobilitie and Clergie: and haue procured themſelues to be continued the Kings ſeruants.
               That there are many things in the dealings of theſe Fathers which offend good men: viz. the contempt of Nobilitie: the turning away of Students from the Colledge at Doway: the attempting to bring the moſt flouriſhing kingdome of England into a Prouince: the polling and pilling of Catholicks in England, vnder the colour of holy vſes by intollerable fraude: a continuall enterdeale with hereticks, and men of ſuſpected religion.
               There muſt be care taken that the Prieſts in England may haue either equall or greater faculties then the Ieſuites, ſeeing their pride by reaſon of their large faculties is fenced (as it were) with authoritie.
               
                  
That the Engliſh Nobles which are in Belgia, wonder that his Holynes ſuffreth Ieſuites in England, who are the firebrands of all contentions eſpecially in any place of authoritie, and that theſe ten yeers and more, notwithſtanding the miſerable clamor and lamentations of our Nobles and Gentlemen, who be oppreſſed vnder the yoke of ſlauery and their tyrannie.
               The Ieſuites do withſtand any mans comming out of England into Belgia, vnleſſe they know him prepared to write, to ſpeake, to do what they will: and that he ſweare to be ruled by them: and herein they exerciſe notorious tyrannie.
               Other infinite matters of this nature are omitted, which are conteyned in the letters that are kept vpon record: Taken out of letters dated at Rome, 8. Nouember 1597.
            
            
               Concerning the whole Societie, and the Ieſuites at Rome.
               
               THe Ieſuites are ſo ambitious, as not content with the bounds which their Fathers placed, in their vnſatiable deſire they haue alreadie ſwallowed vp Kingdomes and Monarchies.
               That being led by this ambition, they go about to change the forme of the Hierarchie, or ſupreme gouerment of the auncient Church by diſordered packing.
               That this pride and ambition of the Ieſuites, is the cauſe of ſeditions not only in England, in the very priſons there, in the Low Cuntries, and in Italy, but all the world ouer.
               That this their ambition hath taken footing not only in Prouinces and Cities, but alſo in priuate families: it ſeparateth brethren one from an other, and the husband from the wife, inflaming them with rancor and enuie one againſt another.
               That men muſt giue way to the time (as in the controuerſie

at Rome) leaſt while they ſet a damme againſt the ſtreame of this their pride, the raging courſe thereof do burſt aſunder all the bands of honeſtic and modeſtie, and carry away headlong many with the force thereof.
               That if this ambition do remayne vnpuniſhed, the age that is to come ſhall ſee that it will bring into bondage not only Prelates, but the very Princes and Monarches themſelues, whom yet ſhe flattereth in her infancie.
               They beſeech the Pope that he would lay the axe to the roote of the tree, and cut off this pride of the Societie, ſpreading it ſelfe farre and neere, leaſt if once it arme it ſelfe with the authoritie of his Holynes, it powre forth a full reuenge vpon all others to their deſtruction, and make an infinite ſlaughter and maſſacre of ſoules, which they haue already begun to attempt in wretched England, to the great decay of the common cauſe.
               That the Prieſts of England can finde in their baniſhment no harbour ſafe enough from this their ambition, vnleſſe they haue firſt receiued the marke of this beaſt in their forehead.
               That the Pope can commaund nothing in all his Mandates but the Ieſuites finde meanes to fruſtrate it by the ſecular power, to the great ſcandall of many.
               That the reuenge of theſe Ieſuites hath neuer an end but with the death of their aduerſaries, and their reproch after their death.
               That the Ieſuites (meaning them of Rome) do vſe to intercept all manner of letters of all men whoſoeuer, not forbearing the packets neither of the Cardinals nor of Princes.
               
                  N. calleth God and his Angels to witnes, that the greateſt part of the Nobilitie and Clergie in England both at home and abroade do bewaile with ſighes and

teares their miſerable eſtate, in that they ſuffer more grieuous things vnder theſe new Tyrants the Ieſuites, then in their dayly perſecutions.
               That the perſecution of the Ieſuites is more grieuous to the Catholicks then of the hereticks in England, in this reſpect, becauſe they ſuffer vnder them for their vertue, but vnder theſe in the name of treacherie and vnfaithfulnes.
               The Ieſuites haue ſo perſecuted ſome Prieſts that are now Martyrs, as that their death hath bin imputed partly to the hereticks, and partly to the Ieſuites.
               That it is a knowne poſition among the Ieſuites (diuide and gouerne) and therefore thoſe Fathers at Rome do both ſtirre vp, and maintayne diſſenſions.
               That the Ieſuites Confeſſors are wont to abuſe the conſciences of their penitentiaries to their owne commoditie.
               That of 300. Prieſts which haue entred into England, ſcarce ſixe or ſeauen haue fallen away. But of twentie Ieſuites eight haue reuolted: which is a notable ſlaunder, ſeeing there can not be found one of them to haue reuolted which were ſent in by the Societie.
               That the Ieſuits in the Low-countries are ſo cruell, as that they haue not only brought many excellent men to a miſerable end, but haue reproched them after their death.
               That nothing doth ſo vex the Engliſh Catholicks as the contempt and hatred of the Preſident that now is: and the ſlaunderous reproch falſely imputed to the renowned Cardinals, Tolet, and Alexandrinus.
               
               That the Ieſuites do eagerly wayt for the death of the Pope, and of the renowned Cardinall Tolet, that they might bring vpon all thoſe that ſlaughter and bloudſhed, which they long ſince aſſayed againſt as many as haue dared to oppoſe themſelues againſt their tyranny.
               
                  
The chiefe remedie wherein the ſtate of all controuerſies at Rome dependeth is, that the affaires of all the Colledges be committed to an aſſemblie of honorable Cardinals that are regular, both to looke into, and to determine of. For there is nothing that theſe tyrants more feare, then that they ſhould be compelled before the Cardinals to render an accompt of their dealings. Neither doth any thing giue them greater libertie of their inſolencie, then that they are free welnie from being called before any iudgement ſeate.
               See you ſee (quoth N) my letters ſecretly and effectually, becauſe the enemy, if he be not preuented, flattereth himſelfe in an aſſured hope of a Monarchie. While the iron is hote, ſtrike: worke out your buſines while your Patrones liue. Your enemies ſeeke but to gayne the time; and if they once ſet free themſelues from the ſtreights wherein they are yet incombred, they will (belieue me) domineere moſt tyrannouſly.
               The Ieſuites ſeeke alſo the gouerment of the Colledge at Doway, neither feare they any bridle wherewith they can be curbed, but only, that the Ieſuite Rectors ſhould be made ſubiect to the regular Congregations.
               The Ieſuites by their Machiuilian practiſes go about to procure the diſſolution of the Colledge at Doway.
               
               The tyranny and inſolencie of the Ieſuites is horrible, eſpecially of thoſe that liuing in Belgia, do reproch, diſgrade, depriue whome they liſt: and I feare (quoth he) do indirectly betray ſome vnto the enemy.
            
            
               The Cenſure of Paris before mentioned for our instification, in ſuspending our obedience to maister Blackwels authoritie, vntill we knew his Holynes further pleaſure.
               IN the yeare of our Lord 1600. vpon the third day of May, it was propoſed to the faculty of the Diuines

of the Vniuerſity of Paris, that by the letters of a moſt illuſtrious Cardinall, an Eccleſiaſticall Superior was conſtituted in a certaine Kingdome with the title and dignity of an Arch-prieſt, to haue authority and iuriſdiction ouer all other Prieſts reſiding in that Kingdome. This Cardinall did alſo declare in thoſe his letters, that he did it according to the wil and good liking of the Pope. Notwithſtanding, many of theſe Prieſts refuſed to ſubſcribe to the authority of the ſayd Arch-prieſt, before he had obteyned letters from the Sea Apoſtolick, conteyning the tenor of his confirmation, as well becauſe that kind of gouernment was altogether new in Gods Church, and hitherto neuer heard of, that an Arch-prieſt ſhould haue charge of a whole Kingdome, and ſuch iuriſdiction ouer euery Prieſt in that Realme: then alſo, for that it ſeemed to them by certaine words of the Cardinals letters, that the Arch-prieſt and his authority was graunted by falſe information: then laſtly, becauſe they noted great partiality in the choyſe of the Arch-prieſt and of his counſellors. Vpon which and ſome other reaſons, theſe Prieſts ſent meſſengers to the Pope, for laying open vnto him theſe their difficulties: and therewithall to ſignifie their greateſt readynes, as in this matter, ſo euermore in all other, to obey his Holynes.
               
                  The Arch-prieſt and thoſe who are of his ſide accuſe the other Prieſts of ſchiſme, in that they deferred to obey the Cardinals letters, which moreouer he ſayd were written according to his Holynes minde and pleaſure.
               
               
                  The Question then is, whether theſe Priests be ſchiſmaticks? and if not, whether they did commit at the leaſt ſome grieuous ſinne?
               
               
                  The head and chiefe men of the faculty of Diuinity in Paris choſen out of the whole company, aſſembled together

in the houſe of the Senior Bedle in the yeare and day aboue written, after full and matureſt conſideration had of the matter, gaue this cenſure.
               
               Firſt, that thoſe Prieſts, who vpon the aboue-named cauſes deferred to obey, were no ſchiſmaticks.
               Secondly, that they committed no ſinne at all in that fact in it ſelfe conſidered.
               
                  By commaundement of our Deane and maſters deputed and ſelected by the whole facultie of Diuinity in Paris De lacourt.
               
            
            
               The raſh and vnaduiſed aunſwere of Mayſter Blackwell to the Cenſure of Paris.
               
               
                  
                     Reuerendi Patres &amp; Fratres.
                     WHereas after the condemnation at Rome of the two Embaſſadors together with all their complices here; and alſo the Pope his Breue confirming the Cardinals letters, as validas ab initio, and vtterly condemning and inualidating all things done to the contrary: Some vnquiet perſons haue ſecretly ſought to the Vniuerſity of Paris, and thence pretend to haue or haue receiued a reſolution, that they neyther incurred ſchiſme, nor any ſinne in their proceedings here againſt mine authority. Whereas alſo it is manifeſt that after notice had from their Ambaſſadors of the Pope his expreſſe will made knowne vnto them partly by their impriſonment, partly by the teſtification of the two Cardinals, Caietan, and Burgheſius, to whome their cauſe was committed: which alſo the aforeſaid two Ambaſſadors did certifie hither by their letters, exhorting all heere to the quiet acceptance of their ſuperior, as being ordayned by his Holynes ſpeciall knowledge and abſolute order, without dependence

of their conſent: that yet notwithſtanding this perfect knowledge they repugned and ſtood ſtill obſtinate in their diſobedience: ſo that the pretence of ſeeking to know the Pope his will was altogether friuolous in thoſe which remayned heere. And thereby it appeareth, that the information giuen of the cauſe to the Pariſians was altogether wrong, and (as it may be thought) fraudulent. For ſo long as they refuſed not their ſuperior appoynted by the knowne will of the Pope, they neuer were condemned as ſchiſmaticks: and ſince and whileſt they acknowledged their ſuperior they were neuer cenſured, but only as ſeditious in oppoſing againſt the Pope his order, and in diſturbing the wiſhed peace and tranquility of the Cleargie and Laity of the Catholicks, and yet could neuer be freed from one of theſe two crimes. Propterea, In Dei nomine Amen. Nos Georgius Blackwellus Archipreſbyter Angliae, &amp; Protonotarius Apostolicus ex authoritate nobis ſufficienter &amp; legitime commiſſa praecipimus ſtrictè in virtute obedientia, &amp; ſub poena ſuspenſionis à diuinis, &amp; amiſſionis omnium facultatum ipſo facto incurrendarum, omnibus eccleſiasticis perſonis: omnibus autem laicis Catholicis ſub poena interdicti ſimiliter ipſo facto incurrendi, that neither directly nor indirectly they mayntayne or defend in word, or in writing the cenſure of the Vniuerſity of Paris (whether it be truly giuen or forged: whether vpon true information or otherwiſe) as being preiudiciall to the dignity of the See Apoſtolicall, and expreſſely contrary to his Holynes Breue: and to the ſentence iudicially giuen by the two Cardinals appoynted iudges in our cauſe: and to our common peace ſo much wiſhed for by his Holynes. And this we inuiolably commaund to be obſerued vnder the paines afore ſpecified, and greater alſo, according to his Holynes pleaſure. Yet hereby we intend in no wiſe to diſgrace the moſt famous

Vniuerſity of Paris. For we hope verily, that eyther there is no ſuch cenſure of theirs: or elſe, that it was procured by wrong informations, and without manifeſting the ſentence of the two Cardinals: and the expreſſe confirmation of his Holynes of thoſe firſt letters, by which our authority was deriued vnto vs, which (God willing) we will ſpeedily procure they ſhall receiue from the Court of Rome. And ſo nothing doubting of your duties towards your ſuperiors, I leaue further to inſtruct, or exhort you, beſeeching God to bleſſe vs all.
                     
                        29. May. 1600.
                        Georgius Blackwellus Archipreſbyter Angliae &amp; Protonotarius Apostolicus.
                     
                  
               
               Areioynder of Maister Darrell Deane of Agen, in defence of the cenſure of Paris, againſt M. Blackwell.
               
               
                  
                     Reuerendi Patres &amp; Fratres.
                     THere is come vnto my hands the ſentence of M. George Blackwell Arch-prieſt, in condemnation of the cenſure and iudgement of the Catholique, auncient, and renowned Vniuerſity of Paris. Wherein was alſo thruſt a very peremptory Prouiſo, but moſt neceſſary to auoyd reprehenſion: that no man ſhould vndertake eyther by word or writing to defend the ſayd cenſure. I deemed it not impertinent in few words to runne ouer the ſayd ſentence, to ſhew in part the inſufficiencie of it, as well for the honor of the ſayd ſacred faculty of Paris (which for the worthy ſchollers it hath brought forth, is highly eſteemed throughout all Chriſtendome) as for the aduertiſement of the abouenamed Arch-prieſt, that he may hereafter be ſomewhat better aduiſed ere he thunder out his cenſures: and do not vainely perſwade himſelfe, that he

can either tye the toongs, or ſtay the pennes of men by any ſuch vnreaſonable writ, vnleſſe he take ſome more ſober and conſiderate courſe of proceeding. And for breſities ſake to omit the friuolous preambles that are partly vntrue and wholy to ſmall purpoſe: the firſt of importance is, where he ſayth, That the information giuē vnto the Pariſians, was altogether wrong, and (as it may be thought) fraudulent. His reaſon is: for that they, who liked not his election at the firſt ſtood ſtill obſtinate in their diſobedience, after perfect notice of the Popes breue in confirmation of it, ſent them by their Ambaſſadors (who for honors ſake (you muſt thinke pardye) he alwayes ſo tearmeth) how ſound and true this aſſertion is, all England (as I think) knoweth right well. Sure I am, the common fame ſpread in all countryes betwixt England and Rome, (where the Engliſh are reſident) approued alſo by ſundry letters out of England, and from other coaſts, was, and is cleane contrary: viz. that they, who before ſuſpended their iudgements attending his Holynes reſolution, as ſoone as they were by the Popes breue certified of his pleaſure, ſubmitted themſelues to the Arch-prieſt, and acknowledged his authority. And that I ſtay not about needleſſe proofes in ſo notorious a matter, the very next words after in this his reſcript, declare as much. Mary I muſt needs confeſſe, that they are ſo clarkly and clea
                           •
                        ely ſet downe, that they may perhaps couer ſome pretie equiuocation. Theſe be his words. For ſo long as they refuſed not their ſuperior, appoynted by the knowne will of the Pope, they were neuer condemned as ſchiſmaticks: and ſince, whileſt they acknowledged their ſuperior, they were neuer cenſured, but only as ſeditious, in oppoſing againſt the Popes order &amp;c. The ſenſe in common vnderſtanding muſt needs be: that at firſt, ſo long as they had not certaine notice by the Popes

breue of his will, and therefore refuſed to accept the new Magiſtrate, they were not condemned as ſchiſmaticks. Afterward they vnderſtanding of the Breue, acknowledged their ſuperior: and therefore were not cenſured as ſchiſmaticks, but only as ſeditious. By the latter part of which ſentence, it is moſt euident and cleare by his owne expreſſe declaration: that after certaine knowledge of the Popes commaundement, they acknowledged their ſuperior; and therefore were not cenſured, but only as ſeditious. What can be more contrary to that which he ſayd before? There, he auoucheth boldly, that after certaine notice giuen of the Popes will, they ſtood ſtill obſtinate in their former diſobedience here, that after intelligence had, they acknowledged their ſuperior. I dare not aske you, whether part of this flat contradiction you will beleeue, becauſe both cannot be true: for you muſt either hold (contrary to the rules of reaſon) both parts to be true, or elſe diſcredit him, that within the compaſſe of a few lines affirmed them both. But no maruayle: for I am almoſt aſtoniſhed, to ſee ſo many foule ouerſights in this one poore ſentence. Let that contradiction paſſe: and marke an other in the ſame end of the ſentence. They are cenſured only as ſeditious, ſayth he: in oppoſing againſt the Popes order. What order was that, I pray you? Was it any other, then that they ſhould receiue Maiſter Blackwell for Arch-prieſt, and obey him? No ſurely: how then did they oppoſe againſt that order, who in that very time acknowledged their ſuperior, as in the ſame period he hath himſelfe ſet downe? What a wilfull peruerſenes is this, and blinde deſire of ſlaundering others, to cenſure thoſe for ſeditious, whom they know and do confeſſe to haue acknowledged their ſuperiors. But not to ſtand vpon theſe contrary points (which giue but ſmall grace vnto a graue ſentence) I may not omit that

ſtrange propoſition conteyned in the former part of the ſentence. It is: that they who liked not of his authority, were not, before they receyued certaine notice thereof, by his Holynes breue, condemned as ſchiſmaticks. This is ſo apparantly falſe, and ſo contrary vnto euery ones knowledge, that I much muſe what he meaneth, and where the ſtarting hole, and euaſion lyeth. If he vnderſtand only, that they were neuer condemned by ſentence of iudge, it may then paſſe: for ſo indeed they could neuer haue bin iuſtly. But to ſay, that he and his fellowes did not ſo call them, ſo report of them, and ſo write of them, and in a rude rayling pamphlet in latine ſo denounce them to the wide world, were (as I take it) to make open profeſſion, that he had made ſhipwrack of verity, modeſty, and honeſtie. Hauing thus briefely examined the preamble, I come now to the ſentence itſelfe: wherein I will yet be more briefe. Me thinks he ſeemeth not a little to abuſe that great authority committed to his charge: ad aedificationem non ad destructionem. For following his letters patents, and the right order of correction, he is to puniſh enormous faults after they be committed, vſing alſo before brotherly admonition: to try whether in the ſpirit of lenity, the party may be amended. But he contrarywiſe goeth about by new decrees to make faults (which paſſeth his Commiſſion for ought that I euer yet could ſee) and to puniſh faults without any warning moſt grieuouſly. But you will ſay: that it is for ſome heynous cryme, or elſe he would neuer haue bin ſo terrible and haſty to reuenge? well: let vs heare what enormous fault it is? Mary ſir, if any maintaine in word or in writing directly or indirectly, the graue, Catholicke and learned iudgement of the famous Vniuerſitie of Paris, although it be vpon due information truly giuen (for ſo much his words ſeeme to import) when he ſaith: whether

it be truly giuen or forged, whether vpon true information or otherwiſe) if he be of the Cleargie, he is preſently to be ſuſpended, and to loſe all his faculties (the greateſt penaltie that he could lay on him) if of the laitie: he is ipſo facto, interdicted. I paſſe ouer, that for a light offence, or rather none at all, he hath ordained a grieuous puniſhment, contrarie to that rule of Iuſtice: Proratione delicti, ſit plagarum modus. But this would I faine know, for the inſtruction of many others: how he commeth by the authoritie to interdict any of the Laitie. Sure I am, that in his letters patents, and the Popes breue, he hath no authoritie giuen him, but ouer Prieſts only: whom neither can he interdict, much leſſe any of the Laitie, ouer whom he hath no iuriſdiction at all, for ought I haue yet heard: let him then take heede, that caſting out thoſe cenſures which belong not to him; he doe not himſelfe incurre the true cenſures of his ſuperiours: and for cenſuring others vniuſtly, fall into the iuſt indignation and diſpleaſure of almightie God. But he taketh it otherwiſe: and deemeth the Vniuerſitie of Paris to haue failed much. Let that be his opinion.
                     But whether is likelier to faile, trow you: either one Bachelor in Diuinitie, or many Doctors: one as yet raw, and little practiſed in the diſcipline of the church: or many, of long time daily conuerſant in Eccleſiaſticall affaires: one haſty man (as it ſeemeth) and in the heate of faction: or diuers graue aduiſed men, free from all paſſion and affection? If he thinke by the priuiledge of his titles, to be any whit holpen: the Vniuerſitie of Paris haue in their facultie preſent diuerſe Protonotaries Apoſtolicke and Archprieſts, and many greater officers of their bodie, as Archdeacons, Chancellors, or Vicar generals: that I may omit Biſhops, who are commonly reſident in their Dioceſſes. But perhaps ſome will ſay; albeit our Archprieſt be

ſurmounted in all other reſpects: yet in reaſons and proofes, he paſſeth them all. Let vs therefore come vnto his reaſons which are three in number, and barely auerred; but not one of them proued. The firſt is, that the cenſure of Paris is preiudiciall to the dignitie of the Sea Apoſtolike. Proue that good ſir. For without proofe, that aſſertion will be taken for fond: and I in a word, will proue it alſo to be falſe: for they ſay, it was neither ſchiſme nor ſinne in that doubtfull caſe of the Archprieſts election, to ſeeke vnto the Popes holines for certaine reſolution, where they are ſo farre off from derogating any whit, from the dignitie of the Sea Apoſtolicke, that they doe highly commend it; acknowledging the right of appellation from all inferiour courts, to appertaine vnto the Court of Rome, which is a ſpeciall prerogatiue, whereby we proue againſt heretikes, the ſupremacie of that Sea. This firſt worthie argument then, is drawne perhaps a contrario ſenſu.
                     
                     The ſecond is, that their cenſure was contrarie to the Popes breue. As iuſt as Iermaines lippes. For their cenſure onely was: whether it were ſchiſme or any ſinne, before there was any breue, and wholy abſtracting from the breue: How could it then be oppoſite to that, with which it did nothing at all meddle, or any whit concerne? The third and laſt reaſon is: that their cenſures were contrary to the ſentence of the two Cardinals. No ſuch matter good ſir: For the Cardinals ſentence was onely againſt two by name, and for no other matter, as the ſentence expreſſeth, then for that they had exerciſed controuerſies with ſome other men of their owne order (which alſo how true it is, let them iudge, that know their conuerſation) therefore they thought it expedient, that they ſhould not returne into the Countrie for a ſeaſon without leaue. Now let them conſider who are of higher capacitie

then my ſelfe: how this ſentence is oppoſite vnto the cenſure of Paris: that in doubtfull cauſes to appeale or ſue vnto Rome, is neither ſchiſme nor ſinne: for my wit is too ſimple to reach vnto it. Well to draw towards an end. After that this good man had in ouer great haſte taxed the cenſure of the Vniuerſitie of Paris, as preiudiciall vnto the dignitie of the Sea Apoſtolicke, and contrarie to the Popes breue and Cardinals ſentence: he forſooth (and if you lift to beleeue him) telleth you that he meaneth not to diſgrace that moſt famous Vniuerſitie. Surely, if he thought, that he could diſgrace it, he deceiued himſelfe fowly. For the grace, credit, and renowne of the vniuerſitie of Paris, little dependeth vpon the verdit of ſo baſe and meane a Magiſtrate, and contemneth the bald vnlearned reprehenſions of ſuch ſimple Clarkes. If they meane in ſubſtantiall arguing, to coape with ſo honourable a companion: let them put downe plainely the caſe, as it was propoſed vnto them, with their cenſure, and withall in Latine (as they may vnderſtand it) without paſſion diſproue it like Diuines: and then it may be, if they ſee any thing worth the anſwering; that they will giue ſufficient ſatisfaction to the world of their cenſure. In the meane ſeaſon it muſt needes bee ſmall honour vnto the Archprieſt and others of his band, to oppoſe themſelues againſt the moſt learned, catholicke and famous Vniuerſitie of Paris, as he himſelfe acknowledgeth it: who doe ſtill auouch, and will vphold their cenſure for iuſt and true in any place, whereſoeuer it ſhall be called in queſtion: which me thinkes ſhould much moue all good Catholickes, not ſo ſtifly to backe that ſide againſt other innocent men, who after ſo long and fruitfull trauels for our Countrey, are now for nothing (as it were) mightilie wronged in their good names and credits.
                     I for my part, who alwaies haue moſt tenderly loued the Catholicke cauſe, am moſt ſory to ſee ſuch pitifull

diſſenſion about trifles: and doe moſt earneſtlie in viſceribus Domini nostri Ieſu Christi, requeſt and require the Archprieſt, and thoſe that are ouer paſſionate on that part; to content themſelues with the ſubmiſſiō of others vnto the Popes Holines Breue (which was a high poynt of perfect obedience, conſidering what ſlender audience was giuen vnto thoſe whom they ſent) and leaue off that fruitles iangling, whether they ſinned before or no: or what kind of ſinne it was. Who would not haue thought, but that vpon the receite of the Popes Breue, and obedient acceptance thereof, all would haue been quiet and appeaſed: one forgiuing another, if ought before had paſſed amiſſe: and all ioyning together in defence of each others credit and good name, which was and is moſt neceſſarie for the maintenance of the common cauſe and comfort of all Catholicks. Well at the length yet, for Gods honour, and the holy Churches good, and your owne quietnes, returne vnto that Chriſtianlike and brotherly peace and charitie, ſo much deſired of all entire and deuout Catholicks: which that our louing Sauiour may giue you grace to doe, my humble prayers haue alwaies been, and ſhall neuer, I hope, fayle. Thus in all dutie and affection, recommending my ſelfe to your good prayers, I deſire to be partaker of your fruitfull trauailes. At Agen the 4. of Auguſt.
                     
                        Your humble brother and ſeruant in our Lord:
Iohn Dorel.
                     
                  
               
               We were here conſtrained to breake off, for feare of ſome danger by an intended ſearch: ſo as we haue omitted M. Blackwels letter, mentioned pag. 49. with anſwere vnto it: which together with ſome other matters you ſhall receiue ere it bee long. In the meane while we commit our ſelues to your faithfull prayers: and you by ours, vnto Almightie God.
               
            
         
      
   

