
   
      
         
            A discription of Nortons falcehod of Yorke shyre, and of his fatall farewel The fatal fine of traitours loe: by iustice due, deseruyng soe.
            Gibson, William, ballad writer.
         
         
            
               1570
            
         
         Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01707
            STC 11843
            ESTC S121786
            99856951
            99856951
            22599
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01707)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22599)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 384:17)
         
         
            
               
                  A discription of Nortons falcehod of Yorke shyre, and of his fatall farewel The fatal fine of traitours loe: by iustice due, deseruyng soe.
                  Gibson, William, ballad writer.
               
               1 sheet ([1] p.)   
               
                  By Alexander Lacie, for Henrie Kyrkeham, dwellyng at the signe of the blacke Boye, at the middle north dore of Paules church,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  [1570]
               
               
                  Signed: q[uod] William Gibson.
                  Verse - "Of late (alas) the great vntruth".
                  Publication date from STC.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
                  Mutilated.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Norton, Christopher, d. 1569 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-02
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-03
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-04
            Jason ColmanSampled and proofread
         
            2007-04
            Jason ColmanText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            ¶ A diſcription of Nortons falcehod of Yorke ſhyre, and of his fatall farewel.
            
               
                  
                     
                        The fatal fine of Traitours loe:
                        By Iuſtice due, deſeruyng ſoe.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     OF late (alas) the great vntruth
                  Of Traitours, how it ſped
                  Who liſt to know, ſhal here 
                        〈…〉
                     e
                  How late allegeance fled.
                  ¶ If Riuers rage againſt the Sea.
                  And ſwell with ſoddeine rayne:
                  How glad are they to fall agayne,
                  And trace their wonted traine?
                  If fire by force wolde forge the fall
                  Of any ſumptuouſe place,
                  If water floods byd him leaue of,
                  His flames he wyll diſgrace.
                  If God command the wyndes to ceaſe,
                  His blaſtes are layd full low:
                  If God command the ſeas to calme,
                  They wyll not rage or flow.
                  All thinges at Gods commandemēt be,
                  If he their ſtate regarde:
                  And no man liues whoſe deſtinie
                  By him is vnpreparde.
                  But when a man forſakes the ſhip,
                  And rowles in wallowing waues:
                  And of his voluntarie wyll,
                  His owne good hap depraues:
                  How ſhal he hope to ſcape the gulfe?
                  How ſhal he thinke to deale?
                  How ſhal his fanſie bring him ſound
                  To Safties ſhore with ſayle?
                  How ſhall his fraight in fine ſuccede?
                  Alas what ſhall he gayne?
                  What feare by ſtorms do make him quake
                  How ofte ſubiecte to payne?
                  How ſundrie times in Dangers den
                  Is throwne the man vnwyſe?
                  Who climes withouten holde on hye,
                  Beware, I him aduize.
                  All ſuch as truſt to falſe contracts,
                  Or ſecret harmes conſpire?
                  Be ſure, with Nortons they ſhal taſte
                  A right deſerued hire.
                  They can not looke for better ſpéede,
                  No death for ſuch too fell?
                  God grant the iuſtice of the worlde
                  Put by the paynes of hell.
                  For ſuch a penſiue caſe it is,
                  That Engliſh harts did dare
                  To paſſe the boundes of duties lawe,
                  Or of their cuntrie care.
                  And mercie hath ſo long releaſt
                  Offendours (God doth know)
                  And bountie of our curteous Quéene
                  Too long hath ſpared her foe.
                  But God, whoſe grace inſpires her harte,
                  Wyll not abyde the ſpight
                  Of Rebels rage, who rampe to reach
                  From her, her title quight.
                  Although ſhee flowe in pitifull zeale,
                  And loueth to ſucke no blood:
                  Yet God a caueat wyll her lend
                  T'appeaſe thoſe Vipers moode.
                  A man that ſées his houſe on fire,
                  Wyll ſeke to quench the flame:
                  Els from the ſpoyle ſome parte conuey,
                  Els ſeke the heate to tame.
                  Who ſée a penthouſe wether beate,
                  And heares a boiſtrouſe wynde:
                  But héedefull ſaſetie of himſelfe,
                  Wyll force him ſuccour fynde?
                  The pitifull pacient Pellican,
                  Her blood although ſhée ſhed:
                  Yet wyll ſhée ſeme her date to end,
                  Or care her young be ſped.
                  The Eagle flynges her yong ones downe
                  That ſight of ſunne refuſe:
                  Vnperfect fowles ſhée deadly hates,
                  And rightly ſuch miſvſe.
                  The Crane wolde flye vp to the Sunne,
                  I heard it once of olde:
                  And with the kyng of byrdes did ſtriue
                  By Fame, I heard it tolde
                  And do woe ſhe wolde not fal f
                        •
                     e no,
                  But higher ſtyll did mou
                        ••
                     :
                  Til paſt her reach (ſaith olde reporte)
                  Shame made a backe recour
                  I touch no Armes herein at all
                  But ſhew a fable wyſe:
                  Whoſe morall ſence doth repr
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
                  Of clymers hye the guyſe.
                  Who buyldes a houſe of many 
                        〈…〉
                     ,
                  and laith not ground work
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
                  But doth ertorte the ground 
                        〈…〉
                     g,
                  His buildyng can not dure
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
                  ¶ Who ſekes ſurmiſing to diſp
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
                  a Ruler ſent by GOD:
                  
                  Is ſubiect ſure, deuoide of grace
                  The cauſe of his owne rod.
                  A byrde that wyll her neſt defyle
                  By right ſhould looſe a wyng:
                  And then is ſhee no ſlying fowle,
                  But ſlow as other thyng.
                  And he that loſeth all at games,
                  Or ſpendes in fowle exceſſe:
                  And hopes by haps to heale his harme,
                  Muſt drinke of deare diſtreſſe.
                  To ſpeake of brydles to reſtrayne
                  This wylfull wayward crewe:
                  They care not for the booke of God,
                  To Princes, men vntrue.
                  To cuntrye, cauſers of much woe,
                  To faithfull fréendes, a fall:
                  And to their owne eſtates, a ſtyng,
                  To others, ſharpe as gall.
                  O Lorde, how long theſe Lizerds lurkt,
                  Good GOD, how great a whyle
                  Were they in hand with feigned harts
                  Their cuntrye to defyle?
                  How did they frame their furniture?
                  How ſit they made their tooles:
                  How Symon ſought our englyſh Troie
                  To bryng to Romaine ſcooles.
                  How Simon Magus playd his parte,
                  How Babilon bawde did rage:
                  How Baſan bulles begon to bell,
                  How Iudas ſought his wage.
                  How Iannes and Iambres did abyde
                  The brunt of braineſicke acts,
                  How Dathan, Chore, Abiram ſéemd
                  To daſh our Moyſes facts.
                  How Romaine marchant ſet a freſh
                  His pardons braue a ſale,
                  How alwayes ſome againſt the Truth
                  Wolde dreame a ſenceles tale.
                  Gods vicar from his god receaued
                  The keyes to loſe and bynd:
                  Baals chaplein thoght hꝭ fire wo
                        〈…〉
                     e
                  Such was his pagan mynd.
                  Good Lorde how hits the ter
                        •
                      their 
                        〈…〉
                     ts
                  That ſaith ſuch men ſhall bée
                  In their religion hot nor colde
                  Of much varietie.
                  And ſundry ſorts of ſects ſur
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
                  Diuiſion ſhall appeare:
                  Againſt the father, ſonne ſha
                        〈…〉
                     ue,
                  Gainſt mother, daughter 
                        〈…〉
                     e.
                  Is it not come to paſſe trow you?
                  Yea, baſtards ſure they bée,
                  Who our good mother Quéene 
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
                  Withſtand rebelliouſlie.
                  Can God his vengeance long reta
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
                  Where his true ſeruants féele
                  Iniuriouſe ſpights of godleſſe men,
                  Who turne as doth a whéele?
                  No no, his ſuffryug long (be ſure)
                  Wyll pay his foes at laſt:
                  His mercye moued once away,
                  He ſhall them quight out caſt
                  With ſentence iuſt for their vntruth,
                  And breakyng of his wyll:
                  The fruits of their ſedicious ſéeds,
                  The barnes of earth ſhall fyll.
                  Their ſoules God wot ſore clogd wt crime
                  And their poſteritie
                  Beſpotted ſore with their abuſe,
                  And ſtand by their follie.
                  Their liuyngs left their name a ſhame,
                  Their deedes with poyſon ſped:
                  Their deathes a wage for want of grace
                  Their honours quite is dead.
                  Their fleſh to feede the kytes and crowes
                  Their armes a maze for men:
                  Their guerdon as examples are
                  To daſh dolte Dunces den.
                  Throw vp your ſnouts you ſluggiſh ſorte
                  You mumming maſkyng route:
                  Extoll your exclamations vp,
                  Baals chapleines, champions ſtoute.
                  Make ſute for pardons, papiſts braue,
                  For traitours indulgence:
                  Send out ſome purgatorie ſcraps,
                  Some Bulls with Peter pence.
                  O ſwarme of Drones, how dare ye ſtyl
                  With labouryng Bées contend?
                  You ſought for home from the hiues,
                  But gall you found in end.
                  Theſe waſpes do waſt, their ſtings be out
                  Their ſpight wyll not auayle:
                  Theſe Peacocks proude are naked lefte
                  Of their diſplayed tayle.
                  Theſe Turkye cocks iu cullour red,
                  So long haue lurkt a loofe:
                  The Beare (although but ſlow of foote)
                  Hath pluct his wynges by proofe.
                  The Moone her borowed light hath loſt,
                  Shee wayned as we ſee:
                  Who hoped by hap of others harmes,
                  A full Moone once to bée.
                  The Lyon ſuffred long the Bull,
                  His noble mynd to trye:
                  Vntyll the Bull was rageyng wood,
                  And from his ſtake did hye.
                  Then time it was to bid him ſtay
                  Perforce, his hornes to cut:
                  And make him leaue his rageing tunes
                  In ſcilence to be put.
                  And all the calues of Baſan kynd
                  Are weaned from their wiſh:
                  The Hircan Tigers tamed now,
                  Lemathon eates no fiſh.
                  Beholde before your balefull eyes
                  The purchace of your parte,
                  Suruey your ſodeine ſorrowful ſight
                  With ſighes of dubble harte.
                  Lament the lacke of your alies
                  Religious rebells all:
                  Bewepe that yll ſucceſſe of yours,
                  Come curſe your ſodeine fall.
                  And when ye haue your guiles out ſought
                  And all your craft approued,
                  Peccauimus ſhall be your ſong
                  Your ground worke is remoued.
                  And looke how Nortons ſped their wills
                  Euen ſo their ſect ſhall haue,
                  No better let them hope to gayne
                  But gallowes without graue.
               
            
            
               
                  
                     
                        
                     
                     que
                   William Gibſon.
            
            ¶ FINIS.
         
      
      
         
            ¶ Imprinted at London by Alexander Lacie, for Henrie Kyrkeham, dwellyng at the ſigne of the blacke Boye, at the middle North dore of Paules church.
         
      
   

