
   
      
         
            Endimion· An excellent fancy first composed in French by Monsieur Gombauld. And now elegantly interpreted, by Richard Hurst Gentleman.
            Gombauld, Jean Ogier de, d. 1666.
         
         
            
               1639
            
         
         Approx. 256 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 111 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01849
            STC 11991
            ESTC S103202
            99838959
            99838959
            3352
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01849)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3352)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1173:14)
         
         
            
               
                  Endimion· An excellent fancy first composed in French by Monsieur Gombauld. And now elegantly interpreted, by Richard Hurst Gentleman.
                  Gombauld, Jean Ogier de, d. 1666.
                  Passe, Crispijn van de, ca. 1565-1637, ill.
                  Gaultier, Léonard, 1561-1641, engraver.
                  Picart, Jean, ill.
                  Hurst, Richard.
               
               [16], 144, 143-206 p.   
               
                  Printed by I. Okes, for Samuel Browne, and are to be sold in Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the Fountaine,
                  London :
                  MDCXXXIX. [1639]
               
               
                  With an additional title page, engraved: L'Endimion de Gombauld Englished ..
                  With an imprimatur on A1. Variant 1: lacking imprimatur. Variant 2: imprimatur printed on verso of engraved title page. Variant 3: imprint date in arabic numerals.
                  The engraved illustrations are from the same plates as the French edition of 1624, and are variously signed by Léonard Gaultier, Crispijn van de Passe, and Jean Picart.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
      
      
         
            2007-01
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-01
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-03
            Celeste NgSampled and proofread
         
            2007-03
            Celeste NgText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
               
               
                  L'ENDIMION
DE
GOMBAVLD
ENGLISHED
MDCXXXIX
                  LONDO
                        •
                     
                  
               
            
         
         
            
            
            ENDIMION.
            
               AN
Excellent Fancy firſt compoſed
in FRENCH by
Mounſieur Gombauld.
            
            
               And now Elegantly Interpreted,
BY
RICHARD HURST
Gentleman.
            
               LONDON:
Printed by I. Okes, for Samuel Browne, and are
to be ſold in Pauls Church-yard at the
ſigne of the Fountaine.
1639.
         
         
            
            
            To the truely Noble,
and much honored,
Sr. ROBERT ANSTRUTHER
Knight, and one of the
Gentleman of his Majeſties
Privy Chamber.
            
            
               SIR,
            
            
               IT is a poſition, and
maine Tenent agreed
upon by the moſt judicious,
that to attaine unto Honour,
Wiſedome is the truly Poleſtarre,
and to retaine it, Vertue
the ſole Patroneſſe: It being non
               
               ad tempus Invitamentum, ſed perpetuae
virtutis premium. To
which, though ſome have arrived
by favour, others by fortune,
yet it may be ingeniouſly confeſt
of You, that by Your owne
merit You have won to this meridian:
Into which the ſacred
Majeſty of Great Brittaine having
a true inſpection, out of
many others, hee made ſelect
choiſe of you, (for your known
abilities) to create his Lord Embaſſadour
to the Majeſty of the
Empire. And during your abode
at Vienna in Auſtria, where
the Emperors Court was then
kept, the Gentleman, Author

hereof, Mr. Richard Hurſt (now
deceaſed) your (then) ſervant
and Secretary, at his more ſpare
and retired houres, made this
his Worke his play, and in his
moſt ſolitude his beſt ſolace.
And unto whoſe Patronage may
it more properly appertaine,
than to your Noble ſelfe, being
writ in your forraigne ſervice.
This was the maine inducement,
which not onely incouraged,
but imboldned me to
this preſentment, knowing that
Honos alit Artes; and the rather
preſuming on your acceptance
hereof, ſince they who in their
life time the Muſes moſt favour,

thoſe, after life, the nine
Siſters moſt honour. Thus,
with pardon for my boldneſſe
crav'd, I humbly take
my leave of You.
            
               Yours in all
Obſervance,
S. B.
            
         
         
            
            To the Reader.
            
               Generous Reader,
            
            
               HEre is commended to thy
judicious view a moſt ingenious
Tractate of Endymion,
vulgarly ſtyld, The
Man in the Moone: a Diſcourſe
intermixed, as well with Philoſophicall
rudiments, as Poeticall
raptures: The matter ſublime, the
ſtile ſuccinct; neither ought it to
be any way miſ-cenſured for the
Title: For all that trade with Luna,
are not therefore to bee held
Lunaticke; neither are all things
that ſeeme fixious meerely fabulous:

for rare fruites may grow of
rugged trees, and golden truths may
be gathered from leaden Fables.
But to ſuch as are not throughly
Verſt in this ſubiect, it ſhall not
be amiſſe to ſpeake ſomething briefly
concerning Endymion and the
Moone, (the argument of this
preſent Fancy) the better to perfect
them in the peruſall thereof.
She is called Trivia, for ſo ſaith
Virgil, Prince of Poets, in theſe
words.

                  Tria virginis, or a Diana
               
And that by reaſon of her three
ſhapes, Coeleſtiall, Terreſtriall,
and Infernall: when ſhe ſhineth
in Heaven, ſhe is Cynthia, or

               Luna: when ſhee appeareth on
Earth, Latonia virgo, or Diana;
being reſident in Hell, Hecate,
or Proſerpina: And for two
reaſons ſaid to bee enamoured on
Endymion: The one, in regard
he was the firſt that ſtudied to obſerve
the courſe of the Moone,
and therefore was thought to have
ſlept thirty yeares, becauſe hee ſpent
ſo much time in ſolitude, to find
out that ſecret. The ſecond, becauſe
the humour of the nightly
Dew, dropping from the Starres
and Planets, is ſucked in, and
commixed with the moyſture and
juyce of the Hearbs and Plants,
to their better animating &amp; cheriſhing;

as alſo being profitable to
flocks of Shepheards, in whoſe
number Endymion was ranked
as the moſt eminent amongſt them.
It is the Tranſlation of a French
Coppy, three ſeverall times impreſt,
and in the Originall cry'd up, even
by the most ſupercilious Criticks:
with many curious Copper Prints
decorated, and to one of the greateſt
Princeſſes in Europe at firſt Dedicated:
and for Mr. Richard
Hurſt, the Tranſlator, he was not
onely knowne to be a Traveller, but
withall an excellent and learned
Linguiſt, of an accute wit, and a
mature iudgement; who in the Interpreting
thereof, hath not onely

equald, but tranſcended it, in the
elegancy both of phraſe and ſtile:
But why ſhould I ſo much labour to
recommend that, which in the Reading
can ſufficiently approve it
ſelfe, onely let me intreate thee to
Read favourably, as it is rendred
unto thee faithfully, and with this
Caution, I commit it to thy free and
friendly Cenſure.
            
               Thine, S. B.
            
         
         
            
            
               
                  L: Gaultier incidit. 1624
               
            
         
      
      
         
            
            ENDYMION.
            
               The Firſt Booke.
               
                  IN the City of Heraclea, when as the
Night was much advanced, and
drowſie ſlumber ſeazing the ſences,
had charmed all cares, and rendred
ſmall difference betwixt the dead, and the greater
part of the living: there was on a ſuddaine
heard a great noiſe of Trumpets and Clarions,
and without, in the fields multitudes of people,
who haſtening to the top of Mount Lathmos,
made all the adjacent places reſound with the
Eccho of divers ſorts of Inſtruments, both of
Braſſe and Copper, whereof they were furniſhed
with plentifull ſtore: For the Moone, who
but a little before ſupplyed the place of the Sun,
and dimmed the luſtre of the faireſt Starres in the
Firmament, was ſurpriſed by a ſuddaine defection,
and, as if ſhee herſelfe had beene by

ſome powerfull hand blotted out of the liſt of
the Planets, her whole light was converted into
ſuch a horrible obſcurity, as added another
Night to the Night it ſelfe. The infernall
ſhades ſeemed to extend their limits even to the
very Heavens, or elſe that Nature becomming
blind, were to returne to her former confuſion;
every thing was ſo repleniſhed with horrour and
aſtoniſhment, that even the moſt prophane were
touched with a feare of the Gods. Now it was
the cuſtome of the Ancients in ſuch Accidents,
to make uſe of Mettalls of the ſhrilleſt ſound
they could get, as thinking by that meanes to
recover the Moone from ſome trance, or deliver
her from the charmes of the Magitians, who
boaſted that they could at their pleaſure bring
her downe from Heaven, under the favour of
Night and Silence: ſo that they, perceiving her at
length by little and little returne, as ſhe had gone,
and in leſſe than a quarter of an houre, (ſo ſoone
as the Sunne had reſtored her the light, which
the ſhadow of the Earth had before robbed her
of,) appeare in all her ſeverall ſhapes, they very
eaſily perſwaded themſelves that ſhee was
much therein obliged to their care and diligence;
and, thus pleaſed, reſolved to imploy the
remainder of the Night, in taking the reſt which
they conceived they had juſtly deſerved at the
hands of the gods, by having travailed themſelves

in the reſcue of a Goddeſſe. But as one
of them, named Pyzander, more curious in the
contemplation of this faire Starre, and ſlow in
his Retreate, had by chance ſtayed on the Hill
a little while behinde the reſt; he heard not farre
from him, certaine accents of Lamentation, and
ſuch as that houre of Night rendred, as more
ſad, ſo more plaine and ſhrill. This ſomewhat
affrighted him, but preſently inſpired him with
a greater curioſity of knowing what it might be;
ſo that ſoftly drawing nearer to it without diſcovering
himſelfe, he underſtood theſe words:
Is not this Mount Lathmos? who is this, that in
an inſtant hath brought me backe into mine
owne Countrey, from whence of late I was ſo
farre diſtant? And who is it, that together with
my Countrey hath reſtored me my life? Alas!
here is the Sacrifice, but what is become of the
Prieſt, or where is the Altar? And what hand
(intending to doe me a favour) hath brought
me from amidſt ſo great a people? Is it thou
Diana, who as thou ſhineſt more faire than ordinary
in the Heavens, ſo thou now beholdeſt me,
if at leaſt thou vouchſafe to looke on me, more
unfortunate than ever? Whether thou be cruell,
or mercifull, wherefore permitteſt thou me not
to die? Although thou bereaveſt me of all other
happineſſe, yet deprive me not at leaſt of this
laſt, as the common comfort of the moſt miſerable:

wilt thou force me to live therein, to ſhew
the whole choler of Heaven aſſembled upon one
man? doeſt thou hinder me to dye once, that
thou mayſt keepe me alwaies dying, and that
the memory of the favours thou haſt heretofore
done me, may conſume me with ſorrow, being
determined (having loſt them) never hereafter
to preſerve any thing. That thou haſt loved me
Diana, is witneſſed by thy expoſing my life to ſo
many dangers, that I could not have expected
worſe from thy hatred, than is arrived to mee
from thine affection: Thou haſt loved me, (I
thinke) intending thereby to imprint in me an ill
opinion of the gods, and to let me ſee they are
neither conſtant nor juſt. I ſhould have judged
thy humour and diſpoſition by that of thine Empire,
which Fortune hath given thee onely over
the lighteſt and moſt inſenſible things in the
World. O yee Mortals, take mine example, to
make you feare the loves of Goddeſſes, leaſt they
bring you to a tryall of all wretchedneſſe: all the
honour and glory of their Love, are but vaine
and ſilly rewards, ſince the exceſſe of ſo many
torments wholly annihilates the ſenſe of it.
               O yee gods, ſayes Pyzander to himſelfe, what is
this I heare? me thinkes I ſhould know this
voice, but I underſtand not this lamentation:
can Endymion bee in theſe parts, and I have no
advertiſement of it? and being returned home,

ſhould he live as though he were ſtill abſent? and
(ſeeking rather Deſert places, than ſociety of
men) bee more diligent in viſiting this Mountaine,
than his deareſt friends? Thus Pyzander,
diverſly aſſaulted, ſometimes with one imagination,
ſometimes with another, continued hearkning,
and Endymion lamenting.
               I endure the puniſhment, ſaies he, O goddeſſe,
and know not the crime I have committed;
except it be for having added the contempt
of all things in the world to the eſtimation
I made of thy good will. Become now
contrary to thy ſelfe, and (forgetting what thou
oweſt to my conſtancy) take up againſt mee the
plea both of the gods and men; all whom I
have injured in the ſole deſire of adoring thee:
If thou accuſeſt me of no other thing, thine accuſation
is ſufficient to juſtifie me. Mine offence
is a great merit, which makes mee farre more
worthy of recompence than puniſhment. Yet
all this while I have not beene able to advance
any one ſtep, nor erect ſo much as a Tombe for
my ſelfe: But peradventure mine affection is
preſumptuous, and my complaint raſh. But now
I am compelled (pardon me O goddeſſe) to require
it of thine eyes; to whom, as to thy promiſes,
I have beene too too credulous. I would
alſo crave it of thy heart and memory, if happily
they may bee true to thee. Thinke not

that I can forget my duty through the too often
remembring thy favours: for although I ſhould
reape no other fruite of them, but the loſſe of
time, and my ſelfe; yet will I dare counſell thee,
to favour thine enemies ſtill in that manner.
               It is either Endymion, ſaies Pyzander, or his
Ghoſt, which perhaps wanting opportunity of
paſſage to the ſhoare of the dead, wanders in
theſe parts. Hath he ended his dayes by Shipwracke,
or ſome other accident, which hath deprived
him of Buriall, and granted him none other
Tombe but the Heavens? So long as the
Sunne ſhall behold his body, his ſoule ſhall not
be received amongſt the Ghoſts. But whither
doth mine aſtoniſhment make me wander? and
what doth my feare cauſe me to utter? Thoſe
are not the Diſcourſes of a dead man, but rather
of ſome one weary of his life. In the meane time
Endymion, whoſe complaint, like his paſſion, ſeemed
infinite, and who, as it were, laboured to
convince a goddeſſe of ingratitude, and inconſtancy,
failed not (in continuing his diſcourſe)
preſently to name himſelfe, and thereby gave Pyzander
a reſolution to interrupt him. I muſt
confeſſe Goddeſſe, ſaid he, that I am not worthy
of the leaſt favour that ever thou haſt done me;
and that the conſideration of what I am, might
juſtly enjoyne mee ſilence. But what! are the
gods blinde? or have they onely an obſcure

knowledge of humane actions? doe they deliberate
without judgement? or can they poſſibly
recant their firſt determinations? As for mee,
I ever made account to ſurpaſſe all other men
whatſoever in vowes, and affection to ſerve thee;
but never thought to exceede a Goddeſſe in reſolution
and conſtancy: yet I finde thee no leſſe
mutable than a mortall; and, as if it were not enough
to change, thou proceedeſt from inſtability
to oblivion. The name of Endymion is no
more in thy mouth, than the eſtimation of him
in thy heart: thou talkeſt no more of him to thy
Nymphes; no, not ſo much as to thy thoughts.
At this name of Endymion, Pyzander (tranſported
with his longing) approaching him, findes
him laid along under the brow of the Hill with
his armes a croſſe, and his eyes fixed upon the
Moone; and thus beginnes to ſpeake to him.
What gods are thoſe, that being at once froward
and favourable, doe make me heare the
voyce of a man ſo deare to me, by a lamentation
ſo grievous, whereof the cauſe is alſo unknowne
to me? Have I ſo often deſired to ſee Endymion
againe, to the end that ſuch a ſiniſter accident
ſhould now make mee affraid of his encounter
when it is offred me? Ah! my deare Pyzander,
ſaies Endymion, (riſing, and giving him his hand)
what good fortune beginnes to approach mee,
in reſtoring me the preſence of him, whom my

ſight, but not my thought hath beene ſo long
deprived of? Or what ſad miſhap is this that
increaſeth my ſorrowes, by afflicting thee? For
I believe, none but the unfortunate, and ſuch as
watch when others ſleepe, doe repaire to theſe
ſolitary places, in this time of night. Tell me, I
beſeech thee, what brings thee hither? Verily,
anſwers Pyzander, I have more cauſe, and a
farre greater deſire to heare thy newes from thy
ſelfe, ſince thou findeſt me in our owne Countrey,
where thou lefteſt us all, to goe ſeeke
(doubtleſſe) more ſtrange adventures than we.
But I wonder extreamly, Endymion, that thou
ſeemeſt ignorant of the cauſe of my comming
hither▪ for if the noyſe wee lately made were
heard by the Moone, much more ſhould it bee
come unto thine eares, to awake thee out of the
deepeſt ſlumber thou couldſt be caſt into. So
farre was I from ſleeping as thou imagineſt, ſaies
Endymion, that I was in a place farre remote
from hence, where me-thought, I was caſt into
an everlaſting ſlumber: From whence I was
freed, like one that dreames, finding my ſelfe in
this place, without perceiving how, or which
way I came hither. I confeſſe there was even
now a great noyſe, which did doe me a very ill
office, and made mee wiſh that all things had
beene more quiet, and that an univerſall ſlumber
had rendred all the creatures on earth as dumbe

as thoſe of the water. Indeed Endymion, ſaies
Pyzander, I underſtand thee not, for thy latter
Diſcourſes are more obſcure than thy former:
I beſeech thee therefore keepe me no longer ignorant
of that which our friendſhip ſhould make
common: Tell me thy good or ill adventures; for
thou knoweſt it is the property of communication
to render contentments more full, and increaſe
the power of them, as alſo on the contrary,
to extenuate and eaſe afflictions and croſſes.
Alas! replies Endymion, where ſhall I beginne,
or how ſhall I end? Shall I robbe thee of thy
reſt this night, by recounting unto thee my ſufferings,
wherein my owne ſpirit ſhunnes the remembrance
of whatſoever moſt delights it: ſo
much am I grieved to ſee fortune, ſo unworthily
inſult over my torments and patience. Thus
Endymion would have excuſed himſelfe touching
the Diſcourſe; but that Pyzander ſtill adding
more intreaties and requeſts to his former, got
him at length to ſit downe by him, and to begin
in this manner.
               O Pyzander! how mighty a Maſter is Fate!
and how vainely doth our reaſon labour in
ſtraining her ſelfe to reſiſt, and not to follow it
whereſoever it leades us, be it to our advantage
or prejudice! It takes away our judgement,
and one while by flattery, another while by force
maketh us loſe the path of every other adventure.

Now, that I may not forget to tell thee
every particular, thou muſt know what chanced
me, when I was in the City of Epheſus. As upon
an Holy-day about the end of the Sacrifices, we
walking the Streets paſſed one of the houſes neereſt
to Diana's Temple: (for Polydamon was by
chance with me) I was mightily amazed, at a
certaine woman, who from her threſhold caſting
her eye upon me amongſt the multitude, called
me by my name, which was very ſtrange, that
ſhe having never ſeene me before, ſhould then
ſo ſuddenly know me, without any information
whatſoever. Beſides, ſhe was ſo old, that ſhe
could ſcarce have found witneſſes to teſtifie that
ever ſhee had beene young: and together with
her miſ-ſhapen &amp; diſcoloured face, hollow eyes,
hanging cheekes, dry and withered skin, ſhe had
ſo few ſignes of life left, that it ſeemed, ſhe ſtayed
onely in the world, to repreſent the image of
Death. In briefe, this woman with extraordinary
paines caſting up her ſight, which before
was continually fixed on the Earth, and which
had beene long diſ-accuſtomed from looking up
to Heaven, ſayes, come hither Endymion; I obſerving
the wildneſſe of her looke, and her geſtures
to be ſuch, as made her ſeeme tranſported
with frenzy, or poſſeſſed of ſome ſpirit more
vigorous than her owne; and not being able enough
to wonder at this accident, ſuddenly

                  
                     Cr Pas inu
                  
                  
ſtayed, without being curious to draw nearer, or
anſwer her: but ſhe comming towards me, ſtooping
and ſtaggering, like one tyred with bearing
the burthen of ſo many yeeres, and to whom
the onely diſtance of three ſteps ſhe had to make,
ſeemed a long voyage, and a moſt tedious exerciſe,
ſaid, Be not affraid to heare thy fortune; for
the Decrees of Themis are inevitable both to the
gods and men: and then ſhe uttered theſe Verſes.
               
                  The Starre that in the Forreſt raignes,
                  A thouſand favourable ſtraines
                  
                     Ʋpon thee with her beames ſhall dart,
                  But in the end thoſe ſhall depart,
                  And thou be forc'd to thinke and tell
                  Inconſtancy in the gods doth dwell.
               
               
                  As the deſires are violent,
                  Th'attempts are faint, not prevalent,
                  'Tis hard the gods to trace:
               
               
                  A heavy-light enchantment doth
                  Stoppe, and make thee wander both,
                  It kills▪ it gives thee grace.
               
               And ſo retiring her ſelfe, Polydamon told me,
he thought ſhe was mad; for ſaid hee, what acquaintance
is there betwixt you? but I, inſtead
of anſwering him, pondered what ſhe had told

me; and gheſſing that there was ſome extraordinary
matter in it, ſavouring rather of a Goddeſſe
than a Woman, and inclining more to inſpiration
than frenzy, for my more full ſatisfaction,
I inſtantly demanded of one of her Neighbours
what ſhee was? who anſwered me, Art thou a
Grecian, or a Barbarian, that thou knoweſt not
the Virgin Parthenopea, one of the chiefe of the
Race of the Iamides, who uſually doe propheſie
at the Olympian Feſtivalls? But another told
me, in more courteous tearmes, that ſhe whom
we tooke for a Woman, was a Maiden, of at
leaſt an hundred yeares old, and who, beſides
that ſhe was indeed of that race of the Prophets
iſſued of Apollo and Evadne, having conſtantly
vowed her Virginity to Diana, and employed
her whole life in her ſervice, had in plentifull
meaſure received from her the gift of fore-telling
things to come.
               The greateſt feare I then had, was, leſt I might
have forgotten ſome of the words ſhee had ſpoken
to me, wherein the meaſure of the Verſes
ſtood me in good ſtead: for by often turning
and repeating them with my ſelfe, and by the
helpe of the ſeverall parts, I had in a ſhort time
imprinted the whole in my memory; wherewithall
I could not enough entertaine me, for
my ſpirit already began to anticipate my good
fortune, by hope and a thouſand kinds of differently

delightfull imaginations. The ſweete
aſpects which were promiſed me in the beginning,
did ſo fully deprive me of the conſideration
of the croſſe adventures which threatned me
towards the end, that the moſt rigorous afflictions
that could befall me, ſeemed delightſome
&amp; honourable, becauſe they were to be for
Diana's ſake.
               From thence forward mine eyes found none
other object that could content them, except ſuch
as put me in minde of her; and ſhunning all variety
or diverſion, I was ſtill contemplating either
her Portraict in the Temple, or her Starre in
the Heaven. But chiefly, after my returne from
Epheſus, I deſired to remaine on the top of this
Mountaine, where I ſlept the greater part of
the day, that I might imploy the night in this
ſweet contemplation; which begot an opinion
in divers, that I ſlept alwayes.
               By this courſe I ſaw the Sunne leſſe ordinarily
than the Moone, whoſe luſtre was to me a thouſand
times more pleaſing, than that of the faireſt
dayes: I did ſo ſeldome let her goe out of my
ſight, that I was able to give the world accompt
of the wayes ſhe held in the Heaven, from the
houſe of Helles even to that of Aſtrea, or that
of Erigone, and thence to Ganymedes and farther:
yea, even when in her Chariot drawne by
Dragons, ſhe parts from the Celeſtiall Manſions,

to goe take her walke in the Countries of ſome
of the Daughters of Atlas: whether on the one
ſide ſhe goe to viſite Caſſiope, Andromeda, and
the whole family of Cepheus; or on the other, ſhe
goe to hunt towards Orions quarter, or by
chance, in the hot weather ſhee ſometimes for
her recreation, retire to the Caves of the Centaure,
or in the coole of the Evening ſhee walke
upon the ſhoare of the great Celeſtiall River,
which is diverſly named, by ſome Nilus, by others
Erydanus. And the Goddeſſe tooke the diligence
and affection I had to make her glory
knowne in all parts ſo well, that ſhee became as
willing to ſhew her ſelfe, as I was deſirous to behold
her; in ſo much that I cannot ſay, if mine
eyes were either more comforted by her favour,
and leſſe dazeled by her light, or that by being
accuſtomed to this exerciſe, they with the more
eaſe pierced the Heaven. But (as if ſhe were deſcended
into the middle Region of the Ayre)
me thought I ſaw her Chariot rowle upon the
Clouds; and (to endeare and gratifie me the oftener)
ſhe inclined her looke towards me with
the ſame aſpect, wherewith ſhee beholds the Sacrifices
that moſt delight her. She darted for my
ſake the ſweeteſt lookes that her heart was able
to ſend forth through the paſſage of her eyes;
wherewith theſe places were ſo enlightened, that
they ſeemed not ſenſible of the abſence of the

day: O wonder of Fate &amp; Nature! A Goddeſſe forgetteth
all the Gods, for the cōtemplation of one
ſimple man, and finds that thing on earth, which
makes her deſpiſe the Heavens. There is nothing
lowlier than the ſubject which ordinarily retains
her looks and thoughts; and by her affection ſhe
ſeemeth to become (as it were) mortall and humane:
And on the contrary, a mortall contemplates
onely heavenly things, hath nothing but
a Deity in his thought, and hath his eye fixed
onely upon beauty it ſelfe, that is, on Diana.
               
               But what an extraordinary proofe did I receive
one day of her goodwill, when as the Heavens,
all covered with Clouds, which ſeemed
jealous of my good fortune, kept me from ſeeing
her: and how happy was it for me, that
there had beene ſome few dayes ſo cloudy, as it
were on purpoſe! For in that time I was advertiſed
by the faithfull relation of one of her
Nymphs, that ſhee was as much troubled therewith,
as I, and that ſhee had bemoaned her ſelfe
of it to the Goddeſſe Iris in this manner. Iris,
ſaid ſhe, it would not trouble me much, to be a
while deprived of ſeeing a good part of the
Earth, provided that I might at leaſt behold
thoſe places which doe moſt delight me. Now
I will tell thee freely, that I have lately taken a
particular affection to Caria, and yet it is full
foure dayes ſince I laſt ſaw it: I had rather be debarred

the ſight of the Iſle Delos, or of my native
Mountaine, the name whereof I beare. Diſperſe
therfore I pray thee the Clouds a little, &amp;
divert them either towards Lycia, or Ionia, or
any way elſe, ſo that any hand thou hide not
the City of Heraclea, nor Mount Lathmos from
mine eyes. Immediately after this there appeared
a great opening in the Clouds, and the darke
vapours vaniſhed at the preſence of the goddeſſe,
who beganne to appeare in her faireſt and
moſt perfect luſtre, and as if ſhe had aſſembled
all her beames about me; I found my ſelfe in
an inſtant wholly environed with light. O happy
and fortunate Endymion! ſayes Pyzander, if
the ſweete lookes of the Moone can be able to
render a man ſo. But tell me, what couldſt
thou be doing? and how couldſt thou diſpoſe
of thy ſelfe, all the times ſhe appeared not in the
Heavens? Even that which ſhe her ſelfe doth,
when ſhe is deprived of the light of the Sunne,
anſwered Endymion: Shee attires her ſelfe in a
blacke vaile, as if ſhe could not miſſe the ſight of
him one houre, without mourning for his abſence.
Even ſo, what light ſoever ſhone, I ſeemed
to live in darkneſſe, and had no other exerciſe,
but a continuall wandring up and downe
the Woods, to trye whether I could learne any
newes of her; or whether my Fate, or her favour

would give me leave to finde her: Wherein I
laboured a while in vaine, but at length, as it is
the cuſtome of the gods, ſometimes to prevent
our hopes, and otherwhiles to come when
our expectations are tyred; ſo this good
happe chanced to mee when I leaſt thought
of it.
               The night had already begunne to furle up
her ſailes, and a gentle coole gale, the fore-runner
of light, ſweetly cheriſhed ſlumber, and with the
force of its wings, drove before it a cleare thinne
Cloud, laden onely with a light dew, beſprinkling
with drops the whole earth, like Pearles,
which ſparkled even as little eyes in the faces
of the flowers and Plants. When as awaking,
and finding an ayre more pleaſing than ordinary,
and ſuch a one as the gods have in Heaven, or do
bring with them when they come downe to the
earth: I came out of the Cave, being moved
thereunto by a certaine pleaſing violence, which
had no leſſe power over me, than if ſome voice
had called me forth. And ſcarce had I paſſed
the threſhold, when as I ſaw before me, upon
the edge of the Hill a woman, for ſuch at firſt
I tooke her to be; but having a little nearer obſerved
her beauty, her ſtature, and more than humane
Majeſty, I knew that it was ſome of the
goddeſſes. With what tearmes now ſhall I

poſſibly expreſſe that, which then mine eyes
beheld? and from whence ſhal I draw compariſons
to repreſent unto thee that which (being
beyond compare) can admit none? I ſhall
have ſooner done, if without attempting to
demonſtrate light by obſcurity, I bid thee fixe
the eye of thy imagination (ſo farre forth as
thou art able) abovt all the Heavens, and
there behold Beauty it ſelfe fitting, accompanyed
with an everlaſting youth, and ſuch as
can neither ſuffer alteration, or be impaired
by any accident whatſoever. O Pyzander,
how farre are the Divine beauties different
from theſe here below! &amp; how ſoon did they
beget in my ſoule a contempt of all that before
I had ever ſeene! But I taſted this felicity
in the moſt abſolute degree of all, when
perceiving the Bow ſhe held in her hand,
and the Creſſant which ſhone upon her head,
I found it to bee the goddeſſe to whom my
heart addreſſed all its vowes: this, I ſay,
made me imagine that the day tooke his
being thence, and not from the riſing of the
Sunne. Endymion, ſayes Pyzander, as I deſire
not to ingage thee in impoſſibilities; or to
buſie thee overmuch in a long and vaine deſcription
of things which cannot be repreſented:
So will I yet entreate thee to give

mee ſome figures of this Divine beauty,
as much as our humane language can
permit thee. Amongſt ſo many perfections,
ſayes Endymion, I know not which I ſhould
firſt obſerve; and the deſire I had to behold
them all, hindred me from taking particular
notice from any one, and was cauſe I ſaw
them but confuſedly. One while I was amazed
to ſee, that in ſo perfect a ſtature,
(wherein ſhe farre ſurpaſſed the beſt formed
of women) ſhe ſeemed to be of ſo tender an
age: for her complexion was tenderer and
fairer, than that which appeares in the firſt
bloome of youth it ſelfe, being mixed with
certaine darting glances, which ſeemed to
participate of both flames and flowers, and
accompanyed with a vertue ſo Divine, as
that it defended it from the injuries of the
Seaſons, and freed it for ever from the juriſdiction
of Yeares. Sometimes I admired
in her a kinde of Majeſticke demeanour,
which as it had force to attract the nobleſt
courages, wanted not alſo auſterity enough
to checke thoſe whom puſillanimity accuſed
of want of worth, and to prohibite them to
approach her. Honour and Majeſty ſeemed
to ſit in her Countenance, as in a ſeate of
well poliſhed Ivory, keeping a perpetuall reſidence

under the rich ornament of her faire
Treſſes, ſome whereof were plaited and
wreathed; others bound up and curled after
the Laconian manner, with farre more grace
than Art, there being no neede of addition
either to their luſtre or number. Some
others careleſly diſperſed, and, as it were, eſcaped
from the bands and captivity of the
reſt, danced on her vermillion cheekes,
and faire ſhoulders; catching, and captivating
(in their ſporting) both Love and Zephirus:
round about her Corrall Lippes appeared
the ſweeteſt ſmiles, and the moſt delicate
of all the Graces, both which joyntly
with their attracts and courtings, did there
manure the Gilly-flowers amidſt the Lyllies
and Roſes. Which way ſoever ſhee turned
her faire eyes, both browne and cleare, the
ayre became in an inſtant ſo ſweete and pure,
that every thing was beautified and refreſhed
therewithall. Thoſe eyes are really
the two Starres, who at their pleaſure doe
beget a new Spring on Earth, and appeaſe
the Sea when it rageth and is troubled. But
what doſt thou embarke me in Pyzander?
and what is this that I undertake? to ſpeak
to thee of thoſe eyes, in whoſe preſence, there
is none other able to looke up, or conteſt

never ſo little without being dazelled: which
was the cauſe that I my ſelfe was conſtrained
ever and anon to caſt downe mine eyes, and
let them fall on her faire necke, although it
were onely a diverſion of them from flames
and lightnings, to looſe them in the Snow
of her boſome and breaſts: where I could ſee
no more on each ſide (they being by chance
halfe covered) than a ſmall Creſſant of thoſe
two little (but truely Celeſtiall) Globes,
which were in continuall motion, and who,
as ſcorning to be reſtrained of liberty, forced
open her garment, as much as poſſibly they
could; ſo that if they could not fully diſplay
their dazelling whiteneſſe and beauty, at leaſt
they gave ample teſtimony of the perfection
of their round forme; and if they troubled
not the eye, yet ſpared they not to ſhake the
imagination. Herein it is, Pyzander, that the
moſt eloquent would become dumbe, and
therefore will I ſpeake no more of it, leaſt
the onely remembrance thereof ſhould render
me ſpeechleſſe, and leave me nothing
elſe but ſighes.
               All thoſe places rejoyced in the preſence of
this Goddeſſe, who ſeemed to have made
another Olympus of Mount Lathmos. As for
me, I was ſo fraught and repleniſhed with

contentment, that enjoying whatſoever can
in this life be moſt delightfull, me thought
I then firſt began to live: I was wholly raviſhed
with the wonders of ſo rare an object,
when as directing towards me her lookes, every
motion whereof ſeemed to bee conducted
by the Graces themſelves: Endymion
(ſayes ſhee, with a voice ſo cleare and pleaſant,
as would with the firſt word have charmed
any breaſt) thy vowes have touched
me even in Heaven, and thine affection hath
beene acceptable to me. I know what care
thou takeſt to imprint my glory and greatneſſe
in the knowledge of the Mortalls; if I
ſhould not be ſenſible of it, thou wouldſt have
juſt reaſon to complaine of me, and to publiſh
over all the World, that Ingratitude is
lodged as well in Heaven amongſt the gods,
as on Earth amongſt men. Make uſe therefore
of thy good Judgement, and aſke of
me whatſoever thou wilt, wherein I may
have opportunity to teſtifie mine acknowledgment,
and doubt not of the grant: I (remaining
wholly mute and confounded, not
onely by ſeeing her, and receiving ſo great
honour at her hands, but alſo, for that admiration
and reſpect equally enjoyned me ſilence)
had not the power to deſire any thing;

eſteeming my paines and watchings too fully
recompenced with one only looke of hers,
or the leaſt word ſhe had vouchſafed to ſpeak
to me: Inſomuch that at firſt, I was not able
to ſpeake at all; and although I could, I
knew not what to ſay unto her: and this forced
ſilence wa
                     •
                   advantagious to me, in that
ſhe gave me (by an act of her accuſtomed
goodneſſe) ſome ſmall time to bethinke
and recollect me. I was once minded to beg
of her the ſame thing which my Father obtained
of Jupiter; which was, to live, and
dye according to his good liking. At length
finding that I muſt needs ſpeake, the conſideration
of my duty ſurmounting my feare,
and furniſhing me with ſubject of diſcourſe,
in deſpight of the diſtraction wherewith I
was poſſeſſed, I thus anſwered her: Great
Goddeſſe, the honour thou doſt me, doth infinitely
exceed my condition; grant me therfore
what thou thinkeſt fitting; for what
could I requeſt of thee? I forget all that is
paſt, and can thinke of nothing for the future,
being ſo throughly poſſeſſed with what
I at preſent enjoy. Give me leave rather to
offer my ſelfe to thee, and if thou gratifie me
ſo farre as to receive me, I will beleeve thou
haſt granted me all things. I would gladly

begge of thee, that the happineſſe I now enjoy,
might be made everlaſting: but ſhe, well
obſerving the extaſie wherein ſo unwonted a
felicity had caſt me, and which having in
the beginning deprived me of ſpeech, went
on alſo to ſeize upon my underſtanding, replying
aſkes me, how wouldſt thou be able,
(ſaid ſhe) to endure that long, which in a
moment hath ſo diſtempered thee, as thou
hadſt need of ſome body to reſtore thee to
thy ſelfe? And as for that which thou requireſt,
thou couldſt not obtaine it, albeit thou
wereſt in the principall Ranke amongſt the
Immortals: thinke therefore quickly on
ſome other ſuite, that I may be no longer detained.
Aſſuredly ſaid I to her, mortall men,
who live ſo ſhort a ſpace, have great reaſon
to thinke time precious, ſince the very gods
themſelves, whoſe Nature is infinite, are ſo
tender and carefull to looſe none of it. But
whereunto doſt thou oblige me ô Goddeſſe?
for, conſidering thee as Diana, I doe not ſee
what I can aſke of thee ſuitable to my deſire,
ſince the honour of attendance, and perpetuall
ſerving of thee, belongeth onely to thy
Nymphs? and for me, I can eſteeme nothing
gratefull, that ſhall enjoyne me a long ſeparation
from thy preſence: I will therefore

ſpeake unto thee as to the Moone, beſeeching
thee, that by the power thou haſt in Heaven,
thou wilt be pleaſed to allow me ſome place
amongſt the Starres, and that I may be one
of thoſe, which goe leaſt out of thy ſight, and
moſt frequently waite on thy Chariot whither
ſoever thou goeſt. Or, if the number
of the Starres be ſo compleate, that not one
more can bee added thereunto, and if the
Fates reſiſt me herein, grant me at leaſt, the
priviledge amongſt the Mortals, of rendring
thee the moſt acceptable Vowes and Sacrifices,
and of employing my whole life in thy
ſervices. Hereat the Goddeſſe (not content
to teſtifie her approbation by a gracious
nod of her head onely) with a ſmile, able
to raviſh both gods and men, added theſe
words: Well ſaies ſhe, be it in Heaven, or on
Earth, I will never omit any occaſion of gratifying
thee; neither would I have thee
doubt of mine affection or memory of thee.
Scarce had ſhe ſaid thoſe words, when on a
ſuddaine I loſt the ſight of her, and heard
onely a ſmall noiſe of the Arrows, and Quiver
which ſhooke upon her ſhoulders, as ſhe
turned her ſelfe to be gone. In the meane
time I forgot not to meditate on that which
I had often heard ſpeech of, to wit, that the

                  gods have a forme of going, different from
that of men, and that without the trouble
of putting one foote before another, they
have power in the twinkling of an eye, to
tranſport themſelves where they pleaſe, and
that every way on Earth or in Heaven is alike
eaſie to them. But alas! I much over-ſaw my
ſelfe, in that I procured her not to ſweare by
the River Stix, an Oath inviolable amongſt
the gods. Endymion, ſayes Pyzander, either
the gods are not, or elſe they are true, and
doe infallibly acknowledge the love is borne
them; for if they faile us, whom ſhall wee
truſt? all things muſt faile us with them: but
this Hill will bee ſooner converted into a
Plaine or Valley; and ſooner ſhall Meander
(ſhunning the Ionian Sea) runne retrograde,
and ſtoppe in the ſource, than the
words of the gods prove inſtable; and chiefely
thoſe of Diana, that great Ornament of
the World, who by ordinance of the Deſtinies
doth in ſo many Countries ſupply even
the place of Jupiter himſelfe: But good Endymion,
proceede, for I am ſorry that I
ſhould imploy the time in any thing, but hearing
thee; ſo much I long to ſee the ſucceſſe
of thine adventures.
               The ſenſe I had of this ſo high a favour,

was for a great while the onely ſupport of
my life, and raiſed my contentment to that
height, that it admitted no compariſon; no,
not with the moſt fortunate amongſt men.
The greatneſſe and ſtate of the perſon I adored,
and who reciprocally graced me with ſo
much good liking, did place all the honours
and dignities in the world beneath my condition
and glory: All converſation, yea, even
that of my deareſt friends, ſeemed tedious to
me; as well for that they onely interrupted
the ſweeteſt delights of my ſoule, as for the
ſcruple I made to communicate unto them
the leaſt of my thoughts. My memory often
repreſented this goddeſſe to me, as vively as if
ſhee had beene before mine eyes: Wherein
I tooke more pleaſure, than in the very time
in which I enjoyed her preſence; becauſe, as
then, the exceſſe of my rapture depriving
me of my ſences and judgement, permitted
me not to be mine owne. I went a hundred,
and a hundred times to viſit the place where
I had ſeene her, and was never weary of ſeeking
ſome new foote-ſteps of hers, which I
had not before taken notice of. I kiſſed
the graſſe which her feete (accuſtomed to
walke in Heaven) had bruiſed; and became
as ſtrict a Guardian of the place, as if it had

beene of a Temple or Altar. But as my
thoughts preſented her before mine eyes,
ſo alſo alſo did my dreames; dreames indeed,
more faire, and more reſplendent than
the day; and ſuch, as truely I never deſired to
awake from. Sometimes me thought I beheld
her ſpeaking to me, onely with the language
of her eyes, which looked on me with
ſo ſweete an aſpect; that no tongue is able to
expreſſe that which they ſeemed to ſay unto
me. Another while me thought ſhe ſpake
to me, with a geſture equalling, yea, exceeding
ſpeech it ſelfe. Sometimes, caſting
my ſelfe at her feete, I endeavoured to ſtay
her, and kiſſed the hemme or skirt of her
Vaile, and ſometimes (O too preſumptuous
dreams!) me thought I kiſſed her hand it
ſelfe. O to what altitude of glory and felicity
doth ſleepe raiſe even the moſt wretched!
And how much greater favours did it
give me taſte of, then the mouth which received
them dares rehearſe, it being ſo
cloſe ſhut, as if thereby ſilence had beene
impoſed upon it: and indeed I onely diſcourſed
thereof to my thoughts. Oh Heavenly
contentments, ſaid I, are you counterfeit
or reall? But how counterfeit, becauſe
ſo ſenſible? and how reall, being onely

in a dreame? If I would complaine of
them, or give my vowes and thankes for
them: to whom ſhould I addreſſe my ſelfe,
to Slumber, or to Diana, or to both at once?
The one ſhutteth mine eyes, the other ſeales
up my lippes, and with a pleaſing violence
contrary to it ſelfe, ſteales my ſoule from me,
and yet permits it not to iſſue. Oh goddeſſe!
if thou art ſo favourable to me, as
that thou aſſiſteſt, and art really preſent in
this ſweete Myſtery, wherefore doſt thou
make uſe of the opportunity of ſlumber?
Or if thou be not preſent, or beareſt no part
herein▪ wherefore then doſt thou ſuffer ſleep
to abuſe thine Image for my ſake? Oh,
but perchance thou cauſeſt the charmes
thereof to accompany thine, that being thus
tempered, and the moderation of the one
quallifying the force of the other, my life
may be preſerved. Is this then the way
which the goddeſſes take, to communicate
moſt familiarly with Mortals? And are
their greater favours of ſuch diſproportion
with our ſences, that they muſt be entranced,
before they can participate of them?
or in a manner halfe dead, to prevent a full
dying: It is to me indeed a favourable foreſeeing,
and diverting of what might thence

befall me; for I doe verily perſwade my ſelfe,
that if thou (when thou daigneſt to make
me thus happy) ſhouldeſt not take me in my
ſleepe, thou wouldſt inflict more than a
thouſand deaths upon me by an exceſſe of
contentment, and ſo be as many times troubled
to reſtore me my life, as thou hadſt before
deprived me of it: Thus, Pyzander, I
knew by day that I was a Man, although the
night rendred me equall to the gods.
               
               Pardon me Diana, if by chance I diſcourſe
freely that which I am not obliged by any
Law to conceale. The wiſe man, ſayes Pyzander,
conceales the greateſt part of his
thoughts; but what rule of Wiſdome tyes us
to keepe ſecret our Dreames? Every man
takes the liberty to ſpeake of them to whom
he pleaſeth, and forbids not his curioſity to
conſult with any Interpreters, thereby to diſcover
and obtaine (according to their feares
or deſires) ſome light from their obſcurity,
or ſome certainty from their ambiguity:
and beſides, no man can be cenſured for the
follies or vanities of Dreames, ſince to them
all manner of liberty and freedome is allowed.
There is no man, Pyzander, ſayes Endymion,
but in his ſleepe doth ſometimes ſee
certaine obſcure and cloudy repreſentations

of ſuch things as moſt content and delight
the minde being awake: but to have (as I
had) every Night continuall viſions of Diana,
to ſee ſo cleare, mine eyes being cloſed,
and ſo ſenſibly to enjoy (my whole ſences
being charmed) ſuch pleaſures as exceed any
mention I am able to make of them, is a ſecret
which I cannot comprehend.
               The end of the Firſt Booke.
            
            
               
               ENDYMION.
               The Second Booke.
               
                  AWhile after, not enduring to feed
longer on vaine images or repreſentations,
how delightfull ſoever,
at ſo great a diſtance, I impatiently
longed, once more to ſee, on Earth,
her, whom I only beheld in Heaven. Wherein,
albeit a Goddeſſe, and a very favourable
one, yet to me ſhe ſeemed tedious, and of
too ſlow and ſmall a reſolution. I durſt promiſe
my ſelfe, that ſhe, who in reſpect to the
diligence and care I had taken to keepe me in

her preſence, had beene moved to wiſh ſo
well to me, would bee yet more induced
thereunto by my words, if I might but ſpeak
to her. And that I might loſe no opportunity,
I frequented for her ſake, Hunting and
Fiſhing; in both which paſtimes I knew ſhe▪
as Miſtreſſe of thoſe Exerciſes, tooke eſpeciall
delight. But all that was in vaine; for whilſt
I went to ſeeke her in the moſt deſart places
about Meander, ſhee was perchance on the
Banke of Eurotus or Peneus▪
                   or elſe courſing
ſome Lion in Getulia, or ſome Hart in Creta,
or Tiger in Armenia: For there are ſo
many Rivers, Forreſts, and Mountaines▪
more delightfull than thoſe of Caria, ſo many
by-waies and turnings, and ſo many
Courriers, and travailers that ſhe takes care
of, as indeed it had beene a wonder for me
to have encountred her.
               At laſt, not knowing more what to doe,
or with whom to conſult, I called to mind
Iſmen, with whom I had a very familiar acquaintance.
Thou knoweſt the eſteeme ſhe
deſerves above all other women, and the
great judgment and inſight ſhe hath both in
divine and humane things: Apollo himſelfe
exceeds her not, in the knowledge of the power
and vertue of Hearbs, and the Moone
                  
will ſooner for her ſake come downe from
Heaven, than for any other. Indeed, ſaies Pyzander,
it is held that ſhe is able to compaſſe
whatſoever ſhee will undertake, and that
Theſſalia never had her equall. I reſolving
one day to goe ſee her, ſaies Endymion, and
to uſe my uttermoſt endeavours to charme
the moſt charming of Women, did thus accoſt
her: Oh bleſſed Iſmena, ſole honour of
thy Sexe, and thou whoſe manners and vertues
are ſuch, as yeeld no place to the Goddeſſes
themſelves: What praiſes ſhall I ſpare to
ſet forth thy glory▪ and what a high obligation
of duty ſhall I be bound to thee in, if
thou wilt befriend me ſo farre, as to free me
from the torment and affliction wherewith I
am at preſent enveloped; for whoſoever, diſtreſſed
in body or minde, labours for the honour
of ſeeing thee, finds thee preſently favourable.
Thine encounter is a good preſage
unto all, and whither ſo ever thou goeſt,
thou art more deſired than preſent: but
as thou haſt power of doing that good,
which none can ever be able to requite by any
equall retribution: ſo muſt it neceſſarily follow,
that thou findeſt the recompence thereof
in the glory that thou duely gaineſt thereby.
Beſides, what can all mine endeavours

adde to the felicity of her, who needs not the
helpe of any Mortall, and to whom her owne
vertue is a ſufficient ſupply of whatſoever ſhe
hath uſe of? who with an equall power diſpoſeth
both of gods and men, and can at her
owne diſcretion alter the courſe of Nature
and Deſtiny! If thou wilt in all things exactly
imitate the Example of the gods, thou
knoweſt it is the hurt they have power to
doe, which makes them feared, but it is
their clemency and good deeds which chiefly
make them adored; and all power is fruitleſſe,
that being implored, aſſiſts not. My
ſupplication and ſuite is not of ſuch a difficult
nature, as that ever the Night ſhould thereby
be made to ſurpriſe men at noone-day, or
the force of Charmes hinder the courſe or
brightneſſe of the Starres. The Rivers ſhall
never for my ſake, run backwards to their
ſources, nor their waves ſwell in a calme.
The Husband-mans graine ſhal not be thereby
tranſported from one field into another,
to beguile his hopes at Harveſt: and the Hils
or Woods ſhall not change their ſcituation
or owners. Neither doe I petition thee to
diſquiet the contentment of the living, or
repoſe of the dead, nor yet that the Ghoſts
ſhould ariſe and anſwer thee: and farre leſſe

that thou ſhouldſt by any charming or ſiniſter
potions, create or extinguiſh any affection:
No, I know thou never doeſt abuſe thy
ſkill, and for that cauſe it is, that the gods
love thee, and give thee a daily increaſe
thereof, rendring thee equall to themſelves.
But yet I will tell thee freely, that I have
beene of late moved by a juſt occaſion, to a
continuall viſiting of the moſt remote and
ſolitarie places of the banke of Rivers,
Plaines, Woods, and Mountaines, to find,
if it be poſſible, an opportunity of ſeeing the
Goddeſſe Diana, who hath heretofore obliged
me with ſo great a liberality, both of her
preſence and promiſes. Wherein firſt, I will
preſume to crave thy advice, and then afterwards
ſome effect of thy power and aſſiſtance.
               She having awhile ſilently conſidered with
her ſelfe, lifted up her eyes which were before
fixed on the Earth, and anſwered mee
thus: I ſhould thinke my ſelfe infinitely happy,
Endymion, in finding any occaſion, wherein
I could be able to ſerve thee, which as I
have devoutly wiſhed for, ſo I will not ſpare
to ſeeke it even amidſt the greateſt difficulties.
I confeſſe, there is nothing ſo hard, but
may by Art and Diſcretion be compaſſed: for

not onely the Goddeſſe thou deſireſt to ſee,
whether thou ſueſt unto her as to the Moone,
Diana, or Hecatea; but even both the Jupiters,
and all the gods, muſt at length give
place to the power of Charmes. The moſt
ſpeciall and important thing now is, that
care be employed in making a right uſe of it,
leſt the abuſe bring inſeparable revenge with
it. Haſt thou never heard, that Nemeſis (the
puniſher of offences) otherwiſe called Andraſtea,
becauſe ſhee is inevitable, hath her
Throne placed upon the Moone, (according
to the repreſentation the Egyptians have
made of her) that ſhe may thence the more
perfectly take a view of the actions of men
and puniſh ſuch as are audacious and raſh?
Knoweſt thou not alſo, thot others figure her
with a Scourge, in that hand on which ſide
Hope is ſeated, to the end that none ſhould
thinke to eſcape with impunity, if they aſpire
to ſuch things, as are not fit for them to deſire?
If therefore thou, inſtead of bringing
downe the Moone, wouldſt not draw on thy
head the anger of Heaven, bee carefull that
thou call her not, but on good and juſt
grounds▪ and with the opportunity of a
perfect ſilence, and that when all things, even
to the very leaves of the Trees, be at reſt:

for if the leaſt noyſe ſurprize her▪ before
ſhe have ſet foote on the ground, ſhe will preſently
before thy face returne up to the
Heavens with greater ſpeede than ſhee came
downe. The gods, Endymion, with difficulty
and much labour are moved to come to
men, but doe returne with great and eaſie
haſte; as having alwayes more cauſe to be averſe
than favourable to them: and the leaſt
inconvenience or hindrance is of force to diſtemper
and give interruption to the greateſt
miſeries. Eſpecially this one requireth ſo
much obſervance and dexterity, that it muſt
be ſtolne from the eyes of all the gods and
Men: and although a generall ſlumber ſhould
ſeize both the one and the other, yet we are
taught, both by neceſſity and providence, that
Jupiter himſelfe (and hee onely▪) never
ſleepes.
               If the favour of Heaven towards us, Iſmena,
ſaid I, be ſo ſmall; perchance that of
the earth may be greater. And ſince this
goddeſſe doth equally divide her care, and
preſence to the one and the other, if we can
encounter her in the Mountaines or Forreſts,
what need have▪ wee to ſeeke more
difficult meanes? and (with ſo much danger
of loſing it) to prevent the opportunity,

which of it ſelfe may follow us? Indeede,
ſaies ſhe, that is the other meane I intended
to tell thee of, which alſo wants not its obſtacles
or difficulties. For although we may
ſometimes find her in Ionia it ſelfe, or ſome
other part of Greece: ſometimes in the
Woods of Merathon, or Erymanthus, other
whiles on the tops of Hymettus, Cytheron▪
Othrys, or Pindus; yet we muſt oftner expect
and ſeeke her amongſt the Sarmatae, or Garamantes,
or in ſome other the moſt ſecret
and remote place of the World. Beſides,
ſhe is moſt commonly accompanyed of her
Nymphes, whoſe profeſſion and exerciſes
have rendred them for the moſt part ſo rigorous,
and unfit for converſation, that the
onely ſight of men ſo offends them, that a
ſmall provocation would induce them to
denounce the ſame warre to them which
they have done to the moſt ſavage Beaſts.
But (which is yet more faſtidious, and leſſe
ſupportable to thoſe that deſire the enterview
of this goddeſſe) ſome of them keepe
their eye ſo conſtantly upon her, as if Heaven
had made them her Guardians Doris and
Laomeda, ambitious, jealous, and curious
Nymphes, doe ſo nearely watch, and ſo ſtrictly
beſiege her, that ſhe is not onely inacceſſible,

but indeed really captive. Yet, that
they ſhould aime, to know, controle, and
conduct all were more tollerable, if they
did not alſo labour to poſſeſſe all. It is almoſt
incredible, how the very gods themſelves,
as well as men, by a ſecret exceſſe of
goodneſſe and indulgence, are inſenſibly overſwaied
by the deſires of thoſe whom they
favour. So that by over-gratifying ſome
one, or two, or three perſons, they ſeeme to
retrench the greater part of their liberality
they owe to many; I will not ſay unto all. And
whilſt a ſmall number doth even ſurfeit on
their beneficence; whole multitudes ſuffering
it, accuſe Heaven, and hate Government, together
with their owne lives, and the light.
Shall we therefore inferre that the gods are
not juſt? farre be it, but let us rather acknowledge
that they governe all things by the will
of Fate, according to its innocence, or the
corruption of the times. This I tell thee, Endymion,
out of the affection I beare thee, to
the end thou maiſt remember, and duely conſider
every poynt.
               Oh Iſmena, ſaid I, let me ſee Diana and
dye: ſhe may perchance be touched her ſelfe
with a deſire to ſpeake with me: for the gaining
of this favour I am ready to expoſe

my life to all manner of perills; and if I
loſe it, that ſhall not at all grieve me, if ſhee
onely may know it was for her ſake. O yee
gods! replyed ſhe then, my memory doth
me ill offices very often: and I have much
abuſed both the time and thy patience:
for my laſt nights dreame fore-told me all
that thou haſt recounted to me; wherein I
ſaw Diana her ſelfe, and received directions
from her what I ſhould doe, and preſcription
of meanes, which but juſt now I
was ſo much troubled to finde out. This is
the very time, and the moſt fit, wherein ſhee
leaves the Heaven to paſſe a few dayes on
Earth. I know of a Forreſt in the World,
conſecrated to this goddeſſe, whereunto the
beauty of the place, and the innocence of the
inhabitants, doe often invite her to come for
her recreation. That is the place where
ſhe uſually keepes her Chariot and her
Armes: beſides the great number of wilde
beaſts doe there afford her more different
and acceptable paſtimes than in any other
part. Faile not thou on the day of the
Sunne, towards evening, to be at the toppe
of Mount Lathmos: and the morrow after,
which will be the day of the goddeſſe, I will
endeavour to make thee happy, if at leaſt

thy felicity onely conſiſt in the honour of
ſeeing her.
               Vpon this reſolution, Pyzander, which was
taken on Venus day, I tooke leave of her,
untill the time ſhe had aſſigned me; which
ſeemed ſo long in comming, that I can
ſcarce tell thee, whether I had greater torment
by mine impatient deſire, or more
comfort in my hope. But above all, the
day of the Sunne ſeemed to me ſo long,
that I would have beene glad to have ſeen
Phoebus haſtened with a precipitation to his
ſetting. At length the ſhadowes of the
Woods and Hills beganne to increaſe, and
the fore-runner of the day and night, which
appeares alwaies in the Heavenly Carriere,
had already lighted his Torch, and the Weſt
became as red, as if all the fire in the World
had beene encloſed in the boſome of it, or
the fall of ſome other Phaëton had enflamed
it of new. Such are the Evenings which
preſage faire and untroubled dayes; and ſuch
was that to be, which promiſed me the ſight
of Diana on the morrow: When I perceived
Iſmena, who as lively and cheerefully
mounted to the toppe, where I attended her,
as if Mercury had conducted, or Zephyrus
carryed her. At the very firſt ſhe asked me

what I ailed, adding, if thy heart be no better
than thy looke, how doſt thou thinke to accompliſh
thy enterpriſe? I thinke thou
haſt not ſlept ſince I was laſt with thee,
thou art ſo diſtempered: this indeede I did
feare, and that the diſquiet of thy minde
could not permit thy body to take any reſt;
and fore-ſeeing the inconvenience, have not
failed to fit thee with a remedy. Behold
wherewith, ſaid ſhe, preſenting me a Violl, I
was not long ſince in the Kingdome of ſlumber,
where I drew this water from the
Fountaine which bedewes her Gardens, and
begets her Poppeyes, and Mandragora's; being
one of the ſources of the River Lethes:
Take onely two or three droppes of it, and
I will aſſure thee thou ſhalt ſleep the ſweeteſt
Nappe that ever thou yet tookeſt. Beſides,
it is neceſſary that thou ſleepe whilſt I labour
for thee, leſt thine impatience ſhould trouble
me. Theſe Myſteries, Endymion, require
reſt and ſilence, and will admit none other
ſpectators, or witneſſes, than onely thoſe that
act them, and are deſigned for the office.
Free me then from the feare of thy diſtemper,
and ruine not thine owne deſignes by
thy curioſity, or preſence: which way ſoever
I turne, goe, or ſtirre, leave me wholly to

                  
                  
mine owne liberty, leaſt thou become aſtoniſhed
by the ſight of incredible things,
and ſo at length horrour and affright ſeize
thee. For what wouldſt thou ſay if thou
ſhouldſt ſee me preſently deſcend for Heaven
in the Chariot of the Moone? I obeying
whatſoever ſhe commanded me, laid
me downe in this Cave, where I felt ſuddainly
the great vertue of that little water
ſhe had given me, which ſo ſtupified me, that
if no body had awaked me I beleeve I ſhould
have continued in an everlaſting ſlumber.
The calme of ſilence was generall (as you
may beleeve) and the Starres had well advanced
their courſe; when as, not knowing what
Iſmena had done, or what vertue of Hearbs,
actions, or words, or what force of Creatures,
or Heavenly, or earthly power ſhe had
employed: I ſuddenly found my ſelfe tranſported
with great contentment, and little or
no feare; but doe not yet know whether it
were in a Chariot of Ivory, or Ebony, or
whether it were drawne by Horſes, or Dragons;
for I could ſcarce diſcerne that which
was neareſt to me: like unto vaine and ambitious
men, who alwayes perceive things remote,
better than they ſee themſelves. I
cannot judge whether it were by the inſpiration

of the gods, or by the induſtry of Iſmena,
or whether Morpheus gave me ſuch cleare
viſions: But I knew places which, if mine
eyes had beene open, I ſhould not have
knowne, even to the diſcovering and diſtinguiſhing
of the Hills, Rivers, and Provinces
over which I was carried. I had one encounter
which gave me matter to thinke on
even from the beginning: which was, that
juſt as I felt my ſelfe taken up, I heard a
voice, and ſaw a Monſter in the Aire, faced
like a Man, but in all other parts reſembled
a Fowle, which followed mee till
hee had uttered theſe words. Now goe
thy wayes, with a miſchiefe, and make
the Oracle a lyer, which hath pronounced
that one of thy race ſhall deprive the
Citie of Olympia of a part of her glory, by
building another to the memory of his owne
Name, whereunto our Games muſt one day
be transferred. Oh Pyza, Pyza, thou art not
yet borne, and yet thy fame and the mention
of thee annoyes me.
               This firſt Viſion was enough to have amazed
me, if what I had heard concerning the
Oracle, had not given me more hope, than
the firſt words feare: But if I knew not what
this name of Pyza might ſignifie, except it

were meant for the name of ſome Citie, to be
hereafter built by ſome one of mine offſpring:
For the reſt, I ſuppoſed it was the Genius
of Olympia that had thus ſpoken, or at
leaſt ſome Magitian of that place, who had
aſſumed the forme of ſome Bird of Night to
flie in the darke withall. So making way towards
the Eaſt, borne by a divine and all
Celeſtiall motion, I paſſed as it were in an
inſtant Licia, a great part of Mount Taurus,
Licaonia, Tyanea, the River Melas, Mount
Argeus, and all Capadocia, even to Euphrates,
which I began to diſcover in the leſſe
Armenia, and immediately after, in Armenia
the greater I obſerved the Sources thereof
at the Hill Periardes, ſo famous for its fertility:
then turning a little towards the
North, I paſſed the River Araxes, neare unto
the mouth of it, where it falls into the
Caſpian Sea.
               
               At length having traverſed many Hills and
Vallies, I found my ſelfe in a ſeeming quiet
place, where having remained awhile in my
former aſtoniſhment and trance, I felt Iſmena,
who taking me by the hand, raiſed me
up, ſaying; Now Endymion, now is the
time to goe, and to take reſolution and courage
with thee; gird on thy Sword, (for

ſhe had a care to bring it along from the Hill)
draw it, brandiſh it in thine hand, and ſee
that thou be not much moved at whatſoever
thou encountereſt: for here thou haſt to doe
onely with a vaine and giddy people, who not
enduring the light, are conſtrained to wander
in darkneſſe; and who at the onely glance
of Steele, doe tremble with feare. What
Monſters ſoever ſhall follow, or appeare to
thee, ſuppreſſe all affright with this confidence
and aſſurance, that their formes render
them farre more terrible than their forces.
Goe ſtraight forward, but above all,
when thou commeſt into the Forreſt, where
thou art to ſee the Goddeſſe, beware of cutting,
breaking, or violating the leaſt
branch or leafe, for the place is ſacred, and
thou maiſt peradventure thereby unwittingly
offend ſome Nymphe, to whom, by the
favour of Diana, a priviledge is granted to
live a ſecond life, and paſſe many ages under
the barke of ſome Tree. For me, I will be as
carefull to know what becomes of thee, as I
have beene to know where Diana was; that
if any danger threaten thee, thou ſhalt no
ſooner have thrice pronounced the name of
Iſmena, but thou ſhalt ſee mee at hand to
ſuccour thee: and if thy hazard be ſuch, that

my power alone, without the helpe of the
gods, be not ſufficient to deliver thee, I will,
rather than faile thee, uſe force upon the gods
themſelves, and draw the Moone from Heaven,
to free thee from the danger whereinto
thou ſhalt be plunged for her ſake.
               Upon theſe aſſurances I reſolved to march
through the darke, wherein I had enough
to doe to keepe my way: and having ſcarce
gone three ſteps, I thought to have turned
mine eyes towards Iſmena, but could neither
ſee her any more, nor know what was
become of her. Here I beleeve, there is no
courage ſo reſolute, that would not have
beene moved; for I found my ſelfe environed
with the moſt horrible Monſters that
can be imagined, and ſuch as ſeemed to have
beene created in ſo generall a confuſion, that
neither the kinds, or ſexes were diſcernable.
There is not that thing in Africa ſo prodigious,
but was there preſented: the Hydra's,
Gorgons, and ſuch infinite ſorts of Chymaera's
appeared to me, that I ſhould have had much
trouble in my reſolution, and no ſmall cauſe
to feare a Metamorphoſis of my ſelfe by the
horrible aſpect of their ſhapes, if the remembrance
of Iſmena's words to me, had not
made mee repoſe more truſt to mine eares

                  
                  
than mine eyes. If I looked backe, I ſaw my
ſelfe purſued with an infinite number of wild
beaſts, ready to aſſaile and devoure me▪ and
what endeavour or invention ſoever I uſed to
eſcape their purſuit, or ſhun their encounter,
I could make none other haſte, than if
I had had Fetters on mine ankles, or that
my feete had beene faſtened by ſome charme.
On the other ſide, I ſaw great numbers of
Centaures continually croſſing my way, ſeeking
inceſſantly ſome loſt thing which they
could not finde. Anon I ſaw Harpyes flying
and devouring on all ſides, not ſparing to
exact tribute even from the dead carkaſſes:
then againe I found my ſelfe amidſt a deformed
people, and a ſtrange kinde of men,
vaine; fantaſtick; and mutable; who had
more than a thouſand aſſemblies about nothing,
ſome where of were crippled, crooked,
and miſhapen, others hunger-ſtarved
and feeble, and very few rightly ſhapen. But
as their features were vaine and miſerable,
their exerciſes were farre more extravagant;
ſome of them buſied themſelves in erecting
ill compoſed edifices upon in the ruines of their
fellows: others, amongſt the ſad Reliques of
a devouring fire, turned all things topſieturvy
to ſeeke treaſure, but found nothing

but burning coales: and ſome ſold ſmoake,
and others trafficked with the fruits of Tantalus
Garden, which howſoever they ſeemed
to me of no uſe, were nevertheleſſe bought
up at very deare rates.
               By this time I began to diſcover the Skie
cleare up a little towards the Eaſt, and foretell
the riſing of Aurora from one end of the
Earth to the other, when as all thoſe other
objects began to become more rare, leſſe viſible,
and at length wholly vaniſhed; or at
leaſt the Sylla's and Meduſa's were converted
into Rocks and Trees, and the Serpents into
broken Reeds. Immediately I deſcryed a
great Forreſt, which ſeemed to rejoyce at
the approach of the day, and in the ſhade
whereof I was well advanced, before the Sun
had diſplayed his beames: Since, ſayes Pyzander,
that was the day, wherein thou wert to
have the honour of ſeeing Diana, it would
have beene too much to behold two ſuch
great lights in one day. The hope of this inter-view,
ſayes Endymion, did extraordinarily
move me, and the uncertainty of what
might befall me, poſſeſſed me ſometimes with
one thought, ſometimes with another, becauſe
I neither knew the time nor place
wherein this good fortune was alotted me.

In the meane while I obſerved the growth &amp;
height of the Trees, and the large extent of
their branches, which repreſented ſo great an
antiquity, as that they ſeemed to have beene
borne with the World. Oh immortall
Nymphs ſaid I to my ſelfe, (for the place
was ſo ſhady and ſilent, that me thought I
was not free to open my mouth, ſo much as
to utter a ſigh:) Oh Hamadryades! how many
long-lived Harts and Crowes have had
leaſure to live and die, and how often hath
the Phoenix renewed her ſelfe ſince your
birth! Thus I continued walking a long
time, when inſtead of finding an increaſe of
light, I ſeemed to remaine wholly betwixt
the Night and the Day, and even to follow
darkneſſe, yea, move with it, ſo much did
the miſts grow thicker and thicker to my
ſight. Silence and ſolitude brought with
them a ſecret kind of horrour and affright,
which no leſſe aſtoniſhed me, than the Monſters
I had ſeene before: Beſides, all this time
I had gained ſo little on my way, that I knew
it no more; and the more I went forward,
the more was I touched with a certaine reſpect
of the places, which made me imagine,
that now, having loſt the ſight of humane
foot-ſteps, I was not farre from the reſidence

of the gods. And indeed, lifting up
my head I perceived a Table, fixed on a Tree,
which for bulke and taleneſſe exceeded the
reſt, wherein was this in Inſcription in Capitall
Letters.
               Stay not long in this place, Mortalls,
except you meane ſuddainly
to ſuffer the puniſhment of your temerity.
               I had ſcarce read theſe words, when I felt
the Earth ſhake and tremble in ſuch a manner
under my feete, that the toppes of the
Trees were mooved therewithall. Theſe
accidents indeed had power to ſtay me,
but not ſo eaſily to divert my courſe▪
for, I being already ſo accuſtomed to
Prodigies and Monſters, would have beene
loath to flye before the gods themſelves.
What couldſt thou thinke to doe, ſaies Pyzander,
ſince thou knoweſt there is neither
valour, or force in man, but muſt preſently
give way to the threatnings of the gods?
And whoſoever would be ſo raſh, as to make
them the leaſt reſiſtance, would onely ſhew

the exceſſe of his deſperate reſolution to his
owne ruine. There was one ſole conſideration
Pyzander, ſayes Endymion, which made
me reſolve to retire thence, which was an unfortunate
cuſtome I have (by ſome ſecret
Fate) never to enjoy, any more than the appearances,
beginnings, promiſes, and hopes
of any great felicity. Inſomuch, that I had a
kinde of feare, that Heaven (already tyred
with ſhewing grace to me) would in ſtead
of Diana, whom I ſought, have expoſed me
to the encounter of Hecatea, whoſe preſence
alone either rendreth men aſtoniſhed, or,
turning them into ſtones, deprives them
wholly of ſence. And indeed I preſently
heard a horrible noyſe, like unto the howling
of Dogges in the darke, mingled with
the roaring of Lyons, the hiſſing of Snakes,
or ſome other more ſtrange ſound, which
cannot be repreſented by the example of any
voyce. This encreaſed more and more, advancing
like the winde, which riſing, murmures,
and ruffles amongſt the Trees, and
Woods, which oppoſe the courſe, or retard
the violence of it; or as the raine and
tempeſt, who have alwaies ſome noiſe going
before them, ſeeming to advertiſe us,
and give us time to take ſome ſhelter, before

they diſſolve upon our heads. With
this, I beganne more and more to adde feare
to obſervation; my face grew pale, my haire
ſtared, and I became wholly ſeized with horrour
and affright. I was conſtrained to leave
the place, and even to ſeeke pathes where
there were none. I knew not which way
to turne me, but wandring thus up and
downe the Forreſt, I began to diſpaire of
my fortune, and repent me of mine enterprize.
But when as we, poore Mortalls, are
are reduced to ſuch exigents, that wee can
doe no more, when our wits and counſailes
faile us, and our beſt wiſedome and judgement
becomming blind, remaines in confuſion;
then I ſay it is, that the gods appeare, and
witneſſe themſelves both powerfull, and favourable
to thoſe that implore their aſſiſtance,
and commit them wholly to their protection.
And ſo it fared with me; for that
which whilome ſeemed to me an ominous
encounter, proved now a meane to conduct
me to that which I deſired to finde. But it
is a common errour amongſt men, to
place the meanes which brings them to happineſſe,
in the ranke of diſaſters and miſfortunes.
For I had not gone farre, when
I perceived before me a certaine ſhining

light, whoſe ſilver beames made as it were
another day, and expelling the Clouldy miſts
on every ſide, made, for a good diſtance,
round about the ſhades leſſe obſcure. Immediately
hereupon I ſaw a Creſſant appeare
farre clearer than the Starres, and to whom,
next the Sunne, the greateſt honour is due.
With which Object mine eyes were preſently
dazeled, and my heart ſo moved with a continuall
panting, that I could hardly ſettle it.
At length, having recollected the powers of
my ſight, I perceived it was Diana, who,
as I thought, had her eyes fixed upon me,
before I ſaw her; becauſe, the feare I had
contracted, permitted me not ſo much to
looke on what was before me, as to thinke
on what might follow me. I ſtopping ſuddainly,
found my ſoule wholly poſſeſſed
with joy, reſpect, and feare. But obſerving
her lookes, no leſſe mild now, than at other
times, I tooke the boldneſſe, yet with ſecreſie
and ſilence, to advance ſome ſteppes,
the better to diſcerne the places and perſons,
becauſe the branches and leaves hid the
whole Company from my ſight, and in part
the goddeſſe her ſelfe.
               Then I perceived her ſitting upon a Rock,
which nature for her ſervice had raiſed to the

                  
                     G pas in
                  
                  
height of a ſeat; from whence there iſſued
a murmuring Fountaine, and about it ſate
her Nymphes upon little greene Turffes,
ſome of them leaning their heads upon
their hands, and their Elbowes upon their
knees, ſeemed to ſleepe, or to be much tranſported
with the pleaſant warbling of the
gliding Spring; and others leaning over it,
beheld their faces in the Water: and ſome others,
whom I could not perfectly ſee, had
laid themſelves downe here and there upon
the graſſe. But I, not diverting my
ſelfe much with conſidering the particularities
of the place, kept mine eyes alwaies fixed
upon Diana, who had hers alſo upon
me. And doubtleſſe, Pyzander, if it bee
true, that the eyes are the faithfull witneſſes
of the ſoule, ſhe had ſome intention to ſpeake
to me: But that a Nymph, who was next to
her, and who before had beene writing upon
the Rocke with the poynt of her Arrow,
lifting up her head, diſcovered me, and
being therewith ſuddainly moved, ſhe turned
towards Diana, ſaying; oh goddeſſe!
what is hee that thus audaciouſly beholds
thee with impunity? What priviledge hath
he to be in this place, and preſent himſelfe
before thee? Surely there is no want

on his part (having preſumptuouſly taken
this liberty) that he is not already received
into our company, and made partaker
of all our actions and ſecrets. Herewith
taking her Bow, and fitting that Arrow to
it, wherewithall ſhe had formerly written:
Give me leave, ſaid ſhe, with one blow to
take downe the man, and abate his preſumption.
No, no, anſwers Diana ſmiling, if he
dye, he muſt dye by my hand. So calling to
a Nymph that ſtood behind her: (and from
whence, as I will tell thee hereafter, I had
knowledge of all paſſages) Bring me hither,
ſaies ſhee, whiſpering to her, the two little
Quivers of Arrowes which Cupid gave us the
other day, as we paſſed by the Forreſt of Idalia.
The Nymph ſtooping onely to take them
up, gave them her immediately. And then
Diana (oh cruell deliverance! oh meane of
ſaving, worſe than the very intention of deſtroying
me!) unbinding them firſt, ſhot
one, then another at me, without taking
much paines about it: for they are Arrowes
which doe almoſt flye of themſelves, and
ſeldome miſſe the marke, whereunto the will
of the ſender directs them, eſpecially being
ſent from the hand of Diana. Sometimes
they eſcape unawares, and yet effect no leſſe

execution, than if they were ſent on purpoſe,
or accompanyed with a deſigne. Theſe
Nymphes doe alſo very often uſe them both
treacherouſly and maliciouſly, taking pleaſure
in inflicting that on others, which they
themſelves will never have either compaſſion
or ſence of. I perceiving that Diana
perſiſted in wounding me with them all one
after another, cryed out (but ſo as ſhe heard
me not) Alas, goddeſſe! what wilt thou doe?
Doſt thou know the power of theſe Darts?
peradventure thou ſcattereſt them negligently,
becauſe they ſeeme weake and light
unto thee. Was it not enough for thee to
have with one or two onely, wounded my
my heart, already wholly accuſtomed to the
ſence of thy Shafts, but that thou muſt cover
me with them from head to foot? I ſtood
firme, Pyzander, in this ſuffering whilſt I was
able; but at length when ſhee had ſo filled
mine eyes therewith, that I was wholly blinded,
I felt ſo ſtrong a poyſon ſlide into my
veines, that by degrees, loſing the uſe of my
ſtrength, I fell flat downe at the foote of the
Tree, where I ſuffered a continuall Death,
and yet ſaw no end of my life, as if life and
death had ſeemed to be in diſpute, which
of them had greateſt intereſt in me, wherein

my extreame torment perſwaded me every
moment, that Death would get the upper
hand: ſo that loſing the hope of ever ſpeaking
to Diana againe, I caſt forth my Lamentations
to the hazard of being tranſported
to her eares.
               Oh it is the onely deſire of ſeeing thee, Goddeſſe,
which hath made me expoſe my life to
all the perills of Heaven and Earth, to come
and receive my death at thy hands! and have
beene ſpared by ſo many Monſters, to be reſerved
onely to thy rigours! Who could ever
have thought that of all the dangers
which threatned me, thine Encounter had
beene moſt terrible? What crime have I committed,
that can deſerve the puniſhment of ſo
ſuddaine a change, that it ſeemes to me thou
conſulteſt hatred and affection, to know
which of them thou ſhouldeſt practiſe towards
me? How canſt thou accord the quality
of a Goddeſſe with thine irreſolution and
inconſtancy? howbeit indeed thou be but
too too conſtant in making me feele the
ſmart of the darts which flye from thine eyes
and hands, wherewith thou haſt ſo wholly
covered me, that my wound is generall, no
roome being left about me to receive one
ſtroake more, except thou wilt make other

wounds within theſe I have already. I requeſt
this onely comfort of thee, that dying
by thy hand, I may at leaſt have the freedome
to tell thee ſo; and that if thou takeſt pleaſure
in my torment, thou wilt vouchſafe audience
to my lamentation, which will witneſſe
unto thee the violence thereof, or at
leaſt ſhew that thou art really a Goddeſſe, and
that thou readeſt in my heart that which my
mouth might in vaine labour to give thee information
of.
               In this wavering eſtate of my good or ill
fortune, Pyzander, wherein the Fates themſelves
ſeemed to be in doubt how to diſpoſe
of me, I eſteemed my ſelfe infinitely happy
by having ſeene Diana, and ſuffered none other
torment than what her hand had inflicted.
And although my felicities were accompanied
with my complaints, yet the cauſe
rendred them ſo delightfull and honourable
to me, that whoſoever could not lament in
the ſame faſhion, ſeemed to me to deſerve
bewayling or contempt: For as on the one
ſide I experimented the whole force of ſorrow,
ſo on the other I enjoyed the contentments
of a felicity not communicated to other
Mortalls, but at ſuch time as ſome one
of the gods intending to raviſh them with honour

and delight, vouchſafes them his ſight
and preſence. And indeed, as if in the midſt
of my moſt violent paſſion, ſome Deity had
approached me, to drive death away, and defend
me againſt it, or as if the ſame hand,
that had injured me, had alſo cured me; I
felt a delightfull Aire, a pleaſing winde, and
a ſweet breath, ſuch as ſeemed to iſſue from
ſome Divine mouth, with ſome other pleaſures,
(which cannot bee expreſſed but by
ſighing) wherein there was a mixture of
ſweet and bitter, ſo excellently tempered,
that the ſower ſerved onely as a neceſſary ingredient
to ſet the ſweet the better off Remaining
in this extaſie, wherein the pleaſures
I found amidſt my ſorrows had caſt me, I
heard a Nymph, who calling aloud for her
Dogge, cryed ſundry times, Licanthe, Licanthe;
and at length ſeeking round about, drew
neare to me; and having awhile beheld me,
called to me, ſaying, Sleepeſt thou? or what
doeſt thou there? doth any thing ayle thee? I
could at firſt, anſwer her only with a ſigh: but
ſhe continuing, ſaid, Speake to me I pray thee,
and tell me thy griefe: Alas I ſaid I, how canſt
thou aſk what I ſuffer, ſeeing me wholly ſtuck
full of arrows? how! full of arrows? ſayes ſhe,
what doſt thou meane? Doſt thou rave? Open

thine eies, looke on me, or indeed, looke rather
upon thy ſelfe: how can I open mine eies,
anſwered I, having more wounds there than
in any other part? Yes for ſooth ſaid ſhe, and
ſo ſtooping opened mine eye-lids with her
fingers, ſaying, See, are they not very ſore?
Wherewith I, (but not without great aſtoniſhment)
beheld the light againe, whereof
I before thought I had bin for ever deprived.
Then ſhe, taking me by the hand, I
endeavoured to riſe, and remaining ſo awhile,
I caſt mine eies towards the place
where Diana was, but I neither ſaw her, nor
any of her traine, ſaving the Nymph that
was with me.
               A little after, beginning to view my ſelfe
ſomewhat better, I neither ſaw the Arrows,
nor the wounds whereof before I had ſo
much complained; yet my heart ſtill feeling
their violence, kept a continuall ſighing. Being
about to riſe, I was going to ſay, what
have I done oh ye gods! to deſerve to be a
But unto all Diana's ſhafts? But the Nymph
interrupted me, ſaying, Doeſt thou thus acknowledge
the grace ſhe hath done thee in
ſaving thy life? for thou hadſt bin expoſed to
the mercy of the moſt rigorous Nymphs, and
greateſt enemies in the World to men, and

ſuch as never ſuffer any that comes prying about
theſe Deſarts and Fountaines, to ſcape
without the puniſhment of their curioſity.
Then I intreated her to recount unto me
what had paſſed concerning me, which ſhe
performed, according as I have already in
part related to thee: but it is no new thing
ſayes ſhe, to ſee the Goddeſſe ſo ready to gratifie
thee. What thinkeſt thou ſhe ſpake the
other day of thee in the Aſſembly of the Nayades
and Nereides, about the Mouth of Meander,
betwixt Milet and Priene? when ſpeaking
alone to us, who are about her by particular
ſervice, ſhe ſaid, Behold Endymions
Countrie, it is now a good while ſince I ſaw
him: informe your ſelves to day of the
Nymphs of theſe places, and of himſelfe, if
it be poſſible, where his uſuall reſidence is,
what ſtudy moſt poſſeſſeth him, and what
we may doe for his contentment. If perchance
he preſent himſelfe where we are in
our moſt ſolitary walkes, and where men
doe leaſt of all frequent, hinder him not
from ſeeing me, uſe him favourably, and
let not your ordinary auſterity deny him admittance.
And in truth ſaid the Nymph,
there is not any one of the Dryades, Nap
                        •
                     ae,
or Oreades, but knows thy Name, though

not thy perſon, and that have not learned it
from the great eſteeme which Diana hath
thee in: who talkes of thee both to the Silvans
and Fawnes, and conceales not her reſpect
of thee from the celeſtiall Deities. Faire
Nymph ſaid I, by what I now obſerve, it
ſeemes thou knoweſt that the Goddeſſe hath
alwaies graced me with her particular goodwill.
O yes, ſaid ſhe, I know it very well:
thinke it not ſtrange then, ſaid I, if from the
ſame ſubject which ſo highly delights me, I
draw alſo the cauſe of all my lamentations.
For how can that conſiſt, that ſhee ſo long
wiſheth me the good, which ſhe never does
me? What know I but that ſome humour
contrary in it ſelfe, oppoſing her intention,
uncertaine of what ſhe hath to doe, and tedious
in reſolving, may at length wholly
deprive me of that which ſhe continually deferres;
and that time, which like her ſelfe attereth
every thing, may adminiſter ſo many
diverſions unto her, that all this affection
vaniſhing, ſhe at length may her ſelfe forget
that ever ſhe thought of it, and then in vaine
will it be for me to accuſe the gods of mutability,
and breach of promiſe as well as men.
Thinke not ſo ill, ſayes the Nymph, but conſider
that the gods themſelves are led by Fate,

and muſt give way to neceſſity. Know, that
ſhe her ſelfe takes not the repoſe and
eaſe ſhe gives to the World. How doſt
thou thinke ſhe can give ſatisfaction, I
will not ſay to ſo many perſons, but
to ſo many different peoples, who deſire her
favour and preſence? One while Scythia requires
her, then Greece, and anon Ethiopia.
But what doe I ſay? the whole world adores;
what Countrey is viſited with the
Sunne but knowes Diana, and her fame?
and if thus ſhe muſt be every where, how can
ſhe remaine long in one place? And yet notwithſtanding
all thoſe great cares of the
moſt weighty affaires of the world, thou
haſt an exceeding great ſhare of her thoughts,
and the merit of her words. Beſides, ſhe
hath this day charged me, by a moſt ſpeciall
command, to aſſure thee, that ſhe often
thinkes particularly on thee, and that the
opportunity of witneſſing it will bee exceeding
gratefull to her: if this ſuffice thee not,
and if thou haſt ought to ſay to her, be to
morrow at high noone in the Valley of
Pines, neare the next mountaine, where ſo
ſoone as I ſhall ſee thee, I will draw her
alone from the reſt of her Nymphes, aſſuring
my ſelfe ſhe will afford thee all the liberty of

ſpeech, thou canſt in juſtice deſire of a goddeſſe.
O faire Nympth, ſaid I, thou doſt
ſo much obliege me, that thon rendreſt my
life eternally ſubject: But give me leave to
tell thee that which thou knoweſt better
than I; that is, that the difference and inequality
betwixt us and the gods is ſo great, that
we are ſo farre from being able to looke
on them, or deſire them, without rendring
our ſelves ridiculous, that wee cannot ſo
much as love them, except they firſt affect us.
But againe, whenſoever they prevent us,
then is it our part to follow them with all
care and diligence, and thus doe I deſire
the honour of ſpeaking with Diana, having
nothing to ſay to her, but onely in purſuit of
what ſhe hath beene formerly pleaſed to gratifie
me withall, having beene oftentimes
deſirous to ſpeak with me, without any other
motion or ſolicitation, ſave onely that
of her owne inclination and good will. If
Miſchance could have plaid me that injurious
pranke, as to make time able to remove
that deſire of hers, then with good reaſon
ſhould reſpect have taken me off from ſuch
preſumption, and confined me to everlaſting
ſilence. O how happy were I, if any ſuch
propitious deſire poſſeſſed her, whereof I will

endeavour to give her to morrow the opportunity,
according to the advice thou giveſt
me. Well, ſaid ſhe, it is thy part to thinke
on it; time calls me away, farewell: So, ſhewing
me the way I was to goe, ſhe gave me
from her hand a taſte of ſuch delightfull felicities,
as that I asked her whether ſhe intended
them to end my ſorrowes, or to prolong
them into a further continuance, and
render me immortall with them; whereunto
perceiving that ſhe anſwered me onely
with a ſmile; as ſhe withdrew her ſelfe, I
bade her farewell, ſaying, Adieu thou the
moſt courteous and diſcreete of all the
Nymphes, I cannot wiſh thee any greater
happineſſe, than the continuance of that
which thou already poſſeſſeſt, of being ſo
neare to Diana. Thus went I on, revolving
in my thoughts a thouſand times all that had
befalne me, ſometimes praiſing, and ſometimes
even daring to accuſe Diana, ſince it being
ſo eaſiy to her to make me happier, ſhe ſtil
kept me in doubt and diſquiet. In the mean
time I being growne weary, and finding the
day beginne to encreaſe, and the way to haſten
towards an end, I beganne to find the
tracing of mens foote-ſteps, which made me
imagine, by the appearance, that I was not

expoſed to any more danger. At laſt I ended
my dayes work with the Sunne, who
was no ſooner at the end of his Carriere, than
I was at the end of the Forreſt; where ſeeing
nothing but Mountaines, and ſeeing no
better retreat than the Forreſt it ſelfe, having
choſen a convenient place, I laid me
downe at the foote of a Mirtle, the Moſſe
being there ſomewhat ſoften than elſe where,
as if Fortune had conducted me to the place
where Nature had long before prepared a
Bed for my repoſe.
               The end of the Second Booke.
            
            
               
               ENDYMION.
               The Third Booke.
               
                  NO ſooner had night and ſilence
impoſed a dumbe tranquility on
all Creatures, when I began to
feele that ſlumber diſdaines not
plaine and ſimple lodgings; but (as the Proverbe
ſaies) is more frequent in the Cottages
of ſilly Shepheards, than in the Palaces
of great Princes, amidſt their golds and
ſilke, as if ſhe were not well pleaſed that, that
which the gods have ſo freely beſtowed on
Mortalls, ſhould be made a Merchandiſe of

ſo deare a rate. So I tooke my firſt ſleepe,
which was ſhort and quiet: but in my ſecond
I was much troubled with Dreames:
One while me-thought I went up and down
ſeeking Diana, with a great deale of toyle, but
could not finde her; another while methought
I had many buſineſſes, and much to
doe with men whom I knew not: And as it
is uſuall to thoſe who ſleepe upon any great
deſigne, or feare, to awake with the leaſt difficulty,
and even in their very ſleepe to ſtand
upon their Guards: So I, with much longing
waited for day, and troubled my reſt
with a thouſand diſquiets. When as, about
the time of Aurora's approaching, methought
I ſaw Aurora her ſelfe approaching
me, or at leaſt a beauty that had her Treſſes,
her colour, and her eyes, and which was ſo
gorgeouſly attired, as if Art had contended
with Nature for the prize, and beene yet ſurpaſſed;
and ſo accoutred, as if ſhe had beene
that day to be marryed to ſome one of the
gods, or of the moſt eminent of men: her
Robe was white, embroydered all over
with Flowers, which of all ſides ſeemed to
fall from her head and boſome; her Girdle
was of gold, wrought in the faſhion of Bees
upon Flowers, whoſe leaves were of Emeralds;

                  
                     G. par in
                  
                  
in her right hand ſhe had a Knife,
wherewith ſhe would faine have cut a branch
of that ſame Myrtle Tree, at the foot whereof
I ſlept; but not being able to reach ſo
high, ſhe was forced to have recourſe to me,
ſo, beholding me with a looke, of it ſelfe able
to informe one of her deſire, if it could have
uttered it, ſhe ſaies to me; I roſe this morning
a good while before the Sunne, being
appoyted very ſhortly to aſſiſt at a Sacrifice,
where I ſhall have uſe of a Branch of this
Myrtle, and finde none that offers it me, except
I put my ſelfe to the trouble of requeſting
it. As for thee, whom peradventure
the gods have ſent to eaſe me of this travaile;
I pray thee grant me this, which ſcarce any
man would deny me, and in acknowledgement
of that good office, I will give to thee alone
that heart, and that affection which ſo
many have deſired, but never yet any could
obtaine: wherein I dare ſay the recompence
will farre ſurpaſſe the paines, and that thou
ſhouldeſt never deſire any other, if thou art
by Nature or Nation courteous, than the favour
I doe thee in requeſting this at thy
hands: this ſhe thought was enough to ſay
on that ſubject, and had there ſtayed, ſeeing
me ready inſtantly to obey her; but as I remained

immoveable, and tyred with ſtriving
againſt the charme which held me ſo
faſt, ſhe thought I was inſenſible, and began
to adde other perſwaſions to the former:
How dull-ſighted ſoever thou art, ſayd
ſhe, that which thou ſeeſt in me, doth ſo
ſufficiently repreſent unto thee what I am,
that thou canſt not with diſcretion engage
me to tell it thee, much leſſe, make any farther
inquiry of the reaſon or cauſe of this my
requeſt; yet to take from thee all ſubject of
doubt or excuſe, I will make no ſcruple to
declare unto thee both the one and the other.
Know therefore, for thy further information,
(if herein it bee more proper to follow
the generall opinion concerning my ſelfe
than mine owne) that I am held the patterne
and honour of all the Damoſells in thoſe
parts, and as one whoſe vertue and beautie
like a Goddeſſe amongſt Mortalls, ſuffers neither
compariſon, or envy, ſued unto, and
in vaine ſollicited by the whole flower of
the Youth hereabouts, and ſuch as at the
leaſt ſigne I ſhould give them of what I deſire,
would not onely ſeeke it throughout
this Forreſt, but throughout the World;
and I cannot thinke thee inferiour to them
in courteſie or affection if the object deſerve

it. Howſoever, although thine owne inclination
ſhould not move thee to oblige me, I
am of opinion thy Fate would compell thee
to it; and though thou wouldeſt doe that for
a great Goddeſſe, which thou wouldeſt not
doe for me, yet I know not whether it be of
thee or no, that our Oracles ſpeake ſo much,
where they ſay, that a little branch of Myrtle
ſhall be a cauſe of the greateſt and moſt famous
Sacrifice that ever we have made to Diana;
and that ſhee then is to deſcend from
Heaven in favour of, and for the ſake of him
that cut it, and that in the meane time I ſhall
weare it in my boſome for thy ſake; where
if it beare no fruit, it ſhall at leaſt flouriſh,
untill we goe both together to the high Altar,
where I am to ſacrifice my heart to thee,
and thou thine to Diana. At theſe words I
ſtarted up, ready to ſerve her in all her deſires;
but ſhe commanded me to ſtay a while,
and forbeare ſtirring, till ſhee had withdrawne
her ſelfe a little apart; for the day begins
to advance, and if by chance I were diſcovered
by any of the Keepers of this Forreſt,
alone with thee, they might, not knowing
mine intention, impute it for a crime to
me, and the time would adde ſomething to
the ſiniſter opinion that might be thence conceived.

As for thee, as ſoone as thou haſt cut
down the branch, retire aſide, that I may have
time to come &amp; take it. With theſe laſt words,
ſhe with-drew her ſelfe, and I wholly raviſhed
with this Viſion, could not ſuffer the
loſſe of it, but with much griefe; ſo in an inſtant
I roſe and looked about me, to ſee what
was become of her: but perceiving her no
more, and for her ſake forgetting all other
things, I turned towards the Tree, which
was ſo tall a Myrtle, that I could not ſo much
as touch any Branch of it with the point of
my Sword, ſave onely one little one which
was lower than all the reſt, with ſtriving to
get it, I ſtrook the body of the Tree thrice,
whoſe tough Barke thrice turned the edge of
my Weapon; the Forreſt reſounded of it, and
Eccho diſtributed the noiſe into all parts. At
length I cut the fatall ſprigge, and laying it
at my feet, I uttered theſe words to the beautie
I had ſeene: Whether thou be a Goddeſſe
or Mortall, behold, what I owe to thy
requeſt, wherein I deſire thee rather to conſider
the ready and prompt obedience I have
rendred thee, than the thing it ſelfe which
thou requiredſt. I had ſcarce uttered theſe
words, when I perceived three or foure men
come running towards me, armed with Darts

and Axes, according to the faſhion of the
Countrie; and how unequall ſoever the
match was, yet I reſolved in ſtead of yeelding,
to ſell deare either my life or liberty:
I, with ſo much reſolution and quickneſſe, put
my ſelfe in poſture to charge them, that they
began to be affraid of me: but when I had
ſcattered them here and there, others came
(ſuch was my misfortune) from every corner
of the Forreſt, ſo that I finding all meanes
of ſafety within the Wood taken away, was
forced to ſeeke it without: But ere I had
gone farre, I diſcovered Huntſmen, who
ſeeing me alone purſued of ſo many, run after
me with full ſpeed, crying aloud, what
hath he done? whereof is he guilty? It is a
barbarous fellow ſaid the other, (wholly out
of breath) who hath wronged us all, and
violated the Lawes, and honour of theſe
places, to the great contempt of our gods
and Altars.
               At theſe words they preſently preſſed to
ſtay me, but Fortune at firſt ſo favoured
my reſolution and courage, that the firſt that
approached me, ſoone repented his diligence;
for I ſtruck his Horſe ſo rude a ſtroke
on the head with an Axe that I had gotten
from the other, that the Weapon remained

ſo faſt behind his eare, that I could not get it
out againe; and beſides, he riſing an end, fell
backward with the man under him ſo violently,
that hee that next followed him,
ſtumbling thereat, caſt his Rider at my feet,
to the mercy of mine Armes; but turning me
with my Sword in my hand, to looke to that
which more concerned me, and finding my
ſelfe equally environed with horſes and men,
I reſolved upon a deſperate attempt as my laſt
refuge, and ſo laying about me on all ſides
with more vehemence▪ and promptitude
than theſe words can deliver it to thee, which
way ſoever I turned my ſelfe, I ſo aſtoniſhed
mine enemies, that I began to finde my ſelfe
in a manner without reſiſtance; and had
doubtleſſe made them leave the place, and
freed my ſelfe at laſt, from one and other
of them, if amidſt the violence, wherewith
I made their Weapons flye in ſplinters, if
mine owne Sword alſo had not broken at the
hilts, which gave the courage to a young
man who firſt perceived it, to ſpurre his
Horſe ſo rudely upon me, that mine indignation,
ſeeing my ſelfe thus affronted, tooke
from me the conſideration of his youth and
extreame beautie, which were of force to
have moved the moſt barbarous to uſe him

with more mildneſſe: and ſo, not being able
to containe my ſelfe, I threw that piece of
my Sword which remained in my hand, the
pummell whereof hit him (harder than I my
ſelfe deſired) upon the bottome of the ſtomacke,
the paine whereof made him ſuddenly
open his knees, and fall to the ground
as if hee had beene dead. I made haſte towards
him to get his Weapons, but the others,
who loſt no time, failed not to ſeize
on me; and yet in ſuch wiſe, that they durſt
not offer me any violence: and when they
had taken me, they ſtill continued ſo affraid
of me, as if indeed they had beene my priſoners,
and not I theirs. Some complained
of their armes, ſome of their thighes, and
others ſhewed the wounds they had received
in other parts. But when they perceived this
faire young man trembling and waxing pale,
as if he had beene about to give up the ghoſt,
they forget all their owne paine through
their ſenſe of his; and then diſpaire and rage
beginning to ſeize them, I every moment
expected that they would have revenged his
death on me, before it happened to him. I
was inwardly exceeding ſorry to have imployed
my hands towards the deſtruction of
ſuch a Maſter-peece of Nature, and was now

no leſſe ſorry than before I was angry, for the
lineaments of his face, had now no other
motion, than ſuch as were able to ſtirre pitty
in the moſt obdurate minds. The Roſes
onely hid themſelves under the Lillies, which
a tender modeſty, upon the leaſt occaſion
was wont to cover with the Roſes: and his
golden Treſſes, thick, and naturally curled,
had ſo faire a luſtre, that they ſeemed even
to diſpute with the Sunne it ſelfe, inſomuch
that it might have bin ſaid, that Death delayed,
and made ſcruple to ſeize on him, becauſe
ſo much beauty and cleare luſtre could
not agree with the horrours of her obſcurity.
At length he began by little and little to come
to himſelfe, and open his faire eyes, whereat
all the Company, and even thoſe whom I
had worſt treated, were no leſſe rejoyced,
than if he had healed them of their wounds
and hurts.
               Their next care was to informe themſelves
of me, and of mine offence, and to bring
me backe to the place where they found me,
where indeed I could not ſee the branch I had
out, but the place of it was all covered with
blood, which iſſued from the Myrtle in great
abundance. Then they cryed out to me, O
thou ſacrilegious wretch, who brought thee

into this Countrie? or what haſt thou to doe
amongſt us, thus to draw hither the wrath
and vengeance of the gods, and ſpecially
that of the Goddeſſe, our Protectreſſe? what
Euphrates or Thetis will ever ſuffice to waſh
away thy crime? Preſently upon this we perceived
the boughs begin to tremble, and
from the curled top we heard a dolefull voice
mixed with ſuch ſighs and ſobs, as moved us
to compaſſion and ſorrow, which in a confuſed
and ill-pronounced tone, pronounced
this lamentation under the Barke: O wretched
man! thou that diſturbeſt the repoſe of
the ſoules, whoſe new being ſhould free
them for ever from humane paſſions, or the
injuries of Fortune; was there any ſuffering
behind, which I endured not in my life, but
was reſerved for me to receive at thy hands?
Know therefore, that both thy paines and
thine errours are vaine, and thou doeſt herein
onely abuſe hope, and reſiſt the decrees of
Heaven. Whoſoever hath at any time obſerved
a poore Priſoner, pale and confounded
with the apprehenſions of the fatall Sentence
of his Death, may gheſſe the eſtate
whereinto this prodigious Spectacle had reduced
me: as well, in regard theſe words deprived
me of all hope, of the contentment I

ſo long, and with ſo much paine and ſuffering
had ſought, as for that I was in the hands
and mercy of theſe Barbarians.
               This puts me in minde of the Dodonean
Forreſt, ſayes Pyzander, the ſo famous reſidence
of the Oracle of Jupiter Chaonian,
where the Trees give anſwer: Indeed, anſwers
Endymion, it was alſo in my thought,
and I ſeemed amongſt the South-ſaying
Oakes, eſteeming my Diſaſter no leſſe aſſured
than if the Doves of Chaonia had uttered
it. But this is not all Pyzander; for as
they were doubtfully muttering amongſt
themſelves, ſometimes ſaying it was the
voice and ghoſt of the laſt deceaſed Prieſt, another
while, that it was one of Diana's
Nymphs; Heaven permitted them, for clearing
their doubts, and putting them out of
trouble, to heare theſe words: What gods
and men have thus wronged Diophania, who
under this tough Barke, and the protection
of ſo great a Goddeſſe, is yet thus expoſed
to their violence and out-rage. This was
all we could comprehend of her Lamentation,
for here voice failing by degrees turned
it ſelfe into an uncouth mourning, and at
length inſenſibly vaniſhed.
               At the name of Diophania they were all aſtoniſhed,

and looking long one upon another,
they at length began to ſay, Alas!
ſhould this be the Diophania whom we have
lately loſt, and whom her Father ſeekes
throughout all the world. Whereat one yong
man teſtifyed himſelfe more moved at this
Name than all the others, and caſting himſelfe
at the foote of the Tree, embraced it,
and thus powred forth his griefe and heavineſſe
in theſe words: It is I Diophania, it is I
who have really loſt thee, and to whom no
earthly thing can adminiſter comfort: it is I
that have ſought thee in all places, till diſpairing
of finding thee, I have onely hoped
for death, to put an end to my diſpaire and
miſery: And thou without pitty either of my
errours or travailes, hideſt thy ſelfe in this
new ſhape under this Barke, leaving me to
the mercy of horrours and affrights, which
for thy ſake have continually dwelt in my
dreames and thoughts. One while I have imagined
that thine unaparalell'd beauty had
incited either ſome god or man to raviſh
thee, and carrie thee hence, and ſometimes
that ſome Monſter had devoured thee, there
is no danger that can bee incurred by Sea or
Land, but I feared had ſeized thee. O Diophania,
to what hath my love, and thy Fathers

                  
                     Le. Gaultier incidit.
                  
                  
rigour reduced thee? and what can I expect
of this adventure, ſince in the ſtate I find
thee at preſent, thou art much more loſt to
me, than if death it ſelfe had deprived me of
thee: for then I, who now onely expect the
houre wherein diſpaire and my ſorrows will
eaſe mee of my weariſome life, ſhould
have had ſome hope to have found thee amongſt
the ghoſts: but now ſuch is my miſery,
that neither the dead nor living can ever
be able to comfort me. He would eternally
have continued his lamentation, if the exceſſive
ſurcharge of his ſorrow had not rendred
him awhile ſpeechleſſe. The Myrtle,
or rather Diophania, was moved with it, and
her trembling branches gave tokens of her
compaſſion: But when the others endeavoured
to get him thence, and remove him
from the foot of the Tree, which he graſped
and embraced ſo fervently, that it made me
expect another Metamorphoſis: Give me
leave ſayes hee, to end my ſorrows with my
dayes, and goe tell Myrtavia that her daughter
is found; but ſo found, as to her ſhe is no
leſſe loſt than formerly. Hereupon they inſtantly
beſought him to tell them what cauſe
he had above others, thus particularly to bewaile
Diophania: You have there with you,

ſaies he, one of her fathers principall ſlaves,
who knowes the whole ſtory, which I could
not conceale from him, after ſhe had firſt acquainted
him with it: Lentreat, ſaies the ſlave,
that I may be diſpenced withall, &amp; not here
in her preſence relate the ſtory, the remembrance
whereof would no leſſe annoy her
ſoule, than this ſtrangers Sword lately hath
injured her body; if the trunke of a tree may
be this day tearmed Diophania's body, whoſe
beauty equally raviſhed both gods and men:
come along with us, ſayes one of the chiefe,
and let us returne to the City, for wee have
this day hunted enough, having taken this
Stranger, and found Diophania. Thus perceiving
the Mirtle ſtirre no more, nor utter any
other voice, and having uſed new perſwaſions
and attempts to draw this young man
from the Tree, who to ſatisfie them, promiſed
to follow them. One of them taking me up
behind him, carried me towards the City, and
the ſlave began thus to recite the diſcourſe of
this adventure.
               There is not any one of you but knowes
what was the beauty of Diophania, the onely
jealouſie of Stenobia the Prieſts Neece, or
what was her birth, her fortune, the cruelty,
and brutiſhneſſe of her Father, or the conſtant
and violent ſuit of Amphidamas, but

for ought I ſee you knew not of the love of
Hermodan; it was the name Pyzander of
this poore lover, who, as I have beene informed
was borne of an Amazone, having
beene in his infancy adopted by a certaine
man of inferiour quality, whoſe houſe was
neare unto that of Lycaſpis, father of Diophania:
Al theſe things have produced the ſtrange
effects, whereof I am now going to give you
account.
               You cannot but know, ſaies he, that Diophania
from her tender youth frequented
uſually the fields, amongſt her Fathers flocks,
and that by a certaine priviledge of Neighbour-hood,
Hermodan conducted his to the
ſame Paſtures, and ſo paſſing their yonger
yeares in paſtimes and exerciſes, ſutable to
that their age of Child-hood, they were ſo
accuſtomed to be together, that the one
could not live without the other. But at
length they began to grow, and Diophania's
beauty tooke an equall encreaſe with her
age and growth: and howbeit it became of
force to captivate the rudeſt courage, and
tame the moſt rebellious oppoſition, yet
ſhe no whit perceived its force, or the power
of the Charmes of it; and which Hermodan
beheld on the other ſide with ſo much

innocence, that neither, the gods, nor men, no
nor his owne Conſcience, was able to accuſe
any one of his thoughts of the leaſt
crime: And whether the continuall ſeeing
her, made her ſeeme to him leſſe rare and
wonderfull, or whether innocency it ſelfe carry
with it ſome kinde of inſenſibleneſſe, hee
had not ſo ſoone knowne ſhe was beautifull,
if he had not ſo often heard it divulged by
a generall conſent and report. But love,
without whoſe aide our ſences would remaine
in a manner uſeleſſe, and indeed
voyde of ſence, layes before him ſo many allurements,
that howbeit hee be blinde, he
quickly made the other underſtand what
uſe he was to make of his eyes, but yet not
ſo perfectly as that he knew yet what was
the force or manner of a looke that pierces
the breaſt, or was skilfull enough wittingly
to inflict on Diophania the leaſt part of the
great torment, he innocently made her ſuffer:
He contents himſelfe with the contemplation
of her, and by his eyes, from
her lookes to receive the flame which ſecretly
and unknowne to him, ſlidingly
creepes into his heart: he is ſo farre from
labouring to oppoſe the violence of an
enemy he knowes not, or from going about

to maſter that, which perchance in the beginning
was not untameable, that hee not onely
not reſiſts it, but on the contrary ſeemes
to do every thing that conduces to ſtrengthen
it: for he immediately ſuffers himſelfe
to be lead captive as a triumph to this ſecret
Conqueror, and as if hee tooke delight
in betraying himſelfe; he aſpires not
ſo much as to the glory of having made the
leaſt defence: In the meane time he takes
pleaſure in nothing but in his torment, and
what before was wont to divert and eaſe
him, becomes now too importune and afflict
him. By night he longs for the day,
whoſe light nevertheleſſe affords him no
more contentment than darkneſſe, except it
by chance ſhew him his beloved, whom
when he ſees, he is no leſſe diſtempered than
before. He knowes not what to reſolve on,
and becomes ſo much changed from what
he was, that Diophania at length perceiving
it, thinkes her ſelfe engaged by her friendſhip
to demand the cauſe of this ſo ſuddaine
alteration; which ſhe once tryed, but got no
ſatisfaction therein, in regard Hermodan,
who felt more than hee was able to expreſſe,
and who beſides, was no leſſe troubled to
diſſemble and maske his griefe, than to utter

it, would have wiſht ſhe could have underſtood
it by his eyes, or at leaſt would have
contented her ſelfe, with the beſt language
her mouth was able to produce on this
ſubject, which were his fighes: At laſt, ſhe
ſtill more and more urging him, the neceſſity
of anſwering, made him trample both upon
feare and ſhame, which endeavoured to
impoſe everlaſting ſilence upon him: Since,
ſaies he, Diophania, it is thy abſolute decree,
that I declare my griefe unto thee; if thou
chanceſt to be troubled with the knowledge
of it, remember to lay the blame thereof to
the charge of thy curioſity, and not of mine
obedience. It is thy beauty, Diophania, which
wounds all men, and which aſſuredly will kill
me, ſince the remembrance and conſideration
of thy quality and time, ſo farre different,
cauſes on my ſide a continuall diſpaire to accompany
my love.
               At the uttering of theſe words, it would
have ſeemed that Hermodan had caſhierd his
ſhamefaſtneſſe, onely thereby to encreaſe that
of Diophania, who ſo bluſhed, that he would
have beene very fortunate, if he had thereby
kindled as great a heat in her heart as her
countenance, ſhe too late repented her curioſity,
and not knowing what to doe, became

ſo out of order, that ſhe had beene loſt in this
confuſion of thoughts and actions, had ſhe
not embraced ſome pretext and light occaſion
of turning from him: O Love! thy power
produces daily ſtrange wonders, and in a
moment, at thy pleaſure changeth the face
of all things. But how doſt thou beare the
name of Love, ſince thou executeſt the office
of diſcord? Thou putteſt diviſion betwixt
two, whoſe friendſhip and lives ought
to have equall bounds, ſince their affections,
which began in their infancy hath increaſed
with their perſons. Thou interrupteſt the
freeſt actions of the World, by expoſing an
innocent Shepheard to ſo many thouſand rigorous
conſtraints and tortures: She, who
formerly with freedome of heart communicated
with him her moſt ſecret thoughts,
and received his with the ſame generall liberty,
hath now much a doe to looke upon
him: ſhee ſuſpects all her actions,
and her ſelfe too, and (ſo odious is
the name of love) the moſt indifferent diſcourſes
of her owne mouth ſeemed ſuſpect
to her: O yee gods! in theſe, rigour, diſſimulation
and ſlight are naturall to women;
Diophania is already become acquainted
with the things ſhe never learned, and without

                  
                  
conſulting any other Oracle than her
ſelfe, ſhe hath learnt Artifice enough to inflict
a thouſand torments upon him, from
whom ſhe hath never received any thing but
good offices. For one ſole fault, which nothing
but the exceſſe of affection could
make him commit, ſhe on a ſuddaine commits
to oblivion all the ſervices that ever he
hath rendred her, and the juſt acknowledgements
which ſhe owes to his former
affection: ſhe begins ſo to know her ſelfe,
that the more eſteeme men make of her, the
more ſhe contemnes them; and howſoever
the diſſemble it, ſhe becomes no leſſe proud
of her beauty, than of her condition and
birth: and as often as ſhe thinkes on Hermodans
fortune, comparatively with hers, ſhe
laughes at his raſhneſſe, and wonders at his
attempt; whilſt he daily adoring her footeſteps▪
laments and ſighes for her, and the
more he implores her grace and favour, the
more he ſeemes to provoke her diſdaine and
choller, and what petition or entreaty ſoever
he makes to her, ſe either anſwers him nothing
at all, or if by chance ſhe vouchſafe to
ſpeake, the words ſhe utters are as ſo many
ſentences of death pronounced againſt him:
He knowes not by what meanes to render

himſelfe acceptable, nor what counſell to
aſke of his perturbed reaſon; he conſults onely
his paſſion, which formes a thouſand courſes
unto him, whereof he is againe afterwards
aſhamed; his projects drive out one another,
and depend more on hazard than providence.
Sometimes he appeares before her, and is
content to try her by his ſilence; and ſometimes
feigning an acknowledgment, hee
craves pardon of her for the fault which he is
reſolved hourely to commit, and promiſes
her that which he never intends to performe:
Under this diſſembled pretext he reſolves to
try whether he can draw any words of more
comfort from her. How now Diophania
ſayes he! ſince I labou
                     ••
                  d to give the call, or
indeed rather to acquire all, it ſeemes thou
art determined to make me loſe all, as if
thou hadſt no remainder left of thy former
good will. O no, ſayes ſhe, but the wrongs
and miſtakes, which it hath drawne thee to
commit, makes me withdraw the outward
expreſſion and ſhew of it; and if thou trouble
me any further therein, thou wilt make me
recall and withdraw alſo the ſubſtantiall and
reall part. It was ſo long ſince Hermodan had
received from Diophania any word accompanied
with favour, or any kind of freedome,

that to him, the hope, as well as the
cuſtome ſeemed for ever loſt; inſomuch that
herein ſtriving to give ſome moment of eaſe
to his paſſion, he layes hold on the taſt and
reliſh of that little ſweet that was contained
in ſo much gall. But it is ſo difficult a thing
to a minde, to whom Love propounds ſo
many felicities and honours, whereunto it
hourely aſpires, to finde any great contentment
in the ordinary pleaſures of an indifferent
affection, that in a ſhort time hee was
forced to give himſelfe the lye, and to ſigh
more than formerly for her ſake.
               It is a poore enterprize of his, to think to
be able to reſiſt ſo many attracts and charmes;
in what eſtate ſoever he ſayes her, or beholds
her, he is not able to be Maſter of himſelfe,
or ſubſiſt; and what action ſoever ſhee imployes
her ſelfe in, ſeemes to him a continuall
killing of him. So that one day, being
ſurcharged with his ſorrow, he determined
to implore her pitty, without which hee
could no longer live; or at leaſt beg leave of
her to bewaile his condition: but ſhe, not
onely, not contented her ſelfe, to interrupt
and refuſe audience to his lamentation, but
under pretext of ſending him to ſeeke in abſence
the cure of a Diſeaſe, which tooke

hourely increaſe in preſence, ſhee abſolutely
forbad him to come any more neare her,
which ſentence ſhee could not pronounce
without ſome paſſion, and a kind of cholerick
motion, which rendred her eyes more
fervently darting than uſuall, and made her
thereby ſeeme the more beautifull. At this
inſtant Love ſeeming not content to uſe his
ordinary ſhafts, armed himſelfe with a
Thunder-bolt, not onely to threaten Hermodan,
but to overturne him, and in one
moment reduce him to aſhes. Ah woe is me!
Diophania, ſayes he, that ſuch an expreſſe
command requires ſo prompt an obedience:
leſt therefore my life may hereafter be offenſive
to thee, accept not onely the farewell of
ſeparation thou haſt ordained me, but alſo
that of Death, which I am going to ſuffer.
This being uttered, his mouth was not able
in a long time to utter any one word, nor
his eyes to ſhed any teares; and yet Diophania
had the heart to breake company firſt, and
leave him to the mercy of diſpaire and frenzy
which ſeized him. He calls upon Death
without intermiſſion, and finding himſelfe
deprived of his beloved, grows weary of the
company of his life: But his Fate was not
conformable to his will, nor any way plyable

to his intreaties, to whom then ſhall he
have recourſe? It is to no end to ſigh amongſt
the Woods and Wilderneſſes; for
in reſpect of a Lovers lamentation, the Deſarts,
the Rocks, and Diophania are all one,
and have one and the ſame eares.
               This poore Shepheard, who thought
continually on his Birth and extraction, and
in whom the gods had with nobleneſſe and
generous courage, ſupplyed the defects of
his Fortune, was never negligent in the
ſervice of their Altars, as knowing well
that upon their conduct and providence
depends the good or ill Fortune of men.
But as on Earth hee bore an extreame
love to Diophania, ſo in Heaven he performed
a particular Devotion to the Sun;
to him he addreſſes his vowes and ſupplications,
and thus falling cut of one extreamity
into another, hee, who whilome
invoked the moſt dreadfull of the Goddeſſes,
now againe implores and calleth upon
the faireſt of the gods. O great Apollo,
ſayes he, thou Fountaine of life and
light, which giveſt being and increaſe to
all things, if ever the Oblations, which I
with an innocent minde and undefiled hand
have offered thee, have beene acceptable,

give eare to my preſent requeſt; and if there
be any errour in my thoughts or wayes, let
the voluntary confeſſion I make thereof,
expiate the offence. But firſt looke whether
the ſtroke that wounds me be inevitable,
and whether I have not had
cauſe enough to doubt thy ſole and abſolute
authority. O thou great Author of Ages,
grant me the grace of being loved, where I
love and adore, to wit, of the Sunne and
Diophania. Theſe prayers ſent from a heart
ſurcharged with paſſion, touched the Sunne,
but the beauty of Diophania had ſtruck him
before; and he, who ſees every thing, ſaw
nothing more worthy to bee looked upon
than ſhee; as indeed there was nothing more
like unto him, or more worthy of his love. I
have ſundry times heard, that which I never
yet could beleeve; that is, that love hath oftentimes
moved the gods, yea, Jupiter himſelfe
to forſake Heaven, and come downe on
Earth; the verity whereof is ſo confirmed by
this Hiſtory, that it muſt for ever remaine indubitable;
for though I cannot ſay, that the
Magitians charmes are able to draw the
Moone from Heaven, yet well I know that
thoſe of Diophania have prevailed ſo farre upon
the Sun, whoſe beauty may be truely ſaid

to appeare as a Sun in the Sunne it ſelfe. On
a certaine day, as this faire, but over-cruell
Shepheardeſſe, avoiding perchance the love
and preſence of her Shepheard, had driven
her Flock into a place more ſolitary and quiet
than ordinary, not farre from that part
of this ſacred Forreſt, which is neareſt to
the City, where ſhe thought ſhe might bee
moſt exempt from the encounter of any thing
that might diſturbe or moleſt her: This god,
whoſe eye pierces the moſt ſecret corners,
and whoſe darting beames Hell it ſelfe cannot
eaſily ſhun, preſents himſelfe before her
with his beauty, which gives him the advantage
above all the reſt of the gods, and
with a good part of that great luſtre, which
renders him generally knowne; where-with
ſhe was ſo ſurprized, that her feare making
her betake her ſelfe to flight, ſhe would have
bin ſo glad that any one would have lent her
wings to increaſe her ſpeed, that if Love
himſelfe had offered her his, ſhe would not
have refuſed them. She runnes a great way
into the Wood, where albeit ſhe was ſafe enough
at the firſt entry, yet ſhee forbeares
not to runne continually; every ſhade to her
ſeemes to ſhine, and on which, ſide ſoever
ſhe ſees any day, ſhe thinks ſhe is purſued.
               
                  
At length feare having as it were emboldened
her, ſhe thinks there is no ſafety for
her, but in that moſt horrid darkneſſe and
obſcurity, which at other times was wont
to affright her. Take courage Hermodan,
and draw a good Augury from this accident;
ſhe thinkes if thou hadſt not bin ſeparated
from her, this affright had not ſurpriſed
her; ſhe repents her over-ſight, and begins
to wiſh for thee. And thou Diophania, goe
boldly out of theſe ſhady places, for thy
feare is the vaineſt in the World: Of all the
gods, this whom thou laſt ſaweſt, is leaſt
terrible; and I wonder by what chance it
happens, that he, who chaſes away all affrights,
hath ſo diſtempered thee.
               In the meane time the Sunne, howſoever
ſo very ſwift of foote, that hee could eaſily
have ſtayed her, ſeeing her flye in ſuch manner,
would not follow her: The example
of Daphne having tempered him ſo farre,
that he then tooke an Oath, never any more
to make any violent purſuit in the like caſe,
and therefore chuſeth rather to worke by
perſwaſions than conſtraint: But hee finding
that his many faire qualities rendred
him more dreadfull, and leſſe acceptable,
and that the meane to obtaine favour at

her hands, was to abate of his extraordinary
great merit, and that his Deity did
prejudiſe him, he reſolves to aſſume the
forme of a man. Now although the gods
doe all things divinely, yet their wills governe
not ſo all the authorities of Fates, but
that they have ſome ſecret reſervations,
which they know not of. He perceiving
Diophania's rigour to be no leſſe than her
beauty, and that ſhe either could not be
perſwaded, or perſwaded onely to a vertuous
end, he ſo governes his undertakings,
that hee intends with one and the ſame action,
either to ſatisfie himſelfe, or at leaſt
grant the requeſt of him, who inceſſantly
implores his aſſiſtance. Hee therefore puts
on the ſhape of Hermodan, preſuming that
his abſence had by this time wrought ſome
compunction in her breaſt, imagining that
ſhe might diſlike his ſo prompt obedience,
or have conceived an opinion, that if hee
had really loved her, he could never have
beene ſo eaſily commanded to a ſeparation:
ſhee beholds him curiouſly as hee approaches
her, and is ſo farre from ſtarting
aſide, or withdrawing her ſelfe from
him, that, beſides her feare, which before
m
                     •
                  de her deſire his preſence, ſhee

diſcernes ſomething in him which renders
him more gracefull than formerly: O Diophania!
how wilt thou be able to oppoſe
the violence that this day thou art aſſaulted
withall, both by the gods and men? all
the powers and vertues of the world are
aſſembled in one body to attempt thine all
alone, and are ſo much the more fearefull,
becauſe in acknowledging thee Conquerour,
they will render thee vanquiſhed: They
are the ſame eyes thou wert wont to behold,
and yet they have certaine beames and
ſparklings, which render them more cleare
and penetrating than ordinary. The countenance
hath the ſame lineaments, but ſome
attracts and graces withall, which it had not
formerly. It is indeed the ſame voyce and
ſpeech, but what doth it not utte? and what
Charmes doth it forbeare to inchant thine
eares withall? In a word, it is the ſame
ſtature, the ſame body, but inſpired with a
Deity, of whom (to avoyd being perſwaded)
thou muſt ſhunne the conference. She
ſhould have fled him, as formerly, but
poore Diophania knowes not that there
are two Hermodans at once in the world;
and that the counterfeit is farre more potent
than the reall one; whilſt ſhe at

once receives ſuch powerfull and pleaſing
impreſſions of him, as cannot be afterwards
defaced, and his image equally aſſiſted with
Love, and the god he perſonated, enters ſo
firmly into her breaſt, that ſhe will for ever
remaine poſſeſſed therewith: howſoever
ſhe give no other exteriour ſigne or teſtimony
of it, than her patient and attentive
eare to his words; wherein alſo ſhe uſed ſo
much diſcretion and reſervedneſſe, that a
Mortall could not perceive it, but that
it was requiſite to have a Divinity to
diſcerne it. But Apollo, who read her
thoughts, finding, that what arguments ſoever
he alleadged, ſhe could not be induced
to entertaine any undue affection, and that
all his attempts unprofitable to his owne
ſuit, had no other effect, but to render
more acceptable the perſon, of whom he
bore the ſhape, contented himſelfe with
the admiration of Diophanias vertue, and to
grant to Hermodan the aide he required ſo
humble at his hands. It now onely remaines
to make him know, that he is no leſſe fortunate,
than he thinkes himſelfe miſerable:
which he preſently performes before hee
would quit the ſhape he had aſſumed, the
more pregnantly to prove to him, that

notwithſtanding his ſeparation had prohibited
him to ſee Diophania, yet, that he
had beene both ſeene and heard of her▪
                  Hermodan, tyred with ſighing and lamentation,
was by chance riſen from the foot
of a Tree, and ſitting himſelfe to retire, ſtood
a while beholding his flocke, which ſeemed
ſenſible of his anguiſh and affliction; when
as from farre he perceived the Sunne, like his
ſecond ſelfe approaching him, which ſo perfectly
reſembled him, that he could not miſtake
him, without miſ-knowing himſelfe;
which ſo much diſturbed his thoughts, that
to get out of the confuſion wherein he was,
he determined to goe and behold himſelfe in
ſome Fountaine, to ſee whether he were not
by ſome miracle changed into another, as
he really beheld another transformed into
his likeneſſe: he could not underſtand any
poſſibility of being in two places at once,
to walke and ſtand ſtill all at once, or how
he could be intire, and yet divided. And although
in this object, he ſaw no other thing
than what he had beheld every day of his
life; yet if any man ſhould have asked him
the name of it, he would have beene much
troubled to have told it: when he heard

theſe words: Hermodan, I am the god
whom thou imploreſt, and who have aſſumed
thy ſhape for no other end, but to render
thee more powerfull and acceptable to her
who gloried in diſdaining thee: An affright
ſhe lately had, made her wiſh for thy
preſence, which I have this day granted
her in thine abſence, to the end, by this
meanes, and by the ſtrongeſt perſwaſions,
and moſt powerfull charmes, which under
a humane ſhew could proceed from
a Divinity to make her ſenſible. Having
ſpoken theſe words, the Sunne retires,
and night arrives, ſo that Hermodan had
not time, either to adore him, or give him
thankes: And in that intention he ſcarce
knew how to reſolve to demeane himſelfe,
ſo much he feared to offend the gods,
in Honouring his owne Image. He never
had thought himſelfe ſo faire or perfect,
that he could eaſily be induced to take
his owne reſemblance for the Sunne.
Here upon a thouſand doubts aſſaulted his
imagination, eſpecially when he called to
minde what had ſome few dayes before been
told him by an old Shepheard, who had
the name and repute of a Magician or

Sooth-Sayer; to wit, that to purchaſe
the love of the Beauty he affected, were
required the qualities of a god, under
the appearance of a man: Which he
formerly had taken for a teſtimony of
Diophania's Pride and Scorne, and the
ſmall hope hee was to expect of her.
But now comparing theſe ſayings with
the words he had laſt heard, that which
before made him diſpaire, gives him
now more aſſurance: yet as the gods, when
they are diſpoſed to appeare to us, doe
accommodate themſelves to the weakneſſe
of our ſences, and aſſume ſuch ſhapes
as are moſt familiar, and ſupportable by
us, leſt by preſenting themſelves in
their owne reall Formes, the onely glance
of their preſence ſhould deſtroy and conſume
us: ſo alſo by too much diſpoſing
themſelves in ſo gentle a way, they
often leave ſcruples and doubts in us of
their reality, and whether they be themſelves
or no; ſuggeſting by this meanes
to our blindneſſe a thouſand Subjects and
cauſes of incredulity. So this poore ſhepheard,
not knowing what he ſhould beleeve,
vexes himſelfe, and findes his Spirits

overwhelmed in the confuſion of
his thoughts, and paſſing the night with
a thouſand Diſquiets, could not ſleepe,
had he not beene forced to it by the neceſſity
of his former watching.
               The end of the Third Booke.
            
            
               
               ENDYMION.
               The Fourth Booke.
               
                  ON the other ſide Diophania findes
not her ſleepe ſo ſweete or pleaſing
as ſhe was wont, and her
ill reſt beginnes already to make
her awake before Aurora: ſhe never ceaſes
to delight her ſpirit with the pleaſures
which love uſually at firſt repreſents to thoſe
whom he intends to ingage in his ſervice,
and as yet perceived not the ſecret thornes
and prickles, covered with the ſweete pleaſing
Flowers and Roſes: ſhe admires the

conſtancy and loyalty of her ſhepheards, and
inceſſantly revolves in her thoughts his diſcourſes
and his actions, which rendered him
perfectly amiable. But as her beauty acquired
her no fewer ſervants than all young
men that durſt looke upon her; ſo amongſt
others, Amphidamas had already
but too much beheld her, for he thence found
ſuch inward aſſaults▪ as deprived him of his
patience, and induced him, with the day, to
goe interrupt the quiet of Hermodan with
this language. Now is the time and opportunity
Hermodan ſaies he, that together
with the glorious title of the firmeſt friend
in the world, thou maiſt in one inſtant gaine
Amphidamas his fortune; and whatſoever
is his, if thou but accord him one good office,
which, alſo, no reſpect can permit thee to
refuſe him in.
               Thou knoweſt that the extreame beauty of
Diophania, accompanied with as great an auſterity,
renders her inacceſſable to all men,
except onely to thee, whom a long habit of
acquaintance hath rendred familiar with her:
In which reſpect I 
                     •
                  ntreat thee to intimate
unto her my deſire and ſuite to ſerve her,
and to adde in my behalfe whatſoever thy
good will or friendſhip ſhall ſuggeſt unto

thee, to obliege me: I cannot thinke this
meſſage propounded by Hermodan, in
the behalfe of Amphidamas, can diſpleaſe
her, except it be ſo that none but a Deity
onely, can be able to deſerve or obtaine the
grace and permiſſion I ſue for. Hermodan,
whoſe misfortune continually aſſaults and
traverſes his merit, and ſo violently oppoſes
his felicity, that even the gods themſelves
have much travile and difficulty to
witneſſe by effects the good will they beare
him, would faine have excuſed himſelfe
of this ſo fatall Commiſſion: But when we
have to doe with men, whoſe condition
ſo farre exceeds ours, excuſes muſt bee well
grounded, and ſupported with many firme
reaſons, otherwiſe they are taken as refuſals,
and injurious diſcourteſies. But hee
with this beginnes to conceive, that this
imployment will give him a good pretext to
frequent and accoſt Diophania with the more
confidence and be a meanes for him to draw
from her ſome proofe of her late favourable
change: whereupon (through his exceſſive
deſire thereof) he could not yet fixe his hope,
and ſo reſolves to gratifie this his irkſome
Rivall with this ſmooth anſwer: That he
would moſt cheerefully and willingly deliver

to Diophania the meſſage he had charged
him withall, and would with no leſſe
fidelity and promptitude, render him the anſwer
which he ſhould receive from her; that
he ſo perfectly Honourd them both, that
he deſired to render them equally ſatisfied of
his obedience: and that he would rather
expoſe himſelfe to the hazard of incurring
Diophanias diſpleaſure, than to omit any occaſion
of ſerving him. So Amphidamas ſtaied
him no longer, for indeed they were
both travailed with one and the ſame
longing: Hermodan to ſee Diophania,
and Amphidamas to ſee him ſet forward.
               Behold now at length the happy day wherein
Hermodan beginnes to reaſſume the path
he had ſo long loſt: But although hee
was bound to truſt more to the gods than
to himſelfe, yet his incredulity hourely ſuggeſted
new feares, and kept him in a continuall
irreſolution, untill he came even into
Diophanias preſence, whom he at firſt perceived
nothing moved, or ſurprized at his
ſight, as at ſome new thing, which ſomewhat
fortified his reſolution, yet he endeavoured
by theſe words to gather more full
aſſurance. There is, Diophania, ſaies he, a

new occaſion which engages me to make
thee a diſcourſe, which perchance will be leſſe
unpleaſing than that whereby I purchaſed
thy diſpleaſure, and procured baniſhment
from thy preſence: Thou now haſt no further
need to conſult thy rigour for mine
anſwer, or employ it to make me ſuffer
death, ſince the deſigne of Amphidamas is
more than enough to ruine and deſtroy me;
he is wholly reſolved to ſerve thee, and hath
made me promiſe him to give thee notice of
it. Whereat Diophania interrupting him,
ſayes; Tell me no more of this, ſayes ſhee,
neither let me any more heare of thee, or
Amphidamas. Theſe firſt words ſo aſtoniſhed
Hermodan, that he thought himſelfe no
leſſe unfortunate than he was wont: Hee
inwardly accuſes both the gods and men, and
imagines that his evill Genius, or ſome
other Devill yet more fatall to him, had
aſſumed his forme to deceive him, and
mocke his hope. Then Diophania thus
went forward: Had I yeſterday the patience
to heare thee ſpeake thy pleaſure of
thine owne affection, that thereby I ſhould
encourage thee to thinke that I would endure
this day to heare thee talke ſo much
of that of Amphidamas? haſt thou had halfe

a dayes conſtancy? or haſt thou ſo little to
ſue for in thine owne behalfe that thou muſt
of neceſſity either be ſilent, or ſpeake for another?
Away deceiver, thou no more
remembreſt the words thou ſpeakeſt, or the
proteſtations thou makeſt, than as if ſome
other had pronounced them for thee, or
thou never hadſt thought on them: With
this Hermodan manifeſtly perceiving the
verity he had beene informed, beganne too
late to repent his incredulity; yet a ſecret
joy ſeizing his heart, doth ſo tranſport him
beyond himſelfe, that he forgets all his former
ſorrowes, and ſuffers now no paine,
but that of exceſſive pleaſure: He throwes
himſelfe at Diophanias feete, and begges of
her the pardon he is ſure to obtaine; for
now all her rigours are growne feigned, and
her moth utters not that harſh word which
is not preſently contradicted by her eyes. It
was now that theſe two lovers beganne to
ſigh equally for one another, and entertaine
themſelves with ſo much delight and felicity,
that there was no day ſo long, which in
this reſpect ſeemed not ſhort to them; yet
not their pleaſures onely, but even their very
deſires were alwayes accompanyed of innocence;
and whatſoever violent tryalls love

charged them, their vertue was never injured
or impaired in the leaſt. And as they
judged of all things onely in favour, and by
the rule of their affections, ſo they ſoone
forgat the inequality of their fortunes; and
without troubling themſelves with any
thing that might be able to croſſe their deſignes,
they promiſed themſelves that time
would accommodate all things, and from
thenceforward entertained onely good hopes
thereof.
               In the meane time Amphidamas, whoſe
love ſenſible increaſed by the difficulty
Diophania made in receiving the advice of
it, found ſoone after an expedient to procure
him audience: for by addreſſing himſelfe
to Lycaſpis her father, obtained of him
all that he could requeſt at his hands. The
onely reſpect of his power and parentage,
which ranked him as farre above Diophania,
as ſhe was above Hermodan, permits him not
to conſult further upon the poynt, and thinks
his daughter muſt needes be no leſſe pleaſed
therewith than he: and ſo when he ſpeakes to
her of it, he imputes the change which appeares
in her face to modeſty, and the natural
baſhfulneſſe, which in the like occaſion commonly
accompanies thoſe of her Age and

Sexe, and takes her ſilence for conſent; yet
Amphidamas preſſing more and more, Diophania
muſt declare her ſelfe; and her father,
who at firſt is reſolved to conſtraine her, is
deſirous to heare her inclination thereunto
from her ſelfe. But her feare of diſpleaſing
him, makes her not dare to tell him, what ſhe
hath before ſufficiently declared to her mother▪
and therefore Mirtamiſa ſpeaking for
her, informes Lycaſpis of that which he deſired
not to have heard: which was, that her
Daughters diſpoſition, would make her preferre
the condition of the pooreſt ſhepheard
of the World, before all the wealth of him,
whoſe perſon ſhe could not affect: Which
when Lycaſpis heard, his Barbarous inhumanity
would not give him leave to reply
any thing, but words of reproach. And
as he never had the temper either to retaine
his Choler, or conceale his opinion, he failed
not to acquaint Amphidamas, with the
very words, which Mirtamiſa had reported
of Diophania, and to adviſe with him what
meanes were moſt proper to be uſed to gaine
her. Amphidamas bearing himſelfe violently
againſt whatſoever reſiſts him, thinking
all things due to him upon his firſt demand,
is not able to ſupport with patience, at the

hands of whom he ſo much loves, words ſo
full of diſdaine and hatred: Whoſoever now
looks upon her, increaſes his jealouſie, but
eſpecially Hermodan, who never forſakes
her Company; inſomuch that the firſt thing
he counſells Lycaſpis, is to forbid Diophania
any more to ſee him, or admit him to
her preſence. Then he commands her to reſolve,
and joyne a voluntary and cheerefull
obedience to the neceſſity of obeying; that
he had engaged his promiſe therein, and
beſides could not thinke that ſhe was ſo little
carefull of her ſelfe, or void of Judgment,
as to refuſe the greateſt honour and advantage
that ever he ſhould be able to procure
her. Lycaſpis being farre more indulgent to
the deſires of Amphidamas, than to thoſe
of his Daughter, forgot not from thence
forward to repeate often to her that unpleaſing
Oration, and to offer her the choiſe of
two things, either to remaine in his perpetuall
diſgrace, or to give him ſatisfaction in
that which he required.
               
                  Diophania finding her ſelfe thus urged,
howbeit ſhe could not eaſily perſwade her
ſelfe, that her determinations were in every
thing to depend on her Fathers will, or that
it was more convenient for her to enter into

an aſſured misfortune for her whole life, than
once to diſobey him; reſolves nevertheleſſe
to tell him, that her will depends wholly upon
his, and that ſhe will rather chuſe death
than diſobedience: But it was farre eaſier for
her to weepe than to anſwer; and from thoſe
two or three words, which ſhee ſcarce was
able to utter, ſhee fell ſuddenly into an abundance
of teares; this is now all the exerciſe
ſhe can imploy her ſelfe in, and by night
ſhe chiefly torments and afflicts her ſelfe,
whilſt Hermodan takes his reſt, or perhaps
delights his ſpirit with ſome pleaſing hope,
although indeed it were time for him to
diſpaire. He longs for nothing but the day,
to render himſelfe in theſe faire places, as the
ſole witneſſes of his felicity and contentment;
which arrives for him too ſoone, becauſe
with it he encounters Diophania ſad and
deſolate, bringing him this irkeſome and
unpleaſing meſſage. Ah Hermodan ſayes ſhe,
now is the time that my Fathers tyranny is
become compleat, who not onely commands
me to love Amphidamas, but with all
forbids me to ſee or ſpeake to thee: Farewel
therefore Hermodan; the ſmall power I have
over mine actions and my ſelfe, permits me
not any further conference with thee: know

onely that my life cannot ſubſiſt without the
continuance of thy love, and nothing can
comfort me but thy loyalty: How ſhould I
be able to expreſſe the eſtate our poore Lover
was now reduced, to whom this change
was ſo rude and ſenſible, that hee was not
himſelfe able to ſignifie his ſorrow but by aſtoniſhment
and ſilence? he knows not what
way to turne him, and ſeeing her the whole
object of his love, and onely that which
made his life acceptable to him, retire from
him, if he could have thought on any expedient
to facilitate the approach of death, he
would aſſuredly have made uſe of it. And
Diophania from thence forward became ſo
wholly ſeized with ſorrow, that every houre
ſhe viſibly changed, and in a very ſhort time
became wholly unlike to her ſelfe; yet ſhee
continued faire, for her beauty was ſo perfect,
that neither her teares or her ſorrows
were able to deface it.
               I obſerving all thoſe paſſages, and having
before perceived the affection ſhe bare to
Hermodan, although I were not reſolved
much to flatter her paſſion, as imagining it
could turne to no other thing but a neceſſary
change of the one or the other, or at leaſt a
common diſpaire in both, yet her Fathers

cruelty was to her ſo compleate an affliction,
that ſhe needed not the addition of any other
from me, who on the contrary ſought
all opportunities to divert and comfort her:
And perceiving that the onely name of Hermodan
had more power with her than any
diſcourſe I was able to preſent her withall, I
forced my ſelfe, for her ſake, as much as was
poſſible, to comply with her humour, and
by that meanes got knowledge of the whole
Story. If at any time I laboured to reduce
her memory to the conſideration of what ſhe
ought to doe, as by that meanes gently to
draw her back to the knowledge of her duty,
I found the oppoſition of two ſuch ſtrong
paſſions, her love to Hermodan, and her hatred
to Amphidamas, that the onely effect of
all my remonſtrances was a renovation of her
teares, and a drawing of this plaint from
her lips.
               Ah me! ſayes ſhe, either our deſires and
affections are blind, or the Lawes of Heaven
are cruell, that we muſt ſo ardently love that
which we can never poſſeſſe, or be poſſeſſed
by that, which we cannot affect: What likelyhood
is there, that ever I ſhall be able to
perſwade my ſelfe, that Amphidamas, whom
I hate above all other men, ſhould one day

become my better part, or indeed my ſecond
ſelfe? If the gods have ſo much exalted his
fortune, it is onely to diſplay his defects, and
ſhew the many wants in his perſon. My Father
is quite different from the diſpoſition of
other Fathers, whoſe children, how deformed
ſoever, ſeeme faire to them; for it is
his opinion, I muſt ſeeme very defective and
ill-ſhapen, ſince he goes about to preſent
me my Match in the moſt imperfect man of
all others, and as if I were bound to ſee onely
with his eies, and love with his inclination,
he will purchaſe me a contentment,
which I ſhall not onely never enjoy, but rather
eſteeme it for a ſingular affliction. Wherin
have I ever ſo much offended him, that
he inflicts a penance on me no ſhorter than
my life? and whereas others ſeeke the good
and contentment of their Children, he will
unworthily condemne me to the ſufferance
of an eternall affliction. Shall I alone in all
the workes of Nature be linked to my contrary?
If it be a Decree of Heaven, why is
it onely particular to me? And why is not
light as well annexed to darkneſſe, and all other
oppoſites mixed with a like confuſion?
It is a vaine propoſition they make to me,
that even thoſe, who in the beginning are

moſt odious to us, doe become, when once
the Law renders them ours, amiable by cuſtome,
and the neceſſity which is impoſed
upon us to affect them; Is not this a continuall
errour that reignes in us? Thus the poore
Galley-ſlave becomes enamoured on the
Chaine wherewith he hath bin accuſtomed to
be continually fettered; thus the very poiſon,
retaining its proper quality, is to many, food
and nouriſhment: and thus muſt we doubtleſſe
be growne exceeding ill, when we can
finde no taſte but in ill things, and that wee
begin to eſteeme Vice in lieu of Vertue.
               I remember, that as ſhe powred out thoſe
Lamentations, Lycaſpis came and told her,
that neither Amphidamas or he could attend
any longer, and that therefore ſhe ſhould
prepare her ſelfe for the conſummation of
the Marriage within two daies. But ſhe,
ſtriving onely to gaine time, to ſee if thereby
ſhe might obtaine from the gods the favour
that was denied her of men, anſwers
him, that therein her reſolution ſhould be
alwayes conformable to her duty. But ſince
ſhe was now engaged to a ſuddaine forſaking
of her preſent eſtate, to enter into that, which
Fate, at her Fathers command, ſeemed to
have appointed her, and that ſhee was ſuddenly

to be cured of the jealouſie ſhe formerly
had borne to the Damoſells, who had for
ever vowed themſelves to the ſervice of Diana;
that at leaſt, ſhe deſired to quit it with
the approbation and favour of the Goddeſſe,
and ſo deſired of him ſome few daies reſpite,
to render her the vowes which ſhe could not
continue in the practice of during her life.
And that ſhee might the more eaſily induce
him to grant her this licence, ſhe added, ſhe
would never preferre any thing, but the will
of the gods, to that of her Father; who at laſt
unwillingly granted her the requeſt, which
he could not refuſe her: So the ſame day ſhe
provided her ſelfe againſt the next morning
a Lampe, a veſſell of holy water, a Baſket
of Flowers, Garlands, a white Robe, and
Aromatick Odours: I waited upon her to
the Sacrifice the firſt day, which ſhe performed
with a white Heyfer, which by her
command I conducted thither, and immolated
in her preſence, upon the high Altar of
Diana; wherein I marked one ſigne, which
till that preſent I had beene utterly ignorant
of, which was, that the flame from all parts
drew towards the Sacrifice, juſt as you ſee
the roots all joyntly contribute to forme the
body of a Tree; and when it came to the

                  
                  
place, where uſually it aſcends directly upward,
it by the contrary ſpred it ſelfe into
abroad toppe, curled, and wholly reſembling
that of the Mirtle we lately ſaw. The next
day ſhe reſolved to be alone, ſo that I cannot
ſay what ſhe did, or with what preſents
her devotions were accompanyed, ſave
onely that towards the evening I ſaw her returne
ſo pale and diſ-figured, that ſhe ſeemed
onely the ſhadow of the former Diophania,
and I judged no otherwiſe but if that her
voyages and vowes had continued, ſhe
would ſhortly have onely her ſoule to make
offer of, which ſhe was every houre ready to
render: you would have ſaid ſhe had beene
hired to deface the Fabricke of her faire
Body, to prevent Amphidamas of poſſeſſing
it, or at leaſt to aboliſh and deſtroy that beauty
which had rendred her ſo amiable to
him, whom ſhe could never love. Thus daily
perſiſting in this her devout and religious
demeanour, ſhee went abroad the third
morning more early than ſhe had beene accuſtomed:
And this is all that I can ſay of
her; for night being come, we were all
equally amazed that Diophania returned not.
You know what deſolation Mirtamiſa fell
into, and what aſtoniſhment, fury, and rage

ſeized Lycaſpis at this accident; and how
wee were ſent abroad that very night,
and all theſe dayes paſt, to ſeeke her in
all places, without having ever gotten
any tidings of her: And had we not
by chance lighted upon the adventure of this
ſtranger, we might in vaine have continued
our ſearch over all the world of her who
was ſo neare us, and whom we had before
our eyes, and were yet neither able to ſee
or know her. From the offence he hath
committed, we have drawne the good of
knowing what is become of her, and in what
manner hee hath ſtopped the courſe of our
paines and labour: with this the ſlave ended
his ſtory, juſt as we began to enter the
City. They all brought me to their Captaines
houſe, where for a while they locked
me in a Chamber alone, where I employed
me in afflicting my ſelfe, expecting no leſſe
at my iſſue thence, than a ſtraight priſon, or
an eternall and cruell captivity: yet I ſaid
to my ſelfe, I ſhall not be wholly Captive, if
I can get leave but thus to ſigh at liberty.
Shall it be ſaid that I have wholly vowed
my ſelfe to the ſervice of a Goddeſſe, and
that (ſhe not ſo much as regarding it) I muſt
be compelled to ſuffer another bondage, and

undergoe the torment of the injuſtice of
men: Muſt I be puniſhed for a fault which
a Deity hath forced me to commit, deceiving
my eyes and judgement, to make my
hands the inſtruments to ſerve her turne?
But is Heaven ſo exact, as not to pardon an
accident which no Providence could prevent?
Is it your cuſtome, oh yee gods! that you
you your ſelves having an intention to
deſtroy us, make us commit faults, and then
interpret our miſtakes for crimes? Which
of you all, if I may dare to ſpeake thus, could
have refuſed a branch of Mirth to ſo many
beauties, albeit they had not beene ſeconded
with ſo many entreaties and perſwaſions:
It was perhaps ſome dreame or
vaine apparition; yet it was of your owne
forming, if it perchance were not ſome one
of your goddeſſes; what glory will you obtaine
by it, that thus to beguile one poore
man you have imployed ſuch attracts, &amp; forcible
charmes, as your ſelves would not have
bin able to have reſiſted.
               Whilſt I entertained my ſelfe with thoſe
thoughts, more full of feare than hope, I
heard one open the doore, where I ſaw enter
a great number of the principall, and the
moſt ancient of the City, who tooke ſpeciall

notice of my face, my ſtature, and the
whole proportion of my body; and then they
examined me whence I was, what was the occaſion
of my Voyage, and concerning the accident
that was befalne me; which done, they
retired apart, and talked a good while together,
and by their geſtures they ſeemed to me,
all to conſent to one and the ſame thing: In
the meane time, I not knowing what to doe,
could conclude no other thing in my
thoughts, but that I was a loſt man, and
bought and ſold by them, and ſhould bee
preſently delivered over to the beſt Chapman.
I wayted with longing to ſee how
they had diſpoſed of me: And daring to expect
nothing at the hands of my misfortune,
but all manner of diſaſters, I reſolved my ſelfe
to a conſtant ſuffering of more torment than
they could inflict upon me. But in ſtead of
this, I was on the ſuddaine wholly amazed to
ſee them, whom I had newly ſo much incenced;
to treat me, as if they had beene much
oblieged to me: and the chiefeſt of thoſe that
had taken me, ſuddainly turning his Choler
into Courteſie, and his injuries into good offices,
was exceeding carefull that I ſhould receive
all manner of contentment in his
houſe, and be better treated than himſelfe:

this made me ſay with my ſelfe, thoſe people
are not ſenſible of injuries, ſince they thus
mildly puniſh ſacriledges, and ſo ill defend
the cauſe of their gods. But little knew I
that it was their cuſtome to obſerve the
words and geſtures of their Captives, and
ſlaves thereby to diſcerne, which of them
was beſt inſpired to the diſcourſe of
times, and events, and fore-tell things to
come, and then to ſacrifice them. And ſo
walking one evening with ſome of the
principall of them, and being the firſt that
perceived the New Moone, as ſoone as
ſhe appeared in the Skye, I tooke occaſion
to diſcourſe of her, telling them how happy
I thought this Countrey, by being in the
protection of ſo great a goddeſſe; and in purſuit
of this, I beganne to ſhew them her
courſe, her motions, the cauſes of her ſeverall
ſhapes, and all her alterations and effects:
Thus, whilſt I precipitated my ſelfe to
my fatality, theſe people heard me with
great attention, and admiring that which
they underſtood not, they tooke all my
words for Oracles: eſpecially perceiving me
ſo paſſionately to rehearſe the praiſes of the
goddeſſe, and repeat Hymnes in Honour of
her, ſuch as they had not beene wont to

heare. Sometimes I ſeemed to them to be
tranſported even to Heaven; and that the performance
of theſe Diſcourſes, required, that
either I muſt have an extraordinary inſpiration
have beene an eye-witneſſe of all her motions;
inſomuch, that they all unanimouſly
profeſſed, and with one voyce ſaid: this
young man is queſtionleſſe happened fortunately
into our hands, and we have not any
one more worthy of the ſacred Chaine than
he▪ for it was the cuſtome to honour and adorne
with this Chaine, the perſon deſigned
for the Sacrifice) which I then underſtood
not.
               The next morning, before Sunne-riſing,
they led me to the River, where, putting
off their Cloathes, and cauſing mee to doe
the like, the firſt leapt into the water, and
then tooke me, according to the cuſtome of
their Purifications, and plunged me thrice over
head and eares deepe into the water, keeping
my head alwayes towards the Eaſt; then
perceiving me cleane, without the leaſt ſpot,
they clad me with new garments of blacke,
and white, which they had brought along
with them, and added thereunto the ſacred
Chaine, which was of three ſorts, the firſt
gold, the ſecond ſilver, and the third Iron,

                  
                  
wherewith they bound me after their manner,
which was ſo, that mine armes were
not at liberty, and yet told me that, that was
rather a ſigne of Freedome than Captivity, to
the end, that whoſoever met me ſhould honour
me, and ſeeing me a ſtranger ſhould not
take me for a ſlave; that all paſtimes and recreations
were freely allowed me, and that
I might goe and take them in the Forreſts,
and Mountaines, according to mine owne
choyſe; from thence they brought me back
to the City, not to my accuſtomed lodging,
but to their High-prieſt, or Sacrificers houſe,
where they more and more encreaſed their
honour, and good treatment of me: inſomuch,
that I knew not whether I ſhould
impute the cauſe of it to the proofes I had
given them of my courage, or the inſtruction
and light I had given them in other things,
or to the nobleneſſe of my Nation, holding
it a very eaſie thing for a Grecian to
paſſe for a demy-god amongſt Barbarians.
               
               But Endymion, ſaies Pyzander, pardon my
juſt curioſity, which oblieges me to interrupt
thee, by asking thee what became of Hermodan
all this while, whom you loſt at the foot
of the Myrtle? Hermodan, replyed Endymion,
ſtaied there the whole day, beholding

                  Diophania in this new condition, adoring
her, and powring out his lamentations before
her: but it ſeemes ſhe hath neither
voyce nor words more, and that her Fate
had already put a limit to all the Diſcourſes
ſhe was for ever to make, with that caſe ſhee
had uttered to us: neither doe I thinke
that he received any other anſwer from her:
or at leaſt, if ſhe ſpoke any more to him, it
was that which onely ſerved to increaſe his
affliction to the height of diſpaire. At length
perceiving there was no more of Diophania
left him, and that to ſee her in that eſtate, and
to ſee her dead, was one and the ſame thing;
that after having acquired the affection of
the rareſt beauty in the World, and beene
preferred therein, not onely to the greateſt
of men, but even to the gods themſelves,
there remained no earthly thing fit for him to
deſire: And beſides, he having beene the
principall cauſe of whatſoever had beene
tragicall, and moſt deploreable in this ſad adventure
                     •
                  ;
it would have argued a want of
ſence or feeling of it, and a ſtupidity of
courage to have deſired to live longer, and
purchaſe nothing thereby, but contempt and
ſhame: So, finding both love and deſpaire,
yea, and his very Conſcience reproaching

him with every moment he added to his life,
he reſolved to ranke himſelfe into the number
of the dead, provided, that in Sacrificing
himſelfe in her preſence, he might, if it were
poſſible, procure her a place amongſt the Deities.
And thus, having the whole day watered
and bedewed the foote of the Myrtle
with his teares, he reſolved at night to beſprinkle
it with his blood; but juſt as he
was giving himſelfe the mortall ſtroke,
one by chance paſſing by ſaw him, and ſnached
the Dart out of his hand, which he was
going to employ in this fatall execution.
Afterwards he would have ſought ſome
Rocke or Precipice for the accompliſhing
of his purpoſe, if he had not eſteemed it as
a great crime, from thenceforward any moment
to leave her preſence, for whoſe
ſake onely in what eſtate ſoever ſhe were,
hee was fully determined to live and
dye. He therefore implores the pitty of
the gods, eſpecially of Apollo, and conjures
them ſo unfeignedly to put ſome period to
his ſufferings, that the night following, when
all creatures were dumbe and at reſt, they
alſo ſtopped the current of his lamentations,
and by a change, not much unlike that of Diophania,
granted him the repoſe he had ſo

much deſired at their hands. For the next
morning the people who came flocking
from all parts, to ſee this new Nymph, under
the ſhape of a Myrtle, where wholly amazed
with the ſight of another ſpectacle before
her, which was that of Hermodan, repreſented
under the figure of a wilde Olive-Tree,
which Olive and Myrtle were ſo neare together,
that their branches began to intermixe
in token of ſympathy and affection. And
ſince that time, the Nymphes of theſe quarters
have celebrated nothing ſo much as the
names of Hermodan and Diophania, ſinging
continually to their praiſes, as of two incomparable
examples of love and fidelity, whom
they have recommended to everlaſting memory
and renowne.
               There is one doubt more, ſaies Pyzander,
to be cleared, which is, that thou haſt hitherto
diſcourſed of a City, a River, and a Countrey,
without naming either one or other
of them. Indeed ſaies Endymion, that queſtion
is eaſily anſwered; they having all three
almoſt one and the ſame name. The City
is called Alba; the River, Alban; and the
Countrey, Albania. And this, as I ſuppoſe,
by reaſon of the nature of the place, which
produces the people generally flaxen-haird

in their youth: A people excelling in
beauty, of faire ſtature; another race of Cyclops,
inhabiting the Confines of the Caſpian
Sea, and Mount Caucaſus, for the moſt part
ſhepheards; Galactophagi, ſimple, innocent,
and juſt of life and manners, and in a word,
really ſuch as the Abiens, and Nomadi. Furthermore,
it is a Countrey of paſture, the
ſoyle is ſo fertile, that without any manuring
it produces infinite quantity of good
fruits, which in mine opinion is the cauſe
that the people are more negligent, and leſſe
addicted to husbandry; for indeed they
love no kinde of labour, except it bee immediatly
followed with reward, or accompanyed
with pleaſure, as hunting, alſo they imploy
more fervency and affection than induſtry.
But in ſtead of Art, Nature hath furniſhed
them with the beſt and ſtrongeſt
Dogges of the World, ſuch as both fight
with, and deſtroy Lyons, and are not affraid
to ſet upon any living creature. I cannot
give thee any more particular deſcription
of it, ſave onely, that as the fertility of Egypt
is accompanyied with its Crocodiles, ſo
this Countrey hath her Serpents, the teeth
whereof are mortall, and their poyſon of ſuch
a tickling operation, that men dye of it
with continuall laughing.
               
                  
That is the place, Pyzander, where I (not
ſenſible of the diſaſter, which not only threatned
but preſſed my life) have remained ever
ſince thou laſt ſaweſt me, and where I have
paſſed the greateſt part of my time at eaſe, amidſt
the freſh ſhades, on the River ſides,
with fragrant and odoriferous Flowers and
Hearbes, amongſt the Nymphes and the
May-maids, in the fulneſſe of thouſands of
delights, if my Spirit had then beene as ſenſible
thereof, as I became afterwards, when
I was reduced to the like degree of torment
and affliction. There were the feaſts, where
I was treated with the moſt exquiſite Cates,
with the Muſicke both of inſtruments and
voyce, and with the Dances of young Gallants,
and faire Ladies: in a word, there was
nothing but paſtimes and delights▪ If I
were accompanyed, ſo had I alſo the liberty
of being alone when I pleaſed; and ſo making
dayly choyce of the recreations that moſt
pleaſed me; I went uſually up and downe the
Forreſt, where I often encountered Diana,
whoſe ſole preſence made mee live, in the
ſame time that her change, and the remembrance
of the time paſt had even killed me.
Sometimes I ſaw her walke, attended by the
ſixty daughters of Oceanus, and of twenty other

Nymphes, who have charge of her
Bowes, her Arrowes, her Buſgins, and her
Dogges. Sometimes I obſerved her returning
from her game, all haughty, and triumphing
over the Lyons, Beares, and other
Monſters which ſhe had ſlaine. Sometimes
alſo I found her almoſt all alone, where I
had opportunity of ſeeing, and being ſeene
of her: But Pyzander wilt thou beleeve
this? Oh doe, for it is certaine, howbeit it
ſeeme ſcarce credible: Albeit, ſhe ſaw me
in the eſtate wherein I was, bearing the
Chaine, which ſhe knew well (though I knew
it not) to be the marke, not onely of my
Captivity, but of the end whereunto I was
deſigned; although I ſay, ſhe well knew I
was to be ſacrificed for her, yet had ſhe in the
meane time the heart to looke upon me
without pitty, as if ſhe had beene changed
into another, or had ſudainly loſt all compaſſion,
remembrance, knowledge, or ſpeech
of me. If I had preſented my ſelfe to the
flinty Rocke, where the waves of the Sea are
broken, and Marriners ſuffer ſhipwracke;
I might have obtained as much comfort:
And yet it is not lawfull for me to ſay ſhe is
a little rigorous, ſince that from henceforward
there is no other contentment left

me, than to alleadge mine affection to her,
that doth not acknowledge it: Yea, that
Nymph who had promiſed me ſo much favour
and aſſiſtance, and to whom I had
vowed ſo much ſervice, had alſo forgotten
my vowes, and her owne promiſes; and either
vouchſafed not to looke upon me at all, or
elſe looked on me by chāce, or as it were upon
a delinquent. Muſt the tranſgreſſion of the
Lawes which Iſmena had preſcribed me, coſt
me ſo deare? and muſt I thus pay for having
beene compelled to violate things eſteemed
ſacred: O Endymion, happy hadſt thou bin
if thou haddeſt not found any Myrtle in the
Forreſt of Diana: I ſhould at leaſt from the
beginning have beleeved the Oracle which
ſounded thence, and which at length I found
too true. I ſhould have laid aſide the care
of preſenting my ſelfe before her, ſince her
inſenſible carriage continually fruſtrated my
paines and expectation. But that hope
which uſually entertaines men with errour
and vanity, engaging them after to force
their Fate, perſwaded me to tempt fortune
yet once more; yea, and a ſecond time alſo.
I went ſo often to the place where I firſt had
ſeene her, and received more than a thouſand
Deaths from her hand, without dying, that

at length it chanced me to finde her there,
and participate of a ſpectacle farre more worthy
of the gods than of men.
               The noyſe which theſe Nymphes made, to
whom her affection and goodneſſe permitted
all manner of freedome in theſe ſolitary
places, even to a familiar ſporting with
her, gave me occaſion to hide my ſelfe in a
thicket, which I had before obſerved, where
I could ſee all, yet no body could ſee me; they
ſtood all upon their feete before the Goddeſſe,
obſerving heedfully the enterpriſe
which two or three of the chiefeſt of them
had ingaged themſelves in againſt her, which
ſhe reſiſted onely with ſmiling, as if ſhe cared
not much, although they ſhould overcome
her. One would have thought, ſeeing them
ſo imperiouſly to abuſe the power ſhe had
given them, that they had changed conditions
with her, and that ſhe, being really ſubject
to them, had deſerved to be handled as
a diſobedient and criminall perſon; for one
bound her feete, another her hands, with
bonds of ſilke and gold, which they tooke
from the Dryades that ſtood by: O yee gods,
thought I to my ſelfe! being amazed to ſee
ſo many vertues and beauties captive together;
in what eſtate or faſhion ſoever Diana
                  
at it, and could not containe themſelves.
But the Nayades onely laughed at it; and I
tooke that opportunity to retire me.
               Thus much time ſtole away, and the Feaſt
of Sacrifices approached: It was now that
Diana, ceaſing to be any more favourable
to me, Iſmene might have beene to mee in
ſtead of a goddeſſe; if the knowledge ſhe had
of what was to befall me, and the remembrance
of the promiſes ſhe had made me,
had mooved her to have a greater care of
my returne, than I had of it my ſelfe. But
is it poſſible, ſaid Pyzander, that thou wert
not troubled, concerning the time and
meanes ſhe ſhould uſe to free thee from
thence? I was ſo farre from calling her to
mine aide, or once naming her, that I endeavoured
to deny her admittance into
my thoughts, for feare leaſt my thoughts
ſhould come to her knowledge, and making
ſome attempt upon her vertue, ſhould
ſolicite her favour towards mee; as I had
feared nothing more, than to be drawne out
of the torment wherein I was: A blind deſire
made me violently to purſue that which I
ought to have avoyded: for whether Diana
were averſe or favourable, I could not forbeare
to goe daily to ſeeke her: Moreover

the true innocence of theſe people, the
honour and good entertainment they gave
me, the beauty of the place and the perſons,
and eſpecially of the women, who almoſt
generally had faire haire▪ and freſh complexions,
mingled with redde and white,
and the ſtature ſo gracefull and comely,
that if they had added to their naturall
perfections the Art of ſetting them
out, with the grace and ornaments, which
the Greekiſh Dames uſe, they would have
ſeemed goddeſſes. Thoſe things which ſeemed
in a manner to induce Diana her ſelfe
to viſite them ſo often, might well make me
for a while forget the charmes of my native
ſoyle.
               Amongſt other, the High Prieſt, named
Timetes, had a Neece of about ſeventeene or
eighteene yeares of age, who ſhared with
him in the care of the ſacred things, and ſeemed
to vow her ſelfe wholly to the ſervice
of Diana: But her beauty extreamly reſiſted
her vowes, being ſuch, with the Naturall
grace wherewith it was accompanied, that
there are very few in the world can equall
it, but none ſurpaſſe it: From the firſt time
that I ſaw her; I thought I had formerly
beheld and ſeene her elſe where, or at

leaſt ſome ſhadow, or reſemblance of her
beauty; for, having beene alwaies ſeparated
with ſo many Rivers, mountaines, and
remote Countryes, there was no likelyhood
that it could be the ſame: Moreover,
I imagined ſhe thought the ſame concerning
me, becauſe ſhe continually looked upon me,
as if ſhe had knowne me; which made me
ſuddenly beleeve we had ſeene each other in
Heaven before we were borne into the
World; and by conſequence might have
ſome ſympathy of affections: In the meane
time, I who was never unſenſible in the
encounter of ſuch objects (ſave onely ſince
the Law which I impoſed on my ſelfe) to obſerve
conſtantly the vowes I had made to Diana,
whoſe onely Idea purifies my thoughts,
and baniſhes all earthly &amp; mortall thoughts
from my heart, would not engage her affection
by too much Diſcourſe, nor promiſe her
more than I had liberty to performe, having
ever obſerved that Rule amongſt all ſorts of
people, that my words ſhould not in any
thing differ from mine intentions. But yet
from my firſt view of her I endeavoured to
render mine actions acceptable to her, thereby
to doe me good will at her hands.
               It happens uſually that in theſe accidents

we finde ſomething within us which doth
ſo ſtrongly animate us, and ſtirres up in us
deſires of on affection ſo naturall, that we
have much adoe to overcome our ſelves, and
conceale our paſſion: And although in
this reſpect, our owne inclinations were not
of themſelves ſo prompt, yet we are oblieged
by diſcretion and civility, not to ſeeme
wholly inſenſible of it. Great beauties have
a ſecret kinde of Divinity, more powerfull
than Scepters and Empires: And our extreame
diſpoſition to love them, makes our
opinions adde new force, and charmes to
them. They can ſo naturally perſwade and
conſtraine; yea, without the aſſiſtance of
Art, that their very ſilence is more eloquent
than any Language; we cannot looke on
them without amazement and diſturbance;
and their ſole preſence in one inſtant bereaves
us both of judgement, force, and courage:
for by the eyes iſſue ſuch attracts, as
gives us what inſpiration and motion they
pleaſe, and by inviſible Chaines doe ſo ſweetly
force and draw us, that they make us follow
them without contradiction or reſiſtance.
A ſmile, a geſture, or motion, raviſhes
us with admiration and ſighes, and even
tranſports us: what ſhall I ſay more? one

onely looke charmes us, inchants us, drinks
our blood, transformes and renders us inſenſible.
No Pyzander, I am of opinion,
that if the World were without women, we
ſhould have a familiar converſation with the
gods: for indeed, what is there but they may
command over our ſoules? and what perſwaſion,
compulſion, or torture, is comparable
to the force of their attracts? O Iupiter!
wilt thou not pardon all the wrongs
malice, fraudulent Diſcourſes, artifices, falſe
oathes, loſſe of time, and the impertinent
paines and labours they ingaged us in? As
for me, I neither ought nor could love any
other earthly thing, being ſo farre engaged
in the ſervice of a goddeſſe; yet whereſoever
this faire one came into my ſight; I was
much troubled to keepe my ſelfe from uſing
a ſecret language of mine eyes, a perſwading
ſilence, a geſture and garbe more eloquent
than ſpeech it ſelfe, a negligence repleniſhed
with artifice, and a demeanour diſcreet
and moderate in it ſelfe, although towards
others full of violence: Whereof at firſt, by
reaſon of the innocent freedome of her age,
and her ſmall experience ſhe tooke little
heed, but within a few dayes I could plainly
perceive that her heart was as tender as

others, and that her diſpoſition was capable
of love, how carefull ſoever ſhe were to
keepe it private; and that a woman more expert
in diſſembling her thoughts, would
have beene harder to be diſcovered. But
Stenobea (ſo was her name) who had not yet
learned that love is a fire, hard to be hidden,
or kept from ſhining, and that the heate of
it cauſes a thouſand diſquiets, which beget as
many ſeverall motions, thought her ſilence
a ſufficient Maske to cover her inward
trouble, as if love had had no other Organ
but the tongue to expreſſe it ſelfe by: Indeed
ſhe betraid not her thoughts with any
one word, and ſo made it a dumbe love,
though not blind: But the vaile ſeemed to
be taken from her eyes, onely to ſtop her
mouth. How then couldeſt thou perceive
Pyzander, that ſhe loved thee. The end, anſwered
Endymion will give thee proofe of
the truth of it: It was that, which gave me
aſſurance of it my ſelfe; yet I will tell thee
what it was that made me of that opinion
from the beginning, where I might reckon
the extraordinary care ſhe had of me; the
recommendation ſhe gave of me to others,
and the teſtimonies of it, which I could read
in the faces of her ſervants; and the frequent

meſſages, ſhe ſent me upon all occaſions under
the pretexts, as ſometimes ſending mee
little Preſents, or demanding where I was
as ſoone as ever I was out of her ſight: every
thing ſmiled, and looked upon me with
affectionate eyes. But thou maiſt imagine
that all this was onely in reſpect of their Cuſtome
of treating thoſe well, who are deſigned
to dye for them. So I, not building
much on thoſe ſlighter proofes, was wholly
amazed to ſee her in ſo ſhort a time become
unlike to her ſelfe, and change her former liberty,
and free actions, the ſignes of a ſound
mind, into a diſpoſition penſive, ſolitary, and
languiſhing: Her face was become pale,
and her eyes ſwolne, true witneſſes of her
watchings and diſquiet: Her lookes were
ſometimes wandring in the aire, and ſometimes
fixed on the earth, like one in a deepe
frenzy. Sometimes ſhe beganne Diſcourſes,
but ended them not, as not knowing well
what ſhe ſaid: Otherwhiles leaving her
workes undone, and forgetting her moſt
pleaſing exerciſes, they being not powerfull
enough to make her forget her torment; ſhe
inclined to all manner of change, ſhe wandred
impatiently, ſeeking that repoſe every
where, which ſhe could not encounter in any

one place: Sometimes as if ſhe had perceived
that ſhe diſcovered her ſelfe, ſhe laboured to
reprove her ſelfe, by employing an endeavour
to reſiſt her malady, and putting on a
more cheerefull countenance; And if the
compaſſion ſhe had of my diſaſter had not
forbidden her to adde to mine affliction, ſhee
would have made a ſhew of hating mee, to
prevent the accuſation of loving mee too
much. But doe what ſhe could, it was of
ſmall continuance, and immediately as Conquered,
ſhe relapſed into her former paſſion:
ſhe ſighed inceſſantly, without any apparent
cauſe of vexation or ſorrow, and this ſhe
could not forbeare whatſoever ſhe attempted
to ſuppreſſe her ſighes, and ſmother them
in the Cradle. Beſides, the heart, by a ſecret
power, turnes the eyes alwayes towards the
Object of its love: there was nothing able to
poſſeſſe her ſo fully, but that ſhe diverted her
eyes a thouſand times from it, to returne,
without any occaſion at all, to the continual
ſearch of the ſubject of her thoughts; I confeſſe
freely that I often obſerved great alteration
in her diſpoſition, inſomuch that
ſometimes ſhe made me diſtruſt my former
opinion, or feare that ſhe eſteemed me unworthy
of her affection, becauſe I ſhewed my

ſelfe, ſo little ſenſible of it: whereas, if on
the other ſide I had given her cauſe to perceive,
that my breaſt was poſſeſſed with another
more pleaſing care, it would have beene
as much, as if I had played to winne her hatred:
for women are naturally inclined to
fall from one externity to another; and betwixt
thoſe two of their love and hatred,
there is no medium: whatſoever they will,
they will abſolutely; and if happily it be not
granted at the very leaſt ſigne they give of
their will, there is no hope to excuſe it; and
on the contrary, they are all ready to proclaime
to the world the ſmall eſteeme they
make of it, and conſerve their owne intereſt
to the very prejudice of what they moſt
before loved. When once they have changed
their diſpoſition and affection, as they
give themſelves what opinion they pleaſe
of things paſt, ſo they endeavour in the end
to perſwade us that they have never beene:
But when they perceive that they cannot beguile
our ſences and judgement, at leaſt, as
they have loſt the affection of a thing, ſo
would they have us loſe the memory of it,
whereof we dare not ſo much as complaine;
for diſcretion oblieges us to ſilence,
becauſe their tyranny whereunto we attribute

all, hath ſo wonne upon us, that the very
truth it ſelfe would be alwayes imputed to
errour and vanity. But by good chance
Stenobea had neither leaſure nor opportunity
to come by the repentance of it, or make
me taſte her rigours; for I kept my ſelfe alwayes
upright in the termes of the duty
and honour I was oblieged to render her,
yet ſo, that nothing could thereby be alleadged
againſt me, in prejudice of my conſtancy,
or the vowes I had made to bee Diana's
ſervant for ever. And although Stenobea
was ſuch a one, as onely the affection
of a goddeſſe was to bee eſteemed above
hers, and that it is hard to be loved of the
moſt amiable creature of the world, without
growing very ſenſible thereof; yet I had ſo
much power of my ſelfe, as that I was no
way touched or moved with her love; yet
very much with her griefe, and the ſorrow
I had, for not being able to requite her
with the like affection: O ſubject worthy of
a farre better acknowledgment, and of an
affection as loyall and ſincere as her owne!
whom, neither my Captivity, nor inevitable
Death, nor the whole multitude of
juſt reaſons which aſſaulted her, would
ever be able to make her change concluſion.

Have I not cauſe to curſe the day
wherein I found Diana ſo ready to give
me teſtimony of her good will, and promiſe
me her favours; ſince that now, when
ſhe hath made me contemne and deſpiſe
all things, ſhe beares me to the contempt
and loſſe of my ſelfe.
               The end of the Fourth Booke.
            
            
               
               ENDYMION.
               The Fifth Booke.
               
                  WHilſt I thus feaſted my Spirit
with theſe delights, and entertained
my ſelfe chiefely with
the hope of a ſight of Diana, I
was ſuddainly amazed, perceiving my ſelfe
not knowing any thing thereof, at the even
of the Feaſt, every one was buſie in preparing
things neceſſary againſt the next morrow;
decking the Temple and Altars, and
ſcouring the Veſſels with ſalt, and ſulphure:
there was nothing to be ſeene but Baskets

with flowers and branches of Pine-trees;
moſt of the women and maidens were buſied
in making of Garlands, and Poſies of
flowers; ſome prepared Incence, and all
manner of ſweete Odours, others the ſacred
Veſtments and Ornaments: for albeit
theſe people contenting themſelves with
what their fertile ſoyle naturally produces,
entertaine little or no commerce at
all, contemning forraigne Riches: yet
through the great number of Devotions
and Oblations, which the Kings and people
of the bordering Provinces doe daily bring
and offer to this goddeſſe: they doe appeare
at their Sacrifices with great luſtre and magnificence:
As for me, I rejoyced in the hope
I had to ſee every thing in its pompe. But
when I beheld the Harts and Bulls with golden
Hornes, and an infinite number of other
Sacrifices, I little thought that I my ſelfe was
to be the principall piece: Obſerving that
Stenobia's Chariot was preparing, and that
ſhe was to execute a part of the function: I
ſought all opportunityes of ſeeing her, and
that with more greedy paſſion than uſuall,
being more moved thereunto by this new
ſtate which was providing for her; and a
little inward griefe I had conceived by not

having not ſeene her of late, ſo frequently
as J was wont. But whether it were too
hard a taske, and ſevere conſtraint to her to
ſee mee ignorant of the approaching period
whereunto I was deſigned, and not give teſtimony
of the compaſſion ſhe was poſſeſſed
withall; or whether ſhee were over-buſie:
So it was, that I having beene deprived of
her ſight all the reſt of the day, and having
with great impatience ſuffered that privation;
I caſt my ſelfe upon the faire bed (this
time as the laſt) which ſhee had provided
for me from the beginning; where I could
heare, ſpecially by night, the leaſt noiſe that
ſtirred in her Chamber, which joyned to
mine. I had by chance paſſed the better
halfe of the night in a very ſound and
pleaſing repoſe; and the Bird of the day
had ſcarce once invited the approach of
Aurora by his ſhrill-tun'd call: when as hearing
a noyſe at the doore, I ſtarted up, and
drawing the Curtaine a little a ſide to ſee
what the matter was; I ſaw a little boy enter
my Chamber, with a Torch of Virgin-waxe
in his hand, and behind him a ſlave,
which ſet upon the Table a Veſſell filled
with the water of Purification, and a branch
of Pine; for in that Countrey the ſlaves

                  
                     C de Pas inuen.
                      I Picart fecit.
                  
                  
have the ſpeciall charge of ſacred things.
Preſently I perceived ſome more of them
appeare, in the middeſt whereof was Timetes,
who taking the branch, did therewith
ſprinkle a fine light dew upon me, with no
leſſe reverence than ordinarily it rendred to
the gods and their Altars; then, drawing
neere me he uttered theſe words.
               We have hitherto obſerved the great advantages,
Endymion; which the gods have
vouchſafed unto thee above other men;
but there is yet ſomething remaining which
muſt be done, ere thy glory can bee brought
to perfection, and this is the ſolemne day
wherein we are to ſee the ſtrongeſt proofes
of thy generous courage: wherein wee have
nothing to deſire, but that thou appeare alwayes
like thy ſelfe: great mindes never
yeeld to the aſſaults of the ſtrongeſt adverſities,
or encounter any thing greater than
than themſelves: and to ſuch all humane
accidents ſeeme ſo ſlight, that they diſdaine
to live for them: If then neither labour or
toyle can daunt them, or ſorrow wring
plaints from their mouths, what is it that
can terrifie them in death, whom ſo many
vertuous men diſpiſe, ſo many alſo even contemne,
and with all men muſt once ſuffice?

The Oracles which have proceeded from
thine owne mouth, have taught us that
thou art farre more worthy of Heaven than
of Earth, and that the goddeſſe hath made
choyſe of thee above all others, as the
moſt deare and gratefull Oblation wee can
preſent on her Altar. And this is the
cauſe why we have alwaies ſo honored thee,
for which we ſhall be amply recompenſed, if
thou but this day beare thy ſelfe conſtantly,
and not feare, or ſeeme unwilling to ſhorten
thy life, to give ſo great and large an increaſe
to thy fame: Juſtifie then both thy
ſelfe and us; and (if I may dare to ſay ſo) juſtifie
the goddeſſe her ſelfe in the choyſe ſhe
hath made of thee, and we ſhall be all oblieged
to celebrate eternally the memory of
thee, as of one, whoſe life and behaviour
hath rendred ſo deare to the gods, and his
death ſo wholeſome to men. This day is
to thee, Endymion, the moſt happy of all other,
as that wherein thou art to have ſo many
witneſſes of thy glory; when thou ſhalt
ſhew them that they doe not ſo much conduct
thee to death, as to immortality; make
it therefore appeare, that thou art not onely
a man, but that thou haſt a great reſemblance
of the gods themſelves, who will

bereave men of thy Company. At theſe
words they all obſerved attentively what geſture
I would uſe, and tooke ſpeciall notice
of my firſt Motions; which I laboured to overcome
as much as lay in me: for what
man is able (without ſome change) to heare
the report of my extraordinary and unthought
of accident, whether it concerne
him or no, and though hee neither gather
thence any particular cauſe of joy or ſorrow?
Beſides, Death is of it ſelfe alwayes
hideous and terrible, in what ſoothing
forme ſoever it be repreſented: yet I, preſently
reſolving, thus anſwered them. Is it
then for Diana's ſake that I muſt this day
dye? Yes ſonne, anſwered Timetes, it is for
her, the faireſt, the greateſt, and the beſt
of all the goddeſſes. Whoſoever, replyed I,
hath beene judged worthy to dye for Diana,
hath lived but too happily: it is the moſt
gratefull tydings you could have brought
me: doubt not at all of mee, for my reſolution
is already taken, whet your knives and
freely drench them in my blood, powre it
it out even to the laſt droppe for her ſake,
and cover her Altar with the Crimſon dye
thereof: for I am ſo farre from being
troubled or amazed with the feare of it,

that I doe with longing expect the houre.
This day, ſayes he, is yet wholly thine, and
howbeit the Sacrifices of the Celeſtiall Deities
are uſually celebrated in the preſence of
the Sunne, yet we are by ſome ſecret Fate
appoynted to attend the night, to the end
that this may be rendred more famous by
the honour of the goddeſſes preſence, of
which ſecret Fate we cannot gheſſe the cauſe,
except it bee, that thou art the moſt deare
and moſt acceptable of all the Sacrifices
that ever have beene offered to her. Bee
of good cheere then Sonne, ſayes Timetes,
kiſſing and embracing me; for indeede wee
held it fit to give thee knowledge of it, to
the end thou mighteſt be the better prepared.
Goe, goe your wayes ſaid I, and provide
for the reſt, as for me, I will be ſooner
ready than you, and the delay of my death
will bee more tedious to me than the death
it ſelfe.
               Thus they left me, looking one upon another,
letting looſe ſome ſighes and teares.
Ah Stenobea! ſaid I then to my ſelfe, is it for
this that thou hiddeſt thy ſelfe yeſterday?
haſt thou had the heart to refuſe me thy
preſence onely on the laſt day, as if I had
ſome ſuite to begge at thy favour: By this

anticipated and untimely bereaving me of
one of the ſweeteſt contentments of my
life, thou art the firſt that beginnes to kill
me. And thou Iſmena, what is become of
all thy promiſes? is this the care thou
wilt take of me: It may be that thou eſteemeſt
not thy ſelfe oblieged to afford me ſuccour,
ſince I demanded not any at thy
hands: But whatſoever thou oweſt not to
my deſire herein, thou oweſt at leaſt to thine
owne promiſe; whereof, if thou labour not
to render me performance, thou remaineſt
no leſſe guilty: Alas! this ſavage and
Barbarous people have pitty on my Fate;
thoſe that are to kill me, bemoane me, and
even he who is appoynted to give mee the
ſad ſtroake, kiſſes me, and embraces me with
the ſame armes that are to plunge the knife
deepe in my blood, and open my Bowels;
and yet all theſe things will not procure me
at the hands of Diana the leaſt ſigne of
Compaſſion: ſhe remaines unmoved, and
makes as ſlight account of my death as my
life.
               Is the Altar the place then Diana, where
I muſt be preſented to thee, to gaine thy
favour, and receive the effects of thy promiſes:
muſt they be ſought in the Stygian
                  
waters, and through the ſtreames of blood
and teares? Is this the way to goe take poſſeſſion
of a place amongſt the ſtarres? and
can we not without forſaking the apparrell
of this mortall and earthly body, arrive at
the honour of Heaven, or ſhare in the glory
of the gods? Oh no, I perceive the
myſtery of thy deſigne, thou haſt onely
given me verball promiſes, whereof I in
vaine retaine thy memory, ſince thou art
reſolved to take away my hope and life together;
to the end to drowne all thoſe particulars
in everlaſting oblivion. Thou repenteſt
thee for having favoured me with
too much affection: but although thou killeſt
me, thou ſhalt not have power to make
me repent my over-loyall adoring thee:
And although thine affection to mee, bee
wholly blotted out of thine heart, yet thou
ſhalt not be able to baniſh it thy memory,
which, againſt thy will, will ſatisfie mee,
with a continuall reproaching and remonſtrance
of thy fickleneſſe and ingratitude.
Adde yet ſome new torture to my death, &amp;,
ſo it be pleaſing to thee, be ſure I will embrace
it as a peculiar felicity: At leaſt, how
great ſoever thou be amongſt the goddeſſes,
I ſhall have juſt ground to boaſt my ſelfe of

having ſomething more great, and divine
than thou, when I ſhall have witneſſed a
greater conſtancy.
               Whilſt I uttered thoſe words with a low
voyce, and a reſolved, but grieved minde,
the ſighes and ſobs of Stenobea, piercing the
walls betwixt my Chamber and hers came
to mine eares; ſuddainly impoſing ſilence
upon me, that I might give eare to a lamentation,
which was to prove ſo deare to me,
and which more deplored my calamity than
my ſelfe. How is it poſſible that I can this
day behold with drye eyes ſo tragicke and
lamentable a ſpectacle? and that I muſt aſſiſt,
and as it were conſent to an action ſo
ſo cruell and ſo averſe to my life and tranquility:
and that I muſt beare a part in the
execution: O Endymion, Endymion, pardon
mee I beſeech thee, and know that in
the deſigne I had of delivering thee, I
have a great while forgotten my duty both
to my Countrey, and my ſelfe, that I might
render thee that which I never owed thee,
for who ever ſaw any love ſo loyally as I,
having utterly nothing to expect of my love,
ſhould I onely have turned mine eyes on a
perſon penſive, ſolitary, and poſſeſſed with
ſome other thoughts, which I could not

conceive or comprehend, and who onely
reſpected me ſo farre as ſuperficiall civility,
and a kind of generall cuſtome of honouring
my Sexe obliged him? But alas▪ it is now
time to bewayle, rather than accuſe thee:
know then, that if thou this day receive the
mortall ſtroke, I ſhall beare the greateſt
part in the ſuffering, thou onely wilt endure
the violence for a moment, but I ſhall thereby
feele an immortall ſorrow. O Endymion!
why have not the Oracles ſet me in thy
place? why cannot I be accepted there? at
leaſt, why may not I have leave to dye with
thee, ſince my misfortune will not permit
me to live with thee? And thou ô Goddeſſe,
ſo great and powerfull, what advantage wil
redound to thee from a Diſaſter, whereunto
thou mayeſt with ſo much facility apply a
remedy? Doth the glory and felicity which
environs thee, ſtand in want of our affliction,
to render them more compleat? or doe
they reape any advancement or perfection
from our ſorrows and torments? Or if our
ſuperſtition offer thee more than thou requireſt,
ſuffer not our errour to continue longer,
nor force not me, by this act of inhumanity,
which hath no other object than thy
ſervice, to witneſſe more reſentment and

pitty than thy ſelfe: Content thee with a
milder ſacrifice, and chooſe inſtead of Endymion,
ſome Hinde, or ſome one of thoſe
ſtragling Oxen, marked with the Lampe,
and which are conſecrated to thee in Perſia,
and live unprofitably on the bankes of Euphrates;
whilſt the moſt exquiſite of men are
ſacrificed to thee: or if thou loveſt one of
theſe better, receive my life for his: In this
caſe death will be exceeding welcome to me,
whether thou doſt appoint it me in recompence
of the ſervices I have done thee, or for
my puniſhment, for having eſteemed thee
too cruell. Thus did poore Stenobea lament,
and the exceſſe of her griefe not being able to
be ſmothered, or retained within the limits
of any reſpect, made her powre forth more
teares than words. It was a great honour
to me Pyzander, to be thus bewailed, and
yet a greater affliction to ſee her thus torment
her ſelfe; and both theſe extreames
together did ſo comfort me, in torturing
me, that finding my ſelfe thus bewailed, I
could have beene loth to have dyed: I had a
perfect cauſe to eſteeme Death ſweet, both
for that I was to be offered to Diana, and
bewailed by Stenobea; but all thoſe paſſages
were onely as the firſt ſignes of her deſpaire.
               
                  
By this time it was broad day, and the
houre of ariſing being come, I ſaw enter,
not the Slaves, which were wont to ſerve
me, for they kept themſelves farther from
me, rendring me no other duty than that
of their teares; but one of thoſe who had the
prime charge of ſacred things, who brought
me garments whiter than Snow, the ſmell
whereof exceeded the ſweeteſt perfumes of
Sabea, and the delights of the Aſſyrians;
and having preſented them to me with greater
reſpect and reverence, than if it had
beene to the greateſt Monarch of the earth,
hee preſently retired; for now the time entered
wherein Stenobea was to execute her
Function: But beſides that it is the uſuall
cuſtome of Maidens, to bee long making
them ready, chiefly on ſuch daies as they are
to put on their faireſt Ornaments, there is
no doubt but her ſorrow rendered her yet
more ſlow; for ſhee made them expect her a
good while, and at length appeared in
more magnificence and pompe than ever I
had ſeene her, dreſſed as it ſeemed by the
hands of the Graces, who had not forgotten
to beautifie her Treſſes with all the
formes of adornment that Venus had taught
them, to decke her head with the moſt precious

ſtones, or crowne it with the moſt
beautifull Flowers: Then I perceived and
knew her, whom at firſt I had ſo much adoe
to call to minde, and whom I formerly
had ſeene in my Viſion in the ſacred Forreſt,
and who ſeemed never to bee appointed
to appeare before me in the Equipage of
her Attracts, but either to condemne me, or
put me to death. I knew her by the rich
dreſſings of her head, her Girdle of Gold
and Emeralds, and her Gowne embrodered
with Flowers, the ground whereof was
a kind of white ſtuffe, fine, and ſhining,
which the Nymphs who inhabite the ſhores
of Phaſis doe make, of the fineſt wooll in the
world; ſhee wanted nothing to render her
wholly the ſame, that appeared to me in the
Forreſt, but the Knife ſhe had in her hand,
which alſo ſhe had when we came before the
Altar: But I could not any where about her
perceive the branch of Myrtle ſhe had made
me cut, and which ſhee had promiſed to
weare for my ſake. What! ſayes Pyzander,
diddeſt not thou ſee that which was moſt viſible
in her? why, this her extreame but
fruitleſſe, and vaine love of thee was the
true Myrtle, which was to flouriſh long, and
remaine greene in her breſt, yet without

hope of any fruit. This was not like the love
of Thetis (ſayes Endymion) the day ſhee
married Peleus, nor like that of her who
waites upon the Table of the Gods; the day
that by Junoes owne hand ſhe was preſented
to Hercules. And howbeit poore Stenobea
being then more moved than ever, had no
ſtedfaſt colour, but in one inſtant often
bluſhed and waxed pale againe, and bore all
the tokens of ſorrow, vively repreſented in
her face; yet her beauty ſhined in deſpight
of her affliction, the teares upon her cheeks
reſembled the Morning-dew on the bluſhing
Roſes, whereunto her very griefe ſeemed
to adde ſome new grace. She was followed
of ſome of her moſt faithfull Companions,
all gentile and properly accoutred,
and of Maids who carried the Ornaments
wherewith ſhee was to apparrell me. The
firſt thing ſhee did, ſhe beſprinkled me as
Timetes had done before, with ſome few
drops of water, which were preſently followed
with a whole Torrent of her teares.
She no ſooner began to put the Purple-vaile
over mine eyes, and bind it upon mine
haire with a trembling hand, but that her
heart, ſwolne with affliction and bitterneſſe,
over-flowes more than ever with teares and

ſighes. Shee hath neither power, or commandement
more of her ſelfe, and her reaſon
loſing its abſolute power, ſorrow gives
it ſelfe liberty. In vaine doe the poore Maydens
labour to make her compoſe her ſelfe againe,
their owne pitty and compaſſion prevailing
ſo farre on them, that they are like
to fall into the ſame diſtemper; which reſpect
obliged me to ſpeake thus to her.
               What meanes this Stenobea, art thou come
here to afflict me? Haſt thou more pitty, than
either my ſelfe or Diana have of me? for, by
as much as I ſee, if thou wert in her place, perchance
I ſhould not die. Hitherto my reſolution
hath forbidden me to wonder, aud
thou alone doeſt now trouble me; let me, I
pray thee, die in peace, and be contented,
that I tell thee, I doe more pitty thy ſuffering,
than feare mine owne, and ſhould not
be ſenſible of death it ſelfe, but that thine
affliction makes me feele it; and Fate is in
no reſpect cruell to me, but in afflicting thy
beauty for my ſake: If thou continue thus,
thou wilt make me die more than once: O
Stenobea, reſerve my life and blood for the
Altar, and powre them not out before
hand in thy ſighes and teares.
               I had no ſooner ſpoken the firſt word,

but ſhe redoubled her former lamentations,
in ſuch ſort, that my deſire of comforting
her, ſeemed to give addition to her ſorrow:
When I had finiſhed, ſhe would have ſpoken,
but had not the power, by reaſon of
the exceſſe of griefe wherewith ſhe was travailed:
At length (like as after one violent
undertaking we cannot enterpriſe another
without ſome intervall of repoſe) ſo
ſhe, having dryed her eyes, at great leaſure,
began very coldly to re-imbrace her duty,
and drawing nearer to me, began ſometimes
one thing, ſometimes another, but could finiſh
nothing; for being tranſported, and
wholly ſeized with the deſpaire which before
had deprived her of her ſpeech, ſhe loſt alſo
at length the eaſe of teares and ſighes, having
nothing left her but ſilent ſobs, to teſtifie
that there remained ſome little life, but
great griefe within her: Inſomuch that ſhe,
leaning upon my bed, the others were faine
to put their hands to the worke: ſome of
which told me, Alas! ſhee hath done her
uttermoſt endeavour to cauſe ſome other
to be put into thy place; wherein ſhee
hath beene ſo ſerious, that ſhee hath
not for forborne to conſult with old
Women, whoſe Art and Experience ſhee

thought might have furniſhed her with
ſome invention to this effect: Beſides, that
her feare was ſomewhat diminiſhed, by the
hope was given her by a whiſpering report
amongſt the ſlaves, who, all with one accord
ſeemed to propheſie, that the courſe of
the Sacrifices ſhould be altered, and that the
Goddeſſe, as being her ſelfe a Virgin, required
a Virgin for Sacrifice; but could not
notwithſtanding all this, finde any meanes
for thy deliverance, ſhe calls ſaid I, the expoſing
me to a thouſand torments, my deliverance;
No, no, ſaid I, ſince the Moone is
growne weary of ſeeing me, ſo I am alſo
weary of ſeeing the Sunne; but they tooke
no notice of my meaning herein, being
three or foure houres together buſie to
dreſſe me in ſundry colours, and binding
my head, mine armes, and every part with
a thouſand different Flowers and Ribonds.
After this Stenobea, being a little come to
her ſelfe, through the multitude of importunate
requeſts, and remonſtrances they
made her, paſſed ſlightly with her hand
and eye over all thoſe things, and ſo taking
a ſmall Violl of precious Oyle, ſhe powred
it upon my head, and for concluſion crowned
me with a Garland, which ſhe her ſelfe
had prepared for me.
               
                  
The Sunne having done the moiety of his
courſe, the multitude expected me in Jupiters
Temple, where the people aſſembled,
and were to goe thence unto the high places,
which were a good way within the Forreſt,
and where the yearely Sacrifice was celebrated.
Then came Timetes, in a more venerable
and grave manner than uſuall, with
his Turbant, which ſparkled with the number
of Jewells that were therein, and a Cloak
of the Phrigian faſhion, which covered him
from the head to the feete: His other chiefe
miniſters with their Coronets of Flowers,
and all their ſacred Ornaments, came with
him to fetch me, and brought me to the
Temple, where with voices and Inſtruments
they made an excellent Harmony, untill
I was conſecrated before the Altars,
where uſually the Sacrifices were offered, in
the preſence of the Images of their gods, Jupiter,
the Sunne, and the Moone; where the
eyes of the whole Aſſembly were fixed upon
me: on the one ſide ſtood all the men, from
the higheſt to the loweſt, and on the other
ſide the women, where the Mothers, the
new married, and the Maidens, expoſed
their richeſt and faireſt Ornaments to the
publick view. From thence wee were to

part preſently, and goe towards the high
Altar; whither the remainder of the day was
little enough for our March: yea, but Endymion,
ſayes Pyzander, thou paſſeſt this very
ſlightly over, doe they goe ſo without
order, or any pompe to their Sacrifices, and
is there nothing in their whole Ceremony
and State worth the paines of Remembrance?
Thou mayſt well thinke Pyzander
ſayes Endymion, that I could not be ſo curious
a Spectator, being my ſelfe the greateſt
part of the Spectacle, yet I will give thee
briefly an accompt of what I was able to obſerve.
               Thoſe who carried the Holy Water, the
Banners, and the Images of their gods, marched
foremoſt, according to the Cuſtome;
next unto them were led all the Sacrifices, amongſt
which were great numbers of black
and white Bulls, which amply witneſſed
the fertility of the Countrey by the largeneſſe
of their limbes; having faire Heads,
ſtrong Hornes, and unmeaſurable broad
and long backs: in a word, juſt like thoſe
which the Aegyptians worſhip, all worthy
of the Rape of Europa, and to be ranked
amongſt the Celeſtiall Signes; yet I cannot
tell thee, whether there were more or

leſſe of them than an Hecatombe: But well
could I diſcerne about an Hundred or ſixe
ſcore Maidens following them, ſome whereof
carryed Baskets full of flowers and fruits,
other Myrrhe, Incenſe, and other Aromaticke
Drugs, in ſuch abundance, that all the
adjacent places were perfumed withall. It
was a pleaſure to ſee them with their baſkets
upon their heads, their locks ſpred upon
their ſhoulders, by a gentle gale of winde
that then blowed, their hands on their ſides,
and their tall and ſtraight ſtature, with their
robes and bodies of ſeverall colours; in a
word, they were ſuch as Ceres, or Pomena,
would gladly have choſen, than to have bin
the bearers of ſome Preſent of their faireſt
fruits to the gods and goddeſſes. After this
followed Stenobea, (the ſole honour of all
the Troope) borne on high above the reſt,
in a Chariot painted with Azure, enamelled
with ſundry rich colours, &amp; drawne by two
Harts, with ſilvered heads; round about her
marched twelve Virgins, choſen out of the
faireſt of all the reſt, &amp; were the moſt gorgeouſly
apparrelled and decked, as was poſſible
to be imagined, bearing Bowes and arrows
like Diana's Nymphs: The players on the
Flute, Bag-pipe, Harpe, &amp; Viall, never ceaſed
betwixt her &amp; me, who came after, mounted

upon the Chariot of the Moone; for ſo doe
they tearme the Chariot, whereon, for accompliſhment
of all honour and reſpect,
they make thoſe mount, that are to be ſacrificed;
whence they have a Proverb, which
they often rehearſe to ſuch amongſt them as
want courage, chiefly againſt their Slaves;
which is, Alas! thou needeſt not feare, thou
ſhalt never bee ſet upon the Chariot of the
Moone. In effect it is a Type of the goddeſſes
owne Chariot, being one halfe of Ivory,
the other of Ebony, and in like manner
drawne by two Horſes, the one white,
the other blacke. Here it was that I was exalted
above all the reſt of the Troope, and
ſeemed rather in the ſtate of a tryumphing
Conquerour, than of a Sheepe led to the
ſlaughter, or a ſacrifice to the Altar. The
whole flower of the youth in their proudeſt
and moſt ſumptuous accouſtrements, followed,
marching on both ſides of me, and
behind me followed divers yong men bearing
Crownes of Pine, choſen from amongſt
the Slaves, whereof they uſually take the
beſt inſpired to ſerve for publick Sacrifices,
and the others to take charge of the ſacred
things: they ſeemed tranſported with a kind
of rage, for beſides their continuall dancing

                  
                     C pas. in
                  
                  
and leaping, they murmured a certaine
ſtrange kind of Oracles, ſinging ſometimes
praiſes to the Goddeſſe, under different
names, according to the places of her reſidence,
the Functions ſhe exerciſes, and the
Countries of their owne Birth; ſo that at every
other word I heard them name Diana
Ortigia, or of Delos, Diana of Caphria, Diana
of Epheſus, Diana of Perga, Schithia, Ecbatana,
Alphea, Mynthia, Ilithia, Lucina,
Latonia, Cynthia, Artemis, Dictina, and
by a thouſand other names, wherewith ſhe
hath made her ſelfe famous throughout the
world. Amongſt the laſt appeared good old
Timetes, riding upon a little pyed Nag,
which it ſeemed the Moone had ſent him, and
that the Day and the Night had given him
ſo equall a diſtribution of their ſeverall colours,
that to have ſeene him on one ſide
onely, one would have thought him wholly
black, or wholly white: After him followed
the State, of the principall and moſt honourable
men, followed of the multitude,
and behind them againe all the women promiſcuouſly.
               Now, by reaſon of their ſlow March, it
grew late, and the Sun was entred a good
way into the Ocean, when wee firſt entred

the Forreſt, and before we came to the high
places, the day had forſaken us: From
thence wee could ſee the City of Alba, as
from this Mount Lathmos we can that of Heraclea;
and the Forreſt under us, ſeemed like
a waved valley. There, in the middeſt of a
large Plaine, is a faire and ſpacious Altar, a
reverend Teſtimony of the devotion of the
Ancients, horrible and frightfull in reſpect
of the Forreſt it ſelfe; and is not higher raiſed,
than even with the Earth, the place it
ſelfe being ſo high, that nothing can hinder
it from the firſt and immediate beame of the
Moones light. Thither doe repaire, to
render their moſt ſolemne vowes to the
Goddeſſe, not onely the Inhabitants of Albania,
but alſo many of the neighbouring
peoples, as thoſe of Armenia, and Colchos,
the Iberians and Nomades, even from Palus
Meotis, to the Caſpian Sea.
               By this time the Slaves had ranged themſelves
on the ſides, making a Lane betwixt
them for me to paſſe to the Altar, where
round about were more than a thouſand
Torches burning, and the people began to
place themſelves in every quarter: Onely
Stenobea, who was more ſlow and backward
ſtaid behind, by her Chariot, from which

ſhe was but newly alighted, I knew not what
was the cauſe of her delay, neither could I
diſcerne it for the Damoſell that waited upon
her that day, like Nymphs upon Diana,
kept themſelves alwayes ſo cloſe, and neare
about her, that I could not ſo much as ſee
her: It ſeemed to me, that either they were
very attentive to the obſervation of ſome
new adventure, or the diſcourſe of ſome
ſubject which they had not beene accuſtomed
to heare. In the meane time Timetes
and his chiefe miniſters, came and took me,
and as they were leading me to the Altar, Iſmene
came into my thought; inſomuch that
I ſaid to my ſelfe, O Iſmene, Iſmene, thy
helpe is ſlow, and whereſoever thou beeſt,
thine Art muſt be powerfull, to deliver me
from the hands of this people: What honour
or advantage wilt thou acquire, by having
enterpriſed that which thou art not able to
accompliſh; or to have promiſed that which
thou hadſt no intention to performe? If I
accuſe thee wrongfully, God knows, and
thine owne conſcience can witneſſe. It is not
that I any more deſire thine aide, as not
troubling me much about it; for that thou
maiſt know it touches me leſſe than thyſelfe.
I here declare, that I would bee ſorry thou

ſhouldeſt this day prove conſtant, and that
my Fate is ſo anſwerable to my deſires, that
I am farre leſſe troubled with the death I am
going to, than amazed at thy diſſembling:
At length I was brought before the Altar,
where I ſtood with a grave &amp; ſtedfaſt countenance,
and ſhewing more promptitude
towards death than even the moſt contented,
are wont to embrace increaſe of dayes
withall. Sorrow preſented her ſelfe before
me in all her different formes, for which
way ſoever I turned me, I could perceive
nothing but teares, or heare any thing but
ſighes and ſobs: Every one bemoaned me,
but my ſelfe, and there was not one of them
all more willing to live, than I was to dye.
Then they all at once lifting up their voices,
and ſung (as it were the beginning of mine
obſequies) certaine ſad and mournfull
Hymnes, in a pitteous and lamenting Tone,
whilſt I addreſſing all my vowes to Heaven;
where I continually kept mine eyes fixed,
(which had beene long accuſtomed to the
contemplation of the Moone) who then
aſcended the Horizon, more beautifull and
cleare, than ever I had before ſeene her; to
whom the noiſe of their ſong gave me reſpit
to utter theſe words inſtead of prayer: Haſten,

oh inconſtant Goddeſſe, to give thy
preſence to the moſt acceptable Sacrifice
that ever I ſhall be able to render thee; and
looke at leaſt with a gracious eye on my
death, ſince thou makeſt ſo ſmall account
of my life: Then my deſire of giving mine
eyes their laſt farewell of Stenobea, made me
looke a little downwards, where I ſaw her
cloſe by me, and a little behind Timetes: Alas
I ſaw her, but fairer, and better compoſed
than ſhe was wont; whether it were that in
the preſence of this ſo great an aſſembly ſhee
governed her carriage, and uſed more power
over her paſſion, than ſhe had done formerly,
or that misfortune which makes us diſtruſtfull
of every thing, did then beget that error
and opinion in me for an increaſe of my affliction;
howſoever it were, ſhe ſeemed not
the ſame perſon, who before had ſhed ſo
many teares: But on the contrary, looking
firmely upon me with dry and reſolute
eyes, ſhee ſeemed to be another Atropos,
holding the Knife in her hand, (not to
cut any more branches of Myrtle, but
the thred of my Life) the ſharpneſſe whereof
was ſo ſubtile, and well prepared, that
it was in a manner undiſcernable;
ſhee ſeemed very ready, or rather

                  
                  
haſtily deſirous to preſent it to her Uncle;
I knew not who had thus counſailed her,
but ſhe was ſo farre from ſhewing any remainder
or token of ſorrow in her demeanour,
that both in her face and actions appeared
teſtimonies, if not of joy, yet at
leaſt of moderation: O ye gods ſaid I, what
change is this! ſhe, who but lately ſeemed
inconſolable, and wholly bent upon the ſaving
of my Life, is ſo ſuddenly become
ſo reſolute, and ſeemes to long to ſee
me diſpatched. O fraile Sexe! thou haſt
ſpilt all thy ſorrow in thy Teares, thy lamentations
were too violent to be of any
long continuance, and were onely of
force to kill me with ſorrow: but ſince
they are ſo ſoone paſſed, let us now dye
free of care, or the conſent of Stenobea,
to whom our very Deſtiny already ſeemes
to be ſlow.
               With this they made an end of their
Songs, and I expecting every moment the
fatall ſtroke, lifted up mine eyes againe towards
the Moone: And Stenobea gave the
Knife to Timetes, who had no ſooner looked
upon it, but turning ſuddenly towards
her, what doeſt thou meane Stenobea,
ſayes he, and what doſt thou here give

me? are we wont to uſe ſuch Knives in our
Sacrifices? why this is ſo weake and ſo light,
that me thinkes I have nothing in my hand;
from whence proceeds this Novelty? Aſke
this Woman, anſwered Stenobea, that
ſtands heere, who will tell thee ſtrange
things thereof: Hereupon I turning my
ſelfe to ſee who this might be, to my great
amazement and wonder ſaw it was Iſmene,
who thus began to ſpeake.
               You ſhall know Oh Prieſt, and people of
Albania, that the Goddeſſe being the other
day on Hunting in the Countrey of the
Cimmerians, tooke occaſion to goe and repoſe
her ſelfe with one of the gods of that
Countrey, who in a Banquet gave her a
taſte of thoſe rare and delightfull Cates
where with hee is wont to charme the cares
both of the gods an men. Afterwards
having ſhewed her in his Dens and Caves,
as in another World, the Magazin of all
manner of Rarities, he preſented her with
one of the Knives wherewith hee takes
his Recreation, and cuts what hee pleaſes
in his Nocturnall Exerciſes; ſaying,
what more proper or fitter Preſent
can I bee able to make to thee Oh
Goddeſſe, who art ſo great a Lover of

Hunting, then the beſt Knife that ever
our Vulcan made with his owne hand,
where with thou maiſt cut downe all
things that hinders thee, and make thine
owne way through the thickeſt forreſts.
This gift was infinitely gratefull to
the Goddeſſe, the more, becauſe it was neatly
made, light, and fit for her hand: but
through a miſchance, ſhe had no ſooner taken
it, but going to feele the edge of it
with the thumbe of her left hand, ſhe could
not ſo gently touch it, by reaſon of the
ſharpe and ſubtile edge of it, but that ſhe
cut her finger that ſome drops of blood followed;
which he perceiving ſaid, Alas, Goddeſſe,
I gave it thee not for that uſe: I beleeve
it well, ſaid ſhee, but ſince it is ſo greedy
of blood, I will for thy ſake have it employed
in the moſt pleaſing and acceptable
Sacrifice that ever was made to me: herewith
ſaid Iſmene, ſhe gave it me, with command
to bring it hither, and preſent it, as
I have done, to the mayden that ſerves at
the Altar: Doubt not then to obey the
meſſage of the Goddeſſe, and then you ſhall
perceive, that obedience joyned with ſacrifice
is of force even to draw the Gods from
Heaven: for you ſhall preſently ſee her

come downe (if ye be not blinded) to gratifie
with a gracious acceptance, the Oblation
you offer her of this yong man.
               She had no ſooner ſaid this, but there was
preſently heard a confuſed murmur of different
voyces through the whole aſſembly; the
greater part whereof were rejoyced at this
alteration, as ſuppoſed it tended to my delivery:
but ſeeing me appoynted for death,
they re-entred into their former faſhion of
pitty and compaſſion. Now I leave thee
to judge whether I were a little amazed or
no, to ſee her, from whom onely I was to expect
life and delivery, carrying the Knife
wherewith I was to be killed. Then ſaid
Timetes with a loud voyce: O ye people
of Albania, lift up your eyes and hearts to
Heaven, and give thankes to the Goddeſſe
who this day is ſo carefull of you, &amp; your Sacrifices:
And then turning towards me, ſaid,
Endymion, whether thou haſt beene choſen
for the offence thou haſt committed, or
for the generoſity that is in thee, thou thy
ſelfe plainly ſeeſt what confirmation the
Goddeſſe gives to the election we have made
of thee: It is thy part now to carry thy ſelfe
with ſuch reſolution, as that we may have
no cauſe to repent us of having offered

thee, nor the Goddeſſe of having deſired
thee. I, whom the feare of death touched
farre leſſe than the offence, and ſuſpition I
had conceived of Stenobeas change; as in
thoſe extreames, the leaſt ſigne of diſloyalty
we diſcover in thoſe who have profeſſed
love to us, is farre more irkſome to us, than
whatſoever elſe can croſſe us. I could not
containe my ſelfe from ſpeaking thus to
him: Diddeſt thou not obſerve, ſaid I, Timetes,
that the Goddeſſe gave expreſſe command,
that the Knife ſhould be given to the
Virgin that ſerved at the Altar? wherefore
then doſt thou take it out of her hand, and
hinder her from killing me, who of her ſelfe
hath more deſire to doe it, than thou haſt?
and who appeares ſo reſolute? She will,
doubtleſſe, acquit her ſelfe better than thee,
and the Sacrifice will thereby be much bettered.
This is not carryed as thou imagineſt,
ſaies Timetes, neither is it the intention of
the Goddeſſe, or our cuſtome: The ſtroke
muſt be given, Endimon, by that perſon, who
of all the aſſembly, either doth, or ſhould
love thee beſt: Ah me! ſaid I then, it
muſt not be done by Stenobea: But ſhe, beholding
me with the eye of innocence and
amazement, was mightily ſurprized at my

uttering of theſe words; and her receiving
unjuſtly ſo great an injury from one whom
ſhe had alwayes ſo highly oblieged; and
to receive it in ſuch a manner, as that the opportunity
of juſtifying her ſelfe, was for ever
taken away, by my going to death with
this opinion, which ſo vively touched her
heart, that I did more and more perceive in
her the extreame griefe ſhe had hereupon
contracted; which alſo made her retire behind
Timetes; whether it were, that ſhe
would not ſee me any more, or that ſhe deſired
to cover the alteration which appeared
in her looke.
               In the meane time Timetes perceiving
that there was nothing wanting but my
death, to the accompliſhment of the ſacrifice,
lifting up his hand wherewith he held the
Knife, ſaid to me: Now is the time, Endymion,
wherein thou muſt give a notable
proofe of that excellent nature, which hath
beene cauſe thou haſt beene choſen by the
gods. He had no ſooner uttered theſe
words, but that ſuddainly there aroſe a great
murmuring amongſt the people that were
behind him, chiefly amongſt the Damoſells,
who were about Stenobea, ſome of which
haſtened to receive her in their armes, ſeeing

her falling downe, either dead, or in a ſwone,
griefe, deſpight, and choler all at once ſeized
her, and in ſuch a furious and violent manner
ſuffocated her ſpirits, that ſhe became
ſuddainly unable either to ſpeake or breath.
What ſacrifice have we here? ſaies poore
Timetes, who was utterly loſt and deſperate;
Doe the Gods on a ſuddaine require two in
ſtead of one? Endymion for the Moone, and
perchance Stenobea for the Sunne? Why
then am not I, wretched and miſerable
man, as acceptable to Iupiter, to the end, that
every one of our Gods may have a particular
Oblation? What became of me, Pyzander,
at the ſight of this dying beauty, when I diſcerned
the flower and ornament of the
whole aſſembly lying on the ground: Woe
is me, Stenobea, ſaid I, art thou then indeed
ſo ſenſible of mine unjuſt calumnies? and am
I ſo little touched with thy good offices?
Although I have not had juſt cauſe to beleeve
thy mutability, yet I have at leaſt had
ground for my ſuſpition of it: But in vaine
doe I confeſſe a fault, whereof I demand no
pardon; I juſt now deſired death at thy
Hands, and have ſince given it thee: How
ſhall I alone be able to ſuffice to the expiation
of ſo many crimes? Alas, I have neede

to have two lives, the one to offer for Diana,
the other to powre out for Stenobea: O
Stenobea, thou teacheſt me to dye, and I
long to follow thee, and my ſpirit in theſe
vaine lamentations loſes the opportunity of
accompanying thine: Then I became incenſed
againſt my ſelfe, and mine owne Fate:
and being growne wholly weary and impatient
of life, I thrice called upon Timetes,
but he heard me not, being on the other ſide
as buſie in the inceſſant calling upon her, as
his daughter, who indeed was onely his
Neece: and who, by what name ſoever hee
called her, was not able to make him any
manner of anſwer. At length, having by
continuall pulling him by the garment, gotten
him to turne towards me: Wherefore,
ſaid I, doſt thou loſe any more time about
her, on whom thou gaineſt nothing? or what
can thy care adde to her life, or contentment?
Doſt not thou know that it is unlawfull to
interrupt the ſacrifices of the gods for vaine
and unprofitable reſpects? wilt thou keepe
thoſe alive, whoſe death Diana requires?
what knoweſt thou but this may be a ſtroke
of her owne hand: ſeeſt thou not that ſhee
requires nothing but death on every ſide?
uſe then the knife ſhee hath ſent thee, and

keepe me no longer in languiſhing, who
am like to dye with a deſire and longing
for death.
               
                  Timetes preſſed with time, and mine importunity,
making a ſigne with his hand to
the whole aſſembly, to impoſe ſilence upon
the murmur was riſen, by reaſon of Stenobea's
accident, and to obliege every one to
the attention and reſpect he owed to the Sacrifice,
tooke the Knife by the Ebon-haft,
and preſented it to me. Which when I
beheld with amazement, not knowing what
he meant, and imagining that his mind was
exceedingly diſtempered in the occaſion:
How now Endymion, ſayes hee, haſt thou
not yet learned our Lawes and Cuſtomes?
knoweſt thou not, that our Sacrifices are
moſt happy, chiefly when the perſon ſacrificed
dyes cheerefully. Now wee, who
by the commandement of the Oracle, are
to offer men to the Goddeſſe, doe uſe no other
triall of their reſolution and conſtance,
to aſſure us of their willing acceptance of
death, than in engaging them to bee themſelves
the actors of it. This likes me well
Timetes, ſaid I, taking the Knife, I ſhall my
ſelfe farre better know where my life lyes
hidden, and ſhall not miſſe my heart at firſt

ſtroke: And ſo addreſſing my laſt words to
the Moone: O Goddeſſe, ſaid I, I have erred
I confeſſe; but my firme beleefe that the
gods are alwaies true, and not ſubject to
change, hath beene the cauſe of all mine errors.
This heart, the moſt true guardian
of that affection and loyalty, which hath
brought me where I now am, ſhall preſently
expiate the offence I have thereby committed.
Content thy ſelfe, O Goddeſſe, to
ſee, that having forgone all things for thy
ſake, I yet willingly lay downe my life, for
teſtimony that I am thine even unto the Altar,
and further, if it were poſſible. Having
finiſhed theſe diſcourſes, I ſtrooke the
Knife profoundly into my boſome, and
gave my ſelfe a ſtroke, which ſo ſuddainly
cut in ſunder the thred of my life, that I had
onely ſo much ſence left me, as to heare a pittifull
lamentation of many thouſand confuſed
voyces, juſt in the inſtant as I fell downe
upon the Altar.
               What is this thou telleſt me Endymion,
ſayes Pyzander, taking him by the hand, if
from the beginning I had not embraced
thee, and did not ſtill touch thee, I ſhould
rather thinke it were a Ghoſt than a man
that now ſpeakes to me. I doe not my

ſelfe know, ſayes Endymion, what I am, and
therefore thou ſhalt doe me a great pleaſure,
if thou ſeeſt farther into my adventures than
my ſelfe, to give me ſome light; there is yet
ſomething more ſad and tragicall therein,
there is yet another ſacrifice, &amp; another Prieſt;
for I do beleeve that the gods, obſerving the
ſmal eſteem I have made of death, &amp; of whatſoever
is therein moſt terrible, are againe reſolved
to inforce me to live, intending to be
more cruell to me, and keepe me in a continuall
torment with the ſorrow and anguiſh,
wherewith I am poſſeſſed, for having bin the
cauſe of another more ſtrange &amp; lamentable
ſacrifice. What ſacrifice can that be, ſaies Pyzander,
or what more ſtrange accident canſt
thou recount unto me? O Endymion, there
are many thouſand and broad waies to goe
out of this life, but ſcarce any one for return.
How then, ſayes Endymion, have I found it,
without ſeeking, and how am I returned to
my ſelfe, that ſo little deſired it? O ſweet, but
too ſhort death? who, or what hindred me
from ſeeing the Kingdome of the Ghoſts?
was it the ſad and drowſie Lord, or the inexorable
Judges? and that from thence I attained
not the Eliſian fields, which are perpetually
watered with the ſtreames of milke and
honey, flowing and running through the

meadowes, wholly enameled with flowers
which no winter is either able to annoy or
wither. What hindred me that I could not
participate in the delightfull banquets, revellings,
and dances of the Children and favourites
of the gods? I was at the bankes of Acheron,
with an extreame deſire to paſſe it, but
that old, uncivil boat-man would not receive
me into his Barke; whether it were that I
brought not my paſſage mony in my mouth,
like the reſt, or that my body had not yet bin
interred: I had the patience to ſee him croſſe,
and returne often, and as often to offer my
ſelfe to him, out of a hope, that one time
might have rendred me more acceptable
than another; but all my hope was vaine, and
I could never gaine any thing of him: At
length, as I ſtood ſtill obſerving the multitude
of ſoules which repaired thither from al
ſides, in no leſſe number than the leaves in
Autumne uſe (after the firſt froſt) to fal from
the trees, the ſad and unfortunate ſoule of
poore Stenobea, preſented it ſelfe to me, with
the ſelfe ſame lineaments and feature which
I had uſually ſeene in her, ſave onely that ſhe
ſeemed farre greater, which did ſo ſurpriſe
both mine eyes &amp; thoughts, that I knew not
what to thinke of it, untill ſhe began to enter
into this Diſcourſe.
               
                  
What ſtrange adventure, Endymion, makes
thee wander in theſe obſcure and ſolitary
places, whereunto thy Fate hath not yet called
thee? For (to the end thou maiſt not
trouble thy ſelfe to aske me the ſame queſtion)
I tell thee; that it is not the will of Heaven
that thou ſhalt dye yet, or that I ſhould
live any longer: perchance the gods, being
now at length tyred with croſſing me, doe
ſend thee hither to give me opportunity of
juſtifying my ſelfe of the crime thou haſt unjuſtly
laid to the charge of mine innocence;
the onely ſorrow which had power to annoy
me even after death. Thou diddeſt
me wrong in the interpreting of the reſolution,
wherewith I beheld thee dye, and that I
had ſo ſoone forgot thy loſſe. All the
reſolution I tooke, proceeded from the
hope Iſmene gave me, that the Knife would
do thee no harme, &amp; that thy life was in far
leſſe danger than mine owne. But thou eſteemedſt
my joy for thy deliverance as a crime,
and thine exclamations were ſo highly injurious
to mine affection, and ſo ſenſible to me,
that at length they bereaved me of ſence,
making me fall downe in thy preſence, as
the true and reall Sacrifice of Love firſt,
and then of Diana: All the care which the

maydens that were about me tooke to remove
me out of the throng into the graſſe,
produced no other effect, than a tranſporting
me from one death to another, and under colour
of giving me more aire and liberty of
breath, and ſeeking a cure for my preſent
diſeaſe, they gave me a generall cure for all
my diſeaſes at once; for Diana, who for a
while before held me in a continuall purſuit,
had laid a Serpent in ambuſh, which with
his ſting, and mortall venome had wholly infected
me, before I could either come to my
ſelfe, or give any notice of it. This was a
ſtrange kind of Sacrifice, wherein Timetes
bore onely the vaine name and title of a
Prieſt, and a Serpent performed the Office.
Endymion was preſented, but Stenobea was
accepted. I had beene farre more happy Endymion,
if thou hadſt beene leſſe curious, and
hadſt never ſeene Albania; then none of the
gods would have made uſe of my reſemblance,
to make thee violate the ſacred Forreſt,
or have kindled in my breaſt a fire ſo
contrary to my vowes: for to be in love, and
to be vowed to Diana are two things incompatible
in one ſubject: I had not then preſented
my ſelfe at her Altar, with any other care
or duty, than that which I owed to her ſervice,

nor ſhould have bin troubled at the fall
of ſuch other ſacrifices as were made unto
her. Thus ſhe finding me more guilty than
thee, ſlew me to preſerve thee; my life hath
redeemed thine, and now, the ſame image
that made thee guilty, brings thee thy abſolution.
Farewell then Endymion, but remember
this teſtimony I give thee, even beyond
the grave it ſelfe, that I have loved thee, more
than I have loved the gods themſelves. Thou
ſeeſt how the Ferry-man preſſes and calls upon
me, therefore hinder me not to goe looke
for reſt after death, ſince thou haſt poſſeſſed
it in life.
               As ſhe uttered theſe words, I thrice ſtretched
forth my hand to take hold of hers, and
ſtay her, and as often I graſped the aire; ſhee
fled and vaniſhed from my ſight, like a viſion
or dreame, leaving me no further poſſibility
of ſeeing or knowing her. I would have
leaped into the Boat after her, but was more
rudely repulſed than before: when I opened
my mouth to call to Charon, or Stenobea, and
to powre out my plaints and petitions to
them, I found my ſelfe ſtarke dumbe: being
thus tranſported with griefe, I would have
wept, but mine eyes had no more teares: Ah
me, ſaid my poor Ghoſt, wch way ſhal I turne

                  
                  
ſince, as I now am, I can neither be received
amongſt the dead, nor the living? Thus was I
compelled to wander here and there on the
ſhore▪ where inſtead of the bleſſed troopes
which I thoght to have viſited, I encountred
onely lamentations, afflictions, torments, &amp;
ſuch like, the wretched inhabitants of thoſe
ſad confines; at length I reſted my ſelfe under
the ſable ſhadow of a large tree, whoſe branches
ſpred farre and wide, and whoſe fruit
ſeemed to he groundleſſe dreames, and the
leaves vaine hopes. At length having continued
a while like a man that dreams, ſleeps,
is dead, or is not at at all, as I knew not what
path I trod to conduct me into theſe parts;
ſo likewiſe knew I not what way my ſpirit
tooke to returne to my body, or how I came
to my ſelfe, yet I began to recollect ſence and
motion, and was able to ſigh, and open mine
eyes: Howbeit, I ſtood yet in doubt, whether
they were thoſe of my body or mind; for
as if I had bin raviſhed into the heavens, methought
I inſenſibly approached the Moon,
but obſerving more nearely, I again thought
that ſhe approached me: then I perceived her
deſcend ſoftly under the favour of ſilence &amp;
darkneſſe, as though ſhe would have ſtolne
from Heaven, or had bin affraid to bring day
with her unto the earth, in the midſt of the

                  
                  
Night, and had therefore covered her face
with a Vaile: But whether it were too tranſparent
or untied, or that her eyes were too
cleare for it, it could not hinder mee both
from ſeeing and knowing her▪ and ſo the honour
which I promiſed my ſelfe of her, made
me forget my paſſed misfortunes, and bethinke
me what to ſay to her: but ſhe no ſooner
put foot on ground, but ſhee prevented
me with this gratefull language.
               Thy Felicity Endymion, exceeds thy vowes
and thy hopes, from hence forth let thine accuſing
the gods ceaſe, for they give much better
than men are able to demand: Thy ſufferings
are this day crowned with glory, and
have ranked thee in the number of the Immortall;
and this thou art obliged to thine
affection for, or rather, to mine. The names
of the greateſt number of the Stars are ſcarſe
knowne to the world, but as long as there
ſhall be any ſpeech of the Moone, or that ſhee
ſhall ſhine in the Heavens, thy name ſhall remaine
in the mouths and memory of men.
               Thus ſhe continued rewarding my paines
with winde and ſmoke, when on a ſuddaine
a ſhrill noiſe of Trumpets, and Clarions, a
confuſed bruite of Cymballs, and all other
kinds of Inſtruments of Copper, and Braſſe,

iſſued from the Hills, and the Vallies, and
beate the aire with ſuch violence, that it
bereaved me of her, who retired and vaniſhed
in an inſtant. Then I opened mine eies
indeed, juſt like one that ſuddenly ſtarts
out of his ſleepe, and ſuddenly ſtretched
forth my head and hands, as if I would
have followed her, or called her backe againe:
but having wholly loſt the ſight of
her, I looked about me, to ſee if I could
perceive the aſſembly, wherewith I ſeemed
lately environed, but neither ſaw that, nor
the Prieſt, or Altar; nay, I could not ſee my
ſelfe, it was ſo darke; and ſo making more
uſe of my hands than mine eyes, I endeavoured
by feeling round about me, to finde
out where I was; I began to thinke my
ſelfe ſhut up in ſome Sepulchre: At length I
diſcerned a ſmall light, which by little and
little increaſed, and drawing nearer to the
place, where I firſt ſaw it appeare, I found
my ſelfe (to my great aſtoniſhment) upon
Mount Lathmos, and the Moone in the
Firmament, to whom I was making my
complaint, juſt as thou cameſt to me.
               Verily Endymion ſayes Pyzander, if I be not
deceived, I begin to diſcerne the whole my
                  
                     ••
                  ery
of thine Adventures, and in mine

opinion I may ſay, thou haſt done a great
journey, without budging from one place,
in lying ſtill thou haſt travailed farre, and
haſt ſeene ſtrange Cities, peoples, and large
Countries, all in one little Cave: It was
doubtleſſe one and the ſame noiſe that recalled
the Moone from her ſwoune, and thee
from the long ſleepe Iſmene had caſt thee into,
either by ſome ſlight of her craft, or elſe
by ſome inſpiration of the goddeſſe herſelfe;
for ſince the time ſhee gave thee that water
to make thee, as ſhe ſaid, reſt, whilſt ſhe travailed
for thee, I have not obſerved that ſhe
ever waked thee: Onely I have noted that
thou felt'ſt her take thee by the hand, to conduct
thy March in the darke, where thou encountredſt
all thoſe ſtrange Monſters whereof
thou madeſt mention, which in effect are
but dreames, yet images of the truths wee
this day ſee. Moreover, the Arrows of Venus
Boy, comming out of Diana's hand,
which caſt thee downe at the foot of a Tree,
or the Knife of Morpheus, brought as thou
ſay'ſt▪ from the Countrey of the Cimmeriana,
the ordinary reſidence of ſlumber, doe of
their owne nature worke no other execution,
or kill any body otherwiſe than thou
art ſlaine there with, as long as no other

force is uſed with them. But what clearer
proofe canſt thou deſire of what I ſay, than
the very words which the virgin Parthenopea
uttered to thee at the beginning by way of
Oracle?
               What charme can this be, but that of
Sleepe, by the meane whereof, Iſmena to
give thy curioſity ſome kind of ſatisfaction,
hath given thee viſions of thy good or ill
fortune, of the eſtate wherein thou art with
Diana, and in a word, the very ſame things
which thou mighteſt ſee with thine eyes open,
if thou wouldeſt well conſider them. I
alwayes imagined Pyzander, ſayes Endymion,
that mine adventures would ſeeme ſo little
ſtrange to thee, that thou wouldeſt rather
take them for dreames, than verities.
               By this time the Birds began to raiſe their
ſeverall notes, to give a joyfull welcome to
the approach of the Morning, and the wonted
noiſe of the Carts, and men returning to
their accuſtomed labour, was heard on all
ſides, when Endymion at the earneſt requeſt
of Pyzander, came downe from Mount Lathmos,
and returned to his Houſhold-gods in
the City of Heraclea, and to a thouſand
vowes and prayers which his friends inceſſantly
offered for his preſence. From that

time forward he continued recounting, and
extolling to all the World the praiſes of Diana,
although ſhe had beene the cauſe of all
his miſeries and tortures; and that hee had
ſpent the better part of his time and life, either
in the tedious watchings which he had
employed in the contemplation of her beautie
and glory, or in the long ſleepe
which ſhe had cauſed him to
be caſt into.
            
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

