
   
      
         
            The tryall of trauell, or, [brace] 1. The wonders in trauell, 2. The worthes of trauell, 3. The way to trauell in three bookes epitemizd / by Baptist Goodall, merchant.
            Goodall, Baptist.
         
         
            
               1630
            
         
         Approx. 165 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01867
            STC 12007
            ESTC S4320
            24145872
            ocm 24145872
            27249
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01867)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27249)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1817:13)
         
         
            
               
                  The tryall of trauell, or, [brace] 1. The wonders in trauell, 2. The worthes of trauell, 3. The way to trauell in three bookes epitemizd / by Baptist Goodall, merchant.
                  Goodall, Baptist.
               
               [80] p.   
               
                  Printed by Iohn Norton, and are to bee sould by Iames Vpton, at his shop in Paules Church yeard at the signe of the Fox,
                  London :
                  1630.
               
               
                  In verse.
                  Signatures: A² B-K⁴ L².
                  Title in ornamental border.
                  Includes marginal notes.
                  Formerly STC 12008.
                  Imperfect: pages cropped and print show-through.
                  Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.
                  Includes bibliographical references.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Travel.
               Voyages and travels --  Poetry.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-01
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-02
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-07
            Elspeth HealeySampled and proofread
         
            2006-07
            Elspeth HealeyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
               
THE TRYALL OF TRAVELL OR,

                  1. The Wonders in Trauell,
                  2. The Worthes of Trauell,
                  3. The Way to Trauell.
               
            
            In three bookes Epitemizd. By Baptiſt Goodall Merchant.
            
               They that trauaile downe to the ſea in ſhipps, and paſſe opon the great waters, ſuch ſee the workes of the Lord, and his wonders in the deepe.
               
                  Pſalme. 107. 24.
               
            
            Ignoti nulla, cupido.
            
               LONDON, Printed by IOHN NORTON, and are to bee ſould by IAMES VPTON, at his ſhop in Paules Church yeard at the ſigne of the Fox, 1630.
         
         
            
            TO THE THRICE NOBLE And Illuſtrious Lady: prime ſeate of all princely worth, Great honor of trauell, Patterne of Piety and patience ELIZABETH.
            
               Queene of Boheme, Counteſſe Palatz of the Rhine, Dueheſſe of Bauary Marchioneſſe of Morauy.
            
            
               Theſe tripart tryalls of trauell are conſecreated by Baptiſt Goodall: in Hope of her Honourable acceptance, with Wiſhes of ioyes Externall, Eternall.
            
         
         
            
            To all the ſonnes of Noble trauaile whether Merchant, Martiall, or Maryne Negotiators.
            
               TO you the liuely Characters of my muſes Epitome (as more due) I preſent her: not for ſhelter, but ſuruay, her ſonets are in ſhort the trophes of your trauails: Antidots againſt obliuion, and the Aconite of ſkilleſſe cenſure. Therein may ye reuiſe the wonders once viewed, the worths preconceiued, with the wayes of trauaile traced already: ſo doing ſcan how ſhort you are of what may be; as well as reuiue time of that hath bin. Action is proper to you ſpeculation to ſcollers: what they Aenigmatically peruſe, you perſonally viſit, now although ſhe can neyther much augment your notions, nor yet fortifie your Iudgements by theſe her primortiues, ſo ſub alternate to your ſufficiencies: yet hapily in the garden of her diuerſitie▪ ſome flowers may ſelected no leſſe delectable then profitable, if not ſerue they as ſ
                  •
               uchions pendant in memory of more Iuditious obſeruations: or euer dure they as pledges of an vnlimited loue to all the Noble ſonnes of trauaile, Such primly Whoſe wiſhes drilled her out from pen to preſſe I am not ignorant how our crittick can cauill, therefore haue I fortified her with diuine, and Morall Auncient and moderne marginals, as little how our ſatiriſt in his Laciuyous textures confront the like Carpere vel noli noſtra, vell edetua, nor how the Tertullian wil puffe at her plaineſſe, A 
                  〈…〉
                faut point d'enſeigne, alas deformityes in nature, are only 
                  •
               
               dulterate defects obſcured deceptio viſus fits homeſpune punies, not blades who pump for their wits midd ſalt ſurges and haue 
                  •
               ur
                  •
                
               
                  •
               yed more countryes thou the carier countrytownes, my 
                  〈◊〉
                (my preſent wife) is as plaine as yong nor leſſe true then vncommon pleaſe ſhee you with her ſongs I am ſatiſfied our ſpeech by pa
                  •
                death proues ſilence what ſuruiues in abſcence is writing eyther after vs, or farr of, Quo lic
                  •
                at libris non licet ire mihi. ſhe may ſpeake when I cannot, where I may not. I comit her to your cuſtody, wiſhing your happy progreſſe in trauaile, with peace foreuer.
            
               Your fellow trauailer, Baptiſt Goodall.
            
         
         
            
            The Prologue to the Generall
            
               THat our vnwiſe domeſticke many diſcerne
            With the Agreſtick Trauailes worths to learne
            And that Both may behold as in a glaſſe
            Pleaſures of ſuch who foraine parts do paſſe
            Vnuailing ſo the vices of a crue
            Who gueſſe all things by them vnſeene vntrue
            I haue in ſhort ſet downe my thoughts therin
            Some credit to that choyce eſtate to winn,
            Firſt from my owne li
                  •
               es who a ſmall haue ſeene
            Yet better may the worths of trauaile deeme
            Then from the houſe bird, and the Dormouſe dull
            So from our critick, and th' vnletterd g
                  •
               ll
            Now if as 't may be) th' ſonnes of Didimus
            In Stoicke humor Daine not to beleeue vs
            Lo th' Sacred writ will vrge a credit to it
            No Antidote but ſeeing elſe will do it
            Diuine, and Morall, Modern, and the ould
            All in her worths v
                  •
               aſked with vs hould
            The Patriarcks, Princes, Ptophets ſtories Churches
            And worlds of more of all ſorts ſort with theſe
            The Iewes, Greeks, Turks, Moors, Indians: and wee
            All ages times, and ſtates, there to agree
            To Chriſtian ſome, to Mortall trauaile all
            Trovaile to euery mortall muſt befall.
            Ci
                  •
               ill alone is now our muſes taſke
            Which 
                  •
               he (by Zoilas leaue) ſhall now vnmaſke
            Its wonder, worth, and way and plant from hence.
            Canons diſmount all homebred impudence
            
               
                  •…
               pell their falſe auouch, whoſe trembling pen
            Like Canaan ſpies diſconſolateth men
            Read all or none at all, do but as due
            Thou't ſay though yong and ſhort, 
                  •
               hee's plaine and true.
            
               Quem recitas meus eſt fidentine libellus
               At male dum recitas, incipit eſſe tuus,
               Martialis.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
               The wonders in trauaile.
               
                  What time Iehove had all things ready made. 
                     Geneſeoſ. 1. Adam primus homo damnauit ſeenla prima, 3
               
               The Sea, Land, riuers, winds the Sunne and ſhade
               The day and night, both foule and Firmament
               Heauen and earth form'd all to mans content,
               Him made he then the microcoſme of all,
               Seated in coſtly Eden, whilſt his fall, Qui facit magna &amp; inſcrutabillia abſ
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      numero Eliph.
               
               Makes him accurſed of a Lord compleats
               Inſweat of browes adindg'd his bread to eate
               And pilgrimewiſe henceforth on earth to wander,
               Pacing about it as a crookt meander,
               Thenearth for ſin ſuſtaines a whole deluſion 
                     Oſhominiſubline dedit omne metam 1. caput.
                  
               
               And Nimrods plott produces tongues confuſion
               Sin, ſtill and ſorrow relatiues in vs
               We are to ſpend our dayes in trauaile thus.
               Diuineſt for ſight arm'd the world with ſtore 
                     nihil in terra Sine canſa ſit Iob. 5
               
               Of adhuments to trauaile long before
               To this end we are the windes volutions fram'd
               Which eaſt, weſt, north, and ſouth, by man are nam'd.
               To this end were both ſeas and flouds prepar'd
               As is in the Creations rule declar'd.
               And ſo become the tongues confuſion good 
                     Deus 
                     
                        〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                      
                     totus quodenim togitat hoc Loguitur &amp; qvod loqnitur togitat Iren Lib. 2. c, 48.
               
               One aydes the other to be vnderſtood.
               Yea heerevnto was ſhipping preinuented,
               Leaſt entercourſe twixt nations be preuented
               Since man to ſweate and trauailes deſtind heere
               So to conſume in life day, month, and yeare.
               
                  
Tis nothing elſe to trauaile but to breath
               Trauailes ordained poſterities bequeath.
               Tis nothing more to trauaile then to liue 
                     Qunti instit Liber, 
                     
                        •
                     :
               
               Earth cannot leaſt repoſd contentment giue
               Nor may the wiſe, or great, or faire, goe free
               But equaly the trace of trauaile ſee.
               Trauaile tripartite prime to all the reſt
               Is mortall trauaile, all thus intereſt.
               The Chriſtian and Ciuill ſtand dependants
               Both being on our mortall courſe attendants
               Ciuill we treat of tis wee vnderſtand
               Mans ſtate of entercourſe by ſea and Land
               As they are deſtind heere to vndergoe,
               Great Ioue in his degree commands it ſoe.
               To tell ſuch wonders they at ſea haue ſeene,
               His greater fames forgotten to redeeme.
               Of things vnknowne a Credit to procure,
               And men to ſee his greatneſſe to allure
               Of natures rares indifferent of Climes.
               To tell the worths, ſtrange qualities and times. Vti beneficia omnibus horis—ſunt conſideranſa Chriſoſtom:
               
               Acquaint the earth with miracles vnknowne,
               which oney are by ciuill trauailes ſhowne.
               And friendly chang of each lands fruites thus made,
               Yea many thouſands each way fed by trade.
               Thus trauailes wonders firſt their maker praiſe,
               Then add they ſtore and ſollace to our dayes
               The forme of ciuill trauailes thus prepard
               Now ſhall its wonders briefly be declard
               Not able to conceiue the cauſe of much In mare:
               
               Her miracles in her ſurueyes are ſuch Microcoſme
               
               Each mans a wonder of himſelfe alone
               Much wonder may a man ſuruay at home
               Much more in many millions diſagreeing
               Informe wits mannors, nations habitts being
               Th' inviſiue deiety hearin diſcloſd Romans. 1.
               
               Omnipotence in natures frame propoſd
               To leaue ſayth ſcripture man without excuſe
               
                  
When faithleſly men cauſe his powers abuſe Pſalme. 8. Qui deſendunt mare in nauibus facientes operationem in aquis multis ipſi viderunt opera domini &amp; mirab
                           •
                        llia ſua in profundis:
                  
               
               Wiſe Dauid firſt at heauen, then earth admires
               From whence with wondering downe to ſea retires
               Such as deſcend to deepe (quoth he) ſuch ſee
               The powers of Iehova what they bee
               His fame is raiſed by euery dayes ſucceſſe
               The rudeſt region will explaine no leſſe
               When men ſaith he are toſſed in the maine
               So that their ſoules conſume in ſence of paine
               Sometime are toſſed to the cloudy ſkies,
               Hence in a haſt hell low, her ſhipping flyes
               Billowes carreyring toſſe too and fro
               And waſh her as a wherry high and low
               Now pray they and their ſorrow ſeekes an end
               Paſt hope or helpe or harbour to defend
               The ſtormy winds are ſtild, the men haue hope
               When in a calme the ſhip findes larger ſcope
               The men reioyce, bleſſe God, and well ariue
               And in the midd of many perilles thriue
               Twas ſure a wonder Iouas vnder went
               When he in trauaile croſſed Ioues intent
               The monſtrous Whale ſhould harbour be to him
               Who in his ſoule had harbourd ſo much ſinne
               Three dayes aliue tranſported in his Cheſt
               Yet all this time with life and ſafety bleſt
               Then layd aſhore, out of his mighty power
               Whoſe quality is ſolie to deuoure
               
                  Aegypts red ſea to admiration parts
               And from an ocean to drie land conuert
               Billowes, are walles, they paſſe on dry foot ground 
                     Patientia dei 12
                        •
                      
                     annes dura vit cumarca ſi
                           •
                        bat.
                  
               
               When Lo! their foes the Aegiptians are drownd
               No leſſe admired was the Arke of Noe
               
               Prepard to trauaile in earths ouerthrowe
               The monſtrous Generation, mockt his ſkill
               How ere twas formd by God Almighties will
               All earths indeluge he and his are fownd
               
                  
Careyring ſafe in ſhipp, all others drown'd, 
                     Solares eſt quae 
                           •
                        omines obſentes preſentes facit Turp: de fit viciſſ
                     
                        Quibus puſumnusetiam abcetibus alloqui Auguſt,
                     
                  
               
               And by this rare inuentions h
                     •
                  rbinger
               The world doth alwayes with it ſelfe conferre
               Shipping ar embaſies, he get relation
               Through farr remote twixt nation, and nation
               Poſts packing each way with intelligences
               Garners to ſtore mortals aſſure defences
               The wandrous arke anchours Ararats mount
               Her docke, and now the nations recounte
               Hauing a patterne how her like to build
               Then from a future deluge ſtill to ſheyld
               And I, make the waters paſſable they try
               Phenicanus bowe the firſt in hiſtory Naue primus as egypto damnus, aduenit pliny
               
               Aegypt proceedes the Greeke and many omre
               
                  Solomon trads to Opior for his ore.
               Thus did deuine preſcience ſhips inuent
               Mans Cheifeſt friend, the temples ornament 
                     Reg: 1,
               
               Our Lord and his deſciples once at ſea
               Great gulfts ariſe and tempeſt ouerſway
               The ſhipp ſuckes billowes as her onely diett 
                     vide: Mark. 4. 38.
               
               Makes the deſciples fearefull and vnquiet
               He wakes, they cry helpe maſter or wee periſh.
               Oft times thus feare by vnbeleefe is cheriſht
               Chriſt giues the word and bids them all be ſtill
               And gladly they as ſoone obey his will
               So that the faithleſſe Iewes are forſt to ſay
               Oh what is he whom windes and ſeas obey.
               Examples moue oft more then reaſons good
               where ſence and ſight ar wholy vnderſtood monumenta aetotum Leſt: L:
               
               Lo! Laſt in paull his voyage is a wonder.
               When ſea and windes teare all their ſhips in ſunder
               Each boardes conuey, and ſafe the people land Act. 27 20:
               
               Rul'd in the Loue of Paul by higheſt hand
               See now at ſea the wonders trauail knowes
               Where God himſelfe in omnipotence ſhowes
               Proclames a power exceeding other places Vbitung fuerit dei prouidentia
               
               
                  
And ſea aboue the land with wonder grace 
                     
                        •
                     ruſtrautar vniuerſa contraria
                        •
                      Auguſt:
               
               Next acts his matchleſſe mercy greater part
               And ſeeming death to long life doth conuert
               Daily experience fortiſies our faith
               Should we ſurmiſe vnſure what ſcripture ſaith?
               Our eighty eight Gibralter and the reſt
               Would with amazement ſcale our flinty breſt
               As thus on ſea Ioue in high wonder paſſes
               So him in ſea his creatures wonder graces Creatura miranda.
               
               Witneſſe the worlds of fiſh of various birth
               When waters broad doth ſimpathiſe the earth
               Liuiathan Iohes wonder as a rocke
               But at a ſhip maieſtickly doth knocke
               His huge and maſſy beard whole billowes bruſſhes Iob 41 6. Corpus eius quſcuta ſuſillia compactum ſe ſquamis ſe prementibus
                  
               
               He through the ocean as a whirle winde ruſhes
               Or as an earthquake makes the ſeas to ſhake
               Deuouring ſhoules, and ſupping drie the lake
               His ſinnes plowe way in mideſt of proudeſt waues
               Thus Neptune like he all the ſea out braues
               Puffes out a challenge, what can quele my might
               Or who like me can on an ocean light
               Forgetting how the ſea man in meere play
               Winnes him in ſport, to throw his bulcke away
               And drunkard like allyes the Barrell ore
               Till he appeareth naked one the ſhore
               Now gald with darts that cloudes of blood enſue
               And die the neerer ſtreames another hue
               The ſlimy ſea horſe; and the Cowe contend
               Better then the terre
                     •
                   themſelues to ſend
               Yet on the ice will wallouw in a rowte
               And both brought Captiue by the ſeaman 
                     •
                  lente
               Men monſters and the Syrens rares to ſee
               Yet on the waues ſuch wonders dayly be
               Scene in the north and Southerne hotteſt climes
               Chifely the former in our latter times
               The boulting ſea hogg ſpouts againſt the ſtorme
               
                  
And will attend though wild ſweete muſickes charme
               Whoſe conſorrs Saluson, Codd, and Sturgeon bee
               Such in our natiue ſoile hath primacie 
                     
                        〈…〉
                     .
               
               Tis ſaid of ſages not ſo ould as true
               That althings ſilent ſhew Gods powers due
               And that ſome workes of his mirit admire
               Rather then reaſon how and why inquire
               His prouidence in heauens high influences
               To the other regions els are ſole defences
               Sunn, Moone, and ſtarres, aire, Earth, and ſea direct
               Order, diſpoſe, rule, alter, get, protect
               Their diſpoſitions haue effects in all
               In ſea, in ſkie, or earth, men creatures call
               Their conſtant motion diuine influx cauſes
               The ſea ſtore hath at large a ſhare in theſe
               A ſecond earths ſtore, as the ſhapes of vs
               So Brutes, horſe, doggs; and all ſorts wonderouſe
               Yea vegetiue and minerall appeare
               The ſword, fiſt, pike, cuts, tortiſe farr and neare
               All ſorts by ſholes in order know their like
               Their formes ſo ſtrang, men in amazement ſtrike
               For note as euery Clime doth various ſtand
               The obiect Zones ruling the nether land
               So euery ſea as is the Climes degree
               Differs in Creatures ſhape and rarity
               All which howere to home bred men vnknowne
               Yet are in midd of trauaile wondrous ſhowne
               The rule of Reaſon is my argument
               It brings in men (things neere ſo ſtrange) Conſent
               For a relation in one body rownd
               Twixt ſea and land was in Creation fownd
               In Creatures kind though different in forme
               Yet cannot natures likneſſe be out worne
               This of the wonders on, and in the ocean
               The frutes there off are only trauailes notion Cumfreta diſcuditrapidiſ
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                     
                  
               
               See now the ſea it ſelfe miraculouſe
               
                  
His height exceeds earths, and is fluctuos 
                     tumeſ
                           •
                        rre ventis &amp; am circumdare litora terroe metam Lib. 1.
               
               Yet giueth God ſayth Dauid to him bownd
               Nor can earth by its ouerheight be drownd
               A miracle exceeding common ſince
               And wherin reaſons proofe is impotence
               As is the cauſe of tides ſlux and retreate
               Howere by luner motions made compleate
               This watry orbe is various euery where
               Now red, then blacke, then yellow, greeniſh cleare
               Now hot and ſeethes, there ice mountes her couer vtque duae dexcaelum to tidem qu ſi a
                        •
                     ſira, parte ſecant zon
                        •
                     , quinta
                        •
                      ſtard en
                     
                        ••
                     orillis &amp;c.
               
               Wonders beſt knowne by ſuch as trauaile ouer
               Fiue zones earths guards, the Equinoctiall girt
               Which vnder Climes ſtill as they are Conuert
               Two frigid, one fire hot two temporate
               Gouernd by the high Celaeſtiall fate
               the differing ſeas, and ſeaſons vnder each
               How ere knowne part by ſpeculationes reach 
                     Guid metam: 1:
               
               Yet ſights the ſure, and teitruth of a notion
               Not ſubiect, to the pennes vnſure deuotion
               Trauailes adiacents more miraculous
               Inable man to preſſe ſeas reaches thus
               The compaſſe by his loadſtone wonders chiefe
               Yeilds in vnknowneſt pathes a knowne reliefe
               Teaching the ſteareman how to runn his way
               And mideſt of Rockey billowes take ſurvay
               Now ſunn and ſtarres are hid not to digreſſe
               In nauall calculations more or leſſe Inſtrumenta naevallia mir
                        •
                     nda,
               
               In courſe to Cape, Ile, harbour, ſtranger nation
               But find the true rowmb, in winds variation
               In midd of miſty fogges ſecure to runn
               Although in darkneſſe and defect of ſunn
               Knowing and ſurely too, each Cape and Cliffes
               where ſlatts, ſands, ſhoules, ſafe harbours rockes or riffes
               That Ephimerian callender a wonder
               There aſtrolab, Croſſtaff viewd aſunder
               Whoſe iſſues and effects p
                     •
                  ſſe home Conceits
               
                  
Wherewith our ſeamen act admired ſeates 
                     Bernar in Cantic: 76
               
               The Compas Card, ſcale limbes of euery ſhipp
               That plannifp heere, and tranfames ſo be fit
               In rareſt art, ſunnes horall height to know
               And the altitude of euery ſtarre to ſhow
               Northeaſting, aud Northweaſting by a line
               What way is made, which way the length, the time
               The North ſtarre where aboue tho pole or not
               Skilles wherein euery home bredd proues a ſott
               My relation Hebrue, he athen Greeke, yet know
               Tis now my talke ſea miracles to ſhowe
               Sunnes ſurgere greſſe in euery latitude
               Harden then heera at home ar to conclude
               Each lands dimenſion length, and ſquare and ſite
               The ſolar progreſſe, euery where his height
               Tides in all countries by the moone to find
               Their flux and reflux, and the depth they wind
               Timly meridian, ſolles true Declinations
               The North ſtarres power, Globes rule in Nauigations
               The pillotts art his Chanall ſownds, quicke viewe 
                     Veſputiones Ano 1499: Collumbus: Anno 1492. Darcus Anno 1579. In learning aduancement. Magell anus 1520: Candiſh 1587
               
               Lo! from theſe fruits our voyages accrue
               Amazing earth in great diſcoueties made
               Inriching Europ with a potent trade
               Thus euery way at ſea are wonders ſhowne
               I will not name diſcoueries well vnknowne
               Thoſe new found Gulphes: exacter reuolutions
               Collumbus, Drakes, or candiſhes concluſions
               Veſputius Norts or Dauis nouigatianes
               For earths pacts latly rowue by many nations
               The thorow lights by trauell made are cleare
               Through which our new world doth to the ould appeare
               Amerricca her ſiſters three ſcarce knew
               While trauell brought them to an enter view
               And now acquainted both in admiration
               Honour, and vſe as briges Nauigation
               Thence to the skies high wonders travaile ſees
               
                  
Coſmographies the plott diſcouers theeſe
               The leuen heauens, Circular effects
               Trauail in all her wondros deſſects
               That Zodiacke, his twelue parts operation
               Diſcrepant to the ſubdependent nation
               The Equinoctiall change, earths axaltree
               Embraces differently her orb ye ſee
               Heere ſtarres both fixt and motiue alter Caſe
               Wonderous in act according to the place
               The foure winds Rhouts, and thirty two partitions
               Eclipſes ſolar, lunar; ſuch poſitions
               As theſe are plainely writ, I neede not ſay
               The worths in ſight its ſure, beyond denay I am quod videtur ſciri potus quam credi dicitur.
               
               For ſo much as the thing is fancies better
               View paſſeſſe reading, its contents are greater
               The heauens declare Gods glory, Heauens power
               Is picturd in earths woundrous parts each houre 
                     Gregor in Euangeli. 32.
               
               Earths miracles in trauelling are more
               Since the Almighty formd heere greater ſtore
               That ſo the ſonnes of men in admiration Terraemira.
               
               Might paſſe to view from nation to nation
               Varieties ſtill added to deſire 
                     Terra vires vrbeſ
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         gerit frugeſque faeraſque flumina
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         hec ſupereſt Caeliſulgentis. Imago mett: Lib: 1.
               
               Filling the greedy ſtranger with admire
               The men, townes, frutes, riuers and brutes all Change
               Turne any way in trauaile things are ſtrange
               Geography treats moſt of arts hearin
               But trauaile only ſweet of ſence doth winn
               Earths ſipherall orbe both ile and continent
               According to their ſits are different
               Complexions to the Climes do beare relation
               So is in men a diuers propagation
               How full of miracles is nature now
               Which euery way ſuch difference can allow?
               Mens ſtatutes, colloures, haire much different
               In humours, and in manners diuers bent
               Our Northern cleare, the Southern ſwarty browne
               
                  
Thats merry plaine, this cunning bent to frowne
               Ons frolicke other ſad and dull of ſpirit
               Thus diuers Climes their diuerſe breed inheritt
               Europe the Queene though leaſt of ſiſters foure 
                     Ad me undum foc
                           •
                        etatem home naturà ferter ſua Aug. De ciuitat Lib. 19. cap. 12.
               
               Greateſt in fame, in arts in wits in power
               In wines and mines high Garmany exceedes
               As Moſco Beauers, and the rich furr breeds
               The Belgick fiſh, and linen, a iarring nation
               Yet much ſupraſſeth moſt in nauigation
               The french her wines, and ſilkes of Itally
               Spaines fruits, rich ores, and Irons raiſe her high
               The Daniſh tackle ſkinnes, and whales ſuplie
               The Norway plankes, firres furies, and fiſhery
               The poliſh flaxes, Sweadiſh Braſſe, and maſt
               The Turkey ſtuffes Hungarian coppers Caſt
               The florence ſilke, Beames Buffe, moluccoes ſpice
               The Brittiſh wooltrin, lead, corn, cole of price
               Sicillian Coralls ſugaries Candie wines
               Zauts Corrants, and the venice Muſkadines
               The Chinaes gould, pearle, muſke, and Iuory
               The Indian ſilke, and mines of ores ſupply
               Behould the diuerſe ſtore each land affordes
               The wonders in creations due the Lordes
               Each land in worths to wonder diſagreing
               In nature, colour, quantity and being
               Hence may wee wondering in a higher ſtraine
               On trauells ſtage admiring mount againe
               Scorning the leaſt of lying wonders tould inhil
                        •
                     minus i am Obſequium amicos veritas obuim parit. Terentius.
               
               By ſicophants to obiect baſeneſſe ſould
               Telling of foothigh pigmeyes, doggeard men
               Blue blacke and yellow collored, cald by them
               Out ſcoggin, ſkinke, and like to theſe in credit
               Fables, ales hate, trauailes eiection merit
               What need fond men, the vulgar bee deluded
               Or yet the Lord of nature be abuſed?
               His names almighty in true wondrous things
               
                  
And truth alone ſound ſatisfaction bringes
               Hees truly great in all, abhorres all glozing
               Diſhonourd much by each falſe tales compoſing.
               Yet wants no fame; the little ants a wonder
               Much more thoſe many thouſands all out number. 
                     
                        Edifficia miranda.
                     
                     
                        Id circo credere debemus que non vidimus vt videre me reamur quae credimus. Hug: victor cap: 1.
                     
                        De fid invi
                              •
                           :
                     
                  
               
               See but ſome rares in fabrickes admiration
               Duly attends on ſome in euery nation.
               That Chinan wall twelue hundred miles in length
               Their mighty citties and, vnuoted ſtrength,
               Thoſe Piramids of Aegypt twelue miles rownd
               And fiftie cubitts mounted from the grownd
               The tower and walles of mighty Babilon
               
               The Capitall and ruind worths of Roome
               
               The venice fabricks, Cayroes circle ſtronge
               The ſpanniſh bridge admired three leagues long,
               As theſe the creatures vegetiue excell
               And ſenſitiue their alterations tell,
               That Indian figtrees an admired thing
               Whoſe touch to earth cauſeth a world of ſpring
               Breeding a long atracke of mighty ſtore
               Ones brood oft Carreyeth a furlong ore,
               Thoſe ſiluer ſands, and peatlie vaines diſtilling
               The ſpaniſh with their matchleſſe treaſures filling
               The oliue nutmegg, and the cloues are rare
               And may with Mirch, and lemond well compare,
               Land Creatures wonders in the Ellephant Creatura mirada.
               
               He moſt for maſſy fortitude doth vaunt
               Able to tuggſhip laden in a calme
               And fel the Dragon with his maſſie palme
               Carrie a fort of Cannon, vnderſtand
               Yet willingly obay his guiders hand,
               Writters admire at fieirce Rhinoce roſſe
               His horne, ſayd the mightieſt can toſſe
               With glaſſy ſcales encounters greater things
               And to the new beholders terrour bringes
               Poore muſkcats ciuer as a rare receiued
               
                  
The Bezar, ambir, rubies rares conceaued
               But the Camell Leopard hatches an admire
               In all that to the Southern poles retyre.
               A Compoſite, two natures mixt we ſee
               Bearing to both an equall Simpathy
               The cruell Dragons' fell deuouring iawe
               The ſerpent makes his venamous ſting his lawe
               Both lurking cloſe in rockes of deſert ſprings
               And an affrighting of the neighbour things,
               The Crocodile whoſe teeth in ſumder ſharke
               Making deciſion limit to his marke 
                     Numquid 
                           •
                        volet R
                           •
                        moceros, tibi ſ
                           •
                        ruire? aut morab
                           •
                        ur is ad prae ſepe tuum. Iob. 39.
               
               Hatcht of an Egge oh wonder of admire
               To all in trauailes in the torrids are
               Shee men and beaſts often by land deuoures
               More fiſh in ſea and riuers 
                     •
                  ue his powers
               Yet oft the muſket meete his high attempt
               And with his ruine doth a hurt preuent
               Strange Armadillo armed round about
               Scales hath as Iron with, a ſwiniſh ſnout
               Teeth cruell bent, yet helpe his bones to Cure
               Whoſe rareneſſe trauailes view doth oft allure,
               But ſhould I pen the tenth of all the ſtore
               The things ſome ſee; good writers record more
               Nor paper, pen, nor ſkill could ſure ſuffice
               Let vs hearin with modeſty be wiſe
               Inſtancing truths, truth beares the only ſway
               When worlds of extant fictions decay.
               Our dayes are ſhort ſuppoſe no one hath had
               A viewe of halfe in progreſſe of his trade
               Each what it is add truely to the ſtore
               Of wondrouſe brutes now ſay my muſe no more,
               Omit the Lyon, Beare, wolfe, vnicorne
               The Elck, and Eſtrich, and the Hart, forlorne
               In wilderneſſes with the Leopard pacing
               And with the Tiger trauailes wonders gracing
               Paſſe by the Eagle, faulcon, para, kite
               And fly the tortoiſe, and the Rockfiſh ſight.
               
                  
And add to theſe as different conditions Tot ſpecies tani toſ
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      ortus varoſ
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                     uouatus ipſa clies apperit conficit ipſa dies. Ouid: Amorum.
               
               The Spaniſh pride, and inſolent ambitions
               French, and Itallien luſt, and light conceits
               The vnbeleeuing Iewe in cloſe deceits
               Dane, German, Pool, Norwegian Ruſſe, and Duch,
               Tainted with cupping clowniſhneſſe as much
               Brittiſh how bould, how various, belly bent
               Turkes cruell, chinenſes maleuolent, Germani multos poſſunt ſuffèrre labores ó vtinam poſſiut tam bene ferre ſitim. Vt nos dulce me rum ſic vos venus impia turbat; lix ventri impoſta eſt Iulia nalla mere. Veſtitus varys.
               
               Rude Indians, and Tartarians Idolizers
               The moriſh blacke Barbarians bloody mizers,
               The weſt, and ſoutherne ſoyles to luſt runn madd
               The Eaſt, and north, in drunkenneſſe us bad.
               As natures ilneſſe diuerſly doth vent
               Hauing in climes peculier extent,
               See how the habits men, and women weare,
               Varie to admiration euery wheare.
               The Ruſſe his furd long Coat ſlopt, Collers beares
               The Dane his pointed buffes, wiues wreathed haires
               The German Iumphre huicke, Crague hull, and Copp
               The ſwediſh muſtzell, and long flemiſh ſlopp
               The french all puffes, naked Itallian vailes
               The Spaniſh bagg fleues, Long ſauoyan tailes
               The Iriſh rugg, welch freez; and highland trouſes
               The Brittiſh proteus, Courſe norwegians Couſes Ciuitatum varic tas.
               
               Where ere in trauell thou arriue thus ſee
               One named for worlds what various habits bee
               Fabricke of realmes, as faſhions alter much
               One vſed heare of wood; Bricke, with the Duch.
               The Geanovoijs guilt, leaded marble frame.
               Venice for fite and glazing beares the name.
               Mad rid his fiery wall, St. Lawrence grace
               The Ancient Roman edifice, high race
               Cayro and Paris greatneſſe, Londons plenty
               The famous neatherlands ſtructures no place empty
               Antwerp, and Culloyne,, temples goodly ſite
               This handfull for the heape in trauailes ſighte.
               
                  
One paſſing ſtill another in ſome rare
               Wherein alone he triumphs paſt compare,
               But that the wiſeſt God may ſeeme more high
               Heel mixe his honours with diuerſitie,
               And time the Epoch paſſe their fitteſt birth
               And when and where diſperſt to be one earth
               One land this graces, and another that
               Yet the ſupremiſt worths not to relate
               If one way Spaine paſſes for grapes our ile Societatùſub lata omuis cuitaeſt ſuqlata Ciiucunditas. cero: de Amicitia.
               
               In food, and cloth we more then countervaile
               If India paſſe for ores and pearles the Duch
               Their nauies paſſe the Indian as much,
               If china, ſends with Turkey ſilken ſtore
               Our ſheep clad, and our benes feed thouſands more
               If Norway whale, Ruffe furr, and ſwediſh braſſe
               By ſteetes in trafick to the weſterne paſſe
               They turne gould, wine, and fruits of contentation
               So might I inſtance much in euery nation
               One ſuccours other, traficke breeds affection
               The whole is gouernd by the high protection.
               For windes, ſeas ſkie, and trauell all agree
               To frame one earth a iuſt conformity
               That nature hots, and coulds may be ſuffied
               And euery parts commodities be prizd
               And all men muſe to view Earths aged forme Solemaenum do videntur demerequi amiciam. Siue qui auitam incundam nullo modo habere paſſvmu
                        •
                     s Cicer: de Amicitia.
               
               Triumphs in trauaile more; as leſſe out worne
               Thouſands vnſeen aſſiſting one another
               And the Barbarian rude the Chriſtians brother
               This harmony in nature, and each nation
               Hatched by trauailes howrely propagation
               Nor warr, nor iarr, can totally molleſt
               But ſome way finde they mutuall intereſt,
               Ordaind to fit in all parts man entire
               Begetting trauailes wonder, our admire,
               Whereof howres much more might inſtancd bee
               Yet I conceaue enough in what wee ſee
               The wiſe may by the modell iudge the maſſe
               
                  
So ſpeed my muſe to trauailes worths a pace
               In ſea, ſkie, earth, fiſh fleſh; reaſon and ſence
               Lo! wonders of diuine omnipotence
               Some ſcatterd each way; trauaile muſt diſcry
               And induſtry, and wiſdome moue to try
               Occaſionall wonders theſe attend on time
               And we for them ſince none can pre diuine
               In Chriſtian trauailes, an almighty hand
               Protects his Church, and Children in each land
               In mortall trauailes ſteard by force of fate
               Men may preſume but no way can rebate
               What ſtrange effects they are allotted too
               What wonders they are deſtind heere to doo
               Life tis a trauile through earths ſea of woes
               And miracles doth Chriſtian ſtate diſcloſe
               Neyther the matter of my muſes ſonge
               They to diuines and moraliſts belong
               And my diſcourſe of ciuill trauails worth
               After her wonders let her vtter forth
               Proſtrating ſo his ſelfe to trauailes friend
               So much in ſhort of wonder makes an end.
               
                  Aut face, Aut tace.
               
            
            
               
               The worthes of trauels.
               CAuſes fortunne effects Logitians ſay 
                     
                        Eſt enim iuſtitia Vnicui
                              
                                 
                              
                              que
                            Suum tribuere: cic: de officijs.
                     
                     
                        Ignorantiae duae Filiae falſitas &amp; Dubietas, illa miſereor, ista miſerabillior illa peruitiotior iſta moleſtior Auſtin
                     
                  
               
               As ſubiects euer Leade their adiuncts way,
               Though trauells worths are in wonders ſhowne
               Yet by her rare effects ſhees better knowne,
               Iuſtice ſay ſages is to giue each righte
               Oppon its worth apparent to the ſight,
               Worth muſt be knowne, ere't can be iuſtly prizd
               In ignorance it can but be ſurmiſd.
               The fruits then ſeen pluct off the fertill tre
                     •
                  ,
               Can beſt expreſſe it's worthineſſe to thee,
               Commit it to the taſt of any man
               Thens no more need it's excellency to ſcann,
               Pleaſures, and profitts Commonly are croſſe
               And the, gaine of one is ſtill the others loſſe,
               But if they in one ſubiect mett agree
               That neuer faild to prooue a raritie,
               Behould heers both, and larglie too extended,
               Whereby earths ſeede from ruine is defended.
               Profits abayte t'allure the thrifty mind
               Though he ſmall pleaſure in the obiect find,
               How trauail ſutes in both is admiration
               Mans witt, and wealth of theſe a firſt relation
               The wiſe terms witt, a ſiluer gliding ſtreame
               The witts of nobler natures tis I meane
               
                  
For thers the cauſe the earthly minded lake
               Nor will nor can of trauailes worth pertake,
               Such wits I ſay ſtill flowing from the fountaine
               And inbred vigour of the holy mountaine
               Natures remaines more cleare by graces ſhine,
               Both by aſſiſtance influence diuine,
               Still throuh the nations current are more pure
               By ſunnc
                     •
                  re
                     ••
                  ne, made actiue to endute,
               Mans wit and fence by trauailes daily tried
               Remaine by iſſue ſtill vnputrified,
               Oth harmony in diuerſe witts accord 
                     Officiisvitae humana Conſtat mutuis omniſ
                           
                              
                           
                           que
                         ratio &amp; insti Cutiovitae qumanae adiumenta deſiderat cicero off. Lib: 2.
               
               Neuer Could Clime all ſorts Comactt afford,
               Lands muſt bee louing borow much of each
               The nearer witts perfections to reach,
               The God of nature calls for mutuall trade
               Diuerſicie this enter courſe hath made,
               The Stoic Iewe loues of the Chriſtians learne
               And wee in them frugallity diſcerne
               The Could dull northerne practize weſterne witt
               And they a true plaine hartedneſſe in it.
               The rudeſt Indian manners of our planter
               His heathen ſkill became our trades aduancer,
               The orphean muſicke with Itallian dwelles
               The Spanniſh linn
                     •
                  ing euery way excelles,
               The deepe Giunoſophiſt, the Captiue grecian
               The paracelian phiſicks with Venetian,
               The Expert Pool, and Pertian horſt in warre
               The prying Crees his iudgement of the ſtarre
               In ſome all paſſe that none may be deiected
               But none in all that all may be reſpected.
               As arts inuentors heere and there abide
               That they might be to all allwayes diſcried
               When the decree aginſt, Lewd earth was paſt
               And God by waters ment the Earth to waſt
               He then inſtnicted Noah firſt ſhip to build
               Both him and his from waters force to ſhield
               The eye of man Could not forſee the worth
               
                  
This rare art doth poſterities bring forth
               By it earths ſpacious kindred Comes acquainted
               And Chriſtian faith midd infidels is planted,
               But not Enthuſiall, but by practize ſkill
               Men Nauigations miracles fulfill
               A rarat mounts taught the Phenicians how
               A ſecond arke by Induſtry to bowe,
               Hence Egipp, next it to the Greeks extends
               Who add the Deckes, ones art the reſt befriendes
               The Creet, then Carthage hence the Roman next
               But prouidence aſſigens it to them next.
               And winds tranſport a ſhippe of Tyre to them
               So are the Romans made ſea fairing men, Cret
                        •
                     nſis n
                        •
                     ſcrit peligus.
               
               Become ſea maſters, whence our Brittaine learnes
               Belgickes french, ſpsniſh all the art diſcernes
               Behold the fabricke out of diuerſe nations
               As this ſo other arts haue propagations
               Ciprus the large, Illyrians the Barke
               Rhodes formes our frigats; nay the tackles marke
               Beotia ores, Dedalus maſt and ſaile
               Which bred firſt poets fond I Carian tale. 
                     
                        〈…〉
                      nibus grande leuatur onus.
               
               The Tuſcans ruder, heime and ſterne invent
               And ſtearing from ſkild Typhis firſt deſcent.
               Lo! now the lott is euery way diſpoſd
               Wee ſee ſome heere ſome there of artes diſcloſd Icarcus Icarijs, nomina dedit equis.
               
               The wiſe may by his matter iudge the maſſe
               And ſee Gods goodneſſe cleare as in a glaſſe.
               The iſſues they ſhall force thee to beleeue it
               Worthy to tell, and trie true trauailes credit
               As Noah and his ſuruiue by this innention
               And Solomon at Ophirs Long deſceuſion.
               Whence he the temple ornaments did bring
               Gold, pearles, and Iewels, worthy ſuch a King
               So ſince the new world and the ould ſhake hands
               And freinds are found in many, forraine Landes
               wilt man be witty, then thy daies deuote
               or ſome of thoſe ſome traueld worths to note.
               
                  
For trauailes fruit is reapt by obſuruation 
                     eorum filij nos dicimur quorux actiones imitamur Grigeni
                           •
                         ezeck homi. 4.
               
               And thers a ſeuerall Cropp in euery nation.
               For all mens genius ſome way Chiefly bends
               It to accompliſh ſome way he intendes.
               It may he thine cannot at home be ſitted
               Some artiſts proue elſewhere, farr ſharper witted.
               The handmaid trauaile brings you both as friends
               So now ye purchace your deſired ends.
               Thou ſhalt ſuruay behauioures of a world
               All in exact diuerſities in rowld Hec ediſeas &amp; vigilare Laborare Solon.
               
               Cull out the Choice of flowers in the feilds
               So decke thy witts with that each climate yeilds
               Sweet pleſant ſauours of their vertues loue
               And noyſome ſent of vices diſaproue.
               So bring home harueſt with the ant with thee Equidem exempla multa docere Poſſu
                        •
                     t.
               
               Which in thy gray haires may a ſollace bee.
               Come to the proffits next each ſtate enioyes
               By iuſt Comerce, and trauailes Counterpoiſe
               How as in man each member aideth other
               So ouer earth each Climes ſuports the tother
               Earth neuer knew it ſelfe while trauell roſe Ouid: am
                        •
                     :
               
               Which did it ſelfe vnto it ſelfe, diſcloſe
               Mans mcrocoſme can ſcarſely be accquainted
               But Brutall be from rationall diſionted.
               Looſe in himſelfe himſelfe his hart vnknowne
               Though in his mideſt but to his god alone
               Much more the Globe, howere the Globe is round
               Thouſands of Angls meere vnknowne a bound.
               One cannot ayd another while vnſeene
               Trauaile the proſpect medium betweene
               A tripart lameleſſe Long poſſeſt its forme
               Whilſt by the force of enter view outworue,
               In reaſons order twas adiudged rownd
               But which wayt only twas by trauaile found,
               Long time paſt Aſſia vaunting all alone
               She onely ſhe in ſcriptures trauaile knowne
               While affrica aſcends on Churches ſtage
               
                  
And doth it ſelfe for E
                     •
                  ropes ſearch engage.
               Downe to the Romans yea to Spaine it comes
               And ſo to Brittaine hither to her homes,
               Thus in a glory trauailes the moſt high
               O
                     •
                  e earth with that his Arke triumphantly
               Brittaine and thule vngill accounted laſt Chriſtoprero columbo, deind Ameri
                        •
                     oue veſputio vnde &amp; Americiae 
                        •
                     omen fortitur.
               
               When we abroad the earth as ſcumm were caſt
               While latlie Lo! as Light
                     •
                  ing trauils flyes
               And then a fourth America deſcri
                     •
                  s
               With worldes of wealth and mines of ore repleate
               And all but man, wild man there vncompleate,
               Sweet trees, raie gummes, rich ores and liluer ſands
               In length and breadth ſurmounting other Landes. Dubartus.
               
               Collumbus and Magellian Prowdly venetrd
               Then Drake, veſpuritis and our forbiſh enterd,
               
                  Peruana and the Mexican are cleard
               But the ſouth regiones what they are vnheard Terra Auſtralis Incogn. ta eſt.
               
               The worlds of wealth thence to our Lands acc
                     •
                  ue
               And the many fertile Coloines inſue.
               In many large diſcoueries is declared
               An therefore ſhall in my diſcourſe be ſpared.
               I onely aime the wealth trade bringes to tell
               All as one houſehold ruld by fate to dwell.
               Europ the chiefeſt right by trauell tries
               Fixe one thoſe Indies your indicious eyes.
               Virginia, and Bermudaes, Brittaine plantes
               And Spaine in her weſt Indian highneſſe vauntes.
               The Northerne riches; whales and fures brings home 
                     Vt enim Solitudo in odioeſt, ita in dulcedine &amp; appetitio ſodalitalis S
                           •
                        nn ep. 9
               
               Things to our fathers, and to theirs vnknowne
               And we the flemiſh French and all crept in
               A part in Spaines rich Indian ſoyle to winn
               As lands ſo Citties yea and men are made
               Potent by trauile, and recourſe of trade
               Whence comes it princes ſcorne not merchants ſtile
               By it their Coſers they with ſubſtance pile
               For as of warr are ſiluer ſtrings the tyes
               So it by trade and trauaile muſt ariſe.
               
                  
That prowdeſt monarck who the whole Earth claimes
               And would haue Earth cald Gods ſtild onely Spaines
               May make a Saint of trauaile for his ore
               Ere thoſe aduentures, neuer prince more poore.
               Twas Tyre, and Memphis priueledge ſo great
               That holy writts their merchandize repeate
               The Hauen Low become now highlands better
               The Ile though but a blott a whole lands greater
               The merchants warchouſe as a princes ſtore
               Some ſtates in rule are rich in venture more.
               Some vſe them as ſupports in a relation
               On to the other mutuall propagation. Quantum quiſ
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      ſua numorum ſeruatin arca tantum habet &amp; fidei.
               
               Defenſiue potence makes trade better thriue
               As trade preſerues a potency aliue,
               No in ſtance but the Netherlands, and hantz
               A mutuall knot, their welfares to aduance.
               Trafickes true nerues armiſtically mixt
               And twixt marine, and land ende avoures fixt
               No way mechannieke for a boore to know Impiger mercator Horrace.
               
               Nor mind I merchants miſteries to ſhowe
               Yet who Denies thoſe miſtery of exchange
               (If able to be ſounded) ſhew how ſtrange
               The proper ſubiects are themſelues ſhould know
               Nor any elſe how goes it high or low.
               How rich to ſtates ye nether Nobles ſay, Omnia adiues habet nam praeſtrantomnia numin. 1. Marcell.
               
               Who her with can Spaines magnitude or ſway;
               And Countercharme his indies by your tra
                     •
                  le
               And the victorious fleets by flemings ma
                     ••
                  e
               Nor dare I banke our eighty eights defence
               Though primely due to high omnipotence,
               The Noblemeane weare ſhips of victory Martius aduerſo dux ſtrennus obv
                        •
                     at hoſti quandr ſub hac veluti palladi bella gerit. Matheus leiueruill vbi:
               
               Mixt with aduentures oſt tryed v
                     •
                  liancie.
               What agents he who trauaile neuer knew
               Wanting ſuch parts as tradings worths a true?
               But by a broker in a forraine ſoile
               Become meere ſlaue to forrainers beguile.
               See citties clad with ſhipping as a robe
               
                  
Whoſe natiues ſend to ſearch about the globe
               How fraught with riches, both of ſoule and minde
               He that perceius not this is wilfull blind
               Sugars and wines we from caunaries haue
               From Florence ſilkes, from Naples ſatens braue.
               From Candy Currants Oyle and muſkadine,
               From Indies Eaſt ſtore of all ſpices fine
               Arabian odoures, ſwete, and 
                     •
                  ubaes ore
               From the Could ruſſe fine furres and fiſhes ſtore.
               From Newfoundland, the norway firr and flax
               The ſwediſh Coppers, Cordage ambers wax,
               The flemiſh hope his linen flanders ſay. Volupias nonniſi varietate confiſtit.
               
               Our brittiſh ſtores wee know no more ſuruay
               The ſea winde weather ſhippings ſtores and ſaile
               All iump the worthes of trauaile to availe.
               So that in ſhort it ſerues the ſones of men
               No more of trauails profits needfull then
               Now forits pleaſures, pleaſure tis to tell.
               Thoſe multitude that do in trauaile dwell.
               Both ſoule, and ſenſes mutually fild
               A ſecret ſolace in them both diſtild
               Chriſts croſſe a modellis of what we ſay
               Tis a meere trauaile paſſing all denay,
               Wherein (as Paule) the chriſtian is aſſaild
               With many woes, to vertues lot intayld
               Yet Lo! as he in all becomes victorious
               And ioyes in ſorrow, by abaſment glorious
               Tramples on ſin and ſorrow by an ayd
               Which makes the fell infernall curres affrayd
               Of this to come, as man all for content
               Poore man his curſes bitter would preuent
               By various obiects reliſhing his toyle
               Whereof he findes out ſome in euery ſoyle
               His ſences ſeruants to his will deſire
               Nothing ſo much as noueltie require,
               Wiſe Solomon ſaw this when once he ſayd
               My eyes with ſeeing is not ſatiſfied
               
                  
Nor tongue by taſte, nor eares with hearing fild Et deprendi uihill eſſe melius quam Laetari in opere ſua &amp; hane eſſe partem illius Ecleſiafies. Delectant alterna magis vetitiſ
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      potiridulcius &amp; ſordent qua poſſunt ſemper haberi: pallin.
               
               Nor noſe by ſents, nor hands by touching ſtild
               Yet is mens ſolace heere below quoth hee
               To proue what pleaſure may procured bee,
               And as a creature conſolate the mind
               While he in heauen comforts period find
               To this end weare thoſe rares of nature framd
               Where by creation god great power proclamd,
               Diuerſities each clime, and country ſpreading
               Diuerſities, of creatures diuerſe breeding.
               That as the temple made by Solomon
               Was framd of forraine rares as well as ſtone
               From Sheba ſome, from Ophr others ſent
               The Fabricke fmiſht bredd a ſt
                     •
                  ueſhment.
               So we the temples, reaſonable ſoule
               The temple it earths wonders to enrowle
               And view the totall, or iudge by a part
               Each Creatures rareneſſe, the Creators art.
               Our paſſiue humors proue not halfe ſo well
               The actiue chiefly to delight excell
               The ſight, the taſte, and touch, and actions like. 
                     
                        •
                     . Amor,
                  
               
               Thoſe at the ground of noble ſolace ſtrike
               When hearing reading and dull abſence go
               Void of delight, or certainely to know.
               On others pennes or lipps tis to relie
               Onth only organs of vncertainty
               When thou doſt ſee and ſeeing vnderſtand
               The various obiects in a foraine land
               The men in habit, and condition ſtrange
               Their Citties ſites and forme, of ſtru &amp; ures change,
               Religion differre men of ſauage breed
               The rarity in cloth and what they feed,
               There ſpeech and paradox themſelues and all
               Nothing but what thou different maiſt call
               Much inward Cheere the ſences will ſurpriſe
               Taſt, touching ſmelling ſeeing eares and eyes
               
                  
Tis not for vnexperience to expreſſe Dci beneficia omnibus horis Conſideranda. Auguſt.
               
               Such as haue taſted will auouch noleſſe.
               Thout bleſſe thy God for thy Religion pure
               And all will in thee thankfulneſſe procure
               And much contentment in thie courſe of trade
               How ere it with a forrainer be made,
               When thou ſhalt taſt from tree the forraine rare
               Vine iuyce the mirch and ſuch ſpics are
               Viewing the Cloue and cinamonds delight
               And worldes of ſuch a ſtoniſhing the ſight
               Supoſe the pleaſure, and the contentation
               Attend the florehouſes of euery nation.
               When thou ſhalt ſaile the Courſe in ſurges high
               Noting thy ſhip mount proudly to the ſkie Pſalme. 10.
               
               Then delue the deepe then toſſe thee vp againe
               And curtey ſporting with thee through the maine.
               By ayd of card and compaſſe ſtrangly guided
               And by her way thoſe Labyrinths diuided.
               The dolphin and huge whale ſwim tumbling by
               The mariners their trickes to gore them trie
               Theſe wonders ſhall ſurpaſſe thy admiration Stulta placent Slultis obſonia quiſque palato querit Dignaſuo non emnibus vita voluptas mare: Paline.
               
               Yet cleare thee with a world of contentation
               We ſpeake as men (conceiue vs as we ſay)
               The ſoule we know ſuffied another way
               In midd of theſe ſhees actiue by a hope
               Surmounts wide oceans in their largeſt ſcope
               And by a ioy in praiſe of God Creatour
               Extolling thanfully his wondrs power
               Lo landed now thou canſt not turne thy head
               But cauſe is giuen to bee aſtoniſhed
               To view in Eaſt the Beare and Lyon ſtrong
               The Vnicorne or Elaphant, high and long,
               The heards of wilds Ele, beeuer ernim Fox
               Such ſtores of treaſures deluued out the rockes, Pſalme. 19.
               
               Thoſe many models of ancient ruind things
               The rare Erections of our moderne Kings,
               Thy eye will fixe thy heart one pleaſures midd
               Nor wouldeſt thou for a world haue any hid.
               
                  
But be ſpectatour: twas thewiſeſts wiſh
               Who ſpent much time although a prince in this
               And from the Cedar to the Shrub did goe
               The rares in ſtature amplier to know
               Yet thouſands haue more pleaſures vnderſtood
               Who haue in larger trauailes bin improud
               Twas that thy ſpirit ſhebaes queene thee bleſt
               When thou by hearing hadſt bin now poſſeſt,
               And ſeeing of his worthy gouernement
               Raiſed her ſtrangely to aſtoniſhment,
               To cry thy witt o King exceeds report
               Bleſſed was I to Iury to reſort
               A like the ſonnes of forraine trauailes cry
               When they the wonders where they paſſe ſuruay Nam vt quiſe arnant adhibent ſpeculum, ita geſturus negotium Proponat ſibi illuſtrum virorumexempla Plutarke.
               
               Twas of a truth O King of Kings we ſaid
               Thy wonders, each way ſure weare vndenayd,
               But now behold aboue conceit we finde
               Fair more then could while now poſſeſſe our minde
               O! all thy workes great god thee each way praiſe
               Both ſea and thy fame to heauen raiſe.
               Our factour who in youth full dayes is ſene
               The Merchants goods by enter cource to vent
               When ſeated in the clime, and mannor both
               Now to returne to natiue ſoile is loth,
               The change of cuntries and of pleaſures moue
               This man then there as natiue to approue
               Full oft is ſeene in fortunes great preferd 
                     Viri excellentis antipites varijſque caſus habent admirationem, Laetitium, moleſtiam ſiuero exitu notabili conclud untur expletur mens gaudio ſum
                           •
                        o cicer: Lucullo Epiſto. 12.
               
               And die he there is famouſly enterrd
               Thence if returne parts language and behauour
               Mount him to worth reſpectedneſſe and honour
               He longs and's thirſty through the midd of danger
               To trauaile out, remaine at home a ſtranger
               Such pleaſures, and comodities accrue.
               To men who trauaile honeſtly purſue.
               We ſeeaſtatiſt ſcarſe fixe ſtatſman bee
               Vnleſſe he forraine parts, and paſſage ſee
               
                  
And get more language then his mothers ſay.
               Whereby he coop well for his Country may,
               By writ, embaſſage, treaty or proteſt
               As by his ſtate he then is intereſt.
               He ſportes in all their rates ſo entertaind
               His princes welcome is in him proclamd, 
                     
                        〈…〉
                      venuſtas in mari 
                        •
                     Span quid babies laus eſt omneſ
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      vi
                        •
                     e partes bonaeſunt Me
                        •
                     rodorus
               
               Their wines, rare preſents, pleaſures all are his
               And he though great holds his moſt worth in this.
               Returnd prince, people and religion loue him.
               And the forraine prince (if worthy) all approue him,
               Thus ſoule and ſences, both haue pleaſures cropp
               And's brought by trauaile to his wiſhes topp
               The valiant ſouldier, Captaine, Colonell,
               Will not be confind to his mothers Cell:
               But trie the fortunes forraine quarells yeild
               And learne what proiects there beſit a feild.
               Tryall the Guards french ſpanniſh, and Itallien,
               The foot from flanders, horſe from Poole and Perſian,
               Triumph in ſportes of leaguers fortified
               And haue ſeige, afterſeige his valloures tried
               The perſons here in famous ile nor name
               Since ſhortly we ſhall come to perſons fame,
               Their pleaſures now Ingenerall I note qualis qu
                        •
                     que aerbor tales ſolet dere fructus.
               
               Who do them thus to traueling deuote.
               But know the aime of nobleſt youthfull men
               Is ſtill in forraines to accompliſh them
               Sea captaines in the ioyes of Nauigation,
               Land captiues where warr is extant in a nation.
               Nobles at courſes of greateſt ſport, and fame,
               Merchants to port townes of the richeſt name,
               Diſcouers to the farr remoteſt regiones
               The vnſetled Crac-kbrane 't Anſterdams religiones,
               The noueleſt, to'th ſhadow of a ſieidge
               Rome, Compoſtella, or Caſtillian Bridge,
               Laurettoes relicks, or ould Iuryes Celles,
               The wild and ſauage wonders lapland telles,
               
                  
So each his humour couets to attend
               For trauaile euery humour can befreind,
               Some to the Eaſt, ſome weſt, or Northerue runne,
               Others diſcoueries to the South vnknowne
               All ſorts of ſolace trauelers attending
               And them with their deſired ioyes befending, Quallitates des;iderande
               
               Good propertyes in trauailes learnd are many
               Qualities not inferiour to any,
               Of other ſubiects men on earrh enioy
               Or this our tedious pilgrimage imploy,
               That betters man within, without and both,
               Expelling ſickeneſſe, lazineſſe, and ſloth,
               Subiects man both to health and happineſſe,
               Muſt needs be iudgd an earthly worthineſſe
               True trauailes this it excerciſes men
               That theſe home oppilations choake not them
               Clearing the ſtomacke by the ſeas purgation
               The mind of dumps by motiue recreation,
               The braine of melancholly blockiſhneſſe
               The bo
                     •
                  y of laciuious filthineſſe,
               If well purſued, thus worthy I conclude
               Chearing the ſoule and checking ſonces rude,
               That breeds eternall quietneſſe to men,
               Begetting vertuous faculties in them Virtutem veram qui poſſidet ille beatus ille ſatis felix permitat cetera diuis marcell.
               
               Muſt needs be worthy in their natiue kind
               Worth the embraces of each noble minde,
               Lo! trauailes this humility it cauſes
               Conducting man thence to deſerud applauſes,
               Ciuility breeds by experience made
               Dilligence by true practiſe in each trade,
               Pollicy by ſuruay of thouſands acted
               Patience by endure of griefes effected, Siqua amiſiſ
                        ••
                      vitae gaudia negotiatio eſt parua amitere vt maiora lucrerir:
               
               Pitty by religious obſeruations
               Curteſie from the vſe of beſt ſeene nations,
               Complement from the order of the Court
               Manners and trade where factories reſort,
               
                  
Agillity and actiueneſſe by motion
               Wiſedome collecting euery way good notion,
               Sea arts from view of practizd nauiga ion 
                     Chriſoſt: Rom. 7 ad pop: antis:
                  
               
               Partes from the trauaile of each dayes delatian,
               Language by trade and forayners comerce
               And what in briefe of worth man may rehearſe,
               And though moſt miſſe this, tis not it but them
               Wiſdome is hid from greateſt part of men.
               And man muſt practize long with patience
               And thanke his god for what he gathers thence.
               Therefore I ſay neerleſſe, theſe qualities
               Will vrge the wiſe her worthyneſſe to prize,
               O Could we but conſider at the ſea
               How in a ſtorme the trauailer doth plea Mercator facturus iter terretur &amp; alt
                        •
                     : pectore d
                        ••
                      gemitus, metu ens ſcopulos
                        •
                     reta ventos.
               
               With god for mercy, ayd and preſeruation
               Expecting ſtill a fatall invndation,
               His faith now conflicts with his feare therein
               Vowing to god preſerud neere more to ſin
               But liue renewd and thankfull euermore
               The Lord ore come with penitence deplore,
               Soone ſends a calme as wiſht to cure his heart
               And windes and weather to deſire conuert,
               He paſſes now with praiſes to his maker
               And vowes himſelfe to vice and ſin forſaker
               Next courſe he meetes with pirates oppoſition
               And muſt indure a ſouldiers condition,
               The ſmoake and bullets ſmoake it many die
               A time to importune the god on high.
               If Ionas houſe th' whales belly made him pray
               Or the Deſciples when the ſtorme oreſway,
               Or Paules aſſociates at approching night
               Then needs the chriſtian in his nauall fight.
               His faith and valour grow by vſe more ſtrong
               Praiſes to god in conqueſt are his ſong
               So that the foe ſurpreſſed with the ſight
               By proſtrate yeildance forced is to flight
               
                  
The medicinall rares on earth diſperſed
               With exceilencies not to be rehearſed
               Beſides thoſe waters bath and Spaw excelling Sicredire dignum eſt, Ouid.
               
               Both many noyſome foule defects expelling
               The Poets fictions of acadian welles
               Wherein the per
                     •
                  urd onely dy hee telles
               Azaniam cauſing hate of wines and drinke,
               Matters for puny ſhallow pates to thinke
               Such and a crue of frothy fictions vaine
               As ſotts ſurmiſe, meere ſimples entertaine
               I hate to name, the mentions a diſgrace Colligitac ponit temere &amp; mulatur in horrace imberhis iunen is tandem cuſtode remote gaudet equis canibusque &amp; aprici gramine campivtilium tardax prouiſor
               
               Plaine truth that claimes iuſtly trauailes place
               Her worths are in true properties relation
               Not needing any fained innouation
               Note but the ruſticke hatcht with pap at home
               In mothers mannors; plow-trickes only knowne
               Eyther in Citty or with gentry plaſt
               At firſt how motley raw, diſpiſd diſgract.
               While by the nurtures of a better breed
               Hees with behauiours better farr agreed
               Iuſt thus tis with a new hatcht trauailer Noratrus in Arte p
                        •
                     etic
                        •
                     .
               
               In forraine way on each file bent to erre
               Though iudgd, at home ſufficient any way
               Come heere hees wanting what to do or ſay
               Tis with him thus I ſay and nothing leſſe
               Vntill he parts, and language too poſſeſſe
               His home bredd poſture cannot act his part
               Thats folly heere, theers eſtimate an art
               Experience it wiil worke an Vniform
               And obſeruations ſtrangers hedge from ſcorne
               Tis ſomes ambition they were gentile bred
               Too little mannors taught and too much fed
               When ſuch (as oft it fales) are diſapointed
               And from their former golden hopes diſioynted
               Strange tis to ſee the ſhiftes they vndergoe
               Who neere in youth deſire of worth to know
               
                  
The trauailer (the wiſe it is I meane)
               Though of all fortunes diſpoſeſſed cleane
               Wiſely with ſage, ould Bias ſtill can ſay Omnia me a mecum porto cic: Som: ſc:
               
               Yet all my wealth I beare with me away
               In ſpite of Pirate ſoe of ioſſe or croſſe
               Which would a foole to deſperation toſſe
               My witts my arts and learnings and good life Hipocrates.
               
               Are to me riches, houſes, children, wife,
               A trauailers experience as Phiſition
               Is ſuch as none, s' at home of like condition,
               Each for raine ſoile ſtill ſtored with ſome rare
               Hauing it may be elſe where no compare
               Nepenthes clearing of the broken hart
               Euphones purging of the envenomd part,
               The Corrall, Cipres, Rhewbarb, mandrakes vſe
               The Melt take it for all yeilds ſugred iuyce
               Makes weapons, phiſicks needles, thridd, and line,
               Balme, ſuckets parchments, ſweet purſumes, and wine,
               Cures ſerpents ſting, both french, and ſtone diſeaſe,
               One Indian tree to wonder doth all theſe.
               As places proue in nature all deliciouſe
               So are they ſtill in ſome caſe all propicious
               We ſee ſomes health at ſea got by purgation
               Some in the Eaſterne, ſome the Weſterne nation, Pectoribus mores tot ſunt quot in orbe Figurae: Qui ſapit innumeris moribus aptus crit
               
               Some in the freezing North can thriue a pace
               Some though in ſcorching Southerne come to grace.
               Sorting with noble Dauid in opinion
               That Gods ſole ſoueraine King in each dominion
               Promotion comming not from Eaſt nor Weſt 
                     Ouid 1: Amor.
                  
               
               Nor man alone in North, or South are bleſt,
               But euery where cares cround with good effects
               As euery where the Lord the iuſt reſpectes
               And euery ſoile the wiſeſt hath a thing
               Which will him cuſtome, trade, and traficke bring,
               Good propertios are alwaies worth reſpect,
               As bad deſerue reiection, and neclect.
               
                  
In mentall matters faculties of minde
               Some better one way, ſome elſewhere we find. Flumina pauc
                        •
                      vides magnis de fontibusor ta plurima collectis multip licantur aquis ibid.
               
               The workes of ſages: and of churches too
               Tranſported euery way as ſtill they doe
               So harmonize each documents perfection
               That trauails this way worthy als protection.
               Their ſayings, ours, ours theirs, both ſo ſuruiue
               By mutuall fauour cheriſhed aliues
               Next huma
                     ••…
                  , arts we ſee haue propagation
               By reference twixt nation and nation. Barbaro &amp; Indianor peritia,
               
               How acurate ſome wa
                     •
                   mechanicks are
               Whom chriſtians count but brutiſh in compare
               That now the gray haires of the world appeare
               And age her to confuſed vice doth weare
               Trauails tricks vp and keepe her ſtill aliue
               Noy more, ſhee ſeemes in wrincles to ſuruiue
               Since lately that America ſo vaſt
               Hath her whoel ſelfe to the three ſiſters caſt
               And an acquaintance made by traficking
               Makes our new planters much admire the thing
               Each for his ends: ſome paſſe to bleſſed ends
               Whoſe aime to heathens true conuerſion tends
               Others to liue, to labour, and remaine,
               Tranſplants, from Brittaine, Holland, France, &amp; Spaine,
               
               The properties of traualle ſo imenſe
               Taken in chriſtian; or in Ciuill ſence
               Profit eſteemed worthy als embrace
               Pleaſures and properties excell in grace
               The one aſſuring Chiefly youth to trie
               The other midage, the iudicious eye
               The third to gaine euen aged do proceed
               Vntill they run their glaſſe of time decreed,
               Lo! as the obiects thus in briefe appeare
               Next now their ſubiects in their place come neare
               Examples oft aboue all precepts ſway
               Men mind more how we doe, then how we ſay.
               
                  
Twas the holy order God vſed in creation 
                     Non intendunt qua a nobis di
                        
                           ••
                        ntur gen
                           •
                        ilia ſed quae aguntur 
                           〈◊〉
                         
                        
                           •
                        om. 7. ad pop: autio.
                  
               
               Ands worthy euery artiſts immitation
               The ſky, ſea land, fiſh, fleſh, and all elſe framd
               Then formd he man, and man he Adam namd
               So we the inſtance framd, obiects of worth
               Next ſhall in briefe traine trauailes ſubiects forth
               To name thoſe clouds of ſubiects (men I meane)
               Who haue had part in acting trauailes ſceane
               Is with no art, nor labour to be acted
               As much as need ſhall briefly be compacted.
               And by the goulden rule mete what wee ſay
               In mortall, Chriſtian or in ciuill way.
               So by Commixion of this rule of three
               Summe trauailes worthies ſo their worths to ſee.
               Nor neede diſtinction, we of totall treate
               In trauaile men ſaith God his bread muſt eate
               Iew gentle, all ſome way muſt haue a ſhare Eorum fily dicimur quorum actus nos immitamur Grigen: ineze
               
               And all haue intereſt in what we declare.
               When Adam and his houſe had ſpent their dayes,
               In cares and trauaile wandring many wayes,
               Now by the naked ſword from Edon guarded
               And iuſtice thus their treaſons had rewarded, 
                     Geneſ. 4,
               
               We all attainted, all his ofſpring caſt:
               Yet after him in arebellion haſt S
                        •
                     nce the fall, we trauaile all.
               
               So that our maker miſſing his intent
               Fales now of mans creation to repent,
               For Lo! the Sonnes of God mens daughters wedd 
                     Ca. 5.
               
               Whereby a monſtrous generations bred
               The higheſt angry, powrs his furie downe
               And (but a remnant left) all earth doth drowne.
               Noah and his houſe now trauaile in this flood
               And by his arke the waters are withſtood
               A hundred dayes and fifty ſtraying ſo
               Now all the earth beſide lay drownd below. 
                     Geneſ. 7.
               
               
                  
From Vr to Canan, Abram, trauails next 
                     Caput. 11. 12. 14.
               
               With Heathen ills his righteous ſoule now vext
               Forſakes by Iouahs call his fathers land
               By ſaith obeing this diuine command,
               Through Haran, Bethell, Egypt Terah dies
               At firſt: from Hay he then for famine hies
               To Egypt: yet at Egypt cannot ſtay
               His wife abuſd heere makes him furrher ſtray,
               From Bethell now by his brothers quarell chaſt
               Then captiued by the foure Kings, and diſplaſt
               Thence reſcued by his brothers valient hand
               Thus wanders Abram out his fathers land.
               While aged in yeares, and Iorneyes he departes
               To Machpelah his graue: ſole end of ſmartes.
               Nor differs Iſaack from his fathers dayes Genes. 25. 26.
               
               But as a pilgrime downe to Gerar ſtrayes
               As his ſonne Iſaack, Iacob Iſaacks child
               Wanders by Eſaw (brothers ire) exild.
               Goes pilgrime wiſe to Padan with a ſtaffe
               Trauailing from his natiue brothers wrath,
               To Shechem next, whence, he to Beathell goes
               Where in a caue he takes his laſt repoſe
               A hundred and eighty yeares the one
               And fiue yeares leſſe ould Abram? Iacobs mone
               God heard in famine and a Ioſepth ſends
               Who father land and brethren all befriends
               Ould Iacob trauailes) few and ills my dayes
               (Quoth he to Pharaoh) trobleſome many wayes. Hic enimnos diuerſorium comorandi, non habitandi habebus. cic
                        ••
                      ſence
                        ••
                     
                  
               
               He buried now! note Ioſephs traualle bleſt
               Who in his dayes exceeded all the reſt.
               Though in a pit him firſt his brothers caſt
               There iudgd to die; yet ſaud, then brought at laſt 
                     Genneſ. 37
               
               Carried to Egypt ſet to ſale yea ſould
               To Potiphar 'o wonders to be tould
               
                  
By lot made ruler of his Lords eſtate
               But as beſt meritts meet on earth moſt hate,
               His Ladyes Lawleſſe luſt procures him ire Vt hoc ag
                        •
                     mn
                        ••
                      in deum offendere?
               
               Since his chaſt humour croſt her lewd deſire.
               Hees caſt in priſon yets, exalted there
               When by his diuination dreames were cleare.
               Hee, next made Egypts Lord, weares Pharaohs ring
               And by his trauailes bleſt of bondman, King
               His witts the ſeauen yeares of Famine feeds 
                     
                        
                           •
                        enreſ. 50
               
               Supplying fathers lands and brothers needs,
               Heere ruling fourſcore yeares, much bleſt; then dyed
               When thus in trauaile ſtrangely dignified.
               As thus the father ſo the Church did ſtray
               Ands meerly militant, as ſcriptures ſay. Hic Ecleſiamillitans Illie triumphans.
               
               Not Chaird in roome or any where in reſt.
               But's millitary and in trauailes bleſt
               More then in eaſe, ſtill pooles they gather mudd,
               And drouſie ſweets ſoueſt corrupt good blood.
               Both Church, and ſoule, and vertues mount more high
               As they in trauailes through temptations flie. Exodus. 15.
               
               Yea man is modell of the whole we ſay
               Beſt are the beſt men, moſt when motiones ſway. Exo. 1, 2, 7, 8, 9.
               
               Earths in fancy in trauailes nurſed euer
               The Churches in the partriarks thus peſeuer,
               Come now to any growth is Egyps hate
               Ioſeph now gone the blood hound of her fate
               The bondage noted and theit cryes come vp
               Moiſes is raiſed to beget a hope
               Lo! hee at firſt ſaued among the reedes
               And mid wiues knife) him there his mother feeds
               By pharaohs daughter fownd) pitty preſerud
               Nurſt him and ſo's in Pharaohs Court preſerd,
               Where he in ſtate did forty yeares abide
               Whence in greate feare he downe to Midan hied
               Kept ſheepe a while there married alterd thus
               The Lord accommpanies him in a Buſh.
               
                  
Sends him to court thence to redeme his land Vide 
                        •
                     t Iſraelitarum vita deſeribitur quinque libris moyſt Ioſue iudicu
                        •
                     r, &amp; regum.
               
               Where hee with wonders doth before Pharaoh ſtand
               Turnes waters blood, brings frogs, and flies and lice
               Murren ſores thunders graſhopers and nightes
               Inſtead of dayes next are there males deſtroyd
               In trauails thus is Moiſes now imployd.
               Is pharoahs god: the ſocerers Admiration:
               Egyps ſcourge, but deliuerer of his nation
               Bring Iſrael ſafe through the ſea, when foes are drownd Caput, 14.
               
               Six hundred thouſand ſtrong the church is found
               And is to Canaan promiſd traueling
               Hauing bene foure hundred yeares flaues to that king Deutronom. 13
               
               forty yeares trauaile hath now ere they reſt
               Being in their trauailes wonderfully bleſt
               Apparell weares not nor dare foe withſtand Exod. 13, &amp;c.
               
               Pillar of fire their day ſtare, cloud on land
               Forty and two great iorneyes in the wild
               The Rocks yeild waters, are with manna fild Ioſuah: 1.
               
               And with all dainties ſtill their iorneys flowe
               Their foes the heathen haue the ouerthrowe,
               In view of Canaan come, now Moiſes dies Caput. 24.
               
               And with the rule God Ioſua dignfies,
               Who Ierico, then Ay quite ouerthrowes
               And flayes both prince, and people of their foes Iob: 1, 2, 3. &amp;c
               
               Thirty and one lands they in trauaile got
               So now the Church parts Canaan by lot,
               Triumphs in Rule of iudges would ye know
               The caſe more cleare? behold the ſcriptures ſhow Caput. 42. 10.
               
               Nor can we chriſtians ſure be ignorant
               Of what the Iewes of trauaile vſe to vaunt
               This onely this, may ſerue to ſhadow foorth
               The Patriarckes, Churches both their trauails worth.
               About this time was holy Iob in eaſt
               In mortall trauaile oh ſo much oppreſt
               Bereft of Children goods and freinds turne foes
               Be guirt by ſathan round and round in woes
               
                  
Yet Lo! when patience had her perfect aime Ruth. 4 13
               
               Hees eaſd of trauaile and releaſt of paine.
               Come on to ruth a woman trauailer
               Youl finde it will that weaker ſex prefer
               From Iſraelles famine ſhee to Moab goes Heſtre, 2. 16.
               
               Where for a wife her wealthy Boaz Choſe
               Renowned Heſter of a Captine Queene
               Though poore rema
                     •
                  ning as a iemm vnſeene
               Empreſſe of thirty two great prouinces 
                     Vide litincra Daiud a regum 13. priadſ. cunterlij.
                  
               
               Prouing the Churches fauſter dame in theſe
               Hamans confuſion, Mordecayes ſole raiſe
               One woman all the Churches foes ore ſwaies.
               All telling plaine gods bleſſings where meanes want
               Whoſe loues in trauailes are the iuſt to plant
               I need not name great Dauids trauelling Ionah. 2.
               
               Before nor after he was anointed King,
               Though as a flea by ſaule in trauaile chaſt
               Sauls flaine and Dauid Lord of Iſraell graet
               But to that antitipe of our redemption
               Ionah from plague for ſin had no exemption,
               Caſt into ſea the waues deny receite
               The whale may ſwallow but he may not eate,
               But from his vaſte cheſt caſt him one the ſand.
               And after three dayes poſtage comes to land.
               So now lets hence to the churches head away
               Behold how he in trauailes heere doth ſtray
               While he on earth our ſhape did vnder goe
               For of his life himſelfe confeſſeth ſo,
               The foules they haue their hooles, a neſt each bird
               But I poore I no hole to hide my head
               His mates to trauaile choſe he trauellers Math. 3, 15. Eſay 61. 11. Iohn 46 Ma
                        ••
                      
                     
                        •
                     . 21.
               
               Ship men and fiſhers theſe our Lord preferes
               At Beathlem born hies to Ieruſalem,
               Taking a iorney downe to Egypt then,
               In feare of Herods cruell bloody aime,
               But Herod dead, retireth backe againe,
               
                  
To Gallile: and Nazaret, to teach
               And thence to Capernauum there to preach.
               Much cares and croſſes euery way enduring
               Yet euer teaching, doing good, and curing.
               And Lo! at laſt our Lord is firſt betrayd
               Next by another of his owne denayd,
               Araind, whipt, ſcorned, ſpitted, and deſpiſd Omnis Chriſti actio, noſtra eſt inſtructio auguſt
               
               And at Golgotha after crucified.
               Our Lord and King thus trauailed below
               Waies of earths trauailes to vs all to ſhew
               Now out of ſea in middeſt of many ſtormes Math. 27. Math. 16, 19.
               
               And then on land in middeſt of many harmes
               In hunger thirſt, wants, woes and trauails tryed Math, 3, 
                        •
                     
                     ▪
                  
               
               And now with heauens high honoures dignified.
               To tell vs all and giue vs this to know Hebrewes. 11.
               
               Our reſt is vp aboue and not below.
               Which apprehenſion moues by faith our minde Caput. 14. 12. 10: Baptiſtae vita. Luc. 1.
               
               To ſpend our trauailes heere, that reſt to find.
               That graue forrunner of our Sauiour, Iohn
               
               In wandring through the wilderneſſes knowne
               Hard bred with locuſts, and wild hony there
               Rough ſkinn, and Camels haire his ſofteſt weare Actor, 14. 16. 2. Cor. 5. 22. 1 Tim. 4. 16.
               
               After all trauailes by a virgins hand
               Is ſent to heauen, the forexpected land,
               Now Paul and Peter trauaile Chriſt to preach
               And middſt the gentils Chriſt aſcended teach
               In Selench, Cipres, Lyſtra Pergamus
               Antioch, Paphos Derb, and Epheſus,
               Troas, Cilicia, Creet, Neapolis.
               Athens, Ceſarea, Spain, Amphipolis,
               Macedon, Tyre, Samos, and Milletum,
               Phenicia, Ptolomais, Trogillium,
               Theſe for a mapp of cuntries Paul did ſee
               And laſtly ſuffered Roman tyranny. Apocahp. 1▪ 1,
               
               Weel Cloſe with Iohn to Pathmos baniſhed
               So rownd about it by the ſpirit ledd.
               
                  
Much wonders to him in his trauailes tould
               Propheſies ages ſince each day vn fould,
               And hauing much foretould of Church and nations
               With heauens deſcription ends his relations
               I my relation too of perſons worth
               Who haue the way of chriſtians life chalkt forth
               Cloſing as paul theſe clouds of witneſſes
               Our paſſag cleard by worthies worlds of theſe
               Let's arme our feble ioynts with faith paſſe one
               In trauaile to that high Imperiall throne,
               Now that the matter each way plaine appeare
               Let Ciuill caſes ſee themſelues as cleare.
               Tell of A
                     ••
                  illes valloures victories
               Aeneas great ſea trauails noble prize
               The worthy Curios winning worlds of grownd
               And by partition ſighing each his bownd,
               Thoſe three rare Decij vowd to countries good
               In trauaile and feirce battaile venturd blood
               Hectoreroy hope, renowned Sce
                     •
                  uola Vide policron Graſton.
               
               High Pompey braue victorious ſway) theſe may
               With Fablos and Marcellios (Roomes ſupport)
               And lofty Scipios valours well report,
               Much to haue done in trauaile to regaine, Fortitudo parentum filliorum ſegnitia narrat.
               
               Their countries freedome; friends, and houſes name.
               Now ſhould I downe to moderne times retire?
               To tell the tith would Illiads require,
               That Cordeliew his trauailes in the Eaſt
               And Edwards too thence Saladine ſuppreſt
               Wann much of that ould holy land againe
               Wherein both trauaild vndergoing paine
               Our blacke prince battailes in the ſpaniſh warr
               And conqueſts poicters tell his fathers ſhare,
               Henry of Monmouth rare victorious actes
               Our Glouſters, Warwicks Huntingtons high facts
               In trauaile e
                     •
                  ch for countrie to proceed
               Eliza was victorious indeed.
               
                  
Much of her father, Henries fame france ſayes 
                     Erat fide nobilis quae omnibus ornatibus ornamonto ſine quauil tam ornatam quod ornare queatnin. Salui. ep. 1.
               
               Both ſure a ſpurr to our declining daies
               
                  Forhiſh, braue Drake, and Candiſh, hand in hand
               With Willowbeys high ventures graſt our land.
               But now by trippletye our peace combind
               
                  Elizaes ſecond acts her part behind
               Through Paltz, then Beame (oh! fate) ſhe makes retire
               In ſpire of foe with patience paſt admire
               Long liue the friends of this thriſe noble Queene 
                     Netantiuiri laudes minere oratione m
                           •
                        a potus quam exornarem, culpetur ſane in genium non voluntas Chriſ: de ſacr Liber: 1.
               
               And for her branches dure they euer greene
               While pacient trauaile period hath, and then
               Both ſhall be ſcene victorious to men,
               Gracing his greatneſſe whoſe almighty power
               Keeps time that Romiſh Dragon to deuoure.
               Behold next peace, and prince arrelatiues
               Yet trauaile in her acme ſtill ſuruiues,
               Our Soueraigne ſent his ſonne its worth to learne
               What he before by tryall did diſcerne
               Lo? how ſo high a prince paſſes vnknowne
               That trauailes fame might freelier be ſhowne
               His happy crop, great cauſe of comfort giues
               In peace, and true religion Brittaine liues
               Als ioy, our hope true Chriſtians defence
               Reſts primely in his ſacred excellence
               And long may hee great God our ile defend
               With whom (as period Trauailes worthys end.
               Praiſe we the higheſt, cauſe of each good thing
               Vniting loue, and duty to our King.
               Hy hence in haſt halfe mazd Caliopea
               Refreſh thy ſelfe with conſorts of the ſea
               Both Trauailes wonders, and her worths appeare
               Returne and make thou trauailes way as cleare
               Thy choore's not comon) Momus if thou lowre
               Know them the Iſſues of a vacant howre,
               
                  
The ſacred ſonets ſince compild in verſes
               No ſhame to him leſſe worths a like rehearſes. 
                     
                        〈…〉
                      parent animos, compraendunt plurima paucis: aures delectant, priſtina comemorant
               
               Good matter graced by ſo ſweet a forme,
               Shall not by, time, nor enuie be outworne,
            
            
               
               The way to trauaile.
               LYeurgus lacedemons Lord of ould
               When he youths rudeneſſe did at home behold, Iohn ſab comentar in Ariſt: &amp; hoc.
               
               their wits through eaſe as ſtanding pooles corupt
               Their vertues growth, by ſloth of vice ore topt,
               Adds to his volumes of good lawes this one
               That heel, admitt of none to ſtay at home,
               All youth muſt out) ſome traynd in forrayne parts
               Others in tents in th' feilds muſt practize arttes,
               For there ſayth he they'r cleareſt of temptation
               And may in trauaile learne from euery nation.
               What we haue ſaid of wonders and of worths,
               And of aduantage brought by trauaile forth,
               Is modeld in this wiſe mans obſeruation
               A rule well merits each mans imitation
               For the effects braue Lacedemon graſt
               And him among the wiſe of princes plact.
               But as a wiſer Solomon once ſayd
               Thats truely worth to get it vſe all ayd
               The foole ſees, and neglects a thing of prize
               Where as its ſeene and ſought of ſuch are wiſe.
               That wiſeſt Merchant ſaw a pearle quoth Ieſus
               And bought with whole eſtate whats priſed thus
               Tis not the bare hearing of its worths ſuffice
               But th' way to winn them layd before our eyes. Quaeſe ſcopuloſis ardua clmis, in longum prorum pit iter riget. aſpera prim
                        •
                      ingreſſus.
               
               Of the mannor now or forme wee are to treate
               The goods good iſſue, and the bads deceyte
               
                  
Formes of performance, bad as good we know 
                     Heſ
                           •
                        ed Liber. 1.
               
               The taſke is then the better Part to knew.
               Way as an adiunct locall may be held
               So how attendant fitting to be teld
               Way as the mannor, how to trauaile taken
               Whats worthy choice, whats fit to be forſaken
               The latter part the former comprehends
               And firſt my muſe the formall part intendes.
               Tis aſked how a man may beſt attaine
               When, where, and fitteſt way, to croſſe the maine?
               In courſe of traficke ciuill now we treate
               The Cleargy oft the other way repeate
               And Chriſtian life is plentifully ſpread
               But oft where moſt is known worſt waies are led.
               Yet all accord by right of reaſon too
               He that neere knowes the way can neuer doo,
               In ciuill courſe then know againfull way
               Is from the paths preſcribed not to ſtray Quod bene fit his fit.
               
               For note we this the beſts are worſt abuſed.
               Trauailes the bad of all bads, badly vſed
               Twill in a moment ruing man and ſtate
               And proue of all pathes moſt vnfortunate.
               Turne in a trice the ableſt youth to Death
               And as a viper ſucke away his breath
               What miſchiefes are but it illframd procures
               And man confounded then conſtraind endures, 
                     
                        •
                     uſtitia in ſevirtutes continet omnes. Pythagorus.
               
               Wherefore ſome iuſt proportions to be had
               At firſt twixt man and therein hees to trade
               Tis as the ruler ſtearing trauailes ſhipp
               Els muſt the paſſenger ſuffer wracke in it
               Some coreſpondence, poſſible relation
               The mouing cauſe of tradings propagation.
               Tis not each Boor can trauaile to auaile
               Nor call we each ſlugg-ſhip, can hoiſe a ſayle,
               Nor euery place can euery man befit,
               Nor euery one each way imploy his wit
               
                  
Reciprocall affection muſt be had
               And mutuall betwixt'th, perſon and his trade.
               The ſubiects birth muſt ſute his way he aimes Naturam expelolac furcalicet vſ
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      recurret Haman vid Woolſey. &amp;c.
               
               Birth greater aptneſſe then ye thinke containes
               And mi-imployd beyond its reach deſtroyes
               The man imployed, and what he imployes
               If one vnſkilld rawbred, high matters paſſe
               Hee ſpoiles both matter: and is proud an aſſe
               For ignorance gets ſcorne to him of all
               Beſides the thing muſt wanting mannage 
                     •
                  ale
               The reaſons plaine for natures inbred hue
               Vnpotene made aboue her reach to ſerue
               Struggles gainſt fate; and ſtreames of higher ſtraine
               So needs is forced maymed, backe againe, 
                     
                        Exemp, Phaettonis
                     
                     
                        Proprietatum equabilitas requiritur.
                     
                  
               
               As Iſops frogg effuſe her entrailes out
               Coueting proudly lion like to ſtrout.
               Ambition cauſe of this aſpiring ſence
               Euer in finall fales to impotence.
               We ſee our bould Mechanicke vncontent
               In diſcret way, his manualles to vent
               Will now be merchant yea pry hither too
               Whenſkill elſe pride procureth his vndoe
               Our moderne merchant toſſe a ſtatiſts weild
               Nor will in faſhion ſcarce to courtier yeild.
               Deemes hees imployment 
                     •
                  it o' ſilly ieſt 
                     Preda ſuis tanibus non minus ille fuit metam: lib. 1.
               
               By the ſupply of forriners ſuppreſt
               Much like that aſſe clad in the lions hide
               Vncaſt was ſcornd and woried for his pride.
               As ſuch vnmeete aſcents proue ruinous
               So the moſt baſe deſcents befoole it thus
               When high borne minds debaſe their breed for gaine
               Any ſlauiſh trauaile entertaine
               Or vſe in trauale an vnequall hand
               Matters to low for ſuch to vnderſtand.
               Diſtinction in maters vulgar vſe,
               Twixt perſonall, and Caſuall abuſe,
               
                  
Say ſages truly merits to be made
               When as a vertue out extreames is had.
               The frowne of fate may force a iuſt debaſe
               In men of worth and once in mighty place
               Our ſtories tell, proportion is our meate
               Neceſſities are baniſhed our treate.
               Complect ons coreſpondence to our way
               What natiue vigoures more, or leſſer ſway.
               Muſt be obſerud) according to the time
               And place imployd, and qualitie of clime.
               This in theſe paths is needfully requird
               Elſe if not death, diſgrace quells all deſird
               Natures and nations lump in true relation Numquid amore 
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
               
               Though ſcatterd ore the earth, haue propagation.
               Imploy thy trauailes where theſe likes accord
               And as they inbred powers to do afford
               Hott noble ſpirits actiueſt are found
               As could with flemy ſottiſhneſſe a bound,
               Accord thy place and perſon, firſt vnyted
               To tread a nation like, both be incited
               The Ruſſe, and Norway, or could Groynland trade As in Ruſſy a Groynland &amp;c.
               
               Beſt by the could hard Phlegmaticke is made.
               The coulds extreames ſuch ſafely entertaine
               And may a brother hood in dull coulds attaine
               Is potent made to labour, tugg and toyle
               The beſt 
                     •
                  rchiements in a frozen ſoyle.
               For heere his coulder humours meete their like
               When coulds to death the cholericke ſhall ſtrike
               Or noſe, toes cheeke, and hands, we ſee they looſe
               See then proportion heerein is too be choſe,
               Let nobler natures places nobler trace
               For thers accord twixt natures place and place
               Hott natures actiue bent and paſſiue too
               Able t' inuent, and iudgements ſcann to doo.
               The could are meerly patients practizing
               Alike it is in place in time in thing
               
                  
The rareſt fruites I know take putrifaction
               The ableſt parts, worſt chiefely in ill action
               And as twas iudgd Themiſtocles would proue
               Worſt if ill nurtured beſt by good improue,
               So may we cenſure of complexions power
               In trauaile bent to much gaine or deuoure
               Climes their complexions haue in each degree
               To which in trauaile men haue ſimpathy
               The tozzid zones one ſort of rule command
               A differents cald for in the frigidd land
               The obſeruation trauailers daily vſe
               Makes mee no further now hearein peruſe
               As perſons thus muſt be the places meete
               So ſome proportion due in parts diſcreete
               Twixt him now trauailes, and his way of trade
               For triall heereof muſt at home be made
               Wherein reſpectiuely difference is requird
               According to the ſtate of that deſird
               Some generall parts, as ſtrength and languages Qualitatum proportio.
               
               According to the clime, all muſt haue theſe.
               Particular notions as now intereſt In vitium ducit culpae fuga ſicaret arte. Horatiua.
               
               If as in publike or his owne inveſt,
               I cannot ſtand to point at each mans way
               The wi
                     •
                  e may ſee the whole by what I ſay.
               And application proper to the thing
               Can on ly ſollid ſatiſiaction bring.
               He muſt haue tongues each way bownd out to treate
               Elſe ſhall he be a pray to mens deceit. Recte collata retina expectant predam
                        •
                     -
               
               Each aiming at his properends availe
               And ioyes to ſee the ſortiſh ſtranger faile.
               When ignorant to make his ſales or buy
               Or if abuſed vnderſtands not why.
               If ſouldiour, merchant, greater ſtrangers raiſe
               For what they point to he conſtrained paies
               If a mechanicke hoodwinkt walkes all mumm
               A meete alluſion for all cheates to come.
               
                  
If on his way, ambitious to ſee rares
               In high way errours ignorantly ſhares.
               And what hee ſees, or where, not ſay where now? Ignorantia confuſionis mater non.
               
               But whats a guide to ſtrangers, ſtrangers know.
               Chancing on ſales, turnes now, knaue brokers ape
               For as the Dauus wills 't muſt riſe, or bate Potos, Sotos, deuotes.
               
               Yea if more noble in a treaty ſent,
               If ere ſtate ſent out ſuch an imnecent.
               The tearmes appeare in writing, as if there Hiſp: pro.
               
               A ſcipher ſent, and no Embaſſage weare
               In ſhort ſend any meere vnletterd out
               And hees a noſe of wax made out of doubt.
               Tis true times ſhort and many cannot haue
               Paris for each place, where tranaile paſſage craue
               But let vs note language collatrall mixt Non ſateſt bene ali quul ſacere viſietiam fiatvenuſte.
               
               Vnder both Poles by prouidence is fixt
               And generall tongues for generalls lead way
               Which generals each way ſpecials ouer ſway.
               Ould Roman Latin in the weſterne lands
               Italian, Spaniſh, French, and vs commands,
               Ould Greeke the ſpacious Adriaticke climes
               Hebrue the Eaſt, honourd in firſt of times.
               High Dutch the daniſh pole, and Northerne tracke
               So hauing one we cannot wholly Lacke
               And by the generall language that way vſd I anuo lingnarunt gramatica.
               
               Perticulars will more eaſily be infuſd
               Since a propenſitions cauſd in tongues confuſion
               Many as members haue to one head alluſion
               Then fit thy ſelfe ſuch ſpecialles to collect
               And lazineſſe worths canker worme reiect.
               The many parts each ſtate of way requires,
               Cauſing ſucceſfull progreſſe in deſires
               Are in ſuch ſpeciall mannor ſuting it
               So as no parts but ſuch in that place fit.
               In all a ſearch is eaſily made: Let thoſe
               Who paſſe themſelues it to themſelues diſcloſe.
               
                  
The fourth and laſt attending the perſons grace Equabilitas infortune bonis.
               
               I hould propertion 
                     •
                  n Eſtate to place,
               Aſſighning period to the three before
               The rudder ſteareth ſteadily to ſhore
               Mon
                     •
                  es Great Traian tearmes trades nerues to be
               This we in daily courſe of traficke ſee.
               When language, natures worth, mens bredings faile
               Now meanes in trauaile ſeeme to ſtrike their ſaile.
               Yea in the merchanicke how beit their hands
               Seeme to ſupply this want in trackt of landes
               A ſmall tis true accomodates his place Qvantum quiſ
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      ſua, &amp;c,
               
               When higher ſteps aſcend a higher race
               Which as it muſt of force in vſe be had
               So like wiſe coreſpond the place to trade.
               I ſay no more let ſpecials be applyed
               The merchants this way chiefly dignified
               Where many lands, and rarityes are eyed.
               As a meere oreplus; to the gaine of trade;
               Which to aduantage is in forraines made.
               Plesſures attending profits euery way,
               Others conditions coſtlier are to ſtray.
               For trades encreaſe, and minds contents concure
               Accomodating each by trading fuir. Quam fauſta
                        •
                      habet regma pecunia ſortes vt
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      ſit hec ſeltx quamque beata vide ibid. Aruillarj vbij
               
               The faſhioniſts expences buy his humour,
               The nouelliſts paies dearely for a rumour.
               The Noble gallant ſpends, no ſubſtance gaines
               The aiery Camelion only feeds his braines,
               Meanes is the matter, formd by all the reſt,
               But their effects it wanting all ſuppreſt.
               Yet as the little puffe makes ſmall barkes fly
               When greater Caricks, wind bound grouling lye:
               So ſmailer meanes a m
                     •
                  aner way well ſerues,
               When wanting ſuſtenance a greater ſterues
               Or Comes confounded in his croſſed wits,
               This of the foure the perſons ſelfe befits.
               Subiects that haue good adiuncts their attendants,
               Well grace their owne worths, mutuall defendants.
               
                  
Two ſorts of wayes one method hath propoſd
               What way man goes in as his cauſe diſcloſd
               Whereto or which way and the clime, thats next Via in qu
                        •
                     .
               
               The time, and theſe kept trauaile's vnperplext.
               The way or ſtate man paſſes in is tryed,
               And by this touchſtone needfully diſcried.
               If conſonant, not croſſe to pious life, Non nobis ſolum natiſumus ſed liberis, ſed a micis &amp; patriae.
               
               Nor cauſe of countries, or religions ſtrife.
               And honeſt iuſt, and voyd of fraud and guile,
               Cauſing thy owne weale too, this good way ſtile.
               Which foure, though foure, are linkt in vnity.
               And handmaids to our chriſtan trauailes bee. Cicero: de offi.
               
               For chriſtian trauaile it all trauailes bleſſes,
               If not beſure thy harboures in diſtreſſes.
               For us not for vs chriſtianst' vnderſtand,
               As heathens do als good to take in hand,
               After we once from natiue Climate goe,
               As if the great God did not all lands know
               Hee ſees in ſecret as wiſe Dauid ſayes
               As ſeend I to the Heauens, Heauen he ſuruayes
               Decend I downe to Hell he noteth me,
               And in the midd of darkneſſe he can ſee.
               Yea ſhould I ſay Ile hence to ſea als one.
               Or to the outmoſt Ile, he there's well knowne
               Tis therefore mee
                     •
                  e we Chriſtians ſtand in awe
               Forming our trauailes to Iehouahs law
               Well may we then expect great happineſſe
               And in moſt aduers times deſire ſucceſſe 
                     
                        •
                     t quis non cauſas mille doloris babet.
               
               Alas whats Earth as ſea vs mortall tofſes
               Sometimes in ſunny calmes and then in croſſes
               Our deſtinies our ſhips tranſports vs ore
               Times trimmer of the ſailes and hies to ſhore Ouid amor.
               
               What men? all men are paſſengers therin
               Some trauaile in gods ſiruice, ſome in ſinne
               Gods hand it ſteares, yet none the hand can ſee,
               Nor yet fates fleets, wherein we ſayling bee
               
                  
Some ſport, ſome ſleepe, ſome worke, the voyage hies Vns hore zey
                        •
                     
                  
               
               Youth midage, dotage, poſting through he flies.
               Our harbour Earth, graues houſes, welcome death, Royta
                        •
                     n ſkepke royt: all zij
                        •
                     gh diewills ver 
                        •
                     i moyt in hettzee van tribulation icke zal vster ckene met in i
                        ••
                      gration.
               
               By ſortowes, ſickneſſes, when loſſe of breath.
               Thus ore earths ocean glides our fatall ſhipp
               Iehouah ſteares, time rowes, man ends by it;
               This mortall trauaile; Chriſtian conſumates
               And though in both we are guided by the fates
               Yet may we gueſſe ſucceſſe by our attempts,
               And by the forme of trauaile iudge euents.
               Nor need we part, but in the whole we ſay.
               Come by both Chriſtian and Ciuill way.
               With piety our trauailes muſt agree,
               Nor muſt our gaine religions ruin be.
               That proteus like, we as a feather change
               Nor through religions as through realmes we range. Heylichey
                        •
                      ni
                        •
                     t in de ſc
                        •
                     ii
                        •
                     .
               
               Loue Caluin heere, there Luther: Bellermine
               And to aduantage make a ſtall of ſinne
               See maſſe, hugg relicks, trade in Images,
               Bulles, paxes, pardons, or like traſh as theſe.
               Nor as the preiſt, and giddy braine ſteale ore,
               To ſerue before their ſtate, that Romiſh whore.
               And when returnd plot miſchiefe day and night.
               To make ſome ſimple puny profelite
               Entiſe alaſſe in ſhape of boy diſguizd.
               Ore to a Cloyſter to bee Idolizd
               Where oft her guts giue way to ore deuotion,
               And in rebellions rumour make comotion,
               Our crackſculd Browniſt ſteale to Amſterdam,
               Ore to tribe of Gad, their chambered cham.
               There cucko like our Church their Dam bewray
               Profeſſing als prophetical they ſay
               Runn ſtrange diuiſion on their iarring muſe.
               When ſtill the cloſe is natiue ſoyles abuſe.
               In ciuill caſe the mono Politan
               Aiming as Atlas, trades, whole orb to ſpann
               
                  
Feeding open the generall defect Our 
                        〈…〉
                      tranſporters. Ex malo dogn
                        •
                     
                     te pra
                        •
                     uſque moribus dig
                        •
                     oſcuntur lupi. Melancton.
               
               Theſe wayes and more paſt namm meritt reiect
               The comon good we Croſſing cannot thriue,
               But our diſgraces in our deedes ſuruiue
               Nor can in iuſtice fraud, or falſe deceites
               Proue ought but grauell in our taſted meates
               Conueiances exceeding law neere thriue
               When men their common weale of weale depriue
               Turne machiuillians by coueyance ore,
               Of whats in proper of their natiue ſtore.
               For forreynors tis baſe; a worſer thing.
               In ſuch as owe alleagence to their King,
               L'o next our trauaile muſt our owne good breed
               Youl ſay this caueat ſure is more then need
               Tis true the other three the fourth Create
               None benefits himſelfe vndoes his ſtate
               Nor can it be thy gaine thy god offendes,
               Nor when thy trauailes in vniuſtice endes,
               Yet bodily ſome faculties weare meete
               Mentiond before (doubt ye looke backe and ſeet)
               And howſoeuer matters paſſe relation,
               Which out the womb of time haue propagation,
               Yet each may view many vndone alas
               By raſh attempts of trauaile brought to paſſe.
               Somes progreſſe to Vtopia for a toy
               Making their mendicant pilgrimage a ioy
               Currey from Saints to relicks, vp and downe.
               Others by plotting miſchiefe ſeeke renowne
               As Heroſtrats, or Dioniſe ſeeke grace,
               Their owne lands welfare, by their force to face
               Riot and reuell in a lawleſſe wiſe,
               As if their trickes were ſoly worthy priſe.
               Neclect their natiue family, and roue
               After ſome forraine whotiſh lawleſſe loue
               
                  
At leaſt wiſe wander in a thriftleſſe kinde
               Deprauing both the body and the minde Spend
                        •
                     briſts
               
               Such holy writ ſtiles worſe then infidels,
               Whoes careleſſe of his houſhould where he dwels
               And Solomon tearmes a deſtroyers matc,
               The man (more ſoole) that lauiſhes his ſtate
               But ſince our treaty yet ſome pilot wants
               Come we to trauailes true concomitants
               Vertues adorne the progreſſe of the action
               Keeping, its body cleare from putrefaction
               Of vices poyſons fogg, obſcuring earth, 
                     Sollace. Our crack braines come bome by weeping croſſe Qui populari inititur aur a domini in luto extruitur. Mach. 1. princip.
                  
               
               And none as theſe our late dayes equall birth.
               In danger deſperate, and diſconſolate,
               Many ſuch ſymtomes could I now relate.
               But ſee at ſea their frothineſſe is ſcourgd,
               And by a timely pyll there braines are purgd,
               Turne taile to trauaile now retird to ſhore,
               Loue England now ſo well theyl out no more.
               Others in raſhneſſe (placed) dominere,
               As if they Lords, or Denizons weare there
               Eſteeme their pride extold in als abuſe,
               Forgetting fooles they'r heere with out excuſe,
               Are bandied well, informd their not at home.
               And th' other ſweet tooth glad to picke a bone.
               Oh ſy! that trauaile ere allowd ſuch brats,
               Fitter to hedge the fier with doggs, and catts.
               For there they ſtill may play with mothers dugg,
               And pamperd, counſell with an Iriſh rugg.
               Prouident trauaile neuer hatch theſe braines,
               Tis true ſhe ſtill of their abuſe complaines,
               Fond Chimy Cricket know that trauailes way, Orſt: weſt: Thys: beſt.
               
               Is danger, and aduenture: and no play.
               The beſts are hardeſt euer to be gaind
               And with endurance muſt be entertaind
               
                  
In dye
                     •
                  , reſt, ſpeech, welcome, people all,
               Make no exceptions take what lots beſale.
               Expect no ſleepy ſollace as at home,
               Nature it differs in each clime is ſhowne,
               Expect no other but a ſhare in croſles,
               As thou through trauailes deſert each way paſſes
               With good Lo! bad muſt equaly be ſhard,
               Prouide then, be thou for them both prepard,
               See as a ſecond dilligence attends,
               The man that trauaile honeſtly intends.
               Sagacity by ſages termd of ould,
               When wits are actiue and heereby more bould
               Timely aduantage in our way attempt
               And what a foe may plot that to preuent
               On raging ſeas yeald haſt a ſtorme to ſtill, Dilligentia-Sagacitas. Nil tam d
                        •
                     fficile quod non ſolertia vincat. Temperantia, Modum vocoid non dolorem afferens Pythagoras.
               
               And valiently oppoſe a pyrates ſkill.
               If croſt by ſtrangers curteſies timely vſe,
               Whereby a foes engaged not to abuſe.
               If trafickes commodities to cull,
               Yeilding in ſale a harueſt plentifull.
               Hower employd, for tis not to repeate,
               Our ends to purchaſe and preuent deceipt
               Neclects aſſaylants, do moleſt this care,
               And ſottiſh dulneſſe, in a ſlow prepare
               Time crownes with lawrell gaines a quicke embrace,
               And dilligence will many lets diſplace.
               By temperances rule and bodyes kept,
               From routes of illes, in latter ages crept.
               Comands the ſences, rules by moderation,
               In drinke, and meate, according to the nation,
               And pleaſures, too, for know no vice more raighnes
               Then this intemperance in youthfull veines.
               Incontinency iſſues as effect,
               And due reward of temperance neclect.
               
                  
Much like the paſſages of drunkenneſſe,
               Worthily ſaid our Brittons to poſſeſſe.
               As heare at home: in forraine ſoile men tell
               Some place their packhouſe in a frothey Cell moderation praiſed. Quis ſecum preit? ebri
                        •
                     tas, ſopor, otia, Lux us qui comites? rixa, bella, odiae opprobium.
               
               Puft vpſe Dutch, nor failes Laſciuious end,
               Immoderate drinkings duly to attend.
               Whereon the Epicurean vaine ſerues conſtantly,
               Let trauailes worthies worthleſſe vices fly.
               So ſhun ſuch ſinnes ſo many ſtill deſtroy.
               Vnhappy he intemperance ſhall imploy.
               Some haue I noted who haue dyet kept
               In eating, drinking: and pleaſures ſweetly ſlept, Marulus
                        •
                      Lecheritanians.
               
               When others on a ſurgions box append,
               Or on a doctours bill as bad attend
               Some haue I heard of wiſely note the Clime,
               Great dangers to preuent by keeping time.
               In riſing after foggs by ſunn are cleare,
               A death to othets who neclect it there
               The freezing could in ruſſe, know how to quaile,
               And in the Torrid cuntreyes heets aſſaile
               Swellings and ſuddaine pa
                     •
                  ſies ginny boyles.
               For diuerſe illes encounter diuers ſoyles.
               Men muſt, as Maſiniſſa keepe good dyet,
               Elſe muſt the body languiſh out of quiet.
               Luxurious ſardinapals imitation,
               And Bachus Trophyes are in euery nation.
               Couers thou now to ſhun theſe lyon clawen
               Be temperate, and timely ſhun the cauſe.
               For venery is occaſiond oft by Drinke.
               Then men once in, turnd prodigals, ſoone ſinke.
               Wherfore an oppoſition muſt be framed,
               Whereby the lets of trauaile may be tamed,
               Prudence of morall virtues for her grace
               Merits her ranke in trauailes primeſt place,
               
                  
The ſtraites of vertue ſo by vice beſet,
               As we may well perceiue a world of let.
               Where for an oppoſition muſt be framed, 
                     
                        Prud niia eſt habitus agendi orta human 
                              •
                            b
                              •
                           na v
                              •
                           ra cum 
                              〈◊〉
                           .
                     
                     
                        
                           
                              〈…〉
                            Vt corpus abſque 
                              •
                           ceulis, ita &amp; vir
                              •
                           r n
                              •
                           gotio im-prouidens By
                              •
                           n
                     
                  
               
               Whereby the letts of trauaile may be tamed,
               Prudence of morall virtues for her grace
               Merrits her ranke in trauailes primeſt place
               By prouidence the armies ſentinell.
               Diſcry the things that let to trauaile well.
               Forſee the Weſterne luſt with chaſt intents,
               And th' drunkneſſe in the Eaſt alike preuents.
               The vices that attend in court and citty,
               Becomming by the better view more witty.
               It being no leſſe wit ills to eſcue,
               Then that is good by ſcience to purſue,
               A quality, next ſeruing to her worth.
               Wherby a forme of mannage iſſues forth:
               Gracing the ſubiect with admird affection,
               An induſtry well merits alls amplexion
               Pericles ſcience praiſed is heerein,
               As did V
                     •
                  liſſes in his Homer winn.
               Pirgoteles heare by the picture drew.
               To Allexanders wiſh when none elſe knew
               Good Ioſephs foreſight in his trauailes feed,
               Pharaohs, al, Egypts, fathers, Brothers need
               And moiſes ſcience, and great weekeneſſe raiſd,
               Him though a man of Great loue to be praiſd.
               The Churches trauaile, wants, and wichedneſſe,
               By his contriuing, purchaſed releaſe.
               Yea ſo hath arts by ſearch bin brought to light,
               When ſciences peruſe proues mans delight.
               Tireſias, and Archilochus for lines,
               And Ariſtotle phiſickes beſt of thoſe times.
               As Bazaleel, and Aholiabs ſkill.
               God thoſe thus with his ſpirit did fulfill.
               All Curious arts of ſciences to know,
               
                  
And one the temples fabricke all to ſhow
               Thus prouidence is ſent forth to proiect,
               How to ſupplant in trauaile each defect. Opitime crede i
                        •
                     uat rerum pru dentia cunctos, ledtiur aduerſoqui necligit vndi
                        
                           
                        
                        que
                      fate-Heſiod. Note.
               
               This ſeconded by ſcience to an action,
               Both to the ſubiects trauailes ſatiſfaction.
               The Contraryes encountring in this ſeaſon,
               Are raſhnes, and a ſhallow vſe of reaſon.
               Raigning in many a giddy ſtraying pate,
               Who all thinges done doth to the fancy ſhape,
               Lantloping crocheits, any way is beſt. Landloper.
               
               When once the giddy humoures prepoſeſt.
               Little for ſeeing Scyllaes ſtraights ar nigh,
               As they in trauailes from Charibdis flie
               For know howere our whole diſcourſe is forth,
               Of trauails wonder, praiſed way, and worth:
               Tis not to be aſſumd as due to all,
               But only ſuch whom God to it doth call,
               In honeſt wiſe, tis the Appoſtles caſe,
               Wherere mans cald, abide he in that place,
               Conditions praiſd are propper to the men,
               Who are and rightly too inſtald in them.
               And euery man his limits due aſſighnd, Giddy pate-Nunquam tefall aut animi ſub vulpe latentes impia ſub dulci melle venena latent Auguſtin.
               
               We muſt dehort, not raiſe a ſtragling mind,
               Leaſt by refuſall they with Icarus,
               Or Phaeton deſcend to ruine thus.
               Such haue I ſcene in giddineſſe depart,
               From a good ſettled Courſe t' ſome forraine part,
               Squander their meanes in fruitleſſe lawleſſe life,
               Vncald forſaking families and wife,
               Yet ſhrouded euer in ſome poore pretence.
               Of need, friends, bettering faith or conſcience.
               Some ſmall time ſpending vainely, guld retire,
               With pouerty the fruite of raſh deſire.
               What mans to build ſaith Ieſus will not firſt
               Able, or not to end bee prepoſſeſt.
               
                  
Or who is to encounter any foe,
               But firſt his owne ſufficiency will know?
               And if too weake in time from both ſurceaſe,
               Of thoughts to builde, and ſue to haue a peace.
               For know this raſhneſſe founded one the ſend
               Of impotencie withers out of hand
               Such haue I ſeene in diet diſapointed,
               In raging humour on the waues diſtoynted.
               Curſing the climate next, the hochpoch there Iuſtitia in ſe vir
                        ••
                     tes 
                        ••
                     ntinel omnes.
               
               Longing for Engliſh powder beefe, and beare
               One cryes his bones Crach on the Cabin ropes
               A ſecond as forlorne now nightcome gropes
               A third nice youth his clothes are ſpoyled cryed
               Would to god when I came downe I had dyed.
               Of iuſtice worth I ſomewhat ſayd before
               And only ſpeake a diſtribution more
               Comutatiues in dealing iuſt proportion
               Diſtributiue in Charities deuotion
               Giue each his owne in way of honouring De iuſtitia vni
                     
                        •
                     uique quod ſuum diſtribure cic, do: offe:
               
               Feare God aboue fitſt honour then the King
               Preſerue thy credit, and thy fellowes ſtate
               Whoſe chance in trauaile is to bee thy mate
               Do as thou woulſt be done by, Chriſt commands
               And deale with iuſtice, almes in other lands
               A generous and noble minde is meete
               That men may praiſe thy country when they ſet'
                     •
                  
               
               For ſuch as thou thy land ſtands eſtimate
               And by the ſubiects men adiudge the ſtate
               Contraryes are that miſer 
                     ••
                  arous
               Who count a ſtranger as a dogg to v
                     •
                  
               
               Where as the Church of Iſraells c
                     •
                  ld to cheriſh
               The ſtrangers heart, and none by need to periſh
               The Prodigall one luſts will rather ſpend
               Then ſtriue the poore and needy to befriend,
               
                  
Let none here neyther enter a miſtake
               Frugality next trauails worth I make.
               A ſauing habit of both time; and ſtate, Frugalitas cla
                     
                        •
                     is conſe ruandi quod eſt maphae: Note. Magnanimitas▪
                  
               
               Making a man thrifty and conſiderate.
               A worth if ere in any courſe required
               In this its ten times more to bee deſired.
               Preuents a famine oft of ſtore at ſea,
               Yers mercifull when others wantings plea.
               Attends at pinch, and in extreames befriends.
               When lauiſh prodigallity ſtill ſpendes. Si fortuna. Sonat caveto 
                        •
                     o'li, cum fortuna tona tonat: ca
                        •
                     e to mergi Cato,
               
               So haue Poſt ſeene ſouldiers vaineſſe payd
               When with the pot and pipe purſe is decayd
               Trugg towid the Lumber (foole) for more ſupply,
               And now beginnes on lauiſhneſſe to crye
               Where had he i
                     •
                  ueld meanes and ſcore at firſt
               Good licour might ſerued, ſtead of thirſt
               So much in ſhort, one inſtance ſtands for all,
               And hence I downe to next of vertues fall:
               Being a mind magnauimouſly bent,
               With courage ereſſes bitter to preuent:
               Armd in a faith and hope in a tempration
               Anchord firme in gods mercy paſt narration,
               To this the ſcriptures plentifully moue,
               And dayly tryals wonder or ſly improue.
               A barr againſt whole billowes of temptations
               Calling man to diſpaire, in croſſe of nations
               Croſſes are the godlyes lot, true churches ſate
               The earthes ſur
                     •
                  ayours; euery mortals ſtate
               Whence comes it trauailes termd the Godlies lott
               No perfect ſollace can below be got
               The ciuill trauailer firſt (if chriſtion) ſuffers
               Then as a mortall, many, croſſes ſhares.
               Next in his place (for no place ſo defended
               But ſometimes is and ſhall thus bee attended)
               Sometime by ſhip wracke, then by pirates theft
               And then by truſt of any eſtate bereft,
               
                  
Now in profeſſion, then in body beates,
               Then in his trauailes multitudes of cares.
               But Lo! his courage, chriſtian faith begets?
               When any danger ſea or land beſets:
               As Paul hees bould, and fortifies the reſt,
               Being with a heart magnanimous poſſeſt.
               For all things worke he knowes to him for good
               Nor can he be by Hell or Hagg withſtood.
               Croſſe to this worth is fearefull pale diſtruſt,
               Not rating God as mercifull as iuſt.
               Twas the diſciples weakeneſſe; Thomas ſault, 
                     Gratia bene ordinas quae dedit creatio Bernardus in tract: Degr
                           •
                        : Lib: 6:
               
               And too to common ſtill when ſtormes aſſault.
               Or hight of a preſumption in our ſelues
               That th' apprehenſion faith begetteth quelles.
               Thus Peeter ſtood, vpon his reſolution,
               Which made him fall to fearefull in concluſion.
               Though all for ſake thee Lord yet will not I
               Yet lead he firſt the other to denye Note!
               
               Now to a habite effable we come
               Not to be Churliſh bent, or Cinickſom, Effabilit as quid.
               
               Vneffable behauioures purchace hate Haman.
               
               And ſcorne of ſtrangers in a foraine ſtate,
               Yet ſee wee ſome, too many too aſpird Ixion!
               
               Into ſome ſtate of trauaile as deſird:
               Stand puff, and huff, to natiues coming ore Phaeton!
               
               The prieſt forgets he was a clearke before Icarus!
               
               Lookes ſquint at ſtrangers turnes imperious
               A ſmall imployment, hoiſts a Haman thus Primus mali m
                        •
                     tor cachedra peſtilent a ſuperhia, Auguſtin
               
               And higher to! Tis one of thoſe great illes
               Solomon ſayth Earth with impatience filles
               A ſeruant when he raignes, a foole in hanſt:
               wiſe men on foot, and ſotts on horſe aduanſt
               Denyes to know, condition, or kinn,
               Or as a iockey, euer to haue binn
               Armes fixt agambo, and his beauer cocke
               Is learnd in better manners by a knocks
               
                  
Sequeſtred pride, attends a ſpeedy fall,
               whereas the meeke are effable to all.
               Procures of forraynes by the fact a loue,
               Yea with the very infidels approue.
               Thoſe churliſh Nabals, Doeg minded men
               Neuer ſucceſfull ſcarcely one of tenn.
               Come thus farr through the paths of traualling, Ambitis ſecretum virus. pe
                        •
                     
                     tis occulta doliartifex mater hipocreſts liuori
                        •
                      parens vitior un
                        •
                      origo tinea ſanctitatis cordium excatrix. &amp;c: Bernard: in ſer q
                        •
                     adrageſſ-
               
               Lets in our courſe obſerue another thing.
               Verity to be vſed in word and deede
               Through all the paths of trauaile we proceed.
               Adding a credit mid the ſtrangers towne.
               And purchaſing a truth of much renowne.
               For witneſſe, hand, and oth, thus bare word paſſes
               And much a chriſtian Cariage each way graces.
               When lying ſtops a ſtrangers loue intended,
               And trechery when matters paſſe pretended.
               Twas Abners bane, yea Ioabs, Iudas kiſſe,
               Recorded for a trechery in this.
               Great Allexanders fame allurd to trechery.
               By baſe Parmeno, that I ſhould gain ſay.
               Was I Parmeno, but I am my ſelfe,
               And prize ſayre victory aboue all wealth.
               Worthy Fabritlus tould pirrhus though a foe,
               How he was moued to his ouerthrow.
               Not Ianus Bifrons with a Harpey ſmile,
               Bent both wayes equall falſely to beguile:
               But Ionathan like patterne true affection,
               Merits true trauailes grace: a falſe reiection.
               Seeſt thou a ſmooth ſalute, proffer too great
               Beyond relation? Conſure a deceipt
               The whiſtle ſweetly playes the fond birds hye Note! Beware of machi uillian fawning, &amp; ſimplician ſlaues.
               
               Thus are ſurprizd by th'fowers fallacie.
               Comes one to ayde thee ſlauiſhly officious.
               Such haſty helps haue births are to pernitious
               The wolfe will worke the ſleepe from out the bryer
               Poore ſheepe thy ruine is his next deſire.
               
                  
Thy language, and thy owen endeauours truſt;
               Vnuſed armours ſubiect are to ruſt:
               And mens deceipt is ſilly ones to cheare
               They know experience will not brooke dec
                     •
                  ite N
                        •
                     te;
               
               Findſt thou a country man of baſe report,
               With him of all men neuer once reſort,
               No Iew or Turke can proue more rauinous:
               Then will a chriſtian once appoſtulate thus.
               Auoyd as death a reconſciled foe,
               Nor euer with him confidently goe. Weſt 
                        〈◊〉
                      ende 
                        〈…〉
                     .
               
               The ſore ſmothd vp not cured out will f
                     •
                  ie,
               And ſoonſt infect a careleſſe ſtander by.
               Man of a croſſe religion do not truſt,
               He hath cauſion
                     •
                   be with thee vniuſt.
               Power allowes the laweſſe to offend.
               So doth the Lyon on his pray deſcend. Voorzich 
                        •
                     ich in al. keert meni g
                        •
                     en val
               
               Deale not in points beyond thee with a foe,
               Better then wit abuſd, is not to know.
               And in their I and thus falſt thou in a ſnare,
               Of entermedling in beliefes beware.
               A Temporizer ſhunn though allied, Vibanitas quid.
               
               May a viper's in the boſome breed,
               And feare thy mates accompanying thee, Non volo teſcu
                        •
                      ram, ſed fi pot
                        •
                     s eſte facetus 
                        •
                     
                     ▪ alling.
               
               The fox Clad in the ſheepeſkin warning be
               Whoſe vnſpectedneſſe likeneſse did deceaue
               And th' ſilly lamb downe to his den bequeath,
               Theſe caueats ſo in ſhort the wiſe may 
                     •
                  end,
               The world is now too baſely ould to amend.
               Laſt louely poſture ſages noble deeme,
               Vrbanityes defind its an eſteeme.
               Of euery paſſage as its worth requires,
               And ioy in perſon as his loue deſires
               Not ſtoickes, ſurley melencholy all.
               Much merry parts in traueling befall.
               Wherein mens action preſent is at gage,
               And ableneſſe of diſcourſes ſet one ſtage.
               
                  
Now ſtands the caſe and touch ſtone of a man.
               When ſtrangers ſhall his worth of breeding ſcan
               Behauior Crownes the outer mans deſire, merus ſtoicus merus A ſinus.
               
               And makes him great mens preſence to aſpire.
               When Lo. the ſottiſh ci
                     •
                  icke ſelfe deuoted.
               Sits in his tubb, how wiſe ſo ere
                     •
                  noted.
               Opon the way a ſcipher to the view,
               And paſſes Liuing, as one dead in ſhewe.
               Nones ſollace, not his owne, ſad humours ſeate,
               Be ware thou neuer with a ſtoicke treate,
               In melancholy fancies onely ioyed,
               Whereby loues true Vrbanity is deſtroyd.
               And trauailes paths diſconſolaterate made.
               Man a meere deadman mid a Liuing trade. Comes ſecund
                        ••
                      in via pro vebi culoeſt.
               
               Good mirth and gladneſſe grace true curteſie
               As do good properties good men diſcry.
               A merry conſorts chariot in the way,
               And makes a long way ſhort as ſages ſay.
               Artes acting parts, then hiſtory attending,
               Then the merry muſes with their hores deſcending.
               The wood and water nimphe bring in there ſhares,
               And time of ould it ſelfe a new declares,
               A ſcholer's halfe a trauailer at home.
               Attended in his ſtuddy though alone.
               Yet better fitted trauailes rites to vſe,
               Then mid bookes dull acquaintance ſit and muſe.
               Learnings moſt proper to the fortaine breed,
               Whereby both they and theſe at home are fed.
               His protects, plots, and parts of trauelling
               Aſſiſt the ſtate, himſelfe, his church, his King.
               Come to the climes of ſweete diſcourſe hee's rare,
               Heere ſay and ignorance ſtill attendants are.
               Yets heare a moderation much expected,
               Ieſts become ſcurrill once the meane neclected,
               Scu
                     •
                  llity expoſing man to hate,
               Chiefly much vſed in a forraine ſtate,
               
                  
The Clowniſh ruſticke ſhort another way
               Chuff as idoll wanting what to ſay
               Blurts forth in a preſumption homebred ſhame
               Two ſorts vnworthy vſe of trauailes name Horat: in Su: lib: 1:
               
               When Lo! in true vrbanit yes no waſt,
               Offence, ill mirth, preſumption or diſtaſt.
               Apelles like I leaue vnfiniſht quite
               The ſhape of trauailes ſits for ſhould I write?
               The decades decour more: all worth Narration
               So might men Iudge it too prolix relation. Hl
                        •
                      is zo ment acht
               
               With Socrates lets giue a iudgement now,
               Aſke if he would Heracli
                     •
                  s writs avow?
               What I haue viewd and vnderſtand is good:
               So ſure (quoth he) that is not vnderſtood
               Theſe Comly habits for the reſt may ſtand
               As generals may the ſpecials command.
               As for the chriſtian progreſſe, its dayly taught, Viuat, Valeat Vincat Carolus
               
               And bleſſe we him his plenty heere hath brought.
               A like much care for mortall trauailes taken,
               Whats beſt to be embraced? what forſaken?
               Trauaile to forraine parts, I only tend,
               Wherein the reſt I briefly comprehend.
               Circumſtance ſayth our lawyer alters Caſe,
               Our circvmſtances ſhall be time, and place,
               Part for the whole, though more might be propoſd
               The whole may in his parts be full diſcloſd:
               Firſt for the time to trauaile in moſt free,
               Is as the perſons intereſſed be: Met ghemat men gaet verr.
               
               Perſon with place and time colatertali made
               Reſpectiue to the calling, cauſe, of trade.
               The Sunny beames of peace moſt cheare the moſt
               How ere the ſouldier may of quarrels boaſt.
               For warrs a viper that deuoureth euer
               It canker like conſumes, but comforts neuer, 
                     Beati pacifici. math: 5.
               
               Yet thens the time, the warriour trauailes forth.
               And now's the ſeaſon beſt to ſhew his worth.
               
                  
Times they are as mens purpoſes require,
               And hearein euery one muſt backe retire,
               And note his owne occaſion when beſt
               How ſhould I be with each mans way poſſeſt?
               Yet theres a time for all things to be donn,
               The wiſeſt ſaith) enuirond with the ſunn
               A ſeed time, ſpring, a harueſt, and a froſt:
               A time to linger trauailes time to haſt,
               A time to laugh, to morne, to ſport to ſtay. 
                     Elt hefi ze
                           •
                        n tij
                           •
                         Omnia tempus habent, &amp; ſuit ſpatijs tranſe vnt vniuerſa ſub caelo Ecleſ. 3. 1.
               
               A time to fight, to reſt, to warr, to pray,
               A time to fiſh, and furr, and fir in Eaſt
               A time for oyle, and vintage in weſt,
               A time to care, to watch to plodd, yet then
               A time without time, thats vnknowne to men,
               Wherfore while time is preſent paſſe thy trade
               By this purſuite are many wiſe men made
               When as the fooliſh late are wanting oyle: Naufragium, occurſus pirat arnm. Pall.
               
               Others in fruitleſſe deſperation toyle.
               Time is when ſtormes at ſea much multiplie
               And Hymall clowdes Enuelop ſunn, and ſkie,
               When art, and ſkill, and tryall, turne to doubt,
               Ignorant which way now to vſe the route.
               When deckes are clad with cloudy oceann,
               And dreary guſts incarcerate each man.
               Now ſkill of Compaſſe Card and croſtaffe, failest
               Poore man as in a ſecond deluge ſayles,
               No harbour, hope, or helpe ſeemes to aſſiſt
               Yet then the ſhip to wonder doth reſiſt
               She trauiles vp towards heauen as if there,
               Conuoy Elyas fiery Chariots weare:
               And neſts in mounts billowes of Neboos hight
               Quauering as drunke thereon; a ſcarring ſight
               Not now content ſhe ſhifts from hill to hill.
               And in her progreſſe ſore againſt her will. Pſal. 107. Ionas. 3- Acts. 23.
               
               They poſt her downward as an arrow ſhot,
               When lo! her next purſuer ſees her not,
               
                  
As if to thoſe deiected Angels fled,
               Chaced from thence, by the Almightyes dread,
               When ſee no ſooner 
                     ••
                  ovvſd in valleys deepe
               But at a ſtart ſhe monnts a gaine as ſteepe,
               No more, Wife Dauid Limmes it more at life,
               Ionas and worlds of try all end the ſtrife,
               Note only this in all theſe trafickes ſcenes
               Time, ioynes with place, both act as primeſt meanes
               The iſſues ſerue the cauſe, cares are arrendants,
               Since prouidence and wit 
                     •
                  eare, no defendants.
               For ſee the ſea men ſtrangely terrified,
               Nor land, ſunne, ſtarres, or light can be diſcryed▪
               
               Yet pry, and hale, and pump, and all to ſaue. Ziet opt eynde. Apres lapluye vientle beane temps.
               
               And now the merchants bilt the ſaylours ſlaue.
               His life more precious makes him, pump, and pull,
               Stormes make each filly ſhipper maſter
                     •
                  ull,
               Each dye themſelues their couch and goods in waues,
               And in this dreadfull poſtutes play the ſlaues.
               Their prayers, and paines and teares, are multiplied, Eſt modus in rebusſunt certi denique fines.
               
               Winter ſtormes terrours not to be deſcried.
               The vernall view fell Bore as homeward Chaſes
               And Calmes for ſtormes and light for foggs replaces,
               Thus oft at laſt an vnexpected reſt
               Poſſeſſeth Marriners and Merchants breſt:
               Croſſe time growes 
                     •
                  ilder, miſts are vaniſhed,
               Billowes made plaine, and Rockes diſcouered:
               Men are at eaſe, the Ship now quieted,
               And th'hilly Ocean as a ſheete is ſpread
               But ſee! the time, times will be wayted on,
               Tis better therefore, ta
                     •
                  ry 
                     •
                   now at home:
               I meane now Sol to Caprecorne hath hyed,
               And Eolns ſuruayes the Seas in pride.
               When churliſh Neptune counter maunds our ends,
               Herein it is my Muſe true time commends:
               The time againe is as the Climate ſtands,
               Since diuerſe times attend on diuerſe Lands:
               
                  
For Eaſt, and North, by icy hyemes cloſd,
               Trauaile theſe wayes is croſly now opoſd:
               No green-land, nor a Moſco voyage then
               Preſumptions eate the liues of many men: Temporibus modicina valent data tempore proſunt &amp; data non apto tempore vinanocent.
               
               The times of paſſage vnder zoones obſerue,
               Be ſure thy bodyes rule to it reſerue
               Such timely moderation health Commands
               When much diſeaſes neclects attendant ſtands
               A time moſt ſuting euery limb of trade,
               For true auaile by ayd of time is made Ouid: art am:
               
               One time another Croſſing in her ſtate
               And whats a gemm now: thens quite out of date.
               A time when by iuuaſion and warr,
               That country where our courſe is, is at iarr: Temporiſerua, neere ſtauentis phooilides.
               
               And Gariſons, and rutters domineere,
               Tis no good ſeaſon now to trauaile heere.
               For Lyon like fell warr deuowres all right,
               And lawes, are proſtrate to a vulgar might,
               A time for ſpecialles, ſuch ile not diſcouer,
               For Propertyes in time ſurpaſſe each other.
               Iarres ſute ye ſee to ſomes beſt benefit,
               When, 'ts good for others peacefully to ſit.
               Peace fits Republick trafick to auaile,
               And Actuall ſmiles the marriner aſſaile,
               Lo! now a limb of trauailes way is this,
               Not of true times of trauailing to miſſe
               Occaſions figure epitomes theſe things
               Since time ſtill flyes, and hies with ſwifteſt whings
               The deed is crownd thus executed well,
               And now I come of places rites to tell.
               Times howre glaſſe runnes, and ſword deuoures on [earth,
               Yet each dayes diſſolution is his birth: Fronte capillata poſteſt occaſio calua
               
               Seruing attendant to the God aboue,
               Fitneſſe of time one ſuch his grace doth loue:
               Next to the place our trauailes muſt be fitted,
               Elſe muſt the ſequell ſhew vs ſhallow witted.
               
                  
Man muſt Each Climes condition preconceaue.
               And different humoures there in vſe perceaue.
               For natures wondrous fabricke ſorted ſtandes, Natura gaet voor lecre.
               
               In all the parts and paralells of Landes.
               Earths circled kernell with the Heunes according:
               Relatiue courſe to obiect climes affording
               A locall method cauſing to admire,
               Whoſe fruits ſcene; feed, the trauailers deſire
               Since diſcrepant ſubiect to the clime,
               In creature, feature, fruit, delight and time.
               Expect none but colaterall relation, Wat noodich is moet vergaen
               
               Petwixt a diuerſe people, clime, and nation:
               View well their wiles, the Sutherne nations vſe,
               B
                     •
                  nt to alure, betray, cheat, and abuſe,
               The Northerne courſe condition, ſtupid ſence,
               For arme thy ſelfe to theſe by prouidence.
               The Turke Moore Iewe, and Chriſtian haue their illes, Extreman
                        •
                     cent virtus medio,
               
               Man iudging all place one: tis that killes:
               Men to their climes ſtill good or worſe are fitted,
               Had not each then in ſight be ſharper witted?
               With Tom, his plow, or cow no cheats at home,
               But millions are intrauailes traces ſhowne, ziet menkan godt niet bedrieghen
               
               Tis requiſite thou Coreſpond the place,
               In all things fit, to decour trauailes grace.
               For firſt, once ſhipt: now 'ts good to meditate▪
               
               Where thou art now repoſd, thy dangerouſe ſtate
               This place requires much prayers and preparation
               Sorted with ſome ſuruay of nauigation
               See to thy body ſeaficke keepe it warme,
               Vitall powers opend, th' bodies moſt in harme.
               Vſe excerciſe aboue, and little ſleepe,
               This Galene houlds will thee in temper keepe.
               Know thou a Captaine heere is as a King,
               And pleaſe the mariners in any thing.
               Tis they defend thee from fell waues deuoure.
               And hee hath now thy liberty in power.
               
                  
See th, maſter haue in ſeafkilles able ſhare,
               And in the ſtearage looke one haue a care.
               Twas Palinure Aeneas ſhipp did ſaue,
               Neuer make choice then of a ſkilleſſe ſlaue.
               Chanct in a ſtorme hale tackle, and aſſiſt,
               Two better may then one, aſſaultes reſiſt:
               If in a fight ſcorne cowardiſe to vſe,
               Better by farr life, or a limb to looſe,
               Then be a ſlaue to tyranny of ſoe, 
                     
                        Gratiarum enim ceſſat de curſus vbi recurſus non fuerit.
                     
                     
                        Bern: ſerm: 55.
                  
               
               Many by try all haue anoucht it ſoe,
               But gueſſe the worſt, tis odds that valience ſlaues,
               And thus the place well, vſd your foes are ſlaues.
               Landed now's place of thankes for gods defence,
               So each haſt to his owne place free from hence,
               Twere friuolous for me to ſcale the orbe,
               Of locall rites each country doth afford:
               Take compaſſes and mete, each man his owne,
               And in that place keepe compaſſe as is ſhowne.
               Earths various formes, in trauailes wonders ſee,
               Then paralel and with thy owne agree.
               And to thy ſtate, occaſion and clime,
               Fit vpon tryall courſe of place and time.
               And thus the mapp of trauailes way is ſpread
               The Compaſſe in the midd; each line is lead
               By point: the Rhomb, thou ſeekeſt ſhall direct,
               Thee by the cauſes to cenſure they effect.
               Fates Loadſtone right to will of higheſt ſet,
               Cannot we ſay by art of man be let.
               Yet by our runrace; iudge we the arriue.
               Since caſes common to their cauſes thriue.
               So had I done and ſet my muſe at reſt
               Had ſhe not ſmelt ſome ſauours of diſreſt,
               Aſcending from the fogg of miſty Zoyle,
               And with a puffe or two thus endes the broyle
               The Infidell, or home hatcht miſty eye,
               Seeing vs trauailes wonders thus deſcry. 
                     Obiectio: 1.
               
               
                  
Puffes out his froth: I neuer ſaw the things, Defoliuge breue ſort nce.
               
               And ſight alone from me a credit brings.
               Dull didimus the force of thy ſaluation
               Depends not on thy view but application:
               Bleſſed are they ſaith Ieſus truſt vnſeene
               Whoſe faiths their goulden medium betweene.
               Thus then thy ſoule the better parts affected
               Why'es Charity thy ſences quite reiected?
               A locall diſtance cauſing thy diſtruſt, 
                     
                        〈…〉
                     .
               
               Yea all eyes blinde and men but thee vniuſt.
               Lo! euery day a confirmation comes,
               Of wonders wayting at our very homes.
               Strange births and mereoures, deluges. and fires
               Iſſues for ſin of the all potents ires;
               Yea creatures common in our clime no rares,
               But wondrous to a ſtranger heere repaires.
               As is the clime: lands are miraculous,
               Blind ignorance thee metamorphiſd thus.
               Creations worth, though Gods firſt worke vnknowne
               Thy ſight, not reaſon Credits what at home.
               Elie know how ere in tales are much abuſe
               The eye of wit will paſſe twixtlyes and truthes.
               Reaſon, and learning proſpects will diſcerne
               And the' truth amidd a world of fallace learne.
               Well its enough then; now ile read and credit,
               So can I ſit by th' fire and purchace it, 
                     Obiectio. 2.
               
               The wiſe mans ſluggard vſd indeed to ſay
               Yet ſome more ſleepe, as lyons in the way Quiſqxt habet mores ita iudicat itaq fatur: M: Palling.
               
               Such ſhallow puffes are fruits of necligence,
               Still tis enough; is euery ſotts pretence
               This makes thee man ſo vnbeleeuing bent,
               Becauſe come ſhort of trauailes true intent:
               Orlando, Bevis, Palmeryn and ſuch,
               Are by the fire ſide credited as much
               As truer trauailes; if oppofd thoul't ſay
               A man may credit, or he may denay
               
                  
Reeuiew the worth of trauaile and be hold!
               Shee triumphs midd of wonders manifould.
               Then recollect the looſing difference, Licet acrioraqua legas, altius tamen in animo ſedent quae vult us, habitus; &amp; geſtus dicentis ad figit.
               
               Twixe paſſiue, and betwixt the actiue ſence.
               Had our heroickes truſted paſſiue ſences,
               And made their eaſe and ſafety home pretences
               The wayes of trauaile neuer had bin knowne
               Nor Earth it ſelfe ere to it ſelfe bin ſhowne:
               Nor mutually each others rares imparted, 
                     Pliny. Epiſtola: 4: Lib: 2.
               
               Or the rude heathen to the truth conuerted:
               Or yet the wonders of Almighty ſpredd
               But each bin blind fould by relation ledd.
               Be ruld by me ſtill keepe thy chimney warme,
               A ſluggiſh ſpirit breeds but trauails harme. 
                     Obiectio. 3.
               
               Ile not repeate her many worths to thee,
               Tary at home, let others goe and ſee, Omnibus ſane factis in eſt periculum neque quis nouit quo apulſurus eſta: negotii principio Solon
               
               Well I agree a third cryes t' trauaile due
               In wonders: and her worths wotthy purſue
               But oh! the dangers in the way affright
               Better then trye: Ile truſt what others write.
               Twas the fond crochey t Iſraels ſpies poſſeſt,
               Sent by the Church to view that land of reſt
               The An
                     •
                  kims great Giants guard that land
               And how can we theſe enemyes withſtand?
               This cowardiſe theſe ſaithleſſe diſinherits
               Caleb and Ioſua proſper by faiths merits,
               Thou readeſt of Chriſt his trauailing at ſea,
               when helpe vs Lord, was the diſciples plea.
               He checkt ſoone ſtormes as Lord of ſea and land
               Nor can the proudeſt waue his word withſtand
               Art, thou a Chriſtian? know Gods prouidence,
               At ſea, or land is equall ſtrong defence,
               Thy lot thats to thee man predeſtinate
               Nor canſt ouer run or ouer ſtay thy fate
               Periſhes on mans lineage traueling?
               Another dies in bed? why heeres the thing.
               
                  
Ile neuer come ſwearſt thou where theſe weare loſt
               No nor to be by ſea or pirates croſt
               And why forſweareſt not foole thy bed alike?
               Where death each day doth greater numbers, ſtrike?
               And aches, paines, yea croſſes too: are more,
               Then at the ſea or of our natiue ſhore
               I had for got in trauailes wayes to tell
               How thou art ſkild in this diſtruct ſo well
               Tis penury of faith to fortyſye.
               And breed in thee a noble conſtancy
               Thou liueſt at home an vnbeleeuing courſe
               Nor doſt with God in priuacy conuerſe
               Prayers a ſtranger to thy ſtudy caſes,
               This makes thee ſo prophaine in forraine places.
               A conſcience pure is alwayes lion bould,
               Impures to ill and deſperation ſould.
               A good man beares the record in his breſt
               That all to him ſhall iſſue for the beſt.
               The man holy at home hees fortified
               And's, both for ſtormes and oppoſition tryed: 
                     Ibi fides nullum habet meritum, vbi ratio buma nahabet experimentum. Gregor: in euan 
                     
                        •
                     6.
               
               Comes and is bould gods workes at ſea to ſee
               Longing to know his wonders what they bee
               Armd well by prayer, and patience for a ſtorme,
               And fortified by faith can cach no harme
               Knowes prouidence his portion hies a way.
               And ſafely can in middeſt of pirrils ſtray, 
                     Oivitae ſecur a vbi eſt conſcien
                        
                           ••
                        a pura. Romans. 8. Caelum non animum mutant qui transemare currunt.
                  
               
               Counts croſſes, deaths and all, like aduantagious?
               And how can this man chuſe but paſſe couragious?
               Thy ignorance how bleſſt it is, oppoſes.
               Time euery day true trauailes worth diſcloſes.
               Se Moiſes, Ioſeph, Heſter and the reſt,
               In forraine trauaile wondrouſly bleſt
               For where meanes ſeemeth vacant god ſupplies,
               And in defect gods greateſt honour lies, Poſſe pati facileeſt tibi ni patientia deſit. Ouid: amor,
               
               Let men ſaith Dauid tell his wonders then
               Deliuering beſt: when worſt to eyes of men,
               
                  
Life is at home an ocean of croſſes, Iazillan gebuz Baſimah, turk. procua.
               
               Amapp of cares, a labyrinth of loſſes,
               Tis 
                     •
                  ut a change at ſea, a locall ſhift,
               God cannot be preuented of his drift,
               Thy lot is in thy forehead writ by fate 
                     Obiectio. 4. Exemplis flectite quoque poſſe puto Amorum;
                  
               
               It canſt thou not alter, amend, abate,
               Another Mimick and a worſer ſayes
               Tuſh trauailers can liue no other waies
               Looke backe blinde Doeg to the troupes before
               Rings, princes, prophets, who haue trauailed more?
               The wiſeſt, richeſt, greateſt leade the way,
               And well may then the meaner after ſtay,
               Thinkeſt thou becauſe poore in her way are bleſt
               No men but baſe are in her interreſt?
               Gods no accepter of the perſons grace
               His bleſſing waytes on euery lawfull place.
               How able meanes is to the place declard,
               Looke backe: for now that labour ſhall be ſpard.
               Yet Know if thou haſt ſmall at home to ſpend,
               Much leſſe can coſtly traualle thee defend.
               Thou meanſt perhaps the lawleſſe leagauer crue
               Whoſe profits by all nationes bate accure
               Or the land ſtraying ſpendthrifts Indian courſe,
               Or th' bankrupt cheater bandid of the buiſe:
               Or th' giddy pated criticke ſtird with errour,
               Or the offendour chaſt with conſcience terrour.
               The beaſt and nobleſt roades ſome villianes vſe
               Nor can we trauailes noble path excuſe.
               Let lawleſſe ſtrayers ſee in Ionas mapp,
               And turne a ſtraighter courſe for what may happ, Oune ſaurit faired'une buſe uneſpre 
                        •
                     ier.
               
               And thy reuile experience checkes vniuſt
               And ſhewes thou haſt to trauaile leſſer truſt.
               It may be thou and ſuch for mentiond gulles, Acarion crowe neuer good bawke.
               
               Haue ſluggiſhly conſumd your meanes as fooles
               A broad at home and each way baſe neclect,
               Makes mans weldoing equall in defect.
               
                  
Sir tis confeſt a fift ſayes many gaine, Obiectio quinta:
               
               But many more by loſſe of it complaine.
               Tis part amends with Thomas thou beleeue.
               Trauaile hath in it potence to releiue,
               Yet he that Credits clowds ſhall neuer mowe,
               Nor the obiecting flowbacke ſeldome ſow
               Tis true great loſſes many times befall
               But donot greater gaines the loſſe recall? Angli
                        •
                     ano, 
                        〈…〉
                      de: 
                        〈…〉
                      de.
               
               Letts paralell the trafickers condition
               And iudge him, (as thou vs) without commiſſion
               Who more aduentures? paſſes too, and fro?
               To Spaine? to Zant, to eaſt and weſt we know
               Mixing the gaines and loſſes in account?
               Yet do the gaines By much the loſſe ſurmount?
               How comes it earth ore no degree in ſtate
               Proueth ſo wealthy, able, fortunate?
               If (as it ſales by land too) comes a Croſſe Impig
                        •
                     r extremos currit mercator ad indos: per mar
                        •
                      pau periem vitans Horat:
               
               By ſtormes or pirats vnexpected loſſe,
               His comforts this twas not his owne neclect
               Nor as a ſpend-thrift, loſt it by defect,
               Men ſubiect are their loſſes to repeate
               But not of bleſſings thankfully to treate
               Hurts are in marble graud: but guifts in ſande
               And thus miſpriſe men the almightyes hand
               Yea ſome as Changlings trauaile will bely
               Faulting it for their owne ill huſbandry
               Lo! Loſſes wayt one men as much at home,
               And Croſſes charge vs thicker's dayly knowne.
               Vnkindneſſes in ſtrangers grieuie vs leſſe
               Then ſuch who though of land, and blood oppreſſe:
               And man can trauaile harder, and content:
               Then when his home friends eye his poore intent.
               A thouſand honeſt ſhifts men there effect,
               Which end in worth, ſucceſſe, and good reſpect,
               
                  
Which they abaſht at home could neuer try
               Or in a worſe ſort ſuffer miſery.
               To you let me appeale who haue it proud 
                     Note Apapret virtue in proſperis; at emin et aduerſie Bern: cant. 7: Dan: lib:
                  
               
               And paſſe farre vnder what your births behoud
               In loſephs bondage to endure compeld
               And in a willing patience mildly yeild
               By cruell Egypt, or a Turke affected,
               And Daniell like ouer all reſpected.
               Be ye in midd of bloody Lyons caſt,
               Your cauſe (is good) his iſſue good at laſt.
               The more the perill, the more prouidence
               And greater glory God in mans defence.
               Then's only time for him to ſpread his power,
               When dangers ſeeme moſt ſuddaine to deuoure
               So haue I ſeene, but often heard it tould,
               Men by the very ſea ſtormes made more bould.
               And in the midd of likely loſſes gaine,
               And (more abroad then neare home) grace attaine.
               And leſſer cares in forraine caſes ſerue
               Then where their birth more mercy did deſerue,
               Yea more abroad rich then in father land,
               See! trauailers help, in the Almighties hand.
               Infine a ſixe ſayes, what need this a doe
               Vs now in peace to traueiling to woe?
               Sir we are well ſeated vnder mothers whinge
               Ill neuer trauaile further then my king! 
                     Obiecti
                           •
                        
                      6.
               
               Fond How ſworme keepe thy chimny corner ſtill,
               To win vnwilling ſots tis not our will,
               Let euery man in his condition ſtay.
               To Gad is not to trauaile but to ſtray.
               The church, and euery chriſtians militant,
               Yea euery ſoyle ſupplies anothers want
               Thers moſt need man of trauaile in a peace Fac quod fecit.
               
               The cauſe of plenty; author of increaſe.
               Natiue comodius good to vtter forth Iaia oſt weſt thuys beſt.
               
               Cauſing a citty, or a countryes worth,
               Such men whoſe cauſes ſute to ſit at home
               
                  
And the vnwilling may reſide alone,
               Traficke and peace reciprocall ſuruiuers
               Still where the one, to wonder both are thriuers None hac
                        •
                     t Ca
                        •
                     ll
                        •
                     rs A bo
                        •
                      entend
                        •
                     urilnef
                        •
                     ut que demye parol Carpere vell noli noſtra, vel edetua Martiall.
               
               In warts no time for free recourſe to bee
               This wee by tryall, and experience ſee,
               Embrace thy mothers dugg in promiſd peace
               Embrace thy ſlothfulneſſe thy ſhames increaſe
               Till times of tryall or confuſions come
               Then runnſt thou (as a madd man) bout thy home
               If not thy pride is clowniſh ignorance,
               The plow or cart thy vttermoſt aduance.
               See now my muſe no more of momus crue
               Appeare as yet thy progreſſe to purſue Recollectio. Generalis Att male dum recitas incipit eſſe tuus Martiall:
               
               The wiſe can tell ſots ſoone can cauill more
               Thers worth reſpondence, or a rea ding ore:
               And man may ſooner Change the mooriſh hue
               Then force a fooles beleefe, be't neere ſo true.
               To the ingenious traueller I bend,
               Thus by a ſhort ſuruay the totall end
               His wonders great in ſkie, on ſea, on earth
               Hauing each day, and way, a newer birth
               His worth in pleaſure, and true profits gaine
               How they both ſoule, and ſences entertaine,
               His worths the perſons highly dignifie,
               How rares declard in royall property,
               His way worth note, in perſons fitneſſe ſtands
               Nature, birth, parts, and ableneſſe commands
               The place wherein he paſſes, pious good,
               For god our ſtate, and ſelfe is vnderſtood.
               Next note we vertues common worth embrace
               And vices ready trauaile to diſgrace
               The circumſtantiall place and time attend
               So did my muſe againſt the criticke bend
               Who with the dart of truth expelled thence.
               Gaue cauſe (leaſt tedioue now) wee hy vs hence.
               Trauailes a roſe, man the induſtrious bee
               Wiſe trauailers ſucke, and hiue vp ſwauity
               
                  
Badd ſpider like ſuck poiſons to deuoure
               Tiauai e is as the roſe: a curious flowre,
               None can come neere its colloures curious ſents Dat roſa mell apibus qua ſugit aranea virus Granger.
               
               Delicious roſall rites, and ornaments:
               The baſe neere leſſe to uenome vertues change,
               And if growe worſe by trauaile tis not ſtrange,
               One as the Bee ſucks hony from this flower,
               The ſpider gale, and venome to deuoure,
               Not that the venome in this roſe doth grow Exemplo tanginen propriore potes
               
               For tis of natures ſweets moſt rare we ſhow
               But that the others humour poyſonous
               Conuerts theſe ſweetes to Aconita thus:
               In all the parts of mannage more pernitious, Ouid: amor:
               
               As is the ſubiect in affection vitious.
               Well mannagd trauailes only ornament,
               In Chriſtian, ciuill; and a true intent. Diuerſorium enim hic commorandinon habit andi habemus. Cic: deſen
                        •••
                     nt
               
               Als vſe: the heuens, planets, and ſpherall pace,
               The ſoule, and ſences progreſſe, trauailes grace.
               Mans ages childhood, youth, and midd age hye
               To ſumm at death account of deſtiny
               Which deſtiny in ſecret ſet by God,
               From all beginnings ſealed by his word,
               Proceds in progreſſe with vnknowne envent
               Man cannot ſtop his makers iuſt intent:
               He cannot haſt his fate, it keepeth pace
               Nor ſtayes while periods added to the race,
               Its trauaile mazeth all the earth to ſee
               The ſtrange effects in deſtiny there be
               From birth to nonage, midle gray and graue
               Which ſome at ſea, ſome land all ſome way haue.
               Some poore of rich, ſome high of low ariſe,
               Thus wanders man, in him his deſtinyes.
               A ſparrow cannot faile but by his fate
               Who could ere? once prolong; amend abate?
               True Chriſtian trauaile makes the mortall bleſt
               And him that in the two is intereſt,
               The courſe of ciuill trauaile was our taſke,
               
                  
Daily, diuines the other two vnmaſke, Trauails welfare to be added.
               
               The iſſues ſeene (if worthy uiew) tis well,
               Many more learned the forme may happ excell, Veritas 
                        ••
                     e and 
                        〈◊〉
                     
                  
               
               The matter founded on the rocke of truth,
               Both recreations of my muſe in youth
               Courage then trauailes noble ſonnes aduance
               Arme and expect a mapp of croſſe miſchance:
               Rockes pirates gulphs ſtraights ſirens ſtorms &amp; ſtore
               Of remoraes and monſters of the ſhore. Ille quidem dus gratus eſt eu: coginat
                        •
                      hoc ſunt: omnia ſue 
                        〈…〉
                      rerum ſe 
                        〈…〉
                      ad uſus Hefio
                        •••
                     .
               
               Behould as vertues vices are attendants
               ye muſt be both aſſailants and defendants:
               Hange not on aiery hope of fate alone,
               Prouidence only induſtry will owne.
               Suppoſe the worſt in trauaile that may come
               Scorning thoſe flaſhy preconceyts of ſome,
               Who gueſſe all done, to doo ſtrange things effected
               The goulden meane of modeſty neclected
               When if a loſſe, or croſſeth wart there intent
               The gaines diſpaire the end aſtoniſhment Ep: Eronn.
               
               Leuell thy doubts and hopes ſo though all loſt
               Thy patient ſoule of gaine in loſſe may hoſt: Ephilegu
                        •
                     
                  
               
               Thus trauailes wonders worths and wayes declard
               And trauailes walfares as a fourth prepard,
               Caliope by Cinthius cald: flyes forth
               Denying trauaile wellfare to his worth: 
                     
                        •
                     ax pocali Patriaeque 
                        •
                     alus, &amp; gloria regni, Carol
                        ••
                     .
               
               Since oh the times, fell mars his wellfare croſſes
               By pirats rapins ruins murders loſſes
               Mourne o my muſe in ſecre
                     •
                  t and retire,
               Till Europe liue in peace, his long deſire.
               when on his welfares thou more 
                     •
                  ee mayſt ſing,
               And Brittaine bleſſe Iehoue who wrought the thing.
               Then for a fourth her wellfar
                     •
                   
                  
                     •
                   ſhall aſcend
               And untill then my tryall hath an end.
               
                  Si bene quid feci deo gratare Datori
               
               
                  Si male quid feci noueris eſſe meum.
               
               
                  Olimpiad: in ſeriptit
               
            
            FINIS
            
         
      
   

