
   
      
         
            Two treatises concerning the preseruation of eie-sight. The first written by Doctor Baily sometimes of Oxford: the other collected out of those two famous phisicions Fernelius and Riolanus
            Briefe treatise touching the preservation of the eie sight
            Baley, Walter, 1529-1592.
         
         
            
               1616
            
         
         Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01822
            STC 1196
            ESTC S114909
            99850131
            99850131
            15317
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01822)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15317)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 822:06)
         
         
            
               
                  Two treatises concerning the preseruation of eie-sight. The first written by Doctor Baily sometimes of Oxford: the other collected out of those two famous phisicions Fernelius and Riolanus
                  Briefe treatise touching the preservation of the eie sight
                  Baley, Walter, 1529-1592.
                  Fernel, Jean, 1497-1558. aut
                  Riolan, Jean, 1538-1605. aut
               
               [6], 62, [2] p.   
               
                  By Ioseph Barnes [i.e. G. Eld], for Iohn Barnes [in London],
                  At Oxford :
                  1616.
               
               
                  An edition, with additions, of: Bailey, Walter.  A briefe treatise touching the preservation of the eie sight.
                  Actual printer's name and publisher's address from STC.
                  "A treatise of the principall diseases of the eyes, gathered out of fernelius and Iohn Riolamus [sic] Doctors of Phisicke" has caption title.
                  Final leaf is a blank.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Eye --  Diseases --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-03
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-05
            SPi GlobalKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-08
            Judith SiefringSampled and proofread
         
            2006-08
            Judith SiefringText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            To the Reader.
            
               IT is not vnknowne to the world, with what generall applauſe a certaine Treatiſe, concerning the preſeruation

of Eie-ſight, written by Doctor Baylie, ſometimes of Oxford, hach beene accepted; which by the happie experience of many, in the doubtfull cures of that kind, ſtands throughly confirmed. Being therefore vnwilling that a gemme of ſuch worth ſhould lie any longer hidden vnder the ſoile of Obliuion; and withall deſirous to giue a more luſtre vnto it, aſwell for the ornament of it ſelfe, as for the good of the merchant: I haue now at length reſolued to ſet it forth in the world, to the publique view and cenſure of the Time, newly and artificially poliſhed

with most notable Collections, out of thoſe renowned Doctors, Fernelius, and Riolanus, written on the ſame Subiect. Peruſe the booke, and make vſe of it. If thou findest benefit by it, thanke God first, that hath made his goodneſſe manifest to the world by his ſingular gifts beſtowed on theſe most excellent men; next to the Authors themſelues, for their great paines and ſtudie taken for thy profit; and lastly to mee, for my goodwill and costes in the publiſhing of it. Farewell.
            
               I. B.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            
            A breefe Treatiſe concerning the preſeruation of the eye ſight.
            
            
               THe preſeruation of the ſight doth conſiſt, partly in good order of diet, partly in vſe of Medicines.
            Concerning diet:Diet. ſome things hurtfull are to be eſchued, and ſome things comfortable to the ſight are to be vſed: wherefore they, which may choſe their habitations, in this reſpect, may make election of aire cleare,Aire. declining to moderate heate and dryneſſe: cold and moyſt aire, and thicke, miſty, and rainy weather is hurtfull: it is beſt therefore to abide in dry places, from moory, mariſh, and watriſh grounds and ſpecially to prouide, that the ſite of the dwelling be not betweene the

wet places and the ſun:Windes. Duſt. Smoke. Southerne windes doe hurt the ſight: ſo doe low roomes: places full of duſt and ſmoakie are noyſome.
            
               Meates.Meates are beſt which are eaſie to be digeſted, and which doe not ſtay long in the ſtomacke: amongeſt ſuch a young Henne is greatly commended: ſo is Partridge and Pheaſant. Raſis praiſeth the young ſtarne, and the quaile: ſo doe all writers the Doue both tame and wyld, but chiefly the wild Doue, which (as Zoar writeth) hath eſpeciall vertue againſt the weakeneſſe of the ſight, which commeth by defect of ſpirites, and the rather, if the ſame be ſod with rape rootes, and turnep rootes: for it is accorded by all writers, that the turnep hath great faculty to doe good to the eies, and to preſerue the ſight. Croſſe and ſlimy meates, and all water-foule are diſpraiſed. Of ſmall birdes, the martin, the ſwallow, the iay and pie, the witwall, the ſpecht are noted very hurtfull to the ſight: and albeit theſe birds are ſeldome, or not at all vſed of the better ſort, yet common people happily may be compelled to eate them.Fiſh. No fiſh is accompted good: yet ſome fiſhes, which doe

skoure in grauely-places, being ſauery ſodden with white wine, fenel, eiebright, ſage, perſlie, &amp;c. may at ſome times be eaten: and ſo a little ſalt-fiſh moderately taken doth no great harme. Fleſh ſodden with fenell,Preparat
                     •••
                   of meates eiebright, mintes, ſage, &amp;c. is reputed beſt; next are roaſted meates; fleſh fried with butter or oyle is to be reiected, th'entrals,Intrals. and feete of beaſts are not ſo good, nor the braines for the moſt part, yet the braines of an hare, of a cony, and of pigeons,Braines. are ſaid to quicken the ſight.
            Milke and all things made thereof are found by experience to induce dimneſſe of ſight: reare roſted, reare ſodden,Milke. or poched egges are holeſome,Egges. eſpecially eaten with the powder of eiebright: fryed egges and hard are blamed.
            Of ſauces, veriuce, vinigar of wine,Sauces. and the iuce of limonds, are accompted beſt; Pomgranats, not ſo good.
            Of ſpices,Spices. cinnamon is commended by Auicenna, as ſpeciall good ſo the webbe of the eie, and for dimneſſe of the ſight: ſo is ſaffron; ginger, both inwardly taken, and outwardly applyed, doth ſingularly cleare the ſight: cloues, mace, and nutmegs, and all three kindes of peppers, may be vſed.

Suger is conuenient to condite things, but hony is better:
                  
                     〈…〉
                  . no oyle is good, ſaue pile oliue called ſallet oile, and that is better then butter.
            
               
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   herbs.Albeit few raw hearbes in common vſe for ſallets are commended, except fenell, eie-bright, young ſage, terragone, which are very good: yet theſe are to be avoided as moſt hurtfull, namely lettis, coleworts, cabbages, beets, ſpinage, purſlane, buddes of dill, garlike, chibbols, onions, skallions,
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                &amp;c. Gapers may be eaten: Oliues not ſo good: radiſh rootes, perſnep rootes, are greatly diſpraiſed: carrot rootes, the buds of aſperage may be eaten,
                  
                     〈◊〉
                   Rape 
                     〈◊〉
                   Turnep. but the turnup or rape roote, and the nauew roote are aboue all other noted for excellencie to preſerue the ſight, and to that purpoſe many doe preſerue with ſugar theſe rootes, and eate them as ſucket.
            
               
                  
                     ••
                  uites. 
                     •
                  eares. 
                     •
                  pples.The moſt kindes of fruits are hurtfull to the ſight: yet peares and the better kindes of apples, may be eaten with the pouder of eiebright, or with fenell ſeeds thinly incruſted with fine ſugar:
                  
                     •
                  igges. figs are very good, not onely for the ſight, but alſo to open, ſcoure, and to clenſe the breſt, liuer, ſtomacke and kidneies:
                  
                     •
                  aiſons. ſo are raiſons, which

haue a ſpeciall property to ſtrengthen the liuer: nuts are very evil,Nuts. for that they doe fill the head: the walnut more tollerable then the haſell nut, cheſtnuts are very windie, better friends for 
                  Ʋenus, then for the eies: dates are not commended, nor mulberies.Dates. Confects
            
            Confectes made with fine ſugar and thinly incruſted about with turnep ſeedes, and navew ſeeds, fenill ſeeds, aniſe ſeeds almonds, pine aple kernels, ginger, cinamon, the powder of eiebright, &amp;c. are reputed as very good meanes to continue the ſight: likewiſe in the preſeruation of the ſight, amongſt other things, ſuch drinkes,Drinkes. as are in common vſe and accuſtomed, are to be allowed: therefore he that hath vſed to drink beere,Beere. may not forſake the ſame and ſo of ale.
            And in this reſpect it is not amis at meate to drinke wine,Wine. for them which haue beene accuſtomed to the ſame: although wine in ſome affectes of the eies is forbidden, yet to preſerue the ſight, wine is not inconuenient, for the vapours of wine are drying, cleare abſterſiue, and ſo doe conſume and extenuate groſſe and thick humours, ſo it be moderately taken. In this place I doe greatly commend their councels, which do

prepare medicinable drinks with eiebright,
                  
                     •
                  edicinall 
                     ••
                  inkes. and other things comfortable for the ſight, to be vſed in the morning, and at meates, if the patient can well endure ſo to drinke the ſame: our authors herein are very ingenious, ſome addreſſing drinkes with one thing, and ſome with another.
            
               
                  
                     •
                  rinke 
                     •
                  ade with 
                     •••
                  bright.The ſimpleſt and moſt written of, is with the herbe called of the Arabians Adhill, in Latine Euphragia, in Engliſh Eie-bright, of whoſe miraculous vertues in preſeruation of the ſight,
                  
                     •
                  rnoldus 
                     〈◊〉
                   villa no
                  
                     ••
                  
                
               Arnoldus de villa noua hath written in theſe words: Eie-bright is good any way taken, either with meate,
                  
                     •
                  he praiſe 
                     〈◊〉
                   eiebright 
                     〈◊〉
                   the ſight. drinke or medicine, greene and dry, againſt all impediments of the ſight, whereby the clearenes of the ſame may be obſcured. And hee writeth thus of wine made with Eiebright,
                  
                     〈…〉
                  
                which hee calleth 
                  Ʋinum euphragtatum. This wine (ſaith he) is made by putting the herbe in the muſte or new wine, vntill the ſame wine become cleare to be drunke. By the vſe of this wine, old mens ſights are made young, it taketh away the impediments of the ſight in all mens of all ages, eſpecially in fat men, and ſuch which doe abound with phlegme.
            One (ſaith he) which was blind, and did

ſee nothing in long time, by vſing this wine one yeare, was reſtored to his ſight. The herbe is hot and drie, and hath by propertie of ſubſtance to remoue affectes of the ſight.Eiebright taken in an egge. And ſo the powder of the herbe taken in an egge, or drunken in wine, doth vvonderfully performe the ſame. And there are yet aliue (ſaith hee) witneſſes of good credit, which haue made proofe heereof in themſelues, which could not reade without ſpectacles, but by vſe hereof haue recouered their ſight to reade ſmall letters. And ſo Arnoldus concludeth, that nothing to doe good to the ſight, is to be compared with wine made with eiebright. If the wine be too ſtrong, he counſelleth to allay the ſame with fennell water; and to that intention, you may alſo adde ſugar.
            In countries which for their common drinkes do vſe wine and water, they alway do mingle things for the ſight in wine, and not in water: for wine in truth is a fitter liquor to receiue the qualities and to carry the ſame to the eyes, then water: which thinges they do put in the muſte, and ſo let it ſtand, vntill the wine be ripe, and ready to be drunken, and ſo do vſe it.
            Notwithſtanding in other Countries

which haue other vſuall drinkes,Eiebright may be vſed in beere, in ale, or meade the ſame things may be put in their common drinks, So ſome haue put them in ale, ſome in beere and ſome in meade, and no doubt but all theſe meanes are very good according to the vſage and diſpoſition of the partie. So euen in this our Country they which either by vſe or by conſtitution of body, may wel beare the drinking of wine, may well compound the ſame with things good for the ſight others of hot complexions and drie, not greatly accuſtomed to wine, may of ale, beere, and meade make ſuch drinkes, becauſe in the North countries, ale and beere are the vſuall and common drinkes, and in ſome places, meade alſo is much vſed: therefore in mine opinion it is conuenient for moſt men, to make theſe drinkes with ale, beere, and meade, rather then with wine: and meade aſſuredly is a very conuenient thing for them which can well away with hony.
            
               How Eie
                  
                     ••
                  ight wine may be vſed.Touching the direction of thoſe which haue bin accuſtomed to drinke wine, I do nothing doubt, but that they may with out offence beare ſuch drinks for the ſight compounded with wine, to take a draught in the morning, eſpecially if the allay the

ſame with the diſtilled water of fenell, according to Arnoldus counſell. And for this purpoſe, choyſe may bee made of very good white wine, and the thinges may bee mingled in the countries where the wine doth growe, notwithſtanding in that our moſt vſed drinke with meat is ale, or beere,The vſe of Eiebright ale, and of Eiebright beere. theſe are very conuenient to receiue theſe thinges for the ſight, and abſolutely better then wine, if yee like to drinke the ſame with meate: as our authors doe counſell. Which ale I thinke better to be made with grout according to the old order of brewing.Ale made with grout. And ſo the thinges for the ſight may be ſodden in the grout, or other way put in the drinke, when it is newly clenſed,How to make Eiebright Ale and beere. &amp; put into the veſſell in which it is tunned to be kept that in the working of the drink in the veſſel, the vertues and qualities of the thinges may be drawne and receiued into the ſame. When theſe thinges are compounded in meade,Eiebright meade. then the ſame are ſodden with the honie, in ſuch order as other herbes are ſodden, when they make methegline.
            I thinke it beſt to begin with the ſimpleſt order to compound ale or beere to each mans beſt liking with eiebright only,

taking to euery gallon of the drink a great handfull of the herbe,The quantity of eiebright to the drinke. and bind it together, or put it in raw and thinne tinſell of ſilke, and ſo tie the ſame by a ſtring to the tap of the veſſell, that the herbe may hang in the middeſt of the drinke, not too low in the ground, neither to high in the barme, being put into the drinke when it is newlie clenſed: let all worke togither vntill the drinke be cleare and ripe, to be drunken according to the common vſe, and then ye may drinke of it at pleaſure in the morning faſting, and at meate alſo if you will, and can well like thereof; and moſt men may like to drinke it, becauſe this herbe doeth yeeld no vngratefull taſte, but rather with a pleaſant ſapour doth commend the drinke. It were not amiſſe, to avoide windines, to euery handfull of the herbe to adde two drammes of fenell ſeeds,Fenell ſeeds. well duſted, and a little bruiſed. As I doe put this for more proportion to beginne with-all, that the ſtomacke be not at the firſt offended with the ſtrangeneſſe: So after a time, yee may increaſe the quantitie, and put to euery gallon of the drinke, two handfuls of the herbe, wherein yee may beſt be directed by the taſte, that the herbe ſhall

yeeld into the drinke.Spices may be added. In the winter ſeaſon yee may alſo adde ſome ſpices, as ginger, whole mace, a few cloues, nutmegs, cinnamon, and make as it were bragget ale: which drinke, beſides that it doth preſerue and cleere the ſight, will alſo helpe digeſtion, clenſe and cut phlegme, and breake winde.
            I can witnes,The effect confirmed by examples. that many by this ſimple compoſition of eiebright and fenell ſeeds, haue found great good for their ſight, not onely to continue in good eſtate, but alſo that ſome haue found remedie againſt the dimnes and other impediments, growing in their ſight. In truth once I met an old man in Shropſhire, called M. Hoorde, aboue the age of 84. yeares, who had at that time perfit ſight, and did read ſmall letters very well without ſpectacles: hee told me that about the age of 40. yeares, finding his ſight to decay, he did vſe Eiebright in ale for his drinke, and did alſo eate the powder thereof in an egge three daies in a weeke, being ſo taught of his father, who by the like order continued his ſight in good integrity to a very long age. I haue heard the ſame confirmed by many old men Rowland Sherlooke an Iriſh man, Phiſition to Queene

               Marie, did affirme for truth, that a Biſhop in Ireland perceiuing his ſight to wax dimme, about his age of fifty yeares, by the vſe of eiebright takē in powder in an egge, did liue to the age of 80 yeares, with good integrity of ſight.Drinkes more compounded for the ſight.
            
            VVe do reade of many drinkes to preſerue the ſight, compounded not of eie-bright onely, but many moe thinges added: ſo ſome put to it ſage, ſome veruaine, ſome celendine, and fennell ſeedes, aniſe ſeeds, &amp; the forenamed ſpices: others elecampane rootes, iris, galengale, &amp; cubebs, and in truth all theſe are greatly commended to preſerue the ſight, and may very aptly be put in drinkes for the ſight: notwithſtanding, for that we are now to deliuer a drinke for the ſight, which may bee pleaſing, and alowed with meates, mine opinion is, that the ſame ought to be made as ſimple as may be. For if Gallen in his 6. booke de ſanitate tuenda, doth preferre the compoſition of the medicine termed diatrion piperiō, which hath feweſt ſimples, becauſe (as he writeth) that is ſooneſt &amp; with leſſe trouble to nature digeſted:The moſt compound not alwaies beſt. ſurely the drinkes for the ſight, which are compounded of feweſt thinges, are moſt to bee

commended, eſpecially when we meane to vſe the ſame with meate, as all our authors do coūſell vs. Wherefore, for my part at this time, I will onely aduiſe to haue for vſe, either wine, or ale, or beere, according to each mans beſt liking, made as it is before preſcribed with eiebright and fenell ſeeds, and to drinke of the ſame in the morning, or if it ſo like with meat, as other drinke.
            It is holded better to drinke oft and ſmall draughts at meat,Drinke often and ſmall draughts. then ſeldome and great draughts; for ſo meat and drinke will better mingle, and the meat will leſſe ſwimme in the ſtomake,Not beſt to begin the meale with drinke. which giueth cauſe of many vapours to the head. It is affirmed not good to begin the meale with drinke, but to eat ſomewhat before you drinke.
            When you drinke wine if you meane to alay the ſame with water,When to mingle water with wine it is beſt to mingle to the wine fennell water, or eiebright water, and Montagnana doth counſell to doe the ſame ſome reaſonable time before you do drinke, and not preſently when you drinke, as commonly men doe.
            Bread in our intention is to be made of fine flower of choſen wheat,Breade. alway leuened and ſalted ſomewhat more then common bread, well wrought, throughly baked,

not new nor old, of about a day or two daies old.Paſt with fenil ſeeds. Vnleuened bread is not accompted good: and the bread is better, if fenell ſeeds be wrought with the paſt; to which purpoſe ſome do cauſe cakes to be made of ſome portion of the dowgh, in which they knead the powder of fenell ſeeds, and the powder of eiebright, and doe eate them in the morning, and after drink the eiebright drinke, and make that a breakfaſt.
            
               Euacuation.As generally in the preſeruation of health: ſo eſpecially to continue the ſight, it is conuenient that the body be obedient, and doe his office for euacuation accordingly: and if nature herein be ſlack, it may be procured with brothes made of looſe herbes, as mallowes, violet leaues, mercury, ground ſell, great raiſons the ſtones taken out, damaske pruines and currants: and if neede be of more medicinall things, ſurely the ſame muſt be gentle: for as ſtrong medicines, which make agitation of humors are not good to be vſed for this intention: ſo gentle medicines taken in due time, doe great good to the ſight: which I doe leaue to the appointment and direction of a learned Phiſition. Of all manner of euacuation, theſe which are done by vomiting

are moſt hurtfull: ſo are fluxes of blood by the noſe. And as belkes doe eaſe the ſtomacke, ſo much belking giueth occaſion that fumes doe ariſe to the fore-part of the head, whereby the ſight may be harmed.
            Nothing is more hurtfull to health then fulnes.Fulneſſe hurtfull. And he that will continue his ſight good, muſt be carefull of ouer-plentifull feeding, and therefore muſt end his meales with appetite: and neuer lay gorge vpon gorge, but ſo feede, that the former meate may be concocted, before hee doe eate againe. It is beſt to make light ſuppers, and ſome-what timely.Vſe of Venus.
                As modeſt vſe of 
                  Ʋenus perfourmed in the feare of God in due time, when the meate in the ſtomacke is digeſted, and nature is deſirous to be diſburdened, is to be allowed: ſo immoderate and vnſeaſonable vſe thereof, doth of all things moſt hurt the ſight, and ſooneſt induce blindnes: ouer-much watching is not good: very long ſleepes are more hurtfull:Sleepe and watching. the meane ſleeps of about vij. houres, are beſt: yet better to abridge the ſleepe and to inlarge watching, then contrariwiſe: ſleepe taken in the night is beſt, as moſt naturall, when externall aire doth not diſtract natures

motion, and all externall things concurre to helpe ſleepe, therefore the moe houres a man doth borrow of the day for ſleepe, the worſer. It is not good eſpecially to this our purpoſe, to ſleepe immediatly after meate: for two houres at the leaſt ought to be put betweene meate and ſleep. Beſt to begin ſleep vpon the right ſide, and then to turne on the left ſide: to ſleepe vpright vpon the backe is naught generally: to turne vpon the face worſer for the ſight.The Moone ſhine hurtfull to the ſight. Care muſt be had that you ſleepe not in a chamber, or any place in which the Moone doth ſhine.
            
               Exerciſes.Exerciſes are needfull: the ſame beſt, after the belly hath done his office, that the excrements are a voided: otherwiſe by exerciſe vapours are ſtirred, and doe aſcend more plentifully to the head.Writing after meate. All exerciſes muſt be done faſting, and none after meate. And I wiſh you might after meate for beare writing by the ſpace of three houres: but if your courſe of life and calling will not ſo permit you, you may herein follow Montagnana his counſell, to write either ſtanding vpright, or a little leaning and reſting your head vpon your right or left cheeke: in no caſe to write bowing your ſelfe forward,

and holding downe the head. When opportunity and time will ſerue, frictions with a rough linnen cloth are very good,Frictions. which are to be performed thus: firſt to rub the feete, the legges, then the thighes, the hips, the buttockes, aſcending to the ſhoulders and necke with ſoft and long rubbings, euen vntill the partes begin to wax red. Amongſt orders to remooue the weakenes of the ſight, Auicenna writeth that the combing of the head is not of leaſt force,Combing the head. which ought to be done euery morning faſting backwardes againſt the haire for it draweth the vapours out of the head, and remoueth them from the ſight.Affections of the minde.
            
            Mirth, ioy, and pleaſantnes of the minde is good: a little anger doth not hurt: immoderate ſorrow, fearefulnes, and all vehement affections are forbidden in all affects, but in this our caſe chiefly, as moſt hurtfull to the ſight.
            
               
               To preſerue the ſight by Medicines.
               
                  THE order to preſerue the ſight by medicines, doth conſiſt of things outwardly applied,Outward Medicines. &amp; inwardly taken. Amongeſt outward medicines to preſerue the ſight, it is accounted a great ſecret, to ſmel much to marierum.The ſmell of marierū. So theſe things following, are ſound very much to comfort the ſight in ſtaying the viſible ſpirits from waſting: videlicet,
                  Things comfortable to the ſight. corall, pearle, the ſtone called Lapis Armenius, ſpectacles of Chriſtalline or clear and pure glaſſe, greene &amp; sky colours, to dip the eies in cold water, to which purpoſe, many haue cups made in the forme of an eie,Eie cups. called eie-cups: &amp; to waſh the eies with the waters or decoctions of eiebright, roſes,Things put into the eies. and veruaine. Some other things are put into the eies to clear the ſight, &amp; to remoue impediments which do often grow there: to which purpoſe as approued very good &amp; without hurt, the iuices &amp; waters of eie-bright, of fenell, of veruaine, of marigolds, of pearlwort are greatly commended. And

                  Montagnana doeth mention a certaine kinde of preparation of the iuice of fenell,A preparation of the iuice of fenell. ſingular good to preſerue the ſight from dimneſſe, to take the iuce of fenell in the month of Aprill, and to put it in a veſſell of glaſſe, with a long and narrow necke, and let it ſtand fifteene daies in the ſunne, that it may be well dryed, then remoue the glaſſe ſoftly, that you doe not trouble the reſidue, or grounds, and ſo powre it into another veſſell: and to euery halfe pound of the iuice, put an ounce of choſen lignum aloes, beaten into fine powder,
                     Lignum aloes. good for the ſight. and let it ſtand other fifteene daies in the Sun. Then ſtraine it twiſe through a thick cloth, and keepe the cleareſt in a veſſell of glaſſe to your vſe: you may drop a little hereof into your eies to cleare the ſight. And ſome do diſtill this wood in a ſtillatory of glaſſe, and put the water thereof into the eies, and hold this for a great ſecret as miraculous to preſerue the ſight. And the ſame Montagnana doeth compound another medicine more abſterſiue to remedie the dimnes of the ſight, diſſoluing in an ounce of the water of Roſemarie flowers,
                     Sal gemma doth cleare the ſight. two ſcruples of Sal gemma very finely powdered, and filtered, and counſelleth to drop

the ſame often into the eies; affirming by his experience, that it doeth ſo mightily cleare the ſight, that ſuffuſions are thereby wonderfully remoued, and eſpecially moiſtures of the eies.
               I am heere alſo in this place for the clenſing and ſtrenghtning of the eies eſpecially to commend vnto you the frequent vſe of old and cleere white wine, in which the Calaminar ſtone hath beene oftentimes extinguiſhed: and likewiſe the pure liquor of good ſugar-candy diſſolued in the white of an egge, being hard roſted and the yolke taken out.
               
                  The vrine of a childe.Alſo our authors do commend the waſhing of the eies with the vrin of a childe, and ſometimes to drop the ſame into the eies.A lie of fenel ſtalkes. And for this purpoſe alſo they do commend lie made of the aſhes of fenell ſtalkes. Wee doe read in all our writers great commendations,A preparation of the liuer of a Goate for the ſight. of a liquor of the liuer of a goate, prepared in manner following. Take the liuer of a male goat, not diſeaſed, nor newly killed: and after it is well waſhed, pricke it in many places, and fill the ſame with graines of pepper, and infarce the liuer with the leaues of fennell and of eiebright, then roſt it with a ſoft fire cleare, not ſmoakie,

vntill it bee reaſonably roſted: and in the time of roaſting, receiue the liquor which doth diſtill, in a conuenient veſſell, and apply the ſame to your vſe.
               
                  Auicenna in his third fen. third booke and fourth treatiſe, cap. de debilitate viſus, aboue all other things doth commend the medicine called collyrium de fellibus,
                  Collyrium de fellibus for that it cleanſeth the pores of the eies, cleareth and conſerueth the ſpirits, mundifieth the moyſtures or waters of the ſight: as you may reade in Auicenna in the foreſaide place.
            
            
               Inward Medicines.
               
                  MEdicins to be taken inwardly are in number many: but I thinke beſt at this time to mention a few, which are eaſie to be had, and as of great efficacy moſt commended: &amp; of ſuch the powder following is moſt ſimple:A powder for the ſig
                        ••
                     
                   yet by experience aproued of ſuch force that many, after their ſight hath bin decaied, haue by the vſe of it, receiued againe

the ſame perfectly: the powder is thus made.
               Take of the powder of eiebright foure ounces, of mace one ounce, mingle them togither, and take thereof the weight of three pence before meate.
               
                  Montanus in his 92. counſel giueth great praiſe to a ſirup,A ſirup for the ſight. againſt the decay of the ſight through the weakenes and dimnes of the ſame, which he compoundeth thus.

                     Take of the iuices of fennel, of each two ounces.
                     of veruaine, of each two ounces.
                     of roſes, of each two ounces.
                     The leaues of the herbe eiebright of each M. S.
                     
                     of endiue, of each M. S.
                     
                     of celendine. of each M. S.
                     
                  
boyle the herbes in two pints of water vntill the halfe be ſpent: then ſtraine it hard, and mingle the iuices with the decoction, and with ſugar according to art make a ſirup, which is to be kept in a glaſſe veſſell. You may take two ounces of this ſirup in the morning faſting. In windy bodies hee maketh the ſirup thus,

                     Take of fenell ſeeds, of each iij. ounces.
                     of aniſe ſeeds. of each iij. ounces.
                     
                        of the herbs of eiebright of each M. iij.
                     of veruaine, of each M. iij.
                     of roſe-leaues, of each M. iij.
                     of celendine. M. j.
                     of rhue. M. j. S.
                     
                  
boile theſe in water vntill halfe be conſumed: ſtraine it harde, and with ſugar ſiruppize the decoction: both theſe ſirups are excellent good to defend the ſight from dimneſſe.
               
                  Meſue in his booke called Grabadin,
                  An excellen
                        •
                      electuary 
                        〈◊〉
                      preſerue the fight. writing of the diſeaſes of the eies, aboue all other medicines extolleth an electuary vnder the name of Humaine, as hauing noble vettues to perſerue the eies, and to continue the viſible ſpirites in their cleareneſſe, which he compoundeth thus.
               Take the herbe called Adhil, that is

                     eiebright, ounces, ij.
                     fenill ſeeds, Drams. v.
                     mace, of each Dra. j.
                     cubebs, of each Dra. j.
                     cinamom, of each Dra. j.
                     long-peper, of each Dra. j.
                     cloues. of each Dra. j.
                  
beate all into powder, ſearſe it, then take of good hony clarified, lib. j.

                     
                     of the iuice of fenill boyled and clarified, one ounce.
                     
                        
                           of the iuce of Rhue
                           of Celendine
                         both boiled and clarified, of each halfe an ounce.
                  
boyle all to the height of an electuary, and then put to it the powders according to art, and ſo reſerue it in glaſſe veſſels. You may take hereof the quantity of Dra. iij, in wine as Meſue writeth: If wine ſeeme too hot, you may allay it with fenill water, or with Eiebright water: it muſt be taken in the morning faſting: and you ought to forbeare the taking of other things, by the ſpace of three houres, and ſo at night, but then you muſt make a light ſupper, and ſup the more timely.
               
                  Diſtilled 
                        •
                     aters.Where in this little Treatiſe mention is made of diſtilled waters, I wiſh the ſame to be artificially done in ſtilli tories of glaſſe, that the qualities of the herbes may remaine in the diſtilled waters. And therefore I doe not allow of the common maner of diſtilling in ſtillirories of lead, by the which the watry parts onely are drawne.
               FINIS.
            
         
         
            
            
               A Treatiſe of the principall diſeaſes of the eyes, gathered out of Fernelius and Iohn Riolamus Doctors of Phiſicke
            
               AS the Eyes are of a delicate and ſoft nature, ſo ar they by the moſt light occaſion offended, as by ſmoak, by duſt, and the Sunne beames: ſo the north winde, and vapours riſing from minerals doe hurt the eyes. But this peculiar property the eyes haue, that they congeale not becauſe they are of a fiery property, and doe conſiſt of an airy fatnes.
            The eyes are ſubiect to euery kinde of diſeaſe, Simeler, Organical, and commune as the ſimiler parts doe labour with euery diſtemprature, with an hot diſtemprature, as often as they are offended with ſmoake, or duſt, which offence proceeding from an outward cauſe, is properly called Taraxis, rednes of the eyes is more like vnto Phlogoſis, then Phlegmon becauſe they arred without

tumor. A cold diſtemprature doth dull the ſight. A moyſt doth dilate the pupill: A dry diſtemprature doth either ſhrinke vp the whole eye, or the pupill thereof is dryed or extenuated, as it hapneth in extreame old age, or by the immoderate vſe of venerie. From thence Pthiſis, and an Atrophia hapneth of the eye: I call that Pthiſis which is an extenuation of the pupill, or apple, and becometh more anguſtior, and ſtreyter, and more obſcure: but that is an Atrophia, when the whole eye is conſumed for want of nouriſhment. And as the Inſtrument doth ſuffer diſeaſes of number, of magnitude, of ſituation and conformation, (I ſay) conformation in the figure, Meatus, and Aſperitie, for it is a diſeaſe in magnitude, as often as the eyes are more great, and more ſtanding forth then they ſhould, for the leſſer eyes are beſt, becauſe the viſible vertue being coacted and drawne togither is greater then when it is diſperſed, and is leaſt ſubiect to outward iniuries: from whence it doth happen, that thoſe which by nature haue ſmall balls or apples of the eye, haue their ſight moſt ſharpe, I meane not thoſe which haue it ſo by accident, as if they be extenuated by immoderate venerie,

for then thinges ſeeme to be greater then they are: to this may be referred Enchanthis, and Rhinas, for they are the contrary of the ſame kinde. Encanthis is an excreſcence of the ſame fleſh which is in the greater Cantho, but Rhinas is when the ſame caruncle being eroded and eaten, doth appeare as it were hanging forth. To diſeaſes of number, doe appertaine Suffuſio, which is commonly called the Cataracte, which is an humor concreate betweene the Cornea, and the Vuea: in like manner, the web called Pterigium and Onix or Vngula and Hipopion. The web is a neruoſe membrane, which according to diuers men, doth proceede from the great corner vnto the apple, and ſometimes at length doth couer the whole eye. Onyx or Vnguis is a Cicatrix from ſome vlcer, which is referred to the likenes of a nayle. Hypopion is a certaine Pus, collected vnder the Cornea, which doth ſucceed a ſuppurated inflammation &amp; Chemoſi, Hypoſphagmati bloudy and ſuggillat eyes, ſuch as are when ſome veine is opened, broken, or gnawne, the bloud waxeth blewe and liued:
            To diſeaſes of Site or ſituation doth appertaine Ecpieſmos, which is, when the whole

ball hangeth forth, which hapneth by the Muſcles relaxed, which muſcles do obuolue the opticke nerue, which diſeaſe may be called Prolapſus oculi, although Paulus doth cal it Proptoſin, when the Cornea being eroded or eaten, the Vuea doth hang forth, of which Proptoſeos there are diuers names, for firſt when the vuea doth hang forth, becauſe it appeareth like vnto the head of a Flie, it is called Myocephalos, but when it doth increaſe more, and doth repreſent Acinum vuae, it is called Staphiloma, when it doth more increaſe, and the eye is ſtarke blinde and hath the likenes of the head of a nayle, it is called Clauus, but either affect is Morbus in ſitu, but the firſt is of the whole eye, the latter of one onely part, that is of the vuea. Diſeaſes of conformation are, when the naturall figure of the eye is peruerted, as in Strabiſmo or conuulſion, Midriaſei or dilatation of the ball: alſo diſeaſes in 
                  Ʋia, as a ſodaine obſtruction of the Opticke nerue, which is called Hamaroſis. The Sicke ſeeth nothing at all, when notwithſtanding no cauſe appeareth in the eye, the tunicles of the eyes ought to be light, terſe▪ and fayre are ſometimes exaſperated with an inward and outward cauſe, as with ſmoake and duſt.
            
               The eyes do ſuffer moſt often common diſeaſes, as vlcers, and tumors againſt nature, firſt phlegmon, which is called Opthalmia, that is knowne by tumor, inflamation, rednes and paine.
            The vlcers do manifeſt themſelues by itch, by paine and Saines, but not alſo the Adn
                     •
                  ta, but alſo the Cornea is ſometimes vlcered, and whether it bee vlcered, wee may eaſily know by this ſigne: There doth appeare a white ſpot in the black of the eye, with the ſignes aforeſaid: and when the Coniunctiua is vlcered there doth appeare as it were a red ſpot in the white of the eye: But firſt, I will ſet downe the manner of curing of thoſe diſeaſes, and then I will ſpeak of the Symptoms.
            
            The precept of Plato in Charmide is familiar with Galen. Euen as it is in vaine to cure the diſeaſes of the head without conſideration bee firſt had of the whole, ſo raſhly to preſcribe remedies to the eyes, except we firſt conſider of the head, where is the originall both of the eyes and the fountaine of all diſeaſes which come by defluxion.
            Therefore firſt of all the body is to bee purged with pillulis lucis maioribus in a cold

cauſe, and in an hot cauſe, with pil. lucis minoribus, or with Sena and Agarick which ſhall bee boyled in a decoction, or with the diſtilled waters of Fenel and Eyebright, with which vehicles the purgatiue vertue is carried to the eyes: and conſider that the Agarik doth eſpecially profit the braine, and the Senna the eyes.
            The opening of a veine in hot diſeaſes is profitable, but not in cold, yet the common people do hold an opinion that bloud-letting doth weaken the ſight, for it draweth the animall ſpirits and ſo doth weaken their force, becauſe the vapour of bloud or the naturall ſpirit is the matter of the vitall ſpirit, as heere of the animall: for the eyes ought to be fiery and full of Animall Spirit.
            
               Masticatoria, without doubt, doe profit to the deriuation of the humor from the braine, but your errhina are hurtfull, eſpecially the ſtronger ſort, becauſe they draw to the part affected, for there is great affininity of the noſtrils with the eyes: there is alſo a manifeſt foramen, from the eye into the noſtrill, whoſe opercle or couer is a litle lacrimall fleſh. But ſome man may ſay Aerius doth preſcribe errhina: I anſwer thoſe

are the lighter ſort, neither is the diſeaſe as yet confirmed, but now beeing confirmed and the humor fixed and not flowing, Cupping glaſſes adplied to the ſhoulders doth pluck back the fluxe from the eyes, euen as a Seton, and Cautier, in Inio Iohn de Ʋigo doth apply behind the eares bloudſuckers and 
                  Ʋeſicatorium, as
            
               Veſicatorium.
               
                  Recip. Fermenti acris one ounce.
                  
                     Cantharidum et Seminis Synapi, one dramme.
                  
               
            
            Mixe them for a 
                  Ʋeſicatorium.
            
            There Fernelius willeth to apply a cautier, and doth giue a reaſon that from thence a branch from the iugular vaine ſpringeth and doth runne through to the Optick Nerues.
            As often as the veines of the forehead do ſwell, they ſhew the fluxe to bee externall and the tumor to deſcend from the pericoranium from whence ſpringeth the coniunctiua, which fluxe is profitably ſtayed with ſome adſtringent frontall, ſuch as in this maner may be prepared.
            Recip. Emplaſt. contra rupturam deſiccatini rubri an. one ounce.
            Malax them with oyle of myrtles or roſes, and ſpred it vppon lynnen and make a

frontall, which apply all ouer the forehead: or,
            Recep. Farinae volatilis an ounce &amp; a halfe. boli armeni et Sanguinis Draconis ana. two drammes.
            Worke them well together with the white of egges and oyle of roſes, and make a frontall as before. Alſo topicall meanes applyed to the head are not to bee neglected.
            For this is a generall precept, as often as diſeaſes come by defluxion. we muſt not onely reſpect that part that is offended but alſo that part that ſends it. Beſide a thinne humor is to bee ingroſt and made thicker, and the laxe wayes are to be made ſtraiter: this laſt preſcribed frontall is moſt excellent, but firſt cephalicall thinges and ſuch as reſpect the head muſt be remembred.
            The vſe of Eyebright wine doth confirme and ſtrengthen weak and ill affected eyes or the powder of Eyebright as,
            Recep. Eupraſiae,
            
            
               Feniculi dulc. ana one ounce.
            
               Cum duplo Saccharo, take of it after meales or,

                  Recep. Coriandri praeparat. one ounce.
                  
                     Euphraſiae et feniculi an. halfe an ounce.
                  
                     
                     Cinamomi. one dramme.
                  
                     Macis. two ſcruples.
               
            
            With the double weight of Sugar make a powder to be taken out of a ſpoone after meales, if you pleaſe you may boyle the iuyces of Fenel and Eyebright with hony and make a confection: of which take morning and euening the quantity of a Walnut.
            For generall thinges outwardly to bee applyed, I will preſcribe two Colliriums, the one in hot diſeaſes to be preſcribed in the beginning of the fluxe, that it may bee repelled, the other in the ſtate and declination of hot diſeaſes, and in cold alſo, they may at all times be vſed, the firſt Colirium ſhall be after this manner.
            Recip. Muccaginis Semi. Pſyl
                     ••
                  . et Cydoniorum, extractae in aqua Roſarum, vel plantaginis, an. halfe an ounce with two ounces.
            Of the ſame water make a liquid Colirium: it is commonly made with the white of a new laid egge, being wrought together with Roſewater or Plantain water: a Colirium to reſolue is made in this manner.
            Recip. Muccaginis faenugreci extracted with Eyebright water or Fenel water an.
               
one ounce make a Colirium, or with two ounces of the ſame water make a Collirium liquidum: a litle of the Muſcilage is to bee preſcribed becauſe it doth quickly grow ſower.
            And now I aſke whether your Colliriae are to bee diſtilled into the eyes as hot as may be ſuffered? as it liketh Scribonius: or cold as it pleaſeth Meſue, or luke warme according to Galen: But in my opinion they are to be inſtilled luke warme, vnleſſe the affect do require ſome other thing, for in eyes that be exceedingly inflamed and burning, wee drop it in cold; but in very cold affects wee droppe it in very warme, otherwiſe meanely warme doth alwaies ſerue the turne.
            Now to proceed to cure thoſe diſeaſes whereof wee haue already ſpoken: euery diſtemperature is cured by his contrary: as eyes that bee inflamed and ouer-hot, ſhall be cooled with the dayly waſhing of them with cold thinges, or with the waters of Roſes and Plantaine: but if the diſtemperature be cold, we warme the eyes with putting in the waters of Eyebright, Fennell, Rue, Celendine, waſhing them often therewith: if the eyes bee ouer-moiſt wee dry

them if wee macerat tutia in thoſe waters, as for example.
            Recip. Tutiae one dram.
            Infuſe it in eyebright water two ounces, make a Collirium if the eyes be ouer dry we humect them by inſtilling womans milk, or with a fotus of mallowes, holy hocks and violets: But if ſome matter be ioyned with the diſtemperature, let it bee reſolued with a Collirium of the Muſcilage of Fenugreeke extracted in the aforeſaid waters; or waſh the eyes with the decoction of Fenugreeke, with a ſponge, or boyle a bag being filled with Fenugreeke in water, and apply the bagge to the eye warme: hitherto we haue ſpoken of the Similer diſeaſe, now we will ſpeake of organicall, and firſt of diſeaſes of magnitude.
            If the eyes ſhall be greater or leſſer then they ſhould be from their firſt conformation, all remedies are vnprofitable: if they happen ſo by accident, as by ſome fluxe from the braine, all the body is often to be purged, the moiſt eyes are to be dryed, we muſt looke to the head that is ouer-moiſt with Cephalicall thinges. Alſo Cautiers muſt be applyed to dry vp the offending humor: we muſt apply for Topicall, linnen

dipt in the water of Rue, Celendine, or Eyebright, and the infuſion of Tutia, or the bagge filled with Fenugreeke, or of the ſame Hydroticall Decoction of the infuſion of Tutia make a Collirium.
            
            
               Encanthis groweth whiles the bloud doth more abundantly flow to the caruncle for nouriſhment, which being turned into the ſame ſubſtance groweth greater then it ought to doe: ſometimes it is ſo great that it hindreth the eye lids to be ſhut: it is burnt with gold, or els with a burning iron, or els cut off, or when it doth ſurmount it is bound with a thread, after it is ſoftly bound vp, and after being deſtitute of nouriſhment, the excreſcence doth fall away of its owne accord. Our ancient Phiſitions called this kind of remedy Anabronchiſmon, if the ſick bee of a delicate conſtitution and ſhall refuſe the Chirurgery, let the excreſcence be eaten away with burnt Alum or with oyle of vitriol: but it muſt be diligently corrected with roſewater or milke, for the exquiſite ſenſe of the part. In the meane time while theſe things are a doing, wee muſt defend the eye with ſome defenſure to auoid the offence of a fluxe. Rhyas doth oftentimes ſucceed

               Epiphora if the Caruncle be plainely eaten it admitteth no cure: but if ſome part bee onely eaten, the fleſh may bee regenerated by applying incarnatiues as tutia, aloes. thus, or infuſe the ſame in ſucco granatorum, and being ſtrained inſtill it by drop meale into the greater corner of the eye. But perhaps you will ſay wil you mixe adſtringents with your incarnatiues, ſuch as is the iuyce of Pomegranets? which is altogether forbidden by Galen: leaſt the dry excrement ſhould be retained in the part. But hitherto of diſeaſes of magnitude: now follow diſeaſes of number.
            
               Of the Webbe of the Eye. Chap. 3.
               
                  Pterigium gooweth by the defluxion of thick and groſſe humors, beeing ſoft and white in the beginning. Dioſcorides doth commend a Collirium of Snailes, they are to bee burned whole, and the pouder to be mixt with honny, the pouder of the cuttle bone or the pummis ſtone may bee alſo mixed with honny as before; If you would haue it ſtronger, mixe a little ſalt Armoniac, but firſt foment the eye with a decoction

of Fenugreeke. Aetius vſeth to burne Plantaine ſeed, and addeth to the pouder mirhe, and alſo the ſcales and flowre of braſſe, but wee ſhould apply no mettals to the eyes, except it be firſt burnt and waſhed, for by the burning and waſhing, the ſharpnes and biting quality is remoued, and ſo it doth raiſe no fluxe, of which our cheefeſt care ſhould bee. Alſo wee may vſe oyle of vitriol, but it muſt bee well corrected with milke: but yee ſhall note that a great and inueterate web can be cured by no meanes but by Chirurgery: ſuch are thoſe that couer the whole ball and black, of the eye: webs groſſe and thick, black: and which do affect the temples, by conſent are in no hand to bee medled withall.
               In like manner if there be ſuſpition of a Catarhact beginning, and there be alſo a web that is white and ſoft, we muſt abſtain from thinges eating, becauſe they generate and increaſe the Catarhact. Aetius &amp; Celſus doe ſhew Chirurgery, and eſpecially Paulus Aegneta in his 6. booke and Cha 28. where he doth ſhew a double kind of cure; the firſt, that the web be ſtretched once with a thread, &amp; then with a launcet

to be excoriated; the ſecond, to make a paſſage with a needle that may containe a thread or ſetam (which is the briſtle of an hogge) and ſo hanging with the thread the web ſhall be cut with the briſtle about the apple as it were with a ſaw, and that which doth remaine about the lachrimall, ſhall with the launcet be cut away.
            
            
               Of the Hypopion or matter vnder the Cornea. Chap. 4.
               
               Becauſe that Hypopion followeth to Hypoſphagma, that is, eyes that are bloudy by meanes of ſome veine being rupted, or open, which is alſo called Aimalops, becauſe in this affect all thinges ſeeme red: therefore the bloud-ſhotten eyes muſt be quickly lookt vnto, leaſt by neglect it growe into a leady colour, and then doth ſuppurate and degenerate into Hypopion, for that hapneth to the eye that hapneth to the ſkin by ſome blowe, and groweth when corrupt matter is in great aboundance, ſo that it doth occupie halfe the blacke of the eye, or ſhineth through the horny coate, which couereth the whole apple of the eye: this

affect may riſe not onely of an vlcer, but alſo of great payne in the head, or inflamation in the eye that is corrupted, and beſides inflamation, it may grow from aboundance of humors which doe breake open the mouthes of the veines: alſo, or ſtroake or falls may make the bloude diſperſe and flye abroad, which turneth to ſuppuration ad Pus when it is out of their proper veſſels. To preuent the inconueniences, the patient muſt forthwith be let bloud in the arme, and in the temples, and in the corner of the eyes: if it be poſſible alſo we muſt vſe cupping glaſſes vpon the ſhoulders, and ſuch medicines as may ſtay inflamations: afterwards, we muſt vſe ſuch medicines as doe reſolue and aſſwage payne, ſuch as theſe.
               
                  Recip Cadmie one ounce.
                  
                     aeris vſti. halfe an ounce.
                  
                     Roſarum ſiccar. foure drammes.
                  
                     Croci. one dramme.
                  
                     Folii. one dramme.
                  
                     Lapidis Suſ. one dtamme.
                  
                     Mirrhae two drams.
                  
                     Gummi ſix drams.
               
               Beat them with ſweet wine, and vſe them with an egge. Alſo a Collirium ex Thure called Diolibanum.
               
               
                  
                  Recip. Thuris.
                  
                  
                     Ceruſae an. one ounce and a halfe.
                  
                     Cadmia
                  
                  
                     Pompholigis.
                  
                  
                     Terrae ſanctae.
                  
                  
                     Amili.
                  
                  
                     Gummi an. ſix dramms
                  
                     Opii. two drammes.
                  
                     Squam aeris one ounce.
                  
                     Tragacanth. fiue dramms.
               
               Let this be framed with rayne water, Or this.
               Recip. Croci, Aloes, Mirrha, an. one dramme, 
                     Ʋini three drams, Mellis ſix drams.
               Let the Saffron be diſſolued in wine, then let it be mixt with hony, and kept in a glaſſe veſſell, with which, twiſe or thriſe a day annoynt the eies.
               If theſe medicines and remedies doe not preuaile, then we muſt trye another way: let the patient be ſet in a conuenient place, hauing one to ſtay his head behind, then let the Chyrurgian hold his with one hand with the inſtrument called Speculum oculi, deſcribed in Parcus Chirurgery, and with the other hand, with the point of a launcet he ſhall neatly and cunningly ſcarifie the

horny tunicle, vntill he come to the corrupted and ſlimy matter, which he ſhall make to auoide by little and little: After this worke ended, he ſhall vſe repercuſſiue medicines, and medicines auoyding and ceaſing paine, as the white of an egge beaten with roſe and plantain waters, and then apply the remedies which ſhal be ſet down for vlcers in the eyes, which be clenſing, increaſing fleſh, and cloſing vp: Moreouer the Chyrurgian muſt be very carefull leaſt fleſh grow in the inciſion of the Membrain, which will bring both hurt, and alſo deformity to the partie; to preuent which, this Collyrium is much availeable, and alſo commended, and doth alſo preuent inflammation.
               
                  Recip. Gummi. Arabic. ſix drammes.
                  
                     Spodii. foure drammes.
                  
                     Thuris.
                  
                  
                     Mirrhae.
                  
                  
                     Acatiae.
                  
                  
                     Spicaenard.
                  
                  
                     Squamae aeris.
                  
                  
                     Opii an. two drammes.
               
               With rayne water bring them to a perfect forme, and then make them into ſmall

trociſkes, and when you will vſe them, wet them in the white of an egge with roſe and plantaine waters.
               
                  Of Strabiſmus.
                  
                     Strabiſmus is an euill motion of the Muſcles, mouing the eyes, or a conuulſion of the eies, which if it be vnnaturall is vncurable, and that which commeth by accidents, is hardly or neuer to be cured, vnleſſe perhaps it be in infants: for the eye, for examples ſake, being conuulſed, is reduced ad leuam Raſis, and Auicen doth commend the bloud of a Turtle to be inſtilled: alſo the pye is eaten with profit, and the powder thereof is referred into a Collyrium: ſome ſuppoſe that the head of a Bat being burnt and powdered; others commend the head of a Swallow taken by inſufflation.
               
            
            
               Of Amauroſis, or Gutta Serena, or Obfuſcatio, starke blindnes, or Hallucinatio. Chap. 5.
               
               
                  Amauroſis is commonly an hindrance to the whole ſight, without any appearance at all in the eye, for the apple appeareth ſound and vnchanged, onely the Neruus opticus is ſtopped: this diſeaſe is vncurable, becauſe there are no remedies therefore:

wherefore as yet the humor being not ſetled as Aetius doth teſtifie, that he ſaw one that did recouer the ſight, onely with the applying of cupping glaſſes with ſcarification. Remedies are not to be neglected, often purgation with pils of Iod, with Trochiſks of Alhandall, Hydroticks, Maſticatoria, and alſo vehement Errhina are not to be neglected, for in this onely affect of the eyes they doe good, the braine muſt be dryed with a cappe fit for the ſame, cautiers muſt be applyed at the roote of the eare, for that cauſe remembred by Fernelius, and in Inio for reuulſion, beware you forget not to vſe cupping glaſſes. When the eye is exaſperated, annoynt it with freſh butter, aed inſtilling therein womans milke, alſo the muſcilage of philium, of quinces, of fenugreek, and of tragagant are to be applied, let the Muſcilage be drawne in the decoction of Mallowes, Holy-hocks, Violets &amp;c. Aetius doth much commend this ſalue.
               
                  Recip. Croci. one dramme.
                  
                     Mirrhae one dramme.
                  
                     Piper. gran. 15.
                  
                     Spicaenard. two ſcruples.
                  
                     Succi feniculi ſixteene drams.
                  
                     
                     Ammoniac.
                  
                  
                     Thimiamat two drams.
                  
                     Mellis ſix ounces.
               
               When they are all beaten finely, powre into them the Iuyce of Fennell, then beate them againe vntill they be dry, afterwards pur the hony vnto them, and keepe this ſalue in a braſen box for your vſe,: before you vſe this ſalue, you muſt haue a fomentation of Sea water hot, wherein dip a ſponge and often bath the eyes, alſo a Cucupha or cap prepared as followeth.
               
                  Recip. Flor. lauendula.
                  
                  
                     Stacados.
                  
                  
                     Hyſopi.
                  
                  
                     Beton.
                  
                  
                     Camomil. an. p. 1.
                  
                     Roſ. rub. p. 2.
                  
                     Calami aromat.
                  
                  
                     Ligni Aloess
                  
                  
                     Ciperi an. one dramme.
                  
                     Fol. lauri.
                  
                  
                     Maioramau p. 1.
                  
                     Nucis muſcat.
                  
                  
                     Rad. ireos.
                  
                  
                     Cinamoni an. two drams and a halfe.
                  
                     Gariphil. one dramme and a halfe.
                  
                     Stiracis cal. one dramme.
                  
                     
                     Ambrae griſeae. gran. 6.
                  
                     Muſci gran. 4.
               
               Beat all theſe to fine powder, and therwith make a cap quilted, or quilt bagges, and apply to the head.
               This electuary is commended to comfort the ſtomach, and to preuent the ingendring of groſſe phlegme in the braine.
               
                  Recip. Cinamom. opt. 1 dram, 1. ſcruple.
                  
                     Gariophil.
                  
                  
                     Ligni Aloes.
                  
                  
                     Maceris an. halfe a dram.
                  
                     Zinzib. halfe a ſcruple.
                  
                     Aniſipul. one ſcruple.
               
               Make all into powder, and take the equall waight in ſuger to them all, and with wormewood water make into tables the weight of three drammes, they are to be vſed in the morning three howers before dinner. I haue forborne to preſcribe topicall meanes, which haue little or no vſe in this caſe, becauſe the originall default is not in the eye.
            
            
               Of Opthalmia, or infl
                     •
                  mation of the aduata, or coniunctiua. Chap. 6.
               
               
                  Opthalmia is properly an inflamation of the Adnata or Coniunctiua, which is known by rednes, payne, heat, and ſtretching out:

when there is rednes without tumor, eſpecially by ſome outward cauſe, as by duſt and ſmoake, it is properly called Taraxis: when the white of the eye is ſo ſwollen vpon the blacke, ſo that a kinde thereof appeareth to hang forth, it is then called Chemoſis: ſome affirme it to be Chemoſis when the Membrain coniunctiua is higher lifted then the Cotnea, as if this were in an hole, which beſides the rednes and heat cauſeth the eye-lids to be turned, ſo that they cannot couer the eye: contrary to this is Phimoſis, when by ſome great inflamation the eie-lids doe ſtick faſt each to other, and cannot be opened, but the hurt which they receiue is but an accident in this diſeaſe. Epiphora, is generally taken for a ſuddaine ſtreame of humors in any part. As Pliny calleth epiphoram vteri or ventris, notwithſtanding it is properly vſed for the affect in the eies: when with great inflamation great quantity of humors flow vnto them all theſe aforeſaid affects do accompany each other: the cauſes are the recourſe of bloud, choler, flegme, and melancholy, but moſt commonly bloud &amp; choler: the generall oure for this diſeaſe doth conſiſt in bloud-letting, diet, purging by the aduiſe of a learned Phiſition

becauſe Opthalmicis Diarrheam ſuperuenire bonum eſt, we muſt not omit to vſe cupping glaſſes vpon the Shoulders with ſcarification which wilbe good for reuulſion, alſo an Aſtringent frontall to intercept the fluxe, if it ſeeme to be outwards. In the beginning a repellent Collyrium to hinder the generation of Phlegmon which muſt be framed of the muſcilage of phillium and of quinces, and then a reſoluing Collyrium of the muſcilage of fenugreek, being well waſhed from its byting quality. Abſtinence from wine, in the beginning is very neceſſary, yet in the declination wine may be permitted euen as a bath of ſweet water, to contemperate the bloud, is at the beginning denied, leaſt it ſhould cauſe the humor to ſhed, and increaſe the defluxion. If the inflamation do continue the muſcilages beforſaid ſhalbe drawne in the water of poppy, or in a decoction thereof, adding thereunto a little camphire or opium, and apply to the eie this cataplaſme. Take of ſodden apples iiij. ounces, and with the white of an egge and womans milk, make a cataplaſme: you muſt be carefull to renew theſe medicine leaſt they dry ouer faſt, and ſo cauſe heate: not long after vſe this Collyrium.
                  
                     
                     Recip. Gummi arabici
                     
                     
                        tragogant ana one dram.
                     
                        ceruſa lota halfe a dram.
                     
                        opij gran, iij.
                  
Diſſolue all with the white of an egge and womans milke that giueth ſuck. In the declination of this diſeaſe this may be vſed. Take of the muſcilage of fenugreek, and quince-ſeed drawne in roſe-water, and eiebright-water ana. one ounce and a halfe, in which diſſolue ſarcocoll in the milke of a woman that giueth ſuck two drams; aloes lot. one dram; mirh halfe a dram: and ſo make an eye-ſalue; and where there is any great itching, or rather where the inflammation commeth of fleagme, this is a moſt ſingular Collirium.
                  
                     Recip. tutia prep.
                     
                     
                        aloes lota ana. halfe a dram.
                     
                        ſarcocol.
                     
                     
                        myrrha ana. halfe a ſcruple.
                     
                        ſacchar. cand. one dram.
                     
                        vitriol. albi halfe a ſcruple.
                     
                        aqua roſ.
                     
                     
                        aqua faniculi ana. two ounces.
                  
Boyle them altogether a little while in a viol-glaſſe, and then drop thereof into the eie. Some commend this Collirium in all

inflamations of the eies, to take ſnayle with the ſhells, and to beate them with a little ſalt, and thorow an hypocras bagge to let the water thereof diſtill, which being cleare put thereof into the eies. It ſometimes falleth out by vnaduiſed applications, which doth coole and beate back, or elſe by ſome inflamation, that the naturall heate is extinguiſhed and choaked, and therevpon enſueth a worſe inflamation, then any of the aforenamed, which is a ſphaceloſous opthalmia, which doth depriue the eie of naturall temperature, doth make it corrupt and vtterly periſh, which diſeaſe Galen in his introduction calleth grangrena opthalmon the gangren or mortification of the eie: when this happneth wee muſt haue recourſe to proper remedies for gangrens, chaunging them as the ſtate of the diſeaſe and the part ſhall require.
            
            
               Of the ſuffuſion of ſight called Cataracta. Chap. 7.
               
               
                  Hypochyma or Cataracta is an heape of ſuperfluous humors made thick betweene the coate Cornea and the humor cryſtalloydes or cryſtallinus, directly vpon the apple

of the eie, ſwimming aboue the aqueus humor in that place, which Celſus doth affirme to be voyd and empty: it hindereth the ſight, or at the leaſt the diſcerning of ſuch things as are before our eies. Fernelius appointeth the place of it betweene the membraim Vuea and the Criſtallin humor: The difference thereof is borrowed from the quantity or quality; from the quantity, when it is whole, couering all the compaſſe of the apple of the eie, in ſuch ſort that the patient cannot ſee any thing, ſometimes it doth couer onely halfe the apple of the eie or ſome part of it, either aboue or beneath, or in the midſt, in ſuch manner that that onely part of the thing before our face can be diſcerned, which is placed againſt the part of the eie, which is affected: Some there are that doe contend and affirme that this ſuffuſion is no diſeaſe, but an outward moyſture collected before the pupil, or apple of the eie, which humidity ſeeing that it is a ſubſtance doth not ſeeme to be a diſeaſe, becauſe it is a quallity, and is placed vnder the predicament of quality: but to leaue an ouer curious queſtioning, whether it be a diſeaſe, or quality, we will proceed to the cure. Now to proceed in order to

the cure: firſt you muſt purge the braine, with pils that are proper for that purpoſe, and giue them to the patient, the day before you begin your cure: then the next day following, about nine of the clock in the morning, the patient yet faſting, (prouided that the cataract be ripe, and confirmed) cauſe him to ſit ouert: vhart a ſtoole, in ryding faſhione, and ſit on the ſame ſtoole face to face, and make the parient to hold his ſound eie cloſed with his hand, and in that ſort charge him to ſit ſteadfaſtly without ſtarting, or ſtirring in any-wife: let another alſo ſtand behind him, and hold his head very ſtedfaſt: this done, firſt with your owne hand lift vp the ouer-eie-lid, and then with thy other hand put in thy needle, made for that purpoſe in at the greater corner of the eie, and finely trilling the tunicle called ſaluatella, or ſaluatrix, writh alwaies thy finger to and fro, till thou touch with the point of thy needle the corrupt water, which is indeed the cataracte: and then begin by little and little, to remoue that water from before the ſight, to the corner of the eie, and keepe it there with the point of your needle; the ſpace of three minuts of an houre, and then remoue your needle eaſily

from it, and if it happen to riſe againe, bring it back the ſecond time: but this you muſt beware of, that when the needle hath touched the catarract, you doe not writh it about with your fingers to and fro, till it be ſet in his place before named, but to draw it thither gently, and when you haue it there, trill the needle about vntill it hath gathered the water about it, and then pull it out: when this is done cauſe him to ſhut cloſe his eie, and apply therevpon a plaſter of flaxe, and the white of an egge, and cauſe him to lie in his bed nine daies together, remouing the plaſter three times in the day, and ſo many times in the night, without any other ſtirring of it, and prouide alſo that hee lie in a very darke place, and let him be kept in a thin diet, as reare egges and white bread: and if hee be young, and of ſtrength, let him drinke Barly water, but otherwiſe let him drinke ſmall ale, and wine delayd with water, for truely too much nouriſhment would offend, in procreating too much bloud in the eie, which is very hurtfull in the beginning of the cure. When the ninth day is paſt, let him ariſe and waſh his eies with faire cold water, and hee ſhall inioy his ſight by the helpe of GOD.

euen as well as hee had it before.
            
            
               Of the Aegilops or the lacrimall Fiſtula. Chap. 8.
               
               Betweene the noſtrills and the greater corner of the eye riſeth an Apoſthume, which the Grecians do call Aegilops, that is, oculus Caprinus a Goats eye, becauſe that Goats are ſubiect to this diſeaſe, wee call this diſeaſe, Fiſtula lacrimalis. This Aegilops may happen through euery humor, yet neuertheleſſe it happeneth moſt often through fleagme, ſeldome through bloud, but ſeldome or neuer from choller or melancholly: the flegmatick humor continually flowing by the fleſh of the lacrimall corner to the noſtrils, and ſometimes vnder the ſame fleſh being there detained, doth putrifie and breaketh out into a fiſtulous vlcer, from whence certaine doe imagine that Aegilops happeneth alwaies from fleagme; and by bloud alſo this diſeaſe is wont to bee excited, but not ſo often as with fleagme: but it is ſufficient to know that this lacrimall fiſtula happeneth from ſome virulent humor and that which is corroſiue.
               
                  As concerning the cure, at the firſt beginning we muſt preſently vſe repellents, ſuch as is roſe-water and the white of an egge well beaten together, or with oyle of roſes mixt with vineger: which oyle muſt be boyled to the conſumption of the vineger: then adde thereto a little milke: wee muſt be carefull that none of the oyle ſtick to the eye, for to that part it is very biting: or apply thereto Halica boyled in vineger and beaten well together, for it doth not onlye help them in the beginning, but after they alter into Apoſtume; and doth breake them and pierce euen to the very bone: or a medicine framed of theſe, glaucium, ſaffron, and the iuyce of Pellitory of the wall, but the medicine muſt be oftentimes changed. I, ſaith, Trallianus, haue hindered theſe Aegilops as yet not growne to matter by the vſe of theſe things that they neuer came to ſuppuration: or the place is to be anointed with a Collyrium which doth vehemently ſtupifie; and leaſt the matter ſhould happen to be cold we take bdellium diſſolued in vineger with oyle of Roſes which may be mixed therewith, or Ammoniacum and the iuyce of fennel, or ſnailes with their ſhells; ſometime with Aloes and

ſometimes with Myrhe mixed, and ſo apply it. In the meane time wee muſt ordaine a diet of ſuch meate as is of good nouriſhment, and containing but few ſuperfluities, as are Chickins, Hens, Partriges, Feſants, Doues, Larkes, new laid Egges, Raiſons and ſweet Almonds: let his drinke be Hydromell or wine delayed with water: for diuerſion of the humor flowing, the humerall veine of that ſide in the arme muſt be cut, or ſome other diuerſions with cupping glaſſes, or frictions and ligatures muſt bee vſed: alſo the humors abounding, digeſted and prepared, muſt be auoided with hiera piera, or hiera logodion, or with pilles of cochia, or by clysters and ſharpe Suppoſitories, neither will one purgation ſuffice, but diuers and often reiterated: but if the diſeaſe doe continue, wee muſt vſe topicall meanes and ſuch as are diſcuſſiue. Paulus commendeth ruta Satiua cum lixiuio, framed of Aſhes and lime: indeed in the beginning it is ſomwhat biting: but afterward it is moſt gentle and doth penetrate vnto the very bone. Alexander Trallianus doth ſhew an approued medicine which is the inward membrain of the reede, that which we find about the knots, and mixe it with

honny and apply the ſame, changing the ſame foure times a day: when the place is well clenſed and purged, dip a ſpunge in mulſa and foment it: this aforeſad menbrain of the reede may bee applyed by it ſelfe or elſe.
               Recip. Staphiſagriae, two drammes. Ammoniaci in aceto diſſoluti, halfe an ounce, mixe them and apply it.
               An other.
               
                  Recip. Mellis puri,
                  
                  
                     Aloes hepat. an. two ounces.
                  
                     Myrrhae, one ounce.
                  
                     Croci, halfe a dramme.
                  
                     Aquae. lib. 2.
               
               Boyle all at a gentle fier, to the conſumption of the one halfe, and in that decoction being hot infuſe a new peece of ſponge, and with the ſame clenſe the ſore, and then bind a ſoft peece of ſponge wet in the ſame liquor, and it will worke a wonderfull effect, as hath often beene proued.
               An other medicine.
               
                  Recip. Succi foliorum lilii vel radicum eius. foure ounces.
                  
                     
                        Ʋiridis aeris vſti, one ounce.
                  
                     Mellis puri, three ounces.
                  
                     Olei nucum, Cerae q. ſ.
                  
               
               
                  Boyle all to the conſumption of the iuyces, and make an oyntment, of which put it in cum licinio or tent, as is fit. I will deſcribe an other medicine which doth not onely cure the Lacrimall fiſtula, but all other Fiſtulas.
               
                  Recip. Centauri minoris.
                  
                  
                     Ariſtolochiae rot. an. aur. 1.
                  
                     Mirrhae aur 3.
                  
                     Aluminis.
                  
                  
                     Gallae an. aur. halfe.
                  
                     Ireos.
                  
                  
                     Sarcocollae
                  
                  
                     Seif memitae an. aur. 1.
                  
                     Viridis aeris. one ſcruple.
               
               Mixe all with hony and make an oyntment. When the bone is foule, we vſe an actuall cautier, and touch the bone through a Canula, which cautier muſt be either of braſſe or ſiluer, and being artificially applied, will cure the fiſtula: (I, ſayth the Author, haue wrought with the Cautier, as aforeſaid, and haue had very good ſucceſſe.
            
            
               Generall rules for the conſeruation of the ſight. Chap. 9.
               
               
                  Whoſoeuer doth deſire to preſerue his ſight, let him take heed of the inequality of the ayre, of fire, ſmoake, winde, immoderate Coiture, much labour, ſuperfluous weeping, drunkenneſſe, ouermuch ſleepe, eſpecially in the day-time vpon meat, immoderate watchings: Let them alſo auoid meates that doe ingender vapours, ſuch as Cabbidge, Coleworts, Onions, Garlick, all ſharpe thinges, and Salt, ſallets, beanes and peaſon, all fat thinges, whether they be of fleſh, or of oyle, all thinges of hard digeſtion muſt be auoided, and all thinges that are vaporous. Medicines that doe conſerue the ſight, ſome are abſterſiue and clenſing, and meanely temperate, ſuch as are Fennell, and a Collirium of the ſame, Succus memitae, and Eiebright of its owne property: ſome there are which doe preſerue the eyes by altering, or warming, by cooling, moiſtning, or drying, ſome preſerue the ſight by lenifying the aſperitie, and other thinges, by other meanes, of which we will ſpeake afterwards.
               
                  
                  A Collirium Democriti which doth cleare the ſight and preſerue the ſame.
                  Recip. Succi faeniculi depurati lib. halfe.
                  Boyle it a little in a veſſell of braſſe, and let it remaine a while til it haue a reſidence, then add two ounces of pure hony, and boyle it againe at a gentle fire with ten or twelue leaues of good gold, then ſtraine it, and put it into a violl of glaſſe, ſtopping the mouth thereof very cloſe, then ſet it in the ſunne, powring it from veſſell into veſſell, taking alwaies away the reſidence, and put thereof into the eyes: ſome doe add thereunto the gall of a Cocke, the quantitie of two drammes.
               
               
                  Another that doth conſerue the ſight.
                  
                     Recip. Tutiae Alexandrinae praep.
                     
                     
                        Antimoniipraep.
                     
                     
                        Lapidis haematitis.
                     
                     
                        Oſſis ſepiae marinae abluti.
                     
                     
                        aeris vſti.
                     
                     
                        Cortieum aeris.
                     
                     
                        Aloes, folii, croci, an. partem
                     
                     
                        
                           Ʋnam.
                     
                     
                        
                        Piperis.
                     
                     
                        Macropiperis.
                     
                     
                        Salis ammoniaci an. partem. halfe.
                     
                        Margaritarum.
                     
                     
                        Myrobal. cheb.
                     
                     
                        Spumae maris.
                     
                     
                        Clymiae aureae.
                     
                     
                        Saccari.
                     
                     
                        Muſci, caphurae an. partem quartam
                     
                  
                  1. Let it be very finely beaten and ground vpon a marble diuers times, vntill it be a very fine powder, of which put into the eyes.
                  The eyes of a Crowe hung about the neck, ſtrengthneth a weake ſight, and doth preſerue the eyes: the roote of ſwines graſſe or knot graſſe dryed in the decreaſe of the Moone, and hung about the neck, doth alſo conſerue and ſtrengthen the ſight, neither doth it ſuffer them to be inflamed. Alſo take the leaues of Rue, of Roſes, Fennell, Eiebright and Celendine, of each equall parts, diſtill them all togither, and put a little of this water into the eyes, for it is the beſt Collirium for clearing of the eyes, for the conſeruation and comfort of the ſight: and it muſt be made in the ſpring-time. Alſo longe Comings and frictions of the head

doth diuert and turne away the vapours that doe offend the ſight: alſo it is good to behould greene thinges, and the ſkies: Cleare ſpectacles are alſo very good. Moreouer fill the hollownes of the hand in the morning with cold water, and with the ſame waſh open the eies: Alſo a nutmeg beaten with hony and eaten in the morning doth preſerue the ſight: alſo your Mirobalans Condite doe the ſame.
               
               
                  An excellent oyntment for the eyes.
                  Take Auxungia recens two ounces, ſteepe it in roſe water for ſix howers ſpace, afterwards waſh it againe in white wine twelue ſeuerall times, for the ſpace of ſix howers more, then add thereto of Tutia praep. and in fine powder one ounce, Lapis hematites well waſhed one ſcruple, Aloes lota et pul. gr. 12. margaritarum gr. 3. mix it, and with a little water of fennell make an oyntment, whereof put a ſmall quantity into the corner of the eyes.
               
            
            FINIS.
            
            
            
         
      
   

