
   
      
         
            The Leuites reuenge containing poeticall meditations vpon the 19. and 20. chapters of Iudges. By R. Gomersall.
            Gomersall, Robert, 1602-1646?
         
         
            
               1628
            
         
         Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01850
            STC 11992
            ESTC S103307
            99839064
            99839064
            3460
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01850)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3460)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1068:06)
         
         
            
               
                  The Leuites reuenge containing poeticall meditations vpon the 19. and 20. chapters of Iudges. By R. Gomersall.
                  Gomersall, Robert, 1602-1646?
                  Cecil, Thomas, fl. 1630, engraver.
               
               [18], 76, [4] p.   
               
                  [By Miles Flesher for John Marriott],
                  Imprinted at London :
                  in the yeare M.DC.XXVIII. [1628]
               
               
                  In verse.
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  With an additional title page, engraved, signed "Tho Cecill sculp", with imprint: London. Printed for Iohn Marriott 1628.
                  "A thanksgiuing for a recouery from a burning feauer", [4] p. at end.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Bible. --  O.T. --  Judges XIX-XX --  Meditations.
            
         
      
      
         
            2007-08
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2007-08
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-10
            Pip WillcoxSampled and proofread
         
            2007-10
            Pip WillcoxText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2008-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            The explanation of the Frontiſpice.
            A Leuite in his iourney goes
            To wicked Gibeah for repoſe,
            Which is deny'd, but hauing found
            Another lodging then the ground,
            (Such is th'vnkindneſſe of their ſinne)
            They make a priſon of his Inne.
            From whence he ſhall not iſſue free,
            But by his wifes Adultery;
            So when from thence to haſt he minds,
            Her dead before the doore he finds,
            When to expreſſe their crime, and make
            The villaines at their owne guilt quake,
            Into twelue pieces hee diuides
            The body that was once his Brides,
            Now Gibeah is beſieg'd, and though
            They twice haue giu'n the ouerthrow
            Vnto thier betters, yet at length
            They find Vice hath no laſting ſtrength:
            For now their town's as hot as their Deſire
            And as they burnt in Luſt, ſo that in fire.
         
         
            
            
            
               
                  THE LEVITES
REVENGE.
by
Robert
Gomerſall.
                  
                  LONDON.
Printed for
Iohn Marriott
1628.
                  
               
            
         
         
            
            THE
LEVITES
REVENGE:
Containing
POETICALL
MEDITATIONS
VPON
The 19. and 20. Chapters
of IVDGES.
            BY
R. GOMERSALL.
            Imprinted at London in the yeare
M. DC. XXVIII.
         
         
            
            
            TO
HIS VVORTHILY
RESPECTED
FRIEND,
MASTER
BARTEN HOLYDAY
ARCH-DEACON
OF OXFORD.
            WOrthy Sir; Whileſt others are
ambitious of an honourable Dedication,
I am thankfull for
a friendly one, this in the
meane time being mine happy aduantage
ouer them, that they expect, but I inioy a
Patron. And yet I haue not ſuch a ſcarcity
of great names, to whom I might pretend
with as good a confidence as the greateſt
part of Writers, but that ſome of the higher

                  ••
               nke (to whom for their frequent courte
               
                  •
               ies
I muſt confeſſe my ſelfe an vnequall
debtor) might haue expected, others almoſt
challenged my Dedication: to whom

I know no other anſwer of more reſpect and
ſatisfaction then this, that I concluded
the worke to bee below their notice,
how much more their protection; and that
I would haue others to take notice more of
my Friendſhip, then of my Ambition: But it
may be that ſome will conceiue an Ambition
in this Friendſhip, when I of ſuch an infancy
in ſtudy ſhall boaſt the fauours of ſo
growne a vertue, and intrude vpon his fame.
If this be an offence, I muſt profeſſe I glory
in it, this accuſation I confeſſe and am proud
of: ſuch is the ambition of him that is enamoured
on vertue, of the man who would
be indeared to heauen; whoſe deſires would
not be ſo good, were they not ſo high, and
the Angels might ſtill haue ſtood, had theye
neuer knowne another Pride. But not to
inſiſt on that (which neuertheleſſe I can neuer
too much inſiſt on, the remembrance of
our friendſhip) to whom could I more fitly
dedicate a Poem, then to him that hath
ſhewed ſuch excellency? or a Diuine Poem,
then to him that hath ſhewed ſuch Religion
in his compoſures? Of this truth Perſius is
a witneſſe, whom you haue taught to ſpeake
Engliſh with ſuch a grace, that wee can vnderſtand
when we heare him, and find no

one ſyllable in his Dialect offenſiue either to
the Elegant, or to the Chaſt Eare. Of this
truth Iuvenall may bee a witneſſe, whom
though we doe not yet heare in publike bettering
his expreſſions by your exact rendring
him, yet they that haue inioy'd the happineſſe
of your neerer friendſhip, confidently
and vpon the hazard of their vnderſtanding
affirme, that hee is farre vnworthy of ſuch an
impriſonment, that he ſhould bee obſcured
by that hand which cleared him. But it is
Diuinity that is the ſubiect of theſe verſes,
and it is Diuinity which is the exerciſe, and
glory of your ſtudies, which makes you an
inhabitant of the Pulpit, nay which makes
euery place where you will vouchſafe to diſcourſe,
to be a pulpit, for ſuch is the bounty
of your religious conuerſation, that howſoeuer
the place may be changed, the Sermon is
perpetuall. Sermons that at the ſame time
make vs deuout and witty, which by firſt
winning the Preacher, haue the eaſier Conqueſt
of the Auditory: who are neuer with
leſſe difficulty intreated to their happineſſe,
then when they ſee they doe not goe alone.
So that now when I conſider what I preſent,
and to whom, I beginne to ſuſpect the
lightneſſe of my worke, and thinke I haue

ſome reaſon to feare the cenſure of ſuch a
Friend, to whom if I ſhall bee excus'd, I expect
ſome glory from others, not becauſe the
Leuite, but becauſe He was mine; to whom,
hauing thus farre tryed his patience, I haue
nothing more to adde but this, that I am his,
            
               In all the duties
of Affection,
ROBERT GOMERSALL.
            
         
         
            
            To the Reader.
            REader, I muſt firſt intreat thy Patience,
afterward thy Ingenuity; thy
Patience, that thou wilt read ſomewhat
before my verſes: thy Ingenuity,
that thou wilt not cenſure the worſe of them,
becauſe thou ſhalt find them cenſur'd to thy
hand. The purpoſe of this Poem is Religious
Delight, which if thou ſhalt find in any
place wanting, or disjoynd, vnderſtand, that it
was either not my intent, or mine Error. And yet
I dare affirme no man ſhall be the worſe by it, and
that if there be any want, it is more of the Delight
then of the Religion: If I intended excuſes I
could tell you, and that truely too, that theſe Verſes
were not now firſt made, although they are
now firſt publiſhed, and the Compoſure was a
yonger mans, though the Edition be a Diuines.
This I could ſay, if I thought Poetry incompatible
with Diuinity, if it were a ſerious truth, that
God could bee onely magnified in Proſe: But
when I conſider that Nazianzen could be both a
Poet, and a Saint, and that it was hereſie that
caſt Tertullian out of the Church, and not his
Verſes. I dare acknowledge theſe for mine owne

and feare not to ſuffer in that cauſe, wherein
thoſe Worthies were ſo magnify'd: Eſpecially,
ſince theſe Eſſayes (which I feare their weakeneſſe
will too ſtrongly teſtifie) were not my ſtudy,
but my Recreation when in the vacations hauing
for a time intermitted my more ſerious affaires
I choſe Poetry before Idleneſſe; yet I haue not
choſe Poetry with the hazard of my Conſcience,
and ſo in ſtead of a Diuine haue writ a ſuperſtitious
worke; howſoeuer Malice or Ignorance
may wreſt a paſſage vnto Popery; I meane that,
where Abraham prayes for the victory of the
Iſraelites: But beſides that the Interceſſion is
generall for the Church, which no iudicious Diuine
but will allow for Orthodox, it is made by
him, whom a Popiſh Diuine will deny at that
time to be able to intercede: there was no ſolliciting
of him they ſaw not, and God they did not
ſee (as they would tell you) till after the Aſcenſion:
I haue the more fully expreſt my ſelfe
in this, becauſe I would not be eſteem'd as one of
them (whereof there is now too great an harueſt)
who play the wantons with Religion, that will
halt betweene two parties, and in ſpite of the
Prophet, at the ſame time ſcrue God and Baal▪
who like not Orthodoxe truth, vnleſſe deliuered
in hereticall termes, and ſo by a notable new trick
of Iuggling, call that Pacification, which is

Conſpiracy; of whoſe proficiency in Religion I can
ſpeake little; but this I may moſt confidently affirme,
that (perhaps not after the Apoſtles
mind, yet certainely in his words) they goe on
from Faith, to Faith. Of this crime, and of the
ſuſpition of it, I truſt I am ſufficiently acquitted:
for other errors which Malice and Curioſity will
aboundantly multiply, I onely referre my ſelfe to
the truely Iudicious, who know that a good Poem
is as a good Life, not wherein there are none, but
wherein there are the feweſt faults.
         
         
            
            
            To my learned and highly
eſteemed Friend, Mr.
ROBERT GOMERSALL.
            HAd ſuch a Labour in this iugling age
            Sought after Greatneſſe for its patronage,
            Not after Goodneſſe, I had then beene free
            To loue they worke, though not to fancy thee;
            But thou haſt wonne me: ſince I ſee thy booke
            Aymes at a iudging eye, no ſmiling looke.
            Greatneſſe doth well to ſhelter errours, thou
            Not hauing any, feareſt no frowning brow,
            But wiſely crau'ſt a view of his, that can
            Not onely praiſe, but cenſure of a man.
            Thou needſt not doubt ſeuerer eies, if he
            Adde but applauſe vnto thy Poetry.
            His workes ſuch monuments of fame doe raiſe,
            That none will Cenſure, if he once but Praiſe.
            Commend I would, but what? here's nothing knowne
            Can be call'd thine, when each hath claim'd his owne.
            
               Ioue-bred-Minerua challengeth the wit,
            
               Mercury flyes, and ſweares he languag'd it.
            Thy Arts the Muſes claime; the Hiſtory
            Sauours of nothing but Diuinity,
            Tranſcrib'd from Gods records; Then nothing's thine
            (But griefe for the Leuites ſinne) ſince th'yſe is mine.
            But now deare Friend, though this ſufficient be
            To raiſe vp Trophees, and eternize thee:
            Giue leaue to him that loues thee, to deſire
            To ſerue thee friendlike, though in meane attire.
            
               
The glittering ſtarre that darts a glorious light
            Were loſt if not commended by the night:
            So ſtands it with thy verſe; I writing ſet
            Their beauty off, as Chryſtall is by lett.
            Nor doth it trouble me; ſince that my end
            Is not to be a Poet, but a friend.
            And yet perhaps theſe looſer lines of mine
            May proue eternall; cauſe they vſher thine.
            
               
                  Midd. Temp. C. L. I C.
            
         
         
            
            
               Epitaphium Concubinae.
               Quae triſtis ignes, Gibeah, paſſa eſt tuos,
               Cultrumquè sponſi, cuius amplexum peti
                     •
                  
               
               Non vnus ardor, ecce in amplexu perit,
               Non vna facta victima &amp; multus rogus.
               Diſcant puellae formaſit quantum Nihil,
               Virtus venuſta eſt, pulchramens ſolus decor.
            
            
               Engliſhed thus.
               Who ſuffer'd Gibeahs Luſt, and her Lords knife,
               Whom not one Suitor would haue had to wiſe;
               By many Suitors periſhing, here lyes,
               A not-one Courſe, and many ſacrifice.
               O who would truſt in formes, that houres impayre
               Vertue's true ſhape, and onely Goodneſſe fayre:
            
         
         
            
            
               
                  PSAL. 9. 2.
I will be glad and reioyce in thee, yea my
Songs will I make of thy name, O thou
moſt High.
            
            FAther of Lights, whoſe praiſes to rehearſe
            Would poſe the boldneſſe of the ableſt verſe;
            Who art ſo far aboue what we can ſay,
            That what we leaue is greateſt: ſhew the way
            To my weake Muſe, that being full of thee
            She iudge Deuotion the beſt Poeſie,
            Teach her to ſhunne thoſe ordinary wayes
            Wherein the greater ſort ſeeke ſhamefull prayſe
            By witty ſinne, which ill affections ſtirres,
            Whoſe pennes at leaſtwiſe are Adulterers.
            O teach me Modeſty: let it not be
            My care to keepe my verſe from harſhnes free
            And not from lightneſſe; let me cenſure thus,
            That what is Bad, that too is Barbarous.
            Then ſhall my ſoule warm'd with thy ſacred fire,
            Aduance her thoughts, and without Pride aſpire;
            Then ſhall I ſhew the glory of my King,
            Then ſhall I hate the faults which now I Sing.
         
      
      
         
            
            THE
LEVITES
REVENGE.
            
               Canto I.
               
                  The Argument.
                  The Leuites loue, her flight, and then,
                  His fetching of her home agen:
                  
                     Gibeahs harſh vſage, with the free,
                  Vnlookt for old mans courteſie,
                  Their baſe attempt, her wretched fate
                  This ſong to Time doth conſecrate.
               
               VVHilſt Iſraels gouernement was yet but rude,
               And Multitudes did ſway the Multitude,
               Whilſt all the Nation were ſo many Kings,
               Or elſe but one great Anarchy. Fame ſings
               That there a Leuite was (Leuites may erre)
               Who had a Concubine, and doubted her.
               
                  
Durſt Luſt, and Iealouſie ſo high aſpire
               To one that onely knew the Altars fire?
               Muſt he feele other Flames? to wanton eyes
               Muſt eu'n the Prieſt be made a ſacrifice?
               Or hath he offerd incenſe ſo long time
               For Iudah's fault, that he hath gain'd their crime?
               Appeas'd for ſinnes to learne them? in times paſt
               Whilſt yet the ancient innocence did laſt,
               
                  Leuy could kill a Rauiſher, but now
               
                  Leuies baſe off-ſpring does not diſauow
               To be a Raviſher. Perhaps to ſhow
               His Grandſires raſhneſſe, who would headlong goe
               To puniſh that crime, which ere long might be
               His owne, at leaſt in his Poſterity.
               For ſo 'twas now: the Leuite loues, and more,
               Suſpects at laſt, whom he did firſt adore:
               For Fame ſpeakes hardly of her: but poore man
               What other hope couldſt thou imagine? can
               One that hath broke with honeſty, be true
               To him that made her breake? or elſe are you
               The onely Tempter? does there no blood boyle
               Beſides the Leuites? can they onely toyle
               In ſinnes, that preach againſt them? if they can,
               Yet ſuch as ſhe are made for euery man.
               What none can challenge his, is due to all,
               Luſt ſhould not imitate a Nuptiall.
               She now ſuſpects her Leuites iealouſie,
               And haſts home to her fathers houſe: ô why
               Left's thou that houſe? or why return'ſt thou euer?
               Where thou ſhouldſt alwayes ſtay, or returne neuer.
               Was then a Father to be viſited
               When thou wert made a Mother? what hope bred
               That madneſſe in thee, that vnto a mild
               Father, thou ſhouldſt be welcome for a child?
               Or vnto whom wouldſt thou haue welcome been?
               A Father? 'tis the nature of thy ſinne
               
                  
To make them doubtfull: they that liue like thee,
               Aſham'd of nothing but of Modeſty,
               Baniſh themſelues from all, but their deare ſinne;
               And looſe at once their vertue, and their kinne.
               But when the Leuite ſaw that ſhe was gone,
               That ſhe was loſt, whom he ſo dored on,
               Reaſon almoſt forſooke him too, to proue
               Anger can blind a man as well as loue:
               It may be Iſrael was holy then
               And ſacrifices for the guilty men
               Came ſlowly in, this might increaſe his griefe,
               And be an acceſſory, if not chiefe:
               This might confirme him in his angry ſinne,
               Rob'd of his profit and his concubine.
               But hee'l not looſe her: wilt thou ſeeke her then
               That does fly thee? that to an hoſt of men
               Hath giv'n thy due? as if ſhe meant to try
               Which were the moſt vnvanquiſht luxury
               Of Prieſt or people: whom if thou ſhould finde,
               Thou haſt not yet recouered her loſt mind,
               That wanders ſtill, and wilt thou fetch her thence
               To try, or elſe to teach thee Patience?
               Can ſhe teach any vertue? can there be
               Ought learnt from her beſides immodeſty?
               All that this iourney can effect, that thou
               Can'ſt promiſe to thy ſelfe, if thou ſpeed'ſt now,
               Is, that ſhee'l looſe the baſhfulneſſe ſhe had,
               And onely proue more confidently bad.
               You now may thinke him neere his iourneyes end;
               Where long before his thoughts had met his friend,
               Scorning his bodies ſluggiſh company,
               And now both are arriu'd, where to his eye
               
                  
                     •
                  he firſt appear'd, for whom alone, I find,
               Be thank'd the heav'n that did not make him blind,
               For which he ſhould haue thank'd them: he had been
               Then nor a Louer, nor a Prieſt: no ſinne
               
                  
Had crept in with the light, nor euer made
               In that good Darkeneſſe, an vnhallowed ſhade.
               But who had ſeene him when he firſt deſcry'd
               Who 'twas that met them, how he ſlipt beſide
               The wearyed beaſt, and with full ſpeed did run
               As if he meant to tempt temptation;
               He would haue iudg'd that women ſtrongeſt were,
               And men obiect the weakeneſſe which they are.
               Thus when he ſhould wiſely haue vnderſtood,
               And thank'd the kinder heau'ns, who made him good
               Againſt his will almoſt, hauing remou'd
               That which did hinder him from being belou'd
               Of God, and goodneſſe, not vnlike the Fiſh
               Which ſeemes to be deſirous of the diſh,
               (As if for his deliuery he did waite,
               And therefore were ambitious of the baite:)
               Into a knowne ſnare, he does gladly run,
               And fooliſhly purſues, what he ſhould ſhun.
               And is not this, Ide know, the readieſt way
               To make God thinke, we mocke him when we pray
               When we pretend deſire, that we may bee,
               As from the Fault, ſo the Temptation free:
               Whilſt (as we had not knowne what we had ſaid
               Or hop'd that God obſeru'd not how we praid)
               Leſt that we ſhould receiue our hurt from farre,
               We both the Tempted, and the Tempters are,
               And thus the holyeſt name we take in vaine,
               Praying as neuer meaning to obtaine.
               And now her father comes, who after words
               As kind and Elegant as that place affords,
               Intreats her pardon: but alas, good Age,
               Who ſhall intreat thy pardon, or aſſwage
               The Leuites paſſion now? who does auerre,
               That he alone does ſinne, who taxes her:
               With this he ſmiles on her, and yet does feare
               Leſt ſhe ſhould thinke that this a Pardon were,
               
                  
Or reconcilement: without much adoe,
               You might perſwade him now he came to wooe,
               And not to fetch her backe; but by the haſt
               Of carrying her from thence, fearing the waſt
               Of the leaſt minute, ſhe might well deſcry,
               What ere his words, his deeds ſpoke Iealouſie.
               Hardly he condiſcends to one nights ſtay
               Though t'were with her, but how he ſpent the day,
               How his deſires were ſpeedier then the Sunne,
               (VVhom then he thought to creep, and not to runne)
               Twere tedious to relate, though the old man
               VVith all the Art, and all the Cheare he can,
               Detaines him three daies longer, which appeare
               As long as fancy can extend a yeare.
               Minutes are Ages with him, and he deemes
               He hath out-lingred grave Methuſalems
               
               Nine hundred yeare by ſuch a ſtay, and feares
               That ſhe may once more ſhunne him for his yeares.
               Sure ſuch accounts the wiſe Aegyptians made
               VVho added wings to Time, as if he had
               Mou'd on too ſlowly, or as if they meant
               To take his fore-top from him, with intent
               To make him bald before too, whoſe records
               Had very neere as many yeares as words.
               Making full forty thouſand ere the fall,
               And pu'ny Adam of no age at all.
               The fifth day dawnes, but ere the riſing Sunne
               Had ſhew'd the victory which he had wonne
               Of cloudy night, before the ſleepy Cocke
               Had prou'd himſelfe to be the Country Clocke
               Shewing the mornings houre, when now wee might
               Haue ſpoke no falſhood had we call'd it Night.
               Our Leuite for his iourney does prepare,
               And his are dreſt, ere Phoebus horſes are:
               To whom the Father comes, and gently chides
               
                  
                     •
                  is earely ſonne-in-law, who, forſt, abides
               
                  
Till afternoone with him, and then he goes
               Not from the houſe ſo faſt, as to his woes.
               Sure the old man did prophecy the harme,
               Which would inſue, when he did ſeeke to charme
               Our Leuite to a longer ſtay: but O
               Tis double miſery before hand to know
               We ſhall be miſerable! then why hath man
               That curſt ability, that well he can
               Prognoſticate miſhapps, when they are neere?
               And all his knowledge teaches but to feare.
               Which yet our Leuite hath not learnt, who rides
               Doubting no danger: now the worlds eye glides
               To his weſt Inne, when Iebus he eſpies,
               Whom he counts his, becauſe Gods enemies.
               Hearken ye Gallants that will croſſe the ſeas,
               And are induſtrious for a new diſeaſe,
               If you will needs be gadding, and deſpiſe
               For forraine toyes, our home-bred rarities,
               Take this example with you, if you goe
               Trauell not from Religion: why, although
               You neuer touch at Rome, or elſe perchance
               You ſcarce ſee Spaine, and gleane but part of France▪
                  
               
               You may be weary, thinke your trauell great,
               And ſpare at once your conſcience, and your ſweat▪
               
               You ſee our Leuite though the night draw neere,
               His loue be weary, and no towne appeare
               Where ſhe may reſt herſelfe, although the way
               Were troubleſome enough ev'n in the day,
               Yet ſhe reſolues gladly to vndergoe
               More miſeries then Night and danger know,
               Ere he will venture there to make his ſtay
               From whence the Idols had droue God away.
               O farre vnworthy of thy future Fate
               By this beſt Action! miſerable ſtate
               Of too great vertue ill-imploy'd! to be
               Puniſh't, when he did ſhunne Iniquitie
               
                  
As he did Iebus. How he ſpurs, how rates
               His tardy beaſt! how his owne ſlackneſſe hates
               Which forc't him by his trauelling ſo late
               If not to ſtay, yet to deliberate.
               Within the Center of the Earth there ſtands
               Neere to the fiery ſtreames, and aſhy ſands,
               A dreadfull pallace, of ſuch vncouth frame
               Each part ſo ſhap't as if twere built to ſhame
               All Architecture, that if one did ſee
               The vaſtneſſe of it, and deformity,
               He would not make the leaſt demurre to tell
               That t'was a lodging for the Prince of Hell.
               What ere does beautifie a houſe, here wants,
               The walls are blacke as the Inhabitants,
               Made out of Iett, into ſuch figures fram'd
               That Nature dare not owne them, nor be blam'd
               With ſo much Monſter: wee in doubt may call
               Whether the trimming, or materiall,
               Had the more horror. No birds here are heard,
               But ſuch whoſe harſher accents would haue ſeard
               The moſt reſolu'd: they puniſh in their rimes,
               And all their ditty does conſiſt of crimes.
               The fly Praeciſian that could gull the eye
               Of the moſt ſharpe, by cloſe hypocriſie,
               Whoſe miſchiefes onely he that did, could tell,
               Who, we may thinke might eu'n haue cheated Hell
               VVith ſuch diſſembling, ſees his vices bare,
               Naked, and foule, as when they acted were:
               One layes oppreſſion to his charge, another
               His ſiſters inceſt, murther of his brother.
               They ſhew his zeale was onely to contend,
               And all his reformation not to mend
               But to confound the State, that his knitt brow
               (Which lookt ſo ſterne as it would diſallow
               The moſt indifferent act, and like of none
               But ſuch as did pretend perfection)
               
                  
VVas but an eaſie Vizor, ſuch as Rage
               Can giue it ſelfe, and muſt receiue from Age.
               That he did onely know externall Grace,
               And all his holineſſe was in his face.
               Is goodneſſe in a wrinckle? can we find
               That what does cloud the face, does cleanſe the mind?
               To me it is a tricke of rareſt art
               That hollow browes ſhould haue the ſoundeſt heart.
               Theſe are the ſounds, but then the ſmells are worſe,
               Enough to make that Harmony no Curſe.
               Vnder the walles there runnes a brimſtone flood
               The top of flames, the bottome was of mud:
               Of ſuch groſſe vapour, that to ſmell was Death,
               Priſons are ſweet, compar'd vnto that breath.
               And to maintaine the fire and ſtench at once,
               The fewell is prepar'd of vſurers bones.
               Looſe Madams lockes, the feathers of their Fanne,
               VVith the foule inſide of a Puritan.
               In this ſweet place as ſweet a Prince doth dwell,
               The cheife of fiends, the Emperor of Hell
               Grand Lucifer, whom if I ſhould relate
               In the worſt figure that the eye doth hate:
               I ſhould but faintly his foule ſelfe expreſſe,
               Nor reach to his vnpattern'd vglineſſe.
               Death keepes the entrance, a tall ſturdy groome,
               Who emptying all places fills no roome.
               But like the fond Idolater of pelfe
               Denyes men, what he cannot haue himſelfe:
               Here does this ſhade ſend challenges to all,
               Who would h
                     •
                  ue entrance firſt to try a fall,
               They try, and they are throwne ther's none ſo great
               But yeelds to him, who knew but one defeat
               And that long after, but his prime was now,
               His bones ſome marrow had, ſome grace his brow.
               No plagues as yet, no famines had beene knowne
               The ſword was thrifty, making few to groane
               
                  
Vnder his edges. Death yet had luſty thighes,
               Nor ſpent himſelfe with too much exerciſe.
               Here there ſtand numbers, which exceed all ſummes
               (For they refuſe none here, who euer comes)
               The murtherer firſt, and without much adoe,
               Sometime he will admit the murtherd too.
               Then the incontinent, but if that he
               Be knowne by Inceſt or Adultery,
               His ſeat is chiefe: nor haue they a low place,
               Who with an open and alluring face,
               Delude their truſting friends, till they haue woon
               Their deeper proiects, which they built vpon.
               The reſt of lower crimes, whom we may call,
               Downe-right offenders, ſuch as after all
               Their time of treſpaſſe, haue not gain'd the skill,
               And onely know the taint, not art of Ill:
               Haue no diſtinguiſht roomes, but venture in,
               As headlong to their paines, as to their ſinne.
               But now ſome other enter; for a charge
               Paſt from the Prince of ſhadowes, to inlarge
               Th'impriſon'd Crimes, that all might now conferre
               (Such is his will) with their Lord Lucifer.
               What noyſe there was? what ſtriuing at the doore?
               This would be firſt, and that would goe before:
               Pride claimes precedency, and cryes who ere
               Ventures to make a ſtep before her there
               Is impudently fooliſh, that the place
               Is hers by due, and onely theirs by grace,
               When ſhe would yeeld it: vnleſſe firſt they would
               Bring more conuincing reaſons then ſhe could:
               For who ſhould to the Prince of Hell firſt goe
               To viſit him, but ſhe that made him ſo?
               And who had made him ſo, ſhee'd know, but ſhe,
               When with his God he claim'd Aequality?
               Peace, Wrath exclaimes, and with ſo deepe an oath
               As all thoſe fiends, with Hell to boot, were loath
               
                  
To heare another ſuch, he vowes no more
               To beare the brauings of that ſcarlet whore,
               Hee'l firſt a Rebell, firſt a Vertue be,
               And no more VVrath, but Magnanimity.
               She ſmil'd, and bid him be ſo but whilſt they
               Were hot in this contention, Enuy lay
               Gnawing her breaſts: faine would ſhe haue bin higher
               Had but her ſpirit equall'd her deſire.
               But ſince ſhe cannot be reueng'd of them,
               She vſeth an vnheard of ſtratagem,
               Teares her owne haires, and her grimme face beſlimes
               Thus puniſhing herſelfe for others crimes.
               By this time Idleneſſe comes in the reare,
               As proud, though not as actiue, as they were;
               He ſcarce would take the paines to ſpeake, but loth
               To looſe his dignity by too much Sloth,
               He giues them theſe few words, VVhy ſtriue you ſo
               About the place which all to mee doe owe?
               Doe not ye know, I am the raigning Crime,
               Moſt generall, and moſt lofty of the time?
               I make the Lawyer ſilent, though he ſee
               His clyent full; I am beyond a Fee:
               When Lawes doe not, I make the Preacher dumbe
               Eu'n when the Tyger, or the Wolfe doe come:
               But aboue all, I in the Court doe grow,
               Beggars are proud, but Emperors are ſlow.
               Drunkenneſſe could not anſwere, but does thinke
               Twas fit that Idleneſſe ſhould yeeld to drinke:
               And reeling to encounter him, does fall
               Iuſt in the entrance, and excludes them all.
               Now is the skirmiſh hotter then before,
               Now Pride begins to ſcratch, and VVrath to roare;
               Drunkenneſſe lyes vnmou'd, and Sloths intent
               Is to ſit ſtill, and to expect th'euent.
               But in this ciuill broyle, at laſt comes Craft
               Of whom no Painter ere could take a draft,
               
                  
He had ſuch change of ſhapes, who when he ſaw
               Theſe tumbling warriours, and that no awe,
               No feare of Lucifer could teach them peace,
               Hee'l try his skill to make theſe broyles to ceaſe.
               Fie Pride, ſayes he, What? giue your ſelfe the fall?
               And Wrath, are you no more diſcreet withall
               Then quarrell with a woman? Come agree,
               If not for feare of Hell, for loue of me.
               But out alas, you doe too well agree,
               When VVrath is Proud, and Pride will Wrathfull be.
               Goe hand in hand (thus friendly Craft decides)
               Onely the vpper hand let that be Prides.
               They enter the great hall, where they doe ſee
               The Helliſh Monarch in his Maieſty,
               VVhere hauing made obeyſance, he beginnes,
               Thus to breake ſilence, and vpbraid the Sinnes.
               The reaſon why I call'd you (not to dwell
               On an vnneceſſary praeamble)
               Is to informe you, that we find of late
               You haue not beene officious to the State:
               Tis true, you bring me daily what's mine owne,
               And plentifully reape what I haue ſowne.
               In the groſſe Heathen you doe hourely cauſe
               Vices, which neuer were forbid by Lawes,
               Becauſe ne're thought of: but what's this to me,
               VVhether that Luſt or Infidelity
               Fill Hell with thoſe, nay and oppreſſe it too,
               VVhich muſt come thither, whatſoere they doe?
               You doe like thoſe, who in the other life
               Buy their owne lands, and wooe againe their wife.
               A goodly act, and wherein's danger ſtore,
               You giue me that, which was mine owne before.
               VVhilſt Iudah all this while hath me withſtood,
               And dares, when I forbid them, to be good.
               They honor Parents with a zealous ſtrife,
               And with their goodneſſe doe prolong their life.
               
                  
In them no malice nor no rancor lyes,
               Nor ſhed they bloud, but for a ſacrifice:
               Adultery's ſcarce heard of in a life,
               And they are men only vnto their owne wife.
               In ſuch a lou'd community they liue,
               None need to ſteale, all are ſo apt to giue.
               While you ſuppoſe that highly you deſerue,
               If you can ſay that you haue made them ſwarue
               From goodneſſe that ne're had it: well y'aue done
               If that Semiramis once doate vpon
               Her wondring iſſue, and begin to ſwell
               With ſuch a birth, that would poſe vs to tell
               How ſhe ſhould call it; and what ſhe did beare
               If it her daughter, or her grandchild were.
               You haue diſcharg'd your office, if you make
               Some bloudy Nations their owne iſſue take
               And offer vnto me; or if you draw
               Some to the practice of that wicked Law
               That after fifty they their parents kill,
               And not that onely, but ſuppoſe that ill
               To be their duty. O fond thought! and thence
               Doe eſtimate their childs obedience?
               Hence truant Crimes, auant, no more appeare
               In my dread preſence, no more let me heare
               Thoſe petty actions, if you doe not ſtraight
               Reuenge my wrongs, and eaſe me of this waight,
               VVhich thus oppreſſeth me, if Iſrael ſtill
               Shall dare to croſſe what I ſhall call my will;
               By Hell Ile doe—but what? I ſay no more,
               If you are wiſe, preuent, if not, deplore.
               This ſaid he ſtar'd ſo fiercely that they fear'd
               He would performe much more then they had heard,
               Nor know they wel how they their tongues ſhould vſe,
               VVhether twere beſt to promiſe or excuſe.
               At laſt Luſt riſes, and becalmes him thus,
               VVhy doe you looſe your wrath, great Prince, on vs?
               
                  
Vs your ſworne vaſſals? who nor thinke nor doe
               But what your will is their command vnto.
               What though w'aue ſpent our paines not the right way?
               Yet they were paines nor can an enemy ſay
               But we were actiue Furies, and haue done
               VVhat leſſer feinds durſt not haue thought vpon.
               And yet (if that I may haue leaue to tell
               From your dread grace) preciſer Iſrael
               
               Hath not eſcap'd vs wholly, nor hath bin
               More noted for their Law, then for their Sinne▪
               
               VVas that a Vertue too, when being led
               By Gods owne hand, and fill'd with Angels bread,
               They did, (I ioy to caus't, but bluſh to tell,)
               They did repine eu'n at that miracle.
               Faſting and full they murmure, nor are leſſe
               Angry with Manna then with Emptineſſe.
               I could ſpeake more, and truely: but in ſumme,
               To proue my paſt acts by my acts to come;
               If by your gracious leaue, I haue the fate
               To haue a ioynt commiſſion with Debate,
               Ile make a fire within their blood to burne,
               Shall their proud Cities into aſhes turne:
               And they ſhall know how fooliſhly they erre,
               VVho are not willing ſlaues to Lucifer.
               Lucifer nods, and Luſt does ſwiftly runne
               VVith his vnlimited Commiſſion:
               VVhich with what Art, what miſchiefe he did vſe,
               Is now the griefe and bus'neſſe of my Muſe.
               But now ſhe muſt to our ſad Leuite haſt
               VVhom we left trau'lling, when the day was paſt.
               The ſunne ſets ouer Gibeah; when that he
               Drawes neerer thither ward, but then to ſee
               The bluſh of Heau'n, with what a red it ſhin'd,
               (As if the Sunne his office had reſign'd
               Vnto thoſe clouds) to all that vnderſtood,
               It would haue ſhew'd that it did figure blood.
               
                  
And now our Leuite is arriu'd, but finds
               The walls more courteous then the peoples minds:
               For theſe had gates which let him in, but they
               Were mercileſſe, and rougher then the way:
               Men that had onely ſtudied to oppreſſe,
               Whoſe minds were ſhut againſt the harbourleſſe:
               And yet he ſees large houſes, ſome ſo high
               As if they learn't acquaintance with the sky,
               What euer pleas'd their fathers now growes ſtale,
               Their buildings to the hills exalt the vale:
               And ſuch thicke palaces the mountaines fill,
               As if the quarry grew without the hill.
               Some are of that circumference, you'd gueſſe,
               They had beene built for him, who had no leſſe
               Then the whole world his Family. But when
               Our Leuite was inquiſitiue, what men
               Fill'd vp that Princely dwelling? and if there
               Might be found hope of reſt for them that were
               But two more then the Family? they tell
               That two are the whole Family, 'twas well,
               And ſtately too (as ſtate is at this day)
               So might they liue at home, and yet away.
               O the great folly of Magnificence!
               Houſes are little Cities, and from thence
               Cities are leſſer worlds, that man may haue
               Roome enough here that cannot fill a graue.
               He muſt haue Halls, and Parlors, and beſide
               Chambers inuented, but not nam'd by pride:
               And all this for one man, as if he ſought
               To haue a ſeuerall lodging for each thought,
               But none for any ſtranger: this truth ſeemes
               Too certaine to our Leuite, who eſteemes
               That pris'ners are in better ſtate then he;
               Nay, eu'n the pris'ners of mortality,
               Such as are faſt immur'd within the graue
               Who though they want a life, a lodging haue:
               
                  
Inhumane wretches! haue you then forgot
               That you were ſometime ſtrangers? Were you not
               In Aegypt once? where the Propheticke land
               Did iuſtly ſcourge your baſeneſſe before hand,
               Knowing you would be barbarous, and ſo
               Made you to reele the harſhneſſe which you ſhow?
               O
                     ••
                  uelly forgetful 
                     〈◊〉
                   that indure
               To act, or elſe out-doe the Epicure,
               Whilſt he feeds on the Ayre; that thinke it meet
               To lye in Downe, while he lyes in the ſtreet!
               An old man thought not thus, but to his houſe
               Intrea
                     ••
                  s the ſtrangers: 'tis malicious
               To lay the imputation vpon Age
               That it is couetous (as if the ſage
               Haires of the Ancient were therefore white
               To ſignifie their ſiluer Appetite.)
               Peace you blaſphemers, ſee an aged man
               Couetous onely of a Gueſt, who can
               Repay him nothing, but his Prayer, and be
               Indebted once more for his Piety;
               But if my Muſe haue any power o're time
               And ſinne haue more mortality then rime,
               Old man thou ſhalt be euer old, and haue
               No entertainment in the ſilent graue
               For this thy entertainment: here a while
               Let me admire how that a towne ſo vile,
               Which we would thinke with ſtangers had decreed
               To ſhut out Vertue too, ſhould rarely breed
               Such a ſtrange Vertue? quietly we heare
               Of courteſies in Rome; of kindneſſe there
               Where Greece is nam'd, who counted it a ſinne
               Not to haue made each noble houſe an Inne
               For worthy ſtrangers: but when one ſhall fall
               In commendation of the Canniball,
               Shall ſay that they, who on their gueſts doe gnaw
               And entertaine their ſtrangers in their maw,
               
                  
Are hoſpitably minded, that eu'n there
               May be a mouth which is no Sepulcher.
               VVe ſtand agaſt, as if we did conſpire
               Not to beleeue the good we did deſire.
               VVhence ſprung this Singularity? whence came
               This worth which ſo deſerues and conquers Fame?
               Our Vertues are not borne with vs, and they
               Which will innoble man till times laſt day
               Liue after them they make to liue, what we
               Call goodneſſe is the gift of Company.
               Our ſtudy not our Nature, and could theſe
               Teach any other thing beſides diſeaſe
               In manners? it is fit then we confeſſe
               Mercy is learn't amongſt the mercileſſe,
               And rather then a Leuite ſhall want reſt
               Auarice ſelfe ſhall entertaine a Gueſt.
               But now the Leuite hath forgot that he
               Had felt the hard ſtreets hoſpitality;
               He finds ſuch kindneſſe, that he does ſuppoſe
               Courteſie wore no other haires then thoſe
               To grieue the honeſt world, who now might feare,
               That ſhe was haſting to her ſepulcher.
               Into an anticke roome he leads him firſt.
               Where one would gueſſe that Abraham had been nurſ:
               Or a more ancient Patriarch, the walles
               Compos'd of that which from a wett ſhooe falles
               In weeping winter, which a man would thinke
               Their age had now dry'd vp into one Chinke.
               Yet ſuch a roome one comfort does afford,
               It was not built to ruine its ſad Lord.
               For who will begge a Cottage? who would make
               A guilty wretch, that he his rags might take?
               To that whence nothing comes is no regard:
               None would be vicious too but for reward.
               No, let them feare who dwell in arched vaults,
               Who in much roome doe ſeeke to hide their faults.
               
                  
Where hundred columnes riſe to mate the skie,
               And mocke their Lords with falſe Diuinity.
               Enuie is proud, nor ſtrikes at what is low,
               And they ſhall onely feele who ſcorne her blow:
               She on no baſe aduantage will inſiſt,
               Nor ſtriue with any but that can reſiſt.
               Now is the table ſpred, and now the meat
               Be'ing ſet, each takes him his appointed ſeat:
               No courtſhip here is ſhew'd, no caruing grace,
               The entertainment (homely as the place)
               Spoke onely hearty, and that plaine intent
               Which greater entertainers complement.
               So Abraham feaſted heau'nly gueſts, as when
               He made the Angels eate the bread of men:
               Soon the like gueſts hoſpitable Lot,
               
               Beſtow'd the diet which they wanted not;
               In this ours differs, nay in this exceeds,
               That he beſtowes his kindneſſe where it needs.
               One would haue thought ſo, when he heard the noiſe,
               Of confus'd multitudes, men mixt with boyes,
               All ages in the cry, as if they meant
               That now the Babes ſhould not be innocent:
               Bees doe not murmure ſo, and angry hounds
               In their full rage ſend forth but eaſy ſounds,
               Compar'd to this: their inland Sea ſtood ſtill,
               Wondring to heare himſelfe out-ſcar'd, and till
               This time, that noiſe hath ſuch a ſilence bred,
               That euen ſince it hath beene ſtyl'd the Dead.
               Now they beſiege the houſe, and one would feare
               That their loud tongues ſo many engines were
               To batter it: downe with the Gate, cryes one,
               Another laughes at that, and with a ſtone
               Threatens to force a Gate, and deepely ſwore
               To giue them entrance, all the Houſe was Doore.
               But then another that would needs be wiſe,
               And counted cheife in this great enterpriſe,
               
                  
Exhorts them to a Parly: Why, my friends,
               Make you ſuch haſt, ſayes he, to looſe your ends?
               Haue you indented with the ſtones you throw
               To miſſe the Leuite? Doe you thinke no blow
               Can faſten on him, or d'ye meane to proue
               If that the ſtones are riualls in your Loue?
               Stones and not men! with that the hands were ſtill,
               But all the noyſe, the Hubbub, with an ill
               Conſent, cries for the Leuite, whom they faine
               Would onely know, and ſo returne againe.
               And could you ſee him in the ſtreet ſo long,
               As farre from beeing laid, as this your wrong
               Shall be from after-Ages, when he had
               No couer, but the kinder heau'ns, (whoſe ſad
               Compaſſion hindred them from ſhedding teares,
               Leſt ſuch a griefe ſhould make th'vnkindneſſe theirs)
               Had you ſo full a view of him, and yet
               Doe you deſire to know him? No, forget
               That euer there was ſuch an one, and then
               Poſterity may thinke that you were men:
               How will they wonder elſe, when they ſhall heare
               You lou'd him in the houſe, whom you did feare
               To bring into your houſe; that you were mad,
               In the purſuit of that you might haue had?
               You aim'd another, a worſe way, and iuſt
               His anſwere is, that calls your Knowledge, Luſt.
               But how were they ſo long time innocent?
               How was this Prodigy of Deſire eu'n ſpent
               Before it was expreſt? here we may ſee
               In impudence there was ſome Modeſty:
               They would not ſinne at home, the worſt abhor'd
               To be a Beaſt, where he ſhould be a Lord.
               And it ſeem'd better to the vileſt breaſt
               Not to receiue, then to abuſe a Gueſt.
               Now the Old-man not fearing any harme
               That might enſue, whether he hop'd the warme
               
                  
Luſt of their Youth, would by his Age bequelld,
               And that thoſe flames would to ſuch winter yeeld:
               Or whether he was then rather addreſt
               To offer vp himſelfe before his Gueſt
               Vnto their Fury, forth he goes: they thought
               That now they ſhould obtaine what they had ſought,
               Whom thus he does beſpeake, Haue patience
               My friends, I come, not to intreat you hence,
               But to fulfill your pleaſure, onely change
               The Se
                     ••
                   I haue a daughter and what's ſtrange
               In this not towne a Virgin
                     •
                   at your ſure
               I am content to make her proſtitute.
               So that my ſtranger may nor iniur'd 
                     •
                  e
               Nature ſhall yeeld to Hoſpitality.
               O conſtant goodneſſe! O beſt act, which can
               Conclude the Vertue, older then the Man▪
               
               How I could 
                     〈◊〉
                   my ſelfe in prayſing thee,
               Man not of Age, but of Aeternity!
               Who didſt reſpect thy gueſt beyond thy blood,
               And knew'ſt the difference betwixt Fond, and Good.
               Henceforth ſcorne all compariſons below,
               Onely thy Maker, thy Superiour know:
               Such was his Mercy that he did beſtow
               His onely Sonne a ranſome for his Foe;
               (This was a patterne fit for the moſt High)
               Yet next this Mercy, was thy Charitie:
               Thy Act at leaſt is ſecond to the beſt,
               Who wouldſt not ſpare thy Daughter for thy Gueſt
               But they'l not be preſcrib'd in their deſire,
               Who thinke to alter, were to quench their fire:
               They muſt the Leuite or his Siſter know,
               (For Siſter they interpret her) to ſhow
               Our ſawcy Lay-men how they ſhould expound
               Their Preachers actions, not to be profound
               To ſearch their faults, but well and wiſely too,
               Doe what they ſpeake, and not ſpeake what they doe.
               
                  
This they exclaime, and this our Leuite heares,
               Who now hath ſpent his Reaſon, and his Fares,
               Such a Confuſion he is falne into,
               He knowes not what to ſhunne, nor what to doe,
               So in rais'd Seas, when that the angry wind
               Threatens deſtruction to that daring kind,
               Who to a flying houſe themſelues commit,
               (Seeming at once to flye too from their wit.)
               The well-ſtor'd paſſenger, (when he does find
               That all this fury of the waue and wind
               Is for this Treaſure) now reſolues to dye:
               (Death is not ſo much fear'd as Pouerty)
               And now reſolues that he will venture on
               More loſſe before that Reſolution:
               He does from this vnto that purpoſe skip,
               And now his mind more totters then his ſhip.
               Till after all this tedious, fooliſh ſtrife,
               Which he ſhall ſaue, his treaſure, or his Life,
               He ſhall ſaue neither; and thus being loath
               To hazard either, he does forfeit both.
               And now ſhe ſhall be Paſſiue. O Fates ſport!
               Hee'l now betray, that ſhould defend the Fort.
               Such Revolution did you euer ſee?
               Who earſt was Iealous, will a Pander be.
               O Life, thou moſt deſir'd, and wretched thing!
               Thy loue betrayd his loue, from thee did ſpring
               This Contradiction of croſſe Faults. O why
               Choſe he not rather to doe well, and Dye?
               Why did he ſo deſire to ſhunne his Friend,
               And call that Miſery, which was an End?
               The Dead doe feare no Rauiſher, no Luſt
               Was ere ſo hot, to dote vpon cold duſt,
               Were he once dead he ſhould feare no crimes then,
               Neither his owne, nor thoſe of other men:
               And could he wiſh a longer life? let thoſe
               Who doe not know (but by inflicting) wees
               
                  
Hugg that deſire, but hee who wiſely wayes
               What many miſeries are in many dayes,
               Let not him be ſo mad to wiſh his feares,
               And onely proue his Dotage by his Yeares.
               Neuer did Morning bluſh ſo much as that
               Which next appear'd; when vp our Leuite gat,
               And running nimbly to the doore, he ſees
               His loue before the doore with her faire knees
               Growne to the Earth, ſo cloſe, that one would ſeare,
               She tooke a meaſure of her Sepulcher,
               With hands outſtretch'd, as if, fearing to faile,
               She meant to make a Sexton of her naile
               To dig her graue: or elſe (for who can tell?)
               Suſpecting by her iniuries an Hell
               Not to be farre, where ſuch ſinnes had a birth,
               She lay ſo cloſe, to feele if it were Earth.
               He wonders at the poſture, nor knowes why
               She had not choſe to reſt more eaſily.
               And now he will be ſatisfy'd, but ſhe
               Had loſt her tongue too, with her Chaſtity.
               He thinkes ſhe ſleepes, and therefore louder cryes,
               Why doe we dally here? Wake, and Ariſe.
               But let him cry on, ſhe hath heard her laſt,
               Deafe to all ſounds now, but the lateſt blaſt.
               And art thou dead, he cryes? what dead? with that
               You'd wonder which had beene aliue, as flat
               He lay, and ſpeechleſſe, glad of the ſame death,
               But that thicke ſighes betray that he had breath:
               Which onely ſerues his Anger: now he hyes
               Home to mount Ephraim, all his ielouſies
               Are dead with her, and now he meanes to make
               Her common after death: each Tribe ſhall take
               A peice of her; O the obdurate mind
               That ſo could part, what God had ſo combin'd!
               I faint in the relating it, nor well
               What he durſt act, dare vndertake to tell.
               
                  
Twelue made of one? O who would not be mad,
               To thinke vpon that madneſſe? if ſhe had
               But ſuch another griefe, with both oppreſt,
               My Muſe would then be dumbe, which now doth reſt.
            
            
               Canto II.
               
                  The Argument.
                  The twelue peices of his wife
                  Cut out by the Leuites knife,
                  To the field to doe him right,
                  Draw the neiled Iſraelite.
                  
                     Abrahams Prayer, Heau'ns decree,
                  
                     Beniamins glad victory
                  Twice repeated, make the ſumme
                  Of the booke which is to come.
               
               SVch crimes amongſt the Iſraelites? I feare
               Incredulous poſterity will ſweare
               Mine was the fault, and when they muſe hereon
               They'l iudge the Crime was in my Fiction.
               When Vice exceeds a Probability
               It gaines excuſe, ſo that to ſinne on high
               Is politicke offence, for he that ſhall
               Sinne ſo, is thought not to haue ſinn'd at all.
               'Tis the corruption of the minds of men
               To iudge the worſt of actions, but 'tis when
               The fault is frequent, when the daily vſe
               Giues it at once, the guilt, and the excuſe:
               But if a crime ſwell to the height of this,
               Murder, or Inceſt, or if any is
               Of fowler name; when man will man abuſe,
               We doe abſolue more gladly then accuſe,
               
                  
Can it be poſſibly preſum'd that they
               To whom the God of Iacob ſhew'd the way,
               Both of their feet and manners, who had ſeene
               His frequent Miracles, nay who had been
               Part of the wonder too, ſo to haue fell
               As to commit a greater Miracle?
               
                  Sodome in Iudah? now the Fable winnes
               Credit, and is out-acted by true ſinnes:
               Report hath made Pygmalion to haue lou'd
               That which he made, who by his Art was mou'd
               To palpable Idolatry, yet ſo
               At leaſt he lou'd a woman in the ſhow:
               Hee's fixt on his faire Image, ſo that one
               Would wonder which had beene the truer ſtone.
               Yet 'twas a Womans Image, ſo that I
               Wonder at's lucke, more them his vanity,
               A Painted Woman will cauſe loue: i'me mou'd
               More, how he did obtaine, then why he lou'd.
               Theſe doe affect what to obtaine is worſt,
               What in the very thinking is accurſt:
               In other loues the wife may barren proue,
               In this the barrenneſſe is in the Loue,
               In other faults there haue excuſes beene,
               This hath no other Motiue then the Sinne.
               And can this ſinne be theirs? Yes know it can,
               Man forſakes God, and then he doates on man.
               But who did tutor them to this offence?
               For, though we find it in each conſcience
               That we are naturally vicious,
               That ther's no true good in the beſt of vs,
               That we purſue our ill, as drawne by Fate,
               Yet 'tis example does ſpecificate,
               That teacheth vs This ſinne: 'tis mine owne Vice,
               But that I am more loſt in Auarice,
               That I doe chooſe Adultery, or preferre
               The luſtfull man before the Murtherer,
               
                  
I haue from Praeſident: and thus our ill
               Comes from the Patterne too, as from the Will.
               Aegypt denyes to haue an hand herein,
               (Aegypt the houſe of bondage, not of ſinne.)
               Their cruelty I heare, and which is odd,
               I read that their chiefe ſinne, is their chiefe god.
               They make their gardens heau'ns, and in each plant
               They find a Deity: If that any want
               Be in their fields, if thence they doe not gaine,
               It is their gods they want, and not their graine.
               Their ſuperſtition yet might iſſue hence,
               The Calfe, on which they plac'd their confidence,
               Which act this glory to them doth afford,
               They make themſelues the beaſt which they ador'd.
               Or did the Deſart make them thus to ſtray,
               And cauſe them looſe their Manners with the Way?
               Did thoſe vaſt places, which wiſe Nature fram'd,
               Wherein wild man ſhould by his feare be tam'd,
               His feare of wilder beaſts, inſtruct theſe men,
               That there are beaſts which are not in the Denne:
               And that when euer we neglect, or ſcanne
               The Lords commands, the Monſter is the Man?
               No, theſe ſuſpitions may ſuſpected bee,
               As farre from Truth, as they from Honeſty:
               Aegypt was free from this fault, and much leſſe
               Can we impoſe it on the Wilderneſſe.
               They had no King: as well the fooles as wiſe
               Did all what did ſeeme right in their owne Eyes.
               And Sodomes crime ſeem'd right to ſome to ſee
               When euery man will his owne Monarch bee,
               When all ſubiection is 
                     •
                  one quite away,
               And the ſame man does gouerne and obey,
               How there is no obedience nor rule,
               How euery man like to the Horſe and Mule,
               Which want the vnderſtanding of their bit,
               And neither haue their owne, nor Riders wit,
               
                  
Make a ſwift pace to Ruine. Giue me then
               Leaue to admire, and pitty thoſe poore men,
               Who thinke that Man ſhould his owne Ruler be,
               And exerciſe Home-principality:
               Who in one ſpeedy minute ſtrangely doe
               What Alexander but aſpir'd vnto,
               Conquer all Kingdomes, which they'affirme to be,
               No better then a well-nam'd Tyranny.
               Let me inquire of theſe, if they haue read
               Any ſuch crimes where people had an head?
               Let me inquire of men, as yet not wild,
               Whether they thinke themſelues Lords of their child?
               Whether their ſeruants Maſters? whether they
               Suppoſe that God did not make ſome t'obey.
               In Innocence there was Dominion,
               And the firſt man was the firſt Lord: that one
               King of the Creatures, whom for this none blames,
               He prou'd his Soueraignty by their Names.
               That he was his wiues Soueraigne, in the Fall
               He fell not from his Monarchy, when all
               His Righteouſneſſe was vaniſh't, that remain'd
               And ſo a knowledge of this truth he gain'd,
               (A truth he could not know had hee ſtill ſtood)
               We can be longer Powerfull then Good.
               Nay let vs looke on Hell, and we ſhall ſee
               That there's a Prince of that obſcurity.
               It is a torment ſuch as Hell hath none,
               To want that order in confuſion:
               That is the beſt, we may conclude from hence,
               That is in Hell, and was in Innocence.
               But I doe wonder at the fault ſo long
               That I deferre the puniſhment: my ſong
               Muſt to the Leuite turne, or rather be
               No more a Song, but a ſad Elegy.
               He hauing caru'd his Loue, as you haue heard,
               And done that act, which Hell and Furies fear'd;
               
                  
Sends a choice piece to euery Tribe, to plead
               Their iniuries, and tell why ſhe is dead:
               
                  Beniamin ſhall haue one of them, leſt hee
               Might dare commit a crime, he durſt not ſee.
               A ſeuerall meſſenger to each Tribe is ſent:
               But he that vnto Princely Iudah went,
               Carying the head of the diſmembred coarſe,
               With ſuch a voice which ſorrow had made hoarſe,
               (Leaſt he ſhould raue too highly) thus beginnes,
               Is there an Heau'n? and can there be ſuch ſinnes!
               Stands the Earth ſtill? me thinkes I hardly ſtand,
               Feeling the Seas inconſtancy on Land.
               After this Act, why flowes the water more?
               Why does't not ſtaine, which alwaies clear'd before?
               It is not Ayre we draw now, 'tis a breath
               Sent to infect vs from the Land of Death:
               The Fire, whoſe office 'tis to warme and ſhine,
               Growes blacke and downewards, as it did repine
               To ſee the fact, and ſheds a kinde of teares,
               Quenching his heat, becauſe he cannot theirs.
               Can you behold theſe eyes without a teare?
               Can you with patience longer thinke they were,
               And are not the worlds wonder? yet I erre,
               It is Reuenge, and not a Teare fits her:
               Let women weepe for women, then you ſhall
               Shew you haue ſorrow'd heartily, if all
               Doe ſorrow which haue iniur'd her, and be
               Examples, as of Crimes ſo Miſery.
               
                  Gibeah 'twas (O 'twas not Gibeah)
               
               Credit me not, beleeue not what I ſay,
               I ſcarce dare truſt my ſelfe, and yet agen,
               
                  Gibeah 'twas, that did this Fact: and then
               He tells them all, what I before haue wept;
               Now Iudah ſtormes, and as a Riuer kept
               From its owne courſe by Weares, and Milles, if once
               It force a paſſage, hurryes or'e the ſtones,
               
                  
Sweepes all along with it, and ſo alone
               Without ſtormes makes an Inundation:
               Such was the peoples fury, they're ſo hot
               That they will puniſh what we credit not,
               And be as ſpeedy as ſeuere: but ſome
               Who loath'd the bloudy accents of the Drumme,
               Who thought no miſchiefes of that foulneſſe are,
               But that they gaine excuſe, compar'd with warre,
               And warre with brethren; theſe, I ſay, of age
               The chiefe amongſt them, doe oppoſe their rage,
               Exhort them to a temper: Stay, ſayes one,
               And be aduis'd before you be vndone.
               Whence is this fury? why d'yee make ſuch haſt
               To doe that act which you'l repent as faſt?
               Are any glad to fight? or can ought be
               Mother of warre, beſide Neceſſity?
               Be not miſtaken, brethren, take good heed,
               It is not Phyſicke frequently to bleed.
               He that for petty griefes inciſion makes
               Cannot be cur'd ſo often as he akes.
               Are then your ſiſters, daughters, wifes too chaſt?
               Or are you ſorry that as yet no waſt
               Deformes your richer grounds? or does it ſtirre
               An anger in you, that the ſouldier
               Mowes not your Fields? Poore men, doe you lament
               That ſtill you are as ſafe as innocent?
               We yet haue Cities proudly ſituate,
               We yet haue people: be it not in fate
               That your eſteeme of both ſhould be ſo cheape
               To wiſh thoſe carcaſſes and theſe an Heape.
               Me thinkes our Iordan hath an happier pace,
               And flowes with greater maieſty and grace
               In his owne naturall waue, then if the ſword
               Should higher colour to his ſtreames afford;
               Should paint and ſo deforme it: to mine eye
               A Riuer's better then a Prodigy.
               
                  
But I deſire, deere Countrymen, to know,
               VVhoſe is the blood that we muſt lauiſh ſo?
               Perhaps the Philiſtins ambition
               VVould to our Shilob bring their Aſcalon,
               
               And theſe you would encounter: or t'may be
               Aegypt ſtill enuying that you are free
               Intends a ſecond bondage: or perchance
               Your daily conquer'd Enemies aduance
               Their often flying enſignes, thoſe at hand
               Poſſeſſors and deſtroyers of the Land;
               VVhom God reſeruing for our future Pride,
               Left to our eyes as thornes, prickes to our ſide.
               No none of theſe, but all your ſwords intend
               I grieue to ſpeak't, the ruine of a friend:
               And all the ſonnes of Iſrael doe preſſe
               That Iſrael may haue a ſonne the leſſe.
               
                  Ioſeph I'ue read ſuffer'd his brothers hate,
               
                  (Joſeph of neere acquaintance vnto fate
               The mouth of Deſtiny,) they would kill him firſt,
               But after ſell him, to try which was worſt:
               And yet no reaſon for this ſpleene appeares,
               But that his glory was beyond his yeares:
               To hate the yonger ſtill is too much ſinne,
               And after Ioſeph to ſpoile Beniamin.
               
               Hath twelue no myſtery? doe ye aſcribe
               Meerely to Chance, that there is no odd Tribe.
               Truſt me my brethren, they doe iniure God,
               VVho ſay that he delights in what is odd:
               I thinke 'tis parity beſt pleaſeth heau'n;
               And what is moſt iuſt, loues what is moſt eu'n.
               Doe I excuſe them then to pleaſe the time,
               And onely make an error of a Crime?
               Am I ſinnes Aduocate? farre be't from mee
               To thinke ſo ill of Warre as Sodomy:
               For Sodomy I tearme it, Iuſtice calls
               That, fact; which neuer into action falls,
               
                  
If it hath paſt the licenſe of the will:
               And their intent reacht to that height of ill;
               But whoſe intent? O pardon me, there bee
               
                  Beniamites ſpotleſſe of that Infamy.
               Shall theſe be ioyn'd in puniſhment? a ſinne
               You'd warre againſt, O doe not then beginne
               To act a greater, as if you would ſee
               VVhether Iniuſtice aequall'd Luxury?
               This madneſſe was from Gibeah, 'tis true,
               Yet ſome doe more diſtaſt the crime, then you,
               Euen in that City: heare then my aduice,
               And God ſhall proſper what you enterprize.
               Exhort them to doe iuſtice, if that then
               They ſtill be partiall to theſe guilty men,
               Their guilt is greateſt, let them periſh all
               And equall their offences with their fall.
               Thicke acclamations breake off his diſcourſe,
               Theyle heare no more becauſe they like't: Remorſe
               Ceizeth each conſcience, they already hate
               The ciuill warre, which they ſo wiſht of late.
               Embaſſadors by generall voice are ſent:
               But Beniamin conceits that to repent
               VVere the worſe ſinne, and that who ere will doe
               A wicked act, he ought defend it too.
               But are not we true Beniamites in this,
               And aggrauate what ere we doe amiſſe
               By a new act? as if the ſecond deed
               Excus'd the former, if it did exceed.
               Did we not thus, an end were come to warre;
               Did we not thus, no more ſhould priuate iarre
               Moleſt our peace; Kings might put vp their ſwords,
               And euery quarrell might conclude in words:
               One conference would root out all debate,
               And they might then moſt loue, who now moſt hate,
               The moſt ſworne foes: for ſhew me, where is he
               VVould ſeeke Reuenge, without an Iniury?
               
                  
A wrong receiu'd, or thought one? then no need
               But to deny, to excuſe the deed,
               Why is Defence? O what doe they intend
               Who iuſtifie thoſe acts, which they ſhould mend!
               O Pride! O folly! O extreame diſeaſe!
               O Fact, which he condemnes who practiſes!
               Who in his ſoule confeſſeth he offends
               And yet doubles his guilt when he not ends.
               Great crimes find greater patrons: impudence
               Followes each fault, to make vs thinke that ſenſe
               Hath fled vs with our Vertue, and that men
               By ſuch an hardneſſe are turn'd ſtones agen.
               So wifes of Entertainment (who doe know
               More then one Husband) in the publicke, ſhew
               As vertuous as the beſt whilſt vndeſcry'd,
               Whilſt they haue this good left, that they will hide
               And veile ore their offences: but if once
               Either their husbands iuſt ſuſpicions,
               Or their ſecurity betray their fact,
               No more doe bluſh to anſwere, then to act,
               As if 'twere meritorious, and ſo, did
               Appeare no ſinne no longer then 'twas hid.
               Why ſhould the bad be bold? why ſhould there be
               Audaciouſneſſe ioyn'd to impiety?
               Whence is this daring? Sinne was child to Night,
               How dares he then approach and blaſt the light?
               How dares he ſtand th'examining, and try
               If men can find out his deformity.
               I haue the reaſon, we are flatterers all,
               And to our ſelues the moſt; if any fall
               Into groſſe errors, ſtill he thinkes hee's free,
               And Pride ſupplies the place of honeſty.
               He thinkes tis good to haue a vertuous name
               And cares not for the goodneſſe, but the fame.
               Which makes the Beniamites reply: we'admire
               (To ſay no more) at your ſo ſtrange deſire.
               
                  
And at the craft on't moſt, that you pretend
               Loue and aduice, when you ſubiection ſend:
               Are we ſo ſtupid, and ſo ſenſleſſe growne
               As to be thought not fit to rule our owne?
               
                  Beniamin was the yongeſt we confeſſe
               Of Iacobs ſonnes, and yet a ſonne, no leſſe
               Then Leuy, or proud Iudah: he that gaue
               Life to each Tribe, intended none a ſlaue,
               Nor ſhall you make vs. But youle ſay, that you
               Out of a generall loue to goodneſſe ſue
               For iuſtice 'gainſt her Enemies. Tis poore
               If what we would we cannot couer o're
               With ſpecious pretences: tis an ill
               Phyſitians part ſo to betray his pill,
               That children may perceiue it want of dreſſe,
               And chuſe diſeaſe before ſeene bitterneſſe;
               But let me tell you who ſo ere do's deale,
               In the affaires of a ſtrange common-weale,
               Is tyrannous or mad: he would be knowne
               Either anothers Lord, or's not his owne.
               Yet what is't your graue Maſters doe aduice
               Our ſleepy Councell of? whoſe duller Eyes
               See onely open vices: we haue heard
               The Leuite and his Concubine, we feard
               You'd haue vs puniſh him: then you relate
               That comming vnto Gibeah ſomething late,
               And willing to depart the earlier thence,
               He found his Chaſt one dead: O dire offence!
               She had the puniſhment ſhe deſeru'd, and iuſt
               It was, that who had liu'd ſhould dye by Luſt.
               And yet for feare Leuites in time to come
               Might want ſuch eaſie fauourites, and ſome
               Would leaue their courteous trade, if there be found
               No cure, no remedy for ſuch a wound:
               We are content to be ſeuere: but then
               We doe expect, you name thoſe guilty men.
               
                  
Out's the more hard and thankleſſe task I trow,
               For we will puniſh thoſe whom you but ſhow.
               Theſe mockes doe whet the Iſra'elites ſo farre,
               Nothing remaines now but a ciuill warre:
               Now all the Tribes haue vnto Miſpah ran,
               With ſuch conſent you'd thinke they were one man.
               If warre had euer reaſon, or if men
               Had ere authority to kill others, then
               Certainely theſe, in ſo diuine a cauſe,
               Twas not the peoples quarrell, but the Lawes.
               Here no ambition, no vntam'd deſire
               Of Principalitie, of growing higher,
               Put on theſe Armes, nor was it fault enough
               That Beniamin was rich, to raiſe theſe rough
               Spirits of Mars, nor is't a true ſurmiſe
               That priuate wrongs did cauſe theſe Enemies:
               Theſe fight the battel of the Lord, herein
               Iuſtice on one ſide fights, on th'other Sinne:
               So that in height of blood, heat of the warres,
               They rather Iudges are, then Souldiers.
               The Iſraelites if they now ſpare, are ſhent,
               The more they kill, the more they're innocent.
               Our Age makes vs againe theſe actions ſee
               An Age of warre, though not of victory.
               For 'tis not victory to winne the Field,
               Vnleſſe we make our Enemies to yeeld
               More to our Iuſtice, then our Force, and ſo
               As well inſtruct as ouercome our Foe.
               Call you that Conqueſt, or a Theft of State,
               When in a Stranger region of late,
               The Eagle built his neſt, hauing expell'd
               (Vpon a meere pretence that he rebell'd)
               The former Ayry, for no other cauſe,
               But that his bill was ſtrong, and ſharpe his clawes:
               To ſee the malice, and the power of hate,
               That made eu'n the Elector Reprobate.
               
                  
When Caeſar did not ſticke, nor bluſh to doe
               What they deteſted, who aduis'd him too,
               When that all lawes their ancient force might looſe,
               He made a Choyce of him that was to Chooſe.
               Now all occaſions can perſwade to ſight,
               When Power is misinterpreted for Right.
               There is a Luſt of killing men▪ ſo great,
               Riuers of bloud can ſcarce aſſwage the heat:
               Our liues are cheaper then the liues of beaſts,
               Then thoſe whoſe very being is for feaſts;
               Who haue no vſe but for the throat: hard plight!
               Anger not kills them, but our appetite,
               If we haue eaten once, we ſpare: and then
               If we are full are kind: but to kill men
               We haue a laſting appetite, ſhedding blood,
               Our famine is increas'd eu'n by our food:
               Such Eriſichthons are we, they that haue
               Vnlimited deſires, Death and the Graue
               But ſhadow this affection, and to it
               Compar'd, the Horſe-leach wants an Appetite:
               It may be weighing mans high faculties
               (Which make him claime a kinred with the skies)
               They ſeeme to doubt of his mortality
               And onely ſtriue to know if he can dye.
               Nor doe they care on what pretence (leſt ought
               Should make their crime the leſſe) no reaſon's ſought
               To mitigate their fault, and they are thus
               So farre from good, they ſcarce are cautelous.
               But 'tis a ſore will feſter, if you touch,
               Away my Muſe, ſometime a truth's too much
               For Honour, or for ſafety: he alone
               Proſpers who flatters. But if any one
               Shall aske a Probabilitie for this
               How ſuch a multitude, ſuch a ſwarme is
               Aſſembled of the Iſraelites (for then
               There met at once foure hundred thouſand men
               
                  
Againſt their brother Beniamin,) whilſt yet
               They had not diſpoſſeſt the Canaanite,
               (There was a mixture not a Conqueſt made)
               How durſt they then ſo fooliſhly inuade
               Their brethrens Countrey, when they left their owne
               Subiect to imminent deſtruction?
               Or when was this inuaſion made? To me
               The Number hath a more Facility
               For credit, then the Time; doe we not finde,
               That Iſrael wanting Iudges was aſſignde
               To bondage, as to Anarchy? they groane
               Vnder a forraine yoake, wanting their owne.
               Carries it any likelyhood; or can
               It ſinke into the fancy of a man,
               That when they were oppreſt, they ſhould oppreſſe?
               As full of folly as of ſauageneſſe:
               This were to perfect Eglons victory,
               And act what Iabin but deſir'd ſhould be.
               And yet it might be, Ioſhua being dead,
               Then was the time, the people lack'd an head:
               Who taking no care for poſterity,
               Twas the worſt act of Ioſhua to dye.
               
                  Moſes deputed him, and if that he
               Had left another Gouernor, it might be
               Our Leuite had beene chaſt: and Beniamin
               
               Beene noted for his vertue, not his ſinne.
               Then were theſe multitudes no miracle,
               And Canaan ſo oft beat by Iſrael,
               
               In likelihood would reſt quiet, and expect
               If theſe would doe what they could not effect.
               Beſides, their dwellings in the Valleyes be
               So that their ſeat teaches humilitie:
               And then to climbe the mountaines was ſuch paine
               As that the labour did exceed the gaine.
               And thus you ſee, that they may fight: but ere
               Their enemies Countries by them waſted were,
               
                  
They to the Oracle repaire, to know
               If victory ſhall grace them, or their Foe?
               Yet pardon me, I erre, they are ſo ſtrong
               As that they would imagine it a wrong
               Done to their valor, it we ſhould ſuppoſe,
               That they intreated conqueſt of their foes;
               No, being ſure of Victory, they aske
               Which of the Tribes ſhall vndertake the taske
               Of the firſt onſet, and the Tribes refus'd,
               Enuy at Iudahs choyce, as if abus'd,
               And iniur'd they eſteem'd themſelues, that they
               Should looſe the dangerous honor of the day.
               Such was their pride, ſuch thoughts their Nūbers brod
               Numbers, whoſe feare, might ſtrike the Enemy dead:
               Whoſe hands deſeru'd a fiercer Enemy,
               And matter of an harder victory.
               With theſe they thinke, they might to Memphis paſſe,
               And make the Aegyptians know, what bondage was.
               With theſe they thought with eaſe to force a Way
               (Though nature did oppoſe) to India.
               
               And in a ſawcy victory out-runne,
               The primitiue vpriſing of the Sunne.
               How large are our deſires? and yet how few
               Euents are anſwerable? So the dew
               Which earely on the top of mountaines ſtood
               (Meaning at leaſt to imitate a flood)
               When once the Sunne appeares, appeares no more,
               And leaues that parch'd, which was too moiſt before.
               That we are neuer wholly good! that ſtill
               Mixt with our Vertue, is ſome ſpice of ill!
               The Iſraelites are Iuſt, but they are Proud,
               As if a leſſer fault might be allowd
               For puniſhing the greater: yet I'de know
               Whilſt yet they might ſuffer an ouerthrow,
               Why they reioyce as if th'ad wonne! or why
               They haue a Pride ere they haue Certainty?
               
                  
Their numbers are incredible, 'tis true,
               Yet multitudes haue beene orecome by few:
               Their army is compleat, tis right, but then
               We know it is an army but of men,
               Of future carkaſſes, ſo quickly ſome
               They haue no time to thinke of death to come:
               To whom no ſtarre a certainty does giue,
               That they at leaſt to the next Field ſhould liue.
               Foure hundred thouſand carkaſſes; enough
               To giue the beaſts a ſurfet, and allow
               Fertility which Nature had deny'd
               Vnto thoſe Lands: So that their height of pride,
               Of hope, of glory, and of all their toyle
               Is to inrich the Land which they would ſpoile.
               So thought the Beniamites, who though they ſaw
               That Pow'r too was againſt them with the Law,
               Yet reſolutely they intend to die,
               And ſuch deſpaire giues them the victory.
               They are not Cowards, yet, though they are bad,
               They ſlay more numbers then wee'd thinke they had.
               Whence comes this Courage to the Deſperate?
               The bad me thinkes ſhould be effeminate,
               And as the Bees (the ſubiect or the King)
               Hauing abus'd it once, doe looſe their ſting:
               And to inforce a Stoick vnto laughter,
               Being once too fierce, they are alwaies ſluggiſh after
               Conuerted vnto Droanes, ſo it ſeemes fit
               (And not ſo much heauens Iuſtice, as its wit)
               That who hath loſt his Vertue once, ſhould ſtraight
               Looſe courage too, oppreſt with his owne waight.
               The Iſraelites though amaz'd at this defeat,
               Yet gather head, and to their campe retreat;
               There might you ſee Sorrow and Anger ioyn'd,
               Nor doe they grieue ſo much as they repin'd.
               Here fathers weepe their onely ſonnes, and there
               Brothers for as deare loſſes dropp a teare,
               
                  
Accompany'd with threatnings, they are mad
               Till they beſtow the ſorrow which they had.
               Once more to Shiloh they repaire, to heare
               If God at laſt will aide them, and for feare
               That it was pride did fruſtrate their firſt ſute,
               They're now as humble, as then reſolute:
               In ſtead of fighting they now weepe a day,
               Sighes they doe thinke and teares can make a way
               Where ſwords are vſeleſſe, they'l gaine victory
               No longer by their hand, but by their Eye.
               Great and iuſt God, ſayes one, we doe confeſſe
               That all this heauy anger is farre leſſe
               Then our deſeruings: ſhould'ſt thou fully waigh
               Our ſinnes enormity, tis not a day
               Loſt to the Foe, can expiate: did we feele
               What ere we ſaw in Aegypt, did the ſteele
               Peirce deeper in our bowells, ſhould the skyes
               Shed thoſe hot ſhowers in which Gomorrah fryes,
               We could not taxe the Iuſtice of our King,
               But after all, owe ſtill a ſuffering.
               Yet thou haſt ancient mercies, we'aue beene told
               Of all thy courteſies, which were of old
               Shew'd to our Fathers; O vouchſafe them ſtill,
               And make vs heires of thoſe: we haue done ill,
               Prodigiouſly ill, ther's no offence
               Which we are guiltleſſe of, each conſcience
               Accuſeth, and amazeth vs: yet now
               Our flinty hearts to a repentance bow:
               Yet now at laſt vouchſafe thy fauour to vs,
               And as thy rod hath ſcourg'd, let mercy wooe vs;
               We dare not looke for victory: O no,
               Giue vs at leaſtwiſe a more vertuous Foe.
               Thy wrath is iuſt great God, and tis our ſute
               Onely iuſt men thy wrath may execute.
               We beg not for our liues, they are thy loane,
               Which when thou wilt, receiue, yet as thine owne,
               
                  
Let not their ſwords bereaue vs of our breath,
               And we ſhall find a benefit in death.
               Yet what a glory can it be to thee
               That we are dead? and that the Heathen ſee
               Thy anger on thy Children? that thy wrath
               In ſtead of being felt, is told in Gath,
               
               And publiſht in fierce Aſcalon; ſpare vs then
               If not for vs, yet for thy ſelfe; and when
               Thou think'ſt of plaguing vs, thy ſelfe exempt,
               Since that our Ruine will breed thy contempt:
               Let then thy mercy aboue iuſtice ſhine;
               If we are bad, conſider we are thine.
               Thus grumbled they a pray'r: and he that ſees
               Councells vnhatchd, and what he will, decrees,
               (Yet euer iuſtly) does perceiue that they
               What ere they faine, doe murmure, and not pray.
               Which he decrees to puniſh: they would know
               Whether that once more they ſhall fight▪ or no?
               Once more he grants that they ſhall fight and thus
               They're not ſo crauing, as he Courteous,
               If they but aske him, he will not deny,
               Fight's their deſire, and then his anſwere's I.
               Had they but ask'd the victorie as well
               He would haue heard his troubled Iſrael:
               He that deliuer'd them from forraine armes,
               And taught their weake hands to repaire their harmes
               With admirable victory. He I ſay
               Would haue beſtow'd the honor of the day
               On them, had they deſir'd it; they haue knowne
               How he hath warr'd for them from heauen, &amp; ſhowne
               Such miracles in their defence, they fright
               Thoſe whom they ſaue, as when the wondring night
               Thought herſelfe baniſht from the world (the Sunne
               Standing vnmou'd, forgetting how to runne.)
               If they now looſe the day the fault is theirs,
               God does no mercy want, they want right prayers.
               
                  
But they ſuppoſe it too too fond to ſtand
               Begging of that which is in their owne hand.
               This they conceiue were to mocke God, to craue
               That to be giu'n which they already haue,
               A pow'r to vſe their armes: No, if once more
               They may haue field-roome, may but fight it o're
               Though Heau'n doe not fight for them; they ſuppoſe
               They cannot looſe, if Heau'n doe not oppoſe.
               They thinke no chance can poſſibly beſtow,
               The foile on them, the Lawrell on the foe.
               What though they loſt the praiſe of the firſt day,
               And fought as though they came to runne-away:
               Twas not for want of courage ſure, but either
               The foe had got aduantage of the weather,
               Or elſe the wind had rays'd the duſt ſo high
               That they ſuppos'd freſh enemies to be nigh,
               And fear'd to be enuiron'd round: what ere
               Occaſion'd their firſt ouerthrow, no feare,
               No chance, ſhall cauſe another; and the ſlaues
               That now triumph, ſhall find their trenches, graues.
               Is this their Crime alone, or doe not all
               Partake as of their fault, ſo of their fall?
               
                  Iſrael is not onely mad, there be
               Some vices which we giue poſterity,
               And this is one of them: O how vaine is man!
               O how his Reaſon too is but a ſpanne,
               And not his ſtature or his Age! we haue long
               Iniur'd the beaſts, and done them too much wrong,
               By calling them Irrationall; could they ſpeake
               Thus in rough language, they would fiercely breake
               Their mind vnto vs: O you onely wiſe
               To whom kind Nature hath imparted Eyes,
               Leauing all other blind; pardon if we
               Doe tell you where you haue forgot to ſee,
               Where we are clearer ſighted: can you ſhow
               Where euer beaſts did to that madneſſe grow,
               
                  
As to pronounce of that, which is to come,
               Of that which onely ſeemes in Chances doome?
               Yet thus you doe; and doing thus haue ſhowne,
               Reaſon's your title, our Poſſeſſion.
               The Iſraelites had to their coſt of late
               Found confidence to be vnfortunate;
               (Their confidence in Numbers) and yet ſtill
               (Though now contain'd in ſmaller roome) they will
               Foreſpeake their victory: why, becauſe they ſee
               That they are many yet; poore vanity!
               When they were more, they were o'recome, yet dare
               Conceiue a Conqueſt when they fewer are;
               Becauſe ſtill ſome are to be kill'd: as though
               Succeſſe to Multitudes did homage owe,
               And multitudes impair'd: as if the way
               To winne another were to looſe one day.
               But had we ſeene the City now! what ioy
               Raign'd in thoſe ſtreetes, ſufficient to deſtroy
               Thoſe whom it comforted (for pleaſure too
               Can find a way to death, and ſtrangely doe
               The worke of heauineſſe and griefe) I ſay
               Had we but ſeene the glory of that day:
               The whooping, dancing, and the generall noyſe
               To which the ſea and thunder are but toyes;
               We ſhould haue thought it (ſo the ſounds agree.)
               No noiſe of Triumph, but Captiuity.
               At laſt they doe repoſe themſelues, and one
               Of higheſt iudgement and diſcretion,
               Inſtructs them thus: My deareſt Countrymen,
               Who ere intends his priuate ends, does pen
               A ſpeech vnto the Eare, his ſtudy is
               Which words ſound well, and which are thought amiſſe:
               He tryes all wayes, he layes all colours on
               To cheat the Iudgement, ſooth the Paſſion,
               So that he hopes at laſt that it muſt hit
               Either the ſubiect, or the clothing it:
               
                  
But I whoſe end is Publike good, intend
               Nothing but that which caryes to that end:
               Pardon me then if I am harſh and round,
               If that I am not Plauſible, but ſound.
               We wonne a victory laſt day, ſo great
               We hardly dare beleeue we were not beat:
               Our conqueſt eaſier was then our beleife;
               And with great reaſon too: for tell, what chiefe,
               What petty captaine is ſo vaine, ſo mad
               As to aſcribe to his conduct the glad
               Euent of laſt dayes hazard? to my ſenſe
               The Conqueror was onely Prouidence,
               And we but inſtruments: then I'de aduice
               That as you haue beene happy, you'd be wiſe:
               That man does ſtill in greateſt glory ſtand,
               Whoſe braine is better thought of then his hand▪
               
               And ſo I wiſh that yours ſhould be: we know
               That what is gain'd by Fortune is loſt ſo,
               She hath no conſtant Fauorite, then now
               Whilſt yet our victory does meanes allow
               To purchaſe peace at our owne rate, and thriue
               By Couenant more then Battle: let vs driue
               All thought of warre farre from vs, tis in vaine
               To get that hardly, which we may obtaine
               By eaſier meanes, and he does more then raue
               Who hazards that which he may certaine haue.
               More was he ſpeaking, when a thouſand tongues
               Made his be ſilent, one would thinke their lungs
               To be vnequall to that noyſe, ſo fierce
               Their clamor is, ſuch ſounds the heauens doe peirce.
               So haue I oft heard in our Theater
               (When that a daintier paſſage wan the Eare)
               A thouſand tongues, a thouſand hands rebound,
               (As if the Plaudite were in the ſound,
               And moſt noiſe were moſt pleaſing:) they expreſſe
               Their liking ſo, as theſe their frowardneſſe.
               
                  
Who raue from noiſe to action, one ſtoopes downe,
               To reach a ſtone, another fiercer clowne
               Shakes a ſteel'd Tauelin at him, all the hands,
               Againſt which Iſrael but weakely ſtands,
               Ayme now at one; who dreadleſſe, vnimpair'd
               In courage, neither wiſht life, nor deſpair'd.
               At laſt a ſerious Counceller ſtood vp;
               Much had he taſted of the liberall Cup,
               And thankefully expreſt it in his face,
               To which a larger wound would be a grace
               By hiding his rich pimples: This braue man
               Raiſes himſelfe, and with what ſpeed he can
               Stutters thus to them; Ceaſe my noble boyes,
               Quiet your threatnings now, and ſtint your noyſe.
               Tis a iuſt anger you haue ſhowne, but yet
               The time in which you ſhew it is vnfit.
               Now ſhould we dance, my blouds, now ſhould we ſing,
               And make the wondring firmament to ring
               With ioyfull acclamations; now braue ſpirits
               To ſhew the moſt ioy, is to ſhew moſt merits.
               Sadneſſe is onely Capitall: in fine,
               Now ſhould we ſhed no bloud but of the vine.
               For you Sir whom we doubly guilty ſee,
               Of Treaſon firſt, and then Philoſophy
               If theſe doe pleaſe, thus we pronounce: to ſhew
               How little we doe feare you, or the Foe,
               Wee'l ſend you firſt vnto their campe, and then
               Wee'l fetch you by our conqueſt home agen.
               This is a mercy if well vnderſtood,
               You ſhall inioy the fortune you thinke good.
               Here his breath failes: when all the people cry
               He hath ſpoke nobly, none this day ſhall dye.
               And yet the Traitor ſhall not ſcape at laſt
               Whoſe execution is deferr'd, not paſt.
               Twas neither peace, nor warre now, either ſide
               Hauing ſufficiently their forces try'd,
               
                  
Take breath a while: O happy men, if ſtill
               This mind continue in them! If they kill
               Their appetite of killing! if this reſt
               Can at the laſt informe them what is beſt!
               To bury their ſlaine friends▪ both ſides agree
               Vnto a two dayes truce: Stupiditie
               Nor to be borne with! had they knowne the vſe
               At firſt of that which they now call a truce,
               This truce had beene vnneceſſary, then
               They might haue ſpar'd, whilſt now they bury men.
               And that they now may bury, they intreat
               Reſpite a while from warre: thus all their heat
               Is buried for the time: good heau'n to ſee
               Th' Omnipotency of Neceſſity,
               Whom all the neereſt ties of Neighbourhood,
               Religion, Language, nay of the ſame Bloud
               Could not containe from fight, but that they would
               (To ſee if it were theirs) ſhed their owne bloud,
               Theſe are intreated to a forme of peace,
               Their fury for a day or two can ceaſe,
               Commanded by Neceſſity: they feare
               Leſt th' Ayre by ſo much carcaſſe poyſoned were:
               Leſt to reuenge the bloud which they had ſhed,
               They now might feele the valour of the dead,
               Of ſtrong corruption: theſe thoughts hold their mind
               Theſe thoughts a while inforce them to be kind
               On both ſides (for they doe not iarre in all)
               Nature preuailes not, but a Funerall.
               Nor doth this long preuaile, for when they had
               Interr'd ſome carcaſſes, they yet are mad
               Till they haue made ſome more, till they haue done
               A ſecond fault, as not content with one.
               They ſee their Error, and commit it, thus
               Who are not eminently vertuous,
               Are eaſily entrapp'd in vices ſnares,
               And want the poore excuſe, that vnawares
               
                  
They were ingag'd, we greedily runne on
               Offending with Deliberation.
               And can you call this but Infirmity?
               Nick-name a Vice? O call it Prodigy.
               Call it—O what? What name can well expreſſe
               The miracle of humane guiltineſſe?
               Could he pretend an ignorance at leaſt
               And be in Nature as in Fact a beaſt,
               He were not worſe then they, then he might be
               Both from the Vſe and Fault of Reaſon free.
               But what new horror ceizeth me? what fire
               Raignes in my thoughts, and prompts me to riſe higher?
               Hence you low ſoules who groueling on the Earth
               Baſely deiect your ſelues below your birth,
               Sold to your ſenſes: I intend to tell
               What none can know but in whoſe breaſts doe dwell
               Coeleſtiall fires, and vnto whom 'tis giu'n
               To haue a neerer intercourſe with Heau'n.
               Yet pardon you pure ſoules, whom no one dares
               Eas'd of our fleſh, to trouble with our cares:
               Pardon I once more aske, if my weake pen
               Fitting it ſelfe to ordinary men,
               Attaine not to your height (to vs vnknowne)
               And giue you thoſe words which you ſhame to owne.
               The Lawgiuer, who ſaw as in a glaſſe
               All in the Word, what euer 'twas did paſſe
               In theſe neer enmities, as farre as Man
               Perfectly happy knowes a griefe, began
               To feele Compaſſion: Haue I then ſaid he
               Deliuer'd Iſrael for this miſery?
               And did I free them from th' Aegyptian
               Onely to find them graues in Canaan?
               
               I did foretell their Land ſhould ouerflow,
               But neuer thought to be expounded ſo;
               Neuer with bloud: I meant that they ſhould haue
               More bleſſings then the couetous can craue.
               
                  
The flowing Vdder, and the vntyr'd Bee,
               An happy Deluge of Fertility.
               O how would now proud Pharaoh reioyce!
               How would he haue a Ioy beyond a voyce,
               Beyond his tyranny, could he but know
               VVhat Iſrael does indure without a Foe!
               VVas it for this I did ſo oft repeat
               VVonders before him, wonders of ſo great
               Exuberance of powre, ſo highly done,
               That they contemne all admiration?
               How wert thou Nilus bloudy'd into Red,
               Thy waters as vnknowne as is thy Head?
               VVhen all thy finny progeny did find
               That to deſtroy now, which did breed their kind,
               VVhen by a nimble death they vnderſtand,
               The Riuer as diſcourteous as the Land?
               Can I forget that when I did beſtow
               A liberty as heretofore to flow
               Vnto thy now pale waters, there did paſſe
               An iſſue ſtranger then his Colour was
               From the too fertil riuer? Frogges are found
               VVith ſuch a multitude to hide the ground
               That ther's no graſſe appeares, no corne is ſeen.
               The ſpring does bluſh becauſe he lookes not greene.
               Their numbers and their noyſe equally harſh
               Make Aegypt not a Region but a Marſh.
               VVhat a ſmall portion of my acts were theſe?
               How ſcarcely to be counted paſſages
               In my large ſtory? Duſt is chang'd to Lice
               And now beginnes to creepe, which the moſt nice
               And curious eye before could neuer find
               To moue at all, vnleſſe 'twere by the wind:
               VVhich could not ſcatter thoſe thicke clouds of Flyes,
               That would not let them, no, not ſee the skyes.
               VVhen I but threaten all the cattle dye,
               And Aegypts Gods find a Mortality.
               
                  
But leſt the men ſhould thinke that they were free
               From the fault too, if the Calamity
                     •
                  :
               I taught their bodies with blacke goare to runne,
               And imitate their ſoules corruption.
               What was a Face is now a Pimple growne,
               And in each part is plentifully ſowne
               A ſtore of blaines, ſo vgly, that to me
               It was a kind of Iudgement but to ſee.
               And if this were but little, was't not I
               That call'd thoſe candy'd pellets from the sky,
               Which in a moment ouerwhelming all
               Did badly change their colour in their fall:
               And by the murthering euery one they found
               Within their reach came red vnto the ground?
               When to repaire the numbers they had ſlaine
               (Beaſts of all ſorts) the land is fill'd againe,
               But tis with Locuſts, ſuch a ſwarme they ſee
               Made for the ſhame of all their Husbandry,
               That they could wiſh, ſo they were rid of theſe
               The former Murrein, ere this new increaſe.
               But who can tell the following Prodigy?
               Laſt day the Earth was hid, but now the sky
               Chaos returnes, the Sunne hath loſt his rayes
               And Nights obſcurity is turn'd to Dayes.
               Who could a greater miracle afford?
               God made the Light, I Darkneſſe by a Word.
               Which had it laſted, had it ne're been ſpent,
               They would haue call'd it a kind puniſhment,
               They had not ſeen then their firſt borne to dy,
               To challenge death by their Natiuity:
               All 
                     〈…〉
                  , but why? was it to ſee
               
                  
                     〈…〉
                   ſuffer fuller miſery?
               To gaine the Country which they could not hold,
               From which their owne armes ignorantly bold
               Expell their owne ſelues: O let no man tell
               That Iſrael did baniſh Iſrael.
               
               
                  
My prayers forbid, nor let it ere be ſaid
               That Moſes was vnkind ſince he was dead,
               That in the graue I left my goodneſſe too;
               And could not pity when not feele a woe.
               Hauing ſaid this, with all the ſpeed he may
               He ſeekes out holy Abraham, who that day,
               By his deere Iſaac ſeconded, did ſing
               The ancient mercies of their heauenly King.
               One tells how hauing now worne out a life
               And ſo being fitter for his Graue then VVife,
               Nay then when ſhe had liu'd vnto thoſe yeares,
               To be accounted with the Grandmothers,
               When Sara now was ſo vnweildy growne,
               Her legges could ſcarcely beare her ſelfe alone,
               She beares another burthen, and does ſwell
               Not with a child, but with a Miracle.
               This ſaid, he ſtops; and then againe goes on
               No more with ſtory, but Deuotion.
               O prayſe the Lord my ſoule, let me not find
               My body was more fruitfull then my mind.
               O let that teeme with thankefulneſſe, and be
               Made ſweetly pregnant by my memory.
               Father, ſayes Iſaac, I haue often heard
               That we doe tell with Ioy what we haue Feard,
               And what in ſuffring terrifies our ſenſe,
               Does in relating pleaſe: what violence
               Of bliſſe poſſeſſeth me, when I compare
               My dangers paſt with ioyes that preſent are!
               Methinkes I yet carry that fatall wood
               (A burden which I hardly vnderſtood
               Should carry me) methinkes I ſtill enquire
               VVhere is the ſacrifice, and where the fire?
               How little did I thinke, or feare till then
               That God commanded ſacrifice of men!
               How little could I gueſſe in any part
               That God in ſuch ſort did deſire the Heart?
               
                  
Yet pardon Father, if you now muſt know,
               Your ſilence ſeem'd more cruell then your blow:
               Could I oppoſe my mind againſt your will,
               Or wiſh him ſpar'd, whom you decreed to kill?
               Wherefore was all this circumſtance? what need
               But firſt to tell, and then to act the deed?
               I neuer knew what diſobedience meant,
               And your diſtruſt was my worſt puniſhment.
               I muſt confeſſe I was amaz'd, my bloud
               Congeal'd within me, and my faint haires ſtood
               Yet not for feare of death (Death was my profit)
               But for the manner and the Author of it.
               Was this the heau'nly promiſe? and muſt I
               So ſtrangely borne, ſomewhat more ſtrangely dye?
               What ſhould I ſay now? or what ſhall I doe?
               That fruſtrate by my death Gods promiſe too.
               Should I inuoke Heau'ns ayde? alas, from thence
               Came the iniunction for this violence:
               Should I implore my fathers helpe? why, he
               Would ſooner hearken vnto heau'n then me.
               And ſo he did: for when the trembling ſword
               As if he knew the temper of his Lord
               Threatned a death, moſt fortunately then
               He that did arme you did diſarme agen;
               Shewing your will was all he did require,
               Commanding you to that you moſt deſire,
               To be againe a Father: O the power
               And mercy of our God! who in an houre,
               Who in a minute, can make all things well,
               Can bring and then deliuer out of Hell.
               Theſe were their Accents, when that Moſes ſayes,
               It is an holy buſineſſe to praiſe,
               To magnifie our Lord, ſo to goe on
               In the intent of our Creation.
               To this all times, all reaſons doe obey,
               And we may praiſe as often as we pray.
               
                  
But now let's change theſe tones, let vs be mute
               In all diſcourſes now, but in a ſuite;
               Let vs at once conioyne our prayers, and ſee
               If our one God will hearken vnto three.
               Your iſſue, and my charge, whom I haue led
               Thorow thoſe paths that neuer man did tred,
               (As if they fear'd a ſcarcity of foes)
               Doe their owne ſelues againſt themſelues oppoſe;
               And their deſtruction (vnleſſe we repaire
               Sooner to ayde them) will preuent our pray'r.
               It was a place aboue the Ayre, the Sky,
               Whither Man cannot reach, not with his Eye,
               Nay if th' exactneſſe of the height be ſought,
               Whither Man cannot reach, not with his thought.
               Beyond the place where haile, and raine doe grow,
               Aboue the chill-white treaſures of the ſnow;
               To which compar'd the ſtarry heau'n is fell
               Vnto a neerer neighbourhood with Hell.
               And when I ſhall of Gods abode intreat
               It does become his proſpect, not his ſeat.
               To which compar'd, the Chryſtall heau'n does meet
               With Earth, to be a ſtoole vnto his feet.
               This was the Place (yet pardon 'twas not ſo,
               Places are things which onely bodies know,
               Our bounds of Ayre, from which the heau'ns are free
               As from Corruption and Mortality)
               But heere it was His ſacred throne did ſtand,
               Who with a word created Sea and Land:
               Who with a word was Maker of his Throne,
               Who till he made it neuer wanted one.
               Bring me the richeſt goldſmiths treaſuries
               (Thoſe baites that doe allure our hearts and eies)
               The dusky Sapphire, the Pearle richly white,
               The ſparkling Diamond, yellow Chryſolite,
               Or if there be a gemme Nature hath fram'd,
               Of ſo high price that Art hath neuer nam'd.
               
                  
Ranſacke the Inga's tombes, where there doth lye
               With their corrupted duſt their treaſury:
               (Who to that pretty bounty doe attaine
               That they beſtow their gold on earth againe.)
               Search me their graues, or if you fearfull be
               Of treaſure guarded by Mortality,
               Rob all the mines fenc't with ſo many barres,
               (Where Nature in the Earth hath fancy'd ſtarres,
               Whoſe luſter leaſt our weakneſſe cannot beare
               Her kinder wiſedome made her ſtore vp there)
               Bring theſe vnto the view, to an exact
               Figure, which Phidias durſt call his Act:
               Yet to this throne compar'd, it will appeare
               So farre from ſhining, it will ſcarce looke cleare.
               Here does the Ancient of dayes diſcloſe
               The glory of his Maieſty to thoſe
               To whom he daynes his preſence, who enioy
               At full, what would a weaker eye deſtroy:
               Whoſe bliſſe ſhall neuer haue a period,
               Who therefore liue becauſe they ſee their God.
               How could I euer linger, euer dwell
               In this ſo bleſt Relation! O how well
               Should I eſteeme my ſelfe entranc'd, if I
               By ſtaying here ſhould loſe my Hiſtory!
               Here thouſand thouſands wait vpon his call
               Of humane ſeruants, and Angelicall,
               And ſuch a multitude inueſt his throne
               (Millions of Spirits waiting vpon One,)
               That it may be we ſhould not ſay amiſſe,
               Their Number ſtranger then their Nature is:
               Here ſound the Halleluiah's, here the Quire
               Of Heau'n is high, and full as their deſire:
               No voice is here vntun'd, they doe not find
               Aiarre, more in the ſound, then in the mind.
               Their power of ſinging growes on with their ſong,
               And they can longer ſing, becauſe thus long;
               
                  
Thus here themſelues they fully ſtrengthned fee,
               To a melodious eternitie.
               Here Abraham preſents himſelfe, and ſayes
               O thou aboue the iniury of Dayes;
               Who making Times art ſubiect vnto none,
               Who giu'ſt all knowledge, and art neuer knowne;
               Who in my dayes of fleſh didſt gladly lend
               An eare vnto my ſute, and wouldſt not bend
               Thy plagues againſt thine enemies, vntill
               I knew th'intent, and thou hadſt askt my will,
               The will of me poore mortall, nay farre worſe
               Of me a ſinner then, the ancient curſe
               Stucke deepely in me, that I might haue feard
               My faults, and not my pray'r ſhould haue beene heard:
               Could I ſpeake then, and am I ſilent now?
               Did Sodome moue, and cannot Iſrael bow?
               O pardon me if I bewaile their ſtate,
               If I their Father proue their Aduocate.
               Didſt not thou promiſe when I had giu'n ore
               All hope of Father, when I wiſht no more
               Then a contented Graue, that then from me,
               Should come ſo numerous a progeny:
               That all the cleerer army of the sky,
               And the thicke ſands which ſtill vnnumbred lye
               Should come within account before my ſeed,
               Which not my Sara, but thy truth ſhould breed?
               How oft I thought that promiſe did include
               Their laſting too as well as multitude;
               That their continuance ſhould be as ſure,
               As long as either ſands or ſtarres indure.
               If they haue ſinn'd, thou know'ſt they may repent
               And be the better by a puniſhment,
               Neuer by Ruine: O then vſe thy rod
               Thinke that they are thy People, thou their God.
               And if they are ſo, O then let not be
               Any more ſtrife, but who ſhall moſt ſerue thee,
               
                  
If they are ſo, let Abraham once more
               Receiue thoſe children which thou gau'ſt before.
               Now they haue left their heau'nly ecchoing,
               Now all the Quire does wonder and not ſing,
               When from th'eternall Maieſty are heard
               Speeches, which all but the dread Speaker fear'd.
               Am I as Man that I ſhould change? or like
               The ſonne of man to threaten and not ſtrike?
               If I pronounce my wrath againſt a Land
               Shall that continue, and my word not ſtand?
               If I doe whet a ſword, ſhall it be blunt,
               And haue no direr ſharpeneſſe then t'was wont?
               
                  Beniamins crime h'as ſuch an horror in't,
               (Who haue confirm'd their faces like a flint
               Againſt all dye of modeſty) that till
               Their bloud (which now their too hot veines doe fill)
               Flow in their fields, till that their Numbers be
               Of as ſmall note as is their Chaſtity,
               It ſhall not be remitted: yet to ſhow
               That I can pay that which I doe not owe,
               A remnant ſhall eſcape: but for the reſt,
               (Thoſe other Tribes which boaſt they are the beſt,)
               And yet to verifie their goodneſſe, leſſe
               Speake, as if they were iniur'd by ſucceſſe,
               So making the fault mine, who therefore haue
               Beene lib'rall benefactors to the graue
               By their thicke deaths) vntill that I doe ſee
               A confirm'd truth of their humility,
               They ſhall not ſee a victory: Ile make
               
                  Beniamin puniſh theſe, and after take
               Vengeance on the Reuengers, till they ſee
               My mercy hath not ſpent mine Aequity.
               This I pronounce, this is my conſtant will.
               Now all the holy company doe fill
               The heau'ns with ſhouts of prayſe, and loudly cry
               All Honor, Glory, Power to the moſt High.
               
                  
But now the Iſraelites once more haue brought
               Their troopes into the field, once more haue fought,
               And whether 'twas the fault of them that led,
               Or of the ſouldier, once more they haue fled:
               And now becauſe their battle was not long
               I will not be more tedious in my Song.
            
            
               Canto III.
               
                  The Argument.
                  The Leuites viſion, Phineah's Prayer,
                  The Iſraelites late caus'd deſpaire
                  Now turn'd to courage, when by them
                  A new inuenned ſtratagem
                  Drawes the enemy from the walls,
                  
                     Ʋntill within their net he falls,
                  With the full righting of the wrong
                  Does both conclude, and crowne my Song.
               
               VVHen will Vice faile? whē ſhall we ſee th' euēt
               Of wicked acts as bad as the Intent?
               As yet the worſt are proſperous, and worſe,
               The good as yet haue neuer miſs'd their curſe:
               Reuiew the Leuites wife, and you ſhall ſee
               When ſhe had forfeited her honeſty,
               Her father entertain'd her; but once more
               When ſhe was come to what ſhe left before,
               Her Lord and Vertue, when that all her ſtrife
               Shall be to gaine the name of a good wife,
               
                  Gibeah will not harbour her; O poore!
               
                  Gibeah were guiltleſſe had it done no more:
               But Gibeah will murder her; and now
               Returne we to the Campe, and there ſee how
               
                  
They proue this fatall truth, twice had they try'd
               The valour of their enemies, and twice dy'd
               The fields with their beſt bloud, ſo hardly croſt
               That they haue fought no oftner then th'aue loſt:
               And yet their cauſe was beſt: neither were they
               The onely people which haue loſt the day
               Which they deſeru'd to winne: ſearch the records
               Of euery Age, and euery Age affords
               Examples of like ſtrangeneſſe: who can tell
               What the Aſſyrian did to Iſrael?
               
               How in deſpite of all their lofty towers,
               (Which hop'd a ſtanding to the laſt of houres)
               He made one houre their laſt: vnlucky howre,
               Where vice ſhew'd what 't could do when it had power.
               The ſword did ſport with lifes, nor were they ſuch
               VVhoſe loſſe or preſeruation did not much
               Pertaine vnto the ſtate: but the Kings ſonnes
               In the ſame time, the ſame Pauilions,
               By the ſame tyrant are inforc'd to dye,
               And which exceeds all, in their fathers eye.
               Poore Zedekiahs kingdome firſt is gone
               And then his heyres, O harſh inverſion!
               If he had loſt them firſt, it might be thought
               His kingdomes loſſe would not haue mou'd him ought,
               He would haue made the beſt of th'other croſſe
               Eſteeming it an eaſing, not a loſſe.
               As he might now to be depriu'd of ſight
               VVhen he ſhould couet the kind ſcreene of Night
               Betweene his woes and him: if in his mind
               He ſaw, it was a bleſſing to be blind:
               That then he ſhould be forc't to ſee no more
               VVhen he could not ſee what he ſaw before.
               This Iſrael ſuffer'd, and his Aſhur did,
               And yet I dare affirme it was not hid
               Not from th' Aſſyrian eu'n in his owne doome
               That they were better who were ouercome.
               
                  
Or if the goodneſſe to his ſide he drawes,
               Tis that his ſword was better, not his cauſe.
               I could goe on in preſidents as true,
               Actions betweene the Heathen and the Iew,
               Betweene the Turke and Chriſtian: but what need
               To ſhew there is no birth without a ſeed?
               No ſpeech without a tongue? or if there be
               More truths of ſuch knowne perſpicuity.
               How doe they doate then, who would tye the Lord
               To be ſo ayding to his childrens ſword,
               As that he ne're ſhould vſe his owne, nor doe
               Any one act, but what they wiſh him too?
               Are they ſo good? or is his loue ſo fond,
               As of a courteſie to make a bond?
               Shall they indent with him? and ſay thus farre
               Thou mayſt correct, but if thy iudgements are
               Of longer date, they are vniuſt? for ſhame
               (All ye that glory in a purer Name,)
               Hence thoſe blaſpehemous thoughts, far hence remoue,
               Leſt they deſerue the plagues they would reproue.
               Is it iniuſtice to ſuppreſſe our pride,
               To bring vnto our eyes what we would hide,
               Eu'n from our ſelues, our cloſe deformities?
               Or, may not God, to ſhew how he does prize
               His ſeruants labours, make them thus appeare,
               As does the Sunne after a cloud, more cleare?
               His iudgement certainly wee'l ſay's too quicke,
               VVho'l proue one bad becauſe he ſees him ſicke;
               Theſe iudgements are diſcaſes, and beſtowd
               At pleaſure, and not where they moſt are owd:
               Yet due they are where euer they are found,
               Since there are none ſo Catholikely ſound,
               But in a word, but in a thought haue ſtrayd,
               Perhaps in thoſe Afflictions, when th'aue wayd
               Their deeds and ſuffrings which they thinke to be
               Of farre more rigor then Aequality.
               
                  
Then courage noble Countrymen, nor feare
               Though you ſhould want ſucceſſe a while to 
                     •
                  eare
               Your names vp to your anceſtors, (who did
               Thoſe acts which now were better to be hid:
               Leſt that they ſhould vpbraid vs) doe not feare
               That Spaine is neerer the Almighties Eare
               Then our deuotions: he that could beſtow
               A victory after a ſecond blow
               Vpon the doubting Iſraelites, can ſtill
               Create our better hopes eu'n out of ill.
               Or if he doe not, if he haue decreed
               That our iuſt plague ſhall be their vniuſt deed:
               That Iſrael ſhall be once more ouercome,
               And Dauid flie away from Abſalom:
               
               Yet let this glad vs in our chiefeſt woe,
               Man may be good and yet vnhappy too.
               Now are they truely humbled, now although
               No curious eye could gueſſe their ouerthrow
               When he had ſeene their numbers, yet at length
               They will rely vpon another ſtrength,
               Or if to numbers they will truſt agen,
               'Tis to Gods numerous mercies, not their men.
               He can deliuer (they haue ſeene) by few,
               And they doe thinke it poſſible and true
               That he can helpe by many too, they find
               Without him all their actions full of wind,
               Of emptineſſe, and with him they not doubt
               To be as well victorious as deuout.
               Now Pride hath left them, now they goodneſſe yeeld,
               Now haue they loſt their vices with the field.
               Such holy leſſons doe misfortunes teach,
               Which make our once bad thoughts brauely to reach
               At Heau'n and glory: if you marke it well
               Whilſt yet it was a num'rous Iſrael
               
               It was a proud one too, but when that now
               God lookes vpon them with an angry brow,
               
                  
When all their troopes halfe weary and halfe ſicke,
               Are growne to eaſier Arithmeticke,
               Th'are truly penitent▪ hence we may ſee
               The pow'r, the good pow'r of Aduerſitie,
               W'are bad if we are happy, if it pleaſe
               Heau'n to indow vs with a little eaſe,
               If riches doe increaſe, vntill our ſtore
               Meet our deſires, till we can wiſh no more,
               If that our garners ſwell (vntill they feare
               Ruine from that with which they furniſht were)
               We but abuſe theſe benefits: our Peace
               Brings forth but factions, if that ſtrangers ceaſe
               To giue vs the affront; our ſelues will be
               Both the defendant, and the Enemy.
               Our riches are our ſnares, which being giu'n
               To man, to make a purchaſe of the heau'n,
               We buy our ruine with them, the abuſe
               Is double, in the getting, and the vſe,
               So that our ſummes vnto ſuch heapes are growne
               When Auarice ſucceeds Oppreſſion.
               In briefe, our garners ſo well ſtuff'd, ſo cramm'd,
               Detaine our Corne, as if that it were damn'd
               To euerlaſting priſon, none appeares,
               And thus we giue dearth to the fruitfull yeares:
               Being to ſuch a proud rebellion growne,
               Famine is not heau'ns iudgement but our owne.
               So wretched are we, ſo we skilfull grow
               In crimes, the which the heathen doe not know.
               We wrong God for his bleſſings, as if thus
               We then were thankfull, if iniurious.
               Why ſhould not mercy winne vs? why ſhould we
               Be worſe by that, whence we ſhould betterd be?
               Bleſſings were ne're intended for our harme,
               Why doe we hearken then to the fond charme
               Of ſuch temptations? O how baſe is man!
               How fooliſh Irreligion has wanne
               
                  
Vpon his reaſon too! Doe we not call
               Whom onely ſtripes can maſter, beſtiall?
               O what is man then! who ne're heares his Lord,
               Till that the famine call him, or the ſword.
               Who (as he meant to tyre his patient God)
               Yeelds not vnto his fauours, but his rod.
               And can we yet intreat him to be kind,
               To alter his, when wee'l not change our mind?
               If we are heard, we will offend agen,
               And all our pray'r does but intreat a Sinne.
               Thus pray'd the Iſraelites, but if th'are heard
               If he that made them ſcorn'd, will make them feard:
               It is in chance, no, tis as ſure as fate,
               Hauing forgot their miſery of late
               They will rebell againe: like thoſe good hearts
               Who though they know the paines, the many ſmarts
               Which fruitfulneſſe is fruitfull with, ſtill giue
               Death to themſelues, to make their iſſue liue:
               And if they ſcape this death, they try againe,
               And boldly venture for a ſecond paine,
               As if twere pleaſure, or as if they meant
               Rather to dye, then to be continent.
               Thus haue we ſeene a barren, ſandy ſoyle
               (Made onely for the husbandmans ſad toyle
               And not his profit) when the full heau'n powres
               His moiſture downe, eaſing himſelfe by ſhowres:
               Drown'd with the drops, to make vs vnderſtand
               A figure of the Sea vpon the Land,
               VVhen once thoſe drops are ſpent, when that the sky
               Smiles with his new reſtor'd ferenitie,
               Swifter then thought, before that we can ſay
               This was the place; the water's gone away,
               Theres a low Ebbe, againe we ſee the Land
               Changing its moiſture for its ancient ſand.
               Yet he that knowes this their infirmity,
               At laſt will pitty it, and from on high,
               
                  
(When now their thoughts of warre they will adiourne
               When there's no talke now, but of their returne)
               Hee'l hinder it by victory: with that
               (About the time that pitchy night had gat
               The conqueſt of the day, of which being proud
               He wrapt himſelfe within his thickeſt cloud,
               Thinking perhaps his conqueſt to be voyd,
               If any ſaw the triumphs he inioyd)
               Vnto our Leuite he a viſion ſends
               Clad in her deareſt ſhape, in whom he ends
               All thoughts of Fancy: Whom when he had ſeene
               (And quickly he had ſpy'd her) Faireſt Queene
               Of heau'n, he ſayes, what is there here on earth
               That could perſwade thee to a ſecond birth,
               Thus to appeare agen? needs muſt thou know
               (For ignorance belongs to vs below
               Excluded out of heau'n) that our ſad ſtare
               Is for its goodnes prou'd vnfortunate;
               That Beniamin is conqueror, and that we
               Could not reuenge, but onely follow thee:
               Nor was't one loſſe, one petty ouerthrow
               Hath daunted vs, but (as if fate would ſhow
               All her choyce malice on vs) we haue try'd
               How many wayes 'twas poſſible t'aue dy'd.
               Beleeue it, heauenly one, no cowardiſe
               (Which heretofore being baſe, is now tearmd wiſe)
               Loſt vs the day, no prouidence, no zeale
               Nor that (which can the maymes of actions heale)
               Councell, and graue aduice was wanting to vs:
               Only the heau'ns, which we had thought would wooe vs
               To proſecute thy vengeance, and from whence
               We look'd for daies, like a good conſcience
               Shining and cleere, with cruelty vnheard
               Giue vs an ouerthrow for a reward;
               That we can onely (ſuch our wretched fate)
               Deplore the loſſe, which we ſhould vindicate.
               
                  
Is this your Iuſtice heau'ns? nay I would know
               If it at leaſt be wiſedome, thus to ſhew.
               Your wrath vpon you followers? if there be
               Such a deſire in you to make vs ſee
               What powre you haue, wherefore d'ye not vſe
               That powre on thoſe, who impiouſly abuſe
               Vs and your ſelues? O there are heathen ſtill,
               People that neither feare, nor know your will,
               If you will ruine theſe, or any wiſe
               But leſſen, y'aue the fewer Enemies:
               On theſe be powerfull; but if you doubt
               Whether ſuch nations may be ſingled out,
               That ſinne hath fled the world, then here begin,
               For all the Heathen are in Beniamin.
               
               Are we the onely faulty? or am I
               Pickt out for eminent Iniquity?
               All lights on me, twas I that rays'd theſe warres,
               Twas I that this thicke people like to ſtarres
               Haue leſſend into Number; I alone
               Merit both peoples curſes ioynd in one.
               
                  Beniamin does deteſt me, and I gueſſe
               
                  Iſraels hatred is more cloſe, not leſſe.
               What ſhall I doe, what courſe is to be tryde
               When ſafe I cannot goe, nor ſafe abide?
               No more ſayes ſhe, nor fooliſhly conclude
               To giue complaints in ſtead of gratitude.
               Wee'are heard my deare, and he at whoſe command
               The earth will learne to moue, the heau'n to ſtand
               Faſt as the Center, who brings downe to hell,
               And out of deeper mercies (which to tell
               Would poſe them that they bleſſe) brings backe againe,
               Making the pleaſure greater by the paine,)
               Hath crown'd our wiſhes. O ioyfully good!
               Not to be had on earth, nor vnderſtood:
               Heau'ns high ſuperlatiue, for vnto me
               Reuenge is better then Aeternity.
               
                  
Reuenge vpon Gods enemies: know my deare
               (And know that thou muſt doe what thou ſhalt heare)
               It is the will of heau'n, when once the skye
               Is proud of the next mornings liuery,
               All Iſrael ſhould meet, where what ſhall fall
               Iuſt with wiſhes, or exceed them all,
               I muſt not now diſcouer, yet thus much
               I care deliuer (my affection's ſuch)
               A truth, that is confeſt as ſoone as heard,
               That he who knew to plague, knowes to reward.
               Our Leuite wakes, but ſtretching out an arme
               He feeles no body, no, nor no place warme
               To proue ſhe had been there, he thinkes 'tmay be
               No viſion, but a birth of Phantaſie:
               An iſſue of a troubled braine that fram'd
               Formes to it ſelfe which Nature hath not nam'd.
               Haue I not ſlaine enough he ſayes, but ſtill
               Is it my office and my curſe to kill?
               Twas but a dreame inioyn'd me to be bad,
               A dreame, a vapour, and am I ſo mad
               For nothing to bee monſtrous, and commit
               A crime, that men ſhall feare to dreame of it!
               But can I diſobey what it hath pleas'd
               Heau'n to command me? O how I am ceaz'd
               VVith ſtrange extreames! nor readily can tell
               Whether this Reuelation ſhould dwell
               Clos'd in my breſt? or whether I goe on
               As counting it a Reuelation?
               There may be guilty ſilence, if we feare
               In the affaire of heauen to wound an eare
               With threatning Rheroricke; this will not bee
               Excus'd by a pretence of modeſty:
               Rather twill proue the iudgement of iuſt heau'n,
               VVe ſhall receiue the doome we ſhould haue giu'n.
               Now all the people know what he hath heard,
               Now they haue all their forwardneſſe declar'd
               
                  
In ſacrifice, when Phineas appeares,
               One that had liued vnto ſo many yeares;
               He knew not how to count them, and that knew
               The Deſert wonders, and could proue them true
               By his owne ſight, that could the more ingage
               Men to beleeue, not by his tongue, but age.
               Nay I haue heard ſome hauing duely way'd
               How long in that high office he had ſtayd,
               Conceiue they may affirme without a checke,
               Him of the order of Melchiſedec;
               
               And proue (as onely iudging what they ſee)
               Their Prieſthoods, by their Prieſts eternity.
               Who hauing enter'd, all the people bow'd:
               (For 'twas not yet as perfect zeale allow'd
               To be irreuerent to their Prieſt, that name
               Which now is prou'd a title but of ſhame,
               Then was the badge of glory) he indeares
               Himſelfe, more by his office, then his yeares
               To thoſe, who thinke theſe two can ne're agree,
               To ſcorne the Prieſt, and ſerue the Deitie.
               Before the Altar his weake knees he bends,
               Which age before, but now deuotion ſends
               Vnto the ground, where with a voyce ſo low,
               That he could onely heare it, who could know
               What it would haue before it ſpake, he thus
               Whiſper'd a prayer;
               
                  King of Heauen, of Earth, of Seas,
                  And of men exceeding theſe:
                  Thou, that when thy people ranne
                  From the proud Egyptian,
                  Ledſt them through a liquid path
                  Safe, and ſcarce wet, when thy wrath
                  Wonderfully made them know,
                  Twas a Sea vnto the foe.
                  Thou that when the heat, the ſand
                  Of a barren thirſty land,
                  
                     
Made our tongues be ſo confin'd
                  To our roofes, they ſcarce repin'd,
                  But in ſecret, ſo that we
                  Onely fear'd a blaſphemy.
                  Thou then by a powerfull knocke
                  Mad'ſt a Sea within a Rocke,
                  And gau'ſt Iſrael to know
                  For them drought ſhould ouerflow:
                  Thou art ſtill the ſame, and we
                  Stand in the ſame need of thee.
                  Pardon then if we preſume
                  To an hope, and ſo aſſume
                  Courage to vs, when we ioyne
                  Our wants to that powre of thine.
                  Yes our wants, for we can find
                  None of merit, w'aue declin'd
                  Eu'ry good way, and haue ſtill
                  Beene ambitious of ill,
                  So that when we are exact,
                  And haue all our good deeds rackt
                  To the higheſt rate, ther's none
                  Dares appeare before thy throne:
                  Onely this deſert we ſee,
                  Continuance of aduerſity.
                  Nay ſuch monſters haue we bin,
                  Such proficients in each ſinne,
                  That we durſt not looke on heau'n,
                  Nor intreat to be forgiu'n.
                  Hadſt not thou vouchſaf'd to doe
                  What our wiſhes reacht not too:
                  Hadſt not thou vouchſaf'd to be
                  Tutor to our Infancy:
                  And beſtow'd when we were mute
                  Both our prayer and our ſute.
                  O the Courteous
               
               
                  Reſpect heau'ns beares vs! Scarcely had hee done,
                  Scarce finiſht his impos'd deuotion,
                  
                     
VVhen on the ſudden, ere you could haue ſaid
                  The Prieſt had ſacrific'd, or he had pray'd,
                  Through all the Campe a light was ſpread, to this
                  Compar'd, the Sunne but a darke body is:
                  And in reſpect of ſo diuine a light
                  Our day is honor'd, if he be tearmd night,
                  Nor this alone, but that they there might ſee
                  And feare their God in his full Maieſty,
                  Such voyces and ſuch thunders fright the Ayre,
                  That they ſuppoſe they want another prayer
                  To be aſſur'd from them; ſo they declar'd
                  They were afraid to heare, that they were heard.
                  Downe on the pauement euery knee is fixt,
                  Some groueling on their faces, when betwixt
                  Aſtoniſhment and hope, whilſt yet they doubt
                  VVhat all this preface meanes, and whilſt the rout
                  Fear'd iudgments which they merited, they heare
                  A voyce, for which they wiſh a larger care,
                  It was ſo ſweetly mercifull: Once more
                  
                  Goe vp (it ſayes) and though that heretofore
                  Y'aue had the worſt. yet thus my ſentence ſtands
                  Ile now deliuer them into your hands.
                  Haue you beheld how ſome condemn'd to dy,
                  VVhen they were fitted for Aeternity,
                  VVhen life they did deſpiſe, and all below,
                  Receiu'd a pardon, when they fear'd the blow
                  That ſhould vnman them, haue you ſeene them then
                  Almoſt forgetting that they were but men;
                  How to expreſſe their mind they want a word,
                  Ioy hauing done the office of the ſword,
                  And made them ſpeechleſſe? then you may in part
                  Conceiue the wonder of their ioy; which Art
                  Confeſſeth it exceeds her power to ſhow
                  At full, which onely they that haue can know.
                  Thus braue Corvinus, then whom fame nere knew
                  Any that to an higher vertue grew,
                  
                     
When once it pleas'd Fortune to leaue her frowne,
                  Made an exchange of Fetters for a Crowne.
                  Thus, not to ſeeke a forreine preſident,
                  Our Henry, whom the Heau'ns courteouſly ſent
                  To ſet a period to our Ciuill broyles,
                  To ioyne both Roſes: after many foyles
                  Receiu'd and conquer'd, after he had ſeene
                  Himſelfe an Exile, who a Prince had beene,
                  When baniſhment was enuy'd him, when nought
                  Would pleaſe his Enemy, vnleſſe he bought
                  His death of him that harbour'd him; eu'n then,
                  To foole the proiects of the cunningſt men,
                  This wither'd root begins afreſh to ſpring,
                  And from a baniſht coarſe reuiues a King.
                  Thus (not to ſeeke out a ſtale preſident,
                  Mentioning mercies after they are ſpent
                  And loſt in ſtory) Englands preſent Ioy
                  (Whom Fate can onely threaten, not annoy,)
                  How hath he try'd variety of griefe!
                  How beene in dangers, as in Rule our Chiefe;
                  That when there is a ſpeech of ſuffering,
                  He is no leſſe our Patterne, then our King.
                  The Seas ſpoke loud, yet if we rightly poyſe,
                  There was more danger, where there was leſſe noyſe:
                  Yet was he freed from both, when in mans eye,
                  Succeſſe had ſeem'd to ſmile on Treachery.
                  Theſe are your wonders, Heau'n, and not ſo much
                  Fauours (although the Fauour too be ſuch,
                  That it does poſe our gratitude, and ſo
                  Onely proclaimes that we are made to owe,
                  Our pouerty of merit) to be ſhort,
                  Th'are not ſo much your Fauours, as your Sport.
                  You in an inſtant rayſe, whom we would ſweare
                  Nayl'd to the Earth, him that had left to feare
                  More then he ſuffer'd, that had beene ſo long
                  Acquainted with ill lucke, with ſuch a throng
                  
                     
Of miſaduentures, that hee does not know
                  What it is to be free from them, and ſo
                  This courteous intermiſſion he expounds
                  Rather a Change then Cure of his neer wounds:
                  You in an vnthought Minute can depreſſe,
                  Whom we beleeue in league with Happineſſe.
                  And as vpon the Stage we oft haue ſeene
                  Him act a Beggar, who a King hath beene:
                  For no default, but that the Poets art
                  Thought at that time he beſt would fit that part?
                  So in our ſerious Theaters, when you pleaſe
                  Kings are as varying perſons as are theſe,
                  Onely in this their diſaduantage lyes;
                  That they may fall, but cannot hope to riſe.
                  They, whom the bands that make a kingdome ſtrong,
                  Succeſſion to the Crowne both right and long
                  From worthy Anceſtors, obedience
                  At home, and laſtly ſure intelligence
                  Abroad hath fortifyed, thoſe that ſuppos'd
                  True ioy to be wholly in them inclos'd:
                  If you but pleaſe to frowne, in one ſhort day
                  (When they not thinke their Enemies on their way)
                  Are conquer'd by them, and at laſt retaine
                  This comfort onely to allay their paine,
                  That their misfortunes (if the heauens decree)
                  May be the portion of their Enemy.
                  Why then doe trifling miſeries ſo grate
                  Our minds, and make vs more vnfortunate
                  Then heau'n intended? if out of a ſumme
                  Of mony (not ſo rich as troubleſome
                  By the large roome it occupies,) ſome one
                  Willing to teach vs moderation,
                  Nibble a little, how we fret! we raue!
                  How for our treaſure wee diſtraction haue!
                  As if we did beleeue (to ſay no more)
                  Heau'n onely had the powre to make vs poore,
                  
                     
But Iſrael thought not thus, but does prepare
                  All things that for the Action needfull are:
                  He thinkes now double diligence is due,
                  That he may be victorious, and God true.
                  On the Eaſtſide of Gibeah there ſtood
                  An ouergrowne and vnfrequented wood;
                  The trees ſo thickly plac'd, that you would gueſſe,
                  (Had you beheld that horrid wilderneſſe:
                  How darkeneſſe all the Maſtery had wonne,)
                  Twas made for the diſcredit of the Sunne;
                  Neuer did any raye pierce through thoſe leaues,
                  And if at any time it light receiues
                  Tis onely when the heauens doe miſſe their ſtroke,
                  And paſſing wicked men, murder an Oke.
                  So that the brightneſſe that adornes the ſame
                  Serues not ſo much to inlighten, as inflame.
                  Here neuer did the nimble Fairy tread,
                  Nor euer any of the Wood-nymphes bred
                  Within this groue, but it was ſingled out
                  For Pluto's regiment, for that bad rout
                  Of Hell-borne furies, there you might haue ſeene
                  
                     Alecto ſtretch'd at her full length betweene
                  Two fatall Yughs, where while her reſt ſhe takes,
                  She giues an intermiſſion to her Snakes,
                  Who in a thouſand curles there hiſſing lye,
                  And ſhe ſleepes ſweeter by their harmony.
                  Here had the Canaanite in former times
                  (Whileſt that Religion did conſiſt in crimes,)
                  Offer'd his ſonnes in ſacrifice, as though
                  He meant to pay backe heau'n all he did owe
                  Or did conceiue, (that which he ſhould deſpaire)
                  To be without ſinne, when without an heire.
                  This horrid place till now had emptie ſtood,
                  But now the Iſraelites conclude it good
                  To plant an ambuſh there: for thus they plot
                  That when the skirmiſh ſhall be growing hot,
                  
                     
They will draw backe, to make the Beniamite
                  
                  Conceiue that ſtratagem to be a flight,
                  And leaue the towne for the purſuit; when ſtraight
                  Vpon a ſigne giu'n, they that lie in waite
                  Shall ceize vpon the City, and ſo force
                  Their Enemy to ſuch a deſp'rate courſe,
                  That being purſu'd by thoſe he put to flight,
                  He ſhall not know, whether to flie or fight.
                  Hearken ye ſilly ones that doe ſuppoſe
                  You ought not to beare Armes againſt your foes:
                  Who hauing caſt off ordinary ſenſe,
                  Affirme that they doe warre with Prouidence,
                  Who prouidently warre, that they diſtruſt
                  The powre, or care of heau'n, who will be iuſt
                  To their owne cauſe, which you will noyſe to be
                  A ſpice of wiſer Infidelity.
                  To theſe I need no other anſwer find:
                  Shall we be fooliſh becauſe heau'n is kind?
                  And when your induſtry might doe as well,
                  Will ye inforce God to a Miracle?
                  It is a truth I grant, which you pretend
                  That God hath deſtin'd all things to their end,
                  Which ſtands immoueable: nor is't in Fate
                  To alter what he will praeordinate:
                  Yet neuer any did ſo farre proceed
                  In folly, to affirme that he decreed
                  Onely the end, that 'twas in Gods intents,
                  Whileſt we did ſleepe, to bleſſe vs with euents
                  We dreame not of: Such fondnes cannot find
                  Any excuſe (vnleſſe they were deſign'd
                  Ineuitably to't:) for I would know
                  (If they ſuppoſe it poſſible to ſhew
                  Their mind in theſe affaires, or if they bee
                  Not hindred from an anſwer by Decree)
                  Why they doe eate? and why they doe not hence
                  Conclude rebellion againſt Prouidence?
                  
                     
Why they doe cloath themſelues? and why deſire
                  When cold oppreſſeth them to chooſe a fire?
                  Haue you forgot that for his holy ones,
                  God can at 
                        •
                     aſe produce e'ne out of ſtones
                  As ſolid ſuſtenance? or is it loſt
                  In your fraile memory, that when Iſrael croſt
                  The Deſert out of Egypt, forty yeares
                  Nor Taylors they imploy'd, nor Shoomakers?
                  Truſt me if you your ſelues thinke your ſelues true,
                  Your care does vilify Gods care of you;
                  And euery diſh that to your board is brought
                  Vpbraides him to his face, as if you ſought
                  To mend his purpoſe; and by this odd feat,
                  You doe blaſpheme as often as you eate.
                  The Iſraelites are wiſer farre, although
                  They haue that vnknowne happineſſe, to know
                  Their victory aforehand, though they heare
                  This truth from him, from whom they cannot feare
                  Any deceit, (whoſe powerfull word alone
                  Makes that a truth which he reſolues vpon,)
                  Although they will allow his Act for chiefe,
                  Yet they will doe their part too: to be briefe,
                  Euery ſouldier to himſelfe ſayes thus;
                  God will beſtow the victory, but by vs.
                  The night they ſpend in prayer, but when the morne
                  Had dimm'd the pride of Cynthiah's cleereſt horne
                  By higher luſter, being call'd away
                  Not by the Cocke, the Trumpetter of Day;
                  But by an earlier trumpet, then you might
                  By her vnwilling and yet haſting light,
                  Diſcerne, and ſeeing, almoſt rightly poyſe
                  Whether were more, their number, or their noyſe,
                  And vnto which more feare was to be giu'n,
                  Who fill the Earth with Numbers, with Noyſe Heau'n.
                  
                     Beniamin takes th'alarme, and hauing choſe
                  One in whoſe faithfulneſſe they might repoſe
                  
                     
A wary confidence; they quit the wall
                  And to the wider field iſſue out all,
                  Leſt if they ſtay'd within, and did oppoſe
                  Rampiers and ditches onely to their foes,
                  They might haue bragg'd, (as if that they had won)
                  Making a priſon of their garriſon.
                  Now both the Hoaſts themſelues ſo neere doe find,
                  That it would aske more labour t'haue declin'd
                  The field, then to haue wonne it, yet they ſtay
                  Hoping that innocence is in delay,
                  If they are ſlowly guilty: now ſpeares flye
                  Shiuer'd in thouſand fitters to the skye;
                  And whether it reuenge or fortune were,
                  Euery peece becomes a Murtherer,
                  And from their bodies frees a many ſoule,
                  Doing that broken, which they could not whole.
                  Could Xerxes here haue ſate vpon an hill,
                  To ſee theſe warriors, hee would not ſtill
                  Fondly lament, nor lauiſh out a teare
                  Becauſe they could not liue an hundred yeere,
                  But melt into iuſt paſſion away,
                  Becauſe they could not liue out all that day.
                  Now might you haue beheld the fiery horſe
                  Proud of his owne, and of his Maſters force,
                  Robb'd of his Maſter, whom you now might ſee
                  Running, as if twere after Liberty.
                  Or you'de conceiue, had you but ſeene the race
                  That 'twas no more a battle, but a chaſe.
                  No ſtroke falls idle, nay they are ſo neere;
                  They need not ſtrike at all: death is caus'd here
                  By their bad neighbourhood, the whole and ſound
                  You might haue ſeene here dead without a wound.
                  To ſaue the guilt and labour of the ſword,
                  Bodies to bodies their owne ends afford.
                  Now nothing but the duſt is to be ſeene
                  Which like ſo many Emblemes flyes betweene
                  
                     
The mingled armies, which in ſilence ſayes,
                  They are no better then the motes they raiſe,
                  Then thoſe poore Atomes: but they thinke to ſhrowde
                  Their acts from ſight of heau'n vnder that cloud,
                  And therefore did their vtmoſt: yet as though
                  Theſe hands were ſluggliſh, or this fury ſlow,
                  The trumpets chid them to a luſtier guilt
                  And the lowd drummes proclaim'd, you haue not ſpilt
                  Blood enough yet: O what were they that found
                  Out firſt the vſe and malice of that ſound?
                  Which makes vs kill with greedineſſe, and when
                  Tis the Corrupted Nature of moſt men
                  Hardly to yeeld vnto the deſtitute,
                  Theſe will not ſuffer vs to heare their ſuite.
                  This drownes the groanes: but now both armies reele,
                  Now this giues backe ſome ground, now that doth feele
                  That it is preſt too hardly. Thus the ſeas
                  When euer it the angry winds does pleaſe
                  To exerciſe their fury, doe not know
                  What courſe to take, nor whither they ſhould flow:
                  This waue breakes that, and then another blaſt
                  Makes that the conqueror, which was conquerd laſt.
                  At length the Iſraelites giue backe indeed,
                  And though in order, yet with ſuch a ſpeed,
                  
                     Beniamin calls it Flight, all's ours they cry,
                  If we can runne we haue the victory:
                  With that what euer men the towne affords,
                  Skilfull to vſe their fingers or their ſwords,
                  For ſpoyle or for purſuite, iſſue out thence
                  With ſuch a noyſe, they giue intelligence
                  That they haue left it emptie: O the vaine
                  Attempts of fooliſh man! O deſeru'd paine!
                  Th'are made the ſpoile, that they intend to make,
                  So wiſely can iuſt heau'ns their vengeance take
                  On bad attempts, ſo all heate aſſwage,
                  And make our Ruine greater then our Rage.
                  
                     
It neuer entred into their proud thought,
                  They ſhould receiue the dammage which they ſought
                  To giue vnto their brethren: who hauing left
                  Their woody couert, and the friendly cleft,
                  VVhich entertain'd them, by a quicke ſurprize,
                  Take the vnguarded towne: O who can prize
                  Thoſe loſſes to the full? or who rehearſe
                  Thoſe miſaduentures in an equall verſe?
                  They ſpare no age, but (cruell) take away
                  From the old men, the ſolitary day
                  They could expect to liue: now Infants dye,
                  Eu'n thoſe, who yet within their mothers lye,
                  Finding a Night before they ſee the Morne,
                  Being buri'd thus, before that they were borne,
                  For whom their murtherers no crime could chooſe,
                  But that they were, and had a life to looſe.
                  Nor does the weaker ſex eſcape the rage
                  Of theſe intruders, and as euery Age,
                  So euery Perſon ſuffers, onely here
                  May be the difference, (if that any were)
                  Either they're killd out-right, or which is worſe,
                  They thinke their life to be the greater curſe.
                  Here mothers ſee their daughters whom they bred
                  As Votaries vnto their Maidenhead,
                  Vn-virgin'd in their ſight, where hauing loſt
                  That peereleſſe iewell, which they valewd moſt,
                  They doe receiue to vindicate their name
                  A death from them, from whom they had their ſhame.
                  Auarice followes Luſt, now they haue leiſure
                  To ranſacke all thoſe Mineralls of treaſure
                  Long peace and thrift had hoarded vp, at laſt
                  As children when their Appetite is paſt
                  Spoyle what they cannot eate, and badly kind
                  Pamper their dogs with that they leaue behind:
                  So theſe, as ſurfeiting with ſuch a ſtore,
                  (VVhich made them loſe all feare of being poore)
                  
                     
VVhat is not ready ſpoyle, giue to the fire,
                  VVhoſe conqu'ring flames vnto the heau'ns aſpire,
                  As boaſting of their ſeruice: through the towne,
                  Swifter then any thing that has renowne
                  For ſpeedineſſe, they runne, one houre does ſpoile
                  (Vnlucky houre) what was an Ages toyle
                  Now cracke the houſes, now the Temples fry,
                  Now the poore Citizens reſolu'd to dye,
                  Doubt of what death: and know not which to try,
                  The fire, the downefalls, or the Enemy.
                  Had this misfortune hapned in the Night
                  (Though Nature had oppos'd) ſuch a full light
                  Had made a day, and ſo againe had wonne
                  A Conqueſt of the towne, and of the Sunne.
                  Neuer did Sailor with ſuch ioy behold
                  
                     Caſtor and Pollux when his ſhip was roll'd
                  Vpon the angry Ocean, (whoſe proud waues
                  Made the moſt haughty minds freeze into ſlaues
                  VVith a baſe feare,) as Iſrael does view
                  Thoſe flames, which he does feare not to be true,
                  They are ſo great, and yet he hopes to ſee
                  Theſe flames to light him to a victory.
                  Now all the face of things is chang'd anew,
                  Now thoſe which earſt ſeem'd vanquiſh'd doe purſue:
                  The Iſraelites confirming by their Fight
                  That they could cauſe as well as act a Flight.
                  
                     Beniamin growes amaz'd, and does not know
                  VVhat he ſhould doe, nor on what grounds to goe,
                  VVhich probably ſeem ſafe: if he ſhould flye
                  He runnes away vnto the Enemy:
                  And ſhall he fight? alas! but he will find
                  It is impoſſible to fight behind,
                  VVhere he ſhall be aſſay'ld: yet he ſhifts ground,
                  And figures out his battle in a round.
                  And ſince he hath no hope to ſcape away,
                  Hee'l nobly ſell, not giue away the day.
                  
                     
They neuer fought till now, all the whole day
                  Before, was onely ſomewhat fiercer Play,
                  Murder in ieſt, but now they are ſo fierce
                  As if they would inforce their ſwords to pierce
                  Beyond the body; this a while, at length
                  Deſpaire does yeeld the victory to ſtrength;
                  And Fortune (that the world henceforth might find
                  That they had iniur'd her who call'd her blind)
                  Crownes the beſt ſide, and prouidently tryes
                  At once to proue their Conqueſt, and her Eyes.
                  The Parellell is eaſie; was't not thus,
                  When Heau'n was pleas'd to be as kind to vs?
                  We felt the prickles firſt, but then our Noſe
                  Suckt in the ſweeter vertue of the Roſe.
                  We had ſucceſſe, as it were choſe, and pickt,
                  And what we feard to ſuffer did inflict.
                  When Brett and Burrowes (that I ſpeake their due)
                  Reuiu'd to France, Talbot and Montague.
                  
                  (O too like Montague, that loſt thy breath,
                  By the ſame fatall Engine of quicke death.)
                  When the choyce valour of each rancke, and fyle
                  Made vp a double Sea within the Iſle
                  Of blood and teares, O giue vs thankes, kind heau'n,
                  And adde a vertue to our Fortune giu'n,
                  That we may all acknowledge his deſert,
                  Who nobly gain'd a conqueſt of the heart
                  Of them, whoſe bodies he had conquer'd firſt,
                  To whom he then diſcouer'd, what he durſt,
                  And after what his Nature was, when he
                  In the ſad field had ſpent his Cruelty,
                  For when they offer'd to redeeme their dead,
                  Summes which another would haue vanquiſhed,
                  He freely yeelds vnto the ſutors breath,
                  And giues the Graue, as eaſily as the Death.
                  Whilſt they doe giue—O how I bluſh to tell,
                  A poiſon'd knife, a poiſon that will dwell
                  
                     
And eate into their fame till earth be gone,
                  Till poyſon haue no more to worke vpon.
                  Teach vs our right to him, but then to you
                  What ſhall we giue? and yet what not leaue due?
                  Then, O kind Heau'n, for this let me be pleader,
                  May we ſtill ſing your prayſe, who led our Leader.
                  And now I haſt vnto my ſongs concluſion,
                  
                     Iſraels conqueſt, Bentamins confuſion
                  On all that valiant number which but now
                  Made treble numbers to their valor bow:
                  Onely ſixe hundred ſcape away, ſo few,
                  They were ſcarce able to commit a new
                  The Crime for which they ſuffer'd; had not Night
                  Became their vmpire and forbad the Fight,
                  Thoſe few had periſht too; then at the laſt
                  Let future Ages learne of Ages paſt
                  How vice rewards her ſeruants! Let them be
                  Afraid at leaſtwiſe of the miſery,
                  Who ſlight the ſinne: why ſhould a beauteous face
                  Make my ſoule foule? and an externall grace
                  Bereaue me of my inward? O deſpaire!
                  Shall I be bad becauſe another's faire?
                  Hence that poore folly, rather let vs winne
                  A conqueſt by the loſſe of Beniamin.
                  
                  To know that thoſe bely'd, and ſtolne delights
                  Are not of ſo long laſting as the Nights,
                  In which we did inioy them, how the Day
                  Takes both their darkneſſe, and our ſweets away:
                  To vnderſtand that tardy heau'n is iuſt,
                  That Ruine is the conſequent of Luſt.
               
               
                  And now O Father, once more I repaire,
                  To thy great preſence, O thou onely faire!
                  (Who dwelling in the light that none comes neere
                  Canſt not be ſeene of vs, becauſe too cleere;
                  To whom created beauties if compar'd,
                  Ruin ſuch as haue the wiſeſt eyes enſnar'd,
                  
                     
Are nothing but Deformity at beſt,
                  Durt ſomewhat better colourd then the reſt)
                  Inſtruct my youth, O teach that I may know,
                  What miſchiefes lurke vnder a ſeemely ſhow;
                  What a ſweet danger woman is: O thou
                  To whom the knees that doe not loue, doe bow,
                  Whom all obey, eu'n ſuch as haue no ſenſe,
                  Who doe not know their owne obedience;
                  Whom all obey, eu'n ſuch as doe goe on
                  In a perpetuall Rebellion,
                  The Spirits accurſt: Grant me, that chaſtly wife
                  I enter into Couenant with mine eyes,
                  Neuer to looke on Woman, not to ſee
                  What would perſwade my ſoule to forſake thee,
                  To make a God of fleſh: But if that I
                  Forc'd by Temptation, or Neceſſity,
                  Muſt ſee my Ruine, yet thus much, O thou
                  Whom my ſoule loues, and would more, knew ſhe how,
                  (For his deare ſake and worth, in whom was found
                  Onely a place, no reaſon for a wound)
                  If I muſt haue the ſight, yet I require
                  I may at leaſtwiſe not haue the deſire.
                  If I muſt ſee, let it be to deſpiſe
                  So ſhall my heart be chaſt, if not mine eyes.
               
            
            FINIS.
         
         
            
            A Thankſgiuing for a recouery
from a burning Feauer.
            I Burne againe, methinkes an holy fire
            Kindles my dull deuotion, and farre higher
            Raiſeth my ſpirit, then my hot diſeaſe
            Inf
                  •
               am'd my blood: how with a ſacred caſe
            Feele I theſe flames through my glad ſoule to ruſh!
            Life thoſe, which made a Chappell of the buſh
            VVhen God did tutor Moſes; would 'twere found
            That this place too were ſuch an holy ground:
            Then ſhould I boldly vent my Gratitude,
            And being Godly, not be counted Rude.
            The Night approacht, when by my paines I might
            Suſpect it would haue been my laſting Night:
            I had a griefe beyond a Cowards feares,
            And ſuch a griefe, it robb'd me of my teares.
            I was all Fire, the greedy element
            Left no one part vnſing'd, as if it meant
            To croſſe the vulgar notions of our birth,
            And proue that man was not compos'd of Earth,
            That he was made of Flames, that paſt all doubt
            To dye was nothing, but to be put out.
            And yet the truth of this, this truth denyes,
            Man is not made of that by which he dyes.
            And had I dy'd thus, they had beene vniuſt
            VVho had pronounc'd, we giue duſt vnto duſt.
            Aſhes they well might tearme me, and ſo turne
            My Chriſtian buriall to a Pagan vine.
            VVithout a tedious pilgrimage to Rome,
            
            (If that the torment make the Martyrdome)
            I might be Canoniz'd, and ſooner farre
            Then ſome whoſe names in the gulld Calender
            Burne in red letters, of whom none can tell
            VVhether they onely felt a Fire in Hell.
            O heat! O drought! O am I quencht as yet,
            Or is not this Remembrance a new fit!
            
               
Yet in my fierceſt fit how oft I thought
            (Whil'ſt yet there was ſome moiſture left, which fought
            With my hot Enemy) how durſt liberall men
            Giue vs a freedome of our wills, that when
            Euer we liſt we may be good, and ſo
            Owe to our ſelues as well the Cure as Blow?
            Who gaue vs this ſtrange power, can any tell,
            Not to be Bad, and yet not to be Well?
            Can we command our ſinnes ſo eaſily,
            And faint at a poore Feauer? tell me why
            You will conſent to dye? and wherefore ſtill
            You plead not then a liberty of will?
            My God cry'd I, though I muſt needs confeſſe
            Vnto my ſhame, that all my paines are leſſe
            Then my demerits, yet I grant as free
            That they exceed all poſſibility
            Of mine owne cure, and yet I ſooner can
            (Spite of Diſeaſe) turne my Phyſitian
            Then my Redeemer, thou alone canſt doe
            A powerfull cure on ſoule and body too.
            With that I felt recouery: my flame
            Was kindly leſſen'd to a lower name,
            To moderate heat. Sleepe did my ſenſes charme,
            And I that burnt before, was now but warme,
            Health and Deuotion ceize on me, my fire
            Had leſt my bones to liue in my Deſire,
            And I was ſicke of thankfulneſſe: then now
            Teach me O Lord not why to prayſe, but how:
            Bow my ſtiffe knees, that they may beg a powr'e
            Of full thankſgiuing to my Sauiour.
            Some praiſe for leſſe: Iu'e read of Ionab's arke
            (Which was of ſurer cariage then his Barke)
            Th'inhabitable Fiſh, and yet we ſee
            That he giues thankes for his Deliuery,)
            From his Preſeruer; and ſhall retchleſſe I
            Deliuer'd from a neerer death, now dye
            
               
In the Remembrance? firſt, O Lord returne
            My tutor-torment, let me againe burne.
            And now great God, I doe intreat, and change
            My prayſe into a pray'r, (for tis not ſtrange
            That benefits ſhou'd make a ſuppliant,
            Since courteſies cauſe pray'r as well as want)
            Twas thy great mercy made my body whole,
            O let me find that mercy to my ſoule,
            Then ſhall I boldly haſten to the graue,
            And wanting Life, not want what I would haue.
            
               
                  Ʋpon our vaine flattery of our ſelues, that the ſucceeding
times will be better then the former.
               HOw we daily out our dayes!
               How we ſeeke a thouſand wayes
               To find Death! the which if none
               We ſought out, would ſhew vs one.
               Why then doe we iniure Fate,
               When we will impute the date
               And expiring of our time,
               To be hers, which is our Crime?
               Wiſh we not our End? and worſe,
               Mak't a Pray'r which is a Curſe?
               Does there not in each breaſt lye
               Both our ſoule and Enemy?
               Neuer was there Morning yet
               (Sweet as is the Violet)
               Which mans folly did not ſoone
               Wiſh to be expir'd in Noone;
               As though ſuch an haſt did tend
               To our bliſſe, and not our End.
               Nay the yong ones in the neſt
               Sucke this folly from the breaſt,
               And no ſtamm'ring ape but can
               Spoyle a prayer to be a Man.
               But ſuppoſe that he is heard,
               By the ſprouting of his beard,
               
                  
And he hath what he doth ſeek
               The ſoft cloathing of the Cheeke:
               Yet would he ſtay here? or bee
               Fixt in this Maturity?
               Sooner ſhall the wandring ſtarre
               Learne what reſt and quiet are:
               Sooner ſhall the ſlippery Rill,
               Leaue his motion and ſtand ſtill.
               Be it Ioy, or be it Sorrow,
               We referre all to the Morrow:
               That we thinke will eaſe our paine,
               That we doe ſuppoſe againe
               Will increaſe or Ioy, and ſo
               Euents, the which we cannot know
               We magnifie, and are (in ſumme)
               Enamor'd of the time to come.
               Well, the next day comes, and then,
               Another next, and ſo to ten,
               To twenty we arriue, and find
               No more before vs then behind
               Of ſolid ioy, and yet haſt on
               To our Conſummation:
               Till the baldneſſe of the Crowne,
               Till that all the face doe frowne,
               Till the Forehead often haue
               The remembrance of a Graue;
               Till the eyes looke in, to find
               If that they can ſee the mind.
               Till the ſharpneſſe of the Noſe,
               Till that we haue liu'd to poſe
               Sharper eyes who cannot know
               Whether we are men or no.
               Till the tallow of the Cheeke
               Till we know not what we ſeeke;
               And at laſt of life bereau'd,
               Dye vnhappy, and deceiu'd.
            
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

