
   
      
         
            The tragedie of Lodouick Sforza Duke of Millan. By Robert Gomersall
            Gomersall, Robert, 1602-1646?
         
         
            
               1628
            
         
         Approx. 141 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01853
            STC 11995
            ESTC S103225
            99838982
            99838982
            3375
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01853)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3375)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1068:08)
         
         
            
               
                  The tragedie of Lodouick Sforza Duke of Millan. By Robert Gomersall
                  Gomersall, Robert, 1602-1646?
                  Cecil, Thomas, fl. 1630, engraver.
               
               [18], 70, [2] p.   
               
                  [By Miles Flesher for John Marriott],
                  Imprinted at London :
                  in the yeare M DC XXVIII. [1628]
               
               
                  With an additional title page, engraved, signed "Tho: Cecill. sculp.": Sforza by Rob: Gomersall. London. Printed for Iohn Marriott. 1628.
                  Printer's name from STC.
                  The first two leaves are blank except for signature-mark on A2.
                  Running title reads: The tragedy of Sforza.
                  Reproduction of the original in the British Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Ludovico Sforza, --  Duke of Milan, 1452-1508 --  Drama.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-07
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-07
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2007-01
            Mona LogarboSampled and proofread
         
            2007-01
            Mona LogarboText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2007-02
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            
            
            
            
               THE EXPLANATION of the Frontiſpice.
               IT was when Induſtry did ſleepe
               The Wolfe was Tutor to the Sheep,
               And to amaze a plainer man,
               The thiefe was made the guardian.
               But can a Wolfe forget to prey?
               Can Night be lightned into Day?
               Without reſpect of lawes or blood,
               His charge he makes to be his food.
               With that triumphant be ſits downe,
               Oppreſt, not bonour'd with a Crowne,
               And on the leſſer beaſts does try
               A moſt Authenticke Tyranny:
               This the French Lyon heares, and when
               He's thought faſt ſleeping in his denne,
               Vengeance and He at once doe wake,
               And on the Wolfe their fury ſlake.
               Bad acts may bloome ſometimes, but n'ere grow high,
               Nor doe they liue ſo ſure, as they ſhall dye.
            
            
               
               
                  SFORZA
                  by Rob: Gomerſall
                  London Printed for 
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
               
            
         
         
            
            
            THE TRAGEDIE OF LODOVICK SFORZA DVKE OF MILLAN.
            
            By Robert Gomerſall.
            
            Imprinted at LONDON in the yeare M DC XXVIII.
         
         
            
            
            TO HIS MOST WORTHIE FRIEND Mr. FRANCIS HIDE PROCTOR OF OXFORD.
            
            
               
                  HAuing reſolued what to print, I could not be long doubtfull vnto whom: it had beene an vnfriendly abſurdity not to haue intitled him to my ſecond, who might not vniuſtly haue challenged the patronage of my firſt Labour. But if vntill this time I had had no reaſon for ſuch a dedication, if the ſame moſt fruitfull Colledge had not for theſe many years knowne vs of the ſame time and friendſhip, if in all offices of life I had not ſtill found you moſt inſeparably one with mee: yet this Worke at this time could not offer it ſelfe to any ſo iuſtly as to you. It is to your name that I owe what euer fruits of my ſpent time ſhall be preſerued, it is to your name that I owe whateuer fruits of my former time, being vnhappily loſt, may haue a poſſibilitie of recouery. And could I dedicate any of my remaining Labours with
               
               more iuſtice vnto any, then to him, by whoſe friendly care, I dare almoſt aſſure my ſelfe of them which are remaining? But ſome perhaps may ſay for this, that it had beene better if it had beene loſt, or at leaſt that theſe kind of Labours are more iudiciouſly ſuppreſt then publiſhed. Sermons had beene fitter for my ſetting forth, and to preach more proper then to write. But is not this to preach? I haue heard diuers ſpeake an houre, who preach not, and there are many, who effectually preach, that are more ſparing of their breath. If I make the ambitious ſee that he climbes but to a fall, the vſurper to acknowledge, that blood is but a ſlippery foundation of power, all men in generall to confeſſe that the moſt glorious is not the moſt ſafe place: is not this to cry downe Ambition and Vſurpation? or is it leſſe to ſhew, then to threaten? and are not men ſo much moued with the euent it ſelfe, as with the commination of the euent? And yet in this age, wherein only Hereſie or Sedition preferre a Booke, wherein Contradiction is called Learning, and Zeale wonders that ſhe is become Faction, I can expect but a few Readers, whoſe ſmall number ſhall be no diſcouragement at all to me if that your iudgement ſhall counterpoiſe them, which is the onely deſired crowne of
            
            
               Your true friend,
R. G.
            
         
         
            
            The Argument.
            
               
                  LOdovicke Sforza, after hee had cunningly ſupplanted the Ducheſſe from the wardſhip of her ſonne Galeazzo, as cunningly practizeth to beethe murtherer of him, of whom he would ſeeme to be the Protector. To this end he was to remoue this impediment. Iſabella daughter to the Prince of Calabria, and Grand-childe vnto Ferdinand King of Naples, was wife to Galeazzo. A woman of a ſpirit as high as her birth, and equall to Sforza in all things but the ſex: ſhee perceiuing the ſtupidity of her husband, and how that whatſoeuer ſhe proiected for his ſafety, he diſcouered to his vncle, for his ouerthrow, makes her father ſecretly acquainted with all the paſſages, deſiring him to vindicate his ſon in law from the vſurpation of his Protector. This could not be ſo priuately diſpatched, but that Sforza had an incling of it, whether out of his owne reach hee gueſſed it: or by his Nephewes ſottiſhneſſe he vnderſtood it. To preuent then his owne ruine, whilſt he intends his Nephews, he ventures on thoſe remedies which the height of feare rather ruſheth on, then chuſeth,

which more expreſſe and exchange, then remoue, or auoyd a danger. He knew the French claime to Naples, to the proſecution of which he ſollicites the yong King; whom either his right, or inconſiderateneſſe quickly armes vnto the action. But before his comming, hee by continuall meſſengers deludes the old King, and makes him beleeue that there was no purpoſe of his comming, and that the French iourney vnto Naples, as it was onely the childe of rumor, &amp; had no being but frō fame, ſo in a very ſhort ſpace, in the age of a wonder it would vaniſh and expire. Thus was Ferdinand perſwaded from his neceſſary defence, till hauing certainly vnderſtood that all defence would be too late, the French being already very ſtrong vpon his frontires, cheated, not conquer'd, hee dyes and leaues his ſonne Alphonſo heire of his kingdome, and his troubles. The French King being now entred in perſon into Italy, Galeazzo dyes of a poyſon at Pauia, when Sforza has brought this worſe poyſon into his Country. But the French growing prodigiouſly victorious, and almoſt by the very ſeeing ouer comming their oppoſites, Sforza begins to be apprehenſiue of his owne danger, and ſtriues to rid himſelfe of theſe incumbrances, in the which a too much prouidence had intangled him. A conſideration

without doubt neceſſary, but almoſt paſt the ſeaſon, it being neer vnto an impoſſibility to expell him now, whom it was far from any difficulty at the firſt not to admit. So that this ſecond reſolution did onely proclaime the folly of the firſt, which either in wiſdome hee ſhould not haue ventur'd on, or, in honeſty not haue altred. But howſoeuer, hee enters into a new league with the Venetians, and giues the French after their victorious returne from Naples halfe an ouerthrow at Taro. And now when hee thinks himſelfe confirm'd in his Dukedome, when he as little fear'd ruine, as he deſeru'd preſeruation; the French King dyes ſuddenly, to whom Lewis, the true Duke of Orleans, and titular Duke of Millan, ſucceeded, with him Sforzaes late friend, the Venetians conclude a league. Thus Sforza being left alone, raiſeth two armies vnder the conduct of the two Sanſeuerins, men, whom hee had highly fauour'd and aduanced. But it is ſcarce ſeene, that a faithleſſe Maſter ſhould haue a truſty ſeruant, and hee that hath no reſpect to his owne word, ſhall in the extremeſt of his neceſſities, finde all others promiſes but words. The elder reuolts, and the yonger, without the leaſt ſhow of reſiſtance, flyes, and Sforza himſelfe is ſo cloſely purſued, that he can ſcarce get away ſafe into Germany. The French

abuſing their late victory, the Millaneſi with a generall conſent, recall Sforza; who, like a melting ſnow, ouerflowes all before him, and recouers moſt of his Duchy, with the ſame eaſineſſe that he had loſt it. The ſtrength of his Army conſiſted eſpecially of Swizzers, whom the late ouerthrow of the warlike Duke of Burgundy, and theſe Italian wars, had raiſed to the height of admiration. But to be valiant is not to haue all vertues: theſe were as ſtrong in treachery, as in battle, they lead Sforza in the habite of a Swizzer into the French camp, through which in the ſame habit they had promiſed to conduct him. Thus hauing beene twice betrayd, and now a priſoner, after a ten yeers harſh confining hee dyes in France, hauing liu'd in his miſery, longer then in his Duchy, and leauing inſtruction to ſucceeding Princes that height ſhould not be their ayme, but integrity; and that they would not (that I may vſe the words of our Poet) tempt their ſtarres beyond their light.
         
      
      
         
            
            The names of the Actors.
            
               
                  GIovanni Galeazzo the yong Duke.
               
                  Lodovick Sforza His Protector, afterwards Duke.

                     two brothers of the houſe of Sanſeuerin, Sforza's fauorites.
                     
                        Galeazzo
                     
                     Count Caiazzo
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     two of the Nobility.
                     
                        Lucio Maluezzo
                     
                     
                        Carlo Burbia
                              •
                           o Count Belgioſa
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     two old Courtiers.
                     
                        Iuliano
                     
                     
                        Picinino
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                     Poyſoners.
                     
                        Vitellio
                     
                     
                        Malateſta
                     
                  
               
               
                  Aſcanio Sforza's brother, a Cardinall.
               
                  Triulcio The French Generall.
               The Captaine of the Swizzers.
               
                  Iſabella Galeazzo's wife.
               
                  Iulia.
               
               
                  Bettrice wife to Sforza.
               
               Embaſſadors, Souldiers, Seruants.
            
         
         
            
            The Prologue.
            
               CAn horror haue an auditory? can
               Man loue the spectacle of ruin'd man?
               We fear'd we ſhould haue beene alone, that hence,
               The Actors ſhould haue beene the Audience.
               Are you not frighted yet? do
                     •
                   you not riſe?
               Can that inuite, which ſhould diſmay your eyes?
               We ſhew neer murthers, and in that degree
               Where Mariage is vnlawfull, then, the free
               Progreſſe of crimes, by nimble Iuſtice met,
               Aequally horrid, this we ſhew, but yet
               Vnleſſe your Courteſie, your Iudgement ſway,
               We ſuffer a worſe torture, then we play.
            
         
         
            
               
               Actus primi
               
                  Scena prima.
                  
                     Galeazzo Duke of Millane, Iſabella his Wife.
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        .
                     WHy weeps my Deare?
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        .
                     
                        Aske why I do not weep:
                        (Poore Iſabella are thy teares deny'd thee?)
                        Aske why thus long ſuch a ſucceſſion
                        Of ſorrow clogs my boſome, and does rob
                        So much of Woman from mee, as complaints.
                        Aske why I doe not raue, teare my haire, thus,
                        Create a griefe, which Fate would ſpare me, then
                        Cloud the ſad Ayre with ſighes, and at the laſt,
                        With a bold ſtab take from inſulting Fortune
                        The miſerable obiect of her ſport:
                        Aske why I doe not this, not, why I weepe.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        l.
                     
                        Or ſtint thy teares, or mingle them with mine
                        By a relation of their cauſe: theſe eyes,
                        Truſt me, my Iſabella, are not dry,
                        Nor has ſtrong ſorrow ere exhauſted them,
                        To make them bankrout of a friendly teare,
                        Doe thou but proue it once a friendly teare
                        And not a fond one. Why, my Iſabella,
                        
                        Why doſt thou haſten thoſe that come too faſt,
                        
                           Sorrow, and Age? If it be true, I heard
                        Of Sforza, my deare Sforza, ther's no ioy
                        But either paſt, or fleeting, and poore man
                        Growes vp but to the experience of Griefe,
                        And then is truly paſt minority
                        When he is paſt all happineſſe:
                     
                  
                  
                     Jſab.
                     
                        My Lord,
                        My ſorrow dares not argue with your loue,
                        This ſmile expels it.
                     
                  
                  
                     Gal.
                     
                        Be it baniſht farre,
                        Aeternally, or to the yeares of Age.
                        I, thoſe vnclouded lookes become my deare,
                        And giue me ioy too. I muſt hunt to day
                        With my deare vncle: O he is a man
                        That alters all thoſe fond relations,
                        Which Nature giues, who in an vncles name
                        Ou
                              •
                            loues a Father: I could praiſe him ſtill,
                        But that I ſtay too long from him: farewell.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
                  
                     Jſab.
                     
                        O Galeazzol O not Galeazzo!
                        
                        How has Man fled thee! how thy ſoule has fled thee!
                        Onely thy lineaments bely a Man.
                        Thou hunt; 
                              〈◊〉
                            as poore Prince, thou art the Game:
                        Thy vncle hunts: and yet he does not neither,
                        But ſtands a glad, and idle looker on,
                        Whilſt thou inſnar
                              •
                           ſt thy ſelfe, ſinfully fool'd,
                        Flattering thy Executioner, and ſo
                        Doſt no
                              •
                            preuent thy miſery, nor yet know.
                     
                  
                  Enter G
                        〈…〉
                     
                  
                  
                     Gal.
                     
                        I am return'd once more; before I'me gone,
                        To ſee if thy fond griefe be not return'd;
                        What ioy is there in a forbidden griefe?
                        What comfort in the eyes ſad flux? once 
                              〈…〉
                           
                        
                        Is it my fault giues you theſe teares?
                     
                  
                  
                     Jſab▪
                     
                     
                        My 
                              〈…〉
                           
                           ▪
                        
                        
                           For which ſo ſtrange a ſad neſſe ſeizes me,
                        That it increaſeth when I ſtriue with it,
                        And makes my face rebellious to my Lord,
                        When my heart yeelds.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           •
                        al.
                     
                        Then once againe, adieu,
                        Forſake your griefe, or griefe will forſake you.
                     
                  
                  Exit.
                  
                     
                        
                           ••
                        ab.
                     
                        Forſake my griefe—O bid me forſake heau'n,
                        My reaſon, and mine honor: onely ſighes
                        Doc keepe me in opinion of Beeing,
                        And without them I were a ſtupid coarſe.
                        Shall I obey impoſſibilities?
                        Forſake the ſorrow, and retaine the cauſe?
                        How can I thinke that yet the vntyr'd Sunne
                        Has iourny'd but a twelue-month, ſince I was
                        In Ferdinando's Court, the Paragon
                        Of happy Naples, when his Palace ſeem'd
                        Guarded with Princely ſutors, and mine eye,
                        Caught with ſo many rarities of men,
                        Taught me that too much choyce did hinder choyce,
                        That Galeazzo then muſt cary me?
                        This Galeazzo, neither Prince, nor Man,
                        Fool'd out of both by Sforza, his deare vncle.
                        Can I thinke this, and thinke of ioy againe?
                        Can I thinke this, and dare to thinke againe?
                        Why ſhould ſome toyes of after-torment fright
                        A reſolution of eaſing me
                        From preſent ones? O tis the curſe of man
                        To be vnhappy at arbitrement,
Enter Iulia.
                        
                        Till heau'n pleaſe to relent▪ My Iulia,
                        
                        Breath's Naples any comfort? quickly ſpeake.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           •
                        al.
                     
                        None, Madam, and your courteous Grandfather
                        In ſtead of Armies ſends you Patience.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           ••
                        ab.
                     
                        What patience? he ſhould haue ſent me rage,
                        Ayded my anger, if not my reuenge:
                        
                           Patience? O God! can griefe be patient?
                        Can Thunder whiſper? or chaf'd ſe
                              ••
                            not ro
                              •
                           re?
                        In me is Sea and thunder, I will be
                        A patterne of Reuenge not miſery.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scena ſecunda.
                  
                     Sforza.
                     
                        
                           SForza as yet thou but beginſt to act,
                        And yet beginſt to ſtagger: wert thou not
                        A Princes ſonne? why art thou not a Prince?
                        Protectors are but ſubiects, and this ſtaffe
                        But ſhewes me vnder whoſe command I am.
                        Is this our hindrance that our mother firſt
                        Swell'd with another? what her wombe denyde
                        Our head ſhall giue, or we will looſe our head,
                        What was her labour to a Crowne? Perhaps
                        A monſter might haue fill'd her firſt, a thing
                        Of royall prodegy, and ſhould this thing
                        Grow to be hooted to a crowne before vs?
                        Or if that Crownes be due to the moſt yeares,
                        Why ſhould the Nephew be the Vncles Lord?
                        And Lawes of Nations conquer thoſe of Nature?
                        Nature intended Sov'raignty to them
                        Of ſoueraigne vnderſtanding; to the reſt,
                        How euer aged, but ſubiection,
                        Which Iſabella would detaine vs in:
                        And whilſt ſhe truſts to Naples, our ſad brow
                        May ſooner weare willow, then Diadems.
E
                                 •
                              ter Belgioſa
                        
                        Return'd ſo ſoone, my Belgioſa? thankes,
                        Before I heare thy meſſage, for thy haſt.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     
                        
                           •
                        el.
                     
                        My Lord, our ſudden comming into France,
                        
                        Left fame behind vs, where ariu'd, we crau'd
                        A priuate audience?
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           •
                        f.
                     
                        But had you it?
                        Did not our enemies ſharpe eſpies deſery
                        The depth of our hid counſells?
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           •
                        el.
                     
                        They might firſt
                        Deſery the ſubtill path of a ſwift ſhip,
                        The voyage of a bullet, or of thought,
                        Before your more myſterious purpoſes?
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           •
                        f.
                     
                        Then ſince we are alone, and in a place
                        Free from the bold intruſion of an eye,
                        Feigne Vs the Prince to whom we ſent you forth,
                        And ſpeake our Embaſſy vnto our ſelfe.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           •
                        el.
                     
                        Great Prince, to haue the offer of a Crowne
                        Is rare, and your felicity: my Lord,
                        
                           Millans Protector, but your ſeruant, knowing
                        The ancient right your predeceſſors had
                        In vſurpt Naples, by vs wooes your Grace
                        (Conſider vnto what he wooes your Grace)
                        Not to maintaine his pow'r, but make your owne,
                        To take a Kingdome that e'ne ſighes for you.
                        So ſhall the infamy of a loſt crowne
                        Rot in the earth with your dead Anceſtors,
                        And the recouery reuiue their names
                        To waite vpon your triumph with your foes:
                        For ſo much iuſtice needs no other power,
                        And yet ſuch is your pow'r, that it is able
                        To make what euer you ſhould fancy, iuſt:
                        But that your vertue is aboue that pow'r.
                        I will not call you vſurer of Fame,
                        By this large act, when the aſtoniſht world
                        Now fifty Ages off from vs, ſhall reade
                        Not in the boaſtings of a painted tombe
                        
                           (The flatteries of great rottenneſſe) but your 
                              〈…〉
                           
                        
                        Writ in 
                              〈…〉
                           s true Characters,
                        For making conquer'd Crownes the 
                              •
                           udiments
                        Of your victorious infancy i
                              •
                            armes,
                        When France ſhall know no other Charlemaign
                                 •
                              .
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     But ſhould we faile in the attempt? what then?
                  
                  
                     Belg.
                     
                        Can Heau'n faile Iuſtice? or thoſe pow'rs commit
                        Sinnes which they puniſh? O my gracious Lord
                        Sinne not with that weake thought: but if they ſhould
                        
                           Sforza will neuer:
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        He is alwaies noble,
                        But hee'l vndoe vs with a benefit,
                        To giue a kingdome is aboue requitall.
                     
                  
                  
                     Belg.
                     
                        His hopes are but the prayſe of honeſt deeds,
                        If in the rereward of your ſpreading Fame,
                        That fils all mouthes, ſome happy tongue may glance
                        At him, as a poore engine of your glory,
                        That could impart, but no
                              •
                            poſſeſſe a Fame.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        Excellent man, if to this welcome ſpeech
                        Thou giu'ſt as faire an anſwer.
                     
                  
                  
                     Bel.
                     
                        This in briefe
                        After ſome ſcruple, and a little pauſe
                        He whiſper'd he would come.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        Exactly done.
                        But leaue vs now, my noble Belgioſa,
                        
                        Till we may ſtudy a reward for thee.

                              
                                 •
                              x. Belg.
                        
                        The twilight haſtens, when Vitellio
                        
                        And Malateſta one of an high truſt
E
                                 〈…〉
                               Vitell. &amp; 
                                 〈…〉
                              .
                        
                        With our fond Nephew, promiſed conference.
                        And here they are. Is it decreed braue friends▪
                        
                        Shall it be ſwiftly done
                              •
                            nay, tis no matter,
                        Your colour ſayes you dare not.
                     
                  
                  
                     Vit.
                     
                        It lyes then:
                        If that my colour ſhew me diſobedient
                        
                           To my good Lord, be I for euer pale:
                        But when ſhall Galeazzoes wiſh'd-for death
                        Shew we dare ſomewhat?
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           •
                        f.
                     
                        We would gladly haue
                        A poyſon teach him linger to his death,
                        And a month hence we ſhall expect his knell.
Ex.
                        
                        Now are we entred, and now to retire
                        Were the worſe treaſon: like an inrag'd fire
                        The more we are oppos'd, the more wee'l ſpred
                        And make our foes our fewell: to be head
                        Wee'l cut off any member, and condemne
                        Vertue of folly for a Diadem,
                        Baniſh Religion, and make blood as cheape
                        As when two Armies turn'd into one heape
                        Of carcaſſes, lye grou ling, what care we
                        For the ſlight tainture of diſloyalty?
                        None will commend the race till it be run,
                        And theſe are deeds not prais'd till they are done.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scena tertia.
                  Iulian
                        •
                     , Picinino.
                  
                     
                        
                           •
                        ul.
                     My Picinino, holds this ſad newes true?
                  
                  
                     Pici.
                     
                        My Iuliano, yes; tis in each voyce
                        That ſome perſwaſion flatt'ring Ferdinand,
                        
                        That the French iourney was but a report,
                        Made him reuoke Alphonſo, his braue ſonne,
                        Who with an Army had indanger'd vs:
                        For the wiſe old man fearing, a deepe feare
                        Might arme an enemy, elſe too weake for him,
                        And make vs haſten the French warre, gaue o're
                        
                           His warre with vs: but when he vnderſtands
                        That all this qui
                              •
                           t does not purchaſe peace,
                        The coozen'd Prince ſeekes the ſure peace of death,
                        And leaues his ruine to deſtroy his ſonne.
                     
                  
                  
                     Iul.
                     
                        Will the French come? then prethee, Death, come too.
                        Why ſhould our eyes dull'd to all other ſights
                        By Age and ſorrow, be reſeru'd for ſight
                        Of warre and ſorrow? ô diſcourteous heau'ns!
                        Why haue you dally'd with vs to white hayres?
                        Why kept till this time, muſt we periſh now?
                        O wherefore are we come ſo neere the graue
                        And are not in it yet? yet pardon me
                        Good heau'n, your acts are aboue queſtion:
                        Yet I may ſhed theſe teares for Italy;
                        
                        Slaue of that world, which once, her valour ſlau'd,
                        Reſtoring backe her triumph's with her ſpoyle,
                        Diſtracted in herſelfe, and onely fit
                        To make a bankrout Poet heale his credit
                        With matter for freſh Tragedies.
                     
                  
                  
                     Pic.
                     
                        Good heau'n!
                        Is this to eaſe misfortune, or increaſe it?
                        If Paſſion could whine out felicity,
                        Or plenteous teares could drowne vnhappineſſe,
                        I haue eyes too, and they containe their ſhowres,
                        Nor would I ere be niggard of a Griefe.
                        But teares being onely teares, an eaſie de
                              •
                           
                        
                        Of childiſh eyes, and all the reſt of Griefe
                        Commanding ſmiles, more then Compaſſion,
                        I thanke my Genius I am reſolute
                        To laugh at Fortune when ſhe is moſt angry▪
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Iul.
                     
                        Such laughter may haue little mirth in it,
                        And I ſhall haue more comfort in a teare.
                     
                  
                  
                     Pic.
                     
                        You may, good Fountaine, y
                              ••
                           , droppe on, to ſoe,
                        If ſo much moyſture will reuiue thy cheekes
                        
                           Whilſt Ile be yong with laughter. I am he
                        That feares a ſorrow, more then miſery.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scena quarta.
                  
                     
                        Ʋitellio.
                     
                        THis is the place, and this the time: good heau'n!
                        What an odd place, and what an vncouth time?
                        Had I beene hyr'd to murther Sforza here,
                        Hell could not prompt more fit occaſion.
                        I like nor it, nor him: but here he comes.
                     
                  
                  Ent. Sforza.
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        VVelcome Vitellio, thy haſt is welcome:
                        Nay complement with him, whom thou wouldſt kill,
                        Be free to vs as we doe know thee true.
                        Speak, yet I need not bid thee, for thine eye
                        Sparkles a ioyfull anſwer. It is done.
                     
                  
                  
                     Vit.
                     
                        Tis done my Lord, and now my Lord, 'tis told
                        (That Galeazzo is no more a man)
                        And with an euen ſcruple, for to me
                        The act's as eaſie as relation.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        Thou ſpeak'ſt true manhood: 'tis thy art alone
                        That giues vs certaine honour: there are ſome
                        Striue for Aeternity with loſſe of life,
                        At leaſt with hazard of the loſſe of it,
                        And thinke they are reueng'd when they are kill'd?
                        Theſe are our valiant duelliſts, and theſe
                        Doe bleed whilſt we doe conquer▪ heale their wounds,
                        VVhilſt we receiue none: then, at laſt, vnfold
                        (Man of deepe Art, that canſt preuent the Fates,
                        And cut a thread, which they had thought to ſpunne
                        Fourty yeares yonger) thy wiſe myſteries.
                        
                           Thy conſtant, 
                              〈…〉
                            failing 
                              〈…〉
                           ,
                        Which cauſe a death, without a feare of death,
                     
                  
                  
                     Vit.
                     
                        Here are ſome drugs, but of theſe ſome, not one
                        But can command a life where ere it is,
                        And ruinate the ſtrongeſt workemanſhip
                        That Heau'n ere brag'd to haue compos'd of Earth.
                        Powders of ſpeedy Fate, but aboue all
                        The inſtruments, which make me neere to death
                        Of ſuch indear'd familiarity,
                        This glaſſe has nimbleſt operation:
                        Whoſe liquor caſt vpon the face of man
                        Straight du
                              •
                           ls him to an euerlaſting ſleepe.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        Is this the liquor of Aeternity?

                              Ʋitellio fall as dead▪
                           
                        
                        Then take thy 
                              •
                           ethe, and goe ſleepe for euer.
                     
                  
                  
                     Mal.
                     
                        I am deceiu'd, or eſſe this is the place
Enter Mal
                                 ••
                              .
                        
                        Which Sforza chooſeth when he is alone.
                        Yes, this is it.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        What Malateſta come?
                        What Deuill brought him hither? O croſſe ſtarres▪
                        
                        Be ſudden, Sforza, now, or thou art loſt:
                        He muſt beleeue out guilt was accident.
M
                                 •
                               fa
                                 •••
                               vpon Ʋitellio.
                        
                        Speake, my Vitellio▪
                            O tune thy lips
                        But to one ſyllable, but to one groane
                        And I am ſatisfi'd.
                     
                  
                  
                     Mal.
                     
                        What fight is here?
                        
                           Vitellio dead, and 
                              
                                 •
                              forza tur'nd a Mourner?
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        Shouldſt thou dye thus, how would my name be 
                              •
                           oyl
                              •
                           
                           ▪
                        
                        For though I am at guiltleſſe of thy death,
                        As Innocence, or if there be a name
                        That hath leſſe beeing: yet the enuious world
                        Will quit curft Fortune of ſo great a crime,
                        And giue it me: yet ſpeake.
                     
                  
                  
                     Mal.
                     
                        I'
                              〈…〉
                            my Lord,
                        To aske your 
                              〈…〉
                            when 
                              〈…〉
                            chanc
                              •
                           
                        
                        
                           Firſt frighted Heau'n?
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        Now, Malateſta, now▪
                        
                        When could vnhappineſſe ra
                              ••
                           ne ſo, but now?
                        As if he meant to be before his Lord,
                        He had no ſooner told the Prince muſt dye,
                        But he ſtraight dy'd.
                     
                  
                  
                     Mal.
                     
                        Then courage, my good Lord.
                        Since it is thus, make the beſt vſe of it:
                        For now you need not feare to be reueal'd,
                        When one mouth's ſtopt, and th'other is your owne:
                        But ſince your laſt retyrement, we haue beene
                        Inſtructed by the ſpeed of frequent Poaſts,
                        Of the a riuall of the King of France.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        With thankes, a while, my Malateſta, leaue vs.

                              
                                 •
                              x.
                        
                        Why ſhould we longer thinke of other pow'rs,
                        And not bring offrings now to our owne braine?
                        Which giues vs Agents of all kinds of men,
                        And Kings alwell as poys'ners: this w
                              ••
                           e King
                        Muſt trouble Naples, who would trouble vs,
                        Diuert inuaſions which are yet not made,
                        And thus ou
                              •
                            ends are cheapely brought about,
                        We onely at the charge of plott: they fight,
                        And Galiazzo dyes, whom either King
                        Were they not thus intangled, would preſerue:
                        We ſhall be conquerors without fighting thus,
                        And their poore ſwords ſhall cut a way for vs.
S
                                 •
                              rg
                                 ••
                               Vitellio.
                        
                        I'me for you France.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Vit.
                     
                        And I am for you, Sforza,
                        
                        Not poyſon'd yet, vnleſſe 'twere by thy teare
                              •
                           .
                        The other liquor had an Antid
                              ••
                           e.
                        Happy ſuſpect! had I beene credulous
                        And thought his loue as free as it would ſeeme
                        I had not beene, diſtruſt has ranſom'd me.
                        But Malateſta is intr
                              •
                           pp'd, I know
                        
                           
                           Sforza for nothing did not aske the skill▪
                        
                        My equall villaine p
                              •••
                           ſhes, and I
                        Thus being acceſſary to his death
                        May ſinne to Innocence, by poaſting off
                        The Princes fate to him: whilſt a diſguiſe
                        Shall keepe aliue the fame that I am dead.
                        And thus halfe truth ſhall come to light, and I,
                        Be wiſely cleer'd by double villany.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        ••
                     
                     ▪
                  
               
               
                  Scena quinta.
                  Caiazzo, Sanſeuerin, Maluezzo.
                  
                     Sanſ.
                     
                        AS I am noble, 'twas a glorious ſight,
                        To ſee two Princes, in their State at once:
                        As if two Sunnes had harmleſly conſpir'd
                        To beautifie, and not to fright the Heau'ns.
                        Why ſhould the formall nicety of State
                        Debarre theſe often enter
                              •
                           iewes? I thinke
                        They would be medicine againſt Tyranny:
                        For, when a Prince ſees all things vnder him,
                        Heads of eternall nakedneſſe, and men
                        That make their glory of their ſeruitude▪
                        
                        He thinkes hee's vncontroulable, that none
                        Without a ſaucy imputation
                        Dares warne him to his duty: but ſuppoſe
                        An equall Maieſty ſhould once become
                        His vſuall obiect, one, whoſe vncheck't blood
                        Runnes full as high as 
                              〈◊〉
                           , then he does learne,
                        That ther's a Common-wealth of Princes too,
                        Not one ſole Monarch▪
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Cai.
                     
                        Yet, Sanſeuerin,
                        
                        If you obſeru'd ſome clouds obſcur'd both Sunnes,
                        
                           For, when they ſmil'd moſt freely, and expreſt
                        Their neereſt friendſhip by a ſtrict embrace,
                        They lookt ſo iealouſly, as if they fear'd
                        A cloſer ſtab: and then the King tooke leaue
                        With that exceſſe of haſt, that one would thinke
                        (After this eager preparation,)
                        He did intend his iourney to leaue vs,
                        Not to winne Naples.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Mal.
                     
                        'Tis a dangerous time,
                        (And yet I ſeeme to croſſe the truth I ſpeake
                        When I not feare to call't a dangerous time)
                        
                           Sforza is ouer-wiſe, and ſo attempts
                        Vpon the confidence of his owne braine
                        (A braine, though wiſe, yet I may ſafely ſay,
                        Within the poſſibilitie of error)
                        Things, that can onely hap by miracle
                        To any good.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sanſ.
                     
                        Why, what can happen ill?
                        Feare you a warre? and what's to be fear'd there?
                        Leaſt that a mortall dy, leaſt that the life
                        Due to a knotty gout, or grating ſtone,
                        Haue a more eaſie period by the ſword.
                        Let them feare warre, who feare to ſee their gold▪
                        
                        Leſt that the Sunne ſhould haue a ſight with them▪
                        
                        Holding ſo much of Earth, th'are turn'd to it,
                        Who haue no more life then their duity akers,
                        Men, I may ſay, in the worſt part of men.
                        And why like theſe runne we an idle race
                        Of threeſcore yeares, and then ſneake to a Death?
                        Whilſt ſouldiers maſter their mortality
                        And dye by men, if that at all they dye.
                        
                           Malvezzo know, when all things ſifted are,
                        Peace onely pleaſeth them that ne're knew warre.
                     
                  
               
            
            
               
               Actus ſecundi
               
                  Scena prima.
                  Iuliano, Picinino.
                  
                     Iul.
                     HEard you the generall whiſp'ring▪
                     
                  
                  
                     Pic.
                     No, what i
                           〈…〉
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Iul.
                     The Duke is ill.—
                  
                  
                     Pic.
                     And doe they whiſper that▪
                     
                  
                  
                     Iul.
                     Yes: and, they ſay, he has ſtrange fits.
                  
                  
                     Pic.
                     
                        How ſtrange
                        Is poyſon ſtrange in Italy▪
                            why, know,
                        As Princes liue aboue the vulgar, ſo
                        Their death has a Prerogatiue: meane men
                        May dreame away their time to foureſcore yeares,
                        And when their rotten ioynts drop to their duſt▪
                        
                        Onely ſome triuiall infirmity,
                        A Pal
                              •
                           ie, or an Aguebeares the blame:
                        But'tis not State for Princes to be old,
                        And yet they muſt not be ſuppos'd to dye
                        By the reſpectleſſe treaſon of diſeaſe,
                        But by ſome ſtrange vnheard▪ of accident
                        That Fate did neuer dreame of: but no more,
                        You know Vitellio, and the height of grace
                        
                           Sforza has ſhew'd him▪ 'tis ſuſpitious
                        When wiſedome flatters villany: then come,
                        Let vs be priuate, and diſcourſe ſome treaſon.
                     
                  
                  
                     Enter, after ſolemne Muſick, Sforza, Sanſeuerin, Caiazzo, and Souldiers: when after ſome priuate whiſp'ring they depart ſeuerall waies.
                  
                     Iul.
                     But ſtay, my Picinino, who are here?
                  
                  
                     Pic.
                     
                        O the grand favorite, Sanſeuerin,
                        
                        A moſt full bubble, valiant vanity:
                        That in high termes can ſweare downe fortreſſes,
                        Blow away Armies with a pow'rfull breath,
                        And ſpoyle the enemy before he ſees him:
                        But when he comes to action, lye as ſtill,
                        As in the tale, that lumpiſh King of Frogs,
                        Which Ioue did giue them in his merriment.
                        Were tilting valour, I ne're knew a man
                        Of larger worth: could he but breake the rankes
                        Of enemies aſwell as he does ſpeares,
                        
                           Millan ne're ſaw a brauer Generall.
                        But there's his brother too.
                     
                  
                  
                     Iul.
                     I, thats the man.
                  
                  
                     Pic.
                     
                        (Tis wonder we can know ſo much of him)
                        He that can ſound the depth of that ſly braine
                        Has a large plummet, truſt me Iulian,
                        
                        An hundred Lawyers make vp that one head,
                        And ſcarcely too: quicke Proteus to him,
                        To this Caiazzo was an Ideot,
                        A plaine flat Ideot, I tell thee man,
                        
                           Meander neuer knew ſo many windings▪
                        
                        If, as they ſay, an Aemulation
                        Is bred by likeneſſe, 
                              •
                            doe wonder much
                        How Sforza is induc'd to imploy him.
                        Who has more Deuill in him, then himſelfe.
                     
                  
                  
                     Iul.
                     
                        But why is this imployment? why theſe Armes?
                        
                           When all but Naples are our friends, and they
                        Not able now to ſhew themſelues our foes,
                        Ingag'd, and almoſt loſt in the French warre.
                     
                  
                  
                     Pic.
                     
                        Trickes, Iuliano, Statiſts call them Arts,
                        Not to be fado
                              •
                           'd by a vulgar reach:
                        But though I want the villany to know,
                        Yet I haue ſo much ſpleene to laugh at them;
                        And take a comfort in this plainer ſenſe:
                        No ſubtilty can coozen Prouidence.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scena ſecunda.
                  Aſcanio, Galeazzo, Iſabella, Iulia.
                  
                     Aſc.
                     HOw reſts the Prince?
                  
                  
                     Iſab.
                     
                        O my good Lord, he reſts▪
                        
                        But 'tis a quiet, ſuch as the Seas haue,
                        When that the winds haue ſpent their violence,
                        And out of impotence beſtow a calme:
                        'Tis more a death, then ſlumber, you may ſee
                        His ſenſes rather weary, then at reſt.
                     
                  
                  
                     Aſc.
                     Are then his 
                           •
                        its ſo raging?
                  
                  
                     Iſab.
                     
                        Nothing elſe,
                        Should he but wake, youde thinke two Armies met▪
                        
                        And ſtroue together for the loudeſt ſhout.
                        Diſeaſe has ſpred herſelfe ore all his parts,
                        And onely ſpar'd his tongue, as if ſome ſtarre
                        Not knowing otherwiſe to cleare it ſelfe
                        From imputation of tyranny,
                        For ſuch exact plaguing of Innocence
                        
                           Had left him that to curſe withall, that ſo
                        To all that heard his fury, he might ſeeme
                        To be thus tortur'd for his Blaſphemy.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        al.
                     Water, ſome water.
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        ab.
                     Now the fit beginnes:
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        al.
                     
                        Some of my ſlaues runne, and exhauſt the 
                              •
                           o,
                        Charge him no more to vent his idle ſtreames
                        Into the glutted maine, but rather poure
                        All his moyſt mouths on me: d'yee ſtare, begone,
                        Vſe not your eyes at all, vnleſſe to weepe:
                        And that, not teares of ſorrow; but of helpe,
                        Such as may coole me.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        c.
                     
                        Patience, ſweet Prince,
                        Adde not vnto the fire of your diſeaſe,
                        The heat of paſſion.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        l.
                     
                        What red thing is this?
                        Ha, Iſabella, tell me.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈◊〉
                        
                     
                     
                        'Tis your vncle.
                        The noble Prince Aſcanio.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        l.
                     
                        'Tis falſe;
                        He is nor Prince, nor noble: hearke you friends,
                        He talkes of Paſſion, and of Patience,
                        Let him diſcourſe of Aetna, or Veſuuius,
                        
                        Or of a greater heat then I doe feele,
                        And I will anſwer him: Patience to me?
                        Goe bid rough ſeas be patient.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        c.
                     
                        He growes worſe,
                        And oppoſition does inflame him more:
                        Me thinkes I ſee his eye-lids faintly ſtriue,
                        Againſt Deaths cloſing.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        l.
                     
                        O! my ioynts are fire,
                        Why does not heau'n ſhed Cataracts, and lowr
                              •
                           
                        
                        Once to my comfort? are they hot as I,
                        Haue they no moyſture, for a Suppliant?
                        
                           Then, though hot heau'n oppoſe, when once my br
                              〈…〉
                           
                        
                        Hath left this corps, Ile haue a cold by death.
                     
                  
                  
                     Iſ.
                     
                        Heard you that grone my Lord—ô he is dead:
                        Cracke then ye tardy heart ſtrings, quickly cracke,
                        And giue me leaue to ouer-take the fligh▪
                        
                        Of my dead husband.
                     
                  
                  
                     Aſc.
                     
                        What is paſt our helpe,
                        Let it be paſt our griefe: tis fortitude
                        To ſuffer chances counterbuffes as one
                        That by his expectation had deceiu'd
                        All her faint threatnings: till this 
                              •
                           adder time
                        Your life has had one conſtant ſcene of ioy,
                        Which here is interrupted: you ſhould thanke
                        The heau'ns becauſe they were not tedious
                        In their delights: for this variety.
                        As hunger prayſeth feaſts, ſo it may be
                        Youle loue ioy better for this miſery.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scena tertia.
                  Sforza, Beatrice.
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        HOW couetous thou art to learne miſhap?
                        
                           Beatrice the anſwer kills thee.
                     
                  
                  
                     Bet.
                     
                        Kill me then,
                        But not deny me.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        Deareſt, I am loſt,
                        And in my ruine, thou.
                     
                  
                  
                     Bet.
                     
                        I would be ſo,
                        Safety were ruine were it otherwiſe.
                        Yet tell me Sforza, how are you ſo loſt?
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        O what a buſie torture woman is!
                        I muſt ſay ſomewhat, but the maine is ſilence,
                        
                           Vitellioes loſſe, yes, that hathloſt me too:
                        
                           No ſooner kill'd then loſt, ſo ſtrangely gone,
                        As if the dead had learnt a motion
                        So to conuey themſelues vnto the graue.
                        Will you be ſtill vnkind?
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈◊〉
                        
                     
                     
                        Thou ſhalt heare all▪
                        
                        The French haue conquer'd Naples, and which drawes
                        Blood from our ſoule, without a drop of blood:
                        When thus we plotted it, that when both Kings
                        Had wearied out themſelues with equall ſlaughter,
                        And here Alphonſo totter'd, and there Charles;
                        
                        When loſſe had ceiz'd the conqueror, then we
                        Would haue amaz'd the conqueror afreſh
                        With new alarmes: when by the flattery
                        Of chance, France gets a kingdome without blood,
                        And by dry victory has vndone a plot
                        Worth many Kingdomes: I preſum'd on this,
                        
                           Naples had ſouldiers enough to laſt
                        Killing a yeare, in which ſpace, we reſolu'd
                        To arme all Italy againſt the French,
                        And cunningly driue out, whom we call'd in:
                        Which, ere we could accompliſh, is diſclos'd,
                        And conqu'ring France intends to hinder it,
                        By our inuaſion: ô my policy!
                        Muſt I be wounded with the ſword I gaue?
                        And find thoſe enemies, whom onely I
                        Enabled to my iniury? well; heau'n,
                        Your kindneſſe is a miracle ſometime,
                        Beyond all reaſon, but your curſe is wit,
Enter Aſcan.
                        
                        My fault is my faults puniſher.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        c.
                     
                        Long life,
                        And happy to our Duke.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈◊〉
                        
                     
                     
                        How my Aſcanio?
                        
                        Recall thy ſelfe, good Cardinall, what Duke?
                        Whilſt Galeazzo liues?
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     Aſ
                           •
                        .
                     
                        Moſt truly Duke,
                        For Galeazzo's dead.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        Alas, poore child,
                        I could haue wiſh'd thee longer life, but ſince
                        Heau'ns willis otherwiſe, twere blaſphemy
                        To ſtorme at that which is the will of heau'n.
                        I hate that impotent rebellion.
                     
                  
                  Enter Sanſen.
                  
                     Sanſ.
                     
                        My Lord, ſo croſſe was Fortune, that you were
                        Made almoſt banqu'rout by a too much thrift:
                        For when you had diſcharg'd thoſe numerous troope
                              •
                           ,
                        Whoſe charges lay as hard vpon the State
                        As an inuaſion could, then Orleance mou'd
                        And ſtole N
                                 •
                              uarra, which diſaſtrous newes
                        So heated the remainder of your troopes
                        (As if you had added to their valour more,
                        When you abated from their multitudes)
                        That by a nimble victory, they made
                        His conqueſt be his priſon.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        Noble friend
                        Stand thou, and our State ſtands: ô why doe men
                        Cry out on Age, on eating Age? as though
                        Our many griefes were from our many yeares,
                        And the laſt times were worſt: we rather find
                        That nothing is ſo dangerous to Kings
                        As a yong Principality: for tis
                        With them almoſt as with yong plants, which yeeld
                        Vnto the leaſt intreaty of the wind,
                        And need no ſtronger blaſt, but gaining Age
                        Scarce ſtoope to thunder: may we once ariſe
                        Vnto this happy firmeneſſe of eſtate,
                        This bleſt maturity of Prince, we ſtand
                        Fearleſſe of fall, but if heauen enuy vs
                        And haue decreed our fuine with our riſing,
                        Yet ſuch weele haue it voyde of all baſe feares
                        Our foes ſhall grieue our ruine was not theirs.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  Scena quarta.
                  Caiazzo, Belgioſa, Maluezzo.
                  
                     Mal.
                     
                        MY Lords, ſince we are met ſo happily,
                        (If you eſteeme me not too bo
                              •
                           d, to aske
                        The ſtory of your high fam'd actions)
                              •
                           
                        
                        Bleſſe me with the Relation.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           •
                        ai.
                     
                        I much feare
                        Mine are not worthy your attention:
                        Yet if it pleaſe you, noble Belgioſa,
                        
                        (Becauſe my ſtory will depend on that)
                        To ſhew the reaſon why the giddy French,
                        So ſtrangely left their conqueſt: ſuch your pow'r,
                        Such a full conqueſt haue you of your friend,
                        I'le ſhame my ſelfe for your content.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        l.
                     
                        Then, thus:
                        From vs France hurry'd thorow Lumbardy
                        
                        And fled to conquer, who had ſeene that haſt
                        Would eaſily ſuppos'd it to haue beene
                        Rather a flight then an inuaſion.
                        The Pope quakes at the progreſſe, and admits
                        Yong Ferd'nand into Rome, that if the French
                        Should dare a fight, they might find Naples there.
                        
                           France ſlights that fainter oppoſition,
                        And ſpeakes his ſcorne in thunder, Naples flyes,
                        And all his army hath no other vſe
                        Then to become vnwilling harbingers
                        To ſhew their lodgings to the conqu'ring French▪
                        
                        Who like fierce winds that ſweepe away their lets,
                        Or like incroaching tydes, take 
                              •
                           wiftly in
                        The offer'd Countries, not defended, now
                        Saint German yeelds, and ſawcy Capua
                        
                        
                           That dar'd a competition once with Rome,
                        
                        
                           Averſa takes the preſident, and now
                        The Kng of Naples finds home foes, and ſuch
                        As durſt be valiant againſt their Prince,
                        And vſe their fond armes in a mutiny,
                        Which were not ſafe enough for a defence.
                        He taking the aduantage of thou crime
                        Vnconquer'd by the French, to theſe he yeelds,
                        And chuſeth rather to become no Prince
                        Then keepe the Crowne, which they would take away.
                     
                  
                  
                     Mal.
                     What was the iſſue?
                  
                  
                     Bel.
                     
                        Strangely pittifull:
                        He that had Nauies yeſterday, has now
                        Scarce a barke left him, ſearce a plan
                              •
                           e or two,
                        To truſt him to the mercy of the Seas,
                        The Seas more courteous then the multitude:
                        In which he makes for Iſchia, and leaues
                        His enemy his ſucceſſor.
                     
                  
                  
                     Cai.
                     
                        And he
                        (As I haue ſeene ſome wav'ring amoriſt)
                        Neglects his conqueſt for the 
                              •
                           a
                              ••
                           neſſe,
                        For when twas certaine F
                                 •
                              r 
                                 •••
                              a
                                 •
                              d was fled,
                        Whilſt they might iuſtly yet feare his returne,
                        The French returne, as if they meant to try
                        Which would be ſooneſt weary of the haſt,
                        Who had the ſwifter pace to 
                              〈…〉
                            away:
                     
                  
                  
                     Bel.
                     
                        That is 
                              〈…〉
                            act of new gouernors,
                        Such ſtories are as an
                              〈…〉
                            as the world.
                        Till they doe try what they can doe, they thinke
                        They may doe all things, their firſt act is 
                              •••••
                           
                        
                        (As if they meant 
                              〈…〉
                            to kill then 
                              •
                           a
                              •
                           g
                              ••
                           )
                        It matters not vpon what ground▪ there is
                        Pretence enough to quit a conqu
                              ••
                           o
                              •
                           
                        
                        From the leaſt ſhew of 
                              〈…〉
                           y: but then
                        
                           VVhen they haue felt the leaſt of warres extreames
                        They raue, they faint, they croſſe what they firſt did,
                        And are e'ne weary of a victory.
                     
                  
                  
                     Cai.
                     
                        
                           France made this certaine truth, who in his brags
                        Had ſworne the fall of Mahomet: but now
                        VVhen he might heare the groanes of Graecia
                        
                        Deliuer'd by the ecchoes of their ſea,
                        To make them more, he thinkes on a retreat,
                        And chuſeth home before a victory▪
                        
                        It was a vally, where our Taro laues
                        The root of Appe
                              •
                           nine, and a large plaine
                        Spheard with a row of ſwelling Earth makes warre
                        A ſpatious Amphitheater: where we
                        Stayd for their comming; when mature aduice
                        That crownes moſt actions, ſtrangely iniur'd vs,
                        For raſhneſſe would haue ſtole a victory
                        VVhich tedious conſultation gaue away.
                        Succeſſe had ſmil'd on our temerity
                        Had we aſſaulted them vpon the hills
                        And added to the mountaines with the French.
                        But I am tedious: onely our vanne fought,
                        And twas the Frenchmens victory to reſiſt:
                        Both were o'recome, both conquerors, for they
                        Still kept the field, and wee ſtill kept the prey.
                     
                  
                  
                     Bel.
                     
                        O what is valour ioyn'd with Modeſty!
                        This conquers both your Fortune and your skill.
                        Should you but write a ſtory; and profeſſe
                        That pureneſſe from all paſſion which y'aue ſhowne.
                        You would be credited, though twere your owne.
                        But what reward is't to be but beleeu'd?
                        You ſhall be euer prays'd: what you haue done
                        Feares neither enuy, nor obliuion:
                        And for this act ſucceſſion ſhall ſee
                        
                           Caiazzo as long-liu'd as Italy▪
                           
                        
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  Scena quinta.
                  
                     
                        Vitellio diſguiſed.
                     
                        I Wonder Malateſta ſtill ſuruiues:
                        Sure Sforza has forgot himſelfe; my death
                        Does but halfe cleare him, and if th'other liue,
                        He cannot looke for a full innocence.
                        It is not mercy, certainly: ô, no,
                        Mercy with him is folly: but t'may bee
                        He feares that had he kild vs both at once
                        Rumor would be too buſie, and all mouths
                        Would cry, that Chance had too much proiect in't.
                        This is the place of Deſtiny, 'tis here
                        
                           Sforza does actuate his bloody arts,
                        Miſtaking priuacy for innocence,
                        And thinkes hee's good, becauſe he is not ſeene▪
                        
                        Here muſt I wayte for a diſcouery.
                     
                  
                  Enter Sforza.
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        I muſt once more be cruell, yet not I,
                        This is the murther of Neceſſity:
                        But what has he deſeru'd, who has done nought
                        But what we charg'd, and ſo perform'd our thought?
                        Is Death due to Obedience 
                              〈…〉
                           can this hand
                        Yeeld to his Fate, that fe
                              ••
                           'd to his command?
                        Yet he, or I muſt periſh: ſhall I ſee
                        My life, my honor, my Aeternity▪
                        
                        Lye at his mercy, and be ſafe, ſo long
                        As he is pleas'd to temper his rude tongue?
                        Till he be drunke, or treacherous? Ile firſt
                        Study amongſt all actions, which is worſt
                        And ouer-act it▪ though our former deed
                        Was from ambition, this is yet from need:
                        
                           Death is too good reward for ſuch a ſlaue,
Enter Malateſta.
                        
                        And ſure there is no blabbing in the graue.
                        But here he comes: why are thy looks ſo grim?
                        Why, Malateſta, in thy 
                              •
                           urrow'd face
                        See I the ſignes of Anger, or of Griefe?
                        Command thy face to a more ſmiling forme,
                        That I may thinke thee pleas'd when thou doſt tell
                        What does diſpleaſe thee.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        al.
                     
                        'Twas a fooliſh dreame,
                        That ſtole my colour from my paler cheekes.
                        Laſt night I ſaw 
                              Ʋitellio.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈◊〉
                        .
                     
                        And what?
                        Canſt thou feare ſhadowes?
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        al.
                     
                        Yes if ſhadowes ſpeake,
                        If that their threatnings be ſubſtantiall.
                        From ſuch a paper as your Highneſſe holds,
                        He forc't me breath in Death.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        f.
                     
                        This Paper holds
                        A ſtrange perfume, of ſuch a cunning vertue,
                        That at a diſtance it ſcarce ſmels at all.
                        And at the noſe it gives the beſt of ſents.
                        Make the experiment:
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        al.
                     O! I am 
                           ••
                        aine.
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈◊〉
                        .
                     
                        Heau'ns what a ſtilneſſe here is? what a death
                        Of the whole man at once? the wandring eye
                        Now findes a ſtation, and the buſie pulſe
                        Is now for euer idle: where's the tongue
                        That but eu'n now could ſay as much as this,
                        When that the ſoule could prompt it? but e'en now
                        Here was a thing could ſpeake, and poiſon too,
                        That knew more wayes to kill, then euer Heau'n
                        Did to make man: and could his ſubtlety,
                        That could giue death, not know to keepe out death?
                        Fye, what a bulke it is, what a great lumpe
                        
                           Of Nothing, that ſhall loſe that nothing too?
                        What a dead toy is Man, when his thin breath
                        Flyes to its kindred Ayre? ô why at all
                        Did Heau'n beſtow, or why at all bereaue
                        Man of this Vapour of Eternity?
                        And muſt we one day be a ſtocke like this,
                        Fit onely to inrich the greedy Earth,
                        And fill an houſe of Death, perhaps before
                        We ſee the iſſue of another Plot?
                        Muſt we lye ſubiect to be trampled on,
                        By ſome, perhaps not Politicians?
                        Where's then our Wiſedome? our deepe Prouidence
                        Are they durt too? ô heau'ns! but if they are
                     
                     Enter ſome N
                           •
                        
                        groes to cary 
                           •
                        
                        way the body
                     
                        Or durt▪ or nothing, Ile enioy my fame.
                        And rottenneſſe ſhall ceize me, not my name.
                     
                  
                  
                     Vit.
                     
                        Are thoſe the Inſtrumens? well my black friends,
                        I eas'd you of a labour: all ſucceeds
                        According to the flatt'ry of my wiſh,
                        And my ſuſpition turnes to prophecy.
                        But my ſo bloody, and ſo wary Sforza,
                        
                        Your Agent's dead, but not your crime: 'twill out,
                        And by this carcaſſe: I will flye to France,
                        Divulge loud papers,—they are writ already,—
                        And here they are, theſe I will ſweare were found
                        In the dead pois'ners pockets: by this meanes
                        
                           Sforza's proclaim'd a murtherer, I'me freed,
                        And make it be his guilt, which was my deed.
                     
                  
                  
                     Ʋitellio going forth meets with Iſabella.
               
               
                  
                  Scena quinta.
                  
                     Ʋitellio, Iſabella, Julia.
                  
                     
                        
                           〈◊〉
                        
                     
                     MAdame I haue ſome newes of that import, That (if you pleaſe to command priuacy) Will both deſire, and fright your patience.
                  
                  
                     Iſ.
                     Be briefe.
                  
                  
                     Vit.
                     Firſt know I am Vitellio.
                     
                  
                  
                     Iſ.
                     
                        Thou art a villaine, and a pois'ner then,
                        Haſt thou a drugge for vs?
                     
                  
                  
                     Vit.
                     
                        Yes ſuch an one
                        Shall make you loue a poyſon: reade, and wonder.
                     
                  
                  
                     Iſ.
                     I doe: and more, how thou couldſt purchaſe this Without a guilt.
                  
                  
                     Vit.
                     
                        I did peruſe the ſpoyles
                        Of Malateſta's carcaſſe, whom I found
                        Moſt ſtrangely guilty, and as ſtrangely dead,
                        Whoſe pockets furniſht me with theſe inſtructions.
                     
                  
                  
                     Iſ.
                     
                        Thus we learne Murther from thy Fellony:
                        But what ſhould make me truſt a confeſt rogue?
                     
                  
                  
                     Vit.
                     
                        My villany: my credit is my crime:
                        Had not I ſtole, you had not vnderſtood.
                     
                  
                  
                     Iſ.
                     
                        I muſt beleeu't: but darſt thou poiſon well?
                        Commit a crime, which thou maiſt glory of?
                     
                  
                  
                     Vit.
                     On whom deare Lady?
                  
                  
                     Iſ.
                     
                        Nay I care not whom.
                        But I can giue reward to a wiſe crime.
                     
                  
                  
                     Vit.
                     
                        My quicke diſpatch ſhall make you gladly know
                        I vnderſtand, what you deſire, and hide.
                     
                  
                  Exit.
                  
                     Iſ.
                     
                        Now ſhould he poiſon Sforza. O fond hope!
                        That mak'ſt vs thinke all true that we deſire.
                        Should he betray vs now? for what? that we
                        
                           Intreated him to kill, we knew not whom.
                        By this expreſſion thus much I haue wonne:
                        I may be made, but cannot be vndone.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scena ſext
                        •
                     .
                  
                     Picinino.
                     
                        FOrtune is merry, and the heau'n diſpos'd
                        To play with me, I am turn'd Fauourite.
                        Me thinkes my haires aſham'd of their white hue
                        Should bluſh to youth: O how I could looke big,
                        Take Gyant ſtrides, doat on my louely ſelfe,
                        And talke as ſilly as any Lord.
                        To ſee the prettineſſe of action,
                        Of State-imployment: Sforza's to be crown'd,
                        And I muſt winne the popular ſuffrages.
                        Good Heau'ns! was euer ſuch a merry load
                        Impos'd on Man: ſome cry the times are ill,
                        Others could wiſh them better, and a third
                        Knowes how to make all well, but tels not how,
                        And, cauſe that he is ſilent, would be wiſe.
                        But in concluſion I doe finde them ready
                        (On ſuppoſition of no more expence,
                        And that their voice is ſu'd for, not their purſe)
                        To giue a luſty acclamation.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     Sforza, 3 Ambaſſadors, Caiazzo, Sanſeuerin, Maluezzo, as in proceſſion, they offer vp the French Banners at the Altar, whilſt this is ſung.
                  
                     Song.
                     
                        IO, Io, gladly ſing,
                        Till the Heau'n with wonder ring.
                        He is fled, let Millan ſay
                        Once more, he is fled, the day
                        Cleares againe, and makes vs ſee
                        A brauer light of victory.
                        Io, Io, &amp;c.
                     
                     
                        Yet he had before he fought
                        (By the ſpeedy warre of thought)
                        Conquer'd Italy, and ſo
                        Has haſten'd his owne ouerthrow.
                        Io, Io, &amp;c.
                     
                     
                        Henceforth let them learne to liue
                        In the peace, that home doth giue,
                        Nor againe ſo fondly raue,
                        To trauell for a forren graue.
                        Io, Io, &amp;c.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        Firſt we thanke Heau'n, by whoſe moſt gracious ayd
                        We haue the meanes, and reaſon to thanke you.
                        Now we beginne to lift vp our faint heads,
                        And entertaine, though ſcarce beleeue a peace:
                        Now Italy at length has loſt her yoake,
                        Which ſhe was wont to giue, but neuer beare,
                        And therefore wondred at the ſtrangeneſſe more
                        
                           Then at the weight of't: in this noble act
                        
                           Sforza claimes nothing but the happineſſe,
                        Which he acknowledges receiu'd from you.
                     
                  
                  
                     1 Amb.
                     
                     
                        Sforza's deſerts exceed the height of praiſe.
                  
                  
                     2 Amb.
                     
                     He has ſlau'd Italy by freeing it.
                  
                  
                     3 Amb.
                     
                     Millan muſt know him for her Romulus.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        We know our ſelfe ſo vnderneath this praiſe,
                        That could we but ſuſpect vntruth in you,
                        Wee'd call all this but mockery.
                     
                  
                  
                     Pic.
                     
                        D'yee doubt?
                        Make you a queſtion of the name of it?
                        Why call it as it is, plaine flattery.
                     
                  
                  
                     Caiaz.
                     
                        We wondred lately at the prouder French,
                        And gaue too high a valew to their acts:
                        VVhen in a ſerious eſtimation,
                        Their chiefeſt victory was of the miles,
                        And more a iourney then a warre: if they
                        Could gaine a fame by nimble trauelling,
                        How ſhall we reare a trophee to his name,
                        That made them goe farre faſter then they came?
                        For my part (though I know his Modeſty,
                        VVhich will refuſe the honours he deſerues)
                        I'de haue him forc'd vnto the gouernment,
                        To rule that happy land which he hath ſau'd.
                     
                  
                  
                     Omnes. A Sforza, a Sforza. Aſcanio crowns him.
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        
                           Sforza will ne're gaine ſay the gen'rall voice,
                        Your loue I like beyond your gift: kind Heau'ns!
                        Shew by my gouernments integrity
                        You were the peoples prompter, and I'le ſhew
                        (If you but actuate my iuſt deſires)
                        I onely am their Duke in goodneſſe: ſince
                        Millan hath choſe, it ſhall applaud her Prince.
                     
                  
               
            
            
               
               Actus tertii
               
                  Scena prima.
                  
                     Vmbra G
                           •
                        leatii.
                     
                        NO reſt in death? why then I ſee they erre
                        That giue a quiet to a ſepulcher.
                        'Tis our hard fate, nor can Man chuſe but dye,
                        But where Griefe is, is Immortality.
                        This drawes our iuiceleſſe bones to a new day,
                        From Lethes bankes, where we haue learnt the way,
                        (An eaſie learning) to returne our woes,
                        And laugh at our misfortunes in our foes.
                        Wee'll draw felicity out of our fall,
                        And make our ghoſt reuenge our Funerall.
                        That our dimme Eyes, and with pale death benighted,
                        May by reuenge be clear'd, and we be righted
                        (If other puniſhment ſhould come too 
                              •
                           low)
                        By the exacter iuſtice of our foe.
                        When being betray'd by them he truſted moſt,
                        He ſhall be pris'ner in a forren coaſt,
                        When wanting ſuſtenance, his teeth ſhall chaw
                        His armes for food, and their onee fe
                              •
                           ders gnaw.
                        When Hell ſhall haue but part of him, when he
                        That now triumphs ſhall be leſſe ghoſt then we.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  Scena ſecunda.
                  Sforza▪ Aſcanio.
                  
                     Aſc.
                     
                        SForza, you are vndone.
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        Why my Aſcanio?
                        
                        Fortune is fearfull of ſo foule a crime.
                     
                  
                  
                     Aſc.
                     
                        You durſt be bad, and yet improuident,
                        And ſo it is not Fortunes, but your crime.
                        Which ſhall I firſt beginne to blame? your fault
                        Or (pardon if I call it) Fooliſhneſſe:
                        I faint to thinke that you are paſt excuſe,
                        Both with the honeſt and the Politicke.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        Come neerer, my deare Cardinall, and tell
                        In eaſier termes what tis that troubles you:
                        Is Galeazzo's death divulg'd?
                     
                  
                  
                     Aſc.
                     
                        It is:
                        The time, the manner, and the murtherer,
                        Nor am I free from th'imputation:
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        You ſpeake what you ſuſpect, not what is true,
                        Does ſpeech come from the dead? can their dry'd nerues
                        Borrow a tongue for accuſation?
                        This is no other then the voice of Guilt,
                        The ſpeech of our home-executioner:
                        And yet I feare—and yet what ſhould I feare?
                        Bloud hath ſtrange organs to diſcourſe withall,
                        It is a clamorous Oratour, and then
Enter Sanſeuerin, Halberdeers &amp; Vitel.
                        
                        Euen Nature will exceed her ſelfe to tell
                        A crime ſo thwarting Nature.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sanſ.
                     
                        My good Lord,
                        Pardon the zeale of my intruſion,
                        I bring hid danger with me: 'twas my chance
                        As I was paſſing to the bedchamber,
                        
                           Iuſt at the doore to finde this muffled man,
                        VVaiting ſome trecherous opportunity.
                        Each circumſtance ſwell'd with ſuſpition,
                        The place, the time, the perſon, all did ſeeme
                        To beare a danger worthy of your feare,
                        At leaſt your wiſer diſquiſition.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        Thou art all goodneſſe, and deſeru'ſt of vs
                        Beyond the niggardly reward of thankes:
                        But what are you that thus be cloud your face,
                        VVho, not vnlike that ouer-baſhfull fowle,
He diſcourſe himſelfe.
                        
                        Delight in darkneſſe? Ha! Vitellio!
                        
                        The wonder is reſolu'd by a new wonder.
                     
                  
                  Ex. Sanſ.
                  
                     Vit.
                     
                        
                           Sforza I liue: d'yee ſtare? I liue: theſe words
                        Are not the fond deluſions of the Ayre,
                        As you officiouſly would gull your ſelfe;
                        But from a ſolid ſubſtance, had not we
Enter Sanſ. with two Negroes.
                        
                        Bin by your diligent ſpy too ſoone ſurpriz'd,
                        Before our proiects full maturity,
                        Thy death more fully ſhould haue prou'd my life.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        Foole that I was, who thought to take thy life
                        By that which nouriſht it: there's none ſo mad
                        Would poiſon Serpents, Ile worke ſurely now,
                        Once more Ile try your immortality.
                        Strangle the Monſter.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        it.
                     
                        'Twas a doubtfull chance
                        Within this houre who firſt ſhould owne thoſe words.
                        But, Tyrant, weary thy inuention
                        To finde variety of puniſhment,
                        Yet all that thou canſt doe, exceeds not this,
                        A pinne could doe as much: weake, ſilly Sforza,
                        
                        All thou canſt doe to me exceeds not that
                        Which I did on the perſon of thy Prince:
                        Diſeaſe would proue a better murtherer.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        f.
                     
                        Stop that malignant throat.—O my Aſcanio,
                        
                        
                           Thus muſt they toyle which worke an hight by bloud,
                        How I could wiſh an innocent deſcent
                        To new ſubiection? how I hate that wiſh
                        How ſcorne all thoughts that haue not danger in them▪
                        
                        Get vs more Remora's, ſweet Cardinall,
                        Or rather then to droope to Idleneſſe▪
                        
                        Wee'll worke to be no Prince, our ſelfe re-calling:
                        In riſing, moſt, ſome wit there is in falling.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scena tertia.
                  
                     Caiazzo.
                     
                        ASſiſt me, Hell, for I intend an Act,
                        Which ſhould your puny fiends but thinke vpon,
                        Would make their blacker cheekes receiue a bluſh,
                        Would giue a redneſſe which your weaker Fire
                        Had ne're that heating pow'r to worke in them:
                        An act, the Heau'ns did onely then declare
                        They would permit to be perform'd by man
                        When they created Night: for were all Day,
                        Could ſuch a Crime be as well ſeene as done,
                        Their Immortality might iuſtly feare,
                        Leſt all the guilt ſhould be remou'd on them,
                        As Idle, or as Cruell lookers on,
                        Whilſt Heau'n, on Earth did ſuffer: this blacke night
                        Muſt Iſabella dye, dye, by this hand:
                        This Chappell is her ordinary walke,
                        Diſcouer'd to me by her Iulia,
                        
                        Where when ſhe comes to ſee her husbands tombe,
                        This hand ſhall make her 
                              •
                           it for ſuch a roome.
                     
                  
                  
                     Enter Iſabella and Iulia with two torches, ſhee places them at either end of the Tome, &amp; Exit. Iſabella drawes towards the Tombe, and ſpeaks.
                  
                     Iſ.
                     
                        PRince of ſhades, (for vnto me
                        Still thou keep'ſt thy Maieſty)
                        If thou art not wholly loſt,
                        And there's ſomething in a Ghoſt:
                        Heare thy Iſabella's vow:
                        If hereafter I allow
                        Of a ſecond match, or know
                        Any man, but for a foe,
                        Sauing him that ſhall ingage
                        His reuenge vnto my rage:
                        (Heare iuſt Heau'ns) may I then be
                        Made another Ghoſt like thee,
                        May I dye, and neuer haue
                        What I viſit now, a Graue.
                     
                  
                  
                     Cai.
                     
                        O doe not heare her Heau'n, and kill me ſtraight
                        If I dare touch her: he that ſees thoſe eyes
                        And dares attempt to make thoſe eyes not ſee,
                        Has a blinde ſoule: burne clearer, you kind lights▪
                        
                        O doe not enuy me the ſight of her:
                        But what's there in a ſight? I muſt be briefe,
                        If not for loue, yet for ambition:
                        Her Mariage makes me greater then her Death,
                        And ſhe has taught me the condition.
                        Pardon, bright Angell, and returne the ſword,
                        Which Sforza made me ſweare to ſheath in you,
                        Into my boſome▪
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Iſ.
                     
                        No, obey your Prince,
                        
                           If you haue goodneſſe in you keepe your oath,
                        Murther is nothing vnto periury.
                     
                  
                  
                     Cai.
                     
                        By this faire hand you iniure me, and more
                        Then euer Sforza did: can you ſuppoſe
                        (Though you had heard the vowes he forc't me to)
                        I meant what I proteſted? that this hand
                        Which euer yet has vs'd a ſword for you,
                        Would vſe it now for your deſtruction.
                        Reuoke that thought, deare Lady, that harſh thought,
                        And let not ſo much ſweeter innocence
                        Make it ſelfe guilty by ſuſpition,
                        Suſpition of impoſſibilities.
                        Rather command, and you ſhall quickly ſee
                        That he, who would haue arm'd me againſt you,
                        Shall finde in his owne entrailes the iuſt ſteele.
                     
                  
                  
                     Iſ. aſide.
                     
                        What traps are theſe to catch the Innocent?
                        
                           Sforza I ſmell your proiect, 'tis too ranke.
                        My Lord, no more: your ſpeech is dangerous,
                        I muſt not heare it.
                     
                  
                  
                     Cai.
                     
                        You ſhall ſee it then:
                        Doe not beleeue me Madam till I'ue done,
                        Till I doe bring my credit in my armes,
                        The Traitors head, and when you ſee that time▪
                        
                        Confeſſe you owe your life vnto my crime.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scena quarta.
                  Picinino, Iuliano.
                  
                     Iul.
                     
                        VVHat will become of this declining ſtate?
                        Can we beleeue that the yet patient heau'n
                        Will any longer ſuffer? and not giue
                        Deſtruction as notorious as our crimes.
                        Awake, ſterne Iuſtice, and vnſheath thy ſword,
                        
                           The Scabberd will not heale vs, but the edge,
                        Nor is't enough to brandiſh, but to ſtrike:
                        Let then thy terrour giue vs innocence,
                        That mildneſſe may no longer iniure man.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           •
                        ic.
                     
                        Why, thou perpetuall Murmurer, thou ſea
                        Toſt with eternall tempeſt, thou darke sky
                        With euerlaſting clouds, thou—any thing,
                        Whom, being angry I can call no more:
                        Thinke better of thoſe acts thou canſt not mend.
                        Will Sforza be leſſe bad, becauſe thou whin'ſt?
                        Or doſt thou thinke thy pittifull complaints
                        Can beg a goodneſſe of Aſcanio?
                        
                        I neuer knew that mighty vſe of teares,
                        That they could waſh away anothers fault:
                        When thou ſhalt want a teare for a fit griefe,
                        
                           Sanſeuerin will be a Coward ſtill:
                        And when thy groanes are turn'd to thy laſt gaſpe,
                        
                           Caiazzo will not be leſſe trecherous.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        •
                     nter Sanſeuerin, with diuers ſuitors following him, ſome of whoſe bils he teares, others laughs at, others puts vp. Sxit.
                  
                     
                        
                           ••
                        l.
                     
                        Now for thy thunder, Heau'n, now for a piece
                        Of thy moſt eminent Artillery.
                        Are you ſtill ſilent? ſee, he teares their papers,
                        Papers, perhaps, wherein they worſhip him,
                        Giue him more titles, then they giue their God▪
                        
                        And yet he teares them. O vaſt Fauourite!
                        Swell'd by the airy fauour of thy Prince,
                        Till thou haſt dimm'd the light that made thee ſhine,
                        Till Sforza's leſſe then his Sanſeuerin.
                        
                        Tell me, good Picinino, does the Sunne
                        Spend all his rayes vpon one Continent?
                        Or haue you euer ſeene the partiall Heau'ns
                        Vpon one A
                              •
                           e
                              •
                            lauiſh all her ſhowres,
                        
                           While the reſt moulder with dry barrenneſſe?
                     
                  
                  
                     Pic.
                     I haue not, Iuliano, but what then?
                  
                  
                     Jul.
                     
                        Are you to ſeeke for the collection?
                        Why, has not Sforza made himſelfe our Sunne?
                        Are not his fauours our refreſhing ſhowres?
                        Why ſhould one ſucke vp what is due to all,
                        Why is the Prince made a Monopoly?
                     
                  
                  
                     Pic.
                     
                        Thou mak'ſt me laugh at thy fond queſtion:
                        What? are not Princes men▪ of the ſame mould,
                        Of the ſame paſſions with inferiours?
                        Doe not they feare, deſire, and hate (as we)
                        And ſhall we onely hinder them from loue?
                        Coblers may haue their friends, and why not Kings?
                        Becauſe th'are higher then the reſt of men,
                        Shall they be therefore worſe? and therefore want
                        The Benefits, becauſe they haue the Rule?
                        O hard condition of Maieſty!
                        The former accuſation of Kings
                        Has beene their cruelty, that they did hate
                        The people they ſhould gouerne: O hard plight!
                        O ſtrange peruerſneſſe! ſhall their loue at length,
                        Their friendſhip be imputed as their fault?
                        Would Heau'n our Sforza had no worſe a crime.
                     
                  
                  Enter Sanſeuerin againe with his traine of Suiters.
                  
                     Iul.
                     
                        You are a worthy Aduocate, and here
                        Comes your great Patron: goe and aske your 
                              •
                           ee:
                     
                  
                  
                     Sanſ.
                     
                        This is a ſawcy importunity:
                        You haue your anſwer.
                     
                  
                  
                     1 Sutor.
                     
                     
                        O my gracious Lord,
                        Looke on theſe ſcarres I gain'd in the French 
                              ••••
                           e,
                        Where I haue loſt my Fortunes.
                     
                  
                  
                     2 Sutor.
                     
                     
                        So haue I,
                        
                           Scarce left aliue to tell my miſery.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           •
                        anſ.
                     
                        You haue bin drunk, and quarrell'd—muſt the State
                        Finde plaiſters for your broken heads?—no more—
                        Nay, if you'll take no anſwer, I muſt call
                        Them that will driue you hence. O my tyr'd eares!
                        Henceforth I vow to ſtoppe them at your ſuites,
                        And be as Deafe, as you are Impudent.
                     
                  
                  Exit.
                  
                     Iul.
                     
                        Yes, doe good Aeolu
                                 •
                              
                           —how he blowes them hence!
                        How cleares his paſſage with a luſty frowne!
                        And yet it may be that deſpiſed wretch
                        Worne out of cloathes, and fleſh, whom his high ſcorne
                        Would not vouchſafe once more to looke vpon,
                        Durſt in the field doe more, then he durſt ſee,
                        Then he would there vouchſafe to looke vpon.
                     
                  
                  
                     Pic.
                     
                        As if that Valour were the onely praiſe,
                        And none were to be lou'd, but they that fight:
                        Where were we then? what would become of vs?
                        Thou thinkſt it Paradox, but tis moſt true,
                        A Souldier is the greateſt enemy,
                        Of whom the Common-wealth can be afraid:
                        Preferre you which you pleaſe; yet vnto them
                        VVhich are the ſole Phyſitians of State,
                        VVho with the teeming of a pregnant braine,
                        Search the diſeaſes and the remedies,
                        Valour is nothing but a deſp'rate vice,
                        And there's no ſafety, but in cowardice.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scena quinta.
                  Sforza, Aſcanio, Maluezzo.
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        VVE are not man, for ſuch an empty thing
                        Could not haue this ſolidity of ioy:
                        
                           Say the French King is dead, and ſay withall
                        We are immortall, and ones happy truth,
                        Shall expiate for the others flattery.
                        But ſpeake the manner too as well, as death▪
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Aſc.
                     
                        When now his gadding thoughts had won the world▪
                        
                        And Italy was to be taken in
                        But onely as an eaſie ſeat, from whence
                        He might deriue his further victories;
                        
                           Ottoman quak'd, and 'twas in chance, if now
                        New Rome, ſhould be new-French, &amp; the proud T
                              〈…〉
                           
                        
                        Be brought to know what their beginnings were▪
                        
                        When Fortune had aduanc'd him to that height▪
                        
                        That growne forgetfull of a lowly tombe,
                        He rear'd huge Pyramides, and troubled Art
                        To match his fancy with magnificence
                        Fit for a conqu'ring builder, who had learnt
                        To ruine firſt, and then to build a City.
                        When Marbles were to be in rich with wounds▪
                        
                        And cut for their aduancement▪ then, Heau'ns ſpo
                              •
                           t▪
                        
                        He rais'd competitors to dare the Heau'ns:
                        Nor dreames his owne deſcent into low Earth.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        
                           Aſcanio, you make him liue too long,
                        Tell how he dy'd, without more circumſtance.
                     
                  
                  
                     Aſc.
                     
                        He went (ſuch was his vſe) to ſee the play
                        At Tennis▪ court, when by his trembling Queene
                        He ſanke into halfe-death: thence he's conuey'
                              〈…〉
                           
                        
                        To the next roome, where on a couch of ſtraw,
                        As if a downe-bed were too ſoft for him,
                        Whom rottenneſſe attended, and the graue,
                        That harder lodging of Mortality,
                        A King, a conqu'ring, youthfull King expires.
                        Thrice from deaths ſlumbers he awak't to ſpeake,
                        Thrice did he cry to heau'n, vnto deafe heau'n▪
                        
                        
                           And after nine houres death he dy'd.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        
                     
                     
                        I find
                        A certaine grumbling againſt Fortune here:
                        Which that I may whet to a liuely rage,
                        Repeat Maluezzo her laſt treachery
                        Againſt the French, and Neopolitan.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        al.
                     
                        
                           Naples now wonne, and the vnſtable French
                        (As if they were afraid of their owne lucke)
                        Ridiculouſly leauing what th'ad wonne▪
                        
                        The Deputy was Mompen
                                 •
                              eer, a man
                        Of an high birth, but of vnequall deeds.
                        For when yong Ferdinand with ſome few boates
                        (Which onely feare might make a Nauy of,
                        And nothing but the ſtrength of cowardize
                        Could poſſibly iudge ſtrong) approacht the ſhoare,
                        As if the poore Prince once more had deſir'd
                        Onely to ſee his ancient gouernement,
                        And therefore had aduentur'd to the Sea,
                        The Sea was in the City, for ne're was
                        Such a confuſion in the vulgar waues:
                        All cry a Ferdinand, a Ferdinand,
                        
                        Eu'n thoſe who lately baniſht Ferdinand:
                        
                        Part ope the gates to him, and part ſhut vp
                        The French into the Cittadells, where 
                              •
                           e
                        Beſiegeth his once Conquerors.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        
                     
                     
                        Tis true
                        Not the world onely▪ but a man's a ball,
                        Will Fortune neuer leaue her toſſing him▪
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        al.
                     
                        Whether their owne neglect forc'd them to want,
                        Or want to yeeld, 'tis doubted: but they yeeld:
                        Thus as in triuiall ſports we oft haue ſeene
                        After a tedious inconſtancy,
                        The Corke returne to him that ſtrucke it firſt,
                        So in this fatall reuolution,
                        
                           Fortune giues Naples vnto him againe▪
                        
                        Whom ſhe firſt iniur'd in the taking it.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        Who hearing this would not erect his ſoule
                        To a contempt▪ of Fortune! that blind wretch
                        Whom onely ſottiſhneſſe hath Deifi'd?
                        Man hath a nobler Godhead in himſelfe,
                        His vertue and his wiſdome, vnto theſe▪
                        
                        Bend all our knees▪ let vs ſtill honour theſe:
                        And count it comfort in our loweſt ſtate,
                        He that is vvi
                              •
                           e, would not be fortunate.
                     
                  
               
            
            
               Actus quarti
               
                  Scena prima.
                  Sforza, Aſcanio, Caiazzo, Sanſeuerin, a Boy.
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        WE leaue it to your care, Sanſeuerin;
                        
                        But ſee the night grows old, good reſt my Lords▪
                        
                        Why ſtayſt thou▪ my Aurelio? good boy
                        Ile ſee no bed to night; then goe, yet ſtay,
                        If they haue not eſcap'd thy memory
                        Sing me thoſe verſes which you made of ſleepe.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           
                              Song.
                              
                                 HOw I laugh at their fond wiſh
                                 whoſe deſire
                                 aymes no higher
                                 Then the bayts of Midas diſh?
                                 What is Gold but yellow durt?
                                 which th'vnkind
                                 heauens refin'd
                                 
                                    When they made vs loue our hurt.
                                 Would to heau'n that I might ſteepe
                                 my faint eyes
                                 in the wiſe,
                                 In the gentle dew of ſleepe?
                                 Whoſe effects doe poſe vs ſo,
                                 that we deeme
                                 it does ſeeme
                                 Both Deaths brother and his foe.
                                 This does alwayes with vs keepe,
                                 and being dead
                                 that's not fled:
                                 Death is but a longer ſleepe.
                              
                           
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        f.
                     
                        Pretty Philoſophy! goe boy, goe ſleepe,

                              
                                 •
                              x.
                        
                        Enioy the good thou ſing'ſt—this boy can ſleepe,
                        Sleepe quietly, and ſing himſelfe aſleepe:
                        Making that gentle Reſt vnto his Song.
                        But lle goe read: what haue we here? a Map?
                        Welcome thou liuely picture of the world:
                        Now Ile peruſe my large Dominions,
                        What a vaſt compaſſe they doe fill in thee?
                        How Poe is wearied with his tedious courſe,
                        But running onely through our Continent?
                        Ha! where is Poe? which is our Continent?
                        If that my eyes deceiue me not, I ſee
                        My Empire is compriz'd within my nayle:
                        What a poore point I me Maſter of? a blot▪
                        
                        Made by the ſwifteſt tincture of the Inke?
                        But what did this point coſt me? this ſmall blot?
                        My innocence, my conſcience, my ſoule;
                        I kill'd a Nephew, to obtaine this blot.
                        O horrid purchaſe! all this toyle, this guilt
                        For ſo deſpis'd a Nothing? let me ſee,
                        
                           Here is no roome to ſit, to walke, to ſtand,
                        In all my land I cannot place my ſelfe,
                        Nor be at all, where I would be the Duke.
                        But the ſad tapers doe deny their light,
                        And ſtranger fire ſupplyes an horrid day
                        Of Lightning: help vs, heau'n, make vs confeſs,
Aſc
                                 •••
                               vmb. Gal
                                 ••
                              
                           
                        
                        There is a Power in your Mercy too.
                     
                  
                  
                     Vmb.
                     
                        Is then a time, when all our time is ſpent
                        That thou of vs ſhouldſt feare a puniſhment?
                        O happy purchas'd priuacy! to haue
                        The free poſſeſſion of an humble graue.
                        Wu't poyſon vs from that? why ſtareſt thou ſo?
                        We doe not ſhunne a kinſman, but a foe:
                        Beleeue it Sforza, I am a neer ghoſt,
                        Nor is our kindred by thy murther loſt:
                        Rayſe thy cheer'd looke, ſee Galeazzo here:
                        Traitor, and coward, does thy faint breaſt feare
                        The ſhadow, which is made? or is a ſoule
                        Vncloath'd of Earth, more abled to controle
                        Him that vncloth'd it! Then I ſee to dye
                        Is more to right, then ſuffer iniury.
                        Know I am ſtill thy Prince, and if that man
                        In ſuch a Miracle of villaine can
                        At laſt be ſound, in this thy manhood ſhow
                        That thou darſt heare thy doome of ouerthrow.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        Villaine be dumbe: we are too tamely mild
                        That deadmen dare affront vs, aſſume fleſh,
                        And we will make a ſecond ghoſt of thee.
                     
                  
                  
                     Vmb.
                     
                        Thy threats are Ayre, like vs: but to goe on
                        In curſe; now that thy wiſdome hopes vpon
                        A ioy in vnmoleſted royalty,
                        Now ſhalt thou haue onely a certainty
                        Of high vnhappineſſe, and be vndone,
                        Loſing thy rule no better then twas w
                              ••
                           ne.
                        
                           Fetters ſhall bind thy legs, not Crownes thy head,
                        And as a curſt beaſt is prohibited
                        From common ſhew; ſo thou, of beaſts the worſt,
                        Muſt die impriſon'd, and, what's moſt accurſt,
                        Obey, to death, all comforts tane away,
                        Rob'd o
                              •
                            the light, and the ſweet heau'n of day:
                        Then flatter not thy miſeries, to know
                        Is not to hinder Fate, fall ſhalt thou low,
                        Sinke to deſpaire, deſpaire to nought, and dy,
                        Then lower fall, and then as low as I.
Deſ
                                 •
                              endit vmb.
                        
                        Sinke into earth, and doe not reach thy hell,
                        Propheticke bubble: might thy threats proue true,
                        For we could wiſh the death that thou foretell'ſt,
                        That our f
                              •
                           irce ſhadow might purſue thee ſtill,
                        To fright thy Ghoſt to nothing: O weake Heau'ns!
                        VVas this a terror for a man? to ſend
                        A Bug-beare, fram'd out of the empty Ayre.
                        This does confirme, not fright vs: this might be
                        A terror to my picture, not to me.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scena ſecunda.
                  Caiazzo.
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        .
                     
                        IT muſt ſucceed: Fortune may ſhew her ſpite,
                        Her pow'r ſhe cannot, in the houre I'me made
                        A Princes Lord, or murtherer: I'ue plac'd
                        Cloſe at the outward doore, Sanſeuerin,
                        
                        That if ſucceſſe doe crowne my hopes, his cares
                        May giue me ſafety, with my happineſſe,
                        That I be not ſurpris'd: but if I faile
                        I haue in ioyn'd him on the noyſe he heares,
                        Straight to goe call the Duke, &amp; enter hither.
Ent▪ Iſ
                                 •
                              b.
                        
                        Madame, tis done: and now the guilty head
                        
                           (Which whilſt it ſtood, made all to feare their head,
                        Who durſt affirme it did vſurpe a crowne,)
                        Moſt humbly bends, and offers it to you.
                     
                  
                  
                     Iſ.
                     
                        Which I accept: but for no other end
                        Then to reuenge his death, baſe wretch, on thee:
                        If that head be not planted there, 't ſhall off:
                        You ſhall inioy your Maſters death.
                     
                  
                  
                     Cai.
                     
                        How's this?
                        Is this a loue-tricke, Lady? I had thought
                        After your thankes parted twixt heau'n and me,
                        You would with greedineſſe haue giu'n your ſelfe
                        To him that gaue you your deſires:
                     
                  
                  
                     Iſ.
                     
                        Fond thought!
                        Doſt thinke Ide loue a man that kils a man?
                        Make him my Prince, who hath diſpatcht his owne
                        Was Treaſon euer Preface vnto Loue?
                        Hadſt thou monopoliz'd perfection,
                        And ſhar'd a thouſand Cupids in each eye:
                        I would contemne the proudeſt of their ſhafts,
                        And giue thee onely what is due, Diſdaine.
                     
                  
                  
                     Cai.
                     
                        Youle vrge me to iuſt vengeance? doe you heare
                        Madam ingratitude, quickly profeſſe
                        That this harſh language was but a wiſe baite
                        To make him faſter, who was ſure before,
                        Or I profeſſe Ile ioyne your death with his
                        With thy loath'd Sforza.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Iſ.
                     
                        I beleeue thee now,
                        And truſt me, ſo beleeue, that I could thanke thee,
                        I loue thy cruelty, though not thy perſon.
                     
                  
                  
                     Cai.
                     
                        Hath death ſo little horror? well Ile doe
                        What ſhall inforce you to deſire a death.
                        This ponyards point ſhall naile thee to the 
                              •••
                           t
                              •
                           
                        
                        Strucke through thy armes: where doe not hope vp
                        A noble rauiſhet, my ſwa
                              •
                           ty ſlaues,
                        
                           Slaues hated of their fellow Black a mores,
                        Shall on thy Honors ruine tyre then Luſt,
                        And kill thee in thy loathfull ſuffering.
Ent. Sforza, Sanſeuerin▪ Belgioſa.
                        
                        What dare you ſtruggle?
                        A rape, a rape.
                        O my good Lord you come in ſuch a time
                        As I could wiſh for, for this houre or more
                        This wicked woman hath beene wooing me,
                        To murther your moſt ſacred Maieſty,
                        And for reward hath promis'd me herſelfe,
                        Together with the Duchy: my good Lord,
                        In deteſtation of ſuch treachery,
                        I gaue her ſome harſh anſwers, with which mou'd,
                        She vs'd a womans craft, and cry'd a Rape.
                        Is this truth, Iſabella; ſee, ſhee's dumbe:
                        Haue I then liu'd to haue you ſeeke my death?
                        A Coſin-Traitor? yet you ſhall not dy,
                        Nor know another priſon then my Court,
                        I loue to ſee my Murtherer: O heau'ns!
                        Why, ſhould I feare to kill her? yet tis reaſon:
                        Who is no true Prince, can ne'er puniſh treaſon.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        .
                     And I ſhall take you at your word, deare Sforza.
                     
                  
                  Ex.
               
               
                  Scena tertia.
                  Iuliano, Picinino.
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        .
                     
                        IT cannot be, good Iulian, no more:
                        I doe not loue theſe ouer-earneſt dreames.
                        The French inuade vs? when their iolly King
                        With limber ſlaues does onely mocke a warre,
                        Which like ſo many reeds againſt a ſtone
                        
                           Puniſh their owne attempt with their owne r
                              〈…〉
                           
                           ▪
                        
                        Breaking themſelues, no
                              •
                            a
                              •
                           mors: when we 
                              〈…〉
                           
                        
                        The Court is loſt in Ma
                              •
                           kes, reality
                        Is ſo farre fled ſince the laſt victory,
                        That we may thinke the Court it ſelfe a ma
                              •
                           ke▪
                        
                        Aeternall Muſicke, reuells without end
                        Tire the too-much delighted ſouldier,
                        Whoſe armes haue now forgot their ancient vſe,
                        His ſpirits onely actiue in his heeles,
                        And canſt thou thinke theyle dance to Italy?
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Iul.
                     
                        I'ue heard ſo
                              •
                           e tell that a great City once
                        Was built by Muſicke: would we might not 
                              •••
                           d
                        Our Country to be ruin'd by a dance:
                        O feare the toying of an enemy.
                     
                  
                  
                     Pic.
                     What cannot be beleeu'd, cannot be fear'd.
                  
                  
                     Iul.
                     
                        Youle not beleeue, not you, till the French ſwords
                        Diue to the bottome of your doubting heart,
                        Till that th'vokinder newes is brought ſo nere,
                        You cannot haue the power to beleeue it:
Ent. Sa
                                 〈…〉
                               with ſ
                                 〈…〉
                              
                           
                        
                        Can you beleeue this is a drum that beats?
                        That this is the couragious Generall?
                        Can you beleeue, that he beleeues 'tis true?
                     
                  
                  
                     Pic.
                     But who aſſiſts vs in this dreadfull time?
                  
                  
                     Iul.
                     
                        As many as we haue deſeru'd: not one:
                        
                           Sforza has too much wiſedome to haue friends.
                     
                  
                  
                     Pic.
                     
                        And we haue too much—I ſaid nothing, did I?
                        I did not ſpeake againſt the State▪ I hope?
                        Nor ſaid that we had too much patience?
                     
                  
                  
                     Iul.
                     
                        Is Picinino then orecome at laſt,
                        Now I could change my ſorrow for a ſmile.
                     
                  
                  
                     Pic.
                     
                        I muſt confeſſe an anger though not griefe:
                        O how I loue to fit me to miſchance
                        And when that has no reaſon, then I'me 
                              •
                           ad.
                        Why ſhould our Millan blood ſtaine the french ſwords
                        
                           Vnto a glory? Sforza does offend,
                        Deny's the heau'nly pow'rs, or names them then,
                        When he does dare them with bold periury,
                        Loads his blacke ſoule with murther of a man
                        That could haue made his execution, iuſtice.
                        This Sforza does, but what is this to me?
                        Why ſhall this throat be cut for his? why thine?
                        Why ſhall our Countryes ruine fill his penance?
                        The heau'ns doe know no meane but either waſt
                        Their benefits on dull ingratitude
                        Or throw away their thunder, ſo it hit
                        So it not faile, they care not whom it ſtrike,
                        VVhether the guilty, or the innocent.
                     
                  
                  
                     Iul.
                     
                        This is a griefe of higher fault then mine,
                        You make a warre with them you ſhould appeaſe,
                        And vrge the heau'ns to our calamities.
                        Firſt we were puniſht with, and now for Sforza,
                        
                        Could any iuſtice haue more method in't.
                     
                  
                  
                     Pic.
                     
                        Well Iulian, I me ſorry for my griefe,
                        And ſo perſwade thee to that holy truth.
                        I now could raue againſt my ſelfe, not heau'n,
                        But tis as fruitleſſe, as to wiſh good lucke:
                        Then let the French preſſe vpon victory,
                        Let them amaze the Ayre with ſtranger fire,
                        Rais'd by our Cities flaming Funeralls.
                        Swell they the Poe with blood, act o're, what ere
                        Has beene the brag of royall murtherers,
                        Yet our defence is here: Fortune may faile
                        But our true ſouls ſhall neuer, we may loſe
                        An aged life, but not Aeternity:
                        And with this ſtrength the field muſt needs be ours:
                        Who doe not feare, doe beat the Conquerors.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  Scena quarta.
                  Sforza. Aſcanio. A Guard.
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        VVHat noyſe is this that from a forraigne foe
                        Recalls our anger? yet our purer hands
                        Know not the dy of blood: we ſhould be loath
                        To learne a valour on our ſubiects firſt.
                     
                  
                  
                     1 Nunc.
                     
                     
                        The people now haue rau'd to quietneſſe:
                        But till that Landrian
                                 •
                              , whom you vs'd
                        About the laſt taxation, was become
                        Their rages ſacrifice, I durſt haue ſworne
                        The French were in the City.
                     
                  
                  
                     2 Nun.
                     
                     
                        This ſad houre
                        (I'me ſorry that you hear this truth from me)
                        Your Ducheſſe is departed.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     VVhither villaine?
                  
                  (Fren
                        ••
                     
                  
                  
                     2 Nun.
                     
                     
                        To that free Crowne, where ſhee ſhall feare no
                        To Heau'n.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        O enuious heau'n! why doe you giue
                        Men ſuch hard precepts of mortality,
                        And take them hence before that they can learne?
                        Muſt not ſhe liue, becauſe ſhe liu'd too well?
                        Alas my wife!
                     
                  
                  
                     Aſc.
                     Alas my ſiſter, 
                           •
                        !
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        VVho dar'd that groane? good Cardinall, no more,
                        I know not what I could deny to thee:
                        Take to thee all for what the French ſo toyle,
                        But kindly leaue my griefe vnto my ſelfe.
                     
                  
                  
                     3 Nun.
                     
                     
                        Pardon, my Lord, ill Fortunes eloquence,
                        Vnleſſe you h
                              ••
                           re you cannot cure your harmes;
                        The French, now enter'd Lombardy, ſat downe
                        Before Valenza: where the mouth of Death,
                        
                           The thundring Canon being ſcarcely brought,
                        But iuſt preſented to the yet ſound wall,
                        Diſcouered there was ſomewhat more vnſound:
                        For Rattagnino, the falſe Gouernour
                        Entreats a Parly, giues away the ſtrength,
                        Sweares the towne French, and 
                              •
                           iues the key to them,
                        VVith which they open Lombardy.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        
                     
                     
                        My fact;
                        None can be guilty of this crime, but I:
                        That after Treaſon durſt againe truſt treaſon.
                        This very man, whoſe eaſie heart relents
                        At a French death, and wiſely is afraid
                        His manners might be call'd in queſtion,
                        If he ſhould put them off to ſue againe,
                        To aske the ſecond time, for what he held:
                        Out of his zeale to vertue, and good lucke,
                        Did the like act for vs, and gaue a ſtrength
Ent. Mal. wounded
                        
                        VVhich all our Duchy neuer could haue forc't.
                        VVhat more reuolting yet?
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           •
                        al.
                     
                        O my good Lord!
                        I feare this is beyond Addition.
                        O my blood failes me, but my tongue does more,
                        Fearing the ſtory that it muſt relate.
                        Your Army being parted, and this halfe
                        
                           Caiazzo leading, that Sanſeuerin,
                        
                        My troopes did fall among the French mens ſcouts.
                        From whom we learn't their numbers, and intent,
                        To march with ſpeed for Millan: this ſad newes
                        VVe ſent to Count Caiazzo, with aduice,
                        That he would inſtantly reioyne with vs,
                        To ſtop their further entrance: hee pretends
                        That the Venetians hemming in his campe
                        Haue made his danger greater: yet he moues,
                        Makes to the riuer, and when now our thoughts
                        
                           Had left their wau'ring, and did ſeeme aſſur'd
                        His actions would be better then his words,
                        I ſaw, O miſery that ere I ſaw!
                        That croſſing o're the Po he did embrace
                        Thoſe men which he in duty ſhould haue kill'd:
                        (O tis this kils me, not my want of blood)
                        I in iuſt anger ſet vpon the Reare,
                        And after many vaine attempts, haue brought
                        My carkaſſe, to intreat for my reuenge.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        This is conſpiracy: Caiazzo falſe?
                        Tell me that contradictions then are true,
                        Tell me the heau'ns no more doe trauell now
                        Being growne inconſtant to their motion:
                        Or that the Earth purſie with too long eaſe
                        VVould with a walke at length refreſh her ſelfe:
                        Tell me that Princes may be fortunate,
                        Thoſe that like me are credulous: or if
                        You'd ſpeake of things more hard to be beleeu'd,
                        Tell me, there are, that birth of feare, call'd Gods,
                        And if they be, that they doe thinke of Man:
                        Tell me, O prethee tell me ſomewhat elſe,
                        Or I ſhall thinke thee falſe, and not Caiazzo,
                        
                        But I doe know thee true, know thy wounds true,
E
                                 〈…〉
                               Sanſeu
                                 〈…〉
                              
                           
                        
                        And muſt conclude Caiazzo is moſt falſe.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sanſ.
                     
                        To be o'recome, my Lord, is wretched chance,
                        But not to fight at all will be thought crime,
                        I ne're durſt thinke ſo to ſuruiue ill lucke
                        As to become the fatall meſſenger?
                        But I muſt ſay, I durſt not fight, and more,
                        I muſt intreat your cowardize, your foes
                        Are ſtrengthned with your Army (ô pardon me
                        Let me not tell you, how) and all our troopes,
                        Haue no pow'r left vs but for a ſafe flight.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        I did expect this: was not man at firſt
                        
                           Plac'd on this curious Theater, to ſee
                        How he could act all parts: doe we not know
                        VVhat we can feare is nothing? prouidence
                        Long ſince hath ſpent our feare; for a wiſe man,
                        VVhen he does found his happineſſe, forecaſts
                        Miſchiefes, that Fate had neuer practiz'd yet,
                        VVhich if they happen, if they proue too true,
                        They meet, not ouertake him, and ſo find
                        A ſcorne, becauſe a preparation.
                        I knew it might be thus, though I not fear'd,
                        And know it may be better, though not hope:
                        Yet let vs ne're deſpaire, nor by low thoughts
                        Excuſe Fate for her preſent iniury.
                        And when once more her fauours we ſhall feele,
                        Then ſay, that Fortune has no ſtanding wheele.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scena quinta.
                  
                     
                        〈…〉
                     ter at one doore, Triulcio, Aubeny, Caiazzo: at the other ſome Senators of Millan, who deliuer the keyes of the City.
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        
                     
                     
                        WE here preſent you with our keys great Lords,
                        Yet doe not thinke vs cowards, who doe part
                        So eaſily with that, which if we pleas'd
                        VVe might, in ſpite of force, as eaſily keepe:
                        VVe know your right, iuſtice does ope theſe gates,
                        And not your ſwords, nor our diſloyalty;
                        VVe leaue a Traytor that hath firſt left vs,
                        And now are glad to entertaine our Prince.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        iv.
                     
                        Is he fled then? O our vnhappy ſloath!
                        VVhy ranne we not as well as we did fight?
                        Are Cowards ſwifter then their Conquerors.
                     
                  
                  
                     Aboue as in the Cittadell appeare Iſobella, and Iulia.
                  
                     Iſ.
                     
                        Doe not diſſwade me, Iulia, 'tis true
                        I may eſcape, but whither? all is loſt,
                        In Naples we find France, as well as here.
                        O who'od indure the tyranny of hope,
                        That could ſo quickly gaine a liberty?
                        If I but fall I'me free; ô Iulia,
                        
                        The greateſt diſtance twixt my bliſſe, and me,
                        Reacheth no farther then to the next earth.
                        Can I behold in a perplexed flight
                        (Of which I know no comfort, and no end)
                        This my ſweet infant crying for the food,
                        Which I'me vncertaine where to beg for him?
                        No, Ile deſcend, and if the greedy French
                        Will haue our blood with our Dominions,
She comes down with ſome ſouldiers▪
                           
                        
                        Yet I ſhall ioy to haue a ſpeedy end
                        And call a nimble enemy, a friend.
                     
                  
                  
                     Tri.
                     
                        What anſwer from the Cittadel? once more
                        Giue them a ſummons, if they yeeld not then
Ent
                                 ••
                               Iſabella
                        
                        Giue an aſſault.
                     
                  
                  
                     Iſ.
                     
                        You ſhall not need my Lords,
                        What you could wiſh you haue, moſt cheapely haue,
                        The conqueſt of a woman, and a child.
                        I'me Iſabella, (let not that ſad name
                        Be ominous to conquerors,) and this
                        This pretty infant, is my luckleſſe child,
                        Borne Prince of that, which you haue made your prey.
                        Why doe you one conſult anothers face,
                        As you would ſee, who could be cruell firſt?
                        Be not at all, or if at all, to me.
                        O doe not warre with infants! can theſe hands
                        Deſerue your feare or anger? theſe weake hands
                        That cannot reach themſelues vnto their teat?
                        
                           Who haue ſo much of yong infirmity,
                        They cannot lift themſelues to ask your mercy?
                        O let them haue, becauſe they cannot aske.
                        How many diſmall accidents may chance
                        To take him hence, before he grow to man,
                        And ſo excuſe, and yet fulfill your purpoſe?
                        O let diſeaſe be cruell, and not you.
                     
                  
                  
                     Tri.
                     
                        Madame, you ſhall be honourably vs'd,
                        You, and your faire ſonne: take your liberty
                        To chuſe your owne free courſe: for this yong Lord,
                        He muſt to France with vs, where he ſhall learne
                        The good of royall education:
                        Where he ſhall know the happy difference
                        Betweene a petty, and a kingly Court.
                        Some waite vpon the Princeſſe.
                     
                  
                  
                     Iſ.
                     
                        O my ſtarres!
                        What haue I done? ay me? I haue betrayd,
                        What Tyranny had left me, my ſweet boy:
                        For whom I neuer knew a griefe; till now
                        I brought him forth with pleaſure, when I thinke
                        Vpon this paine of parting: my deare child,
                        O too too like thy mother; if thou chance
                        To draw thy life vnto that hated length,
                        That thou arriue to the diſcretion
                        To know, what by my folly, thou haſt loſt,
                        Call it no more, ô doe not call it crime,
                        No mother willingly would loſe a ſonne:
                        VVhilſt in ſome darker cell I will in tombe
                        Thy ruines cauſe, where whatſoeuer teare
                        Sorrow did once force, no deuotion ſhall:
                        That my new name vnto the heau'ns may reach
                        VVhom miſery the way to bliſſe did teach.
                     
                  
                  Exit.
                  
                     Tri.
                     
                        Neuer till now had we the victory,
                        And now no ſingle one, this happy houre
                        
                           Has gain'd a a conqueſt for Poſterity.
                        They may be idle now, now the French youth
                        May grow vp without wounds, and at their homes,
                        Steale to a priuate graue, no more being forc't
                        To death, though by a glory; nay this Land
                        May thanke vs, for our thrift of victory,
                        For lighting on this bleſt occaſion,
                        Which makes vs need no more to conquer them:
                        If heau'n continue vs this kindneſſe ſtill,
                        Wee'll meaſure out our conqueſts by our will.
                     
                  
               
            
            
               Actus Quinti
               
                  Scena prima.
                  Sforza, Aſcanio, Sanſeuerin.
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        O What is man? and all that happineſſe
                        That puffes him to ſecurity? to day
                        One acts a Prince, and ſwell'd with Maieſty
                        Fills a proud throne, from whence the Multitude
                        Thinkes he rules Fortune too, as well as them,
                        Whilſt ſhe in iuſt eſteeme of her owne name,
                        Makes him forgot, or odious, that none
                        Can be ſo miſerably fool'd, to wiſh
                        His well-apparell'd miſery: thus we
                        That did enioy beyond a Crowne, a braine
                        Able to meet, or challenge the worſt chance:
                        Yet in the ſpace of a few dayes, a ſpace
                        Of too ſhort laſting to expell a man
                        (By the moſt ſubtle fetches of the Law)
                        Out of a falſe inheritance: we loſt,
                        We were expell'd out of a Monarchy;
                        But does Fate make a ſtand at this? O no,
                        She is not conſtant, no not in her curſe,
                        But giuing moſt againe, which once was mine
                        
                           She giues me too the capability
                        Of a new curſe.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        ſc.
                     
                        Of a new ioy: for ſhame
                        Giue thankes at leaſt for your felicity:
                        Can you repine being cramm'd, and ſo deſerue
                        A bountifull vnhappineſſe? I'ue knowne
                        Some that haue long endur'd a tedious ſiege,
                        Or a more tedious ſickneſſe, who haue beene
                        Forſt to a laſting Lent, when they haue come
                        Or to their health, or to their liberty,
                        Not dare to take the nouriſhment they might,
                        Making themſelues their ſickneſſe, and their foe:
                        Is not my Sforza one of theſe? you grieue
                        Becauſe you haue no longer cauſe to grieue.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        anſ.
                     
                        O I doe feare your griefe, that it does glance
                        With a moſt vndeſeru'd diſgrace at me;
                        As if I were a-kinne vnto the fault
                        Of my falſe brother: O repeat that thought,
                        It is no great thing I requeſt you to,
                        But truſt vnto the faith that you haue found.
                        Would I betray, and follow you? d'yee thinke,
                        I'de be ſo mad to buy my baniſhment?
                        No man would be vnprofitably falſe,
                        Nor I for any profit: ſpeake your ſelfe
                        If I haue left you, when your Fortune did?
                        Nay, then my loue was greateſt, when you leaſt,
                        I was your ſubiect, when you were no Prince.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        f.
                     
                        
                           Sanſeuerin, thy feare is too too fond,
                        And like the people, the Authoritie,
                        Who make an impious confuſion
                        Of an high birth, and of an higher crime:
                        Who in a ſawcy thwarting to their Prince,
                        Count him ſtill worſt, whom he has made the beſt,
                        As if we gaue him, with his honors, crimes,
                        
                           And made him vicious, when fortunate.
                        No, let them ſpend their breath in idle talke,
                        Count thee or trecherous, or cowardly?
                        Whilſt to thy Sforza thou art ſtill the ſame,
                        Moſt valiant, and with thy valour, wiſe,
                        That by thy abſtinence a while from warre,
                        Haſt ſau'd vs forces for a victory.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sanſ.
                     
                        The Subiects life lies in the Princes voice:
                        Now you haue cleer'd me I dare haſten warre,
                        And wiſh more enemies, then cowards feare:
                        That you may ſee, by my neglect of bloud,
                        (Which I ſhall onely loue when ſhed for you)
                        How ſlaunder was my moſt fear'd enemy.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        No more, my deareſt friend: we loſe all time
                        Which we doe ſaue from fight, ſtill there does flock
                              •
                           
                        
                        New forces to our Army, and the French
                        Are now as much amaz'd, as proud before:
                        We lately tooke the Swizzers into pay,
                        Thoſe that dare ſell their liues to any cauſe,
                        Whom Gold hath arm'd for me: if they proceed
                        In their firſt heat, we winne: but if they faile
                        We cannot be more wretched then we were:
                        The vileſt chance of lucke can make vs know
                        But an Addition to an Ouerthrow.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scena ſecunda.
                  The Captaine of the Swizzers, with a Souldier, as a fugiti
                        〈…〉
                      from the French.
                  
                     Soul.
                     
                        NOw w' are alone I dare reueal
                              •
                            my ſelfe,
                        I am not what I ſeeme, a Fugitiue,
                        But one that from Triulcio doe bring
                        
                           Letters that much concerne you.
                     
                  
                  
                     Capt.
                     
                        VVhat? to me?
                        Letters vnto his enemy? let's ſee:
Ex. Soul.
                        
                        Expect an anſwer in my Tent.—VVhat's here?
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           
                              Letter.
                              
                                 THou Man of Action, whom th' Italians
                                 Feele their Achilles, both to wound, and heale:
                                 
                                    Triulcio ſalutes thee: what is paſt,
                                 As paſt recall he will not mention,
                                 But for the future this; you ayd a man,
                                 From whom you cannot any way expect
                                 Reward, or Honor, ſuch his pouerty
                                 Both in deſert, and meanes? but againſt whom?
                                 I will not vrge they are your Countrymen,
                                 Partakers of the ſame ſweet ſoyle with you,
                                 Who onely differ in their better choice:
                                 Yet ſo farre doe I prize your worth, to thinke,
                                 You haue not put off Nature, nor haue chang'd
                                 With your home ayre, your home-affections.
                                 That you are ſtill a Swizzer: thinke of this,
                                 And that at other times twere ſhame to flye,
                                 Now onely flight ſhewes Magnanimity.
                              
                           
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Triulcio.
                     
                        VVhat ſhall I doe? O I am loſt in doubt,
                        Nor know, what to refuſe, or what to grant.
                        Shall then the Swizzers to their valour adde
                        A tainture of diſloyaltie? to whom?
                        VVho can accuſe vs for our trechery?
                        One that has patroniz'd it by his act:
                        That hath betraid his Nephew: ſhall a man
                        Be counted trecherous, that betrayes vice?
                        It was a crime to aide him, can it 
                              •
                           e
                        A crime to leaue him too? O paradox!
                        
                           Reſolue me Goodneſſe what tis beſt to doe:
                        And that does whiſper a diſlike: for what,
                        What goodneſſe can there be in ciuill warre?
                        When we ſhall kill them that were borne with vs,
                        When we ſhall make the Father dye his ſword
                        In the ſonnes bloud, and ſtrangely giue a death
                        To him, to whom he kindly gaue a life,
                        When the mixt bloud of the ſame Family
                        Shall make a cruell inceſt: this we doe
                        If we are honeſt: Ile learne treaſon firſt,
                        And the moſt accurate ſinne. Triulcio,
                        
                        Our Country calls vs, and not thou, to be
                        Diſhoneſt then is the beſt honeſty.
                     
                  
                  Ex.
               
               
                  Scena tertia.
                  
                     Picinino in his ſtudy, with a Deaths-head and a Watch.
                  
                     Pic.
                     
                        THis is the ſumme, I can but be like this.
                        After the prouder threatning of the French,
                        After the ſure impreſſion of Diſeaſes
                        I can but be like this: then let me thinke
                        What loſſe I haue when I am made like this:
                        This feares no French: a peace of ordinance
                        Can breake, but not aſtoniſh this, no force
                        Can draw a teare, no not a ſigh from hence:
                        And can it be a loſſe to be like this?
                        O Death! why art thou fear'd? why doe we thinke
                        Tis ſuch a horrid terror▪ Not to Be?
                        Why, not to be, is, not to be a wretch,
                        Why, not to be, is, to be like the heau'ns,
                        Not to be ſubiect to the pow'r of Fate:
                        O there's no happineſſe but not to be.
to the Watch.
                        
                        
                           But thou diſcloſer of the ſtealth of Time,
                        Let me inquire how much is worne away
                        Of this ſad houre: the halfe? O ſpeedy time!
                        That mak'ſt vs feele, ere we can thinke of Age,
                        Ere we can take an order for the Graue.
                     
                  
                  Enter Iul.
                  
                     Iul.
                     
                        What? deepe in meditation, noble friend?
                        So ſtudious of your Watch? alas good man,
                        Thou needſt not this faint helpe to gueſſe at Fate,
                        Theſe ſiluer haires are watch enough for thee.
                     
                  
                  
                     Pic.
                     
                        I onely looke how many minutes hence
                        
                           M
                                 ••
                              an expires.
                     
                  
                  
                     Jul.
                     
                        O ſwift Arithmeticke,
                        To ſumme by minutes our ſad Duchies age.
                     
                  
                  
                     Pic.
                     
                        This VVatch doth teach reall Philoſophy,
                        There is no tutor to this actiue braſſe:
                        VVhat is a Kingdome, but a larger watch?
                        VVound vp by Fate vnto ſome ſcores of yeares,
                        And then it falls: good Iuliano liſt,
                        Harke how it beats, how ſtrongly, and how faſt,
                        Beyond the motion of a nimble pulſe:
                        VVho would not thinke this were a laſting noiſe?
                        And yet it ends: after ſome date of houres
                        The watch will be as ſilent as the head.
                        O tis our folly, folly, my deare friend,
                        Becauſe we ſee th'actiuity of States,
                        To flatter them with falſe Eternity:
                        VVhy longer then the dweller laſts the houſe?
                        Why ſhould the world be alwaies, and not man?
                        Sure kingdomes are as mortall as their Kings,
                        And ſtay but longer for their period.
                     
                  
                  
                     Iul.
                     
                        I feare our Climactericall is now:
                        When all profeſſions turne to ſouldier,
                        To that eurſt Art that thriues by Deſtiny.
                        The ſithes are ſtraighted into ſwords, and th'Earth
                        
                           Being not wounded is vndone, where once
                        Stood buildings, which an humble Poetry
                        Without too bold a ſwelling might giue Kings:
                        Whole Mines vndone to beautifie one roofe,
                        Now onely Deſolation dwels: weake griefe,
                        To ſay Corne growes, where once a City ſtood,
                        That ſuſtenance is there where no men are,
                        This is a trifling, and halfe-miſery:
                        Our Lands now onely furniſh vs with Graues,
                        Can hide vs, but not feed vs; we would thinke
                        Our Cities ſtanding, though the buildings fell,
                        If we had no griefe, but Fertility.
                     
                  
                  
                     Pic.
                     
                        But on what ſtrength does Sforza ſtill ſubſiſt
                        Againſt ſo powrefull foes?
                     
                  
                  
                     Iul.
                     
                        The Emperor
                        Has ſold him ſome few Almaines, but his hopes
                        Chiefly depend vpon the valiant Swizze,
                        Who were the chiefe in his depreſſion.
                     
                  
                  
                     Pic.
                     
                        Has his groſſe braine not learnt the danger yet
                        Of bringing ſtrangers into Italy?
                        
                        He call'd the French to Naples, who haue now
                        Found Millan too: O what's the difference
                        Betwixt a mercenary and a foe?
                        But that we kill one for his outrages,
                        And hyre the other? Juliano, I
                        May feele misfortune, but will neuer buy.
                     
                  
                  Ex.
               
               
                  Scena quarta.
                  Sforza, Sanſeuerin.
                  
                     Sanſ.
                     
                        THe French are mighty, and portentouſly
                        Riſe by their fall: ſtrong ſhame begets a rage,
                        And a diſdaine, that you whom they expell'd
                        
                           Should hazard their expulſion, makes them hazard,
                        What ere being ventur'd, addes a fame to Man,
                        And giues a glory to his miſery.
                        They are ſo farre from the baſe feare of death,
                        That they embrac't, and like thoſe fiercer curres,
                        That ſpend their anger on the ſenſeleſſe ſtone
                        Not daring to attempt on him that threw,
                        They with a ſenſeleſſe anger breake the darts
                        That naile them to the Earth, as if they ſcorn'd
                        Their killer ſhould ſuruiue them: other lets,
                        As heat, or hunger, are their exerciſe:
                        That one would thinke they'd loſt all part of man
                        VVhen they did meane to ſhew the beſt: my Lord,
                        I wiſh a ſwift, but loue a certaine conqueſt:
                        I thinke twere wiſedome to protract the fight.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           •
                        f.
                     
                        I know thou ſpeakſt what thou thinkſt beſt: but know,
                        Tis wiſedome to delay on equall fame:
                        But when a foe has wonne opinion,
                        Which drawes all eyes, and hearts to him, O then
                        A valiant deſperation fits a man:
                        For victory is not impoſſible,
                        And honour neceſſary: my beſt friend,
                        Call forth our Swizzers, and if happy ſwords
                        Though few, may cut a way to glory, come:
Enter Capt with Swiz:
                        
                        The purchaſe is aboue the paines: but here
                        Come they that ſhall fill hiſtories: braue friends
                        Now is the time we ſhall imploy your ſwords,
                        And teach the world your valour.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           ••
                        pt.
                     
                        You may faile:
                        'Tis better to be wiſe: Sforza, I'me come
                        To take my leaue of you, nor ſhall much breath
                        Be ſpent in ceremoniall complement,
                        I am the French Kings ſouldier.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        
                     
                     
                        Speake low,
                        
                           Let not the ayre feele ſuch a treaſon, know
                        There is a pow'r aboue vs, and that pow'r
                        Thunders ſometimes, I know, thou darſt not ſtand
                        In conteſtation with the pow'r of heau'n:
                        Reuoke thy words.
                     
                  
                  
                     Capt.
                     
                        Ile doe no miracles:
                        My voice and faith are paſt.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        Yes they are paſt:
                        Thou art made vp all of diſloyalty,
                        Reaſon hath nothing of thee: yet relate
                        (If thou haſt any reliques left of ſenſe,
                        Ile not coniure thee by ſtrange Honeſty)
                        Why doſt thou leaue the heau'ns, and vs, and ſo
                        For nothing doſt commit a double Treaſon?
                     
                  
                  
                     Cap.
                     
                        Ile ſatisfie you thus, you ſee I doe't:
                        Strike vp a march.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        Yet ſtay: what is the price
                        That makes thee trecherous, Ile turne prodigall
                        To buy thee to a vertue: ſtay: be rich,
                        Without a curſe, without a fault.
                     
                  
                  
                     Cap.
                     
                        Tis vaine,
                        I'me deafe to Rh
                              •
                           toricke: yet ſay th'aſt met
                        With a good periurer, my word is paſt,
                        And to be twice a traytor, is a fault
                        No ſorrow can attone for: yet thus farre
                        Ile ſtraine my ſelfe to pleaſe thee, tis well knowne,
                        Vnleſſe you get vnto Aſcanio,
                        
                        Your hopes are at the laſt, but betweene you
                        And him, the French haue interpos'd themſelues,
                        Nothing remaines but that you truſt to me,
                        And in a Swizzers coat diſguiſe your ſelfe,
                        That you may paſſe their Army.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        O hard ſtrait,
                        Muſt Sforza impotently hide himſelfe?
                        
                           Or can a Prince be hid? I haue oft heard
                        Sparkes of Diuinity adorne his face,
                        To cleare him from the multitude: why then,
                        The being a Prince will make vs be no Prince,
                        We being betraid by our owne Maieſty.
                        Yet off ye enuy'd roabes, fall to the Earth,
                        O fall ſo low, that henceforth Man may ſcorne
                        The labour of deſcent to take you vp:
                        On, on, ye happy roabes, that like good clouds
                        Doe not obſcure, but for a time defend
                        The threatned Sunne, that he may after ſhine
                        With higher vigour: I haue heard of ſome,
                        That weare their fleſh with hairecloth for their crimes,
                        As thinking to be good if they were rough,
                        By ſuch a wilde repentance: be it ſo
Enter Triulcio with the French.
                        
                        Theſe robes offended, then there is an hope
                        Theſe ragges may expiate heau'n
                     
                  
                  
                     Tri.
                     
                        Braue ſouldiers,
                        How we reioice we may embrace at laſt,
                        Not with arm'd hands, without the guilt and ſhame
                        Of ciuill murther▪ but are theſe the troupes
                        That now muſt learne to vſe their valour well?
                        To giue a death without a prodegy?
                        A conqu'ring cheerfulneſſe adornes their face▪
                        
                        Theſe are not common ſouldiers: looke you pale,
                        Then I muſt know the myſtery.
                     
                  
                  
                     Cap.
                     I'me betrayd.
                  
                  
                     Tri.
                     
                        Yea I know all, but yet from thy forc'd tongue
                        Will I extract confeſſion; fetch a racke,
                        To make him howle the truth, he will not ſpeake.
                     
                  
                  
                     Cap.
                     
                        I can dare torments for wiſe honeſty,
                        But when you know as much as I can tell,
                        Should I conceale't, all policy would iudge,
                        I did deſerue the worſt that I endur'd:
                        
                           Who told you this was Sforza?
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Sf.
                     
                        O my braine!
                        Muſt ſubtletie periſh by ſubtlery?
                        And our high wiſedome finde a Conqueror?
                        Make an end Nature, the great worke is done,
                        
                           Sforza is ouer-reacht—weake, childiſh rage:
                        Is this to leſſen, or make miſery?
                        Can paſſion looſe vs, or a courteous teare
                        Waſh off our fetters? if it can, poure eyes,
                        Poure out wet comfort; if it can, refuſe
                        The curſe of ſlumber, but it cannot, then
                        Couet a ſlumber euerlaſtingly,
                        And be like 
                              〈…〉
                           , impriſon'd in your lid
                              •
                           .
                        Conuey vs quickly hence, kinde friends, you know
                        
                           Sforza can neuer be a priſoner here.
                        Conuey vs thither where we are no Prince.
                        And muſt we wooe our Ruine? neuer man
                        Is a true wretch, but when he loſeth all,
                        And wants the ſad Election of his fall▪
                        
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scena vltima.
                  I
                        ••
                     i
                        •••
                     , Picinin
                        •
                     
                  
                  
                     Iul.
                     
                        I'Me loſt in this confuſion: one reports▪
                        
                        We haue loſt all; another inſtantly
                        Kil
                              •
                            all the French at once: thus eu'ry ſtreet▪
                        
                        Is filld with w
                              ••
                           d
                              •
                           ing people; ſome cry▪ Arme,
                        Others runne crying, to perſwade a ſlight:
                        All haue an earneſt buſ
                              ••
                           eſſe in the ſtirre,
                        But in the helpe not any.
                     
                  
                  
                     Pic.
                     
                        Theſe are they▪
                        
                        That if a
                              •
                            happy meſſenger ſhould come
                        
                           With Sforza's victory, would pretend at leaſt
                        To be orecome with ioy: the gorgeous wals
                        Should ſhine with painted triumphs, and the French
                        Should be againe vanquiſht in pageant.
                        But if his fortune yeeld to the French force,
                        What obloquy's will be enough for him?
                        Diſgrace will then be wit, and any braine
                        Will venture on a Libell.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        l.
                     
                        'Tis the vſe,
                        The popular folly to admire euents,
                        And thoſe low ſoules thinke that the ſword is iuſt,
                        Proportioning the reaſon by the end
                        Of the chiefe acts, of the beſt enterprize,
                        And ſo by folly runne into a crime.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        ic.
                     
                        No matter for their wiſedome, were they good:
                        O why are ſuch term'd Innocents? but friend,
                        What is our ayme? a flight our age denyes,
                        And whither ſhould we flye, but to the graue?
                        O I haue ſo much people in me too,
Enter Maluezzo.
                        
                        That I could wiſh thy company.
                     
                  
                  
                     Mal.
                     
                        Good Heau'ns!
                        Am I eſcap'd? may I ſtay ſafely here?
                        My feare has left ſuch neere impreſſions,
                        I ſcarce dare thinke that this is Liberty.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        ic.
                     Noble Maluezzo, is there any hope?
                  
                  
                     Mal.
                     
                        As much as in deſpaire: we are betraid,
                        
                           Sforza is made a priſoner, all's loſt,
                        And Millan, without blowes, is once more French.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈…〉
                        ic.
                     
                        Now I remember what I dream't laſt night,
                        (If it be ſafe to call a viſion, Dreame,)
                        I ſaw our Sforza in ſo pale a ſhape,
                        That Enuy neuer was deſcrib'd more wan,
                        Who frighted me with this relation.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                     
                        STart not aſtoniſht mortall: let no feare
                        Chill thee to my pale image, but fixe here:
                        Let thy once Prince be thy now ſpectacle,
                        Whilſt I the direſt Tragedy ſhall tell
                        That euer challeng'd wonder: briefly then,
                        I was betraid, betraid, and by thoſe men
                        By whom I conquer'd:] tis an happy end
                        To periſh for, but neuer by a friend.
                        This our firſt death: but then—O could curſt Time
                        Dare euer ſuch a Minute, ſuch a Crime?
                        Then was I pinion'd, then theſe royall hands
                        Were forc'd obedient to the baſe commands
                        Of an inſulting conqueror, and knit
                        Vnto a hated vnion; 
                              •
                           were fit
                        If euer Heau'n ſhed teares, then to diſtill
                        Mournings El
                              •
                           xar, though th'expence ſhould kill
                        The hopes of after Ages: but Heau'n ſmil'd
                        Nor any courteous cloud▪ were wiſely pil'd
                        Ouer the Sunnes ſharpe beame
                              •
                           , but they gaz'd on
                        With the ſame viſage of compaſſion
                        As did my torturers, [by whom I'me brought
                        Vnto a place the which ſome ſhallower thought
                        Has faintly term'd a priſon, but to tell
                        The truth of horror, t'was on Earth, an Hell:
                        Darkneſſe ſo dwell there, that I might be wonne
                        To wiſh the cruell comfort of the Sunne,
                        Which earſt I rau'd at: twas a narrow caue,
                        Form'd to the modell of a leſſer graue,
                        Or ſtraitned Coffin, all was length, for they
                        Left not the height that I might kneele to pray.
                        Was euer ſuch a bed? could euer yet
                        Cruelty boaſt of ſuch a ſubtle wit
                        To bury ſo! ſome that haue entred Earth
                        Aliue, like me, yet by the vſuall mirth
                        
                           Of iuſtice had their buriall with meat,
                        As if't ſhould be their puniſhment to eate,
                        From which I me barr'd, I had no food, but me,
                        And yet a gueſt of famine; courteſie
                        At laſt ceiz'd heau'n, I dy'd, and ſo though late,
                        I both appeas'd and triumpht ouer Fate.
                     
                  
                  
                     But where am I? what extaſie was this?
                  
                  
                     Iul.
                     
                        How quickely we learne miſery? no ghoſt
                        Would haue ſo courteouſly relinquiſht Hell
                        To teach vs happineſſe: if a kind ſtarre
                        Had caſt a Fortune on vs beyond wiſh,
                        We might expect the ſtory from the ſtarre
                        Aſſoone as the deare benefit: but when griefe
                        That againſt which we would ſeale vp our eares,
                        When that is meant vs, we ſhall ſurely heare,
                        Though heau'n doe ſtraine for a new Miracle,
                        So to amaze vs to a certainty:
                        Though rotten carkaſſes regaine a voice,
                        And hell is bounteous of intelligence,
                        To giue vs teares.
                     
                  
                  
                     Pic.
                     
                        Why, then an end to teares,
                        Let's ſcorne the ſorrow, which we owe to hell:
                        Now learne we the prodigious effects
                        Of wiſe Ambition: for twere eaſie iuſtice
                        To ruine fooliſh vſurpation,
                        Heau'n needs not ſtickle in't: but when thoſe men
                        Who are as accurate, as bad, who can
                        So ſhape their vice into a vertuous mould,
                        That we repine at the accuſers more,
                        Then at the guilty: when that theſe men fall,
                        Who then will call that wiſe, which he ſees bad?
                        Such wiſdome made, and ruin'd him: then ye
                        That dazle with your Maieſty, and ſit
                        Too neere to thunder, and not feare it, know
                        
                           
                           Sforza, and learne a wiſe contempt of wiſedome,
                        Frailty attends your beſt, and ſtrongeſt tricke,
                        And there's no foole vnto the Politicke.
                     
                  
               
            
         
         
            The Epilogue.
            
               SOmewhat beyond an end? and can there b
                     •
                  
               
               Tediouſneſſe counted an Apology?
               It was prolixity of ſpeech offended,
               And can that error by more ſpeech be mended?
               Your patience ſtints the wonder: that is it
               Hath dar'd vs to be publike, and to fit
               Theſe times of tempeſt, with a bluſtring ſcene.
               If ought doe pleaſe, if we haue hit the meane,
               That neither cloyes the Auditor, nor ſtarue
                     •
                  ,
               Felicity hath crown'd vs, if ought ſwarues
               From plauſible inuention, know 'twas it
               Which we intend, which is in ſtead of wit.
               Teares grace a Tragedy, and we are glad
               To haue the happy power to make you ſad.
               Continue it, and our applauſe is high,
               Not from your Hand ſo much, as from your eye.
            
         
      
      
         
            To the Ambitious.
            
               TEll me, mortall
                     •
                  , if there be
               Ought beſide ſtupidity
               Hidden in you 
                     〈◊〉
                   the leaſt,
               If you are not all one beaſt
               
                  Wherefore doe you cloud your face
               If you want the chiefeſt place?
               Why doe you reſpect? O why?
               Not how good 'tis, but how high?
               Would you all be King
                     •
                  ? Ô vaine,
               This is but to entertaine
               Such deſires, that you may feare,
               Leſt the heau'n ſhould lend an eare,
               Leſt you haue what you deſir'd,
               And in your owne boggs be myr'd.
               Height is baſeneſſe, if it be
               Leuel'd by Aequality,
               And the Earth were a plaine ſtill.
               If it were but one great hill.
               Would you all be Kings? as though
               Standing pooles ſhould wiſh to flow.
               Or a riue
                     •
                   make his plea
               To exceed into a Sea:
               As if of the ſtars not one,
               But ſhould ſtriue to be the Sun,
               Or the Larke would partner be
               In the Eagles ſoueraignty.
               Would you not be mad to ſee,
               If a beaſt, a ſtone, a tree
               To the heau'nly powers ran
               Angry that they were not man?
               Nay in vs conſider well
               To what Monſters we ſhould ſwell,
               If but any Part ſhould be
               Of the Mans infirmity.
               What ſhould lead, or what be led,
               If the foet were made the Head?
               What ſhould ſpeake, or what ſhould ſee,
               If this itch of Maieſty
               
                  Made the mouth, for being nigh,
               Beg aduancement to the eye.
               Would you all be Kings, poore men!
               Wiſh, what you would wiſh agen,
               Which within your thoughts dares bide,
               And's not fearfull to be try'd.
               What's a King, conſider well,
               But the publike Sentinell?
               But a Beacon, which we find
               Highly ſubiect to the wind?
               And can any ſtill deſire
               To be worſe, ſo he be higher?
               Are you weary of your ſleepe,
               Can you count it bliſſe, to creepe,
               To take paines vnto that height,
               Whence your fall may gaine a weight,
               Would you all be Kings? you may,
               Euery man hath regall ſway,
               And 'tis this the fault does beare,
               Not that he commands, but where
               Doe thy thoughts rebell? would Pride
               Haue thy worſt acts magnifi'd?
               Does Ambition make thee flee
               To forbidden Sou'raignty.
               Know it is a brauer way
               To forbid, then to obey:
               Know it is a nobler deed,
               To giue ouer, then to ſpeed.
               Were this all? would euery one
               But command himſelfe alone,
               But command his owne deſire,
               From the thought of riſing higher:
               It would not be a griefe to ſee
               An vniuerſall Monarchy.
            
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

