
   
      
         
            The arke of noah for the Londoners that remaine in the cittie to enter in, with their families, to be preserued from the deluge of the plague. Item, an exercise for the Londoners that are departed out of the cittie into the coutnrey, to spend their time till they returne. Whereunto is annexed an epistle sent out of the countrey, to the afflicted cittie of London. Made and written by Iames Godskall the yonger, preacher of the word.
            Godskall, James.
         
         
            
               1604
            
         
         Approx. 153 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01800
            STC 11935
            ESTC S120518
            99855714
            99855714
            21216
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01800)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21216)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 774:14)
         
         
            
               
                  The arke of noah for the Londoners that remaine in the cittie to enter in, with their families, to be preserued from the deluge of the plague. Item, an exercise for the Londoners that are departed out of the cittie into the coutnrey, to spend their time till they returne. Whereunto is annexed an epistle sent out of the countrey, to the afflicted cittie of London. Made and written by Iames Godskall the yonger, preacher of the word.
                  Godskall, James.
               
               [132] p.   
               
                  Printed by Thomas Creede,
                  London :
                  [1604]
               
               
                  Publication date from STC.
                  Signatures: A-H I² .
                  Imperfect; Date obliterated.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Guildhall Library.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Plague --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2006-03
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2006-03
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2006-04
            Jonathan BlaneySampled and proofread
         
            2006-04
            Jonathan BlaneyText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2006-09
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE ARKE
of Noah,
FOR
The Londoners that remaine in the Cittie
to enter in, with their families, to be preſerued
from the deluge of the Plague.
            Item,
An Exerciſe for the Londoners that are departed out
of the Citie into the Countrey, to ſpend their time
till they returne.
            Wherevnto is annexed an Epiſtle ſent out of
the Countrey, to the afflicted Citie of London.
            
            Made and written by Iames Godskall the yonger,
Preacher of the word.
            
               Pſal. 50. 15. Call vpon me in the day of trouble and I will deliuer thee, and thou
ſhalt glorifie me.
            
               Dan. 9. 18. O my God, encline thine eare, and heare: open thine eyes, and behold
our deſolations, and the Citie wherevpon thy name is
called.
            LONDON
Printed by Thomas Creede
         
         
            
            
            AN EPISTLE TO
the afflicted Citie of London.
            
               To all you that be at London, beloued of God, called to be
Saints. Grace be with you, and peace from God our Father,
and the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, Rom. 1. 7. with all
that call on the name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt in euery
place, both their Lord, and ours. 1. Cor. 1. 2.
               
            
            
               AS Naomi (dearely beloued in the
Lord) the title of honourable at this
time I do omit) ſpake vnto the people
which ſawe her;Ruth. 1. 20. Call mee not
Naomi, (which ſoundeth beautifull
or pleaſant) but call me Mara, for the
almightie hath giuen me much bitterneſſe,
the Lord hath humbled me, &amp; the Almightie
hath brought me vnto aduerſitie. So likewiſe thou
afflicted London, mayeſt anſwere to them that ſee, and
heare of thee: Call me not Naomi, but Mara, for the
Almightie hath brought thee now vnto aduerſitie.
In which affliction I may ſpeake with the Apoſtle,
wee are mindfull of your teares.
               2. Tim. 1. 4. And although as Paul
ſpeaketh, we be abſent in the fleſh, yet are wee with
you in the ſpirit, Coll. 2. 5. kept from you for a ſeaſon,
concerning ſight, but not in the heart. 1. Theſſ. 2. 17.
               
For we haue you in perfect memorie. Phil. 1. 3. hauing
you in our hearts. 2. Cor. 7. 3. And thus being affectioned
toward you, 1. Theſſ. 2▪ 8. without ceaſing,
God is my witneſſe, (with the Apoſtle wee may proteſt)
we make mention of you alwaies in our prayers.
Rom. 9. 1. 10. Of thee ô London, with the Leuites of Ieruſalem,
vnfeignedly I may ſpeake, Pſal. 137. 5. If I forget
thee ô Ieruſalem, let my right hand forget to play: If I doo
not remember thee, let my tongue cleaue to the roofe of my
mouth. True it is, by the Riuers of Babel as it were wee
ſit in a pleaſant Countrey;Pſ. 137. but neuertheleſſe, here we
weepe, when we remember thee ô London; we hang
vp our harpes, and the pleaſantneſſe of the countrey
cannot ſtay our teares, remembring you that are afflicted,Heb 13. 3.
as if we were afflicted our ſelues, weeping for
the Citie, as Chriſt did for Ieruſalem, Luk. 19. and not
onely for you, but for our ſelues. Luk▪ 23. 28. How
could we feaſt, while the yron enters Ioſephs ſoule in
the Citie? We are not Nero, ſinging and triumphing
when Rome is on fire, but as Abraham prayed for Sodome,
and the Prophet for the peace of Ieruſalem, ſo
we for the peace of London. As for the Romiſh Edomites,
the ſuperſtitious Papiſts, who reioyce at this
ours and your preſent calamitie, inſulting ouer vs in
this land, and in others, preaching it vnto theirs publikely,
and muttering it priuately, that this deluge of
the plague is iuſtly broken through among vs, becauſe
we haue (as they ſpeake) forſaken the religion
and profeſſion of our forefathers; iuſtly we doo acknowledge,
although it is falſely imputed to that pretended
cauſe. What is this their accuſation elſe, but
that old ſong of the ſuperſtitious Iſraelits, Ier. 44. 18. 19▪
               
               
Since wee left off to burne incenſe to the Queene of
heauen, we haue had ſcarceneſſe of things, and haue
beene conſumed by the ſword and famine. Were not
alſo the good Chriſtians in the time of Tertullian, Cyprian,
Arnobius, and others, in this manner vpbrayed
by the Heathens, who imputed to them the cauſe of
Peſtilence, Warre, Invndations, Earthquakes, and
other troubles? But O yee blind ſonnes of men, what
was the cauſe of the flood in the time of Noah? was it
the Religion of that time, or was it Noah the preacher
of righteouſneſſe? The Lord himſelfe ſheweth the
cauſe, Gene. 6. and 7. Chap. the ſinnes of that age, and
the flood of iniquitie. For which like ſinnes, both we,
and their profeſſors alſo, as well as we at diuers times
haue felt this rod, and alſo at this preſent time in Flanders
they doo taſte of this ſmart-whip: which giueth
vs iuſt occaſion to ſpeake vnto them that of the Prophet,Iere. p 18.
               Thine inuentions haue procured thee theſe things.
Remember O Lord the children of Edom (theſe ſuperſtitious
Romaniſts) which ſpeake,Pſal 137. 7▪ 8. raſe it, raſe it to
the foundation thereof. O daughter of Babel worthie to
be destroyed. But from whence am I digreſſed? To returne
to the head of the race, where I firſt began, I returne
to you my brethren with ſighes, to whome, I
may vſe the Apoſtles words,2. Cor. 2, 4. 
               In anguiſh of heart I write
vnto you with many teares. Of Prayer, of which this
treatiſe following doeth intreate: I may ſpeake that
which Martha ſaid vnto Chriſt, If thou hadſt beene here,
my brother ſhould not haue died. So likewiſe, if feruent
and humble prayer had beene amongſt vs, we ſhould
not haue ſuffered theſe things. But ſeeing wee are in
the flood, and that the waters are entred euen to our

ſoules, Pſal. 69. 1. Therefore behold, againſt this deluge
I ſend to you a delineation of the true Arke of
Noah, whereunto yee and we ought to flie to be preſerued,
which is the name of Iehouah, Prou. 18. 10. the
little Zoar, and the Sanctuarie to hide and ſafegard
our ſelues.
            Two things beloued, may put you in minde this
yeere of two things. Firſt, of Noah: Secondly, of Ionas
withered Gourd, vnto which your preſent calamitie
for diuers reſpects fitly may be compared.
            
                The firſt is, your great ioyes, preparations and
ſtately buildings in the beginning of the yeere, like
vnto the ioy, feaſting, marrying, and building of thoſe
who liued in the dayes of Noah, Matth. 24. Luke 17.
            
            
                The ſecond is, the ſuddaine alteration which enſued
thereupon, like vnto the vnexpected flood and
deluge which came vpon the ſecuritie of the olde
world. We liued before as in the dayes of Noah, wee
are now as it were in the flood (the afflictions and
troubles of the ſonnes of men being not vnfitly compared
vnto waters by the Kingly Prophet Dauid)
which prayer at this time London thou mayeſt make,
Saue me O God,
               Pſal. 69. 1. 
               for the waters are entred euen to my ſoule.
Seeing therefore, that thou with Ionas mayeſt ſay,
Lord, the floods compaſſe me about, what remaineth
but that we enter into the Arke to be preſerued? Giue
me leaue beloued, by a compariſon to ſhew you two
things, the flood wherewith ye are compaſſed about,
and the Arke which yee ought to enter.
            In the flood of Noah the holy Ghoſt noteth foure
 things; Firſt, the cauſe for which it was ſent. Secondly
the time when it began. Thirdly, the cōtinuance of it.

Fourthly, his decreaſing. The cauſe of which, was
the ſinne of that age, which was growen vp as a mightie
tree, producing diuers ſower and deadly fruites.
The firſt was, the great ſecuritie of the ſonnes of God,
that is of thoſe which made profeſſion of the true Religion,
eating and drinking, marrying and building,
Luke 17. 27. The ſecond, their diſobedience and contemning
of Noah, the Preacher of righteouſneſſe, and
of the long ſuffering of God,Gene. 6. 1, 2. 
               1. Pet. 3. 20. The third,
their fornications, and vngodly alliances with the infidels,
and with that damnable race of Cain, without
reſpect either of family or Religion. The fourth, their
crueltie and oppreſſion of their neighbours, Gene. 6.
11. and 13. Laſtly, the corruption of their wayes, Gen.
6. 12. and becauſe their wickedneſſe was great vpon
the earth. 2. Sam. This is alſo the cauſe (to applie the
firſt to our ſelues) which hath mooued the Lord to
ſend this deluge of the Plague into the land, becauſe
the ſelfe ſame ſinnes did raigne among vs: and as it
was in the dayes of Noah, ſo hath it beene in theſe
laſt dayes of the ſonne of man:Luke 27. 26. and therefore ſeeing
a flood of iniquitie hath ouerwhelmed vs, hath not
this flood of the Plague iuſtly and ſuddenly ouertaken
vs?
            From the firſt let me leade you to the ſecond, the 
circumſtance of the time, when the flood began, noted
in the 7. Chap. of Gene. ver. 11. In the ſecond moneth,
the ſeuenteenth day of the moneth, which was
about the beginning of May, or as others ſay in April,
when all things did moſt flouriſh, and when it was
leſſe expected, which ſuddenneſſe hath changed their
ioy into ſorow. So likewiſe, to applie the ſecond to vs,

this deluge of the Plague began to encreaſe about the
beginning of May (as I haue noted) when all things
did flouriſh in the Countrey, and in the Citie, when
we were merrie as the ſonnes of the old world, marrying,
feaſting, building, and erecting our armes trivmphants,
when we leſſe expected it, which hath turned
alſo our ioy into ſorrow.
            And as Noahs flood cauſed them to flie vpon high
mountaines and trees that the waters ſhould not
reach vnto them: So this deluge hath it not cauſed
thouſands to depart into the Countrey farre and
neere to be preſerued?
            
                From the ſecond I come to the third, the continuance
of the flood, noted Gen. 7. 24. The waters couered,
and preuailed vpon the earth an hundreth and fiftie dayes
(which is about halfe a yeere) and then, in the end of
an hundreth and fiftie dayes the waters abated, Gene.
8. 3. which was in Nouember, reckning from the beginning
of them. To applie the third, our deluge
hath not yet preuailed an hundreth and fiftie dayes,
and I hope through the mercie of God, that it wil not
ſo long encreaſe and bee in his full ſtrength and force,
(and yet O Lord, by the great flood of our iniquitie
we haue deſerued a longer encreaſing, But haue mercie
vpon vs O Lord according to the multitude of thy compaſsions,
Pſal. 51. 1.) Let mee applie the fourth thing,
which is the decreaſing of Noahs flood, noted Gen. 8. 5▪
               
and they decreaſed vntil the tenth moneth (which
was the moneth of December) this decreaſing beginning
from Nouember, after the hundreth and fiftie
dayes. Our flood the Lord bee thanked, hath begun
reaſonably to decreaſe in the moneth of September,

and the Lord graunt that theſe waters from henceforward
may not bee going and comming, but that
they may altogether decreaſe vntill the tenth month.
And as the tops of the mountaines which were couered
becauſe of the flood, were ſeene in the tenth
moneth, Gene. 8. 5. which was in December: So the
Lord graunt, that the heads of the Citie, the Merchants,
and principall Citizens, which becauſe of
this deluge haue beene couered, may be ſeene againe
in the Citie, the tenth moneth. Further, as on the
firſt day of the firſt moneth, Gene. 8. 13. the vpper part
of the ground was wholly drie, which was in March
and part of Aprill. So the Lord graunt that this deluge
may in that moneth wholly bee dried vp, and
that there remaine not any reliques therof: if it pleaſe
him to remember vs in his mercie as hee did Noah,
Gene. 8. 1. Now that he may remember vs in his mercie,
let vs forſake the ſinnes of the olde world, let the
flood of iniquitie which is broken through among vs
decreaſe, and wholly be dried vp. Great hath beene,
and extraordinarie (I doo confeſſe) the invndation
of the Plague this preſent yeere, and therefore let our
repentance bee great and extraordinarie. It is reported
of many of the Aegyptians by Sozom, lib. 7. cap. 20.
that being terrified by the ſtrange invndation of Nilus,
higher then the wonted maner thereof was, immediatly
they condemned their ancient Idolatry, and
applied themſelues to the worſhip of the liuing God:
So likewiſe, ſeeing that this deluge of the Plague hath
beene higher then the wonted maner, as the weekly
Bils doo ſhewe vnto vs, let vs bee terrified, and remooue
our ancient iniquities, let vs applie our ſelues

to humble and feruent prayer, a principall part of the
worſhip of God. And as the Arke in the flood reſted
vpon the high mountaines of Ararat, Gene. 8. 4. So
let vs in this flood reſt vpon the Lord, and vpon the
holy mountaine of Heauen; the power and mercie of
our God, are the mountaines whereupon the Arke
may finde reſt; thoſe are the holy hils whereon Sion
hath her euerlaſting foundation.
            Hauing ſhewed to you the flood, I come to the
Arke. The holy Ghoſt in the deſcription of the Arke
into which Noah entred, Gene. 6. and 7. noteth theſe
fiue things. The Arke it ſelfe. The perſons entring.
The cauſe why. The time when. The end wherefore.
            
                As for the Arke, into which wee muſt enter, it is
not an Arke made of corruptible wood, nor an Arke
heere beneath ſloating and toſſing in the ſea of this
world, but the true Arke of Noah, and of the righteous,
the name of the Lord, that ſtrong tower wherevnto
the righteous runneth by the feete of prayer,
Prou. 18. 10. an immortall, eternall, and incorruptible
Arke. I know no ſurer refuge from the tempeſt, as
Eſai ſpeaketh, no ſafer harbour, and receptacle, wherin
to repoſe your wearied ſoules.
            
                The perſons entring, were Noah and his family.
Noah the righteous, or the Preacher of righteouſneſſe
as he is called, 2. Pet. 2. 5. Noah and his little family, the
remnant of the earth, as the ſonne of Syrach termeth
them. Let vs with our families enter into the aforeſaid
Arke, and although they conſiſt more then of
eightie and eight ſoules, yea of infinite, they cannot
fill this Arke, neither hinder one another, as it happeneth
in the bulwarkes and fortreſſes of mortall

men; but let vs be righteous Noahs: for how can wee
be elſe preſerued? If wee enter as an impious Cham,
perhaps we ſhall eſcape a temporall flood, but not the
deluge of Gods eternall wrath.
            The cauſe moouing Noah to enter, was the Commandement 
of God, Gene. 7. 1. Enter, &amp;c. the ſame
cauſe ought to mooue vs to enter, it is the Commandement
of the moſt high, the Proclamation of the
King of heauen, Pſal. 50. 15. Cal vpon me, &amp;c. And as in
the time of the olde world hee ordained himſelfe an
Arke for Noah, ſo he hath himſelfe prepared, appointed
and ordained himſelfe as an Arke and refuge for
the righteous Noahs.
            
            The time when, was in the flood, Gene. 7. 7. So 
               Noah entred, becauſe of the waters of the flood: Are
not we in the flood?Pſal. 6. 9. 1. Are not the waters entred euen
to our ſoules? And is it not therefore high time to
keepe our ſelues within this Arke?
            The end wherefore, (that he might bee preſerued,
               Gen. 6. 18, 19.) For the ſame ende let vs enter beloued,
to bee preſerued from a threefold deluge, from the
flood of iniquitie wherewith our ſoules haue beene
ouerwhelmed; from the deluge of the Plague, that
calling vpon the name of the Lord, and ſeeking his
peſence the land may be healed, 2. Chron. 7. 14. Thirdly,
from the deluge of Gods eternall wrath. Follow
therefore the obedience of Noah, Gene. 7. 6. who did
according vnto all that the Lord commanded him,
and was alſo remembred, Gene. 8. 1. Enter therefore
O yee righteous ſoules, let your miſerie ſpeake for
audience. The waues doo now ſmite and toſſe your
ſhip; and as the tempeſt aroſe, Matth. 8. when they

were a ſleepe: So likewiſe this preſent tempeſt wherewith
we are toſſed, did ariſe when wee are a ſleepe,
but ariſe,Matth 8. ariſe from the ſleepe of ſecuritie, call vnto
Chriſt with the Diſciples, Maiſter ſaue vs, or elſe wee
periſh. Caſt your eyes on high (as the Marriner in the
tempeſt) Ad ſtellam polarem, on the right North ſtarre
Chriſt Ieſus, who is alſo the bright morning ſtarre,
Apoc. 22. 16. And in the ſea of theſe afflictions, Quite
you like men,
               1. Cor. 16. 13. 
               and be ſtrong, (tis the Apoſtles precept)
begin you to the ores of the Spirit, inuocations, interceſſions
to the liuing God, praying as the Apoſtle
exhorteth, Ephe. 6. 18. With all maner of prayer and ſupplication
in the Spirit, with all perſeuerance. The arme of
fleſh is too weake to beare vs out, and if our ſtrength
were braſſe, it could not helpe vs: Theſe are my brethren,
the onely ores which are able to row our ſhip
through all the ſtormes of the ſea, (theſe veſſels of our
bodies and ſoules I meane) and if the bankes of the
land doo faile vs, that is temporall health, they will
land vs in the hauen of eternall felicitie.
            
                Giue mee leaue brethren in the ſecond place, to
amplifie vnto you another compariſon, not vnfit for
this time, for the ſuddaine alteration and eſtate of this
yeere, doth put me in minde not onely of the flood of
Noah,
               Ion. 4. but alſo of Ionas Gourd. To enter therein, firſt
 our Citie (as yee all know) hath long bene, and principally
in the beginning of the yeere for diuers reſpects
a flouriſhing Gourd, and as a greene Laurell
tree, wee had builded a Tabernacle of pleaſures, yea
Arches, and Theaters, and ſome of the workes like
Babel. Proſperitie as a Gourd was come ouer vs, we
were ſitting vnder the ſhadow of it, euery one as the

Prophet ſpeaketh vnder his vine,Mic. 4. 4. and vnder his figge
tree, none making vs afraide; and perhaps, (what doo
I adde perhaps?) Without doubt many of vs in this
our proſperitie haue ſpoken with Dauid,
               Pſal. 30. 6. I ſaid in my
proſperitie, I ſhall neuer be mooued. Secondly, as Ionas
               
reioyced exceedingly for the Gourd: So likewiſe
haue we reioyced exceedingly for this our proſperitie,
witneſſe our feaſtes, our braueries, preparations,
and triumphs, (would to God that it had beene in
the Lord.) And as Peter was reioyced to be vpon the
mountaine,Matth. 17. ſaying, Maiſter it is good to bee here, let vs
make here three Tabernacles: whereas hee was but a
ſtranger, and knew that there was not the permanent
Citie,Pſal. 119. 
               Heb. 13. 14. So although we know we are
but ſtrangers in this life, yet we haue ſaid to our fleſh,
as Peter vnto Chriſt, let vs make here Tabernacles.
And therefore as the Gourd of Ionas ſuddenly withered,
and his exceeding ioy was changed into ſorrow:
ſo our ioyfull ſongs haue beene changed into lamentations,Lam. 1. 16.
and our pleaſure hath beene quite daſht; the
Lord hath made vs to ſay with Ieremie, For theſe things
I weepe, and mine eye caſteth out water. Hee hath made
others to ſay of thee, O London, as Ieremie of Ieruſalem,
how doth the Citie remaine ſolitarie that was
full of people, ſhee is a widow, ſhee that was great
among the nations, her Prieſts ſigh, her virgins are
diſcomfited, and ſhee is in heauineſſe, Lam. 1. 1. And
hereunto I may adde that in the fifth verſe, it is for
the multitude of her tranſgreſſions, for which her
people is now in diuers places ſcattered, liuing as it
were in exile and baniſhment, and ſighing (as the Iſraelites
did in Babel) when they remembred thee O
London. But the Lord hath giuen, and the Lord

hath taken away, and hee that had power ouer the
bleſſings, hath alſo had power ouer the plagues,
Apoc. 6. As Ionas little thought of ſo ſpeedie an alteration;
ſo did we little expect ſuch a ſudden change; but
it was feared and alſo prophecied of many (as I my
ſelfe haue heard) and behold the trueth of their prophecie.
Nullum violentem perpetuum. Some haue died
through immoderate ioy, as Diagoras of Rhodes, and
others, and we (I may ſay) haue beene ſicke through
immoderate ioy, and ſome dead. The ſonnes and
daughters of England in this their exceeding ioy, did
little thinke of this ſorrow, as the ſonnes and daughters
of Iob, when they were banquetting, did not
once dreame of the wind that came from the wilderneſſe
and ſmote the foure corners of the houſe. Babylon
which was called tender and delicate, and the
Lady of kingdomes, Ephe. 4. 7. which aſſumed to her
ſelfe, I am, and there is none elſe: I ſhall not ſit a widow,
nor know the loſſe of children; did not imagine
how neere they were, that came with a contrarie
newes (Thine ende is come, Iere. 51.) Neither London
tender and delicate which hath vſed the ſame voice,
did expect to bee a widow for a time, and to ſee the
loſſe of her children by thouſands. You the Edomites
and Epicures of theſe dayes, yee that haue mocked
your Prophets and watchmen, as they did, Ephe.
21. ſaying to them, (yee ſpeake of iudgement) haue
yee not a time of ſorrow and darkneſſe, as yee haue
had a time of light and delights?
            
                The time when the Gourd withered, was when
the morning, or the Sunne did ariſe, in the comming
foorth of the Sunne, when the ſhadow of it ſhould

moſt haue pleaſured him: So in the riſing as it were
of the Citie (which by the death of our late Soueraigne
had beene as it were laide downe in the bed of
ſorrow) and in the comming foorth of a new Sunne,
whoſe beames were comfortable to the whole land
(and the Lord graunt that he may long ſhine ouer
vs) euen then, when proſperitie could not haue pleaſured
the Citie, and all her inhabitants, then the
Gourd withered, and the worme of Gods iudgement
came. And as Chriſt wept ouer Ieruſalem in
the midſt of his triumph, when the people cried,
Bleſſed is the King that commeth in the name of the Lord,
               Luk. 19. 38.
               when the multitudes did reioyce, and ſpred their cloathes in
the way: So the Lord hath giuen vs cauſe to weepe
ouer the Citie, when we were almoſt in the midſt of
our ioyes and triumphes, when euery one was reioycing,
and made preparations for the triumph, againſt
the entire of him, of whom we may ſay, as the Iſraelites
of Dauid, Pſal. 118. 26. Bleſſed be hee that commeth
in the name of the Lord. Let the concluſion of this point
be, all thy iudgements O Lord are number and meaſure,
thou knowed beſt the time when it is moſt conuenient
to inflict them.
            The meanes or the inſtrument (which is the fifth 
thing to bee conſidered) which the Lord vſed to afflict
Ionas, and which hee ſent as a meſſenger from
heauen, to ſmite the Gourd, was firſt (a worme)
ſecondly, the wind and the Sunne. The worme, a little
and a baſe meſſenger, with weapons of no power,
and yet giueth a mortall blow, he that could haue
ſent a great wind to turne it vpſide-downe, a lightning
to haue blaſted it, or a whole armie of wormes,

ſendeth but one little contemptible worme to execute
that buſineſſe: So the Lord to beate downe the
pride and immoderate ioy of our Citie, the flouriſhing
Gourd of our proſperitie, hath not ſent whole armies,
deuouring beaſts, Earthquakes, fire or brimſtone
from heauen, he ſendeth only a peſtilence, litle
Carbuncles, ſpots, and tokens in our fleſh, which
ſeeme to bee nothing, or to haue no force, and yet
ſuddainely they beate downe the proudeſt and the
ſtrongeſt. Iſt not ſtrange that a little botch or carbuncle
hath ſuch admirable force? Well may they be called
Gods tokens, for thereby he ſheweth his ſtrength.
Let this ſerue on the one ſide, to make vs to ſtand in
awe of the mightie power of God, and on the other
ſide, adoring this his power, to humble our ſelues before
his Maieſtie; for how dareſt thou O ſonne of Adam
lift vp thy ſelfe againſt that Lord, who can caſt
thee downe with a little carbuncle? Let not the pleaſures
of this life make vs ſecure, and ſitting vnder the
couert of them; let vs not ſay, we ſhal neuer be mooued,
for they are but Gourds, and the Lord hath a
worme of iudgement. And what is the freedom from
the rod of God, our dauncing to the Tabert &amp; Harpe,
but a Gourd for a time? I call to witneſſe young men,
yee luſtie gallants,Iob. 12. ſome of you haue had your Gourd
to reioyce in, Eccle. 11. the dayes of your youth, the
cheerfulneſſe of your hearts, the luſtes of your owne
eyes; but the Lords worme, the peſtilence, hath ſmitten
downe ſome of you. Rich men, ſome of you, haue
had your Gourd, your purple and fine linnen your
delicious fare euery day, Luk. 16. But this is withered
with your ſelues, and ſome of you lie in the graue.

The worme then which the Lord had prepared for
this yeare, to change our ioy into ſorow, is as now experience
teacheth, the Peſtilence, the King of heauens
Purſiphant; and therefore wee may crie with the Angels,
Apoc. 14. With a lowde voice, feare God, and giue glorie
to him, for the houre of his iudgement is come. The ſecond 
inſtrument which the Lord vſed, was the wind
and the Sunne, good creatures, created both for an
other ende, to gouerne the day, to giue light to the
world, to purifie the ayre, &amp;c. and yet they receiue a
commandement to beate vpon the head of Ionas, the
principall part of the body, wherein is the gouernement
of the whole creature: the ſeate of the minde,
from whence the ſenſes and neereneſſe take their beginning.
So the Lord hath commanded his Angel to
infect the ayre, to hunt &amp; annoy vs, both good creatures,
erected to another end, to preſerue and comfort
vs, and yet behold he hath commanded them to
beate the very head, the principall part of the body of
his kingdome, our Citie I meane beloued, the ſeate
and imperiall Chamber of the Realme, from whence
the other members receiue their maintenance, which
redoundeth to the danger of the whole body, for
which the members and the daughters haue ſmarted,
and yet doo ſigh for; which argueth that our ſinnes
make the good creatures of God to become our enemies.
Seeing therfore the Lord hath ſmitten you that
are the head, let not the effects which it wrought in
Ionas, bee ſeene in you. Firſt, faint not, although the 
force of heate is great, be ſteadfaſt, and aboundant alwayes
in the worke of the Lord, 1. Cor. 15. 58. And I
would not brethren haue you ignorant, concerning

them that are a ſleepe, that ye ſorrow not euen as they
which haue no hope, 1. Theſ. 4. 13. Be not aſhamed of
the teſtimonie of our Lord, 2. Tim. 1. 8. but ſuffer as
good ſouldiers of Chriſt, 2. Tim. 2. 3. The Lord hath
not caſt thee downe without reuocation of his fact, he
afflicteth thee not in his furie, but in his mercie, to doo
thee greater honour and fauour in the time to come,
if this in iudgement mooue thee. Let this heate inflame
your hearts with the fire of Gods loue, that the
Lord ſay not of vs, Amos 4. I haue ſmitten you with blaſting
               
               and burning, and you returned not. Secondly, be not
angrie and impatient, wiſh not deſperately to die,
grudge not, nor repine at the Lord, but let your patient
mind be knowen vnto all men, Phil. 4. 5. to whom
doo yee rather owe the quietneſſe and ſubiection of
your ſpirits, then vnto him, who giueth both his benefites
vnto vs, to teach how eaſily hee can beſtow
them, and taketh them away, that we may know how
little wee deſerue them: with Ionas out of the waters
which did compaſſe him, call rather vpon the
name of the Lord, follow him not in his anger, but in
his prayer.Rom. 15. 15. I haue brethren (to vſe the Apoſtles
words) ſomwhat boldly after a ſort written vnto you,
as one that putteth you in remembrance thereof,
through the grace which is giuen me of God: but yet
as Paul ſpeaketh,2. Cor. 1 13. 
               Wee write none other things vnto you,
then that yee reade, or elſe that yee acknowledge. For this I
ſay not by commandement, 2. Cor. 8. 8. But this ſay we vnto
you by the word of the Lord, 1. Theſ. 4. 15. you haue
already entred this Arke, for wee haue heard of your
faſting, prayer, and liberalitie to the poore, how that
yee haue charged them that are rich in the world to

doo good, and to be readie to diſtribute, 1. Tim. 6. 17,
18. And therfore, although we are abſent in the fleſh,
yet are we with you in the ſpirit, reioycing and beholding
(tis the Apoſtles ſaying) your order, and your
ſteadfaſt faith in Chriſt, waiting for his appearing, 1.
Cor. 1. 7. So continue in the Lord,
               Col. 2. 4. 
               Phi. 4. 1. And be not weary
in well doing, 2. Theſ. 3. 13. And I am perſwaded of this
ſame thing, that hee that hath begun this good worke
in you, will performe it, Phil. 1. 6. Follow the zeale of
Abraham in his prayer for Sodome;
               Gene. 18. the longer hee talked
with God, the more he gained. And as Abraham although
he had begun to ſpeake once, twiſe, &amp; thrice
vnto the Lord, yet he continued: Behold I haue begun
to ſpeake vnto my Lord, and am but duſt &amp; aſhes,
let not my Lord bee angrie and I will ſpeake againe:
So although yee haue begun to ſpeake vnto the Lord
for London, that the fire might be quenched (yee that
may ſpeake with Abraham, we are but duſt and aſhes)
yet ſpeake againe, pray continually, Rom. 12. For the
Lord will not bee angrie, as hee was not angrie with
Abrahams inſtant requeſt, but as he gaue him a patient
eare and a gracious anſwere, Ver. 32. ſo the ſame God
will heare our prayers. It pleaſeth the eares of his Maieſtie
to be long intreated; he that hath twiſe and tentimes
together ingeminated the riches of his mercie,
Exod. 34. The Lord, the Lord is mercifull, gracious,
ſlow to anger, aboundant in goodneſſe and trueth, reſeruing
mercy for thouſands, forgetting iniquitie and
ſinne: what did he meane thereby, but that twiſe and
tentimes together we ſhould crie for his mercie. And
as Abraham by his continuance, and ingeminating
prayer, brought the Lord from fiftie to fortie fiue:

from fortie fiue to fortie: from fortie to thirtie: from
thirtie to twentie: and laſtly from twentie to ten: So
continue and ingeminate your prayer, endeuour by
your continuance to diminiſh the number, and to
bring it from thirtie foure hundreth to thirtie: from
thirtie to two hundreth: from twentie to ten: from ten
hundreth to ten perſons: and yet not then ceaſe to
ſpeake vnto the Lords as Abraham did: and what ſhall
not your prayer obtaine? I may ſpeake vnto you that
which Zedekias ſaid to the Princes of his land; The
King can denie you nothing.
               Iere. 38. 5. So the King of heauen will
denie you nothing. Zedekias ſpake it in a ſeruile and
popular affection that hee bare to the Princes of his
land, but God ſpeaketh it out of the aboundance and
riches of his mercie. And therefore O Lord let thy
mercie triumph againſt iuſtice, that both great and
ſmall, the infant and dumbe beaſt, may ſing of thy louing
kindneſſe. With this wiſh I will end beſeeching
brethren for our Lord Ieſus Chriſts ſake, and for the
loue of the ſpirit, that ye would ſtriue with vs by praiers
to God, Rom. 15. 13. Praying alſo for vs, Col. 4. 3. Finally
beloued,2. Cor. 13. 11. fare yee well (it is the Apoſtles farewell
to the Corinthians) bee of good comfort and of
one minde: The grace of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and
the loue of God, and the comming of the holy Ghoſt
be with you all, Amen.
            
            
               Written at Springfield, the
28. of September, 1603.
               
               
                  Your wel-wiſher in the Lord, Iames Godskal the yonger.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            THE ARKE OF
NOAH.
            
               Collected out of the 18. Chapter of
the Prouerbs, verſe 10.
               The name of the Lord is a ſtrong tower: the righteous runneth
vnto it, and is preſerued.
               Confirmed by the practiſe of King Dauid,
1. Chron. Chap. 21. ver. 17. and 26.
               And he called vpon the Lord, and hee anſwered him by fire
from heauen.
            
            
               THe whole Colledge of the bodily Phyſitians,
and the prince of them, that wiſe
and learned Galen, preſcribe for the time
of Plague, that of all remedies, to preuent
the contagion, the beſt is, to flie
and ſhunne the infected and corrupted
ayre, and to depart vnto a wholeſome
and purer ayre: and that with theſe three
rules, Citò, longè, tradè. Depart ſpeedily, farre off, and returne
ſlowly. As this is phyſically preſcribed, ſo it is diligently
practiſed, as daily experience teacheth, of all ſorts of men,
yea of the Phyſitians themſelues; I will not contradict the
preſcription of the Phyſitian, nor diſprooue the diligence of
the ſonnes of men, if they vſe departure lawfully, therein not
ſinning, (Contra patriam, charitatem, vecationem,) againſt
their Countrey, their calling, and Chriſtian charitie. But becauſe,
by the corruption of our nature, we ſuffer our ſelues as

with maine ſayle to be carried away from the Creator to the
creature; fixing all our ſenſes more vpon the aeriall corruption,
then vpon the inward cauſe of the contagion, the rottenneſſe
of our bones, which we carrie within our ſelues, and are
more carefull to depart into the Countrey then vnto the
Lord; as if by the ſwiftneſſe of our feete we could out-runne
him who rideth vpon the wings of the Cherubims,Pſal. 10. 4. which
cauſeth that the Lord hath a Purſiphant, which hee ſendeth
to arreſt ſome in the pure ayre, (namely the Plague it ſelfe)
which hath arreſted ſome in the Countrey, as the experience
of this yeere ſheweth vnto vs all, verifying the threatning
of the Lord, Deut. 28. 22. This is the reaſon why the whole
Colledge of the ſpirituall Phyſition of our ſoules haue preſcribed
for the time of Plague, a better flight and departure,
then that which is preſcribed by Galen and the reſt; namely
(to the name of Iehouah) by the feete of prayer, mentioned
and ſtoried by that wiſe Salomon in the words prefixed. And
as it is preſcribed, ſo it hath beene practiſed of the Saints of
God: among the reſt, of King Dauid in the time of Plague,
as the ſecond place adioyning vnto the firſt doth witneſſe.
Of this place then, which is the right Arke, and the little
Zoar, whereunto our firſt care ought to bee in the time of
plague to depart, and which is alſo the truſtie friend and ſeruant
to aide the ſicke, and the exerciſe for them that are departed,
to ſpend the time till they returne, giue me leaue
Chriſtian Readers to diſcourſe out of the harmonie of theſe
two places here prefixed.
            To pray well ſaith Chryſoſtome, is an excellent art, which
doth adorne a Chriſtian, but it is not ſufficient to know that
we muſt pray, but alſo in what manner: and therefore that we
might the better be inſtructed in the going to this place, and
become skilfull in this art, I will braunch the deſcription of
this place into theſe three ſeuerall parts, which will ſtore vs
with a cluſter of ſingular meditations.
            The firſt is, the name of the place, it is (the name of the
Lord.) The ſecond is, the qualitie, condition, propertie, and
the ſafeneſſe of it, expreſſed in two things: Firſt, becauſe it is

               (a ſtrong towre): ſecondly, by the ſucceſſe of thoſe that runne
vnto it (and is exalted) or deliuered: which is the thing which
they receiue that run to it.
            The third thing is, what maner of perſons they muſt be
that flie to it, and what houſehould ſtuffe they muſt carrie thither
with them to be receiued, noted in theſe words (the rightious
runneth vnto it.) As for the place, let me obſerue 
                  〈◊〉
                things. For as in the time of plague, for our departure, firſt it
is neceſſarie, that we know the name of the place whereunto
we go: ſecondly, that we haue feet to beare &amp; carie vs thither:
thirdly, that we haue a directiō that we might not erre: fourthly,
that wee haue ſome right &amp; intereſt there, or ſome acquaintance,
that we may be receiued. So likewiſe theſe foure things
are neceſſarie to be knowne of vs, in our ſpirituall departure.
            Touching the name of the place whereunto Dauid fled in 
the time of plague,The name of the place. as it hath diuers names, ſo in this place it is
called the name of Iehouah. Heere I pertermit the fiue ſeueral
ſignifications of the name of the Lord vſed in the book of
God, taking it in this place, firſt for the Lord himſelf: ſecondly,
for his attributes by which hee doth manifeſt himſelfe. Of
which Moſes, Num 14. bringeth in a perfect catalogue: &amp; the
Lord hath deliuered this his name by proclamation, Exo. 34.
5. 6. The Lord, the Lord, ſtrong, merciful, &amp; gratious, ſlow to
anger, &amp; aboundant in goodnes and truth, &amp;c. God then the
almightie, eternall, immortall inuiſible Lord, the iudge of the
world, Pſal 94. 2. God, merciful &amp; gratious, the ſupreme phiſition
of our ſoules, who healeth all our iniquities, Pſal. 103.
God to whom power belongeth, and whoſe is ſaluation alone,
Pſal. 62. is the place it ſelfe whereunto Dauid, and wee
ought to flie from the contagion. The name of a place if it be
known, famous and renowned, hath often much force to perſwade
vs rather to goe vnto ſuch a place, then vnto ſuch or
ſuch: ſurely there was neuer name of place more worthy to
goe vnto, then the name of Iehouah. O ye righteous ſoules
that thirſt by reaſon of the heate of the plague vpon your
beddes, flie vnto this place, to the waters of comfort: here are
wels enough to be drawne at: this is the name which God
hath proclaimed to the world, and whereby he would be

knowne to men, that if euer they come to him, they may
ſpeake their mindes in the confidence and truſt of this amiable
name. Eſteeme it not ſtrange beloued, that the name of a
place is attributed to the Lord: for that he is a place of refuge,
 three things are able to prooue: Firſt, the witnes of God himſelfe:
ſecond, the confeſſion of the righteous: third, the word
(running) here vſed by king Salomon. As for the Lord he doth
attribute vnto himſelfe this name by the pen of the holy
Ghoſt, calling himſelfe a ſecret place, pſal 91. 1. a throne of
grace, Hebr. 4. 16. a refuge pſal. 9. 9. a fortreſſe, pſal. 18. 2. a
 ſtrong towre, and ſuch lyke more. Secondly this is the confeſſion
of the righteous: Of Dauid the father in diuers places,
pſal. 18. 2. The Lord is my fortreſſe and my refuge: and in the
32. 7. Thou art my ſecret place▪ &amp; compaſ
                  •
               eſt me about with
ioyfull deliuerance: and ſo Pſal 94. 22. This is alſo the confeſſion
of the ſonne in this place: and of all the Saints of God,
vnto whoſe confeſſions I referre you, as they are ſet downe
 by the holy Ghoſt in the booke of God. Thirdly, the word
(runneth) implieth as much, which giueth me entrance to the
ſecond point, opening vnto vs the feete which we neede to
goe vnto this place, the which if ye are deſirous to know, they
are two in number (Faith and Praier).The feet to carry vs thither. Faith the firſt, for if
by faith we ſtand. 2. Cor. 1. 24. by faith we may alſo goe to the
lord who is faithful. Now how could we go vnto him by the
feete of prayer, if we did not, beleeue in him? Rom 10. 14. The
ſecond, is prayer, a ſpirituall legge to beare vs thither, noted
by Salomon, making mention of running: by Ionas, ſpeaking of
comming. Iohn. 2. ver. 7. And my prayer come vnto thee in
thine holy temple By the Apoſtle, whē he ſpeaketh of going,
let vs therfore goe vnto the throne of grace, Heb. 4. 16. Laſtly,
by the holy Ghoſt, vſing this word Climbing. Apoc. 8. 4. Both
the name of the place which is appointed for vs to goe vnto,
and the ſpirituall legs which the Lord hath giuen vs to carrie
vs thither, doe preach vnto the ſonnes of men the admirable
goodnes and mercie of the Lord toward them. In this world
wee are as pilgrims, Pſal. 119. hauing here no continuing
Citie, Heb 13. 14 and while we are at home in the body, we
are abſent from the Lord, 2. Cor. 5. 6. In which pilgrimage

               Many are the troubles of the righteous, Pſal. 34. O the great
goodneſſe of the Lord then, that hee hath giuen vs feete to
come vnto him, and made himſelfe a place of refuge for vs
in all our troubles! which goodneſſe is comfortable vnto the
faithfull: for as it is a comfort vnto the pilgrim, ſhepheard, or
ſouldier, to haue in the heate of the day a place of refuge to
refreſh their wearied members: So likewiſe what a comfort
is it for you O afflicted ſoules in the heate of your afflictions,
to haue the name of Iehouah for a ſacred Sanctuarie! the
Lord is not like vnto the princes of the earth, who deſire not
to be moleſted with the requeſts of their diſtreſſed ſubiects.
It is a ioy to the wearied ſtudent, that he may ſometime come
home to his fathers houſe and recreate himſelfe: Into this
world the Lord hath ſent vs as in an Vniuerſitie, which although
it is farre off from our fathers houſe, yet the Lord
hath giuen vs ſpirituall feete, by which in a moment we can
aſcend vnto our fathers houſe, and recreate there our wearied
ſpirits. This world is a waſte deſart, if wee neede any
thing, here are the legges by which ſpeedily wee may runne
to this place, and prouide our ſelues. If the Lord hath caſt vs
downe vpon our beds, and that wee can not vſe the feete of
our bodies, behold, hee hath giuen vs other feete, to vſe in
ſteade of theſe. King Ezekias viſited with the plague, could
not vſe the feete of the fleſh, but with the feete of the ſpirit,
went vnto this place, knowen vnto him by the name of Iehouah.
Ionas is locked vp in a priſon, in the belly of the Whale,
(the Lords priſon) and can not ſtirre himſelfe, and yet by the
vertue of theſe feete, out of the depth, he aſcendeth to the holy
temple of Iehouah.
            
            Now that theſe feete may be able to beare vs thither,The hoſe to put on. and
that they may not faile vs in our voyage, they muſt put on
the hoſe of faith: and as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, our feete muſt
be ſhod with the preparation of the Goſpell of peace. And
as the feete to that Image of Daniel were part of yron,Ephe. 6. 15. part of
clay, which the Prophet expoundeth partly ſtrong, partly
weake or broken:Dan. 2. 42. So the feete of our prayers are, according
to the hoſen wherewith they are couered; if they put on feare

and diſtruſtfulneſſe, they will bee ſhiuering and ſinking
downeward, of clay, weake, and impotent; if they put on
faith and confidence in the mercies of God, they will be feete
of yron, ſtrong, ſtable and firme, keeping vs vpright, and wil
carrie vs to the very throne of grace.
            Further,A direction to know the way. as they that depart into the Countrey, if they
know not the way to the place whereunto they goe, muſt
haue a guide, or a direction, becauſe they ſhould not erre; So
in the going to this place, becauſe there are ſo many falſe
guides and directions, the Lord himſelfe hath giuen vs a
carde of direction to leade vs thereunto, the witneſſe of his
holy word, written and ſealed, that can neuer deceiue vs. As
the fierie pillar in the deſart, ſhewed he way vnto the Iſraelites:
So this word of the Lord is a fierie pillar vnto vs in the
darke deſart of this world, to ſhew vs the way to that heauenly
Canaan; it is the lanthorne vnto our feete, and a light to
our pathes, Pſal. 105. and therefore, according to the direction
of our Sauiour,Luk. 12. 35. 
               Let our loynes be girded, and let vs beare in
our hands this ſhining light.
            
            Fourthly,4. The right or intereſt which the faithfull haue to this place. to goe to this place, it is neceſſarie to know
what right or intereſt we haue in it. In the places wherevnto
men betake their ſelues in the terme of plague, either they
haue ſome right or intereſt there, becauſe they are their own,
or becauſe they haue ſome friends or acquaintance there that
will receiue them; or laſtly, becauſe they haue either hired or
purchaſed a houſe. So likewiſe vnto the name of Iehouah,
the place where we ought to goe in the time of plague, as alſo
 at all other times, we haue a ſpeciall right and interreſt. Firſt,
becauſe it is our owne, for hee is our God and our Lord, not
 by nature, but by gift and donation. Secondly, there we haue
acquaintance and our beſt friends; God our father, Chriſt
 our brother, the holy Ghoſt our comforter. Thirdly, becauſe
we haue purchaſed it; not we our ſelues, by corruptible gold,
or by our merites, but Chriſt for vs by his precious blood,
hath obtained this place of refuge for vs in our troubles. Dauid,
1. Chron. 21. 17. in his prayer, ſheweth vpon what right
and encouragement in the time of plague hee went to this

place, (O Lord my God I beſeech thee, &amp;c.) it was then, becauſe
the Lord was his God; he had a particular feeling of the loue
of God toward him, and knew him to be his God for he had
had ſome experience of deliuerance. The reaſon why wee
muſt haue this right, is becauſe being infected with the
plague of ſinne, we ſhould not be receiued. In the Countrie,
they will not receiue thoſe that are infected with the plague:
Neither can they alſo, in whoſe ſoules the plague of ſinne
doth reigne, be admitted to this place, and therfore the Lord
hath giuen vs Chriſt the righteous, to couer our vnrighteouſneſſe,
that thus as pure and cleane wee might come vnto
him. I know by mine owne experience, that in the Countrie
this yeere, they would not admit ſome that came from the
Citie, vnleſſe they had put on new apparrell. To come vnto
that heauenly Ieruſalem by the feete of prayer, we cannot
be admitted,Ephe. 4. 24. except we put off the olde man, and put on the
new man which is created in righteouſneſſe, and therefore,
that we ſhould not be hindered to goe thither, He hath put on
vs, the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, Rom. 13. 14. that being adorned
with his righteouſneſſe and holineſſe, as Iacob was with the
garment of his brother Eſau, We might with confidence approach
to the throne of grace, Heb. 4. It is onely then in the name of
Chriſt that we muſt goe to the name of Iehouah, Ioh. 14. 14.
Ioh. 5. 7. Mat. 21. 22. Ioh. 16. 14. 1. Tim. 2. 5. 1. Ioh. 2. 1. In
his name, the poore Lazarus hath as much right to goe vnto
it, as King Salomon: the infected as the ſound: the learned
as the vnlearned: for Chriſt prayeth for them all: and as Auguſtine
ſpeaketh, Chriſt prayeth with vs all as our brother; he
prayeth in vs all as our head, hee is prayed vnto by vs all, as
our Lord, but hee prayeth for vs all, as our high Prieſt. Let
then the Romaniſts in the time of plague, runne vnto the
name of Iehouah, in the name of Saint Sebaſtian; Alas, they
ſhall not be admitted: for Chriſt alone, as Ambroſe ſpeaketh,
is the eye wherewith wee ſee the father, the hand to offer vp
our prayers, and the mouth to ſpeake vnto him. But as for vs,
with Dauid let vs goe vnto him by force of this right, ſaying
with him, O Lord our God, we beſeech thee, &amp;c.
            
            
               
Hauing vnderſtood the name of the place,The practiſe▪ of King Dauid▪
                with other
circumſtances, let vs now examine the practiſe of King Dauid;
vnto this place, with theſe feete, by the ſame right, following
the true direction, he runned in the time of the plague
with his family, the Elders of Iſrael. For hee fled not to his
Caſtle, neither departed hee out of Iewrie, nor tranſported
his family into another place, but as it is ſtoried, 1. Chron. 21.
26. (He called vpon the Lord.) Here is a foundation wherevpon
ſome prodigall of their liues, vncharitable to others,
proude in their conceites, build the vnlawfulneſſe of departing
out of the contagious places in the time of plague, condemning
it by the example of King Dauid in generall,Obiection. without
any exception, in all manner of perſons; which their vncharitable
conceit I will not heere refute, I referre the Reader
to that learned Treatiſe of that reuerend father▪ 
               Theodorus
Beza, written touching this matter, wherein he learnedly,
ſoundly and religiouſly refuteth their groſſe opinion; onely
let me deſtroy their building which they erect vpon the example
of King Dauid.
               Anſwere. Foure particulars can hinder them to
 make a generall concluſion out of this example: Firſt, the
ſhort continuance of that plague, for the ſpace of three dayes,
or of a halfe of a day, as ſome of the learned are of opinion;
whoſe reaſons I will not alleadge, which left him no time to
 deliberate vpon departure. Secondly, the generalitie of the
Peſtilence, being ſpred from Dan to Beerſhebah, which left
him no place free to go vnto: for whither ſhould he flie ſeeing
that the peſtilence was ſpread all ouer the land: 2. Sam. 24.
                Thirdly, his owne guiltineſſe, that plague being cauſed by
his ſinne, the numbring of the people, which cauſed ſuch a
ſorrow in Dauid, that he was readie by his owne death to redeeme
the publike calamitie, praying vnto the Lord, 1. Chro.
21. 17. O Lord my God I beſeech thee, let thine hand be on mee,
and on my fathers houſe, and not on thy people for their deſtruction.
                Fourthly, the ſoundneſſe of Ieruſalem, the place where hee
was, the Angel hauing not yet, or very ſparingly touched
the head Citie, 1. Chron. 21. 15. the Lord repenting of the
euill, when the Angel came to Ieruſalem: theſe foure particulars

are able to caſt downe their building, and to diſprooue
their conſequence: Dauid fled not, Ergo, it is vnlawfull for
any man to depart: the true conſequence, if we would argue
out of this place, might be this: Dauid and the Elders departed
not: Ergo, let not Magiſtrate forſake his Citie, nor the
Miniſter his flocke. Hauing pluckt out the weedes and the
thiſtles, let vs as the good husbandman ſow the good ſeede.
As this then prooueth not the vnlawfulneſſe of departure; ſo
on the other ſide, it doth commend vnto vs king Dauids praying,The true vſe of the example
and his ſpiritual departure, teaching vs that in the time of
plague, our firſt and principall care ought to bee, as well before
our departure, as in our departure if wee are ſo minded,
(for I vrge no neceſſitie of it) to flie and runne by the feete of
faith and prayer to the name of the Lord, which being forgotten,
omitted, or negligently practiſed, maketh our departure
vnlawfull. Imitate the King then O yee righteous
ſoules in this tempeſt of the plague, let your ſoules take (the
wings of a Doue) the motion and agility of the ſpirit of God,
and let them flie by the ſtrength of their prayers to the boſome
of Gods mercies where they ſhall bee at reſt. Dauid in
this his going to the name of the Lord, hath ſhowen and manifeſted
foure things: His Conſcience, Humilitie, Memorie,
Wiſedome. His Conſcience, that it was good: his Humilitie
great: his Memorie holy: his Wiſedome right.
            Touching the firſt, the ſpirit of prayer is a ſigne of a 
good Conſcience; for as Tertullian ſpeaketh, Lib. de caſt.
Oratio de conſcientia procedit, ſi conſcientia erubeſcat, erubeſcet
oratio. Prayer doeth proceede from the Conſcience: if the
Conſcience bluſh, prayer will alſo bee aſhamed. O it is an
excellent thing that we can giue our ſelues to this holy exerciſe:
let one haue riches, honour, pleaſures, let him bee adored
as a little god, if hee haue not the ſpirit of prayer to puſh
him forward with Dauid, in the midſt of his felicitie, hee is
moſt miſerable.
            Secondly, his miſerie and humilitie, for a King is become 
a begger, and at the gate of the King of heauen he vſeth ſpeeches
of ſubmiſſion. (I beſeech thee O Lord) Loe here, O proud

ſonne of Adam, of thy ſelfe thou haſt nothing, but like a poore
ſuppliant begger thou are conſtrained to goe before the gate
of that right God, aſwel the king that ſitteth vpon his throne,
as poore Laxarus that ſiteth before the doore of the rich man.
 Thirdly his memory, the ſubiect wherof was the Lord, O holy
remembrance! Although he had as it were forgotten him
by his ſinne in his proſperitie, yet he remembreth him by his
praier in his affliction: O the excellencie of praier, it is a remembring
of our beſt friend, whoſe remembrance is comfortable
to our diſtreſſed ſoules. The ſubiect of our memories,
haue beene along time commodities, pleaſures riches, honor,
triumphs, and therfore ô England behold another ſubiect to
exerciſe the art of thy memorie: If then we haue forgotten
him in our proſperitie by our ſinne, let vs now remember
him by our feruent praier in our affliction. Many haue
practiſed the art of memorie according to the memoratiue
Art, and preceptes of memorie, which appoint places and
their furniture, for the helpe of ſuch as are vnexperienced;
but let vs practiſe the art of this holy memorie, let God be the
 ſubiect, and in this our affliction, let theſe be our helpes: Firſt
 let vs remember in our praier the commandement of God,
Pſal. 50. Secondly the name of him, whom we call vpon, that
it is Iehouoh, Lord, our God, a God not in ſhew, but in ſubſtance
and performance: a ſtrong God, a towre of defence,
 they that knowe this name wil truſt in him, Pſal. 9. 10. Thirdly
what he is by nature, how ſweete and amiable, how rich in
 mercie, Ephe. 2. Fourthly, what he is by promiſe, how faithfull
 and true, 2. Tim. 1. 3. Laſtly what he is by couenant, made vnto
Abrahams ſeede, not in the blood of bulles, but in the blood
of the ſeede of Abraham. Further, Dauid hath ſhewen his wiſdome,
and that in the choice of the place, taking his marke aright,
and directing his petition to the true and proper periode.
Imitate the wiſdome of king Dauid in his choice, he that
goeth to a place, runneth aright and wiſely, i
                  •
                he be wiſe, and
not by crooked and erroneous waies: Dauid ſheweth vs the
right way, for to what place ſhould we goe but to this, when
our ſorrowes are multiplied? ſhall we follow the waies of the

wicked, and ſay with them, Malac. 3. It is in vaine, that I haue
ſerued him, and what profit is it, that I haue kept his Commandements?
Or ſhall wee runne vpon the way of impatience, adding
griefe to griefe, liuing the life of Caine, or dying the
death of Iudas, drowning our ſoules in a gulfe of deſperation?
Shall wee ſpend the time in bannings, execrations, curſing
the day and night, the earth that beareth vs, the ayre that inſpireth
vs? Not ſo O Chriſtian ſoules, call vpon the name of
the Lord with Dauid, there was neuer name ſo worthie to be
called vpon, in heauen or earth, ſo mightie for deliuerance,
ſo ſure for protection, ſo gainefull for ſucceſſe, ſo compendious
to cut off vnneceſſarie labours as the name of Iehouah.
            
            Hauing vnderſtood the Conſcience,The cauſes to mooue vs to goe to this place. Humilitie, Memorie,
and Wiſedome of Dauid, let me open to you the reaſons
to mooue and perſwade vs to goe to this place. Fiue things
mooue the ſonnes of men in the time of plague to depart
from contagious places, vnto a purer ayre. Firſt the counſel
of the Phyſitians. Secondly, the practiſe of others. Thirdly,
the danger or perill which they are like to fall in. Fourthly,
deſire of health and life. Fifthly, the experience of ſucceſſe.
Let the ſame bee motiues vnto vs in this infection, to perſwade
vs to runne ſpeedily vnto this Arke of Noah. Firſt, it 
is preſcribed by the whole Colledge of the ſpirituall Phyſitians,
by God the father, Pſal. 50. 15. King Dauids Phyſitian;
by God the ſonne, who preſcribing the remedies which men
ought to vſe in the laſt dayes, in which the Trinitie of puniſhments,
famine, warres, and peſtilence ſhould raigne, giueth
this counſell, Luk. 21. 36. Watch and pray continually; by Prophets,
Apoſtles, and wiſe men, Iam. 5. 13. Eccle. 38. 9. and
17, 23. Secondly, the practiſe of the ſpirituall Phyſitians, as 
they haue preſcribed it, ſo they haue alſo practiſed it, and
haue fled vnto this place; to this Sanctuarie went the renowned
Patriarkes, the godly Princes, the holy Prophets, the
bleſſed Apoſtles, the Prince of glorie, the ſonne of the immortall
God, the conſtant Martyrs: whoſe examples yee
ſhall finde in the ſtore-houſe of the Scriptures. The example
of the bodily Phyſitians, of which ſome depart in the

time of plague, hath much force to make vs haſten our departure;
how much more ought the practiſe of the ſpirituall
phyſitions ſpurre vs forward vpon our ſpirituall voyage.
 Thirdly, the danger, which is threefold, (In nobis, circa nos,
contra nos) In vs, round about vs, againſt vs. In vs, the plague
of ſinne: round about vs, the fire of the preſent plague: againſt
vs, Sathan who ſeeketh to make vs curſe the Lord, and the
fire of Gods wrath and anger: To auoide this threefold
danger, runne to the Arke and to this bleſſed Zoar. The
 fourth motiue, is the deſire of life and health; we neede at this
time a double health, the health of the ſoule and body: let vs
therefore goe boldly vnto the throne of grace, that wee may
receiue mercie, and finde grace to helpe in time of neede,
Heb. 4. 16.
               Math. 9. 20. Why went that woman which was diſeaſed with
an iſſue of blood twelue yeares vnto Chriſt, but that ſhee
might receiue her health: Verſ. 12. The ſickneſſe of the
plague is an iſſue of blood, which being once opened, will
euer runne, and keepe a courſe if it bee not ſtanched by the
power and mercie of God: which mercie is onely obtained,
by going vnto his ſacred name: to obtaine this double health,
Dauid went vnto this place, 1. Chron. 21. that the plague of
his ſoule might be healed, and the bodily plague bee remooued.
If we are as it were dead for ſorrow, prayer will reuiue
vs, for it is Vita animae, the life of the ſoule: and as Chryſostome
termeth it, Eſt anima ipſius animae. It is the ſoule of the ſoule. If
we goe into the Countrey which cannot ſaue vs; how much
more ought we to flie to this name, which hath the power to
doe it: this his power, being acompanied with mercie and
kindneſſe, for thou O Lord, art good and gracious, and of
 great compaſſion, Pſal. 86. Fiftly, experience of good ſucceſſe,
is the laſt motiue, they which haue fled to this place,
haue not beene ſtopped by the way, but haue had good
ſpeede. Goe vnto King Eezekias, Iob, Dauid, and the reſt,
and they will preach vnto you by experience, the experience
 of this ſucceſſe. This ſucceſſe is grounded vpon three things,
 as vpon three firme pillars, the power, the will and promiſe,
 the goodneſſe and mercie of God.
            
               
His power, I haue heard it that power belongeth vnto God,
               
               Pſal. 62, 11. There was neuer affliction or ſore ſo great, but
the hand of that Phyſitian hath beene able to maſter it, the
leaſt finger of his right hand being of more puiſſance, then
the whole arme of fleſh.
            
               His will and promiſe, Pſal 91. 1. Ioel 2. 32. Iam. 5. 15. Eccle.
               
               31. 9. Matth. 77. Ioh. 14. 13. The King of heauen is not like
vnto the Princes of the earth, or vnto that Philip of Macedon,
who anſwered vnto the widow comming in his Court
to him, to be heard, I am not at leiſure, (vnto which alſo ſhee
anſwered iuſtly, then bee not a King any longer) for ſeeing
that he hath promiſed it, he is alſo willing, his promiſe being
ſigned with the finger of the holy Ghoſt, and ſealed with the
blood of his beloued and annoynted. Neither is he like vnto
him, Matth. 7. who anſwered, trouble mee not, my doores
are ſhut; the gate of heauen is alwayes open for vs. God reuoketh
not his promiſe as King Salomon, 1. Reg. 2. 20. 21.
23. Aske my mother, for I will not ſay thee nay; and yet behold
how this time is changed, Adoniah hath ſpoken this word againſt
his owne life; of the Lords promiſe wee neede not
doubt, but with Dauid boldly we may ſpeake, Pſal. 86. 7. In
the day of my trouble I will call vpon thee, for thou wilt heare me.
            
            Thirdly, His goodneſſe, mercie, and liberalitie, which is ſo
               
               great that he giueth meate to the yong rauens which call vpon him,
Pſal. 147. 9. Doubt not then, but that hee will heare the ſupplications
of men, whom he hath made a little lower then the
Angels, to crowne them with glorie aboue other creatures,
Pſal. 8. 5▪ 6. Let therefore, ſaith Auguſtine, thy prayer aſcend,
and Gods mercie will deſcend; ſhall wee diſtruſt his goodneſſe,
who is rich to all that call vpon him? Rom. 10. 12. Or
ſhall we ſuſpect his bountifulneſſe, which powreth out plentifully
his bleſſings vpon all fleſh? Rom. 8. 32. And although
wee haue offended him, yet our offences will not ſtop his
mercies. Men, when they haue done any good turne to any,
if they bee neuer ſo little offended, they caſt men in the teeth
with the benefits they haue done them, and vpbraide them
with the good turnes they haue ſhewed; wherefore men are

loath to make requeſt to ſuch for any thing: If wee goe vnto
the Lord, we ſhal not meete with one that is of ſuch a diſpoſition
and nature:Iam. 1. 5. he, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, reproacheth no
man; nor keepeth his anger for euer, Pſal 103▪ 9. The willingneſſe,
mercie, and goodneſſe of the Prince to haue vs,
maketh vs alſo willing to goe to him; who more willing, then
he that is our Father, our Sauiour, then he that hath ſuffered
for vs, ſcoffings, ſpittings, bands, ſtripes, and death it ſelfe?
Neuer lap of the mother hath beene ſo open to her babes, as
the bowels of Gods compaſſions are open to the righteous.
Harken to this, yee faint ſpirits, be ſtrengthened yee weake
hands and feeble knees, receiue this comfort, that he hath deliuered,
he doth deliuer, hee yet will and can deliuer. I ende
this point with the 13. 14▪ and 15. verſes of the 10. Chapter
of the Epiſtle to the Romanes: wherein behold a ſingular
and compendious gradation. As they that would come to
King Salomon ſitting vpon his throne, were faine to runne
vp ſixe ſtaires (for his throne was mounted vnto by ſixe
ſtaires) ſo the perfection and conſummation of man going
to the throne of the true Salomon Ieſus Chriſt aſcendeth and
ariſeth by ſixe degrees: the higheſt and the happieſt ſtaires
being, inuocating and ſauing, prayer and deliuerance. Theſe
are then the fiue reaſons, by which wiſe Chriſtians ought to
bee guided. I imitate King Dauid, onely reſorting to the
wings of the Lords fauour. And herein we ſhould be wiſe,
if we leuell our hearts and affections at the very right center
and marke of prayer (which is the name of Iehouah alone) and
the period or ſcope in whom our requeſts muſt end.
            But alas,Fiue ſorts of men erring in the going to this place. there are fiue ſortes of men, which make choice
of other places, reiecting the wiſedome of Dauid, the counſell
of the ſpirituall Phyſitions, and the practiſe of the Saints
of God, going a crooked, a circular, and endleſſe way, not
towards the marke, nor with a right foote as the Apoſtle
 ſpeaketh, Gal. 2. The firſt kind, flie firſt to the helpe of mortall
man, and with Aſa make ſpeede to the bodily Phyſitian,
to the confections of Arte, or to the purer ayre, not once
mindfull of this place; but when all helpes faile them, and

that the Lord ſendeth his Sergiant and heauenly Purſiphant
to arreſt them, then they returne to runne to this place. What
name ſhall wee giue you (O yee of little faith) but the name
of weake Chriſtians? Put not your truſt in the ſonne of man,
for there is no helpe in him, Pſal. 146. There is a ſecond 
ſort, which runne onely to the ordinarie creatures, deriding
the name of Iehouah, yea denying that there euer hath beene,
or is yet at this preſent, ſuch a place to be found, wherevnto
the righteous is preſerued, ſuch as Dauid deſcribeth in the 10.
Pſalme, 3. 4. Which ſeeke not God, but contemne him, and thinke
they ſhall neuer be mooued. O yee meere Atheiſts, what name
deſerue you, but that name, which the Lord himſelfe giueth
you, Pſal. 14. 1. the name of fooles. If Cain hath bene reiected,
becauſe he offered an vnworthie ſacrifice, what deſerue
they that offer none at all? The third ſort runne to a place,
whoſe name is Hell, ſeeking to Sathan and his artes, gadding
to the woman of Endor, or to the Idoll of Ekron, a Saul, a
Nero, a Iulian: Returne, returne, O yee wretched and bewitched
ſonnes of men, with the name of diuelliſh idolaters. The
fourth ſort, ſeeketh to dwell vnder the protection and aſſurance 
of their merites and good workes: but theſe alas, as
Bernard writeth on the 91. Pſalme, are ill lodged and haue a
poore Tabernacle, the diuell hath ſoone blowen that away.
The laſt ſort, are the ſuperſtitious Papiſts, who in the time of 
plague runne to the houſe of the Spider to bee preſerued, to
ſtickes and ſtones, mettals and papers, Angels and Saints,
and principally to Saint Sebaſtian, for as euery ſickneſſe and
diſeaſe hath his Apothecarie and Phyſitian among them: So
the plague hath Saint Sebaſtian, vnto whome with their families
they runne to bee preſerued. That execrable Pſalter
of the 
                  Ʋirgine Marie, compiled by them, maketh her to be
this ſecret place wherevnto wee ought to runne: the prayer
of Dauid which hee made being viſited with the plague, Pſal.
38. is abuſed in this maner. O Lady rebuke me not in thine anger,
neither chaſtiſe me in thy wrath: The 91. Pſalme is in like
maner abuſed, Who ſo dwelleth in the ſecret of the bleſſed Virgin,
&amp;c. But O ye blind ſeducers of ſoules, it may be firſt a challenge 
               
vnto you all, that neither Dauid, Iob or Ezechias viſited
with the plague went to Cherub or Seraphin, Gabriel or Raphael,
Abraham or Moſes: whome haue I in heauen but thee,
ſaith Dauid: he ſaith not, that hee had a Moſes or a Samuel:
                haue all theſe erred? Euen ſo will wee with them. Secondly,
yee goe to them that cannot helpe you, let them ariſe, if they
can helpe you in the time of your miſerie, Iere. 2. In the famine
of Samaria, 2. Reg. 6. a woman crying to the King,
helpe me O King, hee anſwered, ſeeing the Lord doeth not
ſuccour thee, how ſhould I helpe thee? Concluding ſecondly,
that if the Lord withdraw his helping hand, it lieth not
in the power of mortall man to helpe. So wee may anſwere
the Papiſts crying in the time of plague to their Sebaſtian,
helpe and aide vs Saint Sebaſtian. If it lieth not in the power
of mortall men that are liuing with vs to helpe, how much
leſſe can they that are dead? And farre leſſe, one that perhaps
 hath neuer beene? As for the Angels, they are diſpleaſed
that yee come to them, to thruſt vpon them ſuch a dangerous
honour: they may ſay as Dauid, Pſal. 115. Not vnto vs O Lord,
not vnto vs, &amp;c. they that refuſed a farre ſmaller offer vpon
the earth,Apoc. 22. 9. the onely bowing of the knee vnto them (See thou
doo it not) will bee much more diſcontented, to ſee the
knees of the heart to ſtoupe to them for the ceaſing of the
plague: for although an Angel ſmote ſeuentie thouſand in
the time of Dauid, yet he was but the inſtrument, God onely
the agent, and therefore he onely to bee prayed vnto. If the
Papiſts reply that they intreate onely Saint Sebaſtian to
ſpeake vnto God for them;Obiection. the anſwere is, that God needeth
not a Sebaſtian, nor any Saint ſo euer, to be his Maiſter of requeſts:
this is a ſeruice not vnmeete for the gouernours of the
earth,Anſwere. the Lord is not like vnto earthly Princes, vnto the
which may be ſaid, that which Iethro ſaid, Exod. 18. to Moſes,
the things is too heauie for thee, thou art not able to doo
it thy ſelfe alone: for the Almightie is able to doo it alone,
neither is there any defect in his hearing, whoſe eares are open
to the prayers of the poore. Let vs therefore hold Chriſt
Ieſus alone for the Maiſter of requeſts, it is he onely that can

preſent our requeſts which wee make vnto the Lord for the
ceaſing of the plague: let others runne where they will, to
ſtickes and ſtones from the name of the Lord: I doo you no
iniurie to impute this to you, for as Hillarie writet vpon the
firſt Pſalme, It is as great an offence to make a new, as to denie the
true God. The Lord annoynt your eyes with his eye-ſal
                  ••
               ,
that ye may returne to flie to the name of Iehouah. As for vs,
wee will follow the holy Canon, and leaue the broad way,
whoſe end is deſtruction, ſaying with Dauid, Pſal. 11. 1. In the
Lord put I my truſt,
               Matth. 7. 
               how ſay yee then to my ſoule, flie to your mountaine
as a bird. I ende the firſt braunch of this diſcourſe with
that holy Epiphoneme of King Dauid, Pſal. 146 5. Bleſſed
is hee that hath the God of Iacob for his helpe, whoſe hope is in the
Lord his God.
            
            After the name of the place,The ſecond part, the properties of the place. and other circumſtances,
there followeth in the two places, the condition, properties,
qualitie and ſafeneſſe of the place whereunto we muſt runne
in the time of the plague. The ſonnes of men in the time of
infection, before their departure, haue a ſpeciall regard of the
place where they will goe, of the ſituation, nature, and ſuch
like, and being led by the preſcription of the Phyſitian: Secondly,
by their owne minde, they make choyſe commonly
of a place in which they perceiue theſe ſeuen properties following:
and although Salomon here maketh mention but of
one, namely of a ſafe place, yet giue me leaue to diſcourſe of
the reſt.
            Firſt, they goe where there is a good, wholeſome and
pure ayre,1. A pure place. not ſubiect to ſtinking euaporations, and it is the
preſcription of the phyſitians, that wee ſhould goe vnto places
where the ayre is not corrupted, farre from the infection.
Dauid fled to ſuch a place, for ſuch is the name of Iehouah, a
pure place, farre from the corruptions of this world, for hee
is a pure, and incorruptible God, in whom there is no infection
of ſinne: the Lord, holy, holy, holy, not admitting thoſe
in whoſe mortall bodies the plague of ſinne doeth raigne: to
pray then and to repent, is to returne and go to a wholeſome
light, Eccle. 17. 24. The places wherevnto the ſonnes of men

flie, although they are for a time vncorrupted, yet they are
not warranted ſtill ſo to remaine, diuers alterations by ſundrie
meanes may befall, as by the reſort of perſons infected,
and ſuch like: but the name of Iehouah, this place of refuge,
ſhall neuer be altered, for he is the immutable and vnchangeable
God, and in the gates of that Citie no vncleane perſon
ſhall enter, Apoc. 22. 14, 15.
            
            Secondly,2. A pleaſant place. men make choyſe of a pleaſant and delectable
place, both for their bodies and ſoules, where there is good
companie to recreate themſelues in their ſorrow and exile,
foode and neceſſaries for their bodies, further by the riuer
ſide, or where there is good water: laſtly, where they may alſo
haue foode for their ſoules, the word of God Preached.
This place of refuge, the name of Iehouah, is a pleaſant and
delectable place, where canſt thou better recreate thy ſelfe,
then by thy Father and brother Ieſus Chriſt in this thy exile
and miſerie? Comfortable is the boſome of the mother to the
yong infant, but more comfortable is the name of the Lord
to the righteous which are called little babes by the Apoſtle.
Paul maketh mention in his voyage toward Rome, of a certaine
place which was called (The faire hauens) Act. 27. this
place of refuge better deſerueth this name, let vs goe thither,
for it is a harbour and rode for thoſe which are toſſed in the
ſea and deluge of the Peſtilence: happie is the ſoule that landeth
at theſe hauens. If we deſire water, there is the fountaine
of life: Iere. 2. the water of grace, Pſal. 51. If wee deſire
the word; there is the word it ſelf Ieſus Chriſt, Ioh. 1. the truth,
Ioh. 14. There is the beſt, the firſt, the ancienteſt Preacher,
God himſelfe that preached in Paradiſe.
            Thirdly,3. A ſafe place. in our choyſe we ſeeke out a ſafe place, whither
we may goe without danger, and where wee may abide ſafe,
and dwell without danger. The name of Iehouah is a ſafe
harbour, the ſecret place and ſhadow of the moſt high,
Pſal. 91. 1. vnder whoſe wings we ſhal abide ſafe and harmeleſſe.
 Three things prooue the ſafenes of this place: Firſt, the
name of the place, it is A ſtrong t
                     •
                  wre, Prou. 18. 10. A ſecret
place, Pſal. 32. 7. A rocke and fortreſſe, Pſal. 18. which is inuincible.
               
Such are not the fortreſſes of mortall men, which they
are conſtrained to render vp, being driuen therevnto either
by famine, or force, as Seba in the time of Dauid hereof is a
witneſſe. Secondly, the Lord of the ſoyle, which inhabiteth 
that place, his name is Iehouah: the Almightie, Pſal. 91. 1. the
ſtrong and inuincible God, who will and is able to preſerue
vs. Thirdly, it is prooued by the ſucceſſe of thoſe who runne 
to it, and by that which they receiue, they are (exalted, preſerued
or deliuered, ſaith Salomon) which Dauid acknowledgeth,
Pſal 32. 7. and is confirmed by the ſucceſſe of Dauids
prayer, 2. Sam 24. 25. and the plague ceaſed from Iſrael.
Comfortable is the ſaying of Dauid, Pſal. 91▪ 3. 15, 16. in
which, ſixe things prooue the happie ſucceſſe of the righteous
that runneth vnto it. Firſt, Gods ready anſwere: Secondly,
his preſence: Thirdly, his deliuerance: Fourthly, his aduancement
to honour: Fiftly, length of dayes: Sixtly, fruition
of ſaluation: O the excellent riches, pleaſures, and ioyes
which the righteous there ſhall enioy. As Lot there ſled
vnto little Zoar to bee preſerued from the fire of Sodome:
               Gene. 18. So
let vs flie to the name of Iehouah, to be ſafe from the fire of the
plague. The earthly places wherevnto men runne, do want
this propertie: they are not warranted to be ſafe there, either
from danger or from the plague, and the experience of this
yeere doeth declare it vnto vs all. Some haue returned, and
ſome haue died there, but as for the name of Iehouah, thy
ſoule is certaine to be preſerued, if thither ſhee taketh her recourſe;
and as they onely eſcaped the flood, that entred into
the Arke of Noah: So likewiſe, they that enter into this incorruptible
and immortall Arke, ſhall onely bee ſafegarded
from the deluge of afflictions. The Doue of Noah at her firſt
flight from the Arke, although ſhee mounted aloft, and fetched
many retires, yet ſhee could finde no reſting place, vntill
ſhee returned againe to the Arke: So the poore ſoule may
flie where ſhee will, but yet ſhee ſhall not haue any ſure footing
to reſt, except ſhee returne to the heauenly Arke: let vs
therefore bee wiſe as Serpents, and ſimple as Doues, for as
they being perſecuted, flie vnto the rockes; ſo let vs in our

calamities take our recourſe to the rocke of Dauid, Pſal. 18. 2.
neuer haue there beene holes in the rockes ſo open for the
doues, as the name of Iehouah for the righteous ſoules. There
are two renowned places mentioned by Plinie, Locris, and
Crotone, where the plague was neuer, as he writeth lib 1. cap.
96. and without doubt many reſorted thither: but although
we ſhould flie at this day to Locris and Crotone, if we carrie
within vs the plague of ſinne, the inward cauſe of the bodilie
contagion, we haue no warrant to bee ſafegarded. But me
thinkes I heare a controuerſie:Obiection. Many righteous haue fled to
the name of the Lord, and yet haue not beene ſafe from the
deluge of the peſtilence, or from the ſnare of the hunter: but
thouſands, and thouſands are fallen, yea ſome of the choſen of
Iſrael. The anſwere is, that they haue firſt obtained, either that
which they prayed for;Anſwere. ſecondly, or that which is better; or
thirdly, that which is ſufficient And the Lord heareth vs alwayes,
although alwaies he granteth not our petition: this
ſeemeth a Paradoxe, and yet the trueth thereof is manifeſt:
for in ſteed of that we asked, he giueth vs a better thing, and a
better place: thou askeſt the earth, ſaith Auguſtine, and the
Lord giueth thee heauen: temporall life, and he giueth thee
the eternal. The Surgion that ſaweth off the arme or legge of
the patient, who crieth for impatience and apprehenſion;
heareth him, Non ſecundum voluntatem ſed ſanitatem, not according
to his will, but according to his health: and ſo the
Lord dealeth with his patients.
            Fourthly,A place where they haue friends. to proceede, men make choice of places where
they haue their friends: the children reſort to their parents, the
parents to their children, brethren to their brethren, and one
friend to another. The name of the Lord is a place of refuge
where we haue our beſt friends, there we haue our father, our
eldeſt brother Chriſt Ieſus, the holy Ghoſt our comforter:
and therefore Dauid in the time of plague went to this comfortable
place. In earthly places vnto which the ſonnes of men
reſort, either we haue no friends, or they are farre off, and therfore
wee ſeeke other: or ſometimes although we haue friends,
yet they will not receiue vs for feare of infection: but in this

holy temple, and vpon this holy mountaine, we are ſure to
finde at all times the aforeſaid friends.
            Fiftly,5. A place acceſſible for all men we haue regard to chooſe a place which is lawful for
all men to come vnto, which is not prohibited or forbidden
by the Lord of the ſoyle &amp; magiſtrate of the place, and where
we knowe we ſhall be receiued. This place of refuge is ſuch,
acceſſible for all men, for whoſoeuer ſhall call on the name of
the Lord, ſhall be ſaued, Ioel. 2. 32. Neuer a cittie of refuge ſo
free for all manner of tranſgreſſions: hither may come the
King and the ſubiect, the rich and the poore, the learned and
the vnlearned, the merchant and the tradeſman: the ſound
and the ſicke, yea the infected with the plague. In the time of
infection, it is not lawfull for them that dwell where the contagion
raigneth, to come vnto the princes court, they are forbidden
by proclamation to reſort thither. But the court of
heauen is open for all men, yea for the infected, for they cannot
infect the court of heauen:The King of heauen his proclamation. the King of heauen hath made
a proclamation in the 50. Pſal. that we ſhould reſort thither,
and the prince of glorie Ieſus Chriſt who keepeth his reſidence
there, will not keepe vs backe. If the prince had made a
proclamation that the infected ſhould reſort to his court to
be healed, who would not haſten thither? It was not lawfull
for all men to come to the inner court of King Aſſuerus;
               Eſth 4. none
might approach but they to whome he held out his golden
ſcepter, except he would die the death that was appointed for
ſuch as durſt come neere:Heb. 4. 16. no ſuch kind of puniſhment is appointed
for thoſe that goe vnto the courte of the King of
heauen, we may approach boldely to the throne of grace, the
ſcepter of our King (I meane not that yron ſcepter of his iuſtice,)
but the golden of his mercie, is euer held forth to man,
woman, children, bond or free, ſtranger or Citizen, infected
or not infected, whether they be called, or not called: and they
all may ſafely approach: I name not neither inward or outward
court, but euen to the throne of grace, where the King
himſelfe ſitteth: and if there we craue of him, I ſay not to the
halfe of his Kingdome (as Aſſuerus ſpake vnto Eſter) but to
the whole, it ſhall not be denied vs. Feare of puniſhment

keepeth vs from the princes court. Let not feare keep vs from
the court of heauen.Neh 
                     ••
                  .2. 
               Nehemias although he held the cup to the
King, yet how fearefull he was to make a requeſt vnto him:
But as for you O ye righteous ſoules, feare ye not O you litle
flocke, for it is your fathers pleaſure to giue you a Kingdom.
Luc. 12. Further in time of contagion, not only the court, but
alſo the other citties, townes and villages, will not often lodge
them that come from contagious places, either the Lord of
the ſoile, or the magiſtrate of thoſe places forbidding it; but as
for that heauenly Ieruſalem, and the Lord of the liuing, thervnto
euery one may reſorte, the Lord and magiſtrate of
heauen doeth not interdict it. Dauid cried vnto the Lord, and
ſaid, thou art my portion in the land of the liuing. Pſal. 142. 5.
At Roome the houſen of the Aediles, were alwaies open for
all men, that they might reſort thither, to haue their cauſes
heard: and ſo is the houſe of the Lord for the afflicted ſoules.
In ſome places there are appointed (as I my ſelfe haue ſeene)
watchmenwith halbards, to aske the paſſengers from whence
they come, and ſometimes to keepe out thoſe that come from
infected places, but in our going to this place, we neede not
to haue ſuch feare, for as Chryſoſtome ſaith, Hic non eſt miles aſſiſtens
qui expellat, here there is no Sergiant or ſoldier to keepe
thee out. If the citties of the earth ſhut their gates before thee,
thou canſt not enter. As for that heauenly Ieruſalem, it is not
lockt, and although it were, prayer as Auguſtine ſpeaketh is a
key to open heauen, and to bring thee to the preſence of God.
Serm. 226. de temp. the towne and villages in times of infection
although they receiue ſome, yet they will not harbour
manie: and often there is no place for multitudes: but ſo is it
not with the name of Iehouah, with this ſtrong tower, it is not
like vnto the bulwarkes of mortall men, into the which if too
manie enter, they will hinder one another; this fortreſſe can
receiue millions and millions without any impediment. Further
the temple is alſo interdicted to the infected, for they are
commanded by the magiſtrate to keepe their houſen for a
time, or if they come, they are entreated to ſitte aſide: but the
Lords holy temple aboue in heauen, is not forbidden vnto

the infected, nor to any man: it is lawfull for them to goe thither
and pray, and that with the ſucceſſe of Dauid, Pſal. 18.
In my trouble I did call vpon the Lord and cried vnto my God, and
he heard my voice out of his Temple.
            
            Sixtly,6. A place neere vnto the Citie. ſome make a choyſe in the plague time, of a place
which is neere, wherevnto they may eaſily goe without any
great trouble or coſt: the name of the Lord is ſuch a place,
compendious to cut off vnneceſſarie labours, yee neede not
to runne farre, the Lord is neere as the Prophet ſpeaketh to
all them that call vpon him: neither will it coſt vs any thing,
money or merites, interceſſion of friends or gifts: poore men,
yee that want friendes or money, and therefore cannot prouide
your ſelues a place, bee not diſmaide, behold, here is a
place which will coſt you nothing. It is a place wherevnto
we may goe at all times, at dinner time, and at ſupper, as Cryſoſtome
ſpeaketh, in the day time, and at mid-night, in thy
health, and in thy ſickneſſe: the ſicke man may lye downe
vpon his bed and goe vnto it, and when with King Ezekias
he cannot vſe the feete of the fleſh, yet may he vſe the feete of
the ſpirit. In a moment we can flie thither, for as ſoone as we
haue finiſhed our prayer, we are alreadie come to this place,
and to the Lord of this ſoyle, our prayer and God meeting
one another in heauen, as Ieſus Chriſt and the woman at the
Well, Ioh▪ 4. As for earthly places wherevnto men reſort, either
they are far off, vneaſie to goe vnto, and that with trouble
and coſt, or expences, ſometimes we are ſtopped, we muſt
haue warrants and certificates of the Pariſh &amp; Church wardens,
that our houſe is not infected, before we can be admitted:
all this trouble we neede not in the time of plague in our
going to the name of the Lord: nothing will ſtop vs, the bodily
plague ſhall be no impediment, for wee haue a warrant
that we may paſſe, the King of heauen his warrant in the 50.
Pſalme;
               The warrant of the infected▪
                
               Call vpon me, &amp;c. and therefore this place is better
then the earthly, where the fearefull ſonnes of men dwell
which feare the apparrell, houſhold-ſtuffe, and thy letters:
I know nothing then to ſtop our paſſage, but the plague of
the ſoule, as the Lord of this ſoyle telleth vs in the; 2 Cor▪ 6.
               
               17. Touch none vncleane thing,
               Obiection. 
               and I will receiue you. But I heare
the weake conſcience obiect, I am infected with the plague
of the ſoule, and therefore it is not lawfull for me to call vpon
the name of the Lord: it is for the righteous as Salomon
ſpeaketh: but alas, I am vnrighteous, and how can I therefore
goe vnto this ſtrong tower?Anſwere. The anſwere is, for thy comfort
O weake conſcience, that Salomon ſpeaketh not of them
that are righteous by their owne righteouſneſſe, but by the
righteouſnes of Chriſt Ieſus: ſuch are all the faithful in whoſe
mortal bodies the plague of ſinne doth not remaine, their infirmities
being healed by Dauids Phyſitian, Pſal. 103. If yee
deſire a certificate thereof, you haue the Goſpel, ſubſcribed
and ſealed by God the Father, the Sonne, and the holy
Ghoſt. If yee deſire a witneſſe, ye haue a threefold witneſſe,
The ſpirit, the water, and the blood, 1. Ioh. 58.
            
            Laſtly,7. A place where we may haue a Phyſitian. wee make choyſe of ſuch places, where if neede
be, we may haue good Phyſitians; for wee eſteeme it a great
miſerie, to bee deſtitute of a good Phyſitian, and of meanes
to helpe vs in our neede. The place of refuge wherevnto
Dauid fled, and wee alſo ought to flie, following his direction,
hath the beſt Phyſitian which is both in heauen or earth,
God the Father, King Dauids Phyſitian, who hath both
health and ſickneſſe, life and death in his power, to diſpoſe
of them for our good and ſaluation: knocke therefore boldly
with the hand of prayer and repentance at the gate of his
mercie, and thruſt in his hands, both thy life and health. And
thus much for the qualities and properties of the place.
            Further,To pray for others is alſo requiſite. wee haue to obſerue that Dauid went not to this
place of refuge alone, but with his whole family, for he prayed
with the Elders of the people, for the people, and for the
deliuerance of his whole kingdome. Herein imitate King
Dauid, remember in thy prayer thy whole family, and the
 ſtate of the whole kingdome, the Tribe of Iudah, and the
Tribe of Leui. There are foure ſorts for which we muſt pray:
 Firſt, for thoſe which are Supra nos, aboue vs: Secondly,
 for thoſe which are equall vnto vs: Thirdly, for thoſe which
 are Sub nobis, vnder vs: Fourthly, for thoſe which are Comra

nos, againſt vs. In the going to the name of the Lord, wee
muſt not imitate the negligence of many, who depart into
the Countrey, and care onely for themſelues; as for their families,
or at leaſt their ſeruants, they are not once mindfull of
them: but wee muſt as well carrie with vs in our prayers, the
ſeruants which are vnder vs, as ſhee that lieth in our boſome:
And the Oliue plants which are round about our tables, Pſal. 108.
3. The Athenians would offer ſacrifice, but onely for their
owne Citie, and their neighbours of Chios: but wee Chriſtians
muſt pray, not onely for the mother Citie, but for all the
daughters: Chriſt teaching vs to ſay, Our father, &amp;c. as if we
all came from one wombe. It is a principle both of nature
and policie, Vis vnita fortior, Srength vnited, receiueth more
ſtrength. It holdeth likewiſe in Diuinitie. If the prayer of
one righteous perſon auaileth much, the prayer of many
righteous ſhall auile more. If the Syrophenician obtained for
her daughter the ſute ſhee made, much more the whole
Church of England ſhal obtaine for all her daughters: Where
two or three be gathered together in his name, he is in the midſt of
them: Much rather in the midſt of a people, in the midſt of
thouſands, in whom there is Anima vna, cor vnum: One ſoule,
one heart, one tongue, as if they were all but one man. Lord,
heale the ſores of our land, for behold, both the mother and
the daughters, the head and the members doo proſtrate our
ſelues before his Maieſtie. Yee of the ſect of Rome, diuide
not at this time of the plague in your prayers, the ſoule, the
voice and language of the Countrey into two places: Elias
and his companie, praying in one place and with one ſtile:
O Lord God of Abraham, and yee in another: O Baal heale vs:
Some praying for the life of Dauid, and ſome for the life of
Iabin. As for vs, we will pray for the Lords annoynted, that
God may hide him vnder the ſhadow of his wings from the
noyſome peſtilence, knowing that this is one of the parts of
our obedience towards him, that we (as Conſtantine the great
taught his ſouldiers to ſhew their allegiance in nothing more
then this) ſhould pray for him, his children and poſteritie. I
end this point, with the ſaying of an ancient Father: That

there is no better garde, or Halbards to ſafegard a Prince,
then the prayers of the righteous.
            Before I come to the third branch of this diſcourſe,Three rules to be obſerued in our going to this place. giue
leaue Chriſtan Readers to the ſpirituall Phyſitians, to lay
downe three rules, which are to be obſerued in this our ſpiritual
departure to the name of the Lord. The bodily Phiſitians
touching departure preſcribe three rules, Longè, cuò,
tardè: Goe farre off, depart ſpeedily, returne ſlowly. The
 ſame rules are to be obſerued by the righteous: Firſt, we muſt
flie farre,Longè. not with the prodigall and forlorne ſonne in a farre
Countrey, farre from the feare of God and thought of death,
or with Ionas from the preſence of the Lord, who rideth vpon
the Cherubims and can ouertake vs: for whither ſhall I
goe ſaith Dauid,
               Pſal▪ 139. 9. from thy ſpirit? Or whither ſhall I flee from
thy preſence? But farre from this world and the earth, vnto
the holy temple and mountaine, vnto heauen which is high
aboue the earth, as Dauid ſpeaketh, Pſal 103. 11▪
                vnto that
place which is called the land of the liuing. Secondly▪ flie
farre from the plague of ſinne, and the infected ayre of this
world, and being come vnto that farre Countrey, the Lord
 of the ſoyle will receiue you. The ſecond rule is, flie ſpeedily,Citò.
and deferre not your departure: which rule is not in any
maner to be omitted, it is the counſell of the wiſe man, Ieſus
Syrach, Eccle. 38▪ 9▪ My ſonne faile not in thy ſickneſſe but prays
vnto the Lord, and he will make thee whole. Tis the commandement
of the Lord to call vpon him in the time of neede,
Pſal. 50. Which muſt be performed with ſpeede, according
to the example of Dauid, Pſal 119. I will runne the wayes of
thy Commandements. If we make haſte to flie into the Countrey,
and forget to goe ſpeedily vnto this Sanctuarie: it is as
Auguſtine ſpeaketh of another matter, Curſus celerrimus praeter
viam: A ſwift race beſides the way. Haſte in this matter
is prayſe worthie, and a man can neuer run too faſt that runneth
to this place. The delay that Elizeus made, let mee goe
kiſſe my Father; and thoſe ſhifts in the Goſpel: Let me firſt
goe burie my mother, or take leaue of my friends, are not admitted
in this buſineſſe: commune not therefore with fleſh

and blood. If in the time of plague, we make ſuch haſte to
depart, before we haue ordained our buſineſſe aright, or bad
our friends farewell: How much more ought wee to haſten
our ſpirituall voyage? While the fal-bridge is let downe, let
vs make ſpeede to enter. Many, becauſe they went not farre,
not made ſpeed to depart, haue endangered their bodies, but
many more, becauſe they fled not from the contagion of
ſinne with ſpeede, haue endangered their ſoules: and therefore
as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, 1. Cor. 9. of another matter, ſo
I may ſay of this going: So runne that yee may obtaine.
            
            The third rule is,Tardè. Returne ſlowly: that is, continue where 
thou art: a neceſſarie rule to bee obſerued in the going to the
the name of the Lord. It is the rule of the ſpirituall Phyſitians,
Ephe. 6. 18. Rom. 12. 1. Theſ. 5. Pray continually, &amp;c. As
it is preſcribed,Lukk▪ 2
                     •
                  . 36. ſo it hath beene practiſed: the woman of Canaan
continued in her prayer, and returned not in haſte.
They which are in the Countrey, although there bee many
things which might mooue them to returne, yet for the ſafetie
of their bodies, they continue till the plague be ceaſed: So
continue in thy prayer by the Lord, and be not wearie of wel
doing. Although three things might haue mooued thy Syrophenician
to returne, the ſilence of Chriſt, her back-friends,
and the odious names giuen vnto her: yet theſe diſcouragements
her poore ſoule digeſted, obtaining both a cure for her
daughters infirmitie, and a commendation for her faith. O
woman thou haſt wrought a myracle by the perſeuerance of
thy prayer, and haſt giuen to thy Sauiour occaſion to doo a
memorable act, conuenient to his nature: glorious to his holy
name. Let vs at this time follow her perſeuerance, and although
the Lord ſhould ſeeme to be ſilent for a time, yet let
vs not draw backe, that wee may receiue a cure both for our
ſoules and bodies, and deſerue a commendation both by
God and other nations, and thereby giue occaſion vnto the
Lord to ſhew his omnipotent power in the ceaſing of the
plague: and to doo an act in England conuenient to his nature,
and glorious to his holy name. And as Iacob wraſtled
with the Angel and would not let him goe vntill hee had receiued

the bleſſing: So let vs as it were ſtriue with the Lord
by our prayers, and let him not goe vntill he haue heard vs,
in that which we aske of him in this afflicted time. Let our
prayers be now as the ſhowers of the raine, if the firſt ſhowre
faileth of watering the earth ſufficiently: the ſecond, the third
or the fourth, wil fulfill the thirſt thereof. Let vs be like vnto
the widow, Luk. 18. and our importunitie will draw him
vnto audience: but yet let vs hold a better opinion of the
iudge of the world, then of a common vulgar friend. It delighted
his eares to heare our redoubled obſecrations, and he
ſuſpendeth our deſires in expectation, that we ſhould be importunate
to craue.Hbak. 2. 
                     •
                  . The bodily Phyſitians cannot away
with the importunate patient: but God, King Dauids Phyſitian,
loueth the importunate prayer, and more acceptable is
to him the ende of our prayer then the beginning. I would
the children of light were as wiſe in their generation, as the
wodden Prieſts, 1. Reg. 18. who cried long to Baal: yea cut
themſelues with kniues that they might be heard: and what
ought not wee then doo to obtaine our ſuite? Let nothing
then mooue vs to returne: but as the King of the Philiſtines,
1. Sam 6. though they had Calues at home, yet they kept
the ſtraight way to Bethſhemeſh, and held one path: turning
neither to the right, nor to the left hand; neither euer ſtood
ſtill, till they came into the field of Ioſuah. So in our going to
the name of Iehouah, the affection of our ſoules bearing the
Arke and coffer of our ſuites, though it hath worldly allurements
to draw it backe, as the Kine had Calues: yet let it in
the way to the houſe of God, as they to Bethſhemeſh, hold one
path of perſeuerance, turning neither to the right or left hand
with wandring cogitations, till it commeth into the field and
garden of God, and there let it remaine. Many hauing not
continued in the Countrey, in their haſtie returning are fallen
ſicke,The third part containing the houſhold ſtuffe which we muſt carrie vnto that place. and died: So many hauing not continued in this
ſtrong bulwarke, haue endangered both body and ſoule.
And thus much hitherto of the ſecond part.
            There followeth now the third and the laſt, which openeth
vnto vs the houſhold-ſtuffe which we muſt carrie with

vs thither noted in the word (Righteous.) As they which go in
the country in the time of plague, carie with them their houſhold-ſtuffe,
their furniture, &amp; thoſe things which are neceſſarie
for their bodies, and as Noah entring the arke carried with
him neceſſaries; ſo likwiſe in our going to this place, we muſt
carrie with vs thoſe things which are neceſſarie for our ſoules,
that we may be receiued by the Lord of that ſoyle, and without
which wee can not goe thither. There are fiue peeces of
ſpiritual houſhold-ſtuffe which are neceſſary for vs, noted in
the word Righteous.
            
            The firſt is Repentance and holines of life,1. Repentance. for he that is
righteous giueth himſelfe to righteouſnes. And this furniture
carried with him Dauid, 2. Sam. 24. 11. As they which goe in
the countrey haue their reaſons why they carrie with them
ſuch and ſuch neceſſaries: So giue me leaue in the opening of
this furniture, to ſhew you alſo the reaſons which muſt moue
vs to carie them with vs.2. Tim. 2 19. As for this firſt, the firſt reaſon is, the 
preſcription of the ſpirituall Phiſitions, it is the Apoſtles
precept: Let euery one that calleth on the name of Chriſt depart
from iniquitie. The ſecond is, that we may be receiued,
for the righteous Lord, loueth righteouſneſſe: his countenance
doeth behold the iuſt. Pſal. 11. 7. His eies are vpon the
righteous, and his eares open to their crye, but his face is againſt
them that doe euill, to cut off their remembrance from
the earth, Pſal. 34. 15. 16. If I regarde wickednes in my heart
ſaith Dauid,
               Pſal. 66. 18. the Lord will not heare me. For as Salomon teſtifieth,
the Lord is farre off from the wicked, but he heareth the
prayer of the righteous. Prou. 15. 29. Drawe therefore neere
to God, and he will drawe neere to you: cleanſe your handes
ye ſinners,Prou. 28. 9. and purge your hearts ye wauering minded. Iam.
4. 8. 9. The third is, that the bodily plague may ceaſe, for how 
dare we approach vnto the Lord, to craue that it might be
remooued, and yet carie with vs the inward cauſe thereof: let
the Phyſitions maxime heere preuaile, remooue the cauſe,
that the effect may ceaſe. Let vs not as the ſonnes of Iacob,
bring into the preſence of our father,Pſal▪ 59. the garment of Ioſeph
which we our ſelues haue beblooded. As Aaron could not

come before the Lord before he was waſhed, ſo let vs not goe
vnto him before we haue cleanſed our ſelues from infection
of the ſoule. And as Iacob Gen. 43. exhorted his ſonnes,
when they were going to Ioſeph, carrie with you the beſt
fruites of the land and giue them him: ſo let vs in our going to
to the true Ioſeph Ieſus Chriſt, carrie with vs the beſt fruites of
our hearts to offer vp the ſacrifice of our prayers, our corrupt
affections, as Abraham left behinde him at the foote of the hill
his aſſes I conclude this firſt point with the ſaying of Chryſoſtome,
as in a garland, it is not enough that the flowers bee
pure and cleane, but the hand alſo which handleth them: ſo it
is not ſufficient that the words of our prayers be holy, but the
heart alſo which conceiueth them.
            
                The ſecond piece of houſhold-ſtuffe is (Faith) for the righteous
is alſo hee that beleeueth in Chriſt,Faith. and is righteous
through the righteouſnes of Chriſt the righteous. This furniture
carried Dauid with him,1. Sam. 24. for as he had a deſire of health
and remiſſion of his ſinne, ſo he had alſo a ſtedfaſt faith and
confidence that it ſhould be forgiuen him. This perſuaſion of
deliuerance, and hope of obtaining, we muſt haue with vs
 entertaining it in our hearts. The reaſons, are firſt the preſcription
of the ſpiritual Phiſitions, it is the Apoſtles precept,
Iam 1. 6. Let him aske in faith and wauer not. And in the fourth
to the Hebr. 16. that we ſhould goe boldely to the throne of
grace: drawing neere vnto him with a true heart in aſſurance
of faith, Heb. 10. 22. caſting not away that confidence which
hath great recompence of reward,Ver. 35. tis the counſaile of
 Chriſt, Mar. 11. 24. Secondly, carrie it with thee, that thou
maiſt receiue that, for which thou goeſt vnto him faithfully.
Pſal 145. 18▪
                And whatſoeuer yee ſhall aske in prayer, if yee
beleeue ye ſhall receiue it. Math. 21. 22. Without this, there is
no going thither. Rom. 10. 14. But as righteouſnes and trueth
kiſſe each other, ſo muſt prayer and faith, which is the ground
of prayer: firſt beleeue, and then ſpeake, this was the order of
Dauid, Pſal. 116. this faith will make vs acceptable to the
Lord of that ſoile, and make vs finde fauour at his hands.
Faith is a beautifull queene, as highly fauored of the King of

Kings, as euer Eſther was of King Aſſuerus: ſhe ſhall not be
ſtayed without at the gate, but with an humble preſumption,
may approach into the inner court, and ſhall receiue her requeſt:
for if we ſhall receiue a Kingdome, Luc. 12. how much
more that which is leſſe, being asked by faith? come not then
without this aduocate. Cyprian, in his treatiſe de Idol vanit, ſayeth,
(ſpeaking how hee and his brethren did much good in
the viſitation of the ſicke) prout fides patientis adiuuat, aut gratia
curantis aſpirat, that he proſpered according as they and the
patient had faith to ſpeake vnto God: the greateſt enemie to
the efficacie of our prayer is diſtruſtfulnes. And therefore
God forbid ſaith Auguſtine that what we deſire God to doe
for vs with our mouthes we ſhould deny him to be able to doe
in our hearts.In Hipolito. A heathen man Seneca could ſay, he that asketh
fearefully and doubtfully, teacheth him to denie of whom he
asketh: and men doubting they ſhall not obtaine, make God
vnwilling to heare them. As vnbeleefe did ſhut the doore vnto
the Iewes that ſome of them enter not into Canaan, a tipe of
heauenly Ieruſalem; ſo diſtruſtfulnes is able to ſhut our praier
out of that heauenly Canaan. And therefore as Iacob going
to his father Iſaac, to receiue the bleſſing, put on the garment
of his eldeſt brother, ſo let vs going to our heauenly father to
obtaine our requeſt, be cloathed with faith through the righteouſne
                  ••
               e
of our eldeſt brother Ieſus Chriſt. Further, this
confidence giueth vs entrie into that place. Open the gates
ſaith the prophet, Eſ. 26. 2. that the righteous nation which
keepeth faith, may enter in. Faith is as a key that openeth vnto
vs the gates of the cittie. Thirdly, this furniture is neceſſarie 
for the feete which muſt beare vs thither, that they may be
firme, ſtedfaſt, and faile vs not in the way: the moiſture and
iuice whereby the ſpiritual feet of our prayers are nouriſhed,
is faith. By faith yee ſtand, ſaith the Apoſtle, 2. Cor. 1. It is the
roote that beareth vs, the legges and ſupporters, and the
ſtrong men that hold vs vp that we fall not. As the Doues
neſt is the cleftes of rockes that cannot be aſſaulted, ſo faith
reſteth it ſelfe in the wounds of Chriſt, it caſteth an anchor in
knowledge of the true God, and ſtandeth as firme, as mount

                Sion that cannot be remooued. Fourthly, we muſt carrie it
with vs, that we may liue: why doe wee with our houſholdſtuffe
goe into the Countrey, but becauſe we are deſirous of
life? If in the going to the name of Iehouah for remiſsion of
ſinne and ſpirituall life, and for the remoouing of the effect
of ſinne the bodily contagion, we are deſirous of it, we muſt
not forget this furniture, for by Faith we liue, Abac. 2. It is
the life of the ſoule, and the ſoule and ſpirit of the new man. Wee
may haue a name that wee liue, but indeede wee are dead to
God-ward, if wee beleeue not: doubting then neither of
might, mercie, or of his promiſe, becauſe they are paſſed by
couenant, oath, before vnmooueable witneſſes, the beſt in
heauen, and the beſt in earth, and becauſe they are ſigned
with the finger of the holy Ghoſt, and ſealed with the blood
of his annoynted and beloued, let vs with a holy confidence
runne to this place in this afflicted time of the contagion, that
we may receiue mercie.
            
                The third peece neceſſarie for our voyage, is (Humilitie)
which excludeth all opinion of our owne worthineſſe and
righteouſneſſe.Humilitie. 2. Sam. 24. 
               Dauid carried his furniture with him, yea
this royall ornament: as appeareth out of two things. Firſt,
out of the tearme and phraſe of obſeruation (I beſech you) a
proper terme of ſubmiſſion, and the poore ſurers phraſe. Secondly,
out of his bodily proſtrating of himſelfe in ſackecloath
with the Elders of Iſrael, 1. Chron. 21. Herein let vs in
this time of plague imitate King Dauid in our going to the
name of the Lord, carrying with vs this ornament, this ſubmiſſion
and lowlyneſſe: let vs vſe the poore ſuters phraſe,
and not pride of ſpeech: ſaying, we are worthie O Lord: let
vs not goe thither to bragge, as many runne into the Countrey
to dominire; but let vs pray that the Lord will giue vs
with vs this ſubmiſſion, that we may bow not only the knees
of our bodies, but of our hearts: yea, that wee may euen
bow the very phraſe of our words with Dauid, that wee
may vtter them as if the ſmalleſt Graſhopper of the earth
were to ſpeake with feare and reuerence before that dreadfull
Maieſtie.
            
               
Three things muſt mooue vs to carrie it with vs in this our
voyage: Firſt, the perſon to whome we goe, his greatneſſe,
excellencie, Maieſtie, his glorious name which is Ieuouah.
It was the counſel that Aeſope gaue to Solon, enquiring what
ſpeech he ſhould vſe before Craeſus: either very little, or very
ſweete, ſaid he. If when we goe to the Princes of the earth,
who are but ſmoake and vanitie, wee ſpeake with humilitie
much more doth the preſence of the moſt high God require
it. Secondly, the conſideration of our owne perſons which 
doe goe thither: the conſcience of our owne vnworthineſſe,
and deformitie of ſinne wherwith we are ſpotted: let vs then
with Abraham ſpeaking to the Lord,Gene. 18. confeſſe that we are but
duſt and aſhes. Let vs as Lazarus with all our vlcers (which
are many in the time of plague) and withall our ſores detected
and laide open: he before the gates of him who is rich in
mercie, lamenting, crauing, and beſeeching to be refreſhed.
Chriſtians, learne of Chriſt to pray, who although there was
no vnworthineſſe in him, yet hee kneeled, fell vpon the
ground, the footeſtoole of his owne Maieſtie, and lay vpon
his face, which neuer Angel beheld without reuerence. The
third is, that our comming to him, may bee acceptable, and 
that we may receiue the health we ſue for. To him looketh
the Lord, that is poore, and of a contrite ſpirit, Eſa 66. 2.
which hee will not deſpiſe, Pſal. 51. 17. for hee is neere vnto
them that are of a contrite heart, and will ſaue ſuch as bee
afflicted in ſpirit,Eccle. 35. 17. 
               Pſal. 34. 18. The prayer of him that humbleth
himſelfe, goeth through the clouds: the Lords mercie
can onely giue vs the twofold health which we ſue for at this
time: now this mercie to whome doth hee giue it, but to the
humble? 1. Pet. 5. Humilitie is both grace it ſelfe, and a veſſel
to comprehend other graces: and ſhee emptying her ſelfe
by a modeſt eſtimation of her owne gifts, is filled againe by
the Lord. Let vs now beloued as it were ſtriue by humilitie
with the Lord, according to the policie of Iacob: Let vs
winne by yeelding, and the lower wee ſtoupe towards the
ground, the more aduantage wee ſhall get to obtaine. The
Lord to whom we goe, if this humilitie bee in vs, will both

dwell with vs and in vs. O Lord, ſaith Auſtine, how high art
thou, and yet the humble of heart, are thine houſes to dwell
in: I he proude Phariſie, Luk. 18▪
                went vnto the Lord without
his furniture, praying with pride and with a skornefull
demonſtration, and therefore returned not iuſtified as the
Publican. O that we had not for the moſt part of vs all ſuch
Phariſaicall eye-browes, whether wee talke with God or
man, that we might heare that comfortable voice which was
ſpoken vnto Daniel,
               Cap. 10. 12. 
               Feare not, for from the firſt day that thou
dideſt humble thy ſelfe before thy God, thy words were heard.
Let vs therefore vſe to conclude this point: this humble ſtile
of Dauid, it hath beene the ſtile of a King: and although it
ſeemeth inglorious, yet it hath beene the ſtile of the glorious
Saints of God: it will giue vs the honour of Saints, and raiſe
vs from the duſt, ſet vs vpon the thrones, and if it pleaſe the
Lord to take vs away by the plague, it will place vs with Angels:
let vs not then brethren forget it, that the anger of the
Lord may ceaſe, and that with ioy hereafter wee may ſing
with Marie in her Canticle, Luk. 2. He hath regarded the lowlineſſe
of his handmaide.
            
            
                The fourth peece of houſhold-ſtuffe, is Reuerence, deuotion,
               Ferfencie and zeale.
               zeale and feruencie. For the noyſe of our lips, if it bee as
the ringing of Baſans: a vocall modulation, without cordiall
meditation, it cannot procure vs audience: for it is as the offering
of the halt and the lame, a body without a ſoule: it is
the counſell of the wiſe man. Eccle 5. 1. Bee not raſh with thy
mouth, nor let thine heart bee haſtie to vtter a thing before God.
Our prayers muſt not bee a formall ſeruice onely, but the
ſighes of our ſoules muſt bee ſent with an earneſt meſſage to
the eares of God: they muſt not bee perfunctorie and cold,
rather of cuſtome then of deuotion: for a prayer from fained
lips, wil returne emptie into the boſome that ſent it vp. When
wee goe to this place, let vs not goe, as if our ſoules and
tongues were ſtrangers, the one not knowing what the other
doth: our lips babling without, and our heart not pricked
with any inward compunction, for elſe it is as the altar without
fire: a perfunctorie prayer, is as the prayer of the Parret.

               Iohannes Fridericus the Prince of Saxonia, had a Parret who
could rehearſe the Latine Pater noſter. Cardinall Aſcanius
had another, who reiected the Creede, repreſenting perhaps
the faith and praying of his Maiſter. What are the careleſſe
deuotions of thoſe, who leaue their ſpirits as is were in a ſlumber
while they are a praying▪ but like vnto thoſe two Parrets
babbling: as they muſt bee deuote, ſo muſt they bee feruent,
kindled by a burning zeale, inflamed with feruent loue: and
as the Harts bray after the water brookes,Pſal. 42. ſo muſt our ſoules
after the liuing God: For the prayer of a righteous man auaileth
much, &amp;c. if it bee feruent, Iam 5. 16. If wee are deſirous to
know the neceſſitie of this zeale and feruencie, receiue theſe
directions following. Firſt, the example of Chriſt biddeth 
vs goe thither with this zeale: Chriſtians receiue directions
for the framing of this holy exerciſe from Chriſt, who offered
vp prayers with ſtrong crying and teares, Heb. 5. he that
was the mightie Lyon of the Tribe of Iudah hath roared in
his ſupplications. Secondly, the ſpirit of God biddeth vs goe 
thither with zeale, for he maketh requeſts in our names with
grones not to be expreſſed, Rom. 8. Thirdly, the Maieſtie of 
the ſacred Lord of Hoſts, to whom we flie: the royaltie of his
nature ſublimitie of his place, dominion ouer Angels, biddeth
vs goe thither with zeale. Fourthly, the view of our 
moralitie and of our ſinne, by which wee haue cauſed the
Lords deſtroying Angel, biddeth vs to goe thither with
zeale. Laſtly, the hope and expectation of ſucceſſe, the delicacie
and tenderneſſe of the eares of God, and the precious
fauour of his countenance, which muſt bee wiſely intreated
and carefully ſought for: biddeth vs to goe thither with
zeale, vnleſſe we will ſowe, and not reape: plant Vines and
not drinke the wine thereof.
            The fift and laſt peece of houſhold-ſtuffe, is Chriſtian
               
               patience,
               Patience. a ſubmiſſion vnto his holy will and pleaſure, a vertue
proper vnto the righteous. Dauid carried it with him thither,
and wee muſt not leaue it behinde vs, following the
ſtreames of our fooliſh appetites:2. Sam. 24. we muſt limit our prayer
in God and his holy will, asking abſolutely his glorie, and

our ſaluation: but remitting the meanes vnto his wiſedome
and pleaſure. The fountaine of our heart muſt not powre
foorth ſweete and ſowre together, praying, but with impatience:
let vs ſet him no time as the Diſciples did about the
kingdome of Iſrael, but let vs come to the reſolution of Dauid,
2. Sam. 15. Behold, here am I, let him doe to me as it ſeemeth
good in his eyes. Worthy is the Oration of Iudith which ſhee
made to her people of Bethutia,
               Iud. 8. who would deliuer vp the
Citie into the hands of the enemie, vnleſſe within few dayes
the Lord ſhould helpe them: Who are you that haue tempted
the Lord, and ſet your ſelues in the place of God? Let vs
waite for ſaluation from him, and call vpon him to helpe vs,
and he will heare our voice if it pleaſe him: thus ſhould wee
exhort our ſelues in our prayers, when impatience doeth beſiege
our hearts. It is ſafe for vs to caſt the ankers of all our
purpoſes, and to ſtay our wils vpon his will. The reaſons to
 perſwade vs to bring it with vs, are three: the firſt is the preſcription
of the ſpirituall Phyſitians of Chriſt, Luk. 21. and
in the prayer which he hath taught vs: of Dauid, Pſal 37. 7.
                and of the reſt. The ſecond is, the Lords equitie in all his actions:
he gouerneth not by luſt, but by law: he draweth thee
not to obedience by a violent chaine of his vnchangeable
purpoſe, but by reaſon and iuſtice: eſteeme not his will in
the moderating of the world as immoderate: hee hath a will,
but not as inordinate Princes, who hauing the raines of dominion
giuen into their hands, doo many things inordinately
without law, reaſon, iuſtice, equitie: proclayming with
Nero, that they may doo all things, and that no bodie may
controll them. No, no, beloued, his will is alwayes holy, alwayes
iuſt and equitable, although it ſeemeth vnto thee vniuſt.
 The third is the example of Chriſt; Chriſtians, the wiſdome
of God it ſelfe, in whom the Deitie dwelt bodily, was
content to forſake his wiſedome, and to be ordered and rectified
by this ſquire of his Fathers will: Father, not my will, but
thine be fulfilled. This is then the ſpirituall furniture which we
muſt carrie with vs, if wee will goe to the name of Iehouah.
Prayer with theſe companions will returne laden with the

ſheaues of comfort and bliſſe from the plentifulleſt fieldes.
And by theſe it is manifeſted, that the righteous onely goe
to this place: the name of Iehouah is not like vnto the earthly
places, vnto which in the time of infection reſort both good
and bad. The vngodly may make a ſhew to goe vnto it, but
yet they can not come thither, for there is the ſpirit of prayer,
Zach. 12. which is giuen onely to them that bring with
them this ſpirituall furniture. As for weapons to ſafegarde
our ſelues, we neede none, for this houſhold-ſtuffe are ſpirituall
weapons, Epheſ. 6. This ſhall ſuffiſe for the Arke of
Noah.
            
            Now becauſe the Ciuill Magiſtrate appointeth in euery
Pariſh truſtie men to aide the infected,A truſty friend and ſeruant appointed by the Magiſtrate of heauen, to aide the ſicke in the time of Plague. and to prouide them
with neceſſaries: Giue mee alſo leaue to ſhew vnto you beloued,
a truſtie friend and ſeruant to ayde the ſicke, appointed
by the Magiſtrate of heauen. If yee are deſirous to know
who it is, prayer is his name, Pſal. 50▪ Call vpon mee, &amp;c. Dauid
hath vſed this faithfull friend in the time of the plague, he
hath ſent it as an Embaſſadour into the court of heauen to
ſue for peace: he ſent not merites, diſtruſtfulneſſe, impatience,
or blaſphemies: but prayer the ſureſt and effectualleſt Embaſſadour,
happie for ſucceſſe. Wee are all deſirous if the
Lord viſite vs with the rod of Dauid, to haue ſome truſtie and
faithfull friend or ſeruant to keepe and ayde vs, to diſpatch
our buſineſſe, to ſend here and there, and to prouide vs, with
neceſſaries: and wee make much of ſuch that will aſſiſt vs in
ſuch a fearefull ſickneſſe. Wee can haue no better ſeruant
then King Dauids friend, who hath many good qualities: we
deſire in the time of plague a ſeruant or friend,The qualities of this friend▪
                in whom wee
finde theſe good qualities: Firſt, Faithfulneſſe, for many haue
beene robd by their keepers,Faithful. as experience teacheth. Prayer 
is a meſſenger of eſpeciall truſt, it wil trauaile with vs by day:
awake with vs by night: it will not forſake vs by land, by
water, in weale, in woe, liuing nor dying, it is our laſt friend
and indiſſolubleſt companion.Quicke. Secondly, wee deſire one 
quicke of ſpeede: Prayer is able in a minute to mount aboue
the Eagles of the skie, into the heauen of heauens, and is a

chariot of fire bearing vs aloft into the preſence of God to
ſeeke his aſſiſtance; hee knoweth to addreſſe himſelfe in waies
vnknowne in the ſtilleſt ſilence of the night, till he come to
the ſecrets and chamber of the Lord, King Dauids Phiſition.
 Thirdly,Willing. we ſeeke one who is willing, and is not afraid, (for
they are ſcarce to be found) prayer is ſuch a friend, he is not afraid
to be with thee: neither the tediouſneſſe of the way, or
difficultie of the paſſage can hinder him from his purpoſe.
            
                Fourthly, we are deſirous to haue one that can ſpeake language
which the Phyſition can vnderſtand, if neede were to
ſend him thither, and who can prouide vs of neceſſaries, ſuch
one is prayer: for what language ſoeuer it ſpeaketh, the Phiſition
of heauen can vnderſtand it.Learned.
            
            
                Fiftly,A comforter. one that is able to comfort vs in our diſtreſſe, ſuch a
comforter is praier, it is the life of the ſoule: if thou art perplexed
with ſuch greefe of heart, as neither wine (according
to the aduiſe of Salomon) nor ſtrong drink can bring eaſe vnto,
thy ſpirit melting like waxe, finding no comfort at all either
in light or darknes, pleaſures or riches, kinsfolkes or
friends, wiſhing with Iob. 4. O that thou wouldeſt hide me in
the graue, and keepe me ſecret vntill thy wrath is paſt: yet
then this friend is our comfort, he will ſpeake for vs vnto the
Lord, King Dauids Phiſition, by this we may flie into the boſome
of Gods mercies. If any then be afflicted amongſt you,
let him pray▪ 
               Iam. 5. The reaſon why we deſire a friend with
all theſe qualities, is that he might both aide, and prouide vs
with all neceſſaries: praier is a friend who is able to diſpatch
 all our buſineſſe. Deſireſt thou a Phiſition in thy ſicknes to
cure thee, ſend this friend praier to King Dauids Phiſitian
 dwelling in heauen, and he will bring him with him. If thou
needeſt phiſick to heale thee, and which is good for thy diſeaſe,
ſend praier into heauen to fetch the hearbe of patience,
 which groweth not in our owne garden. If thou deſireſt neceſſaries
for thy ſoule, ſend him to the Lord, he will fetch for
thee, all that thou wanteſt, the bread of life, that heauenly
 Manna, the blood of Chriſt; the waters of mercie. Needeſt
thou a comforter, ſend praier vnto the Lord, and he wil bring

with him the beſt comforter of the ſicke, the holy Ghoſt, it is
his name; Iohn. 14. he will not feare to come to thee, as often the
bodily Phiſitian. Laſtly, if we deſire our friends to come and 
viſite vs, ſend prayer for them, and they will come: God the
father, God the ſonne, God the holy Ghoſt. No friend then
better then prayer. There are ſome bad ſeruants of which we
muſt take heeede, and as in the time of plague there are ſome
bad ſeruants who robbe and bereaue the ſicke of that he hath:
ſo there are ſome wicked friends who will depriue vs of ſpirituall
comforts,1. Bad ſeruants. if we be not ware of them. Firſt if we ſhould
vſe the aide of merits and ſend them vp, the ſtarres in heauen
would diſdaine it,Merites. that we which dwell at the footeſtoole of
God dare to preſume ſo farre,Ephe. 6. 4. when the pureſt creatures in
heauen are impure in his ſight.Feare. Secondly, if we ſend vp feare 
and diſtruſtfulnes, the length of the way will tire them out,
they are as heauy and lumpiſh as gaddes of yron, they will
ſinke to the ground, before they come halfe way to the throne
of ſaluation.Blaſphemies. Thirdly, if we ſend vp blaſphemies and curſes, all 
the creatures betwixt heauen and earth will band themſelues
againſt vs. The Sunne and the Moone wil raine down blood,
the fire, hote burning coales, and the ayre thunderbolts vpon
our heades. And therefore let vs not vſe the ayde of theſe
three bad ſeruants. As prayer is a ſeruant to ayde the ſicke, ſo
it is a truſtie friend or ſeruant to keepe your houſen, and families.
(O ye Londoners that are departed) in the Citie yee
vſe the ayde and truſt of others, but they are not the beſt, for
they are mortall and corruptible: exhort them therfore to vſe
this friend towards the Lord, both for you &amp; for themſelues:
for except the Lord build the houſe, they labour in vaine that
build it: except the Lord keepe the citie, the keeper waiteth
in vaine ſaith Dauid.
               Pſal. 127. 1. Thus I haue ſhewen you that be at
London, beloued of God, called to be Saintes, the Arke of
Noah, to enter in with your families.
            I come now to you beloued that haue left your mother
citie for a time,An exerciſe for the Londoners that are in the Countrey. which hope to returne: your departure I will
not diſprooue, nor wiſer then I, if ye haue vſed it lawfully, remembring
in your exile the affliction of Ioſeph. And ſpending

the time in thoſe things which make for the peace of
your cittie. To refeſh your mindes, and ſpend your time there
becauſe the workes of your vocation you cannot exerciſe:
diuers other exerciſes I knowe haue beene vſed, perhaps not
ſo well as ye might: al of them I do not condemne: but it is to
be feared, that the exerciſes of ſome haue beene friuolous, and
game ſome quarrellers, and that carding, dicing, and that
Cup challenging Profeſſion, by which many drinking to health,
drinke theirſelues out of health, haue beene to others as vſuall
paſtimes, as the fieldes to walke in. Giue me leaue beloued to
ſhew you a better exerciſe, and another paſtime, the paſtime
of King Dauid, a roiall exerciſe, which he vſed in the time of
plague, his prayer and inuocation with the elders of Iſrael:
ſpend heerin your time beloued till ye returne: when your
mother mourneth, will you ſport? when the head ſmarteth,
ſhall the members be ſenſeleſſe? pray with the prophet for the
peace of your Ieruſalem. It is the Apoſtles precept, to pray
continually, which if it euer was time to practiſe, it is at this
preſent.The prayſe of Prayer. Suffer me to enter into the prayſe of this exerciſe,
diuers things doe adde commendation to it, which ought to
 preſuade you to the vſe thereof. The firſt argument of prayſe
may be taken from the author thereof.It is Diuine. Not Moſes or Samuel,
prophet or Apoſtle, Patriarke or martyr, but God the father,
God the ſonne, God the holy Ghoſt, the bleſſed trinitie haue
bene the authors, which make it a diuine and heauenly exerciſe.
 The ſecond argument from the perſons which haue vſed
it▪
               Honourable. we delight in exerciſes which are accounted honorable, &amp;
which men of credite and good account doe commonly vſe;
this exerciſe is honorable, yea royall: not baſe and contemptible
onely haue ſpent their time with it, but Kings and princes,
King Dauid, Manaſſes, Exechiat, and the reſt. The bleſſed
Prophets, Patriarks, yea the prince of glorie, the ſonne of the
immortall God Chriſt Ieſus: It is ſo heauenly and honourable,
that by prayer we doe approach neere vnto God, and doe
as it were conioyne our ſelues with him: while we are in the
bodie, we are abſent from home: but by prayer we do aſcend
into heauen, prayer being as it were the band of our internall

coniunction with God. Further, it is honorable, not onely in
regarde of the perſons which haue vſed it; but alſo, to God
and vs. To God, for thereby we honor and glorifie him, Pſal.
               
50 acknowledging that all might, glorie, felicitie, health and
ſaluation belongeth to him, and that from him alone we muſt
receiue it.
            To vs, for thereby we are familiar with the Lord: if it be an 
honor for vs to be familiar with earthly Princes, which are
but duſt and aſhes, O what an honour is it then to be familiar
with the King of Kings, and monarke of the world! It is the
cheefeſt honour wherevnto he can aduance vs, when hee giueth
vs the ſpirit of prayer. If we deſire the valor of Knighthoode,
by prayer we may ſtand in place where Gods hand
hath made a breach, and doe as much as all the chariots and
horſemen in a kingdom. If you eſteeme it an honour to be in
the ſeruice of the Prince, giue your ſelfe to prayer, it is one of
the chiefeſt parts of Gods ſeruice. Yea it is ſo excellent, that
the ſacrifice of prayer is offered alone to him, whom Salomon
calleth excellent and glorious.Chriſtian. It is an honor to be a chriſtian,
let vs therefore vſe the chriſtian exerciſe: two things doe admoniſh
vs, our name, and the example of Chriſt: Chriſtians 
we are called, annointed alſo to be Prieſts and Prophets, and
that royall Prieſthood in Chriſt Ieſus. As the Prieſts offered 
the ſacrifices of bullocks and rammes, ſo let vs offer the ſacrifice
of prayer, which hath alſo beene Chriſts exerciſe. Mercie
hath prayed, and ſhall not miſerie? charitie hath prayed, and
ſhall not iniquitie pray? the Phyſition proſtrated vpon the
ground prayeth, and ſhall not the ſicke and the patient call
vpon the Lord? the innocent, and he in whoſe mouth there is
no fraude prayeth, and ſhall not the ſinner? the iudge prayeth,
and deſireth that the Lord would be mercifull and ſpare his
people, and ſhall not the guiltie bee ſuppleant to receiue
mercie?
            The pleaſure of it, may bee the third argument of commendation:
               Delectable
this exerciſe is pleaſant and delectable. To ſpend
the time in the Countrey, diuers vſe pleaſant and delectable
exerciſe: this is both acceptable to God, &amp; pleaſant to man:

                to God, for the ſweete odours of our prayers aſcend into heauen,To God.
               Apoc. 8. And as the ſent of incenſe and Odoriferus things
is pleaſant to the noſtrels of mortall man: So the prayer of
the righteous, ſaith Chryſoſtome, is pleaſant to the immortall
God. It is not then, the lamentation of men, eiulation of women
and children, mingling heauen and earth together with
a confuſion of out-cries, that is acceptable to God, and which
can enforce him to giue vs audience: but it is humble prayer,
the voyce of repentance: which as Ieſus Syrach ſpeaketh, Eccl.
35. 16. ſhall bee accepted with fauour, and reach vnto the
 cloudes. Secondly to vs all that our heart deſireth is in this
exerciſe.To man. Some being in the Countrey, ſpend their time in
diſcourſes, prayer is a diſcourſe with our beloued. If it was a
pleaſure to Iacob to ſpeake vnto Rachel, and to Ionathan with
Dauid: O what a recreation is it for our ſoules that they may
familiarly ſpeake with him, whoſe loue vnto vs is better then
gold or pearle. If we delight to ſpeake languages, by prayer
wee may ſpeake the excellenteſt language which hath euer
beene, the language of Canaan: let vs not feare to diſcourſe
with the Lord by our prayers, for hee is not like vnto the
ſpruce and finical ſonnes of men: feare not, ſaith Chryſoſtome,
he ſeeketh not at thy hands painted eloquence, an angelicall
tongue, filed phraſes: but beholdeth only the beautie of thy
ſoule. Others take their pleaſure while they are in the Countrey,
to ride vp and downe in their Coches and Chariots, being
carried therein betwixt heauen and earth. Let prayer bee
your Coache beloued: it is as one ſaith, as a Chariot of fire,
bearing vs aloft in the preſence of God, able to mount vs aboue
the Eagles of the skie to ſeeke the Lords aſſiſtance. In
the time of plague, there is appointed a Waggon or Coache
to carrie the ſicke to the Peſt-houſe, and there to be healed:
there is no better Chariot to carrie our ſoules vnto the houſe
of heauen to bee healed by that heauenly Phyſitian, then
humble prayer. Some delight to goe vp and downe and ſee
their friends; our beſt friends at this time, and at all times who
can do vs the moſt good: are God the Father, the Sonne and
the holy Ghoſt: let vs viſite them therefore continually by

our prayers. Others in writing letters, what is prayer elſe,
but as it were a letter ſent to God in which wee declare our
neede: and as a letter is an amiable diſcourſe and conference
of one friend with another, as if they were both preſent: So is
our prayer, as a friendly letter or diſcourſe of vs which are
abſent from home: with our beſt friend the Lord, as if wee
were preſent with him in heauen. Send this letter, and letter
vpon letter: yee that are now exiled, ſhew vnto the Lord
your neede: pray vnto him that hee will bring you home againe,
and remooue that in his mercie which keepeth you
backe. Laſtly, ſome in running of Races, or in Hunting; but
yee beloued in this afflicted time, runne the way of Gods
Commandements: as Dauid, Pſal. 119. runne to the name of
Iehouah with the righteous, Prou 18. runne the race which is
ſet before you, and that with patience, looking vnto Chriſt
Ieſus, Hebr. 12. 1. and ſo runne that yee may obtaine that
which you ſue for. Hunt not after the pleaſures of this life,
but after the liuing God: and as the Hart brayeth for the ryuers
of waters, ſo let your ſoules pant after the liuing God,
Pſal. 42. 1. That the Lords Hunter, Pſal. 91. hunt vs not, but
that the Lord may deliuer vs from the ſnare of the Hunter,
and from the noyſome peſtilence, Pſal. 91. 3. Vſe therefore
this comfortable exerciſe: the childe is neuer better but when
it is in his fathers and mothers lap: So ſhal you neuer be better,
but when by prayer you creepe as it were in your heauenly
Fathers boſome: it will kindle your loue toward him,
as the loue of louers is kindled, the more they come together:
and if yee remaine there this Winter, feruent prayer
will bee in ſteade of fire, to kindle in your hearts the loue of
God.
            Fourthly, the profit of this exerciſe commendeth it much,
it is not onely delectable,Profitable. but alſo profitable. Some which
are in the Countrey at this time ſpend their time I doo confeſſe
profitably, riding vp and downe to buy commodities 
againſt the future:To vs. but prayer is a farre profitabler exerciſe
for this time, for it is not onely profitable to our ſelues, but
alſo vnto others: yea, to the whole Realme. And as the Apoſtle

ſpeaketh of Godlines, that it is profitable for al things;
ſo I may ſay of prayer, that it can obtaine any thing: profitable
for vs in two reſpects: Firſt, to obtaine that we haue not:
 Secondly, to keepe that we haue obtained. Firſt, if thou lackeſt
knowledge and wiſedome, prayer is the meanes to obtaine
it, Iam. 1. If thy vnderſtanding bee darke, pray with
Dauid, Pſal. 119. Open mine eyes O Lord, that I may ſee the myſteries
of thy Law. If thou lackeſt zeale, pray with Dauid, Pſal.
119. Lord incline my heart vnto thy law, &amp;c. And becauſe this
world is a deſart where we may eaſily erre, pray with Dauid,
Pſal. 50. Leade me in thy pathes, &amp;c. If our ſoules be infected
with the plague of vanitie and couetouſneſſe, the meanes to
remooue it, is prayer, Pſal 119. O Lord remooue farre from me
vanitie, and encline not my heart to couetouſneſſe. The meanes
to obtaine a contented minde, is alſo prayer, Prou 30. Pouertie
nor riches giue me not, &amp;c. If thou deſireſt to thinke vpon
thy mortalitie, by the ſubiect whic
                  •
                now is preſented to thee,
pray with Dauid, Pſa. 90. Teach vs O Lord to number our dayes,
that we may applie our hearts to wiſedome. If yee deſire to returne,
it is not your ſports or delightes, but your prayers that
muſt bring you backe.2. Sam. 24. If yee deſire the ceaſing of the plague,
it is your prayer that muſt remooue the cauſe, that the effect
 may ceaſe. As prayer obtaineth, ſo it keepeth that you haue
already obtained: ſuch are not your exerciſes, which ye your
ſelues haue inuented O ſonnes of Adam: for by them you
often looſe that which you had purchaſed ryotouſly (which
Alexander blamed in his friends) waſting and conſuming
your whole abilitie. There is another thing which ought to
perſwade you to this exerciſe:2. To others. which is, that it is profitable
to others: prayer doeth more good then Almes: for by our
Almes we can helpe but a fewe; but by our prayers wee can
helpe thouſands and thouſands: yea thoſe which are farre off.
Prayers, are the almes of the rich as well as of the poore: for
Pharao did as well begge for prayers, as poore Lazarus for
crummes. Yee rich men that are in the Countrey, beſtowe
theſe almes vpon the poore, as well as the almes of your purſes:
and in this afflicted time, ſeeke more to profite the whole

Realme by your prayers, then by your commodities. I ende
this point with the ſaying of Auguſtine: Plus profeci orando quā
legendo, I haue more profited by praying, then by reading.
            Fiftly,5. To ſtrengthen vs. this exerciſe is commendable, becauſe it is able to
to ſtrengthen vs. Some in the Countrey doo ſpend their time
in exerciſes, by which they may maintaine their health, and
ſtrengthen their bodies, that they may bee able to doo any
thing: the exerciſe of prayer is good to make vs recouer the
health of our ſoules, which was waxen weake: as this preſent
plague, and your preſent exile both doo witneſſe. Yea,
it is able to make vs doo admirable things. Was it euer heard
that mightie Potentates, as there haue beene many: Alexander
the great, Iulius Caeſar and the reſt could make the Sunne
or the Moone to ſtand ſtill in the firmament? And yet this
hath done the prayer of Ioſua. Haue there euer beene any armies
ſo great and mightie, which could make the earth to
tremble vnder their feete? No beloued: the mightie armie of
Xerxes could not doo it, and yet this hath done the prayer of
the Apoſtles, Act. 4. Who hath euer heard that it hath beene
poſſible to mortall man, to raiſe the dead and to giue life to
the deceaſed? The Phyſitians doo acknowledge their impotencie,Heb. 11.
and yet this hath done the prayer of Elizaeur. As the
Apoſtle then in the commendation of faith, rehearſeth the
wonders which they haue wrought by faith: So it may bee
ſaid of prayer which is done in faith: by prayer Moſes diuided
the red ſea: by prayer Ioſua beat down thewals of Iericho:
by prayer Sidrach and Abednago quenched the fire: Daniel
ſtopped the Lyons greedie and deuouring throates: the Apoſtles
opened the priſons and brake their bands. And I
will yet adde one thing, by prayer brethren you ſhall be able
to ouercome him, who is inuincible. The Lord hath beſieged
and taken in your Citie by his deſtroying Angel, the only
meanes to reſiſt him, and to make him retire, are your
humble prayers: O the admirable force of prayer, which
ouercommeth him who ouercommeth al things! I may compare
the prayers of the righteous to the haires of Sampſon: as
long as his head was adorned and couered with them, hee

was in a maner inuincible, hee brake the cordes and roapes
wherewith he was bound: his ſtrength lying in his haire; but
being ſhauen, his ſtrength went from him, he waxed weake
and like other men. All your ſtrength beloued lieth in your
prayer, as long as you exerciſe your ſelues therein, you ſhall
be able to reſiſt, I ſay not the tyrants &amp; the diuel, but the Lords
Angel himſelfe. You haue another enemie, the which to reſiſt,
it is neceſſarie that you learne to handle the ſword of prayer,
this enemie is cruell, malicious, mightie, ſubtile and induſtrious,
his name bewrayeth his nature; Sathan by name,
who is not onely in the citie, but followeth you in the country
(for as a deuouring lion he compaſſeth the earth) and there
he ſeeketh to make you forget the Lord, and the affliction of
Ioſeph: to ſticke to the creature, and forget the creator; to withſtand
this enemie and his fierie darts, let this be your continuall
exerciſe: Imitate the induſtrious wraſtlers, who to caſt
downe another, firſt fall downe themſelues: ſo to ouerthrow
this enemie who ſeeketh in the countrey to ouerthrow you,
caſt downe your ſelues by humble prayer and faſting, that in
that place you may triumph ouer him who thought to triumph
ouer you. To end beloued, to you all I ſpeake togither,
you that are in the cittie, enter this Arke: you that are caſt
downe vpon your beddes, vſe the aide of this friend: you that
are departed, let this be your paſtime, that we altogether may
bee preſerued from the deluge, and the waters may decreaſe
more and more, till they bee dried vp, that beeing
decreaſed wee may offer the ſacrifice of thankeſgiuing; as
Noah offered vnto the Lord after the flood. But let vs
not bee like vnto the ſea-ſicke, who onely are weake, lament
and crie as long as they are in the tempeſt, and when
they begin to ſmell the ayre, and are gone out of the ſhip, they
forget both their ſicknes and their deliuerance.Gene. 28. But rather as
Iacob (ye that are departed) flying to heauen, the remembrance
of his countrey being ſweete, made an excellent vow
and prayer, that if he came againe to his fathers houſe in ſafetie,
the Lord ſhould be his God, and that he would giue vnto
the Lord the tenth of all he had: ſo likewiſe ye that are departed

from your mother citie, as Iacob from his fathers houſe,
the remembrance thereof being ſweete to you, as I know it is,
make the vow and prayer of Iacob, that when the Lord bring
you home againe in ſafetie, that he ſhall be your God, and
that ye will ſerue him with more zeale and feruencie then ye
haue done before:2. Pet. 3. 17. 18. further, that ye will (if not the tenth) yet
ſome part of your goods, beſtow vpon the Lord in his poore
members. Let the Apoſtles words be the concluſion,
Ye therfore beloued, ſeeing ye know theſe things
before, beware leſt ye be alſo plucked away
with the errour of the wicked, but grow
in grace, and in the knowledge of
our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt,
to him be glory both now
and for euermore,
Amen.
            FINIS.
         
      
   

