
   
      
         
            A briefe declaratio[n] of the shews, deuices, speeches, and inuentions, done &amp; performed before the Queenes Maiestie, &amp; the French ambassadours, at the most valiaunt and worthye triumph, attempted and executed on the Munday and Tuesday in VVhitson weeke last, anno 1581 Collected, gathered, penned &amp; published, by Henry Goldvvel, Gen.
            Goldwel, Henry.
         
         
            
               1581
            
         
         Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-07 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01848
            STC 11990
            ESTC S105771
            99841497
            99841497
            6083
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01848)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6083)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 384:19)
         
         
            
               
                  A briefe declaratio[n] of the shews, deuices, speeches, and inuentions, done &amp; performed before the Queenes Maiestie, &amp; the French ambassadours, at the most valiaunt and worthye triumph, attempted and executed on the Munday and Tuesday in VVhitson weeke last, anno 1581 Collected, gathered, penned &amp; published, by Henry Goldvvel, Gen.
                  Goldwel, Henry.
               
               [36] p.   
               
                  By Robert VValdgraue, dwelling vvithout Temple-barre, neere vnto Sommerset-House,
                  Imprinted at London :
                  [1581]
               
               
                  Signatures: A-B C² .
                  Running title reads: A declaration of the triumph shewed before the Queenes Maiestie.
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Elizabeth --  I, --  Queen of England, 1533-1603.
            
         
      
      
         
            2003-03
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-04
            AptaraKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-05
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2003-05
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-06
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            A briefe declaratiō
of the shews,
deuices, speeches, and inuentions,
done &amp; performed
before the Queenes Maiestie, &amp;
the French Ambassadours, at the
most valiaunt and worthye Triumph,
attempted and executed
on the Munday and Tuesday
in VVhitson weeke
last, Anno
1581
            Collected, gathered, penned &amp; published,
by Henry Goldwel, Gen.
            
               Imprinted at London, by Robert
VValdegraue, dwelling
vvithout Temple-barre,
neere vnto Sommer-set-House.
         
         
            
            
            To the verie worshipfull
and his approued patrone, Master Rowland
B
                  •
               asebridge of great VVickombe, in the countie
of Buck. Gen. his humble and faithful anowed:
Henrie Goldwell wisheth that welfare
which highteth eternall
happines.
            
               SIr, I stande at a stay like the Ladie of
TH
                  •
               SSALI
                  •
               , and in a ma
                  •
               mering
maze like ALEXANDERS man, the o
                  •
               
making pitious plaintes in beholding
the picture of her person, fearing she
                  •
               
shoulde not be fancied, and alwaies lamented
when she wrote any letter,
doubting it shoulde be disliked: The other wept in winter
for extremitie of colde, and sorowed, in summer to remember
the returne of HY
                  •
               MS. So rest I assayled vvith
such perplexities, and frozen with like 
                  •
               eare, not only douting
to discouer these hono
                  •
               rable Actions, for feare of the
misreporting: but also fearing mine 
                  〈◊〉
                vnworthiness
                  •
               
and want of skilfull eloquence to set f
                  ••
               th so woorthie a
matter (as was the last Triumph perfourmed before her
Maiestie:) Yet I considered with my selfe, better an ill reporter
then a dumme speaker, better badly 
                  〈◊〉
                open then
quite forgotten, &amp; better Porredge then no 
                  〈◊〉
                VVhen
APPOLLO is a sheepe then 
                  •
               AN is chief
                  •
                
               
                  ••
               nstrill: vvhen
PALLAS is absent, then SERES is 
                  〈◊〉
                when TVL
               
                  •
               IE
is out of tovvn, thē CRASSVS may crake of his cunning.
Therfore s
                  ••
               h no mā vvriteth at al of these vvorthies,
nor no persō publisheth the exploits of these nobles, rather
thē oblition should diminish their merits, I haue attēpted
the vvriting. And so nere as I could I haue made a collection
both of their names, speaches, and chiefest inuentions,
vvhich as they bee, I present to your presence in name of
a nevvse or noueltie, knovving none more vvorthie then
your self, to vvhom to present this Pamphlet, both for your
knovvledge in approued Martial Chiualrie, nor none vvhō
I honour or ovve more dutifull loyaltie. As report hath
rong forth your deserued vvorthynes, and flying FAM
                  •
               
hath resou
                  •
               ded your seruice, both in greene youth
                  •
                and

these your graue yeres, employed asvvell in vvarres as in
peace, in quailing the enemie, as in ruling your countrey,
in aduenturing abroad, in aduertising at home, then a conductor,
novv a 
                  〈◊〉
                valiant as MARS, novve made
a ciuill MAGISTRAT
                  •
               , then boldly in battell till the last
blovve, novve 
                  〈◊〉
                home in trayning vp souldiers, and
to be short, then 
                  〈◊〉
                ted a Captaine, like ACHILLES
for coura
                  •
                
               
                  〈…〉
                as SCIPIO for singuler c
                  •
               unsaile.

                  〈…〉
                vvould delight you to heare of the
tovvar
                  •
                
               
                  〈…〉
                English Nobles, and of the courage of
our courtlie crue, sith you vvere absent at the perfou
                  ••
               ing
of these pleasures, I haue at this present for your recreation
thus certified these courtly and knightly discourses, to
you vvho in times past haue bene, as gallant a courtier as a
valliant souldier: But if you ere this haue bene tolde of this
Triumph, it may be you heard not the names of the parties▪
a
                  •
               d though you haue heard of the number of rumours, ye
                  •
               
paraduenture you knowe not theffect of their speaches,
and though you haue h
                  •
               d of their seueral coppies: yet happely
you misse of their sund
                  •
               e inuentions, and though
you be priuie to most o
                  •
                these matters, yet hope I you vvill
like nere the vvorse of my labours, nor make lesse account
of this my vvel meaning: therfore as one more aduenturus
thē vvarie, more presu
                  •
               ptuous thē vvittie, more 
                  •
               oole hard
                  ••
               
then praise vvorthy, I submit my selfe to the knees of your
courtesie, to like of me and my present, hop
                  •
               ng to find that
fauour at your handes vvhich an Emperour once shevved
to his simplest Subiect, vvho more esteemed his poore
dish of vva
                  •
               er, thē the gifts of gold of his richest ma
                  •
               chāts,
the one proceding of loue to his povver, the other in hope
of a greater gain? vvhose Image if you imitate I pronounce
my self happie, and tho gain that I looke for, is your gracious
good vvill? vvhereby I shalbe emboldened to attempt
some vvorke more vvorthy, to gratifie your goodnes and
to make mo
                  ••
                manifest my dutifull loyaltie, vvishing you
novve and eueral things vvorldly to your vertuous vvill,
&amp; after the time of this transitorie life, your soule may sing
Alle
                     •
                  ia vvith the number of thelect, and reap that revvard
vvhich remianeth endlesse.
            
               Yours most vvilling to be commaunded,
&amp; moste desirous to discharge his duety.
H. G.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            ¶A Declaration of the
Triumph shewed before the Queenes
Maiestie, and the French Ambassadours,
on VVhitson Munday &amp; Tuesday.
            
               
                  TO beginne particularly to
wright of these attempts,
and briefly to runne ouer

                     •
                  ache s
                     •
                  uerall action, the
cause of the same is firste
to be considered. After the
arriuall of the French Ambassadours, and
vpon thei
                     •
                   comming to the English court,
The Nobles and Gentlemen of the same,
desirous to sh
                     •
                  w them alcourtesie poss
                     •
                  ble
fittest for such estates, and to sporte them
with all courtly pleasure, agreede among
them to prepare a Triumphe, whiche was
very quickly concluded, and being deuised
in moste su
                     •
                  ptuous order, was by them
performed in as valiant a manner, to their
endlesse fame and honour. The cheefe, or
challengers in these attemptes, were these.

The Earle of Arundel, the Lord Windsore
Master Philip Sidney, and Master Fulke
Grevill, Who calling themselues the four
Foster Children of Desire, made their inuention
of the foresaide Triumphe in this
order and forme following.
               The Gallary or place at the end of the
Tiltyard adioining to her Maiesties house
at Whiteball,
                  The excellent ineuntion of the Triumph. whereas her person should be
placed, was called and not without cause,
the Castle or Fortresse of perfect beautie,
for as much as her highnes should be there
included, whereto the said Foster children
layde Tytle and claime as their due by
discent to belong vnto them. And vppon
deniall or any
                     •
                   cpulse from that their d
                     •
                  s
                     •
                  
                  red
pa
                     •
                  rimonie, they vowed to vanquishe
&amp; conquer by force who so shoulde seeme to
wit
                     •
                  stand it. For the accomplishing wherof
they sent their challenge or first defiance
to the Q
                     •
                  eens maiestie: which was vttred
by a boy on Sunday, the sixt
                     •
                  enth of April
last, as her Maiesty came frō the Chappel,
who being apparrelled in red and white, as
a Martial messenger of Desires fostered
Children, without making any pr
                     •
                  cise reuerence

at all, vttered these speeches of defiaunce,
from his masters to her Maiestie,
the effect whereof ensueth.
               O Lady,The first defie or challenge. that doth intitle the titles you possesse
with the honour of your worthinesse, rather crowning
the great crowne you holde, with the fame to
haue so excellinge an owner, then you receiuinge
to your selfe any encrease, keeping that outward ornament?
Vouchsafe with patient attention to heare
the wordes which I by commandement am here to
deliuer vnto you, wherein if your eares (vsed to the
thankes giuing of your people and the due prayses
of the earth) shall feele a stately disdayne to heare
once the sounde of a de
                     •
                  ie? yet dare I warrant my
selfe so farre vpon the reply deceiuing show of rare
beauty, as that malice can not fall from so fayre a
minde vppon the sely messenger, whose mouth is a
seruant to others direction. Know ye therefore al
onely Princesse, that hereby (for far of they are neuer)
there lyes encamped the foure long h
                     •
                  ples, now
hopeful fostered children of Desire: who hauing bin
a great vvhile nourished vp vvith that infectiue
milke, and to 
                     •
                  o much care of their fiery fosterer,
(though full oft that dry nurse dispaier indeuered to
vvaine them from it) being novve as strong in that
nurture, as they are vveake in Fortune, incouraged
vvith the valiaunt counsaile of neuer fainting DESIRE,
and by the same assured, that by right of inheritaunce
euen from euer, the FORTRESSE OF
BEAVTIE doth belong to her Fostered Children,
Lastly, finding it blazed by all tongues, ingraued in
all hearts, and proued by all eies that this fortresse

built by nature is seated in this Realme: These foure
I say and say againe, thus nourished, thus animated
thus entituled, and thus enformed, doe vvill you by
me, euen in the name of Iustice, that you wil no lō
                  ger
exclude vertuous DESIRE frō perfect BEAV
TIE? VVhereto if you yelde, (O yelde for so al reason
requireth) then haue I no more to say, but reioice
that my sayings hath obteined so righfull, and
yet so blissefull a request. But if (alasse but let not
that be needful) BEAVTIR be accompanied vvith
disdainfull pride, and pride vvaighted on by refusing
crueltie. Then must I denounce vnto you (VVoe is
me, ansvvere before it be denounced) that they determine
by request to accomplish their claim, And
because they vvill better testifie to the vvorlde, they
haue bene brought vp vnder the vvings of honorable
DESIRE, this honourable forevvarning they
sende you. That vpon the xxiiii day of this month
of April they vvill besiege that fatal FORTRESSE,
vowing not to spare (if this obstinacie continue) the
svvoorde of faithfulnesse, and the fire of affection?
Novve if so it fall out, the vvorthie knights of your
Court (moued vvith passion in them selues) disdaine
of my senders boldenesse, or partiall liking (vvhiche
I moste doubt) to the maiestie of your eyes, will either
bid them battell before they approch, or suffering
them to approch, will after la
                     •
                  or to l
                     •
                  uye the
siege, They protest to meet them in vvhat sort they
vvill chuse, vvihning onely it may bee perfourmed
before your ovvne eies, vvhome they knovv as euen
in iudgement, as daintie in chusing, vvhere if so they
list. First at the Tilte in so many courses, as your self
shall please to appoint. And then if any wil call them
to the course of the field vvith Launce and svvord,

they hope to giue such true proofes of their valler,
as at least shal make their desires more noble, vovving
on the other side, that if before the night part
the fray, they do not ouercome al thē that come in
against them, they vvil yeeld themselues slaues vnto
you for euer? This therefore O Queene (greater in
that you are Queen of your selfe, then in passing the
vvhole compasse of the earth) haue I deliuered my
charge, not as a challenge to your knightes? againste
vvhome, (but in so iust a cause) they acknovvledge
themselues vnable to match the meanest, But as a
plaine proclaimation of VVarre, vnlesse the FORTRESSE
OF BEAVTIE, that hath vvoon so many
to lose themselues, be speedily surrendered: And
novv it shalbe seene vvhat knights you haue, whom
BEAVTIE may draw to resist a rightful title, And I
for my pore part moued by that I see in you (thogh
I serue your enemies) vvill daily pray that all men
may see you, &amp; then you shal not feare any arms of
aduersaries: Or if enimies you must haue, that either
they may haue the mindes of them that send me,
or their fortunes in that they haue long desired.
               At which day abouesaid for certain vrgent
occasions,Vrgent ca
                        •
                     
                     ses why the Challenge was deferd. the saide Challenge and Triumph
by her Maiesties commādement,
was deferted till the first day of May. At
which day for like causes it was further
deferred til the next Munday following,
beeing the eighth day of May: And so
till Whitson Munday, when they first
began to perfourme it.
               
                  
The said day being come, the foure Foster
children had made preparation to besiege
the Fortresse of Beawtie. And thereto
had prouided a frame of wood which was
couered with Canuas, &amp; painted outwardly
in such excellent order, as if it had bene very
naturall earth or moulde, and caried the
name of a Rowling trench,
                  The order of the rovvling trench vvith most excellent inuentions. which went on
wheeles, which way soeuer y• persons with
in did driue it. Upon the top whereof was
placed two Cannons of wood, so passing
well coullered, as they seemed to be in deed
two fayre field
                     •
                   peeces of ordinances, and
by them was placed two men for Gunners
clothed in Crymson Sarcenet, with their
baskets of erth for defēce of their bodies by
them. And also there stood on the top of the
trench, an Ensigne bearer, in the same sute
with the gunners, displaying his ensigne,
and within the saide trench was cunningly
conueyed, diuers kinde of most excellent
musicke against the castle of Beauty. These
things thus al in a readinesse, the Challengers
approched, &amp; came from the Stable
toward the Tyltyard, one after another in
braue and excellent order. And the manner
of their seueral entrings was as foloweth.
               
                  
First,The Earle of Arundels entrie the firste day. the Earle of Arundell entred the
Ty
                     •
                  teyarde, all in Gylt and engrauen Armour,
with Caparisons and furniture richly
and brauely embrodered, hauing attendaunt
on him, Two gentlemen vshers, iiii.
Paages riding on foure spare horses, and
twentie of his Gentlemen. Al which aforesayde
were apparayled in shorte Clokes
and venetian hose of Crymson veluet, layd
with gold lace, doublets of yellow Satten,
hattes of Crymson veluet with gold bands
and yellow fethers, and yellow silke stocks.
Then had hee sixe tump
                     •••
                  ers that sounded
before him. And xxxi. 
                     •
                  eomen that waited
after him apparailed in Cassock coats,
and venetian hose of Crimson veluet, layde
on wich red silke and golde lace, Duble
                     •
                  s
of yellow taffatie, Hats of crimson Taffatie,
with yellowe feathers, and yellowe
worsted stockings.
               After him proceded the Lord Windsore,
                  The Lorde VVindsors entrie the first day.
in gilte and engrauen Armour, with caparisons
and furniture, richely embroydered
with golde, hauing attendant on him foure
Pages riding on foure spare horses, and
foure and twentie gentlemen, All apparailed

in short cloaks of scarlet, lined through
with orange tawnie taff
                     •
                  tie, &amp; laide about
with siluer lace, Dublets of orange taw
                     •
                  y
Satten, venetiāhose of orange tawnie veluet,
blacke veluet caps, with siluer bandes
and white feathers, and silu
                     •
                  red rapiers &amp;
daggers, with scabberds o
                     •
                  blacke velue
                     •
                  .
Foure trumpetters, and 
                     •
                  wo footemen in
cassocke coats and ven
                     •
                  tian hose of orange
tawnie veluet, and black veluet caps with
siluer bands &amp; white fethers, foure gromes
of his stable leading of his foure horses, in
cassocke coats and venetian hose of orange
tawnie 
                     •
                  affatie, and orange tawnie feltes
with siluer 
                     •
                  ands, and white fethers. Then
had he three score yeomen in coates of Orenge
tawnie clothe, with the Vnicorne of
of siluer plate on their sleeues, and orange
tawnie feltes with siluer bands and white
feathers.
               Then proceeded M. Philip Sidney,
                  M. Sydneys entry. in very
sumptuous maner, wt armor part blewe, &amp;
the rest gilt &amp; engrauen, with foure spare
horses, hauing caparisons and furniture
veri riche &amp; costly, as some of cloth of gold
embroidred wt pearle, &amp; some embroodred

with gold and siluer feathers, very richly &amp;
cunningly wrought, he had foure pages y•
rode on his four spare horses, who had cassok
coats &amp; venetiā hose al of cloth of siluer,
layd with gold lace, &amp; hats of y• same with
golde bands, and white fethers, and eache
one a paire of white buskins. Thē had he a
thirtie gentlemen &amp; 
                     •
                  eomen, &amp; foure trumpetters,
who were all in cassoke coats and
venetian l
                     •
                  ose of yellow veluet, laid wt siluer
lace, yellowe veluet caps with siluer bands
and white fethers, and euery one a paire of
white buskins. And the had vppon their
coates, a scrowle or bande of siluer, which
came scarse wise ouer the shoulder, and so
downe vnder the arme, with this po
                     •••
                  e, or
sentence written vpon it, both before and
behinde, Sicnos non nobis.
               
               Then came M. Fulke Gr
                        •
                     uill, in gylt armour,M. Fulke Greuils entry.
with riche and fayre caparisons and
furniture, hauing foure spare horses with
foure Pages riding vpon them, and foure
Trumpeters sounding before him, and a
Twentie men gentlemen and yeomen attending
vpon him, who with the Pages &amp;
Trumpe
                     •
                  ers were all apparelled in loose

Ierkins of Tawnie taffatie, cut and lined
with yellowe sarsenet, &amp; laied with golde
lace, and cut downe the arme and set with
loopes and buttons of golde, Uenetian hose
of the same lined as asoresaid, laied with
golde lace downe the side with loopes and
buttons of golde, with each a paire of yellow
worsted stockings. And ha
                     •
                  ts of Tawnie
Taffarie with golde bands and yellow
Fethers. Hauing thus all entred the Tilte
yard, they proceeded on with the rowling
trenche before them, which staied against
the Queene, and they passed by, as though
they would behold the Fortresse of Beauty.
And so went about the Tilt, At last the boy
that vttered the firste deflaunce pronounced
these speeches to her Maiestie.
               If the message lately deliuered vnto you had bene
beleeued and followed.The second defie or chalenge. (O Queene) in whom the
whole story of vertue is written with the language
of BEAVTIE. Nothing should this violence haue
needed in your inuiolate presence, your eyes which
til now haue bene onely wont to discerne the bowed
knees of kneeling heartes, and inwardly tourned,
found alwaies the heauenly peace of a sweete mind,
Shoulde not nowe haue their faire beames reflec
                     •
                  
with the shining of A
                     •
                  moure, shoulde not nowe be
driuen to see the furie of Desire, nor the fyery force
of fury: But since so it is (alasse that so it is) that in

the defence of obstinate refusal ther neuer groweth
victory but by compassion? They are come, what
neede I say more, you see them, ready in hart as you
knowe, and able with handes as they hope, not only
to assailing but to preuailing. Perehance you dispise
the smalnesse of number, I say vnto you, the force of
DESIRE goes not by fulnesse of company. Nay
rather Vew with what vnresistable determination
themselues approch, And howe not onely the heauens
send their inuisible Instrument to ayde them.
But also the very earth the dullest of al the Elements
which with naturall heauinesse still striues to the
sleepie Center,Meaning the musicke vvithin the mount. yet for aduancing this enterprise is
cōtented actiuely as you shal see to moue it self vpō
it selfe, to rise vp in height, That it may the better
command the high &amp; high minded FORTRESSE?
Many wordes when deedes are in field are tedious
both to the speaker and hearer,VVhervvith the mount moued and rose vp in height. you see their forces
but know not their fortunes, if you bee resolued, it
boots not, and threats dread not, I haue discharged
my charge, which was euen when all thinges were
ready for the assaulte, then to offer partlie a thinge
not so much vnused as gratious in besiegers, you shal
nowe be sommoned to yeld, which if it be reiected,
then looke for the affectionate Allarme to bee followed
with desirous Assaulte: The time approcheth
for their approches: But no time shall stay me from
wishing, that how soeuer this succeede, the worlde
may long time enioy her cheefest ornament, which
deckes it with her felfe, and herselfe with the loue
of goodnesse.
               Which speach being ended, the Rowlling

trench or Mounte of earth was mooued
as nere the Queenes Maiestie as might
be, which being setled, the musike played
verie pleasauntly, and one of the Boyes
being then accompanied with Cornets,
summoned the Fortresse with this song.
               
                  Yeelde yeelde, O yeelde, you that this FORTE do holde,
                  which seated is, in spotlesse honors fi
                        •
                     lde,
                  Desires great force, no forces can withhold:
                  then to DESIERS desire, O yeelde O yeelde.
               
               
                  Yeelde yeelde O yeelde, trust not on beauties pride,
                  fayrenesse though fayer, is but a feeble shielde,
                  VVhen strong Desire, which vertues loue doth guide,
                  claymes but to gaine his due, O yeelde O yeelde.
               
               
                  Yeelde yeelde O yeelde, who first this Fort did make,
                  did it for iust Desires, true children builde,
                  Such was his minde, if you another take:
                  defence herein doth wrong, O yeelde O yeelde,
               
               
                  Yeelde yeelde O yeelde, now is it time to yeelde,
                  Before thaslault beginne, O yeelde O yeelde.
               
               When that was ended, another Boye turning
him selfe to the Foster children and
their retinue, sung this Allarme.
               
                  Allarme allarme, here will no yeelding be,
                  such marble eares, no cunning wordes can charme,
                  
                     
Courage therefore, and let the stately see.
                  that naught withstandes DESIRE, Allarme allarme.
               
               
                  Allarme allarme, let not their beauties moue
                  remorse in you to doe this FORTRESSE harme,
                  For since warre is the ground of vertues loue,
                  no force, though force be vsed Allarme allarme.
               
               
                  Allarme allarme, companions nowe beginne,
                  about this neuer conquered walles to swarme,
                  More prayse to vs we neuer looke to winne,
                  much may that was not yet, Allarme allarme.
               
               
                  Allarme allarme when once the fight in warme,
                  then shall you see them yelde, Allarme allarme.
               
               Which ended, the two Canons were short
off,The shooting of, of the tvvo Canons, the one vvith svveet vvater, and the other vvith svveet poulder. the one with sweet poulder, and the other
with sweete water, very o
                     •
                   oriferous
and pleasaunt, and the noyse of the shooting
was very excellent consent of mellodie
within the Mounte: And after that,
was store of prettie scaling ladders, and
the footemen threwe Flowers and such
fancies against the walles, with all such
deuices as might se
                     •
                  me fit shot for Desire,
All which did continue till time the
Defendaunts came in.
               Then came in the defendaunts in most

sumptuous maner,The maner of the defendants comming in. with euery one his seruaunts,
Pages, and trumpeters, (hauing
some more, some lesse) in such order as I
haue here vnder placed thē, with euery one
his sundrie inuention, which for that some
of them be mistical and not knowen to manie,
I omit therefore for bre
                     •
                  ties s
                     •
                  ke to
speake of anie, yet such speeches as weare
spoken or presented for them to her Maiestie,
so manie as were, or at the least as I
c
                     •
                  uld come by, I haue 
                     ••
                  re in their order
placed them, whereby their inucntions for
whome they were spoken, are therin plainlie
declared. Therefore I refer you to the
reeding of them hereafter, But thus the
desendaunts, entred the title yarde, one after
an other as followeth.
               First M. Henry Grey, Sir Thomas Parat,
                  The defendant names that run at Tilte.
M. Anthonie Cooke, M. Th
                        •
                     mas Ratcliffe,
Master Henrie Knowles, M. William
Knowles, M. Robert Knowles. M. Frauncis
Knowles, M. Raffe Bowes, M. Thomas Kelway,
M. George Goring, M. William Tresham,
M. Robert Alexander, M. Edwarde
Dennie, M. Herculus Meautus, M. Edward
Moore, M. Richard Skipwith, M. Richard

Warde, M. Edward Digibie, M. Henry Nowell,
M. Henry Brunkerd. And afterwards
in the middest of the running, came in Sir
Henry Lea, as unknowen, and when he had
brokē his sixe staues, went out in like maner
againe.
               So passing on one after another, when sir
Thomas Parat and M. Cooke came to the
end of the Tilt, ouer against the Queens
Maiestie, one of their pages arraied like
an Angel, vttred these speches vnto her.
               Dispayre,The speeche of sir Thomas Parrat and master Cooke, to the Queene no not dispaire (moste high and happie
Princesse) could so congeale the frozen knighte in
the ayer but that DESIRE, (ah sweete DESIRE)
enforced him to behold the Sun on the earth, wheron
as he was gasing with twinckling eye (for who
can behold such be
                     •
                  mes stedfastly) he begun to dissolue
into droppes, m
                     •
                  lting with such delighte that
hee seemed to preferre the lingering of a certaine
death, before the lasting of an vncertaine life, suche
is the nature of engrauen loyaltie, that it chuseth rather
to haue the body dissolued then the minde disliked,
Thus consuming with con
                     •
                  ent, (a sweete sicnesse
is conceite) and pining with more then speakable
passions, he suddenly beheld that Sunne to be
besieged which he so deuoutly serued, wherewith
boiling in no lesse disdain
                     •
                  , then surprised with immoderate
pensiuenesse, he vttered these wordes: O
Ioue, if thou mean to resolue nature into contraries,
why doe I liue to see it, if into nothing, why doe I
liue at all, if the foote scale the head, there is no rest

if DESIRE ouershoote duetie, there is no reason,
and where either of these are, there can be no rule.
And so setting more sighes then may bee numbred
by syphers, this present time, (ah greefe) this present
time, that honest and fayre harted frozen Knighte
died, (what said I) euen that which againe with grief
I must say died, whose ghost making speedy passage
into the ELISIAN fieldes (for what more swifte
then a soule) in the middest of the infernall multitude,
with s
                     •
                  re
                     •
                  ches, cryes and clamers, made both
Heauen and hell to redouble this Eccho,By the Sun is meant her Maiestie, called before the Fortres of Beavvtie. O times,
O men, O cu
                     ••
                  uption of manners, the Sunne is
besieged, the Sunne (O mischiefe) the Sunne is
besieged which strange and vnacquainted tea
                     ••
                  es,
caused not onely murmuring amongest the Ghosts
beneathe, but amusing among the Gods aboue,
who aswell to represse the tumultes whiche might
haue risen among the shaddowes, as to reuenge
the pride which began to growe on the earth, sente
downe an Angell with this commaundemente,Sir Thomas Parrat and M. Cooke vvere both 
                        •
                     n like ar
                     
                        •
                     our beset, vvith apples and fruite, he one sig
                     
                        •
                     ifiyng Adā, 
                        〈◊〉
                      the other 
                        •
                     ue, vvho 
                        •
                     ad haire 
                        •
                     ung all 
                        •
                     ovvn his 
                        •
                     elmet.
Goe discende, and cause ADAM and EVE to appeare
on the earth in that sort as they were in Paradise,
that the world may know them and wonder at
them, 
                     •
                  or seeing out of their loines haue issued those
preposterous lymmes, I know none more fit to correct
them! Certes none more willing: They will attempte
any thing for thy sake and seruice of that
earthly, and yet (O straunge consceite) moste heauēly
Sunne, for as they were before driuen frō their
DESIRE, because they desired to knowe the best,
so now shall they be driuen to their DESIRE whiche
they couet to honour most, This shall be their
rewarde, they shall come neeere and yet shall not
searche, and bee they farre of, it shall warme, A
cloud may sometimes barre their sight, but nothing

shall depriue them the sauegarde, yet commaunde
them to be humble in affection, thoughe 
                     •••
                  uente,
leaste they seeme to disdayne that pride 
                     〈◊〉
                  ,
whiche they desire themselues,The Angell speaketh to the Queene The 
                     〈◊〉
                   
                  
                     •
                  he
higheste, delighteth in the shaddowe whiche 
                     〈◊〉
                  
shortest, and nourisheth the tree whose roote grow
                  
                     •
                  th
deepest, not whose toppe springeth loftiest. This
commission and counsell ended all thinges were in
a moment accompli
                     ••
                  ed with suche seleritie (for to
the Gods time is tied) that they were sped as soone
as they were spoken, And now most renoumed and
deuine Sunne, Adam &amp; Eue being present, vouchsafe
to heare somwhat in their behalfs pronounced,
Sir Knights, if in besieging the sunne ye vnderstood
what you had vndertaken, ye would not destroye a
common blessing for a priuate benefite: VVill you
subdue the sunne,He speaketh to the challengers in the behalfe of the tvvo knights, Adam &amp; Eue. who shal rest in the shadow where
the weary take breath, the disquiet rest, and all comforte,
wil ye bereaue all men of those gl
                     •
                  stering and
gladsome beames, what shall then prosper in the
shining, but you will limbe it by the rayes. O rare
exhalations, brothers you may bee to DESIRE,
but sonnes ye are to ill hap, whiche thinkes you can
not sincke deepe enoughe into the sea, vnlesse you
take your sal from the sunne, Desist you knights, desist,
sithe it is impossible to resist, content your se
                     ••
                  es
with the sunnes indifferent succour, suffer the Ieniper
shrub to growe by the loftie Oake, and claime
no prerog
                     •
                  tiue where the sunne grauntes no priuiledge,
for being of the same mettall that others are,
the sunne wil work the like effects, as she doth 
                     〈◊〉
                   others,
The Giants wold haue ben gods, if they could
haue scaled the heauens &amp; you no lesse then star
                     •
                  es,
could you cōquer the same But as their throwing hil
vpō hil did manifest their pride, but nothing further

their pretence, So your laying challenge vpō claim,
&amp; conquest vpon challeng, may wel proue a wil but
no worthinesse, A desire to reach, but no possibility
to recouer, In which your soaring attemptes if you
chāce to fal, the only cōfort you haue, is to cry with
PHAETOn MAGNIS EXCIDIMVS AVSIS: But if no
perswasions may moue your minds: Know ye proud
Knights, there are that haue hearts as big as mountaines,
and as far aboue you in provvesse, as ye are
aboue all in presumption, yet not so vaine (vvhiche
ye terme valiant) to assault the sunne, and vvhy, because
it is impregnible, vvee content to enioy the
light, ye to ecclipse it, vve to rest vnder the feete, ye
to run ouer the head, we to yeeld to that vvhich nothing
can conquer, you to conquer that vvhich maketh
all men Captiues. But vveare it possible, that
head could deuise, courage attempt, or hand execute
any thing that might shevv the depth of our vnspot
ted Loialty, soone should be seene (and for your selues
to soone) that your enterprises should bee of as
small account then, as novv they are of lightlihood,
to deepe an impressi
                     •
                  n is engrauen in our thoughts,
for the maiestie of that sunne vvhich novv pearcing
our eyes hath fully subdued our hearts, that vve are
prest in her defence to offer the vvhole vvorld defiance,
In proofe vvhereof I am charged to throvve
dovvne his Gauntler, vvhich vvho so dareth take vp,
shall feele both the heate of their iuste conceiued
quarrell, and the reproch of their ovvn deserued folly,
not my riding in breaking a fevve staues to ende
the strife, but at Tournie or vvhat else so euer they
can deuise or dare aduenture for to vvin the benefite
of BEAVTIE, Thus moste renoumed and deuine
BEAVTIE, vvhose beames shine like the Sun, haue
ADAM and EVE aduentured to defend the Sunne,

the same I call Beautie the lighte of the vvorlde, the
maruel of men, the mirour of nature, on vvhich their
encounter, if those fauourable gleams may fall, they
vvil not onely thinke to haue done good herein, but
to be restored ag
                     •
                  ine to Paradi
                     •
                  e, the one meaneth
to repose his trust in a vvoman, vvho like Eve cannot
be beguiled, t
                     •
                  e other to rest on a Saint, vvhich
by a Serpent vvill not be tempted, Thus being placed
in the Garden of your Graces, O of all thinges
moste gratious vvhere vertues grovve as thicke
as leaues did in Paradise. They vvill take heedeto
taste of the forbidden fruite, contented to beholde,
not coueting to take holde, And for that it hath bin
long argued, 
                     •
                  nd no arguing can end? vvhether the
first offence came by the crudelitie of ADAM, or the
simplicitie of Eve, the one defending his faulte by
sounde arguments, the other excusing hers by sharp
ansvveres, they most humbly s
                     •
                  e for this, that either
by Six courses betvvene them the quarrell may bee
ended, or by your highnes peremptory sentence determined,
for they both being in the vvorld are desirous
that one might beare the blame of both, And
vvhat herein your excellencie shall set downe, there
is none shall gainsay, For whensoeuer the question
shall be moued, No other reason shall bee allovved
then this.
               Elizabetha dixit.
               This speech being thus ended, Sir Thomas
Parat, and M. Cooke proceded backward
on the other side of the Tilte, And
when M. Ratcliffe came likewise against
the Q
                     ••
                  ene, one of his Pages pronounced

these speeches in his Masters behalf
to her Maiestie.
               So manie vvere the misfortunes, (most renoumed
and beavvtifull Princesse) of the desolate knight my
master,M. Ratcliffes speech to the Queene as neither the shortnes of the time vvil suffer
me to repeat, nor the greatnes af the misterie to
remember? But let this su
                     ••
                  ise that some there vvere
and so manifold, that Geometrie vvhere on the body
of man hangeth coulde not beare being intollerable,
not the minde vvhich consisteth in Arithmeticke,
number being infinite. Thus alvvayes crossed
by fortune, vvhose crossing is no blessing, he determined
to seperate him selfe as farre from societie, as
his actions vvere from successe, vvho vvandering
through many desertes, yet finding as he thought no
place desolate, happened at the last to come to a
Cliffe adioyning to the maine Sea, couered all vvith
moste vvhereon he vvas vvalking, much delighted
vvith the sol
                     ••
                  arie seate, but not vvell liking the cold
scituation, he suddenly sunke into a hollovv vaulte,
surprised at the first vvith feare, but seeing it at the
last a place of succour, he accounted his former miseries
mee
                     •
                  ly appeased by this present fortune. In
this Denne he vsed for his bed mosse, for his candle
mosse, for his ceeling mosse, and vnlesse novve and
then a fevve coales, mosse for his meate. A dry food
God vvot and a fresh, but so moistened vvith vvette
t
                     •
                  ares, and so salt, that hard it vvas to coniecture,
vvhether it vvere better to feede or to fast. Here he
gaue himselfe to continuall meditation, seperating
his mind frō his body, his thought from his hart, yea
deuorcing him self frō himself, in so much that with

his strange diet &amp; nevv conceites, he became so enchaunted,
that neither the remembrance of others,
nor a thought touching himselfe coulde enter into
his minde: An alteration seldome heard of, that the
place vvhere
                     •
                  s he vv
                     •
                  s shrovvded in, shoulde make
him to forget vvho he is? Liuing thus a long time
for that no limme should seeme short, rising according
to 
                     ••
                  s maner to vvalke in the mosse in the grisping
of the day hee espied vpon the shore certaine
men either cast avvay by shipvvrake, or cast ouerborde
by Pyrattes, vnto vvhome he vvent and perc
                     •••
                  ing
by their pl
                     •
                  ints one vvhich lay dead amōgst
thē to be their master, enquired vvhence they vvere,
but they not vvilling to repeate their misfortunes,
opened the bosome of the gentleman, and pulled
out as crovvle containing a claime, a challenge, nay
a conquest of BEAVVTIE. At the sight vvherof, suddenly
(quoth he) Beavvtie, and therevvithall apalled
paused, entring by litle and litle out of his present
M
                     •
                  LANCHOLI
                     •
                  S into his former misfortunes, who as
one avvaked out of a long dreame, beganne thus to
debate. O Beavvtie vvhere thy Fortresse is sounded
I knovv, but what these brethren should mean
I mar
                     •
                  ile, for as I am assured that to vvinne thee
none coulde be so fortunate, so did I 
                     〈◊〉
                   that to
claime thee none coulde be so fonde, vvhen as
thou O deuine BEAVVTIE art of euery one to be desired,
but neuer to be conquered of DESIRE. But as the
Eagle beholding the sunne, cou
                     •
                  teth to builde her

                     •
                  est in the same, and so dimmeth her sight. So they
vevving the brighnesse of BEAVVTIE are incensed
to conquer it by DESIRE. And vvhat then? because
she is inuincible shall I be indifferent. No, I vvill
forsake this caytifly Cottage, and vvill take Armes

to defende that BEAVVTIES CASTLE. Nothing shall
remoue me from mine attempt, which being perfourmed,
nothing can mooue me, yea but shee hath
seruantes alreadie a number, I but vnlesse I be there,
not the vvhole number, but many vvere famous but
none more faithfull, yet alasse, if thou go, thou shalt
euer be infortunate, better alvvaies infortunat, then
one disloyal, vvhich vvords being ended, he demāded
vvhether they vvoulde in like case aduenture vvith
one of no lesse courage then their master, but certainly
of greater affection: VVhose seruice he hauing
vpon small entreatie obteined, for that belyke
they were desirous to see the euent for the vvhich
they had suffe
                     •
                  ed such aduentures, hee departed to
his caue, hevving a shield out of the hard cliffe enriched
onely vvith soft mosse: A double signe of his
desire, thinking that nothing could manifest BEAVVTIE
so well as PITHAGORAS wallunt, a tender 
                     •
                  yne
and a hard shell. And novve most excellent and deuine
BEAVVTIE, deuine it must needes be that vvorketh
so heauenly,Here the boy deliuered M. Ratclifs shild to the Queene sith he is called from his solitarie
Caue to your sumptuous Court, from bondage to
liberty, from a liuing death to a neuer dying life, and
all for the sake and seruice of BEAVVTIE: Vouchsafe
his shielde vvhich is the ensigne of your same to be
the instrument of his fortune. And for prostrating
himselfe to your feete, he is here readie prest to aduenture
any aduentures for your gracious fa
                     •••
                  r.
               Which speeche beeing ended,Here entreth the iiij. sons of S. Francis Knovvles. he retyred
back as the rest. And af
                     •
                  er him came the
foure Sonnes of Sir Frauncis Knowles,
on after another, according to their age,

and all in like armour, who comming to
the end of the Tilt, stayed till these speeches
were vttred by one of their Pages,
who being apparailed like vnto Mercurie,
pronounced these speeches in the
Knights behalues to her Maiestie.
               Report hath bruted all abroad,The speech of the foure sonnes of sir Frauncis Knovvles, pronounced by their page being apparelled like vnto Mercurie. that desperate DESIRE
vvith a vvonderfull armie of affections hath
laid his siege against the inu
                     •
                  ncible FORTRESSE OF
PEEERELESSE BEAVVTIE, and that the chiefest champions
of this most famous enterprise, are foure of

                     ••
                  incies fellovves, Fosterbrothers to DESIRE, and drie
nurst by dispaire, valiant Knights, and honourable
personages, vvhose hautie hearts deserue renovvne
at least, for venturing to vvin the goldē fleece vvithout
MEDEAS helpe. The Gyaunts long agoe did scale
the cloudes men say, in hope to vvinne the fort of
IVPITER. The vvantō youth, vvhose vaxed vvings
did ftie vvith soaring vp aloft, had scapt vnscorcht
if he had kept a meaner gale belovv. So falles it ou
                     •
                  
in this attempt, DESIRE vaunts to conquer BEAVVTIES
FORTE by force, vvherin the goddesse keepes
continually vvatch and vvarde, so that DESIRE may
dispaire to vvin one ynche of her against her vvill.
Her stately seate is set so high, as that no leuell can
be laid against her vvalles, and sooner may men vndertake
to hit a starre vvith a stone, then to beate her
braue bulvvarkes by batterie. No vndermining may
pre
                     •
                  aile, for that her forte is founded vpon so firme
a Rocke, as vvill not stirre for either fraude or force:
And is there any hope to vvinne by famine such a
forte as yeeldes continuall foode to all her foes, and

though they feede not fat therevvith, yet must they
either feede thereon or fast, for BEAVVTIE is the only
baite vvhereon DESIRE bites, and loue the chiefe
restoritie that lady BEAVVTIE likes, so that she cā no
more be left vvithout meat, then men can liue vvith
out mindes: Of all affections that are, DESIRE is the
most vvorthie to vvoe, but least deserues to vvinne
BEAVVTIE, for in vvinning his sainct he looseth him
selfe, no soner hath desire vvhat he desireth, but that
he dieth presently: So that vvhen BEAVVTIE yeeldeth
once to desire, then can she neuer vaunt to bee
desired againe: VVherefore of force this principle
must stād it is conuenient for DESIRE euer to vvish,
nec
                     •
                  ssarie &amp; that he alvvaies vvant, O rare &amp; most
renovvmed BEAVVTIE, O goddes to be honored of
all, not to be equalled of any, become not novve a
prisoner, your FORTRESSE is inuincible, no doubt
DESIRE vvill content him selfe vvith a fauourable
parley, &amp; vvaight for grace by loyaltie not chalenge
it by lavvnce, although he make nere so braue, the
vvordle doth knovve, that Ladi
                     •
                   BEAVVTIE needes
no rescue to rayse this siege, for that she sits aboue
al reach, her heauenly looks aboue when she so listes
can dazell all mens eyes. But though she liste not vse
those meanes, yet it is meete that all her seruantes
come and shevve them selues deuout to do her vvil
                     •
                  
perchaunce her pleasure is to see the fortes tried of
these iiii. FOSTER friendes. O happie, tenne times
happy they vvhose happe shalbe vvith fauour of her
D
                     •••••
                  , to take in hand this braue attempt: In hope
wherof these iiii legitimate sonnes of Despaire, bre
thren to hard mishappe, suckled vvith sighes, and
svvathed vp in sorovv, vveaned in vvo, &amp; drie nurst
by DESIRE, long time fostered vvith fauourable

countenāce, &amp; fedde vvith svveet fancies, but novv
of late (alas) wholy giuē ouer to griefe &amp; is disgraced
by disdain, are come vvith readie hearts and hands,
to proue against these other 4. that DESIRE doth
not deserue one vvinke of good fauour from Ladie
BEAVTIES smiling eyes, for threatning to winne
her, forte by force? They dout not the victorie if only
they may find some litle shew from their Saint in
fauour of their enterprise. If Mercurie haue saide
amisse, blame those bright beames vvhich haue be
                  
                     •
                  eft
him of his wit, if well, v
                     •
                  uchsafe one becke to
bid him packe avvay.
               These speeches beeing ended, both they &amp;
the rest marched about the Tyl,
                     •
                  and so
going backe to the nether ende thereof
prepared themselues to run,The running of the Tilte. euery one
in his tourne, each defendant six courses
againste the former challangers, Who
perfourmed their partes so valiantly on
both sides, that their prowesse hath demerited
perpetuall memory, &amp; worthely
woone honoure both to them selues and
their natiue countrie. As Fame hath the
same reported.
               When this dayes sporte was thus accomplished,
the boy that vttered the defiances,
in these fewe speeches tooke his
goodnight of the Queene.
               
                  
In the tryall of this debatefull question (O your
selfe) then vvith vvhat can be saide more,the boy that vttered the defiance, in this speeche tooke his goodnighte of the Queene. you see
that seeing begins to faile. Might the ordinary truce
maker though no truce be treated, (if at least your
presence make it not lightsome to vvrappe all in her
blacke and mourning vveedes) perchaunce mourning
that since night first, vvas the noblest DESIRE,
haue bene subiect to vndeserued tormentes: And
therefore these knightes by thaucthoritie of darknesse
verie vndesirously are compelled to departe
from vvhence they came. (neuer part yet ere they
goe) Thus much they command me in their names
to confesse. That such excellencie they find in your
knights and in comparison of them, such vnablenes
in their selues. That if Desire did not banish dispaire
as a traytor out of his kingdome, it vvoulde haue already
vndermined their best grounded determination:
but no invvard nor outvvarde vvounde, no
vveakenesse, no vvearinesse, can daunt Desire, nor
take avvay the natural effects that follovve it. T
                     •
                  erfore
hauing left them no other courage then Desire,
no other strength then Desire, no other beginning
or ending cause but Desire. They vvill continue
this harde and hardie enterprise to morrovve, in
the meane time they can finde no place in their
heartes that doeth not vvish you as svveet rest, as
Psiche vvas conueyed vnto by the gentle Zephirus,
and if it be p
                     •
                  ssible by the same gueste visited. They
vvishe that vvhen your liddes looke vp, their Iuelles
they may preserue them, to see to morrovv a better
day thē this, &amp; yet not so singuler successe, s as you
may long, freely, &amp; ioifully enioy; your selfe, to the
delight of lookers, and vvonder of maikers: this said,
the Knightes in order as they came departed.
            
            
               
               The seconde dayes sport.
               The nexte dayes showe was done in this
order.Here entereth a most excelling, &amp; braue chariot, with rare curious, and costly vvork vvith the four challengers in it, vvhich chariot vvas very curiously shadovved vvith fine Lavvne. The four foster children of Desire,
entered in a braue Charriot, (very finely
and curiously decked) as men f
                     •
                  rewearied
&amp; half ouercome, The charriot
was made in suche sort as vpon the top
the 4 knights sate, wt a beautiful Lady,
representing Desire about them. Wherunto
their eyes were turned, in token
what they desired, In the Lu
                     •
                  ke of 
                     〈◊〉
                  
Charriot was conueied roome 
                     •
                  or a full
consort of Musicke, who plaied still very
doleful musicke as t
                     •
                  e Charriot moued,
the charriot was drawne by four horses
according to the foure knightes, which
horses were apparelled in White and
carnation silke, beeing the colloures of
Desire, and as it passed by the vpper end
of the Tylt, a Harrault of Armes was
sent before to vtter these speeches in the
knights behalfe to her Maiestie.
               No confidence in themselues,The firste speech the second day. O most vnmached
Princesse, before whome enuy dieth, wanting all
merenes of comparison to susteine it, And admiration
is expressed, finding the scope of it void of conceaueable

limits, Not any slight regarding the force
of your valliant knights, hath encoura
                     •
                  ed the Foster
children of Desire to make this day an inheritour of
yesterdayes action: 
                     •
                  ut the wing of Memorie alasse
the sworne enimie to the wofullmans qui
                     •
                  tnesse,
being constantly helde by the hande of perfection,
And neuer ceassing to blow the cole of some kindled
Desire, hath broughte their invvard fyer to blaze
forth this flame vnquench
                     •
                  ble by any mean
                     •
                  s 
                     〈◊〉
                  
by death the whole fewel be consumed, and ther
                     •
                  
                  fore
not able to maister it, they are violently bo
                     ••
                  e
vvhether desire dravves. Although they must con
                     •
                  es
(alas
                     ••
                  ) that yesterdayes braue onse
                     •
                   should come to
such a confession: That they are not greatly companied
vvith hope, the common supplie
                     •
                   to Desi
                     •
                  es
army. So as novve from summoning this Cast
                     •
                  l to
yeld, they are fallen lowly to beseech you to vouchsafe
your eyes out of that Impregnable Fortresse to
beholde vvhat vvill fal out betvvixt them and your
famous knights: vvherein though they bee so eu
                     ••
                  
                  pressed
vvith the others vallure that a
                     •
                  ready they
could vnnethe haue bene able to come 
                     〈◊〉
                  
                  ▪ if
the charriot of Desire had not carried them, yet vvill
they make this vvhole assemblie vvitnesses so fai
                     •
                  e
of their vvil, That sooner their souls shall leaue their
bodies then Desire shall leaue soules: In that on
                     •
                  lye
standes their strength that gaue them th
                     ••
                   fi
                     •
                  st courage,
and must be their last comfort. For vvhat resistance
is there vvhere not onely they are met with
fo
                     •
                  ren enemies, such as stately disdain, vvhich looks
from so high a Tower to pore Desire. That though
(in it selfe) it bee greate yet in her eies (so seated) it
seemes small or such on the other side as vnfortunat
dispair, vvhich makes the count
                     •
                  ie so barren vvhere

they lay their siege, that it woulde take avvay all the
foode of fancie: But euen ciuill warre yesterdaye
grew betwixt them and others, who beares the same
badge of Desire: that they do so, as thus bestead they
are brought to this fayer passe, to desire no more,
but that this death or ouerthrowe, may be seen
                     •
                   by
those eyes who are onely vnhappy, in that they can
neither finde fellowes nor see them selue
                     •
                  .
               Which speech being done, the defendants
came in, in such order as they came in
the day before, therefore I shal not need
to make a newe repetition of the same,
sith al hath bene touched already. Then
wente they to the Tourney, where they
did very Nobly,Tourneyes, and Barriers couragiously tried. as the shiuering of the
swordes might very well testefie, And
after that to the barriers, where they
lashed it out lustely, and fought couragiously,
as if the Greekes and Troians had
dealt their deadly dole, no partie was
spared, nor estate expected, but eache
knight indued to win the golden fleece,
that expected eyther fame or the fauoure
of his maistresse, whiche sporte
continued all the same daye, And towardes
the euening the sport being ended,
ther was a boy sent vp to the queen
being clothed in Ash colored garments

in t
                     •
                  ken of humble submission, wh
                     •
                  
hauing an Oliue brauch in his hande,
and falling down prostrate on his face,
and then kneeled vp, concluded this
noble exercise with these wordes to her
Maiestie,
               Most renoumed Princesse of Princesse,The last speeche to the Queene in wh
                     ••
                  
can nothing obtein victorie, but vertue, The Foster
children of Desire, (but heires onely to misfortune)

                     •
                  end me to deliuer in such wordes as sorrowe can
a
                     ••
                  orde their most humble hearted submission, they
acknovvledge this Fortresse to be reserued for the
eye of the whole vvorlde, farre listed vp, from the
compasse of their d
                     ••
                  tinie, They acknovvledge the
blindenes of their error, in that they did not knovv

                     〈◊〉
                   (hovv strong so e
                     •
                  er it be) vvithin it self to be
no stronger vvithout it selfe then it pleased the desired,
they acknowledge they haue degenerated frō
their Fosterer in making violence accompany Desire,
They acknovvledge that Desire receiued his
beginning and nourishment of this 
                     〈◊〉
                  , and
therefore to committe vngratefulnesse in b
                     •••
                  ing
Armes (though desirous Armesl) against it
                     •
                   They aclovvledge
Noble Desire should haue desired nothing
so much, as the flo
                     •
                  ishing of that For
                     ••
                  esse,
vvhich vvas to be esteemed according to it selfes

                     〈◊〉
                   They acknovvledge the least determination
of vertue (vvhich stands for guard of this Fortresse)
to be to strong for the strongest Desire, And therefore
they do acknovvledge them selues ouercome,
as to be 
                     〈◊〉
                   to this 
                     〈◊〉
                   for euer, which Tylt

they will beare in their foreheades, as their other

                     〈◊〉
                   i
                     •
                   engrauen in their hea
                     ••
                  s: For witnesse therof
they present this Oliue branch to your presence,
in token of your Triumphant peace, And of their
peaceable seruitude.
               VVhereby they present themselues as bondmen
by those bondes, vvhiche the losse of life, can onely
loose: Only from out of that vvhich was theirs they
craue thus much, to giue sōe token to those knights
vvhich may be iudged to hauedon best in each kind
of vveapon, or vvho by his deuise hath come in best
sort in this desirous strife, this being don, they being
now slaues (in whom much duetie requires) for fear
of offēce, dare say no further, but wish from the bottom
of their captiued hearts, That while this realm
is thus fortified and beautified: Desire may be your

                     〈…〉
                   aduersarie.
               Which speech being ended her maiestie
gaue them al praise and great thankes,
which they esteemed so well &amp; thought
themsel
                     •
                  es rewarded according to their
own wishing, And so they departed each

                     〈◊〉
                   in order, according to their first comming
i
                     •
                  .
            
         
         
            
            The Aucthors conclusion
to the Reader.
            THVS haue I (good Reader) according
to my s
                  •
               mple skill set forth this
singuler pastime that thou maiest▪ beeing
farre of? peraduenture knowe more, then
they that were present and eye beholders of
the same, which so 
                  •
               eere as I coulde either
gather or get, I haue for thy pleasure here
placed it, If any thing be wanting which is
not here mentioned, or ought awry and not
right reported, let this suffice, that my 
                  •
               il
was good to haue gotten all, and most vnwiling
to do ought amisse, yet s
                  •
               ch as it is if
thou well accept it, I shal thinke my paines
wel emploied for thy pleasure, and gratified
enough with that good will: Therefore
wishing thee to thinke no worse of my work,
then I thought the laber litle in working,
crauing but P
                     •
                  na verba for my well meaning.
I giue thee the friendly Farewell.
            
               Thine to command in all courteous
manner. HENRIE GOLDVVIL.
            
            
         
      
   

