
   
      
         
            The couragious Turke, or, Amurath the First A tragedie. Written by Thomas Goffe Master of Arts, and student of Christ-Church in Oxford, and acted by the students of the same house.
            Goffe, Thomas, 1591-1629.
         
         
            
               1632
            
         
         Approx. 127 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.
         
            Text Creation Partnership,
            Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :
            2003-05 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).
            A01836
            STC 11977
            ESTC S122361
            99857512
            99857512
            23262
            
               This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.
            
         
         
            Early English books online.
         
         
            (EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01836)
            Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23262)
            Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 958:19)
         
         
            
               
                  The couragious Turke, or, Amurath the First A tragedie. Written by Thomas Goffe Master of Arts, and student of Christ-Church in Oxford, and acted by the students of the same house.
                  Goffe, Thomas, 1591-1629.
               
               [64] p.   
               
                  Printed by B. Alsop, and T. Favvcet, for Richard Meighen,
                  London :
                  1632.
               
               
                  In verse.
                  Signatures: A²  B-H⁴ I² .
                  Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.
               
            
         
      
      
         
            Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      
         
         
            EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.
            EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).
            The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.
            Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.
            Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.
            Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.
            The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.
            Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).
            Keying and markup guidelines are available at the Text Creation Partnership web site.
         
         
            
            
         
      
      
         
            eng
         
         
            
               Bayezid --  I, --  Sultan of the Turks, ca. 1360-1403 --  Drama --  Early works to 1800.
            
         
      
      
         
            2002-12
            TCPAssigned for keying and markup
         
            2003-02
            Apex CoVantageKeyed and coded from ProQuest page images
         
            2003-03
            Olivia BottumSampled and proofread
         
            2003-03
            Olivia BottumText and markup reviewed and edited
         
            2003-04
            pfsBatch review (QC) and XML conversion
      
   
   
      
         
            
            
            THE COVRAGIOVS TVRKE, OR, AMVRATH the First.
            
               A Tragedie.
            
            
               Written by THOMAS GOFFE
Master of Arts, and Student of ChristChurch in OXFORD, and Acted by the Students of the same House.
            LONDON
            Printed by B. ALSOP, and T. FAVVCET, for RICHARD MEIGHEN.
            1632.
         
         
            
            
            TO THE NO LESSE HOnoured then Deserving, Sir WALTER TICHBORNE Knight.
            SIR,
            
               THis with another Tragedy intituled, 
                  
                     •…
                   heraging Turke, the issue of one mans braine; are now come forth together from the Presse, neerer allyed, even as Twins in this their second birth▪ They are full of Glory, Strength, and indeed full of what not; that beautifies? The more apt to b
                  •…
                soyled, opposed, and disgra▪ ced; the rather, because the Author ha's made Exit hence. The intent, and use of Dedication as I have observed, is to no

other end then that ignorance and spite, (sworne Enemies to ingenuity) should know vpon their dull or envious dislikes, whether to repayre 
                  •…
               nd receive reformation. The 
                  •…
               atherlesse fel
                  •…
               ow-Orphan to this work r
                  •…
               steth safe under the protection of your most noble Brother, my much honoured Friend, Sir Richard Tichborne Knight and Baronet; Now for these reasons, and that I might not make them strangers by remote fosterings, but especially standing to you (most worthy Sir) equally engaged, I this to you Present and Dedicate: Together tendring the Love and vnfained acknowledgements, of
            Your most embounden Servant
            RICHARD MEIGHEN.
         
         
            
            TO THE AVTHOR IN THAT Transcribing his Book, without his knowledge I was bound by promise to stand to his pleasure to keepe it orburne it.
            
               I Will not praise this Worke, 'twere labor lost,
               Rich Pearles best praise themselves, nor will I boast
               To be possest of more than Indians wealth,
               That were the way to loose't since I my selfe
               D
                     •…
                  strust my selfe in keeping it, and stand
               In feare of robbing by some envious hand:
               Rob'd of it said I? Alas that fate were just,
               Since I am found first theefe to you, who durst
               Vnbidden thus, Ransacke your pretious store;
               This magazine of wit, so choyce; nay more,
               Steale from the chariot of the glorious Sunne,
               This heavenly fire, what shall I say 'tis done;
               I doe confesse the inditement, pitty then
               Must be my surest Advocate 'mongst men.
               None can abate the rigor of the Law,
               But the Law-giver; but methoughts I saw,
               (Or hop'd I saw) some watry beames of Mercy,
               Breake glimpsing forth of your imperious ey
                     •…
                  
                  ▪
               
               O let me beg reprive, your pardon may
               By due observance come another day.
               Here low I tender'd backe to bid the doome,
               By promise bound to him, to him with whom▪
               
               I would not breake for all rich Tagus sands,
               Now he the Prisoner at your mercy stands.
            
            
               —Ergo ibit in igne
                     •…
                  
               
               Hoc opus, aeternum ruet &amp; tot bella, tot Enses;
               In Cineres dabit h
                     •…
                  r a nocens:—
            
         
         
            
            The Prologue.
            
               VV
                     •…
                  re not our present subject mix
                     •…
                   with seare,
               'Twould much aff
                     •…
                  ight us to see all y
                     •…
                  u heere.
               One would suffice us, or no Auditor.
               Each to hi
                     •…
                  selfe an amp
                     •…
                  e Theater,
               Let rude Pl
                     •…
                  bejans thinke so, b
                     •…
                  t we know
               All judgments here from the same Spring doe flow.
               All here have but one c
                     •…
                  nsure, all one brest▪
               
               All sonnes of the same Mother; but the rest
               We pre
                     •…
                  ccupate their Censure, and 
                     〈◊〉
                  ,
               What after may be said not to be well,
               As in most decent Garments you may see▪
               
               Some gracious Ornaments inweav
                     •…
                  d bee:
               Which serve for lit
                     •…
                  le use▪ but on some day
               Destin'd to please himselfe, the wearer may
               Without a blush put on, when his best friends
               Intend to visit him, so our hope intends
               The sacred Muses Progeny to greet,
               Which under our Roo
                     •…
                  e, now the t
                     •…
                  ird time meet,
               We will not ope the booke to you, and show
               A story word by word, as it doth goe,
               But give invention leave to undertake,
               Of it's owne straines, some ben
                     •…
                  fit to make:
               For though a Tragicke P
                     •…
                  n may be confin'd,
               Within a studies private Walles, the mind
               Must be unbounded, and with inventions steele,
               Strike fir
                     •…
                   from ali
                     •…
                  nt Flints —
               So free we are from set
                     •…
                  ing any price,
               On these our studied Vanities, that advice
               Almost d
                     •…
                  dain'd the whispers of those 
                     •…
                  ngues
               Which private fi
                     •…
                  t, though vented publike wrongs▪
               
               To the Patient Patient oft▪ We'il here begin
               To be alitle perempto
                     •…
                  y, oh that sinne
               Of wilfull indiscretion, 'tis no bayes
               To make us Garlands of our owne mouthes prai
                     •…
                  e,
               Which who aff
                     •…
                  ct, may they so Lawrell lacke,
               That slanders Thunder may behi
                     •…
                  d their back
                     •…
                  
                  ▪
               
               Blast them with C
                     •…
                  lumny, for we vow th
                     •…
                  y deare
               Pay for their paines, that give attention here.
               And since it's suffered with kind indulgence
               We hope that Kingly Parent's our d
                     •…
                  fence,
               Who would not have his d
                     •…
                  dling love be knowne,
               But unto tho
                     •…
                  e had off spring of 
                     〈◊〉
                   owne,
               And for we are assured that here be
               No br
                     •…
                  ines so curst with blacke sterilitie.
               But of 
                     〈◊〉
                   nature they can freely call,
               Bi
                     •…
                  ths more mature, and Caelestiall,
               Their stud
                     •…
                  es 
                     •…
                  ssue, they like kindest Mothers,
               With tend
                     •…
                  r hands will swath the limb
                     •…
                   of others.
            
         
         
            
            THE ARGVMENT.
            
               
                  A Suppos'd Victory by AMVRATH
               
               Obtain'd in Greece, where many captives ta
                     •…
                  e,
               One among the rest, IRENE, conquers him;
               For taken with her love, he sounds retreat.
               Eternally from Warre: but after, mov'
                     •…
                  
               
               With murmur of his Nobles, in her Bed
               Before his Councels face, strikes off her head.
               Then ruinating former bloudy br
                     •…
                  yles,
               He straight ore' comes all Christian Provinces,
               Invades the Confines of his Sonne in Law,
               Fires Caramania, and makes Aladin
               
               With's Wife and Children suppliant for their lives;
               At length appointed his greatest Field to fight,
               Vpon Cassanae's Plaines, where having got
               A wondrous Conquest 'gainst the Christians,
               Comes the next morne to overview the dead,
               'M
                     •…
                  ngst whom a Christian Captaine Cobelitz,
               
               Lying wounded there, at sight of Amurath,
               
               Rising and staggering towards him, desperately
               With a short dagger wounds him to the heart,
               And then immediately the Christian dyes.
               The Turke expiring, Bajazet his Heyre
               Strangles his younger brother: Thus still springs
               The Tr
                     •…
                  gick sport which F
                     •…
                  rtune makes with Kings.
            
         
         
            
            The Actors.
            
               AMVRATH.
               LALA SCHAHIN.—Tutor to Amurath.
               
               EVRENOSES, CHASE ILLIBEGGE. two Turkish Captaines.
               
               COBELITZ.—a Christian Captaine.
               
               LAZARVS the Despot or Governour of Servia.
               
               SASMENOS—Governour of Bulgaria.
               
               ALADIN—Sonne in Law to Amurath: and King of Caramania.
               
               Two Lords with ALADIN.
               Two Embassadors.
               BAIAZET,—Eldest Sonne to Amurath.
               
               IACYL,—Youngest Sonne to Amurath.
               
               CAR
                     •…
                  ADIN BASSA.—A Governor under the Turke.
            
            
               For the Maske.
               Iupiter.
               Iune.
               Mars.
               Venus.
               Apollo.
               Pallas.
               Neptune.
               Cupid.
               Hector.
               Achil.
               Alex.
               Phil.
            
            
               Women Actors.
               EV
                     •…
                  ORPHE,—Concubine to Amurath.
               
               MENTHE.—An attendant on Eumorphe.
               
               HATYN,—Daughter to the Lord of Phrygia, married to Baiazet.
               
               ALDINES Wife.—Two little Boyes with her.
            
            
               Mutes.
               Men Christians taken, given to Amurath for Ianizaries.
               
               Sixe Christian Maidens presented to Hatun supposed to be Kings Daughters.
            
         
      
      
         
            
            THE COVRAGIOVS TVRKF, OR, AMVRATH the first.
            
               Actus, I.
               
                  Scaena, I.
                  Enter asfrom Warre, Lala-Schahin at one doore, with 
                        〈◊〉
                      Musicke, Souldiers, a March. Enter to him at 
                        〈◊〉
                      
                     
                        •…
                     
                     ther doore, Amurath in State, with Eumorphe his Concubine, attendan
                        •…
                     s 
                        •…
                     . and L
                        •…
                     .
                  
                     Amurath.
                     
                        
                           BE dumb those now harsh notes, our 
                              〈◊◊〉
                           
                        
                        Shall never be acquainted with such 
                              〈◊〉
                           ,
                        Peace (our grand) Captai
                              •…
                           , se
                              •…
                            h
                              •…
                            
                           
                              〈◊〉
                           ,
                        That would have once confronted 
                              
                                 〈◊〉
                              
                            hi
                              •…
                           
                           selfe,
                        (Acknowledged for a better Deity)
                        Puts off ambitious burdens, and doth ha
                              •…
                           e
                        Through bloudy Rivers to make passages,
                        Whereby his Soule might flote to A
                                 •…
                              heron,
                        
                        Wrin
                              •…
                           kle your browes no more (sterne fates) for we
                        Scorne to be made the servi
                              •…
                           e Ministers
                        To cut those threads, at which your selves have trembled▪
                        
                        
                           
                              •…
                           ming us the fiercer Destiny.
                        
                           Yet m
                              •…
                           st great Amurath thanke those sacred powers,
                        They have enricht our soules with such a price,
                        As ha
                              •…
                            those Heroes whose revengefull Armes,
                        S
                              •…
                           v'd Mars a ten yeares Prentiship at Troy,
                        
                        
                           
                              •…
                           re d
                              •…
                           eam'd succeeding times should b
                              •…
                            possest,
                        With such an unparalel'd unprized beauty as my Saint:
                        They would not have prevented so their blisse,
                        But beene most humble Sutors to the Gods,
                        To have protra
                              •…
                           ted their then fond spent life,
                        But to behold this object. Which out-shines
                        Their 
                              
                                 〈◊〉
                              . as much as doth the eye
                        O
                              •…
                            all the World, dazle the lesser fires.
                        
                           
                              
                                 •…
                              ove Ile outbrave thee! melt thy selfe in Lust
                        Embrace at once a
                              •…
                           l starre-made Concubines,
                        Ile not envie thee, know I have to spare
                        Beauty enough, to make another Uenus;
                        
                        And for fond Gods, that have no reward in store
                        To make me happier, here Ile place my Heaven.
                        And for thy sake, this shall my Motto be,
                        I conquered Greece, one Grecian conquered me.
                     
                  
                  
                     E
                           •…
                        m.
                     
                        But (gracious Lord) those streames (we see) soone ebbe,
                        Which with outragio
                              •…
                           s swelling flow to fast,
                        Forbid (
                              
                                 •…
                              ucina) this soone kindled fire,
                        Should ere burne out itselfe 'tis a true Theame,
                        That nere last
                              •…
                           long, that seemeth most extreame.
                     
                  
                  
                     Amur.
                     
                        Can this rich price of nature, precious jem
                        Give entertainment to suspecting guests?
                        Come, come, these armes are curious chaines of love,
                        With which thou link'st my heart aeternally,
                        Thy cheeks the royall Paper interlined,
                        With Natures Rhetorique, and love perswasion,
                        Stands there attracting still my gazing eye:
                        This then 
                              •…
                           le read, and here I now will faine,
                        That these all Antique fables of the Gods,
                        Are writ in flowing numbers; first thy lip,
                        Was faire Euro
                                 •…
                              aes which they say made Iove,
                        
                        Turne a wild Heyfer: next, this sparkling eye
                        Was the Aemonian Io's; then, this hand
                        
                           
                           Laedaes, faire Mother to those Stare made Twins,
                        Thus, thus, Ile Comment on this golden Booke:
                        Nature nor Art, have taught how to faine:
                        Fairest, 'twas you first brought me to this vaine:
                        In loving Combats now I valiant prove,
                        Let others warre, great 
                              
                                 •…
                              murath shall love.
                     
                  
                  
                     Scha.
                     
                        Brave resolution, O the fond thoughts of man,
                        Awake Enuo! Ile find stratagems:
                        There shall be Physick, to purge this disease,
                        Light sores are gently us'd, but such a part,
                        Must be cut off, least it infect the hart.
                     
                  
                  
                     Amar.
                     
                        
                           Schahi
                                 •…
                              , Our Tutor, we command this nigh
                              •…
                           
                        
                        Be solemniz'd with all delightfull sports,
                        Thy learn'd invention best can thinke upon.
                        Prepare a Maske, which lively represents,
                        How once the Gods did love: that shall not teach
                        Vs by examples, but we'll smile to thinke:
                        How poore and weake their idle faining was
                        To our affection. Scahin, be free in wit▪
                        
                        And suddaine: now come my Kingdomes Pride▪
                        
                        
                           Hymen would wed himselfe to such a Bride.
                     
                     Ex
                           •…
                        nnt all but Scah▪
                     
                  
               
               
                  Actus, Primi, Scaena, 2.
                  
                     Scah.
                     
                        Nature, and all those universed powers,
                        Which shew'd such Admirable Godlike skill,
                        Inframing this true modell of our selves,
                        This Man, this thing cal'd man, why doe you thus,
                        Make him a spectacle of such laughter for you,
                        When in each man we see a Monarchy?
                        For, as in states, all fortunes still attend:
                        So with a Kingdome, with a compleat state
                        Well govern'd, and well manag'd in himselfe,
                        Both each man beares, when that best part of man,
                        (Reason) doth swayand rule each Passion.
                        Affections are good Servants: but if will
                        Make them once Master, theyle prove Tyrants still.
                        No more King now: poore Subject AMVRATH,
                        Whom I have seene breake through a Troope of Men,
                        
                           Like lightning from a Cloud: and done those Act
                              •…
                           ,
                        Which 'ene the Furies would have trembled a
                              •…
                           :
                        Treading downe Armies, as if by them he meant
                        Of d
                              •…
                           ad mens backes to build up staires to Heaven:
                        A
                              •…
                           d now lyeth lurking in a womans armes
                        
                           
                              〈◊〉
                            in the Le
                              •…
                           he of Ignoble lust,
                        
                           
                              〈◊〉
                            its me for the wanton Enginere
                        
                           
                              •…
                           o ke
                              •…
                           pe his so loose thoughts in smoothing tune▪
                        
                        
                           
                              〈◊◊〉
                            woman: golden hooke
                        To 
                              〈◊◊〉
                            thoughts: and when we once are caught▪
                        
                        
                           
                              •…
                           o 
                              〈◊〉
                            i
                              •…
                           to the publike view of shame:
                        A
                              •…
                           d 
                              〈◊〉
                            we lye b
                              •…
                           thed in incestuous pleasure
                        
                           
                              〈◊〉
                            
                           
                              •…
                           od 
                              〈◊〉
                            to laugh and scorne at once.
                        
                           
                              〈◊〉
                            to 
                              〈◊〉
                            s
                              •…
                           ses! 
                              •…
                            could eyther wish
                        
                           
                              〈◊◊◊〉
                            like tho
                              •…
                           e Creatures, which we say
                        A
                              •…
                            
                           
                              〈◊〉
                            fr
                              •…
                           m Put
                              •…
                           id and corrupted matter;
                        
                           
                              〈◊◊〉
                            we should acknowledge our deare being
                        
                           
                              〈◊〉
                            grasse and flowers: for what else is our 
                              •…
                           tate?
                        V
                              •…
                            to the top but then the waight sh
                              •…
                           ll fall
                        Vpon t
                              •…
                           eir head that caus'd it. Worke (my braine)
                        Tush, bloud, not wat
                              •…
                           r must wash off this staine.
                     
                     Exi
                           •…
                        .
                  
               
               
                  Scaena, 3. Actus Primi.
                  E
                        •…
                     ter Amurath in state with Nob
                        •…
                      
                     Eumorphe with attendant Ladies: whi
                        •…
                      
                     Amu
                           •…
                        ath ascends 
                        •…
                     is Throne, and placeth Eumorphe by him.
                  
                     Am.
                     
                        Shine here (my 
                              〈◊〉
                           ) and expell the night
                        More than a thousand starres that grace the Heavens:
                        Me thinkes, I see the Gods inventing shapes
                        In which they meane to court thee. Iove he frownes
                        And is farre more jealous, more suspitious
                        Of thee, then all the painted Truls, whose eyes
                        Bedecke the all ennameld Firmament.
                     
                  
                  
                     Eum.
                     
                        Beauty (my Lord) 'tis the worst part of woman.
                        A weake poore thing, assaulted every houre
                        By creeping minutes of defacing time:
                        Asuperfici
                              •…
                            which each breath of care.
                        
                           Blasts off: and every hum
                              •…
                           rous 
                              〈◊〉
                            of gri
                              •…
                           e,
                        Which flowes from forth these Fountaines of our eyes▪
                        
                        Wash
                              •…
                           th away, as rain
                              •…
                            doth Winters snow.
                        But those bles
                              •…
                            guiders of all Nuptiall rites,
                        Have wrought a better sement to mak
                              •…
                            fa
                              •…
                           t,
                        The hearts of Lovers; the tr
                              •…
                           e name of Wife
                        Guilds o're our th
                              •…
                           ones, with a more constant shape▪
                        
                        Than can be subj
                              •…
                           ct or to time, or c
                              •…
                           re:
                        And in our selve
                              •…
                           ; yea in our owne tru
                              •…
                            brea
                              •…
                           ts▪
                        
                        We have 
                              〈◊〉
                           , d
                              •…
                           ty, carefull Love;
                        And last and 
                              〈◊〉
                            of all, we may have Children▪
                        
                        Children are Hym
                                 •…
                              ns pl
                              •…
                           dges, these shall be
                        Perpetuall chaines, to linke my Lord a
                              •…
                           d me.
                     
                  
                  
                     Amur.
                     
                        Art thou a W
                              •…
                           man? Godd
                              •…
                           sse, we ador
                              •…
                           
                           ▪
                        
                        And Idolize; what we but loved before;
                        What Divels have men 
                              〈◊〉
                           , whose furious brain
                              •…
                           
                        
                        Have oft abus'd that Deity cald Woman:
                        Dipping thir Ravens quill in Stygian Inke,
                        To blast such heavenly pap
                              •…
                           r as your faces.
                        Were all the enticing lusts, damn'd polici
                              •…
                           s,
                        Prodigious fas
                              •…
                           inations, u
                              •…
                           searcht thoughts,
                        Dissembled teares, brok
                              •…
                            vowes, loath'd app
                              •…
                           tites,
                        Luxurious 
                              •…
                           nd 
                              〈◊〉
                            desires.
                        Were all these of Women 
                              •…
                           qually weighed,
                        That vertue in thy brest, 'twill out-ballance all
                        And r
                              •…
                           compence th
                              •…
                            
                           
                              •…
                           uine of all thy Sexe.
                     
                     Enter a Serv
                           •…
                        t a
                           •…
                        d speakes.
                  
                  
                     S
                           •…
                        rv.
                     
                        So please 
                              •…
                           our Majesty, L. 
                              
                                 〈◊〉
                              
                            ready
                        For entrance with 
                              〈◊〉
                            M
                              •…
                           sque.
                     
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     
                        Tell him we're wholly 
                              •…
                           ent for 
                              •…
                           xpectation. Exit 
                                 •…
                              erv.
                        
                        Sit, sit (my Queene) Musi
                              •…
                           ke exceed your Spheares,
                        Thi
                              •…
                           ke I am I
                                 •…
                              ve, and Godlike please our eares.
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  Scaena, 4. Actus, 1.
                  A Masque. Enter from aloft two T
                        •…
                     rchbearers, then Iupiter and I
                           •…
                        no, and tw
                        •…
                      T
                        •…
                     rchbearers more, then Mars and Ue
                           •…
                        us, and two Torchbe
                        •…
                     
                     rers more, then Apollo and Pallas, and two 
                        •…
                     ore Torchbearers, the
                        •…
                      
                     Neptune and Diana. Whilst th
                        •…
                     y are discending, Cupid hanging in the Ayre, sings to soft Musicke this Song following.
                  
                     Cupid
                     sings.
                     
                        Gaze you mortals, gaze you still,
                        On the Gods now looke your fill.
                        
                           Iove and Iuno are discending,
                        Yet her lealousie's not ending,
                        
                           Mars, sterne Mars, he will not fight,
                        But with Venus when 'tis Night.
                        
                           Daphne crownes Apolloes head,
                        Whom she would embrace in Bed,
                        
                           Neptune swels his frothy cheeke,
                        Cause Diana is not meeke.
                        
                           Gaze you mortals, &amp;c.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Jup.
                     
                        Come now my (Sister and Wife) wee'l begin
                        To court afr
                              •…
                           sh! Nay, lour
                              •…
                            not (Heavens Queene)
                        Heere on this greene we'll a Lava
                              •…
                           to dan
                              •…
                           e,
                        What if our haires grow silver, yet our strength,
                        Is young, and vigorous! Say (fellow Gods)
                        (Since we are full of Nectar, and our cares,
                        Lye drencht in our Nepenth
                                 •…
                              
                           ) take your Queene
                              •…
                           , and be all
                        Ioviall, Mars for our Daughter Ve
                                 •…
                              s!
                        
                        
                           Apollo joyn
                              •…
                            with Pallas! Brother of Flouds
                        
                           
                              •…
                           mbrace Diana! Gods sometimes merry be:
                        But in the night, when mortals m
                              •…
                            not see.
                     
                     Each God as appointed by Iove, takes his Goddesse, they dance a Masque dance, and in the dance Jun
                           •…
                         observes loves gl
                           •…
                        nces t
                           •…
                         
                        Eumorphe, 
                        
                           •…
                        nd at the end of the dance, 
                           •…
                        peaketh thus.
                  
                  
                     J
                           •…
                        p.
                     
                        How now (wanton?) Can I no wh
                              •…
                           e goe,
                        
                           For recr
                              •…
                           ation but you f
                              •…
                           llow me?
                     
                  
                  
                     Jun.
                     
                        Is this your Recreation? Fye! My Lord
                        Will you be wanton still? For here you came Points at Eum
                                 •…
                              rphe▪
                           
                        
                        For some new Harlot, some new Queene for you.
                     
                  
                  
                     I
                           •…
                        p.
                     
                        Jun
                              •…
                           , Wife.
                  
                  
                     Iun
                           •…
                        .
                     
                        Your Sister, (thunderer,) and not your Wife!
                        Banisht from Heav
                              •…
                           n I am; and your Bed,
                        Resigne them both to Strumpets, Concubines, Points at E
                                 •…
                              morphe▪
                           
                        
                        And now you com
                              •…
                            to see a fresh new lasse
                        In which Pole now or in what part of h
                              •…
                           aven,
                        Shall she be stellified?
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           •…
                        pit.
                     
                        Shall still sinister thoughts wrong our intent,
                        Wel (I
                                 •…
                              o) wel, you'le ever be a woman,
                        A very, very woman! But 
                              •…
                           ince she scolds,
                        Let's hence (yee Gods) lest her infectious breath
                        Blast the s
                              •…
                           cceeding day: and mortals curse
                        Her hel-bred jeal
                              •…
                           usie: Calumnious woman
                        Come scold in heaven! For if Gods liv'd on Earth
                        S
                              •…
                           spitious tongues would blame most innocent mirth.
                     
                     Here all the Gods and Goddesses as
                           •…
                        end at the top of the ascent, Iu
                           •…
                        o 
                           •…
                        tops and speakes.
                  
                  
                     Iun.
                     
                        Wel! love lookt pale! I toucht him to the quicke!
                        'Tis some new Mini
                              •…
                           n he came downe to see!
                        Harke (jealousie) know Jun
                                 •…
                              
                            is a woman!
                        Am I not mad yet? Mistris Bride, adiew:
                        
                           Jove shal not steale a kisse? My curse is past,
                        When thou sleep'st first a Bride, may
                              •…
                           t sleepe thy last.
                     
                     Exit.
                  
                  
                     C
                           •…
                        pid.
                     
                        Faire Bride I sang thy 
                              
                                 •…
                              pithalamy,
                        
                        And left 
                              
                                 〈◊〉
                              
                            for thy Nuptials:
                        
                           Iuno here thundered gainst the Thunderer,
                        Knowing how thy beauty dazles hers,
                        She durst not let heavens King once glance a looke,
                        But threatned with her helbred incantations,
                        To metamorphise thine unparaleld
                        And most caelestiall shape into worse formes;
                        And more prodigiou
                              •…
                            than ever poysoned charmes.
                        Wrought on the fabled Concubines of love:
                        
                        
                           But kn
                              •…
                           w great Queene▪ my Mother Venus vowes
                        Her everlasting guard to save such beauty,
                        Lest if thou perish, Nature 
                              〈◊〉
                            selfe
                        Loose he
                              •…
                            o
                              •…
                           ely patterne of 
                              •…
                           erenity,
                        But I must ha
                              •…
                           t, Love which the Gods protect,
                        Can never 
                              〈◊◊〉
                            by neglect.
                     
                     Ascendit.
                  
                  
                     Amur.
                     
                        
                           
                              
                                 •…
                              cahin, thine Art is excellent; but say,
                        Doe Gods fall out for love amongst themselves?
                     
                  
                  
                     Scah.
                     
                        My Lord, these are but fables: yet to make
                        The shew more p
                              •…
                           rtinent, and to grace your Queene,
                        Co
                              •…
                           ceipt tooke leave to put the frowne on Iu
                                 •…
                              o.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈◊〉
                        .
                     
                        My Lords and friends, we shall be ever thankfull
                        And rest a Debtor to your curtesie.
                     
                  
                  
                     Schah.
                     
                        Not so faire Queen, but durst 
                              •…
                            now 
                              •…
                           ntreat
                        The Kings detaining from th
                              •…
                            sweets of Bed▪
                        
                        There yet remaines one thought upon conceipt,
                        Which you would doubly grace me to behold.
                     
                  
                  
                     Amur.
                     
                        Our worthy Tutor shall obtaine a Night,
                        A night ofus, in any case we can!
                     
                  
                  
                     Scah.
                     
                        But then let me informe your Majesty,
                        That 'tis a warrier
                              •…
                            shew, which once you loved,
                        But now are free from.
                     
                  
                  
                     Amur.
                     
                        'Tis best of all, with greedinesse we'l see it,
                        O how the soule doth gratulate it selfe
                        When saf
                              •…
                           ly it beholds the dangerous state
                        Of others, and it selfe securely free!
                        Glad are we still to stand upon the shore,
                        And see a farre off ot
                              •…
                           ers tost in the Sea,
                        Or in a Gallery at a Fencers stage,
                        We laugh when mutually each one takes wound
                              •…
                           ;
                        Sit still (
                              
                                 〈◊〉
                              ) Sc
                                 •…
                              hin, thy shew in hast;
                        'Tis best delight, to think
                              •…
                            on troubles past.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scaena, 5. Actus, 1.
                  Enter in 
                        〈◊◊〉
                      of Hect
                           •…
                        r and Achilles, to t
                        •…
                     em Alexander the great 
                        •…
                     ands gazing on them, whilst Fame 
                     
                        〈◊〉
                      from 
                        〈◊〉
                     .
                  
                     
                        
                           〈◊〉
                        .
                     
                        Stay you most worthy fhades▪ brave Hector stay▪
                        
                        And proud Achilles, know your massi
                              •…
                            Tombes,
                        
                           Which have so long orewhelm'd your valiant bones
                        Yawnes wide to let the imprisoned coarses forth.
                        I must afresh imbalme your sacred Trunkes,
                        And swe
                              •…
                           t your memory with most happy oyle,
                        Of just report, the Gods awakt me Fame
                        From out the oblivious Sepulch
                              •…
                           r of sleepe,
                        To drop that Inke into old Homer
                                 •…
                              
                            pen,
                        Werewith he curiously hath lin'd your names,
                        Enfolding them in Everlasting Cedar,
                        And made them live to all posterity.
                        Vertue to valour hath his guift assign'd▪
                        
                        Great men may dye, yet deeds still rest in mind.
                     
                     
                        
                           〈◊〉
                         vmbrae Hector
                           •…
                        s &amp; Achillis, Manet Alexander looking after them, reading i
                           •…
                         
                        Homer.
                     
                  
                  
                     Alexand.
                     
                        
                           
                              〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                           
                        
                        Most fortunate young man, whose worth is crown'd
                        With everlasting Trophies of renowne,
                        How hath he set thee on the wings of Fame
                        Which soare i'th middle region of high glory
                        Propos'd to all, a never dying story.
                     
                     
                        Enter to Alexander, Philoicen
                              •…
                           s a Capt
                              •…
                           ine.
                     
                  
                  
                     Phil.
                     
                        May it please the (Sonne of Iupiter) to accept
                        A Present, which our fight enricht us with?
                     
                  
                  
                     Alex.
                     Is it a Band of stubborn Souldi
                           •…
                        rs Captaine?
                  
                  
                     Phil
                           •…
                        x.
                     
                        O no (my Lieg
                              •…
                           ) of exquisite form'd Ladies▪
                        
                        
                           Darius his wife, the wonder of her Sexe,
                        Besides a Troope of such shapt Ganim
                                 •…
                              des,
                        
                        That love 
                           
                              •…
                           ot equals.
                     
                  
                  
                     Alex.
                     
                        
                           Philoxenus▪
                            We thanke thee! Yet harke!
                        There is a secr
                              •…
                           t we would know of thee,
                        And you must tell Vs: on your faith you must.
                     
                  
                  
                     Phil.
                     My L
                           •…
                        ige —
                  
                  
                     Alex.
                     
                        Nay, no Court oyle (by your leave) no flattery▪
                        
                        We are but man, this very trun
                              •…
                           ke of ours,
                        Is but a Vessell fild with human
                              •…
                            bloo
                              •…
                           
                        
                        And we trust not that Parasite like 
                              〈◊〉
                           
                           ▪
                        
                        
                           I 
                              〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉
                           .
                        All the destroying vices of fraile man,
                        I may be subject to, but what base loosenesse,
                        Or supple Luxury, didst thou ere obscure
                        So to benumne our sence, that thou shouldst thinke
                        We could be pleas'd with such effaeminate Presents,
                        * Know sir our eyes shall have that abstinence
                              
                                 •…
                              er 
                                 〈◊◊〉
                              
                           
                        
                        That will not looke on them, on boyes, of women, Exit Phi
                              
                                 •…
                              .
                        
                        Hence then, and present some coward with them,
                        Give me a spectacle would please the Gods,
                        And make them bend their Ivorie browes to the Earth,
                        A man, a Souldier, 
                              •…
                           trong with his wounds,
                        'Mongst fate and ruine, upright and unshap't,
                        His minde 
                              •…
                           eing all his guard, his wall, and armour,
                        And if he fall, 
                              •…
                           till noble wrath remaines,
                        In his amased Trunke: not 
                              •…
                           ll the darts
                        Stucke in his sides, making him a
                              •…
                            one wound,
                        A
                              •…
                           right his courage, but wrath lending weapons,
                        Himselfe doth seeme a new and horrid Warre,
                        Nor are those Milke-sops which beguile the time,
                        With 
                              •…
                           tealing minutes from their Ladies lips
                        Such as the Gods doe love; foras the Winde
                        Looseth it's force, if it be not oppos'd
                        With woods of strong and stubborne planted trees▪
                        
                        So vertue, if it wa
                              •…
                           ke in troden paths
                        That breakes up honours gap, and makes the way
                        Through pathes of death, that flame burnes strong
                        Which is resisted: valor 
                              •…
                           hines in wrong:
                        Of Alexanders Souldiers be this sed,
                        Warre was a
                              •…
                            peace, when he the army led.
                     
                     Exit.
                  
                  
                     Fame.
                     
                        Brave Macedon, how truly hast thou weighed,
                        The reason of mans birth, who is equall borne,
                        For all the world, as well as for himselfe.
                        The world's a field t
                              •…
                           o narrow for thy worth!
                        And although Nature, hath her enacted bounds
                        For Sea and Earth, nay for the Heavens themselves,
                        Nor Sea nor Earth, shall coope thy valour up:
                        
                           Valour of Nature ever this attaines
                        That it breakes forth, farre, and beyond her chaines,
                        And this Ile trumpet out. the whole worlds Ball
                        In which thou art so great, to thee is small;
                        When men want worlds to 
                              •…
                           hew their vertue in,
                        That is the crime o'th 
                              •…
                           ods, and not their sinnes:
                        * 'Tis a decree of a true Soul
                              •…
                           iers mind,Lu
                                 •…
                              an de 
                                 •…
                              il crede▪ cum qu
                                 •…
                              a 
                                 •…
                              sset age
                                 •…
                              
                           
                        
                        To thinke nought done, when ought is left behind,
                        On (valiant youth) for, know I will appoint;
                        A Grecian Prince who so shall steepe his quill
                        To paint out thy name in W
                              •…
                           ls of eloquence,
                        That this thy soorne of Lust shall be
                        Propos'd to all Kings example to posterity,
                        Know mortals that the men the Gods most love
                        In hard and da
                              •…
                           gerous Arts, they alwayes prove,
                        When men live brave at first, then fall to crimes,
                        Their bad I Chronicle to future times:
                        For, who begins good Arts, and not proceeds
                        He but goeth backward in all noble deeds.
                        Death consecrates those men whose awfull end,
                        Though most men feare, yet all men must commend.
                     
                     ascends. Amurath s
                           •…
                        emes tr
                           •…
                        bled yet collecting himselfe, dissembles his Passion, speakes.
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     
                        
                           Scahin, the Macedo
                                 •…
                              s beholding to the
                              •…
                           ,
                        And history shall pay you thankes for this▪
                        
                        Which we rest Debtors for.
                     
                  
                  
                     Scah.
                     
                        Great Prince, such kindnesse of acc
                              •…
                           ptance payes:
                        For things which are but for a Kings delight,
                        In 
                              •…
                           eeing them, he amply doth requite.
                     
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     
                        
                           Eumorphe, Love, Queene, Wife, let's haste to Bed!
                        And may we wish this night aeternall time,
                        
                           Scahin, good night: good night (kind Gentlemen!)
                        Thus when we are dead shall we revive oth stage:
                        One houre can present a Kings whole age.
                     
                     Exe
                           •…
                        nt o
                           •…
                        nes.
                  
               
            
            
               
               Actus, II.
               
                  Scaena, I.
                  
                     Enter Schahin, Eur
                           •…
                        noses.
                  
                  
                     Schah.
                     Observ'd you not the Kings looks? Grew th
                           •…
                         not pale?
                  
                  
                     Euren.
                     
                        O yes (Lord Scahin) you mu
                              •…
                           t be his Parent?
                        And snatch him out'h the Gulph he's falling in,
                        That fayned speech of Alexanders wrought
                        Like to most purging Physicke, nights then blacke
                        When 'tis compar'd with day: Boldnesse is cleare,
                        When 'tis presented before bastard feare.
                     
                  
                  
                     Schah.
                     
                        Ile tell thee (Eurenoses) thou art a Souldier:
                        And I am both a Souldier, and a Scholler,
                        And for these two Professions, am both most glorious:
                        And most meritorious, Pall
                                 •…
                              s is for both:
                        O what Tysiphon, what snaked scourge
                        Ca
                              •…
                            make a Scholler, that should never sleepe,
                        But 'twixt th
                              •…
                            Pillowes of Pernassus Hils,
                        And dip his lips in springs of Helicon,
                        
                        Make him by snoaring on a wanton breast,
                        And sucke the adulterate and spiced breath
                        Of a lewd fained woman?
                     
                  
                  
                     Euren.
                     
                        And for a Souldier (Scahin,) let me speake!
                        We that doe know the use of swords, and fire,
                        We that doe know, halters can throatle us,
                        Shall we ere venture on a Womans cruelty?
                        We that endur
                              •…
                            no Lords, shall we endure:
                        A woman to overcome us? Most true Demophoon!
                        
                        I reverence thy memory, no pewling phrase
                        Could so euchaine thee to thy Thraci
                                 •…
                              n Dame,
                        But thou wouldst r
                              •…
                           her perish than she save thee.
                        Ile not declaime long on that common Theam
                              •…
                           ,
                        But they have lust lyeth in their fingers ends,
                        And whilst their sweet-hearts breath stickes in their sheets,
                        
                           They will admit another. Lucrec
                                 •…
                              
                            in the day
                        To be a Thais, if the night will not gain-say.
                     
                  
                  
                     Scah.
                     
                        Why (Euren
                                 •…
                              ses) why should we endur
                              •…
                           
                        
                        A new Queen now? this Kingdom wants not heires?
                        We know (should we have more) 'twere dangerous,
                        But harke! The Queens for Bed, inticing sleepe soft Musicke▪
                           
                        
                        With charmes of Musicke: wel, even such a Night▪
                        
                        May yet prove dismall ere the following Light!
                     
                  
                  
                     Eure
                           •…
                        s.
                     
                        
                           Scahi
                                 •…
                              , let's in:
                        The first degree to purge such ils as these▪
                        
                        Is to instruct the patient his disease:
                        That you have done.
                     
                  
                  
                     Scah.
                     
                        Yea, and wil yet once more
                        Adventure a new stratagem, just when the King
                        H'as rid his Chamber, and with covetous hast
                        Thinks for to clip Elizium, and drinke deepe
                        Of his long wished delight, I having skil
                        And uncontroul'd acce
                              •…
                           se, will in disgu
                              •…
                           se
                        Seeme his deceased Fathers apparition:
                        And by all tyes of children to their Parents,
                        Bid him forsake that vile bewitching woman.
                     
                  
                  
                     Euren.
                     
                        An easie Medicine doth and sure wil work,
                        To rub shrewd wounds, make them but fester more,
                        Foule Medicines we worse brook, than a foule sore.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scaena 2. Actus 2.
                  Enter Eumorphe as to Bed in her Night-robes, 
                        •…
                     ttended with Tayers and Ladies.
                  
                     Menthe.
                     
                        Madam make hast 
                              •…
                            The King will be impatient
                        If h
                              •…
                            be from you long. O Happinesse.
                     
                  
                  
                     Eumorph.
                     
                        Why Menthe, then thou deem'st us happy no
                              •…
                           
                        
                        Thus to command a world of services,
                        To have a King my subject; and attended
                        With these harmonious sounds t'affect our eares?
                     
                  
                  
                     Menthe.
                     Yes (truly Madam) 'tis a happinesse.
                  
                  
                     Eumorph.
                     
                        'Tis, were't Eternal: but I feare a pow
                              •…
                           r
                        A womans power, doth but make 
                              •…
                           port with us;
                        
                           Why, were we not once Menthe, a Captive (Wretch?)
                     
                  
                  
                     Menthe.
                     
                        Yes Lady▪ now your happinesse the more:
                        Riches please best, when there w
                              •…
                           nt want before.
                     
                  
                  
                     E
                           •…
                        m.
                     
                        That power which rais'd us from so base, so high,
                        Can throw us downe againe as suddainly:
                        Me thi
                              •…
                           ks my life is but a Players Scaene,
                        In the last Act my part was then to play,
                        A Captive 
                              〈◊〉
                           , 
                              •…
                           nd a 
                              •…
                           ueene to day.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈◊〉
                        .
                     
                        Your Morals (Madam) are too serious▪
                        
                        Me thinks the
                              •…
                           e Ornaments should elevate
                        Your dumpish spi
                              •…
                           its. Thinke this Bed a place
                        In which no 
                              •…
                           cie slipping chance hath power;
                        A Ki
                              •…
                           gs safe Bed is like a guarded Tower.
                     
                  
                  
                     Eum.
                     
                        No (
                              
                                 •…
                              enthe) no, 'tis not the Bed of state,
                        Nor the free smile of a well pleased King:
                        'Tis not the embracing Armes of Emperors,
                        N
                              •…
                            all the Gemmes that so inwreath the browes
                        Can so allure Fortune unto their gaze,
                        As she should still be constant; O she's blind,
                        Nor doth she know her selfe where she is kind;
                        Close, those are Kings, and Queenes whose brest's secure
                        Like brazen walles, Lust's entrance not endure!
                        Where impotent ambition not intrudes,
                        Nor the unstable talke of multitudes;
                        Fo
                              •…
                           tune sernes such, they happinesse command
                        More than all 
                              
                                 〈◊〉
                              
                            gold, all Tagu
                                 •…
                              
                            sand;
                        As Heaven hath given us no more conspicuous thing
                        Than forme or beauty: so like a forward spring.
                        Nothing more short.
                     
                  
                  
                     Menth
                           •…
                        .
                     
                        Madam, divine 
                              〈◊〉
                            of a change; Beliefe
                        
                           
                              
                                 〈◊〉
                              : 
                                 〈◊〉
                               in 
                                 〈◊◊◊◊◊〉
                              
                            Is too too pro
                              •…
                           e, in entertaining griefe!
                     
                  
                  
                     Eum.
                     
                        Our Lord attends to enter in,
                        And surely sleepe envyeth his delig
                              •…
                           t,
                        For he sits heauy on my drowsie liddes,
                        Draw all our Curtai
                              •…
                           es; sleepe beguiles our ear
                              •…
                           s.
                     
                  
                  
                     Menthe.
                     (Madam) good night; time helpes suspitious feares!
                  
                  Exit Menthe.
                  
                  This Song is to be sung in the Musicke roome  Dreames to soft Musicke, now when , she lookes, she's dreaming 
                        〈…〉
                      sent to Elisium.
                  
                     
                        Drop golden showers, gentle sleepe,
                        And all the Angels of the Night,
                        Which doe us in protection keepe,
                        Make this Queene dreame of delight
                        
                           Morpheus be kind a little, and be
                        Deaths now true Image, for 'twill prove
                        To this poore Queene, that then thou art hee;
                        Her grave is made i'th Bed of love:
                        Thus with sweet sweets can Heaven mixe gall,
                        And marriage turne to Funerall.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scaena 3. Actus 2.
                  Enter Amurath in his Night rob
                        •…
                     s, 
                        •…
                      Taper in his hand, se
                        •…
                     mes much disturbed, spe
                        •…
                     kes.
                  
                     Amur.
                     
                        Turke, Amurath, slave nay something baser▪
                        
                        King! For all aery titles which the Gods
                        Have blasted man withall▪ to make them swell
                        With puft up honour, and ambitious wind,
                        This name of King holds greatest antipathy
                        With manly government▪ for if we waigh▪
                        
                        'Tis subjects, and not Kings beare all the sway.
                        Each whispered mur mur from their idle breath,
                        Condemnes a King to Infamy, to death;
                        Were there a Metempsucocosis of soules,
                        And nature should a free Election grant
                        What things they afterwards would reinforme
                        The vaine and haughti
                              •…
                           st minds the Sun ere saw,
                        Would chuse it's Cottage in some Shepheards flesh,
                        Nay, be confin'd within some Dog or Cat,
                        Than Antique like prancke in a Kings gay-clothes▪
                        
                        Were I no King, and had no Majesty,
                        I had more than all Kings, blest liberty;
                        And without rumor might enjoy my choyce,
                        Not f
                              •…
                           aring Censure of each popular vo
                              •…
                           ce;
                        Poore men may love, and none their wils correct:
                        
                           But all turne Satyres of a Kings affect!
                        O my base greatnesse! What disasterovs starre,
                        Profest it selfe a Midwife at my birth,
                        To shape me into such prodigious States,
                        But hence regard of tongues! Were we a Saint,
                        Some envious tongue would dare our names to taint:
                        And he from slander is at securest rest,
                        Not that hath none, but that regards it least.
                        Open you envious Curtaines here's a sight, Drawes the Curtain.
                        
                        That might commend the act of Love so Chast;
                        Were now the chariot-guider of the Sunne
                        Weary on's taske, and would intreat a day
                        Of Heauen to rest in, here's a radiant Looke,
                        That might be fixt ith' midst oth' Axletree;
                        And in despight of darke conspiring Clouds,
                        She would out-shine Sunne, Moone, and all the Stars,
                        O, I could court thee now (my sweet) a fresh,
                        Mixing a kis
                              •…
                           e with every period:
                        Telling the Lillies how they are but wanne,
                        Earth in the vernant spring is dull, and darke,
                        Compar'd with this aspect! the Aeasterne ayre,
                        Famed with the wings of Mercury and 
                              
                                 •…
                              ove,
                        
                        Infectious, but compar'd with this perfume!
                        Hence then th'ambition of that furious Al
                                 •…
                              x. youth,
                        Who knew not what a crime his rashnesse was!
                        I might orecome more Kingdomes; have more dominion
                        Enthrone my selfe an Emperor! oth' world,
                        I might! I might! Amurath thou mightst!
                        The Christians now will scoffe at Mahomet;
                        
                        Perchance they sent this wretch thus to inchant me!
                        O my perplexed thoughts! tush Ile to bed
                        Should the commanding Thunder of the Gods
                        Prohibite me, or strike me in the act!
                        Talke on (vaine rumor) fame I dare thy worst!
                        Call me a Lusty, Lazy, wanton, Coward!
                        Should I win all the world, my breath once fled,
                        My bad would still survive, all good be dead.
                        
                           Eum
                                 •…
                              rphe, sweet, I come! you sacred powers,
                        
                           Who have bestowed some happinesse on man,
                        To helpe to passe away this sinful 
                              •…
                           ife,
                        Grant me a youthfull vigor yet a while,
                        Full veines, free strength, compleat and manly fence
                        To know, and taste a beauty most immense!
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scaena 4. Actus 2.
                  
                     Amurath makes haste to the Bed, on a suddaine enter Schahin dis. guised like the Ghost of Orchan
                           •…
                        
                      father to Amurath.
                  
                  
                     Scahin.
                     Amurath, Amurath?
                  
                  
                     Amur.
                     
                        Divel, Divel? What?
                        Dar'st thou appeare before an Angell (Fiend?)
                     
                  
                  
                     Scah.
                     
                        O Amurath, why doth intemperate Lust
                        Raging within thy furious youthfull veines,
                        Burst through thy fathers Tombe? Disturbe his soule?
                        Know, all the torments that the fabulous age
                        Dream't, did afflict deceased impious Ghosts,
                        Hartbiting-hunger, and soule-searching thirst,
                        The nere consumed, yet ever eaten prey
                        That the devouring Vulture feeds upon,
                        Are not such tortures as our off-springs crimes!
                        They, they sit heavy on us, and no date
                        Makes our compassionate affection cease.
                        O thou hereditary Vlcer, hearke
                        By the name of Father, and by all those cares,
                        Which brought me to my grave, to make thee great▪
                        
                        Thou that hast nothing of me but my crowne:
                        My enterprise surpast the boundlesse Sea,
                        Cutting the churlish Waves of Hellespont,
                        
                        When the flood stood which wind for to obey!
                        
                           Euxinum groan'd beneath my burdenous Ships;
                        I was the first of all the Turkish Kings
                        That Europe knew, and the fond Christians plagu
                              •…
                           
                        
                        What coward blood ran flowing in my veines,
                        When thou wert first begot: who marrest all
                        Thy Fathers acts, by thy untam'd desires,
                        Wherefore with Stygian curses I will lade thee
                        First, may she prove a Strumpet to thy Bed
                        Be her lips poyson, and let her loose embrace,
                        
                           Be venemous as Sco
                              •…
                           pions! If 
                              •…
                           he conceiv'd,
                        A Generation from thee, let it be
                        As ominous as thou hast beene to me!
                        Rebellious to thy Praecepts, printing care
                              •…
                           ,
                        Vpon thy aged browes, O may they prove,
                        As Faeries for to lash thee in thy rest!
                        But Amurath, if thou canst quench this flame,
                        If thou wilt cut this Gordian thred, and rend hence,
                        That putrid Wenne which cleaves unto thy flesh,
                        Be all thine actions prosperous! Mahomet,
                        
                        Sha
                              •…
                           l be auspitious unto each designe;
                        Fortune to shew thee favour shall be proud,
                        Farewell! if that men doe speake last, before
                        They dye, take root, then dead mens should take more. Exit Scahin.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Amur.
                     
                        What art thou vanisht? Know (thou carefull spright)
                        Thou shalt no sooner pierce the wandring Clouds
                        With unperceived flight, than my resolue
                        Shall expiate my former Vanity!
                        Looke on thy sonne thou (aery intellect)
                        And see him sacrifice to thy command!
                        Now Titan turne thy breathing curses backe!
                        Start hence bright day, a sable Cloud invade
                        This Vniversall Globe, breake every prop,
                        And every h
                              •…
                           ndge that doth sustaine the Heavens:
                        For straight must dye a woman, I have named
                        A crime, that may accuse all Nature guilty.
                        The Sexe wisely considered, deserves a death;
                        For thinke this (Amurath) this woman may,
                        Prostrate he
                              •…
                            delicate and Ivory limbes,
                        To some base Page, or Scul, or shrunk up Dwarf:
                        Or let some Groome lye feeding on her lips,
                        She may devise some mishapen trick,
                        To satiate her goatish Amurath,
                        
                        And from her bended knees at Meditation,
                        Be taken by some slave toth' deepe of Hell!
                        Th'art a brave Creature, were thou not a woman:
                        
                           
                              〈◊〉
                           ! Come! thou shalt see my well-kept vow,
                        
                           And know my hate, which saw me dote but now:
                        
                           Schahin! 
                                 〈◊〉
                              ! Captaines ho!
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scaena, 5. Actus, 2.
                  Enter, Schahin, E
                        •…
                     renoses, Ch
                        •…
                     se-Illibegge.
                  
                     Our Tutor, Eurenoses, Captaines, welcome!
                     Gallants, I call you to a spectacle:
                     My breast too narrow to hoard up any joy:
                     Nay, gaze here (Gentlemen!) give Nature thanks,
                     For framing such an excellent sence as (Sight)
                     Whereby such objects are injoy'd as this!
                     Which of you now imprison not your thought
                     In envio
                           •…
                        s and silent policy.
                  
                  
                     Scab.
                     
                        My Lord to whatsoever you shall propose,
                        My sentence shall be free.
                     
                  
                  
                     Euren.
                     And mine. Chase-Il. And mine.
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     
                        Which of you then dare chalenge to himself,
                        Such a pathetique a Praerogative,
                        So stoically 
                              •…
                           evered from affection,
                        That had he su
                              •…
                           h a Creature as lyeth here,
                        One, at whom Nature her selfe stood amazed:
                        One, whom th
                              •…
                           se lofty exta
                              •…
                           ies of Poets,
                        Should they decay, here't must not barely dump
                        Their dull inventions with similitudes,
                        Taken from Sunne, Moone, V
                              •…
                           olets▪ Roses,
                        And, when their raptures at a period stand;
                        A silent admiration must supply
                        Onely name her, and she is all describ'd.
                        
                           Hyperbole of women, Colour it selfe
                        Is not more pure, and incontaminate!
                        Sleep doates on her: and grasps her eye-lids close▪
                        
                        The sky it selfe hath onely so much blew
                        As the azure in her vei
                              •…
                           es, bends by reflexe.
                        Here's breath that would those vapors purifie,
                        Which from Avernus choakes the flying Birds!
                        Here's heat would tempt the numb'd Atkenian,
                        
                        Though all his bloud with age were conjealed yce!
                        Now, which of you all is so temperate;
                        That, did he find this Iewel in his Bed
                        
                           (Vnlesse an Eunuch) could refraine to grapple,
                        And dally with her? Come! Speake freely all.
                     
                  
                  
                     S
                           •…
                        a.
                     
                        Truly (my Lord) I came of mortall Parents
                        And much confesse me subject to desires;
                        Freely injoy your Love!
                        That were she mine, I surely would doe no lesse.
                     
                  
                  
                     Amur.
                     What sayth Euren
                              •…
                           ses?
                     
                  
                  
                     Euren.
                     
                        My Lord, I 
                              •…
                           ay;
                        That they may raile at light, that nere saw day;
                        But, had I such a Creature by my side
                        Were the world twice enlarged, and all that world
                        Orecome by me, all volumes writ,
                        Made cleane and fild up by Rhetorique straines:
                        Of my great deeds, Historians should spend
                        Their Inke and Paper in my sole Chronicle,
                        A thousand such alluring idle charmes,
                        Could not conjure me from betwixt her armes.
                     
                  
                  
                     Amur.
                     Your sentence Chase 
                              〈◊〉
                            Beg?
                     
                  
                  
                     Chas.
                     
                        What need your Grace depend upon our breath?
                        I vow (my Lord,) if all those scrupulous things
                        Which burden us with praecepts so praecise,
                        Those Parents which when they are married once
                        And past their strength of yeares, thinke their sonnes 
                              •…
                           traight,
                        Should be as old in every thing as they,
                        I say my Lord, did my head weare a Crowne
                        That Queen should be the chiefest jem t'adorne it,
                        Spite of all hate, that's an unhappy state
                        When Kings must feare to love, least subjects hate.
                     
                  
                  
                     Amur.
                     
                        Wel spoke three Milk-sops, S
                                 •…
                              hahin! Your Sword!
                        Now, now be valour in this manly arme Scahin gives him 
                                 •…
                               Sword.
                        
                        To cut off troupes of thoughts that would invade me!
                        Thinke you my minde is waxie to be wrought,
                        By any fashion, Orch
                                 •…
                              nes thy strength,
                        Here doe I wish as did that Emperour,
                        That all the heads of that inticing Sexe,
                        Were upon hers, thus then should one full stroake
                        Mow them all off. Heere Amurath cuts off Eumorphes head, shewes it to the Nobles.
                        
                        
                        There, kisse now (Captaines) doe! and clap her cheeke;
                        This is the face that did so captive me:
                        These were the lookes that so bewitcht mine eyes▪
                        
                        Here be the lips, that I but for to touch,
                        Gave over Fortune, Victory, Fame, and all;
                        These were two lying mirrors where I lookt
                        And thought I saw a world of happine
                              •…
                           e.
                        Now Tutor, shall our swords be exercised,
                        In ripping up the breasts of Christians.
                        Say Generals! Whether is first?
                     
                  
                  
                     All.
                     For Thracia!
                     
                  
                  
                     Amurath.
                     
                        On then for Thracia, for he surely shall
                        That conquers first himselfe, soone conquer all.
                     
                     Exeunt omnes.
                  
               
            
            
               Actus III.
               
                  Scaena I.
                  
                     Enter Cobelitz solus.
                  
                  
                     Cobelitz.
                     
                        Thou sacred guider of the arched Heavens,
                        Who canst collect the scattering starres, and fixe
                        The Erratique Planet in the constant Pole,
                        O why shouldst thou take such solicitous care
                        To keepe the ayre, and Elements in course?
                        That Winter should uncloth our Mother Earth,
                        And wrap her in a winding sheet of snow;
                        That then the spring duly revives her still,
                        Vnlinds her sinews, fils her cling'd up veynes,
                        With living dew, and makes her young againe;
                        Next that, the Nemean terror breathes her flames,
                        To parch her flaxie haires with furious heat;
                        Which to allay too, thou op'st the Chataracts,
                        And watereth the worlds Gardens with blest drops;
                        Canst thou▪ which canst sustain the ponderous world,
                        And keepst in true poize, securely sleepe,
                        Letting a Tyrant (which with a Philip, thus;
                        
                           Thou mightest sinke to Earth) to baffle thee?
                        A warrier in thy Fields, I long have beene
                        To see if in thy sacred providence,
                        Thou meanst to arme me with thy thunder-bolt,
                        Yet, yet, it strikes not now, he Gyant-wise,
                        He dares thee againe; pardon our earnest zeale
                        What ere's decreed for man by thy behost,
                        He must performe: and in obedience rest.
                        Thou, like Spectators when they doe behold
                        An hardy youth encountring with a Beare▪
                        
                        Or something terrible; then they give a shout,
                        So dost thou even applaud thy selfe to see,
                        Religion striving with Calamity.
                        Which while it often beares, and still rests true,
                        It's fence 'gainst all that after shall ensue.
                        
                           Turke, ile oppose thee still! Heaven has decreed:
                        That this weake hand, shall make that tyrant bleed.
                        A man religious, firme, and strongly good
                        Cannot oth' suddaine be, nor understood.
                     
                     Exit.
                  
               
               
                  Scaena, 2. Actus, 3.
                  Enter Amurath in Armes, Schahin, Captaines, Souldiers.
                  
                     Amurath.
                     
                        Rise (Soule!) injoy the prize of thy brave worth!
                        
                           Scahin! the Present that thou so profest,
                        Should from the City of Orestias,
                        
                        Make proud our eyes! then tell me. hast thou slaine
                        A thousand superstitious Christian soules;
                        Make them stoope to us; O, I would bath my hands
                        In their warme bloud to make them supple. (Schahin;)
                        That they may weild more Speares! our hands are dull,
                        Our furie's patient! now will I be a Turke,
                        
                        And to our Prophets altars doe I vow,
                        That to his yoke I will all necks subdue,
                        Or in their throates my bloudy sword imbrew.
                     
                     
                        Here Schahin calls in his souldiers, and each of them presents to Amurath, the head of a dead Christian.
                  
                  
                     S
                           •…
                        ah.
                     
                        Then King, to adde fresh oyle unto thy hate,
                        And make it raise it selfe a greater flame,
                        See here these Christians heads; thus still shall fall
                        Before thy fatall hand, these impio
                              •…
                           s slaves;
                        So long as number's wanting to the sand,
                        So long as day shall come with Sunne, and night
                        Be spangled with the twilight dawning starres,
                        Whilst floods shall fall into the Ocean
                        Shall Christians tremble at Turkes thundring stroakes.
                     
                  
                  
                     Amurat.
                     
                        Soam I Amurath the great King of Turkes,
                        
                        O how it glads me thus to pash thei
                              •…
                            braines,
                        To rend their lockes, to teare these Infidels!
                        Who thundered when these heads were smitten off?
                        Starres I could reach you with my lofty hand,
                        'Tis well enough, enough, (great Amurath)
                        For now I sit in Orchanes great throne,
                        And sacrifice due rites to Mahomet;
                        
                        Yet why enough? Ile on and dung the Earth,
                        With Christians rotted trunckes, that frō that soyle,
                        May spring more Cadmean Monsters to orecome thē.
                        Captaines, what Conntries next shal we make flow,
                        With Channels of their bloud?
                     
                  
                  
                     Euren.
                     
                        To Servia (my Lord) there are troupes of armes,
                        Gathered to resist Mahometans.
                     
                  
                  
                     Chase.
                     
                        At Bulgaria, there they set on fire,
                        The Countries as they passe, 'twere good we haste.
                     
                  
                  
                     Amur.
                     
                        Why they doe well! we like of their desire
                        To make the flame in which themselves must fry!
                        Ruine, destruction, famine, and the sword,
                        Shall all invade them, Sunne stay thou thy flight,
                        And see the snakes in their owne River drencht,
                        Whil
                              •…
                           t with their bloud our furious thirst is que
                              •…
                           cht!
                     
                  
               
               
                  
                  Scaena 3. Actus 3.
                  Enter in aermes, Lazarus, Despot of Servia, Sesmenos Governour of Bulgaria.
                  
                  
                     Lazar.
                     
                        Whether (Bulgaria) whether must we flye?
                        The Butcherous Tur
                                 •…
                              e's at hand. Blest Sanctity▪
                        
                        If thou didst ere guard goodnesse, wall our towers?
                        Bring strength into our Nerves! For in thy cause
                        Our Brests upon their Rapiers we will run;
                        We'll with just hope 
                              〈◊〉
                            the tyrants rage,
                        Meet him in the face, fury will 
                              •…
                           de us armes:
                        There is a power can guard us from a
                              •…
                           l harmes.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sesm.
                     
                        Let's be su
                              •…
                           dain: for we'
                              •…
                            not find scope,
                        To see our haps. Who most doth feare, may hope.
                     
                     
                        Enter to them Cobelitz.
                  
                  
                     Cobel.
                     
                        Governor, Captaines, hast unto your armes:
                        The dangers imminent, and the Turke's at hand
                     
                  
                  
                     Lazar.
                     
                        (Cobelitz) must we still wade thus deepe
                        In blood and terror.
                     
                  
                  
                     Cob.
                     
                        Yes (Servia) we must, we should, we ought,
                        Ease and successe keeps basenesse company,
                        Shall we not blush to see the register
                        Of those great Romans, and Heroicke Greekes,
                        
                        Which did those acts (at which our hearts are struck
                        Beneath all credence) onely to win fame:
                        And shall not we for that Eternall name?
                        To live without all credence even to win fame,
                        Is not to know life's chiefe, and better parts:
                        To us of future hopes; calamity
                        Must helpe to purchase immortality.
                     
                  
                  
                     Ses.
                     
                        Well spoke (true Ch
                              •…
                           istian) they who still live high,
                        And snoare in prais'd applause nere know to beare,
                        A contu
                              •…
                           ely, or checke a fate,
                        Wisely to steere a Ship, or guide an Army,
                        Vndanted hardinesse is requisite;
                        (O) then lets to our weapo
                              •…
                           s! make him yeild▪
                        
                        They which deny all right, of
                              •…
                           give't ith' Field.
                     
                     
                        Enter Christian Souldiers falling out amongst them▪ se
                           •…
                        es fighting confusedly.
                  
                  
                     Cob.
                     
                        Why (Gentlemen) we want no foes to fight,
                        Nor need we turne our weapons on our selves!
                     
                     One Souldier speakes as drunk.
                  
                  
                     1.
                     You lazy rogue, what! come in my Cabinet?
                  
                  
                     2.
                     
                        Conspiring slave you murmur'd gin's th'allowance,
                        And would
                              •…
                           t perswade upon a larger pay, A
                                 •…
                              swer the other.
                        
                        To betray all Garrisons, and turne Tur
                                 •…
                              .
                        
                        Thou halfe Can-carousing rascall, Ile teare thee,
                        And those treacherous veines of thine, will you see.
                     
                  
                  
                     Llew-
                           •…
                        ackets.
                     
                        Will you see your Corporall wrong'd?
                        Well, since I fight for victuals for company,
                        Vse now your swords and Bucklers.
                     
                     The other to his m
                           •…
                        n. Here they all fall by the 
                           •…
                        ares.
                  
                  
                     Lazar.
                     Treason the next man that speakes or strikes a blow▪
                     
                  
                  
                     Sold.
                     Then shall our Laundresses fight for us.
                  
                  
                     2.
                     Why, Amazo
                           •…
                        s! Baudicans, come helpe to scratch!
                     Enter some Truls 
                           〈◊〉
                         both sides, th
                           •…
                        y fight and scr
                           •…
                        ch.
                  
                  
                     Sesm.
                     O Cobelitz, what way shall we appease them?
                     Truls scold con
                           •…
                        usedly: thus.
                  
                  
                     1. Trull.
                     
                        Out thy Corporal (huswife) hath the itch,
                        You now will have foule washing, Drab ile teare your mouth;
                     
                  
                  
                     2.
                     An inch or two yet wider.
                  
                  
                     Cob.
                     
                        What, souldiers thinke you each distastfull word,
                        Given ▪mo
                              •…
                           gst your selves so strong an obloquie The Generall parts them with his sword.
                        
                        That revenge spurs you to each others death?
                        And will not seeke to wash those blasphemies,
                        In Seas of their foule blood, which they belcht out.
                        By our approaching foes, against the Essence
                        Of the Eternall.
                     
                  
                  
                     Laz.
                     Leave, leave, these factions; cease these Mutinies▪
                     
                     A Drum from the Turke's Cam
                           •…
                        .
                     
                        Harke their Drums take advantage of these stirre
                              •…
                           
                           ▪
                        
                        Let us oppose our strength against our foe!
                        And in our Campe let not one souldier be,
                        Who will not finde and strike his Enemies.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        Cob.
                     
                        Now (blest guider and great strength of armes)
                        If in thy secret and hid decree,
                        Thou hast not yet appointed the full time,
                        Wherein thou meanest to tame this tyger,
                        Who dare murmur against thine hidden will?
                        Be we slaine now, there's victory in store,
                        Which when thou pleasest thou't give, &amp; not before.
                        Give us still strength of patience, not to wish,
                        A funerall honour unto all the world,
                        When we are perishing we'l still beleeve,
                        Those dangers worth our death we undergoe.
                        Whilst who is ours, is all alike thy foe;
                        Should fortune loose this day when we are slaine,
                        Thou canst give hands, and strength, and men again
                              •…
                           ;
                        On thee we trust then, and on thee beare,
                        Scorning for Heavens sake to shed a teare.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scaena 4. Actus 3.
                  A march within, excursions, alarmes. Enter as Conquerours, Cairadin Bassa, Scahin, leading young men Christians, Prisoners.
                  
                     Schah.
                     
                        
                           Bassa! we thanke thy valor and discretion▪
                        
                        In finding fit occasion to invade
                        The mutinons Christians! these Captives here
                        Shall be good presents to our worthy Master.
                     
                  
                  
                     Bassa.
                     
                        Generall now trust me these young slaves,
                        To be full of Valor, they have mettall in them.
                     
                  
                  
                     Schah.
                     
                        Yes; and to his Highnesse shall performe
                        A service which I long have thought upon,
                        And which his Turkis
                                 •…
                              
                            Majesty requires;
                        They'l fit to be a neare attendant guard,
                        On all occasions to the Emperour;
                        Therefore they shall be called 
                              
                                 〈◊〉
                              
                              ▪
                           
                        
                        By me first instituted, for our Princes safeties sake.
                     
                  
                  
                     Bass.
                     
                        Their vigor and strong hearts becomes such service,
                        For to orecome them made our soldiers sweat,
                        Much Turkish blood: the Servians kept the Fight,
                        
                           With stubborne hard resistance, The Bulgarians
                        
                        Left the right wing; there set I forward first,
                        And like a torrent rowl'd destruction on,
                        Raising huge stormes of bloud, as doth the Whale,
                        Puffe up the Waves against a mighty Ship;
                        Me thinkes I see the Rivers of their gore:
                        Their Leaders trampled on by Turkish Horse,
                        The body of their army quite disperst;
                        Themselves all floating in Vermillian pooles,
                        With their owne weapons hasting to their death.
                        And such a slaughter did we make of them,
                        As Nature scarce can ere repaire againe.
                        One hasting to others death, pulling to ground,
                        Him that held up, so they each other drown'd.
                     
                  
                  
                     Scah.
                     
                        Still are they confident upon a power,
                        They know not what, who (as they think) can snatch
                        Their praecise soules from out the jawes of death.
                     
                  
                  
                     Bass.
                     
                        Yes, such a superstition doth possesse them,
                        For when they lookt for nothing but their fate,
                        And danger stood in sweat upon their browes?
                        They yet scorn'd Mahom
                                 •…
                              t, and prophan'd his rites,
                        And nought but horror made them to beleeve him;
                        So many men were fighting on his side:
                        As might have chang'd my seat, and part ith' world,
                        (Though Nature stood against) to a new place:
                        Or carry Sestos whereby Abydos stands,
                        Or pull downe Atlas with so many hands▪
                        
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scaena 5. Actus 3.
                  Enter Amurath with Embassadour▪ from Germaine Ogly, concerning Bajazet, Amurath's E
                        •…
                     dest 
                        •…
                     onne, and the Mahometans Daughter. Cairadin Bassa presents Amurath with his Captives for 
                        •…
                     anizaries, Schahin. &amp;c.
                  
                     Amurath,
                     
                        How like our Captaines the last Victory?
                        (If any can prophesie of future things)
                        Me thought I did dreame of this blessed hap,
                        
                           How Fortune did involue them in their ruine,
                        And slight from danger, brought them into danger,
                        Each one astonished with a suddaine feare,
                        Knew not the danger that was then most neare.
                     
                  
                  
                     Bass
                           •…
                        .
                     
                        To adde more tryumph, I present my Liege, Bass
                                 •…
                               &amp; Schahin presents Amurath with Cap
                              
                                 •…
                              ives for Ianizaries.
                        
                        With these young Rebels, which you may bring up,
                        In all the praecepts of our Mahomet:
                     
                  
                  
                     S
                           •…
                        ah.
                     
                        And for great Emperor, your person wants,
                        A thing which much ore-Clouds your light of state,
                        Attendant Ianizarie
                                 •…
                              
                            to a Prince:
                        These may be so trained up, as to supply
                        The duty fit for such a Majesty:
                     
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     
                        
                           Bassa we thanke thy strength: Schahin your counsaile,
                        And to that end, let them have safe protection.
                        But we must treat now of a marriage (Lords)
                        The German Og
                                 •…
                              y, he who Scept
                              •…
                           r swayes
                        The 
                              
                                 〈◊〉
                              
                            confines in strong Asia,
                        
                        By Embassie intreates that he may joyne
                        His Daughter H
                                 •…
                              tam to our 
                              
                                 〈◊〉
                              !
                        
                        Embassador here to our Councell speake,
                        Your Masters Message.
                     
                  
                  
                     Emb.
                     
                        Please then your Maj. and these reverend heads
                        To be inform'd my Masters will by me,
                        In Wedlocke; if your Prince may be combin'd
                        To the faire Princesse his sole Daughter:
                        He freely giues the Phr
                                 •…
                              gian territories,
                        And B
                                 •…
                              thinia to you for your Dowry;
                        
                           Cata
                                 •…
                              , Simon, Egreg
                                 •…
                              os, Sansale,
                        
                        
                           Abbettin
                                 •…
                              on, the Ottomans estate,
                        Which Ottomans, because he not endures,
                        The Noble Zelzucciom family protests,
                        To joyne with you in quelling their ambition.
                     
                  
                  
                     Scah.
                     
                        May't please your Majesty to like mine advice
                        It's good to have allyance with such friends;
                        Kings that combine themselves are like to shafts,
                        The ancient Sage propos'd unto his sonne!
                        Which whilst together they were close compact:
                        Armes, knees, and his wh
                              •…
                           le strength▪ could never breake;
                        
                           Take one by one, they with a touch were tract,
                        So Kings may be orecome that stand alone;
                        But two such Princes, knit thus hand in hand,
                        Should Nations totter, they would firmely stand.
                     
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     
                        Yes Schahin we'll approve what thou sayest;
                        Then from us carry the great Asians Monarch,
                        This his kindest greeting:
                        Tell him the gates of Prusa shall stand ope,
                        And the glad ayre shall Eccho notes of joy,
                        To ent
                              •…
                           rtaine her who shall blesse our Land,
                        With hopefull issue; gre
                              •…
                           dy thoughts expect
                        Her soone arrivall; and so (Emba
                              •…
                           sador)
                        Enforme thy Priucesse, when she shall appeare,
                        A lasting Starre shall shi
                              •…
                           e within our Sphaere!
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scaena 6. Actus 3.
                  Enter Sasmenos, La
                        •…
                     arus, Cobelitz.
                  
                     Sa.
                     
                        O Servia, our Cities are turned flames;
                        Each stayes to hast his owne and others death:
                        And as though Heaven conspir'd destructiou too,
                        That raignes downe scalding Sulphure on our heads,
                        Here one that lyes thicke gasping for his breath,
                        Is choakt with bloud that runs from's fellowes wounds,
                        Whilst others for the dead are making Graves,
                        Themselves are made the coarses that doe fill them!
                        Nobles, and base, together perish all:
                        And a drawne sword stickes fast in every rib;
                        Our stones are dyed Vermillion with our bloud!
                        Old creatures that are creeping to the graue,
                        Are thrust on fast
                              •…
                           r!
                        Infants but in the 
                              〈◊〉
                            of their lives,
                        And thus kickt off, O most disastrous times,
                        To love our deaths, and make our life our crimes.
                     
                  
                  
                     Laz.
                     
                        See, see, the ruines of our goodly Walles,
                        Our Cities smoake hinders the sight of heaven:
                        The conquerour yet amaz'd measures ou
                              •…
                            our Townes▪
                        
                        
                           With eyes of terror, and doth scarce beleeve
                        He hath orecome us; yet among these fires,
                        Our dead men are denyed their funerall flames:
                        Aud those infectious Carka
                              •…
                           ses doe performe,
                        A second murder on the rest that live!
                        And all the hope of safety that we have,
                        Is now to fixe our flattering lips at's feet:
                        Mercy (perhaps) may wearied slaughter meet.
                     
                  
                  
                     Sas.
                     Wil you doe so? speake for I am determi'nd —
                  
                  
                     Cob.
                     
                        No (worthy Generall) Heaven avert
                        And 
                              •…
                           rme you with the proofe of better thoughts!
                        What though a Tyrant strives to terrifie
                        All Christendome, and would not be beloved?
                        Let not your feares give impious rage such scope!
                        As for to bring Religion to prophanesse:
                        Fortune and Heaven will scorne to try a man,
                        That hurles his weapons hence and runs away!
                        How is he worthy of heavens victory;
                        That, when it frownes, dares not looke u
                              •…
                            and see?
                        Me thinks w
                              •…
                            three are now inviron'd round,
                        With hosts of Angels, and our powerfull Mars.
                        
                        Is putting bowes of steele into our hands:
                        He doth suggest our wrath, and bids us, on!
                        O what an army 'tis to have a cause
                        Holy and just; there, there's our strength indeed.
                     
                     
                        — Tu mente Labantes,
                        Dirige nos, dubios: Certo Robore firmâ.
                     
                     
                        If we must dye, the narrow way to blisse,
                        Shall be made wide for us, the gate wide ope,
                        And the spread Pallace entertaines with joy.
                        Meane time, let's looke like men upon our g
                              •…
                           iefe.
                        Out frowne fate, Despot, Bulgaria, come!
                        Turke! once more at thee (Tyrant) mortals must,
                        Command Heavens favor in a cause so just.
                     
                  
               
            
            
               
               Actus IIII.
               
                  Scaena I.
                  Enter Aladin King of Caramania, sonne in Law to Amurath, with Nobles, Embassad
                        •…
                     rs from Amurath.
                  
                     Aladin.
                     
                        Sends our proud father in Law this greeting to us?
                        Was our sword sheath'd so soone to heare this answer?
                     
                  
                  
                     Embass.
                     
                        My Lord, he bad me tell you that 'twas you
                        
                           
                              〈◊◊〉
                            him leave off this great Prophets Warres,
                        When he was hewing downe the Christians;
                        Therefore submission 
                              •…
                           hould not now appease him,
                        Mo▪ though your Wife, his Daughter, 
                              •…
                           hould her selfe,
                        Vpon her penitent knees be supplyant!
                        No sooner shall the Tycian splendent Sol,
                        Open Heavens Casements, and inlarge the day,
                        But his horse hoofes shall beat your treacherous Earth;
                        And that you may be warn'd of his approach,
                        Murder and flames shall be his Prodromo's!
                     
                  
                  
                     Alad.
                     
                        Confederate Princes and my kind allyes,
                        Shall his proud nosthrils breath those threats on us?
                     
                  
                  
                     Emb.
                     
                        Moreover, my Lord wil or win, or raz
                              •…
                           ,
                        
                           I
                                 •…
                              ouium and Larenda.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Alad.
                     
                        
                           Iconium and Larenda? I? No more?
                        Had best looke first, how safe his Prusa stands!
                        Lords, I am mov'd, and will forget my Queene
                        Was ere the issue of his hated blood!
                        My splene is tost within; mine entrailes pant,
                        As, wen the Sea is rais'd with Southerne gusts,
                        The wind allay'd, yet still the Waves will tremble,
                        Princes, now binde your selves with such strong chaines,
                        Your faith and breaths can make; sweare to me all,
                        To be as firme to me 'gainst Amurath,
                        
                        As is the skin and 
                              •…
                           lesh unto the Nerves;
                     
                     Here they all kneele, and sweare vpon his sw
                           •…
                        rd.
                  
                  
                     
                        Nobles.
                     We all sweare we will.
                  
                  
                     Aladin.
                     
                        Then all here kisse my Sword,
                        Which shall be steept within the head-mans thr
                              •…
                           at▪
                        
                        We'l make him know those will not 
                              •…
                           lye in Warre,
                        Which may in policie in treat a peace!
                        Hast thy course (time) and soone reduce the yeare!
                        Ensignes may Ensignes meet, 
                              
                                 〈◊〉
                              
                            King,
                        Great 
                              
                                 〈◊〉
                              , scornes to avoyd a Turke:
                        
                        Princes, and Neighbours, muster up your strength,
                        That we may meet him on his full Cariere!
                        And let it be Car
                                 •…
                              nia's pride to say,
                        To overcome him we askt no second day.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scaena 2. Actus 4.
                  Enter Amurath at one doore with Nobles Bajazet, Enter at th'other, Hatam, richly attended, they meet, salute in dumbe shew; Amurath ioynes the hands of the Prince, and Princesse; whilst this is solemnizing, is sung to soft Musicke, this Song following.
                  
                     
                        Song.
                        
                           Thne O Hymen, thine: O shee,
                           Whose Beauties verse Calliope,
                           
                           Sing to Marriage rites an Io,
                           
                           
                              Io to Hymen.
                           
                        
                        
                           Thorus. 
                           To thee Apollo is my sute,
                           Lend me a while thy silver Lute,
                           O what a woe it is to bring,
                           A Bride to Bed and never sing.
                           
                              Io to Hymen.
                           
                        
                        
                           When she's old, still seemes she young,
                           When she's weke, to her be strong!
                           Be Cyprus, both, and Paphos here,
                           Love, sing with merry cheere.
                           
                              Io to Hymen.
                           
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        Am.
                     
                        You Gods of Marriage: sacred Protectoresse
                        Of lawfull propagations, and blest Love
                        Be most propitious to these grafted stemmes!
                        Drop dewing showers of gen
                              •…
                           ration on them!
                        Thinke (Sonne) this day too prodigall of blessing
                        As, that had 
                              
                                 •…
                              uno taskt thee (like Alcides)
                        To grapple with St
                                 •…
                              mphallides, or clense
                        
                           Angelas stables: or like the Trojan Boy,
                        Sit like a Shephe
                              •…
                           rd on Dardadias Hils,
                        Such a reward as this faire Queen repayres,
                        O thou hop'd future off-spring spare thy Parent!
                        Hurt not this tender wombe, these Ivory worlds,
                        When you are borne; O be within your limbes,
                        The Grandsire Amurath, and fathers strength!
                        Line their faces (Nature) 
                              •…
                           ith their Mothers dye!
                        And let the Destinies marke the ensuring night
                        In their Eternall Bookes, with notes most white.
                     
                  
                  
                     All.
                     Grant it great Ma
                              •…
                           omet!
                     
                  
                  
                     H
                           •…
                        tam.
                     
                        Most awfull father and my honored P
                              •…
                           inee,
                        Although it be enacted by the Heavens,
                        That in these bonds of marriage such curse
                        Attends on Princes above private men,
                        That nor affection, nor home-nourisht Love
                        But 
                              •…
                           tate and policy must elect their Wives.
                        Which must be fetcht from Countries farre remote!
                        Yet the protecting Powers have such a care,
                        Both of their off-springs and their Kingdomes state,
                        That to what they ordaine, they worke in us
                        A suddaine willingnesse to make us obey;
                        For, in this brest, I doe already feele
                        That there's a kindling a Diviner heat:
                        Which disobedience never shall extinguish.
                        And, if there be any felicity
                        From these u
                              •…
                           ited Loves to be derived
                        From the weake sexe into the husbands soule,
                        Then may my Lord make his affection sure,
                        To be repayd with unattainted Love,
                        In which a pritty peopl
                              •…
                            ye shall live,
                        
                           Wi
                              •…
                            soft and yeilding curtesie in all
                        He shall command, my willing armes shall still,
                        Be ope t'enfold within a Wives embrace,
                        If any comfort else there be in store,
                        (Which modesty keeps silent to it selfe)
                        Cause onely husbands and the night must know't,
                        My Loyalty shall ever all performe▪
                        
                        And (though my) Lord should frown, Ile be the 
                              •…
                           ame▪
                        
                        Greene wood will burne with a continued flame:
                     
                  
                  
                     Baiaz.
                     
                        Princesse our ardor is already fired,
                        Yet with no violent temerity;
                        Such as might feare it's short and soone decaying▪
                        
                        Thy vertue seemes so to exceed thy Sexe,
                        And wisdome so farre to out-pace thy yeares,
                        That, surely (Ptincesse) soone maturity,
                        Argues in them, hidden Divinity.
                        Expected (Hymen) here hath bound our hands,
                        And hearts, with everlasting ligaments▪
                        
                        Fortunate both we are, and have one blisse
                        The want of which for ever doth infect,
                        With anxious cares the sweets of marriage Beds:
                        Our Parents benediction and consent,
                        They are the truest Hymens, and should be
                        To children the best marriage Deity.
                        Thus then attended with 
                              •…
                           uch sacred charmes
                        Our last day of content shall never come;
                        Till we must part by th'unresisted doome,
                        With a pleas'd error we will age beguile,
                        All starres on us, an aequall yoke must smile.
                     
                  
                  
                     Amur.
                     
                        Now (Lords) who'le dance
                        A Turkish measure? Ladies our nerves are shrunke;
                        And you now fixe the signe of age on me,
                        You who have bloud still flowing in your veynes,
                        Be nimble as an Hart: Caper to the 
                              •…
                           phaeres!
                        O you are light, that wrnt the weight of yeares!
                     
                     Musicke. Here Amurath 
                           •…
                        cends his Throne, the rest set downe to dance, Bajazet with Hatam, &amp;c. the end of the dance, all kneele, Amurath begin an health, a flourish with Cornets.
                  
                  
                     
                        Amur.
                     
                        And health to our Bride and her father!
                        O (Nobles) would this wine were Christians blood,
                        But that it would Phrenetique humours breed,
                        And so infect our b
                              •…
                           aines with Superstition!
                     
                     Enter Eurenoses with sixe Christian Maidens, richly attyred, their Haire hanging loose, in their hands C
                           •…
                        ps of Gold with 
                           〈◊〉
                        
                        ▪ &amp;c.
                  
                  
                     Euren.
                     
                        Auspitious fortunes to great Amurath!
                        
                        To ope more springs unto this full tide of joy,
                        Know (potent Emperor) I from Europe bring
                        Sixe daughters of sixe severall Kings,
                        Whose Cities we have equall'd to the ground;
                        And of their Pallaces did torches make,
                        To light their soules through the blacke Cave of death (Acherō
                           )
                     
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     Describe (good Captaine) how the dogs were wearied.
                  
                  
                     Euren.
                     
                        So weary were they to indure to indure our swords,
                        That by impetuous mutiny themselves,
                        Turn'd on each other; slew their Maisters;
                        Childrens own hands, tore out their fathers throats.
                        And each one strove who should be 
                              •…
                           laughtered first;
                        Here did a brother pash out a Brothers braines,
                        Some in stinking Quagmires, and deepe Lakes
                        (Which they had made t'avoyd their excrements)
                        Ran quicke, and in the lake lay buried.
                     
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     (Goon Executioner of our most just wrath!)
                  
                  
                     E
                           •…
                        .
                     
                        Nor did it leave till death it selfe was weary▪
                        
                        Murder grew faint, and each succeeding day,
                        Shewed us the slaughter of the day before.
                        'Mongst carkasses and funerals we stood,
                        Denying those that liv'd such Ceremonies
                        As i
                              •…
                            their Temples to the Indian Gods,
                        With prayers and vowes they dayly offred:
                        Nor destiny, nor cruelty ere left,
                        Till they had nothing to worke upon;
                        For, of so many soules that breath'd
                        These sixe are all remain'd: which as a Pledge
                        
                           Of my best service to your Majesty.
                        I here am bold to yeeld an offer.
                     
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     
                        Nor shall this present b
                              •…
                            unrecompenced;
                        For thy true service, on thee 
                              •…
                           e bestow
                        All the rich guifts, which all these Asian Lords
                        B
                              •…
                           ought to adore these happy Nuptials,
                        On you faire Bride great Princesse and our Daughter
                        Doe we bestow the
                              •…
                           e Virgins (daughters to Kings)
                        For your attend
                              •…
                           nce.
                     
                  
                  
                     Hat.
                     We are too much bound unto our Princely Father▪
                     
                  
                  
                     Am,
                     
                        No (Daughter) no! we hope thou art the spring,
                        From whence shall flow to all the world a King▪
                        
                        
                           
                              •…
                           Captaines and Lords▪ to morrow we must meet,
                        To thinke of our rebelliious sonne in Law)
                        Be this time all for comfort and delight,
                        Short wedding dayes make it seeme long to night.
                     
                     Exeunt 
                           •…
                        mn.
                  
               
               
                  Scaena 3. Actus 4.
                  Enter Lazarus and Cobelitz, bringing the dead body of Sesmenos.
                  
                     L
                           •…
                        z.
                     
                        Here set we downe our miserable load,
                        O 
                              
                                 〈◊〉
                              
                            with whom is't that we fight?
                        With Lydia
                                 •…
                              
                            Lyons, and Hyrcania
                                 •…
                              
                            Beares;
                        Which grinde us dayly in their ravenous te
                              •…
                           th?
                        The Tyrant (as it were dest
                              •…
                           uctions Enginere)
                        Helpe Nature to destroy the worlds frame quickly,
                     
                  
                  
                     Cob.
                     
                        Alas my Lord that needs not, every day
                        Is a sufficient he
                              •…
                           per to decay:
                        Great workman, who art sparing in thy strength
                        To bring things to perfectio
                              •…
                           , a
                              •…
                            to oret
                              •…
                           rne
                        All thy best wo
                              •…
                           kes, thou usest suddaine force,
                        When mans a
                              •…
                            E
                              •…
                           rio! and first con
                              •…
                           eived
                        How long 'tis ere he see his native light?
                        Then borne, with expectation for his growth!
                        Tenderly nourisht, carefully brought up,
                        Growne to p
                              •…
                           rfection, what a little thing,
                        Serves to call on his suddaine ruining?
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        Laz.
                     
                        Come Cobelitz, 
                           ▪mongst those demolisht ston
                              •…
                           s
                        We'll sit as Hecub
                                 •…
                              , at those Troy
                                 •…
                              n Walles:
                        Our teares shall be false glasses to our eyes:
                        Through these we'l looke, and thinke we yet may see
                        Our stately Pinacles, and strong founded holds;
                        That which one houre can delapidate,
                        One age can scarce repaire.
                     
                  
                  
                     Cob.
                     
                        No sir, for nothing's hard
                        To Nature, when she meanes t'consume
                        A thousand Oakes (which time hath fixt i'th earth,
                        As Monuments of lasting memory)
                        Are in a moment turn'd to ashes all;
                        Things that rise 
                              •…
                           lowly, take a suddaine fall.
                     
                  
                  
                     Laz.
                     
                        What course now Cobelitz, must we still be yoak▪
                        
                        To misery, and murder? We scarce have roome,
                        Vpon our bodies to receive more wounds,
                        And must we still oppose our selves to more?
                     
                  
                  
                     Cob.
                     
                        Yes! We are ready still; a solid minde
                        Must not be shakt with every blast of Winde!
                        
                           Pollux, nor Hercules, had none other art,
                        To get them Mansions in the spangl'd Heavens
                        Then a true firme resolve; th' A
                                 •…
                              riatike Sea,
                        Shall from his currents with tempestuous blasts,
                        Be sooner heard, than vertue from it's ayme,
                        Let us but thinke (when we so many see,
                        Enjoying greater quiet than our selves.)
                        How many have endur'd more misery;
                        
                           Ilion, Ilion, what a fate hadst thou?
                        How fruitfull wert thou in matter for thy foe?
                        Thus we'll delude our griefe, make our selfe glad,
                        To think of miseries that others had.
                     
                  
                  
                     Laz.
                     
                        I (Captaine) I! they that furnisht thee
                        With sentences of comfort, never saw,
                        Their Cities burnt, their C
                              •…
                           untries desolate!
                        'Tis easie for Physitians for to tell
                        Advice to others, when themselves are well!
                     
                  
                  
                     Cob.
                     
                        Tush, tush (my Lord) there's on our side we know,
                        One that can both, and will our weake hands g
                              •…
                           ide,
                        
                           One that will strike and thunder; Gyant then,
                        Looke for a dart! we must not appoint when;
                        Meane while helpe for to convay this burden henc
                              •…
                           
                        
                        
                           Turke, though thy tyranny deny us graves,
                        Corruption will give them spite of thee!
                        Nor doe our corps, such Tombes and Cavernes need:
                        For our owne flesh, still our owne graves to breed:
                        And, when the Earth receiveth not, when they die;
                        Heavens Vault ouerwhelmeth them, so their tombe's ith' skie.
                     
                     Exeunt with a dead Truncke.
                  
               
               
                  Scaena 4. Actus 4.
                  Enter Aladin as flying, an arrow through his arme, wounded in his forehead, his sh
                        •…
                     eld st
                        •…
                     cke with darts▪ with him two Nobles.
                  
                     Alad.
                     
                        Besieged on every side? Iconi
                                 •…
                              m taken?
                        Entrencht within my foes my selfe must lye
                        Wrapt in my Cities ruine! Turkes come on!
                     
                  
                  
                     1. N
                           •…
                        b.
                     
                        Nay but my Lord, meane you to meet your death?
                        Let's hast our flight, and trust more to our feet
                        Then words, or hands —
                     
                  
                  
                     Alad.
                     
                        Why, so much of our bloud
                        Is already spilt▪ as should the glittering Sunne
                        Exhale it upward, 'twould obnubulate
                        It's luster, else to fiery Meteors turne.
                        Some councell (Lords) he that's amidst the Sea,
                        When every curled wave doth threat his death
                        Yet trusts upon the oares of his owne armes,
                        And sometime the salt fome doth pitty him,
                        A Wolfe, or Lyon, that hath fild his gorge
                        With bloudy prey, at last will lye to sleepe,
                        And the unnaturalst creatures not forget
                        Their love to those whom they do know their own!
                        My wife's his Daughter; si
                              •…
                           ce we can
                              •…
                           ot stand
                        His 
                              •…
                           ury longer▪ she sh
                              •…
                           ll s
                              •…
                           age his wrath.
                        The boysterous Ocea
                              •…
                            wh
                              •…
                            
                           
                              •…
                            no 
                              〈◊〉
                            oppose,
                        Growth's 
                              〈◊〉
                            is lo
                              •…
                           t, whe
                              •…
                           't hath no foes.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        2. Noble.
                     
                        Why then (my Lord) array your selfe in weeds▪
                        
                        Of a Petitioner: take the Queene along,
                        And your two children; they may move his eyes;
                        For, desperate sores aske desperate remedies.
                     
                  
                  
                     Alad:
                     
                        Goe (Lords) goe: fetch some straight. O Heavens!
                        O fortune they that leane on thy crackt wheele,
                        And trust a Kingdomes power, and domineere
                        In a wall'd Pallace, let them looke on me,
                        And thee (Carmania) greater instances
                        The world affords not to demonstrate
                        The fraile estate of proudest Potentates,
                        Of sturdiest Monarchies: high Pinacles
                        Are still invaded with the prouder winds;
                        They must endure the threats of every blast;
                        The tops of Caucasus and Pindus shake,
                        With every cracke of thunder; humble Vaults
                        Are nere toucht with a bolt, ambiguous wings
                        Hath all the state, that hovers over Kings.
                     
                     
                        Enter the 2. Nobles with a winding sheet, Aladin puts it on.
                     
                     
                        I, I, this vesture fits my miserie!
                        This badge of poverty must now prevaile,
                        Where all my Kingdomes power &amp; strength doth faile,
                        Why should not a propheticke soule attend
                        On great mens persons, and forewarne their ils?
                        Raging Bootes doth not so turmoile
                        The Lybian ford, as Fortune doth great hearts.
                        
                           Be
                                 •…
                              tona and Erynnis scourge us on▪
                        
                        Should wars and treasons cease, why our owne weight
                        Would send us to the Earth; as spreading armes
                        Make the huge trees in tempest for to split.
                        For as the slaughter-man to pasture goes,
                        And drags that Oxe home first, whose Bulke is greatest,
                        The leane he still lets feed: disease takes hold
                        On bodies that are pampered with best fare;
                        So doth all ruine chuse the fairest markes:
                        At which it bends, and strikes it full of shafts,
                        Ambition made me now that eminent but:
                        And I that fell by mine owne strength, mu
                              •…
                           t rise
                        
                           By profest weaknesse; Buckets full sinke downe:
                        Whilst empty ones danceith' ayr
                              •…
                           , and cannot drowne.
                        Come (
                              •…
                           ords) he out o
                              •…
                           
                           ▪s way can never range,
                        Who is at f
                              •…
                           thest! worst nere finds ill change.
                     
                  
               
            
            
               Actus V.
               
                  Scaena I.
                  Enter at o
                        •…
                     e 
                        •…
                     ore Amurath, with 
                        〈◊〉
                     ; at th
                        •…
                      
                     
                        •…
                     ther doore Aladin, his Wife, two Chi
                        •…
                     dren, 
                        •…
                     ll 
                        〈◊〉
                      white s
                        •…
                     ets, kn
                        •…
                     le dow
                        •…
                     e to Amurat
                        •…
                     .
                  
                     A
                           •…
                        ur.
                     
                        Our hate must not part thus, Ile tell thee (Prince)
                        That thou hast kindled violent Aetna in our brest,
                        And such a flame is quencht with nought but blood:
                        His bloud whose hasty and rebellious blast,
                        Gave life unto the fire; should Heaven threat us;
                        Knowes we dare not menace it; are we not Amurat
                                 •…
                              ?
                        
                        (Whose awfull name is even trembled at)
                        So often dar'd by Pigmy Christians;
                        Which we will crush to ayre; what haughty thought
                        Buzz'd thy praesumptuous eares with such vain blasts,
                        To puffe thee into such impetuous acts?
                        Or what, durst prompt thee with a thought so fraile,
                        As made thee covetous of so brave a death?
                        As this known hand should cause it? know that throat
                        Shall feele it strangled with some slave brought up
                        To no
                              •…
                           ght but an Hangman: thy last breath,
                        Torne from thee by a hand that's worse than death
                     
                  
                  
                     Alad.
                     
                        Why then, Ile (like the Roman Pompey) hide
                        My dying sight, scorning Imperious lookes
                        Should grace so base a stroake with sad aspect;
                        Thus will I muffle up and choake my groanes,
                        Least a griev'd teare should quite put out the name,
                        Of lasting courage in Carmanias fame.
                     
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     
                        What? still sti
                              •…
                           e necked? Is this the tru
                              •…
                           e you b
                              •…
                           g?
                        
                           
                              •…
                           prinkled before thy face those Reb
                              •…
                           ll Brats,
                        
                           Shall have their braines, and their dissected lim
                              •…
                           es,
                        Hurld for a prey to Kites; for (Lords) 'tis fit
                        No sparke of such a Mountaine threatning fire,
                        Be left as unextinct, least it devoure,
                        And prove more hot unto the 
                              
                                 〈◊〉
                              
                            Emperie,
                        Then the 
                              
                                 〈◊〉
                              
                            blaze did trouble Iov
                                 •…
                              !
                        
                        First sacrifice those Brats —
                     
                  
                  
                     All. Wife.
                     
                        (Deare father) let thy fury rush on me!
                        Within these entrailes sheath thine unsatiate sword,
                        And let this ominous, and too fruitfull wombe,
                        Be torne in sunder? For from thence those Babes,
                        Tooke all their crimes; error made them guilty,
                        'Twas Natures fault, not theirs; O if affection
                        Can worke then; now shew a true Fathers Love,
                        If not, appease those murdering thoughts with me▪
                        
                        For as 
                              
                                 〈◊〉
                              
                            pleaded with her sonnes
                        For their deare Father, so to a Father I
                        For my deare Babes and husband; husband, father▪
                        
                        Which shall I first embrace? Victorious father,
                        Be bl
                              •…
                           t those now sharpe thoughtsllay downe those threats,
                        Vn
                              •…
                           laspe that impious Helmet! fixe to earth
                        That monumentall Spheare looke on thy child
                        With pardoning lookes, not with a Warriers eye:
                        Else shall my brest cover my husbands brest,
                        And serve as Buckler to receive thy wounds,
                        Why dost thou doubt? Fearest thou thy Daughters faith?
                     
                  
                  
                     Am
                           •…
                        r.
                     
                        I feare, for after Daughters perjurie
                        All Lawes of Natures shall di
                              •…
                           tastfull be;
                        Nor will I trust thy children or thy selfe.
                     
                  
                  
                     All. Wife.
                     
                        No Father 'tis I, feare you him, he you,
                        I both, but for you both, for both you warre;
                        So that 'tis best with him that's overcome.
                        O let me kisse (kind father) first the Earth
                        On which you tread, then kisse mine husbands cheeke.
                        Great King embrace these Babes! you are the stocke
                        On which these Grafts were planted —
                     
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     
                        True, and when sprouts do
                              •…
                            rob th
                              •…
                            tree of sap,
                        They must be prun'd,
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        Wife.
                     
                        Deare Father, leave such harsh similitudes▪
                        
                        By my deceased Mother, (to whose wombe
                        I was a ten months burden:) By your selfe,
                        (To whom I was a pleasing In
                              •…
                           ant on
                              •…
                           e)
                        Pitty my husband, and these tender Infants!
                     
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     
                        Yes to have them collect a manly strength,
                        And their first lesson that their Dad 
                              •…
                           hall teach them
                        Shall be to read my misery.
                     
                  
                  
                     Al.
                     
                        Sterne Conqueror: but that thy daughter shews,
                        There 
                              •…
                           nce dw
                              •…
                           lt good in that ob
                              •…
                           urate brest,
                        I would not 
                              •…
                           pend a teare to soften thee!
                        Thou seest my Countries turn'd into a Grave:
                        My Cities 
                              •…
                           carre the Sunne with fiereer flames,
                        Which turne them into ashes! all my selfe
                        So slickt and carved, that my amazed blood
                        Knowes not through which wound first to take it's way;
                        If not on me, have mercy on my Babes! —
                        Which, with thy mercy thou mayst turne to Love.
                     
                  
                  
                     Am
                           •…
                        rath,
                     
                        No sir, we must root out malitious seed:
                        Nothing sproutes faster, then an envious weed!
                        We see a little Bullocke, 'mongst an heard
                        (Whose hor
                              •…
                           es are yet scarce crept from out his front)
                        Growes on a suddaine tall, and in the Fields,
                        Frolicks so much, he makes his Father yeild.
                        A little twig left budding on an 
                              •…
                           lme
                        (Vngratefully) barres his mother 
                              •…
                           ight from Heaven!
                        I love not 
                              〈◊〉
                            
                           Aladins.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Alad.
                     
                        Threat all a Conquerour can, canst threat but death,
                        And I can die, but if thou wouldst have mercy! —
                     
                  
                  
                     Wife.
                     
                        O see you feete we're prou'd with this hands kisse!
                        The higher those great powers have rais'd you,
                        Presse that which lyes below with gentler weigh
                              •…
                           
                           ▪
                        
                        To pardon miseries is Fortunes height:
                        Alas, these Infants, these weake sinewed hands
                        Can be no terror to these Hectors armes!
                        Beg (Infants) beg, and teach these tender joynts
                        To aske for mercy; learne your lisping tongues
                        
                           To giue due accent to each syllable:
                        Nothing that Fortune urgeth too, is base;
                        Put from your thoughts all memory of discent:
                        Forget the Princely titles of your fathers:
                        If your owne misery you can feele,
                        Learne thus of me to weepe, of me to kneele▪
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Al.
                     
                        Doe (boyes) and imitate your Parents tea
                              •…
                           es▪
                        
                        Which I (like 
                              
                                 〈◊〉
                              
                           ) shed, when he beheld,
                        
                           H
                                 •…
                              ctor thrice dragg'd about the 
                              
                                 •…
                              rojan Walles.
                        He that burst ope the gates of Erebus,
                        
                        And rouz'd the yelling Monster from his Den,
                        Was conquer'd with a teare! great Monarch learne,
                        To know how deare a King doth weeping earne.
                     
                  
                  
                     1. C
                           •…
                        .
                     Good Grandsire see, see how my father cries!
                  
                  
                     2. Ch.
                     Good mother take my napkin for your eyes!
                  
                  
                     Wife.
                     
                        (Good father) heare, heare how thy daughter pr
                              •…
                           yes:
                        Thou that know'st how to use sterne Warriers armes,
                        Learne how to use mild Warriers pitty too!
                        Alas? can er
                              •…
                            these ungrowne strengths repaire
                        Their Fathers batter
                              •…
                           d Cities? Or can these
                        These orethrowne Turrets? (Jconium) what small hopes
                        Hast thou to leane upon? If these be all?
                        Not halfe so mild hath our misfortune beene
                        That any can ere feare us: Be pleased —
                     
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     
                        Rise (my deere child) as Marble against raine,
                        So I at these obedient showers, melt!
                        Thus I doe raise thy husba
                              •…
                           d: thus thy Babes:
                        Freely admitting you to former state.
                        But Alad
                                 •…
                              , wake not our w
                              •…
                           ath agai
                              •…
                           e!
                        "Patience growes fury that is ofter stirred;
                        When Conquerours waxe calme, and cease to 
                              •…
                           ate,
                        The conquered should not dare to reite
                              •…
                           ate.
                        Be thou our sonne and friend.
                     
                  
                  
                     Alad.
                     By all the rites of Mahomet I vow it!
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     
                        Then for to seale u
                              •…
                           o our love,
                        Your selfe shall leade a wi
                              •…
                           g in 
                              
                                 •…
                              ervia,
                        
                        In our immediate Wa
                              •…
                           res, we are to meet
                        The Christians in Cassanoe's Plaines with speed:
                        
                           Great Amurath nere had time to breath himselfe:
                        So much, as to have warring with new foes;
                        No day securely to 
                              •…
                           is Scepter shone,
                        But one Warres end, still brought another on.
                     
                     Ex
                           •…
                        t.
                  
               
               
                  Scaena 2. Actus.
                  Enter La
                        •…
                     s, Cobelitz, Souldiers, all armed.
                  
                     Cob.
                     
                        Let now victorious wreathes ingirt our 
                              •…
                           rowes,
                        Let Angels 'stead of Souldiers wield our armes,
                        'Gainst him, who that our Citti
                              •…
                           s might be his
                        Strives to depopulate, and make them none!
                        But looke, looke in the ayre (me thinks) I se
                              •…
                           
                        
                        An host of Souldiers brandishing their swords;
                        Each corner of the Heaven shoots thunderbolts,
                        To naile these impious forces to the Earth.
                     
                  
                  
                     Laz.
                     
                        Souldiers stand to 't! though fortune bandy at's
                        Let's stand her shockes, like sturdy Rockesith' Sea.
                        On which the angry foaming Billowes beat,
                        With frivolous rush: and breake themselves, not th
                              •…
                           m;
                        Stand like the undainted countenance oth' sky,
                        Or, like the Sunne, which when the foolish King▪
                        
                        Thought to obscure with a Cloud of Darts,
                        Out lookt them all, our lives are all inchanted,
                        And more i
                              •…
                           vulnerate than Thetis sonne.
                        We shall have hands snd weapons, if the stone,
                        Of fortune glide from under our weake feet,
                        And we must fall: yet, let all Christians say,
                        'Tis she, and not the cause, that wins the day.
                        We must beleeve Heaven hath a greater care
                        Of them, whom fortune doth so oft out dare!
                     
                  
                  
                     Cob.
                     
                        Gentlemen, brothers, friends Souldiers, Christians,
                        We have no reason to command of Heaven
                        A thing denyed to all mortality.
                        Nor should we be so impude
                              •…
                           tly proud,
                        As in this weake condition to repute
                        Our selves above the stroake of Lady Chance,
                        A caution must divine it ever fixt,
                        
                           That whil
                              •…
                           t her checkes, equally fall out,
                        Community should ease their bitternesse.
                        I could afresh now shed those Princely teares
                        To thinke su
                              •…
                           h suddaine raine should attend
                        Heroicke spirits glittering in bright armes▪
                        
                        But if the Grecian (when he heard the dreames
                        Disput
                              •…
                           d subtilly by Philosophers,
                        To prove innumerable extant worlds)
                        Was 
                              •…
                           trucke with pensive
                              •…
                           , and wept to thinke
                        He had not yet obtain'd 
                              •…
                           ne for himselfe;
                        What terror can affright a Christians thoughts
                        Who knowes there is a world, at liberty
                        To breath in, when this glasse of life is broke?
                        Our foes with cir
                              •…
                           ling furie are intrencht;
                        Pelions of earth and darknesse shall orelade them,
                        Whilst we shall mount, and these our spirits light,
                        Shall be yet ponderous to depresse them lower.
                        Nay, my 
                              •…
                           nthesiasticke soule divines,
                        That some weake hand shall from the blazing Zone
                        Snatch Lightning, which shal strike th
                              •…
                            snarling C
                              •…
                           r
                        With horror and amazement to the Earth!
                        Which Hell cannot oppose! Turke, Tyrannize!
                        Stand, yet at le
                              •…
                           gth to fall my sacrifice.
                        Super-Olympicke vigor will (no doubt)
                        Squease all thy supercilious rancor out!
                     
                     Exeunt i
                           •…
                         a M
                           •…
                        .
                  
               
               
                  Scaena 3. Actus 5.
                  
                     The Heavens seeme on fire, Comets and blazing S
                           •…
                        arres appeare, Amurath speakes.
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     
                        Who set the world on fire? How now (ye Heavens)
                        Grow you so proud that you must needs put on curl'd lockes▪
                        
                        And cloth your selves in Peri
                              •…
                           igs of fire?
                        
                           Mahomet (say not but I invoke thee now!)
                        Command the puny-Christians demi-God
                        Put out those flashing sparkes, those Ignes 
                                 〈◊〉
                              ,
                        
                        Or ile unseate him, or with my Lookes so shake
                        The 
                              •…
                           taggring props of his weake seated Throne,
                        
                           That he shall finde he shall have mo
                              •…
                           e to doe
                        To quell one Amurath, then the whole Gyant brood
                        Of those same sonnes of Earth then ten Lycaons!
                        
                        Doe the poore snakes so love their misery
                        That they would see it by these threatning lights?
                        Dar
                              •…
                            ye blaze still? Ile tosse up Buckets full
                        Of Christians bloud to quench you: by those haires
                        Drag you beneath the Center: there put out
                        All your praesaging flames in 
                              
                                 〈◊〉
                              !
                        
                        Can you outbrave me with your pidling Lights?
                        Yawne earth with Casements as wide as hel it selfe▪
                        
                     
                     Here a Va
                           •…
                        lt opens.
                     
                        Burne Heaven as ardent as the Lemnian flames!
                        Wake (pale Tysiphon) spend all thy snakes!
                        Be Eacus, and Minos as severe
                        As if the Gaole delivery of us all
                        Were the next Sessions! Ile pull Radamant
                        By his flaming furres from out his Iron Chaire.
                     
                  
                  Whilst he is in his fury, arise foure Fiends, framed like Turkish Kings, but blacke, his supposed Predecessors dance about him to a kind of hideous noyse, sing this Song, following.
                  
                     
                        
                           
                              
                                 1. Fiend.
                                 
                                    Horror dismall cryes, and yells
                                    Of these thy Grandsires thee fore-tells,
                                    Furies sent of thee to learne
                                    Crimes, which they could nere discerne.
                                 
                              
                              
                                 All.
                                 
                                     Furies sent, &amp;c.
                                 
                              
                              
                                 2. Fiend.
                                 
                                    O Amurathl thy Father's come,
                                    To warne thee of a suddaine doome,
                                    Which in Cassanoe's fields attends
                                    To bring thee to thy Hellish friends.
                                 
                              
                              
                                 All. 
                                 
                                    Which in Cassanoes, &amp;c.
                                 
                              
                              
                                 
                                 3. Fiend.
                                 
                                    
                                       Megaera and Ennio both doe stand,
                                    Trembling, least when thou art damn'd
                                    Chiefe of Furies thou shouldst bee,
                                    And they their snakes resigne to thee.
                                 
                              
                              
                                 All.
                                 
                                    Chiefe of Furies, &amp;c.
                                 
                              
                              
                                 4. Fiend.
                                 
                                    Terror we a while will leave thee,
                                    Till Cocytus Lake receive thee.
                                    
                                       Cerberus will quake for feare
                                    Where he a new Turkes fate shall heare.
                                 
                              
                              
                                 All. 
                                 
                                    
                                       Cerberus will, &amp;c.
                                 
                              
                           
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     
                        Now who the Divell sent my Grandsires hither?
                        Had Pluto no taske else to set them too?
                        He should have bound them to Ixions wheele,
                        Or bid them roule the stone of Sysiphus:
                        
                        Beshrew me, but their singing did not please me!
                        Have they not beene so drunke with Lethe yet
                        As to forget me? Then can portend no ill
                        For, should the fates be twining my last threed;
                        Yet none durst come from Hell to tell me so!
                        Shall I be scar'd with a Night-walking Ghost;
                        Or what my working fancy shall present?
                        Why, I can looke more t
                              •…
                           rrible, then Night,
                        And command darknesse in the unwilling day:
                        Make Hecate start: and draw backe her head,
                        To wrap it in a swarthy vaile of Clouds.
                        Drop sheets of Sulphure, you prodigious skyes!
                        
                           Cyclops, run all thy Bullets into Ae
                                 •…
                              ,
                        
                        Then vomit them at once! should Christians
                        Couch to the bottomlesse abysse of 
                              
                                 〈◊〉
                              ,
                        
                        Or hide themselves under Avernaes shade,
                        This mine arme should fetch them out! Day must performe
                        What I intend, wrath raines a bloudy storme:
                        And now 'gins rise the Sunne, which yet not knowes
                        The misery it shall see on Amuraths Foes,
                        
                           Lords, Leaders, Captaines:
                     
                     Enter Schahin and others.
                  
                  
                     Schah.
                     Your Highnesse up so soone?
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     
                        He small rest takes,
                        That dreames on nought but bloudy broyles and death.
                     
                  
                  
                     S
                           •…
                        hah.
                     
                        Your Grace seemes much distempered: Beds of sweat
                        Bedew your browes with never wonted palenesse.
                     
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     
                        Why; see you not? The heavens are turn'd Court Ladies,
                        And put on other Haire besides their owne:
                        Canst guesse (learn'd Schahin) what these flames portend?
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈◊〉
                        .
                     
                        My Lord, such things as these we 
                              〈◊〉
                            mu
                              •…
                           t 
                              〈◊〉
                           ,
                        And wonder at, and yet not search the reason,
                        Perchance unwholsome fogs exhailed 
                              〈◊〉
                            th'Sunne
                        Are set a blazing by his too neere heate:
                        But 'tis not lawfull that a mortall eye:
                        Should dare to penetrate Heavens secrecy.
                     
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     Doth it not bode a Conquest?
                  
                  
                     Schah.
                     
                        Yes, 'gainst the Christians:
                        For, unto them it bends sinister lookes,
                        And frownes upon their army more then ours.
                     
                  
                  
                     Amur.
                     
                        So, so! 
                              •…
                           ome on, ere 'Phosphorus appeare
                        Let's too't, and so prevent that sluggard Sol!
                        
                        If we want light, we'll from our Winnards▪
                        
                        Strike fire enough to scorch the Vniverse▪
                        
                        Mine armour there!Some g
                                 •…
                               for his arm
                                 •…
                              ur.
                        
                        Now (Mahomet) I implore
                        Thy promist ayde for this auspitious day!
                        To
                              •…
                           e me aloft, and make me ride on Clouds!
                        If my horse faile me, those fire breathing jades,
                        (Which the boy Phaethon k
                              •…
                           ew not how to guide)
                        Will I plucke out from out the flaming teame,
                        And hurle my selfe against those condense Spheares,
                        On which ile sit, and stay their turning Orbes;
                        The whole vertigious Circle shall stand still,
                        But to behold me:Mine armour 
                                 〈◊〉
                              !
                        
                        So helpe on here, now like Alcides do I girt my selfe, They bri
                                 •…
                              g his Armor.
                        
                        With well knit sinewes, able to stagger Earth,
                        And threaten Nature with a second Chaos:
                        If one impetuous broyle remaine to come
                        
                           In future ages, set on foote this houre!
                        How well this weight of steele befits my strength?
                        Me thinks the Gods stand quivering, and doe feare
                        (When I am arm'd) another Ph
                                 •…
                              egrae's neare!
                        
                           Chiron shall see his Pindus at my feet!
                        And, ile climbe to Heaven, and pull it downe,
                        And kicke the weighty b
                              •…
                           rden of the world,
                        From off the Babies shoulders that supports it!
                        For I am safer Buckled 'gainst my foe.
                        Then st
                              •…
                           dy Iason who by the inchanted charmes
                        
                           Medea gave, incountred Vnicornes,
                        Queld Lyons, struggeld with fiery belching Buls:
                        Obtain'd a glorious prize, a Fleece, a Fleece
                        Dipt deepe in tincture of the Christians bloud.
                        Shall be my spoyle, nay should they hide their heads
                        In their Gods bosome, here's a sword shall reach thē 
                           
                              •…
                           
                        
                        Come they shall know no place is free from wrath,
                        When boyling bloud is stirr'd in Amurath.
                        
                     
                     
                        Exeunt. An alarme, excursions: fight within. Enter at one doore a Christian, at another a Turke; fight, both 
                              〈◊〉
                           : so a new charge, the Turkes kill most. Enter Lazarus, Schahin kils him. Enter Eurenoses, Cobelitz, they fight, Cobelitz 
                           
                              •…
                           aints, falls for doad. A 
                              •…
                           howt within, a token of Victory on the Turkes side, a Retrait sounded.
                     
                  
               
               
                  Scaena 4. Actus 5.
                  
                     Enter above Amurath, Bajazet, Nobles, to 
                           •…
                        e the spoyle.
                  
                  
                     Schah.
                     
                        Here (mighty Prin
                              •…
                           ) take view of Victory,
                        And see the field too narrow for thy spoyles!
                        
                           Erynnus hides her head as if afraid,
                        To see a slaughter. She durst never hope for,
                        Earth hath the Carkasses, and denies them Graves,
                        And lets them be and rot, and fat her wombe,
                        Scorning to be unto slaves a Tombe.
                     
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     
                        Where are b
                              •…
                           come those ominous Comets now?
                        What? ar
                              •…
                            those pissing Candles quit
                              •…
                            extinct?
                        
                           Leave their disasterous snuffes no stench behind them?
                        'Tis something yet, that their God seeth their slaughter.
                        
                           
                              •…
                           ending sulphurious Meteors to behold
                        The blest destruction of these Parasites▪
                        
                        I knew the Elements would first untye
                        The Nerves of the Vniverse, then l
                              •…
                           t me dye!
                     
                     Here Cobelitz riseth as aw
                           •…
                        kt, amazed le
                           •…
                        ning on his Sword, s
                           •…
                        mbling ore the dead bodies, lookes towards Amurath.
                     
                  
                  
                     E
                           •…
                        ren.
                     
                        See (King) here's one worme yet that dare confesse
                        He breaths and lives, which once this hand crusht downe.
                     
                  
                  
                     Am
                           •…
                        r.
                     
                        Ha, ha, by Mahomet and we are weary now:
                        Some Mercy shall lay Victory asleepe.
                        It will a Lawreat prove to this great strife,
                        'Mongst all these murdered to give one his life,
                        So we'll discend.
                     
                     He go
                           •…
                        th from alo
                           •…
                        .
                  
                  
                     C
                           •…
                        .
                     
                        From what a dismall grave am I awaked,
                        Intombed within a Golgotha of men;
                        Have all these Soules prevented me in blisse,
                        And left me in a dreame of happinesse?
                        But soft! m
                              •…
                            thoughts he sayd he would descend!
                        Then, Heavens one minutes breath, that's all I aske,
                        And then I shall performe my lifes true taske.
                     
                     Amurath descends on the Stage, C
                           •…
                        belitz staggers towards him.
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     Poore slave, wouldst live?
                     Here Cobelitz is come to him, seeming to kneele, stabs him with a pocket Dagger.
                  
                  
                     Cob.
                     
                        Yes Turke to see thee dye!
                        Howle, howle▪ (grim 
                              
                                 •…
                              artar) yell (thou gristly Wol
                              •…
                           e)
                        Force the bloud from out thy gaping Wound!
                        
                           Dij tibi non mortem, quae c
                                 •…
                              ctis p
                                 •…
                              na paratur,
                        
                        
                           Sed sensum post fata, tu
                                 •…
                               dent (imp
                                 •…
                              e) morti.
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Amur.
                     
                        My spirit makes me not to f
                              •…
                           ele thy weapon!
                        Hold you (crackt Organs) of my shottered life,
                        I am not toucht yet! can 
                              •…
                            not mocke my death,
                        And thi
                              •…
                           ke 'tis but a dreame t
                              •…
                           lls me I am hurt?
                        Dar'st thou then leave me (bloud?) Canst be so bold
                        
                           As to forsake these veynes to flow on Earth?
                        And must, I like th'unhappy Roma
                                 •…
                              , dye
                        By a slaves hand?
                     
                  
                  
                     Cob.
                     
                        Tyrant, 'tis knowne
                        He's Lord of others lifes that scornes his owne!
                     
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     
                        I that could sca
                              •…
                           ce ere sleepe, can I ere die?
                        And will none 
                              •…
                           eare my life when I am dead
                        Tortures and torments for the murderer!
                     
                  
                  
                     Cob.
                     
                        Ha, ha, ha!Le
                                 •…
                              ning on his sword.
                        
                        I thanke the (great omnipotent) tha
                              •…
                            I
                        Shall ere laugh out the lag end of my life!
                     
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     
                        Villaine, thy laugh wounds worse then did thy Dagger!
                        Are you Lethargick (Lords) in cruelty?
                     
                  
                  
                     Cob.
                     
                        Nay, heare me (Turke) now will I prompt their rage
                        Locke me in the Bull of Phalaris,
                        
                        Cut off these eye-lids, bid me then out-gaze
                        The parching Sun-beames; flea this tender ski
                              •…
                           ,
                        Set nests of Hornets on my rawest flesh,
                        Let the Siconian Clouds d
                              •…
                           op brimstone on me,
                        Powre boyling Lemnos on my greenest wounds,
                        Put on my shoulder Ne
                                 •…
                              us poysoned shirt, The Lord that holds 
                                 〈◊〉
                               
                              Amurath offers to touch his wounds.
                        
                        Bind all these bloudy faces to my face
                        Rocke me Procra
                                 •…
                              tes like —
                     
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     Hell, oh! I cannot brooke your smallest touch,
                  
                  
                     Cob.
                     
                        Ha, ha, each groane is Balsome to my wounds:
                        I am perfect well!
                     
                     Bajazet offers to kill Cobelitz; a Nobleman holds his hand▪
                        
                     
                  
                  
                     Schah.
                     Rascall dar'st deride us?
                  
                  
                     Cob.
                     
                        Yea? and while your witty furies shall invent
                        For me, some never heard of punishment;
                        I see a guard of Saints ready to take me hence.
                        Take then froe flight, my new rewarded soule,
                        And seate thee on the winged Seraphims,
                        Hast to the Empyreum, where thy welcome
                        Shall be an Haleluia, anthem'd forth
                        By the Chorus of the Angell-Hierarchy.
                        Pierce with (swift plumes) the concave paths oth' Moone
                        Where the black ayre enlightened is with starres.
                        
                           Stay not to wonder (there) of wandring Signes
                        At the inhorn'd Gemin
                                 •…
                              , or Amph
                                 •…
                              s Harpe,
                        At Arctos, or Bootes, or the Beare,
                        (Which are to pl
                              •…
                           se wizard Astrologers)
                        Soare higher with the pitch and then looke downe
                        To la
                              •…
                           gh at the hard trifles of the world!
                        Perchance some oft have knowne a better life,
                        Never did none ere leave it more willingly.
                     
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     
                        Feare your deaths (Gods) for I have lost my life,
                        And what I most (complaine) my tyranny!
                     
                  
                  
                     C
                           •…
                        b.
                     
                        Soule to detaine thee from thy wished rest
                        Were but an envious part 
                              •…
                            arise, farewell:
                        To stay thee to accuse or fate or man
                        Would shew I were unwilling yet to leave thee
                        But deare companion hence: cut through the ayre:
                        Let not the grosen
                              •…
                           sse of my Earth ore-lime
                        Thy speedy wings, fly without weight of crime.
                     
                     He dyes.
                  
                  
                     Am.
                     
                        O now have I and Fortune tryed it out.
                        With all her best of favours was I crown'd
                        And suffred her worst threats, whē most she frown'd.
                        Stay (Soulel) a King, a Turke, commands thee stay!
                        Sure 
                              •…
                            am but an actor, and must strive
                        To personate the Tragicke ends of Kings.
                        And so (
                              •…
                           o winne applause unto the Scaene)
                        With fained passion thus must graspe at death!
                        O but I see pale Nemesis at hand:
                        Art thou dull fate, and dost not overspread
                        
                           Gimmerion wings of death throughout the world;
                        What? Not one Earthquake? One blazing Comet
                        T'accompany my soule t'his Funerall?
                        
                           
                              •…
                           s not this houre the generall period
                        To nere returning time? Last breath command
                        A new Dewcalions deluge, that with me
                        The world may swim to his Eternall Grave,
                        Cracke hindge that holds this globe, and welcome death,
                        Wilt thou not stay Soule? Friend not stay with Kings?
                        Sinke th
                              •…
                           n, and sinke beneath the Thracian Mou
                              •…
                           .
                        Sinke beneath Athos, be the B
                                 •…
                              sh Waves
                        
                           Of Acheron thy Tombe, ile want a Grave;
                        So all parts feare, which first my Corps shall hav
                              •…
                           ;
                        For in my Grave, ile be the Christians foe.
                        Here like a Massie Pyramide ile fall,
                        Ile strive to sinke all the whole fabricke with me,
                        Quake Pluto, for 'tis I that come
                        A Turke, a Tyrant, and a Conquerour,
                        And with this groane, like thunder will I cleave,
                        The timerous earth, whilst thus my last I breath.
                     
                     He dyes.
                  
                  
                     Baiaz.
                     
                        O eafie powers, to give's all at first,
                        But in their losse they make us most accurst.
                     
                     Here all the Nobles kneele to Ba
                              •…
                           azet.
                     
                  
                  
                     Schah.
                     
                        The Taper of your Fathers life is spent
                        We must have light still and adore a Sunne
                        That next is rising, therefore mighty Prince,
                        Vpon your shoulders must the load
                        Of Empire rest.
                     
                  
                  
                     Baiaz.
                     
                        Why (Lords) we have a Brother
                        Who, as in the same bloud he tocke a share,
                        So let him beare his part in Government:
                     
                  
                  
                     Sc
                           •…
                        .
                     
                        My Lord! within the selfe-same Hemispheare
                        It's most prodigious when two Sunnes appeare!
                        One body by one soule must be inform'd.
                        Kingdomes like (marriage beds) must not indure
                        Any corrivall! 
                              
                                 〈◊〉
                              
                            was nere secure
                        Whilst she contain'da Pompey, and a Caesar.
                        
                        Like as one Prophet we acknowledge now
                        So of one King in state we must allow.
                        You know the Turkish Lawes, Prince be not nice
                        To purchase Kingdomes, whatsoever the price.
                        He must be lopt, send for him he must dye.
                     
                  
                  
                     Baiaz.
                     
                        O happy Baiazet that he was borne
                        To be a King when thou was Counseller.
                        Call in our Brother 
                              
                                 •…
                              cup,
                        
                     
                     Some goes for him. Here six
                           •…
                         m
                           •…
                         
                        
                           •…
                        e vp Am
                           •…
                        raths Trunke on their should
                           •…
                        rs.
                  
                  
                     Baj.
                     
                        Why (Lords!) is Am
                                 •…
                              rath so light a weight?
                        Is this the Truncke oth' T
                                 •…
                              rkish Emperor?
                        Oh what a heape of thoughts are come to naught
                        
                           What a light weight is he unto sixe men
                        Who durst stand under Ossa, and sustaine it:
                     
                  
                  
                     Euren.
                     
                        My Lord, these Meditations fit not you:
                        You are to take the honour he hath left,
                        And thinke you of his rising, not his fall!Enter Iacup.
                        
                        Let your decree be suddaine, heere's your Brother.
                     
                  
                  
                     B
                           •…
                        j.
                     
                        B
                              •…
                           other, I could have wished we might have met
                        At tim
                              •…
                           s of better greeting! Our father hath
                        Bequeath'd to the Grave these ashes, to us his State.
                        No
                              •…
                            have we leysure (yet) to mourne for him
                        Brothe
                              •…
                           , you k
                              •…
                           ow our state hath made a Law,
                        That, he that sits in a Majesticke Chayre,
                        Must not endure the next succeeding heyre.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           •…
                        ac.
                     
                        Yes, we doe:
                        And (Brother) doe you thinke 'tis crime enough
                        To dye, because I am sonne to an Emperour?
                     
                  
                  
                     S
                           •…
                        ah.
                     
                        My Lord, we know their breathes in him that ay
                              •…
                           
                        
                        Of true affection, that he doth much desire
                        You should be equall in his Kingdome with him:
                        But still when two great evils are propos'd:
                        The lesse is to be chosen.
                     
                  
                  
                     E
                           •…
                        ren.
                     
                        My Lord, your life's but one:
                        Kings are the threads whereto there are inweaved
                        Millions of lives, and he that must rule all
                        Must still be one that is select from all.
                        Although we speake, yet thinke them not our words,
                        But what the Land speakes in us! Kings are free▪
                        
                        And must be impatient of equality.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈◊〉
                        .
                     
                        And is't ene so?
                        How have th
                              •…
                           se Dogs fawn'd on me lickt my feet
                        When A
                                 •…
                              th yet lived? Felt all my thoughts,
                        And soothed them to the sight of Empyrie▪
                        
                        And now the first would set their politique hands
                        To strangle up that breath, a blast of which
                        Their nosthrils have suckt up like perfum'd ayre
                        Well brother well by all men this is spoke,
                        That heart that cannot bow, may yet be brok
                              •…
                           .
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           〈◊〉
                        .
                     
                        Brother you must not now stand to upbraid;
                        
                           They which doe feare the vulgars murmuring tongue,
                        Must also feare th'authority of a King;
                        For rulers mu
                              •…
                           t esteeme it happinesse
                        That with their government they can hate suppresse:
                        They with too faint a hand the Scepters sway,
                        Who regard love, or what the people say:
                        To Kindred we must quite put off respect,
                        When 'tis so neare it may our Crowne affect.
                     
                  
                  
                     
                        
                           •…
                        ac.
                     
                        Then name of Brother doe I thus shake off,
                        For 'tis in vaine, their mercy to implore
                        When impio
                              •…
                           s Scatists have decreed before.
                        Yet King although thou take my life away
                        See how 
                              •…
                           le dye in better state then thou!
                        Who like (my Father) after his greatest glor
                              •…
                           
                        
                        May fall by some base hand: The Minister
                        To take my breath, shall be to thy selfe, a King.
                     
                     Here lacu
                           •…
                         takes a Scarfe from his Arme, and p
                           •…
                        ing 
                           •…
                        t about his necke gives one end to Bajazet.
                     
                     
                        Yet give me leave a while▪ to Prophesie,
                        You that so Puppet-like delude your hopes,
                        And Miser-draw th
                              •…
                            ancestry from Kings,
                        Thinking, that fates dare not app
                              •…
                           oach your bloud
                        Till they doe seize you, then you leave this Earth
                        Not as you went, but by compulsion dragg'd;
                        Still begging for a morrow from your Grave,
                        And with such shifts you doe deceive your selves:
                        As if you could deceive mortality,
                        No (Brother King) nor all the Glow-worme state,
                        Which makes thee be a Horse-leach for thy bloud,
                        Not all the Parasites Minions thou maintaines▪
                        
                        Nor the restorative Dishes that are found out.
                        Nor all thy shifts a
                              •…
                           d trickes can cheat mortality,
                        Or keepe thee from a▪ death that's worse then mine.
                        Shoul
                              •…
                            all this faile, age would professe it selfe
                        A slow, but a sure Executioner.
                        O 'tis a hard thing well to temperate
                        Decaying happinesse in great estate
                        But this example by me may you gaine:
                        
                           That at my death I not of Heaven complaine
                        P
                              •…
                           ll then, and with my fall pull on thy selfe
                        Mountaines of burdenous honor which shall curse thee
                        Death l
                              •…
                           ades the willing by the hand
                        But spurs them headlong on, that dares command.
                     
                     
                        
                           •…
                        ere himselfe pulls 
                           •…
                        e end Bajazet the other. 
                           
                              •…
                           acup dyes. 
                           •…
                        azet.
                     
                        Take up this Trunke; and let us first appoin
                              •…
                           
                        
                        O
                              •…
                            Fathers and our Brothers Funerals,
                        The sencelesse body of that Ca
                              •…
                           fe slave,
                        Hurle to a Ditch, Posterity shall heare
                        Our lesse ill Chronicled, but time shall heare
                        These minutes rather, then repeate their woe.
                        Now Primacy, on thee ile medi
                              •…
                           ,
                        Which who enjoy thee, are in blest estate.
                        Whose age in secure silence fleets away,
                        Without disturbance to his funerall day;
                        Nor ponderous nor unquiet honours can
                        Vexe him but dyes a primate ancient man,
                        What greater powers threaten inferiour men
                        A greater power threatens him agen:
                        And like to wasted Tapers Ki
                              •…
                           gs must spend
                        Their lives to light up others: So a
                              •…
                           l end.
                     
                     Exeunt bearing o
                           •…
                        t solemnely the bodies of Amurath and Iacup.
                     
                  
               
            
            FINIS.
            
         
      
   

